<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0051-B654-5174-20EE"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>State starts new push</title><source>Winston-Salem Journal (North Carolina)</source><author>BERTRAND M. GUTIERREZ, JOURNAL REPORTER</author><text><![CDATA[The N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources announced Friday it plans to modify permits that Duke Energy must have to operate its coal-waste ponds at three power plant sites.

DENR plans to make Duke “eliminate all unauthorized discharges and potentially move coal ash from the basins at the Riverbend and Asheville power plants,” according to a DENR news release. The modifications will also require Duke to dewater and accelerate closure of the coal-ash ponds at the utility’ s Sutton plant.

The announcement comes two days after Duke Energy CEO Lynn Good, responding to Gov. Pat McCrory’s request for a quick response on dealing with the company’ s coal-waste problem, said in a four-page letter that the company will remove its coal waste from ash ponds at two of its 14 power plants — Dan River and Riverbend.

“We want to make certain that we, our regulators and other stakeholders can have a high degree of confidence in the integrity of our ash basins,” Good said.

The utility company does not have much of a choice, according to a Superior Court judge.

Last week, the judge ruled in favor of conservation groups requesting that Duke Energy stop contaminating groundwater at its power plants statewide, including the Belews Creek Steam Station in Stokes County.

The judge ruled that Duke Energy must 'take immediate action to eliminate sources' of contamination, such as ash ponds that allow sludge-like coal waste to leach into the ground. And, the judge said, the utility company must do so regardless of the continuing negotiations it has pending with DENR over past groundwater contamination or future cleanup efforts.

Duke Energy has the option of appealing the decision.

Removing coal waste from the ponds is the best way to eliminate the source of contamination, conservationists say.

While Duke Energy's March 12 letter referred to removing ash from the coal-waste dumps at the Dan River and Riverbend power plants, the letter did little to say how the company will specifically deal with coal ash at its 12 other power plants, except to say that a team has been assembled to study the appropriate actions.

'Although Duke committed to near-term actions, the response lacked the detail necessary to ensure Duke Energy abides by the commitments outlined in their letter. Reopening these permits allows DENR to ensure that Duke Energy resolves this long-standing issue at these fa cilities,' said John Skvarla, the DENR secretary.

The ash spill Feb. 2 into the Dan River demonstrated what risks a coal-waste dump poses. In addition, ash ponds at all 14 Duke Energy power plants have been cited by the N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources as violating federal or clean-water laws.

DENR's announcement about new permit reviews raises red flags for D.J. Gerken, senior attorney for the Southern Environmental Law Center, which represents conservation groups in the legal effort to force Duke to stop violating federal and state clean-water laws.

'If DENR is serious about addressing water pollution, the quickest solution is to take the authority that the judge just gave them and ask the judge to enforce it,' Gerken said.
]]></text></news-item>