<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0076-0101-429B-CD00"><date>2014-03-09</date><title>Extra Holding: Dankner fabricated documents; Moti Ben-Moshe Extra Holding submitted evidence alleging Nochi Dankner filed a forged document and false affidavit with the court.</title><source>Globes [online] - Israel's Business Arena</source><author>Efrat Peretz</author><text><![CDATA["We are talking about criminal acts that carry nine years imprisonment," said Extra Holding GmbH's strategic consultant Adv. Raanan Kalir at a press conference today. Extra Holding's owner Moti Ben-Moshe was not present at the press conference. "The evidence has been sent to the Tel Aviv District Prosecutor as part of a request to open a criminal investigation against Dankner, [Barlev Investigative Auditing owner] Yehudah Barlev, and [Black Cube Ltd. VP] Avi Yanus on suspicion of criminal conduct and preparing false affidavits. Dankner and his aides filed several complaints by various parties, every time making new complaints with the intention of creating a false presentation through multiple complaints that were also presented to the media."
Extra Holding today filed with the Tel Aviv District Court evidence alleging that former IDB Holding Corp. Ltd. (TASE:IDBH) chairman Nochi Dankner and his people had filed with the court, and presented to the Israeli media and European authorities a forged document and false affidavit. Extra Holding's statement of claim alleges Dankner is engaged in persecution and character assassination of Ben-Moshe.
"Barlev is backed by an expanded team that operates in Israel and overseas in order to support Dankner's allegations. Another partner is Avi Yanus, a partner in the Black Cube business intelligence firm, in which Dan Zorella and others are also partners. The German authorities were shown allegations made by Dankner in Israeli court - false allegations against Extra Holding and Ben-Moshe about VAT and tax evasion and financial fraud," said Kalir.
"The German authorities unequivocally concluded that there is not even suspicion of misconduct or a need to open an investigation. There are no grounds for the allegations by Dankner's people. We have been in possession of this material for only a few days, but Dankner's people have had it for much longer."
Kalir detailed the alleged false affidavit, saying, "In his last motion filed with the court, Dankner makes disproved allegations as if Ben-Moshe is involved in money laundering This is a false affidavit and the document appended to it is a forgery that does not belong to Meinl Bank to which it attributed. Ben-Moshe is not mentioned and he has no rights in any account at this Austrian bank. In view of these findings, Adv. Reznik has asked the Tel Aviv Prosecutor's Office to open a criminal case against Dankner, Barlev, and Yanus on suspicion of forging evidence and using forged evidence to mislead the judiciary. Complaints against the latter will filed at the same time in Germany on suspicion of false accusations, fraud, and forgery."
The notice of today press statement was sent by Extra Holding alone. The company of Ben-Moshe's partner, Eduardo Elsztain, is not a signatory.
Today, Danker will submit to the court new findings from his investigation against Ben-Moshe in Germany. This material is apparently in response to Ben-Moshe's statement to the media.
Published by Globes [online], Israel business news - www.globes-online.com - on March 9, 2014
© Copyright of Globes Publisher Itonut (1983) Ltd. 2014
]]></text></news-item>