<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0165-02B3-63FD-36A7"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Congressional Votes for Alabama the Week of 03/07 - 03/13/2014</title><source>Targeted News Service</source><author>by TARGETED NEWS SERVICE, Targeted News Service</author><text><![CDATA[WASHINGTON, March 16 -- There were six key votes in the Senate this week; there were 11 key votes in the House. The House voted 19 times in the week ending Thursday; the Senate voted 18 times. The most important vote in the House was to pass a bill to require the executive branch to enforce federal laws; the most important vote in the Senate was to pass a bill changing the government's flood insurance program.
The House, on voice vote, also passed the Farmers Undertake Environmental Land Stewardship Act (H.R. 311), sponsored by Rep. Rick Crawford, R-Ark., to direct the Environmental Protection Agency Administrator to change the agency's Spill Prevention, Control, and Countermeasure rule with respect to certain farms; passed the Equitable Access to Care and Health Act (H.R. 1814), sponsored by Rep. Aaron Schock, R-Ill., to amend the Internal Revenue Code to provide an additional religious exemption from the individual health coverage mandate; and passed the Federal Communications Commission Process Reform Act (H.R. 3675), sponsored by Rep. Greg Walden, R-Ore., to increase transparency and efficiency in procedures followed by the Federal Communications Commission.
The Senate, on voice vote, also agreed to a resolution (S. Res. 365), sponsored by Sen. Robert Menendez, D-N.J., criticizing the violent repression of peaceful demonstrators in Venezuela and supporting the free and peaceful exercise of representative democracy in Venezuela; passed the Gabriella Miller Kids First Research Act (H.R. 2019), sponsored by Rep. Gregg Harper, R-Miss., to eliminate taxpayer financing of political party conventions and use the savings to fund a 10-year pediatric research initiative through the Common Fund administered by the National Institutes of Health; passed the Home Heating Emergency Assistance Through Transportation Act (H.R. 4076), sponsored by Rep. Bill Shuster, R-Pa., to address shortages and interruptions in the availability of propane and other home heating fuels in the U.S. by suspending certain regulations; and passed the National Flood Insurance Program Act (S. 2137), sponsored by Sen. Mike Lee, R-Utah, to ensure that holders of federal flood insurance policies do not receive refunds of insurance premiums paid on second homes.
Here's a look at how area members of Congress voted over the previous week.
HOUSE VOTES:
House Vote 1:
VETERANS AND HEALTH CARE REFORM: The House has passed the Hire More Heroes Act (H.R. 3474), sponsored by Rep. Kevin Brady, R-Texas. The bill would state that veterans who are enrolled in the military's TRICARE health insurance program or a health insurance program operated by the Department of Veterans Affairs do not count toward the 50-employee threshold for triggering the health care reform law's mandate for employers to provide health insurance for their employees. Brady said that currently, small businesses with close to 50 employees have a disincentive to hire veterans because such hires could create higher costs for the businesses by triggering the mandate, and so the veterans exemption is needed to "help ease the burden on small businesses while incentivizing them to hire veterans who have found themselves out of work as they return home from overseas." The vote, on March 11, was 406 yeas to 1 nay.
YEAS: Rep. Robert B. Aderholt R-AL (4th), Rep. Mo Brooks R-AL (5th), Rep. Bradley Byrne R-AL (1st), Rep. Mike Rogers R-AL (3rd), Rep. Terri A. Sewell D-AL (7th)
NOT VOTING: Rep. Spencer Bachus R-AL (6th)
House Vote 2:
VOLUNTEER FIREFIGHTERS AND HEALTH CARE REFORM: The House has passed the Protecting Volunteer Firefighters and Emergency Responders Act (H.R. 3979), sponsored by Rep. Lou Barletta, R-Pa. The bill would create a special rule in the tax code exempting local governments with volunteer firefighters and other emergency services volunteers from a requirement to provide health care insurance to their volunteers. Barletta said: "We owe our emergency service volunteers who risk their lives every day rock-solid certainty. This legislation says, once and for all, that volunteer firefighters are just that, volunteers, and should not be subjected to the employer mandate." The vote, on March 11, was unanimous with 410 yeas.
YEAS: Rep. Robert B. Aderholt R-AL (4th), Rep. Spencer Bachus R-AL (6th), Rep. Mo Brooks R-AL (5th), Rep. Bradley Byrne R-AL (1st), Rep. Mike Rogers R-AL (3rd), Rep. Terri A. Sewell D-AL (7th)
House Vote 3:
RUSSIA-UKRAINE RESOLUTION: The House has passed a resolution (H. Res. 499), sponsored by Rep. Edward R. Royce, R-Calif., to condemn Russia's government for its military intervention in Crimea and application of economic pressure on Ukraine, and call on Russia to cease such activities. Royce said that by continuing the U.S. effort to impose real costs on Russia for its actions against Ukraine's new government, the resolution would discourage Russia from attempting to bring Crimea under its control. The vote, on March 11, was 402 yeas to 7 nays.
YEAS: Rep. Robert B. Aderholt R-AL (4th), Rep. Spencer Bachus R-AL (6th), Rep. Mo Brooks R-AL (5th), Rep. Bradley Byrne R-AL (1st), Rep. Mike Rogers R-AL (3rd), Rep. Terri A. Sewell D-AL (7th)
House Vote 4:
CHALLENGING CIVIL RIGHTS ACTIONS: The House has rejected an amendment sponsored by Rep. John Conyers Jr., D-Mich., to the ENFORCE the Law Act (H.R. 4138). The amendment would have excluded from the bill's scope presidential actions and actions by other government officials that are intended to combat discrimination or protect civil rights. Conyers said the exemption would maintain the ability of government to protect civil rights and other constitutional protections without concern over the possibility of ill-founded Congressional challenge. An opponent of the amendment, Rep. Bob Goodlatte, R-Va., said it "would immunize from accountability in court this President and any President and other Federal employees when they fail to enforce the civil rights laws, as written." The vote, on March 12, was 188 yeas to 227 nays.
YEAS: Rep. Terri A. Sewell D-AL (7th)
NAYS: Rep. Robert B. Aderholt R-AL (4th), Rep. Spencer Bachus R-AL (6th), Rep. Mo Brooks R-AL (5th), Rep. Bradley Byrne R-AL (1st), Rep. Mike Rogers R-AL (3rd)
House Vote 5:
THE EXECUTIVE AND PROSECUTORIAL DISCRETION: The House has rejected an amendment sponsored by Rep. Jerrold Nadler, D-N.Y., to the ENFORCE the Law Act (H.R. 4138). The amendment would have stated that the bill did not limit or affect the constitutional authority of the executive branch to exercise prosecutorial discretion whether or not to prosecute alleged violations of federal laws and regulations. Nadler said the amendment would mitigate what he called the bill's "unconstitutional encroachment into the President's authority to faithfully execute the law." An opponent of the amendment, Rep. Bob Goodlatte, R-Va., said it addressed an issue that was not the proper subject of the bill, given that the bill addresses policies and procedures, not prosecution for violations of the law, and therefore the amendment would create confusion. The vote, on March 12, was 190 yeas to 225 nays.
YEAS: Rep. Terri A. Sewell D-AL (7th)
NAYS: Rep. Robert B. Aderholt R-AL (4th), Rep. Spencer Bachus R-AL (6th), Rep. Mo Brooks R-AL (5th), Rep. Bradley Byrne R-AL (1st), Rep. Mike Rogers R-AL (3rd)
House Vote 6:
THE EXECUTIVE AND JUDICIAL DECISIONS: The House has rejected an amendment sponsored by Rep. Sheila Jackson Lee, D-Texas, to the ENFORCE the Law Act (H.R. 4138). The amendment would have stated that the bill had no affect on the ability of the executive branch to comply with judicial decisions interpreting the Constitution or federal laws. Jackson Lee said the amendment would prevent Congress from attempting to use legal challenges to delay executive actions that are necessary to comply with judicial decisions. An opponent of the amendment, Rep. Bob Goodlatte, R-Va., said it went against the bill's design because it would give the president authority to defy court decisions relating to the Constitution's separation of powers between the three branches of government. The vote, on March 12, was 185 yeas to 231 nays.
YEAS: Rep. Terri A. Sewell D-AL (7th)
NAYS: Rep. Robert B. Aderholt R-AL (4th), Rep. Spencer Bachus R-AL (6th), Rep. Mo Brooks R-AL (5th), Rep. Bradley Byrne R-AL (1st), Rep. Mike Rogers R-AL (3rd)
House Vote 7:
THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH AND EXECUTING THE LAW: The House has passed the ENFORCE the Law Act (H.R. 4138), sponsored by Rep. Trey Gowdy, R-S.C. The bill would authorize Congress or either branch of Congress to file lawsuits against the president and other federal government officials who adopt policies or procedures that do not implement laws adopted by the government. Gowdy said that given the Obama administration's failure to execute the health care reform law and other laws as envisioned by Congress, Congress needs to have available the remedy of petitioning U.S. district courts and the Supreme Court to ensure that laws are faithfully executed. An opponent, Rep. John Conyers Jr., D-Mich., called the bill "another attempt by the majority [Republicans] to prevent the President of the United States from implementing duly enacted legislative initiatives that they oppose." The vote, on March 12, was 233 yeas to 181 nays.
YEAS: Rep. Robert B. Aderholt R-AL (4th), Rep. Spencer Bachus R-AL (6th), Rep. Mo Brooks R-AL (5th), Rep. Bradley Byrne R-AL (1st), Rep. Mike Rogers R-AL (3rd)
NAYS: Rep. Terri A. Sewell D-AL (7th)
House Vote 8:
FUNDING FOR REPORTS ON ENFORCEMENT OF LAWS: The House has rejected an amendment sponsored by Rep. Keith Ellison, D-Minn., to the Faithful Execution of the Law Act (H.R. 3973). The amendment would have waived the bill's reporting requirements until the Attorney General found that Congress had appropriated enough money to fund the additional reports required by the bill. Ellison said the voluminous number of reports possibly generated by the bill would be "so burdensome that they shut down and interfere and gnarl up the instrument of government," making the amendment necessary to ensure adequate funding. An opponent of the amendment, Rep. Trent Franks, R-Ariz., said it would give the Attorney General "unilateral power to negate the entire bill based on his own subjective determination of what constitutes 'sufficient' appropriations" to produce the required reports. The vote, on March 13, was 191 yeas to 227 nays.
YEAS: Rep. Terri A. Sewell D-AL (7th)
NAYS: Rep. Robert B. Aderholt R-AL (4th), Rep. Spencer Bachus R-AL (6th), Rep. Mo Brooks R-AL (5th), Rep. Bradley Byrne R-AL (1st), Rep. Mike Rogers R-AL (3rd)
House Vote 9:
ENFORCING FEDERAL LAWS: The House has passed the Faithful Execution of the Law Act (H.R. 3973), sponsored by Rep. Ron DeSantis, R-Fla. The bill would require the Attorney General to report to Congress regarding instances in which Justice Department officers or other federal officers adopt or implement policies that do not enforce federal laws, policies or regulations. DeSantis said the requirement would hold the president to his "duty to take care that the laws are faithfully executed" and not "amend, suspend, or change duly enacted laws" passed by Congress. An opponent of the bill, Rep. Zoe Lofgren, D-Calif., said it would lead to illegal immigrants who have had their deportation deferred and are relatives of U.S. soldiers being at risk of deportation over the objection of military officials who have requested deferrals for the soldiers' families. The vote, on March 13, was 244 yeas to 171 nays.
YEAS: Rep. Robert B. Aderholt R-AL (4th), Rep. Spencer Bachus R-AL (6th), Rep. Mo Brooks R-AL (5th), Rep. Bradley Byrne R-AL (1st), Rep. Mike Rogers R-AL (3rd)
NAYS: Rep. Terri A. Sewell D-AL (7th)
House Vote 10:
SKI AREAS ON FEDERAL LANDS: The House has rejected a substitute amendment sponsored by Rep. Jared Polis, D-Colo., to the Water Rights Protection Act (H.R. 3189). The amendment would have barred the Forest Service from conditioning any water right granted in conjunction with permits for ski areas to operate on federal lands and barred any Forest Service requirements for ski area permittees to obtain water rights in the name of the United States as a condition of receiving or continuing ski area permits. Polis said his amendment would replace the overly broad bill with a precise measure that prevents the Forest Service from demanding that ski area permittees to transfer their water rights to the federal government. An opponent of the amendment, Rep. Doc Hastings, R-Wash., said the amendment would only protect ski areas operating on federal lands, leaving all other groups vulnerable to federal government demands to take over water rights from farms and ranches and municipal governments. The vote, on March 13, was 175 yeas to 236 nays.
YEAS: Rep. Terri A. Sewell D-AL (7th)
NAYS: Rep. Robert B. Aderholt R-AL (4th), Rep. Spencer Bachus R-AL (6th), Rep. Mo Brooks R-AL (5th), Rep. Bradley Byrne R-AL (1st), Rep. Mike Rogers R-AL (3rd)
House Vote 11:
WATER RIGHTS AND FEDERAL LANDS: The House has passed the Water Rights Protection Act (H.R. 3189), sponsored by Rep. Scott R. Tipton, R-Colo. The bill would bar the Interior Secretary and the Agriculture Secretary from requiring any potential signer of an agreement to use federal land to transfer or relinquish their water rights to the federal government. Tipton said the bill upheld the constitutional requirement for government to offer just compensation to property owners for depriving them of property or the full use of their property, preventing the government from violating property rights and hurting the economy by depriving farmers, ranchers and ski areas of their water. An opponent of the bill, Rep. Grace F. Napolitano, D-Calif., called the bill poorly drafted and irresponsible, saying "it would mean the very end of the public lands activities it is supposed to protect, because those activities could no longer be managed responsibly" by putting well-considered restrictions on the use of water on land leased from the government. The vote, on March 13, was 238 yeas to 174 nays.
YEAS: Rep. Robert B. Aderholt R-AL (4th), Rep. Spencer Bachus R-AL (6th), Rep. Mo Brooks R-AL (5th), Rep. Bradley Byrne R-AL (1st), Rep. Mike Rogers R-AL (3rd)
NAYS: Rep. Terri A. Sewell D-AL (7th)
SENATE VOTES:
Senate Vote 1:
SEXUAL ASSAULT IN THE MILITARY: The Senate has passed the Victims Protection Act(S. 1917), sponsored by Sen. Claire McCaskill, D-Mo. The bill would establish various measures to improve the military's ability to prevent and respond to sexual assaults against members of the military, including the formation of a Special Victims' Counsel to provide advice to victims of sexual assault on the advantages and disadvantages of taking their cases to civilian courts. McCaskill said the bill sought to "make sure our military does the right thing by victims and puts perpetrators where they belong--in prison--and out of the ranks of the military where they stain the good name of the bravest men and women in the world." The vote, on March 10, was unanimous with 97 yeas.
YEAS: Sen. Jeff Sessions R-AL, Sen. Richard C. Shelby R-AL
Senate Vote 2:
DUPLICATIVE EARLY LEARNING PROGRAMS: The Senate has passed an amendment sponsored by Sen. Mike Enzi, R-Wyo., to the Child Care and Development Block Grant Act (S. 1086). The amendment would require the Health and Human Services Secretary and Education Secretary to review early learning and child care programs in the federal government and recommend ways to streamline and consolidate the programs. Enzi said: "Streamlining programs to eliminate duplication is essential for program integrity and good governance but also for eliminating service gaps for eligible children." The vote, on March 12, was unanimous with 98 yeas.
YEAS: Sen. Jeff Sessions R-AL, Sen. Richard C. Shelby R-AL
Senate Vote 3:
CHILD CARE FUNDING FOR TRIBES: The Senate has passed an amendment sponsored by Sen. Al Franken, D-Minn., to the Child Care and Development Block Grant Act (S. 1086). The amendment would reserve 2 percent of annual federal funds appropriated for child care and development block grants for payments to Indian tribes and tribal groups. Franken said reserving the funding would ensure that Indian children and youth receive help in improving their low educational outcomes, and thereby improve employment levels for Indians. The vote, on March 12, was 93 yeas to 6 nays.
NAYS: Sen. Jeff Sessions R-AL, Sen. Richard C. Shelby R-AL
Senate Vote 4:
MILLIONAIRES AND CHILD CARE GRANTS: The Senate has passed an amendment sponsored by Sen. Tom Coburn, R-Okla., to the Child Care and Development Block Grant Act (S. 1086). The amendment would bar families with $1 million or more in assets from receiving federal child care grants. Coburn said the eligibility restriction would help "make sure the significant amount of money we spend in this area goes to people who really need it." The vote, on March 13, was unanimous with 100 yeas.
YEAS: Sen. Jeff Sessions R-AL, Sen. Richard C. Shelby R-AL
Senate Vote 5:
BLOCK GRANTS FOR CHILD CARE AND DEVELOPMENT: The Senate has passed the Child Care and Development Block Grant Act (S. 1086), sponsored by Sen. Barbara A. Mikulski, D-Md. The bill would reauthorize through fiscal 2019 the government's program of issuing child care and development block grants to the states, require criminal background checks of child care providers, and require states to submit three-year child care and development plans to receive grants. Mikulski said the bill would reform the block grants program to utilize "new knowledge and best practices of how to help children in childcare be able to be safe, have a sense of security and stability, and then also enhance their ability to learn." The vote, on March 13, was 96 yeas to 2 nays.
YEAS: Sen. Jeff Sessions R-AL, Sen. Richard C. Shelby R-AL
Senate Vote 6:
GOVERNMENT FLOOD INSURANCE RATES: The Senate has passed the Homeowner Flood Insurance Affordability Act (H.R. 3370), sponsored by Rep. Michael G. Grimm, R-N.Y. The bill would bar the Federal Emergency Management Agency from increasing flood insurance premiums to reflect updated flood risks in certain areas or reducing subsidies for property that was first insured after July 6, 2012. A supporter, Sen. Robert Menendez, D-N.J., said it would protect homeowners who have maintained their policies in the federal government's flood insurance program from the harm of sharply higher premiums that could force them into defaulting on their mortgages or make it impossible to sell their homes, through no fault of the homeowners. An opponent of the bill, Sen. James M. Inhofe, R-Okla., said it "prevents flood insurance policies from being written at an actuarially sound rate when homes are sold to a new buyer or when a flood insurance policy lapses. New purchasers of homes in areas that require flood insurance should not be subsidized for making that decision." The vote, on March 13, was 72 yeas to 22 nays.
YEAS: Sen. Jeff Sessions R-AL
NAYS: Sen. Richard C. Shelby R-AL
For more information about Targeted News Service, please contact Myron Struck, editor, 703/866-4708, editor@targetednews.com; for technical questions about transmission or for retransmissions, please contact Kevin Meek, kevin@targetednews.com
For more information about Targeted News Service products and services, please contact: Myron Struck, editor, Targeted News Service LLC, Springfield, Va., 703/304-1897; editor@targetednews.com; http://targetednews.com.
-1154564
]]></text></news-item>