<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="017C-2C9F-00FE-944D"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Eccotopia Enters Talks with Local Mining Industry</title><source>Ground Report</source><author>Richard Kruger</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 14, 2014 (Ground Report:http://www.groundreport.com/ Delivered by Newstex) http://groundreport.com/report/?Article=Eccotopia%20Enters%20Talks%20with%20Local%20Mining%20IndustryArticle-ID=5065209 Eccotopia Enters Talks with Local Mining IndustryArticle Views47 GroundReport | Author: Richard Kruger[1] Filed Under: Infrastructure[2], News[3] | Posted: 03/14/2014 at 2:37PM Comments[4] | Region: South AfricaEccotopia enters discussions with a mining industry consortium over how to address environmental concerns at gold and platinum pits.
Cape Town, South Africa - Julian Moses, Chief Executive Officer at South Africa-based sustainable forestation company Eccotopia, Ltd. has confirmed that the company are currently negotiating the terms of a potential joint venture agreement with local mining companies, which would see it take an active role in mitigating the adverse effects of mining activities on groundwater in the vicinity of several deep ground pits. 'We are endeavoring to address the issues surrounding acidic contamination of groundwater in the vicinity of gold and platinum mines on a collective basis rather than having a situation whereby individual companies attempt to implement their own solutions - if any - to standards that will inevitably vary. Much of South Africa's future prosperity is tied to the activities and production of the mining industry but so is the environmental legacy we leave our children,' said Mr. Moses. The domestic mining industry has keenly followed Eccotopia's phytoremediation projects at several oil and gas sites in the United States and believes that the potential demonstrated abroad can be replicated in South Africa and have approached Eccotopia directly with a view to establishing a number of test sites for long-term evaluation. Eccotopia is proud to have a joint venture agreement with the Pacific Tree Company for the development of Megafolia projects in various regions throughout South Africa and the surrounding regions. The Pacific Tree Company's Megafolia trees have been proven to help reduce contaminants in topsoil and ground water when introduced in areas proximate to mining or drilling sites whilst adding to the aesthetics of areas ravaged by intensive activity. 'With precious metal mines at depths of 3,000 meters commonplace in South Africa, this collective effort is been seen as marking a new era of cooperation between mining companies and environmental groups to preserve the natural beauty of the country,' concluded Mr. Moses. About Pacific Tree West, LLC.Pacific Tree West, LLC has developed proprietary genetics and methodologies in agro-forestry of the Megafolia Paulownia tree, and these Agro-forestry methodologies take advantage of the methods, science, and technologies of agri-business and apply them to the business of raising forests for commercial uses, including Phytoremediation, carbon sequestration, biofuel and energy production. About Eccotopia, Ltd.Eccotopia understands the dynamics of combining ecological and environmental improvements with industrialization and profitability. They have begun to explore linkages between ecology and economics, looking to create new kinds of partnerships and enterprise out of environmental protection and restoration initiatives. Eccotopia's principal commitments are to their partners and the environment. Eccotopia, Ltd. Is a BVI Corporation with offices in the Republic of South Africa. ISIN # VGG2922031090 Website: http://www.eccotopia.comFor more information on Eccotopia, Ltd., please contact:Richard Kruger at Client ServicesGround Floor, Liesbeek HouseGloucester Road, River ParkMowbray, Cape Town 7700Republic of South AfricaTel: +27216805252Fax: +27-11-881-5611Email: info@eccotopia.com[5] Filed Under:Infrastructure[6], News[7] http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/This is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License[8].Attribution (Very Relaxed) Loading...[9] [1]: http://groundreport.com/profile/26378 [2]: http://groundreport.com/category/news-world/infrastructure-news-world/ [3]: http://groundreport.com/category/news-world/ [4]: http://groundreport.com/eccotopia-enters-talks-with-local-mining-industry/#disqus_thread [5]: mailto:info@eccotopia.com [6]: http://groundreport.com/category/news-world/infrastructure-news-world/ [7]: http://groundreport.com/category/news-world/ [8]: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/ [9]: http://mgid.com/

]]></text></news-item>