<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="021A-6419-F568-205D"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Anti-Corruption Bureau nabs four retd irrigation officials</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Mohammed Akhef</author><text><![CDATA[AURANGABAD: The Anti-Corruption Bureau (ACB) officials on Saturday morning five persons, including four retired officials of the minor irrigations department, on the charges of cheating the government by allegedly submitting bills of the works not done and withdrawing money.
The arrested accused have been identified as Shivaji Madhavrao Borode (59), retired deputy engineer (Khuldabad), Madhukar Balwantrao Kulkarni (60) retired sub-divisional officer (Gangapur), Suryakant Kashinathrao Gursude (56), retired sectional engineer (Gangapur), Prakash Chanappa Valandikar (60), retired divisional accounts officer (class-I) and government contractor Arjun Vasantro Salunke (38), a resident of Gangapur. All the accused have been remanded in police custody till Monday.
Besides, a deceased executive engineer of the department, Sudhakar Wamanrao Kulkarni, has also been named as one of the accused. Kulkarni died last year.
Deputy superintendent of police (ACB) Suresh Wankhede said that in 2010, Salunke approached the ACB with a complaint against Sudhakar Kulkarni for allegedly demanding Rs 50, 000 for clearing a bill of about Rs 5 lakh for removing silt from a Kolhapur Type (KT) Weir at Jambarkheda in Vaijapur.
Following the complaint, the ACB sleuths arrested Kulkarni while accepting the bribe money. During interrogation, Kulkarni said that he refrained from signing the cheque for the works that were not completed by the contractor and offended by it, he framed Kulkarni.
Based on Kulkarni’s statement, the ACB sleuths found that the contractor did not complete the work and the four government officials in connivance with other four officials who were in service then, helped and forwarded the bill.
ACB sleuths said the operation started around 4 am and utmost care was taken for keeping it under wraps.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>