<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0228-D2C4-4D77-D7F0"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Bankers face payback time; RULE WOULD SEE BONUSES RETURNED CITY DESK</title><source>Daily Mirror</source><author>GRAHAM HISCOTT</author><text><![CDATA[RECKLESS bankers could be stripped of bonuses even after they've cashed them in under plans revealed yesterday.
The Bank of England is proposing tougher rules that would allow payouts to be seized up to six years after high-flyers have pocketed the money.
Regulators already have the power to force firms to halt bonus payments that have not yet been cashed in, but once they have been paid out nothing can be done.
Reckless won't The Bank is considering a plan to get bonuses paid back if there is evidence of misbehaviour or significant error, where a business has suffered a financial hit, or there has been a failure in risk management.
If given the green light, the rules will come into effect on January 1 next year, in time for the next round of City and bank bonuses.
The proposal follows recommendations by MPs on the Parliamentary Commission on Banking Standards.
It comes in the wake of the financial crisis and a series of banking scandals in recent years, such as the mis-selling of payment protection insurance (PPI), which has already cost the industry more than £20billion.
As the Mirror revealed, former Lloyds chief executive Eric Daniels was among five ex-bigwigs who were denied a £2.7million shares bonanza.
The taxpayer-saved bank refused to hand over the shares the six had already earned but not yet received because of its spiralling PPI bill.
Explaining the planned rule change, Andrew Bailey of the Prudential Regulation Authority said: "We won't ael s allow remuneration schemes to exist that encourage behaviour likely to jeopardise financial stability."
Tory MP Andrew Tyrie, chairman of the Treasury Select Committee,o sa d said: "Clawback of bonuses can help drive up standards.
The Institute of Directors argued that a new EU bonus cap would limit the payouts which could be clawed back in future.
Banks have sidestepped the cap - preventing bonuses of more than 200% of salary - by handing out more in guaranteed pay instead.
Reckless won't keep the rewards of failure
]]></text></news-item>