<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0286-7191-4066-5FC3"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>sheriff gusman wins third term in runoff ; He withstands attacks on leadership to defeat Charles Foti</title><source>Times-Picayune (New Orleans)</source><author>Naomi Martin Staff writer</author><text><![CDATA[Orleans Parish Sheriff Marlin Gusman easily won re-election to a third full term Saturday, after his predecessor, Charles Foti, forced him to defend his management of the city's troubled jail through two elections in two months.
Thought it was clear he would win the night as soon as the first few precincts reported their results, Gusman milked the evening, waiting until right at 10 p.m., just in time for the evening newscasts, to deliver his victory speech.
"We tonight got a clear message from the people that they hear, and they endorse our message," Gusman said, surrounded by an enthusiastic group of supporters celebrating at LACE the Grand Ballroom in eastern New Orleans. "We are going to keep this progress up for the next four years."
A far cry from his landslide primary victory four years ago, Gusman weathered a blitz of print and TV attack ads from Foti in the runoff campaign's final weeks. Foti had spent three decades running the jail before being elected state attorney general in 2003.
Running on promises that Orleans Parish Prison is on the cusp of a new era, Gusman vowed to fully comply with a wide-ranging federal consent decree mandating changes at the jail and open a new 1,438-bed building by June.
The fact that Gusman was forced into a runoff shows a downward shift in public opinion about his leadership after a year of public sparring with Mayor Mitch Landrieu and numerous negative headlines about violence and escapes at the lockup.
Gusman survived a difficult 18 months that saw two of his top deputies plead guilty to corruption charges. In addition, one deputy publicly complained that supervisors were retaliating against him for helping expose violence in the jail.
Now firmly at the helm, Gusman faces several challenges as his office implements the provisions of the federal consent decree aimed at getting the jail to comply with constitutional standards. He must find the money to pay for the sweeping changes as he negotiates the prison's final size with Landrieu and the City Council.
Gusman's feud with Landrieu, which was on hiatus during the winter as both men campaigned for re-election, appears to be continuing behind the scenes, albeit with less venom.
Landrieu allocated Gusman's office $24.2 million for 2014, even though the sheriff had asked for $41.4 million to comply with the additional staffing and equipment required by the consent decree. A court-appointed monitor tried unsuccessfully to mediate the financial dispute between the mayor and the sheriff for more than a month and a half, according to a March 7 court filing.
At a hearing scheduled for Thursday, the federal Department of Justice and inmate advocates are set to argue that Gusman's jail remains woefully understaffed with many inmates left unsupervised much of the time, according to court filings. They say the jail urgently needs $10 million to $22 million more than the $2 million the city budgeted to implement the provisions of the federal order this year.
Although he has denied the jail conditions are unconstitutional, Gusman has long argued the city does not give him enough money to adequately cover inmate care. His lawyers recently indicated they plan to call on Landrieu to testify at the upcoming hearing.
Landrieu's argument, meanwhile, has been that he does not want to waste limited taxpayer dollars on the Sheriff's Office, which he described last summer as an agency "where waste, fraud, and abuse run rampant."
On the campaign trail, Gusman and Foti blamed each other for the prison's current state. Gusman said he inherited a dysfunctional system from Foti and was just starting to make progress when Hurricane Katrina hit in 2005.
Foti said he handed Gusman buildings in good condition and a large budget surplus that he frittered away as the prison's infrastructure deteriorated.
Foti, 76, a lawyer, has been out of public office since 2007, when he lost a re-election bid for attorney general after his controversial arrests of Dr. Anna Pou and two nurses who Foti said acted criminally in the deaths of nine patients at Memorial Medical Center in the days after Katrina.
He said he decided to run again for sheriff after his former employees and political supporters begged him. As sheriff, Foti oversaw a massive transformation as the facility ballooned from 800 inmates to a jail with more than 7,000 beds. There are now about 2,000 inmates.
Reached by a reporter at about 9:15 p.m., long after it was clear he would lose, Foti declined to concede. By the time Gusman finished his brief remarks, Foti had turned off his phone.
366 of 366 precincts votes pct.
Marlin Gusman 40,068 67%
Charles Foti 19,996 33%
]]></text></news-item>