<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0335-3E54-2355-C868"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Fracking critics are preventing job opportunities</title><source>The Courier (Findlay, Ohio)</source><author>MARK CARES</author><text><![CDATA[A sign on the outskirts of Cygnet, south of Toledo, is one of the few remaining reminders of northwestern Ohio's oil boom. It reads, "Established in 1885 rich in oil history."
To those unfamiliar with Cygnet's history, it's hard to imagine that this small town, population 597, was once the center of a major oil discovery. Today, instead of derricks, the rich farmland is planted in corn and soybeans with only an occasional pumpjack here and there.
Although Cygnet is no longer a major oil-producing community, Ohio is experiencing another energy boom due to the Utica and Devon Shale formations. In the third quarter of 2013, Utica wells alone produced 1.3 million barrels of oil and 33.6 billion cubic feet of natural gas. It's believed that unconventional drilling in the Utica Shale could outproduce Ohio's traditional vertical wells by 2015.
But despite the success of the Utica wells, thanks to horizontal drilling and hydraulic fracturing, critics are continuing to look for ways to stop drilling activity in its tracks. Their weapons are fear and loathing aimed at scaring and angering Ohio residents with tall tales short on facts about contaminated water, environmental damage, and a never-initiated pro-development PR campaign.
As an oilfield worker who has been involved in fracking operations in Ohio, I can state unequivocally that these complaints are politically-inspired distractions that have little to do with the facts about fracking. Fracking is safe and effective.
Look across the state border to Michigan. Since the 1970s, over 12,000 wells have been fracked and re-fracked at depths 300 to 2,000 feet below the surface, well within the water table. There has been not one proven case of well water pollution. Ohio's shale is well over 5,000 feet below the surface.
To date, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency has found no recorded incident in which fracking has polluted drinking water. Yet critics continue to call for federal oversight, assuming that federal regulations will somehow be better than state statutes. They are wrong.
A 2009 study by the prestigious Ground Water Protection Council, which represents water quality regulators, found that federal regulations would be "duplicative" of state laws and too far removed from drilling operations to be effective.
Ohio's oil and natural gas operations are regulated by the ODNR's Division of Mineral Resources Management. In 2010, the agency invited an outside group of experts to review its hydraulic fracturing oversight effectiveness.
The study called Ohio's fracking program "well-managed" and "professional" and noted that it is "meeting its program objectives." Furthermore, the study commended the agency for its efforts to prevent contamination from fracking.
Perhaps most importantly, the study notes that an estimated 80,000 wells were fracked in Ohio between 1951 and 2010, adding that "agencies have not identified a single instance where groundwater has been contaminated by hydraulic fracturing operations."
Testifying before a congressional panel, former EPA Administrator Lisa Jackson said, "I'm not aware of any proven case where the fracking process itself has affected water ..."
And while many of Ohio's citizens may view me, an oilfield worker, as a tourist with a sledgehammer and coveralls, I have a job to do. You all have your grandparents' experiences and stories to fall back onto. And if you do not speak up, then you will let a minority of environmental extremists push their personal agenda against your best interests and future.
Ohio and U.S. energy policy should not be held hostage by naysayers who use unsubstantiated fears to delay or stop tried-and-true technologies. Their Luddite-like philosophy could harm Ohio's slow but steady job growth. Today, Ohio's unemployment rate stands at 7.5 percent, higher than the national average, but far better than it was before Utica Shale development.
By standing in the way of progress, fracking critics prevent job opportunities for thousands of Ohio workers who would prefer to work rather than accept a handout from the government.
Cares is an oil field worker from Williamsport, Pa., who has spent the last two years working in and around Ohio.
]]></text></news-item>