<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="03F3-F238-B4BA-BC66"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Ex-head of top court: Those involved in graft will be punished sooner or later</title><source>Cihan News Agency (CNA)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ISTANBUL (CIHAN)- Former Supreme Court of Appeals president Sami Selçuk has said that everyone who is currently trying to block an ongoing corruption and bribery investigation, which has implicated four government ministers, several bureaucrats and various renowned businessmen, will be tried at some point in the future.
Sharing his assessment on recent issues as part of a Samanyolu News TV program on Thursday evening, Selçuk criticized Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan for describing the recent corruption and bribery probe, which became public on Dec. 17 of last year with simultaneous police operations, as a civilian coup designed to overthrow his government, stating that no coup has ever been staged by civilians in Turkey. Stating that the word "coup" has lost its meaning due to overuse by government officials, Selçuk noted that it is nonsensical to call a corruption probe a coup, adding: "The definition of a coup is clearly stated in the law. This argument is a fallacy from start to finish." Pointing to what he called another fallacy, namely the theory of a "parallel structure" within the state that has been repeated by top government officials, particularly Erdogan, in the last three months, Selçuk stated that if there were the kind of parallel state described by the government, it should be tackled with evidence. "There is considerable proof of the suspects' crimes in the probe. Their activities are quite clear. All of them will be punished for their actions," Selçuk added. In reference to voice recordings posted on social media by a pseudonymous Twitter user, which allegedly provide evidence of top government officials, including Erdogan and his son Bilal Erdogan, being involved in bribery and corruption, Selçuk stated: "If someone believes he is innocent, he or she has to turn to the judiciary to prove his or her innocence. The problem here is that you [the implicated officials] haven't appealed to the judiciary, and you say that all these things are purely lies. The people are not the ones who decide whether you have committed corruption. Do you [the government] believe that you will be cleared of the corruption allegations when you receive 99 percent of the vote in the upcoming local elections? The authority to do this rests with the judiciary." Noting that a prosecutor does not need permission from anyone before he launches an investigation, Selçuk went on to say: "Although a prosecutor is required to ask permission from his chief before a probe, the prosecutor has to collect or seize evidence in advance and then has to place this evidence in front of his chief and ask for permission to move further in his probe. The Chief Public Prosecutor's Office doesn't have to consult the police department, the prime minister or the justice minister to grant permission for a probe. If these [the non-judicial authorities] ever intervene in the process of launching a probe, that means they have clearly committed a crime."
Selçuk added: "No matter how much they [government officials] cry and shout at people [in rallies and public meetings], they will not be able to cover up their crimes. An investigation file can wait. Sooner or later you will have to face the crimes you have committed. Sooner or later they will be prosecuted for their deeds. No one should believe they can get away with their crimes. We will all see in the future." Since the corruption investigation began, in addition to thousands of police officers, the government has replaced the prosecutors who initiated the probe as well as others in public prosecutors' offices and dozens of officials at various state institutions. The reassignments have been seen as government attempts to block the major corruption probe and potential future probes as well. Over 8,000 police officers from across the country have been reassigned since December of last year in an extensive transformation of the police force. (Cihan/Today's Zaman) CIHANCopyright © 2014 Cihan News Agency.
]]></text></news-item>