<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0401-4E61-D4FC-5C7A"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Blotter 3/16/14</title><source>Belleville News-Democrat (Illinois)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The following incidents were listed among the official reports of local law enforcement agencies and court clerks. Readers are reminded that an arrest or charge does not constitute a finding of guilt. Only a court of law can make that determination.
ST. CLAIR COUNTY FELONIES
WEDNESDAY, MARCH 12
Joey N. Farias, 35, 106 N. 12th St., East Carondelet, was arrested on suspicion of aggravated domestic battery/strangulation and two counts of domestic battery/physical contact, on or about March 10 by St. Clair County Sheriff. Farias, in committing a domestic battery, allegedly intentionally strangled Danielle Farias, a family/household member of the defendant, in that the defendant placed his hands around the throat of Danielle Farias and applied pressure, thereby impeding the normal breathing of Danielle Farias. Farias also allegedly struck Danielle Farias' head against the steering wheel of a vehicle and struck her head with his head. Bail ws set at $50,000.
Brandon T. White, 27, 1203 N. Enterprise Way St., Marion, was arrested on suspicion of two counts of aggravated fleeing on or about March 10 by Marissa police. White, while operating a motor vehicle, was given a visual signal by a police officer Steve Laramore, who was in police uniform and driving a police vehicle, directly the defendant to bring said vehicle to a stop, allegedly willfully fled or attempted to elude the police officer. The defendant allegedly disobeyed two or more official traffic control devices and caused property damage in excess of $300.
Larry B. Alverson, 39, homeless, was arrested on suspicion of residential burglary and unlawful restraint on or about March 9 by Belleville police. Alverson allegedly, knowingly and without authority, remained within the dwelling place a female minor, located at 508 S. 22nd St., Belleville with the intent to commit therein an unlawful restraint. He allegedly physically prevented the minor from leaving her bedroom.
THURSDAY, MARCH 13
Matthew J. Gendron, 25, of 1002 N. Lincoln Ave., O'Fallon, was arrested on suspicion of stalking and phone harassment from between Sept. 15, 2013 and March 9 by Fairview Heights police. Gendron allegedly, engaged in a course of conduct directed at a specific person, REbecca Stetzen, and he knew or should have known that this course of conduct would cause a reasonable person to fear for ther safety; used telephone communication to cause the telephone of another, Rebecca Stetzen, to repeatedly ring, with the intent to harass Rebecca.
Corey R. Keys, 23, of 6 cathy Ann Drive, Belleville, was arrested on suspicion of attempted burglary on or about March 11 by Faiview Heights police. Keys allegedly, with the intent to commit the offence of burglary, performed a substantial step toward the commission of that offense, in that he knowingly and without authority, tried to enter into a building, being Neuropsychiatric Services, located at 10111 Lincoln Trail, Fairview Heights, with the intent to commit theft therein.
Montrell D. Spencer, 20 of 1624 N. 23rd St., East St. Louis, was arrested on suspicion of first degree murder, on or about Feb. 22 by Illinois State Police. Spencer allegedly, discharged a firearm into an occupied vehicle knowing such an act created strong probability of death or great bodily harm to Leon Lucas Jr., a passenger of said vehicle, thereby causing the death of Leon Lucas Jr.
Vonzell D. Williams, 29, of 1308 Hall St., Murphysboro, was arrested on suspicion of unlawful possession of a controlled substance and aggravated fleeing and attempting to elude a police officer on or about March 12 by Brooklyn police. Williams allegedly, had in his possession a substance containing phencyclidine; while operating a motor vehicle, a silver 2009 Kia Rio, was given a visual signal by a police officer, Dean Anderson, who was in police uniform and driving a vehicle which displayed illuminated, oscilliating, rotating or flashing red or blue lights which when used in conjunction with an audible horn or siren would indicate the vehicle to be an official police vehicle, directing the defendant to bring said silver 2009 Kia Rio to a stop, willfully fled or attempted to elude the police officer and that when willfully fleeing or attempting to elude the police officer, the defendant disobeyed two or more official traffic control devices, being stop signs.
Marcus E. Stewart, 42, of 1401 N. Illinois St., Swansea, was arrested on suspicion of aggravated unlawful possession of stolen motor vehicle on or about March 11 by Metro East Auto Theft Task Force. Stewart allegedly, a person who was the driver of a red 2012 Mazda, who was not entitled to the possession of that vehicle and who knew that the vehicle was stolen, willfully failed to obey the direction of a peace officer who had signaled said defendant to bring said vehicle to a stop.
Tony D. Sayles, 46, of 124 Liberty Torch Court, Belleville, was arrested on suspicion of unlawful possession of a controlled substance on or about March 11 by Metro East Auto Theft Task Force. Sayles allegedly, had in his possession less than 15 grams of a substance containing cocaine.
Laquesar Stringfellow, 25, of 229 Freedom Drive, Belleville, was arrested on suspicion of forgery on or about March 11 by Washington Park police. Stringfellow allegedly, with the intent to defraud, knowingly delivered to Shop Wise Food Mart, a retail establishment, located at 4715 Caseyville Ave., Washington Park, a document apparently capable of defrauding another, in that it was purported to have been made by another, a representative of Staffing Synergies, Inc., said document being a check, drawn on the Bank of Edwardsvislle, dated March 7, payable to Laquesa Ronesha Stringfellow in the amount of $406.52, knowing the document to have been thus made.
Eugene D. Compton Jr., 34, of 507 S. Benton St., New Athens, arrested on suspicion of retail theft, subsequent on or about Jan. 21 by Belleville police. Compton allegedly, took merchandise from Shop N Save, 4201 North Belt West, Belleville, being one bottle of Tangueray Gin, total retail value not in excess of $300. Defendant had been previously convicted of Retail Theft on Aug. 12, 2013.
Kasey T. Richardson, 17, of 3908 W. Main St., 6G, Belleville, arrested on suspicion of armed robbery, aggravated robbery and aggravated fleeing police on or about March 11 by Cahokia police. Richardson allegedly, while carrying a firearm on his person, knowingly took property, being U.S. currency, from Tanya Munie, by use or threat of force; while indicating his actions to Tanya Munie that he had a firearm, knowingly took property, being U.S. currency from the presence of Tanya Munie, by the use of force or by threatening the imminent use of force; while operating a motor vehicle, a green Pontiac Gran Prix displaying no registration paltes, was given a visual sign by a police officer, Patrolman Eric Waszak, who was in police uniform and driving a vehicle which displayed illuminated, oscillating, rotating or flashing red or blue lights which when used in conjunction with an audible horn or siren would indicate the vehicle to be an official police vehicle, directing Kasey Richardson to bring said Pontiac Gran Prix to a stop, willfully fled or attempted to elude the police officer and that when wilfully fleeing or attempting to elude thepolice officer, traveled at a rate of speed 21 mph over the legal speed limit.
Kevin L. Richardson, 25, of 5409 Sterling AVe., Centreville, arrested on suspicion of armed robbery, aggravated robbery and aggravated fleeing on March 11 by Cahokia police. Richardson allegedly, while carrying a firearm on his person, knowingly took property, being U.S. currency, from the presence of Tanya Munie, by use or threat of force; while indicating by his actions to Tanya Munie that he had a firearm, knowingly took property, being U.S. currency from the presence of Tanya Munie, by the use of force or by threatening the imminent use of force; while operating a motor vehicle, a green Pontiac Gran Prix displaying no registration plates, was given a visual sign by a police officer, Patrolman ERic Waszek, who was in police unifrom and driving a vehicle which displayed illuminated, oscillating, rotating or flashing red or blue lights which when used in conjunction with an audible horn or siren would indicate the vehicle to be an official police vehicle, directing Richardson to bring said Pontiac Gran Prix to a stop, willfully fled or attempted to elude the police officer and that when willfully fleeing or attempting to elude the police officer, traveled at a rate of speed 21 mph over the legal speed limit.
ST. CLAIR COUNTY SHERIFF
FRIDAY, MARCH 7
Alonzo A. Smith, 28, of Washington Park, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Kemonde L. Wilson, 29, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Justin D. Case, 35, of Collinsville, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Allen M. Harvey, 24, of St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of probation violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Kyshawn J. Jennings, 33, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of unlawful use of a weapon by Alorton police.
Deborah J. Dougherty, 60, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of two counts of driving under the influence and traffic violation by Illinois State Police.
Harry S. Odell, 35, of Belleville, warrant arrest by Fairview Heights police.
Ronald E. Juniel, 29, of Centreville, arrested on suspicion of possession of cannabis and warrant arrest by O'Fallon police.
Loren E. Chitwood, 21, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of driving under the influence and traffic violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Grant E. Huff, 34, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of driving under the influence and traffic accidents by Swansea police.
Larry D. Overall, 19, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Triston J. Roberts, 26 of Centreville, arrested on suspicion of probation violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Edrick O. Wicks, 35, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of probation violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Douglas A. Wallace, 39, of Collinsville, warrant arrest by New Athens police.
Eric D. Oliver, 25, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by East St. Louis police.
Demetris L. Beaver, 41, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of probation violation by East St. Louis police.
Traveon O. Gamble, 21, of Alorton, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Anthony J. Finchen, 46, of Cahokia, arrested on suspicion of possession of methamphetamine and probation violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Demetrous L. Harris, 35, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of possession of a controlled substance and warrant arrest by East St. Louis police.
Demarcus C. Spraggins, 20, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of probation violation by East St. Louis police.
Derrick Henry, 44, of Alorton, arrested on suspicion of probation violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Cortez D. Smith, 34, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of possession of cannabis, possession of drug equipment and probation violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Antonio D. Oliver, 23, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by East St. Louis police.
Brendan C. Smith, 37, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of possession of cannabis and multiple warrant arrest by East St. Louis police.
Ricky McGary, 30, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
John K. Houston, 35, of Cahokia, arrested on suspicion of aggravated domestic battery by Cahokia police.
Ricky A. Jones, 22, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of stalking by Belleville police.
Kenny B. McCline, 34, of Centreville, arrested on suspicion of delivery or possession with intent by St. Clair County sheriff.
Bobby A. Daniel, 31, of Cahokia, arrested on suspicion of delivery or possession with intent by St. Clair County sheriff.
Crystal M. Stephens, 25, of Collinsville, arrested on suspicion of interference with emergency equipment and resisting, obstructing or disarming a peace officer by St. Clair County sheriff.
SATURDAY, MARCH 8
Vance S. Johnson, 58, of Belleville, multiple warrant arrest by Belleville police.
Larry L. Harper, 24, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of motor vehicle theft by Lebanon police.
Bud G. Rhodes, 35, of Red Bud, multiple warrant arrest by Millstadt police.
Darell F. Morris, 25, of St. Louis, warrant arrest by Illinois State police.
Robert M. Davis, 31, of St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of unlawful use of a weapon and multiple warrant arrest by Brooklyn police.
Trymaine J. Davis, 24, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of obstructing justice and two traffic violations by Swansea police.
Arnitha N. Turner, 27, of Cahokia, warrant arrest by Cahokia police.
Derrick E. Hickman, 29, of Roxana, arrested on suspicion of suspended or revoked driver's license by Fairview Heights police.
Brandon J. Jackson, 30, of Fairview Heights, arrested on suspicion of aggravated domestic battery by Fairview Heights police.
Jason C. Kennedy, 44, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of suspened or revoked driver's license, obstructing justice, two traffic violations by Smithton police.
Erin S. Shanks, 20, of Swansea, arrested on suspicion of theft of $300 and criminal damage to property by Swansea police.
Curtis D. Fenton, 24, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Chase A. Robinson, 23, of Cahokia, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Keldon T. Moore, 22, of Alorton, arrested on suspicion of criminal trespass to land.
William C. Kramer Jr., 28, of New Athens, warrant arrest by New Athens police.
Quinton C. Chaney, 22, of Belleville, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Albert T. Ivory, 37, of East St. Louis, multiple warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Mario A. Foster, 35, of Lovejoy, arrested on suspicion of possession of cannabis by St. Clair County sheriff.
Tonnie T. Robinson, 23, of Shiloh, warrant arrest by Dupo police.
Jonathan D. Klein, 33, of O'Fallon, arrested on suspicion of driving under the influence, suspended or revoked driver's license, five traffic violations by Illinois State police.
Todd A. Halt, 42, of Waterloo, arrested on suspicion of driving under the influence and traffic violation by Illinois State Police.
Kouri J. Collins, 22, of St. Louis, multiple warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
SUNDAY, MARCH 9
Li Yongsheng, 47, of Indianapolis, Ind., arrested on suspicion of illegal entry, alien by Illinois State Police.
Elroy Sims, 45, of Washington Park, arrested on suspicion of theft from building by Fairmont City police.
Otis D. Scott, 50, of Washington Park, arrested on suspicion of retail theft and warrant arrest by Fairmont City police.
Keith A. Muckensturm, 35, of Shiloh, arrested on suspicion of possession of a controlled substance by St. Clair County sheriff.
Stephen M. Pray, 37, of O'Fallon, multiple warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Travis L. Dallas, 34, of Caseyville, arrested on suspicion of probation violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Marc S. White, 20, of Milstadt, arrested on suspicion of driving under the influence and traffic accidents by St. Clair County sheriff.
Joshua M. Robinson, 25, of Belleville, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Andrew Brazier, 23, of Cahokia, arrested on suspicion of delivery of cannabis by St. Clair County sheriff.
MONDAY, MARCH 10
Bernie J. Gildehaus, 59, of O'Fallon, arrested on suspicion of possession of a controlled substance by O'Fallon police.
Brandon T. White, 27 of Marion, multiple warrant arrest by Marissa police.
Derrick A. Barnes, 32, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of no registration, operating uninsured motor vehicle and suspended or revoked driver's license by St. Clair County sheriff.
Everrett J. Jacks, 31, of Granite City, arrested on suspicion of operating uninsured motor vehicle, suspended or revoked driver's license and traffic violation by Swansea police.
Edeisha D. Rush, 22, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of battery and all other disorderly conduct by Belleville police.
Tony D. Cotton, 38, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of suspended or revoked driver's license by St. Clair County sheriff.
Jeremiah J. Beison Jr., 28, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by East St. Louis police.
Veronica A. Morris, 52, of St. Louis, warrant arrest by Cahokia police.
Patrice A. Austin, 33, of Cahokia, arrested on suspicion of driving under the influence, operating uninsured motor vheicle, suspended or revoked driver's license and traffic violation by Cahokia police.
Levada Brown, 63, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Arturo Cruz, 22, of Imperial, Mo., arrested on suspicion of driving under the inflouence, traffic violation and traffic accidents by Cahokia police.
Marvell F. Rogers, 29, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of probation violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Andre F. Parks, 24, of Belleville, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Bryant K. Lee, 45, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of battery, two counts of resisting, obstructing or disarming a peace office and warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Michael L. Wright, 41, of Washington Park, arrested on suspicion of aggravated battery and resisting, obstructing or disarming a peace officer by Belleville police.
Cicero C. Maple, 29, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of unalwful possession of a weapon and warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Kevin M. Johnson, 23, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of probation violation by Fairview Heights police.
Scott T. Hyden, 23, of Edwardsville, arrested on suspicion of unlawful sale of a weapon and multiple warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Trinese Y. Johnson, 39, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by Belleville police.
Carl K. Calbert, 35, of Swansea, arrested on suspicion of harassment by telephone by Swansea police.
Cortez C. Guyton, 24, of Sparta, multiple warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Jason M. Buck, 27, of Collisnville, arrested on suspicion of credit card fraud by St. Clair County sheriff.
TUESDAY, MARCH 11
Carl R. Townsend, 44, of O'Fallon, multiple warrant arrest by O'Fallon police.
Willie C. Williams, 23, of Belleville, multiple warrant arrest by Swansea police.
Richard R. Kane, 57, of Troy, arrested on suspicion of failure to register as a sex offender.
Dante M. Dixon, 20, of Belleville, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Zachary A. Cox, 20, Carbondale, warrant arrest by Fairview Heights police.
Brian D. Watson, 21, of Belleville, warrant arrest by Belleville police.
James Bohanna Jr., 43, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by Fairview Heights police.
Keith A. Baker, 44, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Merissa J. Bradley, arrested on suspicion of neglect of a child by St. Clair County sheriff.
Antown D. Nelson, 21, of Cahokia, arrested on suspicion of assault and possession of cannabis by St. Clair County sheriff.
Arbree L. Hudson, 24, of Belleville, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Nica L. Lovett, 22, of Belleville, warrant arrest by Belleville police.
Steven A. Williams, 26, of Washington Park, arrested on suspicion of probation violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Demario L. Cleveland, 28, of Shiloh, arrested on suspicion of possession of a controlled substance and warrant arrest by O'Fallon police.
Ruben A. Vital, 31, of Collisnville, arrested on suspicion of suspended or revoked driver's license by St. Clair County sheriff.
John L. Hightower, 30, St. Louis, multiple warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Marquita L. Toller, 30, of Belleville, warrant arrest by Swansea police.
David L. Lauer Jr., 46, of Centreville, arrested on suspicion of probation violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Brett R. Spinner, 21, of East Carondelet, multiple warrant arrest by Dupo police.
Toneeko J. Miller, 34, of St. Louis, multiple warrant arrest by Swansea police.
WEDNESDAY, MARCH 12
Charlene N. Otey, 31, of St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of operating uninsured motor vheicle, suspended or revoked driver's licnese and traffic violation by Swansea police.
Audley A. Lyons, 31, of Centreville, warrant arrest by Belleville.
Larry P. Alverson, 39, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of residential burglary by Belleville police.
Ratravion D. Wade, 26, of Fairview Heights, warrant arrest by East St. Louis police.
Chris A. Pearson, 48, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of battery and probation violation by East St. Louis police.
Cortez R. Prater, 44, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of violation of orders of protection by East St. Louis police.
Markus T. Walton, 28, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Trina A. Jackson, 47, of Alorton, arrested on suspicion of obstructing justice and multiple warrant arrest by Norfork Southern Railroad.
William H. Garrett, 54, of St. Louis, warrant arrest by Illinois State Police.
Matthew J. Gendron, 25, of O'Fallon, arrested on suspicion of harassment by telephone by telephone by Fairview Heights police.
Lauren A. Ordiway, 25, of Belleville, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Marcus E. Stewart, 42, of East St. Louis, multiple warrant arrest by Belleville police.
Michael A. Meier, 29, of Belleville, multiple warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Terrence D. Hunter, 31, of Belleville, warrant arrest by Freeburg police.
John J. Villa, 20, of Belleville, warrant arrest by Dupo police.
Kelly E. Crook, 22, of Centralia, warrant arrest by Millstadt police.
THURSDAY, MARCH 13
Kyle G. Korobey, 22, of Belleville, warrant arrest by Belleville police.
Heather N. Manley, 33, of Fairview Heights, multiple warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Paisha C. Eastman, 38, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Sanchez D. James II, 32, of Cahokia, multiple warrant by Illinois State Police.
Dondre T. Lewis, 21, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Cameron Schooler, 37, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of probation violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Andre Jackson, 25, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of probation violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Marshawn M. Heard, 28, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of resisting, obstructing or disarming a police officer by St. Clair County sheriff.
Montrell D. Spencer, 20, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of first degree murder by East St. Louis police.
Joshua M. Phelps, 19, of O'Fallon, arrested on suspicion of criminal damage to property by St. Clair County sheriff.
Nickie B. Schlegel, 43, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of domestic battery by Belleville police.
Markeez J. Jones, 20, of East St. Louis, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Kevin L. Richardson, 25, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of armed robbery by Cahokia police.
Pamela R. Patterson, 62, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of retail theft and probation violation by St. Clair County sheriff.
Ashlie C. Harris, 26, of Belleville, arrested on suspicion of aggravated battery and warrant arrest by Fairview Heights police.
Santorrian M. Winters, 36, of Cahokia, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Justin D. Bishop, 22, of Caollinsville, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Joshua P. Jefferson, 22, of Collinsville, warrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
Dominique D. Williams-Kelly, 20 of washington Park, arrested on suspicion of domestic battery by Brooklyn police.
Donald White, 47 of Caseyville, multiple warrant arrest by Caseyville police.
William V. Alexander, 46, of East St. Louis, arrested on suspicion of operating uninsured motor vehicle, suspended or revoked driver's license and multiple wrrant arrest by St. Clair County sheriff.
]]></text></news-item>