<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="04B9-C192-F7A3-4A4F"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Abbott has prosecuted dozens of officials</title><source>Austin American-Statesman (Texas)</source><author>Sue Owen American-Statesman Staff</author><text><![CDATA[Texas Attorney General Greg Abbott drew heat for a February speech in which he likened official corruption scandals in Texas-Mexico border counties to "third-world practices."
His comparison drew criticism from lawmakers, the McAllen newspaper and his main opponent in the governor's race, state Sen. Wendy Davis, D-Fort Worth, who said, "Abbott even went as far as comparing the Texas border to a third-world country."
Responding to such criticism, Abbott said in an opinion article in the McAllen Monitor newspaper that his concerns about corruption expressed in his speech "apply wherever corruption is found."
"Public service is a public trust," Abbott wrote. "As attorney general, I have prosecuted judges, district attorneys and other public officials across Texas who violated that trust, who have been corrupted."
We were curious about that, especially since the primary job of the attorney general is representing the state in civil matters. Still, state law permits the attorney general to help prosecute a criminal case if a local prosecutor requests assistance.
We asked Abbott's office for information on the prosecutions he referred to in his commentary.
Spokeswoman Lauren Bean sent us a list of 104 prosecutions handled by his office since Abbott became attorney general in late 2002. The attorney general's office was the lead prosecutor in the vast majority of the cases, she told us.
The list included cases involving public officials from dog catcher (a child pornography case that ended in a guilty verdict) through higher city and county officials, tax assessors, sheriffs, justices of the peace, judges, assistant district attorneys and one former district attorney (who pleaded guilty to paying himself and others more than $2 million illegally while in office).
Crimes involving child pornography and taking public funds are certainly violations of the public trust, though we also wondered how many of Abbott's cases involved corruption like the examples he presented in his "third-world" speech: a former state district judge sentenced to six years in prison for his role in a cash-for-favors scheme; a former sheriff's captain who took bribes from drug traffickers; and law enforcement officials who stole drugs and resold them to dealers.
So, we set aside the prosecutions on Abbott's list that did not immediately appear to relate to misusing a public office. Deleting DWI cases, child pornography or indecency, murder, assault/injury, sexual offenses and gambling left 61 prosecutions on Abbott's list.
Eleven of those 61 prosecutions cited theft by a public servant. Others fell into criminal offense categories including bribery, breach of public integrity, official oppression, election violations, fraud and abuse of official capacity, as well as misappropriation or misallocation of public funds or property. The type of case in one prosecution involving an assistant county auditor was specifically given as "public corruption."
So certainly some of the prosecutions involved what ordinary citizens might regard as corruption.
Finally, we looked at whether the prosecutions occurred across Texas, as Abbott wrote, and at whether the prosecuted individuals included judges and district attorneys, as he said.
The 104 prosecutions occurred in about one-fourth of Texas' 254 counties - six on the border and 193 scattered elsewhere across the state.
Nine of Abbott's public-official prosecutions involved a judge, assistant district attorney, county attorney or district attorney (at the time of his crimes). Four seemed not to be related to abuse of office: a child pornography case, two drunken-driving cases and one case involving misdemeanor offensive contact with an employee.
The remaining five prosecutions involved a district judge in Childress County, a district judge in Kerrville, a district attorney in Corpus Christi, a Galveston County court-at-law judge and a West Texas county attorney.
Our ruling:
Abbott said, "As attorney general, I have prosecuted judges, district attorneys and other public officials across Texas who violated that (public) trust, who have been corrupted."
During Abbott's decade-plus as attorney general, his office has helped prosecute 104 cases against public officials across Texas - 61 of them appearing to involve public corruption and five of those against judges, a county attorney and a DA.
We rate his statement as True.
Contact Sue Owen
at 512-445-3882.
]]></text></news-item>