<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="05A5-4543-24DE-F421"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Hunter falls behind in broadband quest; OPINION &amp; ANALYSIS</title><source>Newcastle Herald (Australia)</source><author>Phillip O'Neill</author><text><![CDATA[LABOR'S communications spokesman, Jason Clare, came to Newcastle last week and slammed the federal Coalition government for its plans for the National Broadband Network. His comments made me shake my head and laugh.
Surely Labor can only blame itself for the digital backwater in which the Hunter now flounders. Labor's efforts during its six years of office from 2007 were dismal. Its ambition to build a network of fibre-optic cable reaching 93 per cent of homes was foolhardy. Its idea of building a monopoly company, NBN Co, to roll out the cable and sell internet services was naive. The people it appointed to run NBN Co failed to meet deadlines and targets. The capital cost blowout - which soared from $37.4 billion to $55.9 billion by late 2013 - was embarrassing.
The Coalition government has not yet revealed in full what it will do to fix the mess. But its Communications Minister, Malcolm Turnbull, had no choice but to trim NBN Co's cloth immediately, strip back its ambitions, and go back to the drawing board to see what is now possible.
The map shown here is listed on the Australian government's Department of Communications "My Broadband" website. It shows that broadband services in Newcastle and the lower Hunter are as bad as they can possibly be. Apart from the Williamtown RAAF base with its own high-speed arrangements, and two unexplained red splodges towards the end of the F3, all our suburbs and towns are rated shades of beige, meaning you can't get worse.
If you hunt around the other maps on the "My Broadband" site, you find that Newcastle and its lower Hunter periphery have the worst broadband quality of any Australian urban region save for Darwin. We are well behind all the capital cities and well behind Canberra, Gold Coast, Geelong and Launceston. We get beige cul-de-sacs, they get purple and red superhighways.
Our internet beige-ness arrived in the early 2000s when Telstra introduced ADSL2+ broadband - or fraud-band as many call it - on its old copper wires. And beige it remained for the two terms of federal Labor, 2007 to 2013. All its eggs were in the NBN Co basket and Labor failed to deliver.
Some, including me, warned of the NBN Co inadequacies. One was that Labor's plan didn't include fibre-optic cable for many Hunter townships and villages, especially those in Joel Fitzgibbon's Hunter electorate and the western reaches of Greg Combet's Charlton electorate. These were only ever going to receive lower-speed services running off micro-wave towers.
Yet our Labor representatives failed to press our case. Why would they? They knew they had our votes. We are loyal. But we are put upon as a result.
Beige quality means our download speeds - for email, visiting websites, downloading games and videos - run at no more than about 15 megabytes per second. In contrast, fibre-optic cable delivers 1000 megabytes (a gigabyte) a second.
For uploads, ADSL2+ delivers two to three megabytes per second at best. The professional and commercial world can't survive on such a miserable trickle. Businesses, schools, colleges, universities, hospitals and medical firms need to send off information quickly. Fibre-optic cable gives fast upload speeds to firms in architecture, engineering, media, design and so on so they can get on with their work.
Newcastle and the lower Hunter should be excelling in these fields. But we aren't. World-worst, beige, broadband speeds are prohibiting investment in these 21st century jobs-creating sectors.
In the early 2000s, prior to Labor's idiotic NBN Co plan, there were proposals for privately run fibre-optic cable networks for Newcastle. One pre-Labor broadband provider survives, Ipera, with a selective cable roll out in inner Newcastle. Maybe you are one of its lucky high-speed customers.
Then in 2005, following its sale of Telstra, the Howard Coalition government set aside funding for a $3 billion high-speed wireless network for rural and regional Australia, including for the Hunter.
But Labor grabbed this money and gave it to NBN Co. And then federal legislation stomped on the private providers. And the Hunter got nought.
Instead, we struggle on the old copper. During the day, it gives modest service to a light household user. But then it slows noticeably within minutes of the kids in the neighbourhood arriving home from school and jumping on to to Facebook and Angry Birds.
Labor spruiked its NBN Co by pointing to the advantages of high-speed broadband: smart energy use, on-line medical help, innovation and investment in companies that didn't need to congregate in capital cities any longer, home-based education, amazing entertainment options.
All around the world, high speed internet is now delivering these services.
But not here in the Hunter. And who do you think is to blame? And when will our beige existence end?
Phillip O'Neill is a professorial
research fellow at the University
ofWestern Sydney.
]]></text></news-item>