<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="05A7-663C-6128-D430"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Riverfront Vs Riverfront</title><source>Free Press Journal (India)</source><author>FPJ Bureau</author><text><![CDATA[Sabarmati Riverfront Development Project is as unique for riverfront development as it is for social inclusiveness. Although the project has been acclaimed and awarded on various facets, both nationally and internationally; it's social inclusiveness hasn't been understood and appreciated yet.
Ideas of developing Sabarmati River began in 1960s. In 1997, Sabarmati Riverfront Development Corporation Ltd. was formed by Ahmadabad Municipal Corporation but work began in 2004. In 2012, KPMG included Ahmadabad's Sabarmati Riverfront Development Project (SRDP) in the list of '100 Most Innovative Projects' towards urban regeneration.
True appreciation of an achievement is possible by 'Comparison and Contrast Method'. Following is a comparison between 'Yamuna Riverfront Development Scheme', New Delhi with SRDP.
The Second Master Plan of Delhi - 2001, stated: "The possibilities in respect of river Yamuna have been studied in depth and indications are that it could be channelised within 550mt. width and an area of about 3000-4000 hectares could become available for river front development" (DDA 1999)
DDA prepared a Rs 18 billion (at March 1992 Prices) development scheme for Yamuna riverfront. (Gupta 1995). The scheme envisaged development of 8000 hectares of riverbed area for recreational, residential, commercial, institutional and public purpose with private sector funding to the extent of over 60% of the total project cost. ('Inside the Transforming Urban Asia: Processes, Policies, and Public Actions' edited by Darshini Mahadevia.)
While the riverfront development in Yamuna is yet to start, lot of things related to it have happened in Yamuna in the name of development, such as removing slums.
"What the Eye Does Not See: The Yamuna in the Imagination of Delhi, by Amita Baviskar published in Economic & Political Weekly, December 10, 2011, Vol xlvi No 50 is my source on the status of Yamuna and Yamuna Riverfront Development Project.
Since 1980s, the encouragement of Congress politicians led to settlement of 3, 50,000 squatters on both sides of Yamuna . In 2004, defecation along the Yamuna became the ground of demolition of their homes. An estimated 1, 50, 000 were displaced in one week of June from Sanjay Amar Colony, (western side) of river.
As per Delhi government policy they were eligible to receive, a plot of 18 square metres (upon payment of Rs 7,000) to 12.5 square metres. Resettlement colonies such as Bhalaswa and Holambi Kalan were with no amenities, and 20-30 kilometres from people's place of work (Menon-Sen and Bhan 2008). Only 16% of displaced were given plots. Evictions from the east bank in the summer of 2006 left more than 50,000 squatters homeless, most received no compensation.
As far as slums are concerned, Sabarmati riverbed was no exception. Exception came in the form of dealing. Nearly 12000 hutments on both banks occupied nearly 20% of the critical project area. A committee was formed under an ex-High Court Judge for finalization of beneficiaries. A Comprehensive Settlement was arrived at under the supervision of the Gujarat High Court. More than 10,000 families have already been allotted houses of 26.77 sq m carpet area, in the prime locations of city. 9078 families, i.e. 6 Christian, 3874 Muslims and 5198 Hindus; have already shifted and remaining are under process. Complex has playing area for kids along with recreation facility. To empower women, houses are allocated in the name of the woman member or in joint name.
The SRDP revived the financial condition as well. Gurjari Bazaar is an age old Sunday Market, where women traders comprise close to 40% (half of these describe themselves as Dalits). The bazaar provides livelihood for an estimated 200,000 lower-income residents. Bazaar operated near Riverfront without any infrastructure and used to spill out on the adjoining roads. It was unhygienic and had the risk of flooding.
Today it is the first well developed informal market in India. Spread over 70,000 sq.mt on the river front and 1600 vendors can do their business on 778 pucca platforms and 783 laris. Parking space is provided for 280 two wheelers, 425 four wheelers (1700 two wheelers) and 8 heavy vehicles. Lights, toilets, food-court, drinking water, and seating area have been provided. More than 800 trees have been planted.
Washer men who use the river are accused of polluting the river, but it was different in Ahmadabad. There were nearly 172 Dhobis using the river bank for washing. They were relocated into the Dhobi ghat, constructed on the eastern bank
This is in sharp contrast to what happened in Yamuna. "Cleaning" of Yamuna, didn't take the form of installing sewage treatment facilities but entailed removal of people. Rivers are an intrinsic part of religion, but in her 22 km-long flow through Delhi, Yamuna is neither revered nor respected. Worshippers have to bathe in sewage.
Again, condition of Sabarmati was not different, but it changed. An interceptor sewer system was constructed on both the banks of the river to intercept the sewer running into the river through 36 drainage and divert it to the treatment plants.
Today, Sabarmati river plays an important role for all religious groups. Lord Jagannath is worshipped, with the Sabarmati water before the Rathyatra starts, Jains perform group Parna (Releasing fast though a ritual) and procession of Tajiya by Muslims concludes at the river.
Yamuna in Delhi is remembered only during floods or land scams. By 2007, selectively cleared of its encroachments, the Yamuna riverfront became a money spinner. Emaar MGF, the Dubai-based real estate developer was to build the Games Village under a public-private partnership arrangement. The DDA allotted 27 acres of prime land for free to the company to build 1,168 luxury flats for athletes and officials. Under the terms of the contract, the firm would sell two-thirds of the flats while DDA would sell the remainder. Later the company appealed to the government for help sighting financial constraint and the DDA responded by giving it an interest-free loan of $100 million, to be repaid in the form of additional flats.
The writer of this article is Sandeep Singh, author of 'Third Curve: Saga of Women and Child Development - Gujarat', www.swastik.net.in
]]></text></news-item>