<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="05CC-CB32-0D21-7984"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Stores shut down after 8-liner raids</title><source>Valley Morning Star (Harlingen, Texas)</source><author>Ed Asher, Valley Morning Star, Harlingen, Texas</author><text><![CDATA[March 15--HARLINGEN -- A Harlingen food store and gas station and a San Benito business were shut down in raids this week after investigators said they found illegal gambling taking place on the premises.
The businesses were illegally operating eight-liner game machines, the Cameron County District Attorney's Office said.
Law enforcement agents raided the Lone Star Food Store and gas station at 14755 W. Expressway 83 and The Prize Barn at 32360 FM 2520 Thursday night, the DA's Office said.
Authorities said the food store had four eight-liner machines with management paying out cash prizes.
The Prize Barn had 56 eight-liners with management paying out cash and items valued at more than $5, the District Attorney's office said.
The Prize Barn had 32 patrons operating the machines, officials said.
"Of additional concern was the locked rear exit door that prevented patrons from leaving in the event of an emergency," the DA's Office said in a release.
No arrests had been made as of Friday but the businesses remain under investigation, the release said.
The Harlingen and San Benito police departments assisted along with the DA's Office, county Office of Emergency Management and county Constable's Office Precinct 5.
District Attorney Luis Saenz began what he calls Operation Bishop last year to rid the county of eight-liner establishments.
"After almost a year since we launched Operation Bishop, everyone has to know that our office has been shutting down illegal gambling businesses," Saenz said.
"It is surprising to see people blatantly break the law even after the operation's continued enforcement."
According to state law and the Attorney General, eight-liner and sweepstakes businesses that give cash prizes of $5 or more, even if some or all proceeds benefit a non-profit/charity, are deemed an illegal gambling operation.
It is estimated that the eight-liner/sweepstakes industry generates at least $300 million annually, Saenz said.
___ (c)2014 Valley Morning Star (Harlingen, Texas) Visit Valley Morning Star (Harlingen, Texas) at www.valleymorningstar.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>