<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="05F2-5F8B-EAEA-0137"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Wanna Know More About Wannakuwatte?</title><source>Ponzi Clawbacks</source><author>Michael Hackard</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 14, 2014 (Ponzi Clawbacks:http://ponziclawbacks.com/ Delivered by Newstex) http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/files/2014/03/Deepal-Wannakuwatte.jpg Deepal Wannakuwatte Dental Town Accused Ponzi schemer Deepal Wannakuwatte has been formally indicted[1] on three counts of bank fraud. The 63-year-old Wannakuwatte, once the owner of the Sacramento Capitals tennis team[2], was presented with the charges yesterday in US District Court in Sacramento. He is alleged to have defrauded multiple investors of at least $125 million through his medical equipment businesses International Manufacturing Group (IMG) and RelyAid.
Wannakuwatte's indictment is more limited in scope in relation to the scheme; it focuses on an alleged incidence of bank fraud from 2011. In that year, the Sacramento businessman obtained a $4.5 million line of credit from Bridge Bank, purportedly to finance construction of manufacturing facility for latex gloves in the town of Olivehurst. According to federal prosecutors, however, this was accomplished through fraudulent means. Wannakuwatte is said to have fooled the bank into issuing the loan based upon the claim that IMG and RelyAid enjoyed around $100 million in annual contracts from the US Department of Veterans Affairs. Among other details, the government's indictment asserts that Wannakuwatte used false or doctored tax returns and financial statements to obtain the multimillion credit line. He is also accused of having an employee tell the bank that the VA owed RelyAid $25 million. The actual value of Wannakuwatte's contracts with the VA has been projected at around $25,000 a year. So what did Wannakuwatte do with the $4.5 million in credit he secured from Bridge Bank? The US Attorney's Office contends that $3 million of that amount was used to pay off a lawsuit filed by Bank of America over another loan, while most of the remainder was distributed as fictitious interest in the scheme or transferred to Wannakuwatte's pockets. Only $70,000 was used for the production of latex gloves. If Wannakuwatte doesn't reach a plea agreement with federal prosecutors, there's a high probability of more charges forthcoming due to the massive scale of the alleged scam. As Assistant US Attorney Benjamin Wagner noted: Our investigation is continuing and, unless this matter resolves very quickly, it is likely there will be additional charges. SEE THE DOCUMENTS: US v. Deepal Wannakuwatte Indictment[3] US v. Deepal Wannakuwatte Criminal Complaint[4] Search Warrant Affidavit[5] Search Warrant[6] Arrest Warrant[7] Detention Order[8] Financial Statements: RelyAid[9] Sammy Cemo v. Deepal Wannakuwatte Civil Complaint[10] IMG Funding v. Deepal Wannakuwatte Civil Complaint[11] Michael A. Hackard, Meriam Hansen, Nou Lee and Jeremy Rutledge are experienced in prosecuting civil actions against Ponzi scheme perpetrators as well as defending and resolving clawback cases filed by Bankruptcy Trustees and SEC Receivers. If you have been a victim in a Ponzi scheme and face legal action, contact Hackard Law[12] today. [1]: http://www.sacbee.com/2014/03/14/6236517/wannakuwatte-indicted-on-three.html [2]: http://www.bizjournals.com/sacramento/news/2014/03/13/former-world-teamtennis-owner-charged-with-bank.html [3]: http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/files/2014/03/US-v.-Deepal-Wannakuwatte-Indictment.pdf [4]: http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/files/2014/03/US-v.-Deepal-Wannakuwatte-Criminal-Complaint.pdf [5]: http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/files/2014/03/Deepal-Search-Warrant-Affidavit.pdf [6]: http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/files/2014/03/Deepal-Search-Warrant.pdf [7]: http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/files/2014/03/Deepal-Arrest-Warrant.pdf [8]: http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/files/2014/03/Deepal-Wannakuwatte-Detention-Order.pdf [9]: http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/files/2014/03/RelyAid-Financial-Statements.pdf [10]: http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/files/2014/03/Sammy-Cemo-v.-Wannakuwatte-Complaint.pdf [11]: http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/files/2014/03/IMG-Funding-v.-Deepal-Wannakuwatte-Civil-Complaint.pdf [12]: http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/contact/

]]></text></news-item>