<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="05F8-33CB-CAF7-621C"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>2014 session was historic for the state's air quality</title><source>Deseret Morning News (Salt Lake City)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[By Amy Joi
O'Donoghue
Deseret News
SALT LAKE CITY - The escalating angst over Utah's air pollution problems drove historic action in this latest budget-crafting legislative session, with the governor and lawmakers carving out a whole host of measures to cut emissions.
Public pressure helped to dial up the policy response to pollution and politicians were keenly aware they could not remain stuck in neutral on the path toward clean air.
Some say the gubernatorial and legislative action marked a turning point in Utah due to the general political acknowledgment that air pollution has become a public health problem demanding precise response.
"This realization we need to focus on the science and specific strategies shows a higher degree of understanding of the problem and a focused attempt to try to solve it," said Amanda Smith, executive director of the Utah Department of Environmental Quality.
Her agency received millions more this session in new money designed to tackle the problem. One block of funding, $1.4 million, is aimed squarely at research.
Smith said the successes playing out in the Uintah Basin Ozone study helped to direct that layer of attention to the fine particulate, or PM2.5 problem, along the Wasatch Front and in Tooele and Cache counties - the non-attainment areas in violation of federal clean air standards.
"We realized how little we know about precursor pollutants," she said, and how meteorological conditions create a complex chemistry problem with no readily apparent answers.
Armed with that new funding, Smith said the goal is to start to shore up that gap of local knowledge that exists about the area's ugly winter-time temperature inversions and the blanket of pollutants that become trapped.
"We will develop a study plan specifically for the Wasatch Front," she said.
Matt Pacenza, policy director for the HEAL Utah - a grass roots advocacy organization - said this last legislative session stands in marked contrast to other years when it comes to air pollution.
"You just have to acknowledge that most previous years you would get one or two bills that had to do with an air quality focus and in the worst years you had sessions where the staff who worked on this lost their jobs," he said. "Agencies were cut and they eliminated programs."
This year, lawmakers endorsed more than a dozen bills or appropriation requests related to air pollution. Overall, lawmakers directed $4.6 million at air quality this session, split between ongoing money and one-time allocations for specific programs.
"I think eight or nine bills passed and you have several millions of dollars in new money that is going to spent on the problem and new programs. There were some really solid, significant actions that were taken and I think everybody should be pleased about that," Pacenza said.
Lawmakers doled out money to reduce wood smoke pollution, convert dirty diesel engines and bumped tax credits for electric vehicles and plug-in hybrids.
They passed a mandate that 50 percent of the state's fleet be "clean" or highly fuel efficient by 2018 and provided new money to hire a state coordinator to keep an eye on what's being done by agencies to reduce emissions. In addition, they exempted new pollution controlling purchases by industry from sales tax and directed $400,000 at the air quality division for new staff to work on compliance issues.
Still, lawmakers failed to pass what many said would have been one of the most significant measures to cut air pollution - a bill that would have let counties put to ballot a sales tax increase to fund locally identified needs for more transit and bike paths.
"It wasn't just the environmental groups who wanted this. It was the cities and towns, the counties, the Salt Lake Chamber," Pacenza said. "There was broad based, mainstream Utah organizations that really worked hard on this. It would have meant tens of millions of dollars in investments designed to get people out of their cars."
There were other disappointments.
Utah Gov. Gary Herbert, who is pushing for the state's early adoption of Tier 3 standards involving cleaner fuel and cleaner cars, did not see the Legislature endorse a resolution of the Environmental Protection Agency rule, nor did he see the $14 million he wanted to replace old school buses.
"But it is not all or nothing this session," he said. "It has increased awareness and whatever we didn't finish this session we will come back and pick up in the next session, and do more," he said. "The good news is the air is getting cleaner and will continue to get cleaner."
Lawmakers did not repeal a law that forbids Utah regulators from invoking clean air standards tougher than the federal government, so that battle remains to be fought.
Advocates say their biggest fear is that the memory of the back-to-back ugly inversion seasons will be sullied by the clear skies of the coming months, and the issue of air pollution will trail away like a puff of smoke from public view.
"Folks who are concerned about air quality certainly have a lot left to do. We will be putting a lot of pressure on the Division of Air Quality to be bolder and pass tougher rules for industry," Pacenza said. "There is plenty of work left to be done beyond the Legislature."
Email: amyjoi@deseretnews.com
Twitter: amyjoi16
]]></text></news-item>