<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="068C-64FA-46FA-4CAC"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>@HD2 New Briefs head;Indonesian haze triggers #124airport closure – and #124impatience from president</title><source>The Nation (Thailand)</source><author>The Nation</author><text><![CDATA[@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;Worsening haze from forest and brush fires on Indonesia's Sumatra island forced the closure of an international airport, officials said yesterday.
Smog pollution reached hazardous levels in the island's Riau province, and has been linked to respiratory and skin problems in about 60,000 people, said Sutopo Purwo Nugroho, spokesman for the National Disaster Management Agency.
The Sultan Syarif Kasim airport in Riau capital Pekanbaru has been closed until Saturday, he said. Sixteen local and regional airlines serve the airport.
President SusiloBambang Yudhoyono urged local authorities to intensify their fire-fighting efforts.
"I instructed related ministries to conduct emergency operations using all means at their disposal," Yudhoyono said on his official Twitter account late on Thursday.
"Why does this thing keep happening at the expense of the people?" he said, adding he would take over the emergency response if local authorities were not able to bring the fires under control in the next day or two.
@HD2 New Briefs head;Teens die in collapse
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;Five teenagers discovered dead on the banks of a river in central Vietnam were killed when a sandbank collapsed on them, police said yesterday.
The teenagers, aged between 13 and 19, were playing in a hole in the sand caused by a flood earlier in the year, said Colonel Tran VanVien, chief of police in Krong Bong district, Dak Lak province.
Their bodies were discovered by a fisherman, who notified police after seeing a hand sticking out of a sand bank. Authorities then found the five bodies, which were identified as children at a local boarding school who went missing three days earlier. – DPA
@HD2 New Briefs head;Aid for typhoon survivors
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;The Asian Development Bank has approved a US$20-million (Bt626 billion) grant to fund cash-for-work #124programmes and help rebuild infrastructure damaged by Typhoon Haiyan in the Philippines.
The Manila-based bank said the grant would support thousands of affected families through cash-for-work programmes and help restore income to farmers and fishermen by providing seeds, fertilisers, fishing nets and fishing boats.
The funding would also be used to repair schools, build skills in masonry and set up a system to monitor vulnerability to future disasters, the bank said.
The bank earlier provided a $3-million grant and approved a $500 million emergency loan for immediate post-disaster costs. – DPA
@HD2 New Briefs head;Elephant monument
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;The Philippines is to build an elephant monument from the ashes of seized tusks it destroyed in a landmark action against the ivory trade.
The ash will be mixed with concrete to build a giant sculpture of a mother elephant protecting her calf, said Josie de Leon, chief of the environment ministry's wildlife division.
"It is a reminder to everyone about the Philippines' historical action regarding the destruction of ivory," #124she said. – AFP
]]></text></news-item>