<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="06C1-D18E-B953-0F04"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>While you were tweeting; How digital connection is eroding the public sphere</title><source>National Post (f/k/a The Financial Post) (Canada)</source><author>Saleem Khan, Weekend Post</author><text><![CDATA[BOOK REVIEW
The People's Platform: Taking Back Power and Culture in the Digital Age By Astra Taylor Random House Canada 266 pp; $24.95
On March 2, Hollywood luminaries gathered for their annual spectacle devoted to honouring themselves. The Oscars were watched by some 40 million people in North America alone. Many spent the night on social media, discussing the telecast moment-by-moment.
One moment - a "selfie" of famous actors - was shared by Twitter users a record-setting one million times in about an hour, and broke two million retweets by the event's end.
Meanwhile, half a world away, Russian military forces were invading and occupying Crimea, seemingly unnoticed amid a tide of media and fan commentary about celebrities and clothes.
Such is commercialized culture's impact, Astra Taylor argues: The network effect of electronic avenues and airwaves that connect us inform and amplify a world view that reinforces existing power structures, entices, distracts and ultimately co-opts us.
In The People's Platform, she meticulously details how work, education, and the public sphere have been eroded. Ideas, practices and tools of enlightenment, emancipation and opportunity are subverted even by people who profess those ideals.
And the Internet is the linchpin, the Winnipeg-born documentarian asserts.
The influential digerati culture of openness cuts both ways in Taylor's critical gaze: "Openness alone does not provide the blueprint for a more equitable social order, in part because the 'freedom' promoted by the tech community almost always turns out to be of the Darwinian variety. Openness in this context is ultimately about promoting competition, not with protecting equality. ... Inequality is not exclusive to closed systems. Networks reflect and exacerbate imbalances of power as much as they improve them."
Casting an appropriately jaundiced eye on pundits promoting technology as panacea, Taylor notes that for all of their talk of the Internet's egalitarian sharing economy that rewards free agents pursuing their passions, "new-media thinkers" are often hypocritical, pronouncing from privileged, well-paid positions.
She cites "self-proclaimed 'thought leader' " Don Tapscott as one example when he talks of former Goldcorp Inc. chief Rob McEwen releasing data on a mining property in a contest to find its elusive minerals, garnering novel methods to net $3.4-billion in gold. "The market value of his company goes from $90-million to $10-billion, and I can tell you, because he's my neighbour, he's a happy camper," Tapscott said.
Taylor: "This is Tapscott's idea of openness in action: a banker-turned-CEO goes from rich to richer," in a tale that omits miners' labour and compensation, and "Goldcorp's lengthy record of human rights and environmental violations."
In contrast, culture and public good producers such as artists, musicians and journalists face shrinking income potential if they hold to principles that give their labour-intensive work integrity and social value, she observes. Taylor devotes a full chapter to journalism - a crash course in industry afflictions that she revisits throughout her book as she examines advertising and marketing's growing, pernicious influence. It is fuelled by Internet-driven fragmentation of news and content that newspapers bundled to attract large audiences whom advertisers paid to reach.
Now, those audiences bypass bundled news for niche content, and advertisers follow. So, news media lose traditional revenues, online advertising at a fraction of the price can't cover the shortfall and publicinterest journalism such as investigations loses funding.
Worse, we are regressing to an era of offers, inducements, rewards and payola to bloggers, social media "influencers" and a generation of digital-only media that may have no ethical standards.
"Under the 'open' model, where the distinction between commercial and non-commercial has melted away, everything is for sale," Taylor writes.
Traditional media, struggling with a collapsing business model, is not immune. It is now common to devote staff to create advertiser-driven stories: Branded or sponsored content, native advertising and so on. One executive at a major newspaper recently confided that the focus of their "innovation lab" was to create new ways for companies to advertise.
The approach is fraught with peril for intellectual, creative or cultural work, Taylor argues: "Advertisingfinanced culture is not free. We pay environmentally ... with our selfesteem ... attention, privacy and knowledge. But we also pay with our pocketbooks. ... Promotional budgets are factored into the price we pay for goods. ... That means, altogether, we spend more than $700-billion a year on advertising, a tremendous waste of money on something that has virtually no social value and that most of us despise."
A commercialized culture in which the winning ideas and activities are only those that can be marketed or earn a profit is avoidable, Taylor says: "The shift to sustainable culture is possible, but implementing the necessary changes cannot fall to individuals and the marketplace alone. The solutions we need require collective, political action."
Taylor advocates revitalizing government's role in developing and renewing public good, as it did in building the Internet, for example.
This is where her argument breaks down in the U.S. context of the book's focus, where the default position from the nation's foundation is to minimize the state's role.
While cultural creators like artists and musicians might welcome the support, it would likely be seen as undesirable at best by the journalism sector, and certainly by fiscal conservatives.
Even in Canada, where publicly funded institutions are wellreceived, Taylor's proposition sounds possible only under a majority NDP government.
Still, that may not be reason enough to forgo an attempt.
As the aphorism apocryphally credited to American civil rights lawyer Clarence Darrow states: "Lost causes are the only ones worth fighting for."
Saleem Khan (@saleemkhan) is a Toronto-based journalist.
]]></text></news-item>