<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0811-A405-AF17-560D"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Viewpoint: Support divestment, support human rights</title><source>Michigan Daily: University of Michigan-Ann Arbor</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[This past Tuesday, members of Students Allied for Freedom and Equality proposed a resolution to the Central Student Government titled "A Resolution For the University of Michigan to Divest From Socially Irresponsible Companies that Violate Palestinian Human Rights." The resolution calls on the University of Michigan to re-evaluate its financial investment in corporations that unethically profit from and facilitate the violation of Palestinian human rights. The companies in question include United Technologies, Caterpillar, Heidelberg Cement and General Electric. All these companies are explicitly linked to Israel's illegal occupation of Palestine and ongoing human rights abuses.
United Technologies possesses millions of dollars in contracts with the Israeli Air Force for the manufacture of armed Blackhawk helicopters, which have been used by the Israeli military in offensive campaigns against Palestinian communities, resulting in many civilian deaths and casualties. In addition, United Technologies produces the engines for the F-15 and F-16 aircraft used in strikes that result in the killing of innocent civilians. F-15 and F-16 aircraft were used in Operation Cast Lead in 2008/09, when 1,400 Palestinians were killed over a three week period, the vast majority of them innocent civilians.
Caterpillar produces the D9 military bulldozers that are used to illegally demolish Palestinian homes. Its bulldozers and civil engineering tools have also been crucial to the construction of the separation wall and settlements on Palestinian land. The #UMMockEviction campaign SAFE organized last semester raised awareness about the illegal demolition of Palestinian homes. Since 1967, more than 27,000 Palestinian homes have been demolished.
Heidelberg Cement is involved in the exploitation of natural resources in occupied Palestinian land for the benefit of the Israeli construction industry. It operates two concrete plants and one asphalt plant in the West Bank and has provided the cement used for the building of illegal settlements as well as the building of the separation wall.
Lastly, General Electric sells engines for a variety of Israeli military aircraft and provides the propulsion systems of AH-64 Apache helicopters that have been used in terrorizing raids against Palestinian towns and villages.
The human rights violations in which the University is invested are severe. Five million Palestinian refugees are forcibly prevented from returning to their homes. In the West Bank, Palestinians live under a military occupation, in Gaza they are under constant siege and Palestinian citizens of Israel are explicitly denied equal rights under the law. Israel arbitrarily and punitively destroys Palestinian homes and farms, imprisons and tortures Palestinian children and has killed thousands of Palestinian civilians since the year 2000.
Investing in companies that profit from military occupation and violence, no matter where or why, is wrong. And with thousands of viable alternatives, it is not necessary. In asking for the divestment from companies that continue to cooperate with the violation of Palestinian human rights, we are merely holding our University accountable to its stated moral and ethical standards.
]]></text></news-item>