<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0840-B6F6-D2F6-63D2"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Bristol Street Group Ltd.: SEAT Leon Cupra becomes Nurburgring record breaker</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
The SEAT Leon Cupra 280 is the latest model to take a lap record at the impressive Nurburgring track in Germany.
It has become the quickest ever front-wheel drive (FWD) production car to take a lap of the circuit, clocking up a time of 7:58.4 minutes. It is also the first FWD model to finish faster than eight minutes.
Jurgen Stackmann, SEAT S.A. president, said: "Our ultimate expression of the successful Leon formula is the all new Leon Cupra. It is the fastest and the most powerful car we have ever built and yet is a comfortable family car. The Cupra is our new icon."
The car to complete the lap was not modified beyond the addition of the optional Performance Pack, which will soon be made available to UK customers. This provides Brembo high-performance brakes, specially designed 19-inch alloy wheels and Michelin Pilot Sport Cup 2 tyres.
SEAT is now showing off the model at the Geneva Motor Show, alongside the new Mii by MANGO - a range-topping, fashion inspired version of the Mii.
click http://www.bristolstreet.co.uk/news/seat-leon-cupra-becomes-nurburgring-record-breaker-801703407/
COMPANY BACKGROUND
ACTIVITIES
Bristol Street Group Ltd. operates a chain of franchised motor dealerships offering sales, service, parts, and body shop facilities for new and used cars, and commercial vehicles in the United Kingdom. It offers new and used cars, vans, trucks, and bikes. The company also operates the Motor Nation brand of used car hypermarkets. In addition, it assists its clients in obtaining car finance. The company was formerly known as Bristol Street Holdings Limited and changed its name to Bristol Street Group Ltd. in November 2001. Bristol Street Group Ltd. was founded in 1946 and is based in Newcastle upon Tyne, the United Kingdom. As of March 27, 2007, Bristol Street Group Ltd. operates as a subsidiary of Vertu Motors Plc.
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
13 March 2014: Bristol Street Group Ltd.: Suzuki CELERIO makes European debut at Geneva Motor Show
The latest model from Suzuki has stood in pride of place at its stand at the Geneva Motor Show, as the manufacturer shows off its latest European-specification version of the CELERIO. It has been developed as an A+ compact car, heralding a new type of A-segment machine that exceeds the category standards it should adhere to. The CELERIO comes with a dual-injection system which helps to minimise CO2 emissions, while reduced body weight and improved aerodynamics also succeed in cutting carbon.
click http://www.bristolstreet.co.uk/news/suzuki-launches-celerio-at-the-geneva-motor-show-801703041/
12 March 2014: Bristol Street Group Ltd.: Casillas and Kaka to cheer for Hyundai at 2014 World Cup
Hyundai has revealed two sensational soccer stars will be cheering them on at this year's Fifa World Cup in Brazil. Spain and Real Madrid goalkeeper Iker Casillas and Brazil and AC Milan midfielder Kaka are the latest brand ambassadors for the manufacturer. With the World Cup in Rio just under three months away, Hyundai is stepping up its efforts to promote its brand ahead of one of the biggest sporting competitions on the planet. Both players have appeared at three World Cup tournaments and are highly respected in their positions. Casillas is known as one of football's greatest modern goalkeepers and was a key part of Spain's World Cup winning side of 2010. Kaka was part of the Brazil team that won the tournament in 2002 and has since gone on to feature for the national team in the 2006 and 2010 competitions.
click http://www.bristolstreet.co.uk/news/casillas-and-kaka-to-cheer-for-hyundai-at-2014-world-cup-801702610/
12 March 2014: Bristol Street Group Ltd.: Citroen announces UK trims for C1
With the Citroen C1 set to hit the UK market in July, the manufacturer has announced the three trim levels that customers will benefit from. The trio of choices are known as 'Touch', 'Feel' and 'Flair' and each will offer customers a unique array of benefits. Its standard lead-in model is the Touch, which comes with anti-lock brakes, emergency brake assist, electronic stability program, power steering, remote central locking, electric front windows, six airbags, MP3 compatible audio system, a USB socket and LED daytime running lights. Next in line is the Feel, offering these features on top of air conditioning, a DAB digital radio, a seven-inch Touch Drive interface and steering mounted controls.
click http://www.bristolstreet.co.uk/news/citroen-announces-uk-trims-for-c1-801702609/
11 March 2014: Bristol Street Group Ltd: Vauxhall adds 'whisper diesel' Astra to fleet lineup
Vauxhall will unveil its new 'whisper diesel' engine Astra, which is the quietest and cleanest model the car maker has ever produced. The super-quiet and smooth new generation 1.6-litre CDTi engine offers fuel consumption of up to 73.6mpg and carbon emissions of just 97g/km, which will reduce the road tax burden on fleet operators in the UK. The new model will be introduced to businesses at the Fleet World Fleet Show at the Silverstone Circuit on April 9th. This follows on from the debut of the 'whisper diesel' engine in an Astra model at the Geneva Motor Show earlier this month, where 110PS and 136PS versions were in attendance, in hatchback and sports tourer body types. The engine is regarded as best-in-class in terms of noise and vibration generation due to the optimised components it is manufactured from and the improved efficiency of its combustion process and multiple injection. Vauxhall's new 1.6-litre CDTi Astra is available to order now with first deliveries expected from April, with prices starting at Pound17,635 for the 1.6-litre CDTi 16v (110ps) ecoFLEX. Source: Company Website
click http://www.bristolstreet.co.uk/news/vauxhall-adds-whisper-diesel-astra-to-fleet-lineup-801702257/
11 March 2014: Bristol Street Group Ltd: Ford Transit and Transit Connect pick up two Arctic Van Test awards
The Ford Transit and Transit Connect came through the Arctic Van Test with flying colours, picking up two wins, the first time the van maker has claimed a double prize in its 23-year history. Both vans finished first in their respective classes after competing in the punishing five-day ordeal, during which the vehicles and drivers are pushed to the extreme in ice, cold and snow, in Finland - where temperatures can drop as low as -50 degrees Celcius. The test the models were put through included slaloming across a frozen airfield, tackling a 700km route covering icy, rutted roads. Paul Randle, vehicle line director, global commercial vehicles, Ford of Europe, said: "Every one of our new Ford Transits is tested in the world's toughest climates and driving conditions long before launch, so they are prepared for just this kind of challenge." Expert drivers from six European commercial vehicle magazines sat behind the wheel of the models in the Arctic Van Test and rated the two Transits winners to deliver Ford's first double victory in the event's 23-year history. The all-new Ford Transit was rated top or joint-top in nine out of 13 categories, while the more compact Ford Transit Connect was ranked top or joint-top in seven categories, impressing with its stability and handling in icy conditions. Source: Company Website
click http://www.bristolstreet.co.uk/news/ford-transit-and-transit-connect-pick-up-two-arctic-van-test-awards-801702273/
]]></text></news-item>