<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="089A-593E-B3D4-C84A"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Pakistan: Law enforcers accused of playing judge, jury and executioner</title><source>Right Vision News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[KARACHI, March 14 -- Hours before a blast rocked Lyari's Jhat Pat Market, two young brothers were whisked away by paramilitary soldiers.
Badal, 18, and Naseem, 20, residents of Dhobi Ghat, were picked up by Rangers from the neighbourhood at 7am, insists their family.
Hours later, they were found shot dead and their bodies turned up at the Civil Hospital.
Their claimants, mostly women, protested outside the mortuary at the Civil Hospital demanding that the bodies of their loved ones be handed over to them.
"Two of my sons have died the same day. They used to work at a garage. They played football. They did not belong to any gang," wailed Ghauri, their mother.
The victims were apparently tortured before being murdered. There were bruises and burn wounds on the bodies.
"Naseem had recently gotten married. His wife is pregnant with his first child," said their brother present outside the mortuary.
As the day proceeded, three more residents, Fateh Khan, Adnan Asif and Farman Iqbal, were killed in encounters with the police at Jhat Pat Market, pushing the number to five.
On Friday, another youngster, Zahid, was picked by police from Dhobi Ghat. His family received his body bearing torture marks on Sunday.
Residents claim that the law enforcement agencies are engaged in extrajudicial killings in the area.
"They are trying to corner the Baloch. One day we will have an independent Balochistan," screamed an angry woman.
However, a resident of the locality, speaking on the condition of anonymity, admitted that early in the morning young men such as the ones who were killed guarded pickets set up by rival gangs.
"Why else would someone be out in the neighbourhood at six in the morning," he said.
The recent breakup of the banned People's Aman Committee into Baba Ladla and Uzair Baloch groups has plunged Lyari into a new form of bloody violence.
In a highly unprecedented incident on Wednesday, a blast rocked Jhat Pat Market killing 12 and injuring dozens others, many of them bystanders who had nothing to do with the gangs. The dead included two schoolchildren and some women.
The law enforcers are conducting search operations in Lyari every day. They claim that the people they kill in encounters are gangsters who attack them. Four injured paramilitary soldiers and two police officials were brought to the Jinnah Hospital on Wednesday.
A spokesperson for Rangers said three of the dead residents, Khan, Asif and Iqbal, shot at the law enforcers while they were they conducting a search operation at Jhat Pat Market and killed in retaliatory firing.
The two others, Naseem aka Ippi and Adil aka Badal, also shot at Rangers and were killed when the law enforcers tried to defend themselves.
"All of them were members of the Baba Ladla group. They were carrying weapons including grenades and rocket launchers," the Rangers spokesperson said
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Right Vision News. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>