<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="08BD-43DA-BEBA-9A63"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Ludhiana Inc in crisis: Dy CM</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[LUDHIANA: Deputy Chief Minister Sukhbir Badal who till some time back seemed euphoric about big investments in the state admitted for the first time that the industry here was in deep crisis.
Squarely blaming the poor governance of "scam tainted" Congress led UPA government junior Badal added that the industry's condition was bad not only in Punjab but in the entire country. "Not only in the state but in the entire country, the industry is in a deep crisis. The major reason for this poor condition is the lack of good governance by the Central government that remained involved in all kinds of corruption and scams," said Badal.
He was responding to a question over the pitiable condition of the industry as has been highlighted by the Income tax department and the study of the Associated Chamber of commerce and industry in the state recently. Junior Badal was in city, for the inauguration of the election office of SAD-BJP candidate from Ludhiana Parliamentary seat, Manpreet Ayali on Friday.
Recently Income tax department has raised serious concerns about the Industry not doing well in the state especially in Ludhiana while pointing out that the department was facing difficulties in meeting the targeted collection of the Income tax. A study by the Associated Chamber of commerce and industry in India has also highlighted that the cheap imports from China were badly affecting the industry. The study pointed out that the imports from China had increased by 41 percent since the year 2009 and that a lot of government support was needed to help the ailing industry come out of crisis.
Notably a much hyped 2-day Progressive Punjab Investors Summit was organized in Mohali on December 9 and December 10 while projecting the state as a key business destination by the Punjab Government.
Describing it as the most favourable destination, the Badal and his government in the presence of country's top corporate honchos had claimed that the state has managed to ink 117 agreements with both domestic and overseas companies involving investments of over Rs 65,000 crore.
The summit was attended by corporate honchos including RIL Chairman Mukesh Ambani, Arcelor-Mittal Chairman L N Mittal, Fortis Healthcare Executive Chairman Malvinder Mohan Singh and Hero MotoCorp Joint MD Sunil Kant Munjal.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>