<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="08E1-4FD9-AB30-4844"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Utility Seeks High Court Reversal Of Ruling Allowing State Law Air Torts</title><source>Inside EPA Weekly Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Utility GenOn Power Midwest is urging the Supreme Court to reverse an appellate ruling that split with other courts by allowing state lawsuits for alleged public nuisance from power plants' emissions, saying the ruling could create major risks for utilities who could be in full federal Clean Air Act compliance and still be sued under state tort law.
If the U.S. Court of Appeals for the 3rd Circuit's ruling in Kristie Bell and Joan Luppe v. Cheswick Power Station is allowed to stand, GenOn says in a petition for the Supreme Court to review the case, there is a risk that the expert determinations from EPA and states on how best to regulate air pollution may be "ignored in favor of the decisions of lay judges and juries" in nuisance suits over air pollution damages that lead to penalties or injunctions on utilities for their emissions. The petition is available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID: 2463848)
The 3rd Circuit, in a unanimous Aug. 20 ruling, reversed a lower court's decision to dismiss a class action lawsuit against a power plant under Pennsylvania state common law for trespass and nuisance, finding there was nothing in the Clean Air Act suggesting Congress intended the statute to preempt state common law tort claims.
A district court had rejected the suit that claimed GenOn's Cheswick Power Station was emitting soot, metal compounds and acid gases that were polluting the air and damaging personal property, but the 3rd Circuit said that the "savings clause" of the air statute allows citizens to proceed with common law suits over damages.
But GenOn, in its Feb. 20 petition to the high court to hear the case, says the ruling exposes industrial sources that have worked, "often at great expense," to obtain air permits and comply with the federal air law to lawsuits under a "nearly limitless range of liability theories" that could force them to curtail their operations or pay for damages.
Congress wrote the Clean Air Act to provide a comprehensive system that would provide "some level of uniformity, certainty and predictability" on how to regulate air pollution, GenOn says. However, that goal will be "critically, perhaps fatally, undermined if nuisance claims of the sort alleged in this case are allowed to proceed," it adds.
Damages suits would not be limited to soot, as was the case in Kristie Bell, but could also extend to "ubiquitous emissions such as carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases," GenOn warns. And state damages lawsuits over air pollution could actually exacerbate air pollution, the company argues, by forcing companies to take steps to cut emissions that inadvertently cause increases in emissions from other sources that are more harmful to the environment.
For example, GenOn says lawsuits could end up creating differing standards across jurisdictions that cause utilities to shift power generation to areas with less stringent rules, while the risks of lawsuits deter companies from investing in new plants that are typically cleaner than the old plants they replace.
Whether the high court takes the case may hinge in part on its decision in 2011 in American Electric Power (AEP) Co. v. Connecticut, in which an 8-0 majority rejected an effort by eight states and New York City to bring federal common law nuisance claims against six power companies for their carbon dioxide emissions. The court held that the Clean Air Act's regulation of those emissions displaced any federal common law claims.
However, in a key part of the ruling, the justices did not declare whether the Clean Air Act should displace state common law claims, explicitly stating that it would "leave the matter open for consideration," a decision seen as potentially reviving state common law damages suits over greenhouse gas emissions.
GenOn, in its petition for the high court to hear its appeal, says the Supreme Court should answer the question it had earlier left open, which it says is "whether the Clean Air Act preempts nuisance claims under state common law." Even though that question was left open, the company argues that under the reasoning in AEP, the preemption of federal common law should "apply equally" to state nuisance claims at issue in Kristie Bell.
In the AEP ruling, the court had noted that it was "altogether fitting" that Congress designated EPA as "best suited" to regulating greenhouse gas emissions, as the agency was "surely better equipped to do the job than individual district judges issuing ad hoc, case-by-case injunctions." The ruling noted that unlike EPA, judges cannot commission scientific studies, convene experts, consult with state agencies or issue notice-and-comment rulemakings.
GenOn in its petition to the high court says there is "no difference whatsoever" between the claims at issue in AEPand the air pollution damages claims in the 3rd Circuit ruling, as both seek to hold a power plant liable for damages from air pollution already regulated by the statute and both would have "judges and juries making decisions" about emission limits already established by EPA.
The company challenges the 3rd Circuit's interpretation that the savings clause in the Clean Air Act preserved state common law claims, saying that the language in the statute was written to allow state law claims intended to enforce emission standards "established through statute or regulation."
And it objects to the appeals court's reliance on a Supreme Court decision in 1987 in International Paper Co. v. Ouellette that focused on the to the savings clause in the Clean Water Act, as it argues that the goals and policies of the water statute differ from that of the air statute. -- Chris Knight
]]></text></news-item>