<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="08FA-B244-356C-27D8"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Profile: Carl and David McCann</title><source>Sunday Business Post</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Fact file
**Carl and David McCann**
**Appearance:**The brothers' youthful features mask a patrician and aloof public persona
**Newsworthiness:**Fyffes, where David is the chief executive, recently announced a merger with Chiquita to create the world's largest banana company
.....
If the Irish Stock Exchange had an index of the personality types of its chief executives, unquestionably at one extreme end would be Ryanair's voluble and uncouth Michael O'Leary.
At the other end, equally doubtless, would be the controlled, patrician, and aloof McCann brothers -- Carl and David -- of the Fyffes fruit empire.
Last week David, the younger of the two, became chief executive of the world's largest fruit company, the soon to be merged ChiquitaFyffes company.
Carl, meanwhile, is chief executive of Total Produce, which was once a division of Fyffes, but was spun out in 2007. Though the two companies are often taken as part of the wider McCann fruit empire, they are entirely separate -- and the merger between Fyffes and Chiquita will widen that gap. But in temperament, publicly at least, the brothers couldn't be closer.
Consider, for example, the response given by David when in one of his rare interviews, given to a Sunday newspaper in the early 2000s, he was asked a simple question about his personal life.
''I don't do stuff like that. No nonsense like that. No family and no hobbies, no nonsense like that, he said.
His brother Carl was not a whole lot more forthcoming in an interview a few years later with a daily newspaper. He did reveal that he used to run before he injured his knee and he waxed lyrical about his father's business acumen, but he also shut down any form of personal question. He left the flummoxed journalist to write: ''He will politely answer questions and seems happy enough to supply basic personal information, but nothing is volunteered or given away without consideration.
That careful protection of their interests is just as evident in other areas of their lives.
When men's clothing store owner Niall O'Farrell applied to redevelop his house on Shrewsbury Road, near David's house, the younger McCann filed an objection letter to planning authority An Bord Plean ¡la that fashioned an unselfconscious elitism into a rapier with which he filleted O'Farrell's plans.
''Visitors to Shrewsbury Road are immediately struck by the mature, airy opulence of the streetscape, McCann's submission read. ''This is a notable feature. It affords the green context that adorns and complements the houses.
''Shrewsbury Road had acquired this exalted status by the mid-20th century. When the makers of the ever-popular property board game, Monopoly, came to produce an Irish edition, pride of place fell to Shrewsbury Road. That was in 1972. In achieving this accolade, the street matched the exclusivity set by its English counterpart at Mayfair.
''Shrewsbury Road is distinguished by an emphasis on secluded maturity. It is not a place for ostentatious braggadocio.
It amounted to a cutting evisceration of O'Farrell's plans.
Carl, too, has a slightly courtly air that disguises a fairly vicious pen when required, best encapsulated by one of several letters he wrote but never sent to Jim Flavin (former chief executive of Irish company DCC) as their relationship was souring. In one particularly difficult dispute over money, McCann wrote: ''Your . . . compulsion to dominate everyone and every meeting is well known . . . There is no excuse for bad manners, a bullying approach and a lack of courtesy, appreciation and respect for your elders . . . I do not know if your moodiness is random or related to other business hassles, but it is painful to deal with.
They did not inherit their demeanour from their father, Neil, who was best known for his warmth and populism, but they did inherit his ruthless business sense. And, more importantly, they inherited the Fyffes business strategy: growth through acquisition. In many ways, the merger with Chiquita is as much a product of historical momentum as it is a carefully-plotted corporate strategy.
**Banana empire**
The McCanns' banana empire stretches back three generations to their grandfather, Charles McCann, who set up his greengrocer's shop on Dublin's Clanbrassil Street in 1902. At the time, the fruit-selling business in Ireland was fractured between small shops and distributors, so Charlie's strategy was to bring them all together.
David and Carl's father Neil - known as Neily stepped in to run the business in 1954 after the death of his father and of his brother Jackie, and he set about accelerating the strategy, hoovering up a number of the Irish fruit and vegetable industry's traditional family-owned businesses. By the company's own account, in the quarter century after taking over the reins Neil McCann bought nearly 200 businesses of various sizes to create a company he named United Fruit Importers of Ireland.
During that period, both David and Carl had come aboard -- David after a law degree from UCD and time spent as a partner in a Dublin law firm, and Carl after training as an accountant at KPMG.
Through all of this, the McCann family business had maintained a solid relationship with Fyffes, a British banana company founded in 1880, when bananas first started arriving from the Canaries. And in 1986 -- with United Fruit Importers of Ireland having been renamed and restructured as Fruit Importers of Ireland Limited (FII) -- Neil McCann spotted the opportunity for more growth. FII bought Fyffes for £27 million. United Brands, shorn of Fyffes, would go on to be renamed Chiquita. In the same year, the McCanns' company floated on the Irish Stock Exchange, becoming FII Fyffes and later simply Fyffes.
The expansion continued although Neil McCann, who had driven most of the strategy during the company's most aggressive expansionary phase, retired as chief executive in 1995 to be replaced by David and Carl -- as chief executive and executive chairman, respectively. Around the same time, they decided to split the fruit business into Fyffes, which would focus broadly on tropical produce including bananas and melons, and Total Produce, which would focus on fruit and vegetable distribution in Europe.
But not all of the growth under David and Carl would be as successful as the growth driven by Neil.
In fact, the brothers rushed headlong into the two biggest bubbles in recent memory: the dotcom bubble and the property bubble, costing them hundreds of millions of euro in losses.
In 2001, the brothers finally pulled the plug on worldoffruit.com, into which they had pumped around EUR 12 million (by Carl's reckoning) in an attempt to create an internet business through the planned fruitXchange trading operation.
The McCanns also spent a fortune on property acquisitions at the top of the market, launching a new entity called Blackrock International Land on the stock exchange with a property portfolio of nearly EUR 200 million.
Within a year the collapse in prices in Ireland had decimated the company, with assets dwarfed by the loans Blackrock had taken out to buy the properties. It was quietly delisted and its name changed to Balmoral, and the most recent set of Fyffes accounts note that its share of the remaining assets is now reduced to EUR 400,000. ''Fyffes wrote down its investment in Balmoral to EUR 50,000 in 2011, the accounts report.
In 2007, Fyffes was embroiled in European Union competition investigation into the fixing of banana prices, alongside Chiquita, Dole and Del Monte, related to the sale of nearly EUR 3 billion worth of bananas between 2000 and 2002. Fyffes and Chiquita were cleared, but such competition issues are a common symptom of an increasingly concentrated market, with four main players at the time and just three now.
The biggest controversy of all, though, was the lengthy insider trading case involving Jim Flavin of Irish investment company DCC, who had been a stalwart of Fyffes from the beginning. Flavin had been a key advisor to Neil McCann. In 2002, Fyffes sued DCC and a number of other companies claiming that DCC had sold off its shares in Fyffes while Flavin, who was a director of Fyffes at the time, was in possession of price-sensitive information, with DCC ultimately reaping a profit of EUR 106 million on the trade before Fyffes issued a profit warning that had the result of lowering the share price.
The lawsuit led to a long and unpleasant case over nearly 90 days that saw David McCann in particular dragged through seven days of detailed testimony.
In the end, the case was settled and Fyffes got EUR 42 million.
After three generations and more than a century of McCann control of the family business, the Chiquita deal represents a notable deviation from the family's usual modus operandi.
For starters, Fyffes is usually the suitor rather than the target, and the company can often spend millions a year on advisory fees for deals that may ultimately never go through. But in this case, Fyffes was not the instigator of the deal.
By David's own admission, it was Chiquita's chief executive Ed Lonergan who made the running, approaching David at a conference in New Orleans and proposing the idea. Since Chiquita's predecessor sold the McCanns the Fyffes brand in 1986, Fyffes and Chiquita have engaged in occasional flirtations, and McCann also said recently that there had been ''tentative discussions over many, many years between the two firms.
**Share price**
Now, in fact, is probably not the best timing for the deal. Fyffes could easily have snapped up Chiquita in 2001 just before the company filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy. Or, had Chiquita been able to do so, any time in the preceding three years would have been a better time to buy Fyffes, when the company's share price was on the floor.
And while the structure of the deal is a roughly 50:50 merger, the scale of the American outfit is significantly greater. It has a market capitalisation of around EUR 580 million compared to Fyffes' EUR 380 million, it has 20,000 employees compared to just over 2,500 for Fyffes and it has twice the sales globally. (Perhaps for those reasons, non-Irish news outlets such as the New York Times are describing this more like an acquisition for Chiquita than a merger of equals.).
Perhaps the biggest question for David McCann remains to be answered -- just who runs the company?
Some observers are claiming that the structure of the new company is a victory for Fyffes, who appear to have cannily won the battle to stack the board, where Fyffes' Tom Murphy as chief financial officer and Coen Bos as chief operating officer sit just under McCann as chief executive.
But Chiquita's Ed Lonergan is not just chairman in this structure, he's executive chairman.
It's not clear yet how the two roles will operate together, but history has shown that a saddle can't be shared, and it remains to be seen how well the two sides of the deal will play together.
Over the course of more than a century, the McCanns have tended to emerge holding the whip. Just ask Jim Flavin or Niall O'Farrell, or any of the absorbed companies that now make up the banana behemoth.
Reckoning with the giants of Chiquita, however, will prove to be their biggest test yet.
]]></text></news-item>