<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="093C-BBE2-8D14-7407"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>PUTIN COULD PAY PRICE FOR CRIMEA MOVES</title><source>The Augusta Chronicle (Georgia)</source><author> Paul Richter  Tribune Washington Bureau </author><text><![CDATA[Supporters of Russian President Vladimir Putin expect to savor victory as residents of Crimea vote today on splitting from Ukraine. But Western officials and analysts increasingly feel that in the long run, Russians will come to see their nation's military and political move into Crimea as a mistake.
Two weeks after Russian forces entered the peninsula en masse, Russia's stock market and economic data have started to signal trouble - the start of what could become a lasting pullback by foreign investors. That would badly hurt Russia's efforts to modernize and diversify its economy.
At the United Nations and other international forums, the number of countries supporting Moscow's strong-arm action has shrunk close to zero. Even China has turned sour.
Nor has Putin succeeded in splitting the Western coalition and stopping U.S.-led efforts to impose sanctions. Instead, he seems to have driven the alliance together while frightening countries on Russia's borders into closer cooperation with the U.S. and Western Europe.
The clearest indication of how Putin's action might be backfiring came Thursday when German Chancellor Angela Merkel, who had been the foremost advocate for a soft line, shifted position and warned Moscow of a possible new East-West division that could "massively damage Russia, economically and politically."
Other world powers have been unpersuaded by Putin's arguments that military action was necessary to protect the majority ethnic Rus-sian population in Crimea from Ukraine's interim government. The new government took over from a Russian ally, President Viktor Yanukovych, last month in what the Russians call an illegal coup but which most other countries have recognized as legitimate.
Belarus, which hews closely to Russia's line, signaled its ambivalence by recognizing the government in Kiev.
Perhaps most ominous for Russia are signs of an economic pullback.
The most harmful effects "may not be from other governments' sanctions, but from the gradual deterioration of an economic situation that is already weakening," said Blair Ruble of the Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars in Washington.
Russia has long sought to diversify its economy, which now depends heavily on energy. Moscow has hoped to add new centers of technology and innovation. But the Crimea seizure "has left the impression that Russia is an unreliable partner," Ruble said.
Since Putin sent troops into Crimea on Feb. 28, the ruble has hit record lows, the stock market has fallen about 20 percent and many economists have slashed their 2014 growth forecasts.
Moscow's strategy since the invasion has been to try to divide the European Union's few assertive countries from the many that didn't want to tangle
with the Russians because of concern about damaging their own fragile economies.
Russia has signaled it could cut off gas exports that much of Western Europe depends on and retaliate against sanctions with financial punishments of its own. It has mobilized tanks and troops near Ukraine's borders, reawakening fear of a new East-West military confrontation.
How real the Western threat of sanctions will be remains to be seen. Broader-gauge sanctions "are still in a discussion stage" within the European Union, a Western diplomat said, speaking anonymously to comment on negotiations. Merkel, despite her tough language, will remain under pressure from German business and labor groups to not inflict penalties that would harm Germany's economic relationship with Moscow.
]]></text></news-item>