<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0951-74B1-C985-E06C"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>IFC issues largest offshore rupee bonds</title><source>Global Data Point</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Well-written articles depend on sustained investments. You can purchase individual and corporate subscriptions as well as copyright permissions by contacting us at subscribe@theasset.com or on +852 2165 1627. To read more :
http://www.theasset.com /article/26210.html#ixzz2vvIANegj The International Finance Corporation (IFC), a member of the World Bank Group, on March 13 issued a five-year, 20 billion rupee global bonds (US$328 million) to promote capital market development and encourage foreign investment in India. This is the largest offshore Indian rupee bond issuance to date, highlighting the growing confidence of international investors in India's economy. The order book reached close to 25 billion rupees. Over two-thirds of the IFC bond buyers are US and European asset managers, insurance companies, private banks and real money investors. The bond yield is 7.8%. "IFC's five-year global rupee bonds come to market at a time when foreign investors are seeing renewed opportunity in India's capital markets," said IFC vice-president and treasurer Jingdong Hua in a statement. "The bonds support this momentum while providing a unique bridge that links international investment with India's private sector financing needs." The issuance brings to nearly US$815 million the amount of notes issued under IFC's US$1 billion global rupee bond programme, launched late last year. IFC global rupee bonds are denominated in Indian rupees but settled in US dollars, with all principal and coupon payments tied to the US dollar-rupee exchange rate. The IFC converts the bond proceeds from dollars into rupees on the domestic spot exchange market, and uses the rupees to invest in the country. Under the programme, the IFC also has a three-year outstanding bond of 30 billion rupees. India accounted for US$4.5 billion of IFC's committed investment portfolio as of June 30 2013 - more than any other country. In fiscal year 2013, the IFC invested US$1.38 billion in India to achieve several strategic priorities such as promoting inclusive growth in India's low-income states, addressing climate change and supporting global economic integration. Over the years, the IFC has issued bonds in 14 local currencies, including the Brazilian real, the Chinese renminbi, the Nigeria naira, and the Russia ruble. Often, the IFC is the first international or corporate issuer of local-currency bonds in a market. When issuing local currency bonds, the IFC works closely with the regulators and market participants to refine the regulatory framework, encouraging greater participation in the local markets and providing a model for other international issuers.
Deutsche Bank, J.P. Morgan and TD Securities acted as lead managers for the latest global rupee bond issue.© 2014 Global Data Point.
]]></text></news-item>