<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="096E-FB36-E71A-124C"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Getting away with crimes against humanity</title><source>The Straits Times (Singapore)</source><author>Andy Ho, Senior Writer</author><text><![CDATA[CAN the International Criminal Court (ICC) bring North Korea's leaders accused of crimes against humanity to justice'
Not in the near future.
Here's why.
Based on testimony from more than 320 witnesses, a United Nations Human Rights Council panel has prepared a 400-page report that implicates North Korea's leaders of crimes against humanity.
The report describes "deliberate starvation, forced labour, executions, torture, rape and the denial of reproductive rights enforced through punishment, forced abortion and infanticide". Hundreds of thousands are estimated to have died in political prison camps over the past six decades.
The UN report notes "many parallels" with Nazi crimes against humanity during World War II.
However, it was only since the ICC was set up in 2002 that these types of crimes, when they occur outside the context of armed conflict, could be prosecuted under international law.
The Rome Statute which established the ICC now defines crimes against humanity as systematic or large-scale violations of human rights perpetrated by repressive regimes upon only their own civilian populations - outside the context of armed conflicts.
Hence, allegations of serious human rights abuses in a solely domestic context may now be brought against officials of such regimes. Genocide and war crimes are legally considered separate from crimes against humanity.
But how could serious human rights abuses perpetrated upon the civilian population in one nation by its own officials be considered a crime against "humanity"'
Perhaps one may conceive of humanity as having its own interests, much in the way we talk of a big company with thousands of employees as having its own vision and mission and, thus, its own interests. In this sense, we might say humanity has conquered outer space, for example.
Likewise, North Korea's human rights abuses would be inimical to humanity's interests and diminish the human species in an intangible way, even if they do not pose direct risks to global order, peace and security of humankind.
More practically, one may simply think of the idea as another legal concept, say criminal breach of trust. Then, one assesses if the very idea of crimes against humanity can achieve the goals set for it by the global community.
The political goal might be for all states to respect the human rights of their citizens, and the moral goal may be for all states to feel legally obliged to extradite to the ICC all those accused of crimes against humanity.
Although North Korea is not party to the treaty, its leaders could be hauled up before the ICC if the Security Council referred it to the court, as the UN panel recommends. But the North's ally, Beijing, is likely to veto such a move.
An alternative is for the ICC prosecutor to initiate his own investigations and, if there is a case, issue arrest warrants for Mr Kim Jong Un and his cadres.
Say such arrest warrants are issued. Now suppose some North Korean leaders were apprehended in a country that is not party to the treaty, like the United States. Is the US then obliged to extradite them to the ICC nevertheless'
It would be obliged to do so if it were already generally accepted by most states that they have the legal obligation (opinio juris) to extradite all such accused persons.
Some experts and activists claim it is already accepted as customary international law that all states have that obligation, with or without its codification in treaty. However, Leiden University law professor John Dugard argues in International Law: A South African Perspective (2006) that although international law has indeed been evolving over the past 70 years towards the recognition of such an obligation, there is no universal acceptance just yet.
That is, it is not yet received as customary international law.
The evidence for such a lack of universal acceptance is the opposite practice of granting amnesties. This practice is common in states which are in transition after an internal conflict. They often decide to grant amnesty to officials of the previous regime who perpetrated crimes against humanity on their own population.
Amnesties, in effect, say: Forget the past for the sake of national reconciliation; none of the horrific abuses need be publicly exposed and expiated; just leave the evil behind and move on with life.
Whether this is morally right or not, it is the very opposite of saying that all officials of the previous regime who abused the human rights of civilians in a systematic and widespread manner must be publicly held accountable.
Amnesties have been granted during transitions after conflicts in South Africa, Haiti, Argentina, Uruguay, Chile and Sierra Leone, where widespread human rights abuses have been documented.
The granting of amnesties is contrary to and seriously undermines the norm that all states are legally obliged to extradite all such accused to the ICC.
Moreover, such amnesties have not only been widely granted but also been generally well received by the global community. For example, the Organisation of American States supported the Haitian amnesty. Conversely, few states deign to criticise such amnesties.
Thus, there does not yet seem to be a wide consensus among an overwhelming number of states that they are legally obliged to extradite someone like Mr Kim and his cadres, were ICC arrest warrants actually issued for them.
Today, only the 122 states that have ratified the treaty would see it as their legal obligation to do so. Non-member nations including giants like the US, India, China and Russia would not necessarily consider it their legal obligation to the international community to extradite such individuals. Unfortunately, this also means that the treaty's scope of protection for the oppressed, like those in North Korea, remains quite limited.
andyho@sph.com.sg
]]></text></news-item>