<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="099A-61DB-2DB3-DA9C"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Massive tree planting to highlight NorCot's centennial celeb By Edwin O. Fernandez</title><source>Philippines News Agency</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[KIDAPAWAN CITY, March 15 -- As part of its greening program, the North Cotabato provincial government is launching a massive tree planting activity to highlight the centennial celebration of the province in September this year.
North Cotabato Gov. Emmylou Mendoza took a cue from the saying of famous Indian leader Mahatma Gandhi who once delcared "What we are doing to the forests of the world is but a mirror reflection of what we are doing to ourselves and to one another.'
The "Tree Growing Festival" with the theme 'Pagbubuklod Ngayong Sentenaryo: Magtanim'Puno Ay Buhay'Pagyamanin, will be highlighted by massive planting of endemic tress in three different locations of the province.
These are the Mt. Akir-Akir in Pigcawayan on June 13, 2014, Lake Malingling in Ganatan, Arakan on June 20, and Pisan Caves in Kabacan on June 27.
Mendoza said that while every Cotabate'o rekindles the history and culture of the province this year, it is equally important to celebrate the centennial with a simple sacrifice that will uphold environmental protection.
The program will be carried out with the active participation of local government units and other sectors like the academe, non-government organizations, business, environmental groups, mountaineering and many others.
More than a thousand people from the three districts of Cotabato are expected to join the activity that is expected to boost environmental conservation among the constituents.
They will plant Narra, Apitong, Tinikaran and other endemic trees in all the three locations or target areas.
All the employees of the provincial capitol are mandated by the governor to join the activity while the respective LGU's are also expected to enjoin their constituents to actively involved themselves in the environmental undertaking.
Three departments from the provincial capitol - the Provincial Governor's Office (PGO), Provincial Engineers Office (PEO) and Provincial Health Office (PHO) will be in charge of coordinating and monitoring the massive tree planting.
Tree seedlings or planting materials will be supplied by the Office of the Provincial Agriculturist (OPAG).
Those who want to join and be counted at Tree Growing Festival are advised to call or send a message to cell phone number 09999937363 and look for Russel Villorente or visit the PAATSDD, PEO and PHO at the Provincial Capitol, Barangay Amas, Kidapawan City.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Philippines News Agency. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>