<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0A36-0920-730C-9483"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>NOW THAT REALLY IS UNUSUAL</title><source>Manchester Evening News</source><author>Jack Crone</author><text><![CDATA[PENSIONERS' social club has been slapped with an official noise warning by the council for blaring out classic songs from the likes of Tom Jones too loudly.
Droylsden Catholic Club, where the average age of members is 70, was served a statutory nuisance notice, which comes with a maximum fine of £20,000 fine and an appearance in the High Court if it is breached.
The all-men's club recently spent more than £25,000 soundproofing the venue after repeated complaints from one neighbour, and members are now becoming exasperated by the demands. Karl Jones, 38, who has been a steward at the club for seven years, said: "You would understand if it was two or three people complaining but it's one person who is threatening to shut us down. "We've spent a lot of money now. It's beyond a joke."
The venue, which has 300 members, hosts a three-piece band on Friday, Saturday and Sunday nights, usually playing pre-1970s classics, which play two 45-minute slots, from 8.30pm to 11.30pm, with a break for bingo.
Until recently, the club, established in 1959, had never received a complaint.
A new mum who lives nearby is unhappy, with the volume of the music, She also complained that members were standing outside the premises and could be heard swearing, leading the club to spend £6,000 on a new gate.
After further complaints, the club replaced old windows and installed an acoustic soundproof door.
The council recently fitted a sound limiter, designed to cut music out when it exceeds a certain level, however the devices can be ineffective if a window or doors is left open. Now the club's committee must comply with the legal notice, issued under the Environmental Protection Act, or face a hefty fine and a court appearance.
The club has until March 27 to appeal the notice but has written to the council to say it will co-operate.
Ian Saxon, assistant executive director for environmental services at Tameside council, con-firmed the abatement notice had been served and said so far there is no evidence it has been breached.
He said: "We believe the nuisance is coming from amplified music and amplified voices.
"This is an entirely routine issue which we expect to be settled amicably.
"We have received a complaint from a resident and are now speaking to officials of the club who are being entirely co-operative."
]]></text></news-item>