<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0ABF-477B-9486-0263"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>VIEWS OF THE BAY </title><source>Patriot News (Harrisburg, Pennsylvania)</source><author>CARL T. SHAFFER</author><text><![CDATA[ABOUT THE ISSUE: Weeks after 21 states signed on to a lawsuit challenging the Environmental Protection Agency's Chesapeake Bay pollution limits, more than 25,000 people have signed a petition condemning the suit. The Chesapeake Bay Foundation petition has garnered an unusually high response from the public since theattorneys general from states such as Florida, Kansas and Alaska filed an amicus brief in support of the lawsuit.
The lawsuit, filed by the American Farm Bureau Federation, the Pennsylvania Farm Bureau, the National Association of Home Builders and other related industry groups, challenges pollution limits set by the EPA under the Clean Water Act. The 21 states opposed to the plan question the EPA's authority to impose pollution limits, also known as total maximum daily loads, or TMDLs, saying the agency is violating states' rights. - Capital News Service In September 2010, this newspaper editorialized:
"The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency at times has been called overly aggressive and out of touch with reality. The way the agency is handling the Chesapeake Bay Watershed problems unfortunately epitomizes that stereotype. It appears the EPA wants the Chesapeake Bay issues solved overnight no matter what the costs to local communities and states in the midst of a big recession."
Unfortunately, your Feb. 10, 2014, editorial bashing 21 states for filing a friend-of-the-court brief in an appeal challenging the Environmental Protection Agency's violation of the Clean Water Act completely misses the mark.
You suggest that these states are sticking their noses into Pennsylvania's affairs, mischaracterizing what this appeal is all about.
These states, including one in the bay watershed, are trying to protect their local land-use decision-making authority from the extreme regulatory measures the EPA has attempted to impose in the bay. The federal Clean Water Act clearly recognizes that states retain the sole power to make land-use decisions in response to a total maximum daily load, or TMDL.
But the lower court ignored this clear directive, suggesting that EPA can stick its nose into virtually every detail of how land will be used, what infrastructure local communities will build and how local government dollars will be spent under a TMDL.
This lawsuit and appeal are not about stopping the progress of water-quality improvements. In fact, those efforts are continuing and netting positive results. We do agree with the statement in your recent editorial that the EPA has the authority to set the TMDL. Some research would have shown that neither the Farm Bureau nor any of the 21 states dispute this point.
But we object to the notion that a TMDL gives the EPA free rein over what state and local governments must do, how much they must do and when they must do it. These 21 states believe the EPA has overstepped its legal bounds and they fear the outcome if EPA's sledgehammer policies are given a free pass by the courts.
You also failed to mention the friend-of-the-court brief filed by five Pennsylvania counties in the Chesapeake Bay Watershed. These counties are legitimately concerned by the likelihood of changes, restrictions, requirements and costs that EPA could very well decide to impose.
Less than four years ago, The Patriot-News rightfully chastised the EPA for sticking its nose into decisions that should be made by Pennsylvania's public officials. State and local efforts, in coordination with the farming community, have achieved significant environmental improvements before any of the EPA's dictates.
A study recently published by the U.S. Department of Agriculture revealed the serious commitment farmers in the bay watershed have made to implement conservation practices to improve water quality.
Contrary to the EPA's apparent need to micromanage activities in the watershed, the measures reported in the study were being implemented by farmers voluntarily - with the support of state and local agencies - before the imposition of the EPA's "pollution diet."
Some choose to make "clean water" the straw man of this litigation when, in fact, the real argument is, Who should govern local land-use decisions: federal agencies or local elected officials who live in our communities?
Carl T. Shaffer is the president of the Pennsylvania Farm Bureau.
PENNLIVE/PATRIOT-NEWS EDITORIAL
From a Feb. 10 PennLive/Patriot-News editorial on the issue: "Many Pennsylvanians probably don't know (or care) who Florida's governor is. Or Alaska's. Or Louisiana's.
"But governors in those states, and 18 others, are sticking their nose into Pennsylvania's business. They're trying to torpedo a multistate pollution-fighting plan that involves cleaning up the Susquehanna River.
"That plan is designed to cut pollution flowing into the Chesapeake Bay. The Susquehanna River, the Chesapeake's largest tributary, dumps huge amounts of sediment, phosphorous and nitrogen into the bay. Together, the three pollutants are a big part of why the bay's fish, shellfish and native plant life struggle to recover to more normal levels, even after 30 years of cleanup efforts..
"In a reaction as discouraging as it was predictable, powerful special interests in the agriculture industry balked..
"Apparently, the governors worry that the big, bad, mean ol' federal government might press them to do more than just shrug off all that pollution running off their states' farms and feedlots.
"Let those states fight that battle if and when the time comes."
]]></text></news-item>