<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0AD2-D68E-B4B1-1E36"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Investigation into medical schemes registrar 'should extend to his tax affairs'</title><source>The Independent on Saturday (South Africa)</source><author> laura du preez</author><text><![CDATA[The Board of Healthcare Funders (BHF) this week expressed its concern about allegations of corruption levelled at |Dr Monwabisi Gantsho, the Registrar of Medical Schemes, and said it hoped the investigation would extend to a tax judgment obtained against the registrar |in 2012.
The South African Revenue Service (SARS) obtained a default judgment against Gantsho for R817 000, according to a |circulated credit report on the registrar.
The investigation cited by the BHF was announced by chairman of the Council for Medical Schemes, Professor Yosuf Veriava, following allegations made by the former curator of Medshield Medical Scheme that Gantsho had asked for R3 million of R10 million that Medshield paid to buy its trademark name from the former owners of Medshield's administration business.
The allegations were made as part of a High Court application that Gantsho brought to have the curator of Medshield, Themba Langa, removed. In his replying papers, Gantsho dismissed Langa's allegations as "scurrilous"and questioned why Langa had not laid a charge.
The Prevention and Combating of Corrupt Activities Act obliges anyone in a position of authority to report a corrupt activity involving more than R100 000 to the police.
The council has initiated a forensic investigation into the allegations against Gantsho as well as into Langa's conduct, but without waiting for the outcome of the investigation late last week, Veriava put out a statement saying the council was not discouraged by "the unsubstantiated allegations" made against the registrar.
The registrar has not been suspended but is on ordinary leave. Yesterday the council announced it would extend his leave until the investigation was complete.
The BHF's managing director, Humphrey Zokufa, says the registrar is the custodian of an industry that collects R113 billion annually from members of the public, and it is of utmost importance that the regulator is beyond reproach.
He says the judgment SARS obtained needs to be investigated to determine whether it was a result of any attempt to evade tax, whether the registrar was badly advised, or whether he made an honest mistake with his tax.
Zokufa says the investigation must establish whether Gantsho has enough integrity to regulate the industry.
The allegations made by Langa were contained in his replying affidavit in |the application to remove him as provisional curator of Medshield. The matter was settled out of court, Langa resigned and Tebogo Phaleng was appointed the new curator.
After the allegations against Gantsho were made, a document prepared by attorneys in 2012 at the behest of the acting chairman of the council before Veriava was appointed also came to light. It recommended that disciplinary action be taken against the registrar and said that the relationship between him and senior staff had broken down.
]]></text></news-item>