<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0B1C-8D12-E7F0-49C3"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Understanding the con; Suit details how Zeek duped victims</title><source>High Point Enterprise (North Carolina)</source><author>Paul B. Johnson; Enterprise Staff Writer</author><text><![CDATA[Triad - Buried midway through a lengthy court filing on the mammoth, malicious Zeek Rewards pyramid scheme is a two-word phrase that may sum up the con - "Monopoly money." That's what perpetrators of the global swindle - which was based from a small, nondescript office in Lexington - called the supposed revenues of the alleged multilevel marketing business and penny auction site.
A lawsuit filed recently by the receiver seeking to recoup money for Zeek Rewards victims - who range from thousands of residents in the Triad to people in 157 nations - details how the insiders in the pyramid scheme ripped off affiliates through promises of exponential returns.
All the while, the lawsuit contends, the tight-knit group of Zeek Rewards perpetrators privately acknowledged that their scam played out through the classic Ponzi scheme tactic of using revenues from newcomers to pay off initial investors.
When the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission seized the assets of Zeek Rewards on Aug. 17, 2012, authorities referred to it as a monumental Ponzi scheme on the verge of collapse.
In the lawsuit, attorney Kenneth Bell of Charlotte, the receiver in the Zeek Rewards case, says more than 700,000 participants lost more than $700 million from January 2011 until August 2012.
"This lawsuit is one of several steps the receiver is taking in his continuing effort to force those who were responsible to repay the losses caused by their unlawful conduct," Bell says in the legal action, which was filed in the U.S. District Court for the Western District of North Carolina.
The 40-page document lays out in detail how the perpetrators of Zeek Rewards used the facade of a penny auction site and multilevel marketing business to entice people, called affiliates, to contribute more and more money. One of the key ways that the insiders kept the con going was to lure people to become VIPs, offering them even greater returns if they would purchase so-called "bids." But the perpetrators of Zeek Rewards knew the whole time that the bids were illusory, the lawsuit contends. The money brought in was partially paid out as winnings to keep the scheme afloat. Indeed, one executive with Zeek Rewards referred to the bids as "Monopoly money," referencing the fake currency used in the iconic board game.
The first affiliates to join Zeek Rewards "were told to expect profit shares of 0.5 percent to 4 percent daily," according to the lawsuit.
"As the scheme progressed, participants continued to be told to expect large, consistent daily returns." However, Bell says in the lawsuit that the supposed profits for early affiliates came from the proceeds of new ones recruited to Zeek Rewards. And Zeek Rewards perpetrators used the examples and testimonials of affiliates who were enjoying big winnings to draw more people into the scheme.
As with any Ponzi scheme, Bell says, "the so-called 'profit' awards greatly exceeded total receipts, which, of course, was unsustainable." The lawsuit alleges that Zeek Rewards' insiders even used "false tax notices to perpetuate the scheme," including inaccurate filings with the Internal Revenue Service.
By its last month of its operation, Zeek Rewards was near implosion, the lawsuit says. The daily average awards were supposed to be $38.2 million, but daily receipts were averaging about $8.8 million.
As Bell concludes, the Zeek Rewards insiders "engaged in self-dealing with no regard for the fact that in a matter of months or weeks, Zeek Rewards would be unable to pay back those individuals who unwittingly bought into the lie." pjohnson@hpe.com 888-3528
]]></text></news-item>