<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0B87-70A8-B5A5-206B"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Borenius Top Ranked in Chambers Global 2014</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Since 1999, Chambers Global has been researching the legal markets of over 180 countries, identifying the leading lawyers and law firms worldwide through interviews with thousands of lawyers and their clients.
Attorneys at law Borenius and its lawyers are ranked in top tiers in Chambers Global's newest edition. Among others, Borenius is in the tier one in Intellectual Property, Restructuring/Insolvency and Tax.
See all our firm's rankings at the following link:
click http://www.borenius.com/InEnglish/News/News/Article/tabid/10570/ArticleId/1621/Default.aspx?Return=10524
COMPANY BACKGROUND
ACTIVITIES
Attorneys at law Borenius Ltd provides legal advisory services. The firm¿¿¿s practice areas include banking, bankruptcy, competition, copyright, corporate restructuring, entertainment, energy, media, environment, information technology, Internet, labour, mergers and acquisitions, patents, private equity and venture capital, private international law, financing, shipping, tax, telecom, transport, and general intellectual property law. Attorneys at law Borenius Ltd was formerly known as Attorneys at law Borenius & Kemppinen Ltd and changed its name to on May 13, 2011. The firm was founded in 1911 and is based in Helsinki, Finland. Attorneys at law Borenius Ltd operates as a subsidiary of Borenius Group.
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
26 February 2014: Borenius Excelled in the 2013 Europe Women in Business Law Awards
Euromoney Legal Media Group's annual Europe Women in Business Law Awards provides law firms recognition for their efforts in helping women advance in the legal profession. Firm and country/regional winners are judged on their ability to support the development of women in the legal profession and provide innovative work-life policies for their employees. Mainly thanks to Borenius' Crowded Years Initiative, which aims to provide for a better and more flexible working environment for employees that are living their crowded years, the firm excelled in the 2013 awards, receiving awards in the following categories: Finland - Country Award Best national firm mentoring programme Best national firm for work-life balance Source: Company Website
click http://www.borenius.com/InEnglish/News/News/Article/tabid/10570/ArticleId/1603/Default.aspx?Return=10524
25 February 2014: Borenius advised CapMan in its Acquisition of Suomen Lampoikkuna Oy
We advised funds managed by CapMan in their acquisition of the majority of the shares in Suomen Lampoikkuna Oy, a leading provider of turnkey window and door renovation solutions. Source: Company Website
click http://www.borenius.com/InEnglish/News/News/Article/tabid/10570/ArticleId/1602/Default.aspx?Return=10524
14 December 2013: Attorneys at law Borenius Ltd: Global Legal Insights - Employment & Labour Law / Jani Syrjanen, Tuomas Sunnari
This article appeared in the Second Edition of Global Legal Insights - Employment & Labour Law; published by Global Legal Group Ltd, London Read Finnish Chapter by Jani Syrjanen and Tuomas Sunnari. Source: Company Website
click http://www.borenius.com/InEnglish/News/Publications/Article/tabid/10574/ArticleId/1580/Default.aspx?Return=10524
12 December 2013: Attorneys at law Borenius Ltd: Legal Alert - Employers' Share of Funding of the Unemployment Benefits to Increase
As of 1 January 2014, the maximum amount of liability component of the unemployment insurance contribution shall be increased. The aim is to promote the employment of seniors by increasing the costs related to the termination of an employment relationship. If an employment relationship is terminated after an employee reaches the age of 56 and he/she does not find a new job before retiring, an employer may be obliged to pay as much as 90% of the employee's unemployment benefit costs.
click http://www.borenius.com/InEnglish/News/Legalalerts/Article/tabid/10572/ArticleId/1581/Default.aspx?Return=10524
12 December 2013: Attorneys at law Borenius Ltd; The International Comparative Legal Guide to Cartels & Leniency 2014 / Ilkka Aalto-Setala, Eeva-Riikka Makela
his article appeared in the 2014 edition of The International Comparative Legal Guide to: Cartels & Leniency; published by Global Legal Group Ltd, London Read Finnish Chapter by Ilkka Aalto-Setala and Eeva-Riitta Makela. Source: Company Website
click http://www.borenius.com/InEnglish/News/Publications/Article/tabid/10574/ArticleId/1582/Default.aspx?Return=10524
]]></text></news-item>