<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0BAF-A700-4466-CE7F"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Putin chooses the wrong investment; Alan Mitchell</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>Economic briefing Alan Mitchell Economics editor</author><text><![CDATA[Perhaps the biggest danger in the Ukraine crisis is that of an isolated and underperforming Russia.
The Russian economy, which grew at an average real rate of 7 per cent a year in the decade before the global financial crisis, now is struggling to grow at half that rate.
The economic development ministry has halved its estimate of Russia's long-term growth rate while prime minister Dmitry Medvedev is talking about a middle income trap and the International Monetary Fund is warning that Russia needs reform and investment to lift its potential growth rate.
Middle income traps typically afflict emerging market economies when they run out of cheap labour; Russia is running out of physical capital. Spare capacity left over from the Soviet era allowed the economy to grow strongly before the GFC without high rates of investment. But, as the IMF points out, increasing the utilisation of existing capital is relatively low risk, and can be easily reversed. Raising the rate of investment is a whole new ball game.
"Fixed capital investment - the main contributor [to capital input growth] in the next decade - is well known to be sensitive to the investment climate, including the strength of property rights and macro-economic stability, as it is more costly to reverse the investment decisions," it says.Expansion of military spending
But, instead of economic reform, president Vladimir Putin seems intent on a different kind of investment more in tune with his professional background and interests: an expansion of Russia's military spending and reclaiming Russia's role as a global power.
Before the Ukraine exploded, Russia had become the third-biggest market for arms behind the United States and China.
Having failed to reform when strong growth would have softened the pain of adjustment, Putin now offers Russian voters military power and national prestige as a substitute. His aggressive defence of Russian interests in the Ukraine is a necessary - and possibly welcome - part of his political strategy.
It is a familiar third-world story, and one that rarely ends happily. Russia is being launched on a course that could see its reasserted global power weighing ever more heavily on its partially reformed economy.
The spectacular growth from which Putin has launched Russia's strategic comeback began with the chaotic privatisation and reform of the 1990s, but it was driven by the boom in oil prices.
With the rouble appreciating strongly, Russian nominal gross domestic product measured in US dollars grew at an astonishing average annual rate 27 per cent.
On the eve of the GFC, Russia was the world's eighth-largest economy with by far the highest per capita GDP of the big emerging market economies.Putin's economic failure
But successfully managing a transition of that magnitude was a superhuman political task, and Putin was not up to it.
Anders Aslund of the Peterson Institute for International Economics in Washington says Russia allowed itself to become a victim of the same curse that has enfeebled other developing oil-rich economies.
The strength of the oil-driven rouble crushed investment in other export and import-competing industries. The huge energy revenues made it easy to put off difficult economic reform. And the concentration of energy revenues facilitated the centralisation of political power and rent-seeking.
Instead of completing the transition to a modern, market economy, Putin is accused of presiding over the development of sophisticated regime of crony and state capitalism.
His popular re-nationalisation of major oil and gas companies, including Sibneft, Yukos oil and Gazprom, is credited with undermining private investor confidence and weighing down the economy with poorly managed state-owned "national champions".
State control has also increased in the banking sector - from 35 per cent at the start of Putin's first term as president to almost 60 per cent now.Poor governance
Among the large emerging market economies, Russia is in the bottom half or, more often, at the bottom of the World Bank's governance indicators.
These include control of corruption, rule of law, regulatory quality, government effectiveness, political stability and "voice and accountability".
The IMF warns that Russia's economic outlook is increasingly dampened by supply-side constraints. The main sources of the post-communist growth surge, it seems, are exhausted.
After a rapid rebound from the GFC, growth stalled in 2013 and the IMF is projecting medium-term growth of just 3.5 per cent.
Yet, with little spare capacity, inflation has been above the central bank's target.
The central bank talks of stagflation while the economic development ministry has cut its growth projections to 2030 from an annual 4.3 per cent to just 2.5 per cent.Business climate concerns
The key factors weighing on Russia's economic outlook are the poor business climate and its continuing impact on investment.
Major business decisions of Putin's "national champions", it is claimed, frequently are driven by political considerations. At the same time, foreign oil companies have held back on investment.
Indeed, as Aslund points out, Russia's investment as a percentage of GDP has been consistently below that of countries successfully making the transition from communism to capitalism.
When oil prices were rising strongly and high rates of growth could be generated by utilising spare capacity, the weakness of investment could be overlooked. But not now.
Russia needs a new growth model.
None of this is news in Moscow. Medvedev and the minister for economic development talk about the need for reform to boost investment. The government has a plan to privatise state corporations, reform banking and improve the business investment climate. It wants to put Russia in the top 20 of the World Bank's "Doing Business" ratings by 2018, and hopes to develop Moscow as an international financial centre.
But, as the IMF says, there is no shortage of reform plans. The problem is that the implementation is too weak to change investors' perceptions of the Russian economy.
]]></text></news-item>