<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0BB2-7CF0-D111-9490"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Bus strike is set for Monday</title><source>The Burlington Free Press (Vermont)</source><author>By, Elizabeth Murray</author><text><![CDATA["Of course management doesn't want to see a strike, but they keep bludgeoning the drivers into place." Chuck Norris-Brown retired bus driver
A bus drivers' strike seems more imminent than ever in Chittenden County.
After the drivers voted unanimously to reject a final contract proposal Wednesday - the Chittenden County Transportation Authority's "last best offer" - CCTA management proposed the two parties try to settle the dispute through binding arbitration.
The drivers responded with a resounding, "No."
"We rejected binding arbitration for the same reasons we rejected management's last proposal," driver and spokesperson Rob Slingerland said in a statement. "Management and their lawyer don't have to live under the terms of their proposed contract. We do. Agreeing to binding arbitration does not move us closer to having safer working conditions, safer conditions for passengers and other drivers, or livable jobs. Those are our core demands and what is necessary to reach a settlement."
Drivers are set to strike Monday, Slingerland said. The authority serves some 9,700 riders every day, including Burlington schoolchildren. A strike would force the cancellation of all CCTA local routes and LINK Express routes, and local commuter trips operated by union drivers.
If the walkout happens, CCTA General Manager Bill Watterson told the Burlington Free Press on Thursday, the work stoppage would be the first time a drivers' strike has occurred at the authority.
At issue: the length of drivers' shifts, their working conditions and the presence of part-time workers, drivers have said.
No new negotiations with management have been scheduled, Slingerland said. Thursday afternoon, Watterson said he was confused by the announcement for a strike, because he had heard nothing directly from the Teamsters Local 597 bus drivers' union, which had been representing drivers during contract negotiations.
Mayor Miro Weinberger, meanwhile, issued a statement Thursday afternoon urging the drivers to accept the binding arbitration proposal to avoid a strike and a "damaging interruption of bus service."
"The harm that will result from a service interruption can still - and we hope will - be avoided," Weinberger said. "I continue to call on both parties to do everything possible to avoid what would be an unfortunate outcome."
Disagreements abound
The latest contract proposal followed 19 hours of negotiations with CCTA management during the weekend. The parties have been working on a contract since April 2013.
Watterson said the two sides made some headway in the latest offer, adding compensation and offering ways for employees to better submit input through the creation of an Employee Committee, which would discuss subjects affecting the workplace. The offer also clarified certain rule violations, such as sanctions for repeat offenses and being late for work, Watterson said.
When asked whether, if he were a driver, he would accept the contract offer that was presented after last weekend's negotiation, Watterson hedged.
"Boy, that's a hypothetical that's hard to say," Watterson said. "What I can tell you is that the bargaining process requires both parties to enter into it with a willingness to compromise, and a willingness to listen to the issues and concerns of the other side. I can tell you that we've done our very best to do that. It is very concerning to me that in doing that, there has been constant commentary about striking as if the process itself can't yield a satisfactory result."
The binding arbitration process would have allowed both parties to present their positions to an independent third party who then would make a decision about how to resolve differences, Watterson said. The CCTA and the union would be legally obliged to accept the arbitrator's decisions.
Watterson said an independent arbitrator differs little from a fact-finder, which also was involved in the negotiation process in January. However, the fact-finder could make only nonbinding recommendations. The fact-finder cost money, though Watterson declined to say how much, and the cost was split between the union and management. Watterson said he was unsure if an independent arbitrator also cost money, adding that the purpose in helping to solve differences would have been worth the expense.
The major points of disagreement are shift lengths, discipline and the employment of part-time workers, according to the union. Drivers also have complained of disrespectful work conditions, stating that they are constantly "spied on" by management and are threatened with suspension for small issues.
Watterson said cameras on buses are meant for ensuring driver and passenger safety, not to spy.
"We don't proactively go through video," Watterson said. "When there is an issue that arises, we will go to the video and know close in time when something occurred to be able to verify something that was claimed or what have you. ...
"Clearly the fact that drivers are saying they're having these issues and concerns means that we have to find more constructive ways to address them," Watterson added, mentioning that the Employee Committee in the most recent contract proposal would have helped alleviate many of these issues.
More action
Supporters of CCTA bus drivers and students met Thursday at the University of Vermont in the Dudley H. Davis Center to discuss ways to get more students to support the employees.
A group of about 25 people exchanged ideas about rallies, passing around fliers in classes and inviting bus drivers to speak at the university.
No current drivers were present at the gathering, but they were expected to attend a second solidarity meeting Thursday night at the Vermont Workers' Center.
CCTA supporters plan to hold a rally and speak-out at 4 p.m. today on Cherry and Church streets to help inform the public of why the drivers have chosen to strike.
Chuck Norris-Brown, a retired CCTA driver who has been involved in past negotiations but not regarding the current contract, said he is impressed by the solidarity of the drivers and the amount of support the drivers have received from community members.
"The idea is to avoid a strike for the drivers by getting management to sit down again and just listen to these things," he said. "Of course management doesn't want to see a strike, but they keep bludgeoning the drivers into place."
"Of course management doesn't want to see a strike, but they keep bludgeoning the drivers into place." Chuck Norris-Brown retired bus driver
]]></text></news-item>