<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0C11-3E79-D9FE-443B"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Gang who posed as 'King of the Gypsies' Paddy Doherty to blackmail Brum firms given 31 years; William Adams and Terrence Cunningham Snr headed the scam that targeted firms in the city </title><source>birminghammail.co.uk</source><author>By Nick McCarthy</author><text><![CDATA[Gang members who posed as 'King of the Gypsies' Paddy Doherty in a bid to blackmail cash from Birmingham business owners have been jailed for a total of 31 years.
William Adams and Terrence Cunningham Snr headed the scam that targeted firms in the city as well Newcastle, Hull, Devon and Sheffield.
The gang toured the country to carry out driveway jobs, sometimes without permission. When victims refused to pay they made threatening phone calls claiming to be Big Fat Gypsy Wedding star Paddy Doherty.
There is no suggestion Mr Doherty, the winner of Celebrity Big Brother, had any connection with the group.
William Adams, 46, and Terrence Cunningham Snr, 48, both of Askern, South Yorkshire, were handed eight-and-a-half year sentences for conspiracy to blackmail.
They were also made the subject of a director disqualification order for five years.
Terence Cunningham Jnr and Darren Squire were found guilty of conspiracy to blackmail after a six-week trial.
Gang members who posed as 'King of the Gypsies' Paddy Doherty jailed  
Cunningham, aged 26 of Askern, South Yorkshire, was handed a six-year jail term and Darren Squire, 43, also of Askern, will serve four years in prison.
Michael Howley, 72, of Messingham, Scunthorpe, who is already behind bars, was found guilty of money laundering. He was given four years.
Judge Roger Thorn QC said: "Over a 12-month period a well-planned conspiracy was in operation to blackmail, with utterly vile threats, victims who were themselves utterly honest, decent and members of the community."
The victims included landlord Steven John, from a company called Troy Best Holdings, which owns a number of properties in Birmingham.
The court heard he was in Spain when he received a call from a man describing himself as "Paddy Doherty" on August 3, 2011. The caller allegedly claimed to have some spare tarmac after doing work in the area and offered to repair some potholes in exchange for a few "drinks for the lads".
But just minutes later he was called again and told the price had rocketed to £7,500 and was warned that if he didn't pay there would be hundreds of caravans on his land, "recreating Dale Farm". Later, the gang allegedly struck at Future Garments in Birmingham, who were threatened and charged £2,600 for "shoddy" work.
]]></text></news-item>