<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0D4C-0917-87DC-FA84"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Events favour merger of two parties (Interview)</title><source>EKantipur.com</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Nepal, March 16 -- After the November 19 elections, UCPN (Maoist) Chairman Pushpa Kamal Dahal has rarely appeared in the media. The largest force in the last CA, the party is reviewing the reasons behind its poll debacle. Dahal listed party split, abandoning the party's class character and its flawed policy on national sovereignty as the major reasons for the poor show. Akhilesh Upadhyay and Kamal Dev Bhattarai spoke to Dahal on election review, possible unification with the CPN-Maoist, the party's position on local polls and the ongoing peace and constitution-drafting process. Excerpts:
After the Constituent Assembly election, you remained silent for a long time. Why?
It's not true that we remained silent because of the electoral loss. Soon after the elections, we spent time reviewing the results and other party-related activities. It would have been inappropriate to make public statements without revamping the political, ideological and organisational aspects of the party. There are no other big reasons.
What is your take on your party's loss in the election?
We have broadly pointed out two reasons-internal and external factors-that led to our defeat. In totality, we have reviewed that internal factors-party split, organisational mess at the grassroots level and the lack of proper management of party cadres-were primarily responsible.
There were external factors also in play. We have concluded there was a big a conspiracy to marginalise the Maoist party by status-quoist forces. There were irregularities in the election. But all these happened due to our internal weaknesses so we have to strengthen our internal situation.
Another reason is that we lost our class character and switched over to the opposite class. Our approach to national sovereignty was also flawed. We gave more priority to diplomatic solution to issues related to sovereignty but failed to communicate to the people and mobilise the masses.
Was your position on federalism flawed and hence the defeat?
Our policy on federalism is not flawed but it was misinterpreted by regressive and status-quoist forces. We have never raised the issue of single-ethnic identity-based federalism. What we have been saying is that people who have been marginalised or oppressed on the grounds of caste, class and geography should be given equal rights. We have realised that we should properly communicate our position on federalism to the people. We want cordial relations among all caste/ethnic groups.
Could you explain the "external factor"?
External forces do not only mean the factors beyond our party. State mechanism did not work independently and in an impartial way to hold the polls. I have made a conclusion that the state mechanism made efforts to marginalise the Maoist party in the election. On the international factor, I do not want to comment further.
But, your party failed to provide concrete evidences of vote fraud.
The voting process was normal, peaceful and problem-free. But during the transportation of ballot boxes, we sensed there was a conspiracy to defeat our party. We had decided to ask the government and the EC to halt the counting process and investigate such incidents. We have not abandoned our position that there was a fraud. We are seeking a parliamentary probe committee as stated in the cross-party agreement.
Baburam Bhattarai is publicly saying that the party chairman should consider giving up his position taking moral responsibility for the electoral outcome.
I have taken moral responsibility for the defeat. But election was just a political battle and we have not lost the entire war. Bhattarai has no ground to say the chairman has been unsuccessful and should take all the responsibility for the poll debacle. In all the decisions regarding the polls, we worked very closely. All the political decisions were made in consensus between the two leaders. I implemented the suggestions made by Baburamji while he was the PM.
It is wrong and subjective to now say that the party chairman has failed. It would not be in Baburamji's interest to make such remarks as we took decisions jointly in the crucial period. Leadership handover won't happen now. There should proper planning and preparations for it.
The UCPN (Maoist) says that formation of the Khil Raj Regmi government was a blunder. Is it true that Bhattarai was in favour of a party-led government?
Originally, we were in favour of holding the CA election under a political party-led government. Bhattarai first proposed a government led by NC President Sushil Koirala and I agreed. But he backtracked and took a strong position that he would not accept Koirala as PM. He took a firm position that the government leadership should not be handed over to the NC. So it was not possible to form a party-led government.
Bhattarai has been talking about the need for a new political force. What is your opinion?
We have not discussed the issue in party. We will soon hold an intra-party discussion on it. As the party chairman, it would not be appropriate to comment on it. After intensive discussion and consensus in the party's Central Committee, we are implementing a party rebuilding plan and policy at the grassroots level. The problems facing the party will not be resolved by talking about a new force. Our priority should be to strengthen party ideology and organisations. New force is an abstract terminology. Bhattarai seems more worried about the party after the polls. We are holding a national convention for the party rebuilding process.
Why has the national convention been called?
We want to rebuild the party in a bottom-up approach. We want the focus of leaders and cadres on the grassroots. We are establishing a system in order to win the hearts and minds of people. In essence, we want to bridge the gap prevailing between the people and the leaders.
You are in talks with the CPN-Maoist for unification. Does this mean you will backtrack on the line of peace and constitution?
It is now clear that the party split was wrong and it caused a great loss to the parties, the country and the revolution. Our belief that even after the split, we would win the election and form a government as the largest party proved wrong. Similarly, the CPN-Maoist thought that revolt was possible after split. They also failed to launch a revolt. The realisation that the split was a blunder creates common ground for reviewing our positions. This is the starting point for party unification. As forces fighting the war together, Truth and Reconciliation Commission and Commission on the Disappeared were another common concern. Attempts to revive war-era cases and arrest cadres of both the parties are compelling us to get closer.
But are you ready to change the political line passed by the seventh general convention?
We have already decided that the political line taken by the seventh general convention should be revised. We will change the political line from our upcoming national convention that begins on May 1. But let me state that there is no possibility of a People's War or revolt in the near future. The two parties can formulate a common ground so that we can move ahead in drafting a progressive constitution. The CA can hold a round-table conference to bring the CPN-Maoist in the constitution drafting process. On the contents of the new constitution, there are no big differences between the UCPN (Maoist) and the CPN-Maoist.
Your election manifesto pledges local election in six months. Why is your party opposing it now?
In principle, we would not oppose the idea of local elections. But drafting a constitution at the earliest-not holding local elections-is our prime responsibility. Parties have agreed to prepare the first draft of the new constitution within six months. Local elections will spoil the environment of cordiality and consensus among the parties. It will only make it difficult to forge consensus on contentious issues of the constitution. We can hold local polls after having the constitution. Another point is that the Interim Constitution does not envisage local elections and the constitution will have to be amended for holding the polls. There cannot be consensus among the parties for constitution amendment.
Is there any possibility of a compromise for holding local elections before the constitution?
Holding local elections before drafting the constitution is impossible.
What is your bottom-line on drafting a new constitution?
Our view is that the change in the size of political parties does not affect constitution-writing. The 12-point understanding, Comprehen-sive Peace Agreement and Interim Constitution define basic principles for the new constitution. Progressive restructuring of the state and granting rights to oppressed and marginalised communities are the basic principles of the new constitution and no party can go against them. But there are no positive signs. The political trend post-election does not head to that direction. If the NC and the UML try to use their numerical strength to impose their ideas, we won't simply remain a witness.
Relating to corruption, there were complaints before the polls about the conduct of Maoist leaders. Has there been any review?
We have discussed it at length. But there has not been corruption in the same level as the people believe. But the gap between leaders and cadres is widening. We formed a commission to investigate corruption charges against our leaders, including me. On the basis of the report, we have taken action against some leaders.
Many believe that you are involved in joint ventures with some businesspeople. Is it true?
It is totally false, malicious and misleading. It is a conspiracy to defame me and the party. I do not have any shares or joint ventures with any business houses and individuals. People often linked me with Ajaya Sumargiji but I have equidistant relationship with all the business people of the country. I don't have any special relation with Sumargiji.
People term the Tinkune-Maitighar road as Prachandapath saying that you have invested in some businesses in this area.
(Laughs). It's baseless. There is Mukti Tower which many people think is named after my father and I have invested there. I have not invested in any business. The tower is named after Muktinath temple.
In the past, you achieved a number of victories, but at the crucial constitution drafting phase you lost the election. Don't you think you are failing in the constitution drafting process?
I realise that my political successes made me subjective in analysing national politics. Ever since I took the party helm, the party has witnessed many ups and downs. I thought that my party would win the election but that proved wrong. I have realised that I was overconfident. But in defeat, the army gets an opportunity to learn battle lessons. I have felt a greater responsibility to revamp party organisations.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from EKantipur.com. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>