<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0DE2-C813-7CA9-C180"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Faruqi &amp; Faruqi, LLP Encourages Investors Who Suffered Losses in Excess of $100,000 Investing in LifeLock, Inc. to Contact the Firm</title><source>Marketwired</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP, a leading national securities law firm, reminds investors in LifeLock, Inc. ("LifeLock" or the "Company") (NYSE: LOCK) of the May 5, 2014 deadline to seek the role of lead plaintiff in a federal securities class action lawsuit filed against LifeLock and certain executives.
A complaint has been filed on behalf of all persons who purchased or otherwise acquired LifeLock securities between February 26, 2013 and February 19, 2014, inclusive (the "Class Period") in the District of Arizona.
The complaint alleges that the Company and its executives violated federal securities laws with respect to its disclosures concerning its business, operations, and prospects.
Specifically, the action alleges that throughout the Class Period defendants made false and/or misleading statements and/or failed to disclose that the Company: (i) engaged in marketing and advertising practices that violated applicable government rules and regulations; (ii) violated a March 2010 settlement order it entered into with the Federal Trade Commission ("FTC"); and (iii) earned revenue through violations of the FTC Act and the settlement order.
On Sunday, February 23, 2014 an article published on www.SeekingAlpha.com disclosed that LifeLock met with the FTC regarding the Company's alleged non-compliance with the settlement order.
Following this news, the Company's stock declined $1.47 per share, or over 6%, to close at $20.32 per share on February 24, 2014.
Request more information now by clicking here: www.faruqilaw.com/LOCK. There is no cost or obligation to you.
Take Action
If you invested in LifeLock stock or options between February 26, 2013 and February 19, 2014 and would like to discuss your legal rights, visit www.faruqilaw.com/LOCK. You can also contact us by calling Richard Gonnello or Francis McConville toll free at 877-247-4292 or at 212-983-9330 or by sending an e-mail to rgonnello@faruqilaw.com or fmcconville@faruqilaw.com Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP also encourages anyone with information regarding LifeLock's conduct to contact the firm, including whistleblowers, former employees, shareholders and others.
Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP is a national law firm which represents investors and individuals in class action litigation. The firm is focused on providing exemplary legal services in complex litigation in the areas of securities, shareholder, antitrust and consumer litigation, throughout all phases of litigation. The firm has an experienced trial team which has achieved significant victories on behalf of the firm's clients. To keep track of the latest securities litigation news, follow us on Twitter at www.twitter.com/MergerActivity or on Facebook at www.facebook.com/FaruqiLaw.
Attorney Advertising. The law firm responsible for this advertisement is Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP (www.faruqilaw.com). Prior results do not guarantee or predict a similar outcome with respect to any future matter. We welcome the opportunity to discuss your particular case. All communications will be treated in a confidential manner.
SOURCE: Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP
]]></text></news-item>