<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0E41-DE9C-6F2B-8201"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>The Wall Street Journal</title><source>JAGfn.com</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Temasek-Led Consortium Offers to Buy Out Olam - A consortium led by Singapore's state investment firm Temasek said it will put up $1.99 billion to buy the rest of commodity trader Olam International.French Minister Weighs In on SFR - French Industry Minister Arnaud Montebourg said the board of Vivendi prefers cable operator Altice's bid to buy a controlling stake in its SFR phone unit, above a rival offer from conglomerate Bouygues, a merger he dislikes.Google Settlement Seems Unsettled - Google Inc.'s wrangles with European antitrust regulators appeared all but over in February. Five weeks later, the case looks far from closed.Surge in Oil Shipments Sidetracks Other Industries - A snarl in railroad traffic, stemming largely from pileups at BNSF Railway, is ricocheting through the supply chains of businesses across the U.S., causing delays and losses for shippers of goods ranging from coal to sugar. GE Plans IPO of Credit-Card Unit - GE filed for an initial public offering of the unit that provides financing plans and private-label credit cards for North American retailers.BP Reaches Agreement With U.S. - BP's pact with the EPA will allow the energy company to do business again with the federal government following the Deepwater Horizon explosion.UniCredit Caught in a Dilemma - Executives at the Italian bank faced an unpleasant decision about fourth-quarter results: announce a record-breaking loss or run the risk of displeasing investors and Italian regulators.DOT Lacked Information on GM Ignition Switch Problem - U.S. Transportation Secretary Anthony Foxx, testifying before a Senate committee, said the agency might have pushed for a recall sooner.
Pressures Over Sale to Russian Firm - Russia's intervention in Ukraine signals trouble for OAO Rosneft's bid to buy Morgan Stanley's oil-trading unit, according to people involved in the deal and others familiar with the U.S. government's approval process.Toshiba Sues SK Hynix - Japanese tech giant says Friday it filed a lawsuit seeking damages against the South Korean chip maker, alleging that it illegally obtained its NAND flash memory technology.
]]></text></news-item>