<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0E4A-DB94-BA3C-A61F"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Crash deaths 'preventable'; North Sea helicopter accident inquiry finding</title><source>Dumfries and Galloway Standard</source><author>Sharon Liptrott</author><text><![CDATA[Bereaved relatives are calling for a criminal probe after a fatal accident inquiry found that the North Sea helicopter crash deaths were preventable.
The lawyer for the families, Tom Marshall, yesterday called for a "wider public inquiry" and a meeting is being sought with the Lord Advocate.
Dumfries father-of-two, 63-year-old David Rae, was the oldest of the 16 men who died when the Super Puma helicopter, dropped "like a torpedo" into the North Sea 12 miles off Peterhead on April 1, 2009. It had been en route from BP's Miller Oil Platform to Aberdeen in clear and sunny conditions and calm sea.
Mr Rae, who was nearing retirement after more than 30 years in the oil industry, was one of 10 crew employed by KCA Deutag on board and had spent a fortnight on the oilfield platform. His wife, Shona, and children Callum and Fiona, had expected him home later that day.
Although a "routine" flight, it ended in tragedy with all 14 oil workers and two crew killed.
Days before the flight there had been a problem with the gearbox but it had not been replaced because of a series of verbal and email misunderstandings with the manufacturer.
Yesterday, Sheriff Principal Derek Pyle, published the findings of the fatal accident inquiry held during January and February in Aberdeen Townhouse, in which evidence was given by owners of the Supa Puma GREDL, Bond Offshore Helicopters Limited, manufacturers Eurocopter, as well as crash investigators.
He found that Mr Rae died from "multiple injuries" sustained during the crash.
The sheriff principal said "the pattern of injury was entirely consistent with the circumstances and death would have been instantaneous".
In keeping with an earlier Air Accidents Investigation branch report, he also found that the cause of the accident was the "catastrophic" failure of the main rotor gearbox. This was a result of a "fatigue fracture".
The FAI found that, on that fateful day, co-pilot Richard Menzies had told air traffic control at Aberdeen Airport to expect them in 20 minutes but six seconds later an oil warning light came on, followed by a "grinding" noise.
Two mayday calls were made but it was too late: the main rotor broke away and severed the tail boom, sending the fuselage into a "rapid descent into the sea."
It had all taken just 20 seconds.
Sheriff Principal Pyle found that Bond failed to follow correct procedure and the aircraft maintenance manual.
He said it was "possible" that if the failures had not occurred "the accident might have been avoided".
In his report, he said there was a "laxity in following correct procedures in dealing with Eurocopter - and undoubtedly that should not have happened.
"The essential fact is that everyone in the company well knew that maintenance must be done by the book.
"On one occasion that fundamental rule was broken.
It resulted in the failure to detect a significant fault in the helicopters gearbox, which possibly - only possibly - resulted in the crash."
In a statement yesterday, Bond Offshore Helicopters said: "We have always accepted that we made mistakes through honest confusion over telephone calls and emails. Lessons needed to be learned, lessons have been learned and lessons continue to be learned."
The sheriff principal had praised the "courage" of the families during the FAI.
They now want a criminal inquiry, despite the Crown Office saying there was "insufficient evidence" for a prosecution last year. Mr Rae's family were unavailable for comment.
]]></text></news-item>