<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0E7D-AE1E-6DB5-19AB"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>£1m to combat abuse</title><source>The Huddersfield Daily Examiner</source><author>Louise Cooper</author><text><![CDATA[WEST Yorkshire's Crime Commissioner has announced £1m funding to support victims of domestic abuse to ensure they 'don't suffer in silence'.
Mark Burns-Williamson made the funding pot available to tackle an issue which sees an average of 100 domestic abuse reports every day across West Yorkshire.
He said: "Domestic violence is a serious and violent crime that is of particular concern to people and partners across West Yorkshire and it should not be tolerated by anyone.
"Abuse in the home can often be hidden but can have far reaching effects. I take this issue so seriously that I have agreed this funding of £1m with councils and community safety partners.
"Because of its seriousness and the implications it can have for victims' and children's health and wellbeing, protecting those in most danger is rightly the focus for those involved in policing, community safety and health.
"I am pleased to acknowledge the work that West Yorkshire Police is doing every day, and specifically this week, to raise awareness of the support available to victims and offenders and would encourage anyone being subjected to abuse not to suffer in silence."
Mr Burns-Williamson said the introduction later this year of new domestic violence protection orders will give more powers to police and magistrates and demonstrate to deal with offenders.
Assistant Chief Constable Geoff Dodd said: "Domestic abuse is not a crime that is confined to any particular neighbourhood or group; it can and does affect people from any background. The abuse is often physical but it can also be controlling or coercive behaviour designed to make a victim feel subordinate or frightened.
"We know that on average, a victim suffers abuse on 35 occasions before calling the police. I would encourage victims to step forward and seek our support."
For those seeking help or advice, whether a victim or a family member, friend or colleague calling on their behalf, you can speak to your local Police Safeguarding Unit by calling 101 or the National Domestic Violence Helpline 24 hours a day on 0808 8024040.
There are also a number of local services available with details on the West Yorkshire Police website at: www.westyorkshire.police.uk/domesticviolence
]]></text></news-item>