<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0ECB-5BC3-E1B7-9D36"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>ob</title><source>The Washington Post</source><author>Samantha Raphelson</author><text><![CDATA[George F. CombsFTC staff attorney
George F. Combs, a staff attorney with the Federal Trade Commission for more than three decades, died Feb. 11 at the Homewood at Crumland Farms retirement community in Frederick, Md. He was 92.
The cause was congestive heart failure, said his son, George Combs.
Mr. Combs, a Frederick resident, joined the FTC in 1949 and served as the legal adviser to several FTC commissioners before retiring in 1980.
He received the FTC's Distinguished Service Award for his career contributions. His award citation stated that he had prepared drafts of more than 100 of the commission's adjudicative opinions.
George Frailey Combs was born in Emmitsburg, Md., and was a 1942 graduate of what was then Mount St. Mary's College in Emmitsburg. He received a law degree in 1948 from the Dickinson School of Law, which is now part of Pennsylvania State University.
During World War II, Mr. Combs served in the Army Air Forces. His decorations included the Distinguished Flying Cross and three Air Medals.
He was a member of Fairlington United Methodist Church in Alexandria.
His wife of 60 years, Doris Peppler Combs, died in 2011.
Survivors include two children, George Combs Jr. of Roswell, Ga., and Virginia Combs of Lutherville, Md., in Baltimore County; two grandchildren; and one great-grandson.
- Megan McDonough
Mildred C. DeGroate, a dietitian at the Naval Medical Hospital Center in Bethesda for 36 years, died Jan. 27 at her home in Washington. She was 88.
She had Alzheimer's disease, her granddaughter Shavonne Bowman said.
Mrs. DeGroate left the Naval Medical Hospital Center in the late 1970s. Later, she worked as a private home health-care aide for the elderly for eight years.
Mildred Chance was born in Emporia, Va., and settled in Washington in 1966. She was a member of the Elizabeth Ross Golden Society Temple, a woman's missionary group in Washington.
Her husband of 16 years, George DeGroate, died in 1967. Survivors include a daughter, Debbie DeGroate of Washington; three grandchildren; and four great-grandchildren.
- Megan McDonough
Rosemary Stanfield, a former chief deputy clerk of the tax division of the D.C. Superior Court who later became a real estate agent for the Washington area, died Feb. 7. She was 78.
The cause was cardiac arrest, her daughter, Vicki Hammond, said, and she was pronounced dead at a hospital in McDonough, Ga.
Mrs. Stanfield, a McDonough resident, began her career in the D.C. court system as an administrative assistant in 1958. She was named chief deputy clerk of the court's tax division in the early 1980s.
After her retirement in 1990, Mrs. Stanfield worked as a real estate agent with Town & Country Properties in Arlington County from 1997 until 2004.
Rosemary Winebrenner was born in the Allegany County, Md., community of Carlos. She moved to the Washington region in 1953 and lived in Centreville, Va. In 2004, she settled in McDonough.
She volunteered at Centreville United Methodist Church and at elementary schools in Northern Virginia.
Her husband of 42 years, James B. Stanfield, died in 1996.
Survivors include three children, Vicki Hammond of Seattle, Barry Stanfield of Aldie, Va., and Adam Stanfield of Tampa; six grandchildren; and one great-grandson.
- Megan McDonough
Martin E. Sloane, who championed against discrimination in employment and housing as a longtime official with the National Committee Against Discrimination in Housing, died Feb. 12 at the Washington Home hospice. He was 85.
The cause was pneumonia, said his daughter Phoebe Sloane.
Mr. Sloane worked with the rights group from 1973 to 1987, initially as general counsel and later as executive vice president. He testified before Congress on employment discrimination and equal education opportunities and wrote extensively in reports on residential segregation and mortgage credit discrimination.
Martin Everett Sloane was born in the Bronx. He was a 1949 graduate of New York University and received a master's degree in English from the University of Michigan in 1950.
After serving in the Army Counter Intelligence Corps, he graduated from Columbia University Law School in 1958. Early in his career, he was chief of the housing section at the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, a lawyer-adviser at the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development and an assistant staff director of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights Office of Program and Policy Review.
He was a District resident and, in retirement, continued to advocate for fair housing by representing tenants in their grievances against the D.C. public housing agency.
Survivors include his wife of 61 years, Glenda Goldberg Sloane of Washington; three daughters, Jessica Sloane of Takoma Park, Md., Amy Sloane of New York and Phoebe Sloane of San Diego; a brother; and four grandchildren.
- Zach C. Cohen
Sara S. Donnelly, a sales representative for the Beauty Counselors cosmetics company from the late 1950s to the early 1970s, died Feb. 25 at a hospice in Mount Airy, Md. She was 94.
The cause was cancer, said a friend, Joseph Rezash.
Sara Strong was born in Adamstown, Md., and raised in Washington, where she was a 1937 graduate of Roosevelt High School. She did secretarial work for the Navy Department during World War II.
She was a resident of Leisure World retirement community in Silver Spring and a past officer with the Wheaton Woods Citizens Association. She attended Our Lady of Grace Catholic Church in Silver Spring.
Her husband of 58 years, Edward F. Donnelly, died in 2006. She had no immediate survivors.
- Samantha Raphelson
Nicholas J. Cinciotta, an official reporter of debates for the U.S. Senate from 1954 to 1974, died Jan. 19 at Montgomery Hospice's Casey House in Rockville. He was 99.
The cause was pneumonia, said his daughter, Linda Cinciotta Olguin.
After an early career as a shorthand reporter employed by private Washington companies, Mr. Cinciotta was a shorthand reporter for the U.S. District Court in Washington from 1946 to 1954. He then spent 20 years in the Senate and continued worked as a freelancer until 1979. He was a longtime resident of the Leisure World retirement community in Silver Spring.
Nicholas Joseph Cinciotta was a New York native and graduated in 1933 from a shorthand reporting school in Brooklyn. He served in the Army in the Pacific during World War II.
He was a member of the choir at Our Lady of Grace Church in Silver Spring.
His wife of 63 years, LaVerne Oakley Cinciotta, died in 2004. Survivors include his wife of eight years, Lydia Evan of Silver Spring; three daughters from his first marriage, Linda Cinciotta Olguin of Rockville, Cathleen Cameron of Haymarket, Va., and Ruth Lobe of Ellicott City, Md.; two sisters; four grandchildren; and four great-grandchildren.
- Samantha Raphelson
Nan Hillman, who gave private piano lessons at her home in Silver Spring since the mid-1970s, died Feb. 27 at Montgomery Hospice's Casey House in Rockville. She was 80.
The cause was complications from kidney disease, said her son, Richard Bucheimer Jr.
Claire Nanette Baker was born in Moscow, Pa. She received a teacher's certificate from the Peabody Institute of Johns Hopkins University and moved to the Washington area in the late 1960s. She was a 1980 music graduate of the University of Maryland.
Mrs. Hillman was a member and monitor with the Washington Music Teachers Association and chaired many of the association's piano competitions, including the Viola Hartman Piano Performance Awards in Washington and the Tselentis Bach Competition.
In the 1960s, she fought for the desegregation of the old Tivoli Theatre in Frederick, Md., and was involved with a tutoring program for children of migrant workers.
Her first marriage, to Richard Bucheimer, ended in divorce. Survivors include her second husband of 43 years, Erik Hillman of Silver Spring; four children from her first marriage, Richard Bucheimer Jr., David Bucheimer and Robert Bucheimer, all of Frederick, and Christine Allen of Annapolis; a sister, Audrey Chalk of Sterling, Va.; nine grandchildren; and three great-grandchildren.
- Megan McDonough
Evelyn E. Meadows, who did administrative work for the CIA from the late 1960s to the late 1980s, died Jan. 21 at her daughter's home in Winchester, Va. She was 89.
The cause was myelodysplastic syndrome, a form of blood cancer, said a daughter, Janet Fearson.
Mrs. Meadows did administrative work at the Pentagon for a decade before becoming a homemaker in 1953.
Evelyn Eleanor Krigosky was born in Jermyn, Pa., and settled in the Washington area in 1943. She was a resident of Vienna.
Her husband of 60 years, Max Meadows, died in 2011.
Survivors include three daughters, Ellen Shell of Winchester, Va., Janet Fearson of Vienna and Kerry Meadows of Hamilton, Va., in Loudoun County; seven grandchildren; and nine great-grandchildren.
- Megan McDonough
William J. Chambliss, a criminologist and professor of sociology at George Washington University for more than two decades, died Feb. 22 at his home in Washington. He was 80.
The cause was cancer, said a daughter, Lauren Chambliss.
Dr. Chambliss was a sociology professor at the University of Delaware for a decade before joining George Washington University's sociology department in 1986. He co-directed the university's Institute on Crime, Justice and Corrections and taught courses in criminology, criminal justice, sociological theory and the sociology of law.
According to the Law and Society Association, Dr. Chambliss was a leading figure in conflict criminology and the contemporary sociology of law. Earlier in his teaching career, he taught at the University of California at Santa Barbara.
William Joseph Chambliss was born in Buffalo, N.Y. He was a 1955 sociology graduate of the University of California at Los Angeles and received a PhD in sociology from the University of Indiana in 1962.
He wrote, co-authored and edited more than 25 books and published scholarly articles. His honors included two lifetime achievement awards from the American Sociological Association. He was past president of the American Criminological Society and the Society for the Study of Social Problems.
In 2012, the Society for the Study of Social Problems created the William J. Chambliss Lifetime Achievement Award to "recognize career-spanning excellence and achievement in the area of law and society."
His marriage to Louisa Mackie ended in divorce. Survivors include his wife of 25 years, Pernille Baadsager Chambliss of Washington; three children from his first marriage, Lauren Chambliss of Ithaca, N.Y., and Jeff Chambliss and James Chambliss, both of Santa Barbara; a sister; and four grandchildren.
- Megan McDonough
]]></text></news-item>