<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0F30-EA30-AEBD-142C"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>--- MISSING HEADLINE</title><source>Vincennes Sun-Commercial (Indiana)</source><author>Staff Writer</author><text><![CDATA[Body found ID'd as missing woman
MONTGOMERY - Authorities say a body found near a southwestern Indiana creek has been identified as that of a former Illinois woman who was swept away by floodwaters in December.
Indiana Conservation Officer Mike Kellner said Saturday in a statement that an autopsy also found that 31-year-old Kathryn McGill's had drowned.
A local resident found the former Des Plaines, Ill., woman's body Friday amid corn stalk debris near the mouth of a creek that feeds into the White River at the Pike-Daviess County line.
That's near the site where crews launched a search for McGill on Dec. 29 after a vehicle she and her husband were riding in was swept away by floodwaters along Indiana 257.
Adam McGill was rescued by hunters, but his wife could not be located.
Biomet plans $40.5 million  upgrade, 150 new jobs
WARSAW - Medical device maker Biomet Inc. is planning a $40.5 million expansion company officials say would create 150 high-paying new jobs at Biomet's northern Indiana operations by 2018.
Biomet's project calls for building renovations and adding 3-D printing and optical scanning technology. The Warsaw-based company would also upgrade a center where surgeons interested in introducing a new product, technology or technique can explore the idea with an expert.
The Fort Wayne Journal Gazette reports Biomet's global vice president of finance presented the project Thursday to the Kosciusko County Council, which voted unanimously to move the company's request for incentives to the next stage.
Paperwork prepared by the company says the jobs the expansion would bring are projected to pay $75,000 a year on average and will be added in stages.
Lawmakers preserve O'Bannon's pension
INDIANAPOLIS - Indiana lawmakers have deleted language in a law that threatened the state pension former first lady Judy O'Bannon began drawing after Gov. Frank O'Bannon died in 2003.
The Democratic governor's widow married attorney Donald Willsey in November at age 78. Soon after, it came to light that a state employee pension law specifies that if a governor's spouse remarries, that person will lose the governor's pension.
Once that information reached political circles, leaders of both parties agreed the law needed to be changed.
Lawmakers researched the law and found that it contained a provision that applied only to the spouse of a governor who remarries. Other state employees in similar circumstances were not affected.
Language deleting the provision was added to a public pension bill that passed both chambers and is now awaiting Gov. Mike Pence's signature, The Indianapolis Star reported Saturday.
Senate President Pro Tempore David Long said that if Judy O'Bannon lost any pension in the interim, it would be reinstated. He said Judy O'Bannon had served beside Gov. O'Bannon - who died during his second term in September 2003 after a stroke - throughout his years in office and she had earned the pension.
"It was the right thing to do," Long, R-Fort Wayne, told the newspaper. "It was one of the good things we were able to do this session."
Firm, owner fined $200,000  for dumping grease into sewer
HAMMOND - A federal judge has ordered a northwestern Indiana company and its owner to pay $200,000 in fines and restitution for illegally dumping grease into the city of Hammond's sewer system.
U.S. District Judge Philip Simon also sentenced NH Environmental's owner, Ronald Holmes, on Friday to four years of probation and 100 hours of community service.
The Griffith man and his East Chicago company pleaded guilty last year to felony and misdemeanor pollution discharge counts for dumping waste - mostly grease from local restaurants - into Hammond's sewers, not paying the proper city fees and failing to file monthly reports.
Holmes' attorney, Jackie Bennett Jr., argued that his client had thought his company had a valid waste discharge permit because Holmes had previously leased the building to another company and allowed that company to use his permit.
In fact, the permit had expired and the tenant had applied for, and kept, the permit under its own name, the Post-Tribune of Merrillville reported.
James Morgulec, an attorney with the Department of Justice's Environmental Crimes Division, argued that Holmes, who has worked in the waste industry for decades, should have known from experience the permit wasn't his to use.
Holmes must pay a $30,000 fine, and NH Environmental must pay a $70,000 fine and $100,000 in restitution to the city of Hammond and its sanitary district.
'Hair' bares all, covers up in 2 Indiana shows
EVANSVILLE - Indiana theater patrons got different versions of the 1960s-era musical "Hair" when it stopped in Fort Wayne and Evansville recently.
The audience at Fort Wayne's Embassy Theatre saw the original version that included a brief nude scene. Evansville theater-goers were treated to a "clean" performance in which cast members kept their clothes on.
The Evansville Courier & Press reports the Aiken Theatre opted for no nudity after receiving complaints that a 2010 production of "Spring Awakening" was vulgar. The show features nudity and simulated sexual encounters.
Embassy Theatre marketing director Barb Richards says the Fort Wayne venue polled theater-goers on Facebook to gauge whether they wanted the original version or the "clean" version. She says the theater advertised the nudity in advance and had no complaints.
Kokomo presses for cleanup of tornado damage
KOKOMO - Kokomo officials are pushing owners of tornado-damaged properties to repair the properties or tear them down.
The Kokomo Tribune reports (http://bit.ly/1nMlqvB ) the city's code enforcement section has begun sending letters to owners of damaged structures urging them to make a decision about how to proceed.
Some owners say they haven't started to repair damage from the Nov. 17 storms because they are still working with their insurance companies.
Deputy Fire Chief Nick Glover says officials haven't pushed the issue with property owners until now because of the harsh winter. But he says it's time for the cleanup to pick up steam.
City and state officials estimate that more than 100 commercial and business structures were damaged by the tornado and that up to 1,000 homes were damaged or destroyed.
Report: City councilman likely didn't violate oath
SOUTH BEND - An attorney for the South Bend Common Council says council member Henry Davis Jr. likely did not violate his oath of office when he posted an explicit photo of a naked man and a dog to his Facebook page.
But the South Bend Tribune reports that a report by council attorney Kathleen Cekanski-Farrand says Henry Davis Jr. may have violated the council's rules of decorum. The council's Rules Committee must now review the report and determine whether Davis' actions constitute a code or statutory violation.
State police also are investigating the photo. Kosciusko County Prosecutor Daniel Hampton has been assigned to act as special prosecutor in the case.
Davis held a news conference last month calling the posting a mistake and asking for forgiveness.
]]></text></news-item>