<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0F77-A0CB-A1A5-51AB"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Wisconsin goes boom, locker room bigotry and French smog</title><source>Cynic Central</source><author>mozzie</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 15, 2014 (Cynic Central:http://cynic-central.blogspot.com Delivered by Newstex) - Look the hell out, Latvia. Heads are rolling and apparently, it's unacceptable for a government official - even one with as little power as the country's environment minister - to participate in annual commemorations of Latvian soldiers who fought in Nazi units during World War II. What would seem like a wonderful event for anyone to be a part of given that people died for their country and are being honored was instead a reason to pink slip Environment Minister Einars Cilinskis of the right-wing National Alliance.
Cilinskis announced Friday that he would attend Sunday's events in Riga, flying in the face of warnings from Prime Minister Lamidota Straujuma. The prime minister's spokesman, Andis Blinds, explained that because of an act of direct and willful defiance, Straujuma had no choice but to dismiss Cilinskis, who was not only the minister of environmental protection, but also of regional development. Why would any prime minister dare order members of his government to stay away from a seemingly positive happening? The warning for Cabinet ministers to stay away from the March 16 events was allegedly issued because they are expected to prompt counter-protests from members of Latvia's Russian-speaking minority. Oh, and most Latvians consider the Waffen SS veterans as heroes who fought for independence from the Soviet Union. Russians commonly view the march as an attempt to glorify fascism, which quite frankly does not happen often enough in the world these days as fascist, dictatorial leaders are in dwindling supply. This charade isn't going to help matters at all…….. - It's cash-grab time for one of the most iconic rock bands of all-time. Yes, Led Zeppelin wants in on the gravy train once again. Jimmy Page, Robert Plant and Co. are reaching into the wallets of loyal fans with the tired, er, tried and true move of reissuing digitally re-mastered versions of their old albums and tossing in a handful of 'previously unreleased rarities' that have never been heard before. Led Zep will re-release its first three albums and sprinkle in four new tracks to entice fans to buy music they already own. The new song 'La La' will appear on the second disc of 'Led Zeppelin II,' while 'Led Zeppelin III' will feature 'Jennings Farm Blues,' 'Bathroom Sound' and 'Keys To The Highway/Trouble In Mind.' Previously, the unreleased tracks had only been available to the 100 percent of music fans willing to pick up bootleg albums and get their hands on the same music as everyone else, except for free. There will also be a live music inclusion in the package, as a recording of a gig recorded at Olympia Theatre in Paris from October 1969 will accompany the overhauled version of the original 'Led Zeppelin' album. The companion audio for the new 'Led Zeppelin II' will get a boost from alternate mixes of five songs from the album, backing tracks to 'Thank You' and 'Living Loving Maid (She's Just A Woman).' The 'Led Zeppelin III' re-release will come with a bonus disc filled with seven studio outtakes of songs from the album as well as the aforementioned three previously unheard compositions. "The material on the companion discs presents a portal to the time of the recording of Led Zeppelin," Page said. "It is a selection of work in progress with rough mixes, backing tracks, alternate versions and new material recorded at the time." To appeal to hipsters as well as those stuck in the 1990s, the reissues will be released on CD and vinyl as well as digitally on June 2, with all tracks remastered by Page. Eventually, all nine of the band's studio albums will be reissued in the same style…….. - Never let it be said that northern Europe doesn't love the environment. An ugly haze of yellowish air pollution has hung over Paris for several days and cloaked the normally picturesque streets of Belgium has led transportation officials to extend a unique offer in the name of environmental protection. With a belt of smog stretching hundreds of miles, all the way from France's Atlantic coast to Belgium and well into Germany, public transit around Paris and in two other cities is being offered for free for the remainder of the weekend. Drivers in Belgium have been forced to slow down significantly on account of the smog and nearly all of France was under some sort of pollution alert Friday, with levels in the Parisian region surpassing some of those in the world's most notoriously polluted cities, including Beijing and Delhi. It was the worst air pollution France has seen since 2007, according to the European Environment Agency said. Other areas of France and Belgium's southern Wallonia area offered free transportation on Friday only, but if conditions don't improve, that offer could resurface. Smog levels are believed to be on the rise on account of France's current unusually high number of diesel vehicles, whose nitrogen oxide fumes mix with ammonia from springtime fertilizers and form particulate ammonium nitrate. Mix in pollutants from the burning of dead leaves and wood and the scene is ugly enough to prompt environmental groups to denounce the lack of government response to the mini-crisis as putting lives in danger. European Environment Agency air quality manager Valentin Foltescu noted that pollution can be an immediate health hazard, especially for those with respiratory or cardiac disorders. "Some people will, unfortunately, die," Foltescu said. "There is a high correlation of pollution of this kind and mortality.' As the smog lingered, speed limits were lowered in France and Belgium and electronic billboards in Paris dispensed advice and emergency information. Foltescu said if everyone follows the government's advice "you will see an instant difference." If not, he predicted that the smog would last as long as the region's unseasonably warm and sunny weather…….. - What it cold, slippery and goes boom when you strap dynamite to it? Trick question. Anything cold and slippery goes boom in such situations, but this week it was an ice dam on a creek in the small town of Onalaska, Wisc. As happens when a state is locked in below-zero temperatures from October through May (approximate), bodies of water of all shapes and sizes tend to freeze up. The water on Sand Lake Coulee Creek in the town of Onalaska could not hold off the cold any longer and its once-flowing waters eventually turned into a ginormous mass of ice. Town officials knew they needed to take action and do something about ice that was six feet deep at some points. When heavy machinery wouldn't clear up that ice block out of the way, it was clearly time for more….um…explosive measures. After what were undoubtedly intense discussions and plenty of wonderful brainstorming sessions, they settled on dynamite to blow up the ice. The blockage had to go because the ice dam was causing water to flow around a dike and get close to about a dozen homes. The town council went to the state legislature and the Department of Natural Resources to get all the proper permits they needed to blow the sh*t out of that ice. "That fractured the ice out and the explosions took what ice came out straight up in the air and came back down, there's no debris outside of the creek bed," town spokesman Rolly Bogert said. The explosion went as planned, crews dug out the channel after everything went boom and water was flowing smoothly (and coldly) by the next day…….. - In case there was any doubt that professional sports locker rooms remain among the many places in the world were ignorance and racial insensitivity still reside, this should resolve that wondering. The central character in this drama is New York Mets pitching coach Dan Warthen, who didn't exactly go on a slur-laced rant but did manage to prove that he's an old, out-of-touch guy who should probably join the rest of us in 2014. Warthen publicly apologized Wednesday night for having directed a slur once commonly used to denigrate people of Asian descent at Cutler. He reportedly approached the interpreter for right-hander Daisuke Matsuzaka to apologize for using a common racial slur for Asians during a previous conversation. Interpreter Jeff Cutler was speaking with a reporter who happened to be a Chinese American from San Francisco and in apologizing to Cutler, Warthen mentioned the slur again. The reporter was offended and Warthen found himself having to apologize all over again. Thankfully for him, Matsuzaka and Cutler are two forgiving guys and in addition to pitching well in his bid for the final spot in the Mets' rotation, the veteran Japanese pitcher is big enough to accept a mea culpa and move on. "Today I was just preparing for my game, so I just spoke to him about today's lineup and what was going on during the game," Matsuzaka said through his interpreter after holding the Washington Nationals to one run on three hits and striking out four in 3 2/3 innings. "... I think everyone makes mistakes, and Dan has already commented on it. I don't want to dig deeper into it or try to add to what it is." Cutler said he too has forgive Warthen and that team officials have addressed the issue as well. He added that it was not productive to speak about whether he was personally offended by Warthen's use of the slur, which shows the he too is smarter and less stuck in a bygone era than Warthen himself. Score one for lack of enlightenment…….

]]></text></news-item>