<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="0FC9-1061-2036-93BA"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Pakistan: Eight killed, 33 injured as bomber blow himself up near police APC</title><source>Right Vision News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[PESHAWAR, March 15 -- A suicide bomber on Friday here blasted himself
near a Armoured personnel carrier(APC) in Sirband bazaar in the outskirts of provincial capital, killing eight persons and wounding 33 others in the first deadly terrorist strike after the formation of new Govt committee to hold talks with Taliban.
SP Cantonment, Faisal Kamran told reporters the suicide bomber
tried to target police APC at Bhattal Thall locality in the limits of Sirband police station when it was passing through people crowded area and blasted himself up near it.
As result of huge explosion, eight people were killed and 33 others
injured. The wounded also include women, three policemen and children. The death toll may rise further as condition of several victims was stated to be critical in Lady Reading Hospital.
The police, rescue 1122 and local residents rushed to the spot and
shifted the injured to Lady Reading Hospital's Accident and Emergency Department.
The condition of several victims is stated to be critical. Emergency has
been enforced in Lady Reading Hospital and doctors, paramedics on leave were called in for duty. No group have claimed responsibility of the deadly terrorist attack. Several vehicles were damaged in the bombing.
Police & law enforcement agencies' personnel rushed to the bombing
site following the attack and cordoned-off the area and launched search operation. Bomb Disposal Squad has also been summoned to the site of explosion.
The injured identified are policeman Akram Khan son of Mehtab Gul
resident of Charsadda, Muhammad Sharif son of Bahadar resident of Bara Khyber Agency, Najeen Khan son of Payam Noor resident of Sarbanad Peshawar, Gulshana son of Khan Wazir resident of Jalozai IDP camp Nowshera, Hasan Baz son of Ahmed Jan resident of Sarband Peshawar, Salam son wife of Tariq resident of Jalozai IDP camp Nowshera, Tahira wife of Abid resident of Molazao Peshawar, Fauzai wife of Maqballay Khan resident of Bara Khyber Agency, Javed Khan son of Bangash resident of Bara Khyber Agency, Din Muhammad son of Ali Khel resident of Bara, policeman Zahir Shah son of Syed Rahimshah, policeman Gul Wali son of Sabz Ali, Samiullah son of Muslim Shah, Naseerullah son of Abdul Razak resident of Sarband Peshawar, Kamran son of Zaiyarat Gul resident of Sarband Peshawar, Gul Ghamir son of Akbardin resident of Bara Khyber Agency, Nasrullah Khan son of Abdur Rada resident of Sarband and Roquia.
The LRH Spokesman said four dead bodies were brought to the Lady Reading
hospital and their identity could not be immediately ascertained.
He said emergency has been enforced in Lady Reading Hospital and
patients were referred to different wards. The Spokesman urged people to avoid rush in Emergency and others wards so that doctors and para medical staff provided treatment to victims without any hurdles and problems.
Meanwhile, the Khyber Pakhtunkhwa Governor Engineer Shaukatullah
strongly condemned the suicide attack on a Police Security Vehicle at Batta Tal market of Sarband area, situated in surrounding of Peshawar.
Expressing his deep sympathies with members of bereaved families the
governor has said that the elements involved in the heinous act of terrorism will no more remain at large and will be brought to court of law. He has also prayed for the eternal peace of the departed souls and courage to the bereaved families to bear the irreparable loss with patience.
He has also wished early recovery of the injured. The Governor has also
appreciated the Police Jawans for fulfilling their duties with courage
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Right Vision News. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>