<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1029-90DE-0951-23E0"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>3 charged in Texas co-op credit card abuse</title><source>Associated Press State &amp; Local</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[JOHNSON CITY, Texas (AP) - A theft investigation involving more than $50,000 in unauthorized purchases on credit cards of Pedernales Electric Cooperative led to the arrest of two fired employees and the ex-police officer husband of one of the former workers.
A Blanco County grand jury this month indicted Bryan Geeslin, Jeanny Geeslin and Zelenny Martinez on charges of organized criminal activity, the Austin American-Statesman (http://bit.ly/1fzhbN2 ) reported Friday.
Martinez, 44, is a former information technology manager at PEC. Jeanny Geeslin, 32, was her assistant. The women are accused of making the unauthorized transactions, which included purchases of electronic equipment. Bryan Geeslin, 36, formerly a captain with the Johnson City Police Department, was also named in the indictment.
Police say the investigation is ongoing and offered no details about what else was purchased on the credit cards or what happened to those items.
Martinez was arrested Tuesday by Castle Hills police and booked into the Bexar County Jail on $75,000 bond. The Geeslins were arrested in Lamar County the same day. Jeanny Geeslin was booked on $75,000 bond. Bryan Geeslin's bond was set at $55,000.
Jail records for both counties showed the defendants were no longer in custody Saturday and did not include attorney information for them. No publicly listed phone numbers could immediately be located for the Geeslins or Martinez.
The investigation into the credit card charges on cards of Johnson City-based PEC began in mid-2012. Jeanny Geeslin and Martinez were fired days later.
"Pedernales Electric is aware that two former employees have been indicted by a grand jury on charges related to theft of Cooperative property," company officials said in a statement. "When PEC learned of a potential issue through its whistleblower program, the co-op took immediate action, contacting local authorities and working closely with those authorities during the initial investigation of the issue. The case is now a matter for law enforcement officials and the courts."
A former Pedernales Electric Cooperative manager, Bennie Fuelberg, was convicted of theft, money laundering and misappropriation of fiduciary property. Fuelberg in February 2011 was sentenced to 300 days in jail and ordered to repay $126,000 for stealing co-op funds.
Former co-op attorney Walter Demond, later in 2011, was sentenced to 100 days in jail annually for five years after a jury found him guilty of felony theft from the company. Demond was also ordered to repay $212,000.
Both men are appealing.
___
Information from: Austin American-Statesman, http://www.statesman.com
]]></text></news-item>