<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="108F-01B5-7FCD-B9FF"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>CRS AWARDS PRESENTED TO TWO NEW JERSEY COMMUNITIES</title><source>States News Service</source><author>States News Service</author><text><![CDATA[The following information was released by FEMA:
Two New Jersey municipalities were recognized for reducing their flood hazard risk through the FEMA Community Rating System in awards ceremonies on March 10, 2014.
The ceremony honoring Pompton Lakes was held at 25 Lenox Avenue, the town's municipal building. Fairfield Township was honored in a separate ceremony at 230 Fairfield Avenue.
The Community Rating System (CRS) is a program administered by FEMA that provides lowerFEMA Natural Hazards Program Specialist Crystal Tramunti and Mitigation Branch Director William McDonnell present Mayor James Gasparini and Administrator Joseph Catenaro with a plaque recognizing Fairfield. insurance premiums under the National Flood Insurance Program. Communities can apply to participate in the CRS, and residents of participating communities pay lower premium reduction rates based on the implementation of floodplain management policies.
Communities earn points toward their rating based on 18 creditable activities in four categories: Public Information, Mapping and Regulations, Flood Damage Reduction and Flood Preparedness. For towns participating in the CRS, flood insurance premium rates are discounted in 5 percent increments. Premium reductions are in the form of CRS Classes, similar to the classifications used for fire insurance.
Councilman Michael Simone and CRS Co-Coordinators Elizabeth Brandsness and Barbara Padula are honored with a plaque recognizing the town of Pompton Lakes. Pompton Lakes is one of 10 New Jersey municipalities (Sea Isle City, Avalon, Beach Haven, Bedminster, Brigantine, Long Beach Township, Longport, Mantoloking, Pompton Lakes and Stafford Township) to achieve Class 5, the highest level of compliance currently achieved in the state. The borough's participation in CRS has saved residents $308,395 on their insurance premiums. Fairfield Township, in Essex County, is in Class 6. Township residents have saved $499,201.
The highest level of compliance possible in the program is Class 1. The 61 communities participating in the program have saved more than $17 million.
Participating communities have better organized and more formal local flood programs, which can be evaluated against a nationally recognized benchmark. The discounted premiums give communities incentive to maintain its programs. The program also helps to remind residents that their towns are working to protect them from flooding and that their town is becoming more knowledgeable and successful in supporting and improving flood protection measures.
Learn more about the NFIP's CRS program at http://www.fema.gov/business/nfip/crs.shtm.
Photographs are located at http://www.fema.gov/media-library/assets/images/92323 and http://www.fema.gov/media-library/assets/images/92322
For more information on New Jersey's disaster recovery, visit fema.gov/SandyNJ, twitter.com/FEMASandy, facebook.com/FEMASandy and fema.gov/blog.
FEMA's mission is to support our citizens and first responders to ensure that as a nation we work together to build, sustain, and improve our capability to prepare for, protect against, respond to, recover from, and mitigate all hazards.
Follow FEMA online at www.fema.gov/blog, www.twitter.com/fema, www.facebook.com/fema, and www.youtube.com/fema. Also, follow Administrator Craig Fugate's activities at www.twitter.com/craigatfema.
The social media links provided are for reference only. FEMA does not endorse any non-government websites, companies or applications.
]]></text></news-item>