<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="119E-13A6-A1DF-FB9F"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Diocese urges health sign-ups</title><source>Orange County Register (California)</source><author>BY DAVID OLSON, STAFF WRITER</author><text><![CDATA[Despite impending battles over hot-button issues, the Roman Catholic Diocese of San Bernardino is urging parishioners without health insurance to sign up for coverage under the Affordable Care Act.
Bishop Gerald Barnes' letter, coaxing his flock to obey the law of the land, will be read during all Masses this weekend at the 91 parishes in San Bernardino and Riverside counties. The bishop's message comes days after Catholic organizations filed a lawsuit challenging the Affordable Care Act's requirement that insurance policies require birth-control coverage.
Dozens of businesses and other religious groups have filed similar suits alleging that money paid for health care will then be used by the federal government to subsidize contraceptives and abortion, which are morally unacceptable to the Catholic church.
Barnes is worried that the Catholic Church's vocal opposition to the parts of the law that deal with coverage of contraception and abortion services led some Catholics to believe the church opposes the entire Affordable Care Act, said John Andrews, a spokesman for the diocese, which covers Riverside and San Bernardino counties and 1.6 million Catholics.
"These factors do not mean that we, as Catholics, should disobey the new health care law," Barnes said in the letter. "If we happen to have an insurance plan that includes services that are objectionable to our faith, which most plans in California do, our response is to not utilize these services. We do this through an informed conscience and reflection on the teachings of our Church about the value and dignity of every human life and God's plan for creation."
The Diocese of San Bernardino appears to be the only one in Southern California to make such a move. The Diocese of Orange or Bishop Kevin Vann do not plan on making a similar announcement, said spokesman Ryan Lilyengren.
"Any outreach in Orange County in connection with health care is being done by Catholic Charities of Orange County," he said.
Barnes is concerned that many without health insurance - especially Latinos - are not signing up for the Affordable Care Act, also known as Obamacare, Andrews said.
"This is an opportunity for a lot of families who haven't had health insurance before to get it, and the church is all for that," he said.
The deadline to sign up for coverage for this year is March 31.
Under the health care law, most health insurance plans have to cover all Food and Drug Administration-approved contraceptives as preventive care for women, free of cost to the patient.
Churches and other houses of worship are exempt from the birth control requirement, but affiliated institutions such as nonprofits, universities and hospitals are not. Church-related entities can, however, choose to sign a form registering their objection and receive the exemption.
The government has argued that these entities have to do very little to be "exempted," but Catholic groups say signing that form makes them complicit in providing contraceptive coverage, and therefore violates their religious beliefs.
At least one other Catholic diocese in California, Fresno, has sent parishes materials on Obamacare enrollment and clarifications of the church's position on health care coverage, said Steve Pehanich, director of advocacy for the California Catholic Conference, which represents the state's 12 dioceses. Pehanich said he's not aware of another California bishop who has had the message delivered during Mass.
Catholic leaders have conflicting views about the Affordable Care Act, which aims to provide health care coverage - much of it government-subsidized - to millions of uninsured Americans. The church has long supported access to medical care as a human right and a matter of basic dignity. But the church also teaches that contraception and abortion are sins.
The Affordable Care Act mandates that insurance policies cover contraception, including intrauterine devices and the "morning-after pill," which some people view as akin to abortion because it can prevent a fertilized egg from implanting in the uterus.
There are some accommodations and exemptions for religious organizations, but the church contends they aren't broad enough.
The U.S. Supreme Court is scheduled March 25 to hear two lawsuits challenging the birth-control coverage mandate. Both were filed by businesses whose owners - evangelical Christians in one case, Mennonites in another - have religious objections.
The Affordable Care Act does not mandate coverage of abortion. But in about half the states, women can pay out of their own pockets for abortion coverage under insurance plans they buy on government insurance marketplaces.
Barnes notes in his letter that the law requires people who are legal U.S. residents or citizens to carry health insurance and that "as faithful citizens we are obligated to follow it."
The bishop's letter is the latest step Inland Catholic institutions have taken to inform people about health care reform. In January, the diocese distributed a question-and-answer brochure on the Affordable Care Act to parishes.
Catholic Charities and Dignity Health/St. Bernardine Medical Center in San Bernardino have been informing clients and patients about the law and connecting people with enrollment counselors with Covered California, the state's insurance exchange. Staff members at St. Joseph Health/St. Mary Medical Center in Apple Valley were certified by Covered California to directly sign up people for the program.
On Wednesday, the Spanish-language Catholic radio station KHPY 1670AM, known as El Sembrador, taped an interview in which Barnes talked about the law at length with Petra Alexander, director of the diocese's Office of Hispanic Affairs.
Staff writer Deepa Bharath and The Associated Press contributed to this report.
]]></text></news-item>