<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="11DF-1E60-3A60-2492"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Srikant Jena lobs mining scam ball at CBI</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Rajaram Satapathy</author><text><![CDATA[BHUBANESWAR: Union minister Srikant Jena on Friday asked CBI to initiate suo moto inquiry into the mega mining scam in Odisha, which has been corroborated by the M B Shah Commission constituted by the Centre.
Coinciding with the election season, Jena in a letter to the CBI director said there had been an 'increasing presence of mafia in mining sector of Odisha under the state's patronage for more than 10 years'.
He quoted Shah commission report as saying: "There is enormous and large-scale multi-state illegal mining of iron ore and manganese ore running into thousands of crores every year, having several pernicious evil effects on the national economy, good governance, public functionaries, bureaucracy, public order, law and order. It has encouraged huge corruption at all different levels in public life, mafia in society and money power. It is not only national loot, but also has deleterious effects on the national economy and society. This has to be stopped immediately and effectively."
He said the commission has estimated that ore worth more than Rs 59,000 crore was looted. "The commission findings has clearly pointed out that the mineral wealth of the state has been illegally plundered by the mining mafia right under the watchful eyes of the state government to enrichment of a few and impoverishment of millions," the minister's letter to the CBI director Ranjit Sinha said.
The mining scam during the Naveen Patnaik regime is considered the worst corruption to have ever happened in Odisha.
Public expectation of law catching the culprits reached its peak when the Shah Commission visited mines in Keonjhar and other areas. But excepting the commission report no tangible progress has yet been made for punishing those responsible for the large-scale looting of precious ores.
Even the opposition Congress and BJP barring making occasional whimpers have not done anything worth the name to take the scam to its logical conclusion. Demand for CBI inquiry was also made to Congress vice-president Rahul Gandhi during his recent visit here. The silence of political parties has all but stoked the public suspicion of people across parties being involved in the scam. CBI director Sinha too invited criticism when he met chief minister Naveen Patnaik here earlier this month. Jena's letter in this backdrop is seen as an attempt to make mining scam a major election plank in the coming days.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>