<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1205-DA57-FA16-B2E8"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Storm Over Kejriwal's Latest 'Will Jail Journalists' Remark</title><source>Economic Times (E-Paper Edition)</source><author>OUR POLITICAL BUREAU NEW DELHI</author><text><![CDATA[AAP convenor Arvind Kejriwal's latest diatribe against the media landed him in a fresh controversy on Friday as he accused the fraternity of selling out to the BJP and allegedly threatened to throw those found guilty of indulging in such practice in jail if and when his party comes to power.Although Kejriwal,who said this at a fund raising dinner in Nagpur the night before,tried to backtrack from his remarks on Friday,AAP came out all guns blazing in support of what its leader said.Speaking at a press conference,which witnessed a hostile exchange of charges between AAP leaders and journalists,the party named four channels,accusing them of running motivated stories and said that it would soon lodge a complaint with the EC "with proof".Defending the former chief minister of Delhi,AAP leader Ashutosh,who was constantly heckled by journalists at the press conference,insisted that Kejriwal's accusation was directed at a "section of media" and that there is nothing wrong in questioning journalists and editors if they are suspected of paid news.This is not the first time that either Kejriwal or his colleagues have gone hammer and tongs after the media.The party has been escalating its attack against newschannels in tandem with its criticism of BJP's prime ministerial candidate Narendra Modi.On Friday,the fresh round of controversy was triggered by alleged threat to jail journalists.Kejriwal,who was addressing over 100 businessmen and party sympathizers on Thursday night,insinuated that media was guilty of promoting Modi as it's more interested in debating his security cover and not the 800 farmer suicides that have happened in Gujarat over the last decade."If our government comes to power then we will set an inquiry into this.And along with media people,all will be sent to jail," he added.Slamming him for these comments,the Broadcast Editors' Association said such "vague and sweeping" allegations were aimed at diluting the credibility of media which is discharging its responsibility in a fair and objective manner.The political class was also unsparing in its criticism.J& K CM Omar Abdullah tweeted,"I really don't get AAP & (sic) Kejriwal's criticism of the media.But for blanket coverage,AAP wouldn't exist today." "Media has essential place in our democracy.Saying you will jail media is condemnable.One should be able to handle criticism," said Union Minister and Congress leader Manish Terwai.Sushil Kumar Shinde had last threatened to "crush" what he called "elements in the electronic media spreading false propaganda." According to sociologists Shiv Vishwanathan,the activist turned politician has probably taken it too far this time."It's true that a section of media is soft on Modi and more aggressive towards Kejriwal as it's evident from editorials and news programmes.It's also true that certain business houses close to Modi are trying to influence the media and the journalist fraternity should not be upset if someone calls for a fair inquiry into this.But to threaten to jail journalists is not right."

]]></text></news-item>