<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="12A4-9089-B3FF-5255"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Premier vows to fight pollution</title><source>Shenzhen Daily</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[CHINA needs tough measures and tough regulations to fight pollution, Premier Li Keqiang said at a press conference following the conclusion of the annual legislative session in Beijing on Thursday. Polluters, which harm both nature and human health, will be severely punished, said Li, when responding to a question about smog that has frequently blanketed Beijing and other major cities since winter.
Watchdog entities that turn a blind eye to polluting activities and fail to perform their duties will be held accountable, Li added. “To declare a war on smog doesn’t mean we are declaring a war on nature. Rather, we are going to declare a war on our own inefficient and unsustainable model of growth and way of life,” he said. Li admitted that persistent smog in many cities had taken a toll on people’s welfare. “The first thing many people do in the morning is check the readings for PM2.5 pollution,” Li said. He added that levels of PM 2.5 pollutants — tiny particles smaller than 2.5 microns wide that are regarded as most dangerous to human health — were monitored in 161 of the country’s 660 cities, the most extensive scale of monitoring in any developing country. “[The readings] remind the public to take necessary protective measures against pollution,” Li said. “(They) also put pressure on governments.” Li said the country aimed to cut coal use by 22 million tons this year to cut energy intensity — a measure of the economy’s energy efficiency — by 3.9 percent. He also promised that “grave penalties” awaited polluters including coal-fired power plants, heavy industries and high-emission vehicles, as well as officials who ignored violations, but Li did not specify sanctions. Li acknowledged that the government needs to find a fine balance between maintaining growth, creating jobs and protecting the environment. Missing flight Li vowed Thursday that his country will not give up its efforts in searching for missing Malaysia Airlines Flight MH370. As the multinational hunt entered day six for the Boeing 777 aircraft, no solid leads about its whereabouts had been found so far. “We will not give up (on) any suspected clue,” Li said. “We are also looking very closely at all possible clues (from) satellite images.” Social fairness Li said the Central Government will prioritize the promotion of social fairness and the improvement of people’s livelihood. “We need to meet people’s basic living needs, to provide the last resort for people to fall back on in case of special difficulty, and to promote social fairness,” Li said, calling them three major tasks for the government this year. “Those topics related to people’s livelihood present priorities for the government’s work agenda,” he said. Li said the government will endeavor to make China’s medical insurance and basic pension programs “truly portable and transferable” to further expand their coverage in urban and rural areas. The premier urged all government employees to put the special needs of the people, such as those who run into special difficulty because of serious illnesses or sudden disasters, on the top of their mind. Sino-U.S. relations China and the United States should expand common interests while respecting each other’s core interests and major concerns and properly managing differences to raise the level of their bilateral relationship, Li said. The Sino-U.S. relationship is, in essence, the one between the largest developing country and the largest developed country in the world, Li said. Due to different historical and cultural backgrounds and development stages, it is natural for the two countries to have some differences on certain matters and friction in cooperation, but these are just “pains” amid growing cooperation, Li said. “As long as the two sides respect each other’s core interests and major concerns, properly manage their differences and engage in equal consultations, and in particular, continue to expand their common interests, the two countries will be able to further raise the level of their relationship,” Li said. Trade disputes China and the European Union (EU) can work out solutions to trade disputes through mutual respect and proper consultations, the premier said. As each other’s biggest trading partners, it’s natural for China and the EU to experience trade frictions, Li said. “As long as the two sides respect each other and engage in proper consultations, problems can be solved,” Li said, citing last year’s trade dispute case involving photovoltaic products as a successful example. Trade disputes are individual cases and account for a small percentage of the two-way trade, he added. Both China and the EU are strong advocates of greater investment facilitation, so companies from the two sides entering each other’s markets and investing mutually is an irresistible trend, he said. Li expected that China and EU would conduct negotiations for an investment treaty in a fair, reciprocal and facilitating way, so there will be greater mutual investment and deeper economic integration between the two sides. Financial reforms The premier said fiscal, tax and financial reforms are priorities on the country’s overall reform agenda in 2014. “In the course of comprehensively deepening reform, we certainly need to be focused on key reforms and initiatives and we need to see breakthroughs in key areas,” Li said. “We will press ahead with fiscal, tax and financial reforms as our priorities this year.” Authorities will continue to streamline administration and delegate power to ensure that the market plays its role fully and effectively, he said. The premier also listed reforms in other areas, including taking new steps to ease the tax burdens on micro- and small businesses, deepening reforms of State-owned enterprises, and vigorously developing a mixed-ownership economy. Market access would also be eased, especially in service sectors such as health care, support for the elderly and financial services, to bring greater competition in the market, he said. “The ultimate goal of all the reforms is to fully energize the market and the creativity of society,” said the premier. “In the course of reforms, vested interests will be shaken.” Taiwan ties Li called for new progress in relations between the mainland and Taiwan. He said people-to-people exchanges and business cooperation are important components of ties across the Taiwan Strait. “I hope to see even greater, new progress in cross-Strait ties this year,” Li said. Li said a record 8 million visits were recorded between the mainland and Taiwan last year, adding that he hoped the good momentum would continue in the future. HK prosperity Li expressed confidence Thursday in Hong Kong’s competitive edge and ability to maintain prosperity. The Central Government’s policy toward Hong Kong and Macao is consistent and clear-cut, the premier said. “We will continue to support Hong Kong in maintaining and elevating its status as an international financial, trading and shipping center,” he said. The mainland’s reform and economic upgrading will open tremendous opportunities for Hong Kong, Li said. Debt risks China has placed strong attention on government debt and related risks are generally within control, the premier said. Citing an official audit of government debts last year, Li said the country’s debt-to-GDP ratio is still below the internationally recognized warning line. China’s mounting government debt is considered a latent danger to financial stability, and the country has started to take steps to address the issue. After two months of nationwide audits, the National Audit Office disclosed that governments at various levels were liable for total direct debt of 20.7 trillion yuan (US$3.4 trillion) at the end of June, up 8.6 percent, or 1.63 trillion yuan, since the end of 2012. While the level is within control, Li cautioned that the problem should not be overlooked and promised to take further regulatory steps, including putting the debt under budgetary management, to strengthen oversight. Common interests China will enhance common interests and narrow differences with neighboring countries for the sake of peace and stability, Li said. China has an unwavering commitment to pursuing peaceful development and an unshakable will in safeguarding its sovereignty and territorial integrity, both for the sake of upholding stability and creating a favorable environment for its development, the premier said. As a developing country, China needs a favorable neighboring and international environment for its modernization drive, he said. “When neighbors interact with each other, it is only natural that sometimes they will run into problems of some kind or another,” Li said. “As long as they respect each other, properly manage differences and pursue mutual benefits, there will be harmonious sound instead of jarring noises.” (Xinhua)
]]></text></news-item>