<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="12BD-A9DA-F19D-9C80"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>A month out of office, Kejriwal stays in news</title><source>Hindustan Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[New Delhi, March 16 -- It has been over a month since Arvind Kejriwal stepped down as the chief minister of Delhi. Kejriwal and his Aam Aadmi Party (AAP) let go of power on February 14 after failing to table their brand of anti-corruption legislation, the janlokpal bill, in the assembly.
Detractors said quitting power was a part of the AAP game plan all along, especially with the Lok Sabha polls up ahead.
Kejriwal and his party have a robust presence in the media, but they hit the headlines on Friday by accusing the media of having "sold out".
A look at the 10 big moments in Kejriwal and his party's journey between Valentine's Day and now.
1. Taking on Modi on his turf Kejriwal headed to Gujarat on a "fact-finding" mission to check on chief minister and Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) prime ministerial candidate Narendra Modi's claims of development in the state.
2. Itching for a fight against Modi from Varanasi The BJP is coy about Modi's candidature, even as the buzz around Varanasi grows. The AAP, however, smartly let it be known on March 2 that Kejriwal will take on Modi from Varanasi.
3. Attacking the media, seen to be manipulating them too Kejriwal and the AAP have been swift and smart in using the media, but the ties are souring fast. He is accusing the media of having sold out, and then going
on the defensive.
4. Local train, auto travel triggers chaos in Mumbai
Kejriwal's visit to Maharashtra, marked by his chaotic local train and autorickshaw travel in Mumbai, reportedly tested the nerves of some locals. He blamed the media for the 'tamasha' (drama).
5. Staying in official house even after quitting as CM Kejriwal has not vacated his official flat in Tilak Lane despite resigning as CM. He has offered a reason that many would be willing to buy. He wants to stay put in the house for a few months because of his daughter's Class 12 examinations.
6. Violence outside BJP office Kejriwal had to apologise after his party's supporters sent on the rampage outside the BJP headquarters in Delhi. The violence broke out after Gujarat Police stopped Kejriwal from going to meet Modi.
7. Rinfra's Rs. 100-cr defamation suit against AAP On March 4, Anil Ambaniled Reliance Infrastructure (RInfra) filed a Rs 100-crore defamation suit in Bombay high court against the AAP, which alleged the power company had overcharged consumers in collusion with Maharashtra Electricity Re gulatory Commission.
8. AAP founder member Ashok Agarwal quits Prominent AAP member Ashok Agarwal ter med the party "a private limited company" before quitting its top decisionmaking unit, the national executive.
9. Donations rise as attacks mount The AAP's coffers swelled every time there was a controversy. The party saw a 260% jump in donations the day news of Kejriwal being "detained" in Gujarat hit the headlines.
10. Chartered flight and swanky car ride Kejriwal's common man credentials came under fire after he was driven in a swanky car and flown in a chartered plane to Delhi to attend a private media event.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Hindustan Times. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>