<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="12ED-C9E2-1B13-2987"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>The meteoric rise of Qatar's 'first lady'</title><source>The Toronto Star</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The bar for expectations is set fairly low in the first ladies club. Smile, stand behind your husband and nod encouragingly as he speaks. Perhaps participate in a safe, worthy cause such as obesity (Michelle Obama) or literacy (Laura Bush).
Smile some more.
Occasionally there is an undignified love triangle involving French actresses and getting dumped by the president (Valerie Trierweiler). That is the sorry state in the emancipated West, where highly accomplished women often play second fiddle to their husbands.
It is worse in the Middle East, where leaders' wives rarely appear in public; in the even more conservative Gulf Arab states, women tend to remain shrouded in black, totally unknown.
In that context, Sheikha Mozah of Qatar is remarkable.
The wife of the former emir and mother of the current one - who rules the tiny kingdom with near absolute authority - has had a meteoric rise on the international scene in parallel with Qatar's profile and power.
She is a brand ambassador for a country that many cannot place on a map but identify as a byword for superlative wealth - Qataris are the richest citizens on the planet; GDP per capita is $108,000, twice as much as Canada.
Sheikha Mozah, 54, works hard to improve education, literacy and health, but she also takes on tougher assignments, such as free speech and domestic violence, using her husband's fabulous riches to further her causes. Her statuesque good looks and old-fashioned, retro glamour certainly help her PR, too.
The royal represents top-down reform, undemocratic and authoritarian, and she derives that power from her husband and now son's position, which may not sit well with enlightened notions of feminism.
But it is change, says an Iranian women's rights activist who did not want to be identified because of security concerns.
"I met Sheikha Mozah and she is impressive," the activist says in an interview from London. "It is good to have pressure from below, but you need to bargain with authority - her husband in this case - when it comes to the change of law. In that sense she is a very enabling figure and plays an important role."
Sheikha Mozah is a popular figure in the Middle East, which sits oddly with Qatar's more controversial reputation.
The Qataris are believed to be sending weapons and cash to rebels, including jihadists, all over the Middle East, Syria in particular, in an attempt to control the outcome of the Arab uprisings.
On March 5, Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates and Bahrain withdrew their ambassadors from Qatar to protest Qatar's meddling in regional affairs and support for the Muslim Brotherhood.
Last month, Qatar set up a workers' right charter after criticism from groups, including Human Rights Watch and Amnesty International, over the deaths of South Asian labourers who were building football stadiums for the 2022 football World Cup.
For the 275,000 indigenous Qataris, it is a different world. The fund set up to manage and invest the oil and gas riches is worth $115 billion (U.S.), according to the Sovereign Wealth Fund Institute.
It wasn't always that way.
Sheikha Mozah's father was a dissident jailed in the 1970s for demanding that the natural resources be more fairly distributed among Qataris.
Mozah bint Nasser al Missned was born in Doha and, as a pretty 18-year-old sociology student, caught the eye of the future emir, Sheikh Hamad bin Khalifa al Thani. She became the second of his three wives - the others have never been photographed in public - and they had seven children.
Her husband ruled Qatar for 18 years. In 1995, Sheikh Hamad rang his father, who was on holiday at a luxury hotel in Switzerland, to inform him he had taken the crown for himself, according to the book Current Leaders of Nations. One of the couple's sons, British-educated Tamim, 33, was named emir last year when Sheikh Hamad abdicated peacefully.
The sheikha remained out of public sight until 2003 when she suddenly appeared next to her husband in an interview with the American network CBS. It was a careful decision on the part of the Qatari leadership on the eve of the Iraq invasion to show the West a progressive view of the country, says a source in Doha.
"It was a stroke of genius having Sheikha Mozah because it has helped bring investment from foreign countries," he says.
The vehicle for her reforms is the Qatar Foundation for Education, Science and Community Development, a private, non-profit organization of which she is chairman. Its stated aim is to develop Qatar into a modern, knowledge-based society.
It finances the Doha Debates, a highly popular series filmed in the Qatari capital and launched in 2004, which debates motions such as "this house believes the Egyptian military is not interested in genuine reform."
For the Middle East it is radical stuff, says Isobel Coleman, director of the women and foreign policy program at the Council on Foreign Relations in New York.
"You had citizens of the Gulf get comfortable with the idea of discussing issues and debates on issues that had never been publicly aired before," she says.
Reform abroad is one thing, reform at home is another. Last year, the Qatari poet Mohammed al-Ajami was jailed 15 years for criticizing the Gulf Arab states in a poem, yet the sheikha backed the creation of the Doha Centre for Media Freedom, which promotes free expression.
Through the foundation she also launched in 2003 the ambitious Education City, a campus for prominent universities, including Georgetown and Cornell, which set up branches that are educating a younger generation of Qataris. Women make up 70 per cent of the student body.
"She has taken on issues that are among the most important in the region. It is about education and youth unemployment, and she is not just about window-dressing," Coleman says.
Forbes magazine lists her as one of the 100 most influential women in the world.
The royal is UNESCO's special envoy for basic and higher education.
But Sheikha Mozah really became something of an international celebrity when she landed on Vanity Fair magazine's annual best-dressed list in 2009.
Vanity Fair describes her style as "royal opulence meets Hitchcock heroine." A Tumblr account is dedicated to her signature look: elegant turbans and oversized sunglasses framing pale, chiseled features.
She travels alongside her husband on state visits and walks next to him dressed in head-to-toe couture gowns, furs, diamonds, cinched Hermès belts, the lot.
The sheikha requests her favourite designers, Chanel or Valentino, to modify outfits to be less revealing on the décolletage or sleeves, says Gemma Champ, a London-based style journalist and former fashion editor in Abu Dhabi.
"She brings together a sense of international glamour - a little Elizabeth Taylor-esque with her turbans - and the sort of modesty that's essential in her role," she says.
She is certainly under no pressure to appear in low-cost outfits, like the Duchess of Cambridge, to reflect economic austerity.
Qatar's drowning in cash and unafraid of appearing flamboyant in its spending.
Most of it is directed toward Europe. The Qatari royal family bought luxury Italian fashion house Valentino in 2012 for $850 million, according to the Wall Street Journal, and a chain of five-star hotels in Paris and Nice. The state bought about 20 per cent of the London Stock Exchange, financed the famous Shard skyscraper and owns Harrods, the London department store, where Qatari royals sometimes illegally park their baby blue Lamborghinis. They are probably unconcerned with the $203 parking fine.
In Canada, bilateral trade with Qatar is worth $559 million a year, the vast majority of which is imports of liquefied natural gas, according to the Canadian Trade Commissioner Service.
Sheikha Mozah doesn't seem to simply be playing the role of a progressive wife to win over a western audience. When dignitaries arrive in Doha she is photographed greeting them at the airport - albeit in a black, silk abaya, the traditional covering for Gulf women.
Focusing on her sartorial choices isn't a sexist double standard; she uses fashion to send messages about herself as a modest Muslim woman in a public, if unelected, role.
"She is no mere consort," says Champ. "She's saying that Qatar is a progressive country with a tradition, culture and religion, sure, but not a medieval mindset."
]]></text></news-item>