<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="130C-3874-4CA7-0992"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>600 children caught in conflicts died in Turkey</title><source>Cihan News Agency (CNA)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ISTANBUL (CIHAN)- Berkin Elvan was 14 years old when he was struck in the head by a police tear gas canister while on his way to buy bread for his family during the Gezi Park protests in June of last year that turned into months-long anti-government demonstrations.
Elvan had been in a coma for 269 days when he died at the age of 15 on March 12. That sparked nationwide protests in Turkey. He is the eighth person to have died as a result of the Gezi protests, including a policeman. Yet based on earlier experiences, it is not expected that a thorough investigation will be carried out to punish those responsible for Berkin's death. On March 12, in a press release the Turkey branch of Amnesty International (AI) noted, "In the nine months that have passed [since Berkin was first injured], the police officers responsible for firing the tear gas canister have not been identified." "The protracted and ineffective investigation into his case is typical of those opened following allegations of police abuses during the weeks of Gezi Park protests. In response to the thousands of complaints only two criminal prosecutions have been opened against police officers. Unfortunately, there is very little evidence that Turkish officials are getting the message. Investigations are not being carried out with any urgency and, with Turkey's culture of impunity intact, the police are free to continue abuses," it said. Elvan's death triggered the largest street demonstrations since the Gezi Park protests, illustrating the deepening unease over the Turkish government's growing authoritarianism and suppressing all opposition. That authoritarianism has created a mood of fear that is now felt in every segment of society since the government increased pressure on the opposition by subjecting those urging for a transparent investigation of a corruption and bribery scandal disclosed on Dec. 17 of last year that is allegedly directly linked to Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan and his family to a smear campaign coupled with threats that they will face criminal charges. It is common knowledge to everyone in Turkey that if Erdogan's party emerges as the winner of the March 30 local elections -- even if it's vote percentage, as is speculated, goes below 40 percent, a psychological threshold for the ruling Justice and Development Party (AK Party) -- serious legal procedures against those opposition groups are anticipated, as Erdogan has vowed. One can imagine how these legal procedures will be misconducted, since the government has brought the judiciary under its full control with a recent change made in the related laws.
Prime Minister Erdogan stubbornly persists in saying that the demonstrations that have been taking place following Berkin's death are part of attempts to sabotage his government, insisting on not reading the tension in the streets correctly. People are going to the streets to express their aspirations for democracy and in reaction to his growing authoritarianism. An opposition party leader's reminder of an event that occurred in Egypt but is linked to Erdogan stands as important evidence that Erdogan, once Turkey's reformist leader, has already distanced himself from being sensitive to Turks' grievances, resulting in serious setbacks in democratic standards. Kemal Kiliçdaroglu, leader of the main opposition Republican People's Party (CHP), recalled during his election rally on Wednesday that Erdogan publicly wept over 17-year-old Asma el-Beltagi, daughter of Mohammed el-Beltagi, the secretary-general of Egypt's ousted Muslim Brotherhood party, who was killed during a police raid on the party protest camps in August of last year, but has not cried for Berkin Elvan. He then questioned the sincerity of Erdogan's tears for Asma when he has none for Berkin. In the meantime, though the Turkish people are in the streets to mourn Berkin's death as a result of state violence, neither Turkish intellectuals nor the political parties are sensitive enough to display reactions to, for instance, the deaths of nearly 600 children in Turkey, mostly Turkish Kurds, caught in other conflicts, i.e., the almost three-decade-long fight against terrorism. Berkin is not the first child to die as a result of violence instigated by state security officials, the independent media platform Bianet noted on its website on March 12. Bianet quotes a report on the violations of children's rights in east and southeast Turkey, where the fight against terrorism has been felt the most, that was released recently by Turkey's Human Rights Association (IHD), which says that 569 children died between 1988 and 2013 due to conflict in the region. In 2012 alone, seven children died when they stepped on mines and bombs placed by the state, two children died when they were subjected to violence by security officials and five more died due to the negligence of security officials during the fight against terrorism, said the report. The United Nations Fund for Children (UNICEF) Turkey office also released a statement on March 12 offering its deepest condolences to the family and friends of Berkin Elvan and urging the Turkish government to take the necessary measures to protect children.
"It is with immense sadness that UNICEF observes preventable child deaths in Turkey. It is the State's responsibility to protect and promote every child's inherent right to life, by intervening against all forms of violence against children, holding perpetrators of such violence accountable and exercising due diligence whenever children are threatened or at risk," the UNICEF statement read. In the final analysis, the government is turning a blind eye to the messages coming from the Turkish streets, further jeopardizing, among other things, the already fragile state of the Turkish economy. Yet about 70 percent of the voters asked in a recent poll said that while they believed that the government was involved in the graft scandal, they would still vote for the ruling AK Party simply because they do not trust the AK Party's political rivals to provide similar economic benefits to them. LALE KEMAL (Cihan/Today's Zaman) CIHANCopyright © 2014 Cihan News Agency.
]]></text></news-item>