<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="132E-FE23-10B3-A8D3"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Kate Adie talks about 'Fighting on the Home Front' at Huddersfield University; Almost 600 attend watch war journalist event at Huddersfield Town Hall</title><source>examiner.co.uk</source><author>By Andrew Hirst</author><text><![CDATA[An audience of almost 600 people heard broadcaster and war correspondent Kate Adie talk at Huddersfield Literature Festival.
The well-respected war journalist was promoting her book Fighting on the Home Front: The Legacy of Women in World War One, which partly inspired the 'Remembrance' theme of this year's Huddersfield Literature Festival. She talked about women's changing roles during World War One and then took questions from the audience at Huddersfield Town Hall.
Kate was interviewed on stage by Alison Fell who is Professor of French Cultural History at Leeds University and chairwoman of the Steering Group for Legacies of War 1914-18/2014-18, a series of research projects and activities focusing on the centenary of the First World War.
The event had Speech to Text reporting for those who have difficulty hearing and the charity Hearing Link, of which Kate is a patron, attended to hand out information. The talk was sponsored by Huddersfield solicitors Wilkinson Woodward, a company that has supported both this year's and last year's festival.
The 10-day festival continues this weekend, ending with a series of four linked events tomorrow afternoon at Huddersfield University looking at different aspects of human rights. These are:
Remembrance Sunday - Jim Greenhalf's powerful verse about the 307 soldiers shot for offences against the Military Act.
Teaching Men to be Feminist - a talk by bestselling author Anne Dickson.
In Protest: 150 Poems for Human Rights - talks and readings from poets.
Lemn Sissay: The care leaver as Superhero - festival patron Dr Lemn Sissay MBE talks about his own personal view of human rights in relation to his experiences as an adopted child and from his perspective as an adult.
Tickets are available on the door for all these events and full information can be found at www.litfest.org.uk
The festival is expecting a total of around 2,500 people will have attended its 30-plus events between March 6 and 16, with a post-festival Afternoon Literary Tea on Sunday, April 6l with authors Marina Lewycka and Matt Haig.
Click here to take you back to more Huddersfield news.
Want to read, watch and hear more? You can download the FREE Examiner Apple App here, the FREE Examiner Android App here or you can view the paper as an e-edition on your Apple, Android or Kindle device by clicking here
To follow us on Twitter click here
Facebook Page plug in like bar
]]></text></news-item>