<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="13B0-33DD-F048-1079"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>-Washington Trust Announces Promotions</title><source>ENP Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ENP Newswire - 14 March 2014Release date- 13032014 - Washington Trust Announces Promotions.Washington Trust recently announced the promotion of the following employees:Elaine Fiore of Mystic, Conn. has been appointed Vice President, Deposit Operations. In addition to her supervisory responsibilities, Fiore is actively involved in key projects, Deposit Operations efficiencies and cross-training her staff. Her efforts have been a key to the growth of the department and the capability to support a variety of Cash Management services. She joined the Bank in August 2003 as a GL Reconciliation Associate in Financial Administration and was promoted to Deposit Operations Supervisor In October 2006 and to Deposit Operations Officer in June 2009. Fiore holds a Bachelor of Science from Rutgers University and a Masters in Finance from the University of New Haven.
Kevin M. Hanrahan of Warwick, R.I. has been appointed Assistant Vice President, Commercial Real Estate. Hanrahan joined the Bank in July 2010 as an Intern with the Commercial Real Estate team. He joined the Bank full-time as a Credit Analyst in January 2011, and was promoted to Commercial Real Estate Officer in June 2012. In a short period of time, he has become an integral part of the Commercial Real Estate team, fully supporting the analysis and underwriting process. Hanrahan volunteers as a mentor at the RI Financial Coaching Corps. He holds a Bachelor of Science in Finance from the University of Rhode Island, where he is currently enrolled in the MBA program.Holly M. Knott of Carolina, R.I. has been appointed Assistant Vice President, Wealth Management Business Planning Officer. Knott joined the Bank in 2001 as a Teller for the Narragansett Branch. In 2002, she moved to Merchant Service Sales for the Franklin St. office in Westerly and then in 2005 to the role of Mortgage Loan Officer for the Richmond Branch. She also acts as Vice President of Canochet Cliffs in Hope Valley, R.I. and serves as Chair on the Town of Richmond's Affordable Housing Committee. Knott holds a Bachelor of Arts in Psychology from the University of Rhode Island.Jennifer M. LaBore of Narragansett, R.I. has been appointed Treasury Support Officer. LaBore joined the Bank in June 2009 as a Loan Servicing Specialist. In March 2010, she joined the Financial Administration team as a Treasury Specialist. She is responsible for cash management, regulatory reporting and administration of the investment portfolio accounting system. LaBore holds a Bachelor of Science in Accounting from American InterContinental University and is a Six Sigma yellow belt.Courtney G. Marr of Carolina, R.I. has been appointed Online Servicing Officer. Marr joined the Bank in February 2007 as a Flex Banker at the Mystic McQuades Branch. After working at several branch locations, in October 2011 she transferred to the Call Center as an Online Services Specialist. In 2012, Marr assumed responsibility for management and customer support of the Banks Mobile Banking. Marr holds a Bachelor of Science in Human Development and Family Studies from the University of Rhode Island.Lina C. O'Leary of Westerly, R.I. has been appointed Vice President, Online Services and is responsible for managing Personal Online Services, providing online banking training to new employees and internal departments and communicating and managing online banking growth and retention initiatives. O'Leary joined the Bank in 1995 as an Administrative Assistant in the Consumer Credit Department. She joined the Online Services Department in 2003 where she was promoted to Online Services Officer in June 2008 and to AVP, Online Services in December 2011. She currently serves on the board of directors for Stand up for Animals, is co-chair for the Greater Westerly Heart Walk and volunteers with the Providence chapter of the American Red Cross. In 2005, the American Heart Association recognized O'Leary, along with the team who organizes the Greater Westerly Heart Walk, with their Volunteer of the Year Award. In addition, she was awarded the Washington Trust Community Service Award in 2006.Andrew L. Thompson of North Kingstown, R.I. has been appointed Special Assets Officer. Thompson joined the Bank in September 2013 as a Risk Management and Special Assets Trainee. He has extensive experience in collections, loss mitigation, loan workout, foreclosure and bankruptcy knowledge. Most recently, he worked at Textron Financial Corporation managing a large group of workout personnel. In his new role as Special Assets Manager, he will oversee all consumer collection for the Bank. Thompson holds a Bachelor of Arts in Political Science from the University of Rhode Island and a Juris Doctorate from the University of Maine School of Law.Elizabeth M. Turner of Groton, Conn. has been appointed Vice President, Risk Management and is responsible for many risk management functions including monthly reserve calculations, migration analysis, watch list preparation and preparation of quarterly reports on loan review. Turner joined the Bank in February of 2009 as a Risk Management Analyst and was promoted to Risk Management Officer in December 2009. In January 2011 she was promoted to AVP, Risk Management. Turner is a Six Sigma yellow belt and has been involved in many special projects including automation of asset review, revised risk ratings, design and implementation of front-end quality control and retail loan reviews. She holds a Bachelor of Science in Finance from the University of Connecticut.ABOUT WASHINGTON TRUSTFounded in 1800, Washington Trust is one of New England's premier financial services companies, providing mortgage banking, commercial banking, small business banking, personal banking, and wealth management and trust services to individuals and institutions through its offices located in Rhode Island, Connecticut and Massachusetts. The Washington Trust Company is a subsidiary of Washington Trust Bancorp, Inc., (NASDAQ Global Select, symbol: WASH). Web site address: www.washtrust.com.MEDIA CONTACT: Elizabeth B. Eckel, Senior Vice President, MarketingTELEPHONE: 401-348-1309EMAIL: ebeckel@washtrust.com[Editorial queries for this story should be sent to newswire@enpublishing.co.uk ]
]]></text></news-item>