<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="13B1-BE08-3DA0-F4CE"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Cover story: Halftime at the Colorado Capitol; With the Legislature about halfway through its 120-day session, Colorado business has so far avoided major hits from lawmakers. But few measures to help business grow jobs have been adopted, either.</title><source>Denver Business Journal</source><author>Ed Sealover</author><text><![CDATA[For business leaders, the 2014 legislation session at its halfway point has been a little like the opening rounds of a prize fight. None of the body blows they were expecting have been thrown yet, but they've scored a few jabs in the form of targeted tax credits.
Business spent the months before the session bracing to fight back hard against workers' compensation reform and stronger oil and gas regulations, but those measures haven't come up yet. Then again, neither have expected changes protecting condominium developers from the worst effects of construction-defects litigation - a bill that many builders view as the last, best hope to jump-start a sluggish condo construction market.
Instead, there have been smaller skirmishes, such as a successful effort to pare down a bill increasing employer penalties for not paying workers the full wages and benefits they've been promised. And the rewards for business also have been small - a bevy of industry-specific tax credits, many of them pushed by the Colorado Office of Economic Development and International Trade to spur growth in high-paying industries.
This slow movement on more controversial topics can be attributed in large part to the tenuous political balance in the state Senate. There, Democrats hold a one-vote advantage in the form of Sen. Cheri Jahn of Wheat Ridge, but she often crosses party lines to vote with Republicans on business legislation.
Jahn said that House Democrats, who hold a more substantial 37-28 voting advantage, have come to her more often than ever to vet bills before they introduce them.
"The members [of the Legislature] are really concerned about the upcoming election. I think that's clear," said Loren Furman, senior vice president of state and federal relations for the Colorado Association of Commerce and Industry. "I think there is a real sense of caution based on the makeup of the Senate now, and the thought that any anti-business bills will go down in flames."
To understand why elections are so important, one need only to rewind to September, when voters who were angered by new firearms restrictions passed in the 2013 session recalled two Democrats - then-Senate President John Morse of Colorado Springs and Sen. Angela Giron of Pueblo - and created the razor-thin, caution-inducing margin in the Senate. Members of the majority party often prefer not to run controversial legislation in an election year to avoid angering deep-pocketed interest groups, such as business, that could play major roles in swing districts.
And thus far, 2014 is a far cry from 2013. Last year, business interests were unable to block a number of measures that leaders claimed were going to raise operating costs, including a law that allows plaintiffs to win bigger damages from small companies in discrimination lawsuits. And then there was the measure requiring rural electric cooperatives to sell more renewable energy, which some groups didn't like either.
The National Federation of Independent Business said the atmosphere at the Capitol seemed outright hostile to for-profit companies.
That, in part, explains why some of the legislative efforts that concern businesses this year are taking so long to become actual legislation ­- and which may not get introduced at all this year, which would be a big win for business interests.
Here's a mid-session look at four of those major legislative efforts.
Rep. Angela Williams, D-Denver, was working with the Colorado AFL-CIO and business groups to find consensus on workers' compensation reform. Labor leaders have pushed for several years for changes - including enlarging the pool of doctors that workers can choose to see and eliminating the 50 percent settlement penalties for workers who were not following safety guidelines when injured. But businesses have resisted, citing the fact that the state has some of the lowest workers' comp premiums in the country under the current system.
After months of negotiations, Williams said recently that the chances are "50/50" that she will introduce any type of workers' comp reform bill this year. She believes she's found some compromise on the issue of doctor choice but she is finding it harder to get agreement on the reduced settlements question.
"I'd like to see a bill where industry and myself and labor could come to an agreement," said Williams on the prospects of introducing a bill this year. "It's a very delicate situation. And, as I promised, we would listen to both sides of the equation."
Supporters of increased regulation of energy companies have concentrated their efforts on two non-legislative solutions. They submitted a proposed constitutional amendment on Feb. 21 to give local governments more control over drilling, and two days later they cheered the Air Quality Control Commission's approval of more stringent rules against methane emissions from oil rigs.
That doesn't mean that drilling-related legislation won't come up this year. House Majority Leader Dickey Lee Hullinghorst, D-Gunbarrel, said she continues to work with stakeholders on a local-control bill that she would prefer take the place of a constitutional amendment. And on Feb. 27, Rep. Joann Ginal, D-Fort Collins, reintroduced a bill that would direct the Colorado Department of Public Health and Environment to conduct an analysis of whether oil and gas operations have an impact on the health of Front Range residents - a measure she sponsored last year but withdrew for lack of support.
But there has been no effort to introduce some of the more controversial bills that died in close votes last year, such as the attempt to remove promotion of the oil and gas industry from the mission of the Colorado Oil and Gas Conservation Commission. And, according to several legislative leaders, there are no efforts to bring forward a statewide fracking ban that would be easily be among the most fiercely contested bills this year.
Many Capitol observers believe that a key reason for the lack of movement on oil and gas bills is that Gov. John Hickenlooper has defended the state's existing rules vigorously and would be likely to veto any regulations that alter them significantly.
Business leaders have been enjoying the many tax-credit proposals being introduced this year by members of both parties to try to benefit certain industries.
Proposed laws are advancing through the Legislature that target tax credits for space travel, biogas production, brownfield cleanup and investments in "advanced industries" - advanced manufacturing, aerospace, bioscience, electronics, energy/natural resources, information technology and infrastructure engineering. Another bill that passed its first House committee even proposes for the state to pay half the costs of internships companies in those advanced industries offer to Colorado students.
There also are several wider-ranging tax-credit bills. One would expand the pool of expanding or relocating businesses eligible for job-growth incentive tax credits, while another would bring some long-sought business personal property tax relief, raising from $7,000 to $25,000 the amount of property a business could own and be able to apply for a tax credit to get back its tax payments.
Some of this legislation is coming from Democrats who, just four years ago, were the bane of businesses' existence when they adopted what industry leaders and Republicans dubbed the "Dirty Dozen" - suspensions or eliminations of 12 longtime business-related tax credits.
The barrage of new or raised tax credits has confused and frustrated both liberals and conservatives this year.
The left-leaning Colorado Fiscal Institute called 2014 the "Tax Credit Oprah" session - as in, tax incentives are being handed out the same way Oprah Winfrey gave away cars to audience members on her TV show.
Meanwhile, Rep. Spencer Swalm, a Centennial Republican who derides the use of such incentives to pick winners and losers among industries, said he was shocked at how many industries the Legislature - and the House Finance Committee that he sits on, in particular - was agreeing to subsidize.
"At this point in the session, I don't think we've gone one week without having at least one tax-credit bill go through here," Swalm said.
While none have huge impact on the Colorado economy, Furman said lots of businesses benefit from them. But both she and Democratic legislative leaders say that some of the tax credits will not survive the budget-setting process, as lawmakers are likely to have to kill some proposals in order to balance the budget.
"I do think there are economic-development benefits from these bills," she said. "I don't think we're going to have enough money to pay for them all, so I think it's going to come down to a lot of lobbying. The bills that help only one or two companies probably won't make it through the process."
Business leaders continue to wait on what many call one of the most important pro-business ideas that's come up in years.
The Metro Mayors Caucus, Denver Metro Chamber of Commerce and Colorado Association of Home Builders have been working with legislators to introduce a construction-defects tort reform bill that they believe will restart a housing sector that essentially has gone dormant since a series of litigation laws was adopted in the 2000s.
Just 2 percent of the new housing starts in the Denver area last year were condominiums - an affordable-housing option that city leaders say is being stifled by laws that make builders of such projects vulnerable to class-action lawsuits even for minor construction defects.
Those laws require just a small number of condo owners to claim defects in order to file $20 million class-action lawsuits. The risk of suits has scared off many developers and caused insurance on builders of such projects to go through the roof. Instead, the vast majority of multi-family homebuilding has been for apartments, which don't carry the same lawsuit risk.
Sen. Jessie Ulibarri, D-Commerce City, has been given permission to introduce a bill later in the session but said he is still trying to find some common ground among builders, trial lawyers, homeowners associations and economic-development leaders.
Lakewood Mayor Bob Murphy said the coalition pushing for changes in the defects law wants two things: A requirement that a majority of condo owners, rather than just a small number, have to agree to pursue a lawsuit and some opportunity for alternative dispute resolution before a lawsuit can be advanced.
Murphy said he's optimistic that a bill will be introduced and will make it to Hickenlooper's desk, because backers are teaming with affordable-housing advocates to push for its passage to spur condo development around the FasTracks line for young families and empty-nesters.
But homeowners association leaders including Jonathan Harris, vice president of The Point Homeowners Association in Five Points, are asking legislators not to take away any of their rights to remedy what they say have been exacerbating defects.
Murphy, like many of the business leaders who are waiting to see what else is coming, is aware that the next two months could include a very crowded calendar.
"For a decade this issue was sort of a clash of titans between the plaintiffs' bar on one side and the homebuilders on the other side. But it's broadened to so much more now," he said. "I'm certainly hoping that we can get this through this year."
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Denver Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>