<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="13B8-A109-5DB2-A750"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Philippines: Nueva Vizcaya lawmaker renews call for alternative mining law</title><source>Thai News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[House Deputy Speaker and Nueva Vizcaya Rep. Carlos M. Padilla on Thursday said the enactment of alternative mining law is important to provide a new policy in managing the country's mineral resources and in resolving glaring flaws of the Republic Act No. 7942, otherwise known as the Mining Act of 1995.
Given the track record of mining in the Philippines under the Mining Act of 1995, we have witnessed one mine disaster after another, displacement of population and the militarization of communities where mining operations exist, said Padilla.
In his privilege speech Wednesday, the Nueva Vizcaya solon renewed call for Congress to revisit the Mining Act of 1995 and assess its implementation.
He cited the increasing opposition and public opinion towards mining due to various disasters attendant to large-scale mining operations.
In light of the foregoing facts, it is high time for Congress to put premium in the human dignity of communities and biodiversity value of our country's mineral resources. No less than an alternative minerals law will do this, said Padilla.
Under the present law, it allows 100 percent ownership of minerals by foreign entities through Financial and Technical Assistance Agreements (FTAAs); allows for more open areas to mining than to mining-free zones; grants auxiliary entitlements to mining firms such as timber rights, water rights and even the right to use explosives among others; and allows tax deduction, yet leaving communities divided and underdeveloped and which traditional livelihoods directly dependent on natural resources destroyed.
The province of Nueva Vizcaya is home to two large-scale mining companies, Oceana Gold and FCF Minerals. One of the first Financial and Technical Assistance Agreement (FTAA) approved under the law is Didipio Gold Project in Kasibu, Nueva Vizcaya, now under the operation of Oceana Gold Philippines Incorporated (OGPI).
The two mining companies are all threats to my province's mountains, water systems and agricultural products. This is true because at a broader scale the impacts of mining are not contained within the mining area but the use of explosives naturally results in deforestation and slope destabilization, said Padilla.
I won't allow my province of Nueva Vizcaya's natural resources wantonly destroyed in the name of profit, he emphasized.
He added: We saw the increasing number of barricades put up and managed by peoples who refuse to give up their ancestral lands. And we saw numerous provincial and municipal ordinances passed opposing the entry of mining companies in their areas.
In February 2014, the House of Representatives has approved on third and final reading House Bill 3667 seeking to declare the province of Nueva Vizcaya as a mining free zone.
The measure penned by Padilla provides it shall be unlawful for any person to mine or engage in mining operations in Nueva Vizcaya. Violators shall be penalized with 6 to 12 years imprisonment and a fine of P100,000 to P500,000.
The campaign against large scale mining in Nueva Vizcaya has strong public sentiment and this is led by the Diocese of Bayombong Bishop Ramon Villena, people's organizations and civil society organizations.
This week -- dubbed Mining Hell Week -- as a time of reckoning of the tragedies and the irreversible damage mining activities have continuously inflicted on communities since the enactment of Mining Act of 1995.
Various environmental groups have called on Congress to repeal the Mining Act of 1995 and replace it with the proposed Alternative Minerals Management Bill. - PNA
]]></text></news-item>