<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="13F0-7D9B-9BCB-1E9D"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>In Brief</title><source>Record-Journal (Meriden, Connecticut)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[March 31 is deadline for health care sign up
HARTFORD - Officials at Connecticut's health insurance marketplace are reminding people to sign up for coverage before March 31 to avoid facing a tax penalty.
Kevin Counihan, CEO of Access Health CT, said Friday that a public service announcement will soon be launched, advising people to enroll. Those that don't will have to pay $95 or 1 percent of their income - whichever is greater.
"We've got an ongoing marketing campaign that's been very successful," Counihan said during a conference call with reporters.
Counihan said it's unclear how many people in Connecticut could be forced to pay the penalty, likely when they file their 2014 taxes.
But he said Access Health CT has surpassed its goal of enrolling 100,000 individuals.
As of March 9, 152,561 people had enrolled in places through the marketplace, also known as an exchange. Of those who've enrolled, 60,534 were in the private insurance plans offered on the exchange and 92,027 in Medicaid plans.
Counihan said the exchange will work with people in the final days to make sure they're successfully enrolled by March 31 and can avoid the penalty, especially those who may not have fully completed their applications.
- Associated Press
Prison worker charged with taking bribes
NEW HAVEN - An employee of the federal prison in Danbury has been arrested on charges that she took part in a scheme to collect bribes from inmates in exchange for recommendations that they be released early to halfway houses.
Federal prosecutors say 42-year-old Kisha Perkins of Waterbury was arrested at her home Friday morning. She appeared in federal court in New Haven was released on $100,000 bond.
A woman who answered the phone at Perkins' residence said she was not available to comment.
- Associated Press
]]></text></news-item>