<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="151A-08B7-1505-5AD3"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>ED officials to visit Mormugao Port Trust, mines department to collect documents</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[PANAJI: Enforcement directorate (ED) officials will visit the directorate of mines and geology, Mormugao Port Trust (MPT) and Goa port, next week to collect necessary documents to investigate the illegal mining scam estimated at 35,000 crore.
In February, the ED had begun a preliminary inquiry against mining companies, politicians and bureaucrats who are allegedly involved in illegal mining in Goa. The ED is investigating only the financial transactions in the case.
ED sources said that they had requested authorities concerned to submit the documents for investigatio. But as the documents are not in a good condition. the team will visit the offices to collect them.
"We are investigating the case under the Prevention of Money Laundering Act," sources added.
The ED is conducting an inquiry based on an FIR filed by the anti-corruption branch (ACB) of directorate of vigilance against former chief ministers Digambar Kamat and Pratapsingh Rane, politically influential mine owner Praful Hede and others.
The ED had started a preliminary inquiry on the complaint filed by social activist Sudip Tamankar in 2011 before the ACB, outlining criminal conspiracy, cheating under Section 13 of the Prevention of Corruption Act 1988, and Section 22 of the Mines and Minerals (Regulation and Development) Act 1957.
On September 9, 2013, the government constituted the special investigative team (SIT) to inquire into the case and all mining cases were transferred to SIT. SIT has been investigating 11 illegal mining cases.
On August 19, 2013, the crime branch had registered an FIR against politicians, bureaucrats, mine owners, officials of the mines department and others as identified in the reports.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>