<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="15E7-AB4F-08B1-791D"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>State officials discuss new oil, gas emissions rules</title><source>Greeley Tribune (Colorado)</source><author>Sharon Dunn, Greeley Tribune, Colo.</author><text><![CDATA[March 16--Area oil and gas companies soon will be operating under the most stringent emissions compliance regulations in the country after the state Air Quality Control Commission adopted new rules last month.
The rules come after a year-long review of policies and receiving input from practically every interest involved from the operators themselves to environmental and public groups.
The oil and gas industry is thought to be responsible for 55 percent of the state's volatile organic compound concentrations in the air, most of which is believed to come from storage tanks.
The result of the new rules is a collaborative effort that officials believe will reduce VOCs in Colorado's air by 93,500 tons per year and methane/ethane emissions by 65,000 tons per year. In all, the new rules, to take effect in May, are expected to reduce VOCs by 34 percent statewide.
"We think these are fairly common sense rules, even though they're cutting edge on a certain level, the fact that they had buy-in from industry and environmental groups shows the value," said Will Allison, division director of the Air Pollution Control Division of the Colorado Department of Public Health and Environment. "Yes, they're not free, but operators, we think, will capture more gas, which has value, and we think a lot of it is common sense and the social license of doing business in some of the communities."
The Tribune recently sat down with Allison, and Larry Wolk, executive director and chief medial officer for the department, to talk about the impetus for the new rules and what they mean in the future.
The Tribune -- Why was Colorado looking at new rules in the first place? Is it because of a study at the Erie observation tower showing higher concentrations of VOCs?
Will Allison -- The Erie tower issue was one of many things involved here. One of the reasons we started this whole thing is because the federal government finally promulgated nationwide oil and gas rules in 2012, and they were largely patterned after things we were doing in Colorado for years.
We adopted the federal rules and implemented that as a state agency. But we looked for ways that we could enhance them and fill any gaps that might exist. The directive from the governor was to ensure that our rules remain some of the best in the nation and for us to look at areas we thought we could do better. And we identified five or six areas we thought we could.
The cornerstone of this proposal is it is the first-of-its-kind leak-detection and repair program, which is not part of the federal guidelines. And it builds off of things oil and gas operators are already doing, which is going out and inspecting and finding and fixing leaks.
We thought it made sense to have a level playing field and a clear set of rules that set a bare minimum for going out and inspecting sites, and finding and fixing leaks. The frequency, which depends on how big of a facility they have, ranges monthly to annually.
Tribune -- We understand the operators will have to basically police themselves here. Isn't that a little like the fox guarding the henhouse?
Allison -- There is state oversight. Operators are in the best position to inspect and know their own facilities and fix them. We think it's important to put the primary onus on them, and we verify through our own independent inspections, and operators will be required to file annual reports with us detailing their annual inspections. ... We have four infrared cameras now that the legislature helped us get, and we have inspectors who utilize those on a daily basis.
Tribune -- You say a lot of the environmental groups are buying into this, but there is still some concern that the rules don't go far enough, for example, when it comes to oil and gas operations closer to neighborhoods and schools.
Allison -- There are certainly folks who still quibble around the edges of the rules. We recognize concerns about proximity. A lot of growth is now occurring in communities struggling with that, and we hear them loud and clear. Although the new rules only have limited pieces that have the proximity element, we believe these rules are protective no matter where the facility may be.
Tribune -- How much do you expect the numbers to come down with the new rules?
Allison -- With the ambient air quality monitors we have, you can see dramatic drops in certain types of pollution since 2003, when we started instituting more stringent oil and gas controls. So it's gone down. Now, we're trending up again because of the growth. As for whether you will see (visible changes), that's trickier. The hope is there will be fewer pollutants to be tracked.
We've made great strides on the brown cloud in the last 15 years, but there are some days when Mother Nature works against us.
Tribune -- There are other industries in the state besides oil and gas that could be contributing the state's pollutants. What is the state doing about them?
Allison -- Pursuant to the Colorado Clean Air/Clean Jobs Act, several power plants and other industrial sources will need to reduce their emissions, and by the time its fully implemented in 2018, it'll reduce 72,000 tons a year of nox (nitrogen oxides) emissions.
It's a phased rule, so some of this has already happened. Xcel has convereted some of its Front Range plants, particularly Cherokee plant, to natural gas.
Larry Wolk -- We may have to start picking on cows. We're watching it like anything else. If there truly is a concern, no matter the source, then it will come out as oil and gas starts to drop, then we'll see who work what is doing anything else.
Allison -- We are working with the agricultural community on best management practices like handling manure or reducing nitrogen impacts on Rocky Mountain parks. But clearly, oil and gas is an industrial source with point-source emissions and cost-effective technologies, whereas other industries, such as cows, that don't lend itself to the same simple fix.
Tribune -- Will the state tweak the rules in the future or revisit them to monitor their success or lack thereof?
Allison -- One of the great things about rules, is they were adopted at the state level. They're not part of the federal implementation plan, which is going to be required in a few years to try to come into attainment and ozone standards. At that time, it's a natural opportunity to see if any tweaks are appropriate. ... The Air Quality Control Commission directed us to come back and give annual briefings. We try to do that on any new rules because these are significant initiatives. We do want to take a look at the annual reports.
Tribune -- With adopting the new rules, are you hearing from other states to follow Colorado's lead?
Wolk -- There's industry concern. Every state is different with topography and climate, so there is concern at least the industry has about making sure it's apples to apples. The governor spoke at a conference in Houston and got quite a bit of support from the industry.
Tribune -- Is the state on track to reducing its ozone?
Allison -- I'm cautiously optimistic we can get there. It's a very challenging subject. We've had very hot and dry summers that have worked against us, so we're going to need help from reducing emission and Mother Nature.
As a state, our ozone non-attainment area is from Chatfield Reservoir (south of Denver) to Wellington.
___ (c)2014 the Greeley Tribune (Greeley, Colo.) Visit the Greeley Tribune (Greeley, Colo.) at www.greeleytribune.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>