<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1603-3AB9-1A37-9CD1"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Nuclear reaction</title><source>Gulf Daily News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Three years ago Japan was the second-most nuclear-dependent country on Earth. Only France relied on nuclear plants for a higher proportion of its energy. Now, Japan uses no nuclear energy at all. Since the Fukushima Daiichi disaster it has shut all 48 reactors not already destroyed by the original tsunami on March 11, 2011.
The results are clear: Domestic energy costs are 20 per cent higher than before the meltdown. Japan's trade deficit has never been higher and its energy utilities have never been more dependent on imports, chief among them Russian gas. The right solution is the one promoted by Prime Minister Shinzo Abe - a cautious, gradual return to nuclear power generation.
No one should understate the scale of the Fukushima fiasco or of a clean-up that has barely started. It was the worst nuclear accident since Chernobyl, emitting a fifth as much radiation but still enough to prevent 100,000 people returning to their homes. Tens of thousands are still living in converted sports halls and shipping containers, as engineers still struggle to make the site safe.
Every day hundreds of tonnes of groundwater seep into the wreckage of the reactors, where it is poisoned. Much of it - about 400 tonnes a day - is pumped into holding tanks, but no amount of ingenuity or effort has prevented a steady seepage into the Pacific Ocean or kept the tanks secure.
The real work of decommissioning Fukushima by removing the fuel rods from its reactors will be done by robots. But it will not start until 2020 and will not be complete, even on an optimistic forecast, until the middle of the century. More earthquakes and tsunamis are virtually inevitable before then.
Anti-nuclear activists seized on Fukushima to press for a renunciation of nuclear power in Japan, as they did in Germany. In reality neither the earthquake nor the tidal wave made their case compelling. On the contrary, as an independent commission setup by the government established, the nuclear disaster was distinct from the natural ones, and it was "man-made" and avoidable.
Fukushima's defences should have been able to withstand a surge commensurate with a magnitude 9 earthquake, but could not. As a result its reactors were overwhelmed and every back-up power system failed. Those whose job it was to shut the reactors down were plunged into darkness. Chaos and fumbling defined the immediate response. It also defined the decision-making, or lack thereof, within and between the plant's management and Japan's government in the weeks that followed.
Since March 2011 Tokyo has set up a new Nuclear Regulation Authority, which has drawn up new nuclear safety rules. As of last year, nuclear power stations needed better seismic monitoring, higher tsunami defences and, crucially, remote control rooms on high ground that could never be swamped by a tidal wave.
Public opposition to nuclear power has lost some of its intensity as the death toll directly attributable to the disaster has stayed stubbornly low. What have not changed are Japan's energy fundamentals. It wastes less than before Fukushima, but its net long-term demand will rise. It has few reserves of its own, and the risks of dependence on imports are as clear to the east of Russia as to the west. The lesson of Fukushima is that nuclear power must be safer, but not scrapped.H G
]]></text></news-item>