<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1618-6840-5535-3633"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Tajik official says 45m-dollar aid received to strengthen Afghan border</title><source>BBC Monitoring Central Asia UnitSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Text of report by Tajik private weekly newspaper Asia- Plus on 13 March
The world community has spent 45m dollars [to acquire] modern equipment to improve the protection of border with Afghanistan, the deputy chairman of the State Committee on National Security [SCNS] of Tajikistan, Mansurjon Umarov, said at the European Union-Japan international conference on Tajikistan-Afghanistan borders management and cross-border collaboration [held in Dushanbe on 4-5 March 2014].
He said that donor countries were now helping to strengthen security on the Tajik-Afghan border due to the withdrawal of the anti-terrorist coalition forces from Afghanistan. "The situation is expected to deteriorate and we hope that the Afghan authorities have resources to regulate the situation," Umarov said.
In addition, the SCNS deputy chairman said that Tajikistan's law-enforcement bodies and security forces had conducted 180 special operations on the Tajik-Afghan border, killed 36 smugglers in 38 armed clashes on the Tajik-Afghan border, seized more than 3.5 tons of drugs and 120 firearms over the past three years. Umarov said that despite the results, drug smuggling remains a major problem at the moment due to this Tajikistan needs the international community's help and support.
The European Union [EU], which consists of 28 member states, is the world's biggest aid donor. Tajikistan is receiving the bulk of bilateral aid in the Central Asian region (66m euros in 2007-10 and 62m euros in 2011-13) in the form of sector programmes, technical assistance and grants.
The provided assistance is focused on the spheres of social protection, health care, development of private sector and basic sector of management of government finances. Tajikistan also receives regional and thematic support in the areas, such as border management and drug trafficking control (BOMCA/CADAP [Border Management in Central Asia/Central Asia Drug Action Programme] programmes), education (TEMPUS, Erasmus Mundus programmes), water supply/environment protection, migration, human rights protection and democracy (EIDHR programme), non-governmental organizations (NSA programme) and development of small and medium-sized businesses (CA-Invest programme).
The EU's programmes have been functioning in Tajikistan since 1992 and about 25m euros is annually allocated to support the [economic] development.
Source: Asia-Plus, Dushanbe, in Russian 13 Mar 14 p 2
]]></text></news-item>