<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1656-B933-D9E8-BAE8"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>In Colombia, Two Warring Officials Provide a Portrait of a Nation's Political Divide</title><source>The New York Times</source><author>By WILLIAM NEUMAN; Susan Abad contributed reporting from Bogotá.</author><text><![CDATA[BOGOTÁ, Colombia -- The political battle royale playing out between the mayor of Bogotá and the country's powerful inspector general, who ordered him removed from office, has been compared to a Latin soap opera. But as it drags on, it more closely resembles an absurdist drama in which two actors alternately fascinate and irritate their audience with squabbling, philosophizing and the occasional kick in the pants.
The conflict has captivated the nation since the inspector general, Alejandro Ordóñez, ruled in December that the mayor, Gustavo Petro, had violated the law in 2012 by switching Bogotá's garbage collection from private companies to a city-run service.
Mr. Ordóñez determined that Mr. Petro's transgressions -- he was also accused of mismanaging the handover -- were so serious that he should lose his job and be barred from public office for 15 years. The punishment seemed excessive to enough citizens that it provoked widespread sympathy for the mayor, who called supporters into the streets to protest, then urged them to flood the courts with petitions to keep him in his job.
Coming as the national government is seeking a peace deal with the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia, or FARC, the guerrillas who have fought the government for 50 years, the altercation in Bogotá has taken on added significance because it pits icons of the left and right against each other.
''What they're doing here is trying to get rid of a leftist officeholder who potentially could become a national leader, and therefore there is a probability he could become president,'' Mr. Petro said.
He has asserted that the move was meant to send a message to those involved in the peace talks, taking place in Havana, that there is no room in Colombia for left-wing politicians. But he has also cast the conflict in personal terms, calling Mr. Ordóñez a religious fanatic and noting his conservative political and religious affiliations. Mr. Petro sees himself as the target of a conspiracy by the rich and powerful.
Mr. Ordóñez brushes aside these comments and points out that he has removed officials from the right and the left.
''Petro was removed for failing to carry out his duties,'' he said. ''For wasting public funds with his improvisation. That is to say, for being a bad mayor.''
The men are polar opposites whose careers trace familiar lines in Colombian society. Mr. Petro, 53, speaks in a low voice that forces listeners to lean in to hear him. Mr. Ordóñez, 58, speaks forcefully and loudly.
Mr. Petro wears Emporio Armani glasses, plush Oxford shirts open at the collar, blue jeans and loafers. Mr. Ordóñez wears dark gray suits, white shirts with French cuffs, and tightly knotted neckties.
Mr. Petro reads Michel Foucault, the radical French philosopher. Mr. Ordóñez reads Sir Thomas More; in his office is a large Bible on a stand that on a recent morning was open to Ecclesiastes.
They have traveled very different paths.
Mr. Petro was a leader of the M-19 guerrillas. He was arrested and tortured in the 1980s, then helped negotiate a 1990 peace deal that allowed the group to enter mainstream politics. He was elected to Congress and the Senate, where he exposed links between right-wing politicians and paramilitary groups.
In 2010 he ran unsuccessfully for president, and a year later he was elected mayor of Bogotá, the country's capital and largest city, with close to eight million people.
In his story, some Colombians see the possibility of a nation free of armed conflict, where left and right would limit their fighting to politics.
Mr. Ordóñez forged a career solidly within the conservative establishment. A lawyer and a judge, he rose to lead the Council of State, one of the highest courts here. In 2009 the Senate chose him as inspector general. Mr. Petro voted for him.
In that job, Mr. Ordóñez has drawn criticism for stances including his opposition to abortion and same-sex marriage.
In December, Mr. Petro predicted that the protests against his ouster would inspire a political transformation, with Bogotá's Plaza de Bolívar becoming like Tahrir Square in Cairo, where millions rallied for change. But while early demonstrations filled the plaza, they soon dwindled.
Nonetheless, Mr. Ordóñez's ruling has raised questions about the inspector general's office, which investigates accusations of corruption or bad administration by public officials and then rules on those cases. It is police, prosecutor and judge, and even decides appeals of its own rulings. Mr. Ordoñez upheld his own decision when Mr. Petro appealed.
While some are now saying it is time to dilute the office, many still feel a strong watchdog is needed, reflecting the depth of official corruption and the general lack of regard for public officials here.
Since 2001, the inspector general has removed 816 mayors, 72 governors, 10 senators and 38 members of Congress. More have received lesser penalties.
The current contretemps derives from Mr. Petro's decision to assign garbage pickup to a city agency instead of the companies that had made hefty profits from the job for years. But the city was unprepared and the handover was widely seen as a fiasco, as garbage piled up on the streets.
Mr. Ordóñez says the change was illegal because it did not allow for competition and free enterprise. Mr. Petro has asked the Inter-American Court of Human Rights to step in. He and hundreds of followers also fought the ouster in the Colombian courts.
The Council of State is expected to decide soon if Mr. Petro must leave office. The question could wind up on the desk of President Juan Manuel Santos, who would have to sign off on the removal, something Mr. Ordóñez calls a formality. Mr. Santos is running for re-election, which could add another twist.
If the case drags on or Mr. Petro wins, he could face another challenge. Early in his term, opponents collected signatures for a recall election. After many delays, that vote was set for April 6 -- if Mr. Petro is still in office.
He first fought the recall attempt, but now he embraces it. If he wins, he can claim that voters have ratified his handling of his job and that removing him would be undemocratic.
Mr. Petro has not been a popular mayor. He won just 723,157 votes, less a third of the ballots in a race with multiple candidates. For most of his tenure, he has struggled with low approval ratings, and many see him as arrogant and a poor manager. But then came the ruling and the surge of support, and now, even if he loses his job, many say his political career is far from over.
In a sense, Mr. Ordóñez did Mr. Petro a favor, Paul Bromberg, a former mayor of Bogotá, said. ''This launches him politically as a person persecuted by the system, persecuted by the inspector general, who lots of people hate,'' he said. ''He made him an important person again.''
http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/16/world/americas/in-colombia-two-warring-officials-provide-a-portrait-of-a-nations-political-divide.html
]]></text></news-item>