<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1661-176B-3714-3064"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>PM's adviser tells him: it's time for GM crops</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Sarah Knapton</author><text><![CDATA[GENETICALLY modified crops could be more nutritious than natural produce, the government's Chief Scientific Adviser has told the Prime Minister.
Sir Mark Walport has written to David Cameron recommending that farmers should start to plant GM crops.
There is no scientific evidence to suggest that such crops are dangerous to humans or the environment, he says.
They could even be more beneficial to health, he argues. Scientists could add nutrients to the genetic make-up of plants.
They would cut down on the need for pesticides and help farmers feed a growing population at a time when global warming threatens climates. "Extensive studies have failed to reveal any inherent risks to humans or the environment," said Sir Mark. "We take it for granted that because our shelves and supermarkets are heaving with food that there are no problems with food security. But we have limited land in the UK and climate disruption and population growth are putting pressure on food supply."
GM crops have polarised opinion since they were first produced by American scientists in 1982. Activists claim they could cause cancer, damage ecosystems and cross-pollinate with grasses to produce "super-weeds".
No commercial GM crops are grown in Britain. Sir Mark is calling for a new body to approve GM crop production on a caseby-case basis, in the same way that the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence regulates new drugs. Currently GM crops must be passed by the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) and then approved by the Advisory Committee on Novel Foods and Processes - an independent body of scientific experts.
But scientists have accused the EFSA of being increasingly "hostile" to GM plants.
However, other academics said that the European Union regulations were important. Prof Joe Perry, of the University of Greenwich, said: "The regulatory process within the EU gives confidence to consumers."
Previous studies have suggested that some modified crops could cause tumours and early death. But a report published yesterday by academics from Cambridge and Reading Universities ruled out any link to cancer. A spokesman for the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs said the Government was working to allow GM crops to be grown commercially in Britain.
MATT 'I've developed a parsnip that can frack for shale gas'
]]></text></news-item>