<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="16A4-AB52-59A9-4B59"><date>2014-03-10</date><title>US accuses separatists in eastern Libya of oil theft; Military force authorized to liberate ports</title><source>ANSA English Media Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[(ANSAmed) - TRIPOLI, MARCH 10 - The United States on Monday accused separatists in eastern Libya of oil theft. On Saturday the group announced they were beginning to export oil without authorization from the central government.
The exports are occurring on a North Korean-flagged ship that entered the Sidra port illegally, said Jen Psaki, US State Department spokeswoman. She said that the rebels' selling of oil was tantamount to stealing from the Libyan people. ''The oil belongs to the Libyan National Oil Company and its joint venture partners,'' Psaki said, noting the partners include US companies and warning would-be buyers of possible sanctions and liabilities.
The selling of the oil was called a ''criminal act'' by Tripoli, and the Libyan defense ministry ordered intervention to stop the Morning Glory tanker whenever it leaves the port. The former rebels nevertheless continued to load the tanker, which has a capacity of 350,000 barrels. Local media report that the tanker has loaded crude oil worth some 36 million US dollars. The intention to export crude oil independently of Libyan authorities was announced on Saturday by Abdo Rabbo Al-Barassi, prime minister of the self-proclaimed government of Cyrenaica.
The export operation will be the first attempted by the Barqa (Arabic name of Cyrenaica) Political Office, which declared regional autonomy in recent months. The body was formed by a former revolutionary, Ibrahim Jadran, who in late July led the blockade on the country's largest ports, demanding the right to a greater share of export revenues and accusing the government of corruption in oil sales. Some sources say that Morning Glory is registered in the Persian Gulf and not actually under Pyongyang's control.
The Libyan General National Congress (GNC) has meanwhile passed a resolution calling for the formation of a military force to liberate the largest oil terminals in the country, occupied since late July by a separatist group. The news was reported by parliamentary sources. The resolution authorizes Libyan army units and militias from different areas but affiliated with the government to set up a military force to put an end to the blockade of the largest ports and restore control over them by the authorities. The new formation will later be tasked with protecting oil facilities. The military operation will begin next week.
Libyan oil output fell to its lowest-ever level in 2013: 110,000 barrels per day (bpd) compared with the 1.6 million during the Gaddafi period. The oil crisis has had detrimental effects on the Libyan economy, which depends primarily on oil.
]]></text></news-item>