<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="16A6-86BA-1C93-D179"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Paris firm talks down building duopoly fears</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>James Chessell</author><text><![CDATA[Paris One of the world's largest construction firms, Bouygues, has challenged the notion Lend Lease and Leighton Holdings have a duopoly in Australia, arguing it has become easier for foreign companies to win big contracts in Australia despite challenges from unions.
However, a senior executive from the Paris-based Bouygues, Christian Gazaignes, said he would still only partner with the two dominant domestic construction firms for big projects because they were better able to negotiate tough workplace conditions.
On Sunday, a consortium including Lend Lease, Bouygues and Transurban were awarded a contract to design and construct the $3 billion NorthConnex tunnel that will link Sydney's M1 and M2 motorways.
But asked if it was impossible to win a substantial tender in Australia without Leighton or Lend Lease Mr Gazaignes said: "If you had met me one year ago I would have said yes but I think there is a move in the market."
His comments come at a critical juncture for the local construction industry, which is the subject of a Productivity Commission inquiry ordered by the Abbott government ito the challenges facing major projects. Independent Contractors of Australia last week lodged a submission saying Lend Lease and Leighton are effectively running a cartel that inflates costs by as much as 30 per cent.
Italian construction firm Salini argued in November that the tender process for big infrastructure projects was "almost designed to protect the Australian duopoly".
Mr Gazaignes, who is Bouygues's chief executive of complex projects, said it had been easier for public servants to pick Australian companies such as Leighton because it was politically sensitive if there were problems with the project.
"You chose Leighton and if you have a huge claim at the end then obviously it could not be done without a claim. Nobody is criticised. If you are French or Italian or German and it ends up in a big row then the question is, 'Why did you chose this foreigner,'" he said.Skytrain success
But Mr Gazaignes said he had been heartened by Salini's success in securing the contract to design and build the $300 million Skytrain bridges as part of the North West Rail Link in Sydney, which came "to the total surprise of the market".
"Everybody was expecting it would be between Lend Lease and Leighton," he said. "At the end of the day there is a move [in Australia]."
Mr Gazaignes said the Australian tendering process - including the question and answer process after initial bids had been submitted - allowed bidders to influence the process.
"So the big problem is in the process of the assessment," he said.
"Something that is quite surprising for us is, OK, you tender, you finalise a price and then after that you have questions and answers. And after the questions and answers there is an assessment. It opens the door to a lot of manipulation."
Bouygues is presently tendering for three big Australian projects: the $800 million Westadium in Perth; the East West Link road in Melbourne; and the NorthConnex tunnel. Mr Gazaignes said the French group had partnered with Lend Lease on the NorthConnex and East West Link projects because it was part of the company's broader Australian strategy. Mr Gazaignes said Canadian-controlled Multiplex was the favourite for the Perth Stadium. Different projects, different partners
"We change partners depending on the size of the projects," he said. "If it is above $1 billion we say, 'We need to go either with Leighton or with Lend Lease' because we consider that due to the union conditions it is very hard to work in Australia if you are by yourself.
"If the projects are below $1 billion Leighton and Lend Lease are not interested to team up with us. So we try to team with a second-tier contractor. Traditionally we were teaming up with Macmahon Holdings. But to prevent us from entering the market Leighton bought 20 per cent [of Macmahon] and then afterwards they bought the whole thing because it is a war."
Mr Gazaignes indicated the move to outright control of Leighton by German majority shareholder Hoctief would not change the local landscape. "[Politicians] say, 'We want to award to the projects to a consortium that is a mix of foreigners and local.' And Leighton is pretending they are both. For us the relationship with Lend Lease is excellent. I think the mix can work. If people learn it is possible to work with foreigners then things may change."
Australia is one of the most expensive places in the world to do business for construction companies. Mr Gazaignes an average worker costs $80 per hour in Australia compared with EUR30 ($46) in France.
"What is true is that today the labour costs in Australia are the highest in the world," he said. "It is hard to believe the cost of your manpower."
]]></text></news-item>