<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="16B7-6211-23B7-C4BE"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>EPA to haul away hazardous waste from landfill</title><source>The News Journal (Wilmington, Delaware)</source><author>By, Jeff Montgomery</author><text><![CDATA[The News Journal
The Environmental Protection Agency plans to haul away hazardous waste in part of a riverside landfill adjacent to the Gov. Bacon Health Center south of Delaware City, after decades of see-saw talks about risks and growing concern over erosion.
EPA and Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Control officials have scheduled a public workshop on the project for 6 p.m. to 8 p.m. March 27 at the Grassdale Conference Center in nearby Fort Delaware State Park.
A series of military and state agency users contributed to the problem at Landfill No. 1 along the Delaware River, with past reports citing questions about everything from demolition debris to old cartidges, lead, paint, tar, pesticides, solvents and other materials, as well as the posibility of polychlorinated biphenyls in some spots. Lead contamination concerns have surfaced repeatedly over the years.
"There's a very focused, very specific small portion of the site where that [removal] is going to occur," said Bonnie Smith, spokeswoman for the EPA's regional office in Philadelphia. "It's very important for people to understand that this is not anywhere in the health center or Fort DuPont, where people have been."
DNREC Secretary Collin P. O'Mara briefly cited the problem earlier this month, during his agency's briefing for the General Assembly's capital budget committee.
"There's an old Army landfill, and the challenge of that particular site is, a lot washed out during Sandy, a lot wound up in the river. We're not sure how much," O'Mara said.
"There's going to be a bigger announcement in the next few weeks on a cleanup."
Richard Cathcart, Delaware City's manager, said he had only general information about the removal.
"It looks like it involves lead and other debris that was uncovered during Hurricane Sandy," Cathcart said. "I asked if it was going to be hauled off site. They said the destination will depend on what it is that they're hauling."
Cathcart said that landfill is near some of the site's walking trails, which have been closed and reopened over the years during a succession of investigations.
Attention has focused more intensely on the issue recently as Gov. Jack Markell's administration moves ahead with a proposal to redevelop the historic, 325-acre park and health center into a mixed-use residential, commercial and institutional addition to Delaware City. Designs to date emphasize the area's history, access to water and natural amenities.
DNREC and the Army Corps of Engineers recently agreed to discuss shared liability for cleanup of the landfill, estimated by the Corps to have been in use as early as 1937. Formal military activities at the site date to 1863 and the Civil War, when the area was designated for support of Fort Delaware.
The federal government sold the area to Delaware in 1947, with the property used by a range of agencies that handle a variety of hazardous materials, including pesticides, paints, oil, solvents and other government supplies. A serious fire was reported in a portion of the landfill as recently as 1985, involving both drums and gas cylinders.
"I do know that when I was the director of the Division of Purchasing back in the '80s, there was some cleanup," Cathcart said.
DNREC closed walking trails in the area in 2000 to allow surveys for unexploded ordnance. Although none were found, officials recommended installation of signs advising visitors to stay on marked trails when they were reopened in 2002.
The Corps proposed ending its cleanup activities and responsibilities at the site in 2005, but DNREC requested that it remain active under a federal program for formerly used defense sites.
Contact Jeff Montgomery at (302) 463-3344 or jmontgomery@delawareonline.com
]]></text></news-item>