<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="16BF-7C4B-8CAC-7105"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Waterloo City Council to consider local traffic citation tickets</title><source>Waterloo-Cedar Falls Courier (Iowa)</source><author>Tim Jamison, Waterloo-Cedar Falls Courier, Iowa</author><text><![CDATA[March 16--WATERLOO -- A plan designed to increase city revenue for traffic violations is up for City Council approval Monday.
Safety Services Director Dan Trelka is proposing a new "city infraction ticket" that would allow Waterloo police officers in certain cases to issue a $100 city ticket instead of the current Iowa uniform citation and complaint.
It would allow the city to keep all of the fine revenue instead of the $95 it currently receives when officers issue the standard $195 fine and court costs associated with the state traffic citation.
Motorists who don't pay the city ticket within 15 days or who wish to contest the violation in court would be issued the state citation.
Violators would save money by getting the city infraction ticket and would not have the offense counted against their driving record. But Trelka has said the increased revenue would come from his officers issuing city infraction tickets instead of warnings.
City Council members last months expressed some concerns about the citation being viewed as a money grab for the city budget.
Violations eligible for the municipal infraction ticket include red light and stop sign violations, speeding for six to 15 mph over the posted limit, following too closely, seat belt violations, failure to secure a child and failure to maintain control of a vehicle.
Officers will not be allowed to issue the city ticket if the violation involves a traffic accident with injuries, if the driver has no license or is driving under the influence of alcohol or a controlled substance. A person who does not live in Black Hawk County or who has a traffic violation within two years is not eligible for the city ticket.
Other scheduled council business includes:
-- A $641,171 contract with Municipal Pipe Tool Inc., of Hudson, to line 4.5 miles of sanitary sewers in the area generally bounded by Rainbow Drive, Black Hawk Creek and the Cedar Falls city limits.
-- A $35,975 increase in the contract with Active Thermal for asbestos removal at the former Operation Threshold building, 300 W. Third St. Unexpected layers of roofing were discovered during the project, which will result in the building coming down to provide open space and parking for the Cedar Valley SportsPlex.
The meeting is scheduled for 5:30 p.m. in the Law Court Theater at the Waterloo Center for the Arts, 225 Commercial St.
___ (c)2014 Waterloo-Cedar Falls Courier (Waterloo, Iowa) Visit Waterloo-Cedar Falls Courier (Waterloo, Iowa) at www.wcfcourier.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>