<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="177C-868C-5440-990E"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Paris bars every other driver to tackle pollution at danger levels</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Rory Mulholland</author><text><![CDATA[PARIS will today impose alternate driving days for motorists in an attempt to tackle a blanket of Beijing-style smog that cloaks the city.
From 5.30am, only cars with odd-numbered licence plates will be allowed to drive in the Ile-de-France region, with the restrictions applying to even-numbered cars tomorrow if, as predicted, the air pollution continues.
Hundreds of police officers have been deployed to enforce the ban.
It is only the second time the French authorities have resorted to the drastic restriction, prompted after pollution exceeded safe levels last Wednesday.
On Friday, Paris authorities announced that travellers could use public transport for nothing over the weekend as a result of "significant risks to the health of residents" posed by the sharp rise in pollution. The cities of Caen, Grenoble, Reims and Rouen announced similar measures.
Paris had already made the municipal rental bike and electric car scheme free.
A light breeze reduced the pollution on Saturday, when Ireland's rugby team beat France in the French capital to take the Six Nations championship.
The previous day, particulates in the air reached 180 microgrammes per cubic metre - well over double the safe limit. These so-called PM10 particulates are created by vehicles, heating and heavy industry.
With pollution levels forecast to rise further last night, the prime minister's office announced the decision to restrict drivers in and around the capital for the first time since 1997.
Police said that around 700 officers would be deployed today at 60 points around the capital, with powers to impose (EURO)22 (£18) fines for drivers with the wrong number plates.
Electric or hybrid cars are exempt from the ban, as are taxis, buses, and emergency vehicles. Cars carrying three or more people can also travel regardless of their number plate, in a bid to encourage car-sharing. The government also unveiled other pollution-lowering measures including restrictions on vehicle speeds and on burning fuel.
The Automobile Club Association (ACA), which has 760,000 members, criticised the move as hasty and "bound to lead to chaos". "This measure had no effect in any country where it was introduced," said Didier Bollecker, the ACA's head.
Pierre Chasseray, head of a drivers' association called 40 Millions d'Automobilistes, said: "I am amazed that a small lobby has managed to convince people that cars were behind this peak in pollution. This measure is worse than unfair, it is stupid."
French environmental agencies claimed that pollution levels in Paris rivalled those in Beijing, one of the world's most polluted cities.
The conditions have been caused by a combination of cold nights and warm, sunny days, which have prevented pollution from dispersing. The pollution particulates in the air can cause asthma attacks as well as respiratory and heart problems, while finer particulates - known as PM2.5 - are cancer-causing.
]]></text></news-item>