<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1784-899A-72E0-E723"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Cellectis drops 2.4% - trailing 93% of stocks</title><source>News Bites - Western Europe: France</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Cellectis (FR:ALCLS), France's 2nd largest biotechnology company by market capitalisation, dropped 12.0c (or 2.4%) to close at EUR4.85. In the French market of 566 stocks traded today, the stock has a 6-month relative price strength of 7 indicating it is trailing 93% of the market.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Cellectis, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/0010518119403141137
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- The stock dropped 2.4% on high volatility today.- In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week low once. - The present value of EUR1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Cellectis is EUR692, for a capital loss of EUR308.
- Return on Assets has seen consecutive falls and seems to be on a slippery slope in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

Bullish Signals- The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 22.0%. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 1.1. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.
NoteVolume: there were 133,003 shares worth EUR645,065 (US$896,769) traded. The volume was 0.9 times the average trading of 151,157 shares. Beta: the Beta of Cellectis stock is 1.5. A Beta greater than 1 suggests this is a high risk, high return stock with volatility greater than that of the market. - Cellectis is at a discount of 31.2% to its 12-month high of EUR7.05 on 14 Mar, 2013. It is also at a premium of 129.9% to the 12-month low of EUR2.11 on 17 Dec, 2013.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 17: Cellectis and Servier announce collaboration in allogeneic cell therapy: UCART19 to treat leukemia and 5 product candidates targeting solid tumors[News Story]
Cellectis (Paris:ALCLS) (Alternext: ALCLS), an expert of allogeneic CAR T-cell therapies, today announced that it has signed a strategic collaboration agreement with Servier, the first independent French pharmaceutical research company, to develop and commercialize novel product candidates targeting leukemia and solid tumors.The partnership covers the development and potentially the commercialization of Cellectis' lead product candidate, UCART19.
February 05: US Patent Institutions Recognize the Patentability of Institut Pasteur/Cellectis Early Inventions on Meganucleases[News Story]Cellectis (Paris:ALCLS) (Alternext: ALCLS), the genome engineering specialist, announced that, by the turn of the year, the US Patent and Trademark Office (USPTO) and the Courts of Appeal for the Federal Circuit (CAFC) independently recognized the merits of Cellectis and Institut Pasteur's early inventions on meganucleases.Their decisions awarded the efforts made by Cellectis over the last ten years to advocate that meganucleases were originally invented by Cellectis and Institut Pasteur's researchers.1 - On December 30, 2013, the CAFC overturned an ill-founded decision by the USPTO dated March 2012, which had invalidated three patents filed by Institut Pasteur (US 7, 309, 605; US 6, 610, 545 and US 6, 833, 252).These patents were broadly protecting the use of meganucleases to genetically engineer living cells.
February 04: Cellectis grants genOway an exclusive sublicense for its homologous recombination technology in the field of genetically modified rodent models[News Story]Cellectis (Paris:ALCLS) (Alternext: ALCLS), the genome engineering specialist, and genOway (Alternext: ALGEN), the animal model specialist, today announce an exclusive agreement under which genOway becomes the exclusive provider of Cellectis' homologous recombination technology for research applications in genetically modified rodents.
January 30: Precision BioSciences and Cellectis SA Announce Cross-License and Settlement Agreement for Gene Editing Technology[News Story]Precision BioSciences, Inc. and Cellectis SA (Paris:ALCLS), today announced that they have reached an agreement to settle patent litigation involving engineered I-CreI meganuclease technology. As part of the settlement, the companies will cross-license certain genome engineering patents and drop their on-going lawsuits and patent challenges.
January 29: Cellectis Plant Sciences and Bayer CropScience Extend Their Partnership to Improve Crops by Gene Editing[News Story]
Cellectis plant sciences, the plant genome engineering company and subsidiary of Cellectis SA (Paris:ALCLS), has signed two new agreements with Bayer CropScience, a subsidiary of Bayer AG and a leader in the areas of seeds, crop protection and non-agricultural pest control, on gene editing in plants.
January 17: Axxam and Cellectis Bioresearch Announce Their Collaboration to Offer a New Generation of Cell Based Assays[News Story]Axxam (Milan), a leading provider of discovery services including assay development for high-throughput screening, and Cellectis bioresearch (Paris), the cell engineering expert, have started a collaboration to offer to the Life Science industry an extensive range of integrated discovery services based on genomic engineering technologies.Under the joint offering, clients will be provided with a one-stop-shop approach for the generation of cell-based assays through genomic engineering.
January 09: Cellectis Plant Sciences Announce the Finalization of the First Glycosylation Lines of Their Program[News Story]
Cellectis (Paris:ALCLS) plant sciences, the plant genome engineering specialist, today announced the attainment of an important milestone in its collaboration with Medicago Inc. (Quebec City, Canada). In January 2012 Cellectis and Medicago entered into a research agreement to improve therapeutic proteins expressed from tobacco leaves.At this point, the intended modifications of all targeted genes have been obtained and the 8 edited alleles are assembled in a Nicotiana benthamiana plants without detectable morphological or growth defects.
ISIN: FR0010425595
FR:ALCLS; EPA:ALCLS; PA:ALCLS; FP:ALCLS
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>