<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1799-1BE3-7FC9-38D1"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Ecclestone to sell his F1 stake 'when CVC exits'</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Christian Sylt</author><text><![CDATA[BERNIE Ecclestone has revealed that he will sell his 5.3pc stake in Formula One when its controlling shareholder, the private equity firm CVC, exits the business. CVC has a 35pc stake and planned to exit in an initial public offering on the Singapore stock exchange in 2012. The eurozone crisis put the brakes on this and they have stayed on since due to bribery charges against Mr Ecclestone.
Next month, he is due to go on trial in Germany for allegedly paying part of a $44m (£26m) bribe to steer the sale of F1 to CVC in 2006. He denies the charges and has stepped down from the board of F1's parent company, Delta Topco, until the trial comes to a close in September.
"If I sell, I would sell with CVC," says Mr Ecclestone, 83. "If somebody wants to buy CVC's shares but doesn't need mine, then I will keep them."
Last week, one of F1's minority shareholders, Norway's Norges oil fund, voiced concerns over the delays to the IPO and Mr Ecclestone's forthcoming trial. Norges is the world's largest sovereign wealth fund and can only buy a stake in an unlisted company if it plans an IPO. F1's listing was cancelled three weeks after Norges invested $300m to buy its 4.5pc stake on May 11, 2012.
It is nearly 18 months since an F1 stake changed hands. Its third biggest shareholder, the estate of collapsed investment bank Lehman Brothers, has filed documents which indicate that it may have to sell its 12.3pc holding by June 30 to pay creditors. However, a source close to CVC suggests that it wants to retain it for longer as its value is accelerating. F1's revenues have increased by 31.7pc over the past five years to $1.6bn (£961m), with net profits of $378m.
"Lehman had the opportunity to sell lots of times," says Mr Ecclestone. "Lots of people tried to buy those shares and they won't sell. Maybe they would sell at an overrated price. The obvious thing is for them to sell along with CVC, too."
CVC has right of first refusal if any of F1's minority shareholders want to sell. It is understood to have had talks with American media mogul John Malone's Liberty Global, which has teamed up with Discovery Communications to consider a takeover of Delta Topco.
]]></text></news-item>