<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="179A-A3B4-8CC3-0936"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Bill would let you warn drivers about police; </title><source>The Columbus Dispatch (Ohio)</source><author>Darrel Rowland, The Columbus Dispatch</author><text><![CDATA[Are you one of those drivers who blinks your lights to warn oncoming motorists that a traffic cop waits just ahead?
State Rep. John Becker wants to make sure your right to flash is protected under Ohio law. The Cincinnati Republican introduced House Bill 475 last week because a Missouri driver was prosecuted for his headlight harbinger.
A federal judge issued an injunction to bar the law from being enforced, which he said was a violation of the First Amendment's freedom of speech guarantee.
Lt. David Smith of the State Highway Patrol's Columbus Metro post said troopers don't mind the headlight signal because it's a deterrence to speeders. "If they want to slow down on their own, more power to them."
* * * *
The oft-made assertion that there's no fracking in Ohio's state parks should come with an asterisk.
About 4 acres in a corner of Quail Hollow State Park southeast of Akron already are open to the process to extract oil and gas from shale deep beneath the surface. However, no drill rigs will appear on park property; the material would be accessed from horizontal wells outside the boundary, state officials say.
Ironically, the out-of-state fracker -- Chesapeake Energy -- took advantage of Ohio's controversial "unitization" law to gain access to the park.
That provision allows frackers to add properties of unwilling owners to large drilling units as long as at least 65 percent of the acres in a unit have been leased. Ohio taxpayers would get an eighth of the net royalties from any oil and gas pulled from underneath the property; state officials turned down a signing bonus of $5,002.50 since they didn't want to be part of Chesapeake's plan.
Sharen Neuhardt mentioned almost in passing last week that she and Ed FitzGerald would be making their income-tax forms public as part of their campaign as the Democratic gubernatorial ticket.
Gov. John Kasich and Lt. Gov. Mary Taylor are undecided whether they will. Campaign spokeswoman Connie Wehrkamp said the GOP ticket would be filing financial-disclosure statements, as required by law.
"It touches on far more than a tax return ever could and includes information on investments, loans and other important information that Ohioans deserve to know to ensure that their public officials are doing their jobs with integrity," Wehrkamp said.
Four years ago, Gov. Ted Strickland released 10 years of his tax forms and repeatedly chided Kasich for not making public the filings that would have detailed his compensation from Lehman Brothers, the investment firm that went belly up in 2008.
Kasich allowed reporters to view, but not copy, portions of his 2008 return that showed he and his wife made more than $1.1 million.
drowland@dispatch.com
]]></text></news-item>