<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="17C5-DF33-BDA9-EC90"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Teen repeatedly raped by friend's brother</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[BHOPAL: A youth from Tilajamalpura area in city has been booked for repeatedly raping a teenaged girl over the last three months. Parents of the girl realized about it only after the girl became pregnant and lodged a complaint.
Accused Shubham Ahirwar, has been booked for rape and protection of children and sexual offences act 2012.
Rape survivor, a student of class X, resided near Sheetla Mata temple in old city. Accused also resided in the same locality. Police said the girl is friend of Shubham's sister. The incident took place when went to her friend's house in December last. According to police Shubham dragged her to a room inside his house and raped her.
Later, he had raped her a number of times and threatened her of dire consequences if she revealed it to anyone, police said.
Man ends life after dispute with wife : An argument with wife led a 42-year-old man to commit suicide by consuming poison here on Friday afternoon. A case was registered at TT Nagar police station. and father of three,
Asad Khan had a dispute with her after which he left home and returned consuming celphos pills. Soon his condition started deteriorating.
He told his family members that he had consumed poison.
He was rushed to Hamidia hospital and later to a private hospital where he succumbed.
Police have ruled out recovering any suicide note from him. Investigations are on.
Woman relieved of gold chain: A 44-year-old woman was relieved of her gold chain here on Friday. A case of loot was registered at Govindpura police station. Arpana Shrivastava, a resident of Shakti Nagar, was returning home from market. When she reached home, a youth approached her and snatched the gold chain at her doorstep. He fled on a bike of his accomplice, who waited with a bike at some distance
Body found: A 22-year-old youth, who was missing from March 13, was found dead in Kaliasot dam here on Saturday morning. A case was registered at Chuna Bhatti police station.The dead, Salman Khan, was an employee of the private company was a resident of Sudama Nagar. A missing person report was lodged with Aishbagh police station.
His two-wheeler was also spotted parked at some distance from where the body was recovered. His family suspected a foul play in the death.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>