<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="17C5-17A5-039B-9898"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Malaysia Q2 2014</title><source>Malaysia Water Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Malaysia has seen a change in its water landscape, from one of relative abundance to one of scarcity as population growth, urbanisation, industrialisation and the expansion of irrigated agriculture are placing increasing pressures on water resources and infrastructure. Water management is becoming increasingly complicated due to a lack of clear division of responsibilities between federal and state government agencies. With large concentrations of population, commercial activities and industries in cities and towns, and increasing water consumption; effective water management is becoming a pressing issue as water pollution and climate change threaten water security.
Government Ministries And Agencies
These agencies include:
Pengurusan Aset Air Berhad
PAAB, or Water Asset Management Company (WAMCO), was established on May 5 2006 as a wholly owned company under the Minister of Finance. It has acquired the majority of state-owned assets with the view to enabling them to focus on treatment and distribution. The company has an authorised capital of RM1bn and currently, the paid-up capital is at RM410mn.
One of its primary goals is to consolidate ownership of and responsibility for funding water assets in Peninsular Malaysia and Labuan (in the Eastern Malaysia State of Sabah), hence separating the roles of water operator and asset owner, and to achieve full-cost recovery and financial independence by all the operators and PAAB.
As cited in PAAB's mission objective the role of the organisation is to:
Suruhanjaya Perkhidmatan Air Negara
In view of the need for a more holistic approach in water resources planning and development, the Malaysian government's Water Services Industry Act (WSIA) of 2006 regulates the water industry in the country. The National Water Services Commission Act established a National Water Services Commission, known as SPAN. SPAN issues licences for water operators, mainly state water companies, with the power to revoke licences if standards are not met. Other functions include:
Public Water Companies
Indah Water Konsortium Sdn Bhd (IWK) is the largest public owned sewerage company in Malaysia. It is a wholly government-owned company which has been entrusted with the task of developing and maintaining a modern and efficient sewerage system. Prior to 1994 this was a responsibility previously held by the local water authorities.
Over the years IWK has taken on responsibilities for sewerage services from local authorities in most areas, with the exceptions of the states of Kelantan, Sabah, Sarawak and the Majlis Perbandaran Johor Bahru.
IWK is responsible for maintaining the network of public sewerage pipelines for areas which have a sewerage system that is connected to a public sewage treatment plant.
]]></text></news-item>