<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="17EB-3860-3838-B3B4"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Oklahoma: EQUIPMENT TECHNICIAN (Animal Welfare)</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Department of Employment, The State of Oklahoma has issued the following job announcement:
EQUIPMENT TECHNICIAN (Animal Welfare) Opening Date/Time: Mon. 12/16/13 12:00 AM Central Time Closing Date/Time: Continuous Salary: $9.00 - $11.50 Hourly Job Type: Part Time - Non Seasonal Location: 2811 S.E. 29th Street, Oklahoma City, Oklahoma Department: Development Services NOTE: City employees are required to receive pay electronically, either direct deposit or paycard. NOTE: This position will work no more than 29 hours per week. NOTE: This position may be subject to work weekends, holidays and/or irregular hours.
EQUIPMENT TECHNICIAN (Part-time Custodian) Salary: $9.00 to 11.50/Hourly Dependent Upon Qualifications This position is located in the Animal Welfare Division of the Development Services Department. The Equipment Technician is primarily responsible for performing various facilities and grounds maintenance tasks utilizing vehicles, mowing equipment, and standard electrical and hand tools. Work performed follows an established routine, which may include manual labor duties in addition to equipment operation. The primary functions of this position include cleaning restrooms, offices, and public areas of the shelter. Essential job functions may include: performs maintenance repair tasks for basic upkeep of City grounds and facilities; and locating and disposing of dead animals in accordance with departmental policy and procedure. The worker must be able to assume responsibility for following all procedures and guidelines related to safety, safe operation of equipment, and equipment maintenance tasks. The necessary skills, knowledge, and ability and/or licenses and certifications to perform departmental specific tasks must be acquired prior to assuming the duties of the position.
Job Requirements: Skill in using various types of tools. Skill in following procedures used to repair or replace various items. Ability to perform preventive maintenance repairs. Ability to use work aids and hand/power tools. Ability to work with others. Ability to follow safety procedures, rules, and regulations. Ability to make independent decisions. Ability to follow oral and written instructions. Valid Oklahoma Driver License.
Working Conditions and Physical Requirements: WORKING CONDITIONS Outside; continually exposed to heat, cold, humidity, dust, etc. Subject to working on or around slippery surfaces such as wet streets, mud, and oil. Exposed to hazards due to lifting, cleaning, and using tools and/or equipment. Will work near moving objects such as traffic and equipment. Frequently exposed to toxins and chemical irritants such as pesticides and herbicides. Exposed to dead and decomposing animals. Exposed to pronounced strain or vibrations, high concentrations of dust, and intermittent or continued loud and insistent noises when operating equipment such as concrete saws, jackhammers, and grinding machines. Exposed to allergy causing agents such as bee or wasp stings, poison oak, ivy, or sumac. May be required to work weekends, and/or holidays. Local travel on a daily basis. PHYSICAL REQUIREMENTS Strength enough to lift, push, pull or carry objects weighing up to 95 pounds such as cement bags, asphalt materials, animals and equipment. Stamina enough to exert oneself physically throughout the working day. Extent flexibility and gross body coordination enough to bend, twist, or reach out to load and unload trucks; to dig trenches. Near and far vision enough to see oncoming traffic and to use equipment with which one is working. Hearing enough to understand a conversation in a noisy environment and to determine location of traffic. Speech enough to communicate clearly and distinctly with co-workers and supervisor.
Other Notes: The City of Oklahoma City may use the services of HireRight, Inc., a consumer reporting agency, for lawful employment purposes to collect background information about you in connection with your employment or application for employment.
For further information please visit: http://agency.governmentjobs.com/
]]></text></news-item>