<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1814-2D17-9570-B346"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Daniels joins residents opposing proposed sand mine </title><source>Jackson Citizen Patriot (Michigan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[URL: http://www.mlive.com/news/ann-arbor/index.ssf/2014/03/jeff_daniels_joins_about_500_r.html
By Ben Freed
benfreed@mlive.com
Nearly 500 people, including a state representative and Chelsea's most well-known resident, turned out Thursday night to oppose a new sand and gravel mine in Lyndon Township.
The crowd at the Washington Street Education Center broke into applause when Jeff Daniels walked to the microphone at the front of the auditorium and broke into laughter as he scolded one of the applicant's consultants for snapping a quick photo of him.
"In the last couple days, I've been thinking about what to say, because I'm against this," he said to further applause.
Daniels said he had thought a lot about his father, who ran a lumber company in Chelsea for a number of years, and how he would have handled the situation.
"What Dad would have done is, if it was right for the lumber company and right for the community, he'd go ahead," Daniels said.
"But if it was right for the company and it wasn't necessarily right for everyone in the community, or if it would impact the community negatively, he would kill it. It wouldn't get off of his desk."
Mining permits
McCoig Materials Inc. has applied for a special land use permit and mining permits for the property at 18100 and 18200 M-52, which is owned by the Donald and Janet L. Cunningham Trust. The property, near the corner of M-52 and North Territorial, incorporates one residential house and a telecommunications tower.
ForEnergy LLC, a consulting firm based in Lowell, chose the site and has been communicating with the Planning Commission and residents on behalf of McCoig. Owner Tim Forell has attended both public hearings and said he and his team are taking the public's input seriously in their plans.
"When I see the passion (citizens are showing), we want to show empathy toward that and work with people. We respect their views," he said.
"Believe it or not, we are going to do everything we can to work with them as best we can. Unfortunately, there is no perfect site for a sand and gravel operation. It just doesn't exist."
Forell said after the first public meeting that the proposed site is optimal, because it is in a rural area and has direct access to a major public road.
After more than three hours of public comment, the Lyndon Township Planning Commission agreed to submit its questions to the ForEnergy within two weeks and gave the consulting company until April 11 to respond to any issues they and the public presented.
The township's staff will then have four weeks to examine the applicant's responses, and the special use and mining permits will be on the commission's agenda for its regularly scheduled meeting May 15.
'The Public's evening'
"Tonight was the public's evening ... I think everyone that wanted to talk got to talk, which is a good thing," commission chairman Kevin McLaughlin said after the meeting Thursday.
"The planning commission did not get a chance yet to ask questions of the applicant, but we're going to do that in written form and then again on May 15, and we'll continue from there."
McLaughlin and the township's legal adviser indicated it would be unlikely the commission would come to a conclusion on the matter at the May 15 meeting, and a deadline for written public comment was set for June 12.
Cindy Blum, who spoke during public comment, said she attempted to email her letter to the planning commission, but it bounced back because the mailbox was full.
"We do seem to be receiving a lot of mail about this," McLaughlin said. "We may have maxed out our township server ... we're working to make sure that we'll receive everything."
A range of residents stood up to speak against the mine during the meeting, including University of Michigan lecturers and professors with expertises from geology to law to environmental epidemiology.
"It seems to me like they must have whacked a hornet's nest, because I had no idea we had so many experts living out here," Kathy Bradbury said while addressing the commission.
Homeowner pleas
While the experts delved into the important minutiae of hydrologic studies and traffic patterns, many of the most impassioned pleas came from residents with homes near the property.
"My wife has asthma, and we would be forced to move if this went through," Richard Cook said.
Cook also said the Michigan Zoning and Enabling Act, which asserts an ordinance "shall not prevent the extraction, by mining, of valuable natural resources from any property unless very serious consequences would result from the extraction of those natural resources," is not a just law if the harm to the community does not rise to the level of "very serious consequence."
"We had a reasonable expectation of what Lyndon Township would be, and we look to the board and planning commission for their protection," Gary Murphy, a property owner on Island Lake, said.
He pointed out the property owners on the lake control approximately $10 million of real estate.
"McCoig's expectation of making a profit requires us property owners to give them millions from the investments we've made," he said.
The Master plan
A number of residents, including Sean Kiebler, pointed to Lyndon Township's master plan, which was adopted in 2010 and states: "The next ten years will see Lyndon Township much in the same way it looks today. The Township's landscape will be dominated by public natural resource-based recreation and privately held lands. The wildlife which abounds today will continue to be plentiful. The natural resources of the Township, including its air and water resources, will be pristine, and there will be an overall atmosphere of health and vigor among the residents and families of the township."
The master plan is not a regulatory document, but it is intended to serve as a foundation upon which the township can adopt regulations.
The proposed sand and gravel mine would turn Stofer Hill, one of the highest points in Washtenaw County, into a lake over the course of 30 years.
"The last thing we need around here is another lake 30 years from now," Daniels said. "So that's not much of a selling point."
A number of ecologists and hydrologists said they believe the mining could affect surrounding lakes and ecosystems.
Joel Blum, a University of Michigan professor of geology and environmental science, also pointed out if water were able to seep through the ground more easily, it could release greater amounts of naturally occurring contaminants, including arsenic and nitrate, into the local groundwater.
Forell said his company has started discussions with the township's review team about performing a pump test to more accurately assess the potential hydrologic effect the mine could have on the area.
Traffic concerns
A number of Chelsea residents at the meeting said they came to express their concern about the trucks that would be moving along M-52 at a rate of up to 80 round trips per day.
Chelsea Planning Commission chairman George Kinzer noted with the increase in high-speed rail trains coming through the city, the addition of so many trucks could complicate traffic patterns on the city's Main Street.
"It's difficult for me to believe that the advisers to this firm have done their homework, because there's a red light in the middle of Chelsea, and when that light turns red, traffic backs up across the railroad track -- it's only a block away," he said.
"You might think it's only Chelsea; it's not a lot of traffic. Come visit us at 3 p.m. in the afternoon. There are three schools right there, and a lot of people driving their kids to and from school and activities."
The presence of children and elderly pedestrians along the haul route were also of concern to speakers from Chelsea.
Forell said a traffic study was already underway, and his company was awaiting word from a hydrologist hired by the township to determine if and when a pump test would be performed.
@aa-river @jx-river @statewide more-washtenaw
]]></text></news-item>