<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1829-AF2A-C199-16F8"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Plant requires hard look; Edwardsport might become expensive white elephant.</title><source>Kokomo Tribune (Indiana)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[In 2007, when the Indiana Utility Regulatory Commission approved construction of Duke's huge new generating plant at Edwardsport, the commission put a cap on building costs that could be passed on to ratepayers of $1.985 billion.
Today, the cost of the still-not-quite-right plant hovers at about $3.5 billion - most of which may or may not be the responsibility of ratepayers - with the company seeking permission to add another $180 million to the expense line for a plant that is years behind its projected completion date.
The plant's opponents last week filed a motion with the commission seeking a formal investigation into delays and cost overruns at the plant before the commission acts on Duke's most recent request for cost reimbursement. The motion is the latest in a series of battles with the company.
The commission, often criticized for being too utility-friendly, has already placed a hard cap on the amount of costs that can be added to the rates at $2.6 billion, but Duke has attempted in various ways to shift new costs to ratepayers, which the company hopes is allowed for with this most recent $180 million request.
The fight will go on long after the plant is up and running - or is converted to burn suddenly plentiful natural gas as large reservoirs of it are tapped with new "fracking" technology - but one thing is clear. Duke already has told us that we can expect to see an eventual 16 percent rate increase to pay consumers' share of costs. That doesn't include this latest almost $200 million.
Where is all this going? We really need to know that and if what's been sold as an investment in our collective future might turn into a very bad investment. The investigation sought by opponents, with contractors and the company already slinging accusations at each other and with a still uncertain and balky technology, should be undertaken.
When the plant was conceived in the middle of the last decade, it was seen as a way to produce vastly cleaner energy from coal, thus allowing retirement of the much dirtier coal-fired plants that dot the landscape of southern Indiana. So far, it hasn't produced that, and given the fast-changing energy landscape, Edwardsport may become a very expensive white elephant.
- The Herald-Times, Bloomington
]]></text></news-item>