<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="18A1-11E3-AA74-280F"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>'Our night of terror': collapse victims speak</title><source>WeekendPost (South Africa)</source><author>Riaan Marais, Cindy Preller; Shaun Gillham</author><text><![CDATA['Our night of terror': collapse victims speak 16 in hospital as top-level probes start at factory maraisr@timesmedia.co.za AS MULTIPLE investigations get under way into the collapse of a mezzanine floor at Eyethu Fishing in the Port Elizabeth Harbour, officials rushed yesterday to shut down another building owned by the company. Labour Department officials said this was to ensure that a thorough investigation was carried out and to prevent conditions that might have led to the floor collapse on Thursday night being repeated. The building closed down yesterday is next door to the one where 86 people were injured when the floor crashed down.
Sixteen of the injured workers, two of them in serious condition, are still in hospital. Labour Department officials visited the premises - where 300 people are employed - early yesterday to begin their investigation. In a statement released by its Cape Town offices yesterday, Eyethu Fishing's management said a formal inquiry by the company and relevant authorities would be conducted. They had contacted the Labour Department to investigate the collapse. Eyethu is a subsidiary of Pioneer Fishing, whose chairman is Port Elizabeth businessman Stephen Dondolo. Eyethu is the company's processing and freezing factory, and its operations include an ice plant, cold rooms, engineering services as well as a retail and wholesale fish shop. Harbour operator Transnet National Ports Authority is in the process of gathering information to establish the need for further investigation. Cosatu is also pushing for a full investigation. Spokesman Patrick Craven said it was a miracle that there were no fatalities. "Just the sheer number of injured people makes this a tragedy," he said. Eyethu part-time employees Nokuzola Nogaya, 38, and Nosisi Zakhe, 28, had worked at the fish processing factory for only a day when the floor collapsed at the end of their shift shortly after 8pm. The women, who both sustained fractures, are single mothers from Soweto-on-Sea and were working to earn extra money for their families. Speaking from her hospital bed at the Netcare Greenacres Hospital, Zakhe said all she thought of as the floor gave way was her children. "We were about 30 people finishing our 8pm shift of packing fish and we were standing in line waiting to clock out. "I had found out about the job from a friend and wanted to earn some money to look after my daughters, one-yearold Amila and six-year-old Athanam," Zakhe said. Nogaya, at the same hospital, was crying in pain when Weekend Post arrived. She thought she was going to die when the floor collapsed, causing her to fall on top of screaming colleagues. Netcare Greenacres Hospital marketing manager Adele Kennedy said 17 patients had been admitted to the hospital on Thursday night, with 11 treated for minor injuries before being discharged. All the other patients were in a stable condition and receiving treatment, mostly for fractures. Life Healthcare regional manager Bruce Janssens said 23 people were treated at Life St George's Hospital, with nine of them still at the hospital and in a stable condition. "Thirty-nine patients were seen at the Life Mercantile Hospital accident and emergency unit. Only one was admitted, with the rest receiving medical attention and being discharged," Janssens said. Eyethu chairman Dondolo expressed shock over "the serious accident at our fish processing plant". He said: "Our main concern is for the wellbeing of the workers who were injured. "Eyethu Fishing management immediately responded to ensure all staff received appropriate medical care and we will continue to do everything in our power to assist the staff going forward. "... In the interest of safety, the affected area has been closed until repairs and recommendations requested by the authorities have been implemented." Dondolo said he planned to visit the injured later yesterday. He confirmed two of the workers were seriously injured. "We have established a direct line to our factory for staff and families for any queries and assistance. We have also arranged trauma counselling. "After an investigation by the Labour Department, the areas not affected by the accident have been released to allow normal processing activities to continue as from [today]." Other Eyethu directors are Eastern Cape House of Traditional Leaders deputy chairman Prince Zolile Burns Ncamashe from Alice; Eastern Cape Development Corporation sector manager Mlamli Athanacious Nodada from Grahamstown, and former Eastern Cape Tourism Board chief executive Zola Baba Tshefu of Port Elizabeth. Two Western Cape businessmen, Johannes du Preez and Carl Andre Neethling, are also listed as directors, with Dorothy Joyce Forlee of Port Elizabeth listed as the company secretary. Meanwhile, a Bay structural engineer, who did not want to be named, hoped the authorities would investigate whether or not an engineer had been involved in the construction of the mezzanine floor. It is believed to have been constructed with a steel frame supporting a wooden floor. A mezzanine is usually not a complete floor, but a raised section above another floor, accessible by an attached staircase. "Any proper engineer would have designed a floor that wouldn't collapse for no obvious reason. They would also be on site during construction to ensure the right materials were used, and that no shortcuts were taken." He said the absence of an engineer, due to cost cutting, could be a possibility. Another factor could be that the structure was overloaded beyond the capacity for which it was designed. "A structure like that should also be subject to maintenance, especially with operations that close to the ocean, and a lot of work being done with salt water. Corrosion occurs easily and that mezzanine should be treated once every six to 10 years." But plant engineers who were usually in charge of maintenance were also subject to strict budgets, the consultant said. TRAUMA VICTIMS: Nokuzola Nogaya, 38, above, sheds a tear as she recalls her nightmare experience. Top right is another victim, Zuziwe Qekeze, 25, and, below right, is Nosisi Zakhe, 28. All are recovering at Greenacres Hospital PHOTOGRAPHS: MARK WEST
]]></text></news-item>