<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="19BA-23EF-8347-6E3D"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Colorado: CDOC Dentist I</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Division of Human of Resources, The State of Colorado has issued the following job opportunities:

Job Title: CDOC Dentist I Class Title: DENTIST I Type of Announcement: This position is open only to Colorado state residents. Closing Date/Time: Continuous Primary Physical Work Address: Applications are being accepted to establish an eligibility list for future vacancies throughout the state.
Salary: $8,095.00 - $12,385.00 Monthly Job Type: Full Time Location: Statewide, Colorado How To Apply: Thank you for your interest. Submit an on-line application by clicking the link below or submit a State of Colorado Application for Announced Vacancy and all supplemental questions according to the instructions provided below. Failure to submit a complete and timely application may result in the rejection of your application. Applicants are responsible for ensuring that application materials are received by the appropriate Human Resources office before the closing date and time listed above. If not applying on-line, submit application to: The Colorado Dept. of Corrections has a special application that can only be submitted online through CO-Jobs. If you cannot submit an online application you must contact Lorie Sanchez before the closing date. Department Contact Information: Lorie Sanchez: lorie.sanchez@state.co.us or 719-226-4401 Methods of Appointment: Appointment to the vacancy or vacancies represented by this announcement is expected to be from the eligible list created. However, at the discretion of the appointing authority, the position(s) may be filled by another method of appointment for a valid articulated business reason.
Department Information
The mission of the Colorado Department of Corrections is “To protect the citizens of Colorado by holding offenders accountable and engaging them in opportunities to make positive behavioral changes and become law abiding, productive citizens” Our vision…“Building a safer Colorado for today and tomorrow” If your goal is to build a rewarding, meaningful career, state employment offers:
Distinctive career advancement opportunities throughout the state system; Retirement benefits including PERA Defined Benefit Plan, PERA Defined Contribution Plan, plus 401K and 457 plans; Medical and dental health plans; Paid life insurance; Short and long-term disability coverage; 10 paid holidays per year plus vacation and sick time; Training opportunities and more.
Effective. Measure every aspect of government to be sure it's doing what it's supposed to do and to look at outcomes to judge whether our programs are successful. Efficient. Deliver services in ways that are timely and effective including identifying waste and duplication and measure for efficiency. Elegant. Deliver state services in a way that elevates both the state employee and the person receiving state services.
Description of Job: Provide professional dental care and treatment of oral pathology for offender patients in both routine and emergency settings, to include: diagnostic, preventive, restorative, periodontal, endodontal, oral surgery and prosthetic services. Position advises patients to resolve dental complaints and post dental procedure care; educates to encourage preventive care and appropriate hygiene and refers patients to the appropriate specialty provider, as authorized. Actively participates in the daily dental clinic operations which includes tool control, chemical control, infection control practices, bio hazardous waste, hazardous materials and radiation control exposure control regulations. Provides clinical guidance and direction, consultation, education, and other professional development relative to dental assistants’ performance/duties. Provide guidance on a day-to-day, and as needed, basis to the dental care staff regarding appointment book management to achieve maximum efficiency in the delivery of service. Position may be required to provide treatment in other facilities on occasion. This position may be required to participate in restraining an offender, primarily for medical reasons.
For further information please visit: http://agency.governmentjobs.com
]]></text></news-item>