<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="19CD-8B2D-1946-C8C3"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>'I broke the council's rules but I have not broken law'; DEFENCE: COUNTY AUTHORITY STAFF ARE ACCUSED OF £220K SCAM</title><source>Leicester Mercury</source><author>SUZY GIBSONCOURT</author><text><![CDATA[A county council stores controller accused of defrauding his employers out of tens of thousands of pounds has told a jury he broke council rules but not the law.
Malcolm Farnish (65), who worked in the highways department, said: "I haven't deliberately set out to break the law, that was never my intention."
The prosecution allege he failed to declare that his wife, Valerie (64), also employed by Leicestershire County Council, was a director of a company, Ground Products Limited (GPL), which supplied goods to the authority.
It is claimed the council was cheated out of up to £200,000 in a scam operated by the pair and another couple they were friends with, successful businessman Stephen Reynolds and his wife, Anna, both 61.
Mr Farnish, based at the highways depot in Croft, deliberately placed orders for equipment with a firm set up to facilitate the fraud, by grossly overcharging, it is claimed. Giving evidence in his defence yesterday, Mr Farnish told the court he regretted not declaring an interest, saying: "In hindsight, I should have told the council. I've made a grave error of judgement.
"I broke the council's rules but I haven't broken the law." Mr Farnish accepted he lied when questioned by council officials, by falsely stating his wife received no payment in connection with supplying road cutting blades to the council - when she had, in fact, received dividends totalling £67,000 from GPL.
He lied because he feared losing his job, he said.
His barrister, Tyrone Silcott, said: "The prosecution say you've used your position with the council to defraud the council and you and your friend, Stephen Reynolds, and your two wives, plotted to defraud the council, effectively stealing money from them?" Mr Farnish, a father-of-three, said: "No, I didn't do that. I didn't think we'd done anything wrong."
In his defence statement, given to police following his arrest, Mr Farnish stated he had contacted six suppliers, including GPL, when sourcing road cutting blades to be used by the highways department - and samples were tested in trials.
He stated: "I was instructed the blades provided by GPL were best and most suitable."
Mr Farnish claimed the blades were more expensive than other firms because they were of a better quality.
He said senior managers approved the purchases, although they were unaware his wife was a director of the supply company, run by their friend, Anna Reynolds.
The Farnishes, of Whitestone Road, Nuneaton, and the Reynolds, of Homestead Close, Cossington, deny conspiracy to steal credit balances from the county council between 2004 and 2007. They each deny four counts of conspiring to commit fraud by abuse of Malcolm Farnish's position with the council, between 2004 and November 2010.
Prosecutor Andrew Peet estimated the council lost between £147,000 and £200,000 by overspending up to four times the correct amount for specialist industrial diamond blades for use on the highway.
Mr Farnish claimed he believed, at the time, his wife was recruited to GPL to establish a plumbing side of the business, and was not involved in blades.
Mr Peet alleges the Farnishes were not being "transparent" about their involvement with GPL, whose sole customer was the county council.
Mrs Reynolds, who did GPL administrative work, allegedly instructed a delivery firm to ensure there was "no paperwork with the goods delivered to the county council," to preserve the secrecy.
Her husband allegedly negotiated deals with two portable cabin contractors to supply the council with cabinets, with GPL taking about £21,000 and £4,000 "introduction" and "consultancy" fees. Mr Farnish said he had no involvement in ordering the cabins. The trial continues.
]]></text></news-item>