<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="19CF-3776-B3B7-5926"><date>2014-03-09</date><title>. . . and DiNapoli, too</title><source>Daily News (New York)</source><author>NLVL</author><text><![CDATA[State Controller Tom DiNapoli's attempt to pressure oil giant Chevron to settle a massive environmental lawsuit has blown up in his face.
First, a Manhattan federal judge trashed the case, ruling that lead lawyer Steven Donziger had relied on bribery and false evidence. Then, Chevron's attorney said the company would press an ethics complaint that the company filed against DiNapoli in 2012.
The state's Joint Commission on Public Ethics must do a full-scale examination, adding an investigation of the controller to a docket that already includes a probe of the state attorney general. (See editorial above.)
The lawsuit focused on pollution of the Ecuadorian rain forest in the 1970s and '80s by Texaco, which Chevron took over in 2000. In 2011, an Ecuadorian court awarded Donziger's clients a judgment of $19 billion, later reduced to $9 billion.
Speaking as sole trustee of the state pension fund - which owns 5.8 million Chevron shares - DiNapoli hounded the company to settle in official letters, shareholder resolutions and an Op-Ed for The Huffington Post.
But, as Judge Lewis Kaplan's decision makes clear, the controller pushed the company to spend potentially billions of dollars to close a matter steeped in fraud. Worse, DiNapoli carried water for friends and campaign donors.
As Chevron detailed in its complaint to JCOPE, Donziger and allies ponied up $68,000 for DiNapoli's campaign account as they wheedled his office for help.
"The advantage of a guy like this is that he is political," Donziger said of DiNapoli in an email shortly after DiNapoli took office. "Meaning, if we show him how he can look good going after Chevron, he might be even more likely to help us." His reading proved dead-on, as DiNapoli warned Chevron about "reputational damage" and "massive payouts."
Chevron lawyer Randy Mastro says that, now that the court case is over, the company will give JCOPE evidence to support the accusation that DiNapoli violated state law barring officials from having "any interest, financial or otherwise . . . which is in substantial conflict with the proper discharge of his duties."
DiNapoli's office rejects the charge as "baseless." That's the same word used above by the AG's staff. The conclusion is the same as well: Let the commission decide.
]]></text></news-item>