<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="19E8-DEC3-F366-029F"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Establishes New Headquarters</title><source>Market News Publishing</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[FORTINET INC ("FTNT-Q") - Establishes New Headquarters
Fortinet(r) -- a global leader in high-performance network security, announced that the company has moved its global headquarters to a new and larger 150,000+ square foot facility in Sunnyvale, California. The move reflects Fortinet's expansive growth, fueled by the growing demand for its high performance network security platforms.
According to industry market research firm IDC, Fortinet is gaining market share and is currently the third largest network security appliance vendor in the world. The company makes high performance network security platforms for a wide variety of businesses, such as large enterprise, carrier and government organizations. Additionally, Fortinet is a recognized innovator for network security and has earned numerous industry awards, including having been named to Deloitte's Technology Fast 500(TM) for eight consecutive years. Furthermore, the company has been recognized by Frost &Sullivan for Market Penetration, Enterprise Firewalls, and has received a myriad of editorial and third-party awards, including outstanding enterprise-class performance and protection in three NSS Labs' independent tests for Next-Generation Firewall, Network IPS, and Enterprise Firewall.
As part of the company's growth, Fortinet has significantly increased its headcount over the last two years. As of December, 2013 Fortinet had 2,263 employees, which represents a 19 percent increase over the last two years.
"We are excited to move our headquarters to this state of the art, environmentally friendly facility in Sunnyvale, the heart of Silicon Valley," said Ken Xie, founder and CEO of Fortinet. "This move represents years of expansive growth for the company, and with this new facility, Fortinet will have room to add top-notch engineering, operational, sales and marketing talent."
"Sunnyvale's diverse and thriving business community is one of the foundations of our city's healthy economy," said Sunnyvale Mayor, Jim Griffith. "We congratulate Fortinet on their new headquarters and are delighted they've chosen to remain and expand here in Sunnyvale."
Prior to this move, Fortinet's headquarters were located at 1090 Kifer Road, Sunnyvale, California. The new location, which was purchased by Fortinet, is at 899 Kifer Road, Sunnyvale, and represents the latest in "green" building technology; highlighted by low energy consumption, small carbon footprint, and minimal environmental impact.
In particular, the new Fortinet headquarters leverages the latest in energy conservation technologies, such as auto-dimming light sensors that are integrated with ceiling skylights. As well, the company meets California Title 24 and U.S. Green Building Standard, "Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design" (LEED), which includes the use of low volatile organic compounds throughout the building. Future plans include solar panel integration so that one-third of the power used for the building is self-generated.
Bay Area commuters will appreciate the fact that the new location is also near the Sunnyvale Caltrain station so that employees from Gilroy to San Francisco can easily commute to work. And, to accommodate those with electric cars, the new facility sports multiple electric charging stations.
About Fortinet
Fortinet (NASDAQ: FTNT) helps protect networks, users and data from continually evolving threats. As a global leader in high-performance network security, we enable businesses and governments to consolidate and integrate stand-alone technologies without suffering performance penalties. Unlike costly, inflexible and low-performance alternatives, Fortinet solutions empower customers to embrace new technologies and business opportunities while protecting essential systems and content. Learn more at www.fortinet.com.
Copyright (c) 2014 Fortinet, Inc. All rights reserved. The symbols (r) and (TM) denote respectively federally registered trademarks and unregistered trademarks of Fortinet, Inc., its subsidiaries and affiliates. Fortinet's trademarks include, but are not limited to, the following: Fortinet, FortiGate, FortiGuard, FortiManager, FortiMail, FortiClient, FortiCare, FortiAnalyzer, FortiReporter, FortiOS, FortiASIC, FortiWiFi, FortiSwitch, FortiVoIP, FortiBIOS, FortiLog, FortiResponse, FortiCarrier, FortiScan, FortiAP, FortiDB, FortiVoice and FortiWeb. Other trademarks belong to their respective owners. Fortinet has not independently verified statements or certifications herein attributed to third parties, including IDC and others, and Fortinet does not independently endorse such statements. Notwithstanding anything to the contrary herein, nothing herein constitutes a warranty, guarantee, binding specification or other binding commitment by Fortinet, and performance and other specification information herein may be unique to certain environments. This news release may contain forward-looking statements that involve uncertainties and assumptions, such as statements regarding continued growth and market share gains. Although we attempt to be accurate in making forward-looking statements, it is possible that future circumstances might differ from the assumptions on which such statements are based. Important factors that could cause results to differ materially from the statements herein include the following: general economic risks; specific economic risks in different geographies and among different customer segments, including specific economic risks such as those that may result from the U.S. budget process; uncertainty regarding increased business and renewals from existing customers; uncertainties around continued success in sales growth and market share gains; failure to convert sales pipeline into final sales; risks associated with successful implementation of multiple integrated software products and other product functionality risks; execution risks around new product development and introductions and innovation; customer support challenges; litigation and disputes and the potential cost, distraction and damage to sales and reputation caused thereby; market acceptance of new products and services; the ability to attract and retain personnel and the loss of any key personnel; changes in strategy; risks associated with management of growth; lengthy sales and implementation cycles, particularly in larger organizations and service providers; technological changes that make our products and services less competitive; risks associated with the adoption of, and demand for, the UTM model in general and by specific customer segments; competition and pricing pressure; and the other risk factors set forth from time to time in our most recent Annual Report on Form 10-K, our most recent Quarterly Report on Form 10-Q and our other filings with the SEC, copies of which are available free of charge at the SEC's website at www.sec.gov or upon request from our investor relations department. All forward-looking statements herein reflect our opinions only as of the date of this release, and we undertake no obligation, and expressly disclaim any obligation, to update forward-looking statements herein in light of new information or future events. NASDAQ closing price for FTNT-Q Date: 2014/03/13 Closing Price: 22.60
____________________________________________________________
(c)2014 Market News Publishing Inc. All rights reserved. Toronto:(416)366-8881 Vancouver:(604)689-1101 Fax:(604)689-1106
]]></text></news-item>