<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1A0A-5645-FE4F-5497"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Woman who threatened to kill deputy among 15 indicted</title><source>Norwalk Reflector, Ohio</source><author>Cary Ashby, Norwalk Reflector, Ohio</author><text><![CDATA[March 15--A rural Norwalk woman accused of attempting to stab a Huron County sheriff's deputy was indicted Friday. In a separate case, a Huron County grand jury charged a rural New London man in connection with setting fire to a stolen truck.
Blanche M. Myers, 54, of 602 Greenwich Milan Townline Road, is charged with felonious assault. The first-degree felony is in connection with a Feb. 19 incident and is punishable by three to 11 years in prison. Deputy Steve Mancuso responded to Greenwich Milan Townline Road in Hartland Township for the report of a male subject who reportedly threatened to commit suicide. "Deputy Mancuso responded and was able to determine the individual was not threatening suicide with a knife or gun," Detective Sgt. Josh Querin said soon after the incident. Mancuso then encountered Myers, who was in the roadway near the scene. "The female was in the roadway with a knife and her actions were aggressive in nature," Querin said. "She told Deputy Mancuso she was going to kill him and began to charge at him." Huron County Prosecutor Russell Leffler, citing the deputy's report, said Friday it doesn't appear Mancuso "actually got stabbed." "I know he used a stun gun on her. He ended up stopping her with a stun gun," Leffler said. "She (Myers) stated several times, she wanted to kill all of us pigs (and was) spitting at deputies," according to the sheriff's office report. Myers was transported to Fisher-Titus Medical Center and then booked into the Huron County Jail. She remains in custody. "We're fortunate Deputy Mancuso was equipped with a Taser and avoided possible serious injury. ... It was a good result to a potentially dangerous situation," Querin said. In a separate case, Elliott J.M. Shepherd II, 27, of 2678 Jennings Road, New London, was indicted Friday on one count each of grand theft of a motor vehicle, theft, burglary and arson. The charges are in connection with a Dec. 28 incident. "He allegedly stole his ex-father-in-law's truck and torched it -- along with a fancy welder," Leffler said. In a third case, Charles B. Coleman, 24, and Angela L. Wargo, 24, both of Lorain, were indicted Friday on trafficking in a counterfeit controlled substance in connection with a Feb. 23 incident. According to their indictment, the Feb. 23 "offense was committed in the vicinity of a juvenile." Also indicted were: Melanie B. Bath, 50, of 80 Norwood Ave., Apt. 3C, on six counts of forgery in connection with incidents on Dec. 19, 26 and 28 and Jan. 9, 10 and 16. Katie M. Collins, 32, of 223 1/2 Woodbine St., Willard, on complicity to theft in connection with a Jan. 23 incident. Gia L. Guerra, 42, of 1420 Ohio 61, on one count each of possession of oxycodone and possession of hydromorphone, both in connection with a Nov. 16 incident. Curtis M. Hale, 34, of 515 E. Howard St., Willard, on theft in connection with a Jan. 23 incident. Laura K. Hunt, 28, of 739 Ash St., Willard, on one count each of credit card-related receiving stolen property and misuse of a credit card, both in connection with a Dec. 23 incident. Jacob A. LeClair, 24, of 20 North St., Plymouth, on possession of oxycodone in connection with a July 10 incident. Emery R. Slone, 30, of 4039 Weirs Road, Willard, on tampering with evidence in connection with an Oct. 15 incident. In other action, grand jurors transferred the following misdemeanor cases to Norwalk Municipal Court for further possible prosecution: Hope E. McVeigh, 32, of 2720 Prairie St., New Haven, on permitting drug abuse in connection with a Nov. 7 incident. Joseph A. Story, 29, of 19 Pitt St., on obstructing official business in connection with a Feb. 4 incident. Jared L. Welch, 27, of 394 Cleveland Road, Apt. 7D, on menacing by stalking in connection with a series of incidents from Nov. 21 to Feb. 3. Corey J. Williams, 35, of Sandusky, on complicity to theft in connection with a Jan. 25 incident. Two local residents were among 30 people indicted this week by an Erie County grand jury. Here are the local suspects and their charges: Stephen R. Barnhart, 35, of 2342 Fitchville River Road, on possession of heroin; tampering with evidence. Tricia A. Hoover (aka Tricia A. Pickett), 38, of 20 Reed St., on driving while under the influence of alcohol or drugs. The full list of those indicted is posted at www.norwalkreflector.com.
___ (c)2014 the Norwalk Reflector (Norwalk, Ohio) Visit the Norwalk Reflector (Norwalk, Ohio) at www.norwalkreflector.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>