<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1A55-53D5-8EFC-331A"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>The President And The "I' Word</title><source>Investor's Business Daily</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Constitution: Right now, the public would not support the cure the Framers provided for a president who skirts the laws. But what might the charges against President Obama look like?
If Americans could read for themselves specific articles of impeachment against Obama, would they really think the charges were trumped up, as polls suggest and the media insist is the case?
Has, for instance, the president "failed without lawful cause or excuse to produce papers and things as directed by duly authorized subpoenas issued by . . . the House of Representatives"?
Fact: The Obama administration has withheld plenty of materials requested in House Oversight Committee subpoenas regarding, for instance, the IRS scandal, the Benghazi scandal and the ObamaCare debacle.
Has Obama been "making or causing to be made false or misleading public statements for the purpose of deceiving the people of the United States"? Well, if you liked your health plan were you able to keep it?
Has Obama caused "income tax investigations to be initiated or conducted in a discriminatory manner"? Ask the Tea Party groups seeking the tax-exempt status that were harassed by the IRS during the 2012 presidential campaign, and are still being persecuted.
Has the federal government conducted "electronic surveillance or other investigations for purposes unrelated to national security, the enforcement of laws, or any other lawful function of his office"? 
Only under Obama has the U.S. government conducted bulk collection of law-abiding Americans' communications records, spurring even liberal Democrats to join with Republicans on comprehensive legislation to stop the practice.
All of the above quotes are excerpted from the three articles of impeachment that were hanging over Richard Nixon's head when he resigned from office in 1974.
Now, how high was the impeachment bar for President George W. Bush?
On June 11, 2008, with Democratic nominee Obama looking well on his way to Pennsylvania Avenue, the Democratic-controlled House voted 251 to 166 to send no fewer than 35 articles of impeachment -- 167 pages -- to the House Judiciary Committee for consideration.
Not a single Democrat voted against the measure, and 24 Republicans, including some as prominent as Ron Paul of Texas and Peter King of New York, voted for it.
Here are some of the charges made to remove from office the last Republican president, followed by a reminder of their familiar ring in the Obama era:
V"Creating a Secret Propaganda Campaign" -- ObamaCare? Benghazi?
V"Misleading Congress and the American People" – ObamaCare?  Benghazi?  Syria?
V"Reckless Misspending and Waste of U.S. Tax Dollars" -- Trillion-dollar stimulus? ObamaCare?
V"Detaining Indefinitely and Without Charge Persons, Both U.S. Citizens and Foreign Captives" -- Is Gitmo still open?
V"Supporting Terrorist Organizations Within Iran" -- Appeasing Iran's terrorist government?
V"Creating Secret Laws" -- Clinton-appointed federal Judge Ellen Segal Huvelle ruling in December that the Obama administration is engaging "in what is in effect governance by "secret law' "?
V"Spying on American Citizens, Without a Court-Ordered Warrant, in Violation of the Law and the Fourth Amendment" -- Judge John D. Bates, then chief FISA court judge, ruling in 2011 that NSA bulk email collection violates the Fourth Amendment?
V"Directing Telecommunications Companies to Create an Illegal and Unconstitutional Database of the Private Telephone Numbers and Emails of American Citizens" -- Obama forcing Verizon to turn over customers' call records?
V"Failing to Comply With Congressional Subpoenas" -- Obama's stonewalling the House Oversight Committee's subpoenas on virtually everything?
V"Tampering With Free and Fair Elections, Corruption of the Administration of Justice" -- IRS targeting of Tea Party? Attorney General Eric Holder dropping Black Panther voter intimidation?
V"Misleading Congress and the American People in an Attempt to Destroy Medicare" -- the House on Friday passing a measure to spare doctors from Obama Care's looming Medicare pay cuts?
V"Repeatedly Ignored and Failed to Respond to High Level Intelligence Warnings of Planned Terrorist Attacks in the U.S." -- Obama routinely failing to attend intelligence briefings?
The "I" word may not stay taboo for long.
]]></text></news-item>