<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1BDF-50BA-FEEC-9BB7"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Ethics commission rules against Skidmore</title><source>Charlotte Sun (Port Charlotte, Florida)</source><author>GARY ROBERTS; Staff Writer</author><text><![CDATA[The Florida Commission on Ethics reached a split decision on several complaints filed against Robert Skidmore, finding probable cause that the former Charlotte County commissioner used his position to provide special treatment for one person and unfairly target another.
The ethics commission issued an order March 7 finding reason to believe Skidmore pushed county officials to selectively enforce code violations against a specific property. In addition, the ethics board found probable cause that Skidmore misused his role as commissioner to direct a county staff member to approve a liquor license application for a third party.
The Florida Commission on Ethics now must decide whether the law was actually violated and, if so, whether a penalty should be recommended. At this stage, the accused has the right to request a public hearing at which evidence is presented, or the ethics commission may order such a hearing.
On the two complaints that were dismissed, the ethics commission found no probable cause that Skidmore requested a county employee continue a hearing or that county staff waive the code violations of a constituent.
The complaints were filed by Michael Brown on Sept. 12, 2011. Neither Skidmore nor Brown could be reached for comment.
In the complaint regarding selective enforcement of purported code violations, Brown alleges the former commissioner used his authority to repeatedly seek violations against a restaurant run by a man who shares a child with Skidmore's wife.
In the second complaint moving forward, Brown states that Skidmore asked Shonna Jenkins, then a county code compliant officer, for help in securing a liquor license for another person in February 2011, offering to get Jenkins a pay raise and promotion for her assistance. Skidmore denied harassing the restaurant operator.
Jenkins, who resigned her position on June 27, 2011, also was the central figure in a sexual harassment suit filed against Skidmore and the county in August 2012. In November 2013, Charlotte County settled its portion of the lawsuit by agreeing to pay $115,000.
In the lawsuit, Jenkins charges the former commissioner with creating a hostile work environment by harassing her with sexual innuendo, overt sexual comments and propositions. The suit also claims county officials failed to act on Jenkins' complaints to the county Human Resources Department.
In return, Jenkins waived the right to any future claims. The case, filed in U.S. District Court of the Middle District of Florida, was slated for a jury trial next month.
Email: groberts@sun-herald.com
]]></text></news-item>