<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1CF2-4C66-1817-056E"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Starting gun fired in battle to win Government deals; ANALYSIS: David Shand reveals how scandals have led to £100bn outsourcing shake-up</title><source>Scottish Express</source><author>David Shand</author><text><![CDATA[IT is better known as a tough training ground for soldiers honing their skills for overseas duty but Salisbury Plain this week became a battleground for outsourcing firms vying for billions of pounds of Government contracts.
Capita stole a march over rival Serco after being named by the Ministry of Defence as preferred bidder for a 10-year, £400million contract to work alongside the Defence Infrastructure Organisation to help improve the running of its 230,000-hectare military estate.
Such deals are part of a Whitehall efficiency drive to deliver better value for taxpayers. Companies are estimated to get close to £100billion a year from public sector contracts - but it is not quite business as usual.
The outsourcing process has come under closer scrutiny following the scandal over tagging contracts which engulfed Serco and G4S. Both have overhauled their senior management and will be hoping there is no longterm impact on Government work while they rebuild their reputation.
Capita is also adjusting to life without long-serving chief executive Paul Pindar who has retired.
The debate over whether offering contracts to the private sector provides value for money had already intensified after the National Audit Office claimed there is a "crisis of confidence" surrounding contracting. This intensified yesterday with a critical report on the Government's ability to negotiate and manage outsourcing contracts by the Public Accounts Committee.
The NAO cited a lack of transparency over the role contractors play, the business they do, the rewards they make and the way they perform as it suggested Government departments were "not on top of things" and contractors appeared "not to treat the public sector fairly".
NAO head Amyas Morse said: "There is a clear need to reset the ground rules for both contractors and their departmental customers."
According to Morgan Stanley analyst Allen Wells, the Government is keen to get Serco and G4S back in the competition and there is no "witch hunt" to keep them on the sidelines.
Despite previous transgressions, there are concerns that denying major players the chance to bid for work will weaken the competition process, especially when they are perhaps better placed with their vast resources to handle some of the larger contracts.
Wells said: "The Government continues to view the outsourcing-based model as a key tool to help drive down public sector spending."
The Cabinet Office expects to see more international outfits entering the market to keep existing players on their toes and is looking to simplify the bidding process to drive down costs, thereby encouraging smaller firms to throw their hat in the ring.
There could also be more joint venture and partnership deals.
CBI director-general John Cridland said: "The public has a right to know how its money is being spent and the industry has pledged to meet a higher bar on transparency."
]]></text></news-item>