<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1CFF-1D90-9F2B-517A"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>NMC overlooked 8-yr property tax on controversial plots</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Anjaya Anparthi</author><text><![CDATA[NAGPUR: Yet another irregularity has come to fore in Nagpur Municipal Corporation's (NMC) property tax department. Documents obtained under the Right to Information (RTI) Act have revealed that the department did not recover pending property tax for eight years from five big plots. This hints at yet another modus operandi adopted by officials of the department to benefit some taxpayers, while causing the civic body major loss.
The property tax scam involves the controversial flat schemes being constructed by Fariyas Hotels Private Ltd. Fariyas Hotels is constructing the flat schemes on these five plots, but the irregularity happened before Fariyas Hotels purchased the plots.
In November 2013, TOI had highlighted the dilly-dallying tactics adopted by NMC property tax department and Laxmi Nagar Zone office in providing information about the property tax for these five plots. RTI activist TH Naidu had applied for information in May 21, 2013. Naidu appealed to GM Rathod, assistant commissioner of Laxmi Nagar Zone, on February 3. Rathod held a hearing and pronounced order on February 12, 2014, directing officials to permit Naidu to inspect the file and also give him all documents related to the case.
Naidu told TOI, tax demand notes and receipts of the five plots - 3638/A/99/A, B, C, D and E - situated in khasra no. 82 and 95 at mouza Khamla were not generated from 1968 to 2004. "Land had been converted into non-agriculture by the district administration on July 2, 1996. Land became liable for property tax from 1996-97. Property tax department assessed the plots following an application on December 27, 2004, by members of the Nilawar family. Finally, property tax was recovered from the applicants with effect from July 1, 2004. Thus the civic body lost property tax of eight years," he said.
Naidu said members of Nilawar family had purchased the plots from Nagpur Beghar Mitra Gruhnirman Sahakari Sanstha Limited, with an unregistered sale deed on September 3, 1997. "Registered sale deed was executed on February 18, 2005. Later, Fariyas purchased the plots on June 26, 2008," he said.
Naidu added there may be many such cases. "I suspect similar irregularities happened in remaining plots developed on khasra no. 82 and 95. Property tax from these khasras should be audited," he said.
Rathod told TOI, the property tax department's head office situated at Mahal has been asked to verify whether tax was recovered from the plots before 2004 or not. "I can comment only after detailed verification," he said.
Reacting to Rathod's statement, Naidu said the department at Mahal has already given in writing that it had no information about property tax paid before 2004.
Naidu said NIT and NMC were not taking any action against Fariyas Hotels or previous owners of the plot or the officials concerned, despite several violations exposed by him through RTI. "Chief minister Prithviraj Chavan has refused approval to amalgamation of plots regularized under the Gunthewari Act. But NIT approved amalgamation of these five plots and sanctioned building plan of three multi-storey flat schemes. In fact, a layout for weaker sections had been approved on these plots under ULC's Talegaon Dabhade scheme," he said.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>