<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1D52-0430-25B2-75CD"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>CITY MANAGER TO MAKE $260K; Carlsbad mayor say it?s warranted, as Sarkozy was top candidate in the nation</title><source>The San Diego Union-Tribune</source><author>DAVID GARRICK, U-T</author><text><![CDATA[Carlsbad
Carlsbad’s new top administrator will be the highest-paid city manager in the county, earning a base salary of $260,000 — at least 10 percent more than his counterparts.
Steven R. Sarkozy will also receive some unusual perks, such as $25,000 to cover his moving expenses from Bellevue, Wash., and nearly $47,000 to offset his housing costs in Carlsbad during his first year on the job.
The leader of a local taxpayer group said Friday that Sarkozy’s pay and benefits are excessive. But Mayor Matt Hall said the compensation package is warranted, calling Sarkozy one of the top city managers in the nation.
In addition to his salary, Sarkozy will receive a car allowance of $9,600 a year; the option to cash in four of his eight weeks of annual vacation for $20,000 a year; a $27,000 annual contribution from the city into his 401(k) retirement plan; and free medical, dental and vision insurance.
Scrutiny of salaries for municipal executives has increased since 2010, when news broke that the city manager of Bell — a small suburb of Los Angeles — was being paid nearly $800,000 a year. The scandal led to the arrests of several city leaders and the city manager, Robert Rizzo, eventually pleaded guilty to fraud, misappropriation of public funds and dozens of other charges.
In Carlsbad, Sarkozy’s base salary will be at least $25,000 higher than the county’s other 16 city managers. His closest competitors are the city managers in Escondido, Oceanside and Chula Vista, who each make between $232,000 and $235,000 per year in base pay.
San Diego doesn’t have a city manager because the city operates under a “strong mayor” form of government.
A San Diego taxpayer advocate said Friday that Carlsbad could have hired another qualified applicant for much less money.
“I’m sure this guy is top-notch, but do you really need the best person in the nation?” said Richard Rider, chairman of San Diego Tax Fighters said, noting that 42 people applied for the Carlsbad job. “Any businessman will tell you that if there are 42 applicants, you don’t need to pay top dollar. They could have settled for another qualified applicant and paid $180,000 and no housing costs.”
The 60-year-old Sarkozy, who is scheduled to arrive in Carlsbad April 14, said in a phone interview Friday that he chose Carlsbad over several other cities that offered him more money.
“It’s a very competitive market now for people who’ve managed large cities successfully,” Sarkozy said. “I chose Carlsbad because it’s a city with a great vision of where it wants to go and the will to get there.”
And not all taxpayer advocates are howling over his pay. The top official at the San Diego County Taxpayers Association, which frequently criticizes cities for inflated salaries, said Friday that city managers are a possible exception.
“A top-notch chief executive makes many decisions that can cost or save taxpayers much more money than his salary,” said Sean Harafin, interim president of the taxpayers association. “It’s a frustrating reality because most people aren’t getting this kind of compensation, but taxpayers benefit from effective leadership. I would look to San Diego to see what happened last year when they had a bad chief executive.”
In Carlsbad, Sarkozy will oversee 700 employees and a $110 million annual budget.
Mayor Hall said Sarkozy’s salary and benefits are appropriate based on his track record of meeting goals in his previous three stints as a city manager in Bellevue — Seattle’s largest suburb — and smaller cities in Minnesota and upstate New York.
“When you want someone great to come and run your city and make it world-class, you have to pay top dollar,” Hall said.
In Carlsbad, Sarkozy will be eligible for a pension based on how many years he works for the city. His annual pension payment will be 2 percent of his compensation multiplied by his years of service.
Sarkozy won’t receive pensions from Minnesota or New York because he’s already taken payouts from those states. He will begin receiving an annual pension of roughly $55,000 a year from Washington when he turns 65, a state official said this week.
Hall acknowledged Friday that the money Carlsbad is paying to move and house Sarkozy was unusual. But he noted that most city managers in California don’t receive such compensation because they are promoted from within or hired away from another city inside the state.
“If it was somebody within the state of California, I never would have approved it,” Hall said. “But he and his family have to move here from Washington.”
Dave Morgan of Ralph Andersen & Associates, the recruiter who helped find Sarkozy, said Friday that the increased competition is based partly on many top managers retiring in recent years along with the rest of the baby boomer generation.
“There really is a small group of the highest qualified candidates,” he said.
Hall said Carlsbad wouldn’t be spending so much on Sarkozy if the City Council wasn’t extremely confident. He noted that Sarkozy’s interview process included meetings with Walt Ekard, the county’s longtime chief executive who retired in 2012, and Ray Patchett, Carlsbad’s city manager from 1987 to 2007.
“Steve stood out way above any of the other applicants,” the mayor said.
]]></text></news-item>