<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1D69-6FEA-53CA-BA5B"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Community</title><source>Charlotte Observer (North Carolina)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Economics lecture: Alexander Field, the Orradre Professor of Economics at Santa Clara University and former executive director of the Economic History Association, will give the annual Phi Beta Kappa lecture 8 p.m. March 20 in Tyler-Tallman Hall of Sloan Music Center.
Field will speak about “The Interwar Housing Cycle, the S&L Insolvencies and the Real Estate Bubble of the 2000s: Implications for Crisis and Recovery.”
Admission is free. For information, call 704-894-3130.
Davidson Friends meet: Davidson Friends Meeting will host a question-and-answer session 11:15 a.m.-12:15 p.m. March 23 at the Quaker meetinghouse, 625 South St., Davidson.
The public is invited to learn about Quakers, Quakerism and Davidson Friends Meeting, part of the Religious Society of Friends.
For information, email DavidsonQuaker@yahoo.com or visit http://davidson.quaker.org .
Holocaust scholar: Davidson College and UNC Charlotte will host the 2014 Southeast German Studies Workshop March 27-28.
Preeminent Holocaust scholar Omer Bartov will give the keynote lecture and participate in panel discussions. Bartov, a professor of European History and History and German Studies at Brown University, will speak about “The Voice of Your Brother’s Blood: The Holocaust as Communal Genocide” at 4:30 p.m. March 27 at the UNC Charlotte Center City campus auditorium. A reception will follow at 6:30 p.m.
Bartov attended Tel Aviv University and Oxford University and was a Junior Harvard Fellow and the 2002 Guggenheim Fellow. He has published seven books and three edited volumes.
Panel discussions will be held at 1:30 p.m. March 27 and 8:30 a.m. and 11 a.m. March 28, all in the Alvarez College Union Smith 900 Room at Davidson College.
For more information, visit http://sites.davidson.edu/german/2014segsw/ .
Christian lecture: The Rev. John Philip Newell, a poet, scholar and teacher, will deliver the annual Staley Distinguished Christian Lecture at 7:30 p.m. March 31 in the 900 Room of the Alvarez College Union at Davidson College. Admission is free.
Newell will speak about “The Light at the Center of Every Cell: Toward a Christian Vision of Earth’s Wellbeing.” An ordained Church of Scotland minister, Newell is internationally acclaimed for his work in the field of Celtic spirituality. His most recent book releases are “A New Harmony” and “Praying with the Earth.”
For more information, contact Davidson College Chaplain Rob Spach at 704-894-2423 or rospach@davidson.edu .
Soccer for special needs: Cornelius PARC will offer TOP Soccer for boys and girls ages 5-16 who have a mental or physical disability. Games are 9-10 a.m. Saturdays, April 26-May 31 at Richard Barry Memorial Park in Huntersville. The soccer is league is free for residents, $40 for others.
For information, call 704-892-6031 or visit www.cornelius.org/parc .
Shrine Club bass tournament: The Lake Norman Shrine Club will sponsor its 35th Annual Dogwood Bass Tournament 7 a.m.- p.m. April 5 at Midway Marina, 8693 N.C. 150, Terrell.
Pre-registration will be held noon to 7 p.m. April 4 at the marina.
Cash payouts range from $2,500 for first place, based on 100 boats, to $100 for 10th place.
For registration forms or information, contact William Cork at wbcork@yahoo.com or 704-516-0506.
Medical
Volunteer chaplain: Edward Ramsey, youth minister at Central United Methodist Church in Mooresville, is the newest Volunteer Chaplain to join Lake Norman Regional Medical Center’s Pastoral Advisory Council.
A graduate of South Iredell High School and Pfeiffer University, Ramsey grew up in Troutman. He also is a member of the Board of Directors with Carolina Cross Connection and the Western North Carolina Conference Christian Educators Fellowship.
Look Good, Feel Better: Female cancer patients are invited to participate in the American Cancer Society’s “Look Good Feel Better” program 6:15-8:15 p.m. March 17 in the private dining room at Lake Norman Regional Medical Center. A free dinner is included.
Volunteer cosmetologists will help patients learn how to use makeup and skincare techniques to overcome the appearance-related effects of chemotherapy and radiation.
For information, contact Cathy Quade at 704-662-0770.
Acid reflux treatment: Dr. Peyton Davis will present “No Heartburn. No Pills. No Scars. Treatment for Acid Reflux Disease” at 6 p.m. March 18 in Community Room B at Lake Norman Regional Medical Center.
Davis is the first surgeon in North Carolina certified to conduct Transoral Incisionless Fundoplication (TIF). He will discuss the procedure’s effectiveness and benefits. A question-and-answer session will follow.
For information, call 888-995-6762.
Diabetes support group: The Diabetes Support Group will meet noon to 1 p.m. March 24 in the Burlington Room at the Charles Mack Citizens Center in Mooresville. The free program provides education and support for those living with Type 2 diabetes and their families.
Registration is not required. For information, contact Mitzie McCurdy at 704-660-4859 or mitzie.mccurdy@hma.com .
Healthcare showcase and symposium: The Mooresville/South Iredell Chamber of Commerce and The Leading Edge HealthCare Leads Group will present the “Live the Good Life” healthcare showcase 10 a.m. to 3 p.m. March 26 at the Charles Mack Citizen Center, 215 N. Main St. in Mooresville.
More than 50 healthcare organizations will provide information and free screenings. The annual event draws more than 500 participants. Admission is free, and the healthcare showcase is open to the public.
A community blood drive will be held 10 a.m.-1 p.m. in the Lowrance Room. To make an appointment, visit www.carolinadonor.org .
The Novant Health Breast Center Mobile Unit will offer mammograms 10 a.m.-2 p.m. Call 704-385-7226 for details.
Unused and unwanted prescription drugs may be safely discarded 10 a.m.-3 p.m. For information, visit www.projectlazarus.org .
For information on Live the Good Life, call the chamber at 704-664-3898.
Colorectal cancer seminar: Lake Norman Regional Medical Center will host a free colorectal cancer awareness seminar on “Detection, Screenings, Diagnosis and Treatment Options” at 6 p.m. March 27 in Community Room B.
Dr. John Clements, a gastroenterologist, will present the latest information on colorectal cancer and answer questions.
For more information or to make a reservation, call 888-995-6762.
Stroke screening: Lake Norman Regional Medical Center and Life Line Screening will offer affordable, convenient medical screenings March 28 at the South Iredell Senior Center in Mooresville.
A painless ultrasound will check for plaque build-up in arteries, a leading cause of stroke. Cost is $60.
To register, call 877-237-1383 or visit www.LifeLineScreening.com/community-partners .
Compiled by Leigh Pressley
]]></text></news-item>