<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1D95-C5E1-95E4-173C"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Chrysler boss standing firm; Few details offered on Windsor investments</title><source>Windsor Star (Ontario)</source><author>Grace MacAluso, The Windsor Star</author><text><![CDATA[Citing months of unsatisfactory negotiations with Ottawa and Queen's Park, Chrysler Canada CEO Sergio Marchionne said Friday he was not interested in restarting talks aimed at securing government assistance for a multibilliondollar investment at the automaker's plants in Windsor and Brampton.
"Fiat-Chrysler is no longer interested in the package," Marchionne told reporters following the launch of the Chrysler 200 sedan at the carmaker's plant in Sterling Heights, Mich. "It's over."
Marchionne disclosed for the first time that discussions with Ottawa and Ontario started nine months ago. "We found the process lengthy and we found the outcome unsatisfactory for our needs," he said.
Both the federal and Ontario governments said they were leaving the door open to Chrysler after Marchionne abruptly withdrew his request for financial assistance March 4, in part because it had become a "political football" in a growing controversy over government subsidies for automotive investment. But the CEO said "that chapter was closed."
He also came out swinging at Ontario politicians and political pundits who called Chrysler's request "extortion, ransom" and "corporate welfare."
"What I found fundamentally distasteful is the fact this issue, which involves the investment by a private organization in the country, treated as a political matter in what potentially would be an election campaign, and the designation of the support mechanism which is available globally to everybody who invests in the car business today is referred to as a handout. A handout is not what Chrysler wants.
"Chrysler," he continued, "is not in the business of accepting handouts. And if provincial and federal authorities in Canada think that's the way to attract foreign investment, I think they are in for a big shock."
While Marchionne said development of the next-generation minivan would cost about $2 billion - $1 billion for the platform, $1 billion for retooling, he offered few details on the size of the investment earmarked for Windsor Assembly.
"The only thing we've said is that we would invest in the new minivan architecture and that investment is continuing."
The next-generation minivan should be on the market by 2016, he said, adding that the new platform would be capable of building more than one type of vehicle.
"The decision to move in Windsor was made for a variety of reasons, including the fact that we ran out of time," he said.
"There's a point in the cycle of the architecture when you've got to make the call and replace it because the runway was finished and the noise surrounding this announcement became so distasteful that Fiat decided to go it alone."
But, Chrysler's Windsor and Brampton plants would have to be competitive if they hope to have a long-term future, he said.
"I will make a long-term commitment to every factory that continues to demonstrate
the desire to remain competitive internationally on a global scale.
"I made it clear in my letter that I sent back to the prime minister of Canada and premier of Ontario that our continued commitment to invest in Canada remains contingent, as it does here and in other parts of the world, on remaining competitive. That is a function of a variety of factors. It's not contingent on what has been called a handout. Chrysler is not in the business of receiving handouts."
Marchionne also took exception to reports that the carmaker's request was at least $700 million. "That number is so far out of reach, that we were talking about different worlds."
He would not reveal Chrysler's request because "Fiat-Chrysler is no longer interested in the package."
It was time, he said, for Chrysler to move on for the benefit of the car company and its Windsor workforce.
"It has an obligation to the people who work in Windsor to make sure that we move the agenda forward," Marchionne said.
"I've closed the chapter. And one of the things I've learned ... you never make the same decisions twice."
gmacaluso@windsorstar.com
]]></text></news-item>