<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1DA7-096D-3606-5B6B"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Seismic shock about to hit the workplace; Workshop Wayne Smith, a director and solicitor with Nottingham firm of specialist employment solicitors Integra Legal Limited, highlights changes to the law which employers need to be aware of</title><source>Nottingham Evening Post</source><author>Wayne Smith</author><text><![CDATA[SPRING is a busy time of year for employment lawyers and a number of significant changes to the law have been made or are about to be made. Wayne Smith highlights some which employers need to be aware of.
¦ Mandatory early conciliation in employment tribunal claims: This has been described as a huge change in the landscape by the chief executive of Acas, the Government's Advisory, Conciliation and Arbitration Service. The head of the Employment Lawyer's Association says the changes are "seismic".
Acas has always had a duty to help the parties to an employment tribunal claim to settle their differences and reach agreement. There will be a new duty on Acas, employers and employees to attempt conciliation before a claim is submitted.
In most cases started from May 6 an employee (or ex-employee) will not be able to commence a claim without a certificate from Acas to confirm conciliation has been attempted, and the time limit for bringing claims will be put on hold for up to a month while early conciliation occurs. Employers who have initial contact from an Acas conciliator should consider quickly whether they want to offer a financial settlement to avoid the cost and business disruption of defending tribunal proceedings. ¦ Financial penalties for employers: From April 6, employment tribunals will have the power to fine an employer up to £5,000 (payable to the Government) if they lose their case in the employment tribunal and there are one or more "aggravating features".
It's not clear yet what is meant by "aggravating features", but employers should act reasonably when dealing with employees. ¦ Discrimination questionnaires abolished: Potential claimants in discrimination claims can currently send their employer a questionnaire aimed to gather evidence of whether unlawful discrimination has occurred.
A tribunal can subsequently draw adverse inferences from a failure to answer questions properly. For acts of discrimination occurring on or after April 6, this procedure, set out in the Equality Act 2010, will be abolished.
This will be replaced by Acas guidance on asking and responding to questions of discrimination in the workplace.
A tribunal will no longer be able to draw adverse inferences from a failure to answer questions properly, although Acas has suggested that the tribunal may treat a failure to answer as a "contributory factor" when deciding whether discrimination has taken place. ¦ Flexible working: Currently only parents and certain classes of employee have a legal right to have a request to work flexibly considered. Usually flexible working requests involve the employee wanting to work on a part-time basis, or to work from home.
From the end of June the law is expected to change so that all employees will have the right to request flexible working, whether or not they are carers and regardless of the reason.
Employers will have a duty to consider requests reasonably and within a reasonable timeframe.
Employers should consider putting in place a policy and flexible working and procedure for dealing with these requests when they come.
Keep updated at www.nottinghampost.com/business
]]></text></news-item>