<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1DD7-D8C8-A779-3813"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>New global goals must tackle traditional beliefs that 'undermine women's rights'</title><source>guardian.co.uk</source><author>Liz Fordtheguardian.com</author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
The laws, traditional beliefs and practices that undermine women's rights must be tackled in the next set of development goals through the inclusion of indicators that measure whether attitudes are changing and women are becoming more empowered, a meeting at the UN was told on Thursday.
At a side event during the Commission on the Status of Women conference in New York, the Overseas Development Institute (ODI) and the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) outlined a set of six targets and indicators against which a greater understanding of the root causes of women's disempowerment could be achieved.
The targets would sit under a standalone goal on gender equality and women's empowerment, which women's rights activists have been campaigning to see mentioned in the outcome document of the CSW and included in the future sustainable development goals (SDGs). The targets would also be mainstreamed through all the other goals.
"Social norms ... drive discrimination and disempowerment," said Hanna Alder, programme manager at the ODI, but there is a reluctance to tackle them because they are considered unmeasurable and too complex.
But a report, Measuring women's empowerment and social transformation in the post-2015 agenda, published by the ODI and the OECD to coincide with the panel event, suggests the identified target areas and indicators could be measured using data already collected in at least 80 countries, through demographic, health and household surveys.
The six areas relate to women and girls' sexual and reproductive rights, violence, decision-making, participation in public life, the equal distribution of unpaid care work, and equality between girls and boys.
Suggested indicators to assess progress under these six targets include the age a woman gets married, the percentage of men who justify domestic violence under certain circumstances, and the average time women and men spend on household chores.
The ODI and OECD believes these indicators would offer a clearer understanding of persistent areas of discrimination. They argue that if progress towards ending domestic violence, for example, is measured by legislation outlawing the practice, along with data examining men's and women's attitudes towards violence, politicians would get a more rounded picture of where resistance to change still exists, enabling them to better target policies.
Ultimately, said the report, this should bring long-term transformative change for women, which was not achieved under the millennium development goals (MDGs). The MDGs have been credited for galvanising international action to address poverty, and improve health and education, but they have also been criticised for the limited impact they had on achieving gender equality and their failure to bring change for women.
"The MDG experience shows us that failing to use indicators that illustrate social transformation has limited progress towards gender equality. At this moment, we have a golden opportunity to build a post-2015 framework that produces sustainable human-rights based social transformation for girls and women," says the report.
"The MDGs focused donors' interest, so it is critical we get it right this time," Caroline Harper, head of programme for social development at the ODI, told the meeting. "Changes need to be empowering. You don't give power to someone, you have to be able to claim and shape it for yourself. But what is given is the space ... and freedom to do so."
Justine Greening, Britain's international development secretary, said a holistic approach was needed "if we are ever to really see progress" on women's rights. She told the event that change did not happen overnight. "We need to be prepared to stick with it for the long-term," said Greening.
She announced that a July summit in the UK would propose a package of policies to tackle two social norms that Britain is particularly focused on ending: female genital mutilation and child marriage.
The ODI/OECD report calls on the international community and national governments to invest in stronger statistical data collection systems to measure the SDGs, which will replace the MDGs when they expire in 2015.
The report points to the OECD's social institutions and gender index, launched in 2009 to measure the underlying drivers of gender inequality in more than 100 countries, and the World Value Surveys, a global network of social scientists who study the impact of changing values on social and political life, as evidence that data collection is much more sophisticated than it was when the MDGs were launched. As a result, said the study's authors, it is now possible to capture information on the impact of social norms on development.
The report argued that the inclusion of its six recommended measurement areas and indicators in the post-2015 framework would send a robust message to the international community, governments and national statistical offices to invest in statistical systems to improve existing data collection and include new indicators on social norms and gender equality. "Only then can we hope to achieve the kind of lasting transformative change that will catalyse real and long lasting empowerment for girls and women," said the authors.
]]></text></news-item>