<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1E8D-7EF2-A211-1C27"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>EXPOSED: CRECHES THAT LET CHILDREN SIMPLY WANDER OFF; How, even AFTER the Prime Time exposé, childcare workers allowed at least three youngsters to slip out alone... without being noticed More disturbing childcare claims A child's hair was pulled... and it is alleged toddlers were left in soiled nappies and babies were force-fed</title><source>Irish Daily Mail</source><author>Jennifer Bray</author><text><![CDATA[CHILDREN were allowed wander off alone from creches or were left unattended outside, in at least three separate incidents, according to shocking new HSE reports.
The new information shows that, less than a year after Prime Time's creche exposé, youngsters are still not being properly cared for in facilities across the State.
The latest revelations about children escaping creches unnoticed will be deeply alarming for parents in the wake of recent child abduction cases.
The HSE reports also document other findings of mistreatment or abuse.
A child's hair was pulled in Coco's creche in Booterstown, south Dublin, and in other facilities toddlers were allowed to wander outside the creche unsupervised.
A number of allegations of physical abuse against a worker at another creche was referred to social workers for further investigation.
There are also allegations in the complaints made to the HSE of the force-feeding of babies as well as refusals by staff to change dirty nappies or contact parents when illness was suspected among children.
One complaint alleged that two children were allowed to frequently wander away from the facility, and on some occasions managed to get into the fridges in its kitchen.
A stark claim relating to the same creche is that its manager was 'heavily medicated' and appeared 'out of it' while working with babies.
Many of the complaints are still being investigated and have been referred on to social workers for further investigation. However, shockingly, a number of serious complaints have been upheld.
In relation to the Booterstown creche, an FoI request released by the HSE to the Mail, states: 'Staff member pulled a child's hair. A lot of tension between staff and parents.' A full inspection was completed and the complaint was 'founded', according to the HSE. When contacted, the creche said it did not want to comment 'at the moment'.
In another creche - Firhouse Montessori, also in Dublin - the HSE found that a 'child left pre-school unnoticed by staff and was found alone in the estate'.
A review of security within the premises later took place. There was no response to queries made by the Mail from this facility either at the time of print. At the Gracelands creche in Portlaoise, the HSE revealed that a 'child [was] left unattended outside service for approximately ten minutes and staff [were] unaware of his absence.'
According to the HSE, it was alleged that there was also a 'delay in notifying parents of [the] incident' and that 'no record of the incident [was] shown to parents until [the] following week.'
The complaint was upheld and a follow-up inspection was due to take place in January of this www.year.No further information was given, and a worker at the creche told the Mail that the manager could not respond to queries as they were 'out of town'.
In relation to another upheld complaint, the HSE states that a parent of a child at Kidzstuff creche in Celbridge, Co. Kildare, 'arrived couple of minutes late to pick child up (four years old) on Tuesday'. The mother said she found her child was outside with another parent who was not authorised to pick the child up.
The documents also detail a number of complaints made against the Links creche in Abington, north Dublin, which was previously at the centre of the Prime Time exposé.
Those five complaints which were lodged in the months after the programme had aired have all been referred to a specific Social Work Department, according to the HSE.
Another complaint to the HSE in relation to the Donard Glen Day-care centre stated: 'When the child was in the service roughly about a year, it came to parents' attention that people were taking photographs of child on their personal camera phones and distributing them outside the creche without parents' permission.'
Of this complaint, the HSE noted: 'Complaint founded. If photographs are taken of children attending the service, parental consent must be obtained. The use of personal equipment for this purpose is not permitted.'
A spokesman for the creche told the Irish Daily Mail: 'This was something which happened three years ago. This was, in fact, a very minor incident. It was in relation to one child only and was resolved. If you go by the letter of the law, yes there was a breach, and we have no problem saying that but this was actually a very minor incident.'
Further, and often more serious cases, are either still under investigation by the HSE or are being investigated by social workers. While some complaints were upheld, some were not and others are either still under investigation or were serious enough to warrant a further investigation from social workers or child protection officers.
In another creche, it was alleged in the HSE information that there was a 'complaint from former employee RE two preschool-aged children managing to get out of the creche and who were found wandering around the green area in the estate'.
'The children got out through the back door in the kitchen which was left open. It was reported the same two children were often seen in the creche kitchen and in the fridges.'
In one creche currently under investigation, ten specific allegations were viewed as serious enough to be referred to a child protection department. Other allegations include: 'A general lack of care of the children's welfare and viewing them only in terms of monetary gain; forbidden to ring parents when illness suspected/ injury occurring to children; withholding information from parents about their children.'
The allegations also state that nappies weren't changed, broken toys were not discarded, children were made to sleep in a cold cot room and the children were put in their cots for lengthy periods outside routine nap times because they were 'too noisy - and were left to cry in their cots'.
In the same creche, it was alleged, according to the HSE data, babies under one year were force-fed; that food was not given on several occasions; that cold dinners were given at inappropriate times; that there were fears of cross-contamination and also that the 'employer [was] heavily medicated while working with babies and often "out of it".' The information obtained by the Irish Daily Mail applies to all complaints made for the latter half of last year. We previously revealed the shocking content of the complaints for the first half of the year.
Those complaints detailed how, at one creche, a mother wrote to complain that she was distressed after finding her child 'freezing' at the back of a creche in a bloody jumper.
In another complaint, from May 31 last, it was alleged a knife fell on to a child's hand and 'sliced' into it and that there was 'no heating'.
The complainant also claimed staff were 'told to put extra socks on the babies and get them moving' instead. In another complaint, the HSE documents allegations that a mother ran crying from a facility after seeing footage of her child being forced to clean up litter from the ground.
Comment - Page 14 jennifer.bray@dailymail.ie
HSE has greater powers
WHILE the HSE's pre-school inspectors have always had the power to raise issues with creches in their inspection reports, changes have seen their enforcement powers increased.
Inspectors can now raise issues in reports and request that they are followed up on. But previously creches could only be prosecuted for serious breaches of childcare regulations.
Many breaches were in the mid to low range. However new measures announced last year gave pre-school inspectors the power to issue statutory notices and orders to creches and other facilities found to be in breach of standards.
Facilities which repeatedly fail to comply with orders will face closure. The legislation also increased fines for non-compliance available to district courts from around (EURO)1,270 to (EURO)5,000.
FIVE SHOCKING EXAMPLES
'Forbidden to ring parents if child was injured'
1. In one creche currently under investigation, ten specific allegations were viewed as serious enough to be referred to a child protection department.
These include, according to a HSE summary of the complaint, 'a general lack of care of the children's welfare and viewing them only in terms of monetary gain; forbidden to ring parents when illness suspected/injury occurring to children; withholding information from parents about their children.'
The allegations also say nappies weren't changed, children were made to sleep in a cold cot room and the children were put in their cots for lengthy periods.
In the same creche, it was alleged, according to the HSE information, that babies under one year were force-fed; food was not given on several occasions; cold dinners were given at inappropriate times. The report also said that there were fears of cross-contamination and also that the 'employer [was] heavily medicated while working with babies and often "out of it".'
Two pre-schoolers 'wandered out to green area'
2. In one creche in the mid-Leinster region, an ex-employee lodged a complaint with the HSE, according to the documents, to state that two children were let wander off the premises.
The summary of the complaint reads: 'Complaint from former employee RE two preschool-aged children managing to get out of the creche and who were found wandering around the green area in the estate. The children got out through the back door in the kitchen which was left open. It was reported that the same two children were often seen in the creche kitchen and in the fridges'.
'Physical abuse' reported in one childcare centre
3. In one creche, an allegation of physical abuse has been made.
According to the HSE information, it reads: 'Poor practice - wet or soiled nappies, food diary, visits to creche & physical abuse.' The HSE states: 'The personal records of the child were not available, hence the alleged failure to change the child's nappy and record a food diary could not be investigated. The allegation of physical abuse was referred to the Social Work Department.'
'Shouting and behaving in unprofessional manner'
4. Another complaint about staff misconduct in the southern region of the country has also been referred to social workers.
The shocking Health Services Executive documents state: 'Complaint about a number of incidents, including one staff member shouting and behaving in an unprofessional manner.'
According to the HSE: 'This complaint remains under investigation and is not yet completed. Referral to Social Work Department.'
Staff member 'pulled a child's hair'
5. According to the HSE, one creche, Coco's in Booterstown, was the subject of a complaint about a staff member pulling the hair of a child. According to an Freedom of Information request released by the HSE, it states: 'Staff member pulled a child's hair. A lot of tension between staff and parents.'
A full inspection was completed and the complaint was founded, according to the HSE. When contacted, the creche said it did not want to comment 'at the moment'.
'Heavily medicated and out of it'
'Got out through the back door'
]]></text></news-item>