<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1F25-2B64-4230-2228"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Business of Sport</title><source>Sunday Business Post</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A handful of years back, a friend who was fanatical about his local League of Ireland club was struggling to come to terms with their demise. Having cheered them on across country and continent, he decided to act as they reached a precipice following a dangerous financial gamble. So he donated his life savings and began fundraising to the point where he played a major role in their rescue. His reward was a place on the board. Only it didn't last long. After just months, and despite his previous efforts, he left in frustration because he felt the same people were making the same crazy mistakes all over again, and refused to listen to sense or to the past.
It's a story that always comes to mind when the new league season kicks off, but there are many other tales out there too.
Pat Fenlon recalled his time at Shelbourne and how he was in the dressing room, a month since staff had been paid, when the late chief executive Ollie Byrne strode onto the scene. ''There you go lad, chirped Byrne, handing over a rucksack. ''Twenty fucking grand. That'll sort the lads out for a week or two. But there's one problem -- it's in sterling.
Another day he was shouting, ''It's fucked, Pat, we've no fucking money, when Byrne's mobile suddenly rang and his humour changed. ''Yes, Sir Alex, how are you? Manchester United were looking for a friendly.
Thankfully the gambles and recklessness have to an extent gone away. No more are the days when many Drogheda players were on between EUR 1,200 and EUR 1,500 a week, when St Patrick's Athletic were paying one player more than EUR 3,000 and when Joe Gamble was on enough in Cork to turn down a substantial six-figure salary offered by the Inchicore side. Indeed before the return of Stephen McPhail and Keith Fahey recently, it's believed there was no one on more than EUR 1,000. While some of the arrogance has been drained from inside the domestic game, the indifference remains on the outside when you ask most Irish people that are passionate about soccer.
Among all the others, that's the biggest issue right now. The reduction in ridicule here hasn't resulted in an increase in interest.
And in some ways you can feel sorry for those trying to grow the league because there are several key factors outside their control.
Firstly, we're one of the only European countries where it's not the main sport. Secondly, the league next door has become the world's most powerful at a time when travel has never been cheaper and media saturation has never been greater. Thirdly, Gaelic games have a monopoly on local identity. And fourthly, there aren't enough decent-sized soccer towns like Dundalk and Sligo that can support a successful side.
However, it's time people faced up to this rather than complained about it. The League of Ireland is a niche market and it needs to understand what can work within its limited parameters in order to maximise its limited potential. Delusions of even relative mediocrity have to go.
In the English Championship for example, smaller clubs have turnovers of around £10 million, bigger clubs bring in three times that, while those here at home still rely mostly on gate receipts. There isn't even a whole lot of those.
The average attendance in England's second tier last season was 17,495, in the third tier it was 13,288, in the fourth tier it was 4,509. Those numbers were on top of a three-year TV deal worth £195 million.
In Ireland, top flight attendances average 1,600, while in the First Division they drop to 370. Clearly ours is a league that cannot compete and has to offer something different if it's to survive. It's a very basic business principle that's for too long been ignored.
The truth is, those attendances are more in keeping with the English Conference, and Irish clubs need to study the successes and failures of that model. They need to consider too the prize money available because Premier Division clubs here will compete for EUR 241,500 this year (that was EUR 700,000 as recently as 2010), while EUR 74,000 is at stake in the First Division. That our leading football clubs cannot win more than a Rehab executive earned might seem wrong, but it's the harsh reality. This is simply the market value of the League of Ireland right now.
Perhaps it's all that which leads to the insecurity exuded by many who follow a league that had as its motto until last season, Real football, real fans'. It insinuated that following soccer abroad lessened your link to the game, but you can't force people to like what you like. Rather than sneer and moan, you've to try and give them reasons to change.
Besides, while the wages, investment and standards may have dropped over the last five years, ironically that has brought some opportunities. The spread of players has helped success become less Dublin-centric: sides have been forced to go with youth, which lessens turnover of players and creates greater continuity and local links. Clubs have been forced to set up under-19 teams. Meanwhile, all that has led to a chance for a return to basics and the creation of slow, sensible, organic growth.
The fact remains, the League of Ireland cannot break into areas where locals have no affinity with a team. On top of that, our sporting culture and history limits what can ever be achieved.
But while those who follow the league need to stop pretending it's something it's not, those running the league need to realise what it can never be. Only then will it improve at its own level, and even the greatest cynics can ask for no more than that.
]]></text></news-item>