<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="1F6A-E37B-24B8-AECE"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: McConnell to Pay $125,000 for Illegal Handling</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Rick Kornak, writing for Mesothelioma.com, reported that McConnellEnterprises, Inc., an Essex, England-based demolition company,will pay up to $125,000 in civil penalties for the illegalhandling of asbestos. According to the Attorney General, thepayment amount breaks down to $82,500 in penalties to thecommonwealth and an additional $42,500 in penalties if McConnellfails to conform to waste regulations over the next 18 months. During a demolition project in 2011, workers for the companyallegedly discovered piping wrapped with asbestos insulation.McConnell is a state-licensed asbestos removal contractor;however, rather than follow proper procedure, the company left thehazardous material in an area where it could potentially beinhaled by anyone in the vicinity. As a state-licensed asbestos contractor, failing to follow thelaws is especially inexcusable. "Licensed asbestos contractors arefully aware of the removal, handling, packaging and storagerequirements that must be followed when dealing with asbestos-containing materials and of the requirement to providenotification to MassDEP in advance of this work," saidMassachusetts Department of Environmental Protection (MassDEP)Commissioner Kenneth Kimmell. By neglecting to follow propernotification procedure, McConnell was able to keep MassDEP fromfinding out about the company's unlawful activities. Although the laws regarding safe asbestos handling areparticularly stringent, it's important for them to be followed tohelp minimize the risk of inhaling harmful asbestos fibers, whichcan lead to a variety of respiratory problems, includingmesothelioma and numerous other types of cancer. "Companiesworking with asbestos-containing materials must be held to thehighest standards of care as ordered under our state air laws andregulations," said State Attorney General Martha Coakley. "Ouroffice takes the mishandling of asbestos very seriously because ofthe health effects."
]]></text></news-item>