<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2029-5B3D-3A10-4B51"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>A House built on scandal; Weekend Books Edited by Caroline Jowett www.express.co.uk/books</title><source>The Express</source><author>LEO MCKINSTRY</author><text><![CDATA[PARLIAMENT: THE BIOGRAPHY ***** by CHRIS BRYANT
Doubleday, £20 (RRP £25)
CONVENTIONAL wisdom holds that our Parliamentary system, once a source of inspiration to the rest of the world, has never been so degraded or self-serving as it is today. This image of decline has been fuelled not only by the recent expenses furore but also by individual scandals such as the jailing of former Cabinet minister Chris Huhne for perverting the course of justice.
Yet as Labour MP Chris Bryant reveals in this magnificent book the modern narrative of institutional decay is wrong. The conduct of other Parliaments and MPs in the past was often far worse. The levels of venality, corruption and debasement regularly exceeded anything that is perpetrated today.
One MP in the 1800s effectively bought his seat in Wales by treating his electorate to 11,070 breakfasts, 36,901 dinners and 25,275 gallons of ale. Another MP was such an alcoholic that he reputedly drank five bottles of port every morning "and when that ran out supplemented it with eau de cologne". Nor is there anything new about dubious lobbying. In the 1430s, for instance, the Brewers' Company of London paid the chancellor the "whopping" sum of £40 to drive forward their campaign for a new charter.
Some might complain about rowdy behaviour at Prime Minister's Questions but such conduct is nothing compared with the climate of savage discord that enveloped Parliament right up until the 18th century.
Indeed much of Bryant's book amounts to a catalogue of political violence and brutality in the relentless power struggles that once gripped Britain.
One of the darkest episodes was the so-called Merciless Parliament of 1388, which acquired its nickname for its "blood-curdling purge" against the court of the young King Richard II.
Large numbers of ministers, clerks and courtiers associated with the regime were executed after show trials in Parliament. Some were left to the mercy of the London mob.
After his Parliamentary conviction the lord chief justice Robert Tresilian was dragged from his place of sanctuary, stripped naked, had his throat slit and was then hanged.
Although Bryant is something of a myth buster the central theme of his book is classic: the long-running battle for political supremacy between Parliament and the Court.
This fight went back to the 13th century when the first assemblies began to act as a check on royal prerogative, even Henry VIII had to take account of Parliamentary opinion. Westminster's growth in importance was accompanied by its increasingly representative nature through the gradual establishment of elections and the codification of the franchise.
The long-running duel between the monarch and Parliament reached its climax in the civil war and Bryant provides a powerful account of the crucial moment in 1642 when speaker Lenthall refused to recognise the authority of Charles I, who had burst in to the chamber to arrest five "disruptive" members.
It was the last moment in Britain that a royal set foot in the Commons and the country was soon engulfed by conflict.
IRONICALLY Cromwell, once the champion of Parliament, came to loathe the institution as much as Charles I, turning himself into a dictator.
After his departure Westminster dominated the political landscape, deposing James II in 1688 and forcing through Acts of Union with the Scottish and Irish Parliaments.
As Bryant shows it is another myth that Scottish MPs were bribed to accept unification in 1707, although the Irish certainly were in 1801.
This is the first volume of a two-part history, taking the saga up to the beginning of the 19th century.
Bryant is a fine historian. His understanding of political processes shines through.
After this epic the next volume will be eagerly awaited.
LEO MCKINSTRY
]]></text></news-item>