<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2051-AF23-3F29-B925"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Clothing with a conscience; Designers bringing ethically produced lines to Toronto</title><source>The Toronto Star</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Designer Laura Siegel wants to make a different kind of style statement when she shows her work March 18, the second day of the Toronto's World MasterCard Fashion Week's fall-winter shows, at David Pecaut Square.
She's not alone in putting the emphasis on ethically handcrafted fashion created by fairly compensated artisans in Asia, India, Africa and Latin America. And she believes it's what consumers want.
"I want it to be. I'd like that to happen," said Siegel, 26, of the growing popularity of clothing with a conscience.
"I think there's definitely a shift toward that.
"People are definitely a lot smarter. Shoppers are smart today," said Siegel, a graduate of Parsons School for Design in New York, who splits her time between Manhattan and Toronto.
She spoke to the Star recently while showing her designs featuring elaborate dyeing and block printing, quilted silk and hand-knitted suede at the Woman New York fashion and design trade show held in a Greenwich Village industrial space.
"You see that even reflected in the retail stores opening in the retail landscape; eCommerce stores, focusing on socially responsible sections," Siegel said.
"Holt Renfrew opening up H-Project, I think spoke words to where the market is today."
In addition to carrying Siegel's clothing, Holt Renfrew is selling scarves created through her new fundraising initiative for the families of victims of the Rana Plaza collapse in Bangladesh in April 2013. Siegel's Project Eleven27 channels the proceeds from one-of-a-kind scarves handwoven from a silk-cotton blend and recycled saris from women in rural areas of Bangladesh to Sreepur Village Organization.
As part of her business model, Siegel works with local organizations in various countries that manage production.
The goal is not only bringing fair wages and economic education to garment workers and artisans but also reviving lost crafts.
"There's plenty of work, but mostly the women who are getting to practice their craft aren't making hardly any money," she said.
"They make 10 per cent of what the goods cost at the end of the day."
"When we work with them, they make 50 per cent and then the organization keeps 50 per cent and they use it in a really wise way ... they use the rest of their funds to hold (financial management) workshops for these women and they're reviving crafts."
Kumala Nio, owner of shop-café-studio Room 2046 on Yonge St. north of Summerhill Ave., dropped by Siegel's display at the New York show and said she plans to order some of her designs for her store.
"I'm always on the lookout for young talent and local designers," she said. "I feel the pieces and design are strong and unique. It's what I want to have on the shop's roster ...
We're drawn to products that have been tended to from the beginning."
The idea of ethical clothing appeals to her and some of her clients, but not all.
"The cost increases and sometimes people are more reluctant to spend money on certain products that they may be able to get somewhere else," said Nio.
Ethically produced, organic and sustainable clothing doesn't have to come from offshore sources. French-born Cecile Raizonville's co-operative designs for Montreal-based Matière Noire are produced by nearby Quebec artisans.
"It's really important. We try to do everything locally," said Raizonville, who became involved in the movement while working for eco-friendly brand Bodkin in New York. She moved to Montreal in 2012.
"The idea is I find my fabric and bring everything from Montreal. We work with artisans and weavers in Quebec. I think it is a better way to do business," she said.
Her fall/winter 2014 collection includes pieces influenced by Inuit design and others created by a Quebec weaver.
While it can be more expensive to produce sustainably, it doesn't have to be a deal-killer for designers, Raizonville said. She keeps costs down by selling much of her clothing online.
"There is not so much difference in price; you can mix fabrics between cotton and polyester," she said. While they may not get the volume discounts offered in Asia, "we can control the quality," with local manufacturers.
Matière Noire and Edmonton designer Malorie Urbanovitch shared the title of Awarded Designer in the Mercedes-Benz Start Up 2013 program at Toronto Fashion Week in October 2013.
The two designs return to fashion week March 18 at 7 p.m., each with 20-look collections.
Urbanovitch is concerned about animal rights and her collection includes hand-knit pieces made from "completely ethical" humanely sourced fibres from angora rabbits raised in Nova Scotia, rather than far cheaper Chinese fur, harvested under cruel conditions as exposed in recent PETA Asia undercover video.
She also has pieces that mimic angora made from nylon microfibre and vegetable dyes.
"For me, angora as an example of a luxury fibre and seeing a sweater selling for $30 makes it feel very disposable," Urbanovitch said, adding she prefers to work with natural, organic materials that don't contribute to landfill. "People should be investing it in and treating a garment with care."
Urbanovitch said savvy consumers are recognizing the value of buying ethically although it can be challenging for her to compete with Asian manufacturing prices. But if consumers care about how and where their clothes are made, the choice becomes easier to make.
"I hope that (people will) reflect a little bit on what that's actually doing to the world," she said, adding donated clothing thrown away after just a season of wear can end up shipped overseas in bulk lots where it collapses local manufacturing and contributes to environmental damage.
"All of my manufacturers are treated well and paid well and they do beautiful work and I think it shows in the garment itself," said Urbanovitch.
Both Urbanovitch and Raizonville see ethical buying as a growing trend, although it won't happen overnight.
"It is coming slowly but I think it will be the normal way of doing things," said Raizonville.
]]></text></news-item>