<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2077-9B72-FE93-2A84"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>G.M. Calls the Lawyers</title><source>The New York Times</source><author>By MATTHEW GOLDSTEIN and BARRY MEIER</author><text><![CDATA[Late last summer, a lawyer named Lance Cooper sensed that his long battle with General Motors was coming to an end.
For three years, he tussled with lawyers from a high-powered firm hired to defend G.M. against his clients, the parents of Brooke Melton, a 29-year-old woman killed when her Chevy Cobalt lost power and collided with another vehicle. He sought internal documents and crucial witnesses, but at G.M.'s direction, lawyers from that firm, King & Spalding, fought him every step of the way, even refusing to disclose how many similar lawsuits the carmaker faced.
Then, in September, G.M. quietly settled Mr. Cooper's case. The type of faulty ignition in Brooke Melton's vehicle has become a major scandal for America's biggest car company and has since been linked to other deaths and led to the recall of 1.6 million cars.
And King & Spalding, the law firm that handled the Melton case for the company, has undergone a role reversal. This month, G.M. asked the firm, along with Jenner & Block, to conduct what the G.M. chief executive, Mary T. Barra, has called an ''unvarnished'' investigation into why the company failed for more than a decade to alert regulators and consumers to the defect.
To Mr. Cooper, King & Spalding's switch from a fierce defender of G.M. to a potential inquisitor into the company's actions may also pose a conflict.
For one, some of the firm's lawyers may have to ask their own colleagues if they advised G.M. about whether to recall the vehicles at the time the Melton case was settled.
''They are part of the story,'' said Mr. Cooper, whose firm is based in Marietta, Ga.
There is a predictable trajectory to the modern institutional scandal: Charges of wrongdoing surface, then mount, and then the company announces that it will bring in an outside law firm to conduct an internal investigation. The announcement, made in sober, corporate language, sends a calming message: We're not hiding. We're taking this seriously. We've got this.
Hiring outside counsel in these cases is part investigation, part public-relations gambit and part legal strategy. In most cases, the goal isn't to publicly flog a company or its top executives, but rather to limit damage to an institution's reputation or to contain the financial harm to shareholders of a publicly traded company. And it does so under the protection of the attorney-client privilege. From the point of view of the company, a well-done internal investigation can shape the accepted story of what happened -- and produce findings that allow the company to negotiate for lower penalties from prosecutors or regulators down the road.
To achieve those ends, the law firms conducting the investigations must be viewed as forthright and uncompromised. In this respect, some critics have already questioned G.M.'s choices.
The G.M. investigation will be led by Anton R. Valukas. Mr. Valukas gained credibility as the examiner in the Lehman Brothers bankruptcy, when he revealed several accounting tricks that the investment bank had used to spiff up its balance sheet. He has also served in a number of special investigative roles for government agencies in Chicago. But he is also the chairman of Jenner & Block, which has done high-profile securities work for G.M. Both Jenner and King & Spalding have done product liability cases for the company.
Les Zuke, a spokesman for King & Spalding, declined to comment. Greg Martin, a G.M. spokesman, said that both King & Spalding and Jenner & Block had ''reputations for adhering to the highest standards.'' Mr. Valukas did not respond to a request for comment.
William R. McLucas, a partner at WilmerHale, a big name in corporate internal investigations, said that if companies want credibility with prosecutors and investors, it is generally not wise to use their regular law firms for internal inquiries. The Justice Department has already announced that it will investigate G.M.'s handling of the ignition defect.
''If you are a firm that is generating substantial fees from a prospective corporate client, you may be able to come in and do a bang-up inquiry,'' said Mr. McLucas, who was the Securities and Exchange Commission's director of enforcement for eight years. ''But the perception is always going to be there; maybe you pulled your punches because there is a business relationship.''
Charles Elson, a professor of finance at the University of Delaware who specializes in corporate governance, agreed: ''I would not have done it because of the optics. Public perception can be affected by using regular outside counsel.''
Internal investigations aren't new, but as a practice of law, they really began to take off in the last decade. The housing bubble and crash pushed companies like Goldman Sachs to hire outside counsel to review their roles in the mortgage-backed securities market. New laws holding corporate directors more accountable for a company's actions, as well as laws allowing whistle-blowers to collect big recoveries, have led to investigations of problems that companies might otherwise have ignored. The push by prosecutors to crack down on United States companies engaged in bribery and corruption abroad has also given businesses a big incentive to investigate themselves because of potential large fines.
''The government expects companies to do these,'' said Jill E. Fisch, a corporate law professor at the University of Pennsylvania. ''If you are going to cooperate with the government, this is part of the cooperation they expect. Internal investigations are pretty routine.''
Internal investigations are a boon for law firms. Mr. Valukas's work in the Lehman case, which produced an exhaustive 2,200-page report, generated nearly $40 million in fees for the firm. Mr. Valukas charged $900 an hour; other lawyers at Jenner charge a blended rate of $400. These investigations, it's fair to say, are now seen as the cost of doing business for any big publicly traded company and a reliable source of income for big law firms.
''Every law firm now says, 'We are experts in internal investigations,' '' said Mr. McLucas at WilmerHale, who most recently oversaw a JPMorgan Chase investigation into the London Whale trading scandal.
Public companies are not the only institutions that have turned to lawyers to conduct internal investigations. When a Miami Dolphins football player was accused of bullying a teammate, the National Football League hired Ted Wells, a noted white-collar defense lawyer, as well as lawyers from Paul, Weiss, Rifkind, Wharton & Garrison to look into the incident. Penn State University reached out to a former F.B.I. director, Louis J. Freeh, to determine whether university officials had covered up for Jerry Sandusky, the former assistant football coach who was convicted in 2012 of sexually abusing young boys.
Mr. Freeh's investigation was notable for its toughness. It concluded that Joe Paterno, the revered Penn State football coach, who died in 2012, had known of the accusations of abuse but said nothing. Few internal investigations result in disclosures that imperil top officials. But they can offer prosecutors a blueprint.
Mr. McLucas helped with something of a road map to the London Whale debacle. His report faulted the bank for poor risk management in its London operation, but it did not lay any blame on Jamie Dimon, the chief executive of JPMorgan Chase -- a point some have criticized. Prosecutors eventually indicted two former JPMorgan traders in the scandal, which cost the bank $6.2 billion and resulted in penalties of more than $1 billion.
Prosecutors expect an internal investigation to be an honest assessment of a company's misdeeds or faults, says Adam G. Safwat, a former deputy chief of the fraud section in the Justice Department, where he worked on a number of foreign bribery investigations.
''What you want to avoid is doing something that will make the prosecutor question the quality of integrity of the internal investigation,'' said Mr. Safwat, who recently joined the Washington office of Weil Gotshal & Manges.
A shrewd law firm that gets out in front of scandal can use that to its advantage in negotiating with authorities to lower penalties and sanctions, said James McGrath, a principal at McGrath & Grace, a Cleveland firm that specializes in corporate investigations. ''There is a great incentive to ferret out information so they can spin it.''
It is way too soon to say whether G.M.'s decision to retain two of its go-to law firms will cause government investigators to cast a skeptical eye on the internal investigative report that is ultimately produced.
Both firms have done extensive work for G.M. The carmaker has used Jenner for more than a decade, and its work includes advising G.M. on its post-bankruptcy initial public stock offering and negotiating a $5 billion line of credit for the company in 2012. The firm's website says it has represented G.M. in ''product liability cases involving vehicle incompatibility/aggressivity; crashworthiness; air bags; rollover/roof crush and seatbelts.''
King & Spalding, in addition to its recent involvement in the ignition-switch litigation in Georgia, has represented G.M. in other product liability lawsuits arising from accusations of manufacturing flaws with the company's vehicles. The law firm's website lists G.M. as one of its ''representative clients.''
In another sign of King & Spalding's close ties to G.M., Harold E. Franklin Jr., the partner who represented G.M. in the Melton litigation, served as an ''in-house counsel'' of sorts to the auto company's product litigation group. Mr. Franklin's profile on the King & Spalding website describes his job as having been ''on loan from King & Spalding.''
Some suggest that there is logic behind G.M.'s decision to retain law firms it has worked with for many years. Ellen S. Podgor, a professor of criminal law at the Stetson University College of Law, said that from a corporation's perspective, there is an advantage to hiring lawyers who are familiar with a company. They understand how the company is structured and can get up to speed quickly.
Other lawyers said a respected lawyer like Mr. Valukas was unlikely to soft-pedal his review of the recall issue at G.M. He, too, has a reputation to uphold. And companies won't hire him if he is seen as just going through the motions.
Mr. Martin, the G.M. spokesman, made a similar point in an emailed statement: ''Mr. Valukas has been charged to go where the facts take him and give the company an unvarnished report on what happened.''
G.M. retained the outside lawyers just days after it received a detailed order from the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration. The order directed G.M. to answer 107 specific questions related to the defect and the company's handling of it.
That G.M. has known about the problem for more than a decade may force the review to address a fundamental question if it is to be credible: Did the company's handling of the ignition-switch defect reflect its underlying culture as opposed to being an isolated problem? It is a question that companies rarely look to outside lawyers to answer.
In fact, one company that found itself facing a product-safety firestorm, the Guidant Corporation, took a different approach. Its heart defibrillators had a potentially fatal defect that it did not reveal to patients or doctors. When that came to light, Guidant, rather than relying on outside lawyers, took the unusual step of setting up a panel of independent heart specialists, engineers and corporate governance experts to conduct its own investigation of the episode and whether the company's culture had played a role in causing it.
That panel's report, issued in 2006, was critical of Guidant. It found that engineers, rather than safety experts, drove the company's decision-making about product safety issues.
For the most part, corporate governance experts said that internal investigations done today, even by firms that have worked previously with a company, are far better than the ones performed more than a decade ago. Big law firms have become skilled at walling off lawyers in one practice group from another to avoid conflicts.
Vinson & Elkins's investigation into questionable accounting at Enron is viewed as an utter failure or a corporate whitewash. The review essentially gave Enron a clean bill of health just months before it collapsed in one of the biggest accounting frauds of all time. In 2006, the law firm paid $30 million to Enron's bankruptcy estate to resolve claims that its actions had contributed to the energy company's demise.
The best internal investigations, said Ms. Podgor and other lawyers, are the ones that don't receive much media attention. A company deals with a problem quickly, and if there's something to report to authorities, the company tends to be treated leniently for its forthrightness.
It's the kind of work that may not give the lawyers involved any public adulation. But, ultimately, they are well compensated all the same.
http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/16/business/general-motors-calls-the-lawyers.html
]]></text></news-item>