<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2091-CA42-7A98-6FD7"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Big Soul Project sings for Ancoura</title><source>Ottawa Citizen</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[What happens when you bring together Big Soul Project Community Gospel Choir and Band with a cause as worthy as Ancoura? You get a joyous benefit concert in support of creating homes for people living with a mental illness.
Who is Ancoura? Ancoura was incorporated in 2008 as a not-for-profit registered charity in Ottawa whose mission is to provide a fulfilling environment for adults living with a mental illness, through stable housing and a supportive community. It follows the model of Montreal's L'Abri en Ville. Volunteers are at the core of this model, providing a "circle of friends" with the residents. Ancoura's work is carried out through many partnerships, including faith groups and other community organizations. To date, four homes have been opened.
Mental illness leads to alienation, isolation and homelessness. The fundamental needs of adequate housing and the presence of a supportive community are often lacking. Ancoura addresses these needs. The name Ancoura is characterized by heart (coeur) - mutual respect, co-operation and care; courage and encouragement - a belief in the potential for individuals to be empowered to grow; and all anchored in stable, affordable and long-term housing within a supportive community. In recognition of their community service, Ancoura received the 2013 Inspiration Award from The Royal Ottawa Foundation for Mental Health.
Fundraising is a constant challenge. Through donations, Ancoura is able to pay the salary of co-ordinators, rent an office, pay office expenses and insurance, and add those little touches that turn our residences into real homes. Ancoura does not receive any government funding. This is where Big Soul Project steps in - to stage a benefit concert for Ancoura.
What is Big Soul Project? Ottawa's vibrant Big Soul Project Community Gospel Choir and Band has more than 100 choir and band members. Their aim is to entertain and inspire audiences with songs of hope, love, joy and peace, performed with a soulful beat. The choir has an incredible onstage energy and is led by dynamic choir director Roxanne Goodman. Their music has its roots in gospel, R&;B, reggae, pop and Motown. The choir's enthusiasm is contagious, and dancing in the aisles at their concerts is always welcomed.
They have performed at Westfest, Bluesfest and the Black Sheep Inn. Recently they were invited to be part of the Christmas Lights Across Canada show on Parliament Hill.
In the fall of 2012, Big Soul Project performed in the finale with Barbra Streisand in her Back to Brooklyn tour.
More importantly, they give back to the community. The choir's annual Christmas concert at Dominion-Chalmers United Church is always sold out, and last December's one was no exception. The proceeds from their Christmas concert help fund the many benefit shows they do throughout the year. And Ancoura is the fortunate recipient of Big Soul Project's first concert of 2014. The driving force behind this fundraiser is the First Unitarian Congregation of Ottawa. A group of dedicated volunteers from the church has been fundraising for Ancoura for several years.
Ancoura also means chorus (choeur) - residents and volunteers united as one voice. It is said that music brings people together, brings out the best in human nature. Come support Ancoura, raise our voices with Big Soul Project and celebrate the coming of spring.
It all happens on Saturday evening, March 29, at Southminster United Church, 15 Aylmer Ave. in Old Ottawa South.
Tickets are $20 for adults ($25 at the door), $10 for children under 12, and are available from:
Ottawa Folklore Centre, 1111 Bank St.
Compact Music, 785 and 206 Bank St.
Legend Records, 1315 Wellington St. W. ..Siam Bistro, 1268 Wellington St. W.Also available from: Paul McGinnis: 613-829-7156, John Gall: 613-237-3214.
]]></text></news-item>