<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="20DB-AAD8-3EED-BA67"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Man charged with trafficking in sex sting</title><source>Courier-Post (Cherry Hill, New Jersey)</source><author>By, Andy McNeil</author><text><![CDATA[A Trenton man is accused of holding three women against their will at the Inn of the Dove in Cherry Hill and forcing them to work as prostitutes, police said Thursday.
Brian A. Moore, 44, was arrested after an undercover sting at Cherry Hill's Crowne Plaza hotel.
It's believed the women had been traveling with Moore for five to nine months, police said. He is accused of "using violence and threatening their lives if they attempted to leave," Cherry Hill police said.
An Inn of the Dove employee, who declined to give a name, said Moore had been staying there for the last two or three months. The employee said workers were not aware of the alleged crimes.
Moore was arrested March 5 after he dropped off a prostitute who then tried to solicit an undercover officer at the Crowne Plaza, on Route 70, police said.
Authorities said the prostitute had been advertised on Backpage.com.
The website became one of the nation's top forums for "adult services" ads - with thinly veiled references to prostitution - after Craigslist.com shut its adults services section in 2010, according to the Associated Press.
"We monitor that page," said Cherry Hill Police Sgt. Richard Humes.
He said if officers notice more activity than normal for the area, they'll set up operations such as the one that snared Moore.
Brenda Antinore, director of She Has A Name, a nonprofit that helps Camden's prostitutes, said Backpage.com is a "huge problem" and that she knows of prostitutes being advertised on the website in both Cherry Hill and Brooklawn.
"(If) you know that it's being used that way, why are they allowed to advertise on there?" Antinore asked.
This isn't the first time Moore has faced prostitution charges in Camden County, according to court records. He was charged with promoting prostitution in Gloucester Township in 2008 and in Cherry Hill in 2009.
In the latter case, he used Craigslist.com to advertise prostitutes at the Extended Stay America on Route 70, court records show. He eventually pleaded guilty to a lesser offense.
In July 2010, Moore and a woman were arrested for allegedly holding another woman against her will at a Runnemede hotel, according to court records. It's alleged the victim was injected with heroin and forced into prostitution.
Moore was charged with promoting prostitution, criminal restraint and drug possession, according to court records. He pleaded guilty in the case and was sentenced to three years in prison in 2011.
In the current case, Moore is charged with human trafficking and promoting prostitution and is being held at the Camden County Jail on $250,000 bail. The woman accused of soliciting the officer was charged with promoting prostitution and released on her own recognizance. The other women were not charged.
Antinore called on authorities to "ratchet up the heat" on traffickers who prey on young woman.
A state law hit a roadblock last June when Backpages.com filed a challenge in federal court. The law sought to penalize anyone who knowingly publishes or disseminates any ad for a commercial sex act that includes the depiction of a minor, the Associated Press reported.
A federal judge last August ruled the law likely is unconstitutional, putting the legislation on hold indefinitely.
Reach Andy McNeil at amcneil@gannett.com or (856) 486-2458.
]]></text></news-item>