<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="20E3-BA08-42D5-2E09"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Rights lobby get it so wrong; Hold the Back Page</title><source>Sunday Independent</source><author>EAMONN SWEENEY</author><text><![CDATA[TIME to say something controversial. In 2003, my father died after a very brave and dignified struggle against cancer. I was extremely distraught about his death. In fact for several months I had a kind of nervous breakdown and couldn''t do anything. That happens quite a lot with bereavement. There''s no trauma quite like the loss of a close family member.
Now, last year my pet dog Toto died. He was a fine, friendly character and I''d had many a fun hour with him. But he took sick and that was that. I was a bit sad but I would have to say that this sadness was not the same kind which attended the death of my father. It wasn''t in the same ballpark. The death of an animal, no matter how beloved, isn''t the same thing as the death of a human.
This isn''t actually a controversial thing to say at all. Any sane person knows it''s true. A dead dog is not the same as a dead dad, a dead cat is not the same as a dead child, a dead guinea pig is not the same as a dead granny. Yet, simply for making this obvious point last week Ruby Walsh was forced to endure a torrent of vile abuse from anonymous cowards on the internet and criticism of the most surpassing stupidity from organisations who claim to represent 'animal rights'. '.
The furore came about because on being asked his feelings about the death of Our Conor in the Champion Hurdle, the jockey said, "It''s sad, but horses are animals, outside your back door. Humans are humans, they are inside your door. You can replace a horse, you can''t replace a human being."
" He later added: "We look after horses like they're pets. There''s a huge difference between your pet and your family. That''s the point I was making. There''s a big difference between you going home tonight and something''s happened to your dog, and you go home tonight and something''s happened to your kids ... at the end of the day, it''s still your pet. It ain''t your son, your daughter, your brother, your sister."
" These are eminently sensible comments and they would have been coloured by Ruby's knowledge of what can happen to jockeys on the racecourse. He''ll remember JT McNamara being paralysed by a fall at Cheltenham last year, the death of young jockey Ryan Cusack in an accident last month, of Jack Tyner killed by a fall at a point-to-point three years ago, of Ronan Lawlor killed in a training accident four years ago, of Sean Cleary, Dary Cullen and Kieran Kelly, who also died on the racecourse since 2000, of Shane Broderick, paralysed from the neck down since a fall at Fairyhouse in 1997. Closer to home, he''d have thought of Jason Maguire who as Cheltenham began was lying in a coma and having part of his liver removed after a fall at Stratford. Or, away from the racecourse altogether, of Tony McCoy''s seven-month-old son Archie who was recovering from heart surgery. To imply that the human suffering endured by the McNamara, the Cusack, the Tyner, the Lawlor or the Cleary families compares in any way to the suffering involved in having one of your pets die is not only insulting, it''s downright monstrous. Yet apparently there were people out there who thought Ruby Walsh should have done it all the same.
Because he didn''t they decided to subject him to a barrage of threats and insults on Twitter. Among other things the jockey was told, 'Ruby Walsh, I hope you get your skull crushed by one of the horses ...
Shame more jockeys aren''t killed instead of beautiful horses!!!!!! All jockeys are complete c**ts!! ... I hope you fall off a horse and get trampled.' There was plenty more of this kind of stuff but I''ll spare you.
This type of anonymous rhetoric tends to proliferate on Twitter where every day someone new is the subject of a digital equivalent to the Two Minute Hate from George Orwell''s 1984.
But Walsh''s remarks also drew criticism from spokespeople for organisations who believe they should be taken seriously on these matters. Chief among these has been one Ingrid Newkirk of People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals who said, "Walsh''s comments expose the true emotion behind horse racing, They are deeply offensive to anyone who ever loved and lost a horse or other beloved animal companion."
A group called Animal Aid, who are currently campaigning for the banning of the Grand National, also got in on the act.
The torrent of abuse aimed at Walsh would have been unpalatable enough in any event but it''s made worse by the fact that the jockey is one of the most admirable figures in Irish sport. Throughout his career, his good humour, his lack of egotism, his professionalism and his ability to treat triumph and disaster just the same have been inspirational. That''s something he has in common with many of his colleagues. In an era where hero worship of major sporting figures is rife, perhaps only our jockeys genuinely display heroism. They do a dangerous job and make no fuss about it.
The day after Our Conor''s death, Bryan Cooper suffered a horrendous leg break when he was kicked by a horse after falling. On Friday, there were anxious moments when Daryl Jacob suffered a heavy fall on to concrete after being thrown by a horse on the way down to the start.
And, of course, Ruby Walsh himself will be out for the next three months after a fall on Abyssial in the Triumph Hurdle left him with a compound fracture of the right arm. This is the kind of thing he''s learned to live with and he doesn't make a fuss about it. He didn''t make a fuss about the threats and abuse either, telling journalists, "I didn''t know about it." Ruby Walsh isn''t the kind of man who goes in for self-pity.
Yet what rankles is that it''s the most attractive features of Walsh''s personality which sparked the attacks. When he''s asked a straight question, he gives a straight answer and that''s what he did at Cheltenham. And he, like other jockeys, is hugely co-operative with the media, never dodging a question or coming out with a 'no comment'. It''s a pity that this honesty and approachability has drawn the wrath of these people. In fact, it's laughable.
Ruby''s father Ted noted that Britain "is a funny country. They can remember the names of the horses that got blown up in London but not the names of the people riding them." PETA, so often quoted on these matters, has been criticised for sexism, they''ve used naked models in advertising campaigns, and racism, they''ve used photographs of lynched black men in campaigns which compared them to animals suffering from cruelty. The leading feminist website Jezebel has even run a column headed, 'Is Ingrid Newkirk the worst woman in the world?', pointing out that PETA actually puts down animals in its custody.
Newkirk, a self-proclaimed "press slut," who wants her skin to be made into wallets when she dies, even went so far as to comment that, "Walsh needs reminding that it wasn''t so long ago people used to deride his fellow countrymen using the same kind of ignorant language, and he''d do well to think a little harder and apologise for his comments." Such condescending nonsense is unlikely to persuade many people of PETA''s case.
This then is the calibre of those who decided to hound one of this country''s most noble sportsmen over the past week. If this is the kind of stuff they''re going to come up with, perhaps they should take a leaf out of Doctor Dolittle''s book and let the animals speak for themselves. Because in linking the death of a pet with the death of a human, they come across as not just stupid but inhuman.
Pass no heed, Ruby.
backpage@independent.ie
This is the kind of thing he's learned to live with and he doesn't make a fuss about it
]]></text></news-item>