<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="20F0-43EC-56C1-5674"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>EU's GSP PLUS STATUS FOR PAKISTAN</title><source>Business Recorder</source><author> A. Q. KHALIL</author><text><![CDATA[The European Union (EU) granted Generalised Scheme of Preference (GSP) Plus status to Pakistan, which has become effective from January 1, 2014. The grant of GSP Status to Pakistan is undoubtedly a significant achievement of the present government and has been warmly welcomed by the business community but some of leading industrialists believe that Pakistan may not be able to substantially improve its exports to EU countries due to a number of issues including the poor infrastructure and severe energy crisis. EU's GSP Plus Status is likely to increase access to the EU market through duty free imports of GSP-eligible products.
The EU is not only one of the largest trading partners of Pakistan, but is actively engaged and contributing effectively to socio-economic development of Pakistan. Trading relations have, however, weakened over the years. One-third of Pakistan's exports used to go to the EU in 1995-96. These declined to one-fourth in 2000-01 and further declined to almost 10 percent by 2010-11. The slower pace of economic activities in Pakistan since 2007-08 and the emergence of the European debt crisis in the aftermath of the great recession appear to be the reason behind the weakening of trade relations.
GSP plus is clearly an opportunity for those who are ready to grab it. Unfortunately, few in Pakistan are prepared to handle the huge opportunity provided by the European Union under its GSP Plus scheme, comprising generous trade concessions.
The Karachi Chamber of Commerce and Industry (KCCI) and the leadership of Businessmen Group (BMG), while hailing the EU parliament's decision to approve GSP Plus status for Pakistan, extended deep gratitude to the Pakistani government for making efforts towards acquiring GSP Status, which has finally been granted.
According to KCCI, GSP plus will give a boost to Pakistani exports by at least US $2 billion keeping in view the enormous demand of Pakistani products in the European markets but the Pakistani manufacturers and exporters must also focus on producing high-quality products according to European standards so that they could not only maintain their market share but take it to new heights. KCCI further advised the government to facilitate the business community, particularly the export-oriented industry by ensuring adequate infrastructure along with uninterrupted power supply so that the exporters could play their role in boosting Pakistan's export to Europe which will certainly help in earning the much-needed foreign exchange for the country, besides efficiently dealing with the economic crisis.
However, it must be kept in mind that the provinces need to fine-tune the labour laws in line with the conventions of the International Labour Organisation (ILO) to ensure that Pakistan continues to benefit from the free-market access given by the European Union (EU) under GSP Plus scheme for an initial period of three years.
The opportunity for Pakistan to have a duty-free access to the European markets has fortunately come at a very crucial time when it is facing a crisis in the external sector, its foreign exchange reserves are depleting fast, rupee is under a great deal of pressure and its textile exports are facing a tough competition from Sri Lanka and Bangladesh who already have a duty-free access to European markets. Under the facility, Pakistan's more than 600 items, mainly textile items, are now eligible to enter into 27-member EU bloc duty-free. The sectors likely to benefit include yarn, textile fabrics, textile garments including hosiery, bed, kitchen and toilet linen, footwear, protective leather gloves and sports gloves, ethanol and plastics. Many Pakistani products like footballs, mangoes and other fruits, pine nuts, animal products, cutlery products and surgical instruments already have zero duty in the EU.
Experts believe that a comprehensive strategy needs to be designed to ensure that export commodities, particularly those in greater demand in the EU market, could be produced in abundance at competitive rates in the country. For this, energy supply has to be vastly improved, investment has to be enhanced and other impediments to production of exportable commodities removed as early as possible; failing which the fresh opportunity may be squandered by the country. Secondly, as the voting pattern in the European Parliament has shown, Pakistan needs to continuously observe certain mandatory standards on human rights, etc, to the satisfaction of international community. Otherwise, countries who have voted against Pakistan may be able to get more support from other friendly European countries and deprive Pakistan from the facility at the time of review. We cannot always count on floods to get long-term relief. It needs to be recalled that Sri Lanka lost its GSP Plus status due to human rights violations and opponents of Pakistan may refer to the Balochistan unrest as a negative factor for refusing the facility during the next review.
EU trade concessions will benefit the country's largest manufacturer and exporter, the textile and clothing industry, the most by enabling its products to compete with those of regional rivals like Bangladesh and Sri Lanka, which already have duty-free access to the bloc's market. At present, our textile and clothing exports to the EU constitute more than half of the country's total exports of almost $9.5bn to the bloc. These have the potential to more than double in a few years. Though the scheme caps annual growth in the textile and clothing imports from Pakistan at 14.5 percent, the industry expects to boost its earnings from the EU by up to $1billion annually.
For many years now, the industry hasn't invested in capacity expansion due to various reasons - growing energy shortages, high credit cost, poor security conditions, etc. A substantial part of its capacity in Punjab is inoperative because of severe gas and electricity shortages. By the time the EU trade concessions become effective, more capacity will be closed down, though temporarily, as the government plans to cut off gas supply to the industry for three months to facilitate domestic users. Indeed, a few large manufacturers have invested money in value-added textiles despite all these problems with a view to take full advantage of the GSP Plus scheme. But even they have invested in traditional, cotton-based products. The government's skewed policies that have discouraged the use of manmade fiber and diversification of textile exports will restrict the industry's ability to reap the full benefits of the newly acquired status. If the government wants the industry to gain maximum advantage from the concessions, it must help the manufacturers revive capacity by ensuring uninterrupted gas and electricity supply as well as cheap credit for new projects and by easing restrictions on the import of fabric and other raw materials not produced domestically, in order to encourage product diversification.
Furthermore, the exporters must focus on diversification and exporting high-quality goods to European Union Markets as exporting the same old limited number of goods will not yield positive results and Pakistan will not be able to enhance its share in European Markets.
]]></text></news-item>