<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="210B-CDCA-5503-E990"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Lake County begins push to recycle textiles; Towns to accept everything from socks to bedspreads</title><source>Chicago Tribune</source><author>By Sheryl DeVore, Special to the Tribune</author><text><![CDATA[Torn socks, old dust rags, tattered jeans, sheets, bedspreads and other textiles clutter landfills in Lake County as well as nationwide.
But Lake County residents soon will be able to recycle those throwaways by tossing them in steel 7-by-4-foot bins to be set up this month in communities including Vernon Hills, Grayslake, Gurnee and Wauconda. The municipalities are partnering with the Solid Waste Agency of Lake County to start a pilot clothing and textile recycling program.
Even with the availability of resale and thrift shops to recycle such items, the average person throws out about 60 pounds of old clothes and other textiles each year, said Peter Adrian, the agency's recycling director.
"People are throwing away their old dirty socks, towels they turned into a floor mat or to wipe down a car," Adrian said. "When they don't want it, they pitch it. But it still has the value of fiber."
The Vernon Hills Village Board agreed March 4 to work with SWALCO on the project. A new bin will be placed by the public works facility, where the village also collects electronics year-round to be recycled.
Each bin can fit about 500 pounds of recyclables. Other county communities are expected to join the partnership.
The textile recycling program "provides another opportunity for recycling in our community and hopefully on a broader scale throughout Lake County," said John Kalmar, Vernon Hills village manager. Recycling textiles will help reduce the county's impact on landfills, he said.
SWALCO is calling for a 60 percent landfill diversion rate in Lake County by 2020.
Kevin Timony, economic development manager for Grayslake, said he expects the bins to be delivered within the next couple of weeks. They'll be placed inside the public works building along with other bins already there for recycling electronics, newspapers, plastics, cans and glass.
"Grayslake residents have supported our other recycling projects, and we expect good participation with this as well," Timony said.
SWALCO is working with Chicago Textile Recycling, a family-run business in Hillside that sells items for reuse or to be recycled into new products. The automotive industry, for example, is one of the largest buyers of used garments, which it remakes into items such as insulation and padding, Adrian said. Through a revenue sharing program, SWALCO will receive about $15,000 per year or more from the company and will divvy up one-third of that to participating communities, he said.
For several years, Chicago Textile Recycling has been setting up collection days throughout Chicago and the suburbs. Supplying bins and working with local communities are a new venture.
"Eighty-five percent of textiles generated in the country are ending up in the landfill," said Kim Woycke, the firm's recycling executive. "We're working to decrease that number."
Woycke said the company hopes to collect 900 pounds of textile recyclables a month from each of the participating Lake County towns.
People can recycle household linens, hats, purses and clothing, both wearable and nonwearable.
Collection sites scheduled to open later this month include Gurnee Fire Station No. 2, 6581 Dada Lane; Vernon Hills Public Works Department, 490 Greenleaf Drive; Grayslake Public Works Department, 585 Berry Ave.; and Wauconda Public Works, 302 Slocum Lake Road.
For more information, call SWALCO at 847-336-9340 or go to swalco.org.
ct14 0004 140314 R S 0000000000 00003603
]]></text></news-item>