<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2130-2473-DEB7-096C"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Rexnord Estimates $35-Mil Potential Liability</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Rexnord Corporation estimates the potential liability for theasbestos-related claims as well as claims expected to be filed inthe next ten years to be approximately $35.0 million, according tothe Company's Form 10-Q filing with the U.S. Securities andExchange Commission for the quarterly period ended December 28,2013. The Company's subsidiaries are involved in various unresolvedlegal actions, administrative proceedings and claims in theordinary course of business involving, among other things, productliability, commercial, employment, workers' compensation,intellectual property claims and environmental matters. TheCompany establishes reserves in a manner that is consistent withaccounting principles generally accepted in the United States forcosts associated with such matters when liability is probable andthose costs are capable of being reasonably estimated. Although itis not possible to predict with certainty the outcome of theseunresolved legal actions or the range of possible loss orrecovery, based upon current information, management believes theeventual outcome of these unresolved legal actions, eitherindividually or in the aggregate, will not have a material adverseeffect on the financial position, results of operations or cashflows of the Company. In connection with the Carlyle acquisition in November 2002,Invensys plc ("Invensys") has provided the Company withindemnification against certain contingent liabilities, includingcertain pre-closing environmental liabilities. The Companybelieves that, pursuant to such indemnity obligations, Invensys isobligated to defend and indemnify the Company with respect to thematters relating to the Ellsworth Industrial Park Site and tovarious asbestos claims. The indemnity obligations relating to thematters are subject, together with indemnity obligations relatingto other matters, to an overall dollar cap equal to the purchaseprice, which is an amount in excess of $900 million. In 2002, Rexnord Industries, LLC ("Rexnord Industries") was namedas a potentially responsible party ("PRP"), together with at leastten other companies, at the Ellsworth Industrial Park Site,Downers Grove, DuPage County, Illinois (the "Site"), by the UnitedStates Environmental Protection Agency ("USEPA"), and the IllinoisEnvironmental Protection Agency ("IEPA"). Rexnord Industries'Downers Grove property is situated within the Ellsworth IndustrialComplex. The USEPA and IEPA allege there have been one or morereleases or threatened releases of chlorinated solvents and otherhazardous substances, pollutants or contaminants, allegedlyincluding but not limited to a release or threatened release on orfrom the Company's property, at the Site. The relief sought by theUSEPA and IEPA includes further investigation and potentialremediation of the Site and reimbursement of USEPA's past costs.Rexnord Industries' allocated share of past and future costsrelated to the Site, including for investigation and/orremediation, could be significant. All previously pending propertydamage and personal injury lawsuits against the Company related tothe Site have been settled or dismissed. Pursuant to its indemnityobligation, Invensys continues to defend the Company in knownmatters related to the Site and has paid 100% of the costs todate. Multiple lawsuits (with approximately 1,000 claimants) are pendingin state or federal court in numerous jurisdictions relating toalleged personal injuries due to the alleged presence of asbestosin certain brakes and clutches previously manufactured by theCompany's Stearns division and/or its predecessor owners. Invensysand FMC, prior owners of the Stearns business, have paid 100% ofthe costs to date related to the Stearns lawsuits. Similarly, theCompany's Prager subsidiary is a defendant in two pending multi-defendant lawsuits relating to alleged personal injuries due tothe alleged presence of asbestos in a product allegedlymanufactured by Prager. Additionally, there are numerousindividuals who have filed asbestos related claims against Prager;however, these claims are currently on the Texas Multi-districtLitigation inactive docket. The ultimate outcome of these asbestosmatters cannot presently be determined. To date, the Company'sinsurance providers have paid 100% of the costs related to thePrager asbestos matters. The Company believes that the combinationof its insurance coverage and the Invensys indemnity obligationswill cover any future costs of these matters. In connection with the acquisition of The Falk Corporation("Falk"), Hamilton Sundstrand has provided the Company withindemnification against certain products-related asbestos exposureliabilities. The Company believes that, pursuant to such indemnityobligations, Hamilton Sundstrand is obligated to defend andindemnify the Company with respect to the asbestos claims, andthat, with respect to these claims, such indemnity obligations arenot subject to any time or dollar limitations. Falk, through its successor entity, is a defendant in multiplelawsuits pending in state or federal court in numerousjurisdictions relating to alleged personal injuries due to thealleged presence of asbestos in certain clutches and drivespreviously manufactured by Falk. There are approximately 100claimants in these suits. The ultimate outcome of these lawsuitscannot presently be determined. Hamilton Sundstrand is defendingthe Company in these lawsuits pursuant to its indemnityobligations and has paid 100% of the costs to date. Certain Water Management subsidiaries are also subject to asbestoslitigation. As of December 28, 2013, Zurn and an average ofapproximately 80 other unrelated companies were defendants inapproximately 7,000 asbestos related lawsuits representingapproximately 26,000 claims. Plaintiffs' claims allege personalinjuries caused by exposure to asbestos used primarily inindustrial boilers formerly manufactured by a segment of Zurn.Zurn did not manufacture asbestos or asbestos components. Instead,Zurn purchased them from suppliers. These claims are being handledpursuant to a defense strategy funded by insurers. As of December 28, 2013, the Company estimates the potentialliability for the asbestos-related claims described, as well asclaims expected to be filed in the next ten years to beapproximately $35.0 million, of which Zurn expects its insurancecarriers to pay approximately $27.0 million in the next ten yearson such claims, with the balance of the estimated liability beingpaid in subsequent years. The $35.0 million was developed based onan actuarial study and represents the projected indemnity payoutfor claims filed in the next 10 years. However, there are inherentuncertainties involved in estimating the number of future asbestosclaims, future settlement costs, and the effectiveness of defensestrategies and settlement initiatives. As a result, actualliability could differ from the estimate described herein.Further, while this current asbestos liability is based on anestimate of claims through the next ten years, such liability maycontinue beyond that time frame, and such liability could besubstantial. Management estimates that its available insurance to cover thispotential asbestos liability as of December 28, 2013, isapproximately $252.6 million, and believes that all current claimsare covered by insurance. However, principally as a result of thepast insolvency of certain of the Company's insurance carriers,certain coverage gaps will exist if and after the Company's othercarriers have paid the first $176.6 million of aggregateliabilities. As of December 28, 2013, the Company had a recorded receivablefrom its insurance carriers of $35.0 million, which corresponds tothe amount of this potential asbestos liability that is covered byavailable insurance and is currently determined to be probable ofrecovery. However, there is no assurance that $252.6 million ofinsurance coverage will ultimately be available or that thisasbestos liability will not ultimately exceed $252.6 million.Factors that could cause a decrease in the amount of availablecoverage include: changes in law governing the policies, potentialdisputes with the carriers regarding the scope of coverage, andinsolvencies of one or more of the Company's carriers. The Company's subsidiaries, Zurn PEX, Inc. and Zurn Industries,LLC ("Zurn Industries"), were named as defendants in a number ofindividual and class action lawsuits in various United Statescourts. The plaintiffs in these suits claimed damages due to thealleged failure or anticipated failure of Zurn brass fittings onthe PEX plumbing systems in homes and other structures. In July 2012, the Company reached an agreement in principle tosettle the liability underlying this litigation. The settlement isdesigned to resolve, on a national basis, the Company's overallexposure for both known and unknown claims related to the allegedfailure or anticipated failure of Zurn brass fittings on PEXplumbing systems, subject to the right of eligible class membersto opt-out of the settlement and pursue their claimsindependently. The settlement received final court approval inFebruary 2013, and utilizes a seven year claims fund, which iscapped at $20 million, and is funded in installments over theseven year period based on claim activity and minimum fundingcriteria. The settlement also covers class action plaintiffs'attorneys' fees and expenses totaling $8.5 million, which was paidin the first quarter of fiscal 2014. Historically, the Company's insurance carrier had funded theCompany's defense in the proceedings. The Company, however,reached a settlement agreement with its insurer, whereby theinsurer paid the Company a lump sum in exchange for a release offuture exposure related to this liability. The Company has recorded a reserve related to this brass fittingsliability, which takes into account, in pertinent part, theinsurance carrier contribution, as well as exposure from theclaims fund, opt-outs and the waiver of future insurance coverage. In January 2010, Sloan Valve Company ("Sloan") filed a complaintagainst the Company's subsidiary, Zurn Industries, for patentinfringement in the United States District Court for the NorthernDistrict of Illinois. The complaint alleges, among other things,that Zurn Industries' manual dual flush valve infringes Sloan'spatent for its "Flush Valve Handle Assembly Providing Dual ModeOperation" and seeks an unspecified amount of damages, including arequest for treble damages and attorneys' fees related to Sloan'sallegation of willful infringement. Trial for this matter iscurrently scheduled for September 2014. While the Company intendsto continue vigorously defending itself in this action, it may besubject to liability beyond the reserves that have recorded todate. Rexnord Corporation (Rexnord) is a multi-platform industrialcompany. The Company comprises of two platforms, Process & MotionControl and Water Management. Rexnord's Process & Motion Controlproduct portfolio includes gears, couplings, industrial bearings,aerospace bearings and seals, FlatTop chain, engineered chain andconveying equipment, and are marketed and sold globally underbrands, including Rexnord, Rex, Falk and Link-Belt. Its WaterManagement platform operates in the commercial constructionmarket. Its Water Management product portfolio includes drainageproducts, flush valves and faucet products, backflow preventionpressure release valves, PEX piping and engineered valves andgates for the water and wastewater treatment markets. In August2013, Rexnord Corp acquired the assets of Micro Precision GearTechnology Limited. In December 2013, Rexnord acquired PrecisionGear Holdings, LLC (PGH). PGH has two operating subsidiaries,Merit Gear LLC and Precision Gear LLC.
]]></text></news-item>