<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="21D5-2DBF-39EE-0E46"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Fraudster 'still owes us £4.75m'; Turkish property scam - the aftermath</title><source>Grimsby Telegraph</source><author>Mark Naylor</author><text><![CDATA[TWO of fraudster Hayley Brown's main victims say she owes them a massive £4.75 million after her big Turkey property investments scam, it has been revealed.
They lost a net figure of £609,000 in bank transfers that were actually handed over to her - but they insist that the £4.75 million total losses figure represents their expected investment income retur ns.
They say the figure was agreed by solicitors acting for them and for her, as well as by her accountants.
Simon and Julie Marshall spoke out after Brown was jailed at Leeds Crown Court for a total of nine years.
Brown, 41, of Goodwood Lane, Cleethorpes, denied ten offences of fraud, three of obtaining a money transfer by deception and two of using a false document with intent to deceive, between March 2006 and July 2009.
She was convicted by a jury of 14 of the 15 offences after a trial.
She was jailed for four years for the frauds, with a consecutive five years after she admitted two separate firearms offences.
They included possessing a stun gun which was capable of discharging 50,000 volts but was made to look like a mobile phone.
The other was a canister of CS-type gas.
The prosecution claimed that Brown "swindled" hundreds of thousands of pounds out of trusting investors by selling them supposedly lucrative property investments in the resort of Bodrum.
She "seduced" them into shelling out large sums of money through a "web of duplicity" and "thoroughly dishonest" deals, the court heard.
She lied "consistently and persuasively" to win their confidence but they were left hugely out of pocket.
Mr and Mrs Marshall were two of the three directors and shareholders of the Goldchip investment company, along with Carol Pycroft.
Mr Marshall, who lives near Lincoln, said they were very disappointed with the prison sentence and believed Brown should have got a longer sentence for the frauds. He said that they invested £609,000 with Brown to buy Turkish properties but, when Goldchip brought a bankruptcy order against her, the figure of £4.75m was agreed and ratified by Grimsby County Court as their total loss.
His wife said: "That must seem like an awful lot of money to make from £609,000 - we appreciate that - but it was continually rolled over.
"She swore on her children's lives twice to us that she would pay us our money back. "You would not believe the impact she has had on our lives. It's completely turned us upside down."
Mr Marshall said: "She does owe us £4.75m.
"We were the ones who bankrupted her because she owed us the money.
"There was a statutory demand saying it was £4.75m she owed us."
He said the total sum was based on figures supplied by Brown's accountants and provided to her then solicitors.
Goldchip's solicitors accepted the figures as a settlement, said Mr Marshall. He added that the couple became very close to Brown during their dealings with her and even took her, together with her son and daughter, on a skiing trip to Chamonix, in the French Alps. A week later, she was due to pay money back to them that she owed but did not do so.
"That's when the relationship started to break down," he said.
The couple also went on a trip to London with Brown.
Mrs Marshall said: "We really did bring her into our lives.
"We feel foolish, believe you me, we do.
We are good business people. To pull the wool over our eyes takes some doing.
"We didn't get any money back."
Mr Marshall branded as a "farce" Brown's claim in court that she had millions of pounds in a Cyprus bank because of her supposedly successful business skills. He criticised the court's decision to allow her Turkish accountant to give evidence to the trial via a video link when the prosecution had apparently not been allowed to have a video link to the Turkish police because it would supposedly have been hearsay evidence.
Mrs Marshall added: "There's a lot of wealthy people that she went out to 'do'."
It was believed that other victims had also lost a lot of money but they had not come forward for reasons including embarrassment, she said.
"We regret trusting her, big time," said Mrs Marshall.
l. ? ON THE WEB: Read the original story on the case at www.grimsbytelegraph.co.uk
]]></text></news-item>