<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="21F4-1E58-BFCE-5E86"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>UMS Holdings keeps rising: up 13.1% in 6 days</title><source>News Bites Asian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[UMS Holdings Limited (SI:558), Singapore's 26th largest manufacturing company by market capitalisation, extended its gains Monday, rising an additional 1.0c (or 1.4%) to close at 73.50c. The shares have soared 8.50c (or 13.1%) over the past six trading days. Compared with the FTSE/ASEAN 40 Index which rose 29.7 points (or 0.28%) in the six days, this represented a relative price increase of 12.8%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on UMS Holdings, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051921770314780
Bullish SignalsUptrend- The stock increased on firm volume, rising for a sixth consecutive day.- The stock hit a year-high 12th time in one month and 17th time in three months.- The stock continues its significant uptrend.- Rises to Falls: in the past month the number of rises outnumbered falls 11:5 or 2.2:1.- The present value of SGD1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in UMS Holdings is SGD1,794, including a capital gain of SGD633 and dividend reinvested of SGD161.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Earnings of 14.9 [17.0]. - Return on Equity 9.4% [7.5%].- Return on Assets 8% [3.2%].- Return on Capital Employed 10.3% [9.1%].- Dividend yield of 6.8% [2.5%].Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 1.1 is comfortably below 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 12.9%. - Interest cover defined by EBIT/I is 71 times. This indicates it is less leveraged. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 1.2. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- Net profit margin has averaged 20.5% in the last 3 years. This is considered superior and suggests a high margin of safety.- The Enterprise Value/EBITDA multiple of 8.0 compares favourably with sector average of 8.6. Enterprise Value is estimated at MCap SGD252.7 million plus net debt of SGD-14.9 million and EBITDA is estimated at SGD29.5 million.- Economic Value Added defined by Net Operating Profit After Tax of SGD16.8 million less Cost of Capital of SGD4.9 million was SGD11.9 million. The multiple EVA/Cost of Capital was exemplary at 2.4 times. - As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity of 9.4% is better than sector average of 7.5%. This is computed as net profit margin of 15.0% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 0.53 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 1.2.
NoteVolume: there were 1,744,000 shares worth SGD1.3 million (US$1 million) traded. This has been propped up by firm volume of 1.5 times average.
Bearish Signals:Overbought/Bearish/Resistance Signals- The Relative Strength Index (RSI) of 76.9 has penetrated the overbought line of 70, suggesting the price gain of 11.4% in the last 14 days is unusually high. - The Money Flow Index [MFI] is 88.1 suggesting an overbought 14-day trend, being above 80. The Money Ratio of 7.4 suggests positive money flow was 7.4 times negative money flow.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price/Sales of 2.2 [0.5]. - Price to Book of 2.6 [1.6]. - Price to EBITDA of 8.6 [6.9].Other Bearish Signals:- Revenue and Net Profit growth have shown signs of deterioration in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]
- EBITDA growth has seen consecutive falls and seems to be on a slippery slope in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 28: Net Pacific Financial Holdings: Notice of Book Closure Date for DividendDividend Value : SGD 0.02 Per 1 Ordinary sharePayment Type : Tax Exempted (1-tier)Dividend Type : FinalRecord Date : 08/05/2014Record Time : 17:00Date Paid/Payable (if applicable) 28/05/2014http://infopub.sgx.com/Apps?A=COW_CorporateAnnouncement_Content&B=AnnouncementTodayByCompanyNameAndCategory&F=1063591Source: Singapore Exchange
February 28: UMS Holdings: Notice of Book Closure Date for DividendDividend Value : SGD 0.015 Per 1 Ordinary sharePayment Type : Tax Exempted (1-tier)Dividend Type : SpecialRecord Date : 08/05/2014Record Time : 17:00Date Paid/Payable (if applicable) 28/05/2014http://infopub.sgx.com/Apps?A=COW_CorporateAnnouncement_Content&B=AnnouncementTodayByCompanyNameAndCategory&F=1063591Source: Singapore Exchange
November 13: UMS Holdings announces dividendUMS Holdings today announced an interim dividend of 1.0c per share. The record date is December 05, 2013 and it is payable on December 20, 2013.
August 06: UMS Holdings: Second quarter results financial statement and related announcement[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Singapore/Stock/News/28446.pdfhttp://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Singapore/Stock/News/28446.pdfSource: Singapore Exchange
August 06: UMS Holdings announces dividendUMS Holdings today announced an interim dividend of 1.0c per share. The record date is October 10, 2013 and it is payable on October 29, 2013.
June 28: UMS Holdings appoints Non-Executive Independent DirectorUMS Holdings has appointed Chay Yiowmin as Non-Executive Independent Director. The effective date is June 28, 2013.
May 09: UMS Holdings: First quarter results financial statement and related announcement[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Singapore/Stock/News/25400.pdfSource: Singapore Exchange
ISIN: SG1J94892465
SI:558; SGX:558; SP:558
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>