<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2212-8084-4E13-492A"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Commentator criticise Somali leader over his defence on corruption allegations</title><source>BBC Monitoring Africa - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Text of report by privately-owned Somali news website Alldhacdo
The recent attack on Villa Somalia by Al-Shabab was a surprise to most of the Somali people, but certain political analysts who follow Somali politics were not astonished that the president, the day after attack, held a press conference and undermined the whole issues as mere occurrence in which Al Shabab made one of its last desperate move.
In a press conference, President Hasan Shaykh Mahmud stated that his government would put a plan in place to wipe out Al Shabab out of the country within the next few months without mentioning the detail of the plan. During his campaign to win the presidency, President Hasan stressed that his first priority would be to secure the safety of the capital. Later on in that press conference, he pointed out that Al Shabab was so weak to the point that it attacked Villa Somalia.
Most were left confused by conflicting assertions in the president's statement.
It seemed that the president was not forthcomng with answers the Somali people needed. A Couple days before the attack of Villa Somalia, Prime Minister Abdiweli expressed his concern regarding the lack of security in the country in a way that was very different from the president's.
In that press conference, PM Abdiwali said it was well known that Al-Shabab's had escalated their attacks in Mogadishu in recent months and that regular mortar attacks were now a norm in the city. He basically implied that the government did not have the capacity to fight back.
The PM added that he does not want to sound frail or disappoint his listeners, but it is the reality on ground. Having said that, the PM assured the Somali people that with their help, Al- Shabab can be defeated. After that speech, his supporters applauded him as someone who can be trusted with the position he holds since there was no single Somali politician that could be equated to the prime minister in terms of giving a realistic assessment on the ground.
His critics blamed him as sounding weak and less established because, his speech days before attack, was what encouraged Al-Shabab to take such an invasive action for the first time and infiltrate Villa Somalia.
Some analysts have also said they aren't surprised by President Hasan' remark of defending an allegation of corruption and laxity against his government without any independent investigation because it is not the first time that the president denied an allegation against his government. Few months ago when the allegation of corruption at central bank came to light, the president became his own spokesman when he publicly denied any wrongdoing on the part of his government without even attempting to establish the facts of the allegation.
There has been public concerns as to why the president who was not directly linked to the accusation over the central bank fiasco defended his staff directly before any independent investigation was concluded.
Some political analysts concluded that the only way the president could defend his staff without any investigation being done, is that he was personally aware such corruption took place and was meant to send a signal to staff members that it is tolerable and he stood behind them. The President is normally expected to be neutral to any accusations or corruption alleged to his government until a final investigation is done and the result of that investigation is made public.
It seems that the president thinks that he can solve all problems by himself by any means necessary. A few months ago, when the president noticed a lack of progress made by the government in terms of all he wanted accomplished including the safety of the Mogadishu and other areas, he resorted to following the best practice followed by transitional presidents, which was to change the prime minister as that would cure all ills.
Now, since he cannot blame the second PM he nominated a little over year, he is trying to paint a picture to the Somali people that everything will be okay since his government will implement the grand plan to wipe out Al-Shabab within months even though the PM who is supposedly expected to execute that plan cannot see the light at end of the tunnel based on the President's recent statement.
Somali people are aware that when the president was elected, he promised that his government's priority top priority would be security, security and security, and the result on the ground, year after, became a lack of security to the point where Al-Shabab militias finally entered inside Villa Somalia, resulting in the killing of senior government officials including director of the prime minister's office.
Instead of denying all the accusations against his government, most analysts suggested that the president should have been neutral to any accusations leveled against his government and let the executive branch led by the PM assign an independent committee to investigate all allegations without interference by his staff. The President should not influence the result of pending investigation by the public by denying the existence of such allegations. By doing this, it sends a bad signal to all that the president is hiding something.
Finally, the president will need to look himself in the mirror and come clean to the people of Somalia who expect a lot from this government, the first one recognized by international community since the collapse of the central government in 1991. He should also be upfront with the Somali people by telling them the situation on the ground as it is like Prime Minister Abdiweli did. Somali people are tired of politicians whose first priority is their career and just want a trustworthy individual that is able to tell them as it is, not a president that is his own spokesman in times of scandals.
Writer: Muhammad Husayn
Source: Alldhacdo in Somali 0000gmt 07 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>