<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2233-3EF9-470A-5FAE"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Families awarded $3.5M in fatal toxic-fume case </title><source>The Star-Ledger (Newark, New Jersey)</source><author>Thomas Zambito, STAR-LEDGER STAFF</author><text><![CDATA[The families of two workers who died when they inhaled toxic fumes while cleaning a storage tank at a Linden dry cleaning plant in 2007 were awarded $3.5 million yesterday by a jury in state Superior Court.
Victor Diaz, 42, of Hillside, and Carlos Diaz, 41, of Paterson, succumbed to a deadly mix of chemicals that included sulfuric acid, which singed their skin and paralyzed their lungs, court papers say.
In separate lawsuits, the men's families accused North East Linen Supply Co. of causing their deaths by intentionally disregarding the safety of their employees by exposing them to chemicals they knew were dangerous.
Victor Diaz's estate will get $1.9 million and Carlos Diaz's $1.6 million, according to the verdict delivered after a three-week trial. The men were not related.
Victor Diaz's lawyer, Jeffrey S. Mandel, said his client -- a father of three -- had no experience cleaning tanks and was sent in to power wash the tank wearing surgical gloves, a lint mask and plastic duct tape over his shoes.
Diaz endured chemical-induced burns over nearly 50 percent of his body, including first-degree burns to his face, forehead, eyes and esophagus.
"It was a grotesque death that didn't have to happen," said Mandel. "He was a truck driver asked to come in on the weekend. He was told it was wastewater, and it turned out to be sulfuric acid."
Emergency workers were forced to wait nearly three hours before retrieving Diaz's body because a metered device detected dangerous levels of carbon monoxide in the tank, the lawsuit said.
The 20,000-gallon steel tank was used to dilute highly toxic chemical waste from dry cleaning.
The company had recently received a complaint alleging that chemicals above a safe limit were being discharged into the municipal sewer system, the lawsuit says.
John O'Dwyer, the lawyer for the family of Carlos Diaz, did not respond to a request for comment.
Edward DePascale, the lawyer who represented Rhode Island-based North East Linen Supply, could not be reached for comment.
In June 2008, the federal Occupational Safety and Health Administration cited the company for violating multiple safety and health violations and recommended a fine of $79,000.
]]></text></news-item>