<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="22C8-D959-9A61-8D3F"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>THE POINT IS ...</title><source>The Examiner Newspaper</source><author>Natalie Ashdown</author><text><![CDATA[Dog rules ignored
ABOUT 40 per cent of dog walkers follow the clearly marked rule "dogs must be on lead at all times" put up at several entrances to the beach sites at Greens Beach.
The rest can't be bothered to follow the regulations, as it doesn't show the sum of the fine.
On March 8, while sitting at the beach for 112 hours, we counted altogether 21 dogs not being held on the lead, one of them taking off wildly.
The council could fill their empty pockets by letting someone have a relaxed day, sitting at the beach on a weekend, incognito of course.
- H SCHETTER, Grindelwald.
Sale of Nazi items
IN RESPONSE to Mr Waldon's letter (The Examiner, March 9), I would like to thank him for his clarification on the legal status of the sale of Nazi paraphernalia.
However, Mr Waldon misses my point in focusing his reply on the origins of the swastika.
I also studied World War II in college and am aware of the symbol's beginning.
By writing to The Examiner last week I was highlighting my dismay and disgust at these items being for sale and questioned its legality, and at the very least the seller's moral judgment.
By doing so I was hoping to create debate on the issue.
Mr Waldon may be impartial to the sale of these items and that is his right. I for one believe it should be illegal.
- ADAM SAUNDERS, South Launceston.
Property rights
ACCORDING to Aaron Lane (The Examiner, March 11), "It is one of the fundamental principles of property rights that individuals who own property take care of it. Environmental disasters occur when no property rights have been allocated". Wow.
Wonder how the people of Morwell feel about that with their privately owned smouldering coal mine?
Has he forgotten Bhopal?
The Third World has a deplorable record for environmental pollution but often private companies are implicated - in New Guinea (Ok Tedi mining waste discharge), Borneo (massive deforestation), Hungary (massive tailings spill).
One suspects that another meaning for IPA (the Institute of Public Affairs) may well be the Institute of Permanent Amnesia.
- TONY NEWPORT, Hillwood.
]]></text></news-item>