<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="231E-E341-D172-C761"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Massachusetts: MassDEP Fines Millbury Business Entities $23,570 for Operating an Unlicensed Solid Waste Processing Facility</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Department of Energy and Environmental Affairs, The State of Massachusetts has issued the following news release:
The Massachusetts Department of Environmental Protection (MassDEP) has assessed a $23,570 penalty to three entities that have the same operating address for failure to obtain a site assignment from the Millbury Board of Health and MassDEP for the operation of a solid waste facility in Millbury. Westboro Road Realty Trust, Treeline Construction, Inc. and Atlantic Construction Services, Inc. were using a parcel at 130 Westborough Street as a dumping ground for rock, masonry and concrete.
On December 7, 2011, a MassDEP inspection of the site, responding to a complaint, discovered continued storage of rock, masonry and concrete on the ground. A previous Notice of Noncompliance required the removal of all materials from the site, citing prohibitions against open dumping. The December 2011 inspection revealed that no removal of material had occurred.
In a recently signed consent order, the three entities agreed to pay the penalty and they have developed a compliance plan for MassDEP approval. The approved compliance plan includes the removal and recycling of all stored solid waste from the site by early summer 2014.
“Business owners have important responsibilities under Commonwealth regulations to obtain appropriate local and state approvals before managing solid wastes,” said Lee Dillard Adams, director of MassDEP’s Central Regional Office in Worcester.
MassDEP is responsible for ensuring clean air and water, safe management and recycling of solid and hazardous wastes, timely cleanup of hazardous waste sites and spills, and the preservation of wetlands and coastal resources.
For further information please visit: http://www.mass.gov/eea/
]]></text></news-item>