<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="237E-6581-AB7C-447F"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Unions now lack clout to win wage increases</title><source>The Examiner Newspaper</source><author>Barry Prismall</author><text><![CDATA[UNIONS don't matter much to the broad economy these days.
Yes, they matter to the Labor Party because they fund it and also hurt it by putting crooked unionists like Craig Thomson ito Parliament.
While the opportunities are diminishing, some unions can gain excessive wage rises in protected sectors of the economy (as can non-unionists and executives).
Sometimes they still matter to ill-treated workers with no other source of support.
The modern union's role is not always adversarial. Employers pleading for corporate welfare find them a useful ally.
At present, unions have teamed up with Victoria's Coalition government and the British defence giant BAE Systems to demand that Tony Abbott's government immediately give the company a contract to build new warships at its Williamstown shipyard,
although they aren't needed at this stage and can be imported more cheaply when needed.
On Friday, BAE announced global earnings for 2013 before interest, tax and amortisation of 1.925 billion ($3.573 billion).
Unions now lack the clout to win damaging wage increases across the economy.
With unemployment edging up, the latest figures show the wage price index rose by only 2.6 per cent in the year to December.
This is slightly under inflation and well below the average 3.5 per cent wages increase since the late 1990s.
As David Bassanese noted in The Australian Financial Review on Thursday, unsurprisingly, the index suggests the labour market is more flexible now that only 13 per cent of private sector workers are union members. Total membership is 18 per cent
versus 50 per cent in the mid- 1980s.
In this context, Bassanese described the recent call from the boss of the Australian Workers Union, Paul Howes, for a "grand compact" between unions and business as 'somewhat laughable".
The comment is underlined by the drop in wages share of GDP from 62 per cent 40 years ago to about 52 per cent. Profits share has risen by about 10 percentage points.
The unions' problems run deeper than financial malfeasance by some officials.
However, the despicable behaviour of Thomson and Michael Williamson, while officials of the Health Service Union, hardly helps.
On Tuesday, a magistrate convicted Thomson of fraud in misusing union funds for his own benefit, including visits to brothels.
Thomson was a Federal Labor MP by April 2009 when Fairfax Media published revelations about his fraudulent behaviour.
However, Labor again endorsed him as a candidate for the 2010 election and paid a large part of his legal bills.
It's then PM Julia Gillard told Parliament he retained her "complete confidence".
Board positions paid lucrative fees.
Williamson's behaviour, while president of the Labor party and the HSU, involves far more money, more than $5 million according to a civil claim from the union.
Williamson has pleaded guilty to misusing union funds. Apart from a salary of over $500,000 at a union whose members are poorly paid, he received lucrative fees from board positions on industry super funds and First State Super.
Last year, the NSW anti- corruption commission made adverse findings against a former mining union official John Maitland who made up to $15million by obtaining coal mining rights from the state Labor government.
Labor's problems aren't confined to "rogue" union bosses.
Last year, the commission found that the businessman-Labor factional boss Eddie Obeid had acted corruptly in relation to the granting of mining leases, potentially generating $100 million for his family and associates. Obeid was also a good
Labor fund-raiser.
However, Labor remains beholden to the union movement for the main source of campaign finance. This would cease if Labor successfully supported a ban on both union and corporate donations to political parties.
The Australian Financial Review
]]></text></news-item>