<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="246B-522B-7F43-77AB"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Congresswoman Lowey Calls for Action to Address Gas Leaks in Wake of Tragedy in East Harlem and Local Scares</title><source>Targeted News Service</source><author>Targeted News Service</author><text><![CDATA[Rep. Nita Lowey, D-N.Y. (17th CD), issued the following news release:
Congresswoman Nita Lowey (D-Westchester/Rockland), the senior Democrat on the House Appropriations Committee, today called on Con Edison and Orange & Rockland Utilities to step up action to address gas leaks.
"Protecting the health and safety of local residents is paramount," said Lowey. "As the investigation continues in East Harlem, prevention is essential to ensure that no more lives are lost in explosions resulting from gas leaks. From more training and education of consumers and construction workers to faster action to address existing leaks, we can and must do more to protect the public."
Lowey sent a letter to the utilities after residents were evacuated from the Harbors at Haverstraw condominiums in Rockland County, during a week that had seen numerous fatalities at the site of a gas explosion in East Harlem.
Lowey was at the time working with Julie Kirshner, who contacted her in February to request assistance addressing an ongoing gas leak in Harrison. She and a neighbor had been complaining about a gas odor to Con Ed for months. Con Ed told Lowey that it was the least serious type of leak, and, therefore, repairs would not begin for six more months.
" 'Not a dangerous leak' are words that don't go well together," said Kirshner. "I have been calling Con Edison for months. They come, inspect the leak, but don't fix it. Of course I want to believe Con Edison when they say it's fine, but there's a reason why the odorous materials are put in the gas - to alert you when there's a leak. I felt safe until the gas explosion in New York City. Do I feel safe now? Not really. Fixing a leak is not like fixing a meter."
Orange & Rockland has in recent years stepped up its response time. Yesterday's evacuation was reportedly the result ofa construction accident following the failure to alert O&R to the work near the gas line at the condo complex. Fire and utility officials secured the site.
"While utilities must prioritize the greatest threats to our communities, the goal must be to eliminate and prevent any dangers to the health and safety of local residents quickly," Lowey wrote in the letter. "In the interest of public safety, I hope that your companies will aggressively and urgently assess what more you can do to reduce the risk of gas leaks through training, consumer education, expedited repairs to known leaks, and any other safety measures you deem appropriate. I will work closely with local utilities, emergency responders, and residents to ensure that all protections possible are in place."
Full text of the letter can be found here and below.
March 14, 2014
Mr. John McAvoy
President and Chief Executive Officer, Con Edison
Cooper Station
P.O. Box 138
New York, NY 10276
Mr. Timothy P. Cawley
President and Chief Executive Officer, Orange & Rockland Utilities
390 W. Route 59
Spring Valley, NY 10977
Dear Mr. McAvoy and Mr. Cawley:
In light of the fatal explosion in New York City and yesterday's evacuations in Haverstraw, I am particularly alarmed to learn that it can take longer than six months for a reported gas leak to be repaired.
On February 24, my constituent Julie Kirshner, of Harrison, contacted me about a gas leak in the Park Ridge neighborhood. According to Ms. Kirshner, she noticed a gas odor when she moved to the neighborhood in August. She and at least one neighbor alerted Con Edison, which sent a crew to investigate but did not fix the leak.
My staff contacted Con Ed and was informed that the leak was deemed a "Type 3," the least serious in its classification system, and that it would be fixed within six months, sooner if it worsened. There is no such thing as a safe leak. Ms. Kirshner is living in fear.
The March 12 explosion in East Harlem claimed eight lives and caused dozens of injuries. Yesterday, 35 of my constituents in Rockland County were evacuated from their building at Harbors at Haverstraw when a contractor hit a gas main. O&R and local authorities capped the leak. I applaud the response and am aware that response times in Rockland are improving. However, two years ago a natural gas explosion at a home in West Haverstraw injured two firefighters and an O&R employee, and last June an explosion at Nyack College resulted in the injury of two students and a police officer. We must work harder to prevent leaks from developing into explosions.
While utilities must prioritize the greatest threats to our communities, the goal must be to eliminate and prevent any dangers to the health and safety of local residents quickly. In the interest of public safety, I hope that your companies will aggressively and urgently assess what more you can do to reduce the risk of gas leaks through training, consumer education, expedited repairs to known leaks, and any other safety measures you deem appropriate. I will work closely with local utilities, emergency responders, and residents to ensure that all protections possible are in place.
Sincerely,
Nita M. Lowey
Member of Congress
Copyright Targeted News Services
TNS 30VitinMar-140315-4668610 30VitinMar
]]></text></news-item>