<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="247E-1A7A-AA78-C3CF"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Business of politics</title><source>TOI.com &amp; ET.com Blogs</source><author>Jug Suraiya</author><text><![CDATA[Trotsky called for perpetual revolution. Indian politicians today might paraphrase this Trotskyite formula and call for perpetual elections. For election time is money-spending and money-making time.
According to reported estimates the forthcoming elections for the 16th Lok Sabha will pump in some Rs 30,000 crore into the country's economy – an amount equal to that of the special stimulus the Centre gave in 2008 when India felt the ripple effects of the global financial crisis triggered in the US. The Rs 30,000 crore price tag of Ballot Box 2014 is double that of what was estimated to have been spent on the 2009 elections. Obviously, ‘money power' is increasing and not decreasing in keeping the wheels of Indian democracy in motion. Commentators claim that the injection of such huge funds into the market – in fields as diverse as advertising, transport, air travel, etc – will help to boost the sagging economy, which has witnessed a sharp slowdown in growth, from 9%+ a few years ago to barely 4.9% now. Most of the money being spent during the run-up to the polls is likely to be in the form of cash. And to keep tabs on this, the Election Commission, playing party-pooper, has issued special directives to all airports, airfields and helipads, particularly in remote areas, to check passenger baggage for large amounts of currency. Anyone carrying more than Rs 10 lakh in cash, or one kg in gold, will be reported to the income tax authorities, and be made to explain the source of the money or the bullion, and the reason for its transportation. Though more and more people with a corporate or professional background are now entering politics – particularly after ex-public servant Arvind Kejriwal launched his Aam Aadmi Party – in India the political arena is still overwhelmingly dominated by those who have no career experience, or qualifications, other than standing for elections and trying to win them, by hook or crook, only too often by crook. Regrettably, all too many of such full-time professional politicians have given Indian politics a bad name. But now with the pre-election clouds about to shower money down onto the parched earth and help to regenerate the withering economy, the ‘business' of politics might come to be seen in a kindlier light by its critics who decry the role of ‘money power' in elections. By helping to revive the economy, the business of politics as practised in India seems to be good for overall business. That's the silver lining to remember when we lament the many dark clouds of scams and corruption that loom over our political horizon. jug.suraiya@timesgroup.com
]]></text></news-item>