<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="24A3-6493-EE56-F83B"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Hard-selling, deal-making National's mode of business</title><source>The Dominion Post (Wellington, New Zealand)</source><author>#BB# Dave</author><text><![CDATA[IWILL not make many friends on the Left when I admit that there are things I like about Judith Collins.
She's confident - admittedly to the point of arrogance on occasions - and direct. She has a good sense of humour and is accessible - as her many Twitter skirmishes demonstrate. On some issues - her support for water fluoridation, for example - Ms Collins' sensible, scientific view is refreshing, and her attempts to prevent online bullying have met with widespread approval. The justice, ACC and ethnic affairs minister sits on the Right of the National Party and is not scared to take swift action. That's why she's nicknamed "Crusher".
Boy racer incidents plummeted since she introduced car-crushing. Yet there's little hard evidence that it is due to her very public, though rarely enforced, legislation. As any first-year science student will tell you, correlation and causation are very different. That's why you don't read about the decline in major earthquakes since David Cunliffe became Labour leader.
Nevertheless, Crusher's tough stance on boy racers gave her the Iron Lady- type status that her hero Margaret Thatcher achieved when she sunk the General Belgrano as it was sailing away from the Falklands.
About eight months ago, Paula Bennett announced some highly popular child welfare reforms, one of which prevented suspected child abusers from being near children. I'm all for reducing child abuse, but putting 10-year restraining orders on people simply suspected of a crime horrified me, and I said so online. "Pathetic, Dave," replied Ms Bennett's staunch ally Ms Collins. "So you'd let any of the adults who so- called 'cared' for the Kahui twins look after kids?"
My answer was, sadly, yes, if they hadn't been convicted of a crime. Headmistress Collins scolded me - I should be ashamed for believing Opposition lies.
But it was bluster. This part of the Vulnerable Children Bill has been put on hold as a regulatory impact statement said it was an "infringement of fundamental human rights". Yet we've heard little about this back-down.
It worries me far more that our justice minister staunchly supported a draft law that obviously infringed fundamental human rights than her having a private dinner in China that she didn't report. Strangely enough, since the revelations about her Oravida meetings in China, Countess Homogensied, as Grant Robertson cruelly but brilliantly dubbed Ms Collins, seems far more self-effacing. Yet when the Oravida allegations first emerged, the hubristic minister counter- attacked in true Crusher style.
Surely promoting New Zealand companies is a good thing? Well, yes, but maybe a few besides the one your husband is a director of. You could be forgiven for forgetting that Ms Collins is minister of justice, not our economic development and trade minister.
So why does a justice minister have such an interest in trade with China? I would have thought that she might have more interest in the draconian Chinese justice system, which puts some people to death. Then there's the appalling treatment that dissidents receive.
Yet it seems that dairy products - whether those made by Fonterra or Oravida - occupied much of her time there. Is that in her job description? I look forward to Economic Development Minister Steven Joyce calling for the NZSO to improve its intonation and Foreign Affairs Minister Murray McCully introducing a law to ensure safer playground equipment.
Yet it's not only Ms Collins who seems quiet about China's seedier side. Since the Fonterra botulism botchup, our biggest trading partner has been treated with governmental kid gloves.
It's also why government minsters quietly ignore talk of gambling addiction when they're around Sky City executives, and why Rio Tinto's massive profits, even though they're receiving government handouts, go without official comment.
I'm all for trade with China, but there are other things in life besides money. As well as embarrassing her leader, Ms Collins has contributed to the impression that this Government sees economic growth best achieved by hard selling and deal-making, even if it flouts a few rules. Meanwhile, justice and transparency seem to be for Left-wing sissies.
]]></text></news-item>