<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="24F4-3E32-A398-4E0E"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Colorado: Chief Engineer/Transportation Program Director</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Division of Human of Resources, The State of Colorado has issued the following job opportunities:
Job Title: Chief Engineer/Transportation Program Director Class Title: MANAGEMENT Type of Announcement: This announcement is not governed by the selection processes of the classified personnel system. Applications will be considered from residents and non-residents of Colorado.
Closing Date/Time: Sun. 03/23/14 11:59 PM Mountain Time Primary Physical Work Address: 4201 E. Arkansas Ave. Denver, CO 80222 Salary: $10,000.00 - $12,000.00 Monthly Job Type: Full Time Location: Denver, Colorado How To Apply: Thank you for your interest. Submit an on-line application by clicking the link below or submit a State of Colorado Application for Announced Vacancy and all supplemental questions according to the instructions provided below. Failure to submit a complete and timely application may result in the rejection of your application. Applicants are responsible for ensuring that application materials are received by the appropriate Human Resources office before the closing date and time listed above. If not applying on-line, submit application to: Joe Czajka CDOT 4201 E. Arkansas Ave Denver CO 80222 Department Contact Information: Joe Czajka Workforce Staffing Manager Joseph.czajka@state.co.us 303.757.9150 Methods of Appointment: This position is not part of the classified state personnel system.
Department Information
Close Date is extended to 3/23/2014
Applications will be reviewed beginning March 10, 2014 and CDOT will continue to accept applications until filled. Please submit your application early.
About CDOT The Colorado Department of Transportation is a 1.2 billion dollar business dedicated to provide the best multi-modal transportation system for Colorado that most effectively and safely moves people, goods, and information. Capital construction is typically about $600 million a year or half of the total budget. CDOT, with more than 3,300 employees and scores of public and private partners throughout the state, is responsible for multi-modal engineering, planning, and roadway maintenance for a 9,146 mile highway system including 3,447 bridges which handles over 27 billion vehicle miles of travel. Although the Interstate system accounts for only about 10% (914 miles) of the total mileage in the state system, 40% of all travel takes place on our Interstate highways. In addition, CDOT’s Aeronautics Division supports Colorado’s general aviation community through distribution of entitlement funds, an aviation grant program, and long-range system planning in partnership with Colorado’s general aviation airports. CDOT’s Division of Transit and Rail is responsible for the planning, development, finance, operation, and integration of transit and rail servicesinto Colorado’s overall transportation system. CDOT’s core values of safety, people, integrity, customer service, excellence and respect make CDOT a great place to work, making Colorado a great place to live.
Description of Job: The Chief Engineer serves as a key member of CDOT’s Senior Management Team (SMT), reporting to the Executive Director (ED) and working closely with the Deputy Director (Chief Operating Officer). As a principal strategist and steward of resources for achieving CDOT’s state transportation mission, the Chief Engineer provides executive leadership and guidance for achieving visionary plans and best practices in planning, design, construction, and program management/delivery for transportation systems statewide. Visionary plans and best practices are accomplished through day to day leadership and supervision of directors and managers of CDOT’s Divisions of Transportation Development, Transit and Rail, Staff Engineering Services, and Office of Major Project Development. The Chief Engineer will also take a leadership role in the establishment of a Program Management Office dedicated to improving CDOT’s capabilities in this mission critical area. The Chief explores new opportunities and ideas and integrates them into CDOT processes and culture in a way that brings value to both internal and external stakeholders. Primary Roles and Responsibilities:
Leadership for and supervision of directors and managers of CDOT’s Division of Transportation Development, Division of Transit and Rail, Staff Engineering Services, Office of Major Project Development, and soon to be created Program Management Office; Serve as key resource to CDOT’s SMT that helps establish and implement organizational and policy changes and future process and system improvements to ensure a well-coordinated and efficient state transportation system; Serves as the senior level engineering technical expert for CDOT, responsible for transportation planning, design, and construction program for Colorado; Analyze engineering, financial, and performance data affecting Colorado's transportation systems and provide sound decisions and recommendations affecting short and long range policy formulation and strategic plans; Ensure the effective and efficient delivery of CDOT’s statewide transportation project program; Provide high level oversight of a multi-department program management organization and delivery over a statewide geography; Work collaboratively with other CDOT Headquarters and regional staff on facilitating and standardizing program delivery statewide; Fully integrate CDOT Office of Major Project Development into the project development process; Serve as CDOT’s engineering representative to the Federal Highway Administration (FHWA) and American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials (AASHTO); Identify and formulate critical intra-CDOT (e.g., Region program delivery, DTD, PMO, OMPD, etc.) relationships including roles and responsibilities intended to compliment and optimize staff resources and reduce work redundancies; Assist with the implementation and start-up of a Program Management Office; Other duties as assigned.
During the first 6 months in the position:
The Chief Engineer will partner with the ED and Deputy Director to establish the Program Management Office and effect other organizational changes to create an effective delivery capability Develop and execute an effective communication management strategy to keep the ED and Deputy Director aware of programs and initiatives affecting CDOT’s highest priorities.
Work Environment: · A passion for safety · Travel within the State of Colorado as well as occasional out of state is required · This position may be subject to many interruptions to handle multiple projects · Operate in a politically sensitive environment
For further information please visit: http://agency.governmentjobs.com
]]></text></news-item>