<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="25FA-CDA7-DBCC-F670"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Anti-union workers at VW's Chattanooga plant file suit against automaker and UAW</title><source>IHS Global Insight</source><author>Stephanie Brinley</author><text><![CDATA[Several Volkswagen (VW) workers opposed to joining the United Automobile Workers (UAW) union have filed a lawsuit against the union and the automaker, reports theWall Street Journal. The five workers are being represented by the National Right to Work Foundation, according to aDetroit Newsreport. The suit alleges co-operation between the UAW and VW violates US labour laws that block companies from providing aid or "things of value" to trade unions. The suit has been filed in the federal district court for Eastern Tennessee, and alleges that VW allowed the union to use an office in the plant, agreed to "align" communications about the recent vote on unionisation at VW's Chattanooga plant, organised workers' meetings during company time when the UAW asked for support, and prevented managers from voicing any opinions about the vote. The suit alleges these actions have value and asks the court to prohibit VW from providing further assistance. UAW president Bob King said the lawsuit is another example of "outside interference" in the union's efforts to organise, according to theDetroit Newsreport.
Significance:The suit follows the decision of the US National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) that the anti-union workers in Tennessee can defend the results of the vote on unionisation at an expected future hearing (seeUnited States: 13 March 2014:). The ongoing dispute is said to be slowing VW's announcement on whether a new mid-size sport utility vehicle (SUV) will be built in Tennessee or in Mexico. While VW's global sales are strengthening and the company this week said it expects to break the 10-million-unit mark in 2014, US sales have been slowing and an entry into the mid-size SUV segment is likely to assist VW in reaching its sales target of 800,000 units in the country by 2017. IHS Automotive forecasts the new SUV will add at least 50,000 units to VW of America's sales total each year, once it arrives in 2016 - whether built in the United States or in Mexico.
]]></text></news-item>