<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2630-99FA-15B1-2FBF"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Programme summary of Iranian TV news 1030 gmt 15 Mar 14</title><source>BBC Monitoring Trans Caucasus UnitSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A. Headlines
B. News reports:
1. 1032 Religious video is shown on the occasion of the death anniversary of Fatimah, daughter of Prophet Muhammad.
2. 1034 Funeral ceremonies have been held for 95 unidentified "martyrs" of the Iran-Iraq war. Video shows the ceremonies.
3. 1035 At today's Majlis open session, Majlis Speaker Larijani said that Islamic Iran is considered a great country in fighting with narcotics, and criticized United Nations for criticizing Iran for applying death penalty to drug dealers. Larijani also spoke about nuclear negotiations, saying: "It seems that America does not have anything new to say. Therefore, with new provocations and in unclear situation, it wants to change the path of the negotiations". Video shows the Majlis session.
4. 1040 At a news conference, Malaysian Prime Minister Razak has said that it is possible that the disappeared plane might be hijacked. However, he added, that investigations in this regard still continues.
C. 1043 Recap of news headlines.
D. 1044 Weather.
E. More news:
1. 1045 The head of Supreme Leader's office, Hojjat ol-Eslam val-Moslemin Mohammadi-Golpaygani, has travelled to Bushehr Province to inaugurate four cultural and educational projects in Kangan and Asaluyeh counties. Video shows his meeting with a number of provincial officials and clerics.
2. 1045 Red Crescent Society has started rescue and relief exercises ahead of the Iranian New Year holidays. Video shows the exercises.
3. 1047 Video report on accommodation and restaurants on provincial roads ahead of the Iranian New Year holidays.
4. 1049 Video report on a museum in Mashhad City.
5. 1051 Report on latest sanctions imposed on Iran by the USA. Video shows US Secretary of State John Kerry speaking at a news conference.
6. 1052 Report on Foreign Minister Zarif's news conference held today.
F. News in brief:
1. 1053 Iran's Central Bank has approved new bank notes.
2. 1053 A ceremony has been held to inaugurate a new refinery for refining diesel fuel with Euro 4 standards in Markazi Province.
3. 1054 Deputy Vice-President for Management Development and Human Resources Mahmud Asgari-Azad has said that the number of managers in government sectors will decrease.
4. 1054 Venezuela's Foreign Minister has labelled US Secretary of State Kerry as the "murderer" of the people of Venezuela for provoking them to participate in protests against the Venezuelan government.
5. 1055 Afghan President Karzai has warned foreign powers not to intervene in the presidential election of this country.
6. 1055 People in Yemen have held rallies in support of the Palestinian people.
7. 1056 Video shows rainfall in West Azarbayjan Province.
G. Other reports:
1. 1056 Reporter interviews people about saving energy and decreasing energy consumption.
2. 1100 Reporter interviews a farmer who produces mangos in Sistan-Baluchestan Province.
H. 1102 Sport.
I. 1105 Calendar and prayer times.
J. 1105 Recap of news headlines.
1106 End of bulletin.
Source: Vision of the Islamic Republic of Iran Network 1, Tehran, in Persian 1030gmt 15 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>