<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="263B-4F4E-4BAF-63C2"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>DKSH Holdings (Malaysia) keeps rising: up 3.4% in 3 days</title><source>News Bites Asian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[DKSH Holdings (Malaysia) Berhad (MYX:5908), Malaysia's 36th largest trading/services company by market capitalisation, extended its gains Monday, rising an additional 15.0 sen (or 1.9%) to close at MYR7.90. The shares have lifted 26.0 sen (or 3.4%) over the past three trading days. Compared with the FTSE Bursa Malaysia 100 Index which fell 36.3 points (or 0.3%) in the three days, this represented a relative price increase of 3.7%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on DKSH Holdings (Malaysia), please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051911770314235
Bullish SignalsUptrend- The stock rose 1.9%, for a 3-day rise of 3.4%, on high volatility today and expanding price range.- The stock hit a year-high 9th time in one month and 17th time in three months.- Rises to Falls: in the past month the number of rises outnumbered falls 12:6 or 2:1.- The Moving Average Convergence Divergence (MACD) indicator of 12-day Exponential Moving Average (EMA) of 7.6 minus the 26-day EMA of 7.42 is positive 0.18 suggesting a bullish signal. Both EMA prices are rising, another bullish signal.- A two-bagger in the past year, the present value of MYR1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in DKSH Holdings (Malaysia) is MYR2,520, including a capital gain of MYR1,469 and dividend reinvested of MYR52.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Earnings of 16 [19.0]. We estimate DKSH Holdings (Malaysia) stock is trading at a current year P/E of 9.6 and a forward year P/E of 5.7. - Price/Sales of 0.3 [1.6]. We estimate DKSH Holdings (Malaysia) stock is trading at a current year Price/Sales of 0.2 and a forward year Price/Sales of 0.2. - Return on Equity 26.7% [10.0%].- Year-on-Year Earnings Growth of 75% [17.1%].- Price/Earnings/Growth of 0.2 [1.1].- Return on Assets 6.1% [4.5%].- Return on Capital Employed 30.4% [9.6%].Other Bullish Signals:- Interest cover defined by EBIT/I is 14.4 times. This indicates it is less leveraged. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 1. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity is high at 26.7%. This is computed as net profit margin of 1.6% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 3.7 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 4.4. Also, this has improved from 20% last year.
- Net Profit margin is positive and has seen consecutive rises in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]
- Net Profit margin, EBIT margin and EBITDA margin are positive and have seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 3,922 shares worth MYR30,984 (US$9,447) traded. The volume was 0.9 times the average trading of 4,475 shares. Beta: the Beta of DKSH Holdings (Malaysia) stock is 1.7. A Beta greater than 1 suggests this is a high risk, high return stock with volatility greater than that of the market.Bearish Signals:- The 1.1% discount to 12-month high of MYR7.99 against the 150.0% premium to 12-month low of MYR3.16 suggests the climb might be peaking. Overbought/Bearish/Resistance Signals- The Relative Strength Index (RSI) of 77.2 has penetrated the overbought line of 70, suggesting the price gain of 12.9% in the last 14 days is unusually high. - The stock is overbought according to the Williams % R indicator of -8.4, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day high of MYR7.99. - The Money Flow Index [MFI] is 82.6 suggesting an overbought 14-day trend, being above 80. The Money Ratio of 4.8 suggests positive money flow was 4.8 times negative money flow. - The Stochastic indicator of 96.5 has broken through the overbought line of 80.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price to Book of 4.4 [2.6]. - Dividend yield of 1.5% [3.0%].Other Bearish Signals:- Total Liabilities/ EBITDA of 7.9 is more than or equal to 5, this compares unfavourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - Net profit margin has averaged 1.1% in the last 3 years. This suggests the company is less profitable with a low margin of safety.- The Enterprise Value/EBITDA multiple of 11.1 compares unfavourably with sector average of 8.3. Enterprise Value is estimated at MCap MYR1.2 billion plus net debt of MYR98.5 million plus minority interest of MYR18.1 million and EBITDA is estimated at MYR123 million.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 25: DKSH Holdings (Malaysia): Change in BoardroomDate of change 25/02/2014Name Alexander Stuart DavyAge 56Nationality United Kingdom nationalType of change RedesignationPrevious Position OthersNew Position OthersDirectorate Independent & Non ExecutiveQualifications Mr.Davy graduated from the University of Bristol with a Bachelor of Science degree in Economics.
February 25: DKSH Holdings (Malaysia): Change in Boardroom[News Story] Date of change 25/02/2014Name Thon LekAge 66Nationality MalaysianDesignation OthersDirectorate Independent & Non ExecutiveType of change Resignation Reason Mr.Thon Lek intends to pursue his personal interests. Details of any disagreement that he/she has with the Board of Directors No Whether there are any matters that need to be brought to the attention of the shareholders NoQualifications Bachelor of Economics, majoring in Applied Economics from the University of Malaya.Working experience and occupation Mr.Thon started his career with Harpers Trading (Malaysia) Sdn Bhd in 1971, and held various managerial positions until he was appointed as Managing Director in 1995.
October 29: DKSH Holdings (Malaysia): Announcement[News Story] PROPOSED DISPOSAL BY DKSH HOLDINGS (MALAYSIA) BERHAD OF ITS 51% EQUITY INTEREST IN DKSH TRANSPORT AGENCIES (M) SDN BHD FOR A CASH CONSIDERATION OF RM30,600,000We refer to the Company's announcements released on August 30, 2013 and September 3, 2013 in relation to the Proposed Disposal.
October 17: DKSH Holdings (Malaysia): Announcement[News Story] Proposed disposal of all that piece of leasehold land held under pajakan negeri 3696, lot 52 seksyen 13, bandar petaling jaya, daerah petaling, negeri selangor together with the office and industrial buildings and warehouses erected thereon by dksh central services malaysia sdn bhd to pjd central sdn bhd (formerly known as sun-pjdc sdn bhd)We refer to the Company's announcements released on May 31, 2013, June 5 2013 and August 20, 2013 in relation to the Proposed Disposal.
October 03: DKSH Holdings (Malaysia) substantial shareholder sellsDKSH Holdings (Malaysia) (MYX:5908) substantial shareholder Lembaga Tabung Angkatan Tentera sold 195,800 shares worth approximately MYR1.2 million on September 25, 2013. The selling price was MYR6.0.
October 03: DKSH Holdings (Malaysia) substantial shareholder sellsDKSH Holdings (Malaysia) (MYX:5908) substantial shareholder Lembaga Tabung Angkatan Tentera sold 5,000 shares worth approximately MYR29,950 on September 26, 2013. The selling price was MYR6.0.
October 03: DKSH Holdings (Malaysia) substantial shareholder sellsDKSH Holdings (Malaysia) (MYX:5908) substantial shareholder Lembaga Tabung Angkatan Tentera sold 115,400 shares worth approximately MYR691,246 on September 27, 2013. The selling price was MYR6.0.
ISIN: MYL5908OO008
KL:5908; MK:5908
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>