<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2665-7515-DEC5-4CD3"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Have your say</title><source>The Advertiser (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Drones stupidity It has taken me a while to recover from my laughing fit regarding the location of drones in SA for Australia's border protection.
I suggest we all refer to a classic Yes Minister episode called "Man Overboard", wherein it was quite rightly pointed out that for strategic reasons the British Admiralty Ships Division needed a deep sea port - so it was located in Bath, 30 miles inland.
So now we have our drones based in SA to protect us from the Japanese whaling threat and invading fairy penguins from the south.
I'm sorry, but to me the greatest concerns of illegal arrivals, possible military threats, and humanitarian aid to assist in disasters, always occur north of Australia.
Basing these drones in SA is ridiculous. Put them in Darwin or Broome where they will be able to respond quickly - and not in Adelaide. Unless the Government fears an invasion from New Zealand - or Kangaroo Island.
ALAN JONES, Adelaide.
Customs hold-ups I FULLY agree with Sean Rahaley (The Advertiser, 14/3/14) when he says that Adelaide Airport cannot cope if more than one international arrival occurs at a time.
We returned from a holiday in Malaysia last June on a flight that landed around 7am. As we entered the baggage claim/customs area we were met by an already overcrowded barn full of soldiers waiting to collect bags.
They had just returned from a tour of duty in Afghanistan and were naturally anxious to get home to loved ones after many months away. Yet these brave young men, who had been serving our country, had to wait in line with returning holiday-makers and incoming tourists for more than one hour.
I believe they should have been given priority and taken through customs in a separate area. I was pleased to see many Australians stood aside and invited soldiers to go ahead of them in the queue once they had reclaimed their bags, but some overseas tourists tried to push ahead of the queue, disgusted with the long wait.
Surely when two or three flights all arrive together about 7am there should be some way a modern airport could arrange for enough customs officers to process passengers without such a lengthy delay?
CLIVE FORSTER, Coromandel Valley.
Taxing SA roads WITH 60 per cent of the price of fuel being state and federal government tax plus GST, I would think we are already paying enough for every kilometre we drive.
And country folk don't have the luxury of public transport - every place we want to go we have to drive. If the government wants to save a few dollars, get rid of the pencil-pushing nitwits who come up with these ridiculous ideas.
CHRIS DOHNT, Snowtown.
Society's monsters THERE is something radically wrong with a society that allows monsters like the killers of Daniel Morcombe and Jill Meagher to walk free and reoffend.
P. ALLISON, West Lakes.
Sentence sickens IT was sickening to read of the manifestly inadequate sentencing and serving time of a serial paedophile Brett Cowan for previous offences against children.
JOANNE HOUGH, Keith.
Legally let down THAT repeat offender Brett Cowan was ever released after his first crime is unconscionable, unacceptable and appalling.
How many hideous crimes must these perpetrators perform before our pathetic legal system does what it is paid to do - protect the innocent.
SUE PEARCE, Hawthorn.
Multi-task driver WHO says men can't do two things at once? While walking my dogs on Friday morning, I had a semi driver coming down the hill towards me having an animated conversation on a mobile phone in his right hand, while changing gear with his left hand.
One speculates as to how he was steering.
GAIL MANSON, Murray Bridge.
Long ticket wait I AM becoming increasingly concerned about the Rolling Stones concert in Adelaide. The tickets were bought a long time ago but many people have not received them. Sorry organisers, this isn't good enough.MARGARET DAVIES, Hallet Cove.
]]></text></news-item>