<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="266A-E14E-8D0D-5F8B"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Children bear the brunt of Syria's brutal conflict</title><source>Weekend Australian</source><author>JOHN LYONS, MIDDLE EAST CORRESPONDENT</author><text><![CDATA[``HELL is better.'' Those words were uttered by a mother in Syria as she desperately tried to keep her baby alive on water and almost no solid food.
The 29-year-old woman was trapped in Yarmouk, a suburb of the capital, Damascus.
When Syria's war began three years ago today, nobody could have imagined the devastating toll: not just the number of dead but the legions of walking dead with their shattered lives, hollowed faces and empty eyes.
More than 140,000 people have been killed and 5.5 million children made refugees -- four million inside Syria and 1.5 million outside.
UNICEF's description today is chilling: ``Syria is now one of the most dangerous places on earth to be a child.''
They are now warning that millions of young people are in danger of going from a ``brutalised generation'' to a ``lost generation''.
One woman trying to help this brutalised generation is Brisbane nurse Jane MacPhail, who has worked with thousands of children who have fled Syria to neighbouring Jordan.
MacPhail says the savagery occurring in Syria today was comparable to that which occurred in Liberia, where she worked with child soldiers.
In three years Syria has gone from one of the cradles of Arab civilisation to a country where the buildings are ruined and the people traumatised.
Before the war it was one of the fastest-growing tourist destinations.
Damascus was a thriving metropolis with old villas converted into boutique hotels, their courtyards displaying some of the extraordinary tiles and artworks of Syria's rich history.
Thousands flocked to the markets of Damascus and the antique shops and outdoor restaurants that dominated the capital and cities such as Aleppo and Homs.
Children accompanied their parents to markets, ice-cream shops and cafes in a country where family was central.
But children now dream of death rather than games, blood rather than toys.
``I dream I am carrying a dead man,'' says one 10-year-old girl, Fatima.
``I dream that someone is coming to kill me, to eat me,'' says a small boy, Marwan.
These children are among the hundreds of thousands who have fled Syria.
Nowhere typifies the horror of Syria better than Yarmouk.
It was to an official from the UN that the mother said ``hell is better''.
For the first two months of Khaled's life, his mother, Zahra, breastfed him, but that stopped because of her own poor diet.
Then for two months he survived on water and almost no solids.
He was about to die when a UN doctor intervened and after 20 days of food and medication, he recovered.
Credible reports given to aid workers say that children are being targeted for killing; infants have been killed by snipers, summarily executed, tortured to death, gang raped and forced to the frontlines as human shields where they are made to stand between tanks and fighters.
The targeting of children was highlighted in the massacre in Houla in May 2012: 108 people were killed, including 49 children, many of whom had had their throats cut or were shot in the head at point-blank range.
The UN, after an investigation, believed the massacre was carried out by Alawite militiamen working with soldiers.
A British doctor has reported children as young as two with gunshot wounds to the head and neck, and pregnant women being shot in the abdomen.
Another doctor wrote to UNICEF from a field hospital: ``We have to drink from polluted wells and wash in the sewage. We eat leaves and rotten rice. We have had no electricity for 500 days.''
An estimated three million buildings have been destroyed in Syria, but the human toll is even more devastating.
``In their thousands, children have lost lives and limbs, along with virtually every other aspect of their childhood,'' says UNICEF in a new report marking the third anniversary of the war.
``They have lost classrooms and teachers, brothers and sisters, friends, caregivers, homes and security.''
In a special report for The Weekend Australian, aid workers speak of the ``medieval'' medical conditions in basements or mosques converted into hospitals.
Save the Children says many children are now disfigured by amputation; extensive bleeding and lack of equipment to stem this means doctors are opting to amputate limbs to save lives.
``Syria's health system is now in such disarray that we have heard reports of doctors using old clothes for bandages and patients opting to be knocked out with iron bars for lack of anaesthesia,'' says Save the Children. ``Sterilisation for bandages is nearly impossible with the lack of clean water, and using an unsterilised bandage on a wound or burn can lead to infection, which can result in death if not managed.''
Nurse Rachael Cummings from Save the Children says the country has gone from having a well-functioning health system to one no longer functioning.
``We now have children inside Syria who were born two to three years ago who have received few or no vaccines, meaning that vaccine-preventable diseases, like polio and measles, are on the increase,'' she says.
Aid workers mention blood transfusions using rubber hoses or cups.
UNICEF says boys as young as 12 have been recruited as fighters or as informers, guards or arms smugglers.
It says interviews with children and their parents suggest some young people are being encouraged to join armed groups.
As refugees, UNICEF says, girls are being pushed into early marriages to help economically, or to give them protection.
Save the Children says Syria risks becoming ``a child survival crisis''.
``The scale, brutality and duration of the conflict have created levels of need almost impossible to imagine and stretched limited resources to their breaking point,'' it says in a report marking the third anniversary of the war.
``As the civil war intensifies, children are the most affected.''
Three years ago today, a few hundred people gathered for a protest in Daraa in southern Syria.
It was the height of the Arab Spring, a democratic surge in the Arab world, which traditionally had been ruled by dictators.
The demonstrators in Daraa gathered only 32 days after Hosni Mubarak, the dictator in neighbouring Egypt, had been ousted by massive protests.
Both Mubarak and Syria's President Bashar al-Assad governed with iron fists: regimes enforced by the fear generated by their secret security services.
Material life in Syria was better than in Egypt, as were education levels, but as in Egypt, freedoms were severely curtailed.
Assad's father, Hafez, showed his attitude to dissent when in 1982 he surrounded Hama with tanks and for several days pounded the city, then sent in troops, killing as many as 20,000 people.
Like father, like son: on this day three years ago, Bashar made clear he would not allow any Arab Spring to flower.
His security forces opened fire on unarmed protesters, killing scores of demonstrators.
The brutality of the crackdown quickly turned what had been a peaceful protest movement into an armed conflict with a new opposition army, the Free Syrian Army. Three years on, there are scores of different fighting forces amid one of modern history's worst humanitarian disasters.
GREG SHERIDAN P14
]]></text></news-item>