<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="26A3-1FE8-69CB-48B5"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>NC plans to rewrite permits for Duke Energy plants to halt coal ash discharges</title><source>Charlotte Business Journal</source><author>John Downey</author><text><![CDATA[N.C. environmental officials say they will require Duke Energy (NYSE:DUK) to eliminate unauthorized coal ash discharges at the Riverbend Steam Station and Asheville Plant. And they may direct the removal of ash from the ponds at the plant sites.
In addition, they say they will order Duke to speed up the closure of the ash pond at the Sutton Steam Plant.&nbsp;
Regulators sent Duke notice of their intentions in a letter Friday that starts an administrative process to reopen wastewater permits that govern coal ash discharges from the ponds at the three sites.
The proposed actions are steps Duke CEO Lynn Good said Thursday the company is already preparing to do. Good outlined Duke's plans in a letter to the N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources.
DENR spokeswoman Bridget Munger says the agency's announcement Friday is unrelated to Good's letter. Spokeswoman Michele Walker says they are the result of preliminary determinations made by DENR that the three plants are the sites that need the most immediate attention following a Feb. 2 accident at another Duke plant dumped up to 39,000 tons of coal ash into the Dan River.
Frank Holleman of the Southern Environmental Law Center, which has been fighting both Duke and DENR on coal ash issues, disputed that DENR's decision represents any independent action.
"It is very conspicuous that DENR is only preparing to order what Duke has said it is willing to do, and the requirements are even less than what Duke volunteered," he says, noting that Good said Duke would remove the ash at Riverbend and Asheville. "And they are going about it in the least effective way possible."
He says once DENR proposes the permit modifications, Duke will have 60 days to respond. If there is a dispute, the permit will go before an administrative hearing officers. Once the officer makes a decision, it can be appealed to a state court.
But Holleman notes that DENR is already in state court with enforcement actions against Duke. He contends DENR should just go into court and require Duke to clean up the ponds at the three plants.
DENR acknowledges the administrative procedure will take time. But it says individual plans will be drawn up for each specific site.
Walker says DENR personnel are performing rigorous inspections at each of Duke's 14 active and retired coal plants. The results of those inspections will be used to specify what Duke needs to do.
Holleman says DENR's notice to Duke on Friday amounts to "more cozy relationships between it and Duke while trying to make public think (DENR is) taking some kind of action."
Charlotte-based Duke says it will respond to the state's notice.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Charlotte Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>