<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="26D2-892D-E99E-0618"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>NTN drops to eight-month low</title><source>News Bites Asian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NTN Corporation (TO:6472), the 23rd largest machinery/industrial goods company by market capitalisation in the Tokyo Stock Exchange, traded at its 217-day low of JPY350.0. The stock fell for a fourth consecutive day on Monday bringing its four-day fall to JPY37.0 or 9.5%. The stock price decreased JPY3.0 (or 0.8%) to close at JPY354.0. Compared with the Nikkei 225 Index which fell 50.0 points (or 0.4%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -0.5%. The volume was 0.7 times the average trading of 6.6 million shares.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on NTN, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/0010517117703142182
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- The stock decreased on weak volume falling for a fourth consecutive day.- The Moving Average Convergence Divergence (MACD) indicator of 12-day Exponential Moving Average (EMA) of 375.92 minus the 26-day EMA of 389.2 is negative 13.28 suggesting a bearish signal. Both EMA prices are falling, another bearish signal.- The price tumbled 9.0% in the last week and 6.1% in the last month. - Compared with the Nikkei 225 Index which fell 5.6% for the week and 0.8% for the month, this represented a relative price decrease for NTN stock of 3.4% for the week and 5.3% for the month.
NoteVolume: there were 4,386,000 shares worth JPY1.6 billion (US$15.4 million) traded. Beta: the Beta of NTN stock is 1.6. A Beta greater than 1 suggests this is a high risk, high return stock with volatility greater than that of the market. - NTN is at a discount of 34.1% to its 12-month high of JPY537.0 on 16 Jan, 2014. It is also at a premium of 62.4% to the 12-month low of JPY218.0 on 04 Apr, 2013. - The present value of JPY1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in NTN is JPY1,383, for a capital gain of JPY383.
Bullish Signals:Oversold/Bullish/Support Signals- At JPY354.0 the price is below the lower Bollinger band support of JPY358.58, indicating an upside for it to return to the band. - The stock is oversold according to the Williams % R indicator of -91.5, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day low of JPY350.0.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Sales of 0.3 [2.3]. We estimate NTN stock is trading at a current year Price/Sales of 0.3 and a forward year Price/Sales of 0.3. - Price to Book of 0.9 [4.1].Other Bullish Signals:- The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 28.0%. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.2. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued and ranks in the top quartile of stock by value of Q Ratio.- Revenue growth has shown signs of recovery in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]
- Return on Capital Employed is negative but improving in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 10: NTN Establishes New Company for CVJ in Hubei, China[Company Release] NTN Corporation (hereafter, NTN) has decided to establish the "Xiangyang NTN-Yulon Dr.vetrain Co., Ltd. (hereafter, Xiangyang NTN)" joint venture in Xiangyang, Hubei Province, China, with the Yulon Group in Taiwan, as the third plant for the production of CVJ.http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Japan/Stock/News/18709.htmlSource: Company Website
February 10: NTN: Notice of Revised Earnings Forecast[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Japan/Stock/News/18710.pdfSource: Company Website
October 10: NTN Exhibits at "China Wind Power 2013"[Company Release] NTN will run a booth at the Beijing international wind power exhibition, "China Wind Power 2013" with the theme "Proposals for next-generation wind turbines: contributing to the Chinese wind power industry."The front of the booth will feature a moving cutaway model of a wind turbine (with a 4 m model nacelle), as well as a range of bearings designed for use in wind turbines.The Condition Monitoring System (CMS) for Wind Power Generators will also be displayed with the model nacelle, with videos outlining its characteristics and structure.We look forward to seeing you at the event.Source: Company Website
October 04: NTN Exhibits at "3rd Next-generation Monozukuri Core Technology Industrial Fair TECH Biz EXPO 2013" [Event][Company Release]NTN will run an exhibit at the "3rd Next-generation Monozukuri Core Technology Industrial Fair TECH Biz EXPO 2013." The NTN booth will feature the two-seater microcompact electric vehicle (EV) equipped with the "In-wheel Motor System" that recently started out on a public road demonstration project, the first of its kind in Japan for a vehicle registered as a light vehicle.
October 03: NTN Starts the First Demonstration Project of Microcompact Mobility Equipped with the In-wheel Motor in Japan[Company Release] NTN Corporation (hereafter, NTN) delivered a two-seater EV (microcompact mobility) equipped with the in-wheel motor developed by NTN to Ise City, Mie Prefecture. The vehicle will be the first to acquire registration of microcompact mobility in Japan*1 and will be used to embark on a public road demonstration project.This initiative comes about as NTN participates as a local company in the "Okagesama Action! For residents and visitors*2" action plan aimed at developing a low carbon society in Ise City.
September 04: NTN: Development of "High Load Capacity Cylindrical Roller Bearings" with Rolling Element Separator[Company Release] NTN Corporation (hereafter, NTN) has developed the High Load Capacity Cylindrical Roller Bearings that takes both load capacity and high-speed rotating performance to new levels.Cylindrical roller bearings have a greater load capacity than ball bearings, and are primarily used in industrial gearboxes and reducers that are subjected to relatively high loads.
August 15: NTN signs an agreement with Rolls-Royce to supply bearings for Trent XWB Engines[Company Release] NTN Corporation (NTN) has received an order of the bearings for the Rolls-Royce Trent XWB jet engine. The engine has been developed specifically for the Airbus A350 family.The Trent XWB jet engine is the latest variant in Rolls-Royce's widely acclaimed Trent family of aero engines.
ISIN: JP3165600002
TO:6472; TYO:6472; T:6472; JP:6472
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>