<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="26F6-47C9-7654-DF61"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Public to vet new police; Mthethwa speaks at Khayelitsha summit</title><source>Cape Argus (South Africa)</source><author> JAN CRONJE</author><text><![CDATA[IN A bid to clean up their ranks and image, the police will start publishing the names of applicants in newspapers to allow members of the public to help "vet" future officers.
This was announced by Police Minister Nathi Mthethwa at an anti-crime summit in Khayelitsha yesterday. He said he hoped the public would "comment and follow up" when the names get |published.
The South African police have taken a battering in recent years over what many perceive as a heavy-handedness reminiscent of the apartheid-era security structures while communities have lost faith amid increasing evidence of corruption and poor functioning.
Mthethwa, who was invited by the Khayelitsha Development Forum (KDF) to speak to residents about crime, policing and community relations, said the names of 668 applicants who had been selected for the police basic training course in the Western Cape would be published later this year. He did not say when or where they would be published.
The new initiative will be instituted in the Western Cape, Northern Cape and Mpumalanga, with other provinces to follow at a later date.
Police have already started changing the wording on the job adverts in these three provinces to reflect the drive by police management to recruit only the best candidates and those acceptable to the public.
A recent advert in Mpumalanga inviting people to apply for the police's basic development learning programme said that in addition to checking criminal records, academic qualifications, driving licences and citizenship, police would also "publish the names of applicants in the newspapers for public comment".
It is hoped that through the public participation process potential bad apples will be identified and kept out of the service which is engaged in a battle to win back public confidence and trust.
The Marikana massacre in 2012 when police opened fire and killed 34 striking mine workers near Rustenburg, and last year's video of police beating Mozambican national Mido Macia and dragging him behind a police vehicle in Daveyton near Johannesburg and his subsequent death made world headlines.
Closer to home Khayelitsha has seen a spate of mob killings of people accused of being criminals, with many residents blaming the outbursts of public violence on community anger over police corruption and inefficiency.
The police deny this is the case, saying the killings are no different from any other criminality.
The Khayelitsha Commission of Inquiry is investigating allegations of a breakdown in trust between the police and residents, as well as complaints directed at the sprawling township's three police stations.
The commission, set up by Western Cape Premier Helen Zille in 2012, will resume public hearings on Monday.
Just over a week ago Capetonians were shocked when cellphone footage emerged of two police officers viciously assaulting a
]]></text></news-item>