<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2806-C2F6-0BEE-7FFB"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Prepare for invasion, Ukraine told; Moscow is ready to go further than annexing Crimea, says acting president, as pro-Kiev protester is killed in Donetsk</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Damien McElroy; Bruno Waterfield</author><text><![CDATA[UKRAINE must be ready for a full-scale Russian invasion "at any moment", the country's acting president warned yesterday, as officials announced the call-up of a 60,000-strong national guard.
Oleksander Turchynov claimed Moscow was "ready" to go much further than the annexation of the Black Sea territory of Crimea, which is expected to vote to secede from Ukraine in a referendum on Sunday.
"Only clear international pressure could slow the momentum of the Kremlin, he said. "All of civilised humanity supports our country. I am sure that this united effort in the international arena, bringing together all democratic countries, can still allow us to halt this aggression."
A pro-Kiev protester was killed yesterday in the city of Donetsk in eastern Ukraine. The 22-year-old was stabbed as demonstrators were attacked by a pro-Moscow group, the local health ministry said. Some 1,000 pro-Kiev demonstrators had rallied in the city when they were attacked by participants in a 2,000-strong pro-Moscow rally, which broke through a police cordon. More than a dozen people were reported injured.
The US ambassador to the United Nations, Samantha Power, said more than 20,000 Russian troops were in Crimea and repeated her call on Russian forces to return to their bases. She said the US was proposing a Security Council resolution on the Crimea crisis and that "Russia has to want a diplomatic solution".
Western diplomats are preparing sanctions against Russian officials and politicians. They are likely to be imposed on Monday after the referendum, which does not offer Crimeans the option of remaining an autonomous part of Ukraine.
Ukraine's parliament voted to create a national guard from interior ministry employees and members of the militias that emerged from the pro-Western protest movement that toppled Viktor Yanukovych, the former president. The measure was passed as Russia confirmed that it was conducting military manoeuvres in the Rostov, Tambov and Belgorod regions near the Ukrainian border, involving 8,500 ground troops, 270 tanks and 180 armoured personnel carriers.
"The main purpose of these actions is to completely check teamwork of the units and make them implement combat missions on an unknown territory," the Russian defence ministry said.
With tensions mounting across the region, Moscow also sent three fighter jets to Belarus at the request of its government following the deployment of 12 F-16 fighters to Poland by the US. Senior Nato and Russian generals discussed the moves by hotline.
Mr Turchynov said mismanagement of the security forces by MrYanukovych had rendered the country incapable of defending itself. He said the forces would be rebuilt "effectively from scratch".
Illustrating the volatility of Crimea, the Ukrainian commander of an airbase in Sevastopol asked his superiors in Kiev for instructions should he be fired upon.
"To avoid armed confrontations, I ask you to tell us as quickly as possible what commanding officers need to do if troops or members of their families come under threat," said Col Yuli Mamchur on Ukrainian television. "If you do not make a decision, we will act according to the status of the Ukrainian armed forces, even opening fire if need be."
Two weeks ago, an unarmed Col Mamchur braved heavily armed Russians at the base as he attempted, in vain, to lead his men back to work.
David Cameron and William Hague, the Foreign Secretary, will meet John Kerry, the US secretary of state, in London today to discuss the sanctions and the looming referendum. "Britain, as part of the EU, has set out a very clear map of those things that we will [do], those steps that we will take in terms of asset freezes and travel bans if the contact group talks between Ukraine and Russia don't get going," said Mr Hague.
Following the meeting in Downing Street, Mr Kerry and Sergei Lavrov, the Russian foreign minister, will hold another round of talks in London in an attempt to defuse the crisis.
In an unusually robust and emotional speech, Angela Merkel, the German chancellor, warned of "catastrophe" unless Russia changed course. "We would not only see it, also as neighbours of Russia, as a threat," she said. "This would also cause massive damage to Russia, economically and politically."
The head of the Russian Duma's international relations committee acknowledged that Russian troops were controlling Crimea, in a break from Moscow's position that armed men in the area were "self-defence units". "There are some military units there, which are in position in case there is an aggression, expansion from Kiev," Leonid Slutsky said.
]]></text></news-item>