<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2813-EE70-E2B5-C16D"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Navy SEALs Seize Oil Freighter 'Morning Glory' in Mediterranean that had been seized by armed Libyan Jihadists</title><source>Atlas Shrugs</source><author>Pamela Geller</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 17, 2014 (Atlas Shrugs:http://pamelageller.com/# Delivered by Newstex) Lots of small skirmishes, little acts of war until …… boom. Armed jihad militias control much of Libya i[1]ncluding the oil industry. I would love to know where these Libyan jihadists got their weapons. Odds are …. US supplied. More of the realities of Obama's pro-jihad policy in Libya.
Libya is out of control. It's just another Obama catastrophe the enemedia doesn't report on. Libya is in meltdown since Qaddafi's ouster and murder. It has become the epicenter of the illicit arms trade[2]. Western powers fear the vast North African state could even break apart with the government struggling to rein in armed [jihad] militias who helped oust dictator Muammar Gaddafi in 2011 but want to grab power and oil revenues. Libya's Prime Minister Zeidan, a liberal weakened for months by infighting with Islamists, will be temporarily replaced by Defence Minister Abdallah al-Thinni, who was sworn in by parliament on Tuesday evening. Zeidan, who came to power in 2012 after Libya's first free parliamentary vote following four decades of Gaddafi rule, had been facing opposition from jihadists and the public blaming him for Libya's anarchic transition since 2011. (more here)[3] Over the last month, the Libyan Navy has sought to impose a siege on oil ports seized by jihad militias. The seizure has slashed oil production and exports [4]by nearly 80 percent over the last six months. Libya's prime minister lost a vote of confidence and has been dismissed after his government was unable to stop a North Korean flagged tanker [5]at a rebel-held port and reportedly breaking through a naval blockade. Ali Zeidan was replaced temporarily by the country's defense minister, Abdallah al-Thinni, parliamentary spokesman Omar Hmeidan said. (more here)[6] Libya's ousted prime minister ignored prosecutor's order and fled to an undisclosed [7]European country. Reuters reports that Libya's navy opened fire on the tanker as it tried to leave Sidra, one of three ports that has been in the hands of jihadist forces since August. NPR's Leila Fadel reports that: 'The militia bypassed the central government and made its first oil sale last weekend. Associated Press reported[8] this March 10: 'There was no word immediately available from [Zeidan] on his ouster, which raises anew the potential for armed conflict. Most politicians in Libya are backed by militias with regional or ideological allegiances, and many are not likely to accept his removal.'Going on a year and a half and no arrests have been made on the attack on our embassy in Benghazi. No one has been held accountable. Not even Obama. Unbelievable. But he'll send in the Navy SEALs for this:http://pamelageller.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/Screen-Shot-2014-03-17-at-3.47.50-AM.png 'Navy SEALs Seize Oil Freighter 'Morning Glory' in Mediterranean,' ABC News[9], March 17, 2014 The Pentagon says that a team of Navy SEALs has boarded the oil freighter 'Morning Glory' in the Mediterranean that had been seized by three armed Libyans. No one was hurt in the raid, which took place late Sunday in international waters off of Cyprus. The ship and its illicit cargo of Libyan oil will now be sailed back to Libya under the control of U.S. Navy sailors. According to Pentagon Press Secretary Rear Admiral John Kirby, 'No one was hurt tonight when U.S. forces, at the request of both the Libyan and Cypriot governments, boarded and took control of the commercial tanker Morning Glory, a stateless vessel seized earlier this month by three armed Libyans.' The team of Navy SEALs boarded the oil freighter from the guided missile destroyer USS Roosevelt (DDG-80) which, according to Kirby, 'provided helicopter support and served as a command and control and support platform for the other members of the force assigned to conduct the mission.' The Morning Glory will soon head to Libya under the control of a team of sailors from another American destroyer, the USS Stout (DDG-55), who will supervise the transit. Media reports earlier in the week indicated that the freighter was a North Korean-flagged vessel loaded with 200,000 barrels of oil. The port is currently under the control of Libyan rebel forces seeking more autonomy from the Libyan government who control crucial oil facilities and ports in eastern Libya. It is unclear if the vessel really is a North Korea vessel. State Department spokesperson Jen Psaki issued a statement last week that the United States was 'deeply concerned by reports that a vessel sailing under the name Morning Glory is loading a cargo of illicitly obtained oil at the Libyan port of As-Sidra.' Psaki said 'This action is counter to law and amounts to theft from the Libyan people. The oil belongs to the Libyan National Oil Company and its joint venture partners. These partners include U.S. companies in the Waha consortium. Any oil sales without authorization from these parties places purchasers at risk of exposure to civil liability, penalties and other possible sanctions in multiple jurisdictions.' The Morning Glory escaped a blockade of Sidra imposed by the government in Tripoli. That precipitated a political crisis in Libya where the Libyan Parliament passed a vote of no confidence in Prime Minister Ali Zeidani, who then reportedly fled to Europe. There are real concerns now that Libya could spiral into a civil war between factions from eastern and western Libya.The post Navy SEALs Seize Oil Freighter 'Morning Glory' in Mediterranean that had been seized by armed Libyan Jihadists[10] appeared first on Pamela Geller, Atlas Shrugs[11]. [1]: http://www.worldtribune.com/2014/02/28/u-s-intelligence-sees-libya-out-of-control-for-another-1-to-2-years/ [2]: http://rt.com/news/libya-illegal-arms-trade-986/ [3]: http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/03/11/us-libya-oil-idUSBREA2A0R820140311 [4]: http://www.worldtribune.com/2014/03/10/rebel-militias-export-libyas-oil-tripoli-threatens-to-seize-n-korean-tanker/ [5]: http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/03/11/us-libya-oil-idUSBREA2A0R820140311 [6]: http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2014/03/11/289067263/libyan-premier-dismissed-over-oil-port-standoff-with-rebels [7]: http://t.co/XWwd8P2R0Y [8]: http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/middle_east/libya-says-its-forces-seize-disputed-oil-tanker/2014/03/10/7e0242fe-a8bf-11e3-8a7b-c1c684e2671f_story.html [9]: http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/politics/2014/03/navy-seals-seize-oil-freighter-morning-glory-in-mediterranean/ [10]: http://pamelageller.com/2014/03/navy-seals-seize-oil-freighter-morning-glory-mediterranean-seized-armed-libyan-jihadists.html/ [11]: http://pamelageller.com

]]></text></news-item>