<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="288B-0105-7F40-9B2D"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Syria: Three Years and a Lost Childhood</title><source>Digital Journal</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 15, 2014 (Digital Journal:http://www.digitaljournal.com Delivered by Newstex) Today marks three years since the conflict in Syria began- three incredibly long, tumultuous years for far too many innocent children. On March 15 2011, Syrian protesters peacefully demonstrated against President Bashar Assad on the basis of government corruption and civil rights abuses. The government responded[1] with police brutality, arrests and torture. This escalated further and by April 2011, the Syrian army was unleashed on towns and cities. Assad launched large-scale military operations and civilians[2] retaliated by taking up arms of their own.
Now, here we are three years later in the worst humanitarian crisis of the 21st century. A reported 146,000 Syrians have been killed, at least 10,000 of those being children. The United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF) stated that the child casualty rates are the highest figures recorded in any recent conflict in the region. According to UNICEF[3], the number of children affected by this crisis is 5.5 million and an estimated 9 million Syrians have been displaced from their homes. Children are the most vulnerable, as in any conflict, and with one in five schools destroyed or taken over by armed rebels; half of Syria's school-aged population is unable to receive an education. In the neighboring country of Jordan, where many Syrians fled, one in five Syrian girls are victims of child marriage (often, these young brides marry men who are far older). Additionally, opposition groups in Syria are recruiting refugee children to engage in the armed conflict. A U.N report[4] found that some of the horrific crimes children were exposed to included "beatings with metal cables, whips and wooden and metal batons; electric shocks, including to the genitals; the ripping out of fingernails and toenails; sexual violence, including rape or threats of rape; mock executions; cigarette burns; sleep deprivation; solitary confinement; and exposure to the torture of relatives."  Three years of unspeakable violence against children is unacceptable, and the world is outraged. This week, to mark three years of suffering, UNICEF faded out their social media profiles and called on world leaders to end the violence against Syrian children. To sign the No Lost Generation Call to Action, please sign this petition[5]. The renowned and elusive graffiti artist Bansky also raised awareness about the Syrian conflict and released a new image where a Syrian refugee girl releases a heart-shaped balloon[6]. Vigils are being held in 30 countries around the world, where red balloons, with attached messages of solidarity, are released. On this day, the three-year anniversary of bloodshed and violence, we must keep Syria in our thoughts and never forget the atrocities that civilians and children are subjected to on a daily basis. We must not be removed from the conflict, but instead, do everything in our power to stop it. We can all be champions for the children of Syria. Play Video[7] [1]: http://time.com/24741/the-cost-of-war-syria-three-years-on/ [2]: http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/an-unhappy-anniversary-why-the-end-of-bashar-alassad-is-as-far-away-as-ever--and-how-syrias-rebelslost-the-plot-9193594.html [3]: http://blogs.unicef.org.uk/2014/03/11/syria-three-years-conflict-unicef-under-siege-report/ [4]: http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/02/04/un-report-syria-child-abuse_n_4725833.html [5]: https://www.change.org/petitions/world-leaders-act-now-don-t-let-the-childrenofsyria-lose-another-year-to-bloodshed-and-suffering [6]: http://www.nydailynews.com/news/world/banksy-releases-image-syria-civil-war-article-1.1720598 [7]: http://www.youtube.com/embed/xpG3jLGGkvc?wmode=transparent

]]></text></news-item>