<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="28BE-33CD-9E3B-302B"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>PHARMACEUTICALS : BEUC PUSHES FOR EU INVESTIGATION ON LUCENTIS</title><source>Europolitics (daily in English)</source><author>Sophie Mosca</author><text><![CDATA[After Italy's fine on Roche and Novartis for giving precedence to the costly drug Lucentis, BEUC wants to see the EU take strong action
It may be one of the biggest scandals in the pharmaceutical industry. It will in any case have a major impact on European health budgets, with a cost in the billions of euro. Italy took the initiative in Europe but other states may follow. On 5 March, the Italian anti-trust authorities fined two Swiss pharmaceutical giants, Roche and Novartis, EUR182.5 million for cartel practices aiming to ensure use of the drug Lucentis to treat age-related macular degeneration (AMD), the leading cause of blindness among adults over the age of 50. They did so to the detriment of a closely related drug, Avastin, which is available at a fraction of the cost (average of EUR30 for Avastin and EUR900 to EUR1,400 for Lucentis).
The active ingredients of both drugs are very similar and equally effective to treat the wet form of the disease, according to several studies. This is hardly surprising since they are both manufactured by the same American biotechnology laboratory, Genentech. In the United States, they are both marketed by Roche, which bought Genentech in 2009. In Europe, Roche holds licences for Avastin, while Novartis holds licences for Lucentis. Novartis obtained a positive opinion from the European Medicines Agency for the treatment of AMD and an official marketing authorisation in almost all the member states.
SUSPICIOUS INERTIA
The alternative treatment Avastin has a marketing authorisation only for the treatment of cancer. Roche has not applied to add AMD to its therapeutic indications. For a number of analysts and the European Consumers' Organisation (BEUC), this is an intentional business strategy meant to keep from creating any competition for the very profitable Novartis product, which also benefits Roche since it holds the original patents on Lucentis. "We fear that the Roche decision not to seek the marketing authorisation is the result of a secret agreement with Novartis to maintain on the market only the more expensive medicine Lucentis," the organisation wrote in a letter to Competition Commissioner Joaquin Almunia, in November 2013. There have also been legal complications and defamatory claims about Avastin to discourage doctors, who are reluctant to prescribe a drug for an off-label use.
BEUC has asked the Commission to determine whether this anti-competitive strategy is indeed being applied widely in the EU and to estimate the cost to European consumers and public budgets. If appropriate, it should also impose severe penalties on the pharmaceutical firms.
The association notes that patients are still being deprived of treatment either because of the high price of Lucentis or because they do not tolerate the drug. Italy has also brought a legal action against the two pharmaceutical firms for intentional health disaster and criminal conspiracy. It estimates the loss to the health insurance system at EUR600 million per year.
WAIT AND SEE
The Commission has taken note of the Italian decision but says the situation in Italy is specific in terms of the off-label use of medicines. To put it plainly, it is not considering further investigation into Roche and Novartis at this stage, but is following developments in this case via the European competition network in which it participates. The executive has also been monitoring potentially anti-competitive practices in the pharmaceuticals sector since initiating a sector-based study in 2008. It pointed out in that study that disparagement is a questionable act. Last December, it fined Novartis EUR5.5 million for having delayed the market entry of its generic painkiller fentanyl.
The Commission seems ill at ease because there is no legal basis for obliging a pharmaceuticals firm to file an application for marketing authorisation for a given therapeutic use. In the wake of the Italian decision, to compensate for Roche's inertia, France adopted a decree, on 8 March, permitting temporary off-label use of a drug for economic reasons.
]]></text></news-item>