<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="290A-B09A-938C-17EA"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>The LRT contract is the 'deal of the year,' if you're in the P3 business</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The city touts this award, which apparently involved a gala dinner in New York City, that named Ottawa's contract with Rideau Transit Group the "deal of the year" among North American public-private partnerships in 2013. It's given by a trade publication called ( http://www.projectfinancemagazine.com/AboutUs.html ).
Says the City of Ottawa:
The award recognizes the innovative project financing structure developed by Rideau Transit Group in their successful bid to design, build, finance and maintain the 12.5 kilometre light rail system, including the fleet of 34 Alstom CITADIS Spirit trains.
"Last November, the Confederation Line was recognized with the 2013 Gold Award for Transportation Innovation from the Canadian Council for Public-Private Partnerships," said Mayor Jim Watson. "This new award provides even more proof that our partnership with RTG has made us P3 leaders, not just in Canada, but across the continent. Together we are transforming Ottawa's transportation network and we have established new standards of excellence for large-scale infrastructure procurement."
I note that it's Rideau Transit Group that gets the award. And, sure, good for them. But it's not an award for protecting taxpayers or for the city's getting a great deal or anything.
You need to register with Project Finance to see how they describe the award, which I did. It's all about what a good deal this is for the lenders involved. For instance:
The project's construction risk allowed bank lenders to prove that they remain relevant to PPPs in Canada, though banks lent alongside a private placement, the financing route of choice in Canadian infrastructure...
The bank debt came from three lenders - Scotiabank, Bank of Tokyo-Mitsubishi UFJ and Sumitomo Mitsui Banking Corporation. The five-year revolving credit facility and the long-term private placement were both aggressively priced. The 34.5-year private placement has an average life of 22 years and priced at 230bp over the 30-year government of Canada bond. The bank debt priced at 145bp over CDOR on drawn amounts, but is not exposed to operational risk, since it will be repaid with government milestone payments.
Hooray for the banks' proving they remain relevant? I guess? It's actually not entirely clear to me what makes this a "deal of the year" other than its size. By any measure, a $2.1-billion construction deal plus a multi-billion-dollar maintenance component is huge.
The piece does note something I don't think I'd heard before, which is that Rideau Transit Group was created with $75 million in equity from its major partners: 40 per cent from SNC-Lavalin, 40 per cent from ACS Infrastructures and 20 per cent from EllisDon.
]]></text></news-item>