<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="29A8-D00F-2486-7650"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Court Dismisses KBR Request to Be Indemnified From Exposure Lawsuits</title><source>Workers' Compensation</source><author>Jon Gelman</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 16, 2014 (Workers' Compensation:http://workers-compensation.blogspot.com/ Delivered by Newstex) The United States Court of Federal Claims has dismissed a complaint filed by Kellogg Brown Root [KBR] demanding reimbursement from the US Government for claims arising out of exposures to toxic substances. KBR provided services the US Government to refurbish and rebuild the Iraqi oil (Restore Iraqi Oil [RIO] contract) infrastructure in support of Operation Iraqi Freedom .
KBR was sued by persons involved in force protection which involved Nation Guard personnel and British soldiers. Sodium dichromate, a potentially hazardous chemical, had been used at Qarmat Ali and the site may have been contaminated with this chemical. KBR had sought indemnification from the US Government.https://ecf.cofc.uscourts.gov/cgi-bin/show_public_doc?2012cv0780-24-0[1]Kellog Brown Root Services, Inc., v The United States, The US Court of Federal Claims No. 12-780 C (Filed March 7, 2014)"In one of several lawsuits stemming from the work, a group of Oregon veterans won a judgment of more than $80 million in 2012 after accusing KBR[2] of knowingly allowing a carcinogen — sodium dichromate — to contaminate the area around the plant that soldiers guarded. KBR[3], which disputed the suit, appealed the jury verdict.Read more: http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2014/mar/10/judge-dismisses-kbrs-attempt-to-divert-legal-bills/#ixzz2wAYSV7lI[4] Follow us: @washtimes on Twitter[5]" See also: http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2014/mar/10/judge-dismisses-kbrs-attempt-to-divert-legal-bills/Judge dismisses KBR's attempt to divert legal bills on sickened troops in Iraq to taxpayers (The Washington Times) 3.10.14http://burnpitclaims.blogspot.com/2014/03/kbr-halliburton-found-not-immune-in.htmlFederal Appeals Court Rules Burn Pit Lawsuit Can Proceed 3.10.14…. http://www.gelmans.com/Firm/Bios/tabid/69/Default.aspxJon L. Gelman of Wayne NJ is the author http://store.westlaw.com/workers-compensation-law-3d-vols-38-39a-new-jersey-practice/722/17152728/productdetailNJ Workers' Compensation Law (West-Thompson) and co-author of the national treatise, http://store.westlaw.com/modern-workers-compensation/2339/13515915/productdetailModern Workers' Compensation Law (West-Thompson). For over 4 decades thehttp://www.gelmans.com/PracticeAreas/WorkersCompensation/tabid/64/Default.aspxLaw Offices of Jon L Gelman https://mail.google.com/mail/?view=cmfs=1tf=1to=jon@gelmans.comjon@gelmans.com have been representing injured workers and their families who have sufferedhttp://www.gelmans.com/PracticeAreas/WorkersCompensation/tabid/64/Default.aspxoccupational accidents and illnesses. [1]: https://ecf.cofc.uscourts.gov/cgi-bin/show_public_doc?2012cv0780-24-0 [2]: http://www.washingtontimes.com/topics/kbr/ [3]: http://www.washingtontimes.com/topics/kbr/ [4]: http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2014/mar/10/judge-dismisses-kbrs-attempt-to-divert-legal-bills/#ixzz2wAYSV7lI [5]: http://ec.tynt.com/b/rw?id=ctd-fI3Dar4z1uacwqm_6ru=washtimes

]]></text></news-item>