<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="29A9-F0A3-FB2C-1125"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Leaders Take Heat For Joining Bay Suit; In Email Campaign</title><source>Intelligencer Journal/New Era (Lancaster, Pennsylvania)</source><author>Ad Crable</author><text><![CDATA[Staff Writer
acrable@lnpnews.com
For several decades, Lancaster County has been a focal point in the prodigious effort to clean up that large body of water downstream, the Chesapeake Bay.
So it's all the more startling that two of its three county commissioners would join a court effort that challenges the cleanup of the Chesapeake, says the chief environmental group backing the cleanup.
Last week, the Chesapeake Bay Foundation urged 1,400 members in Lancaster County to register their disappointment with the commissioners.
The form email says, "As a Lancaster County resident, I want you to know that I am disappointed, and quite frankly, surprised by your decision to sign our county as a 'friend of the court' in support of the Farm Bureau Federation's appeal on clean water in our region.
"It seems counter-intuitive that you should decide to sign on to an appeal that would halt all of the progress that local leaders, volunteers, farmers, and others have made to improve the Conewago, Lititz Run, the Little Conestoga, the Quittapahilla, and so many other streams in the county."
Republican Commissioners Scott Martin and Dennis Stuckey agreed to join the appeal, filed by American Farm Bureau Federation, Pennsylvania Farm Bureau and home-building groups.
On Tuesday, they said they had not received any emails as part of the letter-writing campaign.
Democrat Commissioner Craig Lehman, who refused to go along with the appeal, said he had received one email from a disgruntled resident.
The email "blast" stems from an ongoing court battle that now involves 21 other states.
Farm bureaus and building groups had unsuccessfully challenged the federal Environmental Protection Agency's decision to order the state to meet specific pollution limits under the Clean Water Act.
The opponents said that states, not EPA, should set pollution limits and that those limits were not based on sound science.
Last September, a federal district court judge ruled against the groups and upheld EPA's authority.
When the farming and building groups appealed the decision, they fished for supporters. Five counties in Pennsylvania - Lancaster, Perry, Clearfield, Cambria and Tioga - agreed to sign on in support of the appeal.
So did 21 states, apparently worried that the Chesapeake Bay model requiring aggressive clean-water initiatives under the Clean Water Act will be used in their areas next.
Stuckey said the county's opposition is not about being against clean water or a clean Chesapeake Bay, but about a federal agency overstepping its bounds.
"We have been leaders in Lancaster County," Stuckey said. "This letter reinforces what we've done here, but we've done it on our own - yes, with some prodding and heavy-handedness from EPA.
"We have done it ourselves and will continue to do it ourselves. We don't need them to come in here and micromanage at the individual or watershed level because we have shown we can do it ourselves."
Martin stressed his belief that EPA is requiring reductions in nutrients when it hasn't tallied all the reductions Lancaster County farmers have made on their own.
"This isn't about whether people agree with clean water or saving the Bay. For me, it was more about the fact of who is making the decisions on the local level."
Martin noted that the Lancaster County Conservation District also supports the appeal.
Commissioner Lehman said he continues to oppose any county opposition to the Bay cleanup.
"It's disappointing from my perspective because of all the farmers that have stepped up to do the right thing and put best-management practices on the ground that are really making a difference in cleaning up local waterways.
"I wouldn't want to do anything to disrespect those efforts."
Harry Campbell, Pennsylvania director for the Chesapeake Bay Foundation, said that "Lancaster County is and has been considered a spearheader and leader in implementing and moving forward and thinking of novel and innovative ways ... to meet a common challenge."
He said that questioning whether all best-management practices were being counted, and other concerns about the bay model, "are very valid questions to have. But to say that, because of these questions, we should holistically oppose it, that was quite surprising."
]]></text></news-item>