<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="29C1-043C-C327-4481"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>New Initiative By Global Faiths To Eradicate Modern Slavery And Human Trafficking By 2020</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ Eradicating modern slavery and human trafficking across the world by 2020 is the objective of a ground-breaking agreement announced today at the Vatican. This unprecedented agreement among representatives of major faiths inaugurates the Global Freedom Network (GFN) which also has the Walk Free Foundation as a major partner. [1]

The Memorandum of Agreement and Joint Statement establishing the Global Freedom Network had the following signatories:
On behalf of the Holy Father, Pope FrancisBishop Marcelo Sanchez Sorondo, Chancellor of the Pontifical Academies of Sciences and Social Sciences On behalf of the Grand Imam of Al Azhar, EgyptDr Mahmoud Azab On behalf of the Archbishop of Canterbury, The Most Reverend Justin WelbyThe Most Reverend Sir David John Moxon, his representative to the Holy See On behalf of the Walk Free FoundationMr Andrew Forrest, founder.
The Joint Statement by the Global Freedom Network signatories underscored the searing personal destructiveness of modern slavery and human trafficking and called for urgent action by all other Christian Churches and Global Faiths. The Global Freedom Network is an open association and other faith leaders will be invited to join and support this initiative.
JOINT STATEMENT
Modern slavery and human trafficking are crimes against humanity.
The physical, economic and sexual exploitation of men, women and children condemns 30 million people to dehumanization and degradation. Every day we let this tragic situation continue is a grievous assault on our common humanity and a shameful affront to the consciences of all peoples.
Any indifference to those suffering exploitation must cease. We call to action all people of faith and their leaders, all governments and people of goodwill, to join the movement against modern slavery and human trafficking and support the Global Freedom Network.
Only by activating, all over the world, the ideals of faith and of shared human values can we marshal the spiritual power, the joint effort and the liberating vision to eradicate modern slavery and human trafficking from our world and for all time. This evil is manmade and can be overcome by faith-inspired human will and human effort.
We salute all those already engaged in this struggle, and fervently hope that this new project will further encourage their commitment to set free the most oppressed of our brothers and sisters.
Despite the best endeavours of so many in so many countries, modern slavery and human trafficking continue to expand. Victims are hidden away: in places of prostitution, in factories and farms, on fishing boats, and illegal establishments, in private homes behind locked doors and in myriad other places, in cities, villages and slums in the world's richest nations and poorest nations.
The Global Freedom Network will take up the instruments of faith - prayer, fasting and almsgiving. There will be a world day of prayer for the victims and for their freedom. Everyone of faith and everyone of goodwill will be requested to join in reflection and action. Dedicated prayer networks will be formed in all parts of the world.
Under the Agreement, all parties commit to pursuing all avenues and pathways to galvanise global action to eradicate modern slavery and human trafficking. Action plans for the first year will be developed to engage:
All global faiths to modern slavery-proof their supply chains and investments and to take remedial action if necessary All global faiths to mobilize their youth sections to support programmes to eradicate modern slavery and human trafficking Families, schools, universities, congregations and institutions to educate on the nature of modern slavery and human trafficking, how to report it and the destructiveness of harmful social attitudes and prejudices and social systems in relation to modern slavery and human trafficking Government leaders to modern slavery-proof public sector supply chains 50 major multi-national businesses whose CEOs are people of faith or of goodwill to commit to modern slavery-proof their supply chains 162 governments to publicly endorse the establishment of the Global Fund to End Slavery, with 30 heads of state publicly endorsing it by the end of 2014 The G20 to condemn modern slavery and human trafficking and adopt an anti-slavery and human trafficking initiative and support the abovementioned Global Fund.
The Joint Statement then concludes:
Our world must be freed of these terrible evils and crimes against humanity. Every hand and heart must be joined to bring this freedom to all those who are trapped and suffering. This agreement is a beginning and a pledge - the victims of modern slavery and human trafficking will not be forgotten or ignored: everyone will know their story. We will walk with them to freedom.
Note to editors: Definition of slavery
The Memorandum of Agreement defines modern slavery and human trafficking as an umbrella term referring to the systematic removal of an individual's freedom. It encompasses the following types of modern slavery, as defined by the following international instruments:
Human trafficking including forced prostitution - Palermo Protocol 2000, European Trafficking Convention*; Slavery - The Slavery Convention (1926) and Supplementary Slavery Convention (1956); Forced Labour - ILO Forced Labour Convention (No. 29, 1930) and Convention Concerning the Abolition of Forced Labour (No. 105); Children in armed conflict - Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Rights of the Child on the Involvement of Children in Armed Conflict; Child Prostitution - Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Rights of the Child on the Sale of Children, Child Prostitution and Child Pornography*; Worst forms of child labour - Convention on the Rights of the Child and Convention Concerning the Prohibition and Immediate Action for the Elimination of the Worst Forms of Child Labour (No. 182); Debt bondage and forced marriage - Supplementary Slavery Convention (1956). Any other forms of modern slavery and human trafficking that the Board considers should be included within the vision and objectives of this Memorandum of Agreement.
*The focus is on forms of forced prostitution and pornography, which fall within these definitions of modern slavery and human trafficking. 

Video -http://origin-qps.onstreammedia.com/origin/multivu_archive/PRNA/ENR/FX-NY84243-Andrew-Forrest.mp4Photo -http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20140317/NY84243

SOURCE Global Freedom Network
]]></text></news-item>