<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2A36-A0A3-C6A2-3E58"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Watchdog is called to account; The IFRS financial regulator has itself failed to follow accounting rules and faces a far-reaching inquiry</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Louise Armitstead</author><text><![CDATA[Few can remember the last time a regulatory authority provided the industry with such a laugh. The body responsible for setting ferociously complex accounting standards in 100 countries has proved itself incapable of following the most basic UK filing rules.
The International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS) Foundation has, for more than 10 years, been regarded as a linchpin of global finance; the very source of the accounting system that bosses, investors and regulators rely on to judge the viability of companies.
But at Companies House, where all UK businesses have to make filings by law, it has become a bit of a joke.
To recap on the unfolding saga: the London-based foundation has always boasted an illustrious roster of global trustees, from Paul Volcker, the American economist and investment bank nemesis, to Tommaso Padoa-Schioppa, former finance minister of Italy. Yet the official records of their tenures were found to be in disarray.
According to documents filed at Companies House, Mr Padoa-Schioppa, for example, stepped down from the foundation in February 2013 - two years after he'd died.
Some directors hadn't had their appointments registered at all. Meanwhile, for a few years the address for the foundation's legal correspondence was a private flat in Wapping, east London.
When The Telegraph pointed out the errors last month, the foundation dug itself into a deeper hole, issuing an indignant open letter that declared there was no requirement to list all trustees as directors. It added that at least now all its filings were up to date.
But another cursory look at Companies House showed even the clarification was wrong: the rules had required all the trustees to be listed.
And the foundation had failed to file a single directorate change on time, ever. Yael Almog, executive director, finally came clean and admitted the mistakes. She also agreed that the foundation's administrative processes should be beyond reproach.
There may have been sniggers in Britain but MEPs weren't laughing. Sharon Bowles, the chairman of Europe's Economic Affairs Committee, was in the middle of considering a £50m five-year funding package for the IFRS Foundation and its European counterpart, Efrag.
She sent a stinging letter to Michel Barnier, EU internal markets commissioner, raising serious concerns about channelling public money to a foundation with such poor governance. Bowles was backed by Syed Kamall, MEP for London, a frequent critic of actual IFRS accounting rules.
The threat to funding wasn't funny for the foundation, either. Almog swiftly requested a meeting with Kamall to explain matters. After her appearance last Tuesday, Kamall told The Sunday Telegraph: "She assured me that everything was in order and it would never happen again," he said.
The funding decision was approved on Thursday. But the vote was accompanied by severe health warnings from MEPs, who voiced concerns not just about the filing mess but about the IFRS accounting system itself.
They also had deep concerns about the fact that those responsible for overseeing the rules, including the foundation's standard-setting arm, the International Accounting Standards Board (IASB), are almost all from the Big Four accountancy firms. The European Commission has announced a review of all the issues.
Bowles said questions had been raised about the "governance structures and lack of transparency" at both the foundation and at Efrag "as well as their close links to the accounting industry".
Warning that MEPs had the power to stop the funding next year, she added: "The release of these EU funding streams will therefore only be forthcoming upon sufficient reform to prevent conflicts of interest, which will bring about much-needed trust and scrutiny on how these highly influential public bodies operate."
Kamall went further. "I am not convinced that it was right for the EU to outsource standard-setting to what is, in effect, a private-sector body funded by public money," he said.
"There must be a root-and-branch review of the IFRS Foundation and the IASB to decide whether these bodies are best suited to ensuring accounting standards are fit for purpose and whether they are showing value for money."
This weekend, the IFRS Foundation's leaders might be wondering how some basic filing errors have snowballed into questions over its own future and of the integrity of its global accounting standards, too.
However, for a group of dogged investors, politicians and experts, the need for an official review of IFRS is no surprise; it's a vindication of years of arguing that the organisation has caused a regulatory fiasco at the heart of the global financial system.
They say the rules, which were introduced in the UK in 2005, disguise the build-up of risks in companies, particularly in banks. They argue that IFRS did not just exacerbate the last financial crisis but will hide the emergence of another one, too.
Hubris, greed and excessive risk played their part but the bigger problem with Britain's banks was far simpler: the accounts were wrong. For them, the review has not come out of the blue, but in the nick of time.
For the critics of IFRS, the foundation's administrative errors are only the tip of the iceberg. They argue that poor governance has run deeper than mere record-keeping and, crucially, that this has led to the introduction of a dangerously flawed accounting system.
Embarrassments have occurred before. In November 2012, the foundation was forced by HMRC to set aside £460,000 for failing to pay the correct income tax and national insurance contributions for its foreign members of staff. Back in 2004, the foundation was embarrassed when a judge described its commercial director, Kurt Ramin, as "not credible" after the IASB was sued by a language interpreter over unpaid fees.
The judge was highly critical of the foundation's conduct during the case and finally ruled in favour of the translator because, he said, the IASB was deemed to be "relying on the false evidence of its commercial director".
Ramin, who could not be reached for comment, has long since left the IFRS Foundation. But he was a key player there when IFRS was introduced into Britain - a period that has also come under fresh scrutiny.
Ramin, a former partner of PriceWaterhouseCoopers in America, was seconded to the foundation in the mid-1990s, when the UK GAAP accounting system was still governed by rules in the Companies Act of 1879.
At the time, there was demand for change from both sides of the Atlantic, driven in part by a growing irritation with banks apparently making profits from bad-debt provisions.
Under the old rules, banks had to mark down loans deemed to be at risk of default. However, under this "expected loss model", when some bad loans were repaid, the banks were seen to be making bigger profits.
The Americans led the charge, introducing a new rule called IAS39 in 2003 that was designed to bring some solid numbers to bank accounts. Under the new "incurred loss" system, loans were either good or bad; they were not marked down until they actually failed.
In a post-Enron world of big liabilities, accountants warmly welcomed the system which meant they no longer had to put their necks on the line by judging the likelihood of defaults.
David Tweedie, head of Britain's Accounting Standards Board (ASB), wanted to introduce a similar system in Europe. He also saw the possibility of creating a new accounting system that could be used across the world. He helped establish the IFRS Foundation and the new rules.
The foundation was based in London but registered in Delaware - a structure that allowed for efficient giving from US donors who funded the project at the beginning.
Prof Kees Camfferman, an economics academic at the University of Amsterdam, recently published a paper arguing that the IASB put itself under immense pressure to introduce the new IFRS rules by 2005 - with alarming results. He argues that the new rules were drawn up "in a process with a considerable risk of an incomplete understanding of the issues by the IASB's constituents".
He says the board's plans "vacillated" between various models, only some of which were ever put out to consultation. "The wording of the standard as finally approved by the board, with respect to loan impairment, differed considerably from the proposals on which the constituents had been asked to comment," he wrote.
In the end there was a "vulnerability" of the system to "ambiguity and misunderstanding in a complex area, such as accounting for financial instruments" - but few beyond the IASB had a chance to spot it.
Long before Camfferman's study, the problems had been noted by Tim Bush, a London-based fund manager at Hermes. Bush, who now works at investor adviser Pirc, said the rule change had an immediate impact on banks where bad loans didn't show in the accounts any more, which in turn flattered profits. Suddenly the banks were booming - on paper, at least.
Bush told The Sunday Telegraph: "If a bank's capital is the speed limit, then the accounting rules are the speedometer. If the accounting rules are wrong, the speed limit is irrelevant because no one knows how fast you're going anyway."
He added: "Big change happens at the margins. The differences look tiny. But a 1pc loss at a bank is huge. A bank is typically geared by 20 times, or 5pc of capital. Each 1pc understatement of loan provisions led to an overstatement of 20pc of the capital base."
Bush says it was clear to him by 2007 that HBOS had a black hole developing of as much as £20bn. When the bank finally had to be rescued a year later, this figure proved to be remarkably accurate. RBS was hiding £32bn of loan losses in 2008, just at the time the bank insisted it was solvent.
As the banks unravelled, Bush became an increasingly vocal critic of IFRS. But he found his warnings were not welcomed by an accounting profession that, remarkably, had escaped unscathed despite the implosion around it.
In 2010, a frustrated Bush wrote to the new Business Secretary, Vince Cable, warning him that IFRS had led to "mistakes of such severity that it is difficult to overstate". The faulty accounts had "misled creditors, misled shareholders, the Bank of England, FSA and others".
When the letter was reported, there was silence from Cable but Lord Lawson, the former chancellor, was appalled. Early in 2011, Lawson led the Lords Economic Affairs Committee in an investigation of IFRS which concluded that it had serious concerns.
Others agreed. Iain Richards, a fund manager at Threadneedle, said that billions of pounds of bonuses may have been paid out on false profits. At the end of 2011, even the FSA admitted that hedge funds had spotted the black hole in RBS before regulators because they didn't believe the accounts.
By 2012, the Bank of England's Andrew Haldane argued that IFRS gives a "hit and miss" view of the solvency of banks. He said that trying to get an accurate view of bank assets was like trying to "pin the tail on a boisterous donkey".
By January last year, the investors were fed up with the lack of response from UK regulators and politicians and turned to Brussels.
Investors from 10 leading groups, including Threadneedle, Railpen and the Local Authorities Pension Fund Forum, wrote to Barnier warning him that the accounting rules were harming shareholders and destabilising the economy. A few months later, Barnier agreed to intervene, setting in motion events that have led to this latest review being announced.
Meanwhile, UK authorities have started to catch up. Last summer, the Parliamentary Commission on Banking Standards called for banks to produce a "separate set of accounts for regulators according to specified, prudent principles" on top of IFRS - in other words, to revert to a system similar to the old GAAP.
The Financial Reporting Council, which oversees UK accounting rules and was instrumental in the introduction of IFRS too, has ordered a review of the rules.
The IFRS Foundation and the IASB last year finally launched a public consultation into the "conceptual framework" of its rules. The consultation ended in January and a spokesman said the results would be discussed at a board meeting in May.
But they will have to move fast on any reforms. The Commission will have started its review into the exact impact of IFRS in Europe.
MEPs want fundamental change. Having realised the enormous power and influence of the rules, they are also determined to wrest responsibility for them from the private and opaque foundation.
As Kamall says: "It is often said that accounting standards are not political, but technical. This is quite clearly not the case."
]]></text></news-item>