<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2A5A-7B83-20F1-DD94"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Thomasville sued over alleged water violations</title><source>Winston-Salem Journal (North Carolina)</source><author>BERTRAND M. GUTIERREZ, JOURNAL REPORTER</author><text><![CDATA[A conservation group based in Winston-Salem said Friday it filed a lawsuit against the city of Thomasville alleging the city has repeatedly violated federal clean-water laws.

More than 20 million gallons of sewage with fecal coliform, viruses and disease- causing bacteria have been dumped over the past five years by the city into streams flowing to the Yadkin River and High Rock Lake, according to Dean Naujoks, executive director of the Yadkin Riverkeeper.

The Yadkin River is a drinking-water supply for 734,000 people.

The lawsuit comes as the Yadkin Riverkeeper, other conservation groups and the N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources press Duke Energy to clean its coal-waste ponds at the company’s 14 power plants statewide, such as the one that contaminated the Dan River on Feb. 2.

“Polluters like Thomasville and Duke (Energy) need to stop breaking the law and stop polluting High Rock Lake with raw sewage and contamination from toxic coal ash,” Naujoks said. 'Fishable, swimmable, drinkable water is a fundamental right granted to every citizen under the Clean Water Act.' Thomasville is trying to fix the sewage-overflow problem, said Joel Pierce, a member of the Thomasville City Council.

'We understand the issues and we're spending a lot of money to rectify those issues,' Pierce said. The city has spent about $5 million to repair two pump stations most susceptible to overflows, he said. 'They would significantly help the issue.' A system of pipes and pump stations transports sewage from homes and businesses to a wastewater treatment plant. Thomasville's sewage overflows are caused by several factors, including mechanical failures, pipe failures and seepage resulting from an aging collection system, according to the Yadkin Riverkeeper.

Mayor Joe Bennett did not respond to phone messages requesting comment on the alleged violations. Calls made to council members Neal Grimes, Pat Shelton and Raleigh York were not returned. Calls to council members Ronald Bratton and Scott Styers revealed that the phone numbers they list on the city's website do not receive voice mails. Council member Joe Leonard does not list a phone number on the city's website.

The city manager, Kelly Craver, was out of the office Friday, according to an office clerk.

In the fall, the Southern Environmental Law Center filed a 60-day notice of intent to sue Thomasville on the Yadkin Riverkeeper's behalf. Since filing the notice, the Yadkin Riverkeeper and SELC have been working with Thomasville on a compromise in which the N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resource played a role.

'DENR has taken a collaborative approach to solving the city's sanitary sewer issues, working with the cooperation of city leadership.

'We are now at a point where, with DENR's help, the city has a plan and the funding to address the issues in a meaningful way,' Secretary John Skvarla said in a letter to the Winston-Salem Journal in November.

'The SELC's approach?

'Sue Thomasville. ? I am happy to say that after DENR's strongly worded response on the city's behalf, the SELC lawyers have refrained from suing - for now. Which is better use of Thomasville's tax dollars: paying for a legal defense or fixing the problem?' Skvarla said.

DENR did not act aggressively enough to pro tect the Yadkin and High Rock Lake, according to Naujoks.

'What DENR and Thomasville have been doing has not fixed this problem,' Naujoks said. 'We've done everything we could to avoid this.'
]]></text></news-item>