<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2AA0-6EE5-52DB-F64B"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Getting away with foreclosure </title><source>The Star-Ledger (Newark, New Jersey)</source><author>Joshua Denbeaux</author><text><![CDATA[If Gov. Chris Christie's administration does only one thing well, it is keeping New Jersey residents waiting. The administration kept New Jersey residents waiting in a massive traffic jam outside Fort Lee last year. Christie kept New Jersey residents waiting 10 months for him to appoint a compliance monitor to oversee Hurricane Sandy recovery funds.
The untold story of the Christie administration is how the Attorney General's Office has continually failed to protect the rights of New Jersey homeowners despite the epidemic of foreclosures as a result of banks' predatory lending strategies. The Christie administration keeps New Jersey residents waiting for accountability.
The Attorney General's Office repeatedly reaches agreements that appear to protect homeowners. The agreements certainly make for great press releases, promising that mortgagors are entitled to loan modifications or that banks are held to greater scrutiny. However, the unfortunate reality is that the agreements are merely empty promises to homeowners that the Attorney General's Office breaks.
I have met with thousands of New Jersey homeowners who ask me to help them defend their homes from foreclosure. My law office, Denbeaux & Denbeaux, dedicates our practice to foreclosure defense and litigating consumer fraud. Too many New Jersey homeowners have asked me the same questions: How do the banks get away with what they do? Shouldn't the government do something about this?
The answer is that banks get away with exploiting homeowners and persuading them to sign bad loans because the Attorney General's Office does not hold the banks accountable for their practices.
One famous example is an agreement the Attorney General's Office reached with Wells Fargo in 2010. The Attorney General's Office agreed not to prosecute Wells Fargo for predatory business practices. In exchange, Wells Fargo agreed to offer loan modifications to New Jersey homeowners who had "pick-a-payment" loans that were designed to increase the amount outstanding on the loan each month. These types of loans are destined to fail and result in foreclosure.
Many of the homeowners who come to me for help have the predatory loans that the 2010 agreement should have remedied. I have never met a single person who told me that the Attorney General's Office enforced the agreement with Wells Fargo. I have never met a single person who received the loan modification to which they were entitled through the agreement.
The Attorney General's Office repeatedly ignores requests to enforce the 2010 agreement. My office has conducted an extensive investigation into the 2010 agreement and a related nationwide class-action settlement between Wells Fargo and homeowners who were victims of "pick-a-payment" home loans. In order to hold the government accountable to the public, my office submitted our report to the New Jersey attorney general and the Attorney General's Office in eight other states where similar agreements were reached. We have received deafening silence from the New Jersey attorney general in response.
Under terms of the 2010 agreement, the Attorney General's Office should have more than a dozen compliance reports from Wells Fargo by now, and it should receive a dozen more by the end of 2017. So the question is why the Attorney General's Office is not forcing Wells Fargo to comply with the agreement.
Another example of the Attorney General's Office's failure to hold banks accountable is the 2012 National Mortgage Settlement, the largest consumer financial protection settlement in U.S. history, which penalized five of the biggest banks in the United States, including Wells Fargo, for routinely signing mortgage-related documents without verifying their accuracy. The NMS required the banks to report to a monitoring body that in turn reports to the New Jersey Attorney General's Office. We have waited years to hear what those reports contain. We are still waiting.
We demand, and New Jersey homeowners deserve, an explanation.
Joshua Denbeaux is a partner in the Denbeaux & Denbeaux law firm in Westwood. Join the conversation at nj.com/opinion.
]]></text></news-item>