<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2AB7-287A-86EE-80D5"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>U.S. lifts ban barring BP from federal government contracts</title><source>Xinhua General News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency agreed Thursday to lift its ban barring British oil giant BP from securing federal government contracts, ending a months-long suspension imposed on the company in the wake of the 2010 Gulf of Mexico oil spill.
The agency said in a press release it had reached an agreement with BP resolving the suspension, which was put in place after BP pleaded guilty in November 2012 to criminal charges related to the Deepwater Horizon rig explosion. The explosion killed 11 workers and triggered one of the worst environmental disasters in the country's history.
"This is a fair agreement that requires BP to improve its practices in order to meet the terms we've outlined together," said Craig Hooks, assistant administrator for EPA's Office of Administration and Resources Management.
"Many months of discussions and assessments have led up to this point, and I'm confident we've secured strong provisions to protect the integrity of federal procurement programs," he said.
Under the agreement, which takes effect immediately and will be in place for five years, BP is required to retain an independent, EPA-approved auditor to conduct an annual review of the company's safety, ethics, environmental and other procedures in order to bid for and hold government contracts. EPA also has the authority to penalize BP if it does not meet safety standards.
John Minge, chairman and president of BP America, Inc., called the final deal "fair and reasonable."
"Today's agreement will allow America's largest energy investor to compete again for federal contracts and leases," he said in a statement.
Although the 16-month suspension did not affect BP's existing government contracts, the oil company lost out on potentially billions of dollars of business with the U.S. government, including the chance to bid on new offshore oil and gas leases and to win lucrative contracts supplying the military with fuel.
The London-based company now will be free to present bids to the Pentagon and bid for Gulf of Mexico drilling rights during a March 19 auction in New Orleans. The company currently has 10 rigs working in the Gulf.
]]></text></news-item>