<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2AC0-EF65-BB2F-B716"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>This Week in History: 1948; When Canadian Communist leader Tim Buck took to the stage at UBC in 1948 he surely didn't expect to have a dead cat thrown at him</title><source>The Vancouver Sun (British Columbia)</source><author>John MacKie, Vancouver Sun</author><text><![CDATA[Anti-Communism was at a fever pitch in Canada in the late 1940s and early '50s. So, when Canadian Communist leader Tim Buck agreed to speak at the University of B.C. on March 15, 1948, he had to expect there would be protests.
But he probably didn't anticipate that somebody would throw a dead cat at him.
"A near-riot, with Labour-Progressive leader Tim Buck at the centre, broke out Monday at the University of B.C. campus," reported The Vancouver Sun. "During the melee students scuffled, peashooters were used, cap pistols were brandished and a dead black cat was hurled to the speaker's platform at Mr. Buck's feet."
No one claimed responsibility for hurling the dead cat, but then-UBC student Norman Young said it was widely believed to have been thrown by a member of the campus Progressive-Conservative club. Buck's supporters charged the Conservatives had organized the noisy disturbances that dogged Buck's speech.
"Two thousand students crammed the auditorium to hear (Buck) expound his party's views," The Sun reported. "But for two-and-a-half hours jeers greeted his remarks." It got so raucous, student union president Grant Livingstone had to take the stage twice to calm things down. When it did, the "soft-spoken" Buck talked about the Labour-Progressive Party's controversial declaration of support for the CCF (today's NDP) in the forthcoming federal election.
"We're appealing to all people who realize the need for defeating the Liberals and the Tories to unite at the polls to elect CCF candidates," Buck said.
The CCF didn't really want Buck's endorsement. CCF club president CliffGreer jumped onstage to state "both the LPP and CCF are socialists in theory, but the CCF believes in democracy." The Communist party had been banned in Canada in 1940, so Canadian communists formed the Labour-Progressive Party in its stead. It became the Communist party again in late 1959.
Buck had been a member of the party since it was founded as the Workers Party of Canada in 1921 (it became the Communist party in 1924). He was elected General Secretary of the Communist party in 1929, and remained party leader until he retired in 1962. It wasn't easy being a Communist in Canada. In 1931 Buck was charged with sedition, and spent three years in jail at Kingston Penitentiary. A Labour-Progressive MP, Fred Rose, was jailed in 1947 for spying for the Soviet Union.
The Sun ran a series of anti-Communist stories the week Buck spoke. One was headlined "Communist party Hierarchy Traced from Moscow's Kremlin to Vancouver." The feature by Don Cameron turned to a second page, where the headline was "Reds Dupe Loyal Canadians in 'Harmless' Citizen Groups." Another wire story out of New
York stated "Communists are attempting to propagandize 3,000 teenage girls through the Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA)."
Buck's appearance came amid worldwide outrage over Czech Communists seizing power in the February 1948 "Czech coup." After the end of the Second World War, Czechoslovakian Communists and non-Communists had formed a coalition government. But relations soured between the two camps, and the non-Communist cabinet members resigned, intent on forcing the Communists to call an election. But the Communists simply used their absence to take power. The plot thickened when Czechoslovakia's non-Communist foreign minister, Jan Masaryk, was found dead two weeks after the coup. The Communists said he'd committed suicide, but many felt he'd been assassinated. Buck was unrepentant about the Czech situation - he'd long been a supporter of Soviet dictator Josef Stalin. He accused the United States of "war mongering" over its threats to stop the spread of communism in Europe.
Buck's trip to B.C. was quite eventful. When he took the stage for a speech in Port Alberni, he was doused with eight buckets of water that had been placed in a shelf over the stage. The trap was tripped by an unknown anti-Communist. A few days later Buck auctioned offthe buckets following a speech at the Exhibition Gardens at the PNE.
jmackie@vancouversun.com
]]></text></news-item>