<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2AF0-5EFE-4645-D7BA"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>ORGANIC STORE BRANDS; Natural boom; Stores rush own brands to market to get business of health-conscious customers</title><source>The Columbus Dispatch (Ohio)</source><author>Mary Vanac, THE COLUMBUS DISPATCH</author><text><![CDATA[Natural and organic food isn't just for hippies anymore. Four out of five U.S. families buy organic products at least occasionally, according to the Organic Trade Association.
In their quest for a share of those sales, grocery chains serving central Ohio have rushed everything from all-natural chicken breasts to organic granola onto store shelves under their own brand names.
The store brands reflect a growing consumer move toward natural or non-allergenic ingredients, and away from pesticides, artificial additives and genetically modified organisms. The brands also reflect cost-consciousness: Store-branded food tends to cost less than national brands.
"More than ever, savvy, health-conscious consumers are looking for natural and organic options when making food purchases," said Dan Donovan, spokesman for Pittsburgh-based Giant Eagle, which introduced its Nature's Basket brand in 2004. It now covers more than 600 natural and organic products.
"Having a brand like Nature's Basket helps us meet the demand of this growing consumer base by providing high-quality natural and organic offerings at a considerable value when compared with the national brands," Donovan said.
For instance, a 32-ounce container of Kroger's Simple Truth Organic free-range chicken broth costs $2.99, while the same product by national brand Imagine costs $3.49, also at Kroger. Meanwhile, Aldi's Simply Nature organic free-range chicken broth costs $1.79 for the same size container.
U.S. sales of natural and organic products grew 10 percent to $98.9 billion in 2012, according to the latest annual survey by Natural Foods Merchandiser, a trade publication.
Also, sales of organic food and beverages nationwide grew to $26.7 billion in 2010 from $1 billion in 1990, according to the Organic Trade Association. Mass merchandisers, such as supermarkets, sold slightly more than half of organic food and beverages in 2010, the trade association said.
Although the double-digit growth rate of organic food sales slowed during the depths of the Great Recession, organic sales still are growing at about 7 percent per year, according to the Economic Research Service of the U.S. Agriculture Department.
Will the growth in health and wellness sales continue for grocery stores? "All signs point to yes," said David Orgel, executive director of content and user engagement for trade publication Supermarket News.
"In (our) annual health and wellness survey, 75 percent of retailers and wholesalers said sales in this segment have increased in the past 12 months," Orgel wrote in a Feb. 25 editorial in his publication. "More than 40 percent of retailers/wholesalers said sales have grown 10 percent or more, which represents an unmistakably 'healthy' direction." And more chains are adding store brands to respond to shoppers' interest.
Kroger introduced its Simple Truth and Simple Truth Organic brands in late 2012.
"Sales have more than doubled, compared to this time last year," said Kroger spokeswoman Jackie Siekmann. "The Simple Truth brand is close to becoming a $1 billion brand" that covers more than 500 products.
Kroger shopper Jamie Somers, of Columbus, buys Simple Truth chicken and turkey for her family, saying during a visit to the store at W. Sycamore Street that she believes the poultry is raised in a humane way.
Somers' perception illustrates the problem with labeling food "natural." While the "USDA organic" label means the U.S. Department of Agriculture has certified growers and processors who do not use artificial chemicals or genetic engineering, food labeled "natural" is whatever the producer or retailer says it is.
Kroger says its Simple Truth chicken is raised "in a humane environment" and "cage-free."
But a recent California lawsuit against the company points out that this does not mean the chicken is "free-range," meaning the birds have had access to pastures. The industry standard for raising cage-free chickens (including those that produce eggs) is housing them in barns rather than cages. These chickens may never see a pasture.
In response to the recent lawsuit, Kroger responded: "We want customers to know that our Simple Truth chicken exceeds industry animal welfare standards and is accurately labeled. Simple Truth chickens are raised by our supplier in cage-free environments and fed a 100-percent vegetarian diet with no antibiotics ever."
The grocer's Simple Truth Organic chicken is labeled "free-range."
In general, Kroger defines its Simple Truth natural food as free from 101 artificial ingredients, such as nitrites used to preserve lunch meat, that customers said they didn't want in their food, Siekmann said.
The top-selling Simple Truth product is cage-free organic brown eggs. The next best-seller is Simple Truth Organic skim milk, she said.
Minneapolis-based retailer Target introduced its Simply Balanced line of natural and organic food in June.
"We identified that many of our guests are looking for great-tasting, wholesome food with simple, recognizable ingredients that they can pronounce," said Mike Fahey, store group director in Ohio, in an email.
"Simply Balanced products also exclude 105 common food-additive ingredients, avoid high-fructose corn syrup, never use trans-fats and are mindful about the amount of sodium in each product," he said.
Sales of natural and organic products are growing more than three times faster at Target than other grocery items, Fahey said.
German-owned Aldi officially launched its SimplyNature line of natural and organic products in the Columbus area in December after a "strong performance in test markets last year," said Dan Gavin, Springfield division vice president, in an email.
Though in the local market only for a short time, "We've seen a favorable response so far," Gavin said.
mvanac@dispatch.com
@maryvanac
Store brands
Major grocery-store chains and their in-house natural and organic brands:
Aldi: SimplyNature
Giant Eagle: Nature's Basket
Kroger: Simple Truth and Simple Truth Organic
Target: Simply Balanced
]]></text></news-item>