<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2B19-0880-0078-3295"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Fridman to pay EUR 5.1bn for German O&amp;G company</title><source>RosBusinessConsulting Database</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Mikhail Fridman, ranking second in the Russian Forbes list, is buying one of the largest oil and gas companies in Germany RWE Dea for EUR 5.1bn. If the deal is closed, it will become one of the most expensive purchases abroad of the Russian business.
The deal will be funded using proceeds received by Fridman and his Alfa Group partners from the sale of share in TNK-BP a year ago. The buyer is an investment company LetterOne established by Mikhail Fridman, German Khan, and Alexey Kuzmichev in 2013.
German energy concern RWE, the owner of Dea, announced on March 15 that it agreed with LetterOne on sale of the asset for EUR 5.1bn ($7.1bn). This price included Dea's debt of EUR 0.6bn, which means that Letter One will pay for Dea EUR 4.5bn ($ 6.3bn). L1 Energy, which manages energy investments of LetterOne, confirmed the agreement.
According to RBC, this is a record deal signed by a Russian company with a foreign counterpart. In 2011, VimpelCom acquired telecom assets of Egyptian tycoon Naguib Sawiris for $6.5bn, yet the cash-component amounted only to $1.8bn, while the rest was paid for with shares. In 2007, Norilsk Nickel bought Canadian LionOre for $5.9bn.
RWE and LetterOne have yet to sign a legally binding agreement. The deal will be examined by the RWE supervisory board and regulators in several countries. Dea has operations in Germany, the United Kingdom, Denmark, Norway and Egypt. Still, the EC anti-monopoly portal did not post a notice about the deal. Without politicizing Russian investments in Europe, there should be no problem with regulatory bodies in Brussels.
The news about Fridman's interest in Dea appeared in November last year. Even the Ukrainian events did not hamper negotiations between the two companies. Recently, due to the Crimea conflict and the risk of Western sanctions against Russia, several Russian IPOs in London were put on hold and domestic companies are continuing to withdraw their money from Western banks. An RWE spokesperson said that the company had informed German authorities about the upcoming deal and did not see any objections.
]]></text></news-item>