<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2B27-B775-900A-6A7F"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Speaker from Philippines to discuss her work to help exploited women and children</title><source>Carroll County Times (Westminster, Maryland)</source><author>Alisha George Times Staff Writer</author><text><![CDATA[Michelle Tolentino knows that women and children in poverty can be forced into a life of abuse and exploitation.
Growing up in the Philippines, she lived in poverty but was sponsored by an American family through Compassion International.
"Because of the help they extended to me in the Philippines, I got to go to school," she said. "It helped me develop in all aspects of my life."
The Lazarus Church congregation will host a worship service of Music and Missions Sunday at the Lineboro volunteer fire company Fellowship Hall, the church's temporary home after its building burned down in December.
During the family-friendly event, Tolentino will share her story of growing up as a Compassion International-sponsored child and talk about the organization she co-founded, Made in Hope. Christian musician Caitlin Jane will also perform her music, which shares the message of hope. The event is open to the community.
Compassion International is a Christian child advocacy ministry that helps more than 1.2 million children in 26 countries.
Tolentino graduated from a university in the Philippines, where she earned her arts and communications degree. She worked as a marketing director for six years for a theater company before attending the Moody Bible Institute in Chicago to earn her master's degree.
In 2007, she started Made in Hope, which provides education and work opportunities for women who are former prostitutes and victims of human trafficking in the Asia Pacific, particularly the Philippines, Tolentino said.
"It's becoming a lifestyle for women who are living in poverty," she said.
She now speaks around the world at events to spread awareness about human trafficking. Part of the advocacy involves efforts at prevention, so Made in Hope started a program called Beauty for Ashes to help stop women and children from being exploited.
At the worship service Sunday, Tolentino will talk about the Christian response to the overwhelming need of the world.
"All of us are called to do something," she said. "God has something for us to do so we can make an impact."
Jane, who is based in Delaware, said she's been friends with Tolentino for 7 years. She visited the Philippines to help with Made in Hope and visit Compassion International sponsor sites.
"We've been able to partner in ministry and encourage each other," she said of their friendship.
Jane is passionate about Compassion International and she advocates for the organization during her concerts. Jane has sponsored children for 10 years.
"I like to advocate for the dignity of human life," she said.
Tolentino speaks to audiences with passion, love and zeal, Jane said.
"I know that anyone who comes out will absolutely be blessed by her message and encouraged and filled with hope" she said.
Lazarus Church Missions Chairwoman Carol Kicas said the congregation has been blessed with assistance since a fire destroyed its church building, so this event is a way to give back, Kicas said.
"It's a great chance to hear something interesting from a girl who had nothing," she said.
The church community has heard Jane sing but will now get the chance to learn a lot from Tolentino. It can be difficult for Americans to understand what poverty means in other countries and to be aware of its effects, Kicas said.
"We'd like to expose people to a different way of life and how fragile life can be for other people," she said.
]]></text></news-item>