<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2B4D-6468-92A3-7D01"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Today in History - March 27; Today in History - March 27</title><source>Canadian Press</source><author>The Canadian Press</author><text><![CDATA[Today in History for March 27:
On this date:
In 1513, Spanish explorer Juan Ponce de Leon sighted present-day Florida.
In 1613, Newfoundland's first English child was born.
In 1625, King James I died. In 1604, at the Hampton Court Conference, he authorized the translation project that produced the 1611 King James Version of the Bible. Charles I acceded to the English throne.
In 1667, English poet John Milton published "Paradise Lost," his epic of humankind's creation and fall.
In 1834, William Lyon Mackenzie was elected the first mayor of Toronto, the capital of Upper Canada.
In 1836, the first Mormon temple was built in Kirtland, Ohio.
In 1845, German researcher Wilhelm Roentgen, who discovered the x-ray, was born. He won the first Nobel prize for physics in 1901.
In 1848, the city of Fredericton was incorporated.
In 1855, Halifax inventor Abraham Gesner received a U.S. patent for distilling kerosene.
In 1883, Pile-O'-Bones, later renamed Regina, was made capital of the Northwest Territories, which then included Alberta, Saskatchewan and what became the Northwest Territories.
In 1885, the U.S. Congress approved spending $30,000 to buy camels for use by the American army in Texas.
In 1913, the French-language daily "Le Droit" began publication in Ottawa.
In 1918, Lt. Alan McLeod of the Royal Flying Corps won a Victoria Cross during the First World War. He safely landed his burning bomber in France and dragged his crewmate to safety. But the 18-year-old from Stonewall, Man., died of influenza seven months later in a Winnipeg hospital.
In 1933, Japan withdrew from the League of Nations.
In 1935, novelist John Buchan, Lord Tweedsmuir, was appointed governor general. He instituted the Governor General's literary awards in 1937.
In 1953, Canada's External Affairs minister Lester B. Pearson formally presented the United Nations with seven main doors for its headquarters in New York. The doors, which cost $75,000, were a gift from the people of Canada to the United Nations. The nickel-silver doors had actually been installed the previous October when the UN headquarters was completed.
In 1958, Nikita Khrushchev became Soviet premier, in addition to head of the Communist Party.
In 1964, the most violent earthquake known to have struck North America hit southern Alaska. The magnitude-8.3 quake affected over 500,000 square kilometres and killed 131 people.
In 1966, an instrument package was launched from Churchill, Man., to study the aurora borealis. It was the first all-Canadian space project.
In 1968, Soviet cosmonaut Yuri Gagarin, the first man in space, died when his plane crashed during a training flight. Gagarin, who travelled in space in 1961, was 34.
In 1973, Marlon Brando turned down the best-actor Oscar for "The Godfather" to protest Hollywood's treatment of natives.
In 1977, in the world's worst airplane disaster, 582 people died when two jumbo jets collided and burned on a runway at Tenerife in the Canary Islands. The worst single-plane disaster was the 1985 crash of a Japan Air Lines jet, which killed 520.
In 1980, 123 workers died when a North Sea floating oil field platform, the Alexander Kielland, capsized during a storm.
In 1992, New York state walked away from a $17 billion contract with Quebec Hydro in a dispute over price. The utility said the move would not affect plans to build the contentious $12.6 billion Great Whale project in northern Quebec. But the project was shelved in November 1994.
In 1998, Canada's health ministers announced a $1.1-billion compensation package for people who contracted hepatitis C through tainted blood. But the aid was limited to those infected between 1986 and mid-1990, when screening was available but not used. On Nov. 22, 2004, the Liberal government under Prime Minister Paul Martin announced it was willing to talk about compensating everyone who contracted hepatitis C through tainted blood, regardless of when they might have been infected.
In 1998, U.S. regulators approved a new drug to treat impotence. Viagra became an instant success. It was approved in Canada a year later.
In 2000, the Canadian Alliance became the official Opposition party in the House of Commons.
In 2002, comedian Milton Berle died after a battle with colon cancer. He was 93.
In 2003, the final report on the crash of Swissair Flight 111 off Nova Scotia in 1998, said the wiring that fed a controversial onboard entertainment system likely contributed to a fire that brought the plane down.
In 2003, the House of Commons unanimously adopted an opposition motion calling for an international tribunal to try Saddam Hussein and other Iraqi officials on charges of genocide, war crimes and other human-rights offences. (The motion was an expression of the view of Canadian government and Parliament, but had no force in itself).
In 2004, the body of nine-year-old Cecilia Zhang, abducted from her Toronto home in October, 2003, was found behind a church in Mississauga. In 2006, Min Chen pleaded guilty to second-degree murder and was sentenced to life imprisonment with a chance of parole after 15 years.
In 2004, Kevin Taft was elected leader of the Alberta Liberal Party.
In 2009, U.S. President Barack Obama announced an extra 4,000 U.S. soldiers would be deployed to Afghanistan, on top of the 17,000 already committed, to train that country's military and police forces.
In 2011, Cpl. Yannick Scherrer of Montreal was killed by an I.E.D. blast while on foot patrol near Nakhonay, southwest of Kandahar city. It brought to 155 the total number of Canadian military members who died as part of the Afghan mission since it began in 2002.
In 2012, former Mountie Janet Merlo launched a class-action lawsuit against the RCMP, alleging widespread sexual harassment.
In 2013, Richard Kachkar, who hit and killed Toronto police officer Sgt. Ryan Russell with a snowplow in January 2011, was found not criminally responsible because he was mentally ill. He was sent to a mental health facility in Whitby, Ont.
----
(The Canadian Press)
]]></text></news-item>