<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2B9E-8321-086A-EDD1"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Kenya; Jubilee Is Staring At Economic Collapse</title><source>Africa News</source><author>The Star (Nairobi)</author><text><![CDATA[President Uhuru Kenyatta has no right to threaten to cut Kenyans' salaries against their will in support of wage bill sustainability. Intimidate and threats will not help to salvage the sinking economy which seems to be at the verge of collapse. The president should have been more diplomatic in his approach to persuade Kenyans and to make them understand the real economic situation in the country.
Chest thumping and using power and authority vested in him as president to intimidate and threaten workers will only make the situation worse.
Professionals are marketable everywhere. President Uhuru should be reminded of brain drain that affected most Africa countries sometimes back due oppressive leadership like what he is trying to exercise.
Iam sure his statement at the Kenyatta International Conference ( KICC) shocked many delegates especially the Civil Society fraternity and organisations such as COTU and KNUT which represent workers.
Workers whether civil servants, teachers, law enforcers or legislators have a right as entrenched in the Bills of Rights in the constititution.
Uhuru though president has no right or authority to order workers around like small children and even to demand that they reduce their wages.
A good and worthy leader is humble and respectable. A leader should not impose decisions on people without proper and thorough consultation.
I admire Uhuru for personal agreeing to cut his salary to support Wage Bill. I hope he did not take the initiative just for a mere public relation exercise to hoodwink Kenyans into supporting it.
In fact the president should have taken the decision further by cutting his whole salary in support of the initiative Kenyatta and his Deputy Ruto have enough money so foregoing their salaries for the sake of Kenyans is not a big deal.
It appears that Jubilee government has lost control of itself and has now become dictatorial. Dangerous signs of desperation and frustration by the government is already showing especially when a president give ultimatums in public forums warning citizens of dire consequences if they fail to heed to his demands.
People go to school in order to become professionals and to earn good salaries. Better salaries are negotiated and not donated. Employees are not volunteers.
Neither are they charity undertakings. Professionals struggle and compete to become professionals and even to occupy positions which determine what they earn. High wage bill deficiency is Uhuru's headache as the president of Kenya. He should not shift blames to other innocent Kenyans.
Uhuru is not from the planet of Mars. He has been around. He served successive regimes of Moi and Kibaki in very key and senior positions.
He has been part of the rot in the Kenyan economy presiding over some of them in the past as Deputy Prime Minister, Minister of Finance, Trade and Local government.
Huge wage bills that have become a hindrance to his government were created by governments that he was part of. He can easily fix what went wrong because he was part of the problem.
Personally Iam not opposed to the reduction of the wage bill but Iam opposed to forcing people to back the exercise. I believe that there are better and more professional ways of dealing with than forcing workers to cut their hard earned earnings.
Cabinet Secretaries, Governors and other top government officials are spending lots of money on unnecessary activities including using big vehicles which guzzle fuel like water.
They enjoy massive security details which they don't need. The President and his Deputy has fleets of vehicles as escort around them when they travel and even when just moving from office to office where they can easily walk.
Some constitutional office holders are earning exorbitantly and yet many Kenyans cannot afford three meals a day even though they are working perhaps even harder than even those high paying constitutional organizations.
First ladies and Governors have become small presidents enjoying massive security escort with huge salaries and allowances spending government recklessly even going for salon and shopping.
Kenya should emulate Rwanda where Ministers or so called Cabinet Secretaries are given car loans to buy certain categories of vehicles.
If there was any wisdom left in the mind of Jubilee leadership they should have considered reducing spending on irrelevant and unnecessary expenditure rather than harassing, intimidating and threatening innocent and hard working professionals to cut their salaries.
It appears that all is not well with the Jubilee government after one year in office. The three arms of the government are fighting each other.
National Assembly has become just a show house where Members of Parliament uses their numerical strength to pass any law which favors them and they feel threatens the existence of Jubilee government.
Vilifying and criticizing donor agencies and other development partner organizations like USAID will not help to improve lives of suffering Kenyans.
The speakers of the National Assembly and Senate have become dictators making decisions and ruling which favors them, overrule and contradict policy matters and the constitution including disobeying court orders and threatening the existences of other constitutional offices.
Uhuru and Ruto should be reminded of Uganda where many scholars started fleeing the country in 1971 when former President Idi Amin Dada started behaving abnormally; issuing threats to the people of Uganda anyhow the same way president Kenyatta is beginning to behave in the name of controlling the wage bill.
Perhaps both Uhuru and Ruto were so young then that they actually have no idea or knowledge of what happened in Uganda and later in Rwanda in 1992.
Kenyans were warned against electing Jubilee leaders into leadership and that choices have consequences but the advised and warning were ignored .
Kenyans are now paying the price for their ignorance. Kenya like most African nations cannot survive without donor support. Life is becoming unbearable because of lack of support from donors. Many people are dying through road accidents and from curable, controllable and manageable diseases simply because they cannot afford medicines and proper medical care.
Cost of essential services such as postal, school fees, transport among many others has gone up unreasonably. Jubilee government seems to be hell bent and determined to destroy and suppress the media and the Civil Society organizations to ensure that there are no voices of reason against its failure and short comings.
Many observers believe that both Uhuru Kenyatta and Ruto have neither capability nor capacity to manage the country and to provide good leadership because of their background.
Besides not being tested and experienced, both Uhuru and Ruto are from milky background and found their way into position of leadership and big money and wealth too early without actually working hard to achieve them.
Unlike Uhuru who was borne and bread in the royal family of the late President Jomo Kenyatta, Deputy President William Ruto's claim that he is a hustler is contradictory because it is clear how he joined the political arena through the Moi's Youth for KANU brigade in 1992 becoming a millionaire straight from University.
The recent protest by Matatu owners and operators in Nairobi was a good beginning for fighting for people's right. Although the strike made commuters and other motorists to suffer and to lose business as it paralyzed operations in the city it showed maturity, solidarity and commitment by members of the transport sector especially Matatu.
The protest was successful in the sense that it managed to create some sense in the minds of certain Kenyan leaders who do not care for the welfare of the common mwanainchi.
Time has come for flamboyant and truly people minded leaders like Nairobi Senator Mike Sonko and the Civil Society organizations to rally people for peaceful protests to demand for good service, good governance and even for removing pancake type of leaders who have no respect for the welfare of the common people like the Arab spring that engulfed north African countries sometimes back.
Although transition and stability has become a serious challenge in those countries, the people of Egypt, Libya and Tunisia showed the whole world that irresponsible leaders and dictators can also be removed through mass movements and not necessarily by the gun.
African leaders themselves create room for civil disobedience like was the case of the Arab spring. They do unorthodox things, involve in massive corruption and misuse their powers and authorities.
Kenya like other African nations e.g. Rwanda, Uganda, and Burundi are likely to go the same way of the Arab countries. South Sudan is already in turmoil because of corruption, nepotism and bad leadership.
Wind of change is blowing across Africa uncontrollably. It is likely to bring down many autocratic leaders in a way that they might not believe. Most of them are blind, drunk with power and still living in the past. They cannot even feel the wind of change the change coming.
By Denise Kodhe, Executive Director, Institute for Democracy & Leadership in Africa- IDEA
]]></text></news-item>