<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2CE9-A940-721A-0878"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Welcome to the Jungle; Vice's fearless muckrakers confront the world's seamy underside</title><source>The Vancouver Province (British Columbia)</source><author>Bill Brownstein, Postmedia News</author><text><![CDATA[The series began where the first season left off, heading off to one of the world's most volatile hot spots. The correspondents are fearless, frequently putting their lives on the line. Welcome to Season 2 of Vice, which debuted Friday on HBO Canada, following Real Time with Bill Maher. The latter spit-disturber also happens to be executive producer of Vice.
These Vice investigative reporters are not from the traditional foreign correspondent TV mould.
They are muckrakers, prone to profane outbursts and a certain subjectivity when uncovering situations unsavoury. That was the case in the seasonopener, which followed the American money trail in Afghanistan and then headed off to the drugand-murder capital that is Rio de Janeiro. The Vice correspondents are led by a pair of Canadians from Montreal, who are not averse to plunging themselves into life-and-death scenarios in some of the world's most dangerous places: Shane Smith and Suroosh Alvi have made a career out of following the road less travelled. Smith and Alvi, along with fellow Montrealer Gavin McInnes, are the founders of Vice, which has, against all odds, mushroomed into a media empire.
Under the Vice Media banner, the company marks its 20th anniversary this year, and has tackled just about every aspect of media since setting up shop. There is Vice Magazine, Vice Film, Vice Records, Vice Publishing, Vice TV and the Viceland.com site that fuels all of the above.
Vice's roots are modest, to say the least. It actually began as Voice, an alternative cultural publication for Montreal Anglos - not the most surefire way to turn a buck in a town where there were already two alternative cultural publications, the now-defunct Hour and Mirror, serving the city's Anglos.
And let's just say Smith, Alvi and McInnes are about as unlikely a group of media barons as were ever unleashed on the universe. Although they may have been former city slackers living on welfare, they did have moxie - and then some. To drum up publicity for their new mag, the boys spread a rumour that the Village Voice was threatening to sue them over their name. They received international coverage, a boost in circulation and street cred, here and around the continent.
Now based in the U.S. (with an office in Montreal), Vice Media operates in 35 countries and reaches an audience in the tens of millions with its unorthodox, though compelling coverage of news, music, travel, sports and fashion.
What began as a raunchy, marginalized lifestyle street mag for the disenfranchised and disaffected between the ages of 18 and 29 has morphed into a groundbreaking - though still unconventional - media operation for all ages.
Rather than soak up praise at 20th-anniversary bashes, Smith chose to go to Afghanistan for this year's opening episode.
He is aghast to learn - as viewers will be - that the U.S. has spent $100 billion on reconstruction projects in Afghanistan.
Bad enough to know that much of that money has been essentially tossed away, but, even worse, has fallen into the mitts of the very people U.S. forces have been fighting for control of the country, the Taliban.
Smith points out how the U.S. has a long history of rebuilding countries it has destroyed, going back to post-Second World War Germany. His allegations about the misuse of funds are not just idle speculation.
He gets the goods straight from someone who knows: John Sopko, a former crimebusting prosecutor, is the U.S. point-man, the Special Inspector General for Afghanistan reconstruction. And when Sopko says things aren't going well, that Afghanistan is "one of the most corrupt countries in the world," we can take that to the ... well ... bank.
As an example of wastage, Smith visits a power plant in the country, built at a cost of $300 million. Problem is a lack of electricity to power the plant. The plant managers have to buy $20 million of imported fuel to get it going. Because they lose too much in the process, the plant can't operate regularly. The bigger problem for the U.S. is that after 12 years of occupation and about $1 trillion spent to protect the country with its troops and military machinery, Afghanistan is still not safe and will be less so when there are no longer boots on the ground. All of which leaves Sopko realizing that the U.S. is actually building an infrastructure for the Taliban to take over.
Talk turns to cost of the U.S. providing aircraft that will end up rusting on tarmacs, to IEDs (improvised explosive devices), which wind up in the wrong hands and which are responsible for countless American deaths and casualties, and to other forms of military hardware, which are being plundered, stolen and sold, with the resulting funds lining the pockets of the Taliban.
Sopko says there is no personal accountability from the U.S. generals responsible for losing some of the $100 billion in reconstruction. Sobering stuff.
More of same beckons as another Vice team hits Rio, which is trying to clean up its act in advance of this year's World Cup and the 2016 Summer Olympics.
The Brazilian powers that be desperately want to live down Rio's rep as a drug-andmurder centre nonpareil. So the country's Special Police Operations Battalion (BOPE) has undertaken a "pacification" program of Rio's slums - favelas - wherein much of these nefarious activities take place.
Alas, in their zeal, some BOPE members have become just as heavy-handed and vicious as those on whom they are cracking down. Reports of extortion, torture and murder have become altogether too routine. Then there are the criminals who have simply vanished and are more than likely dead, thanks to some of the more corrupt BOPE officers, with drug money often ending up in the hands of the police.
In the season's second episode (airing March 28 at 10 p.m.), the Vice squad ventures off to Greenland to catch that country's glaciers in free fall. While some in these parts tend to downplay global warming in light of the polar vortex that has put a viselike grip on us, a visit to Greenland should convince even the most skeptical that this dilemma is very much with us and getting more out of control.
Consider these factoids: Greenland has lost an amount of ice large enough to supply Los Angeles with water for the next 2000 years.
Additionally, if Greenland's glaciers start melting even more quickly - as they might - 80 of the world's 100 largest cities could eventually end up under water. Another frightening revelation comes in the bottom half of this episode with the news that three million to eight million bonded labourers are essentially working as slaves in Pakistan. Many are displaced tenants at the mercy of overlords who have them trapped in debts from which they can never escape. Even more horrifying is the number of bonded labourers who are children, some as young as four.
Not that we needed reminding, but reality can bite.
]]></text></news-item>