<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2D45-1BCF-8C27-6B37"><date>2014-03-09</date><title>YOUR SAY</title><source>The Examiner Newspaper</source><author>Natalie Ashdown</author><text><![CDATA[Convenient sexism
JULIA Gillard continually heaped abuse on Tony Abbott but the moment he criticised her it was sexist.
Lara Giddings has followed the same path in her criticism of opponents, but now that someone points out her short comings it is sexist.
When did sexism become one-way?
- FRED WOODS, Devonport.
Shambolic electricity
FOR anyone wondering whether to restore the Labor-Green government for a further four years, I commend reading page 118 of the Independent Assessment of the Tasmanian Electricity Supply Industry draft report published in December 2011.
The three independent experts provided what they called "key messages".
One of these tells how the Labor-Green government directed Aurora to purchase and complete the Tamar Valley Power Station after the promoters failed.
These independent experts pointed out that the purchase price, which the government negotiated, resulted in a cost of $150 million, yes, $150 million, more than valuation advice given to government.
Just imagine what that $150 million has done to the price of electricity.
Is this why the electricity industry has reached the shambolic state in which it is in?
Governments should let the electricity industry experts run the system rather than interfering and creating costs and losses.
- TONY BENNEWORTH, Launceston.
Qantas reaps 'reward'
IT IS noticeable that at no time during the current dilemma facing Qantas has any reference been made to its own creation of one of its strongest competitors, Jetstar.
The inevitable impact and outcome of this arrogant and short-sighted business management decision was only a matter of time in coming - and that time has come.
It's not difficult to pinpoint the person responsible.
It's also a pity he wasn't shown the door at the time of that decision as it's a bit late now, when the number of those who have and continue to lose their jobs grows.
- JOHN J SEATON, Prospect Vale.
Nazi clarification
I UNDERSTAND Adam Saunders' (Examiner, March 6) concerns with the sale of Nazi memorabilia.
This period of history has attracted more researchers, historians, authors, collectors and military vehicle buffs than any other.
My interest is in the latter.
As far as I can research, it is not yet illegal to sell the items Mr Saunders is concerned with.
In fact, similar items were on offer at a Launceston auction house in the recent past.
I believe the Nazi period is now part of the German education system.
Before being hijacked by the Nazis, the swastika was for thousands of years considered a good-luck charm, and still is in some Middle Eastern countries.
Mr Saunders is incorrect to associate the Iron Cross with the Nazis.
It goes back way before them, and further back than World War I.
The Iron Cross is a Prussian medal and was first struck and awarded in 1813.
It was adopted as the German national symbol in World War I and re-introduced after the second.
It is carried on current German military vehicles and aircraft.
- GREG WALDON, Invermay.
Irresponsible policies
THE latest social reform by the Greens - abolishing poker machines - is another attempt by this divisive party to force businesses to lay off staff and find alternative streams of revenue.
Given that most of the Greens' policies are the reason for this state being in collapse, are Nick McKim and co serious about the loss of tax revenue and the monies donated by the Federal Group to communities being put at serious risk by this
irresponsible party.
The Greens hide behind environmental issues but are in reality a blight on the political landscape, witness the damage they have done to this state.
Wake up Nick McKim, Cassie O'Connor and Kim Booth and get ito the real world and start working towards worthwhile policies such as small business, responsible economic management, ecotourism job creation and a sustainable timber industry, to name
but a few.
- STEVEN HANCOCK, Norwood.
Political dichotomy
TASMANIANS have a clear choice on Saturday, March 15.
A huge debt that will only grow bigger, an education system that's spiralling ito an abyss, an economy that's choking to the point it's conking out and a dysfunctional health system.
Or a reduction in debt, fiscal responsibility rather than broken promises, an education system that can and should rightly be repaired, an economy that is freed of suffocating red and green tape with every Australian supported to either start
their own business (without myriad rules) or work for a business that is unconstrained by burdensome over-regulation and a proper fast responding health care system?
Debt or no debt?
Education or failure?
Freedom to work or unemployment?
Health crisis or care?
Do I need to mention who you should consider voting for?
- TONY GRIGGS, Palana.
Tell us what you think about issues concerning North and North-West Tasmania. Letters should be 150 words or less. Shorter letters will get priority. Send letters to The Sunday Examiner, PO Box 99, Launceston, 7250 or email sunday@examiner.
com.au. Writers must include their full name and address.
]]></text></news-item>