<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2D5F-6477-2968-3A35"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Toxic leak bursts bubble for Satos</title><source>Sydney Morning Herald (Australia)</source><author>Peter Hannam</author><text><![CDATA[Putting a positive spin on CSG is proving challenging, writes Peter Hannam.
Up until a week ago, the mood within emerging gas giant Satos was buoyant.
The NSW government had declared the company's coal seam gas exploration in the Pilliga Forest a "strategic energy project" on February 20, setting a timetable for approval assessments.
"That was really good," Chandran Vigneswaran, head of corporate communications, said on Thursday from Satos' offices overlooking the Opera House. "We were feeling positive that we were moving forward."
Then, as regularly happens in the controversy-dogged industry, the public's perception of CSG safety took a dive.
Fairfax Media revealed last weekend that uranium readings in groundwater beneath Satos's leaking wastewater pond near Narrabri in the state's north were 20 times safe drinking water levels. The detail was unearthed by the Wilderness Society via freedom of information requests and then confirmed by the NSW Environment Protection Authority.
The first known case of aquifer contamination in Australia from CSG ignited a firestorm of reaction from CSG foes. "This is game over for coal seam gas," said Greens MP Jeremy Buckingham, hailing the findings as "definitive proof that unconventional gas ... pollutes aquifers with extremely toxic elements".
While the threat was deemed minimal, questions remain about the processes that lifted uranium levels above natural amounts in surrounding soils.
The fact the NSW EPA announced Satos had been fined $1500 for a "pollution incident" without naming the elements involved in its low-key media release on February 18 didn't help. Its investigations report was only made available days after the contamination exposure, and only on request.
Sensing a cover-up, the Greens and Labor will next week demand the O'Farrell government produce all documents to identify whether ministers knew of the contamination before agreeing to prioritise the Satos project.
Suspicion that federal and state Coalition governments are determined to ram through CSG is fanned by their eager support for a "one-stop shop" to cut environmental "greentape". Federal Resources Minister Ian Macfarlane has also warned of "a gas crisis looming in 2016 ... we're running out of time", a call echoed by the gas industry.
Energy analyst Gundi Royle, though, says the gas squeeze is "a created shortage", caused mostly by three $20 billion-plus liquefied natural gas export ventures in Queensland that were approved before gas supplies were fully secured.
"I came away from dialogue with the Queensland authorities convinced that the primary objective was to push the (CSG) industry activity through and leave industry largely self-regulating," said Royle, who is principal of Royle Energy Partners.
"The lack of resources frustrated all genuine effort by individuals in the regulatory bodies to discharge their duties properly," Royle said. "I felt that was a desired outcome."
While governments declare a need to rely on the science to determine whether CSG ventures can operate safely, cash-starved regulatory bodies have little option but to rely on data supplied by the companies themselves.
James Baulderstone, the executive in charge of Satos' unconventional gas operations in Australia, said "everyone agrees there has been no harm to humans and animals" from the Pilliga incident.
The leakage of briny water had freed up uranium in the soil but had only filtered to contained "perched layers". The pollution remained separated by dozens of metres of impervious clays from the main Pilliga aquifer used to supply homes and livestock in the region, Satos hydrogeologist Glenn Toogood said.
Satos is spending tens of millions of dollars to ensure against future waste water leakages when the project ramps up - if approved. The company is also setting up online portals to make public more of its data. Even so, Satos remains wary that more disclosure will necessarily win more support.
"Every time we put something in the public domain it is misconstrued to its most significant serious impact," Baulderstone said.
For instance, while the company aims to drill 850 wells that tally would be over 40 years, with about 100-150 operating at one time. Salt produced from drilling ito salty aquifers as deep as one kilometre would be about 20,000 tonnes a year rather than the one million tonnes some have speculated.
Too good said the CSG industry is now tightly regulated: "I can guarantee you that most older service stations, built pre-1985, would have massive plumes of migration (in groundwater) of much nastier things than the low concentrations of uranium that we have."
While the EPA might want to start taking a look at the odd local servo, the uranium readings have opened new questions about CSG.
"CSG water, by its nature, carries a high risk of mobilisation of otherwise stable uranium in soil and transporting it to aquifers or surface waters," said Stuart Khan, a water expert at the University of NSW who prepared a CSG water study for the NSW chief scientist's independent review of the industry.
"Neither the EPA or Satos has yet identified these precise mechanisms of mobilisation," Khan said.
While Satos is confident it can ride out the latest bump, it is unlikely to be the last one. "If the gas industry is going to be successful in NSW, it needs a community that wants it," Vigneswaran said.
]]></text></news-item>