<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2DB6-20A8-B8F5-7A57"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Hedge fund Hayman raises Nationstar bet</title><source>THE DALLAS MORNING NEWS</source><author>HANAH CHO, Staff Writer hcho@dallasnews.com</author><text><![CDATA[Dallas-based Hayman Capital Management is taking a bigger gamble on Nationstar Mortgage Holdings despite regulatory scrutiny facing the Lewisville servicing company and others like it.
Founded by Kyle Bass, Hayman Capital owns a 5.3 percent stake in Nationstar, or nearly 4.8 million shares, according to a securities filing disclosed Friday. At the end of last year, Hayman owned about 1.1 million shares of Nationstar, according to the hedge fund's filing of its holdings.
"Hayman believes that Nationstar offers a compelling investment opportunity as misinformation has created a divergence between perception and reality," Steele Schottenheimer, Hayman's managing director of investor relations, said in an email.
Earlier this month, New York's top banking regulator sent a letter to Nationstar, questioning the company's servicing practices and requesting data on its portfolio and policies.
New York State Superintendent of Financial Services Benjamin M. Lawsky said his office received "hundreds of complaints" from New York consumers about the company's mortgage practices.
Appearing on CNBC's Squawk Box by telephone Friday, Bass explained his fund's thinking behind the increased investment.
Non-bank servicing companies such as Nationstar, Bass said, do a better job of servicing loans than the big banks.
In determining their effectiveness, Bass said Hayman found that non-bank servicers had fewer customer complaints per delinquent loan than banks.
In fact, Nationstar had the lowest ratio of complaints versus seriously delinquent loans at 1.9 percent, Bass said.
Large banks, such as Bank of America and Wells Fargo, had an average ratio of 7 percent.
"The banks are three times worse at doing this, but the regulatory inquiry is in the nonbank sector," Bass said. "Ben Lawsky should focus on who the worst players are and not who the best are."
Bass made his name and money betting against securities based on subprime mortgages.
The stock rallied on Bass' investment, also lifting other non-bank servicers.
Nationstar shares gained $1.50, or 4.8 percent, to close at $32.77.
Sterne Agee analyst Henry J. Coffey Jr. said in a research note that the rally "shows how heavily oversold these stocks are."
The nonbank mortgage servicing business has exploded in recent years as banks seek to unload problem loans in the face of higher capital requirements.
Nationstar is the sixth-largest mortgage servicer in the U.S. The company oversees nearly $391 billion in unpaid principal balance in more than 2.3 million loans, according to its annual report.
"Over the last several years, Nationstar has invested heavily in infrastructure and personnel to scale their platform," Schottenheimer said. "The company is now in great position to reap the benefits of these investments and grow servicing profitability in 2014 and beyond."
Follow Hanah Cho on Twitter at @hanahcho.
]]></text></news-item>