<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2DC7-FE04-C6BC-8E22"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Treasury in ultimatum to Buffalo City</title><source>WeekendPost (South Africa)</source><author>Asanda Nini</author><text><![CDATA[Metro stands to lose R700m FINANCE Minister Pravin Gordhan has given Buffalo City Metro a choice - flush out crooked officials and politicians or lose grant funding worth R700-million. Council must now table any forensic reports it has kept under wraps within the coming months. At least two completed forensic investigations that never saw the light of day, will come into play.
The first is an Ernst & Young report into the metro's R2-billion Make-a-Difference (MAD) campaign. The report implicates various councillors and officials and although it has been referred to a council committee, it has been swept under the carpet. The second concerns a R17-million refuse bag contract. A forensic report by MMB Consultants, completed early last year, has been collecting dust in the office of executive mayor Zukiswa Ncitha. A circular from National Treasury to all municipalities warned grant funding could be withheld if forensic investigation reports are not dealt with. "Councils are again reminded of their responsibility to discuss the reports in council and to implement a fair procedure in dealing with the findings of those reports. This would in all probability require action against councillors and/or officials. "If it is found that a municipality commissioned a forensic audit and that the subsequent report did not serve before the municipal council, National Treasury will invoke Section 216 (2) of the constitution against that municipality and stop all grant transfers." Treasury spokesman Jabulani Sikhakhane yesterday confirmed that affected municipalities were set to lose all their conditional grants . "This will be done on a case-by-case basis and in line with the release of funding. Affected municipalities will have to provide evidence that they have implemented the recommendations arising out of such an investigation." Ratepayer groups said the millions BCM is at risk of losing could be spent on upgrading the roads, tackling the issue of izinyoka (illegal electricity connectors), upgrading the sewerage works and maintenance of public areas. Metro spokesman Keith Ngesi said in the financial year ending in June this year, BCM received more than R659-million in grants from Treasury. For their 2014-15 allocations, they are expecting R706-million. Ngesi said the grants were used for infrastructure development. He would not comment on why council had failed to act on graft reports. Council speaker Luleka Simon-Ndzele and Ncitha yesterday could not be reached for comment. Border Kei Chamber of Business chairman Les Holbrook described it as a sad state of affairs, citing the unauthorised increase of councillors' salaries as a possible reason. Local Government MEC Mlibo Qoboshiyane yesterday said he agreed with Treasury's approach. He said all forensic investigations were supposed to be commissioned and tabled in council. DA councillor Lance Weyer this week submitted a motion to Simon-Ndzele's office requesting council table the graft reports at the next council meeting. Gonubie Ratepayers' Association chairman Andre Swart said withholding the grant might be a good thing as it could be a wake-up call to provincial government to start acting on corruption. "Only 35% of this year's annual budget was used towards the city's infrastructure. Then they want to go to a conference in Port Alfred to decide how to spend the rest. It's just not on," Swart said. Berlin Residents' Association chairman Khaya Witbooi said the grants could have assisted in eradicating the bucket system in the Berlin area, improving roads and for the maintenance of "run-down" municipal buildings. - Additional reporting by Zisanda Nkonkobe
]]></text></news-item>