<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2DE1-626B-D08F-B47C"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Miners' union has not been silent</title><source>The Star (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The article by Mohamed Motala titled "All should be safe in South Africa" (The Star, Opinion and Analysis, March 11) refers.
Mr Motala lashed out at the National Union of Mineworkers (NUM) and Cosatu and accused them of having made a minimal response to the deaths of the Zama Zama illegal miners and of not publicly campaigning to have those miners trapped underground rescued.
Mr Motala is uniformed about the position of NUM on illegal mining - our general secretary, Frans Baleni, has been outspoken about illegal mining in South Africa.
Last month, Mr Baleni, during the NUM post-NEC media briefing, warned that a major tragedy is looming in disused mines if the government does not take decisive action to curb thriving illegal mining.
He said: "We have been urging the ministers of police and mines to improve on their intelligence side. These illegal miners are just troopers, the network is really big. There is going to be a big disaster one day - we will not be talking about the death of nine |people."
He said the government needed to be proactive and rein in the leaders of these illegal mining networks.
He pointed out that they were processing gold particles underground and it was highly dangerous to have open flames underground because of the presence of methane gas.
The national executive committee of NUM met over two days - on February 20 and 21 - and pronounced on illegal mining in South Africa.
Part of the NEC statement read: "The NEC is concerned that poor people are made to take risks for a pittance while syndicates derive pleasure and extract millions from illegal mining."
When the foot soldiers are arrested and charged the real big guns of organised crime are never brought to book.
The desperate unemployed poor people are lured into the cycle of dirty money as long as the big guns are not effectively pursued.
In this regard, NUM calls on the government to intensify efforts to track down the kingpins of illegal mining operations in order to protect the poor from falling prey to this dangerous cycle.
"This also undermines the South African economy and it cannot be left unattended.
"Any business and government that is serious about its people must take urgent steps to tackle this.
"This NEC further urges all companies to put more effort and seriousness into the closing of deserted mines.
"Illegal mining is not only a manifestation of negligence by mining companies, it is also a challenge to the security of the state and must be responded to accordingly."
It is very sad that Mr Motala did not do research before writing his column.
Livhuwani Mammburu
Acting NUM national spokesman
]]></text></news-item>