<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2E08-785F-79A4-F368"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Massachusetts: Residential Supervisor</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Department of Human Resources, The State of Massachusetts has issued the following job opportunities: Agency Name: Dept. of Developmental Services Official Title: Residential Supervisor (A/B) Functional Title: Residential Supervisor Occupational Group: Social Service Position Type: Civil Service Full-Time or Part-Time: Full-Time Salary Range: $44,139.16 to $59,857.72 Annually Bargaining Unit: 08 Shift: Day Confidential: No Number Of Vacancies: 1 City/Town: Athol Region: CENTRAL Facility Location: Monadnock Program - State Operated Homes 41 Brickyard Road Athol, MA 01331 Application Deadline: 03-28-2014 Apply Online: Yes Posting ID: J40275
This position is funded from the Commonwealth's annual operating budget. Duties:
The Residential Supervisor (A/B) participates and directs the clinical and administrative operations of an assigned residence, including residential program development and implementation or compliance with policies, regulations and procedures; monitors residential budgets and resident funds; promotes principles of normalization and dignity within the program; and perform related work as required. The basic purpose of this work is to supervise and direct overall operation of community residences for the developmentally disabled in meeting the active treatment needs of the individuals. Qualifications:
MINIMUM ENTRANCE REQUIREMENTS:
REQUIRED WORK EXPERIENCE: At least three years of full-time, or equivalent part-time, professional experience in counseling, guidance, teaching, or therapeutic services for individuals with mental retardation, of which at least one year must have been in a supervisory capacity.
SUBSTITUTIONS: - A Bachelor's degree in social work, rehabilitation, psychology, sociology, human services, education of the physically or emotionally handicapped, education of the multiple handicapped, or education of the learning disabled may be substituted for two years of the required nonsupervisory experience on the basis of two years of education for one year of experience. - A Master's or higher degree social work, rehabilitation, psychology, sociology, human services, education of the physically or emotionally handicapped, education of the multiple handicapped, or education of the learning disabled may be substituted for an additional year of the required nonsupervisory experience on the basis of two years of education for one year of experience.
- One year of education equals 30 semester hours. Education toward a degree will be prorated on the basis of the proportion of the requirements actually completed.
- No substitution will be permitted for the required supervisory experience.
LICENSES: Based on assignment, travel may be required. Those employees who elect to use a motor vehicle for travel must have a current and valid Massachusetts Class D Motor Vehicle Operator's license or the equivalent from another state.
For further information please visit: https://jobs.hrd.state.ma.us
]]></text></news-item>