<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2E0F-9CA2-69BE-6288"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Citations raise concerns about park's trails</title><source>Courier-Post (Cherry Hill, New Jersey)</source><author>By, Carly Q. Romalino</author><text><![CDATA[A Logan soil recycler was found to be out of compliance with state regulations Thursday, 10 days after being named in a federal lawsuit that claims the company violated state-issued permits.
Chris LaChall/Courier-Post
Soil Safe, a Maryland-based company, was cited after a solid waste inspection for noncompliance on 12 items and possible violations on four more on the state's 44-point checklist, according to state Department of Environmental Protection records.
Citations ranged from storing unprocessed material on the site for more than a year to accepting soil containing sludges, high amounts of oils or other contaminants exceeding department standards, state records indicated.
Since 2009, state solid waste inspections have turned up violations or compliance failures three times - 2012, 2013 and Thursday, according to the DEP.
The inspection comes shortly after Delaware Riverkeeper Network filed a federal lawsuit attempting to cease Soil Safe's operations. Riverkeeper, an environmental group, claims the company violated its state-issued permits. Its operations endanger public and environmental health, according to court documents file by the group.
The lawsuit is backed by other environmental groups in the state including the New Jersey Sierra Club, NY/NJ Baykeeper and the Rahway River Association. The groups also oppose Soil Safe's proposal for a site remediation project in Union County.
Soil Safe officials declined to comment Friday.
The lawsuit has raised concern about the condition of soil from the company that was used for a nearby Gloucester County project. Soil Safe supplied dirt for a walking and horseback riding project at the county's Delaware River Marine and Equestrian Park in Logan.
The trail project broke ground in 2009 under the direction of then-Freeholder-Director Stephen M. Sweeney. The trail project is expected to wrap up in 2015, according to county spokeswoman Debra Sellitto.
N.J. Sierra Club Director Jeff Tittel said possible contaminated material at the DREAM Park works against the reason the park was built - to protect the land from contaminated Delaware River dredge spoils.
"Gloucester County freeholders were very much opposed to the Delaware deepening and the dumping of dredge spoils in county parkland," Tittel said.
Soil that has not been properly cleaned at the facility could be more hazardous than the dredge, he said.
Larry Wallace, a former Gloucester County freeholder, walked the property line Friday between Soil Safe and the soybean farm next door. The farm is sandwiched between Soil Safe's dirt mounds and the county park on Route 130.
Rahway River Association founder Andrew Voros contacted Wallace last year as the group researched its own fight against Soil Safe.
"It's a public safety issue," Wallace said, dwarfed by the company's soaring dirt mounds. "We could be putting human, horses and our environment in danger."
Gloucester County is trusting the DEP, Sellitto said.
"The procedures Soil Safe has to go through with the NJDEP are somewhat rigorous," Sellito said. "We feel confident that the NJDEP would let us know if there is an issue."
Wallace said the questions could be answered with random soil sampling at DREAM Park.
"Then we know if it's dirty or not."
Reach Carly Q. Romalino at (856) 486-2476 and cromalino@cpsj.com
]]></text></news-item>