<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2E8C-3851-3E23-AD0D"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Lawyer takes on sex traffickers</title><source>The Sunday Star-Times (Auckland, New Zealand)</source><author>By ROB STOCK</author><text><![CDATA[ONE OF the country's top commercial litigators, who has been involved in some of the biggest commercial and tax cases of recent years, is heading to Asia to help fight the sex-trafficking of children.
Bell Gully's Ralph Simpson has been in the thick of some of New Zealand's most momentous commercial cases including the recent multi-million dollar tax cases involving Sovereign and Alesco, and the court-sanctioned break- ups of Fletcher Challenge and Fisher & Paykel.
Simpson is heading to South East Asia next year to work for Nvader, a charitable trust and NGO (non-government organisation) set up by Kiwi investigator Daniel Walker to rescue young women and children trafficked into the brothels of South East Asia. The trust gathers the evidence to bring the criminals to justice.
Nvader works closely with the local police, and assists authorities and other NGOs to help victims build a new life. Where necessary, it also stands as witnesses to help put the criminals behind bars.
Simpson, a straight- talking man with a measured demeanour and unwavering eye contact, is frank about life as a commercial lawyer.
"It has been stimulating, never-boring, highly- fulfilling, and has involved work that has made a difference in the business community, and it has brought him recognition and financial rewards," he said.
"But it is no longer enough, and hasn't been for some years.
"As you move through life, you spend the first half of your life trying to win success," he said.
"Sometimes, about your late 40s, you start thinking about trying to make your life significant and the world a better place."
After hearing Walker speak, he felt he could make a contribution to Nvader's work.
"When I got an appreciation of human trafficking, particularly sex trafficking, I thought there was nothing worse for a kid than to be raped twenty times a day and I thought I can do something about it."
Simpson said as a commercial litigator his job was principally about money. "It's not going to make a difference to history."
But the skills to succeed in his current role are the contributions he can bring to Nvader. And Nvader is effective, said Simpson, who joined its board last year. It rescued 40 women and children in 2013 alone and so far this year the tally is at 23, he said.
He asked for the name of the city in which he will be based to be kept confidential as there are dangers to challenging organised crime. But he and his wife have met some of the children rescued from brothels and seen the way they are being helped.
Leaving the commercial life will bring personal challenges though.
"I wonder how my ego will cope for a little while," he admits. "I'm a senior litigation partner in one of the largest law firms in New Zealand. That has a lot of kudos."
The cases he has been involved with may have been high profile, but, Simpson said: "In a year, I will be forgotten."
"In some ways that [leaving his current role] will be a healthy change. I will have to focus on who I am, not what I am."
"Human trafficking is now the fastest-growing organised criminal activity in the world," Simpson said. "If it keeps growing at this rate, it will overtake drugs trafficking."
--------------------
CAPTION:
Big change: Commercial litigator Ralph Simpson wants to join the fight against the sex-trafficking of children.
Picture: Chris Skelton/Fairfax NZ
]]></text></news-item>