<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2ED5-85C5-51A5-D727"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Wesleyan welcomed Pulitzer Prize winning author to campus</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Wesleyan College has issued the following news release:
Douglas Blackmon, Pulitzer Prize-winning author of Slavery By Another Name: The Re-enslavement of Black People in America from the Civil War to WWII, was on campus to discuss his book at Wesleyan College’s Porter Auditorium on Thursday, February 7 at 11:15AM. On February 6th, the College hosted a screening of Blackmon’s acclaimed PBS documentary by the same name, in the Peyton Anderson Amphitheatre in Taylor Hall. Both events are free and open to the public.
Blackmon is a contributing editor at The Washington Post and chair and host of Forum, a public affairs program produced by the University of Virginia’s Miller Center and aired on more than 100 PBS affiliates across the U.S. Until joining The Washington Post in 2011, Blackmon was the longtime chief of The Wall Street Journal’s Atlanta bureau and the paper’s Senior National Correspondent. He has written about or directed coverage of some of the most pivotal stories in American life, including the election of President Barack Obama, the rise of the tea party movement, and the BP oil spill. Overseeing coverage of 11 southeastern states for The Journal, he and his team of reporters were responsible for The Journal’s acclaimed coverage of Hurricane Katrina and the failed federal response after that disaster, the Journal’s investigation into the training and preparations of the 9/11 hijackers in Florida, immigration, poverty, politics and daily reporting on more than 2,500 corporations based in the region. Blackmon is also a co-founder and board member of two socially and ethnically diverse charter schools serving more than 600 students, including his own two children, in grades kindergarten through eight in the inner city of Atlanta.
In addition to winning the 2009 Pulitzer Prize, Slavery by Another Name was a New York Times bestseller in both hardback and soft cover editions, and was awarded a 2009 American Book Award, the 2009 Mississippi Institute of Arts and Letters non-fiction book prize, a 2008 Gustavus Myers Center for the Study of Bigotry and Human Rights Book Award, the NAACP Freedom Fund Outstanding Achievement Award, and many other citations. He has been honored by the state legislature of Georgia for distinguished scholarship and service to history. In 2010, Blackmon received the Grassroots Justice Award from the Georgia Justice Project.
Blackmon is a much sought after lecturer on race, history and social memory. In Spring 2010, he was invited by Attorney General Eric Holder to present a lecture to senior Department of Justice of officials in Washington D.C. He also has lectured at Harvard School of Law, Yale University, Princeton, the New School, Emory University, Vanderbilt School of Law, the Clinton and Lincoln presidential libraries, and many other institutions.
For more information please visit: http://www.wesleyancollege.edu
]]></text></news-item>