<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="2F60-2004-E45C-195A"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Dentist with local office facing tax charges; BrooklineAccused of using businesses to hide money from IRS - .</title><source>The Telegraph (Nashua, New Hampshire)</source><author>JOSEPH G. COTE; Staff Writer</author><text><![CDATA[BROOKLINE - A dentist with a local office is facing federal tax evasion and obstruction charges in Massachusetts.
Dr. George Fenzell, 56, of Douglas, Mass., was indicted by a federal grand jury on six felony charges, including five counts that he didn't pay taxes from 2000-11. The indictments, filed at the U.S. District Court in Boston and unsealed last week, accuse Fenzell of using a number of businesses, including at least one registered in New Hampshire, to hide his income from the Internal Revenue Service.
Government prosecutors asked a judge to unseal the court files on Friday, March 7, following Fenzell's arrest. He pleaded not guilty to all of the charges, according to records.
The charges against Fenzell accuse him of creating multiple business entities, including Brookline Dental Associates Trust and Brookline Dental Professional Corp., to hide his income through a series of payments and withdrawals, many using commingled "warehouse" accounts that more than one entity deposited money into, according to court records.
Fenzell named people as trustees and made it appear they owned or controlled certain aspects of the businesses and used cash extensively to limit his "paper trail," according to court documents.
In 2007, Massachusetts authorities investigated Fenzell for unpaid state income taxes, and he filed a delinquent federal income tax return for 2000-05. The IRS told Fenzell he owed more than $320,000 in back taxes and penalties for those years, and from then until 2012, Fenzell "endeavored to obstruct and impede the IRS," according to court documents.
Fenzell is facing five counts of tax evasion and a single count of "corruptly endeavoring to obstruct the IRS," according to court records.
He is listed as the agent for one business registered with the New Hampshire Secretary of State. Brookline Dental P.C. is in good standing with the state, according to the secretary of state website, and has offices at 55 Route 13 in Brookline.
Fenzell posted a $50,000 bond and was released on conditions he not travel outside of Massachusetts, according to court records.
Joseph G. Cote can be reached at 594-6415 or jcote@nashuatelegraph.com
]]></text></news-item>