<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="307C-39A8-45B5-33AD"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Hoeness stands down as Bayern president after being sentenced to three-and-a-half year jail term for tax evasion</title><source>MailOnline</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Uli Hoeness has tendered his resignation as president of Bayern Munich after being sentenced to three and a half years in prison for tax evasion.
The 62-year-old admits his decision to evade taxes by using a secret bank account in Switzerland amounted to the "biggest mistake" of his life and he confirmed he will not be appealing Thursday's judgement by the Munich state prosecutors.
That stance flies in the face of the initial claims of his defence solicitor Hanns Feigen, who announced an appeal would be made in the wake of Thursday's verdict.
'After discussions with my family, I have decided to accept the decision of the Munich state prosecutors regarding my tax issues,' Hoeness wrote in a statement on Bayern's website.
'I have asked my solicitors not to appeal the decision. That reflects my views on decency, conduct and personal responsibility.
'Tax evasion was the biggest mistake of my life and I will face up to the consequences of this mistake.
'I will also be resigning from my position of president of Bayern Munich. By doing this, I would like to prevent any damage to my club.
'Bayern Munich are my lifetime's work and they will remain such. I will remain attached to this amazing club and its people in a different way for as long as I live.
'I would like to thank all my personal friends and the supporters of Bayern Munich from the bottom of my heart for their support.'
After learning of an investigation by a German magazine into German tax evaders using accounts in Switzerland, Hoeness voluntarily approached the German tax authorities to admit his actions early last year.
However, a four-day trial in Munich this week revealed that Hoeness had evaded far more taxes than he had declared, with the initial amount of 3.5million euros rising sharply to over 28million euros.
Friday's announcement brings an end to Hoeness' long involvement with Bayern, having first joined the club as a player in 1970.
After ending his playing career due to injury in 1979 he moved into a managerial role, becoming the youngest general manager of a Bundesliga club in the history of German football.
He held that position for 30 years before being elected club president in 2009 after Franz Beckenbauer stepped down.
Bayern moved quickly to fill the vacancy left by Hoeness' departure with adidas chairman Herbert Hainer elected as his replacement.
Hainer, 59, will assume Hoeness' duties after the club accepted his earlier resignation.
Hainer received a majority vote in an emergency board meeting on Friday and assumes his new position with immediate effect.
'Uli Hoeness has always served Bayern Munich's best interests with his leadership qualities, his high personal involvement and his exceptional lifetime achievements,' Hainer said in a statement.
'He has made a considerable contribution to Bayern Munich becoming one of the most successful and attractive clubs in the world, financially and sportingly, and we will always be extremely grateful to him for this.'
SO, WHAT'S GOING ON? YOUR FULL GUIDE TO THE TRIAL...
Uli Hoeness has just been found guilty of tax evasion by a German court and sentenced to three and a half years in jail. But, unless you've been following the trial closely, you may have a few questions. Like who is he, what has he done, and why does it matter? 
Who is Uli Hoeness?
Winner of the World Cup, European Championship and three European cups as a player with Germany and Bayern Munich, Hoeness is now the President of the most successful club in the world, having led Bayern to an unprecedented treble last season. He also part owns a sausage factory and has outspoken views about European football.
Outspoken views? Like what?
Hoeness has been highly critical of the super-rich clubs, in particular Manchester City and Paris Saint Germain. In fact, he was instrumental in the creation of the new financial fair play rules.
But now he's going to prison for tax evasion? 
That's right. Despite the prosecution calling for a five and a half year sentence the ex-footballer has only been given three and a half years. But that's still a long time, considering Hoeness himself turned himself in.
Why did he do that?
The German authorities have been getting tough on tax evasion. Whether Hoeness knew they were investigating him or not, he seems to have come to the decision that any sentence would be less harsh if he cooperated. Although he said he was "aware that reporting myself doesn't change this fact," it seems clear that he hoped he would earn some sympathy from coming forward. So he didn't try to defend himself, and actually seemed to help the prosecution.
He helped the prosecution in his own case. How does that work?
There isn't a plea system in this type of case, but when the prosecution came forward with the suggestion that he had failed to pay (EURO)3.5m in taxes, he said the actual figure was more like (EURO)18m. He had hoped that he would be able to gain some form of amnesty by cooperating
But that didn't work, did it?
No. The prosecution successfully argued that he hadn't made a full enough disclosure early enough. The court then saw documents that suggested he should have paid (EURO)27.2m, and Hoeness admitted that he hadn't come forward earlier because he hoped there would be a deal between Germany and Switzerland, where he held an account, for tax evaders. 
Where does this leave Bayern?
Hoeness has been a hugely successful President since taking over from Franz Beckenbauer in 2009. The club have never been in better shape, currently 49 games unbeaten in the Bundesliga and into the quarter-finals of the Champions League. Their President's trial doesn't seem to have damaged performances so far, but it seems certain that Hoeness, permitted to remain in charge throughout the investigation, will be removed now. Whether that will lead to instability or not remains to be seen, but it can't be good news.
And what about Germany as a whole?
Hoeness isn't just a footballing figure, he's a national icon, and a regular to TV chat shows. This case, and those like it, has already caused thousands more Germans to turn themselves in, while Angela Merkel, the German Chancellor and a political ally of the Bayern President, has spoken of her 'disappointment' in Hoeness' actions.
By Jonny Singer
]]></text></news-item>