<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="308A-816A-A032-37AD"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Mission to save king of beasts March details The fight to stop hunting comes to town</title><source>The Independent on Saturday (South Africa)</source><author> DUNCAN GUY</author><text><![CDATA[In the ecology of the internet age, the elephant is paving the way towards saving the lion.
Humans will be involved, too, when they march today in 62 cities around the world, including Durban, against canned lion hunting and its by-product, lion bones, which are sent to the Asian market.
This New Age symbiosis has its roots in the dune forests south of Mozambique's capital, Maputo, where single mother Christine Jordaan says she once "lived like a hermit" on the edge of the Reserva Especial de Maputo and dreamed up a march to save the lions.
She brought the idea with her in October when she and her 2-year-old son left their idyllic life to join Jordaan's mother in Pennington on the KwaZulu-Natal South Coast.
Jordaan also brought the experience of having organised a march in Maputo against elephant poaching.
Recalling the origins of that first march, she says: "The children living in the buffer zone to the elephant park have the choice of one day becoming poachers."
She was well aware of the conflict between elephants and the community. "The elephants were angry from the war (when they were often shot at). They ate villagers' crops."
Even so, villagers managed to co-exist with them.
"A friend told me how, during the war, he walked through the elephant park for two days, to get to Kosi Bay to fetch food to bring back to his family."
Jordaan made it her mission to get the children to love elephants. She arranged for an ecologist from the reserve to speak to them.
Next thing, she was on a ferry to Maputo filled with children to lead a march, backed by supporters from all over the world with whom she had been in contact on the internet.
Later, alone, dressed in white and with a bunch of white flowers, which symbolise mourning in Chinese culture, she approached the embassy of the People's Republic of China in Mozambique.
"I explained the story of elephant poaching to a woman who came down to see me but she would not allow me in. On my way home the taxi passed a beautiful Roman Catholic Church, so I said a prayer and left the flowers there.
"I felt I had made my point at the embassy. At least I had irritated the woman."
Jordaan says people in Mozambique are afraid of speaking out.
"Everybody is too scared to protest against China."
Leaving Mozambique behind, she brought with her to South Africa her next dream - to save the lion - and started organising this weekend's march, keeping in the loop her network of elephant contacts.
Other wildlife activists and organisations have come to the party, enabling Jordaan's idea to be translated into action.
"Lion paws and lion bones are driving the lion business more than the canned hunts," says Jordaan.
"The poor lion is bred into slavery. When it's old it lives in miserable conditions, waiting on Death Row, until some rich hunter comes to shoot it in an enclosure.
"It's used to humans and probably drugged as well as lured by bait. The same bakkie that brings it food brings the hunter. What kind of person breeds a lion to be shot in a canned enclosure?"
Jordaan says the march aims to send out a warning to South Africa that people are boycotting the country as a tourism destination.
"The way South Africans are allowing our wildlife to be treated has caused the boycott. Our government sits with a choice: to pander to the wealthy few or look after the majority of people, among whom are small communities who depend on tourism."
Jordaan says her drive to promote the welfare of wildlife is a legacy from her teenage years at Pietermaritzburg Girls' High when she became depressed by animals' plight.
She says she understands that good people sit on the fence when confronted with this sort of horror. "But it eats at you."
She believes the human race behaves on Earth like a brutal dictator.
"We think other species don't have the right to be here. How can we write the lions' deaths into law? Their lives are not ours to dictate."
Jordaan hopes to get King Goodwill Zwelithini and the Zulu nation to take a stand against canned lion hunting.
Durban's first global march against canned lion hunting will start with a meeting outside the Suncoast Pirates Surf Lifesaving Club at 10am today.
At 11am marchers will move south along the promenade towards the New Beach Amphitheatre.
]]></text></news-item>