<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="310C-43BA-FC8B-7820"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>? State stops work on tolled 460 with new ideas in mind</title><source>The Virginian-Pilot(Norfolk, VA.)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[By Dave Forster
The Virginian-Pilot
A new, tolled highway between Suffolk and Petersburg that would cost $1.4 billion and destroy hundreds of acres of wetlands may not be built after all, a state official announced Friday.
The turnabout in policy follows nearly $300 million in expenditures, a change in governors and the realization in recent weeks that bridging waterways and other design maneuvers would not minimize the environmental damage as much as previously thought.
The administration of Gov. Terry McAuliffe slowed the pace of preconstruction work on the road this winter when it said expenditures would be limited to what was needed to get a permit for the project. The governor's transportation secretary, Aubrey Layne, went a step further Friday, saying officials had temporarily halted the permitting work and suspended the contract with the state's private developer, US 460 Mobility Partners.
Layne said the state now is more likely to forgo building a 55-mile highway and instead expand and improve the existing U.S. 460, potentially by adding bypasses or bridges. If that were to happen, the improved highway might not be tolled, he added.
Layne stressed that McAuliffe remains committed to improving the corridor. He cited the need to better move shipments to and from the port in Hampton Roads and to provide another hurricane evacuation route for residents. Both goals were often given by former Gov. Bob McDonnell's administration in pushing for a new highway.
"We are not backing off the project," Layne said.
An environmental group that has long criticized the state's plan to build a separate highway applauded Layne's remarks. The Southern Environmental Law Center has contended for years that a new road is unnecessary and would bring little benefit to motorists. It has railed against McDonnell's decision to spend millions on the project despite warnings from federal regulators that it might not be permittable.
"The amount of taxpayer money the McDonnell administration blew through on this boondoggle is outrageous," Trip Pollard, director of the law center's land and community program, said in an email.
The permit application by 460 Mobility Partners, a joint venture of American Infrastructure and Ferrovial Agromán, estimated that the new 55-mile highway could destroy nearly 480 acres of wetlands as it cut through swamps and over the Blackwater River. That would represent the greatest destruction of permitted wetlands in Virginia since the creation of the Clean Water Act in 1972.
Layne said a closer look at what could be done to limit the environmental damage determined that design changes might reduce the impact by 40 acres. A consultant working for the state highway department told officials that such a reduction would not be enough to secure a permit from the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, which has been warning VDOT for years that it may face regulatory hurdles.
Layne said it may take another year before the state determines a new approach for improving the corridor. If the planned route is scuttled, much of the $300 million spent on design, permitting and mobilization of assets will have been for naught, he said.
To put such a loss in perspective, an extra lane will be added to 6 miles of Interstate 64 on the Peninsula in both directions for less than half that amount.
The state signed a $1.4 billion contract with the developer in 2012 under McDonnell to design and build the road. That contract has technically only been suspended, Layne said.
Canceling it may give rise to claims against the state by the developer and complications with investors.
Most of the project was to be paid for with public money. The rest was to come from $240 million in bonds that were sold in late 2012, with that debt to be repaid from toll revenue.
Nearly $100 million from the bond sale was spent as of Dec. 31. Layne said the state is not obligated to repay the money, but there would be "reputational risks" at stake if it did not.
Typically, the state does not allow significant sums to be spent on a project until the Army Corps of Engineers has signaled that its blessing is a near certainty, Layne said. The U.S. 460 project took an expedited route through the state's office for public-private projects, however, and a contract was signed before that stage.
In late 2012, Layne said, the permitting issue with the Corps had been resolved. He was then an appointed member of the Commonwealth Transportation Board. McAuliffe picked him to be his transportation secretary after his election in November.
"I'm much more informed than I was a year ago as a CTB member," Layne said.
Dave Forster, 757-222-5005, dave.forster@pilotonline.com
When it became known that 480 acres of wetlands would be destroyed, a new plan to cut the damage by 40 acres wasn't enough to get the permit needed.
the money spent
The tolled highway would cost $1.4 billion, $300 million of which has been spent.
why the holdup?
The governor is now looking to forgo the tolled highway and instead expand and improve the existing U.S. 460.
]]></text></news-item>