<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3112-6B8F-2CB6-B9C3"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Firm suspends employees after turkey-abuse video released</title><source>Times Colonist (Victoria, British Columbia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Disturbing video showing employees of one of the world's leading turkey producers clubbing, kicking and otherwise abusing the hapless birds is evidence of a culture of cruelty and neglect at the factory farm, an animalrights group said Friday. The company in question, Hybrid Turkeys, said it had suspended four employees and called the abuse depicted in the video an isolated incident.
The video was shot at a Hybrid plant in Bright, Ont., by a member of the animal rights group, Mercy for Animals Canada.
Footage also shows workers apparently crushing the spines of birds while others are left to die from festering and bloody wounds. "This investigation graphically illustrates that the hidden price of Canadian turkey meat is horrific animal abuse," said Twyla Francois, a spokeswoman for Mercy for Animals.
In anticipation of the video's release, Hybrid said last week that it had taken immediate steps to ensure the ethical treatment of its turkeys. "Hybrid has zero tolerance for animal abuse," managing director David Libertini said in a statement.
Hybrid, of Kitchener, Ont., said it would co-operate with any investigations into the abuse and had already initiated a third party review of company policies and procedures.
Helen Wojcinski, the company's science and sustainability manager, said in an interview Friday that she was concerned by what she had seen on the video.
"Employees are not using the method of euthanasia that we want them to use," Wojcinski said, noting blunt-force trauma is an approved killing method.
While the employees remain suspended, the company is still waiting to talk to them as part of its investigation because it didn't have the full, unedited video.
"It's trying to get the whole context or perspective," Wojcinski said.
The company also said it would become the first turkey producer in North America to employ mandatory video monitoring and veterinary review of all turkey euthanasia.
Mercy for Animals said national standards across the county need to be tightened to include immediate veterinary care for sick or injured birds.
All facilities that handle farmed animals should install video monitoring and livestream the footage on the Internet, the group said.
The activists also called on the industry to forgo some profits by stopping the breeding of turkeys for rapid growth that can leave them crippled under their own weight.
]]></text></news-item>