<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="316E-D1DA-7286-4735"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Report shows nine cops used as spies in Stephen Lawrence case</title><source>Daily Star Online</source><author>Jonathan Corke</author><text><![CDATA[POLICE had nine spies linked to the justice campaign by the family of murdered Stephen Lawrence, the Daily Star Sunday can reveal.
So far publicity about the covert ­police operation has focused on two undercover officers.
One was whistleblower Peter Francis and another, with the codename N81, was highlighted in this month's report by Mark Ellison QC into the surveillance scandal.
But we have found buried in the report references to seven more undercover ­officers who did work relating to the Lawrence case from 1993 onwards.
The spies from the Metropolitan ­Police's now-disbanded Special Demonstration Squad were embedded in left and right-wing campaign groups.
After Stephen, 18, was murdered in a racist attack in Eltham, south London, in April 1993, groups from both political sides were said to be "warming up around" the Lawrence campaign "trying to progress their own agendas through association with it".
One spy, identified as N78 in the report - who had been deployed in left-wing groups prior to Stephen's murder - was in a position to "pick up intelligence about the Lawrence family campaign".
Mark Ellison QC
This was done "through indirect means and by knowing people who were close to the family".
Ellison, whose team interviewed the mole, said: "N78 provided quite a lot of reporting about the Lawrence campaign. That might well have contained personal information if N78 felt it might be of ­relevance to any part of Special Branch."
Francis, a top SDS operative, infiltrated pressure group Youth Against Racism in Europe and says he was asked by a ­detective chief inspector, N86, to report any intelligence that could smear the campaign.
Francis, known as N43, says he ­reported a ­rumour that "Mrs Lawrence might have been out drinking without Mr Lawrence on the night of Stephen's murder". The whistleblower told Ellison that "DCI N86 had been pleased to get that information and said it was exactly the sort of thing they were looking for".
Bob Lambert, who became a manager in the SDS after Francis had started his deployment, claims the spy "wasn't tasked to smear anyone".
Related articles Government spy plane uncovers 319 beds in sheds owned by landlords exploiting immigrants Spies used Facebook to help 'hack' in to millions of computers Spies at GCHQ intercept saucy webcam pics rather than hunting terrorists
Testimony by Lambert, though, reveals the SDS had at least six other spies in left and right-wing groups at the time.
According to Ellison, Lambert was last year asked by detectives investigating the SDS whether there were "any other officers within the unit at that time with direct tasking to Lawrence?"
Lambert, an ex-SDS spy who fathered a child with an unsuspecting activist ­during his time in the field, reeled off the coded identities N123, N27, N89, N101, N15 and N17.
He said N89 had infiltrated the far right and was "someone to whom ­Peter ­Francis would turn to for advice."
By 1998, Ellison discovered the SDS had a spy, N81, in the "family camp".
That year a public inquiry was under way and Ellison found reports revealing N81 fed personal information on the Lawrence family back to his bosses.
One report included comment on the state of the marriage of Stephen's ­parents Doreen and Neville Lawrence, who were divorced in 1999.
After the public inquiry, Ellison found the Met had collected intelligence on ­Duwayne Brooks, 39, the friend Stephen was with on the night he was killed.
He also discovered police bugged ­meetings with Brooks and other murder probe ­witnesses.
Since the ­report Home ­Secretary Theresa May has ordered a public inquiry into undercover policing.
]]></text></news-item>