<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3180-A7AA-8748-0032"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Thailand: Prime Minister Yingluck granted additional 15 days to defend herself of mishandling rice pledging scheme</title><source>Thai News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The National Anti-Corruption Commission (NACC) has decided to give a 15-day reprieve to caretaker prime minister Yingluck Shinawatra to present her defence over the problematic rice-pledging scheme, the Bangkok Post reports.
Ms Yingluck's lawyer Norawit Lalaeng asked the NACC on Wednesday if the premier could delay submitting her defence for the case by 45 days but the anti-graft agency said on March 13 it will not wait that long.
In a decision reached on March 13, Ms Yingluck will have 15 more days from the original date of on March 14 to present her defence.
The NACC says Ms Yingluck, in her capacity as the chairwoman of the National Rice Policy Committee, was negligent in her duties as she failed to stop the rice-pledging scheme, despite the fact that she knew it was plagued with huge losses and corruption.
Ms Yingluck failed to meet the NACC to acknowledge the matter late last month. If the NACC indicts her, she will have to leave office.
The premier on March 13 accused the anti-government People's Democratic Reform Committee (PDRC) and protesting rice farmers of obstructing the government's rice auction at the Commerce Ministry on Wednesday.
This will further delay efforts to pay farmers who participated in the rice-pledging scheme, she said.
The groups had previously blocked the Bank for Agriculture and Agricultural Co-operatives (BAAC) from borrowing from other banks to pay rice growers.
Ms Yingluck warned that any lawsuits concerning the rice-pledging scheme would also delay payments.
Many people may say that people lack confidence in this government, unlike past governments, but I believe that any government would do the same.
Why must the process be delayed in a way that troubles rice growers? Ms Yingluck said.
Niwatthamrong Bunsongphaisan, caretaker deputy premier and commerce minister, said protesters cut off electricity and water supplies to the Commerce Ministry on Wednesday, disrupting the rice auction.
He said the ministry had put about 250,000 tonnes of pledged rice worth about 3 billion baht up for auction through the Agricultural Futures Exchange of Thailand.
The auction will be organised again at the Commerce Ministry in a few weeks.
The government sold 730,000 tonnes of rice worth about 9 billion baht and needs to raise nearly 100 billion baht through borrowing or selling bonds to pay rice growers.
Mr Niwatthamrong said the government will start to pay the 20 billion baht it borrowed from its contingency budget through the BAAC from next Monday. He added that the government will not sell pledged rice at low prices.
Chavanond Intarakomalyasut, Democrat Party spokesman, said Ms Yingluck wanted to postpone her meeting with the NACC because she could not answer its questions.
He said she was ignoring the importance of the independent organisation and that Ms Yingluck intended to avoid meeting the NACC on March 14 as she had set her upcountry trip from on March 13 to Sunday in advance.
He said the rice-pledging scheme would pose another problem in the near future. He pointed to the government's 20-billion-baht spending from its contingency budget to pay for pledged rice.
He doubted the government could return the sum to the contingency budget by May 31 this year as scheduled.
Kittisak Ratanawaraha, a leader of rice growers from Phichit and other provinces in the upper North, said on March 13 his group of about 300 farmers together with PDRC guards blocked the government's rice auction at the Commerce Ministry on Wednesday because they felt the auction would not really benefit rice growers.
The caretaker government was only trying to buy time and most rice growers did not want the government to stay on and continue damaging them, he said.
We dislike this government and do not want it to even touch the rice that we grew. We will do anything we can to persuade it to leave office to pave the way for a new government and compensate for the damage done to rice growers,'' Mr Kittisak said.
He said the rice auction on Wednesday was likely to make a loss anyway because the rice was priced at only 6,000 baht per tonne. Rice growers realised the likely proceeds from the sale would not be enough to compensate them for their losses.
The government will only worsen our losses. Why does it do this when global rice prices are plunging? Why does it leave us indebted and default on us for so long? Mr Kittisak said, adding the best way out was for the government to resign.
PDRC co-leader Issara Somchai on March 13 denied his group had cut electricity to the Commerce Ministry, bringing the government's rice auction to a halt.
He said PDRC demonstrators had showed up at the ministry only to give moral support to protesting rice growers and he believed there was an attempt to put the blame on the PDRC.
Mr Issara also said the auction involved rice worth only 2 billion baht and could not pay the 130-billion-baht sum that the government owed to farmers participating in its rice-pledging scheme.
About 100 pro-government demonstrators rallied in front of the Office of the NACC on March 13 to protest against its investigation into Ms Yingluck's role in the rice-pledging scheme. They threw bags of excrement at pictures of national anti-corruption commissioner Vicha Mahakhun who investigated Ms Yingluck's role in the rice scheme.
The demonstrators also burnt a mock coffin for Mr Vicha there. They accused the NACC of trying to overthrow Ms Yingluck's government.
Two companies of police guarded the office of the NACC and its front gate was locked on March 13.
]]></text></news-item>