<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="31E5-8B95-7692-08F7"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Derby woman sues Metro-North for injuries in derailment</title><source>New Haven Register (Connecticut)</source><author>Michelle Tuccitto Sullo, New Haven Register, Conn.</author><text><![CDATA[March 15--A Derby couple is suing Metro-North Commuter Railroad Co. for $10 million because of injuries the wife suffered when the train she was riding in derailed last year.
Lina Pacelli and her husband, Francesco Pacelli, filed the lawsuit in U.S. District Court on Friday.
The lawsuit claims the company's negligence caused the eastbound train Lina Pacelli was riding in to derail May 17, 2013, in Bridgeport.
The derailed train was then struck by an oncoming westbound train, injuring dozens of people.
Attorney Steven Errante of New Haven, who is representing the couple, said Lina Pacelli suffered a compression fracture of her spine.
"This resulted in her needing surgery, and she has suffered pain and has difficulty walking," Errante said.
His client also suffers from post-traumatic stress because of the accident and is fearful of traveling on trains, according to Errante.
"I think mostly this needs to be put in context with all of the train accidents that have occurred recently," Errante said.
In this derailment and collision, "People got thrown around and a number of people got hurt -- a lot of people could have gotten killed," Errante said. "It was a traumatic and unexpected event."
Marjorie Anders, a spokeswoman for Metro-North, said Friday night she hadn't seen the lawsuit.
"We don't comment on pending litigation," she said.
The lawsuit claims some of Lina Pacelli's injuries may be permanent. It says she suffers pain when moving her lower extremities and suffers from nightmares, mental anguish and anxiety.
"She has a fear of riding on trains and is no longer able to use a train as a form of transportation," the lawsuit states.
Because of her injuries, she has incurred financial losses for medical care, including surgery, medication and physical therapy. She suffered additional financial damage from being unable to work, according to the lawsuit.
Lina Pacelli's husband, Francesco Pacelli, was not on the train. He is a plaintiff because he is claiming a loss of consortium.
The company has had a series of problems, including accidents and power outages, in the last year.
In January, the estate of a Metro-North worker who was struck and killed by a passenger train filed a lawsuit against the company for $30 million. The worker, Robert Luden, 52, of East Haven, was working as a track foreman when he was struck on May 28 in West Haven, after a student rail traffic controller mistakenly put the track where Luden was working in service.
Call Michelle Tuccitto Sullo at 203-789-5707. Have questions, feedback or ideas about our news coverage? Connect directly with the editors of the New Haven Register at AskTheRegister.com.
___ (c)2014 the New Haven Register (New Haven, Conn.) Visit the New Haven Register (New Haven, Conn.) at www.nhregister.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>