<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="330B-6E13-A706-53AA"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Football cannot and will not change - ban it</title><source>The Evening Standard (London)</source><author>Nick Curtis</author><text><![CDATA[LET'S ban football. Just shut the whole sordid business down. Greedy clubs are already colluding with greedy developers to turn their grounds into ugly, unliveable, investment-only real estate, so let's just accelerate the process and force them to flog off the lot. Tax the profits to fund apprenticeships in proper, useful trades that could lift a generation out of poverty, rather than just elevate a few working-class lads with nifty feet to brain-bending levels of vulgar wealth. Build a running track or even a cricket pitch as part of each deal, which might produce proper sporting heroes.
This week, Arsenal striker Nicklas Bendtner - a man thought to earn £50,000 a week - is alleged to have abused a taxi driver in his native Copenhagen, called the man a "fat little pig" and "unbuttoned his trousers and rubbed his body against the side of the cab". Charming, no? But such behaviour is a mere drop in the rotten ocean of football. The whole business is base, corrupt, polluted, skewed, Neanderthal. The only people worse than the players and the managers and the club owners are the so-called fans, who remain drenched in a trinity of hateful prejudice: sexism, homophobia, racism.
I don't know if Sol Campbell would, as he has been claiming in interviews to promote his recent book, have been England captain if he had been white. I do know the crowds never let him forget his colour or their imbecile assumptions about his sexuality. The abusive chants replayed to preface his Newsnight interview this week - the nasty words bleeped out, ironically, to protect the sensibilities of the very Newsnight-watching, middleclass, revisionist-apologists who insist that the "beautiful game" has changed - were every bit as ugly as the fascist salutes we are again seeing on and off the pitch. The same week, Bayern Munich fans unveiled a homophobic banner aimed at opponents Arsenal. Sexism - from rapey terrace chants, to the derision of women's football, to the salacious enjoyment of players' sexual exploits in which Wags and wannabes collude - is so ingrained it barely warrants mention.
Full disclosure: I have been to precisely three football matches in my life. The first was so long ago I can remember little apart from the all-standing terraces and a certain delight that someone actually shouted "Come on ref, where's your glasses?" At the second, last year, I was hermetically sealed from offence in Chelsea's executive lounge. The third one was the recent Arsenal match against Sunderland. The visual evidence suggested the fan base was pretty varied in terms of gender, age, ethnicity and class. But the terrace discourse betrayed the same old monoculture: "yid" chants about Tottenham, crude jokes, vicious slurs. Hooliganism may be less prevalent these days but it seems football hasn't changed, can't change, won't change. Let's ban it.
The so-called fans remain drenched in a trinity of hateful prejudice: sexism, homophobia, racism
]]></text></news-item>