<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="332D-8A6D-8358-F8DA"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>GM Crossroads</title><source>ABC Transcripts (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[PIP COURTNEY, PRESENTER: Genetically modified crops are gradually making their presence felt across Australia. Although it hasn't been a sudden embrace of the new technology, only two states; South Australia and Tasmania today maintain a ban on GM crops and trials.
The South Australian moratorium ends in 2019 and already debate is underway about what happens in five years time. It's a subject that the growers of the livestock fodder crop lucerne are watching closely.
As Leah MacLennan reports.
LEAH MACLENNAN, REPORTER: It's not often you get farmers together in such large numbers, but these lucerne seed producers are keen to share information.
WARRICK THORPE, LUCERNE AUSTRALIA: Some guys were putting on two, three hundred kilos a hectare. Some guys are putting on 50 kilos a hectare. The guy two or three hundred's not game enough to cut back and the guy at 50 doesn't want to pay more and hope for the best so we'll throw you into the mix along with the...
LEAH MACLENNAN: The farmers are looking at test sites for this year's crop, but they're also talking about the future.
One thing they want to know is whether the future will include lucerne that's genetically modified.
WARRICK THORPE: There's a lot of media and emotion attached to GM and the Australian lucerne seed industry at the moment has a moratorium on GM that you can't actually grow GM in Australia at the moment anyway with lucerne.
LEAH MACLENNAN: Lucerne farmer and Chairman of Lucerne Australia, Warrick Thorpe, wants to make sure the region is on the same page if GM lucerne becomes available here.
One of the biggest concerns is the industry's export markets, the biggest of which is Saudi Arabia, a country that does not accept GM seed.
WARRICK THORPE: A lot of the markets don't accept GM into their markets, the essential thing for us at this stage is to keep it GM free and part of the reason for having the symposium was to give a lot of our members in our industry a little bit more knowledge of what's happening overseas so they're better prepared if that decision ever comes along.
This field day is South Australia's upper south east. Almost 85 per cent of Australia's lucerne seed is grown here. At present, no varieties of GM lucerne have been approved for use in Australia.
And in South Australia both the Government and the opposition have committed to extending the moratorium on GM until 2019.
(Charlie Hilton speaking to another farmer)
CHARLIE HILTON, LUCERNE FARMER: You're happy with it in a tight season, a hot season like this?
LEAH MACLENNAN: One lucerne farmer who is quite happy for GM to stay out of this region is Charlie Hilton.
Internationally, the biggest GM development in lucerne is a herbicide tolerant variety, or as it's known under its brand name, Roundup Ready.
Charlie Hilton says a herbicide tolerant trait wouldn't benefit his crops.
CHARLIE HILTON: I think you have to really look at market access, because there's not really, for a producer of lucerne seed, there's not much of a difference, no real advantage for us in growing lucerne or GM lucerne. The roundup is not something which I'd be looking to do. I don't grow lucerne under a system, I grow lucerne with grass in the winter time and that there so I wouldn't be looking to take everything out and grow a monoculture. I don't that's a, a monoculture's the best way to grow lucerne seed.
So I would look at it but certainly, unless there's some advantages in market access or pricing or something major agronomic advantages, so at this stage I don't think there is, I probably wouldn't but, you know you've always got to look at these things and keep an open mind.
LEAH MACLENNAN: Late last year, lucerne Australia's members packed out a hall in Keith in the heart of lucerne country.
WARRICK THORPE: I'd also like to thank the nine speakers who've taken the time out to come here today. Some of them have travelled a long way, especially from the USA to be part of it.
LEAH MACLENNAN: They came to learn about GM crops from the experience of others, with speakers from as far away as the United States, to talk about how GM lucerne has or hasn't worked for them.
Chairing the symposium is former South Australian Premier, and now head of the peak body Primary Producers SA, Rob Kerin.
ROB KERIN, PRIMARY PRODUCERS SA: It's a very complex topic. Today is very much about education and trying to understand the intricacies of you know, what GM lucerne would actually mean.
LEAH MACLENNAN: Rob Kerin was State Opposition leader in 2004, when the government suspended the use of genetically modified crops.
He's hoping the moratorium will be lifted.
ROB KERIN: The debate got away from us around the 2002, 2003 mark. The science was put aside. There was a lot of rhetoric, a lot of argument. I just wish we could get back to the science, understand the technology, understand the argument of a premium for non GM versus productivity increases using it. I think the you know, I wish we could get away from the politics of it and just look at what is best for South Australia.
(Philip Geertson speaking at meeting)
PHILIP GEERTSON, LUCERNE FARMER: I'm going to mainly concentrate on the contamination issue, because that is the really big issue.
LEAH MACLENNAN: Philip Geertson is one farmer who says GM lucerne, or alfalfa as they call it in the States, hasn't worked for him.
Until 2005, he was growing lucerne seed in Idaho, Oregon and Nevada. He exported to GM free markets, until he found there had been cross contamination between his farm and a neighbours' farm.
Philip Geertson was the lead plaintiff in a case that forced the US Department of Agriculture to do an environmental impact statement on GM lucerne.
PHILIP GEERTSON: Early on, I was selling seed in New Zealand and I had spent quite a bit of time developing a market there for our seed and I had a field grown in Nevada by another grower that I was intending to ship to New Zealand. We tested that and it showed, out of the two tests, one of them showed positive for the roundup ready gene and that came from a neighbour's field that was several miles away, that he'd planted some roundup ready alfalfa. So I knew that if I shipped some of that seed to New Zealand that it might be tested there. The test might show positive and then I'd be stuck with a load of seed there that I couldn't sell and I'd have to return it to the United States. So good business practices indicated to me that I should not send it there and take a chance, so I didn't send it.
LEAH MACLENNAN: On the other side of the fence is Mark Wagoner from Washington State.
MARK WAGONER: We've had a huge decrease in seed usage. That's what's affected my farm. The seed business is really crappy, early part of the two thousands and all the way up until a couple of years ago.
LEAH MACLENNAN: Mark Wagoner uses GM herbicide tolerant lucerne and says while his yield is similar; there is significantly less seed contamination in his harvest.
He acknowledges that cross contamination can be a problem, as bees that pollinate lucerne can travel for miles.
As a former chairman of the US's National Alfalfa and Forage Alliance, he helped set up a system where selected valleys are GM free.
And have you found that's worked so far, have there been many complaints from the conventional or organic growers about that?
MARK WAGONER, LUCERNE SEED GROWER: Well we've only done it for two years now and so far it's working really good. We have a really comprehensive system where we're testing each seed lot and the last I heard, the fields that were in these APF zones were free of round up so our export markets are safe. Now that's a big deal in the United States, 38 per cent of our seed is exported, so we wanted to set up these zones so we wouldn't lose the export markets, plus protect the organic growers.
LEAH MACLENNAN: These are the first shots fired in much longer campaign.
On the ground in Keith, farmers are busy tending to their non-GM crops.
But the decisions these farmers make over the next few years will determine whether they remain GM free in the future.
CHARLIE HILTON: Certainly there's some people with very strong opinions who were at the symposium, so it's certainly a very divisive issue, that's for sure and very emotional. I think you know, for the lucerne seed industry, there's a lot of markets out there that still do not want GM lucerne there, so there's no access into those markets. So that's something Australia has to be very careful of, that going down that track, once you've got GM in you know you can't go back to non GM. So you know I think at this stage, it's probably with the moratorium being in place for the lucerne industry, it's a good thing there. Let us evaluate those markets, get down a bit further down the track of the advantages of GM in the lucerne industry. There's not a lot of advantages for the growing of GM lucerne at this stage, so you know, I think another couple of years moratorium is a good thing.
]]></text></news-item>