<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="335E-283D-3812-90FE"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Washington: Assistant Maintenance Superintendent</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The State of Washington has issued the following Job Vacancy:
Job Title: Assistant Maintenance SuperintendentOpening Date/Time: Wed. 03/12/14 12:00 AM Pacific TimeClosing Date/Time: Tue. 03/25/14 11:59 PM Pacific TimeSalary: $4,878.00 - $6,256.00 MonthlyJob Type: Agency Internal - PermanentLocation: King County – Bellevue, WashingtonDepartment: Dept. of Transportation
Description Benefits Supplemental QuestionsThe Area 5 of Northwest Region is seeking a new Maintenance & Operations Assistant Superintendent. This position will report to the Superintendent concerning staffing, project scheduling, financial resources being utilized in a responsible and economic manner. Will at times represent the department at meetings with local agencies and is a person of knowledge with regards to WSDOT agreements, policies, facilities and responsibilities. The incumbent will work with the team of four maintenance supervisors to maintain 1450 lane miles of state highway, Area 5 is the largest Maintenance Area in Washington State.This position requires the individual to be self-motivated and able to think quickly during times of emergencies, making the appropriate decisions for the safety of the public and our employees. Outstanding communication skills and the ability to build relationships with internal and external stakeholders will be critical for success. This person is expected to partner with people inside and outside the agency to make long range plans to meet the needs of WSDOT and the community. The incumbent is responsible for reviewing and submitting comments for all stages of contract plans and provisions, preservation projects such as concrete or asphalt overlays, safety improvement projects and outside agency projects, as well as utility permits for maintenance or repairs. May compose and issue general permits to external customers such as abutting property owners or contractors to perform work in the right of way. This person is the primary contact for the largest transient cleanup program in the State and is responsible for cross agency interaction with the Seattle Police Department, Washington State Patrol, Department of Corrections and homeless advocacy groups.As an Assistant Maintenance Superintendent you must be able to effectively plan and coordinate all activities while maintaining a strong customer focus by constantly meeting public, regulatory, and management needs. The successful candidate must be available 24/7 to direct the safe operation of road and bridge maintenance, winter operations, and vegetation management for the South Seattle maintenance area. This area consists of 4 maintenance Supervisors and sections. The incumbent must effectively manage emergency and crisis situations, possess valuable budget and people management skills. Our ideal candidate will possess a solid background and understanding of WSDOT’s maintenance operations program. This position provides leadership for up to 85 staff to meet targeted service levels within budget by conveying strong strategic direction and providing sound tactical guidance in all areas.Please note: The salary for this position is currently approved up to $6,256.00 monthly but is under review and may be adjusted before the recruitment concludes. Questions about salary should be directed to the recruiter listed below.
The successful candidate will:
Lead and direct delivery of routine and emergency maintenance and operational activities consistent with program goals and priorities Manage the maintenance budget while ensuring alignment between program delivery and the Maintenance Accountability Program (MAP) Determine and implement appropriate road restrictions and closures to protect roadways and traveling public Serve as program representative for area maintenance involvement in the Region’s Project Development and Construction Programs for project scoping, design, and acceptance Develop short and long range plans, highlighting maintenance goals and objectives, required staffing levels, training, and procedures Authorize and approve expenditures for existing contracts and special purchases within purchase authority Estimate, track and document disaster maintenance expenditures for reimbursement by Federal Highway Administration (FHWA) Ensure proper application of Washington’s Civil Service rules, collective bargaining agreements, and personnel policies Advocate and ensure staff work safely while in compliance with environmental laws and other state/federal regulations ·Coach/mentor staff, conduct thorough performance appraisals, initiate disciplinary/corrective action, and ensure employee compliance with training/licensing requirements Assess staffing needs and conduct interviews for hiring and promotional opportunities
At WSDOT, our top performing employees have a variety of skills and experience. An ideal candidate for this position will possess the following knowledge, skills, and abilities:
Knowledge of construction processes, rights-of-way rules/regulations and utility franchise permitting processes Extensive knowledge and practical experience of roadway maintenance practices, vegetation management and winter operations Ability to effectively manage a biennial budget and develop estimates, expenditure forecasts, and work plans Knowledge of hazardous waste management procedures, federal and state air/water quality requirements, and OSHA/WISHA laws Ability to read and comprehend engineering and construction plans as related to highway maintenance activities Experience supervising and directing staff Have a basic knowledge of both light and heavy equipment operation, service and repair. Two years leadership experience Ability to effectively communicate with diverse groups utilizing oral, written and electronic communication methods Possess valid Washington State Driver license Have ability to travel to job sites, maintenance sheds, and various agency/public meetings
It is preferred that the candidate will possess the following experience:
A minimum of two years’ experience in a position that plays a significant role in administering a program, including management of a biennial budget, budget analysis, directing and/or supporting emergency operations, and monitoring supply inventory. A minimum of two years’ of Supervisory experience in highway maintenance or the highway construction field. Experience coaching, mentoring, and training supervisory and hourly staff, with the ability to communicate a positive attitude that will connect with a broad spectrum of professionals. Experience in emergency response and winter snow and ice control operations. The ability to evaluate business management practices and to develop, promote and implement practices that will enhance the maintenance operations department. Experience developing and maintaining multi-million dollar budgets. Able to be on call for emergencies 24/7
For Further information please visit: http://agency.governmentjobs.com/washington
]]></text></news-item>