<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="33C8-8290-700B-CE77"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Bolstering air pollution agency is a work in progress</title><source>The Courier-Journal (Louisville, Kentucky)</source><author>By, Greg Fischer</author><text><![CDATA[If you grew up in Louisville like I did, you know all about our struggle to make our air clean and safe to breathe. You may remember the brown, hazy smog that hung over downtown in the 1980s, or have heard your grandparents talk about thick, black coal smoke blotting out the sun during the 1940s.
In 1945, citizens and government leaders began pushing for cleaner air by forming the Louisville Smoke Commission, which has evolved over the decades into the Louisville Metro Air Pollution Control District.
APCD is critically important to the health and wellness of our citizens and our economy. Rather than rely on Frankfort or Washington, it is the APCD - a branch of Louisville Metro Government - that monitors our air and ensures that companies are playing by the rules. The dedicated staffers are your friends, relatives and neighbors, people who breathe the same air as you and want to make it as clean as possible. And this isn't just about health, it's about quality of life - people and businesses don't want to move to a community that is known for having poor air quality.
Last year, both the state of Kentucky and the federal government conducted audits that were highly critical of the way the APCD performs the vital mission of monitoring our air. Upon learning this, I immediately ordered an investigation to address the problems raised by the audits and uncover any other issues impeding us from attaining EPA compliance. I also appointed a new APCD director and charged him with making the district more effective and accountable.
Both the state and federal audits and an external investigation called for major changes in the APCD's Air Monitoring Section. Staffers had not been properly supervised, and in some cases their jobs had evolved beyond their skill sets and education. Meanwhile, an organizational review conducted by a former top state environmental official found the APCD's upper management lacked oversight and control. The report also asked hard questions about staffing and how the district is structured. It was clear to me that major change was needed.
My team issued a national proposal asking for qualified bidders for this project and we received two responses, including one from Scott Smith, who is a consultant with Smith Management Group. Smith has decades of experience with environmental regulation, most notably as the chief of staff for Kentucky's Environmental & Public Protection Cabinet in 2004-06, which made him uniquely qualified. During that time, he managed a reorganization of the cabinet very similar to the process that we are undertaking. He has a unique perspective on the challenges and opportunities that are faced by a regulatory agency like the APCD - and that is one reason we hired him to help us devise a plan to improve.
I ordered a top-to-bottom restructuring of the APCD and we asked Mr. Smith to help give us guidance and direction. Let me emphasize this point clearly and concisely: This was my call to make, not a third party's.
Some have questioned the intentions of Mr. Smith because his firm has also done work for some of the companies that APCD regulates. When we hired Mr. Smith, we knew his firm has done work for industry as well as government - we have since learned that his firm, but not necessarily Mr. Smith himself, has represented industries as diverse as Cemex, Diageo and even The Courier-Journal. That representation, in my view, does not disqualify him. During the hiring process, we sought the advice of state, federal and environmental leaders who praised Mr. Smith's work.
During my three years as mayor, we have audited and reorganized many city departments from Public Works & Assets to Metro Animal Services. This process is neither easy nor painless. With APCD, some employees may lose their jobs. Others may find themselves in new positions with changed responsibilities and increased expectations. But it is clear that the APCD was overdue for deep examination of its staff and its practices.
This reorganization is a work in progress. But here is what will not change:
We will continue to monitor the air to ensure that it meets the EPA's tough national standards.
We will continue to issue and enforce air pollution permits that meet all federal, state and local rules and regulations.
We will continue to enforce the Strategic Toxic Air Reduction (STAR) program, which aims to reduce toxic emissions and goes beyond EPA standards.
We will continue to inspect facilities to ensure they are following their permits.
We will continue to investigate air pollution, odor and dust violations and issue citations if needed.
We will continue to work with government agencies, universities, environmental advocates and civic groups to tackle problems like climate change and urban heat.
We will continue to promote clean, healthy air via the Kentuckiana Air Education outreach program.
It is healthy for citizens - and the media - to question what has happened at the Air Pollution Control District. My team questioned it, too - and we came to the obvious conclusion that significant change was needed at APCD to make it the strong organization that our city deserves.
Greg Fischer is the mayor of Louisville.
]]></text></news-item>