<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3414-9A5A-7D6B-E9B0"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Digital Futures, Why Bother?</title><source>Concurring Opinions</source><author>Deven Desai</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 17, 2014 (Concurring Opinions:http://www.concurringopinions.com Delivered by Newstex) I enjoy thinking about the implications of technology but some recent 'Theses about the digital future' at Pew[1] are not satisfying as compared to a recent article by Neil Gershenfeld and JP Vasseur called 'As Objects Go Online[2].' Pew does some excellent work, but this one is rather odd. The predictions are vapid, and some contradict each other. In contrast, the Gershenfeld and Vasseur piece focuses on one idea, The Internet of Things, and offers much more. My work on 3D printing with Gerard[3] was partly inspired by the digitization of things. The idea there is about digital mapping and reproducing tangible goods. Gershenfeld and Vasseur are looking at how we are already networking objects:
Thanks to advances in circuits and software, it is now possible to make a Web server that fits on (or in) a fingertip for $1. When embedded in everyday objects, these small computers can send and receive information via the Internet so that a coffeemaker can turn on when a person gets out of bed and turn off when a cup is loaded into a dishwasher, a stoplight can communicate with roads to route cars around traffic, a building can operate more efficiently by knowing where people are and what they're doing, and even the health of the whole planet can be monitored in real time by aggregating the data from all such devices. The connection between Gershenfeld (also a leader in 3D printing) and my ideas is the drive to show that many battles will be about 'command-and-control technology [versus] distributed solutions.' Gershenfled and Vasseur believe open, distributed ideas will win. I am hope they do. I am not as certain that such outcomes are necessarily where we are headed. That is why even with its somewhat thin offering the Pew Report may help. The collection of obvious observations may help draw attention to pressing issues of today, not Digital Life in 2025, as Pew has dressed up its report. The descriptions are decent but not prescient. They are below in case you want to see them here. THe key take away, I think, is that anyone who thinks the implications of digitization have been addressed, understood, and solved by our experiences with copyright and privacy to date is mistaken. This world and the one coming are quite different. I must admit that I can't pinpoint exactly how and why it is different. That is my goal over the next several years. But I can say don't expect the analogies, frameworks, and laws of old to make much sense as we move forward. That does not mean all is lost. Rather it means we get to shape what happens next, just as folks did at the dawn of Western capitalism and individualism in England and at the Industrial Revolution. Should be fun and frightening; so buckle in.The 15 Pew Theses: 1) Information sharing over the Internet will be so effortlessly interwoven into daily life that it will become invisible, flowing like electricity, often through machine intermediaries. 2) The spread of the Internet will enhance global connectivity that fosters more planetary relationships and less ignorance. 3) The Internet of Things, artificial intelligence, and big data will make people more aware of their world and their own behavior 4) Augmented reality and wearable devices will be implemented to monitor and give quick feedback on daily life, especially tied to personal health. 5) Political awareness and action will be facilitated and more peaceful change and public uprisings like the Arab Spring will emerge. 6) The spread of the 'Ubernet' will diminish the meaning of borders, and new 'nations' of those with shared interests may emerge and exist beyond the capacity of current nation-states to control. 7) The Internet will become 'the Internets' as access, systems, and principles are renegotiated 8) An Internet-enabled revolution in education will spread more opportunities, with less money spent on real estate and teachers. 9) Dangerous divides between haves and have-nots may expand, resulting in resentment and possible violence. 10) Abuses and abusers will 'evolve and scale.' Human nature isn't changing; there's laziness, bullying, stalking, stupidity, pornography, dirty tricks, crime, and those who practice them have new capacity to make life miserable for others11) Pressured by these changes, governments and corporations will try to assert power—and at times succeed—as they invoke security and cultural norms. 12) People will continue—sometimes grudgingly—to make tradeoffs favoring convenience and perceived immediate gains over privacy; and privacy will be something only the upscale will enjoy. 13) Humans and their current organizations may not respond quickly enough to challenges presented by complex networks. 14) Most people are not yet noticing the profound changes today's communications networks are already bringing about; these networks will be even more disruptive in the future. 15) Foresight and accurate predictions can make a difference; 'The best way to predict the future is to invent it.' [1]: http://www.pewinternet.org/2014/03/11/15-theses-about-the-digital-future/ [2]: http://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/140745/neil-gershenfeld-and-jp-vasseur/as-objects-go-online [3]: http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2338067

]]></text></news-item>