<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="34AE-FBBD-5300-658E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Right-wing NGO reports on Israelis taking part in Israeli Apartheid Week events</title><source>Jpost.com (The Jerusalem Post online edition)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Head of policy at the organization Im Tirzu says it wanted to show how Israelis were giving the BDS movement legitimization.

A new report by the Zionist organization Im Tirtzu works to expose Israelis playing central roles in Israeli Apartheid Week events taking place on campuses around the world. The paper, titled "Delegitimization Awareness Month: Information on Israelis participating in Israeli Apartheid Week events, was published this month.
Israeli Apartheid Week, according to its website, apartheidweek.org, states that it "is an international series of events that seeks to raise awareness about Israel's apartheid policies towards the Palestinians and to build support for the growing Boycott, Divestment, and Sanctions (BDS) campaign." Alon Schvartzer, the head of policy at Im Tirtzu, told The Jerusalem Post in an interview, "We wanted to show that Israeli organizations and individuals are justifying the BDS movement, giving it legitimization, even if they are not on the front lines." "They don't want to be on the front lines," he said adding that the organizations abroad that are pushing the movement use material from Israelis. "They have freedom of speech but it is important for Israelis to know what they are doing." University professors and filmmakers should not be receiving state funds if they are involved with groups that are promoting BDS against Israel, said Schvartzer. For example, the report names the Coalition of Women for Peace (CWP), an organization that publicized Israeli Apartheid Week on its Facebook page. The organization describes itself on its website as a "feminist organization against the occupation of Palestine and for a just peace." Founded in 2000 during the second intifada, CWP gives "its unwavering support of the right of return of Palestinian refugees" and works with other "human rights activists and organizations" to launch "public campaigns, internet campaigning, and legal counseling for activists." The Jerusalem Post contacted the Coalition of Women for Peace and was told that the organization prefers not to respond to the report. Eran Efrati, who works at the organizations Anarchists Against the Wall and Boycott from Within, lectures during Israeli Apartheid Week under the title, "The Soldier and the Refusenik". lan Pappé, an Israeli historian and professor at the University of Exeter, and the author of the books, The Ethnic Cleansing of Palestine and The Struggle for Academic Freedom in Israel, supported the British academic boycott of Israel and is now "at the forefront of academics leading the BDS campaign," said the report.
He wrote a chapter titled, "The Boycott Will Work: An Israeli Perspective," published in 2012 in the book, The Case for Sanctions Against Israel. He was on the program to speak at Israeli Apartheid Week 2014 at the University of Oxford in England. Another Israeli, Guy Davidi, director of the film "Five Broken Cameras," lectures and presents his film during Israeli Apartheid Week at a number of locations, including Paris, France and the University of Alberta in Canada. All rights reserved © The Jerusalem Post 1995 - 2014 Provided by Syndigate.info, an Albawaba.com company
]]></text></news-item>