<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3527-F4B4-6846-6019"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Human rights based politics</title><source>Ground Report</source><author>Ginette Blansjaar</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 16, 2014 (Ground Report:http://www.groundreport.com/ Delivered by Newstex) http://groundreport.com/report/?Article=Human%20rights%20based%20politicsArticle-ID=5065405 Human rights based politicsArticle Views22 GroundReport | Author: Ginette Blansjaar[1] Filed Under: News[2], Politics[3] | Posted: 03/16/2014 at 1:47PM Comments[4] | Region: DenmarkTo act in the best interest of the people, human rights - and the just social principles that follow self-evidently from those - as well as intelligent economics should be the basis for governing a country.
Yet what we see in many places in the world, is either a chosen leader with too much power to act without consulting representatives of the different groups in the…ir society, or political parties still based on outdated ideologies. Then it might easily happen, politicians are so preoccupied with ideological debates, that they do not even realize some things are undebatable, because they are fundamental rights. This way, they come (close) to crimes against their citizens without even noticing it; or without acknowledging it. It undermines a state, as it destroys peoples trust in justice. The first citizen can get into trouble by some anonymous mischief maker, accusing them falsely, or faces fines and punishment for the slightest breaking of rules, while authorities are almost above the law, can make mistake after mistake, introduce policies that cost human lifes, and only after long-lasting law procedures may incidentally be corrected. Unfortunately, such situations exist even in the worlds most prosperous countries. So we need another approach. Democracy means that different parties with different interests will find the best solutions to a country's problems through dialogue. Those interests have nothing to do with ideology, but with the position of each party in society. We do not need political parties, based on 'ideology'. Those debates cost millions, and resulting policies are ineffective and too often proven to violate human rights. We need parties like for example a party that stands for the protection of the environment, a farmers party, an employers party, an employees party, a free enterprise party, a health care party, an interfaith party, a children's party, a science party, groups like that. Then a human rights based approach, together with unbiased expertise of professional economists and lawyers, will work to find balanced and fair policies to govern the state. Filed Under:News[5], Politics[6] http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/This is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License[7].Attribution (Very Relaxed) Loading...[8] [1]: http://groundreport.com/profile/23763 [2]: http://groundreport.com/category/news-world/ [3]: http://groundreport.com/category/news-world/politics/ [4]: http://groundreport.com/human-rights-based-politics/#disqus_thread [5]: http://groundreport.com/category/news-world/ [6]: http://groundreport.com/category/news-world/politics/ [7]: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/ [8]: http://mgid.com/

]]></text></news-item>