<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="35DD-927A-5357-45B9"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>OPINION: Worker misclassification on government radar</title><source>Business First of Buffalo</source><author>Vincent Miranda, Guest Columnist</author><text><![CDATA[Worker misclassification has been a hot-button topic as various state and federal government agencies and legislative bodies have taken action to combat the employer practice of not reporting an employee or incorrectly labeling an employee as an independent contractor. President Obama's 2015 fiscal year budget reveals that worker misclassification remains a top priority for his administration and the U.S. Department of Labor (DOL). The President's budget provides the DOL with $11.8 billion in discretionary funding in addition to dedicated mandatory funds. The budget seeks nearly $14 million to combat the misclassification of workers through grants for state governments and additional investigators at the Wage and Hour Division of the DOL. Notably, the budget also provides that the Wage and Hour Division will receive an increase of more than $41 million to ensure that employees receive, among other things, proper wages and overtime pay.
These initiatives dovetail with the Obama administration's goals of helping grow and strengthen the middle class. To help accomplish this objective, the White House formed the Middle Class Task Force, and the task force's major initiative seeks to raise the living standards of middle-class, working families. In 2011, the DOL launched a Misclassification Initiative as part of the task force. The initiative has resulted in the collection of more than $18 million in back wages for approximately 19,000 misclassified workers. On Nov. 18, 2013, New York joined the initiative when the New York State Department of Labor and the Labor Bureau of the New York State Office of the Attorney General executed separate agreements with the U.S. DOL Wage and Hour Division.
New York is not sitting by passively either. In addition to joining the Misclassification Initiative, on Jan. 10, 2014, Gov. Cuomo signed the New York State Commercial Goods Transportation Industry Fair Play Act, which is similar to a law that went into effect in 2010 that targeted worker misclassification in the building and construction industry. This new law amends the New York Labor Law to create a rebuttable presumption that any individual performing commercial goods transportation services for a commercial goods transportation contractor is an employee and not an independent contractor. New York's Joint Enforcement Task Force on Employee Misclassification issued its annual report on Feb. 1 of this year, and its figures highlight the broad actions being taken by our state government.
he New York task force identified approximately 24,000 instances of employee misclassification and discovered approximately $333.4 million in unreported wages in 2013. These numbers do not even include the New York DOL's misclassification investigation results from 2013.
New York is not alone in its efforts. Fourteen other states have partnered with the U.S. DOL in its Misclassification Initiative. Notable legislative efforts include California's "Job Killer Act," which became effective Jan. 1, 2012. This law increased penalties for worker misclassification and contains a unique "scarlet letter" type of penalty - the requirement in some circumstances for an employer to have to post on its website that it committed a serious violation of the law.
What does this all mean for employers?
Employers can no longer afford to casually issue 1099s and hope an investigator does not come knocking. Under New York's Wage Theft Prevention Act that became effective in April 2011, employers can face stiff penalties, including liquidated damages of 100 percent for underpayment of wages, when misclassified workers are found to be owed wages.
A proactive approach by employers can help avoid the financial penalties, legal fees and possible negative publicity that can arise from a worker misclassification investigation or a misclassification lawsuit. Employers should first conduct a self-audit of their labor pool. In reviewing the nature of the relationship between employer and worker, employers must be aware that no single factor or agreement defining an individual as an independent contractor will govern. While courts and government agencies will use different tests in making a determination about worker classification, it is important to remember that independent contractors will generally be free from supervision, direction and control in the performance of their duties. Conversely, indicia of an employee-employer relationship include setting the rate of pay and hours of work, requiring attendance at meetings, evaluating job performance and having the right to hire and fire.
The regulatory and legislative activity in this area has increased over the past few years in an employee-friendly direction, and there is no sign of it stopping. An employer's best defense is to act early and to seek advice from employment counsel in navigating the fact-intensive inquiry of worker classification. Taking such pre-emptive measures now will help mitigate higher costs later.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Business First of Buffalo for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>