<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="35FB-A2E5-24C8-CD39"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>The last walkout; Bob Crow</title><source>The Economist</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Britain's most famous and militant trade unionist dies
BRITISH public figures these days tend to be bland, inoffensive types. Politicians twist their way around questions; businessmen speak fluent management jargon. Even most union leaders wear suits and ties and speak softly. Bob Crow, the general secretary of the Railway, Maritime and Transport workers' union (RMT), who died of a heart attack on March 11th, aged just 52, was a big exception. He represented a strand of the left that has otherwise all but disappeared.
With his thick neck, tracksuits and bull terrier, Mr Crow looked like a figure from a London gangster film. But he also brought to mind trade unionists of old: London's dockers (his father was one) or perhaps Harry Pollitt, the 1930s secretary general of the Communist Party of Great Britain. The terrier was named Castro, after Fidel; in his office, he kept a bust of Lenin. His home, in Woodford, on the suburban border between London and Essex, was a council house. Despite his high salary, Mr Crow never moved; nor did he take up Margaret Thatcher's offer to let him buy his house from the state.
His approach to his job was similarly anachronistic. British trade unions these days tend not to strike much—working days lost have fallen from an average of 13m per year in the 1970s to less than 500,000 now. Under Mr Crow, the RMT stood out, forsaking protests for traditional industrial activism. Under his tutelage, the RMT cut its ties with the Labour Party in 2004. Instead it was to be, in his own words, "a militant trade union", with one simple aim: to win for its members a standard of living "that enables them to share in the fine wines and fine times that the likes of David Cameron and his old Etonian mates take for granted."
Nowhere was this more visible than on the London Underground, where in 2011 RMT-affiliated drivers won a deal entitling them to £52,000 ($86,000) per year in basic pay—twice the median wage in Britain. And yet the strike threats kept coming. In February, when staff walked out over proposals to close ticket offices, London was left immobile for two days. Such was Mr Crow's ability to cause chaos and wind up commuters that his small union—just 80,000 of Britain's 7m union members—was almost single-handedly responsible for inspiring a Conservative campaign for tougher strike laws. In turn, he was rewarded, increasing his membership when most unions' ranks were thinning.
Yet while the Tube strikes reminded Britain of an earlier, more strife-filled age, Mr Crow was not all that he appeared. Unlike his mentor Arthur Scargill, who led the failed miners' strike in 1984, he did not pick fights he could not win: many of his "victories" were in reality careful compromises. For all that he denounced privatisation, it was the source of much of the RMT's success: splintered franchises could not hold down wages as easily as a state monopoly. Even his tough proletarian persona broke down under inspection: he was at ease schmoozing in clubby London restaurants and his brother is a stockbroker.
What will happen to his union now? The RMT is sure to remain powerful—as London's economic might grows, the chaos a union can cause on its transport network grows too. Politicians and transport chiefs, who greeted their old opponent's death with genuine sadness, may yet miss him: his replacement could prove more militant, says Christian Wolmar, an expert on Britain's railways. Yet without Mr Crow's voice, Britain's other unions may accelerate their transformation into campaigning and mutual-aid organisations.
That, however, would be no bad thing. Few workers are in the position that RMT members are. Becoming a train driver means hurdling remarkable barriers to entry, which helps keep wages high. And transport, unlike car manufacturing or coal mining, cannot be exported overseas. But such industries are becoming rarer—even train drivers may soon lose out to computers. Last month Mr Crow told an interviewer that though he was a dinosaur, "they was around for a long while". True enough. But the ones that survived evolved into gentler animals.
]]></text></news-item>