<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="36AA-50F0-0AC7-A185"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Coal ash landfill worries residents</title><source>The Tennessean (Nashville, Tennessee)</source><author>By, Duane W. Gang</author><text><![CDATA[Dressed in yellow T-shirts emblazoned with the words "Beyond Coal," more than a dozen Sierra Club activists and other area residents voiced their concerns Thursday that Tennessee lacks the proper oversight for coal ash.
The Tennessee Valley Authority plans a new 54-acre landfill to store coal ash from its Gallatin Fossil Plant, and the activists turned out for a public hearing on the proposal at the Sumner County Administrative Building.
Coal ash is the waste from burning coal to produce electricity, and it contains arsenic, selenium, mercury and other pollutants - all harmful to people and wildlife when found in high concentrations.
TVA needs a permit for the landfill from the Tennessee Department of Environment and Conservation, which has granted tentative approval. The state held Thursday's public hearing to gather input from area residents.
Chris Ann Lunghino with the Sierra Club's Beyond Coal campaign said if coal ash is not stored properly it can lead to "dangerous contamination of our drinking water."
"We need stronger standards for coal ash disposal," she said. "That is why we arehere tonight."
The $30 million landfill is part of TVA's work to install more than $1 billion in new air pollution-control equipment at the site, the closest coal-fired power plant to Nashville.
But removing all those pollutants from the air translates into waste that must be stored in a landfill.
The new landfill will hold what is called dry coal ash. Environmental groups, including the Sierra Club, say that is far safer than wet storage. But they still raise concerns because of the landfill's proximity to the Cumberland River.
Pat Flood, TDEC's director of solid waste management, said the state's landfill requirements have safeguards in place. The state is requiring multiple liners and a collection system so any runoff does not make its way into groundwater supplies or the river, as well as monitoring, he said.
TVA officials said the landfill is part of the agency's plans to convert all of the power plants it plans to continue operating from wet- to dry-ash storage.
In 2008, a dike at a wet-ash storage pond failed at TVA's Kingston Fossil Plant, spilling 5.4 million cubic yards of coal ash into the Emory and Clinch rivers.
Existing wet storage ponds at Gallatin will eventually be closed, dried and capped, according to TVA.
Speakers at the public hearing included Sumner County commissioners and Gallatin Mayor Jo Ann Graves.
"I am an avid boater. We boat. We fish. We swim in that river," Graves said, expressing her support for the environment. "But the TVA plant represents jobs, and it represents economic development to this area."
Other residents asked TDEC to simply do its job.
Michelle Haynes, 62, can see the power plant's smokestacks from her Lock 4 Road home.
"TDEC, please monitor what is going on," she said. "That is the key to what is keeping our environment the way it should be."
Reach Duane W. Gang at 615-726-5982 or on Twitter @duanegang.
Landfill facts
Size
A 54-acre landfill on the site of TVA's Gallatin Fossil Plant.
Cost
The $30 million landfill is part of TVA's ongoing $1 billion project to install new air pollution control equipment at the coal-fired power plant.
Coal ash
The material is the waste from burning coal to produce electricity . It contains arsenic, selenium, mercury and other pollutants.
At issue
Environmentalists are concerned that pollution could leak into the nearby Cumberland River and groundwater supplies.
]]></text></news-item>