<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="36DA-B2F9-5E12-4138"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Today in History - March 28; Today in History - March 28</title><source>Canadian Press</source><author>The Canadian Press</author><text><![CDATA[Today in History for March 28:
On this date:
In 1380, gunpowder was first used in Europe in a battle between the Genoese and the Venetians.
In 1515, Spanish mystic St. Teresa of Avila, founder of a reformed Carmelite order, was born. Her mysticism is evident in her "Life Written By Herself" (autobiography), "Way of Perfection," "Book of Foundations," and "Interior Castle."
In 1797, Nathaniel Briggs of New Hampshire patented a washing machine. Three months later he placed an ad in a local newspaper that marketed the machine to the "fair sex," saying it was about time inventors took their needs into consideration. Briggs believed the hardest part of housework was laundry. He said women shouldn't continue washing clothes by hand just because their mothers had.
In 1843, John A. Macdonald, Canada's first prime minister, was elected as an alderman in Kingston, Ont.
In 1918, conscription riots broke out in Quebec.
In 1928, Ottawa's first automatic street light system began operation.
In 1930, the names of the Turkish cities of Constantinople and Angora were changed to Istanbul and Ankara.
In 1935, the Canadian Radio Commission, a forerunner of the CRTC, prohibited "sales talks or spot advertising" on Sundays.
In 1939, the Spanish Civil War ended as Madrid fell to the right-wing forces of Francisco Franco.
In 1941, novelist and critic Virginia Woolf committed suicide by drowning herself in the River Ouse.
In 1944, humourist Stephen Leacock died in Toronto at age 74. A pioneer Canadian political economist, he was also a historian of early Canada and the British Empire. But Leacock is best remembered for his humorous books, including "Sunshine Sketches of a Little Town" and "Arcadian Adventures with the Idle Rich."
In 1959, China ordered the dissolution of the Dalai Lama's government in Tibet.
In 1960, the Ontario government announced a plan to build a bilingual university at Sudbury. It is now Laurentian University.
In 1969, former U.S. president, and Second World War Allied commander, Dwight Eisenhower, died at 78.
In 1978, Heritage Canada was incorporated as a national trust to promote the preservation of scenic and historic sites.
In 1979, the worst nuclear accident in U.S. history occurred at the Three Mile Island generating plant near Harrisburg, Pa. The plant began emitting radiation when problems with its cooling system exposed part of the core. The accident, which forced thousands of people from their homes, was brought under control within two days.
In 1985, artist Marc Chagall died at age 97.
In 1987, Maria von Trapp, whose 1938 escape from Nazi-occupied Austria with her husband and children inspired "The Sound of Music," died in Stowe, Vt., at age 82.
In 1990, British customs officials announced they had foiled an attempt to supply Iraq with 40 U.S.-made devices for triggering nuclear weapons.
In 1999, Venus Williams beat kid sister Serena 6-1, 4-6, 6-4 to win the Lipton Championships in the first all-sister women's final since Maud Watson beat her older sister, Lilian, in the Wimbledon final in 1884.
In 2003, at least 60 civilians, including 15 children, were killed when U.S. bombs fell on a market in a poor neighbourhood of Baghdad.
In 2005, Canadian filmmaker Robin Spry, 65, best known for his documentary on the "October Crisis," was killed in a car accident.
In 2005, an 8.7-magnitude earthquake hit Indonesia's Sumatra island, killing nearly 500 people on the island of Nias. The Indian Ocean epicentre of the quake was just about 160 kms southeast of the upheaval three months earlier which triggered a tsunami that left nearly 300,000 people dead or missing across Asia.
In 2008, B.C. Solicitor General John Les stepped down after it was revealed a special prosecutor had been looking into allegations he may have improperly benefited from a land deal.
In 2009, Canadians Barbara Underhill, Paul Martini and Brian Orser were inducted into the World Figure Skating Hall of Fame. Underhill and Martini captured gold for Canada in pairs in 1984 and Orser was the 1987 world champion.
In 2010, 153 miners were trapped underground after water gushed into the Wangjialing coal mine in Shanxi province of China. The workers accidentally broke into a network of old, water-filled shafts. On April 5, 115 miners were pulled out alive, but the other 38 perished and their bodies were recovered days later.
In 2011, a fatality inquiry into the deaths of four Alberta Mounties near Mayerthorpe in March 2005 found the RCMP acted appropriately in dealing with gunman James Roszko, given the information they had at the time. Judge Daniel Pahl ruled that despite Roszko's long criminal history, there was nothing to suggest he would engage in a premeditated attack against the Mounties at his farm in March, 2005. Pahl recommended a "threat assessment co-ordinator'' in each detachment and that the RCMP consider national policy guidelines to secure potential crime scenes.
In 2012, Leonard Braithwaite, the first black member of Ontario's legislature, died at age 88. He represented the Toronto area Etobicoke riding from 1963-75 as a Liberal. He spoke out against racial segregation in Ontario schools, and called for the admission of female pages in the legislature. He received the Order of Canada in 1997 and Order of Ontario in 2005.
----
(The Canadian Press)
]]></text></news-item>