<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3758-F413-B47E-1018"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Mainstreet: Arlington Place Health Campus Opens</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Indianapolis, IN - The Arlington Place Health Campus, located on the near eastside near Community East Hospital, is celebrating its grand opening with a public open house on Sunday, March 16 from 1-3 pm.
The brand-new Arlington Place Health Campus (1635 N. Arlington Ave) is an innovative approach to the design and delivery of health care services for a new generation. The 63,935 square-foot center offers 30 service-rich assisted living apartments and 70 private and companion suites for those in need of top-of-the-line rehabilitative care, assisted living or long-term care. Ninety percent of the rooms are single-bed rooms with private bathrooms. The handsomely-appointed design and hotel-like environment will be comfortable and engaging with concierge-style delivery of services and intergenerational activities.
Learn more about the opening and what Arlington Place Health Campus has to offer - Arlington Place Opening.
click http://www.mainstreetcap.net/arlington-place-health-campus-opens/
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
14 March 2014: Mainstreet CEO Appears on Bloomberg
Carmel, IN - Mainstreet CEO, Zeke Turner, appeared on Bloomberg's "In the Loop with Betty Liu". This television program provides the fastest and most comprehensive coverage of the headlines and major events set to shape the business day ahead. Turner appeared during the 8:00 a.m.
click http://www.mainstreetcap.net/mainstreet-ceo-appears-on-bloomberg/
20 February 2014: Mainstreet Named One of The Best Places to Work in Indiana 2014
Mainstreet was, once again, named one of the Best Places to Work in Indiana! Winners were determined through employer reports and employee surveys. All companies that participated in the 2014 Best Places to Work program received and in-depth evaluation identifying strengths and weaknesses according to their employees. The Indiana Chamber noted that this year saw the most number of applicants ever for this program which makes this win for Mainstreet even more substantial.
click http://www.mainstreetcap.net/mainstreet-named-one-of-the-best-places-to-work-in-indiana-2014/
11 February 2014: Mainstreet's Jobs Announcement Raises National Attention
Mainstreet's jobs announcement on February 7, 2014 at the 16th and Arlington property garnered outstanding local coverage and also raised national attention, being picked up by Yahoo Finance. Click the hyperlink to see their coverage. Source: Company Website
click http://www.mainstreetcap.net/mainstreets-jobs-announcements-raises-national-attention/
10 February 2014: Mainstreet: HHS wants civil monetary penalty rules changed
Civil monetary penalties for providers will be revised if two proposed rules from the Department of Health and Human Services Office of the Inspector General are approved. The rule changes, which were sent to the Office of Management and Budget by the OIG, are needed in order to implement Affordable Care Act statutes.
click http://www.mcknights.com/hhs-wants-civil-monetary-penalty-rules-changed/article/333245/
10 February 2014: Mainstreet: Former SNF worker charged with reckless homicide in resident death
A former skilled nursing facility employee in Indiana is facing charges including reckless homicide in the death of a resident, according to local reports. Kathy J. Hess worked at Woodland Hills Care Center in Lawrenceburg and was fired shortly after the December death of 77-year-old resident Dionne Scalf. The investigation by the Dearborn County Special Crimes Unit began when a witness said she saw Hess abusing the resident in a manner consistent with what a pathologist later determined was a broken vertebra. Hess was charged with battery resulting in the death of an endangered adult, neglect of a dependent resulting in serious bodily injury, and reckless homicide last week. Deputy County prosecutor Aaron Negangard noted Scalf had been scheduled to be cremated. "The investigators did an exceptional job investigating this case.
click http://www.mcknights.com/former-snf-worker-charged-with-reckless-homicide-in-resident-death/article/333246/
]]></text></news-item>