<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3780-1A01-64AD-9D83"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Water district board decides not to fire general manager amid controversy</title><source>Whittier Daily News (California)</source><author>Steve Scauzillo</author><text><![CDATA[COMMERCE >> In a raucous public meeting, the Central Basin Municipal Water District board censured fellow board member Art Chacon on Thursday for lying to authorities and driving without a license but gave its general manager a reprieve.
He still has a job, said attorney Rick Olivarez, referring to General Manager Tony Perez.
The board agenda included replacing Perez and considering an interim general manager. But after a two-hour closed session, Olivarez said the board did not take action on that item.
Perez found himself in the hot seat days after this news organization revealed he had approved mileage reimbursements and car allowance payments to Chacon, who hasn t had a driver s license since 2003.
The general manager also signed off on a $16,000 payment to a woman injured in a 2010 car accident that was caused by Chacon. Additionally, Perez agreed that Chacon should receive $63,000 in workers compensation payments for injuries he allegedly suffered in the accident.
The purpose of that (agenda item) was to get answers from the general manager, said board member Leticia Vasquez. That judgment was about a personal auto accident that had nothing to do with district business. In fact, that is a gift of public funds, she said during an interview after the meeting.
Perez, 56, who has been on the job for about 11 months, seemed stunned. He said he was not sure he still had a job, but Olivarez reassured him he did.
Vasquez indicated that Perez may still have some explaining to do in the coming weeks. She and other board members say they never approved of the payment to Chacon and that Perez acted without a board vote.
We are still looking at it. We are not satisfied with the responses he gave us, Vasquez said.
On the issue of the $597 a month car allowance issued to Chacon, Vasquez said she tried to get other board members to require Chacon to pay back the money and stop taking the car allowance. She was unsuccessful, she said.
Chacon announced he has a driver s license but refused to show it to district staff. He also said that during the accident in 2010 that involved six cars and injured five people he was driving on district time.
Chacon told the California Highway Patrol he was on his way home from work when the crash occurred. He later told an insurance investigator he had been asked to inspect road conditions near a Central Basin construction site.
However, an insurance company attorney noted that Chacon was neither asked or directed to go to the construction site by anyone employed by or associated with the Central Basin Municipal Water District.
Chacon receives no pay to investigate construction sites, nor is he qualified, the attorney, Robert Gokoo, also noted.
The board majority, by a 3-2 vote, approved a motion for censure because he broke his oath of office by lying to police about his identity after he was arrested on suspicion of driving under the influence. And he drove without a license. Chacon received six additional suspensions on the expired license from 2011-2013 for offenses such as drunken driving and failing to provide proof of insurance, according to the DMV. I know this is politics, Chacon said.
The censure is more symbolic than practical. Chacon can still attend board meetings and vote. Board member Robert Apodaca, who voted for the censure, said there s not much else the board can do to Chacon.
The only way you can get him out is if you recall him, he said after the meeting.
Vasquez said the fate of Chacon will be in the hands of the voters. He is up for re-election in November.
Meanwhile, Perez, the fourth general manager of the embattled district in the past two years, will continue in his position, having survived a closed session performance evaluation.
When he came to the district, he was director of operations and business development for DR Consultants. He spent most of his career, more than 22 years, as an engineer with Metropolitan Water District of Southern California.
In April 2013, Perez was awarded a five-year contract by the board and is earning an annual base salary of $195,000.
Staff writers Mike Sprague and Jason Henry contributed to this article.
]]></text></news-item>