<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3B07-D28F-7473-B1E1"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>MPs condemn 'veil of secrecy' over £100bn of private contracts</title><source>The Independent (London)</source><author>NIGEL MORRIS DEPUTY POLITICAL EDITOR</author><text><![CDATA[The Government is condemned by MPs of all parties today for hiding behind a "veil of secrecy" over the award of contracts worth nearly £100bn a year to huge private companies.
Problems are particularly acute at the Department for Work and Pensions (DWP), which is on the "verge of meltdown" over the private running of welfare reforms and employment programmes, they say.
In a scathing verdict on the Coalition's drive to contract out public services, the Commons Public Accounts Committee (PAC) accused ministers of trying to cover up mistakes by refusing to divulge details of contracts.
It said the Government was failing to get best value for money and lacked the expertise to ensure "privately owned public monopolies" provided quality services.
The committee's chair, Margaret Hodge, said: "If it's not sorted out it will become the biggest ad for renationalising public services."
Protesting that contracts were often "shrouded in a veil of secrecy", she claimed: "We are in danger of creating a shadow state that is neither transparent nor accountable to Parliament or the public."
The committee reached its conclusions after a series of scandals involving corporate giants. These included the disclosure that G4S and Serco had charged the Ministry of Justice for years to fit electronic tags to non-existent offenders and the failure by G4S to supply enough security guards for the 2012 London Olympics.
The committee demanded that contracts with private companies are put into the public arena. It said four major firms it questioned - Atos, Capita, G4S and Serco -were prepared to agree to the move, adding that it appears that "the main barriers to greater transparency lie within Government itself".
Ms Hodge said: "An absence of real competition has led to the evolution of privately-owned public monopolies which have become too big to fail. Some public-service markets, such as for private prisons, asylum accommodation or disability benefit assessments, are now controlled by just one or two major contractors."
Ms Hodge tore into the DWP over the involvement of private companies in the Work Programme, which aims to find jobs for the unemployed, and in the administration of the personal independence payments for the disabled and the new universal credit scheme.
"It's in danger of meltdown in relation to too much of its business," she said. "The reluctance to be transparent is in part a reluctance to be honest about a failure to deliver services. They hide behind commercial confidentiality."
The PAC is calling for Freedom of Information legislation to cover government deals with private firms, for contractors to be obliged to "open their books up" and for the National Audit Office to be given greater authority to scrutinise contracts.
"Too often the Government has used commercial confidentiality as an excuse to withhold information, often in response to Freedom of Information requests from the public or MPs," the committee says.
It warns that central government management of private contracts has "too often been very weak" and lacks the expertise to extract the greatest value from contractors.
A Cabinet Office spokeswoman said: "As the PAC acknowledges, this Government is reforming Whitehall and improving the Civil Service's commercial capabilities. Our reforms saved taxpayers £3.8bn last year, but there is more to do as part of our long-term economic plan and to build on our world-leading transparency record."
A DWP spokesman said: "We've already successfully launched the benefit cap, universal credit and the new personal independence payment??? the Work Programme has got almost 500,000 of the hardest-to-help into jobs."
]]></text></news-item>