<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3B4E-A96B-9848-2229"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Carbon Conscious jumps 8.7% on robust volume</title><source>Australian Company News Bites - Stock Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[STOCK REPORT
Carbon Conscious Limited (ASX:CCF), Australia's 39th largest commercial & professional services company by market capitalisation, jumped 0.20c (or 8.7%) from its last traded date of March 12, 2014 to close at 2.50c. Compared with the All Ordinaries Index which fell 82.0 points (or 1.5%) in the day, this represented a relative price increase of 10.2%. This has been propped up by robust volume of 2.7 times average.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Carbon Conscious, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/0010510219403142576
Bullish SignalsUptrend- The stock's relative price strength percentile is rising at 39 for 6 months, 44 for 3 months and 78 for 1 month.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Sales of 0.4 [1.0]. We estimate Carbon Conscious stock is trading at a current year Price/Sales of 0.3 and a forward year Price/Sales of 0.2.Other Bullish Signals:- The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 19.8%. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.1. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued and ranks in the top 2% of stock by value of Q Ratio.- Net Profit margin is negative but improving in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]

Bearish Signals- The present value of $1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in Carbon Conscious is $556, for a capital loss of $444.
- Net profit margin has averaged 1.9% in the last 3 years. This suggests the company is less profitable with a low margin of safety.- Revenue growth rate has shown signs of deterioration in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 188,180 shares worth $4,705 traded. Beta: the Beta of Carbon Conscious stock is 0.2. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market. - Carbon Conscious is at a discount of 47.9% to its 12-month high of 4.80c on 14 Mar, 2013. It is also at a premium of 31.6% to the 12-month low of 1.90c on 27 Nov, 2013.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:November 28: Carbon Conscious Announces Successful First Issuance of ACCUsCarbon Conscious announced that its 'Carbon Conscious Carbon Capture Project 1' has been issued with its first ACCUs (Australian Carbon Credit Units) by the Clean Energy Regulator. The company has long term contracts to manage its carbon estates for customers, which delivers stable quarterly revenue to the company through to 2027.
November 07: Carbon Conscious Reports NPAT of $40,000 for the Half Year to 30 September 2013Carbon Conscious reported NPAT of $40,000 for the half-year ended 30 September 2013. Revenues from ordinary activities were $727,000, down 89% from the same period last year. Basic and Diluted EPS was (0.07) cents compared to (2.36) cents last year. The net operating cash outflow was $(219,231) compared to an outflow of $(1.29m in the pcp.
September 17: CCF Carbon Capture Project Declared an Eligible Kyoto Offset[Company Release] * Carbon Capture Project 1 Declared "Eligible Kyoto Offsets Project".* Application for first ACCUs Submitted to Clean Energy Regulator.* Delivery of ACCUs expected in October 2013 for customers and the Company.* Additional income from balance sheet ACCU sales will add to existing quarterly customer revenue.Carbon Conscious ("Company") is pleased to announce that its 'Carbon Conscious Carbon Capture Project 1' ("Project") has been 'declared' by the Clean Energy Regulator ("CER") as an Eligible Kyoto Offsets Project under the Carbon Credits (Carbon Farming Initiative) Act 2011.Executive Director Mr.Andrew McBain said, "The declaration of the Project is a major milestone for Carbon Conscious, which has planted in excess of 18,000 hectares of carbon plantations in Australia since 2008, establishing itself as a leading carbon offsets project developer".An application for Australian Carbon Credit Units (ACCUs) has been lodged with the CER and the Company expects first ACCU's to be issued for customers and the Company in October.Carbon Conscious has long term contracts to manage carbon estates for customers, which delivers stable revenue of approximately $600,000/quarter out till 2027.
September 10: Carbon Conscious announces AGMCarbon Conscious has announced its Annual General Meeting will take place on December 12, 2013.
July 08: Carbon Conscious: ASIC Form 484[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Australia/Stock/News/227713.pdf
July 03: Carbon Conscious: Appendix 3Bhttp://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Australia/Stock/News/227087.pdf
June 27: City of Perth & CCF Extend Carbon Offset PartnershipCarbon Conscious Limited (Carbon Conscious) is pleased to announce the successful execution of a new contract with the City of Perth to offset the vehicle carbon emissions associated with the operation of the City of Perth's parking facilities.Over the coming weeks, Carbon Conscious will be planting many thousands of native mallee eucalypt trees on a site in the West Australian wheatbelt on behalf of the City of Perth.
ISIN: AU000000CCF4
AU:CCF; ASX:CCF; AX:CCF
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>