<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3BC0-A308-C562-16C6"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Capping to take another year</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Umesh Isalkar</author><text><![CDATA[PUNE: The deadline for scientific closure of the garbage depot in Phursungi-Uruli has been extended from June 2014 to March next year following revision in the original capping design.
The revised deadline will help accommodate huge amount of waste that has piled up because the capacity of the processing plant at the depot could not be utilized fully, resulting in open dumping. The move caused unrest among villagers who staged an agitation and prevented civic authorities from bringing in the city's trash.
The issue was temporarily resolved a few days back when villagers agreed to allow the Pune Municipal Corporation (PMC) to dispose its waste for the next two months. Union agriculture minister Sharad Pawar intervened seeking more time in view of the election code of conduct. Pawar, meanwhile, instructed civic officials to get their act together and prepare short-term and long-term plans to sort out the issue for once.
"We have extended the deadline because we want to see if we could accommodate all the garbage piled up at Phursungi-Uruli in the capping work which has been going on since January 2012. We have made an additional financial provision of Rs 10 crore to expedite the work," said Suresh Jagtap, head of the municipal solid management at PMC.
The civic body has also planned to create a landfill site at the capping area. "There are two landfill sites at the depot. We want to create one more site at the suitable area marked for capping. When done, we will be able to take care of rejects left over after processing at processing plants. Such a scientific landfill site will be able to take 500 tonne reject every day for the next three years," Jagtap said.
The Hanjer processing plant has been working below capacity for some time due to financial instability and workers' issues. "We plan to bring all the unprocessed trash under capping until we get proper land to create a landfill site at the area marked for capping," Jagtap said.
As per the estimates of environment engineers, the ongoing capping work can cover around 3.70 lakh tonne waste. The proposed additional landfill site at the capping area can take care of 4.80 lakh tonne.
"According to Municipal Solid Wastes (Management and Handling) Rules, 2000, if garbage processing plant breaks down, the accumulated garbage can be accommodated in a scientific landfill site," he said.
The civic body has appointed ILFS Environment Ltd, a Delhi-based company working in environmental services to supervise the work being executed by Concord Enviro Systems Pvt Ltd, a company based in Mumbai.
Divakar Chandekar, project head of ILFS Environment Ltd, said, "Of the proposed capping of 20 hectare land, we have already finished scientific capping of 14 hectare of land. This means almost 65% capping work is done. Since the civic body has taken a policy decision in view of the unprocessed garbage accumulated at the garbage depot, the revision has been effected in the original capping design."
The deadline for finishing the capping work is now extended to March 2015. We will see how we can take the unprocessed garbage under capping and construct a scientific landfill site at the suitable capping area. Landfill site requires flatter surface with good stability, Chandekar added.
According to environment rules, the capped garbage site area cannot be made open to public for 15 years. "However, green activities like developing a garden or a jogging track can be initiated on the capped site," Chandekar said. Besides stopping frequent fires, leachate generation and subsequent groundwater contamination, capping will enable us to trap methane from the garbage underneath and harness it for power generation reducing air pollution, he added.
"Capping will trap the methane and a gas extraction system will ensure proper utilization and can be used for power generation. Atmospheric air pollution which is currently high due to presence of garbage will also reduce," said Chandekar.
Capping will also involve reclamation, resources extraction and post-closure maintenance of the dumping ground. Procurement of a gas flaring unit and vegetative cover over the capped site will follow once capping is complete. Storm water drains, compound work and fencing, roads, an administrative building and complete electrification of the area is part of the project. The company will ensure maintenance of all facilities for 15 years.
More than 1,000 metric tonne of garbage generated in the city was openly dumped at the site for years which has stopped since June 1, 2010, following a series of protests by villagers of Uruli Devachi and Phursungi.
Repeated fires at the dump site, pollution of groundwater due to leachate seepage, continuous foul odour and passing of garbage trucks from the village are some of the complaints made by the villagers.
THE WOES
Fire breaks out at the garbage dump often, pushing them and civic officials on a confrontational path
Villagers also complain about pollution of groundwater due to seepage of leachate, a lingering odour and droning of garbage-laden trucks as they pass through the village.
CAPPING WORK SO FAR
Capping work, which will address issues like frequent fires at the garbage depot and stem leachate from flowing freely during the monsoon, is now 65% complete.
Earlier, the deadline for finishing the capping work was June 2014. It is now extended to March 2015 due to latest revision in capping design
The garbage is spread on 30 hectare in Urali Devachi and Phursungi areas and will be compacted on 20 hectares
The scientific closure of the landfill will cost Rs 79 crore
HOW THE WORK IS BEING DONE
Flattening the side slopes of the existing waste by cutting, leveling, relocation and reformation of waste to a safe slope
Removing waste from low-thickness areas and filling it in elevated areas - thereby reclaiming a part of the land
Providing a surface cover to minimise penetration of rain water, thus reducing / eliminating generation of leachate
Cover component will have different layers in the following order from bottom (waste surface) to top: like compacted soil layer of 200 mm, non-woven geo-textile layer (400 gsm) to act as a protective layer, both side textured high density polyethylene (HDPE) geo-membrane of 1.5 mm thickness to act as an impervious barrier, geo-composite layer (200 gsm) to act as a drainage layer, compacted soil layer of 300 mm to act as a protective layer for the components underneath and garden soil layer of 300mm to support vegetation growth
WHAT DOES CAPPING ENTAIL?
Provision of leachate (toxic liquid waste that seeps from wet garbage) collection, conveyance and treatment system
Provision of gas collection, conveyance and treatment system: Active gas collection system, comprising vertical and horizontal pipe network, has been proposed to collect and convey the landfill gas efficiently
Provision of gas flaring system: The collected gas will be flared on-site using an enclosed flaring system in the interim period till the power generation unit starts functioning or in the event of non operation of gas engine due to unforeseen reasons
Provision of storm water drainage system: Suitable sized drain network constructed in RCC is proposed to collect and divert storm water from the site.
Provision of internal road network: Road connecting various parts of the closed area as well as along the periphery of the closure is proposed to allow movement of vehicles for maintenance purpose.
Provision of boundary wall to restrict entry into the closure area.
Provision of admin block and security cabin: Administrative building accommodating office room, lab, wash/change rooms and store with necessary amenities has been proposed at a convenient location at the site. Security cabin is also proposed at the entry of the site to regulate entry of personnel and vehicles.
Provision of green belt: Landscaping and green belt development have been proposed to give aesthetic look to the site.
(Source: ILFS Environment Ltd, New Delhi)
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>