<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3C0C-6E38-3A5A-6A0E"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Ezz Steel decreases 1.1% on low volume</title><source>News Bites - Middle East &amp; North Africa: Egypt</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Ezz Steel (CA:ESRS), Egypt's largest basic resources company by market capitalisation, decreased 20.0 qirsh (or 1.1%) to close at LE17.80. Compared with the EGX 30 Index which fell 13.7 points (or 0.2%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -0.9%. The volume was 0.3 times the average trading of 1.2 million shares.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Ezz Steel, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051101740314149
Bearish Signals- Net Profit margin has shown signs of deterioration in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]

Bullish Signals- The 3.5% discount to 12-month high of LE18.44 against the 137.0% premium to 12-month low of LE7.51 suggests the stock continues to push for new highs. - The present value of LE1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Ezz Steel is LE1,882, for a capital gain of LE882.

NoteVolume: there were 337,588 shares worth LE6 million (US$862,902) traded.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 10: Ezz steel 3Q2013 results below estimates, Beltone[News Story]Arab Finance: Beltone Financial stated that Ezz steel net profit for 3Q2013 misses estimates on the back of weaker revenues and operating margins stemming from the subpar performance at the two scrap-based subsidiaries, with both recording a loss on the operating level.Beltone added in a research note "Ezzsteel released its 3Q2013 results with a net loss of EGP84 million, improving y-o-y when compared to the EGP128 million net loss posted in 3Q2012, mainly on higher steel prices and lower iron ore costs that translated into higher margins.
December 22: Ezz Steel to issue solidarity guarantee for El Ezz Flat Steel[News Story]Arab Finance: Ezz Steel (ESRS) BOD approved in its meeting to issue solidarity guarantee for its affiliate El Ezz Flat Steel Co. to guarantee credit facilities to finance working capital with maximum limit of $ 30 million.
Source: arabfinance.com
December 15: Egyptian court overturns steel tycoon Ahmed Ezz's 37-year sentence[News Story]Cairo - The Egyptian Court of Cassation overturned on Saturday the 37-year prison sentence given to business tycoon Ahmed Ezz in March on charges of profiteering and squandering public funds, ordering a retrial.The court verdict came in response to an appeal by Ezz and six former state officials who was also convicted in the case, which related to Ezz's acquisition of El-Dekheila steel plant.Ezz Steel (ESRS) has a 55 percent stake in Ezz Dekheila (IRAX), the largest steel producer in the Middle East.
November 07: Mubarak-era tycoon Ahmed Ezz to be retried in monopoly case[News Story] A Cairo court has accepted an appeal by prosecutors against the release of business tycoon Ahmed Ezz and two associates on monopoly charges.Ezz - majority-owner of Ezz El-Dekheila steel company and a senior figure in Hosni Mubarak's National Democratic Party - and company CEO Alaa Abul-Kheir were ordered by the court on Wednesday to pay fines of LE100 million ($14.2 million) each, while sales manager Samir Noaman was fined LE500,000 ($71,000)The three men were accused of monopolistic practices for penalising steel distributors who did not sell their entire market share during a given month by reducing their shares for the next month.Ezz is to be retried on other corruption charges, including money laundering, illegally procuring steel licenses, and receiving unmerited benefits from Egypt's Industrial Modernisation Centre.Overall, Ezz has been sentenced 60 years, but his appeals were accepted in many of those cases and he is to face retrials.In September, Cairo Criminal Court ordered his release on bail of LE100 million after he was retried on charges of laundering LE6.4 billion in illegally acquired funds between 2003 and 2011 in deals related to his acquisition of Ezz El-Dekheila (EZDK) steel plant.Ezz is the former chairman of Ezz Steel (ESRS) and has a 55 percent stake in EZDK, the largest steel complex in the Middle East.
October 28: Egypt's Ezz Steel plans $1 bln investment[News Story]CAIRO - Egypt's largest steel maker Ezz Steel (ESRS) plans to invest $1 billion to build two steel plants in the country once the government pushes through a stimulus package to boost spending on large infrastructure projects, a firm official said.Kamel Galal, the company's investor relations manager, told Reuters that his firm was planning to build the plants in Ain el-Sokhna, a region near the strategic Suez Canal.He did not give a time frame for the projects.
October 24: Egypt's Ezz Steel says 2nd quarter net profit rose 76 %[News Story] Cairo - Ezz Steel (ESRS), Egypt's biggest steel maker, said on Wednesday that consolidated net profit for the second quarter rose 76 pct year-on-year and that a new plant it was building would increase earnings in coming years."The strong domestic housing market coupled with the restart of the construction of the direct reduced iron (DRI) plant in Suez gives us confidence moving forward," Ezz Steel said in an emailed statement.The economic turmoil that followed Egypt's popular uprising in 2011 hurt demand for cement and steel for the construction of infrastructure and luxury housing, but a lack of enforcement of building regulations has triggered a boom in low-cost housing.Ezz said in July it was due to bring a DRI factory on line in the second half of 2014 that would shave $50 to $100 off the cost of each tonne of iron it makes.The company said on Wednesday that net profit for the second quarter of 2013 rose to 250 million Egyptian pounds (US$36.3 million) from 82 million pounds in the first half of 2012.Net sales increased to 5.56 billion pounds from 5.11 billion, Ezz said.For the first half of 2013, net profit rose to 302 million pounds from the year-earlier 82 million pounds.Net sales for the first half rose to 11.14 billion pounds from 10.31 billion in the first half of 2012, the company said.
Source: arabfinance.com
September 11: Ezz Steel jumps as Egypt mulls punishing Turkish steel[News Story]Cairo - Ezz Steel (ESRS), Egypt's biggest publicly-traded producer of the metal, gained the most in two months after the government said it's studying anti-dumping fees on Turkish imports to protect the local industry.Shares of the Cairo-based company climbed 4.2 percent to 11.18 Egyptian pounds at the close in the capital, the largest advance since July 9 and bringing a rally in the past three days to 5.8 percent.
ISIN: EGS3C251C013
CA:ESRS; CAI:ESRS; EY:ESRS
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>