<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3CBE-B95A-5A73-DDE3"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Short-sighted Biennale artists who bit the hand that fed them may be left very hungry</title><source>Weekend Australian</source><author>MATTHEW WESTWOOD, ARTS CORRESPONDENT</author><text><![CDATA[A row over a patron linked to detention centres has the government redesigning funding deals
MELBOURNE artist Gabrielle de Vietri was planting a garden for her installation in the Biennale of Sydney. Her Garden of Bad Flowers, according to an artist statement, references the 19th-century symbolism of certain plants: so lavender becomes distrust, cypress mourning, basil hatred.
They aptly describe some of the emotions swirling around this year's Biennale, thanks to protests led by de Vietri and others.
Last month, artists and activists took exception to one of the Biennale's sponsors, Transfield Holdings. The company is a minority shareholder in Transfield Services, which has a $1.22 billion contract to run detention centres at Manus Island and Nauru. Drop Transfield, the artists pleaded, and find another sponsor.
When the board refused, nine artists pulled out of the show: de Vietri uprooted her garden and donated it to a sustainability farm. No way were they going to be seen at an event that, through a ``chain of associations'', linked them with offshore processing. They withdrew their work, cancelled their public events and relinquished their fees. ``We see our participation in the Biennale as an active link in a chain of associations that leads to the abuse of human rights,'' reads their manifesto.
Surely these artists, if they were in receipt of government grants, would give that money back, too. In the ``chain of associations'' between the art festival and funding sources, the buck stops at the federal government: the primary sponsor of mandatory detention.
Inquirer has learned that de Vietri has received $55,000 in Australia Council grants from the commonwealth: $35,000 in 2010 for a residency in Berlin, and another $20,000 in 2012. The two other Australian artists among the nine have also taken Australia Council money: Nathan Gray ($10,000 in 2008) and Charlie Sofo ($10,000 in 2008 and again last year).
De Vietri saw no contradiction in rejecting the Biennale fees -- Transfield Holdings contributed 6.1 per cent of the Biennale budget -- and taking public money from the Australia Council. The arts grant is distributed at ``arm's length'' from government, she reasons, so there's no chain of associations there. She says that by dealing with one government agency, one does not necessarily condone the actions of another.
Political correctness has been exposed in a stunning turn of events that will have far-reaching ramifications for the arts sector. The Biennale last week caved in to pressure from artists and activists, and Luca Belgiorno-Nettis resigned as chairman, ending a 41-year partnership between his family and the art festival. He has described in bitter terms the insults directed at him, his family and Biennale staff.
Federal Communications Minister Malcolm Turnbull -- whose Turnbull Foundation is listed as a Biennale supporter -- struck out at the ``vicious ingratitude'' of the boycotting artists.
Then Arts Minister George Brandis took decisive action. He has directed the Australia Council -- in a strongly worded letter to chairman Rupert Myer, revealed in The Australian -- to consider cutting subsidy to arts organisations that refuse corporate sponsorship.
The letter specifically refers to the board of the Biennale and the ``appalling insult'' to Transfield and the Belgiorno-Nettis family: no doubt the Australia Council will ``have regard to this episode'' when Biennale funding comes up for renewal next year.
The minister goes further, demanding an Australia Council policy to deal with arts organisations that ``unreasonably'' refuse private-sector funds. A consequence may be that ``Australia Council funding would no longer be available''.
The minister is permitted under the Australia Council legislation to give general directions to the funding body, but opponents say Brandis's intervention comes close to political interference in funding decisions.
The Biennale controversy has become a lightning rod for arguments over private-sector support for the arts. Arts organisations are increasingly seeking funds and in-kind support from businesses and private donors, as governments retreat from high subsidy. Both sides of politics have leaned on arts, businesses and donors to find alternative sources of funds.
There is a proud history of arts philanthropy in Australia but the sum of private-sector support is small. The most recent figure shows sponsorships and donations were worth $221 million in 2009-10, about 10 per cent of all arts funding.
That's a drop in the ocean compared with the fundraising done on behalf of medical research, for example. And Australian arts development is still in its infancy when compared with the US, where some cultural institutions have multi-billion-dollar endowments.
Both parties in a sponsorship benefit from the association. Arts organisations want the cash, of course, but also the professional expertise and in-kind support that corporations offer. Companies and private donors want to be seen as good citizens who give back to the community.
It may even be a way for the rich to ``launder their souls'', as The Economist's culture editor, Fiammetta Rocco, citing a director from the museums world, told a seminar in Melbourne recently.
It is wrong to assume there is an unyielding ideological divide between the arts and business -- not all artists or arts managers are lefties -- but inevitably there will be differences of opinion.
Fiona Menzies, chief executive of Creative Partnerships Australia, a government body charged with bringing arts and business together, says the Biennale-Transfield break-up may lead arts companies to develop a clearly-started policy on sponsorship, ``aligned to their values, and which is reviewed regularly''.
Sponsorships, donations and bequests from the private sector should be valued because they help art happen. Enlightened cultural organisations recognise this: they operate within a sophisticated space where people from different backgrounds and beliefs come together in common cause.
Belgiorno-Nettis, whose father, Franco, helped establish the Biennale of Sydney in 1973, wanted the art festival to be a place for public debate. By thumbing their noses at a generous supporter, de Vietri and her cohorts have jeopardised Australia's oldest and most prestigious contemporary art event.
]]></text></news-item>