<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3CDB-B478-9491-D263"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>PUBLIC NOTICE</title><source>Laramie Boomerang (Wyoming)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Pursuant to the Wyoming Administrative Procedure Act and the Wyoming Public Service Commission's (Commission) Rules, the Commission hereby gives notice of the application of SourceGas Distribution LLC, (SourceGas or the Company) for authority to revise the Fuel, Lost and Unaccounted for Gas Percentages (FL&U) in all of its Divisions, as more fully described below.
SourceGas is a natural gas public utility as defined by W.S. § 37-1-101 (a) (vi) (D) and, as such, is subject to the Commission's jurisdiction under W.S. § 37-2-112.
On February 28, 2014, SourceGas filed an annual application requesting approval to revise its FL&U gas percentages as directed by the Commission. The Company seeks to [i] increase the percentage to mainline customers in its Casper Division; [ii] increase the percentage to the distribution transportation customers in its Casper Division; [iii] increase the percentage to the Choice Gas Program in its Casper Division; [iv] increase the percentage to the distribution transportation customers in the Gillette Division; [v] increase the percentage for reconciliation for the Choice Gas Program suppliers in the Gillette Division; [vi] decrease the percentage to the distribution transportation customers in the Torrington Division; and [vii] increase the percentage for reconciliation for the Choice Gas Program suppliers in the Torrington Division. Each increased or decreased FL&U percentage would apply to SourceGas' Casper, Gillette or Torrington Divisions for the current Choice Gas program year, June 1, 2014, through May 31, 2015.
The Company's proposed FL&U percentages for the Casper Division are: [i] 1.153% for Mainline System Interconnect and Mainline System End-Users; [ii] 3.579% Distribution System End-Users; and [iii] 3.759% Choice Gas Program. The Company's proposed FL&U percentages for the Gillette Division are: [iv] 2.013% Choice Gas Program suppliers; and [v] 1.493% Distribution System End-Users. The Company's proposed FL&U percentages for the Torrington Division are: [vi] 0.118% Choice Gas Program Supplier FL&U Reconciliation Process; and [vii] 0.228% Distribution System End-Users. These figures would replace the current FL&U percentages approved in Docket No. 30022-207-GA-13.
This is not a complete description of the application. Interested persons may inspect the application at the Commission's offices in Cheyenne, Wyoming, and at any SourceGas office located in Casper, Gillette or Torrington, Wyoming.
Anyone wishing to file a statement, intervention petition, protest or request for a public hearing in this matter must do so in writing filed with the Commission on or before April 4, 2014. Any intervention request filed with the Commission shall set forth the grounds of the proposed intervention or request for hearing as well as the position and the interest of the petitioner in this proceeding. Please be sure to mention Docket No. 30022-226-GA-14 in all correspondence with the Commission.
If you wish to intervene in this matter or request a public hearing which you will attend, and you require reasonable accommodation for a disability, call the Commission at (307) 777-7427 or write to the Commission, 2515 Warren Avenue, Suite 300, Cheyenne, Wyoming 82002. Communicationsimpaired persons may contact the Commission through Wyoming Relay at 711.
Dated: March 5, 2014.
Publish: March 7, and 14, 2014
PUBLIC NOTICE
The Wyoming Public Service Commission (Commission) has given SourceGas Distribution LLC (SGD or the Company) authority to pass on to its customers in the Casper Division taking service under the Pass-On Rate [Regulated Rate] a retail gas rate increase of $0.08993 per therm, effective on and after March 1, 2014. This approval is subject to notice, protest, investigation, opportunity for hearing, change, refund and such other orders as the Commission may deem appropriate.
The proposed pass-on rate is attributable to: [i] a projected increase of $0.07267 per therm in the wholesale cost of gas, [ii] an increase of $0.01674 per therm to the Commodity Balancing Account surcharge, and [iii] an increase of $0.00052 per therm to the Working Gas Storage Adjustment. The increase will result in a dollar-for-dollar projected increase of $542, 478 in the Company's revenue from March 1, 2014, through May 31, 2014.
The average small general service customer using approximately 82 therms per month during the rate effective period of March 1, 2014, through May 31, 2014, may expect a monthly gas bill increase of approximately $7.40, or about 10.9%, before taxes. Actual bills will vary with usage.
Commission Rules §§ 249 and 250, allow a utility to pass on to its customers known or prospective wholesale commodity cost increases or decreases on a dollar-for-dollar basis and subject to public notice, opportunity for hearing and refund.
SGD's application is on file at the Commission's offices in Cheyenne, Wyoming, and in the Company's Casper, Wyoming, business office, and may be inspected by any interested person during regular business hours. Anyone desiring to file an intervention petition, request for a public hearing, statement, public comment or protest in this matter must file in writing with the Commission on or before April 3, 2014. The petition shall set forth the grounds of the proposed intervention or request for hearing and the position and interest of the petitioner in this proceeding.
If you want to intervene in this matter or request a public hearing that you will attend, or want to make a statement, a protest or a public comment, and you require reasonable accommodation for a disability, please contact the Commission at (307) 777-7427, or write to the Commission at 2515 Warren Avenue, Suite 300, Cheyenne, Wyoming 82002, to make arrangements. Communications impaired persons may also contact the Commission by accessing Wyoming Relay at 711. Please mention Docket No. 30022-225-GP-14 in your communications.
Dated: March 3, 2014.
Publish: March 7, and March 14, 2014
FORECLOSURE SALE NOTICE
WHEREAS, default in the payment of principal and interest has occurred under the terms of a promissory note ("Note") and real estate mortgage ("Mortgage"). The Mortgage dated May 22, 2009, was executed and delivered by Lisa Konija and Christopher Konija ("Mortgagor (s)") to The Mortgage Source, Inc., S-Corporation, as security for the Note of the same date, and said Mortgage was recorded on May 28, 2009, at Reception No. 2009-3208 in the records of the office of the County Clerk and exofficio Register of Deeds in and for Albany County, State of Wyoming; and WHEREAS, the mortgage was assigned for value as follows:
Assignee: Jonah Bank of Wyoming Assignment dated: May 22, 2009 Assignment recorded: June 3, 2009 Assignment recording information: at Reception No. 2009-3375
Assignee: Franklin American Mortgage Company Assignment dated: December 29, 2010 Assignment recorded: January 18, 2011 Assignment recording information: at Reception No. 2011-348
Assignee: Wells Fargo Bank, N.A. Assignment dated: December 22, 2010 Assignment recorded: January 18, 2011 Assignment recording information: at Reception No. 2011-349
All in the records of the County Clerk and ex-officio Register of Deeds in and for Albany County, Wyoming.
WHEREAS, the Mortgage contains a power of sale which by reason of said default, the Mortgagee declares to have become operative, and no suit or proceeding has been instituted at law to recover the debt secured by the Mortgage, or any part thereof, nor has any such suit or proceeding been instituted and the same discontinued; and WHEREAS, written notice of intent to foreclose the Mortgage by advertisement and sale has been served upon the record owner and the party in possession of the mortgaged premises at least ten (10) days prior to the commencement of this publication, and the amount due upon the Mortgage on the date of first publication of this notice of sale being the total sum of $206, 062.04 which sum consists of the unpaid principal balance of $188, 900.68 plus interest accrued to the date of the first publication of this notice in the amount of $10, 232.17, plus other costs in the amount of $6, 929.19, plus attorneys' fees, costs expended, and accruing interest and late charges after the date of first publication of this notice of sale; WHEREAS, The property being foreclosed upon may be subject to other liens and encumbrances that will not be extinguished at the sale. Any prospective purchaser should research the status of title before submitting a bid; NOW, THEREFORE Wells Fargo Bank, N.A., as the Mortgagee, will have the Mortgage foreclosed as by law provided by causing the mortgaged property to be sold at public venue by the Sheriff or Deputy Sheriff in and for Albany County, Wyoming to the highest bidder for cash at 10:00 o'clock in the forenoon on March 26, 2014 at the front door of the Albany County Courthouse located at 525 Grand Avenue, Laramie, WY, Albany County, for application on the above-described amounts secured by the Mortgage, said mortgaged property being described as follows, to-wit: LOT 11, BLOCK 16, COUGHLIN ADDITION TO THE CITY OF LARAMIE, ALBANY COUNTY, WYOMING, ACCORDING TO THE PLAT THEREOF RECORDED MAY 10, 1967 IN THE RECORDS OF ALBANY COUNTY, WYOMING.
with an address of 1602 Mitchell Street, Laramie, WY 82072.
Together with all improvements thereon situate and all fixtures and appurtenances thereto.
Wells Fargo Bank, N.A. By: The Castle Law Group, LLC 123 West 1st Street, Ste. 400 Casper, WY 82601-0000 (307) 333-5379
Publish: February 28, 2014, March 7, 2014, March 14, 2014, March 21, 2014
]]></text></news-item>