<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3D40-F52D-C382-97DC"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>A taboo, a problem, a sin and a crime</title><source>Daily Times (PK)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Pakistan, March 15 -- Child abuse is a widespread issue, which is growing at an alarming rate in our country and has largely been left unchecked because of its sensitive nature. Although Pakistan is a signatory of the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child, and even though article 34 of the convention says,"The state partakes to protect children from sexual exploitation and other abuses including prostitution", one out of every three children is a victim of some kind of abuse in Pakistan. Most of these children are abused by someone they know and trust, like a relative, family friend or a caretaker. However, there are also cases where unfamiliar people are found guilty of the sexual abuse of minors.
The term 'child abuse' covers a wide array of very diverse kinds of crimes against minors. It signifies physical as well as mental pain. When an adult tries to use a child as a sex toy, it is child abuse. When an adult tries to meet his labour needs at a lower cost, it is also child abuse. When a child is exploited as a commodity and traded for monetary or non-monetary produce, it is child abuse. When an adult forces the child to push himself beyond his strength, overlooking all health guidelines for children, it is child abuse. Pakistan is a country that does little to protect its younger generation from the many horrors of child abuse to which they are exposed.
The data collected by a non-governmental organisation highlights that the highest number of child abuse cases were reported in Punjab where 3,772 boys and girls were subjected to inhuman treatment. In Sindh, this figure was 2,412, Khyber Pakhtunkhwa stood at 498 while in Balochistan 98 incidents of child abuse were reported. Among the cities, Multan remains on top of the list with 1,041 cases of child abuse, while in Karachi the number of reported cases was 516. In Gujranwala, as many as 820 child abuse cases were reported, Lahore 749, Sialkot 701, Rawalpindi 699, Faisalabad 598, Peshawar 574, Larkana 478, Hyderabad 415 and in Sukkur 189 children were subjected to inhuman treatment.
However, most child abuse cases go unreported in Pakistan. Research suggests that, across the globe, the incidence of sexual abuse of children is at least 15 percent to 20 percent; small-scale research done in Pakistan also produced similar results. Sadly, most offenders are relatives or religious teachers (as per the survey conducted by some international agencies). These people lure children in different ways to achieve their ends. Victimised children, who are usually vulnerable, do not talk about abuse because, in most cases, the perpetrator is part of their family and they fear their revelations may disrupt their family life. When the perpetrator is a representative of religion and things that are meant to be pure and divine, it becomes even more difficult for victims to report them. Then confusion, embarrassment and pain are confused with faith and religion.
We should remember that this is a society in which domestic violence and abuse are regarded as internal family matters and are sometimes endorsed as well. Until and unless such crimes are punished, these issues will never just go away. Moreover, children of both sexes suffer from child sexual abuse in Pakistan. It is difficult for girls but even worse for boys because of our stereotypical views about masculinity. In a society that promotes the strong and macho image of men who are capable of handling anything, becoming the victim of sexual abuse is the most degrading stigma. Girls face different circumstances altogether. They are considered the 'honour' of society and of their families. They are supposed to be protected and are constantly taught the value of virtue. In such circumstances, sexual abuse is the worst thing to report. If they reveal the abuse, then in most cases they are urged and ultimately forced to stay quiet about it. If the abuse is revealed, the girl is marked forever. No one will marry her and she will remain a spinster. It is a social stigma that is unforgivable and intolerable.
The biggest hurdle we face in addressing this issue is society's attitude towards sexuality. It is a taboo, a problem, a sin and a crime. We need to guide our children in this regard. Parents need to rethink their positions of authority and become friends to their children. It is only then that these issues can be addressed and solved. The victims are vulnerable and fragile. They are confused. They can never tell their parents about their abuse until they know for sure that their parents will understand. They are full of shame and sometimes a guilty perverted pleasure because they are not aware of what has happened to them. They blame themselves and think that they are responsible for the abuse. During this confusing and shameful time it is imperative that children are handled with extreme care and consideration.
We are all aware that the 18th constitutional amendment enshrined the responsibility of ensuring legislation for the protection of children but there are still no child protection policies or a plan of action for children at the provincial level. Nor is there a focal department or statutory body with a mandate to deal with the issues of child protection. Article 25 (3) of the constitution recognises the need for the special rights for children due to their vulnerability. It is a growing problem that continues to be ignored. The government seems too preoccupied to solve the problem and parents are still naive about it. We need to rethink the values and norms that give children almost no rights.
These statistics cannot be ignored any more. Law enforcement agencies must change their attitude towards this issue. Sensitive and appropriately trained individuals should be made a part of special task forces set up to deal with cases of child sexual abuse. If we keep neglecting the victims, not only will they ruin their own lives but the lives of the next generation as well. It will become a vicious circle. We need a social revolution. For that we need to change ourselves, our everyday practices and interactions.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Daily Times. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>