<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3D4A-B4B3-EF4D-B87A"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>$20,000 Fine After HR Staff, Supervisor Fail To Immediately Report Injury To MOL</title><source>Mondaq</source><author>Mr Adrian Miedema</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 14, 2014 (Mondaq:http://mondaq.com/ Delivered by Newstex) An Ontario employer has been fined $20,000 for failing to report an injury to the Ministry of Labour, showing that employers need to educate their managers about the types of injuries that must be reported under the Occupational Health and Safety Act.
A worker was injured when a loaded skid tipped and his leg became trapped under parts. He suffered a broken bone which is a "critical injury" under the OHSA. The OHSA requires employers to immediately report critical injuries to the Ministry of Labour. The employee told his supervisor and, later, human resources staff that he had broken his leg.Four days after the accident, the Ministry of Labour contacted the company about the accident. The human resources staff said that the company was in the process of reporting to the Ministry of Labour.The company pleaded guilty to failing to immediately report this critical injury to the MOL, contrary to section 51(1) of the Occupational Health and Safety Act. The court imposed a $20,000 fine plus the 25% "victim fine surcharge", for a total of $25,000.It is not always obvious what types of injuries are "critical injuries" under the OHSA. Employers should educate their managers and, where there is any doubt, obtain legal advice.The Ministry of Labour's press release may be accessed here[1].For more information, visit our Occupational Health Safety Law blog at www.occupationalhealthandsafetylaw.com[2]About DentonsDentons is a global firm driven to provide you with the competitive edge in an increasingly complex and interconnected marketplace. We were formed by the March 2013 combination of international law firm Salans LLP, Canadian law firm Fraser Milner Casgrain LLP (FMC) and international law firm SNR Denton.Dentons is built on the solid foundations of three highly regarded law firms. Each built its outstanding reputation and valued clientele by responding to the local, regional and national needs of a broad spectrum of clients of all sizes - individuals; entrepreneurs; small businesses and start-ups; local, regional and national governments and government agencies; and mid-sized and larger private and public corporations, including international and global entities.Now clients benefit from more than 2,500 lawyers and professionals in 79 locations in 52 countries across Africa, Asia Pacific, Canada, Central Asia, Europe, the Middle East, Russia and the CIS, the UK and the US who are committed to challenging the status quo to offer creative, actionable business and legal solutions.Learn more at www.dentons.com[3]The content of this article is intended to provide a general guide to the subject matter. Specialist advice should be sought about your specific circumstances. Specific Questions relating to this article should be addressed directly to the author. Mr Adrian MiedemaDentons LLPToronto-Dominion Centre77 King Street West, Suite 400TorontoOntarioM5K 0A1CANADA E-mail: samantha.francis@dentons.comURL: www.dentons.comClick Here [4] for related articles (c) Mondaq Ltd, 2014 - Tel. +44 (0)20 8544 8300 - http://www.mondaq.com[5] [1]: http://news.ontario.ca/mol/en/2014/02/walinga-inc-fined-20000-for-failure-to-report-injury.html [2]: http://www.mondaq.com/redirection.asp?article_id=299310company_id=288redirectaddress=http%3A//www.occupationalhealthandsafetylaw.com [3]: http://www.mondaq.com/redirection.asp?article_id=299310company_id=288redirectaddress=http%3A//www.dentons.com [4]: http://www.mondaq.com/search/relate.asp?article_id=299310online_host_id=0 [5]: http://www.mondaq.com/default.asp?online_host_id=22id=299310

]]></text></news-item>