<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3D4A-5AB1-A8AE-F991"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Rio Tinto PLC Annual Financial Report</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[In accordance with the requirements of Rules 4.1 & 6.3.5 of the UK Listing Authority's Disclosure and Transparency Rules, a description of the principal risks and uncertainties affecting the Group and a responsibility statement are set out in appendix 1 to this announcement. Contacts media.enquiries@riotinto.com www.riotinto.com Follow @RioTinto on Twitter
Appendix 1 Risk factors Rio Tinto's business units and functions assess the potential economic and non-economic consequences of their respective risks using the framework defined by the Group's Risk policy and standard. Principal risks and uncertainties are identified when the Risk Management Committee, business unit or function determines that the potential consequences are material at a Group level or where the risk is connected and may trigger a succession of events that, in aggregate, become material to the Group. Once identified, each principal risk or uncertainty is reviewed by the relevant internal experts and by the Risk Management Committee. The following describes all currently-known principal risks and uncertainties that could materially affect Rio Tinto. There may be additional risks unknown to Rio Tinto and other risks, currently believed to be immaterial, which could turn out to be material. The risk factors outlined do not include the management detail on how each is managed and mitigated, which is discussed in more detail on page 66 of the Group's 2013 Annual report. Risks may materialise individually, simultaneously or in combination and could significantly affect the Group's: - short, medium and long-term business and prospects; - earnings, cash flow and financial position; - overall financial results and product demand; - current asset values; - future asset values and growth potential; - safety record and the long, medium and short-term health of its employees; - environmental effects; or - Group or business unit reputation. The principal risks and uncertainties should be considered in connection with any forward-looking statements in this document and the cautionary statement on the inside front cover. External risks
]]></text></news-item>