<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3D89-6D0E-A344-9367"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>'Acid House King' and the £1¼m fraud</title><source>Western Daily Press</source><author>KATE FERGUSON</author><text><![CDATA[A cyber gang led by the "Acid House King" who plundered £1.25 million from British banks are facing jail after being found guilty of fraud.
The organised crime group used a trojan horse device to hijack computers at branches of Barclays and Santander and siphon off cash.
They also stole credit and bank card details from around one million intercepted letters and used them to splash out on Rolex watches and designer jewellery worth more than £1 million, police said.
The gang was led by Tony Colston-Haytor, from Ilminster in Somerset. He threw the notorious Acid House raves in the Home Counties which sparked controversy in 1989. The son of a university lecturer and solicitor, Colston-Haytor had earlier pleaded guilty to masterminding the fraud while ten others also admitted their part in the scam.
Yesterday at Southwark Crown Court, two more men, Lanre Mullins-Abudu, 25, and Steven Hannah, 52, were found guilty of their roles in the audacious fraud.
Jurors had heard that the gang used a device known as a keyboard video mouse (KVM) switch to access and control Barclays and Santander bank accounts remotely on three occasions. Darius Bolder, 34, walked into a branch of Barclays in Swiss Cottage, north London, on April 4 last year, allowing the group to access the bank's IT system. The gang used the trojan-horse style KVM device to make 128 transfers worth £1,252,490 to a network of mule accounts set up to launder the stolen cash.
Their victims included London Metropolitan University and the University of Portsmouth.
Just three months later the gang struck again.
Dean Outram, 32, went into the Lewisham branch of Barclays on July 17 last year and illicitly gained access to its computers, stealing £90,000. And two months later Outram managed to gain access to Santander's IT system by fitting a KVM switch into a bank computer at one of its branches in Surrey Quays, south east London.
Meanwhile, Lanre Mullins-Abudu, 25, and Asad Ali Qureshi, 26, tried to hack into Santander's banking system in order to steal what police warned would have been "substantial funds". But police swooped on an address in Kingsley Avenue in Hounslow, west London, where Mullins-Abudu, Qureshi and eight others were arrested.
They arrested Outram nearby after he left the bank.
Barclays has recovered around £600,000 of the stolen money. Mullins-Abudu, of Weimar Street, Putney, south west London, was found guilty of conspiracy to commit fraud, two counts of conspiracy to steal, possession of articles for use in fraud, and concealing criminal property.
Hannah, of Bell Street, Marylebone, west London, was found guilty of conspiracy to commit fraud.
Duane Jean-Jacques, 25, of Belsize Road, South Hampstead, was cleared of conspiracy to steal and concealing criminal property.
They will be sentenced at a later date.
MORE ONLINE www.westerndailypress.co.uk An elderly couple were conned out of their life savings in a single phone call - more at www.westerndailypress.co.uk
]]></text></news-item>