<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3DA3-7EA4-7224-E647"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Facing Growing Uncertainty, Biomass Sector Pushes EPA For GHG Waiver</title><source>Inside EPA Weekly Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Faced with growing regulatory and legal uncertainty, biomass industry groups are stepping up pressure for EPA to at least propose a plan for how to regulate greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions from combustion of the fuel at stationary sources, though prospects for such a step appear limited, at least in the short term.
The industry concern is exacerbated by a series of factors, including the looming expiration of the agency's temporary GHG permit waiver, which an appellate court has already held is unlawful, regulators' increasing requirement to impose GHG permit limits on new biomass facilities and the possibility that an upcoming Supreme Court ruling will provide the industry with a longer-term exemption by finding GHGs cannot on their own trigger permits.
"If they don't do anything, they're just leaving the uncertainty alive," says a source with the National Alliance of Forest Owners (NAFO), adding that EPA has not "clarified the answer to the question of when" it will act.
A source with the Biomass Power Association (BPA) says EPA is working on its approach and is expected to unveil a plan this summer. This source also stresses the need for an EPA policy, including that the agency is working on a number of other GHG rules that could impact biomass. "EPA has got to act on this," the source says.
An EPA spokeswoman says the agency is "undertaking a detailed examination of the science associated with biogenic carbon dioxide (CO2) emissions from stationary sources, including engaging with federal partners, technical experts, and an independent Science Advisory Board (SAB) to consider technical issues. At this stage, EPA is considering the recommendations made by the SAB to determine next steps."
One environmentalist says EPA does not appear to be crafting a proposal at this time. "I have no indication that EPA is working on" a rule right now, or when anything might be released, the environmentalist says.
At issue is how or whether the agency regulates GHG emissions from biomass combustion. Industry wants the agency to permanently exempt biomass GHG emissions from regulations, arguing that the emissions are carbon-neutral as long as forest stocks continue to grow and sequester carbon.
But environmentalists argue that burning whole trees for fuel can be worse for the climate than burning coal, and they want EPA to set tight requirements depending on what material is burned and how fast it regrows.
In July 2011, the agency issued a temporary rule deferring CO2 permit requirements for biomass-fueled stationary sources for three years while the agency worked to craft a biomass accounting framework (BAF) for measuring GHGs that was expected to provide the basis for a permit regulatory system.
But the agency's SAB strongly criticized the agency's draft BAF, charging that the agency could not justify its finding that the fuel source is carbon-neutral. "Carbon neutrality cannot be assumed for all biomass energy a priori," SAB concluded in its 2012 report, where it also issued a series of recommendations for EPA to improve its accounting framework.
And a federal appellate court vacated the temporary waiver, finding that it violated the Clean Air Act. Industry may still appeal the ruling, but for now it is on hold -- including the court's "mandate" implementing the ruling -- until the high court decides the fate of EPA's GHG permit program.
If the Supreme Court in Utility Air Regulatory Group v. EPA holds that GHGs cannot by themselves trigger stationary source permit requirements, then the temporary permit deferral will be moot -- at least in the near term -- because it will no longer matter whether a GHG is emitted by a biogenic source -- such as wood that also sequesters carbon -- or a fossil fuel.
But even before the Supreme Court rules, EPA and other regulators have effectively been implementing the D.C. Circuit's ruling, including severing biomass deferrals in approvals of state implementation plans (SIPs) for GHGs, most recently in its proposal to approve Texas' GHG SIP last month and also in New Mexico's GHG SIP last summer.
Prior to the D.C. Circuit ruling, EPA had approved a handful of GHG SIPs adopting the three-year deferral, including in Washington, Minnesota, Illinois and Massachusetts.
Further, the environmentalist says EPA regions appear to be adopting the court ruling, leaning away from biomass GHG permit deferrals in permit decisions. The source points to a November 2013 statement of basis accompanying a permit proposed by Region IX for Sierra Pacific Industries (SPI) to construct a 31-megawatt co-generation facility that would be primarily fueled by biomass in California.
The document notes that EPA previously issued a final permit for the project in February 2013 but that was appealed to EPA's Environmental Appeals Board (EAB) which remanded the permit because Region IX failed to hold a public hearing on the matter. The remand required the region to reopen the prevention of significant deterioration (PSD) permit proceedings, which were underway when the D.C. Circuit vacated the biomass deferral rule. Relevant documents are available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID: 2463870)
"EPA has not made any decisions at this time with respect to application of PSD permitting requirements after the court's opinion on the deferral rule. Due to its grant of an earlier extension request, the D.C. Circuit has not yet issued the mandate in its decision on the biogenic CO2 deferral rule, and the decision remains subject to possible additional legal proceedings. . . . To facilitate EPA action on this permit while these matters remain unresolved, SPI requested" that EPA review the appropriate emission limits and the agency opted to add GHG limits to the proposed PSD permit, the document says.
Additionally, the Vermont Public Service Board Feb. 11 rejected a proposed 35-megawatt biomass facility due to its GHG impacts, denying the plant a certificate of public good because the project would interfere with the state's ability to meet statutory goals for cutting GHGs 50 percent from 1990 levels by 2028 "as a result of the large annual releases of greenhouse gases that would result from the combustion of the wood fuel."
The Partnership for Policy Integrity (PFPI) calls that "an important decision for the state of Vermont, and nationally. When policymakers see that bioenergy involves harvesting forests and burning wood in low-efficiency power plants, they conclude that large-scale bioenergy isn't compatible with greenhouse gas reduction goals." The plant would have had a 28 percent efficiency rate, lower than the 33 percent efficiency rate of the average coal fleet, PFPI says.
The Vermont board concluded that "the evidentiary record supports a finding that the project would release as much as 448,714 tons of CO2[equivalent] per year, and that sequestration of those [GHG] would not occur until future years, possibly not for decades, and would not occur at all in the case of forest-regeneration failures."
The industry groups say that they are not focusing on a looming Supreme Court ruling, expected by June 30, just weeks before the deferral's July 20 expiration date, that could remove GHGs as a trigger for stationary source permits, saying that such a ruling would provide only a temporary reprieve and that the industry needs EPA to move forward with a biomass CO2 accounting rule.
That is because EPA will still need to address how to regulate biomass emissions for other policies, including its new source performance standards for power plants, as well as to provide national consistency for states to follow, industry sources say.
The NAFO source says it is imperative that EPA issue its BAF rule, even if it only issues a proposal prior to the expiration of the deferral.
The source did not rule out asking Congress -- where the industry has a lot of support -- to intervene. "We will consider all options," the source says, but adds that the most straightforward approach "is to get a clear policy out of EPA." The BPA source adds that it is already asking Congress to press the administration to issue the rule.
NAFO considers the pending high court ruling "neither here nor there" and is "neutral with respect to the question of completing this accounting framework."
If the deferral -- issued under EPA's GHG "tailoring" rule before the high court -- expires without a replacement, then that could open biomass facilities to citizen suits. "If the tailoring rule goes back into effect retroactively, some facilities will lack necessary PSD permits and if the rule goes into effect prospectively, some facilities will be subject to PSD permitting," a second NAFO source says.
Industry officials say it is imperative to provide the certainty they are seeking so that the industry can plan for future investments. "The significant uncertainty about what the rules will be for our industry, and the looming compliance deadlines, make business planning difficult," Donna Harman, president of the American Forest and Paper Association, says in a March 10 statement to Inside EPA.
And NAFO President Dave Tenny says that until EPA provides the certainty the industry is seeking, it will be difficult for the sector to join the administration's broader climate policy agenda. "EPA needs to complete its rulemaking on carbon accounting for biomass no matter what," he said.
"Doing so would remove the cloud of uncertainty over biomass energy investment, provide an option to achieve GHG emissions reductions in the various policies the administration is pursuing and remove a significant deterrent to full forest owner engagement in the president's climate action plan."
But environmentalists say they are getting no signals from EPA about its plans to move forward with a biomass rule. One source expects the agency might be waiting for the high court ruling, "but by the time they get a decision they will be right up against the time when the exemption would otherwise expire." It could be "a bit of a game of chicken."
This source adds that citizen suits against individual biomass facilities are possible, depending on how the Supreme Court rules. How to treat biomass GHG emissions is something "EPA will have to solve one way or the other. I don't think the Supreme Court gets them out of it entirely," the source notes.
Environmentalists met with EPA officials on the rule in December and outlined high-level points for what they want in the accounting rule, including no blanket exemptions for biomass from PSD applicability requirements, with biomass lifecycle analysis taking place in best available control technology reviews.
]]></text></news-item>