<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3E6C-9B4E-BE70-BCF1"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Feeling the heat over steam; Critics want a review of oilsands extraction process after Cold Lake leaks</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Originally published August 10, 2013.
COLD LAKE - In a hard hat and overalls, Canadian Natural Resources Ltd. president Steve Laut stands on a new boat launch on the edge of a marsh while behind him a fleet of watercraft are skimming an oily film off the water.
Noise cannons are booming, screeching recorded bird calls, plastic flags and decoys help keep wildlife away from this site where bitumen is leaking into the water on the company's Primrose East oilsands project near Bonnyville. It's an oddly colourful scene in the middle of muskeg and boreal forest, but the questions put to the Calgary executive this week on-site were serious.
About 80 per cent of Alberta's oilsands will be extracted by in situ methods as opposed to open pit mines. In situ (using wells and pipelines) involves injecting steam into the ground to melt the bitumen, separate it from the sand and bring it to the surface.
Some say this method is more environmentally friendly than mines that carve up the earth. So in the boreal forest here, shiny pipelines stretch many kilometres through the forest at about waist height, partly to let wildlife pass underneath. One pipe takes the steam to the well, the other brings bitumen out for shipping.
But in the wake of CNRL leaks (the second since 2009), environmentalists and First Nations are raising some red flags about the steam-injection process. They fear it may be causing fissures in the rock that allow the bitumen to ooze to the surface in the swamp and threaten groundwater.
On the four sites, the leaks are now contained and the bitumen is vacuumed up daily or weekly.
Walter Janvier, a councillor with the Cold Lake First Nations, is worried because there's no sign the leaks are slowing down, and no one knows for sure when it started or how to stop it.
While the company reported one leak site as early as May 20, the leaks probably started
in late winter or early spring, possibly when workers on a seismic line noticed something. Laut acknowledged it will just take time for the underground pressure to subside and the leaks to stop. Janvier says CNRL's high pressure, cyclical steam stimulation method should undergo a serious technical review to see if it is still appropriate.
"We are concerned about this high pressure process, as some of those wells go half a kilometre down," said Janvier, who is worried about aquifers deep underground. "It's not so much the surface spill, that can be cleaned up. But when you can't control what happens underground, that's a different story. We want an investigation that looks at all the technical data."
Janvier said he's also concerned that the company only allowed First Nations to visit this week and they were only allowed on two of the four sites (the same two media were taken to visit on Thursday).
"There's a reason for that and it's because two other sites are more damaged," said Janvier.
Janvier also pointed to a 2009 report by the provincial energy regulator that concluded there was no clear evidence to support the theory of faulty well bores in the 2009 leaks. The company should not be allowed to inject more steam until the cause is found, he added.
Laut is adamant that CNRL's high pressure steam method is viable. It's been used for 25 years with thousands of wells in the area with only a few incidents, he says. "We're very confident, we've got a lot of data right now," said Laut.
Laut said there are two layers of caprock, called Colorado shale, on top of the bitumen. The caprock cannot be cracked by the steam, but the upper layer has natural fractures.
If bitumen flows up an old well, it could reach the upper layer and then move sideways through a natural fissure, he says.
"It is physically impossible to inject steam through that caprock, we know that for certain," said Laut. "But you could have a failure in the well bore" that would allow bitumen to seep to the surface.
"Once you get into the upper Colorado, occasionally (bitumen) will hit a natural fracture and present itself to surface."
Laut said he does not disagree with the regulator's report on 2009 that cited possible geological weakness in the area. But the problem starts with a faulty well that allows bitumen to move up, not weak rock formation, he said, adding there are 8,000 in the Cold Lake area.
The company is now checking all well bores in the region and the cement casing around them, he said.
spratt@edmontonjournal.com( mailto:spratt@edmontonjournal.com )( mailto:spratt@edmontonjournal.com )
© Copyright (c) The Edmonton Journal
]]></text></news-item>