<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3EA3-33A6-1D1C-CBA6"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Fatal helicopter crash 'could have been prevented'</title><source>Scottish Express</source><author>Rod Mills</author><text><![CDATA[THE relatives of 16 men killed in a North Sea helicopter crash expressed outrage yesterday at the findings of a Fatal Accident Inquiry into their deaths.
Family and friends have waited almost five years for answers to explain why the Super Puma, operated by Bond Aviation, crashed off the coast of Peterhead on April 1, 2009.
They sat through six weeks of evidence, including a harrowing witness account of how the aircraft fell from the sky "like a torpedo", followed by its detached rotor blades.
The families were horrified to learn of the catalogue of failures in the lead-up to the crash.
And yesterday Sheriff Principal Derek Pyle, who led the inquiry, ruled that the disaster could have been prevented.
Responsible Relatives of the oil workers said they could not understand why the Crown Office decided last year that no one would be prosecuted in relation to the men's deaths.
They are now calling on the Lord Advocate to review all the evidence and reconsider charging those they believe to be responsible for the accident.
Unite Scottish Secretary Pat Rafferty branded the sheriff's determination "toothless" in its inability to to be legally enforced on what he called a "negligent employer".
Audrey Wood, of Newmachar, Aberdeenshire, whose son Stuart, 27, died in the accident, said families had been "surprised and disappointed" at the decision of the Crown Office not to proceed with prosecution and added: "How they arrived at that decision will haunt us."
John Edwards from Liverpool, who lost his 33-year-old son James, said seeing similar crashes in recent years, including that of the police helicopter that plunged into the Clutha Bar in Glasgow in November killing 10 people, had forced him to relive the pain of his loss.
Sheriff Pyle found that Bond Aviation could have taken "reasonable precautions" to prevent the accident, after potentially serious problems were twice flagged up on the aircraft's flight safety monitoring system. Metal particles were detected on a gearbox part the week before the disaster, and multiple epicyclic chip detection warnings were recorded on the Health and Usage Monitoring Systems (HUMS) on March 24 and March 25. Bond staff also discovered a metallic particle in the epicyclic module of the gearbox on March 25.
But a communication error between maintenance staff and the helicopter manufacturers meant a referral to a maintenance manual was not made and the helicopter went back into service with a gearbox part that could lead to a crash.
Bond said mistakes had been made through "honest confusion" but added: "Lessons needed to be learned, lessons have been learned and lessons continue to be learned."
The Crown Office said the findings had not changed the decision not to prosecute, as it would have to prove the case "beyond reasonable doubt". ?FOUR people are feared dead after a WestlandAgusta AW139 helicopter crashed in fog at Gillingham in Norfolk last night. The aircraft belonged to Haughey Aviation, owned by Northern Ireland's richest man, Sir Edward Haughey, 70.
The crash site is near Gillingham Hall, which is jointly owned by Sir Edward and a trust.
Sir Edward is head of veterinary pharmaceutical giant Norbrook Laboratories.
An ambulance service spokesman said calls started coming in at 7.45pm.
He added: "Sadly, it is believed that four people in the helicopter are believed to have died in the crash."
]]></text></news-item>