<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="3F04-34BC-0577-630C"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Wall St club under scrutiny; Washington</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>John Kehoe AFR correspondent</author><text><![CDATA[In America's capital, it is known as the revolving door. The seamless transition of executives from Wall Street's big banks to influential positions in the White House and important government jobs. The crossover is frequent and the movement is happening in both directions.
President Barack Obama's nomination as US Federal Reserve vice-chairman, Stanley Fischer, came under stern questioning at the Senate banking committee on Thursday, about being part of the club. Mr Fischer is the latest former senior Citigroup executive to be appointed by President Obama.
The bank received a $US45 billion bailout from US taxpayers at the height of the global financial crisis in 2008.
Many believe the "too big to fail" problem, whereby banks rely on government underwriting to survive a crisis, still exists in the US today.
Other former Citi executives serving in the Obama administration include Treasury Secretary Jack Lew, US Trade Representative Michael Froman and senior Treasury officials Marisa Lago and Nathan Sheets.
Mr Obama's former budget adviser, Peter Orszag, left the administration to join Citi in 2010, and former Treasury secretary Larry Summers held a consulting position at Citi after leaving government. Mr Summers' perceived close ties to Wall Street ultimately cost him becoming Fed chairman, after a Democrat uprising forced him to withdraw from the race against Janet Yellen.
Citi is not the only Wall Street bank to infiltrate Washington, but its alumni currently make it the most prominently represented bank in the upper echelons of the Obama administration.'Dangerous' connection
Democrat Senator Elizabeth Ann Warren, a former Harvard Law School academic specialising in bankruptcy law, said at Dr Fischer's confirmation hearing that it was "dangerous if our government falls under a tight-knit group connected to one institution".
"Former colleagues get access through calls and meetings, economic policy can be dominated by group think, other qualified and innovative people can be crowded out of top government positions," she said.
Mr Obama has enacted rules preventing presidential appointees working on matters directly related to a former employer for two years after taking a government job.Fischer stresses financial experience
Dr Fischer, who served more recently as the governor of the Bank of Israel until last June, admitted there was "obviously something to be worried about". But he said private sector experience, particularly in finance, can assist in government.
"My three years at Citigroup were the most important element that enabled me to be an effective supervisor of banks, which was one of my duties as governor of the Bank of Israel," Dr Fischer said. "Without that experience I would have come to it with largely an academic background, without ever having seen the inside of a bank or having worked in the private sector."
To be fair to Dr Fischer, he is not generally considered a prime problem example of the revolving door. He left Citi in 2005 before the crisis hit and his long-term interest in public policy is evident by his previous role as deputy managing director at the International Monetary Fund. But more broadly, many are questioning the close links between Wall Street and Washington.
Most financial institutions under scrutiny have been involved in money laundering, tax dodging, market rigging and unnecessary risk taking, and fined billions by regulators.
Mike Mayo, who began his career as a bank supervisor at the Fed before working as a bank analyst at Wall Street firms UBS, Lehman Brothers, Credit Suisse and Deutsche Bank, said he was concerned about the revolving door between the public and private sector.
He cites examples of former senior Fed colleagues being lured to bail out insurer AIG and the failed Bear Stearns.
"These people could not be blamed for wanting to make more money," he says in his book Exile on Wall Street. "But to me these moves made the Fed's Men of Silver appear merely mortal."
He suggests the trend of poachers turned gamekeepers creates an incentive for regulators to be too lenient on banks, in the belief it may improve their job prospects in the private sector.
]]></text></news-item>