<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4044-66BC-DD05-3CD7"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>US Contract Notice: Department of the Interior, Issues Solicitation for "Z--Mount Rushmore WW Clarifier Tank Clean and Paint"</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Department of the Interior, National Park Service Officer has issued requirement for "Z--Mount Rushmore WW Clarifier Tank Clean and Paint"
Solicitation no: P14PS00566 Posted on: Mar 13, 2014
Notice Type: Presolicitation
The NAICS code number for this requirement: 238320
Description: The National Park Service, Midwest Region, NEKOTA Major Acquisition Buying Office, intends to issue a Request for Proposals RFP to solicit a construction requirement for Mount Rushmore National Memorial. Work will consist of providing all labor, qualified supervision, material, tools, equipment, supplies, and incidentals to necessary to perform total coating rehabilitation of one clarifier tank as specified in a formal RFP that will follow. The clarifier tank stripping, surface treatment and painting project work shall be completed using full containment to control dust from abrasive blasting and overspray. The tank is approximately 21 feet in diameter and 20 feet deep. The contractor will also be responsible for subcontracting daily hauling and disposal of waste water captured while the construction project is underway. SOLICITATION NUMBER P14PS00566 Request for Proposal, TYPE OF CONTRACT This will be a firm-fixed price construction contract and expected to be awarded to a prime contractor in early-May, 2014. It is anticipated that due to heavy visitation, work on this project will not commence until late in September, 2014. Davis Bacon Prevailing Wages for Pennington County, South Dakota will apply, MAGNITUDE OF PROJECT Between $25,000 and $100,000, NAICS CODE CLASSIFICATION and SET ASIDE The North American Industry Classification System (NAICS) Code is 238320, and the size standard is $14 million. This project is set aside 100% for Small Businesses, SITE VISIT A site visit date, time, and meeting location will be announced in the solicitation. Offerors are highly encouraged to attend the scheduled site visit, to inspect the site, and to ensure they fully understand the requirement and conditions that may affect the cost of the project, specifications, and performance PUBLICIZING The official solicitation package (RFP) and its attachments will be issued and available on or about April 3, 2014 and will be posted to the Federal Business Opportunities (FBO) website at https://www.fbo.gov. The contracting office will not provide hardcopies or email copies of the solicitation REGISTRATION All offerors must have a DUNS number, be registered and active in the System for Award Management SAM, and have completed their Online Representations and Certifications, in order to be awarded a contract http://www.sam.gov. POINT OF CONTACT: Ron Kesterson, Contract Specialist, ron_kesterson@nps.gov, 605-574-3183.
Set Aside: Total Small Business
Deadline for All responses: N/A
Point of Contact(s): Ronald Kesterson
For more information visit: https://www.fbo.gov/index?s=opportunity&mode=form&id=dd14c8a224ba891ccda7493661945f0b&tab=core&_cview=0. In case of any query regarding this article or other content needs please contact: editorial@plusmediasolutions.com
]]></text></news-item>