<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="412C-1549-CD4D-613A"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Five Egyptian soldiers killed in militant attack on military checkpoint</title><source>Kuwait News Agency (KUNA)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[| CAIRO, March 15 (KUNA) -- Five Egyptian soldiers were killed in a militant attack on a military police checkpoint in the northern Cairo suburb of Shubra Al-Kheima early Saturday.
In a statement on his Facebook page, the Army Spokesman Colonel Ahmad Mohammad Ali confirmed the attack and the deaths. Ali also accused the Muslim Brotherhood group of perpetrating it.
"An armed group belonging to the terrorist Muslim Brotherhood attacked a military police checkpoint, leading to the martyrdom of five conscripts," Ali wrote.
He added that the militants opened the fire on the soldiers who were about to finish their morning prayers and they also planted two bombs at the checkpoint to target expected reinforcements.
He expressed the Army's deep condolences over the deaths and sincere sympathy with the relatives of the victims.
Ali vowed that the army would continue its fight against terrorist groups in the country.
For his part, Prime Minister Ibrahim Mehlib also voiced his cabinet's condolences to the death of the soldiers.
He promised that relevant authorities will do all in power to bring perpetrators to justice and to put an end to terrorism in Egypt.
Egypt's Mufti Shawqi Allam condemned the cowardly criminal attack on the military checkpoint.
The attack came two days after gunmen riding a motorcycle opened fire on an army bus in Cairo killing an officer and injuring three others.
Over 200 police and army personnel were killed in militant attacks across the country since the army ouster of Islamist president Mohamed Morsi in July. Many of the attacks were claimed by a Sinai-based Jihadist group as revenge to the army and police killing of over 1400 of Morsi supporters since July. (end) rg.ibi KUNA 151315 Mar 14NNNN
]]></text></news-item>