<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="413A-2AB8-3634-5CE8"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Around the world</title><source>The Sunday Star-Times (Auckland, New Zealand)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[UNITED STATES
Cleanup continues
The bodies of eight people reported missing have been found and identified at the site of a deadly gas explosion that levelled two New York City apartment buildings, although the rescue operation will continue in case there are unknown survivors still in the rubble, the city's fire commissioner says. Detectives and fire marshals hope to be able to access the basements of the buildings to begin their investigation into what caused the blast. More than 60 people were injured when the explosion on Thursday destroyed the two five-storey East Harlem buildings, which were served by an 1887 cast-iron gas main.
THAILAND
Refugees rescued
Thai police have rescued about 200 people believed to be Chinese Muslim Uighurs from a human smuggling camp in southern Thailand, in the latest crackdown on a burgeoning trafficking network in Southeast Asia. More than 800 people have been freed from human traffickers since a media investigation exposed the whereabouts of the illegal camps in December.
MEXICO
Last message
A Salvadoran fisherman who says he spent 13 months adrift in the Pacific has arrived in Mexico ready to meet the family of a young companion who died early in the voyage. Jose Salvador Alvarenga said he promised Ezequiel Cordoba that he would give a message before Cordoba died about a month into the ordeal. Alvarenga's boat washed up in the Marshall Islands in February.
FRANCE
Genocide sentence
A Paris court yesterday delivered France's first-ever conviction for genocide, sentencing a Rwandan former intelligence chief to 25 years in prison over the 1994 killings of at least 500,000 people in the African country. The landmark trial of 54-year-old Pascal Simbikangwa sets off what could be the first of dozens of French trials into one of the 20th century's greatest atrocities .
UNITED STATES
A kiss is still a kiss
A man who became well known for claiming he was the American sailor kissing a woman in Times Square in a famous World War II-era photo taken by a Life magazine photographer has died. Glenn McDuffie, 86, has died in a nursing home in Dallas, his daughter Glenda Bell said. McDuffie became a mailman and semi-professional baseball player after he returned from World War II, but his life became more exciting about six years ago when a Houston Police forensic artist was able to identify him as the young man in the photo. This kicked off a whirlwind lifestyle of going to air shows, gun shows, and parties to tell his story. Women would pay US$10 to have a photo of them kissing McDuffie on the cheek.
--------------------
CAPTION:
Picture: Reuters
]]></text></news-item>