<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="41A1-6FCA-D9B3-CAC6"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Drinking water sampling rigged; Workers say they were under orders not to bring back samples with too-low levels of chlorine, which can allow bacterial growth in the water. . Low levels of chlorine can indicate bacteria in the water.</title><source>Palm Beach Post (Florida)</source><author> By Joel Engelhardt   Palm Beach Post Staff Writer </author><text><![CDATA[City workers have been under orders to collect water samples in a way that violates industry practices meant to assure safe, clean drinking water, The Palm Beach Post has learned.
Workers who asked to remain anonymous because they fear for their jobs told The Post they are instructed to never bring back a sample low in chlorine, which fights bacteria.
If the initial reading is below a minimum level, the workers flush water out of the pipe until they get a better reading. The action reduces the chance that harmful bacteria will be found when the samples are tested in the lab.
The practice came to a head in late January when, workers say in an internal complaint, a supervisor told a technician sampling near Baywinds on Okeechobee Boulevard to discard a sample after he had recorded it. He refused.
The Palm Beach County Health Department, which monitors city drinking water under a 10-year consent decree, is investigating the sampling methods. Department officials say there's no indication West Palm Beach's drinking water is unsafe.
City officials, who forwarded the complaint to the health department on Feb. 13, are mum, awaiting the results of the investigation.
Health concerns about the city water system, which serves more than 100,000 customers in West Palm Beach, Palm Beach and South Palm Beach, harken back to 2007, when bacteria in the water supply forced restaurants to close and residents to boil water for 10 days. A month later, authorities determined that the contamination originated in the city's treatment plant.
The city settled a wrongful termination suit last year and rehired an employee who said she had been told to falsify records of bacterial content in water samples before the 2007 outbreak.
The city has paid the health department $80,000 a year to monitor its water treatment procedures under the consent decree and has made improvements, health department director Dr. Alina Alonso said in a statement.
"Although we are conducting a review," she said, "we have not seen anything that would have compromised the water quality."
Flush, then sample
The health department is investigating whether samples were manipulated for better results, samples were destroyed and records were altered to remove references to destroyed samples, a questionnaire given to city workers says.
Here's how employees say the samples were manipulated:
Workers in the field flush the line for 10 minutes before taking an initial sample to determine the chlorine level. Other utilities flush for a shorter period, but the city's written protocol allows 10 minutes.
Workers say it would not be unusual for the chlorine level to be low, particularly at outlying locations, such as Baywinds, Ibis off Northlake Boulevard and South Palm Beach. In that case, they continue flushing, sometimes for up to 45 minutes until new water entering the pipe raises the sample's chlorine level.
The outlying locations are at the end-point of water mains and are a long distance from the city's downtown water treatment plant, where initial doses of chlorine are added to the water.
Chlorine levels naturally drop as water flows through pipes after treatment. The city boosts chlorine levels at pump stations along the way. Water treatment plant workers also flush regularly to move water through stagnant pipes so that bacteria does not grow.
The readings help determine how much chlorine they add and how often they flush the lines.
But the lab techs gathering water samples are not supposed to let the remedy -- flushing -- influence the testing, industry experts say.
In West Palm Beach, workers say -- and documents support them -- they do.
"You should flush more when there's a problem. But you should also know what's in that line to know there's that problem," said Jeff Poteet, president of the Florida Water and Pollution Control Operators Association and utilities director in Marco Island.
Bring a book to read
Workers made note of flush times greater than 10 minutes on several official documents since at least September. But they didn't always write them down, they said, because it was so common.
In September and again in October a worker noted flushing for 30 minutes when the initial sample did not meet the minimum chlorine level.
In December, a supervisor scrawled "FLUSH!" beneath a map of a testing site in Baywinds along with instructions on which samples to take first.
In February, a worker sampling at Baywinds wrote that after flushing for 45 minutes the chlorine reading still stood below the acceptable standard of 0.6 milligrams per liter. He turned in that sample.
Workers said they also flushed water lines and fire hydrants before taking samples in places where residents had complained about drinking water color, odor or taste.
The field workers would spend so much time flushing that one worker said he had been instructed to bring a book to read while he waited.
Testing for bacteria
On Jan. 24, a worker taking samples at Baywinds flushed for 10 minutes and encountered a low chlorine reading, 0.4. He wrote on a document meant to assure an unbroken chain of custody between sample and lab that he flushed the line for an additional 20 minutes. That pushed the reading up to 0.6, the minimum acceptable.
From there, he would take the sample to the lab, where it would be tested for harmful bacteria, a test that takes 24 hours. If bacteria indicating fecal coliform were found, lab workers would return to the site for more testing and a boil-water order may be needed.
But in this case, the worker said, his supervisor told him to discard the sample and go back for a new one -- after another worker flushed the line for a few hours. He refused.
The dispute turned out to be unnecessary: The sample came back the next day negative for bacteria.
But fearing he would face backlash for insubordination, the worker wrote in a complaint, he informed the department's quality control officer.
Two weeks later, the city issued a "corrective action." Without naming the worker, it described a worker asking the quality control officer about the correct flushing time. It recommended "more sampling training is needed for better understanding."
Discarding samples or intentionally watering them down may be criminal behaviors, said Jerry Phillips, a former Florida Department of Environmental Protection attorney who directs the Florida chapter of Public Employees for Environmental Responsibility.
"If the city is intentionally violating environmental regulations, then yes, they are committing criminal offenses," Phillips said. "Regulations are there for a purpose. They are there to protect the health, safety and welfare of the public."
Meantime, city lab workers and supervisors had been divided over workplace issues. One lab worker raised an overtime pay issue in December. The departure of a co-worker prompted an investigation by the city's Human Resources Department. In February, a worker complained that a supervisor made a racially charged comment.
The lab technicians filed a formal complaint over the workplace issues, including the Jan. 24 incident, on Feb. 12.
The next day, the city notified the health department, prompting its investigation. The employee complaints are being investigated by an outside attorney hired by the city.
Two of the three lab workers who collected water samples in the field have been reassigned.
Their work is now being done by water treatment plant operators, including the workers whose duties include flushing water lines and hydrants.
jengelhardt@pbpost.com Twitter: @JoelEpbpost
what the post found
Workers taking water samples to test for bacteria in the West Palm Beach water supply, which serves 100,000 customers in West Palm, Palm Beach and South Palm Beach, routinely go beyond protocol to get best results.
]]></text></news-item>