<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4205-53AF-A428-9B05"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Judge approves Ricardo's sex harassment case settlement</title><source>Erie Times-News (Pennsylvania)</source><author>Lisa Thompson, Erie Times-News, Pa.</author><text><![CDATA[March 15--U.S. Magistrate Judge Susan Paradise Baxter has given final approval to a proposed settlement that resolves a federal agency's claims that the co-owner of Ricardo's Restaurant Inc. subjected female employees to a sexually hostile work environment.
Under the agreement with the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, Ricardo's, 2112 East Lake Road, has agreed to pay a former worker $20,000 and take several measures to safeguard against future sexual harassment.
Ricardo's is barred from sexual discrimination. It may not retaliate against any female employees who have filed sexual discrimination or harassment complaints or those who took part in any investigations of illegal practices. Managers, owners, supervisors and employees must undergo legal training about sexual harassment.
The EEOC, the federal agency that enforces anti-discrimination employment laws, filed the complaint in July on behalf of a former employee, Dorothy Hannah, who resigned amid alleged sexual harassment, and other female workers who were affected by the restaurant's alleged practices.
The lawsuit focused on the conduct of co-owner Peter West, who continues to deny any wrongdoing.
"The requirements of this settlement were carefully designed to protect all employees at the restaurant from harassment or retaliation," said Regional Attorney Debra M. Lawrence of the EEOC's Philadelphia district office.
EEOC District Director Spencer H. Lewis Jr. added, "The EEOC receives many sexual harassment charges against restaurants. This settlement should remind all restaurant owners and managers that EEOC will take action, including litigation, when appropriate, to stop this kind of misconduct."
Arthur Martinucci, the lawyer for Ricardo's, countered that the settlement was a "business decision."
"The amount of the settlement is a small fraction of what had been demanded by the government before the lawsuit was filed. The idea that this constitutes a victory for the government is simply wrong," he said.
He stressed it contains no admission of wrongdoing or liability. "There was no sexual harassment of Ms. Hannah or of other female employees," he said.
Martinucci said that while state and federal law appropriately bar harassment based on gender, race, creed and other features, "these laws are not a general workplace civility code."
"'Rough' language is not an uncommon thing in many workplaces these days, and anyone who has watched an episode of 'Kitchen Nightmares,' 'Restaurant Impossible' or the like, knows that this is especially true in the food service industry," Martinucci said.
He said the EEOC's lawsuit highlighted for Ricardo's "the need to have appropriate policies and training in those policies, for employees at all levels of the workforce."
LISA THOMPSON can be reached at 870-1802 or by e-mail. Follow her on Twitter at twitter.com/ETNthompson.
___ (c)2014 the Erie Times-News (Erie, Pa.) Visit the Erie Times-News (Erie, Pa.) at www.GoErie.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>