<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4291-594B-9897-74FD"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Washington: SPEECH OF HON. RODNEY P. FRELINGHUYSEN OF NEW JERSEY IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES FRIDAY, MARCH 14, 2014</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Library of Congress, The Government of USA has issued the following Speech:
Mr. FRELINGHUYSEN. Mr. Speaker, I rise today to honor the Market Street Mission located in Morris County, New Jersey, as it celebrates its 125th Anniversary.
The Market Street Mission ministers to those who suffer in the battle against alcoholism, drug abuse, and homelessness in the northern New Jersey area. The Mission provides its ministries through physical, emotional, and spiritual support that will guide those who suffer toward responsible and productive lives.
Established in 1889 by the Reverend Dr. F.W. Owen and his wife, Mrs. Louisa Graves Owen, the Market Street Mission began as a residential program for alcoholic husbands in the Morristown area. With support from the South Street Presbyterian Church, the Mission provided meals, lodging, clothing, and temporary employment for homeless men. Throughout its first decade, the Mission started support meetings and programs for the homeless and drug addicted.
In 1926, a series of explosions at the Picatinny Arsenal left many families homeless and without food or clothes. The Mission was able to help these displaced families by providing them with shelter and other basic necessities.
During the Great Depression, the Market Street Mission ended its affiliation with the Presbyterian Church and added the ``Industrial Department,'' a self-supporting thrift store that provided jobs during difficult economic times.
Today, residents of the Mission continue to work at the Industrial Department as part of the successful ``New Reality of Recovery'' program, as well as attend chapel and classes. The Market Street Mission has added an Emergency Assistance program that provides meals and lodging for disadvantaged men, women, and children. In addition to its growing development thoughout the years, the Mission continues to focus on alcohol and drug treatment programs, incorporating new treatments each year.
The Market Street Mission is proud to celebrate its history and looks forward to its continuous growth in the future.
Mr. Speaker, I urge you and my colleagues to join me in congratulating the Market Street Mission and their dedicated employees as they celebrate 125 years of serving the northern New Jersey community.
For more information please visit: http://thomas.loc.gov/
]]></text></news-item>