<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="42DC-C080-47EE-BCE4"><date>2014-03-15</date><title></title><source>Cape Argus (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[HARARE: Zimbabwe's President Robert Mugabe has vowed to crack down on corruption involving high-profile officials at state institutions following recent damning exposures of graft, including at the national airline. "If there was any corruption, people will answer for it, I tell you," Mugabe said at a belated party hosted yesterday by civil servants and security forces to celebrate his 90th birthday. "It has ruined the country," said Mugabe describing corruption as a "growing disease".
KINSHASA: The World Bank is likely to approve $73 million (R783m) next week to fund an expansion of the Inga hydroelectric dam in Democratic Republic of Congo, a bank official said. The decision will be a relief to investors, particularly mining companies, which have been threatened with electricity rationing due to a lack of power generation, but environmentalists say the impact of the project has not been properly evaluated.
HAT YAI, Thailand: Police have rescued about 200 suspected Muslim Uighurs from a human smuggling camp in southern Thailand, bringing the number freed from human traffickers to well over 800 since the camps were exposed in December. At least 200 of them were Bangladeshis. The rest were Rohingya, mostly stateless Muslims from western Burma, where clashes with ethnic Rakhine Buddhists in 2012 killed at least 192 people and left 140 000 homeless.
BEIJING: A Chinese human rights activist died yesterday after falling critically ill in detention after police denied her medical treatment for months, her brother said. "Her body was weak; she was sent to the hospital too late," Cao Shunli's brother Cao Yunli said. "The police are responsible." Amnesty International condemned Chinese authorities over the death of the 52 year old, saying they had "blood on their hands." Cao had been detained since September.
PARIS: France has accused the EU of shirking its responsibilities for international security after an EU plan to send up to 1 000 troops to Central African Republic next week seemed close to collapse. They were to join African and French troops, who have struggled to stop fighting that started a year ago when mostly Muslim Seleka rebels seized power in the majority Christian state. The plan was in jeopardy because European governments had not provided the soldiers and equipment they promised.
BAMAKO: French air strikes in northern Mali have killed militant Oumar Ould Hamaha, a jihadist with a $3 million (R32m) US government bounty on his head, Malian military sources said. Hamaha, known as "Red Beard" because of his henna-dyed whiskers, was a leading figure in the coalition that seized control of northern Mali in 2012. He was a former member of al-Qaeda's north African wing.
TOKYO: The Nobel Prize-winning head of a Japanese institute whose scientists' work on stem cells was hailed as a game-changer in the field of medical biology has called the lead researcher's handling of data "sloppy" and "irresponsible". "The problem here is one immature researcher collected a huge amount of research data and her handling of data was extremely sloppy and irresponsible," president of Japanese research institute Riken Ryoji Noyori said yesterday.
]]></text></news-item>