<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4329-3F87-79BE-642C"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>SEX TRADE IN S.D. WORTH $97M IN 2007, INSTITUTE SAYS; Local link to gangs key finding in report on illicit industries</title><source>The San Diego Union-Tribune</source><author>DANA LITTLEFIELD, U-T</author><text><![CDATA[SAN DIEGO
Pimping, prostitution and other forms of human trafficking were big business in San Diego in 2007, generating an estimated $97 million, according to a new study that shed light on the inner workings and economy of the sex trade.
The landmark study by the Urban Institute examined what it referred to as the “underground commercial sex economy” in San Diego and seven other cities: Atlanta; Dallas; Denver; Kansas City, Mo.; Seattle; Miami; and Washington, D.C.
According to the study:
•?Prices for acts of prostitution in San Diego range from $40 to $200 on the street to several hundred or even several thousand dollars for escort services. They average $150 an hour in the cities studied.
•?The operating income of pimps in San Diego was estimated at $11,129 a week.
•?The size of San Diego’s illicit sex business is less than half that of Miami’s and smaller than those trades in Atlanta and Washington, D.C.
•?Much of the sex trade in San Diego — in the streets and online — is dominated by gangs.
The local link to gangs was one of the report’s key local findings.
“These pimps tend to network with one another,” said Meredith Dank of the Washington D.C.-based Urban Institute and lead author of the report.
“They look at each other as partners rather than business competitors, which was something of a surprise to us,” Dank said. “They view themselves as entrepreneurs… and in some cases have business models.”
The U.S. Department of Justice commissioned and funded the study to get a handle on the economic side of the sex trade. In each location, researchers collected economic data and conducted interviews to estimate the size of the illicit economy as of 2007, and to try to understand its structure.
While focused on the sex trade, the report also touched on the value of the illegal drugs and guns markets. The $97 million spent in San Diego’s sex trade was said to be slightly higher than the underground market for illegal drugs and twice that of guns.
Researchers interviewed 18 people in San Diego, including representatives from the FBI, the county sheriff’s and city police departments and the Internal Revenue Service. Some former pimps were interviewed in prison.
What they found confirmed what many authorities knew anecdotally, while debunking a few persistent myths.
Mary-Ellen Barrett, a prosecutor in the district attorney’s sex crimes and human trafficking division, said some still believe that pimps and the women they lure into the sex trade are willing partners who both benefit from the endeavor.
“It’s not ‘Pretty Woman,’?” Barrett said, referring to the movie in which a prostitute falls in love — and presumably lives happily ever after — with a wealthy customer. “No guy is (showing up) in a limo,” she continued. “The girls aren’t out there because they’re oversexed. It’s all about the money.”
According to the study, the sex trade economy ranged from nearly $40 million to $290 million in the eight target cities, and decreased in five of those locations — including San Diego — from 2003 to 2007.
“It is a real industry; it does have some economic impact,” said Kelly Cunningham, an economist at the National University System Institute for Policy Research.
He acknowledged the difficulty in attempting to gauge the economic impact of an underground industry, particularly one for which there was such a small data sample, but said the methodology used in this study seemed to be a valid approach.
“I think this is a good start and it gives us an idea as to what this underground industry is,” he said.
San Diego’s underground sex economy, which includes street and online prostitution, residential brothels, massage parlors and escort services, has more gang involvement in the sex trade than the other locations that were studied.
Gangs dominated both the street and online markets, and operated sex trafficking rings that spanned several cities and states, the study reported. Gangsters as young as 16 found that recruiting their underage classmates into the sex trade is a much less risky way to make money than trafficking drugs and guns.
The study also noted that some gangs were formed solely for pimping and prostitution, and often included members from rival groups.
Robert Howe, assistant special agent in charge of the San Diego FBI office, said websites are set up so the women appear to be independent brokers, which helps insulate the pimps from law enforcement. Moving women between cities and across states keeps them dependent on their handlers.
Howe said gang members know that investigators are constrained by certain rules and they use that to their advantage.
“They have a business model that works and they seem to be just one step ahead (of law enforcement) because of the freedoms they enjoy,” Howe said.
He said local authorities have noticed in recent years that local gangs are moving away from drug sales and focusing their moneymaking activities increasingly on pimping and prostitution.
“The profit margin is just so much higher in the sex trade,” Howe said.
In January, the U.S. Attorney’s Office announced that members of two North Park gangs had been indicted in a racketeering case in which the defendants are accused of luring women into prostitution and selling sex in 23 states.
Susan Munsey, executive director of GenerateHope in San Diego, which provides shelter for human trafficking victims, said many women and girls find themselves in the sex trade after they become involved in romantic relationships with men. She called it “boyfriending.”
Eventually, the pimps put the women to work and even persuade them to recruit others into the business. The report noted how pimps often use physical violence to keep the prostitutes in line.
“Every woman that I’ve known that has been trafficked has been beaten brutally,” Munsey said. She said they usually experience some form of post-traumatic stress disorder.
The study also found that child pornography is an escalating problem, aided by the prevalence of online communities that trade photos, videos and other media.
Howe said there are three FBI-led task forces in San Diego County that focus on violent crime and other criminal activity, including human trafficking. There’s also a child-exploitation task force that targets sex crimes against children on the street and online.
The authors of the study made several recommendations based on their findings, including additional resources for law enforcement, and the expansion of state laws to allow wiretaps in human trafficking investigations.
dana.littlefield@utsandiego.com (619) 293-1287 Twitter: @danalittlefield
]]></text></news-item>