<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="432D-1C25-082D-EE29"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>INTERVIEW WITH DUSAN KORUNOSKI, SECRETARY-GENERAL, SERBIAN ASSOCIATION OF EMPLOYERS : "SERBIA'S POLITICIANS IMAGINE JOBS FOR THEMSELVES IN THE COMMISSION"</title><source>Europolitics (daily in English)</source><author>Markus Bernath</author><text><![CDATA[Highly critical of the political class in his country, Dusan Korunoski, secretary-general of the Serbian Association of Employers (SAE-UPS, Unija poslodavaca Srbije, the country's oldest entrepreneurs' association - www.poslodavci.rs), sets hopes on the European Commission and on the ambassadors of the EU countries in Belgrade in order to keep the next government on a path of austerity and reform. "We are on the verge of bankruptcy," Korunoski states in an interview with Europolitics on the eve of the 16 March parliamentary elections.
Serbia has just started accession negotiations with the EU, but at the same time it wants to follow an austerity programme until 2016 and faces a gloomy economic outlook for this year. How will that work out?
We will go fast through these negotiations, this is my impression. The austerity programme will not affect them. The majority of the citizens wants to join the European Union, and so do the Serbian politicians. Their motives are very obvious. They have their own future in mind and imagine jobs for themselves in the European Commission and in Parliament with high wages. Our concern, as representatives of the employers, is that the national delegation will opt for speed instead of quality of the accession negotiations. We cannot afford to pay for even more administration that would deal with the implementation of the EU acquis; we are on the verge of bankruptcy. There are also a number of sectors where the liberalisation of the market should go at a slower pace, especially in agriculture, an undeveloped sector. Without protection by the state, the situation of the producers could become even worse then it is now.
Are the Serbs ready to vote for a government whose financial consolidation policy would mean job losses and painful cuts?
Austerity is unavoidable in Serbia. We have these elections because the Progressive Party of Deputy Prime Minister Aleksandar Vucic sees the chance to get a majority on its own. He wants to secure this majority before implementing some kind of austerity programme. We hope that the EU and the ambassadors of the EU countries continue to urge the government to not deviate from that path. Now the Serbs seem to have found themselves a new leader in the person of Mr Vucic. They will therefore accept his austerity measures - at least for a while. There are figures claiming that up to 50% of GDP in Serbia stems from the public sector. It would mean that only Belarus is ahead of us in that respect. Some here call it "wild Socialism".
The reform of the labour law has just failed. The government, including Deputy Prime Minister Vucic, withdrew the draft. What will happen now with this key reform?
I was a member of the commission which was working out the amendments to the labour law, and I gave up after some months. The trade unions were sabotaging this process, the Progressive Party finished by dismissing its Minister of Economy, Sasha Radulovic, in January. After the elections, the picture might be different. The trade unions may have to swallow much more radical changes in the labour law. We have restarted negotiations anyway already and are meeting every week. The idea is to have a new draft by June.
There are a number of provisions in the current labour law that also bother investors from the EU: you get two days off if you donate blood as an employee of a public company, for example. Or severance pay that is calculated not on the basis of years worked in the company but on the total amount of years of your professional life.
Serbia ranks 72nd in the perceived corruption index of Transparency International of 177 countries. Whose fault is it?
Seventy-two is too good an estimate. This index only shows perceived corruption. We in business know that nothing can be done in Serbia without paying money on the side. The only institution that survived Socialism in this country is bureaucracy. Bureaucrats are now in charge, and this without any accountability. Once I was asked to pay money for a public tender I applied for and that I won. I refused, and tenders were called three more times as I, as the only domestic bidder, was always the cheapest and leading the shortlist. In the end, a European company was accepted; investors from EU countries can afford paying bribes.
Since 2007, Serbia receives each year some EUR200 million from Instrument for Pre-Accession Assistance (IPA) funds. What did this change for the private sector in the country?
Same problem. If you apply for projects funded by IPA in Serbia, corruption comes first. We as the Serbian Association of Employers were facing it before, we will face it again. It is similar to the Apex credits [a credit facility offered by the European Investment Bank to small and medium-sized enterprises - Ed]. Normally, the interest rates for Apex credits are 1% or 1.5%. In reality, however, I cannot get these credits below 6%, because in between these loans and my enterprise stand banks, which are, of course, in good relations with politicians. They take percentages off every loan and distribute loans with better conditions to their favourite company bosses.
]]></text></news-item>