<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4334-FF89-E0BD-3BA7"><date>2014-03-10</date><title>Ei Towers falls for a second consecutive day, a two-day fall of 1.2%</title><source>News Bites - Western Europe: Italy</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Ei Towers SpA (MI:EIT) fell 20.0c (or 0.5%) for a second consecutive day on Monday bringing its two-day fall to 47.0c or 1.2%. The stock last traded at EUR40.04. Compared with the FTSE MIB Index which fell 52.2 points (or 0.25%) in the two days, this represented a relative price change of -0.9%. The volume was 0.3 times the average trading of 39,528 shares.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Ei Towers, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051181650314114
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- The stock's relative price strength percentile is falling at 63 for 6 months, 55 for 3 months and 37 for 1 month.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Dividend yield of 1% [2.6%].
Bullish Signals- The 2.2% discount to 12-month high of EUR40.95 against the 88.8% premium to 12-month low of EUR21.21 suggests the stock continues to push for new highs. - In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week high thirteen times, pointing to a significant uptrend. - The present value of EUR1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Ei Towers is EUR1,806, including a capital gain of EUR780 and dividend reinvested of EUR26.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Sales of 0.5 [0.5]. - Return on Capital Employed 6.7% [3.0%].- Price to EBITDA of 1.2 [6.2].Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 3.5 is comfortably below 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 19.2%. - Interest cover defined by EBIT/I is 6.8 times. This indicates it is less leveraged. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.1. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued and ranks in the top 4% of stock by value of Q Ratio.- Net Profit margin is positive and has seen consecutive rises in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]
- EBIT margin and EBITDA margin are positive and have seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 11,782 shares worth EUR471,751 (US$654,413) traded. Beta: the Beta of Ei Towers stock is 0.4. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 27: Ei Towers: Board of Directors' meeting 26 february 2014 - Share buy backsThe Board of Directors of EI Towers will ask the forthcoming Annual General Meeting to renew authorisation to effect share buy backs, in line with the provisions of Article. 132 of the Consolidated Law on Finance, and Articles 73, 144-bis and A in outline in Annex 3 n. 4 of Consob resolution no.
January 08: Ei Towers: Financial Calendar 2014http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Italy/Stock/News/78162.pdfSource: Company Website
December 20: Ei Towers director sells; shares at a two-month lowEi Towers (MI:EIT) director Anna Girello sold 830 shares worth EUR27,398 on December 19, 2013. The selling price was EUR33.01. The shares hit a two-month low on the day.
December 16: Partial demerger of subsidiary Towertel S.p.A. in favor of EI Towers S.p.A.[Company Release] EI Towers S.p.A. and its subsidiary Towertel S.p.A. signed today the deed of partial demerger of Towertel S.p.A. into EI Towers S.p.A. As already disclosed to the market, the purpose of this transaction is to concentrate the asset of TLC infrastructures/towers of EI Towers Group in Towertel, which already owns it.
November 13: Ei Towers: Publication of the 9M 2013 Interim Results[Company Release] EI Towers S.p.A. would like to inform you that the Quarterly Report as at September 30, 2013 is available to the public at the Company's Registered office, on the website www.eitowers.it, in Investors section - Financial reports, and on the website of Borsa Italiana.Source: Company Website
November 07: Ei Towers: Third Quarter 2013 results[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Italy/Stock/News/77406.pdfSource: Company Website
August 02: Ei Towers: Publication of the Half Year Report[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Italy/Stock/News/76129.pdfSource: Company Website
ISIN: IT0003043418
MI:EIT; BIT:EIT; IM:EIT
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>