<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4388-4FDC-D83A-D259"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Fracking law yields gusher of confusion</title><source>Orange County Register (California)</source><author>BY ASHER KLEIN, STAFF WRITER</author><text><![CDATA[Confusion swirling around new regulations has put a pause on fracking in Long Beach, according to state conservation officials and drilling operators.
Long Beach's offshore oil wells have been fracked for the better part of 50 years, but the requirements of a new law have brought forth reports of confusion in the oil industry.
Until the beginning of the year, oil companies were free to frack an oil well without disclosing when it was done, but regulations in Senate Bill 4, which went into effect in January, require companies to obtain permits before fracking. The process has recently come under scrutiny as potentially harmful to the environment.
"The intent of SB4 was not to put a moratorium but, so far in the first two months of the year, we have a moratorium," said Kevin Tougas, oil operations manager at the Long Beach Gas and Oil Department, which operates the oil wells in the city.
As of Thursday, 249 applications to stimulate oil wells have been filed with the state. Most were filed in Kern County, the state's biggest oil producer, and none were filed in Long Beach, where offshore fracking in California has long been concentrated, officials said.
Long Beach Gas and Oil's drilling contractor hasn't fracked since December, Tougas said, because it's unclear what SB4's new groundwater monitoring plan should take into account.
"From what I've heard, there's confusion on what they can and should be looking at. So far we haven't fracked anything this year," Tougas said.
Ten wells were fracked in Long Beach last year, said Tougas. A state Coastal Commission report delivered in February said that, since the 1990s, 195 wells have been fracked off Long Beach, with 17 more fracked in Seal Beach during the same span.
SB4 was passed in September and was intended to improve what's known publicly about hydraulic fracturing and other well-stimulation techniques, which can inject complex or toxic chemicals into the ground.
The law mandates increased notification, disclosure and monitoring of the process as well as a large-scale study of the procedure, where fluid and sand is blasted into an oil field to loosen oil and gas deposits. Until permanent regulations are created in 2015, interim regulations require groundwater monitoring, notification of an upcoming procedure and chemical disclosures for new fracks.
Rock Zierman, chief executive of the California Independent Petroleum Association, said in an email that there is a "lull in activity" since SB4 went into effect, but said that's because the law is in the early stages of implementation. He noted the Division of Oil, Gas and Geothermal Resources is "working diligently to implement the law."
Jason Marshall, chief deputy director at the California Department of Conservation, acknowledged the confusion about what the interim regulations required.
"We are working with oil and gas operators to ensure they understand the requirements and provide the required information," he said in an email.
The state Coastal Commission is apparently seeing a halt in fracking as well, although it has not required the review of fracking in state waters. Since the law's passage, commission staff members have inquired about the process with oil-well operators, said commission Deputy Director Alison Dettmer.
"We have new projects that are coming in the doors soon, new wells. We've been asking the question now, 'Are you intending to do any well-stimulation treatments?' and so far, they're telling us no," she said.
Fracking in state waters is considered much less potentially harmful than fracking in federal waters because of regulations that were already in place, Dettmer said.
Oil rigs outside of 3 miles from shore have been able to discharge fracking byproducts directly into the ocean, although the federal Environmental Protection Agency began requiring a permit for discharges as of March 1. Fracking in state waters has always required trapping liquid and gaseous byproducts.
"Anybody doing any kind of oil and gas production (in state waters) either needs to re-inject their fluids or they need to bring them onshore and treat them. That takes away a lot of concern about fracking," Dettmer said.
Environmental groups such as the Center for Biological Diversity oppose fracking, and the group actually opposed SB4 as well. Kassie Siegel, an attorney with the center, didn't think fracking in state waters was safe despite the precautions.
"You could still have a well blowout, you could still have a spill," she said.
The oil industry's use of fracking has been on the rise in the last decade, causing a heightened awareness among activists, said Cal State Long Beach professor Richard Behl.
The technique merits regulation but not a moratorium, he said, noting only a few fracking locations or depths are close to drinking-water aquifers and that other industries that use heavy metals and toxic chemicals to produce everyday household items such as televisions don't bear the brunt of environmentalists' outrage.
"I believe people are focusing on this because it's a big unknown to them and it's scary," he said. "It isn't an unknown. It just needs to be done carefully and correctly, like any other industrial process."
]]></text></news-item>