<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4408-ABE3-8544-E38B"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Denso drops 2.0%</title><source>Global Round Up - ADRs and Depository Receipts</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ADRS AND DEPOSITORY RECEIPTS
Unsponsored Denso Corporation (formerly: Nippondenso Co Ltd) (OT:DNZOY), the ADR market's 2nd largest auto parts & equipment company by market capitalisation, dropped 51.0c (or 2.0%) to close at US$24.74. Compared with the Bank of New York Mellon Composite ADR Index which fell 0.3 points (or 0.2%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -1.8%. The volume was 0.7 times the average trading of 22,207 ADRs. The ADR fell for a fifth consecutive day on Friday.
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- The ADR dropped on thin volume falling for a fifth consecutive day.- The ADR dropped to a three-month low.- The Moving Average Convergence Divergence (MACD) indicator of 12-day Exponential Moving Average (EMA) of 25.71 minus the 26-day EMA of 25.98 is negative 0.27 suggesting a bearish signal. Both EMA prices are falling, another bearish signal.

Bullish Signals- The present value of US$1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in Denso is US$1,207, including a capital gain of US$189 and dividend reinvested of US$17.
Oversold/Bullish/Support Signals- At US$24.74 the price is below the lower Bollinger band support of US$25.07, indicating an upside for it to return to the band. - The Relative Strength Index (RSI) of 27.0 has breached the oversold line of 30, suggesting the price decrease of 6.3% in the last 14 days is unusually high.
NoteBeta: the Beta of Denso ADR is 0.5. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return ADR with volatility less than that of the market. - Denso is at a discount of 9.0% to its 12-month high of US$27.19 on 17 Jan, 2014. It is also at a premium of 24.6% to the 12-month low of US$19.86 on 02 Apr, 2013.
AGGREGATE VOLUMES, PRICES AND TURNOVER PERIOD [Volume Index or VI in brackets; 1 is average]US Market: DNZOY.OT 16,633 [VI of 0.75]; volume 0.4% of aggregate. Price: US$24.74. Tokyo: 6902.TO 4,050,000 [VI of 1.69]; volume 99.6% of aggregate. Price: JPY5,029.0. Using the current exchange rate of JPY1 equals 0.01 USD, the shares are at a 0.4% discount to the close price in the US Market. Aggregate volume: there were 4,066,633 shares worth USD200,012,510 traded. The aggregate volume was 1.68 times average trading of 2,420,753 shares.
SHAREHOLDER PATTERN- Top 11 Institutional Shareholders of Denso(DNZOY.OT) hold 631,803 shares (or 0.03%).- Parametric Portfolio Associates Llc was the largest institutional holder with reported holdings of 229,941 shares as at September 30, 2013.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 18: DENSO Develops EGR Valve Unit[Company Release] KARIYA (Japan) - Global automotive supplier DENSO has developed an exhaust gas recirculation (EGR) valve unit, a major component of EGR systems that helps make diesel engine emissions cleaner. The new unit, the first in the world to integrate an air intake throttle valve and an EGR valve, is half the size of conventional models and requires fewer components, thus reducing costs.
February 03: Denso Announces Third-quarter Financial Results[Company Release] Kariya (Japan) - DENSO Corporation today announced its third quarter global financial results for the nine months ending Dec. 31, 2013:Consolidated net sales totaled 3,016.6 billion yen (US$28.8 billion), a 17.4 percent increase from the previous year.Consolidated operating income totaled 289.9 billion yen (US$2.8 billion), a 54.2 percent increase from the previous year.Consolidated net income totaled 225.6 billion yen (US$2.2 billion), a 72.5 percent increase from the previous year.http://www.globaldenso.com/en/newsreleases/140203-01.htmlSource: Company Website
January 16: Toyota Industries and DENSO Establish Automotive Air-Conditioning Compressor Manufacturing Company in China[Company Release]KARIYA (Japan) - Toyota Industries Corporation (TICO) and DENSO Corporation (DENSO) have established a new company, Yantai Shougang TD Automotive Compressor Co., Ltd. (YST), in Yantai City, Shandong Province, People's Republic of China, for the manufacture of automotive air-conditioning compressors in response to the growing Chinese automobile market.
December 23: Denso: The Korea Fair Trade Commission's Announcement Concerning the Monopoly Regulation and Fair Trade Act related to Certain Automotive Components[Company Release] KARIYA (Japan) - The Korea Fair Trade Commission (the "KFTC") announced today that it decided to order to rectify illegal conduct, impose a surcharge and bring an accusation to certain automotive suppliers pursuant to Articles 19, 21 and 22 of the Monopoly Regulation and Fair Trade Act, in connection with sales of automotive windshield wiper systems and instrumental panel clusters.The KFTC has investigated this matter at certain automotive suppliers, including DENSO Corporation and its subsidiaries in Republic of Korea, and the DENSO companies have fully cooperated with the KFTC.As per the KFTC's announcement, DENSO Corporation and its subsidiaries, DENSO Korea Automotive Corporation and DENSO Korea Electronics Corporation, were named as the suppliers involved in violation of the Monopoly Regulation and Fair Trade Act (No.
October 08: DENSO to exhibit at the 20th ITS World Congress Tokyo 2013[Company Release] KARIYA (Japan) - Global automotive supplier DENSO will exhibit at the 20th World Congress on Intelligent Transport Systems, at the Tokyo International Exhibition Center, Tuesday, Oct. 15, - Friday, Oct. 18. DENSO will present its intelligent transport system (ITS)-related products and technologies mainly in the area of safety, under the theme "Technology to keep people safe wherever they drive-Everyday Confidence, Extraordinary Safety."http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Japan/Stock/News/17603.htmlSource: Company Website
September 27: DENSO and Nagoya University Jointly Develop In-vehicle Battery-based Energy Management System[Company Release]KARIYA (Japan) - Global automotive supplier DENSO and Nagoya University have developed an in-vehicle battery-based energy management system (EMS), which uses forecasting models of household electricity demand and vehicle use to reduce electricity costs. The two organizations will start to evaluate the performance of the system in October this year under the Toyota City Low-carbon Society Verification Project, one of the Next-Generation Energy and Social System Demonstration Projects in Japan led by Japan's Ministry of Economy, Trade and Industry (METI).The EMS coordinates with batteries used in electric and plug-in hybrid vehicles to use their stored electricity to help keep down electricity bills.
September 27: Denso announces dividendDenso today announced a cash dividend of 19.15c per share. The ex dividend date is September 27, 2013 and it is payable on December 10, 2013.
ISIN: US24872B1008
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>