<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4460-ACDF-B9B8-69CB"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Stephen Harper's empty sloganeering on Ukraine</title><source>The Toronto Star</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The two dominant narratives on Ukraine are by now familiar. Vladimir Putin is using Soviet bully tactics to keep satellite states in line, including this weekend's illegal and illegitimate referendum in Crimea. The other view is that the West had been encroaching too much into the Russian neighbourhood for him not to react, and that it is hypocritical of us to be condemning him when the United States and its allies often interfere in and wage war on nations, plus support secessions selectively, as in South Sudan and East Timor. Apropos the West's inconsistencies, let's look at our own prime minister's.
In 2003, Stephen Harper wanted Canada to join the American invasion of Iraq. In 2006, he backed the Israeli invasion of Lebanon as a "measured" move to protect its interests. In 2011, he was silent when Saudi Arabia marched tanks and troops into Bahrain to protect its interests. Last year, he backed France's military intervention in its former colony of Mali. But Russia invading Crimea is akin to the 1938 Nazi annexation of part of Czechoslovakia.
Harper wants Russia booted out of the G8 but he never suggested tossing Saudi Arabia out of the G20.
He supports the Ukrainian popular revolt that toppled a corrupt president. But he did not back the popular revolt in Bahrain against an autocratic king, or the historic uprising in Egypt against the corrupt and brutal autocrat Hosni Mubarak. In fact, he backed the Egyptian army when it toppled the democratically elected president Mohammed Morsi last year. The coup restored "stability," Harper said. That's what Putin said, too, in embracing Egyptian strongman Gen. Abdul-Fattah el-Sisi. Putin is at least consistent - he has no use for democracy in either Egypt or Ukraine.
Putin has blamed the Ukrainian crisis on anti-Semites. Harper has characterized the critics of his stance on Israel as anti-Semites, and called the critics of his policy on Afghanistan unpatriotic.
Putin demonized the Kyiv protesters as Nazis. Harper often raises the spectre of the Nazis - besides saying that the Russian moves in Crimea are Nazi-like, he and his ministers describe those who do not fully stand with Israel and those who wish to negotiate with Iran as Nazi appeasers.
This is not to equate Harper's political posturing with Putin's war propaganda. Nor to pretend that national interests do not force leaders into double standards. But his hypocrisy seems driven mostly by the Conservative party's re-election manual - hijack selected foreign policy issues in the service of pleasing targeted ethnic groups.
As valid as his criticisms of Russia's outrageous actions have been, his pronouncements are clearly not designed to carve out a constructive role for Canada but rather tailored to elicit applause at home from Canadian Ukrainians - just as his piano-playing gig in Israel reduced the prime minister to an entertainer desperate to please his audience.
Harper's actions on Russia parallel his approach to Iran. He recalled the Canadian ambassador to Moscow, just as he closed our embassy in Tehran. Canada does not have much power over either Iran or Russia. What little difference we can make as a mid-level western power lies in being able to mediate between the U.S. and Europe, on the one hand, and the other parties, on the other. Abandon that, and you are left with the rhetoric of escalating adjectives and symbolic gestures - Ottawa "condemns," "strongly condemns" and "condemns in the strongest terms" and pledges $200,000, whereas what Ukraine needs is $35 billion to get out from under Russian hegemony.
The mess in Ukraine is partly the Ukrainians' own doing.
What the nation needed, especially after the highly hopeful 2004-05 pro-democracy Orange Revolution, was a Nelson Mandela to unite its two main factions, the largely Ukrainian northwest and the largely Russian-speaking southeast. What it got instead was a Morsi - in fact, three of them, Viktor Yushchenko, Viktor Yanukovych and Yulia Tymoshenko, each serving his or her own constituency and, indeed, fanning the divisions.
It is not naive to think that Canada could have made a difference. As the first western country to recognize Ukraine in 1991, we could have advanced good governance, transparency and human rights - precisely what the pro-democracy forces in the Kyiv Maidan have been demanding for three months. Canada could have helped with sustained engagement from 1.2 million Canadian Ukrainians, the most influential Ukrainian diaspora in the world.
Instead, Ottawa, under both Liberals and Conservatives, watched as Ukraine fell under the sway of one oligarch after another. Now the prime minister is shouting empty slogans from the sidelines.
Haroon Siddiqui's column appears on Thursday and Sunday. hsiddiqui@thestar.ca
]]></text></news-item>