<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4468-930D-D48F-BB12"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Woman charged after pulling out man's tooth</title><source>The Polk County Democrat (Bartow, Florida)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A woman was charged with domestic battery when in an argument that turned physical when she ripped a tooth from her boyfriend's mouth, a Bartow Police Department report said.
Jennifer Lynn Suydam was charged with the incident on March 8 at the Bartow Police Department as that is where her boyfriend went to report the incident.
According to an arrest report, John Scarborough and Suydam got into a verbal argument and when Scarborough approached Suydam she allegedly punched him on the left side of his face. Scarborough pushed Suydam and when she grabbed his mouth with her right hand and pulled out his tooth, the report said.
Scarborough then pinned Suydam and continued to argue with her spitting blood onto her, the report said.
He then left the place and walked to the Bartow Police Department.
Officers saw his bloody mouth and missing tooth and though he didn't need medical attention, Suydam was questioned. Police noticed a bruise on her right knuckles and hand and she was arrested, police reported.
First rabies case confirmed
On Saturday, March 8, a Lake Wales woman reported that she had been bitten by a raccoon and that her neighbors' dogs had been fighting with it, in the area of  952 Campbell Ave.
The PCSO Animal Control Section responded, impounded the raccoon, and sent its body to the state lab for rabies testing. The raccoon was confirmed positive for rabies by the State Laboratory on Wednesday, March 12.
The dogs' owner was notified of the test results and the dogs will be quarantined for 180 days.
The Polk County Sheriff's Office wants residents are reminded bats and raccoons are among the mammals considered to be high risk species or "rabies vector species." People should not approach any animal which is acting in an unusual or suspicious manner. Those who think they or their pet has had an exposure, contact the PCSO Animal Control Section at 863-499-2600.
Crash kills 3, injures 2
POLK CITY(AP) - Deputies say Justin and Sharonda Sims and their 5-year-old son Savio died when a tractor trailer struck their 1998 Buick Century at an intersection in central Florida early Tuesday morning.
The Polk County Sheriff's Office says two other children - Ariel, 7, and Kitty, 2 - were critically injured. An infant, 3-month-old Arienne, was properly strapped into her car seat and is in stable condition at a Lakeland hospital. Deputies say the parents and other children were not wearing seat belts.
Deputies say the car, driven by Justin Sims, 31, of Dade City apparently ran through a stop sign as the returned home from shopping at an outlet mall in Orlando. The car was dragged some 400 feet. The boy was in the front seat with his parents.
Ariel and Kitty Sims were airlifted to Arnold Palmer Children's Hospital in Orlando in critical condition.
Investigators say Justin Sims had a suspended driver's license due to failure to pay traffic fines in September.
Antonio Garcia, 31, of Tampa, was driving the truck that hit the family. He was not injured in the crash.
The intersection was shut down for hours as authorities investigated the crash. All roads are now open.
An investigation continues.
PCSO, DBPR crack down  on unlicensed contractors
From Monday, March 3 through Thursday, March 6, the Polk County Sheriff's undercover deputies, working in conjunction with investigators from the Florida Department of Business and Professional Regulation did an investigation into unlicensed contractual work performed in Polk County. At the end of "Operation Tool Time," detectives arrested 20 people for advertising and proposing contracting work in Polk County without a professional business license.
"When you don't take the time to research the people you hire to do repairs in your home, you open yourselves up to being victimized. Don't trust your home repairs to people who aren't licensed and insured - spend the extra time and money verifying licenses and insurance credentials before letting someone into your home," said Polk County Sheriff Grady Judd. "Unlicensed contractors can perform shoddy work, resulting in damage, fires, or even injury."
During the operation, detectives answered ads placed online or in periodicals advertising home repairs, and scheduled appointments with those who placed the ads. The types of home repairs the suspects claimed they did ranged from plumbing to electrical. Those who provided written or verbal proposals to perform the work showed up at the location where the "work" was to be done, and were arrested for engaging in contracting business without a license
"Unlicensed activity not only threatens the livelihood of Florida's consumers, but it also takes away jobs from those who are licensed as required by law," said DBPR Secretary Ken Lawson. "Floridians should always verify an individual's professional license with my department prior to having any work performed on their home."
Those arrested were:
Ernie Garcia, 33, of 512 Petteway Drive in Lakeland
Reynaldo Morales, 24, of 513 West Crescent Drive in Lakeland
John Ziegler, 29, of 449 Park Drive in Babson Park
Allen O'Rilley, 23, of 408 Street North in Dundee
Jason Stern, 30, of 3210 Bloomingdale Village Court in Brandon
Jorge Davila, 41, of 227 Satinwood Circle in Kissimmee
Blanca Rodriguez-Baez, 40, of  277 Satinwood Circle in Kissimmee
Anthony Higgins, 51, of 1310 McClellan Road in Frostproof
Manuel Cordero-Acevedo, 46, of  1917 4th Street NE in Winter Haven
David Canfield, 39, of 200 Dennis Avenue in Winter Haven
Nephtali Otero, 30, of 929 Kenbar Avenue in Haines City
Deborah Ferra, 31, of 929 Kenbar Avenue in Haines City
Terry Hines, 35, of 167 Lake Thomas Drive in Winter Haven
Randy Monk, 32, of 4631 Carl Boozer Road in Haines City
Basilio Rios, 33, of 658 Caribou Court in Kissimmee
Daniel Martinez-Matassini, 34, of  539 Hummingbird Court in Kissimmee
Michael Spring, 29, of 315 Coronado Court in Lakeland
Terry Wellington, 28, , of 3018 Helms Drive in Auburndale
Jonathon Wellington, 36, of  116 Temple Street in Winter Haven
Dean Menendez, 48, of  334 Appaloosa Hill Road in Polk City
Woman charged  with beating daughter
A woman accused of beating on her daughter was charged with domestic violence on March 5, the Bartow Police Department reported.
Mary Jessie Snell, 56, was booked into the Polk County Jail after she was accused by her daughter of swinging at her daughter several times, leaving and returning and beating on her again, a police report said.
On March 4, Officer Kristi Tew responded to the house which address is not listed in the report, and the victim said the two were in an an argument and during it Snell struck grabbed her by the right arm, scatching her and then pushed her.
The victim also said Snell swung at her several times but did not strike her. She said Snell also scratched her right hand sometime during the altercation, the report said.
Then Snell packed all her belongings and left the house. She returned several times that night causing an argument each time until the victim called the police, the report said. The victim said Snell's actions were unprovoked and against her will and she had sustained a scratch on her upper right arm. The victim refused medical treatment however, photographs were taken of the marks, the report said.
Snell denied the allegations of a physical altercation, the report said, despite the fact that she was charged.
Parolee charged  with resisting arrest
A man who was in violation of his parole for sexual battery was arrested March 6 after two K-9s searched for him after he left an apartment through a window and ran away, the Bartow Police Department reported.
Dennis Ray Robbins, 56, of 901 E. Seward St., Tampa, was found by a sheriff's office K-9 in a wooden area on the northside of the apartment complex at 260 N. Van Fleet Drive.
Officer Jose Joglar responded to an apartment at the complex at 3:08 a.m. as there was a warrant for Robbins arrest and he heard the suspect was there. When he arrived there, Joglar contacted Officer Quinn who arrived with Flash, his K9. As they were entering the apartment two dogs came toward Flash, Joglar reported he pushed the door to avoid an incident.
While he was getting his taser the door was closed and locked, the report said.
Robbins then left through an apartment window and fled west, the report said.
A search with Flash was done but due to exhaustion, a bloodhound from the Polk County Sheriff's Office was requested and Ponch took over the search. This dog eventually found Robbins in a thick wooden area on the northside of the apartment where he was arrested without any struggle, the report said.
Trespass violator charged, metallic knuckles found on him
Michael Christopher Hatfield was charged with trespassing and carrying a set of brass knuckles March 7 for violating a trespass warning where he was, the Bartow Police Department reported.
Hatfield, 19, of 428 Old Fort Meade Rd., Homeland, was issued a trespass warning on Jan. 16 for 1350 E. Main St., Bartow.
Upon being searched Officer Michael Bennett found a set of metallic knuckles in his pants pocket, he reported.
]]></text></news-item>