<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="44A3-3126-F39A-A531"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Tony Benn (1925-2013): Contrast to Cameron in British politics</title><source>Daily News (Sri Lanka)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Sri Lanka, March 17 -- It was a significant juxtaposition of events that symbolised the status of contemporary international politics that the current British Prime Minister David Cameron was in Jerusalem at the moment of death of the principled Labour politician Tony Benn in London last week.
Cameron's pilgrimage to Jerusalem, obviously to beg for indulgences well in advance of the upcoming elections in return for his services to the Zionist cause, symbolised the death of an earlier, more measured, approach to politics in the Middle East by Britain that appeared to project a semblance of sympathy towards the suffering of the Palestinians.
The current bipartisan homogenisation of post-imperial British approach to the world with the arrogant, selfish American neocon mould, under the typically deceptive neocon banner of a "special relationship" between the two countries put an end to such decency; The process began under corrupt Labour leaders like Harold Wilson, continuing through the Tories Margaret Thatcher to David Cameron, not to mention the role of Tony Blair, who infiltrated the Labour movement.
The death last week, at the age of 88, of the former Labour politician Anthony Neil Wedgwood Benn, better known by the more unpretentious moniker "Tony Benn", probably removes the last link with a previous era of Britain with a slightly more decent outward character as a nation.
Tony Benn was a great, and an exceptionally decent man due simply to his renunciation of the privileges of aristocracy he was born in to, and his fight against the very sources of his privileged background - monarchy, hereditary peerage and the House of Lords. His humble demeanour was such that he is also known to have treated 'crumbs' of privileged background as his attendance at the exclusive Westminster School as embarrassing details.
Benn had dedicated his life to represent, in an outspoken, honest and courageous manner, those who continue to have no voice in the chronically feudalistic British social and economic system. Tony Benn was probably the last such politician in any so-called Western democracy where politics has become a career rather than vocation, and where clash of ideologies at the ballot box has ceased to be the determinant of national destiny. Born in London on April 3,1925 to a politically active family, Benn's grandfather and father had both been Liberal MPs, with his father crossing the floor of the House to join the Labour Party in 1927. Upon retirement in 1942, his father was created Viscount Stansgate and appointed to the House of Lords.
Tony Benn first entered Parliament in 1950, aged just 25 as Labour representative for Bristol and served as an MP for more than 50 years until he stepped down from Parliament in 2001, famously declaring that he wanted to "spend more time on politics". During his parliamentary career Benn became an iconic figure in the Labour Party in the 1970s, and was the main author of the manifesto on which Labour fought the 1983 election.
The greatness of the man can be measured by the fact that one of the early battles he fought was to renounce his hereditary peerage as Viscount Stansgate which he was 'forced' to inherit on the death of his father in 1960. The death of elder brother Michael during the war had made Tony Benn the heir for the peerage.
Benn resisted the automatic elevation to hereditary nobility because, according to the law at the time, the peerage barred him from sitting among the elected "commoners" in the House of Commons, the path he had chosen in 1950. He fought hard to forsake his inherited seat in the House of Lords which he described as "the British Outer Mongolia for retired politicians" in favour of the House of Commons which he considered the legitimate seat of legislative power.
Tony Benn's battle to reject his inherited title on grounds that he was "not a reluctant peer but a persistent commoner" made him a cause celebre - but his attempts failed. Having forced to give up his lower house seat, Tony Benn contested and retained his seat in a by-election. But Parliament refused to allow him to take his seat as he was still a peer, and under the laws of the time, an election court gave the seat to the Conservative runner-up. Only in 1963 a law was enacted, permitting the renunciation of hereditary titles, and within 22 minutes Tony Benn shed his, leading to the resignation of his Conservative opponent in Bristol and a by-election, with Benn sweeping back into the Commons.
Benn's political life since the 1960s shows that his battle to renounce hereditary peerage was not a cheap trick aimed at gaining popularity among the masses, or an exception to an otherwise 'snout in the trough' sort of political career. It clearly was an early sign of integrity and passion for a cause - which he described as "on the right wing of the middle of the road, with a strong radical bias" - that turned him into a national treasure.
Benn made no secret that he extended his antipathy towards peerage to its very source, the monarchy. As Postmaster General from 1964-6, perhaps symbolically, Benn wanted to replace the Queen's head from British stamps and to permit "non-traditional" designs such as landscapes, portraits, drawing the ire of the Buckingham Palace. A compromise resulted in the form of the current small silhouette in the corner of pictorial stamps. Benn continued the struggle to introduce changes to the stamp by asking rhetorically - "If the Queen can reject the advice of a minister on a little thing like a postage stamp, . the whole democratic facade turns out to be false.
In 2002, Benn wrote in an essay titled "A State Of Palestine Now", that "The main responsibility for the appalling crimes being perpetrated against the Palestinians must be equally shared between Jerusalem and Washington, for successive American governments have funded Israel, armed Israel and used their Veto at the Security Council to protect Israel from being forced to comply with what World opinion wanted it to do".
The British position on Israel at the time, slightly demarcated by a miniscule degree of decency towards the Palestinians, enabled Benn to point out the American complicity on "crimes against the Palestinians". Benn's demise removes the last semblance of a pro-Palestinian voice from among the selfish, vulture class that currently infests the British Labour and Tory establishment.
Tony Benn spoke the truth fearlessly without shying away from plain truths other politicians were concealing either dishonestly or through fear - he declared that "Britain was ruled by vested interests and that elected MPs wielded little power. If the British people were ever to ask themselves what power they truly enjoyed under our political system they would be amazed to discover how little it is", he added.
Obviously threatened by such expressions of truth, the vested interest groups led by Rupert Murdoch-owned newspapers often travestied his opinions, ridiculously accusing him of wanting to turn Britain into a Soviet colony. The Sun newspaper asked the question whether Tony Benn was "the most dangerous man in Britain".
Not surprisingly, such forthright opinions also subjected Tony Benn, for much of his life, for vilification by his opponents within the Labour party. Prime Minister Harold Wilson - the man who 'leased' the Comoro islands (Diego Garcia) to his US neocon cousins for the 'princely sum' of just one dollar a year, saw Benn's idealism as irrational and famously remarked that Benn 'immatured' with age. But unperturbed, Benn made enemies and kept them.
Following the ousting of the Labour government in 1979, Benn battled with Denis Healey for the deputy leadership of the party in 1981, narrowly losing due to treachery by some unions. Denis Healey, who is remembered for little else than the ignominy of being on record as the first Labour politician to anoint Tony Blair for Labour leadership, in 1994 following the death of Labour leader John Smith, accused Benn of "destroying the Labour Party as a force in 20th-century British politics."
Tony Benn held that any institution that was not accountable to the people was dictatorial, justifying his opposition to institutions like the monarchy and the House of Lords, and military and pseudo-economic "clubs" such as NATO and the EU. He supported Sinn Fein and a united Ireland and the miners' strike of 1984-85, strongly supporting of the National Union of Miners' President, Arthur Scargill, who was being brutalised by Margaret Thatcher.
Tony Benn's pursuit of pristine progressive policies drove many senior traditionalist Labour figures out of the movement altogether to form the ideologically nondescript and politically naive Social Democratic Party that is currently sleeping with the Tories. But with his passionate beliefs in democracy and social justice, he inspired - at least temporarily - a generation of young Labour activists.
In a recent radio interview, Benn summarised his past experiences relating to the undermining he faced from players who pretended to represent the working poor in Britain - "You look back and, as long as you say what you believe and believe what you say - that's the test of authenticity."
Tony Benn's enlightened views shone in the arena of international politics too. Apart from his well-known views on Israeli atrocities against the Palestinians, he opposed such politically motivated, cynical exercises as Thatcher's Falklands War and Bush Senior's similarly dishonest Iraq war of 1991.
An advocate of nuclear disarmament and a prominent anti-war campaigner all his life, Benn became president of the Stop the War Coalition during the lead up to the atrocity of the British-American Iraqi invasion of 2003, visiting Baghdad in February 2003 to talk to Saddam Hussein as a pacifist emissary.
In the dispute over Iran's nuclear technology, Benn said in 2005, "We might be told that Britain must support Bush, yet again, because of the threat of weapons of mass destruction, thus allowing him to kill even more innocent civilians."
In the final analysis, Tony Benn was a great human being who failed to counter the more forceful, sinister moves of lesser beings who undermined him from within his own Party. This they did through the agency of opportunists like Neil Kinnock and infiltrators like Dennis Healy and Tony Blair. The Labour Party orthodoxy nurtured by the lesser beings has disappeared into a crevice at the feet of the Tories, otherwise referred to as the "middle ground of British politics".
Clear signs of this "group thinking" was reflected in the messages of condolences of past and present leaders of both Labour and Tory Parties - The current Labour leader Ed Miliband (whose father is supposed to have been a close friend of Tony Benn) eulogised - "Whether you agreed with him or disagreed with him, everyone knew where he stood and what he stood for"; David Cameron said "There was never a dull moment listening to him, even when you disagreed with everything he said."
The expression of such backhanded compliments on the life of Tony Benn by the leadership of the two Parties is more a reflection of the current value-free quagmire British politics is in, rather than any failure on the part of Tony Benn.
In his most recent public appearance, on December 12, 2013, at a service remembering Nelson Mandela in the Westminster Hall where Mandela addressed British Parliament as President of South Africa in 1996, Tony Benn is on record to have told the audience that Mandela had fought for justice, "not as a South African, or a black, but as a member of the human race".
Tony Benn who died as he lived, holding dear the convictions he espoused will similarly continue to inspire the human race, well beyond his own tribe that is fast becoming almost an alien species. Tony Benn's successors in the British Labour Party, and opponents like David Cameron shrivel by comparison.
In the case of David Cameron, no amount of huffing and puffing against Sri Lanka will do nothing other than inflating his adolescent ego.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Daily News Sri Lanka. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>