<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4519-0D05-F852-6084"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>John T. Moore: Keeping government in full view</title><source>Ventura County Star (California)</source><author>John T. Moore is editor of The Star.</author><text><![CDATA[Open government is good government.
That’s the simple mantra for Sunshine Week, which begins today around the nation. The designation, sponsored by news organizations, is an annual reminder on the importance of a free flow of public information, and of a transparent government, to a free society. When you let the sun shine in on government, then we all can see.
California’s approach to open government is built around two strong laws — the Ralph M. Brown Act mandating open meetings, passed in 1953, and California Public Records Act, passed in 1968. It’s enhanced by a constitutional amendment, supported by 83 percent of California’s voters in November 2004, that placed the public’s right of access to government meetings and records of government officials in the state constitution alongside freedom of speech and assembly. Both sunshine laws provide all citizens with rights to access meetings and documents. On your behalf, we invoke them regularly. Here are a few of the stories we wrote in the last year after filing a request for information based on the California Public Records Act and the companion law that covers the Legislature: n Specifics of the city of Simi Valley’s investigation into allegations against the city attorney. n The number of mailers sent by local members of the state Assembly regarding the health care act implementation, and how much they cost. n Compensation paid to pharmacists at the Ventura County Medical Center, showing they were paid 27 to 39 percent above base pay when bonuses and premiums were counted. n Pesticide records for a Somis farm that was the subject of local complaints. n Personal use of county cars driven by county officials. n Salaries and benefits paid to school superintendents throughout the county. n Travel records for a trip by county pension board members to Scotland. n Details, for the first time, on the amount of money donated to foundations run by the county’s three community colleges, and how that money is spent. n Names and titles of 100 county employees who received 30-year loyalty payments. We also relied on the Brown Act to challenge actions by local bodies. For instance, in July we wrote about the hiring of a new city manager by Port Hueneme in closed sessions, questioning whether it met open meeting statutes. The District Attorney’s Office investigated and said that it did. But the most important impact of these laws comes in times when we don’t have to use them. One of our reporters recently told me that because of the public records law, many agencies are more responsive to routine requests. We ask for documents. They provide them. No fuss. Those agencies understand the importance of their relationship with the public — with you. Over the years, both the open meetings and public records laws have been amended, altered and chipped at to provide exceptions. That’s why there are books hundreds of pages long that deal with the laws and how courts in California have interpreted them. And that’s why we often need to submit a formal request for information, and are often denied. When we think we’re right we are willing to challenge the denial in court. We did that last year and will continue to do it in the future. We’re all happy to live in a state with so much sunshine. We will continue to do our part this year to make sure that it shines brightly in all the nooks and corners of governments throughout our state. There should be no such thing as “their business” when it comes to government. It is all “our business.”
]]></text></news-item>