<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4562-0418-163C-BEAD"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Business</title><source>The Economist</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Zhou Xiaochuan, the governor of China's central bank, said that official controls on the interest rates that Chinese banks can offer savers would be lifted within two years. This is the latest reform in China's push to liberalise its financial industry. Banks are already allowed to set their own lending rates. The government this week allowed five private banks to be set up in China's wealthiest regions in order to boost lending to small firms.
? This article contains a table. Please see hard copy.
Meanwhile, China's annual rate of inflation slowed to 2% in February from 2.5% in January and producer prices continued down their two-year path of monthly declines, providing more evidence of slackening demand in the economy. Chinese exports unexpectedly fell in February, by 18%, the most since 2009 and leaving the country with a rare trade deficit for the month. The central bank made further moves to weaken the yuan, possibly to help exporters.
Chaori Solar, which has become the first company in China to default on a corporate bond, said it would sell assets to repay debt and would try to avoid bankruptcy. The markets took a chilled approach to the solar-equipment company's default, which the authorities may have permitted as a message to investors about pricing risk adequately. China's corporate-bond market has grown rapidly since 2008's credit binge.
?
Puerto Rico's $3.5 billion sale of municipal bonds was more than four times oversubscribed, giving the heavily indebted island a few more months' breathing room before it risks a default. The junk-rated bonds mature in 2035, and offer investors high yields and tax breaks.
?
Mark Carney, the governor of the Bank of England, said that the unfolding scandal concerning alleged manipulation of foreign-exchange rates went "to the heart of integrity of markets" and was possibly more serious than LIBOR. The central bank has been accused of ignoring warning signs in the matter, and will soon unveil new oversight rules.
The chief executive of Britain's Co-operative Group resigned after a testy ten months in the job. Euan Sutherland stood down complaining that the group, which is mutually owned and controlled through a patchwork of committees and regional boards, is ungovernable. He became chief executive last May, seeing through a rescue plan for the Co-op's bank that ended up with the group losing full control of the business. The Co-op is expected to reveal huge losses when it reports its annual results.
?
UniCredit surprised even the most grizzled observers of Italy's troubled banking industry when it reported a ?15 billion ($21 billion) net loss for the fourth quarter. The bank portrayed the loss as a "courageous decision" to write down bad debts and goodwill and tidy up its balance-sheet ahead of European stress tests. It also proclaimed a new start under a four-year turnaround plan in which it will shed 6% of its workforce.
?
The share price of Herbalife, an American seller of dietary supplements, fell after it said it was being investigated by the Federal Trade Commission. Bill Ackman, an activist investor, has shorted Herbalife's shares; the company rejects his claim that it is a "pyramid scheme".
?
?
?
?
?
?
?
?
?
?
?
?
?
The banana world was split over the merits of a merger between Chiquita and Fyffes that will create the fruit's biggest distributor. Antitrust regulators will look closely at the deal, especially in Europe, which imposed stiff tariffs on Latin American bananas until 2012. But some say a merger makes sense, given the current squeeze in profit margins as a result of the costs of tackling potentially disastrous diseases in banana crops.
Johnson & Johnson sold its K-Y intimate-lubricant brand to Britain's Reckitt Benckiser in a deal that underlines the rapid growth of the sexual-well-being market. To ease the passage of the deal, only the brand is slipping between hands; no workers or assets are being transferred.
?
After five months of bids, counter-bids and "Pac-Man defences", Men's Wearhouse and Jos A. Bank at last agreed to combine in a $1.8 billion deal to fashion America's fourth-biggest retailer of men's apparel. Because of the takeover Jos A. Bank is terminating its planned acquisition of Eddie Bauer, a clothing brand.
Martin Winterkorn, Volkswagen's boss, warned that the increasing integration of smart technology into cars risked creating a "data monster". Smart cars have gadgets that link easily with smartphones, but other features, such as on-board cameras and systems that can alert insurers to aggressive-driving patterns, are worrying privacy advocates. Mr Winterkorn says "yes to Big Data?but no to?Big Brother".
]]></text></news-item>