<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="45B4-A516-D5CA-F887"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Developers get the call as ICAC focus shifts to funds for favours</title><source>Weekend Australian</source><author>MARK COULTAN, NSW POLITICAL CORRESPONDENT</author><text><![CDATA[THE Independent Commission Against Corruption is set to call a host of Sydney developers as it investigates secret donations to political parties and candidates.
And Australian Water Holdings, which provides water infrastructure services in northwest Sydney, will come under the microscope from Monday.
ICAC amended its terms of reference this week to investigate if AWH artificially drove up its expenses by including other business costs, or drew funds allocated for other purposes, as part of a scheme to profit from its contract with Sydney Water.
ICAC's second but related inquiry will look at donations for favours, focusing on three central coast MPs, including former resources minister Chris Hartcher, and their staff, as well as donations from prohibited companies. It has been illegal since 2009 for property developers to donate to political parties.
ICAC is investigating whether the MPs and staff ``solicited, received and failed to disclose political donations'' from companies, including prohibited donors.
Among those who may have to give evidence are an associate of former Labor factional boss Joe Tripodi; a former executive of Nathan Tinkler's company Buildev; and one of Sydney's biggest developers of luxury apartments.
Pasquale Sergi once was in a property business with Mr Tripodi which bought and sold government land.
Mr Tripodi is set to appear in next week's AWH inquiry, which is examining whether he or other former Labor ministers Eddie Obeid and Tony Kelly misused their positions as MPs over a contract with AWH, in which Mr Obeid had a secret investment.
Mr Sergi was mentioned in the Woodward royal commission in 1979 as working for the drug boss Robert Trimbole, finding properties for him as part of a money-laundering operation. He was never charged with any offence out of the commission.
Another business identity who may be called is Angelo Maggiotto, a long-time property developer around Liverpool, in Sydney's southwest, and active in ALP politics. He has also donated to the Liberal Party.
He was involved in the redevelopment of the council-owned School of Arts building, which is near another council-owned building bought in 2011 from Gazcon, whose directors Nicholas and Nabil Gazal may also give evidence.
Another developer who will be represented by legal counsel at the inquiry is Iwan Sunito, whose company Crown Group Holdings claims a pipeline of $3 billion of luxury apartment developments in Sydney.
Another who may be called is David Murray Sharpe, once general manager of Newcastle-based developer Buildev, a big donor to both parties before 2009.
]]></text></news-item>