<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="45BE-2936-E6F6-67E6"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Kol firm dupes Bokaro residents</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Divy Khare</author><text><![CDATA[BOKARO: Despite the district administration alertness against illegal non-banking financial companies (NBFC's) operating in the districts, a Kolkata-based company - Gurukul Project -duped residents of Rs 6 crore.
While two local company staff - Anil Kumar and Manikant Kumar - have been arrested, raids are on to nab four others, including managing director Gautam Majumdar and officers Rajeev Ranjan, Vinay Kumar and Anil Kumar, who are absconding.
SP Jitender Singh said based on a complaint made by a resident Narayan Singh, the FIR against six persons of Gurukul Project has been lodged with Sector-IV police station. The arrested duo are residents of Bokaro. Majumdar is a resident of Kolkata and runs a company head office there.
Most victims are retired employees of Bokaro Steel Limited. There are few who have deposited their entire savings which they received after retirement of their service in the Gurukul Project. They are in a state of shock. The company had its office in the heart of the town. It lured residents offering them lucrative monthly interest payback scheme.
The complainant Singh, who is resident of Ramdih More, has deposited Rs 20 lakh while Hari Singh of Chas area deposited Rs 6 lakh, Ram Prasad Rs 19 lakh and there are many others on the list who have deposited their earnings. They alleged that the company officials paid them their monthly interest until September, 2013, but then it was stopped.
When they went to check the problem in office, they found it to be closed and the officials and staff had disappeared. SP said that they have taken the case very seriously and would nab the accused soon. District administration on December, 2013 had launched massive raids on NBFC's operational in the district.
Bokaro DC Uma Shanker Singh then had banned about 20 NBFCs on finding them doing illegal business. He then had appealed to residents to stop depositing money in NBFCs and withdraw the sum they had deposited from these financial institutions.
DC then had also directed all nationalized and private banks to freeze the accounts of NBFCs in a bid to save public money. But Gurukul Project had not come under the scanner of the administrative team.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>