<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="45F8-2010-DCCA-E6FE"><date>2014-03-10</date><title>Attention Conn's, Inc. Investors: Conn's Misled Investors According to a Recently Filed Class Action</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Shareholder rights law firm Robbins Arroyo LLPannouncesthat an investor of Conn's, Inc. (NASDAQ: CONN) has filed a federal securities fraud class action complaint in the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of Texas.  The complaint alleges that the company and certain of its officers and directors violated the Securities and Exchange Act of 1934 between April 3, 2013 and February 19, 2014 (the "Class Period").  Conn's is a retailer of durable consumer products, including appliances, furniture, and mattresses in the United States.

Conn's Is Accused of Misleading Investors About Company's Susceptibility to Bad Debt
According to the complaint, shares of Conn's fell $23.91 per share, or over 42%, to close at $31.89 on February 20, 2014.  The fall in Conn's share price came in reaction to a press release announcing the company's diluted earnings per share for its fiscal 2014 fourth quarter was below the company's previously issued full-year fiscal 2014 guidance, and that its 2015 fiscal guidance would be lowered.  The complaint alleges that the earnings decline resulted from higher than anticipated account receivable charge-offs and delinquency rates during the quarter, requiring Conn's to take increased provisions for bad debt.  Specifically, Conn's loan portfolio delinquency rate for customers 60-days delinquent increased 30 basis points during its fiscal 2014 fourth quarter to 8.8% at January 31, 2014.
The complaint further alleges that Conn's concealed from investors that the company's growth was based on underwriting and business practices that weakened portfolio quality and threatening the company's financial performance. As a result, Conn's statements regarding financial performance and expected earnings in 2014 and 2015 were materially false and misleading throughout the Class Period.
Conn's Shareholders Are Encouraged to Contact Shareholder Rights Law Firm Robbins Arroyo
If you invested in Conn's and would like to discuss your shareholder rights, please contact attorney Darnell R. Donahue at (800) 350-6003,DDonahue@robbinsarroyo.com, or via the information form on the firm's shareholder rights blog:http://www.robbinsarroyo.com/shareholders-rights-blog/conns-inc
Robbins Arroyo LLP is a nationally recognized leader in securities litigation and shareholder rights law.  The firm represents individual and institutional investors in shareholder derivative and securities class action lawsuits, and has helped its clients realize more than $1 billion of value for themselves and the companies in which they have invested. 
Attorney Advertising. Past results do not guarantee a similar outcome.  
Contact:Darnell R. DonahueRobbins Arroyo LLPDDonahue@robbinsarroyo.com(619) 525-3990 or Toll Free (800) 350-6003http://www.robbinsarroyo.com
Logo -http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20130103/MM36754LOGO
SOURCE Robbins Arroyo LLP
]]></text></news-item>