<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4601-5BB6-FDAF-A39D"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Petitioner told to file fresh plea against company</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Abhijeet Patil</author><text><![CDATA[KOLHAPUR: The Pune bench of the National Green Tribunal (NGT) on Friday directed petitioner Narsing Patil, former MLA, to file a fresh application against a chemical firm. However, the company counsel said the petition filed should not be entertained as it had been filed much after the firm received the consent of establishment from the appropriate authority.
AVH Chemicals Private Limited is in the process of setting up a coal tar distillation plan at the Halkarni industrial area in Chandgad, around 110 km south of Kolhapur. The construction of the plant began in 2012. However, people residing near the plant started agitating against it in December 2012 alleging that it would be hazardous to the environment. Patil in his application to the NGT pointed out that Chandgad is a part of the ecologically sensitive Western Ghats region, according to the Gadgil Committee report. So the construction of the plant should be stopped to avoid any environmental damage.
According to the law, a petitioner’s application can be filed within 90 days of the approval of such a project or it would not be entertained by courts.
Lawyer for the petitioner Asim Sarode said, “The company counsel said the petition against it has been filed much after the establishment of the project was approved. So according to the counsel, the petition should be abolished. However, the company has not yet got consent to operate the plant and the court suggested that either the petitioner should argue the legality of the application or file a fresh application within a stipulated number of days after the company gets consent for operating the plant.”
Sarode further said that he would argue the case claiming that as there were agitations taking place since the construction of the plant, the petition is valid. “We will try to convince the court that though the petition was filed much later, the affected people were trying to protest. Considering the larger environmental interest, the case should be heard for its merit. However, in case the petition is dismissed, we will apply for fresh application,” added Sarode.
The directives were issued by a bench comprising Justice V R Kingaonkar and Justice Ajay A Deshpande. The petition is considered important as it has also pointed out that the Maharashtra Pollution Control Board fraudulently granted consent to establish the coal tar distillation plant. The court has given the petitioner a timeframe of 40 days to argue the points raised by the company or file a fresh application.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>