<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4650-DD41-B26F-7052"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Factory that faced closure now building Chrysler 200</title><source>The Detroit News (Michigan)</source><author>By, Bryce G. Hoffman</author><text><![CDATA[The Detroit News
Sterling Heights - Chrysler Group LLC officially began production of the all-new 2015 Chrysler 200 here Friday at a plant that was marked for closure just five years ago.
The Sterling Heights Assembly Plant was an early victim of Chrysler's 2009 bankruptcy. But community leaders and workers rallied to save the factory and ultimately convinced the new Fiat-controlled Chrysler to purchase the plant back.
Now, the new Chrysler has invested nearly $1 billion in the factory and added 800 jobs to support production of the new midsize sedan.
"All of you at this plant have shown a never-give-up attitude," said CEO Sergio Marchionne as hundreds of auto workers cheered him at the Sterling Heights plant, which he called "an apt symbol of how far Chrysler had come because of the courage and the resilience of its people."
"With the support of our UAW partners, this plant has flourished," Marchionne continued, praising the way workers embraced the new quality and production standards he introduced from Fiat SpA. "We're counting on this car. ... The 200 will redefine the Chrysler brand."
Based on the same Alfa Romeo platform that also provides the foundation for the Dodge Dart and Jeep Cherokee, the new 200 is Chrysler's latest - and most important - entry into the hotly contested midsize sedan segment that is dominated by vehicles such as the Toyota Camry and Ford Fusion.
Early reviews have been mostly positive, praising the 200's power but criticizing its back seat room.
Marchionne also praised community leaders, including Sterling Heights Mayor Richard Notte, for setting up an automotive task force that helped build support for the factory and secured state and local incentives that helped persuade Chrysler to keep it open.
United Auto Workers President Bob King said Sterling Heights is a case study in how labor and management can work together for mutual benefit. But he urged workers, both hourly and salaried, to remain mindful of the plant's near-death experience.
"When the crisis is over, people sometimes have a tendency to fall back into old practices and old habits," he said. "Chrysler cannot be the successful company that we all want it to be unless there is a daily true partnership between every worker, hourly and salaried."
Workers said Friday that they were committed to making the Chrysler 200 - and their factory - a success. They even recited a pledge they had written as part of grassroots campaign to improve morale and quality inside the plant.
"Believing gave us the opportunity to reinvent Chrysler, to reinvent SHAP," said Rickey Lawrence, one of the initiators of the campaign. "With that came a huge responsibility to manufacture a quality vehicle, a vehicle we see on the road and we stick our chest out with pride, and we say, 'I built that!'"
It was a theme echoed by Charles Bell, president of UAW Local 1700, which represents workers at the factory.
"If you all believe, we can build the best midsized sedan in America," Bell declared. "Do you believe?"
The plant erupted as workers cheered and shouted that they did.
"Let's do it!" cried one man.
The Chrysler 200 is due to go on sale in the second quarter.
"The success of the Chrysler 200 will ultimately depend upon the pride and of the integrity of the men and the women who work here," Marchionne said.
Bryce.Hoffman@detroitnews.com
(313) 222-2443
Twitter.com/brycehoffman
Chrysler officially began production of the all-new 2015 Chrysler 200 today at a plant that was marked for closure just five years ago.
]]></text></news-item>