<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4658-1282-F832-EE0B"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>CHINESE CHECKERS</title><source>Herald Sun (Australia)</source><author>Samantha Maiden National Political Editor</author><text><![CDATA[EXCLUSIVE FEARS that Chinese investors are pricing first-home buyers out of the market as they plunge $6 billion into Aussie real estate will be investigated by Parliament.
As the rise of China's cashed-up middle class creates new opportunities for Australian developers, Coalition MPs have raised concerns that young families are being locked out of owning their own homes.
Treasurer Joe Hockey will now ask the House of Representatives economics committee to examine whether foreign investment in real estate is being properly policed.
The parliamentary inquiry follows a recent report by Credit Suisse that estimates Chinese investors are snapping up 18 per cent of all new apartments and houses in Sydney and 14 per cent in Melbourne. In Brisbane, an estimated 7 per cent of new apartments are purchased by Chinese investors.
The figures do not include the purchase of existing homes by foreign buyers. The report predicted the growing overseas demand was good news for local building suppliers, construction jobs and developers but was also likely to drive property prices even higher.
Chaired by Victorian MP Kelly O'Dwyer, the parliamentary inquiry will hold public hearings in real estate hot spots including Sydney and Melbourne.
"We need more homes, so foreign investment that increases the number of homes available is a good thing, particularly where it is housing for first-home buyers," she said.
"That is the objective of current policy, but we need to examine what is happening on the ground.
"The great Australian dream to own your own home is hard enough to achieve on two incomes, with years of savings and a large mortgage. We need to make sure that we aren't making it more difficult - which is why we are going to examine the facts in our inquiry." But there are concerns the Foreign Investment Review Board lacks the manpower to police the rules, with the latest data suggesting investment in existing properties by foreign investors is growing.
There are also concerns that rules requiring temporary residents to sell Australian properties when they leave are not being policed.
The terms of reference being prepared for the new inquiry will ask the committee to investigate whether the current rules are adequate and if existing laws are being enforced.
The top investors in Australian real estate, according to the Foreign Investment Review Board, are Chinese families, followed by Canadians, Americans, Singaporeans and Malaysians.The parliamentary inquiry also follows Reserve Bank Governor Glenn Stevens' recent warning that Asian investors' love affair with the east coast was driving demand in Sydney, Melbourne and Brisbane.
]]></text></news-item>