<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4724-E93E-34EF-4BB7"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>New Haven residents voice their concerns about Route 34 West project</title><source>New Haven Register (Connecticut)</source><author>Randall Beach, New Haven Register, Conn.</author><text><![CDATA[March 14--NEW HAVEN -- Some residents who live near the proposed Route 34 West corridor development proposal told members of the Board of Alders Legislation Committee Thursday night they are concerned about more cars and a large parking garage coming into their neighborhood.
The aldermanic legislation committee voted 6-1 to approve the zoning changes for the 16.2 acres of the project, which would extend from Dwight to Tyler streets. The item now moves to the full board for approval. One of the new zoning districts would allow for denser mixed-use retail, commercial development and medical mixed-use. The other would allow for mixed-use retail, residential and office development.
The centerpiece of the project would be a new home for Continuum of Care Inc., a not-for-profit provider for persons with psychiatric and developmental disabilities. Their headquarters would occupy a 5.5 acre block.
The new development, to be developed by Centerplan Development Co., would include construction of a parking garage for about 800 cars.
City Plan Director Karyn Gilvarg, who presented the plan to the committee, noted city officials have held at least 10 community meetings to gather public input about the project.
She said the area would feature "walkable streets" and appropriate scale.
Speaking about design guidelines for the project, Gilvarg said, "We think, we hope, it's an expression of agreement between neighborhood stakeholders and city development officials."
But the first three members of the public who addressed the committee expressed misgivings, mostly about that parking garage.
Mark Griffin said he favors the Continuum Care development. "But we've got enough parking garages as it is." Raising concerns about pollution from vehicles, he said, "A lot of small kids in the area have asthma."
Griffin also objected to a proposed Rite-Aid pharmacy coming in as a tenant.
Lena Largie also expressed worries about more motor vehicles. Already, she said, they are "racing around here, cars going back and forth. We need more people here. We can put more trees in."
She added, "We have too many parking garages over here. Garages, garages, garages. Now we have surface parking, which we were told would be just temporary."
Ohan Karagozian of Hill North said it would be better to do residential development and include small businesses such as grocery stores, restaurants, a barber shop and a hair salon, "to support the people living there."
"Extending this into a business district would be doing a disservice to the entire city, not just the neighborhood," he said.
Karagozian charged the project is intended to benefit Yale-New Haven Hospital. "This is an extension of the hospital into the bosom of the community. Even though there may be a private medical facility initially, Yale has a of slowly homogenizing medical facilities into their umbrella. Allowing a monopoly to grow does not help," he concluded.
Call Randall Beach at 203-789-5766. Do you have questions, feedback or ideas about our news coverage? Connect directly with the editors of the New Haven Register at AskTheRegister.com.
___ (c)2014 the New Haven Register (New Haven, Conn.) Visit the New Haven Register (New Haven, Conn.) at www.nhregister.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>