<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="47C1-2FAD-6CD5-0F32"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>More than 20 people facing prison after drugs ring smashed in Cleveland Police's biggest ever drugs operation; Three people convicted of conspiracy to supply Class A drugs with more than 20 others already pleading guilty to roles in the enterprise</title><source>gazettelive.co.uk</source><author>By Gareth Lightfoot</author><text><![CDATA[More than 20 people are facing prison sentences for their roles in a huge drugs network after a trial came to a close today.
The drugs ring was smashed in Operation Cobweb, Cleveland Police's biggest ever drugs operation.
Three people - 28-year-olds Robert Hickman and Scott Pickering aka Scott McGowan, and Hannah Hesketh, 25 - were all convicted of conspiracy to supply Class A drugs this afternoon.
They had denied the charge but were found guilty by a jury after almost eight hours' consideration at Teesside Crown Court.
A fourth defendant Jordan Harrison, 22, of Briar Road, Thornaby, was cleared by the jurors and released from court.
More than 20 other people, many from Teesside, have pleaded guilty to their roles in the drugs enterprise.
They and Hickman, of Shepherdson Court, South Bank; Pickering, of School Walk, Stockton; and Hesketh, of St James Street, Ashton-under-Lyne, will be sentenced in a two-day hearing at a later date.
Judge Simon Bourne-Arton QC, the Recorder of Middlesbrough, remanded Hickman and Pickering in custody.
Hesketh, who cried in the dock following the unanimous verdicts, was bailed.
The jury of nine women and three men heard of a well-organised network transporting Class A drugs and "vast sums of dirty money" between Manchester and Teesside.
Prosecutor Nick Dry had said: "In 2012 these defendants were part of a larger conspiracy to supply Class A drugs which include heroin, cocaine and crack cocaine.
"It was a well organised enterprise driven by dedicated criminals motivated by the rewards to be had from trafficking large quantities of drugs.
"These drugs were transported from the Greater Manchester area up to Teesside on a regular basis throughout that year, with payment in hard cash heading the other way.
"The Manchester couriers who delivered the drugs and collected the money made over 100 trips up and down the A1 and A19.
"And it's also known that those from Teesside who were involved would sometimes travel down and collect the drugs themselves from the Manchester area, taking with them tens of thousands of pounds.
"The stakes are high, the risks equally high. High-value illegal substances are being transported across the country along with vast sums of dirty money."
He told how the conspirators used "dirty phones" to conduct business and frequently changed numbers to evade detection.
He added: "Dirty phones, drugs phones, call them what you will, used to peddle drugs are a common device of the organised criminal engaged in serious drug dealing, going to great lengths to avoid being identified."
Mr Dry said the drugs ring was headed by people in the Manchester area who had affluent lifestyles and children at private school, including Ben Crombie, 31, from Lancashire.
He said they had access to wholesale quantities of drugs taken to Teesside for distribution.
He added: "There existed a tier, a level of significant drug dealers in this area, some of whom would use or run others to do their dirty work. Robert Hickman was the most prominent amongst them."
A heat-sealing device, large sums of cash and a money-counting machine were seized from Hickman's addresses.
Hickman used more than 20 mobile numbers, Pickering 13, to communicate with co-accused, most of whom pleaded guilty, said Mr Dry.
The jury was told how Pickering was at the same level, and he and Hickman were in regular contact with Crombie.
Pickering was associated with two other men who were involved in a high-speed police chase where almost 2kg of heroin was thrown from a car window.
Hickman used a right-hand man and runners including Danny Wilks, 24, to carry out deals.
Wilks, of Grange Road, Thornaby, had also been in the dock but pleaded guilty in the middle of the trial.
He was "caught red-handed" with half a kilo of cocaine up his jumper and £20,000 cash.
Hesketh was said to have acted as a driver with a courier.
Mr Dry said police pieced together evidence from seizures, arrests, observations and vehicle sightings, and unravelled thousands of communications between dealers.
]]></text></news-item>