<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="47C7-EA84-8F2F-9B2D"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Singson sacks Camarines Norte district engineer By Manilyn Ugalde</title><source>Philippines News Agency</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[LEGAZPI CITY, March 15 -- ' Department of Public Works and Highways secretary Rogelio Singson on Saturday sacked Camarines Norte's district engineer to serve as a warning to those who will not adhere to the 'tuwid na daan' policy of President Aquino.
Removed district engineer Simeon Arias, who had been the district engineer of Camarines Norte since 2009, has been reassigned at the regional office here on a floating status.
Singson has designated former Masbate district engineer Elmer Redrico as Arias' replacement.
Arias' relief came as a surprise to other district engineers and regional officials as, they said, Singson's decision was sudden.
They have the same sentiment over Redrico's designation as he was reportedly relieved in Masbate over the same issue as that of Arias.
Arias, they said, was himself surprised over his sudden relief but he cannot be contacted for comment.
DPWH insiders said Singson does not want to give sensitive positions or assignments to engineers who have pending cases.
In an interview with local reporters, DPWH regional director Danilo Dequito defended the designation of Redrico, saying it was the recommendation of the management committee.
He refused to elaborate on Arias' relief other than saying that the latter will be reporting to the regional office.
Redrico, who was also on a floating assignment at the regional office after his Masbate assignment, had been tapped as the operations officer of the Bicol engineering team that helped in the emergency construction of bunkhouses in Tacloban City for 'Yolanda' victims.
The project had been completed a month ago but not without the issue of alleged substandard works.
According to information gathered, Singson ordered Arias' relief after his projects were found in a review to have failed to comply with the directive of not less than '5-percent variance' between the government cost estimate and the winning bid amount on projects bid out to avoid suspicion of collusion between the DPWH and the bidders.
Review of projects during the past administrations showed a scandalous and glaring closeness in variance between the agency estimate and the winning bid price that usually ranged from 1 to 3 percent, putting the government at a loss and without savings.
In some cases, there were even awarded contracts whose variance were less than one percent and worse, the program of work was highly bloated.
Adding gravity to the decision to relieve Arias was the alleged complaints on project implementation, which are now being investigated.
Prior to Arias' relief, a district engineer at the Abay 3rd district engineering was also relieved last year on the issue of variance and other bidding anomalies.
DPWH insiders, however, said Singson should also fire engineers who were exposed and charged of corruption.
According to documents, at least 42 top DPWH officials and employees have been implicated in a plunder case in 2012 pending before the Office of the Ombudsman involving a P150-million equipment scam.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Philippines News Agency. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>