<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4801-911B-0588-5B49"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Thailand: Study finds Thai tuna processors adhering to international and local labour laws</title><source>Thai News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Thai tuna processors are indeed adhering to international and local labour laws in their dealings with migrant workers, according to a Chulalongkorn University research project, dispelling contrary claims by foreign human rights activists, The Nation reports.
The study, which was revealed on March 12, just a few months prior to the expected annual review by the US State Department for its Human Trafficking in Persons (TIP) report, found that businesses in the Thai tuna industry had followed the labour practices required by the International Labour Organisation and local laws.
The study did not come across any cases of migrant workers entering the country illegally, child or forced labour, human trafficking, violation of human rights or unfair labour treatment.
Commissioned by the Thai Food Processors' Association, the Asian Research Centre for Migration at the university's Institute of Asia Studies took six months last year to conduct interviews of 527 Myanmar and Cambodian migrant workers at 13 tuna plants in Samut Prakan, Samut Sakhon, Songkhla, Rayong and Nakhon Pathom. Professor Suphang Chantavanich, director of the centre, said there remain some areas for improvement, but those deviations from standards mostly were due to misunderstanding of the legal provisions.
However, Andy Hall, a British human rights activist, who attended the seminar on the survey's conclusions on March 12, said the research was "not real".
Scared of losing job
"Since the interviews were conducted at the workplaces, as a person who has been working in this area for 10 years, [i think], it is unlikely that the workers would speak up. Foreign workers are so scared of losing their jobs and thus they wouldn't dare to speak the truth.
"Only two days ago I was just talking with 15, 16 and 17 year-old workers," he said. Suphang said the research team brought their own translators and the workers gave their interviews without fear.
"The workers told us how happy they are at the workplaces. Andy should not try to generalise. Wherever he found the cases, they weren't at the factories where we conducted the research," she said.
Chanintr Chalisarapong, vice president of the association and chairman of its tuna processors' club, said Hall might have run into some exceptional cases since the industry employed as many as 50,000-60,000 workers.
"Based on the [ages on the workers'] passports, every factory uses 18 years old and up workers. If Andy found 14-17-year-old workers, can he provide proof, or can he suggest a system that allows us to prove that? Right now, we abide by the Thai and international laws that use passports as proof," he said.
Thailand's food processors and frozen food operators have expressed concerns that the industry that generates more than Bt180 billion in annual export income for the country will be in bad shape if the US downgrades Thailand to the third tier of countries ranked in the TIP report, after putting it on the second-tier watch list for four years.
Results of the next annual review are expected around June.
Ghanyapad Tantipipatpong, president of association, said Thailand's processed food exports were expected to grow 5 per cent this year, thanks partly to the recovery of the tuna industry.
Related report
Expert discredits tuna worker study
Chulalongkorn University's research into Thailand's tuna industry has found the country takes good care of its migrant workers, but some labour advocates doubt the findings, the Bangkok Post reports.
The Asian Research Centre for Migration of Chulalongkorn University's Institute of Asian Studies interviewed 527 Myanmar and Cambodian people working for 13 tuna food manufacturers in Samut Prakan, Samut Sakhon, Songkhla, Rayong and Nakhon Pathom, between February and June last year.
Ratchada Chaiyakupt, head of the research project on problems of alien labour in the tuna industry, said on March 12 that 87% of the interviewees were satisfied with their work and 95% did not want to change their job.
According to her, the workers said they had good wages that comply with laws and comfortable working conditions. All the interviewees said they were employed legally, they did not face abuse or sexual harassment and were neither victims of child or forced labour. The interviewees included six pregnant workers who said they enjoyed legal protection and had not been discriminated against after falling pregnant.
The research found the workers paid 5,000-20,000 baht each for the job placements in Thailand. Some of them had paid the total fee before their arrival while others opted to pay in installments.
Their employers had been urged to pay them overtime at a legal rate. Based on the minimum daily wage of 300 baht, overtime should be 56.25 baht per hour, but the workers actually received 51-54 baht an hour.
Employers were prohibited by labour laws from deducting fees for accommodation, water and electricity from workers' wages, or from keeping workers' passports without the employees' consent.
Employers were also urged to make available written details of workers' rights in the native languages of their employees.
Supang Chantavanich, director of the Asian Research Centre for Migration, said she was relieved that 98% of the enterprises studied obeyed laws and relevant conventions of the International Labour Organisation, and that neither child nor forced labour were present. She pointed out the research covered only the tuna food industry.
During a presentation of the research, adviser to the State Enterprises Workers Relation Confederation, Andy Hall, praised Thailand's tuna food industry for its job creation and considerable exports, but argued against some important aspects of the research.
He pointed out that the research had been carried out by interviews with employees at their workplaces, so it was unlikely completely true information was given.
He said inaccurate replies from the workers compromised the reliability of the research's conclusion.
He also contradicted the study's claim the tuna food industry in Thailand was free of child labour, saying he had met workers aged 14-17.
He added that workers in the industry faced problems with their job brokers' fees and employers withholding important documents such as passports.
Chanintr Chalisarapong, chairman of the Tuna Processors' Group of the Thai Food Processors' Association, said that operators were trying to meet higher standards to help Thailand be removed from the human-trafficking watch list.
]]></text></news-item>