<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="485B-FB68-2CF9-FD40"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Cloaks, daggers and the CIA</title><source>The Roanoke Times (Virginia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Congress needs to get to the bottom of Sen. Dianne Feinstein's astonishing allegations of a CIA attempt to intimidate congressional staffers investigating the spy agency's past actions.
Feinstein, a Democrat and chairwoman of the Senate Intelligence Committee, can have no partisan motive in roiling these waters. And she has been a firm supporter of the agency, even defending the CIA's controversial use of armed drones to kill terrorists overseas.
When she publicly accuses the CIA under President Obama of breaking the law against domestic spying and violating the Constitution's separation of powers, the country should pay rapt attention and demand a full accounting.
Congressional leaders and members of the intelligence oversight committees need to look with healthy skepticism on CIA Director John Brennan's quick dismissal of Feinstein's accusations against his agency. Dissimilation and diversion, after all, are tools of the clandestine trades.
Yet, as the committee's ranking Republican, Sen. Saxby Chambliss, said after a two-hour classified meeting Tuesday, "Right now, we don't know what the facts are." Which points to a need for a full investigation by the Senate or a special prosecutor.
Either can descend quickly into a divisive partisan witch hunt. That appears unlikely in this case, though, for the same reason Republican leaders have not stepped quickly to the microphones to demand action.
The Obama administration would be the target of scrutiny into alleged CIA attempts to suppress a scathing, still classified Senate report on the agency's post-9/11 detention and enhanced interrogation (i.e. torture) program - started in the George W. Bush administration.
Both parties stand to be embarrassed.
Obama ended the program upon taking office. But he has not declassified the Senate Intelligence Committee's 60,000-page report, completed last year after years of study.
The New York Times reported last week: "People who have read the study said it is a withering indictment of the program and details many instances when CIA officials misled Congress, the White House and the public about the value of the agency's brutal interrogation methods, including waterboarding."
Feinstein this week accused the CIA of searching computers used by committee investigators and removing some documents, and of asking the FBI to investigate how some came into the committee's possession - an effort, she said, to intimidate staffers.
If even part of this is true, the agency will have acted outside the law and defied oversight by the elected government that ultimately answers to the public.
Neither party will cover itself in glory by uncovering this festering ulcer on the body politic and exposing the report, and the drama surrounding it, to the light of public scrutiny. But it is essential to America's narrative that, imperfect though the nation is, it is exceptional in its ability to bare painful truths and learn from them.
Let's make it so.
]]></text></news-item>