<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4869-5C06-97E5-41F1"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>HELPING CHINA?S CHILDREN; U-T profiles of notable local people</title><source>The San Diego Union-Tribune</source><author>STORY BY NINA GARIN, PHOTO BY K.C. ALFRED, U-T</author><text><![CDATA[Growing up in Southwest China, Hongmei Shen experienced firsthand the struggles rural children — specifically girls — encounter when trying to get a good education.
Thanks to good teachers and volunteers, Shen became the first person in her family to attend and graduate from college.
Now, Shen is an associate professor and coordinator for San Diego State University’s School of Journalism & Media Studies, but she continues to reach out to the children back in her home country.
The San Carlos resident volunteers for Overseas China Education Foundation.
Q: What is the Overseas China Education Foundation (OCEF)?
A: It’s a nonprofit organization dedicated to improving rural education in China, operating primarily on unpaid volunteers. We believe that every child deserves equal access to quality education, regardless of his/her gender, ethnicity, religion, birthplace and socio-economic status.
Q: How is OCEF reaching these kids?
A: Through its library, teachers’ training, financial aid/scholarship, and special programs, OCEF has raised $2.5 million in donations to support 440,000 rural students in 22 provinces and regions. It has also built over 610 libraries and sent 410,000 books for kids to read. Behind these numbers is the hard work of our 4,000 unpaid volunteers both in the U.S. and in China. They inspected schools, visited students’ homes, tracked student growth, and ensured the best use of all donated funds.
Q: Why did you become involved?
A: Simple. I was once that schoolgirl in need of help. I was born and raised in Sichuan Province, Southwest China. To many Chinese students, education is the only way out of poverty. I almost couldn’t go to high school due to family financial situations, if it was not for a teacher who helped.
Q: You particularly focus on the inequalities of girls in remote villages. Why?
A: Traditional gender roles are expected of girls. They often are the first to be asked to drop out of school and/or expected to marry early, due to Chinese parents’ favoritism for boys. With little sex education available, these girls sometimes fall victim to sexual abuse and/or assault. Another layer of the problem is their lack of life skills and, as a result, a lack of self-awareness and self-esteem.
Q: Why is this an issue Westerners should be concerned about?
A: Gender equality is a basic human rights issue. Educating girls in developing countries like China is a powerful way to tackle global poverty, build communities, and reduce health risks. These girls in remote villages in China are just like your own daughters, with simple dreams as being able to attend school.
Q: Do you think college students are informed enough about global issues?
A: Many are. Quite a few of my students at SDSU take advantage of study abroad programs to learn about other cultures. Some volunteer for global charities. In this mobile age, global has become local to many students.
Q: Have your own students been involved?
A: One of my students joined SDSU’s poverty-alleviation summer exchange program in China in 2011. After two weeks of teaching English at a remote village in South China, he decided to stay in China after graduation. The experience helped him see who he wants to be and what he wants to do in life.
Q: What is one thing people would be surprised to find out about you?
A: I am not a kung fu master, even though I’m from China. But I’m a passionate hiker who just climbed Africa’s highest mountain, Kilimanjaro, and wishes to conquer Mount Everest one day.
Q: What is the best advice you ever received?
A: From “Finding Nemo”: When life gets you down, do you wanna know what you’ve gotta do? Just keep swimming. Just keep swimming.
Q: Please describe your ideal San Diego weekend.
A: Morning hike at Cowles Mountain, followed by a brunch at La Jolla Cove, a stroll and afternoon reading in Balboa Park, sunset walk at Windansea, ending with stargazing on top of Soledad Mountain. These are some of my favorite spots in San Diego. What I love about San Carlos …
I live nearby Mission Trails Park. Growing up in a small mountainous town in China, I have always loved the solitude of mountains. Standing atop Cowles Mountain at sunset time, I often feel humbled and blessed to admire the whole city and beyond. It is one of the highlights of my week.
]]></text></news-item>