<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4881-A98C-7596-BFEA"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>House OKs bill to deter 'revenge porn'; Senate panel to review</title><source>Knoxville News-Sentinel (Tennessee)</source><author>Tom Humphrey</author><text><![CDATA[Senate to review ‘revenge porn’ bill after House votes to deter
NASHVILLE — The state House has unanimously approved legislation intended to deter what the Democratic sponsor calls “revenge porn” and now moves on to a Senate committee vote under sponsorship of state Sen. Stacey Campfield, R-Knoxville.
The bill, HB2201, makes it a misdemeanor to distribute a picture or video of an “intimate part” of another person’s body without permission and with an intent to cause “emotional distress.” A typical situation, House Democratic Caucus Chairman Mike Turner said in a floor speech, would come when “some girl makes a mistake and shows an intimate part of her body to her boyfriend, they break up and he sends it out on a cell phone.” Rep. Sheila Butt, R-Columbia, said political opponents had once distributed photographs where “my face was put on other people’s bodies” and asked whether that would be covered by the bill. Turner said it would not, though he believes such an occurrence could already be considered illegal as fraud. House debate also included Rep. Andy Holt, R-Dresden, questioning Turner, known as one of the more liberal members of the Legislature, about collaborating with conservative activist Campfield, whom Turner called “my dear friend” at one point. “We disagree about 80 percent of the time,” Turner said, then added their agreement on the bill is perhaps “in the two percent category.” Holt said the alignment shows “the great compromise that can come about on the state level.” Campfield has the bill scheduled for a vote Tuesday in the Senate Judiciary Committee. Charter schools management: Legislation authorizing charter schools to be managed by for-profit companies has won approval of committees in the House and Senate. The measure, SB1684, was approved by the Senate Education Committee and the House Education Subcommittee with Democrats voting no and Republicans voting yes with two exceptions. The exceptions were Rep. John Forgety, R-Athens, who voted no on the House panel, and Sen. Steve Dickerson, R-Nashville, who voted no on the Senate panel. Senate Education Committee Chairman Delores Gresham, R-Somerville, the Senate sponsor, said Tennessee is one of just six states that prohibit charter schools from contracting with for-profit companies for management services. “As charter schools grow in Tennessee, they deserve every management tool in their tool box,” she said. Sen. Reginald Tate, D-Memphis, argued against the measure, contending a single corporation could get management contracts with charter schools statewide for private profits from public education. “I think it opens the door for monopolies,” Tate said. The bill now awaits a floor vote in the Senate while the full House Education Committee is scheduled to debate it this week. The House bill is sponsored by Rep. John DeBerry, D-Memphis. AG says electrocution acceptable: The state attorney general says a bill to authorize electrocution as an alternative means of carrying out the death penalty in Tennessee could withstand legal challenges under the state and U.S. constitutions. Rep. Dennis Powers, R-Jacksboro, and Sen. Ken Yager, R-Harriman, requested the formal opinion from Attorney General Bob Cooper. They are sponsors of SB2580, which declares that if the state’s current lethal injection procedure for executions is deemed invalid by courts or the necessary drugs become unavailable, electrocution will then be used. The bill is up for its first House committee hearing Tuesday. “If enacted as proposed, SB2580’s conditional imposition of electrocution would be defensible against a challenge under the constitutional prohibition against cruel and unusual punishment,” says the opinion, outlining various state and federal court decisions to support the view. ’Trail of Tears’ renounced: The House has approved a resolution renouncing Tennessee’s involvement in the 1830 removal of Indians from the state and hailing Davy Crockett for opposing what is now known as the Trail of Tears at the time. The Senate, meanwhile, has approved a resolution calling for a statue of Crockett to be placed at the state Capitol. The Trail of Tears resolution (HJR553), sponsored by House Republican Caucus Chairman Glen Casada, was approved unanimously by the House. It reads, in part: “We, the citizens of Tennessee, wish to close this chapter in our collective history, so that our past does not cast a shadow over our future. Tennesseans stand against acts of injustice perpetrated against any people or group regardless of race, gender, or religion. “Therefore, we offer our sincere regret to the Cherokee, Chickasaw, Yuchi, Creek, Choctaw, and Shawnee Nations and all Native American Nations who were tragically and unjustly confined and removed from their lands by our participation in the Removal Act of 1830 and the subsequent death march known as the Trail of Tears. “Greed and prejudice have no part to play in the future of Tennessee. We stand today as David Crockett stood, prepared to lay down our lives in defense of freedom for all people in this great nation.” Davy Crockett statue: The Senate has unanimously approved SJR505, sponsored by Senate Majority Leader Mark Norris, to have the State Capitol Commission locate a statue of Crockett inside the state Capitol building. The first step would be a contest with sculptors submitting plans for creation of the monument. There is already a statue of Andrew Jackson, who as president engineered the Removal Act of 1830 over Crockett’s protests, astride a horse on the lawn of the Capitol and a separate bust inside. Crockett, born in Greene County, lived in Jefferson County, Lincoln County, Franklin County, Lawrence County and Gibson County before leaving the state for Texas, where he died at the Alamo during Texas’ war with Mexico. During the House floor discussion of the Trail of Tears resolution, Casada said he has engaged in discussions for a resolution “soon” to apologize for Tennessee’s support of slavery.
]]></text></news-item>