<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4992-BED0-0DCC-94F3"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Failure to listen drives protests</title><source>Sowetan (South Africa)</source><author>George Matlala</author><text><![CDATA['Government fails to respond adequately to grievances' Deputy Political Editor THE increase in service delivery protests around the country was in part due to the government's failure to listen to angry poor communities, and an unstable public service beset by perceptions of corruption.
This is revealed in the government's 20-year review, released by President Jacob Zuma on Tuesday. The report - which recorded government's performance for the past two decades - states the trend of service delivery protests could be blamed on the fact that councillors were estranged from their communities. Councillors and municipalities are the first contact communities have with the ANC government. The public service on the whole is the vehicle through which government delivers its promises to the people, as contained in the manifesto for the May 7 elections. The National Development Plan, the country's 30-year blueprint, states that the government's ability to achieve its developmental goals requires an effective public service. Although the government has taken steps to strengthen public service, the review paints a picture of a state still emerging from the challenges of the past and grappling with the ones created by democracy, such as political interference and lack of capacity. "The increase in the service delivery protests provides visible evidence that the state is struggling to ensure that poor communities feel that they are being heard ... Attention needs to be given to improving accountability mechanisms for routine day-to-day interactions between citizens and the state, particularly at the point of delivery. This includes enabling citizens to provide direct feedback on the quality of services..." the report states. Political jostling for resources in government has had a negative impact on public service delivery. "Over the past 20 years, South Africa has experienced high levels of instability in the top levels of administrative leadership. This has been a particular challenge during the transitions between administrations, when the arrival of new ministers and members of the executive council [MECs] can lead to sudden changes in senior management as new ministers and MECs often prefer to appoint heads of department," the review says. However, the government has been able to achieve successes in the quality of service in that front-line staff treated people with dignity at about 300 state service centres between 2011 and 2013, according to the report. The Zuma administration has also moved swiftly to establish the National School of Government to improve service and skills. And, the government has also put measures in place to prevent public servants from doing business with the state in an attempt to curb corruption and issues of conflict of interest. The review found youth unemployment a concern. "The estimated unemployment rate for the youth in this age group [18 to 29] rose from 30% in 1994 to 40% in 2013 and the number of unemployed youth doubled from 1.3million." PLANNING: President Jacob Zuma REALITY CHECK: The 20-year review of the government's performance says that the increase in service delivery protests provides visible evidence that the state is struggling to ensure that poor communities feel that they are being heard Photo: Simphiwe nkwali
]]></text></news-item>