<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="49CC-7003-C187-3B28"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>AAP accuses Mumbai-based Netcore of sharing mobile database of nearly 1.5 crore people with BJP</title><source>The Economic Times</source><author>Sruthijith K K</author><text><![CDATA[NEW DELHI: Even as Aam Aadmi Party (AAP) and Bhartiya Janata Party (BJP) are emerging as the bitterest rivals this election season, a vast database of mobile phone numbers is becoming a bone of contention.
A senior AAP official has accused Netcore Solutions, a Mumbai-based vendor of communication services to both AAP and the BJP, of sharing its database with the latter. The accusation is problematic because Netcore's promoter Rajesh Jain is a prominent outside supporter of Narendra Modi's campaign and convenor of Friends of BJP, an official cell of the party.
"One fine day I and a number of my friends who were working with AAP started getting SMSes from the BJP. Obviously none of us had signed up for it. That made us suspicious that our database was being shared with the BJP," said Ankit Lal, AAP's IT head and a member of its national council. "We raised it with the Netcore people who used to come here to work with us. And they said they would never do something like that. But we then scaled down their involvement and started using other vendors," Lal said.
The database in question had mobile numbers of 1.5 crore people who must express their consent to receive messages once every six months. While large databases are reportedly available in the market for a small price, marketers don't like to work with them as they result in poor targetting. A 1.5 crore-strong database of numbers that have people who have opted in to receive messages from a party, is significantly valuable. The database is a key reason why AAP is able to quickly mobilize support and volunteers. Lal said they have segregated it by state and by categories of interest so that it is cost effective.
Netcore MD Jain directed queries to CEO Girish Nair, who dismissed the allegation as "baseless". "We take client database privacy very seriously. There is no question of sharing the database," he said. He confirmed that AAP had raised the issue with Netcore. Nair explained that while Netcore is also in the business of selling databases to clients, those are gleaned by the company from various public sources legally and tested to separate active numbers.
But the database that helps AAP reach a large number of people instantly, is also of controversial provenance. The database belonged to India Against Corruption, the umbrella entity under which the anti-corruption movement featuring Anna Hazare began long before Arvind Kejriwal branched out to form a political party. The IAC had carried out a massive campaign in which you could make a missed call to a number to register as a supporter. Jain's Netcore implemented that campaign.
Lal has been with Kejriwal since the IAC days and used to handle the database and the website, which was used by more than 2 lakh volunteers to sign up.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>