<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4A69-6158-EE16-28F4"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>ViewPoint: Upcoming ban on food waste should be boon for state</title><source>Boston Business Journal</source><author>Staff</author><text><![CDATA[On Oct. 1, 2014, Massachusetts will ban the landfilling of food waste. This ban will affect nearly 1,700 non-residential facilities disposing of over one ton of food waste per week, saving Massachusetts' limited landfill capacity, and creating opportunities for a host of Massachusetts businesses.
About 25 percent of Massachusetts' solid waste is organic trash that consumes valuable and dwindling landfill capacity and, as it breaks down, contributes to greenhouse gas emissions. Most of that waste can be put to better uses - whether by feeding people, ensuring a reliable feedstock for operators of anaerobic digestion units, or providing opportunities, including for Massachusetts farmers, to operate commercial compost facilities.
In addition, by reducing the amount of organic material rotting in Massachusetts landfills and by expanding renewable energy options, the waste ban should help Massachusetts meet its statutory obligation to reduce greenhouse emissions by 25 percent below 1990 levels by 2020 and by 80 percent below 1990 levels by 2050.
The food waste ban will affect hotels, colleges, hospitals, convention centers, corporate campuses and grocery chains, among others. State Department of Environmental Protection regulations will implement the ban. Whether the ban applies to a particular facility depends on the nature of that facility's operations. For example, total food waste from multiple facility sites like chain restaurants will be calculated per facility, but college and corporate campuses will be subject to campus-wide thresholds. For seasonal businesses, the ban will not apply during periods when a facility produces little or no waste.
Facilities that are subject to the ban can select from a host of alternatives from waste reduction and food donation to diverting waste for use as animal feed, to commercial composting facilities, to anaerobic digestion facilities that use biological processes to produce heat and generate electricity from organic waste material. In an effort to accommodate the food waste ban and to expand its renewable energy capacity, Massachusetts has already made it easier to site anaerobic digestion facilities.
While there are likely to be bumps on the road to full implementation - think of the neighbors of a poorly maintained commercial compost facility - and while we can only speculate on whether, in this case, one person's trash really will become another person's treasure, it's certain that these regulations will reduce waste. And that's a goal that all business people, environmentalists, and citizens of the commonwealth should be able to support.
Katy E. Ward and Colin G. Van Dyke are associates in the environmental law practice at Mintz, Levin, Cohn, Ferris, Glovsky and Popeo in Boston.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Boston Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>