<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4ADE-EBF2-B08A-F2A3"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Canada aims to end EU seal ban; Officials make last effort to convince World Trade Organization</title><source>Ottawa Citizen</source><author>Louis Turcotte, Ottawa Citizen</author><text><![CDATA[This week the final act of a Canadian drama on ice will unfold, not in the Arctic, but in a courtroom in Switzerland.
Beginning Monday, Canadian officials will make a lastditch effort to convince the World Trade Organization to end the European Union's ban on the sale of seal products.
The much-politicized ban was first enacted in 2009, and it was upheld in November 2013 against a Canadian appeal. The decision of this week's panel will be rendered in mid-April. This will mark the end of a process that has fired up both opponents and supporters of the hunt.
For sealers, the hunt is a traditional activity, a part of coastal culture and a way to not only feed their families but also make supplementary income outside of the fishing season. The majority of commercial sealing is done in the Maritimes, off the coast of Newfoundland and in the Gulf of the St. Lawrence, but indigenous populations in the Arctic also rely on the hunt for subsistence.
"To me, the (EU) ban is Orwellian," says Terry Audla, president of the Inuit Tapiriit Kanatami, which represents Canada's 55,000 Inuit. "It's highly judgmental about how we Inuit rely on the seal, and the Europeans assume we have other means."
Audla says the ban has been devastating for small communities that rely on the sale of seal furs to survive. The EU seal ban has an exemption in place for indigenous hunters, but Audla says this is meaningless because the Inuit rely on the broader Canadian seal industry to sell their products, and without them they have no way to reach the European market.
Historically, the trade in seal products has been driven by foreign demand. A number
of countries, from the United States to Russia, have banned the sale of seal products over the years, but it is the 2009 EU ban that hit hardest. From 2006 to 2012, the Canadian sealing industry went from netting $18 million to around $1.35 million.
"Because of the ban, the market has shrunk significantly," says Gail Shea, Canada's minister of fisheries and oceans, "but (the Canadian government is) going to continue to support the seal hunt."
Shea says her department will continue working with the sealing industry to develop new products and explore new markets. Asian countries such as Japan and South Korea have bought significant amounts of seal meat, but China is now considering following the EU and banning the sale of seal products.
The EU seal ban was enacted in 2009. Animal rights activists had long petitioned European parliamentarians to oppose what they describe as "the largest mass slaughter of marine mammals in the world."
But David Dakins, a chairman of the Seals and Sealing Network, says the industry has taken many steps to professionalize, regulate and enforce humane hunting methods in the industry.
A native of Newfoundland, Dakins is also chief executive of Carino, Canada's largest seal-processing company.
To him, the seal ban no longer rests on an issue of humaneness, but on sensibilities. The seal hunt may look horrific, he says, but it is no different from the killing of other animals in the commercial sector.
"Most people are not accustomed to, or exposed to having to see where their beef, or where their chicken, or where their leather belt or their leather shoes or their Prada bags, how they originate," says Dakins.
The fact that the seal hunt happens in open air and provides striking images of bright red blood on the pristine ice of the North Atlantic makes it an easy target for animal activists, he says.
Rebecca Aldworth is also a native of Newfoundland. As executive director of the Humane Society International in Canada, she has campaigned for years for an end to the hunt, during which she says she has observed countless acts of brutality. She's also critical of the support the government gives to the sealing industry.
"Supporting the seal hunt, politically and openly, is a cheap way for the federal government to look as though they're standing with residents in rural communities in Atlantic Canada," she says.
"In fact, they're doing very little to address the real economic problems that exist there," something she says would cost millions.
Aldworth says the only proper solution to end the hunt is to buy out the seal industry, a move she says would save an enormous amount of money for the federal government. Sealers, she says, could follow whalers in the '80s, who turned to tourism and the whale-watching industry for work after an international whale-hunting moratorium.
For Terry Audla, the argument doesn't hold water. "Of course there are alternatives; there are always alternatives," he says, "I could become a vegetarian if I wanted to, but I'm not going to." And the Inuit, he says, should not be pushed into alternatives over foreign sensibilities.
This year, weather conditions have made sea ice form farther offshore, making the seal hunt less accessible and more dangerous. But bad weather won't rain on the sealing parade as much as upholding of the seal ban would.
International trade lawyer Robert Howse, it is highly unlikely that Canada will be able to overturn the European Union's ban on the sale of seal products.
"It will be virtually impossible for Canada to win the appeal," says Howse, "because appeals at the WTO can only be founded on issues of law, not issues of fact." And because the WTO panel previously concluded it is impossible to prove beyond doubt the humaneness of the seal hunt, the ban will most likely stand, says Howse.
lturcotte@ottawacitizen.com
]]></text></news-item>