<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4BB9-FD52-4615-F977"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>A low-level lawyer and a high-stakes indictment for accounting fraud; Common Sense</title><source>International New York Times</source><author>JAMES B. STEWART</author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
''You've been indicted,'' an assistant district attorney in New York, Peirce R. Moser, told Zachary Warren, a 29-year-old magna cum laude graduate of Georgetown Law School with a prestigious clerkship on the Federal Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit in Memphis.
''Can you say that again?'' a stunned Mr. Warren asked when he received the call two weeks ago on Friday.
Almost as surprised as Mr. Warren himself were Mr. Warren's cellmates before his arraignment last Thursday - the top managers of Dewey & LeBoeuf, the global law firm that imploded in 2012. Although some of them had trouble remembering who Mr. Warren was, the indictment says that all four were co-conspirators in a major accounting fraud. The firm's chairman, executive director and chief financial officer, ages 60, 57 and 55, had long known that they were the subjects of a criminal investigation. All had prominent criminal lawyers, whose fees were paid by a Dewey & LeBoeuf insurance policy.
But Mr. Warren was so low-level he isn't covered by the firm's insurance policy. He hired a lawyer only after the phone call that Friday.
Alone among the defendants, Mr. Warren was charged in two separate indictments, one accusing him of a ''scheme to defraud'' and the other, which was sealed, charging him with six felony counts of false entries in books and records. Mr. Warren pleaded not guilty and was released on $200,000 bail.
How did Mr. Warren end up as an accused mastermind of what the New York district attorney, Cyrus Vance Jr., called ''a massive effort to cook the books.''
According to several criminal defense lawyers I spoke with this past week, Mr. Warren became caught up in an increasingly common prosecutorial tactic. Mr. Warren thought he was being questioned as part of a civil Securities and Exchange Commission investigation. He thought he might be a witness, and thus did not need a lawyer. Defense lawyers said prosecutors were increasingly using so-called parallel investigations to insert criminal investigators into what their targets thought were civil proceedings.
''It's a serious threat to civil liberties, and people should know about it,'' said Thomas J. Curran, a criminal defense lawyer in New York and a former prosecutor under the former New York district attorney Robert Morgenthau. Mr. Curran added, ''They're using civil proceedings to advance their criminal investigations. It's a real threat to the cherished right to counsel.''
A spokeswoman for the New York district attorney, Erin Duggan Kramer, said that was not the case. ''The claim that an attorney with a federal clerkship could have any misunderstanding of what it means to speak with and agree to meet with the D.A.'s office is preposterous,'' she said.
Mr. Warren thought he was far removed from the troubles of Dewey & LeBoeuf, since he left long before the 2010 bond offering that is the focus of the S.E.C.'s civil fraud charges. Mr. Warren was a 24-year-old Stanford graduate when he was offered a $40,000-a-year job helping partners collect client debts. He was promoted to ''client relations manager'' in June 2008, earning a salary of $100,000 a year.
Mr. Warren saw his stint at Dewey & LeBoeuf as a way station to law school. His father is a retired California state court judge, and his mother is a professor at William & Mary's Marshall-Wythe School of Law.
Mr. Warren excelled at Georgetown, where he was articles editor of the law review. He landed a coveted clerkship on the Federal District Court in Baltimore with Judge J. Frederick Motz, and then on the Sixth Circuit with Judge Julia Smith Gibbons. He is a member of the California and District of Columbia bars, and has a job offer from the prestigious Washington law firm Williams & Connolly.
''Zack is a wonderful person, a decent, fine young man,'' Judge Motz told me during the past week. ''I'm so sorry he's being put through what's happening.''
For Mr. Warren, the first inkling of potential trouble came early last year, when he received a call from prosecutors in the New York district attorney's office. Mr. Warren answered questions and provided what he interpreted as background information, according to accounts he subsequently gave to his friends.
In late October, an S.E.C. lawyer investigating the bond offering contacted him. Mr. Warren had nothing to do with it, and because he had not been subpoenaed, he was under no obligation to testify. But he wanted to be helpful and cooperative, and he agreed to take time off from work in Memphis and travel to New York, at his own expense, to provide what he continued to think was just background information in a civil investigation. Then, in a subsequent call, an S.E.C. lawyer told him that a lawyer from the district attorney's office would be sitting in. Did Mr. Warren mind?
This is what upsets Mr. Curran, the defense lawyer. ''You want to cooperate, you agree to a meeting, then, whoa, the district attorney is in there,'' he said. ''They say, 'You don't have a problem with that, do you?' What can you say?''
Perhaps by now he should have realized that this was anything but a friendly interview. But Mr. Warren had no involvement with the $150 million bond offering that he thought was the focus of the investigation.
Mr. Warren arrived at the S.E.C. offices on Nov. 15. After the S.E.C. lawyer asked some introductory questions, Mr. Moser, the assistant district attorney, took over. An F.B.I. agent was also present, and other prosecutors were listening from New York.
By all accounts, the interview was a disaster for Mr. Warren. He had trouble remembering details from his time at the firm, which prosecutors interpreted as evasion or, worse, lying. They showed him emails and documents, most of which he did not recall. He was not prepared for the hostile tone and became defensive.
Mr. Warren asked, ''Should I hire an attorney? Maybe I shouldn't be talking to you.'' The prosecutor said he couldn't advise people whether they should have lawyers.
This, in any event, is what Mr. Warren has told his friends. Others familiar with the interview insist that he was told point-blank to hire a lawyer and that he was in jeopardy.
Mr. Warren went to see a former Georgetown classmate and fellow District Court clerk right after the meeting. He thought that he might be subpoenaed to appear before a grand jury as a witness.
As the year was drawing to a close, the five-year statute of limitations was about to expire, since some of the events in which Mr. Warren was involved occurred on Dec. 31, 2008. The three other defendants - the firm's top-ranking officers - were all asked if they would voluntarily extend the statute of limitations, which is usually a routine request. They agreed. But no one contacted Mr. Warren, which would have put him on notice that he was a target and would need a lawyer to negotiate the extension. Instead, prosecutors obtained a secret indictment from a grand jury against Mr. Warren alone, which was sealed. The indictment charged him with six felony counts of false entries in books and records.
Mr. Warren heard nothing until he received the news of his indictments. Ordered to appear in court, he finally said, ''I think I'd better check with a lawyer.'' A lawyer for Mr. Warren, Martin S. Himeles Jr., declined to comment.
Mr. Warren spent last weekend in Washington, with his law school classmates and other friends. I asked his fellow clerk how he was faring. ''He's scared,'' he said. ''He's tired.''
Judge Gibbons continues to employ him as a clerk, and Williams & Connolly has not withdrawn its job offer.
Whatever the outcome, Mr. Warren's case has been the talk of the criminal defense bar. ''The whole thing is bizarre. On its face, it seems outrageous, it's over the top,'' Mr. Curran said, adding that there ''must be a reason the district attorney proceeded against this young kid this way, and I and a lot of other people will be very interested to hear what it is.''
]]></text></news-item>