<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4BC2-0F34-3465-2CC2"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>PROTEST MARKS FUKUSHIMA DISASTER</title><source>Press Association Mediapoint</source><author>Raziye Akkoc, Press Association</author><text><![CDATA[More than 100 protesters have rallied against nuclear power following the third anniversary of the Fukushima disaster in Japan.
Protesters held placards and banners calling for ``no nuclear power'', ``protect mountains, rivers'' and ``no new nukes'' with signs in English, French and Japanese. As the march progressed through central London, the crowd chanted ``no more nuclear'' and ``no more Fukushima''.
The organisers hoped the march would send a message warning of the dangers of nuclear power as well as remembering the victims of the Fukushima disaster on March 11, 2011.
Shigeo Kobayashi, a spokesman for Japanese Against Nuclear UK (JAN), told the crowd decisions about nuclear energy were being made on the basis of politics and economics rather than people and safety.
``Companies have large profits but when things go wrong, society and people deal with damage and losses,'' he said.
``In Japan, families have been broken up and children cannot play outside because radiation levels are too high. The people that are paying the price are the Japanese people dealing with the contaminated area.''
He went on: ``Nuclear energy is not a necessary evil. Safer and cleaner energy solutions exist, they are only a matter of political choice. This is why we shouldn't forget Fukushima. We must remember, learn and act to build a better world.''
David Polden, who helped organise the protest, said: ``We're here because it's the third anniversary of the Fukushima disaster. We're trying to remember the victims and point out that the damage is still continuing with water (used to cool reactors) flowing into the Pacific and the main buildings are in a very bad state. It's still very dangerous.''
Mr Polden, a London region worker for the Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament (CND), added: ``The message we want to send is 'stop nuclear'. There are plans in Japan to reopen nuclear power stations but the majority of Japanese people are against them and there are plans for power stations here in the UK.''
The Chernobyl, Fukushima and Three Mile Island disasters all illustrated the danger of nuclear power, he said.
The protesters gathered at Hyde Park Corner in central London before marching past the Japanese Embassy and one of the buildings housing the Tokyo Electric Company.
Green Party leader Natalie Bennett spoke of her fears about the impact of nuclear energy in the UK.
``Since the anniversary, I have been reflecting on realities,'' she said.
``The disaster made 340,000 nuclear refugees. We don't want to see the same thing happening to British cities like Bristol or Cardiff.''
Fashion designer Katharine Hamnett called on the crowd to change the current political system.
She said: ``I'm calling for a devolution where we have everything decided by referendum and a government like the government of Switzerland. We can do it, and we can do it quite simply.''
]]></text></news-item>