<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4C00-0807-BDCB-1EE8"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>ISU grad students make revitalization proposals</title><source>Des Moines Register</source><author>By, Melanie Lageschulte</author><text><![CDATA[| mlagesch@dmreg.com
An outdoor gathering space, support for local businesses and more recreational trails are among the suggested improvements for the Capitol East and Capitol Park neighborhoods under revitalization proposals going before city officials.
Graduate students in a community and regional planning program at Iowa State University gathered input from residents, business owners and neighborhood leaders in the fall to create the plans. The project was part of an ongoing partnership between the university and the city.
Des Moines city planner Amber Lynch, who received her master's degree from ISU, helped set up the program with professor Jane Rongerude. Educators seek real-world projects for students and Lynch said the need to update Des Moines' neighborhood plans is a perfect fit.
With more than 50 neighborhoods and just four city planners, "we can only do so many at a time," Lynch said. "It's been a great extension for us."
The students evaluated the city's neighborhood-based service programs in fall 2011, Lynch said. Students then updated revitalization plans for the Woodland Heights and Beaverdale areas in fall 2012 before taking on Capitol East and Capitol Park.
Lynch said the partnership will extend to other neighborhood proposals. "We expect that they will be part of River Bend, coming up later this year, in some way."
Capitol East is bounded by Interstate Highway 235 to the north, the railroad tracks to the south and east, and East 14th Street to the west. Capitol Park borders are East Washington Avenue on the north, I-235 on the south, East 14th Street on the east and the Des Moines River on the west.
Approved
The suggestions for Capitol East and Capitol Park have been approved by the neighborhood associations in those areas and moved on to the Neighborhood Revitalization Board last week. They also will go before the Plan and Zoning Commission and the City Council for approval.
The updated neighborhood revitalization plans will become part of the city's comprehensive plans once they are approved. Polk County leaders also will get a look at the ideas.
ISU graduate student Marie Louise Ryan will present the plans at the meetings. The 14 students in the class divided into two teams to work on the Capitol East and Capitol Park projects, Ryan said. Some students in each group gathered feedback and others served on steering committees with neighborhood leaders, city staff, business owners and other stakeholders.
Ryan said the proposals identify groups and organizations that could help see each project through, "so that the plan becomes more than just paperwork."
While the research was done during the fall semester, Ryan said some students began work in the summer, "kind of getting a feel for the neighborhoods themselves and establishing contacts in those neighborhoods."
Conducting door-to-door surveys, meeting with business owners, talking with English-language learners at East High School and gathering input from residents at East football games were ways the ISU student planners gathered suggestions, she said.
It was important to get feedback from a wide range of people, Ryan said, given the makeup of the neighborhoods.
More than a third of the residents in both areas are younger than 18, according to statistics provided by project organizers. More than 40 percent of Capitol Park residents are Latino, as are more than 30 percent of those in Capitol East.
"They are more diverse than Des Moines as a whole and that's something that those neighborhoods see as a very valuable asset for their community," Ryan said.
Priorities
Five priorities were identified in each neighborhood. Improving housing stock was noted in both areas, which Lynch said translates to building new structures and rehabilitating current homes.
"To help connect homeowners with resources is a big thing," she said.
Building community identity and participation were also on the list for both neighborhoods, along with programming for youths.
Capitol East residents also showed interest in improving features such as streets and utilities, along with supporting the East Grand Avenue commercial corridor. The formation of a business association is one suggestion for that goal, Lynch said. Residents also showed interest in a possible plaza to serve as an outdoor gathering area for residents.
The other priorities for Capitol Park were addressing crime/public safety and neighborhood appearance. Residents there suggested highlighting the trails along the Des Moines River that are already in place, Lynch said, and creating more connections for bicyclists.
The Martin Luther King Jr. Park neighborhood adjacent to Capitol Park and Capitol East is creating its first revitalization plan. The three neighborhoods expect to work together on projects and brand themselves as the East Bank neighborhoods, Lynch said.
More groups and organizations are expected to be brought on board to implement the plans starting in late spring or summer, Lynch said.
"There a re a lot of partnerships that are being formed as part of this," she said.
See the plans
Ideas for improvements in Capitol East and Capitol Park neighborhoods are being presented to officials at several meetings next month.
路 Des Moines Plan and Zoning Commission, 5:30 p.m. April 3 at City Hall.
路 Polk County Board of Supervisors workshop, 9:30 a.m. April 16 at the Polk County Administration Office Building, 111 Court Avenue.
路 Des Moines City Council, 4:30 p.m. April 21 at City Hall.
路 Polk County Board of Supervisors meeting, 9:30 a.m. April 22 at the county administration building.
GET INVOLVED: Residents wishing to volunteer may contact their neighborhood association leaders; Amber Lynch at amlynch@dmgov.org or 283-4223; or Emily Boyd at Community Housing Initiatives, emilyb@chihousing.com or 262-5965.
]]></text></news-item>