<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4C9A-3048-CA14-1C7B"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Hazards of e-waste pollution</title><source>Assam Tribune (India)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Guwahati, March 14 -- About eight lakh tones of e-waste is generated in India every year. Sixty-five cities in India generate more than 60% of the total e-waste generated in the country. Mumbai is the top e-waste generator followed by Delhi, Bangalore, Chennai and Kolkata, India also gets a huge amount of e-waste from Europe, America and other countries.
E-waste management in our country is mostly unorganized. It goes through a chain of steps. Obsolete goods from the households are either dumped or sold to Kabadis, who pick up all the useful materials and sell it to the local scrap dealers; the local scrap dealers after dismantling and separating crude components sell it to the specialized dealers who through a specialized process extract metals like gold, silver, aluminium, copper, irons, brass, platinum, etc. Metals are sold to the respective metal dealers and the leftover solid waste is then dumped at the dumping place. From there, it goes to the landfill sites. This system is responsible for processing about 80% of India's e-waste. The remaining 20% is dumped and ends up in the landfills. This is the mode of disposal in the metro cities. E-waste from most of the States in our country finds its way into the garbage dumps from where the rag pickers collect them for recycling.
There is a lack of legislative framework in our country to address the issue of electronic waste management. In the West, there are specific rules on how to dump household e-waste. Either the companies take back the e-waste or specialized vehicles pick up e-waste and dump in recycling units. Most of the organizations in India do not have any policy on the disposal of obsolete e-waste. Only 40% of e-waste enters the recycling stream; the rest remains in warehouse/store houses. The Expended Producer's Responsibility Approach (EPRA) wherein the producers be made responsible for their products even after the consumer has bought them, a successful system of e-waste disposal in various countries of the world, can be thought of to be introduced in the country.
The Indian e-waste recycling system is neither technically and economically equipped nor hazard free even to handle in-house e-waste. More than 70% of e-waste collected in Delhi's recycling units is actually dumped by the developed countries. This waste, when subjected to the primitive and highly polluting recycling operations, contaminates air and water and harms the health of workers. The developed countries are wise and prefer to dispose of their e-waste by paying for its export instead of actually investing in developing recycling infrastructure which is very expensive. They find India a cheaper place to recycle e-waste. As a policy, the Government should take steps to control import of hazardous wastes in the country.
Today, the e-waste has become a serious problem. Thus, either it has to be recycled or reused or disposed of. Recycling can be defined as the assembling, developing, promoting or buying of new products, which are prepared from waste materials. But some toxic substances cannot be recycled, because they affect the human health and the environment as well. Burning the e-waste in incinerators leads to the formation of harmful gases due to the hazardous substances present in it. If these harmful substances can be disposed of with some chemicals, then it will reduce the pollution of environment and also reduce the extent of danger it poses to human health. The guidelines with legislative backing for e-waste disposal should include : 1) the electronics industry should encourage reuse/recycle of obsolete electronic items; 2) the products produced in the country should last longer to minimize fresh purchases; 3) all manufacturers should come up with a take-back policy for the used electronic and electrical goods; 4) institutional users must mandatorily be put in place on e-waste management and disposal and 5) the Government should explicitly identify and define the role of each stakeholder ' manufacturer, user, vendor, segregator, recycler and regulator. To save our nation from e-waste, a proper awareness is highly needful amongst all.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Assam Tribune. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>