<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4D02-2E60-183E-85F4"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>FLANAGAN: Winter in Attleborough was tough 100 years ago</title><source>The Sun Chronicle (Attleboro, Massachusetts)</source><author>MARK FLANAGAN FOR THE SUN CHRONICLE</author><text><![CDATA[The winter of 1914, the year the Town of Attleborough became the City of Attleboro, may not rival the one that ends next week for snow and chilliness, but it was a rigorous one nonetheless. "COLD WAVE TO END SAYS FORECAST; MONTH HAS BROKEN RECORDS," proclaims a headline on the front page of the Feb. 25, 1914 Attleboro Sun. The story below reported that the local temperature had been 6 degrees that morning and that for all of February the aggregate temperature had been 186 degrees below normal.
A cold winter in 1914 was good news recreationally: On Jan. 20 The Sun reported that more than 200 people had enjoyed ice skating the day before on the lake at Capron Park. It was even better news economically in an era when household refrigerators were virtually unheard of. "Ice prices will drop on Feb. 1," The Sun reported in late January, noting that there was a "hopeful outlook for a large harvest."
On Feb. 13 the newspaper reported there was a 9-inch ice crop on Farmer's Pond and announced "men wanted to cut ice on Thacher's Meadow." A week later The Sun warned "fourth storm on way," in a period of just over a week, and that the area had experienced "the most snow since 1907." On Feb. 23 came a report that more than 70 men had been employed cutting ice at Meadowbrook.
Unemployment was a serious enough concern in 1914 for the Attleboro YMCA to offer free classes to people out of work. It was also a factor in many of the cases heard in Fourth District Court against men charged with the crime of "being a tramp."
While ice-cutting offered relief and provided a valuable commodity to fill local iceboxes, it was dangerous work. The front page of The Sun on Feb. 26, 1914 told how William Bartlett, 40, an employee of the Dorchester Ice Co., had slipped beneath an ice planer during a harvest at Lake Archer in Wrentham. The accident took his right leg off at the hip and his left at the knee. Med-Flights weren't even a dream at the time, but a special train was sent to take him to Massachusetts General Hospital. Alas, his injuries proved fatal.
With snow too frequent and the blessings of cheaper ice mixed, at best, Attleborough residents of a century ago were no doubt as relieved as those of today to look at the calendar on March 15 and reflect that spring would arrive in five days.
Whether they also looked ahead to a bright display of green shamrocks on March 17 and munching into a zeppola on March 19 is hard to say, but appears unlikely. The Sun's editorials of a century ago were wary of secular holidays, never mind celebrations linked to religiously-based celebrations like St. Patrick's Day and St. Joseph's Day.
And the Attleborough of 1914 was far less ethnically diverse than the Attleboro of 2014, you might surmise from browsing through editions of The Sun from early that year. Yankee names predominate among the newsmakers of the day. The law passed that year to put a check on immigration from Asia drew a hearty round of applause in a Sun editorial. News of the local clubs - and they played a dominant role in community life when television was science fiction and even radios were rare - included a couple of Irish-oriented groups, but no Italian ones that I have noticed.
But the newspaper was publishing a weekly column of news written in a foreign language - Swedish. That may have given some pleasure to the leading newsmaker of the day, Frank Mossberg, inventor, industrialist and Board of Trade president, who had immigrated from Varmland, Sweden, in 1882. His imposing factory off Lamb Street, destroyed by fire several years ago, was only five years old in 1914.
As St. Pat's Day approached that year, The Sun had been serializing a book based on the play "Seven Keys to Baldpate," a mystery (and the basis for a 1983 Vincent Price flick). Subscribers were probably eating it up - like they had "Broadway Jones," serialized in January and early February - as the author was known at the time as "the king of Broadway."
But The Sun's Irish American readers had a special connection to the playwright. He was George M. Cohan, a Roman Catholic and Irish American kid born in nearby Providence. The guess from here is that in Attleboro and North on March 17, 1914, you would have heard at least a few choruses of Cohan's "I'm A Yankee Doodle Dandy...." sung in a brogue.
MARK FLANAGAN is a retired Sun Chronicle editor.
]]></text></news-item>