<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4D1F-B46D-6ED6-5BE4"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Female, Fifty and Forced Out of a Job - Life for Older Women Teachers Can Be Tough, Says ATL</title><source>Targeted News Service</source><author>Targeted News Service</author><text><![CDATA[The Association of Teachers and Lecturers issued the following news release:
Female teachers over age 50 are being managed out of their jobs and discriminated against during their careers, alleged Pat Kyrou, a teacher from Essex and member of the Association of Teachers and Lecturers (ATL).
Speaking yesterday at the TUC women's conference in London, Pat Kyrou, who was part of a 14-strong ATL delegation, told delegates at the conference* that: "Women are often being punished for being female and fifty. An unexpectedly large number of teachers being put on capability are women over fifty.
"Until older women have a similarly respected profile to that of older men, their abilities will be under appreciated and they will be more likely to experience discrimination in all aspects of the job market.
She said that in 2012 the average salary for female teachers in state-funded schools was Pounds36,600, whereas for male teachers it was Pounds39,900. So you lose Pounds3,300 just for being a woman.
And fewer women are promoted to senior roles in schools, so they are over represented in the classroom where their work is more stressful than if they were in management.
Pat Kyrou added: "But it's not just a case of straight forward gender discrimination. Women in their fifties are the sandwich generation, the squeezed middle. As the majority of those with caring duties, women are penalised again: for caring, for saving the state money, and for helping relatives to enter or stay in the workforce.
"But this does not mean that they are less capable at work. If anything many of their responsibilities make them good team-players, make them work more effectively, enable them to multi-task and to have more empathy with their pupils - some of whom inevitably will also be carers."
Pat Kyrou warned that: "The new link between performance management, pay and capability forms a terrifying stick with which to beat education staff. Teachers are concerned that this makes it much easier for employers to quickly and easily dismiss teachers through the capability process. Schools can use performance management as an opportunity to get rid of anyone too old, too expensive, or whose face doesn't fit, by setting effectively unachievable targets.
"We are noticing a trend that education staff will resign rather than be dragged through formal disciplinary procedures, with the result that sometimes it can be as little as three weeks between the first communication from management and the end of a decades-long career in education."
Pat Kyrou concluded: "Instead of trying to get rid of older women, employers should be supporting them and working with them to find how best they can combine their roles as workers and carers.
"Age and gender discrimination, as other forms of discrimination, are illegal and employers need to be reminded of this in the strongest language possible."
*Pat Kyrou was introducing ATL's motion on discrimination facing women over 50 at the TUC's women's conference. This calls for the TUC and its member unions to: work with organisations such as The Age and Employment Network (TAEN) to support older workers in the workplace; raise awareness of the effects of multiple discrimination in terms of age, race/ethnicity, sexual orientation and/or gender in the workplace; and promote the benefits of flexible working more widely and resources to support older workers.
[Category: Education]
Copyright Targeted News Services
TNS 30FurigayJof 140315-4669400 30FurigayJof
]]></text></news-item>