<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4D36-6509-4961-E9CE"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Company told to drain lake; Unusual order seeks to halt bitumen leak</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Originally published September 25, 2013
COLD LAKE - In an unusual move, oilsands company Canadian Natural Resources Ltd. has been ordered to partially drain a small lake on the Cold Lake Air Weapons Range to find a way to contain bitumen seeping up into the water.
The provincial environmental protection order, the first to require draining of, or "dewatering," a body of water, calls for CNRL to partly empty the lake, locate the leaking fissure in the lake bottom, construct containment measures and restore the lake next March.
This spring, CNRL reported bitumen leaking on four sites on its lease at the weapons range, with one site involving a small, unnamed, 53-hectare lake. In the three other cases, the fissures on the surface were located and surrounded by berms to keep the seeping bitumen out of the forest.
But the leakage into the small lake proved more challenging, so the company said it approached the environment department about draining the lake "temporarily," said CNRL spokeswoman Zoe Addington. This summer, the company spent weeks skimming bitumen off the surface of the lake and keeping away migrating birds.
Now, it has moved the lake's frogs to another site as part of an "amphibian salvage plan" before draining the lake. The plan is to refill the lake in the spring.
The company must also do a fish inventory, though it's unclear if any fish live in the lake, which at times freezes solid.
To reduce any risks, CNRL must submit plans to prevent damage such as erosion or silt buildup, and minimize impact on wildlife and nearby wetlands, plus test soil samples for bitumen.
The department is waiting to get CNRL's final containment plans, due Oct. 6, before signing off on draining the lake by Oct. 15, said environment department spokesman Trevor Gemmell.
About two-thirds of the water will be removed. A large portion will be stored in the remaining one-third of the lake, with the rest piped to a nearby pit and wetland, said Addington.
Asked how the company will ensure no bitumen will contaminate the water being pumped out, Addington said the company will take two weeks to pipe the water out to the storage spots and will have a mobile lab on-site to test water quality.
The company says the leaking fissure is located generally along the edge of the lake and that portion of the lake may be left dry, exposing the fissure, when the water is put back, said Addington.
But the effort raised concerns among environmentalists and government critics, who have called this uncontrolled leakage a "new type of industrial accident."
This order is "damage control, not a solution," said Rachel Notley, NDP environment critic.
"Without knowing the cause of the leaks, I'm not convinced this order is worth the paper it is written on," she said.
The government dropped the ball in 2009 when a similar leak first appeared on the CNRL Cold Lake site, but the company was allowed to continue using its underground, high-pressure steam method, said Notley.
The company says the bitumen seepage from underground is caused by faulty well bores that allow melted bitumen to seep up to cracks near the surface.
A report by the Alberta Energy Regulator raised the possibility the leaks are caused by cracks in the cap rock as a result of the highpressure steam.
The Alberta government should "at a minimum, put a hold on approving new underground oilsands operations until we understand how these leaks are happening and if other sites could run into similar problems," said Greenpeace's Mike Hudema.
Though the company has said for months that all four leaks are contained, the order notes that CNRL "has been unable to determine the exact location and the subsurface conditions under which the release is continuing."
The order also notes the cause of the leaking is unknown, and it is not known how long it was going on before it was reported June 24. The order also requires CNRL to report to Cold Lake First Nation on issues around wetlands impacts and other issues.
spratt@edmontonjournal.com( mailto:spratt@edmontonjournal.com )( mailto:spratt@edmontonjournal.com )
© Copyright (c) The Edmonton Journal
]]></text></news-item>