<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4D4C-CEDF-D7E5-FA29"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Class act</title><source>The Herald-Palladium (St. Joseph, Michigan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[DOWAGIAC - No one would have blamed Jason Robert Brown for saying no.
By all accounts, the Tony Award-winning composer and lyricist is in the midst of his long-awaited New York moment.
His unlikely musical adaptation, "Bridges of Madison County," starring Broadway darling Kelli O'Hara, opened at the Gerald Schoenfeld Theater last month to glowing reviews. His reimagining of the 1992 movie "Honeymoon in Vegas" is expected to land on Broadway next season. And the film version of "The Last Five Years," his musical deconstruction of a failed marriage, is slated for release by year's end.
None of it, however, has kept Brown away from college campuses - where he is considered a theater god - to offer master classes or critique performances of his works. That's why Paul Mow, the operatic tenor and theater director at Southwestern Michigan College, sent Brown a bold request to visit the small community college in Dowagiac, which is staging four performances of his 1998 Broadway musical, "Parade," beginning Thursday.
"I saw him do a similar residency at Notre Dame three or four years ago," Mow says. "On a lark, I shot him an email and told him what we were doing and if he would consider coming out and he wrote back and said, 'Yeah, let's try to make it work.'"
They did. Now, Brown is en route to Dowagiac, where he will hold a concert that spans his musical theater catalog Wednesday night and a master class with Mow's students on Thursday.
"It's not about the prestige of it," says Brown, when asked during a telephone interview why he accepted Mow's invitation. "When I do these things I do it because I believe in working with young people and having the opportunity to meet them and share music with them and be a part of their experience of what the performing arts can be. I had a lot of wonderful mentors when I was a young performer and young writer, and I like the opportunity to be in the middle of all of that."
Brown, who was raised in Monsey, N.Y., about an hour north of Manhattan, doesn't come from a musical family, so when he began begging his parents for a piano at age 7 it seemed like a strange request.
"Finally my grandfather had a piano in his basement tucked away in the back," Brown says. "They dragged it out and put it in my living room and I sat down, and I don't know how to put it into words, but from the minute I started playing it I was like, 'Yes, this is what I wanted.' I wanted to make music on this piano and I found my voice playing the piano. ... There was a yearning to make music and be a musician and to be a musician who cared about the music. I don't know why, but it was there."
At 9 or 10, Brown was writing his own pop songs, and at 11 he began attending a performing arts camp. His piano-centric, high-energy music, even today serves as a nod to the influence Billy Joel had on him during those years.
"Most of what you heard at that time were guys who wrote on the guitar, but Billy Joel was a composer who worked at the piano," Brown says. "There is something about his connection to those 88 keys that was very powerful to me. He communicated his identity through an instrument. Billy Joel sings through that piano as clear as Joni Mitchell sings through that guitar."
Brown was just 24 when he started working on his first musical, "Parade," which deals with such weighty subjects as the trial of a man falsely accused, the specter of anti-Semitism, and the revival of the Ku Klux Klan.
Daisy Prince, the daughter of Tony Award-winning director Harold Prince, found Brown at a piano bar in Manhattan and brought the young composer to her father's attention. Harold Prince, who helped conceive the show, and the Pulitzer Prize-winning playwright Alfred Uhry, who wrote its book, gambled on Brown.
"It felt clear to me that (the music) needed to be a very big canvas," he says. "This wasn't going to be an intimate little piece. So I started looking for every possible thing that might fit in that canvas. There was Charles Ives and Stephen Foster and John Philip Sousa and slave songs and spirituals and I sort of threw all of that stuff into a pot with my usual pile of influences - Stephen Sondheim, Leonard Bernstein, Gershwin, Billy Joel and Joni Mitchell - and I mixed it all together and 'Parade' is what came out."
The musical dramatizes the 1913 trial of Jewish factory manager Leo Frank, who was accused and convicted of raping and murdering 13-year-old employee, Mary Phagan. The trial aroused anti-Semitic tensions in Atlanta and Frank received a death sentence.
Court-watchers around the country considered it a mockery. Editorials from New York to San Francisco sought a new trial. Frank's lawyers were rebuffed at appealing his conviction, and petitioned departing Georgia Gov. John Slaton, who agreed Frank failed to receive a fair trial and commuted his sentence to life in prison.
Frank was transferred to a prison in Milledgeville, Ga., where a lynching party seized and kidnapped him. He was taken to Phagan's hometown of Marietta and hanged from an oak tree.
In 1982, Alonzo Mann, a 14-year-old office boy in 1913, testified he saw factory janitor Jim Conley, the key witness against Frank at the trial, carry Phagan's body through the lobby alone. Conley threatened to kill Mann if he told. Mann passed a lie detector test. Georgia granted Frank a posthumous pardon in 1986.
The plot of the musical dramatizes the historical story, emphasizing the evolving relationship between Leo and his wife, Lucille, and does not shy away from the conclusion that Conley was likely the killer.
The difficult subject matter of "Parade," however, proved a hard sell on Broadway - the show closed after two months - but both Uhry and Brown won Tony Awards for best book and best original score.
"I felt so passionate about that story and so empowered by the visceral importance of what we had to do," Brown says. "I think it made me brave. Having to write something so intense, I think it made me a brave writer. ... I don't think any of us imagined that this show about a legendary lynching in the early 1900s was the thing that was going to buy us our villas in the south of Italy. ... But I think that's how I found my musical voice, just by having guts."
Mow, whose first foray into directing musical theater was for a production of Brown's "The Last Five Years," brought "Parade" to his theater students for much the same reason.
"We're not some high-end musical theater program where everyone is chomping at the bit to show off to him," Mow says. "We're a small upstart theater program at a community college. So it's amazing to be able to do this kind of work and bring in this level of expertise. It's a heavy, tragic story, but there's not a better place than a college campus to do this kind of work. It's just rife with opportunities for education."
Since his mother was a teacher, Brown admits he has a soft spot for theater education, adding, "I've always felt like it was a big part of my calling."
In fact, when a gig teaching musical theater performance and composition at the University of Southern California came up in 2005, he and his wife, Georgia Stitt, moved to Los Angeles, seemingly leaving Broadway in the rearview mirror. There's even a song on his 2005 solo album, "Wearing Someone Else's Clothes," with the title "Getting Out."
It was a collaboration with writers Dan Elish and Robert Horn for the musical "13" that brought Brown back to Broadway, and it appears with "The Bridges of Madison County," an adaptation of Robert James Waller's novel about the romance between an Italian immigrant farm wife and a roving photographer, might just keep him there.
"It has been an absolutely magical experience," Brown says of "Bridges." "We started with this novel, which was not a book that I was ever a real fan of, but it spoke to me when we started writing this piece. I felt there was singing all over it and it sounded different then the stuff I had written before. We have this beautiful cast and wonderful production and it's been so gratifying to sit and watch the show take shape. Whenever I can, I'm still going to the theater to watch it. I'm very proud that I wrote it. I'm sort of surprised that I wrote it, but I'm very proud."
Brown also beams when talking about seeing his earliest work now in the hands of students.
"Writing for the theater is a long-haul business and "Parade" was always sort of meant to be for the long haul," he says. "When I saw the first college production of 'Parade' a couple of years after we closed, it was speaking in a vocabulary that the kids understood. I still see that now. ... It's very powerful for me to see the way students interact with material, to see the way they take it on and begin to understand it or don't understand it and the ways I can help eliminate that. I think it changes my writing and it changes my teaching and all for the better. ... I don't know if it's what I got into this business for, but if that's it, it's enough."
Email: jbonfiglio@TheHP.com
Twitter: @HPBonfiglio
-- WHO: Jason Robert Brown in concert
-- WHEN: 7:30 p.m. Wednesday
-- WHERE: Southwestern Michigan College 's Dale A. Lyons Building Theatre, 58900 Cherry Grove Road, Dowagiac
-- HOW MUCH: Free
-- CONTACT: 800-456-8675 or swmich.edu/parade
-- ARTIST INFO: jasonrobertbrown.com
-- WHAT: "Parade"
-- WHEN: 7:30 p.m. Thursday-Saturday, and 2 p.m. March 23
-- WHERE: Southwestern Michigan College's Dale A. Lyons Building Theatre, 58900 Cherry Grove Road, Dowagiac
-- HOW MUCH: $7, $5 for seniors, free for students
-- CONTACT: 800-456-8675 or swmich.edu/parade
-- PARENTAL GUIDANCE: "Parade" involves controversial and sometimes graphic subject matter and is not recommended for children
]]></text></news-item>