<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4D95-5D70-7E08-66B7"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Restaurant owner attacked while jogging</title><source>Pacific Daily News (Hagatna, Guam)</source><author>By, Amanda Francel Blas Pacific Daily News</author><text><![CDATA[A 41-year-old man was attacked Friday night while jogging in Tamuning.
"Three guys came out from the baseball field and one of them had a (child's) wooden bat in his hand," Taro Tsuruga said.
"I was mugged."
Tsuruga, who owns Aji Ichi Japanese Restaurants, was running along Chalan San Antonio toward Tumon.
As he passed Tamuning Elementary School, he noticed three men at the baseball field.
"I really didn't take it seriously," Tsuruga said, noting they had vanished from view.
"I felt that they were a little unsafe, but I didn't really think they're going to attack me."
Tsuruga ran for about another 45 feet when he came across them again. The three stood on the sidewalk.
"The three of them blocked the pavement, and I didn't know what to do. I was too close (to them), so I was sure I couldn't go back," Tsuruga said.
He tried to run through the group. But the man holding the bat attacked.
Tsuruga threw his arms up over his head. He ended up in a crouch, trying to protect his head.
The bat slammed into his head and shoulder.
"I tried to go to the roadside and just try to protect my head, but the main thing I thought about was not to get killed," Tsuruga said.
The men took his waist pouch, which held his cellphone, and left Tsuruga, who was now lying on the road.
"It was Friday and not too late, so I thought, hopefully, some driver would recognize me and call the police," he said.
"After I was hit, I was bleeding with no shirt (on) me, but nobody would stop, ... a couple of cars passed by and I gave up."
He slowly made his way back to Tumon where he had parked his car near one of the hotels. He drove to one of the restaurants he owns in Tumon, and called police.
While he was left with numerous bruises on his back and shoulder and six stitches near his right ear, Tsuruga said things could've been worse.
"I think I was lucky. ... I'm not in the hospital and I'm alive," Tsuruga said. "Compared to what could've happened, I have to say I was lucky."
Rare event
Tamuning Vice Mayor Ken Santos said he's never heard of someone being mugged in that area.
"This normally doesn't happen, not in our streets," Santos said. "We're very apologetic this had happened. We'll do all we can to make sure it doesn't happen again."
Tamuning Mayor Louise Rivera said the village is building a neighborhood watch program.
"We're working with Guam Police Department, a private security company and residents in our community," Rivera said. "We need to be more cautious of our surroundings."
TIPS FOR SAFETY
Police have offered the following tips to avoid becoming a victim of would-be thieves:
· Try to run in areas where there are regular joggers.
· Try to run with a partner.
· Try not to run in dark areas.
· When leaving a store, pay attention to your surroundings.
· Have your car keys ready before you get to your car.
· Try not to show cash when purchasing items. If you can, use a credit or debit card.
· Try not to shop after dark alone. If you find yourself in that situation, ask the store guard or manager to walk you safely to your car.
· Banks and business owners are advised to exercise caution when opening or closing their businesses.
· They should also take note of all people entering their business.
There are many other useful safety tips that can help individuals avoid dangerous situations. It's important to note, however, that whether you remember to use these tips or not, it's never your fault if you're attacked. It's the attacker's fault.
· Yell "Fire" to attract attention.
· Trust your danger instincts: Don't ignore the little voice that tells you when something seems "off."
· Escape if possible: It's always safer to flee rather than fight.
· Fight back: You can always fight back if you can't escape. Always fight back, never bargain.
· Never go with them: Going to a second location is always a bad idea.
· Property isn't worth it: It's much safer to call and cancel your credit cards than get into a fistfight over your purse.
· Enforcing boundaries: How close is too close? Maintaining the correct distance can keep a situation from getting physical.
· Projecting confidence: Attackers look for easy targets, so act like a difficult target.
· Stay alert: Keeping a close eye on your surroundings can keep you from being caught off guard.
Guam Police Department and Safety and Self-Defense Solutions, http://www.womensselfdefense.info/safety-tips/
]]></text></news-item>