<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4E7B-491B-9DB3-A879"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Lending Club's Jason Altieri wins by staying out of the ring</title><source>San Francisco Business Times</source><author>Michael Fitzhugh</author><text><![CDATA[Staying out of the courtroom has been one of Jason Altieri's biggest career successes at Lending Club. Since he joined the company as general counsel and chief compliance officer in 2009, the online credit lender has never been sued.
As an online marketplace for consumer credit, Lending Club works in a legally complex landscape, matching borrowers looking for loans with investors looking for attractive yields from investing in those loans.
The company has originated more than $3 billion in personal loans.
Lending Club is regulated by the SEC and state regulators for investors and by federal and state regulators for its interactions with borrowers.
That has meant that Altieri has had to learn about areas in which he hadn't practiced before and develop close relationships with regulators to better advocate for why certain regulations do and don't apply to the company's business.
"Trying to keep a broad and open mind about how the law can apply to our business means that I'm a heads-up kind of lawyer," Altieri said.
"It makes us all much more aware how changes on one side of the business, whether on a legal or operational level, may flow through and affect the legal or operational aspects of the other side of the business."
Altieri credits his experience as an associate at Wilson Sonsini Goodrich & Rosati for his keen problem-solving skills.
While there, he said he was inspired to think creatively to understand the legal and business needs of clients and find the most efficient intersection between those two.
Cindy Hess, co-chair of Fenwick & West's startup practice, has worked with Altieri in putting together the company's venture financings, documentation and other legal work as Lending Club's outside counsel.
She said Altieri has a very laid-back style and isn't one to get too worked up over unimportant details. "He has a very measured approach and comes to analyze problems in a thoughtful and analytical way," she said. "He's truly the modern GC. He's not one to pontificate over issues. He'll text me and ask if I have three seconds while he's running between meetings.
"He'll use me as a backstop, to bounce things off me. He's not stuck on formalities. He's a really bottom-line, practical guy," she added.
Carrie Dolan, Lending Club's CFO, also works closely with Altieri and said he's very practical in his approach.
"Given that he understands so much about the business aspects of our company, he's broad and deep and able to leverage that in his problem solving."
Outside of Lending Club, Altieri is a prolific baker - a holdover from days as a chief baker and partner in a group of coffee shops - and invests his professional talent in Astia, a global nonprofit that supports female entrepreneurs.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to San Francisco Business Times for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>