<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4F51-5031-A3DA-0AF3"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Reports: Prison employee killed in DeSoto hit-and-run</title><source>Charlotte Sun (Port Charlotte, Florida)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[DESOTO COUNTY - A 50-year-old Arcadia man found dead in a ditch alongside S.E. Westfarm Road was the victim of a hit-and-run, according to the Florida Highway Patrol.
The victim, Jeffery Worth, was struck shortly after noon Wednesday, the report shows. Worth was employed at the DeSoto Annex - a prison in Arcadia.
Authorities did not have any information about the suspect's vehicle Thursday.
Anyone with information about the incident can call FHP at 941-751-8350 and ask for Cpl. Louis Smith, Jr.
Shooting  suspect detained
PORT CHARLOTTE - The man accused of shooting at a car Tuesday in a Port Charlotte neighborhood has turned himself in, according to the Charlotte County Sheriff's Office.
Craig Steven Barra Jr., 24, of the 21500 block of Winlock Avenue in Port Charlotte, was arrested at the CCSO's Promenades Mall office Wednesday evening.
Barra's wife - Alyssa Paige Fisher, 18 - allegedly drove him to a home on the 200 block of Azalea Avenue around 2:30 p.m. Tuesday, and Barra shot out the two back windows of a Chevrolet Suburban parked outside.
A woman inside the home came out and saw Barra trying to hide a semi-automatic handgun before he and his wife sped off, the report shows. A warrant was issued for Barra's arrest. The victim knew the couple.
Barra is charged with discharging a firearm in public, possession of a firearm by a felon and criminal mischief. He was being held Thursday at the Charlotte County Jail on $27,500 bond.
Authorities are still looking for Fisher. She may be in the North Port area. Anyone who knows her whereabouts can call the Sheriff's Office at 941-639-2101.
Report: Employee stole over $27K
PUNTA GORDA - A local woman has been charged with 20 felonies for scamming a Punta Gorda business out of more than $27,000 while she was an employee, according to the Charlotte County Sheriff's Office.
Ashley Michelle Polk, 30, of the 1500 block of Abalone St., was arrested Wednesday for allegedly defrauding AADisaster Restoration24/7 out of $27,382.61 from November to February, the report shows. Polk was an office manager there.
Authorities say Polk forged the company owner's signature on checks, which she cashed. Polk is also accused of using the company's credit card to make three unauthorized purchases totaling $4,540.
Polk is facing eight counts each of uttering a forged instrument and grand theft, three counts of credit card fraud and one count of scheming to defraud. She was being held Thursday at the Charlotte County Jail without bond.
The Charlotte County Sheriff's Office reported the following arrests:
· Nicholas Edward Adair, 34, 5200 block of Wentworth Road, Port Charlotte. Charge: three counts of possession of a controlled substance without a prescription, and one count each of possession of opium or a derivative with intent to sell and possession of drug paraphernalia. Bond: none.
· Nancy Renee Golden, 33, 3600 block of N. Giblin Drive, North Port. Charge: DUI. Bond: $1,500.
· Vito Anthony Plusch, 42, 1400 block of Robwood Terrace, North Port. Charge: possession of a controlled substance without a prescription and possession of drug paraphernalia. Bond: none.
· Katherine Marie Greten, 21, of Fort Myers. Charges: bond revocation from two previous charges. Bond: none.
· Travis Lee Henry, 22, homeless in Englewood. Charge: violation of probation (original charges: battery and harassing a witness). Bond: none.
· David Michael Lind, 21, 1100 block of Edgemere Court. Charge: two counts of possession of less than 20 grams of marijuana and possession of drug paraphernalia. Bond: $10,000.
· Lavell Allen Hall, 22, 6200 block of Cavan St., Englewood. Charge: possession of less than 20 grams of marijuana and possession of drug paraphernalia. Bond: $5,000.
· Charlene Catherine Carr, 57, 2900 block of E. Mark Drive, Sarasota. Charge: refusing a DUI test. Bond: none.
· Michael Shawn Jones, 29, 27100 block of Townsend Terrace, Punta Gorda. Charge: violation of probation (original charges: grand theft auto, DUI and resisting an officer). Bond: none.
· Isaiah Isaac Roberts III, 42, of Port St. Lucie. Charges: two out-of-county warrants. Bond: none.
· Chantel Charlene Katherine Nixon, 21, 300 block of Allworthy Ave., Port Charlotte. Charge: disorderly intoxication. Bond: $500.
· Stephanie Lee Nichols, 33, homeless in Port Charlotte. Charges: driving with a suspended license and violation of probation (original charge: possession of drug paraphernalia). Bond: none.
· Angel Anthony Rivera, 38, 2500 block of Elkcam Blvd., Port Charlotte. Charge: battery. Bond: $2,000.
· Michael Paul Anderson, 32, homeless in Port Charlotte. Charge: failure to appear. His bond information was unavailable Thursday.
· Bradley Harold Bennett, 45, 3700 block of Easy St., Port Charlotte. Charge: violation of probation (original charges: burglary, grand theft and tampering with evidence). Bond: none.
· Lauren Renee Vener, 28, 6200 block of Cavan St., Englewood. Charges: possession of less than 20 grams of marijuana, possession of drug paraphernalia and violation of probation (original charge: sale of cocaine). Bond: none.
· Steven Bradley Mashke, 20, 11200 block of Waterford Ave., Englewood. Charge: failure to register a motor vehicle. Bond: $1,000.
· Darrin Woodside, 47, 7100 block of Teaberry St., Englewood. Charges: two counts of possession of a controlled substance without a prescription. Bond: none.
· Travis Alan, Rogers, 23, 2200 block of Tennyson Ave., Port Charlotte. Charge: DUI. Bond: none.
· Scott Edward Baber, 48, 3200 block of Port Charlotte Blvd., Port Charlotte. Charge: violation of probation (original charge: resisting an officer). His bond information was unavailable Thursday.
· Ronald Joseph Birchler, 52, 21800 block of Buxton Ave., Port Charlotte. Charge: driving with a suspended license. Bond: $1,000.
- Compiled by Adam Kreger
]]></text></news-item>