<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4F5D-6882-6837-72B9"><date>2014-03-10</date><title>Exclusive: Another Air India staff strike brewing?</title><source>Headlines Today</source><author>Pankaj Upadhyay</author><text><![CDATA[There is trouble yet again for the national carrier. And it is brewing within the Air India family. All India Cabin Crew Association has told Headlines Today that they do not rule out striking work in the days to come. AICCA member on condition of anonymity said, "There have been twelve terminations in the last couple of days in Delhi itself. Management says refusal to fly is the reason for the action. But has anyone even bothered to ask on what grounds have the crew refused to fly. The management is painting a false picture. There is rampant corruption in the organisation that is responsible for the present state". The AICCA further states that they are expecting a reply from the MD and if they do not receive a reply then they would be forced to serve strike notice to the management.
Let's just understand what this means for the passengers. If indeed the crew association goes on strike then the passengers travelling by Air India in the international sectors will be worst hit. Air India has some three thousand strong crew force for the international sector that flies to places like London, New York, Chicago, Frankfurt, Paris, Singapore, Hong Kong, Shanghai, Sydney, Melbourne among others. Strike and that too at the onset on summer would spell doom for the carrier and harass the passengers to the core. AICCA also says that they enjoy the support of domestic crew members and if need and situation be they would stand by them in protest.
Now lets get you clear picture of what's happening. Delays, strikes and union unrest have been a part and parcel of the Air India story for long. The tussle specifically between the Air India management and the Cabin Crew Association has also been going for years now. It is just off late that the management realising that its image was taking a thorough beating owing to the falling OTP ( On Time Performance) started getting tough on the employees. That meant suspending crew that refused to fly or were late for work or showed sector preference. And then terminations followed and that made the scenario ugly. The AICCA charged the management of favouritism and corruption in the organisation.
Headlines Today had earlier reported on how the management had allegedly failed to live up to the rule book of the DGCA when it came to crew compliment in the international sectors along with rest hours and other related issues of the Long Range flights. So how has the situation got out of hand for the carrier. Sources tell Headlines Today that the management had served a circular to AICCA asking it to comply by the rules set by the management or face action. In retaliation the association shot back a hard hitting letter. Here are some of the content of the letter:

An Air India management source on condition anonymity said that the airline was complying by all the rules and that they were interested in the OTP of the airline which was going down for the last couple of months. Aviation expert Harshawardhan says " The issue of the crew members needs to sorted by the management but the crew cannot be allowed to harass the passengers. There are union issues to it as well and there has to be a way out of this to avoid further image damage to the national carrier."
While in all this the passengers look askance there is there is yet another important issue that has been brought up by the employees. They say that the airline is now creating false scarcity of crew members and hiring crew on contract basis so that they could be paid cheap. The section of employees state that this is against the DGCA ruling and that this was clearly playing with the safety aspects as the contract crew paid on an hourly basis and much less than the regular ones have little training of tackling emergency situations.So as things stand the there could be bad days in the near future. Summer is just around and strike is the last thing that the Indian Aviation needs at this hour.
pankaj.upadhyay@aajtak.comTwitter: @pankajaajtak
]]></text></news-item>