<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="4F5E-54A0-5087-4DA1"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Tinder's trying to empower women - but it isn't working; Tinder, the dating app that often comes across as a sex app, is trying to change its image to show it supports female empowerment. Radhika Sanghani admires it's goals, but isn't convinced</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Radhika Sanghani</author><text><![CDATA[I tried Tinder once. I only lasted 24 hours because I just received sex requests through the dating app du jour. I'm not sure if it was my Facebook profile picture (I was wearing summer shorts) or just the people I was matching with, but I only received pervy messages from my matchs. When someone asked me if I'd go and meet him in the loos of Clapham nightclub Infernos, I finally deleted the app.
Instead I hopped straight onto traditional online dating site OKCupid where you can actually read someone's profile instead of just judging them on their Facebook pictures, and find people who are actually interested in you as a person (yes, and what you look like).
But, after months of women complaining that Tinder is superficial and based entirely on looks, it seems like the app is trying to change it's image. Tinder has teamed up with Amnesty International to highlight the fact that now all women have the power to choose how they live their life.
The ad shows images of a man being swiped to the left on Tinder (that means you're uninterested in him, while going to the right means 'yes you're keen'), and then has the message: "Not all women have the choices you do. You pick your partner. Many women aren't given a choice."
It's there to "remind people that many women don't have the luxury of choice - and recruit new supporters to join our fight for women's rights across the world," according to its website . It is exactly the kind of positive message I expect from the charity, but I never would have associated the 'dating app that's occasionally just a sex app', to support it.
But Tinder's co-founder Justin Mateen said: "We are honoured to partner with such an esteemed organisation as Amnesty International Australia to raise awareness of the human rights abuses faced by millions of young girls and women, Empowering women is a vital part of Tinder's overall mission."
Well, I had no idea this was the case when I was getting inappropriate sexual messages and felt scarily un-empowered, but clearly Tinder is keen to try and change it's unwholesome image.
The positive ad is a step in the right direction, but Tinder is still a long way from empowering women. A new video showing what Tinder swiping would look like in real life illustrates the banal superficiality of the app. In it, a woman goes through her day swiping men to the left until she meets one attractive man and swipes him to the right.
He takes one look at her and flicks her to the left. It is a brutal assessment of what Tinder is like, and that actually, neither women nor men are empowered on it. Instead they're reduced to judging each other solely on their looks. Some people I know even use the app to just play 'hot or not', and have no intention of going on a single date.
This is why Tinder is suddenly all over the web with new schemes to try and be seen as more than just a sex app. Recently Tinder's chief executive, Sean Rad, told The Hollywood Reporterthat they have plans to add verification for any celebrities or high-profile figures using the app, similar to Twitter's blue ticks.
Celeb' verification would make the app appeal to any mortal who fancies having a chance with An Actual Famous Person, but the move does hint at the fact that Tinder is trying to become a network rather than a mere app. Rad has previously spoken about Tinder's long-term vision to be used to find people for any purpose, such as people trying to find fellow travellers in other countries.
It is a worthy goal, but so far, Tinder is nowhere there. Yes, some people may be using it to find company for a variety of reasons, but at the end of the day, it still doesn't empower women and some celebrity ticks plus one heart-warming advert isn't going to change that. So for now when it comes to Tinder, I'm swiping to the left.
]]></text></news-item>