<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5094-7908-40D9-62A5"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Two wanted ships docked in Mombasa</title><source>Sunday Nation (Kenya)</source><author>PATRICK MAYOYO -1</author><text><![CDATA[Two ships wanted by Interpol for alleged illegal fishing and human trafficking called at the Mombasa port in February, investigations by the Nation have revealed.
According to the Kenya Ports Authority's list of vessels expected to call at the port, Mv Samdera Pacific and Berkat Menjala arrived at the Kilindini harbour on February 4 and docked at the Mbaraki wharf for provisions.
PURPLE LIST
This happened yet the two vessels had been put on Interpol's purple list of wanted ships.
Interpol issued the purple notice on January 21 as the ships are wanted by South African authorities for sneaking away from Cape Town harbour after they were impounded in December 2013.
According to a campaigner for seafarers' rights, Mr Andrew Mwangura, the two Indonesian vessels were part of seven or 10 ships seized for Illegal and unregulated fishing in Cape Town last December.
"It is not clear why Kenyan authorities did not intercept these vessels given that they called at Mombasa port after Interpol had issued the purple notice," he said.
Mr Mwangura said it is suspected sailors working aboard the vessels are under instructions from an international syndicate of maritime commercial criminals dealing with human trafficking and illegal fishing.
The vessels are believed to have been behind illegal fishing in Kenya and Somali waters using fake documentation.
President Uhuru Kenyatta recently revealed that Kenya loses Sh10 billion annually to foreigners who fish in its waters.
The Head of State noted said the foreigners carry out illegal activity in the country's exclusive economic zone, depleting valuable fish stock like tuna.
The fish, he said, end up being sold to the country at exorbitant prices.
Yesterday, Interpol's National Central Bureau chief Vitalis Okumu said Kenyan security agencies are on high alert following the release of details of the wanted ships.
BACKGROUNDWhat purple notice entails
Interpol notices are international requests for cooperation or alerts allowing police in member countries to share critical crime-related information.
The purple notice is issued to seek information on objects, devices and concealment methods used by criminals.
]]></text></news-item>