<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="50F8-5038-EFE9-BCDF"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>PROFILE: New Serbia premier cashes in on turn from extremism</title><source>dpa-AFX International ProFeed</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[By Boris Babic, dpa Belgrade (dpa-AFX) - Aleksandar Vucic, Serbia's next prime minister, has made a drastic turnaround during his rise to power. In the last two decades, he re-invented himself from a far-right nationalist who is hostile to the West to a soft-spoken moderate requesting broad support to carry out pro-EU reforms. In Sunday's snap elections he won the political mandate he sought, taking a projected 157 out of the 250 seats in the parliament with his centre-right Progressive Party (SNS). While Vucic, 44, now radiates pragmatism as a firm but benevolent leader, the Vucic at age 25 was much different. 'So bomb if you dare,' Vucic told Western powers in July 1995 as they were preparing to bomb Serb positions in Bosnia, 10 days after armed forces overran the UN-safe haven of Srebrenica.
'Kill one Serb, we will kill 100 Muslims. Let's see if the international community or anybody else dares hit Serb positions,' the young legislator told the Serbian parliament. Even as he spoke, Bosnian Serbs were carrying out a massacre of 8,000 Muslim boys and men in Srebrenica. The International Court of Justice later ruled the episode a genocide. But just a year ago, Vucic was the force behind an EU-brokered agreement with Kosovo, Serbia's mainly Albanian former province that declared independence in 2008. The move ended a political and diplomatic imbroglio that bedeviled the region since the war 15 years ago. On January 20, nine months after the historic deal, the European Union opened membership talks with Serbia and Vucic called for snap elections a week later. In his campaigns, he promised a better life for Serbs through investments lured by economic and social reforms as well as progress toward EU membership. Vucic's party won a significant part of the votes in May 2012, claiming 73 of 250 seats, and his most recent campaign adopted the slogan, 'Let's finish what we started.' 'Our aim is to conclude the membership talks with the EU by 2018 or 2019,' he said in February, promising that Serbia will 'swiftly adopt an important set of reformist laws after the elections.' He also promised to spearhead a crackdown against widespread corruption, particularly in politics and big business. Vucic's modern political platform emphasizes human rights, justice and open political dialogue. But during his first public stint as information minister from March 1998 until the fall of Slobodan Milosevic's regime in October 2000, he enforced a law providing trails within 24 hours of journalists and media outlets accused of unpatriotic writing. The law all but gagged newspapers, radio and TV stations not considered a part of Milosevic's propaganda machinery. The turnaround became visible after elections in May 2008, when he was still the deputy chief of the then mighty far-right Radical Party (SRS) with a staunchly pro-Russian, anti-Western agenda. He abandoned the SRS and its leader at the time, current Serbian President Tomislav Nikolic, after failing to steer it from the extreme to the centre-right. The SNS formed by autumn that year and adopted a pro-EU agenda. Nikolic since won the presidential election and the party was able to form a governing coalition after winning majority seats in the legislature. Nikolic formally left the party when he became the head of state, giving the reins to Vucic, who ceded the post of the prime minister to his junior Socialist partner Ivica Dacic. The move enabled Vucic to remain in the backroom while Dacic negotiated with the Kosovo Albanian counterpart Hashim Thaci and to build his own credentials as a moderate internationally and a corruption fighter at home. In a January interview with the German newspaper the Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung, Vucic owned up to his mistakes and said that his transformation was a 'process.' 'It is not like waking up one morning and simply saying - I am different,' he said. 'Unlike other politicians in Serbia ... I am not ashamed to say that I misjudged. Erred. Was wrong. Though it is not easy, I acknowledge my mistakes,' said Vucic. On Sunday night, he choked back tears as he was thanking voters for 'the great power ... and great responsibility' that they placed in his hands. Copyright dpa
]]></text></news-item>