<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5162-09E0-D542-373F"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Putting alcohol and fizzy drinks at the end of supermarket aisles DOES make us buy more - so could moving them reduce obesity?</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>SEAN POULTER, CONSUMER AFFAIRS EDITOR</author><text><![CDATA[Sales of fizzy drinks increase 52% when they are put at the end of aislesSales of alcohol increase 46% when it is placed at the end of aislesCoffee sales soar 74% when it is put at the end of the aisleAs a result, supermarkets could be banned from putting alcohol and fizzy drinks in these premium locations in a bid to reduce consumption
Supermarkets could be blocked from putting sugary drinks and alcohol in premium eye-catching positions in a bid to curb consumption.
New research found that sales of fizzy drinks like Coca-Cola, Pepsi and Fanta soar by 52 per cent when placed at the end of aisles.
Similarly, sales of alcohol rise by up to 46 per cent when placed at the end of the aisle rather than in the middle.
The study, which was funded by the Department of Health, will inform decisions by ministers who are under fierce pressure to tackle obesity and the health problems associated with sugar and alcohol.
The researchers involved were from the Behaviour and Health Research Unit (BHRU), which is a collaboration between the University of Cambridge, the University of East Anglia, and MRC Human Nutrition Research.
The government's chief medical officer, Dame Sally Davies, recently suggested it may be necessary to impose a sugar tax on fizzy drinks and other foods to curb consumption.
Separately, David Cameron is under fierce pressure from the medical profession to impose a minimum price on alcohol to remove the cheapest beer and spirits from sale amid concerns about binge drinking.
However, the BHRU research suggests a meaningful reduction in consumption could be delivered by simply putting controls on where products are placed.
At the same time, a decision by stores to put healthy foods, such as fruit, in these premium positions could boost sales and improve the nation's diet.
The researchers used sales data for beer, wine and spirits as well as three non-alcoholic options - fizzy drinks, coffee and tea - from a branch of a major high street supermarket.
After taking into account prices, promotions and a number of display locations, they found that sales of fizzy drinks soared by 51.7 per cent when placed at the end of an aisle. The rise for coffee was even higher at 73.5 per cent, while tea sales rose 113.8 per cent.
In terms of drink, sales of beer went up by 23.2 per cent, wine by 33.6 per cent and spirits by 46.1 per cent.
Supermarkets have long been aware that certain shelves generate stronger sales and many charge big brands a fee to ensure their products are seen at eye level.
However, this is the first time that independent scientific research has been able to quantify the remarkable impact on products linked to diet and health.
Dr Ryota Nakamura, from the BHRU and the University of East Anglia, said controls on where products are placed in stores may be necessary.
'Our study shows, for the first time, that these types of displays dramatically influence people's decisions to purchase alcohol and carbonated drinks,' he said.
'Prohibiting or limiting this marketing tactic for less healthy options, or utilising this for healthier ones, holds the promising possibility of encouraging healthier lifestyle choices.'
A debate about where products are promoted in stores is already raging around the placing of sweets, drinks and snacks that are high in sugar at the check-outs, where they capture the attention of children.
Former public health minister, Anna Soubry, made efforts to get rid of what she called 'guilt aisles' while in post. David Cameron has also been critical of chains like WH Smith for offering chocolate oranges at checkouts.
Research published by the 'Junk Free Checkouts' campaign last year found eight in ten parents were unhappy that stores continue to fuel obesity and pester power by putting sweets at the tills.
The BHRU research team also found that price does have an impact on sales. For example, for every one per cent reduction in the price of beer there was a 5.6 per cent rise in sales.
Similarly, there was a 5.2 per cent rise in sales of wine and five per cent for spirits.
Lower prices were a smaller factor for non-alcoholic drinks. A one per cent price drop saw a 2.3 per cent rise in sales of fizzy drinks, two per cent for coffee and 1.8 per cent for tea.
The director of the BHRU, Professor Theresa Marteau, from Cambridge, said: 'Although we often assume price is the biggest factor in purchase choices, end-of-aisle displays may play a far greater role.
'It would therefore make sense that any intervention to curb the consumption of alcohol and sugar-sweetened drinks takes this into consideration.'
The research is published in the journal Social Sciences and Medicine.
]]></text></news-item>