<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="52A2-F084-2EFA-58AA"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>VINNIE'S FRACKING FEARS</title><source>Wales on Sunday</source><author>James mccarthy</author><text><![CDATA[fEARS fracking could contaminate water supplies with chemicals and wipe out plants and wildlife in Wales have been voiced.
The National Trust has called for shale gas extraction to be banned from vast swathes of the country - including Snowdonia, Brecon Beacons and Pembrokeshire national parks - and the organisation's concerns have been echoed by former Wales captain Vinnie Jones.
Keen angler Vinnie - the star of Lock, Stock and Two Smoking Barrels - feared the effects fracking might have on fish.
"Fracking will increase the risk of pollution and that will be bad for wildlife," he said.
The trust's James Lloyd warned the risks of things going wrong with new technologies in "sensitive areas" was too great to chance. "If you value these places you should not allow that to happen," he said.
The trust's views were made clear in a report penned with groups including the RSPB, the Wildfowl and Wetlands Trust and the Angling Trust. "Disturbance can be quite great in certain places, things like habitat fragmentation," he said.
"In these special places impacts can be even greater."
Fracking could impact on migratory birds like the pink footed goose, found in North Wales.
"These are the kinds of risks that can be assessed at every site," Mr Lloyd said.
"Preventing needless harm is about saying some areas are more valuable than others."
The trust wants to ensure pollution caused by the industry would be cleaned up by it.
"We are in a situation where there are lots of cuts to Natural Resources Wales," Mr Lloyd said.
"We are asking to make sure that the industry picks up some of the costs of any environmental damage so that it does not fall on the taxpayer."
The trust is calling for fracking firms to pay bonds to ensure they pay for accidents.
"If you have a company that is responsible for pollution but they go out of business the cost of the clear up is left," Mr Lloyd said.
Fracking firms needs public support to operate.
"It will be difficult to get that social license to operate if public support is not there," Mr Lloyd said. Angling trust chief executive Mark Lloyd accepted there was no problem with fracking "if everything goes well and they operate as they say."
But pollution could wreck eco systems. "Any spillage could cause pollution down river which could be fatal for fish and it could take years for them to recover," Mr Lloyd said. The impact could be felt for "many decades after.
"If there was a big pollution incident it could kill thousands of fish. That could be especially disastrous on rivers where there is a five-year life cycle."
The Wildlife and Wetlands Trust, which has a site at Llanelli, was concerned about water quality.
"That is the main thing we are looking at because of the chemicals that are used in pressurised fracking," a spokesman said.
"There is a lot of liquid used that something has to be done with.
"If it gets into the water supply you are going to affect the entire habitat. That is what makes wetlands particularly vulnerable."
He worried "exclusion zones" to keep fracking sites away from human water supplies would not be www.effective.UK government ministers this week rejected a "blanket ban" on fracking in national parks. They claimed councils should decide whether it was suitable.
]]></text></news-item>