<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="52D9-A945-70A7-112B"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>LINES OF FIRE; FILM</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>John McDonald - John McDonald also writes on visual art for The Sydney Morning Herald.</author><text><![CDATA[The Monuments
Men Directed by George Clooney
Screenplay by George Clooney and Grant Heslov, based on the book by Robert Edsel and Bret Witter
Starring George Clooney, Matt Damon, Cate Blanchett, Bill Murray
USA, rated M, 118 mins
Hannah Arendt
Directed by Margarethe von Trotta
Screenplay by Pam Katz and Margarethe von Trotta
Starring Barbara Sukowa, Axel Milberg, Janet McTeer, Julia Jentsch, Germany, Israel, Luxembourg, France; rated PG, 114 mins
George Clooney takes a populist view of Nazi art theft, while Hannah Arendt is all about complex conviction, writes John McDonald.
When you see German soldiers with flame-throwers destroying works of art in one of the most striking scenes from The Monuments Men, remember that it never actually happened. The Raphael picture we see going up in flames is still listed as "missing" today, not officially torched.
One might think the Nazis were bad enough but Hollywood always needs to take matters that little bit further.
The Nazis made bonfires of modernist pictures they found "degenerate", but even some of the worst war criminals could not bring themselves to destroy works by artists such as Van Eyck, Michelangelo or Rembrandt. Nevertheless, Hitler invited such a catastrophe with his Nero Decree, which called for the destruction of everything of value to the enemy once it became obvious the war was lost. The fanatical Gauleiter, August Eigruber, believed the looted art stored in salt mines in the Austrian village of Altaussee should also be destroyed, but it was his own comrades who stopped the process.
Watching The Monuments Men, directed and co-scripted by George Clooney, who also plays the role of group leader Frank Stokes, one is constantly wondering what is true and what has been invented. Having now read the book by Robert Edsel and Bret Witter, I can report that Clooney has taken some severe liberties with the historical record. He is not in the same class as Quentin Tarantino, whose I nglourious Basterds (2009) was positively offensive in its rewriting of World War II, but there is the same persistent jauntiness with a subject that may not seem especially cheerful.
One may give Clooney the benefit of the doubt and assume he was not trying to make a popular cash-in, but an old-fashioned, patriotic war flick, in which the Allies are spotless heroes and the Nazis are rats. The giveaway is the score by the versatile Alexandre Desplat, which is all marching music and synchronised whistling - a parodic echo of the great war films of the past.
There was an offbeat aspect to the Monuments, Fine Arts and Archives division of the United States army: it was made up of art historians, curators, conservators and artists. Their task was to identify sites of historical and cultural value and try to prevent unnecessary damage. They were also tasked with finding works of art stolen by the Nazis, which had to be returned to the rightful owners. There has never been anything like the MFAA before or since, although the looting of the Iraq national museum in 2003 suggests the Americans may have abandoned the idea too soon.
As the book reveals, the MFAA had only partial success in dissuading the army from its destructive ways. The Monuments Men couldn't save the Abbey of Monte Cassino, or the antiquities of Saint-Lo, while most of Germany seemed to be flattened by the time they arrived. The damage was virtually indescribable, along with the lists of artworks lost forever.
Where this small group had more success was in tracking down works the Nazis had plundered and stashed. The thefts were organised and methodical, on an outlandish scale. The great private art collections of Paris, which were mainly owned by Jewish collectors and art dealers, were quickly seized. Works from museums and cathedrals, such as Michelangelo's Madonna of Bruges, were purloined under the fiction of "safe-keeping". Almost nothing was safe from the Nazis' greed. They didn't stop at paintings and sculpture; they took furniture, tapestries, jewellery, books, silverware, archives, artefacts and anything else that caught their fancy.Simple concepts
Hitler and Göring were the two greatest thieves, with the most important works going ito their private collections. For the Führer, everything was destined for a glorious museum in his home town of Linz, which would bring together the art treasures of Europe.
The stories of the real Monuments Men are extraordinary enough but Clooney has added a little drama and suspense to the mix. Edsel and Witter's book invites such a treatment, being written in a brassy "best-seller" style that soon becomes irritating.
George Stout, the basis of Clooney's Frank Stokes, is described as "dapper" no fewer than nine times. James Rorimer, the model for Matt Damon's James Granger, is repeatedly called a "bulldog".
We are told on several occasions that Rose Valland, who is Cate Blanchett's Claire Simon, was "no wilting flower".
It seems the authors drew inspiration from Hitler's observation: "The crowd will succeed in remembering only the simplest concepts repeated a thousand times." It's a lesson that has been well learnt by Australia's political leaders.
If one can stop thinking about history and simply surrender to the action and entertainment, The Monuments Men, with its all-star cast, is a diverting experience. It alerts us to a part of the war effort which has been overlooked and undervalued. It makes a case for preservation of cultural heritage that is forever being forgotten by the military hierarchy.
It even raises a big ethical question as to whether any work of art, no matter how great, is worth a human life.
It's a shame these worthy achievements are tied ito a film that feels like a cross between The Dirty Dozen and Hogan's Heroes. There may be a comforting familiarity about the Hollywood clichés that Clooney employs, but it's hard not to feel that, in the midst of this cheesy confection, an excellent documentary has gone begging.Hannah Arendt
The jollities and distortions of The Monuments Men would not have impressed Hannah Arendt, the German-Jewish intellectual who wrote an impressively forensic account of the trial of Adolf Eichmann, whom some describe as the architect of the Final Solution. Neither would they go down well with Margarethe von Trotta, who has made a long line of deeply serious, deeply feminist movies about German politics and interpersonal relationships, starting with The Lost Honour of Katharina Blum (1975) co-directed with her then-husband, Volker Schlöndorff.
Von Trotta's typically spare biopic of Hannah Arendt (1906-75) concentrates on a brief, dramatic period of the writer's life, when she flew to Jerusalem in 1961 to attend the trial of the Nazi bureaucrat, and report for The New Yorker. The account, serialised in the magazine, then published as the book, Eichmann in Jerusalem (1963), was a sensation, as Arendt refused to accept the ideological claims of the Israeli government of David Ben-Gurion that had kidnapped Eichmann in Argentina and brought him to trial.
She found this show trial, of dubious legality, did not help explain anti-Semitism. Instead, she analysed the hypocrisy of the Israelis and the terminal mediocrity of the defendant. Watching Eichmann in the dock, she coined the famous phrase, "the banality of evil". Back home in New York, her unwillingness to take the easy, propagandistic line generated enormous hostility. She received death threats, was spurned by friends and colleagues, and vilified in the press.
Her detractors were not simply one-eyed fanatics. Many of her intellectual peers felt she was too willing to treat Eichmann as a buffoon, while apportioning blame to the victims, who are portrayed as being complicit in their own extermination.
Then, and today, the Holocaust is not a subject that allows for fine discriminations in determining guilt.
Today, we know a little more about Eichmann and the consensus is that he was a more responsible figure than Arendt believed. Yet the arguments still rage about the role of ordinary Germans in the Holocaust and the reasons the Jews were seemingly so co-operative with their executioners. Many of these arguments are rehearsed in Hannah Arendt, a film filled with ideas and intelligent conversation. The overall impression we take away is of Arendt as a martyr to the truth - a woman of unflinching honesty whose views have now been vindicated.
The reality is that some of her views have been vindicated and others refuted. Von Trotta's position is influenced by her obvious admiration of Arendt, whom she portrays in a warm, human manner. Much of the film is about Arendt's relationships with figures such as her husband, Heinrich Blücher (Axel Milberg); her friend, Mary McCarthy (Janet McTeer); and colleague, Hans Jonas (Ulrich Noethen). We even have ambiguous flashbacks to her student days, when she was the mistress of Martin Heidegger, the great philosopher forever tainted by his involvement with the Nazis.
Barbara Sukowa gives a convincing performance in the lead role, constantly puffing away on cigarettes and poring over papers. How else does one portray thinking or writing? Her Arendt is a tough cookie with a compassionate soul. It's a plausible portrait which suggests Arendt had a touch of intellectual arrogance that wouldn't allow her to be diverted from the course she had chosen.
In one scene, Arendt is confronted by Mossad agents on a lonely road, who ask her not to continue with her account. Had George Clooney been directing, she would have floored her antagonists with a few karate kicks and fled in a hail of gunfire. For von Trotta, it's enough they have a chat.
It's clear von Trotta is holding Arendt up as a model of fearless conviction rarely found in academic circles today. Arendt's account of the trial threatened her reputation and her university job. It placed her marriage and friendships under strain, and made her the target of mindless hostility. It's a long way from the bloodless battles fought by deconstructionists and pop culture theorists. She would diagnose our present situation as a world in which banality has become its own form of evil.
]]></text></news-item>