<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="530C-C081-744A-4B95"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Colleges, Ukraine and safeguarding hospitals</title><source>European Union News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Office of the MP Chris Leslie, UK Government has issued the following news release:
We’re debating the Government’s Care Bill in the House of Commons on Monday and Tuesday next week – and I have already received many emails and letters from local people concerned about the so-called ‘hospital closure clause’ of this Bill, which many fear will enable the Secretary of State to close NHS services with minimal local consultation.
The background is this: in July 2012 the Government announced that South London Healthcare Trust (SLHT) would be put into administration because of financial difficulties, appointing an administrator who recommended the breakup of that Trust and that Lewisham Hospital should lose its A&E and maternity department. Campaigners challenged that decision and the High Court ruled in July 2013 that the Health Secretary’s decision was unlawful and the Court of Appeal upheld this verdict. I’m glad that the courts took this view, because there was no real consultation or local input into what should happen. But in response, Ministers are trying to change the law to allow rapid, centralised decisions without meaningful consultation. I appreciate that sometimes difficult decisions do need to be made on hospital services and when they are based on a clear clinical case that lives will be saved, this should be supported. But the problem with the Government’s proposals are that they focus purely on financial planning rather than the community interest and saving lives. It is also striking that the Government are embarking on the single biggest hospital closure programme the NHS has ever seen at the same time as A&E departments are under increasing pressure.
I hope that the Government does not succeed in introducing its new powers to close hospital services without proper consultation in future. As such, I will be voting to amend this Bill to ensure patient and resident views – and healthcare professionals – are properly involved in future planning.
NOTTINGHAM
Further education is under great strain across the country and also in Nottingham. I met with the Deputy Chief Executive of New College Nottingham, Paul Lonsdale, and also Paul Eeles from the East Midlands FE Council this week to discuss the Government’s decision to cut funding for 18 year olds by a massive 17%, creating real problems for course planning and a risk that this age group will suffer as a result. There are real dangers to the approach to funding that Ministers have chosen – especially if young people who choose a vocational route are punished at age 18 by this bizarre drop related to age rather than need. There are two funding bodies – the Education Funding Agency and the Skills Funding Agency – but 18 year olds are falling between the gap left by these disjointed organisations. Local businesses in Nottingham need a stable and growing level of skilled people into the workforce and decisions like this will undermine such an approach.
It was National Apprenticeship Week this week, and I am pleased that Nottingham City Council has welcomed 50 new young apprentices into its Neighbourhood Services Department. This is the start of a joint initiative called Get Notts Working, which is asking companies to pledge to take on an apprentice with the aim of identifying at least 300 apprenticeships in the next 100 days. Apprenticeships are really important for young people, but research this week has criticised the Coalition Government for not raising enough awareness of its apprenticeship programme, with many businesses completely unaware of the scheme. In particular, the Government’s statement on Wednesday included nothing about raising employer demand for apprenticeships – even though 92% of firms in this country do not offer apprenticeships – improving the quality of further education courses or licensing colleges as specialist centres of technical education.
On Friday I met with Nottinghamshire Police Chief Constable Chris Eyre to discuss issues facing the local force and options for future reform. The Chief Constable has a clear vision for local policing but also an understanding of the financial pressures and challenges that will test the ability of the police to respond in the years ahead. Together with local Police Commissioner Paddy Tipping, I hope to work closely with the police as the contend with some severe budget pressures and especially to make sure that the right arguments are heard regarding the funding formula for allocating grant.
I had a chance to visit the team at a new company called McGibney Productions on Friday who are trying to make a film called ‘Stereotype’, which is about knife crime, stereotyping and the power of choice. The film they propose to make is centred on a teenager who takes a knife out with him for revenge, and has the choice of whether or not to use it. They intend the film to be used as a tool to educate young people on the dangers of knife crime and creating a positive change. The recent knife amnesty by Nottingham Police saw 278 handed over, and it is important that we raise knife-crime awareness. They are just over £1,000 off raising the £5,000 they need to complete the film. You can support this project here.
I was the guest speaker for the University of Nottingham’s British Party Politics students on Friday, where I discussed issues that may arise in the 2015 General Election. There was then a short Q&A session with the students, and it was great to hear some of their ideas on politics.
Congratulations to Pat Ferguson who was elected as a Nottingham City Councillor in Clifton at Thursday’s by-election. Labour took the seat with a majority of 154, and the national media picked up the fact that the LibDems were pushed into last place, beaten by the Bus-Pass Elvis Party…..
POLITICS AND PARLIAMENT
The crisis in Ukraine has dominated matters in Parliament this week, as diplomatic talks continue to try to resolve what is the most serious threat to European security in decades. Russia’s incursion into Ukraine is an unambiguous, unprovoked and unjustifiable violation of the sovereignty and independence of Ukraine and it deserves to be condemned across the international community. The immediate priority must now be to de-escalate the crisis and stabilise the situation. The Ukrainian Government has shown remarkable restraint in the face of this severe provocation and has a key role to play in helping to diffuse the situation. I believe the UK Government, the EU and the international community now need to give the Ukrainian Government necessary support while making it clear that they must be inclusive and protect the rights of Russian-speaking populations within Ukraine. As I said when I met Leigh Harrison, the Chair of Nottingham’s Ukrainian Cultural Centre this week, I also believe that all diplomatic and economic options should remain on the table and that the Government need to make it clear to President Putin that there will be costs and consequences if Russia do not alter their present course in the days ahead.
On Thursday the Home Secretary updated MPs on the findings of the Ellison Review, which was set up to examine allegations of police corruption in the investigations into the death of Stephen Lawrence and allegations that undercover police had been deployed to ‘smear’ and gather evidence on the Lawrence family. These are, of course, extremely serious allegations and the findings of the Ellison review are deeply disturbing. Ellison found that there were reasonable grounds for suspecting that one of the officers involved in the Lawrence case acted corruptly, that the full information about corruption and internal corruption investigations within the Metropolitan Police was not given to the 1999 Macpherson inquiry and that key evidence was the subject of “mass shredding” by the police in 2003. The review also concluded that undercover police operations were carried out against the Lawrence family and friends and that these operations were completely improper and wholly inappropriate. These are shocking findings and it is right that a public inquiry will now be set up to investigate the conduct of undercover police officers in the Met’s former Special Demonstration Squad (SDS). Separately, in Nottingham we have had recent experience of issues surrounding questionable undercover police operations and the collapse of the trial of environmental protesters four years ago. I also hope therefore that the Home Secretary considers wider reforms, including on the oversight of undercover policing and replacing the Independent Police Complaints Commission (IPCC) with a new independent police standards commission which can get to the truth much more quickly and prevent injustices from occurring.
The Commons also debated the issues facing the 4 million households living in the private rented sector this week. It is clear that too often renters are unable to find the secure, affordable and decent homes they need. Indeed, some 33% of all privately rented homes are estimated to be ‘non-decent’ and the CLG Select Committee’s report highlighted the need to raise standards in this sector. The Select Committee’s report also outlined a number of wider concerns about the private rented sector, including affordability, lack of security of tenure, lack of regulation for letting agents, illegal evictions and lack of protection for tenants. The Government’s response to these problems, however, has been hugely complacent and they are failing to reform the private rented sector so it works for tenants. A national register of landlords could help here, and we should regulate letting and management agents to help end excessive fees and take stronger action on introducing longer-tenancies. The Government also need to look seriously at raising the housing supply in the private rented sector, as private rents are rising faster than wages, home ownership is being pushed further out of reach for many people and access to social housing is becoming increasingly difficult.
WHAT DO YOU THINK?
Is there a growing problem with gambling in Nottingham? The Campaign for Fairer Gambling this week published some startling figures for the city; there are 53 licenced betting shops locally, with over £218million gambled, and £40million of cash inserted into the ‘fixed odds betting terminals’ (FOBTs), sometimes known as B2s; touch screen roulette machines found in betting shops on which gamblers can play casino style games with £100 maximum stake per spin. As a society, should we be relaxed about the free choice individuals have to use money in this way? Or are there forms of gambling – high-speed and high-stakes – which risk serious addiction and financial ruin? If you, family or friends have encountered issues especially with these FOBT machines, I’d be interested to hear our observations. Should we be looking at reforms which limit the maximum stakes, speed of play and how we can break up the cycles of continuous play that lead to large sums of money being lost in a relatively short space of time? I think that local authorities should have a greater role in regulating the numbers and availability of these high stakes machines. But I’d welcome any thoughts you might have.
For more information please visit: http://www.chrisleslie.org.
]]></text></news-item>