<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="533E-E89B-24E4-78A0"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Energy firm is urged to take part in public event on fracking; E YORKS: Company behind drilling refuses to attend debate</title><source>Hull Daily Mail</source><author>James Campbell</author><text><![CDATA[InShort An energy company behind drilling in East Yorkshire is refusing to take part in public events on fracking because it insists it is not involved in the practice.
ANTI-FRACKING campaigners are urging a company behind well drilling in East Yorkshire to attend a public event on the controversial practice.
HEY Frack Off wants a representative from Rathlin Energy to explain exactly what it is doing at sites in Walkington and Aldbrough. But Rathlin insists it is not fracking - a way of breaking up shale rock to release natural gas - and has no reason to take part in such a debate.
HEY Frack Off is holding two public information events in the next week, where a documentary on fracking will be screened. Richard Howarth, of the campaign group, said: "We want people to be informed and ensure they know what is happening in their backyard.
"Rathlin Energy has said it is not fracking, but it has submitted an application for a permit to pump liquid into the wells.
"We would love for someone from Rathlin to come to a public event and explain what it is doing.
"Why is it drilling well below the conventional reserves if it's not looking to frack for shale gas? "The important thing is that people are informed and they can then make up their own minds."
But the Canadian energy company says an application for environmental permits relates to drilling that has already taken place and has no intention of fracking.
A spokesman said: "Why would we take part in a public event about fracking when we are not involved in it? "We will not be attending events about fracking because that isn't what we are doing."
The company began drilling in a field off Walkington Heads in Crawberry Hill in February 2012 to look for oil and gas deposits and then began to explore the site at the village of Fosham, near Aldbrough, in Holderness.
Initial drilling has now been completed at both sites but concerns have been raised by residents after Rathlin submitted an application for environmental permits.
They allow for the drilling and the disposal of low-grade radioactive waste.
Rathlin decided to drill after commissioning a seismic survey of the area to look for oil and gas deposits, although there was only a one in ten chance of fuel actually being discovered.
The company is also carrying out fall-off tests, known as a mini-frac, which it insists is to determine the layout of the rock and is not a precursor to fracking.
If the results show fossil fuels are present at the site, the company will need to secure further planning permission before extracting it.
Meanwhile, the first of the two public events, organised by HEY Frack Off, will take place on Friday, from 7.15pm, at the Methodist Hall in Hallgate, Cottingham.
The second will take place on Wednesday, from 7pm, at the Elm Tree Inn in High Street, Aldbrough.
A documentary by Marco Jackson, called Fracking In The UK, will be aired at the free events, followed by a question and answer session.
Drilling deep underground FRACKING is short for "hydraulic fracturing".
The process involves drilling deep underground and releasing a mix of water, sand and chemicals to crack rocks and release the gas stored inside.
The water is pumped in at high pressure to crack the shale with the gas fed into a pipeline.
In May 2011, there were two minor earthquakes around Blackpool, which were caused by fracking nearby.
One of the tremors registered 2.3 on the Richter scale.
]]></text></news-item>