<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5384-DAEA-59B2-BF39"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Holding out pays off: 75% tax-free</title><source>The Journal News (Westchester County, New York)</source><author>By, Jonathan Bandler</author><text><![CDATA[Westchester County correction Officer Rocco Caldarola got used to getting a regular paycheck for 16 years while not actually going to work.
So much so, that after his disability retirement was approved in December - giving him a tax-free pension equal to 75 percent of his final salary - he bemoaned his status because retirement amounts to a pay cut from his $90,020 annual salary.
Caldarola said he's gone through tough times in recent years. His wife died in 2010 and he said he also suffered a stroke. And then there were the years, he said, spent sitting at home during his shift as required by his disability leave.
"People think it's a thrill. But it's not," Caldarola said. "It's the worst thing that can happen. You're a prisoner in your house."
He had five years on the job when he was injured on Sept. 2, 1992. Caldarola slipped on a wet floor at the Valhalla jail, injuring his left thumb, wrist and hand. He returned to work in 1994 but that September re-injured his hand when he turned a large key opening a door. County officials could not provide work records for the next three years, but after Oct. 28, 1997, he never worked again.
In 1999, he was on a list of disabled correction officers suspected of working other jobs despite their injured status. He was among five arrested and paraded before the media that summer. Even though the tip that he was running a landscaping business didn't pan out, he was accused of defrauding taxpayers by living in Connecticut in violation of the law that public officers live in the state. He had bought a home in New Fairfield, which is where he was in January when he spoke briefly to a reporter.
The charge was eventually dismissed - Caldarola insisted he also had a place in West Harrison, where he was actually living to satisfy the residency requirement. His federal lawsuit against the county for false arrest went nowhere.
Caldarola could have retired in 2012 once he reached his 25th anniversary. But a service retirement would have given him a pension of only 50 percent of his final salary - about $40,000 - and it would have been taxed.
So he held out for the disability retirement, which will likely amount to $60,000 to $65,000 a year tax-free. Correction officers whose disabling injury involved an inmate get the three-quarters pension. So how did Caldarola qualify for this? An inmate had just mopped the floor the day he slipped in 1992.
]]></text></news-item>