<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="538E-223D-AFA8-A60A"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>'Sports bodies must use face value of icons'</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Shatabdi Chakraborty</author><text><![CDATA[PANAJI: The future of Olympic sports hit a roadblock last year when Indian Olympic Committee imposed a ban on the Indian Olympic Association (IOA). After a long stand-off, the suspension was finally withdrawn in February this year when the IOA conducted a fresh poll.
Anurag Thakur, who is the current joint secretary of the Board of Control for Cricket in India (BCCI), was elected the vice president of IOA. During an exclusive mail interview with TOI, he revealed where IOA and other sports bodies lack when it comes to emulating BCCI's success. Excerpts...
What is the objective of the newly elected IOA body, keeping in mind the controversies your predecessors had been embroiled in?
Our objective was to get the IOC ban lifted and we have successfully achieved that. The next step is to work for the 2016 Rio de Janeiro Olympic Games and to have better coordination with various federations and the central government to win more medals.
You are well versed with the functioning of the "rich" BCCI. Now you are with the IOA. Is it money only that the other boards lack when it comes to bettering their image and the prospect of sports?
BCCI is financially an independent body and IOA is still dependent on government aid. This makes a lot of difference.
The legends of cricket have helped in better marketing of the game. Other sports bodies should also market their respective sports using the face value of the icons and generate more revenue. Most importantly their activities should be more transparent than they have so far been.
There have been charges made against the newly elected IOA president that he cold-shouldered Indian athletes at the Sochi Winter Olympics...
Mr Ramachandran, soon after getting elected as the president, went to Sochi to boost the morale of the Indian athletes. That shows how committed he is about the betterment of the athletes. So the question of ignoring or cold-shouldering the athletes doesn't arise. If there is any communication gap or misunderstanding, it can always be sorted out.
IPL has been under the scanner so is N Srinivasan. As a BCCI joint-secretary you were close to him. Do you believe he is the right person to don the ICC mantle?
I think there is the law of the land in this country and all the allegations leveled against him have been probed into by two of the best police forces in the country: Delhi and Mumbai. Even the Supreme Court is monitoring the case. Let the law take its own course. If the ICC elects him as president, it means they have faith in him.
At this moment when people fear every cricket match is fixed, do you have any answer to assure the followers of the game that it still is a gentleman's game?
There are few bad people in every walk of life but that doesn't mean every person is corrupt, right? Having said that, cricket is the most popular game (in the country) and cricketers shouldn't indulge in malpractices which bring bad repute to the game. BCCI is trying hard to educate players about it and make the anti-corruption unit more effective. Those who are found guilty will be punished. We have done it in the past and we'll act firmly in the future as well.
Running any sports body is all about team work. But what contribution can we look forward to from you personally in terms of betterment of Olympic sports and sportspersons at large?
I think we need to create a more pro-sport atmosphere in the country. We need to involve corporates in creating infrastructure besides providing jobs to athletes. The annual budget of the youth and sports affairs ministry in this country is about Rs 1,000 crore. Is it enough for a country of 1.2 billion? We need more CSR (corporate social responsibility) funds to help promote other sports (besides cricket).
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>