<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="53D5-8618-D410-B747"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Aer Lingus to sue SIPTU for (EURO)3m; Strike action 'cost us money and passengers'</title><source>Irish Daily Mail</source><author>Neil Michael Chief Reporter</author><text><![CDATA[AER LINGUS plans to sue SIPTU for an estimated (EURO)3million damages for breach of contract and 'conspiracy' over strike action that had been planned for the St Patrick's weekend.
The airline claims the secret ballot taken by SIPTU before the four-hour strike planned for yesterday was 'wrongful and unlawful.' It also claims notification of the proposed industrial action was 'unlawful'.
The action was blocked by a High Court injunction earlier this week.
As well as 'damages for conspiracy', the airline is also suing the union for 'inducing a breach of the [airline's] contracts with its customers'. And Aer Lingus is seeking damages for 'the unlawful interference with [its] business'.
Airline bosses insisted last night the action was going ahead because the union's decision to stand down from its planned strike was 'too little too late'.
SIPTU had planned the action for yesterday as part of its row over pension entitlements. And the airline - which has said it is unable to meet demands to pump more money into the deficit-hit workers' pension - has also issued proceedings directly against Dermot O'Loughlin, SIPTU's pensions policy adviser.
He was unavailable for comment last night but union sources have said he intends to mount a 'rigorous' defence against the airline.
After the strike was first threatened, Aer Lingus hired four extra planes and extra staff. It said it had to offer refunds or book new flights for thousands of passengers for one of its busiest days.
Industry sources told the Mail the damages could reach around (EURO)3million. It is believed the Dublin Airport Authority could also attempt to recoup its estimated (EURO)50,000 costs.
It made the successful court bid to halt SIPTU's strike.
Aer Lingus said: 'SIPTU's decision on March 12 to stand down its work stoppage planned for March 14 was too little too late. The damage had already been done. The decision came less than 36 hours before the stoppage was due to commence.
'The cloud of uncertainty created by the strike threat has damaged Aer Lingus' business and disrupted thousands of our customers.
'The changes made to our flight schedule, to circumvent the planned strike, could not be undone at such short notice.' Ryanair last night welcomed the decision to sue SIPTU.
But Roisin Shortall TD last night said Aer Lingus's action was 'a despicable act of corporate bullying.' neil.michael@dailymail.ie
NOW AIRLINE'S PILOTS COULD WALK OUT
AIRPORTS and passengers could still be plunged into chaos as Aer Lingus pilots are set to vote in a secret ballot for strike action of their own.
The Irish Airline Pilots Association's Aer Lingus members are conducting a ballot on March 25 for industrial action.
They claim the airline is going to withhold increment payments that are due to staff under a cost-cutting deal.
In a letter to members, seen by the Mail, IALPA claimed the airline's management has 'declared they do not intend to pay the 2014 increment'.
IALPA has recommended members vote in favour of industrial action, saying 'together we bargain, divided we beg'.
So-called gain-sharing payments are due to staff as part of the Greenfield programme - a multi-million euro cost-saving plan agreed with workers.
The deal provided that from 2009 onwards, a lump sum was set aside for staff each year for four years if productivity targets were met.
The money, averaging (EURO)1,200 to (EURO)1,400, was due to be paid to Aer Lingus employees on April 1. Neither IALPA nor Aer Lingus was available to comment.
'Despicable act of bullying'
]]></text></news-item>