<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="53DB-AB79-6AC5-93E3"><date>2014-03-09</date><title>Sen. Binay eyes probe into rising drug trades in casinos</title><source>Philippines News Agency</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ANILA, March 9 -- 'Sen. Nancy Binay has filed a Senate resolution urging proper committees to investigate reports about the rising activities of drug dealers that make rounds in the gambling circles, mostly in the high-end casino hotels.
Binay said the increasing number of drug dealings and other transnational crimes in the gaming and gambling centers in the country remain unchecked by law enforcement agencies.
'Now, syndicates are using some casinos and gaming centers,' Binay said in filing Senate Resolution 539.
'These places have now become convenient hubs where drug deals easily exchange hands. They don't need cash to close deals'transactions are done discreetly using chips instead of cash,' the lady senator pointed out.
Binay added that it is important that drug enforcement agencies be more efficient, effective and stricter in implementing dangerous drugs laws to prevent the trade of illegal drugs in the country.
The Philippine National Police (PNP) has confirmed that drug deals are being done in casinos where gaming chips are used to launder dirty money in exchange for drugs.
Binay noted that international syndicates and other organized crime groups have already infiltrated casinos in Metro Manila where they carry out their transactions with the help of local counterparts.
She said that the PNP and anti-drug enforcers should see the pattern of complex crimes involving drugs, prostitution, high-roller lending operations, loan sharking and money laundering.
'The operations are conflicting and it is clear that Filipinos are not involved in the operations. There are well-entrenched organized groups behind these underground operations,' she said.
Last December, Binay said a certain Jerry Sy'an alleged assassin'was arrested at the parking lot of a popular casino in Metro Manila for illegal possession of high-powered firearms and explosives.
Sy was later released by police because he did not have any document to establish his identity.
'What is more alarming is that Sy had no passport, no immigration record, no valid ID, no address, no personal records, no next of kin and cannot even speak English,' Binay said.
According to the lady senator, law enforcement authorities should look into cases like these, as well as dig deeper into the circumstances surrounding similar cases of transnational crimes.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Philippines News Agency. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>