<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="53DB-5985-8825-2890"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Activists threaten art and corporate funding; Quagmire</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>Samantha Hutchinson</author><text><![CDATA[The art and capital relationship is under fire.
Queensland's Gallery of Modern Art (QAGOMA) is beefing up security in the wake of threats from an activist group proposing to "poison" an exhibit in protest against coal-seam gas operations of sponsor Satos.
Brisbane-based anti-fracking group Generation Alpha has threatened to attack Heritage, an installation by renowned Chinese artist Cai Guo Xiang depicting wildlife drinking from a crystal blue lake.
The threats follow the success by a group of activist artists in forcing patron Luca Belgiorno-Nettis to resign as chair of the Biennale of Sydney because of his links via Transfield Holdings to offshore detention centres.
QAGOMA director Chris Saines is adamant that leading arts institutions could not exist without long-term corporate sponsorship.
"I think certain kinds of industry will be more wary where they put their money, going forward," Mr Saines told AFR Weekend. "These groups realise that in the operations of any organisation, there is always going to be some form of activity someone in the broader community is going to object to."
Transfield, which is helping to manage the Manus Island detention centre, was a founding partner of the coming biennale and the incident has prompted concerns that companies will decrease their appetite for sponsoring the arts.
Attorney-General George Brandis has responded to the affair by asking the Australia Council to formulate a policy where government funding could be cut if recipients rejected private sponsorships.
The move has angered artists, who claim this would infringe on freedom of speech. The biennale's board is also angry, claiming it unfairly shifts blame to them for the incident. "It was Luca's decision to resign from the board and to terminate the Transfield relationship," biennale deputy chair Andrew Cameron said; Mr Belgiorno-Nettis made the decision in hope of "clearing the air" so the event could proceed uncompromised. "The board reluctantly agreed to respect his decision."
Mr Belgiorno-Nettis and wife, Anita, will remain ambassadors of the biennale, but there is uncertainty what will happen to future events in the absence of a founding partner reported to contribute upwards of $600,000 annually.
For other members of the arts community, the events have raised concerns about future funding prospects in a sector in which funding opportunities are hard to come by.
"Most of the contemporary art world would collapse without government and corporate sponsorship," renowned Australian painter Rick Amor said.
In line with comments by Communications Minister Malcolm Turnbull, Amor argued that artists intent on protesting against Australia's offshore processing activities should also refuse grants from central government funding body the Australia Council.
Prominent gallerist and artist representative Stuart Purves was more strident. "Sponsorship is incredibly hard to come by in any circumstance, and I think its totally misguided to attack the few people who have been extraordinarily supportive of the arts," he said.
Creative Partnerships Australia chiefexecutive Fiona Menzies said arts institutions had a choice, rather than a necessity, to align with corporate and private sponsors, but these partnerships were highly desirable.
"Arts organisations have to consider whether they need to have a sponsorship policy, and whether that policy aligns with their values," she said.
International artist Isaac Julien, in Sydney ahead of his exhibition Playtime, said artists were naive to believe they could function without concern for the commercial issues governing exhibitions and funding sources.
"Its completely naive to believe that there's no connection between art and capital, but it can be an impossible position to occupy. All artists have choices they can make on these positions."
]]></text></news-item>