<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5467-F86E-B8F4-985D"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>The e-crime war that's proving hard to win; Home Affairs</title><source>The Independent (London)</source><author>Paul Peachey CRIME CORRESPONDENT</author><text><![CDATA[When one of America's most notorious robbers was asked why he targeted banks, his answer was refreshingly straightforward: "That's where the money is."
The first law of Willie Sutton - who died in 1980 after decades of robbing banks - lives on. It was mentioned at a summit this week, as security experts consider the rise in e-crime and how best to tackle it.
Where does a self-respecting criminal go to make his money? It's a lot more difficult to rob banks and raid security vans. Dyes and tracking devices have made the benefit of such crimes outweighed by heavy prison sentences. But as a parliamentary-committee report found last year, many cyberspace criminals get off scot-free.
The MPs described it as a "black hole" where e-crime is committed with impunity. It is unsurprising that the enterprising criminal has sought benefits in the safer, virtual world.
And that approach has become more diverse and more professional, and is not limited to fraud, credit-card scams and other internet rip-offs. The head of Britain's élite cyber-crime unit told the e-crime conference that gangs are hiring hackers for help in "traditional" crimes in one of the growing threats to law enforcement.
Andy Archibald spoke of a sophisticated plot to hack into the computers of shipping companies in Northern Europe to help drug smugglers to evade arrest. The case highlighted how the trade has moved on from greasing the palm of a corrupt customs officer and a dodgy transport company.
Police in Belgium and the Netherlands last year seized a couple of tons of heroin and cocaine after cracking an ingenious plot by the smugglers to work out how their product was being moved through the complex container port system at Antwerp. The criminals installed malware on shipping companies' computers to break in. Able to work out the location of the containers where their drugs were loaded, the traffickers sent drivers to pick them up.
A long-established marketplace to provide illicit technology services for criminals has grown along with a smarter and more able core of professionals, said Don Smith, the technology director of Dell SecureWorks. They are more wary of police masquerading online as potential customers trying to snare the criminals. They populate a number of online places and are difficult to track. "There is no eBay of e-crime," Mr Smith said. "They know who they're doing business with."
The growing threat from e-crime is a well-known one but the capability of law enforcement to tackle it is less certain. "Law enforcement must develop and embed a new set of research, investigation and evidential skills, in order to respond," said Karen Bradley, a Home Office minister with responsibility for organised crime. A report by MPs last year was blunter. "We are not winning the war on online criminal activity. We are being too complacent about these e-wars because the victims are hidden in cyberspace," it said.
The Government says that it has dedicated £860m over five years "to deliver a step-change in the UK's cyber capabilities".
But the buzz phrase is collaboration, with a recognition that the police will struggle to entice expertise from the private sector. Five thousand detectives will be trained over the next two years in the area. The National Crime Agency has a scheme for "specials" - unpaid experts who will work with the agency - but by May it will have only 24 spread across the organisation.
]]></text></news-item>