<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="547D-FD0C-63E3-2539"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>@HD2 New Briefs head;Israel; Kerry pressuring</title><source>The Nation (Thailand)</source><author>The Nation</author><text><![CDATA[the wrong side
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;An Israeli minister yesterday said Washington's top diplomat was "wrong" for pressuring Israel in peace talks, a day before Palestinian leader Mahmud Abbas visits the White House.
His remarks came two days after US Secretary of State John Kerry criticised Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's repeated demand that the Palestinians recognise Israel as a Jewish state.
"John Kerry is wrong because he is putting pressure on the wrong side," said Environment Minister Gilad Erdan, who is considered close to Netanyahu.
"Kerry should be asking Abu Mazen [Abbas] why he is stubbornly refusing to recognise Israel as the Jewish state," he told public radio.
@HD2 New Briefs head;Safety lapses criticised
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;A fire which sparked the evacuation of a major underground US nuclear waste plant last month was preventable, according to a report highlighting safety lapses at the site.
Poor training, badly maintained equipment and unclear procedures were criticised in the report into the subterranean blaze at the Waste Isolation Pilot Plant near Carlsbad, New Mexico.
Eighty-six workers were underground when the fire broke out on a salt-hauling truck on February 5, in a rare accident at the site used to dispose of material including plutonium-contaminated waste.
Less than two weeks later a low-level radiation leak was detected, although it was not clear whether it was linked to the fire.
@HD2 New Briefs head;Rebel town in army hands
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;Syrian troops seized full control of the rebel bastion Yabrud in the strategic Qalamun region near the Lebanese border, Syrian state media reported.
"Our brave armed forces have full control over Yabrud in Damascus province and are combing through the town and removing explosive devices placed by terrorists," state television said, citing a military source.
It said troops had arrested and killed large numbers of "terrorists"— the regime's term for all opponents. It added that the army was targeting fighters fleeing Yabrud.
@HD2 New Briefs head;Modi picks Varanasi
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;India's opposition leader Narendra Modi, frontrunner to be the country's next prime minister after elections starting on April 7, will contest the polls from the Hindu holy city of Varanasi.
"Grateful to the party for giving me opportunity to contest the election from the holy city of Varanasi! An honour to contest from Varanasi," Modi tweeted.
The move is part of the Bharatiya Janata Party's tactics to win the critical northern battleground state of Uttar Pradesh, where the Hindu temple city of Varanasi, home to around 1.4 million people, is located.
@HD2 New Briefs head;Venezuela cracks down
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;Anti-government demonstrators clashed for almost two hours with riot police, who finally subdued them after President Nicolas Maduro's security forces cracked down.
Venezuela has seen almost daily anti-government demonstrations over violent crime, shortages of essential goods such as toilet paper, and soaring inflation, in the most serious challenge yet for Maduro since he succeeded late socialist-populist Hugo Chavez last year.
Maduro announced he would propose to the US the creation of a high-level commission for bilateral talks – after days of tenser than usual rhetoric between the long-time foes.– AFP
]]></text></news-item>