<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="54BF-D96F-481C-7AA5"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>AFP Asia News Agenda</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Duty Editor: Katy Lee
Tel: +852 2829 6211
ASIA NEWS HIGHLIGHTS ON FRIDAY
+ Malaysian jet search widens to Indian Ocean
+ Japan stem-cell author 'retracts' major study
+ Warnings of landslides after big Japan quake
MALAYSIA/VIETNAM/CHINA
-- The search for the Malaysia Airlines jet expands into the Indian Ocean, after the White House cited "new information" that it might have flown for hours after vanishing nearly a week ago. Malaysian authorities expected to hold press briefing around 0900 GMT (MALAYSIA-VIETNAM-CHINA-AVIATION)
JAPAN
-- The lead author of a study that promised a revolutionary way to create stem cells reportedly agrees to retract it after claims that its data was faulty. Press briefing by the institute that sponsored the research from 0500 GMT (HEALTH-JAPAN-US-STEMCELL-RESEARCH)
-- Officials warn residents to be alert to the danger of landslides after a strong 6.3-magnitude earthquake struck off southern Japan, injuring 17 people (JAPAN-QUAKE)
-- OTHER AGENDA ITEMS --
VARIOUS DATELINES
-- Rugby union. Super 15 (RUGBYU-SUPER15)
AUSTRALIA
-- Australian police drop an investigation into drugs trafficker Schapelle Corby after she was accused of profiting from crime after her release on parole from an Indonesian jail (AUSTRALIA-INDONESIA-CORBY-CRIME-DRUGS)
-- Formula One. Australian Grand Prix free practice sessions at 12:30-2:00 pm (0130-0300 GMT) and 4:30-6:00 pm (AUTO-PRIX-AUS)
-- Football. A-League action (FBL-ASIA-AUS)
BANGLADESH
-- Cricket. Previewing World Twenty20 tournament (CRICKET-T20-WORLD,PREVIEW)
CHINA
-- Moving a FOCUS on Chinese President Xi Jinping's careful efforts to build his image as a "man of the people" (CHINA-POLITICS-XI-IMAGE)
INDIA
-- India releases wholesale price inflation figures, the last before the Reserve Bank of India's scheduled monetary policy meeting in early April (INDIA-ECONOMY-INFLATION)
JAPAN
-- Nuclear power plant workers stage a rally outside the office of Fukushima operator Tokyo Electric Power to demand better working conditions (JAPAN-NUCLEAR-RALLY-LABOUR)
-- Toshiba sues South Korean rival SK Hynix following the arrest of a Japanese engineer who allegedly leaked Toshiba's trade secrets to its competitor (JAPAN-SKOREA-CRIME-TECHNOLOGY-TOSHIBA-SKHYNIX)
MACAU
-- Verdict expected in a corruption case involving Hong Kong tycoon Joseph Lau, who is charged with bribery and money laundering. Around 0700 GMT. (MACAU-HONGKONG-COURT-BUSINESS-CORRUPTION)
MALAYSIA
-- Field hockey. Sultan Azlan Shah Cup in Ipoh (FHOCKEY-MAS)
PAKISTAN
-- A special court set up to try former Pakistani military ruler Pervez Musharraf for treason resumes hearing in Islamabad (PAKISTAN-MUSHARRAF-POLITICS-COURT-TRIAL)
-- Moving a FOCUS on Pakistan's blind cricket team, who have defied the stigma they face in their home country due to their disability (PAKISTAN-INDIA-CRICKET-BLIND)
PHILIPPINES
-- Negotiators brief the press on the progress of a proposed defence accord allowing US forces greater access to Philippine bases. 0100 GMT (PHILIPPINES-US-DIPLOMACY-DEFENCE)
-- Moving a FEATURE on the women in AFP photographer Philippe Lopez's World Press Photo Award-winning image of a dramatic procession that took place days after Super Typhoon Haiyan hit the Philippines (PHILIPPINES-TYPHOON-RELIGION-CATHOLIC)
afp
]]></text></news-item>