<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5511-10D4-BC5D-651F"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Sunday's letters; Learn how to help</title><source>Tallahassee Democrat (Florida)</source><author>By, Hohmeister, Mark</author><text><![CDATA[abused children
Re: "Protection: Focus on case managers to help children" (Our Opinion, March 7).
If you could look into of the eyes of a terrified child who has just been abused and removed from the only home she knows - it's hard for most of us to imagine just how scary and isolated she feels. Now imagine being shuffled from one case manager to another and interviewed over and over again by the various agencies that are working to help you.
I urge you to contact the Children's Home Society to learn more about a powerful and important initiative that is under way in Tallahassee. The CHS is working toward the development of a Children's Advocacy Center (similar the Niceville operation) where representatives from each organization involved in the process such as child services, sheriff's department, medical professionals and licensed therapists are co-located in one warm and inviting center.
This isn't just about exams and interrogation rooms, it is about supporting children for the long term through the process, into a new home (if necessary) and ultimately through to adulthood providing nurturing support every step along the way. Please find out how you can get involved.
KIMBERLY S. DIXON
Kim.Dixon@ambwealth.com
Urge Florida's leaders
to join climate fight
Sen. Bill Nelson's statement that Florida is "ground zero" for sea level rise was a clear sign that he understands the urgency of addressing global warming. Given the PR campaign by the dirty-energy industry to spread junk science and deny climate change, elected officials making statements like this is critically important.
The next step is acting, and that means cleaning up our power plants - America's number one source of carbon pollution - and shifting to cleaner energy (like wind and solar) and energy efficiency. President Obama is moving forward with a new climate action plan to limit carbon from power plants, but he'll need the support of Florida to make that happen.
I urge more of Florida's elected leaders to join Sen. Nelson and support action on climate, starting with strong limits on carbon from power plants, so that we can protect the future of our children and our coastal communities from the worst impacts of global warming.
JENNIFER RUBIELLO
Environment Florida
That bunny can make
a terrible Easter gift
Pet stores and others may try enticing parents and grandparents into buying a beloved child a cuddly, live bunny for Easter. The sad reality is that many of these sensitive creatures will be abandoned outdoors - eventually dying of neglect or ending up in a cage, alone at an animal shelter.
Rabbits, as prey animals, are not cuddly by nature; they can be easily frightened and, being fragile creatures, injured by overly excited or active children. Their spines are easily broken. Additionally, rabbits require as much work, attention and veterinary care as dogs or cats. And, as they can live 10 years or more, they are long-term commitments, not something one may confine to a shelf when interest is lost.
If you wish to make your child's Easter truly memorable, please don't give a live rabbit unless the child's family is willing to ensure that it will be loved and cared for throughout its natural life. Otherwise, consider giving a soft, cuddly plush rabbit instead. The child will be just as happy, and you may save the life of a furry, sensitive, long-eared friend.
SHERRY GLASS
President, TLC Rabbit Rescue Inc.
Don't tweak SYG law;
it must be repealed
During the NAACP-sponsored "Moral Monday" rally March 3 at the Capitol, many members of the Florida Black Legislative Caucus passionately addressed the crowd about a number of issues including the Affordable Health Care Act, minimum wage, voting rights, and even Stand your Ground.
However, when Rep. Alan Williams failed in November to persuade a House Committee to approve a repeal bill, the Black Caucus began to settle for half-hearted efforts to "repair" or tweak SYG. They maintain it is too late to mount a serious attempt at a repeal of SYG during the current legislative session and will try for repeal next year.
But the NAACP has called for repeal now; the Dream Defenders on March 4, the first day of this legislative session, called for repeal now; black legislative bodies nationwide have called for repeal now. It is never too late for justice. It is never too late to do the right thing. It is never too late to stop the gunning-down of young black men on the streets of Florida.
During a news conference in Jacksonville this month, a group of Baptist ministers headed by the Rev. R.B. Holmes called for SYG to be repaired or repealed. It was not clear what "repairs" they would accept, but repeal is very clear. Go back to the Castle Doctrine that existed before SYG was signed into law in 2005.
Bills to tweak, repair or simply amend SYG will likely fail or make matters worse if passed. Moreover, the tweaks will not likely meet with approval by the NRA.
Currently under consideration (to name a couple of tweaks) are measures to limit neighborhood watch activities and give gun owners the right to fire warning shots. These and other halfway measures will not correct a law that shouldn't have been enacted in the first place. Don't amend it; end it!
BILL TUCKER
NAACP, Tallahassee Branch
drbilltucker@gmail.com
]]></text></news-item>