<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5558-EB0E-BBD1-7D77"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Minding their own business; DISCONTENT 'Whiz bangmarketing and a corporate box at the football, how does that help the average small or medium business?'</title><source>The Age (Melbourne, Australia)</source><author>Ben Schneiders, Royce Millar</author><text><![CDATA[There was a time when a "chamber" president's dinner was a must-attend function for Victorian Liberal MPs on the up and up. But when Victoria's leading industry group gathered at the Myer Mural Hall for the annual do in late 2011, not a single state Liberal minister fronted.
Two Labor frontbenchers found themselves the only state MPs schmoozing with the state's bosses. "We were looking for our political opponents but none appeared," says one of the ALP duo. "Clearly something was wrong." Indeed.
It was almost a year since the Baillieu Coalition's surprise victory over Labor premier John Brumby, but relations between the conservative government and the Victorian Employers' Chamber of Commerce and Industry were frosty, at best. The Liberals' no-show at their traditional friends' dinner was due, in part, to tension between a sensitive Coalition government and a proud lobby and one-time natural ally.
But the failure of ministers to pay homage to this 160-year-old institution was also a reflection of a wider problem. Like Scouts and Guides, Rotary, churches, unions and political parties, industry groups are battling a global trend away from membership, involvement and collective action. It is a cruel paradox that, like their old enemies the unions, employer groups such as VECCI are under threat from the rampant global success of their own ideology of individualism.
Founded in the mid-1800s as an employers' counter to the emerging labour movement, the current VECCI grew out of the Victorian Employers' Federation and the State Chamber of Commerce and Industry in the early 1990s. Since that time the chamber's focus has been advising, and advocating for, the many small and medium sized employers across Victoria. It has been an influential business lobby that has pressed hard on issues including industrial relations, taxation, regulation, transport and training.
Its core business has been industrial relations advice to small companies struggling with complex workplace regulations, especially around unfair dismissal. But as The Age reveals, VECCI is struggling to maintain relevance and clout amid collapsing membership, increasing reliance on government grants, and infighting over strategic direction.
It has long been regarded as a natural ally of the Liberal Party. However, as one Labor MP explains, Liberal MPs are increasingly suburban lawyers and business people who do not necessarily share the noblesse oblige community traditions of their more blue-blooded forebears from Toorak and Hawthorn.
Labor is traditionally more comfortable working in groups, and suspicious of business. But as it has drifted from its socialist objectives the ALP has reached out to employers. In Victoria, groups like VECCI have provided a handy bridge. The Bracks and Brumby governments were especially accommodating. Throughout the 2000s VECCI played the role of tough but fair and friendly agitator, pushing with considerable success on tax breaks and infrastructure. Labor poured millions - record amounts - ito VECCI coffers for programs ranging from apprenticeship training to assistance with bushfires and carbon reduction.
So close did Labor and its erstwhile enemies become that in 2010, before the state poll, the chamber elected one-time Melbourne city deputy lord mayor and Labor figure Peter McMullin as its president. Like most pollsters VECCI anticipated a Labor victory. It was a bad miscalculation, especially when the new premier was unforgiving Tory torch-bearer, Ted Baillieu.
For a full year Baillieu and his ministry had little to do with VECCI. Liberal and Labor sources agree that Baillieu felt "betrayed" by VECCI's relationship with the ALP. Relations only deteriorated further when the chamber criticised aspects of the fledgling government's first budget, complaining it had done nothing new to contain business costs and taxes and had gone soft on cuts to the public sector.
Through senior chamber figures connected to the Liberal Party, the message was passed down: tone it down or stay out in the cold.
Soon after, a new chief executive, Mark Stone, took over at VECCI. Stone, a former senior state public servant, had worked closely with influential VECCI board member and former Kennett-era minister Mark Birrell.
Not surprisingly, Stone's arrival heralded a new strategic direction for VECCI, which was battling declining membership and access to government. In a bid to compensate for its shrinking small business base, it decided to target big corporates with headquarters and offices in inner Melbourne. The Melbourne Chamber of Commerce was launched in mid-2013. Initiatives, including a corporate box at the AFL, a wine club and soirees with senior MPs, were meant to act as lures to the big end of the city.
Stone insists his city chamber is a success and, with 71 members, well on its way to reaching its five-year goal of 150 to 200. He says the city chamber gives VECCI more grunt. "It's making sure when we go to federal or state governments with a case or representing an idea, that we cover the full spectrum, we are unique in covering all industries."
But internal budget figures leaked to The Age show that in October the new city chamber was failing to meet even half of its revenue targets. Well-placed sources also say Stone's stated aim was to reboot the rest of VECCI with a record membership of 20,000. But confidential documents reveal membership is in freefall and, at just over 5100, a record low.
Stone insists the numbers are misleading; that his membership revamp ended a cut-price affiliate membership package. Once that cheap package is excluded, membership is stable, Stone says. He defends the aim of 20,000 members as more an aspirational figure to motivate staff early in his tenure.
But numbers do matter, particularly for an organisation that bills itself as the voice of business in Victoria. And one that has built its reputation representing the "little guys", the backbone of the Australian economy.
Frustrated insiders insist the new strategy only alienates VECCI's core - the small and medium enterprises in need of the advice and voice of a no-frills advocate. "Whiz-bang marketing and a corporate box at the football, how does that help the average small or medium business?" says a senior VECCI figure. "It's ridiculous."
The critics also argue that the exodus of small business has been hastened by a notable loss of VECCI's public voice. A Fairfax analysis shows the chamber's media profile has indeed slumped in the past two years, with print media mentions in 2013 just one-third of those in 2011. A review of media releases reveals it rarely criticises the Baillieu/Napthine government since the 2011 budget.
Anecdotal observations from political and media circles support the observation that the once pesky advocate for lower business taxes and improved infrastructure has all but disappeared from public debate.
Nor does Stone's insistence on the success of his membership strategy gel with the fact that just last week he summarily removed a senior executive in charge of membership, and five of the membership and marketing team.
Yet, for all its political miscalculations and doubt about its strategic direction, VECCI's leadership is not solely to blame for the organisation's plight. Other business bodies are also struggling. The Australian Industry Group lost 20 per cent of its members from 2004 to 2012. Farming groups are in similar trouble and would be lucky to represent a 10th of their constituency.
Mick Keogh, the head of the agricultural research body, Australian Farm Institute, says Australia's "fiercely individualistic" farmers are seemingly becoming even more so. Farmers' federations in Victoria and NSW are losing ground, and influence, fast. "Most organisations are losing members and therefore shrinking resources."
After a recent detailed study of farmer lobby groups, Keogh says he was frustrated by the lack of corporate information, and the reluctance of state and national farmers' bodies to disclose membership.
Rarely do industry bodies, unless forced to by regulation, disclose membership numbers. VECCI is required to by workplace law.
The demise of some business groups is explained in part by the peculiar challenges of their industries; manufacturing is an obvious example.
Deregulation of the economy is also a factor, leaving government with a lesser role in, for instance, setting prices for products such as wool or protecting industry with a tariff wall. In such cases individual businesses don't have the same need for a voice at the government table.
But wider cultural, social influences are also in play. Globally, and especially in the West, people are far less active in large collective organisations than in previous generations.
Andrew Leigh is the federal shadow assistant treasurer and a former economics professor. In 2010 he published Disconnected, a book that looked at the decline of community engagement in Australia. His work was modelled on a similar tome, Bowling Alone by US academic Robert Putnam, regarded as a landmark study in the decline of social capital in the US.
Leigh says large institutions, once the heart of civil society, are shrinking almost everywhere. "You see that with political parties regardless of their ideology. Political party membership is down about two-thirds. Church-going has halved since the 1950s. Union membership has halved since the early 1980s." Mass organisations such as Scouts, Guides, Rotary and Lions are all down, says Leigh, who cites long working hours, car commuting, television and the internet as contributors to declining engagement in community activity. He says this "tectonic shift" has undermined representative bodies and risked pushing many ito a "death spiral" of declining relevance.
VECCI as the state's main business lobby is not there yet. But the signs are not promising. In Victoria there are about 200,000 businesses that employ workers (another 300,000 or so are sole traders). VECCI represents barely 5000 of them or 2.5 per cent. Australia's embattled union movement represents about 18 per cent of workers, but its dwindling numbers have been a far greater point of focus.
As traditional mass-member organisations crumble many have developed creative ways to arrest the decline. Churches have propped up their operations through commercial investment, government funding and schools. Unions have done the same through slush funds, training and their involvement in commercial enterprises, notably superannuation. VECCI has grown both more entrepreneurial and - ironically given its small government inclination - increasingly reliant on taxpayer money (about half its income).
But its reason for being is as the voice of Victorian business. Senior insiders now fear that the organisation's bleeding base and loss of voice threatens its legitimacy and it could end up speaking only for a self-sustaining bureaucracy.
At that point maybe even "the chamber's" Labor mates might stop turning out for an annual drink.
VECCI
by numbers
Membership
7699
(2001/02)
down to 5100
(Oct 2013)
Revenue
$33.8 million
(2012/13)
up from $16.3 million
(2001/02)
% of revenue from government
49%
(2012/13)
up from 21%
(2001/02)
SOURCE: VECCI ANNUAL REPORT
]]></text></news-item>