<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="55A1-08EA-9659-9790"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Irish Continental Irish Continental Group Plc : Director/Pdmr Shareholding</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Notification of Transactions of (1) Persons Discharging Managerial Responsibility and (2) Persons closely associated with Persons Discharging Managerial Responsibility
This form is intended for use by an issuer making a notification required by Rules 7.2 and 7.3 of the Central Bank of Ireland's Market Abuse Rules in relation to a person falling within either of the above categories of individual. These categories are defined in Regulation 12 (8) of the Market Abuse (Directive 2003/6/EC) Regulations 2005 and are detailed as part of this form.
All relevant boxes should be completed in block capital letters.
Information required under Irish Stock Exchange Listing Rule 6.10
The following additional information is required to be disclosed under ISE Listing Rule 6.10 in respect of interests in securities of a director or secretary or their connected persons. An issuer is not being required to submit the information below to the Central Bank in respect of any PDMR who is also a director/secretary/connected persons.
If a person whose interests are required to be disclosed under ISE Listing Rule 6.10 has been granted options by the issuer, please complete the following boxes:
The duly designated officer of the issuer responsible for making this notification acknowledges and confirms that he/she is aware that the information as has been provided in response to the questions 15 to 26 above is not information which has been required by or which has been requested by the Central Bank, and is information which is required to be provided to the Irish Stock Exchange only.
This announcement is distributed by NASDAQ OMX Corporate Solutions on behalf of NASDAQ OMX Corporate Solutions clients.
The issuer of this announcement warrants that they are solely responsible for the content, accuracy and originality of the information contained therein.
Source: Irish Continental Group plc via Globenewswire
HUG#1768952
www.icg.ie
]]></text></news-item>