<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="55AC-C8BA-2280-CFBD"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Washington: PUBLIC BILLS AND RESOLUTIONS -- (House of Representatives - March 14, 2014)</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Library of Congress, The Government of USA has issued the following news release:
Under clause 2 of rule XII, public bills and resolutions of the following titles were introduced and severally referred, as follows:
By Mr. PASCRELL (for himself and Mr. ROONEY):
H.R. 4251. A bill to direct the Secretary of Health and Human Services, acting through the Director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, to establish a surveillance system regarding traumatic brain injury, and for other purposes; to the Committee on Energy and Commerce.
By Mr. ROTHFUS:
H.R. 4252. A bill to amend the Federal Deposit Insurance Act to allow mutual capital certificates to satisfy capital requirements for mutual depositories, to amend the Revised Statutes of the United States to establish mutual national banks, and for other purposes; to the Committee on Financial Services.
By Mr. BISHOP of Utah (for himself, Mr. AMODEI, Mr. PEARCE, and Mr. YOUNG of Alaska):
H.R. 4253. A bill to permanently withdraw, reserve, and transfer Bureau of Land Management lands used for military purposes in Alaska, Nevada, and New Mexico to the appropriate Secretary of the military department concerned; to the Committee on Natural Resources, and in addition to the Committee on Armed Services, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned.
[Page: H2484] GPO's PDF
By Mr. ROYCE (for himself, Mr. LOWENTHAL, Mr. WOLF, and Ms. LORETTA SANCHEZ of California):
H.R. 4254. A bill to impose sanctions on individuals who are complicit in human rights abuses committed against nationals of Vietnam or their family members, and for other purposes; to the Committee on Foreign Affairs, and in addition to the Committees on the Judiciary, Ways and Means, and Financial Services, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned.
By Mr. CARTWRIGHT (for himself, Mr. HORSFORD, Mr. CONNOLLY, Mr. GEORGE MILLER of California, Mrs. NAPOLITANO, Mr. GRIJALVA, Mr. VAN HOLLEN, Mr. NOLAN, Ms. HAHN, Ms. SLAUGHTER, Ms. LEE of California, Mr. FARR, Mr. HONDA, Ms. LORETTA SANCHEZ of California, Ms. ESHOO, Ms. SPEIER, Mr. HASTINGS of Florida, Mr. JOHNSON of Georgia, Mr. TONKO, Mr. FATTAH, Mr. BRADY of Pennsylvania, Ms. JACKSON LEE, Ms. EDDIE BERNICE JOHNSON of Texas, Mr. LYNCH, Ms. BONAMICI, Mr. DEFAZIO, Mr. COHEN, Mr. CÁRDENAS, Ms. KAPTUR, Mr. RUSH, Mr. GARCIA, Mr. NEAL, Ms. PINGREE of Maine, Mr. ELLISON, Mr. PALLONE, Mr. LANGEVIN, Ms. NORTON, Mr. DOYLE, Ms. CHU, Mr. THOMPSON of California, Mr. CONYERS, Ms. CLARK of Massachusetts, Mr. RANGEL, Ms. WILSON of Florida, Ms. SHEA-PORTER, Ms. LOFGREN, Ms. BROWN of Florida, Mr. CARSON of Indiana, Ms. VELÁZQUEZ, Mr. TAKANO, Mr. RUPPERSBERGER, Ms. ROYBAL-ALLARD, Mr. GENE GREEN of Texas, Mr. CLAY, and Ms. DELAURO):
H.R. 4255. A bill to require the Federal Housing Finance Agency to establish a 6-month moratorium on foreclosure of mortgages guaranteed by Fannie Mae or Freddie Mac on homes of individuals who have lost Federal unemployment insurance as a result of the expiration of such program, and for other purposes; to the Committee on Financial Services.
By Mr. STEWART (for himself, Mr. BISHOP of Utah, and Mr. CHAFFETZ):
H.R. 4256. A bill to amend the Endangered Species Act of 1973 to require, in counting the number of a species in a State for purposes of determining whether the species is an endangered or threatened species, inclusion of the number of the species on State and private lands as determined by the State, and for other purposes; to the Committee on Natural Resources.
By Mr. CALVERT (for himself, Mr. ROKITA, Mr. NUNES, Mr. COTTON, Ms. GRANGER, and Mr. ISSA):
H.R. 4257. A bill to provide for a limitation on the number of civilian employees at the Department of Defense, and for other purposes; to the Committee on Armed Services.
By Mrs. NAPOLITANO (for herself, Ms. GABBARD, Ms. HANABUSA, Mr. CARTWRIGHT, Mr. COSTA, Mr. HUFFMAN, Mr. LOWENTHAL, Mr. CÁRDENAS, Mr. RUIZ, Mr. SIRES, Mr. GRIJALVA, Mr. BEN RAY LUJÁN of New Mexico, Ms. LOFGREN, Mr. LARSON of Connecticut, Ms. HAHN, Mr. PASTOR of Arizona, Mr. DOGGETT, and Mr. TAKANO):
H.R. 4258. A bill to reauthorize and update certain provisions of the Secure Water Act; to the Committee on Natural Resources.
By Ms. DELBENE (for herself and Mr. HANNA):
H.R. 4259. A bill to amend the Higher Education Act of 1965 to lower the cost of college education by establishing pilot programs to expand student access to digital course materials; to the Committee on Education and the Workforce.
By Mrs. ELLMERS (for herself, Mr. THOMPSON of Mississippi, and Ms. EDDIE BERNICE JOHNSON of Texas):
H.R. 4260. A bill to ensure that the Ryan White Comprehensive AIDS Resources Emergency Act program is as effective as possible in saving lives and preventing the spread of the HIV epidemic by ensuring that funding allocations are evidenced-based and by promoting greater utilization of patient-centered care; to the Committee on Energy and Commerce.
By Mr. COFFMAN (for himself, Mrs. KIRKPATRICK, and Mr. MICHAUD):
H.R. 4261. A bill to improve the research of Gulf War Illness, the Research Advisory Committee on Gulf War Veterans' Illnesses, and for other purposes; to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs.
By Mr. DUFFY:
H.R. 4262. A bill to apply the requirements of the Federal Advisory Committee Act to the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection; to the Committee on Financial Services, and in addition to the Committee on Oversight and Government Reform, for a period to be subsequently determined by the Speaker, in each case for consideration of such provisions as fall within the jurisdiction of the committee concerned.
By Mrs. BROOKS of Indiana (for herself, Mr. PAYNE, Mr. PALAZZO, and Mr. SWALWELL of California):
H.R. 4263. A bill to amend the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to authorize the Department of Homeland Security to establish a social media working group, and for other purposes; to the Committee on Homeland Security.
By Mr. FORTENBERRY:
H.R. 4264. A bill to authorize the Secretary of Agriculture to enter into a lease involving the South Central Agricultural Laboratory in Clay County, Nebraska, to facilitate the improvement of the laboratory to support cooperative State and Federal agricultural research; to the Committee on Agriculture.
By Mr. HUNTER (for himself, Mr. GEORGE MILLER of California, Mr. CALVERT, Mr. PETERS of California, Mr. VARGAS, and Mr. COLE):
H.R. 4265. A bill to direct the Secretary and the Attorney General to promptly take all steps necessary or appropriate to execute and implement the San Luis Rey settlement agreement, and for other purposes; to the Committee on Natural Resources.
By Ms. MATSUI (for herself, Mr. GARAMENDI, and Mr. BERA of California):
H.R. 4266. A bill to amend the Reclamation Wastewater and Groundwater Study and Facilities Act to authorize the Secretary of the Interior to participate in the design, planning, and construction of the South Sacramento County Agriculture and Habitat Lands Water Recycling Project in Sacramento County, California; to the Committee on Natural Resources.
By Mr. MCALLISTER:
H.R. 4267. A bill to amend the Commodity Exchange Act to provide relief for end users who use physical contracts with volumetric optionality; to the Committee on Agriculture.
By Mr. NUNNELEE (for himself, Mr. THOMPSON of Mississippi, Mr. HARPER, and Mr. PALAZZO):
H.R. 4268. A bill to amend title 23, United States Code, with respect to United States Route 78 in Mississippi, and for other purposes; to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure.
By Mr. POLIS (for himself and Mr. PAYNE):
H.R. 4269. A bill to amend the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 to improve teacher and principal effectiveness, and for other purposes; to the Committee on Education and the Workforce.
By Mr. RENACCI (for himself, Mr. HIMES, Mr. CONAWAY, Mr. PETERSON, Mr. MURPHY of Florida, Mr. FLORES, and Mr. SHERMAN):
H.R. 4270. A bill to clarify that funding for the standard setting body designated pursuant to section 19(b) of the Securities Act of 1933, the Securities Investor Protection Corporation, and the Public Company Accounting Oversight Board is not subject to the sequester; to the Committee on the Budget.
By Mr. RUIZ (for himself, Mr. MCGOVERN, Ms. KUSTER, and Mr. GARCIA):
H.R. 4271. A bill to authorize the Export-Import Bank of the United States to use 3 percent of its profits for administrative expenses; to the Committee on Financial Services.
By Mr. WALDEN:
H.R. 4272. A bill to stop implementation and enforcement of the Forest Service travel management rule and to require the Forest Service to incorporate the needs, uses, and input of affected communities before taking any travel management action affecting access to units of the National Forest System derived from the public domain, and for other purposes; to the Committee on Natural Resources.
By Mr. WALDEN (for himself, Mr. DEFAZIO, Mr. BLUMENAUER, Ms. BONAMICI, and Mr. SCHRADER):
H.R. 4273. A bill to name the Department of Veterans Affairs community-based outpatient clinic in The Dalles, Oregon, as the ``Loren R. Kaufman Memorial Veterans' Clinic``; to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs.
By Mr. ROYCE (for himself and Mr. ENGEL):
H. Res. 520. A resolution calling for an end to attacks on Syrian civilians and expanded humanitarian access; to the Committee on Foreign Affairs.
By Mr. GRIJALVA (for himself, Mr. LANGEVIN, Mr. DANNY K. DAVIS of Illinois, and Mr. TAKANO):
H. Res. 521. A resolution supporting the goals and ideals of ``National Middle Level Education Month``; to the Committee on Education and the Workforce.
By Mr. TIBERI (for himself and Mr. NEAL):
H. Res. 522. A resolution expressing support for designation of September 2014 as National Brain Aneurysm Awareness Month; to the Committee on Energy and Commerce.
For more information please visit: http://thomas.loc.gov
]]></text></news-item>