<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5681-RWW1-DXCW-C0VP"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Report: Ethics investigator to question FIFA executives on Qatar vote</title><source>dpa-AFX International ProFeed</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Berlin (dpa-AFX) - The executive committee of the ruling body FIFA was meeting Thursday and Friday amid a report that several members face questioning from the ethics committee over awarding the 2022 World Cup to Qatar and new criticism from trade unions over workers' rights there. British paper Daily Telegraph said Thursday that FIFA ethics committee chief investigator Michael Garcia will question executives 'in the coming weeks' over the World Cup vote in December 2010. Thirteen of the 22 voting members are still on the decision-making committee. The report comes two days after the same paper said that former FIFA vice-president Jack Warner appeared to have received 1.2 million dollars from a company owned by former FIFA executive committee member Mohamed Bin Hammam of Qatar in 2011. The report said Warner requested the payment in December 2010 through one of his companies, 'for work carried out between 2005 and 2010', two weeks after Qatar were elected 2022 hosts by the FIFA executive.
An additional 1 million dollars was allegedly paid to two of Warner's sons and an employee, the report said, adding that the case was investigated by the FBI as well. World Cup organizers in Qatar say they did not violate FIFA bid regulations. The Qatar World Cup has also been plagued by accusations of workers' rights violations. International Trade Union Confederation general secretary Sharan Burrow said that no progress has been made on the issue and that 4,000 workers may die by the time the tournament kicks off, given current death rates of migrant workers from countries such as Nepal. 'As the FIFA executive committee meets in Zurich today, will it continue to accept false claims of progress?' Burrow said on opendemocracy.net. 'There has been no change to the kafala regime. There have been no moves to bring legislation into line with international standards on freedom of association and collective bargaining,' Burrow said. Qatar had pledged improvement after first reports of hundreds of deaths on World Cup construction sites, and FIFA boss Joseph Blatter called the situation unacceptable. Former Netherlands coach Bert van Marwijk has asked players and coaches to voice opposition against the Qatar World Cup. 'There are enough reasons not to stage the World Cup (there). Players and coaches should offer resistance. No one does it because FIFA is untouchable,' he told Dutch paper Spits. Former FA chairman and England World Cup bid boss Lord Triesman expressed his doubts that FIFA can overcome its corruption-tainted image, quoted in the Telegraph as saying the executive is 'incapable of taking the steps they should' and that its culture 'is deep in corruption and has been for decades.' Copyright dpa
]]></text></news-item>