<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5681-RWW1-DXCW-C0VK"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Bangladesh collapse victims seek compensation</title><source>dpa-AFX International ProFeed</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Dhaka (dpa-AFX) - More than 100 people, among them survivors and relatives of the victims of last year's deadly building collapse, demonstrated Monday near Dhaka, as Bangladeshi authorities began collecting applications for financial compensation. According to Barkat Ali, one of the supervisors of the documentation project in Savar, where the eight-storey Rana Plaza building that housed garment factories collapsed on April 24, 2013, information about 22 families had been collected on the first day. The accident killed more than 1,100 people, most of them garment workers.
Officials say they will need three months time to collect details about the victims and their relatives. A three-member commission will eventually set individual compensation levels, taking into account the recommendations of the International Labour Organisation and Bangladeshi law. In February, a fund known as the Rana Plaza Donor's Trust Fund was set up using contributions made by international brands who source their products from Bangladesh. According to IndustriALL, UNI Global Union and the Clean Clothes Campaign, three pressure groups, the fund will need to collect 40 million dollars to cover compensation for more than 3,000 workers and relatives of those killed. Frustrated at the slow pace of the compensation process, survivors and relatives of the victims took to the street near the collapse site Monday. 'Loss of earning should be the criterion for providing the compensation package to the victims and sufferers,' Aminul Haque Amin of the National Garment Workers Federation said after a demonstration in Dhaka. Bangladesh, the world's second biggest apparel producer after China, came under severe criticism over poor safety standards after last year's collapse and an earlier factory fire that killed 112 workers. The government has since worked to improve safety to protect its 20-billion-dollar clothing industry, which exports mainly to Europe and the United States. Copyright dpa
]]></text></news-item>