<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5681-RWV1-DXCW-C4YS"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>LEAD: Former Israeli premier Olmert found guilty of bribery</title><source>dpa-AFX International ProFeed</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[By Ofira Koopmans, dpa Eds: Updates with possible appeal; adds details, quotes, background Tel Aviv (dpa-AFX) - Former Israeli prime minister Ehud Olmert was found guilty Monday of accepting bribes during his terms as major of Jerusalem and as trade and industry minister, between 1993 and 2006. Olmert and a host of other defendants were accused of smoothing over legal and zoning restrictions for a construction project in south-west Jerusalem, known as Holyland, in return for money. The verdict likely spells the end of Olmert's political career. In Israel, the maximum sentence for accepting bribes by a public figure is 10 years.
Experts say he could face several years in jail. Sentencing arguments are scheduled to begin on April 28. The verdict makes Olmert the first former Israeli premier to have been found guilty of taking bribes. 'Olmert lied in court,' Tel Aviv District Court judge David Rozen said as he delivered the verdict. The former premier's attorney, Roy Blecher, said his team would study the 700-page verdict before deciding on an appeal, but told reporters: 'The last word hasn't been said.' 'It's not an easy day for us. It's not an easy day for Mr. Olmert,' he said. 'We will study our steps.' The judge based his decision on evidence provided by a state witness, according to whom Olmert had asked him to transfer 500,000 Israeli shekels (approximately 140,000 dollars) to his brother, Yossi Olmert. The state witness, businessman Shmuel Dechner, died last year aged 75 in the midst of the trial. Corruption allegations had forced Olmert to resign as prime minister and call early elections in 2009. Those brought Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of the nationalist Likud party back to power. A centrist, Olmert had been in the midst of far-reaching negotiations with Palestinian President Mahmoud Abbas when he was forced to step down. Both later said they had been inches from a breakthrough. In July 2012, a Jerusalem court largely acquitted Olmert in another corruption trial in which he was accused of accepting cash donations in envelopes without reporting them, and of submitting travel expenses multiple times to different institutions. He was found guilty of a lesser offense - breach of trust - and handed a one-year suspended sentence. His former office manager, Shula Zaken, had initially backed him, but last week reached a plea bargain with the prosecution. The deal involved her agreeing to serve 11 months in jail and paying a fine. The state wanted her as an additional state witness in the Holyland trial. In return it would drop its appeal to Israel's supreme court against her acquittals on major charges in the previous Jerusalem corruption trial. In that trial, she had been convicted on two minor counts. Judge Rozen, however, said he was not certain he would accept the bargain. She and Olmert were found guilty along with eight others defendants in the Holyland affair. Last week, Zaken produced a series of recordings that the prosecution argued raise a 'serious suspicion' that Olmert had attempted to obstruct justice and tamper with witnesses during the trials. The recordings could lead to further investigations. Copyright dpa
]]></text></news-item>