<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5681-RWW1-DXCW-C02F"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Toyota Enters Into $1.2 Bln Settlement With U.S. To End Criminal Probe</title><source>dpa-AFX International ProFeed</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TOYOTA (dpa-AFX) - Toyota Motor Corp. (TYT.L, TM) entered into a $1.2 billion settlement with the U.S. to end a criminal probe into unexpected acceleration that led to the recall of over 10 million vehicles. The U.S. Department of Justice said that Toyota Motor admitted that it misled U.S. consumers by concealing and making deceptive statements about two safety issues affecting its vehicles, each of which caused a type of unintended acceleration.
U.S. Attorney General Eric Holder, U.S. Secretary of Transportation Anthony Foxx, U.S. Attorney for the Southern District of New York Preet Bharara, Inspector General of the U.S. Department of Transportation (DOT) Calvin Scovel III, National Highway Traffic Safety Administration or NHTSA Acting Administrator David Friedman and Federal Bureau of Investigation or FBI Deputy Assistant Director Joe Campbell announced a criminal wire fraud charge against Toyota Motor that designs, manufactures, assembles, and sells Toyota and Lexus brand vehicles. The charge was that TOYOTA defrauded consumers in the fall of 2009 and early 2010 by issuing misleading statements about safety issues in Toyota and Lexus vehicles. The U.S. Department of Justice said that the agreement requires TOYOTA to pay a $1.2 billion financial penalty and imposes on TOYOTA an independent monitor to review and assess policies, practices and procedures relating to TOYOTA's safety-related public statements and reporting obligations. TOYOTA agrees to pay the penalty under a Final Order of Forfeiture in a parallel civil action also filed today in the Southern District of New York. The criminal charge was contained in an Information alleging one count of wire fraud. If TOYOTA abides by all of the terms of the agreement, the Government will defer prosecution on the information for three years and then seek to dismiss the charge.
]]></text></news-item>