<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="56C1-48AB-B2B9-9531"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>IRDA's Rs275 crore refund order to SBI Life proves botched product approval process</title><source>Money Life</source><author>Raj Pradhan</author><text><![CDATA[IRDA has asked SBI Life to refund Rs275 crore for collecting premium upfront on a policy, which had two premium payment terms. But why did IRDA approve this product which was cleverly designed to earn hefty commission for SBI?
The Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (IRDA) has ordered SBI Life to refund Rs275.29 crore to the policy holders as the money was collected from them in violation of norms.The product had two premium payment term (PPT). Yet, in nearly 95% of the policies sold, SBI Life had collected the second year premium for its policy Dhanaraksha Plus Limited Premium Paying Term in the first year itself. What is worse, this policy was sold to those who availed of home loans from SBI and its associate banks during the period 2008-2011. The policy was intended to cover the outstanding loan in case of death of the policyholder during the term of the loan. As every one who has taken a mortgage in recent times knows, there is also an element of indirect coercion to take these policies to secure the borrowing.SBI Life also had a single premium version of the product, but it did not provide an informed choice to the buyer. The reasons were simple. The single premium policy earned only 2% commission for intermediaries, which in this case was mainly SBI and its associate banks. The two PPT policy earned hefty 40% of the first year premium as commission and 7.5% of the second year premium as commission to banks which sold the policy. Clearly, the two PPT policy was bound to be much more expensive than the single premium policy if the commission levels have such huge difference.It can be concluded that SBI and its associated banks did not act in best of customer interest by offering a cheaper option. SBI Life crafted a product with two PPT which could not have been for customer convenience. It would have been justified if the PPT was for two-thirds or at least half of the loan repayment period. In that case, there is respite to the customer in having flexibility to pay premium over a period of time. But, what is the advantage of two PPT versus single premium for customer? It is disadvantageous as the premium paid over two years would be higher than single premium due to inbuilt humongous difference in commission levels.So, why did IRDA permit the two PPT toxic product to be launched at all? Did the regulator fail to anticipate that the product was structured to be mis-sold and is completely against customer interest? While IRDA may seem to have helped investors by asking for the premium to be refunded, this is a fit case for holding the regulator itself accountable. In fact this would also be a fit case for class action, both against SBI Life as well as the regulator. Did IRDA expect that the consumers can easily find out that single premium option was available? Approving a toxic product can remind one of ULIPs before September 2013 which even had high upfront charges of up to 70% and mind-boggling surrender charges.Getting a loan application approved itself is a task and the customer is at mercy of the bank which ensures that the customer accepts whatever loan and property insurance is offered. Any resentment from the consumer can even be deal breaker for loan application. It can be seen from the fact that 93% of second year premiums were received in advance along with first year premiums in the year 2008-09, 94% in the year 2009-10 and 97% in 2010-11. Thus the premium collected is more on lines of a single premium than two yearly regular premiums against the approved File and Use features.Making the two PPT product work as single premium by taking the second year premium upfront is a violation of approved File and Use features, but the insurer may argue that paying second year premium in advance was allowed by IRDA till 2013. But, SBI Life cannot be exonerated from its culpability to offer toxic insurance product; it casts a shadow over other life insurance products offered by the insurer.IRDA order states the following issues (a) Dhanaraksha Plus Limited Premium Paying Term product was sold as single premium policy in violation of approved File and Use features, (b) Paying excess commission to Corporate Agents over and above the eligible 2% commission they would have been otherwise eligible had the single premium version of the policy been offered. (c) No informed choice given to the members of these group insurance policies as envisaged under Regulation 3(2) and 3(3) of IRDA (Protection of Policyholders' Interests) Regulations, 2002. Thus it is concluded that these violations were detrimental to the interests of members of group insurance schemes of the concerned master policyholders.SBI Life will be appealing against the IRDA order as per the recourse available to them.
]]></text></news-item>