<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="56JX-SXK1-DXCW-D1YT"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Environment activists voice concern over river pollution</title><source>Bangladesh Government News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The official news Agency of Bangladesh (BSS) has issued following news release:
Environment movement activists today voiced deep concern over land grabbing, widespread pollution and leasing of the rivers around Dhaka city posing an environmental threat to the city dwellers.
Dhaka and its adjacent areas will face serious environmental hazards unless the Buriganga, Shitalakhya, Balu and Turag rivers are protected, they expressed the concern at a joint press conference at the Jatiya Press Club here.
Nine environment and citizen rights organizations including the National Committee to Protect Rivers, Roads and Railways jointly organized press conference.
The environment activists said the rivers around the capital were almost dead because of unabated encroachment, establishment of illegal construction on the river bank and dumping both human and industrial waste.
The Buriganga River, the lifeline of Dhaka city, could be revived as soon as possible by just putting an end to the spilling of industrial and household pollution into the river, they added.
Covenor of National Committee to Protect Rivers, Roads and Railways Ashish Kumar Dey, Secretary general of Citizen Rights Movement Tusar Rehman and leaders of other organizations, among others, addressed the press conference.
Professor Dr Md Mujibur Rahman of the Department of Civil Engineering Division of BUET presented the keynote paper at a seminar held recently in the city on the occasion of World Water Day-2014
In his keynote paper, he said, "The rivers Buriganga, Balu,and Sitalakhya are typical examples of serious surface water pollution. The worst pollution is found in Buriganga river in Dhaka mostly due to tannery wastes and domestic sewage."
"We have to protect the rivers and water sources surrounding Dhaka city from pollution to environmental hazards. Otherwise a catastrophic situation will be facing the nation" he added.
The industrial effluent discharged from Hazaribagh, DEPZ, Gazipur and Savar, and the domestic sewerage from a large part of Dhaka city through storm drain outlets are the reasons for the pollution of Buriganga-Turag-Bangshi- Dhaleshwari river system in Dhaka's watershed areas, he said.
Prof Mujibur said the Buriganga River is severely being affected due to huge pollution load from Hazaribagh industrial cluster and most of the Dhaka city domestic sewage.
]]></text></news-item>