<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="56JX-SXK1-DXCW-D1Y9"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>PM inaugurates locally made BIWTC vessel M.V. Bangali</title><source>Bangladesh Government News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The official news Agency of Bangladesh (BSS) has issued following news release:
Prime Minister Sheikh Hasina today inaugurated the commissioning of the country's first locally-made passenger vessel M.V. Bangali saying another vessel would join the state-owned BIWTC by June next to deliver better services to water route commuters.
She said rivers are the lifeline of Bangladesh. So her government is making efforts to revive all river routes through necessary dredging to put in place a wide and better water transport service in the country.
Addressing a function on the occasion on the deck of the vessel, the Prime Minister said the government has taken a project for construction of two more passenger carrying ships for Dhaka-Barisal-Khulna route.
The vessel would ply on the Dhaka-Barisal route via Chandpur,resuming BIWTC steamer service on the route after 75 years.
She said nine ferries and seven pontoons were constructed to strengthen the BIWTC ferry services. This year six ferries and one pontoon would be built while construction of two more ferrieswould be completed by 2015, she added.
The government has undertaken a plan for construction of container trailer at Mawa, special ferry and pontoon and coastal ferry services for crossing of transports in the coastal areas, she said.
Sheikh Hasina said Bangladesh Water Transport Corporation (BIWTC) has a long tradition in carrying passenger on water routes. But, no new ship was procured for the BIWTC for a long time, whereas the old ships became obsolete day by day.
She said BNP-Jamaat alliance and subsequent caretaker government created stalemate in every sector. Like other sectors, they also turned the shipping sector into a haven of unbridled corruption, she said.
Shipping Minister Shajahan Khan presided over the function arranged on lower deck of the ship on its cruise to Chandpur. Shipping Secretary Syed Monjurul Islam and BIWTC Chairman Mujibur Rahman also spoke on the occasion.
Deputy Leader of the Jatiya Sangsad Syeda Sajeda Chowdhury, Industries Minister Amir Hossain Amu, Commerce Minister Tofail Ahmed, LGRD and Cooperatives Minister Syed Ashraful Islam, Water Resources Minister Anisul Islam Mahmud, Relief and Disaster Management Minister Mofazzal Hossain Chowdhury Maya, Food Minister Quamrul Islam, state minister for Women and Children Affairs Meher Afroz Chumki and State Minister for Land Saifuzzaman Chowdhury Jabed were present.
Parliament members Dr Dipu Moni, Qazi Firoz Rashid, Hazi Mohammad Selim and Nazrul Islam Babu were also present on the occasion.
Local shipbuilder Western Marine Shipyard Limited constructed MV Bangali at a cost of Taka 26.80 crore. The ship--- 75.5 meters in length and 12.50 meters in width--- can carry 750 passengers.
The Prime Minister said the BIWTC activities were digitalized. E-ticketing would be introduced at Paturia, Dowlatdia and Kazirhat ferry ghats very soon. Vehicle Tracking System (VTS) in the BIWTC ferries and passenger vessels has made it easy to monitor the water transports to ensure safety and services of the passengers. As a result, mishap on the river routes reduced to a large extent, she said.
The Prime Minister said Father of the Nation Bangabandhu Sheikh Mujibur Rahman established the BIWTC in 1972 on-war ravaged economy. He procured eight K-type ferries from Oxfam and purchased five bay-crossing tugs, five inland tugs and 23 sea- trucks for carrying passengers in the coastal areas and between different islands.
At that time, Sheikh Hasina said, 21 bay-crossing barges and two oil tankers were constructed in Khulna Shipyard. Two dredgers were procured in 1972 while five in 1975 to maintain navigability of the rivers.
In addition, two out-of-order dredgers were repaired at a cost of Taka 34 crore, she said, adding that since then BIWTC has been playing an important role in inland water transport through its ferry, passenger and cargo services.
Sheikh Hasina said her government after assuming power in 1996 has increased BIWTC's operational and infrastructural facilities many times. Seven dumb barges, two tankers and six K- type ferries were rehabilitated. The K-type ferries are still delivering satisfactory services in ferrying transports at Aricha, she said.
Sheikh Hasina said her government in 2001 introduced ferry service on Chandpur-Shariatpur route. Sea-truck services were introduced in the coastal areas and islands apart from tourist service from Teknaf to Saint Martin and from Mongla to Hiron Point, she added.
The Prime Minister said her government has constructed 30 water vessels since 2009 including six water buses, four sea- trucks, two ghat pontoons and two inland passenger carrying water transports.
Nineteen more vessels including four container carrying ships, six water buses, eight ferries, and one pontoon remained under construction, she said.
Sheikh Hasina said her government had attached special importance to overall development of the shipping sector in the last five years. A master plan of Taka 12,000 crore was undertaken for the dredging of 53 rivers, she added.
Massive programmes were taken to check illegal encroachment on river banks and pollution as well as for maintaining their navigability, increasing water storage capacity and overall development of the shipping sector.
She said the government has taken a step to construct a deep seaport at Sonadia to facilitate neighboring countries to use our ports. She also highlighted her government's initiative to save the Buriganga river from pollution saying in this regard the government has taken a project for diverting the Jamuna water to Buriganga through Sitahlakkhya.
Shahjahan Khan said the BIWTC is constructing two specialized ferry-cum- passenger vessels for river communication between Barisal and Chittagong.
During her journey from Sadarghat to Chandpur, the Prime Minister saw herself pollution, eviction of land grabbers and dredging of Buriganga and Shitalakkhya and Meghna rivers.
She wanted to know from concerned ministers and parliament members about the execution of the government decisions taken for saving the rivers particularly Buriganga from pollution and illegal encroachment.
She also asked them about the actions taken for closing the source of pollution of the rivers.
]]></text></news-item>