<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5756-7D22-1050-BBFF"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Auburn tragedy recalled; 100 years ago, mill supt. slain</title><source>Telegram &amp; Gazette (Massachusetts)</source><author>Ellie Oleson, CORRESPONDENT</author><text><![CDATA[AUBURN — It has been 100 years since Pondville Woolen Mills Superintendent Erhardt Reithel was gunned down while saving the life of an employee in what newspapers of the time called "the worst tragedy that ever occurred in the peaceful little village of Auburn."
The shooting and resulting court case set a precedent still cited in some cases involving the state's Workmen's Compensation Act.
Edward D. Stuczko, who lives in the house at 11 Reithel St., and others on the street that was named in Mr. Reithel's honor soon after his murder, think he should be remembered on this anniversary year.
Mr. Stuczko said, "When we moved into his house 30 years ago, it was in sad shape after several owners. There were 21 broken windows, but we have restored it. Reithel Street used to be the Reithel family's driveway off Oxford Street. He should be remembered. Mr. Reithel was a hero."
According to numerous Worcester Telegram accounts of the day, Mr. Reithel died two days after being shot between the eyes at point-blank range by Thomas H. Bombard, 32, of Leicester on July 9, 1914 at the Pondville Woolen Company on Mill Street in Auburn.
Erhardt Martin Reithel was born in Bavaria, Germany, on Feb. 15, 1874, to John and Anna Ruktassel. Young Erhardt came to America, where he apparently had his name Americanized by an immigration official. He was 8 years old when he traveled on the ship Donau from Bremen, Germany, with relatives Cathine, 16, and Elisah Reithel, 34, arriving in New York on Sept. 15, 1882.
At the age of 20, he married Margaretha Shopf, also 20, in Auburn on April 16, 1894. A daughter born later that year did not survive long. The couple had three surviving children: Alma, Anna and Lillian.
In 1908, town records listed Mr. Reithel as a weaver. On Feb. 26, 1912, he was admitted to the Oxford Lodge of Masons, and by then he listed his occupation as "assistant superintendent."
His death certificate states that he was 40 years old when he died in Worcester City Hospital of "Bullet around of (sic) brain — Homicide," according to then-Worcester medical examiner F. H. Baker.
Mr. Bombard's original target was Exilda King, a married mother of three who had been deserted by her husband about five years earlier. Unable to support her family, she had placed her children in St. Ann's Orphanage in Worcester and gone to work at the mill, where she met Mr. Bombard. He was fired from the mill and hired at the Leicester Woolen Mill, then at Ashworth's Mill in Cherry Valley. When he tried to return to the Pondville Mill, Mr. Reithel declined to hire him.
Mr. Bombard continued to see Mrs. King and to help support her and her children, but he also became abusive.
Mrs. King contacted lawyer John F. Jandron, who wrote Mr. Bombard a letter in early July, 1914, warning him to stay away or "I will be compelled to bring the affair before the court."
This apparently enraged Mr. Bombard, who later told police he had come to Auburn three times with a gun to try to kill his former girlfriend.
When he barged into the Pondville Mill that hot summer day, Mrs. King was running a pair of looms. Employees nearby said they heard yelling before Mr. Bombard pulled out a .32-caliber revolver he had borrowed from a co-worker, John Butterfield.
Mr. Bombard told Mrs. King she had five minutes to pray before he would shoot her.
Alma Reithel, 18, the superintendent's daughter, who was working in a nearby office, heard the commotion and ran for her father. When Mr. Reithel bravely approached the armed gunman and told him to leave, Mr. Bombard shot Mr. Reithel in the head, then shot Alma in the hand and collarbone as she screamed and raced to her father's side.
Then Mr. Bombard turned back to Mrs. King and shot her in the face before fleeing.
Employees dropped out of windows and ran for exits from the three-story mill as word spread of the shooting over the noise of the looms.
Mr. Bombard paused in the mill yard to toss out his spent rounds, reload and light a cigarette before striding away, crossing the railroad tracks and walking through Hillside Cemetery toward the home of his 65-year-old mother, Philinda Bombard, in Leicester, with plans to say goodbye, then escape on a passing freight train.
Meanwhile, mill officials called for Dr. Albert G. Hurd of Millbury for help. The doctor drove himself to the mill and called Worcester police. Auburn had no police, fire or ambulance service at the time.
A half hour after the shooting, the police and ambulance finally arrived and took all three victims to City Hospital in Worcester. Mr. Reithel died two days later. Mrs. King was left scarred, but survived a single bullet that glanced off her left temple and came out by her left ear.
Alma Reithel was shot through the right hand and shoulder and was able to attend her father's funeral.
The shooting was followed by a massive manhunt, with selectmen, local constables, state police, Worcester police and others searching for the gunman. He was disarmed and arrested that night after a brief struggle wth Worcester Patrolmen Edwin Butcher and James F. Swan.
Mr. Bombard was kept in the Summer Street Jail in Worcester until he was convicted on Oct. 5 of second degree murder and sentenced to state prison for life.
Mr. Reithel's funeral, on July 14, 1914, at the First Congregational Church in Auburn, was reported by the Telegram to be the largest ever seen to that time in town.
Fellow Americans of German heritage in the Deutscher Orden der Harguari from Boston to Lawrence marched in the funeral procession, as did Masonic Lodge members, family and hundreds of friends and neighbors. Mr. Reithel was buried in Hillside Cemetery.
Mrs. Reithel went on to have a major impact on state law after the Employers Liability Assurance Corp, declined her request for compensation for her husband's death at work under the state's Workmen's Compensation Act. On appeal, the state Supreme Judicial Court overruled that decision, and she was awarded compensation on Nov. 23, 1915. That decision is still cited in court cases.
Mrs. Reithel died in 1932 and is buried next to her husband and baby Rosie in Hillside Cemetery.
All three of the Reithels' surviving daughters married and raised families. Alma was married twice, first to Christopher Cotto, then to Willis H. Kemp on Jan. 5, 1924.
Their son, Willis Kemp Jr., and his wife, Shirley, had a daughter, Melinda Kemp, who works in Auburn Town Hall, and a son, Paul Kemp, owner of Everlift Industrial Truck of Leicester. His daughter, Audrey Burnett, is a professor at James Madison University in Virginia. Alma's other grandchildren include Kurt Cotto, owner of KDC Landscape Repair in Charlton and Philip Cotto of Auburn.
Ms. Kemp said she never knew her grandmother Alma, who died before Ms. Kemp was born, but she is proud of her heritage.
"I vaguely remember hearing my grandmother had been shot, but had no idea about all this," she said, adding that it was odd to think that if Mr. Bombard had been a better shot, her grandmother also could have died, and none of Ms. Kemp's immediate family would exist.
]]></text></news-item>