<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5769-E6AB-EF9B-FB5A"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>5 Questions with Randall Snapp of Crowe &amp; Dunlevy Tulsa</title><source>Tulsa World (Oklahoma)</source><author>ROD WALTON World Staff Writer</author><text><![CDATA[1: Several states have legalized marijuana use, and others are looking at that. What impact could this have on how corporations handle drug-testing for employees?
Employers can still enforce substance abuse and valid, written drug-testing policies on pot-smoking workers who legally get high in Colorado, or any other state that legalizes marijuana, and return home to a state in which marijuana use remains illegal. Marijuana possession and use remains illegal under the federal Controlled Substances Act and Oklahoma state law. Colorado's passage of Amendment 64 allowing recreational use of marijuana will not keep Oklahoma employers from enforcing their substance abuse policies and valid, written drug-testing policies.
Employers should consider updating their drug-testing policies to make clear to employees that they are still subject to disciplinary action even if the drugs found in their system were purchased and consumed legally elsewhere, as long as the drug in question remains illegal in Oklahoma.
2: A recent study by Workplace Options indicated that office romance was on the rise among millennials, those born beginning in the early 1980s. What kind of challenge would this trend present to company human resource departments?
Workplace romances can pose many challenges to a company's human resource department, including claims of harassment, discrimination and retaliation. Employers should implement and enforce policies that are designed to identify and immediately resolve any issues that arise from a work relationship. If no policies are in place, employees are left to their own devices.
Perhaps most important, a sexual harassment policy should be developed that both defines the kind of verbal and nonverbal conduct that constitutes sexual harassment and informs employees how to report this kind of behavior. The policy should also assure employees of nonretaliation for making a harassment complaint.
3: The state Legislature is considering a bill to ban employers from accessing the Facebook and other social media of applicants. But once you're working there, it's really hard to turn down your boss' Facebook friend request. So what's the real connection between our jobs and our social media?
Employers do not currently have the right to ban employees from using social media altogether. In fact, employees have the right to participate in social media and in some situations may comment on their workplace in a way that is protected speech. However, employers have the right to make sure employees participating in social media do not disclose the employer's confidential information, are not discriminatory or derogatory, do not commit threats of violence, do not commit defamation, and do not post illegal content.
The best practice for employers is to develop formal written policies for electronic communication for employees to follow during both business and non-business hours. Such policies should also dictate whether the employer will access information on potential or current employees. Policies should inform employees that social media is not private and that misuse may result in disciplinary action.
4: Crowe & Dunlevy's Tulsa office is turning 25 this year. How have labor and employment issues most changed in the past quarter-century?
When I first started practicing employment law 25 years ago, we spent most of our time defending discrimination lawsuits. With the statutory expansion of employment law remedies and protection, such as the amendments to the anti-discrimination laws and the passage of the Americans with Disabilities Act and the Family and Medical Leave Act, there are more potential issues facing employers. In addition to defending lawsuits, we now spend more time on preventing violations of the law and resulting lawsuits. We develop effective policies and procedures, conduct employment-law training and employment audits for employers, speak at seminars and meetings for human resources organizations, and respond to questions and resolve issues raised directly by our clients.
5: Tell me something about your personal interests, hobbies, passions, etc.
When I'm not working, I spend time with my family, including the numerous activities of my four children, my faith, my friends, various civic and charitable activities and all things related to the Kansas Jayhawks. I also enjoy spending time outside, whether in my garden, at Grand Lake or anywhere else.
Randall J. Snapp joined Crowe & Dunlevy's Tulsa office in 1993 and serves as a director and the co-chairman of the firm's Labor & Employment Practice Group. He has focused his practice extensively in employment law, workers compensation law and commercial litigation since 1987 and restricts his employment law practice to representation of management and employers.
]]></text></news-item>