<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5789-F2FB-196E-7728"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>United States, et al., v. US Airways Group, Inc., et al.; Public Comments and Response on Proposed Final Judgment</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Office of the Federal Register has issued the following notice:

Table of Contents Back to Top
UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT FOR THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA RESPONSE OF PLAINTIFF UNITED STATES TO PUBLIC COMMENTS ON THE PROPOSED FINAL JUDGMENT INTRODUCTION I. Procedural History II. The Complaint and the Proposed Settlement A. The Complaint B. The Proposed Final Judgment 1. Terms of the Proposed Final Judgment and Status of the Divestitures 2. Explanation of the Proposed Final Judgment a. Consumer Benefits from LCC Entry b. The Importance of the Remedy Assets to Enhancing LCC Competition III. Standard of Judicial Review IV. Public Comments and the United States' Response A. Any Challenge to the Merits of the Complaint Is Beyond the Scope of Tunney Act Review B. The Proposed Settlement Will Counteract Competitive Harm From the Merger by Enhancing LCC Competition 1. LCCs Provide Meaningful Competition 2. The Remedy Adequately Addresses the Harms Alleged in the Complaint C. The Remedy Does Not Mandate Changes in Service Patterns at Reagan National 1. Background on Slot Regulation at Reagan National 2. Nothing in the Remedy Requires New American to Discontinue Service to Particular Airports 3. Mandating Service on Any Particular Route Is Unwarranted D. Delta Is Not an Appropriate Divestiture Candidate E. Additional Concerns Raised by Commenters 1. Airline Consumer Disclosure and Alliance Issues Are Outside the Scope of This Action 2. The Proposed Final Judgment Precludes New American from Reacquiring the Divested Gates at LAX; No Modification of the Decree Is Necessary 3. The CIS Fully Complies with Tunney Act Requirements
4. The Remedy Is Not the Result of Political Pressure 5. Closing of the Merger Prior to Entry of the Final Judgment Is Consistent with Tunney Act Requirements CONCLUSION Footnotes
Tables Back to Top
Table of Contents
Pursuant to the Antitrust Procedures and Penalties Act, 15 U.S.C. 16(b)-(h), the United States hereby publishes below the Response of the United States to Public Comments on the proposed Final Judgment in United States, et al., v. US Airways Group, Inc., et al., Civil Action No. 1:13-CV-1236-CKK (D.D.C. 2013).
Copies of the 14 Public Comments and the Response of the United States to Public Comments are available for inspection at the Department of Justice Antitrust Division, 450 Fifth Street NW., Suite 1010, Washington, DC 20530 (telephone: 202-514-2481); on the Department of Justice's Web site at http://www.justice.gov/atr/cases/usairways/index.html; and at the Office of the Clerk of the United States District Court for the District of Columbia, 333 Constitution Avenue NW., Washington, DC 20001. Copies of any of these materials may also be obtained upon request and payment of a copying fee.
Patricia A. Brink,
Director of Civil Enforcement.
For more information please visit: https://www.federalregister.gov/
]]></text></news-item>