<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="57RP-5811-J9XT-N1BP"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>2ND LEAD: New allegations but Qatar says it adhered to WCup bid rules</title><source>dpa-AFX International ProFeed</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Eds: adds FIFA reax in sixth para London (dpa-AFX) - World Cup organizers in Qatar say they did not violate bid regulations amid new corruption allegations around their successful bid for the 2022 tournament. British paper Daily Telegraph reported on Tuesday that a former vice-president of the ruling body FIFA, Jack Warner, appears to have received 1.2 million dollars from a company owned by former FIFA executive committee member Mohamed Bin Hammam of Qatar in 2011. The report said Warner requested the payment in December 2010 through one of his companies, 'for work carried out between 2005 and 2010', two weeks after Qatar were elected 2022 hosts by the FIFA executive committee. An additional 1 million dollars were allegedly paid to two of Warner's sons and an employee, the report said.
The Daily Telegraph said the FBI were understood to be investigating as well because the money was transferred via a bank in New York, after a bank in the Cayman Islands did not want to process it over legal concerns. Warner and his family reportedly declined to comment on the accusations, and so did FIFA, saying only that any kind of evidence can be passed on to its ethics committee. Qatar World Cup organizers said in the report they are 'unaware of any allegations surrounding business dealings between private individuals' and insisted that 'the 2022 bid committee strictly adhered to FIFA's bidding regulations in compliance with their code of ethics.' Warner resigned from all his football jobs in 2011 over allegations that he bribed Caribbean football officials on behalf of Bin Hammam when the Qatari was running for the FIFA presidency against Joseph Blatter. Bin Hammam stepped down as presidential candidate shortly before the 2011 vote and was later banned for life by FIFA. But the ban was lifted by the Court of Arbitration for Sport which said the case was not fully proven. The Qatar World Cup has been plagued by corruption allegations and accusations of workers' rights violations. In addition it is expected to be moved away from its original June/July 2022 slot to a date with cooler temperatures. Copyright dpa
]]></text></news-item>