<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5801-MKW1-DXCW-D2BR"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Corruption charges: Director suspended over alleged embezzlement of Rs70 million</title><source>Daily The Pak Banker</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Sindh Education Foundation’s (SEF) finance and planning director, Shukri Rehman, has been suspended from office on Tuesday following allegations of fund embezzlement.
The semi-autonomous organisation that claims to improve access to educational facilities came under fire for an alleged Rs70 million embezzlement of taxpayers’ money.
According to education department officials, the fraud surfaced as learning material worth Rs50,000, which the foundation is responsible of procuring and distributing to each of its 1,500 partner schools during the academic year 2012-13, was found to be worth less than Rs2,000.
The learning materials – including books, stationery, wall charts, satchels and uniforms – were meant for the students at each of SEF’s partner schools in the Integrated Learning Education Programme (IELP).
The programme was launched in 2009 in collaboration with the education department and is funded by the provincial government.
Investigations begin
Sindh education minister Nisar Ahmed Khuhro has formed a two-member committee, including education department’s additional chief secretary Dr Fazlullah Pechuho and SEF managing director Nazeer Hussain Jamali, to probe the corruption charges.
“I will not let these officials supply themselves with booty from the taxpayers’ money and government funds,” promised Khuhro.
“This isn’t a one-man operation,” said Jamali, while talking to Daily The Pak Banker. “We have suspended the key person in the affair, but one man cannot embezzle funds on such a large scale.”
Jamali, who is also a special secretary for the provincial education department, explained that the corruption became known when partner schools registered complaints with the department about SEF-distributed learning material.
“A carton-full of learning material, which was meant for the schools, had to include 50 to 60 goods, but many of the items were missing,” said Jamali. “Interestingly, the contractor who was responsible for the procurement of materials has been the same for a while. This means that the embezzlement was a collaborative effort.”
Meanwhile, a senior official at the foundation, who refused to comment as he was likely to be a part of the inquiry, told Daily The Pak Banker that Rehman may not be directly involved in the corruption. However, he was suspended in order to ensure that he doesn’t influence investigations.
]]></text></news-item>