<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="581F-995E-31D4-F9FA"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Public sector pain is the price of tax cuts for everyone</title><source>Express Online</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[PUBLIC sector employers will no doubt be deeply upset that it has fallen on them to fill the £1billion funding black hole in their occupational pension schemes.
However, this is undoubtedly the right course of action.
Dealing with the problem in this way has created the potential for an extra £1billion of tax cuts in the forthcoming Budget. The complaints from those forced to stump up are understandable but the bigger picture is unquestionably positive with everybody in Britain set to benefit when the Budget is announced next week.
A fall in taxes - however Mr Osborne chooses to implement it - will be a great boon to the British economy. An increase in people's spending power will drive more custom for businesses and a greater reward for work will encourage more people to get off their sofas and into employment.
What all this means is that the pain felt by public sector departments is a necessary evil. It will be worth it.
........................................................................
Council house madness
Endless calling on human rights continues to leave rational  Britons wondering if common sense has completely deserted these isles. The latest example is a man who has had 18 children with 10 different women and now claims it is a breach of his human rights to be forced to live in a three-bedroom council house.
Peter Rolfe has not worked for more than 20 years but still believes he has the right to be upgraded to a six-bedroom house to accommodate the massive family.
That is, of course, a house that will be paid for entirely with our taxes. His sense of entitlement is a damning indication of the effects of our benefits culture in which getting something for nothing has become the norm.
It now appears likely that Rolfe will get his wish. This is a terrible shame and an awful message to send to others looking to use the system for their own material gain.
........................................................................
A man of commitment
This newspaper has little in common with the political views espoused by Tony Benn but his passing is to be lamented. Today's politicians have much to learn from his example.
His commitment to the causes he held dear, selfless pursuit of his ideals and the power of his heartfelt rhetoric are all sadly lacking in too many of the key figures in politics.
This country's political landscape is undoubtedly a drabber place without him.
]]></text></news-item>