<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="597D-AC48-CCA0-E63D"><date>2014-03-17</date><title></title><source>South China Morning Post</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Officials must help resolve lease problem
I am a parent of a student at the International Montessori School and am now not sure what will happen for the next school term, because the lease arrangement for the Tin Hau campus remains unresolved.
I must now look at the possibility of having to find a new school for him at short notice that does not meet all the requirements of the Montessori school.
It will not match Montessori for location, facilities, quality of teachers and ancillary staff, and, of course, the friends he has made. He has been going there since pre-school.
The time and money we have invested in his education is now in jeopardy, and the government and Education Bureau refuse to get involved.
I have lived here for 20 years and am very upset by the leaders of this city that I and my family call home.
I have always promoted Hong Kong as one of the best places to live, but now there is serious doubt about the government and whether it sees education as a priority.
I was told that some bureau official has said it cannot get involved because of a conflict of interest as a special committee was to be set up to do a study on Hong Kong's education system. I do not see how there could be any conflict of interest as the bureau deals with education issues and that is what this is.
Also, it was the government that suggested the Tin Hau campus in the first place for Montessori when it was forced to move from its previous location.
If discussions with the landlord, the Construction Association, fail to resolve the lease issue, then the government should step in.
Education officials have a duty to help International Montessori School stay at its Tin Hau campus.
David G. McIntyre, Pok Fu Lam
MTR's maps and messages are sufficient
The MTR is a topical subject in these columns.
Let's be clear, it is one of the best transport services in the world - efficient, clean, cheap and safe.
However, MTR travellers are plagued with incessant, pointless and very irritating announcements in two or three languages, none of which serves any useful purpose. The station maps and on-train illuminated maps/messages are more than adequate.
Most of us would like to enjoy a peaceful, stress-free journey. This is completely impossible with this cacophony of unnecessary announcements.
Please take a leaf out of the wonderful silence you find at Hong Kong International Airport.
Unfortunately, the MTR Corporation has fallen for the Hong Kong obsession with pointless announcements and signage.
It should take the opportunity to change this absurd culture.
Philip Nourse, Discovery Bay
Ban all bulky items during rush hour
I totally agree with Doug Miller ("Bicycles on MTR trains unacceptable", March 3).
The carriages of MTR trains are for passengers, not bicycles.
All Hong Kong citizens are entitled to use the network, but it is a selfish act to bring something as bulky as a bicycle onto an MTR train.
So many people depend on this mass-transit system to take them to and from work every day. During rush hours these coaches are already full.
Having bicycles as well would only make things worse for passengers.
In fact the MTR Corporation should not allow passengers with any large items to board during these rush hours.
People need to show consideration for the feelings of their fellow passengers.
Andy Chan Chi-wa, Tseung Kwan O
Live poultry ban will lead to job losses
Sales of local live poultry resumed last month after a three-week ban was imposed at the end of January.
However, many people are calling for a permanent ban to prevent the spread of bird flu. I am strongly opposed to this suggestion.
I see the bird flu cases so far as isolated incidents. I do not think the recent cases justify stopping people from enjoying eating fresh chicken.
Such a policy would create more problems than it would solve.
A lot of Hongkongers depend on this trade, such as wet market stallholders and wholesalers.
If a ban was put in force these people could lose their livelihoods.
The government would then face a higher unemployment rate and claims for compensation for those who were affected.
I also do not think it is fair to single out poultry.
You can fall ill from eating pigs or cattle which have infections. If we imposed a ban on live poultry where would we stop and what would the next ban apply to?
It will give Hong Kong people a false sense of security and their level of awareness will be lowered. And there will remain a risk of flu from wild migratory birds.
Instead of introducing a blanket ban, the government should think about some more sensible and reasonable ways to prevent bird flu. For example, there should be tighter checks at the border when imports of poultry from the mainland are resumed.
Linus Wong, Fanling
Invest more in research and development
Hong Kong has developed into one of the most highly developed cities in the world.
In this new century the quality of most people's lives has improved.
But while it is an important international financial centre and has a strong Western influence because of its colonial past, it is not as highly-developed or modern as many people think.
In many areas it is still lagging behind cities in South Korea and Singapore when it comes to technology.
Embracing technological advances is important for any city in this day and age if it wants to continue to move forward and remain competitive.
Hong Kong still lacks maturity when it comes to research and development projects into new technology.
Therefore, the government must allocate more resources for R&D projects.
If it does this it has a better chance of attracting more talented people to come to Hong Kong to live and work.
This is necessary if Hong Kong is to keep abreast with all the latest innovations.
Cyrus Ng Kai-cheung, Kwai Chung
Government turning blind eye to abuse
Burning with irons, beatings and deprivation of food and sleep may appear to be a list of the brutality seen in the Oscar-winning film 12 Years a Slave, but it isn't. It is, according to Simon Parry's well-researched article ("A world of pain", March 2), some of the brutal punishment meted out these days to foreign domestic workers by their employers in Asia's leading world city, Hong Kong.
It is a shocking indictment that there is insufficient support for this particular group of law-abiding citizens when they speak out against employer abuse and unscrupulous employment agencies. The government is turning a blind eye to the modern-day slavery that exists in our midst.
It is not enough for Matthew Cheung Kin-Chung, secretary for labour and welfare, to say that a hotline is available to all workers and that foreign domestic helpers are accorded legal protection equal to local workers; 8,000 complaints against local employment agencies resulted in four being punished.
These figures speak volumes. Moreover, the procedure and time frame of the complaints' system against abusive employers is designed to deter victims from making a complaint.
Hong Kong needs a modern-day William Wilberforce. Is there such a person in the government?
M. James, Sai Kung
Chief executive trying to fight poverty
A large section of society is opposed to Chief Executive Leung Chun-ying and wants him to quit.
Maybe he has done things which have resulted in public anger. However, if you look at parts of his last policy address it is clear he wants to tackle the root causes of poverty.
This is far better than measures taken by his predecessors, such as the HK$6,000 handout to permanent residents which did little to alleviate the plight of the poor. Despite the measures he unveiled in his speech there were still people criticising his policy address.
Hong Kong is a society with a lot of problems that need to be solved.
We read about abusive employers of foreign domestic helpers and helicopter parents who create overdependent children. And there are debates about Hong Kong's core values.
Also, we have to deal with environmental problems such as landfills nearing capacity and controversial proposals to build an incinerator.
When C. Y. Leung comes up with proposals to deal with some of these problems opponents keep saying he is wrong.
I think there is a need for thorough reflection and for citizens to show some respect for our leader.
Wah Chi-shing, Hung Hom
]]></text></news-item>