<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5985-9311-BD8A-C5A2"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Graft-busters sent to more provinces; Science ministry, university in Shanghai and massive state-owned conglomerate also targeted</title><source>South China Morning Post</source><author>He Huifeng huifeng.he@scmp.com</author><text><![CDATA[Sudden anti-corruption inspections would be a "Sword of Damocles" to deter suspect officials, the mainland's anti-graft chief said yesterday.
Wang Qishan , secretary of the Central Commission for Discipline Inspection (CCDI), made the comments while announcing a new round of inspections to be carried out at 11 provincial-level governments, two institutes and a massive state-owned enterprise.
It would be third round of sweeps since May. Inspectors will go to Beijing, Tianjin , Liaoning , Fujian , Shandong , Henan , Hainan , Gansu , Ningxia and Xinjiang , and the Xinjiang Production and Construction Corps, a semi-military government development organisation in the remote far western region.
Special "investigation projects" would be conducted at the Ministry of Science and Technology, Shanghai-based Fudan University and state-owned China National Cereals, Oils and Foodstuffs Corporation.
Speaking at a meeting on Saturday on the deployment of disciplinary inspectors this year, Wang said his inspectors could be more effective if they focused on individual departments or enterprises, Cnr.cn reported.
"We can send a team to any unit if we believe an individual official may be involved in corruption," Wang said. "We must be mobile and flexible, making it hard for suspected officials [to anticipate our movements]. If we arrive suddenly, it will be a good deterrent.
"Such innovative disciplinary inspection would be 'the Sword of Damocles' hanging over corrupt officials' heads."
Wang asked inspectors to work with a "sober mind" as the situation in the anti-corruption fight remained "grave and complicated". He also warned that inspectors who turned a blind eye to violations would be held accountable.
Last year, discipline inspectors conducted 155,000 investigations based on tip-offs from the public, resulting in more than 160,000 officials in government and state enterprises being prosecuted, Wang said.
Last year, CCDI handed state prosecutors the cases of 2,871 public servants at the county-level and above - including 253 at the city-level and eight at provincial and ministerial-level - in almost 2,600 cases of graft, bribery, and embezzlement of public funds
]]></text></news-item>