<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="59C5-595E-58F9-9AA0"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>View from the Left: Energy; Carbon levies can reduce emissions</title><source>Norwich Bulletin (Connecticut)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[If indirect costs, such as environmental degradation, medical costs and adverse health effects, were factored into gasoline sales, pump prices would well exceed $25 per gallon.
Instead, "carbon capitalism" is an economy of unpaid bills. Negative impacts are unaccounted in entrepreneurial outlays, but instead socialized, shifted to and ultimately borne by us and ecological communities at large. Despite such detriment, we never share trillions of dollars in annual carbon-industry profits. They're privatized, going largely to the 1 percent.
As a congressional candidate in 2008 and 2010, I proposed carbon levies to curb greenhouse gas emissions and force carbon industries to put skin in the game other than just our own.
Lower taxes
During debates, I exposed cap and trade as an unenforceable shell game beyond the UN's regulatory oversight. Revenue-neutral carbon levies reduce job and business taxes by up-taxing corporate resource depletion and environmental harm. British Columbia's carbon levies give tax credits to citizens to offset income taxes. For years, Green Party platforms have included carbon levies to offset regressive sales or income taxes and fund public transportation and alternative energy.
Corporations failing to control pollution are corporations out of control. It's trivial and cheap for oil, natural gas and coal extractors to leverage money to elect Democrats and Republicans doing nothing about carbon pollution but offering shams and slipping dominion pretexts into euphemisms like stewardship. Truth and logic become menaces to officials approving "fracking" wastes to melt highway ice the way carcinogenic PCBs were spread on roads to suppress dust before the Toxic Substances Control Act.
Transport danger
Every oil train carrying three million gallons of crude is a terrestrial Exxon Valdez. Few are double-walled and rupture when derailed. Freight trains hauling oil across North America have caused more than a dozen major spills in just six years, the deadliest killing 47 in Lac Megantic, Quebec. To put the danger in perspective, one gallon of crude can make one million gallons of water undrinkable.
A quarter century regulating chemical storage taught me all piping eventually fails. The proposed Keystone XL would join 2,900 miles of pipeline transporting 830,000 barrels of crude from Alberta's tar sands to Gulf Coast refineries ─ every day ─ creating only 50 permanent jobs after construction.
Author Bill McKibben calls Keystone XL the "fuse to the largest carbon bomb on the planet" which, if fully developed, will warm the planet another 3.6 degrees Fahrenheit by 2100.
The climatologic ruse of using tar sands to replace coal is like replacing a cobra with a mamba. Both bites should be avoided.
Scott Deshefy is a Green Party member and two-time congressional candidate. E-mail him at baronarad11@yahoo.com
]]></text></news-item>