<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="59V8-P9K1-DXCW-D083"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Community Bank President - Rochester</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Iowa Association of Business and Industry has issued the following Job Vacancy.
Community Bank President - Rochester Wage Location = ROCHESTER, MN 55901Title: Community Bank President - RochesterLocation: Minnesota-RochesterOther Locations:DescriptionThe employment policy of Associated Banc-Corp, and its subsidiaries and affiliates (¿Associated¿) provides equal opportunity to all persons. We support a diverse and inclusive work environment where colleagues are respected, treated fairly, and given equal opportunities to perform to their fullest potential. We believe it is only with a diverse and inclusive workplace that the organization can truly perform at its best, carry out its vision, and make a difference for the communities we serve.
JOB SUMMARYUnder functional guidance, responsible for providing leadership, direction, and guidance of the Banking Offices to ensure the short and long-term profitability of the banking offices; equitable treatment and development of staff; and the maintenance of bank-community citizenship.
Operates in full compliance with internal policies and procedures as well as applicable regulations and laws, including but not limited to Bank Secrecy Act/Anti-Money Laundering requirements. Responsible to report any procedure or process that doesn¿t meet regulatory requirements including fraud, whether suspected or confirmed, to management. This reporting can be done directly to any member of management, including Human Resources or Corporate Security, or can be reported through Associated¿s anonymous Ethics Hotline.
KEY RESULT AREAS
JOB ACCOUNTABILITIES
¿ Develop and implement bank strategies and objectives for the Offices consistent with and in support of the Associated Bank Green Bay goals and objectives for growth, net income, and the financial performance of these offices.
¿ Manage the activities of Business and Retail Banking functions and support areas including marketing, personnel, and operations.¿ Establish and create a business development process to maintain current customer base and expand market share to include fee based products like brokerage/trust referral, etc.¿ Represent the bank and provide leadership in key community activities including business, charitable, civic and social organizations in support of a responsible citizen stature for the bank.¿ Provide leadership to and involve the Board of Directors in business development and community affairs to develop new business relationships and enhance the Bank's community presence.¿ Manage personnel activities which include hiring, training, salary administration, personnel reviews, and banking office objectives and performance, to insure solid team efforts toward attainment of Bank's goals.
OTHER DUTIES AND RESPONSIBILITIES
¿ Direct and indirect resources managed may vary based on market size.
QUALIFICATIONS:Required Education: Bachelor's DegreePreferred Education: Master's DegreeRequired Experience: 7-10 years Customer service experience and financial sales, 5 years consumer and mortgage lending, 3 years supervisory experience, 2 - 4 years trust and bank investment experience, business developmentPreferred Experience: 10-12 years 10 years or more of varied community bank management experienceSpecial Skill Requirements:Budgetary & Fiscal MgmtVerbal CommunicationWritten CommunicationManagement ExperienceCustomer RelationsOther: Business DevelopmentOrganizationalAnalyticalMathematical
Other Duties and ResponsibilitiesPerforms other duties as assigned.
Job RequirementsAdherence to Company policy and procedures is required.Perform duties in accordance with the Vision & Values of Associated Banc-Corp.Regular attendance is required.Basic math and reading skills, and attention to detail.Use of basic office equipment (e.g., photocopier, voice mail, "fax" machine, calculator, multiple line telephones, typewriter, computers etc.).Represent the organization in a professional and positive manner.Maintain credit exception approval percentages within corporate approved guidelinesBanking ManagementExperience Education Skills Shift Availability Days Off Openings 1 Work Schedule Lifting Capacity Driver License None Endorsements Job Benefits Commission No
For further information please visit: https://www1.iowajobs.org/
]]></text></news-item>