<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5A65-460B-E5F5-F17B"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>UKRAINIAN TYCOON ARRESTED</title><source>Pittsburgh Post-Gazette</source><author>Compiled from news services</author><text><![CDATA[MOSCOW -- A Ukrainian oligarch with deep and lucrative ties to Russia's state-owned energy monopoly has been arrested in Vienna at the request of the FBI, according to Austrian press accounts, in what could be the beginning of a U.S. effort to inflict financial pain on Russia over its role in the Ukrainian crisis.
Dmytro Firtash acted as Russia's very-well-paid agent, buying natural gas cheap and selling it to Ukraine's national gas company at a steep mark-up.
Yulia Tymoshenko, the former Ukraine prime minister, accused him of kicking back a large portion of the proceeds, effectively creating an offshore slush fund for Gazprom, which is the primary pillar of the political-financial structure built by Russian President Vladimir Putin.
Egypt brokers truce
JERUSALEM -- Egypt has mediated a truce ending two days of clashes between Gaza Strip militants and Israel's military, a militant leader said Thursday. There was no immediate confirmation from Israel or Egypt.
Khaled el-Batch, a senior leader of the Islamic Jihad militant group, said in a statement that Egypt brokered a restoration of the cease-fire that ended Israel's November 2012 offensive in the Palestinian territory.
Iran's culture, media wars
TEHRAN, Iran -- A long-smoldering battle over government control of media and culture in Iran is heating up, as opposing political forces fight over where the limits should be drawn on access to information.
Iran's president, Hassan Rouhani, and his supporters argue that press restrictions should be reduced.
The debate intensified last week when Ali Jannati, the minister of culture and Islamic guidance under Mr. Rouhani, described as "ridiculous" many of the policies that Iran has adopted since the revolution of 1979 to control the flow of information.
'Trail of blood'
PRETORIA, South Africa -- Blood on the stairs, walls and furniture, a cocked 9 mm pistol, bloody towels, fallen wall tiles. Like pieces of an unfinished puzzle, the photos of the blood-splattered interior of Oscar Pistorius' home gave a fragmented picture Thursday of his girlfriend's violent end.
The 27-year-old Mr. Pistorius faces 25 years to life in prison if convicted of murder, and also faces three firearms charges. He has pleaded not guilty and says he shot the 29-year-old model, Reeva Steenkamp, by mistake, believing she was an intruder hiding in the toilet cubicle.
Congress invites pope
WASHINGTON -- Congressional leaders have invited Pope Francis to deliver a joint address to Congress, during an expected trip to the United States next year.
The Rev. Gerald Fogarty, a historian of Christianity at the University of Virginia who has written on papal visits, said he believed it was the first time a pope has been invited to Congress.
No medical aid in Myanmar
BANGKOK -- Nearly 750,000 people, most of them members of a Muslim minority in one of the poorest parts of Myanmar, have been deprived of most of their medical services since the government banned the operations of Doctors Without Borders, the international health care organization and the main provider of medical care in the region.
The government ordered a halt to the work of Doctors Without Borders two weeks ago after some officials accused the group of favoring the Muslims, members of the Rohingya ethnic group, over a rival group, Rakhine Buddhists.
]]></text></news-item>