<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BC2-80EE-1C30-17BE"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>David Cameron: Businesses are demolishing Alex Salmond's 'scaremongering' claims; The Prime Minister will use his speech at the Scottish Tory conference in Edinburgh to argue that politically impartial companies are spelling out the damaging consequences of independence.</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Simon Johnson Scottish Political Editor</author><text><![CDATA[Business leaders are demolishing Alex Salmond's claims that critics of Scottish independence are waging a campaign of political scaremongering, David Cameron will say today.
In a speech to the Scottish Tory conference in Edinburgh, the Prime Minister will cite a series of warnings about separation that have recently been made by companies such as BP, Shell and RBS.
He will argue that they and other impartial figures who have entered the independence debate, such as the Governor of the Bank of England, are not "political puppets" and do not make "empty warnings".
Mr Salmond's separatists have repeatedly accused the pro-UK Better Together campaign of scaremongering about independence, referring to it with the moniker "Project Fear".
But Mr Cameron will argue this is a "myth" that the business leaders are helping to dispel. He will deliver his speech after another of Scotland's largest companies, the engineering giant Babcock, told its shipyard staff separation threatened its business.
Trade union leaders at its Rosyth yard in Fife said the firm, which employs 5,000 people in Scotland, told them it was "unlikely" to win any more Royal Navy refit contracts and work on aircraft carriers could be carried out at Portsmouth instead.
The warning coincided with a major survey of Scottish engineering companies, which found a majority oppose independence and only a "very few" were in favour.
They were the latest in a series of major employers in Scotland who have recently gone public with their concerns about the impact of separation.
Standard Life, the Edinburgh-based financial services giant, and the Alliance Trust, the historic Dundee investment firm, have already started setting up companies in England in case there is a Yes vote.
But Mr Salmond's separatists have repeatedly accused the pro-UK Better Together campaign of scaremongering about independence, referring to it using the moniker "Project Fear".
Speaking at the Edinburgh International Conference Centre, Mr Cameron is expected to say the referendum is a "major life decision" that requires voters to get all the information they can.
"You wouldn't buy a house without getting a survey done. You wouldn't choose a car without an MOT," the Prime Minister will tell delegates.
"And you shouldn't make a decision about changing your nation - forever - without knowing in full what the consequences may be. And look at who's laying out those consequences."
Mr Cameron will cite Mark Carney, the Bank of England's Governor, who this week warned an independent Scotland would have to join the euro if it wanted EU membership and there was a "distinct possibility" RBS would move to England.
He will also name check José Manuel Barroso, the European Commission President, who has said it would be "extremely difficult, if not impossible" for a separate Scotland to join the EU.
Listing a series of major businesses that have issued warnings, including Lloyds and Barclays, the Prime Minister is expected to say: "‪These are not political puppets, they are serious, non-partisan figures.
‪"So, the idea that these are empty warnings and political scaremongering is a myth - and we owe it to the people of Scotland to take that myth apart."
Vince Cable, the Business Secretary, yesterday predicted that more large financial services firms could be forced to "decamp" from an independent Scotland as there would be no lender of last resort without a currency union.
Speaking at Glasgow University yesterday, the Liberal Democrat said: "If you are talking about the reality of risk it's very difficult to see how really major financial institutions would continue to operate here."
Babcock, which has annual revenue of around £3.2 billion, yesterday confirmed it considers independence an "additional risk and uncertainty for our business" and it has started to discuss this with staff.
The Rosyth Dockyard Industrial Joint Council, consisting of the yard's three trade unions, issued a statement outlining the problems the company had forecast.
This stated it would be unlikely that the yard would be eligible to receive contracts to refit Royal Navy warships "as existing rules restrict these to UK yards."
Babcock had also warned it was possible the UK Government could have two new aircraft carriers completed in Portsmouth instead, the statement warned.
It was "unclear" whether the Nationalists' plans to turn Faslane, the home of the UK's nuclear submarines, into a conventional naval base would compensate for the loss of Royal Naval contracts.
But the unions said the company had told them there was a "strong possibility" the yard would become the "preferred location" for refitting the aircraft carriers if Scotland remained part of the UK
In a separate intervention, Scottish Engineering, the trade body representing the sector, said it had completed a year-long consultation with its members about independence that found a majority opposed independence.
Nicola Sturgeon, the Deputy First Minister, said: "With just one MP in Scotland, the Tories have no mandate here. And yet people across Scotland are paying a huge price at the hands of a Tory-Lib Dem Government that they did not elect.
"David Cameron's increasingly ham-fisted attempts to scare the people of Scotland into voting No will fool no one."
A spokesman for Keith Brown, the SNP's Veterans Minister, said Rosyth would support an independent Scotland's naval fleet and UK military orders "could, and should, still come to Scotland."
]]></text></news-item>