<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BE3-5732-F3BB-09C5"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>WCL vigilance officer faces fraud probe</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Shishir Arya</author><text><![CDATA[NAGPUR: Coal PSUs often face flak for corruption. But in Western Coalfields Limited (WCL) the chief vigilance officer (CVO)- whose job is to keep an eye on irregularities- is himself under the scanner. The ministry of coal is examining a case against CVO S K Gupta for allegedly fudging expenses to get a leave travel concession (LTC) reimbursement.
The complaint was forwarded to the management by union leader Vidya Sagar Chaudhary, who passed away last month. Sources in the ministry handling this case say the matter is being examined. It may take longer to decide due to the complexity and volume of documents to be examined.
Gupta calls the allegations deliberate to settle scores with him. "Had the management scrutinized and made the deductions accordingly, there would have been no over-billing," he said. Gupta had held an inquiry against WCL's chairman-cum-managing director D C Garg.
The management's report put up before the ministry says Gupta claimed Rs 92,000 towards air tickets for his family of four from Nagpur to Delhi for one side. LTC rules call for using the shortest route, which according to the report could have cost Rs 23,000 per adult on the same day as against Rs 32,256 spent by the CVO. The fare for a child could have been Rs 13,500 as against Rs 27,000 claimed.
While Gupta himself was on an official tour, the kin were on vacation. According to complaint, the officer conveniently clubbed his tour with family's holiday, so his kin could get benefits at company's cost. This included a stay at The Taj Mahal Hotel to which only Gupta was entitled to. He first availed LTC for his family for travelling to Agra, his home town, via Mumbai and Delhi. Under LTA, only the travel expenses are reimbursed. Since Gutpa was on an official tour to Mumbai on the same day, he was entitled to stay in the luxury hotel where he accommodated his spouse and children too. The food expenses incurred during the period were also claimed from the company. This happened at The Taj Mahal at Delhi also, where he was on an official tour and the family on holiday, the report says.
"The rules allow taking the spouse during official tours, Gupta took his children too but did not report their stay while making claims," said a management source. "The CVO has paid back Rs 1 lakh on his own. However, it does not dilute the charges," said the source.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>