<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BFH-13B1-J9XT-P0V2"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Massachusetts: Cleanup of General Chemical Corporation Property in Framingham to Include Phased Cleanup, Public Involvement</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Department of Energy and Environmental Affairs, The State of Massachusetts has issued the following news release:
A Massachusetts Department of Environmental Protection (MassDEP) consent order has established a framework for the long-term cleanup of contaminated soil and groundwater that remains beneath the former General Chemical Corporation (GCC) chemical and hazardous waste facility located at 133-138 Leland Street in Framingham.
The property, currently owned by Trinity General Corporation (TGC), had served as the location for a solvent storage and distribution facility from 1960 to 2012, at which time GCC voluntarily closed down its operation. GCC later removed all tanks and cleaned the facility surfaces, all under MassDEP's supervision.
"The residents living nearby will continue to have a robust public involvement process available, and MassDEP will continue to vigorously oversee and regulate the response actions taken by the responsible parties so that the cleanup is done safely and thoroughly," said Eric Worrall, director of MassDEP's northeast regional office in Wilmington.
The order enshrines the existing public involvement process, which will allow residents' concerns to be heard and addressed on proposed cleanup response actions. Further, the order stipulates that an annual assessment will be done by GCC and TGC on the future cost of necessary response actions to clean up the site in order to ensure that adequate funding - through a financial assurance mechanism (FAM) - is in place to cover the cleanup.
Specifically, today's order includes:
Corrective Actions - MassDEP will review and approve all cleanup actions. The site has already been designated a public involvement plan (PIP) site, meaning that GCC and TGC are required to inform and update the community with information concerning ongoing and future cleanup activities. MassDEP will review and approve the scope of work; the identification, evaluation, selection and implementation of comprehensive remedial action alternatives, and ensure that responses to public comments that are received on the proposed remedy are addressed by the responsible parties. Also, an audit will be conducted by MassDEP of the corrective actions.
Post Closure - A groundwater and surface water monitoring plan must be prepared and submitted by GCC and TGC within 60 days; no post-closure use of the property is permitted that would damage any corrective action, treatment or remedy implemented at the site. Groundwater monitoring activities will occur at nearby drainage ditch areas, Course Brook and the Massachusetts Water Resources Authority (MWRA) Aqueduct and can be modified based on site conditions observed by MassDEP.
Financial Assurance - Each year beginning with February 1, 2015, a cost estimate will be submitted by GCC and TGC that will cover post-closure activities and any corrective actions work. The estimates must include the anticipated costs for any additional required corrective actions based on site conditions known. Today's order requires the immediate raising of the FAM from its current level of $1,549,000 to $1,851,766. GCC will also surrender the hazardous waste facility license it holds for the closed facility.
Performance Failure - In the event that MassDEP determines GCC and/or TGC is deficient in its performance, a notice detailing the failure will be issued by MassDEP, giving up to 45 days to remedy the circumstances. If MassDEP determines that a remedy has not been achieved, the Department will have immediate access to the FAM to provide for the necessary means to achieve that remedy.
MassDEP is responsible for ensuring clean air and water, safe management and recycling of solid and hazardous wastes, timely cleanup of hazardous waste sites and spills and the preservation of wetlands and coastal resources.
For further information please visit: http://www.mass.gov/eea/
]]></text></news-item>