<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BHD-9GV1-JC8V-42XD"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Alcoa World Alumina Pleads Guilty to Foreign Bribery and Will Pay $223 Million in Fines and Forfeiture</title><source>International Enforcement Law Reporter</source><author>Bruce Zagaris</author><text><![CDATA[On January 9, 2014, Alcoa World Alumina LLC, a majority-owned and controlled global alumina sales company of Alcoa Inc., plead guilty and agreed to pay $223 million in criminal fines and forfeiture to resolve charges that it paid millions of dollars in bribes through an international middleman in London to officials of the Kingdom of Bahrain, in violation of the Foreign Corrupt Practices Act (FCPA). n1
n1 U.S. Department of Justice, Alcoa World Alumina Agrees to Plead Guilty to Foreign Bribery and Pay $223 Million in Fines and Forfeiture, Press Release, Jan. 9, 2014.
Alcoa World Alumina plead guilty in the U.S. District Court for the Western District of Pennsylvania to one count of violating the anti-bribery provisions of the FCPA in connection with a 2004 corrupt transaction, to pay a criminal fine of ยง209 million, and to administratively forfeit $14 million. As part of the plea agreement, Alcoa Inc. (Alcoa) has agreed to maintain and implement an enhanced global anti-corruption compliance program.
In a parallel action, Alcoa settled with the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) and will pay an additional $161 million in disgorgement, bringing the total amount of U.S. criminal and regulatory penalties to be paid by Aloca and Alcoa World Alumina to $384 million.
The court filings allege that Alcoa of Australia, another Alcoa-controlled entity, originally secured a long-term alumina supply agreement with Aluminum Bahrain B.S.C. (Alba), an aluminum smelter controlled by the Bahrain government. At the request of certain members of Bahrain's Royal Family, who controlled the tender process, Alcoa of Australia inserted a London-based middleman with close ties to certain Royal Family members as a sham sales agent and agreed to pay him a corrupt commission intended to conceal bribe payments, according to court papers. Over time, Alcoa of Australia expanded the relationship with the middleman, identified as Consultant A in the court, to start invoicing increasingly larger volumes of alumina sales through his shell companies, which allowed Consultant A to make larger bribe payments to certain government officials.
In the charging documents, Alcoa World Alumina admitted that it corruptly secured a long-term alumina supply agreement with Alba by agreeing to purportedly sell over 1.5 million metric tons of alumina to Alba through offshore shell companies owned by Consultant A. The sham distributorship allowed Consultant A to mark up the price of alumina by approximately $188 million from 2005 to 2009, the duration of the corrupt supply agreement. Court filings allege that Consultant A used the mark-up to pay tens of millions in corrupt kickbacks to Bahraini government officials, including senior members of Bahrain's Royal Family. In order to hide the illicit payments, Consultant A and the government officials used various offshore bank accounts, including accounts held under aliases, at several major financial institutions around the world, including Guernsey, Luxembourg, Liechtenstein, and Switzerland.
The case illustrates some common elements in transnational bribery cases: the use of middlemen who poae as sham agents and funnel commissions intended as bribes; the use of multiple intermediary jurisdictions to pay the bribes and conceal the payments; and the use of shell companies to disguise bribe payments. The case also illustrates the fact that the extractive industries have been a common sector in which transnational bribes have been paid. The case is a sensitive one for Bahrain and its Royal Family, since there have already been major disturbances and riots over governance issues.
]]></text></news-item>