<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BM0-C8K1-J9XT-P4JX"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>New York: Former President And Chief Executive Officer Of Software Company Sentenced In Manhattan Federal Court To 63 Months In Prison For $6.3 Million Offering Fraud Scheme</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[United States Attorney's Office for the Southern District of New York has issued the following press release:
Preet Bharara, the United States Attorney for the Southern District of New York, announced that SCOT ZARKIEWICZ, the co-founder and former President, Chief Executive Officer, Treasurer, and principal owner of SingleClick Systems Corp. (“SingleClick”), a Delaware-incorporated, New Jersey-based software company, was sentenced today in Manhattan federal court to 63 months in prison for perpetrating a scheme to defraud SingleClick investors. From mid-2009 through June 2013, ZARKIEWICZ solicited several investors to purchase millions of dollars of privately-held SingleClick stock based on fraudulent misrepresentations about the company’s operations and financial performance. As a result of his fraudulent scheme, ZARKIEWICZ collected, and maintained in SingleClick, approximately $6.3 million from 35 victims. ZARKIEWICZ pled guilty in November 2013 before U.S. District Judge Denise L. Cote., who also imposed today’s sentence.
Manhattan U.S. Attorney Preet Bharara said: “With today’s sentence, Scot Zarkiewicz is being held to account for misleading investors and betraying their trust with his multimillion-dollar fraud scheme.”
According to the Information to which ZARKIEWICZ pled guilty, statements made in open court, and other court documents:
SingleClick is a privately-held software company that was engaged in the business of providing individuals and businesses with network software products that facilitate content access and network and systems management from any internet-connected device. From mid-2009 through June 2013, ZARKIEWICZ solicited investor contributions to, and caused investors to maintain their investments in, SingleClick based on fraudulent misrepresentations.
Specifically, during the relevant period, ZARKIEWICZ told SingleClick investors, in both oral and written communications, that SingleClick had several large corporate clients, millions of dollars in annual revenue, and millions of dollars in cash in bank and brokerage accounts, when, in truth and in fact, and as ZARKIEWICZ well knew, SingleClick conducted minimal business operations, collected significantly less than a million dollars in annual revenue, and did not have more than approximately $513,000 in cash on hand. ZARKIEWICZ made these misrepresentations to induce potential investors to purchase SingleClick shares, and to induce existing investors to purchase additional shares and/or refrain from requesting redemptions of their investments. ZARKIEWICZ made these misrepresentations by, among other means, distributing fabricated bank, brokerage, financial, and tax statements to investors.
In May and June 2013, investors learned that SingleClick had very little cash available and confronted ZARKIEWICZ. ZARKIEWICZ admitted to investors that he lied about SingleClick’s business performance, fabricated records, and misled investors about the number of investors in, and operation of, SingleClick. Notwithstanding representations made in preceding years by ZARKIEWICZ that SingleClick had millions of dollars in revenue – including representations that SingleClick had generated $48 million in revenue in 2012 – since mid-2009, SingleClick has actually been generating thousands of dollars in revenue, not millions, and SingleClick’s total aggregate bank account balances have not exceeded approximately $513,000. In August 2013, after admitting his fraudulent conduct, ZARKIEWICZ resigned as CEO of SingleClick.
For more information please visit: http://www.justice.gov/usao/nys
]]></text></news-item>