<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BMG-0FN1-JCB2-W3BR"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Pattern Recognition. Better than TV</title><source>Financial Mail (South Africa)</source><author>Toby Shapshak</author><text><![CDATA[: Pattern Recognition
Better than TV
Never has such an unsexy technology been such a sexy story as the debate over the new digital plumbing to deliver television gets fiery
It's rough being a monopoly in SA these days. Everywhere you look, they are under attack.
The SABC doesn't think managers who can think are important. Eskom's stranglehold on our economy continues as its flagship new power station Medupi, mired in delays and bad riveting, is held hostage by striking workers.
Vodacom and MTN have taken to full-page newspaper ads to defend their massive margins on mobile calls, prompting a rush on newspaper advertising spend not seen since the Great Banking War of 2012.
Even Cosatu's monopoly on trade unions is under threat, replaced at the traditional coal face of strikes (in the mining sector) by that dangerous, strike-first, angry upstart Amcu.
The ANC, also a monopolist of a sort, is on the back foot as it tries to explain away and defend the indefensible over Nkandla's lavish spending.
Thank god for Thuli Madonsela. She is the Desmond Tutu of this generation. A fearless crusader for something ethical and honourable in a world gone mad with corruption and greed. Tutu fought against the injustice of apartheid and Madonsela fights against the destruction wrought by the tatty, tenderpreneur remnants of the once-mighty ANC, now a haven for thieves and liars.
And then there's MultiChoice. Last week the company - which has an unassailable monopoly in pay television and rights to all the sports, movie and news channels that matter - struck out at communications minister Yunus Carrim over plans to switch our TV signal.
MultiChoice and e.tv have different reasons to be irked by the foot-dragging of the communications department in previous years over the critically important but often-ignored digital terrestrial television (DTT) switch-over.
Despite being a signatory to the UN-backed umbrella body's global switching date of November, the department under previous, ill-suited (and often scurrilous) ministers has been asleep at the wheel (not surprising, given the breadth of the government/monopoly) and missed every deadline.
The current impasse is over whether set-top boxes (the technical term for decoders) should be encrypted or not.
This is a valid and important argument which should have been settled years ago, instead of the preoccupation with Dina Pule's relationships and red-soled shoes.
But MultiChoice's angry response to Carrim is disproportionately strong.
And it's always hard to feel sorry for monopolies - be they in business, telecoms or broadcasting - when they complain of "narrow commercial interests" (meaning e.tv) or when any company (including Cell C, with its 12m customers) is suddenly a friend of the "consumer".
MultiChoice is obviously protecting its rather large monopoly on satellite pay-TV. And e.tv wants the decoders to include encryption because that will allow it to compete against the DStv parent in offering services that require the additional control that encryption offers.
This is vastly simplifying the debate, but you have to feel for MultiChoice's argument that e.tv is essentially asking government to fund a decoder rollout for its satellite plans, as well as services that require the so-called return path (a way for the viewer to send information back to the broadcaster).
At the core should rather be concerns about future-proofing the decoders so that other services - including subscriptions to limit other countries hijacking a signal or even some broadband delivery - can ultimately be implemented.
But these DTT delays have a more dangerous result, which is freeing up the current frequencies being used, which will be much better utilised for providing wireless broadband. There is little debate about the value of this "digital dividend" for these updated uses of the frequencies, but there needs to be some level-headedness and MultiChoice and e.tv need to find some middle ground.
The squabble is better than actual television itself.
Shapshak is editor and publisher of Stuff magazine (stuff.co.za). Follow him on Twitter: @shapshak
]]></text></news-item>