<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BN3-CT01-DY0P-G2BR"><date>2014-03-03</date><title>North Carolina Spill Seen Showing EPA Limits Over 'Inactive' Coal Ash Ponds</title><source>Superfund Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The recent major coal ash spill in North Carolina from an "inactive" storage pond is sparking renewed debate about whether regulating the coal combustion material as a non-hazardous solid waste, as EPA is widely expected to do later this year, will provide enough regulatory oversight to surface impoundments no longer receiving new wastes.
As much as 39,000 tons of liquid coal ash spilled last month from an inactive surface impoundment at a Duke Energy power plant into the nearby Dan River after a stormwater pipe running underneath the pond broke. The spill has already triggered a federal investigation, with prosecutors last month subpoenaing almost 20 employees from the state's Department of Environmental and Natural Resources (DENR) to testify before a grand jury.
Even as cleanup is just starting, environmentalists and industry are sharply divided about whether the spill shows a need for EPA to take another look at designating coal ash as a "special waste" under more stringent "subtitle C" of the Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA) that would impose new cleanup rules for inactive ponds like the one owned by Duke.
Industry widely believes EPA has all but abandoned subtitle C since it was proposed in a 2010 rule.
Alternately, even if the agency moves ahead with a weaker option to designate coal ash as a non-hazardous solid waste under "subtitle D" of the waste law, environmentalists say the recent North Carolina spill indicates a need to make changes to the rule to ensure inactive coal ash ponds no longer pose health and environmental risks.
But industry officials remain convinced that even with the recent spills, EPA will almost certainly move ahead with early indications that it would regulate coal ash under subtitle D. Further, they argue that EPA lacks authority to regulate inactive coal ash ponds under subtitle C or subtitle D, but rather say EPA could only address inactive sites that pose an "imminent and substantial endangerment" risk using enforcement authority under RCRA or through the Superfund law.
EPA will have to reconcile those divergent views on what to do about inactive coal ash sites, and the material in general, as it works to comply with a settlement committing the agency to finalize the RCRA coal ash rule by Dec. 19.
The agency in 2010 proposed to regulate coal ash as a "special waste" under subtitle C that would carry greater federal oversight or as a non-hazardous solid waste under subtitle D that would leave enforcement authority to states and citizen suits.
Both options would eventually require utilities to retrofit their existing active surface impoundments -- used so that coal ash can settle out from water that transport that material -- with liners to prevent leaks. A third proposed option, called "D prime," would allow existing surface impoundments to continue operating without liners for their useful lives.
EPA has been widely believed to be moving ahead with subtitle D after officials indicated in a 2013 proposed Clean Water Act effluent limitation guideline (ELG) for power plants that, accounting for the new data on the location of coal ash facilities, it had revised its risk assessment on coal ash and that its "current thinking" was that subtitle D would be adequate (Superfund Report, April 29).
But environmentalists say that only subtitle C would ensure that inactive and retired coal ash ponds would be regulated. And they say that the recent North Carolina spill, combined with recent coal slurry and chemical spills in West Virginia that have caused significant water quality problems, are "game changers" for the coal ash rule.
"In light of the need to address legacy sites, provide federal enforcement authority and require financial assurance, EPA must regulate coal ash as a special waste under subtitle C," says the same environmentalist source.
They say the Duke coal ash spill highlights a need to better regulate inactive surface impoundments and the pitfalls of allowing state regulators who may have close ties to industry to have the primary oversight role over coal ash facilities, problems they say would be addressed by finalizing the rules under subtitle C.
Even if EPA doesn't finalize the rule under subtitle C, advocates and others say there are ways the agency could adjust the regulations under subtitle D to improve the regulation of inactive or retired surface impoundments. "There is nothing in the statute that prohibits" regulation of inactive ash ponds, says the environmentalist source. "It would just involve a change to the proposed rule."
An industry attorney agrees that EPA may have the authority under RCRA to adjust subtitle D to cover inactive sites, potentially by changing the definitions on what it meant for a site to be an "active" or "inactive" unit, effectively by saying that "any surface impoundment with liquids and materials in it is an active unit" that would need to be retrofitted with liners, meeting operational and design standards, or be shut down by a certain date.
"If you've got an impoundment that still has juice in it, technically EPA can say that's still an active facility," the attorney says.
Utility and coal ash recycling officials, in contrast, say there is no reason to think that the recent coal ash spill in North Carolina will make much of an impact on EPA's final RCRA rule, particularly in regard to subtitle C, given the agency's comments last year that revisions to its risk assessments have found instead that subtitle D is adequate.
The problem for environmentalists' arguments is that "EPA can't defend the subtitle C rule if they wrote one," says an industry source. "The Dan River spill does not change any of that, it does not change that EPA's original subtitle C proposal was based on a faulty risk assessment, so [subtitle] D is the only legally defensible option."
The industry source says that environmentalists are "playing a shell game" and that -- had it not been for lawsuits filed by environmentalists trying to get subtitle C regulations -- EPA would have been able to finalize its proposed ELG for power plants that would have stopped water from traveling through inactive coal ash disposal sites.
"All of the legacy sites that they're talking about are impoundments and they're more appropriately regulated under the Clean Water Act than they are under the solid waste section of the law," says the source.
The industry source says that if EPA were to finalize the coal ash rule under subtitle C, it would create a stigma over the recycling of coal combustion material in concrete and other uses, causing about 50 million tons of coal ash that are currently recycled each year to instead be diverted to landfills.
Another industry source says that despite EPA's claims that it can regulate inactive coal ash impoundments under subtitle C, such an approach would be "illegal" and in conflict with legal precedent on the waste law.
But environmentalists believe their arguments for subtitle C will be significantly bolstered by the problems highlighted by the North Carolina coal ash spill and the chemical spill in West Virginia earlier this year that caused hundreds of thousands of residents to be without drinking water for days.
The North Carolina spill, the environmentalist says, shows that state regulators frequently provide inadequate oversight. In the Duke case, for example, state regulators preempted a threatened citizen suit over the coal ash facility and proposed to issue a $99,000 fine for groundwater contamination from two coal ash facilities, without any remediation requirement -- though regulators withdrew the proposed settlement shortly after the spill.
A second environmentalist says the recent spills and leaks of chemical and coal ash into the water will help them counter arguments from utility groups that states can provide adequate oversight authority. "I've got to believe the whole mess in North Carolina with the legacy site leaking, all the sweetheart deals, and now the investigation of [DENR] has highlighted the problem with the utility argument that this is an area where states are doing fine," the source says, adding that if states are in charge, it is likely that "nothing will happen."
The second source adds that the recent spills are likely to quash momentum in the Senate to consider a House-passed bill to codify EPA's subtitle D approach. -- Chris Knight
]]></text></news-item>