<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BN3-CT01-DY0P-G2BN"><date>2014-03-03</date><title>EPA Proposes First-Time Risk Values For Chronic PFC Exposures</title><source>Superfund Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EPA's water office is proposing first-time draft risk estimates for chronic drinking water exposures to two ubiquitous perfluorochemicals (PFCs), values that will eventually allow regulators to craft health advisory levels and cleanup requirements at sites contaminated with the substances that have been widely used but are now being phased out.
But the proposed risk values are likely to be controversial with liable parties facing potential additional cleanup requirements and with some community plaintiffs potentially facing exposures above the advisory and regulatory levels that the agency may eventually derive from its risk estimates.
The new draft risk estimates are also likely to be controversial because the agency maintains that the chemicals -- perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) and perfluorooctane sulfonate (PFOS) -- are "suggestive of carcinogenity," effectively dismissing advice given years ago by most members of its Science Advisory Board (SAB) who said that PFOA is a "likely" carcinogen.
According to a draft EPA study on the toxicity of PFOA, the agency is proposing a reference dose (RfD), the maximum amount of a substance EPA estimates can be ingested daily over a lifetime without adverse non-cancer health effects, of 0.00002 milligrams/kilogram/day (mg/kg/day) due to adverse changes in the liver linked to developmental effects and adverse changes in the kidney. Relevant documents are available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID: 2462602)
EPA also proposed a cancer slope factor -- a measure of a substance's cancer potency -- for PFOA but said the RfD is likely to be more protective than any cancer protections.
In a similar study on PFOS, the agency is proposing a RfD of 0.00003 mg/kg/day due to developmental toxicity and adverse liver effects.
EPA formally unveiled the studies Feb. 28 and also requested nominations for an expert panel to peer review the draft studies. Nominations are being accepted until March 21.The agency has also crafted draft charge questions for the panel. And the agency is taking public comment on the studies until April 29.
PFCs are emerging contaminants that are "extremely persistent in the environment" and resist typical environmental degradation methods, EPA says in a March 2013 fact sheet. "As a result, they are widely distributed across the higher tropic levels and are found in soil, air, and groundwater at sites across the United States," it says.
Recent studies have suggested a range of possible adverse health effects from PFOA, including testicular and kidney cancers, as well as ulcerative colitis, thyroid disease, pregnancy-induced hypertension and medically diagnosed high cholesterol.
PFOA and other PFCs have been used to manufacture a wide range of consumer products, such as non-stick products like Teflon. The chemicals also have widespread applications in chemical manufacturing, metal plating, aircraft production processes, fire control equipment and some electronic products such as cell phones and circuit boards.
After a draft EPA risk assessment showed greater cancer and non-cancer risks than previously believed, EPA in 2003 struck rare agreements to require the chemicals' manufacturers to provide missing data on PFOA. And the agency later won commitments from the manufacturers to phase out the compound's use in consumer products.
While these actions may eventually limit the manufacturers' prospective liability, less clear is their liability for legacy contamination, particularly adjacent to manufacturing plants in West Virginia, Minnesota, North Carolina, New Jersey and Alabama.
Regulators and other officials have also suggested that contamination may be even more widespread due to broad use of the chemicals in firefighting material used extensively at Air Force bases and other facilities. One study showed record-high levels of PFCs at the former Wurtsmith Air Force Base near Oscoda, MI, due to firefighting training areas that used aqueous film forming foam, which contains PFCs. Following the scrutiny at the site, the Air Force announced a program to systematically sample for PFCs in fire training areas that operated from 1970 to 2000.
But while the chemicals are widespread in the environment, assessing the risks is proving difficult in part because recent studies that rely on limited data have shown effects only at the lowest doses of exposure.
While EPA and several states, including Minnesota, New Jersey and North Carolina, have developed interim risk levels, these levels are disparate. EPA's provisional health advisory of 0.4 parts per billion (ppb) for PFOA and 0.2 ppb for PFOS are set for short-term exposures and used as interim "action levels."
The agency's waste office is also crafting first-time technical guidance to be used at sites contaminated by PFOA and PFOS, a document that will eventually provide long-sought soil and drinking water screening values for regulators struggling to set cleanup levels for the compounds (Superfund Report, Feb. 3).
The RfDs the agency is now proposing will eventually help regulators determine if enforceable drinking water requirements are needed and at what levels they should be set, though EPA's acting water chief Nancy Stoner in 2012 told lawyers representing West Virginia and Ohio residents exposed to the chemicals that it would take several years before the agency even decided whether a standard was warranted.
Stoner noted that the agency would still have to receive PFOA monitoring data from drinking water utilities that are required to monitor for the substance between 2013-2015 as a result of the agency's unregulated contaminants monitoring rule.
If EPA makes an affirmative determination to regulate, the Safe Drinking Water Act gives the agency two years to propose the regulation for public review and comment, and then finalize it within 18 months of the proposal. "The agency expects that we will have sufficient information to determine whether it is appropriate to develop a drinking water regulation for PFOA within the next 5 to 7 years," Stoner said.
But the agency may be able to set new health advisory levels using the new RfDs more quickly.
Based on standard default assumptions EPA uses for its drinking water standards and health advisories, the RfD the agency is proposing for PFOA would appear to translate into chronic drinking water health advisory levels of 0.1 ppb, a stricter level than the provisional value of 0.4 ppb that EPA set in 2009 for short-term exposures.
The RfD for PFOS would likely result in the agency maintaining its advisory level of 0.2 ppb for both short- and long-term exposures.
Such health advisories for chronic exposures relate to the concentration of a chemical in drinking water not expected to cause any adverse noncarcinogenic effects exposure over a lifetime of exposure, "incorporating a drinking water [relative source contribution] factor of contaminant-specific data or a default of 20 percent of total exposure from all sources," the agency says in its 2012 Drinking Water Standards and Health Advisories. The lifetime health advisory "is based on exposure of a 70-kg adult consuming 2 liters of water per day."
But the health advisories that are expected to be derived from the new RfDs would still allow PFOA exposures found in some water districts adjacent to DuPont's Washington Works plant in West Virginia. For example, the Village of Pomeroy, OH, had levels reported at 0.06 - 0.07 ppb, while the Mason, WV, water district had levels at 0.06 - 0.1 ppb.
The communities and their lawyers are likely to raise concerns about any levels derived from the health studies that continue to allow high exposures.
They are also likely to raise concerns about EPA's cancer classifications, which appear to be weaker than most members of the agency's SAB panel recommended in 2006, when three quarters of the panelists recommended that PFOA be deemed a "likely" carcinogen.
But EPA in the PFOA health effects document says the "findings for cancer in humans are equivocal," noting that "some epidemiological studies show a positive association with exposures and others are negative." The agency also considered animal studies.
As a result, it says "the evidence for the carcinogenicity of PFOA is considered suggestive because only one species has been evaluated and studies for gene mutations were negative."
For PFOS, EPA also says the evidence for carcinogenicity is "suggestive," but is "not sufficient to assess human carcinogenicity potential." -- Suzanne Yohannan
]]></text></news-item>