<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BN3-CT01-DY0P-G2BW"><date>2014-03-03</date><title>EPA To Release Housatonic Cleanup Plan After End Of High-Level Talks</title><source>Superfund Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EPA Region I expects to release in May a cleanup plan for sediment in the Houstatonic River contaminated with polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs), after 16 months of closed-door, high-level talks with the site's potentially responsible party, General Electric (GE), ended "amicably" in December but without agreement, sources say.
GE says EPA's demands that the company relinquish certain rights under a long-standing consent decree for the site were mostly to blame for the talks ending.
At stake is the level and type of cleanup that will be required for a significantly contaminated sediment site, which one long-time environmentalist says could set a precedent for other polluted rivers, particularly if EPA allows for a less extensive remedy.
A technical advisor to citizen groups says if EPA Region I disregards recommendations made by two EPA national review boards three years ago that questioned the strength of earlier proposed cleanup actions for the site, then the agency could lose support both at the technical and political levels.
The agency hopes to release a proposed cleanup plan in May in the form of a revised Resource Conservation & Recovery Act (RCRA) permit for the site, along with proposed performance standards, an EPA Region I spokesman says. The plan would be released for public comment, followed by a final cleanup decision.
At issue is the so-called "Rest of River" portion of the river and site cleanup. GE's Pittsfield, MA, facility, which manufactured and serviced electrical transformers from 1932-1977, released PCBs and other hazardous substances into the Housatonic, contaminating the facility's property as well as the river, its banks and floodplains from Pittsfield to Long Island Sound, according to an EPA fact sheet. While GE has undertaken other aspects of the cleanup involving the first two miles of the river closest to the plant, the "Rest of River" cleanup refers to the remaining cleanup stemming from "Reach 5" of the river, including the main stem of the river and its floodplain from the confluence of the river's east and west branches in Pittsfield downstream to the Derby-Shelton Dam, CT -- a distance of about 135 miles, according to EPA.
The cleanup is unique in that it is being implemented as a Superfund remedial action but is going through the RCRA permit process.
In 2012, EPA indicated it was considering a cleanup plan at the site that was comprised of a combination of targeted soil and sediment removal, riverbed capping and so-called monitored natural recovery in order to address PCBs posing the largest threat, according to an EPA status report from May 2012. According to the report, EPA outlined a potential framework for a remedy that included removing PCB-contaminated bed sediment and containing residual contamination in some reaches of the river, removing some soil in the floodplain adjacent to the river, limiting bank erosion and PCB transport downstream by natural channel design and other measures, and undertaking other actions including institutional controls. Roughly, this cleanup proposal would mean the removal of 750,000 cubic yards to 1 million cubic yards of material, EPA estimated. Relevant documents are available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc: 2462780)
In that same year, GE sought high-level and technical talks with EPA to better understand the potential remedy approaches outlined in the May 2012 status report, according to an EPA summary of the first round of talks among the EPA Region I administrator and other regional staff, Massachusetts and Connecticut environment officials and GE officials. The monthly meetings included discussions on technical issues, concerns and options within the status report, according to the summary. An EPA Region I spokesman says the talks were "constructive and informative," and says EPA had an eye toward speeding up the cleanup process by discussing technical issues early with the company. But when asked whether EPA officials were successful in speeding the cleanup process, the spokesman said there will need to be further discussions.
GE says the talks ended by mutual agreement but concluded "for reasons that had less to do with the proposed remedy and more to do with EPA's demand that GE forfeit rights it has under the Consent Decree and the law," according to a spokesman for the company.
The regional spokesman disagrees with GE that the agency sought to deny the company its rights under the consent decree -- a 1999 document to address EPA and state claims for response actions and costs and natural resource damages at the site. He says the agency hopes that through the talks GE gained a good understanding of technical issues, and noted that "we dove down pretty deep on some issues," such as capping. The spokesman notes that GE under the consent decree has a number of rights including dispute rights. According to the agency, GE can invoke administrative dispute resolution regarding EPA's intended final decision. In response, EPA would then issue a RCRA permit modification, and this final cleanup decision would then be subject to appeal by GE and the public through the agency's Environmental Appeals Board and then through the federal courts, according to an agency fact sheet.
The GE spokesman says the talks began at the company's request because GE was committed to reaching an agreement with EPA, Massachusetts and Connecticut "on a common sense solution for the Housatonic Rest of River that would have resulted in a responsible remedy that addresses the River, balances the benefits of additional PCB removal against the unavoidable negative impacts of that work and provides certainty for all parties."
The EPA spokesman agrees "certainty" was what EPA was hoping for, but adds, "We didn't achieve certainty on all the issues, that's for sure."
Neither the EPA nor GE spokesmen would provide details on the "rights" GE says EPA sought to eliminate or other issues that went unresolved.
An earlier proposed cleanup action for the Rest of River portion of the site underwent a joint review by two national panels: EPA's National Remedy Review Board and its Contaminated Sediments Technical Advisory Group (CSTAG), which generally questioned the strength of the cleanup plans. The national remedy review panel typically reviews proposed cleanup decisions at sites where remedies are expected to cost more than $25 million, while CSTAG generally gives guidance to regions on appropriately managing large, complex or controversial sediment sites, with an aim toward encouraging national consistency in their management.
The boards in 2011 made a number of joint recommendations to the region on its proposed plans for the Rest of River site, for instance questioning a preferred plan to leave large quantities of PCBs in place along the site's floodplain, telling the regional site cleanup office it should coordinate with the region's Toxic Substances Control Act (TSCA) program given soils will remain in excess of 50 parts per million (ppm), and questioning why the high concentrations of PCBs -- in some cases greater than 800 ppm -- in floodplain soils would not be considered principal threat waste (PTW) subject to the Superfund law's preference for treatment to the maximum extent practicable, among other concerns.
EPA in 2012 responded to the recommendations, adopting some of the ideas and defending itself in other areas. For instance, the regional site cleanup office said it was coordinating with the TSCA program to ensure the remedy meets TSCA requirements for PCBs, but generally defended itself on the question of PTW, saying that no residential properties would see concentrations of PCBs greater than 100 ppm, and citing EPA guidance that states although Superfund's regulatory blueprint -- the National Contingency Plan -- has a preference for treating PTW, treatment has often not been selected for sediment sites given high costs, uncertain effectiveness and community preferences.
The technical advisory group expert is critical of the direction in which the region has gone since the review boards' recommendations, saying it has moved toward a weaker remedy, at least until GE and the agency ended their talks. The source specifically contends that the agency has moved toward less removal of PCB contaminated sediments and more capping and "natural recovery."
The environmentalist says citizens around the site are closely watching for the upcoming cleanup plan from EPA, citing dissatisfaction with EPA's release of information at the site.
]]></text></news-item>