<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BP4-D6V1-JDHS-H4NN"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Jury Awards $11MM to Victim in Pneumo Abex Suit</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Heather Isringhausen Gvillo, writing for Legal Newsline, reportedthat a jury awarded the family of a deceased auto parts workerdiagnosed with mesothelioma $11 million in damages in the family'swrongful death lawsuit after previously awarding the family nearly$4 million in a personal injury lawsuit. The wrongful death lawsuit was the second trial in a pair oftrials in the Alameda County Superior Court. The jury deliberatedfor less than two hours after the two-day trial, reaching itsverdict on Jan. 15 in Judge Jo-Lynne Q. Lee's courtroom. Itawarded $6 million to decedent Gordon Bankhead's wife EmilyBankhead and $2.5 million to each of Gordon Bankhead's adultdaughters -- Tammy Bankhead and Debbie Bankhead-Meiers. The family filed its wrongful death lawsuit against defendantPneumo Abex LLC, successor of Abex Corporation, in June 2012. According to the complaint, Gordon Bankhead worked as a parts manfrom 1965 until 1999 in the service and repair of heavy dutyvehicles. His exposure to asbestos dust is primarily attributedto his work with vehicle brake parts. Gordon Bankhead was involved in regularly inspecting, replacing,grinding and blowing out dust from the asbestos-containing brakes. Defendant Pneumo Abex manufactured brake linings Gordon Bankheadwas exposed to, which were attached to brake shoes and axles andwere sold to his employers. He was diagnosed with mesothelioma inJanuary 2010 and filed his asbestos personal injury complaint inMarch 2010. Gordon Bankhead died from his illness at age 68 in October 2011,which led to the wrongful death lawsuit, intended to compensatehis family for their loss of his companionship. Pneumo was not allowed to dispute its responsibility for GordonBankhead's death during the wrongful death lawsuit, and the jurywas not informed of the details behind the defendant's liabilitynor the family's previous verdicts in the personal injurycomplaint. The jury was asked to determine an appropriate number tocompensate the family for losing their loved one 17 years beforehis life expectancy. "Immediately prior to the conduct of defendants herein giving riseto the decedents exposure to asbestos and asbestos-containingmaterials and before the fatal asbestos-related disease wasdiagnosed, plaintiff's decedent was an adult person in goodphysical and mental condition and was a faithful and dutifulhusband and father," the complaint stated. According to the 10-count complaint, Pneumo Abex knew of thedangers associated with asbestos exposure but suppressedinformation relating to the dangers and failed to properly warnGordon Bankhead. "Each of the foregoing acts, suggestions, assertions andforebearances to act when a duty existed to act, the saiddefendants, and each of them, having such knowledge, knowing thedecedent did not have such knowledge and would breathe suchmaterial innocently, was done falsely and fraudulently and withfull intent to induce decedent to work in a dangerous environmentand to cause decedent to remain unaware of the true facts," thecomplaint says. The Bankheads' personal injury lawsuit went to trial in October2010, and was conducted in two phases. The first phase of thetrial was to determine liability. The second phase of the trial,beginning in January 2011, was to determine punitive damages. As part of the first phase, the jury found that the defendantsdefectively designed their brakes, failed to adequately warnconsumers and customers of the dangers in working with the brakes,were negligent and intentionally failed to inform the claimant ofpreventative measures. They presented 30 percent liability to each brake manufacturer,including Pneumo Abex, 15 percent to each brake shoe manufacturerand 10 percent to Gordon Bankhead's employers. The jury awarded Gordon Bankhead $1.47 million for his past andfuture economic loss and $1.5 million for his pain and suffering.They awarded Emily Bankhead $1 million for her loss of herhusband's support and companionship. Defendants Pneumo Abex and ArvinMeritor were the only twodefendants left by the time the second phase of the first trialcommenced. The rest had settled. The jury awarded $9 million inpunitive damages, finding that the defendants' actions weremalicious, fraudulent and oppressive. Pneumo Abex appealed, butthe verdict was upheld. The Bankheads were represented by Joseph Satterley and Justin Boslof Kazan, McClain, Satterley & Greenwood and former partner LeighKirmsse in the first trial.
]]></text></news-item>