<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BP4-D6V1-JDHS-H4NH"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Housing Trust &amp; Firms Fined for Fibro Risk</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Northumberland Gazette reported that a trust providing housing andcare for the elderly, and two firms hired to carry outrefurbishment work at its premises in Alnwick, England, have beenfined more than GBP20,000 after staff and residents were put atrisk of exposure to asbestos. West Yorkshire firm, Express Elevators Ltd, was contracted byAnchor Trust to replace the lift at St Paul's Court shelteredhousing, off Prudhoe Street, in November 2012. PC Lifts, of London, was subcontracted to remove the existing liftahead of the new one being installed but the lift shaft containedasbestos boards, which PC Lifts removed without putting anymeasures in place to prevent the spread of asbestos fibres. The Health and Safety Executive (HSE) said that Anchor Trust had aduty as the client to ensure that arrangements made for managingthe lift replacement were suitable, and ensured there was no riskto health. They failed in this duty as they provided ExpressElevators Ltd with conflicting information and, although anasbestos survey was provided, it was not sufficiently accurate ordetailed enough for the work being carried out. The HSE investigation found that Express Elevators Ltd failed inits duty to plan and manage the work as it did not make adequateinquiries about the presence of asbestos. The company relied onverbal information from Anchor and although it received thesurvey, no reference was made to it before work began. PC Lifts was also found not to have made adequate inquiries and tohave worked in the lift shaft without adequate lighting. Thesefactors may have contributed to the company's failure inidentifying the asbestos. Asbestos boards were broken out from thetop of the lift shaft, but no measures were put in place toprevent the spread of asbestos fibres through the building. The combined failures of all three parties led to the unsaferemoval of the asbestos and the potential spread of asbestosfibres, which exposed residents and others to a potential risk totheir health. Anchor Trust, of Bedford Street, London was fined GBP10,000 andordered to pay GBP346.40 in costs after pleading guilty tobreaching Regulation 9(1)(a) of the Construction (Design andManagement) Regulations 2007. Express Elevators Ltd, of Otley Road, Baildon, Shipley, WestYorkshire was fined GBP8,000 with GBP827.30 costs after pleadingguilty to breaching Regulation 13(2) of the same legislation. PC Lifts Ltd, of St John Street, London, was fined GBP4,000 withGBP346.40 costs after pleading guilty to breaching Regulation 16of the Control of Asbestos Regulations 2012. Speaking after the case, HSE Inspector Natalie Wright, said:"Asbestos is the single greatest cause of work-related deaths inthe UK and those involved in the construction and refurbishmentindustry have a clear duty to ensure that work is managed so as toprevent the spread of asbestos. "This incident occurred because not one of the defendantsfulfilled their respective duties when carrying out the liftreplacement at St Paul's Court, leading to asbestos fibres beingdisturbed. "As well as the companies' employees, the residents at St Paul'sCourt were also potentially put at risk. "This incident was entirely preventable, had the companies carriedout their respective safety duties. This prosecution should act asa reminder to all involved in such work, that whenever work iscarried out which is liable to expose employees to asbestos asuitable survey must be done to establish whether asbestos ispresent before any work begins."
]]></text></news-item>