<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BPM-R4P1-JBKP-900H"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>The Billionaies Philippines-Poland</title><source>Forbes</source><author>Forbes Staff</author><text><![CDATA[GDP: $276.5 Bil
Population: 98.4 Mil
billionaires: 10
Total net worth: $40.1 Bil
10% Drop in Philippine peso over the past year (lowest level since 2010)
PORT OF MANILA Enrique Razon's International Container Terminal Services owns 28 ports worldwide, 8 of them in the Philippines, including the nation's biggest in Manila. Razon made waves last year when he fired Global Gaming Asset Management of Las Vegas, manager of his new Manila casino (located just a poker chip's throw from the port), for allegedly not doing its job. The dispute is under arbitration in Singapore.
RESCUE WORKERS November's typhoon, which killed 6,000 people, was classified as the deadliest natural disaster in the world for 2013. Henry Sy responded by putting $2.2 million into a calamity fund set up by his SM Group. Tobacco and beer tycoon Lucio Tan contributed a similar amount and deployed his personal airplanes to deliver medicines and other supplies to victims.
97 Henry Sy &amp; family DOWN $11.4 bil diversified
227 Lucio Tan &amp; family UP $6.1 bil diversified
319 Andrew Tan UP $4.7 bil diversified
354 Enrique Razon Jr. DOWN $4.2 bil ports
388 John Gokongwei Jr. NEW TO LIST $3.9 bil diversified
483 David Consunji UP $3.3 bil construction
764 George Ty &amp; family DOWN $2.3 bil banking
1046 Tony Tan Caktiong &amp; family UP $1.7 bil fast food
1154 Robert Coyiuto Jr. DOWN $1.5 bil power
1565 Andrew Gotianun DOWN $1 bil real estate
PORTUGAL
GDP: $219 Bil Population: 10.6 Mil billionaires: 3 Total net worth: $10.6 Bil
POWERFUL PARTNER Américo Amorim partnered with Angola's first daughter (and billionaire), Isabel dos Santos, to start Banco Internacional de Credito in Angola in 2005. The two are also coinvestors in listed Portuguese oil-and-gas firm Galp Energia.
267 Americo Amorim UP $5.3 bil energy, investments
609 Alexandre Soares dos Santos & family DOWN $2.8 bil retail
687 Belmiro de Azevedo UP $2.5 bil retail
POLAND
GDP: $517.1 Billion Population: 38.5 Million billionaires: 5 Total net worth: $12.8 Bil
430 Jan Kulczyk UP $3.6 bil telecom, oil, beer
446 Zygmunt Solorz-Zak UP $3.5 bil TV broadcasting
731 Leszek Czarnecki UP $2.4 bil finance
764 Michal Solowow UP $2.3 bil investments
1565 Dariusz Milek NEW TO LIST $1 bil real estate, retail
Lower Silesia This province in southwest Poland is home to a growing finance and high-tech industry -- the eye-popping Wroclaw Technology Park opened in 2007 in the provincial capital. Financier Leszek Czarnecki's Sky Tower, Poland's tallest building, was inaugurated in 2012.
NEW BLOOD Over half of Jan Kulczyk's investments lie in South African beermaker SABMiller (which bought his stake in Polish brewer Kompania Piwowarska in 2009). SABMiller's stock price is down 15% over the past year. He is looking to new ventures and the next generation to lift returns; son Sebastian runs the family investment firm, which has a stake in an importer of Audi and Volkswagen vehicles. Daughter Dominika joined its supervisory board last July. Kulczyk is also active in real estate investments.
ROMANIA
GDP: $188.5 Bil Population: 20 Mil billionaires: 1 Total net worth: $1.2 Bil
1372 Ioan Niculae UP $1.2 bil agriculture
]]></text></news-item>