<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRF-P461-JB2D-51WT"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>EC official faces charges over airport lease</title><source>Daily Dispatch (South Africa)</source><author>Mphumzi Zuzile</author><text><![CDATA[By Deputy Political Editor A SENIOR Eastern Cape roads and public works official is facing misconduct charges after he allegedly leased out government land and property without approval. The official allegedly leased out the Mthatha Airport to a Pretoria-based company, JetVision, and later cancelled the lease.
Documentation seen by the Daily Dispatch shows that OR Tambo acting regional manager George Sidaza signed a lease between the department and JetVision on May 29 last year to lease the airport, all assets, infrastructure, structure and other facilities. "JetVision (Pty) Ltd is to operate as an airport company and as an airport service delivery on these said land and structure and premises," the lease agreement states. But on May 30, Sidaza wrote to JetVision cancelling the lease. "My investigation has since discovered that the land upon which the airport assets, infrastructure and other facilities are situated does not belong to public works but to the Ncise community." The department's spokesman, Sisanda George, confirmed the lease had been cancelled by the department. "The official was charged for concluding leases without properly delegated authority. "The department is not the custodian of the airport and has no authority to go on tender for the airport lease," George said. He said Sidaza had been charged with misconduct and had pleaded guilty. "The department is awaiting the report of the chairperson in the disciplinary inquiry with regard to the appropriate sanction that can be imposed," he said. JetVision is an aviation company, with experience in all sectors of aviation. According to the company's website it was formed to cater for small projects such as pilot training and larger projects such as airport infrastructure and aircraft fleet finance and lease. JetVision owner Attie van Deventer said they had had big plans for the Mthatha Airport, including the introduction of a flight school. "We would have introduced more flights from other regional airports. We invested a lot of money and in the end it turned out to be fraudulent. It seems to me the entire Eastern Cape government is corrupt. "We could have brought in other opportunities, commercial and retail. The airport would have been world class and introduced other routes. We spent nearly two years on a project where people had no power, knowledge nor experience." Asked if the company was considering taking legal action he said: "Do you think I'm going to spend more money on the Eastern Cape government? It is going to cost me millions and endless years to prove to people that we wanted to do good." Sidaza confirmed to the Dispatch that he was facing disciplinary charges and had pleaded guilty but would not comment further. SUBJECT OF CONTROVERSY: A public works manager has been charged for leasing Mthatha Airport without approval Picture: LULAMILE FENI
]]></text></news-item>