<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRF-P461-JB2D-51WJ"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Summit resolves to fight corrupt traffic officials</title><source>Daily Dispatch (South Africa)</source><author>Msindisi Fengu</author><text><![CDATA[By Senior Reporter AN ANTI-FRAUD, corruption and bribery summit was held in East London by transport authorities on Friday and a plan was drawn up to eliminate corrupt traffic management.
Discussions involved representatives from businesses and police. The plan is aimed at tightening up the eNaTIS system, which is currently managed by privately-owned company Tasima and will prevent traffic officials from getting involved in corrupt activities. Based on the eNaTIS anti-fraud and corruption strategy developed in 2011, it is hoped the plan will root out the "rot" in the system. Part of the plan includes looking at ways to create a secure environment in eNaTIS by: lNot only relying on passwords but also other identification measures; l Establishing a database for eNaTis transgressors in the form of a fraud and corruption register; and l Undertaking anti-fraud and corruption training for all authorities, among other measures. Fake vehicle registrations and ID details of offending motorists submitted by officials to get offenders off paying fines were some of the cases picked up in the eNaTIS system. The case of a Tshwane metro official who allegedly pocketed R1.1-million by clearing drivers' fines by transferring the fines of the original drivers to fake IDs was cited as an example. Four more officials were also reported in the media for transferring fines of drivers using the IDs of dead people. But officials said they had not identified such cases in the Eastern Cape other than incidents relating to normal road traffic irregularities where officials accepted bribes from motorists. Provincial transport department chief director Romilla Metune said: "There is a rot in the country. But, no such reports in the province." However, Metune said there were concerns about the corrupt conduct of traffic officers on the roads in the province. Business Against Crime South Africa project manager Kevin Kara-Vula said the department also needed to catch up on technological developments to prevent officers from being lured into illegal activities. He said there was a trend of web users urging people to sell them illegal traffic documentation, while others were offering illegal documents online. Special Investigative Unit senior cyber forensic examiner Jason Jordaan said authorities should use the law to deal with corrupt motorists offering bribes. eNaTIS executive security service at Tasima Daniel Sodladla said traffic officials involved in wrongdoing should be named and shamed. - msindisif@dispatch.co.za
]]></text></news-item>