<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRM-KW11-JD6S-R324"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>ACTC: Celebrating 75 years in the Tri-State</title><source>The Herald-Dispatch (Huntington, West Virginia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Ashland Community and Technical College is a comprehensive community and technical college serving the Tri-State area of northeastern Kentucky, southeastern Ohio and northwestern West Virginia. ACTC is one of 16, two-year, open-admissions colleges of the Kentucky Community and Technical College System.
75th Anniversary
This year ACTC celebrates 75 years of college service to the community. In 1937, Ashland Junior College was formed by the City of Ashland and Ashland Vocational School was formed by the Ashland Independent School System. The two colleges evolved over the years to meet changing student educational needs, and they merged into ACTC in 2003.
Anniversary events have included a fundraising dinner, YouTube video of alumni and past presidents, and a commemorative brick project. Planned for later this year are an oral history presentation and a birthday party at Summer Motion.
"As we celebrate 75 years of providing access to higher education, we look forward to the future," said Dr. Kay Adkins, ACTC's president since 2012. "We will continue to provide programs, services, events and activities that expand opportunities for a new generation of students and that support community growth and development."
Milestones 2013
In April, ACTC was ranked among the top 50 community colleges in the United States by Washington Monthly, a rating based on measures of student retention and completion, interaction with faculty, teaching practices and student support.
In November, Community College Week recognized ACTC as one of the country's Top 50 Colleges in the number of associate degrees awarded for science technologies/technicians.
Graduation 2013 recognized a record number of 568 students.
ACTC's Associate Degree Nursing Program accreditation by the Accreditation Commission for Education in Nursing was reaffirmed in July.
Student service
ACTC serves approximately 3,900 students at three campuses with technology-focused career programs and university transfer programs.
Bi-term courses have been expanded to give students access to classes on a year-around basis.
Several federal grants were received this year to enhance technical education for students in diesel, industrial maintenance, welding, and health and other technical fields.
ACTC and Ohio University have signed a Memorandum of Agreement to develop transfer programs in RN-BNS, Criminal Justice, Specialized Studies, Applied Management, and Technical and Applied Studies. This will add to the transfer choices at Marshall University, Shawnee State University, Morehead State University and other four-year institutions.
ACTC is a partner in CollegeFish.org, a web tool created by Phi Theta Kappa to help community college students plan for transfer to four-year institutions.
An online Transfer Fair and series of campus visits to area universities help students define their opportunities to transfer for bachelor's degrees.
Seven academic/honors organizations and five student organizations offer opportunities for student involvement and development, and students can participate in a variety of community services activities.
Community events
In addition to academic programs, ACTC offers lifelong learning and continuing education programs, adult and workforce education, business and industry programs and services, and cultural and educational programs for the area residents.
The college hosts SkillsUSA and FFA Competitions, Rotary Access to Careers Day and a Young Women Lead conference to encourage high school students to plan on attending college. A Science and Technology Fair, FIRST LEGO League Regional tournament, and summer technology camp give youth opportunities to display their technology skills.
Ashland Independent Schools and ACTC have initiated an Early College venture to help selected high school students earn college credit.
In partnership with governmental and business organizations, ACTC has created a Community and Economic Development Center at the college's Roberts Drive Campus, which also houses The Entrepreneur Center and Kentucky Innovation Network office. The Kentucky Innovation Network office worked with 25 knowledge-based, technology-driven, innovative businesses last year.
ACTC hosts Go2College Adult Learner and Tri-state Job and Career Fairs for adults and is a member of Healthy Choices Kentucky to help improve the health or area residents.
Community events include ACTC Theatre productions, a student art show, and programs celebrating Black History Month, Woman's History Month, Constitution Day and Native American Heritage Month.
Gayle Fritz is the Public Relations Coordinator at Ashland Community & Technical College. She can be reached at Gayle.fritz@kctcs.edu
]]></text></news-item>