<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRN-J5K1-JB2D-517K"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>IMF deficit warning to Mozambique</title><source>The Times (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Economy could grow by more than 8% this year MOZAMBIQUE'S budget deficit will widen to 9.5% this year from 3% in 2013, the International Monetary Fund predicts as the country continues its spending-driven quest for economic growth.
In a report published on its website, the IMF said the mineral-rich country's economy might grow by more than 8% this year after expanding by about 7% in 2013, but warned that the deficit it was running was unsustainable. The growth forecast is in line with that of the Mozambique central bank but, after a visit to the country by one of its inspection teams, the IMF said the country would have to increase spending to cover the costs associated with electoral reform. The former Portuguese colony is holding elections on October 15 to appoint a successor to President Armando Guebuza, who is barred from seeking re-election after two terms in office. The ruling Frelimo party this month named Defence Minister Filipe Nyusi as its presidential candidate. Frelimo, rulers since Mozambique's independence in 1975, this year agreed to expand the electoral commission after its composition was criticised by the opposition for favouring Frelimo. The IMF's budget deficit projection takes into account a one-off tax revenue windfall equal to 4% of annual economic output in 2013, and another expected bonanza this year, equivalent to 2.9% of GDP. Mozambique's hopes rest largely on its coal and gas resources. About 4.2trillion cubic metres of offshore gas have been discovered so far - enough to supply Germany, Britain, France and Italy for 15 years. The government and international energy companies say the total volume might be double the present estimate. Mozambique's north-central Tete province also has some of the world's largest untapped reserves of thermal coal, used for power generation, and of coking coal, used in steel production. The IMF projected that the current account deficit would reach 43% this year, reflecting imports for large foreign investment projects. Central bank governor Ernesto Gove said in February that he expected the deficit to reach 36% of GDP this year. The IMF team's report expressed hope that the country would closely monitor and report on the operations of a new state-controlled company, the Mozambican Tuna Company, which issued $850-million in government-guaranteed bonds last year. Western donor governments expressed concern about what they said was a lack of transparency in the bond issue. Mozambican ministers have said the money raised by the issue will be used to buy tuna-fishing boats, marine patrol vessels and coastal radar systems. Donors asked if such purchases should be priorities for a country still receiving hundreds of millions of dollars in foreign aid annually to fight poverty two decades after the end of a devastating civil war.
]]></text></news-item>