<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRV-X801-JCDY-Y0R1"><date>2014-03-16</date><title></title><source>Star-News (Wilmington, NC)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[You've got to be kidding. That's a natural first reaction to Duke Energy's insistence that customers pay the estimated $1 billion cost of digging up and reburying coal ash stored in ponds at 14 sites. How arrogant of this $50 billion company to try to saddle customers with the cost of fixing its flagrant mistakes.
At this point it is difficult to imagine that Duke Energy would be able to justify a rate increase to cover the cost of cleaning up the mess its leaking pipes made of the Dan River near Eden. But the company wants customers to foot the bill for removing toxic coal ash from unlined storage ponds around the state and burying it in a dry, lined landfill, where it would be far less likely to leach into ground and surface waters.
It seems like a slap in the face to customers and to environmentalists who have been arguing for years that the coal-ash ponds, including two at Wilmington's Sutton Steam Plant, were hazards that needed to be cleaned up. Alas, the reality is not so simple.
It's easy to say that Duke should bear the full cost. It probably won't happen that way, although North Carolina lawmakers and regulators need to be clear that the company must bear the financial consequences of its lack of action over the years. There is plenty of precedent for utilities to include the cost of pollution mitigation and remediation in customers' bills, but if the N.C. Utilities Commission allows such an increase, it must insist that the company absorb the majority of the expense.
According to early estimates, the cost per customer probably would come to 75 cents per month or less for the typical household. Yet there is something morally unsettling about insisting that customers pay for a cleanup that environmental groups have been pushing for years and which only became a priority for Duke after a high-profile, preventable disaster. The costs might have been reduced had Duke and Progress Energy (now part of Duke Energy) had taken steps years ago to begin shutting down the ash ponds.
Perhaps if Duke's shareholders shared the pain, they would press harder for more responsible management of hazardous by-products. There is a "yes, but ..." here.
Duke's shareholders include not only wealthy investors but also ordinary people who have retirement funds invested in mutual funds that may include Duke Energy stock; pushing the burden entirely onto shareholders could have an unintended impact on average investors. Still, Duke must not get off with a light fine - like the $99,000 slap on the wrist the state Department of Environment and Natural Resources proposed to head off an environmental group's lawsuit over a coal-ash spill in Asheville.
Given what is being revealed about the chummy relationship between Duke and environmental regulators, residents have a right to demand severe penalties.
Many observers worry that the pro-business agenda of the current crop of leaders has effectively neutered state regulatory agencies. Gov. Pat McCrory and the General Assembly now know the public won't stand for practices that weaken environmental protection; they must demonstrate that "business-friendly" does not have to mean hiring regulators who don't adequately regulate.
]]></text></news-item>