<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRV-T501-JCV0-10NP"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Cosatu's Corruption Watch wants anti-graft bureau back</title><source>The Sunday Independent (South Africa)</source><author> LOYISO SIDIMBA</author><text><![CDATA[TRADE union federation Cosatu's Corruption Watch group wants Public Service and Administration Minister Lindiwe Sisulu to reintroduce the proposed anti-corruption bureau that has been removed from the Public Administration Management Bill.
In a submission to Parliament's Portfolio Committee on Public Service and Administration, Corruption Watch says the establishment of the anti-corruption bureau is necessary in the fight against corruption.
"We are gravely disappointed that instead of re-thinking the formulation of the provisions that created the anti-corruption bureau, the anti-corruption bureau has been scrapped altogether and replaced with a unit that, in essence, is responsible for technical support," reads Corruption Watch's 24-page submission.
The aim of the bill is to establish a uniform, efficient and ethical, system of public administration in all three spheres of government and to address concerns raised by citizens, in numerous auditor-general reports and by other state entities.
During deliberations on the bill, Sisulu's department removed reference to the anti-corruption bureau and instead made provision for a public administration ethics, integrity and disciplinary technical assistance unit. Corruption Watch says that does not go far enough in the fight against corruption.
The Cosatu watchdog says the public administration ethics, integrity and disciplinary technical assistance unit's powers are watered down compared to those of the anti-corruption bureau and that it will not be effective in tackling corruption-related misconduct in the public service.
Corruption Watch says the excising of provision for an anti-corruption bureau and replacing it with a technical assistance unit with fewer powers was unnecessary.
Sisulu defended the planned integrity-technical assistance unit, saying it would deal with a variety of disciplinary and ethical-conduct cases as the government had no expertise to deal with most cases and was unable to immediately apply corrective measures while officials sat on paid suspension for years at taxpayers' expense.
One of Cosatu's largest affiliates, the National Education, Health and Allied Workers' Union, supports the establishment of the public administration ethics, integrity and disciplinary technical assistance unit, which it says will deal with corruption and misconduct and co-operate with other institutions and state organs.
This week President Jacob Zuma released his government's Twenty-Year Review of South Africa's progress since 1994.
It concedes that corruption impedes service delivery and undermines public confidence in the state and it says that graft is partly a symptom of weak management and operations systems, which create space for graft to thrive.
"While actual levels of corruption are difficult to measure, there is a general consensus that corruption poses a serious threat to many of the gains that have been made since 1994," the review states.
However, it also says an increase in perceptions of corruption does not necessarily mean that corruption has increased.
"It could mean that more incidents of corruption are being exposed, thereby increasing public awareness," says the review.
But the government also agrees that "perceptions of corruption are sufficiently high to impact adversely on public confidence in the state and strong efforts are needed to tackle this issue".
Corruption Watch says it is also unhappy with the Public Service and Administration Department's removal of compulsory "cooling-off" periods for public officials before they can enter the private sector.
The watchdog wants these sections reinstated.
It says "cooling-off" periods to curb the "revolving door" phenomenon of public servants securing well-paid jobs in private companies to which they may have awarded lucrative contracts while on the government payroll, undermine the integrity of the state.
loyiso.sidimba@inl.co.za
See Page 16
THE TRADE union federation Cosatu's Corruption Watch group wants Public Service and Administration Minister Lindiwe Sisulu to reintroduce the proposed anti-corruption bureau that has been removed from the Public Administration Management Bill.
]]></text></news-item>