<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRV-S5N1-JD34-V283"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>LETTERS</title><source>Sunday Age (Melbourne, Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Act on blockade
It is fair to assume that behind the continued attacks on the environment/environmental activists and the resulting expansion of "Joh Bjelke-Petersen-style move-on" powers is pure right-wing ideology ("Move-on bill likely to become law", 9/3).
However, the event that comes immediately to mind as having caused the most significant civil disruption is the unrelenting blockade of the East Melbourne abortion clinic.
Since 1972, the participants and organisers of this "protest" have been intimidating and obstructing people attempting to go about their private business of either providing or seeking lawful, professional healthcare. In 2001 a security guard was murdered by a member of these so-called "right-to-lifers".
It is long past time that this and similar blockades of similar clinics all around the state were "moved on", and I expect to see this done as a matter of priority if this legislation is to be anything more than a blatant and specific attack upon environmentalists, and anyone who wants to peacefully protest against this government.
Michelle Goldsmith, Eaglehawk
Rewarding neglect?
Greg Garde, president of VCAT, believes the tribunal gives everyone a fair go (Opinion, 9/3). As someone who has spent many days at the tribunal over the past two years fighting a powerful and politically influential developer, I beg to differ. At the very least, the scales are weighted against objectors who cannot afford to employ an SC and barristers and "independent" expert witnesses to spout the line on behalf of the developer.
A recent decision to allow the demolition of an 1854 heritage hotel in Williamstown is one example where there were just as many planning reasons to retain, as there were to demolish, the building. The hotel deteriorated because the owner failed to carry out basic maintenance to keep out the rain. Yet the developer is rewarded for this neglect and allowed to replace the heritage hotel with six storeys of nondescript apartments.
Val Green, Williamstown
Get baking, people
Is VCAT really a level playing field when developers, especially with industry or multinational backing, can engage Queen's counsels and other highly paid experts while communities have to resort to lamington drives to fund even limited representation. Furthermore, developers can keep coming back time and again with virtually the same application until they wear down community opposition.
Maldon, designated Australia's first notable town by the National Trust, is again having to mobilise its resources to fight off a proposal for 24 MCG-size chicken sheds on the pristine Baringhup plains. The application will undoubtedly end up at VCAT. It's time the legislation governing VCAT was examined to ensure genuine procedural fairness, or perhaps the government should consider a line of funding to give communities a more equal voice. Otherwise it seems that all small communities can do is get baking.
Deanna Buck, Maldon
Risky business
The announcement that the new environmental workforce for 18-25 year olds - the "green army" - will not be covered by any workers' compensation scheme is extremely worrying ("Tony Abbott's green army enlisting now", 2/3).
These young workers will undertake heavy manual labour including clearing local creeks and waterways, fencing and tree planting - work that carries a high level of physical risk.
If state and federal governments are serious about providing these young workers with a fair and reasonable opportunity to join the workforce, they should work together to provide them with the same workplace injury protection as other employees.
Rachael James, Slater & Gordon
Fighting for rights
The article "Bikies in illegal worker scandal" (2/3) reported incorrectly that the CFMEU turns a blind eye to the issue of Chinese workers employed unlawfully as plasterers.
We have expended considerable resources to gain the trust of Chinese workers to stop their exploitation. We have secured backpay to the tune of millions of dollars and have even been fined by the Fair Work Building Commission for doing so.
We have campaigned against 457 visas because we believe all workers should have the same rights and we want more apprenticeships for young people who are missing out on opportunities. Yet the Abbott government has just reopened a visa loophole enabling employers to hire an unlimited number of foreign workers. This runs counter to what Australians expect from their government.
Dave Noonan, CFMEU
Show some humility
I do wish Gina Rinehart would shut up about Australians needing to learn to "work hard". It is so hypocritical coming from one who became wealthy from an inheritance and has always had access to the best healthcare and education. I am happy to pay more taxes to help support those who have a disability or health problems or come from a disadvantaged background, being grateful to not have experienced any of these circumstances. People do not choose to have any of these difficulties and you injure them further with your insults. It is time we looked at cutting the schemes that advantage the wealthy to fund much-needed improvements to welfare, health and education. I suggest we start with negative gearing, assets testing for pensions and stop subsidising Rinehart's massive mining profits.
Sarah Wilson, Mount Waverley
Crack down on all cheats
In a morally sound system, real need creates a real entitlement. So Ms Rinehart is wrong to deride all welfare recipients. She may be justified in targeting people who cheat on welfare, but she would then have to target tax cheats. I suggest she encourage Tony Abbott to equip Centrelink and the Tax Office to pursue cheats of both persuasions.
Gavan O'Farrell, Oakleigh
Just say no
As a taxpayer I demand that schools be free of covert evangelism. Teach critical thinking on matters of social justice and human relationships; teach empathy, philosophy and ethics; teach comparative religion; teach real science, not the nonsense that is "intelligent design"; and teach that the body is beautiful and that guilt-free sexual exploration is a healthy and necessary part of adolescence.
Christian missionaries who claim the right to indoctrinate our children have no place in government schools. It is unconscionable to give them access. Minister Martin Dixon, in their own words: "Just say NO!"
Murray Barson, Hurstbridge
Pure cost-cutting
The article "Performance pay haunts teachers" (9/3) is on the money - the draft is but a version of "performance pay". The real question is "why would the government want performance pay"? There is no evidence to suggest it leads to better outcomes for students - quite the reverse. The answer, of course, is money and this is obvious when one looks closely at the draft.
The emphasis is placed squarely on "performance" with an array of hurdles for teachers to jump every year. Nothing is said about how the government will fund the "development" of teachers. It is quite clear that this is nothing more than a cost-cutting attempt by the Napthine government.
Judith Crotty, Dandenong North
Happy families
I am pleased Sunday's sports section was a liftout so I could read it at the same time as my wife read the news section. It is the way we'd been reading The Age for years before it became compact. Is it too much to ask that in the new format the Sports section be a liftout every day?
Tony Satospirito, Camberwell
]]></text></news-item>