<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRV-S2S1-JD34-V15F"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Creating deals in an artistic world</title><source>Sunday Age (Melbourne, Australia)</source><author>Andrew Taylor and Fiona Gruber</author><text><![CDATA[Is arts sponsorship a moral issue? Andrew Taylor and Fiona Gruber report.
Money might make the world go round, but it has sent the Biennale of Sydney spinning out of control ahead of its opening this week.
Biennale chairman Luca Belgiorno-Nettis quit and the event lost major sponsor Transfield following a growing boycott of artists angered by the company's links to the offshore processing of asylum seekers, which they regard as morally wrong.
Communications Minister Malcolm Turnbull expressed astonishment at the "sheer vicious ingratitude" of the artists. Arts Minister George Brandis said it was "fine for artists to make political statements" but the views expressed on this occasion were "irrational". The Biennale board had capitulated "to the blackmail effectively of a small number of artists", he added.
Asked if it was appropriate for an organisation to refuse sponsorship from a tobacco company on political grounds, Senator Brandis told ABC radio: "I don't think that arts companies should reject bona fide sponsorship from commercially sound, prospective partners on political grounds - I don't."
That approach is echoed by the Australian Chamber Orchestra, which counts Transfield as a major sponsor and Luca's brother, Guido Belgiorno-Nettis, as its chairman.
The ACO's general manager, Timothy Calnin, said the orchestra would only deal with sponsors that had a pristine legal record. "We'd never enter ito a sponsorship relationship with a company that has broken the law," he said.
But he said the ACO would not reconsider its relationship with Transfield, despite its link to the controversial offshore detention centres on Manus Island and Nauru.
"Sponsors don't walk towards you. You have to go chasing after them," he said. "We're always the ones that initiate the relationship with sponsors."
The artists' revolt against Transfield has thrown a spotlight on the behaviour of other corporate sponsors of the arts. But in today's straitened times, can artists and cultural organisations afford to pick and choose who sponsors them?
The Star casino runs a legal operation even if its gambling business causes misery to gambling addicts and their families. Yet there was barely a peep of protest when the Sydney Festival secured a sponsorship deal believed to be worth more than $2 million with the gambling palace. There were few murmurs of dissent when James Packer and Crown Resorts Foundation each pledged $30 million over 10 years to the Sydney Arts Fund.
The ethics of sponsorship change over time. It seems inconceivable to have a tobacco company sponsoring sports and the arts, yet Benson & Hedges were high-profile funders of cricket and the Australian Ballet until the late 1980s.
Fast food and alcohol sponsorship of sport, as well as arts, could well go the way of tobacco, as health tops the agenda for change alongside concerns about the environment and human rights.
It is also worth noting that Transfield's sponsorship of the Biennale was not just a munificent handout by an indulgent corporation, but a carefully thought-out brand management strategy to win community respect and influence.
Mining giant Rio Tito is a generous sponsor of the arts in Western Australia where it is the principal partner of Black Swan Theatre Company and sponsors the Perth Festival to the tune of more than $1 million. Last year, Rio Tito signed a three-year deal to fund the Pilbara Arts Program, supporting indigenous artists, and deals with the Museum of Contemporary Art Australia to support its new Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander program as well as a partnership with the National Gallery of Australia.
But the company has a dubious environmental reputation, especially at the Grasberg gold and copper mine in the Indonesian province of Papua. The Norwegian government pension fund divested itself of $US855 million ($947 million) of Rio Tito shares in 2008 over the destruction and poisoning of the area around the mine.
Oil and gas company Satos, which has a $1.5 million sponsorship deal with the Queensland Art Gallery and Gallery of Modern Art has come under fire recently from environmental activists Generation Alpha over serious contamination of ground water due to its fracking operations in the Pilliga Forest.
In Britain and the United States too, there have been several well-publicised divorces between corporate sponsors and arts organisations over environmental issues.
But it is unfair to paint a picture of companies sponsoring the arts to launder dirty reputations.
The chief executive of Creative Partnerships Australia, Fiona Menzies, said most business funding comes from a genuine engagement with the arts and is not corporate whitewashing. "Don't demonise corporate sponsorship over a much bigger and more complex picture," she said.
The executive director of the Arts Law Centre, Robyn Ayres, said arts organisations needed a framework of ethical considerations to help guide decision-making on what help it should take and if it would conflict with its goals and values.
"If there was an industry-wide set of guidelines, hopefully the government would realise the importance of this issue to the arts industry; it would be harder to dismiss," she said.
But ethics are subjective and quite political, said Dr Ben Neville, a senior lecturer at Melbourne University's Faculty of Business and Ethics.
"Many organisations already do have a code of ethics, but again, what you ban depends on consensus. In the case of tobacco, you might get 90 per cent agreeing; in the case of offshore detention centres, you may get 50 per cent."
]]></text></news-item>