<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRV-S9Y1-F0NV-F07P"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Obituaries - Sunday, March 16, 2014</title><source>The Register-Herald (Beckley, West Virginia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ROCK VIEW - Mary Lunda Johnson Brooks, 82, of Rock View passed from death unto life Friday, March 14, 2014, at Bowers Hospice House in Beckley following a long illness.
Born June 23, 1931, she was the daughter of the late Paul and Jane Stewart Johnson of Rock View.
Mary was a graduate of Pineville High School and attended Concord College. She was a member of the Rock Castle Baptist Church, was a former Sunday School teacher and member of the Lael Bible class. She loved her family, flowers, hummingbirds and visiting with people.
Survivors include her husband, David L. Brooks of Rock View.
5 daughters, Linda Glander and her husband, Thorne, of Knoxville, TN; Kati Walls and her husband, Stephen, of Rock View; Susie Ellison and her husband, Wayne, of Rock View; Paula Brooks and her husband, Danny, of Jesse; Laura Burdette and her husband, Danny, of Beckley.
9 grandchildren, David Boggs of Freemont, CA; Mary Beth Boggs of Raleigh, NC; Megan Jane Boggs of Beckley; Zach Cook of Beckley; Katie Hill of Morgantown; Amie Mullens and her husband, Chris, of Oceana; Samuel Toler of Beckley; Drew Hill of Auburn, AL; and Hannah Walls of Rock View. 2 stepgrandchildren, Jonathan Brooks of Jesse and Jewell LaClaire of Moneta, VA. 2 great-grandchildren: Claire Mullens of Oceana, and Donovan Cook of Ansted. A stepgreat-grandchild Jillian Baird of South Hill, VA.
A brother, Jimmy Johnson and his wife, Betty, of Rock View.
A sister, Gayle Wright and her husband, Joe, of Rock View.
Sister-in-law, Garnette Brooks of McGraws.
Mary is also survived by many aunts, uncles, nieces, nephews, cousins, friends and neighbors.
A celebration of Mary's life will be held at 1 p.m. Monday, March 17, 2014, at the Rock Castle Baptist Church with the Rev. Evan Arkell and Rev. Doc Adkins officiating.
Burial will follow at Palm Memorial Gardens, Matheny.
Family will serve as pallbearers.
The family will receive friends from 4 to 6 p.m. Sunday, March 16, 2014, in the Calfee Funeral Service Chapel, Pineville.
In lieu of flowers, memorial contributions may be made to Bowers Hospice House, 454 Cranberry Drive, Beckley, West Virginia 25801.
Online guest book may be signed at www.calfeefuneralservice.com.
Calfee Funeral and Cremation Service of Pineville is serving the Brooks family.
Alfred Lee 'Pluto' Davis
LASHMEET - Alfred Lee "Pluto" Davis, 95, of Lashmeet, died Friday, March 14, 2014.
Arrangements by Bailey-Kirk Funeral Home in Princeton.
Rev. A.R. 'Jill' Dishner
ROCK - The Rev. A.R. "Jill" Dishner, 84, of Rock, died Saturday, March 15, 2014.
Arrangements by Bailey-Kirk Funeral Home in Princeton.
James Lawrence Holesapple
SECOND CREEK - James Lawrence Holesapple, 89, of Second Creek, passed away Friday, March 14, 2014.
Wallace & Wallace Funeral Home in Ronceverte is in charge of arrangements, which are incomplete at this time.
Verda Magalene Knight
PEARISBURG, Va. - Verda Magalene Knight, 90, of Pearisburg, Va., formerly of Rock Camp, passed away Friday, March 14, 2014.
Arrangements are incomplete at Broyles-Shrewsbury Funeral Home, Peterstown.
Donald Ray Lemon
TRUE - Donald Ray Lemon, 63, of True passed away Friday, March 14, 2014.
Arrangements have been entrusted to the Ronald Meadows Funeral Parlors in Hinton.
Calvin Cecil Lemons
ASBURY - Calvin Cecil Lemons, 88, of Asbury, passed away Thursday, March 13, 2014.
Services will be at 2 p.m. Sunday, March 16, at Morgan Funeral Home in Lewisburg with the Rev. Ron Miller and Pastor Emory Hanna officiating. Friends may call from 6 to 8 p.m. Saturday, March 15, and one hour prior to services Sunday at the funeral home. Burial will follow at Wallace Memorial Cemetery at Clintonville.
Morgan Funeral Home in Lewisburg is in charge of arrangements.
Melissa Croy Long
LINDSIDE - Melissa Croy Long, 54, of Lindside, passed away Saturday, March 15, 2014.
Arrangements are incomplete at Broyles-Shrewsbury Funeral Home, Peterstown.
Emmitt 'Gizmo' Arthur Massey
SETH - Emmitt "Gizmo" Arthur Massey, 91, of Seth, died Friday, March 14, 2014.
Funeral services will be at 1 p.m. Monday, March 17, in the Armstrong Funeral Home, Whitesville, with Pastor Jr. Perdue and Roger Halstead. Interment is in Pineview Cemetery, Orgas. Visitation will be two hours before the service at the funeral home.
Coy McKinney Jr.
Coy McKinney Jr., 74, of Sophia, died Friday, March 14, 2014.
Private online condolences, floral tributes, and other expressions of sympathy may be directed to the family via our guestbook at www.roseandquesenberry.net.
Arrangements are by Rose and Quesenberry Funeral Home, 1901 S. Kanawha St., Beckley.
Barbara Jean Meadows
Barbara Jean Meadows, 76, of Beaver, passed away Friday, March 14, 2014.
Arrangement pending with Blue Ridge Funeral Home and Cremations, 5251 Robert C. Byrd Drive in Prosperity.
William Kyle 'Billy' Owens
William Kyle "Billy" Owens, age 62, of Sophia, went home to be with the Lord on Thursday, March 13, 2014, at the Bowers Hospice House in Beckley with his family by his side. Romans 8:28 "And we know that all things work together for good to them that love God, to them who are called according to his purpose."
Born on May 28, 1951, in Welch, W.Va., he was the son of the late Joseph Ben Owens and Clara Alberty Owens. Though born in Welch, he spent most of his childhood in Stotesbury and attended Mark Twain High School.
He was a coal miner, and a member of the UMWA, local district #17. He was disabled in 2007.
Billy enjoyed fishing on his boat with family and friends, watching westerns, racing, and his beloved "West Virginia Mountaineers." Recently he became a member of the Truth Assembly Ministries. He was very proud that he gave his life to the Lord. The family wishes to thank each and every one of you for your thoughts and prayers.
Billy was preceded in death by his parents, Joseph and Clara Owens, and by two brothers, Franklin and Jimmie Owens.
On December 22, 1972, he married Brenda Rutherford Owens, and they just celebrated their 42nd anniversary. They have three children, Donna Owens and her companion Aaron Asbury of Sophia, Michelle Owens and her companion Darrell Cantley of Pulaski, Tenn., and Kevin Owens and his companion Lorrie Ayers of Sophia. Billy also has three granddaughters, Brianna Wilson of Lake Park, Ga., Samantha Robertson of Sophia, and Savannah Lilly of Pulaski, Tenn.; two grandsons, Justin Reed of Pulaski, Va., and Travis K. Owens of Pulaski, Tenn.; and one great-grandson, Bryson Reed of Pulaski, Va.
He is survived by one brother, Joseph Owens and his wife Sharon of Coal City; four sisters, Janell Meadows of Columbus, Ga., Juanita Lilly and her husband Pete of Landover, Md., Trula Burgess and her companion Dennis Adkins of Beckley, and Susie Owens and her companion Mike Wyco of Beaver. Billy had many nieces and nephews, and one who was close to his heart, Jenny Lynn Owens Welch and her husband Terry of Mabscott.
Funeral services will be conducted at the Rose and Quesenberry Peace Chapel in Beckley on Wednesday, March 18, 2014, at 8 p.m., with Rev. Hibbard Hatfield officiating.
Friends may visit with the family from 6 to 8 p.m. on Wednesday at the funeral home.
Pallbearers will be Darrell Cantley, Aaron Asbury, Dennis Adkins, Gene Perkins, Kevin Owens. Honorary pallbearers will be Travis Owens and Justin Reed.
Private entombment will follow at Blue Ridge Memorial Gardens Mausoleum at Prosperity, W.Va., on Thursday morning.
In lieu of flowers, donations of sympathy may be made to the Bowers Hospice House, 454 Cranberry Drive, Beckley, WV, in memory of Mr. Owens.
Arrangements are by Rose and Quesenberry Funeral Home, 1901 South Kanawha Street, Beckley.
Carl E. Radford
PRINCETON - Carl Edward Radford, 70, of Princeton passed away on Thursday, March 13, 2014, in a Princeton hospital following a short illness.
Born September 10, 1943, in Welch, he was the son of the late Byrd James and Marguerite Ellen Hicks Radford.
Carl loved talking and being with people. He enjoyed his videos and music.
In addition to his parents he is also preceded in death by two sisters, Donna Sue Radford and Nancy Lee Billings; and one brother, David Ray Radford.
Those left to cherish his memory include his sister, Helen Ruth McKinney and her husband, Ronnie, of Princeton; brother, Eugene Radford and his wife, Mary, of Crab Orchard; a niece Lisa Duffy and her husband, Joseph, of Princeton, whom he made his home with; a nephew Howard Riley McKinney of Tennessee; brother-in-law, T.D. Billings, and family; and other nieces and nephews.
Committal services and burial will be 1 p.m. Monday, March 17, 2014, at Sunset Memorial Park Mausoleum B, Beckley, with Pastor Duane Pease officiating.
Friends may call from 11 a.m. to 12 noon Monday at the funeral home.
Those wishing to attend the committal service are asked to meet at the funeral home by 12 noon for a procession to the cemetery.
Pallbearers will be Michael Dickens, Eric Billings, Bo Billings, Jerry Wayne Dickens, and other family members.
Online condolences may be expressed to the family at www.tankersleyfh.com.
The family of Carl Edward is being cared for by Tankersley Funeral Home, Mullens.
Charles Jefferson Ramsey
Charles Jefferson Ramsey, 89, died Saturday, March 15, 2014.
The Ronald Meadows Funeral Parlors in Hinton is serving the Ramsey family.
Kathern Wood Reeves
Kathern Wood Reeves went to be with her Lord on Friday, March 14, 2014. Kathern was the daughter of the late William Mack and JoAnna Frances (Sears) Bragg and spent her childhood years in Raleigh County.
As a child, her best playmate was her loving sister, Wanda, with whom she spent many years roaming the hills and woods playing make believe. Her childhood was cut short when her mother passed away and she along with Wanda had to take over running of the household. She was a homemaker through her teenage years.
In 1944 she married George Matthew Wood and their union lasted 39 happy years until his death in 1987. Together they raised four children as well as a host of injured birds, rescued tadpoles, stray dogs, and even once a brood of freshly hatched (in the house) praying mantises. In this way Kathern taught her children a love of nature and all living things.
Most importantly she spent her lifetime in Christian service to her family, her church, and her community. Her family has often remarked that it was because of Kathern's dedication to God that now four generations are following in her footsteps of service to God and family.
Although often short on funds, Kathern was never short on imagination and taught her four children to celebrate life's little moments. No birthday or holiday ever passed without a party or special meal and on Saturday nights she often gathered the family around the TV for popcorn and a movie together.
Later in life, Kathern married the Reverend Marvin G. Reeves. Marvin served as pastor of the Pleasant View Church of the Brethren where she was his faithful companion and co-worker. Kathern and Marvin were blessed with 19 happy years of marriage.
She was a member of the Crab Orchard Church of the Brethren for over 50 years where she sang in choir, taught Sunday and Bible School, and was a faithful attendee.
For the past two years, Kathern was a resident of Raleigh Rehab Center where she received diligent and loving care. She formed a special bond with one worker, Joy Byrd.
In addition to her parents and husbands, she was preceded In death by a daughter, Brenda Carol Wood; sisters, Nora Blair, Wanda Coleman, and Ann Goodson; and a brother, Roy Bragg.
Those left to carry on her legacy include her four children, Jeannie Cummings and husband Eric of Prosperity, George F. Wood of Nashville, TN, Kathy Zirckel Hicks and husband Mike of Cool Ridge, and Peggy Smith of Marion, NC; 10 grandchildren, 19 great-grandchildren, and an ever growing number of great-great-grandkids.
A celebration of Kathern's life will be conducted at 11 a.m. Tuesday, March 18, 2014, at the Crab Orchard Church of the Brethren with Rev. Michael King and Kathern's nephew, Minister Tommy Lilly, officiating.
The gentlemen having the honor of serving as pallbearers are nephew, Donzei Goodson, and grandsons, Jeffrey Cummings, Matthew Koesy-Wood, Steven Hosey, and John Hosey.
Friends may gather with the family on Monday evening beginning at 6 p.m. and lasting until 8 p.m. at the Blue Ridge Funeral Home Chapel in Prosperity and a Celebration of life led by Russ Coulter and Connie Runion. Everyone who attends will have the opportunity to share stories and testimonies reflecting on Kathern's life.
In lieu of flowers those wishing to make a donation in the memory of Kathern may do so at Alzheimer's Foundation of America, 322 Eighth Ave., 7th fl., New York, NY 10001.
Online condolences may be made to her family by visiting this obituary online at www.blueridgefuneralhome.com.
Arrangements with Blue Ridge Funeral Home and Cremations, 5251 Robert C. Byrd Drive in Prosperity.
William Clarence Shrewsberry
William Clarence Shrewsberry, age 71, of Barkers Ridge, WV, passed away at the Raleigh General Hospital in Beckley on Thursday, March 13, 2014.
Born on February 3, 1943, at Bud, he was the son of the late William Ward Shrewsberry and Ruth Ilene Thornton Shrewsberry.
Mr. Shrewsberry was a retired employee of the Department of Highways in Wyoming County. He was a member of the Mountaineer Baptist Church at Barkers Ridge, WV.
Mr. Shrewsberry was preceded in death by his wife, Bobbie Jean Shrewsberry, a son Eddie Dean Shrewsberry, a grandson, Dustin Daniel Shrewsberry, and a sister Elizabeth Mae Robinson.
Survivors include three sons, David Monroe Shrewsberry and his wife Lena Gail of Barkers Ridge, Clarence Shrewsberry Junior and his wife Marie Ann of Barkers Ridge, and Toby Lee Shrewsberry of Barkers Ridge. One daughter, Pamela Regina Osborne and her late husband Jeff Osborne of Rainelle, nineteen grandchildren, fifteen great-grandchildren also survive.
Funeral services will be conducted at the Mountaineer Baptist Church at Barkers Ridge, WV, on Monday, March 17, 2014, at 2 p.m. with Rev. Charles A. McKinney Jr. officiating. Burial will follow at the Thomas Wayne Shrewsberry Cemetery at Barkers Ridge, WV. Friends may visit with the family from 6 to 9 p.m. on Sunday at the church. Pallbearers will be family members and friends.
Private online condolences, floral tributes, and other expressions of sympathy may be directed to the family via our guestbook at www.roseandquesenberry.net.
Arrangements are by Rose and Quesenberry Funeral Home, 1901 South Kanawha Street, Beckley, WV.
]]></text></news-item>