<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRV-S5N1-JD34-V285"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>No place at work for exploitation</title><source>Sunday Age (Melbourne, Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The exploitation of workers is most often seen as a Third World problem. The picture that is most often presented in the First World is of men and women employed by multinationals in sweatshops working dangerously long hours in unsafe conditions for a meagre wage on a product that is then sold on Western shelves for a thousand times the cost of production.
This deplorable abuse and manipulation of the vulnerable for profit is quite rightly condemned. Yet it also occurs near home, indeed, in our own city.
The Sunday Age today continues its reporting of a home-grown aspect of the exploitation of foreign workers. It is the use of illegal labour from China in the construction industry, notably in plastering. Some of Melbourne's more prominent new buildings are sites of such labour: the Royal Children's Hospital and the Docklands headquarters of Medibank Private.
The builders on both projects, Bovis Lend Lease and Brookfield Multiplex respectively, used subcontractors who employed cheap Chinese workers whose status to do such work as plastering is often fraudulent or in breach of industry awards and requirements. Last week, The Sunday Age revealed that there were links showing infiltration of the plastering industry by motorcycle gangs seeking to rort the system.
We have been provided with examples of one such rort where Chinese workers swap documentation to enter building sites, and then receive half the award rate of $35 an hour. Other Chinese labourers are required to work 60 hours a week and are paid for only the normal 36-hour week.
The exploitation of foreign workers is not new. More than a decade ago, a raid was conducted on a Port Melbourne building site involving Chinese plasterers and visa irregularities. The continued practice sadly cements the perception that if it has been occurring for so long then obviously it is OK.
The CFMEU has known of "unscrupulous employers taking advantage of the workers' visa status, lack of knowledge of their rights, their pay and conditions. We have expended considerable resources to communicate with and gain the trust of Chinese workers in order to stop their exploitation."
It cites the case of a plastering firm that employed more than 100 Chinese workers on temporary visas. "Many had tourist visas with no working rights in Australia while others were working in breach of their visa conditions and some were over-stayers. None spoke English, all were being paid well below the award, were given an ABN and forced to work as sham contractors."
The industry's peak body, the Association of Wall and Ceiling Industries, also says exploitation is widespread. Yet it continues.
Fair Work Building and Construction concedes it does not have the power to raid "detain, arrest or deport people", while the Department of Immigration from 2011 to 2013 issued about 200 illegal-worker notices to employers in this state, without a single prosecution.
Notwithstanding the human cost of this rorting, there is an economic cost and a concomitant rending in the legal framework. The honest subcontractors who pay proper rates, who do everything by the book, are put at a disadvantage with which they cannot compete. Rogue contractors who collapse, simply reinvent themselves under a different company name and continue to ply their trade.
The association has called on the state government to establish a system of licensing and registration for plasterers. We concur. This is an underbelly of the building industry that must be brought ito the light. While the federal government puts the spotlight on workplace reform and union corruption, it is also incumbent on governments to rid the economy of worker exploitation.
Plastering is a good place to start.
]]></text></news-item>