<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRV-S3H1-JC8S-C3WT"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Programme summary of Pakistan's AVT Khyber News 1600 gmt 15 March 14</title><source>BBC Monitoring South Asia - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The following is a summary of the 1600 gmt bulletin consisting of news from Pakistan's Federally Administered Tribal Areas (FATA), aired by Islamabad-based private Pakistani television news channel AVT Khyber News on 15 March.
A. News Headline
B. News in details
1. Unknown armed men have kidnapped at least 18 persons from Badhbir area of Peshawar. Police have started search operation after the incident; no arrest came into effect so far. Presenter-read report on video showing footage of security forces.
2. At least nine persons were killed and 12 are critically injured in blast near Sarband area of Peshawar. Video showing footage of the blast site.
3. Nearly 11 persons (who were injured in Sarband blast) were discharged from the hospital after medical treatment; their relatives have complained about lack of health services in the hospital. Presenter-read report on video showing footage of the injured in hospital.
4. Taleban's committee members met with Interior Minister Chaudhry Nisar Ali Khan in Islamabad; discussed peace talks process; Nisar has lauded the sincere efforts of the committee; said government is also sincere in holding peace talks with Taleban. Presenter-read report on video showing archive footage of the committee members and Nisar.
5. Chief of Army Staff General Raheel Sharif has lauded the sacrifices rendered by Pakistan Army for the defense of the country. He visited to Gujaranwala Garrison, addressing to army personnel, he said that high standard of training professionalism and commitment to serve the motherland has been Pakistan's army hallmark; paid rich tributes to army personnel who embraced martyrdom in war on terror. Presenter-read report on video showing footage of COAS was addressing to army personnel.
6. Defence Minister Khwaja Asif has said that improvement in the country's economy will lead to the regional peace. Presenter read-report on video showing footage of Asif was talking to media.
7. Khyber News reporter, Wahidur Rahman's father Khalilur Rehman passed away. Video showing footage of the people were offering prayers for his soul.
8. Khyber Pakhtunkhwa chief minister took notice of the killing of Sikh Narjeed in Shabqadar, and ordered the concerned authorities to arrest the accused within three days. Presenter read-report on video showing footage of the Sikh Narjeed shop.
9. Sehat Ka Insaf (justice for health) programme was successfully completed in Peshawar. At least 4,000 polio teams have participated in the campaign; nearly 400,000 children were administered polio drops; section 144 remained imposed during the campaign. Presenter-read report on video showing footage of children were administered polio drops.
10. The death toll has reached to 11 in Jinnah Road blast. Report of Khyber News correspondent in Karachi, Jabbir Shah, he said that several vehicles and buildings were badly damaged; 35 persons got injured in which eight persons are in critical conditions; Ahrarul Hind group has claimed the responsibility; locals have asked the government for compensation for the blast victims. Video showing footage of the blast site.
11. Commercials
12. Adviser to PM on National Affairs, Sartaj Aziz has said that US did not announce to stop drone attacks in Pakistan. Presenter- read report on video showing footage of Aziz was talking to media.
13. Security forces have arrested at least 120 militants during their search operation in Karachi; heavy weapons were recovered from their possessions. Presenter- read report on video showing footage of security forces and their vehicles.
14. Sindh Rangers Chief Rizwan Akhtar has claimed that terrorists got full political support in Layari area Karachi. It is the need of the hour that security forces should disclose that which political party supports terrorists; and why security forces are not taking concert steps against them. Video showing footage of Akhtar meeting with PM.
15. Patients are faced with several problems due to non-availability of health facilities in drought hit region Tharparker. Report of Khyber News correspondent in Tarparker, Naimat Zada; he said risky diseases erupted in the region; no medicines in hospitals; no doctors; patients who were interviewed asked the government to pay attention towards their problems. Video showing footage of locals being interviewed.
16. Commercials
17. Locals of Charsadda have set up relief camps for the victims of Tharparker; donated 60,000 rupees to the relief fund. Presenter-read report on video showing footage of the camp.
18. Schools teachers staged protest over delay in their salaries for the last seven months in Dir. Report of Khyber News correspondent in Dir, Muhammad Israr, he said protesting teachers blocked the main road for three hours; urged the authorities to immediately provide their salaries. Report on protest footage.
19. The Government Postgraduate Girls College has initiated polio campaign in Kohat. On this occasion teachers and students also shed light on the importance of plantation. Video showing footage of teachers being interviewed.
20. Large number of visitors came for Snow festival in Malamjabba. Visitors who were interviewed said they have enjoyed the festival. Video showing footage of the visitors being interviewed.
21. Musical show held in Snow festival in Malamjabba. Live report of Khyber News correspondent in Malamjabba, Saeedur Rehman, people who were interviewed said; they said peace restored in the region; enjoying the show; strict security arrangements were taken during the show. Video showing footage of the musical show.
22. Commercials
23. Traffic problems were increased due to illegal encroachments in Mardan. Locals have asked the government to remove illegal encroachments in the city. Video showing footage of the locals being interviewed.
24. People in Nilaoray are facing problems due to poor and dilapidated condition of the main road in the region. Report of Khyber News correspondent in Shangla, Khalid Khan, locals said the government does not take notice of the problem; demanded of the government to reconstruct the road to facilitate them. Video showing footage of the road.
25. Poor audio quality
26. Sports
[End of bulletin]
Duration; 58 minutes
Source: AVT Khyber TV, Islamabad, in Pashto 1600gmt 15 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>