<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRV-SBK1-JCBD-D2HR"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>CBI CHIEF WARNS: THIS BUDGET IS MAKE OR BREAK</title><source>MAIL ON SUNDAY (London)</source><author>BY VICKI OWEN</author><text><![CDATA[BRITAIN'S most senior business leader has warned that the recovery could be derailed if Chancellor George Osborne fails to encourage investment in Wednesday's Budget.
John Cridland, director general of the CBI, said the Budget was a make or break moment for the economy, with tax reliefs to encourage investment an urgent priority.
Speaking to The Mail on Sunday, he declared: We are at the early stages of a vital but not inevitable rebalancing of the economy. Whether we do this actually depends on whether we choose to do it. There's nothing inevitable about it.
The default position is that we'll continue with an unbalanced growth pattern based on consumption.'
Cridland said that 90 per cent of the economic recovery seen last year was a result of increased consumption and businesses needed encouragement to invest to boost production and exports in particular. His call was echoed in research by accounting giant KPMG, which surveyed 161 medium-sized businesses on their wishes for the Budget.
Almost 20 per cent said tax incentives for investing in plant and machinery would be the single most important measure the Chancellor could introduce. And 21 per cent said they needed more help exporting to overseas markets, while 22 per cent said they would like steps to allow them to put more money in their staff's take-home pay by cutting employers' National Insurance contributions, which could be passed on to workers.
Cridland said the most important step would be to extend the Annual Investment Allowance, which lets businesses offset up to £250,000 on capital investment each year against tax bills. The scheme is due to expire at the end of this year, but he said it should be extended because now was the critical moment to encourage business to invest.
I have spoken about it with the Chancellor and think he was quite interested,' Cridland said, adding he had no inkling whether it would be included in this year's Budget.
The CBI's other key demand is for a freeze on the controversial carbon tax, known as the Carbon Price Floor. Big polluters are charged £9.55 for every ton of carbon they emit and the figures is set to rise steadily over the next five years. The levy is passed on in energy bills, currently at about £5 a year.
Cridland said: The heavy lifting [high cost] at the moment is on British business and it's making us uncompetitive with French and German business. The gap between the [carbon] price in Britain and the price in France and Germany is just getting unbridgeable. I've suggested the Government changes the trajectory of the Carbon Floor Price.'
The CBI says the Government should freeze the UK carbon price from 2015-16, at a cost of £90 million. It is likely to be granted its wish. As reported by The Mail on Sunday in January, industry insiders are convinced the Chancellor will freeze the levy at next year's level of £18.08 a tonne, though some are lobbying for a freeze at the current lower level.
Small business - Page 98
© Mail On Sunday
]]></text></news-item>