<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRW-0FY1-JCTS-G3X1"><date>2014-03-16</date><title></title><source>Huntsville Times (Alabama)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Do not support SB380.
I encourage you, as an elected official, to refrain from voting to repeal the Alabama College and Career Ready Standards, and do what is right for our students by rejecting any attempts to repeal the standards. Please vote against SB380. Strong standards not only benefit our students going to post-secondary institutions or the workforce, but they also strengthen the arts community, where so much of our culture and history is celebrated.
I want to express my ongoing support, on behalf of the fine arts community in Alabama, for Alabama College and Career Ready Standards. While many works in fine art have abstract interpretations, the knowledge and skills needed to create such brilliant works are very concrete and rooted in mathematics and language arts. Accomplished artists know just how important critical thinking, problem solving and reasoning are to the creative process, and all of these skills are emphasized in Alabama College and Career Ready Standards.
Here is an excerpt from an article titled Arts in Research: “I have heard business school deans express concern that when their students first arrive they are interesting but that, by the time they leave, many are homogenized — wanting the same job and motivated by the same life goals. Art school students are interesting when they arrive and typically are even more interesting and actualized when they leave, because the work they are encouraged to do is original to their own person.
Growing bodies of research show a positive relationship between the arts and other academic subjects, so it would be irresponsible to abandon research-based standards that will elevate student growth and achievement across the educational landscape.
I believe that the adoption and implementation of the new, rigorous standards will not only benefit our students in college and the workplace, but also expand Alabama’s community of talented artists.
Timothy P. Walker
Boaz
Kudos to CVS for ending tobacco sales.
The American Cancer Society applauds the bold decision by CVS Caremark to end the sale of cigarettes and other tobacco products and to begin a campaign to protect the health of millions of Americans in our communities by helping them quit smoking and bring down health care costs.
While we have made great progress in the cancer fight, tobacco use remains the single largest preventable cause of disease and premature death, responsible for one in five deaths across the U.S. For every person who dies from a smoking-related disease, 20 more people suffer with at least one serious illness from smoking.
The American Cancer Society and its 3 million volunteers thank CVS CEO Larry Merlo and we encourage all business leaders to take action and work with the American Cancer Society to: limit access to tobacco products in the workplace; create smoke-free workplaces and help employees stop smoking; and work with CEOs Against Cancer to make a positive impact on your business and community.
Ginny Tucker
Birmingham
]]></text></news-item>