<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRW-D0B1-DXDT-60H2"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Ukraine crisis: Crimea voters go to the polls in Russia referendum; Polls open in referendum to decide whether Crimea will join Russia</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Lucy Kinder</author><text><![CDATA[路 Crimea holds referendum on joining Russia 路 Russian troops 'in mainland Ukraine' 路 Nato websites targeted over Crimea stance 路 Ukraine's acting defense minister says 'this is our land'
11.55 The head of EON, Germany's leading power supplier, warned Berlin against "recklessly" damaging ties with Russia over the crisis in Ukraine.
Johannes Teyssen told Der Spiegel that the tensions risked hobbling a fruitful "partnership".
"I don't want to interfere in foreign policy questions but I think that we have exercised very responsible policy toward the east in the last few decades,"
"The build-up of trust and the interlocking of our economies have led to the fact that more than 6,000 German companies are active in Russia."
He said that at the same time, Russian companies had invested heavily in Germany, particularly in the gas sector.
"Through this partnership, our continent has grown more peaceful. That should not be recklessly jeopardised."
11.44 Dr James Summers, director of the Centre for International Law and Human Rights at Lancaster University, said that the referendum could backfire on Russia.
"The referendum in itself violates international law, as it stems from an illegal act, the invasion of the Crimea, which it seeks to legitimise.
"Russia may be using the referendum as a bargaining chip in negotiations, though this may backfire as the vote is so clearly tainted.
"Other neighbouring states will be looking anxiously at what is happening in Crimea"
"They will see that it could also happen to them, and that could work against Russia by turning more former Soviet states away from it and towards the West in the search for allies and support.
11.32 Some more information from Ukraine's acting defence minister Ihor Tenyukh from that Interfax interview. "We are seeing an increase in the number of Russian servicemen in Crimea," he said. "And the Ukrainian armed forces are therefore taking appropriate measures along the southern borders."
He added that every senior Ukrainian officer in Crimea "clearly knows what is to be done depending on the situation".
"Decisions will be taken depending on how events unfold. But let me say once again that this is our land and we will not be leaving it."
11.29 Here is an update from our Foreign Affairs Correspondent Damien McElroy:
"Russian forces have become involved in their first stand-off outside Crimea with Ukrainian troops after seizing a gas distribution facility in Kherson province.
Ukraine deployed its own armed personnel for the first time on Saturday to counter the Russia move but has not dislodged the occupation.
"We are seeing an increase in the number of Russian servicemen in Crimea," said Mr Tenyukh. "And the Ukrainian armed forces are therefore taking appropriate measures along the southern borders."
As many as 130 Russian soldiers are at the site in eastern Ukraine, digging trenches and doing "other engineering work," said Oleh Slobodyan, a spokesman for the Border Guard Service.
11.23 Ukraine news agency Interfax have got some information about Russia's build-up of troops in Crimea- Ukraine's acting defence minister said they now number up to 22,000 servicemen.
He said that under agreements covering the basing of Russia's Black Sea fleet in Crimea, Russia had set a limit of 12,500 for the number of its servicemen in Crimea for 2014.
11.05 The head of Crimea's unrecognised Russian-backed government Sergei Aksyonov
11.01 A woman holds a Russian flag as she casts her ballot during the referendum
11.00 Ukraine's former prime minister, Yulia Tymoshenko has urged the West to unite against Russia.
"This aggressive striving for power with regard to Ukraine represents not only a danger for the Ukrainian state - other parts of eastern Europe are also in danger," she told German daily Der Tagesspiegel.
"Should Putin continue his attack on our country after the annexation of Crimea, I would call on the leaders of the democratic world to use the strongest measures to stop this aggressor."
10.50 Polling stations opened this morning at 8 am local time and will close 12 hours later, at 6 pm GMT
10.40 At the United Nations Russia vetoed a Security Council resolution declaring the referendum illegal, and China, its ally, abstained.
10.37 AP have quotes from voters in Sevastopol, the Crimean capital, where voters apparently lined up outside polling stations before they opened. More than 70 people surged into a polling station within the first 15 minutes of voting.
"Today is an important day for all Crimea, Ukraine and Russia," said voter Manita Meshchina. "I think that people are expecting the majority of people will vote 'yes.' What it means is that people believe and think they need to be with Russia."
"Today is a holiday," said one of them, 66-year-old Vera Sverkunova. Asked how she voted, she broke into a patriotic war song: "I want to go home to Russia. It's been so long since I've seen my mama."
10.34 Good morning. The Crimea region is voting today about whether to demand greater autonomy from Ukraine or split off and seek to join Russia, in a referendum that has been condemned as illegal by the United States and European countries.
Yesterday Ukrainian officials said Russian forces backed by helicopter gunships and armored vehicles had advanced about 6 miles over the Crimean border into another Ukrainian region.
]]></text></news-item>