<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRW-7TB1-JDKC-R4YK"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>(Un)Holy Men in Holy Hell</title><source>Indian Currents</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[India, March 16 -- Holy men are pillar of any religion. Recent years have brought to light many self-styled god men who are less known for their spiritual compassion and humanitarianism and more for their basal instincts, greed, and exploitation of gullible masses. More and more Indian godmen, with worldwide followers running into millions, are now being accused of rape, sexual exploitation, and immoral acts under the garb of religious practices. These (un)holy men's followers include governors, chief ministers, assorted politicians, business tycoons, newspaper magnates, jurists, sportsmen, academics and, yes, even scientists.
After the popular godman known as Asaram Bapu was arrested last year for the alleged sexual assault on a minor girl, the, latest to join the list is Mata Amritanandamayi from Kerala.
It is not that these are the first one's to have been brought to social attention; such incidents have been coming to social notice time and over again. One recalls in recent history many such cases have startled the media and society like the allegation of a foreign writer about Satya Sai Baba, self styled Kerala godman Santosh Madhavan's criminal activities which landed him in jail, and many other similar stories are quite well known to the public by now. From other religious traditions, one recalls the recent book by former nun Jesme of 'Amen' fame and the news that the Roman Catholic Church is seized with the controversy of abuse of children by priests in USA and Europe and its cover up. Largescale children's sexual abuses by priests have been reported in western media. Church officials have taken remedial actions, though not sufficient.
Godmen galore Most recently, Asaram Bapu, with a following of millions across the globe, has landed in a controversy, with a 16-yearold girl student of his gurukul (residential school) alleging that he sexually assaulted her at his Jodhpur ashram in Rajasthan.
The godman had purportedly threatened to eliminate the victim's parents if she revealed the incident to anyone. Later, his son too was arrested on the charges of rape in his 'ashram' in another case.
In 2007, a former member of the Asaram ashram, Raju Chandak, had claimed in an affidavit filed with the police that tantric (black magic) rituals were being performed in the ashrams of Asaram, and that he had personally been witness to Asaram Bapu sexually exploiting women.
In December 2009, Raju Chandak was attacked by two unknown persons with guns in the city of Sabarmati in Gujarat.
The Gujarat police filed an attempt to murder case against Asaram Bapu and two others.
In 2008, a Commission was set up to probe the mysterious death of two children, whose bodies were found on the Sabarmati riverbed after they went missing the same year. Dipesh Vaghela, 10, and Abhishek Vaghela, 11, were cousins studying at Asaram's Gurukul at Motera in Gujarat.
Following a public outcry, the case was handed over to the Crime Investigation Department (CID), which, after a year of probing, filed a complaint of culpable homicide and booked seven sadhaks (religious practitioners) of the ashram. Praful Vaghela, the father of one of the children, believes that the children were killed as a consequence of a tantric ritual.
However, Asaram Bapu is hardly the first Hindu godman to be charged with sexual crimes. In the spring of 2010, Indian media feasted on reports of several swamis allegedly engaged in sexual practices and other forms of wrongdoing across the nation.
A New Delhi-based swami named Bhimanand Ji Maharaj Chitrakootwale was revealed to have run a massive prostitution ring comprising more than 1,000 girls, who "serviced" many politicians and big business men. Another 'guru', Swami Nityananda of Bangalore, was filmed having sex with an actress (he claimed the video was "doctored" in order to frame him). After another similar sex video surfaced, the swami fled his ashram as a fugitive.
Many other 'holy men' have been accused of such crimes as child sexual abuse, sexual exploitation of women, encroaching public property, tax evasion, embezzlement and fraud. These allegations followed the public's revulsion at 'gurus' who have amassed huge wealth and lived luxurious lifestyles.
In 'God's own land' Swamis, or Hindu holy men, are getting a bad reputational all over India due to the unholy acts of some among them. However, "God's own country" Kerala, which is the state with highest literacy in the country, seems to be on the top of the list. Several scandals have broken recently involving 'holy men' and 'gurus' who have committed sexual crimes.
Santosh Madhavan, from Kerala, became popular as Amritha Chaithanya. After founding Shantitheeram Trust in the name of his parents, he was arrested near Kochi on May 18, 2008 on charges of fraud. He has been charged with pedophilia and making videos of sexual misdemeanours with underage girls. On May 20, 2009, he was sentenced to 16 years in prison for molesting two underage girls.
Madhavan's arrest seemed to have opened a can of worms.
Since then the state police have raided the homes of several swamis - Divya Joshi, a self proclaimed sanyasi in Thrissur district, Swamy Thapasyananda, a godman in Panthalam (Pathanamthitta), Swamy Almachaithanya in Kannur district, Matha Prasanna, who runs a 'charitable' trust, and Amma Thaya Mahamaya - both in Kottayam district.
The Supreme Court accorded 57-year-old Swami Premananda a double life sentence. He was convicted of 13 rapes and a murder in his ashram in Tiruchi.
Premananda moved to India in 1984 from Matale in Jaffna. He claims to have discovered his "spiritual powers" at 18 when "a great spiritual vibration entered the prayer room and my white robes slowly turned to orange." With his uncanny resemblance to the Sathya Sai Baba, Premananda's popularity grew in Tiruchy and by 1989 his ashram was sprawled across 150 acres, had branches in 15 countries, and with an international youth wing.
Godwomen now After the turn of fake swamis, now it is their female counterparts' turn to seek media attention. The latest news is that an allegation has been erupted against a swamini, who had amassed wealth worth millions after offering 'bhasmam' which was dried cow dung to devotees.
The swamini, identified as Usha (50), resides in Kerala. It has been alleged that she amassed millions from people by saying that she can cure all kinds of illnesses.
She claims that she was gifted divinity by Lord Ayyappa when she was sick for 11 years.
Amma's "Holy Hell" In the long list of controversial godmen and godwomen Mata Amritanandamayi is new addition. A memoir written by a former disciple of Mata Amritanandamayi has sparked a controversy over its allegedly explosive content.
Amritanandamayi, also known as 'Amma' or the 'Hugging Saint' is a Hindu spiritual guru and has followers worldwide. Australiaborn Gail 'Gayatri' Tredwell in her book "Holy Hell: A Memoir of Faith, Devotion and Pure Madness" claims that she was a close disciple of Amma for several years and lived in her ashram in Kerala before she escaped from there following bitter experiences.
For two decades, Tredwell acted as Amma's personal servant, expected to be available at the "saint's" disposal at all hours. She became fluent in the Malayalam language and was with Amma continuously. Tredwell's riveting book allegedly recounts stories of donations intended for charity being converted into gold jewelry and hidden under the garments of Amma's 'sanyasis' (monks) as they passed through Customs and later the gold being passed to Amma's family to make them fabulously rich. Tredwell's book also speaks of her discovery of the alleged secret immoral activities involving Amma and her closest swamis. In addition, she speaks of being raped herself, repeatedly, by one of these same swamis, and names him.
Not only Kerala but also Amma's followers all over the world are furious over such "false allegations". Mata Amritanandamayi said, "The working of the ashram is an open book. People come up with such rumours because they did not get what they expected from the ashram. I am trying to forgive and forget." Some Hindu organisations are planning legal actions against Tredwell.
Kerala Chief Minister Oommen Chandy has given clean chit to Amma and said he did not think anything unlawful had happened at the mutt of Mata Amritanandamayi and added that the services her mutt does for the poor cannot be forgotten.
In the name of spirituality In the birthplace of several leading religions like Hinduism and Buddhism, magic and mysticism still rule. In traditionbound India, if someone claims to be able to exorcise ghosts, levitate or pull a gold chain out of thin air, it does not take long for him to become known as a "godman." The problem is that many of these godmen/godwomen are anything but godly and holy.
In today's consumaristic world the old respectful babas and gurus have been replaced, and in their place, a new breed of modern godmen holds the sway; some of them saffron-robed, and others sporting wild hair-dos.
Many of them command cult following, run huge ashrams on large expanses of land, own luxury cars, television channels and lavish homes. They flourish as their supporters make large donations in cash and kind.
The godmen jet set around the country and the world 'serving' their flock of devotees.
The majority of real Indian holy men (sadhus) live a life of poverty, meditation and performing blessing ceremonies.
To achieve heightened spirituality, sadhus may meditate for days on without end. But there are a few bad elements. The problem is that their number is increasing in India.
Public opinion Pavan K. Varma, former IAS officer and writer, said the country's vast demand for spiritual peace is often exploited by 'godmen' who are "less than spiritual." "Everybody is looking for spiritual anchorage and anyone purporting to offer that peace of mind acquires a following; but often behind the walls of the ashram they find the swamis have feet of clay and it leads to outrage," he said.
Kamini Jaiswal, a senior Supreme Court lawyer, who has fought a case against Sathya Sai Baba, blames blind followers for such incidents. "It is shocking to see that well educated people are followers of such godmen," she said.
Police say they cannot act against fake swamis until they get a complaint. "It's a social issue; with proper evidence, police will do its duty and arrest fake godman. As for the public, it's high time they recognised such fraudsters," Rajan Bhagat, Delhi Police spokesman, told media.
But there are those who are angry with the names of gurus being dragged into scandals.
One of them is yoga guru Baba Ramdev, who said the recent arrests were "a very big conspiracy." "Some politicians and communal forces are conspiring to malign the name of Indian saints by trapping them in cases related to fake currency, rape, murder, sex scandals and drugs," he said.
Agreed Anitha Swaminathan, a member of the Theosophical Society in Chennai. "Our country has veteran sadhus and swamijis.
Such fake godmen are just a bubble in the water," she said.
Naunidhi Kaur, a follower of Radhaswami Satsung, said: "There are numerous ashrams and satsangs that stand out for their spiritual teachings and true selfless service to mankind. A follower just needs to be more knowledgeable about the faith and not just be a blind one." Any amount of incriminating evidence does not seem to dither the followers and devotees of godmen, and they continue to invest their faith, trust and affection in them. The sociology of faith in a deeply divided and hierarchy/status-conscious society like ours needs deeper probing and public reasoning, even if this phenomenon looks beyond reason.
Godmen in Globalisation Since the beginning of 1990s the revolution in information and communication technology are influencing contour of religious belief as globalisation brought enlightenments and rationalism brought fear of unknown - both of economic and individual identity among the masses. The godmen of India took full advantage of modern information technology to spread their influence areas.
Today there are more than 32 TV channels airing only dharmik karyakram (spiritual programme).
Why have these godmen become so powerful? Modern society based on critical rationality and self-doubt has created unknown fear among the simple people all around the world. This leads to a vacuum.
For the common men, to find someone whom they could trust without second thoughts could be a very uplifting experience. Much of the discourse of the religious cults of babas and gurus place the follower exclusively at the centre of their explanations as to why things happen the way they do.
This gives both a sense of control over one's own life and also creates a justification for absolute trust in the godman / guru.
This also goes well with the new middle classes and their acquisitive nature that new market relations have shaped with their unrelenting encroachments into personal and cultural domains.
The scores of poor and marginalised who come to godmen / gurus seem to find in them a mode of bridging the class and social exclusion that they experience as a routine.
The per formative meetings/ spectacles held by the godmen / gurus emerge as new social spaces shared with the well-todo, allowing them to reclaim a residual assertion of dignity and perceive a degree of social visibility and inclusion. Unlike the traditional religiosity of visiting a temple, the lively aspect of seeing a real-time 'godman' in blood and flesh could be empowering and offer a dose of self-confidence that is in massive scarcity in societies like ours.
Breaching this formidable social logic and undercurrent could be unimaginable for them.
The attempt to create a godless modernity in India has led to the wild growth of dubious godmen. The recovery of hope would turn into a hopeful search if it is addressed towards fresh understanding of the earthly roots for the resurgence of religiosity, especially among the oppressed and the more authentic secularity inherent in it.
Faith is good. It keeps us grounded, pushes us forward and help us to hold on in life. But blind faith in godmen/godwomen is dangerous and should be opposed.
(Joseph Anthony Gathia is humanitarian writer, former journalist and human rights campaigner.
Email: joseph.gathia@gmail.com)
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Indian Currents. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>