<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRW-SR51-JCMC-V00B"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Putin's Brand of Russian Nationalism Does Not Seem To Include Anti-Semitism</title><source>The Forward</source><author></author><text><![CDATA['Putin may be good for Jews, but he's bad for Russia.'
When even Russian policemen had to pass security checks to enter the Sochi Winter Olympics, Rabbi Berel Lazar was waved in without ever showing his ID.
Lazar, a Chabad-affiliated chief rabbi of Russia, was invited to the opening ceremony of the games last month by President Vladimir Putin's office. But since the event was on Shabbat, Lazar initially declined the invitation, explaining he was prevented from carrying documents, among other religious restrictions.
So Putin ordered his staff to prepare an alternative entrance and security-free route just for the rabbi, according to one of Lazar's top associates, Rabbi Boruch Gorin.
It is unusual, but the security detail acted like kosher supervisors so Rabbi Lazar could attend, Gorin said.
To him, the Sochi anecdote illustrates Putin's positive attitude toward Russian Jewry an attitude Gorin says is sincere, unprecedented in Russian history and hugely beneficial for Jewish life in the country.
Others, however, see more cynical motives behind Putin's embrace of Russian Jewry.
Putin has been facing international criticism for a long time now over human rights issues, said Roman Bronfman, a former Israeli Knesset member who was born in the Soviet Union. He needs a shield, and that's the Jews. His warm relations with Russia's so-called official Jews are instrumental.
In recent weeks, Putin has positioned himself as a defender of
Jews as part of his effort to discredit the revolution that ousted his ally, former Ukraine President Viktor Yanukovych. During a March 4 news conference, Putin called the anti-Yanukovych protesters reactionary, nationalist and anti-Semitic forces.
While right-wing Ukrainian factions including some that have embraced anti-Semitic rhetoric in the past played a prominent role in the opposition movement, Ukrainian Jewish leaders have sharply disputed Putin's characterization and condemned Russian incursions into Crimea. Some individual Jews, however, have told JTA that they agree with Putin's analysis and welcomed the intervention by Russia.
Few would dispute that Putin has been friendly to Jewish institutional life in Russia especially to organizations and leaders that belong to the Chabad Hasidic movement.
Gorin, a Chabad rabbi and chairman of Moscow's $50 million Jewish Museum and Tolerance Center, credits Putin personally for providing state funding for the institution, which opened in 2012. Putin also donated a month's wages to the museum.
Putin has facilitated the opening of synagogues and Jewish community centers across Russia, at the Jewish community's request. This has had a profound effect on Jewish life, especially outside Moscow, Gorin said. He instituted annual meetings with Jewish community leaders and attends community events. His friendship with the Jewish community has given it much prestige and set the tone for local leaders.
Putin's relationship with the Jewish community is consistent with his larger strategy for governing Russia. His brand of Russian nationalism extends beyond just ethnic Russians to include the country's many minorities. Putin has carefully cultivated relationships with Russia's many subgroups and regions as a means of projecting his government's authority.
Mikhail Chlenov, secretary general of the Euro-Asian Jewish Congress, says Putin's pro-Jewish tendencies are part of the reason that anti-Semitic incidents are relatively rare in Russia.
Some Russian Jews recoil at Putin's authoritarian tendencies.
Putin may be good for Jews, but he's bad for Russia, said Michael Edelstein, a lecturer at Moscow State University and a journalist for the L'chaim Jewish newspaper.
Putin traces his earliest connection to Judaism back to his early childhood in Leningrad, now St. Petersburg, when he befriended a Jewish family that lived in his apartment block. In his 2000 autobiography, Putin wrote that the unnamed family loved him and that he used to seek its company.
They were observant Jews who did not work on Saturdays and the man would study the Bible and Talmud all day long, Putin wrote. Once I even asked him what he was muttering. He explained to me what this book was and I was immediately interested.
Zvi Gitelman, a professor of Judaic studies at the University of Michigan who studies the relationship between ethnicity and politics in the former Soviet Union, said the relationship between Putin and the Chabad organization in Russia is one of mutual convenience.
Shortly after taking office, the Putin government clashed withseveral prominent Jewish business moguls, including VladimirGusinsky and Boris Berezovsky, both of whom went into self-imposed exile.
When he went after these oligarchs, Putin sensed that thiscould be interpreted as anti-Semitism, Gitelman said. Heimmediately, publicly, demonstratively and dramatically embraced Chabad.
]]></text></news-item>