<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRW-96K1-JD34-V2XD"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Joyce's cavalier attitude to maintenance prioritises profit</title><source>Sydney Morning Herald (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[I was amazed to read in your front-page article "Qantas safety shock" (March 15-16) Alan Joyce's statement regarding offshore maintenance that "any mistakes were fixed when found". Perhaps he should have said "when and if found".
It is unbelievable that someone in Mr Joyce's position (and presumably his board) are not aware of the basic tenet of quality assurance that "one cannot inspect quality ito a product".
To achieve assurance of quality the process (and that includes aspects of maintenance) must have been developed, validated and adhered to, to ensure the desired outcome every time.
As a very much simplified example, it is not sufficient to check that a nut is tight as it may have been over-tightened with possible drastic effects on the bolt.
All equipment must be calibrated with fail-safe devices, methods developed, authorised and unequivocally followed by trained personnel. Obviously this is not achieved without cost, which, apparently, Qantas is not prepared to meet, taking the easy route of "fixing faults when found".
Peter Lublin Balmain
Matt O'Sullivan's article highlights the priorities and woes of Qantas under the stewardship of Alan Joyce ("Union dossier claims Qantas engines 'not secure' after offshore maintenance", March 15-16). His report card reads, huge financial losses, huge job losses, unsafe aircraft with dubious off-shore maintenance program. Are the shareholders and board in need of a maintenance reality check here? Alan Joyce must surely be on late finals now.
Pat Neville Eden
The unions are now threatening industrial action following the announcement of job losses in Qantas. They have learnt nothing. Such action will only serve to further undermine the finances of this loss-making company and accelerate its collapse and job losses. Such idiocy.
Michael Gamble Belmont (Vic)
If Alan Joyce and Qantas are so sure of the maintenance standards in Singapore, Hong Kong and Kuala Lumpur, why do they send Australian engineers to check the finished results? Surely this is an unnecessary drain on their budget, and if the odd plane or two starts falling out of the sky, it would be someone else's fault.
Brian Johnstone Leura
The article on Qantas' troubles by Matt O'Sullivan contains an interesting quote. It says: "Coalition senators accused [Steve] Purvinas of dog-whistle politics, and pointed out that some of the best cars in the world were built in Asia."
Apparently that's why we don't need Holden and Ford any more, and locally built Toyotas and,
according to National-Liberal party thought bubbles, Asia can do the lot.
Andy Busuttil Hazelbrook
Evidence would survive
As a former aircraft maintenance engineer, I must respectfully disagree with the premise that there would be no wreckage remaining of MH370 (Letters, March 15-16). There are numerous cases of aircraft that have met violent ends due to fire or explosion yet in all cases there is enough wreckage for investigators to determine the probable cause.
Take, for instance, the European MD11, with an in-flight fire caused by an incorrectly installed entertainment system that burnt hot enough to leave globs of copper imbedded in the pilot's seat. Or the American DC9, with a fire that erupted just after takeoff. Fuelled by incorrectly packed oxygen generators in the cargo hold this fire melted the cabin floor, probably jamming the controls.
While there is a slim hope the Boeing 777 will be found intact, this diminishes as time goes by.
If there is indeed wreckage to be found the only issue is that it may be at a great depth if the aircraft went ito the ocean. The investigators must determine the circumstances surrounding this mystery so the lessons can be learnt. It just takes time.
Anthony Rassias Glebe
Too risky for cyclists
Once again cyclists have been hit on Southern Cross Drive ("Cyclists injured after collision with car", smh.com.au, March 16).
This is a very busy road and the breakdown lane where a lot of cyclists ride is not very wide, so surely it's time they were banned from riding here, as they are on motorways, the M5 tunnel and other extremely busy roads.
Victor Marshall Erskineville
]]></text></news-item>