<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRW-WSJ1-F0NV-F3JY"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Carroll legislators propose more than 50 bills in Annapolis</title><source>Carroll County Times (Westminster, Maryland)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Carroll County's legislators to the Maryland General Assembly have submitted more than 50 bills during the 2014 legislative session in Annapolis.
Here is a breakdown of the Carroll-centric and statewide bills the delegates and senators have filed thus far:
Del. Don Elliot, District 4B
HB 320
Exempting historic vehicles and street rod vehicles from having to display two registration plates.
Status: Awaiting hearing in House Environmental Matters Committee
HB 327
Requiring the Motor Vehicle Administration to issue a single registration plate to all classes of vehicles.
Status: Received an unfavorable report by the House Environmental Matters Committee
HB 535
Altering the allocation of proceeds from instant ticket lottery machines operated by veterans' organizations and requiring that a specified amount of the net after-payout proceeds be used to benefit a charity. The remainder of the proceeds would be required to be used to further the purposes of the veterans' organization.
Status: Awaiting hearing in House Ways and Means Committee
HB 930
Decreasing a specified limitation on non-economic damages in health-care malpractice claims arising on or after Oct. 1, 2014, to $500,000.
Status: Received an unfavorable report by the House Judiciary Committee
HB 937
Requiring the Maryland Water Quality Financing Administration to ensure the fair and equitable distribution of specified financial assistance among wastewater facilities with a design capacity less than 500,000 gallons per day and wastewater facilities with a design capacity of 500,000 gallons per day or more.
Status: Passed the House, awaiting hearing in Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
Del. Justin Ready, District 5A
HB 277
Prohibiting the state or a local jurisdiction from imposing a vehicle-miles-traveled tax or specified other similar fees, tolls or taxes and prohibiting the state or a local jurisdiction from requiring the installation of a device in or on a privately owned vehicle to facilitate the reporting of the number of vehicle-miles-traveled.
Status: Awaiting hearing on House Ways and Means Committee
HB 339
Reducing the state corporate income tax rate from 8.25 percent to 7 percent beginning in tax year 2014.
Status: Awaiting hearing on House Ways and Means Committee
HB 423
Prohibiting the State Board of Education and specified county boards of education from establishing specified educational policies, curriculum and guidelines that include or are based on the Next Generation Science Standards and requiring the state board to take steps to rescind the adoption of the Next Generation Science Standards by July 1, 2014.
Status: Awaiting hearing on House Ways and Means Committee
HB 656
Restrict a register of wills or court from granting letters of administration to a person convicted of a crime that reflects adversely on an individual's honesty, trustworthiness or fitness to perform the duties of a personal representative.
Status: Second reading in the House
HB 737
Requiring certain state agencies and departments to prepare efficacy analyses for bills or regulations relating to agriculture, environment, natural resources and planning.
Status: Awaiting hearing on House Rules and Executive Nominations Committee
HB 1520
Creating a tax exemption period for the 7-day period starting on the third Sunday in April for certain hunting and sporting goods if the taxable price of the item is less than $1,000.
Status: First reading in the House Rules and Executive Nominations Committee
Del. Nancy Stocksdale, District 5A
HB 1471
Requiring a person to be registered by the State Real Estate Commission as a registered rental property manager no later than 20 days after the person begins providing rental property management services.
Status: First reading in the House Rules and Executive Nominations Committee
Del. Susan Krebs, District 9B
HB 155
Exempting a county or municipality that maintains adequate program funding to support infrastructure and programs from the requirement to adopt a watershed protection and restoration program under specified circumstances.
Status: Received an unfavorable report by the House Environmental Matters Committee
HB 157
Requiring a public body to include an agenda containing detailed information in the advance notice of a meeting being held.
Status: Awaiting hearing on House Health and Government Operations Committee
HB 184
Repealing the inheritance tax and the estate tax.
Status: Awaiting hearing on House Ways and Means Committee
HB 186
Repealing a limit on the unified credit used for determining the Maryland estate tax.
Status: Awaiting hearing on House Ways and Means Committee
HB 522
Increasing the amount of certain exemptions allowed under the state income tax by a specific cost-of-living adjustment.
Status: Awaiting hearing on House Ways and Means Committee
HB 528
Increasing the minimum and maximum limitation amounts of the standard deduction allowed under the state income tax by a specified cost-of-living adjustment.
Status: Awaiting hearing on House Ways and Means Committee
HB 557
Increasing state income tax rate bracket thresholds for taxable years after 2013 by a specified cost-of-living adjustment.
Status: Awaiting hearing on House Ways and Means Committee
HB 558
Including income from retirement plans within a subtraction modification allowed under the Maryland income tax for retired individuals who are at least 65 years old, are disabled or whose spouse is disabled.
Status: Awaiting hearing on House Ways and Means Committee
HB 593
Requiring that specified disclosure statements in pre-need contracts inform a buyer whether the contract is a guaranteed contract or nonguaranteed contract.
Status: Received favorable report with amendments by the House Health and Government Operations Committee
HB 1336
Requiring the Maryland Health Benefit Exchange to ask individuals for certain information when facilitating enrollment of the individuals in specified health insurance plans and specified health insurance programs.
Status: Awaiting hearing on House Health and Government Operations Committee
Sen. Joseph Getty, District 5
SB 244
Repealing the inheritance tax for decedents dying on or after Jan. 1, 2014.
Status: Awaiting hearing on Senate Budget and Taxation Committee
SB 321
Restrict a register of wills or court from granting letters of administration to a person convicted of a crime that reflects adversely on an individual's honesty, trustworthiness or fitness to perform the duties of a personal representative.
Status: Passed the Senate, awaiting hearing on House Judiciary Committee
SB 322
Requiring that a motor vehicle on an expressway or a controlled access highway be driven in the lane nearest to the right edge or curb of the roadway when that lane is available for travel.
Status: Awaiting hearing on Senate Judiciary Proceedings Committee
SB 365
Reducing the sales-and-use tax from 6 percent to 5 percent beginning July 1, 2014.
Status: Awaiting hearing on Senate Budget and Taxation Committee
SB 366
Reducing the state income tax on the Maryland taxable income of corporations from 8.25 percent to 7 percent.
Status: Awaiting hearing on Senate Budget and Taxation Committee
SB 431
Providing a grant to specified county boards of education if total direct education aid in the current fiscal year is less than in the prior fiscal year.
Status: Awaiting hearing on Senate Budget and Taxation Committee
SB 651
Requiring the governor annually to proclaim March 13 as "K9 Veterans Day."
Status: Passed the Senate, first reading in the House Health and Government Operations Committee
SB 768
Specifying that a license issued by another state to an individual to carry a regulated firearm is valid in Maryland.
Status: Withdrawn
SB 769
Reducing the state income tax rates imposed on married couples filing a joint income tax return and for specified individuals with income between $150,000 and $500,000.
Status: Withdrawn
SB 933
Repealing provisions requiring public school employers in all jurisdictions of the state to negotiate with specified employee organizations regarding service or representation fees charged to nonmembers.
Status: Withdrawn
SB 1043
Requiring, under specified circumstances, a candidate or a treasurer to file an affidavit with the State Board of Elections requesting that the State Board place a certain campaign finance entity on inactive status.
Status: Awaiting hearing by the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
SB 1049
Specifying that a day on which public schools are closed during a state of emergency shall be credited against the required minimum number of days that public schools shall be open.
Status: Awaiting hearing by the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
Sen. David Brinkley, District 4
SB 155
Altering a limit on the unified credit used for determining the Maryland estate tax.
Status: Awaiting hearing in the Senate Budget and Taxation Committee
SB 277
Exempting Frederick County from the requirement to adopt a watershed protection and restoration program.
Status: Received unfavorable report in the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
SB 384
Reducing the state corporate income tax rate from 8.25 percent to 6 percent.
Status: Awaiting hearing in the Senate Budget and Taxation Committee
SB 385
Providing a subtraction modification under the Maryland corporate income tax for specified dividends included in federal taxable income as a result of a repatriation holiday enacted by federal legislation.
Status: Received an unfavorable report by the Senate Budget and Taxation Committee
SB 386
Exempting the sales-and-use tax from the sale of home wheelchair lifts and stairlifts.
Status: Passed the Senate, in the House Ways and Means Committee
SB 590
Limiting the state income tax rate to 2.875 percent and the county income tax rate to 1.6 percent for members of an S corporation, partnerships, a limited liability company or trusts.
Status: Awaiting hearing in the Senate Budget and Taxation Committee
SB 1024
Prohibiting an official from using the prestige of office or public position to solicit, compel or oblige a public or private entity to enter into an agreement with a labor organization.
Status: Awaiting hearing in the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
SB 1068
Increasing the amount of state money that must be used in an elementary or a secondary school construction project before the Prevailing Wage Law applies to 75 percent.
Status: Received an unfavorable report by the Senate Finance Committee
Senate Joint Resolution 9
Rejecting items included in the Resolution of the General Assembly Compensation Commission relating to salaries for all members of the General Assembly, the per diem allowance for meals, reimbursement for lodging expenses, and travel allowances and reimbursements.
Status: First reading in the Senate Rules Committee
Sen. Allan Kittleman, District 9
SB 5
Repealing the requirement that a county or municipality subject to a specified municipal stormwater permit adopt and implement laws or ordinances to establish a watershed protection and restoration program.
Status: Received an unfavorable report by the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
SB 421
Prohibiting a member of the General Assembly whose residence is located less than 50 miles from the State House from using the General Assembly housing allowance to pay for housing except under specified circumstances.
Status: Received an unfavorable report by the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
SB 422
Requiring a regulated lobbyist that invites members of a legislative unit of the General Assembly to a meal during the legislative session to file a specified report with the State Ethics Commission.
Status: Awaiting hearing by the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
SB 738
Altering the definition of "public body" for the purposes of the Maryland Open Meetings Act to include a multimember subcommittee of a standing committee of either house of the General Assembly.
Status: Awaiting hearing by the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
SB 739
Altering the Senatorial and Delegate Scholarship Programs to require that the money appropriated under the programs be awarded by the Office of Student Financial Assistance in the Maryland Higher Education Commission.
Status: Awaiting hearing by the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
SB 740
Proposing an amendment to the Maryland Constitution to change the process of legislative districting and apportionment in the state by establishing a General Assembly and Congressional Legislative Districting and Apportionment Commission.
Status: Awaiting hearing by the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
SB 741
Allowing an individual who is a teacher a credit against the state income tax for classroom expenses and supplies.
Status: Awaiting hearing by the Senate Budget and Taxation Committee
SB 845
Prohibiting a member of the General Assembly who uses the General Assembly housing allowance for lodging at an establishment that provides individuals with specified rewards from accepting the rewards earned.
Status: Awaiting hearing by the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
SB 847
Requiring a public body to include an agenda containing specified information in the advance notice of a meeting being held.
Status: Awaiting hearing by the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
SB 848
Requiring a chief election official of an election authority who is determining the sufficiency of the format of a specified petition to determine the sufficiency of any summary of local legislation that is contained in the petition.
Status: Awaiting hearing by the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
SB 1027
Requiring the Maryland Department of Health and Mental Hygiene to notify the State Board of Physicians of the amount of a specific fee.
Status: Received an unfavorable report by the Senate Education, Health and Environmental Affairs Committee
]]></text></news-item>