<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRW-1K71-DYRV-315P"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Thai police file lawsuits against 220 suspected Uighur immigrants</title><source>BBC Monitoring Asia Pacific - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Text of report published by Thai newspaper Bangkok Post website on 16 March
Police have lodged lawsuits with the court against the 220 suspected ethnic Uighurs from northwest China found hiding in a rubber plantation in Songkhla on Thursday amid international calls for Thailand not to deport them.
The lawsuits of illegal entry were filed yesterday at the Songkhla Municipal Court, said Pol Maj Gen Thatchai Pitaneelaboot, commander of the Immigration Bureau's Division 6.
He said the Turkish embassy had agreed to pay any fines imposed on them. The embassy has said that they originally claimed to be Turkish citizens seeking refugee status, which is why they agreed to pay the fine.
Officers will verify the nationalities of the suspects before sending them to either third countries or their nations of origin, he added. According to a police source, officers believe most of the suspects are Uighurs, an ethnic Muslim minority in China's northwestern Xinjiang region. The suspects, however, asserted they were from Turkey and were heading to Malaysia.
Officers believed they were afraid of being sent back to Xinjiang, the source said.
The suspected illegal immigrants consist of 69 men, 56 women and 95 children. They were rounded up in the plantation in Ban Khlong Tor in Rattaphum district's tambon Kamphangphet on Thursday evening.
The women and children will be sent to the Songkhla Children and Family Aid House, while the men will be detained at the Padang Besar border crossing in the province's Sadao district, Pol Maj Gen Thatchai said.
Turkish embassy officials have been sent to check the identities of the suspects and send the information back to their country for verification. Some of the suspects seem to be able to communicate in Turkish.
The UN was checking yesterday on the humanitarian needs of those detained, a spokesman said.
"We are working with the Thai government to determine the humanitarian needs of these people," said Vivian Tan of the UN High Commissioner for Refugees. "We cannot confirm that they are Uighurs at the moment."
On Friday, US State Department spokeswoman Marie Harf said the US was concerned about the plight of the predominantly Muslim minority, but did not directly address the possibility of the group's repatriation to China.
Yesterday, the New York-based Human Rights Watch appealed to the Thai government to ensure that they were not returned to China before determining their status as possible political refugees.
"Thai authorities should realise that Uighurs forced back to China disappear into a black hole," said Brad Adams, Asia director at Human Rights Watch.
"They need to allow all members of this group access to a fair process to determine their claims based on their merits, not on Beijing's demands."
Caretaker Social Development and Human Security Minister Pavena Hongsakula yesterday visited the detained people and gave them provisions.
She said the Department of Social Development and Welfare would earmark money to take care of the people. The ministry will also contact Songkhla police to provide security for them around the clock, she added.
Source: Bangkok Post website, Bangkok, in English 16 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>