<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRW-44S1-JCW9-X3VJ"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Maravilla Clemens: Our challenge is speaking out to change the future</title><source>Ventura County Star (California)</source><author>Maravilla Clemens, the 2012 Oxnard High School valedictorian, attends Colby College in Waterville, Maine.</author><text><![CDATA[I find myself sitting in a quiet coffee shop, looking out onto the bustling streets of Washington, D.C., as I contemplate my cause for being here.
The towering buildings that surround me are a stark contrast to the soaring redwoods of my home state and I yearn to look up and see green branches against a blue sky.
I have to remind myself of the reason that I am here: So that in the generations to come, children will have the opportunity to walk under the same redwoods that I once did; so that tribes that have inhabited a land for generations can continue to prosper on their own soil; and so the United States of America may continue to prosper as a county that has not exploited its natural resources to a level of near depletion. On paper, my arrest was in protest of the Keystone XL pipeline. In reality, I was arrested in protest of a federal government, which, in the words of former Secretary of the Interior Stewart Udall, is continuing to pass legislation without “distance in their eyes.” In my short 19 years of life, I have seen a sea on fire as a film of black oil covered the Gulf of Mexico as a result of the BP oil spill. I have seen almost 20 percent of the Amazon Rainforest fall as deforestation rates increase largely due to the high demands for timber by western countries. I have seen an unprecedented number of climate disasters rake across the planet. However, in my lifetime I have also seen the U.S. Supreme Court ruling that states have the power to regulate greenhouse-gas emissions. I have seen Wangari Maathai awarded the Nobel Peace Prize for her efforts in converting Kenya from a barren landscape to one with budding trees and empowered citizens. And just recently, I saw 398 students get arrested for protesting the passage of a 17,000-mile pipeline and a government that is not acting in the best interest for the future of our country. Udall stated that it is possible to accomplish “saving work ... if there are enough Americans of this generation who have “distance in their eyes.” I know this generation has the passion and power to not only change history, but to create the future.
]]></text></news-item>