<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRX-2TB1-F0NV-F44T"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Volunteer Center of Story County: March 16</title><source>The Tribune (Ames, Iowa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Volunteer Center of Story County connects people of all ages with volunteer opportunities, promotes volunteering and recognizes volunteers.
Visit www.vcstory.org for additional information, to volunteer or to list volunteer needs. Or call (515) 268-5323, email director@vcstory.org or visit from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Monday through Friday.
VOLUNTEER OPPORTUNITIES
PICK UP TRASH
Stash the Trash
Stash the Trash, VEISHEA Service Day and Keep Iowa State Beautiful are joining together again this year in a campus/community partnership to clean Ames community public spaces. On Saturday, March 29, volunteers are invited to pick up trash in their neighborhoods, along streets, in parks and schoolyards - any public place that trash has accumulated over the winter. Participants are welcome to work individually, with a group of people or with a club or organization. Volunteers can sign up online for a location until 6 p.m. on Wednesday, March 26. After that time, assignments will be made Saturday at Reiman Gardens. VEISHEA Service Day participants sign up at www.veishea.iastate.edu/vsd for an assignment on the Iowa State University campus. Ames community participants sign up on the Volunteer Center of Story County Web site at www.vcstory.org/ for an assignment in the Ames community. Volunteers are also encouraged to clean up unlisted public areas.
CARPENTER NEEDED FOR HISTORIC EXHIBIT
Ames Historical Society
The Ames Historical Society will present an exhibit at the Octagon Center for the Arts as part of Ames' sesquicentennial celebration. The exhibit will highlight 150 defining people, places and events throughout Ames history. The Historical Society is looking for someone to help with the design and construction of 10 temporary exhibit walls. Supplies will be provided. Further explanation of the project will be given upon request. The project needs to be completed by July 1.
FRONT DESK ASSISTANT
Ames Historical Society
The Ames Historical Society has recently expanded our open hours to include Saturdays from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m., in addition to our regular open hours, 1 to 5 p.m. Wednesday through Friday. In order to maintain efficient open hours we are looking for volunteers to operate the front desk on Saturdays with shifts of 10 a.m. to noon, noon to 2 p.m. and 2 to 4 p.m. The front desk volunteer is in charge of meeting and greeting patrons, answering the phone and assisting patrons' needs including but not limited to: donations, research needs and brief tours.
CAMP VOLUNTEER
Octagon Center for the Arts
Each Spring Break, the Octagon provides a uniquely themed and educational week-long day camp the week of March 17 where children in first through sixth grade exercise their imaginations and spend their days learning about art in a fun, creative atmosphere. You can be a part of this by becoming an Art Camp leader! Leaders assist the education director by helping to guide the day's activities, helping to keep the campers on task and acting as a chaperon on walks to nearby Bandshell Park for picnic lunches (weather permitting).
VOLUNTEER APPLICATION PROCESSING
Youth and Shelter Services
Volunteers are sought to assist with processing volunteer applications. This includes verifying references, sending out authorizations for background checks and maintaining volunteer files. This is done using electronic, phone and mail communications. Records are maintained in an Access-based database. Up to 20 applications are received weekly. This position has a flexible schedule and can be broken down to specific components as necessary. Volunteers must be familiar with using MS Office software including Access database. Professional writing and communication skills are recommended. Volunteers must be able to pass a background check for Iowa DHS approval and be clean and sober for a minimum of two years. Volunteers will be expected to follow the YSS policy regarding confidentiality and maintenance of program and volunteer records.
DONATIONS DATA ENTRY
Youth and Shelter Services
Volunteers are needed to help with the Community Resource Development program at Youth and Shelter Services, in Ames. In-kind donations of goods and services are received on a daily basis. Accurate records of items received are crucial to the efficient operation of our agency. Volunteers in this position will be responsible for entering records of items and services received into a donations database and generating reports about those donations on a monthly and sometimes more often basis. This position will also send out thank you notes used by donors for tax purposes.
FOOD SUPPLY HERO
Mid-Iowa Community Action (MICA)
When donations are lower than demand, MICA's food pantry has a couple options to keep our shelves stocked. One low-cost option is to get food from the Food Bank of Iowa, 30 minutes or so south of our Ames location in Des Moines. Volunteers are needed to make this trip. A vehicle is provided. Volunteers must have a clean driving record.
VOLUNTEER BILL PAYER
The Salvation Army
The volunteer bill payer assists persons in paying bills and managing finances. A minimum of 2.5 hours per month commitment is needed. Applicants must pass a comprehensive background check and have experience balancing checkbooks and managing finances (can be your own).
CLOTHES PANTRY VOLUNTEER
Ballard Community Clothes Pantry
Organize, sort and help in a free clothes pantry during open hours: Saturday, 10 a.m. to noon; Sunday, 1 to 3 p.m.; and Wednesday, 4 to 6 p.m.
PICK UP FOOD DONATIONS
ACCESS (Assault Care Center Extending Shelter & Support)
Volunteers are needed on Friday, March 14, to pick up donations from various manufacturers in Iowa who offered to donate food to area food pantries. There are three manufacturers, and the times would vary based on which location you would be picking items up from. The earliest is 9 a.m., and the latest is 10 a.m. Your own form of transportation is needed, and directions to the site will be provided. Volunteers will meet at the shelter, and depart for the manufacturer from there.
HELP SORT FOOD DRIVE DONATIONS
ACCESS (Assault Care Center Extending Shelter & Support)
ACCESS is looking for five volunteers to help sort food donations. We will have other volunteers drop the donations off at ACCESS shelter, and the volunteers will be evenly distributing them into 25 groups for area food pantries. The volunteers will be needed from 11 a.m. to 3 p.m. on Friday, March 21.
RECEPTIONIST/OFFICE VOLUNTEER
Creative Counseling Services
Creative Counseling Services is looking for a part time receptionist/office volunteer. Duties include answering phones, scheduling appointments for our counselors, helping clients with paperwork, filing, light cleaning and other office duties. Position is approximately 6-12 hours per week. Work Monday from 9 a.m. to 3 p.m. and possibly Wednesday from 9 a.m. to 3 p.m., or Wednesday and Thursday from 9 a.m. to noon.
MATH AND READING TUTOR
Community Housing Initiatives
We are looking for an individual to help a 7-year-old boy improve on his math and reading skills. Times are flexible, but Wednesdays after school are typically better for the family.
OUTDOOR TRAIL IMPROVEMENT VOLUNTEERS
Story County Conservation
Be a part of our TEAM (Trail Enhancement and Management!) on April 19 and help make improvements to county trail systems. Responsibilities could include re-routing or fixing trails and the removal of weeds, trash and unwanted tree debris. All volunteers are asked to wear a long-sleeved shirt, long pants and gloves and bring a water bottle. Sturdy, closed-toed shoes are strongly recommended.
GEOCACHE EGG HUNT VOLUNTEERS
Story County Conservation
Help will be needed on April 9 to assist with acquiring GPS coordinates and setting up collecting sites. At the event on April 19, three to nine volunteers are needed to assist naturalist Jess Lancial with registration, hiding and collecting eggs and assisting with GPS instructions.
ANNUAL SPRING FISHING TOURNAMENT VOLUNTEERS
Story County Conservation
Five volunteers are needed to help SCC Rangers as they lead the annual Spring Fishing Tournament on May 4. Volunteers will help with check-in and registration, clean-up and other tasks throughout the day.
VOLUNTEERS FOR SPRING PARTNER'S FESTIVAL
Story County Conservation
We are looking for around 40 volunteers for our annual Spring Partner's Festival on May 4. This year's theme is Sounds of Spring and our special guest will be the Flying Pig Fiddle and Banjo band.
BIRDING PROGRAM VOLUNTEER
Story County Conservation
One volunteer is needed to help naturalist Heather Hucka on April 26 with clean-up after the program. The program involves learning birding basics and a hike to look for some of Iowa's fine feathered friends. The morning will end with bagels, fruit and watching birds at the feeders at the Conservation Center.
PHOTO SCANNING AND DATA ENTRY
Ames Historical Society
The Ames Historical Society is looking for volunteers to help with our ever-growing historic photo collection. We literally have thousands of negatives that have been given to us by the Ames Tribune that need to be scanned onto our network. We are looking for volunteers to scan negatives, research articles that go with the negatives and then enter the necessary information into the Past Perfect program. We are currently working on negatives from the 1970s. This is a perfect project for a long-time Ames native who will enjoy looking at old photos from the past but also for someone who wants to learn more about Ames.
PHOTOGRAPHER VOLUNTEER
Ames Historical Society
The Ames Historical Society is looking for a volunteer to take photos of different buildings/businesses around town. History is a continuing process and 50 years from now the businesses/buildings that are around now may not be there, and will be forever lost in history. We need a volunteer to take photos of specific areas around Ames, download them onto our network, and then enter them into the Past Perfect museum program.
INTERNSHIP
Ames Historical Society
The Ames Historical Society is looking for an unpaid intern to work during the summer or school year. Hours are flexible depending on the volunteer's needs and schedule. Ideally, an intern would work 20 hours a week (or more if desired). We have many projects that span a wide variety of interests. This would be a great opportunity for someone wanting to enter the field of museum work, or someone just interested in history. Many of our projects require research, scanning, data entry into our network system and Past Perfect, and compiling research into a final project that we can use for educational purposes.
VOLUNTEER MENTOR FOR AFTER-SCHOOL AND SUMMER
Community Housing Initiatives
We are currently seeking Volunteer Mentors for our Ames Enrichment Academy. AEA is a summer and after-school program for children on the free and reduced school lunch program. Activities are hands-on and enticing for kids and mentors! We have weekly and monthly activities that focus on math, reading/literacy, science and social studies.
BRAIN BOOSTERS MATH ACTIVITY
Community Housing Initiatives (CHI)
Brain Booster is a program that supports a child's understanding of numbers and math. Each week we use different tools to explore math and numbers. Commonly used tools are food, Legos and games. We are seeking consistent volunteers to help staff math sessions. Duties include setting up the room, assisting kids with the activity, encouraging positive behavior and clean up.
READING AVENUE
Community Housing Initiatives (CHI)
Reading Avenue is a program designed to pair a school age child with a trained therapy dog for a one on one reading session. This program is held onsite at Eastwood Apartments, in Ames, for the children and families that live there. We are seeking a few regular volunteers to assist us with staffing the reading sessions. Duties would include setting up the room for the dogs and kids, ensuring each child is allowed their allotted time, encouraging the child to read for their entire appointment, playing games with the child who is waiting for their turn and cleaning up the room after the session. We are also seeking volunteers who may have a certified therapy dog to add to our roster of "Rovers."
STORY TIME/CRAFT TIME VOLUNTEER
Community Housing Initiatives (CHI)
Story Time/Craft Activity is held on Thursdays from 3:45 to 5:15 p.m. at our Ames location. The program involves reading stories and facilitating a related craft activity for school-aged children. The average participation runs from five to eight kids each session. A CHI/Resident Services staff also attends each session for added support. Through this activity, children have an opportunity to socialize, have fun and use their imaginations to link the story they hear with the craft they will create.
DENTAL CLINIC VOLUNTEER
Mid-Iowa Community Action
Created to fulfill the dental needs of low-income families, the Story County Dental Clinic has helped many adults and children who have Medicaid or who have no dental insurance obtain affordable dental care. The clinic offers a range of dental services to patients of all ages. Our volunteers help staff manage patient records, remind patients of upcoming appointments and track information for sending to organizations that help fund our operations through grants. Our office hours are Monday to Thursday from 8 a.m. to 6 p.m., and we have particular need for volunteers Monday and Tuesday mornings. Due to screening and placement processes, we look for volunteers looking to make an ongoing commitment. Most volunteers come in for an hour or two at a time at the same time each week.
TOUR GUIDES
Reiman Gardens
Youth and Adult Tour Guides give tours of Reiman Gardens to children in pre-school through high school or adult community groups. Tour guides talk to the groups as they walk around the garden and enjoy the many different beauties! A short training is required in order to become a tour guide.
BUTTERFLY DOCENTS
Reiman Gardens
Reiman Gardens is always looking for volunteers to help in the butterfly wing. This position is simple and relaxing. Volunteers monitor the butterfly wing and assist visitors with opening doors as they go in and out, give them the "do's and don'ts," share some facts and stories about the butterflies and garden in general, and just socialize with the visitors. There is a short training done by Reiman Garden staff in order to become a butterfly docent. It consists of watching a video and a quick tour of the butterfly wing.
COURT APPOINTED SPECIAL ADVOCATES
CASA
CASA stands for Court Appointed Special Advocates. CASAs are regular, everyday people who care enough about abused and neglected children to get involved... and make a huge difference in their lives. CASAs have about 30 hours of training before they take a child abuse case. CASA work can be very, very emotionally demanding. If abuse and neglect are hard to talk about for us as adults, how must those fragile, innocent little ones feel as they live this day in and day out?
MAKE A BLANKET
Project Linus of Story County
Make a blanket and share it with a child in need by donating it to Story County Project Linus. Your new, handmade, washable blanket or afghan will be given to a child who is seriously ill, traumatized or otherwise in need. All sizes and types are happily accepted! Ames Sewing and Vacuum Center accepts Project Linus blanket donations during their regular business hours (9 a.m. to 5 p.m. weekdays and 9 a.m. to 3 p.m. Saturdays) at 214 Main St., Ames. Please feel free to drop off your blankets there or contact us for additional drop off locations. Project Linus welcomes volunteer of all ages and all abilities. Every blanket donated is loved by the child who receives it.
GRIP MENTORING
Youth and Shelter Services
GRIP (Great Relationships in Pairs) is a school-based mentoring program working with Kindergarten through 8th grade youth throughout Story and Boone Counties. We ask that our volunteers be enthusiastic about working with youth and have a desire to help children by becoming a friend and a trusted adult they can rely on. It is school-based, meaning pairs meet during the mentee's (child's) school day, usually over a lunch or recess time. GRIP is very flexible and can work with your hours. We ask mentors (volunteers) to spend 30 to 45 minutes a week with their mentee. The commitment is one school year, ending in May of the school year you start in. We facilitate matches all throughout the school year. We have a two-hour training before the mentor starts their year. Besides training, we have facilitators for each school who work with the mentors and the mentees to make the year the best it can be. They are always available for questions, problems and, the best parts, the success stories.
SATISFACTION SURVEY ENTRY
Youth and Shelter Services
Volunteers are needed on a monthly basis to enter customer (internal and external) satisfaction survey results into our computer system. This assignment will most likely involve two- to four-hour shifts, for one to three days per month, dependent on the volume of data to be entered. Depending on the program, the task may involve entering data from paper copies and/or identifying customers, sending out surveys and then entering results when received. This position will work with Prevention Programming Staff and the Volunteer Services Office primarily.
COMMUNITY RESOURCES DRIVER
Youth and Shelter Services
Every weekday, Youth and Shelter Services benefits from area business who donate food items to our Rosedale Shelter, 712 and Youth Recovery Homes, Transitional Living and Family Development Programs. Volunteer Drivers are needed on an ongoing basis to help pick up these donated items from area businesses and deliver them to the various YSS facilities located in Ames. Interested volunteers should be available weekday mornings. A valid driver's license and proof of insurance is required. Volunteers may use their own vehicle. Volunteers using YSS vehicles will be required to attend a defensive driving training and complete the YSS vehicle orientation/training.
ADOPT-A-ROOM
ACCESS (Assault Care Center Extending Shelter & Support)
ACCESS is seeking community members and volunteer groups to renovate and rejuvenate living space. Spaces include but are not limited to: bathrooms, hallways, donation closets and bedrooms. For more information about our Adopt-A-Room program please contact Annie at (515) 292-0500. To learn more about ACCESS, please visit assaultcarecenter.org. We hope to hear from you soon.
SHELTER VICTIM COUNSELOR
ACCESS (Assault Care Center Extending Shelter & Support)
This is an opportunity to be a part of social change in your community. As a Victim Counselor you can provide empathetic support to survivors of domestic and/or sexual violence. After training you will be able to provide support, crisis counseling and resources to shelter residents. Community members passionate about housing and economic justice are highly sought for this volunteer position. Must be 18 or older. Must complete 32-hour training. We do complete background checks. Hours are flexible and based on individual schedules.
FOOD PANTRY/ FAMILY DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANT
Mid-Iowa Community Action (MICA)
Volunteers are needed to help weigh food donations, organize them on the food pantry shelves, sort them into packages of different sizes for different families, and distribute food packages. Family Development Volunteers also greet families as they arrive or answer the phone as necessary.
DELIVER MEALS TO HOMES
Heartland Senior Services
Volunteers are needed to deliver hot, nutritious meals to seniors in their homes over the noon hour in specific areas of Story County. Volunteers pick up the meals at a specified location after 10 a.m. and deliver the meals to individuals in their homes. A list of recipients and directions are provided. The meals need to be delivered within one hour of being picked up, so they remain food safe. The communities needing volunteers are Cambridge, Collins, Colo, Gilbert, Huxley, Kelley, Maxwell, McCallsburg, Nevada, Roland, Slater, Story City, Zearing and rural Ames.
GROUNDS CARE
Heartland Senior Services
Heartland Senior Services, located at 205 S. Walnut Ave., in Ames, has many positions for volunteers. One ongoing need is for a person or persons to keep the lawn and grounds looking neat and tidy. This can include keeping the lawn, sidewalks and parking areas free of branches, twigs and pine cones that might cause a senior citizen to trip or twist an ankle. It may include picking up litter and pulling weeds. This work can be done any time of the day, but needs to be done frequently.
DEVELOPMENT AND FUNDRAISING
KHOI Community Radio
KHOI is seeking volunteers to assist with development and fund raising. Volunteer tasks include organizing, event planning and setup, developing invitations and mailers, photographing, taping, fund drives and donor relations.
VOLUNTEER MANAGEMENT
KHOI Community Radio
KHOI is looking for individuals to help with Volunteer Management. The individuals will recruit volunteers, assemble packets of volunteer needs, respond to potential volunteers, assist in conducting interviews, maintain records, and manage volunteer relations including meetings, parties and thank you's.
TECHNOLOGY AND GROUNDS
KHOI Community Radio
KHOI is seeking volunteers to assist with technology and grounds needs. Volunteer tasks include:
· Equipment: recordings, board operator, database, tech support, and maintenance
· IT: Internet service, in-office computer network, streaming, website structure
· Facilities: grounds keeping, building maintenance and repair, studio visual art,
· Broadcast engineering
· Short term: construction - build rooms (carpentry) and broadcast and recording studios (electronic) and production and operations area
· Custodial work: cleaning floors and facilities
PROGRAMS AND PRODUCTION
KHOI Community Radio
KHOI is seeking volunteers to assist with programs and production. Tasks include:
· Production - managing broadcast schedule and automation system, audio editing, creating and editing PSA's, promos, and underwriting credits, and managing music libraries.
· Production of KHOI signature programs - reporting and interviewing, assembling programs in pre-production, assisting with on-air hosting, scheduling guests and interviews, and training new volunteers.
ADMINISTRATION AND OFFICE MANAGEMENT
KHOI Community Radio
KHOI radio is seeking volunteers to assist with the administration and office management duties of the station. Tasks include reception, phone, email, booking events, updating the station calendar, managing office traffic and developing manuals.
OUTREACH AND PUBLIC RELATIONS
KHOI Community Radio
KHOI is seeking volunteers to assist with outreach and public relations. The tasks include: Marketing - writing, editing, newsletter, mailings, fliers, brochures and other promotional materials, email blasts, web site content, social networking; Membership -database management, on-air pitching, phone banks; Events and speaking engagements.
CLOTHING CLOSET VOLUNTEER
Harmony Clothing Closet, Nevada
This is an ongoing or one-time position at the Harmony Clothing Closet. Our service is open every Saturday morning from 8 a.m. to noon and Mondays from 4:30 to 7 p.m. During this time we sort and hang donated items. We also do housekeeping and help our customers pick out and bag free clothing items.
VOLUNTEER CURATORIAL ASSISTANT
Octagon Center for the Arts
The Octagon is looking for art lovers to help us within our Exhibits department! Volunteers will assist our Exhibits Manager with checking in, preparing, and hanging/setting artwork for exhibits in our galleries. This is an amazing opportunity for anyone who's ever wanted to work in a gallery or museum.
HELP DELIVER MEALS ON WHEELS
Mary Greeley Medical Center
Volunteers for Meals on Wheels help by delivering meals to homebound Ames residents over the lunch hour. Typical routes include 5-10 stops that are arranged as much as possible by geographic location. First volunteers stop at MGMC to pick up the meals in carriers and the route information, deliver the meals, and then return carriers to MGMC. Volunteers find this experience to be very rewarding. Volunteers are needed on Sundays and Fridays starting at 11:30 a.m. Shifts last about one to one and a half hours. Volunteers must provide their own vehicle and have proof of insurance.
WOMEN TO HELP
Butterfly Freedom House
The Butterfly Freedom House is established to offer a home that provides a loving, safe and healthy environment where women can be restored. We need women for various amounts of commitment: to mentor, stay overnight, landscape, share a meal, teach a skill, music, financial support, or apply for house manager. We will have up to four women living here, and you could be the one who makes a real difference in their lives. We have an application process to go through, starting with filling out a short application. We need mature women with a heart of service and religious faith in healing.
STORE VOLUNTEER
Worldly Goods
Worldly Goods is a nonprofit retail store specializing in the handcrafts of low-income artisans from developing areas around the world. It serves as an international marketplace where artisans can be assured of a fair income and fair trade practices. Provide volunteer sales staffing, and inform customers about the Fair Trade products in the store and the artisans who make them. Help maintain stock and appearance of store as needed.
FUNDRAISE FOR PREMATURE INFANTS
Holding Tiny Hands
Holding Tiny Hands strives to optimize the outcomes of micro-preemies and chronically ill infants by addressing the parents' emotional and psychological needs through an established support system of parents who share similar experiences. We are looking for philanthropic organizations to assist us in fundraising activities at Iowa State University. We are considering holding a Zumbathon, dance marathon, or any other event/activity that would appeal to the college crowd! If your group is looking for an opportunity to work on behalf of premature infants, please contact us! We would love to talk with you!
ADOPT CAMPUS PROGRAM VOLUNTEER
Keep Iowa State Beautiful
The Adopt Campus Program is designed for groups of people (ISU students, faculty, staff) to remove litter from areas of campus. Recruit your student organization members, your staff, your offices, your departments to help beautify campus. This is a volunteer opportunity for Iowa State University students, faculty, and staff. A completed and signed waiver is required before participating.
BIRTHRIGHT OFFICE VOLUNTEER
Birthright of Ames
Birthright is run entirely by volunteers, which means every volunteer has a lot of responsibility. Center volunteers work one-on-one with clients to administer pregnancy tests, assist with the clothing room, and offer referrals. Volunteers will be responsible for the basic management of the office, and will have the opportunity to pick up projects according to their interests.
POST FLIERS ON CAMPUS
Birthright of Ames
We're looking for individuals and/or groups to distribute promotional fliers on campus in order to inform students and staff about the services that Birthright provides. This volunteer event is extremely time-flexible. After picking up the fliers during our office hours, volunteers can work at whatever time best suits their schedules.
CHILDCARE ROOM HELPER
People Place - Lutheran Services in Iowa
If you enjoy parents and children, then People Place can use you. People Place has an opportunity for an ongoing volunteer on Tuesdays, Wednesdays and Thursdays from 9 a.m. to noon in our child care room. Do a craft, read a book or entertain the children while their parents are down the hall in a class or getting some respite while their child is in a safe and caring environment.
FURNITURE MOVER
FreeStore
Strong individuals needed to move furniture into apartments for women. We drive FreeStore trucks from Des Moines to Story County and provide furniture for domestic violence clients from the ACCESS shelter in Ames. We need local help to unload the truck and set up furniture in client homes.
CLOTHES PANTRY VOLUNTEER
Ballard Community Clothes Pantry
Organize, sort and help in a free clothes pantry during open hours. Saturday, 10 a.m. to noon, Sunday, 1 to 3 p.m., and Wednesday, 4 to 6 p.m.
PREPARE / SERVE / CLEAN UP
Food at First
Prepare, serve, and clean up after meals which are served to the hungry in the Ames area.
HELP RESIDENTS TO MEALS OR THERAPY
Bethany Manor
This is very rewarding as you help assist residents to the main dining room for their meals or help them go to the therapy room for some exercise. Many of them need someone to help push their wheelchair in addition, this is a great activity to not only meet some amazing people but get your exercise too! Peak times for this activity are 7 to 10 a.m.; 11 a.m. to 1 p.m. and again at 4 to 5 p.m. Simple training will be provided to show you how to push wheelchairs for the residents.
BINGO HELPERS
Bethany Manor
How do we spell fun? B-I-N-G-O! Each Wednesday afternoon at 2:30 p.m. in the main dining room at Bethany Manor we play BINGO. This activity is one of the residents' favorites. It is the fastest hour of entertainment for all involved and we always need helpers. In addition we also serve fresh hot popcorn. No special training required for this activity, you will be working alongside the activity staff. Some of our residents need help marking their BINGO cards and will enjoy your companionship.
PLAY CARDS AND GAMES WITH RESIDENTS
Bethany Manor
Residents at the Bethany Manor senior resident community in Story City like to get a competitive or just a fun game going with each other. They love it when volunteers come play with them to give them a new and fun challenge. They play a wide range of card games, dominoes, do puzzles and more.
PROVIDE MANICURES
Bethany Manor
Cedar Place is another campus within Bethany Life Community continuum of care. Every Tuesday at 4 p.m. the service of manicures are provided to the tenants. This is a great way to meet tenants and socialize with them. Your duties would be to help remove old polish, trim or file nails, and apply new polish. The tenants are always very appreciative of the volunteer's help and are very enjoyable to chat with.
SOCIALIZE OVER COFFEE
Bethany Manor
Every afternoon at 2 p.m. Bethany Manor has a coffee hour provided for residents and visitors. Volunteers are welcome to come sit, visit, and enjoy some snacks and coffee or tea with the residents. This is a great way to meet new residents and hear some of their amazing life stories.
MUSICIAN
Bethany Manor, Story City
Play, sing, or otherwise provide music or entertainment for residents.
BAKER
Bethany Manor, Story City
Help residents and tenants at Cedar Place and Bethany Manor bake cookies and breads.
HAIR CARE VOLUNTEER
Bethany Manor, Story City
Do hair sets for residents (no shampooing required). Tuesday and Thursday, 8:30 to 10:30 a.m.
ACTIVITIES VOLUNTEER
Bethany Manor
Participate in social activities with residents of Bethany Manor.
ASSISTED LIVING FUN FITNESS LEADER
Bethany Manor
The residents and tenants love to have a volunteer share fitness activities that are low impact and fun. Chair exercise and music programs are available to help the volunteer lead and interact with the seniors. Fitness fun is usually on Tuesday, Wednesday, and Thursday morning at 10:30 a.m. and trivia games and coffee time follow this event.
WATER OR RE-POT PLANTS AS NEEDED
Bethany Manor
We need a volunteer to lovingly care for the potted plants inside Bethany Manor and outside during the growing season. We receive many donations of plants, and they are in need of a green thumb. The plants need to be watered twice a week and we could have two volunteers share this opportunity.
]]></text></news-item>