<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRX-M401-DXJR-H206"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Right mix of speculation, hedging to deepen commodity exchanges: Forward Markets Commission chief</title><source>The Economic Times</source><author>Ram Sahgal</author><text><![CDATA[MUMBAI: Traders and physical market users who trade on domestic commodity futures exchanges may soon witness a deepening of the decade-old market.
To encourage more physical market users to hedge on domestic commodity bourses, regulator Forward Markets Commission (FMC) will soon write to the finance ministry, under which it functions, suggesting that it urge banks to ask their clients to trade on exchanges like MCX and NCDEX. FMC will also write to capital markets regulator Sebi to make it mandatory for listed companies to declare their commodity exposure and the unhedged part in their annual accounts.
And finally, to bring uniformity in regulation between agri and non-agri futures, the regulator is planning to relax the daily price limit that farm products traded on six national bourses are subject to.
"We are hopeful that these measures will attract more physical market users to domestic commodity bourses," Ramesh Abhishek, chairman, FMC, told ET. "We will be writing soon to both the finance ministry and Sebi about our suggestions and how they would benefit the market. On the measure to relax daily price limits in agri futures we will soon be inviting public comments before implementing it."
Abhishek explained it was important to ensure a right mix between speculation and hedging on commodity markets. Regulatory and brokerage circles feel that the proportion of hedgers on domestic commodity bourses has to increase to make the market more efficient.
In many commodity contracts it is observed that the open interest, outstanding number of contracts, lags the number of contracts traded (volume), which implies more of day trading than actual hedging of positions.
"Banks lend money to corporates and can urge them to cover their commodity price risk by trading on the futures market just as they make it mandatory for clients to hedge their forex exposure on forwards markets. Similarly, if Sebi directs listed entities to reveal their commodity exposure and unhedged portion in annual accounts (as in the case of forex exposure) this could pressurise them to hedge on the domestic futures bourses, increasing the proportion of actual participation and reducing scope of price manipulation by speculators," he added.
"While nobody can be compelled to hedge on domestic bourses, a proactive stance taken by the ministry and Sebi could pressure actual users to increasingly trade on domestic bourses," said a broker who requested anonymity.
The regulator also plans to relax the 4% price limit on farm futures to 6% and slabs of 3% which is the rule in the case of non-farm commodities like gold, silver, etc. In the underlying market, price limits are not prevalent. If the price of a commodity, say soyabean, increases by 4% on the futures market, trading is halted for the day till prices trade within that range. But this is not the case on the physical market where prices could increase well beyond 4%. In such a situation, those who trade farm futures cannot exit because of this limit and prefer to stay away from the futures market, reducing its connect with the underlying market.
Stocks traded on the futures and options segment of the capital markets are not constrained by any price limit, which should be the case in the commodity futures market too, feel certain market participants. Abhishek said FMC would shortly invite public comments to relax price limits for non-farm futures.
The move to increase participation on futures markets come at a time volumes have dipped by 40% to 95.13 lakh crore in the fiscal year through February from 157.82 lakh crore a year earlier because of the imposition of a transaction tax on non-farm and processed farm futures since July last year and the NSEL fiasco which has dented sentiment.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>