<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRX-2TB1-F0NV-F493"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Group's job is to 'root out' public corruption</title><source>Vincennes Sun-Commercial (Indiana)</source><author>Chris Morris Jeffersonville &amp; New Albany News and Tribune</author><text><![CDATA[NEW ALBANY - Since the creation of the Public Corruption Working Group in 2012 by Joe Hogsett, United States attorney for the Southern District, 30 public officials have been charged for various crimes.
In the two years prior to the formation of the PCWG, only 10 public officials were indicted.
Hogsett said he doesn't think more elected or appointed government employees are breaking the law, but that his office, along with the FBI, are quickly pursuing all tips of wrongdoing.
"With the commitment of the United States Attorney's Office and the FBI, we believe the numbers will increase expeditiously," said Hogsett at a news conference Thursday in the Lee Hamilton Federal Building in New Albany. "We will make every effort to root out public corruption."
Hogsett points to this week's arrests to prove his point that corruption in all levels of government will not be ignored in the southern district.
This week, a Putnam County Sheriff's deputy and Greencastle City Council member was charged with excessive force while the head of the Henry County Department of Child Services and New Castle Community School Board member was charged with perjury and making a false statement to federal law enforcement officials.
And Wednesday, a former senior project manager for the city of Bloomington was subject to a 24-count criminal complaint for allegedly embezzling $800,000 in public funds.
"This has been a busy week," Hogsett said. "The week's effort is proof positive we will make every effort in rooting out public corruption."
Hogsett, and Robert A. Jones, special agent in charge of the Federal Bureau of Investigation Indianapolis Division, said the majority of public officials, whether elected or appointed, are law abiding citizens who work for the betterment of the public. He said there is a small percentage of "law breakers" who the PCWG will "vigorously" investigate and prosecute.
"Our message has been consistent," Hogsett said. "It doesn't matter what your politics are or who you know, if you violate the public trust, this working group will find you, will investigate you and the U.S. Attorney's Office will then prosecute you to the fullest extent of the law," Hogsett said.
Jones said any type of law violations by public officials erodes the community's trust.
"There is no acceptable level of corruption or abuse of power," Jones said.
Hogsett said tips from whistleblowers play a huge role in identifying public corruption.
"Very often public corruption prosecutions can be traced back to an anonymous tip," he said. "We encourage anyone with knowledge of such behavior to contact the working group through this hotline."
The hotline number is 317-229-2443.
"Our message today to Southern Indiana officeholders is we are proud of the job you do, but you do have a high degree of expectations," Hogsett said. "If you violate those high standards you will be held accountable."
]]></text></news-item>