<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRX-JS31-F0JP-W24Y"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Our blind eye to blatant abuse</title><source>Hobart Mercury (Australia)</source><author>GREG BARNS</author><text><![CDATA[The Abbott government is fast leading Australia into the territory of this nation becoming a pariah in the international community when it comes to upholding human rights values.
The appalling mistreatment of human beings in the gulags of Nauru and Manus Island are bringing much deserved opprobrium on a nation that is supposed to champion freedom and respect. And Mr Abbott, and his Foreign Minister Julie Bishop, are also attracting attention for their fierce defence of the corrupt and violent Sri Lankan government.
The Sri Lankan government of President Mahinda Rajapaksa has been, and is responsible today for gross human rights abuses against the country's Tamil population. This is a matter of fact. Yet Mr Abbott and his government turns a blind eye to all this simply because Sri Lanka helps Australia's paranoid and xenophobic asylum seeker policies.
In 2009 President Rajapaksa's brother Gotabaya was Sri Lanka's Defence Minister. He co-ordinated the Sri Lankan military's final crushing of the 25-year Tamil insurgency.
It is alleged that about 40,000 civilians, including many women and children, died at the hands of the Sri Lankan military when they surged against 300,000 Tamils who had been forced into a narrow beach area in northeastern Sri Lanka.
At last November's Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting where Mr Abbott cosied up to his Sri Lankan hosts, British Prime Minister David Cameron put President Rajapaksa on notice that he and his government had four months to announce and commence an independent inquiry into the 2009 massacre.
The failure by Sri Lanka to do so saw Mr Cameron announce last week he is pushing for a UN vote to secure an inquiry. "Ahead of the vote, we are working hard to secure support from other countries. The PM has personally written to a number of leaders whose countries are on the human rights council this session calling on them to support this resolution which would help to deliver progress on reconciliation and human rights in Sri Lanka," Mr Cameron's office said last Monday.
Even the United States is supporting UN action. Its Assistant Secretary of State Nisha Biswal said on February 2, after a trip to Sri Lanka; "Lack of progress in Sri Lanka has led to great deal of frustration and scepticism in my government and in the international community. There hasn't been sufficient action taken by the government to address the issues of justice and accountability. We heard from many people about people who are still unaccounted for, whose whereabouts and fates are unknown to their family members." London and Washington are Mr Abbott's favourite allies and normally he and Ms Bishop clamour to be joined at the hip on any serious foreign policy pronouncement from those nations.
At last November's CHOGM meeting Mr Abbott's sycophancy towards President Rajapaksa was nauseating. There was none of Mr Cameron's principled criticism but instead fawning praise for a political leader who is a thug. Mr Abbott callously dismissed concerns about the Sri Lankan government's use of torture and wholesale slaughter by saying that while Australia "deplores the use of torture we accept that sometimes in difficult circumstances difficult things happen".
Mr Abbott thinks Sri Lanka today is a wonderful place to live - a booming economy and more freedom, he said at CHOGM. What a pity no one else thinks that besides the Sri Lankan government and its PR machine.
The US envoy Ms Biswal said last month: "We are concerned about the worsening situation with respect to human rights ... as well as the weakening of the rule of law and an increase in the levels of corruption and impunity. All of these factors lead to undermine the proud tradition of democracy in Sri Lanka." Mr Abbott and Ms Bishop seem prepared to be willing to turn a half blind eye to the Sri Lankan government's past and present sins for the sake of ensuring that Colombo maintains a hard line on those fleeing the country to seek asylum in Australia.
Foreign policy is always untidy and compromises are often the order of the day, but Australia's international reputation is looking awful under the stewardship of Mr Abbott and Ms Bishop.
The Sri Lankan government is beyond the pale and it does not matter what political benefit there may be for Australia in soft-pedalling on well documented abuse of human rights. This country should join its allies in ensuring that the victims of Sri Lankan government violence are able to seek justice.The fact that Mr Abbott and Ms Bishop are prepared to trash Australia's reputation as a nation that believes that the rule of law and liberal democratic values are universal should concern all Australians.
]]></text></news-item>