<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRX-8HK1-JBKB-W0NT"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Here's how to agree to disagree</title><source>THE DALLAS MORNING NEWS</source><author>STEVE BLOW, Sblow@dallasnews.com dallasnews.com/thescoopblog</author><text><![CDATA[A reader, Ron Case of Dallas, recently emailed a heartfelt letter of concern about our country. And I responded with some thoughts of my own.
Only later did it occur to me that our exchange might be good fodder for a wider discussion.
So while I wish I'd said more in my reply, I mostly want to hear your thoughts.
Steve, I am not a right wing nut. I am just a very concerned American conservative who is fed up with all the blaming of Bush, all the lies about Benghazi, the use of the IRS by one party to destroy the other party, the lies about spying on Americans, the more and more restrictions being put upon individuals and companies by a controlling federal government.
And most of all I am really down on the people who call themselves "journalists" and don't ask the hard questions that they should be asking to keep our "leaders" in line with the truth. They, more than anyone, are the guardians of a free society and they are, for the most part, in lock step with one party….
Man, I remembered how the media went after Richard Nixon, as they should have, and he was forced from office. Benghazi was a bungled mess and the cover-up that followed was far worse than Watergate. Yet the main media has done little to nothing about getting to the real truth.
The 2012 election was dramatically affected by the IRS holding up conservative groups' requests for a 501(c)(3) or (4). That produced a chill on the donors. What has the main media done about that?
ABC, CBS, NBC have reporters who have called the Tea Party a racist group, yet they provide no proof. They give the Tea Party little if any coverage but gave overwhelming coverage to those folks who appeared in Washington and other locations… [the Occupy Wall Street movement].
I never thought I would see the day that our president would put his hand on a Bible and swear to uphold and defend the Constitution and then turn around and enforce only the laws he agrees with and ignores the others.
Our country is a Republic, a nation of laws. If we no longer abide by the law - all the laws - we are a banana republic, fresh meat for a dictatorship!
May God help us!
-Ron
Ron, I don't think you are a right wing nut, but I think you have been fed a lot of propaganda that gives you a very distorted view of what's going on in our country. Things are not nearly as bad as you describe.
Of course, you have also been indoctrinated by these same sources to believe that you can only trust them to give you reliable information. Because of this, you are scoffing right now and saying that this is a typical response from the "lamestream media." That's how propaganda works. It undermines other points of view before even hearing them.
There is a grain of truth in all the issues you raise, but only a grain. You have been fed a greatly exaggerated view of each one. There is a very deliberate attempt to frighten you because fear is one of the best ways of manipulating people.
Fear mongering, it's called. If I can scare you, I can also influence your behavior - whether that's voting for a certain candidate or donating money to a certain cause or spreading more fear.
My advice: Try to widen your sources of information. Go to "Google News" and search on any of the topics you mention. You will find a wide range of stories about them that might give you a more balanced and accurate perspective.
We certainly have plenty of serious issues facing the country. But the sky is not falling. And we need a calm, reasoned search for solutions, not a doomsday mindset that could lead us to some bad decisions.
I hope some of this makes sense to you. I have taken the time to write all this because I think you are not a nut but someone truly wanting the best for our country.
-Steve
OK, what thoughts are sparked in you? Lots to talk about there.
I'm struck by how the political divide in our country is rooted in vastly different perceptions of reality. Ron and I are good examples of that.
How do we get to good, productive debate when we start from such different places?
Comment online for a good public discussion. Or send me an email (sblow@dallasnews.com) if you'd rather. If response warrants, we'll continue the discussion next Sunday.
Ron and I managed to be cordial and respectful. I hope you will, too.
Follow Steve Blow on Twitter at @DMNSteveBlow and on Facebook at facebook.com/DMNSteveBlow.
]]></text></news-item>