<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRX-B2S1-JCB3-40N8"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Vallejo council to hold study session on North Mare Island</title><source>Vallejo Times Herald (California)</source><author>By Tony Burchyns/ Times-Herald staff writer/</author><text><![CDATA[The Vallejo City Council will hold a study session Tuesday to review options with respect to North Mare Island in light of several new proposals from developers.
Last July, the council said the city should seek funding for demolition of derelict structures abandoned when the naval base shut down in 1996. The council also said it wanted to explore development ideas that would create jobs and tax revenue for the city.
Council members were also clear that residential development on this portion of the island shouldn't be considered.
Last week city officials said they've received six proposals from six different groups. The proposals include:
* An industrial warehouse facility;
* A high-tech business campus with a possible lodging and tourist destinations, such as a wine-tasting facility and shopping;
* A hotel-casino;
* A veterans' housing community.
While the navy was obligated to clean the land, it was not obligated to demolish the buildings, which contain hazardous materials such as lead paint, asbestos and mercury. The cost of demolishing all 32 buildings has been estimated at more than $10 million, according to the city.
The removal of one building is currently underway at a cost of $700,000.
The purpose of Tuesday's session is for the council to express concerns or support for the various proposals. The proposals are still preliminary in nature, officials said, and further due diligence and negotiation would be needed to determine their merits.
Should the council be receptive to one or more of the proposals, officials said they could return as soon as June with a more detailed project proposal.
The study session is scheduled to begin at 6:30 p.m. at City Hall, 555 Santa Clara St.
]]></text></news-item>