<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRX-7781-JDKC-R4V9"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>THE NEED FOR AN UNITED ASIAN NATIONS ORGANIZATION</title><source>Daily News (Sri Lanka)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Sri Lanka, March 17 -- "The West won the world not by the superiority of its ideas or values or religion (.) but rather by its superiority in applying organized violence. Westerners often forget this fact; non-Westerners never do." - Samuel P. Huntington - The Clash of Civilizations and the Remaking of World Order-Touchstone Books-1996
It is no secret that the West is militaristic and imperialistic and has traumatized other nations through colonial terror. Individualism which is the hallmark of Western culture is the source of all the conflicts created by the West. Western power is fearful to other countries in the world.
The West alone decides whether satellites would be used to educate the people of other nations or drop bombs on them presently by using drone attacks. It crushes the potentialities of the people of the developing nations and invades their lives with its imported products and televised movies that crowd the air waves. It besieges their markets and controls their merest resources and initiatives.
The West creates its power through military research and then sells their products to developing countries who are its passive consumers. To liberate developing countries like Sri Lanka among other nations, we have to liberate ourselves from this subservience.
To a great extent, the rise of the West depended upon the exercise of force, upon the fact that the military balance between the Europeans and their adversaries was steadily tilting in favour of the former which was the key to the success of the Westerners in creating the first truly global empires between 1500 and 1750 AD, which depended precisely upon these developments in their ability to wage war, which has been termed by some writers as 'the military revolution'.
The expansion of the West was also further facilitated by its superiority in organization, discipline and training of its troops. This was further buttressed by their superior weapons, transport logistics and medical services resulting from its leadership of the Industrial Revolution that took place in the West.
When one considers the power of the West in relation to other civilizations two clear pictures emerge. The first is of the overwhelming, triumphant, almost total Western dominance. The disintegration of the Soviet Union removed the only serious challenger to the West and as a result the world is and will be dominated for some time to come by the goals, priorities and interests of the principal Western nations.
As the one remaining super power the United States together with Britain and France make the crucial decisions on political and security issues while the United States with Germany and Japan made the crucial decisions on economic issues. This scenario is changing now with China entering the picture. The West is the only civilization that has substantial interests in every other civilization or regions of the world due to colonialism. Thus it has the ability to affect the politics, economics and security of every other civilization or regions of the world. Developing nations often need Western help to achieve their goals and protect their interests.
From this ability emanates the basis of economic and other sanctions presently utilized to tame the developing nations such as Iran who refuse to toe the line of the West. In brief, Western nations own and operate the international banking system, control all hard currencies and dominate international capital markets. While being a producer of the majority of world's finished products it is also the principal customer of purchasing the finished products of developing nations. It controls sea lanes and dominates the aero space industry and access to space. It conducts advanced research and development and dominates the high-tech weapon industry and hence is capable of massive military interventions.
The second picture of the West is very different from the above as it has become a civilization in decline at the present time.
Its share of world political, economic and military power is declining compared to that of other civilizations. The West is increasingly concerned with its internal problems and needs such as slow economic growth, stagnating populations, unemployment, huge government deficits, a declining work ethic, low saving rates, and in many countries such as the United States social disintegration, drugs and crime. Economic power is steadily shifting to Asia with China rapidly rising to the top and military and political influences are starting to follow suit. India is on the verge of economic take off and the Islamic world is becoming increasingly hostile to the West.
The willingness of other nations to accept the dictates of the West or abide by its sermons of human rights violations, while the West themselves are involved in massive violations of human rights all over the world, is rapidly evaporating and so is the West's self confidence and will to dominate. As the West's primacy erodes, much of its power will simply evaporate and the rest will be diffused on a regional basis among the several major civilizations and their core states.
The most significant increases m power are accruing and will accrue to Asian civilizations, with China gradually emerging as the society most likely to challenge the West for global influence. These shifts in power among civilizations are leading and will lead to the revival and increased cultural assertiveness of non-Western societies and to their increasing rejection of Western culture. It appears probable that for most of history China had the world's largest economy. The diffusion of technology and the economic development of non-Western societies in the second half of the twentieth century are now producing a return to the historical pattern. This will be a slow process, but by the middle of the twenty-first century, if not before, the distribution of economic product and manufacturing output among the leading civilizations is likely to resemble that of 1800. The two-hundred-year Western "blip" on the world economy will be over.
The failures of the United States with respect to Asia stemmed primarily from the increasing economic wealth and self-confidence of Asian governments. Asian publicists repeatedly reminded the West that the old age of dependence and subordination was past. The ability of Asian regimes to resist Western human rights pressures was reinforced by several factors. American and European businesses were desperately anxious to expand their trade with and their investment in these rapidly growing countries and subjected their governments to intense pressure not to disrupt economic relations with them. In addition, Asian countries saw such pressure as an infringement on their sovereignty and rallied to each other's support when these issues arose. Taiwanese, Japanese, and Hong Kong businessmen who invested in China had a major interest in China's retaining its MFN privileges with the United States. The Japanese government generally distanced itself from American human rights policies: "We will not let abstract notions of human rights affect our relations with China", the then Prime Minister of Japan Kiichi Miyazawa said not long after Tiananmen Square.
The countries of ASEAN were unwilling to apply pressure to Myanmar and, indeed, in 1994 welcomed the military junta to their meeting while the European Union, as its spokesman said, had to recognize that its policy "had not been very successful" and that it would have to go along with the ASEAN approach to Myanmar. In addition, their growing economic power allowed states such as Malaysia and Indonesia to apply "reverse conditionalities" to countries and firms which criticize them or engage in other behavior they find objectionable. Overall the growing economic strength of the Asian countries renders them increasingly immune to Western pressure concerning human rights and democracy. "Today China's economic power," Richard Nixon observed in 1994, "makes U.S. lectures about human rights imprudent. Within a decade it will make them irrelevant. Within two decades it will make them laughable." However, Chinese economic development has at the present time made Western sermons unnecessary. Economic growth is strengthening in Asian governments in relation to Western governments. In the longer run it will also strengthen Asian societies in relation to Asian governments.
Western efforts to promote human rights and democracy in U.N. agencies generally came to naught. With a few exceptions, such as those condemning Iraq, human rights resolutions were almost always defeated in U.N. votes. Apart from some Latin American countries, other governments were reluctant to enlist in efforts to promote what many saw as "human rights imperialism." In 1990, for instance, Sweden submitted on behalf of twenty Western nations a resolution condemning the military regime in Myanmar, but opposition from Asian and other countries defeated it. Resolutions condemning Iran for human rights abuses were also voted down, and for five straight years in the 1990s China was able to mobilize Asian support to defeat Western-sponsored resolutions expressing concern over its human rights violations.
In 1994 Pakistan tabled a resolution in the U.N. Commission on Human Rights condemning India's rights violations in Kashmir. Countries friendly to India rallied against it, but so also did two of Pakistan's closest friends, China and Iran, who had been the targets of similar measures, and who persuaded Pakistan to withdraw the proposal. In failing to condemn Indian brutality in Kashmir, The Economist observed, the U.N. Human Rights Commission "by default, sanctioned it. Other countries, too, are getting away with murder: Turkey, Indonesia, Colombia, and Algeria have all escaped criticism. The commission is thus giving succor to governments that practice butchery and torture, which is exactly the opposite of what its creators intended.
With the above backdrop in mind If we now turn to the Preamble to the Constitution of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) which was signed on November 16, 1945, subsequent to World War II and came into force on 4 November 1946 after ratification by twenty countries: Australia, Brazil, Canada, China, Czechoslovakia, Denmark, Dominican Republic, Egypt, France, Greece, India, Lebanon, Mexico, New Zealand, Norway, Saudi Arabia, South Africa, Turkey, United Kingdom, United States, which states inter alia "That since wars begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of men that the defences of peace must be constructed; That ignorance of each other's ways and lives has been a common cause, throughout the history of mankind, of that suspicion and mistrust between the peoples of the world through which their differences have all too often broken into war" it is evident that it has recognized the cherished principles enshrined in Buddhist philosophy which holds that it is the human mind that is supreme. The Charter of UNESCO in its Preamble further clarifies the notion of peace among men as follows:
That the great and terrible war which has now ended (referring to World War II) was a war made possible by the denial of the democratic principles of the dignity, equality and mutual respect of men, and by the propagation, in their place, through ignorance and prejudice, of the doctrine of the inequality of men and races; That the wide diffusion of culture, and the education of humanity for justice and liberty and peace are indispensable to the dignity of man and constitute a sacred duty which all the nations must fulfill in a spirit of mutual assistance and concern; That a peace based exclusively upon the political and economic arrangements of governments would not be a peace which could secure the unanimous, lasting and sincere support of the peoples of the world, and that the peace must therefore be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the intellectual and moral solidarity of mankind.
The above thoughts stand in contra-distinction to the inquisitorial and discriminatory stance adopted by the UNHRC towards the developing nations in the world such as Sri Lanka. The UNESCO Charter further states: In consequence whereof they do hereby create the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization for the purpose of advancing, through the educational and scientific and cultural relations of the peoples of the world, the objectives of international peace and of the common welfare of mankind for which the United Nations Organization was established and which its Charter proclaims. Thus it is evident that international peace and of the common welfare of mankind are the stated objectives for which the United Nations Organization was established and which its Charter proclaims. Is the UNHRC,at the present time engaged in pursuing these goals or persecuting developing nations is the question that now arises.
The hypocritical proceedings, the world is witnessing at present at the UNHRC in Geneva in the name of Protection of Human Rights reminds one of the Spanish Inquisition. It is an abuse of process, that is taking place in the most deplorable manner It becomes obvious and crystal clear that the United Nations Organization has lost sight of its noble objectives stated above and now become the cat's paw and the lackey of Western powers attempting to subjugate the developing nations such as Sri Lanka by acting on the dictates of the West.
The West has now lost all credibility among other nations in the world with their on going attempts to pressurize Sri Lanka on unproven human rights abuses. The time has now emerged for the Asian Nations to come together and initiate proceedings to hold an international conference of all the Asian Nations which include the nations of West Asia which may result in the formation of a United Asian Nations Organization (UANO), which would undoubtedly emerge as a formidable force to defeat the aggression of the West towards the developing countries in Asia such as our motherland, Sri Lanka.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Daily News Sri Lanka. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>