<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRX-7S11-F11P-X37R"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Proposed bill blocking sale of 'strategic assets' to foreign hands could kill Tnuva sale</title><source>Jpost.com (The Jerusalem Post online edition)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[MK Yishai Braverman(Labor) seeks to protect "local manufacture, local employment, workers' rights and competition."

A new bill seeks to limit the sale of Israeli companies to foreigners, in light of Tnuva's sale to China's state-owned Bright Foods company.
MK Avishai Braverman (Labor) submitted legislation that is meant to prevent "the sale of strategic assets to foreign hands." Braverman's proposal would require a committee appointed by the Economy Minister to regulate foreign purchases of Israeli companies and ensure a seed of Israeli control in essential industry. The committee would include three government representatives, including the Economy Minister, a representative of the Manufacturers' Association, a Histadrut Labor Union representative and two economists. The legislation would apply to the sale of any company with 1,000 or more employees or that receives NIS 5 million or more aid from the government. If the committee finds that the deal would harm the public interest, then it may block it. "Unlike Israeli industrialists, foreign managers may not give enough weight to matters that are important to Israelis, like encouraging local manufacture, local employment, workers' rights and competition," Braverman explained. "Foreign owners could have a negative influence on the company's local activity and could move parts of the company abroad without considering potential social and economic ramifications of such an action." The Labor MK already gathered 46 signatures on his bill, including opposition chairman Isaac Herzog (Labor), Knesset Finance Committee chairman Nissan Slomiansky (Bayit Yehudi), Knesset Labor, Health and Welfare Committee chairman Haim Katz (Likud) and several other coalition MKs. "Large corporations in the market have knowledge and strategic assets and employ tens of thousands of workers. We need to make every effort to keep them in Israeli hands," Braverman stated. News that Tnuva, Israel's largest dairy manufacturer, was in negotiations with China's state-owned Bright Foods Corporation, caused an uproar in February, and led Braverman to spearhead Knesset Economics Committee on the subject. In April, Canada's PotashCorp dropped a bid to acquire Israel Chemicals over fear that the company would close down plants in Israel and move operations across the border to Jordan, leaving hundreds of families in the Negev unemployed. Israel's Potash, critics said, were a natural resource that should benefit the nation, not be put on sale to foreign corporations.
Israel would not be the first country to regulate foreign ownership of strategic markets. In the United States, for example, the FCC must approve sale of more than 25% of a television or radio broadcasting company to foreigners. Yoav Chelouche, a Managing Partner at Aviv Venture Capital, says that though Israel suffers from over-regulation, such a committee would probably not affect most businesses. "We have exits every year, most of them wouldn't fall under the category of being strategic or a monopoly or a national treasure," he said. All rights reserved © The Jerusalem Post 1995 - 2014 Provided by Syndigate.info, an Albawaba.com company
]]></text></news-item>