<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BRX-M401-DXJR-H2GR"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Kolhapur Municipal Corporation told to pay Rs 7.42 crore in five days</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Abhijeet Patil</author><text><![CDATA[KOLHAPUR: The state irrigation department has given the Kolhapur Municipal Corporation (KMC) five days to pay the dues of Rs 7.42 crore for lifting charges for drinking water from the Panchaganga and Tulashi river, failing which, the department will stop lifting water from these rivers.
At present, the KMC lifts 120 million litres per day (MLD) water from three sources - the Bhogavati river (8 km), the Panchganga river via Kasaba Bawada (6 km) and via Shingnapur (11km) and the Kalamba tank (3km). The irrigation department charges KMC Rs 30 lakh per month for its daily usage at the rate of Rs 4.20 per 10,000 litres of water.
The Kolhapur division of the irrigation department had penalized the KMC for failing to prevent pollution of the river water. The irrigation department issued a notice to the KMC on Saturday.
Deputy executive engineer of the irrigation department Vijay Patil said, "Since 1992, the water lifting schemes at Balinga, Shingnapur and Kasaba Bawda were transferred to the KMC for operation. According to the rules of the water use for non-irrigation purposes, the local body has to pay for the water it lifts for supply to the residents. Since the KMC has not paid the charges on time, the dues have gone up to Rs 7.42 crore. If they fail to pay the dues, we will stop the KMC from lifting water from the rivers."
Moreover, a state government issued orders in November 2013 that non-irrigation water users, including the civic bodies, gram panchayats and industries, would be penalized with double tariff if they fail to adopt pollution control measures.
"The civic administration has failed to take timely measures to check the pollution of the rivers and therefore we have charged them double tariff while calculating the dues. The dues comprise the penalty of around Rs 20 lakh till December last year," added Patil.
Civic officials said the irrigation department too has pay the KMC dues of Rs 8.50 lakh water charges.
KMC's chief hydraulic engineer Manish Pawar said, "We have paid Rs 2.75 crore and the remaining will be paid soon. Since the irrigation department too has dues with us, it will be deducted and the total sum will be paid."
However, senior civic officials said the civic body may not be able to pay the dues in the given time considering its poor financial condition. A civic official said, "The civic body will not be able to pay the total dues at one go. The civic administration can request the irrigation department to allow it to pay only the principal amount now to avoid water cuts."
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>