<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS0-RNB1-JC8W-6388"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Bangladesh: Primark pays $10m more to Rana Plaza victims: Hopes that move will spur other retailers' donations 581 workers or their families to benefit directly</title><source>The Guardian (London)</source><author>Sarah Butler</author><text><![CDATA[Primark is to pay out a further $10m (£6m) in compensation to victims of the Rana Plaza factory collapse in Bangladesh weeks before the anniversary of the disaster in which more than 1,100 garment workers lost their lives.
The British retailer has agreed to pay $9m to the 581 workers, or their families, from New Wave Bottoms, Primark's supplier, which was based on the second floor of the building in Dhaka. A further $1m will go into a communal compensation pot to be shared among all the 3,600 workers who suffered when the eight-floor Rana Plaza complex collapsed in April last year.
Both payments should be made under the auspices of a compensation scheme backed by UN agency the International Labour Organisation (ILO), under a deal agreed over the weekend.
Campaigners hope Primark's payment will help persuade other retailers linked to the Rana Plaza building to pay up. The latest round of payouts will bring Primark's total compensation bill to $12m after it paid out $2m in short-term support for all workers within the building.
The new compensation agreement will not be finalised formally until the compensation fund's co-ordinating committee - which also includes the Bangladeshi government, factory representatives and workers' rights groups - meets tomorrow.
Primark's desire to make its payments as soon as possible is being weighed against the ILO's battle to ensure that compensation comes via the communal process so that no victims are short-changed.
There are concerns that variations in the timing or amount of payments to different groups of victims might lead to unrest in Bangladesh, which has already seen widespread protests over treatment of workers.
However, before Primark's donation, the communal pot contained less than $5m of the total $40m thought to be needed to compensate all the Rana Plaza victims. Gilbert Houngbo, deputy director general of the ILO, said: "We hope that Primark's payment will bring the debate out so that people will ask other brands 'What are you doing?' We urge other retailers to show good faith and make a donation."
Paul Lister, company secretary of Primark's owner, ABF, said: "We are determined to meet this responsibility to workers in our supply chain. We are therefore pleased to be in a position to now press ahead with payments. We support the ILO in urging other retailers sourcing from Rana Plaza to donate to the trust fund, so that it can pay out in full to the remaining victims."
Primark is only the eighth brand to publicly confirm it has paid into the scheme and its support will boost efforts to raise $40m to help injured factory workers and the families of those who died. Donations from Bonmarche, El Corte Ingles, Inditex, Mango, Mascot, Premier Clothing and Loblaw have been confirmed, but make up less than a quarter of the total needed.
The Guardian has learned at least three other brands linked to the Rana Plaza have paid into the fund. C&A, the Dutch retailer that had sourced from within the factory until about 18 months before it collapsed, said it had donated $500,000 while KiK, the German discount clothing retailer, and Cropp, a Polish brand, also said they had donated. This is not confirmed on the ILO website.
Retailers including Benetton, which stopped sourcing from the Rana Plaza some months before it collapsed, and Matalan have paid into separate schemes to support some workers disabled by the accident. However, it is not known how much they have put into these schemes and they have yet to donate anything to the communal fund. Some companies have yet to confirm any compensation payments.
]]></text></news-item>