<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS0-XFN1-JDJN-6290"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Protection of environment</title><source>Kuwait Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Labeed Abdal Many people believe that there is an inverse relation between environment and oil, in the sense that the former always falls victim to the global race of oil production. Oil is considered a lifeblood by countries of the region, and the main source of income for the economies of the Gulf Cooperation Council countries, who are also active OPEC members. But the importance of oil for the region should also evoke efforts to show similar importance to environmental issues, and not the other way round as happening today.
Oil production is usually mentioned in debates about air, water and soil pollution in the region. In order to address this situation, Gulf states must take serious efforts to protect the environment and seek help of foreign and domestic environmental consultants to achieve that goal. For example, governments can use help of consultation offices for best environmentally-friendly ways for waste management and recycling. Meanwhile, the public and private sectors are required to cooperate when it comes to protecting the environment from violations that include unsafe waste disposal, which continues to happen in Kuwait due to lack of monitoring or to save money that would be used to acquire internationally- approved waste management methods. The Environment Public Authority, which is the Kuwaiti government's environmental body, needs to play the role of environmental police to prevent direct or indirect damage to the environment or any of its components. A clean environment must be transformed into a common goal of top priority over the years. Children must be taught the principles of protecting the environment through cooperation between the family and school. But in order to make sure that environment protection efforts are effective, the judiciary's role must be activated through court cases to convict environment offenders, such as companies that can be fined or even face closure in cases of serious pollution. By Labeed Abdal local@kuwaittimes.net
]]></text></news-item>