<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS1-SNS1-DYR7-V2BH"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Friday's Top Stories in the United States</title><source>The Main Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[* The week ahead will feature housing data, the next meeting of the Federal Open Market Committee and the first press conference by newly appointed Fed Chair Janet Yellen. The big news at the week's Fed meeting could be a seismic change in the committee's forward guidance, which for more than a year has relied on the so-called "thresholds" for the unemployment rate and inflation as the primary tools for communicating long-term monetary policy. Federal Reserve President William Dudley recently stated that the Fed may change this approach in favor of more "qualitative" guidance, removing the thresholds altogether, and that such a change could happen as soon as the next meeting.
* The FOMC's policy statement will be released Wednesday at 2:00 p.m. ET, along with the committee's monetary policy and economic projections. Yellen's press conference will follow at 2:30 p.m. ET. Housing data to be released next week include the National Association of Home Builder's March housing market index Monday at 10:00 a.m. ET, February housing starts Tuesday at 8:30 a.m. ET, and February existing home sales Thursday at 10:00 a.m. ET.
* Other data to be released in the week ahead include initial jobless claims Thursday at 8:30 a.m. ET, the February Consumer Price Index Tuesday at 8:30 a.m. ET, February leading economic indicators Thursday at 10:00 a.m. ET, February industrial production Monday at 9:15 a.m. ET, January Treasury International Capital flows Monday at 9:00 a.m. ET, and the Mortgage Bankers Association's mortgage applications index Wednesday at 7:00 a.m. ET. Also the Philadelphia Federal Reserve's March business outlook survey comes out Thursday at 10:00 a.m. ET and the New York Federal Reserve's Empire State manufacturing index Monday will be at 8:30 a.m. ET.
* The FDIC Friday filed a lawsuit against the 16 largest banks, charging fraudulent collusion to influence LIBOR interest rate settings, harming the 38 banks for which the regulator is received. The FDIC's action followed several settlements already reached with banks for admitted manipulation and suppression of the LondonInterbank Offered Rate, the benchmark index for trillions of dollars in interest-rate swaps and loans that plays a fundamentally important role in financial systems throughout the world. The lawsuit gives the FDIC a chance to participate in such settlements.
* In response to the mounting Ukraine crisis, global investors have been buying gold and U.S. Treasuries aggressively since the start of the month. In currencies, FX carry trades have been unwound and the yen and Swiss franc have benefited. The euro has been propelled higher by a perception of a shift in European Central Bank rate policy as well as by unwinds of euro short positions and many emerging market currencies have firmed also as U.S. Treasury yields fell. Secretary of State John Kerry Friday reiterated the United State's stance that Russia will face international consequences if it doesn't change course with respect to Ukraine and its standoff over Crimea.
* Oil prices were surprisingly calm Friday. NYMEX April light sweet crude settled up $0.69 at $98.89 per barrel, after trading in a $97.55 (Wednesday) to $102.82 (Monday) range this week.
* On the FX front, despite ECB President Mario Draghi's admonishment Thursday suggesting the euro was too high, the pair romped back over $1.3900 to post a high of $1.3936, a bit shy of the $1.3967 high seen a day earlier. The euro was closing the week at $1.3907, up from overnight lows around $1.3846, as well as the week's low of $1.3834, seen Tuesday.
* U.S. stocks Friday were off the best levels of the week, but surprisingly buoyant given the risk aversion in the market. The S&P 500 closed down 0.28% at 1841.13 Friday, after trading in a 1840.36 (Friday) to 1882.35 (Tuesday) range this week. The index posted a life-time high of 1883.57 last Friday after the February non-farm payroll release.
* U.S. consumer sentiment fell in the first half of March, as consumers' view of current conditions rose but expectations for the future dropped to their lowest level in four months, according to the University of Michigan Consumer Sentiment survey released Friday. The preliminary reading of the March consumer sentiment index was far below expectations, reported at 79.9 - the lowest since November 2013 - compared to 81.6 in February and 81.2 in January. The index was at 82.5 in December and 75.1 in November.
* February's bad weather cut store traffic and forced some retailers to cut prices at the same time it forced milk and natural gas prices higher, with the net effect an unexpected decline in overall wholesale prices. The Bureau of Labor Statistics Friday issued its second monthly Producer Price Index report based on new methodology - which melds the dampening effect of services prices with the excursion upward of goods prices to end up with a 0.1% decline for "final demand." The small minus was the result of final demand services falling 0.3% for the month in contrast to the increase of final demand goods of 0.4%. Senior BLS analyst Scott Sager told MNI shortly before the report's publication that weather was a a factor "consistently across the major categories." Retailers found weather diminished their "foot traffic," he said, and tried to compensate with discounts, driving apparel, footwear and accessories retail margins down a record 9.3%.
* Standard & Poor's Ratings Services has affirmed its 'BB+' rating on the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico's general obligation debt, and affirmed the ratings on various general fund-supported and highways and transportation authority debt. At the same time, Standard & Poor's has removed the ratings from CreditWatch, where they had been placed with negative implications earlier this year. The outlook on the debt is negative, reflecting long-term economic and financial trends.
]]></text></news-item>