<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS1-X3T1-F0CC-S2PY"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Infosys Limited Infosys Signs Agreement with Volvo Car Corporation</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[PRESS RELEASE
Infosys Signs Multi-Year Application Development Services Agreement with Volvo Car Corporation
Bangalore and Stockholm - March 17, 2014: Infosys, a global leader in consulting, technology and outsourcing solutions, has been selected by Volvo Cars as a strategic supplier to provide application development services for its global operations. This agreement builds on the long-standing relationship as Infosys has been supporting Volvo Cars since 2010 to rationalize and integrate its enterprise systems.
As part of the new agreement, Infosys will:
* Bring its proven global service delivery experience and ability to drive innovation and transformation - efficiently and effectively
* Develop applications to support multiple domains, including marketing and sales, customer service, manufacturing, product development, and corporate functions
* Deploy best practices specifically related to business process harmonization and delivery excellence, across transformation projects
Quote
Nitesh Bansal, Vice President Manufacturing Europe, Infosys:
"We will be a strategic supplier for Volvo Cars to deliver excellence and innovation to transform their IT landscape to a modern architecture. We are very pleased to collaborate with Volvo Cars in their strategic journey. We have an industry heritage, deep automotive expertise and established track record of delivering that leaves us well positioned to be a strategic supplier to Volvo Cars. This agreement also reflects our strategic focus on the Nordic market and strengthens our presence in Sweden."
About Infosys
Infosys is a global leader in consulting, technology and outsourcing solutions. We enable clients, in more than 30 countries, to stay a step ahead of emerging business trends and outperform the competition. We help them transform and thrive in a changing world by co-creating breakthrough solutions that combine strategic insights and execution excellence. Visit www.infosys.com to see how Infosys (NYSE: INFY), with $7.4B in annual revenues and 158,000+ employees, is Building Tomorrow's Enterprise® today.
Safe Harbor
Certain statements in this release concerning our future growth prospects are forward-looking statements, which involve a number of risks and uncertainties that could cause actual results to differ materially from those in such forward-looking statements. The risks and uncertainties relating to these statements include, but are not limited to, risks and uncertainties regarding fluctuations in earnings, fluctuations in foreign exchange rates, our ability to manage growth, intense competition in IT services including those factors which may affect our cost advantage, wage increases in India, our ability to attract and retain highly skilled professionals, time and cost overruns on fixed-price, fixed-time frame contracts, client concentration, restrictions on immigration, industry segment concentration, our ability to manage our international operations, reduced demand for technology in our key focus areas, disruptions in telecommunication networks or system failures, our ability to successfully complete and integrate potential acquisitions, liability for damages on our service contracts, the success of the companies in which Infosys has made strategic investments, withdrawal or expiration of governmental fiscal incentives, political instability and regional conflicts, legal restrictions on raising capital or acquiring companies outside India, and unauthorized use of our intellectual property and general economic conditions affecting our industry. Additional risks that could affect our future operating results are more fully described in our United States Securities and Exchange Commission filings including our Annual Report on Form 20-F for the fiscal year ended March 31, 2013 and on Form 6-K for the quarter ended December 31, 2013. These filings are available at www.sec.gov. Infosys may, from time to time, make additional written and oral forward-looking statements, including statements contained in the company's filings with the Securities and Exchange Commission and our reports to shareholders. The company does not undertake to update any forward-looking statements that may be made from time to time by or on behalf of the company unless it is required by law.
For further information, please contact:
]]></text></news-item>