<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS1-THT1-JCBG-D188"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>MILLIONS DISAPPEARED IN THE COURSE OF MODELING</title><source>DEFENSE and SECURITY (Russia)</source><author>Yury Senatorov</author><text><![CDATA[The second prosecutor's office at restricted objects approved an indictment and sent to the court materials of the case about theft of 14.7 million rubles in 2010 in Gidropress design bureau, structural division of Rosatom, in 2010.
At the beginning of the last year, investigators of the main department of economic security and counteraction to corruption of the Interior Ministry received operational information that in 2010 Gidropress design bureau (structural division of Rosatom group) received 50 million rubles from the federal budget for designing of equipment of the reactor plant of nuclear power generating units, for instance, for designing of three-dimensional modeling of construction part of nuclear power stations and setting up of software for them. Operatives of the Interior Ministry economic security service of Rosatom found out that management of experimental design bureau Gidropress signed several contracts on development of this project with Deputy General Director of Siemens Industry Software Ilya Lavrenov and top manager of this company Anatoly Suzdaltsev.
However, in the course of the check it was found out that in reality the project of creation of a 3D model was done by students of the department of technical machine building of the Belgorod state technical school named after Shukhov and nobody did setting up of the software at all. Along with this, 14.7 million of the allocated 50 million rubles for the work that was not done was transferred to the account of Pilim-Sfera company established by Lavrenov and Suzdaltsev specifically for this project. According to investigators, this money was cashed and appropriated by participants of the criminal group afterwards.
In April of 2013, operatives of the Interior Ministry conducted searches in Gidropress, Siemens Industry Software (SIVS), subsidiary of Siemens AG, and in Pilim-Sfera. The latter turned out to be a dummy company. Searchers were also conducted at the place of residence of Ilya Lavrenov and Anatoly Suzdaltsev, as a result, operatives confiscated the documents that confirmed suspicions of the police. According to the fact of theft of 14.7 million rubles on April 11 of 2012 the investigations department of the Interior Ministry for Vlasikha settlement (restricted military camp Odintsovo-10) instituted a criminal case according to part 4 of article 159 of the Criminal Code (fraud on a very big scale). According to the verdict of the court, both accused were put into custody.
At first, Lavrenov and Suzdaltsev did not confess their guilt but a few months they changed their position. They repented and signed a pre-trial agreement on cooperation with the second prosecutor's office at restricted objects and also requested hearing of the criminal case in accordance with a special procedure.
Another participant appeared in this case too. This is one of the former managers of Gidropress who is not named yet. It is known only that investigators consider him organizer of the theft.
Source: Kommersant, March 13, 2014, p. 4
]]></text></news-item>