<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS1-D2C1-JB4P-V1W9"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Automotive Wiring Harness Market worth USD41 billion by 2014</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ChinaMarketResearchReports.com adds "Global and China Automotive Wiring Harness Industry Report, 2013" to its store that says the global automotive wiring harness market value climb 2.3 percent to USD40.3 billion in 2013, and is expected to reach USD41 billion in 2014, up 1.6% over 2013.
(Photo: http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20140316/MN82697)
Synopsis
Global and China Automotive Wiring Harness Industry Report 2013 includes the following aspects:
1. The current situation of the global automotive market2. The current situation of Chinese automotive market3. Global and China automotive wiring harness industry4. 18 major automotive wiring harness manufacturers
The globalautomotive wiring harness marketvalue climb 2.3 percent to USD40.3 billion in 2013, and is expected to reach USD41 billion in 2014, up 1.6% over 2013. The slow growth is caused by many reasons. The market share of two major Japanese players of automotive wiring harness totals more than 50%, while Japanese Yen devaluates by 24% in 2013, resulting in a significant decline in the market value counted in the U.S. dollar. Also, due to the decline in copper prices as well as the continuous lawsuits against wiring harness price manipulating, manufacturers are forced to reduce prices to please customers.
After the United States fined several large automotive wiring harness companies who controlled prices, the European Union penalized four wiring harness suppliers (Yazaki, Yazaki's European subsidiary SY System Tech, Leoni and Furukawa Electric) with EUR142 million in July 2013. Yazaki suffered the most penalty of EUR125 million, followed by SY System Tech who paid EUR11.05 million, Furukawa Electric EUR4 million and Leoni EUR1.3 million. Sumitomo Electric was exempted from penalty because it reported Cartel monopoly to the European Union.
Order a copy of this report athttp://www.chinamarketresearchreports.com/contacts/purchase.php?name=114672.
In 2013, Furukawa Electric performs most actively in the investment in the field of automotive wiring harness. Furukawa Electric acquired Mitsubishi's automotive connector business in late 2011 to increase investment in the field. In March 2013, the factory of Furukawa Electric in the Philippines was put into operation officially. In May 2013, Furukawa Electric decided to expand its Philippine factory whose Phase II is expected to be put into operation in January 2014. At the end of 2014, Furukawa Electric is expected to gain annual sales of JPY12 billion. Meanwhile, it established a new automotive wiring harness plant in Mexico, which started construction in May 2013 and will go into operation in January 2014. In September 2013, the Shenzhen subsidiary set up Wuhan Furukawa Automotive Systems Co., Ltd. in Wuhan, with an investment of RMB100 million.
In 2013, the most prominent change in the automotive wiring harness market lies in the poor performance of large manufacturers and the excellent performance of medium and small manufacturers. Top three players Yazaki, Sumitomo and Delphi offer high and inflexible prices. With the launch of a large number of high-quality automotive connectors, the technical threshold to automotive wiring harness is lowered. Due to the low output, small and medium-sized automotive manufacturers prefer small and medium-sized automotive wiring harness suppliers or self-production to control costs strictly. For example, the automotive wiring harness of Great Wall Motor is supplied by its subsidiary Baoding Mande Auto Parts Co., Ltd.; BYD's supplier is its Fifteenth Division; Geely is supported by Geely Haoda Automotive Electrics.
Comprehensive Table of Contents and more for the report "Global and China Automotive Wiring Harness Industry Report, 2013" is available athttp://www.chinamarketresearchreports.com/114672.html.
Browse more reports on Automotive & Transportation Industry athttp://www.chinamarketresearchreports.com/cat/automotive-transportation.html.
About Us:
China Market Research Reports is a database of selected syndicated market reports for global and China industries including but not limited to life sciences, information technology & telecommunications, consumer goods, food and beverages, energy and power, automotive and transportation, manufacturing and construction, materials and chemicals, public sector as well as business and financial services. We provide 24/7 online and offline support to our customers. Call +1 888 391 5441 with your research requirements or email the details onsales@chinamarketresearchreports.comThis e-mail address is being protected from spambots. You need JavaScript enabled to view it and we would be happy to help you find the business intelligence that you need.
Media Contact: Priyank Tiwari, China Market Research Reports, + 1 888 391 5441,sales@chinamarketresearchreports.com
News distributed by PR Newswire iReach:https://ireach.prnewswire.com
SOURCE China Market Research Reports
]]></text></news-item>