<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS1-RDS1-JCMN-Y17F"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Ahtna proposal would give Native corporations a role in game management</title><source>Alaska Dispatch</source><author>Alex DeMarban</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 16, 2014 (Alaska Dispatch:http://www.alaskadispatch.com Delivered by Newstex) The ever-fired-up Rep. Don Young had an earful for the state and feds on Friday morning after they sat out a hearing about a proposed pilot project that would give an Alaska Native corporation a voice in wildlife management on its own land.
The proposal heard before the House Subcommittee on Indian and Alaska Native Affairs would allow Ahtna Inc. and eight tribal governments to form a commission to manage hunting for caribou, moose and other animals on 1.7 million acres of Ahtna-owned land in the Copper River region.The state currently manages hunting on that land. But change is needed because Alaska Natives aren't getting enough moose and caribou for families to eat, said Michelle Anderson, president of Ahtna, the regional corporation for a large swath of Southcentral and Interior Alaska, including the Copper River basin.'The whole reason we're doing this is because the current management system is not providing for our customary and traditional hunting needs,' said Anderson, who testified at the hearing. 'A lot of our elders have empty freezers. That means, too, our children are not being raised on traditional foods."The proposal, currently in the form of draft legislation, would also allow the commission to co-manage hunting -- with state and federal authorities -- on an additional 8.3 million acres of state and federal land outside the Ahtna-owned lands, in an area the Ahtna people say they have traditionally used.The state could opt out of the project, according to the proposal. If it did not participate, about 5 million acres would continue to be managed only by the state.If the plan works, it could serve as a model used by 11 other regional Native corporations hoping to manage hunting on their own lands, supporting documents say. That would remove some 45 million acres of land from state management.The proposal has already generated a lot of heat, with the Alaska Outdoor Council rallying members to contact Young's office to speak out against it, said Rod Arno, executive director of the powerful pro-hunting group.The proposal is unconstitutional because it would allow a public resource -- the wildlife -- to be managed by a private entity -- Ahtna -- said Arno.'We are vehemently opposed to it moving forward,' he said.The issue gets to the heart of a long-standing clash in Alaska, with the state constitution and state courts saying all Alaskans must have equal access to hunting wildlife, while federal law gives subsistence hunters in rural Alaska a priority over sport hunters.As it stands, the state manages hunting across Alaska, including on lands owned by Alaska Natives, most of which was conveyed under the 1971 Alaska Native Claims Settlement Act. Meanwhile, the federal government increasingly manages hunting on federal land, creating a confusing patchwork of boundaries and regulations that frustrate subsistence and sport hunters alike.The co-management proposal would allow the state and federal managers to have final authority on regulations that apply to their lands. But the idea is that most decisions would be made as a group, with Alaska Native input that currently isn't allowed.Young, chair of the subcommittee, said the proposal came from Ahtna residents, and the meeting was designed to bring the different stakeholders together to begin finding a solution.He said management of fish and game needs to 'evolve' in Alaska because the state's increasing population is putting too much pressure on the wildlife. The great danger is that game populations won't be around for future generations, he said.Young has received numerous critical comments in recent days by email. Others have commented on Facebook, saying things are fine and shouldn't be changed. But he plans to keep pushing the issue, even though he's doing it at 'great jeopardy' to himself.'If I have a legacy to leave behind besides the trans-Alaska pipeline, it's the legacy of having availability of subsistence, availability of sport hunting, availability of individuals participating in the great Alaska experience,' he said.Young said nothing has been done to improve management of fish and game on state and federal land.'To blindly stick our heads in the sand and do nothing is not permissible as far as I am concerned,' he said.He added that he's 'disappointed with Department of Interior and the State of Alaska for not coming forth and offering some suggestions,' and with other interest groups that aren't accepting of change.'The way it was will no longer exist,' Young said.Though the Interior Department didn't send a representative to the hearing in Washington, D.C., they provided a statement for the hearing saying they were looking forward to working on the issue. The state provided no written comments, but an official on Friday said they're working on a response.At the meeting, Young said it was 'disgusting' that Ahtna communities took only five moose out of 100 in a community hunting program managed by the state that was originally supposed to benefit local villages in the region.Anderson said that in recent years, the program been dominated by groups outside the region that are not necessarily communities.'That's not a community hunt, that's a statewide hunt,' Young said. 'The whole intent was to have the local community take 100 moose, and you have five.'After a long pause he added: 'For those listening to this program, think about the justice in that.'Doug Vincent-Lang, acting director of the state's Division of Wildlife Conservation, said the state received a copy of the draft legislation only four days before the hearing. It's a complex issue and the state needed more time to address the issue, he said. But he said the state will provide a statement within the 10-day window allowed for written comments.At first blush, the proposal seems unlikely to stand up against the state constitution because it creates an Ahtna subsistence priority, instead of a subsistence priority for all state residents, he said. It also seems counter to federal law because it creates an Ahtna priority instead of a rural priority, he said.The state Board of Game is trying to provide more opportunity for moose hunting for residents in the region, including creating a new winter hunt, he said. It has also created a subcommittee, consisting in part of Ahtna residents, that is working to improve the community hunt.'We're interested in working with Ahtna and many other people to address issues Ahtna is raising in the legislation,' Vincent-Lang said. 'We're just not that sure the legislation is the best means toward that end.'John 'Sky' Starkey, an attorney for Ahtna, said the Board of Game is working in good faith. But he also said the proposal is constitutional, and that co-management systems are already in place in Alaska, including with the Alaska Eskimo Whaling Commission helping manage bowhead whale stocks on the North Slope. Also, Congress also has the ability to improve its laws, as it has frequently done, he said.'This is a way to bring everyone to the table to harmonize management,' he said.As for Young, he said he'll continue to push for change.'The idea that only one side manages game is wrong,' he said. If sport and subsistence hunting is to continue, 'we have to increase the amount of game that's there or we won't have any game left.'Contact Alex DeMarban at alex(at)alaskadispatch.com[1]. [1]: mailto:alex@alaskadispatch.com

]]></text></news-item>