<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS1-PFB1-JCB3-417D"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Human trafficking hidden, but closer than many realize</title><source>The Evening Sun (Hanover, Pennsylvania)</source><author>By Susan Beam For the Daily Record/Sunday News</author><text><![CDATA[Human trafficking is a problem that remains hidden, but is getting worse, an audience of concerned citizens at Dover's Calvary Lutheran Church learned Sunday.
"At this time, there are more slaves in bondage than there have ever been before," said presenter Kristian Kent, county outreach advocate for York County Victim Assistance Center.
According to the U.S. Department of State, 600,000 to 800,000 victims are trafficked across international borders annually for the purpose of either forced labor or sexual exploitation, and more than half are under the age of 18.
Trafficking victims will often live and work in a community which doesn't recognize victims who are being exploited.
"These are victims hidden in plain sight," said Kent, who noted that both U.S. citizens and foreigners are being trafficked and controlled through "force, fraud, or coercion" by a trafficker, including threats of violence, deportation, or harm to loved ones. The average age of a trafficking victim is 11 years old.
In 2005, "Operation Precious Cargo" targeted a sex trafficking ring operating at Harrisburg truck stops, rescuing 150 victims, including 45 children, some of whom were as young as 12.
And more recently, in 2009, Lynda Dieu Phan pleaded guilty to federal charges of human trafficking after it was discovered that two women had been forced to work in her West Manchester nail salons under threat of being turned over to immigration officials.
These cases are not uncommon, said Kent, who gave Pennsylvania a grade of "F" for preventing human trafficking, citing weak anti-trafficking laws, the number of commercial and agricultural businesses in the state and the easy access to the 1-95 corridor.
Kent also said that Pennsylvania ranked 9th in the nation for calls to a national trafficking hotline in 2013.
This month, a bill which calls for tougher prosecution and penalties in human-trafficking cases will go before the state Legislature.
After Sunday's presentation hosted by Rt. 74 Lutheran Cluster, a lively discussion ensued, with several audience members sharing their experiences encountering cases of human trafficking here in York County.
"It's deplorable what's happening," said one audience member.
It's that kind of awareness that Dover resident Roxanne Price, member of the Rt. 74 Lutheran Cluster, was hoping to rise by opening the topic for discussion. She said the group wanted to do something to highlight social issues that were occurring in the community.
"We need to reach out and offer love and support," said Price.
Calvary Lutheran Pastor John Woods agreed, saying that he became aware of the horrors of human trafficking when reports of it surfaced during the Super Bowl and he has included the issue is several of his sermons.
While it's a difficult topic, "people need to hear it," he said, as awareness is key.
If you suspect someone is being trafficked, contact the national hotline at 1-888-3737-888, or call the York County Human Trafficking Task Force at 717-434-1746.
]]></text></news-item>