<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS1-SNY1-JBF5-T33G"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>ICAC: Inquiry hears allegations both sides of politics stood to gain financially from corrupt water deal</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author>By court reporter Jamelle Wells</author><text><![CDATA[The Independent Commission Against Corruption (ICAC) has heard sensational allegations that people from both sides of politics stood to benefit from a corrupt deal with a water company.
The allegations have been made on day one of an inquiry into the water company, known as Australian Water Holdings Pty Ltd (AWH), which has links to the Obeid family.
The public inquiry, codenamed Operation Credo, is looking at allegations that between 2004 and 2012 various people connected to AWH made corrupt financial gains by "adversely affecting the official functions" of the state-owned Sydney Water Corporation.
In his opening address Counsel Assisting Geoffrey Watson adapted Shakespeare saying "corruption acquaints a man with strange bedfellows".
He said the inquiry is looking at allegations about people from both sides of politics abusing their power for financial gain. Â Â Â Â
Mr Watson said former NSW Labor Minister Joe Tripodi doctored a cabinet minute in his colleague Tony Kelly's office to try and influence public officials over the AWH proposal.
"Joseph Tripodi actually re-drafted the cabinet minute on his own laptop computer," he said.
"Mr Tripodi has had a chequered career and at the time he was tooling away on his laptop he was a backbencher.
"It is not clear why Mr Tripodi should or even could be involved in fiddling with a ministerial cabinet minute."
Mr Watson said their Labor colleague Eddie Obeid stood to make up to $60 million from the deal because his family had a financial interest in the company.
He said the deal would have boosted the coffers of AWH by up to $200 million dollars, but it did not get past various advisors and the former premier Kristina Keneally.
The inquiry then heard allegations Eddie Obeid told former Labor Water Minister Phil Costa to sack Sydney Water boss Dr Kerry Schott because she opposed aspects of Â the deal.
Mr Watson said Eddie Obeid told Mr Costa in a parliament house lift "You need to sack that bitch".
The Counsel Assisting then outlined allegations Sydney Water was unknowingly donating money to the NSW Liberal Party.
He said a family friend of the Obeid's, the well known Liberal party fundraiser Nick di Girolamo was once the head of AWH and paid himself around $1 million a year plus bonuses.
Mr Di Girolamo is accused of charging Sydney Water for project managing water infrastructure and claiming thousands of dollars in expenses which were really donations to the Liberal Party.
The inquiry also heard that Federal Assistant Treasurer Arthur Sinodinos stood to make up to $20 million as a director of Australian Water Holdings if the deal went through.
The NSW Premier Barry O'Farrell has issued a statement distancing himself and his former finance minister Greg Pearce from the allegations about Sydney Water aired at the ICAC today.
The statement highlights comments by the Counsel Assisting the ICAC, who told the hearing the watchdog looked carefully at Mr O'Farrell and Mr Pearce's actions and found no evidence to implicate either in any corruption.
"As I've always stated, matters relating to AWH were appropriately handled at arm's length by Sydney Water," Mr O'Farrell said.
Mr O'Farrell says he will not be making any further statements about the inquiry until the ICAC has concluded its work.
The NSW division of the Liberal Party has decided to cancel donations from Australian Water Holdings in light of today's evidence.
The party's acting director Simon McInnes has issued a statement saying more than $75,000 donated by AWH will be refunded to Sydney Water.
He described the donations as "tainted" and says the Liberal Party is returning them because it acts with the highest integrity.
Much of the evidence to be heard over the next three weeks is connected to a second inquiry into allegations former NSW energy minister Chris Hartcher, The Entrance MP Chris Spence and Wyong MP Darren Webber received corrupt political donations connected to AWH.
Separate to the ICAC inquiry, a number of AWH shareholders have started a Federal Court case suing eight former and current directors for deceptive conduct.
They are suing Mr Di Girolamo, Senator Sinodinos, Mr Costa and others, claiming they were given false information about AWH contracts and future business prospects.Â
Â
]]></text></news-item>