<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS1-2VG1-F125-13VN"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Pot growing licenses go up in smoke April 1</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Calgary police say they will show no mercy to unlicensed growers of medical marijuana once a new federal program shifts production to a smaller number of producers, but officers are not planning a sweeping crackdown.
The approach is in contrast to the Vancouver Police Department's plans to be more lenient with businesses that sell medical pot to patients with required permits.
In Calgary, police will face a daunting challenge to weed out illegal growers because they don't know how many there are. Some operators, licensed under current rules, tend plants for their own consumption in their homes, while others grow for clients.
These licenses will no longer be valid April 1, when the new rules will forbid home-based medical pot production and require that commercial growers abide by strict health and safety conditions and introduce security measures, such as surveillance systems.
This will mean that tens of thousands of medical pot producers across the country will have to shut down their operations, forcing patients to buy their dosages from a smaller number of licensed growers. If they don't comply they will face prosecution.
Keith Fagin, who suffers from chronic pain after a car crash as a boy and an industrial accident in the early 1990s, said he will not be able to afford medical pot from commercial growers, who he estimated will charge at least four times what he is paying now.
Fagin, a Calgary cannabis activist, said his grower holds a license under current rules and produces "clean, quality and affordable" medical marijuana. When the new regime comes into effect, the grower will continue harvesting the plants, risking jail time, because he and Fagin survive on disability incomes.
The grower's pot costs Fagin less than $2 a gram - he consumes at least seven to nine grams a day, though he doesn't smoke it all - and he expects commercial outfits will charge at least $7, something he said he can't afford.
"We have no choice but to risk going to prison, risk having police come kick the doors in, take our stuff, put us in prison and leave us in the street when we get out as homeless people because we've got nothing left," he said.
Health Canada's website lists nine approved producers, none of which are based in Alberta, though growers in Calgary, west of Airdrie and in Edmonton have said they are seeking federal approval.
Calgary police say they will shutter any growing facility deemed illegal under the new rules. Officers can charge the operators with possession and production of marijuana, and potentially trafficking as well, said Sgt. Keith Hurley.
Medical marijuana growers are not a high priority for police, who are more concerned with pot produced to help fund organized crime, but they will investigate complaints, said Hurley, who works in the special policing unit Alberta Law Enforcement Response Teams.
"The person who uses it in their home for medicinal marijuana isn't necessarily the people that we're targeting," he said. "However, if we receive a complaint, just like any other drug complaint, we will investigate it to see whether or not it is legal or illegal."
In Vancouver, patients with prescriptions for medical marijuana can get their dosages at dispensaries, most of which already run without city business licenses. According to Health Canada, these businesses pose public safety risks because they are illegal and unregulated.
Police said they don't raid these businesses now and they don't plan to change the policy once the new medical marijuana regime comes into effect.
Const. Brian Montague said Vancouver police would rather direct scarce resources toward keeping the peace, than to raiding dispensaries that appear to operate professionally and safely. In recent years, police have shut down three medical marijuana dispensaries that were found to be fronts for trafficking, but existing businesses don't appear to be doing this, Montague said.
Hurley, who wasn't aware of any dispensaries in Calgary, said the new medical pot regime will not prevent legitimate patients from securing their medicine. What will change, he said, is that producers will be much safer.
Hurley said home-based operations are not equipped to deal with high levels of humidity, which means they can easily spread mould, posing serious health risks.
Last week, police found 743 marijuana plants and growing equipment in a northeast Calgary home that was badly run down and rife with mould. The property, which was not used for medical pot production, was deemed unsafe for human habitation after the bust.
"Medicinal marijuana users will always have a way to getting it; this is just changing how they are able to access it," Hurley said. "Where they were able to grow it in their own home, now they will have to go through a commercial operation to get it, just like you can't produce OxyContin in your own home; you have to get it through a pharmacy."
With files from Postmedia News
rsouthwick@calgaryherald.com( mailto:rsouthwick@calgaryherald.com )
Twitter.com/theredsouth
© Copyright (c) The Calgary Herald
]]></text></news-item>