<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS1-1FN1-DYT4-V19D"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Community encouraged to join coalition for drug-free Doña Ana County</title><source>Las Cruces Sun-News (New Mexico)</source><author>By Charlotte Tallman For the Sun-News</author><text><![CDATA[LAS CRUCES >> The Unified Prevention! Coalition for a Drug-Free Doca Ana County will hold its next meeting Thursday, and members of the community are encouraged to attend. UP!, an initiative of the Community Foundation of Southern New Mexico, works to make sure that those in Doca Ana County have the opportunity to live a life free of drugs and alcohol.
In 2013, UP! was awarded the Partnerships for Success II grant to work on prevention as a means to reduce underage drinking and reduce prescription drug misuse by youth and young adults. The three-year PFS II grant provides $128,806 per year.
At the March meeting, to be held at 10:30 a.m. in the US Bank boardroom, 301 S. Church St., the coalition will begin a partnership with Melissa Cast, a third-year business administration doctoral candidate at New Mexico State University. Cast relocated to Las Cruces two years ago from Indiana, and her previous professional experience was in the nonprofit sector, most recently as program development coordinator/forensic interviewer at a child advocacy center serving southern Indiana.
"As a forensic interviewer, I interviewed many children each year who were alleged to be victims of sexual abuse and/or severe physical abuse. I also participated in court proceedings as necessary," said Cast, who participated on a coalition comprised of law enforcement from multiple levels, prosecutors, nonprofit organizations providing advocacy and mental and physical health services and the Department of Children's Services.
"During my time working on this coalition, I became aware of its importance in solving complex problems in our communities. However, I also understand how difficult working on such coalitions can be at times, and have personally experienced issues like decreased commitment and burnout," she said.
Cast will be researching the UP! coalition and the effects of such coalitions on their individual members as part of her dissertation project. During the summer, Cast will survey coalition members during monthly meetings. Each survey will take approximately 25 minutes to complete, then at the end of the summer, Cast will ask each coalition to participate in a 30-minute interview during a coalition meeting. Cast will share results of the surveys and research at the end of the year.
The coalition plans to use the survey results and Cast's research to strengthen the coalition. As a grant recipient, UP! is required to participate in and use the Strategic Prevention Framework planning model to include: needs assessment, capacity building, strategic planning, implementation and evaluation with cultural competency and sustainability infused into each step. UP! strives to provide a venue for community collaboration and support prevention efforts from every available community resource.
UP! draws from many sectors of the community including law enforcement, youth organizations, government agencies, state and local substance abuse agencies, parents, youth, businesses, media groups, civic organizations, schools, faith community and healthcare professionals.
A Community that's Aware is a Community that Cares is submitted by Charlotte Tallman, media campaign coordinator for the Unified Prevention! Coalition for a Drug-Free Doca Ana County, an initiative of the Community Foundation of Southern New Mexico. For more information on the coalition, visitwww.unifiedprevention.com or call Kirsty Nichols, UP! coordinator at 575-521-4794.
]]></text></news-item>