<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS1-D1X1-F0K8-64F0"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Shifting focus to cloud computing</title><source>MINT</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[New Delhi, March 16 -- The underlying concepts of cloud computing are not new but have now matured and provide, among other things, infrastructure and software as a service, thus reducing the cost of owning and maintaining hardware while paving the way towards autonomic computing-a self-managing computing model styled after the human body's autonomic nervous system. Cloud as a concept is able to allow focus of the business to be directed at innovation and to what it actually takes to change the game, agreed industry experts comprising Varun Sood, chief information officer of Fortis Healthcare India; Vijay Sethi, vice-president, information systems and human resources, and chief information officer with Hero MotoCorp Ltd; Tejpreet Singh Chopra, president and chief executive officer of Bharat Light and Power Pvt. Ltd; Vamsicharan Mudiam, country manager-cloud solutions with IBM India, South Asia; and Jaideep Mehta, vice-president and country general manager at International Data Corp. (IDC) India. They were part of a panel discussion, How cloud computing is changing the face of business, moderated by Jai Menon, group director, technology, HT Media Ltd.
Edited excerpts: As a healthcare provider, how are you using cloud and what was your decision-making process? Sood: We have 60-odd hospitals across the country. Last June, we started thinking how to put in place a model which is scalable and flexible to cater to business needs and demands as and when needed. It took us some time before we decided it has to be a cloud model. The second decision was to adopt a 100% public cloud-based model from the point of scalability, performance, security and flexibly. Cost was an added advantage. We have completed that transition. Every hospital has its own system and you work in different buckets. We moved our entire ERP (enterprise resource planning) backbone, our core hospital information systems, our intranet and line of business systems to the cloud. It has helped us scale on demand. Our ability to respond to business is now in minutes, compared to earlier-which could be weeks or months. We no longer plan for capacity-it is capacity on demand. The organization has also gained a lot in terms of savings, which we actually have been able to put back into other newer initiatives or give back to the business to scale. We are now looking at only maintaining what is needed for housekeeping-everything else would be moving onto the same platform. Has your experience (at Hero MotoCorp) been different with both public and private (on premise) flavours of cloud? Sethi: The cloud as a concept has been there for 50-55 years now, but it was only in the last 5-6 years that people really started talking about the cloud. As an auto company, we have a huge dealer base. We thought if we could automate and include all of them in a single system, it would give all our dealers a similar experience and ensure that processes are common. The cost and speed of rollout were major driving factors. We run a private cloud today on which the entire organization's mission-critical functions and that of dealers and their individual independent businesses are hosted. On festival days like Dhanteras, when you have great demand-huge queues from 12 noon till late night-we can now ensure that all the service levels are met by using the cloud. After we separated from Honda in 2010, we have been having various alliance partners across the globe. We do a lot of design collaboration with them. For this entire thing including R&D (research and development) and what we do with our partners is on a public cloud. We also use cloud for niche services such as security, analytics and big data (analysing huge amounts of structured and unstructured information). Cloud is not just about infrastructure, but about applications. There are many applications which are not cost effective to be put in our own systems and sometimes we don't have skills to manage those applications. It's best if you pay per use for these applications-first, for a few months. If it works fine, good, otherwise, dump it and use something else. It gives you that flexibility and ensures that your entire IT set-up becomes nimble. For cloud and technology providers, what is your strategy from IBM's point of view in terms of getting scale? Mudiam: There are three aspects that cloud solves-One is speed, how quickly we can get things; second is economics-the whole capex (capital expenditure) transformation; and last is empowerment. We are seeing a major shift in IT buying. Because of the applications coming on cloud in SaaS (software as a service) format, CIOs (chief information officers) necessarily are facilitating the process, but the thought process of what they want to buy is pretty much driven by CFOs (chief financial officers) or procurement officers. What we are seeing is, as a vendor, operations can be readied from a CIO (chief information officer) office perspective to give them private -public (clouds), and a mix (hybrid cloud that combines functions of a public and private cloud). We are moving away from infrastructure and going on to the platform and onto SaaS. We have a lot of passive IT assets like expense reimbursements, which we use inside IBM. We put them on the cloud and now don't only offer SaaS but also give people the opportunity to collect and approve the bills-people pay per receipt or per transaction. How is cloud consumption helping you focus on your business in the energy sector? Chopra: Our company is focused on building, operating and owning clean energy power plants in India. As cars go round the Formula One track, they send telemetry data out to engineers in the UK running algorithms and making changes to the parameters of the cars as the race progresses. Using that as an analogy, I kept thinking of a way to take a boring brick and mortar company that builds power plants and attached the power of IT to increase its operating efficiency. Also, if you think about wind energy firm, it has a wind turbines in different parts of the world. So what will happen if we can find some wind turbine that can produce more energy from other wind turbines and what if some turbines could talk to other wind turbines that are not producing enough energy-to increase it. That is where we wanted to match the power of IT with our knowledge of running a power plant. We now have one of the most advanced operating centres in our offices in Bangalore and we get tonnes of data on the cloud in Singapore. We monitor anywhere between 51 and 75 parameters of every single wind turbine, 24 hours a day. So we collect all this data on the cloud, but the question is how do you use it? While technically sitting in Bangalore, we can now actually monitor, forecast, predict and report about any power plant, anywhere in the world. What is driving the growth of cloud? What are some of the trends associated with it? Mehta: Cloud is extremely serious business. We estimated in 2012 that the cloud market-public and private-was about $1 billion. When we telescoped our projections to 2015, the number came out to be $4.67 billion. The country has been in recession and what that has reflected is the aggressive pick up and induction of cloud technology. Public cloud is absolutely the dominant force in the country, but interestingly it is not dominant when you think of business critical applications. So CIOs are indeed business leaders, more than happy to put all sort of workloads onto the public cloud, but don't talk to them about core transaction processing or core banking systems, etc. There are still concerns including vendor integrity and security. A lot of it is around perception. Two years back we said, cloud was at an inflection point. Now it has exploded. Once the supply side ecosystem works together to address some of the CIO concerns, the next wave of cloud will undoubtedly be triggered through business critical apps. It is not only cost and scalability. Organizations are realizing that cloud comes with multi-dimension benefits. When you look at turbulent markets, or at your CEO or acquiring a business internationally, then having a cloud-based infrastructure also helps CIOs to rapidly respond to a sudden business change. The third thing which is driving the cloud growth is increasing scarcity of quality talent. Cloud has also triggered a new model of outsourcing. There is no fixed price involved in cloud. It has all gone to operating cost based, like industry says from capex to opex (operating expenditure). All this sounds too good, but what are the main challenges associated with the cloud? Sethi: A challenge that many of us face today is perhaps that there is no definition of what is a cloud. Is the cloud of IBM better than that of Microsoft's or Amazon's? How do I compare when there are no standards? There is always a fear at the back of everybody's mind that what if that guy (provider) goes out of business or does something with us, since there are no regulations at present. Published by HT Syndication with permission from MINT. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>