<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS1-34P1-DXDT-6306"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Boss 'sacked us when we said no to a threesome at his flat': Female executives seek £100,000 in compensation</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>LIZ HULL</author><text><![CDATA[Anna Mazover and Diana Nicholl-Pierson claimed they were told they would get promoted if they had sex with their married boss Darren ScottMiss Nichol Pierson contacted police after Mr Scott 'touched her thighs and bottom'He allegedly told Miss Mazover: 'I will give you gifts and money, just be my girlfriend or lover'He claims he sacked them for poor performance and being late
Two female sales executives who say they were sacked by their boss after they refused his demands for a threesome at his luxury flat are seeking £100,000 compensation.
Anna Mazover, 29, and Diana Nicholl-Pierson, 24, claim they were told they would get promoted if they had sex with married Darren Scott, 55.
They were constantly leered at and subjected to sexual remarks after being hired by the sales director, the graduates say.
On her first day, Mr Scott told Miss Mazover - who is married - she had a 'great body', adding: 'You are very sexy. Have you ever considered working in a strip club?'
The following evening the pair were at an office leaving party when Mr Scott asked them to have sex with him at his £1.4million penthouse in north London.
'It would be nice if we go back together to my penthouse and have a threesome,' Mr Scott allegedly told them. 'If you have a threesome, you both would prosper within the company and get promoted.'
The women began working at Entico Corporation Ltd, a Central London publishing firm that produces documents and programmes for conferences, in May last year. Almost immediately, Mr Scott began making sexual references, including comments about their breasts, they claim.
He bragged about hiring prostitutes, taking cocaine and visiting his cousin's lap dancing bar. He also showed the women images of scantily clad girls from an escorts website on his work computer, they say.
Mr Scott repeatedly asked Miss Mazover to go to strip clubs with him and begged her to be his girlfriend. She made it clear to the reformed alcoholic that she wasn't interested but he refused to listen, she says. Instead, he began stalking her - even turning up unannounced on nights out with friends.
On one occasion, she says, Mr Scott told her: 'I'm bored of having sex with brainless strippers. When I wake up in the morning, there is nothing to talk about. Please I will give you gifts and money, just be my girlfriend or my lover.'
Eventually, Miss Nicholl-Pierson, of Merseyside, reported Mr Scott to police after he allegedly sexually assaulted her by touching her bottom and thighs.
When the women - who earned up to £3,000 a month - complained, Mr Scott tried to get them to withdraw the allegations before sacking them. They have begun an unfair dismissal claim against Entico and Mr Scott on the grounds of sexual harassment, and are seeking damages totalling more than £100,000.
Miss Mazover, the daughter of a Ukrainian businessman, also claims racial discrimination.
She says Mr Scott mocked her accent and made derogatory comments about Russian women, implying they were 'easy'.
Mr Scott, who has since been promoted to head of international business, denies all the allegations. He says he sacked Miss Nicholl-Pierson for poor performance and Miss Mazover because she was regularly late for work.
Lawyer Michael McDonough, who is representing the women, said: 'It's extremely difficult for women to take these type of cases [sexual harassment] forward, not only because of the stress and trauma involved in going to a tribunal, but also finding representation they can afford.
'We've been able to take this case on a contingency basis and hope that we can... get justice for our clients.'
Last night Mr Scott said the women were taking action only for financial gain. 'We deny all the allegations,' he said.
'The police thoroughly investigated the matter and found there was no case to answer. It is completely money-driven and indicative of the compensation culture in this country, hence their use of a no-win, no-fee lawyer.'
]]></text></news-item>