<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS1-D6Y1-F0NV-F4JG"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Fundraiser bowls 'em over</title><source>The Register-Mail (Galesburg, Illinois)</source><author>Sponsors rack up $19</author><text><![CDATA[GALESBURG - Eight-year-old Malaki Albert and his Big, Kathy Bennett, joined by Malaki's mother, Sheneatha Albert, had bowled three frames when they decided to take a break. They sat in the Club Room of Northgate Lanes enjoying pizza donated by Pizza House.
"I did six pins and five gutters," Malaki said, explaining that Bennett had a score of 36 with "one spare, one strike, a 1 pin and a 5 pin."
Through cookie sales, a jewelry party and a night of donations where Cellar Pizzeria and Pub donated 10 percent of its food sales, Bennett raised $1,009.45 for the Big Brothers Big Sisters Bowl for Kids' Sake fundraiser at the Northgate Lanes on Saturday afternoon.
The 13th annual event is the year's biggest fundraiser for Knox County chapter of Big Brothers Big Sisters, explained Director of Development Blake Long.
"It typically brings in $20,000," Long said. "Donations are raised by bowlers, corporate sponsors give us donations. We're accepting donations (at the door.) People are really generous here in Knox County."
Last year's event brought in around $17,000, a number topped within hours this year. By the end of the day, just over $19,000 had been raised for the 2014 Bowl for Kids' Sake.
There are 33 children in the program and it takes about $1,000 to fund each child per year, Long explained.
About 150 bowlers signed up for the event, many volunteers for Big Brothers Big Sisters, some members of the community involved with sponsors who just wanted to support the organization.
The 2014 Bowl for Kids' Sake was a good year for sponsors, Long explained. A typical year sees 15 to 20 sponsors, but 25 signed up to support this year.
"I think we're really becoming more visible," Long said. "People are understanding investing in Big Brothers Big Sisters is an investment in their community."
As long explained, the program has proven to make children more likely to go to college and help deter drug and alcohol abuse in young people.
"Our program provides them with a role model," Long said. "A lot of these kids live with a single parent and are sort of isolated, this shows them there is so much more out there to see and do."
For Bennett, Big Brothers Big Sisters gives her the opportunity to help out a family.
"It's hard when you're a working mom and trying to do different things with your child in the community," Bennett said. "The program is based on a Little and a Big, but I see it as helping out the whole family."
"I like the fact that it gives Malaki someone to talk to besides Mommy," Sheneatha said. "There are some things he couldn't talk about. It makes it easier to have someone else."
Bennett found out about the bowling event through her volunteer work with United Way. She had met Malaki about a year ago through the Big Brothers Big Sisters Lunch Buddies program, which has a Big eat lunch at school with their Little two or more times a month.
Since meeting, Bennett and Malaki have enjoyed spending time hanging out outside of school.
Malaki especially likes going to the Galesburg Antiques Mall.
"Once I got a wooden sword there," Malaki said. "I just like to look around."
In December, Malaki joined Covenant Church, which Bennett belongs to.
"Because of the time limits, we're limited to four hours per week," Bennett explained. "The church van picks him up on Wednesdays. As long as the church van takes him, it doesn't cut into our time."
Malaki is excited about an upcoming musical at the church.
"I'm playing bells," Malaki said, "and my sister and my next door friend is coming."
Big Brothers Big Sisters is not state funded, nor do they receive any grants. Though this year's Bowl for Kids' Sake event is over, those who wish to donate to Big Brothers Big Sisters can reach Erica Bell, Big Brothers Big Sisters case manager, at (309) 344-2252.
Antwon R. Martin: (309) 342-7181, ext: 266; amartin@register-mail.com; @AntwonRMartin
]]></text></news-item>