<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-JJ91-F12F-F347"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>HOW TO KEEP OUR CITY GREEN</title><source>Star of Mysore (India)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[India, March 17 -- It is now an established fact, that for a clean and better living, we should have wooded surroundings. We have seen that citizens of Mysore city, old and young, take a morning or an evening walk around the Kukkarahalli Lake, Lingambudhi Lake and in all the parks in our heritage city, gasping for fresh air. Walking along the streets, if they are shaded by flowering avenue trees, as seen around the Palace and other old roads of Mysore city, is not only a pleasure but also recuperating.
The more oxygen we inhale, the more energetic we will be. It is a common knowledge that our valuable plants take in carbon di-oxide and exhale life supporting oxygen to be used by all living animals including human-beings for their survival. So it is our duty to plant and protect trees, especially in urban areas where the population is dense and congested. The exciting and enchanting experience one draws while driving on the roads covered by tall trees on both sides is beyond expression.
The sylvan surroundings keep the atmosphere rich in oxygen, lower the maximum temperature in summer and raise the minimum temperature in winter. We may not feel this difference in temperatures in our cities but it is more pronounced in hilly areas, such as Kemmangundi, Talacauvery, Nandi hills or Himad Gopalaswamy hills.
With the scenic beauty there and tree cover, these places are prominent tourist destinations and have to be protected, maintained and conserved without felling any existing trees.
Not only that, we also have to plant more trees in the open areas available to generate more oxygen for our ever-growing population. We have to replant and retain trees in parks, market yards, crematoriums, office, school compounds etc. as "Woodlots." That is not all, woodlots provide fodder, fruits and flowers for birds and other small wild animals and are their habitat too. The tall trees act as wind belts as well as shelter belts and are a feast to our eyes.
With rapid industrialisation, the atmosphere, soil and water are polluted and it requires proper treatment to use in cultivating food crops and drinking. Trees help in the infiltration of rainwater and enrich sub-soil moisture while their roots hold the soil, preventing soil erosion.
Our early rulers of the city ? Krishnaraja Wadiyar, Chamaraja Wadiyar and Jayachamaraja Wadiyar planted beautiful avenue trees of long rotation species, such a Mavu, Bevu, Ala, Arali, Halasu, Bela, Hunse, Ippe, Nerale, Honge, etc. They specially selected exotic species such as Colvillea racemosa, Spathodia companulata around Palaces, which used to bloom in full during Dasara festivities. They planted one single species in rows over long distances to create beautiful and uniform avenues. The planting, maintenance and protection of road side trees were then, the duty of the village leaders such as Patels, Shanbhogs and villagers and by an order. But post-independence, followed by democratic administration, resulted in lenient attitude and many of the well-grown trees in gundu-thopus, roadsides, market yards and other public places were hacked and destroyed illicitly for fuel, small timber and fodder by the increasing population, depriving their use for honey-bees, birds, butterflies, squirrels, monkeys and e
ven snakes.
Now all that we find along these roads are large gaps, which cannot be easily restored or replaced by planting new saplings as the soil has eroded and has no protection. It is now very difficult to raise trees on the roadside avenues since it is an expensive affair as the plants need to be manured, watered and protected by tree-guards.
The existing gaps are now filled with any available species in the forest nursery without any set selection resulting in a hapless conglomeration of species without any thought, control and planning. Many short rotation, shallow rooted and brittle but fast growing species like May flower, Peltophorum, etc. planted in the city have been uprooted, branches broken, frequently creating road blocks, damaging vehicles and even killing persons. There are heavy casualties of plants now, which are being replaced year after year without any monetary limits and considerations.
The Vanamahostava celebrations introduced by late K.M. Munshi in the year 1954 has now just become a obligatory ritual.
The government has taken several steps to bring back tree cover in our heritage city of Palaces.
Steps Taken: The Forest department has created Urban Forestry Division in Mysore, under the Zilla Panchayat to provide seedlings of tree species for urban planting. Several permanent forest nurseries are located in the University campus, Siddalingapura, near APMC on Nanjangud road, at the foot hill of Chamundi, etc.
Seedlings are available for individuals too on nominal payment. The government has introduced Agro-forestry encouragement project, wherein the person who plants tree seedlings will be given incentive bonus of Rs.10 per plant on its survival in the first year, Rs. 15 in the second year and Rs. 25 in the third year of survival. In all, Rs. 45 per plant survived upto the third year. Thereafter the trees can grow on its own without much care. The MCC has also taken up planting inside parks, along the roadsides, in the foreshore areas of Karanji Lake (by Zoo), Kukkarahalli Lake (by University) and Lingambudhi Lake (by Forest Dept).
The success and survival of these trees depend upon the co-operation of local residents. Therefore the management and protection of trees in the parks may be given to the local residents forming committees. The people's participation is necessary and they are the primary beneficiaries who would regularly go to parks for walks. The public and private participation (PPP) is the need of the day for bringing in tree cover in cities. Extensive planting has been done at Chamundi Hill under various schemes by forest department and it is our duty to protect and conserve trees in such inhospitable areas by additional inputs like manure, water and tree guards.
The success of such tree planting activities depends on various factors, of which the choice of species is the most important one. The trees planted in cities must be long rotation species mentioned above, evergreen in character, with straight and clean bole and bright flowers. It is better to avoid fruit yielding species like jack-fruit, mango and Neralu in city roads which attract cattle and urchins during fruiting and create accidents and roadblocks. The branch cuttings of Peepal and Ashoka trees are also not suitable along roadsides, as their low branching interfere with traffic movements. Seedlings of tree species are the best option and should be grown at least 2m tall in the nursery itself, either naked or in large poly-bags and then transplanted to the site. The pits in city planting should be at least 1m or more in depth, so that the tap root and the lateral roots are far below the adjoining foundations of compound walls or buildings. Otherwise the lateral roots, while growing, damage the foundat
ion and the structures.
Manuring, frequent watering and individual tree guards or covering the base with thorns are very essential, due to uncontrolled cattle movements in the city. The side branches should be removed periodically so that the tree grows straight and tall without interfering with the vehicular movements. There is a provision to adopt these trees by the neighbouring residents for maintenance and in return they could use its usufructs. Whenever we take up planting along the roadsides, the nearby residents should be informed, requesting them to maintain and such cordiality is essential for success.
The clarion call of UNESCO ? "GO GREEN" ? should be taken up seriously to make the Globe green with trees and thereby clean for our own survival.
[The author is the former Regional Chief Conservator of Forests under the Ministry of Environment & Forests, Bhopal and now settled in Mysore. Contact e-mail:kodira1@hotmail.com; Mob: 94480-58549; Ph: 0821-2542549].
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Star of Mysore. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>