<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-DRK1-JCDY-T1YJ"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>World Digest: March 17, 2014</title><source>Washingtonpost.com</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NORTH KOREA Short-range missiles are fired into the sea
North Korea fired 10 short-range missiles into the sea to the east of the Korean Peninsula on Sunday, South Korea's Yonhap News Agency reported, citing unidentified government officials in South Korea. Yonhap said the missiles flew for 45 miles before splashing into the sea.
After the report, the U.S. State Department called on the North to refrain from provocative actions. "We are closely monitoring the situation on the Korean Peninsula," department spokeswoman Jen Psaki said in a brief statement. "We once again call on North Korea to refrain from provocative actions that aggravate tensions."
North Korea is not banned from short-range missile launches under U.N. sanctions and frequently tests its arsenal.
The North has toned down its bellicose rhetoric toward the South, although it has denounced ongoing U.S.-South Korean military exercises.
In early 2013, North Korea conducted its third nuclear weapons test, having successfully launched a long-range rocket in 2012 that critics say was aimed at demonstrating technology for an intercontinental ballistic missile. Both of these are banned under U.N. sanctions.
- Reuters
AFGHANISTAN 2nd candidate quits presidential race
Abdullah Rahim Wardak, a former defense minister, on Sunday became the second candidate to drop out of Afghanistan's presidential race.
Wardak was not considered a front-runner in the April 5 election, and he did not throw his support behind any other candidate.
Wardak was one of 10 candidates hoping to replace President Hamid Karzai, who has served two terms and cannot run again.
Qayum Karzai, the president's brother, announced this month that he was dropping out of the race and threw his support behind former foreign minister Zalmay Rassoul. That was widely interpreted as meaning that Rassoul had Hamid Karzai's backing, although the president has not officially given any.
Of the nine candidates still in the race, the three who are considered the front-runners are Rassoul, outspoken former finance minister Ashraf Ghani, and Abdullah Abdullah, an eye surgeon who became the top aide to an anti-Taliban resistance fighter.
- Reuters
EGYPT 16,000 jailed over past 8 months
In Egypt's biggest roundup in nearly two decades, the crackdown on Islamists has put 16,000 people in jail over the past eight months, according to previously unreleased figures from security officials.
Rights activists say reports of abuses in prisons are mounting, with prisoners describing systematic beatings and miserable conditions for dozens packed into tiny cells.
The government has not released official numbers for those arrested in the sweeps since the military ousted Islamist President Mohamed Morsi in July. But four senior officials - two from the Interior Ministry and two from the military - gave the Associated Press a count of 16,000, including about 3,000 top- or mid-level members of the Morsi-allied Muslim Brotherhood. The officials provided the figures on the condition of anonymity because the government has not released them.
The count is consistent with recent estimates by human rights groups.
- Associated Press
U.S. gives Iraq missiles, assault rifles to battle insurgents:The United States delivered 100 Hellfire missiles, along with assault rifles and ammunition, to Iraq as part of its anti-terrorism assistance to the country, the U.S. Embassy in Baghdad said Sunday. In a statement, it said the delivery was made earlier this month to help bolster Iraqi government forces fighting the militant group Islamic State of Iraq and Syria, particularly in the western province of Anbar.
Juror in Jamaica murder trial charged with bribery attempt: A juror has been charged with attempted bribery in the high-profile murder trial of Vybz Kartel, a top Jamaican music star. Kartel and three co-defendants were convicted last week of the 2011 slaying of Clive "Lizard" Williams. Shortly after the 10 to 1 verdict was announced Thursday, Livingston Cain, 50, was arrested on suspicion of attempting to bribe the jury foreman in a bid to free Kartel. The foreman immediately reported the alleged bribery attempt to authorities.
- From news services
]]></text></news-item>