<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-X921-DY0P-G35F"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>House Cites CWA Jurisdiction Policy In New Push For Pesticide Permit Waiver</title><source>InsideEPA.com's Daily Briefing</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[House lawmakers are citing the emerging federal policy covering the reach of the Clean Water Act (CWA) over smaller waters to justify their renewed push for legislation exempting pesticide spraying activities from CWA permit requirements, saying the alleged expansion of the law's reach necessitates the need for the bill.
"The expansion of [the CWA's definition of 'navigable' waters subject to regulation] is a big reason why we are here today," Rep. Steve King (R-IA) told a House Agriculture Committee meeting March 13, where the panel unanimously reported H.R. 935, the bill that would eliminate CWA permitting requirements for pesticide applications.
King's comments appear to refer to the administration's pending rulemaking clarifying when smaller waters are subject to CWA, a rule EPA and the Army Corps of Engineers are developing after a set of Supreme Court rulings created uncertainty about when such waters are considered navigable, or connected to navigable waters, such that they are subject to regulation.
While the pesticide permit legislation appears likely to again win House approval, it is not likely to clear the Senate via regular order as environment committee Chairman Barbara Boxer (D-CA) has long blocked its passage.
The long-running legislative effort was first initiated in response to a 2009 ruling from the U.S. Court of Appeals for the 6th Circuit in National Cotton Council of America, et. al v. EPA, which held that certain types of pesticides discharged "into, over or near" waters of the U.S. require National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) permits, vacating a 2006 EPA rule that exempted the releases.
Since the ruling, EPA has crafted a permit governing the activities, though the agency set a high use threshold that had the effect of exempting many smaller operations from the requirements.
In response, many lawmakers and farm groups have pushed legislation that would amend the CWA so that National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) permits cannot be required by EPA for application of pesticides that are already approved under the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (FIFRA).
But environmentalists and many Democrats have opposed the legislation, charging that FIFRA approval does not take the place of clean water regulations.
Supporters of the bill have also said the 6th Circuit's ruling sets a precedent subjecting other exempt sources, such as fertilizer applications and even power plant emissions, to permit requirements.
The bill, or similar versions of it, have cleared the House several times over the past few years, but never made it through the Senate. Most recently, the House attached identical language to the Farm Bill that would exempt pesticide spraying from CWA permit requirements. But the language was stripped out by the House-Senate conference committee.
Pesticide Applicators
During the markup, lawmakers again cited the need to enact the bill due to its impact on pesticide applicators. "The attempt by those pressing this litigation [in the 6th Circuit ] to have federally registered public health, aquatic and agricultural pesticides regulated through the Clean Water Act permitting process is unnecessary, costly and ultimately undermines public health," committee chairman Frank Lucas (R-OK) said in a statement. "It amounts to a duplication of regulatory compliance costs for a variety of public agencies, adds to their legal jeopardy and threatens pesticide applicators," he said, adding that many mosquito control districts alread have fines for non-compliances set at $37,500 per day per violation.
"For a bill that makes so much sense, it is inexcusable that a couple of our colleagues in the Senate have been allowed to block it," Lucas said.
But King cited actions that he says have the effect of expanding the CWA's reach to further justify the need for the legislative exemption for pesticide applications. While King did not cite specific actions, his comments appear to refer to the administration's pending rulemaking, which is expected to cite waters' hydrological connections to justify regulation.
The administration is developing the rule in response to a pair of high court rulings that created significant legal uncertainty about which tests regulators can use to determine whether waters are jurisdiction. To address the issue, EPA is crafting a rule to codify its policy and has also crafted a draft "connectivity" study to provide a scientific basis for any rule.
EPA sent the proposed rule clarifying when smaller waters are subject to regulation to the White House Office of Management & Budget (OMB) Sept. 17, and OMB officials are reportedly asking the agency to clarify whether the "significance" of a connection, or nexus, between smaller waterbodies and larger downstream waters marks a technical or policy issue, as industry and some EPA advisers have feared the agency might not be weighing the issue.
King charged at the committee meeting that because the pending rule will have the effect of expanding jurisdiction, lawmakers need to approve the bill to limit permit burdens for pesticide applicators. "That definition has expanded to include 'hydrologically connected to' . . . and this bill does cover anything they can hereafter name 'navigable'," he said. -- Amanda Palleschi (apalleschi@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>