<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-GRT1-F091-R36Y"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Offshore oil and gas industry comes with clear environmental responsibilities</title><source>Cape Times (South Africa)</source><author> Trevor Manuel and Obiageli 'Oby' Ezekwesili</author><text><![CDATA[Africa's western seaboard, from Mauritania to South Africa, is among the most productive and fastest-growing offshore oilfields in the world, and has easily the most active deep-water sector.
The region's oil and gas producing countries collectively drill over 4.5 millon barrels a day and have an estimated 48.77 billion barrels in reserve.
The exploration, exploitation and transport of offshore oil and gas are all major industries, bringing economic development and opportunities to the region which are welcome if benefits can be equitably shared, and if those whose livelihoods directly depend on a clean, healthy and plentiful ocean do not have to suffer the consequences of, and pay for, any associated environmental damage.
As the sector continues to expand, it is more vital than ever that we strike a responsible balance between benefits and risks, take action to prevent accidents and equip ourselves with the right technology and strategies to respond to potential problems.
To achieve this, we must work together on a regional level and share our strengths and capacities.
The elaboration of a new protocol on offshore oil and gas exploration and exploitation |is on the agenda of the Conference of Parties to the Abidjan Convention for Co-operation in the Protection, Manage- ment and Development of the Marine and Coastal Environment of the West, Central and Southern Africa Region, opening today in Cape Town.
Beginning negotiation on safety and environmental standards for the booming offshore oil and gas sector would be an important step towards achieving the principal goal of this year's meeting - "Promoting Blue Growth in Africa".
This week, the convention has the opportunity to become a leading example of effective regional co-operation worthy of emulation worldwide.
Protecting the marine environment is absolutely essential for Africa. As commissioners serving in the Global Ocean Commission (GOC), we strongly support measures to improve safety in the rapidly-growing offshore oil and gas industry to reduce the risk of accidents and other problems that could jeopardise the health of our ocean and coasts and potentially harm fishing, tourism and other important maritime sectors. A clear regional agreement setting environmental standards will reduce the uncertainty and inconsistency within the offshore industry.
The direction being taken by the members of the Abidjan Convention is entirely in keeping with the recommendations presented to the GOC by independent French think-tank International Institute on International Relations and Sustainable Development. The institute assessed the risks inherent in the current seascape of the global offshore oil and gas industry, and found it to be the least internationally-regulated marine-related industry.
While the shipping and fishing sectors are subject to a myriad of international and regional agreements related to environmental safety and liability and compensation issues, there is a glaring regulatory gap at the international level when it comes to the offshore oil and gas industry.
Considering that a third of all oil consumed globally is sourced offshore, that we are now routinely drilling at depths of over 2km and that devastating accidents can and do occur, this is a highly precarious situation that must be addressed. We have no right to leave the continent, and indeed the region, vulnerable to the vagaries of the oil and gas industry.
Since recent attempts - for example by the G20 and through the UN's International Maritime Organisation - to reach a global agreement have met with strong resistance by certain states, bolstering regional co-operation is the most logical and practical answer.
The GOC recommends that existing regional agreements, such as the Abidjan Convention, expand and strengthen their provisions to include or reinforce the environmental safety of offshore oil and gas activities. In the case of Africa's western seaboard, this should include special consideration for fishing, which is so important for livelihoods.
Another factor of relevance to our region is the question of capacity building. Regardless of how comprehensive and well-meaning a regional regulation may be, it will not deliver the desired outcomes and results if states lack the means - including technical, financial and human capacity - to implement it.
Alongside regional initiatives, the Global Ocean Commission is also promoting the adoption of an international convention regulating liability and compensation for pollution damage resulting from offshore drilling activities.
l Manuel is co-chairman of the Global Ocean Commission. Ezekwesili is former vice-president of the World Bank for Africa, former Nigerian education minister and co-founder of Transparency International, and GOC commissioner.
]]></text></news-item>