<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-W9T1-JCDG-R2D6"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>PRISM: IBM insists customer data remains safe despite NSA snooping concerns</title><source>V3.co.uk</source><author>Michael Passingham</author><text><![CDATA[IBM has joined the chorus of technology companies slamming the NSA's data snooping practices, insisting that it has never willingly given away customer data following government requests.
In an , the company's general counsel Robert Weber called for an overhaul in the US's spying tactics while attempting to calm client concerns.
"IBM is fundamentally an enterprise company, meaning our customers are typically other companies and organisations rather than individual consumers," he wrote. Weber added that this situation was helped by IBM's business model, which does not involve telephony or other communication services, the information usually sought by surveillance bodies.
Weber categorically stated that IBM has never provided client data to the NSA under the PRISM scheme. He said IBM had never put "back doors" into its technology for surveillance organisations to use, but the firm would continue to comply with local laws when responding to data requests. It maintained that for data stored outside of the US, surveillance operations would have to abide by relevant legal regulations and treaties.
By way of reform, Weber said that governments should "not subvert commercial technologies" such as encryption and called for increased transparency about the data they collect.
IBM also made a jab at European data protection policy, calling some data localisation requirements "short sighted", arguing they "do little to improve security but distort markets and lend themselves to protectionist tendencies". IBM told V3 last week that .
IBM's blog post is very much in line with the tech industry's consistent outrage with the NSA's PRISM programme. While the post was not made in a timely fashion and does not appear to be responding to any recent accusations, Weber said clients had been asking about the firm's approach to relinquishing data.
Last year, IBM alongside EMC and Oracle as the country sought to protect its citizens from any potential snooping from the outside. This reportedly had a significant hit on IBM sales in China, with the company subsequently facing a lawsuit from shareholders accusing it of working alongside the NSA. IBM dismissed the claim as a "wild conspiracy theory".
]]></text></news-item>