<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-NXG1-JC8V-61FD"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>The Wall Street Journal</title><source>JAGfn.com</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Glencore Xstrata Nears Deal to Sell Peru Copper Project - Glencore Xstrata is close to a multibillion-dollar sale of its Las Bambas Peruvian copper project to a Chinese consortium and could announce the deal as early as Tuesday.German Firms Face Risk Over Russia - German businesses and politicians for decades worked hand-in-hand to improve ties with Russia. But those common interests appear to be waning as Merkel threatens trade sanctions over Ukraine.RWE to Sell Oil Unit - German utility RWE AG intends to sell its oil and gas production unit to Russian billionaire Mikhail Fridman for more than $7 billion.EU Probes Liberty Global's Ziggo Deal - Brussels' antitrust watchdog will review the planned $9.6 billion acquisition of the Dutch cable operator as investors look for clues to the regulator's approach to Europe's rapidly-consolidating telecoms industry.U.S. Justice Department Probes TeliaSonera - A continuing probe of TeliaSonera's business dealings in Uzbekistan widened as the U.S. Justice Department and the Securities and Exchange Commission opened investigations.Twitter CEO's China Visit Is Interesting, But Not For The Reason You Think - Twitter Inc. Chief Executive Dick Costolo is in Shanghai for a few days, but that doesn't mean Twitter will follow.Hong Kong Exchange Presses for Rule Changes - Hours after Hong Kong lost the Alibaba IPO to New York, the exchange's head is seeking regulatory changes.Just-Eat to Float in London - Online restaurant delivery company Just-Eat said it intends to raise up to $166 million in an initial public offering on the London Stock Exchange.Adjustable-Rate Mortgages Make a Comeback - Adjustable-rate mortgages, one of the main culprits of the housing crisis, are back in vogue.
But banks say this time is different.Entertainment Chief Extends NBC's Range - With hits like "The Black List," NBC's Bob Greenblatt has made progress in turning around the network, which has spent most of a decade in the doldrums. Now, his task is to sustain its momentum.
]]></text></news-item>