<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-DRK1-JCDY-T229"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>BRTRC Federal Solutions acquires cybersecurity company SecureForce</title><source>Washingtonpost.com</source><author>Mohana Ravindranath;Marjorie Censer</author><text><![CDATA[BRTRC Federal Solutions, a Tysons-based federal technology contractor, announced last week it had acquired Sterling-based cybersecurity company SecureForce. Terms of the deal were not disclosed.
SecureForce's clients include the Department of Veteran Affairs and the Transportation Security Administration. For now, the approximately 15-person firm will maintain its office in Sterling, and be treated as a division of BRTRC, according to BRTRC Chief Operating Officer Larry McDonald.
"[N]ot only does it expand our capabilities in the area of cyber, big data and analytics, it also gives us access to new markets like the [Department of Veterans Affairs, Transportation Security Administration] and the intelligence community," McDonald, also part-owner of the company, said.
The two companies have been collaborating on various projects for the past couple of years, he said. This is the first acquisition BRTRC has made in 25 years.
BRTRC was particularly interested in SecureForce because "cyber is going to be a part of the entire IT backbone," McDonald said. It could be the first of many acquisitions in the cybersecurity and intelligence space, he added.
In 2006, three of BRTRC's then-owners - former executive vice president William Baum, former chief executive and president Gerado Sanzand former vice president Gary Romstedt- pleaded guilty to conspiring to defraud the government, after being accused of falsifying tax returns in an effort to pass off personal vacation homes as corporate offices. All stepped down from their managerial positions that year and no longer are involved with the company.
Contractors lose protests
A Booz Allen Hamiltonunit in Rockville and Fairfax-based SRA Internationalfailed to dislodge Lockheed Martin from work to maintain and update a Food and Drug Administration database. Booz Allen took issue with the technical evaluation, but the Government Accountability Office found the agency within its rights to question Booz Allen's provisions for providing off-hours support. The GAO dismissed SRA's protest, finding the company's offer did not meet bid requirements.
GAO denies Business Integra's protest
The GAO denied a protest by Greenbelt-based Business Integraseeking to force the Department of Homeland Security to reconsider its bid for IT services. The GAO sided with the agency, finding that the woman-owned company failed to propose prices for every labor category as required by the solicitation, even if Business Integra intended the price for some categories to be zero.
Exelis resolves GPS patent claims with Blackberry
McLean-based defense contractor Exelisreached a license agreement with Blackberry, resolving claims that Blackberry's devices containing assisted-GPS technology infringed Exelis's patent rights. Specific details of the license agreement, which Exelis announced last week, were not disclosed.
mohana.ravindranath@washpost.com
]]></text></news-item>