<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-4561-JCW9-X1VF"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>EDITORIAL; Critical questions for GOP gov race</title><source>Chicago Sun-Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Republican voters thinking about sitting out of Tuesday's primary election for governor might want to think again.
The victor almost certainly will take on Democrat Pat Quinn, who has only nominal opposition on Tuesday, in November. That's a match-up a Republican could well win. Tuesday's choice, then, is of potentially profound importance to the future of Illinois.
The next leader of Illinois will set a direction for the state at a most precarious moment. Under Quinn, Illinois has begun a slow, fitful ascent out of a fiscal abyss. But the mountain top remains miles above. A temporary income tax begins to expire in 2015, blowing a hole as large as $2.2 billion in the state's budget; Illinois' unemployment rate remains stubbornly high and its business climate stubbornly unappealing. Add the state's $5.4 billion backlog of bills and the list of Illinois' woes reaches crisis proportions. To help voters make a thoughtful decision in the GOP governor's race, we've compiled a few key questions voters should consider. ◆ The style question: What kind of leader do you want? Tuesday's primary will decide whether the Republican candidate is a bold-talking political outsider who vows to shake up government or an experienced Springfield hand who appreciates the art of compromise and knows how the sausage is made. On the one extreme is billionaire businessman Bruce Rauner, a newbie to politics who vows to turn Springfield upside down. He brags about his lack of political experience - never even served in a student council. Contrast that with Rauner's three opponents - state Sen. Kirk Dillard, state Sen. Bill Brady and former legislator and current State Treasurer Dan Rutherford. All three have paired private sector work with decades in Springfield, a liability in the current climate, but not without value given that a governor needs allies to get things done. How well our next governor can take on House Speaker Michael Madigan, who calls most of the shots in Springfield, is critical. Will he go to war with him? Will going to war work? ◆ The revenue question: Where do you find $2.2 billion? If the temporary income tax begins expiring as scheduled in January 2015, the state is expected to lose $1.7 billion to $2.2 billion, depending on whose estimates you use. By 2016, that is projected to rise to $4.4 billion annually. Much of state spending is mandatory, leaving areas to cut limited to agencies covering education and human services and the like, which already have been slashed. The Civic Federation, a non-partisan budget watchdog group, estimates that dealing with the revenue loss through spending cuts, even without addressing the state's $5.4 billion in unpaid bills, would require state agency cuts of $2.7 billion between this year and 2016. Rauner and Brady oppose extending the income tax. Dillard recently changed his strict opposition to an extension, saying on Thursday that all options should be on the table. As a last resort, Dillard says he's open to phasing out the tax. Rutherford says he can't predict what he'll do until he becomes governor. Like all four men, he favors "a comprehensive, long-term resolution" for Illinois. To make up the lost revenue, all four candidates offer generalities. Dillard speaks of eliminating regulations, reforming Medicaid and growing the economy. Rauner wants tax reform that lowers the tax burden, a plan that "truly" solves the state's pension crisis, Medicaid reform, a government spending audit and a booming economy. Brady talks of improving the business climate, implementing pension reform (he's the only Republican candidate who supported that bill when it passed in December), ending outdated programs, more Medicaid savings and reform of the tax code. No candidate, including Quinn, who will release his financial plan on March 26, has laid out a detailed, comprehensive plan for dealing with that looming hole. ◆ The business question: How to improve Illinois' lagging business climate? This question is at the center of the Republican race, which each candidate insistent that an improved business climate is the elixir to most of what ails Illinois - a more hospitable climate will drive down unemployment rates and generate tax revenue that could go to schools, human services and more. One area of difference between the candidates: Rauner generally opposes tax breaks and incentives to entice businesses to Illinois, saying the government shouldn't be picking winners and losers. A better way, he says, would be to overhaul the tax code and anti-competitive regulations. His opponents generally agree on reforming regulations and the tax code, as well as reforming workers compensation and unemployment insurance, but are open to the limited use of tax incentives. As with the candidates' positions on other issues, voters here are treated to more generalities. What kind of tax reform? How will workers comp reform this time around differ from past efforts that produced only modest results? Voters likely won't get deep-dive answers before Tuesday - that's not the way to win an election. But the basic contours of their positions are widely known and, in the case of the so-called career politicians, long legislative records to mull over. The next governor of Illinois faces a herculean task. It is crucial, beginning with a thoughtful vote in this Republican primary, to choose the very best man for the job.
]]></text></news-item>