<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S1Y2"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Coal Export Advocates Fight Potential Precedent Of State's GHG Review</title><source>Carbon Control News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Manufacturers and states supportive of coal exports fear Washington state's recent decision to assess potential greenhouse gases (GHGs) from overseas coal combustion in a review of a proposed export terminal may set a precedent for other states, and are suggesting the GHG review could be at odds with federal requirements.
The push-back on the review -- which manufacturers warn could endanger exports of other U.S. goods by subjecting them to comprehensive environmental analysis for GHGs or other impacts -- is the latest stage in a long-running fight on whether, and how, to assess domestic and global GHGs associated with coal exports.
The debate is key to the future of coal exports, which the Energy Information Administration (EIA) says will rise from 110 million short tons in 2013 to 160 million short tons in 2040.
EIA in a Feb. 27 "Today In Energy" brief predicts that factors driving that increase will include an increase in coal demand, as well as coal production challenges in countries such as China, India, and South Africa.
Increasing domestic production of oil and natural gas, as well as waning domestic coal demand -- is prompting some energy state lawmakers to push for increasing exports of energy. For example, Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-AK), ranking member on the energy panel, is calling on the Obama administration to take steps under existing executive authority to boost crude oil and other energy exports in lieu of Congress moving a bill to bolster exports, but questions remain about the extent to which agencies must analyze the environmental impacts of exports.
Environmentalist opponents of exports say exporting more coal to those and other countries will lead to significant increases in overseas GHGs associated with coal combustion by industries in those countries.
Advocates are already pursuing some legal efforts to block coal exports, for example filing a legal challenge to a U.S. Export-Import Bank loan guarantee that supports exports of Appalachian coal, which environmentalists claim violates the National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA) and the Administrative Procedure Act.
But observers say any litigation related to pending reviews of proposed coal export terminals in Washington is unlikely at least this year, because the environmental reviews by Washington and the Army Corps of Engineers are still in the drafting stages.
Environmentalists have argued that the Army Corps is violating federal law by restricting the scope of its analysis of the Washington projects related to GHG emissions and other impacts.
The state announced Feb. 12 that its review under the State Environmental Policy Act (SEPA) of a proposed coal export terminal -- the Millennium Bulk Terminal at Longview -- will include at least some review of GHGs from end use combustion of exported coal. The decision to look at least in part at end use combustion of coal also tracks with a similar approach in a pending analysis for a proposed export terminal at Cherry Point, WA.
The focus on end use coal combustion contrasts with the Army Corps' repeated position that GHG emissions from coal burned abroad falls outside the scope of required review under the NEPA.
Coal export projects require an Army Corps permit due to their impacts on waters of the United States, and EPA has called for a broad review by the Army Corps of the projects that includes impacts from coal burned abroad, in order to account for impacts including effects of GHGs and transported mercury on the United States.
Manufacturers' Concerns
In response to Washington's announced intent to partially examine GHGs from coal exports, National Association of Manufacturers Vice President of Energy and Resources Policy Ross Eisenberg said it "sets an unnecessary precedent for manufacturers that could make it harder to obtain approvals -for almost every product we export, from grains to airplanes."
Eisenberg also suggested that any move by the state to curb coal exports would violate World Trade Organization rules, referencing arguments that NAM made in a report it commissioned and released in late 2013 arguing that other countries could challenge federal and state delays in coal or gas exports as violations of free trade rules.
Many officials at the state and federal level, including Washington Gov. Jay Inslee (D) and Oregon Gov. John Kitzhaber (D-OR) have called for several years for a comprehensive reviews of coal exports, in response to coal terminal proposals pending in both states. But observers note that Washington in particular could have significance as a precedent because the state has a SEPA law similar to the federal NEPA, while Oregon does not.
Two separate but coordinated reviews of the Longview project are underway by the Army Corps, Washington State and Cowlitz County, WA, with the latter state and county review to include at least some SEPA review of end use coal combustion. The review will not, however, include environmental effects in importing countries.
Eisenberg in a follow up interview with Clean Energy Report revived several arguments from November 2013 NAM comments that a broad "lifecycle" review of the Longview project would create a troubling precedent that could block exports of numerous types of manufactured goods.
Eisenberg also praised the Army Corps of Engineers' embrace of a narrower review of coal export projects under NEPA not expected to include greenhouse gas emissions abroad. And he downplayed the threat of the SEPA review to the Army Corps' NEPA decision, referencing prior Washington State appeals court suggesting that the NEPA trumps SEPA in the case of "joint" review of the project.
But Eisenberg also expressed concern that Washington's approach sets a precedent other states may try to push in similar environmental reviews of infrastructure projects.
"Environmental policies tend to be contagious from state to state," he said. And he acknowledged that Washington's SEPA and the federal NEPA contain similar statutory language, meaning environmentalists are likely to cite Washington state's broad analysis in any future case challenging the Army Corps narrower view of its responsibilities under NEPA. He also characterized calls for a broad SEPA analysis as a delaying tactic.
Potential Litigation
Several observers say that any litigation pursuant to the Longview or Cherry Point environmental reviews is at least a year or more away, with environmental documents still in the drafting stage and some environmentalists suggesting that a soft coal market abroad is putting coal export projects in jeopardy.
But some coal states appear to be at least weighing such a battle, amid press reports that pending budget legislation in Wyoming includes $500,000 in funding for possible litigation over the next two years on coal exports.
NAM in its November scoping comments on the Longview project raised concern about the policy precedent of examining lifecycle emissions from exports.
The group also argued that NEPA's intent is to require federal agencies to "document and disseminate" information on the environmental impact of their actions to the public, not to "curtail or significantly delay federal action [ or] require a detailed review of the indirect impacts of U.S. commodity exports abroad."
Montana and North Dakota, meanwhile, in separate November comments on the proposed Longview facility criticized any evaluation of GHG emissions from combustion of the exported coal abroad, as well as use of that approach in reviewing the proposed Cherry Point facility. The states also suggested that any restriction on coal exports by the states would be unconstitutional limit on interstate commerce.
"The effect of any decision to limit or prohibit coal exports would fall entirely upon other states . . . It seeks in effect to impose upon other states the cost of a policy decision in the State of Washington, by discriminating against products produced in other states in applying its regulatory jurisdiction," the states argued.
Any move by Washington State or others to curb coal exports from coal states is improper because "the U.S. Congress has not authorized states to regulate interstate commerce in relation to climate change," they wrote.
Washington State Department of Ecology's Sally Toteff in a Feb. 13 statement provided to Clean Energy Reportdownplayed the notion that the inclusion of overseas GHG emissions in the analysis for Longview constitutes a move to block the project. "An environmental impact statement (EIS) is not a permit. It is not a yes or no decision on the project," Toteff said, adding that every project is reviewed on a case by case basis.
The statement also noted that several federal agencies have issued EIS documents taking into account a range of GHGs from coal or energy commodities, including a Bureau of Land Management EIS for coal leasing that includes GHGs from the combustion of mined coal, and the State Department's EIS for the Keystone tar sands pipeline. Observers have split over whether the Obama administration will ultimately approve that project. -- Doug Obey (dobey@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>