<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S1YX"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Environmentalists Urge EPA To Halt Fracking Waste Discharges To Ocean</title><source>Clean Energy Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Environmentalists are asking EPA to amend a Clean Water Act general permit for offshore oil and gas exploration in order to halt the discharge of waste from hydraulic fracturing operations into federal waters off California's southern coastline, the latest step in a battle environmentalists are waging against fracking operations in the state.
But oil industry representatives are criticizing the Center for Biological Diversity's (CBD) push, noting that the group fails to mention that companies are required to treat well stimulation waste according to strict federal standards before it is discharged and that CBD's aim is to halt all fossil fuel energy production by any means.
CBD filed a Feb. 26 petition with EPA headquarters and Region IX officials asking for a "rulemaking on ocean discharge criteria and to modify [an] offshore oil and gas general permit" specific to California.
The petition seeks an amendment to a National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) general permit for offshore oil and gas exploration, development and production operations off southern California, a revised version of which was issued last month by EPA. It also asks EPA to develop national guidelines for offshore fracking pollution.
The 44-page petition says EPA allows offshore oil rigs to dump "dangerous fracking chemicals into the ocean just off the coast of California directly into sensitive habitat for blue whales, leatherback sea turtles, and many other endangered species."
CBD argues that the latest revised permit "lets oil companies discharge more than 9 billion gallons of wastewater into the ocean each year," according to the petition.
"That wastewater can be contaminated with chemicals from unconventional well stimulation such as . . . fracking. This petition seeks to protect human health and California's rich coastal and marine ecosystems from the hazards of fracking by prohibiting ocean dumping of well stimulation chemicals," CBD says.
Oil companies have hydraulically fractured more than a dozen wells in recent years in federal waters off California, CBD claims. About half the oil platforms in the Santa Barbara Channel discharge some or all of their wastewater into the sea, according to the group. CBD says the current NPDES permit authorizes 23 offshore oil and gas platforms to discharge wastewater into federal waters off California.
Fracking Wastewater
Environmentalists say that under California regulations, drilling operators are prohibited from dumping fracking wastewater directly into the ocean in state waters, which is defined as within three miles of the coast. In this area, operators typically treat wastewater and reinject it into reservoirs or into permitted waste disposal wells, according to state officials.
EPA is required to respond to the petition, according to CBD, which quotes federal administrative law in the document. "'Prompt notice shall be given of the denial in whole or in part of a written application, petition, or other request of an interested person made in connection with any agency proceeding,'" the petition states.
CBD is battling fracking and other well stimulation treatments in California on a number of fronts, having filed several state and federal lawsuits challenging environmental reviews conducted by federal agencies on oil lease sales, and pressing state regulators and lawmakers to either ban or stringently regulate the practices.
EPA Region IX officials received the petition "and are currently reviewing it," says a spokesman with the office. In addition, the petition "involves both regional and headquarters matters and we cannot anticipate when our review will be complete," the spokesman says.
An oil industry source responds that water discharges into federal waters "are highly regulated, tested and permitted. If discharges contain harmful levels of chemicals, they are not allowed. CBD has a history of making these unfounded claims."
A spokesman for the Western States Petroleum Association says CBD's petition and accompanying press release represent "typical disinformation from this organization. Nowhere do they mention that all of the fluid produced at offshore platforms is first treated to very strict standards required by the NPDES permits before it is disposed of. Also, there is almost no hydraulic fracturing taking place offshore of California. This is just another of the CBD's ongoing campaign to disrupt energy production by any and all means possible."
]]></text></news-item>