<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-GRT1-F091-R3K4"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Serbia centre-right party tries to tighten grip in snap poll</title><source>Pretoria News (South Africa)</source><author> Reuters</author><text><![CDATA[BELGRADE: Serbia's centre-right Progressive Party tried to cement its grip on power for the next four years in a snap election yesterday, promising an economic overhaul of the former Yugoslav republic as it embarks on talks to join the EU.
Opinion polls suggest the party may win more than 40 percent of the vote - unprecedented in the almost 14 years since Serbia came in from the cold after strongman Slobodan Milosevic was ousted.
Party leader Aleksandar Vucic, 44, a former ultra-nationalist and once feared Milosevic-era minister who converted to the pro-EU cause in 2008, will probably become prime minister.
The Progressive Party forced the snap election after just 18 months in coalition government, saying it needed a stronger mandate to overhaul Serbia's shaky finances.
The party's domination owes much to Vucic's popularity as the face of an anti-crime crusade in which Balkan retail tycoon Miroslav Miskovic and others have been put on trial. The campaign has struck a chord with many Serbs angry at decades of deep-rooted graft.
Critics, however, are unnerved at the power amassed by a man who up until five years ago was a virulent anti-Western disciple of the Greater Serbia ideology that fuelled the wars of Yugoslavia's demise in the 1990s. Vucic now says Serbia must follow fellow former Yugoslav republics Slovenia and Croatia into the EU, and is advocating reform of the bloated public sector, pension system and labour legislation.
"I expect reforms, job creation and the fight against corruption to be the main issues after the election," Vucic said as he voted in New Belgrade.
The country of 7.3 million people must commit itself to reining in its budget deficit and public debt to secure a precautionary deal with the International Monetary Fund for a loan, which could come soon after a new government is formed. The opposition is warning voters against giving Vucic too much power. He was information minister in the 1990s when newspapers were fined and shut under a law designed to muzzle dissent as Milosevic led Serbia into war with Nato over Kosovo.
]]></text></news-item>