<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S218"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Appellate Court Upholds Limited Health Impacts Review Of Mining Permit</title><source>Superfund Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A federal appeals court says the Army Corps of Engineers properly limited its review of health impacts from a Clean Water Act (CWA) dredge-and-fill permit for a Kentucky mine to only "local, proximate" impacts specifically linked to regulated disposal activities, rejecting environmentalists' claims that cancer and other risks from the operation should be weighed.
"The Corps did not entirely ignore the public health effects of granting the permit, but rather reasonably limited its scope of analysis only to those human health effects closely related to the discharge of fill or dredged material into jurisdictional stream beds," a three-judge panel of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the 6th Circuit wrote in its March 7 ruling in Kentuckians for the Commonwealth, et al., v. U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, et al.
The panel, Judges Damon J. Keith, John M. Rogers and Eugene E. Siler, found that the Corps' limitation of its National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA) review of the potential human health impacts resulting from approving a CWA section 404 permit to only those "closely related" to the discharge of dredge-and-fill material did not violate NEPA.
Further, the 6th Circuit rejected environmentalists' argument that acceptance of the mine company's compensatory mitigation plan under the CWA was arbitrary and capricious, deferring to the Corps' expertise that the provisions in the plan were "rationally designed to ensure that there is not a net loss of aquatic function in the mine location's watershed." The ruling is available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID: 2464275)
The decision upholds a district court ruling which rejected environmentalists' challenge to a 404 permit issued to Leeco, Inc. for a large scale mountaintop mining operation in Knott and Perry Counties in Kentucky.
Environmental groups argued that the Corps violated NEPA in failing to take a "hard look" at potential environmental impacts, saying the Corps' finding of no significant impact failed to thoroughly assess the human health effects, including potential birth defects and cancer, of the large scale mine -- though NEPA focuses mostly on environmental impacts.
The advocates' complaint cited a study published in the Jan. 8, 2010 issue of Science, saying, "Adult hospitalizations for chronic pulmonary disorders and hypertension are elevated as a function of county-level coal production, as are rates of mortality; lung cancer; and chronic heart, lung and kidney disease."
The district court ruled that the Corps lawfully limited the scope of its analysis to activities within the jurisdictional waters, adjacent wetlands and riparian areas at issue in the permit, rejecting environmentalists' argument that because the mine could not proceed without the 404 permit, the review should be broader to include the entire mine.
In the appellate court opinion, the panel held that the district court's conclusion that the Corps' minor role in the regulatory regime for surface mining indicates it does not have sufficient control over other aspects of a mine to warrant expanding the NEPA review.
"The Corps did not violate NEPA by deciding not to consider the evidence linking surface coal mining in general to public health problems" because it focused its review narrowly on "local" health effects from potential water supply impacts and those caused by air pollution from machines used in the dredge-and-fill activities, the judges say.
"This analysis of health effects, albeit not as comprehensive and wide in scope as that demanded by the plaintiffs, was reasonable given the more limited nature of the threshold inquiry of whether the Corps's action significantly affects the human environment," the opinion says.
Moreover, Council on Environmental Quality regulations on NEPA give the Corps some discretion on public health effects, suggesting only that they "should" be considered, but not which subsets of health effects are significant, the court says.
]]></text></news-item>