<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-SB11-JBVR-32YV"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>The Canadian Press News Agenda for Monday, Mar 17; The Canadian Press News Agenda for Monday, Mar. 17</title><source>Canadian Press</source><author>The Canadian Press</author><text><![CDATA[EDITORS: Following is a list of news events for Mar. 17 as of 3:05 a.m. ET: x-denotes wire, y-denotes picture, z-denotes graphics coverage. Copy from other events based on merit and availability. All times local unless otherwise noted. Queries about these events and stories in The Canadian Press report should be directed to the departments listed below (all phone numbers 416 area code):
Main Desk (National News) 507-2150; World Desk 507-2165; Sports Desk 507-2154; Ontario Desk 507-2159; Photo Desk 507-2169; Specials Desk (Syndicated Copy) 507-2152; IT Desk (Technical Trouble) 507-2099 or 800-268-8149
WORLD
BOSTON - A delegation of Canadian seafood industry companies and organizations will join the Honourable Gail Shea, Minister of Fisheries and Oceans, on a business mission to the 2014 Seafood Expo North America, from March 16-18. A teleconference takes place at 1 p.m. with Minister Shea and several of the Canadian seafood companies and organizations attending the Expo. Dial 613-990-7537 or email Media.XNCR@dfo-mpo.gc.ca before 11 a.m. to participate in the teleconference.
ATLANTIC
SAINT JOHN, N.B. - Rodney Weston, MP for SaintJohn, and New Brunswick Tourism Minister Trevor Holder participate in groundbreaking ceremony to mark the beginning of construction of Greater Saint John YM-YWCA. (1:30 p.m. at Greater Saint John YM-YWCA, 205 Churchill Boulevard)
x-BRIDGEWATER, N.S. - Jury trial to begin for John Leonard MacKean, who is charged in the confinement of a teenage boy. MacKean is charged with sexual assault and communicating for the purpose of obtaining sexual services from a person under 18. (9:30 a.m. at Nova Scotia Supreme Court)
x-FREDERICTON - Steve Morck of TransCanada speaks to the Fredericton Chamber of Commerce and the Fredericton North Rotary Club about the Energy East pipeline project. (11:45 a.m. at Fredericton Inn)
HALIFAX - Peter MacKay, federal minister of justice, makes an announcement on behalf of Canadian Parents for French. (3:30 p.m. at 8 Flamingo Drive)
PICTOU, N.S. - Carolyn Amy Hood is scheduled to face sex offence charges involving two teenaged boys. Hood is a teacher at Thorburn Consolidated School. (Pictou provincial court)
QUEBEC
Activities for Liberal Leader Philippe Couillard: at 8:30 a.m., an announcement related to seniors at 435 Cure-Labelle Boul. in Laval, at 11 a.m. a visit to a riding in office Laval-des-Rapides at 603 Saint-Martin W. Boul. At 1 p.m., a photo opportunity at Residence Angelica at 3435 Boul. Gouin Est. At 6:30 p.m., party members meet at St-Hubert Restaurant, 725 chemin Jean-Adam in Piedmont.
Activities for Coalition party leader Francois Legault. A news conference at 9:30 a.m. to announce new candidates, at the Delta Hotel at 475 President Kennedy Ave. in Montreal. At 11:30 a.m., a public lunch at Tutti Frutti Restaurant at 265 St Laurent in St-Eustache. At 1:55 p.m., a visit to the Nadeau family at 928 Carre Champetre in Boisbriand. At 3:45 p.m., a visit to the business Jalbert Automatisation at 5060 Ambroise-Lafortune St. in Boisbriand.
OTTAWA
OTTAWA - Statistics Canada releases Canada's international transactions in securities for January. (8:30 a.m. at www.statcan.gc.ca)
OTTAWA - University of Ottawa press conference to highlight some of the 100+ key lessons learned from the demise of Nortel. Three years ago, an interdisciplinary team of University of Ottawa professors from the Telfer School of Management, the Faculty of Engineering and the Faculty of Law set out to learn about corporate failure based on the demise of Nortel, once Canada's largest company. (12 p.m. at Desmarais Building, 55 Laurier Ave. E, Ottawa â(EURO)" 4th Floor, Room 4101)
OTTAWA - Patrick Brazeau appears in court on charges of fraud and breach of trust arising from the Senate scandal. (Provincial Courthouse 161 Elgin St.)
ONTARIO
Conference call with Meagan Duhamel and Eric Radford ahead of world figure skating championships. (11:30 a.m.)
Conference call with Kaitlyn Weaver and Andrew Poje ahead of world figure skating championships. (3 p.m.)
y-Official Opposition Leader Tom Mulcair will be touring Southern Ontario to continue his affordability campaign, talk jobs, agriculture and the Canada Post cut backs. Monday March 17: Time: 10:15 a.m., Location: 1738 Lawrence Avenue East, Toronto. St. Patrick's Day Celebrations. Time: 12:30 p.m., Location: Dora Keogh, 141 Danforth Avenue, Toronto. St. Patrick's Day Celebrations. Time: 6:15 p.m., Location: Brampton Irish Centre, 20 Strathearn Avenue ·5, Brampton. Town Hall on Jobs and Affordability with MPP Jagmeet Singh. Time: 7:30 p.m., Location: Terry Miller Recreation Centre, 1295 Williams Parkway, Brampton.
x-BRAMPTON, Ont. - Trial of Garfield Boothe and Nichelle Boothe-Rowe, charged with second-degree murder in the death of Shakeil Boothe, 10. (9:30 a.m. at 7755 Hurontario St.)
xy-TORONTO - Toronto Fashion Week coverage plans: 5 p.m. Mikhael Kale; 6 p.m. VAWK; 7 p.m. Beaufille; 8 p.m. Line Knitwear; 9 p.m. Sid Neigum (David Pecaut Square, 221 King St. W.)
PRAIRIES
jsc staffing plans: G/A. On working Alberta cancer-tanning beds. Alberta police on school gay-straight alliances. New fines for meat plants that don't follow food safety rules.
BANFF, Alta. - Independent Power Producers Society conference. Alberta Energy Minister Diana McQueen gives keynote address Monday at 8:45. To March 18 (Fairmont Banff Springs, 405 Spray Ave.)
CALGARY - Group of Canadian paralympic athletes returning to Calgary from Sochi. (5 p.m. at Calgary International Airport)
CALGARY - Churchill Corp. releases fourth-quarter and year-end results before markets open, followed by a conference call and webcast at 7:30 a.m. Dial 1-800-319-4610, or go to http://www.churchillcorporation.com/news/events/.
EDMONTON - Introduction of Vickie Kaminski, news president and CEO of Alberta Health Services. (9 a.m. at Legislature, health minister's office, Room 208)
EDMONTON - Wildrose health critic Heather Forsyth and finance critic Rob Anderson discuss government's proposed Independent Budget Officer Act. (10:30 a.m. at Legislature Annex, Media Room, 7th Floor, 9718 107 St.)
EDMONTON - Alberta Association of Municipal Districts and Counties spring convention. Municipal Affairs Minister Ken Hughes speaks Tuesday at 8:30 a.m. To March 19 (Shaw Conference Centre, 9797 Jasper Ave.)
PEACE RIVER, Alta. - Abraham Azhakathu makes his first court appearance on charges of sexual assault and sexual interference against a minor during 2013 when he was a Catholic priest in Manning. (Provincial court)
RED DEER, Alta. - Public hearing by Alberta Utilities Commission into proposed AltaLink transmission line upgrades in central Alberta. Nearly 70 interveners have signed up to take part. (9 a.m. at Holiday Inn and Suites at 33 Petrolia Dr.)
WINNIPEG - Federal Public Works Minister Diane Finley addresses Winnipeg Chamber of Commerce and Aerospace Industries Association of Canada. (12:30 p.m. at Fort Garry Hotel, Provencher Room, 222 Broadway)
PRINCE ALBERT, Sask. - Trial for Art Dagenais on charges of unsafe storage of firearms. Dagenais is the father of convicted Mountie killer Curtis Dagenais. (Courthouse)
REGINA - Transit bus driver Darcy Allen Kluge to appear in court charged with driving without due care and attention in an accident that killed a pedestrian. (Courthouse)
BRITISH COLUMBIA
KELOWNA, B.C. - Trial for Matthew Foerster in the murder of Taylor Van Diest, 18, on Halloween night in 2011 in Amstrong. Jury selection expected March 18-20. File: 47160. (10 a.m. at Courtroom 2, Kelowna Law Courts, 1355 Water Street)
NEW WESTMINSTER, B.C. - James Moore, minister of industry, will be joined by Raymond Louie from the Federation of Canadian Municipalities and Mayor Wayne Wright from the City of New Westminster to announce Government of Canada support from the Green Municipal Fund. (10:30 a.m. at Westminster Pier Park 1 Sixth St.)
PORT COQUITLAM, B.C. - Court date for David May, charged with two counts of procuring, after two teenaged girls were allegedly lured into prostitution in Maple Ridge. (9:30 a.m. at Courtroom 1, Port Coquitlam Law Courts, 2620 Mary Hill Road)
RICHMOND, B.C. - Heart of Richmond AIDS Society holds 10th annual St. Patrick's Day safe sex campaign, handing out "get lucky" condom packages in Richmond bars, including The Flying Beaver, Legends Pub and O'Hares. Follow on Twitter at @heartofrichmond and ·GetLuckyRichmond. (6 p.m. at Various)
VANCOUVER - BC Teachers' Federation annual general meeting. Thru March 18. (Hyatt Regency Hotel, 655 Burrard Street)
VANCOUVER - A lawsuit targeting water withdrawals by oil and gas companies in north-eastern British Columbia will be heard by the B.C. Supreme Court on Monday. Before the hearing, Ecojustice, Sierra Club BC and the Wilderness Committee will hold a press briefing to describe the lawsuit and answer questions. (9 a.m. at Provincial Court terrace (Hearing at B.C. Supreme Court) 800 Hornby St.)
VANCOUVER - American Hotel Income Properties REIT LP releases year-end results before markets open, followed by a conference call and webcast at 5 p.m. Dial 416-764-8688 or go to www.ahipreit.com for the webcast.
NORTH
IQALUIT, Nunavut - Legal arguments and closing statements in the trial of Eric Dejaeger, former priest facing 68 sex abuse-related charged against Inuit children. He earlier pleaded guilty to eight other counts. (Law Courts)
Updated: March 17 3:05 a.m.
]]></text></news-item>