<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S1YD"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>EPA Weighs New Data On Methane Releases From Natural Gas Systems</title><source>Clean Energy Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EPA is seeking public input on how to incorporate new data from studies that produce actual measurements into its long-disputed calculations for natural gas systems' methane emissions, including findings that show emissions at lower levels than the agency has estimated, which have hindered advocates' push for strict new air rules.
The agency announced the review as part of its release of the latest draft estimates of the amount of GHGs released from various sectors. It is expected to include a series of ongoing studies jointly conducted by the Environmental Defense Fund (EDF), industry and the University of Texas at Austin that show emissions measured from some natural gas sources at considerably lower than EPA's annual estimates.
"There are relevant ongoing studies that are collecting new information related to natural gas system emissions," the agency says in its "Draft Inventory of U.S. Greenhouse Gas Emissions and Sinks: 1990-2012," released last month ahead of a March 26 comment deadline. "EPA looks forward to reviewing information and data from these studies as they become available for potential incorporation in the Inventory."
The agency says that it anticipates reviewing upcoming data from the studies on transmission, storage and distribution systems for potential updates to the 1990-2013 inventory report.
Environmental groups and some researchers have used EPA's existing methane emissions data to charge that the overall carbon footprint of gas-fired electricity generation is greater than coal generation, including a high-profile 2011 study by Cornell researcher Robert Howarth that relied on the EPA estimates.
In addition, environmentalists are continuing to press the agency for specific controls on emissions of the GHG methane from natural gas production after EPA opted against imposing direct methane controls in its recent final new source performance standards for the sector.
EPA has for several years taken steps to improve its data on methane from the sector, partially in response to an Dec. 20, 2012, Inspector General (IG) report urging the agency to improve its oil and gas sector emissions estimates.
The agency has since outlined a number of steps it will take to improve emissions estimates, including establishing a joint effort between its air and research offices to craft a strategy for improving its oil and gas emissions data, emissions factors, and methodologies for measuring releases from oil and gas sources.
In the February draft GHG inventory, EPA now says it is "interested in feedback on how information from such measurement studies can be used to update Inventory estimates."
Methane Emissions
Among the assessments that EPA is likely to review is the first in a 16-part series of studies, which EDF is jointly conducting with the University of Texas and a host of oil and gas companies. That study examined direct measurements of methane emissions from the extraction phase of natural gas production at 190 sites across the country.
Those findings, published Sept. 16 in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences (PNAS), are significant because they represents rare actual measurements of methane leaks -- which many believe are necessary to getting a full understanding of the potential GHG footprint over the lifecycle of natural gas production, given that methane is considered to be 72 times more potent a GHG than carbon dioxide over a 20-year time span.
Among the factors the agency is considering include whether measurements taken are representative of all natural gas producing regions in the United States, whether the activities taking place at the time of the measurements were routine operations or high-emission venting events, and how such data can be incorporated into emission factors and used in calculating national estimates.
EPA says that during an expert peer review on the draft inventory, the agency received several comments suggesting that the EDF study be used for comparison and verification of the emission factors, and another comment.
Also in the draft inventory, EPA says that emissions of methane from the sector have dropped by 16.9 percent since 1990, largely due to increased voluntary efforts from the production sector, along with regulatory reductions, and increased use of plunger lifts, and distribution reductions due to a decrease in cast iron and unprotected steel pipelines. "Overall, natural gas systems emitted 127.1 Tg CO2 9 Eq. (6,052 Gg) of CH4 in 2012, a 16.9 percent decrease compared to 1990 emissions," the draft inventory says.
EDF launched the initial study in October 2012 launched the first portion of the study, which is seeking to develop data based on actual measurements for GHG releases from natural gas production, including from hydraulic fracturing. Other phases of the study will examine methane releases from the various stages of the natural gas lifecycle, including gathering and processing, long distance transmission and storage, local distribution and transportation.
EDF's analysis, published Sept. 16 in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, says that the measurements of the amount of emissions released during the flowback phase of fracking ranged from 0.01 megagrams (mg) to 17 mg, levels 97 percent lower than EPA stated in its 2011 greenhouse gas (GHG) estimates. Flowback is the part of the fracking process in which fracking fluid is separated from the well to make way for gas.
EDF says the findings show that the agency's new source performances standards (NSPS) for the sector -- which offers incentives for early adoption of emissions control technology -- are helping cut pollution.
Using industry survey data, EPA last year cut by as much as 20 percent its estimates of the amount of methane emitted from natural gas production, by incorporating the data into its calculations for liquids unloading, a key production process that the agency estimates contributes as much as 51 percent of the sector's methane emissions. -- Bridget DiCosmo (bdicosmo@iwpnews.com)
03-13-2014
]]></text></news-item>