<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-YRG1-JCBD-K212"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Toyota suspends production in India amid wage dispute</title><source>IHS Global Insight</source><author>Paul Newton</author><text><![CDATA[Toyota Kirloskar Motor, the India-based subsidiary of Toyota, has locked out workers at two of its plants near Bangalore as long-running wage negotiations have deteriorated amid allegations that workers used threats to sabotage production. The plants were shuttered yesterday (16 March) and Toyota's subsidiary said it did not know how long the lockout would continue. The lockout comes as the 10-month-old wage negotiations failed to reach a final agreement despite entering arbitration recently. Toyota said it was left "with no other option but to declare a lockout of the premises to ensure the safety of its workers and management personnel". The lockout will affect a total of around 6,400 workers at the two plants, which produce around 700 cars per day. Toyota said that, over the past 25 days, "certain sections of the employees have resorted to deliberate stoppages of the production line, abuse and threatening of supervisors thereby continuously disrupting business".
Significance:The lockout in Bangalore amid allegations of threats to workers again raises the issue of security at India's car manufacturing operations, following a spate of often deadly protests in recent times. In 2012, workers at Maruti Suzuki rioted in a protest that killed one Indian executive and left around 100 injured, and resulted in a USD250-million, month-long production loss. Auto components companies Pricol (based in Coimbatore) and Graziano Transmissioni (based in New Delhi) suffered fatalities to personnel department employees, killed by angry mobs of workers while in their offices. The latest lockout by Toyota again highlights the deep resentment over the vastly differing categories of workers employed in India's auto plants. Permanent employees, whose contracts usually entail a number of additional benefits as well as excellent job security, contrast sharply with short-term contract workers, who have few if any benefits and are hired and fired at will. The growth in the number of the latter is widely used in many companies to avoid India's rigid labour laws. The seemingly limitless availability of casual labour in India also allows companies to use this resource extensively. Driving much of the unrest has been India's persistent double-digit inflation, which erodes the value of wages earned by workers.
]]></text></news-item>