<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S1Y0"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>EPA Opposes Utility Citing 'Wrongly Decided' NSR Ruling In Pending Suit</title><source>Carbon Control News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EPA is opposing an Oklahoma utility's attempt to bolster its defense in a Clean Air Act new source review (NSR) case by citing a recent federal district court ruling that could constrain the agency's NSR enforcement, with EPA saying the ruling was "wrongly decided" and should have no bearing on the Oklahoma litigation.
EPA makes its claim in a March 6 legal filing in United States of America v. Oklahoma Gas & Electric Co. (OG&E), pending in the U.S. District Court for the Western District of Oklahoma, saying the ruling OG&E seeks to rely on is "almost entirely devoid of legal citations" and "defies both logic and the order" of an appellate remand.
In the OG&E suit, EPA says the utility is trying to avoid NSR rules that facilities must provide accurate projections of how upgrades will increase pollution, and instead provided an unenforceable plan that limits emissions until a five-year statute of limitations runs out, which the agency says falls short of requirements under the NSR program.
The case is seen by some observers as a new path for EPA to try to overcome courts' recent limits on NSR enforcement cases, including a March 3 ruling from U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan Judge Bernard Friedman in United States of America v. DTE Energy Company. In the ruling, Friedman said EPA can only provide a "cursory" review over a source's pre-construction emissions modeling when enforcing NSR -- seen as a significant limit to EPA's NSR enforcement authority.
OG&E is now trying to use that ruling to bolster its defense against its pending case, filing a March 5 notice of supplemental authority with the court saying Friedman's decision is "pertinent" to its motion to dismiss the agency's claims that it too had violated NSR. The ruling said because actual emissions at the DTE Energy plant did not increase, the government could not show the renovations were subject to NSR, and OG&E argues the same standard should apply to its project that has yet to increase emissions.
But EPA in its March 6 response says the Oklahoma utility is incorrect that the case is relevant to its case, because the government in OG&E is alleging that the company's "temporary emissions management scheme" does not meet a regulatory requirement to provide emission projections, "and the question of what does or does not suffice for an emissions projection is never addressed" by Friedman's ruling in the DTE Energy case.
An EPA spokeswoman did not respond to a question by press time about whether it plans to appeal the DTE Energy decision back to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the 6th Circuit. Friedman in 2011 originally heard that case and found for the utility, prompting the agency to appeal the case. The appellate court then remanded the case back to Friedman for what it found were "sweeping conclusions" about the agency's ability to pursue pre-construction NSR cases.
NSR mandates that stationary emissions sources obtain Clean Air Act permits prior to beginning construction, and the permits can require the installation of stringent air pollution control technology to prevent air pollution increases.
'Wrongly Decided'
EPA has not commented publicly on Friedman's March 3 ruling, which could pose hurdles for the agency's NSR enforcement efforts after finding the agency can only provide a "cursory" review over pre-construction emission projections and is largely limited to filing cases based on post-construction emissions data.
But the March 6 filing outlines the agency's arguments both for why the ruling in DTE Energy was wrongly decided, and also why it should not serve as a pertinent factor in the pending OG&E lawsuit.
At issue in DTE Energy case was whether the utility was allowed in NSR emission projections to say that any potential air pollution increases from a $65 million coal utility upgrade in 2010 were unrelated to the project, but rather were caused by increase in electricity demand that were exempted under what is called a "demand growth exclusion."
EPA said the utility's use of the demand growth exclusion was illegal -- electric demand was projected to fall, the agency said -- and that the project would increase the plant's potential to emit by thousands of tons each year.
But Friedman said EPA could not "second guess" the utility's use of the demand growth exclusion, and instead could only provide a "surface review" over the emission projections and sue later if they proved inaccurate.
Friedman in the ruling agreed that while the 6th Circuit remand required an operator to follow EPA's regulations for making an emissions projection, the agency did not have "unfettered authority" to challenge the projections. The ruling said the agency was taking DTE Energy "to task over the extent to which they relied on the demand growth exclusion," not their ability to apply the demand growth exclusion at all.
EPA, however, in the new filing says the opinion was "wrongly decided" and is faulting the court for its alleged failure to comply with the requirements of the 6th Circuit's remand last March. That ruling said that although operators could begin construction projects without having the agency "second-guess" their emission projections, their projections could be challenged by EPA to ensure they followed the agency's regulations.
The agency says that when the district court in DTE Energy ruled on the case, it should have followed the 6th Circuit's instructions to determine if DTE Energy was legally allowed under the agency's regulations to use the demand growth exclusion when it made the emission projections on the $65 million project. EPA says that did not occur, "instead replacing the regulatory test with its own 'surface review.'"
In doing so, EPA says the court "ignored volumes of record evidence, accepted the defendants claim of compliance to suffice for actual compliance, and flouted the Sixth Circuit's direct holding that 'a preconstruction projection is subject to an enforcement action by EPA to ensure that the projection is made pursuant to the requirements of the regulations.'" -- Chris Knight (cknight@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>