<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-8FB1-DYN6-W0X8"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>FEATURE: Crafts made by disabled in Fukushima prove popular in Japan, abroad</title><source>Japan Economic Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TOKYO, March 17 - People with disabilities living in the northeastern Japan prefecture of Fukushima, devastated by the March 2011 earthquake and tsunami, are doing their best to promote the area by making craft goods that are proving popular both at home and overseas.
Before the disasters and the subsequent nuclear crisis at Tokyo Electric Power Co.'s Fukushima Daiichi power plant, a number of disabled people used to gather at community workshops, designed to provide them with places and opportunities to work, to make skin toner made from luffa that they then sold. But orders dropped sharply after the nuclear disaster, due to public fears about possible radioactive contamination of the luffa.
Left with nothing much to do but to play games, they asked staff at the workshop in the central Fukushima city of Sukagawa for some gainful work. They said they "want to work, instead of playing games every day," according to the staff.
As a result, the Sukagawa workshop and nine other workshops in the city teamed up to create new jobs for the disabled. Instead of skin toner, people at the workshops started to make handmade buttons for clothes.
After showcasing the products at a trade show held in Osaka, the workshops received an order for 2,000 buttons from a local bag maker. Tomoyuki Ikeda, president of the bag maker Sunward Co., said he "felt something warm" when he saw the handmade buttons. "I could see that disabled people (in the disaster areas) are doing their best," he said.
In November 2013, Ikeda's company launched a new brand featuring the buttons, hoping to support reconstruction efforts in Fukushima. Under the new brand, dubbed "manga knapp" which means "a lot of buttons" in Swedish, Sunward sells bags and purses with buttons handmade at the workshops. Their prices range from 2,000 yen to just under 20,000 yen.
When the company exhibited the products at a major department store in Osaka, they racked up sales of some 500,000 yen within a week. Sunward is now planning to sell them online, according to company officials.
A similar initiative began in another Fukushima city, Koriyama, also prompted by voices of the disabled who wish to stay connected to society through work. Some dozen disabled people started to make bags using used A4-size envelopes at the "Futaba Seisakusho" workshop. Members of the workshop are evacuees from Futaba County, which is located close to the crippled nuclear power plant.
Used envelopes and wax for the water repellent finish were donated free by companies and the bags are decorated with the figure "28" to indicate the name of their hometown, Futaba, as the number two can be pronounced as "futa" in Japanese and the number eight, as "hachi," which is considered to have a phonetic similarity to "ba."
The bags are mainly sold online with a price tag of around 1,000 yen. Futaba Seisakusho has received orders not only from domestic customers but also from Australians who work for the welfare of the disabled. Some 1,000 bags have been sold so far.
The bags come with cards that explain how and why the products are made at Futaba Seisakusho. A customer in the southwestern Japan prefecture of Hiroshima wrote in a payment coupon space that she intends to let many people know about Futaba through the use of the bag, according to workshop staff.
At Futaba Seisakusho, a 50-year-old man from the town of Futaba said he enjoyed working with his fellow workers. "The work gives me a sense of fulfillment," he said.
Kiyoharu Shiraishi, 63, head of an organization that supports the disabled in the disaster-hit Fukushima, said working together can help them become more independent.
According to the Koriyama-based organization, a cumulative total of some 3,600 disabled people had been evacuated from the eight municipalities in Futaba County as of November 2012.
Many workshops in Fukushima are suffering from drops in revenues following the March 2011 disasters, officials of the organization said.
Looking to the future, Futaba Seisakusho is seeking professional advice on design and streamlining, workshop staff said.
]]></text></news-item>