<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-7201-JBKR-P30J"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Industry Perspective</title><source>The Vancouver Sun (British Columbia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[What is your industry doing to help drive the economy of northern British Columbia?
What are some of the barriers that your industry is currently facing?
Why is education important to the future of your industry?
Through the BCCA, the institutional, commerci-al, and industrial construction sector in B.C. leads the development of crucial human resources programs to address the skills shortage.We launched the Skilled Trades Employment Program (STEP) almost a decade ago, which placed more than 2500 skilled workers in-to construction jobs in 2013. Our Foreign Skilled Wor-kers BC program helps employers source highly skil-led journey people internationally when they haven't been able to fill the positions from home. On the pro-curement side, we've introduced Canada's only truly online bidding solution with BidCentral. Last year, BidCentral closed 1,345 projects with a combined va-lue of more than $1.3 billion.
Work can't get done if you don't have the pe-ople to do it. The shortage of skilled tradespe-ople is being felt across the province - but in the north,it's heightened by area-specific challenges. These include a lack of accommodation, hard-to-reach job sites inaccessible by public transporta-tion, and the need to relocate workers from oth-er areas. Employers must build relationships in remote areas with businesses and communities, and take the necessary steps to honour the Im-pact Benefit Agreements structured with First Nations. Most employers are small businesses without dedicated HR staff, which makes these challenges significant.
Education is important to the future of any industry. Construction is a highly competiti-ve, specialized, and fast-moving sector. Wit-hout education,without up-to-date training and mentorship, our skilled workers can't deliver. If our workers can't deliver, our owners can't com-pete,and then B.C.loses.
For decades, Canadians have dismissed the tra-des as a viable career choice. People need to re-learn what it means to be in the trades today, and the incredible career opportunities that the right skills will bring. We need to lose the negative bias and show more students that it may be the right path for them.
We have been the largest employer in the Kitimat-Terrace region for 60 years and our $3.3 billion smelter modernization project that is un-der way will secure the aluminium industry in northern B.C. for decades to come. In 2012 alone, the Kitimat Modernization Project committed almost $500 million of project expenditures to northern B.C. businesses - including mo-re than $200 million each to Kitimat-Terrace and the Prince George area. We employ 2,400 employees on the construction project and ha-ve more than 1,200 permanent employees wor-king at the existing smelter.
Finding skilled workers can be a challenge. We believe in investing in skills training and have worked with our Regional Economic Development department to establish training programs for lo-cal people to help build capacity and create long term sustainability.To date, more than 600 people from Terrace, Kitimat and Kitamaat Village have been trained in a variety of skills.
For Rio Tinto Alcan, it's all about building skills for local residents, building capacity for the coming economic boom and investing in sustainability. Education never goes away - those skills stay with people for the rest of their lives. Through our innovative training pro-grams local residents have participated in cour-ses including confined space entry, welding, construction safety officer training and cement finishing, just to name a few. That represents 75,000 hours of training invested since 2011. We're proud of that.
On top of the $400 million spent in exploration last year in northern B.C., Thompson Creek Metals' opening of Mt.Milligan in 2013 is a clear indicator of the success of exporation and development. Further-more, a number of new mines are under construction in the province that will act as a major boost to the in-dustry and to B.C.'s economy.The Northwest Trans-mission Line is currently under construction and is expected to be completed by May 2014.This nation-building infrastructure,borne out of the determined advocacy efforts of the Northwest Powerline Coali-tion, will bring much needed electricity to key mine development projects and reduce the region's reli-ance on diesel-generated power.
Certainly reduced mineral exploration ex-ploration expenditures worldwide are a challenge for our members both in northern B.C. and around the world. An increase in investor confidence is re-quired for mineral exploration expenditures to re-turn to their record 2012 levels.That said, northern B.C. had over $400 million in mineral exploration expenditures out of the $476 million across the pro-vince in 2013,the second highest number on record. So clearly,northern B.C.is attracting the vast majo-rity of all exploration in B.C. and perceived and real barriers, such as land use certainty and permitting challenges, are being slowly overcome.
Education is critical in order to align the goals of the province with the needs of the industry and students. Over the next ten years, the mineral explo -ration sector in northern B.C. is expected to requi-re 2,920 positions as workers retire.The good news is that university programs in geology and engine-ering and college programs in northern B.C. in the field of mineral exploration and mining technology will help meet this demand. AME BC, together with its partners in the Mining HR Task Force: Explora-tion,Mining, and Stone,Sand and Gravel are working with educational institutions and industry to help identify knowledge and training gaps, and promote mineral exploration and mining as careers.
]]></text></news-item>