<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-5T51-DYRV-32H6"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>BBC Monitoring Pakistan morning media roundup 17 Mar 14</title><source>BBC Monitoring South Asia - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The following is a selection of top stories and comments in the Pakistani media on 17 March as seen by BBCM till 0500 gmt.
The Pakistani media are leading with the Taleban's request to release prisoners and the government's rejection of their demand. The nurses' protest in Punjab and Malaysia asking for Pakistan's help in the search for missing Malaysia Airlines flight are the other top stories.
Taleban prisoners
Pakistani government yesterday rejected Tehrik-i-Taleban Pakistan [TTP]'s demand to release women, children and elderly prisoners. TTP had handed over a list of more than 60 non-combatant prisoners to the government through its committee for peace talks. But Defence Minister Khawaja Asif rejected TTP's request saying there were no women and children in the custody of forces and his government was ready to probe if TTP provided evidence.
English language newspaper Daily Times in its editorial says "However, the fact is that the security establishment is reportedly holding some 735 Taliban prisoners in about a dozen internment centres."
The paper continues to say "The kidnapping for ransom 'industry' has targeted many in Pakistan over many years, with some victims still awaiting release and freedom..... It would be a great service if the agony of their families were put to an end by linking the release of non-combatant Taliban prisoners considered safe to be freed with the release of all non-combatant Pakistanis in the custody of the militants."
Rawalpindi-based conservative nationalist Urdu daily: "... Now Al-Qa'idah and Jundallah too have announced ceasefire. It is hoped that that talks would now succeed. Army chief General Raheel Sharif rightly said during his visit to Gujranwala Garrison that army was fully prepared to combat every challenge including terrorism. Therefore, the issue should be resolved through talks first. If the talks bear no result, the option of operation should be used."
Nurses' protest
The ad-hoc nurses today continued their protest in front of the Punjab Assembly to press the Punjab government and Health Department to regularise their services. While the police on Friday used batons to disperse protesting nurses which called wide criticism from human rights groups.
English language daily Dawn: "... Pakistan still has a long way to go on the road to democracy. The violence unleashed against the nurses by the police in Lahore on Friday was evidence yet again that there is scant respect for the rights that are part and parcel of a democratic system."
Malaysian plane
Malaysia yesterday asked Pakistan to provide with information that may help the search team in finding Malaysia Airlines flight MH370. It has urged nearly a dozen countries for help, making the number of participants in search effort 14 to 25. Earlier, Pakistan aviation official Shujaat Azeem dismissed reports about the missing plane being in Pakistani territory.
The News in its editorial says: "... the search for the plane has been shifted from the South China Sea to two considerably larger zones in the southern Indian Ocean. No one is sure how long it will take for the plane to be found or if we will ever know the cause of its likely crash but one has to wonder if the Malaysians are guilty of gross negligence since they did absolutely nothing despite MH370 continuing to fly for hours after losing contact. As more pieces of information are pieced together it may emerge that this was an entirely avoidable tragedy."
Social media
Pakistani net users are discussing the ongoing T-20 cricket World Cup with cricket related hashtags trending on Twitter.
Source: as listed in Urdu 17 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>