<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-WPV1-DXKS-J257"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Award-winning investigative reporter joins the Scripps Washington bureau; Sydney Freedberg has won four Pulitzers; joins bureau's expanded investigative reporting team</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ Four-time Pulitzer Prize-winning reporter Sydney Freedberg has joined the Washington bureau of The E.W. Scripps Company (NYSE: SSP) as an investigative reporter.
Freedberg joins the bureau from Bloomberg, where she worked on the projects and investigative team. She also has worked for the St. Petersburg Times, the Miami Herald, The Wall Street Journal and the Detroit News.
Her work includes investigations that exposed crime on Wall Street, health care fraud, corruption of public officials, and rigged elections. She is known for her ability to take on tough subjects and write stories of significant impact. At the Herald, she worked on teams that won three Pulitzer Prizes, and she co-authored a series that earned a Pulitzer for public service at the Detroit News.
"Sydney has a strong track record of exposing injustices that otherwise may have remained hidden from public view," says Ellen Weiss, vice president and Washington bureau chief for Scripps. "She is one of the nation's top investigative journalists and a fantastic addition to our national investigative team."
Freedberg is among a number of high-profile journalists hired by Weiss at the bureau since she joined Scripps last year, including:
Dick Meyer, former executive producer of America for the BBC News, as chief Washington correspondent Phil Pruitt, longtime journalist and former Yahoo News politics editor, as director of digital content Marcia Myers, former Bloomberg News reporter, as the senior investigations editor
Freedberg began her journalism career as associate managing editor of the Harvard Crimson while receiving a bachelor's of history and literature at Harvard. She graduated from Harvard cum laude. She also served as a John S. Knight Fellow at Stanford University. She is author of the 1994 book, "Brother Love: Murder, Money and a Messiah," based on her investigation of a self-proclaimed preacher who used his position to control his congregation and even convinced them to commit murder for him.
About Scripps  The E.W. Scripps Company (http://www.scripps.com) serves audiences and businesses through a growing portfolio of television, print and digital media brands. After approval of its acquisition of two Granite Broadcasting stations later this year, Scripps will own 21 local television stations as well as daily newspapers in 13 markets across the United States. It also runs an expanding collection of local and national digital journalism and information businesses including online multi-source video news providerNewsy. Scripps also produces television programming, runs an award-winning investigative reporting newsroom in Washington, D.C., and serves as the longtime steward of one of the nation's largest, most successful and longest-running educational programs, Scripps National Spelling Bee. Founded in 1879, Scripps is focused on the stories of tomorrow.
SOURCE The E.W. Scripps Company
]]></text></news-item>