<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-8341-JBKF-V375"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>NYC: IN BRIEF</title><source>Newsday (New York)</source><author>amNewYork</author><text><![CDATA[Five hurt in Brooklyn apartment blaze
Four children and an adult were injured in a fire in a fifth-floor Brooklyn apartment early yesterday morning, the FDNY said.
Two children, one of them an infant, were critically injured, while another was seriously injured, though all were expected to survive. A fourth child and an adult sustained minor injuries.
The blaze in the Boerum Hill neighborhood started about 2:15 a.m. at 130 Third Ave. About 60 firefighters placed the fire under control about 2:37 a.m., the FDNY said.
One critically injured victim was taken to NewYork-Presbyterian/Weill Cornell Medical Center in Manhattan and the rest were taken to New York Methodist Hospital in Brooklyn.
All of the injured are in stable condition.
- amNewYork
Body found in waters off lower Battery Park
The NYPD Harbor Unit yesterday removed a body found off the tip of lower Manhattan, police said.
The body was that of a woman approximately in her 30s and was found floating against rocks opposite 18 Battery Place about 2:45 p.m.
An NYPD spokesman said the body had no signs of trauma and was removed to Pier A near Battery Park. The medical examiner will examine at the body today, according to the spokesman.
- amNewYork
Homeless character found shot to death
Police are investigating the early Saturday morning shooting death of a 65-year-old homeless man who was a welcomed presence in his Brooklyn neighborhood.
The real estate website Brownstoner reported "with a heavy heart" the death of Gilbert Kelly, the "self-appointed steward of the block."
Kelly was found unconscious with a bullet wound to the chest about 4:20 a.m. in front of 424 Grand Ave. in the Clinton Hill neighborhood, according to the NYPD. Medical workers took him to Brooklyn Hospital, where he was pronounced dead.
- amNewYork
2 MTA workers fined
for ethics violations
Two employees of the Metropolitan Transportation Authority have been fined by the state ethics commission in Albany.
Under a commission settlement, Antonio Cabrera, a 20-year employee now an assistant chief officer in the engineering division, was fined $2,000 for giving information about a potential competitor in 2011 to a company responding to an MTA request for bids for manufacturing and installation of solid cast polymer compound for railroad ties.
In a separate settlement, Mohammad Baalbaki, a former assistant chief officer of infrastructure engineering, was fined $1,500 for using MTA computers, scanners, copiers and software for his personal engineering business between 2008 and 2013.
Fire damages loading dock at luxury condo
A midtown Manhattan fire damaged the loading dock of a luxury condo tower where a crane collapsed during superstorm Sandy in 2012.
The FDNY said the fire at the 75-story building was reported just before 9 p.m. Saturday.
It was under control a little more than an hour later and no injuries were reported.
Witnesses said scaffolding at the building and another building also caught fire.
The West 57th Street tower is scheduled to open later this year.
A crane atop the building collapsed during Sandy and dangled precariously.
Residents on either side of the building were evacuated for several days.
The building, called One57, will be the tallest residential building in the city when it opens.
Some full-floor apartments have reportedly sold for more than $90 million.
Compiled with wire service reports
]]></text></news-item>