<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S200"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>DOE Panel Seeks Strict New System For Verifying Frackers' CBI Claims</title><source>Clean Energy Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Administration advisers are urging state and federal regulators to develop uniform verification and compliance mechanisms for confidential business information (CBI) claims from hydraulic fracturing operators, a move aimed at strengthening the chemical disclosure system for fracking operations and pending rules from EPA and others to codify it.
In a Feb. 24 draft report, the Secretary of Energy Advisory Board's (SEAB) task force reviewing FracFocus, the voluntary state disclosure database on chemicals used in the fracking process, recommended that regulators use the State Review of Oil and Gas Regulations (STRONGER) -- a federal and state board created by EPA to evaluate the adequacy of state energy production oversight -- to craft and facilitate adoptions of "stringent criteria" for CBI exemptions and a process for determining compliance with that criteria, including a mechanism for third parties to challenge CBI assertions.
The panel noted that while CBI law is generally standardized across the country, "there is no accepted standard for asserting a trade secret exemption in the hydraulic fracturing context and no standardized compliance procedure to verify the claim for protection."
As a result, state and federal regulators should "adopt standards for making a trade secret claim and establish an accompanying compliance process and a challenge mechanism," the panel said in the draft report.
The report is just the latest from the group urging state and federal officials to strengthen the system for disclosing data about chemicals used in the fracking process.
In 2011, an earlier SEAB panel called for a broader series of measures for improving the safety and environmental performance of fracking, including broad efforts to increase disclosure of all releases and strict limits on CBI claims.
The current SEAB group was created in response to concerns from former Senate energy committee Chairman Ron Wyden (D-OR) and environmentalists who were alarmed that the Obama administration and many states were planning to allow operators to report their chemicals to FracFocus in lieu of disclosure to regulators, potentially eliminating data regulators may need as well as any enforcement mechanism.
The database, launched in April 2011, is a key source of data that EPA is using in its massive study on the impact of the drilling practice on water quality, slated for submission to Congress in 2016.
Since its launch, nearly a dozen states have passed laws or adopted rules that either require drillers to disclose their chemical usage to the database or allow disclosure to FracFocus in lieu of or in addition to disclosure to the state. States that mandate disclosure to FracFocus include Texas, Utah and North Dakota while states that allow disclosure to the database include Colorado, Louisiana and Montana.
The administration is also considering allowing disclosure to FracFocus in a pending proposed rule being developed by the Bureau of Land Management (BLM) for drilling operations on federal lands, though the draft SEAB report says the proposed BLM rules "do not yet meet the high disclosure standards that the 2011 Subcommittee recommended that BLM adopt." The draft report further states that any CBI exemptions BLM allows in the rules should include a "rigorous process" for making claims, verifying claims and allowing for third party challenges.
In addition to BLM's pending rule, EPA is weighing several potential measures to establish federal oversight of disclosure of fracking chemicals, including Toxic Substances Control Act (TSCA) reporting rules and a petition from environmentalists to add the oil and gas sector to those required to report releases under the Toxics Release Inventory.
Competing Concerns
While regulators have been seeking broader disclosure of chemicals, many efforts have been stymied due to policymakers' difficulties balancing competing industry concerns over disclosure of CBI and environmentalists fears over inadequate disclosures.
In Texas, for example, some companies balked at a disclosure bill touted by environmentalists because it required companies to report what they were using on a well-by-well basis. Industry opposition eventually resulted in lawmakers scaling back the disclosure requirements, prompting environmental groups to drop or weaken their support for the bill.
But Colorado officials in 2011 struck a rare deal with environmentalists and industry when they crafted a rule that required broader disclosure than many others states while also enhancing CBI protections for industry and broader opportunities for activists to challenge those protections than other states have.
The key to winning broad support for the Colorado rule, which took effect in 2012, was a provision allowing industry reporters to file separate disclosure forms for "additives" and "chemicals" used in those products. "The rule permits operators to report the required information in a format that does not link chemical ingredients to their respective hydraulic fracturing additives," the Colorado regulation states.
Now the SEAB is calling on federal and state officials to take a series of steps to strengthen the chemical disclosure and related CBI system.
To help inform the criteria that it wants STRONGER to develop, the draft report is urging DOE to conduct a four- to six-month study on a range of issues related to CBI claims within the oil and gas industry, including trends, the percentage of wells with one or more fracking chemicals claimed as trade secrets, average number of claims per well and the percentage by mass of CBI chemicals used in each wells, the degree to which CBI practices vary by company and the overall state and national percentages of chemicals claimed as CBI.
"We recommend that states use the [STRONGER] mechanism to craft and adopt stringent criteria for trade secret exemption to disclosure and a process for validating compliance. STRONGER should begin by reviewing the practices in different states to determine the effectiveness of different approaches and, when available, draw on the results of the DOE [study] and the independent audit we recommend above of the FracFocus disclosure system, in particular the data collected on trade secret claims," the draft report says.
EPA and BLM should aid in coordinating the study, given that both agencies have interest in CBI issues related to the oil and gas industry, the draft report adds.
Along with the recommendations for establishing the CBI criteria, the draft report is recommending a series of measures for improving and expanding FracFocus, including expanding it to include disclosure of water quality data for water used as the base in fracking mixtures, noting that it can be fresh water taken from wells, rivers or lakes, but it is also increasingly being recycled from previously fracked wells.
"In either case, the chemicals that are part of the make-up water are not always measured and usually not reported" to FracFocus, the draft report says, adding that such disclosures would be appropriate.
It also called on FracFocus to list chemicals claimed as CBI separately from the related additives -- much as Colorado did -- to allow for greater disclosure while still preventing reverse engineering and enhancing the searchability and data retention components of the database.
Additionally, the draft report is recommending that funding levels for FracFocus could be boosted from current funding levels of around $700,000 per year, mostly through DOE grants and occasional state and industry contributions, by introducing a stable, DOE-established multi-year budget and possible user fees for well operators.
"For every 10,000 wells registered each year, a $50 registration fee per well would produce a revenue stream of $0.5 million for FracFocus. A combination of DOE support and use fee will comfortably provide for FracFocus."
The task force is expected to present the draft findings at the SEAB's March 27-28 meeting in Washington, D.C. --Bridget DiCosmo (bdicosmo@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>