<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S1XT"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>EPA Plan To Subject EOR To CCS Permits May Thwart NSPS, Critics Warn</title><source>Carbon Control News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EPA's draft guide for transitioning some enhanced oil recovery (EOR) wells to strict underground injection control (UIC) permits for carbon capture and sequestration (CCS) projects is drawing strong criticisms from industry groups who say it could prompt well operators to refuse carbon dioxide (CO2) from utilities to escape the new regulatory burdens, undermining the agency's pending power plant rule requiring CCS.
EOR operators have "made it clear" they will not purchase CO2 from utilities if it requires them to transition from a "Class II" well to a "Class VI" well, the industry groups say in Feb. 28 comments, and as such the guidance could "have the effect of eliminating CCS as a viable compliance option" for utilities trying to comply with EPA's new source performance standards (NSPS) requiring coal power plants to install partial CCS.
"[B]ecause the EOR industry is not required to purchase the utility industry's CO2, EPA must preserve CO2-EOR as a regulatory pathway or risk delay in the broader implementation of CCS . . . if not its elimination of a climate policy solution," Edison Electric Institute (EEI) writes along with American Coalition for Clean Coal Electricity and the National Mining Association.
The industry groups say they do not believe EPA should require CCS in its utility NSPS, but nonetheless are offering comments so that the agency goes ahead with the rule that it can create a regulatory framework that ensure the ability of EORs to "enter into long-term CO2 offtake contracts" with utilities regulated under the NSPS.
The industry comments on the draft guide adds to the utility sector's warnings that there are too many questions and uncertainties involved with the utility-scale sequestration of CO2 to make it an enforceable requirement under the Clean Air Act. Utility groups have instead urged EPA to wait eight years until is next update of the NSPS, at which time the first generation of coal utility CCS projects will have accumulated years of operational experience.
The draft guide, released in December, outlines how UIC wells should transition from existing Class II wells -- which govern a range of oil and gas sector activities -- to novel Class VI wells intended for CCS projects as they sequester increasing amounts of CO2.
EPA's Class VI program, established in 2010, builds on existing Class II requirements but with more rigorous site survey requirements, a more comprehensive monitoring program and additional financial responsibilities.
EPA in the draft guidance says that EOR operators should transfer from Class II to Class VI permits if they switch from primarily extracting oil to primarily trying to maximize carbon injection volumes for permanent storage -- though the agency does not set a trigger for when such transition should occur.
Legal Certainty
EPA issued the draft alongside its final Resource Conservation & Recovery Act (RCRA) rule for excluding CCS projects from strict hazardous waste rules, a move intended to provide legal certainty for well operators who fear potential RCRA liability from sequestering CO2 underground.
EPA in its NSPS, proposed last September, relies in large part on the demand for CO2 from the oil sector and its long history of successful operations to show that requiring CCS is a viable option, as the alternative option of storing captured utility CO2 into deep underground saline aquifers has not been widely tested and would not benefit from the existing infrastructure and experience built up around the injection of CO2 for EOR.
But officials in the EOR sector say the draft guidance on the transition from Class II to Class VI wells alarmed them, as the guidance creates a host of questions and uncertainties about their EOR operations that they urgently want to avoid -- such as taking on additional financial responsibilities that they fear may last indefinitely, given the long-term nature of the geologic sequestration of CO2.
Many EOR operators thought they would be "just left alone" by EPA and not fall under the Class VI program when the agency proposed and finalized the rule, says an industry source. However, the source says EPA's draft guidance suggests the oil sector might need to look at its operations and see if they had met a threshold for Class VI compliance.
To avoid Class VI permitting, the source says the oil sector might simply say "we don't want to take the CO2." And the oil sector might be particularly wary of taking CO2 from coal-fired power plants complying with EPA's utility NSPS because those regulations, as proposed, also carry additional "Subpart RR" reporting requirements that would require them to create a monitoring, reporting and verification plan that could be subject to litigation.
EEI and the coal sector groups say that although the draft transition guidance was intended to provide regulatory certainty to EOR operators, it unfortunately "does just the opposite by casting doubts" on the trigger for when Class II wells transition to Class VI wells, and the regulator responsible for making that determination.
Kipp Coddington, general counsel for the North American Carbon Capture and Storage Association, told a Feb. 27 conference of the Global CCS Institute that EPA's recent EOR regulations "runs the risk of crimping the EOR opportunity," given the regulatory uncertainty it has created.
To encourage sequestration, Coddington suggested EPA should establish some type of liability transfer, in which after CO2 is injected and operations are stabilized, "you walk away and you're done."
Draft Guidance
North Dakota regulators, meanwhile, are criticizing the draft guidance, and are using their comments to also urge EPA to reconsider part of the 2010 final rule that established the Class VI program, as they say changes the agency made to the final rule were not a "logical outgrowth" of the proposal.
North Dakota is one of a limited number of states that have been trying to win Class VI permitting authority from EPA, which has responsibility for the program until it delegates the authority to states that request it and show they have the capability to manage the program.
The state's North Dakota Industrial Commission, in comments filed Feb. 18, says the agency should reconsider the final rule based on its "unlawful adoption" of a nine-step test describing when operators of wells need to transition from a Class II to a Class VI wells that the commission says was not mentioned as a possibility in the proposed rule.
The commission says the test was added to the final rule without a chance for public comment, representing a "change in philosophy from the proposed rule to the final rule," given that the proposed rule said that the injection of CO2 for EOR would continue to be permitted under the Class II program, and that there would be no transition to Class VI so long as "any oil or gas production is occurring."
In contrast, the final rule creates a transition point where Class VI would be required even if oil production was occurring, the commission says. It says this is unlawful, citing a recent U.S. Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit decision involving air compliance waivers for trucking manufacturers that said EPA a final rule would only be a logical outgrowth of a proposal if "interest parties should have anticipated that the change was possible."
On the draft transition guidance, The North Dakota Industrial Commission says the guidance "appears to be an attempt to expand the the authority" of EPA because it could potentially require Class II operators to report "any and all data that may be required by the Class VI UIC program Director," which would currently be leadership officials at EPA. The commission adds that EPA "appears to obscure the lines" between the Class II and Class VI programs. -- Chris Knight (cknight@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>