<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-1J21-JCXB-22DY"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Grupo Clarin S.A. Annual Financial Report -7-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[In order to continue to provide services and add value to its readers, Diario Clarín constantly keeps up to date and offers a wide range of editorial products together with the core product, addressing the need to satisfy an increasing segmentation among the diverse demographic groups. The following are among the most prominent collectible products for the period: El cuerpo humano en Acción, Todo Clemente, DC Súper Amigos, Los secretos del Gran Asador 2013, Grandes Ideas Grandes Negocios, Los mejores cuentos de siempre, Cuentos con Moraleja, El Gran Libro del Tejido 2013, El Gran Libro de las Tortas, Tartas y Budines, Angry Birds, Un Padre Nuestro, Ver y aprender, Historia del Siglo XX Time, Los autos que enamoran a los Argentinos, El Gran Libro de Clarín del Crochet 2013, Historia Ilustrada de la Biblia, El gran libro del sushi y la cocina oriental, La Historia de los Papas, Biblioteca de Intriga y suspenso, El Mundo de los Dinosaurios y Otros Animales Prehistóricos, Libros del viajero National Geographic, Crecer con Mozart, Monster High.
Internet Clarin.com is a news and opinion portal with updates in real time and free access on a 365/24/7 basis, which has been online since 1996. In addition to the full version of the printed newspaper and its archive, Clarin.com features ongoing updates of news produced and published by its own journalists, high-definition audiovisual content production, Android and iOS applications, and a growing footprint in social networks, such as, Facebook and Twitter. During 2013, Clarin.com embarked in an inclusion initiative and launched a system that can be accessed by people with disabilities. Clarín.com continues to be the news site with the highest market share in the Argentine digital market, with 16 million unique visitors and around 200 million page views per month. With its sites "Deautos", "Argenprop" and "Empleos Clarín"; the company maintains its strong presence in the on-line classified ads for cars, real estate and jobs. The most outstanding sites in the AGEA network are Vía Restó, Clarín's online restaurant guide; Biencasero.com, a site with practical solutions to enjoy the cooking experience; Entremujeres.com, which continued to grow in terms of unique visitors and consolidated itself as one of the most visited sites, with over 4 million unique visitors; and Espectáculos.com, a site that keeps readers updated with the best information on movies, theater plays, TV shows, music and celebrities from Argentina and the rest of the world. El Gran DT is another alternative among online products. Argentina's most popular game managed to engage more than 4 million participants since its launch at the Apertura Tournament. The latest online editions of Gran DT engaged more than 1.8 million participants who had the chance to build their fantasy teams and win outstanding prizes. Magazines AGEA also continued to build upon the achievements attained by the cultural magazine Ñ, reaching average sales of 32,000 copies per issue. The 500th issue of magazine Ñ was published during the year. Several initiatives were carried out, aimed at engaging readers through the launching of collectible products and special editions, and the creation and sponsorship of forums comprising different cultural issues and involvement in and sponsorship of major cultural events, such as the Feria del Libro de Buenos Aires (Buenos Aires' Book Fair). Revista ELLE is a high-end magazine for women mostly focused on fashion, beauty and news. In 2013, its circulation exceeded a monthly average of 30,000 copies. Revista Pymes continued to consolidate its position with a special offering that reflects the voice of entrepreneurs and the keys to their strategies. In 2013, the Company continued to publish the magazines Genios and Jardín de Genios. With children and school in mind, these magazines were created with the aim of integrating content for children, parents, school and society, combining education with entertainment. In 2013, the monthly issue of Genios magazine, along with its classical collectible product "Gran Enciclopedia Escolar Ilustrada", an encyclopedia with full-color illustrations covering school topics, exceeded the previous year's circulation with over 61,000 copies sold; while the monthly issue of Jardín de Genios retained its leading position in the children's magazine segment, with over 78,000 copies sold. During 2013, "Tiki Tiki", a magazine aimed at children aged 7 through 14, continued to strengthen its position. Also in 2013 the company continued to publish the monthly magazine-catalogue, Shop & Co, which includes discount coupons on important brands. Other Newspapers La Razón, which joined Grupo Clarín in late 2000, is the first-ever free distribution newspaper. It is mainly distributed in the public transportation network of the City of Buenos Aires, including trains, subways and highways. La Razón is also distributed at certain bars and among a group of opinion leaders through an exclusive mailing program. Diario Olé is the first and only sports newspaper in Argentina. Since 1996 and with an average annual historical circulation of 40,000 copies per day, Olé continues to lead the sports editorial market, and is one of the highest circulation newspapers in the city of Buenos Aires, including general interest newspapers. Among its editorial offering, it has the broadest and most comprehensive soccer and multi-sport coverage. Since its inception, it has drastically changed reading habits and managed to engage a new generation of young readers, avid for information and critical opinions. The editorial profile is fresh and complicit, with an agile and informal style focused on photography, illustrations and infographics as communication tools, with a good design and modern and effective production technology. In 2011, Clarín launched MUY, a dynamic, visually designed and entertaining newspaper, which features news in addition to regional pages and sports and show business sections. With a "TV-format" design, the newspaper summarizes the most resounding police cases and breaking news on soccer clubs and celebrities. During 2013, the newspaper MUY has continued to offer promotions, optional books and free collectibles. Tinta Fresca Founded in 2004, Tinta Fresca is an Argentine publishing company focused on textbook publishing for all stages of the Argentine education system. Tinta Fresca seeks to place books at the heart of the teaching and learning processes and have teachers and students use them as an effective and updated learning tool. The company has been growing in many aspects over these years. In the editorial area, the company has learned from experience, and has managed to expand its exclusive and original focus on textbooks to a considerably diverse editorial offering. With more than 300 titles, in addition to several textbook series for all school stages, including elementary and secondary education, its editorial offering is currently comprised by a variety of activity books for all levels. Said offering has been enriched with sourcebooks and an interesting catalogue of children and youth literature. In 2013, it strengthened its editorial offering through the launch of the series "Dame la Palabra 1, 2 y 3"; "Abracadabra 1, 2 y 3"; "Aprendo Matemática 1, 2 y 3" and "Descubro las ciencias 3" for the elementary school. For high-school, Tinta Fresca published "Práctica del lenguaje 1, 2 y 3" and launched a series of 10 mathematics booklets that develop the education program per topic. It continued to produce "El Plan Lector", a set of book series that provides teachers a plan to implement reading in the classroom, and launched the series "Efemérides" and "Enseñar matemática". For 2014, Tinta Fresca produced "Aprendo Matemática 4, 5 y 6" and "Dame la Palabra 4, 5 y 6", thus completing the series launched during the year. It developed the areas of natural and social sciences by publishing the books "Econaturaleza" and "Socialmente". As a result of the production of collectible materials, newsstands have again been intensively used as sales channel. During 2013, Tinta Fresca continued to sell dictionaries and literature in supermarkets, an action that substantially contributes to product and content access. The company also made headway in the Digital Development project that focuses on the several ways in which ICT will be introduced in the education system. The Company has made available at Clarín.com a digital and free version of "Diccionario integral del español de la Argentina" since 2011. In 2013, and in spite of the good selection of Tinta Fresca's products, the company was not awarded any contract for the procurement of material by the National Government, while it did receive contracts from the city of Salta and the city of Buenos Aires. Also during the period, the company continued to explore foreign markets, such as Paraguay, Chile and Uruguay. In 2013, the Mexican-based operation, Rios de Tinta, renewed the content addressed to third-year students of high-school as a consequence of a change in the education program, and reinforced local promotions. Artes Gráficas Rioplantense AGR meets certain special printing needs of Clarín and Olé (magazines, optional and collectible products, among others), and also publishes large volumes of graphic material for third parties. It is the leading printing services company in Argentina. In 2013, AGR retained its leading position in the sector with net sales of Ps. 233.8 million.
]]></text></news-item>