<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-R6B1-DYJJ-P096"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Alcohol policies prove costly</title><source>The Post-Crescent (Appleton, Wisconsin)</source><author>By, Nick Penzenstadler</author><text><![CDATA[APPLETON - A $3 bottle of Bud Light served to an undercover Appleton police operative cost the owners of TJ's Japanese Steakhouse their $2.2 million business. Now, an alderman is questioning whether the city's alcohol revocation policy is too harsh.
The 2012 sale to a 20-year-old community service officer went on to haunt both the bartender and restaurant owner after the minor slipped out of the bar to notify a police officer stationed nearby that their alcohol sting had nabbed a violator.
The $389 citation for serving an underage person that was issued to the bartender put TJ's over the limit for Appleton's alcohol demerit system.
And it touched off a 16-month process that concluded in early March when the owners surrendered the valuable liquor license under threat of a city revocation, and sold the business.
Appleton Alderman Jeff Jirschele wants to review the city's alcohol revocation policy and consider the economic impact of the harsh penalties on businesses.
"My concern is we virtually have an execution order and can serve a financial death sentence to a business owner if they lose their license," Jirschele said. "Owners have invested millions. I'm not for saving egregious violators, but I'm wondering if we can deal with the problem in a way that's not such a life-and-death issue."
A citation for underage serving carries 80 demerit points. If 200 points are accumulated, the license can be revoked.
Jirschele authored a resolution that offers alternatives to the revocation rules in Appleton's ordinance. He has particular concerns about blight and vacant storefronts that can result from revocations.
Jirschele's referring to the three-bar string in the 500 block of West College Avenue that formerly hosted Senor Tequila's, Casablanca and Venue. The city revoked all three liquor licenses in August 2012 after a series of alcohol-related violations.
"We're fostering situations like Senor Tequila's with three blighted storefronts across the street from the best economic engine in the downtown with the PAC," Jirschele said. "There has to be another way to look at this that's compatible with our economic development goals."
For years, critics of the city's system also have questioned a policy that prohibits anyone from holding a liquor license at a physical address that has been revoked for six months.
Fox Valley developer Bob Gregorski sent letters to City Hall during the deliberations into TJ's case last month, and called for a recalibration of the city's liquor policies. He says the city is stricter than the state statute calls for, and more severe than surrounding communities.
"With a bad bartender, on two or three occasions they can get a fine, but the owner stands to lose millions in investments - and it's only in Appleton where this happens," Gregorski said. "If a bar gets in trouble, instead of a monetary penalty or suspension the city basically kicks that business out forever and forces a transfer."
Gregorski also criticized the council's hearing process to revoke a license, which he said follows the court process as a "rubber stamp."
Revocations are rare
Despite the two revocation hearings since 2012 in Appleton, the punitive action is rare, said Stacy Doucette, the assistant attorney who handles the process.
"We have so few of these, I don't see a problem," Doucette said. "It's easier for a license holder to argue in court they didn't violate the law than convince the committee that their conviction shouldn't carry any weight."
In 2013, police wrote 17 tickets to bartenders and convenience store workers for serving alcohol to minors and issued eight warnings. That number of citations was 36 in 2012 and 23 in 2011.
Underage drinking citations to minors are much more common, but don't always happen in bars.
Police records show that officers wrote 336 underage tickets in 2013, 385 in 2012 and 577 in 2011.
Alderwoman Kathy Plank, a longtime member of the city's licensing panel, said the current system is effective.
"It's applied equitably and gives ample opportunity to bar owners to make corrections before we take a punitive action," Plank said. "In the case of Senor Tequila's there were multiple chances for leeway."
Neither Oshkosh nor Green Bay utilize a demerit point system for bars. Jim Mueller, assistant city attorney in Green Bay, said the point system was costly and unpopular.
"It's a good idea in theory, but in reality it meant we had increased litigation because license-holders took citations to trial and dragged them on as long as possible," Mueller said. "We review licenses if we see a pattern of negative conduct like serving underage, overserving or violent crimes."
Oshkosh Police Chief Scott Greuel said liquor licenses are reviewed after three incidents within a year or failure to comply with enforcement plans.
Compliance
checks have rules
Controlled alcohol transactions, better known as "stings," take place at each of Appleton's licensed establishments at least twice per year.
The procedure, which is coordinated by Lt. Jay Steinke, uses community service officers who are 18 to 20 years old.
"They have a script of asking for a drink," Steinke said in an email to Post-Crescent Media. "They have only cash. They have no ID on them. If asked questions, they are not to lie, including the question of their age."
Department policy says the undercover workers can't appear older than their age and aren't selected to deceive bartenders.
Alderwoman Patti Coenen, who owns Fox River House, 211 S. Walnut St., said she has a zero-tolerance policy for bartenders caught in a sting.
"If you get a ticket, you're fired. ... It's too important to our license to have violations," Coenen said. "It's not rocket science when they do inspections. Especially when a young girl comes in by herself you can spot the CAT sting."
At nearby McGuinness Irish Pub, 201 S. Walnut St., one of the bartenders was caught serving a person working undercover last year.
Owner John McGuinness was issued a warning and said the bartender, who was ticketed, is still employed.
"We're on our toes all the times and it just happened, I can't tell you why," McGuinness said. "I certainly wasn't too pleased when I found out."
McGuinness said the prospect of losing a license due to underage serving is daunting, and said he was in favor of a new state law that allows bars to take underage drinkers to court and get fined $1,000 - payable to the business owner.
- Nick Penzenstadler: 920-996-7226, or npenzenstadler
@postcrescent.com;
on Twitter @npenzenstadler
Citations for underage alcohol serving in 2013
Jennifer D. Helf, Citgo, 1601 N. Richmond St., May 11.
Hem L. Devkota, Marathon, 415 S. Memorial Drive, May 11.
Mark R. Lemke, Citgo, 1717 W College Ave., May 11.
Marissa L. Gustavus, Kwik Trip, 3232 S. Oneida St., May 25.
Wayne R. Lauterbach, Red Ox, 2318 Oneida St., June 1.
Nicholas J. Wilson, Happy Joe's, 3401 E. Evergreen Drive, June 1.
Nickolas F. Monthei, Beefeaters, 2331 E. Evergreen Drive, June 1.
Peter M. Brennan, McGuinness Irish Pub, 201 S. Walnut St., June 15.
Danielle Emmer, Bad Badger, 215 W. College Ave., June 15.
Angela Rose Kosino, VFW, 501 N. Richmond St., June 19.
Sharon Reader, Emmett's, 139 N. Richmond St., Nov. 30.
Benjamin J. Fredrick, Marathon Gas Station, 1201 N. Badger Ave., Nov. 30.
Brittany Ann Shearier, Good Company, 110 N. Richmond St., Nov. 30.
Melissa S. Greiner, Jack's Apple Pub, 535 W. College Ave., Nov. 30.
Eric D. Johns, McG's, 205 W. College Ave., Dec. 11.
Ashley Heun, University Lounge, 17 S. Appleton St., Dec. 11.
Allen S. Mehring, (establishment not released), Dec. 21.
Source: Appleton Police Department
]]></text></news-item>