<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-7901-JC6P-C4MY"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Hinsdale voters deny road project, take issue with salary proposal for town clerk</title><source>The Keene Sentinel, N.H.</source><author>Meghan Foley, The Keene Sentinel, N.H.</author><text><![CDATA[March 16--HINSDALE -- Monument Road won't be rebuilt this year, the school district now has a school resource officer, and Town Clerk Tammy-Jean Akeley will be paid a salary with an amount to be determined by the selectmen Monday.
And those votes were just part of the roughly five-and-a-half hour town meeting held in the Hinsdale Middle/High School gymnasium Saturday.
In a vote of 122-61, Hinsdale residents opted against a roughly $1.4 million project to upgrade and improve Monument Road from Plain Road to Meetinghouse Road.
While voters for the most part agreed the road, which runs through industrial and residential areas, is a mess, they disagreed with the scope of the proposed project.
The scope included widening the road from 24 to 30 feet, adding bike and walking paths, raising and regrading it in some areas, improving drainage and rehabilitating the surface and subsurface of the road.
Monument Road resident Karyn M. Hammond said she is fine with the road being repaved, but is concerned about the widening of each side by about three feet, especially since she has a small front yard.
Resident Richard A. Schill asked voters if they had the money to pay for the project, given how the economy has been.
Voters answered with a resounding "no."
Selectman Jerome Ebbighausen Jr. defended the project, which was proposed as one to two phases to rebuild the entire 2.5- to 3-mile stretch of Monument Road from Old Brattleboro Road to Plain Road.
"The questions is if not now, then when?" he asked.
Bonds rates are low, the town has some debt coming off its books over the next couple of years, and construction costs are low, he said.
Despite that, voters didn't support the proposed project.
The warrant article that drew the most attention from the roughly 200 people at town meeting involved paying Town Clerk Tammy-Jean Akeley on salary, instead of her collecting a base pay and statutory fees.
The article stemmed from a debacle that started in August 2013 when selectmen announced the findings of an internal investigation into the running of Akeley's office.
According to the investigation, Akeley had been collecting both her salary and a $2.50 fee paid by residents who paid the state portion of their motor vehicle registrations through the town, Selectmen Chairman Michael J. Darcy said at the time. Akeley isn't allowed to collect both under state law, he said.
Akeley defended her actions then, and in front of voters Saturday, saying that as a hourly employee of the town, she was allowed to collect the fee as part of her pay. She was also following the practices of the town clerks who held the position before her, she said.
The selectmen and Town Administrator Jill E. Collins maintain Akeley's pay has always been based on salary and not by the number of hours she works.
In the wake of last year's events, the selectmen had been advised by the town's attorney and auditors to "get rid of the muddy water" and streamline Akeley's pay, Collins said.
While many voters seemed not to take issue with the warrant article, they took issue with what passing it meant for Akeley's paycheck.
Akeley told voters that the annual salary of $28,954 she would receive would be less than if she was allowed to continue collecting a base pay of roughly $18,000 along with the $2.50 she collected in state motor vehicle fees.
The statement brought almost every voter left in the gym after nearly four hours to Akeley's defense.
Over the course of the next hour, discussion became heated, as residents accused the selectmen of being liars, trying to railroad Akeley and deceiving local taxpayers.
The selectmen denied the allegations.
Eventually, Town Moderator Richard S. Johnson Jr. suspended discussion, and the selectmen, Collins and Akeley met at the stage. Johnson continued on to the next warrant article.
Selectmen then came back to the voters and told them they had come to an agreement with Akeley, and the agreement would be finalized at the board's meeting on Monday at 6 p.m. at Town Hall.
Selectmen declined to disclose details of the agreement, saying it would be negotiated Monday, but Akeley told voters she was happy with it.
When asked why the selectmen didn't call a nonpublic session at town meeting to discuss Akeley's pay, Darcy said in a phone interview Saturday night that it would have been messy to do so, and that official negotiations will take place at the Monday meeting.
The amount Akeley will be paid will be around $35,000 annually, but the selectmen will have to look at documents including tax forms Monday night in nonpublic session to finalize that number, Darcy said. Akeley's pay will then be voted on in public session, he said.
Earlier in the meeting, voters agreed to accept a federal grant of $125,000 to hire a school resource officer for the high school for four years. The grant comes from the Office of Community Oriented Policing Services.
For the first three years of the grant, beginning in 2014, the grant would pay for 60 percent of the officer's salary and benefits, while the town would be responsible for the remaining 40 percent. In 2017, the town would be required to cover the entire cost of the position.
Resident and school board member Angela Schill spoke against the warrant article, saying that having a school resource officer would be detrimental to students.
Children might feel threatened by having a police officer in their school, she said.
"I understand what the police are trying to do, and I think it's admirable of them to try to form a tighter relationship with our children," she said.
However, police officers don't belong in a school, or disciplining students who don't behave in that setting, she said.
Schill's opposition was immediately crushed by six people, including former Police Chief Wayne T. Gallagher and current Police Officer Wayne H. Kassotis who spoke in favor of the school having a school resource officer.
Kassotis, who was a school resource officer at Monadnock Regional High School for eight years, will take on the position in Hinsdale.
The job of a school resource officer includes being a resource for students and their families, building relationships with students, assisting teachers with lessons about law and civics topics and lastly being a law enforcement officer, Kassotis said.
"This is not a new concept," he said.
Resident Linda Page said children who are scared of police officers have been taught to be so by their parents.
"Having an officer in the school is going to make a huge difference for the children and culture," she said.
Voters agreed to accept the grant to fund the school resource officer position by a vote of 123-52.
In other business, town meeting voters approved:
A budget of $3,501,166, which is an increase $131,727, or 3.9 percent from the 2013-14 budget of $3,369,439. An amendment to lower the proposed budget to the level of the 2013-14 budget failed.
Appropriating $15,500 to use toward continuing bus service between Hinsdale and Brattleboro.
Meghan Foley can be reached at 352-1234, extension 1436, or mfoley@keenesentinel.com Follow her on Twitter @MFoleyKS.
___ (c)2014 The Keene Sentinel (Keene, N.H.) Visit The Keene Sentinel (Keene, N.H.) at www.sentinelsource.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>