<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-NXG1-JC8V-61FC"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>The New York Times</title><source>JAGfn.com</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[In China, Shaking Up Currency's Strength - Recent developments suggest that the renminbi's day-to-day strengthening is no longer the certainty it once appeared to be. Low-Wage Workers Finding It's Easier to Fall Into Poverty, and Harder to Get Out - For those at the low end of the hourly wage scale, even meeting basic household needs can be a stretch, and roads out of poverty are scarce.Start-Ups Aim to Conquer Space Market - The start-up Planet Labs is challenging the giants of the space industry by producing dozens of small satellites that are cheaper and quicker to build than traditional satellites.Undercover TV Reports on School Security Raise Ethical Questions - School shootings have prompted efforts by news organizations in recent months to assess the effectiveness of safety measures, but some of these reports have gone disturbingly wrong.States Urge Retail Giants With Pharmacies to Stop Selling Tobacco Products - More than two dozen attorneys general encouraged five of the country's largest retailers to follow the example of CVS and stop selling tobacco products in stores that also have pharmacies.Lithium Producer Chases Tesla's Bold Battery Plan - The California company Simbol Materials is building a plant that will use a novel extraction process, in the hopes that it can provide the lithium needed for the batteries in Tesla's cars.2 Oligarchs in $7 Billion Deal for a German Oil Company - RWE said it had reached a preliminary agreement to sell its oil and natural gas subsidiary, RWE Dea, to the Russian billionaires Mikhail Fridman and German Khan for 5.1 billion euros.Canada Explores G.M. Link to Accidents - Canada is looking into whether a fatal crash last June is related to the automaker's faulty ignition switches.In Reversal Since the Recession, Some States Give More Money to Public Television - Funding is still off sharply from the 2008 fiscal year, but 35 states have set aside about $191.5 million for 2014.Guinness Withdraws Sponsorship of St.
Patrick's Day Parade - The decision, brought about by the event's ban on public expression of gay pride, was applauded by gay rights groups that had threatened to boycott the company's products.
]]></text></news-item>