<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S210"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Challenging Safety Finding, Advocates Fault EPA's Coal Ash Reuse Review</title><source>Superfund Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Environmentalists are questioning the quality and scope of EPA's recently released method for assessing the risks posed by encapsulated uses of coal combustion residuals (CCR), as well as the agency's accompanying document that found that reuse of coal ash in concrete and wallboard is safe, calling the process a "kangaroo court of science."
The groups are raising numerous concerns, ranging from the scope of the methodology, which is limited to the consumer use phase of products' lifecycles, as well as what they perceive to be a limited and potentially partial peer review of the methodology document.
Regarding the review that found coal ash reuse in concrete and wall board to be safe, environmentalists are raising concerns that the document relies too heavily on industry-funded studies to determine that only certain exposure pathways and certain constituents of potential concern in the coal ash required EPA's scrutiny.
And advocates are concerned that neither document was released in draft form for public comment, and only one of the two documents underwent peer review. "We were appalled by the process by which EPA proceeded," said one environmentalist, who described the documents' creation as "a kangaroo court of science to reach a pre-determined outcome and shut the door" on concerns about reusing coal ash in building materials.
Answering questions from environmentalists and reporters during a March 5 webinar, staff in EPA's Office of Solid Waste & Emergency Response (OSWER) explained that the applications document was not peer-reviewed because staff was "just applying the methodology that was already peer-reviewed," according to Richard Kinch, chief of EPA's Industrial Materials Reuse Branch.
The methodology document underwent a letter peer review managed by an independent contractor, according to an EPA spokeswoman. Letter peer reviews by contractor represent the lowest level of scrutiny in the types of peer reviews that EPA requests for its scientific products.
Susan Thorneloe, an environmental engineer in EPA's research office, said during the webinar that two publications referenced in the applications document were published in the journal Chemosphere, and so went through peer review for that publication. The papers, published in the journal Dec. 19, shortly before the release of EPA's beneficial reuse documents, describe leach testing performed on concrete containing various amounts of coal ash compared with samples of concrete with Portland cement. They do not address wallboard or other exposure pathways (Superfund Report, Feb. 3).
OSWER staff undertook the risk documents after EPA's Inspector General (IG) in a 2011 report faulted the Coal Combustion Products Partnership (C2P2) program, formerly housed in the agency's Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention. The IG report protested that C2P2 was promoting the practice of re-using CCR as filler agent in various applications without evaluating the potential risks of those uses to human health or the environment.
Though OSWER's recent document concluded that the two largest categories of coal ash reuse are beneficial when conducted appropriately, EPA has yet to determine C2P2's future. "The Agency is evaluating our broader involvement in the beneficial use of industrial secondary materials from a sustainable materials management perspective," the EPA spokeswoman said in response to questions. "Before determining the appropriate course of action, the Agency will consult with stakeholders to identify potential future opportunities for collaboration."
The 2011 IG report said EPA applied "significantly limited" risk screening, testing and modeling for the 15 categories of beneficial reuse it promoted through C2P2. The IG said reuse of the large waste stream is an "important and necessary" part of EPA's mission to protect the environment. But the report said, "In our opinion, the good intentions underlying beneficial use activities do not supersede EPA's mission to protect human health and the environment. EPA should define and implement the accepted practices it will use for assessing the risks and safety of the CCR beneficial uses it promotes" (Superfund Report, April 4, 2011).
Such concerns highlight the difficulty EPA faces as it works to determine how to regulate disposal of CCR, the high-volume waste produced from coal-burning power plants. In a recent court settlement with stakeholders, EPA agreed to finalize by year's end its long-running effort to determine whether CCR wastes should be controlled by strict Resource Conservation & Recovery Act (RCRA) subtitle C hazardous waste controls or less stringent RCRA subtitle D controls.
The proposal to regulate CCR waste with subtitle C has drawn strong opposition from industry groups, which charge that the option for regulating CCR as a "hazardous waste" would shut down beneficial reuse of the material. Environmentalists argue that no other approach will be protective of the constituents of potential concern (COPCs) in the CCR.
During the webinar, OSWER staff said that they are "working on developing a conceptual model for unencapsulated uses." In its response to the IG, OSWER leadership wrote in September 2011 that staff would complete the model in the second quarter of fiscal year 2014.
Kinch added that there were no plans to review any other CCR reuse applications beyond the two already performed "at least for the foreseeable future. The agency has limited resources and competing priorities," he added. "The two examples [we evaluated], concrete and wallboard, are basically the vast majority of encapsulated uses."
Kinch said reviews like those produced for concrete and wallboard were not suited to unencapsulated recycling of CCR, which he described as largely a site-specific decision. "For unencapsulated uses in different scenarios, EPA has taken the position some uses are fine and others aren't," he said. "It's unlikely you'll get a national decision" about unencapsulated uses.
Environmentalists have also questioned EPA's decision to limit the review of encapsulated uses of CCRs to the consumer portion of the lifecycle, an approach they say avoids consideration of some exposure pathways, such as during buildings' renovation and demolition.
During the webinar, Kinch confirmed that renovation and demolition -- processes that tend to produce dust -- are not included in the agency's consumer phase review. While OSWER reviewed dust as an exposure pathway in its concrete review, it did not in its evaluation of wallboard.
For wallboard, EPA relied on a study performed by wallboard producer Georgia Pacific and Exponent consultants, rather than performing its own assessment of dust as an exposure pathway. EPA described the findings of the Yost et al. study on wallboard, published in 2010, and stated that "[b]ased on these findings, the current evaluation limited the selection of COPCs to those with the potential to be released through emanation to indoor air or radioactive decay."
A second environmentalist calls EPA's explanation "threadbare," arguing the agency does not "explain why it would consider one study, rather than multiple ones, preferably not funded by industry, to be sufficient to discount this major potential exposure pathway," dust.
The decision led to questions during the webinar about EPA's definition of the consumer use phase of the product's lifecycle, since dust is often generated during renovation or demolition. OSWER's Jason Mills, replied that EPA considers the consumer use to be "as long as the structure is in use," which for wallboard would be when it is in place and not disturbed.
"In the beneficial use of [CCR] materials, [consumer use] was the critical aspect we wanted to consider" because regulated disposal sites are already adequately controlled and address the end-of-life phase of the product's lifecycle, Kinch added. "With wallboard . . . if there is new construction scrap, basically recycling of that material goes to new wallboard construction, [creating] an internal loop," he said.
The EPA spokeswoman further explains that "the evaluation did consider the pathway for each release that is most likely to result in long-term exposures during use of fly ash concrete and [flue gas desulfurization] gypsum wallboard. The exposures arising from home renovation [including a homeowner drilling or cutting into wallboard] are short-term and will quickly decrease with time."
The spokeswoman notes that exposure scenarios not evaluated in the main portion of the analysis, including home renovation, were addressed in the document's review of uncertainties in its approach and findings. "This analysis concluded that while the existence of other exposure scenarios, introduces some uncertainty into the evaluation, it is unlikely to affect the results of the evaluation," the spokeswoman says.
EPA staff was asked during the webinar how much mercury was in the tested CCR concrete and wallboard samples. Activists have raised this concern because as EPA issues stricter air regulations on coal-fired power plants, enhanced scrubbers and other technologies capture more mercury and other COPCs in CCR, raising the overall amount of COPCs in the CCR. Of particular interest is how tightening air pollution rules for mercury and other toxics produced by coal-burning utilities will affect the constitution of CCR for use in recycling applications.
"The amount of the mercury in the study is thought to consider pollution controls," Mills replied. "It doesn't expect to consider mixes under the current [Clean Air Act maximum achievable control technology] because that would render them unsuitable for use in concrete."
Thorneloe added that the testing used "fly ashes that are considered suitable for making concrete . . . If you've got high carbon content, it wouldn't be considered suitable. We did include fly ash with a high arsenic content, and even for that we did not see leaching . . ."
The first environmentalist explained that the responses addressed only concrete, indicating that CCR with higher levels of mercury would also have higher levels of activated carbon, which would be unsuitable for use in concrete. Staff "didn't answer [the question] for wallboard or any other encapsulated or unencapsulated use," the source says. -- Maria Hegstad
]]></text></news-item>