<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S1YR"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>D.C. Circuit Rejects Suit Over EPA's Utility Conventional Pollutant Air Rule</title><source>Clean Energy Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The U.S. Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit has rejected the utility industry's suit over EPA's new source performance standards (NSPS) setting emissions limits on conventional air pollutants from power plants, finding some of the legal challenges untimely and rejecting criticisms of air monitoring mandates as without merit.
The unanimous ruling, by Chief Judge Merrick Garland with a concurring opinion from Judge Brett Kavanaugh, upholds the Obama EPA's 2012 rule setting emission limits, testing and monitoring requirements for nitrogen oxides, sulfur dioxide and particulate matter from coal- and oil-fired power plants that began construction after May 3, 2011. The rule replaced an earlier utility NSPS for conventional pollutants the Bush EPA developed and released in 2009.
The ruling in Utility Air Regulatory Group (UARG) v. EPA marks an early legal win for the agency in its attempt to curb air pollution from the power sector, though the court has yet to rule on a separate industry challenge to EPA's related 2012 rule imposing maximum achievable control technology (MACT) standards to curb mercury and other air toxics from utilities.
Garland found that industry's challenges to a number of key provisions in the utility NSPS brought by industry and Texas were "not properly before" the court because they were raised for the first time in petitions for reconsideration of the NSPS that the agency is still addressing, whereas the Clean Air Act says that parties can only sue the agency over objections they raised during the public comment period.
For the remaining objections to the rule that were timely, the court rejected a number of industry challenges to the rule's particulate matter monitoring requirements, along with procedural challenges related to notice-and-comment requirements over the earlier 2009 version of the rule.
In its suit over the NSPS, the power sector legal group UARG focused on a provision requiring power plants with continuous emissions monitoring systems (CEMS) to also occasionally conduct measurements of opacity -- used a a proxy to measure soot -- to provide a "secondary check" that pollution control devices were working. UARG argued that it was unreasonable for EPA to force utilities with CEMS equipment to also monitor opacity at the same time.
But the D.C. Circuit rejected this claim, saying EPA had "articulated a reasonable explanation" for the requirement, specifically that it would provide a real-time check to make sure that pollution controls were working.
The court also rejected UARG's challenges over procedural issues related to the earlier 2009 version of the rule developed by the Bush administration that was then reconsidered and revised by the Obama administration. The D.C. Circuit says that even if EPA "did stumble procedurally" in the 2009 rulemaking, it "made up for any procedural error" when it proposed the new version of utility NSPS in 2011 and offered the chance for public comment.
'Affirmative' Defense
Texas also filed suit over the utility NSPS, specifically a provision that related to an "affirmative defense" from civil Clean Air Act penalties that can be used when facilities exceed emission limits because of malfunctions.
EPA has at times allowed industry to use the affirmative defense to avoid facing air law fines for malfunctions, but only when a source can show the malfunctions were unavoidable.
In its challenge to the rule, Texas said EPA had failed to explain why it would not approve state-specific affirmative defense programs for the utility NSPS, but the D.C. Circuit said that "EPA did explain: Unlike some other Clean Air Act standards, new source performance standards are not incorporated into [state implementation plans] as state-promulgated regulations" but are instead federal standards.
Texas also said that EPA was arbitrary and capricious because in its mercury and air toxics standards for utilities issued alongside the NSPS, the agency said it would allow state-specific affirmative defenses, but the D.C. Circuit said that objection was not properly before it because it did not "bring this alleged inconsistency" to EPA's attention until it filed a petition for reconsideration.
In a concurring opinion, Kavanaugh sought to clarify that the opinion's discussion on when parties had exhausted their options through public comments and petitions for reconsideration "should not be considered jurisdictional under" recent Supreme Court precedent established in 2013 in Sebelius v. Auburn Regional Medical Center, a case related to hospital reimbursements under Medicare. -- Chris Knight (cknight@iwpnews.com)
03-10-2014
]]></text></news-item>