<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-3561-DXKH-N2Y8"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Mitsubishi Heavy Industries in 4th daily fall, nears seven-month low</title><source>News Bites Asian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Mitsubishi Heavy Industries Ltd. (TO:7011), the 3rd largest machinery/industrial goods company by market capitalisation in the Tokyo Stock Exchange, slipped further on Monday, sliding an additional JPY12.0 (or 2.0%) to trade at JPY579.0. The stock decreased 0.48% on Thursday and 4.21% on Friday bringing its 4-day fall to 8.1%. It is now approaching its 158-day low of JPY575.0. Compared with the Nikkei 225 Index which fell 50.0 points (or 0.4%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -1.7%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Mitsubishi Heavy Industries, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051711770314101
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- The stock dropped on thin volume falling for a fourth consecutive day.- The stock dropped 2.0% on high volatility today.- The stock dropped to a six-month low.- The stock's relative price strength percentile is falling at 49 for 6 months, 34 for 3 months and 25 for 1 month.- The Moving Average Convergence Divergence (MACD) indicator of 12-day Exponential Moving Average (EMA) of 613.09 minus the 26-day EMA of 623.7 is negative 10.62 suggesting a bearish signal. Both EMA prices are falling, another bearish signal.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Return on Assets 2.5% [3.1%].Other Bearish Signals:- Net profit margin has averaged 1.8% in the last 3 years. This suggests the company is less profitable with a low margin of safety.
Bullish Signals- The present value of JPY1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Mitsubishi Heavy Industries is JPY1,101, including a capital gain of JPY90 and dividend reinvested of JPY10.
Oversold/Bullish/Support Signals- At JPY579.0 the price is below the lower Bollinger band support of JPY591.47, indicating an upside for it to return to the band. - The Relative Strength Index (RSI) of 27.2 has breached the oversold line of 30, suggesting the price decrease of 7.4% in the last 14 days is unusually high. - The stock is oversold according to the Williams % R indicator of -93.8, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day low of JPY575.0.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Sales of 0.7 [2.3]. We estimate Mitsubishi Heavy Industries stock is trading at a current year Price/Sales of 0.6 and a forward year Price/Sales of 0.5. - Price to Book of 1.4 [4.1]. We estimate Mitsubishi Heavy Industries stock is trading at a current year Price to Book of 1.4 and a forward year Price to Book of 1.3.Other Bullish Signals:- Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.5. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity is less than stellar at 7.0%. This is computed as net profit margin of 3.5% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 0.72 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 2.8.- Net Profit margin is positive and has seen consecutive rises in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]
- Net Profit margin is positive and has seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 16,163,000 shares worth JPY9.4 billion (US$92.6 million) traded. The volume was 0.7 times the average trading of 22.2 million shares. Beta: the Beta of Mitsubishi Heavy Industries stock is 1.1. A Beta greater than 1 suggests this is a high risk, high return stock with volatility greater than that of the market. - Mitsubishi Heavy Industries is at a discount of 24.3% to its 12-month high of JPY765.0 on 23 May, 2013. It is also at a premium of 16.5% to the 12-month low of JPY497.0 on 02 Apr, 2013.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Parity:- Return on Equity 7.0% [6.8%].
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 06: MHI to Launch New Models of Multi-split Inverter System Air Conditioners for Building Applications, Targeting Overseas Markets[Company Release] Tokyo, March 6, 2014 - Starting in June, Mitsubishi Heavy Industries, Ltd. (MHI) will progressively launch the new "KXZ Series," multi-split inverter system air conditioners for applications in office buildings and other large-scale facilities, targeting overseas markets.
February 19: MHI Receives Order for Pressurizer Nozzle Spool Piece Replacement on Ringhals Unit-3 at Ringhals Nuclear Power Plant in Sweden[Company Release] Tokyo, February 19, 2014 - Mitsubishi Heavy Industries, Ltd. (MHI) has received an order for pressurizer nozzle spool piece replacement work on the Ringhals 3 reactor at the Ringhals Nuclear Power Plant in Sweden. Pressurizer is a core component of pressurized water reactor (PWR) nuclear power plants, and the replacement work will enhance operating reliability through the use of more corrosion-resistant alloys in critical weld joints.
January 16: MHI Establishing Finance Subsidiary in Singapore As Part of Initiative to Forge Unified Global Financial Management System[Company Release]-- Second Dedicated Unit after Earlier Subsidiary Created in the U.S. --Tokyo, January 16, 2014 - On January 17 Mitsubishi Heavy Industries, Ltd. (MHI) will establish a wholly owned finance subsidiary in Singapore to oversee the financial affairs of its group companies doing business in Asia.
January 14: Mitsubishi Heavy Industries: Demonstration Test for Capturing CO2 In the Flue Gas from a Coal-fired Power Generation Plant Completes Initial Demonstration Phase[Company Release]Tokyo, January 14, 2014 - A demonstration test for capturing and sequestering carbon dioxide (CO2) recovered from emissions from a coal-fired power generation plant, conducted jointly by Mitsubishi Heavy Industries, Ltd. (MHI) and Southern Company Services, Inc.
December 27: MHI to Launch Latest ETC Unit Model "MOBE-700"http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Japan/Stock/News/18347.htmlSource: Company Website
December 24: MHI Receives Order for M501J Gas Turbine and Steam Turbine From KEPCO E&C of Korea[Company Release] Tokyo, December 24, 2013 - Mitsubishi Heavy Industries, Ltd. (MHI) has received an order from KEPCO Engineering & Construction Company, Inc. (KEPCO E&C) for the core equipment of a combined heat and power (CHP) natural gas-fired generation plant, including an M501J gas turbine.
December 20: Shanghai MHI Engine, JV with Shanghai Diesel Engine, Begins Mass Production[Company Release] Tokyo, December 20, 2013 - Shanghai MHI Engine Co., Ltd., a manufacturer and marketer of diesel engines jointly established by Mitsubishi Heavy Industries, Ltd. (MHI) and Shanghai Diesel Engine Co., Ltd. (SDEC) - a major Chinese diesel engine manufacturer - has begun mass-volume production.
ISIN: JP3900000005
TO:7011; TYO:7011; T:7011; JP:7011
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>