<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-RBD1-JDJN-61PS"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Stolen identities</title><source>Global Times (China)</source><author>Fang Yang</author><text><![CDATA[An official stamps on a passport at the border control after checking in an airport in Nanjing, Jiangsu Province, on Tuesday. Photo: CFP
The mysterious disappearance of Malaysia Airlines Flight 370 (MH370), which was carrying more than 200 passengers and crew, has been on every front page since March 8.Public attention has particularly focused on the use of stolen passports by two travellers on the flight. How did they evade security? What risks are there to those who lost their passports?"I lost my passport once in Thailand years ago," Net user Albus Quillan (a Harry Potter-derived online pseudonym) told the Global Times, "and the recent reports make me worried about what will people do with stolen passports and what kind of trouble it will bring to the original owners."According to reports, the owners of these two passports reported the loss.
That they could still be used highlighted a grave security concern about passport control.The disappearance of MH370 does not appear to be related to terrorism, although a CNN report quoted a US intelligence official as saying "that's by no means definitive. We're still tracking."But like many others, Albus's biggest concern was that stolen passports may be used by terrorists and one day the original owner could find that his or her name is on a wanted list.For Wang Xiaofeng, who lost his passport in France in 2013, the big concern is financial. He worries whether the lost passport will be used in other ways, like activating some mobile phone service that will charge money monthly and bill him.There are many kinds of business that use passports to check ID and they don't require the document to be checked by the border authorities, Wang said.LoopholesThe two men who boarded the missing flight with stolen passports were identified as probably Iranians on Tuesday by Malaysian police and the International Criminal Police Organization (Interpol). They appear to have been trying to sneak into Germany and to have no ties to terrorist groups.There is no foolproof system for checking cross-border travel, according to a commentary on CNN written by Brian Havel, a director of the International Aviation Law Institute at DePaul University College of Law. Havel states that although some "smart" solutions, such as biometric passports and electronic visas, are now in play, many forms of documentation used every day by millions of airline passengers are not digitized and are not being checked against any international databases.Fake passports are commonly used. In 2010, reports revealed that at least 10 passengers on the ill-fated Air India Express flight from Dubai, which crashed on a runway offshoot, were using fraudulent passports. In the same year, police in Spain and Thailand smashed a counterfeiting ring which aimed to provide fake European passports to Al Qaeda.The group stole passports, mostly from tourists in the Barcelona area, and sent them to Thailand to be doctored and later distributed to groups linked to Al Qaeda.Interpol has established a database of stolen and lost travel documents. According to Interpol, the database enables Interpol National Central Bureaus and other authorized law enforcement entities (such as immigration and border control offices) to ascertain the validity of a travel document in seconds. But the system is sometimes ignored, since it adds an extra level of validation to an already time-consuming checking process for travel.It was created in 2002, following the September 11 terrorist attacks in the US in 2001, to help member countries secure their borders and protect their citizens from terrorists and other dangerous criminals using fraudulent travel documents. As of March 2014, it contains information on more than 40 million travel documents, such as passports, reported lost or stolen in 167 countries, and it was searched by member countries more than 800 million times in 2013, resulting in some 67,000 positive responses, or "hits."Interpol said that no country checked the two passports used to board the flight, even though they were reported stolen in Thailand.China's efforts"If someone loses their passport and reports the loss, we will issue a new one and the old one becomes invalid," Lin Song, a staff with the Exit-Entry Administration Division of the Beijing Municipal Bureau of Public Security, told the Global Times on Tuesday.Only the information of permanent residents will be recorded into the system, Zhang Huide, an expert on exit-entry management with People's Public Security University of China, told the Global Times."For overseas Chinese who hold Chinese passports and use them as the equivalent identity cards in China, losing the passports can bring more hidden troubles since it won't be recorded in China's exit-entry system," Zhang said.Some South Koreans in China sell their passports to would-be entrants to South Korea, Zhang said, adding that cases of foreigners who lose passports in China are not recorded either.At present, advanced examinations like fingerprint checks haven't not used yet by border authorities in China. But since China's been issuing electronic passports inputting holders' fingerprints, the examination will be upgraded in the future to better screen forgeries, according to insiders.Both Wang and Albus said that after they reported the loss of their passports and applied for new ones, they were thoroughly inspected by Chinese border agents. Lin said new passports have different serial numbers from lost ones, and the lost one cannot be used within the national system. China's Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the Ministry of Public Security, which are in charge of the issuance and management of passports, haven't given any details on cooperation with Interpol. Neither did Interpol, when reached by the Global Times. Interpol encourages its members to extend access to the I-24/7 network to major airports, border crossings and other strategic locations. However, Zhang believed that enforcement will be difficult. "The entry-and-exit information system involves national security, and it will require legal authorization to network with service or business agencies," Zhang said.More countries may set up a passport database coordinated with Interpol after the MH370 incident, Zhang added."More immigration liaison officers will be sent to key regions," said Zhang, adding that anti-forgery measures will also be upgraded to include more electronic and biometric measures.
]]></text></news-item>