<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S1XD"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>EPA Defends 'Emergency' Emissions Rule Exemption For Diesel Engines</title><source>Carbon Control News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EPA in new legal filings is defending its decision to allow an exemption from strict air pollution limits for diesel engines operating up to 100 hours per year under "emergency" conditions, saying the basis for the exemption is long established and that the provision is vital to protect against electric grid blackouts or other instability.
The rules' critics counter that EPA failed to evaluate the environmental harm that could result from exempting engines from emissions controls under the engine standards, which set emissions limits for reciprocating internal combustion engines (RICE). The engines emit more nitrogen oxides (NOx), in particular, per unit of energy produced than traditional power plants, especially where those plants run on natural gas or use emissions controls.
Delaware -- which fears adverse air pollution impacts as a result of the exemption -- along with environmentalists and "clean" utilities that burn lower-emitting natural gas all filed suit over the rule in the U.S. Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit. The court is yet to schedule oral arguments in the consolidated suit.
Opponents of the rule recently filed opening briefs in the suit, faulting EPA for changing a previous policy limiting the exemption to 15 hours. Last year's RICE rulemaking expanded the exemption to 100 hours. If EPA wanted to offer the exemption then under the Clean Air Act it should have, but did not, demonstrate that the move would not result in environmental or public health harm, critics say.
Groups challenging the rule also argue that EPA's definition of "emergency" use is too broad and allows generators to participate in commercial demand-response programs for financial gain in situations that do not qualify as a true emergency, and that electrical grid reliability is not within the agency's regulatory purview.
EPA in its March 11 response brief in the case, Delaware Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Control (DNREC), et al. v. EPA, does not directly address the accusation by Delaware that it never assessed the harm caused by emissions released under the emergency RICE exemption. It says DNREC cannot show that emissions from RICE will harm the state, and hence the state cannot show standing to sue.
The agency argues that its right to establish emergency use exemptions, and definition of demand-response as an emergency use, is well established and "not before the court." The agency's focus in its filing, therefore, is on EPA's expansion of the annual limit for emergency use to 100 hours from 15 previously.
In the RICE rule, the agency justified the increased exemption to ensure that backup diesel generators can provide adequate power to the grid to prevent blackouts and grid instability.
The agency argues that its definition of what constitutes an "emergency" is legitimate, and that grid blackouts present public health and environmental emergencies in their own right, threatening essential services. One example EPA cites are sewage treatment works, which cease to operate without power.
Regulatory Exemption
EPA says it is within its Clean Air Act authority to exempt engines operating to prevent electric grid failures from compliance with the January 2013 rule setting maximum achievable control technology limits for air toxics and new source performance standards for other pollutants emitted by RICE.
In its brief, the agency notes that while it has always allowed unrestricted use of generators during actual power blackouts, "blackouts are not the only type of emergency situation for which emergency engines may be useful for power generation. Emergency engines also serve a valuable function as backup sources of power to help stabilize the electric grid during rare 'near-blackout' situations."
Under a 2010 rule, EPA allowed up to 15 hours of use for uncontrolled RICE in such "near-blackout" situations, but "aggregators" of generators operating in demand-response programs challenged the rules, saying that 15 hours is insufficient to allow engines to participate in "capacity markets" such as the PJM Interconnection.
The agency then reconsidered the rule and expanded the exemption to 100 hours Ã more than the 60 hours minimum required to participate in the PJM capacity market, for example.
The rule's critics, however, say this allows aggregators to run "virtual power plants" without complying with environmental protections, posing risks to public health and states' attempts to attain federal air standards.
In order to prevent blackouts, which the agency says are "truly calamitous" on many fronts, resulting in public health risks and environmental damage, EPA notes that running a subset of generators is preferable to running all available generators in the event of a true blackout.
EPA notes that its 100-hour exemption only applies under very specific circumstances, namely if an Energy Emergency Alert Level 2 has been called under North American Electric Reliability Corporation Reliability Standard EOP-002-3, Capacity and Energy Emergencies, or during periods where voltage or frequency deviates by five percent or more below standard voltage or frequency. Further, the 2013 rule requires emergency generators operating more than 15 hours per year to use ultra-low sulfur fuel, curbing air emissions, EPA says.
The agency denies that by using this yardstick, it is in effect wading into a domain regulated by the Federal Electric Reliability Commission (FERC), an argument made in a Dec. 26 joint brief by utilities Calpine Corporation, First Energy Solutions Corp. and PSEG Power LLC. Critics also say that electric reliability can be achieved by other means such as demand reduction, and EPA discounts this in order to assert an "emergency" where there is none.
EPA says, "the 2013 Rule does not address the participation of emergency engines in capacity markets. Rather, as discussed above, EPA has specified narrow conditions under which emergency engines may operate as emergency demand response resources (whether in capacity markets or otherwise)."
'Remote' Engines
EPA is also defending an exemption in the rules for non-emergency "remote" engines, including those located offshore, from a requirement to install emissions controls as generally available control technology (GACT).
Delaware in the case has said EPA's assertions that installing controls on engines in remote locations would be difficult and expensive are arbitrary, based on an applicability test "that has nothing to do with accessibility and hinges only on the type and number of structures in close proximity to the engines." The state suggests EPA should require non-selective catalytic reduction technology for remote engines to reduce their NOx emissions.
In its response brief, EPA says "EPA reasonably determined that installation of aftertreatment technology did not constitute GACT for this subcategory due to the cost of installing, testing, and maintaining emissions controls for engines in remote areas." The agency instead requires non-binding "best management practices" rather than installation of emissions controls on the remote engines.
The agency continues, "It is unclear whether Delaware's concern is that population density is an improper measure of remoteness, or that there is no correlation between an engine's remoteness and costs associated with installing and maintaining pollution controls. Regardless, Delaware offers no support for either assumption."
EPA further notes that while non-selective catalytic reduction is intended to reduce NOx, the portion of the rulemaking in question deals with air toxics, which means that the exclusive focus on NOx is misplaced because that pollutant is not an air toxic. -- Stuart Parker (sparker@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>