<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-R6B1-DYJJ-P0CF"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>EDITORIAL: Cut storm victims slack on the rent</title><source>Asbury Park Press (New Jersey)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[How many times can Sandy victims be victimized?
At least one more time if those Sandy victims happen to be among the 57 families staying at Fort Monmouth.
This week, in a typical "the federal government giveth and the federal government taketh away" story, the Federal Emergency Management Agency told those displaced families that they could stay at Fort Monmouth through the end of the summer.
But starting May 1, the feds are going to start collecting rent from them: $1,083 for one-bedroom units and $1,865 for three-bedroom units, the 2014 fair-market rates for Monmouth County, according to the federal Department of Housing and Urban Development. That's outrageous.
There is nothing fair about how these people - and many other people -have been treated by both the federal government and state government when it comes to delays in getting them aid. FEMA must reconsider. And Gov. Chris Christie needs to add his voice to the bipartisan voices already protesting the decision to charge the Sandy victims rent.
Rep. Chris Smith, R-N.J., said he plans to push the Obama administration for a reasonable and compassionate resolution to the issue. "I find it profoundly inadequate and insulting," said Smith of charging rent to those at the fort. "I respectfully appeal to President Obama himself to step in and work with us to provide real help."
Frank Pallone Jr., D-N.J. agrees. While there is precedent for victims of other disasters being charged rent for temporary housing, Congress after Hurricanes Katrina or Rita did not hold up recovery funding for weeks, as it did with Sandy, he said.
"In light of the vast mismanagement of Sandy relief funds, it is indefensible for the storm victims temporarily residing at Fort Monmouth to be charged rent," Pallone said. "These people are still unable to get back in their homes through no fault of their own. They shouldn't be penalized as a result of the slow pace of recovery."
He's right. It is understandable that FEMA usually sets an 18-month limit for living assistance after a natural disaster. But the snafus and delays besetting those dislocated by Sandy represent a unique situation requiring a reassessment of the standard policies.
It's not as if these people are scamming the government. Take Pamela Vasquez, 50, a Union Beach resident. She has tried to find temporary housing outside the fort, but she said her options have been limited because her family has a dog and because few landlords have been willing to offer her a fair price for renting a unit month-to-month, rather than for a year.
In the meantime, she finds herself in a bureaucratic limbo, still waiting for word on her state Reconstruction, Rehabilitation, Elevation and Mitigation grant application for her uninhabitable home.
Christie, who has yet to comment on this injustice, should be leading the charge to get FEMA to stop this rent grab.
]]></text></news-item>