<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-3V11-DYT4-K2MF"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Public works, unions in 'patriotic agreement'</title><source>Business Day (South Africa)</source><author>LINDA ENSOR</author><text><![CDATA[Public works, unions in 'patriotic agreement'
Political Correspondent
CAPE TOWN - The Department of Public Works has signed an agreement with two public-sector trade unions that commits employees & to work for effective and efficient delivery of services& The national framework agreement - signed on Friday with the Public Servants Association (PSA) and the National Education, Health and Allied Workers Union (Nehawu) - deals with the rebuilding of the department, its turnaround strategy and the migration of employees from the old to the new structure.
The department has received eight qualified audit reports, followed by three consecutive disclaimers, from former auditor-general Terence Nombembe, who highlighted maladministration and the shortage of technical skills as critical shortcomings. It has been weighed down by the prolonged Nkandla saga and plagued by leasing scandals and allegations of tender fraud involving kickbacks. Wasteful expenditure over the past fives years has been estimated to amount to billions of rand.
Public works is hoping that a dedicated effort by staff behind its turnaround strategy can help pull it out of the doldrums.
The Treasury has allocated R366m over the next three years for cleaning up the department and hiring more staff with technical expertise that will reduce its heavy reliance on consultants. The funds will also be used for the work of the Special Investigating Unit, which is probing fraud and corruption.
Public Works Minister Thulas Nxesi has given trade unions the assurance that no jobs would be lost and no privatisation of sections of the department would take place during the implementation of the turnaround strategy. Speaking at a function to mark the signature of the agreement, Mr Nxesi said: & The issues of fraud and corruption are non-negotiable. If you carry on with fraud and corruption, we will expose you. The unions must help us to expose such people.& A training and development programme will also be developed to enhance skills within the department. The signatories committed themselves to create a patriotic public-service culture. They undertook to promote adherence to the rule of law, code of conduct and effective mechanisms to reverse and prevent corruption and maladministration.
PSA deputy GM Manie de Clercq supported Mr Nxesi's strong stance. & We hope the implementation of the turnaround strategy will create a better public service and country for all.& Nehawu national treasurer Pulani Mogotsi said he hoped the agreement would lead to a more caring department and skills transference to employees.
ensorl@bdfm.co.za.
]]></text></news-item>