<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S1XR"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>CCS Developer's Doubts On Technology May Boost GOP's NSPS Attacks</title><source>Carbon Control News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A key developer of carbon capture and sequestration (CCS) technology will use testimony at an upcoming House science panel hearing to express doubts that CCS is ready to be required at newly constructed coal-fired power plants, which could bolster Republican critics of EPA's proposed climate rules for future utilities that would require use of CCS.
The testimony, obtained by Inside EPA ahead of the March 12 hearing by the House science committee's energy and environment panels, is likely to benefit GOP and industry critics of the rule, who say the CCS mandate cannot be supported because the technology is only beginning to transition to commercial utility-scale use. Opponents of the rule say that because CCS is not viable for coal plants, the rule will block new coal utility construction.
Manufacturing company Alstom believes "that while carbon capture technology has been proven to work, the industry has yet to reach demonstration stages to reduce the cost and reduce the risk of scaling these technologies from pilot or validation scale to full scale," according to prepared remarks that Robert Hilton, the company's government affairs vice president for power technologies, is slated to deliver at the upcoming committee hearing.
"Thus Alstom would challenge EPA on the argument that carbon capture is available and adequately demonstrated," he will say, referencing the agency's conclusion in its proposed new source performance standards (NSPS) for future utilities that CCS is "adequately demonstrated" -- part of the Clean Air Act threshold for requiring its use.
EPA found that carbon capture technology was viable based on years of successful use for enhanced oil recovery, pilot projects, the existing literature and a handful of large coal-fired CCS projects that are expected to begin operating this year, including Southern Company's Kemper plant, but industry has criticized the agency for requiring CCS before they have had sufficient time to develop operational experience or to understand the technology's risks.
In his prepared remarks for the upcoming hearing, Hilton says that although the company's carbon capture technology has worked, the company does not consider the technology to have reached full commercial scale, at which point he says industry would be able to define its risks, optimize equipment and seek cost reductions.
The "true state" of CCS, Hilton says, is that it has so far been deployed relatively infrequently and on small-scale projects, and that the industry has not yet had time to understand the risks of performing CCS at the utility-scale, such as the risks of having to shutdown power plants when sequestration processes fail, how to run carbon capture equipment during fluctuating generation load and how to handle byproducts from impurities in flue gas.
Hilton also says there are not yet suppliers of CCS that are "ready or willing" to provide commercial guarantees on full-scale carbon capture systems, and that all the projects EPA has cited to show the technology is adequately demonstrated were "niche market opportunities like [enhanced oil recovery] and chemicals" or have received large federal subsidies.
'Credible' Testimony
An industry source says the testimony from Hilton is "particularly credible" because the company has been "forefront of CCS technology development," and that while the company has a stake in CCS, "he leaves no doubt that it's not yet ready for prime time." However, Alstom is also a major producer of equipment for conventional coal-fired power plants, which industry has warned would become impossible to build under the NSPS.
Other GOP witnesses at the hearing on the science of CCS are set to offer their doubts on the technology. Scott Miller, a member of the board of directors for the American Public Power Association and the general manager of the City Utilities of Springfield, in his prepared testimony says that the agency's finding that CCS is adequately demonstrated is "premature," given the nascent stages of the technology. Miller also says that EPA failed to look at the environmental impacts of the sequestration of carbon dioxide itself.
The hearing comes less than a week after House Republicans in a 229-183 vote approved a measure to curtail EPA's authority to set NSPS. Lawmakers at the hearing will likely query acting EPA air chief Janet McCabe Ã slated to testify on the second of two panels -- about the rule's CCS mandate and other requirements.
McCabe in her prepared testimony defends the agency's utility NSPS, reiterating the agency's belief that the rule will "set the stage" for continued investments in carbon capture technology. EPA in its rule had said that absent the CCS requirement there would be little incentives for the power sector to further develop the technology.
Democrats on the House science committee have called an environmentalist to testify on the viability of CCS and to defend the agency's utility NSPS. David Hawkins, climate programs director for the Natural Resources Defense Council, in his prepared testimony says the technology has a long history of successful use and deployment, arguing that the agency has shown the technology is able to scale up to the power sector.
Hawkins says coal producers are "profoundly wrong" in their bet that trying to limit EPA's power to write climate rules would revive interest in coal, as he says doing so would cause the power sector to "look elsewhere to hedge its bets against the implications of climate disruption." -- Chris Knight (cknight@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>