<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-DS31-JBG7-44GX"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Crimea secession vote angers West; U.S. urges other nations to 'impose costs' on Moscow</title><source>Chicago Tribune</source><author>By Sergei L. Loiko, Tribune Newspapers Lisa Mascaro in Washington contributed.</author><text><![CDATA[In the face of widespread international condemnation and the threat of punishing new sanctions on the Russian government, voters in Crimea on Sunday appeared to overwhelmingly back a measure to break away from Ukraine and become part of Russia.
Passage would likely deepen the rift between Russia and the West.
"In this century, we are long past the days when the international community will stand quietly by while one country forcibly seizes the territory of another," White House press secretary Jay Carney said in a statement Sunday that called on other nations to "take concrete steps to impose costs" on Moscow.
With half the ballots counted, Mikhail Malishev, head of the Crimea election commission, said in televised remarks that more than 95 percent of voters approved the option of annexation by Russia over a second option that called for seeking more autonomy within Ukraine. Final results are expected Monday.
Even before Malishev's announcement, exit polls showing that trend drew a roar of jubilation from thousands of people gathered in the central square of Simferopol, Crimea's capital.
Secession was widely expected to win approval in a region dominated by Russian-speaking residents and home to Russia's Black Sea Fleet.
Voting was carried out under the watchful eyes of Russian troops and pro-Moscow militia, who largely seized control of the peninsula last month allegedly to protect Russians and Russian interests. Many of Crimea's ethnic Tatars and other minorities boycotted the vote. Still, election officials claimed turnout topped 80 percent.
For Russian President Vladimir Putin and his government, the balloting could be a political victory but an economic burden in a country where the stock market has tumbled and foreign investors are becoming skittish.
The Russians "know that there are costs to their action here. The costs are economic," Dan Pfeiffer, a senior adviser at the White House, said on "Meet the Press." "The more they escalate, the longer this goes, the greater those costs will be."
The response of Russia's European trading partners could come as early as Monday, when foreign ministers from the European Union gather in Brussels to discuss the Ukrainian crisis. British Foreign Secretary William Hague, arriving Sunday in Brussels, called on the alliance to approve measures "that send a strong signal to Russia."
"The referendum has taken place at 10 days' notice, without a proper campaign or public debate, with the political leaders of the country being unable to visit Crimea, and in the presence of many thousands of troops from a foreign country," he said. "It is a mockery of proper democratic practice."
The White House announced Sunday that President Barack Obama told Putin by phone that the U.S. would not recognize the results of the balloting and urged the Russian leader to pursue a diplomatic solution that "cannot be achieved while Russian military forces continue their incursions into Ukrainian territory."
The White House has already sought targeted sanctions on Russian individuals responsible for the military incursions, and senators also said they expected a $1 billion loan package and sanctions that has stalled in Congress to be approved when lawmakers return at the end of the month.
Moscow cited political turmoil in Kiev, the Ukrainian capital, as justification for largely seizing control of the peninsula. Ukraine's pro-Russia president, Viktor Yanukovych, fled his homeland last month after three months of protests against his government, and Russia has insisted that the country's new rulers are not legitimate.
Before polls opened Sunday, Crimea's new pro-Russia leader predicted on Twitter: "Crimea will become part of Russia."
"Tomorrow we will hold a Crimean (parliament) session, which will endorse the referendum results," Premier Sergei Aksenov said in televised remarks later in the day.
Some voters saw the referendum as a chance to reverse Crimea's inclusion in Ukraine. Soviet Premier Nikita Khrushchev in 1954 transferred control of the peninsula to Ukraine, which gained its independence with the collapse of the Soviet Union in 1991.
"I have been looking forward to this moment for the last 23 years, and now my dream is finally coming true," Yelena Gavysheva, 59, told Tribune Newspapers. "Now we will reunite with our real motherland, and our salaries and pensions will grow among other things."
"I am sick and tired of the constant government changes in Kiev, and I don't want the political violence to come here," said Natalia Lapyrina, 30, a primary school psychologist. "Russia will certainly protect us from fascist radicals coming here from (Ukraine's) west."
But some of Crimea's residents oppose what has been widely seen as the inevitable result of the referendum, and many of them boycotted the balloting.
Crimean Tatars mostly stayed home.
"We have all agreed to boycott the referendum as we want to go on living in Ukraine, where human rights and freedoms are much more respected than in Russia," said Memet Eminov, 46.
"We realize that most likely Russia will grab Crimea now, and we can only pray that there's no war," he added.
On the Black Sea coast near the resort city of Feodosia, Russian soldiers besieging a Ukraine marine base were observed setting up about 40 antitank mines around the perimeter of the unit, said Alexei Mazepa, Ukraine's Defense Ministry spokesman.
"As of Monday, when they announce the results of the referendum, Crimea's new authorities and the Russian military will consider our army and navy units they are blocking now an alien armed contingent and may step up their pressure all the way up to direct armed attacks," Mazepa said.
Ukraine acting President Alexander Turchinov called the Crimean referendum "a provocation by the Kremlin," which violates Ukraine's Constitution.
"It's false from beginning to end, and its results will not reflect the real moods in the autonomy," Turchinov said in a statement posted on the president's official website Sunday. "We must understand that its results have already been painted in the Kremlin, which at least needs some grounds to officially deploy troops in our lands and begin a war, which will destroy human fates and the economic prospects of Crimea."
sloiko@tribune.com ct14 0015 140317 R S 0000000000 00004933
]]></text></news-item>