<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S1Y4"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Senate Bill To Boost Natural Gas Vehicles Would End Ethanol Incentives</title><source>Carbon Control News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Bipartisan Senate legislation to promote natural gas-powered cars and other "dual-fueled" vehicles faces uncertain prospects because it would also prohibit incentives for producers of flexible fuel vehicles (FFVs) that can use 85 percent ethanol (E85) fuel blends, which could prompt push-back from senators supportive of the ethanol sector.
The bill, S.2065, is the latest effort to promote natural gas vehicles (NGVs), following legislation introduced in July that would provide an incentive for the vehicles in part by amending EPA fuel economy and greenhouse gas (GHG) standards for light-duty vehicles. That bill would also ensure the vehicles are given equal regulatory treatment with electric-powered vehicles in receiving credit under the agency's regulations.
Currently under EPA's vehicle GHG rules, FFVs will lose GHG credits beginning in 2016. Under 2017-2025 vehicle rules, automakers must be able to calculate E85 fuel use to receive production credits under the rules.
Sens. James Inhofe (R-OK) and Carl Levin (D-MI), who introduced S.2065, say automakers earn the majority of their credits today by producing E85 FFVs, leaving no credits for other alternative dual-fueled vehicles.
Under current law automakers are allowed to earn credits for compliance with corporate average fuel economy (CAFE) rules through the production of alternative fuel dual-fueled vehicles, such as light-duty car and truck models that can use two fuel types, such as electricity and gasoline, which the bill includes as hybrid-electric vehicles, hydrogen vehicles, natural gas cars and trucks, and models that can use biologically produced gases.
S.2065 would aim to promote other types of cars than E85 FFVs by removing the credit cap for natural gas and other alternative vehicles, excluding E85 FFVs, according to a joint press release from the senators.
Inhofe said the bill "will incentivize automakers to bring [natural gas vehicles] to market more quickly by streamlining regulations and removing red tape that automakers currently must comply with."
The E85 prohibition would encourage the production of dual-fueled vehicles by lending CAFE credits to other types of vehicles other than FFVs, say proponents of the Senate bill. But it could prompt opposition from the biofuel industry and its supporters in Congress for being seen as discouraging ethanol's use as a fuel type.
Pending Legislation
The pending Senate bill illustrates the continued pressure that the ethanol industry is experiencing at a time when the EPA renewable fuel standard (RFS) is under attack by refiners and EPA is considering broad cuts to the RFS biofuel blending requirements in response to blending and production constraints. Inhofe has long been a critic of the RFS, and in recent years has introduced legislation giving states the right to opt out of the program.
The Inhofe-Levin bill also gives states the option of allowing alternative dual-fueled vehicles, other than E85 vehicles, the use of high-occupancy highway driving lanes as an incentive for consumers to purchase the vehicles.
Levin also emphasized the bill's role in promoting carbon dioxide reductions while reducing the nation's dependence on foreign oil imports, according to a press release. "This bill will help boost production and sales of natural gas vehicles and plug-in electric hybrids by providing incentives to manufacturers and consumers," said Levin.
"To encourage the production of alternative fuel vehicles, the Levin-Inhofe bill would expand the types of vehicles that manufacturers can exempt from their annual bonus credit caps on fuel economy to include natural gas, hydrogen, fuels derived from biological materials, and electricity," according to a Feb. 28 Levin press release.
The bill would also require a federal study on "financing options" for building out natural gas refueling infrastructure. One hundred eighty days after passage of S.2065, the Department of Energy in consultation with the Department of Transportation will submit the study to Congress.
The senators' bill could get a boost from a coalition of gas utilities and drillers dedicated to promoting policies to boost use of natural gas in vehicles. The coalition recently widened its membership to include an influential vehicle group to expand its efforts, saying that natural gas is a more cost-effective and environmentally friendly transportation fuel compared to other fossil fuels such as gasoline.
The American Gas Association, representing gas utilities, and America's Natural Gas Alliance, representing the largest U.S. independent gas producers, announced Jan. 27 that the Drive Natural Gas Initiative coalition formed in 2010 will integrate its activities with the vehicle group Natural Gas Vehicles for America.
The initiative was formed "to help promote greater use of the nation's domestic abundance of clean, affordable natural gas in transportation," according to the groups. -- John Siciliano (jsiciliano@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>