<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-R6B1-DYJJ-P31P"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Saying 'thank you'</title><source>The Sheboygan Press (Wisconsin)</source><author>By, Kali Thiel</author><text><![CDATA[It's been three years since a devastating earthquake and tsunami hit Leo Sakuma's home country of Japan, but he still remembers vividly the destruction of that day, as well as the fear of not knowing whether a family member had survived it.
Sakuma, an AFS foreign exchange student who is attending Plymouth High School this year, spoke about his experience on Tuesday, March 11, the anniversary of the disaster, before a crowd of about 75 students and community members.
Clare Sedlacek, Plymouth High School AFS chapter representative, said Sakuma approached her about hosting the presentation, saying he felt motivated to share his experience as a way of saying "thank you" to America for some of the relief efforts the country provided in the disaster's aftermath.
"He's a kid who takes opportunities and makes the most out of them," Sedlacek said. "I think he really wanted to get to the fact of the matter that there was a lot of help that came their way and he was touched by it very closely."
Sakuma was 13 when three earthquakes shook Japan, one of them triggering a tsunami. Together, the natural disasters left nearly 19,000 people dead, destroyed coastal communities and ignited a nuclear accident.
Sakuma's hometown of Kashima was one of the most heavily damaged cities.
He was at school when the disaster happened. Because his school was located well away from the coast and on elevated ground, Sakuma said he and his classmates remained safe from the tsunami.
He said he remembers heading outside onto the soccer fields with his classmates to seek safety after the first earthquake hit.
It was there that he saw the 300-foot-high plumes of smoke and a blaze of fire from steel works factories along the coast, which is where his father works. Sakuma said he later found out that a gas tank had exploded as a result of the earthquake, causing a massive fire to spread throughout the buildings.
"You could see the fire from two miles away," Sakuma said. "I thought he (my dad) would be dead."
It wasn't until about four hours later that Sakuma learned his father was alive. His mother and brother were unharmed as well.
"It felt like a long time," Sakuma said. "We couldn't call because the phone lines (were) crashed."
One person in Sakuma's home town was killed, Sakuma said. The 6,000 workers who were in the steel works factories all survived.
Three years after the disaster, the country - as well as Sakuma's hometown - continues to rebuild, however. More than 270,000 people remain displaced from their homes, according to news reports.
Sakuma said his school resumed after a month, but it took other businesses or organizations longer. Roads started getting fixed two months later; his father's workplace didn't resume until three months after; and some stores didn't reopen for six months, he said.
What happened that day is still hard for some to face, said Sakuma.
"It is not as emotional for me as my friend," Sakuma said. "My friend couldn't say anything about (the) tsunami or earthquake."
After the natural disasters, Sakuma said he saw at his mom's city office the mineral water, food and supplies that came from the U.S. and around the world to aid people in need. His friend also met a member of the U.S. Navy who helped with rescue and relief efforts.
"I thought (that) is so neat," Sakuma said. "I thought I could go to the United States someday and say 'thank you' for what was done."
- Reach Kali Thiel at 920-453-5134.
]]></text></news-item>