<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-5591-JBVM-Y1TR"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Mum wrote letters, unaware The Sentinel is running a of son's death; The Sentinel is running a series of articles to commemorate the 100th anniversary of the First World War. Richard Ault tells the moving story of one family's desperate attempt to get news to the frontline</title><source>The Sentinel (Stoke)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A MOTHER wrote to her son to ask him to be a pall-bearer after his best friend's body was recovered from a mining disaster - unaware he had already been killed in the trenches of France.
Private John William Haywood had sent a postcard home on October 19, 1918.
He was killed and buried where he fell just four days later. He was 27 years old.
Two days after John's death, his note reached the family home at Scott Hay Road, Alsagers Bank.
John's father John and stepmother Mary Ann Haywood, along with his nine younger brothers and sisters, were all relieved to hear from him.
Just a few nights before receiving the card, Mary Ann had dreamt John was back on the frontline, facing death in the trenches.
Her fears allayed, Mary Ann immediately wrote back expressing relief. But she also had her own tragic news to pass on to her son. The body of one of her son's best friends, Dan Jones, had been recovered from Minnie Pit, after he had died in the mining disaster of January 12, 1918.
Mary Ann told John that Dan's mother wanted him to be a pall-bearer at the funeral, blissfully unaware that John, too, was dead.
When Ann didn't receive a reply from her son, she wrote again, this time expressing her worry for him and her hope that the war would soon be over and he could return home safely.
Her letters were returned to her - along with a dreaded telegram informing her that John had been killed.
John's niece Ann Platt, aged 70, from Bignall End, said: "All her letters were returned. I didn't know they existed until my mother died and I cleared her house. Everything was in a box.
"I know John was very well loved, they were a very close family and they all loved John.
"He was the only one who served in the First World War.
"Mary Ann was his stepmother, but she treated all 10 of the children like they were her own. She loved him like a son.
"The whole family felt the loss all their lives."
In the first letter, sent on October 26, 1918 - the day after the family had heard word from John - Mary Ann wrote: "We are so pleased to hear from you. I was beginning to feel worried for you.
"I thought you must be up the line again, I dreamt you was up, but I hope you are down again for a rest.
"They have got poor Dan Jones out of the Minnie Pit. They are going to bury him on 29th October.
"Mrs Jones wishes you was over as you could carry him to his grave, but we shall all have to make the best of it I suppose. We are so pleased they have got him for burial.
"I thought you would like to know about poor Dan, and Mrs Jones wishes me to send you word.
"I have sent for a nice bunch of flowers for his grave as that is the only thing we can do for him, and I know you will be pleased to hear about him, as we shall know where he lies and can go down the church, better than the Minnie Pit. "I wish all the poor lads was up. I close my letter with just love from father, mother, sisters, brothers and all at home. "Goodnight with love and good luck to you. Goodnight and may God bless you and keep you safe from all harm. Goodnight, mother xxxxxxxxxxx."
Dan Jones was one of 155 miners killed in North Staffordshire's worst mining disaster at Minnie Pit, Halmerend, by an underground explosion. The tragedy is considered by many to be the darkest day in the history of North Staffordshire, regardless of the devastation that happened to the region's men folk during the Great War. Virtually every household in the close-knit mining communities surrounding the Halmerend pit lost a loved one.
Mrs Platt said: "My grandmother said nearly every house in Alsagers Bank had lost someone. The curtains were drawn for weeks.
"It must have been terrible, so many young lads killed."
Mrs Platt's husband, Stuart, aged 72, said: "I went to watch the Minnie Pit being capped. It was amazing to see.
"But what a terrible tragedy." Mary Ann's next letter was sent on November 1, 1918, just 10 days before Armistice Day. By now the family were racked with worry, but hopeful that the war would soon be over and John could come home.
She wrote: "Just a few lines to you, hoping it finds you in good health. We have been expecting a letter from you for the last few weeks and none has come up to the time of writing this letter. "The last field card which you sent home was sent on the 19th of October, and we have not heard anything from you since and it is troubling us at home. "Above all, we do not know whether you are receiving our letters or not, because we are sending one or two every week and I may tell you that we had a letter returned last week, which I wrote to you on the 11th of September.
"In it, we were telling you about the photo which you sent us and I may tell you that Smoker has come home and has got dressed in his civvies again.
"I think that if you have a bit of good luck, we think that you won't be long as it looks as if the war is nearly over as they are all giving in now, only the old German and he will do, whether he wants to or not."
John served with the 10th battalion of the Essex Regiment. At the time of his death, October 23, 1918, the regiment was engaged in the Battle of the Selle, which started on October 17 and ended on October 26, fought during what is known as The Last Hundred Days of World War I. After defeat at the Battle of Cambrai, the German Army had taken up position to the east of the Selle River.
Following a six-day halt for preparations and artillery bombardments, Allied troops attacked at 5.20am on Thursday, October 17, using tanks to support the infantry.
Advances were made by both the British and French armies before a two-day pause, allowing the Allied troops to bring up heavy artillery.
On October 23 - the day John died - the attack was renewed with fierce fighting as the Germans were driven back and forced into retreat.
Perhaps John was killed during that assault.
What is known is that John was buried on or near the battlefield, but was exhumed in 1920 when he was reburied at Highland Cemetery in Le Cateau, France.
Mr Platt, aged 72, said: "When you read the letters, you think what were the conditions like that Mary Ann was writing in, perhaps sat at the window.
"It makes you think what life must have been like in the trenches as well, far from home."
'The bodies of a father and son lay clasped in each other's arms where they had fallen' THE late mining historian Fred Leigh wrote a piece looking back at North Staffordshire's worst pit disaster. Here, we reprint his piece from 1997.
EARLY on a snowy Saturday morning in 1918, about 250 miners descended the Minnie Pit at Halmerend. In the village the womenfolk were preparing for an old folks' party in the Primitive Methodist Chapel that evening.
But within a few hours, the festive decorations were taken down and the chapel became a makeshift mortuary. There, the women laid out the first mangled bodies from the pit, following a disaster which claimed the lives of 156 men and boys, including one of the rescuers.
The Minnie Pit was part of the Podmore Colliery, which included a sister shaft, the Podmore, and an old drift mine known as the Bullhurst Rearer, or Bursted Onion. Minnie was the name of a former owner's daughter. The colliery worked the rich Banbury and Bullhurst seams.
Ominously, the Minnie already had a reputation for being a jinx pit, with previous fatalities and frequent accidents.
The disaster happened without warning. At 9.45 the colliery manager, Joseph Smith, heard shouts outside his office. He looked through the window and saw smoke, dust and soot pouring out of the Podmore shaft and the fan chimney. He knew right away that an explosion had occurred down below. After frantic telephone calls with men at the pit bottom, the manager alerted teams to mount a major rescue operation. The crisis had begun.
While Mr Smith organised the rescue operations on the surface, the under-manager, Mr Weaver, went down the shaft to investigate. He found a state of utter confusion and everything covered in thick black dust, which affected breathing and made the eyes smart.
No-one seemed to know what had happened, but all the signs were that there had been a methane gas explosion. When Weaver reached the top of the Banbury Dip, his worst fears were confirmed.
Sections of the dip had collapsed, ventilation doors had been smashed and men were lying dead in the darkness. There was also a lot of poisonous gas in the air. The first rescue team to go into the pit was the Minnie's own brigade. They were told to repair the broken doors so that air could circulate again and allow a full-scale rescue operation to be mounted.
The team returned to the surface after an hour, bringing with them about a dozen survivors who were joyfully received by relatives. The captain of the rescue team reported that the explosion had "ripped the guts out of the Banbury and Bullhurst seams". He was pessimistic about finding many more survivors, and distressing scenes soon followed at the pithead as the first body, that of a 16-year-old boy, was brought to the surface around 1.30pm.
Even then, however, a colliery fireman named Charles Greatbatch was leading a party of 47 men and boys to safety up the steep grades of the Bullhurst Rearers towards the old Bursted Onion drift.
The explosion had cut these men off from the pit bottom and the rest of the mine. But Greatbatch ensured their survival by opening two ventilation doors to short-circuit the foul air, giving them long enough to climb out into the daylight up the Rearers. Other survivors emerged from the pit to tell of seeing workmates killed instantly in the blast. Many other victims died after being overcome by the deadly gases.
As the black smoke continued to hang over the pithead there were heart-rending scenes among the families waiting in the terribly cold weather to learn the fate of loves ones, some no more than lads.
Rescue teams worked in relays during the night, carrying out the difficult task of repairing the ventilation in an effort to reach the entombed men.
But it was slow work in such dangerous conditions. The men were held up by roof falls and they had to wear breathing apparatus in the poisonous atmosphere.
One rescuer was overcome and had to be helped out of the pit. Nevertheless, their untiring efforts took the gallant band about 1,000 yards 'inbye' from the pit bottom.
On the Monday morning, the notorious Minnie Pit claimed yet another victim when the captain of the Birchenwood Colliery rescue team, Hugh Doorbar, lost his life tragically through faulty breathing apparatus. The rescue teams continued to locate bodies, some of them in the most poignant circumstances. The bodies of George and Jabez Burgess, father and son, lay clasped in each other's arms where they had fallen. Samuel Richardson, an organist and choirmaster, was found with his bible.
A week after the explosion it was believed that 127 bodies still remained to be recovered. By the end of February the 'gobstink' in the pit was so bad that operations were suspended because of fears of another explosion.
In January and February 1918, funerals became almost an everyday occurrence in Halmerend and surrounding villages. Sixty-one victims were buried in this period immediately after the tragedy.
But it was not until halfway through the following year that the grim job of recovering all the dead was completed. The last body was brought to the surface on August 19, 1919, 20 months after the disaster.
On August 31, 1919, a memorial service held in Audley churchyard was attended by a congregation of 3,000.
The final death toll included 20 boys aged 14, a further 13 aged 15, and 11 aged 16. The Holland family of Shraley Brook lost four sons, and the Warhams of Alsagers Bank lost three. A huge campaign was launched to raise funds for the relief of the bereaved families. Appeals were set up by the mayors of Stoke-on-Trent and Newcastle, and special performances were staged at local theatres. A public inquiry into the disaster concluded that the explosion was probably caused by a defective safety lamp, although the inspector didn't rule out the possibility of sparks from falling stone igniting the gas.
The management were cleared of any negligence, but the report singled out the inadequate way the firemen's duties were undertaken. The lack of a system for removing coal dust was officially acknowledged as contributing to the scale of the explosion.
And although the inquiry made recommendations for improvements in the light of the Minnie Pit Disaster, many people were not satisfied that justice had been done.
The last field card which you sent home was sent on the 19th of October and we have not heard anything from you since, and it is troubling us at home.... '
]]></text></news-item>