<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S1XP"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Sierra Club Opposes CCS Coal Utility EPA Cites In Climate NSPS Defense</title><source>Carbon Control News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Sierra Club is opposing a pending coal-fired power plant in Mississippi that will be among the first to use carbon capture and sequestration (CCS) on a large scale, even though the group backs EPA's proposed utility climate rule that justifies a CCS mandate for new coal plants based in part on the Mississippi plant -- a position critics say is "tortured."
In response, a source with the Sierra Club headquarters says the group's opposition to Southern Company's almost-complete Kemper coal utility in Mississippi "is independent of the CCS question. . . . We support CCS as a requirement for construction of new coal-fired power plants. . . . When we talk about whether we support a plant, we look at the individual situation," the source says, noting that few coal plants escape opposition from environmental groups.
But one industry source says, "An organization that is opposed to all coal plants may not really be in favor of carbon capture. . . . Of course the Sierra Club has a tortured position. They're against coal."
The group's backing of CCS as a mandate for newly constructed coal plants in EPA's pending carbon dioxide (CO2) new source performance standard (NSPS) would "presume they would advocate the use of fossil fuels, and Sierra Club doesn't. I assume at some point their donor base points that out to them," the source says.
A source with environmental group Clean Air Task Force (CATF) also questions Sierra Club's battle against the Kemper facility, saying that the opposition appears to focus more on the capital costs and its impact on electricity rates, rather than more typical concerns about the plant's environmental impacts.
The fight over the Kemper plant highlights several ongoing key issues in the debate over regulating the utility sector's CO2 emissions: the scope of the industry's emissions, the need to promote power sector projects to deploy CCS technology, and hurdles to completing construction of utilities with CCS.
The fate of CCS projects at utilities is central to EPA's pending NSPS for future power plants, which would require partial CCS at new coal-fired plants. Critics of the proposed rule say this represents a "war on coal" that would effectively ban new coal utility construction because CCS is cost-prohibitive and not in wide use.
EPA has defended the CCS mandate, which is based in part on Kemper and a handful of other pending coal utility CCS projects as showing it is viable for new sources. The rule cites other CCS projects, including Summit Power's Texas Clean Energy Project -- though that may be in doubt after its power purchase agreement expired in January.
CCS Project
Southern Company, which is developing the 582-megawatt Kemper County Energy Facility that will capture 65 percent of its CO2, has urged EPA not to rely on the plant to support its proposed CCS mandate. The project has received significant funding from the Department of Energy (DOE), and opponents of the NSPS claim a 2005 energy law prohibits EPA from citing DOE-funded projects to justify CCS regulatory mandates, though EPA in a recent data notice rejected that claim.
The agency first proposed the climate NSPS in 2012 but in response to comments withdrew it and re-proposed it in January. During the lag time, EPA increased its reliance on Kemper, noting in the new proposal that since April 2012 the project has made "significant progress" and is now "over 75 percent complete."
Sierra Club backs EPA's NSPS and its CCS mandate, even as it pursues a challenge to the Kemper facility, prompting criticisms from other environmentalists and industry sources for a "tortured" position.
Sierra Club's Mississippi chapter has been working since 2009 to defeat Kemper, citing its capital costs of more than $5 billion, the impact on ratepayers, and concerns about non-GHG emissions from the plant.
But the source with the CATF -- a vocal supporter of both CCS and Kemper -- says Sierra Club appears to be opposing the project for the wrong reasons, such as costs rather than environmental impacts. The source "is prepared to concede that this is an expensive plant," because with $5 billion in costs and overruns it is the most expensive capital project ever undertaken in the state of Mississippi. However, the source believes the project is vital to advancing CCS, "a technology that is essential to avoiding the worst aspects of climate change."
Many of Sierra Club's attacks on Kemper "focus exclusively on costs and not on the environment. . . . Last I checked that wasn't the central focus of the Sierra Club's mission: saving ratepayer money in Mississippi," the source says.
The industry source concurs with that response, saying, "This is the only time in the history of the planet that Sierra Club has demonstrated any concern with what the ratepayers need to pay. To say it is a smokescreen is way too kind. They have never complained about the rate impact of a wind farm."
However, the Congressional Research Service in a Feb. 10 report on DOE-funded CCS projects notes, "Cost overruns at the Kemper plant, however, have raised questions over the relative value of environmental benefits due to CCS technology compared to construction costs of the facility and its effect on ratepayers."
Sources also point out that Sierra Club's position is somewhat the inverse to Kemper's developer, Southern Company, which in public statements last fall urged EPA not to cite it as a basis for the NSPS rule. For example, Southern Company's gasification manager, Randall Rush, called Kemper a "specific project in a specific place that meets the needs of the state of Mississippi. . . . It doesn't seem to make any sense to me to be a basis for an environmental standard on a national basis."
EPA Proposal
In order to mandate CCS in the NSPS rule being developed under section 111(b) of the Clean Air Act, EPA must show that the technology is commercially available and adequately demonstrated. It also must show that it is not relying solely on Kemper and the other CCS projects it cites in the proposal because they are receiving DOE funding.
In the proposal, EPA cites Kemper as one of the main examples, and lauds its progress, saying, "Performance testing is expected to commence in late 2013 and the facility is expected to be fully operational in 2014."
The Kemper County energy facility will use Southern Company's Transport Integrated Gasification (TRIG) technology, developed with significant DOE funding that will allow it to gasify lower grade lignite coal and then capture the carbon and pipe it to nearby oil fields. GHG and criteria emissions from the plant will be comparable to a natural gas facility.
A second industry source -- who says EPA should not rely on Kemper and other DOE-funded projects to justify he NSPS -- says these projects "fall short of what EPA needs to show for CCS to be adequately demonstrated," but they are nonetheless important for the further development of CCS technologies. "CCS needs more public-private partnerships focused on advancing the technology and more support and incentives for new projects. CCS just isn't ready to respond to a regulatory mandate from EPA, and the mandate alone won't make it ready."
Southern Company in a Feb. 26 statement to Inside EPA said, "The proposed standards for new coal-fired power plants appear to be based on CCS and the anticipated performance of the Kemper County energy facility." But the company added that, "Because the unique characteristics that make the project the right choice for Mississippi cannot be consistently replicated on a national level, the Kemper county energy facility should not serve as a primary basis for new emissions standards impacting all new coal-fired power plants."
The CATF source says the company's and Sierra Club's positions on Kemper and the NSPS "are useful in the broader debate" over the viability of CCS. "Southern is saying we built this plant, and it's great, but it doesn't provide that CCS is viable" in the EPA rule. "Then Sierra Club opposes the plant because they think it's horrible but they think the rule is great. . . . We think it should be built and we think including CCS in the NSPS is viable."
But the Sierra Club headquarters source disagrees, saying, "We evaluate power plant proposals on a plant-by-plant basis in conjunction with local chapters. And a decision was made that we did not support the Kemper proposal. We are not opposing it because it's CCS and we obviously are willing to oppose plants that include CCS as a technology."
The group also believes Kemper serves as proof that it is "reasonable for EPA to conclude it is technologically possible to" include CCS in the NSPS, the source says. But is it also "important to point out that Kemper is not a normal CCS plant. They are trying to prove their own gasification technology," for one.
Further, the group points out, the plant has no regulatory requirement to actually capture any of its carbon emissions if the CCS does not work or other problems occur, as consulting firm Element VI noted in an analysis last year.
Environmentalists' Concerns
A source with Sierra Club's Mississippi chapter details several environmental problems with the plant, including that the particulate matter and mercury controls are not as stringent as they could be, and that it includes a 45-square-mile lignite strip mine. Further, the facility's certificate of need is again before the state supreme court; the state has issued questionable bonds to help finance the project; and residents' taxes have increased, the source says.
"This has definitely been clouded with what I would consider to be a lot of eyebrow-raising events," the source says, the upshot of which shows that Kemper is "dirty, it's expensive and it's unnecessary." The source alleges Kemper is not about CCS but rather a way for the company to win DOE financing for its TRIG technology. Because Mississippi is a regulated state, "For every dollar they spend, they get to collect a 10 to 12 percent rate of return by law."
The $5.25 billion in costs for the project will be most keenly felt by its 189,000 customers in one of the poorest states in the country, many of whom live on fixed incomes, the source adds.
But the second industry source stresses the importance of Kemper as "the world's only coal plant of any meaningful size with CCS that's currently under construction," the source says. "Coal use is growing around the world, particularly in Asia, and it's quite possible that if you don't have projects like Kemper today, then all this overseas coal gets built in the years ahead without CCS and, as a result, without any constraint on their CO2 emissions."
This source faults Sierra Club's Kemper opposition as "very clear in terms of what they don't like but not clear in terms of what they do. You might think you can just get rid of coal, but a quick look around the world shows coal use going up, no matter what happens in the United States. This is why other environmental groups have recognized CCS as a vital part of any effort to address climate change. Sierra Club is basically on its own." --Dawn Reeves (dreeves@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>