<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-5151-JBF5-T2M0"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Royal Commission into the Home Insulation Program: Bureaucrats given 'two days' to plan national scheme</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Two people were given two days to plan the Rudd government's national home insulation scheme, a senior bureaucrat has told the royal commission into the program.
The Federal Environment Department's assistant secretary, Mary Wiley-Smith, was the first witness to give evidence in Brisbane at the public hearing into whether the former Labor government failed to heed safety warnings before the deaths of four workers in 2009 and 2010.
Ms Wiley-Smith told the hearing she and a colleague were given two days to plan and cost the scheme, which aimed to insulate more than 2 million homes.
She told the court she got a call from the Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet after 5pm on the Friday of the 2009 Australia Day weekend and was told she and another colleague had until Monday to have the details ready, including the risks involved.
They were ordered not to discuss the scheme with colleagues or industry members, she said.
Ms Wiley-Smith told the court she expressed concerns to the Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet about not being able to contact industry representatives because it left questions about how the boom-and-bust scheme would affect the existing insulations installers and manufacturers.
She told the hearing she could not recall when she, and others involved in planning the scheme, discussed three similar deaths that occurred in New Zealand in 2007.
Ms Wiley-Smith said they recommended the program be implemented over five years, but the government opted to attempt implementation in two.
Cabinet documents dominate first session of inquiry
Federal cabinet documents relating to the home insulation scheme dominated the opening discussions at the royal commission hearings.
The Coalition Government provided every cabinet document relating to the insulation scheme to the commission, including cabinet notebooks and letters between former prime minister Kevin Rudd and his then-environment minister Peter Garrett.
Cabinet documents are usually kept under wraps for up to 30 years.
Tom Howe QC, representing the Commonwealth, argued today the documents should be suppressed, saying there would be "no information barrier" to the material but "ventilation" of it was another matter.
Commissioner Ian Hanger QC requested an affidavit from the Commonwealth by Thursday, before he ruled on the request.
The hearing heard that Mr Rudd, Mr Garrett, whose department managed the scheme, and former employment participation minister Mark Arbib would be called to give evidence.
The home insulation program was set up in 2009 by Mr Rudd and Mr Garrett to help ward off the effects of the global financial crisis by paying rebates to homeowners or installers of roof insulation.
During the roll-out of the $2.5 billion scheme, four men died and hundreds of house fires broke out, many of them in ceilings where foil insulation had been incorrectly installed.
Mr Hanger said he would investigate whether the deaths of the insulation installers, in Queensland and New South Wales in 2009 and 2010, could have been prevented.
Former and current federal department chiefs and former ministerial advisers were also named on a proposed witness list of 20 people for the first three weeks of what is expected to be five weeks of hearings.
Among them are now retired Environment Department head Robyn Kruk and former Commonwealth coordinator-general, now Infrastructure Department chief Mike Mrdak.
Another former Labor prime minister, Julia Gillard, was also asked to provide documents, and it is believed other senior figures have been contacted by the commission, including current Opposition frontbencher Penny Wong.
Counsel Assisting the Commission, Keith Wilson QC said more than 32,000 documents had been lodged, and 72 interviews conducted, including two with unnamed former federal MPs.
Mr Wilson argued there was a public interest in exposing the documents to scrutiny, which was heightened by the deaths of four workers.
He said the documents were historical and did not relate to any current political controversy or national security.
Focus on whether insulation scheme risks were given to Labor
The Coalition Government established the Royal Commission into the Home Insulation Program in December and charged it with finding out whether the former Labor government was given any advice, warnings or recommendations about the program.
The commission is set to investigate how advice, warnings and recommendations were identified, assessed and managed.
Labor leader Bill Shorten said his party supported any measures aimed at improving workplace safety, but pointed out there had already been several inquiries into the issue.
"There's already been a fair bit of work done there," he said.
"The tragedy is that four young men died.
"When it comes to workplace safety, we don't need politics, and everyone should cooperate with improving workplace safety."
Lawyer Bill Potts is representing the family of Rueben Barnes, who was 16 when he was electrocuted at a home near Rockhampton in central Queensland in 2009.
"It is expected that the royal commission will hear evidence that both industry groups and the experts in this area raised at an early stage safety issues, both with the installation process and the training that was actually being given to the installers," he told AM.
"The question is when those warnings were made and why weren't they heeded."
Mitchell Sweeney was one of the four people killed.
His family's lawyer Peter Koutsoukis spoke outside the hearing.
"Their overall impression is that the scheme was certainly rushed in its early implementation and there was inadequate assessment of the risks," Mr Koutsoukis said.
Kevin Fuller's son Matthew was electrocuted while installing foil insulation in a home south of Brisbane.
Late this afternoon, Mr Fuller said today's hearing was a good start to exposing the scheme's problems.
"As you would all appreciate, today is an extremely hard day in one, but a good day in another, that at least we now have a length of time and a process for the whole truth to come out," he said.
"So we support everything the commission and the commissioner's doing, but it's miles too early, as you all know, in the first hearing and not even finished one witness yet."
A recent report by Queensland Coroner Michael Barnes into the deaths of three of the workers found the home insulation scheme was rolled out too quickly with inadequate safeguards.
That report prompted an apology from Mr Rudd to the families of the workers.
Mr Potts says the royal commission will have a broader scope to investigate the issue.
"What was not explored by the inquest was the upper level government findings and the decision making process and that's what the Royal Commission will focus on," he said.
]]></text></news-item>