<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-XP91-F03R-N197"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Malaysian Airline Pilot May Have Had Radical Islamist Agenda</title><source>The Shark Tank</source><author>Javier Manjarres</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 17, 2014 (The Shark Tank:http://www.shark-tank.net Delivered by Newstex) The Malaysian Prime Minister is now taking the position that U.S. authorities have take, calling the disappearance of Malaysian Airlines Flight 370 a 'deliberate' criminal act.
The captain of Flight 370, Zaharie Ahmad Shah, was a devout supporter of the Malaysian opposition leader Answar Ibrahimm, who was sentenced to jail only couple hours before the flight took off from Kuala Lumpur to Bejing. Authorities are now focused [1]on crew after it was learned that the planes signaling system was turned off before the pilot made his last verbal communication with ground control, and before the plane to a sharp turn to the west. Even more troubling is that the planes banking to west was already pre-programmed into the on-board computer. Here is Pilot Shah wearing a 'Democracy is Dead' t-shirt? http://www.shark-tank.com/2014/03/17/malaysian-airline-pilot-may-have-had-radical-islamist-agenda/tshirt/ Was this an isolated criminal act, or a broader Jihadist act of terror? Shah's deep devotion for Ibahimm could have terror implications, as Ibrahimm's U.S.-based International Institute for Islamic Thought, or IIIT, has direct ties to the radical Islamic Muslim Brotherhood organization.  IIIT has come under fire for their connections with terrorist organizations. In 2002, Anwar Ibrahim's IIIT was included in a lawsuit by victims of 9/11 seeking damages from organizations linked to 'rendering material support to radical Islamism.' In 2003, US government prosecutors 'submitted court documents detailing financial support (PDF) from the IIIT for convicted Palestinian Islamic Jihad fundraiser Sami al-Arian.' They also found that Taha Jaber al-Alwani, the president of IIIT had once stated via a fatwa that 'jihad is the only way to liberate Palestine.' A US Customs official said that the government is also looking into the possibility that IIIT was involved in 'terrorism-related money laundering activities'.-Sarewak Report[2] http://api.lanistaads.com/ServeAd?AdSize=300SiteID=Shark-TankZone=BTF[3] The post Malaysian Airline Pilot May Have Had Radical Islamist Agenda[4] appeared first on The Shark Tank[5]. [1]: http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/03/17/us-malaysiaairlines-flight-idUSBREA2701720140317 [2]: http://sarawakreport.org/arch/newledger/2011/01/muslim-brotherhoods-terrorist-money-flowing-to-anwar-ibrahim/index.html [3]: http://api.lanistaads.com/ServeAd?AdSize=300SiteID=Shark-TankZone=BTF [4]: http://www.shark-tank.com/2014/03/17/malaysian-airline-pilot-may-have-had-radical-islamist-agenda/ [5]: http://www.shark-tank.com

]]></text></news-item>