<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S1YH"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Novel Pact Requiring Gas Plant GHG Cuts, Closure Faces EAB Challenge</title><source>Clean Energy Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Massachusetts residents have filed an EPA Environmental Appeals Board (EAB) challenge over an air permit for a proposed natural gas plant in the state as inadequate, posing a new hurdle to the plant involved in a novel legal pact with environmentalists that imposes first-time greenhouse gas (GHG) reduction requirements and a 2050 closure date.
The EAB suit filed March 3 starts a fresh legal battle over Footprint Power's proposed 630-megawatt plant in Salem, MA. The developer previously reached a settlement with environmental group Conservation Law Foundation (CLF) that required annual GHG reduction requirements and the eventual shutdown date. After the state's Energy Facilities Siting Board (EFSB) approved the pact, CLF dropped a pending suit over the plant.
But residents living near the plant who oppose the facility filed their EAB challenge over the Clean Air Act prevention of significant deterioration (PSD) permit for the plant issued by the Massachusetts Department of Environmental Protection (DEP), seeking more time to detail their complaints with the non-GHG limits in the air permit, according to their opening filing with EAB, In the matter of: Footprint Power Salem Harbor Development.
One industry source notes, "With that old adage, 'You can't please all of the people all of the time,' please note these issues that the residents of Salem and other nearby towns raised" in their new challenge.
The EAB filing says the residents are concerned over carbon monoxide (CO) and volatile organic compounds (VOCs) from the plant. It also questions the adequacy of regional monitoring and compliance with EPA's national ambient air quality standards (NAAQS).
The filing asks EAB to allow the residents an additional two weeks to more specifically explain the PSD permit concerns, noting that the settlement between CLF and Footprint Power came in the midst of the 30-day time frame to appeal the air permit.
Under the terms of that legal agreement, CLF is no longer able to represent the residents, because Footprint Power insisted on that condition as part of the settlement, according to the EAB petition. The filing also notes that Footprint Power opposes the two-week extension and that DEP did not respond before the document was filed with EAB.
EAB granted the two-week extension in a March 6 order, noting that it "will benefit from affording petitioners additional time . . . to fully present their arguments" and that the board has discretion to deviate from its rules and procedures.
Footprint's Opposition
But Footprint filed a formal opposition March 7 urging the board to reject the request. "By their own admission, the petitioners have failed to comply with the substantive requirements for a petition. Instead, petitioners have chosen to file a 'summary petition' and to seek a two-week extension in order to file a fully compliant petition. . . . The regulations simply do not allow this type of filing."
The need for a delay, according to the petitioners, was their loss of the legal representation of CLF after the group settled the EFSB case with the company. "Until very recently, petitioners were represented by a prominent Boston non-profit organization known as the [CLF]. On Feb. 18, 2014 -- more than halfway through the 30-day period for prosecuting an appeal -- CLF informed petitioners that it had settled with Footprint, and that by the terms of the settlement CLF was unable to provide any further assistance to petitioners," the filing says.
The petitioners hired a new lawyer, Matthew Pawa, to pursue their claims on March 1, two days before the EAB deadline for challenging the PSD permit.
The filing urges EAB to grant the extension because the petitioners "who are ordinary homeowners with day jobs were left without legal assistance." It adds that "the public interest in a reasoned appellate decision supports granting this motion. This is a significant project that has generated a complicated record -- a record that DEP changed significantly at the last minute" in the final permit.
However, the Footprint opposition noted that the fact that CLF settled with the company does "not justify the Petitioners delayed hiring of an attorney to represent them in a potential appeal of the PSD permit."
The EAB appeal will focus on what petitioners call significant changes made to the permit after the public comment period, including the elimination of CO limits entirely; allowing the use of a regional air monitor nearly six miles away to determine preconstruction air quality versus site-specific preconstruction monitoring; excluding "de minimus" sources from evaluation of potential NAAQS violations; and failing to limit VOCs.
A CLF source says that the group "did not provide legal representation to any person or party in this matter other than CLF" and denies that the residents are "former" CLF clients. "We emphasize with their concerns" about the non-GHG issues in the permit, the source adds.
Pawa did not respond to a request for comment.
'Baseless' Objections
Scott Silverstein, president of Footprint Power tells Inside EPA in a March 7 statement, "We are disappointed by this last-minute appeal. For four years, we have worked with neighbors, activists, and respected advocacy groups to gather support and understanding for our project. We are confident that our project's immense benefits to energy reliability and the environment will outweigh the baseless objections of these four people."
CLF is touting the legal settlement as one that could be a "groundbreaking" model to force GHG reductions at other gas utilities. The settlement, inked Feb. 18, was approved by the state's EFSB Feb. 20 and requires the plant to achieve annual GHG reductions and ultimately shut down the facility in 2050.
CLF in a Feb. 18 statement said the settlement "reaffirms that natural gas and other fossil fuel projects must comply with state climate mandates, and has important implications for similar projects in the region and nationally."
In response to the settlement, CLF dropped its suit over EFSB's approval of the plant as flawed because it was made without the board determining whether the plant complies with the state's 2008 Global Warming Solutions Act, which requires GHG emission cuts in the state of 80 percent by 2050.
The Footprint Power facility is the first gas plant to go through the approval process since the state enacted the GWSA, so the settlement could set a precedent for other facilities in the state and elsewhere. "The settlement ensures that, for the first time ever, a proposed natural gas-fired plant must comply with conditions aimed at reducing [GHGs] and over-reliance on fossil fuels," CLF said in the statement.
The pact also requires Footprint Power to ask DEP for modifications to incorporate the terms of the agreement into the facility's final comprehensive plan approval, as well as add the agreement as an appendix to its Clean Air Act Title V operating permit application so that it will become part of federally enforceable emission limits at the plant.
Massachusetts DEP finalized the facility's PSD construction air permit last month. CLF in its comments on the draft PSD permit asked that the best available control technology analysis reflect compliance with the GWSA. But the state rejected those comments as "beyond the scope" of the PSD permit. It is that PSD permit that the residents are seeking to challenge before EPA's EAB. -- Dawn Reeves (dreeves@iwpnews.com)
03-12-2014
]]></text></news-item>