<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-5591-JBVM-Y1JD"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Police chief's warning has to be seen as wake-up call; We say</title><source>The Plymouth Herald</source><author></author><text><![CDATA["THE biscuit tin is empty - there is no more". It's a stark analogy especially when used to describe the state of our police force - and particularly so when the words come from the mouth of the man in charge.
But Devon & Cornwall's Chief Constable Shaun Sawyer has spoken out today, laying on the line the state of his depleted resources following years of budget cuts.
Mr Sawyer is not the first police chief to speak in this way - and he probably won't be the last.
But his words are not hollow. He outlines a situation where he must choose between providing a purely responsive 999 police operation and the kind of community service which most of us still want and expect.
This isn't simply a matter of having a reassuring police presence on the streets. It is having officers available to be the eyes and ears of complex communities which face a range of issues from anti-social behaviour to pavement parking, drug abuse to shoplifting.
Mr Sawyer predicts a 20-year gradual decline in crime will soon be reversed with the effect kicking in within a matter of months.
There will doubtless be critics who believe there are unexplored areas of police efficiency which could be plugged to help make up the budget shortfall.
But there comes a point at which the cake can no longer be sliced.
Mr Sawyer makes a grim warning and it is a wake-up call to us all.
He urges greater partnership working and communities taking more responsibility for themselves.
It is right that we expect and demand a proper police service - but it would also be wise to consider how and where we can effectively help Mr Sawyer fill the gaps in community policing and crime prevention. ¦ DEALING with groups of tombstoners on the Hoe takes up a lot of police time and effort.
Fears for the safety of youngsters and complaints about anti-social behaviour are frequently responded to. So a dispersal order covering the Hoe - and extending 50 metres into the sea - is a good way for the police to get in first.
While it might not stop youngsters taking silly risks, it will allow the police to send troublesome youths home - and make the Hoe a far more pleasant place for residents and visitors to enjoy on a sunny day.
]]></text></news-item>