<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S211"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Faulting Data, Grace Urges EPA To Drop Libby Asbestos Risk Analysis</title><source>Superfund Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Attorneys for bankrupt mining company W.R. Grace have filed a Data Quality Act (DQA) petition urging EPA to drop its precedent-setting effort to assess the risks posed by Libby amphibole asbestos (LAA), saying the agency's draft analysis set a noncancer risk value that is so strict it would force cleanup below naturally occurring levels.
The company filed a Feb. 26 petition charging that the agency's draft Integrated Risk Information System (IRIS) assessment uses an inappropriate nonadverse health endpoint for its noncancer risk values and violated a number of quality standards set by the DQA. Relevant documents are available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID:2463778)
"Given the pervasive nature of these deficiencies that call into question the scientific validity of the Draft Assessment, and the likely significant impact on public and private resources if the Draft Assessment continues to be disseminated in this or a similar form, we request that the Draft Assessment be removed from the Agency's IRIS website and not be further disseminated or used in its current or a revised form until the fundamental shortcomings identified herein have been corrected," the petition says.
The petition could give the company a means of challenging any regulatory decisions the agency makes based on the assessment, though no court has ever ruled that such petitions are judicially reviewable or enforceable.
But the agency is not likely to drop the assessment, especially given pressure from Montana lawmakers for the agency to quickly complete it. And an agency source said recently that officials are planning to complete the assessment later this summer -- even before publication of a workplace study that industry and GOP lawmakers have urged the agency to consider.
EPA's science advisors have largely backed the endpoint that the agency selected.
Grace operated a vermiculite mine in the small town of Libby, MT, for decades, beginning in the 1960s, but the vermiculite was contaminated with a particular type of asbestos, LAA. Grace ceased mining operations in Libby in 1990, and the area became a Superfund site in 2002. Since a series of news reports publicized respiratory illnesses in workers exposed to LAA in 1999, Grace filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy in 2001, according to an EPA summary of its 2007 settlement with the company. The agency announced last month that Grace paid EPA more than $54 million "to resolve environmental liability claims pursuant to the company's bankruptcy plan of reorganization" regarding Superfund cleanup liabilities at 39 Superfund sites in 21 states.
That does not include Libby, which EPA and Grace settled in 2008. "Grace paid EPA $250 million to cash out its liability for the Libby site with the exception of the Libby Mine and contamination migrating from the mine," according to EPA's site.
EPA has since 2007 sought to assess the contaminant's risks as part of its influential IRIS program. Once finalized, the risk values in the assessment will be used as the basis for the ongoing Superfund cleanup in Libby, as well as at dozens of manufacturing facilities where the substance was processed.
Many industry officials, as well as EPA peer reviewers, have also said that the methodology the agency uses to assess LAA could also be used to assess other forms of asbestos.
In its 2011 draft of the assessment, EPA proposed a first-time noncancer reference concentration (RfC) -- the maximum amount of LAA the agency estimates can be inhaled daily over a lifetime without adverse noncancer health effects -- at 0.00001 fibers per cubic centimeter (f/cc). The background level of asbestos in United States soils is estimated to be 0.00005 f/cc.
EPA based its RfC on the presence of localized pleural thickening (LPT) and asbestosis, as observed in workers exposed to LAA in a processing plant in Marysville, OH. The agency describes LPT as growths "of fibrous tissue within the sack that surrounds the lung," and asbestosis as "an illness of progressive scarring of lung tissue."
But Grace's petition argues that LPT is not an adverse health effect, but merely a change indicating asbestos exposure. As such, LPT should not be the basis for EPA's RfC, which should be based on an adverse affect per EPA guidelines, the petition argues.
"The Draft Assessment selected LPT as 'adverse' on the basis of the assertion that it 'is an irreversible pathological change associated with constricting chest pain, dyspnea, and decreased pulmonary function.' The Draft Assessment fails to provide scientific support for these assertions because it: (a) lacks a demonstration that LPT is adverse as defined by EPA's own guidance; (b) fails to demonstrate a "causal" association between LPT and an impairment; (c) confuses LPT with other distinct conditions; (d) fails to consider important scientific literature; and (e) for the literature it did reference, fails to consider the quality of the data and studies."
The petition adds that ". . . authoritative sources view LPT as asymptomatic and not on a pathway to any functional impairment; consequently, LPT has not been shown to meet EPA's definition of "adverse" or to be upstream of an adverse effect, and cannot serve as the basis for a toxicity assessment . . ." The petition asks EPA to select another basis for the risk calculations that either meets the agency's definition of adverse, or else provide a justification of why LPT is an adverse affect.
EPA science advisors, however, largely supported EPA's use of LPT and the data EPA selected to calculate the RfC. EPA's Science Advisory Board peer reviewed the draft assessment in 2012, and generally rebuffed industry criticism of LPT and agreed with the agency that it should maintain its use. But some panelists expressed concern about the stringency of the RfC, and pressed EPA to carefully review the draft in light of analyses of other types of asbestos fibers. Among other recommendations, the advisors urged EPA to review the RfC calculation and its basis, and consider studies of other worker cohorts besides the Marysville, OH, studies to bolster the RfC.
Grace also questions EPA's modeling approaches for calculating its risk estimates, and its use of ". . .extremely small data sets, rendering the assessment incomplete and biased when calculating toxicity values . . ."
And Grace questions the utility of the draft IRIS assessment, arguing that its risk calculations will not be useful to the public and cleanup managers because the risk number is below naturally occurring background levels of LAA in soil.
"Because it is EPA's longstanding policy not to remediate sites to below background levels, the proposed values are not useful in making risk management decisions as they will subject communities to considerable, unresolved uncertainty as to whether EPA is leaving unsafe levels un-remediated," Grace's petition states.
Grace's petition goes on to argue that EPA's risk estimate is not practical because "toxicity values below background would suggest that soil disturbance in many situations may be unsafe, such as on farms and in the course of road construction. As a practical matter, if disturbance of background levels of asbestos caused LPT, with the ubiquitous presence of asbestos in soils the United States would be experiencing an epidemic of LPT. EPA has not remotely suggested that to be the case. As such, the toxicity values will not aid rational decision-making and will not be useful to risk managers or the public. To the contrary, those values, not shown by EPA to cause functional impairment at any level, may result in extensive commitment of public resources to address unfounded health concerns not predicated on empirical evidence." -- Maria Hegstad
]]></text></news-item>