<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-FK11-DXCW-D1T6"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Erdoğan ally, state bank official colluded to rig tender, says document</title><source>The Turkish Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Senior officials from state-run and private banks and a leading businessman close to the government negotiated a tender for the sale of land confiscated by the state and agreed to allow a certain company to win the public tender, according to phone transcripts leaked by an anonymous Twitter user last week.
Abdullah Tivnikli, deputy chairman of participation bank Kuveyt Türk and an investor in the construction sector, agrees with Salim Alkan, a member of the board of the state-run banks Halkbank and Ziraat Bankası, to “arrange” the winner in a tender for the sale of a piece of land in İstanbul's Pendik district -- the tender for which was finalized in November 2013 -- the recently leaked document reveals.
A transcript of separate phone conversations allegedly between top public servants and private business owners was leaked by the Twitter account "Hırsıza Oy Yok" (No votes for thieves). The transcript is believed to have come from documents collected by the investigators in a second corruption probe that was blocked by the government.
A plot of 5 million square meters, worth around $200 million, located in İstanbul's Pendik district was first owned by Turkish machinery firm Meksan. This company bought the land with loans it had received from separate creditors, the largest of these being Halkbank. Meksan later failed to repay its debt to Halkbank, and the bank seized the Pendik plot to cover the non-performing loan.
Meksan's creditors, including Halkbank, held a number of auctions to sell the land and retrieve their receivables, but to no avail. In a negotiated tender with restricted parameters, the land was finally purchased by Güven Energy, a sister company of Eksim Holding.
The Twitter account published the transcript on the website hirsizaoyyok.wordpress.com, alleging that Tivnikli and Alkan had arranged the tender for the land in Pendik. In the transcript, Alkan promises Tivnikli that the tender will be won by one of his subsidiaries. Tivnikli, a close friend of Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdoğan, is the main shareholder in Turkish company Eksim Holding, which is active in the energy, retail and construction sectors, and also has shares in a Turkish construction firm, Akabe İnşaat.
Interestingly, 40 days after he bought the land in Pendik, Tivnikli received a court order notifying him that the land he had just bought should be returned to Kemal Derinkök, from whom Meksan had bought the land in the early 1990s. Tivnikli then resorted to the Supreme Court of Appeals, and during the appeal a commission of experts found that the court's ruling to return the land to its former owner had been based on a forged document -- a development which has further complicated the issue.
The latest documents leaked by Hırsıza Oy Yok reveal another side to the matter. Tivnikli and his contacts in senior state positions -- as alleged in the leaked documents -- agreed to set the value of the land at TL 120 million in the tender. The parties first discussed the issue on Sept. 9 of last year, the document alleges. Tivnikli asked the tender board to allow his company to take the land for TL 120 million, the opening price in the tender. The parties agreed that Güven Energy would pay TL 2,000 more than the opening price and thus secure the tender, which was finalized on Nov. 30, 2013. Prime Minister Erdoğan's ever-increasing involvement in Turkey's construction sector had already been a hot topic, and the second corruption investigation launched on Dec. 25 of last year shifted public attention towards irregularities in public tenders and major construction projects.
Early on the morning of Dec. 25, 2013, Prosecutor Muammer Akkaş instructed the police to detain 30 suspects, including a number of parliamentary deputies and businessmen close to the government. However, the İstanbul Police Department, which had seen an extensive purge of its top officers in the week following the exposure of the Dec. 17 probe, did not comply with the detention order. Akkaş was removed from his post the next day and later appointed to a lower position outside İstanbul. After the probe was smothered by direct political interference in the judiciary, a number of anonymous social media users, such as Haramzadeler and Başçalan, started to disclose legally intercepted phone conversations over the Internet, which have been shaking the political stage ever since.
]]></text></news-item>