<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS2-V191-JBHM-S213"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Retailers Call For EPA Clarity On RCRA Treatment Of Consumer Products</title><source>Superfund Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The retail industry says the handling of aerosol can and pharmaceutical waste, as well as determinations on when a product becomes a waste, are among the critical issues it would like EPA to address as it researches how the Resource Conservation & Recovery Act (RCRA) should apply to potentially hazardous waste managed by the retail sector.
Enforcement actions under RCRA over the past few years by regulators against retailers over their management of consumer products have "put retailers on notice," a former EPA official says, noting that it is not a good situation when enforcement actions determine policy.
It is unclear how the law applies to certain products, a retail industry source adds.
"[O]ver the past several years, the retail world and RCRA have collided such that numerous significant enforcement actions have been initiated at the State and federal levels against retailers," Walmart Environmental, Health and Safety Compliance Vice President Richard Leahy said in a letter last December to EPA Resource Conservation & Recovery Director Barnes Johnson, expressing concern over unexplained delays in issuing a so-called notice of data availability (NODA) on the matter.
In light of the stepped-up enforcement actions, large retailers pushed the agency to quickly release the NODA.
EPA responded Feb. 14, publishing a NODA seeking information from the retail sector on waste management practices and advice on how to address challenges in complying with RCRA hazardous waste policies, as well as provide data it has already collected. The NODA asks the retail sector a slew of questions, seeking data on the amount of hazardous waste generated by the industry, suggestions for improving RCRA hazardous waste policies, information about episodic generation of waste from the sector, aerosol can waste handling, reverse logistics and sustainability efforts by facilities, among other requests.
The agency is taking comment until April 15. Relevant documents are available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID:2464403)
Improving the effectiveness of hazardous waste policies and regulations for the retail sector is one of 35 priorities under the agency's plan for improving existing regulations.
In the NODA, EPA says regulating hazardous waste generated by the retail sector under RCRA "presents unique challenges that are not found in more 'traditional' RCRA-regulated industries." It explains that the retail sector manages a diverse array of products, with one retailer for instance reporting about a million products handled nationwide, "many of which may potentially become regulated as hazardous waste under RCRA when discarded."
The agency says therefore retailers must make hazardous waste determinations at thousands of locations -- many of which are handled by store employees with limited RCRA knowledge. "Additionally, the retail sector often uses 'reverse distribution' in their business processes, where non-damaged products from retail stores are routinely shipped back to consolidation centers," EPA says. But how this process is regulated under RCRA has prompted numerous questions, the agency says.
"This NODA is part of the Agency's continuing effort to better understand concerns from all stakeholders about RCRA's applicability to the retail sector, what materials may be affected, what the full scope of the issues are, and what options may exist for addressing the issues," EPA says.
The agency says it is taking comment on several topics that arose in most of the enforcement actionstaken against retailers. "These recurring topics include where and when a hazardous waste determination must be made, episodic generation, reverse logistics and hazardous waste management programs," it says. The agency is also asking for information on the aerosol can waste stream, to determine if it should take any action to aid in managing aerosol cans that are discarded, along with other requests for information.
"They're really on a learning expedition right now," the former EPA official says, explaining the NODA and noting that the agency is not currently drafting any regulations. It is trying to learn how secondary materials are dealt with, including the reverse distribution system, where products for instance may be sent from major retailers to dollar stores for sale and then donated, recycled or disposed of, the source says.
Walmart, along with the Retail Industry Leaders Association (RILA) and others, has been in discussions with agency staff for more than two years "to try to find ways to make the RCRA regulatory framework clearer and more tailored to the retail environment," according to Walmart's Leahy, writing in the December letter.
"Ambiguities and inconsistencies in the application of RCRA to the retail sector present real challenges," he later notes in the letter.
Sources say the crucial issues EPA should focus on include pharmaceutical waste, pesticides, episodic generation, aerosol cans and when does a product become a waste. A RILA source says one priority the industry would like EPA to focus on is the nicotine cessation product category, noting that under existing requirements, an entity such as a retail store can be labeled a large quantity generator if it has just 2.2 pounds of nicotine cessation ingredients to manage as waste. Large quantity generators are the most regulated generators, according to EPA.
On the matter determining when a product becomes a waste, the RILA source says there are questions over when and where in the reverse logistics process a product becomes a waste, and what is considered a hazardous waste. Are, for instance, Reddi-wip containers and electronic toys considered hazardous waste, and are they worth the resources EPA and industry would have to put into them to address that designation, the source asks.
The point of waste generation is a core question retailers have raised, EPA agrees in its notice. The agency briefly explains hazardous waste generation regulations, noting that it is the responsibility of generators to determine if their waste is hazardous at the point of generation.
Also in the NODA, EPA estimates there are more than 41,000 retail sector facilities that have notified regulators they generate hazardous waste, with the vast majority of these small quantity or conditionally exempt small quantity generators. -- Suzanne Yohannan
]]></text></news-item>