<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-T4N1-JBRX-80VT"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>What happened at the Vertac site?</title><source>Arkansas Democrat-Gazette (Little Rock)</source><author>ALYSON HOGE ARKANSAS DEMOCRAT-GAZETTE</author><text><![CDATA[Thirty-five years ago, the story of Vertac wasn't about birds but chemical waste contamination.
In 1979, the federal Environmental Protection Agency announced it was studying 135 hazardous waste landfills across the country. Vertac Inc.'s plant in Jacksonville was the only Arkansas site on the list.
According to contemporary stories in the archives of the Arkansas Gazette and Arkansas Democrat, officials from Vertac and the state were puzzled because the Vertac site supposedly didn't have such a landfill.
But over time, the EPA found out that wastes were buried at the plant and contained in thousands of barrels. Untreated wastewater had been discharged into Rocky Branch, which flows through the Vertac site on its way to Bayou Meto. The EPA found contamination at the Vertac site, the surrounding neighborhood, a Jacksonville wastewater treatment plant and in the creeks.
Over four decades, a series of companies had made insecticides or herbicides at the site. The total area is 193 acres, but the southern part, about 93 acres, was the manufacturing site and main area of environmental concern.
In 1948, Reasor-Hill Co. began making pesticides, including the now banned DDT. In the 1950s, the company produced herbicides such as 2,4-D and 2,4,5-T.
The plant's next owner, Hercules Powder Co., made the same herbicides and, from 1964 to 1968, combined equal portions of them into Agent Orange, the defoliant used in the Vietnam War. Transvaal Inc. leased the site starting in 1971 and bought the plant in 1976. Transvaal evolved into Vertac Inc. and later Vertac Chemical Corp. Vertac stopped making 2,4,5-T in 1979, after the EPA announced it was investigating the site's wastes. The site was added in 1983 to EPA's National Priorities List for cleanup using the Superfund, a federal trust fund that pays for cleaning up hazardous wastes.
Vertac abandoned the site in 1987. In the cleanup that followed, about 25,000 barrels of chemicals were incinerated onsite, and another 3,000 were shipped to Kansas for incineration. The manufacturing plant was dismantled and buried in an onsite landfill. Another on-site landfill holds polluted soil. On the surface, the soil is clean, but the groundwater is contaminated and will be monitored indefinitely, according to the EPA.
Reports by the EPA say the primary pollutant at the site is dioxin, a waste byproduct of the manufacture of 2,4,5-T. Other pollutants are the two herbicides, plus benzene and phenols.
A 1998 Arkansas Democrat-Gazette article on the official end of the cleanup reported that the work cost an estimated $150 million.
Hercules, held responsible for nearly $120 million of that cost, hired Terracon Consultants Inc. to maintain the 93-acre site, which is off limits to the public. Jody Adams, Terracon's project geologist, said the company monitors groundwater and treats water collected in a French drain.
The city of Jacksonville has taken over the northern 100-acre site for use by the police, fire and street departments. It also has a recycling center.
Alyson Hoge is a Democrat-Gazette editor who helped the newspaper cover the Vertac story in the 1980s; she joined the Feb. 15 Vertac bird count. Sources for this article include a November 2008 five-year review report by the EPA.
This article was published 03/17/2014
]]></text></news-item>