<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-RDJ1-JC86-C3YB"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Liberia; Probe Should Be Free of Witch-Hunt</title><source>Africa News</source><author>The NEWS (Monrovia)</author><text><![CDATA[The Liberia Anti-corruption Commission (LACC) has commenced probe into allegation of bribery. The investigation started last week and a number of former officials of government are reportedly responding to the summons issued by the commission.
The Act That establishes the LACC gives the institution the authority to issue an arrest order depending on the situation. The new head of the LACC has promised to investigate allegation of corruption and would do so meticulously.
Already, The Commission is now interrogating some former officials of government who are allegedly linked to bribing some members of the 52nd National Legislature to pass certain concessions. The investigation was triggered by true confession made by Mr. Clemenceau Urey, a renowned Liberian businessman and executive of the ruling Unity Party, who admitted recently that some former policymakers received bribe from the National Oil Company of Liberia (NOCAL) to pass certain concessions. His testimony prompted some influential members of government, including a former Interim President Amos Sawyer to call for the investigation of Mr. Urey and those linked to bribe taking. Based on the gravity of the confession coming from the former chair of the oil company, the LACC decided to establish the authenticity of the claims.
Now, Mr. Urey, who has been cited by the Commission, is claiming that he was assaulted and manhandled by agents of the LACC.
Whether His Allegation is true or not, we believe that the purpose for which the probe has been requested is to establish the truthfulness of Urey's assertion. Although the LACC has authority to arrest and probe individuals accused or indicted for corruption, notwithstanding, to assault or manhandle an individual is a violation of his human rights.
We Strongly Believe that Mr. Urey's statement is an admission of fact which requires that the Commission investigates all parties, including the former Legislators who allegedly received bribe as inducement to pass concessions that were not properly vetted.
We Support The bribery probe because corruption seems to have invaded every facet of our society and has created a negative image for our country.
As The LACC embarks on this exercise, it is our expectation that the investigation would be free of witch-hunt and unnecessary vendetta.
]]></text></news-item>