<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-8TK1-JCTS-G1B5"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Are Michigan's restrictions on gay and abortion rights holding state back? </title><source>Flint Journal (Michigan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[URL: http://www.mlive.com/politics/index.ssf/2014/03/are_michigans_restrictions_on.html
By Chris Andrews
Bridge Magazine
For Kent Love-Ramirez, pulling up stakes from Michigan was both difficult and necessary. Difficult because he was a lifelong Michigander with a good job and family and friends nearby. Necessary, he and his partner concluded, to take care of their family.
Kent and Diego Love-Ramireze recently moved to Minnesota, where a new law allows same-sex marriage.
Kent said he fully expects Michigan voters to eventually repeal a 9-year-old constitutional ban on gay marriage -- perhaps in two years should a ballot drive succeed -- if a federal court does not overturn the ban. But largely because the couple has an adopted young son, they felt they couldn't wait.
"Boy, 2016 is a really long time to not have protection for yourself as a couple and for your child," he said.
While polls show support for expanding gay rights, opposition remains strong, notably among Republican elected officials, who control state government.
The debate also raises a broader policy question: Whether laws restricting gay rights are stunting Michigan's ability to attract talent and sustain its economic recovery.
Experts say the restrictions are creating barriers to growth and prosperity.
"Increasingly, the economy is driven by talent," said Lou Glazer, president of the economic-development nonprofit Michigan Future."... If you are not welcoming, they are not coming here."
personal liberty vs. religious freedom
Some Republican lawmakers, meanwhile, say they are increasingly wrestling with the question of how to balance respect for individual freedoms with religious concerns and shifting public sentiment.
State Sen. Roger Kahn, R-Saginaw Township, is among those who have denounced the anti-gay rhetoric of Republican National Committeeman Dave Agema but don't see a need for broad legislative action.
Kahn said he's willing to consider specific legislation -- for instance, on domestic-partner benefits -- but believes marriage should be between a man and a woman. "It's a slippery slope question ... there's a line I'm not willing to cross on marriage, at least for now."
The anticipated impact of Michigan's ban was fiercely debated at the time, and its meaning has been subsequently challenged in the Legislature and courts. Today, gay rights advocates say it's clear that residents who are gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender are treated as second-class citizens.
"When we are trying to take care of our partner or our children, it hinders our ability to do so because we don't have equal rights under the law," said Emily Dievendorf, managing director of Equality Michigan.
But others oppose what they see as an effort to grant what they contend are special rights. Limiting marriage to a man and a woman "has been pretty much the law of the land since the founding of the country," said John Truscott, a Lansing political strategist. "It's pretty tough to say it's discriminatory when it's been in place for a long time."
Despite Republicans' political dominance in Lansing, legal challenges have made Michigan's situation fluid. Gay rights advocates are hoping a federal judge will strike down the marriage ban when he delivers his decision this month in a lesbian couple's lawsuit seeking joint adoption for their children, which also is prohibited in Michigan.
Fighting the brain drain
After a decade-long economic downturn in Michigan, many things are looking up, including the auto industry and the state's population.
But serious challenges linger, key among them building the skilled, creative talent pool that fuels growth and attracts high-paying jobs. That's especially true for young college graduates; Michigan lags the nation in producing and retaining them.
It's difficult to quantify whether laws affecting gays are affecting Michigan's financial fortunes. But gay rights advocates argue the most prosperous states are taking a different approach.
Michigan's public university system holds the potential for enhancing the state's standing in the talent race -- if new graduates can be persuaded to stay. Nearly two-thirds nationally say they look first for the place they want to live, then for a job in that location, according to a 2006 study by CEOs for Cities. Add to that overwhelming evidence of support for same-sex marriage among young Michiganders.
"If you look at the states ... that have the most prosperous economies and have the largest concentration of talent, they are gay-friendly, immigrant-friendly, women-friendly, better on race issues," Glazer said.
Kahn said Michigan should support policies that encourage everyone to come here, rather than seeking any particular group. Ari Adler, spokesman for GOP House Speaker Jase Bolger, said Republicans already have a strategy.
"Young, talented people want to live where they can find a job and raise a family in a healthy economy, with good schools, good roads and strong public-safety initiatives," Adler said.
Making choices
The Love-Ramirezes' decision to leave Michigan came gradually. Kent was communications director for the MSU College of Law. Diego, a Delta Airlines pilot, moved to Michigan after meeting Kent 11 years ago.
Their exchange of vows at the MSU Alumni chapel in 2007 lacked legal standing. They married again in Washington, D.C., but that wasn't recognized here, either.
The couple considered moving when their adoptive son was born in 2011, and only one of them could have legal status in Michigan as a parent (they declined to say which one). They can rectify that with a stepparent adoption in Minnesota.
"With every advance made around the country and throughout the world, it makes Michigan and states like Michigan look more and more repressive, backwater, uninviting," said Kent Love-Ramirez, now communications director at the University of Minnesota's Humphrey School of Public Affairs. "As a lifelong Michigander for 43 years, it really makes me sad."
recruiting talent
The University of Michigan and the Ann Arbor area are among the most welcoming communities to gay individuals and families in the state. U-M created an office to support gay students about 40 years ago, and officials refashioned domestic partner benefits to ensure that they continued after the marriage ban.
R. Van Harrison, professor of education and coordinator of the U-M LGBT Faculty Alliance, said he served on a search committee where the preferred candidate was a woman in a committed relationship with the mother of a handicapped child. Although U-M could offer benefits, she turned down the position.
"Given the nature of the laws in the state, she said, 'Look, I cannot afford to come here and make my life and try to build a career and find out that three years from now, a Republican majority in the Legislature has found a way to prevent the university from offering this benefit,'" he recalled.
The idea that embracing diversity and inclusion can strengthen communities and economies has grown largely out of the work of urban theorist Richard Florida.
His research showed housing values were substantially stronger in regions with larger concentrations of gay and lesbian residents, as well as artists and musicians. And in focus groups, educated mothers said they were attracted to such communities, "partly because they found it to be more open and welcoming and really provided the diversity they were looking for," said Steven Pedigo, director of research for Florida's Creative Class Group.
Seeking common ground
There are signals that some proponents and critics are trying to reach common ground, and there may be some progress on anti-bias law.
Kary Moss of ACLU of Michigan has engaged in serious discussions with Republicans, Democrats and business leaders about a prohibition on discrimination in employment and housing based on sexual orientation.
"The climate has shifted dramatically in the last 12 months," she said.
Bolger believes in protecting individuals from discrimination but is struggling the religious freedom issue, spokesman Adler said.
"While everyone immediately agrees that something should be done, not one person has been able to provide a solution that protects everyone from intimidation and discrimination," Adler said.
In the meantime, 30 Michigan cities and townships have approved local ordinances protecting gays against employment or housing discrimination.
Copyright Bridge Magazine, reprinted with permission.
-- Bridge Magazine, a publication of The Center for Michigan, produces nonprofit public affairs journalism and is a partner with MLive.com. Visit Bridge at bridgemi.com.
Some experts worry that LGBT and abortion restrictions are driving talented workers from Michigan.
Kent (left) and Diego Love-Ramirez recently moved to St. Paul, Minn., where the law allows same-sex marriage and shared legal custody of their adopted son; rights denied to them in Michigan.
News and Analysis from The Center for Michigan
@mlive-news @mlive-river center-for-michigan
]]></text></news-item>