<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-XCH1-DYJB-J02J"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Personal profits exclusion does not bar duty to defend foreclosure fraud claim; Cornerstone Title &amp; Escrow Inc. v. Evanston Ins. Co., No. 13-1318 (4th Cir. Feb. 19, 2014)</title><source>Insurance Law &amp; Litigation Week</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Fourth U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals held that neither an insurance policy's personal profits exclusion nor the policy's theft exclusion applied to preclude coverage for an underlying claim that an insured engaged in a scheme to defraud homeowners on the brink of foreclosure. Thus, the insurer had no duty to defend or indemnify the insured.
The Maryland Attorney General sued Cornerstone Title & Escrow Inc. and 10 codefendants alleging the defendants collectively violated the Maryland Protection of Homeowners in Foreclosure Act and the Maryland Consumer Protection Act. According to the complaint, the defendants violated those statutes by scheming to "take title to homeowners' residences and strip the equity that the homeowners ha[d] built up in their homes."
The attorney general accused the codefendants of convincing the owners of 13 properties on the verge of foreclosure to sell their homes to them and then rent the homes. The codefendants then charged the homeowners rent that was much higher than the original mortgage payment, driving the homeowners out of their homes and ending any chance for them to repurchase the homes in the future.
Cornerstone provided settlement services for the sale leaseback transactions and the attorney general alleged it failed to deliver the checks for proceeds due to the homeowners at settlement or afterward. The attorney general sought to hold Cornerstone responsible, not just for its own involvement, but also for its codefendants' acts.
Cornerstone then sought coverage under a service and technical professional liability insurance policy Evanston Insurance Co. issued, requesting that Evanston defend it against the complaint and indemnify it for any liability. Evanston denied coverage and Cornerstone eventually agreed to a settlement in which it consented to pay $100,000 in restitution.
Cornerstone sued Evanston for breach of contract. The district court entered summary judgment in Evanston's favor, finding that a personal profits exclusion and a theft exclusion barred coverage for the underlying action. Cornerstone appealed.
The Fourth Circuit reversed the district court's judgment and remanded the case. The personal profits exclusion did not apply because the attorney general's complaint did not allege that any particular profit went to Cornerstone, as required by the exclusion. Moreover, the exclusion did not apply because the attorney general's complaint did not allege illegal profiteering by Cornerstone.
The Fourth Circuit also found the theft exclusion did not apply. The attorney general's claims did not arise from theft, conversion, misappropriation or any of the other acts described in that exclusion, and consequently would require coverage under the policy.
Counsel for Cornerstone : Stephan Y. Brennan, Iliff Meredith Wildberger & Brennan P.C., 410-685-1166, Pasadena, Md.
Counsel for Evanston : Paul N. Farquharson, Semmes Bowen & Semmes P.C., 410-576-4742, Baltimore.
Source: Insurance Law and Litigation Week, 03/17/2014
Copyright © 2014 by Strafford Publications, Inc. http://www.straffordpub.com/ All rights reserved. Storage, reproduction or transmission by any means is prohibited except pursuant to a valid license agreement.
]]></text></news-item>