<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-NM21-DXMP-K4KV"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Know India's Nuclear Weapons Threat Perceptive</title><source>ABC Live</source><author>Dinesh Singh Rawat</author><text><![CDATA[New Delhi (ABC Live): India perceives its nuclear weapons and missile programs as crucial components of its strategic doctrine. New Delhi rejects the Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons (NPT) on the grounds that it perpetuates-at least in the short-term-an unjust distinction between the five states that are permitted by the treaty to possess nuclear weapons, while requiring all other state parties to the treaty to remain non-nuclear weapon states.
India has also been highly critical of the pace of the nuclear weapon states' disarmament progress, arguing that they have not fulfilled their commitments under Article VI of the NPT.
However, India has recently taken steps to integrate into the broader nonproliferation regime, receiving a waiver in 2008 from the Nuclear Suppliers Group (NSG), entering into bilateral civilian nuclear agreements, and expressing interest in joining the major export control regimes.
India's Nuclear Weapons Threat Perceptive
India is not a member of the Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons (NPT) or the Comprehensive Nuclear Test Ban Treaty (CTBT), though it is a state party to the Partial Test Ban Treaty (PTBT). New Delhi embarked on a nuclear energy program in 1948 and a nuclear explosives program in 1964. The latter culminated in the May 1974 test of a "peaceful nuclear explosion."Following five nuclear tests in May 1998, India formally declared itself a nuclear weapon state.
According to the 2013 SIPRI Yearbook, the Indian arsenal comprises 90 to 110 warheads. Estimates in 2012 put India's highly enriched uranium (HEU) stockpile at 2.4 0.9 tons, and its weapons-grade plutonium stockpile at 0.54 0.18 tons.Although India is increasingly concentrating on developing missiles for nuclear delivery roles, aircraft such as the Mirage 2000 and the Jaguar remain integral parts of its nuclear delivery force.
India and the United States announced a nuclear cooperation initiative in July 2005 that would permit New Delhi to participate in international nuclear trade, under certain conditions. In 2008, New Delhi negotiated a limited safeguards agreement with the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA). Subsequently, in September 2008 the Nuclear Suppliers Group removed the ban on India's participation in nuclear trade with its members. In October 2008, India and the United States signed a bilateral '123 nuclear cooperation agreement. India has since signed nuclear cooperation agreements with several countries,including Canada, Russia, France, Argentina, Kazakhstan, and Namibia. India is working to conclude agreements Australia and Japan.
]]></text></news-item>