<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-RDJ1-JC86-C3GK"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Nigeria; Concerns Grow Over Rising Fraud Cases in Banks</title><source>Africa News</source><author>This Day (Lagos)</author><text><![CDATA[The number of reported cases of fraud and forgery in the banking industry has been on the increase since last year, THISDAY learnt at the weekend.
According to banking sources, while there been growing attempt to defraud bank customers, especially on electronic banking channels, disenchantment by some workers who feel their jobs are no longer secured due to the increasing demand for deposit mobilisation and other performance indicators by their employers in view of the tight monetary policy environment, have led some bank workers into criminal acts.
The Central Bank of Nigeria's (CBN's) annual report for 2012 had shown that the number of reported cases of fraud and forgery in the banking industry increased in 2012.
According to the central bank, there were 4,527 cases of fraud and forgery involving the sum of N14.8 billion and US$1.6 million, compared with 2,527 cases involving the sum of N29.5 billion at end-December 2011.
The 2012 report showed that the cases of fraud were perpetrated mostly by outsiders and some staff members of banks through such means as pilfering, theft, suppression and conversion of customersâ deposits, illegal funds transfer and fraudulent ATM withdrawals.
Industry watchers however believe that 2013 will be worse with banks' staff members getting increasingly involved in fraud due to uncertainty about their jobs.
For the Lagos State Chapter of the Chartered Institute of Bankers of Nigeria (CIBN), the number may have risen last year as the institute recently expressed concern over rising cases of identity theft in the industry.
The First Vice-Chairperson, CIBN, Lagos Branch, Mrs. Taiwo Ige, said the impact of fraudulent activities on individuals, the nation and organisations were enormous.
She explained: "The problems of fraud, identity theft and money laundering are increasing at an unprecedented rate. Governments worldwide are introducing new legislations and penalties to curb these white collar crimes.
"Regrettably, the battle seems far from being won. It is therefore, crucial that bankers are fully aware at this trend and are alert because of the consequences on businesses, the national economy and the image of the country."
According to her, there have been lots of reports on the compromise of personal identity number (PIN) of bank customers, especially by those that use Automated Teller Machines.
Concerned by the unfortunate development, especially the risk to banks' ATM channels, the Director, Banking and Payment Systems Department, CBN, Mr. 'Dipo Fatokun in a circular posted on the central bank's website at the weekend, said it was not good for the industry.
He confirmed that there have been an upward increase in the number of ATMS related fraud in the banking system.
According to Fatokun, the situation requires urgent steps to curb the abuse.
"Consequently, in addition to the existing guidelines on card related frauds and in order to guard against card skimming at ATM channels across the country, all Deposit Money Banks (DMBs) are hereby mandated to comply with the provisions of Sections 3.2 'ATM Operations' and 3.4 'ATM Security' of the Standard and Guidelines on ATM operations in Nigeria and also install risk mitigating devices on their ATM terminals on or before June 1, 2014," Fatokun added.
He pointed out that the CBN had observed with satisfaction, the growth in the adoption of ATMs by Nigerians as one of the channels of e-payment, adding that there was need to ensure that the deployment and management of ATMs are in line with global best practice.
]]></text></news-item>