<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-J3S1-J9YR-G11G"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Huge pile of letters is scam post received by just one pensioner as the full scale of fraud costing Britain's elderly millions is revealed</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>RICHARD SPILLETT</author><text><![CDATA[Police say foreign fraudsters are bombarding Britain's elderly with scam mailGangs swap details of those who respond, so others can target themOne retired man lost more than £100,000 in five years to a fake lottery fraudOfficers took photo of one pensioner's mail to show extent of the problemIt is thought UK pensioners send billions to overseas gangs every yearPolice say the issue is leading to huge debts, depression and even suicide
A pensioner was bombarded with hundreds of scam letters as part of the barrage of mail frauds now targeting Britain's elderly.
The 87-year-old from East Sussex, who asked not to be named, lost £90,000 after criminal gangs sent her endless fraudulent letters following the death of her husband.
A photo taken by her local police force in East Sussex reveals the full extent of the deluge of opportunistic mail coming through Britain's letter boxes.
She is just one of the two million victims nationwide now losing billions to criminal gangs, who operate from overseas and exploit the good natures of the elderly and vulnerable.
Telling of one shocking case, Sussex Police's PC Bernadette Lawrie said: 'It was our recent involvement with a 94-year-old local victim that highlighted the despicable nature of this type of criminal activity and the lack of support, advice and recognition currently available for victims and their families.
'He had sent more than £100,000 since 2007 in response to scam mail regarding lottery wins to criminal gangs abroad, making his money transfers through local village post offices.
'He was being bombarded daily with masses of scam mail and telephone calls to his home from criminals demanding money fraudulently.'
Police in the county say around 400 OAPs - aged mainly between 80 and 90 years-old - have lost more than £2million to the scams.
Chief Superintendent Wayne Jones said; 'This is a mean and heartless crime that targets elderly, vulnerable and often lonely people.
'The scams usually involve the victims receiving letters and sometimes phone calls from overseas claiming that they have either won money and need to send a percentage of the "winnings" to claim their prize or that they should send money in with competition entries.
'Sometimes the scams include fake charities and the sending out of catalogues offering cheaply made goods, cakes and biscuits at exorbitant prices.
'Many, if not all of the scammers are based overseas and they do share victims' details with the result that people can receive dozens of letters all telling them that they have been "specially selected".
'They have been specially selected, but sadly to be a victim of crime.
'The volume of mail they receive can be overwhelming, we have visited victims who are receiving hundreds of scam letters every week.
'We have seen victims who have lost their entire life savings and prefer to send their pension to the scammers rather than buy food and pay for heating.
'Several of our victims have incurred large debts and their quality of life has been massively affected.
'Sadly we have even encountered examples where victims suffer anxiety, depression and in one case attempted suicide.'
]]></text></news-item>