<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-3FX1-JC86-31K9"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>March 18th Marks the Third Annual Celebration of Hangover Joe's Day; (HJOE) Proven Relief for the St. Patrick's Day Hangover Now Available in a Growing Number of Locations</title><source>Marketwired</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[HANGOVER JOE'S HOLDING CORPORATION (OTCQB: HJOE), the maker of "The Hangover" Recovery Shot, announces the 3rd annual celebration of Hangover Joe's Day on March 18th. Honoring those of you who tipped a pint or two while enjoying everything Irish on St. Patrick's Day, we invite you to join us in a celebratory two-ounce toast to rapid hangover recovery on Tuesday, March 18, 2014 -- Hangover Joe's Day. Currently available in a growing number of retail locations and growing, Hangover Joe's two-ounce Recovery Shot replenishes your body with key vitamins and minerals that are depleted when you drink alcohol.
Shawn Adamson, VP of Sales & Marketing at Hangover Joe's, stated, "St. Patrick's Day is one of the largest holidays for alcohol consumption in the U.S.A., representing more than 1% of total alcohol revenues each year. That's why Hangover Joe christened March 18 as Hangover Joe's Day....so that every working stiff out there can celebrate in the spirit of the Irish on March 17th with the peace of mind that Hangover Joe's will be there to provide effective relief for them on March 18th." Adamson added, "Although Hangover Joe is definitely no Saint, he knows that on March 17th there is a little bit of St. Patrick in everyone."
According to the 2009 American Community Survey, U.S. residents claiming Irish ancestry are nearing the 37 million mark -- about eight times the current population of Ireland. St. Patrick's Day marks the death of the beloved 5th-century Catholic saint who, according to legend, banished all snakes from Ireland and used the 3-leaf clover, or shamrock, to teach the Irish the doctrine of the holy trinity: the Father, Son and Holy Ghost. St. Patrick's Day has been observed as a religious holiday on the Emerald Island for more than 1,000 years; and the Irish have traditionally used this break in Lent as a reason to sneak off to the pub. Initially, Irish-Americans took the idea of imbibing on St. Patrick's Day to heart and transformed the "high holiday" into a celebration of all things Irish.
Typically, March 18th is one of the leading "sick days" in the country. Hundreds of thousands of people call in sick in order to nurse the after effects of a rousing St. Patrick's Day. The national recovery of this holiday costs American companies billions of dollars each year. In fact, the National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism estimates that over-consumption of alcohol costs the United States an estimated $185 billion each year. Nearly half of that is directly linked to binge drinking and productivity loss from morning after illnesses.
"'The Hangover Recovery Shot' could save world economies tens of millions of dollars in coming years," said Adamson. "Hangover Joe's can now be found in thousands of retail locations nationwide, and more retail business owners are coming aboard each month as consumers learn about and demand effective hangover recovery."Adamson added, "With our initial 10 million bottle agreement for distribution into the Japanese markets starting in the second quarter, I expect that Hangover Joe's will ultimately decrease alcohol-related absenteeism and lost productivity in the workplace on a global basis."
ABOUT HANGOVER JOE'S Hangover Joe's is the exclusive producer of "The Hangover" Recovery Shot, one of the nation's top selling hangover recovery products. Featuring a proprietary blend of antioxidants, vitamins and herbs, "The Hangover" Recovery Shot is proven to provide effective relief from the symptoms and side effects of alcohol consumption.
Hangover Joe's recently launched the Git-R-Done Energy Shot, the first all-natural two-ounce energy shot that has no added caffeine. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration does not allow soft drinks to have more than 0.02 percent caffeine, but energy drinks are not subject to this limit which has caused a firestorm of concerns about the amount of caffeine that goes into these energy drinks. In License with Larry the Cable Guy's Git-R-Done Productions, the Git-R-Done-Energy shot is the first healthy energy shot available to consumers.
For additional information, visit www.hangoverjoes.com and check us out on Facebook and YouTube. Complete company information and securities filings may also be found at www.sec.gov.
Forward-Looking Statements This news release contains "forward-looking statements" as that term is defined in Section 27A of the United States Securities Act of 1933, as amended and Section 21E of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, as amended. Statements in this press release which are not purely historical are forward-looking statements and include any statements regarding beliefs, plans, expectations or intentions regarding the future. Such forward-looking statements include, among other things, regulatory incentives, the development of new business opportunities, and projected costs, revenue, profits and results operations. Actual results could differ from those projected in any forward-looking statements due to numerous factors. These forward-looking statements are made as of the date of this news release, and we assume no obligation to update the forward-looking statements, or to update the reasons why actual results could differ from those projected in the forward-looking statements. Although we believe that any beliefs, plans, expectations and intentions contained in this press release are reasonable, there can be no assurance that any such beliefs, plans, expectations or intentions will prove to be accurate. Investors should consult all of the information set forth herein and should also refer to the risk factors disclosure outlined in our annual report on its reports filed at www.sec.gov.
SOURCE: Hangover Joe's Holdings Corporation
]]></text></news-item>