<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-WBW1-DXKH-N102"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Accor increases on low volume</title><source>News Bites - Western Europe: France</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Accor (FR:AC), France's 2nd largest travel & leisure company by market capitalisation, increased 7.0c (or 0.2%) to close at EUR37.35. Compared with the CAC 40 Index which rose 48.5 points (or 1.2%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -1.0%. The volume was 0.4 times the average trading of 946,503 shares.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Accor, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/0010518117703147
Bullish SignalsUptrend- The Moving Average Convergence Divergence (MACD) indicator of 12-day Exponential Moving Average (EMA) of 37.67 minus the 26-day EMA of 37.18 is positive 0.49 suggesting a bullish signal.- The 3.7% discount to 12-month high of EUR38.80 against the 52.2% premium to 12-month low of EUR24.54 suggests the stock continues to push for new highs. - In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week high twenty-one times, pointing to a significant uptrend. - The present value of EUR1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Accor is EUR1,352, including a capital gain of EUR315 and dividend reinvested of EUR37.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Return on Capital Employed 9% [7.0%].- Dividend yield of 2% [0.7%].Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 2.4 is comfortably below 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 16.1%. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 1.1. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- Net profit margin has averaged 20.4% in the last 3 years. This is considered superior and suggests a high margin of safety.- EBIT margin and EBITDA margin are positive and have seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteBeta: the Beta of Accor stock is 0.6. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Parity:- Price to EBITDA of 4.8 [4.6].Bearish Signals:Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price/Sales of 1.5 [0.4]. - Price to Book of 3.5 [1.8].
AGGREGATE VOLUMES, PRICES AND TURNOVER PERIOD [Volume Index or VI in brackets; 1 is average] Paris: AC.FR 362,188 [VI of 0.4] volume 99.873% of aggregate. Price: EUR37.35. Frankfurt: ACR.FRA 460 [VI of 2.4] volume 0.127% of aggregate. Price: EUR37.24. Aggregate volume: there were 362,648 shares of Accor worth EUR13.5 million traded. The aggregate volume was 0.4 times average trading of 823,000 shares.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 05: Accor: Blurring: all the comforts of travel that integrates work and private lives[Company Release]Plenty of people are already "blurring", they just don't know they are. Examples include all the employees or entrepreneurs who take their personal smartphones or tablets to work in the morning and bring home their Netbook Pros! This growing trend is one of the key factors fuzzing the line between professional and private lives.
March 05: Accor launches an online solution that simplifies leisure group bookings for up to 60 people[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/France/Stock/News/17283.pdfSource: Company Website
February 24: Accor sells its stake in Reef Casino in Australia for AU$85m[News Story]
As part of its asset management strategy, Accor announces the sale of its participation in the Reef Casino in Australia. This participation includes a 29% stake in Reef Casino Trust (RCT), a listed entity, as well as its 50% stake in the related businesses of RCT, i.e.
February 20: Accor: Sustained Growth and Solid Results in 2013[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/France/Stock/News/17079.pdfSource: Company Website
February 17: Potentialpark Award: Accor rewarded for its international digital communications strategy in human resources[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/France/Stock/News/16990.pdfSource: Company Website
February 17: Accor rewarded for its digital communication strategy for human resources[Company Release]The Potential Park firm has published their yearly company ranking based on digital communication on human resources.These rankings are determined through the votes of around 24,000 students from 968 schools in 85 countries.Details of rankings: ' Present on Youtube, LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter and Pinterest, Accor takes 1st place in the "Social Medias" ranking in France, and 8th place in Asia.' AccorJobs.com confirms its position of leader in France, also taking 1st place in Europe and heading up the recruitment websites in Asia.' Accor.com, has climbed to 3rd place in the "Career Websites" category in Europe and 2nd place in Asia.' The mobile site m.accorjobs.com listing all of the Group's job offers, and providing videos, news and information on Accor, has entered the top 10 in the Asia ranking from among only 34 companies using this media in the area.Source: Company Website
February 10: Accor: Disclosure of Share Capital and Voting Rights, January 31st 2014[News Story]
http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/France/Stock/News/16818.pdfSource: NYSE Euronext
ISIN: FR0000120404
FR:AC; EPA:AC; PA:AC; FP:AC
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>