<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-1YG1-F125-11VG"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Kelly McParland: Quebec's Wal-Mart election offers roll-back issues for undiscerning voters</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Pauline Marois is running a Wal-Mart election campaign, with daily promises on "roll back" issues for voters who don't get to town much.
Issues like this haven't been seen in the rest of the country in years, if ever. Independence is on sale is aisle five, at even less risk than ever! There's a special on Jewish conspiracies in the kosher section of the deli department, next to the Islamic aisle, which is temporarily closed for a quick change of marketing material( http://montreal.ctvnews.ca/pq-candidate-steps-down-after-posting-anti-islamic-photos-1.1727311 ). Voters are urged to try the Values department instead, where they will find much of the same xenophobia and intolerance at knock-down prices.
Do people run campaigns like this anywhere else in Canada? Quebec's economy is said to be in poor shape. Former separatist leader Jacques Parizeau says it's the first time in 30 years he'd been seriously worried about its finances. The government continues to pour money into social subsidies it can't afford while productivity is the lowest( http://business.financialpost.com/2014/03/15/as-quebec-election-shifts-spotlight-to-independence-economy-falls-to-back-burner/ ) in Canada and debt the highest. Quebec's equalization payment( http://www.sunnewsnetwork.ca/sunnews/politics/archives/2013/12/20131217-190323.html )from Canada (the country it wants to leave) will rise to $9.3 billion this year, almost five times that of any other province. Yet the biggest event of the first week was Pierre-Karl Peladeau declaring himself a separatist and ruining Premier Pauline Marois's flimsy effort to pretend she wanted a majority government for some other reason than to hold another referendum.
Mr. Peladeau is the opposite of everything separatists hold dear - a pushy, anti-union, multi-millionaire and one-man-band who owns a media chain that is virulently anti-separatist - but his willingness to run as a Parti Quebecois candidate (the better to seize control down the road) suddenly makes him a bosom buddy of the same union leaders he'd have crushed if they'd ever challenged him on a contract issue.
His arrival pushed the kind of concerns that preoccupy ordinary Quebecers deeper into the bog. Forget about education, health care or the crumbling roads and bridges - PQ candidate Louise Mailloux( http://news.nationalpost.com/2014/03/14/jewish-group-accuses-parti-quebecois-candidate-of-spreading-kkk-anti-semitic-conspiracy-theory/ ) seized on the real danger facing Quebec's eight million people: a conspiracy featuring a unique cabal of Jewish and Islamic leaders who extort money from unsuspecting food companies and send it off to shady causes. Seriously people, that's what she thinks. Jews and Muslims aren't known for being the closest of allies, but according to Ms. Mailloux, the Quebec chapters have united in an unholy conspiracy to demand fees for certifying that certain foods meet halal or kosher dietary standards. The money is then funnelled to Zionist or Islamic organizations for God-knows-what nefarious operations. She also thinks baptism and circumcision are similar to rape. (Ms. Mailloux has now apologized( http://www.montrealgazette.com/news/candidate+Louise+Mailloux+apologizes+conspiracy+theory+offended+Jews/9622555/story.html ) if people were offended by her remarks. She's not recanting her beliefs or suggesting she was wrong for saying what she did, she just thinks people shouldn't get upset about it.)
Ms. Mailloux is not some backwoods hillbilly; she's a philosophy professor at the Cégep du Vieux Montréal. A statement like that anywhere else in the country would be met by an angry and embarrassed party leader disavowing the candidate and appearing at the nearest synagogue or mosque to make amends. But this is Quebec, so Ms. Marois is standing by her bigot candidate, insisting "the Parti Québécois is not an anti-Semitic party" no matter what appearances may suggest.
It's never a good sign when a party leader has to deny hating an entire class of people, but it doesn't seem to faze Ms. Marois. In fact, "we have very good relations with the leaders of this community and all the different communities in Quebec," she said, presumably even within the international Jewish conspiracy.
Of course, how could she say otherwise, when the chief accomplishment of her minority government has been to invent a "Charter of Values" making clear that foreigners with funny clothing and religious symbols are not welcome in modern, secularist Quebec? A Sikh in a turban, a Jew in a skull cap or a Muslim in a veil are too great a threat to Quebec's fundamental values to be tolerated in positions of public trust. Crucifixes are also dodgy, though exceptions can be made because a lot of "real" Quebecers are also Christians.
Next door to Quebec, in Ontario, another minority government is facing an election and is busy shoring up its positions on transit, taxes and budget deficits. In Alberta, the premier is in trouble over extravagant airline expenses and fighting to reassure voters she's just as much a hardliner of budget excess as they are. In Ottawa, with an election still 19 months away, it's all about the economy.
But in Quebec, it's separatism, Jewish conspiracies and foreigners in turbans. Separatists maintain they're different from other Canadians. They're right on that, and not in a good way.
National Post
]]></text></news-item>