<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-PPH1-JD8H-P02N"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>State Farm Ordered to Pay $3 Million Judgment in Katrina-Related Whistleblower Case</title><source>BestWire</source><author>Jeff Jeffrey</author><text><![CDATA[State Farm Fire and Casualty Co. has been ordered to pay $3 million in legal fees and damages in a long-running whistle-blower lawsuit after a jury found the company defrauded the federal government in a Hurricane Katrina-related claim.
Under the Feb. 21 ruling, which was posted online late last week, State Farm will be required to pay the U.S. government trebled damages of $750,000 and a civil penalty of $8,250.
Independent adjusters Cori and Kerri Rigsby, who are sisters, will each receive 15% of that amount in addition to $2.9 million in attorneys' fees for alerting the government to the alleged fraud.
The case has unfolded over the past eight years and has taken a number of twists and turns.
The sisters had alleged State Farm defrauded the government by blaming the damage their property suffered on flooding, which would be covered by the National Flood Insurance Program. Last year, a jury decided State Farm had indeed avoided paying a policyholder's claim by deflecting insurance payments onto the NFIP.
In May, State Farm sought to have the jury's verdict thrown out, arguing the jury did not have a legally sufficient basis for its finding (Best's News Service, May 9, 2013).
The Rigsby sisters' original complaint alleged State Farm made similarly improper claim decisions on a number of other properties.
But in issuing his decision, U.S. Judge Halil Ozerden of the Southern District of Mississippi refused to allow the Rigsby sisters to expand their lawsuit to include other claims submitted to State Farm in the wake of the 2005 hurricane. Ozerden limited the case to one claim made on a home in Biloxi, Miss., owned by the McIntosh family.
Phil Supple, a spokesman for State Farm, said in a statement the company has not decided whether it will seek to appeal the verdict. "While we are disappointed that the judge did not set aside the jury's verdict, we are gratified that the court issued a final order, which concludes all of the Rigsbys' claims against State Farm," Supple said. "We are currently considering our appellate options."
The case was initially handled for the Rigsbys by Richard "Dickie" Scruggs, but he was terminated as counsel when he pleaded guilty in 2008 to conspiracy for attempted bribery of a Mississippi circuit court judge. He was sentenced to five years in prison. Federal Bureau of Prisons records show Scruggs was released briefly in December, but he is now back in prison with a projected release date of Jan. 24, 2015.
State Farm Fire And Casualty Co. currently has a Best's Financial Strength Rating of A+ (Superior).
(By Jeff Jeffrey, Washington Bureau manager: jeff.jeffrey@ambest.com)
]]></text></news-item>