<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-XCH1-DYJB-J030"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Companies profit from employees' deaths under current law; Patrick Burns, Peasants' Revolt: Why Congress Should Eliminate The Tax Benefits on Dead Peasant Insurance, 65 Hastings L.J. 551 (2014)</title><source>Insurance Law &amp; Litigation Week</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Corporate-owned life insurance (COLI) is life insurance a company takes out on the life of one of its employees. COLI was intended to protect employers against the loss of "key employees," but in the past two decades, businesses have increased the percentage of employees they insure, even insuring low-wage employees. Thus, corporations have been profiting from the death of their employees and taking advantage of federal tax laws that allow them to exclude those proceeds from gross income. Patrick Burns argues for changes to state insurance interest statutes and federal tax law.
The rationale behind COLI policies recognizes that a company may suffer financially if a key employee dies, giving the company an insurance interest in that person's life. Problems arise, however, in determining who qualifies as a "key employee." "Dead peasant" policies began to arise in the 1990s and 2000s, as employers began to insure low-wage employees and employees who had not worked a significant time for companies, often without their knowledge. Courts found some of those policies invalid because the companies could not show an insurable interest in insuring rank-and-file employees.
There are numerous public policy concerns with allowing COLI. There is often an arbitrary connection between an employee's value to a company and the amount the company stands to gain from the employee's death. In the modern employment relationship, even the most important employees can be replaced without financial ruin to the company. For example, a simple cash payment to Apple would not have helped the company maintain its success after Steve Jobs' death.
COLI policies exist despite Congress' efforts. Congress acted to limit some of the benefits of COLI by ending the ability to deduct interest on loans taken out to purchase COLI in 1996. The Pension Protection Act of 2006 (PPA) also narrowed the death benefits exclusion and requires employers to obtain consent and give notice to employees before being able to exclude death benefits from gross income. Still, loopholes exist that allow large companies to abuse COLI, and Congress' actions do nothing to address the problem of companies not truly having an insurable interest in their employees.
States should amend insurance interest statutes to explicitly block a company from insuring its employees. In addition, Congress should amend the PPA to remove the tax benefits companies receive for COLI policies. The author believes those steps are unlikely to be politically feasible or popular, but current efforts have not gone far enough to stop "dead peasant" insurance.
Source: Insurance Law and Litigation Week, 03/17/2014
Copyright © 2014 by Strafford Publications, Inc. http://www.straffordpub.com/ All rights reserved. Storage, reproduction or transmission by any means is prohibited except pursuant to a valid license agreement.
]]></text></news-item>