<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-8TK1-JCTS-G1H7"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Ken Braun: Dave Agema sees 'genocide' by 'homosexual agenda' against African Americans - What's next? </title><source>Jackson Citizen Patriot (Michigan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[URL: http://www.mlive.com/lansing-news/index.ssf/2014/03/ken_braun_dave_agema_paranoia.html
An "event horizon" is the spot near a collapsing star where gravity becomes so intense even light cannot escape. Dave Agema, the Michigan Republican National Committeeman, serves a similar purpose. He captures ridiculous statements flying within his orbit of paranoia and sucks them down as his own.
Flint activist Stacy Swimp has provided the most malicious assist yet.
Swimp has more than 10,000 Facebook followers and recently appeared on Detroit FOX-2's weekend newsmaker program. In February, USA Today quoted him in strong opposition to same-sex marriage outside the federal courtroom in Detroit where Michigan's ban is on trial.
Earlier this month, Swimp posted an essay with a incendiary title: "Genocide Alert: Homosexuality Systematically Killing Black Americans!"
"Good article, Stacy," chimed in Agema with a March 6 Facebook post referencing Swimp's original title. "I wonder how Ken Braun ... will spin this to serve his agenda!"
Briefly, Swimp presents statistics showing gay men having a higher incidence of HIV infection and mixes this with additional unfortunate statistics regarding HIV and African- Americans. With this, Swimp proclaims the "homosexual agenda" can "rightly be identified as genocidal against black Americans."
"By pushing a behavior, homosexuality, that spreads the HIV/AIDS disease disproportionately in the black community," he writes, "homosexuals, lesbians and their advocates are exacerbating the culture of death in the black community and furthering their systematic genocide of black men and women."
To state the obvious, "genocide" is one of the most violent nouns in the English language and has just one specific meaning: "the policy of deliberately killing a nationality or ethnic group."
As if repeating the word "genocide" didn't get his point across, Swimp tosses in "systematic."
This needs no spin. Swimp is clearly convinced gay men and women are behind the mass extermination of black people in America. GOP committeeman Agema endorses this message and dares critics to challenge it.
Well, if this accusation had been made against Christians and supported by a Democratic committeeman, would it be right to demand a resignation?
It's vaguely possible Swimp and Agema don't know the potent implication of repeatedly using words and phrases such as "genocide," and "systematically killing."
They might not realize their vile allegation could be spun around and pointed in the other direction. HIV began its killing spree in majority-black Africa, so a hateful neo-Nazi could just as foolishly use Swimp's data to accuse blacks of killing gays.
Ironically, Agema began his reign of error a year ago this month by witlessly repeating lies from a source that turned out to be a neo-Nazi Holocaust denier. Using information fabricated by that racist denier of the event that literally gave rise to the word "genocide," Agema passed along absurd claims such as "Homosexuals are ... 19 times more likely to die in a traffic accident."
In his misadventures since, he has accused gay American Airlines flight crews of cheating the company health insurance and told us no Muslim has ever made a positive contribution to America.
Calls for his resignation from prominent Republicans have failed. Emboldened and more outlandish, he now defiantly endorses a theory that homosexuals are systematically mass-killing African-Americans.
That is hard to top: Could he raise the bar, maybe if someone in his orbit accuses lesbians of gathering to feast on the still-beating hearts of infants?
Leave him in place and we'll surely find out.
-- Ken Braun, director of policy for InformationStation.org, is an MLive columnist. He was an aide for a Republican lawmaker in the Michigan House and worked for the Mackinac Center for Public Policy.
@la-river @lansing-news @mlive-news @mlive-opinion @mlive-river Dave Agema Ken Braun
]]></text></news-item>