<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-C821-JCM0-64MG"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Senate to inquire into Government's environmental offset policy</title><source>ABC Transcripts (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TICKY FULLERTON, PRESENTER: Years of protests against an open-cut coal mine in northern New South Wales have in part led to a Senate inquiry into the Federal Government's environmental offset policy.
Under Australian law when major mining projects disrupt the environment, alternative sites of equal biodiversity value must be purchased and protected.
Community opposition to Whitehaven's Maules Creek Mine grew because independent assessments of the mine's environmental offset purchases claimed the company's evaluation was flawed.
Whitehaven says they've met all of their obligations under the offset policy.
Ginny Stein reports.
GINNY STEIN, REPORTER: A holy alliance of sorts but one that police were always certain to break apart.
THEA ORMEROD, HEAD OF RELIGIOUS RESPONSE TO CLIMATE CHANGE: Religious beliefs are a bit beyond the law. We have higher principles that we're working for. I actually serve God before I serve man.
BYRON SMITH, REV, ANGLICAN CHURCH, PADDINGTON: As a follower of Jesus, he tells me to love God and love my neighbour and this mine gives respect to our creator and harms my neighbours.
GINNY STEIN: The arrest of three religious leaders bringing an end to this latest protest at a mine being carved out of a State forest in northern New South Wales. The proposed mine has created a broad church of opponents. Farmers, environmentalists, and Aboriginal elders have also come together to oppose the expansion of coal mining in an area where cropping and beef have long held sway.
CLIFFORD KEDDIE, WALLACE MAULES CREEK FARMER: Perhaps we can both see the extreme damage being done to the environment. I've always been a conservationist, not a greenie sort of thing. I believe in a balanced nature, as well as a balanced farm, sort of thing.
GINNY STEIN: The hills ringing the Liverpool Plains are full of coal and the Laird State Forest is no exception. One open-cut coal mine is already up and running inside the forest. Now work has begun on another. Whitehaven's Maules Creek Mine is the largest open-cut coal mine under construction in Australia.
(Extract from Whitehaven Coal Statement)
VOICEOVER: The Maules Creek mine will clear approximately 1600 hectares of a state Forest that has long been designated for mining and forestry under the Brigalow and Nandewar Community Conservation Area Agreement.
(End of extract)
GINNY STEIN: To gain the right to mine in the forest, the company had to make guarantees under the Federal Government's environmental offset program. Whitehaven agreed to purchase land, designated as like for like, to compensate for the critically endangered habitat it's about to remove. Phil Spark is a local ecologist and head of the Northern Inland Council for the Environment.
PHIL SPARK, PRES, NORTHERN INLAND COUNCIL FOR THE ENVIRONMENT: That should be good there. Can record all the bats that fly over it tonight so we'll come back and pick it up in the morning.
GINNY STEIN: He says the obligation to buy land containing endangered tree species wasn't met.
PHIL SPARK: With what we've looked for, it's looking like about five per cent correct. That's 95 per cent incorrect so that's really, really wrong. This is not just a fudge. This is just - this is really the extreme.
GINNY STEIN: Not a little bit wrong, a real lot wrong?
PHIL SPARK: This is what I call Royal Commission wrong.
JOHN HUNTER, LANDSCAPE ECOLOGIST, UNIVERSITY OF NEW ENGLAND: This is a complete contrast to the offset area we've just been and seen. You can see it's very open.
GINNY STEIN: Fearing he wouldn't be believed, Phil Spark enlisted help from experts. At least four separate independent reports have now been written and they all agree the company's environmental offset assessors got it wrong.
JOHN HUNTER: How wrong it is, is on several levels, it's not just that it's not white box woodland or that it's box gum woodland of any kind of type. But also the other map types that they have there, the dominants just aren't what they say they are.
GINNY STEIN: John Hunter is a landscape ecologist, an adjunct Professor in Geology at the University of New England.
He says part of what the company plans to remove is a large section at the last remaining fraction of white box grassland left in Australia.
JOHN HUNTER: What we're talking about, about is 0.1 per cent, is 0.1 in good condition. We can remedy that by trying to help less good condition patches become good condition. But when you only have that much left in really good condition, that's the stuff you really need to hold onto.
GINNY STEIN: Whitehaven did not want to be interviewed about its offset program. Instead it provided written answers to a number of questions.
(Extract from Whitehaven Coal Statement)
VOICEOVER: Whitehaven considers that 'desktop' analyses which have surveyed a tiny fraction of our approximately 9,000 hectares of offset properties, are a totally inadequate basis on which to make scientifically accurate or credibly judgements about the overall adequacy of the package.
(End of extract)
GINNY STEIN: Whitehaven's critics stand by their assessments. And won't back down.
JOHN HUNTER: I've worked for offsetting, I have worked for offsetting for mining companies in this region. So you know, I am actually on the front ground of this kind of process. I just want to see it done right.
GINNY STEIN: The outcry over Whitehaven's offset properties has thrust both the company and the government's program into the spotlight. A Senate inquiry has just been announced. It's due to report back in June.
Ginny Stein, Lateline.
TICKY FULLERTON: You can hear more about the Maules Creek Mine development on background briefing on Radio National this Sunday morning.
EDITOR'S NOTE (Saturday 15 March): This story originally said the Government had announced an inquiry into its environmental offset policy, in fact, the Greens and Labor combined in the Senate to initiate the inquiry.
WHITEHAVEN COAL STATEMENT IN RESPONSE TO GINNY STEIN'S QUESTIONS:
Q1. Why has Whitehaven not released the report it gave to the Federal Government at the end of December?
The company met its principal obligation to deliver the report to the Federal Government by 30 December 2013. The approval conditions stipulate that the report should, in consultation with the Government, be made public but do not establish any timelines or deadlines for its release. Whitehaven takes the view that the appropriate time to release the report publicly is after the Government has considered its contents and made a determination as to the overall adequacy of the package being proposed. Whitehaven consulted with the Government on this approach.
The process of review and audit undertaken to date has been completely transparent. Further, the Department of the Environment is the proper regulatory authority in this instance to make determinations about the overall adequacy of the offsets package. Opponents of Maules Creek have expressed many perspectives on the package, and have been afforded every opportunity to contribute these perspectives, but it is the Department of the Environment which is the impartial determining authority in this matter.
Q2. Does Whitehaven accept complaints levelled at it that the offsets it procured fail on the basis of not meeting 'like for like' criteria?
No. There is no substantive evidence to suggest that the offsets package Whitehaven has proposed will not comply with the framework that regulates the quality of offset land. Whitehaven considers that 'desktop' analyses which have surveyed a tiny fraction of our approximately 9,000 hectares of offset properties, are a totally inadequate basis on which to make scientifically accurate or credible judgements about the overall adequacy of the package.
It should be remembered that the process of identifying, acquiring and assessing offsets has now been going on for nearly four years. The package has been the subject of significant scrutiny, having been publicly exhibited and considered by a range of State and Federal government agencies.
The Maules Creek mine will clear approximately 1600 hectares of a State Forest that has long been designated for mining and forestry under the Brigalow and Nandewar Community Conservation Area Agreement. To compensate for the disturbance of these 1600 hectares, nearly 10,000 hectares of land of similar habitat and ecological value will be set aside for conservation in perpetuity.
Q3. Does Whitehaven believe the Cumberland Ecology (CE) Report to be a true assessment?
Whitehaven believes the basis of the CE work was appropriate for the purposes of its offsets package. It does not consider that a desktop assessment conducted by one dissenting ecologist, or a cursory survey conducted by another, come close to being a sound platform for critiquing the extensive field work undertaken by CE.
Q4. Is Whitehaven prepared to take additional steps to protect the area listed as CEEC?
Whitehaven is totally committed to complying with all regulations for the protection of CEEC now and into the future.
]]></text></news-item>