<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-KGS1-JCMN-Y057"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>3 Things You Shouldnrsquo;t Do To Rid Your Company Of A Union</title><source>Mondaq</source><author>Mr Howard Levitt</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 17, 2014 (Mondaq:http://mondaq.com/ Delivered by Newstex) The Ontario Labour Relations Board recently issued a decision against Richtree Markets Restaurant. Richtree's loss was predictable, even to people like me, who believe unions are on a steep decline toward eventual virtual extinction.
Any opportunity to de-unionize causes most employers to salivate. But they must be smart about how they do it. The advice which lead Richtree to take its position was simply wrong. I said so publicly when the union first brought its unfair labour practice charge.About 50 unionized employees of the Richtree restaurant at the Toronto Eaton Centre were terminated when the restaurant was relocated, likely for good reason and profitability. However, someone told Richtree the best way to save money would be to argue that the unionized rights of the fired employees did not apply at the new location down the hall from the old one.When the new location opened, the union filed a complaint, asking the OLRB to sanction the company. Once an employer is unionized, the unit of employees is generally defined by geographical scope; the scope could be large (ie. all of Manitoba), or small (ie. a street corner). In this case, Richtree argued that the scope was limited to the precise location within the Eaton Centre where its restaurant used to be.The decision hinged on a combination of common sense and the extent to which the labour board would allow a group of unionized employees to be rendered jobless. Richtree assumed it could win the case on a technicality mdash; a position that was ludicrous, from a legal and public policy standpoint.In its decision, the board commented on the address cited in the collective agreement to define geographical scope and ruled it was essentially a proxy to include the entire Eaton Centre.In practice, this means if the collective agreement representing the employees from the old Richtree location still survives (meaning it has not expired) it will now apply to all the new non-union employees at its new location. It voids any individual employment contracts they might have with Richtree. This could be financially damaging for Richtree as the individual non-union agreements employment contracts likely had lower wages, benefits, paid sick days, etc.Among the financial blows to Richtree, there is also the "just cause" provision for discipline and dismissal in collective agreements. Without this the employer can fire employees for any or no reason at all as long as there is no violation of the Human Rights Code. Now, they will have to prove cause for discharge or risk re-instatement. Richtree best knows the implications of this decision. After all, it used to be their collective agreement.The win likely came at a cost for the union, too. At least a few, if not most, of the new employees at the restaurant's new location will lose their jobs because most collective agreements have recall rights if employees are laid off. Richtree may have to recall the old employees in accordance with the provisions in the collective agreement and terminate the new ones if there are not enough jobs to go around triggering costs and bad will all around.Lessons for employers:You can't close your operations, open a new one a few metres away and throw out the union.Refrain from doing anything blatantly and inherently unfair in your battles with unions. In this case, the Ontario Labour Relations Board likely wanted to send a strong cautionary message to employers looking to displace unionized employees on technicalities.Be conscious of your public image: There is something about collectively terminating a group of people (in this case mostly immigrants) that garners a great deal of public sympathy and antipathy toward your product or service.This article originally appeared in the Financial Post.The content of this article is intended to provide a general guide to the subject matter. Specialist advice should be sought about your specific circumstances. Mr Howard LevittLevitt Grosman LLP480 University Ave., Suite 1600OntarioTorontoM5G 1V2CANADA Tel: 416594 3900Fax: 416597 3396E-mail: info@levittgrosman.comURL: www.levittgrosman.comClick Here [1] for related articles (c) Mondaq Ltd, 2014 - Tel. +44 (0)20 8544 8300 - http://www.mondaq.com[2] [1]: http://www.mondaq.com/search/relate.asp?article_id=300154online_host_id=0 [2]: http://www.mondaq.com/default.asp?online_host_id=22id=300154

]]></text></news-item>