<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-C821-JCM0-64NC"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>ICAC examines muddy waters</title><source>ABC Transcripts (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EMMA ALBERICI, PRESENTER: The New South Wales corruption inquiry has heard that people from both sides of politics stood to benefit from a planned corrupt deal with a water company.
Among the allegations, that a senior Liberal figure stood to bank as much as $20 million from a company linked to the family of former state Labor minister Eddie Obeid.
The fallout has already begun, with the NSW Liberal Party pledging to refund tens of thousands of dollars of tainted donations.
Reporter Liv Casben has more.
LIV CASBEN, REPORTER: Here we go again.
GEOFFREY WATSON, COUNSEL ASSISTING: The inquiry which starts today is yet another investigation into allegations of the misuse of political power for personal gain.
LIV CASBEN: And again former MP Eddie Obeid is front and centre.
GEOFFREY WATSON: If the Obeids owned 30 per cent of Australian Water Holdings, they stood to make somewhere between $30 million and $60 million if the PPP went through. If he was lobbying politicians on behalf of Australian Water Holdings at a time when he knew that his family owned 30 per cent of the share capital, then he may have been acting corruptly. And he was lobbying and lobbying hard.
LIV CASBEN: What's at issue is Australian Water Holdings public-private partnership proposal with Sydney Water and the role of this man, the company's CEO, Nick Di Girolamo.
NICK DI GIROLAMO, CEO, AUSTRALIAN WATER HOLDINGS: It's inappropriate more me to say anything at the moment.
LIV CASBEN: The commission was told as a close friend of Eddie Obeid, he relentlessly lobbied politicians for a water contract in Sydney's north-west that stood to make millions. The ICAC heard that with Di Girolamo at the helm, administration costs charged to Sydney Water ballooned while political donations to the Liberal Party were disguised as expenses for Sydney Water.
GEOFFREY WATSON: Australian Water Holdings were making big donations to the Liberal Party - $20,000 here, $30,000 there - and on what I have seen, those donations were bundled up into the expenses and charged back to Sydney Water. From the records I have seen, it seems that Sydney Water has unwillingly, unknowingly been a principal donor to the Liberal Party.
LIV CASBEN: Federal Assistant Treasurer Arthur Sinodinos was also named. In October, 2008, Mr Di Girolamo organised for Arthur Sinodinos to join the board of directors at Australian Water Holdings. At the time, Mr Sinodinos was the Treasurer of the NSW branch of the Liberal Party. The commission heard, as a director of the company, he received $200,000 a year for 100 hours work and that he stood to make up to $20 million if the lucrative State Government contract was awarded to Australian Water Holdings.
The inquiry alleges corruption at the highest level of government, with an accusation that a draft cabinet minute was doctored by former Labor ministers which would have boosted the value of Australian Water Holdings by as much as $200 million.
Those former NSW ministers are Tony Kelly and Joe Tripodi.
GEOFFREY WATSON: The purpose was to trick the cabinet into approving a transaction which would have handed over the control of water infrastructure in the north-west Sydney to Australian Water Holdings. Had it succeeded, the onus of that company would have reaped a massive windfall profit.
LIV CASBEN: But the plan didn't get through. It was quashed by the then-NSW Premier, Kristina Keneally.
Both sides of politics are in the frame at this inquiry, which will hear from 40 witnesses over the next three weeks.
Liv Casben, Lateline.
]]></text></news-item>