<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-P041-JCBF-231N"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Coal ash ponds in Chatham County under scrutiny</title><source>The News &amp; Observer (Raleigh, North Carolina)</source><author> Craig Jarvis; cjarvis@newsobserver.com</author><text><![CDATA[State environmental regulators are investigating why Duke Energy was pumping wastewater from two coal ash ponds at its retired Cape Fear plant in Chatham County last week.
The pumps were discovered by Waterkeeper Alliance, an environmental group that was documenting evidence of seepage along the Cape Fear River. The organization says the five coal ash ponds at the plant are a hazard because federal officials rated them in “poor condition.”
Donna Lisenby with Waterkeeper Alliance said it sent an airplane over the plant on March 10 and spotted two pumps in place at two ponds. Later in the week, its members took a small motor boat up the Cape Fear River to get a closer look at the site, but were turned by back Duke employees and a Chatham County sheriff’s deputy.
Duke Energy said Monday that it was performing routine maintenance on the ponds, and that it had notified state regulators of that plan in August.
Drew Elliot, communications director for the state Department of Environment and Natural Resources, on Sunday told The News & Observer that the agency didn’t yet know if the pumping was permitted or not.
“Our inspectors noticed this pumping during an on-site inspection ... and we are investigating the utility’s actions,” Elliot said in a statement. Elliot said inspectors went out on March 11.
“While routine maintenance is allowed under the permit, discharge of untreated wastewater could be a violation,” he said.
Waterkeeper Alliance is one of four environmental groups that prompted DENR to file lawsuits against Duke Energy to make the coal ash stored in ponds at 14 sites in North Carolina safe. It contends the state agency hasn’t been aggressive in regulating the utility.
Waterkeeper Alliance was on the Cape Fear River looking for seepage because an Environmental Protection Agency report issued last year graded the five dams there as “poor.” Only one other dam in the state, in Asheville, was graded “poor.” The Dan River plant, which spilled millions of gallons of wastewater and up to 39,000 tons of coal ash into the river in February, had been graded as “fair.” The Dan River spill was due to a collapsed pipe, not a failure of the dam.
But the EPA report only called for maintenance and additional analysis of the Cape Fear dams. DENR, in a formal response to the EPA in September, said inspections have not shown that the dams were in bad enough shape to warrant repairs.
The Cape Fear plant is the closest coal-ash facility to Raleigh, and was built in 1923. It was closed in 2012.
It is upstream from Sanford, Dunn and Fayetteville.
Jarvis: 919-829-4576; Twitter: @CraigJ_NandO
]]></text></news-item>