<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-H3Y1-DYTN-R538"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Will Ken Pruitt be forced to choose?</title><source>The Stuart News/Port St. Lucie News (Stuart, Florida)</source><author>George Andreassigeorge.andreassi@scripps.com</author><text><![CDATA[Public outcry for St. Lucie County Property Appraiser Ken Pruitt to choose between his lucrative Tallahassee lobbying business and his $133,480 a year elected office appears to have been heard by the Florida Senate.
The Senate Appropriations Committee last week approved an amendment to an ethics bill that would bar constitutional officers from lobbying activities not related to their elected offices. If enacted, the restrictions would go into effect after the next election.
Some lobbyists in the state capital have reportedly dubbed the measure “the Ken Pruitt amendment,” according to the Tampa Bay Times, because of a yearlong investigation by TCPalm/Scripps Treasure Coast Newspapers into Pruitt’s private business dealings, including his lobbying activities.
Pruitt’s firm, The P5
Group, received more than $950,000 in fees in 2013 to lobby the state legislative and executive branches, state records show. Pruitt served nearly 20 years in the state Legislature, including a two-year stint as Senate president, before being elected property appraiser in 2010.
Several Treasure Coast political activists have been calling for Pruitt to choose between his elected office and his private lobbying business since March 31, 2013, when the newspapers disclosed Pruitt’s firm signed on to lobby for Florida Crystals.
Some environmentalists suspect Florida Crystals and companies that own expansive sugar cane fields south of Lake Okeechobee are blocking efforts to send polluted lake water south to the Everglades, instead of east into the St. Lucie River estuary and Indian River Lagoon, where it harms marine life and threatens public health.
Maggy Hurchalla, an Everglades expert and former Martin County commissioner, was among those who believe it creates the appearance of a conflict of interest for Pruitt to work as a lobbyist in the state capital while serving as an elected official.
“It looks bad,” Hurchalla said Friday. “I don’t think it’s good public policy. I think he should decide which job he wants.”
Pruitt did not immediately respond to phone messages and emailed questions.
State Sen. Joe Negron, R-Stuart, the chairman of the Senate Appropriations Committee and Pruitt’s successor as the Treasure Coast’s state senator, was among the committee members who voted unanimously for the amendment that would restrict the lobbying activities of Pruitt and other elected officials in the state capital.
“I don’t view this amendment as being directed toward a particular individual or situation,” Negron said Friday. “Rather, it prospectively sets forth rules related to lobbying the Legislature.”
Negron declined to discuss how he feels about Pruitt’s dual roles as an elected official and lobbyist.
“Senator Pruitt’s service as the elected property appraiser is between him and his constituents in St. Lucie County,” Negron said.
Martin County Sheriff Will Snyder, who served three terms as a state representative, said he believes the ethics bill amendment is worthwhile because it would end the controversy swirling around Pruitt’s lobbying in Tallahassee.
“It puts an end to the question,” Snyder said Friday. “It seems to me this legislation lays out pretty clear guidelines and makes a bright line between outside lobbying and our constitutional responsibilities as elected officials.
“I like bright lines. I don’t like ambiguity.”
See pruitt, 17A
Public outcry for St. Lucie County Property Appraiser Ken Pruitt to choose between his lucrative Tallahassee lobbying business and his $133,480 a year elected office appears to have been heard by the Florida Senate.
The Senate Appropriations Committee last week approved an amendment to an ethics bill that would bar constitutional officers from lobbying activities not related to their elected offices. If enacted, the restrictions would go into effect after the next election.
Some lobbyists in the state capital have reportedly dubbed the measure “the Ken Pruitt amendment,” according to the Tampa Bay Times, because of a yearlong investigation by TCPalm/Scripps Treasure Coast Newspapers into Pruitt’s private business dealings, including his lobbying activities.
Pruitt’s firm, The P5
Group, received more than $950,000 in fees in 2013 to lobby the state legislative and executive branches, state records show. Pruitt served nearly 20 years in the state Legislature, including a two-year stint as Senate president, before being elected property appraiser in 2010.
Several Treasure Coast political activists have been calling for Pruitt to choose between his elected office and his private lobbying business since March 31, 2013, when the newspapers disclosed Pruitt’s firm signed on to lobby for Florida Crystals.
Some environmentalists suspect Florida Crystals and companies that own expansive sugar cane fields south of Lake Okeechobee are blocking efforts to send polluted lake water south to the Everglades, instead of east into the St. Lucie River estuary and Indian River Lagoon, where it harms marine life and threatens public health.
Maggy Hurchalla, an Everglades expert and former Martin County commissioner, was among those who believe it creates the appearance of a conflict of interest for Pruitt to work as a lobbyist in the state capital while serving as an elected official.
“It looks bad,” Hurchalla said Friday. “I don’t think it’s good public policy. I think he should decide which job he wants.”
Pruitt did not immediately respond to phone messages and emailed questions.
State Sen. Joe Negron, R-Stuart, the chairman of the Senate Appropriations Committee and Pruitt’s successor as the Treasure Coast’s state senator, was among the committee members who voted unanimously for the amendment that would restrict the lobbying activities of Pruitt and other elected officials in the state capital.
“I don’t view this amendment as being directed toward a particular individual or situation,” Negron said Friday. “Rather, it prospectively sets forth rules related to lobbying the Legislature.”
Negron declined to discuss how he feels about Pruitt’s dual roles as an elected official and lobbyist.
“Senator Pruitt’s service as the elected property appraiser is between him and his constituents in St. Lucie County,” Negron said.
Martin County Sheriff Will Snyder, who served three terms as a state representative, said he believes the ethics bill amendment is worthwhile because it would end the controversy swirling around Pruitt’s lobbying in Tallahassee.
“It puts an end to the question,” Snyder said Friday. “It seems to me this legislation lays out pretty clear guidelines and makes a bright line between outside lobbying and our constitutional responsibilities as elected officials.
“I like bright lines. I don’t like ambiguity.”
P5 LOBBYING INCOME
2013
Legislative branch:
$530,020 to $1,059,947
Executive branch:
$420,028 to $949,947
Total: $950,048 to
$2,009,894
2012
Legislative branch:
$450,017 to $869,957
Executive branch:
$450,016 to $889,956
Total: $900,033 to
$1,759,913
(Lobbyists report income in ranges)
]]></text></news-item>