<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-TTP1-DXCW-D2XS"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>CITY SEEKS INPUT ON EARTH HOUR</title><source>Canadian Government News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[City of Saskatoon has issued the following news release:
On March 29, 2014 at 8:30 p.m., the City of Saskatoon will be taking part in Earth Hour - a global event to acknowledge the importance of environmental awareness and action both during and beyond the hour.
This year, the City of Saskatoon has created an Online Earth Hour forum on shapingsaskatoon.ca. “Businesses, organizations, students and community members are encouraged to post why they feel Earth Hour is important and what they’re doing this year to participate.
“Our collective efforts raise awareness of climate change and promote actions that conserve energy and help reduce GHG emissions.” says Brenda Wallace, Director of Environmental & Corporate Initiatives. “Celebrating and acknowledging these efforts is part of creating a more sustainable Saskatoon.”
FREE Transit March 29, 2014
As a way of showing support for action on climate change, Saskatoon Transit is offering free transit on March 29 from 7:30 p.m. until 1:00 a.m. Reduce your footprint and save money by giving transit a try!
“Saskatoon Transit is once again proud to participate in the Earth Hour initiative by providing free Transit service from 7:30pm until last bus on March 29, 2014,” says Bob Howe, Director of Saskatoon Transit. “This free service will provide citizens who may not have tried Transit in that past, with an opportunity to try it free of charge. For our regular Transit Customers, this event is another way of saying thank you for using Saskatoon Transit.”
Post Your Photos Online
The City of Saskatoon is encouraging residents to show the world how they’re participating in Earth Hour. Residents can simply post their Earth Hour photos to their own Facebook or Twitter accounts using the hashtag #yxeEarthHour to show how they're taking action on climate change. Two lucky winners will be drawn to receive a 1 month bus pass and transit promo prize pack from Saskatoon Transit!
In 2013, the City of Saskatoon partnered with the Saskatchewan Environmental Society to engage businesses and City Facilities in Earth Hour. There were 205 participants who took part by: dimming or turning out lights, shutting down computers and other electronics, lowering their thermostats, engaging their employees and clients in environmental action, or hosting events.
To find out more about the City of Saskatoon’s participation in Earth Hour, please visit Saskatoon.ca and search under “E” for Earth Hour.
For further information please visit: http://www.saskatoon.ca
]]></text></news-item>