<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-F911-JCB2-W2NB"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Gumede hits Survé with R1bn lawsuit</title><source>Sunday Times (South Africa)</source><author>THEKISO ANTHONY LEFIFI</author><text><![CDATA[Gumede hits Survé with R1bn lawsuit
Gijima boss furious over report that he's being probed for fraud
FLAMBOYANT technology billionaire Robert Gumede plans to sue Sekunjalo executive chairman Iqbal Survé and Independent Newspapers for a massive R1-billion for publishing a scathing article claiming that Gumede was being investigated for corruption and fraud.
Gumede, a donor to the ANC and other parties, including the DA, owns 47% of struggling technology company Gijima.
On Friday, Gumede sent a letter to Survé demanding damages for defamation in an article two weeks ago on the front page of the Sunday Independent headlined "ANC funder probed".
The letter said Gumede's damages claim "may very well be the largest defamation claim ever pursued in South Africa, which claim may exceed R1-billion".
The article claimed that Gumede and Gijima were being investigated for corruption and fraud by the Special Investigating Unit.
A seething Gumede said on Friday that the Government Gazette notice made no mention of corruption or fraud at Gijima - only at state agencies, such as the Deeds Office.
"I have never been the subject, nor am I the subject, of any Special Investigating Unit investigation," he said.
Gumede's lawyer's letter said the defamation suit would be against Survé personally, as well as against the Independent Group's executive editor, Karima Brown, and others.
Survé is no less controversial than Gumede.
After leading the consortium that bought the Independent from its Irish owners last year, Survé fired Cape Times editor Alide Dasnois for prominently reporting public protector Thuli Madonsela's finding that Sekunjalo had been "irregularly" awarded an R800-million fishing tender by government.
The row between the two businessmen, both of whom are considered close to the ANC, has now bubbled into the public domain, with Gumede saying: "I hope Iqbal is not using his newspapers to settle scores against competitors."
Though Survé did not respond to requests for comment on Friday - his staff claimed he was "in board meetings" until late at night - there is no indication that Survé had any input in the article.
Nonetheless, Gumede said he believed that the article had the stamp of approval of Survé's management team because "you can't tell me there are independent editorial practices" at the group, citing the firing of Dasnois for the Madonsela report.
Gumede was also in the running to buy Independent Newspapers, but withdrew at the last minute. Survé's consortium, backed by the Public Investment Corporation and Chinese investors, snapped up the company for R2-billion.
"This is a personal attack. He's not attacking a business that is a spaza shop in a village," Gumede said. The corruption allegations had hurt Gijima as well as Tourvest, the tourism company in which his family-owned Guma holds 51%, he said.
Tourvest's sprawling business includes operating the in-flight duty-free services on 13 international airlines, including British Airways, Virgin Atlantic and SA Airways as well as running duty-free shops at OR Tambo Airport and elsewhere.
Gumede's lawyer's letter claimed that although the IT tycoon supported media freedom he "will take action against the media if damage is caused to his reputation and/or the reputation of his companies through reckless and false reporting".
He told Business Times: "[Independent] might have a drum full of ink, but I certainly have a drum full of cash. Ink runs out, cash never runs out. I will spend every iota of my blood to protect my reputation."
He claimed the "attack" on his reputation was deliberate, well-orchestrated and "worked for them".
Referring to the contracts with the Department of Land Reform and the State Information Technology Agency, referred to in the Independent article, Gumede said: "We were paid monies against valid orders, after we'd delivered the services required".
The main contract gave Gijima the job of digitising all of South Africa's deeds records going back to the 1700s.
Claiming he had been "hurt badly" by the article, Gumede launched a startling attack on Survé, saying that his rival "wanted titles - I want money in the bank".
He said that public protector Madonsela had "never made a finding against me". This was a reference to the recent report in which Madonsela said Sekunjalo had been granted the fishing tender irregularly and improperly by Fisheries Minister Tina Joemat-Pettersson.
Gijima has won a number of lucrative contracts from government departments, including Home Affairs and Land Reform, and provides services to about half of the JSE's top 100 companies.
But the company fell on hard times in 2012, when two contracts with Absa and the SA Police Service were cancelled. This led to Gumede firing Gijima's top management team, and necessitated a R150-million rights issue to recapitalise the company.
TONS OF MONEY: Robert Gumede, chairman of the Gijima Group
Picture: KEVIN SUTHERLAND
]]></text></news-item>