<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-S8C1-DY15-S0CR"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Pre-Inspection Irks Uganda Car Dealers</title><source>East African Business Week (Kampala)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Importers of second hand cars under the Used Cars Dealers Association in Uganda, are asking the government to suspend the pre-inspection of motor vehicles so that both parties can iron out their grievances.
They say that the program is costly and unfair because it makes doing business hard as it raises the prices of the cars right from the suppliers to what they sell to their customers.
Under the Pre-Export Verification of Conformity (PVoC) program government's statutory organ, Uganda National Bureau for Standards (UNBS) requires a mandatory inspection of vehicles before their shipped to Uganda to ensure they meet the necessary standards.
According to UNBS the standard specifies the safety related performance characteristics of used motor vehicles and their inspections and tests for roadworthiness.
"We the used car dealers association in Uganda wishes to request that the government suspends the mandatory inspection at port of export requirement on used cars coming to Uganda until a common understanding and modality on its implementation is agreed upon," a statement read out to journalists during the dealers meeting last week stated.
The traders have held meetings including one with the ministry of trade but they are yet to reach a genuine and realistic solution.
The traders want government to review procedure of inspections so that it is not only limited to vehicles coming from abroad but to cover even the vehicles operating in the country.
The dealers say inspection companies abroad are charging a fee, of $140 per unit on vehicles which automatically amplifies the overall cost of the vehicles up to $300 due to delays accrued and due to additional labor in facilitating the process by the seller abroad.
"This will in turn imply that even the final buyer here in Uganda will have to meet the cost, plus of course the remittance cost with bank charges," the traders argued.
"In other words, each vehicle will cost not less than one million Uganda shillings extra on the retail market here in Uganda.
Muhammad Atif Hameed, the General Secretary of the association in an interview said that where the inspection is repeated, the fee doubles.
This is estimated to average $21.6m per annum of foreign exchange earnings repatriated abroad untaxed to foreign Pre Inspection Company contracted abroad by the Uganda government.
The traders draw the figure from an average import volume of 6,000 cars per month.
Apparently 90 percent of vehicles imported into Uganda are of Japanese origin where their standards of manufacture are the highest in the world.
The trader say the government of Japan is very keen on safety ad standards including carbon emissions levels due to types of fuels and oils used.
"Unfortunately here in Uganda, there is laxity in monitoring the elements of critical nature that is meant to safeguard the health of people in this country, because of the low capacity of UNBS and poor performance standards leading to high maintenance costs for vehicles as well," the association stated.
The trader argue that the government of Japan and the international community would not put its reputation and citizens at risk of radiation contamination by allowing contaminated products move through their seas ports and neither would the ship crews would accept to transport cargo that would expose them to radiation.
]]></text></news-item>