<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-1CT1-JDN8-209X"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Bentley protest justified, say organisers</title><source>The Northern Star and Rural Weekly (New South Wales)</source><author> HAMISH BROOME </author><text><![CDATA[LOCK the Gate spokesman Ian Gaillard says direct action by protesters at Bentley is justified, because community appeals against unconventional gas are being ignored by the government.
Mr Gaillard said it was a myth that the local anti-gas protest movement was a "just a bunch of radical greenie extremists".
"A gasfield of 1000 wells is not welcomed by a majority of Northern Rivers residents," Mr Gaillard said.
"Metgasco themselves have said they want 1000 wells; with flaring, infrastructure, truck movements, fly-in fly-out workers for the drilling, and as we're seeing now where a mining camp is being established at Bentley.
"People have written numerous submissions to the government, and all we get are reassurances that this is best practice, and that the government has the strongest (CSG) legislation.
"It's not good enough; and that is why people will be here in droves," he said.
Bentley residents Ross and Rosemary Joseph live 5km from the Rosella site and have become committed to the local movement against the gas industry.
Mr Joseph said they had "very close connections" with the rural population across the region and Metgasco was "not reporting the true extent of opposition".
"We do our stint sitting up on the gates at Bentley alongside the rest of the movement. We'll be there to protest what we see as the encroachment of Metgasco into our valley without ever asking us what we think."
He has written to Metgasco's directors and met with MPs.
While he would rather not be arrested during the predicted blockade, he was comfortable with those who use (non-violent) direct action techniques.
"I would not promote it, but I would understand."
Mr Gaillard said following consultation he was hopeful the local police would reduce the 100kmh speed limit to as low as 40kmh around the drilling site.
He said despite tensions between protesters and the landowners on whose property the Rosella well is planned, the protesters' policy was not to interfere with farming activities.
He cited anti-gas film Gasland II as an example of the potential environmental impacts of unconventional gas.
"It's like tobacco or asbestos - you can't get the proof until 20 years later."
]]></text></news-item>