<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-CDJ1-DXDT-64XY"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Boss 'sacked us when we turned down a threesome'; Two sales executives who claim they were sacked after rejecting their boss's sexual advances are seeking £100,000 compensation</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Padraic Flanagan</author><text><![CDATA[Two female sales executives who claim they were sacked for turning down their boss's demands for a threesome are seeking £100,000 compensation, it has emerged.
Anna Mazover, 29, and Diana Nicholl-Pierson, 24, allege that they were promised they would get promoted if they agreed to have sex with publishing firm sales director Darren Scott, 55.
The graduates claim they were subjected to suggestive remarks and were constantly leered at while working for Mr Scott at Entico Corporation Ltd, a central London publishing firm that produces conference programmes.
On her first day in May last year, Mr Scott is alleged to have told Miss Mazover - who is married - that she had a "great body", before adding: "You are very sexy. Have you ever considered working in a strip club?"
The following evening the two women were at an office leaving party when they allege that Mr Scott asked them to have sex with him at his £1.4 million penthouse in north London.
"It would be nice if we go back together to my penthouse and have a threesome," Mr Scott is alleged to have told them. "If you have a threesome, you both would prosper within the company and get promoted."
The women, whose allegations are detailed in the Daily Mail, claim Mr Scott bragged about hiring prostitutes, taking cocaine and visiting his cousin's lap dancing bar.
He is also said to have showed the women images of scantily-clad girls from an escorts website on his work computer.
Miss Mazover claimed that Mr Scott begged her to be his girlfriend and visit strip clubs with him, despite her making it clear that she wasn't interested.
On one occasion, she said, Mr Scott told her: "I'm bored of having sex with brainless strippers. When I wake up in the morning, there is nothing to talk about. Please I will give you gifts and money, just be my girlfriend or my lover."
Miss Nicholl-Pierson, of Merseyside, is said to have reported Mr Scott to the police after he allegedly sexually assaulted her by touching her bottom and thighs.
When the women, who earned up to £3,000 a month, complained, Mr Scott is alleged to have tried to get them to withdraw the allegations before sacking them.
They have now launched an unfair dismissal claim against Entico and Mr Scott on the grounds of sexual harassment. They are seeking damages of more than £100,000.
Miss Mazover, who is the daughter of a Ukrainian businessman, is also claiming racial discrimination. She alleges that Mr Scott mocked her accent and made derogatory comments about Russian women.
Mr Scott, who is now head of international business at Entico, denies all the allegations. Miss Nicholl-Pierson, he said, was sacked for poor performance and Miss Mazover was dismissed because she was regularly late for work.
The executive told the Mail that the women were taking action only for financial gain.
"We deny all the allegations," said Mr Scott. "The police thoroughly investigated the matter and found there was no case to answer. It is completely money-driven and indicative of the compensation culture in this country."
]]></text></news-item>