<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-F911-JCB2-W2N3"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Goldrich Holdings buys some time</title><source>Sunday Times (South Africa)</source><author>JANA MARAIS and LONI PRINSLOO</author><text><![CDATA[Goldrich Holdings buys some time
GOLDRICH Holdings, the shadowy company in charge of the Blyvooruitzicht mine near Carletonville, has been placed in business rescue as it tries to fight off liquidation attempts from "arrogant creditors".
Thulani Ngubane, chairman of Goldrich and formerly involved with Aurora Empowerment Systems, said the company was not insolvent but "needs a moratorium" from "creditors who are so arrogant", merely three months after it was named the preferred bidder of the Blyvoor mine surface operations and processing plant.
"The body is in ICU to keep it warm so we can give it a new life," Ngubane said.
"We just need some time to put the business in the right way. The child is on life support, but we still believe it's got a life of 10-15 years ahead of it," he said.
The liquidators of Blyvoor are trying for the second time to have Goldrich removed from the premises, accusing the firm of asset-stripping the mine and illegally selling gold. Ngubane denied the claims, and said a meeting with the liquidators was scheduled for tomorrow. Goldrich was confident a favourable agreement would be reached before a court hearing on Tuesday, he said.
The Blyvoor saga increasingly mirrors the troubles of Aurora, which was awarded the bid for Pamodzi Gold's East Rand and Orkney mines when Pamodzi went into liquidation in 2009. Ngubane and Fazel Bhana, who is also involved with Goldrich, as well as president Jacob's Zuma's nephew Khulubuse Zuma, and Zondwa Mandela, grandson of the late Nelson Mandela, face claims of nearly R2-billion for asset-stripping and illegal gold sales during their time at Aurora.
In January, Ngubane insisted that Goldrich had enough funding to get shaft five operational, focus on surface operations such as reworking tailings dams and dumps, and to reinstate 400 workers. He said at the time there would be no repeat of Aurora.
"We paid our school fees there," he said. "What we've learnt from our previous experiences - it will never be repeated, I can guarantee you that."
This week, it was learnt that AngloGold Ashanti had stopped pumping water at shaft number five due to non-payment, leading to the flooding of two levels.
AngloGold Ashanti spokesman Chris Nthite said the company bought the Blyvoor 4 and Blyvoor 6 shafts to ensure its mines did not flood. It also agreed to pump water at the Blyvoor 5 shaft to preserve infrastructure for a potential future sale.
"However, when no payment was made, despite a number of requests which were ignored over several months, AngloGold Ashanti ceased pumping at Blyvoor 5."
No workers have been hired other than those doing care and maintenance. Damage to the processing plant, Blyvoor's most attractive asset, has left it inoperative.
The plant had a number of interested buyers before it was awarded to Goldrich, but Ngubane said it would cost up to R30-million to fix, and he blamed illegal miners for the damage.
Ngubane declined to comment on the security situation at the mine, where more than 30 people are understood to have been killed since Goldrich took over in December, including three security guards who were killed on duty.
He refused to comment on pictures published in the Mail & Guardian of security guards beating up two people at the mine. Both died of injuries. He said: "This is a question for security. If there is a report, I haven't read it yet. I've been busy with critical issues dealing with the liquidators."
Ngubane would also not comment on the arrest last week of former mine manager Ettieen Erasmus in connection with theft, illegal possession of gold nuggets, fraud and defeating the ends of justice charges. Erasmus, who allegedly had 1.3kg of gold nuggets at home, applies for bail tomorrow.
"The legal process should take its course," said Ngubane.
"Our story is simple. Whatever gold was there - we couldn't leave it in the plant because of the zama zamas. Nortje - also known as Ettieen Erasmus - kept the gold for safekeeping," Ngubane said.
]]></text></news-item>