<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS3-CDK1-DXDT-60BH"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Paris bans half of cars on city streets over pollution levels</title><source>standard.co.uk</source><author>John Dunne</author><text><![CDATA[Hundreds of police in Paris are cracking down on driving in the capital in response to soaring pollution levels in the city.
Only motorists whose cars have odd-numbered registration plates will be allowed to drive.
It will be the turn of those with even-numbered plates tomorrow unless pollution levels drop sharply, which would trigger a suspension of the new rules.
Ministers drew up the crisis plan after air pollution exceeded safe levels for five days running in Paris and surrounding areas.
The smoggy conditions have been caused by a combination of cold nights and warm days which have stopped pollution being dispersed.
Forecasters have predicted more warm weather which would make the problem worse.
The measure has been tried once before in 1997. Paris air quality monitoring body Airparif claims it had a noticeable impact on pollution levels.
Motorcycles are also covered by the ban which runs from to midnight on today. There are exceptions for electric and hybrid vehicles, and for cars carrying three or more passengers.
But delivery firms complained the emergency measures will severely disrupt their businesses.
French Opposition leader Jean-Francois Cope complained that the ban "lacks coherence, explanation and on the ground it's really panic".
The capital's air quality has been one of the worst on record according to French environmental agencies, rivalling the Chinese capital, Beijing, as one of the world's most polluted cities.
On Friday pollution levels hit 180 microgrammes of PM10 particulates per cubic metre, more than double the safe limit of 80.
PM10 particulates are emitted by vehicles, heating systems and heavy industry.
The government is due to review pollution levels again throughout today, before deciding whether to extend the driving restrictions for longer.
French authorities appealed to drivers to leave their cars at home.
Public transport was made free from Friday and Sunday in the battle against the smog.
Jean-Paul Huchon, the head of the the capital's transport said: "I am asking all residents in Paris and neighbouring areas to favour the use of public transport," said Jean-Paul Huchon, the head of the the capital's transport authority."
]]></text></news-item>