<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-H0B1-F0JP-W31P"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Forrest's Vatican trio targets slavery</title><source>The Australian</source><author>TESS LIVINGSTONE</author><text><![CDATA[A HISTORIC pact to eradicate slavery and human trafficking was finalised at the Vatican yesterday between mining magnate Andrew Forrest and representatives of the Pope, the Archbishop of Canterbury Justin Welby and Mohamed Ahmed el-Tayeb, the Grand Imam of al-Azhar al-Sharif, a leader of the world's Sunni Muslims.
The Global Freedom Network, representing more than half the world's people, will be headquartered in Rome.
Its action plan for its first year aims to encourage governments and the leaders of 50 major corporations to slave-proof their supply chains and boycott suppliers who use slave labour.
Mr Forrest, who launched the Walk Free Foundation in 2012 with a mission to end slavery within a generation, said he hoped to recruit the leaders of other faiths such as Hindus and Shia Muslims to the foundation.
``It will be well funded and outcomes driven,'' he said. ``It will be truly inter-religious and not concerned with doctrines, but focused on pragmatic initiatives to get the job done.''
Mr Forrest and his wife, Nicola, became interested in the issue of slavery five years ago. Their daughter, Grace, worked as a volunteer at an orphanage in Nepal and later learned it was a centre for selling children into slavery. ``It was a grave shock,'' Mr Forrest said.
Later, at a legitimate orphanage in Kathmandu, Mr and Mrs Forrest met children who had been rescued after being kidnapped and sold into slavery.
Among them was an 11-year-old girl who, after years of sexual abuse, screamed in terror if strangers came near her.
``Never a day goes by I don't think of those kids I saw that afternoon,'' Mr Forrest said.
Walk Free has found that 29.8 million people are living in enslavement, with 76 per cent of them in 10 countries: India, China, Pakistan, Nigeria, Ethiopia, Russia, Thailand, Democratic Republic of the Congo, Myanmar and Bangladesh.
]]></text></news-item>