<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-NGB1-JCF2-8380"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Toyota suspends assembly in India</title><source>The Straits Times (Singapore)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TOKYO - Toyota said yesterday it has suspended production at its two Indian auto assembly plants in response to threats against management and "deliberate" assembly-line stoppages, as efforts to hammer out a labour deal failed.
The world's biggest automaker said the move will see the lockout of about 6,400 employees at the factories in southern India.
Company and union officials had been trying to sign a new contract for the past 10 months, with the local government helping to mediate negotiations.
"In the meantime, under the instigation of the union, certain sections of the employees have resorted to deliberate stoppages of the production line, abuse and threatening of supervisors, thereby continuously disrupting business for the past 25 days," Toyota said in a statement.
A Tokyo-based company spokesman said Toyota hoped to restart production quickly.
But he could not give a timeline for any reopening of the plants, which make a range of models including the flagship Camry sedan, the Corolla and the Prius hybrid.
The two factories, near the city of Bangalore, produce about 310,000 units annually, Toyota said.
The fresh strife comes as Japan looks to boost ties with India to counterbalance China's growing influence in the region.
But the experience of Japanese firms in India has not always been rosy.
A 2012 riot at Maruti Suzuki's Manesar plant near New Delhi saw workers chase supervisors with iron rods, killing a personnel manager and injuring close to 100 other managers during a dispute over wages and working conditions.
Japanese pharmaceutical giant Daiichi Sankyo has also struggled with its majority ownership of Indian drugmaker Ranbaxy since buying it in 2008.
Last week, Ranbaxy shares tumbled following news of a second recall of its cholesterol-busting generic drug.
The company is already reeling from a string of United States Food and Drug Administration import bans involving manufacturing safety worries.
Tokyo is a major investor in India, pumping in about US$15 billion (S$18.9 billion) in the past 12 years and is involved in building the Delhi-Mumbai Industrial Corridor, a huge US$90 billion project linking India's capital with its financial hub.
AGENCE FRANCE-PRESSE
]]></text></news-item>