<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-NGB1-JCF2-836B"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Taiwan mindful of Fukushima lessons</title><source>The Business Times Singapore</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[THE third anniversary of the Fukushima nuclear disaster serves as a grim and powerful reminder why so many people in the region have developed an aversion to atomic energy. The earthquake on March 11, 2011, and the subsequent tsunami wreaked such damage that the clean-up process is still not complete. The Tokyo Electric Power Company (Tepco), which owns the plant, is struggling to find a solution for hundreds of thousands of tonnes of contaminated radioactive water.
So, to no one's surprise, large protests erupted in Taipei and in other major cities in Taiwan on the anniversary. The island is even more prone to earthquakes as it sits astride two major tectonic plates. The protesters demanded that the government immediately halt construction of a new nuclear power plant and remove nuclear waste from its three operating plants from an offshore islet and switch to clean energy.
If only a switch to renewable energy were so simple. About 20 per cent of Taiwan's power comes from its three operating nuclear power plants. A fourth nuclear power plan in Gongliao, New Taipei City, was to have been completed a decade ago, but because of political wrangling, is only now nearing completion. It is being argued that if the oldest nuclear plant were to be shut down in 2018 as planned without the fourth plant being ready to take over, rationing of electricity may become necessary. Clearly, President Ma Ying-jeou's administration is trying to keep a delicate balance on this issue. The government agrees that nuclear energy should be phased out, but gradually so as to maintain reasonable electricity rates and ensure a stable power supply.
Thus the new nuclear power plant would play a key role in buying more time for Taiwan to develop renewable energy sources and prepare the public and industry for the transition. After Fukushima, Taiwan's Ministry of Economic Affairs ordered the Taiwan Power Corporation to conduct a safety review of all operating nuclear reactors, with special attention on the design, the protection of equipment and emergency response systems. Taipower now says that most of the safety enhancements have been completed. Three final alterations are scheduled for February 2015. The fourth nuclear plant would see its improvements completed one year later, in February 2016. The measures, totalling 67 of which 56 have been implemented so far, include making the new plant earthquake and tsunami-proof.
Even so, the Ma administration was forced to defend nuclear energy via TV commercials. The public is being assured that the installation of fuel rods in the fourth plant would not be started before next year and only after all safety tests are completed. Taiwan often takes its environmental cues from Japan and it does not help matters that Tepco has admitted last year that at least 300 tonnes of tainted water were leaking into the sea every day. Worse, there is now the possibility that eventually the radioactive waste water would be dumped into the Pacific Ocean. Until the Fukushima problem is resolved, atomic energy will remain undesirable.
]]></text></news-item>