<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-F8Y1-DY93-M3FX"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>AFPTV Advisory 2200 GMT</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[We will file the following videos:
-- TOP WORLD NEWS --
+ UKRAINE
Coming up:
SIMFEROPOL, UKRAINE: Following developments after Crimea's regional assembly declares independence from Ukraine and applies to join Russia. RAW. TBC
MOSCOW: Russia reacts to Crimea referendum. RAW. TBA
WASHINGTON/ UNITED NATIONS: Monitoring reax to Crimea referendum. TBC
CHICAGO: Following calls from Chicago's large Ukrainian community for further US support against Russian activity in Crimea, city councillors are proposing several measures such as a ban on flights en route to Russia stopping in Chicago. PKG. 2300 GMT
Filed over past 12 hours:
BRUSSELS: The EU says it will freeze European bank accounts and ban visas of 21 Russians and Ukrainians as part of sanctions targeting officials who played a part in Crimea's independence vote. RAW. TBA (Presser)
- German foreign minister outlines sanctions. RAW. VID607793_EN
- French foreign minister outlines sanctions. RAW. VID607685_EN
- French foreign minister arrives for talks. RAW. VID607594_EN
- EU representatives gather for talks. RAW. VID607651_EN
- British foreign secretary says sanctions list is not definitive. RAW. VID607721_EN
KIEV: Opposition leader Vitali Klitschko warns of ethnic cleansing risk in Crimea RAW. VID607853_EN
KIEV: Reaction to referendum from Ukrainian defence minister Ihor Teniukh. RAW. VID607783_EN
SIMFEROPOL: Coverage from inside Crimean parliament. RAW. VID607780_EN
DONETSK, UKRAINE: Pro-Ukrainians avoid public protest in Donetsk. RAW. VID607747_EN
WASHINGTON: President Barack Obama warns that the United States will "impose further sanctions" if Russia "continues to interfere in Ukraine". RAW. VID607701_EN
BRUSSELS: Ukraine's interim foreign minister Andriy Deschytsya met NATO Secretary General Anders Fogh Rasmussen . RAW. VID607588_EN
SIMFEROPOL: Crimean assembly chief Volodymyr Konstantynov says all Ukrainian military units on the peninsula would be "disbanded" as part of a nationalisation of Ukrainian state property. FILE. VID606989_EN
SEVASTAPOL: Crimean assembly chief Volodymyr Konstantynov says all Ukrainian military units on the peninsula would be "disbanded" as part of a nationalisation of Ukrainian state property. FILE. VID606073_EN / RAW. VID607724 (National Guard recruiting centre)
BERLIN: The referendum in Crimea was "against international law", according to German government spokesman Steffen Seibert speaking at a press conference. RAW. VID607613_EN
KIEV: Ukrainians rally outside parliament where politicians approve the interim president's decree on the partial mobilisation of armed forces. RAW. VID607627_EN
SEVASTAPOL/MOSCOW: Crimea's separatist parliament introduces the Russian ruble as a second official currency alongside the Ukrainian hryvnia. RAW. VID607638_EN/ FILE. VID597615_EN/ FILE. VID606571_EN
SEVASTAPOL/SIMFEROPOL: Residents express happiness following Sunday's referendum. RAW. VID607554_EN / RAW. VID607544_EN
SEVASTAPOL: Images of Russian public service vehicles, including public transport and fire engines, arriving in Crimea. RAW. VID607669_EN
SIMFEROPOL, UKRAINE: SIMFEROPOL, UKRAINE: Voters in Crimea vote overwhelmingly to join Russia in a referendum that Kiev and the West have slammed as illegal. PKG. NSV. VID607499_EN - VOICED. VID607500_EN
+ MALAYSIA AIRLINES SEARCH
Filed over past 12 hours:
SEPANG, MALAYSIA: The last words from a Malaysian passenger jet missing for 10 days were apparently spoken by the co-pilot, according to the airline, providing a glimpse into the crucial period when the plane was deliberately diverted. RAW. VID607655_EN
KUALA LUMPUR: The last words from the Malaysian passenger jet missing for 10 days were apparently spoken by the co-pilot according to the airline. RAW. VID607655_EN
MANILA: A security expert says hijacking is not the "monopoly" of terrorist groups as he analyses the disappearance of Malaysia Airlines flight MH370. RAW VID607507_EN
+ PARIS CAR BAN
Filed over past 12 hours:
PARIS: The French prime minister says measures calling for alternate driving days in Paris to tackle air pollution could be extended. RAW. TBA
-The air quality in Paris has improved noticeably thanks to alternate driving in the capital, according to Airparif, the agency monitoring air pollution. RAW. VID607716_EN
- French prime minister says measures calling for alternate driving days in Paris to tackle air pollution could be extended. RAW. VID607557_EN
- Images of Parisian traffic. RAW. VID607556_EN
ROME/LONDON: Images of traffic in Rome, which sometimes enforces partial car bans, and London, where drivers must pay to enter the city centre. FILE. VID607807_EN
-- OTHER WORLD NEWS --
+ NORTH AMERICA
Coming up:
NEW YORK: Irish Americans celebrate St. Patrick's Day with a parade in New York. RAW. TBA
Filed over the past 12 hours:
NEW YORK: Fashion designer L'Wren Scott, the long-term girlfriend of Rolling Stone Mick Jagger, found dead at her apartment.
- Police, medical van and media outside apartment. VID607865_EN
- File images of Mick Jagger - VID538244_EN
- File photos of L'Wren Scott - VID607786_EN
NEW YORK: St Patrick's day parade. RAW. VID607869_EN
UNKNOWN LOCATION: General Motors CEO Mary Barra admits "something went wrong" and that "terrible things happened" following a second massive recall in two months, amid a growing scandal over the safety of the firm's vehicles. RAW. VID607832_EN
WASHINGTON: Barack Obama tells Palestinian leader Mahmud Abbas that both he and Israeli leaders must make tough political decisions and take "risks" for peace. RAW. VID607770_EN
WASHINGTON: The US capital and nearby states were blanketed by some of the heaviest snows of the season. RAW. VID607739_EN
+ LATIN AMERICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
CARACAS: Venezuela's authorities deploy hundreds of security forces, including troops in combat gear, into an opposition stronghold to stamp out protests against the leftist government of President Nicolas Maduro. RAW. VID607820_EN / VID607846_EN
+ EUROPE
Filed over past 12 hours:
PARIS: Stars of "Captain America: The Winter Soldier" including Scarlett Johansson, Samuel L. Jackson and Chris Evans walk the red carpet. RAW. VID607867_EN
BERLIN: Germany and Italy hold talks, with new Prime Minister Matteo Renzi bringing six members of his cabinet to Berlin. RAW. VID6077819_EN
LONDON: Vodafone agrees to buy Spanish cable firm Ono. FILE. VID548354_EN
PARIS: Members of the "Hamidovic clan", the largest child pickpocketing ring in France, are appealing against their convictions. RAW. VID607715_EN
BELGRADE: With a resounding election victory under its belt, Serbia's centre-right SNS party must now forge ahead with tough economic reforms as it plots a course into the EU, analysts said . RAW. VID607496_EN/ RAW. VID607633_EN (Analyst)
GENEVA: A landmark commission of inquiry on North Korea presents its hard-hitting report to the UN Human Rights Council. RAW. VID607586_EN
PARIS: Altice, the company negotiating to buy SFR, said it would invest three billion euros in France as part of the deal. RAW. VID607647 EN
MUNICH: German football legend and former Bayern Munich boss Uli Hoeness is to go to jail for tax fraud after prosecutors said Monday they would not appeal the verdict. FILE. VID605206_EN/ VID566899_EN
+ AFRICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
BUULA BURDE, SOMALIA: A convoy of the African Union's AMISOM force targeted by a car bomb just outside Mogadishu. Recent file footage. FILE. VID607810_EN
ABIDJAN: Ivory Coast begins first census in 16 years. RAW. VID607693_EN
PRETORIA: Oscar Pistorius was in the process of buying six guns at the time he shot dead his girlfriend Reeva Steenkamp, more than usually allowed under South African law, his murder trial hears. RAW. VID607546_EN (Arrivals) / VID607650_EN (Court scenes)/ RAW. VID607691_EN
+ MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
GHARDAIA, ALGERIA: Sectarian clashes have devastated a local market. RAW. 607699_EN
JERUSALEM: Israelis in Jerusalem celebrate Purim. RAW. VID607658_EN
RAMALLAH, PALESTINIAN TERRITORIES: A demonstration in support of President Abbas going into peace talks gathers in the West Bank. RAW. VID607625_EN
AT SEA: US Navy Seals board and take control of a North Korea-flagged tanker that had loaded crude oil at a port held by rebels in eastern Libya, the Pentagon says. FILE. VID607533_EN
AL-NABI OTHMAN, LEBANON: A suicide car bomb attack killed four people late Sunday in an area dominated by the powerful Shiite movement Hezbollah near the Syrian border. RAW. VID607535_EN
Still available:
GHARDAIA, ALGERIA: Sectarian clashes have rocked this UNESCO World Heritage site. RAW. VID607457_EN
+ ASIA-PACIFIC
Coming up:
MANILA: Media tour of US 7th Fleet flagship USS Blue Ridge as it begins a four-day port call to Manila. RAW. 0800 GMT
Filed over past 12 hours:
TOKYO: The head of the UN nuclear watchdog says his agency will keep working to improve safety after the Fukushima crisis, but no atomic plant could be "100 percent" safe from natural disasters. RAW. VID607539_EN
PYONGYANG: The crimes of North Korea's regime are as chilling as those of the Nazis, the apartheid regime or Cambodia's Khmer Rouge, the United Nations says. FILE. VID598405_EN/ RAW. VID607586_EN
-- SPORT --
Coming up:
AFPTV is launching a new service on Europe's main football leagues covering key games of the week in England, Germany, Spain, France and Italy. This service will be available upon request as a special subscription.
MUNICH, GERMANY: Post-match reax after Bayern Munich take on Leverkusen in the Bundesliga. RAW. TBA
QUITO: Interview with Ecuador football coach Reinaldo Rueda. Ecuador will face France, Switzerland and Honduras in the group stages of the World Cup. RAW. 2300 GMT
Filed over past 12 hours:
MADRID: Pre-match training and pressers ahead of second leg last 16 Champions League match between Real Madrid and Schalke. RAW. VID607665_EN (Madrid) / VID607830_EN (Schalke)
-- FEATURES --
Filed:
PARIS: As part of the celebrations for the French National Orchestra's 80th anniversary, classical composer Philippe Fenelon has written a piece of music on Stone Age instruments. The concerts in Paris are the first time these sounds will have been heard in around 10,000 years. PKG. NSV. VID606775_EN - VOICED. VID606776_EN
Contact:
London desk: +44 207 776 2768
Hong Kong desk: +852 2829 6216
Nicosia desk: +357 22 391 453
Washington desk: +1 202 414 0550
Montevideo desk: +598 2 900 5095 ext 257
For contact via email: afptv-en@afp.com
]]></text></news-item>