<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-7HW1-F11P-X43W"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Cihan News Agency Diary</title><source>Cihan News Agency (CNA)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ISTANBUL (CIHAN)- Cihan News Agency Diary GMT: 18:00 Cihan News Agency latest on Monday, March 17, 2014 Here are the main Video News items Cihan News Agency aims to cover today. TOP NEWS INTERVIEW WITH PROMINENT ISLAMIC SCHOLAR GÜLEN: Turkish Islamic Scholar Fethullah Gülen who has been remained silent for long time, has commented on the agenda items in the country. Gülen has responded questions that everyone wonder from 17 December corruption scandal to release of Ergenekon convicts, from slanderous accusations and defamations directed at him to local elections which will be held on March 30.
EXPECTED MISSING MALAYSIAN JET: Developments about missing Malaysian Airlines plane will be followed. DAVUTOGLU/KIRIMLIOGLU: Foreign Minister Ahmet Davutoglu will convene with Mustafa Abdulcemil Kirimoglu, former chairman of the Mejlis (assembly) of the Crimean Tatar People. A press meeting will be held after the meeting. DELIVERED GÜLEN SPOKE TO ZAMAN PAPER: Islamic scholar Fethullah Gülen, who has inspired a worldwide network active in education, charity and outreach, has described large-scale slander, pressure and oppression his Hizmet movement currently faces as worse than that seen during anti-democratic military coup regimes witnessed by Turkey. He also calls on his supporters to remain patient and steadfast and to not despair. MAN DETAINED FOR SELLING SHOEBOXES: A man was arrested for selling empty shoeboxes for TL 1 in Aegean province of Aydin before the ruling Justice and Development Party's (AK Party) rally on Monday. Shoebox attributes a different meaning in the country after December 17th graft and bribery operation as millions of dollars were found in the shoeboxes at the state bank of Halkbank CEO's house. ACCIDENT IN SOUTHERN TURKEY: A man living in the western province of Sakarya was involved with an accident after showing off his friend that he was able to drive car backward on wrong way, which was recorded by cams in vehicle. TURKISH JOURNALIST AWARDED EUROPEAN PRESS PRIZE: Today's Zaman columnist Yavuz Baydar and one of the founders of Platform for Independent Journalism (P24) was awared with the Commentator Award by prestigous European Press Prize, an initiative of seven European foundations. TURKISH NAVY TO / CAPE OF GOOD HOPE: Turkey's Barbaros Naval Group which consists of two frigates, one corvette and a military troopship, started its long African tour with a ceremony on Monday. PRESIDENT GÜL VISITS DENMARK-3: President Abdullah Gül who has rrived in Denmark for a three-day official visit was protested by a group of people who claim he remained indifferent after death of a boy named Berkin Elvan who was shot during last year's Gezi Park protests.
PRESIDENT GÜL VISITS DENMARK-2: President Abdullah Gül has arrived in Denmark as part of an official visit at the invitation of Denmark's Queen Margrethe II, which is a first official visit paid by a Turkish president. TURKEY DOESN'T RECOGNIZE REFERENDUM: Foreign Minister Ahmet Davutoglu has announced that Turkey will not recognize the referendum, which was held in Crimea on whether to join Russia. RASMUSSEN CONVENES WITH UKRAINIAN PM: NATO Secretary General Anders Fogh Rasmussen met with Ukrainian Foreign Minister Andriy Deshchytsya following the referendum held in Crimea. UNEMPLOYMENT IN TURKEY: The unemployment rate in Turkey has reached to 2 million and 809 thousand in December 2013 period which mean the unemployment rate rose to 10 percent. In comparison with the data of the same period of previous year, 19 thousand more people joined the jobless lines. PRESIDENT GÜL VISITS DENMARK-1: President Gül in Denmark for official visit President Gül has left the country for an official visit to Denmark at the invitation of Denmark's Queen Margrethe II, which is a first visit to Denmark by a Turkish president. HOLI FESTIVAL/INDIA-2: People from all walks of life, irrespective of caste, colour or creed, joined the Hindu community to celebrate the colourful festival of Holi in Narendra Modi's home turf Surat. HOLI FESTIVAL/INDIA-1: People in Nagpur are celebrating festival of colour Holi with great fervor today. They have been celebrating the festival by smearing colour and spraying water in enjoyment. FROZEN CONSTRUCTION SITE: A construction site in the eastern province of Bitlis froze completely due to cold weather which has been highly, influential in the last two days. SCANDAL IN EDUCATION/TURKEY: Parents show great reaction to the Ministry of Education which has been questioning students and teachers at different schools across the country through inspectors with a number of controversial questions that allegedly seek to punish respondents if they hold anti-government opinions, a practice reminiscent of the Feb. 28, 1997 coup period. CRIMEA REFERENDUM: According to unofficial figures around 93 percent of Crimean people chose option to join Russia Federation at the end of referendum held at polling sites across Crimea. OTHER DELIVERED CIHAN - LIVE POSITION Slug: TURKEY SYRIA BORDER Event: Covering latest developments from the Turkish province of Hatay along the Turkey Syria border. Location 1: Hatay Yayladagi
Location 2: Gaziantep- Kilis CAIRO, EGYPT (Mobile & Studio): Cihan's complete broadcasting and multi-camera studio with transport allows your firm to access developments in Cairo, the cultural capital of the Arab World. WASHINGTON: (Mobile & Studio): Cihan's complete broadcasting and multi-camera studio with transport allows your firm to access developments in Washington, USA. FRANKFURT: (Mobile) Mobile access to one of Germany's and Europe's largest cities and points. PARIS-(Mobile & Studio): Cihan's complete broadcasting and multi-camera studio with transport allows your firm to access developments in Paris. BEIRUT: (Mobile & Studio) Cihan's complete broadcasting and multi-camera studio with transport allows your firm to access developments in Lebanon's capital city of Beirut. ISTANBUL, TURKEY - (Mobile): Follow the world from the middle of the world. Programming and TV access to Istanbul, a leading world city in art, culture, industry, media and transport. ANKARA, TURKEY - (Mobile): Full programming access to one of the Asia's leading capital cities and the workings of the Turkish government. IZMIR, TURKEY - (Mobile): TV and transport access to Izmir, a city on the Aegean Sea and an important regional leader in the fields of Tourism and Trade. KIRKUK, IRAQ-(Mobile): Mobile access to one of Iraq's largest cities and a point of cultural dialog between Turkey, Iraq. IRBIL, IRAQ - (Mobile): Mobile access to one of Iraq's largest cities and a point of cultural dialog between Turkey, Iraq and Iran. booking@cihan.com.tr Tel: +90 212 454 88 08 (24h) CIHANCopyright © 2014 Cihan News Agency.
]]></text></news-item>