<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-8H61-DYG3-30M1"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>TeliaSonera probed by US DoJ, SEC</title><source>Total Telecom</source><author>Nick Wood, Total Telecom</author><text><![CDATA[TeliaSonera on Monday revealed it is being investigated by the U.S. Department of Justice (DoJ) and the Securities and Exchange Commission regarding its Uzbekistan business.
"The common denominator for our contacts with the authorities is that we are asked for information about TeliaSonera's investments in Uzbekistan and documents related to these," said Peter Borsos, head of group communications at TeliaSonera, in a statement.
"TeliaSonera cooperates fully with all the authorities, as we are doing with the Swedish prosecutor, in order to gain full clarity on these issue," he said.
The Sweden-based telco is still reeling from corruption allegations over its 2007 acquisition of a spectrum licence in Uzbekistan via a Gibraltar-based holding company associated with Gulnara Karimova, daughter of Uzbekistan president Islam Karimov. Karimova and Takilant have been accused of money laundering.
While Swedish law firm Mannheimer Swartling found no evidence of corruption at TeliaSonera, it sharply criticised the operator for neglecting to thoroughly investigate Takilant before doing business with it. The scandal has cost a number of senior TeliaSonera executives and board members their jobs,including group CEO Lars Nyberg.
Last week, Dutch authorities raided the offices of two of TeliaSonera's Netherlands-based holding companies - TeliaSonera UTA Holding and TeliaSonera Uzbek Telecom Holding ? again in connection to Uzbekistan.
TeliaSonera on Monday said the authorities have requested between ?10 million-?20 million of collateral in the event that financial claims are made against TeliaSonera UTA Holding.
Russia-based Vimpelcom announced last week that it too is the subject of investigations by U.S. and Dutch authorities regarding its Uzbekistan operation.
Like TeliaSonera, Vimpelcom has also had dealings with Takilant.
]]></text></news-item>