<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-HC61-JC8H-K1BH"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Briefing.com: Hourly In Play (R) - 17:00 ET</title><source>Briefing.com</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Hourly In Play (R)
Updated: 17-Mar-14 17:00 ET
16:43
MOVE Move and National Association of REALTORS file suit against Zillow (Z) and Samuelson (12.37 +0.07)
Co today filed a lawsuit against Zillow (Z) and Errol Samuelson in the Superior Court of King County, Washington for breach of contract, breach of fiduciary duty, and misappropriation of trade secrets among others actions. The National Association of REALTORS and its subsidiary Realtors Information Network, Inc. joined as plaintiffs in the suit.
"At Move, we take our trade secrets and intellectual property extremely seriously as a valuable asset in our competitive position in the marketplace," said Steve Berkowitz, CEO of Move. "We take action in cases in which we believe our trade secrets have been compromised. We have raised this matter for the courts and believe that the matter will be resolved judiciously."
16:36
FCFS First Cash announces proposed $200 mln offering of senior notes due 2021 (53.62 +0.96)
Co announced the private offering of $200 million aggregate principal amount of its senior notes due 2021. The Notes will be offered only to qualified institutional buyers in accordance with Rule 144A under the Securities Act of 1933, as amended, and outside the United States in accordance with Regulation S under the Securities Act. First Cash intends to use the net proceeds from the sale of the Notes in connection with the repayment of all amounts outstanding under its revolving credit facility, to pay certain other indebtedness in full and for general corporate purposes.
16:34
GLPW Global Power Equipment beats by $0.03, beats on revs; guides FY14 revs in-line (19.95 +0.56)
Reports Q4 (Dec) earnings of $0.38 per share, excluding non-recurring items, $0.03 better than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of $0.35; revenues fell 7.0% year/year to $141.55 mln vs the $136.86 mln consensus. Co issues in-line guidance for FY14, sees FY14 revs of $525-550 mln vs. $549.8 mln Capital IQ Consensus Estimate.
16:33
SMA Symmetry Medical confirms minor fire at Sheffield, UK manufacturing plant (9.89 +0.03)
Co confirmed published reports that a minor electrical fire occurred at its Sheffield, UK manufacturing plant during the evening of Saturday, March 8, 2014. The fire was confined to the temporary Acid Shop, with damage limited to 3 tanks of a line of 9 tanks. Local authorities have confirmed that the temporary Acid Shop's structure remains intact and sound. Further, there was no damage to any other section of the plant. No Symmetry employees or first responders were injured as a result of the fire, which was controlled quickly.
16:32
IVAN Ivanhoe Energy suspends activity on Tamarack project pending regulatory clarity (0.63 +0.01)
Co announced that following a thorough review the Company has suspended activity on its current Tamarack oil sands project. Ivanhoe's decision is based on the uncertainty that there is no timeline defined by the Alberta Energy Regulator (AER) for a new regulatory framework for shallow SAGD projects, and that there is no clarity as to a path for approval for its Tamarack application. Until there is greater regulatory certainty as to a path to approval, Ivanhoe will limit Tamarack spending to only essential items.
16:32
XLRN Acceleron and Celgene (CELG) announce interim clinical data for sotatercept at 2014 National Kidney Foundation Spring Clinical Meeting; Sotatercept produces dose dependent increases in hemoglobin with no dose dependent changes in blood pressure (42.50 -2.75)
Co announced that its collaboration partner, Celgene Corporation, will present interim data from an ongoing phase 2a study of sotatercept in patients with end stage renal disease (ESRD) on hemodialysis at the National Kidney Foundation 2014 Spring Clinical Meeting. The meeting will take place on April 22-26, 2014 at the MGM Grand in Las Vegas, NV.
The data to be presented are from an ongoing phase 2a dose escalation study of sotatercept administered subcutaneously every 28 days to evaluate the pharmacokinetics, safety, tolerability, efficacy, and pharmacodynamics of sotatercept for the correction of anemia in patients with ESRD on hemodialysis. Dr. William Smith of Celgene Corporation, Acceleron's collaboration partner, will present interim safety, pharmacokinetic and hemoglobin data from the first 28-day dose cycle for two dose groups of sotatercept (0.3 mg/kg and 0.5 mg/kg) versus placebo. Following a single dose in the placebo, sotatercept 0.3 mg/kg and sotatercept 0.5 mg/kg dose groups, peak mean hemoglobin changes observed in the first 28 days were 0.1, 0.5 and 0.8 g/dL, respectively. Adverse events were mostly mild to moderate, unrelated to study drug, and generally consistent with patients' medical histories. No dose-dependent changes in blood pressure were observed. The data will be presented in a poster presentation on Wednesday April 23rd from 6:00 - 7:30 PM PST.
16:32
PBF PBF Energy announces CFO Matthew Lucey has been named Executive Vice President; Erik Young named Chief Financial Officer (26.50 -0.46)
16:31
NNA Navios Maritime announced that the co and Navios Acquisition Finance (US), its wholly owned finance subsidiary, priced $60 mln of 8.125% first priority ship mortgage notes due 2021 at 103.250% plus accrued interest from Nov 13, 2013 (3.80 +0.09)
Co announced that it and Navios Acquisition Finance (US) Inc., its wholly owned finance subsidiary, priced $60 million of 8.125% first priority ship mortgage notes due 2021 at 103.250% plus accrued interest from November 13, 2013. The terms of the Notes are identical to the $610 million of notes issued in November 2013. The Company intends to use the net proceeds of the offering for general corporate purposes, including to replace cash on its balance sheet that was used to partially finance the acquisition cost of the Nave Buena Suerte, which was previously delivered on March 10, 2014.
16:31
SFXE SFX Entertainment announces agreement to purchase Flavorus, a premier ticketing co (7.79 0.00)
announced today that it has entered into an agreement to purchase Flavorus, one of the most innovative ticketing companies in the EMC industry. SFX continues its digital expansion by adding the go-to ticketing solution for major electronic music events
16:30
UWN Nevada Gold and Casinos reschedules today's Q3 conference call; will notify the market in less than 24 hours on a new date and time (1.44 +0.03)
16:28
UWN Nevada Gold and Casinos announces rescheduling of conference call (1.44 +0.04)
Co announced a rescheduling of today's scheduled Third Quarter Financial Results Conference Call. The company apologizes for the rescheduling but expects to be able to conduct the call this week. The company expects to notify the market in less than 24 hours of the new date and time for the call.
Michael Shaunnessy, President and Chief Executive Officer of Nevada Gold, commented, "We realized that we had to adjust one of the numbers on our current quarter's financial statements which should be completed and corrected within the next 24 hours."
16:26
CHH Choice Hotels announces secondary offering of 3 mln shares of common stock by selling stockholders (48.20 -0.09)
Co announced today that certain selling stockholders, including Commonweal Foundation, Inc., a private foundation sponsored by the Bainum family, and certain Bainum and Renschler family entities, have agreed to sell 3,000,000 shares of Choice common stock in an underwritten offering. None of co's officers or directors are selling any of the shares of our common stock beneficially owned by them in the offering. Choice Hotels is not offering any shares of common stock in the offering and will not receive any proceeds from the sale of shares in this offering. Deutsche Bank Securities Inc. will act as the sole underwriter for the offering.
16:23
WRAPX Short-Covering Activity Drives Up Market
All of the fear and loathing last week about the Sunday referendum in Crimea was set aside today. Stock markets in Europe and the US rallied, not because there was a de-escalation of the standoff in Ukraine, but because there has yet to be an escalation of the standoff that would threaten global economic growth.
As expected, Crimeans voted overwhelmingly in favor (95.5% of votes cast) of joining the Russian Federation. As expected, the outcome of the referendum was not accepted as valid by President Obama and EU leaders. Still, there were two points of relief that sparked a short-covering rally on Monday:
Military force has not been used; and Hard-hitting economic sanctions have yet to be imposed President Obama made a brief speech today to discuss a signed executive order that freezes the assets and imposes travel bans on a small group of advisors and allies of Vladimir Putin and only warned that more sanctions would be forthcoming if Russia continued to push a provocative stance in Ukraine.
Things have the potential to get more serious, but from the market's standpoint, it hasn't been given reason yet in the aftermath of the referendum to fear a worst-case scenario of economic sanctions being handed down that would impede global GDP growth.
The latter consideration ignited a short-covering rally in European stock markets that carried over to the US. Gains here were fast-paced off the open as the Dow Jones Industrial Average sported a 205-point gain a little more than 30 minutes after the opening bell rang.
The early rush of buying activity was helped along by a positive showing out of China's stock market (+1.0%), which responded favorably to news of a new urbanization plan. Separately, there were reports that the People's Bank of China would expand the yuan's daily trading band to 2% from 1%. In the event of further yuan weakness, that would bode well for the country's exporters.
Basically, then, last week's main points of concern -- Ukraine and China -- were minimized, if only for a day. To be sure, plenty of questions remain about China's growth prospects and shadow banking system, as well as the path Russia will follow in Ukraine.
The gains in the US were broad-based. Every stock in the Dow Jones Industrial Average ended higher and so did every sector in the S&P 500. From a broader perspective, there wasn't any true weakness on Monday. Rather, weakness was couched in terms of which sectors were up the least. Gains for the major indices ranged from 0.6% for the Russell 2000 to 1.1% for the Dow Jones Industrial Average.
The stock market was underpinned throughout the day by quality leadership from some of its most heavily-weighted sectors. That included the technology (+1.3%), industrials (+1.3%), financial (+1.0%), and health care (+0.9%) sectors. The utilities sector (+0.6%) trailed all other sectors, but it still made a respectable showing, particularly with interest rates rising at the back end of the Treasury yield curve.
Some of the weakness there followed an encouraging report that industrial production increased 0.6% in February, bolstered by a 0.8% jump in manufacturing production. The February strength came on the heels of a 0.2% decline in industrial production in January.
Separately, the Empire Manufacturing Index for March was slightly better than expected with a 5.6 reading (Briefing.com consensus 5.4). A number above zero denotes expansion. The NAHB Housing Market index, however, still reflected declining builder confidence with a reading of 47 for March. That was up from 46 in February but below the Briefing.com consensus estimate that called for a jump to 50.0, which is the dividing line between rising and declining confidence.
Despite today's nice-sized gains for the major indices, participation in the move was unequivocally light. Just 593 mln shares traded at the NYSE versus a recent average of 706 mln shares. This was a tacit sign that today's move wasn't so much a relief rally in unbridled form as it was a short-covering move to account for a negative development that has yet to live up to its advance, fear-based billing.
Tuesday's economic calendar will feature the Housing Starts (Briefing.com consensus 915,000) and Building Permits (Briefing.com consensus 955,000) report for February, as well as the CPI report for February. The Briefing.com consensus calls for total CPI and core CPI to be up 0.2% and 0.1%, respectively. After Tuesday's close, Oracle (ORCL 38.22, +0.62) and Adobe Systems (ADBE 68.17, +0.98) will report their quarterly earnings results.
Dow Jones Industrial Average -1.95% YTD Nasdaq Composite +2.5% YTD S&P 500 +0.6% YTD Russell 2000 +2.1% YTD S&P Midcap 400 Index +2.3% YTD
16:22
RIG Transocean provides fleet update summary: total value of new contracts since the February 18, 2014 Fleet Update Summary is approximately $14 mln (38.91 +0.07)
Co issued a monthly Fleet Update Summary which includes new contracts, significant changes to existing contracts, and changes in estimated planned out-of-service time of 15 or more days since February 18, 2014. The total value of new contracts since the February 18, 2014 Fleet Update Summary is approximately $14 million. Other items include:
GSF Galaxy III - Awarded an approximate two and one-half month contract extension for use as an accommodation unit in the U.K. sector of the North Sea at a dayrate of $180,000 ($14 million estimated backlog). The rig's prior dayrate was $226,000. Estimated 2014 planned out-of-service time increased by a net two days. The ultra-deepwater floater, GSF Development Driller I, is idle.
16:21
FRC First Republic Announces 3.5 mln share Common Stock Offering (53.23 +0.44)
First Republic has also granted the underwriter a 30-day option to purchase up to an additional 525,000 shares from First Republic at the public offering price less the underwriting discount
16:20
DTSI DTS misses by $0.03, misses on revs; guides FY14 EPS above consensus, revs below consensus; Board authorizes 2 mln buyback; co files to delay 10-K (21.21 +0.22)
Reports Q4 (Dec) adj. earnings of $0.46 per share, $0.03 worse than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of $0.49; revenues rose 24.5% year/year to $37.1 mln vs the $41.62 mln consensus.
Co issues mixed guidance for FY14, sees EPS of $1.20-1.40, excluding non-recurring items, vs. $1.21 Capital IQ Consensus Estimate; sees FY14 revs of $132-138 mln vs. $142.71 mln Capital IQ Consensus. The co expects growth in 2014 to primarily come from the network-connected markets, specifically connected TVs, mobile devices and PCs. Network-connected markets are expected to represent more than 50% of total revenue in 2014. While the Company will continue to invest in key new product initiatives, through focused cost management efforts, the Company expects to drive a meaningful improvement in overall profitability in 2014. The Company expects non-GAAP operating margin in the mid-20s.
The co has filed an extension (a Form 12b-25, Notification of Late Filing) with the Securities and Exchange Commission to allow DTS up to an additional 15 calendar days to file its Form 10-K for the year ended December 31, 2013. The Company expects to file the Form 10-K within the 15 calendar days allowed, in full compliance with the rules of the SEC. The additional time will allow DTS to account for certain royalty information received late in the close process, the accounting for which impacted multiple aspects of the year-end close and independent audit process. In addition, the Company and its independent auditors require additional time to complete the required tax analysis and documentation of a complex restructuring of certain intellectual property rights that was implemented during the quarter.
DTS announced that its Board of Directors has authorized a repurchase of up to 2.0 million shares of its common stock. During the fourth quarter of 2013, the Company repurchased 0.8 million shares for $16.4 million, completing its previous 2.0 million share repurchase program announced in February 2012. DTS has repurchased a total of 6.0 million shares and returned $145 million to shareholders since initiating its repurchase program in 2007.
16:18
THOR Thoratec provides additional information related to worldwide urgent medical device correction letter regarding use of the HeartMate II LVAS Pocket System Controller (35.00 +0.81)
On March 4, 2014, the co initiated a voluntary worldwide Medical Device Correction in order to update its labeling and training materials for the HeartMate II LVAS Pocket System Controller. The following information is provided as a reinforcement of the initial release.
Failure to completely connect the driveline during the process of exchanging Pocket System Controllers has resulted in serious injuries and deaths. Patients who received the Pocket Controller as a replacement for an older model (EPC System Controller) may be at a higher risk of experiencing difficulty in the controller exchange process, as there are differences between the two controller models, especially differences related to the connection of the driveline. As of February 4, 2014, the rate of serious injury or death during the process of controller exchange for patients who converted to the Pocket Controller from the EPC Controller was 1.5% (8/523), while the rate for patients who received the Pocket Controller at the time of implant was 0.1% (1/1619).
16:16
MTOR Meritor completes redemption of all $250 million of its outstanding 10-5/8% notes due 2018 (11.72 +0.04)
MTOR announced that it completed the redemption of its outstanding 10-5/8% notes due 2018.
The total aggregate redemption price was $276,563,750, including $13,281,250 in accrued interest. The company funded the redemption with proceeds from its $225 million offering of notes completed on Feb. 13, 2014 and cash on hand.
16:15
AKS AK Steel completes new $1.1 bln credit facility (6.12 -0.03)
Co said that it has entered into a new $1.1 billion, five-year revolving credit facility with a group of lenders. The new credit facility will expire in March 2019. Bank of America, N.A., J.P. Morgan Securities LLC and Wells Fargo Capital Finance, LLC acted as joint lead arrangers. The new credit facility is secured by most of the company's inventory and accounts receivable. It replaces the company's existing $1.1 billion credit facility, which was set to expire in April 2016 and was secured by the same classes of assets as the new credit facility.
16:12
CRTO Criteo commences public offering of 5.25 mln ADSs, each representing one of Criteo's ordinary shares; co proposes to issue and sell an aggregate of 525,000 ordinary shares in the form of ADSs and certain existing shareholders of Criteo propose to sell an aggregate of 4.725 mln ordinary shares in the form of ADSs (52.11 +0.11)
Co announced that it has commenced a public offering of 5,250,000 American Depository Shares, or ADSs, each representing one of Criteo's ordinary shares. Criteo proposes to issue and sell an aggregate of 525,000 ordinary shares in the form of ADSs and certain existing shareholders of Criteo propose to sell an aggregate of 4,725,000 ordinary shares in the form of ADSs. J.P. Morgan Securities LLC, Deutsche Bank Securities Inc., Morgan Stanley & Co. LLC and Jefferies LLC are acting as joint book-running managers for the offering. Stifel, Nicolaus & Company, Incorporated, Pacific Crest Securities LLC, SG Americas Securities, LLC and William Blair & Company, L.L.C. are acting as co-managers for the offering.
16:12
RLYP Relypsa reports Q4 results (43.91 +0.29)
Reports Q4 (Dec) loss of $0.68 per share, no revenue. Net loss attributable to common stockholders for the fourth quarter 2013 was $9.1 million compared to $14.4 million for the comparable period in 2012.
Cash Position: Cash, cash equivalents and short-term investments totaled $94.8 million at December 31, 2013, compared to $54.4 million at December 31, 2012.
Outlook: For the full year 2014, Relypsa expects operating expenses in the range of approximately $75-$95 mln, including stock-based compensation of approximately $5.0 to $10.0 million. The 2014 operating expenses will be primarily driven by ongoing development activities and expansion of commercial launch preparation activities related to patiromer and increases in the company's general and administrative infrastructure.
16:11
UFPI Universal Forest subsidiary purchases certain assets of Container Systems (53.34 -1.11)
Co announced that one of its subsidiaries has purchased certain assets of Container Systems, a manufacturer of crates and containers for industrial applications and the moving-and-storage industry, located in Franklinton, N.C. The transaction closed on March 14, 2014.
CSI produces a full line of moving and storage crates, specialized crates for niche markets, and integrated packaging solutions, and is a wholesale cut-to-size panel and lumber supplier to the area's industrial customers. Sales in 2013 were ~$3 million.
16:11
ATEC Deefield Management announces up to a $50 million investment in Alphatec Spine (ATEC); Stock halted (1.60 +0.21)
Deerfield Management Company announced today that it has provided Alphatec Spine (ATEC) with up to $50 million in financing.
The financing supplies Alphatec with capital to satisfy certain obligations arising out of the OrthoTec litigation and growth capital for future commercial activities. Alphatec Spine has the option to draw up to $50 million in one or more increments prior to January 30th, 2015. With each disbursement, Deerfield will receive a transaction fee of 2.5% of the amount drawn. Amounts drawn accrue interest at 8.75% per annum, payable quarterly in cash, and must be repaid in five years. Alphatec additionally issued Deerfield 6.25 million warrants and will issue up to an additional 10 million warrants on a pro rata basis as the facility is drawn down. The warrants will expire on the sixth anniversary of the agreement.
16:10
GBDC Golub Capital announces public offering of 3.5 mln shares of its common stock (18.42 -0.72)
Wells Fargo Securities, BofA Merrill Lynch and Morgan Stanley are acting as joint book-running managers for the offering. The co-managers are Keefe, Bruyette & Woods, a Stifel company, and Raymond James.
The co intends to use the net proceeds from the offering to invest in portfolio companies in accordance with its investment objective and strategies and for general corporate purposes. A portion of the net proceeds from the offering is expected to be utilized to capitalize GC SBIC V, L.P., the co's wholly owned subsidiary, following which the Company expects GC SBIC V, L.P. to issue debentures and make investments in accordance with the Company's investment strategy. A portion of the net proceeds from the offering is also expected to be utilized to capitalize Senior Loan Fund LLC. Senior Loan Fund LLC is an unconsolidated Delaware limited liability company that invests in senior secured loans of middle-market companies and is co-managed by the co and United Insurance Company. The co may also use a portion of the net proceeds from the offering to repay amounts outstanding under its credit facilities.
16:08
LMNX Luminex announces that xMAP Technology is playing a key role in the biobank profiling research within the Human Protein Atlas project; the HPA announced coverage of over 80% of the human protein-coding genes and RNA expression data for more than 90% of the genes (19.17 +0.16)
16:07
ATEC Alphatec and OrthoTec mutually agree to settle ongoing litigation; Alphatec to pay $49 mln over the next 7 years in cash (stock halted) (1.60 +0.21)
ATEC announced that it has entered into a binding term sheet to settle the OrthoTec vs. Surgiview S.A.S. legal matter.
This settlement will result in mutual releases of all claims and the dismissal of the case in the Superior Court of California, Los Angeles County and all other related litigation matters involving the Company, its directors and affiliates. Under the terms of the settlement, Alphatec has agreed to pay OrthoTec $49 million over the next 7 years in cash, with an initial cash payment of $17.5 million. The remaining $31.5 million will be paid to OrthoTec in installments of $1.1 million paid quarterly, beginning in the fourth quarter of 2014. In addition, a 7% simple interest rate will accrue on the unpaid portion of the $31.5 million. All accrued interest is not payable until the $49 million is paid, and such accrued interest shall be paid in $1.1 million installments each quarter. Co also announced today that it has entered into a secured loan facility with affiliates of Deerfield Management Company to provide the Company with up to $50 million in financing, at co's option.
16:07
CNW Con-way announces 2014 general rate increase averaging 5.4% (39.77 +0.31)
16:06
EOX Emerald Oil announces offering of $125 mln in aggregate principal amount of Convertible Senior Notes due 2019 (6.83 -0.25)
Co announced today it intends, subject to market conditions, to offer $125 million in aggregate principal amount of Convertible Senior Notes due 2019 in a private offering to qualified institutional buyers pursuant to Rule 144A under the Securities Act of 1933, as amended. The Convertible Notes are expected to pay interest semiannually and will be convertible at a conversion rate to be determined by negotiations between the Company and the initial purchasers. In connection with this offering, the Company expects to grant to the initial purchasers an option to purchase up to an additional $18.75 million in aggregate principal amount of the Convertible Notes.
16:06
SBLK Star Bulk Carriers announces the acquisition of strategic minority stake in Interchart Shipping ; total consideration is $400,000, consisting of $200,000 in cash and 22,598 restricted common shares of Star Bulk (14.02 +0.10)
Co announced that on February 25, 2014, it acquired 33% of the total outstanding common stock of Interchart Shipping, a Liberian company which acts as chartering broker to our fleet, for total consideration of $400,000 consisting of $200,000 in cash and 22,598 restricted common shares of Star Bulk, to be issued on March 31, 2014. Interchart was founded in 1986 and under the same management since 2003, has performed over 640 fixtures. It maintains offices in Athens, Greece and employs 6 senior brokers. The ownership interest was purchased from an entity affiliated with family members of our Chairman, including our director Pappas. Also on February 25, 2014, the Company entered into a services agreement with Interchart for chartering, brokering and commercial services for our vessels for an annual fee of $685,000.
16:05
ADNC Audience announces $15 mln stock repurchase program (11.82 -1.53)
ADNC announced that its board of directors has authorized the company to repurchase up to $15 million, inclusive of broker fees, of its common stock under a stock repurchase program, in compliance with Rule 10b-18 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, as amended.
The timing and amount of repurchase transactions under this program will depend on market conditions and other considerations. All of the repurchases will be funded by co's available working capital.
16:05
OXBT Oxygen Biotherapeutics announces proposed public offering (6.21 -0.20)
OXBT announced its intention, subject to market and other conditions, to commence a public offering of its common stock.
Co intends to use the net proceeds received from the offering for furthering its clinical trials and efforts to obtain regulatory approval for Levosimendan and Oxycyte, developing its other product candidates, supporting manufacturing of Levosimendan and Oxycyte, research and development and general corporate purposes. Ladenburg Thalmann is acting as the sole book-running manager in connection with the offering.
16:04
SCTY SolarCity announces it will report its earnings Tuesday, after the market closes (73.70 -0.09)
Briefing.com Note: Recall co reported the majority of its metrics on Feb 24 but delayed its EPS release due to accounting issues with an acquisition.
16:04
BA Boeing begins expansion of 737 commercial delivery center (125.42 +2.31)
Co kicked off expansion of its 737 Commercial Delivery Center (CDC) at Boeing Field in Seattle. The project more than doubles the space that will be available for customers and groups supporting increased 737 deliveries. Production of the 737 is set to increase to 42 airplanes per month in April and to 47 airplanes per month in 2017, an increase in output of nearly 50 percent since 2010. Deliveries of the 737 MAX, with the latest technology CFM International LEAP-1B engines and other efficiency enhancements like Advanced Technology winglets, will also begin in 2017 at the upgraded facility.
16:02
DLR Digital Realty Trust announces Michael F. Foust Departs as Chief Executive Officer; Board Appoints A. William Stein as interim Chief Executive Officer (52.76 +1.24)
DLR announced that Michael F. Foust has departed as Chief Executive Officer, effective immediately.
The board has appointed A. William Stein, Chief Financial Officer and Chief Investment Officer, to serve as Interim Chief Executive Officer. The board plans to retain a leading executive search firm to immediately begin a search for a successor. Co expects to record a one-time charge in the first quarter of 2014 of approximately $0.10 per share related to Mr. Foust's separation compensation.
16:02
YY YY announces proposed offering of $400 mln convertible senior notes (81.49 +0.08)
YY announced that it proposes to offer up to US$400 million in aggregate principal amount of convertible senior notes due 2019.
The notes will be convertible into YY's American Depositary Shares (ADS), each representing, as of the date of this press release, 20 Class A common shares of YY. The notes will mature on April 1, 2019 unless earlier converted, redeemed for certain tax-related events or repurchased in accordance with the terms of the Notes. Holders will have the right to require YY to repurchase the notes on April 1, 2017 or upon the occurrence of certain fundamental changes. YY plans to use the proceeds for general corporate purposes, including working capital needs and potential acquisitions of complementary businesses. The conversion rate and other terms of the notes have not been finalized and will be determined at the time of pricing of the offering. Citigroup, Deutsche Bank, and Morgan Stanley are the initial purchasers.
16:01
AXP American Express enters into agreement to create joint venture for business travel (92.16 +1.09)
Under the agreement, co will share ownership of the joint venture with an investor group led by Certares. In the proposed transaction, co will separate its GBT operations into a dedicated holding structure, which will include certain assets and liabilities that currently comprise GBT, and will have a 50% ownership stake in the joint venture following the closing. In exchange for an investment of $900 mln in the joint venture, the investor group will hold the remaining 50%.
16:01
AVHI AV Homes notification of amendment to repurchase right for $5,402,000 aggregate principal amount of its 4.50% convertible senior notes (18.81 -0.06)
Co notified the holders of $5,402,000 aggregate principal amount of its outstanding 4.50% Convertible Senior Notes due 2024 (the "Notes") on February 27, 2014 that, pursuant to the terms of the Notes and the indenture governing the Notes, they have the option to require the Company to repurchase, on April 1, 2014 all or a portion of their Notes at a price equal to 100% of the principal amount of the Notes, plus any accrued and unpaid interest to, but excluding, the Repurchase Date. The CUSIP Numbers for the Notes are 053494 AE0 and 053494 AF7. The Company will pay for any Notes validly surrendered and not validly withdrawn with cash. The appropriate amount of cash for surrendered Notes will be provided to DTC on April 1, 2014 rather than April 2, 2014, as previously announced.
16:00
NDSN Nordson announces opening of a new 2,000 square meter technical center in Shanghai which will provide enhanced engineering, testing, training, service and application expertise to the co's large and growing customer base throughout China and the greater Asian region (71.00 +0.90)
15:30
SUMRX Earnings Calendar
Today after the close look for the following companies to report: DTSI, FF, GERN Tomorrow before the open look for the following companies to report: DSW, FDS, HTZ, YGE
15:02
HII Huntington Ingalls' Ingalls Shipbuilding division receives a $602 mln contract modification to fund construction of the Arleigh Burke-class (DDG 51) guided missile destroyer DDG 119 for the U.S. Navy (101.84 -0.51)
The modification also includes an additional $79.4 million in advance procurement for future destroyers.
14:50
COMDX NYMEX Energy Closing Prices
Apr crude oil fell $0.86 to $98.05/barrel Crude oil fell for the first time in three sessions as investors reacted to relatively limited sanctions against Russia by the West following the completion of Crimea's referendum with no escalation of violence. 95.5% voted in favor of the region joining Russia. The energy component retreated from its session high of $98.69 and brushed a session low of $97.37. It eventually settled with a 0.9% loss. Apr natural gas rose 11 cents to $4.53/MMBtu Natural gas, on the other hand, spent its entire session in the black, trading as high as $4.59 in early morning floor trade. It spent the remainder of the session trading slightly above the $4.50 level and settled with a 2.5% gain. Apr heating oil fell 5 cents to $2.89/gallonApr RBOB fell 8 cents to $2.88/gallon
14:30
GD General Dynamics: Navy awards GD's Bath Iron Works $643 mln construction contract for DDG 51 Class Destroyer (108.73 +1.10)
The U.S. Navy has awarded General Dynamics Bath Iron Works a contract valued at $642.5 million to construct an additional Arleigh Burke-class destroyer. The award brings the total number of ships to be constructed by Bath Iron Works under a multi-year procurement to five, and the total value of the contract to approximately $3.4 billion. General Dynamics Bath Iron Works is a business unit of General Dynamics (GD).
14:21
COMDX CBOT Agriculture and Ethanol/ICE Sugar Closing Prices
May corn fell 7 cents to $4.78/bushel May wheat fell 12 cents to $6.74/bushel May soybeans rose 1 cent to $13.91/bushel Apr ethanol fell 2 cents to $2.45/gallon May sugar (#16 (U.S.)) fell 0.13 of a penny to 21.95 cents/lbs
14:19
SUMRX Dollar Slips in Quiet Trade: 10-yr: -07/32..2.686%..USD/JPY: 101.65..EUR/USD: 1.3919
The Dollar Index clings to small losses as trade presses the 79.50 level. Click here to see a daily Dollar Index chart.Today's weakness has the Index lower for the fourth time in five sessions with trade on track to close at its lowest level in four and a half months. EURUSD is +10 pips @ 1.3920 as trade readies for its best close since October 2011. The single currency has been able to shake off this past weekend's Crimea referendum that made the region a part of Russia, and the cooler than expected CPI data. The 1.3850 level is home to minor support. Eurozone data includes ZEW Economic Sentiment and German ZEW Economic Sentiment. GBPUSD is -10 pips @ 1.6635 amid an uneventful session. Today's action has been limited to a 60 pip range with the pair struggling near minor resistance in the 1.6650 area. Bank of England Governor Mark Carney will speak in London. USDCHF is +5 pips @ .8730 as trade ticks off 29-month lows. Action has been trapped in a 45 pip range during today's session with trade spending most of the day pressing the lows. USDJPY is +30 pips @ 101.65 as buyers take control for the first time in five days. Data and news out of Japan were absent overnight with buyers instead focusing on the appetite for risk assets. AUDUSD is +65 pips @ .9095 as trade contends with three-month highs. The hard currency is trading on its best levels of the session with bulls setting their sights on the .9150 level, which is home to the 200 dma. The latest Reserve Bank of Australia minutes will cross the wires tonight. USDCAD is -55 pips @ 1.1050 as trade presses session lows. Action has been trapped between 1.1050/1.1130 for much of the past month with a breakdown likely putting pressure on 1.0950. Canadian data is limited to manufacturing sales. Bank of Canada Governor Steven Poloz will speak in Halifax.
13:49
COMDX COMEX Metals Closing Prices
Apr gold fell $6.10 to $1373.10/oz Gold fell for the first time in six sessions despite a slightly weaker dollar index. The yellow metal rose to a session high of $1382.90 in morning floor trade but gave up the gain as it slipped to a session low of $1370.00. It spent afternoon action trading just above that level and settled with a 0.4% loss. May silver fell $0.14 to $21.27/oz Silver brushed a session high of $21.44 in morning action but quickly fell back into the red. It settled slightly above its session low of $21.23, booking a 0.7% loss. May copper settled unchanged at $2.95/lbs
12:57
SUMRX European Markets Closing Prices
European markets are now closed; stock markets across Europe performed as follows: UK's FTSE: + 0.6% Germany's DAX: + 1.4% France's CAC: + 1.3% Spain's IBEX: + 1.7% Portugal's PSI: + 1.8% Italy's MIB Index: + 2.5% Irish Ovrl Index: + 1.1% Greece ATHEX Composite: + 3.5%
12:38
QCOM Qualcomm notches minor new session high of 77.09, hovering modestly under last week/early March/multi-year highs at 77.20 (77.08 +2.34) -Technical-
12:32
TECHX Stock indices working back toward morning highs -- S&P +19, Dow +192, Nasdaq Comp +46 -Technical-
Noted in the 10:47 update that was watching 1853/1852 for a read the health of the early run. It dipped to 1853 at 11:40 with it gradually working back toward the morning high (1862). The next short term area of interest 1862/1863 is at 1866/1867.
12:21
COMDX Crude oil and silver futures are selling off along with gold... gold and crude oil just hit new session lows
Current price action:
Apr gold -0.5% at $1371.70/ozMay silver -0.6% at $21.28/ozApr crude oil -1.4% at $97.47/barrel
11:55
SCANX Stocks/ETFs that traded to new 52 week highs/lows this session - New highs (198) outpacing new lows (18) -Technical-
Stocks that traded to 52 week highs: AAN, ABCB, AGN, ALK, ALV, AMKR, AMRI, ASRV, ATVI, BAS, BCR, BEE, BKH, BOFI, BPZ, BWA, BWS, BYLK, CAK, CBOE, CBT, CELH, CHC, CHD, CLDN, CMRX, CNL, CODE, COLB, CPE, CPK, CPS, CRL, CRVL, CUR, CVCO, CVGW, CVS, DBD, DJCO, DLB, DMND, DOX, DPZ, ECA, EMES, ENLK, ENTA, EQT, ETE, EVER, EVK, EWBC, FCH, FCNCA, FFBC, FITB, FNHC, FPRX, FRC, FSRV, GA, GAS, GB, GFN, GIII, GNRC, GPRE, GSAT, GSM, GVA, GXP, H, HELE, HI, HRG, HRTX, HST, IBKC, ICGE, IG, IPXL, ISBC, ISIL, ISR, ISSI, IT, JACK, JASO, KAMN, KNDI, KNX, KONA, KRNY, LBY, LNT, LOGM, LSG, MANH, MDRX, MEAS, MFRM, MGEE, MKL, MOBI, MPC, MPWR, MRH, MVNR, NEE, NEU, NG, NGVC, NRF, NVDQ, NWLI, ODFL, OHRP, OZRK, PAGP, PANW, PCAR, PEB, PEBO, PFSW, PKOH, PLL, PLOW, PMC, PNFP, PPC, PPP, PQ, PRI, PRTS, PRXL, PZZA, QADA, RCAP, REX, RFMD, RLJ, RLYP, RNR, RUSHB, SAAS, SAFM, SGB, SGK, SHEN, SIG, SIMG, SIVB, SOHO, SONC, SPB, SPNC, SRE, SSRI, STAA, STO, SUSS, SWC, SWN, TFX, TMNG, TPC, TQNT, TRCB, TRNS, TSH, TSN, TTWO, UA, UBSH, UCTT, UGI, URI, USEG, USMO, UTL, VGR, VLCCF, VMW, VNDA, VSB, VTSS, VVC, WEC, WG, WGP, WIBC, WLB, WLP, WSCI, WSM, WTFC, YDKN
Stocks that traded to 52 week lows: ALAN, ARO, AVNW, CHL, COOL, COVS, CZZ, ESV, EXPR, FSYS, GGS, ICA, MCGC, OIBR, PBR.A, SDRL, TEU, TLM
ETFs that traded to 52 week highs: COW, DVY, EGPT, EIS, GREK, NIB
ETFs that traded to 52 week lows: none
11:51
SCANX Notable movers of interest -Technical-
The following are some of today's most notable movers of interest, categorized by market capitalization (large cap over $10 billion and mid cap between $2-10 billion) and ranked by % change (all stocks over 100K average daily volume).
Large Cap Gainers HTZ (27.42 +5.54%): FT.com reporting co is consdering spiining off its construction equipment business for ~$4.5 bln BIIB (345.18 +3.82%): To replace American Electric Power (AEP) in the S&P 100 YHOO (38.97 +3.64%): Seeing reports that Alibaba could file for IPO as soon as April, has chosen to list on a US exchange Large Cap Losers FB (66.88 -1.25%): Downgraded to Hold from Buy at Argus STZ (81.69 -0.98%): Downgraded to Neutral from Buy at Goldman CHK (24.79 -0.96%): Filed form 10 registration statement for possible spin-off of Chesapeake Oilfield Services Mid Cap Gainers SINA (68.95 +6.75%): Filed initial F-1 to IPO its Weibo micro-blogging service WTS (59 +4.50%): Upgraded to Buy from Hold at BB&T Capital Markets, target $67 PTEN (29.99 +4.17%): Upgraded to Buy from Neutral at Goldman, added to Conviction Buy list Mid Cap Losers ICPT (395 -14.55%): Missed FY13 EPS by $0.03 (-$3.76 vs -$3.73 estimate); announced Phase 3 POISE trial of obeticholic acid (OCA) for the treatment of primary biliary cirrhosis (PBC) demonstrated that OCA, at both a 10 mg dose and a 5 mg dose titrated to 10 mg, met the trial's primary endpoint SBGI (24.37 -8.25%): Downgraded to Market Perform from Outperform at Wells Fargo VRSN (50.62 -7.71%): National Telecommunications & Information Administration announced its intent to transition key Internet domain name functions to the global multistakeholder community; Verisign said this will no affect the company's operation of the .com and .net registries
11:49
GM General Motors: Follow up to new recalls (33.82 -0.27)
As a result of Mary Barra's request for a comprehensive internal safety review following the ignition switch recall, General Motors today announced three separate recalls involving U.S. production and sales of :
~303,000 Chevrolet Express and GMC Savana from the 2009-2014 model years with gross vehicle weight under 10,000 pounds63,900 Cadillac XTS full-size sedan from the 2013 and 2014 model years1.18 million Buick Enclave and GMC Acadia models from the 2008-2013 model years, Chevrolet Traverse from the 2009-2013 model years, and Saturn Outlook from the 2008-2010 model years The full-size vans with gross vehicle weights of 10,000 pounds or less do not comply with a head impact requirement for unrestrained occupants, requiring a rework of the passenger instrument panel material. Unsold vehicles have been placed on a stop delivery until development of the solution has been completed and parts are available. Customers will be notified at that time. Repairs will be made at no charge to customers.
In the XTS, a brake booster pump can create positive pressure within the wiring harness attached to the pump relay. This pressure can lead to the dislodging of a plug in the brake booster pump relay, allowing corrosive elements to enter the connector and form a low-resistance short that could lead to overheating, melting of plastic components and a possible engine compartment fire.
GM is aware of two engine compartment fires in unsold vehicles at dealerships and two cases of melted components.
With respect to the Enclave, Traverse, Acadia and Outlook, the vehicles are equipped with a Service Air Bag warning light in the driver information center. Ignoring the Service Air Bag warning light will eventually result in the non-deployment of the side impact restraints, which include driver and passenger seat-mounted side air bags, front center air bag (if equipped), and the seat belt pretensioners.
To repair the condition, dealers will remove the driver and passenger side air bag wiring harness connectors and splice and solder the wires together.
GM expects to take a charge of ~$300 mln in the first quarter primarily for the cost of the repairs for the three safety actions and the previously announced ignition switch recall.
11:31
IMGN Immunogen announces presentations scheduled to be made at the American Association for Cancer Research Annual Meeting to be held April 5-9, 2014 in San Diego, CA (16.18 +0.38)
Co announced the presentations scheduled to be made by Company scientists at the American Association for Cancer Research (AACR) Annual Meeting to be held April 5-9, 2014 in San Diego, CA. "The presentations scheduled include the pharmacokinetics modeling work which informed our decision to dose IMGN853 based on adjusted ideal body weight and to assess it dosed weekly. They also include highly encouraging preclinical findings with both our IMGN289 and IMGN853 compounds, as well as data on some of the more recent additions to our ADC technology portfolio."
11:29
TECHX Major averages join small-/mid-caps at new pullback lows -- Dow +140, S&P +13, Nasdaq Comp +31 -Technical-
11:29
MOBI Sky-mobi announces strategic partnership with China Unicom (11.53 +1.63)
Co announced that it, through its controlling subsidiary Mopin Technology Co., Ltd., has recently entered into a strategic partnership with the Wo Store of China Unicom, the official application store of China's second largest mobile operator. Under the terms of the agreement, Sky-mobi was designated as an official business partner of China Unicom to provide customized and tailor-made software services at China Unicom's network of physical stores nation-wide. Sky-mobi's partnership with China Unicom initially covers its physical stores in the lucrative smartphone markets of Zhejiang, Guangxi and Shandong provinces, and will be expanded to cover Hubei, Heilongjiang, Hunan, Shanghai and Guangdong throughout 2014.
11:27
TECHX Small-/Mid-Cap indices slip to minor new pullback lows -- IWM +0.5, MDY +1.21 -Technical-
11:18
AUQ AuRico Gold announces pricing of $315 mln senior secured second lien notes offering (5.03 -0.14)
Co announces the pricing of its private offering of $315 million aggregate principal amount of Senior Secured Second Lien Notes due 2020. The Notes were issued with a coupon of 7.75% and sold at 96.524% of par, and are expected to result in net proceeds to the Company of approximately $297 million, after deducting the initial purchasers' discounts and estimated offering expenses payable by the Company. AuRico intends to use the net proceeds of the Notes to repurchase its Convertible Notes due 2016 that are tendered to AuRico's offer announced March 6, 2014 to purchase any and all of its Convertible Notes, to fund principal and interest payments on any Convertible Notes that remain outstanding following the offer to purchase, to repay amounts outstanding under its existing senior secured credit facility and for general corporate purposes, which may include funding capital expenditures to support organic growth.
11:10
SUMRX Currency Commentary: DXY Slides Ahead of FOMC
The Dollar Index is sliding lower despite a stronger than expected Empire Manufacturing and Industrial Production. A weaker than expected NAHB Housing Market has helped drive the dollar lower as the housing industry remains weak after mortgage rates increased in the second half of 2013. The Index is coming in to test the 79.30 level for support. The Index hit 79.28 which is only 2 pips away from the multi-month low of 79.26 set on March 13. The 52-week low of 78.99 set back on October 25 is also in focus. The FOMC is set to hold a two day meeting with a statement and updated economic projections expected Wednesday afternoon. New Fed Chair Janet Yellen will also hold her first press conference at that time. The euro remains strong despite posting an inflation number that was lower than expected. ECB and EU officials continue to try and jawbone the single currency lower but they have had little impact as market participants do not see the central bank taking any action at this time. The pound remains below key multi-year high resistance levels. Sterling was able to stem some short term selling pressure as it held the 1.66 level. It is now climbing back to test the key 1.6740 area with market participants focusing on the Wednesday morning release of the latest jobs numbers and minutes. Morgan Stanley was bullish on the pound ahead of these releases. The yen has given up some of its recent gains as there was a return to risk overnight despite the Crimea headlines. The yen slipped back to 101.85 before finding support. 102 will remain a key level of support. The yuan has slipped to an 11-month low as China expanded the trading limits on the yuan vs dollar to 2% from 1%. The news had been widely expected as the country continues its slow roll toward making the currency a viable reserve currency. China also announced an urbanization program in an attempt to spur the struggling economy. Credit concerns remain firmly in focus and a headwind (FOREX, BONDX).
11:03
CTAS Cintas revises release of third quarter fiscal year 2014 results; time of the release will now be on Wednesday, March 19, 2014 after the market close (59.59 +0.20)
A live webcast of the call will be available to individual investors and the public beginning at 5:00 p.m., Eastern Time, on Wednesday, March 19, 2014.
10:53
SO Southern subsidiary, Southern Nuclear, announced plant operators safely took Unit 1 of the Alvin W. Vogtle Electric Generating Plant offline on March 16, at 4 a.m. ET for a scheduled refueling and maintenance outage (43.66 +0.17)
10:47
TECHX S&P +14 drifts off morning high -Technical-
Noted in the 09:44 update that the index was probing the 1858/1859 resistance area with the 50% retrace of the March pullback at 1861. It edged just above to 1862.30 at 10:05 and shortly thereafter rotated lower. Watching intraday support at 1853/1852 and 1850/1849 for a read on the health of the early advance.
10:10
CHSCP CHS Inc. agrees to acquire selected Canadian assets from Agriums (AGU), terms not disclosed (30.23 -0.12)
Co has agreed to acquire selected Canadian retail assets from Crop Production Services (Canada) Inc., a wholly owned subsidiary of Agrium, Inc., a major retail supplier of agricultural products and services in North America, South America and Australia. Under the agreement, 16 retail agronomy locations in the provinces of Alberta and Saskatchewan become part of the Country Operations division of CHS. The transaction is expected to be completed on or about April 1, 2014. Financial terms are not disclosed.
10:07
KRE KBW Regional Bank ETF, Banking KBE, Broker IAI displaying relative strength in recent trade (41.38 +0.39) -Technical-
The KRE is the closest to its March/multi-year high at 41.47 (session high 41.41).
10:03
TECHX Fractional new session highs for stock indices -- S&P +20, Nasdaq Comp +53, Dow +197 -Technical-
10:01
GD General Dynamics: The U.S. Navy has awards General Dynamics NASSCO a $128.5 ln contract for the detail design and construction of the Mobile Landing Platform 3 Afloat Forward Staging Base (108.40 +0.77)
09:53
BVN Buenaventura SA announces that beginning Sunday, March 16 at 07.00 am, the Uchucchacua's contractors' unions voluntarily concluded the stoppage that began March 11, 2014; operations were resumed immediately (14.00 0.00)
09:47
CVS CVS Caremark works up toward last week's high at 73.70 and pauses -- session high 73.60 (73.48 +0.73) -Technical-
Its multi-year high/short term range top from early March is at 78.89.
09:44
SPY S&P +18 extends solid opening run -Technical-
The index has extended up to a short term resistance zone at 1858/1859 with the 50% retrace of the breakdown off the March/all-time high at 1861.
09:37
TECHX Broad based strength in early trade -- Dow +115, S&P +11.8, Nasdaq Comp +32 -Technical-
Sector strength has been noted in: Solar TAN, Steel SLX, Finance XLF, Industrial XLI, Ag/Chem MOO, Software IGV, Broker IAI, Biotech IBB, Rail
09:25
WIRES On The Wires
Cleco (CNL) announced the transfer of Coughlin Power Station to its regulated utility, Cleco Power, from its unregulated subsidiary, Cleco Midstream. Cleco Power assumed ownership of the natural gas-fired unit Saturday, March 15.SDL announced that Atmel (ATML) has selected SDL's LiveContent application suite to improve its content creation processes as part of an effort to drive end-to-end improvements in Customer Experience. Interval International, an operating business of Interval Leisure Group (IILG), announced the affiliation of Canyon Woods Grande International Vacation Club, comprising resorts in three of the most popular holiday destinations in the Philippines. Aquantia announced the completion of series G financing for $16 mln. Xilinx (XLNX) led the round and existing investors provided additional capital. American International Group (AIG) has repriced AG Select-a-Term, the customizable term life insurance issued by American General Life Insurance. Kimberly-Clark (KMB) Health Care and 3M (MMM) Infection Prevention Division announced a unique alliance to deliver best-in-class surgical and infection prevention solutions to hospitals and healthcare facilities in the U.S. NetSuite (N) announced new customer wins and strong momentum among outdoor retailers, manufacturers and distributors turning to the NetSuite cloud to improve their business efficiency and sales performance.Daktronics (DAKT) has partnered with the Carolina Panthers to design, manufacture and install an integrated display system at Bank of America Stadium in Charlotte, N.C.inContact (SAAS) announced that a large insurance provider has selected inContact to replace legacy software with a cloud solution that will support high quality customer experiences, boost contact center workforce efficiency and reduce operational costs. Prologis (PLD) has signed two build-to-suit agreements totaling 244,000 square feet in Europe. Vincent Mehdizadeh, the founder and Chief Operations Officer of Medbox (MDBX) announced that he has personally funded campaigns aimed at educating the general public as to all aspects of cannabis in medical and recreational states. Hill International (HIL) has received a contract from Jermyn Real Estate Fund IV to provide project management services for the redevelopment of the Astir Palace resort in Athens, Greece. NQ Mobile (NQ) announced a new preload agreement with PT Smartfren Telecom, a CDMA/EVDO telecommunications operator in Indonesia. NQ Mobile Security will be available from Smartfren under the name "Smartshield." VORNADO REALTY TRUST (VNO) has entered into an agreement to sell Beverly Connection, a 335,000 square foot power shopping center in Los Angeles, California, for $260 mln. The sale will result in a net gain of ~ $40 mln. ShoreTel (SHOR) announced it is shipping the ShoreTel 400 series IP phones for ShoreTel Sky, expanding its UCaaS solutions portfolio.
09:22
CPS Cooper-Standard intends to launch a refinancing of existing indebtedness outstanding under its Senior PIK Toggle Notes due 2018 and Cooper-Standard's 8 1/2% Senior Notes due 2018 (65.77 )
Co announced that it intends to launch a refinancing of existing indebtedness outstanding under its Senior PIK Toggle Notes due 2018 and Cooper-Standard's 8 % Senior Notes due 2018. In connection with the proposed refinancing, Cooper-Standard intends to enter into a $725 million senior secured term loan facility and use borrowings thereunder to refinance $200 million in aggregate principal amount of HoldCo Notes and $450 million in aggregate principal amount of OpCo Notes. Holdings indicated that the proposed refinancing is expected to materially reduce its annual interest expense.
09:21
RPRX Repros Therapeutics receives guidance from the FDA indicating that Repros may proceed to conduct Phase 1 and 2 studies of oral Proellex (18.95 )
Co reports it has received guidance from the FDA indicating that Repros may proceed to conduct Phase 1 and 2 studies of oral Proellex under two separate INDs for endometriosis and uterine fibroids, while remaining on partial clinical hold. The FDA guidance provides that the highest allowed dose will be 12 mg daily. Repros is currently conducting a Phase 2 study for the use of Proellex in severe endometriosis and plans to submit a Phase 2 protocol for the treatment of symptomatic fibroids.
Regarding the proposed uterine fibroid Phase 2 protocol, the FDA provided guidance as to the appropriate inclusion and exclusion criteria for study subjects as well as the preferred efficacy endpoint. The FDA preferred efficacy endpoint is reduction in excessive menstrual bleeding associated with uterine fibroids. The FDA also noted the preferred methodology to determine changes in bleeding. Repros will comply with FDA guidance as well as collecting additional efficacy outcomes such as tumor size and other symptomatic relief. Given the prior experience with Proellex at 6 and 12 mg daily dosages, Repros plans to enroll fewer than 75 women in a three arm, parallel design double blind trial. The study is sized to provide greater than 90% power in demonstrating efficacy associated with reducing subject bleeding.
09:18
AMGN Amgen announces positive top-line results from Phase 3 TESLA trial of evolocumab (AMG 145) in patients with homozygous familial hypercholesterolemia; study meets primary endpoint of LDL cholesterol reduction (122.54 )
Co announced that the Phase 3 TESLA (Trial Evaluating PCSK9 Antibody in Subjects with LDL Receptor Abnormalities) trial evaluating evolocumab met its primary endpoint of the percent reduction from baseline at week 12 in low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C). The percent reduction in LDL-C, or "bad" cholesterol, was clinically meaningful and statistically significant. Evolocumab is an investigational fully human monoclonal antibody that inhibits proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9 (PCSK9), a protein that reduces the liver's ability to remove LDL-C from the blood.Safety was generally balanced across treatment groups. The most common adverse events in the evolocumab group (more than one subject) were upper respiratory tract infection, influenza, gastroenteritis and nasopharyngitis.
Details of the Phase 3 TESLA trial will be submitted to a future medical conference and for publication.
09:18
WRAPX S&P futures vs fair value: +10.30. Nasdaq futures vs fair value: +24.50.
Just reported, February industrial production increased 0.6%, which was above the 0.1% increase expected by the Briefing.com consensus. Industrial production for January was revised up to show a 0.2% decline versus an originally reported decline of 0.3%. Separately, capacity utilization hit 78.8% while the Briefing.com consensus called for a reading of 78.5%.
09:18
KFS Kingsway Fin subsidiary 1347 Capital signs letter of intent to sponsor initial public offering via a SPAC (4.04 )
Co announced that its wholly-owned subsidiary, 1347 Capital, has signed a letter of intent to sponsor an initial public offering by a special purpose acquisition company to be formed by it. The offering is expected to include four million units, each unit consisting of one share of common stock, one right to acquire one-tenth of a share of common stock, and one-half of a warrant to acquire a share of common stock, at an offering price of $10.00 per unit.
09:17
CUR Neuralstem announces final results from Phase I safety trial using NSI-566 spinal cord stem cells in the treatment of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis were published in 'Annals of Neurology'; results showed that NSI-566 human spinal cord stem cells can be safely transplanted in both the lumbar and cervical spinal cord segments, did not accelerate disease progression, and warrant further study on dosing and therapeutic efficacy (3.90 )
"Intraspinal Neural Stem Cell Transplantation in Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis: Phase I Trial Outcomes," results were updated from Phase I interim data, reported earlier, to include data from the last six patients in the trial. These six patients were the first to receive cervical stem cell transplants. Three of them were also the first to be transplanted along the length of their spines, in both the lumbar and the cervical regions. The results showed that NSI-566 human spinal cord stem cells can be safely transplanted in both the lumbar and cervical spinal cord segments, did not accelerate disease progression, and warrant further study on dosing and therapeutic efficacy. Furthermore, the researchers were able to identify potential therapeutic windows, suggesting that more injections, as well as multiple injections, are better and may increase both the length and the magnitude of the potential benefits. This is consistent with the hypothesized neuroprotective mechanism-of-action for this cell therapy.
"Although this was a Phase I trial, and functional outcome data were collected for the purpose of assessing safety, we performed secondary analyses of these data as a means to gain insight into how cellular transplantation affected disease progression rates and to inform outcome assessment approaches in future trial phases," said Eva Feldman, MD, PhD, Director of the A. Alfred Taubman Medical Research Institute, Director of Research of the ALS Clinic at the University of Michigan Health System, principle investigator for the NSI-566/ALS trial and lead author. Dr. Feldman is also an unpaid consultant to Neuralstem. "Pre-surgical disease progression rates for the various functional outcome measures were calculated to create slopes for each patient, so that we could determine if post-surgical data points, at 6, 9, 12 and 15 months, improved relative to predicted points. We also did analyses to determine which, if any, functional outcome assessment most closely correlated with the overall ALSFRS-R scores," said Dr. Feldman. "Comparison of the outcome data to predicted outcome points in group E (patients who received both lumbar and cervical injections) revealed improvements in a significant number of measures at 6, 9, 12 and 15 months post-surgery. Overall, 50% of the patients in the trial showed improvement across multiple clinical measures at the same time points. We also found that a measure of grip strength correlated most closely with the overall ALSFRS-R scores.
09:12
KERX Keryx Biopharmas' Zerenex data selected for Poster Presentation at the AMCP's 26th Annual Meeting and Expo (15.11 )
Co announced that data highlighting the potential pharmacoeconomic benefit of Zerenex (ferric citrate coordination complex), the Company's drug candidate for the treatment of hyperphosphatemia in dialysis patients, has been selected for poster presentation during the upcoming Academy of Managed Care Pharmacy's (AMCP) 26th Annual Meeting and Expo, being held April 1-4, 2014, at the Tampa Convention Center in Tampa, Florida.
09:08
QPAC Quinpario Acquisition Corp reaches definitive agreement to acquire Jason for $538.65 mln (shares halted) (10.04 )
Co announced it has reached a definitive agreement to acquire Jason from Saw Mill Capital, Falcon Investment Advisors and other investors. Jason is a global family of market-leading manufacturing businesses within the finishing, seating, components and automotive acoustics markets. The purchase price of $538.65 million will be funded by the cash proceeds from QPAC's initial public offering, new debt and rollover equity invested by the current owners and management of Jason.Financing for the transaction will be led by Deutsche Bank. The financing will consist of a $40 million revolver, which is expected to be undrawn at closing, a $300 million first lien facility and a $120 million second lien facility. The purchase price of $538.65 million is a 6.75 multiple of the Company's pro forma 2013 EBITDA.
09:05
IRBT IRobot announces availability of Ava 500 (40.25 )
Co announced that the co's Ava 500 video collaboration robot is ready for delivery in the U.S., Canada and select European markets through select certified Cisco resellers. iRobot Ava 500 offers a whole new level of telepresence to the enterprise. The remote user gets the "better than being there" benefits of telepresence plus a physical presence through complete freedom of movement. The easy-to-use, self-driven robot allows people to use video to see and be seen while collaborating in environments that would otherwise be difficult or impossible from afar, including hallways and manufacturing floors. With the benefits of telepresence, Ava 500 helps globally dispersed teams work more closely together without the need for costly and time-consuming travel, enabling increased collaboration between executives, managers and employees. With Ava 500, more work gets done, more collaboration takes place and more relationships can be built. A complete hardware and software solution, Ava 500 brings together iRobot's autonomous mobile robotics platform with Cisco's telepresence solutions. It provides enterprise-class security, reliability and scalability.
09:03
MVG MAG Silver reports high-grade silver-copper-zinc intercepts from the Salamandra property, Durango, Mexico (8.62 )
Co announces assay results from its five hole, 3,500 metre Phase 1 drill program on the Salamandra Property in Durango, Mexico optioned from Canasil Resources. Drilling began in November, 2013 and in February, 2014 an additional 500 metres of drilling was added; this release covers the entire 3,500 metre initial program.
Highlights include:
SM14-15: 7.89m grading 166 g/t (4.9 opt) Ag and 1.2% Cu
Including: 2.3m grading 393 g/t (11.5 opt) Ag and 3.6% Cu
SM13-13: 31.72m grading 3.5% Zn including 17.72m grading 5.0% Zn
09:02
CHK Chesapeake Energy files Form 10 registration statement for possible spin-off of Chesapeake Oilfield Services (25.03 )
Co announced that Chesapeake Oilfield Operating, L.L.C. (COO), its wholly owned subsidiary, has filed a Registration Statement on Form 10 with the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission. COO currently conducts the operations of Chesapeake's oilfield services division, Chesapeake Oilfield Services (COS).
Chesapeake intends for the spin-off to be tax-free to its shareholders for U.S. federal income tax purposes, other than with respect to any cash received in lieu of fractional shares. To that end, Chesapeake has obtained a private letter ruling from the Internal Revenue Service and expects to obtain an opinion of tax counsel regarding the tax treatment of the spin-off. Chesapeake has retained Morgan Stanley & Co. LLC as its financial advisor in connection with evaluating strategic alternatives for COS.
09:02
SGK Schawk to be acquired by MATW for implied purchase price of $20 per share (14.73 )
Matthews (MATW) announced that it has signed a definitive agreement to acquire SGK. Under the terms of the transaction, SGK stockholders will receive $11.80 cash and 0.20582 shares of Matthews' common stock for each SGK share held. Based on the closing price of Matthews' stock on March 14, 2014, the transaction represents an implied price of $20.00 for each SGK share and a total enterprise value of approximately $577 million. The exchange is intended to qualify as a tax-free reorganization on the share portion of the purchase price. The combination is ultimately expected to achieve $35 million to $45 million in annual cost-savings synergies and is expected to be accretive to adjusted (non-GAAP) earnings per share in the first full fiscal year following the closing of the transaction, excluding non-recurring transaction-related expenses and costs to achieve synergies.
09:02
PX Praxair, through its subsidiary Shanghai Chemical Industry Park Industrial Gases Company, was recently awarded a 15-year industrial gases supply contract from Shanghai SECCO Petrochemical Co., Ltd (131.75 )
PX, through its subsidiary Shanghai Chemical Industry Park Industrial Gases Company, was recently awarded a 15-year industrial gases supply contract from Shanghai SECCO Petrochemical Co., Ltd. Under terms of the agreement, SCIPIG will supply large volumes of pure oxygen to SECCO, located in Shanghai Chemical Industry Park, for its sulfuric acid regeneration unit. SCIPIG will construct a new air separation unit (ASU), with a capacity of 900 tons per day of oxygen, as well as an integrated liquefier. The ASU is expected to start up in 2015. Additionally, SCIPIG will extend its pipeline network in the chemical industry park.
09:01
XOM Exxon Mobil: Enable Midstream Partners inks second long-term agreement with XTO Energy to gather Bakken crude oil production (93.47 )
Enable Midstream Partners announces that its crude services subsidiary has entered into a long-term agreement with XTO Energy, a subsidiary of Exxon Mobil, to gather XTO's crude oil production through a new system that will be constructed in North Dakota's liquids-rich Bakken shale.
The agreement is entered into pursuant to an open season announced by Enable Midstream on February 3, 2014. Enable Midstream will provide services to XTO through a crude oil gathering system to be constructed in Williams and Mountrail counties of North Dakota. The new system will have a capacity of up to 30,000 barrels per day of crude gathering and include 85 miles of crude gathering lines. A second agreement includes the construction of a water gathering and transport system for produced water. The water system will include 75 miles of gathering lines.The systems are expected to commence initial operations during the second quarter of 2015.
08:56
VRSN VeriSign provides statement on the NTIA announcement of its intent to transition key Internet domain name functions; announcement does not affect co's operation of the .com and .net registries (54.85 )
Co provided a statement on the National Telecommunications and Information Administration's (NTIA) announcement of its intent to transition key Internet domain name functions.The announcement by NTIA on March 14, 2014, does not affect Verisign's operation of the .com and .net registries. The announcement does not impact Verisign's .com or .net domain name business nor impact its .com or .net revenue or those agreements, which have presumptive rights of renewal. The NTIA announcement involves Internet functions that are entirely different functions from those Verisign performs under its .com and .net agreements. The functions performed by Verisign involved in the NTIA announcement have been performed as a community service spanning three decades without compensation at the request of the Department of Commerce under the Cooperative Agreement.
08:47
WIRES On The Wires
KKR (KKR) announced that effective March 14, 2014, David Drummond has been appointed to the Board of Directors of KKR Management, the managing partner of KKR, and to the Board's Conflicts Committee. His appointment will bring the number of independent directors on KKR's Board to seven out of a total of nine Board seats. Puget Technologies (PUGE) announced an exclusive partnership with Shenzhen Weistek. This agreement establishes Puget's subsidiary, Weistek USA, as the exclusive domestic sales, service and support provider for all of Weistek's product lines. Exelis (XLS) and NIRF Imaging have entered into a long-term exclusive agreement to deliver a noninvasive, nonradioactive, point of care, medical imaging capability, that addresses multiple unmet needs in the global medical imaging market. Capstone Turbine (CPST) announced its first order out of the United Kingdom for a C200 natural gas microturbine to be installed at a Royal Air Force base. Manhattan Associates (MANH) announced that Lennox International (LII) has doubled its distribution footprint via a strategic redesign of its supply chain using Manhattan Associates' Transportation Management System, Warehouse Management System, and Labor Management System solutions in six United States distribution centers. AudioCodes (AUDC) announced that Avaya has selected AudioCodes Mediant platform to help drive efficiency and cost reduction.
08:45
UA Under Armour announces a two-for-one stock split (117.35 )
The stock split will be effected in the form of a stock dividend of one share of Class A Common Stock for each share of Class A Common Stock outstanding and one share of Class B Common Stock for each share of Class B Common Stock outstanding. The additional shares issued as a result of the stock split will be distributed on or about April 14, 2014 to stockholders of record on March 28, 2014.
08:42
NNA Navios Maritime Acquisition Announces Proposed Private Offering of $50 Million of 8.125% First Priority Ship Mortgage Notes Due 2021 (3.76 )
NNA announced that the Co and Navios Acquisition Finance (US) Inc., its wholly owned finance subsidiary, intend to offer through a private placement, subject to market and other conditions, approximately $50 million of 8.125% First Priority Ship Mortgage Notes due 2021 (the "Notes").
The Notes will be offered and sold in the United States only to qualified institutional buyers pursuant to Rule 144A under the Securities Act of 1933, as amended (the "Securities Act"), and in offshore transactions to non-United States persons in reliance on Regulation S under the Securities Act. The terms of the Notes are identical to the terms of the $610 mln of notes issued in November 2013 (the "Existing Notes") and will be secured by first priority ship mortgages on 11 vessels owned by certain subsidiary guarantors and certain associated property and contract rights
08:40
KNDI Kandi Technologies reports Q4 results (no estimates) (17.36 )
Q4 non-GAAP net income was $4.6 million, up nearly 259% year-over-year from $1.3 million.
Revenues rose 92.0% to $50.6 million from $26.3 million in 4Q12. EV sales increased significantly to $40.0 million, a 193.7% jump from the same period last year.
During the quarter, the co sold 3,568 units of pure electronic vehicles.
"We are very pleased to deliver an excellent financial performance for 2013, especially a robust Q4 result. As we have predicted in the past that 2013 was truly a breakthrough year for Kandi and our shareholders. The newly launched Public EV Sharing System in Hangzhou has been well received and highly recognized by our customers and various local governments as another innovative EV business model by Kandi. This EV sharing project was featured in the various national and international media outlets, such as China Central Television (CCTV), Associated Press (AP) and Bloomberg. During the year, we have formed and completed a strategic EV joint venture with Geely Auto which has already produced a profound impact on improving and expanding our EV business by a better consolidation of brands, resources and expertise to gain more market shares in China's pure EV sector." "With the newly unveiled EV subsidy policy in China, many of our pending EV orders have begun to be fulfilled during the fourth quarter in which we sold 3,568 units. For full year 2013, we achieved our expectations for revenue growth, including that almost 50% of total revenue came from EV sales. We expect this growth momentum will carry well into 2014. Together with JV partner, Geeley Auto, we now have three full-scale specialized EV production facilities, located in Shanghai, Changxing and Jinhua, which enable us to meet the strong market demand for electric vehicles in coming years."
08:36
AAMC Altisource Asset Mgmt entered into agreement to sell 250,000 shares of its new Series A Convertible Preferred Stock to Luxor Capital Group and other institutional investors for aggregate net proceeds of $250.0 mln (868.25 )
The holders of shares of Series A Preferred Stock will not be entitled to receive dividends with respect to the Series A Preferred Stock. The shares of Series A Preferred Stock are convertible into shares of common stock of AAMC at a conversion price of $1,250 per share of common stock, subject to certain anti-dilution adjustments.
08:34
HAST Hastings Entmt to merge with subsidiaries owned by Joel Weinshanker; co will receive a cash payment of $3.00 per share (1.91 )
Co has entered into an Agreement and Plan of Merger with Draw Another Circle, LLC and Hendrix Acquisition Corp., which are each wholly-owned, directly or indirectly, by Joel Weinshanker. Mr. Weinshanker is the President and sole shareholder of National Entertainment Collectibles Association, Inc., which holds approximately 12% of Hastings' outstanding shares. Pursuant to the Merger Agreement, Merger Sub will be merged with and into Hastings, with Hastings surviving the merger as a wholly-owned subsidiary of Parent, and each share of Hastings common stock held by a shareholder of Hastings (other than Mr. Weinshanker and his affiliates) will, upon completion of the merger, be converted into the right to receive a cash payment of $3.00 per share.
The $3.00 per share price represents a premium of ~57.1% over Hastings' closing share price on March 14, 2014 and a premium of approximately 61.3% over the average trading price of Hastings' common shares for the last 30 trading days ending on March 12, 2014. The transaction is valued at approximately $21.4 million. Hastings' Board of Directors, acting upon the unanimous recommendation of a special committee of the board directors consisting of independent directors, has unanimously approved the Merger Agreement and the transactions contemplated by the Merger Agreement and has resolved to recommend that Hastings' shareholders vote in favor of approving the Merger Agreement at a special meeting of the shareholders called specifically for such purpose.
08:33
CLDT Chatham Lodging and HG Vora Capital reach agreement; HG Vora Capital has withdrawn its three nominees for election to Chatham's Board of Trustees and agreed to certain customary standstill provisions with respect to the 2014 and 2015 annual meetings of shareholders (21.00 )
Co announced that they have resolved a potential proxy contest relating to this year's shareholder meeting. Under the agreement, HG Vora Capital has withdrawn its three nominees for election to Chatham's Board of Trustees and agreed to certain customary standstill provisions with respect to the 2014 and 2015 annual meetings of shareholders. Chatham has agreed to use the net proceeds received from a sale of the Innkeepers joint venture for the acquisition of hotels, joint venture investments or capital expenditures, and to distribute any remainder as a special dividend to shareholders. Subject to certain exceptions, Chatham has agreed for a specified period not to issue equity unless its net debt is equal to or greater than $325 million on a pro forma basis after taking into account the anticipated use of proceeds from such offering and anticipated acquisitions.Chatham also agreed that if it issues any common shares related to financing an Innkeepers acquisition, the minimum offering price would be $20/share. Furthermore, Chatham has agreed to provide HG Vora Capital with certain anti-dilution protections.
08:33
NRF Northstar Realty enters into definitive agreement to acquire a $1.05 bln healthcare real estate portfolio (16.20 )
Co announced that it has entered into a definitive agreement to acquire a $1.05 billion healthcare real estate portfolio (the "Portfolio") from investment partnerships owned and managed by Formation Capital, LLC or its affiliated entities (collectively "Formation") and Safanad Limited.
The Portfolio is comprised of 43 primarily private-pay senior housing facilities and 37 skilled nursing facilities. Inclusive of this portfolio, NorthStar has an ~$1.6 bln healthcare real estate portfolio consisting of over 160 properties. NorthStar is acquiring the Portfolio in a joint venture with Formation (the "Joint Venture").
Formation is a leading private investment firm focused on senior care real estate and services and post-acute healthcare. NorthStar and its affiliates will contribute ~92% of the $430 million of equity to purchase the Portfolio and the Joint Venture will assume in-place financing for the remainder of the purchase price.
08:32
ARE Alexandria RE increases quarterly dividend by 3% to $0.70 per share from $0.68 per share (72.97 )
08:32
WRAPX S&P futures vs fair value: +7.30. Nasdaq futures vs fair value: +19.00.
The Empire Manufacturing Survey for March registered a reading of 5.6, which was up from the prior month's reading of 4.5. Economists polled by Briefing.com expected the survey to improve to 5.4.
08:31
RTK Rentech: Concerned Rentech shareholders urges Rentech board to immediately halt capital raising plans and promptly hold 2014 annual meeting (1.79 )
Key PointsReiterates grave concerns over the board and management's poor track record and stresses the board cannot be trusted to execute successfully on any initiatives States the board's penchant for continued reckless capital spending and highlights the urgent need to reconstitute the board to include shareholder representation Calls on the board to hold the 2014 annual meeting as soon as possible to allow shareholders to choose the directors they trust to make decisions on their behalf.Letter stated "We agree that shareholder value could be created by forming an MLP structure or through the development and/or acquisition of additional wood assets. However, like many of our fellow shareholders, we do not have the confidence that this Board and management have the ability, track records and commitment to execute on such an initiative successfully. We view this Board's record to date as indefensible and see any potential plans to further dilute shareholders, expose them to greater risk, and/or engage in reckless capital spending as clear evidence of the critical need to reconstitute the Board NOW. Any significant allocation of capital going forward must be reviewed and decided upon by a truly independent, shareholder-oriented Board. Without shareholder representation on the Board, RTK's investors are left defenseless to protect themselves from more of the same risky and wasteful spending. The motivation to raise significant capital prior to the 2014 Annual Meeting puts the Board and management at serious conflict with shareholders who may be knowingly and purposely disenfranchised by such actions."
"CRS remains committed to maximizing shareholder value and will do whatever is necessary to ensure that decisions are made with the best interests of shareholders as a paramount objective. Through prudent capital allocation, careful expense management, proper execution, and appropriate risk-taking, shareholders could finally realize the true value of RTK's assets."
08:31
TECHX Market View: Front-month Jun. E-mini index futures hold a firm bid above fair values following the 8:30 am ET Mar. Empire Mfg. figure
ESm4 currently trades @ 1840.75 +7.75 NQm4 currently trades @ 3639.00 +18.00
08:31
URS URS adds four new independent directors to Board; JANA Partners agrees to support all nominees at 2014 annual meeting; board to establish value creation committee (45.70 )
Co announced that it will add four new independent directors to its Board of Directors, effective March 27, 2014. These four directors will be on URS' slate of directors nominated for election to the Board of Directors at the Company's 2014 Annual Meeting, along with eight incumbents, pursuant to an agreement with JANA Partners. The four new directors will be: Diane Creel, William H. Schumann, III, David N. Siegel and V. Paul Unruh. Biographical information on the new directors is provided below. Under the agreement with JANA, URS will also form a Value Creation Committee of the Board that will evaluate all options for enhancing shareholder value, including by engaging an investment bank to conduct a strategic review of the Company's business segments, operations and capital structure; and reviewing the Company's management compensation structure to enhance alignment with shareholder value creation. The Committee will be comprised of four members, two of whom will be new directors.The agreement between URS and JANA Partners will be filed on Form 8-K with the Securities and Exchange Commission. The agreement includes certain standstill restrictions that will be in effect until 30 days prior to the deadline by which a shareholder must give notice to the Company of its intention to nominate a director at or bring other business before the 2015 Annual Meeting. JANA Partners has committed to vote the shares that it controls in support of URS' twelve director nominees at the Company's 2014 Annual Meeting.
08:26
WIRES On The Wires
Leidos (LDOS) supported the Council on CyberSecurity in updating the 20 Critical Security Controls as part of a panel to update and maintain these controls. Western Union (WU) announced the launch of a new mobile money transfer service to Nigeria, which increases the reach of Western Union payout options in the country.Green Innovations (GNIN) and the co's subsidiary, Green Hygienics, announced that California-based Save Mart has authorized full distribution of Clearly Herbal Baby Wipes for distribution in their 96 stores located throughout Central California and Northern Nevada.Meru Networks (MERU) announced that RiverWoods has deployed a Meru Uninterrupted Care Network to enable its residents to remain connected online wherever they are and to provide its staff with more reliable Internet service.OSI Systems (OSIS) announced that its security division, Rapiscan Systems, received an order worth ~ $7 mln to provide Rapiscan Real Time Tomography hold baggage screening systems and related maintenance services for Oslo Airport. SmartPros (SPRO) announced the release of its new eLP-Mobile eLearning platform, enabling its customers to access continuing education and training courseware directly from supported phones and tablets. eHealth (EHTH) announced a new partnership with Aetna and HR Policy Association to provide health insurance solutions for corporate retiree program beneficiaries.The U.S. Air Force Life Cycle Management Center awarded Lockheed Martin (LMT) a foreign military sales contract to support the Republic of Korea's Peace Krypton reconnaissance aircraft system. This contract is valued at ~ $9 mln. Trovagene (TROV) has released its first multiplexed oncogene mutation assay, integrating the co's proprietary sample preparation and primer technologies with next-generation sequencing as a mutation detection platform. Electrovaya will partner with Canadian Solar (CSIQ) for a micro-grid project. Electrovaya plans to provide a 200 kWh energy storage system which will feature its Lithium Ion SuperPolymer2.0 technology. Significant additional enhancements have been made to SMART's (SMT) solution for Microsoft (MSFT) Lync Room Systems including a new room size, additional collaboration capabilities, as well as premium services for installation, ROI reporting and solution adoption through Unify Square.8x8 (EGHT) announced the completion of another milestone in its Global Reach initiative with the launch of its services platform at a new Hong Kong data center facility. BNY Mellon (BK) has been appointed by SMC as depositary bank for its ADR program.
08:17
ESE Esco Tech signs agreement to divest Aclara Technologies to an affiliate of Sun Capital Partners; gross cash proceeds from the transaction are expected to be ~ $150 mln (36.79 )
Co announced that it has signed an agreement to divest Aclara Technologies to an affiliate of Sun Capital Partners. The gross cash proceeds from the transaction are expected to be ~ $150 mln, comprised of a $130 mln purchase price plus ~ $20 mln in cash related to specific Aclara receivables retained by ESCO.The net cash proceeds from the sale are estimated to be ~ $130 mln after taxes and expenses, which will result in a net debt position of less than $10 mln at March 31, 2014. Post-closing, the co will have over $600 mln of available liquidity under its existing revolving credit facility, which it expects to efficiently deploy to support its strategy of profitable organic growth, accretive acquisitions around its existing core businesses, and opportunistic repurchases of outstanding shares. For the Quarter ending March 31, 2014, the co expects to recognize in Discontinued Operations a net book loss of ~ $50 mln on the sale of Aclara. The amount will be finalized when the transaction closes and the adjustments set forth in the agreement are determined.
08:15
LGND Ligand Pharma earns a $1 mln milestone payment as a result of the recent FDA approval of Merck's (MRK) NOXAFIL (posaconazole) injection (18 mg/mL) (75.39 )
Co announced that it has earned a $1 million milestone payment as a result of the recent FDA approval of Merck's (MRK) NOXAFIL (posaconazole) injection (18 mg/mL). This is a new Captisol-enabled formulation of NOXAFIL for intravenous (IV) use. Ligand will sell Captisol to Merck for this product under a commercial supply agreement.
08:09
GPL Great Panther Silver resumes full operation of the mine and plant facilities at its Guanajuato Mine Complex in Mexico (1.22 )
Co announced that it has resumed full operation of the mine and plant facilities at its Guanajuato Mine Complex in Mexico. Since recovering the co's main administration building and plant facility in Guanajuato on Thursday March 13th, from the illegal occupation that began March 9th, employees and contractors have worked diligently to assess the condition of the facilities and return them to full operation as quickly as possible.
08:08
WRAPX S&P futures vs fair value: +8.80. Nasdaq futures vs fair value: +21.80.
U.S equity futures are pointing to a higher open with foreign markets so far handling the (expected) news well that Crimea voted 95.5% in favor of being annexed to Russia. The next steps in terms of international response remain uncertain, but the current bias would suggest there is a presumption that initial sanctions won't be hard-hitting economically so as to allow more time for a diplomatic resolution.
Reviewing overnight developments:
Asian markets ended somewhat mixed. Japan's Nikkei -0.4%; Hong Kong's Hang Seng -0.3%; China's Shanghai Composite +1.0%; Australia's All Ordinaries -0.2%.Economic data was limited:Hong Kong's unemployment rate held steady at 3.1%.In news:The People's Bank of China announced the yuan's daily trading band will expand to 2% from 1%The Chinese government outlined a new urbanization plan that will include an expansion of transportation networks and authorization for local governments to issue bonds directly
Major European indices are trading higher. Germany's DAX +0.7%; France's CAAC 40 +0.7%; England's FTSE 100 +0.4%Economic data was scarce: Eurozone CPI increased 0.3% month-over-month (0.4% expected, -1.1% prior) while the year-over-year reading increased 0.7% (0.8% consensus, 0.8% last). Core CPI rose 0.5% month-over-month (-1.7% previous) while the annualized reading came in at 1.0% (1.0% prior).Among news of note: Crimeans voted 95.5% in favor of Crimea being annexed to Russia. EU foreign ministers meet to today to determine a response.Vodaphone (VOD) bought Spanish cable operator Ono for $10 bln
In U.S. corporate news: Yahoo (YHOO 38.75, +1.15): indicated 3.2% higher after Alibaba.com announced it is preparing for a US IPOGeneral Motors (GM 34.21, +0.12): trading slightly higher despite news of first lawsuit filed over the ignition recallWells Fargo (WFC 48.09, +0.69): reports out this morning that it is being accused by New York attorney general of fabricating foreclosure documents The Empire Manufacturing Survey for March (Briefing.com consensus 5.4; prior 4.5) will be announced at 8:30 ET while the January Net Long-Term TIC Flows report (prior -$45.9 bln) will cross the wires at 9:00 ET. The Industrial Production (Briefing.com consensus 0.1%; prior -0.3%) and Capacity Utilization (Briefing.com consensus 78.5%; prior 78.5%) report for February will be released at 9:15 ET while the day's data will be topped off with the 10:00 ET release of the NAHB Housing Market Index for March (Briefing.com consensus 50.0; prior 46.0).
08:07
PTX Pernix Therapeutics misses by $0.07 (3.49 )
Reports Q4 (Dec) loss of ($0.15) per share, $0.07 worse than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of ($0.08); revenues rose 31.5% YoY to $23.9 mln vs the $21.7 mln consensus.
Financial Position
As of Dec 31, 2013, the Co had $15.6 mln of cash and ~$3.0 million available under its revolving line of credit subject to borrowing base capacity. As of March 12, 2014, the Co had $64.6 mln of cash and ~$32.0 mln available under its revolving line of credit subject to borrowing base capacity.
08:04
CWH CommonWealth REIT releases additional information regarding Zell's conflict of interest; says 'Zell will be in a position to influence lease negotiations between SIR and Par Petroleum in a way that could be self-interested by Zell and detrimental to the shareholders of SIR, including CWH' (27.32 )
Zell, or one of his entities, is a controlling shareholder (33.4%) of Par Petroleum Corp. (PARR.OB). The recently appointed CEO of PARR, Will Monteleone, also simultaneously serves as a Vice President of Equity Group Investments, a Zell controlled private investment company. In September 2013, Par Petroleum acquired Hawaii's largest oil refinery for approximately $365 million. The funding for this acquisition was largely provided by Zell or entities that he controls.The Hawaii refinery leases approximately 3.1 million sq.ft. of land and easements from SIR. CWH believes that some of these lands and easements may be essential for the continued operation of the refinery by Par Petroleum.
08:03
HOLI HollySys announces two significant high-speed rail signaling system contracts valued at $112.09 mln
Co announces that it signed two significant contracts to provide the Automatic Train Protection equipment and system for two batches of high-speed trains in 200-250km/h and 300-350km/h, with the contract size for each of $29.35 million and $82.74 mln approximately. Yhe on-board signaling equipment A.T.P. (Automatic Train Protection), works together with the ground-based signaling equipment T.C.C. (Train Control Center) as the critical control elements in the high-speed railway signaling systems to ensure the safety and reliability of the high-speed railway operation.
08:03
TROV TrovaGene releases its first oncogene mutation assay using next generation sequencing, expands its non-invasive cancer monitoring platform (5.82 )
Co has released its first multiplexed oncogene mutation assay, integrating the Company's proprietary sample preparation and primer technologies with next-generation sequencing (NGS) as a mutation detection platform. The assay, developed to detect the seven most commonly encountered mutations of the KRAS oncogene, is now available for patient testing and is in use in ongoing clinical collaborations with major cancer centers and integrated healthcare networks. These collaborations are focused on replicating assay performance and validating the clinical benefits of tracking KRAS mutational status over time to assess treatment response and disease status in patients. Utilizing NGS technology improves the genomic information obtained from a given patient sample, with multiple mutations being evaluated in a single test. Following this first successful application of the Company's proprietary sample preparation and assay technologies with NGS, Trovagene now plans to introduce a full line of oncogene mutation tests based on this comprehensive and scalable technology platform.
08:01
AZN AstraZeneca announces progress on global parthenon clinical trial program with BRILINTA n high-risk cardiovascular disease patient populations in advance of american college of cardiology scientific session; enrollment completed for euclid study in patients with peripheral artery disease (65.30 )
Co announced it has completed patient enrollment ~four months ahead of plan in the Phase III clinical trial EUCLID studying BRILINTA tablets. Part of PARTHENON, AstraZeneca's largest clinical trial program, EUCLID has randomized more than 13,500 patients globally with peripheral artery disease (PAD); ~20 percent are patients in the United States (US) from more than 300 active clinical trial sites across the country. EUCLID is designed to evaluate the effects of ticagrelor (monotherapy) compared to clopidogrel (monotherapy) on cardiovascular (CV) events and safety in PAD patients. Ticagrelor is currently not approved for the treatment of patients with PAD. AstraZeneca also announced today that US recruitment and enrollment is underway in two additional Phase III PARTHENON studies -- SOCRATES and THEMIS. SOCRATES (Acute Stroke Or Transient IsChaemic Attack TReated with Aspirin or Ticagrelor and Patient OutcomES) will evaluate the efficacy of ticagrelor compared to aspirin in reducing major vascular events in patients with acute ischemic stroke or transient ischemic attack (TIA). BRILINTA is currently not approved for the treatment of patients with ischemic stroke or TIA. THEMIS (Effect of Ticagrelor on Health Outcomes in DiabEtes Mellitus Patients Intervention Study) will evaluate the efficacy of ticagrelor vs placebo, on top of standard of care including aspirin, for the long-term prevention of major vascular events in patients with Type 2 diabetes and coronary atherosclerosis. BRILINTA is not currently approved for the prevention of CV events in patients with diabetes and coronary atherosclerosis.
08:00
TRS Trimas acquires the remaining 30% interest of Arminak & Associates for cash, plus an earn-out based on the future success of the business (34.72 )
Co announced it has acquired the remaining 30 percent interest of Arminak & Associates, LLC for cash, plus an earn-out based on the future success of the business. The transaction closed on March 11, 2014. Helga Arminak will remain as president of Arminak and the co will continue to operate as part of the Company's Packaging segment. TriMas had previously acquired a 70% share of the business in Feb 2012.
07:47
WIRES On The Wires
EMCOR (EME) announced that its subsidiary, Poole & Kent Company of Florida, has been awarded a contract by Miami Dade County for construction of Master Pump Station No. 3, which will help expand sewer system capacity in the Brickell area of Downtown Miami, Florida. DineEquity (DIN) announced the opening of the first IHOP restaurant in Bahrain on March 17, 2014.Textura (TXTR) announced that GFI Development is using Submittal Exchange to manage design and construction communications for the elaborate renovation of the unique Five Beekman Street project in Manhattan's Financial District.AMN Healthcare Services (AHS) has made a strategic investment in PipelineRx, a clinical telepharmacy company.
07:42
SUMRX Asian Markets Close: Nikkei -0.4%, Hang Seng -0.3%, Shanghai +1.0%
Markets finished mixed across Asia. The People's Bank of China widened its trading band to +/- 2% (+/-1% previous) above or below the officially set midpoint Hong Kong's unemployment rate held at 3.1%, as expected. Singapore's trade surplus widened to SGD4.29 bln (SGD3.97 bln previous). Japan's Nikkei (-0.4%) slumped to its lowest level in six weeks. Heavyweight Softbank outperformed, surging 4.9% on reports its affiliate, Alibaba, announced it will go public in the United States. Hong Kong's Hang Seng (-0.3%) slipped to a five-week low. Property stocks lagged as New World Development sank 5.6% and China Overseas Land & Investment gave up 2.1%.China's Shanghai Composite (+1.0%) rallied on Beijing's announcement its plans to speed up urbanization. Infrastructure and property names saw solid gains with Anhui Conch Cement adding 2.6% and China Vanke tacking on 3.1% to lead their respective sectors higher. India's Sensex was closed for Holi. Australia's ASX (-0.2%) fell to a one-month low as trade closed on the 50 and 100 dma. Heavyweight miners lost ground as BHP Billiton and Rio Tinto both fell close to 0.5%.Regional Decliners: Indonesia -0.1% Regional Advancers: Philippines +0.1%...South Korea +0.2%...Thailand +0.4%...South Korea +0.4%...Vietnam +0.6%...Singapore +0.6% Fx: USDCNY jumped to 6.1779...USDJPY +45 pips @ 101.80...AUDUSD +50 pips @ .9080
07:36
WRAPX S&P futures vs fair value: +9.00. Nasdaq futures vs fair value: +22.80.
US indices are indicated higher, following form with European bourses, which are bouncing back some from last week's big losses. The Crimea referendum went as expected, which is to say annexation to Russia was favored by voters -- and overwhelmingly so with 95.5% of the vote going that way. European markets standing their ground in the wake of that vote has provided some support this morning, but it can be regarded as a tenuous move knowing that sanctions will be forthcoming from the West. The questions are just what form the sanctions will take and when.
07:34
ADS Alliance Data provides Private Label performance update for Feb 2014; reports average receivables of $7.94 bln, up 15% y/y; net charge off rate of 4.6% vs 4.6% in Feb 2013; delinquency rate 4.3% (278.59 )
07:33
DRQ Dril-Quip has been awarded a contract valued at ~$110 mln to supply subsea completion systems and related services for an FPSO development project (100.32 )
Co announced that Dril-Quip Limited, its wholly-owned subsidiary serving the North Sea, Europe and Africa regions, has been awarded a contract valued at ~$110 mln, based on current exchange rates, to supply subsea completion systems and related services for an FPSO development project. In accordance with the contract, Dril-Quip will provide subsea wellhead systems, subsea production and injection tree systems, and subsea and topside control systems for the project. Delivery of these systems is expected to begin in the second half of 2015.
07:32
NBS NeoStem reports fourth Data Safety Monitoring Board (DSMB) Review of PreSERVE AMI Trial; DSMB recommended continuing the PreSERVE AMI Phase 2 clinical trial following a fourth interim data and safety review (7.49 )
The Data Safety Monitoring Board recommended continuing the PreSERVE AMI Phase 2 clinical trial following a fourth interim data and safety review. The PreSERVE trial of AMR-001 is a Phase 2, randomized, placebo controlled, double-blind study designed to enroll 160 patients. AMR-001 is being evaluated for the preservation of heart function after a severe heart attack. Full enrollment has been completed for the trial and data will be available in the second half of 2014.
Dr. Andreas Zeiher, an international expert in the development of cell based therapy for acute myocardial infarction (AMI) and principal investigator of a study published last month in the European Heart Journal, demonstrated that administration of autologous bone marrow derived cells expressing the CXCR4 receptor, five to ten days after an AMI, significantly reduces the cumulative incidence of major adverse clinical cardiac events, including death, heart failure and recurrent cardiac ischemia1. These data further support the ongoing development of NeoStem's lead product candidate, AMR-001, an autologous bone marrow derived CXCR4 expressing cell that was shown in a Phase 1 trial to induce new blood vessel growth and preserve heart muscle function after a severe heart attack.
07:32
TSYS TeleComm Sys and Patent Monetization Associates, L.P. sign patent agreement (2.18 )
Co announced that TCS and PMA have signed an agreement as part of TCS' Patent Monetization Program, whereby PMA has acquired certain patents from TCS' messaging patent portfolio. This agreement positions TCS to receive future royalties.
07:31
ADXS Advaxis announced that it has signed an agreement with the University of California, San Francisco, under which Lawrence Fong will evaluate several new immunotherapy constructs (4.64 )
Co announced that it has signed an agreement with the University of California, San Francisco, under which Lawrence Fong, M.D., Professor in the Department of Medicine and principal investigator of the studies at UCSF, will evaluate several new immunotherapy constructs, in addition to ADXS-PSA, each built on the Advaxis proprietary technology. Data generated from this agreement will demonstrate the combination of the unique Advaxis immunotherapy platform, which generates both tumor fighting T cells and reduces tumor protection inside the tumor microenvironment, with targets that have already been shown to be important in effective immunotherapies for prostate cancer.
07:31
PHII PHI announces receipt of early tenders and requisite consents with respect to its tender offer and consent solicitation for its 8.625% senior notes due 2018 (41.91 )
Co announced that it had received, as of 12:00 midnight, New York City time, at the end of March 14, 2014 (the "Early Tender Deadline"), tenders and consents from holders of 97.52% of the aggregate principal amount of its outstanding 8.625% Senior Notes due 2018 (the "Notes") in connection with its previously-announced tender offer and consent solicitation for the Notes, which commenced on March 3, 2014.
PHI's obligation to accept for purchase, and to pay for, the Notes tendered pursuant to the tender offer is conditioned upon, among other things, its completion of its previously-announced sale of $500,000,000 aggregate principal amount of 5.25% Senior Notes due 2019, which is also expected to occur later today.
07:26
JASO JA Solar beats by $0.22, beats on revs; guides Q1, FY14 shipments (11.42 )
Reports Q4 (Dec) adj. earnings of $0.16 per share, $0.22 better than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of ($0.06); revenues rose 23% QoQ to $357.3 mln vs the $291.82 mln consensus.
Total shipments in the fourth quarter of 2013 were 665.5 MW, exceeding the high end of the Company's previously provided guidance of 500 MW to 550 MW, and representing a 33.0% increase from the 500.2 MW shipped in the third quarter of 2013, and a 33.0% increase from 500.4 MW in the fourth quarter of 2012. Gross margin in the fourth quarter of 2013 was positive 15.5%, compared with positive 11.3% in the third quarter of 2013 and negative 4.6% in the fourth quarter of 2012. Guidance:For the first quarter of 2014, the Company expects total cell and module shipments to be between 580 MW and 610 MW. For the full year 2014, the Company expects total cell and module shipments to be between 2.7 GW and 2.9 GW, including 200 MW of module shipments to the Company's downstream projects.
07:25
SUMRX Dollar Hovers Little Changed: 10-yr: -04/32..2.679%..USD/JPY: 101.79..EUR/USD: 1.3891
The Dollar Index lingers little changed near 79.50 following a quiet overnight trade. Early action has been limited to a tight 10 cent range as action holds near four and a half-month lows. EURUSD is -15 pips @ 1.3895 as trade slips off its best levels since October 2011. The single currency has managed to hold its own despite Crimea's referendum deciding in favor of becoming part of Russia. Leaders from the West are now likely to announce economic sanctions against Russia as they do not accept the outcome of the referendum. Some selling has taken hold in the euro following the cooler than anticipated CPI (0.7% YoY actual v. 0.8% YoY expected). The 1.3850 level continues to be watched closely for near-term support. Click here to see a daily EURUSD chart.GBPUSD is -15 pips @ 1.6630 as trade slips amid a quiet trade. Action over the past week has been locked in a tight range between 1.6600/1.6650 as neither bulls nor bears has been able to take control as action hovers near its best levels since November 2009. USDCHF is +25 pips @ .8750 as trade works its way off 29-month lows. Traders continue to view .8850 as the first level of meaningful resistance. USDJPY is +45 pips @ 101.80 after buyers emerged in defense of the February lows near 101.25. The early bid has erased all of Friday's losses and has action looking towards another test of 102.50. AUDUSD is +40 pips @ .9070 as buyers remain in control for the third time in four days. Today's bid has the hard currency testing its March highs near .9100 with the 200 dma (.9150) lurking just above. USDCNY jumped to 6.1779. USDCAD is -55 pips @ 1.1150 as trade presses support in the area. The pair has spent most of the past month locked between 1.1050/1.1150 with a breakdown setting up a potential move into the 1.0950 region. Canada's foreign securities purchases are due out later this morning.
07:19
WIRES On The Wires
Good Start Genetics announced a strategic agreement with PerkinElmer (PKI) to expand access to GoodStart Select genetic carrier screening tests beyond the in vitro fertilization setting to the broader women's health community, including obstetrics and gynecology and maternal fetal medicine physicians. Zep (ZEP) launched Zep 45 DualForce, a long-lasting, dual-action penetrant and lubricant with PTFE. PC Connection (PCCC) launched a global alliance with Bechtle AG to respond to increasing demands by international businesses for global integration. The agreement extends PC Connection and Bechtle's e-commerce capabilities. Level 3 Communications (LVLT) announced it is providing Invoca with voice services, enabling Invoca to enhance the capabilities of its enterprise inbound call platform, expand its reach in a highly competitive regional market, and simplify its customers' experience. Ball (BLL) Aerospace & Technologies has applied power to the Joint Polar Satellite System spacecraft bus for the first time, a significant milestone for achieving on-time delivery to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration for a planned early 2017 launch. Starting today, Plug Power (PLUG) will be showcasing its comprehensive GenKey hydrogen fuel cell solution during the MODEX 2014 tradeshow taking place March 17-20 at the Georgia World Congress Center in Atlanta.
07:06
AZC Augusta Resource responds to extension of HudBay (HBM) offer and waiver of minimum tender condition; 'the pressure is mounting on HudBay to dramatically improve its offer or go away' (2.93 )
Co responds to the announcement made last Friday by HudBay Minerals that it has extended its offer to acquire common shares of Augusta and has waived the minimum tender condition under the offer.
HudBay's unprecedented coercive tactic of dropping its minimum tender condition part way through its initial bid period is an ill-considered reaction to an obviously failing offer:
The HudBay offer has received virtually no support from Augusta's shareholders (at less than one half of one percent of Augusta's common shares tendered), or from the analysts who cover Augusta; Augusta's share price has consistently traded at a significant premium to the implied offer price since the announcement of the HudBay offer, with the premium currently over 27%; and The early extension of the offer and waiver of the minimum tender condition by HudBay are a clear acknowledgment that its offer was not going to succeed. As Augusta advances the permitting for its world class Rosemont project and the prospect of Augusta's shares being re-rated moves closer, the pressure is mounting on HudBay to dramatically improve its offer or go away. Augusta confirms that its permitting process is progressing as planned with previous guidance remaining unchanged for receipt of both the 404 permit from the Army Corps of Engineers and the Final Record of Decision from the U.S. Forest Service in the second quarter of this year. Richard Warke, Augusta's Executive Chairman, stated,
"HudBay started this process with a low ball bid, which the market clearly has rejected. Now, when their bid is failing, HudBay drops their minimum tender condition in a desperate attempt to give life support to their bid. Their tactics are just appalling. Our Board understands its fiduciary obligation to protect the interests of our shareholders, and we intend to do just that."
Shareholders are reminded that as long as augusta's shareholder rights plan remains in effect, hudbay cannot take up any shares that might be tendered to its offer without triggering the rights. augusta's board of directors intends to meet during the week of march 24, 2014 to receive an update regarding the company's strategic process and discuss the company's response to hudbay's coercive attempt to deprive augusta shareholders of the full value of their shares. augusta will issue a press release following that board meeting to update its shareholders. shareholders are advised to take no actions in response to the hudbay offer pending the issuance of that press release.
07:05
LEI Lucas Energy submits plan of compliance to NYSE MKT (0.69 )
Co announced that on Friday, March 14th, it submitted a plan of compliance to the NYSE MKT as required under the listing standards as set forth in Part 10 of the NYSE MKT Company Guide.In order to maintain its listing on the Exchange, the Exchange had requested that the Company submit a plan of compliance by March 14, 2014, addressing how it intends to regain compliance with Section 1003 of the Company Guide by April 14, 2014.
07:04
YGE Yingli Green Energy supplies 10 MW of PV modules to Solarcentury in the United Kingdom (5.76 )
Co announced that the Company has supplied 10 megawatts of multicrystalline PV modules to Solarcentury, a solar company in the UK. In terms of the agreement between Yingli and Solarcentury, the co is the sole supplier and has completed the delivery of ~ 40,000 PV modules at the end of February. These modules will be installed on the Isle of Sheppey which is located ~ 85 kilometers east of London, UK.
07:03
KTOS Kratos Defense and Security receives $5 mln in missile and radar system product awards (7.14 )
Co announced that its Kratos Modular Systems Division recently received ~ $5 million in new missile and radar system contract awards.
07:03
CANF Can-Fite BioPharma announces Phase II study protocol to treat patients with advanced liver cancer with CF102 has been approved by the IRB in Israel (5.61 )
Co announced that a Phase II study protocol for the treatment of advanced liver cancer with its CF102 has been approved by the Institutional Review Board in Israel. The company plans to conduct the Phase II study in Israel, Europe and the US and it will include 78 subjects that will be dosed with the drug as a second-line treatment of advanced hepatocellular carcinoma with Child-Pugh Class B cirrhosis. The study will investigate the efficacy and safety of CF102 vs. placebo. The protocol has been approved by the IRB at the Rabin Medical Center, Petach Tikva, and the company intends to follow up with European and US submissions shortly. The study protocol was developed with the assistance of Dr. Keith Stuart, MD, Chairman, Department of Hematology and Oncology Professor of Medicine, Tufts University School of Medicine, a well-known internationally expert in Liver Cancer. This center will also participate in the study. The FDA has granted Orphan Drug designation for CF102, for the treatment of hepatocellular carcinoma. FDA orphan drug status grants various incentives for developing these drugs, including shortened approval procedures, tax breaks on R&D costs, and financing assistance. If the drug is the first to reach market, it also receives seven years exclusivity.
According to Global Industry Analysts, the global liver cancer drug market is expected to exceed $2 bln by 2015.
07:03
KIPS Kips Bay Medical announces FDA approval for U.S. expansion of its eMESH I clincal feasibility study (0.74 )
Co announced that the FDA has granted an approval for Kips Bay Medical to include more U.S. patients and U.S. study sites in its "eMESH I" clinical feasibility trial of its eSVS Mesh. In its initial approval, the FDA indicated that it would allow a staged enrollment within the United States, starting with 15 patients at up to four sites in the United States. The FDA has now increased the approved number of U.S. patients from 15 to 27 (15 additional from the 12 enrolled to date) and increased the allowed number of U.S. sites from four to 10.In addition, the FDA has also approved a combination of changes in the application of the eSVS Mesh to the saphenous vein graft and to the surgical implant technique for the eSVS Mesh treated graft. The changes are intended to reduce the risk of early graft occlusion, make it easier to implant the eSVS Mesh and reduce procedural costs.
07:02
AH Accretive Health common stock will commence trading on the over-the-counter market at the opening of trading on March 17, 2014, under the trading symbol 'ACHI' (8.02 -0.42)
Co announced that its common stock will commence trading on the over-the-counter market at the opening of trading on Monday, March 17, 2014, under the trading symbol "ACHI". The Company's common stock, which ceased trading on the New York Stock Exchange prior to the market opening today, will be quoted through the facilities of the OTC Markets Group
07:01
CYTR CytRx establishes research and development team and opens new laboratory to develop albumin-binding anti-cancer drug platform (4.15 )
Co announced the appointment of Felix Kratz as Vice President of Drug Discovery and Andre Warnecke as Senior Director of Drug Discovery. Drs. Kratz and Warnecke and their scientific team will expand the Corporation's novel albumin-binding anti-cancer drug pipeline.The new laboratory, located in Freiburg, Germany, will conduct discovery and translational research to create drug candidates that utilize novel linker technologies that couple chemotherapeutic agents and proteins either inside the body or externally, and then concentrate drug in tumors. The work done at the laboratory will generate new pipeline product candidates and thereby enable expansion of the Company's existing patent portfolio, adding to intellectual property that was originally developed by the KTB Tumor Biology Center in Freiburg and licensed exclusively to CytRx.
07:00
FPRX Five Prime Therapeutics and Bristol-Myers Squibb (BMY) Sign Collaboration Agreement to Discover Novel Immuno-Oncology Therapies for Two Immune Checkpoint Pathways; BMY will make an upfront payment of $20 mln to FPRX and provide up to $9.5 mln in research funding over the course of the research term (18.75 )
Cos announced that they have signed a collaboration agreement for the discovery, development and commercialization of immuno-oncology therapies directed toward targets identified in two undisclosed immune checkpoint pathways using Five Prime's proprietary target discovery platform. Under the terms of the agreement, Bristol-Myers Squibb will obtain exclusive, worldwide rights to develop and commercialize products directed toward certain protein targets identified by Five Prime prior to and during the collaboration. Bristol-Myers Squibb will make an upfront payment of $20 mln to Five Prime and provide up to $9.5 mln in research funding over the course of the research term. Additionally, Bristol-Myers Squibb will make a payment of ~$21 mln to acquire 4.9% of Five Prime's outstanding common stock purchased at ~a 30% premium. Five Prime will be eligible to receive up to $300 mln in future development, regulatory and sales based milestone payments per collaboration target and tiered mid-single-digit rising to low-double-digit royalty payments on net sales of each product commercialized by Bristol-Myers Squibb.
06:53
SXT Sensient files definitive proxy materials and sends letter to shareholders; recommends shareholders support Sensient's qualified board members (54.43 )
Co announced that it filed definitive proxy materials with the SEC in connection with its 2014 Annual Meeting of Shareholders, to be held on April 24, 2014. The Board also sent a letter to shareholders and recommends that shareholders vote FOR the election of Sensient's highly qualified nominees on the WHITE proxy card.
Letter states: "... Our strong, independent Board consists of experienced directors who are deeply familiar with the Company's businesses, are highly qualified to lead the Company in executing its strategic plans and are focused on serving the interests of all of the Company's shareholders. Collectively, our Board brings highly relevant experience across many areas, including expertise in food sciences and the food industry more broadly; experience in leading innovative research and development efforts; broad management experience, including leadership of large multinational companies; and deep expertise in finance, accounting and government regulation. Taken together, the experience and expertise of our Board has been critical to guiding the Company in its current strategy and setting the course for continued and sustainable growth..."
06:38
S&P futures vs fair value: +9.50. Nasdaq futures vs fair value: +26.50.
06:38
Asian Markets
Nikkei...14277.67...-50.00...-0.40%. Hang Seng...21473.95...-65.50...-0.30%.
06:38
European Markets
FTSE...6553.91...+26.00...+0.40%. DAX...9106.21...+49.80...+0.50%.
06:36
STRL Sterling Construction misses by $0.36, misses on revs (9.95 )
Reports Q4 (Dec) loss of $1.83 per share, excluding non-recurring items, $0.36 worse than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of ($1.47); revenues fell 20.4% year/year to $125.9 mln vs the $156.3 mln consensus.
Also included in the 2013 net loss per diluted share attributable to common stockholders was the negative impact from the revaluation of the liability to noncontrolling interest owners of $0.40 per diluted share
Outlook Commentary: "Entering 2014 we believe we are well positioned to deliver significant improvement in profitability. Our current mix of projects in backlog points to meaningful sustainable gross margin expansion over the next several quarters. With several key executive changes and process-improvements largely completed, we expect general and administrative expenses to return to 2012 levels in the 6% of revenues range. Capital expenditures should be in-line with those of 2013. Our current fleet of equipment supplemented by leased assets as needed provides us with more than adequate capacity to execute on our growing backlog, while the continued support of our bank and bonding company gives us the financial flexibility to pursue our robust pipeline of project opportunities. In summary, given the substantial progress we have made over the course of 2013 to strengthen our operational effectiveness, the major shift in the composition of our backlog towards higher margin projects, and the gradual improvement in demand for construction work by the heavy civil infrastructure markets we serve, we begin 2014 confident in our ability to achieve better overall profitability, which we expect to lead to increasing value for our shareholders."
06:27
INO Inovio Pharma misses by $0.04; revs in-line (3.50 )
Reports Q4 net loss of $0.07 vs ($0.03) CIQ est; total revenue of $1.7 mln vs $1.7 mln CIQ est.
Capital Resources
As of December 31, 2013, cash and cash equivalents plus short-term investments were $52.6 million compared with $13.7 million as of December 31, 2012.
Based on management's projections and analysis, the Company believes that cash, cash equivalents and short-term investments are sufficient to meet its planned working capital requirements through the end of 2017.Corporate Update/Corporate Development
In a major corporate development for the Company, Roche and Inovio entered into an exclusive worldwide license agreement to research, develop and commercialize Inovio's highly-optimized, multi-antigen DNA vaccine products targeting prostate cancer and hepatitis B. Roche licensed Inovio's therapeutic vaccines INO-5150 for prostate cancer and INO-1800 for hepatitis B as well as the use of Inovio's CELLECTRA electroporation technology for delivery of these vaccines. Roche also obtained an option to license additional vaccine candidates for prostate cancer in connection with a funded collaborative research program.
Roche agreed to an upfront payment to Inovio of $10 million (paid in the fourth quarter), will pay all preclinical and clinical development costs for these products, and will make milestone payments potentially up to $412.5 million upon reaching certain development and commercial milestones for INO-5150 and INO-1800. Additional development milestone payments could be made to us if Roche pursues other indications with INO-5150 or INO-1800. Inovio is entitled to receive up to double-digit tiered royalties on product sales
06:25
WIRES On The Wires
Bombardier (BDRBF) Transportation South Africa has signed a contract with Transnet Freight Rail for the delivery of electric locomotives. The contract is expected to be effective by end of March 2014, following certain administrative approvals. Alcoa (AA) is investing $13 mln to expand its wheel manufacturing plant in Europe, to meet growing demand for its lightweight, durable, low-maintenance aluminum truck wheels.Science Applications International (SAIC) was awarded a task order to provide the U.S. Army Human Resources Command with full lifecycle IT support. The single award task order has a one-year base period of performance, two one-year options and a total contract value of ~ $221 mln if all options are exercised.TripAdvisor (TRIP) announced plans to extend its TripAdvisor GreenLeaders program into Canada and Europe for the first time, following rapid growth in the U.S.L & L Energy (LLEN) announced that its Special Independent Committee has appointed Mr. Nicholas Chen, Managing Partner at Pamir Law Group, to replace Mr. Mark Bartlett.
06:20
QURE uniQure and Chiesi announce six year follow-up data from Glybera treated patients; review suggests that treatment with Glybera provides long-term beneficial effects with regard to the risk of encountering new pancreatitis events, including the occurrence of severe pancreatitis events (14.83 )
Co and Chiesi Farmaceutici S.p.A. announced initial analysis of retrospectively collected individual patient data from LPLD patients treated with Glybera. The analysis covers follow-up data for up to six years post treatment for 13 patients, all of whom met indication requirements for the current labeling of Glybera in the EU. This analysis represents an extension of the case note review which formed a part of the data package upon which the European Commission approved Glybera in October 2012 under exceptional circumstances for the treatment of a subset of patients with lipoprotein lipase deficiency, or LPLD. An external adjudication board of independent experts performed the review of the individual patient profiles. In the analysis equal time periods of up to six years before and after Glybera treatment were compared to evaluate the number and severity of attacks of pancreatitis in each LPLD patient with a history of severe or repeated pancreatitis. The review suggests that treatment with Glybera provides long-term beneficial effects with regard to the risk of encountering new pancreatitis events, including the occurrence of severe pancreatitis events. These results are in line with the trend exhibited in the first case note review performed up to 3 years after treatment with Glybera.
06:20
HNR Harvest Natural misses by $0.46 (4.34 )
Reports Q4 (Dec) loss of $0.36 per share, $0.46 worse than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of $0.10.
During the three months ended December 31, 2013, Petrodelta sold approximately 3.86 million barrels of oil (MMBO) for a daily average of 41,966 barrels of oil per day (BOPD), an increase of 15 percent over the same period in 2012 and one percent higher than the previous quarter. Petrodelta sold 0.62 billion cubic feet (BCF) of natural gas for a daily average of 6.7 million cubic feet per day (MMCFD), decreasing two percent over the same period in 2012, and increasing 4 percent over the previous quarter. Petrodelta's current production rate is approximately 43,800 BOPD.
06:10
GA Giant Interactive to be taken private for $12.00/share (11.40 )
Pursuant to the Merger Agreement, Parent will acquire the Company for cash consideration equal to $12.00 per ordinary share of the Company and $12.00 per American Depositary Share of the Company, each representing one Share, or ~$3.0 bln in aggregate cash consideration. This represents an18.5% premium over the closing price of $10.13 per ADS as quoted by the NYSE on November 22, 2013, and a premium of 31.6% and 33.6%, respectively, over the Company's 30-and 60-trading day volume-weighted average price as quoted by the NYSE prior to November 22, 2013, the last trading day prior to the Company's announcement on November 25, 2013 that it had received a non-binding "going private" proposal from the chairman of the board of directors of the Company, Mr. Yuzhu Shi, and an affiliate of Baring Private Equity Asia, to acquire all of the outstanding Shares, including Shares represented by ADSs, not already owned by them.
Under the terms of the Merger Agreement, the Company is not permitted to pay any dividends or repurchase any Shares pending consummation of the Merger. As a result, the Company's board of directors has suspended the Company's previously announced share repurchase program and dividend policy.
The Merger, which is currently expected to close during the second half of 2014, is subject to customary closing conditions, including the approval by an affirmative vote of holders of Shares representing at least two-thirds of the Shares present and voting in person or by proxy as a single class at a meeting of the Company's shareholders, which will be convened to consider the authorization and approval of the Merger Agreement and the transactions contemplated by the Merger Agreement, including the Merger, and the other closing conditions specified in the Merger Agreement.
06:03
STAA STAAR Surgical: FDA Advisory Panel votes in favor of STAAR Surgical's Visian Toric Implantable Collamer Lens, TICL (15.37 )
Co reported that its Visian Toric Implantable Lens or TICL received favorable votes to three questions presented to the FDA Ophthalmic Devices Panel of the Medical Devices Advisory Committee. The Panel voted favorably on all three questions posed to it by the FDA's Division of Ophthalmic, Neurological and Ear, Nose and Throat Devices.
The proposed indications for use of the Visian TICL, as presented during the panel meeting, was as follows:
for the correction of myopic astigmatism in adults 21-45 years with spherical equivalent ranging from -3.0D to = -15.0D with cylinder of 1.0D to 4.0D; for the reduction of myopic astigmatism in adults 21-45 years with spherical equivalent ranging from greater than -15.0D to -20.0D with cylinder 1.0D to 4.0D; fith an anterior chamber depth (ACD) of 3.0 mm or greater, when measured from the corneal endothelium to the anterior surface of the crystalline lens and a stable refractive history (within 0.5 Diopter for 1 year prior to implantation); and the Visian TICL is intended for placement in the posterior chamber (ciliary sulcus) of the phakic eye.
06:01
HBAN Huntington Banc appoints Howell D. McCullough III Chief Financial Officer (9.57 )
Co announced that it has named Howell D. McCullough III, senior executive vice president and chief financial officer. During the last seven years, he was the chief strategy officer at U.S. Bank (USB).
04:05
WIRES On The Wires
World Kitchen and Corning (GLW) announced they have entered into a strategic cooperative agreement to explore new technology options in the area of housewares. The agreement provides World Kitchen, one of the nation's leading housewares companies, the opportunity to work with Corning on glass and ceramic technologies, which could lead to new product development for the housewares industry. Accenture (ACN) has opened an Innovation Center for Financial Services in Jakarta to showcase leading digital and mobile-banking innovations designed to support strategic growth for banks and financial service providers in Indonesia. ZTE Corporation (ZTCOY) has announced that the 3G network supplied and developed by ZTE for BASE Company is the fastest 3G network in terms of Uplink and Downlink speeds in Belgium. Micrel (MCRL), an industry leader in high performance linear and power solutions, LAN and timing and communications solutions, announced today that it will be unveiling a family of power modules at APEC 2014. The MIC28304/MIC45205/MIC45208/MIC45212 family of power modules operate from 4.5V to 26.
03:51
ALV Autoliv prices private placement of long-term debt securities (96.49 )
Co announces that it expects to issue $1.25 billion of long term debt securities. Autoliv first announced its intention to issue long term debt on February 19, 2014.
Autoliv currently anticipates that the senior notes planned to be issued would have an average interest rate of 3.84%, and consist of:
$208 million of 5 year senior notes with an interest rate of 2.84%$275 million of 7 year senior notes with an interest rate of 3.51%$297 million of 10 year senior notes with an interest rate of 4.09%$285 million of 12 year senior notes with an interest rate of 4.24%$185 million of 15 year senior notes with an interest rate of 4.44%.
03:18
VOD Vodafone to acquire Grupo Corporativo Ono for EUR7.2 bln (36.98 )
Vodafone has agreed to acquire Ono for a total consideration equivalent to EUR7.2 billion (GBP6.0 billion) on a debt and cash free basis.
Highlights of transaction:
Ono has the largest next-generation network in Spain with ~7.2 million homes released to marketing serving 1.9 million customers in 13 of Spain's 17 regions. It is the market leader in high speed broadband, offering superior speeds and the most innovative pay-TV service in Spain. The network has abundant spare capacity and a future-proof fibre architecture. The Transaction accelerates Vodafone's unified communications strategy in a key, highly converged European market, providing a significant time-to-market advantage and network reach that is complementary to Vodafone Spain's ongoing FTTH build programme Vodafone expects to achieve cost and capex synergies with a run-rate of ~EUR240 million (GBP200 million) before integration costs by the fourth full year post completion, equivalent to a net present value of ~EUR2.0 billion (GBP1.7 billion) after integration costs. Vodafone sees a significant opportunity to accelerate growth in unified communications products and services by leveraging its extensive distribution and marketing capabilities and through cross-selling to each company's customer base. Vodafone estimates revenue synergies with a total net present value of ~EUR1.0 billion (GBP0.8 billion). The Transaction values Ono at a multiple of 7.5x 2013 EBITDA and 10.4x 2013 OpFCF, adjusted for cost and capex synergies. The Transaction is expected to be accretive to adjusted EPS and FCF per share from the first full year post completion after cost and capex synergies and before integration costs.
03:07
GWPH GW Pharma provides update on cannabinoid pipeline (74.69 )
Co provides an update on the Company's cannabinoid pipeline.
GWP42006 (CBDV) for epilepsy
GW has completed a Phase 1 clinical trial of GWP42006 to treat epilepsy. GWP42006 is a product which features the non-psychoactive cannabinoid cannabidivarin (CBDV) extracted from the cannabis plant. This Phase 1 single ascending and multiple dose pharmacokinetic and safety study in 66 healthy subjects demonstrated no safety or toxicity signals. In this study, subjects were dose titrated to investigate the maximum tolerated dose and to determine what, if any, side effects resulted. CBDV was well tolerated even at the highest tested dose and no significant side effects were observed. There were no serious or severe adverse events, nor any withdrawals due to adverse events, and all mild adverse events resolved on treatment.CBDV has shown the ability to treat seizures in pre-clinical models of epilepsy with significantly fewer side effects than currently approved anti-epileptic drugs1. CBDV also appears to employ a different mechanism of action to currently available anti-epileptic treatments. GW expects to commence a Phase 2 study of CBDV in patients with epilepsy later in 2014, using the doses identified as appropriate in this Phase 1 study.GW also announced that the Intellectual Property Office in the United Kingdom has granted a patent for the use of CBDV in the treatment of epilepsy, patent number GB2479153B. GWP42004 for Type 2 diabetes
GW has commenced a 12-week randomized, double blind, placebo controlled Phase 2b study of GWP42004 to treat Type 2 diabetes. GWP42004 is an orally administered product which features plant-derived tetrahydrocannabivarin as its active ingredient. THCV is distinct from THC and does not share its intoxicating psychoactive effects. The primary objective of this study is to compare the change in glycemic control in participants with Type 2 diabetes when treated with one of three doses of GWP42004 or placebo as add-on therapy to metformin with the primary endpoint being change from baseline to the end of treatment in mean glycosylated haemoglobin A1c level. The safety and tolerability of GWP42004 compared with placebo will also be assessed. This study is expected to enroll approximately 200 patients with an estimated completion date of the second half of 2015.This study follows positive findings reported in November 2012 from a Phase 2a exploratory study, showing evidence of anti-diabetic effects and supporting advancement of GWP42004 into further clinical development. The Phase 2a trial enrolled a total of 62 Type 2 diabetes patients and showed that GWP42004 produced a variety of desirable anti-diabetic effects including reduced fasting plasma glucose levels, an increase in fasting insulin, improved pancreatic beta-cell function, increased serum adiponectin, reduced systolic blood pressure, and reduced serum IL-6 levels. Several of these findings are consistent with pre-clinical data suggesting that GWP42004 protects the insulin-producing cells of the pancreatic islets, a highly desirable feature of a new anti-diabetic medicine, increases insulin sensitivity, and reduces fasting plasma glucose levels.GW believes that if the Phase 2b study confirms the Phase 2a findings, GWP42004 would have the potential to offer a novel orally-administered treatment option within one of the largest therapeutic areas where a serious unmet medical need still exists.GWP42003 for schizophrenia
GW has commenced a Phase 2a trial using GWP42003 to treat schizophrenia. GWP42003 featured purified CBD as its active ingredient. The primary objective of this study is to compare the change in symptom severity in patients with schizophrenia or related psychotic disorder when treated with GWP42003 or placebo, added to first-line anti-psychotic therapy over a period of six weeks as change from baseline to the end of treatment using the Positive and Negative Symptom Scale (PANSS)2 total score. Secondary objectives are to evaluate the effect of GWP42003 on quality of life and cognition and to assess the safety and tolerability of GWP42003. This study is expected to enroll approximately 80 patients with an estimated completion date of the second half of 2015.GWP42003 has shown notable anti-psychotic effects in accepted pre-clinical models of schizophrenia and importantly has also demonstrated the ability to reduce the characteristic movement disorders induced by currently available anti-psychotic agents. Rest of Pipeline
In addition to the pipeline programs highlighted above, GW continues to advance other programs, including:Sativex in Phase 3 clinical development for cancer pain. Initial top line Phase 3 data expected towards the end of 2014Sativex in Phase 3 clinical development for MS spasticity. US Phase 3 trial expected to commence in second half of 2014GWP42003 extract in Phase 2 clinical development for ulcerative colitis. Phase 2 data expected mid-2014GWP42002:GWP42003 in Phase 1b/2a clinical development for recurrent glioblastoma multiforme
03:00
ICPT Intercept Pharma announces positive pivotal Phase 3 POISE trial results; meets primary endpoint with high statistical significance (462.26 )
Co announces that its international Phase 3 POISE trial of obeticholic acid for the treatment of primary biliary cirrhosis demonstrated that OCA, at both a 10 mg dose and a 5 mg dose titrated to 10 mg, met the trial's primary endpoint of achieving a reduction in serum alkaline phosphatase to < 1.67x ULN with a = 15% reduction from baseline and a normal bilirubin level after 12 months of therapy.
The proportion of patients meeting the POISE primary endpoint was:
10% in the placebo group, 47% in the 10 mg OCA group and 46% in the 5-10 mg OCA group in an intention to treat analysis. The placebo group experienced a mean decrease in ALP from baseline of 5%, compared to a significant mean decrease of 39% in the 10 mg OCA dose group and 33% in the 5-10 mg OCA titration group. In addition, both OCA dose groups met pre-specified secondary endpoints of improvements in other liver function parameters, including GGT, ALT, AST and total bilirubin.OCA, Intercept's lead product candidate, is a bile acid analog and first-in-class agonist of the farnesoid X receptor in development for PBC, nonalcoholic steatohepatitis and other liver and intestinal diseases.
02:59
ICPT Intercept Pharma misses FY13 EPS by $0.03 (462.26 )
Reports FY13 net loss of $3.76 vs $3.73 CIQ estimate
Cash
As of December 31, 2013, our cash, cash equivalents and investment securities available for sale totaled ~$144.8 million, compared to $110.2 million at December 31, 2012. Based upon our currently expected level of program commitment and expected operating expenditures, co believes that we will be able to fund operations into the third quarter of 2015.
02:31
AFG American Fincl terminates tender offer for National Interstate shares (56.38 )
American Financial Group announces that at a hearing held by the United States District Court for the Northern District of Ohio, the court stated that it would grant a motion for preliminary injunction enjoining the consummation of the tender offer of AFG's wholly-owned subsidiary Great American Insurance Company to acquire all of the outstanding shares of National Interstate Corporation common stock not currently owned by AFG and GAIC.
In light of the court's stated intention, AFG announced that GAIC has terminated the tender offer. The tender offer was previously scheduled to expire at 12:00 midnight, Eastern time, on March 17, 2014. AFG believes that the $30 per share all-cash tender offer would have provided National Interstate's shareholders with compelling value at a significant premium to the market price prior to the announcement of the offer. AFG continues to be the majority shareholder of National Interstate and highly values National Interstate's business, management team and employees. National Interstate continues to represent an important strategic component of AFG's overall operations.
01:57
TGA Transglobe Energy and Caracal Energy announce proposed business combination to create one of the largest independent Africa focused oil producers (7.58 )
Caracal Energy and TransGlobe Energy (TGA) announced that they have entered into an agreement to merge the two companies by way of an exchange of shares pursuant to a plan of arrangement under the Business Corporations Act.
Rationale for the Proposed Business Combination
The Arrangement would create one of the largest independent Africa focused oil producers, poised for strong growth in oil production and reserves from development and high impact exploration in Chad and Egypt. Based on March 14, 2014 closing prices, the merged company would have a combined market capitalization of ~ $1.8 bln and:
Material Onshore Oil Production - Pro forma current oil production of 25,100 bbl/d (company working interest) and 2P reserve base of 135 MMbb (company working interest) from majority operated assets in Chad and Egypt and additional non-operated interests in YemenNear Term Production Growth - Average 2014E production target of 31,000-34,000 bbl/d (company working interest); ongoing appraisal and development programCatalyst Rich Exploration Program - Campaign of 30-42 high impact exploration wells in Chad by 2016, targeting 70+% of a total 833 MMbbl of gross risked mean prospective resources and low risk step out exploration in the Egyptian Eastern DesertStrong Regional Position - Enhanced scale provides a platform for future organic and acquisition growth in Africa, building on core operated positions in Chad and Egypt, with ready access to key infrastructure and export marketsImproved Financial Position - Combined business plan remains fully funded, with a pro forma cash position of $302 million and no net debt as at December 31, 2013, and a growing cash flow profile
01:55
CNMD CONMED confirms receipt of notice of intent to nominate candidates from Voce Capital Management (44.83 )
Co announces receipt of notice from Voce Capital Management of its intention to nominate James W. Green, Alan Kaganov, Joshua H. Levine, Jeffrey Nugent, and Daniel Plants to stand for election to the Company's Board of Directors at the 2014 Annual Meeting of Shareholders. CONMED shareholders are not required to take any action at this time.
CONMED has determined to postpone the record date for its 2014 Annual Meeting of Shareholders and expects that the new record date will be announced in a future press release.
01:54
SHLD Sears Hldg Board approves the separation of its Lands' End business and establishes March 24, 2014 as the Record Date for the pro-rata distribution of shares of Lands' End common stock (44.01 )
In the distribution, Sears Holdings stockholders will receive 0.300795 shares of Lands' End common stock for each share of Sears Holdings common stock held as of 5:30 p.m. Eastern time on the record date. Fractional shares of Lands' End common stock will not be distributed. Instead, fractional shares that Sears Holdings stockholders would otherwise have been entitled to receive after application of the foregoing ratio will be aggregated and sold in the public market by the distribution agent. The aggregate cash proceeds of these sales, net of brokerage fees and other expenses, then will be distributed pro rata to those stockholders who otherwise would have been entitled to receive fractional shares.
Following the spin-off, Sears Holdings will continue to be listed on the NASDAQ Global Select Market under the symbol "SHLD," while Lands' End expects to list its common stock on the NASDAQ Capital Market under the symbol "LE."
01:52
WD Walker & Dunlop announces repurchase of ~2.4 mln shares held by Column Guaranteed (15.45 )
Co announces that it has entered into an agreement to repurchase 2,450,451 shares of Walker & Dunlop's common stock owned by Column Guaranteed, an affiliate of Credit Suisse Securities, at a negotiated purchase price of $14.50 per share.
Following completion of the repurchase, which is expected to settle on March 17, 2014, CG will no longer hold a position in Walker & Dunlop. This repurchase was not part of any broader repurchase plan that the Company has in place.
01:51
DV DeVry Education issues statement on proposed gainful employment rule (39.80 )
Co issues the following statement (in summary):
"DeVry Education Group supports reasonable regulation concerning accountability and affordability in higher education. Today's proposed Gainful Employment regulations issued by the U.S. Department of Education moves closer to that mark, but is not there yet...As currently drafted, the rule would seriously undermine the Obama administration's goal of increasing the number of U.S. college graduates, especially lower-income Americans...The proposed rule holds private-sector programs to a higher standard than public-sector or independent programs...By applying these arbitrary standards and casting too broad a net, the proposal snares many good and historically productive programs in critical areas like information technology and healthcare. And public-sector schools do not have the funding to increase their capacity. It would cost $5.2 billion to provide the capacity to accommodate the estimated 630,000 students displaced by this proposed rule. That level of funding is unlikely to materialize anytime soon...We see a way forward, through regulations that truly gauge the quality of a program, through measures like actual employment, affordability and commitment to serving non-traditional and low-income students. We remain committed to working with the DOE to improve these rules."
01:50
CE Celanese announces Vinyl Acetate-based emulsions price increase in Asia (53.72 )
Co announces it will increase the price of vinyl acetate-based emulsions sold in Asia.
PVAc homopolymer and vinyl acetate ethylene emulsions will increase by JPY240/MT for China and $40/MT for Asia outside of China effective April 1, 2014, or as contracts allow. This price increase affects all applications including, but not limited to, adhesives, paints and coatings, building and construction, glass fiber, carpet and paper.
01:47
SKYW SkyWest reports combined February 2014 traffic For SkyWest Airlines And ExpressJet Airlines (12.39 )
Co reports a 0.1% increase in revenue passenger miles for February, while available seat miles decreased 2.6% compared to February 2013.
SkyWest also reported that passenger boardings for February decreased 3.0% to 4,141,803 compared to 4,269,786 for the same period last year.Load factor increased to 80.7% compared to 78.5% in February 2013. The combined airlines generated 2.1 billion RPMs for the month, while ASMs decreased to 2.7 billion. SkyWest also reported a decrease of 7.5% in departures to 98,906 for February compared to 106,928 for the same period last year. February departures were 7.5% below the same period in 2013. As a result of the extreme weather conditions in February 2014, SkyWest canceled ~7,000 flights due to this extreme weather.
01:45
DATA Tableau Software files registration statement for proposed follow-on offering (90.31 )
Co announces it has filed a registration statement relating to a proposed public offering of shares of its Class A common stock having an aggregate offering price of $300 million. In addition, Tableau Software expects to grant the underwriters an option to purchase additional shares having an aggregate offering price of up to $45 million. All of the shares in the offering are to be sold by Tableau Software.
01:44
SCMP Sucampo Pharma and Takeda announce update on Liquid Formulation Program for AMITIZA (8.04 )
Sucampo Pharma Americas, a wholly owned subsidiary of Sucampo Pharmaceuticals (SCMP), and its development and commercialization partner's subsidiary Takeda Pharmaceuticals (TKPYY) announce that the New Drug Application for the liquid formulation of AMITIZA will not be filed in the second half of 2014. In preliminary pre-NDA meeting comments, the FDA informed Sucampo that it would require additional data to characterize pharmacokinetics of the new formulation.
Sucampo and Takeda announced topline results from a pharmacodynamic, PK and tolerability study of a liquid formulation of AMITIZA in adults with chronic idiopathic constipation.
The study showed directional improvement in spontaneous bowel movement frequency in favor of liquid AMITIZA compared to placebo, but did not reach statistical significance. The safety profile observed in this study was consistent with previous clinical studies of AMITIZA. As a result of this outcome in conjunction with the FDA feedback, Sucampo and Takeda are now assessing next steps, which may include formulation modification. The companies are also evaluating potential impact to the timing of initiation of the second pivotal trial in the global, multicenter Phase 3 program for pediatric functional constipation in children aged 6 months to less than 6 years, as the liquid formulation would be required for this study.
01:43
AMGN Amgen's Talimogene Laherparepvec reduced size of melanoma tumors in new Phase 3 retrospective analysis (122.54 )
Co announces findings from a pre-specified retrospective analysis of patients with metastatic melanoma that showed talimogene laherparepvec reduced the size of injected tumors and also non-injected tumors that had metastasized to other parts of the body. The analysis recorded tumor-level responses from a pivotal Phase 3 study evaluating talimogene laherparepvec in patients with injectable unresected stage IIIB, IIIC or IV melanoma compared to granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor.
The most frequently observed adverse events in the Phase 3 study were fatigue, chills and pyrexia. The most common serious adverse events include disease progression in both groups, and cellulitis and pyrexia in the talimogene laherparepvec group. Serious adverse events occurred in 26 percent of talimogene laherparepvec patients and 13 percent of GM-CSF patients. Immune-mediated events were reported infrequently.
17:03
SCANX This week's biggest % gainers/losers -Technical-
The following are this week's top 20 percentage gainers and top 20 percentage losers, categorized by sectors (over $300 mln market cap and 100K average daily volume).
This week's top 20 % gainers Technology: CALL (22.76 +24.71%)Services: VLCCF (14 +26.13%), BYD (13.82 +14.4%)Industrial Goods: CPST (2.22 +21.31%)Healthcare: CMRX (27.14 +44.9%), TSRO (36.76 +21.88%), AMRI (18.81 +20.42%), VNDA (17.65 +15.21%), UNIS (4.8 +14.56%)Financial: CISG (8.94 +22.13%)Basic Materials: SAND (6.71 +26.37%), EPL (38.05 +26.08%), BPZ (2.97 +20.73%), MUX (3.56 +18.27%), PPP (7.8 +16.59%), ANV (6.39 +15.97%), EMES (53.25 +15.76%), GFI (4.36 +15.65%), ALJ (15.94 +14.59%), NG (4.57 +13.4%)This week's top 20 % losers Technology: VRNS (42 -21.47%), PLUG (6.71 -18.86%), YOKU (29.16 -18.11%), CUDA (34.69 -17.09%), TSL (15.26 -16.79%)Services: DL (19.73 -25.46%), HELI (7.26 -25%), BPI (14.55 -24.53%), HTHT (23.44 -21.47%), ARO (5.83 -21%), HMIN (30.55 -18.66%), QUNR (29.03 -18.29%), DANG (15.54 -16.72%), WBAI (41.43 -16.3%)Industrial Goods: AMRC (7.52 -25.62%), RAVN (32.44 -17.1%)Healthcare: RPTP (11.25 -27.93%), PETX (17.03 -17.21%)Financial: RM (24.45 -19.52%), WRLD (81.03 -17.7%)
17:02
ISBC Investors Bancorp to commence stock offering (stock halted) (27.04 -0.12)
Co announced today that the registration statement relating to the sale of common stock of New Investors Bancorp has been declared effective by the Securities and Exchange Commission. The Company anticipates that on or before March 21, 2014, offering materials will be mailed to depositors and certain former depositors eligible to purchase shares in the subscription offering, and proxy solicitation materials will be mailed to depositors and stockholders.
New Investors Bancorp is offering for sale between 170,000,000 and 264,500,000 shares of common stock at $10.00 per share, representing the majority ownership interest in the Company currently owned by Investors Bancorp, MHC. The number of shares in the offering is based on an independent appraisal of the estimated pro forma market value of Investors Bancorp as of March 3, 2014. At the conclusion of the conversion and offering, the existing shares of common stock held by the public stockholders of the Company will be exchanged for between 1.9733 and 3.0702 shares of New Investors Bancorp common stock, depending on the number of shares sold in the offering. After the completion of the conversion and offering, New Investors Bancorp will be 100% owned by public stockholders, and Investors Bancorp, MHC will cease to exist.
Keefe, Bruyette & Woods, will act as selling agent in the subscription offering.
16:53
DXYN Dixie Group acquires Atlas Carpet Mills (15.59 -0.18)
Co announced its agreement to acquire Atlas Carpet Mills, a high-end manufacturer and marketer of commercial floorcovering products located in Los Angeles, California. As outlined in its agreement, closing of the acquisition is scheduled for Wednesday, March 19. Atlas had sales of approximately $53 million in 2013, having offerings in both broadloom and modular carpet tile. The acquisition of Atlas will be an all cash transaction and will involve retaining the top three officers under five year contracts.
16:49
OPY Oppenheimer Holdings announces retirement of $50 mln of 8.75% senior secured notes due 2018 (26.00 -0.70)
Co announced that it will be retiring a total of $50 million (25%) of its 8.75% Senior Secured Notes due 2018. The Company will deliver to the holders of the Notes a notice of partial redemption, notifying such holders of the Company's intent to redeem on April 15, 2014 (the "Redemption Date") $45 million aggregate principal amount of the outstanding Notes at a redemption price equal to 106.563% of the principal amount of the Notes to be redeemed, plus accrued and unpaid interest thereon to the Redemption Date. In addition, the Company will also be retiring the $5 million aggregate principal amount of the Notes that it currently holds. Upon completion of the redemption and retirement on the Redemption Date, $150 million aggregate principal amount of the Notes will remain outstanding. The retirement of the Notes will reduce the Company's interest costs by $3.9 million annually.
16:47
CALI China Auto Logistics reports services agreement with the Tianjin International Automall has not been renewed; cites competition with recently acquired Airport International Automall (3.96 -0.30)
Co, which recently acquired the Airport International Automall in Tianjin, reported today its agreement to manage the Tianjin International Automall (a cooperation agreement with Tianjin Prominent Hero International Logistics, Co., Ltd) expired on February 28, 2014 and was not renewed.
"To a certain extent the two malls are competitive," stated Mr. Tong Shiping, Chairman and CEO of China Auto Logistics, "and this is the main reason a joint decision was reached with the owners of the Tianjin International Automall to not renew the agreement." Mr. Shiping added, "Despite being a small fraction of our sales, our auto mall management fees generated an excellent bottom line result. In recent periods, this contribution has been magnified by our continuing competitive stance in our much larger luxury auto sales business where profitability has decreased in order to maintain our leadership position. Going forward our focus is on further developing and implementing plans for our Airport Automall and our other businesses."
16:32
BLDP Ballard Power: Anglo American Platinum Limited has converted its $4 million non-interest bearing promissory note into common shares (5.69 -0.29)
Co announced that Anglo American Platinum Limited has converted its $4 million non-interest bearing promissory note into common shares, as per the terms of an agreement announced on March 3, 2013. This strategic investment, made through Anglo American Platinum's PGM Development Fund, supports continued development and commercial advancement of Ballard's fuel cell production.
As part of this development initiative, a prototype methanol-fuelled mini-grid system will be deployed in Q2 2014 in a 12-month field trial designed to validate the technical and operating requirements of a home generator product for off-grid applications in South Africa. Development work on a new lower cost methanol fuel reformer and longer life fuel cell stack for a commercial version of the home generator will continue in parallel with the field trial. This work will also be leveraged in Ballard's commercial telecom backup power systems.
16:31
CMC Commercial Metals settles antitrust class action lawsuit for ~$4 mln (18.75 -0.02)
Co announced that it has reached final settlement in the Standard Iron Works v. Arcelor Mittal et al. lawsuit in the amount of approximately $4 mln, which the Company estimates is less than the anticipated cost to the Company of continuing to defend the lawsuit. The class action litigation, filed in September 2008 on behalf of the direct purchasers of steel products, alleged violation of the federal antitrust laws by eight U.S. steel producers through allegedly concerted restrictions on production. Commercial Metals Company has denied from the outset any and all wrongdoing in connection with the claims that have or could have been alleged against the Company in the lawsuit, and the agreed upon settlement contains no admission of liability from the Company. The settlement requires preliminary and final approval by the Court, which the Company anticipates it will receive. Despite the Company's belief, after extensive discovery and investigation of the facts, that the claims lack merit and that it has full and complete defenses to all of the claims asserted against it, the Company agreed to enter into the settlement to avoid further expense, inconvenience, and distraction of burdensome and protracted litigation.
16:23
WRAPX Closing Market Summary: Stocks End Down Week on Cautious Note Ahead of Crimean Referendum
The major averages ended the week on a lower note as participants continued reducing their risk exposure ahead of the weekend, which will feature a Sunday referendum in Crimea on potential annexation to Russia.
The stock market opened with modest losses, but made a quick recovery with help from most sectors; however, the S&P 500 (-0.3%) was unable to make a sustained move above the 1852 level, which marked the session high for the benchmark index.
After making an early jump to highs, the S&P 500 spent the next hour in a steady retreat towards its session lows as the three top weighted sectors-financials (-0.6%), technology (-0.7%), and health care (-0.5%)-refused to take part in the rally. The three groups remained among the laggards throughout the day, keeping the broader market from maintaining its gain after the major averages jumped back into the green in the late morning.
The return into positive territory occurred after comments from the press conference held by Russia's Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov made the rounds. Specifically, Mr. Lavrov said Russia has no intentions of invading Eastern Ukraine. That remark gained the most traction, but Mr. Lavrov continued, saying U.S. and Russia remain at odds regarding Ukraine and that Russia does not need any international structure to mediate in Russia-Ukraine relations.
After the Russian Foreign Minister delivered his statement, U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry conducted a press conference of his own. Secretary Kerry said that despite prolonged discussions with his Russian counterpart, not much has changed and that the Sunday referendum remains on schedule.
Although stocks made their way back into the green after Mr. Lavrov's press conference, they spent the afternoon in a slow retreat as the largest sectors weighed. Interestingly, small caps outperformed with the Russell 2000 holding a modest gain throughout the session. The index ended higher by 0.4% while large caps were not as fortunate.
The technology sector (-0.7%) ended at the bottom of the leaderboard. The space was pressured by its largest members. Apple (AAPL 524.69, -5.96), Google (GOOG 1172.80, -16.26), and Qualcomm (QCOM 74.74, -0.89) lost between 1.1% and 1.3%.
Elsewhere, the financial sector (-0.6%) trimmed its month-to-date gain to 0.4%. Even though the sector maintained its gain for the month, it surrendered its year-to-date advance (-0.5%). Top sector components registered losses across the board with Bank of America (BAC 16.80, -0.36) leading the weakness with a 2.1% decline.
Even though stocks finished on their lows, Treasuries did not move much during afternoon action. The benchmark 10-yr yield ended little changed at 2.65% versus 2.72% registered last Friday.
While Treasuries did not signal additional safe-haven flows today, the foreign exchange market did. The Japanese yen continued its recent strength, sending the dollar/yen pair to the 101.30 area after starting the week around 103.30.
Volatility protection was in demand throughout the session, pushing the CBOE Volatility Index (VIX 17.77, +1.55) to levels last seen on February 6.
Similar to yesterday, trading volume was on the light side with only 628 million shares changing hands at the NYSE.
Looking back at today's data:
Producer prices declined 0.1% in February after increasing 0.2% in January while the Briefing.com consensus expected producer prices to increase 0.2%. The drop in producer prices was the result of a sharp drop in producer services costs. Final demand for goods rose 0.4% for a third consecutive month whereas final demand for services declined 0.3% in February. Excluding food and energy, overall core prices declined 0.2% in February after increasing 0.2% in January. The consensus expected these prices to increase 0.1%. The University of Michigan Consumer Sentiment Index slipped to 79.9 in the March preliminary reading from 81.6 in February. The Briefing.com consensus expected the index to increase to 82.0. The Current Conditions Index increased to 96.1 from 95.4 in February. The Expectations Index fell to 69.4 in March from 72.7. On Monday, the Empire Manufacturing Survey for March will be announced at 8:30 ET while the January Net Long-Term TIC Flows report will cross the wires at 9:00 ET. The Industrial Production and Capacity Utilization report for February will be released at 9:15 ET while the day's data will be topped off with the 10:00 ET release of the NAHB Housing Market Index for March.
Russell 2000 +1.9% YTD Nasdaq Composite +1.7% YTD S&P 500 -0.4% YTD Dow Jones Industrial Average -3.1% YTD Week in Review: Stocks Slump as Focus Turns Back to Ukraine
The major averages began the new trading week on a slightly lower note with small caps leading the weakness. The Russell 2000 shed 0.3% while the S&P 500 slipped less than a point with six sectors ending in the red. Equity indices started the day in negative territory with only the Nasdaq (-0.04%) making a very brief appearance in the green. After sliding through the first hour of action, the major averages reversed and spent the remainder of the session climbing off their lows with help from the three top-weighted sectors. Health care and financials gained 0.4% and 0.04%, respectively, while technology (-0.1%) ended just below its flat line. Also contributing to the rebound was the energy sector, which added 0.2% even as crude oil fell 1.4% to $101.07/bbl. The S&P 500 tried to regain its flat line, but came up just short as the weakness among consumer discretionary (-0.4%), industrials (-0.5%), and materials (-0.1%) sectors kept a lid on the attempted rally.
Stocks finished the Tuesday session near their lows with the Russell 2000 (-1.0%) leading the slide. The S&P 500 lost 0.5% with nine sectors ending in the red. The key indices started the day with modest gains and spent the first two hours of action in the neighborhood of their flat lines. Although the early trade lacked clear sector leadership, that was overlooked due to the opening strength among heavily-weighted sectors like health care (-0.3%), technology (-0.2%), and consumer staples (unch). The relative strength of the three groups kept the market afloat in the early going considering they account for nearly 42.0% of the entire S&P 500. However, another influential sector-financials (-0.7%)-was a bit more reluctant and never pulled away from its flat line. Fittingly, the group was among the first to show weakness when the broader market slipped into the red while the other sectors followed suit.
On Wednesday, the market finished the session on a mixed note. The Nasdaq (+0.4%) and Russell 2000 (+0.3%) posted modest gains while the Dow Jones Industrial Average (-0.1%) finished in the red. For its part, the S&P 500 (+0.03%) settled just above its flat line. Stocks began the day in the red, but spent the first two hours of action in a steady climb off their lows. The cautious start took place amid broad-based weakness across major European markets where Germany's DAX, Great Britain's FTSE, and France's CAC all posted losses close to 1.0% apiece. In addition to the weakness in Europe, losses among major Asian indices also weighed on the early sentiment. On that note, markets in Japan, South Korea, and Hong Kong fell 2.6%, 1.7%, and 1.7%, respectively, while China's Shanghai Composite (-0.2%) outperformed.
The stock market ended the Thursday session near the lows after renewed concerns surrounding the situation in Ukraine, combined with more warnings signs from China, contributed to participants reducing their risk exposure. The jitters related to China are tied up in economic and financial risk, whereas, the concerns over Ukraine are tied up in geopolitical risk that has the potential to become a global economic problem. The tech-heavy Nasdaq (-1.5%) led the retreat while the S&P 500 lost 1.2% with eight sectors ending in the red. As a result, the benchmark index settled below its 2013 closing high of 1848.36. Equity indices began the session with modest gains, but the early strength was short-lived as the S&P 500 notched its high within the first ten minutes of action, spending the remainder of the trading day in a steady slide. Although stocks opened higher, the dollar/yen pair flashed an early warning signal when it began dropping at the start of the New York Session. The currency pair hovered near 102.80, but slumped all the way to 101.60 by the time the closing bell rang.
16:23
CNS Cohen & Steers increases quarterly dividend 10% to $0.22 from $0.20 per share (37.14 -0.31)
16:22
CRMB Crumbs Bake Shop (thinly traded) announces appointment of Frederick G. Kraegel as Chairman of the Board of Directors; Edward M. Slezak appointed permanent CEO (0.64 +0.01)
Co announced that its Board of Directors has appointed Frederick G. Kraegel as Chairman of the Board of Directors. The Company also announced that Edward M. Slezak has been appointed as permanent Chief Executive Officer and Ronda S. Kase has been named Secretary. Mr. Slezak has been leading the Company as interim Chief Executive Officer in addition to his duties as General Counsel and Ms. Kase has been serving as Assistant Secretary in addition to her duties as Corporate Compliance Officer. Mr. Slezak is also a member of the Company's Board of Directors.
16:16
UPS UPS announces general rate increase of 4.4% (96.27 -0.83)
Co announced a general rate increase of 4.4 percent, effective March 31, 2014. This rate adjustment applies to non-contractual less-than-truckload (LTL) shipments rated on the current UPS Freight tariffs, including 525, 560, 570 and 571. It also applies to all offshore rates and charges and accessorials listed in the UPS Freight 102 Series Rules Tariff.
16:15
HBM Hudbay Minerals acquires additional shares of Panoro Minerals (7.41 -0.05)
Co announced that it has acquired 10,127,500 common shares of Panoro Minerals Ltd. at a purchase price of C$0.28 per Share for total consideration of C$2,835,700. The Shares acquired by Hudbay were purchased over the TSX Venture Exchange pursuant to a private agreement and represent approximately 4.9% of the issued and outstanding Shares. As a result of the investment, Hudbay now owns and has control over 22,907,500 Shares, representing approximately 11.2% of the issued and outstanding Shares.
16:12
FMCC Freddie Mac prices third multifamily securities offering this year, K-037 (184.66 -0.52)
Co recently priced a new offering of Structured Pass-Through Certificates, which are multifamily mortgage-backed securities. The approximately $1.15 billion in K Certificates ("K-037 Certificates") is expected to settle on or about March 25, 2014. This is Freddie Mac's third K Certificates offering this year. Co-Lead Managers and Joint Bookrunners: Wells Fargo Securities, LLC and Merrill Lynch, Pierce, Fenner & Smith Incorporated as co-lead managers and joint bookrunners.
16:06
DRYS DryShips announces Ocean Rig UDW's proposed offering of $500 mln senior notes due 2019 (3.40 -0.12)
Co, and through its majority owned subsidiary, Ocean Rig UDW (ORIG), of offshore deepwater drilling services, announced that Ocean Rig intends, subject to market and other conditions, to offer $500 million in aggregate principal amount of senior notes due 2019 in a private offering within the United States to qualified institutional buyers pursuant to Rule 144A under the Securities Act of 1933, as amended, and to certain other persons outside of the United States in reliance on Regulation S under the Securities Act. Ocean Rig intends to use the net proceeds from the offering of the Notes, together with other available funds, to fund the repurchase or redemption of its 9.5% Senior Unsecured Notes due 2016, for which it is conducting a concurrent tender offer, and to pay related fees and expenses.
16:06
DRAD Digirad acquires Telerhythmics for ~$3.6 mln (3.42 +0.07)
Co announced today that it has acquired all the outstanding membership interest of Telerhythmics, LLC, a 24-hour cardiac event monitoring service used on an outsourced basis by hospitals and physician offices. Based in Memphis, Tennessee, privately-held Telerhythmics provides its monitoring services throughout the eastern region of the U.S. Total up front consideration for the purchase was approximately $3.6 million, which included a $3.47 million cash payment up front and assumption of approximately $131,000 in debt. In addition, there is an earn-out opportunity of up to $501,000 over approximately three years based on meeting certain EBITDA targets. Telerhythmics generated approximately $5.6 million in revenue in 2013. Once Telerhythmics goes through a short integration period, it is expected to be accretive on an EBITDA basis. Under Digirad's ownership and at the 2013 level of annual revenue, it is expected the business will generate approximately $350,000 of EBITDA in the first twelve months, and then approximately $800,000 of EBITDA annually thereafter.
16:04
SBAC SBA Communications elects settlement method of 4.0% convertible senior notes due 2014 (94.96 +0.09)
Co announced that on March 14, 2014 SBA provided notice to the trustee and holders of its 4.0% Convertible Senior Notes due 2014 that it had elected to settle the principal amount of any conversions in cash and any additional conversion consideration at the conversion rate then applicable in shares of its Class A common stock, effective March 17, 2014. Concurrently with the settlement of any 4.0% Notes converted, SBA will settle the associated convertible note hedges and receive an equal number of shares to those issued to the noteholders.
16:04
FII Fed Investors to acquire $421 mln in fixed-income assets from Huntington Funds (26.92 -0.60)
FII and and Huntington Asset Advisors, in investment adviser subsidiary of The Huntington National Bank, have reached a definitive agreement regarding the acquisition by Federated of certain assets relating to Huntington's management of its fixed-income mutual funds. In connection with the acquisition, ~$421 mln in fixed-income assets will be reorganized from five Huntington fixed-income mutual funds into five existing Federated fixed-income mutual funds with similar investment objectives.
The reorganization is expected to be tax-free and is anticipated to be completed in the second quarter of 2014. Closing of the transactions is subject to shareholder approval and certain other contingencies.
16:02
CVA Covanta announces adjustment to the conversion rate on its 3.25% cash convertible senior notes due 2024 (17.36 +0.21)
Co announced an adjustment to the conversion rate on its 3.25% cash convertible senior notes due June 1, 2014 in connection with its previously announced dividend that was payable on January 3, 2014 to stockholders of record as of the close of business on December 26, 2013. As a result of this dividend, the conversion rate was adjusted to 64.6669 shares of Covanta's common stock per $1,000 principal amount of the notes. The adjusted conversion rate is equivalent to an adjusted conversion price of $15.46 per share.
16:00
MEAS Measurement Specialties Announces Consolidation of US Temperature Operations; costs including severance, retention, relocation and equipment transfers are expected to be roughly $2.5 to $3.0 mln (63.69 )
Co announced that it will close and consolidate its US Temperature operations in Dayton, OH, St. Marys, PA, Shrewsbury, MA and Ham Lake, MN into a new Greenfield facility that is being built in Andover, MN."This consolidation will not only improve MEAS' efficiency and capital utilization, but will provide our customers a single point of contact for their temperature sensing needs in the US. Restructuring costs including severance, retention, relocation and equipment transfers are expected to be roughly $2.5 to $3.0 mln while annual savings resulting from consolidation efficiencies are expected to be roughly $2.0 to $2.5 mln. We will begin moving production in calendar year 2014 and expect to complete all transfers and facility closures by the end of calendar year 2015."
]]></text></news-item>