<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-CND1-DXKH-N0KW"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Safety Insurance Group rises 0.8% from 14-day low</title><source>News Bites US Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Safety Insurance Group, Inc. (NASDAQ:SAFT) was up 0.8% from its 14-day low of US$53.25 on 17 March, 2014. Its Williams % R is -85.7. A reading of between -80 and -100 suggests it is near its 14-day low. This is defined as oversold, a bullish signal. Its Relative Strength Index [RSI] is 23.5. An RSI reading of between 0 and 30 suggests the stock is close to its 14-day low. This suggests the stock is oversold; another bullish signal. The stock price increased 5.0c (or 0.1%) to close at US$53.68. Compared with the NASDAQ-100 Index which rose 34.6 points (or 1.0%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -0.9%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Safety Insurance Group, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/0010519717703142123
Bullish SignalsUptrend- Open interest hit a nine-day high.
- The present value of US$1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in Safety Insurance Group is US$1,198, including a capital gain of US$130 and dividend reinvested of US$68.
Oversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The Relative Strength Index (RSI) of 23.5 has breached the oversold line of 30, suggesting the price decrease of 4.2% in the last 14 days is unusually high. - The stock is oversold according to the Williams % R indicator of -85.7, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day low of US$53.25. - The Stochastic indicator of 11.2 has pierced the oversold line of 20.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price to Book of 1.2 [1.7]. We estimate Safety Insurance Group stock is trading at a current year Price to Book of 1.2 and a forward year Price to Book of 1.1. - Return on Assets 3.7% [2.3%].- Dividend yield of 5.6% [1.4%].Other Bullish Signals:- The P/E of 14.2 multiplied by the P/NTA of 1.2 is 16.9. Being less than the Benjamin Graham benchmark of 22.5 the stock appears undervalued. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.5. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- Revenue growth is positive and has seen consecutive rises in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]
- Net Profit margin, EBIT margin and EBITDA margin are positive and have seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

Bearish Signals- The price dropped 3.9% in the last month. The stock has been exacerbated by firm volume of 1.5 times average for the month.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Return on Equity 8.4% [10.9%].Other Bearish Signals:- Total Liabilities/ EBITDA of 9.2 is more than or equal to 5, this compares unfavourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - Net profit margin has averaged 6.5% in the last 3 years. This is lower than the sector average of 7.9% and suggests a low margin of safety.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity of 8.4% is lower than sector average of 10.9%. This is computed as net profit margin of 8.3% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 0.45 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 2.3.
NoteVolume: there were 23,326 shares worth US$1.3 million traded. Trading volume was 25% lighter than average. Beta: the Beta of Safety Insurance Group stock is 0.9. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market. - Safety Insurance Group is at a discount of 6.8% to its 12-month high of US$57.63 on 21 Oct, 2013. It is also at a premium of 13.5% to the 12-month low of US$47.30 on 15 Apr, 2013.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Parity:- Price/Earnings of 14.2 [14.7]. We estimate Safety Insurance Group stock is trading at a current year P/E of 8.8 and a forward year P/E of 5.4.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 13: Safety Insurance Group insider sells; shares at a two-month lowSafety Insurance Group (NASDAQ:SAFT) insider Patrick N Edward Jr sold 1,087 shares worth approximately US$58,481 on March 12, 2014. The selling price was USD53.8. The shares hit a two-month low on the day.
March 13: Safety Insurance Group insider sells; shares at a two-month lowSafety Insurance Group (NASDAQ:SAFT) insider Patrick N Edward Jr sold 1,249 shares worth approximately US$66,822 on March 13, 2014. The selling price was USD53.5. The shares hit a two-month low on the day.
March 11: Safety Announces Fourth Quarter and Year End 2013 ResultsBOSTON Safety Insurance Group, Inc. (NASDAQ:SAFT) today reported fourth quarter 2013 results. Net income for the quarter ended December 31, 2013 was $11.7 million, or $0.76 per diluted share, compared to net income of $9.6 million, or $0.62 per diluted share, for the comparable 2012 period.
February 19: Saft Awarded Contracts from Boeing Exceeding $20M for Li-ion Batteries to Power Geo SatellitesPARIS Saft, the world's leading designer and manufacturer of high technology batteries for industry, has been awarded five new contracts from Boeing to build Li-ion batteries for four of Boeing's current GEO communication satellite programs. Including these orders, Boeing has awarded a total of eleven contracts under its long-term agreement with Saft signed in 2009 to produce Li-ion GEO satellite batteries.
February 19: Saft delivers high-power Li-ion battery system to ECO-H Technologies, Inc. for Hybrid Power Management System[News Story] PARIS Saft, the world's leading designer and manufacturer of advanced technology batteries for industry, has been awarded a contract from Tri-Technic Inc. for the delivery of two Intensium(Registered) Max 20M (IM20M) battery containers to power the Fort Hunter Liggett grid energy storage system.The Fort Hunter Liggett energy storage unit was designated as a "Net Zero" pilot installation by the Department of Defense (DOD), which signifies that it will only consume as much energy as it produces.
February 19: Saft to Deliver Li-ion Battery Containers to Tri-Technic Inc. for Fort Hunter Liggett Energy Storage[News Story] PARIS Saft, the world's leading designer and manufacturer of advanced technology batteries for industry, has been awarded a contract from ECO-H Technologies, Inc. for the delivery of the first Intensium(Registered) Flex Li-ion battery system to power and store energy for the ECO-H System.
February 14: Safety Declares First Quarter 2014 Dividend and Schedules Year-End 2013 EventsBOSTON The Board of Directors of Safety Insurance Group, Inc. (NASDAQ:SAFT) today approved a $0.60 per share quarterly cash dividend on its issued and outstanding common stock payable on March 14, 2014 to shareholders of record at the close of business on March 3, 2014.Safety plans to announce its 2013 annual results on March 11, 2014, with its Annual Report on Form 10-K to be filed with the U.S.
ISIN: US78648T1007
O:SAFT
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>