<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-37J1-JDKC-R0YT"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Relief efforts under way in drought-hit areas</title><source>South Asian Media Network</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ITHI, March 18 -- Sindh Revenue and Relief Minister, Makhdoom Jameel-ul-Zaman, has said that the Federal, provincial and district governments are taking appropriate steps to provide relief to the drought-hit victims of Tharparkar.
He said this while speaking at a meeting here on Tuesday with the district government officials and elected representatives to review the progress of work for dealing with drought situation in the district.
The minister said that the Relief department was working to provide the facilities and relief to drought-hit victims.
The Provincial Disaster Management Authority (PDMA) was also taking steps in this regard, he added.
He directed the deputy commissioner Tharparkar that the dues of transporters should be cleared immediately and where there was a need of anything, concerned department should be informed immediately.
The Sindh government has already released Rs 50 million to clear the dues of transporters, as the wheat distribution process should not halt at any stage, he said.
Speaking on the occasion, Deputy Commissioner Tharparkar, Asif Ikram said that the work of relief has been expedited to save the lives of livestock and children.
A complaint center has been set up at the deputy commissioner Mithi office, he added.
The Deputy Commissioner said that 33823 bags of wheat had been distributed till Tuesday and additional 8000 bags had been sought from Mirpurkhas.
He further said that 69 children died till Tuesday due to multiple causes, including pneumonia, premature birth, delivery at home and other diseases. He maintained that no child died of malnutrition.
In a meeting, Director General PDMA Suleman Shah said that the PDMA had provided 5000 bags of food and 12000 mineral water bottles to the district government for drought-hit victims.
Speaking on the occasion, Food Minister Sindh Jam Mehtab Dahar said that there were 65000 bags of wheat at different go-downs of the district.
PPP MNA Faqeer Sher Muhammad Bilalani, MPA Makhdoom Naeemullah and other district officials were present on the occasion. Saudi Embassy in Islamabad has decided to send twenty three tone of food items for the drought hit Tharparkar.
In a statement Wednesday, the embassy said Saudi Arabia has always stood by Pakistan in the hour of trial. Opposition parties have submitted a joint requisition for convening Sindh Assembly session over the drought in Tharparkar.
The requisition signed by the members of Muttahida Qaumi Movement (MQM), Muslim League-Functional (PML-F) and Pakistan Tehreek-e-Insaf (PTI), has been submitted at Sindh Assembly Secretariat. While calling the session of the provincial legislature, the opposition parties have demanded from the government to unveil the people responsible for the drought in Tharparkar, which claimed several lives in desert region. A meeting of MQM parliamentary party chaired by Syed Sardar Ahmed considering the situation in Thar and the party's strategy over the issue.
Fauji Fertilizer Company (FFC) team with trucks, carrying 22 tons of dry ration, has left for Thar, to help drought-hit people in Thar. Looking beyond profitability, FFC believed in helping deprived communities and pioneered in helping communities in education, health or in case of calamities, said a press release issued here.
FFC applauded the efforts of federal, provincial government, Armed Forces and all non-government and private entities who stand with the nation at this time of need
Published by HT Syndication with permission from South Asian Media Network. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>