<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-C081-JBF5-T2K2"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>FINAL SCOTTISH SCHEDULE</title><source>PA Newswire: Scotland</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Good evening from the Press Association Scotland. Here is our final schedule for Monday March 17:
COURTS Clutha: Two teenagers who broke into a pub which a police helicopter had crashed into have been detained for six months.
SCOTLAND Murphy: Scots tempted to vote for independence on the grounds that ``things can't get any worse'' have been warned that ``things can indeed get worse'' by a senior Labour MP.
POLITICS Kennedy: Unionist warnings that Scotland ``could never go it alone'' are unlikely to resonate with voters in the independence referendum, a veteran MP has said.
SCOTLAND Arrest: A man has been arrested over alleged offences relating to the wearing or displaying of articles linked to terrorist groups.
SCOTLAND Trafficking: Labour and the Scottish Government have united to introduce tougher penalties for human traffickers and provide enhanced support for victims.
SCOTLAND Infrastructure: Infrastructure projects worth £400 million were completed in Scotland last year, the Scottish Government said.
SCOTLAND Education: The Education Secretary will face questions over the resignation of a key architect of controversial new exams just weeks before they are due to take place.
DEATH DicksonWright: Former TV chef Clarissa Dickson Wright has died at the age of 66, her agents said today.
SCOTLAND Heroin: Two men have been arrested after police recovered heroin worth around £140,000.
POLICE Hillwalker: Police searching for a missing hillwalker in the Outer Hebrides have found a body.
SCOTLAND Football: A football supporter is expected in court after he allegedly subjected a Partick Thistle player to racist comments during a match on Saturday.
SPORT Commonwealth: The Queen's baton relay will visit more than 400 communities and pass landmarks such as Loch Ness and the Glenfinnan Viaduct as it tours Scotland.
SCOTLAND Jobs: Scotland has seen the highest increase in permanent starting salaries for more than a decade, new research has revealed.
SCOTLAND Shoppers: Retail leaders have called for a comprehensive reform of the business rates system as new figures showed there has been a fall in shopper numbers.
DEFENCE Reservists: Dozens of reservist marines have endured a fortnight of living in temperatures of -30C (-22F) in the Arctic Circle as they honed their skills in one of the world's most challenging environments.
SCOTLAND Bank: A bank has announced it is to increase its lending to small and medium sized businesses by a further £1 billion this year to help them make the most of the economic recovery.
Late reporter: Hilary Duncanson 07977 252 013
Press Association Scotland provisional diary for Tuesday March 18
POLMONT: First UK public inquiry into a fracking application begins. A public inquiry into Dart Energy's proposed Coal Bed Methane (CBM) development at Airth near Falkirk begins. It is the first public inquiry into fracking in the UK, and is expected to last three weeks, with protests expected from community and environmental groups. Inchyra Hotel, Polmont. Lisa Trainer, Friends of the Earth Scotland, 0131 243 2715.
0930 EDINBURGH: Edinburgh International Festival media launch. Festival director Jonathan Mills will reveal the full programme. Photocall at 9.30am and presentation at 10.30am, followed by interview opportunities. Main Hall, The Hub, Castlehill, EH1 2NE. Susie Burnet 0131 473 2020 / 07810 383 091.
0930 PORTLETHEN: School transport announcement. Transport Minister Keith Brown makes announcement on dedicated school transport. Councillors Peter Argyle and Isobel Davidson from Aberdeenshire Council will also be available for interview. Portlethen Academy, Bruntland Road, AB12 4QL. Caroline Trainer on 0141 272 7195 or 07837 062787.
0945 LOCH LOMOND: John Hartson Foundation golf day. John Hartson will be joined by former footballers, pundits and celebrities to raise money for his testicular cancer charity. Hartson and former Celtic player Alan Stubbs available for short interview before the match. No filming or other interview opportunities available. Carrick Golf Club, Cameron House, G83 8QZ. Lorna King 07795 008 836.
1000 GLASGOW: Amnesty referendum campaign launch. Amnesty International launches its The Rights Referendum campaign to ensure human rights are central to whatever path Scotland chooses in September. The Lighthouse, Viewing Gallery, 11 Mitchell Lane. Pauline Kelly 0131 718 6687 / 07818 453070.
1000 EDINBURGH: Lost WWI magazine copies revealed. Original copies of The Hydra magazine, edited by poet Wilfred Owen while he recovered from shell shock at Craiglockhart War Hospital, have been found after a near decade-long search. Craiglockhart Reception, 219 Colinton Rd, EH14 1DJ. Patrick McFall on 0131 455 6314 / 07917 559 503.
1015 GLASGOW: Lottery grants to help communities during Games. Announcement of grants totalling almost £1.1 million to be made available to allow community groups to mark the Commonwealth Games. Shona Robison and Maureen McGinn of Big Lottery Fund Scotland to make the announcement. Saturday Cafe, Cathcart Old Parish Church, 119 Carmunnock Road, G44 5UW. Landa Rolland on 0141 242 1458/07823 552 889.
1030 EDINBURGH: Labour Devolution Commission report launch. Scottish Labour Leader Johann Lamont will publish the findings of its Devolution Commission offering a ``comprehensive package of devolution'' if Scotland votes No to independence. Holyrood MacDonald Hotel, 81 Holyrood Road. Craig Davidson 07866 377396 press@scottishlabour.org.uk
1030 EDINBURGH: The McLellan Commission will announce remit for investigating Catholic Church in Scotland's handling of abuse. In 2013, it was announced that the McLellan Commission was to be established to undertake a critical review of all aspects of Safeguarding policy, procedure and practice within the Catholic Church in Scotland. At this media event, the Very Reverend Dr Andrew McLellan will discuss, for the first time, the details of the remit of the McLellan Commission. He will also share details of the 11 Commissioners that he has selected to assist him. The Quincentenary Building, Royal College of Surgeons (Entrance via Nicholson Street),, EH8 9DW. Christina Kelly 0141 204 7800 / 0787 588 1955.
1100 GLASGOW: Boxing Scotland finalists announced. Boxers who have qualified for the senior national competition hold press conference. Many of those taking part will be part of Team Scotland at the Commonwealth Games later this year. Olympia Building, Bridgeton Cross. David Walker 07811 693 866.
1100 GLASGOW: Jack Vettriano art auction preview. Three oil paintings by Jack Vettriano - Studio Afternoon, Letter of Consequence and Study for Riviera Retro - are estimated to be worth £50,000 and will be sold at auction later this month. Press preview ahead of sale on March 29. Great Western Auctions, 1291 Dumbarton Road. David Convery 07818 094 951.
1130 GLASGOW: Better Together leaders meet independence voters. Better Together chairman Alistair Darling, campaign director Blair McDougall and activists meet voters with six months to go the Scottish independence referendum. Block 20, Dundasvale Court, Glasgow, G4 0XE. ross@bettertogether.net
1245 PAISLEY: Commonwealth Games announcement. Announcement of a deal making students from the West of Scotland University responsible for looking after hair, make-up and pampering for top-class athletes at the Commonwealth Games. Shona Robison, ice hockey player Michael Bremner and a model will be present. West College Scotland, Paisley Campus, Renfrew Road,, PA3 4DR. Diarmid O'Hara on 0141 581 2318 or 07786 702344.
1600 EDINBURGH: Paralympic Curlers return to Scotland. Media conference featuring ParalympicsGB medal-winning curlers. Edinburgh Hilton, Edinburgh International Airport, EH28 8LL. Colin Hutton on 07772 920972.
1630 EDINBURGH: Ed Davey speech to Scottish Renewables Conference. Edinburgh International Conference Centre The Exchange 150 Morrison Street Edinburgh EH3 8EE Edinburgh International Conference Centre, The Exchange, 150 Morrison Street, EH3 8EE. DECC 03000685222, Scottish Renewables conference organisers 0141 353 4914.
1800 EDINBURGH: Former SSE chief discusses Scotland's energy challenges. Wood Group chairman Ian Marchant, former chief executive of SSE, will reflect on 25 years in the energy industry and critique the UK and Scottish energy situation. The Royal Society of Edinburgh, 22-26 George Street, EH2 2PQ. David Hume Institute 0131 339 9235.
1930 GREENOCK: Scottish Championshp: Morton v Dumbarton. Cappielow Park, Sinclair Street, Greenock, PA15 2TY.
1945 DUNDEE: Scottish Championshp: Dundee v Raith. Dens Park Stadium, Sandeman Street, Dundee, DD3 7JY.
1945 COATBRIDGE: Scottish League Two: Albion v Annan Athletic. Cliftonhill Stadium, Main Street, Coatbridge, ML5 3RB.
2100 KIRKCALDY: BBC 2 referendum debate. Debate to mark six months to the independence referendum. Confirmed speakers include Finance Secretary John Swinney Kirkcaldy. BBC Scotland press office 0141 422 6377.
Press Association Scotland parliamentary diary for Tuesday March 18.
Committee Business
0945. Health and Sport Committee. Room 5.
1. Subordinate legislation: The Committee will take evidence on the Community Care (Personal Care and Nursing Care) (Scotland) Amendment Regulations 2014 [draft] from-
Alex Neil, Cabinet Secretary for Health and Well-being, and Gillian Barclay, Head of Unit, Integration and Reshaping Care, Scottish Government.
2. Subordinate legislation: Alex Neil (Cabinet Secretary for Health and Well-being) to move-S4M-09334-That the Health and Sport Committee recommends that the Community Care (Personal Care and Nursing Care) (Scotland) Amendment Regulations 2014 [draft] be approved.
3. Subordinate legislation: The Committee will take evidence on the Patient Rights (Treatment Time Guarantee) (Scotland) Amendment Regulations 2014 from-
Alex Neil, Cabinet Secretary for Health and Well-being, Margaret Duncan, Head of Branch, Access Support, and Ailsa Garland, Principal Legal Officer, Scottish Government.
4. Subordinate legislation: Alex Neil (Cabinet Secretary for Health and Well-being) to move-S4M-09336-That the Health and Sport Committee recommends that the Patient Rights (Treatment Time Guarantee) (Scotland) Amendment Regulations 2014 [draft] be approved.
5. Subordinate legislation: The Committee will consider the following negative instruments-
National Health Service (Superannuation Scheme) (Scotland) Amendment Regulations 2014 (SSI 2014/43)
Personal Injuries (NHS Charges) (Amounts) (Scotland) Amendment Regulations 2014 (SSI 2014/57)
National Health Service (Optical Charges and Payments) (Scotland) Amendment Regulations 2014 (SSI 2014/61)
Carers (Waiving of Charges for Support) (Scotland) Regulations 2014 (SSI 2014/65)
Community Care (Joint Working etc.) (Scotland) Amendment Regulations 2014 (SSI 2014/66)
6. e-Health: The Committee will take evidence from-
Dr Margaret Whoriskey, Director, Joint Improvement Team, Eddie Turnbull, Head of eHealth, Peter Williamson, Lead for Health & Innovation, Quality Unit, and Alistair Hodgson, Partnership Improvement Officer, Joint Improvement Team, Scottish Government;
and then from-
Professor George Crooks, Medical Director, NHS 24;
Justene Ewing, Chief Executive Officer, Digital Health Institute;
Bill Templeman, Senior Executive, Enabling Technology, Scottish Enterprise;
Francesca Giannini, Senior EU Funding Executive, Scotland Europa;
Professor Mark Parsons, Edinburgh Parallel Computing Centre, and Professor Stuart Anderson, Deputy Head, School of Informatics, University of Edinburgh;
Professor Frances Mair, on behalf of Farr Institute of Health Informatics Research;
Brian O'Connor, Chair, European Connected Health Alliance.
1000 Education and Culture Committee. Room 4
1. Subordinate legislation: The Committee will take evidence on the Teachers' Superannuation (Scotland) Amendment Regulations 2014 (SSI 2014/44) from-
Michael Russell, Cabinet Secretary for Education and Lifelong Learning, and Rachel Sunderland, Team Leader, People and Leadership Unit, Scottish Government;
Chad Dawtry, Director of Policy, Strategy and Development, Scottish Public Pensions Agency.
2. Subordinate legislation: Neil Bibby to move-
S4M-09312-That the Education and Culture Committee recommends that the Teachers' Superannuation (Scotland) Amendment Regulations 2014 (SSI 2014/44) be annulled.
3. Historic Environment Scotland Bill: The Committee will take evidence on the Bill at Stage 1 from-
Ian Walford, and Diana Murray, Joint Chief Executives of Historic Scotland and the Royal Commission on the Ancient and Historical Monuments of Scotland (RCAHMS);
and then from-
Andrew Fleming, Head of Unit, David Fleetwood, Bill Team Manager, Noel Fojut, Bill Team Leader, and Jennie Marshall, Bill Manager, Historic Environment Policy Unit, Scottish Government;
Emma Thomson, Principal Legal Officer, Scottish Government.
1000 Justice Committee. Room 1
1. Decisions on taking business in private: The Committee will decide whether to take items 4 and 5 in private.
2. Courts Reform (Scotland) Bill: The Committee will take evidence on the Bill at Stage 1 from-
Fred Tyler, Member of the Civil Justice Committee, Law Society of Scotland;
James Wolffe QC, Dean, Faculty of Advocates;
Julia Clarke, Principal Advocate, Which?;
Lauren Wood, Policy Manager, Citizens Advice Scotland;
and then from-
Sheriff Gordon Liddle, Sheriff Lindsay Wood, and Sheriff Colin William Pettigrew, Sheriffs' Association.
3. Subordinate legislation: The Committee will further consider the following negative instrument-
Prisons and Young Offenders Institutions (Scotland) Amendment Rules 2014 (SSI 2014/26).
4. Work programme: The Committee will consider its work programme.
5. Standards, Procedures and Public Appointments Committee inquiry into the procedures for considering legislation in the Parliament: The Committee will further consider a draft response.
1000 Public Petitions Committee. Room 6
1. Consideration of new petitions: The Committee will consider-
PE1505 by Jackie Watt on awareness of Strep B in pregnancy and infants
and take evidence from-
Jackie Watt;
Jane Plumb, Chief Executive, Group B Strep Support
and will then consider-
PE1508 by Sean Clerkin on ATOS as a sponsor of the 2014 Commonwealth Games
and take evidence from-
Sean Clerkin;
Iain MacInnes, Secretary, Glasgow against ATOS.
2. Consideration of current petitions: The Committee will consider-
PE1488 by Pete Gregson, on behalf of Kids not Suits, on whistleblowing in local government;
PE1498 by Colin Emerson, on behalf of Edinburgh Secular Society, on religious representatives on local authority education committees;
PE1501 by Stuart Graham on public inquiries into self-inflicted and accidental deaths following suspicious death investigations;
PE1502 by Shonah Gibbon on saving Ecurie Ecosse cars.
1000 Welfare Reform Committee. Room 2
1. Decision on taking business in private: The Committee will decide whether to take item 4 in private.
2. Scottish Welfare Fund: The Committee will take evidence, in round-table format, from-
Graham Ritchie, Revenues & Benefits Service Manager, Angus Council;
Ian Black, Director of Finance & Shared Services, East Dunbartonshire Council;
Morag Johnston, Assistant Director of Financial Services, Glasgow City Council;
Stephen Devine, Scottish Welfare Fund Manager, North Lanarkshire Council;
Leslie Rendall, Revenues Manager, Orkney Islands Council;
Lynn Brady, Revenues & Benefits Sevice Manager, Perth & Kinross Council;
Gary Smith, Revenues and Benefits Manager, Scottish Borders Council;
Nicola Reid, Team Leader, Benefit Operations and Scottish Welfare Fund, West Lothian Council;
and then from-
Margaret Burgess, Minister for Housing and Welfare, Ann McVie, Team Leader, Tackling Poverty and Scottish Welfare Fund, Andrew Waugh, Senior Assistant Statistician, and Jamie MacDougall, Head of Housing Transitions and Support Division, Scottish Government.
3. Subordinate legislation: The Committee will take evidence on the Council Tax (Discounts) (Scotland) Amendment Order 2014 (SSI 2014/37) from-
Jenny Brough, Team Leader, Local Government Finance and Local Taxation Unit, Scottish Government.
4. Work programme: The Committee will consider a draft letter to the Secretary of State for Work and Pensions.
1130 Delegated Powers and Law Reform Committee. Room 3
1. Decision on taking business in private: The Committee will decide whether to take items 5, 6 and 7 in private.
2. Instruments subject to negative procedure: The Committee will consider the following-
Ethical Standards in Public Life etc. (Scotland) Act 2000 (Register of Interests) Amendment Regulations 2014 (SSI 2014/50);
Town and Country Planning (Hazardous Substances) (Scotland) Amendment Regulations 2014 (SSI 2014/51);
Brucellosis (Scotland) Amendment Order 2014 (SSI 2014/63);
Police Service of Scotland (Conduct) Regulations 2014 (SSI 2014/68);
Brucellosis (Scotland) Amendment (No. 2) Order 2014 (SSI 2014/72);
CRC Energy Efficiency Scheme (Amendment) Order 2014 (SI 2014/502).
3. Instruments not subject to any parliamentary procedure: The Committee will consider the following-
Tuberculosis (Scotland) Amendment Order 2014 (SSI 2014/71).
4. Defective and Dangerous Buildings (Recovery of Expenses) (Scotland) Bill: The Committee will consider the response of the Member in charge of the Bill to its Stage 1 report.
5. Disabled Persons' Parking Badges (Scotland) Bill: The Committee will consider further the delegated powers provisions in this Bill at Stage 1.
6. Revenue Scotland and Tax Powers Bill: The Committee will consider a draft report to the Finance Committee.
7. Inquiry into the procedures for considering legislation: The Committee will consider a paper from the Clerk in relation to the inquiry being conducted by the Standards, Procedures and Public Appointments Committee into the procedures for considering legislation.
Chamber business
1400 Time for Reflection
followed by Parliamentary Bureau Motions
followed by Topical Questions:
1. Kezia Dugdale: To ask the Scottish Government what its position is on the resignation of the head of the curriculum for excellence ahead of the first sitting of the new national exams.
2. Stuart McMillan: To ask the Scottish Government what its position is on reports that the Ministry of Defence is seeking to increase the level of liquid waste that it discharges into the Clyde at Faslane naval dockyard.
followed by Local Government and Regeneration Committee Debate: Draft Third National Planning Framework
followed by Scottish Parliamentary Corporate Body Debate: Reappointment of a Member of the Standards Commission for Scotland
followed by Business Motions
followed by Parliamentary Bureau Motions
1700 Decision Time
followed by Members' Business - S4M-08971 John Wilson: Down's Syndrome Awareness Week 2014
]]></text></news-item>