<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-BV91-F05M-K4DS"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>NC investigates whether Duke Energy pumped coal-ash water into Cape Fear River</title><source>Charlotte Business Journal</source><author>John Downey</author><text><![CDATA[N.C. environmental officials are investigating whether Duke Energy (NYSE:DUK) improperly pumped water from two coal ash ponds into the Cape Fear River or into groundwater.
Duke says the water was pumped from ponds at the closed Cape Fear Plant near Moncure simply to reduce the level of the pond to conduct maintenance. Such pumping is permitted at the site, the company says. Drew Elliot, a spokesman for the N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources, says officials have not yet determined whether the pumping was done properly. "While routine maintenance is allowed under the permit, discharge of untreated wastewater could be a violation," he says. "Our inspectors noticed this pumping during an on-site inspection March 11, and we are investigating the utility's actions."
Elliot says the inspection was one of a series announced by DENR on March 5 in response to the Feb. 2 coal ash spill at Duke's Dan River Steam Station. A broken stormwater pipe under one of the ash ponds at the Dan River site spewed up to 39,000 tons of coal ash into the river before it was sealed six days later. DENR is performing new inspections at 31 ash ponds at 14 current and retired Duke coal plants. Donna Lisenby of the Waterkeeper Alliance says her group discovered the pumping, which she contends is illegal, on March 10 and informed DENR of it a few days later. She says the alliance sent an aerial photographer and a lawyer with the organization to photograph the ash ponds at Cape Fear. The organization produced photographs that it says show Duke using portable pumps at two ponds on the site.
One was pumping water into a drainage canal that empties into the Cape Fear River. The other pumped water into woods near the river, she says. Duke spokeswoman Paige Sheehan says crews were using a temporary pumping system to lower water levels in two basins at the Cape Fear Plant to perform upcoming maintenance."
"The water was being pumped to the existing, permitted outfalls. Discharges from those permitted outfalls are monitored and continued to be throughout this process," she says. "This work began last fall, and the company notified DENR in August before it began."
"This maintenance activity is allowed under our permits and (DENR) is aware that this work is occurring," Duke's statement says. Elliot says DENR has authorized maintenance work at Cape Fear's ponds in the past. "What we are still investigating is the timing and the specifics" of any communication about recent work at the site, he says.
Lisenby says she asked for aerial photographs of the site because she was concerned about information contained in U.S. Environmental Protection Agency reports. One, issued in 2009, noted that one of the Cape Fear dams had shown some cracks in the past. She said she was also worried about an August 2013 letter from EPA that informed DENR officials that all five pond dams at the Cape Fear were rated in poor condition by independent experts hired by the EPA. She says the dams are overgrown with brush, and the photographs did not show any cracks.
Elliot says DENR's dam safety division inspected the dams on Feb. 20 and found them to be sound. The Los Angeles Times and The New York Times published stories about the situation in Moncure over the weekend. Elliot says DENR hopes to have more information from its investigation soon.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Charlotte Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>