<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-GN01-JCDS-Y2YP"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Controller and auditor-general to investigate IPTL deal</title><source>Country Report Select</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Event
A local newspaper, The Citizen, has alleged that US$122m held in an escrow account at the Bank of Tanzania (the central bank) was transferred to Pan Africa Power Solutions (PAP) in late 2013. The Public Accounts Committee (PAC) has given the controller and auditor-general (CAG) one month to conduct a special audit into the transaction.
Analysis
The escrow account was established in 2002 following a dispute between Tanesco, the state-owned power utility, and Independent Power Tanzania Ltd (IPTL). IPTL was, at the time, a joint venture between a Malaysian firm, Mechmar Corporation, and a local investor, VIP Engineering and Marketing. In 1995 Tanesco signed a power purchase agreement with IPTL to produce 100 mw of electricity each year for 20 years. Following a dispute over charges, Tanesco lodged funds in the escrow account. Tanesco and IPTL subsequently resolved the dispute, with the escrow funds being owed to IPTL. However, by the time the dispute was resolved IPTL had been put into liquidation and its ownership had changed. PAP bought it, but some have questioned the legality of this deal, since IPTL was under provisional liquidation.
Zitto Kabwe, the chairman of the PAC, said that the audit should examine whether Mechmar signed an agreement to sell its shares to PAP. Mr Kabwe also said that the investigation should look into reports that the attorney-general approved a value-added tax (VAT) exemption worth US$16m (Tanzanian law requires capacity charges paid by Tanesco to independent power producers to be subject to VAT at 18%), as well as the role of the energy ministry in the case.
Meanwhile, Standard Chartered Bank (Hong Kong) has threatened to sue unless the funds are returned to the escrow account. It claims to be a creditor of IPTL, having bought the debt from banks that had financed IPTL projects, and that the funds in the escrow account were its only security.
Mr Kabwe's request that the investigation look at the role of the energy ministry highlights Tanzania's weak public institutions and poor record on governance. Tanzania was ranked 111th out of 177 countries in Transparency International's 2013 Corruption Perceptions Index. Concerns over corruption have prompted action from successive administrations in Tanzania, including the establishment of five separate anti-corruption institutions, but results have been disappointing.
We will maintain our forecast that the government's lack of progress on tackling corruption will lead to periodic tensions with donors.
]]></text></news-item>