<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-CND1-DXKH-N07C"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Powell Industries increases on weak volume</title><source>News Bites US Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Powell Industries, Inc. (NASDAQ:POWL), NASDAQ's 6th largest electrical manufacturing company by market capitalisation, increased 5.0c (or 0.1%) to close at US$67.22. Compared with the NASDAQ-100 Index which rose 34.6 points (or 1.0%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -0.9%. Trading volume was 38% lighter than average. The stock rose for a second day on Monday bringing its two-day rise to 48.0c or 0.7%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Powell Industries, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/0010519717703141941
Bullish SignalsUptrend- The Moving Average Convergence Divergence (MACD) indicator of 12-day Exponential Moving Average (EMA) of 67.56 minus the 26-day EMA of 66.7 is positive 0.86 suggesting a bullish signal.- The 5.0% discount to 12-month high of US$70.75 against the 49.6% premium to 12-month low of US$44.94 suggests the stock continues to push for new highs. - In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week high once. - The present value of US$1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in Powell Industries is US$1,179, including a capital gain of US$175 and dividend reinvested of US$4.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Sales of 1.2 [1.9]. - Return on Capital Employed 14% [5.4%].Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 2.9 is comfortably below 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 13.4%. - Interest cover defined by EBIT/I is 252.1 times. This indicates it is less leveraged. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 1.5. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- Over the last 3 years average annual compound growth rate of earnings per share was 17.9%. This is considered moderate.- The Enterprise Value/EBITDA multiple of 11.5 compares favourably with sector average of 22.5. Enterprise Value is estimated at MCap US$806.3 million plus net debt of US$-104.1 million and EBITDA is estimated at US$61.1 million.- EBIT margin and EBITDA margin are positive and have seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 21,230 shares worth US$1.4 million traded. Beta: the Beta of Powell Industries stock is 0.5. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Parity:- Price to Book of 2.4 [2.2].
Bearish Signals:Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Dividend yield of 0.4% [0.8%].Other Bearish Signals:- Net profit margin has averaged 1.7% in the last 3 years. This suggests the company is less profitable with a low margin of safety.- Revenue growth has shown signs of deterioration in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]

COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 04: Powell Industries Announces Fiscal 2014 First Quarter Earnings Release and Conference Call Schedule[News Story] HOUSTON, Jan. 22, 2014 - Powell Industries, Inc. (NASDAQ:POWL), a leading supplier of custom engineered solutions for the management and control of electrical energy, today announced that it will release fiscal 2014 first quarter results on Tuesday, February 4, 2014 after the market closes.
February 04: Powell Industries Announces Fiscal 2014 First Quarter ResultsHOUSTON, Feb. 4, 2014 Powell Industries, Inc. (NASDAQ:POWL) ("Powell"), a leading supplier of custom engineered solutions for the distribution and control of electrical energy, today announced results for the fiscal 2014 first quarter ended December 31, 2013.Revenues for the first quarter of fiscal 2014 were $171.9 million compared to revenues of $146.9 million for the first quarter of fiscal 2013.
February 03: Powell Industries announces dividendPowell Industries today announced a quarterly dividend of 25.0c per share. The record date is February 19, 2014 and it is payable on March 19, 2014.
January 22: Powell Industries Announces Fiscal 2014 First Quarter Earnings Release and Conference Call Schedule[News Story] HOUSTON, Jan. 22, 2014 - Powell Industries, Inc. (NASDAQ:POWL), a leading supplier of custom engineered solutions for the management and control of electrical energy, today announced that it will release fiscal 2014 first quarter results on Tuesday, February 4, 2014 after the market closes.
January 16: Powell Industries Announces Sale of Transdyn[News Story] HOUSTON, Jan. 16, 2014 - Powell Industries, Inc. (NASDAQ:POWL) ("Powell"), a leading supplier of custom engineered solutions for the management and control of electrical energy, today announced the sale of its subsidiary, Transdyn, Inc., to Kapsch TrafficCom, a global provider of electronic toll collection (ETC) systems, headquartered in Vienna, Austria.
December 11: Powell Industries insider sellsPowell Industries (NASDAQ:POWL) insider Bonnie V. Hancock sold 1,000 shares worth approximately US$67,520 on December 09, 2013. The selling price was USD67.52.
December 03: Powell Industries Announces Fiscal 2013 Fourth Quarter And Year-End ResultsHOUSTON, Dec. 3, 2013 Powell Industries, Inc. (NASDAQ:POWL), a leading supplier of custom engineered solutions for the management and control of electrical energy and other critical processes, today announced results for the fiscal 2013 fourth quarter and year ended September 30, 2013.http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Usnasdaq/Stock/News/519024.htmlSource: NASDAQ Stock Exchange
ISIN: US7391281067
O:POWL
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>