<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS4-CCG1-JCMN-Y3C3"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Leading Chemical Company Releases White Paper About Site Remediation</title><source>Ground Report</source><author>Stacey Doyle</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 17, 2014 (Ground Report:http://www.groundreport.com/ Delivered by Newstex) http://groundreport.com/report/?Article=Leading%20Chemical%20Company%20Releases%20White%20Paper%20About%20Site%20RemediationArticle-ID=5065543 Leading Chemical Company Releases White Paper About Site RemediationArticle Views74 GroundReport | Author: Stacey Doyle[1] Filed Under: Business[2], Regulation[3] | Posted: 03/17/2014 at 7:55PM Comments[4] | Region: New Jersey | United Stateshttp://groundreport.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/file000641794815.jpg Dealing with toxins in the environment is a major concern for businesses around the country. If toxic elements are present, site remediation must be performed to get rid of them. The first step is to identify unwanted elements in the air, water and land then determine ways to eliminate them. Seidler Chemical, a leading chemical company located in New Jersey, just released a comprehensive white paper about site remediation.
Site remediation raises many questions, such as the various types and which method is the proper one. Business owners must assess the scope of the project and know about legal requirements such as those defined by the E.P.A. and O.S.H.A. From defining the process to outlining types of delivery logistics, the white paper addresses the common challenges companies face when they develop and implement plans for site remediation. The white paper addresses questions frequently raised by company owners conducted site remediation projects. Seidler Chemical is a supplier, distributor, blender and re-packager of quality chemical and ingredients for over a century. According to Seidler Chemical, the site remediation methods vary based on the type of contaminant, the amount and the location as well as the accessibility to the site. Some site remediation projects can be done on site. Other requires the contaminated material be removed and treated at a facility away from the site. One of the largest challenges companies face is meeting all the local and federal regulations pertaining to site cleanup. The detailed planning process must take into consideration decontamination of the site based on the current laws. Companies must select the right processes and partners to accomplish the job in an efficient and timely manner. Site remediation is the process that handles the removal of contaminants or pollution from the environment. These contaminants may be lurking in the soil, groundwater, surface water or sediment of a property. These toxins can be harmful to human and other living organisms including wildlife and plants. When a property is being assessed or sold, often the site is tested to determine if contaminants are present. The current property owner is typically responsible to eliminate these harmful elements. Site remediation is usually based on regulatory requirements. When these are non-existent, the remediation might be based on ecological and health risks associated with the contaminants found during testing. According to a press release[5], Richard Seidler, President of Seidler Chemical, stated, 'Anyone can sell chemicals for remediation processes, but it is far more efficient for companies with a contamination problem to work with experienced partners that understand the challenges.' The goal is to deliver remediation products to the proper location in the appropriate amounts and containers. Site remediation is becoming an increasingly pressing problem for various types of businesses. As people go green and express concern about the environment, it is crucial to keep it clean and be in compliance with local and federal regulations. Companies can download the white paper from Seidler Chemical to learn more about site remediation and how to handle these delicate projects. Filed Under:Business[6], Regulation[7] http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/This is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 License[8].Attribution (Very Relaxed) Loading...[9] [1]: http://groundreport.com/profile/23819 [2]: http://groundreport.com/category/Business/ [3]: http://groundreport.com/category/Business/regulation-Business/ [4]: http://groundreport.com/leading-chemical-company-releases-white-paper-about-site-remediation/#disqus_thread [5]: http://finance.yahoo.com/news/seidler-chemical-highlights-remediation-challenges-123000627.html [6]: http://groundreport.com/category/Business/ [7]: http://groundreport.com/category/Business/regulation-Business/ [8]: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/ [9]: http://mgid.com/

]]></text></news-item>