<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS6-YRR1-JDK3-90R1"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>TransGlobe-Caracal merger eyes 'more in Africa' despite political unrest</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[CALGARY - Caracal Energy Inc.'s move to buy Egypt-focused TransGlobe Energy Corp. creates one of the largest independent oil companies targeting Africa in a move executives say will help accelerate growth in a country rocked by political unrest.
Shares of Calgary-based TransGlobe jumped about 5% on the Toronto Stock Exchange early on Monday after the company agreed over the weekend to sell itself to Caracal for about $696-million in stock. The shares retreated and finished the day up 15¢ or 1.8% to $8.56.
The deal, billed as a merger by the companies, values TransGlobe's stock at $9.32 a share, a premium of 11% to its closing price on March 14. The merged entity would have a market capitalization of roughly US$1.8-billion, the companies said. Combined oil production would be 21,500 barrels a day, with a year-end target of up to 34,000-barrels.
Shares of Caracal, which trade on the London Stock Exchange, fell 6.1% to 385 pence. The company, which operates in Chad, would own 65.6% of the combined entity, according to a joint investor presentation.
"This is about creating a stronger entity," TransGlobe president and chief executive Ross Clarkson said Monday. "I don't think we're done yet. I think we're looking at more in Africa."
In an interview, he said the combined company would benefit from access to cheaper capital needed to fund expansions and growth in Egypt.
Related
Caracal Energy to acquire TransGlobe to add assets in Egypt( http://business.financialpost.com/2014/03/16/caracal-energy-to-acquire-transglobe-to-add-assets-in-egypt/?__lsa=d88f-a666 )
Griffiths International (now Caracal) has more modest going-public ambitions( http://business.financialpost.com/2013/06/19/griffiths-international-now-caracal-has-more-modest-going-public-ambitions/ )
The country is the largest non-OPEC producer of crude in Africa, with output averaging 720,000 barrels a day, according to the U.S. Energy Information Administration. But it has been roiled by violence following the ouster of President Mohamed Morsi last July.
The unrest has made life difficult for some companies. U.K. natural gas giant BG Group PLC in February reported a US$1.3-billion after-tax write down on assets in the country, which it blamed in part on a deteriorating business environment.
Mr. Clarkson said the tumult has not affected TransGlobe operations, which are isolated from clashes in major urban centres.
The company produces nearly all of its oil from fields in Egypt. It said March 5 output climbed 5% last year to about 18,000 oil-equivalent barrels a day. Profits for the year tumbled 33% to $58.5-million.
TransGlobe had been looking to diversify into other regions for at least two years before launching talks with Caracal, he said.
FirstEnergy Capital Corp. analysts led by G.F. Donnelly said the deal is "compelling," but noted it wouldn't result in "significant" cost savings.
Nor would it "preclude the need for additional financing for Caracal further down the line," the analysts said in a note.
The transaction also makes it "unlikely" that TransGlobe will follow through with a recently announced 5¢ quarterly payout, they said. FirstEnergy is acting as a strategic advisor to Caracal.
Credit Suisse analysts David Phung and Robert Loebach said the combined company is more likely to attract a takeover bid from a national oil company down the road.
"It attracts the attention of a different set of investors that won't even look at you until you're of that critical mass," Caracal chief executive Gary Guidry said in an interview. He would lead the merged company.
Caracal changed its name from Griffiths Energy International Inc. and completed an initial public offering in London last year. Under terms of the deal, Caracal would seek a listing on the TSX.
The company was formed in 2009 by Brad Griffiths, a Toronto investment banker who died in a boating accident in 2011.
Griffiths Energy last year agreed to pay a $10.35-million fine under Canada's Corruption of Foreign Public Officials Act related to a 2011 bribe in Chad.
The deal with TransGlobe requires shareholder and regulatory approvals. It is expected to close soon after shareholder meetings in June.
]]></text></news-item>