<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS6-RF01-JB4F-Y2CH"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>EBOS Group inches higher, resistance at 12-day EMA</title><source>News Bites Asian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EBOS Group Limited (NZSX:EBO), New Zealand's 7th largest intermediate & durables sector company by market capitalisation, increased 0.2% but fell short of the 12-day Exponential Moving Average [EMA] of NZD10.10. Compared with the NZX 50 Index which rose 40.4 points (or 0.8%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -0.6%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on EBOS Group, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/00105175166031437
Bullish SignalsUptrend- The Moving Average Convergence Divergence (MACD) indicator of 12-day Exponential Moving Average (EMA) of 10.1 minus the 26-day EMA of 9.99 is positive 0.11 suggesting a bullish signal.- The present value of NZD1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in EBOS Group is NZD1,167, including a capital gain of NZD128 and dividend reinvested of NZD39.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Return on Capital Employed 9.8% [6.1%].- Price to EBITDA of 0.2 [1.7].Other Bullish Signals:- EBITDA growth is positive and has seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 32,885 shares worth NZD332,139 (US$284,842) traded. The volume was 0.3 times the average trading of 117,569 shares. - EBOS Group is at a discount of 8.2% to its 12-month high of NZD11.0 on 31 May, 2013. It is also at a premium of 16.1% to the 12-month low of NZD8.70 on 12 Dec, 2013.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Parity:- Dividend yield of 3.2% [3.0%].Bearish Signals:- Total Liabilities/ EBITDA of 35.9 is more than or equal to 5, this compares unfavourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - Over the last 3 years average annual compound growth rate of earnings per share was 4%. This is lower than sector average of 42.1%.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 17: EBOS GROUP Ltd Ongoing Disclosure Notice by an EBOS GM[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Newzealand/Stock/News/8693.pdfSource: New Zealand Stock Exchange
March 06: EBOS Group announces dividendEBOS Group today announced an interim dividend of 20.50c per share. The ex dividend date is March 12, 2014 and it is payable on April 04, 2014.
February 19: EBOS Makes Strong Start to Financial Year[News Story]
9:12am, 19 Feb 2014 | HALFYREBOS MAKES STRONG START TO FINANCIAL YEARNews Release - half year result 19 February 2014Highlights - Excellent Result - on track with Net Profit after Tax (NPAT) of $49.4 million (unaudited), exceeding PFI - All businesses performed well - generating revenue in excess of $3 billion.
January 24: EBOS Group: SSH - Milford Asset Management Limited[News Story]
5:11pm, 24 Jan 2014 | SSHDisclosure of ceasing to have substantial holding Section 25, Securities Markets Act 1988To: The New Zealand Exchange Limited And: EBOS Group Limited Date this disclosure made: 24th January 2014 Date last disclosure made: 16th October 2013Substantial security holder(s) giving disclosure Name(s): Milford Asset Management Limited Contact details: Bryce Marsden, Chief Operating Officer, contact: 09 921 4707 E-mail: bmarsden@milfordasset.com Date on which substantial security holder(s) ceased to have substantial holding: 28th January 2014Summary of previous substantial holding to which disclosure relates Class of listed voting securities: Ordinary Shares Summary for: Milford Asset Management Limited For last disclosure,- (a) total number held in class: 7,420,492 (b) total in class: 146,614,274 (c) total percentage held in class: 5.06% (note, relevant interests held by the manager as follows): Milford Active Growth Wholesale Fund (2.67%), (Custodian - TEA Custodians), Milford Income Wholesale Fund (0.40%), (Custodian - TEA Custodians), NZ Equities Wholesale Fund (0.52%), (Custodian - TEA Custodians), Trust Investments Sustainable NZ Share Fund (0.09%), (Custodian - TEA Custodians), Waikato Community Trust (0.06%), (Custodian - TEA Custodians), New Zealand Superannuation Fund (0.98%), (Custodian - New Zealand Superannuation Fund Nominees Limited), Private Portfolio Clients (0.08%), (Custodian - Investment Custodial Services Limited), Mercer Trans-Tasman Shares Trust (0.26%), (Custodian - BNP Paribas Securities Limited).For current holding after ceasing to have substantial holding: (a) total number held in class: 7,102,818 (b) total in class: 147,610,382 (c) total percentage held in class: 4.81% (note, relevant interests held by the manager as follows): Milford Active Growth Wholesale Fund (2.38%), (Custodian - TEA Custodians), Milford Income Wholesale Fund (0.11%), (Custodian - TEA Custodians), NZ Equities Wholesale Fund (0.62%), (Custodian - TEA Custodians), Trust Investments Sustainable NZ Share Fund (0.10%), (Custodian - TEA Custodians), Waikato Community Trust (0.06%), (Custodian - TEA Custodians), New Zealand Superannuation Fund (1.14%), (Custodian - New Zealand Superannuation Fund Nominees Limited), Private Portfolio Clients (0.08%), (Custodian - Investment Custodial Services Limited), Mercer Trans-Tasman Shares Trust (0.32%), (Custodian - BNP Paribas Securities Limited).Details of transactions and events giving rise to person ceasing to have substantial holding Details of the transactions or other events requiring disclosure under the instructions to this form: Milford Asset Management Limited undertook the below on market transactions.
December 05: Ebos ASX Listing Confirmed[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Newzealand/Stock/News/7878.htmlSource: New Zealand Stock Exchange
December 04: Ebos ASX Listing Confirmed[News Story]
12:13pm, 4 Dec 2013 | GENERALEBOS ASX LISTING CONFIRMED News release December 2013EBOS is pleased to confirm that the Company's application to list on the ASX has been approved. ASX has reserved 6 December 2013 as the listing date and trading is expected to commence on or around that date under the code EBO.
November 08: EBOS - Progress made with ASX Listing Application[News Story]
9:12am, 8 Nov 2013 | GENERAL8 November 2013Listed Company Relations NZX Limited WELLINGTONPROGRESS MADE WITH ASX LISTING APPLICATIONEBOS Group Limited advise that it has made good progress with its ASX listing.EBOS has formally applied for listing and has lodged the attached compliance listing Information Memorandum with ASX.
ISIN: NZEBOE0001S6
NZ:EBO; NZE:EBO
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>