<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS6-RDH1-JCMN-Y075"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>China Accuses Nikon in Expose</title><source>The Legacy</source><author>David Green</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 17, 2014 (The Legacy:http://www.localizedusa.com/ Delivered by Newstex) http://stocktwits.com/widgets/sharehttp://www.lulegacy.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/legacy-16.jpgCCTV the state broadcaster in China accused Nikon, the Japanese maker of cameras, over this weekend of selling cameras that were defective and not addressing the complaints made by customers regarding one of the models it sells.
Nikon released a statement that said they regard the matter very seriously. They wanted to express their sincere apologies to customers. They thanked the government of China, the media and their customers for giving close supervision and attention to the company. The alleged problems with the cameras were highlighted in a program that is broadcast annually on March 15, which is World Consumers Rights Day. In the broadcast, it said that consumers had been complaining about the accumulating of dust in the D600 camera. Nikon said it was accepting any D600 cameras for maintenance and repair even if the warranty period had already expired. Nikon said it would be working harder to make sure the confidence of the customer in their products would return.Accusations of any wrongdoing by state media in China can cause a serious problem for foreign companies doing business in China. Volkswagen in 2013 recalled over 384,000 vehicles from China after a broadcast of consumer's rights. The state media also has targeted big firms including GlaxoSmithKline the British giant drug maker and Danone the French dairy firm, amongst a number of others over the past year for bribery, fixing pricing and products of poor quality. GSK experienced a fall in sales in China and both firms were put under investigation by the government. However, one notable exception or more has taken place. In 2013, consumer defended Starbucks after the huge coffee chain had been denounced in a report by CCTV for the sale of expensive coffee. Some of the viewers felt the report by CCTV had been a laughingstock, while others said buying coffee that was pricey was the choice of the individual and not to be dictated by state media that is too nosy. The report by CCTV against Nikon has been aired at a time when tensions remain high between Japan and China.

]]></text></news-item>