<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS6-YRR1-JDK3-90S9"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Ikea breastfeeding response a 'how to' in good public relations: experts</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[OTTAWA - Ikea's response to a customer's allegations she was called "disgusting" for breastfeeding her daughter in the checkout line should be taught as a perfect example of good public relations, say experts in corporate spin.
"They did absolutely the right thing in dealing with this. It is the classic how-to," said Barry McLoughlin, president of the PR firm McLoughlin Media.
"Ikea could have been on the hook for hundreds of millions of dollars (in lost business) if they had mishandled this story," he said.
"People would ask, 'Is this reflective of your corporate values? Is that what you stand for?' That can kill you."
Customer Brea Rehder of Kemptville made her allegation last Monday, contacting the media and posting a complaint on the Ikea Facebook page that she had been breastfeeding her "fussy" nine-month-old daughter in the lineup at Ikea's Ottawa store when, she said, a manager told her: "When you're done being disgusting, we can resume our discussion. In the meantime, take it to the bathroom because you're holding up the line."
Ikea apologized "profusely" to Rehder the next day and promised an investigation, interviewing all employees who were in the store at the time and reviewing its security camera footage from the entire day. Eventually they spotted Rehder entering the store at 6:45 p.m., more than three hours after she said the incident happened. The video shows no confrontation and in fact, Rehder didn't even have her daughter with her when she went through the checkout line.
On Monday, Ikea spokeswoman Madeleine Lowenborg-Frick said the company hasn't been able to contact Rehder since it finished its investigation.
"Our intention is that we would like to show her the video and after that we would expect an apology," Lowenborg-Frick said.
"We had to question all of our co-workers over this and that doesn't feel good for anyone," she said.
"What's important is that we want to put this whole incident behind us. The public is well aware of our open policy to breastfeeding."
On Sunday, the store welcomed a group of about 25 women who held a "flash feed nurse-in" in the living room section.
Josh Greenberg, associate director of Carleton University's School of Journalism, said Ikea handled the allegations well.
"It's a challenge," said Greenberg. "The issue they were dealing with was highly charged, emotionally and politically."
Pushing back against the complainant was risky but necessary because the allegation "hit at the heart of the Ikea brand," Greenberg said.
The company had to defend its name, without alienating a very vocal community.
"Corporations always face the risk when they respond to the activist community that they're going to be seen as the proverbial Goliath taking on David," he said.
One option open to the company would have been to accept that the incident happened, and promised action in the hope the issue would quickly blow over. Some PR experts would have advised doing just that, McLoughlin said.
"There are two errors you can make: Under-respond or over-respond. They didn't over-respond by hanging their employee out to dry and say, 'We'll automatically believe the customer.' But within the culture of the company, getting to the facts should be an important part of any company's corporate culture."
"You have to tell the truth," added Laura Peck, McLoughlin Media's co-founder and vice president. "You have to be authentic in the circumstances of what happened. That has to be the golden rule."
When the video review showed no confrontation, Ikea was sensitive in how it defended itself.
"I thought they were quite tactful in the way they dealt with it," McLoughlin said. "They allowed the consumer of the information to conclude for themselves as to the veracity of her story. They didn't directly call her a liar, but a reasonable person reading the subsequent stories would draw the conclusion: this appears to be a made-up story.
"They were very smart in not over reaching on that. They were measured in what they said. They welcomed the women who came in to breastfeed in their story ... they encouraged them. They chose it as an opportunity to turn the story around."
Rehder told the Citizen on Saturday that she was sticking to her story. She didn't respond to calls for comment on Monday.
McLoughlin and Peck, meanwhile, intend to present the breastfeeding brouhaha as a case study in good PR at a conference they are attending next month in Los Angeles.
"We always say, 'Have a bad day, otherwise you're going to have a bad year'," McLoughlin said. "Think Rob Ford. Think Justin Bieber. Think (New Jersey Governor) Chris Christie. You name them. It mushrooms, propelled by the power of social media.
"This case was very differently handled. They jumped on it right away."
bcrawford@ottawacitizen.com( mailto:bcrawford@ottawacitizen.com )( mailto:bcrawford@ottawacitizen.com )
Timeline:
Monday, March 10
3:30 p.m. Kemptville's Brea Rehder says she was in the checkout line at the Ottawa Ikea store when a manager said it was 'disgusting' that she was breastfeeding her nine-month-old daughter.
Rehder calls the media with her complaint that afternoon. Close to midnight Monday, she posts the complaint on the Ikea Facebook page.
Tuesday, March 11
Morning: Ikea staff see the Facebook post and immediately send Rehder a personal message asking for her contact information.
Rehder eventually responds and asks for a phone call after 8 p.m.
8 p.m. The manager of Ikea's Pinecrest Mall store calls and apologizes and asks Rehder for more details of what happened. The company promises to interview every employee working that day and to review its security camera video. The company promises to reiterate its code of conduct for all employees.
Thursday, March 14
Ikea says it has reviewed its video and found sign of Rehder in the store at the time she says the incident occurred. The company expands its investigation to other times of the day.
Meanwhile, a group of mothers organized a "mommy mob" at the store in support of breastfeeding.
Friday, March 15
Ikea says it has expanded its review of security video from March 10 and has identified Rehder in the lineup at 6:45 p.m., 'with a smile on her face' and without her daughter, who seems to be in a high chair in the store's bistro and cared for by a companion of Rehder's. The company says the video does not show Rehder breastfeeding in the store at all.
Sunday, March 16
About 25 nursing mothers stage a 'flash feed nurse-in' in Ikea's living room showroom. Rehder does not attend.
Corporate Missteps
Just Do It!
In the 1990s, Nike is accused of producing shoes in offshore sweatshops, relocating them when necessary to take advantage of the cheapest labour. Initially, Nike denied it was responsible for the shops, but eventually established a code of conduct for its suppliers and began advocating for better working conditions in developing countries
RBC outsourcing
In 2013, Canada's banking giant faced a consumer backlash for its use of temporary foreign workers at the expense of Canadian jobs. RBC spent several days trying to explain its actions, before agreeing to a new supplier code of conduct and said it would not to send work offshore just to save on salaries.
Target data breach
Hackers made off with customer records from the giant U.S. retailer in late 2013. At first, the company said the hackers stole the credit card information of 40 million customers. A few weeks later, Target admitted 70 million accounts had been compromised and the information stolen included names, phone numbers, emails and other personal data. The company admits the breach cost it $61 million in expenses in December 2013, but the greatest damage was to its reputation and "loss of confidence" of it consumers.
© Copyright (c) The Ottawa Citizen
]]></text></news-item>