<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS6-X8W1-JDJN-64V1"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Former minister speaks his mind no matter who he is addressing</title><source>Daily Nation (Kenya)</source><author>Nation Correspondent -1</author><text><![CDATA[Hate or love him, former minister Amos Muhinga Kimunya is a man who speaks his mind no matter who he is addressing.
When he lost his Kipipiri parliamentary seat in the March 2013 General Election, he wrote an open letter to his constituents chastising them for being a thankless lot.
"I am very disappointed that the people of Kipipiri did not appreciate my development record," he said in the letter read by the returning officer on the night he announced that Mr Kimunya had been defeated by Nairobi lawyer Samuel Kamunye Gichiga.
Sitting allowance
On February 17 this year, when he was summoned by the Parliamentary Public Investments Committee to respond to questions concerning the standard gauge railway project, he said he was not making any money while appearing before the team yet its members were earning a sitting allowance.
"I am sacrificing my time here ... the MPs here are not bothered to understand the issues ... if you want me to help you, let us engage in a mature way, let us behave with civility and honour in this matter," he said.
Shortly afterwards, he was declared a hostile witness and ejected from the meeting.
"I know my way out," he said when the committee chairman, Mr Adan Keynan, asked security orderlies to show Mr Kimunya the door.The former minister - who served in various portfolio including Lands, Finance and Transport - had earlier declined to honour the committee's summons, saying he was a private citizen and no longer in the public service. He only honoured the summons after he was threatened with arrest.
He was being true to character. As Finance minister, when he was under pressure to resign over the controversial sale of the Grand Regency Hotel - which Goldenberg architect Kamlesh Pattni had surrendered to the Central Bank as part of a settlement with the anti-corruption commission - Mr Kimunya organised a major rally in his Kipipiri backyard where he famously declared: "I would rather die than resign!"
A few weeks later, in July 2008, Parliament passed a motion of censure against him and he stepped aside.
Then President Mwai Kibaki later reappointed him to the Cabinet after he was cleared of any wrongdoing in the case.
Described as one of Mr Kibaki's blue-eyed boys, Mr Kimunya served as Lands minister in the National Alliance Rainbow Coalition government from 2002 to 2006, after which he was moved to the Finance docket.
]]></text></news-item>