<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS6-X8W1-JDJN-64XM"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Two Indian plants of Toyota shut over failure of labour talks</title><source>Big News Network.com</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[BANGALORE Toyota Kirloskar Motor (TKM), an Indian subsidiary of Japanese automobile giant Toyota, has declared lockout at two manufacturing plants in Bidadi industrial estate near Bangalore, amid allegations of threat following failure to reach an agreement with the labour union on a charter of demand, mostly related to wages.
Toyota Motor Corporation holds controlling stake of 89 percent in TKM and the remaining 11% equity stake is held by Indian multinational Kirloskar group.
The lockout from Sunday followed 10 months of negotiations on the charter of demands for the ongoing financial year ending March 31.
"As bipartite agreement was not reached, the Labor Department of the Government of Karnataka conducted 7 tripartite meetings in order to reach a settlement. The conciliation efforts of the Labor Department have not yet resulted in an agreement," the TKM said in a statement.
"In the meantime, under the instigation of the union, certain sections of the employees have resorted to deliberate stoppages of the production line, abuse and threatening of supervisors thereby continuously disrupting business for the past 25 days. All these unlawful activities have been detailed in the lock-out notice."
The company further stated that it was "left with no other option but to declare a lockout of the premises to ensure the safety of its workers and management personnel".
Set up in 1997, TKM recently celebrated the sale of its millionth care in India, a market where Toyota has been eager to expand with a range of affordable models. Toyota has market leadership in the MPV (multipurpose vehicle) segment with its Innova.
The workers have sought Karnataka government's intervention to resolve the impasse.
Additional Labour Commissioner J T Jinkalappa said, "The workers were demanding a Rs. 4,000 pm ($65.5) hike. For over two months, a two-hour strike every day has dented production."
The two plants, situated 30kms from Bangalore, produce 310,000 vehicles a year and employs 6,400 workers. While one plant produces the flagship Innova models and Fortuner SUV, the second plant has been rolling out Corolla Altis, Etios, Etios Liva and Camry
In the recent past, Bangalore's automotive industry has been plagued by union unrest.
A Tokyo based spokesman said Toyota hoped to restart the production quickly but could not give a timeline for any reopening of the plants, reported AFP..
]]></text></news-item>