<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS6-WDN1-F05M-K516"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>California joins Ocwen's $2.1 billion settlement</title><source>San Francisco Business Times</source><author>Mark Calvey</author><text><![CDATA[California's Department of Business Oversight said it's joining a $2.1 billion settlement with Ocwen Financial over mortgage servicing violations.
The move means that an estimated $268 million will be available to assist Ocwen's troubled borrowers in California.
"Californians should not lose their homes because of deceptive and poorly executed mortgage servicing practices," said Commissioner of Business Oversight Jan Lynn Owen.
The Ocwen settlement stems from federal litigation filed last December by 49 state attorneys general and the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau.
In California, violations of state law included impropertly denying loan modifications, failing to honor loan modifications granted by prior servicers and charging unathorized fees.
On Feb. 28, a federal judge finalized a settlement between Ocwen and the plaintiffs. That agreement requires all the proceeds to directly benefit consumers and that no payments go to the federal government or any states.
Last Friday, three nonprofits sued Gov. Jerry Brown demanding that California replace $369 million the state received under the national mortgage settlement to help troubled borrowers, which the state used to pay down state debt issued on behalf of low-income-housing agencies, the New York Times reported. A California official told the New York newspaper, "We're confident that our budget actions are legally sound."
With the Ocwen (NYSE: OCN) settlement, it appears the federal judge wanted to ensure the money goes directly to helping troubled borrows.
The problems borrowers are experiencing with mortgage services recently received front-page coverage in the New York Times.
In a victory for American homeowners, New York regulators recently blocked Wells Fargo's (NYSE: WFC) plans to sell mortgages to Ocwen Financial.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to San Francisco Business Times for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>