<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS6-S8X1-DYN6-W068"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>News from around Wisconsin at 5:58 p.m. CDT</title><source>Associated Press State &amp; Local</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Veterans call for end to asbestos lawsuit bill
MADISON, Wis. (AP) - Veterans opposed to a bill affecting asbestos-exposure lawsuits in Wisconsin urged Gov. Scott Walker on Monday to stop the measure, arguing that it would deny justice to asbestos victims.
The heavily lobbied proposal would require plaintiffs who have suffered from asbestos exposure to reveal how many businesses their attorneys plan to sue. They would also have to go after money from an asbestos trust before they could sue for more in court.
Proponents, including Wisconsin's chamber of commerce and Republican sponsors, argue the bill is needed to prevent filing multiple claims against both trust funds set up to pay victims of asbestos exposure as well as individual businesses.
Opponents who gathered Monday strongly disagreed.
"If you think that the bill is protecting the rights of victims, it is not. It is about protecting corporations," said a tearful Renee Simpson, state commander of the Wisconsin Veterans of Foreign Wars. She held up a picture of her dad, a U.S. Army veteran, who died in 2013 nine months after being diagnosed with mesothelioma, a form of cancer caused by asbestos exposure.
The Senate passed the bill last week on a narrow 17-16 vote. A similar version previously passed the Assembly and it's expected to pass again Thursday, the last day of the session, which would send it to Walker.
Walker said Monday in Milwaukee that he has heard from veterans on both sides of the issue, and he's waiting to see what happens in the Legislature.
___
MADISON, Wis. (AP) - Cancer survivors and others who back a bill that would make oral chemotherapy drugs more affordable in Wisconsin are not giving up hope that the measure can pass the Legislature, saying Monday that public pressure could force lawmakers to act now.
The Republican Senate leader has refused to bring the legislation up for a vote and the Assembly is set to adjourn for the year on Thursday without taking action.
"Our only option is that the transparency and public pressure will get these leaders to reconsider the longer term implications for them and their party," said Paul Westrick, a 16-year blood cancer survivor. Westrick is the board chair for the Wisconsin chapter of the Leukemia and Lymphoma Society.
The proposal, which has bipartisan support in the Legislature, would require insurance plans overseen by the state to provide coverage for expensive forms of chemotherapy drugs that patients take as pills rather than injections.
While a broad array of cancer support and health advocacy groups support the measure, it is opposed by health insurers that fear it will drive up costs. Lawmakers who are against it say they don't support insurance mandates.
Last week, Republican Senate Majority Leader Scott Fitzgerald said he wouldn't bring it up for a vote because most of the 18 Republican senators didn't support it, even though a majority of the Senate's 33 members did.
But the Milwaukee Journal Sentinel reported Sunday that at least 13 of 18 Republican senators and all 15 Democrats have taken a public stance in favor of the bill.
___
BARRON, Wis. (AP) - Investigators say a Rice Lake woman schemed with her boyfriend and another man to kill her ex-husband.
Prosecutors on Monday charged Trista Raven-Hrabak as well as her boyfriend, Ian Skjerly, and Robert McBain with being a party to first-degree intentional homicide in connection with the March 10 death of Daniel Raven.
According to a criminal complaint, Skjerly told investigators Raven-Hrabak wanted her ex-husband dead because they had gone through a tumultuous divorce. He said he and Raven-Hrabak hired McBain to drive him out to Raven's home. He got out of the car and shot Raven through a window as Raven sat watching TV. He and McBain then fled.
Online court records listed public defender John Hinde as the attorney for all three. He didn't immediately return an email message.
___
MADISON, Wis. (AP) - The chairman of the Assembly Education Committee is urging fellow Republicans not to support a proposal that calls for imposing sanctions on poor performing public and private voucher schools.
Rep. Steve Kestell said in an email sent to Republican lawmakers on Monday that if passed, "we will get clobbered across the state on this issue, and we will deserve it."
Kestell is responding to the latest version of a long-debated school accountability measure.
The Senate has passed a version that does not include sanctions. But Republican Assembly Rep. Jim Steineke has introduced an alternative approach that does call for sanctions, but wouldn't impose them immediately.
Steineke says he disagrees with Kestell and the Assembly will vote on his version Thursday.
It's unclear whether it will survive in the Senate.
]]></text></news-item>