<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS6-X8W1-JDJN-64V2"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Kimunya charged with abuse of office over land transfer</title><source>Daily Nation (Kenya)</source><author>PAUL OGEMBA -1</author><text><![CDATA[Former Cabinet Minister Amos Kimunya was on Monday charged with abuse of office over allegations of fraudulently transferring a 25-acre piece of land to a company in which he is a director.
Mr Kimunya was accused of using his office when he was the Lands Minister in 2005 to irregularly transfer the land located in Nyandarua County and valued at Sh60 million to Midlands Limited while knowing that the land was public property and not available for disposal.
The former minister was charged alongside the Director of Land Adjudication and Settlement Lilian Njenga and Midlands Limited chairman Junghae Wainaina with a total of seven counts which if proved could land them jail sentences of up to three years.
Mr Kimunya faced a second count of failing to disclose his interest in the company while allowing the transaction and breach of trust by disposing the piece of land in a manner that was prejudicial to the public.
"On June 30, 2005 at Ardhi House being the minister in charge of the Ministry of Lands and Housing and while knowing the government was not aware of your private interest in Midlands Limited failed to disclose that you were a director of the company and allowed it to be allocated the land," read the charge sheet.
Mr Kimunya and Ms Njenga were further accused of fraudulently issuing letter of offer and title deed to Midlands Limited while knowing that the land was being used as a farmers training centre and therefore not available for allocation.
The two were also alleged to have failed to protect public property contrary to the Anti-Corruption and Economic Crimes Act by allowing the land transfer while aware that it was preserved for public use.
Mr Wainana and the company faced a separate count of fraudulently acquiring the 25-acre land on February 6, 2006 when the land was public property.
The land was part of 75 acres belonging to the Ministry of Agriculture and reserved for a potato seed project. The anti-graft agency report indicated that the former Kipipiri MP was a director and shareholder in the company at the time of the transaction and did not seek the consent of the relevant ministry.
They all denied the charges with senior principal magistrate Doreen Mulyeko releasing each on a cash bail of Sh1 million or an alternative of a Sh2 million bond.
The fall from grace for Mr Kimunya and the embarrassment of being charged in court was too much for him, prompting his lawyer Mwaniki Gachoka to plead with the magistrate to allow him to be escorted to the cells without being handcuffed.
"Mr Kimunya is a public figure and is pleading with the court to spare him the embarrassment of being handcuffed to the cells. We are requesting you to allow him just be escorted as we process the cash bail," said Mr Gachoka.
He submitted that despite Mr Kimunya's status in life, he was entitled to fair treatment and not embarrassment and asked the court to be lenient to him considering that he had cooperated with the Ethics and Anti-Corruption Commission in their investigations and presented himself to court.
Ms Mulyeko allowed the request and directed the court orderlies to just escort the former minister without handcuffs as is the custom for those who are charged for the first time.
]]></text></news-item>