<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS6-X9C1-JB4F-Y3FT"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Davenport Lyons: Government announces increase to National Minimum Wage (NMW) rates</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Rebecca Lynch and Laura Livingstone
The Government has confirmed that NMW rates will rise with effect from 1 October 2014. This announcement comes following a recommendation to the Government from the Low Pay Commission (LPC). The LPC was established following the National Minimum Wages Act 1998 to advise the Government on NMW matters and consists of industry representatives across the board. As a result of the increase more than one million low-paid workers will see their salary rise by up to Pound355 per year.
The NMW hourly rates will increase as follows:
Adult rate - rising from Pound6.31 to Pound6.50 (an increase of 3%)
18-20 year old rate - rising from Pound5.03 to Pound5.13 (an increase of 2%)
16-17 year old rate - rising from Pound3.72 to 3.79 (an increase of 2%)
Apprentice rate - rising from Pound2.68 to Pound2.73 (an increase of 2%)
The Government has accepted every recommendation put forward by the LPC including larger increases to NMW rates in the future, provided that the UK economy continues to recover. The LPC advised the Government that a faster increase to the NMW would be sustainable provided the following three conditions were met:
Sustainable rise in real wages in the UK economy;
Rising or stable employment rates; and
An expectation of sustained economic growth.
The LPC said that it believes that these increases are manageable for employers and will also encourage full-time employment.
This announcement signifies the first increase to the real value of the minimum wage since 2008.
For further information please contact a member of our Employment team on 020 7468 2600.
click http://www.davenportlyons.com/news/news-stories/government_announces_increase_to_national_minimum_wage_%28nmw%29_rates/
COMPANY BACKGROUND
ACTIVITIES
Davenport Lyons provides legal advisory services. The firm's areas of practice include company and commercial, litigation, property, employment, intellectual property, and private client. Davenport Lyons is headquartered in London, United Kingdom.
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
17 March 2014: Davenport Lyons: Government announces increase to National Minimum Wage (NMW) rates
Rebecca Lynch and Laura Livingstone The Government has confirmed that NMW rates will rise with effect from 1 October 2014. This announcement comes following a recommendation to the Government from the Low Pay Commission (LPC). The LPC was established following the National Minimum Wages Act 1998 to advise the Government on NMW matters and consists of industry representatives across the board.
click http://www.davenportlyons.com/news/news-stories/government_announces_increase_to_national_minimum_wage_%28nmw%29_rates/
12 March 2014: Davenport Lyons: Home Office consultation on locally-set fees under the Licensing Act 2003
On 13 February 2014, the Home Office began a six week consultation on the introduction of locally-set fees under the Licensing Act 2003 in England and Wales. As part of the Government's proposals to "rebalance" the Licensing Act in favour of local communities, leading to the introduction of the late night levy, Early Morning Alcohol Restriction Orders (EMROs), and other strengthened licensing powers, views are now sought on proposals for licensing fees to be set locally, on a costs-recovery basis. Davenport Lyons encourages any interested party to respond to the Consultation and Impact Assessment, by the deadline of 10 April 2014. Current licensing fees were set nationally with the implementation of the Licensing Act 2003 in November 2005, and have not changed since.
click http://www.davenportlyons.com/news/news-stories/home_office_consultation_on_locally-set_fees_under_the_licensing_act_2003/
03 March 2014: Davenport Lyons: Increase to Statutory Employee Payments
The Government has announced an increase to the compensation awards that can be made by the Employment Tribunals and to the statutory rates used to calculate certain employee payments. From 6 April 2014 the following increases will come into force: A week's pay (used for calculating statutory redundancy payments and certain tribunal awards) will increase from Pound450 to Pound464. The maximum compensatory award for a successful claim of unfair dismissal will rise from Pound72,000 to Pound76,574 (although since 29 July 2013 these awards are the lower of 52 weeks' pay and the maximum compensatory award). The maximum basic award for unfair dismissal/statutory redundancy pay therefore increases from Pound13,500 to Pound13,920.
click http://www.davenportlyons.com/news/news-stories/increase_to_statutory_employee_payments/
]]></text></news-item>