<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-YK41-JCXB-23FV"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Resolution Limited Annual Financial Report -2-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Aligning strategic aims with social ones is part of our proud heritage. It runs through everything we do. It can be seen in the design of our insurance products which provide customers with comfort in the face of an uncertain future; in the partnerships we make in our long-term investments that support socially responsible infrastructure projects; most of all it can be seen in our people, who make a difference to both our customers and to the wider community.
Over the last few decades there has been a gradual shift in the corporate benefits market towards defined contribution schemes, shifting the investment risk from the corporate sector to individuals. This has been happening at the same time as state support has been reducing. We believe that we have an important role to play in plugging the savings gap: to help people as they accumulate wealth over their productive working years, as a partner as they make the transition to retirement, and by providing them with a secure income through their retirement. In addition to helping families through the accumulation and decumulation cycle we also provide protection products that provide a safety net for when our customers fall ill. There are other ways in which we have a role to play in society. The long-term investment horizon for infrastructure projects is an obvious match with the long-term liabilities of insurance companies. In November, we awarded a GBP500 million mandate to MetLife Investment Management for infrastructure loans. The Group has also agreed a GBP75 million amortising loan facility with Drax Group plc. This loan will part-finance a GBP700 million project to convert three of the six plants at Britain's biggest coal-fired power station into the country's largest green energy generator. This is only the beginning. It makes good business sense to contribute to the UK recovery by investing in socially responsible long-term infrastructure projects of this kind. As a company, we have a clear role to play in the community. This is strongly supported by our employees who engage in a variety of social and charitable initiatives. It is good for the community and good for our people, and is one of the reasons why Resolution is a great place to work. Every year we measure the level of staff engagement and we have seen a strong improvement this year. The Group's strong performance in 2013 was thanks to disciplined execution against a consistent strategy, a stable management, supportive customers and shareholders, and, above all, our great people. Our journey so far... Our actions over the last three years have transformed the Group. The completion of the capital optimisation programme, in which the business was re-organised into two UK life companies for closed and open business, drove efficiencies which have delivered a benefit of nearly GBP300 million to total free surplus over the last three years. Our approach to managing the in-force book is unique in that we believe that a separate, dedicated management team ensures accountability, rigorous financial discipline and helps drive the focus on cash generation. In 2011 we formed Heritage, our closed book division. Heritage continues to generate cash and drive value through outsourcing of the cost base, capital and risk management initiatives, and the development of in-house investment management capabilities. As part of our restructuring journey, we have rationalised our open business in the UK, reducing the number of open lines of business to three. The UK division today is focused on Retirement Income, Corporate Benefits and Protection, where we have scale and expertise to grow new business and where we have delivered a turnaround in value generation. When we started the restructuring and transformation journey, the Group was generating less than GBP100 million of sustainable free surplus. In 2013, this has risen to GBP331 million. The value of UK new business was negative three years ago whereas in 2013 our businesses generated GBP184 million of VNB. This turnaround in profitability has been delivered by applying rigorous financial discipline and we have now reduced our UK and Heritage operating cost base by one-third since 2010.
In our International division, we are focused on cash generation and upstreaming dividend payments to the Group. We target low risk, high value new business and have exited those markets that do not fit these criteria. Following the closure or disposal of a number of non-core International businesses over the last 18 months, our core Friends Provident International ("FPI") business offers savings, investment and protection products for expatriates and affluent local nationals in Asia and the Middle East. In 2014 we will transfer Overseas Life Assurance Business ("OLAB") to our Heritage division following the decision in early 2013 to stop writing new business in Germany. This will allow us to further leverage our expertise in managing closed books in our Heritage division. The Group is now more efficient, more customer-focused and more profitable. Our cash position has strengthened, capital adequacy is robust and we have delivered strongly against our 2013 new business and cost saving targets. In 2014 we intend to create a unified brand for the Group, subject to shareholder approval, renaming our parent company Friends Life Group Limited, reflecting the unified structure and governance of the business. This change demonstrates the transformation of the Group and is not only the right decision for shareholders, but will also provide significant benefits from a customer, distributor and colleague perspective. Operational highlights Heritage In June, the Group completed the single largest remaining element of the separation programme, the Application Hosting Migration ("AHM") which moved legacy AXA business applications and IT infrastructure from AXA-Tech to Friends Life. In the fourth quarter of 2013, the Group executed the first major migration from two legacy administration systems to the BaNCS IT platform operated by one of the Group's strategic partners, Diligenta. This represented a major operational milestone. In addition, as part of a multi-year programme to implement a uniform capital management framework for the with-profits business, circa GBP2 billion of annuity business has been re-allocated from the with-profits fund to the non-profit fund of Friends Life Limited ("FLL") and is expected to deliver circa GBP10 million per annum of sustainable free surplus from 2014. This is a significant achievement and a further tranche of with-profits fund reallocations with a value of circa GBP700 million is being considered in 2014. This is underpinned by progress in our fixed income in-house asset management operation, Friends Life Investments ("FLI"), which was launched in July 2012. FLI now manages a total of GBP17.1 billion of Group assets, including GBP7.0 billion of assets recaptured in 2013. Setting up FLI, and restructuring approximately 20% of the Heritage assets, has saved the Group GBP5 million per annum, utilising its in-house investment capability and asset liability management skills to support the management of fixed income assets within the annuity, shareholder and with-profits portfolios. In 2014 we anticipate FLI will take responsibility for a further GBP2.3 billion of Resolution's sterling fixed income assets. The Group has also announced a new, scalable partnership with Schroders to manage GBP12.2 billion of equity and multi-asset funds from the fourth quarter of 2014. UK division We have also made great progress in the UK division. Our Retirement Income strategy is built on the strong foundations of the Heritage and Corporate Benefits pension books encompassing around 50,000 vesting pensioners per year and we made great progress in 2013 with an increase in the number of existing customers choosing to buy an annuity from Friends Life. The proportion of vestings increased to 34% from 25% in 2011. This proportion increases significantly where customers have engaged with our Lifestyle annuity proposition which is designed to deliver better value to customers by taking account of their lifestyle factors to offer a more tailored solution. Having seen this encouraging response from existing customers, we extended our Lifestyle annuity to the open market at the end of 2013 and we anticipate further growth in this area. We have also strengthened the support we offer our customers nearing retirement by launching a "shopping around" service in partnership with Key Retirement Solutions. In Corporate Benefits we have continued to build scale with assets now at GBP20.1 billion, an increase of GBP2.3 billion over the year, whilst maintaining strict financial discipline on attracting new schemes. Over the course of the year 180,000 employees within 274 schemes of 203 employers have "staged" with the Group. We now have sufficient scale to be cash generative on an underlying free surplus basis and remain focused on writing profitable business. We have positioned ourselves strongly to take advantage of the opportunities presented by auto-enrolment, with our My Money platform providing a strong proposition in the market. In addition, we launched My Future, a new range of default funds that has had an encouraging early take up.
]]></text></news-item>