<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-RTW1-JBVM-Y2CX"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Documents shine light on Fifa's shadow of corruption; Paper trail leads to Trinidad office owned by one of world football's most powerful figures</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Holly Watt; Claire Newell; Claire Duffin; Ben Bryant</author><text><![CDATA[ON Edward Street in Port of Spain, one brightly painted building stands out among the cheap Chinese takeaways and run-down residences.
A large green sign on the roof of the turquoise office block in Trinidad's capital announces the property as the headquarters of the country's Independent Liberal Party. It is a short walk from the Ministry of Finance and is well known to locals as a meeting point for officials.
Now, the building is also at the centre of an international corruption investigation which is casting a shadow over the decision four years ago to award the 2022 World Cup to Qatar.
Documents seen by The Daily Telegraph show that the office appears as the contact address on an invoice to a Qatari company asking for $1.2million to be paid to the then vice-president of Fifa.
The demand for payment was made just days after the controversial decision to host the 2022 World Cup in the Arab kingdom.
Addressed to Khalid Electrical and Mechanical Est (Kemco) in Doha, Qatar - a company owned by Mohamed Bin Hammam, the country's Fifa representative at the time - it requests payment for work carried out between 2005 and 2010.
The invoice is from Jamad Limited, a firm set up by Jack Warner.
For 28 years Mr Warner was one of the most powerful men in world football, serving as president of Concacaf - the Fifa governing body representing football associations in north and Central America and the Caribbean. Mr Warner also held positions in Trinidad's government, including minister of works and transport, as well as national security. The Edward Street property which is home to Jamad Limited is also owned by Mr Warner and was the headquarters of Concacaf.
Evidence seen by this newspaper shows that Mr Bin Hammam's company transferred more than $2 million to Mr Warner, his family and employees in 2011. One letter, dated July 2011, states that a payment of $1.2 million to "Mr Jack Warner" is to "offset professional services provided over the period 2005-2010".
The leaked documents will raise questions about the objectivity of the Fifa executive committee members.
Only seven months before the letters referring to "professional services" were sent, England's bid to stage the World Cup ended in humiliating defeat when Russia was awarded the 2018 tournament.
On the same day, Qatar won the 2022 tournament when it secured 14 out of 22 votes, beating other bidding nations including the US and Australia.
The decision was a contentious one: temperatures in Qatar frequently reach 50C (122F) in summer and the Gulf state's rivals had not seen it as a serious contender at the start of the bidding process.
Harold Mayne-Nicholls, who led a Fifa inspection team, said in October last year that it would be "impossible" to play the tournament safely in the searing Qatari summer.
The Fifa voting process is regarded as opaque: executive committee members cast their votes in secret, so it is unclear which country received each member's vote. Even before the executive members of Fifa met to vote, concerns had been raised about the probity of the process.
Documents seen by this newspaper show that in July 2011, Kemco made two payments to Mr Warner. One, on July 4, for $1.2 million appears to have been rejected by a Cayman Islands bank.
A letter on Kemco headed paper, dated 4th July 2011, states that the payment is being made "to offset legal and other expenses associated with regard to an ongoing matter". It is unclear what the legal expenses could relate to, but in May 2011, both Mr Warner and Mr Bin Hammam were facing bribery allegations in the Caribbean.
A second payment was made on July 14 2011. This time, a letter from Kemco states that the payment is being made to "offset Professional Services provided over the period 2005 to 2010". This transfer appears to have been successful. Other documents show that Mr Warner's sons, Daryan and Daryll, also received money from Kemco.
Daryan, the eldest, appears as a director and shareholder on many of his father's companies including Jamad Limited.
He is also listed as having a correspondence address at his parents' home in Trinidad.
According to a letter that appears to have been written by Kemco, Daryan Warner was paid $316,000 via one of his companies and Daryll received $432,000. One of Mr Warner's employees also received $412,000.
These short letters, which appear to have been pasted in an email, also suggest that the payments to Mr Warner's children and his staff member were linked to "legal expenses". Even if Kemco was covering the cost of Mr Warner's expenses regarding the Trinidad bribery allegations, it is unclear why his relatives would be involved.
The two brothers live in a penthouse apartment overlooking Miami's Biscayne Bay in a condominium with its own tennis courts, marina and concierge service. In the last year, one of Daryan's companies, DW Property Holdings, has bought six apartments in Miami, costing almost a million dollars.
Both Mr Bin Hammam and Mr Warner have faced corruption allegations.
In 2011, Mr Bin Hammam, the Fifa executive committee member for Qatar, was forced to resign after becoming embroiled in a bribery scandal in the Caribbean during the contest for the Fifa presidency.
Mr Bin Hammam was banned for life by Fifa after being found to have offered $40,000 (£25,000) in bribes to Caribbean football officials. He later managed to overturn this ban at the Court of Arbitration for Sport.
Mr Warner was also caught up in the scandal and resigned from all football activities, including his role as Fifa vicepresident.
Mr Bin Hammam is independently wealthy and runs several companies. According to the Kemco website, he has been the sole proprietor of the firm since 1985. The company's website states that the firm has a "good reputation and has become a leading Electro-Mechanical Contracting Co in Doha". From the pictures, it appears that the organisation's work centres around construction. Evidence submitted to Parliament's culture, media and sport select committee in May 2011 alleged that Qatar had offered payments of up to $1.5million to members of the Fifa executive committee to secure votes. The submission, which was made public, named three former Fifa officials and quoted a former employee of the Qatar bid who claimed that cash offers were made for votes.
However, two months later, the whistleblower who made the claims retracted them and said that she fabricated them out of bitterness at the way she was treated by the bid.
Michael Garcia, a US attorney, is now conducting an investigation for the Fifa ethics committee into bidding for the 2018 and 2022 tournaments. His report is expected later this year.
The FBI is also involved in an investigation into Mr Warner's activities and began examining payments made to him in 2011. Many of the payments are understood to relate to money Mr Warner, and other officials, received from the Caribbean Football Union, but as investigators have ploughed through accounts and paperwork, their inquiry has widened to included other funds.
In December 2011, The Daily Telegraph disclosed that FBI officers had come to Britain to interview members of England's failed 2018 World Cup bid as part of the their investigation into alleged corruption.
Mr Warner and his family declined to comment.
In a statement, the Qatari Supreme Committee for Delivery & Legacy said: "The 2022 Bid Committee strictly adhered to Fifa's bidding regulations in compliance with their code of ethics.
"The Supreme Committee for Delivery & Legacy and the individuals involved in the 2022 Bid Committee are unaware of any allegations surrounding business dealings between private individuals."
Mr Bin Hammam did not respond to calls requesting comment.
A Fifa inspection team said it would be "impossible" to play the tournament safely in the searing Qatarsummer
]]></text></news-item>