<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-43X1-JB3N-T29V"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Lockout for Management Safety: Toyota</title><source>Economic Times (E-Paper Edition)</source><author>OUR BUREAU BANGALORE</author><text><![CDATA[Toyota in India alleged on Monday that a "grave threat to the safety of its management" forced it to order a shutdown of its car plants near Bangalore,the latest episode in a war of words between the unit of the Japanese company and its 4,500 workers over the course of wage negotiations.The impasse with the workers led to a loss of output of over 2,000 cars in the last 25 days,as many of the "workers stopped production lines",a senior executive of the company said."We were left with no other option but to declare a lockout on Sunday after some workers disrupted production lines and started abusing our line supervisors," said Shekar Vishwanathan,vice-chairman,Toyota Kirloskar Motor,or TKM."Tempers were fraying,and,as a measure of abundant precaution,we declared lockout," he said,declining to reveal what grave threat was posed by the workers.The management of TKM,which will meet the state labour minister on Tuesday,ruled out raising its wage increase offer of.3,050 a month to its permanent workers."Our offer is final," said Vishwanathan.Workers Petition Former CM He said he remains hopeful politicians "would not play to the gallery and talk the language of discipline".Disputes between workers and managements have many times spun out of control,resulting in violence and even death.In recent years,executives at Graziano Trasmissioni India,Pricol and Regency Ceramics have been beaten to death by enraged workers.In 2012,the general manager of human resources at Maruti Suzuki was burnt to death at the company's Manesar plant."For harmonious relations,the most important issue is that the company should share its profits with all stakeholders justifiably," said Pranabesh Ray,dean of academics at Jamshedpur-based Xavier Labour Relations Institute.Earlier on Monday,workers from the Toyota Kirloskar Motor Employees Union sought political backing by petitioning former chief minister HD Kumaraswamy of the Janata Dal (Secular) and urging him to resolve the impasse.Bidadi,where the plants are located,falls under the Ramanagaram constituency from where Kumaraswamy,the son of former prime minister HD Deve Gowda,is likely to contest the general election."We met Kumaraswamy in the morning and he has promised to resolve this problem," said Shanmukha Gowda,vice-president of the union that represents 4,500 employees.The company has a total of 4,900 workers at its plants,of whom 400 are contract workers and not part of the union."We are being paid far less than what Hyundai or other auto makers pay their workers," Gowda told ET.Vishwanathan,however,refuted the workers' allegations and said the company's salary was on a par with the other auto makers and said any further increase would disrupt the "entire ecosystem in the state"."After 50 meetings (over the last 10 months) with the union,we were constrained for a conciliatory meeting with the labour commissioner and even after seven meetings,we realised we were not making much headway," said Vishwanathan.The company also dismissed any talk that the shutdown was declared to clear inventory pile-up as it said it works on "very less" stock build-up and any continuation of this production shutdown would start affecting the demand at the retail level.Toyota Kirloskar's two facilities are geared to produce 3.1-lakh vehicles a year,including the Fortuner sports utility vehicle,the hatchback Liva and the Innova.However,because of the slowdown,the company produced only 1.1-lakh cars last year.

]]></text></news-item>