<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-V461-JBV0-D0R2"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>U.S., Cuba join Caribbean nations in oil cleanup pact; Deal will allow spill response craft to enter other nations' territory</title><source>The Tampa Tribune (Florida)</source><author>PAUL GUZZO; Tribune staff</author><text><![CDATA[- An international agreement has been approved that makes it easier for Cuban military boats and aircraft to enter United States territory.
Floridians, however, will hope that day never comes: The procedure will be activated only in the event of a catastrophic oil spill.
The Wider Caribbean Region Multilateral Technical Operating Procedures for Offshore Oil Pollution Response was officially released to the public last week after undergoing nearly three years of review among five nations with Caribbean shorelines - Mexico, the Bahamas, Jamaica, the United States and Cuba.
The 60-page document spells out how the five nations should work together if an oil spoil
threatens to extend beyond one nation's territorial waters.
The agreement streamlines the process for public or private sea vessels or aircraft to enter another member nation's territory to help in the tracking, detainment and cleanup. This includes Cuba, a nation with whom the U.S. has tense relations.
The agreement is available at www.cep.unep.org/racrempeitc, by clicking Regional OPRC Plans on the menu to the left.
Cuba or any other of the countries could not just enter U.S. territory without permission, said U.S. Coast Guard Captain John Slaughter, one of the government's leaders in this initiative. They would have to be asked for help or they would have to seek permission to help us. But through this document, if their help is needed, it can be done in a timely manner.
In an oil spill, time is of the essence.
In the past the five nations would have worked together, but it may have taken days after an oil spill for any of the five governments - not just Cuba and the U.S. - to work through diplomatic channels, Slaughter said.
Previously, I may have had to spent three days figuring out who is in charge of certain operations in the Bahamas, said Slaughter.
Visa approval for U.S. personnel to enter other nations' waters could have taken valuable time, he added.
Slaughter confirmed in late January that the operating procedure had been approved by the appropriate parties, but he would not elaborate before the release of a final document.
According to the operating procedure, its intent is to build a responder-to-responder network so that in the event of a large oil spill, participating countries can work effectively together to minimize the environmental impacts of the spill.
To do so, it provides the necessary contacts within each nation for all aspects of oil spill response, such as initial alerts, immigration and visa approval, vessel movement and government approval for specific oil containment and cleaning measures.
Email addresses and phone numbers of the contacts are omitted in the public version of the document.
Other highlights include calling for the nations to work together to establish a safety zone around the spill, rerouting nonresponse vessel traffic away from the affected waters, and establishing a waste-management protocol.
It also recommends that representatives from the five nations meet every six months to consider a host of topics, including discussion of amendments and maintaining professional relationships, participating in oil-spill training exercises, sharing information that can provide better safety practices, seeking private-sector assistance, and fostering relationships with other countries that could be affected by an oil spill in Caribbean waters.
Which country takes the lead on a specific job is not determined in advance.
Those decisions are based on the facts of the incident itself, Slaughter said.
The final decision on how the spill should be cleaned and detained - chemical dispersement, burning or mechanical removal - lies with the host nation. The other four nations will support the decision with appropriate measures.
If the oil spreads into another nation's borders, its leaders can handle the oil in their waters as they see fit.
Slaughter stressed that it is nonbinding, meaning a government does not have to follow, agree to help or allow assistance. However, he said he has no reason to believe any of the governments would ignore it.
The oil spill procedure joins a short of list of joint operations involving both Cuba and the U.S., including efforts to stop drug smuggling and illegal immigration.
This hopefully will allow people to see there is no reason why the U.S. and Cuba should not have similar agreements in other areas when in our best interests, said Al Fox, who has worked from Tampa to encourage normalization of relations with Cuba through his Alliance For Responsible Cuba Policy Foundation. Environment has been put above politics, as it should be. Why should our waters be contaminated with oil because some people disapprove of Cuba's government?
The process to bring the two nations together on the issue began when Fox introduced U.S. oil and environmental leaders from the private and government sectors to members of the Cuban government in 2010.
Following the Deepwater Horizon oil spill in April 2010, these representatives then lobbied the federal government to work with Cuba. A protocol to protect all nations with Caribbean shortlines in the event of an oil spill could not have been established unless the U.S. and Cuba worked together.
The majority of U.S. technology needed to track, contain and clean an oil spill belongs to the private sector.
The trade and travel embargo imposed by the U.S. on Cuba in the 1960s prevented U.S. companies from providing any technology to the Cuban government.
Equipment and resources to deal with a Cuban spill would have been shipped from as far away as the North Sea, England, North Africa and Asia and possibly arrived after the oil reached U.S. waters.
An oil spill in Cuba could reach the U.S. in less than a week due to rapid moving currents.
Cuba's initial oil exploration came up dry but it has announced its intentions to try again in 2015. It is believed anywhere from 5 billion to 20 billion barrels of oil lie beneath Cuban waters.
In 2012, the Office of Foreign Assets Control issued the U.S. Coast Guard a license to enter Cuban waters with its government approval in the event an oil spill there might reach the U.S.
The Coast Guard was also licensed to use necessary equipment owned by private companies.
The multinational meetings were called, in part, to begin clearing clear away red tape that could have slowed the process.
To circumvent the embargo, workshops between the U.S. and Cuba had to involve other countries and operate under the auspices of the United Nations and the Cartagena Convention - an agreement requiring nations in the Caribbean region to take necessary measures to protect and preserve rare and fragile ecosystems.
The workshops included representatives from the U.S. Coast Guard, Department of State and Department of the Interior, and the equivalent from the other nations.
The fact is that we have five nations in a region who clearly understand the implications their activities have on the region as a whole, said Slaughter, with the Coast Guard. That they have come together to streamline the process should it be necessary is noteworthy.
pguzzo@tampatrib.com
(813) 259-7606
PACT, Page 9
- An international agreement has been approved that makes it easier for Cuban military boats and aircraft to enter United States territory.
Floridians, however, will hope that day never comes: The procedure will be activated only in the event of a catastrophic oil spill.
The Wider Caribbean Region Multilateral Technical Operating Procedures for Offshore Oil Pollution Response was officially released to the public last week after undergoing nearly three years of review among five nations with Caribbean shorelines - Mexico, the Bahamas, Jamaica, the United States and Cuba.
The 60-page document spells out how the five nations should work together if an oil spoil
threatens to extend beyond one nation's territorial waters.
The agreement streamlines the process for public or private sea vessels or aircraft to enter another member nation's territory to help in the tracking, detainment and cleanup. This includes Cuba, a nation with whom the U.S. has tense relations.
The agreement is available at www.cep.unep.org/racrempeitc, by clicking Regional OPRC Plans on the menu to the left.
Cuba or any other of the countries could not just enter U.S. territory without permission, said U.S. Coast Guard Captain John Slaughter, one of the government's leaders in this initiative. They would have to be asked for help or they would have to seek permission to help us. But through this document, if their help is needed, it can be done in a timely manner.
In an oil spill, time is of the essence.
In the past the five nations would have worked together, but it may have taken days after an oil spill for any of the five governments - not just Cuba and the U.S. - to work through diplomatic channels, Slaughter said.
Previously, I may have had to spent three days figuring out who is in charge of certain operations in the Bahamas, said Slaughter.
Visa approval for U.S. personnel to enter other nations' waters could have taken valuable time, he added.
Slaughter confirmed in late January that the operating procedure had been approved by the appropriate parties, but he would not elaborate before the release of a final document.
According to the operating procedure, its intent is to build a responder-to-responder network so that in the event of a large oil spill, participating countries can work effectively together to minimize the environmental impacts of the spill.
To do so, it provides the necessary contacts within each nation for all aspects of oil spill response, such as initial alerts, immigration and visa approval, vessel movement and government approval for specific oil containment and cleaning measures.
Email addresses and phone numbers of the contacts are omitted in the public version of the document.
Other highlights include calling for the nations to work together to establish a safety zone around the spill, rerouting nonresponse vessel traffic away from the affected waters, and establishing a waste-management protocol.
It also recommends that representatives from the five nations meet every six months to consider a host of topics, including discussion of amendments and maintaining professional relationships, participating in oil-spill training exercises, sharing information that can provide better safety practices, seeking private-sector assistance, and fostering relationships with other countries that could be affected by an oil spill in Caribbean waters.
Which country takes the lead on a specific job is not determined in advance.
Those decisions are based on the facts of the incident itself, Slaughter said.
The final decision on how the spill should be cleaned and detained - chemical dispersement, burning or mechanical removal - lies with the host nation. The other four nations will support the decision with appropriate measures.
If the oil spreads into another nation's borders, its leaders can handle the oil in their waters as they see fit.
Slaughter stressed that it is nonbinding, meaning a government does not have to follow, agree to help or allow assistance. However, he said he has no reason to believe any of the governments would ignore it.
The oil spill procedure joins a short of list of joint operations involving both Cuba and the U.S., including efforts to stop drug smuggling and illegal immigration.
This hopefully will allow people to see there is no reason why the U.S. and Cuba should not have similar agreements in other areas when in our best interests, said Al Fox, who has worked from Tampa to encourage normalization of relations with Cuba through his Alliance For Responsible Cuba Policy Foundation. Environment has been put above politics, as it should be. Why should our waters be contaminated with oil because some people disapprove of Cuba's government?
The process to bring the two nations together on the issue began when Fox introduced U.S. oil and environmental leaders from the private and government sectors to members of the Cuban government in 2010.
Following the Deepwater Horizon oil spill in April 2010, these representatives then lobbied the federal government to work with Cuba. A protocol to protect all nations with Caribbean shortlines in the event of an oil spill could not have been established unless the U.S. and Cuba worked together.
The majority of U.S. technology needed to track, contain and clean an oil spill belongs to the private sector.
The trade and travel embargo imposed by the U.S. on Cuba in the 1960s prevented U.S. companies from providing any technology to the Cuban government.
Equipment and resources to deal with a Cuban spill would have been shipped from as far away as the North Sea, England, North Africa and Asia and possibly arrived after the oil reached U.S. waters.
An oil spill in Cuba could reach the U.S. in less than a week due to rapid moving currents.
Cuba's initial oil exploration came up dry but it has announced its intentions to try again in 2015. It is believed anywhere from 5 billion to 20 billion barrels of oil lie beneath Cuban waters.
In 2012, the Office of Foreign Assets Control issued the U.S. Coast Guard a license to enter Cuban waters with its government approval in the event an oil spill there might reach the U.S.
The Coast Guard was also licensed to use necessary equipment owned by private companies.
The multinational meetings were called, in part, to begin clearing clear away red tape that could have slowed the process.
To circumvent the embargo, workshops between the U.S. and Cuba had to involve other countries and operate under the auspices of the United Nations and the Cartagena Convention - an agreement requiring nations in the Caribbean region to take necessary measures to protect and preserve rare and fragile ecosystems.
The workshops included representatives from the U.S. Coast Guard, Department of State and Department of the Interior, and the equivalent from the other nations.
The fact is that we have five nations in a region who clearly understand the implications their activities have on the region as a whole, said Slaughter, with the Coast Guard. That they have come together to streamline the process should it be necessary is noteworthy.
pguzzo@tampatrib.com
(813) 259-7606
Pact
From Page 1
]]></text></news-item>