<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-CSW1-JDKC-R1XK"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Toyota locks out 2 plants over wage row</title><source>Hindustan Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[umbai, March 18 -- Auto major Toyota Kirloskar Motor (TKM) has shut down production at its two auto-assembly plants in Bidadi, Bangalore, locking out 6,400 workers amid testy wage negotiations and allegations of threats against management.
Failing to reach a consensus on wage disputes, TKM declared the lockout on Monday.
TKM, in which Japanese auto company Toyota owns 89% and Pune-based Kirloskar group 11%, manufactures Innova, Etios, Altis and Camry at these plants. It churns out nearly 700 units in two shifts every day from these plants as it operates at around 55% of its annualised production capacity of 3,10,000 units.
The Karnataka state labour department is likely to convene a meeting of the management and the labour union on Tuesday to resolve the crisis, said sources.
The management and the union have been negotiating on wages for the past 10 months, but could not reach on a settlement. The company said seven tripartite meetings initiated by the labour department could not yield any result.
"Under the instigation of the union, a section of employees resorted to stoppage of production line, abuse and threatening of supervisors for the past 25 days," said a statement issued by the company.
"The company is left with no other option but to declare a lockout of the premises to ensure the safety of its workers and management personnel."
However, Toyota Kirloskar Motor Employees Union (TKMEU) dismissed charges of threats and stoppage of work. "We did not disrupt production. We were working peacefully and were ready to settle for a slightly better deal than what the management had proposed. But the management hasn't been ready for a compromise," GS Sathish, secretary, TKMEU told the Hindustan Times.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from HT Mumbai. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>