<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-C8N1-JC92-P2VK"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>EU confirms intention to sign political provisions of EU-Ukraine Association Agreement</title><source>Russia &amp; CIS General Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The European Union said that it confirmed its readiness to sign the political provisions of the EU-Ukraine Association Agreement on March 21 and assured its intention to continue providing comprehensive assistance.
"The Council of Europe welcomes the European Commission's proposal for temporarily removing customs duties on Ukrainian exports to the EU and looks forward to its swift adoption. It furthermore looks forward to the signing of political provisions of the Association Agreement on 21 March in Brussels and confirms its commitment to proceed with the signature and conclusion of the remaining parts of the Agreement which together with the political provisions constitute a single instrument," the Council of Europe said in a statement approved at a Council of Europe meeting on foreign affairs in Brussels on Monday.
"These steps will confirm Ukraine's free and sovereign decision to pursue Ukraine's political association and economic integration with the European Union," the document said.
According to the statement, the EU is ready to stand by Ukraine and to provide it with "strong financial support to its economic and financial stabilization, as presented by the European Commission in its assistance package to Ukraine which we are committed to implement rapidly. The Council encourages the European Investment Bank to continue its operations in Ukraine."
The assistance of the International Monetary Fund (IMF) will have an essential importance for the EU support to restore "macroeconomic stability through sound fiscal, monetary and exchange rate policies," the document said. "At the same time, we reiterate our call to the Ukrainian government to urgently launch an ambitious set of structural reforms, including notably the fight against corruption and enhancing transparency of fiscal expenditure," the Council of Europe said.
The EU included the assessment of the latest events in Ukraine in the statement. "The European Union commends the measured response shown so far by Ukraine. The EU again encourages the Ukrainian authorities to implement an inclusive process, to pursue their efforts to ensure free and fair elections and to advance constitutional reform," the document said.
All human rights violations and acts of violence should be investigated and "measures need to be stepped up to combat impunity," the Council of Europe said.
"In this context, the EU looks forward to the early establishment of the Council of Europe International Advisory Panel. The EU also calls on the Ukrainian authorities to continue to reach out to all Ukrainian regions and population groups and to ensure the full protection of the rights of persons belonging to national minorities, drawing on the expertise of the Council of Europe and the OSCE [Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe]," the document said.
The EU is committed to enhancing contacts between people by liberalizing visa regulations and to help Ukraine in future in ensuring its power supply via further diversification and energy efficiency increase, the Council of Europe said.
ez mk
(Our editorial staff can be reached at eng.editors@interfax.ru)
]]></text></news-item>