<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-W2C1-JCT2-M2R2"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Energy institute launches study of private wells</title><source>The Times &amp; Transcript (New Brunswick)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[FREDERICTON - The New Brunswick Energy Institute plans on spending more than $500,000 on research looking at well water quality in areas where industry wants to develop shale gas.
The institute, under fire for being funded by a pro-development Tory provincial government, said yesterday the research would go toward establishing a proper baseline before any more wells are drilled.
It will take place in four areas of southern New Brunswick where exploration or development of the controversial industry is underway: Sussex-Petitcodiac, St. Antoine-Shediac, Harcourt-Richibucto and Boisetown-Upper Blackville.
Kerry MacQuarrie, a civil engineering professor at the University of New Brunswick, was selected as the project lead for the two-year study on about 500 private wells. He said it was important to find out the water quality before any further development takes place because sometimes people don't realize there's naturally occurring pollution with no human cause.
"This will be totally voluntary and it will be up to the homeowners that we contact whether they want to be involved," MacQuarrie said in an interview. "I would assume that people would be interested to know what the quality is for their drinking water, but there won't be any obligation for anyone to take part."
MacQuarrie is well aware of the controversy surrounding the industry and the institute itself. Between opinion polls and the province's two major political parties, New Brunswick society appears to be split on the merits of shale gas development, which relies on hydraulic fracturing. The long-term consequences of fracking are still not completely understood, with critics, such as the Liberal opposition, saying a moratorium should be in place until more studies can be carried out, whereas the Tory government and other shale gas supporters argue that development, with certain safeguards, should go ahead to create more jobs and wealth.
"This is a research study, and it's not really linked to any particular interest group or industry group," MacQuarrie said. "I have no links with the shale gas industry or anything like that. I've been doing ground water research in the province for over 20 years and I publish that in peer-reviewed scientific formats. People probably will take issue that it's related to the shale gas issue, but I think it's something worthwhile to do because it seems a lot of the concerns that have been raised are related to ground water quality and the potential impacts on that."
Stephanie Merrill, freshwater program director with the Conservation Council of New Brunswick, works for the environmental organization that has campaigned heavily to stop shale gas development. She welcomed the idea of further study Monday, though she qualified her support by saying she would have to first see a detailed work plan and explanation of the research methods.
She agreed that baseline studies were important, all the more reason, she said, for a moratorium on exploration and development.
"There should be a decision made right now to halt the further work of companies' with exploration leases and licences while this kind of work is undertaken. That would go a long way in providing an increased level of trust with the public, so they can put aside the question of whether the work is supporting the industry versus having information for providing good solid information for whether the industry should go ahead."
MacQuarrie acknowledged the researchers would have a bit of trouble with their baseline data if the industry continues to develop over the next two years.
"I have no idea to predict what the industry might do in the next couple of years, but I'm guessing it would only be a handful of wells, perhaps, that might be drilled. But again, I have no inside information or any clue about that."
The team, which will consist of MacQuarrie and as many as eight research students, will send mail-outs or hold meetings to pick about 500 private well owners in the select areas. To ensure their results are not contaminated, they want to establish their baseline using wells that are at least one to two kilometres away from any existing oil or gas wells or seismic tests that have already been conducted. Natural gas is currently extracted at the McCully fields near Sussex and dozens and dozens of different hydrocarbon wells have been drilled since the 19th century, most of them now abandoned.
The researchers want to look at newer private water wells built within the last 20 years when provincial regulations became stricter and data was collected on the wells. They also want sites that are nicely spaced apart with different geology so that they get a better variety and breadth of data. The study will run from April 2014 to April 2016, when a final technical report will be submitted.
The project will be the first large-scale examination of natural methane gas occurrences in private water wells in the province, with the objective to collect and report baseline domestic water quality data. The focus is on groundwater quality parameters that are most relevant to the potential impact on shallow groundwater from unconventional shale gas production.
Early results from the project will be provided in an interim progress report on the institute's website. It is intended on being the beginning of a series of water studies that the institute will be funding relating to energy development.
MacQuarrie described the work as labour intensive and requiring a good deal of expertise to properly obtain and analyze samples. He said they'd probably work in concert with researchers at Université de Moncton, who have already begun work on collecting data on wells that might be contaminated by radioactive materials caused by deposits such as uranium.
The institute plans on spending $532,000 overall on the study.
]]></text></news-item>