<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-C6X1-DY91-H55V"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Japan to decide purpose of nuclear materials safegarded by IAEA</title><source>Xinhua General News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Chief of the international atomic agency said here Monday that nuclear materials obtained by Japan is safeguarded by the agency, but the future use of the materials is up to Japan, which needs to explain it to other countries.
Yukiya Amano, head of the International Atomic Energy Agency ( IAEA), told a press conference at Japan's Foreign Correspondent's Club that "one of the core function of the IAEA is, of course, to prevent spread of nuclear weapons," and the IAEA do this "by clarifying that countries are using nuclear material only for peaceful purposes."
Recent reports exposed that Japan possessed a number of weapon- grade plutonium, including the 331-kg plutonium from the United States that could produce 40 to 50 warheads and triggered concerns in the neighboring countries.
"All the materials, including these some 330 kg plutonium, is placed under the IAEA safeguard. Japan is a non-nuclear weapon country and has a comprehensive safeguard agreement," said Amano, adding "we can assure all of the material in Japan stays in peaceful purposes."
However, he said he can not tell on behalf of the Japanese government for what purposes Japan will use on the nuclear materials, adding it depends on the Japanese government to show the transparency of its nuclear materials.
"It is up to the Japanese government how to use it, for peaceful purposes I said, and explain it to other countries," said Amano when he was asked about the final purposes of Japan's holding of weapon-level nuclear materials.
As to the concerned Fukushima Daiichi nuclear power plant crippled by devastating quake-triggered tsunami three years ago, Amano said the impact of the accident, the situation at the site remains complex and challenging issue, such as leakage of highly toxic and radioactive water and decontamination must be addressed.
The IAEA head said that to store the contaminated water and releasing it into sea is not a long-term solution for Japan and to avoid potential difficulties, the IAEA recommend Japan to consider the option of releasing the water after treating it properly and ensuring that satisfies Japan's standard after consulting with stakeholders.
]]></text></news-item>