<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-HT71-JB4F-Y2CW"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Lifescript: Insurers must accept funds from U.S. program that helps HIV-AIDS patients</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
NEW YORK (Reuters) - The lead agency for President Barack Obama's healthcare reform announced on Friday that it would require, rather than merely encourage, insurers that sell Obamacare policies to accept funds from a federal program that helps people with HIV-AIDS pay health insurance premiums.
Earlier this year, BlueCross BlueShield of Louisiana, the state's largest carrier, said it would begin rejecting checks from the Ryan White HIV/AIDS Program for Obamacare policies it sells. For decades the Ryan White program had helped low-income people with HIV and AIDS pay for both AIDS drugs and insurance premiums, but Louisiana Blue said such "third party payments" invited fraud.
The chief federal agency administering Obamacare, the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services, said on Friday it was requiring insurers to accept the funds, after saying last month that it "encouraged" carriers to accept the Ryan White payments and did not see any potential for fraud.
"Given the importance of access to care for people with HIV/AIDS, today CMS amended its rules to require health insurance issuers to accept Ryan White HIV/AIDS Program funds on behalf of eligible enrollees in individual Marketplace plans," said a CMS spokeswoman. "We will work directly with issuers to ensure they are in compliance with this policy."
Although the controversy over the Ryan White payments attracted the most attention, the CMS rule also requires insurers to accept premium payments on behalf of Obamacare customers from Indian tribes, tribal organizations, urban Indian organizations and state and federal government programs.
After CMS had encouraged acceptance of the funds, Louisiana Blue had said it would not take the Ryan White payments after this month, threatening hundreds of customers with loss of coverage due to inability to pay. Lambda Legal, a civil rights group that works on behalf of gay men and lesbians, filed a lawsuit against the company, asking a court to require Louisiana Blue to accept the payments.
On Monday the company said it would do so, but only through November 15, 2014, when the next open enrollment period for Obamacare begins. The current enrollment period, for coverage in 2014, ends on March 31.
Friday's CMS announcement means that Louisiana Blue and all other carriers will have to accept the Ryan White payments for premiums.
If an insurer refuses to comply with the interim final rule, CMS said, the organization that submitted the payment or the affected individual should contact CMS. If a company continues to refuse, CMS might levy a penalty, it said, without specifying its size.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/17/insurers_must_accept_funds_from_us_program_that_helps_hiv-aids_patients.aspx
COMPANY BACKGROUND
ACTIVITIES
LifeScript is a online publishing company based in Mission Viejo, CA.
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
17 March 2014: Lifescript: Police sent to enforce car ban as Paris battles smog
PARIS (Reuters) - France deployed hundreds of police in Paris on Monday to enforce the most drastic curbs on car use in 20 years as authorities sought to reduce health-endangering pollution days before town hall elections. Amid concerns of worsening air quality after a week when unseasonably balmy weather boosted pollution, public transport was free of charge while drivers with even-numbered license plates were told to leave their cars at home of face fines. Paris is more prone to smog than other European capitals because of France's diesel subsidies and its high number of private car drivers. Some 700 police manned key entry points to the city from before dawn to apply the scheme, in which drivers may only use their cars on alternate days depending on whether their license plates finished with an odd or even number. "This is a public health problem.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/17/police_sent_to_enforce_car_ban_as_paris_battles_smog.aspx
17 March 2014: Lifescript: Fitness options multiply for the time-pressed and money-stressed
NEW YORK (Reuters) - Time, money and the Internet are changing where Americans work out, fitness experts say. Time-pressed fitness fans seeking short, focused workouts are flocking to boutique studios specializing in everything from indoor cycling to boot camp, and the no-frills gyms that burgeoned during the financial recession are still thriving in the recovery. Cedric X.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/17/fitness_options_multiply_for_the_time-pressed_and_money-stressed.aspx
14 March 2014: Lifescript: Breastfeeding past two years linked to infant tooth decay
NEW YORK (Reuters Health) - Breastfeeding is credited with a long list of benefits, but one downside of extended and intensive breastfeeding may be a higher risk of cavities in baby's first teeth, according to a new study. The more frequently a mother breastfed her child beyond the age of 24 months during the day, the greater the child's risk of severe early tooth decay, researchers found. "The No.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/14/breastfeeding_past_two_years_linked_to_infant_tooth_decay.aspx
14 March 2014: Lifescript: CORRECTED-Nobel laureate calls handling of stem cell research data 'sloppy'
TOKYO (Reuters) - The Nobel Prize-winning head of a Japanese institute whose scientists' work on stem cells was hailed as a game-changer in the field of medical biology called the lead researcher's handling of the data "extremely sloppy" and "irresponsible." Two papers published in the journal Nature in January detailed a simple way to reprogram mature animal cells back into an embryonic-like state that allows them to generate many types of tissue, offering hope for a simpler way to replace damaged cells or grow new organs in humans. But other scientists have been unable to replicate the research's results since then and there have been indications of problems with its data and images. "The problem here is one immature researcher collected a huge amount of research data, and her handling of data was extremely sloppy and irresponsible," president of Japanese research institute RIKEN Ryoji Noyori told a news conference. "I would like to offer my apology for the Nature articles, having brought into question the credibility of the science community," said Noyori, bowing deeply. Noyori, who won a Nobel prize for chemistry in 2001, was referring to Haruko Obokata, 30, a lead author of the papers who became an instant celebrity in Japan after they were published. A written statement from Obokata and two other RIKEN researchers made available at the news conference said they are discussing the possible withdrawal of the papers with other co-authors. Another scientist on the team, Teruhiko Wakayama of the University of Yamanashi, has already called for the papers to be withdrawn. "It is no longer clear what's right," Wakayama told public broadcaster NHK on Monday. The news conference was called to release the interim findings of investigation on the controversy by a panel of experts from within and outside RIKEN. The panel found, among other things, that some images in one of the papers published in Nature were taken from Obokata's doctoral dissertation, which was on different experiments, and that another image was artificially modified. "Regular researchers would never do something like this," said Masatoshi Takeichi, director of the RIKEN Center for Developmental Biology, a RIKEN unit where Obokata works as a research leader. Takeichi cautioned, however, that despite the flaws in the papers, the science community would have to wait and see if other research groups were able to replicate the results before it could assess the validity of the findings. According to the Nature papers and media briefings, Obokata and other researchers took skin and blood cells, let them multiply, then subjected them to stress "almost to the point of death" by exposing them to various events including trauma, low oxygen levels and acidic environments. One of these "stressful" situations was simply to bathe the cells in a weak acid solution for around 30 minutes. Within days, the scientists - Japanese researchers joined by others from Brigham and Women's Hospital and Harvard Medical School in the United States - said they had found the cells had not only survived but had also recovered by naturally reverting into a state similar to that of an embryonic stem cell. These stem cells - dubbed Stimulus-Triggered Acquisition of Pluripotency, or STAP, cells by the researchers - were then able to differentiate and mature into different types of cells and tissues, depending on the environments they were put in, they said. Source: Company Website
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/14/corrected-nobel_laureate_calls_handling_of_stem_cell_research_data_sloppy.aspx
14 March 2014: Lifescript: Italy prosecutors open probe against Roche, Novartis executives
ROME (Reuters) - Prosecutors in Rome have opened an investigation into four executives at Swiss drugmakers Roche and Novartis on suspicion of fraud and manipulation of the pharmaceutical market, judicial sources said on Friday. Earlier this month, Italy's antitrust authorities said Roche and Novartis colluded to try to stop cancer drug Avastin from being used to treat a serious eye disease and fined the companies 182.5 million euros ($251 million). A Novartis spokesman had no immediate comment, while a Roche spokesman referred to the company statement issued after the antitrust ruling that called the charges "unfounded" and said it would appeal. Source: Company Website
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/14/italy_prosecutors_open_probe_against_roche_novartis_executives.aspx
]]></text></news-item>