<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-C8N1-JC92-P2NB"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>UN aide's position on Ukraine biased, bewildering - ministry (Part 2)</title><source>Russia &amp; CIS Military Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[UN aide's position on Ukraine biased, bewildering - ministry (Part 2)
The Russian Foreign Ministry is bewildered by the statements made by the United Nations Assistant Secretary-General for Human Rights, Ivan Simonovic, over the situation in Ukraine, and has accused him of using double standards.
"We are stunned and cannot comprehend the biased and unobjective assessment by Simonovic of the human rights situation in this country," the ministry said on its website on Monday.
"Simonovic's ranting about some activists and journalists allegedly searched by individuals in uniforms and his silence over the fact that extremists put bounties on journalists' heads, and that the self-proclaimed government follows orders to shut down foreign television channels, massively closes entry for foreign correspondents, and even makes attempts to inhibit re-transmission of satellite signals can be called nothing other than double standards," the ministry said.
"The high-ranking UN official chose not to notice the killings, mass executions, torture, kidnapping, attacks on journalists and human rights activists, imprisonment due to political motives, flagrant incidents with a clearly racist, i.e. anti-Russian and anti-Semitic, subtext being carried out on the orders or with a tacit consent of the individuals who seized power in Kyiv," the statement said.
"Instead, he is talking with feigned alarm about his concerns over the human rights situation in Crimea," the Russian Foreign Ministry said.
"We would like to remind Simonovic about the guarantees that the authorities of the Republic do and will provide in future for the Crimean Tatar minority, as well as the fact that presently Crimea is almost the only place where order and the rule of law remain," the statement said.
The bearer of the Crimean sovereignty is its people whose will was unequivocally expressed at the March 16 referendum, Moscow says.
"We believe that by his statement Simonovic grossly violated the principles that must be followed by all employees of the UN Secretariat in accordance with its Charter: neutrality, independence and good faith. Besides, he discredited the mission the UN Human Rights Commissioner is going to send to this country and questioned its independence and impartiality," the Foreign Ministry said.
kk cm
(Our editorial staff can be reached at eng.editors@interfax.ru)
]]></text></news-item>