<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-C7X1-JCM0-602G"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Morwell cleanup begins</title><source>ABC Transcripts (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ELEANOR HALL: The Victorian Premier has announced a $2 million cleanup package for the community of Morwell in Victoria's Latrobe Valley. Many residents have been forced out of the town; others have been living under a shroud of soot.
The fire causing the problem has been burning in the Hazelwood open-cut mine since early last month, as Rachael Brown reports
RACHAEL BROWN: For the past month, a veil of fine soot and ash has been blanketing Morwell residents' houses, cars and gardens. The toxic smog has been filtering over the town from a coal fire in the Hazelwood open-cut mine, which kicked off during Victoria's heat wave last month.
Those forced to relocate - the elderly, children, pregnant women and those with respiratory issues - were given the all clear to return yesterday, and now the clean up begins. The State Government is pitching in with professional house cleaning, including high-pressure water hoses and vacuum cleaners
The Premier, Denis Napthine.
DENIS NAPTHINE: High quality vacuum cleaners that are able to deal with particles and the ash associated with this incident. Also, all Morwell residents will be able to access, through the city council, free vouchers for laundry and car washing.
RACHAEL BROWN: Those eligible are residents who relocated, and those with special needs, But Morwell resident Gavin Lamb says it'll barely scratch the surface.
GAVIN LAMB: One hundred and fifty vacuums for a population of 13,000 people plus outlying areas - there's no way in the world. I worked it out before: it will probably take me at least three months to get hold of a vacuum cleaner.
RACHAEL BROWN: And some of these people, you were saying, might not be able to use the high-pressure hoses because of other problems that the Latrobe Valley houses face?
GAVIN LAMB: The houses that have got asbestos on them, they're asbestos-clad, they're old commission houses, but if you use high-pressure hoses and paint chips and the like come flying off, we've been told that EPA set a substantial fine for it.
RACHAEL BROWN: It's proving to be a costly exercise. Today's funding comes on top of the $3 million worth of respite and relocation payments and $2 million given to small businesses.
Mr Napthine again.
DENIS NAPTHINE: The cost of the firefighting effort alone will run into many millions of dollars. To think it was started by a deliberately lit fire is an absolute kick in the guts for all of us that somebody can start that sort of fire, put the community at risk, put lives at risk, put our electricity assets at risk.
RACHAEL BROWN: The deputy incident controller at Hazelwood, Henry Barton, says the coal fire is under control, but it's far from out.
HENRY BARTON: There is still quite a few hot spots that we've got to deal with. Unfortunately, over the past few days there's been some fairly strong winds that have hampered our firefighting efforts, and then also about 20 millimetres of rain in the mine made it quite difficult working on the surface. So we took a bit of a step back while those heavy rains were coming.
RACHAEL BROWN: And do you know whether it's still giving off carbon monoxide and those dangerous particulates or has that calmed down?
HENRY BARTON: No, that's calmed down significantly; we're going to do some more work over the next couple of days just to clarify that.
RACHAEL BROWN: And how much longer could you be there before you hand it back to the mine?
HENRY BARTON: (laughs) That's a really good question, but I would be suggesting another two to three weeks before we're able to actually hand it back.
RACHAEL BROWN: Police are continuing their investigation into the blaze.
And separately, the former Supreme Court Justice Bernard Teague will lead an independent inquiry into the fire, the emergency response, and whether the mine's regulatory requirements were strict enough. His report is due at the end of August, which lawyers are waiting on to gauge the possible success of insurance claims.
Slater & Gordon says any traders who've lost revenue should be able to make a claim. But given the restrictive nature of the Wrongs Act, which requires 5 per cent impairment, it's unlikely Morwell residents will be able to sue for personal injuries.
ELEANOR HALL: Rachael Brown reporting.
]]></text></news-item>