<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-P0Y1-J9XT-P184"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Maryland: Important Information for Prince George’s County Residents Regarding Snow Event on Monday, March 17, 2014</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Prince George’s County Government, The State of Maryland has issued the following news release:
A reminder that the Prince George’s County Government will be closed today, Monday, March 17, 2014, for all non-essential employees. All County buildings are closed, however County government essential personnel are required to report to work.
Prince George’s County activated its Emergency Operation Center (EOC) last night at 6:00 p.m. and the county’s Snow Emergency Plan is in effect. The Prince George’s County Department of Public Works and Transportation (DPW&T) is working to make roadways “passable” for residents, citizens and travelers across the network of over 1,800 miles of county-maintained roads, Roads are assigned priority for service by categories: primary, secondary and residential. Primary and secondary roads will be serviced first to ensure that public safety and other emergency vehicles can travel. After completion of these roads, residential roads will receive service.
Information for Residents Regarding Plowing and Roads
Residents are asked to park on the even-numbered sides of residential streets or in their driveways to assist the crews in clearing the roadways. Final plowing on residential roadways will not occur until after the snow ends. Driveways and mailboxes will have snow in front of them as a result of the plowing operation. Residents are reminded to shovel their driveways after plowing has occurred and to remove snow/ice from the sidewalks abutting their homes and businesses. Residents are advised to wait 12 hours after the precipitation has stopped before calling 311 or the Snow Information Center at 301-350-0500.
CountyClick 311
Prince George’s County 311 will be open and available starting at 7:00 a.m. Residents can also use CountyClick online anytime at http://countyclick.princegeorgescountymd.gov/.
Trash and Recyclables
The Prince George’s County Department of Environmental Resources (DER) has cancelled all bulky trash, recycling, yard waste and regular trash collection services due to inclement weather and hazardous road conditions today, Monday, March 17, 2014. Trash collections will resume on the resident's next regularly scheduled refuse day. All recycling collection will resume on a sliding schedule and pickups will move by one day throughout the week ending on Saturday.
County Bus Service
TheBus will be operating on limited service today, Monday, March 17, 2014. Passengers should expect delays. The Department of Public Works and Transportation’s Office of Transportation will monitor the weather and road conditions throughout the day to evaluate when to restore service.
Please follow Prince George’s County winter storm developments online at http://www.princegeorgescountymd.gov/ or via the Prince George’s County (@PrinceGeorgesMD) and County Executive Baker’s (@CountyExecBaker) Facebook and Twitter pages using #StPattySnow.
For further information please visit: http://www.princegeorgescountymd.gov/
]]></text></news-item>