<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-CM41-DXY3-0442"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>RDC Surpasses 75 Million Customer Accounts for Daily Risk Monitoring</title><source>Business Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[RDC, the global leader in risk diligence, announced today that it recently surpassed 75 million customer accounts to its daily risk monitoring capability, a sevenfold increase since 2011. RDC's market-leading technology and service platform significantly improves compliance performance for its clients by actively monitoring their customers each day for material risk developments. RDC screens potential matches for false positives and materiality and delivers to its clients only the relevant information that they need to action.
"RDC is all about making life for our clients better and easier," said Tom Obermaier, CEO of RDC. "Daily monitoring is a classic example. It's a simple 'ping and forget' solution - clients trust us with their customer lists and we monitor against the world's largest risk diligence database, which adds some 6,000 new entries each day. RDC's technology allows our clients to customize the approach that works best for them. Their filtering choices lead to potential matches that our analysts review for potential false positives, relevancy and materiality. This assures our clients get only what they need, significantly improving their compliance while at the same time not burdening their already pressing workloads. It's a huge peace-of-mind."
RDC will have a significant presence at the ACAMS moneylaundering.com Annual Conference attended by more than 1,300 compliance professionals March 17 - 19 in Hollywood, Florida. To learn more about RDC and how its innovative products and solutions could support your AML/KYC programs visit Booth #109 at the show. RDC's team of industry experts will be on hand to offer free product demos and discuss the right solution to fit your compliance needs. Attendees can also enter a drawing for a chance to win a free Google Glass.
Mr. Obermaier will be featured on a discussion panel of industry experts that will address the topic "Managing Increasing Demands from Examiners and External Supervisors" on Monday, March 17th at 4:40PM in the Great Hall 6 at the Westin Diplomat conference center.
About RDC
Regulatory DataCorp, Inc. (RDC) is the leading anti-money laundering compliance solutions provider. It offers superior technology and operational services through its unique platforms, allowing firms world-wide to gain superior compliance protection, conduct reasonable diligence, and manage supply chain risk in the most cost-effective manner. RDC provides AML/KYC compliance; Politically Exposed Persons (PEP) protection; emerging market intelligence; corruption, fraud and crime protection; vendor screening and monitoring; and credit risk monitoring to a wide range of clients worldwide. RDC was founded in 2002 by 20 of the world's leading financial institutions. Learn more about RDC by emailing info@rdc.com or visiting www.rdc.com .
http://www.businesswire.com
]]></text></news-item>