<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-RVM1-JB4P-V4M5"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>The Rise of the Chief Data Officer - HSBC, Deutsch Telekom, The Economist, MIT and More Discuss How to Make a Difference Through Data</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The importance of monetising and integrating data, while developing the right Governance models is rapidly increasing, especially when organisations need to evaluate the cost of data management versus the return to their stakeholders.
Chart the evolution of the data function within any FTSE 500 company, and its clear the new frontiers of business lie in how well organisations understand and use their data, not on the traditional battlefields of Sales or R&D.
PEX Network's exclusive Chief  Data  Officer  Summit will help senior Data executives establish where best to focus their attention, and tackle the implications and challenges as the role of the Chief Data Officer evolves. Offering a unique, boardroom-style meeting for attendees to discuss challenges and best practice of their global organisation's data management strategies, CDO Summit is the industry-defining event of 2014.
http://www.chiefdataofficersummit.com/news
"The  launch  of  the  Chief  Data  Officer  Summit  reflects  a  seismic  shift  in  the  industry.  Whilst  Europe  lagged  behind  the  US  when  it  came  to  formalising  an  internal  Data  management  structure,  this  event  demonstrates  that  the  Data  Office  is  now  being  embedded  into  European  enterprise,  and  offers  a  unique  opportunity  to  those  responsible  for  Data  at  the  most  senior  level  to  get  to  grips  with  how  exactly  you  can  take  an  active  role  in  ensuring  the  effectiveness,  profitability  and  sustainability  of  your  developing  role." - Katie Biltoo, Summit Director
Leading discussion through their thoughts and experience at this year's meeting will be:
Director of MIT Information Quality & Data Science, Massachusetts  Institute  of  Technology Chief Data Officer, The  Economist Chief Data Officer, HSBC Chief Technology Officer, Deutsche  Telekom Chief Analytics Officer, RBS Royal Artillery, Information Security Branch, British  Army Director, Business Intelligence, Telefonica Chief Data Officer, European  Commission Vice President Analytics, Volvo
The Chief Data Officer Summit will take place on 7th - 8th May 2014 in London, UK.
Press are invited to attend this important industry forum. If you would like a complimentary press pass please email Nishkala Thiru atNishkala.Thiru@iqpc.co.uk
For further information, please contact us in one of the following ways:Visit:http://www.chiefdataofficersummit.com/newsCall +44(0)20-7036-1300Emailenquire@iqpc.co.ukMedia contact: Nishkala Thiru, +44(0)20-7368-9725,Nishkala.Thiru@iqpc.co.ukor visithttp://www.chiefdataofficersummit.com/news.
SOURCE PEX Network
]]></text></news-item>