<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-C881-JD8H-P037"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>DC Dept. of Insurance Hearing Over CareFirst Subsidiary Surplus Reset for April 29</title><source>BestWire</source><author>Thomas Harman</author><text><![CDATA[District of Columbia insurance regulators have rescheduled a public hearing to determine whether the 2011 surplus reported by a CareFirst Inc. subsidiary is excessive and whether the company has properly reinvested into local community health.
The April 29 public hearing will review the surplus and community health reinvestment performance of CareFirst's subsidiary Group Hospitalization and Medical Services Inc. as filed in June 2011.
An original hearing scheduled for March 12 was postponed.
The Department of Insurance, Securities and Banking requires the surplus review of any nonprofit corporation organized in the District that offers a hospital service plan, or medical service plan, and to date Group Hospitalization and Medical Services is the only nonprofit performing those services. The Medical Insurance Empowerment Amendment Act that created the review process said a company holds excessive surplus if it is greater than the risk-based capital requirements for the preceding year and if the company does not meet the community reinvestment mandate requirements.
Specifically, rules said surpluses are excessive if they are greater than the sum of the National Association of Insurance Commissioners' risk-based capital requirements for health insurers and the Blue Cross/Blue Shield Association's capital requirements, plus whatever surplus is needed by the corporation to meet unexpected expense.
Consultants have discussed in various research papers what the appropriate surplus threshold might be. According to a report done for the department of insurance by Rector and Associates, surplus is calculated using a percentage of risk-based capital-authorized control level. Rector and Associates recommended a range of 840%-1,040% RBC. Should Group Hospitalization and Medical Services exceed those numbers, it would need to increase its community health reinvestment requirements, and if it were below that range, it would have to build its surplus.
(By Thomas Harman, associate editor, BestWeek: Tom.Harman@ambest.com)
]]></text></news-item>