<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-P0Y1-J9XT-P2X4"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Hawaii: New Security Company Planned For Manus Detention Center</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Pacific Islands Development, The State of Hawaii has issued the following news release:
An Australian company has won a 20-month contract worth $1.22 billion (K2.89m) to provide security at the Manus refugee detention centre.
Transfield Services media and communications general manager David Jamieson confirmed this when contacted by The National.
He said the sum of the contract included the Nauru detention centre.
Transfield Services is a multi-national company operating in 11 countries providing a range of services and will be expanding on its operations in Nauru.
The appointment of the company follows recent violence at the Manus centre that claimed the life of a detainee, resulting in Australian and PNG authorities questioning G4S’s ability to keep order at the centre.
G4S is to be investigated by the authorities in both countries over its role in the violence.
[PIR editor’s note: Meanwhile, Radio Australia reported that "A judge in Papua New Guinea is due to begin an inquiry today into the treatment of asylum seekers at Australia's detention centre on Manus Island. … It will examine the conditions at the detention centre and whether they comply with the rights afforded under PNG's constitution and international human rights agreements."]
When asked about Transfield’s predecessor, Jamieson said he could not comment.
"What I can say is that we’ve gained a lot of experience having operated for over a year on Nauru, and we hope to use that experience for the benefit of both the people in the camp, and Manusians themselves," Jamieson said.
According to Australian media, Transfield will be subcontracting Australian-based security company Wilson Security as it already does in Nauru.
Wilson Security is Australia’s leading provider of integrated security services with a reputable track record.
PNG Security Industries Authority registrar Paul Kingston Isari said Wilson had purchased a security licence and permit and was clear to start operating.
"They have complied with our regulations so they are ready to go."
Kingston said.
Transfield managing director and chief executive officer Graeme Hunt told the Australian media that theydid not underestimate or take for granted the difference in circumstances in Nauru and Manus.
"However, we know that we can bring much of that knowledge and our practical approach to Manus Island (from Nauru) for the benefits of all stakeholders. We take this opportunity and responsibility very seriously."
Hunt said Transfield had already started the mobilisation and transition process, with a formal start expected next month
Jamieson said Transfield would be following the Commonwealth procurement guidelines and the guidelines that are set out in its contract.
"There are requirements for us to employ locals as we have done on Nauru."
For further information please visit: http://pidp.eastwestcenter.org/
]]></text></news-item>