<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-V801-DXMP-K3B4"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Why sports not part of any manifesto?; Wild Card</title><source>DNA</source><author>Nikhilesh Pathak</author><text><![CDATA[With each passing day, India is inching towards the biggest festival celebrated in a democratic country - General Election. And the rolling-election stone has been gathering enough mass.
Political outfits have touched various issues - from environment to community and corruption to security. Abusive words oscillating between the parties are confusing the already confused common man to decide what is right for him and what's wrong.
Interestingly, none of the political parties seem to have included sports in their manifesto. Actually no party has done it in the past. It is strange that the combination of sports and athletes comes in handy for a country in brand building exercise but they don't figure in any party's scheme of things.
One may argue, why not the film industry which has its own set of problems without solutions. The response would then be that politicians don't interfere in Bollywood matters while sports federations are open house for the parliamentarians. At least one leader from almost every national party holds some prime position in national sports federations.
While on one hand BJP's Vijaykumar Malhotra - president of Archery Federation of India - refuses to step down from the position despite a poor show at Olympics during his tenure
spread over two decades, NCP's Praful Patel heads the football body in the country.
Congress leader and former Goa chief minister Digambar Kamat is the chief of Swimming Federation of India - a sport that threw a lot of promises at junior level only to fade away with time.
Cricket is the favourite sport of all politicians, it seems. Not only the Board of Control for Cricket in India (BCCI) but also the state units - equally glamorous and powerful - are filled with politicians. These are just a few examples, and there are many other sports federations governed by politicians.
Reiterating the question, why there is no mention of sports development in any party's manifesto? If someone counters by saying sports is covered in development plans, then I would like to ask if Gujarat is a so-called developed state, then why is it still waiting to see its first Olympian?
The Gujarat government has erected sports complexes across the state, albeit only pillars. There are no athletes visiting the venue on a regular basis. The only visitors are dogs and sundries who only spoil the facilities. And, to top it all, the maintenance is zero.
At the national level, too, the scene is equally disturbing. The country stands nowhere in sports while smaller countries are doing far better.
When India won six medals (55th in medal tally) at 2012 London Olympics these policy makers celebrated the success and felicitated them. But what next? Where are concrete policies and logistics which shall help 120-crore people country take its Olympic tally from 6 to 60?
Consider this, one swimmer Sandeep Sejwal, a medal prospect at 2014 Asian Games, has to fund himself for the qualifying tournaments. It is simply because the federations have budgets only for big events and not qualifying events.
For the record, guardian of swimmers in India, Kamat has been questioned in connection with a multi-crore rupee illegal mining scam (and there can't be smoke without fire!). But unfortunately, he has failed miserably to generate funds and boost the morale of medal prospects.
Moreover, a constant confrontation and ego problems between sports federations and sports ministry is a major hurdle. Everyone knows about it but none of our so called 'honourable' members of parliament have initiated to resolve this issue.
Even a few sportspersons, who have been elected MPs don't advocate for it. Former India cricketer Mohammad Kaif and football captain Bhaichung Bhutia will be contesting elections, and it will be interesting to see whether they play sports or politics, if elected.
The 68th edition of Santosh Trophy football tournament was held recently. The reports suggest that this pre-Independence era competition has lost its appeal. The competition, which once provided and groomed international players, have no takers. Top footballers, too, have opted out of it. Why can't Praful Patel and Co. put efforts to revive it or try and give the tournament a professional look? There are a lot of unanswered questions and unfortunately no solutions in sight.
In this 21st century, when the Indian political parties should be promising of Olympic Games, providing job security to sportspersons and other development projects, they continue to give assurances of providing basic needs like road, electricity and shelter. They talk about erasing corruption (but is it going to happen?).
Why can't anyone pledge to bring transparency in administrative affairs, especially those federations which fail to produce an Olympic medalist for years together? It will be a historic day in Indian politics when a party's manifesto will talk about betterment of sports and sportspersons in our country.
@nikhisporty
]]></text></news-item>