<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-C7X1-JCM0-6106"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>ICAC: Inquiry hears allegations both sides of politics stood to gain financially from corrupt water deal</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author>By court reporter Jamelle Wells</author><text><![CDATA[Federal Assistant Treasurer Arthur Sinodinos stood to make millions from a deal involving a water company, the Independent Commission Against Corruption (ICAC) has heard.
The allegations have been made on the first day of public hearings into the deal involving Australian Water Holdings Pty Ltd (AWH), a company with links to the Obeid family.
The investigation, codenamed Operation Credo, is looking at allegations that between 2004 and 2012 various people connected to AWH made corrupt financial gains by "adversely affecting the official functions" of the state-owned Sydney Water Corporation.
In his opening address, counsel assisting Geoffrey Watson adapted Shakespeare, saying "corruption acquaints a man with strange bedfellows".
He said the inquiry is looking at allegations about people from both sides of politics abusing their power for financial gain.
Mr Watson said former NSW Labor minister Joe Tripodi doctored a cabinet minute in his colleague Tony Kelly's office to try and influence public officials over the AWH proposal.
"Joseph Tripodi actually redrafted the cabinet minute on his own laptop computer," he said.
"Mr Tripodi has had a chequered career and at the time he was tooling away on his laptop he was a backbencher.
"It is not clear why Mr Tripodi should or even could be involved in fiddling with a ministerial cabinet minute."
The inquiry also heard that Senator Sinodinos stood to make up to $20 million as a director of Australian Water Holdings if the deal went through.
In a statement to the ABC, a spokesperson for Senator Sinodinos said he would attend the ICAC as a witness and "is looking forward to assisting the inquiry".
Deal did not get past premier, advisers
Mr Watson said Mr Tripodi's Labor colleague Eddie Obeid stood to make up to $60 million from the deal because his family had a financial interest in the company.
He said the deal would have boosted the coffers of AWH by up to $200 million, but it did not get past various advisers and former premier Kristina Keneally.
The inquiry then heard allegations Mr Obeid told former Labor water minister Phil Costa to sack Sydney Water boss Dr Kerry Schott because she opposed aspects of the deal.
Mr Watson said Mr Obeid told Mr Costa in a parliament house lift, "You need to sack that bitch."
The counsel assisting then outlined allegations Sydney Water was unknowingly donating money to the NSW Liberal Party.
He said a family friend of the Obeids', the well known Liberal party fundraiser Nick di Girolamo, was once the head of AWH and paid himself around $1 million a year, plus bonuses.
Mr Di Girolamo is accused of charging Sydney Water for project managing water infrastructure and claiming thousands of dollars in expenses which were actually donations to the Liberal Party.
The Obeid family is accused of being secret stakeholders in AWH but say the $3 million they paid into the company in 2010 was converted into a "loan".
Mr Watson said Mr Di Girolamo used some of that $3 million to pay off debts incurred over a racehorse called Partners In Crime.
NSW Premier Barry O'Farrell has issued a statement distancing himself and his former finance minister Greg Pearce from the allegations about Sydney Water aired at the ICAC today.
The statement highlights comments by the counsel assisting the ICAC, who told the hearing the watchdog looked carefully at Mr O'Farrell and Mr Pearce's actions and found no evidence to implicate either in any corruption.
As I've always stated, matters relating to AWH were appropriately handled at arm's length by Sydney Water.
I have been a consistent and strong supporter of ICAC and have led reforms since coming to office in March 2011 which strengthened its powers. When requested by the Commissioner, the NSW Government has given the ICAC extra resources to fulfil its responsibilities.
The NSW Government is determined to restore trust in the public institutions of NSW and will continue to implement public sector integrity and accountability reforms, and respect and uphold good governance and proper process.
The NSW Government is determined to respect all statutory requirements of the ICAC Act and accordingly will not make any further statements about the ICAC's Operation Credo and related enquiries until ICAC has concluded its work.
Liberal Party returns 'tainted' donations from AWH
The NSW division of the Liberal Party has decided to cancel donations from Australian Water Holdings in light of today's evidence.
The party's acting director Simon McInnes has issued a statement saying more than $75,000 donated by AWH will be refunded to Sydney Water.
He described the donations as "tainted" and says the Liberal Party is returning them because it acts with the highest integrity.
Much of the evidence to be heard over the next three weeks is connected to a second inquiry into allegations former NSW energy minister Chris Hartcher, The Entrance MP Chris Spence and Wyong MP Darren Webber received corrupt political donations connected to AWH.
Separate to the ICAC inquiry, a number of AWH shareholders have started a Federal Court case suing eight former and current directors for deceptive conduct.
They are suing Mr Di Girolamo, Senator Sinodinos, Mr Costa and others, claiming they were given false information about AWH contracts and future business prospects.
]]></text></news-item>