<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-N891-JCBN-V3MB"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Fonterra sales grow in spite of botulism scare</title><source>The Evening Standard (Palmerston North, New Zealand)</source><author>Hamish Rutherford in Beijing</author><text><![CDATA[Fonterra is shrugging off the impact of last year's botulism scare in China, saying that after a brief lull its sales into the market continue to exceed its expectations.
The company also appeared to brush aside claims about the impact the scare has had on other, smaller dairy exporters, saying the Chinese government's push for consolidation was already under way before it took place.
Speaking at the company's offices in China's capital yesterday, chairman John Wilson said there was "some flatness" in the weeks around the food safety scare, but strong growth quickly resumed. "What we're seeing across all of what we do here in China is that we continue to exceed our sales targets."
Last August the Ministry for Primary Industries (MPI) announced that tests had shown that a bacterium which could cause botulism, a severe form of food poisoning, had been detected in a concentrated whey product produced at a Fonterra plant in Waikato. It prompted a worldwide recall, which was complicated because Fonterra could not immediately find all of the product, which had been produced more than a year earlier.
Several countries blocked New Zealand dairy products at the border, although testing later showed the event was a false alarm.
Wilson said that its ingredients business, its new long-life milk products and initial sales of its own infant formula, along with products for the elderly, were all "exceeding expectations".
The farmer owned co-operative, New Zealand's largest company, has more than $4 billion in annual sales into China, a market which is rapidly growing.
Some smaller dairy companies have complained that even though they were not directly linked to the incident, the scare impacted on them more as they did not have the resource or connections that Fonterra does to resolve blocks or reassure consumers.
Wilson said Fonterra took its leadership role in the market "sincerely", but that the market was changing before last year's product recall.
"The Chinese government and the Chinese regulators are very certain that they want to see consolidation and they want to make sure that they can have real confidence for their consumers," Wilson said.
Fonterra, which took products from the farmgate into the market, was "ideally placed in this marketplace", but other companies may not be as well placed.
Prime Minister John Key is in China, on a trip which centres around his commitment during the botulism scare to come to China to deliver an update on New Zealand's food safety standards. It comes just days after MPI revealed it had laid charges against Fonterra under the Animal Products Act related to the contamination issue.
He declined to comment directly on the links between Judith Collins and Oravida, a company on which her husband is a director, but said it was highly important for companies to show connections with government. Fairfax NZ
]]></text></news-item>