<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-HT71-JB4F-Y2BJ"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Covalence SA: ESG News Review 8 - 14 March 2014</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Toyota was among the most praised companies last week as it announced a wage increase for its Japan-based workers, responding to calls from Japanese Prime Minister Shinzo Abe. Nestle published a new report describing its efforts to meet commitments in areas such as nutrition, water, rural development, sustainability and compliance; Nestle also announced it will implement a new executive remuneration scheme in 2015. Unilever acquired a majority stake in the Qinyuan Group, a leading Chinese water purification business, which will help the company "make safe drinking water available and affordable to people across the world". Solvay has launched the production of torrefied biomass at an industrial scale in the United States, "creating a new business that aims to provide an innovative and renewable energy solution". Cisco announced it has received the 2014 Humanitarian Partnership Award from the Silicon Valley Chapter of the American Red Cross.
Tokyo Electric Power was among the most criticized companies last week, three years after the Fukushima nuclear accident, as some of its workers have protested to request better working conditions and higher wages. General Motors is facing several investigations in the USA regarding late recalls of defective cars. A former Credit Suisse banker pleaded guilty to conspiring to help U.S. customers evade taxes, and said his superiors were aware of his actions, according to documents filed in court. Societe Generale, together with Barclays, HSBC, Deutsche Bank and Bank of Nova Scotia, is being sued by US hedge fund AIS Capital over allegations that the banks manipulated the gold price; Societe Generale, as well as BNP Paribas and Credit Agricole, is also being probed by US authorities for violating American sanctions against countries like Cuba, Iran and Sudan. Herbalife is facing an inquiry by the US Federal Trade Commission regarding its marketing and distribution practices, described by investor William Ackman as a "pyramid scheme".
The tag cloud below shows words found in news about these companies.
ESG News Review 8 - 14 March 2014
Words found in news about most praised and most criticized companies last week
This weekly review has been produced using the EthicalQuote reputation index run by Covalence, which tracks 2800 companies worldwide. It gives a summary of positive and negative news published last week about Environmental, Social, Governance (ESG), Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR), ethics and sustainability.
The EthicalQuote reputation index integrates thousands of news pieces gathered online and classified according to 50 ESG criteria inspired by the Global Reporting Initiative (GRI), and to their positive or negative sentiment.
The next heatmap represents the sentiment calculated for each of the 50 criteria last week. The 50 criteria are embedded into 7 dimensions, following the structure of the GRI. The color indicates the ratio of positive news / total news.
click http://www.ethicalquote.com/index.php/2014/03/17/esg-news-review-8-14-march-2014/
COMPANY BACKGROUND
ACTIVITIES
Covalence SA provides ethical reputation index tracking services to companies and Swiss equities. It provides media analytics and financial ratings to corporates and investors. The company also offers reputation management, ranking, research, research, fund and portfolio rating, and data feed services. It serves corporates, investors, non profit organizations, and SMEs. Covalence SA was founded in 2001 and is based in Geneva, Switzerland.
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
27 February 2014: Covalence SA: 2nd Geneva Summit On Sustainable Finance - Call For Papers & Save The Date: 27.11.2014
We are pleased to announce that the 2nd Geneva Summit on Sustainable Finance will take place on November 27th, 2014 at the University of Geneva in Switzerland. The theme for this year's event is Sustainable Finance, quo vadis? As in the previous year, the conference will provide a platform for sustainable finance related research relevant to academics, investment practitioners, think-tanks, and policy-makers.
click http://www.ethicalquote.com/index.php/2014/02/28/2nd-geneva-summit-on-sustainable-finance-call-for-papers-save-the-date-27-11-2014/
03 February 2014: Covalence SA: Esg News Review 25 - 31 January 2014
Nissan appeared among the most praised companies last week, and so did FedEx. These two companies announced they would begin testing a 100 percent electric compact cargo vehicle. Costco Wholesale was praised by President Obama for "taking the leadership to pay its workers fair wages".
click http://www.ethicalquote.com/index.php/2014/02/03/esg-news-review-25-31-january-2014/
27 January 2014: Covalence SA: Esg News Review 18 - 24 January 2014
Boeing was among the most praised companies last week as it announced a partnership with Abu Dhabi's state-owned carrier Etihad Airways and French energy firm Total to develop biofuels. Boeing, with other members of the Sustainable Aviation Fuel Users Group, has identified a commercially viable "green diesel" that emits 50% less carbon dioxide than conventional fossil fuels. At an announcement during the World Economic Forum in Davos Westpac Banking Corporation was named the leader of Corporate Knights' 2014 Global 100 Index, a ranking of the "100 Most Sustainable Corporations in the World".
click http://www.ethicalquote.com/index.php/2014/01/27/esg-news-review-18-24-january-2014/
22 January 2014: Covalence SA: +26% En 2013 Pour Les Actions Ethiques
Dans ce contexte de croissance, les strategies ethiques BBGI-EthicalQuote ne sont pas en reste, surperformant a la fois en decembre et en 2013. En decembre, les strategies 20, 40 et 60 enregistrent +0,08%, +0,88% et +0,89% contre -0,74% et -0,37% pour les indices SMI et SPI.
click http://www.ethicalquote.com/index.php/2014/01/22/26-en-2013-pour-les-actions-ethiques/
17 January 2014: Covalence SA: Esg News Review 11 - 17 January 2014
Alstom appeared among the most praised companies last week, as it announced it would cease engaging sales consultants to ensure it "conducts business in a responsible way and strives to achieve the highest ethical standards". Alstom is also calling for a target of more than 30% of renewable energy sourced in Europe by 2030.
click http://www.ethicalquote.com/index.php/2014/01/20/esg-news-review-11-17-january-2014/
]]></text></news-item>