<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-CF91-JB4P-V1XD"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>SAIC Awarded Contract by the State of California Governor's Office of Emergency Services; Company to Provide FirstNet Planning Support Services</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ The State of California Governor's Office of Emergency Services awarded Science Applications International Corporation (NYSE: SAIC) with a prime contract to provide planning support services regarding FirstNet.

FirstNet will be the first high-speed wireless, broadband data network dedicated to public safety. It will become a single, nationwide network that facilitates communication for public safety users during emergencies and on the job every day.
Under the contract, SAIC will provide planning and outreach support services, including public safety broadband outreach and education planning; engagement and coordination of stakeholders; and conduct of presentations, town halls, and webinars that advise the Office of Emergency Services on FirstNet legislation. The single award firm fixed price/time and materials contract has a two-year base period of performance, one 12-month option and a total contract value of approximately $440,000, if all options are exercised. Work will be performed throughout California.
"SAIC is uniquely positioned to support the planning and eventual build of FirstNet given the companies deep history and expertise in the various technologies, networking and integration," said Robert Genter, SAIC senior vice president and general manager of the Emerging Markets Customer Group. "We are pleased to be providing the support to select states and agencies in the initial phase. California is an important customer as their success is essential to the national success of this critical infrastructure."
About SAIC
SAIC is a leading technology integrator providing full life-cycle services and solutions in the technical, engineering, and enterprise information technology markets. SAIC's deep domain knowledge and customer relationships enable the delivery of systems engineering and integration offerings for large, complex government and commercial projects. SAIC's approximately 14,000 employees serve customers in the U.S. federal government, state/local, and global commercial markets, specializing in providing a broad range of higher-end, differentiated technical capabilities. Headquartered in McLean, Va., SAIC has annual revenues of about $4 billion. For more information, visithttp://www.saic.com/.    
Certain statements in this announcement constitute forward-looking statements within the meaning of the Private Securities Litigation Reform Act of 1995. These statements involve risks and uncertainties and a number of factors could cause our actual results, performance, achievements, or industry results to be very different from the results, performance, or achievements expressed or implied by such forward-looking statements. Some of these factors include, but are not limited to, the risk factors set forth in SAIC's Form 10 and other such filings that SAIC makes with the SEC from time to time. Due to such uncertainties and risks, readers are cautioned not to place undue reliance on such forward-looking statements, which speak only as of the date hereof.
Photo -http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20131008/PH94180LOGO
SOURCE SAIC
]]></text></news-item>