<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-CHN1-DXKH-N3DY"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Alpha Natural Resources jumps 6.2%</title><source>Global Round Up - Bonds</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[BONDS
Alpha Natural Resources Inc (N:ANR.GA) bond jumped US$5.80 (or 6.2%) from its last traded date of September 27, 2013 to close at US$99.42. The yield to maturity has decreased by 149.1 basis points from 4.42% to 2.92%.
ISSUE DETAILS
COUPON & DATES
RELATIVE VALUATION INDICATORS [RVI] TECHNICALS% Discount to high: alpha Natural Resources is at a discount of 1.1% to its 12-month high of US$100.51 traded on 22 May, 2013. % Premium to low: alpha Natural Resources is at a premium of 15.3%. - The present value of US$1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in Alpha Natural Resources is US$1,154, for a capital gain of US$154. The total return to investors for 1 year is 15.4%.

PRICE UPTREND (or YIELD DOWNTREND)- The price climbed 4.5% in the last week and jumped 7.5% in the last month.
KEY STATISTICS
CREDIT RATING SUMMARY
DESCRIPTIONAlpha Natural Resources, Inc. is an Appalachian coal supplier. The Company produces, processes and sells steam and metallurgical coal from eight regional business units, through its active underground mines, active surface mines and preparation plants located throughout Virginia, West Virginia, Kentucky, and Pennsylvania. It also owns a road construction business in West Virginia and Virginia that recovers coal. The Company is also involved in the purchase and resale of coal mined by others. On September 26, 2008, the Company sold its interest in Gallatin Materials LLC (Gallatin), a start-up lime manufacturing business in Verona, Kentucky.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 5 company announcements are:March 05: Alpha Natural Resources Concludes Comprehensive Environmental Agreement[News Story] BRISTOL, Va., March 5, 2014 -- Alpha Natural Resources, Inc. (NYSE:ANR) today announced that it has entered into a consent decree with the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), U.S. Department of Justice (DOJ) and three states regarding claims under the Clean Water Act.The consent decree resolves a complaint by the EPA and state agencies alleging that the company's mining affiliates in Kentucky, Pennsylvania, Tennessee, Virginia and West Virginia exceeded certain water discharge permit limits.
February 21: Alpha Natural Resources to Participate in Upcoming Investor Conferences[News Story] BRISTOL, Va., Feb. 21, 2014 -- Alpha Natural Resources, Inc. (NYSE:ANR), a leading U.S. coal producer, announced that members of Alpha's management team plan to participate in several investor conferences, including: the BMO Capital Markets 23rdGlobal Metals & Mining Conference on Monday, February 24, 2014; the Simmons & Company International 14th Annual Energy Conference on Thursday, February 27, 2014; Barclays Metals and Materials Cross Asset Forum on Wednesday, March 19, 2014; and Howard Weil's 42nd Annual Energy Conference on Wednesday, March 26, 2014.
February 12: Alpha Natural Resources Announces Results for Fourth Quarter and Full Year 2013[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Usnyse/Stock/News/552317.htmlSource: Nasdaq Stock Exchange
February 10: U.S. Attorney Closes Upper Big Branch Non-Prosecution Agreement Following Full Compliance by Alpha Natural Resources[News Story] BRISTOL, Va., Feb. 10, 2014 -- Alpha Natural Resources, Inc. (NYSE:ANR), today announced that the United States Attorney's Office for the Southern District of West Virginia (USAO SDWV) has closed the Non-Prosecution Agreement (NPA) the company entered into on Dec. 6, 2011.On April 5, 2010, an explosion at the Upper Big Branch Mine (UBB), operated by a subsidiary of Massey Energy Co., claimed the lives of 29 miners.
February 06: Alpha Natural Resources Subsidiary to Open London Office; Vice President Named to Lead Effort[News Story] BRISTOL, Va., Feb. 6, 2014 -- In continuing efforts to enhance servicing of international customers and take advantage of expanding European markets, Alpha Natural Resources, Inc. (NYSE:ANR), a leading U.S. coal supplier, today announced that subsidiary Alpha Coal Sales International Limited will open a London office."Our intent is to build an export platform for U.S.
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>