<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-8361-DXX7-H13B"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>NSW Labor Minister Eddie Obeid's family wanted its stake in a controversial company kept secret, ICAC hears</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author>By court reporter Jamelle Wells</author><text><![CDATA[NSW Labor Minister Eddie Obeid's family wanted its 30 per cent stake in the controversial company kept secret, the Independent Commission Against Corruption (ICAC) has heard.
The ICAC's investigation, codenamed Operation Credo, is looking at allegations that between 2004 and 2012 various people connected to the company Australian Water Holdings (AWH) made corrupt financial gains by "adversely affecting the official functions" of the state-owned Sydney Water Corporation.
AWH has links to the Obeid family.
The inquiry heard that a Liberal party fundraiser, John Rippon, was recruited to the board of a private water company because of his political connections.
Mr Rippon told the inquiry, Mr Obeid's family wanted its 30 per cent stake in the controversial company kept secret.
Mr Rippon told the ICAC a colleague informed him the Obeid family was buying a stake in the company, but they did not want it publicised.
Mr Obeid is accused of trying to get a Sydney Water staffer who opposed the deal sacked.
The Obeid's have previously stated that their investment in the company was "converted to a loan" and that they have done nothing wrong.
Counsel Assisting Geoffrey Watson quizzed Mr Rippon, who was an AWH director, about why Liberal Party fundraiser Nick Di Girolamo was recruited to the company's board.
Mr Rippon said it was because he had "political connections" and AWH had been "having trouble" negotiating with Sydney Water and wanted to go over its head.
The inquiry has previously heard Nick Di Girolamo falsely invoiced Sydney Water for expenses and used the money for Liberal party donations.
On Monday the inquiry heard Federal Assistant Treasurer Arthur Sinodinos stood to make millions from a deal involving the water company if the deal went through.
At the time he was the NSW treasurer of the Liberal Party.
'Dealings with AWH at arm's length'
The New South Wales Premier Barry O'Farrell says he was always confident his government's dealings with AWH were at arm's length.
Mr O'Farrell was interviewed by investigators from the ICAC about his connection to AWH.
But the inquiry was told yesterday there was no evidence to suggest he was involved in any form of corruption.
Mr O'Farrell has welcomed the public validation.
"The dealings that the government had with Australian Water Holdings were as I've said at all times arms length and appropriate," he said,
"And that's consistent with the statements made by counsel assisting the Independent Commission Against Corruption yesterday and that's what I've been saying for some time."
]]></text></news-item>