<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-C8N1-JC92-P218"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>PPF selling stake in Eldorado to partner Jiri Smejc</title><source>Russia &amp; CIS Business and Financial Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[PPF Group is selling a stake in Russian consumer electronics retailer Eldorado, which it wholly owns, to Jiri Smejc's Emma Capital.
The parameters of the deal will be disclosed within a few months, after the details are finalized, PPF said.
PPF, which is controlled by Czech tycoon Petr Kellner, and Eldorado declined to comment.
Smejc is a former shareholder of PPF. Last year he swapped his 5% stake in the group for 13.8% of Home Credit, which among other things owns Russian retail lender HCF Bank.
Under the agreement, Emma Capital representative Ondrej Frydrych will become the CEO of Eldorado, replacing Igor Dolezel. Frydrych was previously a partner with Adastra Business Consulting, the clients of which included portfolio companies of PPF Group.
Smejc became head of Home Credit when he became a minority shareholder under a similar arrangement.
Eldorado had a chain of about 400 stores and 140 order pickup points as of October 2013. The company's sales grew more than 15% to 112.4 billion rubles (with VAT) in 2012, with online sales jumping 67.2%.
Last year PPF held negotiations to sell Eldorado with rival retailer M.Video (MOEX: MVID). The Federal Anti-Monopoly Service greenlighted the deal, but stipulated that the combined company would have to close some stores in 35 Russian regions, including Moscow. Due to the regulator's stipulation and the "absence of consensus on the conditions of the deal," the companies ended negotiations. The regulator wanted more stores closed than M.Video had expected the company's president and co-owner, Alexander Tynkovan said.
A number of market sources said that M.Video acquiring control of Eldorado was seen as an interim stage of a deal in which Smejc, in partnership with Otkritie Financial Corporation and Alexander Nesis' ICT Group, would buy the merged company.
Smejc began working with PPF in 2004 and in 2005 became a minority shareholder of the group. In addition to a number of other positions, he has served as a board director at insurance group Generali PPF Holding since January 2008. In August 2013, Smejc, together with ICT Group and Greek shipping magnate George Melissanidis, acquired 33% of Greek lottery operator OPAP.
Kellner, the wealthiest individual in the Czech Republic, owns 98% of PPF. In addition to Eldorado and Home Credit, his assets include precious metals miner Polymetal (MOEX: POLY) and a property development division. Last year PPF sold 2.87% of shares in Russian potash giant Uralkali (MOEX: URKA) that it received earlier for a blocking stake in Nomos Bank (MOEX: NMOS).
Vp of
(Our editorial staff can be reached at eng.editors@interfax.ru)
]]></text></news-item>