<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS7-9FY1-F0JP-W3F6"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Residents wary of big tip</title><source>Brimbank Leader (Australia)</source><author>Ami Humpage</author><text><![CDATA[ROCKBANK residents are concerned an expansion of Boral's Ravenhall landfill could affect the health of their children and livestock.
But Boral has been quick to discount the fears, assuring the community there is no risk.
Ernie Ewert's family has bred and trained racehorses from their Sheahan Rd property for more than 50 years, relying on the mineral-rich groundwater for their prized stock.
And he's concerned an expansion would not only increase the already unbearable smell wafting from the tip, but leaching could contaminate water relied on by nearby farmers.
He said for years the area had been spruiked as a beautiful place to live. "Caroline Springs has been built, there are residential developments planned for the next five to 10 years; a tip this size is not an incentive for investment," Mr Ewert said.
Neighbour and mother of four Daniela Budinoska agreed, saying she feared for the future health of her children.
"We moved here three years ago for fresh air for the children and a semirural lifestyle. A monster tip is not what we signed up for," Ms Budinoska said.
Boral Waste Solutions business manager Richard McCarthy assured residents the company was committed to operating the landfill within its regulatory, environmental and safety obligations.
He said each waste "cell" was lined with clay and a high-density polythene liner was welded to each cell to prevent water leaching.
"And the groundwater is continuously monitored in accordance with the EPA (Environment Protection Authority) guidelines and routinely audited," Mr McCarthy said.
He also reiterated the landfill did not and was not proposing to accept asbestos, liquids, toxic or hazardous waste.The campaign to convince Melton councillors to reject the proposed expansion continues to gain momentum with more than 1700 objections received by the council and more than 2500 signatures on a petition set to be presented to the Legislative Council in coming weeks.
]]></text></news-item>