<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-VS81-JBHM-S2HK"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>States Urge Senators To 'Inventory' Spill Programs Before Advancing Bill</title><source>Defense Environment Alert</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Posted: March 11, 2014 An alliance of state regulators is urging senators crafting legislation intended to fill gaps in chemical spill response programs to first examine the need for such legislation -- and inventory existing programs and agencies -- before advancing any bill, though the bill's backers recently postponed a planned markup to address state and other concerns.
"We recommend a comprehensive inventory of existing federal, state, and local authorities and programs to determine what gaps exist in our collective statutory and regulatory network and how best to close such gaps," the state regulators said in a March 5 letter.
"Until such an assessment is done, it is too early to determine which statute and/or program should be amended or enhanced, or whether the solution lies in enhancing the use of existing authorities," the letter adds. The letter was signed by the Association of Clean Water Administrators (ACWA), Association of State and Territorial Solid Waste Management Officials, the Association of State Drinking Water Administrators (ASDWA), the Environmental Council of the States (ECOS), and the Association of State and Territorial Health Officials.
At issue is S.1961, a bill sponsored by Sens. Barbara Boxer (D-CA), Joe Manchin (D-WV), Jay Rockefeller (D-WV) and Dick Durbin (D-IL) that would proposes to give EPA new authority under the Safe Drinking Water Act (SDWA) to regulate above-ground chemical storage facilities.
The proposed bill would require EPA to create "a chemical storage facility source water protection program to provide for the protection of public water systems from a release of chemicals from a covered chemical storage facility." Under the bill, the agency would set programmatic requirements for delegated states, which would be required to conduct oversight and routine inspections of above-ground chemical storage facilities.
The senators crafted the bill after the recent Charleston, WV spill that released chemicals from an above ground tank that had not been inspected in decades, contaminating the town's water supply when it entered the Elk River upstream from the local drinking water utility's intake.
ASDWA's Concern
But the bill has drawn concern from ASDWA, whose officials feared it would impose a massive new burden on regulators whose current authority is limited to source water protection efforts. The concern from drinking water regulators may have been a factor that drove Rep. Shelley Moore Capito (R-WV) to craft a bill that created new authorities under the Clean Water Act, rather than the SDWA.
The Senate bill had been slated for a markup this month but Boxer, chairman of the Senate environment committee, recently agreed to a request from Sen. David Vitter (R-LA), the panel's top Republican, to postpone the markup for one month to give senators time to address "some serious substantive concerns" he has with the current language.
In a footnote in the letter to senators, the state groups noted ASDWA's concerns that any chemical storage tank program should not be part of the SDWA, fearing it would divert state and local personnel from overseeing 150,000 public water systems from their "principal mission" of ensuring safe tap water.
But the state groups said that it is "appropriate and critical" that state drinking water program personnel should collaborate with other regulators to protect drinking water sources, including in sharing source water protection assessment data so that "protective activities can best be targeted."
The state officials also said that appropriate oversight of above-ground tanks must occur to prevent contamination of water, productive land and air quality. But the officials said that if lawmakers impose "a potentially daunting set of new requirements," then they should provide resources to states "commensurate with the enormity of the task."
Spokesmen for the senators did not respond to requests for comment. -- Miranda Green (mgreen@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>