<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-D7M1-DXKH-N480"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Tesmec rises 3.4% on high volatility</title><source>News Bites - Western Europe: Italy</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Tesmec (MI:TES), Italy's 20th largest industrial goods & services company by market capitalisation, traded between an intraday low of 72.0c and a high of 77.40c, suggesting a trading opportunity between peaks and troughs. The average daily volatility of 3.2% places the stock in the 2nd quartile in the market meaning it is moderately volatile. Today its volatility (highest price minus lowest price/lowest price) of 7.5% was 3.2 times the average daily volatility of 3.2%, up from 4.3% on Monday and 6.7% on Friday. A price rise on high volatility is a bullish signal. The stock price lifted 2.50c (or 3.4%) to close at 75.60c, ending a nine-day streak of losses. Compared with the FTSE MIB Index which rose 185.9 points (or 0.9%) in the day, this represented a relative price increase of 2.5%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Tesmec, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051181660314474
Bullish Signals- In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week high thrice. - The present value of EUR1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Tesmec is EUR1,285, including a capital gain of EUR222 and dividend reinvested of EUR63.
Oversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The Relative Strength Index (RSI) of 26.3 has breached the oversold line of 30, suggesting the price decrease of 8.8% in the last 14 days is unusually high. - The Money Flow Index [MFI] is 18.6 suggesting an oversold 14-day trend, being under 20. The Money Ratio of 0.2 suggests positive money flow was 0.2 times negative money flow. - The Stochastic indicator of 10.2 has pierced the oversold line of 20.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Return on Equity 18.9% [9.8%].- Return on Assets 4.8% [1.7%].- Return on Capital Employed 20.1% [6.3%].- Dividend yield of 4.6% [2.3%].- Price to EBITDA of 3.1 [3.9].Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 4.8 is less than 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 21.2%. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.5. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- Net profit margin has averaged 5.9% in the last 3 years. This is better than the sector average of 4.3% and suggests a high margin of safety.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity of 18.9% is better than sector average of 9.8%. This is computed as net profit margin of 6.8% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 0.71 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 3.9.- Net Profit margin, EBIT margin and EBITDA margin are positive and have seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

Bearish SignalsFundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price/Sales of 0.7 [0.6].Other Bearish Signals:- Net Profit growth has seen consecutive falls and seems to be on a slippery slope in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 818,384 shares worth EUR618,698 (US$860,547) traded. This has been propped up by robust volume of 2.7 times average. Beta: the Beta of Tesmec stock is 0.6. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market. - Tesmec is at a discount of 18.4% to its 12-month high of 92.70c on 21 Jan, 2014. It is also at a premium of 26.0% to the 12-month low of 60.0c on 27 Mar, 2013.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 4 company announcements are:November 21: Tesmec director buysTesmec (MI:TES) director Gianluca Bolelli bought 13,000 shares worth EUR10,156 on November 20, 2013. The purchase price was 77.95c.
July 01: Weekly disclosure regarding purchase of treasury shares[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Italy/Stock/News/75475.pdfSource: Company Website
June 19: The Joint Venture Tesmec Peninsula supplies Contract Fleet Management for the construction of the New Port Project in Doha, Qatar[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Italy/Stock/News/75476.pdfSource: Company Website
April 06: Tesmec S.p.A.: extension of the deadline for the submission by the minority shareholders of lists for the appointment of Statutory Auditors[Company Release]Grassobbio (Bergamo), 6 April 2013 -Tesmec S.p.A. (MTA, STAR: TES), among the main global players offering integrated solutions for infrastructures related to transmission of electrical power and data and material transport, announces on expiry of the deadline, no list for the appointment of the Board of Statutory Auditors was filed by minority Shareholders.Pursuant to Article 144-sexies, paragraph 5 of the Italian Issuers Regulation, the deadline for the submission of lists for said appointment by minority Shareholders - with the same procedures and documentation reported in the Notice published on 20 March 2013 on Tesmec website (http://investor.tesmec.com/Governance/Meetings.aspx) and in abridged (in Italian) on the daily newspaper Milano Finanza - is thus extended to 8 April 2013, and the minimum threshold necessary for the submission is reduced by half.Source: Company Website
ISIN: IT0004585243
MI:TES; BIT:TES; IM:TES
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>