<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-4XY1-JBVM-Y4D7"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Piping up Road protest hits the wrong target</title><source>The Bristol Post</source><author>Gavin Thompson</author><text><![CDATA[EVEN a "demented monkey with half a brain" could have done a better job of planning works currently digging up Anchor Road in Hotwells, according to one of the city's most successful businessmen.
But Peter Hargreaves, co-founder of the FTSE 100 investment firm Hargreaves Lansdown, vented his anger towards Bristol Water… who were not responsible. The roadworks are close to the Harbourside office of his firm, which employs about 700 people in Bristol. He wrote: "I am absolutely 100 per cent convinced that with a tiny piece of thought the disruption that you have caused could have been completely eliminated. It is a pity in the UK we don't pillory such behaviour. I am appalled that a company whose customers are in the area have behaved in this manner."
However, Paul Kelson, Bristol Water, public relations manager, said: "We are not doing work there at the moment." He said it did have upcoming work nearby, but that would not affect traffic.
However, he did admit Bristol Water was digging up lots of other roads in the city as part of its major investment in renewing the water mains. But it is Wales and West Utilities behind this particular work - part of an "essential" gas pipe replacement scheme to "make sure gas users in the area continue to have a safe and reliable supply".
A spokesman from the firm said: "Work began on February 14 and will be completed tomorrow - one week ahead of schedule. In order to carry out the scheme as safely as possible it was necessary to close one lane on Hotwell Road for the duration of the project.
"We communicated with the local highways authority in planning the scheme and have tried to carry out this essential work with the least amount of disruption to local people as possible. We'd like to thank everyone for bearing with us while we were working."
Despite misdirecting his criticisms, Mr Hargreaves' point remains the same. He said: "These firms have no consideration for anyone. They don't even do the work quickly. If they were told for every week the road is closed you will have to pay £100,000, they would move a lot quicker."
He called for the city council to take a stronger role in co-ordinating road closures and to be tougher when it comes to granting permission.
THE LETTER IN FULL ? I HAVE noticed over the last few years that Bristol Water behaves in a way commensurate with monopoly behaviour.
In other words, they have shown absolutely no consideration whatsoever for the road users in the Bristol area. This behaviour is intolerable. I am absolutely 100 per cent convinced that with a tiny piece of thought the disruption that you have caused could have been completely eliminated.
It is a pity in the UK we don't pillory such behaviour. I am appalled that a company whose customers are in the area have behaved in this manner. The latest fiasco is beyond belief. The works in Hotwells in Bristol have caused queues all the way back to www.Backwell.No one has even taken a second's thought of how that could be avoided. A demented monkey with half a brain could have solved the disruption it has caused thousands and thousands of commuters during the last four weeks.
I would be interested to hear your comments.
Yours faithfully Peter K Hargreaves
]]></text></news-item>