<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-C8F1-JB1X-W186"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Civil society calls for protection of women against violence</title><source>The Patriot</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The government must bring the culprits and authorities to justice in Muzaffargarh rape case, leaving no option for gang-rape victim except to set herself ablaze.
The government must take action against police for torturing protesting nurses in Lahore. This was demanded by the participants of a demonstration entitled `Protect Women against Violence' held in front of Press Club in Faisalabad.
Speaking on this occasion, the director of the PHD Foundation, Suneel Malik said, "The government must realize its obligation to prosecute the rapist and immediately launch practical measures to ensure that no other rape victim has to set herself ablaze to get noticed."
The director of the AWAM, Nazia Sardar said, "The criminal justice system must be strengthened through reforming the rules, procedures and police investigation, and sensitizing the legal enforcing agencies on dealing with cases of violence against women and girls."
A political activist, Robin Daniel said, "When the state fails to prosecute the perpetrators of rape, it not only encourages further abuse, but government's inaction gives the impression that male violence against females is acceptable."
A women's rights activist, Shazia George said, "A helpline service providing referral facilities of legal aid and medical aid must be established at district police officer level, for women in distress, which must be interconnected to all the existing structures at the tehsil and union council levels for easy access of survivors of violence to effective prevention and response."
A human rights activist, Naseem Anthony said, "The sacrifice of gang-rape victim has exposed the ordeals that rape victims in the country face when they try to bring their tormentors to justice. This tragic incident would only discourage victims of sexual violence from trying to get justice."
A social activist, Irshad Parkash said, the government must take substantive measure to devise an efficient monitoring system for strict implementation of laws, and must train forces responsible for the implementation of laws protecting vulnerable groups," she added.
A social activist, Tahir Iqbal condemned the sacking of ad hoc nurses by the health department, and the torture on peaceful nurses by the police, and urged the government to reinstate the nurses on regular basis with dignity."
A peace activist, Aslam Saif said, "Reporting incidents of violence against women is not a common practice in Pakistan, but it is pity that the authorities took action after the courageous rape victim died due to Self-Immolation as a protest against injustice by the police and court.
A political activist, Habkook Gill said, "Transfer, suspension and arrest of the police officials in not enough, therefore the government must set a precedent, and take action against the corrupt authorities favouring criminals to ensure the transparent and impartial police investigation and judicial system across the country."
A human rights activist, Naveed Walter said, "There is no room for a parallel advisory body called Council of Islamic Ideology (CII) in the presence of the elected parliament, which always targets women's freedoms and rights. Therefore, it must be abolished."
The demonstration was joined by people hailing from different communities and different socio-economic background. They were wearing white ribbons as a symbol of opposition to violence against women, and tying black ribbons to mark dark days for women. They enchanted slogans against inhuman and unethical treatment towards women witnessed in Pakistan, and urged the government to take tangible steps for the protection of women's rights. They were carrying placards and banners inscribed with various statements criticizing gender based discrimination and violence.
The demonstration was staged by the Human Rights Defenders Network (REAT), Peace and Human Development (PHD Foundation), Association of Women for Awareness & Motivation (AWAM), National Minorities Alliance of Pakistan (NMAP), Human Rights Focus (HRF), Adara Samaji Behbood (ASB) and Aitbar Foundation.
]]></text></news-item>