<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-7MX1-JBTY-T18W"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Restrictions continue in Indian-controlled Kashmir district for day 4</title><source>Xinhua General News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[SRINAGAR, Indian-controlled Kashmir, March 18 (Xinhua)-- Strict restrictions remained in force in parts of Indian-controlled Kashmir district for the fourth straight day Tuesday to stop protest demonstrations and clashes in wake of killing of a youth in police firing, officials said.
The restrictions are being enforced since Saturday by hundreds of police and India's paramilitary Central Reserve Police Force ( CRPF) personnel in curfew bound areas of Bandipora district, about 40 km north of Srinagar. "The contingents of CRPF and police remain deployed in Bandipora town, Hajin and Naidkhai areas,"said a police official. "The restrictions have been put in place to maintain law and order and prevent the situation from deteriorating."
A police spokesman said stone pelting took place at Hajin and Naidkhai in Bandipora on Monday.
The restrictions were immediately imposed after the killing of 21-year-old youth Farhat Ahmad Dar on Friday allegedly in police firing at village Naidkhai of Bandipora. The people in curfew bound areas were complaining about lack of essentials and not being allowed to move out of their houses by the government forces. "We are facing dearth of essentials, especially milk, bread and vegetables, due to restrictions,"said Tariq Ahmad, a local, over telephone."We have been confined to our houses."
However, life in Srinagar city, the summer capital of Indian- controlled Kashmir, returned to normal after two days on Monday with authorities lifting restrictions on old city thereby allowing opening of businesses and vehicular traffic.
The killing evoked widespread condemnation from separatist groups and pro-India parties.
The local government in Indian-controlled Kashmir has ordered a magisterial probe into the killing.
Meanwhile, the moderate faction of Hurriyat (freedom) Conference headed by Mirwaiz Umar Farooq has filed a petition with State Human Rights Commission (SHRC) seeking action against the policemen involved in killing of the youth.
Anti-India sentiment runs deep in psyche of residents across Indian-controlled Kashmir. Residents in the restive region took to roads to show resistance by hurling brickbats and stones on contingents of police and CRPF personnel. The government forces respond by tear smoke shells and bullets, which often proves fatal.
A separatist movement challenging New Delhi's rule has been going on in Indian-controlled Kashmir since 1989.
]]></text></news-item>