<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-XX31-JCBD-K2KC"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Threat of legal action against mining companies in Myanmar indicates increased risk of contract frustration and operational delays</title><source>IHS Global Insight</source><author>Anton Alifandi</author><text><![CDATA[Villagers in Dawei District said they would sue the Thai and Myanmarese operators of a tin mine later this month, seeking compensation for environmental damage to their farmlands. An American non-governmental organisation (NGO), EarthRights International, said in a media release on 16 March that residents of Myaung Pyo village would file their legal complaint to the Dawei District Court against the owners of the Heinda tin mine, a private Thai company called Myanmar Pongpipat Company and Myanmar's state-owned Mining Enterprise 2. The villagers claim that mud-filled flows out of the mine through creeks and rivers around the village cause floods and loss of farmland, as well as contaminating drinking water. There has been no comment from the mining operators. There have been other environmentally motivated protests against mining and power projects in Myanmar. In November 2012, hundreds of environmentalists, local residents, and monks staged a protest against the Letpadaung copper mine. The protests led to a fight with the police in which approximately 100 people were injured. The USD1-billion project owned by the Myanmar military's investments arm and a Chinese company is now suspended. Similarly in October 2011, President Thein Sein suspended the construction of the Myitsone Dam in Kachin state after violent protests by locals and environmentalists.
Significance:The impending court case brought by Dawei villagers is an indicator of a new channel through which locals will oppose projects they consider environmentally damaging. Myanmar's legal system is generally not considered to be independent. However, over the past two years there have been attempts by opposition leader Aung San Suu Kyi and members of parliament to improve the lower courts' system. The outcome of the Dawei case could be a useful indicator of how Myanmar's court system reacts to complaints against projects supported by the government. If this becomes a trend in the next few years, growing numbers of legal cases could increase the risk of contract frustration and operational delays in the mining sector.
]]></text></news-item>