<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-PVT1-JC3H-02N8"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Radiation level estimates for Ontario site queried</title><source>The Detroit News (Michigan)</source><author>By, Jim Lynch</author><text><![CDATA[The Detroit News
Ontario Power Generation's plans for an underground nuclear storage facility along the shore of Lake Huron have drawn a new detractor - a former employee who is questioning the company's math.
Frank Greening, a former research scientist with the electricity company that provides most of power used in the province of Ontario, recently wrote to Canadian government officials questioning the calculations used to determine the level of radioactivity in materials that would be housed in the deep geologic repository near Kincardine. The location is roughly 55 miles across the water from Michigan's Port Hope in Huron County.
In his letter, Greening refers to several studies offered by Ontario Power to support the facility as a permanent home for low- to mid-level wastes.
"What is notable about these tables is the fact that much of the data are not based on direct measurements at all but rather on 'scaling factors, used fuel ratios and neutron activation calculations,'" he wrote in a letter dated Jan. 6. "Indeed, none of the data for pressure tubes, end fittings and calandria tubes is based on direct measurements and only a handful of radionuclides are reported to have been directly measured for steam generator waste."
Greening's criticisms are being taken under consideration by Ontario Power officials, according to company spokesman Ted Gruetzner.
"Some of the points we think may have some validity, and some we think may be based on outdated information," he said.
Even if Greening's points prove valid, Gruetzner said the project would still fall well within safe operating parameters.
The deep geologic repository has been an issue of contention for many years. Ontario Power is seeking approval to bury nuclear wastes in the limestone and shale 2,230 feet below the surface near Kincardine, and roughly three-quarters of a mile from Lake Huron.
U.S. officials have been struggling to make their reservations about the project known.
The letter from Greening has adds to their concern.
"It seems like OPG has been a little bit loose in regard to this whole situation - this issue of burying nuclear waste next to the Great Lakes," said state Sen. Honn-Yung Hopgood, D-Taylor.
Hopgood said he and other elected officials are keeping a close eye on the approval process in Ontario. On April 4, Ontario Power is expected to submit all of its research and public comment documentation to the Canadian Nuclear Safety Commission's Joint Review Panel. At some point this spring, the panel will close the public comment period and have three months to compile its report.
Once the panel submits its report, the Ministry of the Environment has four months to approve or reject the deep geologic repository proposal.
jlynch@detroitnews.com
(313) 222-2034
]]></text></news-item>