<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-PJ91-F0NV-F3SD"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Companies to spend estimated $200M to reduce water pollution</title><source>Herald-Standard (Uniontown, Pennsylvania)</source><author>Miles Layton, JMLAYTON@HERALDSTANDARD.COM</author><text><![CDATA[U.S. Environmental Protection Agency said the money will be used to reduce discharges of pollution from coal mines in Pennsylvania, Kentucky, Virginia, Tennessee and West Virginia.
United Mine Workers of America says a $200 million legal settlement will improve the environment in areas at risk for water contamination.
U.S. Environmental Protection Agency said the money will be used to reduce discharges of pollution from coal mines in Pennsylvania, Kentucky, Virginia, Tennessee and West Virginia.
Alpha Natural Resources, Inc. (Alpha), one of the nation 's largest coal companies, Alpha Appalachian Holdings (formerly Massey Energy) and 66 subsidiaries have agreed to spend an estimated $200 million to install and operate wastewater treatment systems and to implement comprehensive and system-wide upgrades.
Overall, the settlement covers approximately 79 active mines and 25 processing plants in these five states.
The United Mine Workers of America (UMWA) supports Alpha's moves toward a better environment.
"The investments Alpha and its subsidiaries are making are sizable ones that will help combat these water issues," said UMWA spokesman Phil Smith. "The UMWA has always believed that mining companies should operate in a manner that makes them good neighbors. Our members live in the coalfields; they want a safe environment for their families just like everyone else."
EPA estimates that the upgrades and advanced treatment required by the settlement will reduce discharges of total dissolved solids by over 36 million pounds each year and will cut metals and other pollutants by approximately nine million pounds per year.
The companies will also pay a civil penalty of $27.5 million for thousands of permit violations, which is the largest penalty in history under Section 402 of the Clean Water Act (CWA).
"This settlement is the result of state and federal agencies working together to protect local communities from pollution by enforcing the law," said Cynthia Giles, assistant administrator of EPA's Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance. "By requiring reforms and a robust compliance program, we are helping to ensure coal mining in Appalachia follows environmental laws that protect public health."
CWA permits allow for the discharge of certain pollutants in limited amounts to rivers, streams and other water bodies. Permit holders are required to monitor discharges regularly and report results to the respective state agencies.
The settlement serves as a deterrent to pollution, particularly among at-risk communities susceptible to environmental hazards.
"The unprecedented size of the civil penalty in this settlement sends a strong deterrent message to others in this industry that such egregious violations of the nation's Clean Water Act will not be tolerated," said Robert G. Dreher, acting assistant attorney general for the Justice Department's Environment and Natural Resources Division. "Today's agreement is good news for communities across Appalachia, who have too often been vulnerable to polluters who disregard the law. It holds Alpha accountable and will bring increased compliance and transparency among Alpha and its many subsidiaries."
Alpha, headquartered in Bristol, Va., is one of the largest coal companies in the nation. Alpha operates more than 79 active coal mines and 25 coal preparation plants located throughout Kentucky, Pennsylvania, Tennessee, Virginia, West Virginia and Wyoming.
Smith said the settlement goes a long way toward improving Massey Energy's environmental record.
"We have always said that coal companies need to comply with the law, whether it be with respect to safety, workers' rights, the environment or any other laws," Smith said. "When they don't, they need to be held accountable. It appears that much of the issues related to this particular settlement are a legacy left over from the notorious Massey Energy, which Alpha bought almost three years ago. Alpha appears to have made some progress in improving the safety culture at former Massey mines, hopefully it can soon finish cleaning up the other multiple problems it inherited from Massey, including environmental issues."
The settlement resolves violations of a prior 2008 settlement with Massey Energy and applies to the facilities and sites formerly owned by the company. Under the 2008 settlement, Massey paid a $20 million penalty to the federal government for similar CWA violations, in addition to over a million dollars in stipulated penalties over the course of the next two years. Alpha purchased Massey in June 2011 and, since taking over the company, has been working cooperatively with the government in developing the terms of today's settlement.
The states of West Virginia, Pennsylvania and Kentucky are co-plaintiffs in today's settlement. The U.S. will receive half of the civil penalty and the other half will be divided between the co-plaintiffs based on the number of violations in each state, as follows: West Virginia ($8,937,500), Pennsylvania ($4,125,000) and Kentucky ($687,500).
]]></text></news-item>