<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-C8F1-JB1X-W0X3"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>SECMC's tender for open lignite mine in Thar Block-II: exemption granted is a violation of rules: TI Pakistan</title><source>Business Recorder</source><author> IQBAL MIRZA</author><text><![CDATA[It has been observed that public procurement rules, which are effective check against corrupt practices, are being tossed around and interpreted by departments and ministries to suit their requirements to escape corruption. The latest example is that of the "exemption from Sindh Public Procurement Rules and Sindh Sales Tax on Services for Sindh Engro Coal Mining Company (Pvt) Ltd (SECMC)," granted by the Chief Minister of Sindh.
Chairman, Transparency International, Sohail Muzaffar, in a letter sent to the Director General Sindh Coal Authority (SCA) on March 10 has pointed out that the exemption granted in the case of SCA's tender for development and construction of an open lignite mine in Thar Block-II is a violation of Section 33 B of National Accountability Bureau Ordinance 1999.
In its letter sent on January 30, TI-Pakistan has objected that the tender issued by Sindh Engro Coal Mining Company on April 4, 2013, and the exemption to Sindh Engro Coal Mining Company by Chief Minister on February 27, 2014 cannot be applied on procurements made by SECMC prior to the exemption.
Sohail Muzaffar said: "kindly note that Chief Minister cannot grant exemption from NAB Ordinance 1999, and according to National Accountability Ordinance 1999, copies of all contracts awarded in which government funds are involved, of above Rs 50 million, are to be sent to NAB, along with contract evaluation form".
He has requested the SCA to inform Sindh Engro Coal Mining Company to follow Sindh Public Procurement Rules 2010 in all procurements, till February 27, 2014, and also to send copies of all contracts awarded in which government funds are involved, of above Rs 50 million, are to be sent to NAB, along with contract evaluation form.
The Energy Department, Government of Sindh along with its letter sent on February 27, 2014 to the Secretary (Implementation) Services, General Administration and Co-ordination Department,
Government of Sindh had forwarded a copy of Energy Department's summary on the subject and had stated that "Sindh Engro Coal Mining Company is a private limited company with 51 percent shares held by the Government of Sindh and 49 percent by Engro Corporation. The request of SECMC for exemption as per Clause 2(1) of Sindh Public Procurement (Amendment) Bill, 2013 of February 13, 2013 as well as exemption from Schedule-2 of Sindh Sales Tax on Services has been approved by the Chief Minister Sindh during the currency of majority share holding by the Government of Sindh."
In order to implement the decision, it was further requested that "necessary notification for exemption as per Clause 2(1) of Sindh Public Procurement (Amendment) Bill, 2013 and exemption from Schedule-2 of Sindh Sales Tax on Services for Sindh Engro Coal Mining Company may please be issued at the earliest."
]]></text></news-item>