<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-6841-DY2T-C0JX"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Firm pays millions to World Cup boss, family: report</title><source>The Gazette (Montreal)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A senior FIFA official and his family were paid almost $2 million U.S. from a Qatari firm linked to the country's successful bid for the 2022 World Cup, The Daily Telegraph disclosed Monday.
Jack Warner, the former vice-president of FIFA, appears to have been personally paid $1.2 million from a company controlled by a former Qatari soccer official shortly after the decision to award the country the tournament.
Payments totalling almost $750,000 were made to Warner's sons, documents show. A further $400,000 was paid to one of his employees.
It is understood the FBI is now investigating Trinidad based Warner and his alleged links to the Qatari bid and that the former FIFA official's eldest son, who lives in Miami, has been helping the inquiry as a co-operating witness.
The awarding of the 2022 World Cup to Qatar was one of the most controversial decisions in sports history. The intense summer heat in the desert nation has raised the prospect of the tournament being moved to the winter for the first time.
Although Qatar has repeatedly denied wrongdoing during the bidding process, it has long been suspected that the decision was flawed and several members of the FIFA committee have faced corruption allegations.
It can now be disclosed a company owned by Mohamed Bin Hammam, the FIFA executive member for Qatar, appeared to pay $1.2 million to Warner in 2011. A note from one of Warner's companies, Jamad, to Bin Hammam's firm, Kemco, requested $1.2 million in payment for work carried out between 2005 and 2010. The document is dated Dec. 15, 2010, two weeks after Qatar won the right to host the tournament and states that the money is "payable to Jack Warner." Warner's two sons and an employee were paid a further $1 million by the same Qatari company.
One document states that payments are to "off set legal and other expenses," but a separate letter claims that more than $1 million covers "professional services provided over the period 2005-2010." At least one bank in the Cayman Islands initially refused to process the payment amid fears over the legality of the money transfer. The money was eventually processed via a bank in New York - a transaction that is understood to have come to the attention of the FBI. A well-placed source said: "These payments need to be properly investigated. The World Cup is the most important event in football and we need to be confident that decisions have been made for the right reasons. There are lots of questions that still need to be answered."
]]></text></news-item>