<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-PVT1-JC3H-0362"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>DEQ, company sued over copper exploration permit</title><source>Great Falls Tribune (Montana)</source><author>By, Karl Puckett</author><text><![CDATA[Two environmental groups filed a lawsuit Friday against the Montana Department of Environmental Quality and a company proposing to explore for copper in Meagher County, arguing the state's analysis of potential environmental impacts was flawed violating state laws and the Montana Constitution.
Tintina Resources Inc. defended the environmental analysis, and said the lawsuit likely will lead to delays in the exploration work.
Proposed mining exploration activities at the headwaters of Montana's Smith River 15 miles north of White Sulphur Springs threaten to degrade water and further strain already low stream flows, according to the lawsuit, filed by the Montana Environmental Information Center and Earthworks.
It is supported by Mike Geary of Lewis and Clark Expeditions, the largest outfitter on the Smith River.
"I guess the main thing is, 'How do you dig a hole that far in the ground in a super fragile system and not do any damage?" Geary said.
The Black Butte Mine Project is proposed near Sheep Creek, a tributary of the Smith River and a popular fishery and floating destination. The project has sparked opposition from environmental and angling groups about potential acid-mine drainage and dewatering, but others support the project, arguing it will bring economic development to the area without harming the environment.
A mine has not been approved.
But Tintina Resources Inc. plans to construct an 18-foot-high by 18-foot-wide, mile-long underground exploration tunnel to produce a 10,000-ton bulk sample of rock for testing.
In November 2012, Tintina requested an exploration license amendment to expand underground exploration activities on the project. The DEQ received 4,430 responses from the public on the project before approving the work in January with 16 modifications that agency officials said would ensure no significant harm would come to surface or groundwater.
The lawsuit takes issue with the DEQ's environmental analysis and asks that the court remand the final environmental assessment back to the agency for additional analysis and void approval of the exploration.
"Montanans and the wildlife who depend on pristine water quality and adequate flows in the Smith River deserve no less than the full protections afforded by these laws," Jenny Harbine, an attorney with Earthjustice, which is representing Earthworks, said in a statement.
Montana's laws and constitution prohibit the state from "blindly authorizing potentially destructive activities," she said.
Chris Saeger, a DEQ spokesman, declined to comment on allegations in the lawsuit.
"I can confirm that DEQ attorneys are reviewing the suit," Saeger said. "We are continuing to work on establishing the proper bond amount for this project."
Jerry Zieg, Tintina's vice president of exploration, said the DEQ did an exhaustive job analyzing the exploration permit and the company is equally concerned about keeping water quality in the basin pristine. Zieg, a former White Sulphur Spring resident, said the region has had a tough time of it economically in recent years and the mine, if developed, will bring good-paying jobs to the area.
"We hate to see that opportunity delayed for everyone there, too," Zieg said.
Work hasn't started yet, but the lawsuit likely will lead to some delay, he said.
If the mine is developed, it would employee 200, with life expected to be 11 to 14 years with an estimated 11.8 million tons of copper-bearing material mined, according to an economic assessment for the project by Vancouver-based Tetra Tech.
The proposed Black Butte Copper Project is located on the banks of Sheep Creek, a major tributary of the Smith River. The Sheep Creek drainage accounts for over half of the tributary spawning for rainbow trout in the Smith River drainage, and is a critical source of water for the Smith's frequently low in-stream flows, the lawsuit says.
Dewatering of the mine required during the exploration threatens to exacerbate low-stream flow conditions, the lawsuit says. It also says that chemicals could be introduced into the surface and groundwater during exploration. DEQ's failure to adequately assess the environmental impacts, the lawsuit alleges, is a violation of the Montana Environmental Policy Act.
The lawsuit also alleges that DEQ's conclusion that the watershed will not be affected by mine dewatering is based on insufficient analysis. It says a more stringent environmental impact statement should have been conducted. And it says Tintina's exploration plan of operations lacked sufficient details to allow DEQ to assess the potential impacts to surface waters.
It also says the DEQ violated the Water Quality Act by failing to require a non-degradation review.
]]></text></news-item>