<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-PK61-JD6S-R48N"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Tonawanda Coke to fund community service project</title><source>Tonawanda News (New York)</source><author>Jessica Bagley, THE TONAWANDA NEWS</author><text><![CDATA[Tonawanda News - Chief U.S. District Judge William Skretny will require Tonawanda Coke to fund a community service project despite the plant's objection, the court's presentence decision states.
"This court fully intends to impose, as a term of Tonawanda Coke's probation, a requirement that this defendant fund one or more of the proposed evaluative projects recommended by the community," the decision, which was filed Friday afternoon, states.
Last year, a federal jury found the plant and its environmental manager Mark Kamholz guilty of violating the Clean Air Act and the Resource Recovery and Conservation Act. They face more than $200 million in fines and 75 years in prison when they are sentenced at 10 a.m. Wednesday.
Since the verdict was delivered, residents and environmental organizations have been pushing to keep those fines local, and U.S. prosecutors have requested that the plant fund nearly $12.8 million in community service projects as part of its sentence.
The list of recommended projects include an $11.4 million study on the health effects and coke oven emissions from Tonawanda Coke, a $700,000 air and soil testing project, an industrial pollution prevention initiative, a citizen science lending library, a toxic education project and a tree planting program.
In its decision, the court stated that an evaluative project would aid the community in determining the plant's impact.
"The court therefore finds that, just as a requirement that a defendant remediate the physical result of its conduct is appropriate, a term of probation obligating Tonawanda Coke to help community members understand the effects - or lack thereof - of the pollutants to which they have been exposed is also appropriate," the decision states.
The document also includes Skretny's rejection of prosecutors' request that residents be classified under victims of Tonawanda Coke's crimes pursuant to the Crime Victims' Rights Act. The designation would have given victims the opportunity to speak at sentencing and the right to restitution for harm caused by Tonawanda Coke.
Although the court recognized that the case is extremely important to the local community, Skretny stated that the process of evaluating each victims' factual case would be cumbersome. The questions raised during the hearing would also be very similar to the issues discussed in the 20 pending civil cases against Tonawanda Coke, and the federal court's involvement could adversely affect those cases, the decision states.
Skretny also stated that the community members, who won't be permitted to speak at sentencing, have still had an opportunity to have their voices heard. He noted that 581 residents selected service projects at the Clean Air Coalition voting events, and said he has also received 160 victim impact statements.
"Accordingly, the court is confident that the voices of those affected and those that would potentially be affected by the present sentencing will be heard without any undue delay of sentencing itself," the decision states.
Community leaders said they were pleased that the residents will receive closure at sentencing on Wednesday.
"We are very excited to see what the final decision will be," Clean Air Coalition Director Erin Heaney said. "It was encouraging to see him mention our participatory budgeting process - when the residents voted on what projects should be funded - and that makes me hopeful that some of the projects will be part of the sentencing."
Citizen Science Community Resources founder Jackie James-Creedon said she was disappointed by the judge's decision regarding the Crime Victims' Rights Act, but said she is hopeful that sentencing will provide justice.
"I feel like our voices as a community need to be heard, and they won't be heard on Wednesday," she said. "But we still have an opportunity when the civil cases come to fruition. We have to wait until we get our day in court, and it's important that this gets resolved and it doesn't get delayed anymore.
Contact reporter Jessica Bagley at 693-1000 ext. 4150, or follow her on Twitter @JessicaLBagley.
]]></text></news-item>