<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-P8D1-JCBG-G2KY"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Balkans" suspected drug lord arrested</title><source>The New Zealand Herald</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[BELGRADE, Serbia (AP) The most wanted suspected drug lord in the Balkans, who was accused of organizing an attempted transfer of about 2.7 tons of cocaine from South America to Europe, has been arrested, Serbian authorities said Tuesday.
The Serbian government said Darko Saric was captured, but did not say when or where. Serbian state TV said that he was arrested Tuesday in a joint action by police in Serbia and neighboring Montenegro.
"Drug lord Darko Saric has been taken to the Special Court for interrogation," the Belgrade court"s spokeswoman, Dusica Ristic, told state Tanjug news agency.
Saric has been on the run since October 2009 when the smuggling operation which he allegedly led was disrupted near the Uruguayan coast in an international police action that included U.S. Drug Enforcement Administration agents.
The Balkan countries are one of the main drug smuggling transit routes toward western Europe.
Saric, 44, has been charged in Serbia with drug smuggling and money laundering. Several of his alleged gang members are standing trial in Belgrade on same charges while several others are on the run.
The Serbian authorities accuse Saric of leading a powerful Balkan criminal organization which was involved in cocaine trafficking from Columbia, Argentina and Uruguay through the Balkan countries to western Europe. The group allegedly profited by billions of euros from the smuggling.
Saric, of Montenegrin origin, allegedly laundered the money by investing in privatization of state companies and hotels in Serbia and Montenegro. Much of his property, including luxurious houses and apartments in Belgrade, has been impounded by Serbian authorities since his disappearance.
Serbia had previously accused Montenegro of refusing to hand over Saric because of his alleged links with Montenegrin top officials.
___
AP reporter Jovana Gec contributed.
]]></text></news-item>