<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-P321-JB4F-Y1TJ"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Future Retail Limited keeps sliding: down 3.5% in 3 days</title><source>Indian Company News Bites - Stock Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[STOCK REPORT
Future Retail Limited (NSE:FRL), India's 3rd largest department store company by market capitalisation, extended its slide Tuesday, shedding an additional Rs0.10 (or 0.1%) to close at Rs79.70. The shares have dropped Rs2.85 (or 3.5%) over the past three trading days. Compared with the BSE Sensex Index which fell 23.6 points (or 0.11%) in the three days, this represented a relative price change of -3.3%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Future Retail Limited, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051141660314596
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- The Moving Average Convergence Divergence (MACD) indicator of 12-day Exponential Moving Average (EMA) of 81.12 minus the 26-day EMA of 81.26 is negative 0.15 suggesting a bearish signal. Both EMA prices are falling, another bearish signal.- The present value of Rs1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Future Retail Limited is Rs447, including a capital loss of Rs556 and dividend reinvested of Rs3.

Bullish SignalsOversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The stock is oversold according to the Williams % R indicator of -85.5, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day low of Rs78.60.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Earnings of 6.2 [24.2]. - Price to Book of 0.6 [1.4]. - Return on Equity 8.3% [4.5%].- Return on Assets 1.8% [1.2%].- Return on Capital Employed 23.1% [18.6%].- Dividend yield of 1.4% [1.1%].- Price to EBITDA of 0.6 [1.7].Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 3.7 is comfortably below 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The P/E of 6.2 multiplied by the P/NTA of 0.6 is 3.4. Being less than the Benjamin Graham benchmark of 22.5 the stock appears undervalued. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 11.7%. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.1. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued and ranks in the top 5% of stock by value of Q Ratio.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity of 8.3% is better than sector average of 4.5%. This is computed as net profit margin of 1.4% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 1.4 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 4.5.
Note- Future Retail Limited is at a discount of 56.3% to its 12-month high of Rs182.50 on 15 Mar, 2013. It is also at a premium of 26.5% to the 12-month low of Rs63.0 on 01 Aug, 2013.
AGGREGATE VOLUMES, PRICES AND TURNOVER PERIOD [Volume Index or VI in brackets; 1 is average] NSE: FRL.NSE 617,963 [VI of 0.1] volume 76.7% of aggregate. Price: Rs79.70. BSE: 523574.BSE 187,729 [VI of 0.2] volume 23.3% of aggregate. Day trader volume: 20.1% for the day; 78.6% for the trailing week and 83.4% for the trailing month. Price: Rs79.55. Aggregate volume: there were 805,692 shares of Future Retail Limited worth Rs64.4 million traded. The aggregate volume was 0.2 times average trading of 5.2 million shares.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 11: Future Retail: Announces Q4 results & Limited Review Report for the Quarter ended December 31, 2013[News Story] Future Retail Ltd has announced the following Unaudited results for the quarter ended December 31, 2013:The Company has posted a net profit of Rs. 217.40 million for the quarter ended December 31, 2013 where as the same was at net loss of Rs. (204.10) million for the quarter ended December 31, 2012.
January 31: Future Retail: Occurrence of Fire in one of the Warehouse of the Future Supply Chain Solutions Limited (FSCSL), subsidiary of the Company[News Story] Future Retail Ltd has informed BSE that a major fire occurred on January 30, 2014 evening in one of the warehouse of the FSCSL situated at Jigni, Bengaluru. The fire was controlled after few hours. Further, in addition to inventory of other customers of FSCSL inventory of the Company as also/that of Company's wholly-owned subsidiary Future Value Retail Limited (FVRL), was also damaged in the fire.
December 31: Future Retail: Notice of Postal Ballot[News Story] Future Retail Ltd has informed BSE that the members of the Company will consider to approve the resolutions, by way of Postal Ballot.http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/India/Stock/News/3720549.pdfSource: Bombay Stock Exchange of India
December 20: Future Retail Limited director buys; shares at a seven-month lowFuture Retail Limited (NSE:FRL) director PIL Industries Limited bought 72,166 shares worth approximately Rs4,770,173 on December 17, 2013. PIL Industries Limited previously held 13,423,327 shares and now holds 13,495,493 shares. The purchase price was Rs66.10. The shares hit a seven-month low on the day.
December 17: Future Retail: Updates[News Story] With reference to the earlier announcement dated March 08, 2013 wherein the Company had informed that Industrial Investment Trust Limited ("IITL") had, inter alia, entered into Share Purchase Agreement ("SPA") with Future Retail Limited (formerly known as Pantaloon Retail (India) Limited) ("FRL") to acquire part of FRL's shareholding in Future Generali India Life Insurance Company Limited ("FGILICL") representing 22.5% of the equity share capital of FGLICL on the terms and conditions more particularly contained in the SPA, subject to the receipt of the necessary approvals from governmental and regulatory authorities, Future Retail Ltd has now informed BSE that pursuant to receipt of the necessary approvals from governmental and regulatory authorities, namely CCI, IRDA and RBI, the said transaction has been consummated on December 17, 2013.
December 12: Future Retail: Extension of Financial YearFuture Retail Limited has informed the Exchange that the Board of Directors have passed a resolution by circulation for extending the financial period of the Company by three months from December 31, 2013 to March 31, 2014. Accordingly, the current financial period shall be a period of 15 months beginning from January 01, 2013 and ending on March 31, 2014.
November 02: Future Retail Limited CFO resignsFuture Retail Limited C. P. Toshniwal,CFO has resigned. The effective date is October 31, 2013.
ISIN: INE623B01027
NSE:FRL; BSE:FRL; NS:FRL; IN:FRL
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>