<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-YF01-DXH0-K26H"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Landfill fire spreads 'dangerous' gases</title><source>The Bangkok Post (Thailand)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[More than 200 residents were forced to flee after a Sunday blaze in Samut Prakan province engulfed vast areas of landfill and spread harmful pollution.
Thick smoke engulfs a landfill site in Samut Prakan's tambon Phraeksa. The fire started about noon on Sunday and was still smouldering yesterday. The photo was taken from a remote-controlled helicopter-mounted camera. SITHIKORN WONGWUDTHIANUN
It took firefighters 20 hours to bring the fire under control but they failed yesterday to completely put it out and around 200 people from a nearby community left their homes for safety.
The fire started about noon on Sunday and firemen and more than 20 fire trucks rushed to the landfill site, covering over 100 rai, in tambon Phraeksa in Muang district.
Authorities from various units are currently struggling to control the damage and are providing help to residents whose neighbourhood has been declared a "disaster zone," according to Samut Prakan governor Khanit Iamrahong.
The declaration followed the detection of harmful levels of sulphur dioxide in the air.
Residents living near a burning landfill cover their mouths and noses with masks as they flee to safety after thick smoke engulfed their community. SOMCHAI POOMLARD
Wichien Jungrungruang, chief of the Department of Pollution Control, said the level of sulphur dioxide was high at 8-10 parts per million (ppm) within a 300 metre radius of the landfill. The level drops to 2-4 ppm outside a one kilometre radius from the fire site. The safety standard for sulphur dioxide is a ppm level under 0.75.
Meanwhile, the level of carbon monoxide in the air is quite high, but did not exceed the safety standard. The level of carbon-monoxide is at 12 ppm, compared with the safety standard of under 27 ppm.
He suggested people close to the scene should wear a mask or put a wet cloth over their noses to prevent toxic air from entering the body.
The amount of sulphur dioxide and carbon monoxide will immediately drop to safe levels if the fire is extinguished, Mr Wichien said.
The department suggested people living within 1.5km of the landfill evacuate to a safer place. There are at least six communities nearby that could be affected by the pollution.
Since Sunday night a large number of residents were evacuated to the auditorium of the Phraeksa Tambon Administration Organisation (TAO) while others chose to stay at relatives' homes.
The voluntary evacuation followed pollution and foul odours in the air as well as the risk that homes might catch fire after flames from the landfill, located in Soi Bang Pu Industrial Estate 8, quickly spread and, according to witnesses, the fire was reportedly just 50 metres away from some homes.
Rattana Srivichai, an officer at the Phraeksa TAO, said around 200 people took shelter at Phraeksa TAO on Sunday night. However, many people left for work and returned to their homes yesterday afternoon after the situation improved, thanks to many agencies tackling the crisis together.
''The situation was critical late on Sunday when thick smoke and pungent smells widely covered the community near the landfill,'' she said.
Many people choked. They needed immediate evacuation, said Phraithun Maisankrang, leader of the Moo 4 Phraeksa community as he helped villagers find safer places yesterday.
The pollution spread across at least four districts in Bangkok - Bang Na, Saphan Sung, Lat Krabang, and Prawet, said Somchai Chatsakulpen, deputy director of the Bangkok Metropolitan Administration's Department of the Environment.
A female employee of a company near the fifth km on Bang Na-Trat Road said the smell was like "burning plastic" and was very strong in the morning yesterday. It improved in the afternoon.
Mr Khanit said authorities are investigating the fire's origin, but initially, they suspected hot weather, currently affecting many areas in Bangkok and nearby provinces including Samut Prakan.
Perhaps, the weather might cause methane gas to ''combust'' naturally and ignite piles of garbage, Mr Khanit said.
The landfill site is old and its usage has been banned for a long time, according to an investigation. However, officials found there has been illegal dumping there.
]]></text></news-item>