<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-WDV1-F0JP-W3PT"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>NBN spending `may bite users'</title><source>The Australian</source><author>ANNABEL HEPWORTH</author><text><![CDATA[CONSUMERS could foot the bill for ``undisciplined and excessive'' spending on the National Broadband Network, the nation's second-biggest telco has warned.
In a submission to the Coalition's cost-benefit analysis of the $41 billion project, Optus says the NBN Co's pricing structure -- which includes a usage charge -- is likely to lead to ``significant'' price increases, reversing the recent trend of falling prices.
The submission to a panel chaired by Michael Vertigan points to recent revelations by NBN Co executive chairman Ziggy Switkowski that the total government investment into the NBN Co was approaching $7bn for 3 per cent of the build.
Under the ``current self-policing regulatory regime'', the NBN Co could recover ``all these costs'' from internet services providers and thus end-users, the submission says. ``There are signs that at least some of NBN Co's expenditure has been undisciplined and excessive, yet the regulatory arrangements will enable it to recover that expenditure.''
The comments come as submissions to the cost-benefit analysis -- ordered to give independent advice on fast broadband -- renew debate about key planks of broadband policy.
The Australian revealed yesterday that the competition watchdog has pushed for the scrapping of internal cross-subsidies for the rural rollout of the NBN through the prices that urban consumers pay. The Australian Competition and Consumer Commission says other operators should ``generally'' be able to build broadband networks and compete with the NBN Co as this could drive down prices for consumers. TPG Telecom -- which plans to deploy fibre-to-the-building to 500,000 urban premises -- has entered the fray, insisting in its submission to the Vertigan panel that infrastructure-based competition ``delivers the best outcome to end users''.
``The NBN was not intended to be a fixed-line monopoly and it should not be a fixed-line monopoly,'' TPG's submission says.
Last week, Dr Switkowski warned that the economics of the NBN could be undermined if companies including Telstra and TPG were able to cherry-pick customers in lucrative apartment blocks. Communications Minister Malcolm Turnbull last month indicated that the Vertigan committee would examine the legality of TPG's plan.
TPG says in its submission that the NBN Co's business case is not threatened significantly by infrastructure-based competitors investing their own capital and working within laws introduced under Labor that allow some expansion of superfast networks in place prior to 2011.
]]></text></news-item>