<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-P311-JB4F-Y4B2"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Zicom Electronic Security Systems keeps sliding: down 6.3% in 4 days</title><source>Indian Company News Bites - Stock Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[STOCK REPORT
Zicom Electronic Security Systems Limited (NSE:ZICOM), India's 2nd largest electronic components company by market capitalisation, extended its slide Tuesday, shedding an additional Rs1.65 (or 2.9%) to close at Rs56.10. The shares have tumbled Rs3.75 (or 6.3%) over the past four trading days. Compared with the BSE Sensex Index which rose 6.2 points (or 0.03%) in the four days, this represented a relative price change of -6.3%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Zicom Electronic Security Systems, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051141660314919
Bearish SignalsSignificant Downtrend- The stock continues its significant downtrend.- The stock dropped on weak volume falling for a fourth consecutive day.- The stock dropped 2.9% on high volatility today.- The stock dropped to a five-month low.- The stock's relative price strength percentile is slipping at 60 for 6 months, 18 for 3 months and 13 for 1 month.- The Moving Average Convergence Divergence (MACD) indicator of 12-day Exponential Moving Average (EMA) of 59.28 minus the 26-day EMA of 61.14 is negative 1.86 suggesting a bearish signal. Both EMA prices are falling, another bearish signal.- The price tumbled 6.6% in the last week and plummeted 12.6% in the last month.- The present value of Rs1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Zicom Electronic Security Systems is Rs744, including a capital loss of Rs271 and dividend reinvested of Rs16.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price to Book of 0.6 [0.5].Other Bearish Signals:- Net profit margin has averaged 5.5% in the last 3 years. This is lower than the sector average of 7.2% and suggests a low margin of safety.
Bullish SignalsOversold/Bullish/Support Signals- At Rs56.10 the price is below the lower Bollinger band support of Rs56.16, indicating an upside for it to return to the band. - The Relative Strength Index (RSI) of 24.7 has breached the oversold line of 30, suggesting the price decrease of 11.7% in the last 14 days is unusually high. - The stock is oversold according to the Williams % R indicator of -96.6, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day low of Rs55.80.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Earnings of 2.4 [18.2]. - Price/Sales of 0.1 [0.3]. - Return on Equity 5.3% [2.7%].- Year-on-Year Earnings Growth of 78.9% [48.3%].- Return on Assets 3.3% [1.4%].- Return on Capital Employed 13.7% [5.9%].- Dividend yield of 2.1% [0.8%].- Price to EBITDA of 3.3 [4.2].Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 3.1 is comfortably below 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The P/E of 2.4 multiplied by the P/NTA of 0.6 is 1.6. Being less than the Benjamin Graham benchmark of 22.5 the stock appears undervalued. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 12.6%. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.4. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity is less than stellar at 5.3%. This is computed as net profit margin of 3.0% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 1.1 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 1.6.- Net Profit margin, EBIT margin and EBITDA margin are positive and have seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteBeta: the Beta of Zicom Electronic Security Systems stock is 0.3. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market. - Zicom Electronic Security Systems is at a discount of 40.1% to its 12-month high of Rs93.65 on 17 Apr, 2013. It is also at a premium of 33.9% to the 12-month low of Rs41.90 on 24 Sep, 2013.
AGGREGATE VOLUMES, PRICES AND TURNOVER PERIOD [Volume Index or VI in brackets; 1 is average] NSE: ZICOM.NSE 8,012 [VI of 0.4] volume 51.491% of aggregate. Price: Rs56.10. BSE: 531404.BSE 7,548 [VI of 0.7] volume 48.509% of aggregate. Day trader volume: 90.4% for the day; 2.1% for the trailing week and 14.6% for the trailing month. Price: Rs56.0. Aggregate volume: there were 15,560 shares of Zicom Electronic Security Systems worth Rs881,893 traded. The aggregate volume was 0.5 times average trading of 31,000 shares.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 12: Zicom Electronic Security Systems: Results Press Release[News Story] Zicom Electronic Security Systems Ltd has submitted to BSE a copy of Results Press Release for the period ended December 31, 2013.http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/India/Stock/News/3724611.pdfSource: Bombay Stock Exchange of India
December 05: Zicom Electronic Security Systems substantial shareholder buys; shares at a five-day lowZicom Electronic Security Systems (NSE:ZICOM) substantial shareholder Baronet Properties and Investments Private Limited bought 300,000 shares worth approximately Rs20,055,000 on December 02, 2013. Baronet Properties and Investments Private Limited previously held 1,235,652 shares and now holds 1,535,652 shares (or 8.7%).
December 02: Zicom Electronic Security Systems: Preferential Issue Committee Meeting on Dec 02, 2013[News Story] Zicom Electronic Security Systems Ltd has informed BSE that a meeting of the Preferential Issue Committee of Directors is scheduled to be held on December 02, 2013, inter-aIia, to consider the allotment of Equity Shares to the holders of Warrants against exercise of options attached to the balance 6,00,000 Warrants allotted as above, in accordance with SEBI ICDR Regulations for Preferential Issues.http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/India/Stock/News/3717963.pdfSource: Bombay Stock Exchange of India
December 02: Zicom Electronic Security Systems: Outcome of Preferential Issue Committee Meeting[News Story] Zicom Electronic Security Systems Ltd has informed BSE regarding Outcome of Preferential Issue Committee Meeting held on December 02, 2013.http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/India/Stock/News/3718008.pdfSource: Bombay Stock Exchange of India
September 18: Zicom Electronic Security Systems: Updates on Outcome of AGM[News Story] Zicom Electronic Security Systems Ltd has submitted to BSE a copy of the proceedings of the 19th Annual General Meeting (AGM) of the Company held on August 30, 2013.http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/India/Stock/News/3710644.pdfSource: Bombay Stock Exchange of India
September 02: Zicom Electronic Security Systems: Annual General Meeting Updates[News Story] Zicom Electronic Security Systems Limited has informed the Exchange regarding the outcome of Annual General Meeting held on August 30, 2013.http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/India/Stock/News/3708603.zipSource: National Stock Exchange of India
August 08: Zicom Electronic Security Systems: Results Press Release[News Story] Zicom Electronic Security Systems Ltd has submitted to BSE a copy of Results Press Release for the period ended June 30, 2013.http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/India/Stock/News/3706180.pdfSource: Bombay Stock Exchange of India
ISIN: INE871B01014
NSE:ZICOM; BSE:ZICOM; NS:ZICOM; IN:ZICOM
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>