<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-BT11-JCPJ-W2XR"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Dilworth hotel project gets green light despite opposition</title><source>Charlotte Business Journal</source><author>Susan Stabley</author><text><![CDATA[Charlotte City Council members approved a rezoning request Monday for a 130-room hotel development in Dilworth in a 7-4 vote that included opposition from district representative Patsy Kinsey.
"I just don't think it's an appropriate land use," Kinsey said, adding that other council members should follow their conscience in voting on the proposal.
Only three others - LaWana Mayfield, Claire Fallon and Al Austin - joined her in voting against the project, proposed for a 1.2-acre site at the corner of East Worthington and Cleveland avenues, about a block off South Boulevard.
That's unusual because council members typically vote in accordance with the wishes of a district representative on such issues.
The Rainier Group, an affiliate of real estate investment firm Catellus Group,&nbsp; initially filed a rezoning request in October for a hotel project with 127 rooms. Two months later, the petition was modified to add three more units and to allow valet parking at the site.
Residents have expressed concerns about cut-through traffic generated by the hotel and the potential light pollution caused by the building, which could rise three stories along Cleveland Avenue and five and six stories along Worthington Avenue, according to plans. Access to the hotel will be through a one-way entrance on Cleveland that exits onto Worthington. The hotel would have underground parking.
The site is vacant and outside the boundaries of the Dilworth Historic District.&nbsp;In September, developer Wendy Field&nbsp; opted out of plans to redevelop the tract for up to 33 multifamily units because of concerns of soil contamination.
The city staff and the city zoning committee supported approval of the project.&nbsp;
The rezoning also allows for the hotel to include a restaurant, bar and spa.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Charlotte Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>