<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-PVT1-JC3H-02N7"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Pensions, bond insurer file objections to debt deal</title><source>The Detroit News (Michigan)</source><author>By, Christine Ferretti , and Brian J. O'Connor</author><text><![CDATA[The Detroit News
Detroit - The city's pension funds and a bond insurer were among those filing objections Monday in U.S. Bankruptcy Court to Detroit's proposed plan to end a troubled pension-related debt.
Emergency Manager Kevyn Orr has reached a settlement with two banks - UBS AG and Bank of America - to end interest rate swaps tied to a $1.4 billion debt. At the same time, a lawsuit by the city also seeks to invalidate the 2005-06 pension debt, claiming it was illegal.
Orr's latest settlement calls for the city to pay the banks $85 million. It would save Detroit $201 million and could force other creditors to take $9 billion in cuts in the city's bankruptcy.
Detroit has proposed paying in quarterly installments until the city emerges from bankruptcy. The remaining balance will be paid as part of the city's debt-cutting plan or when the city secures financing.
The city's Police and Fire Retirement System and General Retirement System say that while they aren't opposed to the "economic terms" of the settlement agreement, they don't support the plan because the city pledges its casino tax revenue as collateral, a move they claim is "impermissible" under state law and prohibited by the Gaming Act.
Rhodes has rejected two earlier offers to terminate the swaps. A trial on the latest deal is slated for April 3.
In their filings Monday, the pension boards note that the court previously questioned the validity of the swap counter-parties' liens on gaming tax revenue under the collateral agreement, in light of the Gaming Act.
"It is therefore puzzling that ... the city now seeks to have this court approve a new settlement which again pledges the gaming tax revenue as security for its obligations to the swap counter-parties," the filing reads.
The boards argue instead that income tax revenue could be used to secure the city's obligations under the settlement, if approved.
Orr's spokesman, Bill Nowling, said the city "disagrees with characterizations made by the retirement systems" and will respond through court pleadings.
In addition, Financial Guaranty Insurance Co. filed a response Monday to the city's January lawsuit over the validity of the pension deal.
In 2005, Detroit borrowed $1.44 billion from investors through a financial note called "certificates of participation," or COPs.
Financial Guaranty, the largest single unsecured creditor in the city's bankruptcy, will be on the hook for $1.1 billion if the certificates of participation are invalidated. The insurer wants to join the case, since it will be stuck covering any payment shortfalls to investors in the certificates of participation.
In its filing, Financial Guaranty argues the city was up against the wall in 2005 and 2006, owing nearly $2 billion in constitutionally mandated payments to the pension funds, and that the swaps deal and certificates allowed Detroit to borrow money even when its credit rating was nearing junk status.
The insurer claims Detroit legally set up the structures to market the bonds and certificates, the entire transaction was authorized by city statutes and in obtaining insurance the city repeatedly assured Financial Guarantee that the deal was legal, was backed by the reliable stream of payments from casino taxes and wasn't subject to the city's legal borrowing limits.
Now, after enjoying the benefits of the deals for nine years, the city is engaging in "revisionist history," Financial Guaranty said in the filing.
Now that it's in more financial trouble, Detroit "seeks to turn a crooked eye to history, revising the facts" and "claiming that the city was the innocent victim of fraud perpetrated on a grand scale."
Financial Guaranty's filing adds that similar arguments made in bankruptcy by the city of Harrisburg, Pa., were rejected.
Orr has maintained the deal was "bad for the city" and illegal on claims it exceeded the city's statutory debt limit.
cferretti@detroitnews.com
(313) 222-2069
]]></text></news-item>