<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-67J1-DXMP-K4HB"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>United Spirits trades higher on the bourses; The company is reportedly planning to exit direct operations in three states</title><source>Accord Fintech</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[United Spirits is currently trading at Rs. 2495.05, up by 29.10 points or 1.18% from its previous closing of Rs. 2465.95 on the BSE.
The scrip opened at Rs. 2476.00 and has touched a high and low of Rs. 2499.00 and Rs. 2471.00 respectively. So far 12266 shares were traded on the counter.
The BSE group 'A' stock of face value Rs. 10 has touched a 52 week high of Rs. 2816.35 on 10-Jan-2014 and a 52 week low of Rs. 1708.20 on 05-Apr-2013.
Last one week high and low of the scrip stood at Rs. 2523.75 and Rs. 2441.00 respectively. The current market cap of the company is Rs. 36186.61 crore.
The promoters holding in the company stood at 37.29%, while Institutions and Non-Institutions held 45.83% and 16.44% respectively.
United Spirits (USL), which is majority-owned by global drinks behemoth Diageo, is reportedly planning to exit direct operations (sales, marketing, and manufacturing) from key markets of Kerala, Andhra Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh. This move follows the company's exit from Tamil Nadu late last year, indicates its new owner's (Diageo) concerns about not violating the anti-graft laws in the US and UK.
Diageo is bound by the Foreign Corrupt Practices Act in the US and the UK Bribery Act, which United Spirits is now party to. United Spirits has 21 brands in its portfolio that sell more than a million cases each year or millionaire brands, of which five brands sell more than 10 million cases each annually.
DISCLAIMER: Accord Fintech provides the Content on "AS IS" basis without any express or implied warranties. Accord Fintech does not warrant the accuracy, timeliness, completeness, adequacy, merchantability, or fitness for a particular purpose of the Content, and Accord Fintech shall not be liable to Licensee or to any third party with respect to any actual or alleged inaccuracy, untimeliness, incompleteness, inadequacy, unmerchantbailty or unfitness.
]]></text></news-item>