<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-CX81-JBG7-41R0"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>How China's official bank card is used to smuggle money; Billions of dollars flow out of country using popular UnionPay card for cash-back deals</title><source>Chicago Tribune</source><author>By James Pomfret, Reuters</author><text><![CDATA[Growing numbers of Chinese are using the country's state-backed bank cards to illegally spirit billions of dollars abroad, a Reuters examination has found.
This underground money is flowing across the border and into the gambling hub of Macau, a former Portuguese colony that, like Hong Kong, is an autonomous region of China. And the conduit for the cash is the Chinese government-supported payment card network, China UnionPay.
In a warren of gritty streets around Macau's ritzy casino resorts, hundreds of neon-lit pawnshops and jewelry and watch shops are doing a brisk business giving mainland Chinese customers cash by allowing them to use UnionPay cards to make fake purchases -- a way of evading China's strict currency-export controls.
On a recent day at the Choi Seng jewelry and watch company, a middle-age woman strode to the counter, past dusty shelves of watches. She handed the clerk her UnionPay card and received $50,000 in cash. She signed a receipt describing the transaction as a "general sale," stuffed the cash into her handbag and strolled to the Ponte 16 casino next door.
The withdrawal far exceeded the daily limit of 20,000 yuan, or $3,200, in cash that individual Chinese can legally move out of the mainland.
"Don't worry," said a store clerk when asked about the legality of the transaction. "Everyone does this."
Internal discussion documents prepared by UnionPay and by financial authorities in Macau and China show these fake sale cash-backs are widespread in such retail stores.
The practice violates China's anti-money-laundering regulations as well as restrictions on currency exports, according to Chinese central bank documents reviewed by Reuters. Chinese authorities also fear that the UnionPay conduit is being used by corrupt officials and businesspeople to send money out of the country.
It's unclear why the central bank, the Peoples Bank of China, hasn't cracked down harder on the practice, although the documents Reuters reviewed show the bank was aware it had become a growing problem.
Industry experts point to a weak enforcement culture in China, a reluctance to hurt Macau financially, with 80 percent of the city's revenues drawn from gambling, and a willingness to tolerate some capital flight -- especially if it can be tracked through names on bank cards. Moreover, the rapid growth of UnionPay, including the spread of its terminals at retail stores across the world, is playing a key role in China's strategy for making the yuan a global currency.
No one knows for sure how much Chinese money is being channeled illegally into Macau. Tam Chi Keong, an assistant professor at the Macau University of Science and Technology, puts the total at $202 billion a year through various channels. Tam says his estimate is based on his analysis of Macau's finances and interviews with gambling industry participants.
A senior UnionPay executive said the Shanghai-based company has long been aware of the payment card abuse in Macau and elsewhere but was limited in its ability to act. That's because the primary responsibility lies with authorities in Macau or any other country where the fraud is taking place, he said.
"The problem you are talking about has existed for several years," said the executive, who spoke on condition of anonymity. "We have continuously taken measures."
The government's son
Though relatively unknown in the West, UnionPay has grown to become one of the biggest card brands and payment networks in the world, accepted in 142 countries. There are more UnionPay cards in circulation than any other brand -- 3.53 billion, or nearly one-fourth of the world's total, according to The Nilson Report, an industry newsletter. Visa remains the world leader by transaction value, with $4.6 trillion in card transactions in the first half of 2013; UnionPay was second, with $2.5 trillion.
If UnionPay poses a problem for Chinese authorities, it is a problem of their own making. The card brand is often seen as an arm of Chinese state policy.
UnionPay was established in 2002 by the Peoples Bank of China and the State Council, or the cabinet. Its founding shareholders were 85 Chinese banks, led by the five biggest state-owned banks. Former senior Peoples Bank of China officials still fill the company's top ranks, including UnionPay's chairman, Su Ning, and its former president, Xu Luode. They declined requests to be interviewed.
UnionPay dominates the card market in China because of a central bank decree that requires all card issuers, including foreign ones, to process their yuan-based transactions through UnionPay's electronic payment network.
All Chinese merchants and ATMs are required to process their yuan transactions through UnionPay.
In July 2012, the World Trade Organization ruled that China was discriminating against foreign card brands, but it made no specific recommendations. Foreign card brands still have to use UnionPay for settlements in China.
UnionPay's increasing use overseas is part of Beijing's multipronged strategy to eventually open up China's capital account and internationalize the yuan. Beijing also eased restrictions on many kinds of capital transfers as it gradually loosens control over the currency, making it easier for money to leave China's borders.
The efforts have paid dividends.
The yuan has overtaken the euro to become the second-most-used currency in trade finance, according to data from global transaction services organization Swift.
"(China) may be happy to see UnionPay sweeping different markets across the world in different countries and territories," said Yan Lixin, head of Fudan University's China Center for Anti-Money Laundering Studies in Shanghai. "It is backed up by the government. It is the real son of the government."
Many card users follow their money abroad. Since the mid-1990s, an estimated 16,000 to 18,000 Communist Party officials, businessmen, CEOs and other individuals have "disappeared" from China, according to a separate Peoples Bank of China report prepared in 2008 -- taking with them about 800 billion yuan ($133 billion).
But the practice isn't limited to corrupt officials. The ubiquitous UnionPay card, with its instant access to piles of cash, has made the task of whisking money out of China far easier for ordinary Chinese.
Capital flight
Today, the outflow is gathering pace.
In Macau, UnionPay card transactions reached 130 billion Macau patacas ($16.77 billion) in the first four months of 2012, up from 88.1 billion patacas ($11 billion) in all of 2011, according to a confidential report by Macau's banking regulator, the Macau Monetary Authority, reviewed by Reuters. About 90 percent of those transactions were "highly concentrated in jewelry, ornament and luxury watch sales," the report said.
If that rate persisted for the full year, UnionPay sales in Macau for all of 2012 would have reached nearly $50 billion -- nearly $45 billion of it for jewelry-related sales, a figure exceeding even Macau's total gambling revenues that year.
"Are these actual transactions? Where does this money come from?" the deputy head of the monetary authority, Wan Sin Long, asked in the document.
"Banks have not carried out good monitoring, nor earnestly handled the situation," Wan was cited as saying in the document. "If this continues, this could affect the question of the further opening up of the yuan."
All the counterparties involved benefit from these cash-back transactions, an industry source said.
The retail merchant makes money on the exchange rate, the way a currency trader would.
The Macau banks overseeing the merchant charge 1 to 2 percent on the transaction. And the UnionPay card-issuing bank in China will generally charge about 1 percent on the transaction, the source said.
The cash-back activity is spreading beyond Macau to other Chinese tourist destinations, including Taiwan, Japan and South Korea, people in the credit card industry say.
China isn't standing still. A decade ago, the government began trying to rein in money laundering, and since then it has amended criminal laws and strengthened commercial banking rules.
UnionPay officials say they are trying to stamp out the illicit transfers. One of the main steps the company took came in June 2012, when it required UnionPay card-issuing banks to put a 1 million yuan ($166,000) daily limit on any transaction in Macau, down from 5 million to 10 million yuan. That limit applies to actual sale transactions.
Who is responsible?
In a written response to questions for this article, UnionPay said it "has always strictly prohibited the swiping of cards for cash without any goods being purchased and has collaborated from many sides to boost the investigation of such risks."
According to UnionPay's Operating Regulations, overseas banks participating in the UnionPay system are required to close the accounts of merchants found to be engaged in fraudulent transactions.
But local authorities such as the Macau Monetary Authority have the primary responsibility for investigating suspicious cross-border transactions, the company says.
The Macau Monetary Authority said in a written response that bank card-related businesses in Macau have "been subject to very stringent ongoing supervision."
The authority noted it has "come across a couple of cases of supervisory concerns, and legal proceedings were taken against the parties concerned, including merchants." It didn't elaborate.
Deborah Ng, head of Macau's Financial Intelligence Office, said UnionPay has sought a more active role recently to "take care of whether there are some irregular activities involved."
But the card company can do more, she said. "They need to have some monitoring of abnormally large transactions, (and) frequent transactions from some commercial merchants," Ng said.
No limits
Despite the professed intensity in scrutiny, the practice continues openly.
At a jewelry outlet run by Hong Kong-listed Chow Tai Fook in the Grand Lisboa casino, staff said customers could swipe UnionPay cards to buy gold bullion of up to 10 million yuan ($1.5 million) -- then sell it back for hard cash.
A Chow Tai Fook spokesman confirmed that. He said the store had "no specific limits on the amount that our customers can buy using any form of payment, as long as the payment is approved by the bank when we swipe the card."
At a jewelry store inside the Venetian Macau casino run by Las Vegas Sands, a manager said card cash-backs constituted most of the shop's business. The shop was run by the owner of a VIP room, or "junket" operator, which brings in big gamblers from the mainland.
"I would say there's no upper limit for UnionPay," said the black-suited manager, who spoke on the condition he not be identified. "The credit limits aren't enforced at all." ct14 0066 140318 N S 0000000000 00001560
]]></text></news-item>