<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-VXF1-F0J6-J172"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>ACCC springs an NBN surprise; Chanticleer</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>Tony Boyd</author><text><![CDATA[If Malcolm Turnbull is looking for arguments in favour of killing the National Broadband Network, he got them this week from the competition regulator.
In a submission to the panel of experts conducting an independent cost-benefit analysis of broadband and its regulation, the Australian Competition and Consumer Commission questioned the NBN Co's pricing model, which involves cross-subsidising rural areas with revenue from urban users.
This pricing model has been in place since NBN Co was created five years ago so it will come as a surprise to many that the ACCC is suddenly arguing against it.
Chanticleer cannot find any previous ACCC documents mentioning this hard-line position in relation to cross subsidies. But evidence from sources as noteworthy as McKinsey & Co, shows cross subsidies are far more complex than the ACCC makes out.
The competition regulator says it favours an explicit government subsidy paid directly to rural users rather than cross subsidies within the NBN Co using uniform pricing.
Not only did the ACCC question the core revenue model of the NBN Co, it endorsed a more vigorous and competitive telecommunications market.
It is in favour of non-NBN Co network operators being able to deploy networks in competition with NBN Co.
That is a challenge to one of the most important fundamental principles underpinning the creation of the NBN - a monopoly wholesale network.
Competitors were excluded from the Labor Party's original high-speed broadband plan because of fears rivals would cherry-pick the most profitable areas in the cities and make NBN Co unviable.
But after years of giving its tick of approval to NBN Co's monopoly, the ACCC is now saying it strongly supports infrastructure-based competition.
It claims competition between networks will lead to the more efficient deployment of resources and greater differentiation in downstream services.
The glowing endorsement of facilities based competition must have brought back warm memories for many within the ACCC because it was the core argument used to counter Telstra's dominance in the wake of telco deregulation.
The ACCC followed the lead of governments in Europe which also endorsed facilities-based competition to blunt the power of incumbent telcos and to encourage the roll out of new technologies.
It is noteworthy one of the members of the expert panel appointed by Turnbull to conduct the cost-benefit analysis, Henry Ergas, was employed by Telstra many years ago.
He argued in favour of facilities-based competition but with less regulation of Telstra to encourage it to invest in new services.
In hindsight, the arguments in favour of facilities-based competition put by Ergas and the ACCC did not take account of the impact of digitisation of the copper.
Few realised the old copper wires would gain a second life from digitisation. The advent of ADSL, which morphed ito ADSL 2+ and then ito VDSL, dramatically changed the broadband experience without digging up roads or footpaths.
The real competition occurred inside the exchanges where competitors were allowed to install equipment to run services over Telstra's copper lines.
But this form of competition never really challenged the natural monopoly characteristics in Australia.
The legacy of 17 years of a deregulated market is that Telstra remains the big gorilla with about 60 per cent of all telco revenues, 80 per cent of fixed-line telephone services, about 50 per cent of broadband market share and the leading position in mobiles.
The ACCC's support of facilities-based competition in 2014 comes despite the crazy competitive war between Telstra and Optus over the rollout of hybrid-fibre coaxial cable. That led to HFC being rolled out by both companies past virtually the same premises.
Apart from Ergas, the expert panel includes one of the founders of Australia's telco deregulation, Tony Shaw.
Shaw was a member of the NBN panel of experts who reviewed the competitive tenders for building a fibre to the node network in 2007. That panel decided none of the proposals was in the public interest and the only way an FTTN network would work was with the co-operation of Telstra, which did not put forward a compliant bid.
The panel is led by Michael Vertigan, who holds an honours degree in economics. The ACCC's purest economic arguments in relation to pricing and competition should resonate with him. The other member of the panel is Westpac Banking Corp director Alison Deans.
One final point in relation to the issue of cross subsidies.
A report prepared for the Labor government by McKinsey & Co found that the NBN Co fibre deployment did not actually involve much in the way of cross subsidies.
It found the shape of the fibre deployment cost curve had a gradual slope. In other words, the magnitude of cross subsidy required was manageable. When the subsidy starts to become unmanageable, the satellite and wireless services kick in for the last 7 to 8 per cent of households.
It is one thing for the ACCC to attack cross subsidies. But given the fact that Turnbull's NBN is a mix of different technologies, the regulator should also ask where the subsidies are and what they are.
After all about 30 per cent of households get a high quality broadband service over copper because they live close to the exchange. Those living further from the exchange have a lesser quality service. That is happening in built-up areas which raises the question as to who is subsidising who?
Macquarie Group's decision to sell its fund of funds private equity business in Australia to the fund managers running the unit is a further sign of the fragmentation of financial services ito specialist niche areas.
It fits with the demands of institutional investors who want the people who are managing their money to have skin in the game and not be distracted by the demands of a parent company.
The creation of ROC Equity Partners by a team of Macquarie executives led by Michael Lukin follows similar moves in Australia and overseas.
Most of Australia's leading private equity companies were spun out of larger organisations. Archer Capital came out of Grant Samuel, Ironbridge came out of Gresham Partners, Next Capital used to be Macquarie Direct Investment and Quadrant Private Equity was originally owned by Westpac Banking Corp.
The parent companies have usually been happy to say goodbye to the private equity managers for several reasons.
Westpac did not like the public attention that was attracted by the high salaries paid to its private equity fund managers.
Other owners of private equity businesses did not like the volatility in earnings or were unwilling to make the long-term commitments required for patient investments.
Macquarie is not fussed about losing the 18 people who worked in a division called Macquarie Investment Management Private Markets because its consultancy style model has relatively low margins.
Macquarie has about $350 billion in funds under management and only about $5 billion of that was in the Macquarie private equity division.
Direct private equity investment can earn annual management fees of 2 per cent or 3 per cent and a success fee. But the fund of funds model pursued by Macquarie has annual fees which are tens of basis points.
The trend toward a greater number of discreet private equity fund managers coincides with an increasing allocation of capital by superannuation funds and sovereign wealth funds ito alternative investments.
Private equity fund managers such as ROC Equity Partners can provide better service to their clients if they are focusing on the allocation of money ito fresh investments and not worrying about meeting the goals of a parent company.
The fund of funds private equity model involves choosing the world's best private equity funds and investing alongside the institutions putting their money at risk.
tony.boyd@afr.com.au Twitter @TonyBoydAFR
Tony Boyd
]]></text></news-item>