<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-6851-DY2S-T190"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Fracking opponents point to B.C. gov't policy</title><source>The Vancouver Province (British Columbia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Environmental groups allege the B.C. government is skirting its own laws by allowing energy firms to spend years using large quantities of fresh water for natural gas extraction without having to go through the rigorous process of applying for long-term water licences.
The lawsuit represents the latest attempt by environmental groups to target the controversial practice of hydraulic fracturing, or fracking, which opponents have linked to a litany of problems including water pollution and climate change.
The case is complicated by the fact that recently tabled changes to provincial water laws appear to allow the practice now being scrutinized in court, meaning it's unclear what effect the case could actually have.
The Western Canada Wilderness Committee and the Sierra Club of B.C. were in front of a B.C. Supreme Court judge Monday alleging the government has been "systematically" breaking the law and asking that a series of short-term water approvals granted to Encana be thrown out.
Under provincial water legislation, resource companies that require fresh water for their operations can either apply for a long-term water licence or obtain a short-term approval that lasts up to two years.
The environmentalists' lawyer, Karen Campbell, said the process to obtain a full licence requires that people potentially affected by the licence be notified and permitted to provide input or lodge objections.
Alternatively, the Oil and Gas Commission has the ability to grant short-term approvals on its own.
Campbell said the OGC routinely reissues the same short-term licences, allowing companies to use thousands of cubic metres of water while avoiding the full licensing process.
"What we're looking at is, in effect, each of these approvals ending up being one long approval," Campbell, a lawyer for the group Ecojustice, told court.
Fracking involves injecting a mixture of water, sand and chemicals at high pressure deep underground to break the rock and free the natural gas. The practice is seen as a critical component of B.C.'s push to foster a liquefied natural gas industry.
In a written response filed with the court the government said its officials acted within the law.
]]></text></news-item>