<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-C8F1-JB1X-W3KF"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Joint Rangers-police patrolling of Islamabad soon: Nisar</title><source>The Nation (AsiaNet)</source><author> Our Staff Reporter</author><text><![CDATA[Federal government is all set to release funds for purchase of vehicles, sophisticated arms and other machinery to law enforcement agencies in Islamabad in a bid to make the capital city safe and worth-living.
According to a press note released from office of Minister for Interior and Narcotics Control Chaudhry Nisar Ali Khan on Sunday, a comprehensive strategy has been devised to strengthen security of the capital city.
"Joint patrolling of Rangers and police will start soon to create extra confidence among the citizens of the capital," a press note quoted the minister as saying on Sunday.
Chaudhry Nisar Ali Khan made it loud and clear on Sunday that the federal government would leave no stone unturned to make the capital a safe city.
"Government would provide required funds to purchase vehicles and other stuff needed by the law enforcement agencies. Additionally, it will provide funds to make the 'joint patrolling of Rangers and ICT police' possible in the federal capital. Rangers in the capital have been given extra responsibilities for protecting the life and properties of the people and make capital a safer city," Nisar said on Sunday while chairing a high profile meeting in the premises of Interior Ministry.
During proceedings of the meeting, the minister ordered purchase of new vehicles for patrolling. He also directed the concerned people to hire retired army officers to train the police force on the pattern of Elite Police Force.
"New operational strategy aims to ensure security in the federal capital and will be visible on the streets of the capital from April 15," Nisar was quoted as saying.
Acting Chairman National Database and Registration Authority (Nadra), Director General Federal Investigation Agency (FIA), Commander Rangers and top officials of Islamabad capital territory police attended the meeting.
The minister appreciated performance of FIA and spoke highly of incumbent Director General of Federal Intelligence Agency Ghalib Bandesha. He, however, asked DG FIA to improve its working and directed strict action against the officials including removal from service, the officials involved in facilitating human traffickers.
He also warned that the slightest irregularity would not be tolerated and the officials caught or involved in criminal activities would be arrested and punished.
When asked, high-up of Nadra informed the minister that 12 mobile registration vans had been deployed in Thar for the registration of drought affectees. Due to prudent measures taken - Nadra's net profit increased to Rs 475 million in February as compared to just Rs 18 million in November last year.
He was told that Nadra's sanctioned posts had been reduced to 24 from 36.
The Minister told the participants of meeting that appointment of new chairman NADRA have been referred to the federal commission constituted in the light of Supreme Court's July 2013 decision.
He specified that advertisements for the purpose would be given in both national and international media to attract best talent for such key slot.
]]></text></news-item>