<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-XX31-JCBD-K2HH"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Brazilian president suffers major defeat over investigation into state oil company</title><source>IHS Global Insight</source><author>Juliette Kerr</author><text><![CDATA[A corruption investigation could cause political complications for Brazilian president Dilma Rousseff ahead of the October 2014 election.

President suffers political defeat at hands of allies
Brazil's Senate foreign relations commission voted on 13 March to create a joint commission with the Chamber of Deputies to investigate allegations of improper conduct by Brazilian state oil company Petrobras. This followed a major defeat for President Dilma Rousseff on 11 March in the Chamber of Deputies, when a large majority voted in favour of creating an external commission to investigate allegations that Petrobras officials received improper payments through third parties on behalf of Dutch service company SBM Offshore. Crucially, creating the commission was supported by four parties in the loose governing coalition - the Brazilian Democratic Movement Party (Partido do Movimento Democratico Brasileiro: PMDB), the Republican Party (Partido da Republica: PR), the Brazilian Labour Party (Partido Trabalhista Brasileiro: PTB), and the Social Christian Party (Partido Social Cristao: PSC) - as well as some members of other allied parties.
The allegations centre on claims made by a former employee of SBM Offshore that the company paid USD139 million in bribes to Petrobras officials in return for platform contracts between 2005 and 2011. Petrobras has already launched its own investigation into the allegations. SBM Offshore has also launched an internal investigation into "certain sales practices involving third parties which may have been improper". SBM Offshore said in a press release on 21 February that it has been working with Dutch and US authorities for the last 20 months, and has taken steps to strengthen its compliance procedures. Petrobras also tightened internal controls in 2013, implementing a corruption prevention programme. The external commission is due to travel to Holland to investigate the allegations. It plans to hear testimony from Petrobras's president, Maria das Gracas Silva Foster. If she does not attend, Minister of Energy and Mines Edison Lobâo will be summoned instead.
The government suffered further defeats at the hands of the so-called rebelblocao(or 'large bloc') of allied parties led by the PMDB leader in the Chamber of Deputies, Eduardo Cunha, with the summoning of four government ministers to address various commissions in the lower house and the extension of invitations to six others. The creation of the bloc in early February represented a new low in relations between the presidency and Congress. There are ongoing political problems between the Workers' Party (Partido dos Trabalhadores: PT) and its main ally, the PMDB. The PMDB wants more ministerial seats (it currently holds five) and is frustrated at the slow pace of an ongoing cabinet reshuffle to replace ministers intending to run for political office in the forthcoming election; before last week, only four appointments had been formalised. It is also unhappy over the blockage of spending handouts following the BRL44-billion budget cut announced by the federal government in February. Additionally, there have been divisions at state level over electoral alliances.
There are other indicators of the government's increased vulnerability to pre-election attack over its energy policy. The likely presidential candidate from the Brazilian Socialist Party (Partido Socialista Brasileiro: PSB), Eduardo Campos, has been critical about investment in the electricity sector after a massive blackout left 11 states without power in January. Meanwhile, the PSDB pre-candidate Aecio Neves has claimed that Petrobras and other state entities have been "transformed into instruments in a project of power" rather than serving all Brazilians, and that Petrobras was being "ruined", according to a policy agenda proposal presented in December 2013.
Petrobras is particularly vulnerable to criticism from opposition parties given its close association with the ruling PT. The government has associated itself closely with Petrobras's successes, with President Rousseff and her predecessor Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva frequently attending ceremonies to mark the launch of new projects. The government's economic growth package, known as the PAC, included many of Petrobras's infrastructure projects. Moreover, the company's management has close links with the PT: the two company presidents appointed by the da Silva administration - Jose Eduardo Dutra (2003-05) and Jose Sergio Gabrielli (2005-12) - were both PT members, and the company's current president Gracas Foster is a personal friend of Rousseff. Moreover, as a former minister of energy and mines, Rousseff was instrumental in formulating many of the policies implemented during Lula's government, which remain largely unchanged today.
Outlook and implications
Agreeing to a congressional investigation into the Petrobras allegations could benefit President Rousseff. Political corruption was one of the drivers of nationwide social protests in June 2013, and the recovery in Rousseff's popular approval ratings over the past six months should help to maintain the unity of the coalition. IHS expects the current crisis between the government and its allies in Congress to pass, averting paralysis in the Chamber of Deputies. Indeed, the rebel bloc has weakened already; several opposition parties have already left it, leaving just five members, four of which are allied parties (the PMDB, PR, PTB, and PSC).
Nonetheless, building a political consensus will be more difficult as the election approaches, increasing the likelihood of more key votes being postponed. In that respect, the government will focus on smoothing relations with its most important ally, the PMDB, which is congressionally powerful, while holding five state governorships and the largest number of mayoralties nationally. Rousseff has sought to assuage the PMDB in recent days, offering PT backing for PMDB candidates in six states for the October election. However, there is a risk that the PMDB, emboldened by the government's defeat over the Petrobras investigation, will demand a higher price for its support on upcoming votes. Budget cuts mean the federal government's discretionary spending power is limited. Instead, Rousseff is expected to use further cabinet appointments to help shore up support. Despite these efforts, some departures from the ruling coalition, or at least less fulsome support for the government, are inevitable ahead of the election. For example, the PSC, which initially suggested it would join the opposition ranks said on 12 March that it would now take an "independent" stance on votes, although it was not "breaking" with the government.
Past experience has shown that opening the corruption probe could distract lawmakers from voting on the government's legislative agenda. This is of particular concern in an election year. The window in which to approve proposed legislation before the official election campaign begins in July is relatively narrow. Key pending measures include a new mineral code, tax changes, and a political reform proposal pledged by Rousseff following 2013's protests. The government is now likely to mobilise its supporters in a damage-limitation exercise. Its first task will be to ensure that the external commission, due to be established this week, is dominated by political allies who can limit the remit of the investigation. As the October election draws closer, the investigation will become increasingly politicised.
]]></text></news-item>