<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-VXF1-F0J6-J183"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Sinodinos corruption link</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>Geoff Winestock and Neil Chenoweth</author><text><![CDATA[Assistant Treasurer Arthur Sinodinos was involved in negotiations to sell a $15 million stake in Australian Water Holdings to investors involved in a secret coal venture with the family of corrupt Labor faction leader Eddie Obeid.
Senator Sinodinos, the chairman of Australian Water Holdings, met lawyer John McGuigan on February 25, 2011, to discuss the sale of a stake in the company, according to a diary entry. Chief executive Nick Di Girolamo and Eddie Obeid junior were also present, according to documents tabled at the NSW Independent Commission Against Corruption inquiry on Tuesday.
Mr McGuigan was a director of Cascade Coal, which had the secret joint venture with the Obeids, and was last year found corrupt for concealing the Obeid family's role in obtaining Cascade Coal's coal tenements.
In a letter after the meeting, Mr McGuigan offered to buy 30 per cent of AWH on behalf of a consortium of investors. The purchase was conditional on the $500 million sale of Cascade Coal to White Energy Company, which was listed on the share market.
The AWH deal would have linked its fate to the Obeid family's coal interests and raises new questions about the Obeid family's role in AWH.
There is no suggestion that Senator Sinodinos knew of the link between the Obeids and Cascade Coal. A spokesman said Senator Sinodinos will appear at some stage at the ICAC where these issues will be canvassed.
An ICAC inquiry last year heard that in early 2011 the Obeid family was demanding that the Cascade Coal principals, including Mr McGuigan, John Kinghorn, Travers Duncan and John Atkinson, pay the second instalment of a $60 million deal to buy the Obeids interest in a Cascade joint venture.
The documents tabled on Tuesday renew pressure on Senator Sinodinos to explain his role as chairman of Australian Water Holdings, as the government closed ranks behind him, rebuffing calls by the Opposition for him to stand down. Prime Minister Tony Abbott said he was a man of "good character."
Senator Sinodinos, who was appointed AWH chairman on November 4, 2010, has said he had no knowledge of an agreement that Mr Di Girolamo signed on November 3 to sell half of his 60 per cent AWH holding to the Obeid family for $3 million. Mr Di Girolamo and the Obeids have since described this as a loan.
The letter from Mr McGuigan, which refers to a "vendor shareholder", offered to buy 30 per cent of AWH and was addressed to Nick Di Girolamo and to Eddie Obeid's son, Edward jnr. It is not clear why Mr Obeid jnr was involved. Senator Sinodinos has told parliament he believed Mr Obeid jnr was just an employee working for AWHs Queensland subsidary.
Minutes for an AWH board meeting on March 1, 2011, show Senator Sinodinos described the "McGuigan offer" as a new cornerstone investor and noted AWH's tight financial position.
The Cascade sale to White Energy collapsed on April 12, but the Australian Water talks continued, led by Mr McGuigan and Mr Atkinson.
"On behalf of an investment syndicate we looked at making an investment but decided it was best not to proceed," a spokesman for Mr McGuigan said on Tuesday.
A month before the proposed sale to Mr Atkinson's consortium, Mr Di Girolamo proposed a share grant to Senator Sinodinos.
"I recommend that the Board resolves to provide AS [Mr Sonodinos] 5 per cent equity (shareholding) in AWH and a bonus of 2.5 per cent equity (shareholding) in AWH at financial close of a [Public Private Partnership]," he wrote to directors.
Counsel assisting the ICAC, Geoff Watson, SC, has said the stake, which the board approved, would have been worth $10 million to $20 million if a $1.2 billion proposal had succeeded.
At a public hearing on Tuesday the inquiry heard it was "well known" that the Obeid family was investing in AWH but there was an understanding that it should not be advertised.
John Rippon, executive director and a shareholder in AWH, said that Mr Di Girolamo told him that he planned to sell 30 per cent of the company to interests associated with Eddie Obeid who was then a state Labor backbencher.
He said it was hoped the Obeids would help lobby for water contracts with ministers in the NSW Labor government and Eddie Obeid jnr, Mr Obeid's youngest son, was hired to help.
Mr Watson then asked Mr Rippon if Eddie Obeid jnr had told him about the Obeid family investment.
Mr Rippon replied, "Because it was well known at that stage and Eddie was around the place, young Ed, it would have come up in discussion but I am struggling to think of anything specific."
Senator Sinodinos told parliament that he did not know the Obeids were investors in AWH.
He said he was aware Eddie Obeid jnr worked at AWH but said he "had no reason to regard his presence in the company as signifying some greater involvement by the Obeid family."
Mr Rippon said that Mr Di Girolamo had told him not to publicise the Obeid's involvement.
"I understood the sentiment that because they had a name that was out there all the time they didn't want it publicised who they were."
Mr Rippon said he had one meeting with Mr Obeid senior and this led to a meeting with then NSW treasurer Michael Costa.
The inquiry was shown evidence of donations to the Liberal Party, Liberal party-linked lobbyists and chauffeur-driven cars that were allegedly charged to Sydney Water under the guise of expenses incurred for the purpose of constructing drainage and water supply in north-west Sydney.
AWH also hired a corporate box at the Olympic Football Stadium which it shared with a company called Obeid Investments.
Mr Watson put to Mr Rippon that these expenses could not be justified as part of a contract with Sydney Water since AWH was established as a not-for-profit company to build water services in north-west Sydney on a reimbursement for costs basis. But Mr Rippon said he had a different interpretation of the contract.The inquiry ito corruption in lobbying for water contracts for AWH is expected to last for another three weeks. O'Farrell dismisses attack READ NEXT: Abbott backs Sinodinos amid calls to stand down Sinodinos stood to gain $20m, ICAC hears
]]></text></news-item>