<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-6851-DY2T-D1F0"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Ex-FIFA official faces corruption allegations; FBI is investigating Jack Warner for payments for 'professional services' from Qatari firm</title><source>The Vancouver Sun (British Columbia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A senior FIFA official and his family were paid almost $2 million from a Qatari firm linked to the country's successful bid for the 2022 World Cup, The Daily Telegraph disclosed Monday.
Jack Warner, the former vicepresident of FIFA, appears to have been personally paid $1.2 million from a company controlled by a former Qatari soccer official shortly after the decision to award the country the tournament.
Payments totalling almost $750,000 were made to Warner's sons, documents show. A further $400,000 was paid to one of his employees.
It is understood that the FBI is now investigating Trinidad-based Warner and his alleged links to the Qatari bid and that the former FIFA official's eldest son, who lives in Miami, has been helping the inquiry as a co-operating witness.
The awarding of the 2022 World Cup to Qatar was one of the most controversial decisions in sporting history. The intense summer heat in the desert nation has raised the prospect of the tournament being moved to winter for the first time.
Although Qatar has repeatedly denied wrongdoing during the bidding process, it has long been suspected that the decision was flawed and several members of the FIFA committee have faced corruption allegations.
It can now be disclosed that a company owned by Mohamed Bin Hammam, the FIFA executive member for Qatar, appeared to pay $1.2 million to Warner in 2011.
A note from one of Warner's companies, Jamad, to Bin Hammam's firm, Kemco, requested $1.2 million in payment for work carried out between 2005 and 2010.
The document is dated Dec. 15, 2010, two weeks after Qatar won the right to host the tournament and states that the money is "payable to Jack Warner."
Warner's two sons and an employee were paid a further $1 million by the same Qatari company.
One document states that payments are to "off set legal and other expenses," but a separate letter claims that more than $1 million covers "professional services provided over the period 2005-2010".
At least one bank in the Cayman Islands initially refused to process the payment amid fears over the legality of the money transfer. The money was eventually processed via a bank in New York - a transaction that is understood to have come to the attention of the FBI.
A well-placed source said: "These payments need to be properly investigated. The World Cup is the most important event in football and we need to be confident that decisions have been made for the right reasons. There are lots of questions that still need to be answered."
Warner was one of the most experienced members of the executive committee until he stood down in 2011 and served as vicepresident of the organization for 14 years. He was one of the 22 people who decided to award Russia the 2018 World Cup and Qatar the 2022 tournament. It is understood that the FBI is investigating payments to Warner and that one of his family members has been acting as a "co-operating witness."
The investigators are thought to be focusing on Warner's American and Grand Cayman accounts.
Michael Garcia, the joint chief investigator of FIFA's ethics committee, is also investigating irregularities surrounding the bidding process. He is expected to deliver his report to the committee later this year.
Monday's disclosures will add to concerns that some FIFA executive committee members were not impartial when they cast their votes in December 2010. England suffered a humiliating defeat when it secured only two votes to host the 2018 World Cup and was eliminated after the first round.
Even before the decision was made, there were persistent allegations of corruption. Six weeks before the vote in Zurich, a World Cup official was caught in an undercover investigation agreeing to sell his vote to one of England's rivals. A second member of the same committee was recorded asking for 1.5 million pounds ($2.76 million) for a sports academy. Both officials were suspended, meaning that 22 people voted instead of the usual 24.
]]></text></news-item>