<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-6851-DY2T-D1B7"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Water permits for natural gas fracking illegal: lawsuit</title><source>The Vancouver Sun (British Columbia)</source><author>James Keller, The Canadian Press</author><text><![CDATA[A pair of environmental groups allege the B.C. government is skirting its own laws by allowing energy firms to spend years using large quantities of fresh water for natural gas extraction without having to go through the rigorous process of applying for longterm water licences. The lawsuit represents the latest attempt by environmental groups to target the controversial practice of hydraulic fracturing, or fracking, which opponents have linked to a litany of problems including water pollution and climate change.
The case is also complicated by the fa ct that recently tabled changes to provincial water laws appear to allow the practice now being scrutinized in court, meaning it's unclear what effect the case could have.
The Western Canada Wilderness Committee and the Sierra Club of B.C. were in front of a B.C. Supreme Court judge Monday alleging the government has been "systematically" breaking the law and asking that a series of short-term water approvals granted to Encana be thrown out.
Under provincial water legislation, resource companies that require fresh water for their operations can either apply for a longterm water licence or obtain a short-term approval that lasts up to two years.
The environmentalists' lawyer, Karen Campbell, said the process to obtain a full licence requires that people who are potentially affected by the licence be notified and be permitted to provide input or lodge objections.
In contrast, the Oil and Gas Commission has the ability to grant short-term approvals on its own.
Campbell said the Oil and Gas Commission routinely issues the same short-term licences more than once, allowing companies to use thousands of cubic metres of water for years without going through the full licensing process.
"What we're looking at is, in effect, each of these approvals ends up being one long approval," Campbell, a lawyer for the group Ecojustice, told court.
"The act has more checks and balances in granting licences than it has in granting approvals ... If an applicant wants to use water for more than 24 months, it should do so through a licence."
]]></text></news-item>