<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-PVV1-JC3H-01HH"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>State Capitol news briefs; State agency blocks Genting-Gulfstream deal</title><source>Tallahassee Democrat (Florida)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[State regulators denied a request to move a non-profit pari-mutuel permit associated with Gulfstream Park racetrack to a downtown Miami location, effectively blocking a deal with gambling giant Genting to start a stand-alone casino.
The Department of Business and Professional Regulation on Friday denied the request by the Gulfstream Park Thoroughbred After Racing Program Inc., or GPTARP, saying that the permit was issued to the non-profit for use in Broward County and can't be moved to Miami-Dade County.
The permit is a cornerstone of a deal struck by Gulfstream and Resorts World, a division of Malaysia-based Genting Group, along with breeders and thoroughbred horse owners and trainers, to open a casino hotel at a Miami bayfront property purchased by Genting in 2011 for $236 million.
Under the plan, Resorts World would use the GPTARP permit to operate up to 2,000 slot machines at the Miami locale, while races would continue at the Gulfstream site.
Critics of the plan say that it would essentially "decouple" racing from the more-lucrative gambling - slot machines and poker - the pari-mutuel permits allow. Resorts World lobbyists are also trying to get lawmakers to approve the deal during the legislative session that ends in May.
House looks at med-mal overhaul
Just days after a major Florida Supreme Court decision rejecting a damage cap in medical-malpractice cases, a House committee Monday heard testimony about a proposal (HB 739) that would dramatically revamp the malpractice legal system.
Sponsor Jason Brodeur, R-Sanford, told the Judiciary Committee that lawmakers need to "quit nibbling at the edges" in making changes to the malpractice system. The proposal is backed by a group called Patients for Fair Compensation and, in part, would use medical review panels to determine whether patients were injured because of medical errors. Such a system could keep cases out of the court system. But the proposal faced criticism Monday from an array of groups, including the Florida Medical Association, the Florida Chamber of Commerce, the Florida Insurance Council, the Florida Justice Reform Institute and the Florida Justice Association. Some of the critics said they thought the proposal would increase the number of claims. The committee held a workshop and did not vote on the proposal, which was filed before Thursday's Supreme Court decision. That decision found unconstitutional a 2003 law limiting damages in wrongful-death malpractice cases.
Scott's jobs chief backed by second Senate committee
Gov. Rick Scott's jobs chief was unanimously backed Monday by a second Senate panel as part of a series of confirmation hearings.
Department of Economic Opportunity Executive Director Jesse Panuccio received more praise than criticism for his handling of troubles with the state's new $63-million unemployment-compensation website, as he got the support of members of the Commerce and Tourism Committee.
He received approval last week from the Senate Transportation, Tourism, and Economic Development Appropriations Subcommittee. If Panuccio isn't confirmed this session, Scott would be required to appoint a new director for the agency, which in 2011 was created through a merger of the Department of Community Affairs, the Agency for Workforce Innovation, and the Office of Tourism, Trade and Economic Development.
- The News Service of Florida
]]></text></news-item>