<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-1NH1-DY37-52HS"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>CLOSING THE CIRCLE OF LIFE AT BLACKHAWK</title><source>Wisconsin State Journal (Madison, Wisconsin)</source><author> DOUG MOE , Wisconsin State Journal , dmoe@madison.com , 608-252-6446 </author><text><![CDATA[On his first date with the woman who would become his wife, Derek Schnarr drove her by Blackhawk Country Club in Shorewood Hills.
"That's the best place on Earth," Schnarr said.
Schnarr's family history is connected to Blackhawk like a golfer's hands to a club. His dad, Mike Schnarr, became head golf pro there in 1971, and stayed three decades.
When Derek first saw the inside of the golf shop, he was just old enough to walk. I know, I was there. In the summer of 1972 I worked for Mike Schnarr in the golf shop's back room, cleaning clubs. Mike's wife, Julie, would bring Derek, and later his sister, Darby, in to visit. They were a beautiful family, young and full of life.
In 1979, Julie got a cancer diagnosis. Her courageous fight included doing televised public service announcements for the American Cancer Society. She received an award for her volunteer work from Gov. Lee Dreyfus in 1981. In May 1982, Julie died, at 38.
The Blackhawk membership stepped up.
"They treated us like family," Derek recalled last week. "It was like Darby and I got 200 sets of parents."
Something never to be forgotten. It's one reason the word earlier this month that Derek Schnarr, now 43, is the new director of golf at Blackhawk Country Club resonated on many levels.
"I feel an incredible debt to that membership," Schnarr said.
His story is also one of personal redemption. Schnarr had a debilitating drug and alcohol addiction that came to a head around Christmas 2004. He observed nine years of sobriety this January. Derek and his wife, Christina ? the woman he drove past the club that first night ? now have two young children of their own.
"The things he has overcome give him a clarity of purpose," Ben Dickey, Blackhawk's club president, said of Schnarr. "He's an impressive person on any number of levels."
Schnarr's current association with Blackhawk began last summer when he accepted a position as director of instruction, with an emphasis on growing the club's junior program.
Not surprisingly, given his dad's long tenure as a club professional, Schnarr was an outstanding junior golfer himself. He played varsity four years for Madison Memorial. Schnarr was considering pursuing a job as a club pro when a Madison native and family friend, Sean Toulon ? today a top executive with TaylorMade, a golf equipment company ? offered him a Midwest sales rep job with Toulon's company, Zevo Golf.
Schnarr would eventually follow Toulon to TaylorMade, with a side trip or two into the mortgage industry and other businesses. But his addiction was taking a toll. Attempts to quit left him irritable, morose. In 2004, he moved back to Madison, an unspoken cry for help. Finally, on New Year's Eve, Mike arranged an intervention. Derek would later say his dad saved his life. He entered the Hazelden treatment center in Minnesota.
Golf played a role, too. In the summer of 2005, Schnarr began playing seriously again, practicing until dusk, seeking clarity in the hours previously reserved for oblivion. Soon he took a teaching position at Vitense Golfland, specializing in young golfers.
"Joel Weitz gave me my start," Schnarr said, referencing the Vitense proprietor.
In 2007, Schnarr organized a resurrection of The Capital Times invitational, a once prestigious Madison tournament that Schnarr remade to include the state's top pros, amateurs and ? most significantly ? juniors in the field. By the following year the Cap Times ran a profile of Schnarr and his work with the juniors headlined, "The Pied Piper of Prep Golf."
"It was about more than golf instruction," Schnarr said last week.
He talked about how the game's values translate off the course, and he spoke of his own struggles.
"If I showed some vulnerability," Schnarr said, "it encouraged them to open up to me."
In 2009, Schnarr launched a junior golf tour called Bucket of Hope, with money raised going to cancer research.
His work at Blackhawk last summer, when he was director of instruction, included helping launch a student member program that last year sold out its 25 slots. This year, with Schnarr now the director of all golf operations at Blackhawk, they've upped the number to 35.
It's a smart idea ? private clubs everywhere are looking for an infusion of youth ? but I was able to tell Derek, when we had a cup of coffee last week, that it isn't completely new.
I was a junior member at Blackhawk in the summer of 1971, Mike Schnarr's first year as head pro. I remember my parents paid $125 so I could play. The next year, Mike asked me to work for him.
I can't imagine having a better summer job.
Meeting with Derek last week, all those memories came back to me: the good times, Julie's illness, all the fine people I met up there, some of whom I still see, including Mike Schnarr.
Derek told me his dad is doing well, happy in his long second marriage to Sally. Derek's sister Darby lives with her family in Naperville, Ill.
I told Derek I remember him as a tiny kid in that golf shop. "I'm sure my dad had me up there," he said, grinning. He recognizes the fullcircle aspect of his story. He said that thinking about his dad, his mom, golf, Blackhawk, and his own journey can get him pretty emotional. I know what he means.
]]></text></news-item>