<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-PVV1-JC3H-006Y"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Safe Horizons plants seeds with kids</title><source>Times Herald (Port Huron, Michigan)</source><author>By, , By Nicholas Grenke</author><text><![CDATA[Homeless children will get to eat fresh strawberries and help pick tomatoes and cucumbers this summer because of the work being done by a local agency.
Blue Water Safe Horizons is planning an empowerment garden project near its shelters. The project will give kids a chance to learn about nutrition and also will serve as a form of therapy, said executive director Sarah Prout.
"A lot of kids who have gone through the trauma of abuse or living in a shelter benefit from horticulture therapy," Prout said. "We had the lot and weren't using it - it started as an idea and grew from there."
According to information from the National Coalition for the Homeless, children who are hungry often are in poor health and have behavioral and emotional problems.
Obesity is also a problem because of the low quality of food they eat.
Prout said the garden will have a trained employee to supervise the children while parents are working, in counseling or seeking employment.
She said the garden's main goal is to be educational, but it also will help keep food costs down at Carolyn's Place, a center for women and children who face domestic and sexual abuse, and Pathway, where men or homeless families can go.
"It will be fun," Prout. "We can make salsa with the tomatoes and have strawberry shortcake. We'll learn about canning vegetables."
She said this year more people than ever have been staying at the shelter because the cold winter weather has hit low-income people especially hard.
"We're seeing this garden as a great way to break out of winter," Prout said. "We're putting together a team of volunteers."
She said the agency was hoping to break ground on the garden in March, but continuing snow on the ground means planting probably won't start until April.
In addition to financial donations, Safe Horizons is asking for seeds, lumber, pots, a bench and an outdoor swing.
Proust said she is hoping the garden will be a happy place for children and families to spend time in.
"It's a really great chance to help the community on Port Huron's south side," Prout said.
Contact Nicholas Grenke at (810) 989-6261 or ngrenke@gannett.com Follow him on Twitter @NickSJ86.
HOW TO HELP
BLUE WATER SAFE HORIZONS
Contact Blue Water Safe Horizons at (810) 985-4950, Ext. 209; or email executive director Sarah Prout at Prout@bwsw.com
Bring planting supplies or pots to Blue Water Safe Horizons, 1228 Sixth St., Port Huron
The agency will have a new volunteer training session at 9 a.m. March 29 at 1228 Sixth St. in Port Huron. People interesting in helping should register by March 26 to Prout@bwsw.com
]]></text></news-item>