<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS8-6841-DY2T-60WX"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>The 'everything store' versus Indigo</title><source>National Post (f/k/a The Financial Post) (Canada)</source><author>Peter Foster, National Post</author><text><![CDATA[It seems like just yesterday that the Canadian culturati were complaining about Heather Reisman's Indigo chain "dominating" the Canadian book market, to the detriment of publishers and independent booksellers. Now Ms. Reisman's empire of books, scented candles, Starbucks locations and lounging space for slackers is under threat from a much larger competitor, Amazon. The U.S.-based giant is not merely at the leading edge of the revolution in digital publishing, but at the centre of online retailing more generally. Ms. Reisman's idea of fighting back is to claim that competition hurts her business, so perhaps we should have less of it.
On Monday, Indigo, and its e-book reader associate, Kobo, went to the Competition Bureau to appeal a recent decision - made apparently without consulting Ms. Reisman - which promises cheaper e-books for customers, but more challenging times for e-retailers.
In early February, the bureau "reached an agreement with" four major publishers - Hachette Book Group, HarperCollins, Macmillan and Simon &; Schuster - to stop setting prices for e-books. This followed similar cases in the U.S., which resulted in some hefty fines for allegedly colluding with Apple to fix prices. The bureau notes that bestselling e-book prices subsequently dropped by 20%.
Indigo's appeal suggests that Kobo would "suffer significant unrecoverable losses" from the bureau's decision. And? An affidavit by Ms. Reisman notes that more vigorous competition following the U.S. Justice Department intervention led Sony to exit the e-book market and caused heavy losses at Barnes &; Noble's e-book division. "This suggests," she writes, "that even large, well established companies may not able to effectively compete in a market where contracting practices are constrained in the manner proposed in the Consent Agreement."
While governments' role in overseeing markets is controversial - not least because the main offenders against competition tend to be governments - Ms. Reisman seems to be saying here that governments should collude in preventing competition because it might put somebody out of business. It's a message that is hardly likely to receive much sympathy from the Competition Bureau, let alone the public.
Ms. Reisman seeks to raise the scare that the agreement would allow Amazon to gain "monopoly or near-monopoly on the supply of e-books in Canada." But the main question is how well the book buying public is being served. The answer appears to be: never better.
E-books are a hot commodity not merely because of the amazing technology that allows you to store several hundred books on a small device such as Kobo, or Amazon's Kindle. It's because their marginal cost of production is close to zero. Thus popular books offer big profits, and e-publishing offers high royalties to authors. One of the joys of the market is that big profits invite competition, which lowers prices and profits, to the benefit of consumers. Authors still tend to get higher royalties.
The other big fear raised by publishers is that the quality of books is under threat as "gatekeepers" such as themselves are being "disintermediated" by Amazon, whose founder and chief executive, Jeff Bezos, is portrayed as a cost-obsessed Philistine.
The book business is unusual because each book is unique. Selfpublishing of the kind being developed by Amazon subsidiary Createspace means that every author has a potential shot - albeit a long shot - at stardom (full disclosure: I'm about to publish a book with Amazon). Publishers will still perform a necessary coddling role to the more retiring types (as long, that is, as those retiring types have penned what is considered a hot property). Mr. Bezos has recently been the subject of a critical biography, The Everything Store, by Brad Stone, and of a hatchet job in The New Yorker, whose hatchet jobs often render their victims more likeable. Indeed, there is something reassuring about the fact that Mr. Bezos doesn't claim to want to make the globe "more open and connected," or to "do no evil," or teach the world to sing in perfect harmony. He wants to sell stuff cheaply, and deliver it as quickly as possible.
Another problem for the traditional book publishing industry and its taste-making high priests is that Mr. Bezos prefers to use algorithms - data analytics and statistical probability - to spot what his customers might like. And - gasp - it seems to work.
The New Yorker claims, pompously, that elitist gatekeepers are necessary as "barriers against the complete commercialization of ideas, allowing new talent the time to develop and learn to tell difficult truths." It concludes by asking "When the last gatekeeper but one is gone, will Amazon care whether a book is any good?" Maybe not, but consumers will, and they are Amazon's priority. Meanwhile there will never be a shortage of writers willing to deliver "difficult truths," including those in which traditional publishers are not interested. Now they can get published.
As for Ms. Reisman, her strategy was to diversify away from, and support, the bookselling side of the business by moving into other lines of merchandise, but Mr. Bezos' Everything Store is there too. She has to find some way of doing it better, or go the way of Eaton's.
]]></text></news-item>