<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-61P1-JC92-P341"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Russian Central Bank pulls four licenses</title><source>Russia &amp; CIS Business and Financial Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Central Bank of Russia revoked four banking licenses on March 18.
Three banks held 26 billion rubles in personal deposits as of January 1, and the Deposit Insurance Agency (DIA) will start paying out no later than April 1. The other license was held by a money transfer system.
Moscow-based Stroycredit Bank is the biggest of the three. It was Russia's 161st largest bank by assets, according to the Interfax-100 ranking at the end of 2013. It held 13.02 billion rubles in personal deposits, ranking 110th.
The bank is controlled by Mikhail Metelkin and Anna Belikova and limited cash withdrawals to 100,000 rubles on March 13. The Central Bank says Stroycredit had fallen to 180th among the country's banks by assets as of March 1.
It said the license was withdrawn because the bank conducted a high-risk credit policy, did not create adequate loan-loss and other provisions, and violated reporting requirements.
The second bank to lose its license was CJSC Savings and Credit Bank (S Bank), 170th by assets as of March 1, according to the Central Bank, and 176th by personal deposits as of January 1 with 6.8 billion rubles.
The bank's problems began last year and its offices in Moscow and the Moscow region were shut on Friday, officially due to a technical glitch.
The bank's shareholders include ten private individuals with stakes of just under 10%.
The Central Bank said S Bank conducted a high-risk policy when investing deposited funds and did not create provisions commensurate to risks. The provisions it did create at the regulator's demand resulted in total loss of capital, and the bank's management did not take measures to financially rejuvenate the bank.
A third bank, Russian Land Bank, was stripped of its license for breaking the law against money laundering. The Central Bank said the bank was 227th by assets on March 1. It held 6.28 billion rubles in retail deposits on January 1, ranking it 182nd. The bank stopped serving clients on March 13.
The Central Bank said the bank was involved in questionable cash and non-cash transactions totaling 15 billion rubles in 2013.
The Migom money transfer system, for which Eurotrust Bank was the settlement bank, also lost its license on March 18. The payment system's troubles became known at the end of January. Eurotrust itself had its license pulled on February 11. It was ranked 830 by assets in the Russian banking system as of March 1, the Central Bank said.
Pr of
(Our editorial staff can be reached at eng.editors@iterfax.ru)
]]></text></news-item>