<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-VD31-F0NV-F51P"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Today in West Hawaii history | March 18</title><source>West Hawaii Today</source><author>West Hawaii Today</author><text><![CDATA[Editor's note: This list of notable stories featured in West Hawaii Today throughout the years is compiled from West Hawaii Today archives. It includes historical notes from one, five, 10, 15, 20 and 30 years ago. "Today in West Hawaii history" is a daily feature of West Hawaii Today and is available only online at westhawaiitoday.com.
March 18, 1984: West Hawaii Today did not publish on weekends in 1984. March 18, 1984, was a Sunday.
March 18, 1994: Kona County Councilman Jim Rath introduces a bill that would establish planning commissions for the Big Island's two main regions. Rath's proposal would initiate a county charter amendment to provide nine-member planning commissions for both East and West Hawaii.
The Hawaii County Department of Public Works Building Division is satisfied that several buildings in the Crazy Horse project are ready for occupancy. The structures were approved by the county after the project architects justified the building code deviations.
March 18, 1999: A growing concern about increased levels of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere has led the federal government to to the Kona Coast to examine the disposal of carbon dioxide in the ocean. Preliminary tests have already shown the technology could have a negative impact on the environment and the chemistry of the sea.
In a marathon County Council meeting, three long-standing issues were approved or ratified - a $30 million bond float, the zoning code and the 530-unit Kaupulehu Developments in North Kona.
The double-hulled sailing canoe Makalii reaches Ponhpei in its voyage through Micronesia. Makalii next heads for the atoll of Satawal, South of Chuuk, the home of master navigator Mau Piailug, who is aboard the canoe. It was Mau who navigated Hokulea on its first voyage from Hawaii to Tahiti in 1976. Makalii was built in 1995 by the Big Island voyaging society, Na Kalai Waa.
March 18, 2004: About 90 residents turned a public hearing on the proposed Hawaii County budget into an overwhelming show of support for construction of a police station in South Kona. Funding for a new police station was not included in the 2004-05 fiscal year budget or capital improvement projects planned for the next six years.
More money is released for the face lift of Kailua Pier, and the money is not for the resurfacing that was dropped during the initial budgeting for the project. The $420,493 released last week by Gov. Linda Lingle will pay for further structural repairs. The change order was needed because there was ore undermining that had been originally thought.
March 18, 2009: Hawaii County Council members delay action on a bill that would have allowed county administrators to take money intended for the 2 percent Land Fund and put it in the county's general coffers. The Finance Committee voted 6-3 to postpone voting on the bill until April 7.
Although market values for many Big Island properties have decreased in 2009, some homeowner assessments have increased. The county tax administrator says the reason for the discrepancy lies in the 3 percent cap put on property values in the homeowner classification in 2006.
March 18, 2013: The second annual Sam Choy's Keauhou Poke Contest attracts more than 20 professional, amateur and high school chefs as well as hundreds of spectators.
]]></text></news-item>