<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-K6V1-DYTG-22HN"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Fukushima's army of desperates</title><source>Canberra Times (Australia)</source><author>Hiroko Tabuchi</author><text><![CDATA[Fukushima's army of desperates DANGEROUS WORK: Workers wearing protective suits and masks working at Tokyo Electric Power Co's Fukushima No.1 nuclear power plant. Photo: REUTERS By Hiroko Tabuchi "Out of work? Nowhere to live?
Nowhere to go? Nothing to eat?" the online advertisement reads. "Come to Fukushima."
That grim posting is one of the starkest indications yet of an increasingly troubled search for workers willing to carry out the hazardous decommissioning of the Fukushima No.1 nuclear plant.
The plant's operator, the Tokyo Electric Power Co, has been shifting its attention away from the site, leaving the complex clean up to an often badly managed, poorly trained, demoralised and sometimes unskilled workforce.
At the same time, the company is pouring its resources into another plant, Kashiwazaki-Kariwa, that it hopes to restart this year as part of the government's push to return to nuclear energy three years after the earthquake and tsunami that devastated northern Japan. That has translated into jobs at Fukushima that pay less and are more sporadic, chasing away qualified workers. Left behind, labourers and others say, is a workforce often assembled by fly-by- night labour brokers with little technical or safety expertise and even less concern about hiring desperate people.
Regulators, contractors and more than 20 current and former workers say the deteriorating labour conditions are a prime cause of a string of large leaks of contaminated water and other embarrassing errors that have already damaged the environment and, in some cases, put workers in danger.
"There is a crisis of manpower at the plant," said Yukiteru Naka, founder of Tohoku Enterprise, a contractor and former plant engineer for General Electric. "We are forced to do more with less, like firemen being told to use less water even though the fire's still burning."
That crisis was especially evident in October, when a crew of contract workers was sent to remove hoses and valves as part of a long-overdue upgrade to the plant's water purification system.
According to regulatory filings by TEPCO, the team received only a 20-minute briefing from their supervisor and were given no diagrams of the system they were to fix and no review of safety procedures.
Worse yet, the labourers were not warned that a hose near the one they would be removing was filled with water laced with radioactive caesium.
They chose the wrong hose and a torrent of radioactive water began spilling out. Panicked, the workers thrust their gloved hands into the water to stop the leak, spraying themselves and two other workers who raced to help.
TEPCO refused to say how experienced these workers were but, according to regulatory filings, the company that hired them signed a contract for the work a week before the leak.
Similarly, TEPCO refused to divulge a full accounting of a recent leak at the plant - the worst spill in six months - that occurred when workers remotely filling storage tanks with contaminated water diverted it into the wrong tank.
They ignored alarms warning of an overflow because so many tanks were near capacity that alarms rang all the time.
At a news conference last month, the chief nuclear regulator, Shunichi Tanaka, said: "There is a subcontracting structure that means even workers from third- or fourth- level contractors work at the site, and TEPCO does not have a clear picture of what's happening on the ground."
Mr Naka said many of his best engineers had either quit or could not work at the plant because they had reached legal radiation limits for the year.
Former bus driver Yoshitatsu Uechi was one of the people who stepped in for more experienced workers. He was paid about $US150 a day to build tanks to store vast quantities of contaminated water.
He described hurried days, saying he was told at one point by his contractor to continue sealing the seams of the tanks, despite rain and snow that made the sealant slide off.
He believed such slipshod work eventually compromised the tanks, some of which had since leaked.
"I spoke out many times on the defects, but nobody listened," said Mr Uechi, a father of four who said he left Okinawa and its depressed economy for Fukushima to provide a better life for his children. He said he expressed his worries not only to his immediate bosses, but to TEPCO. Asked about the complaints, TEPCO said it could not discuss individual workers because of privacy concerns. Struggling to maintain 3000 workers at the plant, labour brokers are getting desperate. Mostly chased away by labour activists from urban areas where day labourers and homeless people congregate, the brokers have taken their pleas online and made clear standards are low.
One advertisement, for work involving radiation monitoring, said: "You must have common sense, and be able to carry out a conversation."
"Tokyo Electric has no idea who's really handling the job on the ground," said Takeshi Katsura, who helped one worker win back pay. "It's a free-for-all."
New York Times
]]></text></news-item>