<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-69P1-JDKC-R0JT"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Bad news sells</title><source>Daily Times (PK)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Pakistan, March 18 -- A friend of mine recently approached a certain TV channel for the placement of thirty seconds of paid content. He was shocked to learn that it would cost half a million rupees if aired during prime time. It is regrettable that coverage of terrorist attacks, bomb blasts, carnage, mayhem, kidnapping for ransom, loot and arson is not only free but is all pervasive and hogs all the air time. Terrorists, looters and plunderers have an unfair advantage. If one wants to send out a goodwill message via the electronic media, it will cost an arm and a leg, but terrorists who want to harass the masses and publicise their heinous deeds can do so free of cost.
The predicament raises the decades-old debate around what news we follow and why? The media is often blamed for negative journalism but its rationale needs understanding. The conundrum is that media is an opinion builder but relies on earning revenues to sustain continued operations. In order to gain as well as retain the attention span of the masses, it relies on a certain aspect of the human psyche, which is that media users are more attracted to bad news than good news.
Media practitioners are not habitually pessimistic but they tend to follow the economic equation of demand versus supply. Media houses are basically businesses that thrive on jarring the sensibilities of their audience through 'shock and awe' treatment, hence the reliance on the propagation of bad news. The other essential aspect of this dilemma is that the current milieu is such that terrorist attacks, bomb blasts, mayhem and carnage are the order of the day. If the media chooses to ignore these events, it will not be fulfilling its responsibility of punctually informing its audience. Older readers may recall that once upon a time, when the Pakistani media was in shackles and the state media painted rosy pictures, only projecting the activities of the rulers, people used to resort to the international media to obtain the whole picture, which was sometimes skewed and biased, depending on the origins of the outlet.
The advent of media freedom in Pakistan has provided options to the local population but also unleashed a mad race to provide 'breaking' news, at times without waiting to confirm its veracity or authenticity. It has become imperative that, being an effective tool, Pakistani media takes up the cudgels for exposing the real malice of terrorists who call themselves Muslims but spread evil, bloodshed, and crimes against humanity. Their aim is to attain religious legitimacy, seek credibility and remain relevant while undertaking brutal acts of terrorism with a view to terrifying the audience. Terrorists have targeted innocent people including women and children, political leaders, the armed forces and law enforcement agencies, religious scholars, media and the judiciary to project an image of invincibility and power. The media should be able to see through the veneer of the miscreants' lust for power, pelf and illusions of grandeur. More importantly, the terror mongers are in reality not as powerful as they project themselves. They can be defeated if the nation is united and media is the vehicle most suited for creating awareness in the masses.
The terror groups have also become cognizant of the awesome impact of media and have started blackmailing, threatening and targeting media itself in a bid to acquire media attention. There is a need for media to take steps to thwart the danger of terrorist attacks but also continue to report objectively, rather than glorifying the terrorists or granting them media space. Simultaneously, media has the additional responsibility of raising the morale of the people who are traumatised by the terror attacks. It is an uphill task that requires courage to present objective analysis and denounce the odious agenda of the terrorists. In a country like Pakistan, which is ranked high as a place where journalists face death, pursuing the truth in exposing terrorism is a herculean task. It is the responsibility of media organisations to develop a strategy to create a sense of confidence among the audience rather than falling prey to the terror groups' propaganda, which is aimed at intimidating the media to promote their cause effectively. Simultaneously, a pillar of the state, the judiciary, is also being intimidated to release terrorists apprehended by the law enforcement agencies. While it is the responsibility of the state security organisations to protect the judiciary from terror attacks, the media can also instil confidence among the judiciary to rule in favour of justice and fair play, while meting out judgments to penalise terrorists. Bad news sells but as media users we need to turn the tables on the terror mongers.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Daily Times. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>