<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-13M1-DY2M-W08K"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>India to Appeal Milan Ruling in Canceled Helicopter Deal</title><source>The New York Times Blogs(India Ink)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NEW DELHI - India said Tuesday that it would appeal a Milan court's ruling that denied the country 278 million euros, or $387 million, in bank guarantees in a helicopter deal that was canceled after top officials at AgustaWestland and its Italian parent, Finmeccanica, were arrested on bribery charges last year.
In 2010, the Indian Defense Ministry finalized a (EURO)560 million contract with AgustaWestland, which is based in Britain, to buy 12 helicopters for use by top Indian leaders. India has been trying to recover its investment after scrapping the deal in January, citing a breach of the contract and of an integrity pact, which forbids parties from using unfair practices to secure contracts.
In February of last year, Giuseppe Orsi, then Finmeccanica chairman and chief executive, and Bruno Spagnolini, then the head of AgustaWestland, were arrested by the Italian authorities on charges of bribing Indian officials to win the deal. Both former executives are currently being tried.
The Indian government immediately suspended payments to AgustaWestland, but payments of more than 40 percent of the contracted sum had already been made.
In March of last year, the Indian Central Bureau of Investigation filed bribery charges against Shashi Prakash Tyagi, the former chief of the Indian Air Force, 12 other people and six companies. That investigation is pending.
Bank guarantees act as a safeguard for the buyer, who can redeem them if the seller fails to meet contractual obligations. India has already liquidated guarantees held by the State Bank of India and Deutsche Bank that were worth about (EURO)28 million.
But on Monday the Italian court dismissed India's (EURO)278 million claim deposited as a guarantee with Deutsche Bank's Italian unit.
In a statement released Monday, Finmeccanica described the Indian Defense Ministry's stand as "patently abusive behavior," contending that India was demanding payment of the collateral based on "generic allegations in relation to the unspecified nonperformance of contractual obligations."
The Indian government said in a statement Tuesday that it intended to "vigorously pursue all options for encashment of the bank guarantees."
The Indian government and Finmeccanica have begun the process of arbitration in India. Meanwhile, no decision has been taken on whether to keep the three helicopters that have already been delivered by AgustaWestland, said Sitanshu Kar, a Defense Ministry spokesman.
Italian Copter Scandal Puts Defense Deals Worth Billions in JeopardyFormer Indian Air Force Chief Denies Taking BribesIndia to Investigate Corruption in Italian Copter DealHigh Court Upholds Death Penalty in Delhi Gang Rape CaseCorruption Charges Filed Against Former Air Chief
]]></text></news-item>