<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-H9Y1-JB4F-Y2XP"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Yara International rises 1.1% on high volatility</title><source>News Bites - Nordic: Norway</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Yara International (OB:YAR), Norway's largest materials company by market capitalisation, traded between an intraday low of NOK240.0 and a high of NOK247.50. The price range has expanded in the last two days (from NOK3.30 two days ago to NOK7.50 today) which, accompanied by a price rise, is a bullish signal. The average daily volatility of 2.0% places the stock in the 4th quartile in the market meaning it is least volatile. Today its volatility (highest price minus lowest price/lowest price) of 3.1% was 1.9 times the average daily volatility of 2.0%, up from 1.4% on Monday and 1.4% on Friday. A price rise on high volatility is a bullish signal. The stock rose for a second day on Tuesday bringing its two-day rise to NOK4.60 or 1.9%. The stock price increased NOK2.70 (or 1.1%) to close at NOK246.10. Compared with the Oslobors Benchmark Index which rose 2.3 points (or 0.4%) in the day, this represented a relative price increase of 0.7%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Yara International, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051351660314213
Bullish SignalsUptrend- Rises to Falls: in the past month the number of rises outnumbered falls 13:8 or 1.6:1.Oversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The Stochastic indicator of 19.5 has pierced the oversold line of 20. - Open interest plummeted -70% from 2873 a week ago while the stock dropped -2.5% from NOK252.80 a week ago, suggesting a strong weekly trend.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Return on Equity 22.0% [2.0%].- Dividend yield of 5.3% [4.1%].Other Bullish Signals:- The P/E of 11.9 multiplied by the P/NTA of 1.7 is 20.1. Being less than the Benjamin Graham benchmark of 22.5 the stock appears undervalued. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 14.5%. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.8. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity is high at 22.0%. This is computed as net profit margin of 12.2% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 1.1 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 1.7.
Bearish SignalsFundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price to Book of 1.7 [1.2].Other Bearish Signals:- Net profit margin has averaged 13.1% in the last 3 years. This is lower than the sector average of 13.1% and suggests a low margin of safety.- Net Profit growth has seen consecutive falls and seems to be on a slippery slope in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]
- Earnings per share growth rate has shown signs of deterioration in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteBeta: the Beta of Yara International stock is 0.8. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market. - Yara International is at a discount of 10.6% to its 12-month high of NOK275.40 on 13 May, 2013. It is also at a premium of 6.5% to the 12-month low of NOK231.0 on 11 Oct, 2013. - The present value of NOK1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Yara International is NOK962, including a capital loss of NOK83 and dividend reinvested of NOK46.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Parity:- Price/Sales of 0.8 [0.8]. We estimate Yara International stock is trading at a current year Price/Sales of 0.7 and a forward year Price/Sales of 0.7.
AGGREGATE VOLUMES, PRICES AND TURNOVER PERIOD [Volume Index or VI in brackets; 1 is average] Oslobors: YAR.OB 931,897 [VI of 0.8] volume 97.33% of aggregate. Price: NOK246.10. Stockholm: YAR.STO 22,600 [VI of 0.2] volume 2.36% of aggregate. Price: SEK243.50. Using the current exchange rate of SEK1 equals 0.9351NOK, The shares are at a 7.5% discount to the close price in Oslobors. Frankfurt: IU2.FRA 2,961 [VI of 0.6] volume 0.309% of aggregate. Price: EUR29.59. Using the current exchange rate of EUR1 equals 8.2786NOK, The shares are at a 0.5% discount to the close price in Oslobors. Aggregate volume: there were 957,458 shares of Yara International worth NOK235.2 million traded. The aggregate volume was 0.7 times average trading of 1.3 million shares.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 18: Yara appoints new Chief HR OfficerOslo (2014-03-18): Kaija Korolainen is appointed new Yara Chief HR Officer, effective 1 June 2014.Ms. Korolainen, a Finnish national with a Master's Degree in Law and Economics, brings extensive experience from operational and strategic HR, most recently as Director HR EAME for agricultural equipment producer AGCO, based in Switzerland."It is a great pleasure to welcome Kaija Korolainen as our new Chief HR Officer.
February 28: New Yara Fertilizer Industry Handbook published[News Story] Oslo (2014-02-28): Yara has today released an updated version of its Fertilizer Industry Handbook containing information about the fertilizer market and industry.The Yara Fertilizer Industry Handbook is a tool for analysts, investors, journalists and others who would like to understand the fertilizer industry and in particular the parts most relevant for Yara.
February 18: Yara deputy board member share sale[News Story] Yara International ASA deputy board member Karl Edvard Juul sold 100 Yara shares on Monday 17 February at a price of NOK 241.70 per share.Following this purchase Karl Edvard Juul owns 101 Yara shares.Source: Oslo Bors
February 12: Yara reports lower fourth-quarter results reflecting weaker prices[News Story] http://www.newsweb.no/newsweb/attachment.do?name=4Q%202013%20Presentation.pdf&attId=119444http://www.newsweb.no/newsweb/attachment.do?name=4Q%202013%20Report.pdf&attId=119443Source: Oslo Bors
February 10: Reminder: Program for the publication of Yara International ASA fourth quarter results 2013[News Story] Yara International ASA fourth quarter 2013 results will be released on Wednesday 12 February 2014. The results will be available at www.yara.com from 08:00 CET.The results will be presented at 09:30 CET by President and CEO Jorgen Ole Haslestad and CFO Torgeir Kvidal.
January 22: Program for the publication of Yara International ASA fourth quarter results 2013[News Story] Yara International ASA fourth quarter 2013 results will be released on Wednesday 12 February 2014. The results will be available at www.yara.com from 08:00 CET.The results will be presented at 09:30 CET by President and CEO Jorgen Ole Haslestad and CFO Torgeir Kvidal.
January 17: Indictment and dropped charge for Yara employees[News Story] Oslo (2014-01-17): The Norwegian National Authority for Investigation and Prosecution of Economic and Environmental Crime (Okokrim) has indicted one Yara employee as a result of its investigation into possible corruption since 2011.Tor Holba, who is now indicted, has been charged in connection with the case since May 2012.
ISIN: NO0010208051
OL:YAR; OSL:YAR; NO:YAR
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>