<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-BDC1-JCPJ-W4CS"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Kroger's CEO urged to stop selling tobacco</title><source>Cincinnati Business Courier (Ohio)</source><author>Barrett J. Brunsman</author><text><![CDATA[Cincinnati-based Kroger Co. is among the grocery store and pharmacy chains being urged to stop selling cigarettes and other tobacco products as part of a public health effort co-led by Ohio Attorney General Mike DeWine.
In a letter to Kroger CEO Rodney McMullen, DeWine and 27 other attorneys general urged that all tobacco products be removed from the shelves of company's stores that include pharmacies.
Kroger operates about 2,640 stores in 34 states and the District of Columbia under two dozen names. In addition to pharmacies, some Kroger stores include Little Clinic medical centers.
A spokesman for Kroger didn't respond to a request for comment.
Similar letters have been sent to the CEOs of Kroger competitors Wal-Mart, Safeway, Walgreens and Rite-Aid.
"My fellow attorneys general and I are asking these national retailers to take an additional step forward in keeping tobacco products away from youth by voluntarily not selling them in their stores with pharmacies," DeWine said in a statement. "The health of our kids is just too important."
Among those who also signed the letter was Greg Zoeller, attorney general for Indiana.
Among those who didn't sign the letter was Attorney General Jack Conway of Kentucky, which has the highest rates in the nation for smoking and cancer deaths. More than 930,000 Kentucky adults are smokers, or 28.3 percent of the population.
Tobacco-related disease causes at least 480,000 premature deaths each year, according to the letter sent to the Kroger CEO and others, which cited a report from the U.S. surgeon general.
"Pharmacies and drug stores, which increasingly market themselves as a source for community health care, send a mixed message by continuing to sell deadly tobacco products," said Eric Schneiderman, attorney general for New York, who is co-leading the effort with DeWine. "The fact that these stores profit from the sale of cigarettes and tobacco must take a backseat to the health of New Yorkers and customers across the country."
DeWine was also one of 32 attorneys general who wrote a letter commending Larry Merlo, CEO of CVS Caremark Corp., for being the first national pharmacy chain to "prioritize public health by choosing to stop selling cigarettes and other tobacco products."
Last month's decision to stop selling tobacco at its 7,600 stores by Oct. 1 reportedly will cost CVS about $2 billion in annual revenue. Kroger generates about $100 billion a year in sales, but it's unclear how much of that comes from cigarettes.
On Feb. 7, an editorial in the Cincinnati Business Courier urged Kroger to follow the CVS example and stop selling cigarettes.
Tobacco kills more people every year than illegal drug use, car accidents, firearm-related deaths, alcohol and AIDS combined, according to DeWine. The health care and productivity losses attributable to smoking cost the nation at least $289 billion each year, he said.
The total cost of having a smoker on the payroll for a private employer is about $6,112, taking into account lost productivity because of smoking breaks, excess health care costs and other factors.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Cincinnati Business Courier for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>