<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-1F01-J9YR-G4D8"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Qatar World Cup chiefs deny fresh corruption claims surrounding 2022 bid</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>MARTYN ZIEGLER, PRESS ASSOCIATION</author><text><![CDATA[FIFA should re-run the bid for the 2022 World Cup if an FBI investigation proves corrupt payments were made in connection with the vote, according to the MP who is campaigning for reform of the world governing body.
The Daily Telegraph has claimed the FBI is investigating payments from a company owned by Qatari Mohamed Bin Hammam to fellow former FIFA member Jack Warner, from the Caribbean. Both men left FIFA in disgrace following a 2011 corruption scandal.
Qatar World Cup chiefs have reacted to the latest claims by insisting they adhered to all FIFA's rules.
Damian Collins, who used Parliamentary privilege in 2011 to state allegations that two FIFA members had been paid to vote for Qatar 2022, said: 'If the FBI investigation can prove that corrupt payments were made to FIFA executives in connection to the decision to award that country the World Cup, they should be lose the right to host the tournament and the competition to stage World Cup 2022 should be re-run.
'These reports will only fuel concerns that the decision to award Qatar the World Cup was made for money reasons, not sporting ones, and that's wrong.
'The report on the FBI investigation suggests a web of lies and corruption at the highest levels of FIFA. This is something FIFA has never fully investigated and if these allegations are proven there has to be a top to bottom review of the roles and workings of members of FIFA's executive committee.'
Warner and Bin Hammam's FIFA careers ended in disgrace after they were caught up in a corruption scandal surrounding Bin Hammam's campaign for the presidency of the world governing body in 2011.
Qatar's 2022 World Cup organising committee said in a statement: 'The 2022 bid committee strictly adhered to FIFA's bidding regulations in compliance with their code of ethics.
'The supreme committee for delivery and legacy and the individuals involved in the 2022 bid committee are unaware of any allegations surrounding business dealings between private individuals.'
Qatar were controversially awarded the 2022 World Cup by FIFA in a move that caused widespread shock.
The tiny Arab nation beat off rivals bids from Australia, Japan, South Korea and the United States, despite concerns over danger to players due to stifling heat, lack of facilities for fans and Qatar's stance on homosexuality, which is illegal in the state.
UEFA chief Michel Platini has since led calls for the 2022 World Cup to be switched to the UK winter months for the first time ever in a bid to beat the heat, meaning the tournament is still shrouded in uncertainty.
If played in the winter, the logistics would play havoc with the scheduling of domestic leagues across the globe.
]]></text></news-item>