<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-F1V1-JBKB-V4HX"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Irsay arrest will test Goodell</title><source>Daily News (New York)</source><author>BY GARY MYERS</author><text><![CDATA[ROGER Goodell will have 2,000 players watching intently to see if he's as tough with one of the owners who signs his checks as he is when one of the players gets arrested and embarrasses the league.
Goodell is in charge of not only putting money in the owners' deep pockets with new television deals and sponsorship agreements, but taking it out when one of them messes up.
The video of Colts owner Jim Irsay being led into a police station in Carmel, Ind., after he was arrested Sunday night on misdemeanor charges of driving while intoxicated and four felony counts of possession of a controlled substance - prescription pills - is mortifying to the league and will now be a dominant topic when the annual owners' meetings open Sunday in Orlando.
Irsay's arrest puts Goodell in position to reinforce his belief that owners and executives must be held to an even higher standard than players. Goodell can discipline Irsay for violating the personal conduct policy, even if he's not convicted.
He technically works for Irsay, but he has the power to fine and/or suspend him. Whatever demons Irsay might be dealing with, Goodell will be there to support and encourage him to get help, but there is no way he's letting Irsay off the hook without major discipline. If he did, he would lose all credibility with the players.
Goodell fined Titans owner Bud Adams $250,000 in 2009 for giving the middle finger to Bills fans at a game. A few months after he was voted in as commissioner in 2006, Goodell fined Steelers owner Dan Rooney $25,000 for criticizing the officials. Rooney was Goodell's No. 1 supporter in the commissioner process.
The stiffest penalty given an owner came in 1999 when Paul Tagliabue suspended Ed DeBartolo for one year and fined him $1 million after DeBartolo was found guilty of failure to report an extortion attempt in a case that involved his attempt to get a Louisiana riverboat gambling license. DeBartolo never returned to the NFL.
This will be the first time Goodell must discipline an owner for behavior that has nothing to do with football. I don't think he will take it easy on Irsay.
Irsay spent 30 days in a rehab facility in 2002 to fight an addiction to painkillers. He tweeted last year than he had not had a drink in 15 years. On Monday, following his release from custody, he tweeted, "Deepest thx to family, friends, fans, colleagues for the messages of support, thoughts and prayers. Impossible to tell u how much this means."
Irsay failed several roadside sobriety tests. After searching his car, police said they found prescription drugs in pill bottles, but they were not associated with the prescription bottles found in the car. A hearing has been tentatively scheduled for March 26, the final day of the league meetings.
Irsay told me at the Super Bowl in 2007 that he started getting hooked on Vicodin in the mid-90s after back, wrist and elbow surgery. He said fighting his addiction is never over.
"It's a lifelong thing," he said. "It's something you deal with every day for the rest of your life. For me, it's been tremendous, because when you overcome a potentially fatal disease, it gives you such gratitude. It gives you such appreciation for different things. It gives you a lot of humility and you root for others who have to go through it."
A lot of people will be rooting for Irsay now, including Goodell, even as he decides on how to punish Irsay.
]]></text></news-item>