<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-0HN1-F0BC-M32K"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Environmental groups lodge Harbor Bridge complaints</title><source>Corpus Christi Caller-Times</source><author>Mark Collette</author><text><![CDATA[CORPUS CHRISTI — Environmental advocacy groups on Monday told state transportation officials they failed to fully examine what building the Harbor Bridge highway through Corpus Christi’s minority and low-income Northside would do to those neighborhoods.
The groups — Citizens for Environmental Justice, the Environmental Integrity Project, the Sierra Club and the University of Texas School of Law Environmental Clinic — cited what they called major flaws in the draft environmental impact statement for the U.S. Highway 181 Harbor Bridge Project. That document needs federal approval before construction can begin, and U.S. law requires the government to identify and avoid or lessen the impacts of highway projects on minority and low-income residents. Nearly all of the Northside meets that definition. The Texas Department of Transportation didn’t immediately respond to the comments. The project is widely supported — and partly funded — by local governments. It will correct safety problems and replace a 55-year-old bridge and hurricane evacuation route that is growing more expensive to maintain. It could also lead to redevelopment of the Sports, Entertainment and Arts District. Suzie Canales, a longtime advocate for neighborhoods near the city’s refineries, said in a prepared statement that “people living next to these facilities have endured repeated environmental assaults, marked by explosions, releases of toxic chemicals, and fires and violations of environmental laws so severe that corporations were criminally prosecuted. The proposed highway and bridge project will further isolate these neighborhoods and add to their pollution burden.” The groups said the environmental impact statement devoted considerable space to regional and national impacts but shortchanged the Corpus Christi neighborhoods most affected by the project. “These neighborhoods were developed prior to industrialization and they have a rich history of well-attended schools, vibrant churches, restaurants, locally owned business and community activism,” Ilan Levin, an attorney with the Environmental Integrity Project, said in the statement. Industry encroached on the neighborhoods and Interstate 37, in the 1960s, further isolated them, he said, adding that state and local officials should more carefully consider alternatives to the planned highway realignment. In January, a Caller-Times analysis found that the bridge project, combined with the relocation of several public and subsidized housing complexes, will cause the city’s only historically black neighborhoods to lose as much as 23 percent of their population. Twitter: @CallerMC PROBLEMS CITED Among the criticisms environmental groups lodged about the Harbor Bridge environmental analysis: Failed to look at consequences affecting minority and low-income Northside neighborhoods. No evaluation of off-highway local traffic patterns. Doesn’t fully analyze impacts of raising bridge height. Needs more analysis of air pollution impacts to Hillcrest and Washington-Coles neighborhoods. Doesn’t consider impacts related to emergency evacuations of ship channel neighborhoods. Fails to adequately look at flood-related impacts of the project. Needs closer examination of effects on endangered species.
]]></text></news-item>