<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-BG11-J9YR-G0S5"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Shed a tear for football's reputation; Not good enough to shrug at scandals involving Hoeness, Yeung and Cellino in lead-up to a 'corrupt' World Cup</title><source>standard.co.uk</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Why is football so attractive to criminals? Do you think it's the vast pools of money sloshing around, poorly guarded and easily siphoned? Could it be the invitingly amateurish administration? Or is it just all the swearing? Villains since Bill Sikes have been famous for loving the old cuss words: cor blimey, god's legs yer brute - all that terrace vernacular. I dunno. Probably it's all three.
Setting aside this morning's allegations concerning Jack Warner and the Qatar World Cup, which have not yet been tested let alone proved, of course, the week has brought plenty of football-related criminality. Crook of the week is Uli Hoeness, now the ex-president of Bayern Munich: the world's third-biggest club, runaway Bundesliga leaders and Champions League holders. Hoeness diddled the German taxman out of £22.6million, for which he will do three-and-a-half years in German jankers, a sentence he won't appeal.
Now, I suppose if you're the boss of a club like Bayern, £22.6m is pretty kleine kartoffeln. It is roughly the amount that Toni Kroos wants added to his weekly salary; so perhaps this is the sort of loose change that just slips down the back of your sofa (and into a Swiss bank account). Hoeness certainly seems to have remembered it now, however, and has called tax evasion "the biggest mistake of my life".
I would suggest his biggest mistake was actually getting caught but that is to move into a branch of criminal psychology for which we don't have space.
I've been surprised by how little people seem to care about Hoeness. Perhaps it is a measure of the English media's parochialism: what happens in Germany stays in Germany. Or maybe things will change in the next round of the Champions League, if Bayern Munich are drawn against Chelsea or Manchester Uni... ha ha ha! - I'm joking. Maybe the English fans will make up a tax evasion chant to the tune of the Dambusters.
"Uli/Uli Hoeness/He's in prison/Because his finances/Are a mess." That sort of thing. But actually, I doubt it. I think we don't really care about Hoeness because his conviction confirms all of our assumptions about the characters at the top of football. You know: oligarchs, sheikhs, bankers, pornographers, far-eastern businessmen, American leveraged-finance chancers. That lot. There is a basic expectation of how their world works. Hoeness appears to confirm it.
Once we assumed that all decent transfer deals involved a manager and an agent, both wearing sheepskin and flat caps, exchanging brown paper bags full of cash in the car parks of motorway hotels. Now we believe that the sort of person who can afford to move at the top of football is likely to be one of a breed of international super-crook, with Swiss bank account numbers and private jets, prime ministers' numbers on speed dial possibly even and a shadowy history of robbing some developing economy blind during the 1990s.
A case in point: Carson Yeung,  who stepped down as chairman of Birmingham City last month to do six years in a Hong Kong jail for money laundering. Yeung passed the Premier League's fit-and-proper person test before he took over Birmingham in 2009 - a deal that appears to have been done in part with laundered cash. This, too, has received comparatively little attention - certainly less that was lavished on Sol Campbell's autobiography, say.
Perhaps this is because we believe that Question One on the fit-and-proper test is "Q. Are you a member of the super-wealthy supra-national elite, sailing above laws and jurisdictions and capable of constructing financial networks of sufficient complexity to confound the oversight of sovereign tax inspectorates? A: Yes/No/Obviously."
I wonder whether Massimo Cellino - convicted today of tax evasion on a yacht import in Italy - will be allowed to complete his purchase of Leeds United. You'd think not. But look at the evidence.
And so to the World Cup - or rather, the World Cups. Qatar 2022, if we get there, promises to be the shadiest World Cup in history. And even if we don't, there's Brazil 2014, already a bloody racket that has surely delighted ambitious politicians, beaming ambassadors and those pot-bellied sporting greyfaces who hang around with Sepp Blatter, sucking up the fat crumbs that fall from football's top table, while ignoring the protests of Brazil's poor and indignant football-loving populace.
Fifa oversee a sport whose worldwide audience is generally so extraordinarily apathetic about crookedness and criminality. I guess one day the revolution will come, and the wall will be bloody. But I'm not holding my breath.
Slugger Stokes adds to England's pain
So Ben Stokes misses England's T20 World Cup bid with hand-knack picked up by welting his locker. Is there no limit to the comic ineptitude? Stokes was the one bright thing to appear in the gloom of England's Ashes tour and while his one-day form has been bad, this was not the way to go about organising a bit of R&R. When will this sharp English decline bottom out? Hopefully before India for the summer, although I wouldn't bank on it.
F1's going to drive us to distraction
What a peculiar start that was to the Formula One racing year. While it was great to see a new set of faces on the podium in Australia, far too much of the weekend was given over to interviews with confused drivers and team principals struggling to understand why their quieter cars weren't working or why their results were being nixed on technicalities. Technological topsy turviness has its advantages (unpredictable racing) but a whole season of it is going to get rather wearing.
Hairy styles as body art changes direction
Fan of the week is the hairy Turkish bloke who has published pictures of himself with 'DROGBA 11' shaved into his furry back. He's a Galatasaray fan, natch. I rather enjoy the idea of fans turning to body-hair art to celebrate their loyalties: it's less permanent than tattooing but rather striking all the same. Next up, pictures of your favourite players etched into your hairline, MC Hammer-chevron style. Followed by club crest vajazzles. You read it here first.
Jose keeps quiet but still has his say
"If I give my opinion I bring the game into disrepute." Jose Mourinho was royally jacked off following Chelsea's 1-0 defeat by Aston Villa on Saturday, during which he was sent to the stands. Yet he managed to make all his complaints during his post-match BBC interview without actually giving them. A masterpiece of between-the-lines complaint: making his grievances plain while appearing to say nothing at all. I know all my weekly fawning over him must be getting old. But still: the man gets better and better.
]]></text></news-item>