<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-1851-JBTM-70N9"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Contralesa takes aim at Amcu</title><source>The New Age (South Africa)</source><author>LUYOLO MKENTANE</author><text><![CDATA[MINEWORKERS' union Amcu has lashed out at traditional leaders for "imposing" themselves in the platinum sector strike saying their priorities were misplaced.
This after the Congress of Traditional Leaders of SA (Contralesa) held a meeting with mine bosses representing Lonmin, Impala and Anglo American Platinum (Amplats) and government officials last week.
They were concerned the Amcu strike which started in January was taking its toll "on our people" and wanted to find solutions to end it.
Contralesa president Kgoshi Setlamorago Thobejane said a meeting with workers to decide a way forward would be held at Olympia Stadium in Rustenburg tomorrow.
However, Jimmy Gama, national treasurer of Amcu accused Contralesa of imposing itself on the wage strike.
"Maybe they lack something to do in their rural places.
"We don't understand their role in bargaining processes and how their interference will help," Gama said.
He said the union had met with Thobejane and "put it to him" that their intervention was not welcome because "this is a protected strike under the Labour Relations Act".
Thobejane said: "What we are saying is that we are concerned by the manner in which the strike is taking. The unfortunate scenario would be mine bosses resorting to mine closures.
"Should that happen no union will want to take responsibility when hunger hits our people."
He said: "We are going back to Rustenburg to meet with workers. We won't be deterred by any union or people."
Meanwhile, Gama said their members would march to Amplats' headquarters in Johannesburg today to hand over a memorandum of demands to chief executive Chris Griffith.
The Commission for Conciliation Mediation and Arbitration announced last week it had suspended talks aimed at ending the strike to give stakeholders an opportunity to reflect on their respective positions.
luyolom@thenewage.co.za
]]></text></news-item>