<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-1SX1-F149-S1CP"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Residents show frustration</title><source>Coffs Coast Advocate (New South Wales)</source><author> Belinda Scott </author><text><![CDATA[SUNDAY'S March in March at Coffs Harbour should be a message to politicians that many residents don't like the way politics are being conducted.
One of the largest events of its kind seen in the city, the protest meeting attracted more than 1500 people to the Jetty Foreshores.
This was a startling result in a dyed-in-the-wool National Party seat, which has not elected a Federal Labor politician since the 1960s.
Perhaps the mood of the day was best summed up by one of the signs on display: "How did dinky-di Aussies elect these nitwits?"
Those present included everyone from true-blue Liberals to people who described themselves as "reds".
The ages of attendees was also the full spread, from teenagers to grandparents, with some very senior people waving signs and placards alongside young people, mums and dads.
MC for the day, Tony Black, said they were "totally stunned".
"We thought we might get a couple of hundred people - it's not the sort of thing people in Coffs Harbour are renowned for," he said.
March organiser Sandra Bonney said people had difficulty believing the event had been organised by just one concerned person, helped by a handful of friends.
The blogger and social media communicator said the numbers at the march, especially of younger people, had confirmed her belief that many were dismayed by the current direction of policies, and were particularly unhappy with some politicians.
"We want a dialogue on how we want our country to be run," Ms Bonney said.
Protesters listened to speakers on a number of topics, from the value of Gonski funding for Coffs Harbour High School to the need for the National Disability Insurance Scheme, and the potential for pollution of Orara River catchment from gold mining.The Abbott Government was accused of environmental destruction for economic gain, dismantling the nation's medical safety net, heartless treatment of asylum seekers, recklessly damaging Asian relations, and jeopardising Australia's future through cuts to education.
The mood opposed a government whose agenda was seen to be sacrificing fairness, compassion and concern for the environment.
]]></text></news-item>