<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-BBM1-F031-X0FK"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Corruption commission hearings turn spotlight on Liberal Senator</title><source>ABC Transcripts (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[SARAH FERGUSON, PRESENTER: The scandal surrounding corrupt Labor politician Eddie Obeid has now crossed party lines to embroil key figures on the other side of politics, including a minister in Tony Abbott's Government.
Assistant treasurer and senator, Arthur Sinodinos has found himself in the spotlight at corruption commission hearings in Sydney.
John Howard's right hand man for a decade, Sinodinos joined the board of Australian water holdings in 2008 and went on to be its chairman. The company is now accused of corruptly trying to win a government contract, with a potential windfall to senator Sinodinos of up to $20 million.
The senator maintains he didn't know the Obeid family owned a third of the company, and denies any wrongdoing. The government is resisting calls for his resignation.
Adam Harvey reports.
ADAM HARVEY, REPORTER: As Sydney sprawls north and its farms and market gardens are covered by bitumen and concrete, there are fortunes to be made.
Not just from the houses under construction, but from the water and sewage pipes that must go in first.
This buried infrastructure is worth millions to the companies vying for government contracts; like Australian Water Holdings and its well-connected cast of executives and investors from both sides of politics.
There's corrupt ALP kingmaker Eddie Obeid.
(Eddie Obeid talking to reporters)
EDDIE OBEID: Do you wanna take some good shots? Then you'll go away?
ADAM HARVEY: And one of the most senior MPs in the country; the Coalition's Assistant Treasurer, Senator Arthur Sinodinos.
SEN. ARTHUR SINODINOS, ASSISTANT TREASURER: And if I need any tutoring in how to appear before ICAC, I can ask Greg Combet or Senator Cameron.
ADAM HARVEY: He's been a key Liberal party insider for two decades and was chief of staff to former prime minister John Howard.
LAURA TINGLE, POLITICAL EDITOR, AUSTRALIAN FINANCIAL REVIEW: He was absolutely crucial. Arthur brought a great stability to the office, a great policy focus, and on that basis John Howard was able to launch a really tight political operation which really kept control of his government and kept control of the political agenda.
(Arthur delivering speech in 2011)
ARTHUR SINODINOS: Thank you, thank you, Tony.
ADAM HARVEY: Sinodinos has served as the party's NSW Treasurer and President.
ARTHUR SINODINOS: And in Opposition you have to maintain your shape, you have to have a critical mass.
ADAM HARVEY: He was rewarded for his time behind the scenes with a Senate seat and a spot in Tony Abbott's ministry, as Assistant Treasurer.
ARTHUR SINODINOS: I, Arthur Sinodinos, do swear that I will well and truly serve the people of Australia.
ADAM HARVEY: But his climb through the party has taken a detour. Through the Independent Commission Against Corruption.
GEOFFREY WATSON SC, COUNSEL ASSISTING ICAC: In an uncharacteristic display of bipartisan ship, the events crossed political party lines. It might even be said readapting Shakespeare, that corruption acquaints a man with strange bedfellows.
ADAM HARVEY: Australian Water Holdings was a small company that paid very well. ICAC says that for about 100 hours of work each year as a director of Australian Water Holdings, Sinodinos was paid an annual fee of $200,000.
GEOFFREY WATSON SC: Mr Sinodinos commitments were not onerous. This might seem like a lot for a couple of weeks work especially when one considers the chairman of Sydney Water, and that is a really huge business, the chairman of Sydney Water was paid just over $100,000 a year.
ADAM HARVEY: He was brought onboard by his Liberal Party mate, political fund raiser Nick di Girolamo.
NICK DI GIROLAMO: ...the process that's going on, I respect the process and that's all I'm going to say, thank you very much.
ADAM HARVEY: Di Girolamo arranged a substantial bonus for Sinodinos - five per cent of the company and another 2.5 per cent if it won a big water contract. Known as a public/private partnership or PPP.
GEOFFREY WATSON SC: Based upon PricewaterhouseCoopers' valuation, if the PPP came through Mr Sinodinos would have enjoyed a $10 million or $20 million payday.
ADAM HARVEY: It wasn't just Arthur Sinodinos who would do well out of the deal. ICAC says another group of investors owned 30 per cent of the company.
GEOFFREY WATSON SC: It will become obvious that the Obeid family were the secret stakeholders in Australian Water Holdings.
ADAM HARVEY: The Obeid s deny having any financial connection but today the company's cofounder, John Rippon, told ICAC the Obeid's paid him $2 million for a piece of the business.
And these documents tabled by ICAC appear to show an agreement by Nick di Girolamo to sell shares to the Obeid's for $3 million.
This was at the precise time Arthur Sinodinos was elevated from mere director to company chairman. He claims ignorance of the Obeid link.
(February 2013)
ARTHUR SINODINOS: Obviously I was shocked and disappointed to learn that the company whose mission I believed in and was passionate about was financially linked to the Obeid family. I believe that should have been disclosed to me at the time. I had no reason to suspect any such involvement but it should have been disclosed.
When the Obeid link was finally revealed last year, Senator Sinodinos renounced his rights to shares in the company, worth around $3.75 million.
DR JOHN KAYE, NSW GREENS MP: I find it really hard to understand how somebody like Arthur Sinodinos, who was a senior player in the Liberal Party on his way to the Senate, could become a chair of a company and not find out who the key shareholders were. There were so many rumours around the Obeid family at the time that he became chair that he should have been completely alert to the risk that there was an Obeid connection to this company.
ADAM HARVEY: Also in ICAC's sights is former ALP powerbroker and Eddie Obeid's right hand man, Joe Tripodi. He and former NSW planning minister, Tony Kelly, are accused of changing a crucial cabinet document from rejecting the Australian Water Holdings deal to supporting it. But alleged corruption in New South Wales Labor is old news and it's the Liberals Senator Sinodinos who is making the headlines.
In Canberra today the Opposition was taking aim.
REPORTER: Should Arthur Sinodinos step aside while these ICAC hearings are taking place?
KELVIN THOMSON, LABOR MP: Yes, he should and if he doesn't Tony Abbott should require him to do that.
BILL SHORTEN, OPPOSITION LEADER: Does the Prime Minister retain full confidence in the Assistant Treasurer Senator Sinodinos?
TONY ABBOTT, PRIME MINISTER: The short answer is yes. I want to stress to the House and to the Australian community that people should be in public life to serve our country and not themselves. Now, there are important matters being investigated by the NSW Independent Commission Against Corruption in respect of Senator Sinodinos, the matters in question happened prior to his entering Parliament and becoming a minister.
PENNY WONG, LABOR SENATOR: He was sitting a on a share deal that would have made him a multi millionaire. But he didn't know anything about the company. He didn't know anything about what was going on in the company. This is simply not believable and he should come in and make a statement and clear this up.
CHAIR OF INQUIRY: Senator, your time has expired.
ARTHUR SINODINOS: The only statement I can make in this house is that there is a commission of inquiry under way. I will be attending as a witness and watch this space.
SARAH FERGUSON: Adam Harvey reporting.
]]></text></news-item>