<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-D7M1-JCB2-W37F"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Offshore oil, gas industry needs to be safer</title><source>Business Day (South Africa)</source><author>TREVOR MANUEL and OBIAGELI EZEKWESILI</author><text><![CDATA[Offshore oil, gas industry needs to be safer
AFRICA's western seaboard, from Mauritania to SA, contains among the most productive and fastest-growing offshore oil fields in the world. The region's oil-and gas-producing countries drill more than 4.5-million barrels a day, and have about 48.77-billion barrels in reserve.
The exploration, exploitation and transport of offshore oil and gas are major industries, bringing economic development to the region, which is welcome if benefits can be equitably shared, and if those whose livelihoods directly depend on a clean, healthy and plentiful ocean do not have to suffer the consequences of, and pay for, any associated environmental damage. As the sector expands, it is vital that we strike a responsible balance between benefits and risks, take action to prevent accidents, and equip ourselves with the right technology and strategies to respond to potential problems. To achieve this, we must work together regionally and share our strengths and capacities.
The elaboration of a new protocol on offshore oil and gas exploration and exploitation is on the agenda of the Conference of Parties to the Abidjan Convention for Co-operation in the Protection, Management and Development of the Marine and Coastal Environment of the west, central and Southern Africa Region, which opened in Cape Town yesterday. Starting negotiations on safety and environmental standards for the offshore oil and gas sector would be an important step towards achieving the principal goal of this year's meeting, & Promoting blue growth in Africa& Protecting the marine environment is essential for Africa. As commissioners serving on the Global Ocean Commission, we strongly support measures to improve safety in the rapidly growing offshore oil and gas industry.
Considering that one-third of all oil is sourced offshore, that we routinely drill to depths of more than 2km, and that devastating accidents occur, this is highly precarious situation that must be addressed. We have no right to leave Africa and the region vulnerable to the vagaries of the oil and gas industry. Since recent attempts to reach a global agreement have met with strong resistance by certain states, bolstering regional co-operation is the most logical and practical solution.
The Global Ocean Commission recommends that existing regional agreements, such as the Abidjan Convention, expand and strengthen their provisions to include or reinforce the environmental safety of offshore oil and gas activities. The benefit of regional instruments is that they can be tailored to take each region into account. In the case of Africa's western seaboard, this should include special consideration for fishing, which is so important for the livelihood of our people.
Another factor of relevance to our region is the question of capacity building. Regardless of how comprehensive and well-meaning a regional regulation may be, it will not deliver the desired outcomes and results if states lack the means to implement it. The region covered by the Abidjan Convention includes large states with long-established oil and gas industries, such as Nigeria and Angola, as well as many smaller states, and others that have only recently started offshore drilling, such as Ghana. While it may be impossible to expect every country to develop the necessary capacity required in this complex industry, we must work together to build regional capacity and pool our resources, especially in the event of disaster.
Alongside regional initiatives, the Global Ocean Commission is promoting the adoption of an international convention regulating liability and compensation for pollution damage resulting from offshore drilling activities. This is a global industry, involving governments and private companies from every continent, and while the drilling itself takes place on the continental shelf of coastal states, the effects of major accidents can be felt far beyond the territorial waters of the country where a spill happens. The high seas are also affected by devastating oil spills, and by drilling deep into outer continental shelves. This is quintessentially a global issue and it is preferable, sooner rather than later, that we design the appropriate international standards and regulations. Nothing less should suffice - this is, after all, the global commons.
& 8226;Manuel is minister in the Presidency and co-chair of the Global Ocean Commission. Ezekwesili is a former vice-president for Africa of the World Bank, co-founder of Transparency International and a commissioner of the Global Ocean Commission.
]]></text></news-item>