<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-1F01-J9YR-G4D5"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Was Malaysian co-pilot's last message to base a secret distress signal? Officials investigate possibility unusual sign-off may have indicated something was wrong</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>GUY ADAMS</author><text><![CDATA[First Officer Fariq Abdul Hamid, 27, calmly said 'All right, good night'The cockpit sign-off to air traffic controllers - not the recognised radio drill - came at 1.19am on March 8Around a minute later the Boeing 777-200's transponder which sends out a signal to radar stations, was switched offOfficials are considering if the unusual sign-off was a secret signal
Investigators hunting the missing Malaysia Airlines plane yesterday revealed it was the co-pilot who spoke the last words to ground controllers before it vanished.
First Officer Fariq Abdul Hamid, 27, calmly said 'All right, good night' shortly before Flight Mhl0 vanished ten days ago.
The cockpit sign-off to air traffic controllers - not the recognised radio drill - came at 1.19am on March 8 as the jet left Malaysian airspace on a routine journey from Kuala Lumpur to Beijing.
Around a minute later, the Boeing 777-200's transponder, which sends out a signal to radar stations, was switched off - making the jet disappear.
Officials are considering if the unusual sign-off was a secret signal that there was something wrong on the flight deck.
The other possibility, of course, is that Hamid was by then in sole control.
The hunt for the missing plane has become the biggest search in aviation history, with the total area being examined amounting to 30 million square miles, or a tenth of the planet. 
Malaysian Defense Minister Hishammuddin Hussein said finding the plane was still the main focus, and he did not rule out that it might be discovered intact.
'The fact that there was no distress signal, no ransom notes, no parties claiming responsibility, there is always hope,' Hishammuddin said at a news conference.
Malaysian Airlines CEO Ahmad Jauhari Yahya said an initial investigation indicated that the last words heard from the plane by ground controllers - 'All right, good night' - were spoken by the co-pilot, Fariq Abdul Hamid.
Had it been a voice other than that of Fariq or the pilot, Zaharie Ahmad Shah, it would have clearest indication yet of something amiss in the cockpit before the flight went off-course.
Malaysian officials had said earlier that those words came after one of the jetliner's data communications systems - the Aircraft Communications Addressing and Reporting System - had been switched off, suggesting the voice from the cockpit may have been trying to deceive ground controllers.
Officials will ask friends of Mr Hamid if they think he was speaking normally.
'A GOOD BOY': NOTHING BUT PRAISE FOR Mhl0 CO-PILOT
It has emerged that Fariq Abdul Hamid had his reputation called into question by a South African woman who accused him of inviting her to join him in the cockpit for a journey in 2011, in breach of security rules.
Malaysia Airlines said it was 'shocked' by the reported security violation, but could not verify the claims.
But those who knew him have described the son of a top state civil servant as a mild-mannered young man with a bright piloting future who is reported to have been engaged to wed a woman he met in flight school nine years ago.
His fiancée, Captain Nadira Ramli, 26, flies for Malaysia-based budget carrier AirAsia - Malaysia Airlines' fierce rival - and is the daughter of a senior Malaysia Airlines pilot, local media reports said.
Mr Hamid regularly visited his neighbourhood mosque outside Kuala Lumpur where he also attended occasional Islamic courses, said Ahmad Sharafi Ali Asrah, the mosque's imam or spiritual leader, who called him 'a good boy'.
Mr Hamid appeared in a CNN travel segment in February in which he helped fly a plane from Hong Kong to Kuala Lumpur.
It chronicled his transition to piloting the Boeing 777-200 after having completed training in a flight simulator.
CNN correspondent Richard Quest called Fariq's technique 'textbook-perfect,' according to the network's website.
Meanwhile, footage has emerged of Hamid in a training session a month before the Malaysian Airlines flight disappeared.
CNN aviation expert Richard Quest filmed the 27-year-old who said he had 2,700 hours of flight experience.
When asked about flying, he told Mr Quest that he 'just loved it'. 'It was a wonderful experience, particularly flying the larger big triple 7 plane that we were onboard,' he said.
According to Quest, Hamid had carried out a 'textbook landing' on that day he was filmed.
Meanwhile, footage emerged showing the aircraft's pilots walking through security for the final time before take-off.
CCTV captured Captain Zaharie Ahmad Shah, pilot of the Boeing 777 flight, being frisked while walking through security at Kuala Lumpur International Airport.
He is then joined by co-pilot Fariq Hamid who is also searched before the pair walk onto the plane.
Officials also said today that it is possible the aircraft could have landed and transmitted a satellite signal from the ground. 
Shah, a father-of-three, described as 'loving and generous' in an online tribute video was said to be a 'fanatical' supporter of the country's opposition leader Anwar Ibrahim - jailed for homosexuality just hours before the jet disappeared.
It has also been revealed that the pilot's wife and three children moved out of the family home the
day before the plane went missing.
Some senior US officials believe it is possible the plane was taken as part of a 'dry run' for a future terrorist attack - in order to find out whether a plane can be hidden from radar and satellites.
While investigators visited the homes of Shah and Hamid, it was also revealed by Malaysian police that the two pilots did not request to fly together, reported the Wall Street Journal.
It comes as FBI investigators say the disappearance of Mhl0 may have been 'an act of piracy' and the possibility that hundreds of passengers are being held at an unknown location has not been ruled out.
If the plane was intact and had enough electrical power in reserve, it would be able to send out a radar 'ping'.
'All right, good night' was spoken at 1.19am on Saturday March 8 from the Beijing-bound flight to air traffic controllers in Malaysia rather than the usual sign-off of 'Roger and out'.
Whoever was talking did not mention a problem with the flight, suggesting an attempt was made to mislead ground control.
Two minutes later the transponder - which sends out an identifying signal - was switched off. Turning it off is simply a matter of flipping a switch in the cockpit.
Shortly afterwards the aircraft climbed to 45,000 feet and turned sharply to head back across the Malaysian peninsula. It later travelled some distance at 23,000 feet and even dipped down to 5,000 feet.
Authorities have said someone on board the plane a disabled one of its communications systems - the Aircraft and Communications Addressing and Reporting System, or ACARS.
This is a message sent every 30 minutes to maintenance crews that indicates the plane's speed, altitude, position and fuel levels.
It made its last transmission at 1.07am, just before the last words from the co-pilot.
But it didn't send a transmission at 1.37am, so at some point in the preceding half an hour it had been switched off, a task that requires considerable expertise.
'TERRAIN MASKING': HOW TO USE LANDSCAPE TO KEEP OUT OF SIGHT
The missing jet was deliberately dropped to a height of just 5,000ft to avoid commercial radar after it turned away from its routine path, it was claimed today.
Investigators have told Malaysian newspaper the New Straits Times that the Boeing 777 could have flown low over the Bay of Bengal, avoiding radar in a number of countries.
On military radar, investigators told the New Straits Times, the aircraft would have registered as just a blip. But the stresses on the 200 ton aircraft flying at that height would have been enormous and highly dangerous for the structure.
Investigators said they believed whoever was controlling the plane had flown close to land, or over it, in what is known as 'terrain masking' - using the surrounding landscape to keep out of sight of radar.
The technique is used by pilots of military aircraft to fly to their targets without detection - but it is dangerous and in the dark it would be extremely difficult, calling on great skills.
Maneuvering a large aircraft like the 777 in this way would be a feat judged to be almost impossible, but investigators say they are certain that the aircraft did drop to 5,000ft or possibly lower, in what is thought to be an attempt to avoid commercial radar.
As authorities examined a flight simulator that was confiscated from the home of one of the pilots and dug through the background of all 239 people on board and the ground crew that serviced the plane, they also were grappling with the enormity of the search ahead of them, warning they needed more data to narrow down the hunt for the aircraft.
On Saturday, Malaysia's government confirmed that the plane was deliberately diverted and may
have flown as far north as Central Asia, or south into the vast reaches of the Indian Ocean.
Given the expanse of land and water that might need to be searched, the wreckage of the plane might take months - or longer - to find, or might never be located. 
Establishing what happened with any degree of certainty will likely need key information, including cockpit voice recordings, from the plane's flight data recorders.
'The search was already a highly complex, multinational effort. It has now become even more difficult,' Malaysia Airline chief executive Ahmad Jauhari Yahya said.
The search effort initially focused on the relatively shallow waters of the South China Sea and the Strait of Malacca, where the plane was first thought to be.
Minister of Transport Hishammuddin said he had asked governments to hand over sensitive radar and satellite data to try and help get a better idea of the plane's final movements.
The search area now includes 11 countries the plane might have flown over, Hishammuddin said, adding that the number of countries involved in the operation had increased from 14 to 25.
It also emerged that Mr Hamid had his reputation called into question by a South African woman who accused him of inviting her to join him in the cockpit for a journey in 2011, in breach of security rules.
Malaysia Airlines said it was 'shocked' by the reported security violation, but could not verify the claims.
But those who knew him have described the son of a top state civil servant as a mild-mannered young man with a bright piloting future who is reported to have been engaged to wed a woman he met in flight school nine years ago.
His fiancée, Captain Nadira Ramli, 26, flies for Malaysia-based budget carrier AirAsia - Malaysia Airlines' fierce rival - and is the daughter of a senior Malaysia Airlines pilot, local media reports said.
Mr Hamid regularly visited his neighbourhood mosque outside Kuala Lumpur where he also attended occasional Islamic courses, said Ahmad Sharafi Ali Asrah, the mosque's imam or spiritual leader, who called him 'a good boy'.
Mr Hamid appeared in a CNN travel segment in February in which he helped fly a plane from Hong Kong to Kuala Lumpur.
It chronicled his transition to piloting the Boeing 777-200 after having completed training in a flight simulator.
CNN correspondent Richard Quest called Fariq's technique 'textbook-perfect,' according to the network's website.
The government has called on the public not to 'jump to conclusions' about the two men, saying they were not on record as asking to fly together on March 8.
Sympathetic tributes to them have poured out online with friends of Captain Shah posting a YouTube video that a contains a gallery of photographs of him and a soundtrack of Somewhere Over The Rainbow.
At the end of the video a message appears that reads 'loving, reflective, generous, cool, sporting, intelligent, supportive... the list goes on and on'.
Malaysian media reports have quoted colleagues as calling Mr Shah a 'superb' and highly respected pilot, while acquaintances remember a gentle man who was handy both in the kitchen and around the house.
Meanwhile, footage has emerged of Hamid in a training session a month before the Malaysian Airlines flight disappeared.
Hamid joined the airline in 2007 while Captain Shah, 53, began working for Malaysia Airlines in 1981 and had more than 18,000 hours of flying experience.
Former Concorde captain Jock Lowe told Sky News that a civilian airliner disppearing in Europe would be 'unthinkable' as military fighter jets would have been scrambled.
He said: 'In European airspace, if an aeroplane was out of communication, some military aircraft would be sent up very quickly to intercept it. It's unthinkable that it would have happened in Europe. It just couldn't happen in most places in the world.'
&amp;amp;amp;amp;lt;br/&amp;amp;amp;amp;gt;
Pakistan, India, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan and the Taliban all deny knowing plane's whereabouts
Satellite data suggests Mhl0 could be anywhere in either of two vast corridors that arc through much of Asia: one stretching north from Laos to the Caspian, the other south from west of the Indonesian island of Sumatra into the southern Indian Ocean west of Australia.
Aviation officials in Pakistan, India, and Central Asian countries Kazakhstan and Kyrgyzstan - as well as Taliban militants in Pakistan and Afghanistan - said they knew nothing about the whereabouts of the plane.
'The idea that the plane flew through Indian airspace for several hours without anyone noticing is bizarre,' a defence ministry official said, speaking on condition of anonymity.
Zabihullah Mujahid, a spokesman for the Taliban in Afghanistan, who are seeking to oust foreign troops and set up an Islamic state, said the missing plane had nothing to do with them.
'It happened outside Afghanistan and you can see that even countries with very advanced equipment and facilities cannot figure out where it went,' he said. 'So we also do not have any information as it is an external issue.'
A commander with the Pakistani Taliban, a separate entity fighting the Pakistani government, said the fragmented group could only dream about such an operation.
'We wish we had an opportunity to hijack such a plane,' he told Reuters by telephone from the lawless North Waziristan region.
China, which has been vocal in its impatience with Malaysian efforts to find the plane, called on its smaller neighbour to 'immediately' expand and clarify the scope of the search. About two-thirds of the passengers aboard Mhl0 were Chinese.
Australian Prime Minister Tony Abbott said he had spoken to Malaysian counterpart Najib Razak by telephone, and had offered more surveillance resources in addition to the two P-3C Orion aircraft his country has already committed.
Malaysian Acting Transport Minister Hishammuddin Hussein said diplomatic notes had been sent to all countries along the northern and southern search corridors, requesting radar and satellite information as well as land, sea and air search operations.
The Malaysian navy and air force were also searching the southern corridor, he said, and U.S. P-8A Poseidon surveillance aircraft were being sent to Perth, in Western Australia, to help scour the ocean.
SO WHAT COULD HAVE HAPPENED TO FLIGHT Mhl0 AND WHERE ON EARTH COULD IT BE...
How can an airliner vanish from the skies?
The short answer is: very easily, if a bomb goes off. In all other circumstances, including those that appear to concern flight Mhl0, it takes considerable effort.
The Boeing 777-200 left Kuala Lumpur at 12.41am local time on Saturday, March 8, bound for Beijing.
At 1.19am, shortly before leaving Malaysian airspace, the co-pilot said 'good night' to his home country's air traffic control.
Flight Mhl0's location has been a mystery ever since.
The principal reason for the lack of information surrounding its whereabouts has been the disabling of two crucial communication systems.
The first is its transponder, a device used to send details of location, speed and altitude to air traffic control. It was manually switched off or failed at 1.22am.
The second was its Aircraft Communications Addressing and Reporting System (ACARS), which sends data about on-board systems to the ground every half-hour.
It made a report as scheduled at 1.07am. But at 1.37am, its next report failed to materialise.
What about radar?
Malaysian air traffic control stopped following the flight after it left the country's airspace and entered neutral territory, as protocol dictates.
Since the plane never entered Vietnamese airspace, their colleagues in Ho Chi Minh city (Saigon) never picked it up on their radar screens.
The Malaysian military, meanwhile, maintained primary radar contact with flight Mhl0 until 2.15am.
But because the plane had set off from Kuala Lumpur and remained initially in a major air corridor, they apparently did not realise that an  emergency was developing.
The radar systems of other nearby countries never spotted the plane.
Indian officials say their installations on the Andaman and Nicobar islands were probably switched off at the time because they 'operate on an "as required" basis'.
That aside, any aircraft deliberately flown below 5,000ft is often able to evade radar detection.
Where could Mhl0 have gone after contact was lost?
Malaysia's military radar data suggests that, after bidding farewell to air traffic control off the country's northern coast, the jet climbed to 45,000ft, turned sharply west, then descended unevenly to 23,000ft.
It flew past the northern city of Penang before climbing again to 35,000ft. A final radar signal was detected over the Malacca Strait, to the west of Malaysia.
The low-flying theory is given more credibility by reports in the Singapore-based Straits Times that villagers near Kelantan in the isolated north-west of Malaysia saw bright lights and loud noises at the time the aircraft would have crossed over the region.
Low flying is often employed by fighter jets to use the terrain - hiding behind hills and the curvature of the Earth - to make them invisible to radar.
But those small planes are agile and strong enough for sharp turns, with radar to detect the hills. To attempt this in a large plane at night risks disaster.
Our primary source of information about the aircraft's subsequent movements comes from a satellite owned by Inmarsat, a British firm that provides subscribing airlines with in-flight maintenance data.
It appears to have picked up hourly 'pings' from flight Mhl0 until 8.15am.
But they only reveal the rough distance the aircraft was from the satellite, rather than its exact location.
Investigators therefore believe the flight ended up in one of two 'air corridors'. The first runs from the southern border of Kazakhstan to Laos and northern Thailand.
The second begins in Jakarta and ends in the ocean 1,000 miles off Australia's west coast.
Is there evidence it crashed?
Oil worker Mike McKay, a New Zealander working on a drilling platform in the South China Sea, has said he believes he saw an aircraft on fire at around the time Mhl0 disappeared.
Yet despite a ten-day search, involving 43 ships and 58 aircraft from 15 nations, in a busy and comparatively shallow patch of water, no trace of wreckage has been found.
This is highly unusual, since aviation fuel slicks and other debris tend to make maritime crash sites highly visible.
For example, fragments of Air France flight 447, which went missing off the coast of Brazil five years ago, were quickly discovered on the ocean surface (though locating the actual plane took some time).
Most experts therefore believe that if a crash actually did occur, the most credible location for it to have happened was in the more remote, and still only partially searched, southern air corridor.
Was there a black box?
All commercial flights carry a flight data recorder, which is, in fact, painted bright orange and carries exhaustive data that can usually reveal the fate of a crashed plane.
The tricky bit is locating it.
After an incident, the devices emit a signal beacon to help investigators find them. But their range is only 2,000 to 3,000 metres - and much less if they are in deep water, as this one may be.
How likely is hijacking?
Since 9/11, locked security doors have protected the cockpits of all commercial passenger jets during flights.
While a hijacker could potentially break down such a door, perhaps using the hidden fire axe, it seems highly unlikely that they could do so without authorities on the ground being quickly alerted.
Emergency protocol dictates that the moment the attack commences, the pilot immediately changes the code on the transponder to 7500, a form of instant 'mayday' call.
In this case, that clearly did not happen. In addition, unless the passengers are instantly incapacitated, they might use mobile phones to call or text their families in an emergency.
But there is no evidence that any of the 239 people on board Mhl0 did any such thing.
Why are the pilot and co-pilot being investigated?
The absence of any emergency call  suggests that any hijacking would most likely be 'air piracy' - an inside job, involving the pilot or co-pilot, along with members of the crew.
The two men, Zaharie Ahmad Shah, 53, and 27-year-old Fariq Abdul Hamid, are therefore the focus of investigations.
Could either man have been a potential hijacker?
Shah, a married father-of-three, is an activist for Malaysia's pro-democracy People's Justice Party.
The day before the flight disappeared, he attended the trial of Anwar Ibrahim, an opposition leader jailed for five years on what many believe to have been a trumped-up charge of sodomy.
Last May, Shah was photographed wearing a T-shirt saying 'democracy is dead'.
The picture was taken at stadium where 50,000 protested against the result of a recent election they believed to be fraudulent.
Police who searched his gated pink house in Kuala Lumpur took away a six-screen flight simulator similar to the device the perpetrators of the 9/11 attacks trained on.
Hamid, meanwhile, is a bachelor who lives with his parents and a regular at his local mosque.
His fiancee has been identified as Captain Nadira Ramli, 26, who flies for Malaysia-based budget carrier AirAsia - Malaysia Airlines' fierce rival - and is the daughter of a senior Malaysia Airlines pilot.
There will be renewed interest in Hamid after it emerged it was he, not Shah, who spoke the last words to air traffic control, suggesting he  could have been in control of the  aircraft at that point and perhaps subsequently.
Could the aircraft have landed safely?
A Boeing 777-200 can be landed anywhere there is 2,000 to 3,000 straight metres of relatively flat tarmac.
Flight Mhl0 had enough fuel to travel about 3,000 miles from its last known position over the Gulf of Thailand.
There are approximately 634 suitable runways within that radius.
In extremis, the plane could also  be landed on any empty wide road or on one of the hundreds of old air-strips still to be found in remote regions of Vietnam, Laos and Cambodia.
There is, therefore, no shortage of potential landing sites.
'Given the absence of crash wreckage or any maritime oil slick, I prefer the "safe landing" explanation to the others out there,' says aviation expert Julian Bray.
Such a scenario would only have come about, Bray says, if the flight evaded radar defences (most likely by flying at a few hundred metres).
After landing, the perpetrators would then have had to keep the 73m long plane and its passengers hidden once it was on the ground.
Where does the search go from here?
The absence of evidence of a crash raises the prospect of a hijacking or act of 'air piracy', in which hostages could be traded for financial reward  or political concessions.
The flaw in that argument, of course, is that if the plane was being held somewhere, after ten days it is likely whoever 'stole' it would have broken cover to make demands - unless of course they are already negotiating with a secretive regime such as China or Kazakhstan.
In the case of straight terrorism, the group that perpetrated it will also have to claim responsibility in order for it to exact any political leverage from the attack.
In the meantime, investigators believe that they will eventually be able to sift through the satellite data to establish the exact path the flight took.
However, the process will be hugely painstaking, due to the sheer volume of data that the investigators will be faced with.
'It's like a mobile network trying to trace a mobile phone that didn't have an account set up and which was turned off at the time,' says aviation expert David Learmount.
In other words, the truth is out there, but it could be a long time coming.
]]></text></news-item>