<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-0141-DYRV-33V0"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Putin says he understands why Ukrainians wanted change</title><source>BBC Monitoring Former Soviet Union - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Russian President Vladimir Putin has said that he understands why the people of Ukraine felt compelled to protest against the authorities in Ukraine. He criticized the previous Ukrainian authorities for their disinterest in the lives of ordinary Ukrainians. He also said that there is still no legitimate government in Ukraine and strongly criticized the new authorities there.
Putin was speaking in his emergency address to the Russian Federal Assembly in connection with the Crimea referendum vote to join Russia, broadcast live from the Kremlin on Russian official state television channel Rossiya 1 on 18 March.
"I understand why people in Ukraine wanted change. During the years of independence [Ukr: samostiynist], independence [Russ: nezavisimost], they had had enough of the government, as they say, they simply annoyed them. The presidents changed [applause for seven seconds], presidents, prime ministers, Rada [parliament] deputies changed, but their atttitude to their country and to their people did not change. They milked Ukraine, fought amongst themselves for powers, assets and financial flows. And the powers that be had little interest in how ordinary people are living, including why 1m citizens of Ukraine do not see prospects for themselves in their homeland and are forced to travel abroad for daily earnings to other countries. I want to note, not to some Silicon Valley, but for daily earnings. Almost 3m of them worked in Russia alone last year. According to some assessments, the amount of their earnings in Russia in 2013 amounted to over 20bn dollars. This is around 12 per cent of Ukraine's GDP.
"I will repeat, I understand well those who took to Maydan [Independence Square in Kiev] with peaceful slogans, opposing corruption, ineffective government, poverty. The right to peaceful protest, democratic procedures, elections exist in order to change a government which is unacceptable for people. But those who stood behind the latest events in Ukraine pursued other aims. They were preparing a state coup, another one. They were planning to seize power stopping at nothing. Terror and murders and pogroms were started. Nationalists, neo-Nazis, Russophobes and anti-Semites were the main perpetrators of the coup. It is precisely them in many respects who are still determining life in Ukraine.
"First of all, the new, so-called authorities introduced a scandalous bill on reviewing the language policy, which directly infringed the rights of ethnic minorities. Admittedly, the foreign sponsors of these, the current politicians, the curators of today's authorities reprimanded the initiators of these plans. These are intelligent people - they must be given their due - and they understand what attempts to establish an ethnically-clean Ukrainian state will lead to. The bill was postponed, was set aside, but it is evidently in reserve. The very fact of its existence is hushed up now, evidently counting on short human memory. But it has already become abundantly clear to everyone what precisely the Ukrainian ideological heirs of Bandera - the accomplice of Hitler during World War II [reference to World War II nationalist leader Stepan Bandera, regarded by Russia as a Nazi collaborator] - are intending to do in the future. It is also clear that there is still no legitimate executive power in Ukraine. There is no-one to talk to. Many state bodies have been usurped by self-proclaimed [officials], and they are not controlling anything in the country, and they themselves - I want to emphasize this - often themselves are under the control of radicals. Even to get an appointment with some ministers of the current government is only possible with the permission of Maydan militants. This is not a joke. This is the reality of today's life."
Source: Rossiya 1 TV, Moscow, in Russian 1105 gmt 18 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>