<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-VH01-DYTJ-634F"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>WORLD SPORTS at 1330 GMT</title><source>The New Zealand Herald</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NEW/DEVELOPING:
SOC--REAL MADRID-SCHALKE
MADRID Real Madrid looks to finish off Schalke and reach the Champions League quarterfinals. By Paul Logothetis. UPCOMING: 500 words, photos by 2145 GMT.
SOC--CHELSEA-GALATASARAY
LONDON Chelsea and Galatasaray are 1-1 into the second leg of their Champions League last-16 match at Stamford Bridge, where visiting striker Didier Drogba is set to make an emotional homecoming having spent eight trophy-laden years at the London club. By Samuel Petrequin. UPCOMING: 600 words, photos by 2145 GMT.
FOOTBALL:
SOC--MAN UNITED-OLYMPIAKOS
If Manchester United thought things were bad after a humiliating English Premier League loss to Liverpool at the weekend, they could get a whole lot worse if the team exits the Champions League on Wednesday. A 2-0 defeat in Piraeus in the last-16 first leg has left United with slim chances of advancing to the quarterfinals, leaving the club staring at a trophyless season in manager David Moyes" tumultuous first year in charge. By Steve Douglas. MOVED 757 words, photos.
SOC--DORTMUND-ZENIT
FRANKFURT, Germany Borussia Dortmund holds a 4-2 lead from the first leg at Zenit St. Petersburg and looks sure to advance to the Champions League quarterfinals following Wednesday"s return match. The league is Dortmund"s only remaining shot as a title this season. By Nesha Starcevic. MOVED: 510 words, photos.
SOC--RONALDO vs ROMARIO
SAO PAULO In the latest chapter of a spat between Brazil football greats, Ronaldo has criticized former teammate Romario for making another attack on him, this time over an alleged broken promise to provide free tickets for people with disabilities during the World Cup. By Tales Azzoni. MOVED: 545 words, photos.
SOC--QATAR-CORRUPTION ALLEGATIONS
LONDON Organizers of the 2022 World Cup distance themselves from allegations of corruption involving two former high-ranking FIFA officials that raise new questions about Qatar"s winning bid. The Daily Telegraph alleges it has evidence that former FIFA vice president Jack Warner and his family were paid almost $2 million from a company controlled by Mohamed Bin Hammam, a Qatari who used to be a FIFA executive committee member. By Steve Douglas. MOVED: 707 words, photos.
Also:
CAGLIARI, Sardinia SOC--Cellino-Leeds. MOVED: 129 words.
CYCLING:
CYC--TIRRENO-ADRIATICO
SAN BENEDETTO DEL TRONTO, Italy Alberto Contador is all but assured of overall victory entering the final stage of the weeklong Tirreno-Adriatico race, a 9-kilometer (5.7-mile) individual time trial in San Benedetto del Tronto, with a 2:08 lead over Nairo Quintana. Three-time world champion Tony Martin, Fabian Cancellara and Bradley Wiggins are the favorites for the stage win. UPCOMING: 300 words by 1630 GMT.
CRICKET:
CRI--T20-AFGHANISTAN-HONG KONG
CHITTAGONG, Bangladesh Afghanistan has its first win in the World Twenty20 and keeps alive slim hopes of making the Super 10 with an emphatic seven-wicket victory over Hong Kong. Both teams dropped their opening qualifiers on Sunday. Hong Kong is out of contention for advancing. MOVED: 283 words, photos.
CRI--T20-BANGLADESH-NEPAL
CHITTAGONG, Bangladesh Bangladesh and Nepal, winners of their first group matches, will take a giant step toward advancing to the Super 10 with a win in this match at the World Twenty20. Match starts at 1330 GMT.
Other stories:
INDIANAPOLIS BKN--NBA Roundup. Pacers hand 76ers 21st straight loss, 99-90 MOVED: 361 words, photos.
BOSTON HKN--NHL Roundup. Bruins extend winning streak to 9; beat Wild 4-1. MOVED: 348 words, photos.
TOKYO OLY--Tokyo 2020. Women, athletes on new board to offset criticism. MOVED: 89 words.
SYDNEY BBN--Dodgers-Diamondbacks-Australia. Dodgers, Diamondbacks arrive. By Dennis Passa. MOVED: 789 words, photos.
YOUR QUERIES: Questions and story requests are welcome. Contact your local AP bureau or the AP International Sports Desk in London by telephone at 44-207-427-4105 or email lonsports@ap.org
]]></text></news-item>