<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-92K1-JB5P-J2NB"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Fitch: Australian Utilities Face Near-Term Operating Pressure</title><source>Thai News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Fitch Ratings says that Australian power and utilities companies face difficult operating conditions, including competitive and regulatory pressures, which are reflected in margin pressures across their utility businesses. This has resulted in lower headroom within current rating levels.
However, access to own upstream gas assets provides significant, and transformative upside to the overall credit profile for hybrid/integrated entities. East coast gas prices reflect an increasing linkage to high oil-linked prices from significant gas production earmarked for sizeable export liquefaction capacity from 2015. They also reflect retained options over future gas production for expansions and contracted future gas sales. It supports credit profiles from the near-term negative pressures across the traditional utilities business. However, the extent of transformative benefits of these businesses to the overall credit profile will be subject to the relative access to these assets and associated high execution risks.
In a report published today, Fitch notes the setting of new guidelines governing rates of return and expenditure assessment in late-2013, which will provide more certainty over the investment plans and likely earnings of the regulated network businesses. However, these guidelines will result in lower total invested capital returns and also furnish the regulator with greater control and discretion to determine outcomes. These changes will play a significant role in the long-term credit quality and value of these businesses.
The timing and nature of new government policy governing future emissions and renewable generation growth is unclear, adding to the uncertainties in managing ongoing compliance related to individual emissions, and future investment decisions. Higher domestic gas prices and lower emissions-related costs, expected under the new government policy, will enhance the sizeable cost advantages of coal-fired generation over competing gas-fired generation. As such, coal-fired generation plant utilisation will be higher over the medium term.
These companies' funding profiles greatly benefit from a lower refinancing need in 2014 and ready access to both domestic and international capital markets. Fitch expects utilities to remain well placed to manage their medium-term funding requirements.
(Fitch Ratings: 17 March 2014)
]]></text></news-item>