<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-BMB1-JBVM-Y2S7"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>The Too Big To Fail banks aren't safe yet</title><source>The Evening Standard (London)</source><author>Nick Goodway</author><text><![CDATA[IT is interesting to contrast the views on Too Big To Fail banks of current Bank of England Deputy Governor Sir Jon Cunliffe and his predecessor Paul Tucker. Cunliffe (yesterday): "I do not think we can say with confidence now that we could resolve a failing global giant."
Tucker (last October): "The US authorities have the technology - via Title II of Dodd Frank; and, just as important, most US bank and dealer groups are, through an accident of history, organised in a way that lends them to top-down resolution on a groupwide basis. I don't mean it would be completely smooth right now; it would be smoother in a year or so as more progress is made. But in extremis, it could be done now."
Not quite chalk and cheese but pretty much calcium carbonate and Colston Bassett. So why the differences? One simple answer is the men's backgrounds. Both are economists but Cunliffe plied most of his trade within the cautious walls of Whitehall while Tucker was more embedded in the cut and thrust of the City. Tucker was on his way out of the Bank, having failed to get the top job, when he made his speech last year. Perhaps he was already washing his hands of the Too Big To Fail problem.
But equally importantly, five months ago when Tucker was speaking, no one outside a fairly select group of bankers and Bank of England staff had any idea of how enormous the foreign exchange rigging market scandal is set to become. We know Tucker knew a bit about Libor rigging. We don't yet know what, if anything, he knew about forex fiddles. Notwithstanding that, forex is floating to the top of the sewage tank, which is backing up more than any night soil man might have predicted. Recent developments include UBS admitting that its own investigation into market rigging has extended from currencies to include precious metals trading, the Financial Conduct Authority bringing in rules to claw back bonuses for up to six years ago, and the revelation that many banks have put forex and other traders' multi-million bonuses on hold while their internal probes take place.
None of this bodes well. Libor rigging has cost global banks about $6 billion (£3.6 billion) in fines and settlements, with more possibly to come from civil legal actions. Forex (and potentially the gold fix) could easily end up costing more than three times that.
The City is still resounding to the slamming of stable doors by banks and regulators alike.
We are waiting for the G20 meeting in Brisbane in November to come up with a global blueprint of how a failing bank should be wound down. There is every risk that the forex scandal could trigger a bank collapse well before then.
hole in the system I'VE banged on many times about banks and their desperate need to improve technology systems.
But here is a specific case.
Microsoft said in 2007 it would cease supporting Windows XP. The cut-off date is April 8. Yet only a third of the world's 2.2 million ATMs have been converted from XP to more modern operating systems.
In the UK, the near 26,000 ATMs operated by RBS, Lloyds, HSBC, Barclays and Santander are far from converted. The five banks are negotiating or have negotiated with Microsoft an extended warranty on their cash machines.
What a shambles. But then a full upgrade could cost the banks as much as £60 million each.
]]></text></news-item>