<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-3KH1-JD34-V2RD"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>The late mail is Packer will buy all of Betfair</title><source>Sydney Morning Herald (Australia)</source><author>Jessica Gardner, Patrick Bartley</author><text><![CDATA[Casino operator Crown Resorts is poised to swoop on the 50 per cent of online betting exchange Betfair that it doesn't already own, increasing the odds that chairman James Packer is ready to make a major play for the $26 billion wagering market.
Betfair operates in Australia as a joint venture between Crown and the British parent company. It is understood the British operator is keen to dump its Australian stake because the venture has been far less profitable than it hoped.
Unlike standard bookmakers, who manage a book of bets, Betfair's model matches up punters who will take either side of a bet. In the year ended last April 30, Betfair increased revenue, which comes from commissions on the amount won by punters, 8.6 per cent to $54.9 million.
But the venture is a long way from delivering a return on investment for shareholders. A $1.6 million loss in the last financial year was Betfair's sixth in seven years, taking the loss total to $47.3 million since it began operating in 2007.
Sources say Mr Packer and Crown are keen to take over Betfair because it would give them 100 per cent control of the company's Tasmanian bookmaking licence. This would give Crown the power to change Betfair's business model and push ito the lucrative fixed-odds segment.
A spokesman for Betfair declined to comment. Crown did not respond to requests for comment.
Although the overall wagering pie is growing modestly, at low single digits annually, a significant shift from traditional totalisator betting to fixed odds is occurring.
To illustrate the shift, fixed-odds turnover, the amount bet by punters, for traditional tote operators such as Tabcorp and Tatts Group rose 19 per cent in 2012-13 to $2.2 billion, according to the Australian Racing Board. But turnover to the tote for those same operators dropped 10 per cent to $7.6 billion. Turnover for online bookmakers offering fixed odds rose 16 per cent in the same period to $3.7 billion.
The entry of a new low-cost, online-only player, with the cash reserves of Mr Packer and Crown, could gazump smaller online-only players, as well as threaten the incumbent wagering operators Tatts Group and Tabcorp.
Selling out would be an about face for Betfair, which has failed to profit from the Australian wagering market, despite it proving to be an attractive opportunity for its British peers.
Dublin- and London-listed Paddy Power was the first British operator to make an Australian foray, when it bought out Matthew Tripp's pioneering online site Sportsbet. Mr Packer could derail the comeback of Mr Tripp, who just this month announced he would be returning to the online bookmaking sector with a new website, Beteasy, fresh from a non-compete period after the Sportsbet sale.
]]></text></news-item>