<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-3KH1-JD34-V2P9"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>AWH donated to Hockey committee; Corruption hearing - Obeid-linked water company gave $10,000</title><source>Sydney Morning Herald (Australia)</source><author>Mark Kenny Chief Political Correspondent with Lisa Cox and Jonathan Swan</author><text><![CDATA[The Obeid-linked water company at the centre of conflict of interest allegations that are before the Independent Commission Against Corruption made multiple donations to the Liberal Party as it sought political favour, including a direct donation of $10,000 to Joe Hockey's federal electorate committee in 2010 - just weeks before the election that year.
The link is the first evidence tying Australian Water Holdings (AWH) to the Treasurer and is revealed in the Australian Electoral Commission's Donor to Political Party Disclosure Return - Organisations report for the financial year 2010-11.
The donation to the "North Sydney FEC" was by far the largest single donation to an electorate fund made by AWH, although another gift of $10,000 was made to the National Party of Australia, based in Canberra, and a donation of $30,000 was paid to the Liberal Party NSW Division in December 2010.
The donation to North Sydney FEC was paid back in February last year - $11,000, which was $10,000 plus GST - after reports began to circulate about corruption concerns at AWH.
The revelation is one of many previously unknown dealings by AWH as it attempted to cement links with key political figures as it positioned to secure lucrative public contracts worth hundreds of millions of dollars with Sydney Water.
On Tuesday, Prime Minister Tony Abbott gave his unqualified support to Assistant Treasurer Arthur Sinodinos, describing him as a long and faithful servant of the Parliament.
The NSW senator had been a director of AWH and then its chairman, receiving a $200,000 salary for what counsel assisting the ICAC described as opening up communications with the Liberal Party.
Mr Sinodinos had also been treasurer of the NSW division of the Liberal Party and subsequently its state president.
"The short answer is 'yes'," Mr Abbott said, when asked by the opposition during question time if he retained his support.
Mr Abbott stressed that the matters before the ICAC related to events before Senator Sinodinos' entry to Parliament.
"There are important matters being investigated by the NSW Independent Commission Against Corruption in respect of Sinodinos, the matters in question happened prior to his entering Parliament and becoming a minister," Mr Abbott said. "The senator has been been asked to assist an inquiry ito a particular company. He is doing so fully and frankly, as you'd expect."
Mr Abbott said he stood by comments he made six months ago that he would not appoint Senator Sinodinos to a ministry "if there was any cloud hanging over him".
In the Senate question time, Labor's Penny Wong asked Senator Sinodinos whether he had abided by ministerial standards in his dealings with AWH. She questioned whether he opened doors to the Liberal Party in his role on the board of AWH.
Senator Sinodinos said he could not comment on the matters before the ICAC.
"Watch this space," he said. "I will be vindicated."
Senator Wong said the chamber had witnessed a "cover up" by the Abbott government.
"There are some extraordinarily serious public allegations made against the minister," she said.
"You would have thought [Sinodinos] would have taken the opportunity in question time today to front the Australian people."
]]></text></news-item>