<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-3KH1-JD34-V2PK"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Police given report on union corruption as probes continue</title><source>Sydney Morning Herald (Australia)</source><author>Sean Nicholls State Political Editor</author><text><![CDATA[A report ordered by Premier Barry O'Farrell ito alleged union corruption at Barangaroo has been handed to NSW Police amid investigations ito organised crime links in the construction industry.
Mr O'Farrell ordered the report from the state government's Barangaroo Delivery Authority in response to revelations that Active Labour, a company controlled by crime figure George Alex, had been supplying contract labour to the building site.
Fairfax Media had revealed that Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union(CFMEU) officials, organisers and shop stewards had been given bribes by companies in return for using their influence to ensure the union's backing to win contracts.
Subsequently, the Abbott government announced a royal commission on the union movement headed by former High Court justice Dyson Hayden
Last month, Mr O'Farrell said he had received "a preliminary report that is essentially in line with what I've said before, which is that to the best of [the authority's] knowledge it involves one out of 100 contractors".
At the time, he said he would consider releasing the full report, but his office now says this would be "inappropriate".
"The report was forwarded to both NSW Police and the Office of Industrial Relations," a spokesman said. "As the report has been forwarded to NSW Police, it would be inappropriate to release it at this point."
It is understood detectives began investigating some prominent figures in the construction industry last week.
The police would not comment on any investigation, other than to say they were working with "other state and federal law enforcement agencies to investigate organised crime links to the building and construction industry".
The NSW Office of Industrial Relations has responsibility for policing new guidelines announced last year for how companies in the building and construction industry must operate on public infrastructure projects.
A unit has been established within the office to monitor compliance and alleged breaches of the guidelines.
NSW CFMEU state secretary Brian Parker has been accused of giving "unwarranted favourable treatment" to Active Labour.
The claim was made by a senior NSW union official, Andrew Quirk, in a confidential letter to CFMEU national secretary Michael O'Connor.
The support is alleged to have been given despite Mr Alex owing more than $1 million in workers' benefits and taxes.
Mr Parker has rejected the claim, stating he has "no personal or social relationship with George Alex" and that the union had "no role in getting Active Labour a start on the Barangaroo project".
Barangaroo developer Lend Lease had previously said it had no direct involvement with Active Labour.
In a statement, the company had said it had a "zero tolerance approach towards corrupt or fraudulent behaviour" and would work with the authorities.
]]></text></news-item>