<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BS9-BG11-J9YR-G07W"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Qatar World Cup 2022 investigation: where are the Fifa members who decided to award country World Cup?; Ben Rumsby discovers almost half of the Fifa executive committee have been replaced since 2010, with only 13 of the 24 originally down to decide the hosts for the 2018 and 2022 World Cups still in place</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Ben Rumsby</author><text><![CDATA[GONE
Jack Warner, Trinidad: Retired from all football positions in 2011 after being implicated in the payment of bribes to fellow ExCo members. Appeared to be paid millions by a company controlled by Mohammed Bin Hammam shortly after 2010 vote. At the centre of numerous corruption allegations, from ticket touting to taking kickbacks. Heavily courted by England 2018 bid team.
Mohamed Bin Hammam, Qatar: Banned from football for life after being accused of paying bribes to win votes during doomed 2011 Fifa presidency bid. Court of Arbitration for Sport found he "more likely than not" paid bribes to Fifa delegates.
Amos Adamu, Nigeria: Banned for three years after being caught by the Sunday Times trying to sell his vote to undercover reporters. Denied chance to vote in 2010.
Reynald Temarii, Tahiti: Exposed in same sting, also denied chance to vote and banned for one year.
Chuck Blazer, USA: Former general secretary of Concacaf, who helped bring down Bin Hammam, was accused of committing fraud and misappropriating football money by an internal probe. Blazer denies the accusations.
Nicolás Leoz, Paraguay: Former Football Association chairman Lord Triesman claimed Leoz demanded a knighthood in return for voting for England to host the 2018 World Cup. Stood down last year "due to ill health" weeks before Fifa's ethics committee reported that he had accepted at least £80,000 in bribes from defunct sports marketing company ISL. A list obtained by BBC Panorama suggested he had received at least $730,000.
Ricardo Teixeira, Brazil (below): Fled for Miami after being accused of accepting kickbacks in his native Brazil, something he denies. Fifa ethics committee found he pocketed at least £8.4m in ISL bribes.
Geoff Thompson, England: Humiliated by England gaining a single vote for the 2018 tournament beyond his own.
Franz Beckenbauer, Germany: Stepped down in June 2011 after relinquishing his Uefa post. Was the first to argue for the 2022 World Cup to switch to winter in the days after the 2010 vote.
Chung Mong-joon, South Korea: Lost his seat on the ExCo after Blatter backed his opponent, Jordan's Prince Ali bin al-Hussein, in Asian Football Confederation elections. Hyundai billionaire had been a vocal opponent of the Swiss.
Junji Ogura, Japan: Gone Forced to step down from his home confederation once he reached 72.
STILL THERE
Sepp Blatter, Switzerland: Fifa overlord since 1998 and controversially set to run for a fifth term as president next year. Branded "clumsy" but not corrupt over handling of ISL bribery scandal last year.
Michel Platini, France: Uefa's president openly admitted voting for Qatar and that there had been "direct political influence" on the ExCo to do so but insisted his own vote was purely football-led. Could stand against Blatter next year.
Michel D'Hooghe, Belgium: Straight-dealing Belgian Football Association president and Fifa medical chief who was key in convincing Blatter to order review into timing of 2022 tournament.
Jacques Anouma, Ivory Coast (below): Under parliamentary privilege, it was claimed he accepted bribes from Qatar based on evidence gathered by the Sunday Times. Fifa cleared him of the allegations.
Marios Lefkaritis, Cyprus: Revealed last year to have extensive business links with Qatar.
Angel María Villa Llona, Spain: Secured vote-swapping deal with Qatar in 2010 but failed to beat Russia.
Senes Erzik, Turkey: Said to be among those who promised their vote to England to host 2018 World Cup before reneging.
Worawi Makudi, Thailand: Claims he accepted Qatari development cash in return for his vote. Also embroiled in allegations surrounding the Thai FA headquarters.
Issa Hayatou, Cameroon: President of the Confederation of African Football was censured by International Olympic Committee over his acceptance of money from ISL. He claimed it was reimbursement for money spent on CAF birthday party.
Julio Grondona, Argentina: One of the longest serving Fifa executive committee members. Pre-dates Blatter's presidency.
Hany Abo Rida, Egypt: Said to have accompanied Bin Hammam on a private jet to Trinidad where the Qatari allegedly sought to buy the votes of Caribbean football officials. Nothing was proven.
Vitaly Mutko, Russia: Close to Vladimir Putin, the former head of the Russian Football Union and former Russian sports minister played a key role in securing the 2018 World Cup for his country.
Rafael Salguero, Guatemala: Still in post.
]]></text></news-item>