<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSB-1VG1-DY37-F1WV"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>OFFICIAL: YORKTOWN 'ASH LANDFILL IS SAFE' {SUMMHD} Environmentalists say despite safety measures, there are still long-term consequences, room for strengthening regulations</title><source>Daily Press (Newport News, Virginia)</source><author> By Tamara Dietrich  tdietrich@dailypress.com</author><text><![CDATA[One by one, the coal ash trucks come.
Five days a week during daylight hours, they head up a private paved road that runs from the Yorktown Power Station -- which burns coal and oil to produce electricity -- to the industrial landfill where coal ash is dumped, dispersed by a bulldozer and compacted into a dense, toxic black layer.
The landfill facility covers 48 acres and was built by Virginia Dominion Power 30 years ago in east-central York County, some 2 miles south of the power station and the York River. Its working life is nearly done -- it was designed to hold 1.6 million tons, and already holds 1.4 million.
But last month when a rusty metal stormwater pipe running under a closed unlined coal ash dump near Eden, N.C., collapsed and spilled tens of thousands of tons of toxic sludge into the Dan River, the burning question for communities across the country became: Could it happen here?
For the Yorktown landfill, Dominion officials say that notion is far-fetched -- that it's properly lined, regulated by government agencies and closely monitored.
"The Yorktown Power Station ash landfill is safe," said Kenneth Lazzaro, who manages the Yorktown facility and the Chesapeake Energy Center. "Our landfill is not near a body of water. It meets all local, state and federal requirements and was just given a clean bill of health by the DEQ (state Department of Environmental Quality) as recently as (March 11)."
For environmentalists and legal advocates, though, the fear is real. First, they say, existing state laws are inadequate to protect the public and should be strengthened. And they say there's a risk beyond a sudden dam breach at a coal ash storage pond, or a pipe collapse at a landfill that spills toxic sludge into a neighboring waterway, like that at the Dan River.
"An equally important concern is the long-term leaching of heavy metals -- arsenic, selenium and other contaminants -- from unlined pits into the groundwater into adjacent water bodies," said attorney Cale Jaffe with the Southern Environmental Law Center in Charlottesville. "That may not make for dramatic catastrophic failure like we saw ... outside Eden, but nonetheless it's a significant concern."
Berm failure
Dominion spokesman Dan Genest is quick to point out that the Yorktown landfill differs in critical ways from that at the Dan River Steam Station, owned by Duke Energy Corp.
The Yorktown site has a 6-inch thick clay liner underneath as well as a compacted soil substrate to prevent leaching into the environment, and Dominion samples the groundwater regularly via monitoring wells. It sends the state annual and semi-annual groundwater monitoring reports.
Stormwater runoff from the site's 11 inactive cells -- nearly all of them capped with clay, soil and vegetation -- is directed down the slopes and into a central sedimentation pond. Any overflow from there is directed into ponds on either side. From there, it flows to a stream in the nearby woods.
Under the landfill is a water collection system with plastic piping that directs leachate to a 6,000-gallon underground storage tank, where it's automatically pumped to the Hampton Roads Sanitation District (HRSD) for treatment.
The power company is required by the state to report any incidents or violations. Asked if it was possible for a company to opt not to report, Genest said the risks would be tremendous.
"From Dominion's perspective, it's much better to follow the letter of the law than it is to try and avoid it," said Genest. "That wouldn't be ethical, and it wouldn't be right."
In the last few years, he said, Dominion has received two warning letters from the DEQ after self-reporting isolated erosion incidents at Yorktown and its Clover Power Station in Halifax County, neither of which resulted in fines.
According to records obtained from the DEQ, the Yorktown incident occurred on Sept. 30, 2010, when heavy rains from the remnants of Tropical Storm Nicole damaged the earthen berm at Cell 12 -- the last and only active cell at the landfill -- and sent stormwater laden with toxic ash pouring down the slope, under and across the haul road and into the sedimentation pond.
Within hours, Utah-based Headwaters Resources, Inc., the company Dominion hires to operate and maintain the landfill, used heavy equipment to divert the flow and temporarily repair the berm.
According to a subsequent analysis of the spill by Dominion, a DEQ inspector found that ash "did not appear to have been released offsite," but the analysis did note several violations at the landfill that contributed to the berm failure.
A rock check dam was installed improperly -- without the correct filter fabric or the large riprap needed to keep small gravel from being carried off by rainwater. A straw bale used for filtration was also installed improperly and ended up blocking a culvert pipe, which caused the perimeter ditch to overflow into one of the sedimentation ponds.
Minor contributors, the analysis said, were inadequate grading of the slope of neighboring Cell 11, allowing runoff to enter Cell 12, and sparse ground cover to help slow the runoff.
As a result of that coal ash spill, Headwaters replaced its landfill manager and was directed to familiarize its personnel with Virginia Erosion and Sediment Control standards.
Three engineering firms were called in and under their recommendations, coal ash was removed from the perimeter ditch, culvert pipe and sedimentation ponds. The earthen berm and rock check dam were rebuilt to state specs, and the slope of Cell 11 was regraded.
Six months before that episode, records show Dominion reported to the DEQ that heavy rains had also eroded the side slopes of Cell 9, forcing repairs. The company reported minimal ash exposure.
The risks
Whether coal ash pollutes the environment through human error or act of God, it's still a nightmare scenario for critics.
In January, the Center for Environmental Studies at the University of Richmond School of Law released "A Strategy to Protect Virginians from Toxic Chemicals," noting that Virginia ranks as the 18th largest coal ash producer in the country, with about 2.4 million tons produced every year.
Environmentalists and utility officials agree that coal ash has to go somewhere.
Most of it gets stored in ponds or landfills. And the rest, according to the Southern Alliance for Clean Energy, gets recycled to such things as an ingredient in concrete and wallboard and school running tracks, structural fill for highway embankments or building foundations, fill for abandoned mines or quarries, as a top layer on unpaved roads, an agricultural soil additive and as cinders to be spread on snowy roads.
The Southern Alliance is a partnership between SELC and a variety of environmental and community groups.
Because coal-fired plants need water to operate, they're typically built along rivers and other waterways. So, too, are coal ash ponds.
According to the toxic chemicals strategy report, about half of the coal ash ponds in the country are unlined, and of the 25 ponds operated by electricity generators in Virginia, 13 are unlined.
In 2008, after an old earthen dam at a coal ash pond collapsed in Tennessee and spilled more than a billion gallons of thick, toxic ash slurry into the Emory River, causing massive fish kills, destroying homes and forcing a $1.2 billion cleanup that's still ongoing, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency decided to assess the stability of coal ash storage facilities across the country.
The EPA classified eight coal ash ponds in the commonwealth as "significant hazards," meaning that containment failure could cause "economic loss, environmental damage" and other impacts.
Those eight sites are two ash ponds at Bremo Power Station in Fluvanna County, the bottom ash and sedimentation pond at the Chesapeake Energy Center, the lower ash pond at the Chesterfield Power Station, two ash ponds at Possum Point Power Station in Chester, and two ash ponds at the Clinch River Power Station in Russell County.
The Clinch River facility is owned by American Electric Power. The rest are owned by Dominion; Genest said all its ponds are lined.
If the pond at the Chesapeake facility should ever fail, coal ash would likely spill into the Elizabeth River, a major tributary of the Chesapeake Bay. According to the toxics report, the Chesapeake station also has a 22-acre coal ash landfill that has caused arsenic contamination in nearby groundwater.
If a toxic chemical enters a major river, the impact could be devastating and long-lasting. In 1975, for instance, health officials closed a small chemical plant in Hopewell after discovering massive amounts of a pesticide called Kepone had been secretly and illegally dumped for years into the city sewage system and directly into the James River, forcing the state to close 100 miles of the waterway to fishing, in some cases for years. Health officials called it the worst environmental disaster in the state's history, and environmental experts said the pesticide, a carcinogen and slow to degrade, could affect aquatic life for centuries.
Some 31 sites in Virginia are so contaminated by toxic chemicals -- including coal ash -- that they're on EPA's Superfund list, according to the toxics report.
One of those sites is in York County, where from 1957 to 1974 coal ash from the power station was deposited -- legally, at the time -- by a contractor in unlined pits on private property, contaminating the surrounding environment, including Chisman Creek and the water wells of neighboring homes.
When it was discovered, said Genest, Dominion diverted a 600-foot section of a tributary of Chisman Creek, paid to extend public water to 55 nearby homes, covered the ash pits with layers of clay, clean soil and vegetation, and installed pipes to send groundwater to HRSD for treatment.
While it remains a Superfund site of toxic coal ash, its surface has been converted into the Wolf Trap and Chisman Creek parks, with soccer and softball fields. Dominion continues to monitor for contamination.
Recommendations
Despite the risks to human health, wildlife and the environment posed by heavy metals and toxic chemicals in condensed coal ash, environmentalists complain it's less strictly controlled in many states than household garbage.
"Most of the toxic releases to our environment are not illegal -- they are usually permitted by the DEQ, which implements federal and state environmental laws," write the authors of the toxic chemicals report, environmental lawyer Noah M. Sachs and law student Ryan P. Murphy.
Among their recommendations, they want the DEQ and the state Waste Management Board to stop exempting coal ash ponds and landfills from solid waste permitting and the hazardous waste program, and increase inspections and oversight.
They want the General Assembly to pass laws to treat coal ash disposal sites as hazardous waste facilities, and increase the penalties for violations.
And they want the DEQ to be given the funds and manpower to accomplish it.
The two coal-burning units at Yorktown were scheduled to close at the end of this year, before EPA's more stringent emission standards go into effect in April 2015, said Genest. That would leave one oil-burning unit to act as a "peaker" for periods of high electricity demand.
But Genest says that closure may be postponed a year or two because of construction delays with the transmission line from the Surry Power Station to the Peninsula. That line is intended to ensure a reliable power supply once the coal units close.
When they do close, so will the landfill. Dominion had procured a permit from the DEQ five years ago for a vertical expansion of the site, but Genest said there are no hard plans for expansion, even with the construction delay. That may change if the coal units operate considerably more than expected while the line is being built.
When the landfill finally does close, Dominion will cap and grade it according to state requirements, then monitor it for environmental contamination for 10 years. Any monitoring beyond that, said the company's senior environmental compliance coordinator Laura Schumaker, depends on the DEQ.
Dietrich can be reached by phone at 757-247-7892.
MORE ONLINE
See video and more photos from the Yorktown Power Station ash landfill at dailypress.com.
]]></text></news-item>