<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSB-6PT1-DY93-M4D3"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>AFP World News Agenda</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[What's happening around the world on Wednesday:
-- TOP STORIES --
+ Ukrainian soldier killed in Crimea after Putin 'land grab'
+ Missing Malaysian plane mystery enters 12th day
+ US Fed chair to offer signal on rates
+ Israel vows forceful action after bomb wounds four soldiers
KIEV/MOSCOW/SIMFEROPOL: Ukraine orders its troops to use their weapons in self-defence in Crimea after a soldier died when gunmen stormed a Ukrainian military base, hours after President Vladimir Putin signed a treaty declaring Crimea to be part of Russia (UKRAINE-RUSSIA-POLITICS-CRISIS)
KUALA LUMPUR: Full coverage of the massive search for the missing Malaysian passenger jet that has expanded to involve 26 countries and cover an area the size of Australia with no trace of any wreckage found 12 days after the plane lost contact (MALAYSIA-CHINA-AVIATION)
WASHINGTON: Janet Yellen faces the media for the first time as chair of the Federal Reserve, with markets hoping for a clearer picture on when the Fed expects to hike interest rates. Fed policy committee to issue statement at about 1800 GMT. Yellen press conference to follow (US-ECONOMY-BANK-RATE)
JERUSALEM/MAJDAL SHAMS, Golan Heights: Tracking as Israel promises to "act forcefully" after four of its soldiers are wounded in an explosion along the ceasefire line with Syria (ISRAEL-SYRIA-CONFLICT)
-- OTHER AGENDA ITEMS --
VILNIUS: US Vice President Joe Biden meets with Lithuanian and Latvian leaders as part of a tour to reassure NATO allies during the Ukraine crisis. Start 0735 GMT. Press statements 1130 GMT. (UKRAINE-RUSSIA-POLITICS-CRISIS-US-BALTICS)
BRUSSELS: EU Economic Affairs Commissioner Olli Rehn announces one billion euro aid package for Ukraine. 1115 GMT (UKRAINE-UNREST-ECONOMY-EU-AID)
LONDON: Chancellor of the Exchequer George Osborne gives Britain's annual budget that looks likely to contain more austerity measures with 14 months to go until a general election. From 1230 GMT (BRITAIN-FINANCE-ECONOMY-GROWTH-BUDGET)
DAMASCUS: Syrian regime forces seek to recapture the rest of the strategic Qalamoun region along the Lebanese border after seizing the rebel stronghold of Yabrud (SYRIA-CONFLICT)
ANKARA: Turkish parliament holds a special session from 1300 GMT to consider the corruption scandal rocking the leadership (TURKEY-POLITICS-CORRUPTION)
WASHINGTON: First Lady Michelle Obama heads to China for a week-long visit which the White House is dubbing a "people to people" trip (US-CHINA-DIPLOMACY-EDUCATION-PEOPLE)
HANOI: Former government official turned activist and blogger Pham Viet Dao goes on trial on anti-state charges amid fears of a crackdown on dissent in the communist country (VIETNAM-POLITICS-RIGHTS-TRIAL)
BANGKOK: Lifting of nearly two-month-old state of emergency takes effect as government seeks to lure back tourists following an easing of months of political protests (THAILAND-POLITICS-PROTEST)
BANGUI: UN Human Rights Commissioner Navi Pillay holds talks with Central African leaders on the violence and humanitarian crisis wracking the country (CAFRICA-UNREST-UN-RIGHTS)
afp
]]></text></news-item>