<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSB-5MG1-JD34-V4HC"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Obeid family link in corruption hearing</title><source>The Border Mail</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A company linked to the Obeid family with high-profile Liberal Party figures on its board gouged millions of dollars from the state-owned Sydney Water, including for limousines, horse-breeding and political donations, the Independent Commission Against Corruption heard yesterday.
Assistant Federal Treasurer Arthur Sinodinos was on the board of the Obeid-linked infrastructure company Australian Water Holdings when it was stonewalling attempts by Sydney Water to inspect its books.
Australian Water Holdings had its expenses covered by Sydney Water under a lucrative contract to provide water infrastructure in Sydney's north-west.
By late 2008, the utility was footing the bill for up to $800,000 in monthly expenses, including $7333 paid to a slush fund linked to former NSW energy minister Chris Hartcher and more than $75,000 in donations to the Liberal Party.
Fairfax Media can reveal Australian Water Holdings donated a further $10,000 to Treasurer Joe Hockey's campaign weeks before the 2010 federal election.
But the donation was returned last year.
Documents at the Independent Commission Against Corruption hearing yesterday reveal the company also made a $2200 donation to the Queensland branch of the Labor Party.
Sydney Water, led by Kerry Schott, was trying to halt the massive bills Australian Water Holdings kept submitting.
Senator Sinodinos, who was then treasurer of the NSW Liberals, was one of the recipients of a 2010 email from fellow Australian Water Holdings director John Rippon which read: "If only the bitch (Dr Schott) was gone we could deal with these guys."
The inquiry has previously heard corrupt former ALP powerbroker Eddie Obeid tried to "eliminate" Dr Schott by making false corruption complaints against her.
Among the expenses being forced on Sydney Water were the exorbitant salaries the Australian Water Holdings directors were paying themselves.
Liberal Party fund-raiser and Obeid family associate Nick Di Girolamo was on a $1.1 million salary, plus a $250,000 "sign-on" fee and a bonus of the same amount.
Mr Rippon received $1.7 million for working two days a week.
When asked about the hundreds of thousands Australian Water Holdings secretly billed Sydney Water for its attempts to expand ito Queensland, Mr Rippon agreed it was inappropriate.
Senator Sinodinos' $200,000 salary and bonuses were also allegedly covered by Sydney Water.
The commission heard Australian Water Holdings' monthly expenses escalated after Mr Girolamo was appointed chief executive in 2007.
Other expenses allegedly billed to Sydney Water include $159,300 paid to Mr Rippon's horse-breeding farm.
The commission heard Mr Di Girolamo and Mr Rippon bought a racehorse, Partner in Crime, from the farm for $50,000.
Mr Rippon said he knew an "Obeid entity was involved" in buying a 30 per cent stake in Australian Water Holdings. The family claims this is a loan.
Senator Sinodinos, who denies any wrongdoing, has insisted he was unaware of the Obeids' financial involvement in the company.
]]></text></news-item>