<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSB-9YS1-JCPJ-W4V6"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Newly unsealed lawsuit alleges Tutera Group fraud</title><source>Kansas City Business Journal</source><author>Brianne Pfannenstiel</author><text><![CDATA[Kansas City businessman Michael Tutera was murdered in 2010. But accusations he made before his death about his brother Joe Tutera soon will see new light as a lawsuit makes its way through federal court.
The case, filed under seal in 2011, recently was made public. It alleges that the Tutera Group Inc., which owns hundreds of nursing and skilled nursing facilities, bought durable medical equipment and supplies from Illinois-based Medline Inc. in exchange for illegal kickbacks and bribes.
Specifically, it accuses Tutera Group President Joe Tutera of establishing a shell company through which he funneled those bribes for more than a decade.
"We believe that the claims are completely false, and we'll vigorously defend them," Joe Tutera's counsel said in a statement. Joe Tutera is represented by Polsinelli PC.
Much of the evidence so far comes from Michael Tutera, who allegedly shared information about the Tutera Group's business dealings with friend and business associate August Bogina III in 2008 and 2009.
According to the petition, Michael Tutera held an ownership interest in the Tutera Group, which he sold in 2000. He remained associated with the company as a consultant and received half of any consulting fees or commissions, and at times participated in the alleged illegal dealings.
Bogina filed the lawsuit as a whistleblower on behalf of the federal government in what's known as a qui tam lawsuit.
Such lawsuits are sealed to give the government time to investigate the claims and decide whether it wants to intervene. According to a document filed with the court, the government was unable to complete its investigation of the case prior to the intervening deadline. However, it noted that the government would continue its investigation.
In the lawsuit, Bogina claims that Michael Tutera gave him copies of various contracts before he was killed, and Tutera's widow subsequently supplied him with information. Those contracts are included in court documents.
One such contract outlines an agreement between Medline and Walnut Creek Management Co. LLC - a company of which Joe Tutera is the president and managing member. In that agreement, Medline promised to pay a 5 percent "rebate/administrative fee" to Walnut Creek for every sale it made to the facilities owned by Tutera Group.
In 2007, Medline and Joe Tutera allegedly renewed the rebate agreement, which bumped up Walnut Creek's rebates to 10 percent.
The contracts note that the agreement would fall under the safe harbor provisions of federal anti-kickback statutes that allow discounts. However, the lawsuit alleges that certain conditions required for the discount to fall under the safe harbor provisions were not met.
The suit also alleges that Medline purchased a "membership share" of Walnut Creek in 2004 for "hundreds of thousands of dollars." The membership share did not entitle Medline to any money, voting rights or control of the company, the petition claims.
The membership was structured to decline in value each year until 2007 - when the administrative fee agreement was scheduled to end.
"There is no legitimate business purpose for Medline to purchase a 'membership share' of a shell company, which transacted no other business except to accept bribes and kickbacks from Medline for distribution to Joseph Tutera," the petition states.
In 2007, Joe Tutera repurchased Medline's membership share in Walnut Creek, which had declined in value almost entirely at that time, and resold it to Medline for $600,000.
This isn't the first time Medline has faced these types of accusations. In 2011, the company was ordered to pay an $85 million settlement after a whistleblower accused the company of paying fraudulent kickbacks to companies such as HCA Inc. and HealthSouth Corp.
An attorney for Medline told Reuters at the time that the company continued to deny the allegations and settled to avoid the cost of litigation.
"Corporate compliance is a top priority at Medline," John Marks, a corporate communications representative for Medline, said Tuesday in a statement. "We are committed to operating based on the highest standards of business conduct and ethics, and Medline has a comprehensive compliance program in place to ensure that we conduct our business in accordance with all applicable laws, rules and regulations. We believe that the lawsuit filed by Mr. Bogina is without merit, and we intend to vigorously defend the matter."
The Tutera lawsuit includes multiple counts of False Claims Act violations across multiple states. Summonses were issued to the defendants on March 5.
Named as defendants are Joe Tutera, Tutera Group Inc., Walnut Creek Management Co. LLC, Medline Industries Inc., Illinois Health Care Management II LLC and Tutera Investments LLC.
Michael Brady of Brady & Associates in Overland Park is co-counsel for the plaintiff. He declined to comment for this story. James Helmer Jr., president of Helmer Martins Rice & Popham Co. LPA in Cincinnati, joins him as co-counsel.
Michael Tutera was killed in 2010 when a group of individuals attempted to rob him in his home. Six people were charged and four have been sentenced.
Matthew Hendrix received a 25-year sentence, and his brother, Joseph Hendrix, was sentenced to 14 years. Troy Davis will serve 20 years and Robert Frazier will serve 12. Two others, Joel Thomas and Michael Dear, have not yet been sentenced.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Kansas City Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>