<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSB-11B1-JBG1-845V"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Associa Branch Companies Help Families in Need Through Associa Cares</title><source>Business Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Associa Cares , the philanthropic arm of Associa , recently donated relief funds to several families in need of assistance following the effects of natural or man-made disasters.
Associa Cares relies on volunteers from national and local committees to help identify people in both Associa and non-Associa managed communities affected by tragedies.
Below is a list of the Associa branches that helped families in need in their respective areas of the country.
Washington, D.C. - A donation was made possible through Community Management Corporation to two local families who were displaced from their homes due to house fires.Dallas, Texas - A donation was made possible through Associa headquarters to help a local family of four that lost everything in a house fire. Principal Management Group of North Texas also made a donation to a family whose home was destroyed by fire on New Year's Eve.Seattle, Washington - A donation was made possible through EMB Management to aid a family affected by a mobile home fire that destroyed all their belongings.Mt. Laurel, N.J. - A donation was made possible through Associa MAMCO to a local family who lost all of their possessions and home in a house fire.Houston, Texas - A donation was made possible through Houston Community Management Services to two local families who lost their homes and possessions in house fires. HCMS also donated to a family involved in a car accident that injured some members severely.Falls Church, Virginia - A donation was made possible through Legum & Norman to two local families whose pipes burst due to severe winter freezing, resulting in flooded houses and extensive interior damage.Dublin, Ohio - A donation was made possible through Real Property Management to a local family whose daughter was recently murdered. She was a single mother of two young children.Stockton, California - A donation was made possible through M & C Association Management Services to a local elderly homeowner who lost everything in a house fire.
"As soon as we learned of these incidents from the local committees, we immediately took action to help those affected," said Associa Cares President Joey Carona. "Associa Cares wants to help these families resume life and get back to normal living conditions as quickly as possible."
Associa Cares is a national nonprofit 501(c)(3) organization created to assist families and communities in crisis as a result of natural and man-made disasters. Through donations provided at fundraising events across the country, Associa Cares is able to provide necessary goods and services to the families affected by these types of tragedies. If you know of a family who has been the victim of a natural or man-made disaster, go directly to www.associacares.com to submit a request.
Building successful communities for more than 30 years, Associa is North America's largest community association management firm and serves its clients with local knowledge, national resources and comprehensive expertise. Based in Dallas, Associa and its 8,000 employees operate more than 150 branch offices in the United States, Mexico and Canada. To learn more about Associa and its charitable organization, Associa Cares, go to www.associaonline.com and www.associacares.com .
Find us online:Facebook: https://www.facebook.com/associa Twitter: https://twitter.com/associa LinkedIn: http://www.linkedin.com/company/33264 Pinterest: http://pinterest.com/associa/ YouTube: http://www.youtube.com/associamarketing Google+: https://plus.google.com/+Associaonline/
http://www.businesswire.com
]]></text></news-item>