<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSB-6FK1-JDJN-62DM"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Gay community watching Michigan for changes in legal landscape</title><source>Legal Monitor Worldwide</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[If you're overweight or old, pregnant or African American, your boss can't fire you for any of those reasons. The law says so. But if you're a gay man or lesbian, there's no such protection - one of several legal issues that weigh heavily on the gay community as it awaits a decision in Michigan's historic same-sex marriage trial.
With U.S. District Judge Bernard Friedman on the brink of deciding whether to legalize same-sex marriage in Michigan - a ruling could come as early as today - gay-rights activists say changes in the legal landscape are long overdue for the lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender (LGBT) community. The right to marry is just one battle, they say, arguing this group continues to face discrimination on a number of fronts. In the workplace, gay and lesbian people can be refused employment, get fired, demoted or harassed and there's no law that says that's illegal. And in the housing market, homosexuals can get evicted or denied mortgages, and that's not illegal, either. "There's quite a bit of progress that still needs to be made in Michigan," said Chicago attorney Christopher Clark of Lambda Legal, a national legal advocacy group for the LGBT community. "What comes as a surprise to many people is that there is no federal law that expressly prohibits discrimination in the workplace against LGBT individuals ... Someone can say, 'I don't want gay people here and so leave.' And that is legal in a lot of states, including Michigan." Nationwide, about 20 states have laws banning employment discrimination on the basis of sexual orientation. Michigan isn't one of them. The state has a discrimination statute - the 1976 Elliott-Larsen Civil Rights act - but it does not cover LGBT individuals. Legislative efforts have been made to include this group over the last decade, but with no success. Some lawmakers have argued that forcing a business to hire someone who goes against their religious beliefs is wrong and overreaching for the government. About 20 cities across the state, including Detroit, Ann Arbor and Ferndale, have local ordinances banning discrimination against gays and lesbians. Businesses, meanwhile, are taking action to protect LGBT employees from discrimination. According to Equality Michigan, 89% of the nation's Fortune 500 employers, including General Motors, Ford, AT&T and Hewlett-Packard, have nondiscrimination policies that include sexual orientation. Most recently, Wayne County Executive Robert Ficano signed an executive order in February adding sexual orientation and gender identity to the county's employment nondiscrimination policy, making Wayne the third county in the state to do so. Washtenaw and Ingham counties are the others.
"Sexual orientation and gender identity have nothing to do with someone's job performance. I am aware of the civil rights struggles of LGBT people around the country and here in Michigan. Progress is slow, but that doesn't mean we have to be slow in Wayne County," Ficano stated in February, when he also called on the state to expand its civil rights act to include LGBT community.  "As an employer, it is essential that we ensure there's room for all in our workforce," Ficano said. But legal experts say such ordinances and internal policies have no teeth and are hard to enforce. So when gays or lesbians get discriminated against or harassed at work, advocates say, they don't sue because their cases go nowhere. "It still surprises me how many people in our own communities don't even know this, who think, 'This can't be true,' " said attorney Yvonne Siferd, director of victim services at Detroit-based Equality Michigan, an advocacy group for the LGBT community. Siferd said she frequently gets calls from LGBT individuals about employment discrimination, but can't do much for them. "It's the worst part of my job - telling somebody, 'Well, that's totally legal,' " Siferd said. A civil rights battleIt's those kinds of stories that make Michigan's same-sex marriage decision all that much more important for the LGBT community, Siferd said. LGBT individuals are tired of unequal treatment, she said, adding a same-sex marriage ruling in their favor is long overdue. "It would be hugely symbolic," Siferd said. "This is a major civil rights battle that's going on across the country. Kentucky, Texas - all of these states, they're beating us." A federal judge in Virginia last year ruled that the state's ban is unconstitutional, following a similar ruling in Oklahoma. Utah would have been the 18th state to legalize gay marriage after a federal judge in December ruled its ban was unconstitutional. But the U.S. Supreme Court ordered a stay pending appeal by the state. The U.S. Supreme Court has not yet issued a definitive ruling on same-sex marriage. In June 2013, it did strike down a key part of the 1996 Defense of Marriage Act in declaring that gay couples married in states where it's legal must receive the same federal benefits as their heterosexual counterparts. But the high court stopped short of finding that all gay people have a fundamental right to marriage. That same day, the high court also left in place a lower court decision that said California's ban on same-sex marriage is unconstitutional. That ruling made same-sex marriage legal in 13 states and the District of Columbia, and allowed four other states to follow suit.
Michigan's landmark gay-marriage ruling also comes in the wake of growing public support of same-sex marriage. According to a February survey by the Public Religion Research Institute, 53% of Americans now support same-sex marriage, compared to 32% in 2003. In 2012, President Barack Obama announced his support for same-sex marriage, the first such admission by a sitting president. Still, Siferd noted, that legalizing same-sex marriage doesn't fix everything for the LGBT community. "It's definitely not the be-all, end-all of our struggle," Siferd said. "There's still a lot of work to be done." What defines marriage?At issue in Michigan's case is whether to uphold the will of 2.7 million voters, who decided in 2004 that marriage is a union only between one man and a woman; or, whether to strike down that vote as unconstitutional and give gay and lesbian people the right to marry. Michigan voters rejected gay marriage the same year Massachusetts became the first state in the nation to approve it. Michigan's case involves a lesbian couple, Jayne Rowse, 49, and April DeBoer, 42, who are raising three special-needs children together. They are fighting to overturn the ban so they can marry and adopt each other's children. The state has argued that the people have already spoken on this issue and the decision should stand. "This was not the whim of a few. ... This was the will of the people" Assistant State Attorney Kristin Heyse said in closing arguments in the Detroit case, noting the issue is likely to go before voters again. "Why not let the people decide?" Heyse also argued: "This case is not about the criminalization of same-sex acts; it's about the state's definition of marriage." She said it was not irrational for the voters to want to preserve the traditional definition of marriage or to want to enforce a belief that children thrive best when raised by moms and dads. "Moms and dads are different ... Kids benefit by having both," Heyse said, arguing that same-sex parenting research is too new to change public policy. "We're just not sure if allowing gays to marry would stabilize families." But plaintiffs' experts argued otherwise, saying there is no evidence that there are any differences in the outcomes of kids raised by same-sex couples versus those raised by married opposite-sex couples. The plaintiffs argued the latter shouldn't even be an issue because having kids isn't a prerequisite to getting married.
"For couples like April and Jayne, marriage is forbidden, because they love the wrong kind of person," attorney Ken Mogill said in closing arguments. The plaintiffs also tried to attack the credibility of the state's witnesses, arguing their religious views and opinions on gay marriage tainted their data. All four of the state's witnesses said they think Michigan should keep its ban on same-sex marriage and denied having any biases, saying their research was based on numbers, not views. Traditional-marriage supporters have lined the outside the courthouse every day of the nine-day trial. "We believe that marriage between one man and one woman creates the best possible environment for the health and wellness of children," said the Rev. Lennell Caldwell of the First Baptist World Changers Church International Ministries in Detroit. "While we agree that every American has a right to choose to live as he or she wants, no one is entitled to redefine marriage." Mark Baer, a family law attorney in Los Angeles who has closely followed the same-sex marriage debate and represents same-sex couples in legal disputes, said he thinks Friedman will overturn Michigan's ban. He said he thinks all states eventually will legalize gay marriage, noting public opinion is leaning in that direction, too. "It's going to happen one way or the other because the younger generations don't have a problem with it," Baer said. "In 10 to 20 years, it'll probably be legal in all the states, maybe even faster." © 2014 Legal Monitor Worldwide.
]]></text></news-item>