<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSB-HPK1-JCDS-Y2SB"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Croatia politics: HDZ and ex-PM Sanader found guilty of corruption</title><source>EIU ViewsWire Select</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A guilty verdictagainst a former Croatian prime minister, Ivo Sanader, and his party, the Croatian Democratic Union (HDZ), related to receiving illegal payments, will have a drastic impact on the HDZ's finances, and could significantly impair its ability to operate as a major political party. In addition, the verdict will further damage Croatians' confidence in their political elite more widely, which is likely to given an additional boost to the popularity of smaller and fringe parties. As a result, we see increased risks to political stability.
In perhaps the most important anti-corruption trial to date in Croatia Ivo Sanader, the country's prime minister from December 2003 until his surprise resignation in July 2009, was found guilty by a court of masterminding a scheme to siphon off funds from state companies via a marketing agency, Fimi Media. Mr Sanader is understood to have personally received at least HRK15m (US$2.7m), and perhaps significantly more, from the scheme. The former prime minister, already serving a ten-year sentence (since 2012) for taking a bribe from the sale of the state oil company, INA, to the Hungarian state oil company, MOL, was given a nine-year sentence, and will have a number of his assets seized.
Perhaps even more importantly, the main opposition HDZ, which has been in power for 16 of the 23 years since Croatian independence, was also found guilty of receiving payments illegally through the scheme, amounting to around HRK24m. The party was ordered to pay these funds back, together with a further fine of HRK5m. Both Mr Sanader and the HDZ will appeal against the verdict and, until the second-level court reaches a decision, the monetary fine against the HDZ will not come into operation. As court cases take an inordinate amount of time in Croatia, the appeal verdict is not expected until after the next parliamentary election, due to be held at the end of 2015.
The current HDZ leader, Tomislav Karamarko, although technically not a member of the party at the time of the affair, was head of the National Security Agency and later Minister of Internal Affairs for part of the period. Mr Karamarko openly criticised the court verdict and made it clear that the party does not believe in the fairness of the principle of collective responsibility and guilt, which he argues has been applied in this case. The verdict has far-reaching implications for the HDZ and may even call into question its survival as a significant political force. If the verdict is confirmed, the party will face huge financial difficulties and may well be placed in a disadvantaged position in relation to its main rival, the Social Democratic Party (SDP), which leads the current governing coalition. In the event of the fine being confirmed, the HDZ will be forced to sell some of its assets and make some core staff redundant, at the very least. For 2013, the HDZ declared an income of around HRK36m, not much more than the HRK29m that it will be forced to pay if the verdict is confirmed. Mr Karamarko has removed many, although by no means all, Sanader loyalists from positions of influence within the HDZ, but has not launched any internal investigation into the misuse of funds during the period concerned.
The verdict points to wider concerns about the lack of transparency of the financing of political parties in Croatia, all of whom already receive significant state funding. There is a wider sense that corruption is rife in all of the main political parties, and that when in government, politicians and parties put their own interests before those of the wider public. Those corruption trials that do occur are seen to reveal only a small part of the problem, and tend to be instigated only against those politicians, like Sanader, who are already out of power. As such, the verdict is likely to reduce still further the levels of support for the HDZ, which currently stand at a historically low level. At the same time, it further erodes public trust in the political system as a whole and even, perhaps, in the main government party, the SDP, whose levels of popularity are still continuing to fall as a result of perceived mismanagement of the economy and the party's own alleged involvement in corruption scandals.
]]></text></news-item>