<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSB-BYP1-F03R-N0N5"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Report Published: "Slovenia Pharmaceuticals Healthcare Report Q2 2014"</title><source>SBWire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 18, 2014 (SBWire:http://www.sbwire.com Delivered by Newstex) New Healthcare market report from Business Monitor International: "Slovenia Pharmaceuticals Healthcare Report Q2 2014"Boston, MA -- (SBWIRE[1]) -- 03/18/2014 -- Recapitalisation of Sloveniaaposs banks this year will continue to constrain budgets, with significant pressure on public healthcare spending. The country should benefit from an uptick in the regional economic outlook, though countryaposs unemployment rate and deleveraging by government and corporations will continue to put significant strain on the ZZZS, which is primarily dependent on insurance contributions. Spending cuts, pay freezes and price reductions for pharmaceuticals are all measures that could be employed to reduce the deficit. The pharmaceutical sector faces the prospect of price ceilings and further cost-cutting measures. As a result, we continue to believe pharmaceutical and healthcare spending will not show real growth until 2015 at the earliest.
View Full Report Details and Table of Contents[2]Headline Expenditure Projections - Pharmaceuticals: EUR720mn (US$950mn) in 2013 to EUR730mn (US$920mn) in 2014; +0.7% in local currency terms and -3.1% in US dollar terms. - Healthcare: EUR3.22bn (US$4.25bn) in 2013 to EUR3.18bn (US$4.04bn) in 2014; -1.1% in local currency terms and -4.8% in US dollar terms.Risk/Reward RatingSloveniaaposs Pharmaceutical Risk/Reward Rating score for Q214 stands at 50.9 out of a total of 100, just below the regional average of 51.5. A worsening economic outlook has impacted Sloveniaaposs RRR score.Key Trends Developments - In October 2013, four Slovenian drugmakers were accused of forming a drug cartel to manipulate wholesale drug prices in the country. The Competition Protection Agency (AVK) ruled that Kemofarmacija, Salus, Farmadent and Hopharm had colluded on the tender for the supply of drugs to public institutions and procurement of medicines for public pharmacy institutes. Although the four companies were charged for setting the prices of medicines at the highest permissible level at all times, they insist they did not breach competition laws in the country. - In October 2013 the Ministry of Health and the Health Institute of Slovenia (ZZZS) rolled out reimbursement limits based on therapeutic groups for proton pump inhibitor drugs. We believe this will be rolled out to other therapeutic groups in the near future.BMI Economic View: Slovenia continues to face a weak economic as a recapitalisation of the banking sector adds further strains to public finances. Private consumption remains heavily underwater, while fiscal pressures will act as a major brake on government consumption for at least the next two years, leaving exports as the sole driver of growth. Nonetheless, the improving regional outlook suggests that external demand should improve in 2014, providing one area of support for real GDP growth. We expect the recession to continue into 2014 (-0.48%), with only a modest return to growth in 2015 (1.0%).About Fast Market ResearchFast Market Research[3] is a leading distributor of market research and business information. Representing the worldaposs top research publishers and analysts, we provide quick and easy access to the best competitive intelligence available. Our unbiased, expert staff is always available to help you find the right research to fit your requirements and your budget. For more information about these or related research reports, please visit our website at http://www.fastmr.com[4] or call us at 1.800.844.8156.Browse all Healthcare research reports[5] at Fast Market ResearchYou may also be interested in these related reports: - Sweden Pharmaceuticals Healthcare Report Q2 2014[6] - Kenya Pharmaceuticals Healthcare Report Q2 2014[7] - Croatia Pharmaceuticals Healthcare Report Q2 2014[8] - Mexico Pharmaceuticals Healthcare Report Q2 2014[9] - Thailand Pharmaceuticals Healthcare Report Q2 2014[10] - Japan Pharmaceuticals Healthcare Report Q2 2014[11] - Australia Pharmaceuticals Healthcare Report Q2 2014[12] - Oman Pharmaceuticals Healthcare Report Q2 2014[13] - Jordan Pharmaceuticals Healthcare Report Q2 2014[14] - Algeria Pharmaceuticals Healthcare Report Q2 2014[15]For more information on this press release visit: http://www.sbwire.com/press-releases/report-published-slovenia-pharmaceuticals-healthcare-report-q2-2014-476929.htm[16] Media Relations Contact Bill Thompson Director of Marketing Telephone: 800-844-8156 Email: Click to Email Bill Thompson[17] Web: http://www.fastmr.com[18] [1]: http://www.sbwire.com/?utm_source=ntutm_medium=feedutm_campaign=distribution [2]: http://www.fastmr.com/prod/779527_slovenia_pharmaceuticals_healthcare_report_q2.aspx?afid=501 [3]: http://www.fastmr.com/?afid=501 [4]: http://www.fastmr.com/?afid=501 [5]: http://www.fastmr.com/catalog/browse.aspx?category=15afid=501 [6]: http://www.fastmr.com/prod/777807_sweden_pharmaceuticals_healthcare_report_q2_2014.aspx?afid=501 [7]: http://www.fastmr.com/prod/775199_kenya_pharmaceuticals_healthcare_report_q2_2014.aspx?afid=501 [8]: http://www.fastmr.com/prod/775186_croatia_pharmaceuticals_healthcare_report_q2_2014.aspx?afid=501 [9]: http://www.fastmr.com/prod/775203_mexico_pharmaceuticals_healthcare_report_q2_2014.aspx?afid=501 [10]: http://www.fastmr.com/prod/775447_thailand_pharmaceuticals_healthcare_report_q2.aspx?afid=501 [11]: http://www.fastmr.com/prod/775422_japan_pharmaceuticals_healthcare_report_q2_2014.aspx?afid=501 [12]: http://www.fastmr.com/prod/775153_australia_pharmaceuticals_healthcare_report_q2.aspx?afid=501 [13]: http://www.fastmr.com/prod/777797_oman_pharmaceuticals_healthcare_report_q2_2014.aspx?afid=501 [14]: http://www.fastmr.com/prod/777781_jordan_pharmaceuticals_healthcare_report_q2_2014.aspx?afid=501 [15]: http://www.fastmr.com/prod/775175_algeria_pharmaceuticals_healthcare_report_q2_2014.aspx?afid=501 [16]: http://www.sbwire.com/press-releases/report-published-slovenia-pharmaceuticals-healthcare-report-q2-2014-476929.htm?utm_source=ntutm_medium=feedutm_campaign=distribution [17]: http://www.sbwire.com/press-releases/contact/476929?utm_source=ntutm_medium=feedutm_campaign=distribution [18]: http://www.fastmr.com

]]></text></news-item>