<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSB-J0S1-JB4F-Y4SB"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Decision Diagnostic increases on weak volume</title><source>News Bites US Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Decision Diagnostics Corp (OTCBB:DECN), OTC's 24th largest computers-software/services company by market capitalisation, increased 0.01c (or 0.02%) to close at 50.0c. Compared with the NASDAQ-100 Index which rose 44.1 points (or 1.2%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -1.2%. The volume was 0.6 times the average trading of 171,790 shares.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Decision Diagnostic, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/0010522616603141638
Bullish Signals- A two-bagger in the past year, the present value of US$1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in Decision Diagnostic is US$2,439, for a capital gain of US$1,439.

NoteVolume: there were 101,500 shares worth US$50,750 traded. Beta: the Beta of Decision Diagnostic stock is 2.0. A Beta greater than 1 suggests this is a high risk, high return stock with volatility greater than that of the market. - Decision Diagnostic is at a discount of 53.7% to its 12-month high of US$1.08 on 19 Nov, 2013. It is also at a premium of 257.1% to the 12-month low of 14.0c on 13 Aug, 2013.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 11: Decision Diagnostics Announces Engagement of Mark Krakauer to Head Up Genstrip Private Label Sales Efforts[News Story] LOS ANGELES, CA - 03/11/14 -- Decision Diagnostics Corp. (OTCQB:DECN), the exclusive worldwide sales, service and regulatory processes agent for the popular Shasta GenStrip(TradeMark), the unique Green Glucose Test Strip, specifically designed to work with the Johnson & Johnson's LifeScan Ultra family of glucose testing meters, today announced that that the Company has engaged Mark Krakauer to lead the company's private label marketing strategy.
February 18: Decision Diagnostics Announces Agreement for Funding of Its Prosecution of Anti-Trust and False Advertising Suits Against Division of Johnson & Johnson[News Story] LOS ANGELES, CA 02/18/14 -- Decision Diagnostics Corp. (OTCQB:DECN), the exclusive worldwide sales, service and regulatory processes agent for the popular Shasta GenStrip(TradeMark), the unique Green Glucose Test Strip, specifically designed to work with the Johnson & Johnson's LifeScan Ultra family of glucose testing meters, today announced that that the Company has executed a Terms Agreement with a major east coast based litigation prosecution fund for the financing of the prosecution of DECN's countersuits brought against LifeScan, Inc., a division of Johnson and Johnson, Inc.
February 14: Decision Diagnostics Announces Agreement for the Funding of Its Prosecution of Anti-Trust and False Advertising Suits Against Division of Johnson & Johnson[News Story] LOS ANGELES, CA 02/14/14 -- Decision Diagnostics Corp. (OTCQB:DECN), the exclusive worldwide sales, service and regulatory processes agent for the popular Shasta GenStrip(TradeMark), the unique Green Glucose Test Strip, specifically designed to work with the Johnson & Johnson's LifeScan Ultra family of glucose testing meters, today announced that that the Company has executed a Terms Agreement with a major east coast based litigation prosecution fund for the financing of the prosecution of DECN's countersuits brought against LifeScan, Inc., a division of Johnson and Johnson, Inc.
January 15: Decision Diagnostics Announces Posting and Airing of Its New GenStrip Commercial Titled "A Winter Patchwork"[News Story] LOS ANGELES, CA - 01/15/14 -- Decision Diagnostics Corp. (OTCBB:DECN), the exclusive worldwide sales, service and regulatory processes agent for the Shasta GenStrip(TradeMark), the Green Glucose Test Strip, specifically designed to work with the Johnson & Johnson's (NYSE:JNJ) LifeScan Ultra family of glucose testing meters, today announced that its Pharma Tech Solutions subsidiary has completed and is airing in many regions in the U.S.
December 19: Decision Diagnostics Closes $12.5 Million (Non-Dilutive) Credit Facility With Division of Platinum Credit Management[News Story] LOS ANGELES, CA - 12/19/13 -- Decision Diagnostics Corp. (OTCBB:DECN) the exclusive worldwide sales, service and regulatory processes agent for the popular Shasta GenStrip(TradeMark), the unique Green Glucose Test Strip, specifically designed to work with the Johnson & Johnson's (NYSE:JNJ) LifeScan Ultra family of glucose testing meters, today announced that that the Company has closed its agreement for a $12.5 million revolving credit line from Alpha Credit Resources, LLC, a division of Platinum Credit Management LP of New York, NY.The company also announced that the new $12.5 million credit line will be equity free (no share dilution) and when matched with the company's current 1.8X sales turns per month (velocity), this credit facility will finance company sales of its GenStrip product line through $250+ million annually.
December 17: Decision Diagnostics Receives Mandate From U.S. Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit in the Long Running Dispute With J&J Division[News Story] LOS ANGELES, CA - 12/17/13 -- Decision Diagnostics Corp. (OTCBB:DECN), the exclusive worldwide sales, service and regulatory processes agent for the popular Shasta GenStrip(TradeMark), the unique Green Glucose Test Strip, specifically designed to work with the Johnson & Johnson's (NYSE:JNJ) LifeScan Ultra family of glucose testing meters, today announced that on December 11, 2013 the United States Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit issued its Mandate, making its November 4, 2013 ruling final.
December 10: Decision Diagnostics' Board Votes to Uplist to OTC QX[News Story] LOS ANGELES, CA 12/10/13 -- Decision Diagnostics Corp. (OTCBB:DECN), the exclusive worldwide sales, service and regulatory processes agent for the popular Shasta GenStrip(TradeMark), the unique Green Glucose Test Strip, specifically designed to work with the Johnson & Johnson's (NYSE:JNJ) LifeScan Ultra family of glucose testing meters, today announced that the company's Board of Directors has approved the company's uplisting to the OTC QX, the Premier OTC Market Tier.
ISIN: US45776H2085
OTC:DECN; US:DECN
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>