<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSB-1091-DY93-M4CJ"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>AFPTV Agenda</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[We plan to file the following videos on Wednesday. Please check the daily advisories for any additions and amendments:
-- TOP WORLD NEWS --
+ UKRAINE
KIEV/SIMFEROPOL, UKRAINE: Rolling news coverage of events in Ukraine and Crimea. RAW. TBA
MOSCOW: Reactions from Moscow to Ukraine crisis. RAW. TBA
DONETSK, UKRAINE: After Crimea's vote to join Russia, opinions are starkly divided in the eastern city of Donetsk, home of outsted President Viktor Yanukovych. PKG. 1100 GMT
WASHINGTON: NATO Secretary-General Anders Fogh Rasmussen delivers remarks on the importance of the alliance in an unpredictable world. RAW. 2200 GMT
-- OTHER WORLD NEWS --
+ AFRICA
PRETORIA: News coverage of the Oscar Pistorius trial. RAW. TBA
JUBA: Trial resumes in South Sudan of four top leaders accused of treason for allegedly attempting to topple President Salva Kiir after fighting broke out in December. RAW. TBC
JOHANNESBURG: The National Union of Metalworkers of South Africa (Numsa) strikes against the Employment Tax Incentive Act and in demand of jobs for the youth. RAW. 1100 GMT.
PRETORIA: South Africa's Public Protector releases her findings on President Jacob Zuma's state-funded homestead. Approximately 20 million dollars has been spent upgrading the president's home in Nkandla, KwaZulu Natal -- on a security fence, helipad and houses for his relatives. RAW. 1300 GMT.
We will refile the following report on Nkandla:
NKANDLA, SOUTH AFRICA: As South Africa prepares to vote in the upcoming fifth democratic elections, scandal rages around President Jacob Zuma's residence, threatening his support at the crucial polls. PKG. 0900 GMT.
+ ASIA-PACIFIC
KUALA LUMPUR: Monitoring the search for a Malaysia Airlines jet that vanished with 239 people on board. RAW. TBA
BEIJING: Relatives of the Chinese passengers continue their wait for news in a Beijing hotel. RAW. TBA
KABUL: Afghanistan goes to the polls in two weeks' time, but the new president will have only sketchy information about the people he governs -- something that census officials are hoping to help rectify. PKG 0700 GMT
+ EUROPE
LONDON: Finance minister George Osborne delivers his annual budget. RAW. 1030 GMT
VIENNA: Second round of talks between Iran and world powers aimed towards a final nuclear deal. RAW. 1200 GMT
ROME: The head of the Veneto region, Luca Zaia, holds a press conference amid a drive by separatists in the north to split off from Italy and form a new state. RAW. 1400 GMT
THE HAGUE: Nelson Mandela's daughter Makaziwe and one of his granddaughters launch their wine brand, 'House of Mandela.' RAW. TBA
LONDON: New exhibition of African art in the British capital. RAW. 1600 GMT
LONDON: 'Bond In Motion' exhibition on James Bond film vehicles opens in London. RAW. 1200 GMT
PARIS: Court delivers decision in rogue Societe Generale trader Jerome Kerviel's appeal. RAW. 1600GMT
PARIS: French President Francois Hollande meets Argentinian President Kristina Kirchner. RAW. 1400 GMT
TOULOUSE, France: Memorial for the seven people killed in an anti-Semitic shooting spree in Toulouse two years ago. RAW. 1600GMT
PARIS: Médecins sans Frontières give their report of the atrocities in Central African Republic. RAW. 1400 GMT
PARIS: Hideo Kojima, also known as the Steven Spielberg of gaming, will present the 5th part of the popular video game series "Metal Gear Solid. RAW. 1200GMT
PARIS: Australian singer Kylie Minogue will be signing copies of her new album "Kiss Me Once" in Paris. RAW. 2000 GMT
+ NORTH AMERICA
WASHINGTON: The Federal Reserve decides whether to raise, lower or maintain the US rate of interest, followed by a press conference with chairman Janet Yellen. RAW. On merit.
BALTIMORE, MARYLAND: It's all about the moves for the Baltimore Ravens - and not just for the players. Technique, strength and smooth skills are a must for its cheerleaders too, who hold yearly tryouts for a coveted spot on the recent Superbowl champs' co-ed squad. PKG. 2200 GMT
+ MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
GHARDAIA, ALGERIA: Families mourn after deadly events in Ghardaia. RAW. TBA
CAIRO: Corruption trial of former Egyptian president Hosni Mubarak and his sons resumes. RAW. TBC
JERUSALEM : Ultra-Orthodox Jews protest in several Israeli cities against a recent law that would see young religious Jews conscripted. RAW. TBC.
+ LATIN AMERICA & CARIBBEAN
ARY RONGEL: To get to Antarctica, the brazilian warship "Ary Rongel" has to cross the Drake passage, one of the most dangerous in the world. PKG. 23H00 GMT
MENDOZA, Argentina: Stockshots. 03H00 GMT
-- FEATURES --
TEHRAN : The acrobatic sport of parkour is increasingly popular in Tehran. And women in the Islamic Republic are rising above social constraints to practise the sport with dedication and determination. PKG. 0500 GMT
MANZANARES, Spain: Spain became the world's biggest wine producer in 2013, forcing its vintners to compete abroad in a tough market to sell off the surplus. PKG. TBA
Contact:
London desk: +44 207 776 2768
Hong Kong desk: +852 2829 6216
Nicosia desk: +357 22 391 453
Washington desk: +1 202 414 0550
Montevideo desk: +598 2 900 5095 ext 257
For contact via email: afptv-en@afp.com
aftpv
]]></text></news-item>