<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSD-P0W1-DYRX-X3XS"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Japanese firm accused of trading in ivory and whale meat</title><source>The Guardian (London)</source><author>Justin McCurry Tokyo</author><text><![CDATA[The Japanese e-commerce company Rakuten, which owns the entertainment site Play.com and the e-reader Kobo, is also the world's biggest online retailer of elephant ivory and whale meat, conservationists have claimed.
According to a report by the UK-based Environmental Investigation Agency (EIA) and the Humane Society International (HSI), Rakuten's website carries more than 28,000 advertisements for elephant ivory and 1,200 for whale products.
Many of the whale products originate from species protected since 1986 under the moratorium on commercial whaling established by the International Whaling Commission, the groups say in the report, entitled Blood E-Commerce.
Sale of the species is prohibited under the convention on international trade in endangered species of wild fauna and flora, it says, adding: "Despite this, a number of companies were selling endangered fin whale imported from Iceland."
Fourteen of the products fail to list the names of the species used, in violation of Japanese labelling laws, the report says.
"We call on Rakuten subsidiaries in the US, UK, Canada, France, Germany, Austria and elsewhere to urgently press Rakuten headquarters in Japan to ban all ads offering ivory and whale products," said Kitty Block, vice-president of the HSI.
The company, with operating profits of $244m (£147m) in 2012 and more than 10,000 employees worldwide, has expanded its presence in recent years. Acquisitions include Buy.com (now Rakuten Shopping) in the US and Play.com in the UK. It owns the Canadian Kobo, and is a major shareholder in Pinterest.
Rakuten did not respond to the Guardian's requests for comment. On its website it states: "We are committed to promoting policies which will prevent global warming and protect the environment."
The firm's claim that it wished to protect the environment "can only be cynical lip service as long as it banks the profits of products derived from threatened or endangered species," Clare Perry, head of the EIA's cetaceans campaign, said.
Japanese supermarket chains including Ito-Yokado and Seiyu have prohibited the sale of whale and dolphin products in thousands of stores, while Amazon and Google have stopped all sales and advertisements of whale, dolphin and ivory through their Japanese e-commerce sites.
About 22,000 African elephants were killed in 2012. At that rate, conservationists warn, the animals could become extinct in some areas. About 80% of tusks in Japan are used to make hanko, personal seals that are commonly used to sign documents. Other items on the Rakuten site included a large carved tusk selling for 2.94m yen ($28,186).
"Rakuten's ads are effectively as deadly as giving bullets to elephant poachers and harpoons to whalers," said the EIA's president, Allan Thornton. "(It) must act immediately to ban all ads selling elephant and whale products, or its global brand will be irrevocably tainted with the ongoing mass slaughter of these species."
]]></text></news-item>