<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSD-NYP1-JCXB-211K"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Glencore Xstrata PLC 2013 Annual Report -4-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[MITIGATION: The risk of disruptions to or limitations of freight, storage, infrastructure and logistics support is mitigated through the Group's market position, global reach and its longstanding relationships with third party suppliers of freight. These give the Group an advantage in ensuring its commodity transport needs are met along with its investments in storage and logistic assets such as vessels, oil terminals and tank farms, metals and other warehouses and grain silos.
INDUSTRIAL ACTIVITIES Non-controlling stakes, joint ventures and strategic partnerships or agreements Some of the Group's industrial assets are held through non-controlling stakes or joint ventures and strategic partnership arrangements. IMPACT: The Group does not control a number of its industrial investments. Although the Group has various structures in place which seek to protect its position where it does not exercise control, the boards of these companies may: -- Have economic or business interests or goals that are inconsistent with or are opposed to those of the Group; -- Exercise veto rights or take shareholders' decisions so as to block actions that the Group believes to be in its best interests and/or in the best interests of all shareholders; -- Take action contrary to the Group's policies or objectives with respect to investments or commercial arrangements; or -- As a result of financial or other difficulties be unable or unwilling to fulfil their obligations under any joint venture or other agreement, such as contributing capital to expansion or maintenance projects. Improper management or ineffective policies, procedures or controls of a non-controlled entity could adversely affect the business, results of operations and financial condition of the relevant investment and, therefore, of the Group. MITIGATION: Where projects and operations are controlled and managed by the Group's co-investors or where control is shared on an equal basis, the Group actively participates in the governance structures of the co-managed operation to ensure, where possible, with the Group's policies and/or objectives. Project development The Group has a number of significant expansions planned for its existing operations and plans for certain new projects, the development of which is exposed to a number of risks outside of its control such as technical uncertainties, infrastructure constraints, cost overruns, insufficient labour skills or resources and delays in permitting or other regulatory matters. IMPACT: Any future upward revisions in estimated project costs, delays in completing planned expansions, cost overruns, suspension of current projects or other operational difficulties after commissioning, may have a material adverse effect on the Group's business, results of operations, financial condition or prospects, in turn requiring the Group to consider delaying discretionary expenditures, including capital expenditures, or suspending or altering the scope of one or more of its development projects. MITIGATION: Project development risks are mitigated and managed through the Group's continuous project status evaluation and reporting processes, the significant focus of such being appropriate approval processes and transparent and timely reporting of costs and progress relative to plan. Significant projects are regularly audited against the project plan and reporting processes. Operating risks and hazards The Group's industrial activities are subject to numerous operating risks and hazards normally associated with the development and operation of natural resource projects, many of which are beyond the Group's control. These operating risks and hazards include unanticipated variations in grade and other geological problems, seismic activity, climatic conditions such as flooding or drought, metallurgical and other processing problems, technical failures, unavailability of materials and equipment, interruptions to power supplies, industrial actions or disputes, industrial accidents, labour force disruptions, unanticipated logistical and transportation constraints, tribal action or political protests, force majeure factors, environmental hazards, fire, explosions, vandalism and crime. IMPACT: These risks and hazards could result in damage to, or destruction of, properties or production facilities, may cause production to be reduced or to cease at those properties or production facilities, may result in a decrease in the quality of the products, personal injury or death, environmental damage, business interruption and legal liability and may result in actual production differing from estimates of production. The realisation of such operating risks and hazards and the costs associated with them could materially adversely affect the Group's business, results of operations and financial condition, including by requiring significant capital and operating expenditures to abate the risk or hazard, restore the Group or third party property, compensate third parties for any loss and/or pay fines or damages. MITIGATION: Operating risks and hazards are managed through the Group's continuous assessment, reporting and communication of the risks that affect its business through its annual risk review processes and updates to its risk register. In addition, risk is mitigated somewhat through geographic and multiple project diversification. Title to the land, resource tenure and extraction rights The Group has industrial investments in certain countries where title to land and rights in respect of land and resources (including indigenous title) has not been and may not always be clear, creating the potential for disputes over resource development. Title to the Group's mining and hydrocarbon rights may be challenged or impugned, and title insurance may not generally be available. In many cases, the government of the country in which a particular asset is located is the sole authority able to grant such rights and, in some cases, may have limited infrastructure and limited resources which may constrain the Group's ability to ensure that it has obtained secure title to individual exploration licences or extraction rights. IMPACT: Any dispute, relating to a material industrial asset, could disrupt or delay relevant mining, processing or other projects and/or impede the Group's ability to develop new industrial properties, which may have a material adverse effect on the Group's business, results of operations and financial condition. MITIGATION: Title and tenure risks are managed through geographical diversification of commodities and operations, continuous monitoring and dialogue through and with the Group's network of local offices and a commitment to engage proactively with employees, governments and the communities in which the Group operates to maintain and better its licence to operate. Availability of infrastructure The production, processing and product delivery capabilities of the Group's industrial assets rely on their infrastructure being adequate and remaining available. IMPACT: The mining, drilling, processing, development and exploration activities of the industrial assets in which the Group holds an interest depend on adequate infrastructure. Certain of these assets are located in areas that are sparsely populated and difficult to access. Reliable roads, power sources, transport infrastructure and water supplies are essential for the conduct of these operations and the availability and cost of these utilities and infrastructure affect capital and operating costs and therefore the Group's ability to maintain expected levels of production and results of operations. Unusual weather or other natural phenomena, sabotage or other interference in the maintenance or provision of such infrastructure could impact the development of a project, reduce production volumes, increase extraction or exploration costs or delay the transportation of raw materials to the mines and projects and commodities to end customers. Any such issues arising in respect of the infrastructure supporting or on the Group's sites could have a material adverse effect on the Group's business, results of operations, financial condition and prospects. MITIGATION: Availability of infrastructure risk is mitigated through long-term supply agreements and the continuous monitoring through the Group's network of local offices, and a commitment to engage proactively with governments and the communities in which the Group operates to maintain and improve its licence to operate. In addition, where appropriate, we establish back-up sources of power. Cost control As commodity prices are outside of the Group's control, the competitiveness and sustainable long-term profitability of its industrial asset portfolio depends significantly on its ability to closely manage costs and maintain a broad spectrum of low-cost, efficient operations. Costs associated with the operation of the Group's industrial assets can be broadly categorised into labour costs and other on-site expenses, including power and equipment costs. IMPACT: Production costs are heavily influenced by the extent of ongoing development required, ore grades, mine planning, processing technology, logistics, energy and supply costs and the impact of exchange rate fluctuations on costs of operations. All of the Group's industrial assets are, to varying degrees, affected by increases in costs for labour and fuel. Unit production costs are also significantly affected by production volumes and therefore production levels are frequently a key factor in determining the overall cost competitiveness of the Group's industrial activities. Any increase in input costs will adversely affect the Group's results of operations and financial condition.
]]></text></news-item>