<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-R621-JBVM-Y3TK"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Blatter urged to end his battered reign; Palios says Fifa president has 'overstayed welcome' Qatar corruption claims are foolish, Warner insists</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Ben Rumsby</author><text><![CDATA[Mark Palios, the former Football Association chief executive, warned last night that Fifa might never escape from its corrupt past while Sepp Blatter remained president, after the legitimacy of the 2018 and 2022 World Cup votes was plunged into further doubt.
The existence of documents appearing to confirm that a Fifa vice-president was paid millions in the wake of the votes in 2010 was revealed by The Daily Telegraph yesterday more than three years after allegations of bribery first emerged around the controversial contest.
The documents show the disgraced former executive committee member Jack Warner and his family received almost £1.2 million from a Qatari firm linked to the country's successful bid for the 2022 tournament.
Mohammed Bin Hammam, another ousted vice-president of football's world governing body, appeared to be behind the payments, made before he was banned for life for attempting to buy votes during his 2011 campaign for the presidency.
Despite Warner, Bin Hammam and other corrupt officials having long been banished from football, they continue to cast a shadow over Fifa, of which Blatter has been the public face during a tarnished 16 years for the organisation.
The Swiss himself has been cleared of any wrongdoing amid the numerous scandals to dog Fifa in that time but he has also been accused of failing to do enough to prevent them. Palios believes that trust in the organisation's credibility may never be restored until Blatterfinally stands aside. "If you look at governance, he's obviously overstayed his welcome," Palios said, urging a two-term limit on the presidency.
"I think it's probably right to say that people will tread water in terms of their expectations until such time as Sepp Blatter leaves the scene."
Fifa's refusal to comment on the outcome of The Daily Telegraph's investigation yesterday, short of directing those with any evidence of wrongdoing to its ethics committee, did little to challenge that view.
Blatter may have no choice other than to confront the revelations on Friday, provided he attends the traditional press conference at the end of Fifa's two-day executive committee in Zurich.
Having also refused to comment when approached during The Daily Telegraph's investigation, Warner himself finally spoke out yesterday, saying only: "I have no interest in joining in the foolishness that is now passing as news on Qatar and Jack Warner. Nor do I intend to join those who are on a witch hunt against the World Cup 2022 venue."
Palios said confirmation that payments were made to Warner by Bin Hammam that were now being probed by the FBI reinforced his view that the 2018 and 2022 World Cup bidding process had been "totally discredited". He said: "Regrettably, people will not be surprised as regards allegations now of payments having been made."
Palios also urged the man investigating allegations of corruption during the 2010 vote, US lawyer Michael J Garcia, to examine any new evidence that had come to light.
That call was echoed by a senior official from England's doomed 2018 World Cup bid, its chief operating officer, Simon Johnson.
Johnson, who was interviewed by Garcia last year, said: "This is a very disturbing piece of evidence that The Daily Telegraph has found and it is right and proper that Fifa fully considers the evidence that has been uncovered and that any evidence which is in any way relevant to the award of the 2018 or 2022 Fifa World Cup is made available to the investigation being conducted by Mr Michael Garcia."
Garcia is expected to report his findings by the end of the year and were he to find serious evidence of wrongdoing it would put Fifa under huge pressure to rerun one or both of the bids. As would anything of that nature uncovered by the FBI, which is understood to be investigating the payment made to Warner and his family with the apparent cooperation of his eldest son.
Establishing the precise nature of the payment would appear to be crucial, with Warner and Bin Hammam's refusal to explain it raising suspicions that it was not above board but leaving it unclear whether or not it related to Qatar's World Cup bid, Bin Hammam's doomed attempt to oust Blatter or something else entirely.
Without further proof or a confession that it was a bribe for the former, the documents seen by The Daily Telegraph are unlikely to be the smoking gun that would threaten the Gulf State's hosting of the tournament.
Bin Hammam was not directly involved with his country's 2022 bid and those who were have repeatedly insisted that they did not breach any Fifa rules.
Palios said that the bidding process should not be rerun unless Garcia proved that the bid team itself were guilty of buying votes, but he did call for Fifa to examine "tooth and nail" how it awards its tournaments in future. He said it should follow the example of the International Olympic Committee in the wake of the Salt Lake City scandal but also go further by abolishing its secret ballot.
"I'd say, 'If you don't want that, why don't you want it?'" he said. "Why would you have difficulty in terms of saying who you voted for?"
Unlike Warner, Bin Hammam remained silent yesterday following The Daily Telegraph investigation, as did others involved in England's 2018 bid. Geoff Thompson, the former FA chairman who was on the Fifa ExCo in 2010, declined to comment.
"People will tread water in terms of their expectations until such time as Sepp Blatter leaves the scene
]]></text></news-item>