<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-R2Y1-DXX7-H404"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>ICAC hears Arthur Sinodinos's $200,000 salary seemed a lot for attending monthly meetings</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author>By Emma Renwick</author><text><![CDATA[A witness has told a corruption inquiry Arthur Sinodinos's $200,000 salary did seem a lot for a role that required only attendance at monthly board meetings.
William Macgregor-Fraser, the former director and co-founder of Australian Water Holdings (AWH), is being questioned in relation to claims that some people connected to AWH made corrupt financial gains by "adversely affecting the official functions" of the state-owned Sydney Water Corporation.
The Independent Commission Against Corruption (ICAC) has heard that those costs included the retention of directors and board members for AWH who had powerful political connections on both sides of politics.
Counsel assisting Geoffrey Watson questioned Mr Macgregor-Fraser about what Senator Sinodinos, then an AWH director and treasurer of the NSW Liberal Party, provided to the company in the way of expertise, or whether he was just there to open Liberal Party doors.
Mr Macgregor-Fraser said he did not think Mr Sinodinos had any special knowledge of water or sewerage and denied he was there to open doors.
Under questioning he conceded that $200,000 did seem like a lot for attending monthly board meetings.
Mr Macgregor-Fraser disputed claims that Sydney Water directly paid extraordinary costs associated with his company's expenses.
Mr Watson questioned Mr Macgregor-Fraser about a board meeting in early 2011 where the retention of powerful Liberal lobbyist Michael Photios on a monthly retainer of $5,000 a month was discussed.
Mr Watson revealed documents that showed a potential payment of $1 million to Mr Photios but the board minutes did not reveal what that payment would be for.
Co-founder 'didn't have time' to tell Sydney Water about his salary
Earlier today Mr Macgregor-Fraser was asked about the doubling of his salary to $750,000 per annum.
Mr Macgregor-Fraser said he did not see the need to tell Sydney Water that his salary had doubled and that he did not have time to tell them despite meeting with them on an almost daily basis.
Other costs revealed in the inquiry were hundreds of dollars in chauffeur bills for employees of AWH who were attending sporting functions.
One of those employees was Eddie Obeid Jr, the son of disgraced former Labor minister Eddie Obeid.
Mr Macgregor-Fraser also revealed more than once he organised large lump sum expenses to the order of $20,000 to company director Nick Di Girolamo.
When asked what the money was used for, he said, "It wasn't my job to question how he spent the money."
Mr Di Girolamo is a well known Liberal Party fundraiser and the inquiry has heard he was a long-time family friend of the Obeid family.
]]></text></news-item>