<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-R621-JBVM-Y3VT"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Leeds face crisis after Cellino's conviction; Italian could fail League's 'fit and proper person' test Administration a genuine threat if sale falls through</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Luke Edwards</author><text><![CDATA[Leeds United are facing financial turmoil and the threat of administration because a takeover bid by the Italian businessman Massimo Cellino appears to be on the verge of collapse.
Cellino's attempt to take a 75 per cent stake in the Championship club is likely to be blocked by the Football League after he was found guilty of tax evasion in Italy, although sources have stressed that the League is still looking into the case and has not made a final decision.
If Leeds were put into administration they would automatically be docked 10 points, which would leave them just five points above the Championship's relegation zone. That is not in the interests of the present owner, GFH Capital. It will try to keep the club running while it waits for a decision, although it is thought that it has been able to do that in recent weeks only because of money provided by Cellino.
Cellino agreed to buy Leeds from GFH Capital through a family company, Eleonora Sports, on Feb 1, but he has been unable to take control because of Football League rules designed to protect clubs from unsuitable owners.
The 57-year-old was already under investigation under the "fit and proper person" test because of previous financial irregularity charges during his time as owner of the Italian club Cagliari, before the guilty verdict on a tax evasion charge.
The rule prevents anyone with unspent dishonesty convictions from taking control of an English club, and although Cellino is likely to appeal against the guilty verdict for the nonpayment of tax on a yacht he bought in the United States, Leeds are left facing an uncertain future.
Cellino has been providing considerable funds to cover running costs at Elland Road while he waits for the Football League to ratify the deal he struck with GFH Capital.
It is thought that Cellino has covered the staff wage bill for the past two months and also paid off a loan from Enterprise Insurance, the shirt sponsor, to prevent a winding-up order. Leeds have also been able to sign goalkeeper Jack Butland on loan from Stoke City and striker Connor Wickham from Sunderland because of money provided by Eleonora Sports.
If the Football League were to block Cellino's takeover - it is still discussing its position with the Italian's lawyers - Leeds would not only have to try to find a new buyer, they would also be likely to have to repay him the money he has spent on the club.
David Haigh, the Leeds managing director, insisted last week that there was "no chance" of the club going into administration, but that may change if Cellino were to withdraw his investment.
The Daily Telegraph attempted to contact GFH Capital to clarify the situation, but there has been no response from the Bahrain-based investment group.
A Football League spokesman said: "The Football League has noted the outcome of the court hearing earlier today regarding Massimo Cellino. We are engaged in an ongoing dialogue with his legal representatives in this country and cannot comment further at this time."
A rival consortium to Cellino, headed by Andrew Flowers, chief executive of Enterprise Insurance, withdrew its offer to take control at Elland Road at the end of January.
Another bid, from a group called Together Leeds, had a "derisory" offer rejected by GFH Capital in November, but is thought to remain interested in a deal.
]]></text></news-item>