<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-BF51-JC86-32VV"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Tricentis Partners With Wipro to Accelerate Enterprise Business Innovation; Tricentis Tosca Testsuite Solution Available to Wipro's Global 1000 Customers</title><source>Marketwired</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Tricentis, a global leader in enterprise software testing solutions that accelerate business innovation, today announced that it has entered into a strategic partnership and launched the Tricentis Tosca Testing Center of Excellence with Wipro Ltd. (NYSE: WIT), a leading global information technology, consulting and outsourcing company. This partnership will provide Tricentis and Wipro clients with best-in-class enterprise testing solutions to automate the application testing process, scale testing operations, significantly accelerate speed and efficiency, and minimize business risk.
The partnership will deliver value to clients with model-based software test automation, thought leadership and best practices based on Tricentis' next-generation testing platform technology. It will also enable enterprise-class, industry-specific testing scenarios to help clients realize immediate benefits.
"Software has become the face of your company today. As such, it has become a pillar of building brand value," said Michael Eckhoff, senior vice president, Tricentis. "This partnership will extend the Tricentis advantage to Wipro's global customers, allowing them to successfully harness the power of software to accelerate business innovation, optimize cost and efficiencies, and reduce business-related risks."
Kumudha Sridharan, Vice President, Testing Services, Wipro Ltd., said, "Wipro's Testing Center of Excellence, combined with the Tricentis product suite, will enable us to address our clients' complex business challenges in a constantly changing technology landscape while at the same time we reduce costs and drive efficiency. This partnership is indicative of our Testing Service Line's efforts to enhance our differentiation in the global quality-assurance market."
Wipro offers end-to-end solutions for testing services to global customers in a wide range of areas such as Mobility, Cloud, Analytics, Automation, Performance, Data Centric, SOA and functional across various domains. Wipro's unique approach of focusing on all three dimensions of Testing process expertise, technology specialization and domain focus enables them to provide true Business assurance to their clients. Wipro's testing service line leverages in-house and best-in-class process frameworks and methodologies, tools and solutions to deliver effectiveness and productivity in the Business Assurance journey of its clients. Wipro's solutions, specialized practices and advisory services help their clients 'do business better'.
The Tricentis Tosca Testsuite is a seamless solution providing test teams with unprecedented power to measure, manage and control risk coverage. From the ability to generate test cases based on atomic knowledge of risk, to the simplicity of model-based test automation that enables test execution in plain English, to real-time analytics for proactive optimization, the approach delivers entirely new levels of ease and accuracy while minimizing time, effort and cost. Tosca Testsuite integrates with SAP, Application Lifecycle Management (ALM) and other testing solutions, and interfaces with the full range of applications demanded by today's enterprise environments.
About Wipro
Wipro Ltd. (WIT) is a leading Information Technology, Consulting and Outsourcing company that delivers solutions to enable its clients do business better. Wipro delivers winning business outcomes through its deep industry experience and a 360 degree view of "Business through Technology" -- helping clients create successful and adaptive businesses. A company recognized globally for its comprehensive portfolio of services, a practitioner's approach to delivering innovation, and an organization wide commitment to sustainability, Wipro has a workforce of 140,000 serving clients across 61 countries. For more information, please visit www.wipro.com
About Tricentis
Tricentis provides the leading enterprise software testing solutions for Global 2000 companies to accelerate business innovation with peace of mind. The unique Tricentis approach to software testing enables enterprises to achieve unprecedented automation rates while minimizing business-related risks. Tricentis solutions empower organizations to systematically align software testing with business needs, so they can harness technology change while optimizing cost and efficiency. The company's more than 400 customers include global brands such as Allianz, BMW, Deutsche Bank, HBO, Orange, Siemens, Southwest, Swiss Re, and UBS. Tricentis also has the highest customer renewal rate in the industry, at more than 98 percent, and its industry awards include Best in Test 2013. Gartner recognizes Tricentis as a visionary in the recent 2013 Magic Quadrant for Integrated Software Quality Suites. A fast growing, privately held company, Tricentis has offices in Austria, Germany, Switzerland, the UK, the Netherlands, the United States, Australia, and Singapore. To learn more, visit www.tricentis.com or Contact Sales or follow us on LinkedIn, Twitter and Facebook.
Forward-looking and Cautionary Statements Certain statements in this release concerning our future growth prospects are forward-looking statements, which involve a number of risks, and uncertainties that could cause actual results to differ materially from those in such forward-looking statements. The risks and uncertainties relating to these statements include, but are not limited to, risks and uncertainties regarding fluctuations in our earnings, revenue and profits, our ability to generate and manage growth, intense competition in IT services, our ability to maintain our cost advantage, wage increases in India, our ability to attract and retain highly skilled professionals, time and cost overruns on fixed-price, fixed-time frame contracts, client concentration, restrictions on immigration, our ability to manage our international operations, reduced demand for technology in our key focus areas, disruptions in telecommunication networks, our ability to successfully complete and integrate potential acquisitions, liability for damages on our service contracts, the success of the companies in which we make strategic investments, withdrawal of fiscal governmental incentives, political instability, war, legal restrictions on raising capital or acquiring companies outside India, unauthorized use of our intellectual property, and general economic conditions affecting our business and industry. Additional risks that could affect our future operating results are more fully described in our filings with the United States Securities and Exchange Commission. These filings are available at www.sec.gov. We may, from time to time, make additional written and oral forward-looking statements, including statements contained in the company's filings with the Securities and Exchange Commission and our reports to shareholders. We do not undertake to update any forward-looking statement that may be made from time to time by us or on our behalf.
SOURCE: Tricentis
]]></text></news-item>