<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-1GR1-JCB3-40S9"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Twice-Told Tales</title><source>San Jose Mercury News (California)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[60 years ago
Case against coroner tossed out of court: Owners of funeral homes throughout the county greeted with satisfaction the recent action of Superior Judge Norman Gregg when he granted a demurrer without leave to amend in the $120,000 damage conspiracy suit brought by Vincent Caruso and Roger F. Magleby, operators of a Pittsburg funeral home against Dr. C. L. Abbott, county coroners and 14 owners and employees of funeral homes.
The move, it is explained, has the effect of throwing the action out of court. District Attorney Francis W. Collins and T. H. DeLap, Richmond attorney, represented Dr. Abbott and his co-defendants.
The complaint alleged that Dr. Abbott's appointment of funeral personnel has caused a large financial loss to Caruso and Magleby. Roy Bartheld, deputy coroner in Brentwood, said that the allegations in the complaint were deeply resented by funeral home operators as a reflection of their integrity and business methods.
25 years ago
Handicapped band together, help each other: Karl Fuls was angry and frustrated after losing his legs to circulatory problems. "What I needed was to talk to me now," he says. "Therapists, counselors, doctors, social workers, nobody helped me. How much money I could have saved. How many dead ends I could have avoided."
Fuls last August set up The Broken Wings, a nonprofit organization that matches the newly disabled with a person of the same sex, age, background and handicap to discuss strategies for coping.
"Everybody has questions," Fuls, 62, said sitting in a motorized chair at the Rehabilitation Institute of Pittsburg during a recent meeting. Three of the 16 people were in wheelchairs, three had canes and several wore braces.
-- Brentwood News and Daily Ledger news files
"They're not going to ask a doctor. They're not going to ask a therapist. They will ask questions to people like themselves. 'How do you put makeup on?' 'How do you take a shower?' 'Is my sex life over?' Things like this," he said.
Occupational therapist Annie Miller, The Broken Wings secretary, acknowledges there are innumerable support groups to which the handicapped can turn. But they operate on a communication or verbal level.
-- Brentwood News and Daily Ledger news files
]]></text></news-item>