<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-WM01-JCXB-22JK"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Smiths Group PLC Interim Results -19-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[John Crane, Inc. ("JCI") is one of many co-defendants in numerous lawsuits pending in the United States in which plaintiffs are claiming damages arising from alleged exposure to, or use of, products previously manufactured which contained asbestos. Until 2006, the awards, the related interest and all material defence costs were met directly by insurers. In 2007, JCI secured the commutation of certain insurance policies in respect of product liability. While JCI has excess liability insurance, the availability of such insurance and scope of the cover are currently the subject of litigation in the United States. Pending the outcome of that litigation, JCI has met defence costs directly. Provision is made in respect of the expected costs of defending known and predicted future claims and of adverse judgments in relation thereto, to the extent that such costs can be reliably estimated. No account has been taken of recoveries from insurers as their nature and timing are not yet sufficiently certain to permit recognition as an asset for these purposes.
The JCI products generally referred to in these cases consist of industrial sealing product, primarily packing and gaskets. The asbestos was encapsulated within these products in such a manner that causes JCI to believe, based on tests conducted on its behalf, that the products were safe. JCI ceased manufacturing products containing asbestos in 1985. JCI continues to actively monitor the conduct and effect of its current and expected asbestos litigation, including the most efficacious presentation of its 'safe product' defence, and intends to continue to resist these asbestos claims based upon this defence. Approximately 232,000 claims (31 July 2013: 230,000) claims against JCI have been dismissed before trial over the last 34 years. JCI is currently a defendant in cases involving approximately 81,000 cl-aims (31 July 2013: 81,000 claims). Despite the large number of claims brought against JCI, it has had final judgments against it, after appeals, in only 127 cases (31 July 2013: 121 cases) over the period, and has had to pay awards amounting to approximately US$138m (31 July 2013: US$120m). JCI has also incurred significant additional defence costs and, whilst the number of claims being filed against JCI and other defendants has been declining, the proportion of mesothelioma claims has increased, and JCI's ability to defend these cases successfully is likely to have a significant impact on its annual aggregate adverse judgment and defence costs. John Crane, Inc. litigation provision The provision is based on past history and allows for decreasing levels of new claims based on published tables of asbestos incidence projections and is determined using asbestos valuation experts, Bates White LLC. Whilst published incidence curves can be used to estimate the likely future pattern of asbestos related disease, John Crane, Inc.'s claims experience is significantly impacted by other factors which influence the US litigation environment. These can include: changing approaches on the part of the plaintiffs' bar; changing attitudes amongst the judiciary at both trial and appellate levels; and legislative and procedural changes in both the state and federal court systems. The projections use a 10 year time horizon on the basis that Bates White LLC consider that there is substantial uncertainty in the asbestos litigation environment so probable expenditures are not reasonably estimable beyond this time horizon. The assumptions made in assessing the appropriate level of provision include: -- The period over which the expenditure can be reliably estimated. -- The future trend of legal costs. -- The rate of future claims filed. -- The rate of successful resolution of claims. -- The average amount of judgments awarded. However, because of the significant uncertainty associated with the future level of asbestos claims and of the costs arising out of related litigation, there can be no guarantee that the assumptions used to estimate the provision will result in an accurate prediction of the actual costs that may be incurred and, as a result, the provision may be subject to potentially material revision from time to time if new information becomes available as a result of future events. The provision in respect of JCI is a discounted pre-tax provision using discount rates, being the risk-free rate on US debt instruments for the appropriate period. The deferred tax asset related to this provision is shown within the deferred tax balance. Set out below is the gross, discounted and post-tax information relating to this provision:
John Crane, Inc. contingent liabilities Provision has been made for future defence costs and the cost of adverse judgments expected to occur. JCI's claims experience is significantly impacted by other factors which influence the US litigation environment. These can include: changing approaches on the part of the plaintiffs' bar; changing attitudes amongst the judiciary at both trial and appellate levels; and legislative and procedural changes in both the state and federal court systems. As a result, whilst the Group anticipates that asbestos litigation will continue beyond the period covered by the provision, the uncertainty surrounding the US litigation environment beyond this point is such that the costs cannot be reliably estimated. Titeflex Corporation In recent years Titeflex Corporation, a subsidiary of the Group in the Flex-Tek division, has received a number of claims from insurance companies seeking recompense on a subrogated basis for the effects of damage allegedly caused by lightning strikes in relation to its flexible gas piping product. It has also received a number of product liability claims regarding this product, some in the form of purported class actions. Titeflex Corporation believes that its products are a safe and effective means of delivering gas when installed in accordance with the manufacturer's instructions and local and national codes, however some subrogation claims have been settled on an individual basis without admission of liability. Equivalent third-party products in the US marketplace face similar challenges with the profile of legal activity appearing to increase in recent times. Titeflex Corporation litigation provision The continuing progress of claims and the pattern of settlement, together with the recent market place activity, provide sufficient evidence to recognise a liability in the accounts. Therefore provision has been made for the costs which the Group is expected to incur in respect of future claims to the extent that such costs can be reliably estimated. Titeflex Corporation sells flexible gas piping with extensive installation and safety guidance (revised in 2008) designed to assure the safety of the product and minimise the risk of damage associated with lightning strikes. The assumptions made in assessing the appropriate level of provision, which are based on past experience, include: -- The period over which expenditure can be reliably estimated. -- The number of future settlements. -- The average amount of settlements. The projections use a rolling 10 year time horizon on the basis that there is substantial uncertainty in the US litigation environment so probable expenditures are not reasonably estimable beyond this time horizon. However, because of the significant uncertainty associated with the future level of claims and of the costs arising out of related litigation, there can be no guarantee that the assumptions used to estimate the provision will result in an accurate prediction of the actual costs that may be incurred and, as a result, the provision may be subject to potentially material revision from time to time if new information becomes available as a result of future events. The provision of GBP62.3m (31 July 2013: GBP65.6m) is a discounted pre-tax provision using discount rates, being the risk-free rate on US debt instruments for the appropriate period. Titeflex Corporation contingent liabilities The Group anticipates that litigation might continue beyond the period covered by the provision. However, the uncertainty surrounding the US litigation environment beyond this point (which reflects factors such as changing approaches on the part of the plaintiffs' bar; changing attitudes amongst the judiciary at both trial and appellate levels; and legislative and procedural changes in both the state and federal court systems) is such that the costs cannot be reliably estimated. Other exceptional and legacy Legacy provisions comprise provisions relating to former business activities and properties no longer used by Smiths. Exceptional provisions comprise all provisions which were disclosed as exceptional items when they were charged to the income statement. These provisions cover exceptional reorganisation, vacant properties, disposal indemnities and litigation in respect of old products and discontinued business activities.
]]></text></news-item>