<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-BGB1-JC65-51HF"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Full text of Myanmar's newly enacted Media Law -2-</title><source>Japan Economic Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[YANGON, March 18 - Chapter 4 Responsibilities and Codes of Conduct to be complied by News Media workers 9. A News Media worker is responsible to comply with the following codes of conduct - (a) Evaluation shall be performed to ensure accuracy and reliability of every bit of information and their completeness. (b) When incorrect news have been published and amendment/revision is necessary, and this takes place in the Print Media, this revision shall have to be printed in the eye-catching position of the page or, if in other media, this should be published immediately. (c) While news regarding some cases for which litigation is being run is published, the person prosecuted shall be considered innocent until the court has passed its judgment and any news related criticism which means disregard to the court shall be avoided. (d) While news photos, voices and pictures are published, improper ways of modifying them with the help of certain technologies shall have to be avoided.
(e) Apart from criticisms, opinions and features, no other views and opinions of journalist or reporter shall be comprised of. (f) Intellectual properties which belong to others shall not be plagiarized or published without asking for their permission. (g) Writing news which relate to the interest of the public, writing style which deliberately affects the reputation of a specific person or an organization or generates negative impact to the human right shall be avoided. (h) Ways of writing which may inflame conflicts regarding nationality, religion and race shall be avoided. (i) Ethics and regulations which are published by the Myanmar News Media Council shall be obeyed. Chapter 5 Establishment of News Media Industry 10. A person who wants to participate in the News Media industry is allowed to set up an industry as per one of the following options. (a) Establishment of public limited company or non-public limited company or partnerships in conformity with existing Companies' Act of Myanmar (b) Establishment of industries in conformity with Myanmar Citizens' Investment Law or Foreign Investment Law 11. A person who wants to get involved in the News Media industry shall have to apply for acknowledgement certificate or business licence according to their business types in line with relevant laws. Chapter 6 Establishment of the council and responsibilities 12. The council is the only organization which can perform its tasks independently regarding people from mass media in keeping with regulations stated in this law. 13. The President shall have to publish declaration and establish "Myanmar's News Media Council" in order that objectives and responsibilities embraced in this law shall be realized. (a) The members shall be one representative, which is proposed by the President, and one representative each proposed by the Speakers of Pyi Thu Hlut Taw (People's Parliament) and A Myo Thar Hlut Taw (national Parliament). (b) Representatives proposed by News Media staff, news agencies, publishers, writers, poets, cartoonists according to the specific proportion. (c) Representatives appointed by communities which include scholars and professionals from social, economic, literature, legal, science and technology backgrounds (d) Number of the council members shall have to be specified from the minimum of 15 up to the maximum of 30. 14. (a) The council president, vice-presidents, secretary, joint secretaries shall be elected by the majority of votes given by the council members. (b) The name list of the council members elected by the abovementioned sub-section (a) shall be submitted to the President so that specific responsibilities shall be assigned. 15. (a) The service life of a council member is specified as three years from the date of elected. (b) A council member shall not be allowed to serve their relevant duties more than two service lives continuously. 16. A council member shall be terminated from his employment for one of the following factors (a) Withdrawal from the council voluntarily (b) Being dismissed by the President because of these factors: they deliberately infringe respective duties or ethics to which a News Media worker has to abide by; a council member fails to fulfill his duties to meet requirements; he is found to be irrelevant for the existing position as he purposely breach regulations stated by the committee; two-thirds of the council members insisted to remove from their existing designation. (c) Being sentenced for certain offences and penalties due to their misconducts (d) Insanity and Decease 17. Functions of the council are as follows: (a) Monitoring and enhancing the quality of the News Media (b) Negotiating with respective governmental bodies to smoothly handle importation of necessary materials used in the News Media industry (c) Arranging to hold News Media related workshops and seminars (d) Coordinating with the Mass Media organizations to offer awards to the outstanding news media workers (e) Developing and implementing plans for the improvement of News Media (f) Publishing news whenever necessary (g) Appointing an officer - in charge for news publishing in government departments and entities and people-centered organizations to be executed by the council in order that accurate and reliable information will be accessible to the public (h) Reporting their operational progress and further procedures to be implemented in the future to the President without fail on an annual basis. 18. Responsibilities to be carried out by each committee shall be stipulated according to principles and procedures. (MORE)
]]></text></news-item>