<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-BDK1-JBT2-3148"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>The Almanac -- weekly</title><source>UPI</source><author>UNITED PRESS INTERNATIONAL</author><text><![CDATA[Today is Monday, March 24, the 83rd day of 2014 with 282 to follow.
The moon is waning. The morning stars are Mars, Mercury, Neptune, Saturn and Venus. The evening stars are Jupiter and Uranus.
Those born on this date are under the sign of Aries. They include financier Andrew Mellon in 1855; magician and escape artist Harry Houdini in 1874; silent film star Fatty Arbuckle in 1887; baseball Hall of Fame member George Sisler in 1893; pioneer Disney film animator Ub Iwerks in 1901; Republican U.S. presidential candidate Thomas Dewey in 1902; notorious bank robber Clyde Barrow in 1909; poet Lawrence Ferlinghetti in 1919 (age 95); actors Norman Fell in 1924 and Steve McQueen in 1930; dress designer Bob Mackie in 1940 (age 74); British musician Nick Lowe in 1949 (age 65); fashion designer Tommy Hilfiger in 1951 (age 63); comedian Louie Anderson in 1953 (age 61); actors Robert Carradine and Donna Pescow, both in 1954 (age 60), Kelly LeBrock in 1960 (age 54), Lara Flynn Boyle in 1970 (age 44) and Megyn Price in 1971 (age 43); television personality Star Jones in 1962 (age 52); and pro football star Peyton Manning in 1976 (age 38).

On this date in history:
In 1603, Queen Elizabeth I of England died after 44 years of rule. She was succeeded by King James VI of Scotland, uniting England and Scotland under a single British monarch.
In 1934, the United States granted independence to the Philippine Islands (effective July 4, 1946).
In 1965, white civil rights worker Viola Liuzzo of Detroit, 39, was killed on a road near Selma, Ala. (Three Ku Klux Klansmen were eventually convicted of violating Liuzzo's civil rights, but not for murder.)
In 1975, the beaver became the official symbol of Canada.
In 1989, the Exxon Valdez hit a reef in the Gulf of Alaska, spilling 11 million gallons of crude oil in the largest oil tanker spill in U.S. history.
In 1998, four girls and a teacher at Westside Middle School in Jonesboro, Ark., were killed by bullets fired from a nearby wooded area. (The shooters were two boys, ages 11 and 13, who were convicted as juveniles and served prison time.)
In 2003, British Prime Minister Tony Blair told the House of Commons that coalition forces were well on their way to Baghdad and victory in Iraq was "certain" despite some "anxious moments" ahead.
In 2004, the European Commission fined software giant Microsoft $613 million for EU antitrust violations.
In 2008, the Himalayan monarchy of Bhutan had its first parliamentary elections and attracted nearly 80 percent of eligible voters.
In 2012, former U.S. Vice President Dick Cheney, 71, underwent heart transplant surgery at a hospital in Falls Church, Va.
In 2013, National Rifle Association official Wayne LaPierre said background checks wouldn't have stopped some mass shootings because the gunmen were "unrecognizable" to the system.
A thought for the day: Martin Luther King Jr. said, "I have a dream that my four little children will one day live in a nation where they will not be judged by the color of their skin, but by the content of their character."
Today is Tuesday, March 25, the 84th day of 2014 with 281 to follow.
The moon is waning. The morning stars are Mars, Mercury, Neptune, Saturn and Venus. The evening stars are Jupiter and Uranus.
Those born on this date are under the sign of Aries. They include conductor Arturo Toscanini and Mount Rushmore sculptor Gutzon Borglum, both in 1867; composer Bela Bartok in 1881; actor Ed Begley Sr. in 1901; film director/producer/writer David Lean ("The Bridge On The River Kwai," "Lawrence of Arabia," "Doctor Zhivago") in 1908; Jack Ruby, who killed presumed Kennedy assassin Lee Harvey Oswald, in 1911; sports commentator Howard Cosell in 1918; French actor Simone Signoret in 1921; writer Flannery O'Connor in 1925; astronaut James Lovell in 1928 (age 86); feminist writer Gloria Steinem in 1934 (age 80); singer-songwriter Hoyt Axton in 1938; singer Anita Bryant in 1940 (age 74); soul singer Aretha Franklin in 1942 (age 72); actor/director Paul Michael Glaser in 1943 (age 71); pop star Elton John in 1947 (age 67); actors Bonnie Bedelia in 1948 (age 66) and Sarah Jessica Parker in 1965 (age 49); Olympic silver medalist figure skater Debi Thomas in 1967 (age 47); three-time Olympic gold medalist in basketball Sheryl Swoopes in 1971 (age 43); and race car driver Danica Patrick in 1982 (age 32).
On this date in history:
In 1807, the English Parliament abolished the slave trade.
In 1911, a fire at the Triangle Shirt Waist factory in New York City killed 147 people.
In 1947, a mine explosion in Centralia, Ill., killed 111 men, most of them asphyxiated by gas.
In 1954, the Radio Corporation of America began commercial production of color television sets.
In 1957, Belgium, France, Italy, Luxembourg, Netherlands and West Germany signed a treaty in Rome establishing the European Economic Community, also known as the common market.
In 1975, King Faisal of Saudi Arabia was shot to death by a deranged nephew at his palace in Riyadh.
In 1990, an arson fire swept an overcrowded social club in the Bronx borough of New York City, killing 87 people.
In 1994, U.S. forces completed a withdrawal from Mogadishu, Somalia, except for a small number of soldiers left behind to provide support for U.N. peacekeepers.
In 1998, the first known physician-assisted suicide to be legal under Oregon state law was reported by the group Compassion In Dying.
In 2002, an earthquake devastated rural areas of Afghanistan, killing at least 600 people.
In 2006, an estimated 500,000 people protested in Los Angeles against proposed U.S. legislation that would make it a felony to be in the United States illegally.
In 2010, an explosion sank a South Korean warship on patrol in the Yellow Sea, killing 46 sailors. North Korea denied accusations it had torpedoed the ship.
In 2013, Michel Djotodia, leader of the rebel Seleka alliance, declared himself president of the embattled Central African Republic. (He resigned in early 2014.)
A thought for the day: Mahatma Gandhi said, "It has always been a mystery to me how men can feel themselves honored by the humiliation of their fellow beings."
Today is Wednesday, March 26, the 85th day of 2014 with 280 to follow.
The moon is waning. The morning stars are Mars, Mercury, Neptune, Saturn and Venus. The evening stars are Jupiter and Uranus.
Those born on this date are under the sign of Aries. They include poet Robert Frost in 1874; mythologist and writer Joseph Campbell in 1904; playwright Tennessee Williams in 1911; U.S. Army Gen. William Westmoreland in 1914; French composer/conductor Pierre Boulez in 1925 (age 89); former U.S. Supreme Court Justice Sandra Day O'Connor in 1930 (age 84); actors Leonard Nimoy in 1931 (age 83), Alan Arkin in 1934 (age 80) and James Caan in 1940 (age 74); author Erica Jong in 1942 (age 72); author/journalist Bob Woodward in 1943 (age 71); singers Diana Ross in 1944 (age 70) and Teddy Pendergrass in 1950; actors Vicki Lawrence in 1949 (age 65), Martin Short in 1950 (age 64), Jennifer Grey in 1960 (age 54) and Keira Knightley in 1985 (age 29); TV personality Leeza Gibbons in 1957 (age 57); Rock and Roll Hall of Fame member Steven Tyler in 1948 (age 66); country singer Kenny Chesney in 1968 (age 46); and former Speaker of the U.S. House of Representatives Nancy Pelosi, D-Calif., in 1940 (age 74).
On this date in history:
In 1830, the Book of Mormon was published.
In 1839, the first Henley Royal Regatta was held.
In 1953, U.S. Dr. Jonas Salk announced on a national radio show that he had successfully tested a vaccine against poliomyelitis, the virus that causes the crippling disease of polio.
In 1971, East Pakistan achieved independence as Bangladesh.
In 1975, the city of Hue in South Vietnam fell to the North Vietnamese army.
In 1979, Israel and Egypt signed a peace treaty at the White House, ending 30 years of hostilities.
In 1991, Mali's dictator was overthrown in a violent overnight military coup. Fifty-nine people died.
In 1992, former heavyweight boxing champion Mike Tyson was sentenced to six years in prison for raping a teenage beauty pageant contestant.
In 1997, 39 members of the Heaven's Gate religious cult were found dead in a large house in Rancho Mirage, Calif., in what authorities said was a mass suicide.
In 1998, Bill Clinton became the first U.S. president to visit South Africa.
In 1999, Dr. Jack Kevorkian, the euthanasia advocate, was convicted of second-degree murder in an Oakland County, Mich., courtroom for the videotaped "medicide" of a man suffering from Lou Gehrig's disease.
In 2000, acting Russian President Vladimir Putin was elected president by a more than 20 percent margin.
In 2006, Ukraine's opposition Regions Party won the parliamentary elections, with former Prime Minister Viktor Yanukovych returning to his post under President Viktor Yushchenko.
In 2010, officials in South China said a drought had become so severe that wells dried up and 18 million people were left without drinking water.
In 2011, Japanese nuclear experts said radioactive matter was found at a concentration 1,250 times the legal limit near the drains of four reactors battered by an earthquake and tsunami but that the sea would "significantly dilute" it.
In 2013, Italy's top court ordered a retrial of American Amanda Knox and Italian Raffaele Sollecito for the 2007 death of Meredith Kercher in Perugia. (They were again convicted of murder Jan. 20, 2014.)
A thought for the day: "In politics, If you want anything said, ask a man. If you want anything done, ask a woman." -- Margaret Thatcher
Today is Thursday, March 27, the 86th day of 2014 with 279 to follow.
The moon is waning. The morning stars are Mars, Mercury, Neptune, Saturn and Venus. The evening stars are Jupiter and Uranus.
Those born on this date are under the sign of Aries. They include printmaker Nathaniel Currier, of Currier and Ives, in 1813; German physicist Wilhelm Roentgen, discoverer of X-rays, in 1845; schoolteacher Patty Smith Hill, who wrote the words for "Happy Birthday to You," in 1868; photographer Edward Steichen in 1879; architect Ludwig Mies van der Rohe in 1886; actor Gloria Swanson in 1899; Nobel Peace Prize laureate Eisaku Sato in 1901; jazz singer Sarah Vaughan in 1924; race car driver Cale Yarborough in 1939 (age 75); actors Michael York in 1942 (age 72) and Maria Schneider in 1952; filmmaker Quentin Tarantino in 1963 (age 51); and singers Mariah Carey in 1970 (age 44) and Fergie -- Stacy Ann Ferguson -- in 1975 (age 39).
On this date in history:
In 1886, Apache leader Geronimo surrendered to U.S. federal authorities.
In 1958, Nikita Khrushchev replaced Nikolai Bulganin as premier of the Soviet Union.
In 1964, the strongest earthquake to hit North America -- magnitude 9.2 -- struck Alaska, killing 117 people.
In 1977, two Boeing 747 jumbo jets collided and exploded in flames on a foggy runway in the Canary Islands, killing 577 people in the worst aviation disaster in history.
In 1980, a Norwegian oil platform capsized during a storm in the North Sea, killing 123 people.
In 1993, Jiang Zemin was appointed president of the People's Republic of China.
In 1996, an Israeli court convicted Yigal Amir and sentenced him to life in prison for assassinating Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin Nov. 4, 1995.
In 1998, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration approved Viagra for use as a treatment for male impotence.
In 2004, NASA's unmanned experimental hypersonic plane reached about 5,000 mph in a test flight -- more than seven times the speed of sound.
In 2005, ailing Pope John Paul II appeared at his apartment window before an Easter crowd in St. Peter's Square but was unable to speak. He silently blessed thousands of pilgrims who wept and cheered.
In 2007, leaders of Myanmar staged a military parade to show off the new capital city, Naypyitaw.
In 2010, U.S. President Barack Obama announced an agreement with Russia to reduce the countries' nuclear weapons arsenals -- and have regular inspections.
In 2012, a JetBlue flight landed in Texas after passengers tackled a pilot who screamed obscenities and shouted threats about al-Qaida and bombs.
In 2013, Julia Pierson became the first woman to head the U.S. Secret Service.
A thought for the day: "Fame was thrilling only until it became grueling. Money was fun only until you ran out of things to buy." -- Gloria Swanson
Today is Friday, March 28, the 87th day of 2014 with 278 to follow.
The moon is waning. The morning stars are Mars, Mercury, Neptune, Saturn and Venus. The evening stars are Jupiter and Uranus.
Those born on this date are under the sign of Aries. They include Roman Catholic St. Teresa of Avila in 1515; Nobel Peace Prize laureate Aristide Briand in 1862; Russian author Maxim Gorky in 1868; brewers Frederick Pabst in 1836 and August Anheuser Busch Jr. in 1899; naturalist Marlin Perkins in 1905; Hollywood agent Irving "Swifty" Lazar in 1907; Edmund Muskie, the 1968 Democratic Party vice presidential candidate, in 1914; child star Freddie Bartholomew in 1924; Zbigniew Brzezinski, Carter administration national security adviser, in 1928 (age 86); basketball Hall of Fame member Rick Barry in 1944 (age 70); actors Dirk Bogarde in 1921, Conchata Ferrell in 1943 (age 71), Ken Howard in 1944 (age 70), Dianne Wiest in 1948 (age 66), Vince Vaughn in 1970 (age 44) and Julia Stiles in 1981 (age 33); country singer/actor Reba McEntire in 1955 (age 59); television personality Kate Gosselin in 1975 (age 39); and singer Lady Gaga, born Stefani Joanne Angelina Germanotta, in 1986 (age 28).
On this date in history:
In 1797, Nathaniel Briggs was awarded a patent for the washing machine.
In 1881, P.T. Barnum and James A. Bailey merged their circuses to form "The Greatest Show on Earth."
In 1939, Madrid surrendered to the nationalist forces of Generalissimo Francisco Franco in the Spanish Civil War.
In 1968, the counterculture musical "Hair" opened on Broadway.
In 1969, Dwight D. Eisenhower, World War II hero and 34th president of the United States, died in Washington at age 78.
In 1979, a failure in the cooling system at the nuclear power plant on Three Mile Island in Pennsylvania caused a near meltdown. It was the worst accident at a U.S. civilian nuclear facility.
In 1991, just days before the 10th anniversary of an attempt on his life, former U.S. President Ronald Reagan endorsed a seven-day waiting period for handgun purchases, reversing his earlier opposition.
In 1993, Russian President Boris Yeltsin survived an impeachment vote by the Congress of People's Deputies.
In 1996, the U.S. Congress approved the presidential line-item veto.
In 2005, a massive earthquake jolted the western coast of Sumatra, killing as many as 3,000 people and destroying hundreds of buildings.
In 2006, lobbyist Jack Abramoff, with ties to several members of Congress, was sentenced to six years in prison after a conviction on fraud charges.
In 2009, the space shuttle Discovery landed at the Kennedy Space Center in Florida after a 13-day mission to the International Space Station during which the ISS was brought up to full power with the installation of its fourth set of solar wings.
In 2010, U.S. President Barack Obama visited Afghanistan for the first time since taking office, an unannounced trip to meet with Afghan President Hamid Karzai and address American troops.
In 2011, at least 110 people were killed in an explosion at a southern Yemen weapons factory.
In 2013, teachers in the United States topped all other groups except physicians in how they rate their lives overall, a Gallup poll indicated. Among other things, Gallup's "Well-being Index" said teachers are the most likely to say they "smiled or laughed a lot," experienced happiness or enjoyment and learned or do "something new" each day.
A thought for the day: "Whatever starts in California unfortunately has an inclination to spread." -- Jimmy Carter
Today is Saturday, March 29, the 88th day of 2014 with 277 to follow.
The moon is waning. The morning stars are Mars, Mercury, Neptune, Saturn and Venus. The evening stars are Jupiter and Uranus.
Those born on this date are under the sign of Aries. They include John Tyler, 10th president of the United States, in 1790; baseball pitching legend Cy Young in 1867; Eugene McCarthy, the Minnesota Democrat whose 1968 presidential campaign focused on U.S. opposition to the Vietnam War, in 1916; actor/singer Pearl Bailey, and Walmart founder Sam Walton, both in 1918; political commentator John McLaughlin in 1927 (age 87); former British Prime Minister John Major, actor Eric Idle and Greek composer Vangelis, all in 1943, (age 71); basketball Hall of Fame member Walt Frazier in 1945 (age 69); Karen Ann Quinlan, the focus of arguments over the "right to die" when she fell into an irreversible coma, in 1954; football Hall of Fame member Earl Campbell and actor Brendan Gleeson, both in 1955 (age 59); gymnast Kurt Thomas in 1956 (age 58); actors Christopher Lambert in 1957 (age 57), Amy Sedaris in 1961 (age 53) and Lucy Lawless in 1968 (age 46); model Elle Macpherson in 1963 (age 51); and tennis star Jennifer Capriati in 1976 (age 38).
On this date in history:
In 1812, Lucy Payne Washington, sister-in-law of U.S. President James Madison, married Supreme Court Justice Thomas Dodd in the first wedding performed in the White House.
In 1886, Coca-Cola was created by Dr. John Pemberton who produced it in his back yard in Atlanta.
In 1951, Ethel and Julius Rosenberg, convicted of conspiracy to commit espionage for passing atomic weapons information to the Soviet Union, were sentenced to death. (They were executed in 1953.)
In 1961, The 23rd Amendment to the U.S. Constitution was ratified. The amendment gave District of Columbia residents the right to vote in presidential elections.
In 1971, cult leader Charles Manson and three followers (Susan Atkins, Leslie Van Houten and Patricia Krenwinkel) were sentenced to death in the Tate-Labianca slayings in Los Angeles. (The sentences and a fifth death sentence, for Charles "Tex" Watson, were later commuted to life in prison.)
In 1973, the last U.S. troops left South Vietnam.
In 1991, six-time Italian Prime Minister Giulio Andreotti quit, opening the way for the country's 50th government since World War II.
In 1999, the Dow Jones industrial average closed at more than 10,000 for the first time.
In 2004, Bulgaria, Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, Romania, Slovakia and Slovenia joined NATO.
In 2006, acting Israeli Prime Minister Ehud Olmert's Kadima Party narrowly won the national election, taking 28 seats, forcing it into a coalition situation.
In 2009, Rick Wagoner, chief executive of troubled General Motors during a period of rapid decline, resigned at the request of the Obama administration.
In 2009, eight people died in a shooting rampage at a Carthage, N.C., nursing home and six others were killed in what police called murder-suicide shootings in Santa Clara., Calif.
In 2010, two female suicide bombers killed 39 people in attacks on the Moscow subway system.
In 2011, minuscule levels of radiation from Japan's earthquake-tsunami-damaged Fukushima nuclear plant were detected in at least 15 U.S. states but the Environmental Protection Agency said they posed no threat to public health.
In 2013, U.S. Rep. Don Young, R-Alaska, following withering criticism from Republican leaders, apologized for using the term "wetback."
A thought for the day: "Do something worth remembering." -- Elvis Presley
Today is Sunday, March 30, the 89th day of 2014 with 276 to follow.
The moon is new. The morning stars are Mars, Mercury, Neptune, Saturn and Venus. The evening stars are Jupiter and Uranus.
Those born on this date are under the sign of Aries. They include Spanish painter Francisco Jose de Goya in 1746; German chemist Robert Bunsen, inventor of the Bunsen gas burner, in 1811; English author Anna Sewell ("Black Beauty") in 1820; English social reformer Charles Booth in 1840; Dutch painter Vincent van Gogh in 1853; Irish dramatist Sean O'Casey in 1880; philanthropist Brooke Astor in 1902; former CIA Director Richard Helms and singer Frankie Laine, both in 1913; TV host Peter Marshall in 1926 (age 88); actors Richard Dysart in 1929 (age 85), John Astin in 1930 (age 84) and Warren Beatty in 1937 (age 77); basketball Hall of Fame member Jerry Lucas in 1940 (age 74); rock musician Graeme Edge in 1941 (age 73); British blues/rock guitarist and Rock and Roll Hall of Fame member Eric Clapton in 1945 (age 69); actors Robbie Coltrane in 1950 (age 64) and Paul Reiser in 1957 (age 57); television commentator Piers Morgan in 1965 (age 49); and singers MC Hammer, born Stanley Burrell, in 1962 (age 52), Tracy Chapman in 1964 (age 50), Celine Dion in 1968 (age 46) and Norah Jones in 1979 (age 35).
On this date in history:
In 1842, Dr. Crawford Long became the first physician to use anesthetic (ether) in surgery.
In 1858, a U.S. patent was granted to Hymen Lipman for a pencil with an attached eraser.
In 1867, U.S. Secretary of State William Seward reached an agreement with Russia for the purchase of Alaska for $7.2 million in gold.
In 1870, the 15th Amendment, granting African-American men the right to vote, was adopted into the U.S. Constitution.
In 1923, the Cunard liner "Laconia" arrived in New York City, the first passenger ship to circumnavigate the world. It was a cruise of 130 days.
In 1975, the South Vietnamese city of Da Nang fell to North Vietnamese forces.
In 1981, U.S. President Ronald Reagan was shot by John Hinckley Jr. outside a Washington hotel. White House press secretary James Brady, a Secret Service agent and a Washington police officer also were wounded.
In 1998, Armenian Premier Robert Kocharian was elected president in a runoff election in the former Soviet republic.
In 1999, a jury in Oregon awarded $81 million in damages to the family of a smoker who had died from lung cancer. (A state judge reduced the punitive portion to $32 million.)
In 2006, Jill Carroll, a freelance reporter for The Christian Science Monitor, was freed in Baghdad after being held for 82 days by kidnappers.
In 2008, flooding in Tanzanian mines killed at least 75 men, government officials said. Many of the victims appeared to have been engulfed by rising water as they worked.
In 2010, gunmen killed 10 students after they apparently failed to stop at a checkpoint, similar to those used by drug traffickers, in the Mexican state of Durango while en route to pick up government scholarships.
In 2011, U.S. President Barack Obama called for cutting oil imports by one-third within a decade, a goal he called "reasonable, achievable and necessary."
In 2013, Kenya's Supreme Court upheld the country's disputed March 4 election of Uhuru Kenyatta as president.
A thought for the day: "Moral courage is the most valuable and usually the most absent characteristic in men." -- Gen. George S. Patton Jr.
]]></text></news-item>