<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-C8D1-JC65-52C4"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Summary of action in Alabama Legislature</title><source>Associated Press State &amp; Local</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[MONTGOMERY, Ala. (AP) - A summary of action in the Alabama Legislature on Tuesday, the 25th meeting day of the regular session:
HOUSE:
-Passed a $5.9 billion Education Trust Fund budget that does not give teachers a pay raise but provides more money for their health insurance. Goes to Senate.
SENATE:
-Passed a bill allowing public school students with allergies to carry and self-administer auto-injectable epinephrine. Goes to House.
-Passed a bill to allow public school employees to be voluntarily trained to administer diabetes medication to students. Goes to House.
-Passed a bill to allow public employees to be able to receive unsolicited gifts for exemplary public service. Goes to House.
-Approved a resolution memorializing Anniston journalist Ed Fowler.
-Passed a bill to allow city and county school boards to install cameras on their school buses to catch motorists who drive around buses stopped to load and unload students. Goes to House.
COMMITTEES:
- House Technology and Research Committee approved a bill appropriating $1 million for a study on the effectiveness of using a marijuana derivative to control seizures. Goes to House.
-Senate Constitution and Elections Committee approved proposed constitutional amendments rewriting the state Constitution's articles on impeachment and homestead exemptions. Go to Senate.
-Senate Banking and Insurance Committee approved a bill for the state to create a database of payday loans to enforce the state's limit on a person having no more than $500 in loans at one time. Goes to Senate.
AGENDA:
-Senate Finance and Taxation-General Fund Committee meets at 9:30 a.m. Wednesday in room 727 of the Statehouse to consider the state General Fund budget.
-Senate Health Committee meets at noon Wednesday in room 304 to consider legislation to keep secret the drugs used to execute death row inmates.
-House Health Committee meets at 9 a.m. Wednesday in the joint briefing room for a public hearing on a midwife bill.
-House Commerce and Small Business Committee meets at 2:30 p.m. Wednesday in room 429 for a public hearing on a wind farm regulation bill.
-House Judiciary Committee meets at 3 p.m. Wednesday in room 123 to consider a bill to raise the penalty for possession of an illegal gambling device.
-House meets at 3:30 Wednesday and Senate at 2 p.m.
]]></text></news-item>