<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-BFS1-DYS4-D243"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>NCOC and AGIP to dispute penalties over Kashagan failure in court</title><source>Kazakhstan General Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[North Caspian Operating Company - NCOC, an operator under the North Caspian Sea Production Sharing Agreement - and AGIP KCO intend to dispute in court a compensation amount of 134.2 billion tenge (182.06 tenge/$1) over Kashagan failure.
There is a standard procedure: we issue penalties, the subsurface user has the right to appeal to relevant authorities or to courts and as far as I know they have already put in or are going to put in our calculations before courts to dispute them arguing that the situation, where they got into, does not match with those clause, under which we fined them, and this is a routine process, Kazakhstan's Environmental Protection and Water Resources Deputy Minister Bektas Mukhamedzhanov told Interfax-Kazakhstan.
The Atyrau Regional Environmental Department sent a notification to Agip KCO and NCOC of damages for polluting the atmosphere by sour gas flaring at the processing facilities.
On September 24, 2013 as a result of the burst in the gas pipeline not far away from the oil and gas processing unit hydrogen sulfide leaked and all residual sour gas was flared at the Kashagan onshore and offshore facilities. According to a report on the results of checks, sour gas that was flared over limit totaled 2,795,149 cubic meters.
Oil production at Kashagan began on September 11. According to PSA, the field was to have reached the commercial production level by October 1, 2013. On September 24, 2013, however, a routine inspection of the gas pipeline, running from Island D to Bolashak Unit, revealed a gas leak. The Kashagan field was shut down for repairs until October 6, when oil production was resumed. The company said that the gas leak in the pipeline was caused by sulfide stress cracking.
Kashagan is developed by NCOC as part of the North Caspian project. Its shareholders are Agip Caspian Sea B.V. (16.81%), KMG Kashagan B.V. (16.88%), ExxonMobil Kazakhstan Inc. (16.81%), Inpex North Caspian Sea Ltd. (7.56%), Shell Kazakhstan Development B.V. (16.81%), Total EP Kazakhstan (16.81%) and CNPC Kazakhstan B.V. (8.33%).
Agip KCO is a subsidiary of Eni SpA and acts as an agent for NCOC and is responsible for the execution of Phase I of Kashagan offshore oil field development, including drilling and achieving first commercial production. In addition, Agip KCO is responsible for the implementation of a project at onshore facilities within Phase II of the Kashagan development.
The recoverable resources of the Kashagan field are estimated at 11 billion barrels and oil in place at nearly 35 billion barrels. Kashagan is considered to be the second largest oil field in the world following Prudhoe Bay Oil Field in Alaska, which was opened in 1968.
]]></text></news-item>