<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-F6C1-JCS0-D3Y6"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Fifa response to bribe allegations 'a disgrace'; SPORT</title><source>i-Independent Print Ltd</source><author>Robin Scott-Elliott sports news correspondent</author><text><![CDATA[Fifa's terse response to the latest allegations of corruption aimed at former members of its executive committee has been condemned as a "disgrace", following claims of hidden payments to officials before Qatar was awarded the 2022 World Cup finals.
Football's world governing body did not even request any evidence of wrongdoing be immediately submitted to its ongoing investigation into the Qatar decision or suggest it would actively seek its inclusion.
The controversy over Qatar has been reignited by claims that a company owned by Mohamed Bin Hammam, the Qatari who sat on Fifa's executive committee, paid $1.2m to Jack Warner, a fellow Fifa vice-president, after the Gulf state won the vote.
Fifa released a brief statement declaring it had no comment to make on the matter.
It prompted a withering response from Damien Collins MP, an influential member of the House of Commons Select Committee for Culture, Media and Sport and a long-time campaigner for reforming Fifa.
"This response from Fifa is a disgrace, but shows why there is no public confidence in their desire or ability to take these allegations of corruption seriously," said Mr Collins, who used Parliamentary privilege in 2011 to claim two Fifa members had been paid to vote for Qatar.
"These allegations suggest the bidding process for the 2022 World Cup may have been compromised by the actions of some of the most senior people in world football. Should this be proven, they must state what steps they will take to look again at the decision to award the World Cup to Qatar." Sepp Blatter, Fifa's president, has maintained the tournament cannot be moved from Qatar.
The latest allegations are that one of Warner's companies was paid $1.2m by Bin Hammam's firm Kemco in 2011 for work carried out between 2005 and 2010. There were also payments of $750,000 made to Warner's sons.
The transactions were processed via New York and are being investigated by the FBI, according to The Daily Telegraph. The paper also says the FBI is investigating Warner's links to the Qatar bid.
A statement from the 2022 Qatari World Cup organising committee said: "The 2022 bid committee strictly adhered to Fifa's regulations. [We] are unaware of any allegations surrounding business dealings between private individuals." Warner said: "I have no interest in joining in this foolishness that is now passing as news. Nor do I intend to join those who are on a witch-hunt."
In 2011 Warner resigned from Fifa and Bin Hammam was banned after they were embroiled in a bribery scandal as part of the latter's campaign for the Fifa presidency in 2011.
A new report into previous allegations of impropriety around the World Cup bid is expected later this year.
Past Fifa controversies December 2006: Fifa vicepresident Austin "Jack" Warner, of Trinidad and Tobago, is caught selling 180 World Cup tickets for up to three times their face value. He escapes dismissal from the governing body.
May 2011: Former FA chairman Lord Triesman accuses Fifa members, including Warner, of seeking bribes in return for votes during England's failed 2018 World Cup bid. Warner resigns and proceedings against him are dropped.
May 2011: MP Damian Collins uses Parliamentary privilege to state allegations that two Fifa members - Issa Hayatou of Cameroon and Jacques Anouma of the Ivory Coast - had been paid $1.5m to vote for Qatar 2022.
]]></text></news-item>