<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-BS71-F0NV-F4WN"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Power plant opposition continues</title><source>The Herald (Jasper, Indiana)</source><author>CANDY NEAL</author><text><![CDATA[Herald Staff Writer
JASPER -- Healthy Dubois County will continue its efforts to stop the City of Jasper's power plant from being converted into a biomass plant that would burn natural gas and miscanthus grass.
Litigation the organization brought against the Jasper Utility Service Board and Jasper Common Council was settled out of court earlier this year. But the protest against the plant's conversion continues.
Dr. Norma Kreilein of Healthy Dubois County addressed the utility service board Monday night about the group's many concerns. Organization member Rock Emmert passed out a 14-page statement to board members, and Kreilein began covering a 10-point statement that expressed, among various issues, Healthy Dubois County's ongoing concerns about dioxins and particulate matter polluting the air as well as the chemical atrazine, a herbicide that could be used on the miscanthus grass crop thereby polluting drinking water.
Kreilein said the state does not adequately monitor pollutants. She said dangers are evident through Indiana's infant mortality rate, which has grown worse since 2010. The state was ranked the 44th-worst in the nation four years ago; this year, it ranks 47th.
She also conveyed the group's belief that city officials are not taking their concerns seriously, are not being truthful to taxpayers and are making unfounded claims that their group members are exaggerating the health risks associated with the proposed facility.
Kreilein had been speaking for 15 minutes and reached the fifth page in her statement before she was asked by city attorney Renee Kabrick to conclude her comments. Kreilein stopped.
"The biomass plan is a bad idea," Kreilein said as her concluding remark. "We told you that from the beginning from the financial standpoint. From the health standpoint, it's an even worse idea."
Supporters in the audience clapped when Kreilein was finished speaking. She thanked the board for allowing her to speak and the board continued with the rest of its agenda.
Wayne Schuetter, president of the utility service board, said he didn't have a comment about the information Kreilein presented.
"It is a big packet of information," he said. "We are reviewing it."
A synopsis of the 10 points Kreilein confronted the board with are:
She said that during an October lecture at Vincennes University Jasper Campus about the dangers of pollutants, city officials laughed when her adolescent son Greg suggested the power plant site be turned into a dog park.
She noted that city officials sometimes meet with people who wish to speak at public meetings. Kreilein deemed those discussions, which are held before the public meeting, to be inappropriate.
Kreilein asked for specifics about health-related information Schuetter references as "exaggerated" when he spoke to an Evansville television station.
Dr. Kristin Shrader-Frechette has not been contacted about the three scientific articles she wrote analyzing the power plant's converstion into a biomass plant.
She said the city has given conflicting statements about the lease with Twisted Oak Corp. -- the Atlanta company that is working on converting the power plant into a biomass-producing plant -- not being an obligation, but then said the city described the agreement as an obligation.
She said officials have made threats of litigation while not mandating that Twisted Oak cover legal and plant maintenance fees as laid out in the lease.
She said the city has been silent about the dangers of dioxins, including the dioxin already produced in Dubois County and the amount of dioxin the biomass plant would produce.
She said the state does not adequately monitor pollutants in all of its counties and that those pollutants are evident in the state's poor infant mortality rate ranking.
She said the city has claimed atrazine is safe, but yet said it was a danger to the drinking water when the city pursued a claim from a class-action lawsuit against the herbicide's manufacturer, Syngenta Crop Protection.
Citing emails she received from utility service board member Rick Stradtner, she stated that officials discussed health concerns during executive sessions in 2011, which she said is a violation of the Open Door Law. She also said those emails, notes Electric Commissioner Ken Sendelweck took during executive sessions and emails by Schuetter in his wife's email account were withheld from discovery requests during litigation.
Kreilein's complete statement is on The Herald's website at www.duboiscountyherald.com.
Kreilein's comments are the latest step in the ongoing battle concerning the plant's conversion. It began in October 2010, when a group of citizens circulated petitions and held peaceful protests in front of City Hall as city officials sought proposals from companies interested in transforming the power plant into a biomass combustion facility. Healthy Dubois County was born from those who protested the conversion.
In August 2011, a day before the utility service board and common council signed a lease agreement for the plant with Atlanta-based Twisted Oak Corp., Healthy Dubois County and some of its members filed a lawsuit against the two boards, stating some of the executive sessions the boards held to negotiate the lease violated the Open Door Law. The suit went through the Perry County Circuit Court and reached the Indiana Court of Appeals, who ordered that the lawsuit be heard again in local court. That would have happened in April in Dubois County had the lawsuit not been settled in January.
At this time, the city's attorney for the lease, Bill Kaiser of Bingham Greenebaum Doll in Jasper, is working on an updated timeline for when tasks need to be completed, General Utilities Manager Bud Hauersperger said. Kaiser is waiting for Jay Catasien, owner of Twisted Oak, to send a proposed timeline, Hauersperger said.
The plant is still under the lease agreement, he said.
"We signed a contract," Hauersperger said, "There is really no out for us, unless we buy our way out, which isn't feasible."
The matter is far from over. Healthy Dubois County members are awaiting a response to the concerns they presented at Monday's meeting, Kreilein said, and will continue to voice their concerns.
]]></text></news-item>