<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-BGB1-JC65-51GC"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>China court to take up forced labor lawsuit against Japanese firms</title><source>Japan Economic Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[BEIJING, March 18 - A Chinese court has decided to take up a lawsuit filed by a group of Chinese against two Japanese companies seeking compensation and a public apology for forced labor in Japan during World War II, a plaintiff lawyer said Tuesday.
The lawsuit, the first such legal action in China, was filed with Beijing No. 1 Intermediate People's Court on Feb. 26 against Mitsubishi Materials Corp. and Nippon Coke & Engineering Co., formerly known as Mitsui Mining Co.
The lawsuit seeks compensation of 1 million yuan (about $163,000) for each victim of wartime forced labor in Japan, as well as printed apologies to them and their families in major Chinese and Japanese newspapers.
The 37 plaintiffs include bereaved families, lawyers and scholars from the government-backed Chinese Academy of Social Sciences and Peking University.
The Beijing court decision Tuesday suggests that the Chinese leadership has given the green light for citizens to pursue war-related claims through civil litigation.
The litigation comes as China is stepping up its campaign at home and abroad to warn of Japan's resurgent militarism, especially after Japanese Prime Minister Shinzo Abe visited the war-related Yasukuni Shrine in late December.
Japanese courts have rejected Chinese plaintiffs' similar wartime compensation claims.
In 2007, the Japanese Supreme Court ruled that Chinese individuals' wartime compensation claims were renounced under the joint Sino-Japanese communique issued in 1972 when Japan and China normalized their diplomatic ties.
Citing the communique, the Japanese government has said "there is no outstanding issues" with regard to wartime damage, including claims by individuals, between the two countries.
The communique says the "Government of the People's Republic of China declares that in the interest of the friendship between the Chinese and the Japanese peoples, it renounces its demand for war reparation from Japan."
Lawyers representing the plaintiffs have said a total of 9,415 Chinese citizens, many of whom were under the age of 30 at that time, were forcefully taken to Japan by the two companies to work as laborers.
According to a report made by the group, about 38,953 Chinese people were taken away from where they were by 35 companies and forced to work in Japan, such as at coalmines and construction sites, from April 1943 to May 1945 amid a great shortage of labor.
]]></text></news-item>