<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-R621-JBVM-Y3TY"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>WHERE ARE THEY NOW? THE FIFA COMMITTEE OF 2010</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>BEN RUMSBY</author><text><![CDATA[GONE
Jack Warner, Trinidad (inset) Retired from all football in 2011 after he was implicated in payment of bribes to fellow ExCo members. Appeared to be paid millions by a company controlled by Mohammed Bin Hammam after 2010 vote.
Mohamed Bin Hammam, Qatar Banned from football for life after being accused of paying bribes to win votes during a doomed 2011 Fifa presidency bid. The Court of Arbitration for Sport found he "more likely than not" paid bribes to Fifa delegates.
Amos Adamu, Nigeria Banned for three years after being caught by The Sunday Times trying to sell his vote to undercover reporters.
Reynald Temarii, Tahiti Exposed in the same sting.
Chuck Blazer, US Was accused of committing fraud and misappropriating football money by an internal probe. Blazer denies the accusations.
Nicolás Leoz, Paraguay Former FA chairman Lord Triesman claimed that Leoz demanded a knighthood in return for voting for England to host the 2018 World Cup. Stood down last year "due to ill health".
Ricardo Teixeira, Brazil Fled for Miami after being accused of accepting kickbacks in Brazil, something he denies. Fifa ethics committee found he pocketed at least £8.4million in bribes.
Geoff Thompson, England Humiliated by England gaining a single vote for the 2018 tournament beyond his own.
Franz Beckenbauer, Germany Stepped down in June 2011 after relinquishing his Uefa post. Was the first to argue for the 2022 World Cup to be switched to winter.
Chung Mong-joon, South Korea Lost his seat on the ExCo after Sepp Blatter backed his opponent, Jordan's Prince Ali bin al-Hussein, in Asian Football Confederation elections.
Junji Ogura, Japan Forced to step down once he reached 72.
STILL THERE
Sepp Blatter, Switzerland (pictured) Fifa overlord since 1998.
Michel Platini, France Openly admitted voting for Qatar and that there had been "direct political influence" on the ExCo to do so but insisted that his own vote was purely football-led.
Michel D'Hooghe, Belgium Was key in convincing Blatter to order a review into the timing of the 2022 tournament.
Jacques Anouma, Ivory Coast Under parliamentary privilege, it was claimed that he accepted bribes from Qatar based on evidence gathered by The Sunday Times. Fifa cleared him. Marios Lefkaritis, Cyprus Revealed last year to have business links with Qatar.
Angel María Villa Llona, Spain Secured vote-swapping deal with Qatar in 2010.
Senes Erzik, Turkey Said to be among those who promised their vote to England to host 2018 before reneging. Worawi Makudi, Thailand Claims he accepted Qatari development cash in return for vote.
Issa Hayatou, Cameroon Was censured by the International Olympic Committee over his acceptance of money from sports marketing firm ISL.
Julio Grondona, Argentina One of the longest serving Fifa executive committee members.
Hany Abo Rida, Egypt Said to have accompanied Bin Hammam to Trinidad where the Qatari allegedly sought to buy the votes of Caribbean football officials. Nothing was proven.
Vitaly Mutko, Russia Close to Vladimir Putin, the former head of the Russian Football Union and former Russian sports minister played a key role in securing the 2018 World Cup.
Rafael Salguero, Guatemala Still in post.
]]></text></news-item>