<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSF-X331-JBVM-Y2HY"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Bogus worker raid on 'Curry King' eaterie</title><source>Evening Chronicle</source><author>Dan Warburton</author><text><![CDATA[A FAMOUS Tyneside restaurant was at the centre of a bogus worker raid.
The Bigg Market's Rupali restaurant was raided by a Home Office immigration team on Friday.
The restaurant gained notoriety for their Curry Hell, a dish created by them in 1977 by "King of Curry" Abdul Latif, who died in January 2008.
The original Curry Hell was widely recognised as the hottest in the world, and was acknowledged in the Guinness World Records.
But, during a raid at the property, officers carried out checks which showed a 22-year-old man from Bangladesh was in the country illegally.
He was arrested and has been released on immigration bail.
The raid came as part of a co-ordinated operation involving a number of strikes across Tyneside which saw takeaway bosses issued with penalty notices of up to £10,000 per illegal worker.
Assistant director Phillippa Russell, from the North East and Cumbria Home Office Immigration Enforcement team, said: "Businesses in Newcastle which follow the rules have nothing to fear, but those who employ people with no right to work should expect financial penalties.
"Illegal working is not victimless.
It defrauds the taxpayer, undercuts honest employers and cheats legitimate job seekers out of employment opportunities.
"I would urge members of the public with detailed and specific information about suspected immigration abuse to get in touch." A Home Office immigration team also raided the Lucky Star takeaway, on Shields Road, Byker, after they were fed intelligence that staff with no right to work in the UK were being employed at the premises.
A 29-year-old man from China was found to have no permission to work in the UK. He was escorted from the premises and will have to report regularly to the Home Office while further investigations take place into his case.
If he is found to have no valid leave to remain he also faces removal from the country.
Rupali and Lucky Star were both served with a notice warning that a civil penalty of up to £10,000 per illegal worker will be imposed. This will only be rescinded if it can be proved that legally required preemployment checks were carried out such as seeing a Home Office document or passport.
The Home Office provides support to employers so they can understand the rules, including visits by staff, a dedicated telephone helpline and website.
Employers can access information by logging on to www.ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk or calling 0300 123 4699. Anyone with information about illegal workers can call Crimestoppers anonymously on 0800 555111.
]]></text></news-item>