<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-BHV1-JB4F-Y014"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Daya Materials price 14.8% below VWP</title><source>News Bites Asian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Daya Materials Berhad (MYX:0091), Malaysia's largest chemicals company by market capitalisation, lifted 1.0 sen (or 3.1%) to close at 33.0 sen, ending a two-day streak of losses. The price is at a discount of 14.8% to the 1-month volume weighted average price of 38.75 sen, which may appeal as a value proposition. Compared with the FTSE Bursa Malaysia 100 Index which fell 13.0 points (or 0.1%) in the day, this represented a relative price increase of 3.2%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Daya Materials, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051911530314212
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- The stock's relative price strength percentile is slipping at 49 for 6 months, 3 for 3 months and 1 for 1 month. - Falls to Rises: in the past month the number of falls outnumbered rises 12:5 or 2.4:1.- The price plummeted 23.3% in the last month. The stock has been exacerbated by firm volume of 1.6 times average for the month.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price/Sales of 0.9 [0.6]. - Price to Book of 3.1 [1.6].Other Bearish Signals:- Over the last 3 years average annual compound growth rate of earnings per share was 5.4%. This is lower than sector average of 35.8%.- The Enterprise Value/EBITDA multiple of 12.9 compares unfavourably with sector average of 12.5. Enterprise Value is estimated at MCap MYR458.3 million plus net debt of MYR14.9 million plus minority interest of MYR-54,583 and EBITDA is estimated at MYR36.8 million.- Revenue growth and Profit Margin have shown signs of deterioration in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 86,509 shares worth MYR28,548 (US$8,719) traded. The volume was 0.4 times the average trading of 227,908 shares. Beta: the Beta of Daya Materials stock is 0.8. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market. - Daya Materials is at a discount of 27.5% to its 12-month high of 45.50 sen on 24 Feb, 2014. It is also at a premium of 69.2% to the 12-month low of 19.50 sen on 02 May, 2013. - The present value of MYR1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Daya Materials is MYR1,622, including a capital gain of MYR610 and dividend reinvested of MYR12.

Bullish Signals:- In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week high four times, pointing to an uptrend. Oversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The Relative Strength Index (RSI) of 17.2 has breached the oversold line of 30, suggesting the price decrease of 18.5% in the last 14 days is unusually high. - The stock is oversold according to the Williams % R indicator of -86.4, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day low of 31.50 sen. - The Stochastic indicator of 9.5 has pierced the oversold line of 20.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Return on Equity 8.7% [2.9%].- Return on Assets 5.1% [1.6%].- Return on Capital Employed 11.9% [9.0%].- Dividend yield of 0.8% [0.5%].Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 4.6 is less than 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 14.5%. - Interest cover defined by EBIT/I is 8 times. This indicates it is less leveraged. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 1.1. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- Net profit margin has averaged 7.5% in the last 3 years. This is better than the sector average of 5.8% and suggests a high margin of safety.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity of 8.7% is better than sector average of 2.9%. This is computed as net profit margin of 7.1% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 0.71 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 1.7.- EBITDA growth is positive and has seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 18: Daya Materials: Announcement[News Story] DAYA MATERIALS BERHAD ("the Company" or "DMB") Kuala Lumpur High Court Suit No.: 22NCC-90-03/2014 [Mark Leonard Midgley vs DMB and Daya Offshore Construction Sdn Bhd]The Board of Directors of DMB wishes to announce that the Company and Daya Offshore Construction Sdn Bhd ("DOC"), a wholly owned subsidiary of the Company, have been named as defendants in a civil suit filed by Mark Leonard Midgley (British Passport No.: 500539048) ("Plaintiff"), the former Chief Executive Officer and Director of DOC, in the High Court of Malaya at Kuala Lumpur.The Company had been notified by their lawyers on 18 March 2014 of the said lawyers' receipt in the evening of 17 March 2014, of a letter dated 17 March 2014 from Messrs.
March 06: Daya Materials: Announcement[News Story] DAYA MATERIALS BERHAD ("the Company" or "DMB") - ARTICLE ENTITLED: "Daya to raise RM950 mil"We refer to the article in connection to the above-mentioned in The Star newspaper, Page 4 of StarBiz, on Wednesday, 5 March 2014, which states that "Daya revealed that it is working on a very large fund-raising exercise comprising a 15% private placement, rights with warrants issuance, convertible bonds and senior debt financing worth a cumulative RM950 mil".The Board of Directors of DMB ("the Board") wishes to clarify that the Company is in consideration of various fund raising proposals which include the combination of private placement, rights with warrants issuance, convertible bonds and senior debt financing which could be potentially worth approximately up to RM950 million to finance the intended purchase of two offshore sub-sea construction vessels ("OSCVs").Further information on the above potential funds raising exercise will be made available at the appropriate time.This announcement is dated 6 March 2014.Source: Bursa Malaysia
February 18: Daya Materials: Announcement[News Story] DAYA MATERIALS BERHAD ("DMB" OR "COMPANY")REVISION IN UTILISATION OF PROCEEDS FROM PRIVATE PLACEMENTReference is made to the Company's announcements made on 21 October 2013, 28 October 2013, 31 October 2013, 19 November 2013, 18 December 2013, 2 January 2014 and 3 January 2014 in relation to the private placement and subsequent completion of the private placement of the Company, the Board of Directors of DMB ("Board") wishes to announce that the Board has approved the revision of utilisation of the Company's private placement proceeds of RM43,394 million.Details of the revision are set out in the attached announcement.This announcement is dated 18 February 2014http://announcements.bursamalaysia.com/EDMS/edmsweb.nsf/all/C5F733A33E5862E048257C83003A6DFE/$File/Announcement%20-%20REVISION%20IN%20UTILISATION%20OF%20PROCEEDS%20FROM%20PRIVATE%20PLACEMENT.docSource: Bursa Malaysia
February 14: Daya Materials: Notice of Resale/Cancellation of Treasury Shares[News Story] Date of transaction 14/02/2014 Currency Malaysian Ringgit (MYR) Total number of treasury shares sold (units) 1,220,700 Total number of treasury shares cancelled (units) 0 Minimum price paid for each share sold ($$) 0.420 Maximum price paid for each share sold ($$) 0.420 Total amount received for treasury shares sold ($$) 510,802.11 Cumulative net outstanding treasury shares as at to-date (units) 0 Adjusted issued capital after cancellation/resale (no.
February 13: Daya Materials: Notice of Resale/Cancellation of Treasury Shares[News Story] Date of transaction 13/02/2014 Currency Malaysian Ringgit (MYR) Total number of treasury shares sold (units) 1,000,000 Total number of treasury shares cancelled (units) Minimum price paid for each share sold ($$) 0.415 Maximum price paid for each share sold ($$) 0.415 Total amount received for treasury shares sold ($$) 413,430.50 Cumulative net outstanding treasury shares as at to-date (units) 1,220,700 Adjusted issued capital after cancellation/resale (no.
February 12: Daya Materials: Notice of Resale/Cancellation of Treasury Shares[News Story] Date of transaction 12/02/2014 Currency Malaysian Ringgit (MYR) Total number of treasury shares sold (units) 1,000,000 Total number of treasury shares cancelled (units) Minimum price paid for each share sold ($$) 0.415 Maximum price paid for each share sold ($$) 0.415 Total amount received for treasury shares sold ($$) 413,430.50 Cumulative net outstanding treasury shares as at to-date (units) 2,220,700 Adjusted issued capital after cancellation/resale (no.
February 10: Daya Materials: Announcement[News Story] DAYA MATERIALS BERHAD ("DMB" OR "COMPANY")INCORPORATION OF A SUB- SUBSIDIARY COMPANY - Daya Offshore Construction AS1. INTRODUCTIONThe Board of Directors of DMB is pleased to announce that Daya Offshore Construction Sdn Bhd ("formerly known as SD Equipment Sdn Bhd), a 100% wholly-owned subsidiary of DMB had on 23 January 2014 incorporated a limited liability company known as Daya Offshore Construction AS ("DOCAS").2.
ISIN: MYQ0091OO007
KL:0091; MK:0091
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>