<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-NHW1-DXY3-00W9"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Twisted Pair Solutions' WAVE® Software Granted Department of Defense UC APL Approval</title><source>Business Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Twisted Pair Solutions, a wholly owned subsidiary of Motorola Solutions, Inc. (NYSE: MSI), today announced that its WAVE software was placed on the U.S. Department of Defense (DoD) Unified Capabilities (UC) Approved Products List (APL). WAVE was granted Information Assurance (IA) certification by the Defense Information Systems Agency (DISA) and Interoperability (IO) certification from the Joint Interoperability Test Command (JITC).
KEY FACTS
SUPPORTING QUOTE
Tom Guthrie, general manager, Twisted Pair Solutions
"Twisted Pair Solutions is committed to meeting the most rigorous standards of our defense clients, and the UC APL approval is evidence of this commitment. A listing on the UC APL helps to inform DoD and agency personnel which products meet DISA's demanding IA and IO requirements. We are pleased to see WAVE added to this exclusive list."
About Motorola Solutions
Motorola Solutions is a leading provider of mission-critical communication products and services for enterprise and government customers. Through leading-edge innovation and communications technology, it is a global leader that enables its customers to be their best in the moments that matter. Motorola Solutions trades on the New York Stock Exchange under the ticker "MSI." To learn more, visit www.motorolasolutions.com . For ongoing news, please visit our newsroom or subscribe to our news feed .
About WAVE
WAVE is the industry's most powerful and flexible push-to-talk over broadband solution for secure, real-time collaboration on any device over any network in any location. WAVE transforms smartphones, tablets and PCs into team communication tools and integrates with land-mobile radios to provide unified voice, text messaging and presence in a single, easy-to-use application.
About Twisted Pair
Based in Seattle, Wash., Twisted Pair Solutions has been developing and delivering critical communications software to military, government and commercial organizations since 2002. Its products can be deployed as an on-premise enterprise solution or as a private managed cloud solution providing deployment choices to customers and partners. Twisted Pair Solutions is a wholly owned subsidiary of Motorola Solutions, Inc.
MOTOROLA, MOTOROLA SOLUTIONS and the Stylized M Logo are trademarks or registered trademarks of Motorola Trademark Holdings, LLC and are used under license. All other trademarks are the property of their respective owners. ©2014 Motorola Solutions, Inc. All rights reserved.
http://www.businesswire.com
]]></text></news-item>