<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-N7C1-DXDT-636B"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>World Cup 2022 investigation: demands to strip Qatar of World Cup; Senior MPs say Fifa should launch inquiry into payments by Qatari firm to former Fifa executive and consider stripping the Gulf state of the right to host the 2022 World Cup</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Holly Watt Ben Bryant, Claire Newell and Ben Rumsby</author><text><![CDATA[Football's world governing body is facing calls to re-run the 2022 World Cup bid after an investigation by The Telegraph revealed that a former official and his family were paid almost $2 million from a firm linked to Qatar's successful campaign.
Senior MPs have said that Fifa should launch an inquiry into the revelations and that the organisation should also consider stripping the Gulf state of the right to host the tournament.
Clive Efford, the Labour MP for Eltham and Plumstead and shadow sports minister, said, "Fifa should carry out a full investigation. It looks like there may have been serious corruption in the bid and it has to raise serious concerns about sending the World Cup to Qatar.
"If Fifa looks into all the information and finds that there is corruption, they should reopen the bidding process."
John Whittingdale, the chairman of the parliamentary culture, media and sport committee, said that the payments "provide further evidence that casts doubt over the credibility of the entire process to select Qatar as the country to host the 2022 World Cup".
Tessa Jowell, Labour MP for Dulwich and West Norwood and former secretary of state for culture, media and sport, said of the disclosures made by The Telegraph: "These are very surprising revelations. It's a very large amount of money and in everyone's interests, including [former Fifa official] Jack Warner's, that this matter is investigated."
Paul Farrelly, Labour MP for Newcastle-under-Lyme, added that "if wrongdoing is found, the tournament should be moved elsewhere".
The Telegraph revealed this week that Mr Warner, the former vice-president of Fifa, appears to have been personally paid $1.2 million (£720,000) from a company controlled by a former Qatari football official shortly after the decision to award the country the tournament. Payments totalling almost $750,000 were made to Mr Warner's sons, documents show. A further $400,000 was paid to one of his employees.
The payments were made by a Qatari-based company, Kemco, which is owned by Mohamed Bin Hammam, the former Fifa executive committee member for the Gulf state. It is understood that the FBI is now investigating Trinidad-based Mr Warner and his alleged links to the Qatari bid, and that the former Fifa official's eldest son, who lives in Miami, has been helping the inquiry as a co-operating witness.
The investigators are thought to be focusing on Mr Warner's American and Grand Cayman bank accounts. Michael Garcia, the joint chief investigator of Fifa's ethics committee, is also investigating irregularities surrounding the bidding process. He is expected to deliver his report to the committee later this year.
Mr Warner resigned from all football positions in 2011 amid allegations of bribery linked to Mr Bin Hammam's attempt to unseat Sepp Blatter as Fifa president. Mr Bin Hammam was banned from "any kind of football-related activity" by Fifa, but the Court of Arbitration for Sport overturned the ban in July 2012 due to a lack of evidence.
A new investigation into his financial dealings which dated back to his time in charge of Asian football was launched by Fifa's ethics committee, and this led to a new life ban in 2012.
The awarding of the 2022 World Cup to Qatar was one of the most controversial decisions in sporting history. The intense summer heat in the desert nation has raised the prospect of the tournament being moved to the winter for the first time.
Although Qatar has repeatedly denied wrongdoing during the bidding process, it has long been suspected that the decision was flawed, and several members of the Fifa committee have faced corruption allegations.
One document seen by The Telegraph states that more than $1 million should be paid to Mr Warner to cover "professional services provided over the period 2005-2010". However, a separate document says that payments are to "offset legal and other expenses".
The revelations have fuelled concerns that some Fifa executive committee members were not impartial when they cast votes in December 2010. England suffered a humiliation when it secured only two votes to host the 2018 World Cup and was eliminated after the first round.
Damian Collins, Conservative MP for Folkestone and Hythe, and former member of the parliamentary committee that held an inquiry into England's failed 2018 bid, said: "I think this raises a big concern that the decision to give Qatar the World Cup was based on money, not based on sporting interests."
Simon Johnson, the chief operating officer for the England 2018 bid, who was interviewed by Mr Garcia last year, said: "This is a very disturbing piece of evidence that The Telegraph has found and it is right and proper that Fifa fully considers the evidence that has been uncovered and that any evidence which is in any way relevant to the award of the 2018 or 2022 Fifa World Cup is made available to the investigation being conducted by Mr Michael Garcia."
Mr Warner and his family declined to comment. A spokesman for Qatar's 2022 World Cup organising committee said: "The 2022 bid committee strictly adhered to Fifa's bidding regulations in compliance with their code of ethics.
"The supreme committee for delivery and legacy and the individuals involved in the 2022 bid committee are unaware of any allegations surrounding business dealings between private individuals."
Mr Bin Hammam did not respond to calls requesting comment.
]]></text></news-item>