<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-V4B1-DYX1-N3YF"><date>2014-03-19</date><title></title><source>Star-News (Wilmington, NC)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Man dies after Grand Canyon fall
GRAND CANYON <0x000A>NATIONAL PARK, Ariz. | Authorities are investigating the death of a Texas man who fell about 350 feet off the South Rim at Grand Canyon National Park.
Park officials say 53-year-old John N. Anderson, of Grapevine, had been visiting the park with family.
The Grand Canyon Regional Communications Center received a report about 8 a.m. Saturday about a man falling off the rim near El Tovar Lodge.
Rangers were able to find the man and began CPR, but they say efforts to resuscitate him were unsuccessful.
Grand Canyon spokeswoman Kirby-Lynn Shedlowski says authorities had to use a helicopter to remove Anderson's body from a rock outcropping.
Shedlowski said Tuesday that it's unclear what caused Anderson's fall.
14 charged over child pornography
WASHINGTON | Fourteen men have been charged with operating a child pornography website with 27,000 members and more than 2,000 videos, federal law enforcement officials announced Tuesday.
The investigation, one of the largest online child exploitation probes ever launched by U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement, found 251 victims in 39 states and five foreign countries.
In most cases, young boys were targeted online by the men and tricked into creating sexually explicit videos of themselves, according to a statement from the Department of Homeland Security.
Most victims were male between 13 to 15 years old, officials said. Two victims were 3 years old or younger.
Seattle news helicopter crashes
SEATTLE | A news helicopter crashed into a street and burst into flames Tuesday near Seattle's Space Needle, killing two people on board, badly injuring a man in a car and sending plumes of black smoke over the city during the morning commute.
The chopper was taking off from a helipad on the KOMO-TV station's roof when it went down at a busy downtown intersection and hit three vehicles, starting them on fire and spewing burning fuel down the street.
KOMO identified the pilot as Gary Pfitzner. The other man killed in the crash was Bill Strothman, a former longtime KOMO photographer. Both men were working for the leasing company that operates the news helicopter, the station said.
Fire department settles lawsuit
NEW YORK | About 1,500 minorities who took New York City fire department entrance exams that were found to be biased will be eligible to receive back pay totaling $98 million, a black firefighters' group that had sued the city over racial discrimination said Tuesday.
The settlement of the 7-year-old case capped a long and arduous legal fight by the group, the Vulcan Society, over diversity in the fire department. In a city where more than half of residents identify with a racial minority group, black firefighters have never made up more than 4 percent of the department's total.
<0x000A>- From wire service reports
]]></text></news-item>