<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-R7N1-DYTP-W372"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Big firms under global watch</title><source>Korea Times</source><author>By Na Jeong-ju</author><text><![CDATA[Shareholder advisor pushes for more openness
Korean conglomerates are being pressured to embrace foreign shareholders when picking new board members and making important management decisions amid growing foreign ownership of local stocks.
Foreigners that hold stakes in chaebol firms are mostly 'financial investors' who usually keep low profiles regarding corporate issues and leave decision-making to management.
However, they are increasingly raising their voices against management and owners, especially ahead of annual shareholders' meetings.
Previously, such gatherings were regarded as a rubber stamp for decisions that had already been made by major shareholders and owners.
However, discussions and debates are slowly replacing eulogies for firms and managers because shareholders are becoming more vocal.
Foreign shareholders are behind this change.
The Institutional Shareholder Service (ISS), an advisory firm owned by U.S.-based Morgan Stanley Capital International, recently urged shareholders of Hyosung and SK to vote against the firm's plans at their annual meetings scheduled for Friday.
The firm analyses major issues to be put to a vote at shareholders' meetings, and recommends them to vote yes or no. It provides services to some 1,700 institutional investors from firms worldwide, including some 700 Korean companies.
In a report, the ISS recommended that shareholders vote against Hyosung's plan to give another term to Hyosung Chairman Cho Suck-rae as a board member, claiming he no longer deserves the title.
Hyosung officials said the ISS raised the objection because Cho had been put on trial on fraud and tax evasion charges.
'ISS claimed that Cho cannot fulfill the job properly due to the trial, and that Cho's reappointment as a director could damage shareholders' values,' said a Hyosung official.
'However, Cho has not been convicted of these charges. It's not appropriate to demand voting against him based on the prosecution's claims.'
The official ruled out a possibility that shareholders will reject Cho's reappointment at Friday's meeting, saying that ISS tends to act in the best interest of 'particular' shareholders.
He said the firm will strengthen communication with foreign shareholders to boost their interests.
Industry sources, however, say the firm's foreign shareholders may 'revolt' against management. Foreigners currently hold a combined 29 percent stake in Hyosung.
The ISS has often blamed SK's management for failing to protect shareholders' rights.
Last year, the firm urged shareholders to vote against the reappointment of SK Chairman Chey Tae-won as a director of SK C&C, the de-facto holding company of SK Group, citing his ethical lapses. Chey, however, was re-elected to the position.
This year, ISS demands that SK should lower the salary cap for directors.
Chey gave up his board seats in all SK affiliates last month after receiving a four-year jail sentence at the Supreme Court for embezzling company funds.
His board seats were filled with outside directors in the affiliates, except for SK Holdings and SK Innovation, which instead opted to reduce the number of borad members.
ISS claims the firms should lower the salary cap for board members because Chey is no longer their director.
Some SK officials said ISS is attempting to intervene in the firm's managerial issues using its influence on foreign shareholders.
Foreign investors own 48.5 and 45.7 percent, respectively of SK's two flagship subsidiaries, SK Telecom and SK hynix.
'Of course, it's important for foreign shareholders to raise voices on issues that damage their rights. However, the ISS claims do not serve the interests of all shareholders,' an SK official said.
No ISS officials were available for comments on SK and Hyosung. ISS's reports on firms often become controversial among shareholders here.
Last year, former KB Financial Group Chairman Euh Yoon-dae was punished by financial regulators for providing 'biased' information about nominees for the group's outside directors to ISS earlier amid an internal power struggle.
Park Dong-chang, the group's former chief strategy officer, was also sanctioned for making unauthorized contact with ISS officials and speaking ill of the director nominees.
Based on the information, ISS urged KB's shareholders to vote down the group's plan to select Lee Kyung-jae, Bae Jae-wook and Kim Young-kwa as outside directors at an annual shareholders' meeting, citing their 'close ties' to the government.
Despite ISS's objection, the three were elected to the posts.
]]></text></news-item>