<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-R031-JBJ4-21MK"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Immigration Recruitment Tragedy - Senate Orders Probe</title><source>Leadership (Abuja)</source><author>Adesuwa Tsan, Jonathan Nda-Isaiah and Uchenna Awom</author><text><![CDATA[The Senate yesterday ordered its committee on Interior to carry out a thorough investigation into the tragedy in which about 23 persons lost their lives last Saturday during the recruitment exercise of the Nigeria Immigration Service.
The committee, which was also directed to conduct a public inquest on the unfortunate incident, is to report back to plenary in one week.
However, the opposition All Progressives Congress (APC) caucus of the Senate has demanded the sacking of the Minister of Interior, Abba Moro, and for a state of emergency to be declared on unemployment, even as it urged the executive to come out with a marshal plan to tackle the rate of unemployment in the country.
The resolution was sequel to a motion of urgent national importance sponsored by the chairman of the Senate Committee on Interior, Senator Atiku Bagudu, and Senator Ahmed Makarfi.
Moving the motion, Senator Bagudu, who lamented the tragic event of Saturday across the country when scored died in stampedes at various job exam centres.
He, however, debunked some media reports that lawmakers were given slots in the recruitment exercise, labelling the allegations as baseless and false
Senators in wide ranging contributions labelled the tragedy a national calamity.
However, the call by some senators for the minister of interior to be sacked was rejected by the Upper House; same for the call for the next-of-kin of the victims to be compensated with Immigration jobs.
Senator Ita Enang, in this submission, said in the last five to eight years, only paramilitary organizations had been offering employment as the manufacturing industries offer little or no employment and urged the federal government to declare a state of emergency on unemployment, which he insisted was worse than insurgency.
He attributed the insurgency in the country to the level of unemployment in the country, noting that progress In the UK and United States is measured by how much job the government has created.
Senator Ahmed Lawan (Yobe, APC) blasted the IMF policies being implemented by the Minister of Finance Ngozi Okonjo Iweala as not working for Nigerians since "there are no foods on the table and no jobs".
Moro Must Go - Reps
Members of the House of the Representatives yesterday in wide ranging debates at plenary declared that Nigeria's interior minister, Abba Moro should take "full responsibility" and step down following the deaths of job seekers in Saturday's stampede at the Abuja National Stadium and other recruitment centres nationwide.
Lawmakers however resolved to conduct an investigative public hearing where "stakeholders" will be invited to give first-hand accounts of the tragic incident.
The House Committees on Interior, Labour and Productivity, Justice and Public Service Matters were detailed to carry out the probe.
These were fallouts of a motion of national importance moved by Hon. Sunday Karimi (Kogi/PDP) on Saturday's tragic incident.
In other contributions, Hon. Ali Madaki (Kano/APC) said the jobseekers deaths portrayed "Nigeria as a classical example of a failed state".
Hons. Nkiru Onyejeocha (Abia/PDP) and Abike Dabiri-Erewa (Lagos/APC) among other lawmakers called on the interior minister to resign.
Onyejiocha called on "our leaders should take responsibility for their failings" while Dabiri-Erewa insisted that "the Ministry of Interior must take full responsibility for the tragedy. This issue must not be swept under the carpet."
The House in other resolutions condemned unequivocally the handling of the recruitment exercise.
The federal government was also urged to work in conjunction with the State and Local Governments and Public spirited individuals and organisations including religious organisations, to evolve a job creation scheme that will best address the unemployment situation in Nigeria.
We're Cautious About Releasing Bodies Of Stampede Victims - National Hospital
The National Hospital Abuja has expressed caution over the release of the remaining six dead applicants still in its custody at the morgue, saying that it will not release them to "anyhow" persons.
Speaking to LEADERSHIP, the hospital's director for management information service, Mr Tayo Haastrup, said though one or two persons had come forward, the hospital authorities were being circumspect as they want to make sure the bodies are released to the correct persons.
He said, " We don't want to release the bodies to just anybody especially now that they announced they were going to compensate the families of the dead victims. We want to be very sure. You know how people are," he said.
Meanwhile, three injured applicants, among them two pregnant women, who were on admission at the National Hospital, Abuja, were discharged yesterday.
Of the 40 that sustained varying degrees of injury last Saturday at the National Stadium, 11 had been on admission at the hospital since Monday while five were discharged.
Haastrup expressed the hope that before the week runs out, the three remaining injured victims, including two women and one man, would be discharged from the hospital, saying that they were all doing well.
Earlier, some wounded persons were treated and relocated to district hospitals in Garki and Maitama.
]]></text></news-item>