<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-P8F1-JC86-C0N6"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Nigeria; Jonathan Wants to Remove Our Govs in North East - APC</title><source>Africa News</source><author>Leadership (Abuja)</author><text><![CDATA[The National Executive Committee of the All Progressives Congress (APC), at its meeting yesterday in Abuja, accused the federal government of plotting the removal of its governors in Adamawa, Borno and Yobe states by declaring a full-blown state of emergency. It also called for a criminal investigation of the Immigration tragedy and commiserated with the families of the people who died in the stampedes.
The NEC meeting was attended by members of the party's interim national leadership led by Chief Bisi Akande, governors Rochas Okorocha of Imo State, Rotimi Amaechi of Rivers State, Dr Kayode Fayemi of Ekiti State, and Ibikunle Amosun of Ogun State. National leaders of the party that were also in attendance included Asiwaju Bola Tinubu, General Muhammadu Buhari, Senator Ali Modu Sheriif, Dr Ogbonnaya Onu, former vice president Atiku Abubakar, Chief Olusegun Osoba, Senator Bukola Saraki, Senator Abubakar Goje and other members of the National Interim Executive of the party.
"It has come to our notice that, in pursuant of the Presidency's stance to label anyone who offers it any advice on how to curtail the terrorists' attack and boost the morale of our gallant troops, the imposition of a total state of emergency is being considered for Adamawa, Borno and Yobe states, which is a smokescreen to remove the democratically-elected governors of these APC states.
"We condemn this move unequivocally and urge the President to jettison the idea, if indeed it is being remotely contemplated, because it will not advance the cause of peace in the affected states," the communiqué issued after the meeting reads.
The party frowned at the ongoing PDP rallies, saying they show how insensitive the party and the federal government are to the plight of some parents who lost their children in the Boko Haram attacks and the Fulani attacks in Katsina.
"Amid all of this, the PDP-led federal government has been carrying on as if all is well. After presiding over a wasteful centenary celebration, President Goodluck Jonathan has been gallivanting around the country, addressing political rallies when he should be commiserating with the families of the dead in the affected states, especially Yobe where innocent children were massacred by a cowardly band of terrorists, and Katsina which he visited a few hours after hundreds of people were killed."
The party added: "Against the background of the daily orgy of killings, we are compelled to say that the Jonathan Administration has lost total control of events in the country, with the result that Nigerians are now being left to their own devices. It is clear that the situation in our country today, whether it is in the area of security, job creation, fight against corruption or even growing of the economy, is far beyond the capacity of those at the helm of the affairs."
On the Immigration tragedy that took place in Abuja at the weekend, the party condemned the federal government and accused the PDP leadership of cornering some 3,000 of the vacancies for itself and turned round to be extorting money from the jobless youths. APC also extends its sympathy and prayers to those who were injured in the stampede, and wishes them a speedy recovery.
"The needless deaths of our youth, which resulted from a combination of exploitation, corruption, greed and incompetence of the relevant authorities, represent a needless violation of their right to life and dignity. Out of sheer greed, 1,000 Naira each was collected from the over 770,000 unemployed applicants shortlisted.
"The Jonathan-led PDP government therefore fleeced unemployed youth and their parents of seven hundred and seventy-six million naira (N770 million) using a consultant as conduit. Even then, the available vacancies of about 4,500 have already been filled through the back door by over 3,000 candidates of PDP apparatchik and government officials."
The opposition party bemoaned absence of social security or any form of safety net for the army of the unemployed graduates in the country and accuses the federal government of babysitting corruption.
"The pervasive corruption and incompetence that have become the hallmarks of the Jonathan Administration paved the way for this unprecedented greed in which hapless job seekers were extorted by the same government that has failed to provide jobs for them. Yet, this government has no social security or any form of safety net for the vulnerable army of the unemployed. It should be made clear that this government encourages and babysits corruption, stealing not only from the pension fund of Nigerian citizens, but also from the unemployed and from our collective patrimony, the NNPC.
"That is why we are calling for a criminal investigation to unravel the circumstances that led to the deaths of those innocent Nigerians, to find out who authorized the fleecing of job seekers by a government agency, what happened to the money realized from the heist and why the relevant officials did not ensure a better arrangement that could have saved precious lives."
The party noted that "the job stampede deaths constitute the latest in a series of events that have turned Nigeria into a massive killing field in recent times. The orgy of killings in the past few weeks have left hundreds dead and many more maimed in Borno, Yobe, Adamawa, Kaduna, Katsina and Plateau, just to mention a few. Never in the peace-time history of our dear country has there been such a high number of needless deaths".
It also noted "the ferocious attacks and blackmail mounted against Lamido Sanusi, the governor of Central Bank". "How someone who publicly disclosed the brazen theft of $20 billion from NNPC becomes a candidate for character assassination and blackmail is questionable and condemnable. Sanusi's suspension is an affront to law and a threat to Nigeria's institutional stability. This is also a government of double standard. Why is the minister of petroleum Deziani still in office when the major agency she superintendents is under investigation over the missing $20 billion?"
The NEC also announced dates for its congresses and national convention. The ward congress will hold on April 5, local government congress on April 12, state congress on April 23 and national convention on May 24.
Progressive Governors' Forum designs policies for job creation
Meanwhile, the Progressive Governors' Forum (PGF), the umbrella body of the states governed by the All Progressives Congress (APC), has embarked on policy design sessions on unemployment which it described as one of the major economic and security challenges confronting Nigeria.
Speaking during the inauguration of the policy design session, chairman of the PGF and governor of Imo State Chief Rochas Okorocha tasked the panel which comprises economists, policy development experts, commissioners of economic planning from APC states and other technocrats to develop workable and easily implementable solutions to mitigate the problem of unemployment plaguing our society.
The governor, who was represented by the Imo State commissioner of planning, Ms Adaora Ijezie, said that the policy design sessions were part of the APC's approach to win the confidence of Nigerians and that the party intended nothing less than a total overhaul of the present system which had stagnated development, and only paid lip service to the issues of insecurity and worsening poverty.
Also speaking at the event, the Ogun State governor and host of the session, Senator Ibikunle Amosun, said that the policy design sessions were a follow-up to the Progressive Governance Lecture in Ibadan, three weeks ago, which examined unemployment and the crisis of development in Nigeria. The governor explained that APC states would not stop at mere proclamations, but back up their words with actions by designing policies to create jobs in all sectors of the economy.
Governor Amosun tasked the participants to work assiduously to design policies that recognize the similarities and peculiarities of individual APC states and work out strategies that each state would adopt easily to stimulate job creation, which he described as critical to security and social stability, which the PDP had failed to do.
The director-general of the PGF, Mr Salihu Lukman, who signed the statement, explained that the objective of the policy design session was to develop policy proposals that would assist all APC states in their bid to create jobs.
He lamented the state of unemployment in Nigeria which he said was unacceptable, given the high growth figures being bandied around by the federal government. He said the recent death of applicants trying to get jobs in the Nigeria Immigration Service was a tragic and sad comment about unemployment in Nigeria.
In addition to state commissioners of planning from APC states, other technocrats and development experts participating in the policy design session are Dr Ayo Teriba, who delivered the inaugural PGF lecture in Ibadan in February; Dr Hussein Abdu, country director of ActionAid International; Mr Innocent Chukwuma of Ford Foundation; Professor Okey Onyejekwe; Ambassador Fati Balla; and technical advisors and assistants from the PGF.
It is expected that all policy proposals on employment creation designed by the panel would be presented to APC state governors for adoption and implementation.
]]></text></news-item>