<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-YBW1-DXH0-K1VT"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Government to compel Philex to settle fine for Padcal mine-tailings pond leak</title><source>Business Mirror (Philippines)</source><author> Jonathan L. Mayuga</author><text><![CDATA[AN official of the Department of Environment and Natural Resources said the DENR will compel Philex Mining Corp. to pay corresponding fines for violations under the Clean Water Act.
The DENR said the company's violated provisions in the law with the August 1, 2012, tailings pond leak at its copper-gold mine in Benguet.
Philex said in its 2012 report that "the company voluntarily suspended its Padcal operations when it was discovered that nontoxic water and sediment had discharged accidentally from its tailings pond due to heavy rainfall brought about by successive typhoons."
Demetrio Ignacio, DENR undersecretary for operations, said as a requisite for the permanent lifting of the suspension order issued by the Mines and Geosciences Bureau (MGB), Philex would have to settle the penalties slapped against company.
Philex, listed in the Philippine Stock Exchange, was able to operate Padcal mine in March last year after the MGB issued an order temporarily lifting a suspension order to allow the company to rehabilitate its damaged tailings pond.
Likewise, Philex said in its annual report for 2012 that "the company paid the local government in February 2013 P1.034 billion in fees to cover costs of remediation and rehabilitation activities for the affected area."
The company added that it "was fined by the Pollution Adjudication Board [PAB] on January 18, 2013, in the amount of P92.8 million for violating the Philippine Clean Water Act of 2004 and the terms of its environmental compliance certificate."
The leak at the Padcal mine's Tailings Pond No. 3 contaminated two water bodies-the Balog Cree in Benguet and the Agno River in Pangasinan, for which Philex has been slapped by the PAB with the maximum penalty of P200,000 per day from the time of the discovery of the violation until the time corrective measures has been satisfactorily completed under the Clean Water Act. To date, the running total of the fine is P260 million.
Before that, for violations under the Philippine Mining Act of 1995, Philex was slapped and was forced to settle a fine of P1.034 billion, according to documents from the DENR.
"Philex has to settle the fine first before we lift the suspension order," said Ignacio, a member of the PAB.
He added that a meeting has been scheduled next week to discuss Philex's appeal to reduce the fine, as well as the number of days covered by the penalty. Philex is seeking for the permanent lifting of its suspension order.
However, Ignacio said there is no chance of lowering the penalty considering the magnitude of the spill.
"What we will discuss [in the meeting] is whether Philex should be fined for pollution for two water bodies for the incident, or for just one," he said.
Philex President and chief executive Eulalio Austin earlier appealed to the PAB saying the company has complied with the water-safety standards set by the government as early as October 2012.
However, Ignacio maintained that as far as the DENR and PAB is concerned, water pollution is just one of the violations.
Impeding the flow of water is another violation that has not been satisfactorily addressed by Philex because of huge volume of silt spilt into the Agno river and Balog Creek, according to Ignacio.
"Under the Clean Water Act, impeding the flow of water is a violation. The silt deposited on the river bed impedes the flow of water. It is a provision of law. This is a first."
"Aside from Marcopper, it is only now that we experienced a silt-related pollution of this magnitude," added Ignacio.
]]></text></news-item>