<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-R031-JBJ4-2274"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Liberia - 'Cut Your Share and Go'</title><source>FrontPageAfrica</source><author>Mae Azango</author><text><![CDATA[Liberia is sarcastically referred to as an elephant meat, that anyone can come and cut a piece of it and go, because of the illicit mining ongoing in many rural parts with very little or no regulation from Ministry of Lands, Mines and Energy.
Later over a month ago, Illicit gold mining was taking place on a massive scale in Cestos River in ITI, Rivercess County, where Chinese and other Nationals were and are still mining the Cestos River day and night.
Ministry of Lands, Mines and Energy, responsible for all mining activities in the Country said it was not aware. Fahnseth B. Mulbah, Inspector General for Mines at the Ministry of Land, Mines and Energy at the time termed such mining on the Cestos River, illegal because it miners had Class "C" license and were using machines to mine, and that the case was to be investigated.
Now it was recently discovered again, that Barite mining on a large scale, is being done in Margibi County. The mining that is done by yellow machines, remove tons and tons of Barite from the earth, leaving very big holes behind as they move on to other areas to drill the earth for more Barite.
Large scale mining of Gold, Diamonds and other valuable stones in the Country has attracted many citizens, business people and even foreigners to the industry, but as to whether Liberia is benefiting from these minerals abstracted, is another question.
The Steinbock Minerals Company that is doing the mining is operated by Chinese people, who hardly speak English, but only operate machines to do the mining. They work day and night and sleep on the site under old tents and cars, while the Liberian workers go home to nearby villages after work.
"These Chinese are mining barite, are only contractors who duty is to mine and take it to the port of Buchanan for shipment to Europe," Says Dexhon Kpakilah, a Liberian Supervisor. Kpakilah, who said he does not know the Country in Europe that the Barite is being shipped to, supervises other Liberians at the site.
When questioned as to whether the company is registered with the Ministry of Lands, Mines and Energy, and if it had any license to that effect, Supervisor Kpakilah said they are operating with a class "B" license from the Ministry and they have been operating for nearly two years.
The categories of license that the Ministry of Lands and give says that grade "A" or Class "A" license is for merchandise mining that deals with big companies like Arcelor Mittal and big machine like bulldozers, Dredges and other mining equipment are allowed to be used. While Class "B" or Grade "B" License is Semi merchandize mining also using equipment, but it should include some level of participation by Liberians.
The Environmental Protection Agency EPA who is responsible to observe the environmental laws and the impact on the citizens in the community, admitted to the knowledge of the company and issuance of a permit to the company, but there was no inspector on site.
"I know Steinbock Minerals because it was once halted from mining activities for not getting all their document correct before commencing work," Says Mr. Earl Neblett, Assistant Manager of ESIS at Environmental Protection Agency (EPA).
Mr. Neblett said there should to be an EPA inspector at every mining site in the Country to see that the company does not violate the environmental laws like spilled oil from the equipment, machine pollution and waste, but due to lack of logistics, the EPA does not have an inspector on the Company's operational site.
"EPA only has just a fuel vehicle to cover the entire Country and less than 200 employees. We do not even have bikes for the workers to go to the various sites and one fuel truck cannot cover the entire country."
He said the cutting of the Agency budget from 1.5 million a year to less than one million, has put a strain on the Agency and employees. "We are supposed to operate laboratories and have offices in all of the Counties, but the funds we are getting is only enough to pay employees."
When asked about the very large holes left after drilling for barite, Neblett said before the company leaves, it will cover the holes and do re-vegetation on the site after covering the holes.
It was also noticed on the site by someone who does gold business, that the large machine washing the barite and sending it out from the other end of the machine, also has a component that mines gold, which does not come out from the same side of the barite.
There was no inspector from the Ministry of Lands Mines and Energy to carry on the duty as to what leaves the country. Whereas, it is usually known that the Ministry of Lands Mines and Energy should have a representative from the Ministry deployed on every mining site, but in this case, there was no one on the site that is right outside of Monrovia to see if it is only barite that is being abstracted and shipped out of the Country.
The ministry of Lands Mines and Energy confirmed the knowledge of the SteinBock company and its operations in Liberia, but as to having inspectors on the site to see what is being mined other than barite, it says the ministry hands are tied and cannot do much.
"The Ministry of Lands Mines and Energy is expected to be at all mining sites and at all times, but it is not like that, because we do not have the logistics needed to do the work," Says William S. Hines, Assistant Minister of Mines.
"There are no vehicles or even bikes for the Inspectors to cover these mining sites, some of them have to walk through the bushes to some sites, while other sites are not covered because of the long distance. There are 49 mining sites in the Country and we need twice the number of inspectors and patrol officers to inspect, but we have only 34 inspectors to cover these mining sites and that number is not enough to do the job."
Minister Hines, who was astonished to see photos of illegal miners in Rivercess, mining the Cestos River, said if the Ministry had logistics, it would do more in cracking down illegal miners around the Country.
"If we even arrest illegal miners, how do we bring them for investigation, do we carry them on our backs, when we have vehicles for that operation? It is too much to talk, because the Ministry is stranded and we cannot do much."
Until the government can address the issue of logistics for both the Ministry of Lands Mines and Energy and the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), to tackle the situation of monitoring what leaves the country, illegal miners, who extract minerals for themselves, remains in limbo, and the entire Country would stand to lose its resources.
]]></text></news-item>