<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-R031-JBJ4-21FD"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Fake ARV Drugs Case Ready for Hearing</title><source>Tanzania Daily News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[THE prosecution has completed the investigations into the alleged fake ARV drugs case involving Chama Cha Mapinduzi (CCM) Chairman, Dar es Salaam Region, Ramadhani Madabida and five others, pending at Kisutu Resident Magistrate's Court.
State Attorney Jacqueline Nyantori told Senior Resident Magistrate Nyigulile Mwaseba, who is hearing the case that the prosecution was now preparing memorandum of facts and possibly would be presented on the next session when the court will conduct the preliminary hearing.
She, therefore, requested the court to set a date for preliminary hearing when the prosecution would give more particulars, detailing how the accused persons allegedly committed the offences. The magistrate granted the request and adjourned the trial to April 23.
In the case, Madabida, who is also the Chief Executive Officer with Pharmaceuticals Industries Limited, is charged alongside three other top officials with the company, Seif Salum Shamte, Director of Operations; Simon Alfred Msoffe, Marketing Manager and Fatma Ally Shango, an Assistant Accountant.
The rest are two officials with the Medical Stores Department (MSD), Sadiki Frank Materu, who is a Quality Assurance Manager and Evans Mwemezi, the Quality Assurance Officer.
They are facing five counts, including occasioning losses of more than 148m/- to the government following supply of the drugs in question.
It is alleged that on April 5, 2011 in Dar es Salaam, Madabida, Shamte, Msoffe and Shango, supplied to MSD 7776 Tins of counterfeit Anti-retroviral Drugs, purportedly showing they contained ingredients Stavudine 30mg, Nevirapine 200mg, Lamivudine 150mg, with batch number OC 01.85 manufactured in March 2011 and expiring in February 2013.
On April 11, 2011, in the city, the four accused persons allegedly supplied 4,476 Tins of counterfeit Anti-retroviral Drugs allegedly containing ingredients Stavudine 30mg, Nevirapine 299mg and Lamivudine 150mg with batch number OC 01.85 manufactured in March 2011 and expiring in February 2013.
Between April 12 and 29, 2011 in the city, with intent to defraud or deceit, jointly and together, the four accused persons allegedly obtained from MSD 98,506.8 US dollars (about 148,350,156/-) by falsely pretending that the said money was payments for genuine 12252 Tins of Antiretroviral Drugs supplied.
The prosecution alleged further that between April 5 and 13, 2011, in the city, being employees of MSD, Materu and Mwemezi, knowing that there was a plan to commit an offence of supplying the counterfeit drugs, failed to use all reasonable means to prevent such crime from being committed.
Between April 5 and 30, 2011, in Dar es Salaam, by willful acts and reason of their failure to discharge their duties in a reasonable manner, Madabida, Shamte, Msoffe, Shango, Materu and Mwemezi caused MSD to be supplied with 12,252 tins of fake drugs, leading to a pecuniary loss of the said 148m/-.
]]></text></news-item>