<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-Y2C1-F0J6-J346"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Labor jumps to action over Sinodinos</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>Parliament Fleur Anderson</author><text><![CDATA[Could Australia have lost the greatest treasurer it never had?
There was a nanosecond of silence from both sides in parliament when Senator Arthur Sinodinos announced he would step aside as Assistant Treasurer while the Australian Water Holdings' stink is resolved in a NSW anti-corruption inquiry.
For all the faux outrage and demands for political head rolling, it's a rare thing for a minister to actually step down.
Now that Sinodinos has blinked in the game of political chicken, Labor leader Bill Shorten has some questions he wants answered.
Did Sinodinos give Tony Abbott a full account of his dealings with AWH? When did he give his account? When did he decide to step aside? Did he take the decision himself or on the advice on the PM's office?
Why did Sinodinos take a whole month to stand aside after the NSW anti-corruption inquiry revealed it was investigating the company in early February?
Why did Abbott appoint to his ministry a man on the fringes of a corruption inquiry?
After a surprising lack of attention in question time earlier in the week, finally Labor has its eye on the long game.
Shorten adopted a forensic approach on Wednesday, with 13 questions designed to put the Prime Minister in the frame.
If Sinodinos is found guilty of wrongdoing by the Independent Commission Against Corruption, Labor has set up Abbott as a prime minister who perhaps knowingly appointed to his ministry a man whose private sector dealings were linked to dodgy former politicians and distasteful backroom deals.
Abbott was having none of it. No dates, no details of private tête-à-têtes. Only a repeated insistence of Sinodinos's integrity and the rightness of his actions.
"Senator Sinodinos saw me earlier today and advised me of his decision to stand aside," Abbott said in question time.
"So he made the decision, and I have to say, Madam Speaker, it is in the best and most honourable Westminster tradition that he should do so."
And later: "I am proud of him and I am looking forward to his return."Stepping aside or down?
Now the question is whether his stepping aside will be a permanent resignation.
For the past month, most of the heat has been on the doings of another Abbott minister, Assistant Health Minister Fiona Nash, over her dealings with the junk food industry and her judgment of her former chief of staff.
Abbott declared his full confidence in both Nash and Sinodinos. Yet he now agrees Sinodinos has done the "right and honourable thing".
Shorten wanted to know what had changed in the past 24 hours.
"It's not my job to provide a running commentary on private conversations," Abbott said.
That Sinodinos - an economist, John Howard's former chief of staff and a former Treasury official - is regarded as one of the gentlemen of Australian politics makes it all the more shocking to the many business people and lobbyists who have dealt with him over the years.
When Tony Abbott named his ministry last September, there was great consternation that Sinodinos was not named finance minister - a stepping stone to the position of treasurer should Joe Hockey fall. Or ascend.
Any suggestion this decision was linked to the odour over AWH was met with an arctic response.
Now it seems Abbott's decision to snub Sinodinos and give finance to Matthias Cormann - now Assistant Treasurer as well - was also made with his eye on the long game.READ ALSO: Sinodinos negotiated secret success fee, ICAC hears Tingle | Sinodinos standing his ground for now Anderson | Parliament all heat and no light in race debate
]]></text></news-item>