<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-P3G1-JD6S-R41B"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Balyszak: No excuse for Auburn's voice mail problems</title><source>The Citizen (Auburn, New York)</source><author>Bill Balyszak, AUBURN CITIZEN</author><text><![CDATA[When I first glanced at The Citizen headline of March 12, "Auburn city manager 'disappointed' in Verizon's efforts to fix city's phone system," my initial quick take was that someone must have cut a Verizon trunk cable.
However, upon further reading, it turns out that about three weeks ago - yes, THREE weeks ago - Auburn's voice messaging system went dead because the city's phone lines were "inadvertently" shut off by Verizon.
City departments, including the Auburn Police Department, couldn't receive any voice messages, which is not a situation a city should be in, especially when it concerns thousands of people and their safety.
Auburn contracted with an external agency, Spyglass, to audit the city's telecommunications to identify outdated telecom service lines that were still being charged to the city.
And in today's unbelievable technology, Verizon couldn't figure this out electronically?
With a little legal monetary persuasion, I believe they could.
Spyglass found 170 telecommunication lines that were potentially not used or underutilized.
That number was trimmed by the city to 120 lines and work orders were issued to Verizon to shut these down, which would save the city $40,000 per year, according to Spyglass.
But lo and behold, it appears Spyglass and/or the city and/or Verizon didn't do a communications check of all used lines in combination with the various 120 lines before any switch or all switches were thrown to the off positions or wires disconnected by Verizon.
When a huge monopoly, such as Verizon, doesn't want to do something either for an individual or a city in an expeditious manner that won't financially benefit Verizon, it's because they usually have a "stonewalling/workaround plan."
You see, that's what they told yours truly and stonewalled my small business (TaxSavers Income Tax) from being listed for four years in their Yellow Pages because I had the audacity to switch and port my existing number to a lower-cost carrier.
Unexplainably, Verizon "somehow" couldn't find a way to list my business name - which was the same as when I was with them - onto their Verizon Yellow Pages.
But if I switched back with Verizon - via their suggested "workaround plan" that included exorbitant rates - they would throw in - for free - bold face type. Wow!
Needless to say, I can't write what I told them to do with their bold face type and outrageous rates.
Coincidently, Verizon also has a "stonewalling/workaround plan" for "inadvertently" disconnecting some vital phone lines for the city.
We don't know if these were physical disconnections but based on today's technology, Verizon most likely just got on their computers and threw some switches and the job was done.
City Manager Doug Selby said that "we're disappointed that Verizon hasn't come up with a solution other than replacing our whole phone system." (Emphasis mine)
So yes, monopolistic Verizon will be most happy to oblige the city with a hundred thousand dollar plus new system but somehow can't find the right connections or switches to throw the other way to turn on some of those existing 120 lines?
Amazingly, Verizon ran fiber optic cables throughout Auburn without disconnecting people for weeks on end - and is now competing with Time Warner Cable, another "take it or leave it" monopoly - by offering Auburn their FiOS for phone, TV and the internet but can't find the right cables or wires to either hook back up or just throw the same switches the other way.
Not only did Verizon treat this small businessman very shabbily but for a company that has a monopoly, deep pockets and the latest communications technology, their stonewalling actions against Auburn border on the criminal and needlessly put thousands of residents and others at unnecessary risk.
"Can you hear me now" -- Verizon?
But hark, on March 13, Auburn's voice mail issues were miraculously "resolved for the time being" through the intercession of Verizon's local manager, Stephen Hill.
Does that mean Hill wasn't involved initially? If so -- why not?
And what's this "resolved for the time being" bit anyway?
It appears that Verizon is still pursuing their "stonewalling/workaround plan" by trying to get Auburn to replace their whole phone system and doesn't want to swallow the yearly $40,000 loss in pure profit and keep letting city taxpayers absorb this unnecessary expense.
Stay connected Auburn.
It's your money.
]]></text></news-item>