<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-PTH1-JDJN-607R"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Putin inks Crimea treaty</title><source>Global Times (China)</source><author>Li Qian in Simferopol</author><text><![CDATA[Russia's President Vladimir Putin (second from right), Crimean Prime Minister Sergei Aksyonov (left) and other officials join hands after signing a treaty on the Black Sea peninsula becoming part of Russia in the Kremlin in Moscow on Tuesday. Photo: AFP
Russian President Vladimir Putin inked a treaty to incorporate Crimea into Russia Tuesday and said that the Black Sea peninsula is an "inseparable part of Russia." Putin signed the treaty with Crimean Prime Minister Sergei Aksyonov and other Crimean leaders at a ceremony at the Kremlin attended by both houses of parliament. Lawmakers, who still have to ratify the treaty, broke into applause and cheers after the signing.In a fiercely patriotic address to a joint session of the Russian parliament in the Kremlin before the signing ceremony, Putin said Crimea's disputed referendum vote on Sunday shows the overwhelming will of the people to be reunited with Russia after 60 years as part of Ukraine. "In the hearts and minds of people, Crimea has always been and remains an inseparable part of Russia," Putin said.Although Crimea has been seen as a flashpoint during the Russia-West stalemate, local authorities said everything is in order."There is no emergency, and police departments have everything under control, just like before the Russian troops arrived," Oleg Bogoslavskaya, a deputy director of the social connection department of Crimean police told the Global Times on Tuesday.She said authorities have registered fewer cases of unlawful activities committed by residents in the past two weeks.The Crimean police department changed its name to the Crimean Republic Ministry of Internal Affairs about a week ago, a move seen as reflecting the expanding autonomy of the republic.While Russian soldiers are easily spotted on Simferopol's streets, Crimean police were reluctant to comment on their principles of dealing with cases involving military personnel.In his Tuesday speech, Putin sought to reassure Ukrainians that Russia did not seek any further division of their country. Fears have been expressed in Kiev that Russia might move on the Russian-speaking eastern parts of Ukraine."Don't believe those who try to frighten you with Russia and who scream that other regions will follow after Crimea," Putin said. "We do not want a partition of Ukraine. We do not need this."Making clear Russia's concern at the possibility of the US-led NATO military alliance expanding into Ukraine, he declared "I do not want to be welcomed in Sevastopol by NATO sailors." The port is the base of Russia's Black Sea fleet. US Vice President Joe Biden on Tuesday condemned Russia's actions in Crimea, calling them nothing more than a "land grab" and warning of further sanctions against Moscow.British Foreign Secretary William Hague said Tuesday that Putin has chosen a path to Russia's isolation by moving to annex Ukraine's Crimea region. He added that Britain will suspend all bilateral military cooperation with Russia.So far, sanctions announced by the West have included asset freezes and travel bans, and are not seen to be particularly worrying for Moscow.Japan announced sanctions on Tuesday, announcing the suspension of talks with Russia on investment promotion and visa liberalization.French Foreign Minister Laurent Fabius said France could consider cancelling a 1.2 billion euro ($1.67 billion) helicopter-carrier contract with Moscow if further sanctions are announced. Vladimir Petrovsky, a member of Russia's Academy of Military Sciences, told the Global Times that the relationship between Russia and the US will not retreat to that of the Cold War, as their interests are now interdependent.Petrovsky said that Russia is in an advantageous position militarily and that military power or threats from the US will be useless, as the referendum has been "quietly" carried out in Crimea."After paying a high price in Iraq and Afghanistan, the US won't confront Russia militarily for Ukraine where it does not have a core interest," said Petrovsky.Ukraine's interim prime minister Arseniy Yatsenyuk said on Tuesday that his country's conflict with Russia was entering a "military stage" following claims by Kiev that one of its officers was shot and wounded "during an attack against a base in Simferopol.""The conflict is shifting from a political to a military stage," Yatsenyuk told an emergency government meeting. Ukraine authorities did not specify where or when the incident happened.Liu Yunlong and agencies contributed to this story
]]></text></news-item>