<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-YBG1-DYRD-S1X9"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>News briefing</title><source>Sun-Sentinel (Fort Lauderdale, Florida)</source><author>Tribune Newspapers and news services</author><text><![CDATA[Alleged 9/11 plotter plays down role of Abu Ghaith
The self-proclaimed mastermind of the Sept. 11 attacks said Osama bin Laden's son-in-law, who is on trial in New York on terrorism charges, is "an eloquent, spellbinding speaker" but had no advance knowledge of lethal operations conducted by al-Qaida.
The unusual submission from Khalid Sheikh Mohammed, who is held at Guantanamo Bay, Cuba, was solicited by lawyers for Sulaiman Abu Ghaith, who was captured in 2013 and transferred to New York for prosecution in federal court.
A federal judge allowed Abu Ghaith's attorneys to submit several hundred questions to Mohammed, who provided answers that were reviewed by the government before they were returned and filed in federal court in Manhattan.
Everything Mohammed says is presumptively classified, as are the statements of other high-value detainees held at Guantanamo Bay.
Abu Ghaith's attorneys hope to use the 14-page declaration at the trial, which is entering its third week. Prosecutors assert that bin Laden recruited Abu Ghaith after the 9/11 attacks and used him to attract and motivate new recruits. Abu Ghaith, who is from Kuwait, appeared in al-Qaida propaganda videos.
In one video after the Sept. 11 attacks, Abu Ghaith warned that the "storms shall not stop, especially the airplane storms." He advised Muslims "not to board any aircraft."
Prosecutors say these threats were not idle. At the time, al-Qaida was planning to use shoe bombs to destroy a pair of airliners. Iran: Sabotage attempt on Arak reactor foiled
Pumps at Iran's planned Arak reactor, seen by the West as a potential source of plutonium for nuclear bombs, were tampered with in a failed attempt to sabotage the country's nuclear program, a senior official said Monday.
Asghar Zarean, deputy chief for nuclear protection and security at the Atomic Energy Organization of Iran, said the incident was one of several such attacks foiled in the past few months, the official IRNA news agency reported. China denies dissident was refused treatment
BEIJING -- China's foreign ministry denied Monday that prominent human rights activist Cao Shunli died because she was refused medical treatment while in detention. The case has attracted concern from the United States and Europe.
Cao staged a two-month sit-in along with other activists outside the Foreign Ministry, beginning in June, to press for the public to contribute to a national human rights report. She died Friday. 3rd person dies from SXSW festival crash
AUSTIN, Texas -- A third person has died as a result of a motorist plowing his car into a crowd of people Thursday at the South by Southwest festival in Austin, officials said Monday.
Sandy Thuy Le, 26, has died, officials said. She was one of the five people listed in critical condition after the incident.
Rashad Charjuan Owens, 21, has been charged with capital murder for the incident that has claimed three lives and left nearly two dozen injured. Boston bombing victims' autopsy photos at issue
Federal prosecutors intend to enter autopsy photos of the three Boston Marathon victims into evidence, but they want bombing suspect Dzhokhar Tsarnaev to see only the pictures that will be used in his trial.
On Monday, prosecutors asked a judge to grant a protective order that would bar Tsarnaev from looking at autopsy photos of victims Krystle Campbell, Martin Richard and Lu Lingzi unless the images are entered into the court record. The Newsmaker Rob Ford caught on tape
Toronto Mayor Rob Ford, who last year admitted he had smoked crack cocaine, was caught up in fresh controversy Monday after a new video showed him apparently swearing outside City Hall. The video was taken Saturday by the son of a woman who shared the footage with CTV News. Paris lifts vehicle limit as pollution levels drop
PARIS -- The French government said it's lifting a partial ban on vehicle traffic in Paris as pollution levels receded from last week's peak, when air quality in the capital was worse than in Beijing.
The first partial driving ban in the French capital in 17 years, which halved the number of automobiles circulating in Paris, and the other anti-pollution measures will be lifted as of midnight, energy and environment Minister Philippe Martin said at a news conference. China rejects report alleging N. Korea crimes
GENEVA -- China dismissed on Monday a U.N. report alleging North Korea has committed crimes against humanity, effectively confirming the fears of human rights advocates that Beijing will shield its ally from international prosecution.
The report, published in February, accused the reclusive country of mass killings and torture comparable to Nazi-era atrocities and said officials, possibly even Kim Jong Un himself, should face the International Criminal Court. Morning quake rattles residents in LA area
LOS ANGELES -- The magnitude-4.4 earthquake that struck Los Angeles early Monday was a "rude awakening" for residents who remain vulnerable to being caught unprepared by a major temblor, Mayor Eric Garcetti said.
The earthquake that struck in Sherman Oaks at 6:25 a.m. local time was the most significant shake in Southern California since a 5.5 earthquake hit Chino Hills in 2008. It was followed up by seven smaller temblors.
]]></text></news-item>