<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-YSV1-JBHM-S4F2"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>EPA Says FY15 Risk Analysis Funding Cuts May Hinder Regulatory Agenda</title><source>InsideEPA.com's Daily Briefing</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EPA is proposing to reduce fiscal year 2015 funding for core risk analysis programs including its influential Integrated Risk Information System (IRIS) and research efforts for its ambient air standards, and says the cuts could hinder its regulatory agenda by delaying rules that depend on the research or reducing scientific support for some rules.
The agency's recently released congressional justification for President Obama's FY15 proposal includes a drop from $40 million enacted in FY14 to $37.8 million for the Human Health Risk Assessment (HHRA) program, which includes a host of research efforts including IRIS, the Integrated Science Assessment (ISA) criteria air pollutant research program, the Provisional Peer Reviewed Toxicity Value (PPRTV) program, and general research work to support those programs.
Among the cuts is a $1.55 million funding reduction for IRIS, whose risk assessments underpin many regulatory decisions such as site cleanups or drinking water rules. The agency is also proposing a smaller cut of $491,000 for ISAs which inform EPA's review of the six national ambient air quality standards (NAAQS).
In many instances, the budget document does not specify the existing enacted FY14 funding levels for specific programs such as the ISAs, nor the proposed overall funding -- instead detailing only the amount of the cut.
In the congressional justification, EPA notes the constraints that those funding cuts may place on its regulatory agenda. For example, in describing the proposal to reduce the overall funding for IRIS, the agency says, "This reduction is a resource realignment due to agency priorities and may delay the start, review and completion of IRIS assessments, reducing the number of regulatory decisions which use these peer-reviewed assessments."
Similarly, EPA says that reducing funding for ISA assessments of NAAQS pollutants may delay completion of those analyses, in turn "reducing support for NAAQS decisions" and data collection efforts.
A proposed $351,000 cut to the HHRA program could "slow the development of methods, models, and approaches to modernize risk assessment, including the release of Expo-box updates used by EPA programs and states, several PPRTVs developed in support of EPA's hazardous waste programs and states; and cumulative risk assessment methods used by EPA program offices and States."
Separately, EPA's Endocrine Disruptor Screening Program (EDSP) program faces a $1.1 million cut from its FY14 enacted funding level of $7.5 million down to $6.4 million in FY15. The EDSP is a controversial program intended to assess chemicals for their potential to interact with the human endocrine system, and if flagged, produce data for risk assessment.
"[T]here may be impacts to EDSP, resulting in reduced activities related to additional applications of computational toxicology within the program," the agency says.
In each case, the justification indicates that the reductions are due to priorities elsewhere, or general efforts to reduce agency spending. By contrast, EPA's Science Advisory Board (SAB), which reviews agency science, would receive a $1.1 million boost in FY15 to $6.1 million compared to its FY14 funding of $5 million.
The funding covers a small staff of EPA employees who manage peer reviews conducted by SAB and related peer review committees of independent scientists, engineers and economists.
IRIS Assessments
Most of the increase in SAB's funding, and an additional full-time equivalent employee that would be funded through the budget increase, is for work peer-reviewing IRIS assessments. "This increase in resources will be used to conduct peer reviews and to host meetings to assess IRIS chemicals," EPA says.
But SAB might have fewer IRIS assessments to review after FY15, according to the agency's note in its congressional justification that the funding cuts for the IRIS program may slow development of IRIS reviews.
The proposed cut to IRIS is surprising given its prominent role and efforts by EPA leadership in recent years to respond to criticism regarding the program's efficiency, as well as its scientific quality.
Additionally, EPA's acting IRIS Director Vincent Cogliano said in December that his goal is to treble the program's output within the next two or three years .
EPA's IRIS program produces toxicological assessments that contain cancer and non-cancer dose-response analysis of chemicals and contaminants in the environment and of interest to EPA and other agencies' programs. The documents are often the basis for EPA rules and site cleanup decisions, and are also cited by state, local and international agencies.
The IRIS program has long been controversial, with many industries often claiming the studies are overly conservative, and because of the extensive time that goes into developing each assessment.
Many of the IRIS documents, particularly controversial assessments regarding chemicals for which a stringent IRIS assessment could lead to high cleanup or enforcement costs, can take a decade or more to complete. Concerns about the program's output have been highlighted by the Government Accountability Office, Congress, and EPA's inspector general, while concerns about its products have been raised by the National Academy of Sciences (NAS).
The justification lists among the agency's "major management challenges" "EPA's framework for assessing and managing chemical risks/transforming EPA's processes for assessing and controlling toxic risks." In response, the agency outlines its efforts at improving IRIS over the past several years since the release of NAS' critical review of the agency's draft IRIS assessment of formaldehyde. EPA is in the process of implementing a series of efforts to increase the efficiency and transparency of the program, while also improving the document's scientific quality.
EPA says that it has "instituted a new internal process for developing [IRIS] assessments. Eight disciplinary workgroups . . . have been established to develop and revise specific sections of IRIS assessments and work with the assessment leads to develop an integrated assessment. This approach will improve the scientific quality and consistency of the assessments by having a critical mass of experts in each area write and review the sections."
Additionally, the agency explains that IRIS program managers have created a new group within the agency "[t]o manage the new draft development process, the agency has established an IRIS Management Council, consisting of managers who supervise scientists working on IRIS assessments. The IRIS Management Council is responsible for assigning appropriate staff to assessments, developing schedules, and ensuring that schedules are met."
A parallel IRIS Science Council, consisting of science managers and the chairs of the disciplinary workgroups, "is responsible for identifying and resolving cross-cutting scientific issues," the agency adds.
Funding Reductions
Funding cuts for other EPA research programs would potentially have an adverse impact on the agency's regulatory agenda including for its ambient air standards, according to the justification.
The proposed reduction of $491,000 for the ISA program may delay completion of the ISAs and ecological reviews for the six NAAQS pollutants, "reducing support for NAAQS decisions," the justification says.
The ISA program produces the scientific documents that are the basis for EPA's NAAQS for the six criteria pollutants named in the Clean Air Act: carbon monoxide, lead, nitrogen oxides, ozone, particulate matter and sulfur dioxide. Each pollutant must be reviewed for a possible new health and environmentally protective standard every five years, though in some cases -- for example the ozone NAAQS review -- EPA is behind schedule.
The EDSP would also lose funding under the budget plan, despite EPA's release last month of its updated comprehensive management plan for the program's next five years, with an ambitious agenda for releasing new test orders, finalizing validation of the second tier of tests in the two-tiered screening program and gradually implementing the use of computational toxicology into the program's current animal-based testing procedures.
According to the budget justification, "This reduction is to implement strategic sourcing across a wide range of contracts, with a goal of at least five percent savings for goods and services but, depending on the extent and effectiveness of the changes, there may be impacts to EDSP . . . In particular, the EDSP program may not complete application of a risk-based prioritization approach for the androgen and thyroid pathways." -- Maria Hegstad (mhegstad@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>