<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-0T31-DY2S-R3HV"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Battle with Baytex goes to court; Families want oilsands facility shut temporarily</title><source>Edmonton Journal (Alberta)</source><author>Sheila Pratt, Edmonton Journal</author><text><![CDATA[A group of Peace River-area families who left the their homes because of fumes from a nearby oilsands operation will be in court Wednesday to try to have the facility temporarily closed until air pollution equipment is installed.
The families are taking the unprecedented step because Calgary-based Baytex Energy has not yet installed promised pollution controls on heated bitumen tanks in the Reno oilfield, said Brian Labrecque, whose father and brothers left their farms south of Peace River due to ill health they blamed on the emissions.
Also, court is the only avenue left since the Alberta Energy Regulator has made clear it has no jurisdiction to regulate the fumes coming from the heated bitumen tanks, said Labrecque, who testified at public inquiry in January held by the regulator into the Baytex emissions.
"The regulator has admitted it has does not have any jurisdiction, so the courts are our only option," Labrecque said.
The case could set a precedent if the court rules for the families and grants the injunction. So far, only the regulator has shut down company operations to deal with pollution issues or spills.
Baytex spokesman Andrew Loosley said company studies show the air is safe and that landowners are opposing company efforts to install the equipment needed to capture the fumes from the tanks.
"The landowners asking for the injunction do not live there and have said they have no plan to move back," Loosley said in an email.
"Therefore, they are removed from any risk they may believe exists."
Keith Wilson, lawyer for the area residents, noted that other companies operating near Peace River have installed the tank-top vapour recovery units to capture the fumes. But in its latest letter last week, Baytex offered to install the equipment only where and if it is "operationally feasible to do so," he added. "If this is what the future looks like for people living near a major oilsands development, that's troubling."
Residents said fumes from heated bitumen tanks caused dizziness, headache, fatigue and cognitive impairment.
The bitumen is heated in large tanks to separate the water, oil and sand, and soften it for shipping.
spratt@edmontonjournal.com
]]></text></news-item>