<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-Y2C1-F0J6-J365"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>US inquiry affects Macquarie</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>John Kehoe</author><text><![CDATA[Washington United States prosecutors are investigating potential conflicts of interest in multi-billion dollar government infrastructure tenders, including a bridge contract won by Australia's Macquarie Group.
A Macquarie-led consortium last year won a $US1.5 billion ($1.64 billion) tender by the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey to finance and construct a commuter bridge.
The US Attorney's Office subpoenaed documents last week relating to possible conflicts of interest involving the chairman of the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, David Samson, The New York Times reported on Tuesday. The query focuses on two bridge contracts worth a combined $US2.8 billion.
Mr Samson is also a member of law firm Wolff & Samson, which acts for a separate, unrelated Macquarie-owned business in the United States.
Mr Samson has been under public pressure in recent months after it was revealed the port authority closed road lanes under the orders of associates of New Jersey governor Chris Christie who were imposing a payback on a local political adversary.
There is no suggestion Macquarie has done anything wrong or Mr Samson acted improperly. Macquarie silent
A Macquarie spokeswoman declined to comment on Tuesday.
In April last year, a group led by Macquarie and Kiewit Corp won the public-private partnership contract to finance, design and build a $US1.5 billion replacement for the 85-year-old Goethals Bridge which connects New Jersey to New York's Staten Island and is a popular route for trucks and cars.
The NYNJ Link Partnership awarded the contract, is 90 per cent owned by Macquarie Infrastructure & Real Assets. The remaining 10 per cent share belongs to Kiewit Development.
The other New York bridge project under scrutiny that the port authority approved was the $US1.3 billion raising of the Bayonne Bridge. Macquarie is not named as a party to the consortium involved in that project. Its joint venture partner in the Goethals project, Kiewit, was awarded the contract for Bayonne.
Mr Samson's link to Macquarie appears to be via a New Orleans liquid storage facility business, International-Matex Tank Terminals of which Macquarie Infrastructure Company owns 50 per cent.
IMTT is a client of Wolff & Samson, which Mr Samson founded in 1972. He remains a member of the firm.
There is no evidence Macquarie has directly hired Wolff & Samson.
Macquarie's major legal advisor in the United States is McCarter & English.
Wolff & Samson defended IMTT last year to avoid it becoming a third-party defendant in a river pollution case when the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection sued Occidental Chemical Corp.
Public records show Wolff &Samson also acted as a paid lobbyist for IMTT in New Jersey.
The other owner of IMTT is the wealthy American Coleman family, which controls the management of IMTT, including selecting Wolff & Samson as its legal representative.
In a separate action, Macquarie has been in litigation against the Coleman family to try and claim management control of IMTT.
The Port Authority New York New Jersey declined to comment on Tuesday. Mr Samson did not respond to an email and Wolff & Samson did not respond to a telephone inquiry.
Key points Macquarie consortium has won a $1.64 billion port authority contract for a bridge in New York. Port authority chairman at the centre of the US Attorney Office inquiry.
]]></text></news-item>