<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-54F1-JBVM-Y4WP"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Leeds in crisis as Cellino is found guilty</title><source>Irish Daily Mail</source><author>MATT LAWTON</author><text><![CDATA[LEEDS UNITED are in danger of descending into financial meltdown after prospective owner Massimo Cellino was yesterday found guilty of tax evasion in Italy.
With the Football League now likely to block Cellino's takeover on the basis of their fit and proper persons test, officials at Elland Road fear the club could be forced into administration if the Italian demands the return of the £10million he has invested. Football League rules prohibit people with 'unspent convictions for offences of dishonesty, corruption, perverting the course of justice, serious breaches of the Companies Act or conspiracy to commit any of those offences'.
Yesterday Cellino, 57, who already owns the Italian club Cagliari, was fined (EURO)600,000 after being found guilty of illegally evading (EURO)400,000 import duty on a luxury yacht.
Cellino's defence lawyer, Giovanni Cocco, said his client would appeal, claiming the verdict 'is absolutely unjust'. Yesterday the Football League said they had noted the outcome of the court hearing. 'We are engaged in an ongoing dialogue with his legal representatives in this country and cannot comment further.' If the League block the 75 per cent takeover agreed through Cellino's holding company, Eleonora Sports, on February 1, the question is how he then responds. Cellino has paid around £6.5m to cover wages and general bills as well as an outstanding loan of £1.7m to a club sponsor. More than £3m has also been paid to current owners Gulf Finance House Capital, and the worry is that Cellino (left) would simply demand a return of the cash. GFH would stand to lose money they have invested - believed to be between £35m-£40m - if they then took the club into administration. But with no current alternative to Cellino and little prospect of Premier League football, GFH face some tough decisions. Brian McDermott's side are currently 14th in the Championship, having lost their last four games. A 10-point deduction if they go into adminstration would leave Leeds fifth from bottom.
]]></text></news-item>