<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-R031-JBJ4-21FS"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Prosecution of Kenyan Central Bank Governor Gives Impetus to War On Graft</title><source>Sabahi</source><author>Julius Kithuure</author><text><![CDATA[The impending prosecution of Central Bank of Kenya (CBK) Governor Njuguna Ndung'u for alleged graft and abuse of office sends a strong message that the judiciary will be tough on corruption, officials and citizens say.
Ndung'u is accused of abuse of office for irregularities involving a 1.2-billion shilling ($13.9 million) contract that was awarded last year to Horsebridge Networks Systems East Africa Limited for the installation of security software at the Central Bank.
Director of Public Prosecutions (DPP) Keriako Tobiko says Ndung'u's actions led to the loss of more than 400 million shillings ($4.6 million) in public funds.
While the case looked as though it would join a backlog of other cases involving senior government officials that have not been prosecuted, Tobiko ordered Ndung'u's arrest on February 11th.
Ndung'u, who denies any involvement, appealed the arrest, and the High Court is scheduled to continue hearing the case on March 28th.
While the outcome of the case hangs in the balance, government officials say the case represents a positive step in stemming government corruption.
"We are sending a deterrence message to any government officials who may be tempted to embezzle any public funds or misuse power in the tendering process that we are watching and we will bite back ruthlessly," said Emily Kamau, head of the DPP's anti-corruption and economic crimes division.
"Kenyans have thrown all manner of accusations at us, saying we are reluctant to prosecute the powerful and influential," she told Sabahi. "It will not be business as usual anymore. Let the government employees entrusted with public funds and privileges utilise them lawfully."
Although Ndung'u has been granted a temporary reprieve from arrest, the possibility of his prosecution is real and if this happens, he would have to vacate his position.
"He is lucky that he enjoys the security of tenure thus the president's hands are tied he cannot fire him immediately," constitutional lawyer Anderson Mwiti told Sabahi.
Mwiti said this case will be followed keenly by senior government officials, especially those with pending corruption cases because it heralds an era of boldness by the prosecution. He said the DPP now seems intent to hold senior public officials accountable for loss of public funds, which is a break from past practices.
"Without going after the so-called big fish, anti-corruption institutions ended up focusing on low-level corruption involving small sums of money while the big fish continued to accumulate wealth and power," he said.
"The bold move to prosecute senior personnel such as Ndung'u shows that the era of selective prosecution by the Ethics and Anti-Corruption Commission and the office of the Director of Public Prosecutions is long gone," said Mercy Mwai-Gikonyo, 32, a sales executive at Clarion Hotel in Nairobi.
"The new-found working relationship between the DPP office and the EACC augurs well for the country. This teamwork will definitely rattle the corrupt," she told Sabahi. "I hope they will revisit the old files especially on Anglo Leasing scandal and bring those culprits to book as well."
The Anglo Leasing scandal involved government funds being paid to shadowy foreign companies for services ranging from forgery-proof passports to naval ships and forensic laboratories that never materialised.
Only former Home Affairs Permanent Secretary Sylvester Mwaliko has been found guilty of abuse of office and convicted for his role in the multi-million dollar Anglo Leasing corruption scandal.
"There were other senior government ministers and senior officials involved but they have not been prosecuted to date," said Morris Mokua, 44, manager at Bata Shop in Nairobi. "These serving and former government officials are not untouchable Kenyans. They should take responsibility for the scandal and should not continue to enjoy immunity from the political elite that protects its own interests."
Other pending corruption cases against senior government officials include the case of George Okungu, former managing director of Kenya Pipeline Company, for his alleged role in a 2008 oil scam involving privately-owned Triton Oil Company in which the government lost 7.5 billion shillings ($86.7 million). Okungu still has not been arrested.
In March 2010, then Deputy Prime Minister Musalia Mudavadi was accused by the Kenya Anti-Corruption Commission, which has now been replaced by EACC, of land fraud over a deal worth 283 million shillings ($3.2 million). Mudavadi has never been charged.
Lydia Moraa, 48, a supervisor at Nairobi's Afro Forex Bureau Limited, said says hopes Ndung'u's case is not a smokescreen by the DPP's office to dupe Kenyans into thinking the government has declared an all-out war on corrupt officials.
"Past corruption scandals such as Anglo Leasing have had a direct impact on our economy and when high corruption is not annihilated, it sends out a message that anti-corruption institutions cannot be relied upon to protect against abuse of authority or to deliver justice," she told Sabahi.
"The case raises hopes that the corrupt and powerful are not after all untouchable," she said. "I also hope that there is adequate evidence to sustain a successful trial."
For his part, Maurice Awiti, associate director at the University of Nairobi's school of economics, said investors should not fear that the case will bring instability in the market.
"There is no need to panic because the Central Bank has a continuity strategy which is not based on one person but a strong institutional succession plan," he told Sabahi, explaining that the bank's deputy governor would take the top leadership role if needed.
"The most important thing is for the Central Bank to monitor monetary policy issues and ensure fiscal discipline continuity without letting the governor's case trigger market volatility," Awiti said.
"[Ndung'u's] prosecution is a brave policy departure from the government's deep-rooted lack of political will to address corruption at the highest levels," he said. "It importantly sets an example that the fight against sleaze will be waged from the top downward."
]]></text></news-item>