<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-C3R1-JBG7-43MH"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Defying West, Putin claims Crimea</title><source>Chicago Tribune</source><author>By Sergei L. Loiko and Carol J. Williams, Tribune Newspapers Loiko reported from Simferopol and Williams from Los Angeles. Tribune Newspapers' Henry Chu in London and special correspondent Kim Willsher in Paris contributed.</author><text><![CDATA[-- Russian President Vladimir Putin defied Western warnings by signing a treaty to annex Ukraine's Crimea Peninsula on Tuesday while accusing the United States and its allies of going too far in luring post-Soviet nations away from Moscow.
Putin signed the accord with the region's new Moscow-backed leaders appropriating the region and its vital naval port of Sevastopol less than two days after voters backed secession from Ukraine in a widely criticized referendum. The treaty, which is expected to be ratified by the Russian parliament and the Constitutional Court, were signed in a solemn atmosphere in the Kremlin's lavish St. George hall.
Shortly before, Putin gave a fiery televised speech often interrupted by applause from jubilant lawmakers, government officials and other dignitaries.
While continuing to deny that the thousands of Russian troops in Crimea constituted an armed invasion, Putin reiterated his claim that Ukraine in recent weeks came under the rule of fascists and "Russophobes" based in Kiev, the capital.
Putin justified the takeover of Crimea as fulfilling Russia's "historic legacy." Crimea "should be part of a strong and stable sovereignty, which today can only be Russian," he said, stating that Kiev "isn't in control of anything."
Crimea was part of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics after the Bolshevik Revolution. It was transferred to the administrative control of Soviet Ukraine in 1954 in a gesture that had little strategic meaning when both republics were part of the Soviet Union.
Ukraine's interim president, Oleksandr Turchynov, vowed that Kiev would never accept Russia's seizure of Crimea. "The Ukrainian people and the entire civilized world will never recognize the annexation of Ukrainian land," he said, according to the Unian news agency.
Vice President Joe Biden, on a mission to reassure Eastern European NATO members that the Western alliance will protect them from any Russian aggression, warned that Russia will face increasingly painful sanctions if Putin continues to pursue the "dark path" of violating the territorial integrity of a neighbor.
The U.S. and the European Union on Monday imposed sanctions against some Russian and Ukrainian officials, but Western options seem limited.
"The world has seen through Russia's actions and has rejected the flawed logic," Biden said at his meeting in Poland with leaders of Russia's former communist allies unnerved by what many consider the Kremlin's brazen land grab.
Putin boasted in his speech that Russia had recovered Crimea "without a shot fired" through the careful actions of local self-defense forces -- Moscow's description of the Russian troops that have deployed by the thousands throughout Crimea.
A confrontation Tuesday between Russian and Ukrainian forces, however, turned deadly when Russian snipers reportedly opened fire in the center of Simferopol, the Crimean capital. A Ukrainian soldier died and two others were injured, prompting the Ukrainian Defense Ministry to order its servicemen to return fire if attacked, Unian reported. Russia's ITAR-Tass agency said one member of the local self-defense forces was killed and two wounded.
Putin chastised the West for what he suggested was a campaign to undermine Russia's strategic interests since the 1991 collapse of the Soviet Union.
"They have constantly tried to drive us into a corner for our independent stance, for defending it, for calling things their proper names and not being hypocritical," Putin said. "But there are limits. And in the case of Ukraine, our Western partners have crossed a line."
Kremlin-controlled media have cast European Union and U.S. diplomatic contacts with Ukraine's political opposition in the months before Ukrainian President Viktor Yanukovych fled to Russia last month as meddling aimed at turning the country against its natural alliance and integration with Russia.
Pressure from Putin prompted Yanukovych to abandon an EU association deal that would have boosted Ukraine's trade and economic cooperation with Western Europe, which sparked rebellion against the autocrat.
Three months after the protests began, a bloody crackdown by riot police and snipers spurred a three-day melee of urban combat in which scores were killed and political defections from Yanukovych's ruling Party of Regions shifted power to the opposition leaders behind the protests.
Yanukovych was eventually compelled to agree to early elections and an interim power-sharing agreement but fled after signing the EU-brokered peace deal Feb. 21.
Putin has cast the interim leaders of Ukraine as ultranationalists bent on repressing the country's ethnic Russian minority, which constitutes about 17 percent of Ukraine's 46 million population, but a majority of Crimea's 2 million residents.
Putin and the pro-Russian leaders installed in Crimea less than three weeks ago signed a treaty Tuesday to add the peninsula to the Russian Federation's territory by the end of this year. The agreement has to be ratified by parliament, but that is a mere formality in a legislature dominated by Putin loyalists.
In London, British Foreign Secretary William Hague lamented Putin's choosing "the route of isolation," and warned that the international community will not be swayed by his claims to have been pushed by the West to secure Russia's rightful interests.
Britain suspended military cooperation with Russia in retaliation for the Crimean seizure, and France warned it might cancel delivery of two state-of-the-art Mistral warships, the first due by the end of this year under a $1.3 billion contract.
Russia has been effectively suspended from the Group of Eight industrialized nations that it joined in 1998.
At President Barack Obama's suggestion, the original Group of Seven -- the U.S., Britain, Germany, Japan, France, Italy and Canada -- and the European Union will meet next week to consider further sanctions aimed at compelling Putin to back down.
Loiko reported from Simferopol and Williams from Los Angeles. Tribune Newspapers' Henry Chu in London and special correspondent Kim Willsher in Paris contributed.
sloiko@tribune.com
ct14 0065 140319 N S 0000000000 00003456
]]></text></news-item>