<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-PMS1-JC3H-04KS"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Critics cite Nevada 'fracking' concerns</title><source>Reno Gazette-Journal (Nevada)</source><author>By, Jeff DeLong</author><text><![CDATA[jdelong@rgj.com
"Fracking" for oil could endanger precious water supplies and increase the potential for seismic danger, critics told Nevada officials Monday.
Meeting in Carson City, officials from the Nevada Division of Minerals heard from conservationists, tribal members and others worried that plans to begin drilling for oil through hydraulic fracturing could bring serious problems to Northern Nevada.
Others described proposed regulations as an effective means to protect the public from the impact of a new activity that could provide a needed boost to the Silver State's economy.
Monday's workshop, the first of three this week, came amid plans by Houston-based Noble Energy Inc., to drill using the controversial fracking technique, which injects a pressurized solution of water, sand and chemicals into a well to fracture shale and access deep oil deposits.
Noble Energy hopes to soon use fracking to reach oil deposits near Wells.
While Monday's meeting was designed to garner technical input on new regulations guiding the practice, many attending took the opportunity to question a process they fear could come with significant environmental consequences, with threats to water supplies cited as a big concern.
"The primary goal in a desert is to protect our water. That's how we protect our life," said Bob Fulkerson, executive director of the Progressive Leadership Alliance of Nevada.
Fulkerson expressed doubt the proposed regulations will go far enough, describing the Division of Minerals as too close to the mining and oil industries.
"It's going to be hard to trust these regulations coming from an inherently biased process," Fulkerson said.
"My concern is the sacredness of the water. Water is life to everything," said Raquel Arthur of the Northern Nevada chapter of the American Indian Movement. "The way I see it is it's going to destroy mother earth."
Fracking could increase seismic danger in a state already prone to earthquakes, warned Joe Bryan. Processes linked to fracking have been linked to earthquakes in other states, critics said.
Noble Energy executive Kevin Vorhaben said fracking would occur at depths far below levels where they could threaten groundwater supplies and described Nevada's proposed regulations as strong and effective.
He said his company is committed to protecting the environment.
"Noble Energy believes these regulations are tough and thorough and will ensure the public and the environment is protected," Vorhaben said.
Wyatt Haag supported oil production through fracking as a means to boost the economy.
"Nevada needs money now," he said.
Additional workshops are scheduled by the Division of Minerals Wednesday in Elko and Friday in Las Vegas.
]]></text></news-item>