<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-M5H1-DY33-22KV"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>RETIRED OFFICER PLEADS GUILTY IN CAMPAIGN CASE</title><source>The San Diego Union-Tribune</source><author>KRISTINA DAVIS, U-T</author><text><![CDATA[A retired San Diego police detective admitted Tuesday to helping funnel illegal foreign funds into local political campaigns, marking the first guilty plea in the public corruption investigation.
Ernesto “Ernie” Encinas, 58, pleaded guilty in San Diego federal court to conspiracy to commit crimes against the United States and filing a false tax return.
He faces up to eight years in prison when sentenced June 9.
As owner of a security consulting business, Encinas provided protection for Mexican tycoon José Susumo Azano Matsura, the alleged source of $600,000 in illegal donations.
Prosecutors say Azano, whose family owns two homes in Coronado, wanted to buy political influence so he could transform San Diego’s bayfront into “Miami West.”
The U.S. Attorney’s Office said Encinas had a motive of his own — to have then-Police Chief Bill Lansdowne ousted.
Sources say Encinas wanted a new chief with more-lenient views on alcohol licensing for nightclubs and bars. Encinas consulted regularly for downtown businesses after his retirement in 2009, and he helped lobby city officials on issues relating to licensing, public records show.
Encinas’ attorney, Jeremy Warren, said outside the courthouse Tuesday that the 31-year police veteran wanted a new police chief for broader reasons.
“He was in contact as a retired officer with lots of fellow officers, and the message he was getting was that Lansdowne as a chief was a good guy but had overstayed his term,” Warren said. Encinas wanted a new chief to reflect the diversity of the department and the community, he added.
“He did what he felt was in the best interest of the Police Department ... and the citizens of San Diego,” Warren said. “Obviously, the end didn’t justify the means, and that’s why he took responsibility.”
According to the plea agreement, the scheme began in 2011, when Azano became interested in donating to local campaigns. Encinas consulted a representative of a campaign and was told it was illegal for a non-U.S. citizen to contribute. Encinas passed on this information to Azano, the document states.
Azano then used straw donors to make a series of $500 contributions to an unnamed candidate — identifiable as District Attorney Bonnie Dumanis — in the 2012 San Diego mayoral race, according to the court document. Encinas found out about it and got his own friends and family to make similar donations to show solidarity with Azano, the plea deal states.
An independent expenditure committee was also formed to support Dumanis, raising $114,000.
About $150,000 and social media services were given to support another unnamed mayoral candidate, identifiable in records as Bob Filner, and other support was provided to an unnamed congressional candidate, believed to be Rep. Juan Vargas.
The payments were allegedly made through a straw donor, who has not been named publicly in court documents but is identifiable as Marc Chase, co-owner of a luxury car dealership in La Jolla.
Azano has been indicted in the scheme, as well as City Hall lobbyist Marco Polo Cortes and Ravneet Singh, whose ElectionMall campaign services company provided candidates with website and social media services, authorities said. They have pleaded not guilty.
Encinas also admitted to tax fraud relating to the work his security company, Coastline Protection and Investigations, provided for Azano.
As part of the plea deal, Encinas admitted that Azano paid him about $10,000 a month in cash off the books during 2011 and 2012, and he failed to report a total of $222,000 in income to the Internal Revenue Service. Encinas has agreed to pay back the nearly $69,400 in tax loss as restitution.
There were indications early on in the case that a plea agreement might be imminent. Encinas was allowed to surrender with his attorney at his arraignment in January and was permitted to stay out of custody on his own recognizance. His co-defendants were arrested and had to post bond to be released.
Perhaps most telling was that he waived his right for the charges against him to be argued before a grand jury.
Warren did not comment on whether Encinas will testify against the others charged in the case.
kristina.davis@utsandiego.com (619) 542-4591 Twitter: @kristinadavis
]]></text></news-item>