<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-7MV1-JCTS-G1VY"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Environmental groups file lawsuit against Plaquemines Parish coal export facility ; Opponents say river is being polluted</title><source>Times-Picayune (New Orleans)</source><author>Benjamin Alexander-Bloch Staff writer</author><text><![CDATA[Environmental groups filed a federal lawsuit in New Orleans on Tuesday against United Bulk's coal export facility in Plaquemines Parish, alleging the facility is polluting the Mississippi River.
In their suit, the nonprofits Gulf Restoration Network, Louisiana Environmental Action Network and the Sierra Club allege that the terminal has discharged hazardous coal runoff and petroleum coke into the river every day that it has operated for at least the past five years, and that those discharges have violated the federal Clean Water Act.
In a statement, United Bulk said it has already invested
$40 million of a planned $80 million in upgrades using the latest technology in safety and environmental impact.
The move comes as the Clean Gulf Commerce Coalition -- an umbrella organization for local and national environmental groups -- and some local residents continue to fight against a proposed new coal facility on the other side of the Mississippi River, in Plaquemines' Myrtle Grove community.
Those opponents say the proposed RAM plant would add to the environmental impacts from the two existing coal facilities already in Plaquemines: the United Bulk Terminal near Davant, on the river's east side, and Kinder Morgan's International Marine Terminal coal facility in Port Sulphur, just a few miles away on the river's west side from that proposed RAM terminal.
'A very bad neighbor'
Warren Lawrence, a Myrtle Grove resident who lives just across the river from the United Bulk terminal and within a mile of the IMT facility, described "problems with black dust coating everything, our homes, our boats and even coating in a layer at the bottom of our swimming pool."
He said the proposed RAM facility would be about a mile west of his home.
"I support the Clean Gulf Coalition because I live here and I firsthand know of the pollution," Lawrence said on Tuesday. "I am worried these terminals are polluting the air with their dust, and the river. ... Coal terminals to me are a very bad neighbor.
"We feel it is totally unacceptable. We don't want any more terminals."
In response to NOLA.com and The Times-Picayune requests for comment about the suit, United Bulk Terminals Davant LLC, at 14537 Louisiana 15, released a statement on Tuesday afternoon.
"We are disappointed that the plaintiffs have chosen to file suit despite our ongoing and constructive dialogue with them since they first came to us last November," the statement said. "We invest substantial time and money to ensure compliance with our air and water permits and have demonstrated our commitment to minimizing the impact of our operations on the environment and on the communities where we operate.
"Specifically, before any contact from the environmental groups, we were in process of enhancing environmental compliance efforts and had allocated over $80 million of capital towards a facility modernization program that includes comprehensive upgrades in accordance with the latest technology and practices in terms of safety and environmental impact," the statement continued. "We have already invested approximately $40 million in the facility's upgrades.
"We will continue to take our responsibility seriously to protect the environment and meet or exceed the regulatory requirements that govern our business."
Suit targets pollution
Louisiana accounts for about 20 percent of U.S. coal exports, mostly because of its location at the intersection of Mississippi River barge routes serving Midwestern states with large coal deposits and Gulf shipping routes serving Europe and Latin America, according to a May report from the National Mining Association.
The New Orleans customs district, which includes Plaquemines, was second in the United States in terms of coal exports, according to a quarterly report by the U.S. Energy Information Administration.
The suit against United Bulk in part seeks civil penalties of up to $37,500 per day per violations of the Clean Water Act. It also ask that a judge enjoin the terminal from "leaking, discharging, or disposing of coal" or petroleum coke into the river, order the terminal to remove any coal or coke in the batture and the river, and require United Bulk to fund long-term, independent monitoring of remediation efforts and of the terminal's ongoing operations.
"It is our hope that this legal action results in the clean up and prevention of further pollution from this terminal," said Scott Eustis, a coastal wetlands specialist for Gulf Restoration Network.
The environmental groups state in the suit, which is being handled by Tulane University's Environmental Law Clinic, that they first documented unpermitted discharges at the United Bulk terminal on Dec. 31, 2009, and that they have documented more than 10 unpermitted discharges since then, with the most recent occurring Feb. 18.
"Indeed, every time the Plaintiffs have visited vicinity of the terminal, they have witnessed evidence of unpermitted discharges in the River," the suit states. "The Defendant has failed on a daily basis to take all reasonable steps to minimize or correct the adverse environmental impacts resulting from its spilled wastes for at least the past five years, and continues to fail on a daily basis to minimize or correct the environmental impacts from its waste -- including without limitation waste that is now located in the river.
"United Bulk has also failed on a daily basis to monitor its discharges to determine their nature and impact."
DEQ issues order
Earlier this year, the Louisiana Department of Environmental Quality filed a compliance order against United Bulk stating that the terminal must stop "any spills and/or unauthorized discharges from the Respondent's facility to waters of the state."
That order states that the United Bulk terminal "failed to cleanup and dispose of spilled products and spilled wastes immediately" and that, specifically at the downstream end of the facility, that "coke and coal fall from the conveyor belts onto the batture."
"According to the facility representative, the cleanup occurs as long as the river is low. When the river is high, the piles of coal and coke are submerged in water and cleanup does not occur," the order said.
While United Bulk terminal began operations in about 1965, it was purchased in the summer of 2012 by Oiltanking North America. In a letter to DEQ enforcement officials at the end of December, an attorney for United Bulk wrote that upon purchasing the terminal that "Oiltanking recognized a need to upgrade the downriver conveyor" and that, "towards that end, it set aside $80 million to achieve that goal and immediately began to design the new system."
That letter states that the design work for that downriver conveyor is done and awaiting Corps of Engineer approval before construction can begin.
The DEQ order issued in January requires that those upgrades be completed by June 30, 2015. The order also states that United Bulk must submit a progress report to DEQ each month until the completion of those improvements.
Documenting contamination
The environment groups' suit on Tuesday says the DEQ compliance order and notice of potential penalty "is encouraging" and that the plaintiffs "intend to be alert to opportunities to work with the Defendant to avoid any unnecessary litigation and to achieve expeditious abatement and cleanup of the Defendant's discharges."
The environmental groups on Tuesday also handed out photos that the groups said show "unpermitted discharge into the Mississippi River and significant build-up of coal in the batture and along the river's edge."
They said another of the photos shows "discharged coal downstream from the conveyer system" of the United Bulk terminal."
Marylee Orr, executive director of Louisiana Environmental Action Network, said that discharges are "visible from thousands of feet in the air" with the "black coal contaminated waters spreading in plums."
The suit states that the United Bulk terminal, which sits on about 3 miles of riverfront property on the parish's east bank, annually ships 11 million tons of coal and petroleum coke to overseas markets, and several thousand tons of coal and petroleum coke per hour between land and oceangoing ships. It states that sources of the spills "include a loading and conveyance system that extends more than 200 feet into the Mississippi River."
Some of the other photos, taken after Hurricane Isaac, show coal-contaminated storm water from United Bulk collected in a retention pond, which then flowed into a nearby canal, and storm water collected around piles of open coal at Kinder Morgan's International Marine Terminal in Port Sulphur, according to the environmental groups.
Eustis said "after Isaac, we spent time in the air and on the ground documenting, and we couldn't help notice these blatant discharges."
In generically discussing potential environmental impacts from coal runoff, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency literature states that "if rain falls on coal stored in piles outside the power plant, the water that runs off these piles can flush heavy metals from the coal, such as arsenic and lead, into nearby bodies of water."
Air testing last fall by some Plaquemines residents near the International Marine Terminal found elevated fine particulate matter, known as PM-10, that could potentially cause health concerns to sensitive people if there was long-term exposure.
. . . . . . .
Benjamin Alexander-Bloch can be reached at bbloch@nola.com or 504.826.3321.
]]></text></news-item>