<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-P3H1-JD6S-R0KC"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Duke, Cook settle suits</title><source>Citrus County Chronicle (Florida)</source><author>Mike Wright</author><text><![CDATA[Citrus County Property Appraiser Les Cook and Duke Energy on Tuesday announced settlements of two lawsuits over billions of dollars in taxable value at the company's power plant in Crystal River.
The settlements should result in about $7.5 million in additional funds split among the school board, county commission and other taxing districts, Cook said.
Plus, Cook and Duke agreed to the company's 2014 taxable value, avoiding a third lawsuit from the company and providing stability for taxing districts as they begin preparing budgets for next year.
"It's the right thing to do and it wasn't an easy thing to do," Cook, appointed to office Jan. 6 after Geoff Greene's death, said. "If I didn't think this was good for the community, I would have gone to trial."
In November 2012, Duke made a "good faith" payment of $19.6 million in property taxes - about $15 million less than what county officials said was owed and what they were counting on to provide funding for budgets that were already set.
A year later, the company paid $22.3 million. According to Greene's higher assessment of the property, the tax payment should have been $37.5 million.
Duke sued for both its 2012 and 2013 taxable values.
The biggest issue was the company's pollution-control equipment at the coal plants. Greene, relying on a 1997 judge's ruling on a separate case, said the equipment should be assessed at full value. Duke said state law has pollution-control equipment valued as salvage.
A judge in November sided with Duke, saying Greene could not challenge the law.
Cook said that decision effectively killed the property appraiser's position. He said Greene, just weeks before his death, instructed him to seek settlement negotiations with Duke to avoid going to trial in May.
While the settlement calls for the Duke property to increase in taxable value in 2012 and 2013 by about $500 million, it's far short of what Greene had assessed the property.
Cook said a large chunk of Greene's assessment was for the pollution-control equipment, which was going to be eliminated based on the judge's ruling.
On the other hand, Greene's decision to conduct a "boots on the ground" assessment of the Crystal River Energy Complex provided enough new assessed property to nearly offset a huge drop in value in 2014 because the company took its nuclear plant off line permanently.
The 2014 value is $1.3 billion for Duke, down $300 million from 2013. Cook said he knew that Duke planned to ask the judge to set the value at $900 million - the difference between $900 million and $1.3 billion assessed value is about $7 million in taxes, Cook said.
"I think we've worked out a framework for avoiding litigation in the future," Cook said.
Duke spokesman Sterling Ivey said in a statement the company looks forward to continuing being an important part of the community.
"We appreciate the cooperative efforts between our company and Property Appraiser Les Cook that resulted in the resolution of this matter," he said.
Citrus County Commissioner Joe Meek said he was pleased to see the lawsuits settled.
"Any time you can put an end to costly litigation and find stability to an issue this big, it's a great thing," he said.
Kenny Blocker, assistant superintendent of schools, said locking in the 2014 Duke assessment is important heading into the budget year.
"There are no mistakes. There are no hiccups," he said. "It's very clear and very helpful for everybody."
Contact Chronicle reporter Mike Wright at 352-563-3228 or mwright@chronicleonline.com
SETTLEMENT HIGHLIGHTS
* About $7.5 million net in taxes for 2012 and 2013 combined to be split among the school board, county commission and smaller taxing districts.
* Taxable value for 2014 agreed at $2.3 billion, giving school board, county commission and others assurance of a firm commitment from Citrus County 's largest taxpayer.
* Avoids further litigation costs. County taxpayers have already spent about $1.4 million on the Duke lawsuits.
]]></text></news-item>