<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-YSV1-JBHM-S4F3"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Industry Warns Supreme Court Of CERCLA Ruling's Expanded Tort Liability</title><source>InsideEPA.com's Daily Briefing</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Manufacturers are warning an appellate ruling broadly interpreting Superfund law language preempting state limits on when plaintiffs can file toxic tort claims may have the unintended consequence of extending tort liability far beyond environmental cases, and are urging the Supreme Court to overturn it.
The concerns raised by a coalition of industry groups in a March 3 amicus brief expand on criticisms by Department of Justice (DOJ) and an association of defense attorneys, who all say the U.S. Court of Appeals for the 4th Circuit made an overly broad reading of the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation & Liability Act (CERCLA) when it found in a controversial split ruling that language preempting state "statute[s] of limitations" also applies to time limits included in statutes of repose.
A statute of limitations imposes a limit on the amount of time a plaintiff has to sue once he or she is injured by a tortious act, while a statute of repose abolishes the right to sue after a period of time, regardless of whether an injury is manifest.
The arguments by the American Chemistry Council, American Coatings Association, American Petroleum Institute, National Association of Manufacturers and Precision Machined Products Association calling for a narrow reading of CERCLA section 309 based on a plain reading of the language are similar to amicus briefs filed by DRI, an association that represents defense attorneys known as DRI, and by DOJ in the case known as CTS Corporation v. Waldburger .
But the industry groups go further, saying the 4th Circuit's ruling, if allowed to stand, "will have serious ramifications on state tort law far beyond the context of environmental litigation -- inadvertently upsetting the balance states have struck among competing interests, goals, and priorities in their substantive tort laws." If the high court backs a broad reading of section 309, it "could preserve lawsuits in any area -- even far outside the environmental context -- that happen to involve anything that could be considered a 'hazardous substance' under CERCLA," the groups say.
Congress adopted CERCLA section 309, also known as section 9658 because of where it is found in the U.S. Code, to address concerns that state time limits on when tort claims may be brought would prevent individuals from being able to sue over chemical exposures that would not cause disease until decades after the exposure occurred. The section preempts state limitation periods by creating a federal "discovery rule" that prevents a state statute of limitations from beginning until the plaintiff knows about his injury and its cause.
In the 4th Circuit ruling, a split panel of three judges found that while section 309's language "could reasonably lead to a conclusion that its application is limited only to statutes of limitations," an alternative reading is possible that encompasses statutes of repose.
The 4th Circuit's ruling effectively eliminated CTS' defense that the plaintiffs' claims of toxic torts are time-barred under North Carolina tort law, which includes a 10-year statute of repose.
The Supreme Court earlier this year agreed to hear the appeal of the case, following CTS' petition for certiorari to the high court late last year,
CTS is arguing that the "plain text" of the law and the constitutional principle of federalism require the high court to overturn the appellate ruling.
DOJ's Brief
DOJ -- which is concerned about potential federal liability for exposures at a major Marine Corps base in North Carolina that are being litigated in a separate case -- emphasizes in its March 3 amicus brief that a federal report to Congress in the 1980s made a number of recommendations on changes to state tort laws but that Congress opted only to enact the federal discovery rule for state statutes of limitations.
DOJ explains that in addition to section 309 only mentioning statutes of limitations, the statutory context confirms that Congress meant only to create a discovery rule and not to preempt statutes of repose.
Both the industry coalition and DRI amicus brief say statutes of repose help preserve judicial fairness by eliminating the threat of eternal liability and helping to balance the plaintiff-friendly provisions of section 309.
"Section 9658 preserves state legislative prerogatives to enact and enforce statutes of repose that help to avoid burdening the courts, as well as corporate defendants, with stale claims and the evidentiary nightmares typically associated with them," DRI says in its Feb. 28 brief.
The industry groups also highlight the benefits to limiting liability, arguing that without the limits imposed by statutes of repose, "companies would be incentivized to act unreasonably in an attempt to avoid liability. Manufacturers might decide not to make useful products altogether or they might be deterred from making safety modifications to products that could later be used as evidence in a tort suit for a heightened standard of care."
Statutes of repose are also important state tools to limit stale claims, promote judicial economy and help control insurance costs, the industry groups say. -- Lara Beaven (lbeaven@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>