<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-FNP1-JCV0-148S"><date>2014-03-19</date><title></title><source>The Star (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Tripoli
Libya accuses US of piracy
Libyan rebels said the US's seizure of a tanker that loaded crude at a port under their control was an illegal act of piracy, a rebel television station said yesterday. Abb-Rabbo al-Barassi, the rebels' self-declared prime minister, said the storming of the tanker by US Navy commandoes had violated international law. US forces seized it on Sunday night off the Cyprus coast.
Blackpool
School bars protest pupil
A 14-year-old boy has been excluded from his school after organising a protest about a lack of homework and good teaching. Politically active teenager Aaron Parfitt has been told by teachers|not to return to Bipsham High School in Blackpool following the protest last Wednesday. He organised a walkout and 100 of his classmates joined, rallying behind him.
Strasbourg
Activists held at nuke plant
French police yesterday arrested 34 Greenpeace activists who forced their way into a nuclear power plant operated by EDF in Fessenheim, eastern France, the company said. The activists hung anti-nuclear banners from the plant, France's oldest in operation, but France's nuclear safety authority said they did not enter into its buildings, and its security was not compromised.
Brisbane
Secret baby graves found
Police in Australia were digging up a rural property yesterday searching for what reports said were "multiple babies" in secret graves. Officers swooped on a house near Gin Gin, 370km north-west of Brisbane, after a tip-off that children were born and their bodies hidden on the property by the same family in the 1990s and early 2000s. Police wouldn't say how many children might have been involved.
Nicosia
Refugees' treatment slated
Cyprus routinely detains asylum-seekers and refugees in prison-like conditions, sometimes breaking EU law by holding them for more than an 18-month maximum, Amnesty International said yesterday. Thousands enter the island each year, and Amnesty accused the government of using detention as a way of discouraging this.
Mombasa
Pair held over bombs
Kenyan police have arrested two men suspected of links to a Somali Islamist militant group after they were tracked and found to have two large bombs that may have been aimed for use in the area of the port city of Mombasa, a senior police officer said.
]]></text></news-item>