<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-5CR1-DY2T-22FC"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Ontario says no to plasma-for-cash clinics</title><source>Windsor Star (Ontario)</source><author>Keith Leslie, The Canadian Press</author><text><![CDATA[Ontario Health Minister Deb Matthews vowed Tuesday to shut down private clinics that pay people to donate blood plasma, accusing one firm of targeting the poor.
Canadian Plasma Services was told it wouldn't be given a licence by the province to open clinics in Toronto and Hamilton that would pay people $25 to donate plasma, Matthews said.
"If you look at where they're located, there's no question that they're going into low income neighbourhoods," she said. "It's very clear what their business model is."
Paying people to donate plasma would threaten Canada's voluntary blood donation system, said Matthews, who noted that 30,000 Canadians were infected with HIV and hepatitis C from contaminated blood and plasma purchased from "blood brokers" in the 1990s.
"We really believe that a voluntary system is the best system, and I do not want to jeopardize our volunteer-based blood collection system," she said.
Canadian Plasma Services said it was baffled by the province's attempts to shut down the clinics when Ontario buys plasma products from U.S. companies that pay donors directly, and pointed out that the province compensates organ donors for expenses.
"I cannot comprehend why a minister from the government of Ontario would be trying to prohibit any type of compensation for time, for out-of-pocket expenses, for travel expenses, to plasma donors in Ontario and then go and buy these products from U.S. companies that do the exact same thing," CEO Barzin Bahardoust said.
Canada should develop its own plasma-products sector that could create thousands of well-paying jobs just to service the domestic market, he added.
"Almost all of the $670 million worth of plasma protein products that were imported to Canada last year were made from plasma collected from paid donors in the United States."
The company offers donors two options for payment: a $25 donation in their name to the Hospital for Sick Children or a $25 Visa card that cannot be converted to cash, in addition to reimbursing travel and accommodation expenses. Donating plasma takes three times as long as donating blood, and people need to make a commitment to donate dozens of times each year to maintain their status as a qualified donor, Bahardoust said.
"That time commitment means that a plasma donor has to spend up to 80 hours (at the clinic) every year," he said.
]]></text></news-item>