<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-Y2C1-F0J6-J35T"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Mining's not war, why 26 deaths?; Matthew Stevens</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>Matthew Stevens</author><text><![CDATA[There is a remarkable, grim and thoroughly unacceptable statistic on page 16 of Glencore's 2013 annual report.
"It is with great sadness that we report the loss of 26 lives at our operations during 2013," the new global resources giant acknowledged before confirming the introduction of a new set of safety protocols under the banner SafeWork.
Now, mining is a dangerous business and often a number like that results from some sort of catastrophic tragedy rather than systemic failure.
We recall, for example, the helicopter crash in Peru that caused the deaths of eight Rio Tito employees back in 2008. Or the underground mine collapse at Freeport's Grasberg mine last May. It claimed 33 lives.
So we checked in with Glencore folk to find out what on earth had happened. But, as it turns out, there was no single calamity. Rather, the death toll was the product of a collection of individual events. And no matter how big and diverse your business is, there is no excuse for causing that level of harm to employees.
While there is no 2013 health and safety data yet on the Glencore website, there is a fair bit of information about 2012. And, as it turns out, the numbers were worse.
In the year ahead of the merger, 22 Glencore employees died at work while five lost their lives at Xstrata assets.Shocking number
Which all means that over the past two years, 53 people have died working for this business. That is a truly shocking number. It means that for two years somewhere around the Glencore world a worker has died at work every two weeks.
To put that ito some sort of external context, 40 Australian soldiers died in Afghanistan over six years of a fighting war.
Mining is work not war.
And the numbers at Glencore's new peer group reflect that simple reality.
Through 2013, for example, three workers died in at BHP Billiton operations and the toll was the same at assets operated directly by Rio Tito. That a further 37 died at assets jointly owned but not operated by Rio reflects mostly the tragic toll at Grasberg.
Everybody in mining talks about "zero harm" being the ultimate ambition of their health and safety programs. But talking safe and living safe are two very different things.
The numbers say that, for whatever reason, the Glencore side of this merger has failed to live by the rhetoric of safety and that needs to change fast.
As unfair as it might be, the irresistible conclusion here is that Glencore's inability to operate safely is linked to its relatively unaccountable past.Transparency exposed strength and weakness
Glencore was, very famously, a privately owned commodities trader than evolved from mining investor to mining operator. And the transparency of public ownership has served to expose management's weaknesses as much as its strengths.
That Glencore has an embedded problem with safety is exposed by more than the numbers of critical accidents that occur. It is a surprise, for example, to see that South America was the most deadly operating environment for Glencore people. This should not be the case, given the company is operating in national constituencies that are neither new to mining nor to industry's best practice.
It is less of a surprise, on the other hand, to see that mobile equipment was the major cause of fatalities. It is often said that the most deadly piece of equipment in mining is a four-wheel-drive. But safe management of moving is achieved through systems and firm enforcement of protocols.
Quite sensibly, Glencore has turned to the Australian wing of Xstrata for some guidance on how to more productively seed the message of safety and its management across the group.
The SafeWork program is based heavily on Xstrata Coal's SafeCoal project. Since its launch in 2009, the Xstrata program has materially lowered workplace fatalities and lost-time injuries.
In the recent past Glencore boss Ivan Glasenberg has said that the loss of any life at work is unacceptable and avoidable. It is to be hoped that the best of intentions and a refocused management effort now promptly translate good intentions ito life-saving outcomes.
On matters Glencore, but far less important, it is being reported that a Chinese consortium led by Andrew Michelmore's MMG has winged its way to London to finalise the acquisition of the Baar-based giant's Las Bambas copper project.
The Peruvian copper mine was a crown jewel Glencore was forced to sacrifice to secure approval for the merger with Xstrata by the Chinese competition regulator.
Given all that, it had always been imagined that Chinese interests would end up owning the thing. And, for all Glencore has held tough on price, so it seems to be proving.
After going in to a trading halt on Monday, the Hong Kong-listed MMG confirmed it was up for Las Bambas with CITIC and Guoxin International.
Gordon Cairns can relax, zen-like, for the moment at least. Because his first week at David Jones has been spectacular enough to earn warm public endorsement from his chief executive: "I am not looking back, we are looking forward. Gordon Cairns is in place, he is working very quickly, he has done a lot in just a week, and I am right behind him."
Now, at many places, the chief executive's thoughts on the chairman would not matter much. Indeed, public assessment might well be received as just that little bit rude. After all, it is the chairman who is supposed to hold the executive in his or her thrall.
But David Jones has proven itself just that little bit different of late. I mean, Paul Zahra is rated as having at least a finger, if not a whole hand, in the end of two chairmen and a pair of directors. So his kind words might hold more than usual relevance to the immediate future of Australia's department store of aspirations.
For the record, Zahra denied management played any part of significance in the theatre of destabilisation that has seen first Robert Savage and then Peter Mason return the keys to the chairman's office. "That is a view," he acknowledged abruptly.
"It is not reality."
Whatever the reality is, pretty much all that Zahra's inquisitors wanted to talk about on Wednesday was to discuss an interim result, which he rightly offered as evidence of the turnaround promised by last year's "future strategic direction plan".Encouragingly wide awake
Department store EBIT rose 8 per cent, like-for-like sales grew 1.1 per cent and costs fell by 30 basis points.
Sure, there are problems yet to address, most notably the credit card business, where EBIT dropped 52 per cent and where the lower level of receivables would indicate people just aren't using the various David Jones offerings like they should.
But overall, an encouragingly wide-awake Zahra really seems to be delivering on the promise of last year's reform package.
Mind you, his rhetoric was not always as convincing as his numbers. He was pushed, for example, on the retailer's belated embrace of all things online. "It is fair to say that we have been slow," he said. "But that is history. We are fast catching up. We have moved swiftly, and by not being the first player it also meant we have got significant advantage because we have learned from all the mistakes that others have made," Zahra offered in a quite individual take of Aesop's tale. Online hares versus the omni-channel tortoise, anyone?
In the end, though, Wednesday was never going to be about results. This was the first chance the market had been offered to quiz Zahra on recent turmoil, on his decision to leave then stay and on Myer's merger proposal.
And it was an opportunity seized. On the merger, Zahra foreshadowed an indicative response within months not years while expressing unconvincing ambivalence about staying on should a deal eventuate. Of the confusion over his tenure and the boardroom turmoil it triggered, he said he had never "formally" resigned in 2013, that the indication he had tired of the job came with announcement of succession in planning rather than the firm promise of departure and that, anyway, "it is history, there is a new chairman, a series of new dynamics."
]]></text></news-item>