<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSG-RV01-JBHM-S3V2"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Groups Press EPA To Drop Fragrances From DfE's Approved Chemicals List</title><source>Environmental Policy Alert</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Environmentalists and medical groups are urging EPA to drop fragrance chemicals from the list of "safer" substances approved by its Design for the Environment (DfE) labeling program, charging that it endorses manufacturers' use of the chemicals in their product formulations even though they may pose risks to children and other sensitive groups.
In a March 13 letter, the groups urge the agency to drop its entire category of fragrances from the DfE list, require DfE to routinely consult with the agency's children's health office to ensure consideration of children's vulnerabilities and affirm that DfE is generally subject to the agency's broad children's health policy. The letter is available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID: 2464560)
"We were surprised and deeply disappointed to learn that the agency's [DfE] created a 'fragrance' category of chemicals for commercial and consumer cleaning products," says the letter to EPA Administrator Gina McCarthy. The decisions on fragrances "undermine" the program and give "false assurances to consumers that products approved by the DfE program do not contain unnecessary volatile chemicals that could harm health."
EPA's DfE program is intended to help purchasers find cleaning products that are "safer" than the product standard. The program is voluntary; manufacturers can present their cleaning products to EPA for analysis. If they meet EPA's criteria, the manufacturer can place the DfE logo on the product's label.
But the groups are concerned with EPA's decision to add fragrance chemicals to the list of substances that are allowed in DfE-labeled products. Last July, EPA added some 119 fragrance chemicals to its Safer Chemical Ingredients List (SCIL) for the first time. The SCIL lists those chemicals "that meet the criteria of the [DfE] Safer Product Labeling Program," according to EPA's DfE website. Arranged by functional class, the SCIL is intended to help manufacturers identify "chemicals that the DfE program has already evaluated and identified as safer."
In January, EPA added another 50 fragrances to its SCIL, bringing the total number of chemicals on the SCIL to "nearly 650," according to the agency's website.
The letter's authors, representing Children's Environmental Health Network (CEHN), American Academy of Pediatrics, American Lung Association, American Thoracic Society and National Medical Association, are pointing to DfE's decision to allow fragrance chemicals as a major cause for concern with DfE.
They charge that 93 of the first 119 fragrance chemicals placed on DfE's list of accepted chemicals "have 'hazard profile issues' because they are identified in one of these three categories: 'Known sensitizer'; 'Lacks sufficient sensitization data'; or a 'Repeat-dose toxicant.'"
"Scented chemicals increase risk that some per cent of exposed people will have allergic and hypersensitivity reactions," the groups write McCarthy. "Allergic and asthmatic children are at especially high risk. That's why it is standard environmental health practice to discourage the use of air fresheners, scented products and fragrances in homes and other indoor spaces."
The groups' concerns come as EPA is trying to boost awareness of the DfE brand with ongoing market studies. Last year, EPA's toxics chief Jim Jones announced efforts to enhance the DfE 'brand,' redesigning it to make it's logo easier to understand and generate more interest in and use of the program.
Wendy Cleland-Hamnett, director of EPA's office of pollution prevention and toxics, told attendees at the GlobalChem conference in Baltimore March 4 that EPA is hoping to increase individual consumers' use of the logo. So far, DfE has mainly been successful with institutional purchasers, those that order cleaning products for their business, school system or local government, she said.
"DfE has been very successful particularly in the institutional space, but we believe that it could be a lot more successful than it has been [in] the consumer space," Cleland-Hamnett said. "The feedback that we get from our partners who have DfE labeled products as well as others is that essentially DfE does not really convey to people safer chemicals."
But the letter's authors suggest DfE should not be considered a symbol of safer chemicals. In a March 13 press release announcing the letter to EPA, the groups write that the "Eco-Healthy Childcare Program (EHCC) ... has withdrawn its recommendation that providers and other caregivers look for the DfE logo on products."
The statement explains that EHCC's decision results from EPA's decision to "allow fragrances in DfE-endorsed cleaning products." The groups' March 13 press release describes EHCC as "a national program promoting environmental best health practices in child care, with more than 2,200 participating child care providers..."
In their letter, the groups quote DfE statements that all chemicals in DfE-labeled products have a function, and question the necessity of adding fragrances to cleaning products, arguing they do not enhance cleaners' effectiveness.
"This is a serious misstep and does not protect children's health," Cynthia Bearer, CEHN Board Chair and neonatology professor at the University of Maryland's medical school, says in the groups' statement. "Children, because of their sensitive developing systems, should be protected from unnecessary chemical exposures. This is especially important for the one in ten children with asthma. A parent or caregiver may see the DfE logo and not know that the product may contain an unnecessary and potentially-harmful chemical."
The groups urge EPA to reverse the decision to allow fragrance chemicals in DfE-labeled products, and remove the fragrance category from its SCIL. They are also pressing for "routine consultation by the DfE program with the Office of Children's Health Protection to best assure that children's unique vulnerabilities and exposures are considered in all DfE activities" and "affirmation that the agency's policy directive on children's environmental health is being applied to all agency activities, including DfE; and if this is not the case, that the directive be immediately expanded to do so." -- Maria Hegstad
]]></text></news-item>