<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-3GF1-DYWR-S2HK"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Two Compounders Warned for Mixing Unapproved Drugs, cGMP Violations</title><source>Drug Industry Daily</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The FDA's crackdown on compounders continues with two pharmacies receiving warning letters for compounding drugs without a prescription, mixing an unapproved drug ingredient into compounded products and failing to maintain sanitary facilities.
Louisiana-based Total Pharmacy Services and Florida-based Olympia Pharmacy received the warnings, published by the agency Tuesday.
Both pharmacies were cited for the use of domperidone in drug products. The ingredient is sometimes used in anti-vomiting treatments, but is not an FDA-approved ingredient due to its potential health risks. The FDA bans any imports and compounding of domperidone and Europe is considering similar restrictions (DID, March 7).
The pharmacies were also warned for various violations of good manufacturing practices.
During a May 2013 inspection of Total Pharmacy's Houma, La., facility, FDA investigators saw employees wearing non-sterile gowns in the sterile processing area. The agency also questioned the adequacy of the company's hoods to protect a sterile drug processing area from contamination.
Olympia Pharmacy was also chided for similar violations during a March 2013 inspection of its Orlando, Fla., site. FDA investigators observed employees with torn gloves and exposed skin touching uncapped vials containing sterile drugs. The pharmacy also did not routinely disinfect equipment or supplies used during aseptic processing, the FDA said in the Feb. 18 letter.
Total Pharmacy told DID Tuesday it is crafting a response to the agency's concerns.
Olympia Pharmacy was not available to comment as of press time Tuesday.
The FDA has so far issued seven warning letters to compounders since last year's passage of the Drug Quality and Security Act, which boosted the agency's authority over compounding pharmacies.
Read the Total Pharmacy letter at www.fdanews.com/ext/resources/files/03/03-18-14-TotalPharmacyWarning.pdf. Access the Olympia Pharmacy letter at www.fdanews.com/ext/resources/files/03/03-18-14-OlympiaWarning.pdf. -- Robert King
Release date: 20140319
]]></text></news-item>