<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-YM01-JCB7-100K"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Week in Review</title><source>Charleston Gazette (West Virginia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Feds took gun from Freedom cleanup company, neighbor says
The owner of a company hired by Freedom Industries to clean up its tank farm on the Elk River wouldn't say Sunday, March 9, if federal investigators removed guns from his company's property last week.
Daniel Carlton Kessler said that he had no idea why dozens of federal agents showed up at Diversified Services LLC on Thursday, March 6. The company, which has also hauled chemicals for Freedom Industries in the past, is under federal investigation, and has a history of environmental complaints filed against it.
U.S. Attorney Booth Goodwin, who is conducting a criminal investigation into the leak at Freedom Industries, also wouldn't say why FBI agents were at Diversified Services.
Cecelia Sanson owns CJ's Auto Sales and other property next to Diversified Services, at 110 Virginia St. in St. Albans. Sanson and her family have filed complaints for years with the state Department of Environmental Protection about chemical leaks and odors coming from Diversified, which Kessler founded in 2010.
Sanson said she saw federal agents confiscating a gun from Diversified Services on Thursday, March 6.
She didn't know what kind of gun it was, but thought it was a rifle.
"It was more like something you'd see in war, Sanson said of the gun. "I don't know my guns but I do know it was a real long gun. You could knock a rabbit in the head instead of having to shoot it.
"[Kessler's] wife jumped out of the truck and yelled, Hey, that's my husband's gun.'
Asked if investigators took guns from his property, Kessler referred comment to his lawyer, whom he did not identify.
In 1995, Kessler pleaded guilty to misdemeanor assault and battery in the Circuit Court for Anne Arundel County in Annapolis, Md., according to court records and a court official. He pleaded to that charge in exchange for the state dropping four other charges, including assault with intent to murder and reckless endangerment.
Kessler was sentenced to six months in jail, although the sentence was suspended. He was also sentenced to five years of probation, but violated his probation about a year later, according to court records.
As part of the plea deal, Kessler was required to complete a spousal abuse program, according to court records.
Federal law bans any person who has been convicted of a misdemeanor crime of domestic violence from possessing a firearm. It's not clear if that law would apply to Kessler's conviction.
The Kanawha County Sheriff's Department issued Kessler a concealed weapons permit last April, according to Kanawha County public records.
If investigators find that Kessler had a gun illegally or committed some other crime, they could use that as leverage to make a case against Freedom Industries.
Kessler also owns Buffalo Ridge Environmental Services LLC on Stable Ridge Road in Charleston.
At least as far back as 2011, there have been environmental complaints about odors and possible chemical leaks at Diversified Services.
The Charleston Gazette
Nitro voters reapprove city municipal levy
Nitro voters overwhelmingly reapproved the city's municipal levy during a special election Saturday, March 8, and the city's mayor said the levy's passage will allow the city to proceed with several "bigger projects that will be revealed to the public soon.
City Recorder Rita Cox said preliminary totals show 230 voters were for the levy, while 44 were against.
The levy required at 60 percent affirmative vote to pass. Voter turnout was about 5.8 percent, and Cox said the two precincts in Putnam County had higher turnout than she expected.
There are 4,695 voters in Nitro. Of those, 3,932 live in Kanawha County and 763 live in Putnam County.
"We're very pleased with the results, Mayor Dave Casebolt said.
Casebolt said he plans to reveal several project proposals to city council and the public at upcoming council meetings. The public will have the opportunity to comment and provide input for the projects, he said.
Casebolt has mentioned the projects at recent council meetings, but hasn't yet revealed any details.
The levy approved Saturday will take effect July 1 and will be in place for the next five fiscal years, from FY 2015 through FY 2019.
Charleston Daily Mail
]]></text></news-item>