<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-50C1-DXKH-N46J"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Transcept Pharmaceuticals jumps 6.0% on firm volume</title><source>News Bites US Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Transcept Pharmaceuticals, Inc. (NASDAQ:TSPT), NASDAQ's 96th largest medical/biomedical company by market capitalisation, jumped 18.0c (or 6.0%) to close at US$3.18, ending a six-day streak of losses. Compared with the NASDAQ-100 Index which fell 23.9 points (or 0.6%) in the day, this represented a relative price increase of 6.6%. Trading volume was 1.4 times average.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Transcept Pharmaceuticals, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/0010519715303142476
Bullish SignalsUptrend- The stock rose 6.0% on high volatility today and expanding price range.- The current short volume is 0.5 times its own historical average of 0.3%.Oversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The Stochastic indicator of 19.0 has pierced the oversold line of 20.- The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 66.0%. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.6. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.
Bearish Signals- The present value of US$1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in Transcept Pharmaceuticals is US$583, for a capital loss of US$417.
- Revenue growth has shown signs of deterioration in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]
- Net Profit margin has seen consecutive falls and seems to be on a slippery slope in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 203,563 shares worth US$647,330 traded. - Transcept Pharmaceuticals is at a discount of 39.2% to its 12-month high of US$5.23 on 21 Mar, 2013. It is also at a premium of 26.2% to the 12-month low of US$2.52 on 29 Aug, 2013.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 13: Transcept Pharmaceuticals Reports Fourth Quarter And Full Year 2013 Financial ResultsPOINT RICHMOND, Calif., March 13, 2014 Transcept Pharmaceuticals, Inc. (Nasdaq:TSPT), a specialty pharmaceutical company focused on the development and commercialization of proprietary products that address important therapeutic needs in the field of neuroscience, today announced financial results for the three and twelve months ended December 31, 2013.http://www.nasdaq.com/aspx/stockmarketnewsstoryprint.aspx?storyid=transcept-pharmaceuticals-reports-fourth-quarter-and-full-year-2013-financial-results-20140313-00946Source: NASDAQ Stock Exchange
January 13: Transcept Pharmaceuticals Statement on Dismissal of Derivative LawsuitPOINT RICHMOND, Calif., Jan. 13, 2014 Transcept Pharmaceuticals, Inc. (Nasdaq:TSPT) today announced the dismissal of the derivative lawsuit by the Court of Chancery of the State of Delaware. The derivative lawsuit was filed on October 24, 2013, by a shareholder, Retrophin Inc., against the Transcept Board of Directors, purporting to assert claims on behalf of Transcept, alleging that our Board of Directors approved and paid excessive compensation to our directors."From the beginning, the Transcept Board of Directors believed that this suit had absolutely no merit.
December 19: Transcept Final Voting Results for Special Meeting of Stockholders Provide Strong Support for Current Board of Directors and Tax Benefit Preservation Program[News Story] POINT RICHMOND, Calif., Dec. 19, 2013 Transcept Pharmaceuticals, Inc. (Nasdaq:TSPT) announced today that, based upon the final vote count certified by the independent inspector of elections for the special meeting of stockholders held December 19, 2013, a substantial majority of Transcept stockholders voted against or abstained from voting on the stockholder proposal to remove certain directors from the Transcept Board of Directors, and the stockholder proposal to eliminate the Transcept Tax Benefit Preservation Plan."We are very pleased with the favorable outcome of these results and also for the gratifying level of stockholder support we have received for our strategic plan," stated Glenn A.
December 17: Transcept Pharmaceuticals insider sellsTranscept Pharmaceuticals (NASDAQ:TSPT) insider Roumell Asset Management, Llc sold 1,470 shares worth approximately US$5,204 on December 13, 2013. The selling price was USD3.54.
December 17: Transcept Pharmaceuticals Statement on the Withdrawal of the Unsolicited Indication of Interest from Retrophin, Inc.[News Story] POINT RICHMOND, Calif., Dec. 17, 2013 Transcept Pharmaceuticals, Inc. (Nasdaq:TSPT) today commented on the recent announcements from Retrophin, Inc. that it has withdrawn its unsolicited overture to purchase all of the shares of Transcept, and that Retrophin is no longer a Transcept stockholder, indicating that such overture from Retrophin was not a bonafide offer."The Board of Directors of Transcept did not consider the unsolicited indication of interest from Retrophin, Inc.
December 16: Transcept Pharmaceuticals Announces That Largest Stockholder, Roumell Asset Management, Declares Support Of Company Strategies[News Story] POINT RICHMOND, Calif., Dec. 16, 2013 Transcept Pharmaceuticals, Inc. (Nasdaq:TSPT), a specialty pharmaceutical company focused on the development and commercialization of proprietary products that address important therapeutic needs in the field of neuroscience, today announced that the company's largest stockholder, Roumell Asset Management, had publicly announced its support of the Transcept business strategies that Transcept outlined in its press release dated December 4, 2013.
December 12: Transcept Pharmaceuticals insider sellsTranscept Pharmaceuticals (NASDAQ:TSPT) insider Roumell Asset Management, Llc sold 9,470 shares worth approximately US$33,618 on December 10, 2013. The selling price was USD3.55.
ISIN: US89354M1062
O:TSPT
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>