<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-4N51-DY37-42KC"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Restaurant gripes spur a review of noise rules</title><source>Sarasota Herald Tribune (Florida)</source><author>JESSIE VAN BERKEL and JUSTINE GRIFFIN Staff Writers</author><text><![CDATA[SARASOTA COUNTY
County employees are walking a fine line as they attempt to rewrite the regulations for noise coming from businesses.
They are trying to appease distraught neighbors who can't stand the jam sessions at Bob's Boathouse restaurant without stepping on other businesses' toes.
Earlier this month, Commissioner Charles Hines asked county staff to make sure the commission does not approve new rules then say, "Oops, we didn't think about that."
The county has reached out to residents and businesses before a public hearing scheduled for today to let them know they are considering changes that would:
Allow code enforcement officers to measure sound at the complainant's property if the officer cannot logistically or safely measure sound from the property line of the establishment generating the noise, such as a bar along a shoreline.
Lower the decibel level limits for some noise, like outdoor amplified music, and require businesses to operate more quietly after 10 p.m. instead of 11 p.m.
These possible changes were spurred by an onslaught of complaints following the opening of Bob's Boathouse, a restaurant and bar along Phillippi Creek.
Sarasota residents who live near the restaurant have filed more than 40 noise complaints about Bob's, which offers live music on its outdoor deck and inside on the weekends.
But sheriff's deputies and code enforcement officials have measured decibel readings and never found Bob's to be in violation of county noise ordinances.
Still, some residents say they are taking extreme measures to deal with the onslaught on noise.
Michelle Lee, who lives directly across the waterway from Bob's, said she leaves her home every weekend and returns on Monday after the variety of reggae and rock band performances are over.
Jim McWhorter, the president of the River Forest Civic Association, said his group and residents from the neighboring communities have proposed a change to the current noise ordinance in Sarasota County that they hope will create some relief.
"All other counties on the west coast of Florida use residential receiving limits county-wide for noise," McWhorter said. "The Phillippi Creek residential neighborhoods and others are requesting noise protection that other counties have. Our plan is the best to adopt and will do that, whereas the county's proposal will not."
Business owners on Siesta Key, who historically have run into trouble with neighbors over music, said the changes do not seem like they would impact their businesses.
"I don't think it would impact us because I don't think it can get any stricter than it is," said Russell Matthes, of the Daiquiri Deck Raw Bar.
If they moved all measurements to the receiving line -- as residents have proposed -- it would be bigger news for businesses, Matthes said.
The proximity of bars to condominiums and rental properties around Siesta Village has always made noise an issue, and having regulations that are easily enforceable is key, said Catherine Luckner, head of the Siesta Key Association.
On the key, "You can't pretend you live in a field," Luckner said.
The association wants a lively environment that will attract visitors, but businesses shouldn't prevent someone from enjoying where they live.
Rod Thomas, co-owner of Bentley's Boutique Hotel in Osprey, said his business is severely affected by the current noise rules.
"I would hope the new legislation will take into account the need of the many businesses and musicians that survive by playing live music. Sarasota should not be badgered into submission by grumpy old men and women," said Thomas, also president of the Osprey Nokomis Chamber board of directors. He emphasized that he was not speaking for the chamber, just as a business owner.
That overlap of businesses' noise and residents' peace has not been an issue farther south in Sarasota County.
The North Port Area Chamber of Commerce sent businesses a notification of the proposed changes early last week and had not heard any feedback, executive director Bill Gunnin said Friday.
Meanwhile, Tom LeFevre, the owner of the nautical-themed Bob's at 5515 S. Tamiami Trail and his attorney, E. Dusty Aker, have filed suit against Sarasota County because of permit requirements, claiming that the county readjusted terms after an agreement over the temporary certificate had been made.
]]></text></news-item>