<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-R941-DXX7-H03R"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Declares Dividend</title><source>Market News Publishing</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[AIRBOSS OF AMERICA CORP ("BOS-T;ABSSF-0") - Declares Dividend
AirBoss of America Corp.
The Company is pleased to announce that the Board of Directors has approved a quarterly dividend of $0.05 per common share to be paid April 17, 2014 to shareholders of record at April 3, 2014.
AirBoss of America Corp. develops, manufactures, and sells high quality, proprietary rubber based products offering enhanced performance and productivity to transportation, military and industrial markets. With a capacity to supply over 250 million pounds of rubber annually to a diverse group of rubber manufacturers, AirBoss is also one of North America's largest custom rubber compounding companies. AirBoss-Defense is a world leader in rubber chem-bio protective wear. AirBoss' Flexible Products is a leading supplier of innovative anti-vibration solutions to the North American automotive market. The Corporation's shares trade on the TSX under the symbol BOS. Visit www.airbossofamerica.com.
AIRBOSS FORWARD LOOKING STATEMENT DISCLAIMER
Certain statements contained or incorporated by reference herein, including those that express management's expectations or estimates of future developments or AirBoss' future performance, constitute "forward-looking statements" within the meaning of applicable securities laws, and can generally be identified by words such as "will", "may", "could" "expects", "believes", "anticipates", "forecasts", "plans", "intends" or similar expressions. These statements are not historical facts but instead represent management's expectations, estimates and projections regarding future events and performance.
Forward-looking statements are necessarily based upon a number of opinions, estimates and assumptions that, while considered reasonable by management at the time the statements are made, are inherently subject to significant business, economic and competitive risks, uncertainties and contingencies. AirBoss cautions that such forward-looking statements involve known and unknown contingencies, uncertainties and other risks that may cause AirBoss' actual financial results, performance or achievements to be materially different from its estimated future results, performance or achievements expressed or implied by those forward-looking statements. Numerous factors could cause actual results to differ materially from those in the forward-looking statements, including without limitation: impact of general economic conditions; its dependence on key customers; cyclical trends in the tire and automotive, construction, mining and retail industries; sufficient availability of raw materials at economical costs; weather conditions affecting raw materials, production and sales; AirBoss' ability to maintain existing customers or develop new customers in light of increased competition; changes in accounting policies and methods, including uncertainties associated with critical accounting assumptions and estimates; changes in the value of the Canadian dollar relative to the US dollar; changes in tax laws and potential litigation; ability to obtain financing on acceptable terms; environmental damage caused by it and non- compliance with environmental laws and regulations; potential product liability and warranty claims and equipment malfunction. This list is not exhaustive of the factors that may affect any of AirBoss' forward-looking statements.
All of the forward-looking information in this press release is expressly qualified by these cautionary statements. Investors are cautioned not to put undue reliance on forward-looking statements. All subsequent written and oral forward-looking statements attributable to AirBoss or persons acting on its behalf are expressly qualified in their entirety by this notice. Forward-looking information contained herein is made as of the date of this press release and, whether as a result of new information, future events or otherwise, AirBoss disclaims any intent or obligation to update publicly these forward-looking statements except as required by applicable laws. Risks and uncertainties about AirBoss's business are more fully discussed in the Management's Discussion and Analysis of Financial Condition and Results of Operations in the 2012 Annual Report to Shareholders under the heading "Risk Factors".
AirBoss of America Corp. TEL: (905) 751-1188 P.G. Schoch TSX closing price for BOS-T Date: 2014/03/18 Closing Price: 8.39
____________________________________________________________
(c)2014 Market News Publishing Inc. All rights reserved. Toronto:(416)366-8881 Vancouver:(604)689-1101 Fax:(604)689-1106
]]></text></news-item>