<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-MVB1-JBSN-23DY"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Carousel to repay $3.75 million in settlement</title><source>Austin American-Statesman (Texas)</source><author>Chuck Lindell American-Statesman Staff</author><text><![CDATA[Carousel Pediatrics, a chain of Austin clinics originally accused of defrauding the government of $18 million in Medicaid payments, has agreed to repay $3.75 million for what regulators called a "pattern of billing errors" over four years.
The settlement allowed both sides to claim victory in a frequently public dispute between Carousel Pediatrics and the state Health and Human Services Commission's office of inspector general, which investigated the company amid ramped-up efforts to identify fraud and overpayments in the Medicaid system.
Under the agreement, Carousel will continue serving 25,000 low-income children in Austin without a finding of fraud as it repays billing mistakes in monthly installments over 15 years.
"We've said all along Carousel may have made billing errors, but they were not intentional or for the purpose of overbilling Medicaid," said Dan Gattis, Carousel's lawyer. "We understand why (the inspector general) suspected fraud, and we think it acted reasonably under the facts as they knew them. Fortunately, they listened to us, understood our approach and worked out a repayment agreement."
The settlement also allows the office of inspector general - criticized by several members of the Legislature for overzealous pursuit of fraud allegations - to close its ninth repayment agreement with a Texas Medicaid provider. Eight other settlements have resulted in $10 million to be repaid to the state, the agency said.
"This agreement will help ensure that children with Medicaid coverage can get quality health care services and that the state pays only for services that are necessary and provided to the child," Inspector General Douglas Wilson said.
In 2012, Wilson's office began withholding Medicaid payments from Carousel based on a "credible allegation of fraud" - an aggressive and controversial penalty authorized by the federal Affordable Care Act to stop money from flowing to questionable providers because repayment is often difficult.
Wilson's office also proposed that Carousel repay $18 million in allegedly fraudulent billing and pay a $4.1 million penalty. Carousel offered to repay $50,000 in billing mistakes identified in an internal review - an offer Wilson rejected as inadequate.
Carousel next took its fight public with help from the politically powerful Texas Medical Association, which launched a review of Carousel records that found no evidence of fraud.
Under the settlement signed March 7 by Carousel owner Dr. Glenn Wood, the company admitted to violations that included billing for a higher level of service than was provided to patients, duplicate billings and failure to provide documentation to support some bills from February 2007 through June 2011.
According to a joint statement announcing the agreement, the inspector general's review "demonstrated the quality of care Carousel provided was often similar to other Medicaid providers, but its billing practices meant that it billed the state too much for those services."
Carousel's first payment was $614,000 - the amount of Medicaid payments withheld from the company since 2012 under the "credible allegation of fraud" finding.
The rest of the $3.75 million settlement will be repaid interest-free over 15 years, at $17,420 a month, beginning in 2015.
Since the dispute began, Carousel sold two of its six clinics to remain in business while Medicaid payments were withheld, Wood said.
"I am happy to have this behind us, so we can concentrate on providing excellent care for the lower-income children of Austin," he said.
Contact Chuck Lindell
at 512-912-2569.
Twitter: @chucklindell
]]></text></news-item>