<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-0BV1-JBKH-S3JV"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Gas pipeline partner's safety record a concern</title><source>Orlando Sentinel (Florida)</source><author>Lauren Ritchie, Sentinel Columnist</author><text><![CDATA[Second of two parts.
Florida Power & Light, the company behind a natural-gas pipeline proposed to run through part of Lake and Sumter counties, has partnered with a well-known builder of pipelines to construct the project in Alabama, Georgia and Florida.
Spectra Energy Corp. along with FPL's parent, NextEra Energy, would bury the 473-mile Sabal Trail pipeline expected to carry 1 billion cubic feet per day of natural gas to just south of Orlando in Osceola County, where it would connect to another line for eventual delivery to FPL in Martin County.
Spectra's safety record, however, leaves something to be desired.
Take, for example, the company's Texas Eastern pipeline, a 9,200-mile Spectra project connecting Texas with the markets in the Northeast.
Between 2006 and 2013, the company had 21 "incidents" along the line, causing $8.6 million in property damage, according to the Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration. EcoRI.org, a nonprofit investigative journalism website, reported that the agency cited the company 14 times since 2006, and six citations involved Spectra's failure to control pipeline corrosion. Texas Eastern paid more than $4 million in fines in connection with those violations.
Sloppy maintenance combined with volatile methane, the main ingredient in the natural gas. Can that be a good idea? Just ask residents of New York's Harlem, where natural gas from leaky old pipes exploded two weeks ago, killing eight people and leveling two buildings.
Andrea Grover, director of stakeholder outreach for Spectra, said, "No incident is acceptable." The company's goal, she wrote in an email, is zero incidents. She said the company has a "strong safety record" and that its incident rate for onshore piplines is "half that of the industry as a whole."
Plans call for the pipe welds for the Sabal Trail project to be ultrasonically or X-ray inspected, Grover said.
Additionally, the entire pipeline, including compressor stations and meter stations, would be tested at pressures "significantly higher" than the maximum allowable operating pressure, she said.
Once gas starts flowing, the company plans to conduct on-the-ground inspections and monitor the line using a computer network 24 hours a day, Grover wrote.
But how does Spectra respond when something goes wrong? On New Year's Eve near Bangor, Maine, an explosion rocked a Maritimes & Northeast Pipeline compressor station, a Spectra project.
The station was shut down for a week, and Spectra officials refused to say what happened or whether nearby residents were in danger, according to the Bangor Daily News. They said they'd talk at a public meeting -- three weeks later.
Grover said, "We conveyed to the Bangor Daily reporter that once we had determined the specific facts that we would convey those details in the local Town Hall meeting with the public officials and residents."
That's not good enough. The situation on the ground near Bangor was terriying and chaotic.
Susan Totman, who lives about 1,200 feet from the station, immediately called the pipeline company's emergency number, the Bangor Daily News reported.
"The guy that answered the phone was clearly confused and a little bit panicked," she told the newspaper. "I said 'Are we safe?' And he said, 'I can't tell you that.' "
Ah, shades of Blue Rhino, the Tavares propane depot where an incredible explosion July 29 sent 53,000 propane tanks flying into the air.
Last fall, Spectra mailed safety brochures to people who live or work near their natural-gas pipeline facilities, the Bangor paper reported.
The pamphlet stated that hazards associated with a pipeline leak are dizziness or suffocation if the leak occurs in a confined space, ignition or fire, potential explosion or projectiles ejected from the force of escaping gas.
If there is a pipeline leak, residents would told to evacuate the area, avoid open flames and not use possible ignition sources such as cellphones or pagers.
The pamphlet ordered those nearby not to start or turn off motor vehicles, but it failed to say how a person was expected to evacuate, the paper reported wryly.
A group of residents in the sparsely-populated Bay Lake area of south Lake, where the pipeline crosses, are banding together with environmentalists who want to move the pipeline to the west, where right of way already is owned by the government near a rails-to-trails project. Environmentalists object to the proposed route because it runs into the heart of the Green Swamp, source of most of the water in the Floridan Aquifer, from which most residents of the state drink.
Jane Geraci, who owns about 1,000 acres south of Groveland, said that she has been told that moving the route would make the pipeline 2.5 miles longer, and that was too expensive.
"We don't oppose the pipeline. What we're trying to do is get it moved on government land rather than coming across private property where some of the families have been on the land from the mid-1800s," she said.
A few families would have the 36-inch buried pipeline running just a couple hundred feet from their homes, she said.
Backers of the pipeline say there isn't danger, but Geraci, 73, who came to Lake County when she a babe in arms, doesn't believe it. Smart lady.
Anyone interested in helping her gather signatures to move the route may call her at 352-223-6791. The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, which oversees pipelines, has scheduled a meeting for 6 p.m. March 27 at the Citrus Tower. Anyone may attend.
Want more information on the organized fight against the pipeline?
Visit spectrabusters.com.
]]></text></news-item>