<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-15B1-F0J6-J3PN"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>AWH board looked at paying $1m bonus to Liberal lobbyist</title><source>Sydney Morning Herald (Australia)</source><author>Kate McClymont, Michaela Whitbourn</author><text><![CDATA[The board of the Obeid-linked company Australian Water Holdings considered paying a $1 million bonus to Liberal lobbyist Michael Photios that would not appear as part of a "formal compensation arrangement", the Independent Commission Against Corruption has heard.
Documents tendered at the ICAC on Wednesday show the board, including Senator Arthur Sinodinos, resolved to pay Mr Photios $5000 a month for consultancy services.
The board also considered paying Mr Photios, a former NSW Liberal Party vice-president and registered lobbyist, a $1 million bonus "on financial close" of a proposed public-private partnership between the company and the NSW government.
A draft motion put before the board on January 27, 2011, resolved that Senator Sinodinos and the AWH chief executive Nick Di Girolamo would "negotiate with Michael Photios on [the $1 million bonus] ... such that it would not form part of any formal compensation arrangement with AWH".
"What would formal mean there?" counsel assisting the inquiry, Geoffrey Watson, SC, asked former AWH director William MacGregor Fraser. "Does that mean that the money was going to be paid informally?"
"I don't know," Mr MacGregor Fraser replied.
Mr Watson said it was unclear whether "Mr Photios even knew that this proposal was there" and the motion was not passed.
"What could Mr Photios do which led, would lead, to him receiving $1 million?" Mr Watson asked.
"I do not know," Mr MacGregor Fraser replied.
The ICAC is investigating whether corrupt former Labor minister Eddie Obeid misused his political position in an attempt to secure a public-private partnership between AWH and the state-owned Sydney Water, which would have reaped up to $60 million for his family. The inquiry has heard the Obeids had a 30 per cent "secret shareholding" in AWH, although the family insists its $3 million investment was a loan.
Minutes of a management meeting in November 2010, tendered at ICAC on Wednesday, show the Obeids' intention to buy shares in the company was recorded in a table alongside a comment that Senator Sinodinos was taking over as chairman of AWH.
He had been on the board since October 2008.
The inquiry heard that in 2011, Mr Sinodinos met businessman John McGuigan to try to sell him a stake in the water infrastructure company. Documents show that also at the meeting were AWH's Mr Di Girolamo and Eddie Obeid jnr.
Mr McGuigan, who was found to be corrupt at a previous Independent Commission Against Corruption inquiry ito the Obeids' $30 million coal deal, was to invest profits from the sale of his coal company Cascade Coal to buy ito AWH. However, the $500 million sale of Cascade Coal did not proceed, so McGuigan's investment in AWH also disappeared.
The Obeid family was a shareholder in both AWH and Mr McGuigan's company Cascade Coal.
Mr Sinodinos also attended a meeting at Parliament House in August 2010, where he and Mr Di Girolamo pitched AWH's merits to then opposition leader Barry O'Farrell and planning spokesman Brad Hazzard. According to Mr Di Girolamo's notes, they complained that Sydney Water chief Kerry Schott was "very destructive".
Other associates of the Obeid family were offered stakes in AWH. In July, 2009, property developer Iwan Sunito's Crown Group was offered a half share in AWH for $50 million.
The Herald has previously revealed that the Obeid family bought a string of discounted apartments, including the penthouse, in Crown's residential development in Top Ryde.
Labor powerbroker Eddie Obeid negotiated the purchase of the apartments with Mr Sunito. On November 14, 2012, two days after being accused of being at the centre of the biggest corruption inquiry since the Rum Corps, the Obeids made a 46.8 per cent return when they sold one unit for $558,000, having owned it for four months.
The Pope Street penthouse, which the Obeids bought for $1.48 million in March 2012, was used last year as collateral for a $1 million short-term loan.
Australian Water Holdings: what you need to know
Rouse Hill Infrastructure Consortium formed as a not-for-profit business in 1990. The company won the rights to build water and sewer infrastructure in Sydney's fast-growing north-west two years later. The contract was on a "costs plus" basis, allowing it to bill Sydney Water for expenses.
Lawyer Nicholas Di Girolamo joins as a director in 2005 and the company transforms. It starts to massively increase the bills it submits to Sydney Water and begins paying lavish salaries.
Eddie Obeid Jr is hired in 2007 and the company changes its name to Australian Water Holdings in 2008. AWH refuses to open its books to Sydney Water when chief executive Kerry Schott questions AWH's bills.
AWH starts to lobby for a $1 billion public private partnership to supply more infrastructure. Under Dr Schott, Sydney Water resists. AWH lobbies the NSW Labor government directly for the PPP and starts to lobby the NSW Liberal opposition.
Arthur Sinodinos appointed director in 2008. AWH donates more than $43,000 to Barry O'Farrell's election campaign in 2010 and Sinodinos appointed chairman in November 2010. The Obeid family take a $3 million stake in 2010, though Sinodinos says he had no knowledge of this.
Sinodinos lobbies O'Farrell on behalf of AWH. He stands down as AWH chairman to become Liberal senator for NSW. He relinquishes his shares in AWH when the company's Obeid links are revealed.
Questions Senator Sinodinos still faces
Does he maintain, as he told Parliament, he was unaware AWH was "financially linked" with the Obeid family, when Eddie Obeid jnr was one of just ten employees?
Does he believe $200,000 for 100 hours of work was a fair rate of pay?
Does he still maintain he was unaware of tens of thousands of dollars in political donations from AWH to the NSW Liberal Party when he was a director of AWH and the party's honorary treasurer?
Does he believe AWH's contract with Sydney Water represented good value for the NSW taxpayer?
Was he aware donations to the Liberal Party from AWH were being channelled from Sydney Water? If not, what did he do as chairman of the company? Did he ever discuss with state Coalition MPs the position of former Sydney Water chief Kerry Schott or the make-up of the board?
What did he discuss with Barry O'Farrell and Brad Hazzard when he met them in his capacity as AWH chairman?
]]></text></news-item>