<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-G9W1-DYRK-92T2"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Briefing.com: Hourly In Play (R) - 10:00 ET</title><source>Briefing.com</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Hourly In Play (R)
Updated: 19-Mar-14 10:00 ET
09:59
TECHX Stock indices climb back above flat line after slightly weaker start -- Dow +9, S&P +0.5, Nasdaq Comp +0.1 -Technical-
09:58
DLR Digital Realty Trust announces commencement of Series H Cumulative Redeemable Preferred Stock offering at a price of $25 per share (52.63 +0.70)
Co announced the commencement of a public offering of shares of Series H Cumulative Redeemable Preferred Stock at a price of $25.00 per share. The Company intends to contribute the net proceeds from this offering to its operating partnership, Digital Realty Trust, L.P., which will subsequently use the net proceeds received from the Company to temporarily repay borrowings under its global revolving credit facility, to acquire additional properties, to fund development opportunities, for general corporate purposes, including potentially for the repurchase, redemption or retirement of outstanding debt or preferred equity securities, or a combination of the foregoing. The offering is being made pursuant to an effective shelf registration statement filed by the Company with the Securities and Exchange Commission and only by means of a prospectus and related prospectus supplement. Merrill Lynch, Pierce, Fenner & Smith Incorporated, Morgan Stanley & Co. LLC and Wells Fargo Securities, LLC will be the joint book-running managers for the offering.
09:48
HPQ Hewlett-Packard set new multi-year high (30.91 +0.35) -Technical-
Noted the push toward its early March high at 30.48 here yesterday with the breakout above and the penetration of the Feb peak (30.71) this morning (upgrade/positive comments) extended to 30.93.
09:42
WRAPX Opening Market Summary: Technology Leads Opening Retreat
The major averages began the session just below their flat lines with small caps displaying the largest early decline. The Russell 2000 is lower by 0.4% while the S&P 500 holds a more modest loss of 0.1% with nine of ten sectors showing losses.
Most notably, two of the three top-weighted groups-technology (-0.2%) and financials (-0.2%)-are among the early laggards. The technology sector is being pressured by Oracle (ORCL 37.66, -1.18), which trades lower by 3.0% after missing on earnings.
On the upside, the health care sector (+0.2%) is the lone advancer at this juncture.
Elsewhere, Treasuries remain in the red with the 10-yr yield up one basis point at 2.68%.
09:41
TECHX Relative sector weakness -Technical-
Sectors that have underperformed in early trade include: Telecom IYZ, Energy XLE, Technology/Software XLK/IGV, along with Copper JJC, Gold GLD Coal KOL and Casino BJK.
09:39
TECHX Major averages slip lower in early trade led by Nasdaq Comp -8.6 -- S&P -1.7, Dow -10 -Technical-
09:34
GOGO Gogo receives supplemental type certificate from the FAA to install Ku-Satellite connectivity service on Airbus A330 aircraft (23.49 +0.41)
Co has received an STC from the FAA to install its Ku-band satellite equipment on Airbus A330 aircraft. This is Gogo's second STC for its Ku-band satellite service on Delta; Gogo previously received FAA certification to install its Ku-band equipment on Boeing 747-400 aircraft. Gogo's Ku-band satellite connectivity service is currently in the final phases of customer testing on Delta's 747-400 aircraft with completion of installation for the full 747-400 fleet targeted for the middle of 2014. With the newly-issued A330 STC, Gogo and Delta can begin initial testing of the service on their A330 fleet before the service goes live to consumers. Gogo expects to install its Ku-band connectivity service on Delta's entire international fleet by the end of 2015.
09:34
ORCL Oracle weaker after reporting, slides back near its March low from last week at 37.52/37.50 -- session low 37.53 (38.59 -1.25) -Technical-
09:33
JOB General Employment Ent. granted extension of impairment plan period by NYSE MKT LLC (0.26 0.00)
Co announced that NYSE MKT has granted the Company a second extension of its Impairment Plan Period from February 21, 2014 to March 31, 2014 related to its non-compliance with continued listing standards as set forth in the NYSE MKT Company Guide.
09:32
ISR IsoRay announces milestone - the treatment of a pediatric patient's tumor utilizing multiple Cesium-131 sutured seed meshes for internal radiation therapy (1.09 0.00)
09:29
OIS Oil States' subsidiary files amendment number two to Form 10 in connection with planned spin-off of Accommodations business (97.55 )
Co announced that its subsidiary, OIS Accommodations SpinCo, has filed a 2nd amendment to its Form 10 with the SEC in connection with Oil States' previously announced plan to effect a spin-off of its accommodations business. The amended Form 10 contains important information about the Accommodations business, including standalone financial information and a discussion of the company's operating and growth strategies. Oil States expects that subsequent amendments to the Form 10 will be filed prior to completion of the spin-off.
Under the separation plan announced in July 2013, Oil States plans to execute a tax-free spin-off of the accommodations business to Oil States shareholders by the end of the second quarter of 2014. In addition to its subsidiary filing the second amendment to its Form 10, Oil States International, Inc. has also received an affirmative IRS ruling regarding the tax free nature of the spin-off transaction. The offshore products and well site services businesses will continue to operate under the "Oil States International" name and continue to trade on the NYSE under the symbol "OIS." Oil States shareholders will own shares in both corporations following the completion of the transaction. The accommodations business intends to have its common stock separately listed on the NYSE under a name yet to be disclosed.
09:24
WIRES On The Wires
IntercontinentalExchange (ICE) announced that NYSE Liffe reached a daily volume record of 862,468 contracts in FTSE 100 Index futures on March 18, 2014. The previous record of 822,496 contracts was set on March 17, 2009.Standard Retirement Services, a subsidiary of StanCorp Financial (SFG), announced a new co-marketing relationship with M Financial Group for distributing qualified retirement plan products, including 401(k), 403(b) and 457 plans.TSYS (TSS) Merchant Solutions announced a new partnership with Navy Federal Credit Union designed to provide Navy Federal's merchant members with the ability to accept credit and debit cards as payments for their goods and services.Starwood Hotels & Resorts Worldwide (HOT) announced that its Aloft brand will soon debut in Syracuse, New York.Medical Marijuana (MJNA) has fully funded operations of subsidiary Wellness Managed Services' new co, MPS International.Medbox (MDBX) announced that Dr. Bruce Bedrick, chief executive officer of Medbox, and Mitch Lowe will appear today on Opening Bell with Maria Bartiromo on Fox Business at ~ 10:45 a.m. ET.CenturyLink (CTL) won a contract to provide voice, data network and telecommunications infrastructure services to the U.S. Marine Corps Combat Development Command in Quantico, Va., and the Marine Corps Barracks in Washington, D.C., that could be worth up to $8.5 mln over the next two years.Harris (HRS) has successfully completed initial interoperability testing of its widely fielded Falcon III AN/PRC-117G multiband manpack radio hosting the Mobile User Objective System waveform.InspireMD (NSPR) has successfully enrolled the first patient into the CARENET (CARotid Embolic protection study using microNET) multi-center European clinical trial for the new CGuard carotid embolic protection system. Command Security (MOC) has acquired a minority interest in Ocean Protection Services, a UK based company specializing in armed maritime security, risk management and risk analysis. Co also announced that it has been notified that the Western Region security services contract with a major transportation company will not be renewed beyond May 31, 2014. Boingo Wireless (WIFI) announced its selection as the exclusive neutral host Distributed Antenna System and Wi-Fi provider for the Air Force Academy's Falcon Stadium and Cadet Field House.
09:22
KCG KCG Holdings announces additional $85 mln repayment of first lien credit facility (12.07 )
Co announced the completion of an $85 million principal repayment of the first lien term loan under the co's first lien senior secured credit facility. KCG has completed a total of $485 million in principal repayments on the $535 million loan entered into on July 1, 2013, leaving a remaining outstanding balance of $50 million. Principal prepayments in excess of the $235 million amortization payment due July 1, 2014 will be applied to reduce the remaining scheduled amortization payments of $7.5 million each quarter beginning September 30, 2014 on a pro rata basis.
09:18
VIP VimpelCom and subsidiaries considering multi-step refinancing plan to improve WIND's capital structure (8.96 )
WIND and WAF are currently seeking the consent of lenders to amend WIND's Senior Facilities Agreement ("SFA") to provide operational flexibility and facilitate the implementation of the multi-step refinancing plan. The amendments would include changes to provide sufficient headroom under the financial covenants and up to an additional EUR 800 million plus associated transaction costs, fees and expenses in debt incurrence and distribution flexibility to permit a refinancing of the pay-in-kind notes guaranteed by WIND's immediate parent, Wind Acquisition Holdings Finance. The plan envisages a concurrent refinancing of WAF's junior secured notes maturing in 2017, as permitted by the SFA. Further requested amendments would, among other changes, extend the maturity profile of the SFA, whereby the consenting lenders will roll into new extended SFA tranches. The refinancing plan also contemplates a cash injection of EUR 500 million by VimpelCom, which will be a condition to the refinancing of the WAHF notes and the effectiveness of certain other elements of the amendment request. Execution of the cash injection and the refinancing remains subject to relevant corporate approvals, including by VimpelCom's Supervisory Board.
09:16
SYMX Synthesis Energy Systems rose as much as 36% following morning news (see our 09:07 post)... the stock is currently up 28% here pre-market (1.72 )
09:14
WRAPX S&P futures vs fair value: +0.30. Nasdaq futures vs fair value: +1.20.
The stock market is on track to begin today's session on a quiet note as futures on the S&P 500 trade right above fair value, which has been the case for the better part of the past four hours.
The first half of the trading day is expected to be fairly subdued with participants awaiting the latest policy statement from the Federal Open Market Committee. The FOMC is expected to announce another $10 billion taper, lowering the amount of monthly asset purchases to $55 billion per month. The 14:00 ET announcement will be followed by Janet Yellen's first press conference as Fed Chair.
Treasuries display slim losses after slipping from their flat lines over the past hour. The benchmark 10-yr yield is higher by one basis point at 2.69%.
Although most markets are not showing much change at this juncture, copper futures have dropped to fresh year-to-date lows. Currently, the red metal trades lower by 1.9% at $2.895/lb. Elsewhere among commodities, crude oil trades flat at $98.86/bbl and gold holds a 1.1% loss at $1344.50/ozt.
09:10
COMDX Copper futures extend losses and hit a new session low of $2.89/lb.. Apr copper is now -1.6% at $2.90/lb
09:08
AVNR Avanir Pharmaceuticals presents data from a benchmark study of PBA symptoms in Veterans with mild traumatic brain injury; 758 (19 %) veterans with TBI responded to the survey an unusually high response rate for similar studies (4.04 )
Co announced the presentation of results from a first-of-its-kind study of pseudobulbar affect (PBA) symptoms in veterans with mild traumatic brain injury (TBI) conducted in collaboration with the Department of Veterans Affairs (VA) and Evidera. Highlights from the cross sectional survey results of 4,283 patients within the VA system include:
758 (19 percent) veterans with TBI responded to the survey an unusually high response rate for similar studies. 60 percent of respondents reported PBA symptoms,In contrast, other commonly perceived challenges faced by veterans were reported less frequently, including: PTSD (48 percent) major depression (31%) and anxiety disorders (18%). Veterans who suffer from PBA symptoms were more likely to also suffer from PTSD, a finding not previously understood or recognized. In terms of measuring overall health status, those that suffered from PBA symptoms scored lower on the EQ-5D index suggesting that they have an extra burden impacting their quality of life. More than 94 percent of CNS-LS positive Veterans report at least some problems with pain/discomfort or anxiety/depression, the majority of whom had symptoms of at least moderate severity. 46 percent of CNS-LS positive veterans reported being on antidepressants versus approximately 31 percent of CNS-LS negative veterans
09:07
SYMX Synthesis Energy Systems and Zhangjiagang Chemical Machinery Co receive 20-year business license for China clean coal gasification joint venture (1.72 )
Co announced that its wholly owned subsidiary, SES Asia Technologies, Ltd., and Zhangjiagang Chemical Machinery Co., Ltd. have successfully completed a major step in the governmental approval process with the receipt of the required 20-year business license on March 18, from the State Administration for Industry & Commerce of the People's Republic of China (SAIC) in Zhangjiagang, for the previously announced joint venture, ZCM-SES Sino-U.S. Clean Energy Technologies Limited ("ZCM-SES" or the "JV").
Within the next 30 days ZCM is scheduled to make its first cash capital contribution of RMB 53.8 mln (~US$8.7 mln) and SES is to complete its contribution authorizing SES Gasification Technology usage by the JV. Remaining customary government approvals entail the issuance of a verification report, by an independent accountant, of the registered capital contributions. Once the registered capital of the Company has been contributed, and upon the issuance of the final capital contribution certificates, ZCM-SES will be operational.
ZCM has agreed to contribute a total of RMB 100 mln (~US$16.5 mln) to the JV to fund its working capital needs for a 65% ownership interest. ZCM will have exclusive manufacturing rights for all ZCM-SES customer projects in China as well as the joint venture's additional markets of Indonesia, Malaysia, Mongolia, the Philippines, and Vietnam. SES is contributing exclusive usage of its premiere SES Gasification Technology in these Asian markets for a 35% interest in ZCM-SES.
09:05
WH WSP Holdings announces update on going private transaction and announces disposals of Mengfeng and Liaoyang Seamless (2.08 )
Co entered into an Amendment No. 2 and Assignment and Assumption Agreement relating to the Agreement and Plan of Merger. Pursuant to Amendment No. 2, the original acquiring parties under the Merger Agreement and H.D.S. Investment LLC assigned all of their respective rights and obligations under the Merger Agreement and certain related agreements to New Parent, New Merger Sub and General Transactions, respectively, and New Parent, New Merger Sub and General Transactions, Inc. assumed all such rights and obligations. Amendment No. 2 also made certain other changes to the Merger Agreement, including extending the termination date of the Merger Agreement to May 31, 2014. Co disposed its entire equity interest in Mengfeng for nominal cash considerations to three unrelated third parties, pursuant to a series of agreements entered into in December 2013. As a result of the disposal, co would incur a loss of ~$39 million. This loss is expected to impact financial results in 2013. Co stopped production at Mengfeng since the second half of 2011 as the Company has been able to obtain and produce raw materials at lower costs. Mengfeng has been operating at a loss and the Company decided that it should be disposed to prevent future losses and to reduce negative cash flow impact to the group. As part of the disposal agreement, the buyer is contracted to pay the Company RMB170 million in two installments to settle part of the inter-company owed by Mengfeng. To date a significant portion of the installments has not been received. Co also disposed its entire equity interest in Liaoyang Seamless for nominal cash considerations to two unrelated third parties, pursuant to a series of agreements entered into in December 2013. As a result of the disposal, co is expected to incur a loss of ~$23 million. This loss is expected to impact the financial results in 2013. It has been operating at a loss and the Company decided that it should be disposed to prevent future losses and negative cash flow impact on the group. As part of the disposal agreement, the buyer is contracted to pay the Company RMB50 million and to assume the repayment of a RMB40 million bank loan of the Company when due. These amounts will be due soon.
09:05
VGR Vector Prices offering of variable interest convertible senior notes; the initial conversion rate for the notes will be 36.8155 shares of common stock per $1,000 principal amount of notes (equivalent to an initial conversion price of ~$27.16/share of common stock) (21.73 )
VGR announced that it has priced $225.0 mln aggregate principal amount (or up to an aggregate of $258.8 million aggregate principal amount if the underwriter of such offering exercises its over-allotment option in full) of its variable interest convertible senior notes due 2020 in a registered public offering.
The Company expects to close the Notes Offering on March 24, 2014, subject to satisfaction of customary closing conditions. The Company intends to use the net proceeds received from the notes offering for general corporate purposes, including for additional investments in real estate through its wholly owned subsidiary, New Valley, and in its existing tobacco business. Co may also consider using a portion of the proceeds of the Notes Offering to address upcoming debt maturities. The Notes will be Vector's senior unsecured obligations and will bear cash interest at a rate of 1.75% per year, with an additional cash payment equal to the amount of cash dividends per share actually paid by the Company on its common stock during the prior three-month period ending on the record date for such interest payment multiplied by the applicable conversion rate on such record date. Notwithstanding the foregoing, however, (A) the amount payable on each interest payment date, other than the initial interest payment date, shall be the higher of (a) the Total Interest and (b) an amount reflecting an annual interest rate of 5.50% per year and (B) the initial interest payment shall be based solely on the Floor Interest Rate. Interest is payable quarterly in arrears on January 15, April 15, July 15 and October 15 of each year, commencing on April 15, 2014. The Notes will mature on April 15, 2020, unless earlier repurchased, redeemed or converted in accordance with their terms. The Notes will be convertible at any time prior to the close of business on the business day immediately preceding the maturity date into shares of the Company's common stock, par value $0.10 per share, and cash in lieu of fractional shares of Common Stock. The initial conversion rate for the Notes will be 36.8155 shares of Common Stock per $1,000 principal amount of Notes (equivalent to an initial conversion price of approximately $27.16 per share of Common Stock), subject to customary adjustments.
09:04
OBCI Ocean Bio-Chem declares special cash dividend: $0.05 per/share (2.96 )
09:04
EQY Equity One announces CEO Jeff Olson will not renew contract expiring Dec 31, 2014; Olson to continue to serve as CEO through 2014 (22.61 )
EQY announced that its Chief Executive Officer, Jeffrey S. Olson, has informed co he will not renew his employment agreement, which expires on December 31, 2014.
Mr. Olson will continue to serve as CEO through 2014 and will be responsible for carrying out all strategic initiatives currently underway and for facilitating an orderly transition of his role. The Board of Directors has formed a search committee, led by Chairman Chaim Katzman, to identify the Company's next CEO, and will consider both internal and external candidates. The Board intends to conclude the process expeditiously, consistent with selecting the best possible candidate.
09:04
HSON Hudson Global: Lone Star Value files preliminary proxy materials to elect two director candidates to the Hudson Board Of Directors at the 2014 annual meeting (3.62 )
Lone Star Value Management, together with its affiliates and the other participants in its solicitation, a significant shareholder of Hudson Global, with approximately 7.4% of the outstanding common stock of the Company, announced today that it filed preliminary proxy materials with the Securities and Exchange Commission in connection with the election of directors to the Board of Directors of Hudson at the 2014 annual meeting of shareholders. Lone Star Value stated in its preliminary proxy statement that the current Board has overseen prolonged operating and stock price underperformance and further appears to lack a strategically coherent plan or the commitment or ability to tackle the serious issues facing Hudson.
"We believe meaningful change on the Board is urgently needed. That is why Lone Star Value has nominated two highly qualified candidates for election to the Board at Hudson's 2014 Annual Meeting. We believe Hudson's shareholders will greatly benefit from the expertise of our experienced and proven nominees and from having shareholder representation on the Board. Given the Board's poor track record having presided over an extended period of operating losses and negative stock price performance, we call on the Board to refrain from any changes to the composition, or size of the Board prior to the 2014 Annual Meeting, which we will view as a manipulation of Hudson's corporate machinery, and to let shareholders alone determine who should be their directors."
09:04
FSLR First Solar & GE (GE) plan to develop a utility-scale PV power plant design (57.56 )
The cos are utilizing their recently established technology and commercial partnership to develop a more cost effective and productive utility-scale PV power plant design that combines First Solar's thin-film CdTe modules with GE's new ProSolar 1500 Volt inverter/transformer system. Morjaria said First Solar has already identified projects under construction for initial deployment of the new 1500v system. The 4MW ProSolar 1500V station is the largest inverter in the industry capable of accommodating 1,500 volt DC solar arrays, which is a major factor in utilizing economies of scale by significantly increasing the array size and reducing the number of inverters required by a solar power plant.
09:03
HSOL Hanwha SolarOne supplies 6.2 MW of PV modules to Guatemala (3.73 )
Co has completed a 6.2 MW delivery of its high quality 72-cell solar modules (HSL72) to a consortium of the Spain-based companies Cobra and Gransolar. Both Gransolar and Cobra specialize in the development, construction, operation and maintenance of renewable energy plants. Last year, Cobra, Gransolar and South African company Kensani installed a total of 155 MW Hanwha SolarOne PV modules in the Letsatsi and Lesedi solar parks in South Africa. The projects are expected to be connected to the grid in the first half of 2014.
09:02
MOC Command Security has acquired minority interest in Ocean Protection Services Ltd; also announced contract that was not renewed (2.10 )
On March 14, 2014, Command Security Corporation invested $2.125 million for a 20% ownership interest in a limited liability company that recently acquired OPS. As part of the agreement to purchase this 20% ownership interest, the Company may acquire additional ownership interest. "This is a significant step in our strategic plan to expand Command Security's capabilities and customer base with higher value-added services. We look forward to working closely with Ocean Protection Services to assist in their continuing growth into new markets." Command also announced that it has been notified that the Western Region security services contract with a major transportation company will not be renewed beyond May 31, 2014.
09:02
SHIP Seanergy Maritime completes financial restructuring plan; gain from transaction is expected to be ~ $85 mln, which will be reflected in the first quarter of 2014 (1.65 )
Co announced that it has closed on its previously announced delivery and settlement agreement with its remaining lender to unwind its final secured credit facility. The Company has sold its four remaining bulk carriers to a nominee of the lender in full satisfaction of the underlying loan. In exchange for the sale, approximately $146 million of outstanding debt and accrued interest were discharged and the Company's guarantee has been fully released. After giving effect to the transaction, the Company has no outstanding indebtedness. The gain from this transaction is expected to be approximately $85 million, which will be reflected in the first quarter of 2014.
09:02
ALXA Alexza Pharmaceuticals announces private placement of $45 mln of non-recourse notes (4.99 )
Co announced that it has closed a private placement to institutional investors of $45.0 mln of non-recourse notes. The Notes are secured by royalties and potential milestones from U.S. sales of ADASUVE inhalation powder. Alexza's commercial partner for ADASUVE in the U.S. is Teva Pharmaceuticals. Teva licensed from Alexza the U.S. commercial rights to ADASUVE in May 2013. Under the terms of the license and supply agreement, Teva is responsible for all U.S. commercial and clinical activities, including U.S. post-approval clinical studies. Alexza is responsible for manufacturing and supplying ADASUVE to Teva for commercial sales and clinical trials. Alexza is eligible to receive tiered royalty payments based on net commercial sales of ADASUVE, as well as certain milestone payments based upon successful completion of the ADASUVE post-approval studies in the U.S and the achievement of net sales targets.Alexza established a $6.89 mln interest reserve account from the proceeds of the transaction to cover any potential shortfall in interest payments. Any remaining amounts in the interest reserve account will be released to Alexza after December 15, 2015 or commencing June 15, 2015, subject to meeting certain cumulative net sales targets for ADASUVE.
09:02
DHX Dice Holdings has acquired OilCareers, the leading recruitment site for oil and gas professionals in Europe from DMTGY.PK for $26 mln in cash (7.24 )
Co has acquired OilCareers, the leading recruitment site for oil and gas professionals in Europe. The acquisition strengthens the Company's position in online energy recruiting, which it currently serves through Rigzone, the market leader in the oil and gas industry delivering content, data, advertising and career services.
OilCareers was founded in Aberdeen, Scotland in 1999 and currently has about 800,000 unique monthly visitors and an extensive CV database.
Co is purchasing OilCareers from the Daily Mail and General Trust PLC (DMGTY) for $26 million in cash. OilCareers had trailing 12 months revenues of ~$8 million, with the majority generated in the United Kingdom.
09:01
PG Procter & Gamble and Hello Products agree to a stipulated preliminary injunction (79.77 )
Co entered into a Stipulated Preliminary Injunction in a federal lawsuit currently pending in the Southern District of New York. The lawsuit alleges, among other things, that Hello violated federal advertising laws by claiming that its anti-cavity toothpaste is "99% Natural" when it contains ingredients that are extensively and chemically processed. The P.I. requires that, beginning March 25, Hello Products must suspend making certain claims on its toothpaste packaging and advertising, including the claim that it is "99% Natural." P&G had originally asked Hello to discontinue making the "99% Natural" claim over eight months prior to filing the lawsuit.
09:01
RBCN Rubicon Tech prices 2.5 mln share offering by selling stockholders at a price to the public of $13.00 per share (14.11 )
Co announced the pricing of an underwritten public offering of 2.5 mln shares of its common stock by selling stockholders at a price to the public of $13.00/share. The offering is expected to close on March 24, 2014, subject to satisfaction of customary closing conditions. In addition, Rubicon has granted the underwriters a 30-day option to purchase up to an additional 375,000 shares of its common stock to cover over-allotments, if any.
09:00
IDSY I.D. Systems: U.S. Postal Service awards I.D. Systems contract valued at up to $4 mln to initiate upgrade & expansion of wireless vehicle management systems (5.76 )
Co has received a series of purchase orders, valued in excess of $800,000, to deploy its PowerFleet wireless vehicle management system on fleets of lift trucks at multiple distribution centers of a Fortune 100 company. The orders were generated by one of I.D. Systems' channel partners.
08:59
WRAPX S&P futures vs fair value: +0.60. Nasdaq futures vs fair value: +2.00.
The S&P 500 futures hover right above fair value.
The major Asian bourses ended on a mixed note. Japan's trade deficit narrowed to JPY1.13 trillion from JPY1.76 trillion (expected JPY890 billion). While the deficit was the largest ever for the month of February, the numbers improved from last month as exports jumped 9.8% (consensus 12.4%, prior 9.5%) and imports expanded 9.0% (expected 7.4%, last 25.0%). The trade deficit marked the 20th consecutive negative current account reading and was the eight below-consensus reading out of the last nine.
Japan's Nikkei gained 0.4%, climbing to a one-week high. Robotics maker Fanuc rallied 3.2% after trade data showed exports to China improved. Hong Kong's Hang Seng shed 0.1%. Galaxy Entertainment lost 2.8% after its quarterly results disappointed. China's Shanghai Composite settled lower by 0.2% after erasing the bulk of its losses into the close. Property shares were a drag as China Vanke lost 4.0% and Poly Real Estate gave up 2.8%. The major European indices trade mixed with Germany's DAX (+0.6%) in the lead. Participants received a handful of data points. Eurozone Labor Cost Index increased 1.4% year-over-year (prior 1.1%); Great Britain's Claimant Count decreased 34,600 (expected -25,000, prior -33,900) while the unemployment rate held steady at 7.2%, as expected; and the French current account deficit widened to EUR3.90 billion from EUR1.20 billion.
Among news of note, the minutes from the latest Bank of England policy meeting indicated a unanimous vote to stay the course, keeping the benchmark interest rate at 0.5%.
Great Britain's FTSE trades lower by 0.1%. Miners are on the defensive with Anglo American, Antofagasta, and Glencore Xstrata showing losses between 1.7% and 2.5%. Defense contractors BAE Systems and Rolls Royce outperform with respective gains of 3.0% and 1.6%. France's CAC trades higher by 0.1% with growth-sensitive names in the lead. ArcelorMittal and Technip are both up close to 2.0% apiece. Consumer names Pernod Ricard and LVMH Moet Hennessy Louis Vuitton lag. Both names are down near 1.0%. Germany's DAX holds an advance of 0.6% with BMW in the lead. The carmaker has surged 7.7% after issuing upbeat guidance. On the downside, producers of basic materials are among the laggards. HeidelbergCement and Lanxess are down 1.5% and 0.7%, respectively.
08:58
ORC Orchid Island Capital prices offering of 3.2 mln shares of common stock at $12.55 per share (12.92 )
08:57
NES Nuverra Environmental Solutions upsizes revolving credit facility to $245 mln (16.99 )
Co announced that it has revised its existing Revolving Credit Facility to increase the maximum availability under the Revised Facility from $200 million to $245 million. The co's borrowing base calculation as of the closing date supports the $245 million facility size and makes the full facility immediately available to the Company. The terms and pricing of the facility remain the same and are unaffected by the upsizing of the facility size.
08:54
SUMRX European Markets Update: FTSE -0.1%, CAC +0.1%, DAX +0.6%
The major European indices trade mixed with Germany's DAX (+0.6%) in the lead. Participants received a handful of data points. Eurozone Labor Cost Index increased 1.4% year-over-year (prior 1.1%); Great Britain's Claimant Count decreased 34,600 (expected -25,000, prior -33,900) while the unemployment rate held steady at 7.2%, as expected; and the French current account deficit widened to EUR3.90 billion from EUR1.20 billion.
Among news of note, the minutes from the latest Bank of England policy meeting indicated a unanimous vote to stay the course, keeping the benchmark interest rate at 0.5%.
Great Britain's FTSE trades lower by 0.1%. Miners are on the defensive with Anglo American, Antofagasta, and Glencore Xstrata showing losses between 1.7% and 2.5%. Defense contractors BAE Systems and Rolls Royce outperform with respective gains of 3.0% and 1.6%. France's CAC trades higher by 0.1% with growth-sensitive names in the lead. ArcelorMittal and Technip are both up close to 2.0% apiece. Consumer names Pernod Ricard and LVMH Moet Hennessy Louis Vuitton lag. Both names are down near 1.0%. Germany's DAX holds an advance of 0.6% with BMW in the lead. The carmaker has surged 7.7% after issuing upbeat guidance. On the downside, producers of basic materials are among the laggards. HeidelbergCement and Lanxess are down 1.5% and 0.7%, respectively.
08:49
FFKT Farmers Capital Bank Corp announces termination of regulatory agreement (20.82 )
Co announced on March 19, 2014 that it received written notification from the Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis, after consultation with the Kentucky Department of Financial Institutions, that the Memorandum of Understanding entered into between the parties during the fourth quarter of 2009 has been terminated effective immediately.
08:44
KW Kennedy Wilson subsidiary to offer $250 mln in aggregate principal amount of senior notes due 2024 (23.89 )
Kennedy-Wilson, Inc., a subsidiary of KW, intends to offer $250 million in aggregate principal amount of senior notes due 2024. The Notes will be Kennedy Wilson's senior unsecured obligations and will be guaranteed by Kennedy-Wilson Holdings, Inc. and certain subsidiaries of Kennedy Wilson. Kennedy Wilson intends to use the net proceeds from the offering to repay in full outstanding borrowings under its unsecured revolving credit facility and for general corporate purposes, including future acquisitions and co-investments.
08:42
WIRES On The Wires
Goldman Sachs (GS) and Vestar Capital Partners have signed a definitive agreement to acquire Hearthside Food Solutions, the largest independent bakery and contract food manufacturer in North America, from Wind Point Partners. Terms were not disclosed.Dot Hill Systems (HILL) has developed a reference platform, in conjunction with Intel (INTL) and Mellanox (MLNX), to better support the industry-specific needs of geologists and geophysicists for exploration and production applications.NetScout Systems (NTCT) has been awarded a patent on its Adaptive Session Intelligence technology by the USPTO. The ASI Patent acknowledges the unique innovations in the core technology behind the recently announced nGeniusONE Unified Performance Management platform and powers the nGenius InfiniStream appliances.Tutor Perini (TPC) announced that a JV between its subsidiary, Frontier-Kemper Constructors, and ASL has recently been awarded a contract by Aecon/SNC-Lavalin Constructors JV for the underground excavation package for the John Hart Generating Station replacement project in British Columbia. China Biologic Products (CBPO) received the Good Manufacturing Practice certification from China Food and Drug Administration in respect of its plasma production facility at its Guizhou subsidiary. Eagle Rock Energy Partners (EROC) announced that it has filed a definitive proxy statement with the SEC regarding the contribution of its Midstream Business to Regency Energy Partners LP (RGP) and has set the date for a special meeting of its unitholders to approve the transaction. Alimerka has selected multiple components from Manhattan Associates' (MANH) Supply Chain Commerce Solutions portfolio to enable new supply chain processes and maximize service levels across the 176 supermarket stores it operates in the Asturias, Castilla-Leon and Galicia regions of Northern Spain. Edgewater Technology-Ranzal, a subsidiary of Edgewater Technology (EDGW), has achieved OPN Specialized status for Oracle (ORCL) Planning and Budgeting Cloud Service.BlackBerry (BBRY) announced that customers in the U.S. can now purchase SIM-unlocked GSM models of the BlackBerry Z30 smartphone directly from BlackBerry on ShopBlackBerry.com for $499.
08:39
FDX FedEx: F3Q14 results impacted by weather; profit improvement in Express continues -- Cowen (138.57 )
Cowen notes, FDX earnings were below consensus expectations for F3Q14 due to weather. The outlook for F4Q14 is slightly better than expected. The most important story line continues to remain co's $1.6 billion profit improvement effort in Express, which was not explicitly discussed other than a comment that it remains on track. Firm believes the shares will open mixed this morning and then trend higher as mgmt gives its usual optimistic outlook for co due to 1) their profit improvement plan, 2) modestly improving economy, and 3) share repurchase efforts.
08:37
KBH KB Home beats by $0.02, beats on revs (17.68 )
Reports Q1 (Feb) earnings of $0.12 per share, $0.02 better than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of $0.10; revenues rose 11.2% year/year to $450.7 mln vs the $438.95 mln consensus.
Homebuilding revenues increased 45%, 18%, and 63% in the Company's Southwest, Central and Southeast homebuilding regions, respectively, partly offset by a decrease of 12% in its West Coast homebuilding region. The Company delivered 1,442 homes in the current quarter, compared to 1,485 homes delivered in the first quarter of 2013, as a decrease in the Company's West Coast homebuilding region was mostly offset by increases in its other three homebuilding regions. West Coast deliveries declined from the year-earlier quarter, primarily due to the region's lower backlog at the beginning of the quarter. The overall average selling price of $305,200 rose $33,900, or 12%, from the year-earlier quarter, reflecting the Company's strategic operational targeting of attractive, land-constrained locations that generally feature higher household incomes and demand for larger homes, as well as incremental revenues generated from lot premiums, options and upgrades, and generally favorable market conditions. Average selling prices were higher in all four of the Company's homebuilding regions compared to the year-earlier quarter, with increases ranging from 13% in its Central region to 30% in its West Coast region. The significant increase in the Company's West Coast region average selling price partly mitigated the impact fewer homes delivered had on revenues in the region. The housing gross profit margin expanded 290 basis points to 17.7% from 14.8% for the year-earlier quarter, marking the Company's highest first quarter housing gross profit margin since 2006. Potential future housing revenues in backlog at Feb 28, 2014 increased 21% to $851.6 million from $703.9 million at February 28, 2013, reflecting both a greater number of homes in backlog and a higher average selling price. The Company's backlog was comprised of 2,880 homes at February 28, 2014, up 4% from 2,763 homes at February 28, 2013. The overall value of net orders for the 2014 first quarter was $600.2 million, up 18% from $506.8 million for the year-earlier quarter. The current quarter increase was measured against the first quarter of 2013, when the net order value increased 83% from the prior year. Each of the Company's four homebuilding regions reported year-over-year growth in net order value, with increases ranging from 11% in its Southwest region to 27% in its Central region. Net orders increased 6% from the year-earlier quarter to 1,765, reflecting a rise in the Company's community count, as it continues to convert the substantial land investments it has made over the past several quarters to open communities. Average community count increased 10% to 190 from 172 for the year-earlier quarter. "As we continue to execute on our business strategies, increasing the number of communities we operate will be a key factor in driving higher revenues and profits this year," said Mezger. "Through our substantial investments in land and land development over the past few years, we believe we have created a solid platform for growth. In the current quarter, our double-digit percentage increase in community count helped us generate net order growth, and we are actively working to open additional new home communities. We are entering the spring selling season positioned with more communities open in attractive locations across the country, and we are confident that our balanced approach to sales price and pace, combined with our focus on both top-line growth and profitability, will produce strong results in the coming quarters."
08:33
UTSI UTStarcom announces plans for partnership with Korea's DASAN Networks; will explore joint product design, development and marketing (2.64 )
Co announced plans to partner with DASAN Networks of Korea to explore ways of collaborating that will help both companies bring competitive products to market that serve the increasingly complex needs of cable TV, mobile and telecommunications carriers. The two companies signed a MOU at the Optical Fiber Conference 2014 in San Francisco last week to explore a strategic partnership through which they could collaborate on the design, development, manufacturing and marketing of telecommunications infrastructure products. It stems from both companies' desire to create products that help carriers roll out new revenue generating services quickly and efficiently while significantly reducing expenses.
08:33
WRAPX S&P futures vs fair value: +0.90. Nasdaq futures vs fair value: +2.70.
The S&P 500 futures continue trading less than a point above fair value.
The current account deficit for the fourth quarter totaled $81.10 billion while the Briefing.com consensus expected the deficit to hit $87.60 billion. The third quarter deficit was revised to $96.40 billion from $94.80 billion.
08:32
RAS RAIT Financial Trust increases quarterly dividend by 6% to $0.17 per share from $0.16 per share (8.30 )
08:32
MHGC Morgans Hotel Group issues statement in response to Kerrisdale Capital (7.79 )
MHGC issues statement in response to Kerrisdale Capital, noting the Board will review Kerrisdale's notice in due course, in the context of their 3% interest in the Company's outstanding shares of common stock. Among other things, MHGC said:
"That Kerrisdale would propose the liquidation of Morgans prematurely and categorically, would rob Morgans' stockholders of the value that rightfully belongs to them and further highlights Kerrisdale's self-serving motives. Their platform, based solely on the selling of the Company at any price, is reckless and weakens the Company's hand in negotiations with counterparties. It is illustrative of how little experience and value discipline Kerrisdale and its team possess, and how removed they are from considering what is in the best interest of all stockholders."
08:32
ANAC Anacor Pharma appoints Paul L. Berns as Chief Executive Officer (22.44 )
ANAC announced that the Company's Board of Directors has appointed Paul L. Berns, Anacor's Chairman of the Board of Directors, to assume the role of President and Chief Executive Officer, effective immediately.
Mr. Berns succeeds David P. Perry who has served as Anacor's President and Chief Executive Officer since 2002. Mr. Berns has over 20 years of industry experience as an executive in biotechnology and pharmaceutical companies, most recently serving as the President and Chief Executive Officer of Allos Therapeutics prior to its acquisition by Spectrum Pharmaceuticals, Inc. in 2012.
08:31
VC Visteon signs agreement to sell shares in Duckyang JV for $24.1 mln as step toward interiors divestiture (84.26 )
Co announced that the company has reached an agreement to sell its 50 percent ownership stake in a Korean automotive interiors joint venture, Duckyang Industry, in support of its previously announced intentions to divest its interiors business. The sale to certain management shareholders of Duckyang and associated parties for the equivalent of about $24.1 million (25.9 billion Korean Won) is expected to be completed in April after closing conditions are met. In addition to the $24.1 million from the share sale, Visteon expects to receive approximately $5.9 million (6.3 billion Korean Won) in dividends.
08:31
JPM JPMorgan Chase announces sale of commodities business for approx $3.5 bln (58.06 )
Co announced that it has reached a definitive agreement to sell its physical commodities business to Mercuria Energy Group Limited, a global energy and commodities trading company, for $3.5 billion. The all cash transaction is expected to close in the third quarter of 2014. Following the sale, J.P. Morgan will continue to provide traditional banking activities in the commodities markets, including financial products and the vaulting and trading of precious metals. The firm will also continue to make markets, provide liquidity and risk management, and offer advice to global companies and institutions around the world. The transaction is not expected to have a material impact on JPMorgan Chase's earnings.
08:28
SAL Salisbury Bancorp, Inc. trading halted, news pending (27.30 )
08:26
WIRES On The Wires
Customers in Brazil can now use MoneyGram (MGI) services at 69 Confidence C mbio stores across the country. Core Molding Technologies (CMT) completed production of its 2 millionth truck hood.Raytheon Company (RTN) delivered its ninth AN/TPY-2 ballistic missile defense radar to the Missile Defense Agency, six months ahead of schedule. Broadcom (BRCM) announced an alliance with ShanghaiTech University to bring enhanced Wi-Fi infrastructure to Shanghai and to accelerate product development for the rapidly growing Internet of Things market.Trovagene (TROV) and Catholic Health Initiatives Center for Translational Research have entered into a strategic partnership to conduct clinical validation studies, clinical utility studies, health economic studies, and other activities to determine the effectiveness of Trovagene's urine-based cell-free DNA cancer monitoring diagnostics in clinical practice.Portola Pharma (PTLA) has initiated a Phase 3 study of andexanet alfa, the co's investigational Factor Xa inhibitor reversal agent. The study will evaluate the safety and efficacy of andexanet alfa with Bristol-Myers Squibb (BMY) and Pfizer's (PFE) Factor Xa inhibitor Eliquis (apixaban). The co is pursuing an Accelerated Approval pathway for andexanet alfa.Kratos Defense & Security Solutions (KTOS) announced that the Wall Street Analyst has conducted an audio interview with Kratos' President and CEO, Eric DeMarco.
08:26
DPM DCP Midstream to expand sour processing capacity with new 200 MMcf/d plant in liquids-rich Permian Basin (50.00 )
Co announced capital investments that will support the need by producers for further infrastructure in the rapidly expanding Permian Basin. DCP Midstream will construct a 200 million cubic foot per day (MMcf/d) sour natural gas processing plant, Zia II Plant, in Lea County, N.M., with associated gathering system expansions to service producers in both southeast New Mexico and west Texas regions of the Permian Basin.
In addition to the Zia II Plant, the project includes front-end treating for sour gas, two acid gas injection wells, a 50-mile, 20-inch high pressure trunk line that will intersect DCP Midstream's existing New Mexico gathering system, and new high-pressure pipelines and compression in west Texas. The project is expected to be in commercial operation during the first half of 2015.
The Zia II Plant and new gathering systems will augment DCP Midstream's existing footprint in the Permian Basin, where the company owns and operates 18 gas processing plants with a capacity of more than 1.3 Bcf/d and produces in excess of 130,000 barrels per day of natural gas liquids.
08:25
WIRES On The Wires
Twisted Pair Solutions, a subsidiary of Motorola Solutions (MSI), announced that its WAVE software was placed on the U.S. Department of Defense Unified Capabilities Approved Products List.Veeco Instruments (VECO) announced that II-VI (IIVI) has ordered the SPECTOR-HT Ion Beam Deposition System and added Veeco's new Quest Optical Monitor, for use in its high-volume production of laser optics. AstraZeneca (AZN) launched NEXIUM Direct, a program that provides eligible patients the option of having brand-name NEXIUM delivered directly to their home.Meru Networks (MERU) is currently outfitting several Austrian educational institutions, including commercial centers of learning BHAK and BHAS in Krems and HAK/HAS and HLW/FW in Horn, with Meru's wireless solutions.Cornerstone OnDemand (CSOD) announced its selection by the Higher Education Recruitment Consortium as a Trustee Partner.Agios Pharma (AGIO) announced that the first patient has been dosed in a Phase 1 study of AG-120 in patients with advanced hematologic malignancies with an isocitrate dehydrogenase-1 (IDH1) mutation.Juniper Networks (JNPR) announced that Catholic Health System has deployed Juniper Networks data center solutions to support mission-critical healthcare applications. AMD (AMD) announced three new game developer partnerships for AMD Gaming Evolved, an ISV relationship program that assists developers in creating an enhanced PC gaming experience.WPCS International (WPCS) announced that the beta version of the BTX trader platform, which was previously available only as a downloadable application for Windows-based operating systems, is now available directly from the web. NCR (NCR) and Movio announced that the two cos will enable integration between NCR's cinema point-of-sale and loyalty software and Movio's data analytics and campaign management platform.
08:16
VRA Vera Bradley will resume trading at 8:30am (26.25 )
See 8:08 earnings comment
08:10
BDX Becton Dickinson segment, BD Diagnosstics, receives 510(k) clearance and clinical laboratory improvement amendments waiver from the FDA for nasopharyngeal swab specimens on the BD Veritor System for Rapid Detection of Respiratory Syncytial Virus (116.78 )
Co announced that it received 510(k) clearance and Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA) waiver from the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for nasopharyngeal swab specimens on the BD Veritor System for Rapid Detection of Respiratory Syncytial Virus (RSV). This is the first commercially available rapid CLIA-waived RSV test system that incorporates a digital result. The new assay is cleared for use in physician offices, hospitals, and other patient-care settings.
"Early and reliable detection of RSV is critical among high-risk populations to treat and prevent the spread of this contagious virus and hospitalizations," said Alberto Mas, President, BD Diagnostics -- Diagnostic Systems. "The CLIA-waived BD Veritor System for Rapid Detection of RSV has demonstrated good performance when compared to PCR, the highest reference lab based standard, while providing an objective test result in only 10 minutes."
08:09
KNDI Kandi Technologies announces agreement for registered direct placement of ~$11.05 mln of common stock and warrants at price of $18.24 per share (21.16 )
Co has entered into a securities purchase agreement with two institutional investors for a registered direct placement of approximately $11,053,440 of common stock at a price of $18.24 per share. The Company will issue a total of 606,000 shares to the institutional investors. As part of the transaction, the Company will also issue to the investors warrants for the purchase of up to 90,900 shares of common stock at an exercise price of $22.80 per share, which warrants have a term of 18 months from the date of issuance.
08:08
VRA Vera Bradley (halted) beats by $0.02, beats on revs; guides Q1 below consensus; guides FY15 EPS below consensus, revs above consensus (26.25 )
Reports Q4 (Jan) earnings of $0.48 per share, $0.02 better than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of $0.46; revenues fell 3.1% year/year to $157.5 mln vs the $146.89 mln consensus. These results included a pre-tax inventory write-down of $4.8 million, equating to ~$3.0 million after tax, or $0.07 per share. The inventory write-down primarily related to fabrics in certain retired patterns no longer considered salable and to certain merchandise in the baby gift category, which is being discontinued by the Company.
Current year fourth quarter Direct segment revenues increased 5.2%, to $108.7 million from $103.3 million in the prior year. Fourth quarter year-over-year net revenues in the Company's stores grew 14.5%. This growth reflected the opening of 19 full-price and four outlet stores during the past 12 months and was partially offset by a comparable-store sales decline of 10.2%. E-commerce revenues decreased 7.2% compared to the prior year. The decreases in comparable store and e-commerce sales were due to year-over-year declines in traffic, a lower average transaction size, and underperformance of the product offering. Severe winter weather also negatively affected store traffic during the quarter. Indirect segment revenues decreased 17.5% to $48.9 million from $59.2 million in the prior year, primarily due to lower orders from the Company's specialty retail accounts combined with closing ~ 400 wholesale accounts during the year. Gross profit for the quarter totaled $83.3 million, or 52.9% of net revenues, compared to $94.1 million, or 57.9% of net revenues, in the prior year fourth quarter. The aforementioned inventory write-down negatively affected the current year fourth quarter gross margin rate by ~300 basis points. In addition, the gross margin rate was negatively affected by increased year-over-year promotional activity as well as an increase in the sales mix of lower-margin product.Co issues downside guidance for Q1, sees EPS of $0.11-0.13 vs. $0.22 Capital IQ Consensus; sees Q1 revs of $116-120 mln vs. $123.08 mln Capital IQ Consensus Estimate.
Co issues mixed guidance for FY15, sees EPS of $1.20-1.30 vs. $1.50 Capital IQ Consensus; sees FY15 revs of $545-565 mln vs. $547.09 mln Capital IQ Consensus Estimate.
"We continue to face external headwinds and certain challenges within the business, and fiscal 2015 will be a year of transition for Vera Bradley," Wallstrom continued. "We have spent the last few months developing our comprehensive five-year strategic plan designed to drive improved financial performance and shareholder value over the long-term. Our vision is to build on our rich heritage and establish Vera Bradley as a premium lifestyle brand that is relevant to the future, expanding our customer reach and growing our customer connections.
08:07
ICON Iconix Brand announces exec changes; Seth Horowitz promoted to COO, Jeff Lupinacci appointed as CFO (40.87 )
Warren Clamen is resigning from the Company to pursue other opportunities.
08:07
CWH CommonWealth REIT acknowledges receipt of documentation from Related/Corvex; as directed by arbitrators, co within five business days will inspect and certify results of consent solicitation (26.81 )
Co announced that it has received documentation from Related Fund Management and Corvex Management LP that they claim are written consents reaching the 66.7% threshold required to remove the entire CWH Board of Trustees, without cause. As directed by the November 18, 2013, Arbitration Decision, CWH will inspect the consents and declare the results of the solicitation within five business days from receipt. After conferring with the Inspector of Elections, CWH expects to announce the results of the consent solicitation on or before Tuesday, March 25, 2014.
08:07
ATU Actuant misses by $0.02, misses on revs; guides Q3 EPS below consensus, revs below consensus; lowers FY14 EPS guidance, reaffirms revs in-line (33.29 )
Reports Q2 (Feb) earnings of $0.30 per share, $0.02 worse than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of $0.32; revenues rose 9.1% year/year to $327.8 mln vs the $332.76 mln consensus.
Co issues downside guidance for Q3, sees EPS of $0.60-0.65 vs. $0.69 Capital IQ Consensus Estimate; sees Q3 revs of $370-380 mln vs. $386.34 mln Capital IQ Consensus Estimate.Co lowers FY14 EPS outlook to the lower end of its prior guidance of $2.00-2.10 vs. $2.03 Capital IQ Consensus Estimate; reaffirms FY14 revs of $1.41-1.45 bln vs. $1.42 bln Capital IQ Consensus Estimate.
08:06
NRG NRG Energy and Edison Mission Energy announce that the FERC has approved the previously announced sale of substantially all of EME's assets to NRG (30.16 )
The FERC approval represents the final regulatory authorizations required to close the transaction and parties expect to close the transaction on April 1, 2014.
08:06
CECE CECO Environ. announces Chinese sales alliance with Rehne Environmental (18.56 )
Co announces that a Sales Cooperation Agreement has been formalized between CECE and Jiangsu Renhe Environmental Equipments Company. The two companies will focus on bringing expanded air pollution control technology solutions to the growing China market by leveraging each other's extensive product portfolio, fabrication base and sales channels. Renhe focuses on dust collector and filter cartridge technology products with sales locations in Shanghai, Guangzhou, Xi'an and Ha'erbin City. The target areas for this partnership will include applications across a variety of industrial markets, such as general industry, metals, petrochemical, chemical, plastics, and cement, and will include CECE`s FisherKlosterman Cyclones, Dual Scrubbers, CECO Filtration and Flex-Kleen Dust Collection Technologies.
08:05
GHDX Genomic Health announces presentation of new data further supporting use of Oncotype DX in Europe; physician survey reveals substantial differences in chemotherapy treatment recommendations (29.39 )
Co announced the presentation of multiple Oncotype DX breast cancer studies at the 9th European Breast Cancer Conference, which takes place March 19-21 in Glasgow, Scotland, United Kingdom. New data will include an independently conducted physician survey that underscores the need for broader availability of standard predictive genomic testing, like Oncotype DX, to help better inform chemotherapy treatment decisions in early-stage breast cancer patients in Europe. Additional studies showcasing the unsurpassed volume and consistency of clinical validation, clinical utility and health-economics evidence supporting the use of Oncotype DX will also be presented at the meeting.Physician Survey Reveals Substantial Differences in Chemotherapy Treatment Recommendations, Underscoring the Need for Broader Genomic Testing in Europe to Enable More Informed Decisions.Estrogen receptor positive breast cancer patients receive hormonal treatment after surgery, but sometimes chemotherapy is also needed. The Multidisciplinary Application of Genomics in Clinical Practice survey aims to identify the role of classic pathology criteria that clinicians use in daily practice when recommending adjuvant chemotherapy in ER positive patients. This online survey analyzed responses from 911 physicians representing 52 countries. The results reveal substantial heterogeneity in the criteria used to determine chemotherapy use, suggesting a compelling need for broader use of objective, predictive genomic tests which can help physicians and patients make more informed treatment decisions. In addition to the studies highlighted above, additional Oncotype DX data presented includes: The run-in-phase of the prospective WSG-ADAPT trial confirmed trial design estimates of Recurrence Score results and reduction in markers of proliferation following endocrine induction therapy, indicating that the multi-center prospective ADAPT concept combining static and dynamic biomarker assessment for individualized therapy decisions in early-stage breast cancer is feasible. (Abstract P005: "Early proliferation response stratified by recurrence score demonstrates distinct efficacy of different endocrine therapies in the prospective WSG-ADAPT HR+/HER2- trial run-in phase," March 20, 15:30-16:30 GMT, Systemic Therapy Session, Lomond Auditorium),
08:03
TIF Tiffany & Co names Ralph Nicoletti as Chief Financial Officer; Jim Fernandez, co's veteran COO and CFO, to Retire (92.67 )
Co announced that Ralph Nicoletti will become its next executive vice president and chief financial officer. His appointment to those offices will become effective on April 2, 2014. The Company also announced the intention of James N. Fernandez, chief operating officer and chief financial officer, to retire in July.
Nicoletti will be based in New York and responsible for the Company's worldwide financial functions and information technology. He will report to Michael J. Kowalski, chairman and chief executive officer.
Nicoletti joins Tiffany from CIGNA, the global health services and insurance company, where he was executive vice president and chief financial officer. Prior to that, he was executive vice president and chief financial officer at Alberto Culver and held various financial management positions at Kraft Foods.
08:03
VOLC Volcano announces FDA clearance of its proprietary iFR (instant wave-Free Ratio) modality and immediate commencement of U.S. limited market release (22.58 )
08:03
HTBX Heat Biologics submits revised protocol to FDA for Phase 2 clinical study of HS-110 for the treatment of non-small cell lung cancer; revised protocol specifically designed to mimic expected future combinations with checkpoint inhibitors in preparation of next generation of oncology treatment (6.25 )
HTBX announced that it has submitted its revised Phase 2 clinical trial protocol for its HS-110 product candidate to the U.S. FDA for the treatment of patients with non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC).
HS-110 is Heat's first product candidate in a series of its proprietary Immune Pan Antigen Cytotoxic Therapy ("ImPACT") based allogeneic cell lines designed to direct killer T cells to attack cancer.HS-110 utilizes genetically modified lung cancer cells to stimulate a patient's immune system to activate a robust cytotoxic T cell response against a wide array of lung cancer antigens. Co will host a live conference call and webcast with the investment community on March 20, 2014 at 11:00 a.m. ET to discuss this revised trial.
08:03
EXC Exelon announces acquisition of ETC ProLiance Energy; financial terms not disclosed (31.15 )
Co announced it has reached an agreement to purchase ETC ProLiance Energy, an Indianapolis-based supplier of natural gas to commercial and industrial customers, plus power generators and utilities, over 2,500 customer facilities.
08:02
CTAS Cintas: Shred-it to combine with Cintas' document shredding business (60.23 )
Co announced an agreement with the shareholders of Shred-it International Inc. to combine Cintas' Document Shredding business with Shred-it's Document Shredding business. Under the agreement, Cintas and Shred-it will each contribute its document shredding business to a newly formed partnership that will be owned 42% by Cintas and 58% by the shareholders of Shred-it. The combined entity will operate under the Shred-it brand and is expected to have annual revenues in excess of $600 million. In addition to its 42% ownership of the partnership, Cintas will receive approximately $180 million in cash at the closing of the transaction.
The transaction, which was approved by Cintas' Board of Directors, is expected to close before Cintas' fiscal year end which is May 31, 2014, subject to the customary closing conditions and various approvals.
With regards to Cintas' Global Document Storage and Imaging business, Cintas is currently exploring strategic opportunities for this business and will provide additional details in the future as appropriate.
08:02
MTRX Matrix Service has increased the size and extended the term of its revolving credit facility (34.18 )
Co has executed an amendment to its existing credit agreement to increase its existing senior secured revolving credit facility from $125.0 million to $200.0 million and extend the maturity date from November 7, 2016 to March 13, 2019. Additionally, the amendment lowers the applicable rates on borrowings, the letters of credit fees and the unused revolving credit facility fees. The credit facility may be used for working capital, acquisitions, capital expenditures, issuance of letters of credit and other lawful corporate purposes.
08:01
WRAPX S&P futures vs fair value: +0.90. Nasdaq futures vs fair value: +3.20.
U.S. equity futures trade little changed amid quiet action overseas. The S&P 500 futures hover less than a point above fair value.
Reviewing overnight developments:
Asian markets ended on a mixed note. Japan's Nikkei +0.4%, Hong Kong's Hang Seng -0.1%, and China's Shanghai Composite -0.2%. Participants received several economic data points: Japan's trade deficit narrowed to JPY1.13 trillion from JPY1.76 trillion (expected deficit of JPY890 billion) as exports rose 9.8% year-over-year (consensus 12.4%, prior 9.5%) and imports expanded 9.0% (expected 7.4%, last 25.0%). Separately, All Industries Activity Index rose 1.0% (consensus 1.3%, prior -0.1%). Australia's MI Leading Index slipped 0.1% month-over-month (prior -0.1%). New Zealand's current account deficit narrowed to NZD1.43 billion from NZD4.88 billion. South Korea's PPI was unchanged month-over-month (prior 0.3%). In news: Japan's trade deficit marked the 20th consecutive negative trade balance reading and was the eight below-consensus reading out of the last nine. Major European indices trade mixed. Great Britain's FTSE -0.1%, France's CAC +0.1%, and Germany's DAX +0.7%. Elsewhere, Spain's IBEX +0.4% and Italy's MIB -0.1%. In economic data: Eurozone Labor Cost Index increased 1.4% year-over-year (prior 1.1%). Great Britain's Claimant Count decreased 34,600 (expected -25,000, prior -33,900) while the unemployment rate held steady at 7.2%, as expected. French current account deficit widened to EUR3.90 billion from EUR1.20 billion. Among news of note: The minutes from the latest Bank of England policy meeting indicated a unanimous vote to stay the course, keeping the benchmark interest rate at 0.5%. In U.S. corporate news:
FedEx (FDX 136.30, -2.27): -1.6% after missing the Capital IQ consensus estimate by $0.25 on below-consensus revenue. The logistics company guided fourth-quarter earnings in-line with estimates. Oracle (ORCL 37.89, -0.95): -2.5% after missing bottom-line estimates on revenue that was in-line with analyst expectations. SolarCity (SCTY 75.95, -1.15): -1.5% after its below-consensus guidance overshadowed better-than-expected earnings and revenue. The weekly MBA Mortgage Applications Index fell 1.2% to follow last week's decline of 2.1%.
The fourth quarter current account balance (Briefing.com consensus -$87.60 billion) will be announced at 8:30 ET. Also of note, the Federal Open Market Committee will conclude its two-day meeting with the latest policy statement scheduled to be released at 14:00 ET. The statement will be followed by Janet Yellen's first press conference as Fed Chair, scheduled to begin at 14:30 ET.
07:54
WIRES On The Wires
Fifth Street Senior Floating Rate (FSFR) announced that it and GF Funding 2014, an entity controlled by the Glick family, have signed a Letter of Intent to form a strategic partnership to co-invest primarily in senior secured loans of middle market companies.IMRIS (IMRS) announced that neurosurgeons at Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center in Lebanon, NH, have completed several cases to inaugurate use of intraoperative MRI within the VISIUS Surgical Theatre inside the hospital's Center for Surgical Innovation.Praxair (PX) announced the start-up of the first of two 1,250 metric tons per day air separation units at Steel Authority of India's Bhilai, India facility. The plant will provide a reliable and energy efficient supply of gaseous oxygen, nitrogen and argon under a long term contract to support SAIL's expansion activities.Cardiome Pharma (CRME) has entered into a distribution agreement with Logista Pharma S.A., headquartered in Madrid, Spain, to distribute BRINAVESS (vernakalant IV) within the Spanish market. Financial details of the agreement were not disclosed.
07:49
SUMRX Asian Markets Close: Nikkei +0.4%, Hang Seng -0.1%, Shanghai -0.2%
The major Asian bourses ended mixed. Japan's trade deficit narrowed to JPY1.13 trln (JPY0.89 trln expected, JPY1.76 trln previous). While the deficit was the largest ever for the month of February, the numbers improved from last month as exports jumped 9.8%. Japan's Nikkei (+0.4%) climbed to a one-week high. Robotics maker Fanuc rallied 3.2% after trade data showed exports to China improved. Hong Kong's Hang Seng (-0.1%) ended little changed. Galaxy Entertainment shed 2.8% after is quarterly results disappointed. China's Shanghai Composite (-0.2%) rallied into the close, erasing the majority of its losses. Property shares were a drag as China Vanke lost 4.0% and Poly Real Estate gave up 2.8%. India's Sensex (UNCH) finished flat. Heavyweight Tata Consultancy Services shed 3.9% amid revenue growth concerns. Those worries also dragged down rival Infosys, which lost 2.4%. Australia's ASX (+0.2%) closed on the highs. The 'big four' banks ended mixed with ANZ up 0.5% to lead the way. Regional Decliners: Thailand -0.6%...Taiwan -0.5%...Singapore -0.4%...Malaysia -0.2%...South Korea -0.1%...Philippines -0.1% Regional Advancers: Indonesia +0.3% Fx: USDCNY ticked up to 6.1954...USDINR slipped to 60.94...USDJPY +10 pips @ 101.51...AUDUSD -10 pips @ .9115
07:48
WLT Walter Energy commences private offerings of $100 mln aggregate principal amount of 9.500% senior secured notes due 2019 and $350 mln aggregate principal amount of senior secured second lien PIK toggle notes due 2020 (9.01 )
Co announced that it has commenced private offerings of $100 million aggregate principal amount of 9.500% senior secured notes due 2019 and $350 million aggregate principal amount of senior secured second lien PIK toggle notes due 2020. The Notes will be guaranteed by each of Walter Energy's current and future wholly-owned domestic restricted subsidiaries that from time to time guarantee any of Walter Energy's indebtedness or any indebtedness of any of Walter Energy's restricted subsidiaries. The New First Lien Notes and related guarantees will be secured on a first priority basis by substantially all of the property and assets of Walter Energy and the guarantors. The Second Lien Notes and related guarantees will be secured on a second priority basis by substantially all of the property and assets of Walter Energy and the guarantors. Walter Energy intends to use the net proceeds of the offerings of the Notes to repay in full its term loan A under its credit facility, increase its liquidity and pay fees and expenses related thereto.
07:38
FDX FedEx misses by $0.25, misses on revs; guides Q4 EPS in-line (138.57 )
Reports Q3 (Feb) earnings of $1.23 per share, $0.25 worse than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of $1.48; revenues rose 2.7% year/year to $11.3 bln vs the $11.44 bln consensus.
Unusually severe winter storms throughout the quarter disrupted operations, decreasing shipping volume and increasing costs, and impacted year-over-year operating income by an estimated $125 million.FedEx Express rev down slightly YoY to $6.67 bln; operating income +14% to $135 mln.FedEx Ground rev +10% to $3.03 bln; operating income +2% to $477 mln.Freight rev +9% to $1.35 bln; OI $29 mln from $4 mln.Co issues in-line guidance for Q4, sees EPS of $2.25-2.50 vs. $2.34 Capital IQ Consensus Estimate.
Co lowered FY14 EPS guidance to $6.55-6.80 from $6.73-7.10.
This outlook reflects share repurchases made to date, but does not include any benefit from additional share repurchases. Share repurchases are expected to continue, but the timing will be at the company's discretion. The outlook also assumes the market outlook for fuel prices and continued moderate economic growth. The capital spending forecast for fiscal 2014 is now $3.8 billion, down $200 million from the previous forecast. "While severe winter weather often affects our third-quarter results, the impact from multiple severe storms and frigid temperatures was significantly more pronounced this year and we are reducing our full-year earnings per share guidance as a result of the weather impact," said Alan B. Graf, Jr., FedEx Corp. executive vice president and chief financial officer. "The $1.6 billion profit improvement plan at FedEx Express remains on track despite the near-term impact of weather. Our accelerated stock repurchase program initiated in January reflects our confidence in achieving our financial goals."
07:31
SXT Sensient: FrontFour believes real change is needed at Sensient; says Board must be held accountable for Sensient's substantial underperformance (54.88 )
FrontFour Capital, together with its affiliates, issued an open letter to shareholders of Sensient Technologies in connection with its nomination of four nominees for election to the Board of Directors at Sensient's 2014 annual meeting of shareholders. Letter states:
"FrontFour Master Fund, Ltd., together with its affiliates, is a significant shareholder of Sensient Technologies Corporation, a Wisconsin corporation, dedicated to maximizing shareholder value and enhancing corporate governance by seeking to improve the composition of its board of directors. We have nominated four highly-qualified director candidates, James R. Henderson, James E. Hyman, Stephen E. Loukas and William E. Redmond, Jr., for election to the Board at the Company's 2014 Annual Meeting of Shareholders scheduled to be held on April 24, 2014, because of the Company's prolonged operational underperformance, lack of accountability, governance concerns, and inability to create long-term shareholder value, as more fully described below. With an average tenure of 13 years and de minimus ownership by Board members, we question whether the Board's interests are adequately aligned with shareholders. In contrast, our approximately $40 million investment in Sensient should clearly demonstrate that our interests are directly aligned with all Sensient shareholders...
In order to properly address the Company's prolonged underperformance, we believe the Company must undertake a more robust restructuring plan to return value to shareholders and seek to reduce the Company's cost structure by more than $20 to 25 million annually, as currently targeted by the Company. Based on our extensive due diligence of Sensient, we believe that at least a $75 million annual cost savings opportunity exists through not only plant consolidation, but also streamlining of the Company's organizational structure, procurement savings, price and product optimization, and the elimination of what we believe are excessive pension plans for the Company's executive officers and Board members. We also believe additional improvements can be made through targeted R&D spending, optimized capital allocation, and improved governance that holds management accountable and is performance-driven."
07:26
SUMRX Dollar Drifts Little Changed: 10-yr: unch..2.672%..USD/JPY: 101.52..EUR/USD: 1.3923
The Dollar Index holds little changed as action presses the 79.40 level. The Index saw an early bid probe 79.50, but sellers emerged at the level and managed to drop action back to the flat line. EURUSD is -5 pips @ 1.3930 as trade edges off its best close in 29 months. Early action in the single currency has been limited to a 30 pip range as a lack of data and news flow from the region coupled with today's FOMC rate decision has made for a quiet trade. The 1.3850 area provides the first level of support. GBPUSD is +45 pips @ 1.6635 as trade holds just off its best levels of the session. Sterling found some early support at the 1.6600 level after Britain's claimant count change posted a better than expected -34.6K (-23.3K expected) and the unemployment rate held steady at 7.2%, as expected. The latest Bank of England MPC votes were also released with members voting unanimously to keep asset purchases and the Official Bank Rate unchanged at the most recent meeting. A push through 1.6650 puts the recent highs near 1.6750 in jeopardy. Britain's annual budget will cross the wires later this morning. USDCHF is +10 pips @ .8740 as trade remains trapped near its worst levels since October 2011. Today's light bid comes after Switzerland's ZEW Economic Expectations printed a disappointing 19.0 (28.7 expected). The .8775/.8800 area is home to near-term resistance. Swiss National Bank Chairman Thomas Jordan will speak this afternoon in Bern. USDJPY is +15 pips @ 101.55 as trade ticks off support in the area. The latest Japanese trade data crossed the wires overnight with the trade deficit narrowing to JPY1.13 trln (JPY0.89 trln expected, JPY1.76 trln previous). While the deficit was the largest ever for the month of February, the numbers improved from last month as exports jumped 9.8%.AUDUSD is -10 pips @ .9115 as trade slips off three-month highs. Some light buying early on in the session provided a test of the 200 dma (.9145), but sellers emerged in defense of the level and managed to push trade lower. The ability to hold .9050 will be key for the bull case as important support and the 100 dma lurk in the area. USDCNY ticked up to 6.1954. USDCAD is +55 pips @ 1.1190 as trade looks for its best close since July 2009. The pair caught a bid in response to yesterday's dovish comments by Bank of Canada Governor Stephen Poloz, and that momentum has carried over into today's session. Canada's wholesale sales are due out later this morning. Click here to see a daily USDCAD chart.
07:20
WIRES On The Wires
TherapeuticsMD (TXMD) announced the launch of vitaMedMD's newest prescription prenatal multivitamin, vitaPearl. Men's Wearhouse (MW) launched its omni-channel inventory program, which gives customers visibility and access to all merchandise within the co's distribution center and its 900+ retail locations from one location. Genpact (G) announced the renewal of its contract with international retailing group Ahold to drive significant business impact in the retailer's finance and accounting and human resources services for the next five and three years, respectively.CEVA (CEVA), Brite Semiconductor (Shanghai) and Semiconductor Manufacturing International (SMI) jointly announced a collaboration to provide hard macro versions of CEVA's DSP cores for customers wishing to reduce the risk and design cycle time for their SoC projects.Isis Pharma (ISIS) has initiated a Phase 1 clinical study for ISIS-ANGPTL3, an antisense drug targeting angiopoietin-like 3 protein (ANGPTL3), an independent risk factor for cardiovascular disease. Co plans to evaluate ISIS-ANGPTL3 in patients who have severe metabolic or cardiovascular disease and who would benefit from a drug that simultaneously addresses a variety of adverse lipid and metabolic parameters contributing to their disease. Kratos Defense & Security Solutions (KTOS) announced that its Public Safety & Security Division recently received a new $7.8 mln critical infrastructure security system contract award. ARCA biopharma (ABIO) announced that Michael R. Bristow, president and CEO, will be interviewed live today by host Michael Yorba on Clear Channel Business Talk Radio's The Traders Network Show.
07:17
BA Boeing and South Africa's Comair Limited announce order for eight 737 MAXs valued at $830 mln at list prices (124.04 )
Co and Comair Limited announced an order for eight 737 MAX 8s, valued at $830 million at list prices. It is the first 737 MAX order announcement for an African operator. The order was booked in December 2013 and was previously unidentified on the Boeing Orders & Deliveries website.
07:16
HZNP Horizon Pharma: Deerfield provides up to $250 mln in acquisition financing to Horizon Pharma (14.68 )
Deerfield Management announced that it has provided up to $250 million in acquisition financing to Horizon Pharma for the acquisition of Vidara Therapeutics International. Under the terms of the agreement, Horizon Pharma has the option to draw up to $250 million in exchange for a commitment fee. Amounts drawn will accrue interest payable quarterly in arrears and must be repaid within five years. Horizon has the ability to prepay the loan after the third and fourth anniversaries.
07:11
PEUGY.PK Peugot SA announced its Supervisory Board unanimously approved the proposed resolutions presented by the Managing Board; new corporate governance structure will be put into place as a result of the share issues that are subject to shareholder approval (17.53 )
At its meeting, the Supervisory Board of Peugeot S.A. unanimously approved the proposed resolutions presented by the Managing Board, which will be submitted to shareholders at the Annual Meeting next 25 April.In accordance with the information released last 19 February, a new corporate governance structure will be put into place as a result of the share issues that are subject to shareholder approval. The Supervisory Board will be composed of six members representing the key shareholders, of six independent members and two members representing respectively employees and shareholder employees.
07:08
FSC Fifth Street Finance releases its March 2014 newsletter: Multi-point plan positively impacting earnings (9.36 )
Co released its March 2014 newsletter today. "Our established origination platform and sponsor relationships are combining to drive strong, attractive originations during the second half of the March quarter. The initiatives to improve net investment income, which we discussed in past earnings conference calls and newsletters, are generating the returns we anticipated. As a result, we estimate that we are on pace for the March quarter to cover the current dividend level declared by the Board of Directors. We anticipate future earnings should continue to benefit from maintaining leverage within our target range and further progress on our initiatives should result in the addition of higher yielding assets to the portfolio with favorable risk-adjusted returns. This may provide our Board of Directors the opportunity to declare a higher dividend level in the future."
07:06
GIS General Mills beats by $0.01, misses on revs; reaffirms FY14 EPS guidance (50.71 )
Reports Q3 (Feb) earnings of $0.62 per share, excluding non-recurring items, $0.01 better than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of $0.61; revenues fell 1.2% year/year to $4.38 bln vs the $4.42 bln consensus.
Foreign exchange translation reduced net sales growth by 1%age point. Net price realization and mix contributed 1 point of net sales growth, while lower pound volume reduced sales growth by 1 point. Third-quarter gross margin was above year-ago levels including changes in mark-to-market valuation of certain commodities and grain inventories. Excluding mark-to-market effects, gross margin declined for the quarter. Advertising and media expense was 3% below year-ago levels, while other consumer marketing spending was up 5% in the period. Adjusted segment operating profit was $690 million, 10% below prior-year results excluding the impact of Venezuela devaluation. Co reaffirms guidance for FY14, sees EPS of $2.87-2.90, excluding non-recurring items, vs. $2.87 Capital IQ Consensus Estimate. "We anticipate strong double-digit growth in adjusted diluted EPS for the final quarter of fiscal 2014 [consensus $0.69 vs. $0.64 consensus (+8%)]. Our quarterly input cost inflation is expected to be well below year-ago levels. We also expect the quarterly tax rate and the average number of shares outstanding to be well the below the prior-year." Adj. diluted EPS excludes mark-to-market valuation effects for certain commodities and grain inventories; restructuring and other exit costs; and the impact of changes in Venezuelan foreign currency policy.
"This year's severe winter weather dampened sales performance across the food industry, and third-quarter results for our U.S. Retail and Convenience Stores and Foodservice segments reflect that disruption. International segment results were stronger, with constant-currency sales gains in every region including double-digit growth in both Asia-Pacific and Latin America."
07:02
GPT Gramercy Property Trust subsidiary prices private offering of $100 mln aggregate principal amount of the Operating Partnership's 3.75% Exchangeable Senior Notes due 2019 (5.17 )
Co announced that GPT Property Trust, the wholly-owned subsidiary through which the Company conducts its operations, has priced a private offering of $100 million aggregate principal amount of the Operating Partnership's 3.75% Exchangeable Senior Notes due 2019, which will be sold only to qualified institutional buyers in accordance with Rule 144A under the Securities Act of 1933, as amended. The notes will be senior unsecured obligations of the Operating Partnership and will be guaranteed by the Company on a senior unsecured basis. The Operating Partnership also granted the initial purchasers a 30-day option to purchase up to an additional $15 million aggregate principal amount of the notes to cover over-allotments, if any. The closing of the sale of the notes is expected to occur on March 24, 2014, subject to the satisfaction of customary closing conditions.
07:01
EVHC Envision Healthcare Holdings acquires Life Line Ambulance in Prescott, Arizona and MedStat EMS, Inc. in Winona, Mississippi; announces expanded managed transportation contracts (34.10 )
Co announced it has acquired Life Line Ambulance in Prescott, Arizona and MedStat EMS, Inc. in Winona, Mississippi. The acquisitions will generate estimated annual revenues of $36 million and employ more than 250 clinicians and support team members. AMR also announced it secured a new managed transportation contract and expanded four others which, in total, will generate estimated net-new annual revenues of $37.5 mln.
07:00
HZNP Horizon Pharma to acquire Vidara Therapeutics; accelerated transformation of Horizon to a profitable specialty pharma company (HALTED) (14.68 )
The cos entered into a definitive agreement under which Horizon Pharma will acquire Vidara through a reverse merger for stock and cash valued at approximately $660 million. Horizon Pharma plc will be the name of the resulting company. Horizon Pharma plc will be organized under the laws of Ireland with a portfolio of four products marketed primarily in the United States. The proposed transaction has been unanimously approved by both companies' boards of directors. Pursuant to the agreement, Vidara will combine with Horizon Pharma, Inc. with approximately 74 percent of Horizon Pharma plc's ordinary shares to be exchanged for Horizon Pharma, Inc.'s common shares, with Horizon surviving the merger. The shareholders of Vidara will retain approximately 26 percent of Horizon Pharma plc and receive $200 million in cash, subject to certain adjustments. Strategic and financial benefits of the transaction: Accelerated transformation of Horizon to a profitable specialty pharma company; Expected pro forma combined, full year 2014 revenues of $250 to $265 million and EBITDA of $65 to $75 million; Expanded revenue base to include Horizon Pharma's DUEXIS, VIMOVO and RAYOS marketed in the U.S., Vidara's ACTIMMUNE marketed in the U.S. and Horizon's LODOTRA marketed outside the U.S; and Tax efficient corporate structure enhanced to support Horizon's organic growth and acquisition strategy.
06:53
WIRES On The Wires
Huntington Bank (HBAN) has completed the elimination of its $10 overdraft protection transfer fees for consumer and small business customers. Advantest Corporation (ATE) has received an order from the engineering group within HiSilicon Technologies for a V93000 Smart Scale tester equipped with Advantest's Pin Scale Serial Link digital channel card.
06:50
MCHX Marchex announces proposed offering 5,714,000 shares of Class B common stock (2,857,000 shares by certain existing shareholders) (12.01 )
Co announced that it will commence an underwritten public offering of 5,714,000 shares of Marchex's Class B common stock pursuant to an effective shelf registration statement.The co will be offering 2,857,000 shares of its Class B common stock and an additional 2,857,000 shares of its Class B common stock will be offered by certain existing shareholders identified in the prospectus supplement relating to the offering.The co intends to use the net proceeds of the offering for general corporate purposes, which may include acquisitions or licenses of, or investments in, products, services, technologies or other businesses. Marchex will not receive any of the proceeds from the sale of shares by the selling shareholders. Deutsche Bank Securities will be the lead book-running manager and representative of the underwriters for the offering. RBC Capital Markets and Piper Jaffray will be joint book-running managers. BMO Capital Markets and Stephens Inc. are co-managers for the offering.
06:45
S&P futures vs fair value: flat. Nasdaq futures vs fair value: +2.50.
06:45
Asian Markets
Nikkei...14462.52...+51.50...+0.40%. Hang Seng...21568.69...-14.80...-0.10%.
06:45
European Markets
FTSE...6593.35...-11.90...-0.20%. DAX...9270.62...+28.10...+0.30%.
06:45
MCHX Marchex raises Q1 guidance, also announces 5.7 mln offering (~half existing shareholders) (12.01 )
Co raises call-driven rev to $42 mln or more from $40 mln or more; call-driven adj. OIBA to $1.5-2.1 mln from $1-2 mln; call driven adj. EBITDA to $2.5-3.1 mln from $2-3 mln.
"The momentum continues to build in our business as we provide clear mobile measurement and deliver strong performance to our clients," said Russell Horowitz, Chairman and CEO of Marchex. "The combination of Marchex's ability to deliver high quality calls from our Call Marketplace combined with the insight we can deliver through our Call Analytics platform is helping us gain mindshare as a performance leader. We are excited about our progress as we start off the year and look forward to continuing to execute for our clients over the course of 2014."
Guidance reflect Marchex's expectations as of March 19, 2014 and exclude any contribution from Archeo operations, domain sales and discontinued operations and updates the guidance previously provided on February 19, 2014.
06:21
WIRES On The Wires
Forrester Research (FORR) launched a new Customer Experience Index for China at the Summit for Marketing & Strategy Professionals in Shanghai. PAREXEL International (PRXL) announced the expansion of its global Clinical Logistics Services capabilities. A new distribution center in Singapore and the recent expansion of the co's facilities in Billerica, Mass., will help PAREXEL more effectively manage clients' global clinical trial supply requirements.Multiquip chose Exa (EXA) to help them evaluate and reduce noise propagation from their containerized power generators.Ceragon Networks (CRNT) was selected to design and build a high-capacity wireless backbone for India's Oil and Natural Gas Corporation. The full turnkey project is valued at several million US dollars.Liberty Global (LBTYA) has selected Axiros to remotely provision and manage its customer premise equipment across a new B2B Voice over Internet service.CYREN (CYRN) signed a reseller agreement with eSafe Solutions LTD.
06:05
GRA W.R. Grace provides five-year financial framework; sets $2 bln adjusted free cash flow target at Investor Day (103.09 )
Co provides some targets in connection to its Investor Day. Some highlights include:
Sales and earnings growth from new product introductions, geographic expansion, and margin improvement
Adjusted Free Cash Flow projected to total over $2 billion through 2018
Share repurchases expected to increase total shareholder return
06:01
ENTG Entegris announced that it intends to raise $360 mln in gross proceeds through an offering of senior unsecured notes due 2022 (12.36 )
Co announced that it intends to raise $360 million in gross proceeds through an offering of senior unsecured notes due 2022. The net proceeds from the notes offering will be used to fund a portion of the purchase price for Entegris' previously announced proposed acquisition of ATMI, Inc. The consummation of the notes offering is subject to market and other conditions.
05:59
WIRES On The Wires
Celgene (CELG) reiterated its commitment to patients and their families with the announcement that it will focus significant resources to increase awareness and understanding of the disease. Key initiatives include a clinical study programme involving more than 4,800 patients, as well as investment in research partnerships, both of which can help to uncover innovative new treatment options and advance the understanding of the biology of the disease. Thomson Reuters (TRI) launched a new solution to support financial institutions and their clients to increase efficiency and reduce costs in complying with Know Your Customer requirements. Accelus Org ID was developed in partnership with leading financial institutions, corporations, asset managers and hedge funds and following discussions with nine regulators from key financial markets around the world. Nokia Solutions and Networks and ChinaCache International announced that they have signed a Memorandum of Understanding to incorporate ChinaCache's (CHII) innovative content delivery network technology into NSN's Liquid Applications solution. JDSU (JDSU) announced that Belgacom, a leading provider of telecommunications solutions in Belgium, has chosen to implement the JDSU ariesoGEO platform across its Proximus mobile networks in Belgium. Belgacom will use ariesoGEO to plan and optimize its 2G, 3G and LTE networks, to ensure an optimum VIP experience for its mobile users and to enhance management reporting and network visibility. Pantera Capital Management announced that the firm is focusing its investment advisory services exclusively on Bitcoin, other digital currencies and companies in the space. The firm also announced that Benchmark, Fortress Investment Group (FIG) and Ribbit Capital are acquiring an interest in Pantera Bitcoin Partners LLC. These shareholders and their principals will generally make their purchases of Bitcoin and other digital currencies via investments in Pantera. CNOOC (CEO) announced that the Company has recently made a new mid-sized gas discovery Lingshui17-2, which indicated the first breakthrough on the independent deepwater exploration in Qiongdongnan Basin of South China Sea.
05:56
RENN Renren beats by $0.40, beats on revs; guides Q1 revs below consensus (3.77 )
Reports Q4 (Dec) earnings of $0.28 per share, $0.40 better than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of ($0.12); revenues fell 11.3% year/year to $43.3 mln vs the $30.14 mln consensus.
Guidance:
Co issues downside guidance for Q1, sees Q1 revs of $23-25 mln vs. $30.41 mln Capital IQ Consensus Estimate.
03:57
WIRES On The Wires
The Volvo Group (VOLVY) introduced a UD bus range developed specifically for growth markets.OpenText (OTEX) announced the availability of its new Process Suite, enabling organizations to simplify complicated business and case automation processes around enterprise content management, customer engagement, information exchange, information discovery, and more.
02:34
BA Boeing expects the market for financing new aircraft to remain strong (124.04 )
Co provides an industry outlook at ISTAT forum. Co expects the market for financing new aircraft to remain strong as airline customers continue to demand for new, fuel-efficient airplanes.
Boeing said that airplane financing globally is experiencing a rare balance among primary delivery financing sources -- leasing companies, commercial banks, the capital markets, export credit agency (ECA) support and private equity and hedge funds among them -- as global 2014 deliveries head toward an expected roughly $112 billion total.Boeing noted that the overall healthy new-aircraft financing market encompasses well known financing sources and smaller regional commercial institutions, many entering aircraft financing for the first time.Commentary:
"There seems to good reason behind the softness. The key drivers are fuel prices, interest rates, environmental factors and market trends. The market has put a premium on new-airplane financing costs versus the secondary market. Intuitively the market is readjusting by valuing newness more and starting to rationalize pricing to help create a balanced reality as we move ahead."
02:14
WIRES On The Wires
Hittite Microwave (HITT) announced that it has entered into a definitive agreement to buy substantially all the assets of Keragis Corporation, a provider of extremely high power, wideband amplifier modules, located in San Diego, CA. The purchase price was not disclosed. First Solar (FSLR) and Shams Ma'an Power Generation announced the signing of a Power Purchase Agreement (PPA) for a planned 52.5 megawatt solar power plant in the Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan. The PPA was signed with the National Electric Power Company, the country's regulatory authority for power generation and distribution, and is valid for 20 years.
01:49
YY YY prices of $400 mln Convertible Senior Notes due 2019 (82.00 )
01:46
AMZG American Eagle Energy prices 11 mln shares of common stock at a price of $6.60 per share; reflective of 1-4 stock reverse stock split (1.76 )
Co announces it has priced an underwritten public offering of 11,000,000 shares of common stock at a price of $6.60 per share after giving effect to a 1-for-4 reverse stock split that occurred after the closing of the market yesterday afternoon and will be in effect as of the opening of the market and the commencement of trading on March 19, 2014.
01:39
NAV Navistar prices $370 mln of 4.75% senior subordinated convertible notes due 2019 (34.33 )
01:25
ORN Orion Marine plans to file 10K before expiration of extension period (April 1); does not anticipate any significant change in results (12.42 )
18:05
USCR U.S. Concrete acquires ready-mix assets for West Texas operations (23.88 +0.65)
Co announced that its wholly owned subsidiary, Ingram Concrete, LLC, has acquired the ready-mix assets of T&S Ventures, LLC, headquartered in Sweetwater, Texas.
18:04
STLD Steel Dynamics increases quarterly dividend 4.5% to $0.115 from $0.11 per share (16.93 +0.25)
18:03
STLD Steel Dynamics sees Q1 EPS of $0.13-0.17 vs $0.28 Capital IQ Consensus Estimate; cites extreme cold weather (16.93 +0.25)
Co provided first quarter 2014 earnings guidance in the range of $0.13 to $0.17 per diluted share (vs $0.28 Capital IQ Consensus Estimate).
The extreme cold weather across much of the United States, especially the Midwest, has had a significant negative impact on the company's first quarter 2014 financial results. The uncharacteristically severe and prolonged winter weather conditions have resulted in increased energy costs, diminished availability of transportation, reduced production and lower shipments. Profitability from the company's steel operations for the first quarter 2014 is expected to be lower in comparison to earnings achieved in the sequential fourth quarter 2013. Both shipments and metal spreads are expected to be lower in the first quarter 2014. Anticipated average quarterly product pricing is not expected to outpace increased scrap costs from material consumed early in the quarter. The weather has also negatively impacted production and sales for several key steel-consuming end markets, including automotive, construction and manufacturing. However, improvement in these end markets is anticipated as these consumers re-engage. In addition, order inquiry activity and resulting backlogs continue to improve at the company's fabrication operations.Metals recycling financial results are expected to show improvement for the first quarter 2014 when compared to the sequential quarter, as decreased ferrous metal margins are expected to be offset by modest increases in shipments.
18:01
TER Teradyne announces Unisem has selected and ordered the J750-LitePoint product for testing wireless connectivity semiconductor devices (19.84 +0.43)
17:36
FUL H.B. Fuller announces polymer emulsion price increase in North America (47.71 +1.41)
Co announced that, effective April 14, 2014, or as contracts allow, the North America Polymer group of H.B Fuller will increase the price for all vinyl acetate based emulsion polymer products. Vinyl acetate ethylene (VAE) copolymers, vinyl acrylics and PVAc homopolymers will increase by up to $0.03 USD per wet pound. This price increase includes the Elvace, Plyamul, Copro and PACE product brands. These increases affect applications sold in the U.S. and Canada, including but not limited to: adhesives, construction and building products, nonwovens, glass fiber, carpet and textile applications.
17:29
CWH CommonWealth REIT: Corvex Management and Related Fund Management announce that holders of over 81% of outstanding shares approve removal of entire Board of Trustees (26.81 -0.39)
Corvex Management and Related Fund Management, whose separately managed investment funds collectively own approximately 9.6% of the outstanding shares of CommonWealth REIT (CWH), announced that they have presented consents from holders of over 81% of the outstanding shares approving the proposal to remove the entire Board of Trustees of CommonWealth.
?Keith Meister of Corvex and Jeff T. Blau of Related, said: "The shareholders have exercised their rights and we look forward to working with the Trustees in the coming days to arrange for an orderly transition process that best protects the interests of all shareholders. We will immediately reach out to the Trustees to begin these discussions." Pursuant to the Interim Arbitration Award, CommonWealth has five business days, or until March 25, 2014, to have the written consents inspected and the results of the New Solicitation declared.
17:23
TAC Transalta announces executive leadership team appointments: Donald Tremblay to join as CFO (11.64 +0.10)
Co announced three senior leadership appointments that will enhance our objectives of operational excellence from the base business and growth.
Brett Gellner is appointed to the role of Chief Investment Officer, responsible for leading all growth aspects of the company. Mr. Gellner will also continue to be President of TransAlta Renewables Inc., which was established as a vehicle to grow long-term contracted assets.
Donald Tremblay will join TransAlta as Chief Financial Officer, effective March 31, 2014. Prior to accepting his new role at TransAlta, Mr. Tremblay held leadership positions at Brookfield Renewable Power, a $12-billion public company, as its Executive Vice President, Corporate Development and previously its Chief Financial Officer.
TransAlta is also announcing today that Mr. Wayne Collins will take on the leadership accountabilities of our Coal and Mining Operations.
17:04
PRTA Prothena announces clinical data to be presented at International Symposium on Amyloidosis (37.16 -0.35)
Co announced that an abstract (Abstract #PB-48) reviewing interim clinical data from its ongoing Phase 1 study of NEOD001 in patients with immunoglobulin light chain (AL) amyloidosis and persistent organ dysfunction will be presented at the XIV International Symposium on Amyloidosis (ISA) in Indianapolis, Indiana. Data in the abstract was current as of January 7, 2014. The poster presentation will include data from the ongoing Phase 1 study as of late March. Prothena is developing NEOD001, a humanized novel monoclonal antibody designed to neutralize and clear soluble and insoluble amyloid aggregates in patients with AL. NEOD001 is being studied in an ongoing Phase 1 study.
17:03
NSPH Nanosphere enters into $30 mln common stock purchase agreement with Aspire Capital (2.29 +0.12)
Co announced it has entered into a Common Stock Purchase Agreement with Aspire Capital Fund, LLC, whereby Nanosphere has the right to sell up to $30 million of shares of its common stock to Aspire Capital under certain conditions from time to time. Aspire Capital is an existing Nanosphere shareholder, having invested in the Company's most recent underwritten public offering in September 2013. Key aspects of the Purchase Agreement include:
Nanosphere will control the timing and amount of any sale of common stock to Aspire Capital, and will know the sale price before instructing Aspire Capital to purchase shares.Aspire Capital has no right to require sales by the Company, but is obligated to make purchases as the Company directs, in accordance with the terms of the Purchase Agreement.Aspire Capital shall not impose limitations on use of proceeds, financial covenants, restrictions on future financings, rights of first refusal, participation rights, penalties or liquidated damages. The Purchase Agreement may be terminated by Nanosphere at any time, at its discretion, without additional cost or penalty.
17:02
WPX WPX Energy announces CFO Rod Sailor will resign from the company to accept another position; J. Kevin Vann named interim CFO (18.18 +0.51)
Co announced that Senior Vice President and Chief Financial Officer Rod Sailor will resign from the company effective March 31 to accept a position at another company. The Board of Directors appointed J. Kevin Vann, who serves as the company's Vice President, Controller and Chief Accounting Officer, to be interim Senior Vice President and Chief Financial Officer. Vann will also replace Sailor as director for Apco Oil and Gas International.
16:57
PDCO Patterson Companies increases quarterly dividend 25% to $0.20 from $0.16 per share (41.79 +0.24)
16:32
PMFG PMFG Inc agrees to acquire Combustion Components Associates for ~$8.9 mln (7.00 +0.16)
Co announced it has reached a definitive agreement to acquire substantially all of the assets of Combustion Components Associates, a provider of in-furnace and post-combustion control technologies. The acquisition is subject to customary closing conditions and is expected to close by April 30, 2014. The purchase price is approximately $8.9 million in cash plus performance-based contingent payments and will be funded with cash on hand.
Located in Monroe, Connecticut, CCA is an industry leader in combustion control technologies used to reduce NOx, particulate matter (PM), unburned carbon and CO emissions at variety of facilities including utility power plants, paper & pulp mills, chemical plants, oil refineries, and ethanol plants. CCA employs approximately 30 employees and had 2013 revenue of approximately $14 million. As of November 30, 2013, CCA's order backlog was approximately $3 million.
16:31
CBOE CBOE Holdings announces certain officers enter into 10b5-1 plan (57.10 -1.51)
Co announced that certain officers of the company have each established pre-arranged share disposition plans with a brokerage firm under Rule 10b5-1 of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934, as amended.
William J. Brodsky, Executive Chairman of the Board -- plan authorizes the sale of up to 50,000 shares over the next three months, representing approximately 14 percent of his total holdings; Edward T. Tilly, Chief Executive Officer -- plan authorizes the sale of up to 25,000 shares over the next 12 months, representing approximately 14 percent of his total holdings;David S. Reynolds, Chief Accounting Officer -- plan authorizes the sale of up to 6,000 shares over the next three months.
16:30
GSS Golden Star Resources announces resignation of CFO Jeff Swinoga and promotion of Andre van Niekerk to CFO (0.71 )
Co announced that Jeff Swinoga, Executive Vice President and Chief Financial Officer has resigned from the co to pursue other opportunities. The Board of Directors has appointed Andre van Niekerk, Vice President and Controller as the co's new Executive Vice President and Chief Financial Officer. Jeff has agreed to remain with the co to assist in the CFO transition until early April 2014.
16:30
ORCL Oracle earnigns follow up: ORCL -5% in after hours after missing Q3 earnings estimates (38.84 +0.62)
Q3 non-GAAP EPS was $0.68 vs. the $0.70 Capital IQ Consensus... Excluding the impact of the US dollar strengthening compared to foreign currencies and excluding Venezuela's exchange loss impact on both reporting periods, Oracle's reported Q3 non-GAAP earnings per share would have been $0.71, up 8%.
Our original comment as been edited.
16:24
WRAPX Closing Market Summary: Stocks and Treasuries End Near Highs
The major averages finished the Tuesday session with solid gains, but outside of a few pockets of considerable relative strength, most sectors could be classified as reluctant participants in the daylong rally. Small caps led the way with the Russell 2000 climbing 1.5% while the S&P 500 advanced 0.7% with nine sectors posting gains.
This morning, equity indices were on track for a lower start to the session, but that changed in a hurry when comments from Russian President Vladimir Putin began making the rounds. Although Mr. Putin did not provide any groundbreaking insight, European markets and equity futures rallied when he said Russia does not want to see a break-up of Ukraine.
The comments also gave a boost to risk sentiment in the foreign exchange market, sending the dollar/yen pair from a morning low of 101.33 to 101.80. Interestingly, the yen weakness was short-lived as the currency pair slid to a fresh session low (101.29) over the next five hours while equity indices built on their opening gains thanks to the outperformance of three heavily-weighted sectors-energy (+0.8%), health care (+1.2%), and technology (+1.4%)-that account for just a shade over 41.0% of the entire S&P 500.
The energy sector drew strength from Dow component Chevron (CVX 116.24, +1.17), which gained 1.0%, while also receiving a boost from the 1.7% gain in crude oil ($99.69/bbl).
Elsewhere, the health care sector was underpinned by companies specializing in biotechnology. The iShares Nasdaq Biotechnology ETF (IBB 262.22, +6.75) surged 2.6%, which also factored into the outperformance of the tech-heavy Nasdaq Composite.
Speaking of the Nasdaq, the index got a big boost from shares of Microsoft (MSFT 39.55, +1.50), which rallied 3.9% in reaction to widespread reports indicating the company will release its Office suite for the Apple (AAPL 531.40, +4.66) iPad.
Strikingly, outside of the three influential sectors, the remaining groups could never catch up with the broader market. Most notably, the financial sector (+0.5%) lagged throughout the session, ending behind most of the remaining growth-sensitive groups.
On the countercyclical side, health care was the only outperformer while consumer staples (+0.2%), utilities (-0.2%), and telecom services (+0.66%) lagged.
Treasuries erased their overnight gains in reaction to the comments from Vladimir Putin, but spent the session in a climb towards the early highs. The benchmark 10-yr yield ended at 2.67% after starting the New York session just north of 2.69%.
Despite the mixed sentiment signals emanating from the foreign exchange, Treasury, and stock markets, participants did not show much demand for volatility protection as indicated by the 7.2% decline in the CBOE Volatility Index (VIX 14.52, -1.12).
Trading volume was on the light side for the second day in a row with only 574 million shares changing hands at the NYSE floor.
Today's economic data included the February Housing Starts and Building Permits report and February CPI:
Housing starts fell 0.2% in February to 907,000 from an upwardly revised 909,000 (from 880,000) in January. The Briefing.com consensus expected housing starts to increase to 915,000. After two months where starts surpassed one million, construction levels in January and February returned to their April - October 2013 pace. There wasn't much evidence of significant shocks from winter weather conditions. Building Permits rose to a seasonally adjusted annualized rate of 1,018,000, which was better than the Briefing.com consensus estimate of 955,000. Consumer prices edged up 0.1% in February after increasing 0.2% in January. The Briefing.com consensus expected the CPI to increase 0.2%. Energy costs, which provided a sizable boost to the PPI, fell 0.5% in February. A 1.7% decline in gasoline prices offset a 3.6% increase in natural gas costs. Food price growth, which had been very low and stable for the past several months, shot up 0.5% in February. That was the largest one-month increase since September 2011. Most of the food components rose more than their long-term trends. That included a 1.2% increase in meats, poultry, fish, and eggs. Excluding food and energy, core CPI increased 0.1% for a third consecutive month in February. That was exactly what the consensus expected. Tomorrow, the weekly MBA Mortgage Index will be released at 7:00 ET while the fourth quarter current account balance (Briefing.com consensus -$87.60 billion) will be announced at 8:30 ET. Also of note, the Federal Open Market Committee will conclude its two-day meeting with the latest policy statement scheduled to be released at 14:00 ET. The statement will be followed by Janet Yellen's first press conference as Fed Chair, scheduled to begin at 14:30 ET.
Russell 2000 +3.8% YTD Nasdaq Composite +3.8% YTD S&P 500 +1.3% YTD Dow Jones Industrial Average -1.5% YTD
16:24
RCKB Rockville Financial and United Financial Bancorp (UBNK) receive regulatory approvals for merger (13.79 +0.05)
Rockville Financial, Inc. and United Financial Bancorp, Inc. have now secured approvals from four of the five regulators they submitted applications to, including the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System and the Connecticut Department of Banking. The Office of the Comptroller of Currency also informed both Companies that it does not intend to make any comments on the notice filed with it. The Massachusetts Board of Bank Incorporation application is still pending. Both United and Rockville have scheduled their respective special shareholder meetings for April 8, 2014 when shareholders will be asked to give their final approval of the merger.
16:20
SCTY SolarCity beats by $0.10, beats on revs; guides Q1 EPS below consensus (77.10 +3.40)
Reports Q4 (Dec) loss of $0.46 per share, excluding non-recurring items, $0.10 better than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of ($0.56); reports pre-announced revenues of $47.3 mln (Up 99% YoY).
Co issues downside guidance for Q1, sees EPS of $(0.80)-(0.70), excluding non-recurring items, vs. ($0.49) Capital IQ Consensus Estimate.Co reported preannoucned significant growth in its core business in 2013 with MW Deployed up 78% Y/Y to 280 MW and operating lease revenue growth of 80% Y/Y for the full year Co reports pre-announced Q1 MW deployed of between 78-82 MW, up 74% year-over-year at the midpoint and consistent with its targets for the yearCo reports pre-annuounced guidance for MW deployed of between 475-525 MW. We also continue to expect to generate positive cash flow for the full year 2014
16:20
NHI Natl Hlth Investors announces $175 mln offering of convertible senior notes due 2021 (61.47 +0.51)
Co announced today it has commenced an underwritten public offering of $175 million aggregate principal amount of Convertible Senior Notes due 2021. NHI intends to use the net proceeds from the offering to reduce amounts outstanding under its revolving credit facility and for general working capital purposes. BofA Merrill Lynch and J.P. Morgan are the joint book-running managers for the offering.
16:15
VCYT Veracyte misses by $0.04, beats on revs; guides FY14 revs in-line
Reports Q4 (Dec) loss of $0.42 per share, $0.04 worse than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of ($0.38); revenues rose 53.4% year/year to $6.84 mln vs the $6.43 mln consensus.
Co issues in-line guidance for FY14, sees FY14 revs of $38-43 mln vs. $39.78 mln Capital IQ Consensus Estimate; sees FNA volumes of 76,000 to 83,000.
"We experienced strong revenue gains in 2013, driven by growing physician adoption of our Afirma Thyroid FNA Analysis, combined with increased payer coverage and reimbursement for our Afirma Gene Expression Classifier (GEC). We saw increases in fine needle aspiration (FNA) sample volumes and cash collections during the fourth quarter, which is traditionally our strongest quarter. We look forward to accelerating growth in 2014, primarily through additional payer coverage decisions for our GEC and expansion of our sales force. In May, we plan to commercially launch our new Afirma Malignancy Classifiers, which are currently in the pilot stage at select sites, to further enhance our Afirma offering. We are also on track in advancing product development efforts for our next clinical indication in pulmonology."
16:14
ORC Orchid Island Capital announces public offering of 4 mln shares of common stock (12.92 +0.06)
Co announced today that it has commenced a public offering of 4,000,000 shares of its common stock. All of the shares in the public offering are being offered by the Company. Ladenburg Thalmann & Co. Inc., a subsidiary of Ladenburg Thalmann Financial Services is the book running manager for the offering.
16:12
CHMI Cherry Hill Mortgage increases quarterly dividend 11.1% to $0.50 from $0.45 per share (18.27 +0.02)
16:10
PDCO Patterson Companies increases quarterly dividend by 25% to $0.20 per share from $0.16 per share (41.76 +0.21)
16:10
ADBE Adobe Systems beats by $0.05, beats on revs; numbers leaked out earlier (68.52 +0.35)
Reports Q1 (Feb) earnings of $0.30 per share, excluding non-recurring items, $0.05 better than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of $0.25; revenues fell 0.8% year/year to $1 bln vs the $973.09 mln consensus.
16:08
PSUN Pacific Sunwear reports Q4 results, issues Q1 guidance (3.00 +0.18)
Reports Q4 (Jan) loss of $0.17 per share, $0.02 in line with ($0.21)-(0.18) guidance and the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of ($0.19); revenues fell 1.9% year/year to $218.6 mln vs. $211-214 mln guidance on Jan 9 and vs the $212.73 mln consensus. Comparable store sales for the fourth quarter of fiscal 2013 increased 2%
Co issues mixed guidance for Q1, sees EPS of ($0.17)-($0.12) vs. ($0.12) Capital IQ Consensus Estimate; sees Q1 revs of $169-174 mln vs. $168.56 mln Capital IQ Consensus Estimate. Sees Q1 comparable store sales from 1% to 4%; Gross margin rate, including buying, distribution and occupancy, of 25% to 27%.
16:05
BRX Brixmor Property closes $600 mln five-year unsecured term loan (21.48 -0.34)
Co announced that it has closed on a new $600 mln unsecured term loan facility. The term loan facility has a five-year term maturing on March 18, 2019 and will bear interest at a rate per annum equal to, at the co's option, the base rate or LIBOR, plus an applicable margin based on the co's total leverage ratio. The initial interest rate will be a rate per annum equal to LIBOR plus 1.45% based on the co's total leverage ratio of 45.6%. The term loan facility has an accordion feature allowing the co to borrow up to an additional $250 mln, for a total commitment of up to $850 mln. The co has the ability to prepay the term loan under the facility without premium or penalty any time prior to maturity. Proceeds from the term loan facility will be used to pay-down outstanding balances under the co's $1.25 billion revolving credit facility, which had been utilized to repay maturing indebtedness, a substantial portion of which was secured mortgages.
16:05
ASBC Assoc Banc-Corp announces $120 mln share repurchase program, shelf registration for future acquisitions, and lifting of consent order (17.68 +0.01)
ASBC has authorized the repurchase of up to $120 million of Associated's common stock.
This repurchase authorization is in addition to the previously authorized common stock repurchase program announced on July 23, 2013. There remains approximately $56 million under the previous authorization after Associated's repurchase of approximately $39 million of common stock this quarter. The amount of common stock repurchased in this quarter as compared to recent quarters reflects Associated's efforts to neutralize the effect of equity grants pursuant to its compensation plans. The Board also approved the filing of a shelf registration statement with the Securities and Exchange Commission for up to $500 million of common stock to be issued from time to time in connection with certain future business combinations. Associated has no immediate plans to utilize such registration statement for an acquisition transaction.
16:02
TXMD TherapeuticsMD announces launch of secondary public offering of 9 mln shares of its common stock by selling stockholders (7.97 +0.23)
Co announced the launch of an underwritten secondary public offering of 9,000,000 shares of its common stock. All shares will be offered by the selling stockholders, including certain members of management of the Company and certain of their affiliates. The Company will not sell any shares or receive any proceeds from the offering.Jefferies LLC and Stifel are acting as joint book-running managers for the offering, and Cowen and Company, LLC and Mizuho Securities USA Inc. are acting as co-managers for the offering.
16:02
RBCN Rubicon Tech announces proposed public offering of common stock by selling shareholders (14.11 +0.32)
Canaccord Genuity Inc. is acting as sole book-running manager for the offering. Co will not receive any proceeds from the sale of common stock by selling stockholders.
]]></text></news-item>