<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-15B1-F0J6-J3TC"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Sinodinos must fully explain what he knew, and when</title><source>Sydney Morning Herald (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Assistant Treasurer Arthur Sinodinos has contributed much to the public service, business and government.
But ministerial duties on economic and corporate reform require focus and public trust. To that end the decision of Senator Sinodinos to step aside from the Abbott ministry is most welcome.
Still, if Prime Minister Tony Abbott believes stepping aside was honourable and in the best Westminster tradition, it should have happened much earlier. Senator Sinodinos should remain on the backbench until both inquiries ito Australian Water Holdings by the Independent Commission Against Corruption remove any shadow of doubt about his role as a director and then chairman of the company.
AWH has been linked to disgraced former NSW Labor minister Eddie Obeid. It is accused of corruption in dealings with the NSW government and making spurious political donations. In effect, the water bills of NSW households and businesses ended up in Liberal coffers.
Since the Herald revealed in December 2012 that Senator Sinodinos had served concurrently on the AWH board and as a senior officeholder of the NSW Liberal Party, he has allowed public trust in him to be eroded.
Through opacity and prevarication, he has failed to fully explain his role at AWH.
As chief of staff to former prime minister John Howard, the now Liberal senator is well aware it is vital ministers do not by their conduct undermine public confidence in them or the government.
Both sides played cynical games over Senator Sinodinos on Wednesday. The Senate descended ito what he might call a "sideshow". The upper house should be focused on more important work. So should the government - and that is not possible while doubts linger.
Rather than dodging on AWH, he should have been convincing the public about his attack on red tape, finding fair ways to tackle the deficit and trying to show why his plans to wind back financial advice reforms are not just a blank cheque for big financial firms and a costly blow to consumers.
Now he has done the right thing by stepping aside, Senator Sinodinos should make a detailed statement to Parliament about AWH to clear the air. The ICAC is unlikely to pursue issues of ministerial standards or political party networks.
Earlier this week he refused to step aside, insisting instead he stood by a statement he made in the Senate more than a year ago, before he was sworn in as Assistant Treasurer.
Senator Sinodinos claimed then that he had played no role in the "awarding" of a January 2012 contract with Sydney Water for AWH to provide water infrastructure in Sydney's north-west. He said he did not know when he was at AWH of the Obeids' shareholding in AWH - allegedly a 30 per cent stake acquired for $3 million through a so-called sham loan. Senator Sinodinos said he did not recall talking about political donations while at AWH as they were "handled by management of the organisation at their discretion".
Nonetheless, it has emerged that the ICAC has heard Senator Sinodinos wrote to the NSW Premier about a contractual relationship between AWH and Sydney Water in 2011 and was at a meeting on the issue soon after. The commission heard the resulting contract delivered AWH money which was claimed from Sydney Water as expenses then donated to the Liberal Party. A $30,000 donation was made a month after Senator Sinodinos became AWH chairman. It has heard Senator Sinodinos had tried to open lines of communication with the Liberals.
What's more, the ICAC has been told Senator Sinodinos stood to gain up to $20 million if AWH had secured the Obeids' favoured private public partnership with the O'Farrell government. In addition, ICAC documents show Senator Sinodinos was involved in negotiations to sell a $15 million stake in AWH to investors involved in a secret deal with the Obeid family.
There is nothing wrong with a relationship between a company, its board and a political party - unless there is corruption and people knew. If they did not know, why not?
There is no allegation of wrongdoing against Senator Sinodinos; just questions.
He must explain himself and remain on the backbench until he is vindicated. Then he can return to cabinet as a more effective minister.
]]></text></news-item>