<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-B3K1-F09T-F4GD"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Crack in idle Phillips 66 pipeline spews crude oil onto Wilmington streets</title><source>Press - Telegram (Long Beach California)</source><author>Sandy Mazza</author><text><![CDATA[A crack in an idle Phillips 66 oil pipeline, possibly caused by this week's 4.4-magnitude earthquake, spewed thousands of gallons of crude oil onto a residential street in Wilmington, officials said Tuesday.
Residents in the 1200 block of North Neptune Avenue reported the foul-smelling, dark liquid oozing out of fissures in the street late Monday afternoon, prompting a response from the Los Angeles City Fire Department and county Fire Department hazardous materials units. Phillips 66 officials suspected the pipeline may have been one of theirs, and took over the cleanup Tuesday.
They didn't find the cause of the leak until late Tuesday afternoon, after vacuuming out 70 barrels of oil from the area, fire officials said.
"After a thorough investigation of the source, we can confirm the leak is coming from an idle pipeline owned by Phillips 66," said Monica Silva, a spokeswoman for the oil company. "We are working to stop the leak and have recovered approximately 30 barrels of oil. Clean-up efforts continue."
Silva declined to elaborate on why the unused 10-inch pipeline was filled with crude oil.
County Hazardous Materials Specialist Don Miguel Ellis said that, though the oil seeped into nearby soil, it isn't expected to affect groundwater reserves or create any other major environmental concerns. The only human health impacts were some nearby residents complaining of headaches from the foul-smelling raw crude, and the inconvenience created by street closures, Ellis said.
Normally, when a pipeline is not being used, oil companies will fill it with concrete slurry. However, if they think they may want to use the line again, they try to keep it viable. In this case, the oil may have been stored in the line to keep it from corroding or collapsing, fire officials said. Silva said oil company officials will not say more about the issue until Wednesday.
"A unified command with local authorities has been established and Phillips 66 crews are on site and working to minimize impact to the community," Silva said in a written statement. "As a precaution, we also are monitoring the air quality. The health and safety of our communities is important to us."
Rep. Janice Hahn, D-San Pedro, visited the site on Tuesday out of "concern for the safety and well-being of the residents of Wilmington," she said in a statement. "The harsh, crude oil smell is not only horrible, but can also be potentially harmful to the neighborhood residents and environment."
"As a member of the House Transportation and Infrastructure Subcommittee on Railroads, Pipelines and Hazardous Materials, I plan to make this oil spill incident a priority," Hahn said. "I have already reached out to the subcommittee to find out what federal actions we can take to ensure that an incident like this will not happen again, and that there is proper oversight with our nation's pipelines.
"We have to protect the residents of Wilmington and the environment from the risks of hazardous materials transportation."
The pipeline, which is not a main line, stretches along Neptune Avenue from the border of Carson, at Lomita Boulevard, to the southernof Wilmington at G Street, according to Ellis.
"It was quasi-abandoned, so they don't use it but they don't close it out completely because they may use it again," Ellis said. "It probably would have been the right thing to do to evacuate the line from product. (They may have left oil in it) to keep it from corroding because a lot of these lines are old already and, if they abandon it, it corrodes. It's not proven, but (the leak) could have had something to do with the earthquake because it was discovered at 4:30 p.m. Monday."
Ellis said that Phillips 66 officials were developing a plan Tuesday afternoon to remove the rest of the oil and clean and repair the area.
"It's a significant spill in a public area," Ellis said. "But health risks are minimal."
]]></text></news-item>