<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-MSW1-DYN2-329G"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>EDF 'withheld information about Dungeness nuclear shutdown'</title><source>guardian.co.uk</source><author>Terry Macalistertheguardian.com</author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
EDF has failed to be open and transparent by shutting down its Dungeness plant in Kent for two months without properly informing people, environmentalists have said.
The energy company put a one-line statement on its website in May last year saying unit 22 at Dungeness station had been taken offline on 20 May for maintenance work that included completing improvements to flood defences for extreme events.
Yet five months earlier, EDF had privately admitted to the industry's watchdog, the Office of Nuclear Regulation (ONR), that the shingle bank between the reactors and the sea was "not as robust as previously thought", according to the environmental website ClickGreen.
A review of flood defences followed the Fukushima disaster in Japan, which raised global concerns about the vulnerability of atomic power stations in coastal areas.
British environmentalists have long warned that rising sea levels owing to global warming represent a threat to power stations including Sizewell, off the coast of Suffolk.
The UK nuclear sector, born in the days of the cold war, has a reputation for secrecy. It had promised to be more open in future, but EDF put out a more detailed statement on what it had been doing in Kent only on Wednesday, after media reports on the shutdown.
It went on to quote Martin Pearson, station director at Dungeness B, as insisting that all was well: "The power station has operated normally in the recent high tides and stormy weather."
Doug Parr, policy director of Greenpeace, said it was deeply worrying that the French company, which wants to build a new power station at Hinkley Point in Somerset, "does not feel the need to tell the wider community about serious safety worries over flooding".
The nuclear industry often boasts that it provides almost permanent electricity, unlike many renewables, which function only when the wind blows or the sun shines.
But the older UK plants have often been regularly offline because of sustained need for maintenance or breakdowns. At Oskarshamn, in south-east Sweden, one of the world's largest nuclear reactors shut down five months ago after jellyfish clogged up pipes that bring cool water into the plant's turbines.
John Sauven, executive director of Greenpeace, predicted that as the impacts of climate change took effect Britain would see more incidents of extreme weather, with nuclear power stations along the UK's coastline facing increasing dangers of flooding.
He said: "The added costs of protecting the UK's ageing nuclear stock makes the case for nuclear expansion increasingly expensive, with UK taxpayers having to carry the risks."
]]></text></news-item>