<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-PP51-DY15-S2KM"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Agang SA Submits Election Lists to the Independent Electoral Commission [press release]</title><source>Agang South Africa</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Agang SA's National Assembly candidate list features a top ten that is designed to demonstrate a leadership that is best able to fight corruption, provide leadership to the country, and take the party's manifesto and plan to build a winning South Africa to voters across the country.
"I am particularly pleased that the Agang SA list of candidates for the national assembly features a number of individuals who have shown their mettle in the fight against corruption that is threatening to bring this country to its knees and is stealing resources from those who them most," says Ramphele.
"I am extremely pleased to announce that well-known and respected forensic consultant, Paul O'Sullivan has joined Agang SA and is on our national assembly list," says Ramphele.
O'Sullivan has more than 37 years' experience in law-enforcement, including diverse areas such as counter-espionage, counter-terrorism, counter trafficking (drugs, weapons and human), as well local law-enforcement, including syndicated crime, such as fraud, robbery and murder. He is also one of the world's leading security experts.
He worked on cases that brought Jackie Selebi, former head of Interpol and the South African Police Service, and Radovan Krejcir, to book.
O'Sullivan will be joining a number of candidates with a legal background, including John McConnachie, Andrew Gasnolar, and Mike Tshishonga who, as a former deputy director-general of justice, fought against and exposed, corruption in the liquidations industry as well as the South African justice system itself.
"In addition to fighting corruption, we need to work with citizens to take back our country and build South Africa into a winning nation. To achieve that, we need to be open to the voices of people, to understand them, to be among them," says Ramphele. The candidate lists are representative of the various demographics of the country, drawing from the volunteers who have helped build Agang into the party they are proud of today. The lists are gender-balanced, and draw from a variety of experience, cultures, and backgrounds.
"We have talented young leaders like Nyameka Mguzulo, who has come to us from the African National Congress Youth League and Andrew Gasnolar, who is an admitted attorney and a World Economic Form Global Shaper, among other accolades. We have candidates who have served their communities for years, like Andries Tlouamma and Johanne Mphogo, and we have experience drawn from the corporate world in Garth Towell, and from successful entrepreneurship, like Angela Pitsi,"says Ramphele.
According to Ramphele, the Agang SA candidates list represents all the experience, gender, skills and commitments required to turn the country around.
"I wish to thank each of the candidates who have put themselves forward for election and are willing to serve the country when it needs active and responsible citizens the most. We are a party with no political baggage, with a clear record free of corruption, and with a plan to turn our beloved country around through our plan to bring real change to the citizens of the country through the five E's - empowerment, education, entrepreneurship, employment, and effective government., says Ramphele.
"We are excited, just one year after announcing the formation of our party, to be able to put such strong lists of candidates before voters in this election year," concludes Ramphele.
]]></text></news-item>