<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-YM01-JCB7-1002"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>This Week in W.Va. History</title><source>Charleston Gazette (West Virginia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[March 19, 1925: Basketball teams from 11 of West Virginia's 24 African-American high schools took the court at West Virginia State College (now University) in Institute for the first West Virginia Athletic Union state basketball tournament. Lincoln High School of Wheeling defeated Kimball, 25-24, in the final game to win the championship.
March 19, 1992: Four miners were killed at the Blacksville No. 1 mine in Monongalia County while the mine was being sealed. Drainage pipes were being welded together, and a spark fell into the shaft, igniting methane gas.
March 20, 1936: Recurring storms led to major flooding on the Ohio River. At Parkersburg, the river reached 48 feet, 10 feet above flood stage.
March 21, 1914: The West Virginia boys high school basketball tournament began in Buckhannon. The event was first sponsored by West Virginia Wesleyan College, which, at the time, had West Virginia's largest and finest gymnasium.
March 22, 1922: Physician Mildred Mitchell-Bateman was born in Georgia. She became the first black woman in West Virginia to hold a high-level state administrative position when, in 1962, Gov. William Wallace Barron appointed her as the director of the Department of Mental Health.
March 23, 2003: Private Jessica Lynch of Palestine, Wirt County, was serving as a supply clerk with the Army's 507th Maintenance Company when she was captured by Iraqi forces after her group was ambushed.
March 24, 1890: Confederate Gen. William Lowther Mudwall" Jackson died in Louisville. Jackson, who was born in Clarksburg, joined the Confederate Army as a private. After helping to organize an infantry unit, he was promoted to colonel. He served on the staff of his cousin, Gen. Thomas J. Stonewall" Jackson, and was jokingly nicknamed Mudwall."
Submitted by the West Virginia Humanities Council
]]></text></news-item>