<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-TKR1-DXKH-N51C"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>TeliaSonera increases</title><source>News Bites - Nordic: Finland</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TeliaSonera (HEL:TLS1V), Finland's largest telecommunication company by market capitalisation, increased 2.0c (or 0.4%) to close at EUR5.49. Compared with the OMX Helsinki 25 Index which fell 21.6 points (or 0.8%) in the day, this represented a relative price increase of 1.1%. The volume was 0.9 times the average trading of 966,036 shares. The stock rose for a third day on Wednesday bringing its three-day rise to 16.0c or 3.0%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on TeliaSonera, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051121530314146
Bullish SignalsFundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price to Book of 8.1 [9.4].Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 3.9 is comfortably below 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 14.6%. - Interest cover defined by EBIT/I is 6.3 times. This indicates it is less leveraged. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.9. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- Revenue growth has shown signs of recovery in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]
- Net Profit margin is positive and has seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteBeta: the Beta of TeliaSonera stock is 0.7. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market. - TeliaSonera is at a discount of 11.7% to its 12-month high of EUR6.22 on 28 Oct, 2013. It is also at a premium of 14.6% to the 12-month low of EUR4.79 on 24 Jun, 2013. - The present value of EUR1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in TeliaSonera is EUR1,068, including a capital gain of EUR4 and dividend reinvested of EUR65.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Parity:- Price/Earnings of 14.5 [14.9]. - Price/Sales of 2.1 [2.2]. - Return on Capital Employed 8.4% [9.1%].- Price to EBITDA of 6.1 [6.2].Bearish Signals:- The price decreased 1.1% in the last month. The stock has been exacerbated by firm volume of 1.2 times average for the month.
AGGREGATE VOLUMES, PRICES AND TURNOVER PERIOD [Volume Index or VI in brackets; 1 is average] Stockholm: TLSN.STO 9,600,000 [VI of 1.1] volume 99.934% of aggregate. Price: SEK48.46. Frankfurt: TLS.FRA 6,371 [VI of 1.1] volume 0.066% of aggregate. Price: EUR5.46. Aggregate volume: there were 9.6 million shares of TeliaSonera worth EUR52.8 million traded. The aggregate volume was 1.1 times average trading of 9.1 million shares.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 17: Update on investigations of TeliaSonera's investments in Uzbekistan[News Story] TeliaSonera has been informed that the U.S. Department of Justice (DOJ) has an ongoing investigation regarding TeliaSonera's transactions in Uzbekistan. The DOJ has sent a request for documents to TeliaSonera. In addition, TeliaSonera has received a request from the U.S.
March 10: TeliaSonera: Information about court case concerning Kcell in Kazakhstan[News Story] TeliaSonera's subsidiary in Kazakhstan, Kcell Joint Stock Company, today released the following announcement: Court of the first instance ruled in favor of the Agency for Competition Protection of the Republic of Kazakhstan in the court case against the Company. For further information (http://www.investors.kcell.kz/en/news/show/2412?navipageId=1191).Source:NASDAQ OMX
March 10: TeliaSonera acquires AinaCom's consumer operations and fixed networks[News Story] Sonera, the Finnish arm of TeliaSonera, has signed an agreement to acquire AinaCom's consumer operations and fixed networks. The agreement strengthens Sonera's position on the Finnish market. In total, the price of the arrangement is EUR 47 million on a cash and debt-free basis.AinaCom's consumer operations include around 15,900 fixed broadband and 9,000 fixed voice subscriptions, 29,000 cable-tv subscriptions and 10,000 mobile subscriptions."With the agreement, Sonera strengthens its position in the Hameenlinna region while also deepening its cooperation with AinaCom's remaining B2B business.
February 20: TeliaSonera announces AGMTeliaSonera has announced its Annual General Meeting will take place on April 02, 2014.
February 14: TeliaSonera: Helene Barnekow appointed Chief Commercial OfficerHelene Barnekow has been appointed Senior Vice President and Chief Commercial Officer to lead the Group Commercial function in TeliaSonera's new organization to be launched April 1. Helene Barnekow will be responsible to maximize commercial capabilities and be part of TeliaSonera Group Management.
February 11: TeliaSonera AB issues a 5 year Eurobond of EUR 500 million[News Story] TeliaSonera today issued a Eurobond of EUR 500 million in a 5 year deal maturing in February 2019, under its existing EUR 11 billion EMTN (Euro Medium Term Note) program. The Re-offer yield was set at 1.483 percent p.a. equivalent to Euro Mid -swaps + 45 bp."We continue to take advantage of opportunities in the Eurobond market and are pleased to have successfully issued another bond to an attractive yield", says Christian Luiga, CFO of TeliaSonera.The Joint Bookrunners mandated by TeliaSonera for this transaction were BNP, Citi, SEB and Danske Bank.TeliaSonera AB discloses the information provided herein pursuant to the Swedish Securities Markets Act and/or the Swedish Financial Instrument Trading Act.
February 10: Sonera in Finland reaches agreement with Finnish mobile operators on new interconnection fee[News Story] Sonera, TeliaSonera's Finnish operation has reached an agreement with other Finnish mobile operators on the new mobile interconnection fee The operators have had symmetrical interconnection fees since December 2009. The current fee is 2.8 cents/min.The new interconnection fee is 1.87 cents/min for 1.9.2014 - 30.11.2015.Source:NASDAQ OMX
ISIN: SE0000667925
HE:TLS1V; HEL:TLS1V; FH:TLS1V
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>