<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSH-TGF1-JCPJ-W2B8"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Private tests show arsenic seeping at Duke Energy's Cliffside plant</title><source>Charlotte Business Journal</source><author>John Downey</author><text><![CDATA[An environmental group says water seeping into the Broad River near an inactive ash pond at Duke Energy's Cliffside Steam Station shows elevated levels of arsenic, manganese and other metals commonly found in coal ash.
The Waterkeeper Alliance has also raised questions about corroded metal pipes at the site and whether they run beneath the inactive pond. A metal stormwater pipe under a Duke ash pond on the Dan River broke Feb. 2 and spewed up to 39,000 tons of coal ash into the river.
Duke stands by earlier statements that the Dan River plant is the only one in the state that had pipes running under an ash pond.
Seepage sites
French Broad Riverkeeper Hartwell Carson, an associate of the alliance, says one water sample he took March 10 at Cliffside showed arsenic levels coming from one seepage site showed arsenic levels 27 times higher than state drinking-water standards.
A sample from seepage a few hundred feet downriver showed arsenic levels twice the drinking-water standard, he says.
Carson says the samples came from the sites of the seepage, not from the river. He acknowledges the levels would be diluted in the stream.
And drinking-water standards apply to water that has been processed for drinking, not water coming from plant sites.
But Carson says the seepages are not permitted under Duke's discharge permit for Cliffside. And he says there were as many as a dozen other seepages from the river bank where he collected the first sample.
Susan Massengale, a spokeswoman from the N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources, says the state performed a rigorous inspection at Cliffside on March 13 and 14.
DENR inspectors took more than two dozen water samples from the site and the surrounding area, she says. They include six from seepages along the bank of the river and 12 from the stream of the river, where dilution has taken place.
She says DENR does not have the test results yet.
Duke spokeswoman Paige Sheehan says regular testing of the river water, which Duke has been doing since 2010, shows no environmental problems.
"Monitoring in the Broad River for trace elements show levels are consistently well within surface water quality standards," she says "The volume of ash basin seepage is extremely small and is not impacting water quality in the river."
The inactive pond used to serve four small coal Cliffside units that Duke retired in 2011. The pond has largely been drained of water, although water from elsewhere on the site does drain into it.
The DENR inspection last week was part of its plans to do new and intensive inspections at Duke's 14 operating and retired coal plants across North Carolina. That effort is part of DENR's response to the Dan River spill.
DENR expects to finish those inspections by Friday. Massengale says that with dozens of water samples being tested at all the sites, it may be several weeks before the test results at Cliffside - or any specific plant - are available.
She says they will be made public as soon as the results are confirmed.
Even if toxins are found in the water testing, DENR must decide whether the seeping water violates Duke's discharge permit.
Samples taken from a discharge on the Dan River upstream from the principal spill tested positive for arsenic, aluminum and other heavy metal commonly found in coal ash.
But DENR decided in that case that the discharge was not a violation.
Questions remain about the pipes.
Carson says corrugated metal pipes at the dam for the inactive ash pond are oozing reddish brown material down the bank to the river. He did not test material from the pipes, he says, because he did not want to trespass on Duke's property.
"But it is hard to see where those pipes could be coming from except for under the basin," he says.
Massengale says DENR took samples from four pipes that she described as toe drains for the dam. The agency also took samples from one stormwater pipe.
She says DENR is trying to determine if the pipes run beneath the inactive pond.
DENR has already filed notice with Duke that some of the pipes at Cliffside are badly corroded and must be addressed to ensure proper safety at the dam.
Sheehan says toe drains are generally designed to go under the dam for an ash pond, but not under the pond itself. She says Duke continues to work with the state to resolve any questions at Cliffside.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Charlotte Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>