<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-1291-F0NV-F2XH"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Danville 's legislative and administrative departments report budget overview to City Commission</title><source>The Advocate-Messenger (Danville, Kentucky)</source><author>PAM WRIGHT, PWRIGHT@AMNEWS.COM</author><text><![CDATA[Editor's note: On Thursday, Danville City Commission held a budget department overview session and looked at each department's spending in 2013 and the challenges for the coming fiscal year. The Advocate-Messenger will explore the reports of each department in the coming days to give readers a better picture of where and how city funds are spent.
The legislative and administrative departments of Danville account for 11 percent of the city's yearly fiscal budget.
The legislative portion of the budget in fiscal year 2013-14 was $765,453 with 65 percent of that allocated for personnel.
The employees under the legislative department include the Danville Board of Commissioners, city manager, city clerk, city engineer, a secretary and an administrative assistant in engineering.
Donna Peek, city clerk and human resources director, reported to the commission March 13 detailing the functions of the legislative department, the expenditures for 2013-14 fiscal year, and the challenges the department faces in the coming fiscal year.
"We should attempt to uphold the mission of the city of Danville to improve the quality of life in Danville by working together with all citizens to preserve life, maintain human rights, protect property and promote public safety," she said.
Peek explained the duties of the various departments under the legislative umbrella.
City Manager Ron Scott manages the day-to-day operations of the city, while City Engineer Earl Coffey manages the water and sewer departments and oversees the public works superintendent.
Peek's duties include working for - and with - the City Commission, city manager, other employees and residents of Danville.
Other key players are Erica Engle, administrative assistant for engineering, and Joyce Collins, assistant to Mayor Bernie Hunstad.
"The individuals in this department must be able to multi-task at a very high level, as no one project is more important than another," said Peek.
Twenty-three percent of the department's budget goes to contractual expenditures, including legal expenses, advertising and liability insurance, while the final 12 percent of the budget is used for memberships, training and meetings.
Peek acknowledged that new challenges face the city on a daily basis.
According to Peek, the city strives to serve the community at the expected level without increasing costs while continually seeking new forms of revenue for the city.
"We attempt to answer questions, move projects of the City Commission forward, keep the city moving forward looking out for solutions to future issues facing the city and attempting to always be one step ahead," she said.
The Finance and Administration Department is led by Chief Financial Officer Michele Gosser, who presented the department's report at the March 13 budget overview meeting.
With a budget of $633,933, the department allocates 38 percent toward personnel, 60 percent toward contractual expenses, and 2 percent for other expenses.
Gosser said the department supports not only the residents of Danville but internally supports all departments of the city.
Some of the accounting duties of the department include maintaining the general ledger, compiling and producing financial statements, internal and external financial reporting, internal control procedures, statutory reporting and tax reports.
There are many other duties of the department.
Some include cash management, bank reconciliations, investments, managing debt service, assisting with grant compliance, initiating bids, payroll, and utility accounts and collection.
"In addition to accounting functions, the Finance and Administration is tasked with switchboard duties for city hall," said Gosser. "We consider customer service as part of our duties."
Gosser said the department answers 150-200 calls per shift with another 100-150 walk-in and drop-off payments per day.
For the coming fiscal year, Finance and Administration intends to improve accounting and reporting by integrating a new accounting system that Gosser deems a "past- due upgrade."
To improve customer service, the department is establishing set procedures and telephone protocol to better streamline procedures. In addition, two full-time finance clerks are taking sign-language courses, and the accounts payable clerk is taking an advanced class to better serve the hearing-impaired in the community.
"We continue to improve our day-to-day functions so that we work in the most effective and efficient way," said Gosser.
"As a city, we need to bind together from the top down and bottom up - both citizens and all governmental employees - in support of each other to achieve the ultimate goal of providing service and making our city a great place to live and work," said Peek.
]]></text></news-item>