<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-4WN1-JD34-V1G5"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>CCA seeks $4m from beef cattle levy funds</title><source>Stock Journal</source><author>COLIN BETTLES</author><text><![CDATA[THE Cattle Council of Australia wants $4 million from income generated by the $5 grassfed beef cattle levy, to strengthen industry oversight and strategic policy development powers and free-up other resources for 'critical' industry lobbying.
Senior CCA representatives called for greater support last week when appearing at the first public hearing in Canberra of the Federal Senate inquiry ito industry structures and systems governing grassfed cattle levies.
The levy inquiry was instigated by Federal Agriculture Minister Barnaby Joyce late last year and has so far received 183 written submissions from key industry groups and individual producers.
The Regional Affairs and Transport References Committee will hold five more public hearings: at Broome, WA on May 6, Katherine, NT on May 7 and 8; Rockhampton, Qld on May 21; and Albury, NSW on May 22.
The Senate has granted an extension to June 30 for a final report which could make critical recommendations that alter how the $5-a-head cattle levy is distributed, and bolster CCA's powers.
Out of the $5, MLA receives $3.66 for marketing activities and 92 cents for R&D while 13c goes to Animal Health Australia and 28c to the National Residue Survey.
CCA president Andrew Ogilvie said the $4m would require redirecting about 28c of the levy to his organisation but recent industry consultations showed there was "no appetite" for increasing the total levy.
MLA told the inquiry its $162m total revenue last year comprised $54m from grassfed beef cattle levies, $7.8m from grainfed cattle levies, $800,000 in goat levies and $31m in lamb and sheep levies, while the processing sector contributed $9.4m, government $39m and private investments $9m.
WA Liberal Senator Chris Back suggested the processing sector contributed about 10 per cent of MLA's non-government revenue - but the proportion of expenditure that went ito MLA activities associated with processing sector was about 33pc.
MLA Trade and Economic Services manager Dr Peter Barnard rejected the assertion saying the meat processing sector's major investments went ito joint programs around market access and food safety, but the question was taken on notice.
Mr Ogilvie told the Senate Committee the CCA was Australia's "most representative" beef cattle organisation, with 15,000 grassfed beef producer members via State Farming Organisation memberships, covering more than 50pc of the national cattle herd.
A CCA restructure process started 12 months before the Senate inquiry was initiated, and has now opened the door to direct membership.
But CCA CEO Jed Matz said the new membership category had attracted only 98 direct members since starting in January.
He said CCA had an average annual income of about $1.39m in the past five years but strategic policy development was being "completely forgotten about" because of revenue shortages.
This year's budget is expected to generate $436,000 from member-based subscriptions, including SFOs providing about $400,000 between them, with each paying $25,000, except NSW ($90,000) and Qld's AgForce ($104,000).
Mr Matz said CCA's estimated income included $500,000 from the industry fund administered by the Red Meat Advisory Council. He said disbursements were derived from investments made from a funding base of about $42m which was originally leftover from the merger of industry marketing and R&D organisations, preceding MLA's establishment.
Mr Matz said CCA's budgeted income also relied on $727,000 in service agreements with Animal Health Australia, MLA and the Australian government.
He said the final amount was determined by the volume of work required to meet the different agreements but often fell short of the budget.
MLA chairperson Michele Allan also told the inquiry $24.37m was paid-out last year in staff wages and salaries for 248 equivalent full-time staff, while directors' remuneration, excluding the managing director, was $460,477.
]]></text></news-item>