<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-C071-JCMN-Y4PR"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Is JPMorgan Chase a Safe Investment?</title><source>Wall St. Cheat Sheet</source><author>Victor Mora</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 19, 2014 (Wall St. Cheat Sheet:http://wallstcheatsheet.com/ Delivered by Newstex) With shares of JPMorgan Chase Co. (NYSE:JPM[1]) trading around $58, is JPM an OUTPERFORM, WAIT AND SEE, or STAY AWAY? Let's analyze the stock with the relevant sections of our CHEAT SHEET investing framework[2]:
T = Trends for a Stock's MovementJPMorgan Chase is a financial holding company that provides various financial services worldwide. The company is engaged in investment banking, financial services for consumers and small businesses, commercial banking, financial transaction processing, asset management, and private equity. Financial services companies like JPMorgan Chase are essential for well-functioning economies around the world.Save Time Make Money! A new stock idea each week for less than the cost of a trade. CLICK HERE for your Weekly Stock Cheat Sheets NOW[3]!In the past year, regulators turned their attention to the large financial institutions that dominate the business of physical commodities trading. With new rules penned by Congress limiting the degree to which banks can trade for their own accounts and an ongoing investigation from the Commodity Futures Trading Commission, JPMorgan Chase has decided it is time to get out of the physical commodities trading business. After pursuing a buyer for months, the company finally announced Wednesday morning that Mercuria Energy Group, a fast-growing Swiss trading firm, had agreed to purchase the unit for $3.5 billion in cash. Mercuria, founded by former Goldman Sachs (NYSE:GS[4]) traders, has grown into one of the world's four largest independent commodities traders, with offices in 28 countries and more than 1,000 employees. Subject to regulatory approval, the all-cash transaction is expected to close in the third-quarter of this year. 'Our goal from the outset was to find a buyer that was interested in preserving the value of JPMorgan's physical business,' Blythe Masters, head of JPMorgan's global commodities business, said in the Wednesday press release announcing the sale. 'Mercuria is a global leader in the commodities markets and an excellent long-term home for these businesses.' What the statement did not explain is whether Masters, a long time veteran of the bank, would leave JPMorgan to remain with her team. T = Technicals on the Stock Chart Are StrongJPMorgan Chase stock has done relatively well in the past couple of years. The stock is currently moving higher and looks poised to continue. Analyzing the price trend and its strength can be done using key simple moving averages. What are the key moving averages? The 50-day (pink), 100-day (blue), and 200-day (yellow) simple moving averages. As seen in the daily price chart below, JPMorgan Chase is trading above its rising key averages which signal neutral to bullish price action in the near-term. http://cdn.wallstcheatsheet.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/JPM1.jpg (Source: Thinkorswim) Taking a look at the implied volatility (red) and implied volatility skew levels of JPMorgan Chase options may help determine if investors are bullish, neutral, or bearish.Save Time Make Money! A new stock idea each week for less than the cost of a trade. CLICK HERE for your Weekly Stock Cheat Sheets NOW[5]! What does this mean? This means that investors or traders are buying a significant amount of call and put options contracts, as compared to the last 30 and 90 trading days.As of today, there is an average demand from call buyers or sellers and low demand by put buyers or high demand by put sellers, all neutral to bullish over the next two months. To summarize, investors are buying a significant amount of call and put option contracts and are leaning neutral to bullish over the next two months. On the next page, let's take a look at the earnings and revenue growth rates and the conclusion.E = Earnings Are Mixed Quarter-Over-QuarterRising stock prices are often strongly correlated with rising earnings and revenue growth rates. Also, the last four quarterly earnings announcement reactions help gauge investor sentiment on JPMorgan Chase's stock. What do the last four quarterly earnings and revenue growth (Y-O-Y) figures for JPMorgan Chase look like and more importantly, how did the markets like these numbers?JPMorgan Chase has seen mixed earnings and decreasing revenue figures over the last four quarters. From these numbers, the markets have had mixed feelings about JPMorgan Chase's recent earnings announcements.Save Time Make Money! A new stock idea each week for less than the cost of a trade. CLICK HERE for your Weekly Stock Cheat Sheets NOW[6]! P = Average Relative Performance Versus Peers and SectorHow has JPMorgan Chase stock done relative to its peers, Bank of America (NYSE:BAC[7]), Citigroup (NYSE:C[8]), Wells Fargo (NYSE:WFC[9]), and sector?JPMorgan Chase has been an average performer, year-to-date.ConclusionJPMorgan Chase is a bellwether in the banking space that forms an essential part of the United States financial system. The company finally announced Wednesday morning that Mercuria Energy Group had agreed to purchase the unit for $3.5 billion in cash. The stock has done relatively well in the past couple of years and is currently surging higher. Over the last four quarters, earnings have been mixed while revenues have been decreasing which has produced mixed feelings among investors. Relative to its peers and sector, JPMorgan Chase has been an average year-to-date performer. WAIT AND SEE what JPMorgan Chase does this quarter. Using a solid investing framework such as this can help improve your stock-picking skills. Don't waste another minute — click here and get our CHEAT SHEET stock picks now[10].More From Wall St. Cheat Sheet:If Banking Is a Competition, JPMorgan's CFO Is In It to Win[11] JPMorgan Looks for the Right Mix of Cost-Cutting and Compensation[12] JPMorgan Gives Regulators Evidence of Nepotism in China[13] Read the original article[14] from Wall St. Cheat Sheet [1]: http://wallstcheatsheet.com/stock-research/company/?qs=JPM [2]: https://wallstcheatsheet.com/newsletters/wscs-premium/?ref=PBALCSVMls=7521 [3]: https://wallstcheatsheet.com/newsletters/stock-cheat-sheets/?ref=PBAL143ls=7521 [4]: http://wallstcheatsheet.com/stock-research/company/?qs=GS [5]: https://wallstcheatsheet.com/newsletters/stock-cheat-sheets/?ref=PBAL143ls=7521 [6]: https://wallstcheatsheet.com/newsletters/stock-cheat-sheets/?ref=PBAL143ls=7521 [7]: http://wallstcheatsheet.com/stock-research/company/?qs=BAC [8]: http://wallstcheatsheet.com/stock-research/company/?qs=C [9]: http://wallstcheatsheet.com/stock-research/company/?qs=WFC [10]: https://wallstcheatsheet.com/newsletters/wscs-premium/?ref=PBALCSls=7521 [11]: http://wallstcheatsheet.com/business/if-banking-is-a-competition-jpmorgans-cfo-is-in-it-to-win.html/ [12]: http://wallstcheatsheet.com/business/jpmorgan-looks-for-the-right-mix-of-cost-cutting-and-compensation.html/ [13]: http://http://wallstcheatsheet.com/stocks/jpmorgan-gives-regulators-evidence-of-nepotism-in-china.html/ [14]: http://wallstcheatsheet.com/business/is-jpmorgan-chase-a-safe-investment.html/

]]></text></news-item>