<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-97G1-F05M-K2J4"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Texas coal plants burned 23M tons in 3 months to lead nation</title><source>Dallas Business Journal</source><author>Nicholas Sakelaris</author><text><![CDATA[Texas consumed nearly 23 million tons of coal in the fourth quarter of 2013, making it the top consumer of coal in the country, according to an Energy Information Administration&nbsp; report.
The majority of the coal, 12.5 million tons, was imported via train from Wyoming for electricity generation, according to the EIA. A much smaller amount, 345,000 tons was used in industrial plants.
Texas coal mines produced another 10 million tons for electricity generation with the majority being moved on conveyor belts, slurry pipelines or trucks.
Wyoming is by far the top exporter of coal, shipping more than 94 million tons of coal to 33 states. Other top coal producers are Kentucky, 16.6 million tons, West Virginia, 16.4 million tons and Pennsylvania, 11.4 million tons.
Besides Texas, states that consume the most coal include Illinois, 15.8 million tons, Indiana, 10.9 million tons, Kentucky, 10.8 million tons and Ohio, 10.2 million tons.
Texas' reliance on coal is big reason why the Lone Star state&nbsp; has become ground zero for the war on coal.&nbsp; The Environmental Protection Agency has already cracked down on new coal plants by requiring emission controls that critics say aren't feasible. The EPA's next target would be existing plants like those owned by Dallas-based Luminant, a subsidiary of the financially troubled Energy Future Holdings.
Luminant recently&nbsp; won a court battle against the Sierra Club over pollution at the Big Brown Power Plant in Freestone County. The environmental group was seeking $330 million in civil penalties while pushing for $140 million in emission control upgrades.
Coal plants within the Electric Reliability Council of Texas service area, which covers 85 percent of the state, generated 29.3 million megawatt hours of electricity in October, November and December, according to ERCOT.&nbsp;Coal produced more than 37 percent of the electricity in ERCOT in 2013.&nbsp;
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Dallas Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>