<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-2061-F03R-N3V0"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Verizon defends child-theme porn</title><source>ValueWalk</source><author>VW Staff</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 19, 2014 (ValueWalk:http://www.valuewalk.com/ Delivered by Newstex) Claims choice of content is "tremendous benefit to consumers"Washington, DC - Verizon is defending its distribution of child-theme pornography in a letter to Morality in Media, which included the company on its 2014 Dirty Dozen List of pornography's top facilitators. The company believes that it's 'explosion of choice' in pornography is a 'tremendous benefit' to consumers, according to a letter[1] from Verizon's Director of Global Corporate Citizenship.
'I Did the Babysitter,' 'I Banged My Stepdad,' 'Mom, Daughter, and Me,' and 'Pigtail Teens Pounded,' are some of the hardcore porn titles featured on Verizon's FIOS video-on-demand service. Morality in Media highlighted these and other offensive videos[2], such as 'Gang Bang Sex Slaves' and some with insulting racial overtones, such as 'Massive Black Butts,' in a letter[3] to Verizon notifying the company of its inclusion on the 2014 Dirty Dozen List. 'Verizon should not be profiting from child sex fantasy videos,' said Patrick A. Trueman, Morality in Media's president. 'In fact Verizon should not profit from pornography at all, ' he added. 'America's children and families are suffering a pandemic of harm from pornography and since Verizon became a leading porn distributor, it is responsible for much of that harm,' Trueman said. Morality in Media has now written a letter[4] to Verizon's board of directors asking each one if they believe Verizon should profit from pornographic films that promote child sex abuse and incest. MIM also noted that it is also a violation of federal law for Verizon to distribute hardcore or 'obscene' pornography on its services, citing Title 18 U.S.C. Section 1468. For more information on this campaign, go to the Dirty Dozen website, PornHarms.com/dirtydozen[5]. Founded in 1962, Morality in Media, Inc. is the leading national organization dedicated to opposing pornography through education about its illegality and harms by highlighting the links to sex trafficking, violence against women, child abuse and addiction. The post Verizon defends child-theme porn[6] appeared first on ValueWalk[7]. [1]: http://pornharms.com/wp-content/uploads/VerizonLetter_2014DirtyDozen.pdf [2]: http://pornharms.com/dirtydozen/verizon/verizons-porn-problem/?preview=truepreview_id=4705preview_nonce=fd60247dab [3]: http://pornharms.com/wp-content/uploads/MIM_DirtyDozen_LettersToVerizon_02-21-2014.pdf [4]: http://pornharms.com/wp-content/uploads/DD_Verizon_BoardLetter_ALLFINAL_03-19-2014-copy.pdf [5]: http://pornharms.com/dirtydozen [6]: http://www.valuewalk.com/2014/03/verizon-defends-child-theme-porn%e2%80%8f/ [7]: http://www.valuewalk.com

]]></text></news-item>