<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-8751-DXKS-J3C8"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>The Layfield Law Firm Secures $11.2 Million Verdict in Orange County; The Layfield Law Firm, APC - a Los Angeles business litigation and personal injury law firm - recently secured an $11.2 million verdict in Orange County on behalf of a client that was financially harmed by a financial scheme involving bank instrument fraud.</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Layfield Law Firm, APC has built a reputation for handling complex cases other firms are unwilling to touch, and has recovered millions on behalf of clients who have been physically or financially harmed by the conduct of others. In a recent case handled by the firm, the firm's team of business litigation lawyers - led by founding attorney Philip J. Layfield - managed to successfully secure an $11.2 million verdict on behalf of a client that suffered financial losses as the result of a financial scheme (Case no. 30-2012-00551939, Orange County, CA).
Defendants named in the case - Dakota Holdings, Inc., Global Business Systems, LLC, Matthew Anderson, and Claudia Lopez - were part of the Anderson Group, which misrepresented itself as a group of legitimate professionals. The group was orchestrated by Matthew Anderson. According to the claim filed by The Layfield Law Firm, a previous lawsuit against Anderson claimed that the group's common purpose was to steal money from victims, conceal stolen funds, and avoid legal action and collections. The Layfield Law Firm's lawsuit made similar allegations.
The Layfield Law Firm's client - Element Capital - was a developer of residential properties in Utah. Because of traditional banks' unwillingness to lend during the financial crisis, Element sought alternative sources of financing, eventually coming into contact with Anderson through a financial advisor. Court documents state that prior to entering into a funding agreement with Element in 2009, Anderson made false and misleading representations regarding his group's professional status, as well as false statements about its ability to provide funding.
Attorney Philip J. Layfield was lead trial attorney on the case, with Attorney Christopher Walton as second chair. As a result of their extensive experience, persistence, and thoroughness, The Layfield Law Firm was able to expose Anderson for running a fraudulent scheme, as well as the framework for which financial manipulations were committed against victims, including Element Capital. After litigating the case, Attorney Layfield secured an $11.2 million verdict. This successful resolution not only ensured that justice was served and that Element's losses were recovered, but also that future potential victims would not fall victim to Anderson's deceit.
The Layfield Law Firm, APC provides full-service business litigation and personal injury representation to clients throughout Southern California and Utah. Throughout the years, the firm has secured more than $70 million in compensation on behalf of clients, including million dollar recoveries in complex bank instrument fraud cases. The firm fights aggressively on behalf of clients, and has built a reputation for handling challenging cases other firms turn down. More information about The Layfield Law Firm can be found on the firm's website:http://www.layfield-law.com.
SOURCE The Layfield Law Firm, APC
]]></text></news-item>