<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-1261-F0NV-F1VN"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Keeping Their Eye on the Ash Spill</title><source>The News &amp; Advance (Lynchburg, Virginia)</source><author>THE EDITORIAL BOARD</author><text><![CDATA[Finally, the North Carolina agency responsible for keeping the environment as clean and safe as possible has charged Duke Energy with essentially dragging its feet over the coal ash spill in the Dan River and elsewhere across the state. The spill occurred at the utility's old Dan River Steam Station where some 39,000 tons of pollutants were dumped into the river in early February.
The toxic ash coated the bottom of the Dan River from the spill site in Eden, N.C., to beyond Danville. The water supplies of numerous Southside Virginia localities have been adversely impacted by the ash spill and Duke Energy's response to it.
The North Carolina Department of Environment and Natural Resources makes a good case in urging Duke Power to clean up the mess it has created. The agency had asked that Duke provide a detailed plan by early last week to clean up its coal ash ponds around North Carolina, including the one at the Eden site. The environmental agency also said it wants the utility to speed up closure of coal ash ponds at the Duke plant near Wilmington and another one in Gaston County, N.C.
And for good measure, Virginia environmental regulators are closely following the Duke ash spill and North Carolina's response to it.
"Coal ash ponds" are a relatively new phrase in the lexicon of environmental protection. They are the result of millions of tons of coal being burned to fire steam generators to produce electricity. No one, it seems, gave enough thought to what might happen when disposal sites for the toxic ash became too full and started overflowing into nearby rivers and streams.
In response to letters from the environmental agency, Duke Energy CEO Lynn Good said the company plans to permanently close the Dan River ash ponds and move the ash away from the river to a lined landfill. But that work would take up to two and a half years following the necessary permitting and securing a landfill site.
Good also said Duke would accelerate closure of several other ash ponds and speed up the removal of water from ash ponds at all its retired coal plants.
State officials called those plans "inadequate." John Skvarla, secretary of DENR, wrote in a letter to Duke, "There are far too many questions left unanswered and Duke Energy should provide the information we originally requested, including the estimated costs of the cleanup, plans for the future and a detailed timeline."
The North Carolina agency is only doing its job to protect public health and the environment, something the utility should have given more attention to when the coal-fired plants were constructed years ago.
Questions remain about the cause of the broken pipe that led to the dumping of ash into the Dan River, along with the future of the plant in Eden. And no one is saying for certain what possible toxic effects remain for the drinking water supplies downstream on the Dan River. That would include Danville and South Boston.
The sooner the questions can be answered, the better for everyone directly involved. The North Carolina agency is trying to get answers as quickly as possible from the utility. In that, it is only doing its job.
]]></text></news-item>