<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-1281-F0NV-F51G"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>News in brief Toyota hit with $1B settlement</title><source>The Chronicle (Willimantic, Connecticut)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[WASHINGTON - The U.S. Justice Department has reached a $1 billion settlement with Toyota Motor Corp. over the automaker's handling of consumer complaints tied to unintended vehicle acceleration and is set to announce the agreement as early today, CNN reported.
Sources familiar with the deal told CNN that Toyota was expected to avoid criminal charges.
The U.S. Attorney's Office in Manhattan has been probing allegations the Japanese company misled U.S. authorities after the complaints about the unintended acceleration emerged. The acceleration issue prompted Toyota to recall millions of vehicles beginning in 2009.
"Toyota has cooperated with the U.S. attorney's office in this matter for more than four years," a Toyota spokesman told CNN. "During that time, we have made fundamental changes to become a more responsive and customer-focused organization, and we are committed to continued improvements."
Officials at the U.S. Attorney General's Office could not immediately be reached for comment.
The automaker last year paid more than $1 billion to resolve economic-loss claims related to the recall.
Two dead in helicopter crash
Reuters
SEATTLE - A news helicopter crashed and burst into flames in downtown Seattle near the Space Needle Tuesday, killing a pilot and a photographer on board and setting three cars on fire in the popular tourist area, officials said.
The chopper appeared to have fallen to the street as it attempted to take off from a helipad at the top of a television news station, Seattle Fire Department spokesman Kyle Moore told reporters. Witnesses reported an "unusual noise" coming from the helicopter during its departure.
Two people were found dead in the wreckage of the helicopter when emergency responders arrived at the scene, while the occupants of three vehicles that caught fire managed to escape, Moore said. One person was in critical condition.
Television station KOMO, an ABC affiliate, said the aircraft was one of its helicopters. Photos posted online by the station showed flames and smoke rising from cars at the scene after the crash.
The two people killed were pilot 59-year-old Gary Pfitzner, who worked for a company that operated the helicopter for the TV station, and photographer Bill Strothman, 62, who shot video for KOMO but had retired from the company and worked as a freelancer, according to KOMO.
NSA records all calls in 1 nation
Reuters
WASHINGTON - The National Security Agency has created a surveillance system that can record all phone calls in a targeted foreign nation, allowing it to play back and listen to conversations up to 30 days later, the Washington Post reported Tuesday.
The newspaper cited unnamed sources with direct knowledge of the system as well as documents supplied by former NSA contractor Edward Snowden, who since last year has leaked extensive data revealing sweeping American spying activities.
The voice interception program is known as MYSTIC and started in 2009, with its "retrospective retrieval" capability, called RETRO, reaching full strength in 2011 against the first target nation, the Post reported.
The newspaper said at the request of U.S. officials, it was withholding details that could be used to identify the nation where the system is being used or others where it might be used in the future. The Post cited documents that envisioned similar U.S. spying operations in other nations.
A classified summary of the system said the collection effort was recording "every single" conversation nationwide in the first target country, storing billions of conversations in a 30- day rolling buffer that clears out the oldest calls as new ones are made, the Post reported.
A senior manager for the program likened it to a time machine that can replay voices from any phone call without the need to identify a person for spying in advance, the newspaper reported.
Two tickets share $400M prize
Reuters
Two winning tickets in Florida and Maryland will share about $400 million from Tuesday night's Mega Millions drawing, lottery officials said, marking the third highest jackpot in the game's history.
The winning numbers were 11, 19, 24, 33, 51 and 7, according to the Mega Millions web site.
The jackpot had been rolling over since Jan. 3 and swelled again after no one matched all six numbers in Friday night's drawing of the game, which is played twice a week.
There was no immediate word on where the ticket was sold in Maryland, but local media reported a ticket was sold at a Sunoco gas station in Merritt Island, east of Orlando, Fla.
The identities of the winning ticket holders were not immediately known.
U.S. honors 24 minority vets
Reuters
WASHINGTON - Two dozen U.S. Army veterans received the country's top military honor at the White House Tuesday for acts of bravery in World War II, Korea and Vietnam as part of an effort to recognize those whose service may have been ignored because of their race or religion.
President Obama awarded the medals recognizing the 24 Hispanic, African- American and Jewish-Americans veterans - the largest group of soldiers to be honored for the award since World War II.
Just three of the men honored are still living and were on hand to accept the blue-ribboned award from the president. The others either died in combat or later of natural causes. One veteran is still classified as missing, Obama said.
The review was part of a years-long effort to honor service members despite past discrimination, Obama said. "Here in America, we confront our imperfections and face the sometimes painful past, including the truth that some of these soldiers fought and died for a country that did not always see them as equal," he said. "As one family member said, this is long overdue," Obama told the audience of wives, brothers, sons and daughters who came to accept the awards in a ceremony at the White House.
The three living veterans on hand to accept their award were Melvin Morris of Florida and Jose Rodela and Santiago Erevia of Texas.
The ceremony drew singer Lenny Kravitz, whose uncle Leonard Kravitz was honored posthumously for his service in Korea in 1951.
IRS employee data is leaked
Reuters
WASHINGTON - The personal data of about 20,000 U.S. Internal Revenue Service employees going back to 2007 or earlier may have been exposed on the Internet, but no general taxpayer information or records were part of the security breach, the agency said Tuesday.
IRS Commissioner John Koskinen said in a statement that an unencrypted thumb drive containing the information was plugged into an employee's unsecured home network, making the information potentially accessible to third parties online.
He said the drive contained "sensitive personnel information, including names, Social Security numbers and addresses, of some employees.
]]></text></news-item>