<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-0V21-J9XT-P4T5"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>US Contract Notice: Department of Justice Issues Solicitation for "DAIRY"</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Department of Justice, Bureau of Prisons Officer has issued requirement for "DAIRY."
Solicitation no. RFQP01110001513 Posted on: March 19, 2014
Notice Type: Solicitation
The NAICS code number for this requirement: 311
Description: The Federal Bureau of Prisons, Federal Correctional Institution Memphis, TN, intends to issue solicitation RFQ P0111-00015-13, for the requirements of: QUARTERLY SUBSISTENCE-DAIRY. This solicitation is restricted to 100% Small Business and FOB Destination. Delivery dates will be found within the solicitations. Deliveries will be made to the Federal Correctional Institution, 1101 John A. Denie Rd., Memphis, TN 38134. The contract type is a firm-fixed price. The Government reserves the right upon award to make formal single or multiple awards. The Government will award to the responsible offeror(s), conforming to the solicitation, that are considered to be most advantageous to the Government, with past performance and price considered. Prices will be rated higher than past performance. The solicitation will be made available on or about March 19, 2014 and will be posted to the General Services Administration Federal Business Opportunities website: http://www.fbo.gov. All future information about this acquisition, including solicitation amendments, will also be distributed through this site. Interested parties are responsible for monitoring this site to insure they have the most up-to-date information about this solicitation. The anticipated date for receipt of quotes is March 1, 2013. Payment will be made using the Government Purchase Card for awards $3000.00 or less. For awards greater than $3000.00, payment will be made using Electronic Funds Transfer (EFT). Any contractor interested in obtaining a contract award with the Federal Bureau of Prisons must be registered at www.ccr.gov. Each offer per 52.212-3 is required to complete their representations and certifications via the On-Line Representations and Certifications Applications (ORCA) at http://orca.bpn.gov. The point of contact for all information regarding this solicitation is Ron Brewer, Contract Specialist, at the address listed above and at the telephone number listed below. Complete offers may be faxed to the attention of Ron Brewer at (901)384-5457, mailed to the address above or e-mailed to rebrewer@bop.gov The anticipated award date is April 1, 2013. Faith-Based and Community-Based Organizations have the right to submit offers equally with other organizations for contracts for which they are eligible.
Set Aside: N/A
Deadline for All responses: Mar 01, 2013 2:00 pm Central
Contact Details: 1101 John A. Denie RoadMemphis, Tennessee 38135
Point of Contact(s): Ronald E. Brewer,Contract Specialistrebrewer@bop.govPhone: 901-384-5543Fax: 901-384-5457
For more information visit: https://www.fbo.gov/index?s=opportunity&mode=66bce201c1dc5a95818c8633c1ab47b8&tab=core&_cview=1. In case of any query regarding this article or other content needs please contact: editorial@plusmediasolutions.com
]]></text></news-item>