<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-0351-DYX3-P50C"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Lithuanian PM won't comment on EU official's words about Gazprom probe</title><source>Baltic News Service / - BNS</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Lithuanian PM won't comment on EU official's words about Gazprom probe
(expands)
VILNIUS, Mar 19, BNS - Lithuanian Prime Minister Algirdas Butkevicius on Wednesday declined to comment on an EU official's statement that Russia's gas giant Gazprom has a chance to avoid an EU antitrust complaint as this could be misinterpreted as an act of "aggression" toward Russia amid the Ukrainian crisis.
"As far as I know, this was said, not so firmly, by an official working at a separate division of the competition body. I really would not like to comment on these words.  I will have an opportunity to meet, in early April, with the [European Commission] officials who are looking into this issue and will be able to give a more concrete answer [after the meeting]," he told reporters after the Cabinet's meeting.
Butkevicius acknowledged that tensions between Ukraine and Russia made Lithuania's negotiations with Gazprom on cheaper natural gas more difficult.
"I can say that the talks are ongoing at experts' level, but they are not simple and easy. Certainly, [the events in Ukraine] are adding some tension and making the negotiating process more difficult," he said.
Butkevicius said that it was not clear yet when the talks could be completed.
"I cannot say today as regards the final outcome," he said.
The negotiators were to meet a couple of weeks ago, but the talks have stalled again due to the Ukrainian events.
Celine Gauer, head of the European Commission's antitrust unit for the energy industry, said on Tuesday that sending a statement of objections to Gazprom now would be conceived as an act of aggression against Russia.
The European Commission suspects Gazprom of abusing its market position to impose unfair gas prices in central and eastern Europe by linking them to oil prices. The EU's executive body also suspects that the Russian group may have prevented gas from being traded between countries and hindered customers from finding new energy suppliers.
Gazprom last year presented proposals to settle the anti-trust investigation. However, EU Competition Commissioner Joaquin Almunia said in February that the proposals fell short of addressing the Commission's concerns. He also said that the Commission had almost completed the statement of objections.
The EU's probe focuses on Gazprom's business practices in the Baltic countries, Poland, the Czech Republic, Slovakia, Hungary and Bulgaria.
Vilnius newsroom, verslas@bns.lt, +370 5 205 8517 
]]></text></news-item>