<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-1281-F0NV-F4NG"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Judge approves $3.8-million verdict against Willis Enterprises</title><source>The Vidette (Montesano, Washington)</source><author>Brionna Friedrich, THE DAILY WORLD</author><text><![CDATA[Aside from awarding a few extra costs, a jury's $3.8-million verdict against Willis Enterprises stood up Monday in the final judgment entered by Grays Harbor Superior Court Judge Mark McCauley.
McCauley added about $4,200 in costs but left the rest of the jury's verdict as written. The verdict for Verl and Marsha Lee was announced March 6. The couple sued Willis Enterprises and its employee, Daniel Fletcher, for an injury Verl Lee suffered at the company's Oakville chip mill.
Willis Enterprises and Fletcher are represented by Tom Brown and Mike Spencer of Brown, Lewis, Janhunen and Spencer in Aberdeen. They have 30 days to file an appeal of the verdict. Verl Lee now suffers from severe tinnitus and hyperacusis, an abnormal sensitivity to sound. His attorneys said the injury has forced Lee to give up his job, driving, and his work as an elder in his church and director of the church choir.
Back on Jan. 25, 2010, Lee was a control specialist with Advanced Electrical Technologies, Inc. in Longview when he was sent to work on a "variable frequency drive" at the Oakville mill. The drive controls input into the chipper, but it was malfunctioning.
According to the complaint, Lee worked with Fletcher, first cleaning then disassembling and reassembling the drive. Lee eventually went inside the six-foot-by-six-foot enclosure for the drive to get a look at the fans, which were not spinning. As Lee looked over the fans, he recalls Fletcher suggesting he could get the fans to turn with his screwdriver. The power was still on and the screwdriver struck something active.
"The action triggered an explosion so bright that the mill worker temporarily thought he had lost his sight," a press release from the Lees' attorneys stated. "A massive sound wave from the explosion permanently damaged Lee's hearing system."
The short-circuit was about 700 volts, according to the complaint. As a comparison, a typical wall outlet has 120 volts.
Attorneys for Willis Enterprises initially argued that damages, if any, should be the responsibility of contractor Advanced Electrical Technologies "in not providing training, guidance, rules, instruction and other generally accepted supervisory control over activities of its employees," including Lee.
A hand-written statement from Fletcher on the day of the accident, and inserted into the court record by the defense, states that Lee was "standing above the vector drive and shining his flash light inside so I could try to hit it with a long screwdriver. Not once did he say not to do that, so when I tried to hit the fan to make it work, I hit one of the main power sources and there was a big flash and boom."
Fletcher says his boss later came in to ask what had happened and "we were both quiet about it. ... I don't know why Verl didn't say anything, unless he thought he was in the wrong for letting me do that."
Willis Industries has since changed its safety practices, including who is allowed into the electrical building. Fletcher is no longer allowed in the Variable Frequency Drive, although the defense had argued those facts shouldn't be used in the case.
The jury found Fletcher was negligent, and his actions were 90 percent of the cause of Lee's injuries. Because he was acting in his capacity as an employee of Willis Enterprises, the company is also liable for damages he's found to have caused. The total verdict was $4.3 million, but Verl Lee was found to be 10 percent at fault. The bulk of the verdict stems from non-monetary damages to Verl Lee, $2.25 million of the $3.8-million total. A total of $414,000 is included for Marsha Lee's loss of consortium, or familial relationship.
The Vidette contributed to this story.
]]></text></news-item>