<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-KTW1-JD3N-51B0"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Call to close power station</title><source>Geelong Advertiser (Australia)</source><author>GREG DUNDAS</author><text><![CDATA[ENVIRONMENTALISTS say the State Government should shut down Alcoa's Anglesea coal-fired power station when the company closes its Point Henry aluminium plant.
The Anglesea business was put on the market last month.
While the Government says it is keen to help the company sell the facility and protect its 80 jobs, objectors say it threatens the health of residents and the environment.
With 800 jobs to be lost when Point Henry closes later this year, they say the power station and coal mine can no longer be justified.
Alcoa is one the state's largest energy users, with 40 per cent of the power used at Point Henry generated at Anglesea.
Jacinta Morahan, of Surf Coast Air Action, said Vic-toria's energy market was in surplus, and the closure of Point Henry would further -reduce demand.
Ms Morahan urged Alcoa to shut the site and put the staff to work rehabilitating it.
"There is no longer any -social licence to continue the mine and power station or to continue to impose the associated health and environmental damage to the community of Anglesea," she said.
"It begs the question: for how long will the employment of 80 people or less, trump the health of at least 2000 residents and up to 16,500 visitors." Although the mine and power station is for sale, Alcoa is awaiting a decision from the Essential Services Commission on its application for a licence to generate power beyond -August 1. While any buyer would have to attain a licence, the State Government said it was doing what it could to protect the remaining jobs.
"The Victorian Government is working with Alcoa to assist it to obtain the necessary licences to enable the Anglesea power station to continue to operate once this smelter -closes," a Government spokeswoman said.
"The Government will also support processes that will -facilitate Alcoa finding a buyer for the power station with the intent of securing jobs there." Surf Coast Shire councillors Margot Smith and Eve Fisher want the issue debated before the site is sold.
"The future direction of the Alcoa power station in Anglesea needs to be examined as a priority, not only from an environmental perspective but also because people's jobs and livelihoods are at stake," Cr Smith said ''It is a very delicate balance - a power station and mine operate in a fragile and fire-prone environment and people earn a living there.
"If we shut the mine and power station we need to come up with viable options for those people who would lose their jobs." Cr Fisher said it was time to look for alternative means of generating power. "If we are going to keep producing power in Anglesea we should be looking at renewable sources to fire the plant," she said.Surf Coast Air Action will hold a forum about the coal mine's future at the Anglesea Hall at 2pm on April 20.
]]></text></news-item>