<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-1261-F0NV-F1WS"><date>2014-03-18</date><title>Vacuums to pull coal ash from Schoolfield dam</title><source>The News &amp; Advance (Lynchburg, Virginia)</source><author>DENICE THIBODEAU dthibodeau@registerbee.com (434) 7917985</author><text><![CDATA[Coal ash remediation plans drew officials from state and federal agencies to Danville on Tuesday, with meetings to reassure residents that coal ash in the Dan River would be cleaned up as quickly as possible while tests on wildlife, aquatic life and water quality continue to be taken.
By the time the Gov. Terry McAuliffe and other state and local official had toured the Danville water treatment plant, the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality held a community meeting and Duke Energy filled Danville City Council in on its remediation plans, two things were clear:
» coal ash removal in the Dan River at Danville will begin soon; and
» city officials are angry at the impact the coal ash spill has had on the community.
About 70 miles of the Dan River was contaminated by a coal ash spill from Duke Energy's Eden, N.C., Dan River Steam Station on Feb. 2.
Duke Energy is in the process of getting the permits it needs to vacuum up coal ash that has accumulated at the Schoolfield Dam, the site of Danville's raw water intake from the Dan River.
Mike Hughes, Duke Energy's vice president of government and community affairs, said a contractor has been hired to handle the project and permits should be in hand in about a month. Then residents will see the vacuums pulling coal ash away from the dam for about three months.
According to the different officials who spoke throughout the day, almost everything related to this cleanup project is going to take a long time, and in some cases, years.
Steve Paylor, director of the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality, told a packed City Council chamber that initial tests on the river's fish showed no immediate contamination by heavy metals found in coal ash, though the fish continue to test positive for mercury and PCBs - as they have for many years.
While the first tests on fish show no build-up of heavy metals in their tissue, this test was just the beginning, Paylor said.
Fish and wildlife will need to be tested repeatedly for years to come, to make sure the heavy metals don't build up in their flesh over time, Paylor said.
Mayor Sherman Saunders said the issues he hears about from most residents involves the safety of the drinking water and the overall prosperity of the community, pointing out millions of dollars spent creating and marketing the River District, efforts to attract new companies and efforts to rebuild the city's population
"People are reading about our city all over the world and they are not reading good things," Saunders said, pointing out that estimates that say it will take at least two years to clean up the river could mean potential economic development prospects may wait to see how that works out before they commit to moving here.
City Manager Joe King said that very perception is already affecting economic development projects, with a major company interested in the Berry Hill Road mega park being told by a location competing with Danville for those jobs that the coal ash spill is a reason to avoid this city.
"We can't afford to lose momentum," King said.
Saunders agreed.
"We have worked hard to rebuild our city ... but that image has been tarnished," Saunders said. "We need help repairing that."
Repeatedly, council members asked for reassurances that Duke Energy would fulfill its promises to pay for all of the cleanup costs and to help the city with the perception issues it is having.
"We expect to be there another 100 years; we will take responsibility and do the right thing," Hughes said.
But Vice Mayor Gary Miller said he is still angry because the leaking ponds have been an issue for a long time but has been ignored.
"This isn't the first time this has happened," Miller said. "Duke Energy should know how to clean up their mess."
Councilman Fred Shanks bluntly said he feels let down by the company.
Shanks said he generally favors reducing government regulations on businesses - but Duke Energy's actions with its coal ponds had shaken that belief because it shows how looser regulations can be abused.
Davis Montgomery, Duke Energy's district manager for North Carolina, said he could only offer more assurances that company intends to make good on its promises - and thanked council members for their comments.
]]></text></news-item>