<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-4WN1-JD34-V0T7"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>CATTLE Council of Australia (CCA) is working to have</title><source>Queensland Country Life</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[CATTLE Council of Australia (CCA) is working to have profitability included in a document aimed at developing a 'global verification system for sustainable beef'.
The document put together by the Global Roundtable for Sustainable Beef (GRSB) after two years of discussion is said to provide a "common baseline understanding" that beef industries in different countries can use to guide development of their own verification systems".
The draft document is open to comment for 60 days.
CCA president Andrew Ogilvie said because "the buck stops with producers", producers need to be proactive in shaping how "sustainable beef" is interpreted for Australia.
The CCA is already working to have the prominent omission profitability addressed, he said.
The document's preamble observes that "econo mic viability is a critical element throughout sustainable beef value chains".
"Each participant in the value chain, from the producer to the ultimate consumer of beef, must enjoy viable economic participation in order to ensure sustainable growth."
However, the 'people and the community' section then fails to mention economic viability.
Mr Ogilvie said the same omission has also been picked up by cattlemen associations in the US and Canada, and they too are drafting responses.
"Ignoring the GRSB initiative is not an option," he said. "Even if it doesn't lead to greater profits there is no suggestion it will put more money in producers' pockets it may eventually influence market access."
"We just need to look at the major users of Australian beef: they are listening to their customers, who are telling them that want to buy product that they feel comfortable about.
"If we aren't part of this process, we might find ourselves in a situation that we are not happy with, and find it's difficult to change. We need to be part of the process, and we need to drive the process."
Mr Ogilvie urged Australian grassfed beef producers to consider how "verified sustainable beef" can work in the Australian context, and to provide com ment to CCA via its web page.
"This is not a green plot," Mr Ogilvie said.
"This is a legitimate reaction to consumers who are starting to question the integrity and sustainability of our product.
"We need to address that issue, and be seen to be addressing it, otherwise consumers might choose to eat something else."
McDonald's, the Australian beef industry's single biggest customer the company last year bought about 26,000 tonnes of local beef announced in early January that it will start preferentially sourcing verified sustainable beef from 2016.
In 2008, McDonald's commissioned controversial environmental group WWF to review the sustainability of its supply chains.
WWF found several commodities had sustainability issues, including poultry, coffee, palm oil, fish and beef.
McDonald's January announcement is the delayed outcome of the company's determination to address the sustainability of its supply chains.
When the company stated its intentions, however, there was a conspicuous absence: a definition of 'sustainable beef'.
The GRSB document is a step down the long road of putting some substance behind the term.
McDonald's and WWF were founding members of GRSB in 2012, along with multinational processors Cargill and JBS, animal health companies Merck and Elanco, retailer Walmart, and supply chain specialist Solidaridad.
The GRSB's 'Principles and criteria of global sustainable beef' is a high-level look at what sustainability should look like.
The broad range of ecosystems in which beef can be produced "makes a 'one-size-fits-all' global standard unrealistic", the document notes.
For that reason, it will be up to each country, perhaps even different regions, to develop their own performance-based measurements of sustainability. The main objective, the GRSB believes, is to be able to demonstrate to consumers that continuous im provement is being made around each of the principles, the document reads.
GRSB has also made it clear that it is not just producers involved, but "the entire supply chain, from farm to retail".
l Editorial, p11.
]]></text></news-item>