<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-JNV1-DY06-8358"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Operation Kindle and the ASA</title><source>Bizcommunity.com (South Africa: Marketing and Media)</source><author>Ed Herbst. Ed Herbst is an author and a prize-winning reporter. He worked for SABC television news for 28 years but left in 2005 without other employment in prospect because of the pervasive news and other corruption at all levels of the corporation. He is also a fly fishing enthusiast.http://www.bizcommunity.com/Profile.aspx?pro=71005</author><text><![CDATA['We should never allow expedience to triumph over our history and our values...' - Trevor ManuelTrevor Manuel is right to be perturbed."Democracy is fading" read the Sunday Times front-page headline on 16 March, highlighting Trevor Manuel's concern about the increasing attacks by the ANC on Public Protector Thuli Madonsela. He is right to be perturbed.On Thursday 14 March I was watching the SABC channel 404 7pm TV news bulletin - the flagship news broadcast on the 24-hour news channel - when up popped the weirdest news story I have ever seen and the Mail & Guardian has provided the insert.The opening shot reveals men dressed in brightly coloured clerical raiment. They seem to be speaking in tongues and one of them looks like he is suffering from a virulent and possibly terminal combination of the ague and St Vitus dance.All this is happening over the prone body of, I initially thought, Hlaudi Motsoeneng in drag because he was the subject of this surreal performance.The body was clad in a dark pin stripe suit neatly off set by what looked like some silver-soled Hong Kong Christian Louboutin knockoffs, borrowed I assumed, from the much-loved, highly-respected and hugely admired (by the ANC I hasten to add) Dina Pule. The white-lacquered nails were an elegant touch, I felt.The story was about what our nefarious media practitioners called "fringe church leaders" exorcising a host of devilish demons which have apparently taken up residence in the offices of the Public Protector - all this to protect the Zuma faction's most effective propagandist, Hlaudi "The Conduit" Motsoeneng.It was only a few seconds later that I realised that what I had initially had assumed was a cross-dressing Hlaudi was actually the strikingly beautiful woman wearing a clerical collar in an audience cutaway shot.The men of the cloth were apoplectic and hyperbolic in their rage.
Madonsela, they said, was possessed by "demonic forces which planned to derail the revolution and the freedom of our people". Furthermore, she was "Poisoning the atmosphere". All this because of her report on Motsoeneng, which merely reiterated what has been in the public domain for years and at a time when, on his watch, the state broadcaster's profits have dropped from R329m to R22m within a year.Damning findingsBe that as it may, our beloved Thuli is under such sustained and venomous attack from an increasingly jittery governing party that I would advise her not to take any chances and to place her desk on bricks without further ado.Two days later, on Saturday 15 March, the SABC carried another story of the Hlaudi Motsoeneng group attacking Madonsela as the campaign by Luthuli House to discredit her was ratcheted up and broadcast into millions of households through the ANC's most important propaganda medium. Then on Sunday, 16 March the SABC 's lead story on its 7pm channel 404 TV news bulletin was that Tina Joemat-Pettersson would be using taxpayer's money to challenge the Public Protector's damning findings against her.Trevor Manuel is right to be perturbed.Both Gwede Mantashe and Lindiwe Sisulu, democrats to the core, have also trashed her forthcoming Nkandla report which they have yet to read and indicated that the ANC will simply ignore its findings.Expect the vitriol and venom to increase exponentially when Madonsela releases her Nkandla report today and expect the SABC to give these attacks saturation 24/7 coverage.But it was what came after the insert on exorcising the satanic forces occupying Public Protector House in Pretoria that had me experiencing an attack of the vapours and reaching for the smelling salts.Here, in all its glorious eloquence, is the 24-hour news channels latest advertising blurb and it is so breathtakingly audacious, so astonishingly cynical, that I see the imprimatur of broadcasting's answer to Comical Ali, SABC spokesman' Kaizer Kganyago, writ large all over it. SABC - 'sharing 20 years of inspiration!' "SABC News plays a critical role in providing unbiased and reliable news..."We have a well-established reputation of uncovering, reporting and delivering news..."A significant growth in popularity of our news demonstrates the demand for our news content..."We continue to provide unrivalled coverage of vital events in and out of the country..."Wherever the news is happening, we'll be there to bring them to you at the right time..."No one has the news covered like SABC news..."We lead and they follow!"SABC news: Africa's news leader..."Operation KindleTrevor Manuel is right to be perturbed.According to a press release by the Democratic Alliance Shadow Minister of Communication, Marian Shinn, the SABC has, for several months now, been aware through its own commissioned market research program, Operation Kindle, that the overwhelming majority of South Africans reject the essence of this promotional blurb as an outright lie. Her summary of the Operation Kindle findings (below) reflects this public distaste.•The majority of respondents feel that the SABC's news is biased towards the ANC;•The perception of political bias and pro-ANC political reporting creates low credibility of political reporting among SABC News viewers;•Most consumers seek other news sources to find balanced political views of events such as Marikana or President Zuma's compound at Nkandla;•SABC1 is believed to be the more biased of the SABC's three free-to-air TV channels; and•There is a perception that politicians make decisions on content rather than the editors.Let's analyse each of the above-mentioned claims by the SABC:"SABC News plays a critical role in providing unbiased and reliable news..."Upward referral policyI sketched the origins of the SABC's de facto policy of 24/7 censorship of news damaging to the ruling faction of the ANC in 2002 under CEO Peter Matlare, the head of radio news Pippa Green and the head of TV news Jimi Matthews when it was called the "upward referral policy." Then came Snuki Zikalala's "Blacklist" which was fully supported by CEO Dali Mpofu and SABC board members such as Christine Qunta.Here is the opinion of Judge Neels Claasen on Zikalala's "blacklist" which was no different in principle or intent to Matlare's 2002 "upward referral" policy or its current counterpart, Hlaudi Motsoeneng's "70% good news policy"."Dr Zikalala's blacklisting of commentators perceived to be critical of the government of the day was clearly designed to silence their voices by not allowing them on air. "His purpose was obviously to manipulate SABC's news and current affairs programmes by excluding these critical voices ... To suggest that his blacklisting might not have had an effect is quite incorrect ... the truth could only have been established had both sides of the story been aired." Subsequent to the Claassen judgement the state broadcaster censored the booing of Police Minister Riah Phiyega at the start of the Farlam Commission of Inquiry into what it describes as the "Marikana tragedy" and what everyone else calls the Marikana Massacre; it also censored the booing of Jacob Zuma at the Mandela memorial service in Soweto and silenced the voice of Thabo Mbeki when he criticised the Zuma faction in an Oliver Tambo memorial lecture on 19 October 2012 - to cite just a few examples.Well-established reputation"We have a well-established reputation of uncovering, reporting and delivering news..."In fact, as I outlined in an article, "The horse has bolted - the SABC and Project Spear", the state broadcaster has a well-deserved reputation of abusing taxpayers' money for litigation to prevent the public becoming aware of corruption within the SABC. Examples include its attempts to cover the involvement of Matilda Gaboo in multi-million rand losses in the programme procurement department of the SABC - and news corruption - threatening to interdict the Mail & Guardian to prevent the public from gaining access to the damning report of the Sisulu/Marcus commission of inquiry into the blacklisting scandal. Where it has commissioned investigative reports on major areas of public concern, it has immediately refused to broadcast those programmes when it became clear that they were critical of the ANC and it has gone further and done everything possible to prevent those programmes from being aired by other stations "A significant growth in popularity of our news demonstrates the demand for our news content..."Yeah, right. That's why eNCA has double the number of viewers for its 7pm TV news bulletin without costing taxpayers a cent and why the Operation Kindle research project found that the majority of South Africans "...feel that the SABC's news is biased towards the ANC; most consumers seek other news sources to find balanced political views of events such as Marikana or President Zuma's compound at Nkandla; there is a perception that (ANC) politicians make decisions on content rather than the editors."Unrivalled coverage"We continue to provide unrivalled coverage of vital events in and out of the country..."Yeah, right. Take the SABC's 7pm channel 404 news bulletin on Sunday, 16 March. The Sunday Times front-page lead that morning read: "Zuma Ministers in bitter feud - Sisulu takes Mapisa-Nqakula to Public Protector" and the DA's David Maynier immediately issued a press release, "Lindiwe Sisulu blew R11m on luxury Gulfstream flights." The SABC ignored that story for obvious reasons and, also for obvious reasons, ignored a story headlined in City Press, "R70m cash crunch over Mandela memorial spend". This story showed that the ANC-controlled Mpumalanga provincial government is effectively bankrupt and unable to pay salaries. This is because the municipality diverted almost R40m into the account of Carol Bouwer to organise Nelson Mandela memorial events without soliciting quotes from companies other than hers and even though her company had not tendered in this regard. If the name Carol Bouwer rings a bell it is because her name was linked to the diversion of millions of rands meant for the promotion of the ICT Indaba into the account of Dina Pule's lover, Phosane Mngqibisa. In another ANC-linked corruption story, "Sannieshof's cash vanishes in the bras of workers" City Press revealed that the ANC-controlled municipality had effectively ceased to function but that money was being brazenly stolen from municipal premises. This, too, was not reflected on the SABC bulletin but the lead story on that bulletin was that Tina Joemat-Pettersson was going to use taxpayers' money to challenge the Public Protector's adverse findings against her ... Trevor Manuel is right to be perturbed.As far as the SABC's claim in its advertising promotion to give "unrivalled coverage of events outside the country" is concerned, the state broadcaster has virtually ignored the furore over recently promulgated laws in Uganda that actively promote the persecution of gays there because the ANC has not joined worldwide condemnation of this legislation.Wherever the news is happening"Wherever the news is happening, we'll be there to bring them to you at the right time..."Police Minister Nathi Mthethwa spent millions of rands to prevent the sitting of the Kate O'Regan/Vusi Pikoli commission of inquiry into the complete breakdown of relations between the Khayelitsha community and the three police stations in the area because the ANC knows that the situation there is replicated in every police station in the country. Mthethwa's abuse of taxpayers' money to litigate against the Commission delayed its sitting for a year and that is why the SABC has effectively given the Commission no day-to-day coverage, especially on its channel 404 7pm TV news bulletin.Every South African has been affected by the recent rolling blackouts and on Sunday 17 March, Carte Blanche looked at the quality of coal being delivered to our power stations, why Medupi is years behind its original completion date and billions over budget already and how this affects us as citizens.Go to the website of the SABC equivalent, Special Assignment and type "Medupi" or "Blackout" or "Load shedding" into the search bar on the site and the response is "No results". That's because electricity blackouts embarrass the ANC and it will cost it votes in the coming election. The state broadcaster accordingly remains corruptly silent on this issue and therefore in conflict not only with its code of ethical news gathering conduct but its brazenly false advertising.We lead - they follow "No one has the news covered like SABC news."This is the only statement in the SABC's promotional blurb that is true. Every major news agency in the world that was in South Africa in early December to cover the death of Nelson Mandela and its aftermath reflected the booing of President Jacob Zuma throughout the memorial service at the FNB stadium in Soweto on 10 December but there was no mention of it on the SABC's news bulletins because, as a City Press report revealed, this had been forbidden by Hlaudi Motsoeneng. For the same reason the SABC made no attempt to interview Thamsanqa Jantjie even though every major news agency covering the memorial service headlined the fact that a confirmed schizophrenic had been allowed, without security clearance, within metres of world leaders and interviewed him. This explanation for this censorship, according to SABC spokesman, Kaizer Kganyago was that Motsoeneng, and his news deputies, Jimi Matthews, and Nyana Molete regarded these incidents as trivial "side stories."The above-mentioned claims made by the SABC about its news coverage are not true and it has known for months via its Operation Kindle research that they are not true.This grossly dishonest, unethical but unsurprising advertising should be referred to the Advertising Standards Authority.
]]></text></news-item>