<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSJ-5WJ1-F11P-X1T6"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Amcu takes its fight to Amplats offices</title><source>Daily News (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Platinum mining companies were reverting to involving traditional leaders to end the wage dispute, the Association of Mineworkers and Construction Union (Amcu) said yesterday.
"That trick will never be successful. Traditional leaders cannot mediate in the wage dispute," Amcu president Joseph Mathunjwa told union members in Joburg.
"Their involvement will only result in ethnic violence in the platinum belt."
Mathunjwa was addressing Amcu members who braved the rain in the city centre to march to Anglo American Platinum (Amplats) headquarters.
He said that the union had written a letter to Police Minister Nathi Mthethwa, warning that firms and Contralesa (Congress of Traditional Leaders of SA) would be accountable should violence erupt in the platinum belt in Rustenburg.
"Only an agreement can end the strike - not traditional leaders," Mathunjwa said.
In a memorandum to Amplats, the union demanded that the company meet its R12 500 entry-level pay.
Contralesa president Kgosi Setlamorago Thobejane led a delegation of traditional leaders to a meeting with mineworkers in Rustenburg on Sunday. Thobejane said traditional leaders were involved in the dispute because the strike was no longer an an issue between employees and bosses.
"It is now a societal issue... its impact on families and business will soon retrench workers because the economy does not flow like before," he said.
He denied that the traditional leaders were being used to end the strike. "We told mining companies to give our people what they deserve. If they (the union) were in that meeting, they could have heard our stance."
Thobejane said union leaders liked to portray workers as being united. "On the ground, things are different. Individual workers want to go to work. They want to pay their debts and provide for their families.
"Our people deserve to be paid better, we need to do things in a respectable manner while waiting for better lives."
Another meeting would be held at the Olympia Park Stadium in Rustenburg today.
He said that traditional leaders were intervening in the strike to avoid bloodshed like at Marikana.
Forty-four protesting mineworkers were killed in Marikana during a wage strike at Lonmin. Thirty-four of them were killed on August 16, 2012, when police fired at them.
Ten people, including two policeman and two security guards, were killed in the preceding week.
Mathunjwa said the strike was about the huge inequalities in the mining sector.
"The deeper a mineworker goes underground, the more his pay remains small contrary to executives, the more they climb stairs in this building, the more their pay rises."
He said Amplats was able to pay the company's chief executive R17.6 million a year, but could not afford to pay mineworkers R12 500.
Company representatives took delivery of the memorandum, and said that Amplats was committed to finding a solution to end the strike.
Amcu members at Amplats, Lonmin and Impala went on a strike on January 23. - Sapa
Daily News © 1999 - 2014 Independent Newspapers (Pty) Limited. All rights strictly reserved.
]]></text></news-item>