<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSM-YWT1-DYT4-V4JK"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>The Wire: Flight simulator search; Crimea bases seized; Steenkamp was standing; Toyota to pay $1.2 billion; gibberish girl hits it big</title><source>San Jose Mercury News (California)</source><author>By Karl Kahler kkahler@mercurynews.com</author><text><![CDATA[FBI scrutinizes missing plane captain's flight simulator
The captain of the missing Malaysia Airlines plane used his home flight simulator to practice landing at several airports in the vicinity, and he deleted some data from its hard drive that experts were trying to recover. The FBI is analyzing the data on the flight simulator at the request of the Malaysian government, according to an official not authorized to give his name. Files containing records of simulations were reportedly deleted Feb. 3. The pilot, Zaharie Ahmad Shah, may have been deleting unneeded simulations to free up room on the hard drive, but investigators will try to determine whether he was trying to cover his tracks after rehearsing a scenario in which he would divert a plane for nefarious reasons. Other officials involved in the investigation -- speaking on condition of anonymity, as has been the norm on this story -- said the search for the missing Boeing 777 is now focused on the southern part of a southern corridor in the Indian Ocean. Officials were increasingly raising the possibility that if the plane crashed in water two miles deep without leaving a debris field, there is a possibility that it may never be found.
Russian troops storm Ukrainian naval headquarters in Crimea
Russian troops stormed the Ukrainian naval headquarters in Sevastopol on Wednesday, consolidating their military hold on the Crimean peninsula that Moscow now considers Russian soil. A Russian journalist who witnessed the assault said it was carried out by 200 armed men in Russian army uniforms and masks and by Russian Cossacks. They broke down the gates, surrounded the main building and threw at least one stun grenade, overwhelming the Ukrainians without a shot fired, journalist Oleg Klimov said. A second base was seized a few miles away at Donuzlav Lake, where armed pro-Russian militia broke down the gate of a Ukrainian naval base with a tractor, forcing the sailors inside to retreat. A day earlier, a Ukrainian soldier was killed in the Russian takeover of another base. Vice President Joe Biden, visiting Vilnius, Lithuania, warned Russia that the U.S. is committed to defending its NATO allies from any aggression. "Russia cannot escape the fact that the world is changing and rejecting outright their behavior," Biden said.
Pistorius' girlfriend was standing when shot, expert says
Oscar Pistorius' girlfriend was standing inside his bathroom facing the door when the first of four bullets fired through the door hit her in the hip, a ballistics expert said Wednesday at the double amputee runner's murder trial in Pretoria. Prosecution witness Chris Mangena's assertion casts doubt on the defense theory that Reeva Steenkamp was in the bathroom for the usual reason, rather than having barricaded herself inside it after a loud argument with Pistorius, as the prosecution claims. Mangena described how the Black Talon-style bullet is designed to open up and cause maximum tissue damage, with six sharp talons opening in a star shape upon hitting flesh. Mangena said when the first bullet struck her hip, Steenkamp immediately collapsed backward into a sitting position on a magazine rack and raised her arms above her head defensively. Pistorius kept shooting, and one bullet went through her arm, one hit a wall and ricocheted, and one hit her hand and went through her skull, he said. After the bullet struck her head, she immediately slumped to the right, he said. "I am of the opinion that after this wound was inflicted in the head she dropped immediately," he said. "Her head ended up on the toilet seat," he said. Pistorius has pleaded not guilty to murder, saying he mistook Steenkamp for an intruder who had sneaked into his bathroom at night.
Toyota agrees to pay $1.2 billion to settle criminal case
Toyota has reached agreement with the Justice Department to pay $1.2 billion to settle a criminal case involving how it dealt with the unintended acceleration that led to the recall of more than 10 million of its vehicles. "Toyota intentionally concealed information and misled the public," Attorney General Eric Holder said Wednesday at a news conference in Washington. "Toyota confronted a public-safety emergency as if it were a simple public-relations problem." As part of the settlement, Toyota will fully admit wrongdoing, pay the penalty and submit to "rigorous" review by an independent monitor, Holder said. Toyota will also be charged with wire fraud, though the prosecution will be deferred for three years while authorities monitor the company's compliance. The settlement is the largest criminal penalty ever imposed on a U.S. automaker. Christopher P. Reynolds, chief legal officer for Toyota Motor North America, said the company "took full responsibility" for its actions. "In the more than four years since these recalls, we have gone back to basics at Toyota to put our customers first," he said in a statement. "We have made fundamental changes across our global operations to become a more responsive company -- listening better to our customers' needs and proactively taking action to serve them."
twitter.com/karl_kahler.
]]></text></news-item>