<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSM-PNY1-JBF5-T3J8"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Green group questions CSG regulation after contamination scare</title><source>ABC Regional News (Australia)</source><author>By Sam Burgess</author><text><![CDATA[An environmental group says it has concerns about the lack of oversight on the use of chemicals in the coal seam gas (CSG) industry.
Work has resumed on five Origin Energy rigs in the Surat Basin after it was stopped last week when it was revealed asbestos had been found in a powder used in the drilling process
Doctors for the Environment Australia spokeswoman Merryn Redenbach says the incident shows the dangers of chemical use in the industry.
"We do know that only a handful of chemicals used in the industry have any sort of assessment by our national chemical regulator and in this case we've seen that even products that were supposedly innocuous contain compounds that are a serious health risk," she said.
She says more work needs to be done to ensure workers and the public are not exposed to danger.
"Our view is that this demonstrates a genuine vulnerability of Australians to the potential health risks from inadequate independent assessment and regulation of the unconventional gas industry," she said.
Investigation
Origin Energy's Phil Craig says testing has cleared a number of worksites of contamination and affected workers are being monitored.
"First and foremost we're working through who, if anyone, might have been exposed and then if there are any consequences and what they might be and we're making sure they get the best of advice in that sense, health experts and medical experts," he said.
Mr Craig says the product that caused the contamination scare is no longer being used.
He says work on another seven rigs should start within days.
"So we're working through an investigation that will continue around what exactly happened, who has been potentially exposed, what the exposure might mean and we've got all the right specialists involved and that process will continue," he said.
]]></text></news-item>