<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSM-SM81-DYTJ-G2JN"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>BIR chief faces criminal charges for not collecting P1.56B in taxes</title><source>BusinessWorld</source><author>Imee Charlee C. Delavin</author><text><![CDATA[BUREAU OF Internal Revenue (BIR) Commissioner Kim S. Jacinto-Henares faces criminal and administrative complaint before the Office of the Ombudsman for allegedly "intentionally" failing to collect some P1.56 billion in tax deficiency from Golden Donuts, Inc. (GDI).
In a six-page complaint filed last March 17, former BIR revenue officer 2 Othello E. Dalanon said Ms. Henares and BIR deputy commissioner Estela V. Sales should be charged with violation of Republic Act 3019 or the Anti-Graft and Corrupt Practices Act for their alleged grave misconduct and gross neglect of duty after "deliberately" not collecting said tax deficiency from GDI, which is the exclusive Philippine franchisee of the global fastfood restaurant chain Dunkin' Donuts.
Mr. Dalanon was assigned to the BIR's National Investigation Division but resigned in June 2013 after 28 years of service "because of the irregularities I discovered," as he noted that he conducted a probe on GDI's 2007 financial records in 2008, and found out the alleged discrepancies in the firm's declared sales and tax returns.
He noted that GDI's registered books of accounts showed that its net income for 2007 was P135.3 million while its annual income tax return (AITR) reflected a net income of P44.9 million.
"The books, however, showed that its sales amounted to P1.93 billion, but the amount declared in its AITR was only P1.03 billion, or an underdeclaration of P897.2 million," he said.
Mr. Dalanon added that based on other "independent" documents such as Franchise Agreement, Technical Service Agreement, and Final Withholding Tax Remittance Returns, GDI's sales even reached P2.37 billion "but the amount recorded in its registered books was only P1.93 billion or an unrecorded and undeclared sales was P438.1 million."
Using said records on the company's sales and tax returns, he said GDI still owes the government more than P1.56 billion based on his assessment, including surcharges and interests.
Mr. Dalanon in his complaint said he had reported the case to Ms. Henares in October 2010, and recommended to the BIR chief the filing of tax evasion charges against GDI under the commission's Run After Tax Evaders (RATE) program.
However, he noted that the BIR later referred the case to Ms. Sales, "who refused to act appropriately on the irregularity discovered."
Mr. Dalanon added that from Sept. 13, 2012 to Nov. 28, 2013, he had sent six e-mails and letters to the BIR chief to remind her of the "findings."
"It is apparent that targets set by the bureau have not been met to great prejudice of the Filipino people for reasons such as the instant case. Taxes due from large taxpayers are deliberately not being collected by the respondents," he said in his complaint.
With this, Mr. Dalanon asked the Office of the Ombudsman to place the respondents "immediately" under preventive suspension "so as to prevent tempering of original records, which are relevant to the prosecution of this case, as well as prevent them from influencing subordinates who could shed light on this documented irregularity."
He also urge the Ombudsman to charge the respondents with grave misconduct and gross neglect of duty in "violation of the National Internal Revenue Code (NIRC), particularly "Section 269 (e) neglecting or by design permitting the violation of the law by any other person, and 269 (h) having knowledge or information of any violation of this code or of any fraud committed on the revenues collectible by the BIR, failure to report such knowledge or information to their superior officer, or failure to report as otherwise required by law."
Before filing his complaint against the two BIR officials, Mr. Dalanon wrote a letter to President Benigno S. C. Aquino III last March 16, informing Mr. Aquino of the alleged "intentional" failure of the BIR to collect 2007 tax assessment deficiencies from GDI.
GDI is owned by the Prieto family, which owns the local franchise of pizza restaurant chain Shakey's.
The family also owns other restaurants, including Tia Marias, Pazzo Gelato, Gourmet Palate, Via Mare, Racks and La Tasca.
The Prietos also own the newspaper Philippine Daily Inquirer.
]]></text></news-item>