<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSM-N6C1-DXKS-J3MR"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>J.F. Lehman Welcomes Thomas M. Dyer to Operating Executive Board</title><source>PR Newswire Europe</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ J.F. Lehman & Company, a leading middle-market private equity firm focused on the defense, aerospace and maritime sectors, is pleased to announce the addition of Thomas M. Dyer to its Operating Executive Board ("OEB"). The OEB is a group of seasoned industry and government executives who have significant experience in the firm's target industries. Through key relationships and sector-specific knowledge, OEB members contribute to sourcing and evaluating transactions, advising on portfolio company strategy and recruiting senior level portfolio company management.  
Logo -http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20091221/NY29520LOGO
Mr. Dyer is a recognized leader in the fields of international maritime law and regulation, government contracting and foreign trade. As a skilled strategist and negotiator, Mr. Dyer's regulatory experience includes issues arising under environmental laws, government contract proceedings and customs and foreign-trade regulations. He has advised on a wide range of maritime projects involving U.S. Navy construction, foreign and domestic commercial vessel and offshore drilling construction and vessel operations.
"Mike brings not only an exceptional reputation for business acumen and leadership to our firm, but also a deep knowledge of the maritime industry and government contracting - which are critical to our investment strategy. We are delighted to welcome him aboard," stated Dr. John F. Lehman, Chairman of J.F. Lehman & Company.
Mr. Dyer's distinguished legal career includes his tenure as Co-Chairman of Blank Rome LLP, a leading international law firm, from 2008 through his retirement in 2013. Earlier in his career he founded the law firm of Dyer Ellis & Joseph, which merged with Blank Rome in 2003. Previously, Mr. Dyer served in the U.S. Navy and received a B.A. from Georgetown University and a J.D. with Highest Honors from George Washington University.
About J.F. Lehman & Company, Inc.
J.F. Lehman & Company is a leading middle-market private equity firm focused primarily on the maritime, defense, and aerospace sectors.
For more information about J.F. Lehman & Company, please visithttp://www.jflpartners.com. 
]]></text></news-item>