<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSM-P6N1-JD87-S16M"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Pentagon To Enhance Internal Security Based On Navy Yard Shooting Review</title><source>RTT News (United States)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[(RTTNews) - US Defense Secretary Chuck Hagel announced the Defense Department will implement a series of recommendations to enhance security based on reviews of last year's shooting rampage that left 12 workers dead at the Washington Navy Yard.
Security measures include establishing an insider threat management and analysis center and automated checks of personnel with access to DOD facilities or classified information.
Following the tragedy, Hagel appointed an independent panel co-chaired by retired Navy Adm. Eric Olson and former Assistant Secretary of Defense Paul Stockton to take a bigger-picture look at the challenges of revamping the security clearance process in the United States.
Six months after a disturbed federal contractor shot 12 fellow workers to death, Hagel briefed Pentagon reporters on Tuesday on the recommendations of the review panels.
"The reviews identified troubling gaps in DOD's ability to detect, prevent and respond to instances where someone working for us -- a government employee, a member of our military or a contractor -- decides to inflict harm on this institution and its people," Hagel said.
To close these gaps, DOD will take four actions recommended by the reviewers, he added.
DOD will implement a continuous evaluation program of personnel with access to its facilities or classified information, including DOD contractors and military and civilian personnel. The secretary said he is directing the department to establish automated reviews of cleared personnel that will continuously pull information from law enforcement and other relevant databases. This will help trigger an alert if derogatory information such as an arrest becomes available for someone holding a security clearance.
DOD will establish an Insider Threat Management and Analysis Center that quickly analyzes the results of the automated record checks, helps connect the dots, and determines whether follow-up action is needed. The center also will advise and support Department of Defense components to ensure appropriate action is taken on each case.
DOD will centralize authority and accountability for physical and personal security under a single staff assistant located in the Office of the Undersecretary of Defense for Intelligence. "This action will identify one person within DOD who is responsible for leading efforts to counter insider threats," Hagel noted.
DOD will accelerate development of the Defense Manpower Data Center's Identity Management Enterprise Services Architecture, called IMESA, allowing DOD security officers to share access control information and continuously vet individuals against U.S. government databases.
Along with these actions, Hagel said, the department will review how best to move forward on three more recommendations made by the Independent Review Panel:
The Pentagon will consider reducing the number of personnel holding Secret security clearances by at least 10 percent, a recommendation in line with October 2013 guidance from the director of national intelligence.
Reducing DOD's reliance on background investigations conducted by the Office of Personnel Management and analyze the cost, efficiency and effectiveness of returning the clearance review process to DOD.
Developing more effective ways to screen recruits, further destigmatize treatment and ensure the quality of mental health care within DOD.
Hagel said he has directed Undersecretary of Defense for Intelligence Michael Vickers, who led an internal review, to develop an implementation plan based on the recommendations and report back on progress in June.
For comments and feedback: contact editorial@rttnews.com
Copyright(c) 2014 RTTNews.com. All Rights Reserved
]]></text></news-item>