<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSM-V2R1-JCBD-D3YX"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Q &amp; A</title><source>DAILY MAIL (London)</source><author>BY NO BYLINE AVAILABLE</author><text><![CDATA[Money Mail explains what the pension revolution means to you.
Who is affected?
The 13 million people with the type of company pension known as a defined contribution scheme, or with a private pension.
In these funds, you and your employer contribute each month to your personal pension pot, which builds up over the years you are working. The money is invested in the stock market until you finally take your pension. On retirement, you may take 25 per cent of your accumulated pot of money as a tax-free lump sum. Most people convert the rest into an annuity. The changes also cover those with any form of private pension, but not workers in final salary schemes.
What is an annuity?
A type of insurance policy that pays you a set income for life in return for your pot of money. The amount you receive is based on how much you have saved up, and your life-expectancy.
Why have annuities been criticised?
Payments have fallen hugely in recent years. In 1995, a 65-year-old in good health with a £100,000 pot could have got as much as £940 a month. Today, the same pensioner typically would get around £509. If they wanted their spouse to carry on receiving income after their death, and the income to be index-linked, the monthly payout would be much lower. Also, insurers have been accused of ripping off pensioners. When workers retire, the company that has managed their pension fund offers a quote stating how much annuity income they are willing to pay them. But frequently these are not the best payouts, particularly for married couples, those with small pensions, smokers, and the sick. Millions of pensioners are thought to have blindly signed up to these deals without realising they could have received up to 60 per cent more income if they had shopped around. And once they have taken an annuity there is no turning back - if the retiree suddenly dies the insurer keeps the person's life savings.
What will the changes mean?
From April 2015, no one will have to buy an annuity. Retirees will still be allowed to take 25 per cent of their pension pot tax-free, but will then have complete control of their remaining cash. They will be able to draw out as much as they want in any given year, paying only normal levels of income tax rather than the punitive 55 per cent that currently applies.
Similar rules already work successfully in the United States, Australia and Denmark where savers are trusted to manage their own finances. In addition, from next Thursday, retirees with small pensions will no longer have to buy an annuity. Anyone with a pot or pots of up to a total of £30,000 can take it all as tax-free cash.
I haven't retired yet - how will I benefit?
You will be able to spend your pension as you like but if you run out of money you'll have to survive on your state pension alone. Significantly, any funds left over in your pension after your death will no longer die with you, but can be passed on to your spouse or children or other heirs. Your pension will form part of your estate and normal inheritance tax rules will apply.
I have retired and taken an annuity - what can I do?
Anyone who has already taken their pension is stuck with the contract they are in.
There may be exceptions for those who signed up for fixed-term deals or so-called draw-down pensions where their money is still invested, so they may be able to take advantage of the new rules.
© Daily Mail
]]></text></news-item>