<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-5TN1-JCBF-S3D9"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>UDALL, BENNET, TIPTON JOIN GOVERNOR, PUEBLO LEADERS URGING EPA TO ASSIST IN SMELTER CLEANUP LAWMAKERS REQUEST SUPERFUND DESIGNATION TO REMOVE LEAD, ARSENIC CONTAMINATION</title><source>States News Service</source><author>States News Service</author><text><![CDATA[The following information was released by Colorado Senator Mark Udall:
U.S. Senators Mark Udall and Michael Bennet and Congressman Scott Tipton urged the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) today to include the Colorado Smelting Company site in Pueblo in its Superfund program. The EPA Superfund program was established to clean up abandoned hazardous waste sites. Governor John Hickenlooper, the Pueblo City Council and the Pueblo County Board of Commissioners also are pushing the EPA to help with the cleanup.
From 1883 to 1908 the Colorado Smelting Company contaminated parts of Pueblo with lead, arsenic and other heavy metals, and recent soil tests have confirmed that the contamination has spread to surrounding neighborhoods. In some neighborhoods, contamination levels were found to be three times higher than average.
"Last month, we were contacted by local governments concerned about the health implications of this contamination, particularly on children," Udall, Bennet and Tipton wrote in their letter to the EPA's Office of Solid Waste and Emergency Response. "The local community lacks the funds necessary to remediate the pollution and they feel that inclusion of the site in the Superfund program would provide adequate resources for immediate and ongoing cleanup efforts."
"The community stands ready to partner with your agency to remediate the site in a manner that ensures the safety of local residents while maintaining property values and the reputation of the area," the lawmakers added.
To read the lawmakers' letter, click HERE or scroll below:
Dear Mr. Stanislaus,
We write to support the enclosed requests from Colorados Governor and several local governments that the Colorado Smelting Company site in Pueblo be included in the EPAs Superfund program.
During its operation from 1883 to 1908, the Colorado Smelting Company contaminated portions of Pueblo with lead, arsenic and a variety of other heavy metals. Recent soil tests conducted by EPA and the Colorado Department of Public Health and Environment (CDPHE) found that the contamination has spread from the smelter site to nearby residential neighborhoods. These tests confirmed lead and arsenic in several neighborhood yards were three times higher than average background samples.
Last month, we were contacted by local governments concerned about the health implications of this contamination, particularly on children. The local community lacks the funds necessary to remediate the pollution and they feel that inclusion of the site in the Superfund program would provide adequate resources for immediate and ongoing cleanup efforts.
While Pueblo supports including the site in the Superfund program, some concerns have been raised that a designation followed by a protracted cleanup effort may lead to lower-than-average property values in the area. Therefore, we are requesting that any EPA designation be accompanied by an action plan with a strict and aggressive timetable for completion of the cleanup.
The community stands ready to partner with your agency to remediate the site in a manner that ensures the safety of local residents while maintaining property values and the reputation of the area. Thank you for your consideration.
By: Mike Saccone
]]></text></news-item>