<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-M5X1-DXCW-D3D7"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>HUMAN RIGHTS COMMITTEE CONSIDERS REPORT OF NEPAL</title><source>Premium Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[United Nation Office at Geneva has issued the following news release:
The Human Rights Committee this afternoon concluded its consideration of the second periodic report of Nepal on its implementation of the provisions of the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights.
Presenting the report, Raju Man Singh Malla, Secretary at the Office of the Prime Minister and Council of Ministers, said Nepal was still struggling to manage political, economic and social transitions following a decade-long conflict. The new Government that included the two main political parties had raised hopes for a logical conclusion of the peace process and reflected Nepal’s aspirations to democracy, peace and stability, and fulfilment of human rights. The economic transformation of Nepal was a priority as extreme poverty was the biggest threat to the realization of human rights. It aimed to draft a new democratic constitution within one year, while the interim constitution enshrined a wide range of civil, political, economic, social and cultural rights. Legislative reform and protective measures were also presented.
In the ensuing dialogue Committee Experts expressed extreme concern about continued impunity for the most serious human rights violations, including war crimes, torture and enforced disappearance, and the lack of accountability and reparation for victims. Experts were particularly concerned about the widespread use of torture in Nepal. Steps taken to gender violence, trafficking in persons, caste-based discrimination and harmful traditional practices such as child marriage were asked about. Concern was expressed about refugees and asylum seekers from the Tibet Autonomous Region of the People’s Republic of China and Nepal’s respect of its non-refoulement obligations. Experts also voiced serious concerns about credible allegations of violence, death threat and reprisals against human rights defenders.
In concluding remarks, Raju Man Singh Malla said that Nepal was still in a transition period after a decade-long conflict, but was committed nonetheless to protecting human rights within the best of its capacity and resources. The Committee’s concluding observations would serve as a useful guidance for Nepal to better implement its obligations.
Sir Nigel Rodley, Chairperson of the Committee, said the Committee was fully aware that Nepal was in a transition period, and it welcomed the independence of the Supreme Court in protecting the rights enshrined in the Covenant and the constitution. There was still an impunity gap in Nepal, he said, adding that torture remained a serious problem that needed to be addressed both in law and practice.
The Delegation of Nepal included representatives of the Office of the Prime Minister and Council of Ministers; the Ministry of Home Affairs; the Ministry of Law, Justice, Constituent Assembly and Parliamentary Affairs; the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the Permanent Mission of Nepal to the United Nations Office at Geneva.
For further information please visit: http://www.unog.ch
]]></text></news-item>