<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-9M81-JCBD-Y2C1"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>ROW OVER 'PATRONISING' BUDGET AD</title><source>Press Association Mediapoint</source><author>David Hughes, Press Association Political Correspondent</author><text><![CDATA[A coalition row over a ``patronising'' Budget advert has been triggered by Tory attempts to highlight the cuts to beer and bingo duty announced by George Osborne.
Conservative chairman Grant Shapps used his Twitter feed to unveil the party's advert, which claimed the measures would ``help hardworking people do more of the things they enjoy''.
The image was widely mocked on the social network and Liberal Democrat Treasury Chief Secretary Danny Alexander described it as ``extraordinary''.
The penny off a pint of beer and the cut in bingo duty from 20% to 10% were minor measures in a Budget dominated by help for pensioners and savers.
But Mr Shapps attempted to give them greater exposure, encouraging people to ``spread the word'' on Twitter - leading to a series of messages ridiculing the advert.
Mr Alexander said it was ``rather patronising'' and ``demeans some quite sensible things'' in the Budget.
``There are good reasons to be supporting bingo, there are good reasons to be encouraging our pub sector to be stronger - that's the analysis behind those measures,'' he said.
``This language, well that's for Grant Shapps to justify.''
Twitter was awash with spoof versions, which included whippets, references to health care cuts and legal aid.
The hashtag #torybingo was trending with suggestions for number calling including ``Eton's Den number 10'' and ``Bullingdon mates 88''.
The dispute over the advert distracted from Mr Osborne's radical reforms to tax rules on retirement pots and new-style flexible Isas where people can save up to £15,000 without the Treasury taking a cut.
``The message from this Budget is: you have earned it; you have saved it; and this Government is on your side, whether you're on a low or middle income, whether you're saving for your home, for your family or for your retirement,'' Mr Osborne told MPs.
The Chancellor said people would be ``trusted'' with more control over their pension pots, and no longer obliged to buy an annuity at low rates.
Those approaching retirement will get free financial advice, and they will be able to draw down as much of their defined contribution fund as they want, even if they are in line for relatively small incomes.
Instead of being hit with punitive 55% tax on sums they extract from funds, they will instead pay normal tax rates.
Chris Sanger, head of tax policy for Ernst & Young, said Mr Osborne's ``great granny giveaway'' would ``make saving for a pension much more attractive''.
A new state-backed Pensioner Bond will help people who have suffered low returns since interest rates were slashed to keep the wider economy afloat in the wake of the crash.
Up to £10 billion of the bonds will be issued to as many as one million pensioners, who will be able to save up to £10,000 at interest rates likely to be 2.8% on the one-year version and 4% if they lock in for three years.
The cash and stocks elements of Isas will be merged into a larger tax-free vehicle, with savers now allowed to stash up to £15,000 a year in whatever form they want.
The cap on Premium Bonds will also be lifted from £30,000 to £40,000 in June, and to £50,000 next year. And the 10p starting rate for income from savings would be abolished, benefiting 1.5 million low-income savers.
Mr Alexander acknowledged that the greater flexibility on access to pension pots could lead to some people squandering their savings.
He told BBC2's Newsnight: ``I think people who save for retirement, people who have built up a pension pot, are responsible people who the state should trust.''
But asked whether they could blow the money on holidays, he said: ``I think that's unlikely, but it is possible that someone could do that, but that would be to their own detriment.
``Of course, if they chose to do that they would be taking rather a large pension pot in one go and therefore paying more tax as well.''
The Budget measures will come under independent scrutiny today as the respected Institute for Fiscal Studies presents its analysis of the tax and spending measures announced by Mr Osborne.
Lib Dem pressure to raise the personal tax allowance to £10,500 a year paid off, but Mr Osborne resisted calls from Conservative backbenchers - and two Tory ex-chancellors - for a significant increase in the 40p income tax threshold, which rises more slowly than inflation to £41,865 next month and £42,285 in 2015/16.
With ``grey voters'' more likely than other age groups to go to the ballot box, critics accused the Chancellor of a politically-motivated statement designed to appeal to ``blue rinses not blue collars''.
But aides insisted that the measures are of more benefit to people in their 40s and 50s preparing for retirement than those already of pension age.
Mr Osborne set up a political battleground for the May 2015 election by announcing a £119.5 billion cap on overall welfare spending, excluding the state pension and jobseeker's allowance.
Labour announced it will back the policy in a Commons vote next week, but with the Chancellor already seeking £12 billion further welfare cuts after the election, it seems all but certain that the Tory manifesto will promise to reduce the cap, forcing Labour and Liberal Democrats to say whether they will do the same.
Hailing the success of the coalition's austerity programme, Mr Osborne said UK plc will grow by a better-than-forecast 2.7% in 2014 and the Government will be back in surplus by 2018/19.
He highlighted predictions from the independent Office for Budget Responsibility (OBR) that employment will rise by 1.5 million over the next five years, with earnings growing faster than inflation in every year over the period.
``With the help of the British people, we're turning our country around. We're building a resilient economy,'' Mr Osborne said.
``This is a Budget for the makers, the doers, and the savers.''
Shadow chancellor Ed Balls said Mr Osborne would have to borrow £190 million more than he planned over the course of this Parliament, while social security spending had been revised up by £13 billion over the same period.
Apart from the bingo and beer measures, the Budget contained some other eye-catching policies, including scrapping the duty escalator on wine and spirits and £200 million to repair pot-holes, though tobacco taxes will go up by 2% above inflation.
Mr Osborne said inheritance tax will be waived when members of the emergency services die in the line of duty, and cash from Libor fines on bankers will go not only to military and emergency service charities, but also to search and rescue and lifeboat services, the Scouting movement and St John Ambulance.
Investment allowances for small and medium-sized businesses are being doubled to £500,000, one of a host of breaks for exporters and manufacturers.
In a signal that he believes ``green levies'' have gone too far, Mr Osborne unveiled a £7 billion package to cut annual energy bills for typical manufacturing companies by £50,000, while saving families £15 a year too.
Compensation to protect energy-intensive industries from the rising cost of green levies was extended, prompting Friends of the Earth to complain that the Chancellor was ``caving in to big business lobbying on pollution tax''.
]]></text></news-item>