<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-M5X1-DXCW-D53K"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Alaska: Environmental Program Specialist III (18-7825)</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The State of Alaska has issued the following Job Vacancy:
Job #: 03853Job Title: Environmental Program Specialist III (18-7825)Opening Date/Time: Tue. 03/18/14 12:00 AM Alaska TimeClosing Date/Time: Fri. 03/28/14 5:00 PM Alaska TimePosition Open To: Alaska Residents OnlyJob Type: Full TimeRange: 18Salary: $4,846.00/MonthDepartment: Environmental ConservationLocation: Juneau, AlaskaBargaining Unit: General Government
Job Description Benefits Supplemental Questions
Are you interested in the relationships between cruise ships and government? Are you experienced or knowledge about marine-vessel environmental and engineering systems? Are you experienced in wastewater treatment system design, operation, sampling, or permitting and compliance? Are you experienced in implementing environmental programs?
If yes, you may want this job!
We are recruiting for an Environmental Program Specialist III who is an enthusiastic self-starter that wants to work in a fast paced, dynamic, and unique program. The Cruise Ship Program (Commercial Passenger Vessel Environmental Compliance Program) is focused on monitoring and studying direct or indirect environmental effects from wastewater discharges and the opacity of air emissions.
You will share similar and closely related duties with a five person staff. Your duties will be assigned based on your experience, preferences, and the needs of the program—in relation to those of the other staff members.
You may be assigned duties from the following program areas:
Registration. Each commercial passenger vessel must register to operate in Alaska, each year. The Program works with computer support staff to make sure that the vessels can, and do, register online, and pay their required fees.
Wastewater. Each commercial passenger vessel must have the program’s permission do discharge wastewater in Alaska. The program participates in decisions regarding statutes and regulations for those discharges. And, the program oversees or participates in studies and projects related to wastewater discharge. Program employees may be required to conduct sampling.
Visible Emissions. The program monitors the exhaust smoke coming from commercial passenger vessels. Contractor and program employees certify as EPA Method 9 readers and conduct the monitoring.
Waste Offloads. The program monitors waste offloads when they are performed, or the waste is generated in Alaskan waters.
Ocean Rangers. The program places contracted observers, called Ocean Rangers, onboard cruise ships that carry more than 250 passengers. The observers monitor operational safety, health, and a number of other federal and state requirements; reporting results to the program.
Compliance Enforcement. Commercial passenger vessels must comply with each regulatory requirement that the program oversees. When a vessel does not comply, the program follows a continuum of enforcement options that officially recognize the non-compliance, and encourage and compel future compliance.
Administration. The program shares administrative staff with the rest of the Water Division. Certain administrative tasks are shared by programs, including by you.
We are looking for the following knowledge, skills, abilities, and experience:
Skill in analyzing and summarizing data as well as making recommendations Skill in written and verbal communication of technical issues to a general audience through reports, presentations, and question and answers with an audience. Experience with scientific and technical project design and implementation Experience with environmental permitting Experience with environmental compliance procedures Experience interacting with the cruise industry, other government agencies, non-governmental organizations, and the general public; Knowledge of environmental laws, statutes, regulations, standards affecting the operation of the cruise industry and vessel operations in state and federal waters. Knowledge of ship engineering, environmental practices, and environmental programs Knowledge of the design, operation, and sampling of wastewater treatment systems Ability to communicate effectively using desktop and laptop computers with MS Windows operating system and software, including Outlook, Word, Excel, Project, PowerPoint, DEC databases and Internet browsers. Ability to obtain the DEC inspector credentials Ability to obtain an EPA Method 9 Air Opacity reader certification Ability to obtain a Transportation Security Administration - Transportation Worker`s Identification Credential (TWIC) within the first year of employment
For Further information please visit: http://agency.governmentjobs.com/alaska/
]]></text></news-item>