<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-5TN1-JCBF-S3FN"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>DA VANCE: PHONY CONCIERGE SERVICES PROVIDER SENTENCED TO 4-TO-8 YEARS FOR DEFRAUDING CLIENTS AND EMPLOYEES</title><source>States News Service</source><author>States News Service</author><text><![CDATA[The following information was released by the New York County District Attorney's Office:
Manhattan District Attorney Cyrus R. Vance, Jr., today announced the sentencing of ROBERT GIULIANO, 38, to 4-to-8 years in prison for defrauding clients, employees, friends, and acquaintances out of thousands of dollars through a Ponzi scheme involving the defendants high-end concierge service company. On November 18, 2013, GIULIANO pleaded guilty to Grand Larceny, Identity Theft, Falsifying Business Records, and Scheme to Defraud.
Cybercrime and identity theft come in all forms, including Ponzi schemes, said District Attorney Vance. In this case, the defendant used posh hotel rooms and big ticket events to attract his victims, then stole their money through an elaborate Ponzi scheme in order to fund his own lavish lifestyle.
As admitted in the defendants guilty plea, GIULIANO created an online company called Giuliano Group Concierge that purported to offer discounted reservations at luxury hotels in Manhattan, as well as tickets to high-profile events, including award shows, movie premieres, fashion shows, and inaugural balls. Between 2008 and 2012, GIULIANO made hotel reservations for clients under his own name, accessed his clients credit card information without their authorization, and used it to pay for other clients hotel reservations, food, drinks, and in-room movies.
When confronted by his victims, GIULIANO lied and blamed the error on his employees. In order to reimburse some of his victims, he operated a Ponzi scheme, repaying previous victims with money obtained from new victims of the scheme. To gain their trust, GIULIANO falsified information about his education, degrees, business credentials, former employers, and professional connections. The defendant also used multiple bank accounts, credit cards, business names, email addresses, and phone numbers.
As part of his scheme, GIULIANO asked his employees to book hotel rooms for clients using their own credit cards. Under the pretense of being away on business or requiring an immediate reservation for an important client, GIULIANO told his employees that their cards would not be charged for the reservation or that they would be reimbursed for the booking. In fact, GIULIANO used the hotel rooms for personal use, billing the reservation, room service, and items at the hotel gift shop to his employees, who were not compensated for the expenses.
Assistant District Attorney Laura Millendorf and Assistant District Attorney Kenn Kern, Deputy Chief of the Cybercrime and Identity Theft Bureau, handled the prosecution of the case, under the supervision of Assistant District Attorney Brenda Fischer, Chief of the Cybercrime and Identity Theft Bureau, Assistant District Attorney Emilio Estela, Deputy Chief of Trial Bureau 70, and Executive Assistant District Attorney David M. Szuchman, Chief of the Investigation Division. Senior Cybercrime Analyst Benjamin DiNapoli, Supervising Investigator Robert Muldoon, Detective James Schweiker, and Trial Preparation Assistant Lucy Nicholas also assisted with the case.
Defendant Information:
ROBERT GIULIANO, D.O.B. 9/7/1975
Brooklyn, NY
Convicted:
Identity Theft in the First Degree, a class D felony, 6 counts
Grand Larceny in the Third Degree, a class D felony, 1count
Grand Larceny in the Fourth Degree, a class E felony, 1 count
Scheme to Defraud in the First Degree, a class E felony, 1 count
Falsifying Business Records in the First Degree, a class E felony, 1count
Sentenced:
4-to-8 years prison
]]></text></news-item>