<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-4561-JBV1-X181"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Asia-Pacific News Calendar</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Asia-Pacific news calendar from Saturday, March 22 to Friday, April 18:
Ongoing:
BANGLADESH: Cricket. World Twenty20 (until April 6)
GEORGETOWN, Malaysia: Squash. Women's World Squash Championship (until March 23)
IPOH, Malaysia: Hockey. Sultan Azlan Shah Cup (until March 23)
Saturday, March 22
VARIOUS DATELINES: Chinese president Xi Jinping sets off on a European tour, taking in the Netherlands, France, Germany and Belgium (until April 1)
MELBOURNE: Athletics. Melbourne World Challenge
SYDNEY: Baseball. Arizona Diamondbacks v Los Angeles Dodgers (until March 23)
TOKYO: Rugby Union. Japan Sevens (until March 23)
VARIOUS DATELINES: Rugby Union. Super 15
Sunday, March 23
ISLAMABAD: Pakistan National Day
VARIOUS DATELINES: Rugby Union. Super 15
Monday, March 24
HONG KONG: Chinese oil giant Sinopec releases 2013 full year results.
PHNOM PENH: Cambodian court to deliver verdict in the trial of a British national accused of sexually abusing three children
SINGAPORE: Global Internet group ICANN holds meeting on the web's future after the US government said it was giving up its key role overseeing the Internet's technical operations, handing over those functions to "the global multi-stakeholder community" (until March 27)
YANGON: Myanmar Civil Aviation Development Conference
SAITAMA, Japan: Figure skating. World championships (until March 30, day of the gala exhibition)
Tuesday, March 25
HONG KONG: Court proceedings continue against the employer of Indonesian domestic helper Erwiana Sulistyaningsih, who was allegedly tortured
MANILA: January imports data
KUALA LUMPUR: Squash. Kuala Lumpur Open (until March 30)
YOKOHAMA, Japan: UN Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) (until March 31)
Wednesday, March 26
KUALA LUMPUR: Laureus World Sports Awards
SYDNEY: Football. 2015 Asian Cup draw
TOKYO: Boxing. Kohei Kono (JPN) v Denkaosan Kaovichit (THA) in a bout to decide the WBA super flyweight champion
Thursday, March 27
MACAU: Movie stars attend the annual Asian Film Awards
MANILA: Central bank monetary board meeting to set interest rates
NAYPYIDAW: Annual Armed Forces Day
TAIPEI: Central Bank board meeting
JAKARTA, Indonesia: Golf. OneAsia. Indonesia PGA Championship (until March 30)
KUALA LUMPUR: Golf. EurAsia Cup (until March 29)
Friday, March 28
PHNOM PENH: Cambodian court to deliver verdict in appeal of French journalist Daniel Lainé, sentenced in absentia to seven years in jail on sex charges that rights groups say are linked to his investigative work
TOKYO: February unemployment, inflation data
HONG KONG: Rugby Union. Hong Kong Sevens (until March 30)
SEPANG, Malaysia: Formula One. Malaysian Grand Prix (until March 30)
MELBOURNE: Swimming. Commonwealth Games trials (until April 6)
VARIOUS DATELINES: Rugby Union. Super 15
Saturday, March 29
BANGKOK: Deadline for Thai premier to submit a defence over negligence charges that could lead to her removal from office
SINGAPORE: Cast of the movie Spider-Man 2 lead celebration of Earth Hour. Spider-Man has been named ambassador for the Earth Hour global campaign to draw attention to climate change
VARIOUS DATELINES: Rugby Union. Super 15
Sunday, March 30
KATHMANDU: Nepal celebrates Ghode Yatra traditional horse racing festival
BANGKOK: Nationwide election for Thailand's upper house Senate
TOKYO: New terminal opens at Haneda Airport, one of the world's busiest
YANGON: Myanmar holds its first census in over three decades (until April 10)
Monday, March 31
BEIJING: China Index Academy to release property price statistics
ISLAMABAD: A special tribunal hearing a landmark treason case against Pakistan's former military ruler Pervez Musharraf ordered him to appear in person or face arrest
TOKYO: February preliminary industrial production data
Tuesday, April 1
BEIJING: Official purchasing managers' index
HONG KONG: The Asian Development Bank releases its economic outlook for the year of 2014
JAKARTA: Statistics agency releases March inflation and February trade data
MANILA: The Philippines revives a much-criticised ferry service through Manila's polluted Pasig River
MUMBAI: Reserve Bank of India meets to decide on interest rates
TOKYO: Bank of Japan releases quarterly Tankan survey on business confidence
TOKYO: National sales tax rise comes into effect amid fears it will hurt consumer spending
BRISBANE: Swimming. Commonwealth Games trials (until April 6)
NEW DELHI: Badminton. Superseries. Indian Open (until April 6)
VARIOUS DATELINES: Football. AFC Champions League group games (until April 2)
Thursday, April 3
HONG KONG: Court hearing on a confiscation order for Carson Yeung's assets after the barber-turned-tycoon was sentenced to six years jail for money laundering
MELBOURNE: Athletics. Commonwealth Games trials (until April 6)
Friday, April 4
MANILA: March inflation data
HONGKONG/MANILA: Asian Development Bank releases latest economic growth forecasts for developing countries in Asia
NAYPYIDAW: ASEAN Central Bank Governors' meeting and Finance Ministers' meeting (April 5)
BUSAN, South Korea: Tennis. Davis Cup Asia/Oceania Group 1, second round. South Korea v India Davis Cup (until April 6)
MANILA: Tennis. Philippines face Pakistan or Vietnam in a Davis Cup Asia/Oceania Group II 2nd round tie
TIANJIN, China: Tennis. Davis Cup Asia/Oceania Group I, second round. China v Uzbekistan (until April 6)
TOKYO: Tennis. Davis Cup World Group quarter-final. Japan v Czech Republic (until April 6)
VARIOUS DATELINES: Rugby Union. Super 15 (until April 5)
Saturday, April 5
KABUL: Presidential and provincial council elections
MANILA: Former Philippine president Gloria Arroyo marks 67th birthday under detention and on trial for corruption and election fraud
Sunday, April 6
TOKYO: Boxing. WBC flyweight title match Akira Yamaguchi (JPN) vs Odilon Zaleta (MEX)
TOKYO: Boxing. WBC light-flyweight title bout. Adrian Hernandez (MEX) vs Naoya Inoue (JPN)
TOKYO: Football. J-League matches
Monday, April 7
NEW DELHI: Marathon nine-stage elections start in India with voters in the first two states and territories of Assam and Tripura heading to the polls.
TOKYO: Bank of Japan holds two-day policy meeting
WELLINGTON: Royal visit with Prince William, Catherine and baby George (until April 16)
Tuesday, April 8
BOAO, China: Boao Forum, a gathering of current and former political and economic figures (until April 11)
JAKARTA: Indonesian central bank holds interest rate meeting
TOKYO: February balance-of-payments data
TOKYO: Bank of Japan governor Haruhiko Kuroda holds news conference
SINGAPORE: Badminton. Superseries. Singapore Open (until April 13)
Wednesday, April 9
JAKARTA: Indonesia holds nationwide legislative elections
Thursday, April 10
BEIJING: Customs release March and first quarter trade data
TOKYO: Swimming. National championships (until April 13)
NEW DELHI: India's nine-stage elections continue with the capital and 13 other states and territories voting
Friday, April 11
BEIJING: Government releases inflation statistics
MANILA: Release of January exports data
VARIOUS DATELINES: Rugby Union. Super 15 (until April 12)
Saturday, April 12
LAS VEGAS, Nevada: Philippine boxing great Manny Pacquiao rematch against World Boxing Organization welterweight champion Timothy Bradley of the United States
TOKYO: Football. J-League matches
Monday, April 14
KUALA LUMPUR: Tennis. BMW Malaysian Open (until April 20)
Tuesday, April 15
VARIOUS DATELINES: Football. AFC Champions League group games (until April 16)
Wednesday, April 16
BEIJING: Government releases Q1 GDP growth figure and other data
WELLINGTON: New Zealand inflation data for Q1 2014
Thursday, April 17
KUALA LUMPUR: Golf. Maybank Malaysian Open (until April 20)
NEW DELHI: The biggest day of voting in India's elections with 122 seats of 543 in the national parliament up for grabs
Friday, April 18
SHANGHAI: Motorsports. Formula One. Chinese Grand Prix (until April 20)
VARIOUS DATELINES: Rugby Union. Super 15 (until April 19)
afp
]]></text></news-item>