<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-9M81-JBTY-T3VW"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>42 companies vie for new drilling rights in U.S. Gulf</title><source>Xinhua General News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A total of 42 oil and gas companies are bidding on new drilling rights in the deep waters of the Gulf of Mexico in a lease sale in the U.S. city of New Orleans Wednesday, with high bids expected to exceed a billion U.S. dollars.
The annual auction, run by the U.S. Interior Department, offers more than 40 million acres for oil and gas exploration and development offshore Louisiana, Mississippi and Alabama. The three blocks in central, western and eastern Gulf of Mexico open to bidding this year attracts oil-hungry firms to vie keenly for lucrative business in offshore drilling business.
According to pre-sale statistics released by the Interior Department early Wednesday, 380 bids on 326 blocks have been submitted for central Gulf tracts and three bids on three blocks for western Gulf tracts which are along the U.S.-Mexico boundary in the Gulf. But no bids came in for the limited stretch of available eastern Gulf acreage, generally viewed as less attractive to industry.
Major players among the 42 bidders include BP, Exxon Mobil, ConocoPhillips, Chevron, BHP Billiton, Shell and Statoil. It was BP's first time to join the U.S. offshore auction in nearly two years since the federal government issued a ban in 2012 barring the company from securing new contracts in the wake of the infamous 2010 Deepwater Horizon rig explosion, which killed 11 workers and triggered one of the worst environmental disasters in the country's history. Earlier this month, the U.S. government lifted the ban.
According to U.S. media reports, fewer companies make bids in this year's auction. During the last Gulf sale, 52 oil and gas companies submitted 407 bids on 320 blocks, with high bids totaling 1.2 billion dollars, whereas in 2012, 56 firms pledged 1. 7 billion dollars in high bids for 454 tracts.
Analysts say the shrinkage in bidders' enthusiasm is largely due to a surge in the country's onshore shale oil and gas exploration in recent years. Advancement in fracturing technologies has reduced the costs of shale drilling and made it more accessible to oil giants.
Thanks to its shale boom, the United States will surpass Russia and Saudi Arabia as the world's top oil producer by 2015, and be close to energy self-sufficiency in the next two decades, according to the International Energy Agency.
]]></text></news-item>