<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-7D01-DYY4-30GR"><date>2014-03-19</date><title></title><source>East Grinstead Courier and Observer</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[SUSSEX: The county's police have become the first in the country to attempt to quantify the scale of a scam mail fraud which is costing pensioners millions of pounds.
Criminals worldwide are sending millions of scam letters into the UK, targeting vulnerable members of our country's communities.
For many vulnerable people, the bombardment of scam mail results in fear, severe financial difficulties and ultimately a decline in both physical and mental health.
Working with the Metropolitan Police and the National Scams Hub (set up by East Sussex Trading Standards), Sussex Police has obtained a list of potential victims, containing the names and addresses of 1,537 people living in Sussex.
In Operation Signature, over the past six months, officers have spoken to more than 900 people across the county, who had been named on the seized list.
Owing to the age group of the victims, many had already sadly died, or moved.
From the visits they found that more than 400 of these elderly vulnerable people had lost a total of more than £2,000,000.
The majority of the identified victims were between the ages of 80 and 90 and almost all of these had not recognised that they were victims of fraud.
Among the victims is a Mid Sussex resident.
For further information on the background to Operation Signature and how to prevent this type of fraud see the Sussex Police website, found at www.sussex.police.uk
EAST GRINSTEAD: One of the world's top clarinet players is set to perform at Chequer Mead tonight (Wednesday).
Emma Johnson will be accompanied by acclaimed pianist John Lenehan for the recital.
The concert is being held in aid of The Loiyangalani Trust, which supports education in a remote part of Kenya.
Tickets for the show, which takes place from 8pm, are £17.50.
To find out more, call the Chequer Mead box office on 01342 302000.
]]></text></news-item>