<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-BB01-F11P-X0NR"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Former police official says PM ordered arrest of ex-military chief</title><source>Cihan News Agency (CNA)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ISTANBUL (CIHAN)- Former Istanbul Police Department Intelligence Bureau Chief Ali Fuat Yilmazer has claimed former Chief of General Staff retired Gen. Ilker Basbug was arrested on the order of Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan. Yilmazer also said the prime minister closely followed major criminal cases, including Ergenekon, the Kurdistan Communities Union (KCK) and OdaTV, and ordered some suspects to be arrested as well. "We did not arrest anyone [without the knowledge of the prime minister]. The prime minister supported all those [arrests.] Lists [of suspects] were submitted to the prime minister ahead of [police] operations," he said on Tuesday evening during a Bugün TV program.
Yilmazer was removed from his job and reassigned to another post earlier this month. His reassignment came as part of a government-sponsored purge of thousands of police officers following the Dec. 17, 2013 corruption and bribery operation, which also implicated some government members. Retired Gen. Basbug was arrested in 2012 on coup charges as part of the case against the terrorist Ergenekon organization, which was accused of working to topple the Justice and Development Party (AK Party) government. The general, who retired in 2010, became the highest-ranking military officer to be put behind bars in the Ergenekon case. He was given a life sentence in August of last year. When police first detained the ex-army chief, Erdogan vehemently criticized the move, saying he could not accept the charges of being a terrorist organization leader leveled against the retired general. Following Bagbug's arrest, Erdogan said it was his and his ruling party's preferences that the trial of the ex-military chief continue without his arrest. But, according to Yilmazer, who was once the star of the police department for his role in a number of crucial operations including the Ergenekon and Balyoz (Sledgehammer) coup cases, Erdogan himself ordered the prosecutors and police to arrest Basbug. In a riveting account of the critical investigations in which he took part along with the prosecutors, Yilmazer said no arrests took place without the knowledge of the prime minister, revealing for the first time Erdogan's deep involvement in the historic trials that tamed the once-powerful military. "Basbug's folder was submitted to the prime minister. The prime minister met with the justice minister and the deputy chief prosecutor. The deputy chief prosecutor later told me that the prime minister had ordered that Basbug be arrested. He looked concerned. I told him to do what was necessary," Yilmazer noted, adding that he does not know if Basbug was arrested in accordance with the law or upon pressure coming from the prime minister.
Jolted by a sweeping corruption case that broke on Dec. 17, 2013, and that implicated himself and his close associates, Erdogan then portrayed the Ergenekon and Balyoz trials as a plot to weaken the Turkish military, showing signs of backtracking from his former firm support of the criminal investigations into military plans to topple the civilian government. Earlier this month, Parliament passed a law that abolished specially authorized courts and reduced the maximum period of detention before a final verdict on the appeal to five years. The law allowed dozens of suspects in the Ergenekon case, including Basbug, to be released from prison pending appeal. In a stunning revelation, the former police chief claimed that Erdogan had taken part in every step of those investigations, weakening the prime minister's account. He said the police shared information before the trial began and that Erdogan had given his full blessing for the proceeding of the investigations into claims of the existence of the Ergenekon clandestine network and its plans. "We shared important information about Ergenekon with the prime minister. We carried out those operations with the support we received from the prime minister. The prime minister knew about plans to arrest the suspects," Yilmazer stated. OdaTV, KCK investigations The police chief also said the investigations into OdaTV and the KCK were launched after the prime minister gave the green light. "The OdaTV issue was not on our agenda. The investigation was launched after an order by the prime minister. He asked us to deal with the OdaTV issue, and we complied. He did not make any orders for arrest [as part of the investigation], but he was informed about who would be detained as part of the probe. A list including [journalists] Nedim Sener and Ahmet Sik was submitted to the prime minister," Yilmazer said. Odatv.com is a news portal that is believed to be linked to Ergenekon. Several journalists working for the portal were arrested. According to Yilmazer, Prime Minister Erdogan was shocked when he learned about the reluctance of National Intelligence Organization (MIT) members nested inside the KCK to prevent the terrorist attacks planned by the terrorist group. Yilmazer also touched upon yet another critical issue that wreaked havoc in the Turkish political landscape in recent years -- the prosecutors' summoning of MIT head Hakan Fidan. The call from the prosecutors on Feb. 7, 2012, was interpreted as a legal coup by pro-government circles, officials and newspapers against the prime minister himself for the Oslo Accords between the Turkish government represented by Fidan and Kurdistan Workers' Party (PKK) representatives to outline a roadmap to end the decades-old armed conflict.
Despite readings that the prosecutors aimed to end the nascent settlement talks with the PKK, Yilmazer said the call never implicated spy chief Fidan himself, but rather sought his information over MIT agents' dirty role in the KCK structure, which Turkish state authorities believe aims to create an autonomous body in southeast Turkey. "Hakan Fidan was not the wanted man. He was not targeted, nor was MIT as an institution. The prosecutors who called him only sought his knowledge about some agents' activities, which, according to Turkish law, are deemed illegal and a crime," he said in a televised interview aired on Bugün TV late on Tuesday. He said MIT had never shared information about KCK activities and attacks in cities across southeastern Turkey. Worse, he claimed, some MIT agents were involved in a PKK attack against a military outpost and took part in bloody activities. According to Yilmazer, the accusations raised by pro-government media that the Hizmet movement was behind the Feb. 7 summoning of MIT Undersecretary Fidan was only an attempt to cover up the investigation and served to divert public attention away from some dirty relations between elements within MIT and the KCK. Yilmazer also said the prime minister wanted the match-fixing investigation to be handled in a sound manner. "The issue had nothing to do with the Hizmet community. I was surprised to hear about statements by [Fenerbahçe Chairman] Aziz Yildirim [in which he said the investigation was the work of the community]. I have difficulty in understanding how they made Yildirim believe such a claim," he added. Commenting on claims of mass wiretapping as part of an investigation into a little-known terrorist group, Tawhid-Salam, Yilmazer said he finds the claims incredible as it is not technically possible for prosecutors to wiretap the conversations of up to 7,000 people at once, as claimed by a pro-government newspaper last month. "The Istanbul Police Department's Counterterrorism Unit has the ability to wiretap 2,500 people but no more," he said, but added that the unit cannot wiretap so many people because it does not have so many experts. "The unit can wiretap from 300 to 500 people at a time," he noted. On Wednesday, Republican People's Party (CHP) Deputy Chairman Umut Oran submitted a parliamentary question in which he asked Prime Minister Erdogan if he was really involved in criminal investigations and cases, as claimed by Yilmazer, and if he put himself above the law to punish some suspects. In his question, Oran also asked if the prime minister was really informed about details of ongoing investigations.
(Cihan/Today's Zaman) CIHANCopyright © 2014 Cihan News Agency.
]]></text></news-item>