<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-WBR1-JBVM-Y0RH"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Today's TV</title><source>Daily Mirror</source><author>JANE SIMON</author><text><![CDATA[SOAP UPDATE
EMMERDALE ITV, 7pm & 8pm
Marlon's 40th birthday starts out brilliantly as his friends pull out all the stops to make the day totally special. The bad news is this celebration lasts all of about 10 minutes. And disappointment quickly turns to disaster when he comes face to face with Donna - the woman who broke his heart.
She's got one present for him that he really doesn't want and it's not the sort of gift that can be sent back to the shop for a refund.
EASTENDERS BBC1, 7.30pm
With Janine, Alice and Stacey's freedom all hanging in the balance, Janine's trial takes a very unexpected turn tonight.
And while Kat's in court, back in Albert Square Alfie is in a right old pickle about whether to cheat on Kat with Nicole - the saucy Australian who was so smitten with him, she funded his new fast-food van.
DRAMA
TURKS & CAICOS BBC2, 9pm
Christopher Walken and Winona Ryder are two of the big Hollywood names making their British TV debut in the second instalment of David Hare's Johnny Worricker trilogy.
The first, Page Eight aired in 2011 and introduced Bill Nighy as MI5 whistleblower Worricker.
Several years on, he's now hiding out on the Caribbean islands of Turks & Caicos, going by the alias of Tom Elliot and reading Penguin paperbacks on a sun-lounger. Then, a shady American (Walken) strolls past him on the shore and seems to recognise him. Worricker accepts his invitation for drinks where he meets his PR woman (Ryder) and a trio of other unsavoury American businessmen, one of whom ends up dead the following morning.
Helena Bonham Carter flies in as an old flame of Worricker's from MI5 (who was never mentioned in Page Eight). But this is no Death In Paradise, but a rather talky, damp-squib conspiracy that's distinctly lacking in thrills. Nighy and Walken could have created fireworks, but this feels like a missed opportunity.
DOCUMENTARY
DANGEROUS DOGS ITV, 9pm
During the making of this programme, three people were killed by dogs in the UK and another 6,000 were injured. But the first episode in this two-parter isn't really about dangerous dogs, but neglected dogs, as it follows the work of council wardens Kelly and Kerry in Birmingham.
During one visit, they find an akita has been abandoned in a house filled with dog excrement. "I don't mind being killed by an akita, but I'm not being covered in poo," protests Kelly before the poor dog is eventually dragged, exhausted and dehydrated, out into the front yard.
In another stinking hole of a flat, a man is breeding puppies to sell down the pub. He has so little interest in the pups' welfare he's not even sure how many there are.
In St Helens, Merseyside, a shih tzu has been attacked in its home by four dogs that get in from the next door because their owner won't repair her fence. The message that dangerous dogs are created by irresponsible humans is pressed home again and again.
Brave beyond McCall of duty
DAVINA - BEYOND BREAKING POINT BBC1, 9pm
WATCHING these celebrity Sport Relief challenges can be an uncomfortably sadistic experience.
The fundraiser happens every two years so why, out of all possible months, they decided to schedule Davina McCall's 500-mile cycle, swim and run for February boggles the mind.
You'll almost certainly have already seen the footage of a barely conscious Davina being dragged out of Windermere with suspected hypothermia on Day Three.
An hour later she was back on the bike to cycle another 60 miles.
Bad weather turned a triathlon into torture and although the film is interspersed with footage of the women and children working in a quarry in Kenya who inspired Davina to raise funds on their behalf, it's Davina herself who you end up feeling the most sorry for.
If it had been possible to donate during this challenge to send Davina a neoprene guard to keep the biting cold off her face as she cycled in driving rain and 70mph winds then that's where the money would have gone. That, and tissues, as she is reduced to helpless tears several times a day before soldiering on.
The other person you'll feel sympathy for is her coach, Professor Greg Whyte, who has been involved in all these Sport Relief challenges and was beside Davina every step of the way but never gets any kind of fuss made of him.
One thing's for sure, Davina's next workout DVD should make very interesting viewing.
]]></text></news-item>