<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-B5S1-JD6S-R3G3"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>LETTERS TO THE EDITOR</title><source>The MetroWest Daily News (Framingham, Massachusetts)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Questions for town consultant
Once again Framingham has a familiar question to answer: Are we about to hear from an independent consultant, that is, one who has written a completely independent report with no interference from any town source and/or a hired gun that is one who has been compromised and/or outright told what to write by town employees?
Many of you will remember the infamous audit on the out-of-town Water & Sewer customers. I know many members of the Standing Committee on Public Works remember. It appeared that the consultant firm was so determined to keep its professional reputation that they stated in their report to the Town, that their report was not an audit report, even through that is what the Town had voted for. I have always admired their courage and their professionalism.
Now, we have been promised a full report by the consultant who had investigated the assessors mess. Among many things that the consultant had pointed out were wrong was that critical papers were lost. Will we find out who lost them? If not, why not? Will this report tell what those records were and were they reported to the state Department of Revenue, the district attorney or any other state officials? If not, why not? Will we hear of the billions of dollars in discounts on properties' true sale value not included on the Assessors' example of how the 2012 tax rate was set? Will we hear of the millions of tax dollars discounted and also never shown on said Assessors' example of how the tax rate was set? And of cause we must hear the answers to the questions of the Town Committee, the Board of Selectmen, Town Meeting members and others on who received the discounts on the 160 properties shown on the Assessors' own list and why they range from 5 percent to 95 percent strictly against the DOR regulations?
The list goes on and on, the question is, will the consultant go on and on or will the hired gun leave these questions remain unanswered?
FRANK REILLY
Framingham
Half-marathon too much for Ashland
All of us ask ourselves: what's in it for The Town of Ashland? The City of Quincy was right in sending the pre-marathon race promoters packing. The City felt the race was too disruptive and placed too much stress on the community and therefore could no longer support it.
Quincy city officials said they had received tremendous amounts of complaints about the race because the expansive event affected too many neighborhoods and roadways. Folks felt trapped in their homes due to the size of the race and the determination was made this was too big of an event to take place on a Sunday morning with many people unable to travel freely to and from church services.
The event is too disruptive, not only the road closures, but too taxing of our local services, like police personnel and the emergency stand-by ambulances.
According to an article in the Quincy's Patriot Ledger, the sponsors of the race, The Ashland Sporting Association (ASA), a non-profit corporation, said: "As in the fall race, a large portion of the spring half-marathon proceeds will go toward expanding Marathon Park and building a marathon museum in town." If that is true, why is there an article on the spring town meeting warrant asking the taxpayers to approve $275,000 for the expansion of Marathon Park, the Ashland Sporting Association project? What is the ASA monetary investment? Perhaps, they should show us the books and show us their money?
MARTIN ACEVEDO
Ashland
Ready for global warming
Forecast: More bitter cold and below normal temperatures. All right folks, raise your hand if you will accept some warmer temperatures. Just as I thought, the matter is "settled," we have a "consensus" in favor of some climate change.
BRUCE C. WESTER
Framingham
]]></text></news-item>