<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-9M81-JBTY-T40B"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Roundup: U.S. Gulf offshore lease sales see modest decline</title><source>Xinhua General News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A total of 50 oil and gas companies won bids worth over 872 million dollars for new drilling rights in the Gulf of Mexico at an annual lease auction run by the U.S. Interior Department in the city of New Orleans Wednesday, demonstrating a modest decline in both the number of bidders and in lease sales.
The lease auction offered more than 40 million acres for oil and gas exploration and development offshore Louisiana, Mississippi and Alabama. The three territories in central, western and eastern Gulf of Mexico open to bidding this year attracted oil firms to vie keenly for lucrative business in offshore drilling business.
Secretary of the Interior Sally Jewell announced in a press release that Wednesday's oil and gas lease sales for federal waters in the Gulf of Mexico garnered over 872 million dollars in high bids on 329 tracts.
"The Gulf is a critical component of our nation's energy portfolio and holds vital energy resources that spur economic opportunities for Gulf producing states as well as further reduce our dependence on foreign oil," Jewell said.
A predominant majority of the bids centered on blocks in the central Gulf of Mexico as 50 companies are set to pay 850.8 million dollars in winning high bids for drilling rights in the area. One company submitted three bids on three tracts in western Gulf along the U.S.-Mexico boundary while no bids came in for the eastern Gulf acreage, generally viewed as less attractive to industry.
The highest single bid Wednesday came from Freeport-McMoRan Oil & Gas, which pledged 69 million dollars and beat out five other companies for the rights to drill a lone tract in the Atwater Valley leasing area. The region, home to at least five discoveries, was freshly surveyed last year.
Freeport, headquartered in Phoenix, Arizona, is one of the world's largest producers of copper and gold. Freeport also left the auction with the biggest bill, having won 16 of its 17 total bids, with a price tag of 321.4 million dollars in the high bids.
The next biggest spender is Chevron, which scored 103.3 million dollars in high bids. Murphy Exploration and Production Co. follows with bids worth 49.8 million dollars.
BP spent 41.6 million dollars winning 24 of its 31 bids for Gulf tracts, including territory near its infamous Macondo well, whose rig exploded in 2010, killing 11 workers and triggering one of the worst environmental disasters in the country's history.
It was BP's first time to participate in the U.S. offshore auction in nearly two years since the federal government issued a ban in 2012 barring the company from securing new contracts in the wake of the Gulf oil spill. Earlier this month, the U.S. government lifted the ban.
According to U.S. media reports, fewer companies made bids in this year's auction and the government's haul also was smaller than previous sales. During the last Gulf sale, 52 oil and gas companies submitted 407 bids on 320 blocks, with high bids totaling 1.2 billion dollars, whereas in 2012, 56 firms pledged 1.7 billion dollars in high bids for 454 tracts.
Analysts say the shrinkage in bidders' enthusiasm in offshore investment is largely due to a surge in the country's onshore shale oil and gas exploration in recent years. It is also a reflection both of mergers among the firms active on the shallow continental shelf and the concentration of well-capitalized companies investing in the deep-water frontier.
Thanks to its shale boom, the U.S. is expected to surpass Russia and Saudi Arabia as the world' s top oil producer by 2015, and be close to energy self-sufficiency in the next two decades, according to the International Energy Agency.
The U.S. Interior Department said in Wednesday's press release that the country's domestic oil production currently is higher than any time in two decades, and that natural gas production is at its highest level ever. Combined with recent declines in oil consumption, foreign oil imports now account for less than 40 percent of the oil consumed in the United States -- the lowest level since 1988.
Offshore oil and gas in the U.S. Gulf of Mexico is a major source of oil and natural gas in the United States. The western and central Gulf of Mexico, which includes offshore Texas, Louisiana, Mississippi, and Alabama, is one of the major petroleum-producing areas of the country. According to the most recent available data provided by Wikipedia, U.S. federal leases in the Gulf of Mexico produced 463 million barrels of oil in 2012, which made up 19.5 percent of all U.S. oil production that year.
]]></text></news-item>