<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-R351-DXYD-M36R"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>South Korea to tighten quality controls in procurement</title><source>Jane's Defence Weekly</source><author>Grevatt, Jon</author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
South Korea's Defence Acquisition Program Administration (DAPA) has vowed to tighten procurement procedures following an investigation that found more than 200 local defence companies had allegedly falsified documents related to component certification.

DAPA said on 18 March that its quality assurance body, the Defense Agency for Technology and Quality (DTaQ), had found that 241 defence companies had given false information in 2,749 tests to certify military components and systems over the past seven years.

The inspection, which covered 280,199 military components, expanded on an inquiry undertaken by DAPA in 2013, following which it alleged that 34 local companies had falsified certification documents. DAPA has not identified any of the companies, but said 62% of the falsified testing documents were submitted by small and medium-sized defence companies.

In many cases, test results were forged to avoid disqualification or delays in supplying the product, said DAPA. The procurement agency added that any firm charged with falsifying testing documents faces prosecution and, potentially, a ban from bidding for future defence contracts.

Choi Chang-gon, the president of DTaQ, said in the DAPA statement that the results of the investigation would prompt a reform of procedures related to the procurement and certification of military components. "In light of the testing results," he said, "we will strengthen the quality control system and provide technical support for small and medium-sized companies to strengthen their competitiveness."

ANALYSIS

The investigation is further indication of South Korea's commitment to increasing transparency and accountability in defence procurement processes. This drive, which is linked directly to efforts to improve military and defence systems in the country following the North Korean attacks in 2010, has resulted in several cases of alleged misconduct.

In November 2013, Daewoo Shipbuilding &; Marine Engineering (DSME) was fined USD25 million for undertaking what the Korean Fair Trade Commission (KFTC) said was "unfair trade practices".

In 2012 the KFTC imposed a collective USD5.6 million fine on defence companies Hanwha Corporation, LIG Nex1, Samsung Thales, and STX Engine for what the KFTC said was alleged prearranged bidding on submarine contracts, while in 2011 and 2012 DAPA suspended trade with another 20 unidentified local companies over alleged irregularities.

Other measures implemented since the attacks include restructuring DAPA to improve accountability, introducing guidelines that call on manufacturers to publish details related to cost, and initiating a move to prohibit South Korean agents from taking more than 5% in commission fees.

Credit: Jon Grevatt Bangkok

]]></text></news-item>