<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-BH01-JC65-54TJ"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Tax cuts for oil drilling pass Michigan Senate</title><source>Associated Press State &amp; Local</source><author>EMMA FIDEL, Associated Press</author><text><![CDATA[LANSING, Mich. (AP) - A measure aimed at encouraging a type of oil drilling using carbon dioxide cleared the Michigan Senate Wednesday as nearly all Republicans backed a process that has divided environmental groups.
The tax cut proposal senators approved 25-13 is the last in a four-bill package that lowers the severance tax for drilling projects involving carbon dioxide. The legislation would allow oil and gas companies to construct carbon dioxide pipelines and would expand their authority to build them on private property.
Lawmakers mostly voted along party lines, with Democrats opposing the package. The measure now goes back to the House, which originally passed the tax cut 85-25. It's expected to reach Gov. Rick Snyder's desk soon.
The bills aim to increase enhanced oil recovery with carbon dioxide, a technique that involves injecting carbon dioxide into oil wells that have already been drilled. Since conventional drilling methods extract only 20-40 percent of the oil in wells, injected carbon dioxide can push "stranded oil" from the bottom of wells. The method can result in oil extraction of 30-60 percent, according to the U.S. Department of Energy.
Bill sponsor Rep. Aric Nesbitt, R-Lawton, said the legislation would make Michigan's drilling market competitive with other states', thereby boosting the economy and creating jobs. The bills will help produce "more domestic oil without having to drill a new oil field" or "import it from Russia or Venezuela," said Nesbitt, the Energy and Technology committee chairman.
Michigan's severance tax is 6.6 percent of cash market value for oil and 5 percent for gas. The legislation would lower the taxes to 4 percent for oil or gas extracted with carbon dioxide.
State revenue from the oil and gas severance taxes was $59.5 million in fiscal year 2012-2013 and is projected to total $62 million in fiscal 2013-2014, according to the Senate Fiscal Agency. The agency said the tax bill's fiscal impact is "unknown" because it can't predict whether it will spur production that wouldn't otherwise occur.
A Democratic amendment that also passed Wednesday prevents companies convicted of state anti-trust violations from receiving the lower rate. Sen. Hoon-Yung Hopgood, D-Taylor, said he introduced the amendment because Attorney General Bill Schuette recently charged Chesapeake Energy Corp. and Encana Corp. for colluding to avoid bidding against each other for Michigan oil and gas leases.
Sen. Rebekah Warren, D-Ann Arbor, said she voted against the bill package because cutting a source of state revenue to benefit "a really profitable industry" would send "the wrong message."
"I just don't think we should be lessening state resources at a time when we would need to do enhanced regulation and enforcement," said Warren, the Environment and Great Lakes committee vice chair.
Environmental groups agree that injecting CO2 into the ground is environmentally preferable to releasing it into the air, but they disagree on the legislation's overall effects.
George Peridas, a Natural Resources Defense Council environmental scientist, said that at a time when sustainable energy is still a luxury, enhanced oil recovery helps protect the environment by using existing drilling infrastructure.
The Sierra Club's Michigan chapter says the positive effect of CO2 sequestration will be outweighed by "the intense amounts of energy and virgin resources needed to build a completely new pipeline infrastructure." Sierra Club spokesman Mike Berkowitz said the group also opposes the expansion of eminent domain law to include carbon dioxide pipelines because "land owners have been trampled over and not had their concerns fully met" in past drilling-related construction.
The groups also dispute the technique's effect on nearby water, with Berkowitz warning that "all drilling activity creates potential water risk for contamination." Peridas says oil recovery with carbon dioxide isn't risky because there is typically "miles of rock" between injected carbon dioxide and groundwater.
The groups do agree that careful regulation is needed. The legislation expands the Public Service Commission's regulatory authority over drilling to include carbon dioxide-related production.
___
Online:
U.S. DOE: http://1.usa.gov/OBDETM
___
Follow Emma Fidel on Twitter: http://twitter.com/emmafidel
]]></text></news-item>