<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-9MT1-JC92-P0PD"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Russia has not ventured intervention in Ukraine, will back self-defense units - diplomat (Part 2)</title><source>Russia &amp; CIS Military Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Russia has not ventured intervention in Ukraine, will back self-defense units - diplomat (Part 2)
Russia will be supporting self-defense units defending civilians in Ukraine against extremists, but Russia has not ventured any military intervention in Ukraine, says Alexei Borodavkin, Russia's envoy to the office of the UN and other international organizations in Geneva.
"Russia will support people's self-defense units who have stood up to protect the population from extremists. But Russia has not attempted any 'military intervention' in Crimea or other regions of Ukraine, contrary to how the Kyiv authorities and their patrons would like to depict the events," Borodavkin said at the 25th session of the UN Human Rights Council.
Moscow is particularly concerned about reports on the plunder of Ukrainian military depots by nationalists, Borodavkin said. "More than 5,000 assault rifles and other firearms have been stolen, which gunmen could use against peaceful civilians," he said.
"We are outraged by the position of our Western partners, who, contrary to the opinion of their own parliamentarians and contrary to tragic lessons of history, actually facilitated the seizure of power by these radicals in Kyiv," he said.
The human rights situation in Ukraine is alarming, Borodavkin said. "A lot of instances of murder, torture, arbitrary detentions, and extrajudicial executions by nationalist gunmen have been recorded since the start of the crisis," he said.
A wave of reprisals against political parties unwanted by the new authorities has been observed, and members of these parties and their families are receiving threats of physical violence, he said.
"Employees of media outlets not loyal to Kyiv are feeling psychological pressure and violence. Some journalists and bloggers have been attacked and tortured. Arbitrary seizures of TV companies are under way in the country. Kyiv is blocking the reception of Russian [TV] channels on Ukrainian territory, so violating the right to freedom of the press," he said.
"It looks like these are the democratic values of which the European Union and the U.S. are saying so much to us," he added.
va cm
(Our editorial staff can be reached at eng.editors@interfax.ru)
]]></text></news-item>