<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-B5S1-JD6S-R2TN"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>nation</title><source>The Herald (Jasper, Indiana)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Bribery scandal
SAN DIEGO -- A second person pleaded guilty Tuesday to being part of a bribery conspiracy involving lucrative contracts to service U.S. Navy ships in the Asia-Pacific region.
Alex Wisidagama, 40, a resident of Singapore, pleaded guilty in federal court to scheming to defraud the U.S. into overpaying at least $20 million for supplies and services. He faces a maximum 10 years in prison when sentenced.
Wisidagama is a former executive with Singapore-based Glenn Defense Marine Asia, whose owner, Leonard Glenn Francis, is the key figure in the case. Wisidagama is Francis' cousin.
John Bertrand Beliveau, 44, a one-time senior agent with the Naval Criminal Investigative Service, pleaded guilty in December to leaking confidential documents to Francis about an investigation involving Francis that began in 2010 and then tutoring him on how to avoid giving incriminating statements.
Francis is charged with bribing Beliveau and two Navy officers with money, first-class travel arrangements, entertainment tickets and prostitutes in exchange for inside information about the movement of Navy ships.
The Navy officers allegedly ordered ships steered toward ports where Francis' company had an office. Francis' business then submitted bills that were padded or included services never rendered, according to the indictments.
The charges do not allege that the NCIS agent or the two Navy officers knew the bills were fraudulent.
The two officers, Cmdrs. Michael Vannak Khem Misiewicz, 46, and Jose Luis Sanchez, 41, were on the staff of the Japan-based 7th Fleet and privy to inside information about the movement of ships.
Crash kills 2
SEATTLE -- Witnesses heard an "unusual noise" just before a KOMO-TV helicopter crashed Tuesday morning, killing a veteran Seattle photojournalist and the pilot, a federal safety investigator said at an afternoon news briefing.
Investigators are looking into the possibility that the helicopter's main rotor hit the tail, but all potential causes are under investigation in the 7:40 a.m. crash, said Dennis Hogenson, acting deputy chief of the National Transportation Safety Board's Western Pacific Region.
KOMO-TV identified those killed as Bill Strothman, 62, of Bothell, a longtime station photographer who worked as a contractor for KOMO, and pilot Gary Pfitzner, 59, of Issaquah, also a contractor.
Gas main cracked
NEW YORK -- Investigators Tuesday said they discovered a crack in the gas main outside the two buildings destroyed by last week's deadly explosion in East Harlem, an indication that a failure in the main caused the catastrophe.
In a carefully worded statement, the National Transportation Safety Board said the 8-inch cast iron and plastic main under the street "failed the pressure test," which showed that the low-pressure pipe had a leak "adjacent to" 1646 Park Ave., one of the destroyed buildings.
While the NTSB report of a leak in the main will undoubtedly focus more scrutiny on that 127-year-old pipeline, experts said it was still unclear what caused it to crack and when the fracture occurred. A cracked water main pipe was also found in front of one of the buildings.
The NTSB statement didn't address what could have ignited the blast, something FDNY fire marshals are trying to determine.
Eight people died as a result of the explosion and fire on March 12 at 1644 and 1646 Park Ave., and more than 70 people have been displaced. Tuesday, the FDNY declared the fire under control.
Group following wolf
GRANTS PASS, Ore. -- Wildlife advocates are preparing to retrace the 1,200-mile path of a wandering wolf whose trek in 2011 across Oregon and California attracted worldwide attention.
Members of the Wolf OR-7 Expedition say they hope their upcoming journey will help build greater acceptance of wolves as they reclaim lost territories across the West.
OR-7 became an international celebrity after leaving northeastern Oregon in 2011 in search of a mate. Along the way he crossed territory that had not seen a wolf in decades.
The expedition plans to start in mid-May from a spot overlooking Hells Canyon, and cover 900 miles by bike and 300 miles on foot in 40 days.
The group includes a professional tracker, a storyteller, a documentary filmmaker and a multimedia blogger.
Rauner wins primary
CHICAGO -- Businessman Bruce Rauner defeated three veteran lawmakers to win the Republican nomination for Illinois governor.
In his first bid for public office, Rauner on Tuesday topped state Sens. Bill Brady and Kirk Dillard and Treasurer Dan Rutherford.
The wealthy venture capitalist from Winnetka will face Democratic governor Pat Quinn in November.
Rauner ran on a promise to "shake up" Springfield and the "career politicians" and special interests he says helped create Illinois' financial problems.
A virtual unknown when he got in the race, Rauner spent more than $14 million, including about $6 million of his own money.
Much of the money went toward TV ads that helped him increase his name recognition and fight back against attacks from organized labor.
]]></text></news-item>