<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-52Y1-DYWJ-F2B4"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Besso hit with £315,000 FCA fine</title><source>Insurance Age</source><author>Andrew Pearce</author><text><![CDATA[London market broker Besso has been slapped with a £315,000 fine by the Financial Conduct Authority (FCA).
The regulator said the firm had failed to take reasonable care to establish and maintain effective systems and controls for countering the risks of bribery and corruption.
According to the FCA, Besso operated a "weak control environment" surrounding the sharing of commissions with third parties which resulted in an "unacceptable risk" that they could be used for "corrupt purposes".
Tracey McDermott, the FCA's director of enforcement and financial crime, said: "Despite receiving two visits from us, and numerous industry-wide warnings, Besso failed to ensure that they had proper systems and controls in place to counter the risks of bribery and corruption in their business activities.
"Firms must play their part in preserving the integrity of the UK financial system, including taking all steps necessary to prevent financial crime. Where we find firms failing to do so, we will take action."
ControlsThe watchdog said Besso's rule breaches occurred between 14 January 2005 and 31 August 2011, with Besso in particular having limited controls in place between January 2005 and October 2009.
The FCA stated that although written bribery and corruption policies were introduced in November 2009, they were "not adequate in their content or implementation".
The regulator continued that Besso failed to carry out a suitable risk assessment of third parties before entering into business relationships and did not carry out adequate due diligence on third parties.
The broker also failed to "establish and record" suitable commercial rationale to support these payments, as well as review its third party relationships sufficiently on a regular basis.
The FCA cited that Besso also did not adequately monitor staff to ensure that suitable third party commercial rationales were recorded and that sufficient due diligence had been undertaken.
And it added that the firm did not maintain suitable records of its anti-bribery and corruption measures taken on its thirty party account files.
SettleBesso agreed to settle at an early stage of the investigation, qualifying for a 30% fine discount. Otherwise it would have been £450,000.
The FCA stressed that it is "still finding weaknesses" as part of its review of smaller brokers' anti-bribery and corruption systems and controls.
Several months ago, the regulator £1.8m over bribery and corruption risks.
And back in 2006, Besso was fined by the then Financial Services Authority for failing to apply for approval of a manager who had previous convictions for fraud.
For all the latest industry news direct to your inbox,
]]></text></news-item>