<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-P0F1-JD34-V543"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Water Holdings inquiry</title><source>Newcastle Herald (Australia)</source><author>leader</author><text><![CDATA[MUCH as Prime Minister Tony Abbott might have wished it could be otherwise, his embattled assistant treasurer had no alternative but to stand aside.
Veteran Liberal figure Arthur Sinodinos had to stand aside from his ministerial office, not because he has been found guilty of anything, and not even because he has been accused of any wrongdoing.
He had to stand down because the possible perceptions that arise from his involvement in a company and in deals subject to corruption inquiries would have made his position untenable - at least until those inquiries are concluded.
If the senator is as innocent as he has proclaimed himself and as the Prime Minister believes, then he may be likely to resume a ministerial role again in future.
In the meantime, he, his government and his party face some discomfort while the NSW Independent Commission Against Corruption (ICAC) probes the curious activities of a company named Australian Water Holdings.
Previously this company had been considered a potential liability for the ALP, given its links to the family of disgraced Labor identity Eddie Obeid.
Now the prospect has arisen that any odium that might emerge from investigations ito the activities of Australian Water Holdings might taint the Liberals as well as Labor.
Senator Sinodinos was chairman of the company for about three years and ICAC has been told that he was paid a $200,000 salary for about 100 hours of work a year.
ICAC has been told that Australian Water Holdings was at one time invoicing public utility Sydney Water for about $800,000 a month in expenses, not all of which were - allegedly - clearly explicable.
Mr Sinodinos was allegedly given a 5 per cent share in Australian Water Holdings at no cost while he was a Liberal Party executive. It has been alleged that he stood to get even more shares if the Coalition state government approved an extremely lucrative deal that the company was angling for.
Senator Sinodinos has said he can't remember Australian Water Holdings donating large sums of money to the Liberal Party, and he was "shocked and disappointed" to learn that the company he chaired was "financially linked to the Obeid family".
No evidence suggests any wrongdoing on the part of the senator, who has declared that he will be vindicated when the full facts about Australian Water Holdings become known.
While that unfolds, Senator Sinodinos has properly chosen to remove himself from the spotlight of ministerial responsibility.
]]></text></news-item>