<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-C111-F06S-P39S"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Kurion Establishes Tokyo Office for Cleanup of Fukushima Daiichi Nuclear Power Plant</title><source>Manufacturing Close-Up</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Kurion, Inc., a company focusing on nuclear and hazardous waste management, announced it opened an office in Tokyo to facilitate the company's growing role in the cleanup at the Fukushima Daiichi Nuclear Power Plant.
In a release, Kurion said that after the office opening, company executives attended an event hosted by U.S. Trade and Japanese External Trade Organization (JETRO) to facilitate U.S.-Japan cooperation for cleanup of the plant and surrounding area.
"Following the third anniversary of the earthquake and tsunami that devastated Japan and damaged the Fukushima Daiichi Nuclear Power Plant, Kurion's new Tokyo office is a symbol of our commitment to the Japanese to help minimize and stabilize nuclear waste at the site," said Bill Gallo, Kurion CEO.
The new office will be located in the Shimbashi district of Tokyo, within walking distance of the respective headquarters of the Tokyo Electric Power Company (TEPCO), the Ministry of Economy Trade and Industry (METI), and the International Research Institute for Nuclear Decommissioning (IRID).
Kurion said it anticipates initiating the hiring of administrative and engineering staff shortly.
Kurion has played an active role in the cleanup of the Fukushima site since 2011 when it was part of an international team of nuclear waste management companies to deliver the first external reactor cooling system. This system remains in operation today, and Kurion is the sole U.S. firm with a direct contractual relationship with TEPCO.
In February, Kurion acquired Vista Engineering Technologies, which is developing two Remote Manipulators for the respective inspection and repair of leaks within the Primary Containment Vessel (PCV) of reactor 2 at the Fukushima plant through a contract with Japanese industry company IHI Corp. The inspection manipulator will be delivered to the site in May 2014, and the repair manipulator is in the design stages. Kurion has also presented a variety of technologies to address other challenges at the site.
Fukushima Recovery Forum Demonstrates America's Commitment to Japan
After opening its Tokyo office, Kurion executives attended the Feb. 18 and 19 Fukushima Recovery Forum that commenced with a speech by U.S. Ambassador Caroline Kennedy. The objective of the forum was to facilitate U.S.-Japan cooperation to share experiences, expertise, and lessons learned in remediation and decommissioning for application at the damaged plant and surrounding areas.
"Kurion was privileged to be in a position where we could support the Japanese in the aftermath of the tsunami and earthquake," said John Raymont, Kurion founder and president of international operations. "Since then we have continued to develop and implement our own technologies and work closely with the Japanese to help identify solutions to the many challenges at the site. We are pleased to see the ongoing support of Ambassador Kennedy and other U.S. government experts to lend American support to a truly international cleanup effort."
Headquartered in Irvine, Calif., Kurion operates a technology development center at its radioactive materials licensed facility in Oak Ridge, Tenn.; a detritiation testing facility in Houston, Texas; three facilities in Richland, Wash., for non-radioactive demonstration testing, engineering and storage of mobile systems; an office in Loveland, Colo. for engineering design and development; and an office in Tokyo, Japan.
More information:
www.kurion.com
((Comments on this story may be sent to newsdesk@closeupmedia.com))
]]></text></news-item>