<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSN-N1R1-JCN4-H49Y"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>US LSB to cut emissions, pay penalty in NOx settlement</title><source>Chemical News &amp; Intelligence</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[HOUSTON (ICIS)--LSB Industries and four of its subsidiaries have agreed to reduce emissions of nitrogen oxide (NOx) to limits that are among the lowest for the industry and pay a penalty of $725,000 as part of a settlement with regulators, the US Environmental Protection Agency ([1]EPA) announced on Wednesday.
"In response to the Clean Air Act and state law claims, the companies have taken a constructive and cooperative approach by agreeing to implement global operational changes and mitigate past emissions. These actions raise the bar for compliance in this industry sector," Robert Dreher, US Department of Justice official, said in a news release.
The settlement, filed concurrently with the complaint, alleges that LSB subsidiaries constructed or made modifications to nitric acid plants that led to increased NOx emissions without first obtaining pre-construction permits and installing pollution controls.
In addition to the $725,000 penalty, LSB and its subsidiaries must continually monitor emissions and make modifications to meet new NOx limits, the EPA said.
The companies estimate it will cost between $6.3m and $11.7m to implement the measures required by the settlement, which applies to 10 nitric acid manufacturing plants located in Oklahoma, Arkansas, Alabama and Texas which are owned or operated by four LSB subsidiaries, the EPA said.
The EPA estimates that the measures will reduce NOx emissions by more than 800 tons/year (726 tonnes/year).
The companies have also agreed to spend $150,000 to remediate and reforest 10 acres (4 ha) of land with acidified soils located near one of the Arkansas plants. NOx emissions can contribute to soil acidification, the EPA said.
LSB, headquartered in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, is a major producer of nitrogen-based fertilizers and the largest producer of nitric acid in North America.
References
1. http://www.epa.gov/
]]></text></news-item>