<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-PFP1-DYJJ-P0GV"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Liberty Bell Bank blames $3M loss on alleged fraud</title><source>Courier-Post (Cherry Hill, New Jersey)</source><author>By, Jim Walsh</author><text><![CDATA[Liberty Bell Bank, citing the impact of an alleged fraud and problem loans, has reported a $3 million loss for 2013.
The deficit, equal to 89 cents per share, compared with a net loss of $3.4 million, or $1.12 per share, for 2012, said the Evesham-based bank.
Liberty Bell, operating under consent orders with state and federal regulators, blamed the 2013 loss "primarily" on an alleged scheme by a commercial customer.
Liberty Bell has sued Lease Group Resources of Mount Holly, alleging it defrauded the bank with a scheme based on the financing of phony equipment leases. The scheme caused a loan charge-off for the year of about $2.1 million, or 62 cents per share, the bank said.
A federal judge earlier this month appointed a temporary receiver to oversee LGR, which also faces accusations from Susquehanna Bank and other lenders. Liberty Bell said it still has $2.1 million of loans secured with leases obtained by LGR.
Liberty Bell will benefit from an expected $5 million capital offering later this month, said Kevin Kutcher, the bank's president and CEO. He said the offering's completion would put the bank in "satisfactory compliance with all of the provisions of the consent orders."
"This is the year we're looking at a turnaround," he added Wednesday.
Liberty Bell said it ended the year "adequately capitalized by all regulatory measures." In a lawsuit against LGR, Liberty Bell said federal regulators had reduced the firm's status from "well capitalized."
He predicted increased capital will allow Liberty Bell to sell some foreclosed property at lower prices, and that in turn will reduce the volume of problem loans.
Kutcher said the firm has made "meaningful progress in reducing problem loans." So far this year, transactions have reduced one problem asset by $1 million and provided a partial recovery of about $250,000 for another.
"We can focus on getting our loan officers back to productive lending," Kutcher predicted.
Liberty Bell has three offices, in Cherry Hill, Evesham and Moorestown. A Mount Laurel office closed in June 2013.
For 2013's last quarter, Liberty Bell posted a net loss of $656,000, or 20 cents per share. The year-before loss was $1 million, or 34 cents per share.
The quarterly loss included a $250,000 write-down as the bank adjusted the value of "other real estate owned," or nonearning assets, to market prices.
Liberty Bell also took a $151,000 prepayment penalty when it retired $5 million in debt with an above-market interest rate.
The firm ended 2013 with assets of $157.8 million, down $16.5 million from a year earlier.
Reach Jim Walsh at jwalsh@cpsj.com or (856) 486-2646.
]]></text></news-item>