<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-DPR1-F091-R1TJ"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>JZ's R215m splurge; He benefited improperly from security revamp - Madonsela</title><source>Pretoria News (South Africa)</source><author> Tebogo Monama and Lebogang Seale</author><text><![CDATA[SENIOR government ministers have defended President Jacob Zuma following the release of the damning Nkandla report.
At a briefing in Pretoria, Minister of Justice Jeff Radebe said despite Madonsela's findings that Zuma had improperly benefited from the R215 million project in the name of security, the government maintained that all renovations undertaken at Nkandla were related to security and no public funds had been used.
This came as the DA moved to impeach Zuma while other opposition parties called for criminal charges to be laid against government officials implicated in the report.
"The private house of the president was built by the president and his family. The retaining wall, cattle kraal and culvert, fire pool and water reservoir, accommodation for security personnel and visitors' waiting area are all essential security features which ensure physical security and effective operation of security equipment," Radebe said.
He said Zuma started building the home in 2008 and was paying a bond. He became president in 2009.
Radebe said the government was taking action to recover money that might have been wasted in the project.
The cost of the improvements has ballooned to R215m from the initial budget of R27m.
"The Department of Public Works has finalised the cost of apportionment of the project for recovery of funds from the SAPS and the Department of Defence."
The Department of Defence had set up a board of inquiry to investigate any irregularities that might have occurred during this project, Radebe said.
He said Public Works Minister Thulas Nxesi, Police Minister Nathi Mthethwa and their defence counterpart, Nosiviwe Mapisa-Nqakula, who had been implicated in Madonsela's report, would not be fired or resign until Zuma had pronounced on the issue.
According to Madonsela's report, Zuma benefited unduly from the upgrades.
"President Zuma improperly benefited from the measures implemented in the name of security, which include non-security comforts such as the visitors' centre, the swimming pool, amphitheatre, cattle kraal with culvert and chicken run. The private medical clinic at the family's doorstep will also benefit the family for ever," it said.
"The acts and omissions that allowed this to happen constitute unlawful, improper conduct and maladministration."
Rejecting what seems to have been Zuma's "I saw nothing or heard nothing" approach, Madonsela said he should have been circumspect. She recommended that he repay the costs incurred for non-security upgrades.
Madonsela also found that there was no lease agreement with the Ingonyama Trust for land used for a helipad, among other things, but Radebe insisted there was a deal. Madonsela also complained her staff had been intimidated by interference from the ministers during the investigation.
Basic Education Angie Motshekga said Madonsela should develop a thick skin.
"There should be no holy cows. We have always said she is free to conduct her investigation, but people also have the right to defend themselves," Motshekga said.
Radebe said the government would set up a team to formulate a full response. Zuma had issued a proclamation that the Special Investigating Unit (SIU) investigate the Nkandla upgrades, he added.
He said the SIU's report was expected soon. "This report will form a basis for disciplinary action and/or criminal charges against implicated individuals. The report will be forwarded to the National Prosecuting Authority for prosecutorial consideration."
Apart from condemning Zuma, opposition parties tried to cash in on the Madonsela report before the general elections.
DA parliamentary leader Lindiwe Mazibuko said she would ask Parliament's Speaker Max Sisulu to recall the National Assembly and initiate the process of impeaching Zuma.
Mazibuko said: "Today is a historic day in our fight against the corruption, cronyism and nepotism that have run rampant during President Jacob Zuma's term of office. It is a victory for the constitution and the rule of law."
The DA's Gauteng premiership candidate Mmusi Maimane said he would travel to Nkandla today to open a case against Zuma.
l Last night, Zuma addressed the second SA Premier Business Awards ceremony at Sandton Convention Centre.
Looking subdued, this was his first appearance since the release of the Nkandla report.
He spoke briefly about the achievements of government over|20 years and said where mistakes were made, there was room to fix things up and where their were successes, there was room for growth.
He reiterated the government's support for Brics, saying it was working well. An example was the 32 percent growth in two decades in Chinese investments
He said small enterprises were the cornerstone of business.
He made no reference to Nkandla.
See Pages 3, 7, 15
]]></text></news-item>