<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-P7S1-DY15-S2BD"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Kiambu Bar Owners Protest Levies</title><source>The Star</source><author>Stanley Njenga</author><text><![CDATA[BAR owners is Kiambu have said the levies charged by the county government are oppressive and are hurting their businesses.
Speaking yesterday in Kiambu Richard Kagiri, the chairman of the Kiambu Liquor Welfare Group, said since the county assembly approved the Alcoholic Drink Control Bill their business have been dealt a big blow.
"The Alcoholic Drink Control Act was hurriedly prepared and had no public participation nor were the stakeholders in the business involved in its creation. It has exorbitant licence fees and levies," he said.
Kagiri said the welfare wrote a memorandum to the county government seeking dialogue but it was ignored prompting them to go to court. Their case is ongoing at the High Court.
He said the bar owners are not against fighting illicit brews but are concerned that they are being charged alot of money to transact business.
Kagiri said the new fees amount to more than Sh 150,000 annually for various licenses and levies. They said if one wants to operate a bar in Kiambu he or she must have a business permit.
Kagiri said the permit fees have been increased by 300 per cent as they were paying Sh 10,400 and now its Sh50,000 annually or Sh 30,000 half a year, occupation license, public health license, inspection and application for inspection fees, garbage fee,music copy right fee, clearance certificate from Kenya revenue authority, catering levy, hotel license and tax to national government which is in a tune of 3% turnover.
"We are paying 0.04 per cent to mobile subscribers if one has to buy stock through phone services or Sh 25 per purchase if goods are bought through banks not forgetting amenities like paying staff , security, electricity, water and every purchase of Sh 24,000 the national government takes Sh 4,000 as tax,"said Kagiri.
"If a bar seller of owner is arrested the fines ranges from Sh 20,000 and above and one is guilty even if one has complied with everything and is under regulations which makes the trade vulnerable to extortion by enforces,"said Kagiri.
The welfare now wants a fair trading ground as other trades and be involved in making rules and regulations as they are the major stakeholders.
]]></text></news-item>