<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-D941-JC6P-C1MJ"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Federal government seeks extradition of ex-Tamaulipas governor</title><source>The Brownsville Herald (Texas)</source><author>Mark Reagan, The Brownsville Herald, Texas</author><text><![CDATA[March 20--The U.S. federal government is trying to extradite a former Tamaulipas governor and one-time Matamoros mayor on accusations he took bribes from the Gulf and Zetas cartels that derived from illegal narcotic sales in the United States.
Senior U.S. District Judge Hilda Tagle on Wednesday ordered the District Clerk's Office to provide federal attorney's with three certified arrest warrant copies for Tomas Yarrington Ruvalcaba in order to comply with Mexico's extradition laws, according to the order.
Yarrington, 56, former governor of Tamaulipas, is charged along with Alejandro Cano Martinez, 57, the owner of a Mexican construction firm, with violating the Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organization statute, conspiracy to launder money, conspiracy to defraud and conspiracy to make false statements to federally insured banks.
Yarrington is also charged with conspiracy to violate provisions of the Controlled Substances Act, two substantive bank fraud charges and conspiracy to structure currency transactions at a domestic financial institution, while Cano is separately charged with three counts of bank fraud.
Angela Dodge, spokeswoman of the U.S. Attorney's Office, Southern District of Texas, said Yarrington is not in custody in Mexico though authorities believe he is in that country.
On Tuesday, at the USAO's request, U.S. Magistrate Judge Ignacio Torteya III unsealed the December 2013 arrest warrant for Yarrington and Cano, but by deadline Wednesday the application had not been filed electronically.
The Brownsville Herald made multiple requests and attempts Wednesday to retrieve the arrest warrant application, which is a public document, from the district court clerk's office.
However, for unknown reasons the office was unable to provide a copy of it to The Herald.
The charges
According to the indictment, Yarrington took bribes derived from drug sales in the United States and worked directly with multiple cartels.
Yarrington, who was Matamoros mayor from 1993 to 1995 and Tamaulipas governor from 1999 to 2004, reportedly took numerous bribes from the Gulf and Zetas cartels to allow the organizations to operate freely, according to the indictment. At the time the bribes allegedly were taken, the Zetas were still working as the Gulf Cartel's armed wing, though it has since broken off as a separate cartel.
The indictment alleges that in 2007 Yarrington agreed with representatives of the Gulf and Beltran Leyva cartels to allow unimpeded access for large cocaine loads to the Port of Veracruz, Mexico, in exchange for a percentage of each load. That cocaine was then shipped by boat to the United States, according to the indictment.
The USAO alleges those drugs were sold in the United States and the proceeds brought back to Mexico, some of which were used to bribe Yarrington.
The former governor faces numerous other charges related to money laundering, structuring currency and making false statements to federally insured U.S. banks.
The RICO and money laundering charges each carry sentences of up to 20 years in prison, while conspiracy to commit bank fraud carries a possible punishment of up to 30 years. The drug conspiracy charges carry a term of imprisonment of at least 10 years and the currency structuring charges carry a possible five-year prison term, according to the USAO.
mreagan@brownsvilleherald.com
___ (c)2014 The Brownsville Herald (Brownsville, Texas) Visit The Brownsville Herald (Brownsville, Texas) at www.brownsvilleherald.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>