<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-2TY1-DXKH-N2R0"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Nachi-Fujikoshi: Decision issued by the European Commission regarding automotive bearings</title><source>News Bites Asian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
On 19 March 2014 (Central European time), the European Commission has taken a decision to impose a fine of 3,956,000 euros on NACHI-FUJIKOSHI CORP. ("NFC") and its German subsidiary, NACHI EUROPE GmbH ("NE") on the grounds that they, together with a number of their competitors, infringed EU competition law concerning the supply of automotive bearings in the EEA market (the "Decision").
NFC and NE have fully cooperated with the European Commission's investigation and the Decision was reached through a settlement procedure with the European Commission.
NFC takes the European Commission's findings very seriously and will ensure rigorous implementation of the compliance measures currently in place at NFC, and its group companies based in and outside Japan, and work to restore public trust. NFC expresses its deep regret for causing significant concerns to its shareholders, customers and all other relevant parties.
NFC will account for the amount of the fine stated above as a special loss in the first quarter of NFC's financial year ending November 2014. The Decision does not affect NFC's earnings forecasts for the financial year ending November 2014.
Source: Company Website
Recent TradingNachi-Fujikoshi (6474.TO) MCap is JPY159.5 billion (US$1.6 billion) at the last price of JPY640.0. The value of JPY1,000 invested one year ago is JPY1,671 [vs JPY1,142 for the Nikkei 225 Index], for a capital gain of JPY671. The total return to shareholders for 1 year is 67.1%. Year-on-year growth in EPS of 50% [12.6%]; rank 223 out of 600 stocks with positive earnings. Return on Equity of 8.7% [6.8%]; rank 683 out of 2070 stocks with positive earnings. Return on Assets of 3.2% [3.1%]; rank 949 out of 2076 stocks with positive earnings.
Currency Conversion: Japanese yen JPY1= US$0.0098 [or US$1=JPY102.04]; Against the US$ the JPY slumped 101.01 basis points (or 1.0%) for the day; added 1.0% for the week; was unchanged for the month; weakened 1.0% in the past year. JPY1 = 100sen.
ISIN: JP3813200007
TO:6474; TYO:6474; T:6474; JP:6474;
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>