<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-JBR1-DYS4-D43T"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Moscow press review for March 20, 2014</title><source>Russia &amp; CIS Business and Financial Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The following is a digest of Moscow newspapers published on March 20. Interfax does not accept liability for information in these stories.
POLITICS & ECONOMICS
Russia's Finance Ministry on Wednesday published the first bill in a package of measures against offshore tax havens. The bill on controlled foreign corporations would require all companies and individuals to pay tax in Russia on the income of any foreign companies in which they own 10% or more shares and to report ownership of 1% or more to the authorities or face fines (Vedomosti, p. 1; Kommersant, p. 8).
Ukraine decided Wednesday to pull its forces out of Crimea after its naval headquarters in Sevastopol fell to local forces and Ukrainian troops were told to either switch allegiance to the Crimean authorities or leave the peninsula. Kyiv also decided to withdraw from the CIS and impose a visa regime with Russia (Kommersant, p. 1).
Political sanctions will not become an obstacle to business and mutual investment, participants in the Russian-Japanese forum in Tokyo that closed on Wednesday agreed. Although Japan has announced sanctions over the crisis in Ukraine and frozen the signing of a bilateral investment agreement, business representatives, including Rosneft head Igor Sechin, said they do not intend to reconsider their plans. They reckon only a financial blockade of Russia could sever economic ties (Kommersant, p. 1).
Russia's Industry and Trade Ministry is proposing to create a fund of 30 billion-50 billion rubles with state lender Vnesheconombank (VEB) to lend to manufacturing companies for terms of up to 15 years at interest rates of no more than 5%. The fund is too small and businesses are not currently looking to invest, analysts said. The ministry is also proposing tax incentives for manufacturers (Vedomosti, p. 4; Kommersant, p. 8).
European Union leaders plan to adopt a new package of sanctions against Russia on Thursday. A number of EU members, such as Germany, Austria, Finland, Italy, Spain, Greece and Cyprus, will try to prevent the adoption of excessively tough measures, sources said. Analysts believe that at this stage the EU will not opt for measures that would hurt the business interests of Europeans themselves (Kommersant, p. 4).
The justices of the Supreme Arbitration Court are proposing to curb the aggressiveness of the Federal Anti-Monopoly Service in order to balance private and public interests. Reviewing the case of an Astrakhan utility, they ruled that the regulator's penalties diminish economic freedom. The regulator usually wins court cases, but recently the Arbitration Court has tended to narrow its powers, lawyers said (Kommersant, p. 8).
OIL & GAS
The Crimean authorities intend to reconsider the terms of production sharing agreements for offshore projects in the Black Sea that Ukraine has agreed to with foreign oil and gas companies. A senior Russian official said offshore projects in Crimea would become subject to Russian laws, which require state companies to control such projects. Gazprom could become the new participant in the agreements (Vedomosti, p. 12; Kommersant, p. 11).
Rosneft president Igor Sechin has increased his interest in the state oil major by 50%. The purchase could have cost him $28.9 million and he may have spent a total of more than $90 million on Rosneft shares. His stake of 0.1273% was worth over 3.1 billion rubles at closing on Tuesday (Vedomosti, p. 11).
METALS & MINING
Representatives of minority shareholders might join Alrosa's supervisory board for the first time. Lazard Asset Management has nominated Tav Morgan of Baring Vostok, a former chief strategist for Norilsk Nickel, and Thomas O'Neill, former president of Harry Winston Diamond Corp as independents to the Russian diamond monopoly's board (Kommersant, p. 10).
BANKING, FINANCE & INSURANCE
Moskomprivatbank, the Russian subsidiary of leading Ukrainian lender Privatbank, lost nearly a quarter of its liabilities within ten days after being put under temporary administration due to a run on deposits. The bank's assets shrank by 9.3 billion rubles. It continues to stock up on cash as the flow of depositors has not abated (Vedomosti, p. 10).
The Russian ruble is recovering ground lost due to the conflict with Ukraine. The euro dropped below 50 rubles and the dollar fell below 36 rubles on Wednesday. Serious sanctions have not been imposed against Russia, and speculators have begun to close positions. If sanctions are not forthcoming, the ruble is expected to strengthen further (Vedomosti, p. 11).
The syndicated loan market, which came to a standstill in early March, is seeing some movement. Russian iron ore miner Metalloinvest has signed a deal for a loan of $1.15 billion and potash giant Uralkali is closing a deal for about $500 million, as western banks took Russian statements on the Crimean crisis as a sign of certainty. But the ultimate fate of future big corporate loans will depend on the West's reaction to Crimea joining Russia (Kommersant, p. 9).
RETAIL & CONSUMER MARKET
The business landscape on the Russian cinema market could soon change, as the current owners of leading chains are prepared to sell. The most likely scenario is that billionaire Vladimir Potanin's Interros will sell its Cinema Park chain of 30 movie theaters, possibly to Gazprom Media, which earlier bought ProfMedia from Interros. But other players, such as Karo Film, are also reportedly interested (Kommersant, p. 1).
AUTOMOTIVE & ENGINEERING
French automaker Renault has launched production of the new generation of the Logan sedan at Russia's Avtovaz, but assembly of the old model at Avtoframos has not stopped yet. The two models will co-exist on the market until the end of 2014. The capacity freed up at Avtoframos will be used to assemble the Duster compact SUV, Renault's best selling car in Russia (Vedomosti, p. 10).
Interview: Bruno Ancelin, Managing Director of Renault in Russia (Vedomosti, p. 8).
Vp of
(Our editorial staff can be reached at eng.editors@interfax.ru)
]]></text></news-item>