<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-WB61-JCBD-K36K"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>EU fines SFK, Schaeffler, and three other bearings suppliers USD1.3 bil. in price-fixing probe</title><source>IHS Global Insight</source><author>Tim Urquhart</author><text><![CDATA[The European Commission has found six bearings suppliers - Schaeffler, SKF, JTEKT, NSK, Nachi-Fujikoshi, and NTN with its French subsidiary NTN-SNR - to be involved in price fixing of automotive bearings, according to a press release. The Commission has imposed a total fine of EUR953.3 million (USD1.3 billion) on five of these suppliers; JTEKT has been let off without a fine for blowing the whistle on the cartel. According to the Commission, these six bearings makers colluded to secretly co-ordinate their pricing strategy for automotive customers for more than seven years, from April 2004 to July 2011, across the European Economic Area (EEA). According to the press release, these suppliers co-ordinated in passing on steel price increases to their customers, colluded on requests for quotations (RFQ) and annual price reductions (APR) from customers, and exchanged commercially sensitive information.
Schaeffler was handed the largest fine of EUR370.5 million, followed by SKF with EUR315.1 million, and NTN with EUR201.3 million. NSK agreed to pay EUR62.4 million while another Japanese supplier, Nachi-Fujikoshi Corporation (NFC), will pay EUR3.9 million. These suppliers are eligible for a 10% reduction in return for their co-operation with the Commission during its investigation. JTEKT managed to escape a fine of EUR86 million. Schaeffler, SKF, and NTN were expecting the fines from the Commission and had set aside provisions to pay them.
Significance:The Commission began its probe into the alleged price-fixing cartel in 2011. As part of the investigations, the Commission conducted raids on several automotive bearings suppliers. Automotive suppliers are under scrutiny in key markets including the United States, Europe, Japan, and South Korea for their alleged participation in fixing the price of components sold to automakers. In the United States, for example, 23 companies and 26 executives have been charged by the Department of Justice and have agreed to pay a total of USD1.8 billion in fines. In Europe, last year the Commission imposed a combined fine of EUR141.8 million on four wiring harness suppliers for taking part in five cartels. In January this year, three suppliers Recticel, Carpenter Group, and Greiner Holding agreed to pay the Commission a EUR114-million fine to settle a probe into foam used in mattress and car seats. The Commission is expanding its anti-competition probe to other products including airbags and lighting systems. "We will not stop here - we are still investigating suspected cartels for airbags as well as lighting systems of the cars to mention a few examples," EU competition commissioner Joaquin Almunia told reporters in Brussels following the announcement of the fines.
]]></text></news-item>