<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-NCP1-DYR8-3349"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Liberia; Bribery Suspects Undergo Investigation</title><source>Africa News</source><author>The NEWS (Monrovia)</author><text><![CDATA[The Chairman of the Liberia Anti-Corruption Commission (LACC) Cllr. James N. Verdier on Wednesday revealed that the commission has received intelligence that some of the persons undergoing investigation for acts of bribery allegedly attempted fleeing the bailiwick of the country.
Although Cllr. Verdier did not name which one of the suspects attempted to abscond Liberia, but said LACC is currently probing the former Board Chairman of the National Oil Company, Clemenceau Urey and former lawmaker Alomiza Ennos Barr for alleged acts of bribery.
Cllr. Verdier's revelation was in response to what he termed as 'mishap' which occurred at the LACC when the two suspects, along with their lawyers, appeared for investigation.
Cllr. Verdier told reporters that the quarrel started when the bribery suspects said they were not making any statement to the investigators on grounds that they were held against their will.
The Anti-graft boss further told journalists that the lawyers raised alarm, which prompted investigators to knock the gate so as to prevent intruders from entering the premises of the LACC.
"One of the counsels said they were held against their will. LACC will not engage in violating anyone's rights or disrespect the civil rights of anyone," Cllr. Verdier assured.
Cllr. Verdier said LACC will not relent in doing the work of the Liberian people.
The human rights lawyer made it clear that the Act creating the LACC gives it power to arrest and prosecute individuals for acts of corruption, which he said, is a serious crime in Liberia.
He revealed that the commission has cogent evidence from the General Auditing Commission (GAC) report that Alomiza Ennos Barr allegedly received money to pass the oil law.
"She is a subject of the investigation. She received money to pass the oil law," Cllr. Verdier told reporters.
Responding to question whether or not Rufus Neufville, Chief of Protocol of the Republic of Liberia-designate will also be invited to help the investigation, Cllr. Verdier said the commission will follow where the investigation will lead it.
]]></text></news-item>