<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-NN21-JD6S-R3J3"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>$12.5M may be largest court-ordered fine for pollution</title><source>Tonawanda News (New York)</source><author>Jessica Bagley Jessica.Bagley@tonawandaNews.Com, THE TONAWANDA NEWS</author><text><![CDATA[Tonawanda News - BUFFALO - Tonawanda Coke's $12.5 million criminal penalty may be the largest environmental fine ever imposed by a federal court, U.S. prosecutors said, although companies have paid more as a result of negotiated settlements.
On Wednesday, Chief U.S. District Judge William M. Skretny sentenced Tonawanda Coke to the maximum fine for its Clean Air Act violations - $5.5 million. The plant faced another $295 million in fines for its Resource Recovery and Conservation Act violations, but Skretny said that figure far exceeded what the plant was capable of paying. He ordered that the River Road facility pay another $7 million for the RCRA crimes.
Tonawanda Coke will pay the $12.5 million fine and $12.2 million for community service projects over the course of five years.
The plant is just one of three facilities to be tried pursuant to Clean Air Act's Title V, which regulates large businesses' industrial pollution.
In the first case of its kind, United States v. Atlantic States Cast Iron Pipe Co., the New Jersey facility was convicted on one count of the Clean Air Act and 22 counts of the Clean Water Act, and was sentenced to pay $8 million. This year, Citgo Petroleum Corp. was fined $2 million for violating environmental regulations at its Texas oil refinery.
In total, Tonawanda Coke faced a maximum of $300 million in fines, while its environmental manager Mark Kamholz faced 75 years in prison.
In his opening remarks, Skretny said that he had determined the company could afford $25 million in fines and community service projects based on its cash flow and capital reserve fund. That figure differed substantially from both the prosecutor's and defendant's recommendations.
The government had asked for $44.3 million criminal fine based on its analysis of the plant's 2005-2009 financial information. But in presentencing documents, defense attorney Gregory Linsin argued the plant could not pay more than $1 million per year due to economic stresses and a decline in the steel market that took place after 2009.
"The government has submitted a sentencing recommendation that is fundamentally flawed and flatly ignores the statutory and sentencing factors and far exceeds the bounds of reasonableness," the defense memorandum states.
In response, Assistant U.S. Attorney Aaron Mango drew a comparison between the local residents and the plant, which posted a nearly $50 million profit in the five-year period.
"And we have the people who can't put food on the table, people who have to run to Roswell for treatment, people who have to care for their grandchildren because their son or daughter passed away," he said in court on Wednesday. "$50 million in five years doesn't happen just because, it happens because of a contempt of environmental regulations ... and it resulted in an environmental travesty."
Mango also recommended that Kamholz be sentenced to a term of six to eight years in prison and pay a fine of $250,000, while Kamholz's defense attorney Rodney Personius asked the judge to impose a non-prison sentence.
During his statements, Skretny did recognize character letters sent to court on Kamholz's behalf and said that they do portray him as a committed father, husband and friend.
"But against that backdrop is the criminal behavior you participated in," he said. "It was clear through this trial, that for environmental matters at Tonawanda Coke, the buck stopped with you."
Skretny ordered Kamholz to spend one year and one day in jail, pay a $20,000 fine and serve 100 hours of community service in the Tonawanda or Grand Island area.
Contact reporter Jessica Bagley at 693-1000 ext. 4150, or follow her on Twitter @JessicaLBagley.
]]></text></news-item>