<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-WB61-JCBD-K372"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>French court investigates Equatorial Guinean vice-president for "money laundering", raising risks of reprisal action against French companies</title><source>IHS Global Insight</source><author>Martin Roberts</author><text><![CDATA[The vice-president of Equatorial Guinea has been placed under formal investigation in France for alleged money laundering, his lawyer announced yesterday (19 March). Vice-President Teodorin Obiang, son and heir apparent of President Teodoro Obiang Nguema, was informed of the development by video conference on 18 March, after refusing to answer questions from French magistrates on the grounds of diplomatic immunity. Formal investigation means there is "serious or consistent evidence" pointing to the likely implication of a suspect in a crime, the final step before a possible trial. Teodorin denies the charges. French magistrates have been investigating Teodorin since December 2010, along with the families of Congolese president Denis Sassou Nguesso and late Gabonese leader Omar Bongo, after a complaint brought by anti-corruption groups including Transparency International. They are suspected of having embezzled public funds to buy dozens of luxury properties in France and set up around 200 bank accounts. France has already seized and sold nine luxury cars allegedly belonging to Teodorin and sequestrated a mansion on the Avenue Foch in Paris.
Significance:Teodorin is likely to use his claimed immunity to refuse co-operation with the French investigation, extending to non-attendance at any trial. In 2012, he invoked immunity after French magistrates issued an international arrest warrant following his failure to respond to a summons. There is little chance that Teodorin's troubles will affect his status as president-in-waiting, but he and his father have been infuriated by the damage to the country's reputation and see the judicial proceedings as a conspiracy of the French state. This has led to French companies being blamed for problems in Equatorial Guinea, which President Obiang claims they have deliberately engineered at France's request. In July 2013, the president singled out oil company Total, telecoms firm Orange, and Societe Generale bank for allegedly creating fuel shortages, prompting failure of mobile networks and unpaid transactions respectively. These are all now at risk of contract revision or even expropriation, as are logistics company Bollore and timber firms such as Rougier.
]]></text></news-item>