<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-PFW1-DYJJ-P4VD"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>O'Reilly second company publicly targeted</title><source>Springfield News-Leader (Missouri)</source><author>By, Thomas Gounley</author><text><![CDATA[Springfield-based O'Reilly Automotive is the second company to publicly come under scrutiny by the Washington State Office of the Attorney General as a result of the state's 2012 legalization of same-sex marriage.
But it is the first company to make changes in the wake of it.
In April 2013, the attorney general's office filed a lawsuit against Arlene's Flowers and Gifts, a Richland, Wash., florist. The suit alleged that owner Barronelle Stutzman violated the Washington State Consumer Protection Act when she refused to sell flowers to longtime customers who are gay for their upcoming wedding.
"When it came to doing his wedding, I said, 'I could not do it because of my relationship with Jesus Christ,'" Stutzman wrote on the company's Facebook page last March.
In a news release at the time, Attorney General Bob Ferguson said Stutzman's actions discriminated against customers on the basis of sexual orientation.
"If a business provides a product or service to opposite-sex couples for their weddings, then it must provide same-sex couples the same product or service," Ferguson, a Democrat, said.
The state's Consumer Protection Act, which prohibits unfair or deceptive business practices, is also the basis for the attorney general's investigation into O'Reilly - although that investigation focuses on benefits offered to employees, not products sold to the public.
On Monday, the office filed a petition asking a court to essentially require O'Reilly to answer questions in a Civil Investigative Demand issued in January. Those questions revolved around whether O'Reilly provides health care benefits to opposite-sex couples that are not available to same-sex couples.
In a response to the CID, as well as in comments made to the News-Leader on Tuesday, O'Reilly maintained that many of the questions are overly broad, and unrelated to the attorney general's inquiry. It maintained that its health insurance plans - which don't include same-sex spouses under the definition of "spouse" - comply fully with federal law, which it believes pre-empts state law.
Late Wednesday afternoon, however, O'Reilly announced that it would extend the health insurance benefits to same-sex couples.
Barronelle Stutzman, however, is still fighting.
Prior to the filing of the lawsuit, her attorneys responded to an initial inquiry by stating Arlene's Flowers and Gifts would challenge any state action, according to a release from the attorney general's office. In the lawsuit, the office seeks a permanent injunction requiring the florist to comply with its interpretation of the law, as well as $2,000 for every alleged violation.
An attorney for Stutzman told the Seattle Times last April that the business has many gay customers, as well as gay employees, and the claim that she is "discriminating on the basis on sexual orientation is nonsense."
"This is about gay marriage, it's not about a person being gay," J.D. Bristol told the Seattle Times. "She has a conscientious objection to homosexual marriage, not homosexuality. It violates her conscience."
In October, Stutzman's attorneys asked a judge to toss out the attorney general's lawsuit for lack of jurisdiction and standing and for failing to try to resolve the matter through the Washington Human Rights Commission. The request was not granted.
The American Civil Liberties Union also filed a lawsuit against Stutzman, which has since been consolidated by a judge with the one filed by the attorney general. Stutzman, meanwhile, is suing the attorney general's office in federal court in what her attorneys bill as an effort to protect her religious freedoms.
"Frankly the lawsuit is unconstitutional," Kristen Waggoner, another lawyer for Stutzman, told NBC affiliate KNDU earlier this month. "The constitution guarantees Americans the right to live and work in a manner that's consistent with their religious beliefs."
]]></text></news-item>