<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-VSG1-DXH0-K1VJ"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Karachi Police meeting fuel expenses unlawfully</title><source>Pakistan Observer</source><author> Staff Reporter</author><text><![CDATA[Karachi Police had during past 6 months long targeted operation conducted hundreds of raids and arrested thousands of suspects including hardened criminals and terrorists and recovered huge caches of illegal weapons and ammunitions. Recently, Sindh government had through a Bill that was passed by Sindh assembly allowed Karachi Police to procure modern fighting equipments such as armoured police cars, bullet proof jackets, helmets.
However, sources told Pakistan Observer that neither Karachi Police nor Sindh government paid any attention on expenses being accrued on massive scale patrolling of Police mobile vans in nook and cranny of the metropolis.
Karachi's traffic police had been collecting heavy revenue from lifting motorcycles and cars if parked off the street and in this particular category, averagely Rs 20 million were being accumulated every month. Conversely, Karachi traffic police authority had made it mandatory for each traffic police officer from the rank of assistant sub inspector to SO to fine at least 15 daily with fine money starting from Rs 50 to 500 and that sum of money thus collected was deposited at the selected branches of a bank across te city. Minting money in form of bribe and special illegal root permits issued to private dumpers at the rate of Rs 300 each were not included, claimed the sources.
It was also said that yet, Karachi's Police was claiming to have received just 4 litres of petrol per day for the purpose of patrolling within the respective precincts of Police Stations. While, a Police mobile van on patrol required a minimum of 20 litres of petrol to meet the task. The remaining 16 litres of petrol was purchased through different illicit means.
Police posses on patrol within their respective administrative limits mint money from motorcyclists, fruit and vegetable venders on encroached public land, shopkeepers for placing their saleable commodities on pavements, and restaurants that also encroached pavements with the connivance of district municipal administrations concerned, they added.
Sources further claimed that Karachi traffic police had outsourced one of its section to private contractors for bringing motorcycle and cars from streets of Karachi for being wrongly parked. The cars and motorcycles thus brought to Police Stations' premises were not only fined for heavy sum of money but petrol especially form motorcycles was also stolen and sold to Police mobile vans at cheaper rates.
On the other hand, Police officers at different police stations were also minting money form allocated funds for meeting fuel expenses but there were many Police mobile vans that were out of order and were parked inside the Police Station's premise but still, Police officers were minting money against fake filling through fuel debit cards.
A Police mobile van No. SP-7274 being parked inside Taimooriya Police Station since long due to mechanical faults was also shown as in working order just to mint money on the pretext of regular filling while the said Police van was off the road for long time.
]]></text></news-item>