<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-WB61-JCBD-K386"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Indigenous protests in Panama likely to delay launch of hydroelectric project</title><source>IHS Global Insight</source><author>Diego Moya-Ocampos</author><text><![CDATA[Ngabe-Bugle indigenous communities are staging protests in the district of Tore in Panama's western province of Chiquiri against the Barro Blanco hydroelectric project. Protesters entered the security perimeter of the project's construction site on 18 March and burned grassland, demanding the immediate suspension of the works. The 28.8 megawatt hydroelectric project is planned for construction on the Tabasara River, but Ngabe-Bugle indigenous activists and locals argue it will displace more than 36,000 people and damage the environment and the local agricultural industry. The Barro Blanco project is being developed by Generadora del Itsmo, S.A (GENISA). It was suspended in March 2012 after two protesters were killed in confrontations with the security forces the previous month but it was resumed shortly afterwards when the government reached an agreement with local communities. The Ngabe-Bugle region is an autonomous administrative region that includes parts of the provinces of Bocas de Toro, Chiquiri, and Veraguas.
Significance:The construction of the Barro Blanco project will potentially face delays if authorities prove unable to contain the protesters. The protests are likely to escalate ahead of the 4 May presidential election; Jose Domingo Arias, the former minister of housing and the candidate of the ruling Democratic Change (Cambio Democratico: CD) is leading the polls, closely followed by Juan Carlos Navarro, a two-time mayor of Panama city, for the Democratic Revolutionary Party (Partido Revolucionario Democratico: PRD). Protests, including roadblocks, are expected to take place in the coming weeks in the province of Chiquiri and possibly in the western province of Veraguas, generating operational constraints to transport and cargo operators on a section of the Pan-American highway that connects with Costa Rica. The protests are likely to be supported by local farmers who are also opposing the project. Further unrest can be expected in the one-year outlook, against the Barro Blanco project and three other planned hydroelectric projects in the same area - Bonyic, San Lorenzo, and Tabasara II.
]]></text></news-item>