<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-NFH1-JDJN-630G"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Lagarde questioned in court over adidas deal</title><source>Daily News (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[PARIS: International Monetary Fund (IMF) chief Christine Lagarde was questioned yesterday for the third time by French prosecutors in a corruption case that has become a thorn in the side of one of the world's most powerful women.
Lagarde faced questions over her handling of a E400 million (R6bn) state payout to disgraced French tycoon Bernard Tapie in 2008 when she was finance minister.
She was questioned by prosecutors from the Court of Justice of the Republic, a special court that probes cases of ministerial misconduct, amid suspicions that Tapie got favourable treatment in return for supporting ex-president Nicolas Sarkozy in the 2007 election.
The payout was connected to a dispute between Tapie and partly state-owned bank Crédit Lyonnais over his 1993 sale of sportswear group adidas.
Tapie claimed that Crédit Lyonnais had defrauded him by intentionally undervaluing adidas at the time of the sale and that the state, as the bank's principal shareholder, should compensate him.
Lagarde was questioned for two days last May about her role in the affair.
Prosecutors have suggested that she was partly responsible for "numerous anomalies and irregularities" that could lead to charges for complicity in fraud and misappropriation of public funds.
Lagarde declined comment as she came into court.
Questioning was expected to revolve around a signature stamp used in a letter dated October 23, 2007, that investigators think is crucial in determining who took the decision on the controversial payout
Lagarde said she was unaware of the letter's contents and said it was stamped with her signature in her absence.
But in 2008 she told legislators that she gave instructions to back the decision on the payout and in that sense took responsibility for the contents.
Lagarde avoided being formally charged last year. If she had been, she would likely have had to quit as head of the IMF.
Instead, she was placed under a special witness status that forces her to come back for questioning when asked to do so by the court - and leaves the door open for charges at a later date. - Sapa-AFP
Daily News © 1999 - 2014 Independent Newspapers (Pty) Limited. All rights strictly reserved.
]]></text></news-item>