<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-6511-JBVM-Y2H1"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Taking action to stop stink from landfill site; GILBERDYKE: Assurances given to long-suffering residents</title><source>Hull Daily Mail</source><author>Trudi Davidson</author><text><![CDATA[InShort Residents have been told action will be taken by October to stop the stink from the Gilberdyke tip at talks involving Environment Agency, East Riding Council and City Plant Ltd.
LONG-suffering residents are hopeful the stink from the Gilberdyke landfill site will be stopped by October.
Assurances have been given at talks involving the Environment Agency, East Riding Council, residents and operator City Plant Ltd.
Resident Kevin Clifford said: "After a long and tortuous journey, I am now hopeful that the Environment Agency has finally determined the local residents deserve closure on this issue as soon as possible. "For the first time in many years, I believe there is light at the end of the tunnel."
East Riding ward councillor Victoria Aitken said the Environment Agency had assured residents it intended to ensure full compliance with standards.
She said: "Enforcement notices have been sent to City Plant Ltd requiring that the capping, and the landfill gas, leachate and surface water management systems be substantially completed by October.
"The landfill gas system will dispose of the gas that causes the terrible smell, which residents have experienced for far too long, and the water and leachate systems will prevent the environmental contamination of local dykes and agricultural land."
Cllr Aitken warned progress would be monitored to ensure compliance.
She said: "These might appear to be tight timescales, but the Environment Agency is confident they can be met if sufficient resources are bought to bear.
"We shall be monitoring the progress via future liaison meetings".
A drop-in session will also be held for residents. Cllr Aitken said: "There will be a large number of lorries entering and leaving the site over the next year and residents will want to know this is being managed in the best possible way."
City Plant Ltd will be top-soiling and seeding the site, which will eventually be planted with trees and shrubs.
Resident Roy Hunt said: "The Environment Agency is, at last, taking affirmative action to get this site restored and closed off."
AN ENVIRONMENT Agency spokesman said: "The agency has set a target for full restoration of the site in October and the local community expect the operator, City Plant Limited and its owners to act accordingly. "The responsibility for restoring the Gilberdyke site lies with the permit holder, City Plant Ltd.
"The Environment Agency is responsible for regulating the activities onsite and we have now set the permit holder enforceable timescales to complete a number of activities, including the capture of the landfill gas produced, major improvements to the leachate and surface water management systems, and the covering of the site with clays, synthetic liners and soils to enable planting to take place.
"We will use the regulatory tools available to us to control these activities so they take place with the minimum of disruption to residents, but with all large civil engineering projects of this nature we do envisage some minor impacts.
"The Environment Agency is looking forward to attending the drop-in session later in the year to answer any concerns the local residents have."
]]></text></news-item>