<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-VSG1-DXH0-K1MR"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Don't befriend India at farmers' cost</title><source>Dawn (Pakistan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The rulers may have friendship with India but it should not be done at the cost of Pakistani farmers, said PML-Q leader and former deputy prime minister Pervaiz Elahi here on Wednesday.
Addressing Kissan Convention at the Muslim League House, he demanded that local farmers be provided a level playfield to compete with their Indian counterparts prior to opening agricultural trade with the neighbouring country. The PML-Q, he said, would fully support the farmers in their struggle to save the nation from food scarcity.
The convention was largely attended by farmers' representatives from all over Punjab who kept chanting slogans in favour of Shujaat Husain, Pervaiz Elahi and Moonis Elahi and in support of their demands.
Pervaiz Elahi reminded the farmers that as chief minister his policies were pro-poor and pro-farmer, adding that during his tenure peasants were provided cheap electricity, water up to tail, easy agricultural loans etc. He said land up to 12-and-a-half acres was exempted from tax, roads and concrete channels were constructed and payment to the farmers for every single grain of their crop was ensured during his rule in Punjab.
He also mentioned free distribution of more than 78,000 acres of land among 6,000 families, expansion and rehabilitation of barrages costing billions of rupees, remodeling of irrigation system, construction of 45 small dams, stipends for livestock breeding, establishment of union council level and mobile veterinary dispensaries, establishment of Punjab Agriculture Market, increase in punishment for water theft and provision of laser land levellers as his pro-farmers steps.
He said Indian farmers were many times better off than local ones due to availability of cheap electricity, good quality seed, ample water and special interest of the government. He said as compared to this, local farmer had been a victim of lack of facilities and interest on the part of the government.
Criticising present Punjab rulers, party's Punjab secretary general Chaudhry Zaheeruddin said villages' roads were in shambles and thefts and dacoities had become order of the day. He said the institutions like Punjab Agriculture Research Unit, Bio Institute Faisalabad and Medicine Laboratory established by Pervaiz in his tenure spending billions of rupees were lying shut.
Senior provincial vice-president Basharat Raja said like middleman the N-League too was depriving farmers of their hard earned money. He said the rulers were selling wheat at Rs1,310 which was bought at Rs1200, adding it was being feared that Thar-like conditions could prevail in Cholistan.
Meanwhile, reacting to the speech of the former deputy prime minister, Punjab Law Minister Rana Sanaullah said Pervaiz Elahi was yet to come to terms with his party's electoral defeat. He said people had rejected those in general elections who were making trumpeting their so-called projects.
]]></text></news-item>