<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-J671-JCW9-X058"><date>2014-03-20</date><title></title><source>Chicago Sun-Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[MARKET CLOSE
BRIEFS Brief hed goes right in this space Xxxxxxxx MARKET CLOSE BUSINESS IN BRIEF FAA says Boeing 787's design, manufacture safe WASHINGTON - Boeing's design and manufacture of its cutting-edge 787 jetliner is safe despite the plane's many problems since its rollout, including a fire that forced a redesign of the plane's batteries, according to a report issued jointly Wednesday by the Federal Aviation Administration and the Chicago-based aircraft maker.
The yearlong review concluded "the aircraft was soundly designed, met its intended safety level, and that the manufacturer and the FAA had effective processes in place to identify and correct issues that emerged before and after certification," the agency said in a statement. The report also makes seven recommendations for further improvements by Boeing and FAA. FAA Administrator Michael Huerta asked for the review in January 2013 after a lithium-ion battery caught fire on a 787 parked at Logan International Airport in Boston. A battery aboard another 787 failed less than two weeks later. AP Toyota to pay $1.2B penalty WASHINGTON - The government has announced a $1.2 billion settlement with Toyota that Attorney General Eric Holder said is the largest financial penalty of its kind ever imposed on an auto company. It also filed a criminal charge alleging the automaker defrauded consumers by issuing misleading statements about safety issues in Toyota and Lexus vehicles. Under a deferred prosecution agreement, an independent monitor will review policies, practices and procedures at the company. The action concludes a four-year criminal investigation into the Japanese automaker's disclosure of safety problems, which focused on whether Toyota was forthright in reporting problems related to unintended acceleration. Toyota has blamed drivers, stuck accelerators or floor mats that trapped the gas pedal for the acceleration claims that led to massive recalls of Camrys and other vehicles. The company has repeatedly denied its vehicles are flawed. The National Highway Traffic Safety Administration never found defects in electronics or software in Toyota cars, which had been targeted as a possible cause. AP Toyota says it has made fundamental changes to become "a more responsive and customer-focused organization."
]]></text></news-item>