<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-VSG1-DXH0-K1S2"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>53 countries to take part in NSS 2014 in Hague</title><source>The Frontier Post</source><author> Xischan Javed</author><text><![CDATA[The world leaders from more than 53 countries including Pakistan once again will meet in joint sitting of two-day Third Nuclear Security Summit 2014 in Hague (Netherland) on March 24 to discuss the preemptive measures for countering prophesy fear of nuclear terrorism.
The Prime Minister, Nawaz Sharif will also participate in NSS summit 2014 as Pakistan having unbreakable security system for its nuclear assets, is being considered as an important participant for upcoming joint-sitting of NSS.
The concept of 'Nuclear Terrorism' came to surface in 2009, when US president Barrack Obama 1st time highlighted the issue after threatening by terrorist groups to launch nuclear terrorism in west through different means including 'Dirty Bomb' and termed it as "the most immediate and extreme threat to global security".
The first summit of NSS on this particular issue was held at 2010 in Washington, while the second one was hosted by Seoul (South Korea), however the third upcoming summit is being considered as conclusive discourse to finalize the recommendations about the preemptive measures to counter the global fear of nuclear terrorism and illegal smuggling of material used in nuclear weapons as well.
The Dutch Ambassador to Pakistan, Marcel de Vink on Wednesday said that the upcoming NSS summit hosted by 'Hague' aimed to discuss the opinion and experiences of world leaders to improve security measures for illegal transportation of hazardous nuclear material either on national or international level.
He said that more than 53 countries including Pakistan and four major international agencies including European Union (EU), International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA), International Police (Interpol) and mainstream representatives from United Nation will participate in NSS 2014 to review the recommendations about the security measures of Nuclear Assets; however Iran and North-Korea are not being invited.
The representative of NSS host country to Pakistan applauded the active contribution of Pakistan for milestone achievement to establish the world class Nuclear Security Training Centre (NSTC), which aims to bring improvement in nuclear security not only at home but in region too.
Mr. Vink was of the view that the threat by terrorist groups to use nuclear weapons to hit the global peace could not be sent on back foot, adding "the militants and international criminals involved in the smuggling of hazardous raw material use in nuclear weapons, remained a hanging sword on global community, which not compelled the entire world to sit jointly and take preemptive measure for elimination of fear of nuclear terrorism", he maintained.
The Hague (Netherland) firmly believed that the foresee outcomes of upcoming NSS 2014 would help the global community to take the measures for further reduction in the quantity of hazardous nuclear raw material as set by IAEA and other agencies accordingly, security measures to prevent the illegal transportation of material used in nuclear weapons, security of nuclear installations and radiological sources as well as further strengthening the International Cooperation.
Director General International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) Yukiya Amano on March 12 visited Pakistan's Centre of Excellence for Nuclear Security, where in his remarks; he said that it is very impressive for him that Pakistan established the training system in a very systemic and operational manner.
The countries who expressed their consent to participate in NSS 2014 included Algeria, Argentina, Armenia, Australia, Azerbaijan, Belgium, Brazil, Canada, Chile, China, Czech Republic, Denmark, Egypt, Finland, France, Gabon, Georgia, Germany, Hungary, India, Indonesia, Israel, Italy, Japan, Jordan, Kazakhstan, Lithuania, Malaysia, Mexico, Morocco, Netherlands, New Zealand, Nigeria, Norway, Pakistan, the Philippines, Poland, South Korea, Romania, the Russian Federation, Saudi Arabia, Singapore, South Africa, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, Thailand, Turkey, Ukraine, the United Arab Emirates, the United Kingdom, the United States, and Vietnam.
]]></text></news-item>