<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-NT71-F0CC-S1KM"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>BAE SYSTEMS PLC Doc re. Annual Financial Report -5-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Companies engaged in the supply of defence and security-related equipment and services to government agencies are subject to certain business risks particular to the defence and security industries. These governments could modify contracts or terminate them at short notice and at their convenience. For example, long-term US government contracts are normally funded annually and are subject to cancellation or delay if funding appropriations for subsequent performance periods are not made. Terms and risk sharing agreements can also be amended. In addition, the Group, as a government contractor, is subject to financial audits and other reviews by some of its governmental customers with respect to the performance of, and the accounting and general practices relating to, government contracts.
As a result of these audits and reviews, costs and prices under these contracts may be subject to adjustment. Impact The termination of one or more of the contracts for the Group's programmes by governments, the failure of the relevant agencies to obtain expected funding appropriations for the Group's programmes, or a deterioration in the Group's relationship with any of its key government customers and corresponding reduction in contract awards, could have a material adverse effect on the Group's future results and financial condition. Mitigation The Group regularly reviews performance in its markets and the Executive Committee continues to work closely with the government customers in these markets to ensure the Group's strategy is aligned with theirs. In the event of a customer termination for convenience, the Group would typically be paid for work done and commitments made at the time of termination. Having sovereign governments as major customers offers the benefits of dealing with mature procurement organisations with which the Group can have long-standing business relationships, and well-established and understood terms of trade. For more information on the Group's strategy see page 7 Global market The Group operates in a global market. Description BAE Systems is a global company which conducts business in a number of regions, including the Middle East, and, as a result, assumes certain risks associated with businesses with a broad geographical reach. In some countries, these risks include, and are not limited to, the following: political changes could lead to changes in the business environment in which the Group operates; economic downturns, political instability and civil disturbances could disrupt the Group's business activities; government regulations and administrative policies could change quickly and restraints on the movement of capital could be imposed; governments could expropriate the Group's assets; and burdensome taxes or tariffs could be introduced. Impact The occurrence of any such events could have a material adverse effect on the Group's future results and financial condition. Mitigation The Group has a balanced portfolio of businesses across its markets. For more information on the Group's multiple markets see page 14 Contract award timing The Group is dependent on the timing of award of defence contracts. Description The Group's profits and cash flows are dependent, to a significant extent, on the timing of award of defence contracts. Impact Amounts receivable under the Group's defence contracts can be substantial and, therefore, the timing of awards, or failure to receive anticipated awards, could materially affect the Group's profits and cash flows for the periods affected. Mitigation The Board regularly reviews the Group's performance with regard to contract awards, and the Executive Committee actively manages the assets and resources of the Group in line with the timing of awards. For more information on the Group's major programmes see page 37 Large contracts Certain of the Group's businesses are dependent on a small number of large contracts. Description A significant proportion of the Group's revenue comes from a small number of large contracts. Each of these contracts, which are primarily in the Platforms & Services (UK) and Platforms & Services (International) reporting segments, is typically worth or potentially worth over GBP1bn. Impact The loss, expiration, suspension, cancellation or termination of any one of these large contracts, for any reason, could have a material adverse effect on the Group's future results and financial condition. Mitigation To mitigate risk on UK Ministry of Defence contracts, development programmes are normally contracted with appropriate levels of risk being initially held by the customer. Subsequent production programmes are priced when a platform's development has reached sufficient maturity. A variety of contract structures are used to mitigate risk on production programmes, such as incentive arrangements, whereby the customer and contractor share cost savings and overruns against target prices. The Group has a well-balanced spread of programmes and significant order backlog, which provides long-term visibility. The Board regularly reviews the Group's performance on these large contracts and the Executive Committee continues to work closely with the relevant customers to ensure the Group's strategy is aligned with theirs. For more information on the Group's order backlog by major programme and reporting segment see page 37 Fixed-price contracts The Group has fixed-price contracts. Description A significant portion of the Group's revenue is derived from fixed-price contracts. An inherent risk in these fixed-price contracts is that actual performance costs may exceed the projected costs on which the fixed prices for such contracts are agreed. These contracts can extend over many years and it can be difficult to predict the ultimate outturn costs associated with the terms on which they are based. Impact The Group's failure to anticipate technical problems, estimate costs accurately or control costs during performance of a fixed-price contract may reduce the profitability of such a contract or result in a loss. Mitigation The Group has reduced its exposure to fixed-price design and development activity which is in general more risk intensive than fixed-price production activity. To manage contract-related risks and uncertainties, contracts are managed under the Group's mandated Lifecycle Management (LCM) process at the operational level. Robust bid preparation and approvals processes are well established throughout the Group, with decisions required to be taken at the appropriate level in line with clear delegations of authority. The consistent application of metrics is used to support the review of individual contract performance. For more information on LCM which mandates project management processes see page 69 Component availability, subcontractor performance and key suppliers The Group is dependent upon component availability, subcontractor performance and key suppliers. Description The Group is dependent upon the delivery of materials by suppliers, and the assembly of components and subsystems by subcontractors used in its products in a timely and satisfactory manner, and in compliance with applicable terms and conditions. Impact Some of the Group's suppliers or subcontractors may be impacted by the economic environment and constraints on available financing, which could impair their ability to meet their obligations to the Group. In addition, some products require relatively scarce raw materials. The Group is generally subject to specific procurement requirements which may, in effect, limit the suppliers and subcontractors it may utilise. In some instances, the Group is dependent on one or a limited number of suppliers. If any of these suppliers or subcontractors fails to meet the Group's needs, the Group may not, in the short term, have readily available alternatives, thereby impacting its ability to complete its customer obligations satisfactorily and in a timely manner, which could have a negative impact on the Group's future results and financial condition. Mitigation The Group's procurement function, which is led by a member of the Executive Committee, is responsible for establishing and managing end-to-end integrated supplier arrangements. The Executive Committee continues to monitor this risk and the Group has experienced no material negative impact to date. The Group reviews the financial health of strategically important suppliers globally on an ongoing basis. For more information on suppliers see page 118 Laws and regulations The Group is subject to risk from a failure to comply with laws and regulations. Description The Group has contracts and operations in many parts of the world, operates in a highly regulated environment, and is subject to applicable laws and regulations of many jurisdictions. These include, without limitation, regulations relating to import-export controls, money laundering, false accounting, anti-bribery and anti-boycott provisions. Non-compliance could expose the Group to fines, penalties, suspension or debarment, which could have a material adverse effect on the Group. From time to time, the Group is subject to government investigations relating to its operations. Impact Failure by the Group or its sales representatives, marketing advisers or others acting on its behalf to comply with these laws and regulations could result in administrative, civil or criminal liabilities resulting in significant fines and penalties, and/or result in the suspension or debarment of the Group from government contracts for some period of time or suspension of the Group's export privileges. Mitigation During the year, the Group has continued to add resources dedicated to legal and regulatory compliance in order to enhance further its capability to identify and manage the risk of compliance failure. Internal and external market risk assessments form an important element of the ongoing corporate development and training processes.
]]></text></news-item>