<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-97W1-JCDV-D3H4"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Funding still missing link for fast foot ferry</title><source>Nanaimo Daily News (British Columbia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[News that Island Ferry Services Ltd. and the city of Nanaimo have reached a tentative lease agreement for a downtown fast ferry terminal sounds good.
Staff has been tapped to work on a long-term lease agreement on the Wellcox property. Any news can be regarded as good news in regards to this much needed transportation passenger-only link to Vancouver. But does this announcement mean the service is really any closer to becoming reality? Or is it really a re-announcement about the service in what happens to be an election year? We're also told a hotel, to be built adjacent to the Vancouver Island Conference Centre, should begin construction "this spring."
s was six months ago, only those working behind the scenes truly know.
This is, without a doubt, is the most important piece of the puzzle that we've been waiting for. If and/or when that announcement is made, it will be a welcome sign that proponents hold the belief that a Georgia Strait crossing can be successful, and have the necessary funding to see the service through rough waters. IFS now says that because the financing has not been secured, the service won't be up and running this summer, as hoped. That's too bad, as the fast foot ferry is an important plank in Nanaimo's transportation platform, providing speedier access to Vancouver for commuters.
It also holds promise for local real estate, particularly downtown condominiums. A ferry commute offers commuters an opportunity to work while they travel from their affordable Nanaimo home or condo to an office in Vancouver.
Commutes to the Fraser Valley, which have more affordable real estate, are time consuming and weary.
B.C. Ferries' brief announcement last fall that it was considering a passenger-only ferry made all kinds of waves, and was the greatest fear any investor might have concerning a private venture. A public entity with potentially unlimited taxpayer funds as a competitor?
No investor would like the odds of competing in an environment like that.
But what if the necessary funding for a private passenger service doesn't materialize? Should B.C. Ferries re-enter the conversation? Or be forced to? Although it is now set up as an independent corporation, the current structure of B.C. Ferries isn't working as it could or should in terms of serving customers - the ones who take the sailings.
While on one hand it says it is arms-length from the provincial government and free to navigate its own business plan, that clearly isn't working. At least in terms of rising rates and declining ridership.
B.C. Ferries is operating as a monopoly, and while that may offer advantages in a business case, it is the paying passengers that suffer.
Maybe it's time to bring the corporation back under direct provincial government control and make adjustments that will result in more affordable fares. Business, tourism and residents would welcome the relief from higher ferry fares.
And if private sector funding doesn't arise for IFS, then B.C. Ferries could be ordered to provide what Nanaimo needs -a downtown fast foot passenger ferry to Vancouver.
We want to hear from you.
Send comments on this editorial to letters@nanaimodailynews.com
]]></text></news-item>