<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-D8P1-JC8R-34V0"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>BP ALLOWED GULF OIL LEASES</title><source>Pittsburgh Post-Gazette</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[WASHINGTON -- The Interior Department said Wednesday that it sold $850.8 million worth of leases in the deepwater Gulf of Mexico to major oil companies.
This was the first sale since 2012 in which BP was able to participate and the oil giant submitted winning bids for 24 lease blocks for a total of $41.6 million.
Only last week, BP reached an agreement with the Environmental Protection Agency, which lifted a ban on BP's participation in government contracts including leases. The ban had gone into effect for what EPA called the London-based company's "lack of business integrity" after it pleaded guilty to criminal charges related to the massive 2010 oil spill in the Gulf of Mexico from its Macondo well.
General awaits sentence
FORT BRAGG, N.C. -- A general who broke military law repeatedly during a three-year extramarital affair with a subordinate should be thrown out of the Army and lose his benefits, prosecutors said Wednesday during closing arguments at his sentencing.
The defense argued that dismissing Brig. Gen. Jeffrey Sinclair from the military would do the most harm to his wife and children, calling them the only innocent people in the case.
After both sides finished, Judge Col. James Pohl adjourned the hearing until this morning -- meaning Sinclair, 51, will have to wait at least one more day to learn his fate. His sentencing comes as the military and Congress grapple with sex crimes in the ranks.
Heat blamed in jail death
NEW YORK -- Jerome Murdough was just looking for a warm place to sleep on a chilly night last month when he curled up in an enclosed stairwell on the roof of a Harlem public housing project where he was arrested for trespassing.
A week later, the mentally ill homeless man was found dead in a Rikers Island jail cell that four city officials say had overheated to at least 100 degrees, apparently because of malfunctioning equipment.
The officials said the 56-year-old former Marine was on anti-psychotic and anti-seizure medication, which may have made him more vulnerable to heat. He also apparently did not open a small vent in his cell to let in cool air.
"He basically baked to death," said one of the officials.
Hershey faces lawsuit
WILMINGTON, Del. -- Hershey Co., the nation's largest chocolate maker, was ordered to face a lawsuit by investors seeking to force it to turn over records about cocoa from African farms that may use illegal child labor.
A Louisiana pension fund raised legitimate questions about Hershey executives' knowledge of how much of the company's cocoa, grown in West Africa, may have been produced by child slaves, Judge Travis Laster of Delaware Chancery Court said Tuesday. He overruled a master's recommendation that the shareholders' request to see cocoa-supply chain records be denied.
West Africa, including top growers Ghana and Ivory Coast, accounts for about 70 percent of the world's cocoa-bean production.
2 winners of $414 million
Two winning tickets, sold in Maryland and Florida, will split the $414 million Mega Millions jackpot, officials announced Wednesday.
The winning numbers, drawn Tuesday night, were 11, 19, 24, 33 and 51, and a Mega Ball of 7.
The jackpot of $414 million is the third largest in Mega Millions history. The largest jackpot is $656 million, split among Mega Millions winners in Maryland, Kansas and Illinois in 2012.
-- Compiled from news services
]]></text></news-item>