<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-6521-JBVM-Y1GY"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>MP's backing shoppers' call for new Asda</title><source>Western Daily Press</source><author>JANET HUGHES</author><text><![CDATA[Most places protest when a supermarket giant wants to come to town but the people of Cinderford have been marching for two years because they haven't.
Residents say they want to shop with one of the big four but Midcounties Co-op keep blocking planning applications for superstores. Now the row looks like reaching fever pitch after the local MP accused the Co-op of "using every trick in the book" to stop competitor Asda moving into the Forest of Dean.
The leader of the council has told the head of the Co-op that its action is holding back the town and protesters are urging residents to burn their Co-op loyalty cards after yet another march through the centre of town this weekend.
Midcounties Co-op has stores in three of the four Forest of Dean towns and in recent times has objected to planning applications submitted by Tesco, Asda and Sainsbury's. Tesco gave up after a decadelong legal battle to build a store in Cinderford and the Coop has mounted two High Court battles to stop Asda doing the same, claiming two successful planning applications breached the regulations. Councillor Patrick Molyneux, leader of Forest of Dean District Council, has now written to the Co-op's interim chief executive Richard Pennycook, to say the saga has already cost the council at least £200,000 and he should abide by their decision.
"It has been brought to my attention that Midcounties Cooperative has recently lodged a judicial challenge of this council's decision to grant planning permission for a new food store," he said. "This is the second legal challenge that Co-op has mounted against this authority in a short space of time. This ongoing legal action to attempt the prevention or delay of further retail expansion is not only harmful to the town, but potentially damaging to your own store's future.
"You may already be aware of the huge public support that a new foodstore has from the people of Cinderford and I suspect the impact of local anger over the Co-op's behaviour must affect your store's staff morale and sales. The legal costs we have incurred are met from local taxpayers and many are now turning their back on your store in protest." Campaign group We Want an Asda in Cinderford has around 1,700 members who are backing proposals for a new supermarket. Organisers have arranged regular marches over the last two years and are planning another for this weekend.
Spokesman Amanda Watkins said: "Asda is the third supermarket to try and nobody else is going to waste money trying to go up against Co-op to come here."
Forest of Dean MP Mark Harper, who backs the district council's decision, recently told the Houses of Parliament he wanted to draw attention to the "behaviour" of the Co-op.
He told MPs during a debate by the Department for Business, Innovation and Skills that it was " using every trick in the book to behave in an anti-competitive manner to block a planning application which has been approved by my local council and which is popular with local people. Shouldn't they get on with competing on the basis of price and choice not on the basis of the quality of their legal team" A spokesman for Midcounties Co-operative, said: "Having reviewed the planning application submitted by Asda and following the decision made by the district council, we still feel that the plans for Cinderford are unsound and go against regulations. We remain committed to Cinderford town centre and its residents and are therefore challenging the decision based on these concerns."
Minister Jenny Willott MP told Mr Harper: "The competition regime in the UK is designed to ensure that competition acts in the best interests of consumers."
1,700 Membership of group backing proposals for a new supermarket
]]></text></news-item>