<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-6511-JBVM-Y3BD"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>CAMPAIGNERS' VICTORY OVER 'SMELLY PLANT'; Crowd applauds rejection of factory that turns scraps food into methane gas - but companies could appeal</title><source>Manchester Evening News</source><author>Ollie Gillman</author><text><![CDATA[ACAMPAIGN group has won its battle to prevent a 'smelly' waste processing plant being built.
Hundreds of members of Ramsbottom Against the Waste Site (RAWS) attended Bury council's planning meeting to see it reject the application for the site.
At least 50 campaigners, including young children, held a demonstration beforehand outside Bury town hall, waving placards and chanting.
More than 2,100 people signed a petition against Peel Environmental and Tamar Energy's plans to build an anaerobic digestion (AD) plant - to turn food waste into methane gas - on Fletcher Bank Quarry in Ramsbottom.
The campaigners were unhappy with the plant being built on Green Belt land, and were concerned about its smell.
Ramsbottom councillor Ian Bevan formed RAWS when the plans were submitted in February 2013 and has led the campaign since.
He said the crowd erupted in applause when the council announced its decision.
Coun Bevan said: "We in RAWS are so grateful to all the residents and traders that have joined us in our opposition to this proposed plant.
"It was also heart-warming that the political parties joined us in our fight and that we could express a united front."
A statement from the two companies said they were 'disappointed' and that they were considering their next steps.
Peel Environmental and Tamar Energy said: "We believe AD is a highly responsible way of dealing with organic waste. Directing waste to the AD facility in Ramsbottom, rather than to landfill, would result in a significant displacement of approximately 30,000 tonnes per year of carbon dioxide from the atmosphere.
"The site would support up to 175 full-time jobs during the construction phase and as many as 10 full-time jobs once the facility is operational."
The companies could now appeal the ruling.
]]></text></news-item>