<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-JTD1-DYVR-P4FY"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Sen. Brown Calls On Pres. Obama To Issue Executive Order Protecting LGBT Workers From Workplace Discrimination; Sen. Sherrod Brown (D-OH) News Release</title><source>Congressional Documents and Publications</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[WASHINGTON, DC --U.S. Sen. Sherrod Brown (D-OH), along with more than 175 Senators and Representatives, sent a letter to President Barack Obama yesterday calling on him to issue an executive order banning federal contracts from being awarded to contractors who do not have policies prohibiting discrimination based on sexual orientation and gender identity.
"A fair workplace exemplifies our nation's belief in equality and justice," Brown said. "This executive order would ensure lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender workers can earn a living without fear that they will lose their job because of who they are."
The signatories urged President Obama to join previous presidents who worked to prohibit discrimination by companies receiving taxpayer dollars through federal contracts. Public opinion polls show an overwhelming majority of Americans believe it is already illegal to fire people based on sexual orientation rather than job performance.
Brown is a strong advocate for civil rights and has been a long-time supporter of the LGBT community. Brown voted in favor of the Employment Non-Discrimination Act (ENDA) in November of 2013, an effort to protect Americans from workplace discrimination on the basis of sexual orientation or gender identity. The bill is currently awaiting a vote in the House. He also introduced the Housing Opportunities Made Equal (HOME) Act of 2013, a bill that would protect LGBT individuals from housing discrimination. His legislation would expand the Fair Housing Act and the Equal Credit Opportunity Act to include sexual orientation and gender identity as personal characteristics that may not be used to determine access to housing or credit.
Brown is one of just a handful of sitting senators who voted against the Defense of Marriage Act in 1996.
The full text of the letter is below:
March 18, 2014
The President
The White House
1600 Pennsylvania Ave, NW
Washington, DC 20500
Dear Mr. President,
We are writing to urge you to fulfill the promise in your State of the Union address to make this a "year of action" and build upon the momentum of 2013 by signing an executive order banning federal contractors from engaging in employment discrimination against lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender (LGBT) Americans. As you have said before, "now is the time to end this kind of discrimination, not enable it."
As we continue to work towards final passage of the Employment Non-Discrimination Act (ENDA) with strong bipartisan support, we urge you to take action now to protection millions of workers across the country from the threat of discrimination simply because of who they are or who they love. We are committed to doing all that we can in Congress to get ENDA to your desk this year; however, there is no reason you cannot immediately act by taking this important step. This executive order would provide LGBT people with another avenue in the federal government they could turn to if they were the victim of employment discrimination by a federal contractor. When combined with ENDA, these non-discrimination protections would parallel those that have been in place for decades on the basis of race, sex and religion.
An executive order covering LGBT employees would be in line with a bipartisan, decades-long commitment to eradicating taxpayer-funded discrimination in the workplace. In 1941, President Roosevelt prohibited discrimination in defense contracts on the bases of race, creed, color, or national origin. In subsequent executive orders, Presidents Roosevelt, Truman, Eisenhower, Kennedy, and Johnson expanded these protections to ensure that taxpayer dollars are not used to discriminate.
In addition, most of the largest government contractors - companies like Boeing, Raytheon, and Lockheed Martin - have LGBT non-discrimination policies in place. They adopted them because business leaders recognize that discrimination is bad for the bottom line.
Finally, time is of the essence. Even with an executive order in place, full implementation of these protections will require regulations to be developed and finalized, a process that will take many months, if not longer, to fully put in place.
Issuing an executive order prohibiting discrimination against LGBT workers in federal contracts would build on the significant progress for LGBT rights made during your time as President and would further your legacy as a champion for LGBT equality. We urge you to act now to prevent irrational, taxpayer-funded workplace discrimination against LGBT Americans.
Read this original document at: http://www.brown.senate.gov/newsroom/press/release/sen-brown-calls-on-pres-obama-to-issue-executive-order-protecting-lgbt-workers-from-workplace-discrimination
]]></text></news-item>