<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-0841-DXKS-J165"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>New Website to Assist Millions of Taxpayers with Undisclosed, Offshore Accounts</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Wolfe Law Group is pleased to announce the launch of their new website:IRSOffshoreTaxEvasion.com. The new website is designed to help the estimated 10 million US taxpayers with undisclosed, offshore accounts which will be subject to IRS reporting by the implementation of FATCA (Foreign Account Tax Compliance Act).
Beginning July 1, 2014 up to 400,000 Foreign Financial Institutions will have to disclose their US account holders or suffer the consequences, including being shut out of the US banking system and not having their wire transfers processed.
For those US taxpayers in this precarious position they need expert advice and decisive action to pre-empt imposition of civil tax fraud and criminal tax evasion civil and criminal penalties, which may include: wire fraud, mail fraud, money laundering, failure to file FBAR forms (now known as FinCen Form 1114). Total penalties may be millions of dollars with jail sentences imposed for a maximum of over 80 years for all tax-related felonies.
The known alternative for these US taxpayers is the IRS Offshore Voluntary Disclosure Program (OVDP/2012, still in existence), which is fraught with perils. Please see previously published articles, also available atIRSOffshoreTaxEvasion.com:
Why Tax Evasion is a Bad Idea: UBS and Wegelin Bank, ABA/The Practical Tax Lawyer (Spring 2013); International Tax Evasion and Money Laundering, ABA/The Practical Tax Lawyer (Summer 2013).
About the Wolfe Law Group
The Wolfe Law Group is an elite team of international tax, financial and legal experts who work together to provide clients with a time-efficient, cost-effective "one-stop" shop to solve complex, dangerous IRS tax issues. For a free consultation, please send an e-mail to Gary Wolfe atgsw@gswlaw.com
Media Contact: Gary Wolfe, The Wolfe Law Group, 323-782-9139,gsw@gswlaw.com
News distributed by PR Newswire iReach:https://ireach.prnewswire.com
SOURCE Wolfe Law Group
]]></text></news-item>