<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-NF91-JBHM-S546"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Industry Groups Divided On Fix For EPA Boiler MACT Remand 'Confusion'</title><source>Inside EPA Weekly Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Industry groups are divided on how to resolve growing legal and regulatory "confusion" over EPA's request for an appellate court to remand part of its contested boiler and incinerator air rules to the agency, with some industry groups now asking the court to partially scrap -- not remand -- the rules, while other groups are taking a more cautious approach.
The divisions highlight the mounting problems triggered by EPA's Feb. 28 request for the remand in order to have 60 days to better explain the rules' use of a controversial "upper prediction limit" (UPL) method for setting emissions limits in the regulations, creating questions over the fate of briefing slated to begin March 28 in suits over the rules. Some aspects of the rules would be remanded for much longer. An agency spokeswoman has said EPA would leave the implementation of the rules in place during the remand.
EPA says the temporary voluntary remand of the combustion regulations is necessary so that it can "supplement the record" for the rulemakings by addressing questions raised by a D.C. Circuit decision last August in National Association of Clean Water Agencies (NACWA) v. EPA. That ruling raised questions over the UPL statistical method that the agency used to set air toxics limits when it only has a limited number of data points.
The agency used the UPL in setting its combustion air rules, which include a "major" source boiler maximum achievable control technology (MACT) air toxics rule, an "area" source boiler MACT for smaller units, and an emissions rule for commercial and industrial solid waste incinerators, all of which face pending suits. EPA also used the UPL in a sewage sludge incinerator rule, which was litigated and prompted the court's ruling in NACWA.
Separately, EPA is also asking the D.C. Circuit to remand part of its conventional air pollutant rule for new power plants in order to address the UPL ruling, which could create questions about the fate of that litigation.
In the litigation over the package of combustion air rules, a series of new legal filings by industry groups highlight the regulatory and legal confusion over the remand request, and also divisions among industry about how to resolve it. The boiler MACT rules' compliance date is Jan. 1, 2016, industry groups note, giving industry little time to comply and lending urgency to resolving the litigation and the implications for regulatory compliance. Relevant documents are available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID: 2464444)
The Council of Industrial Boiler Owners (CIBO), JELD-WEN, Inc., American Municipal Power, Inc. and the American Petroleum Institute in two March 13 filings with the court agree to a short suspension of the briefing schedule to allow the court to decide on EPA's request before opening briefs are due March 28.
But the industry groups would oppose any longer delay that would allow EPA to complete its remand. "EPA's motion introduces chaos in an already complicated proceeding and would compel sources to continue planning for compliance with standards that EPA admits may change," the groups say.
Other industry groups however split with that position, and are seeking vacatur of the rules. In two March 13 filings, the American Forest & Paper Association, American Wood Council, Biomass Power Association, National Association of Manufacturers, National Oilseed Processors Association, Rubber Manufacturers Association and American Chemistry Council call on EPA to vacate the affected UPL-derived standards.
"While Petitioners do not oppose EPA's request for the opportunity to reassess standards based on nine or fewer data points, Petitioners staunchly oppose EPA's inequitable request that those standards remain in effect during the pendency of the rulemaking needed to accomplish the reassessment," the groups say.
"Remand of the UPL Standards without vacatur -- the relief requested by EPA -- would require Petitioners to spend time and money complying with standards that, by EPA's own admission, were calculated in a legally indefensible manner," they add. Therefore, "Petitioners oppose the motion to remand the UPL Standards and request instead that those standards be severed from this litigation and vacated," the groups say.
They note that all the area source boiler emissions limits were derived from data sets with nine or fewer data points. Unlike CIBO, they oppose any pause in the briefing schedule while the court responds to EPA's remand request.
Eastman Chemical Company, meanwhile, in a March 13 filing supports a short suspension of briefing in order to allow the court to rule on EPA's remand motion, but also asks for "vacatur of all existing source emission standards that apply to coal-fired energy recovery units" of the type operated by the company.
An industry lawyer says that the "super-complex" nature of EPA's remand motion has split industry groups on how to proceed. As a result, "it looks like the current briefing schedule order will stay in place past March 28, which really is ridiculous."
Environmentalists, meanwhile, have asked the court for an extension until March 27 to file their response to the remand request, citing the complexity of the issues raised.
One issue on which industry groups and environmentalists appear to agree is that EPA in its remand request has picked a seemingly arbitrary yardstick to determine which UPL-based standards would be subject to a full notice-and-comment rulemaking, and which would only be subject to a 60-day remand for the agency. An EPA spokeswoman says the 60-day remand is necessary to "further explain, and thus strengthen, the technical analysis" behind the rules. -- Stuart Parker & Chris Knight
]]></text></news-item>