<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-6511-JBVM-Y41B"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Cries of 'shame on you' as homes plans are approved</title><source>Nottingham Evening Post</source><author>Ben Ireland</author><text><![CDATA[A COUNCIL'S decision to approve a 900-home and 2,000-job development in Hucknall was met with cries of "shame on you" from the public gallery.
At a heated meeting night, Ashfield's planning committee voted six to three in favour of the £27 million plans for the historic Watnall Road Rolls-Royce site.
More than 50 local residents attended a packed council chamber as concerns over traffic, health provision, schools and local jobs were raised.
The site will transform the former runway into a road with houses either side, with football pitches, allotments, play areas and a new primary school. Sally Wyatt, chairman of Hucknall's Reach Out Residents' Association, spoke in opposition to the plans ahead of the vote.
After the meeting, she said: "It's a very sad day for Hucknall.
There were numerous misleading statements from councillors to try and convince people this is a good idea but many of the real questions asked were unanswered."
She called for a public inquiry into the plans and raised worries about the traffic. She said: "There are serious hold-ups now caused by access to local firms on Watnall Road. "Residents have carried out their own survey, which found 1,200 vehicles an hour use this road outside of rush hour at present." Councillor Samuel Wilson, who represents Selston, questioned how many unused industrial sites already existed in Hucknall and whether new residents would noticeably in-crease the town centre's footfall.
He said: "The proposal says 2,000 jobs but how many square metres of employment space are empty in Hucknall already? People there are going to drive straight to Bulwell town centre."
Other members seconded the residents' traffic concerns while issues of contamination left from the former airfield were also brought up.
The council's planning officers responded by saying that the site on a prestigious company's location would attract more investment and drive employment for the area's future workers.
Applicant Muse Developments said it would invest £900,000 in transport links to the Rolls-Royce site, which played a pivotal role in both world wars.
A further £750,000 has been promised towards health provision in the area, and a contribution will be made towards local secondary school development.
The council is set to finalise its future housing plan and aims to build 7,000 new homes by 2024 - 2,460 of which would be in Hucknall.
Leader of the council and planning committee member Councillor Chris Baron, who represents Hucknall East, voted in favour of the development.
He said: "We cannot even consider standstill for our town. It is just not an option.
"We have to think of future generations - they need to have education, jobs and decent places to bring up their families." He feared that by turning down the application, the council could lose the extra investment in local infrastructure and jobs for future generations. ¦ Do you agree with the scheme? E-mail newsdesk@nottinghampost.com
'"We have to think of future generations - they need to have education, jobs and decent places to bring up their families." Chris Baron
]]></text></news-item>