<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-4NJ1-DY2T-34GC"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Encana, pleads not guilty to antitrust charges</title><source>The Calgary Herald (Alberta)</source><author>Andrew Harris, Bloomberg</author><text><![CDATA[The U.S. unit of Encana Corp. and Chesapeake Energy Corp., rivals in developing American oil and gas resources, pleaded not guilty to conspiring to avoid competing for leases in Michigan.
Company representatives entered the pleas Wednesday before a state court judge in Cheboygan, Mich.
Michigan Attorney General Bill Schuette earlier this month said the gas giants violated state antitrust laws by agreeing in which counties each would bid before a May 2010 auction for exploration rights. Each company faces a charge of conspiring to restrain trade, punishable by a fine of as much as $1 million, and an attempted-conspiracy count that carries a $1,000 penalty.
Encana has invested $230 million in Michigan over the past five years, company spokesman Doug Hock said Wednesday.
Chesapeake, which spent $400 million on exploration of Michigan's Collingwood shale formation, has since withdrawn from the state.
Schuette said the alleged agreement may have been a key factor in the decline of lease prices from $1,510 an acre at the May 2010 sale to less than $40 an acre five months later. The companies cite results of internal investigations in 2012 in maintaining they didn't violate Michigan law.
"When all of the evidence is viewed by the courts, we believe the conclusion will be clear that Encana did not breach any antitrust laws," Hock said in an emailed statement confirming the company's plea.
Gordon Pennoyer, a spokesman for Chesapeake, said the state's action has no merit and that the Oklahoma City-based company also pleaded not guilty.
Judge Maria Barton scheduled a May 5 hearing where the companies can challenge whether prosecutors had probable cause to bring the charges.
The internal investigations of Michigan bidding practices were prompted by a 2012 Reuters report citing emails among executives from both companies.
]]></text></news-item>