<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-6V41-JCTS-G1MG"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>Video: Urine poured into manager’s car </title><source>The Oregonian (Portland Oregon)</source><author>Richard Read rread@oregonian.com</author><text><![CDATA[United Grain Corp., which has locked out Vancouver longshoremen for a year, has released a security video showing someone pouring foul-smelling liquids into a car at the home of a company manager.
The footage shows a hooded figure, with face covered, approaching the car in manager John Lindgren’s Clark County driveway early last Wednesday. The person is seen emptying two containers of liquid at the base of the windshield by the vehicle’s ventilation system.
“I believe me and my family are being targeted by ILWU members,” Lindgren wrote in a crime report, referring to the International Longshore and Warehouse Union.
Separately, the United Grain manager reported that a sign titled “memorial dedicated to a scab,” or replacement worker, was placed on his porch in April. In May, he sent the Clark County Sheriff’s Office photos of two of his vehicles defaced with the word “scab,” one with an expletive added.
As United Grain’s lockout enters its second year, tactics have turned nasty, according to the National Labor Relations Board.
The NLRB’s Seattle director has accused union members of assaulting security officers and threatening to rape a manager’s daughter and harm a supervisor’s children. He has also accused United Grain of unfairly locking out union members and unjustly discharging longshore workers who wouldn’t operate equipment they considered unsafe.
Jennifer Sargent, a longshore union spokeswoman, said she expects the accused members to be cleared. Regarding United Grain’s reports of vandalism, she said: “The Oregonian’s focus on unproven allegations and sensationalistic rumors is a distraction from the fact that multinational grain companies are bleeding the Columbia River of its local, family-wage jobs and the incomes that are critical to our communities.”
United Grain spokesman Pat McCormick said there’s no proof that the vandalism is related to the labor dispute at the export terminal. But he said the idea that vandals potentially connected to the labor dispute would come to employees’ homes is intimidating. Someone painted the word “scab” on one employee’s house, he said.
Last year, five vehicles other than Lindgren’s were fouled by smelly liquids, McCormick said. Two were parked at employees’ homes, and two were parked at a hotel where replacement workers stay, he said.
One was a manager’s car parked in a structure at United Grain’s Vancouver headquarters, where McCormick said firefighters responded and concluded the liquid was urine from elk or deer. Hunting supply stores sell animal urine for luring game.
Sargent said “company provocateurs” often conduct vandalism to try turning public opinion against union workers during labor disputes. “The fact that Mitsui-UGC sent their accusations to the media tells me the employer is trying to damage workers’ reputations instead of negotiating a good agreement with them,” said Sargent, who referred to United Grain’s Japanese parent company.
McCormick said the idea of a company frame job stretched credulity.
“I’d do a lot of things for my company,” he said, “but I probably would not pour elk urine into my ventilation system to make it look like somebody was targeting me.”
McCormick said there have been no reports of vandalism connected to Columbia Grain Inc., which has also locked out longshore union members.
]]></text></news-item>