<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-H3J1-JC86-138J"><date>2014-03-19</date><title>your views</title><source>The Virginian-Pilot(Norfolk, VA.)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[CLIMATE EDITORIAL IS ALL WET
RE "SCIENCE, DATA and weather trends" (editorial, March 17): The Pilot continues to take a stand on climate change, saying that scientists have said that man burning things is a contributor to global warming. And, once again, The Pilot offers a biased view with absolutely no science behind its opinions that man is causing any of this.
The editorial never mentions that climate scientists were caught colluding to make up numbers to make their data look the way they wanted. How, in just three years, can they come up with a sound hypothesis that reaffirms their findings? That isn't science. If The Pilot believes in scientific consensus, the Editorial Board doesn't know science. Science isn't consensus, it's years (and not just three) of testing, observing the data and then coming to a conclusion.
The earth hasn't warmed in 16 years. That's a scientific fact, not consensus, but Pilot editorial writers never seem to mention that fact, nor do they mention the truth of climate change, which is that there is undoubtedly climate change on Earth, but it has been going on for millions of years.
The Pilot continues to highlight the idea that man is responsible, which is totally without scientific merit. Editorial opinions should be backed with sound data, not the political data liberals want Americans to believe in order to control our lives a little bit more.
Nicholas Renesis
Virginia Beach
Editorial leads the way
Re "Science, data and weather trends" (editorial, March 17): Thanks for your leadership words: "Nobody has time to argue - and argue again - over settled questions."
The sooner we transform our energy systems, the better chance we have to minimize sea level rise. Mitigation is important, but it can't save our coast unless we also take immediate steps to quit releasing heat-trapping gases into our atmosphere.
We know what to do: We must find investment funding to retrofit our buildings. That will save 30 percent of our electricity needs by 2030. We must build offshore wind facilities. Sixty percent of Virginia's energy can be produced by offshore wind. We need to build more than test windmills. We must change the State Corporation Commission's rules to allow a variety of ownership structures for onsite renewable installations.
Investing in pollution controls and renewable energy production will create 123,000 Virginia jobs. Let's argue about possible new ways to fund these projects, whether publicly, privately or some combination.
Jane Twitmyer
Merrifield
Overtime improvement
I would like to respond to recent stories and letters in The Pilot about overtime for public safety employees. Norfolk Fire-Rescue uses staffing software to manage overtime. It is transparent, automated and has been in use for many years. The rules governing overtime were set by the administration. Supervisory adjustment is allowed, but it is also scrutinized for justification.
NFR members who are eligible for overtime are able to work overtime when it is authorized. We do not force our members to work overtime. Overtime selection is governed by skill set, hours of consecutive work and the last date worked. The staffing software will recommend members' names to fill vacant positions. Supervisory intervention is rare. The transparency of the program all but eliminates concerns about unfair overtime selections.
NFR has experienced a recent spike in the amount of overtime used. This is attributed to an increase in employment separations, as noted in The Pilot's story on the issue. Our most recent recruits graduated from training in late October. With those new employees, our overtime targets are back on track.
I want to assure Norfolk residents that the men and women of NFR work daily to provide the very best fire-rescue service possible while maintaining a high level of integrity to guard the public's trust. In addition, our command staff members constantly consider the cost vs. benefit in how we allocate the tax dollars that fund our budget.
Jeffrey F. Wise
Fire chief
Norfolk Fire-Rescue
Norfolk
Their risks are ours
Duke Energy, the North Carolina General Assembly, the state's environmental regulators and the governor have all failed to place a priority on the health of the residents of both North Carolina and Virginia. This situation points to the extreme danger of a one-party (Republican) government.
I'm a Virginian, so some people might say it's none of my business. But our water supply is also in danger of contamination. Hopefully, as the coal ash spill plays out, the result will be a genuine "job killer" - for North Carolina Gov. Pat McCrory.
Thomas Holliday
Virginia Beach
The name is too big
"Coastal Virginia" sounds elegant and looks great on the cover of a lifestyle magazine, but it's too broad to apply to the Tidewater/Hampton Roads region, unless you're planning to include the Eastern Shore, which has a heck of a lot more coast than Virginia Beach.
To illustrate how audacious it is: Would you refer to Jacksonville as "Coastal Florida" or San Diego as "Coastal California?" It just doesn't work to define a finite region like ours.
Jim Roberts
Norfolk
Keeping flight privileges
One of the privileges of being in the military is that service members, military family members and retirees are allowed to fly on military aircraft for free, if there are available seats after all mission-related passengers and cargo are accommodated.
Unfortunately, when a sponsor dies, the widow or widower of the military member no longer has this privilege.
To change this would not cost anyone a dime. In fact, travelers pay for such costs as flight taxes and federal inspections.
Wouldn't it be wonderful to read about something positive for the military for a change?
Linda Russell
Virginia Beach
]]></text></news-item>