<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSP-9N71-JC17-F4G5"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Featuring dazzling martial arts moves</title><source>Northern Valley Suburbanite (Bergen, North Jersey)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[theater review
schools
Spring break is victim of snow
TENAFLY - Spring break will be shorter this year, after district officials decided to use two of the five days to make up for missed classroom time due to inclement weather. Classes will be in session on April 14 and 15 after using the three days set aside for snow days and declaring two more due to storms that ransacked the area this winter. PAGE 3
streets
Tackling the potholes
Streets in the Northern Valley took a beating after winter storms hit the area on almost a weekly basis this winter season, although the numbers of potholes were not as high as some Department of Public Works (DPW) heads were expecting. PAGE 3
communtiy
Anger grows with parking on Summit
TENAFLY - The Police Department is making recommendations to restrict parking on Summit Street after residents complained that BMW of Tenafly allows employees to park on the street resulting in alleged dangerous and inconvenient conditions - including blocking fire hydrants and private driveways. PAGE 4
field project
Quality-of-life concerns vetted
TENAFLY - While district officials move forward with plans to light and turf Geissinger Field, efforts to mitigate potential problems - such as light spillage and noise pollution - are a top priority. PAGE 5
government
Council awards garbage contract
TENAFLY - After an intensive search for a company to collect solid waste, borough officials opted to continue with Waste Industries - awarding it a five-year contract on March 11 that maintains rear-yard pick up. PAGE 6
community
County celebrates its Irish heritage
BERGENFIELD - Dancers, bagpipers, marching bands and fire trucks passed along Washington Avenue, clapped and cheered on by the crowd. Children dressed in green sat on the sidewalks, excited to get free candy and see law enforcement officers on horseback. PAGE 10
editorial
No snow? Clean out instead
Since snow hasn't been in the forecast recently, we're actually thinking that spring might really be around the corner soon. So maybe we change stop thinking about shoveling snow and turn to another annual task - spring cleaning. PAGE 12
opinion
Killing me softly with your song
As a loyal shopper at your grocery store, I thought it was time to acknowledge the contribution you make to my weekly food shopping experience. PAGE 13
basketball
Panthers push past Cougars, 54-51
CRESSKILL - Cedar Grove burst out of the halftime locker room with an 8-0 run to turn a six-point deficit into a two-point advantage over Cresskill in the March 10 North 1, Group 1 state section final. PAGE 51
LIFE & ARTS
Protecting elephants
ENGLEWOOD - When Max Kauderer saw the body of a dead elephant during a family trip to Africa two years ago, it wasn't only the body that horrified him; it was the apathy of the natives to seeing this gentle, intelligent creature killed. "The rangers reacted to it as it were almost normal to them," said Max, a 17-year-old Englewood resident. PAGE 22
LIFE & ARTS
What does it mean to successfully age?
What does it mean to age successfully? Does it mean that you have to start a new career? Start running marathons? Learn to dance? PAGE 42
life & arts
Vaccines are not just for children
What are vaccines and why do we need them? A vaccine is a preparation that is designed to prevent a specific disease by stimulating the production of antibodies. PAGE 43
]]></text></news-item>