<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-47S1-JB4F-Y0S2"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Forest Oil inches higher, resistance at 12-day EMA</title><source>News Bites US Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Forest Oil Corporation (NYSE:FST), NYSE's 58th largest exploration & production company by market capitalisation, increased 1.0% but fell short of the 12-day Exponential Moving Average [EMA] of US$1.89. Compared with the S&P 500 Index which rose 11.2 points (or 0.6%) in the day, this represented a relative price increase of 0.4%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Forest Oil, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051961580314613
Bullish SignalsUptrend- The stock rose 1.0% on high volatility today and expanding price range.
Top traded Forest Oil call options [volume of contracts in brackets; 1 contract is 100 shares]Exercise 2; Expires 17 May, 2014: 0.15 up 50.0% [40]
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Earnings of 3 [29.2]. - Price/Sales of 0.5 [1.2]. We estimate Forest Oil stock is trading at a current year Price/Sales of 0.4 and a forward year Price/Sales of 0.4. - Return on Assets 6.6% [3.0%].- Return on Capital Employed 20.3% [7.5%].- Price to EBITDA of 0.6 [6.4].Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 2.9 is comfortably below 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 30.2%. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.2. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued and ranks in the top 5% of stock by value of Q Ratio.- Revenue growth has shown signs of recovery in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]

Bearish Signals- In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week low nineteen times, pointing to a significant downtrend. - The present value of US$1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in Forest Oil is US$294, for a capital loss of US$706.
- Revenue growth rate has seen consecutive falls and seems to be on a slippery slope in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 4,699,000 shares worth US$8.6 million traded. Trading volume was 1.3 times average. Beta: the Beta of Forest Oil stock is 1.7. A Beta greater than 1 suggests this is a high risk, high return stock with volatility greater than that of the market. - Forest Oil is at a discount of 72.6% to its 12-month high of US$6.67 on 18 Sep, 2013. It is also at a premium of 8.9% to the 12-month low of US$1.68 on 14 Mar, 2014.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 27: Cohen, Placitella & Roth, PC Investigating Forest Oil, Inc. for Misleading Statements Regarding Results and Debt Agreements[News Story] PHILADELPHIA, Feb. 27, 2014 -- Cohen, Placitella and Roth, PC is investigating claims on behalf of investors who purchased Forest Oil, Incorporated ("Forest Oil" or "Company") (NYSE:FST) stock between October 3, 2013 and February 26, 2014, inclusive. The investigation concerns whether Forest Oil and certain of its officers and/or directors disseminated material false and/or misleading information to investors in violation of Sections 10(b), and 20(a) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934.Forest Oil is an independent oil and gas company that acquires, explores for, develops, and produces oil, natural gas, and natural gas liquids.
February 25: Forest Oil Announces Fourth Quarter and Year-End 2013 Results[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Usnyse/Stock/News/556680.htmlSource: NASDAQ Stock Exchange
February 04: Forest Oil Announces Fourth Quarter and Year End 2013 Earnings Release Date and TeleconferenceDENVER-- Forest Oil Corporation (NYSE:FST) (Forest or the Company) announced today that its fourth quarter and year end 2013 earnings release will be issued after the close of trading on the New York Stock Exchange onTuesday, February 25, 2014.A conference call is scheduled for Wednesday, February 26, 2014, at 7:00 AM MT to discuss the release.
December 02: Forest Oil Announces 2014 Capital Budget and Guidancehttp://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Usnyse/Stock/News/535041.htmlSource: NASDAQ Stock Exchange
November 26: Templar Energy and Le Norman Fund I Announce the Closing of the Forest Oil Texas Panhandle Asset Acquisition[News Story] OKLAHOMA CITY, Nov. 26, 2013 -- Templar Energy LLC and its wholly owned operating subsidiary, Le Norman Operating LLC, (the "Company") and its joint venture partner Le Norman Fund I LLC, announce the closing of the acquisition of Texas Panhandle Assets from Forest Oil Corporation.
November 25: Forest Oil Announces Closing of Texas Panhandle Area Divestiture[News Story] DENVER-- Forest Oil Corporation (NYSE:FST) (Forest or the Company) today announced that it closed the previously announced sale of its properties in the Texas Panhandle Area for net cash proceeds of approximately $944 million, after customary adjustments to reflect an effective date of October 1, 2013.
November 22: Forest Oil Announces Results of Its Cash Tender Offer for Its 7.50% Senior Notes Due 2020 and Its 7.25% Senior Notes Due 2019[News Story] DENVER- Forest Oil Corporation (NYSE:FST) (Forest or the Company) announced today the results of its previously announced cash tender offer (the "Offer") to purchase up to $700 million (the "Aggregate Maximum Tender Amount") aggregate principal amount of its 7.50% Senior Notes due 2020 (the "2020 Notes") and its 7.25% Senior Notes due 2019 (the "2019 Notes" and, together with the 2020 Notes, the "Notes").
ISIN: US3460917053
N:FST
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>