<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-9T91-JBRX-82HV"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Scam robocall firm must pay $168,277.50</title><source>Arkansas Democrat-Gazette (Little Rock)</source><author>LINDA SATTER ARKANSAS DEMOCRAT-GAZETTE</author><text><![CDATA[A federal judge has ordered a Florida-based telemarketing company to pay $78,000 in penalties and $90,277.50 in restitution to Arkansas consumers for violations of state and federal consumer protection laws. Financial Management Partners Inc., owned by Eric Pugh, was one of five Florida-based telemarketing firms that Arkansas Attorney General Dustin McDaniel sued in federal court in 2012. In each case, he sought a court order requiring the company to stop its illegal practices and to pay penalties and restitution.
The suits accused Financial Management and the others of engaging in illegal automated and pre-recorded calls, known as "robocalls," to hundreds of Arkansas consumers. In the calls, the companies touted their ability to help consumers reduce credit-card interest rates, although in reality, the companies did little or nothing to help the consumers in exchange for accepting a fee, the suit said.
Financial Management was accused of transferring existing consumer credit-card debt to new cards with interest rates that were only temporarily lower. The rates soon returned to the same level or higher than the rates on the previous cards, McDaniel said.
U.S. District Judge Susan Webber Wright's order, issued Monday, notes that the defendants didn't dispute that they collected payments from 40 consumers, usually of between $400 and $1,000 each, and then failed to provide the services they promised.
With this order, four of the five cases McDaniel filed now have been resolved. One of the lawsuits is still pending.
In a news release Tuesday, McDaniel said, "Financial Management Partners and at least four other companies inundated Arkansans with annoying, illegal telemarketing calls, and they even disguised their phone numbers to avoid detection. Worse, when consumers did agree to pay for the services that were advertised, the companies took their money and failed to deliver on promises to lower credit-card interest rates. Fortunately, these companies will not be engaging in those types of illegal practices in Arkansas again." Financial Management no longer exists and Pugh could not be reached for comment on Tuesday.
This article was published 03/20/2014
]]></text></news-item>