<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-HCM1-DY2B-13WT"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>'Scam' dispatched DA busts 16 airport taxi 'bribe takers'</title><source> The New York Post</source><author>Philip Messing and Matt Abrahams  </author><text><![CDATA[Sixteen crooked taxi dispatchers from Kennedy and La Guardia airports raked in up to $1,000-a-day in $10 bribes from hacks looking to skip three-hour waits to pick up fares, authorities said Wednesday.
The accused scammers were slapped with bribery charges after an investigation that began when honest hacks blew the whistle on the hustle in December 2012, said Queens DA Richard Brown.
Some of the whistleblowers worked undercover during the investigation, which included visual and audio electronic surveillance of the alleged crooks.
The dispatchers were arrested after they were told to report to JFK for what they thought was a training session.
"They were summoned for training, and when they turned down a corridor they were placed under arrest," a source said of the surprised workers, who are employed by a Port Authority contractor called Gateway Group One Frontline Services.
PA Inspector General Robert Van Etten said the 16 gamed a system that was ironically created to ensure fairness.
"These defendants sold out their position of public trust and chose to line their pockets and enrich themselves," Van Etten said.
The dispatchers also gave the crooked hacks "shorty tickets" meant for drivers taking fares to nearby Brooklyn, Queens and Nassau - even when they were actually driving into Manhattan or further.
The "shorty tickets" would allow them to cut the line again when they returned.
Cabbies at JFK had no sympathy for the greedy dispatchers.
"I'm very excited to see them get put away. But the system is such that it will happen again," said a 39-year-old cabby who gave his name only as Rahil, adding that "I stuck to the law."
As a Muslim, he said bribery would be against his religion.
Rubel Slahudin, 36, of Ozone Park, said the racket was unfair.
"I wait and I wait, and then someone steals the fare without a ticket," he complained.
The dispatchers took $10 bribes from hacks who did not want to wait in "taxi hold lots" at the two airports so that they could pick up more passengers and make more money, authorities said.
"They are supposed to send the taxi drivers to a taxi hold lot where they wait two to three hours and they're dispatched on demand," the source added.
Instead, they were allowed to go straight to the airline terminal pick-up areas, Brown said.
The dispatchers are supposed to summon cabs from the hold lots to pick-up areas at the terminals as flights arrive.
pmessing@nypopst.com
]]></text></news-item>