<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-K9F1-JB5P-J0HV"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Philippines: Akbayan party-list solons file motion to junk Meralco's latest rate adjustment application</title><source>Thai News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A week after the Energy Regulatory Commission (ERC) issued an order to recalculate electricity spot market prices, Akbayan Rep. Barry Gutierrez and Walden Bello on Wednesday filed a motion before the regulatory body to dismiss the Manila Electric Company's (Meralco) latest rate adjustment application as "baseless".
It can be recalled that Meralco filed a petition with the ERC last February 14 to recover in the March billing the P5.33 per kilowatt hour (kWh) rise in generation charge in January.
Gutierrez said that given ERC's ruling that the computations and the prices made in the Wholesale Electricity Spot Market (WESM) during the November and December 2013 supply months could not qualify as reasonable, rational and competitive, there is consequently no basis for Meralco to impose an incremental generation charge to its customers.
In their five-page motion, the Akbayan lawmakers urged the ERC to "immediately dismiss the application for recovery of the differential generation charge for the December 2013 Supply Month filed by Meralco," following the results of ERC's investigation that the power supply rate hike last December 2013 were unreasonable and irrational and, therefore, void.
Considering the finding [of the ERC]...that prices in the WESM during the December 2013 supply month could not qualify as reasonable, rational and competitive, there is consequentially no basis for Meralco to impose an incremental generation charge on its customers," Gutierrez told reporters after the filing.
"The application should thus be dismissed accordingly," Gutierrez stressed.
Akbayan also demanded the ERC to fully investigate and impose due penalties against companies that are proven violators of the established competitive market practices.
"With the discovery of ERC that there, indeed, was an unreasonable and irrational increase in power supply rates, it, inadvertently, admits that there is a lapse on the conduct of power market in the country that requires a thorough investigation," Gutierrez said.
"If proven that the players had come together to manipulate the market, penalties should be imposed against violators of true market competition," Gutierrez asserted.
To prevent future irrational power rate hikes, Akbayan renewed its call for a greater transparency and clarity and improved competition in the power market that will prevent future abuses by profit-driven market players.
"All trades on power should be conducted in an open exchange for public scrutiny. Companies should be required to fully declare and to bring their products into a transparent market where they are exchanged competitively," Gutierrez pointed out.
"This will prevent price-fixing, backroom deals among businesses, irrational cost inflations and unjust power charges that are usually shifted to unsuspecting consumers," he added.
The lawmaker also stressed that these much-needed reforms will aid the government in effectively protecting the rights and welfare of the power consumers against market abuse.
It was reported that Meralco's new rate adjustment application will allow the company to impose an incremental generation charges upon its customers in their March-August 2014 billings until it fully recovers the PhP24.82 billion generation costs it incurred from purchasing expensive alternative fuel for plants and expensive spot market power supply for December 2013 due to the simultaneous maintenance shutdown of various power suppliers.
However, the Philippine Electricity Market Corp. (PEMC), which operates the WESM, and taking its cue from the ERC's latest order, has already recalculated rates for November and December 2013, which resulted in proposed record rate hikes in Meralco bills in December 2013 and January 2014.
According to PEMC's initial estimates, the original proposed increase of P4.15 per kWh for December may become roughly P2.43 per kWh and the original proposed hike of P5.33 per kWh for January may drop to P3.02 per kWh. - PNA
]]></text></news-item>