<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-9WJ1-DY37-C54S"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>DAILY BRIEFING</title><source>The Baltimore Sun</source><author> THE BALTIMORE SUN </author><text><![CDATA[Howard Co. suing Columbia developer over TIF fee
Howard County government has filed a lawsuit seeking $106,161 in damages against Howard Hughes Corp., the principal developer of downtown Columbia, after the developer allegedly failed to pay a county application fee.
The suit, which was filed in Howard County Circuit Court in February and was moved to federal court last week, has been filed to recoup fees allegedly charged by the county to the developer for the request to establish a Tax Increment Financing, or TIF, district for the developer.
Howard Hughes senior vice president John DeWolf and David Nitkin, a county spokesman, both declined to comment.
A Jan. 29 memo sent on behalf of the developer by Mark Keener, an attorney at Gallagher, Evelius & Jones LLP, said no fees are due to the county because Howard Hughes never filed an application for a TIF.
The complaint states that the county did receive an application for a TIF from Howard Hughes on Oct. 10. A copy of the alleged application was not attached to the complaint.
A TIF is a financing tool that allocates increased property tax revenue on newly developed property toward paying debt on county-issued bonds used to make public infrastructure improvements, like parking decks and roads, to the developed area.
The TIF district was never set up.
-- Luke Lavoie, Baltimore Sun Media Group
States to join U.S. review of Comcast deal
Florida and other states will join the Justice Department in seeking to determine if Comcast's plan to merge with Time Warner Cable is legal under U.S. antitrust law.
"We are part of a multistate group reviewing the proposed transaction along with the U.S. DOJ Antitrust Division," the Florida attorney general's office said.
It was not known how many states had joined the task force.
Indiana officials were also looking at the deal to determine "the potential impact in Indiana."
Pennsylvania, where Comcast is headquartered, was "reviewing the case independently," said Joe Peters, a spokesman for the state's attorney general's office.
Comcast had no comment on the states' review of its proposed deal.
Comcast has argued that the combination would not reduce competition because the two cable providers do not compete in any markets. The company pledged to divest 3 million subscribers, so the combined customer base of 30 million would represent slightly less than 30 percent of the U.S. pay television video market.
A combined Comcast and Time Warner Cable would also have about a one-third share of the high-speed Internet market.
Hershey investors win round in child labor suit
Hershey Co., the nation's largest chocolate maker, was ordered to face a lawsuit by investors seeking to force it to turn over records about cocoa from African farms that may use illegal child labor.
A Louisiana pension fund raised legitimate questions about Hershey executives' knowledge of how much of the company's cocoa, grown in West Africa, may have been produced by child slaves, Delaware Chancery Court Judge Travis Laster said Tuesday. He overruled a master's recommendation that the shareholders' request to see cocoa-supply chain records be denied.
West Africa, including the top growers, Ghana and Ivory Coast, accounts for about 70 percent of the world's cocoa-bean production. Pressure to manufacture chocolate without harming children may grow as global sales of sweets head toward a record in 2014 and candy makers process more beans, according to data by Euromonitor International Ltd.
The suit's allegations create "a reasonable inference about the possibility" some cocoa Hershey officials bought from Ghana and Ivory Coast suppliers may be tainted by the use of illegal child labor, Laster said.
Those questions may be "sufficient to warrant further investigation," he said.
Jeff Beckman, a Hershey spokesman, said Laster ruled on a procedural issue and didn't find the company's West African cocoa-supply system was marred by child-labor problems. Hershey will continue to oppose the fund's "overly-broad and unmerited effort to examine our confidential records," he added.
-- Bloomberg News
]]></text></news-item>