<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-T3M1-J9YR-G4SJ"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Pensioners should be free to buy a Lamborghini, minister says but Labour warns against trusting people with their money</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>MATT CHORLEY, MAILONLINE POLITICAL EDITOR</author><text><![CDATA[John McTernan opposes plan to allow withdrawal from pension potsAround 13million would have right to spend private pension how they wantEffectively ends the scandal of paltry pension payouts or annuitiesAnyone turning 55 who isn't in a final salary scheme will be able to dip in to their pension and take the income they needIf they die their spouse or loved ones will be able to inherit whatever is left
People should be free to blow their pensions on buying a Lamborghini if they want to, pensions minister Steve Webb said today as a political row erupted over trusting individuals with their own money.
The centrepiece of yesterday's Budget was a plan to allow people to withdraw their pension pot as a cash lump sum instead of investing in a pension plan, which ministers claim will give people choice to spend their money how they wish.
But as Labour MP Tom Watson warned against handing people large lump sums 'with all the everyday temptations and risk-taking that we all know so well'.
Under the changes workers nearing retirement will be allowed withdraw the cash they have built up in private pension pots.
With no need to take out an annuity - paying regular sums for the rest of their life - pensioners will be free to spend their nest eggs as they like.
If follows anger from pensioners about the dismal payouts that annuity providers offer.
Critics claimed the law was needed to stop people squandering their money because they do not realise how long they will live.
But Mr Webb said changes to the state pension, making it more generous, means people will be able to live even if they spend the savings in a private pension pot.
He told the BBC: 'One of the reasons we can be more relaxed about how people use their own money, and as a Liberal Democrat I want to give people those sorts of freedoms, is that with the state pension coming in, the state pension takes people above those sorts of means tests.
'So actually, if people do get a Lamborghini, and end up on the state pension, the state is much less concerned about that, and that is their choice.
'The main thing we're doing is giving people new choices. We don't think people will stop buying annuities, they'll still be the right product for some, and that's why we need to go on making sure that market works betters than it perhaps has in the past.
'But some people want their money perhaps early on, to spend it while they're more fit and able, and make a conscious choice to do that, knowing they'll have less income later. Annuities will still be part of the mix, but people will have new choices as well.'
PENSIONERS COULD BE PRICED OUT OF BUYING ANNUITIES, IFS WARNS
Pensioners could be 'priced out' of buying an annuity as a result of the radical reforms to retirement savings announced in the Budget, a respected economic think tank has warned.
George Osborne made incentives for savers and pensioners the centrepiece of his Budget statement.
But the Institute for Fiscal Studies (IFS) said there would be losers from the package, with those wanting the long-term security of an annuity among those hit.
The IFS also warned that the Chancellor risked weakening the UK's public finances in the long term by using temporary rises in revenue to pay for permanent tax giveaways and called for greater clarity about the substantial spending cuts needed in the next parliament.
The number of higher rate taxpayers will increase from 4.7 million this year to 5.3 million in 2015/16 - including around 350,000 in the top 45p bracket, the IFS predicted.
However, there is growing opposition to the plan from Labour ranks, with Mr Watson warning the state must have a say in how people spend their savings because they receive tax breaks on pension contributions.
Writing on his blog, he said Mr Osborne's policy will come into effect one month before the next election. 
'Millions will suddenly be allowed to empty their pension pots.  Of course, most people will be cautious, careful and responsible.  But even so, the special deal between the state, the individual and the market will have been eroded. 
'Massive lump sums will be in the hands of individuals with all the everyday temptations and risk-taking that we all know so well. 
'And once that money is blown, it will be the wider community that has to pay. Labour, with its collective values and belief in mutualism must oppose these proposals at all costs.'
His argument was echoed by former Labour party adviser John McTernan, who worked for Tony Blair and Gordon Brown, who said people cannot be trusted with their own money.
Mr Blair's former political secretary told BBC2's Newsnight the implications of the changes are 'quite big'.
He said: 'Basically we compel people to save into pensions and give tax relief for pensions and we used to say you have to turn it into an income to last for the rest of your life.
'Now we are saying "take it, spend it if you want to". The moral hazard is great.
'What will happen is we know in their 80s and 90s a lot of people are going to end up on benefits as a result of this policy change.
'Because you cannot trust people to spend their own money sensibly planning for their retirement because they don't image at 65 that they are going to live for another 30 years.'
Mr McTernan worked as an adviser to Harriet Harman and was Political Secretary to Mr Blair before advising two Cabinet ministers in Mr Brown's government.
He also advised Julia Gillard until she quit as Australian Prime Minister last year.
His remarks reveal a long-held suspicion that some in the Labour party think the state knows best when it comes to spending people's money.
Conservative Party Vice Chairman Bob Neill said 'you can't get more patronising' than saying you can't trust people to spend their own money.
He added: 'It's laughable that Ed Miliband's got no response to the budget. His only plan is more borrowing, more spending and higher taxes.
'The people you can't trust are Ed Milliband and Ed Balls who if given half the chance would bankrupt the economy again.'
Lib Dem peer Baroness Grender insisted people would not fall into financial difficulty because the new single tier pension is 'generous in the extreme'.
'It is not about going back to benefits,' she told Newsnight.
The Labour party today sought to distance itself from Mr McTernan's comments. 'He is not a Labour adviser. He does not speak for the Labour party,' a spokesman said.
The centrepiece of the Budget was what the Chancellor described as the most far-reaching change to private pensions since 1921.
It will remove the restriction on the amount of money the 13million people in defined contribution pension schemes can take out of their pension pot.
They will no longer face a current 'punitive' 55 per cent tax rate - which prompts most people to buy an annuity - and will instead be taxed at normal marginal rates.
The cash they withdraw can be used to invest in property, clear debts or spend - just like savings in a regular bank account.
The shock announcement wiped £4.5billion off the value of pension firms, which have been criticised for their opaque fees and poor value products.
But speaking today, Mr Osborne said people should be 'trusted' with their own money.
'What I would say is that people who saved their whole lives, saved for a pension, these are responsible people," he told BBC Breakfast.
'For many people annuities have not been good value... I want people to be trusted to make decisions about their future.'
He said the shake-up, which will allow people on low incomes to draw down their funds without paying punitive tax rates, had been welcomed by a wide range of consumer groups.
IFS director Paul Johnson said some people would lose out with the pension changes but assessed that overall they were probably a positive development.
'I think this Budget will be remembered longer than possibly any of Mr Osborne's other Budgets, other than his first one, because this really is a big change to the pensions market,' he told the BBC Radio 4 Today programme.
'It will really free up people's choices in pensions and that's probably a good thing.
'There are probably some risks associated - who knows what will happen to the annuities market?
'Some people will be left worse off, let's be clear, because it will become more expensive to buy an annuity because only those who really think they are going to live a long time will be buying an annuity, making them more expensive.'
MONEY MAIL EXPLAINS WHAT THE PENSION REVOLUTION MEANS TO YOU:
Who is affected?
The 13 million people with the type of company pension known as a defined contribution scheme, or with a private pension.
In these funds, you and your employer contribute each month to your personal pension pot, which builds up over the years you are working.
The money is invested in the stock market until you finally take your pension.
On retirement, you may take 25 per cent of your accumulated pot of money as a tax-free lump sum. Most people convert the rest into an annuity.
The changes also cover those with any form of private pension, but not workers in final salary schemes.
What is an annuity?
A type of insurance policy that pays you a set income for life in return for your pot of money.
The amount you receive is based on how much you have saved up, and your life-expectancy.
Why have annuities been criticised? 
Payments have fallen hugely in recent years. In 1995, a 65-year-old in good health with a £100,000 pot could have got as much as £940 a month.
Today, the same pensioner typically would get around £509. If they wanted their spouse to carry on receiving income after their death, and the income to be index-linked, the monthly payout would be much lower.
Also, insurers have been accused of ripping off pensioners.
When workers retire, the company that has managed their pension fund offers a quote stating how much annuity income they are willing to pay them.
But frequently these are not the best payouts, particularly for married couples, those with small pensions, smokers, and the sick.
Millions of pensioners are thought to have blindly signed up to these deals without realising they could have received up to 60 per cent more income if they had shopped around.
And once they have taken an annuity there is no turning back - if the retiree suddenly dies the insurer keeps the person's life savings.
What will the changes mean?
From April 2015, no one will have to buy an annuity.
Retirees will still be allowed to take 25 per cent of their pension pot tax-free, but will then have complete control of their remaining cash.
They will be able to draw out as much as they want in any given year, paying only normal levels of income tax rather than the punitive 55 per cent that currently applies.
Similar rules already work successfully in the United States, Australia and Denmark where savers are trusted to manage their own finances.
In addition, from next Thursday, retirees with small pensions will no longer have to buy an annuity.
Anyone with a pot or pots of up to a total of £30,000 can take it all as tax-free cash.
I haven't retired yet  - how will I benefit?
You will be able to spend your pension as you like but if you run out of money you'll have to survive on your state pension alone.
Significantly, any funds left over in your pension after your death will no longer die with you, but can be passed on to your spouse or children or other heirs.
Your pension will form part of your estate and normal inheritance tax rules will apply.
I have retired and taken an annuity  - what can I do?
Anyone who has already taken their pension is stuck with the contract they are in.
There may be exceptions for those who signed up for fixed-term deals or so-called draw-down pensions where their money is still invested, so they may be able to take advantage of the new rules.
]]></text></news-item>