<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-XKV1-DXCW-D342"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Lahore High Court Judgment: Criminal Miscellaneous (Bails) 6094-B-13 MUHAMMAD FIAZ VS STATE E TC</title><source>Pakistan Law Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Lahore High Court has issued the following Judgment:
Form No: HCJD/C-121 ORDER SHEET IN THE LAHORE HIGH COURT, MULTAN BENCH MULTAN. JUDICIAL DEPARTMENT Crl.Misc. No.6094-B of 2013 Muhammad Fiaz versus The State etc. S. No. of order/ Proceeding Date of order/ Proceeding Order with signature of Judge, and that of Parties or counsel, where necessary 18.02.2014. Mr. Adnan Sardar Nakodri, Advocate for the petitioner.
Ch. Muhammad Akbar, DPG with Asif Noor Nadeem, S.I., FIA. Mian Babur Saleem, Advocate for the complainant. Muhammad Fiaz, the petitioner seeks post-arrest bail in case FIR No.53/13 dated 16.4.2012 registered under Section 22(b) Emigration Ordinance, 1979 at police station F.I.A., District Multan. 2. Muhammad Ishaq, the complainant made an application to FIA, alleging that the petitioner-accused has been working in Dubai for the last so many years. He and his brothers, namely, Muhammad Younas and Muhammad Usman prevailed upon him to hand over a sum of Rs.3,50,000/- to them. On fulfilling this demand, Muhammad Fiaz, the petitioner would get him a Visa of Dubai. He complied with the demand made by the three brothers, delivering an amount of Rs.3,50,000/- to Muhammad Younas and Muhammad Usman, co-accused. On 8.9.2011, the complainant landed in Dubai. He was Crl.Misc. No.6094-B-13. 2 received at the Airport by Muhammad Fiaz, the petitioner who took him to his house and promised to get him some employment in Dubai. After a few days, the complainant came to know that he was provided with a Visa of a Company, which was run by Muhammad Fiaz, the petitioner, but his Company was closed for good. In the circumstances, the complainant was constrained to come back to Pakistan after being disgraced, humiliated and tortured. 3. Learned counsel for the petitioner contends that a bare perusal of the FIR shows that not a single penny was paid directly by the complainant to the petitioner; that there is a delay of almost seven months in lodging the FIR; that admittedly the complainant went to Dubai on a valid Visa, and that if he could not settle there on account of his being a non-technical hand, the petitioner or his brothers cannot be blamed for the same; that no case under Section 22(b) of the Emigration Ordinance, 1979 is made out; that if the petitioner has any claim, he might file a suit for the recovery against Muhammad Younas and Muhammad Usman, the co-accused; that the criminal prosecution has been launched just to pressurize the petitioner, who had had no role at all in the matter; that the petitioner was admitted to bail by this Court in a similar case in Crl. Misc. No.155-B of 2014 on 21.1.2014; that the investigation is complete, and the petitioner is no more required for further investigation, and Crl.Misc. No.6094-B-13. 3 it would be useless to keep the petitioner behind the bars indefinitely or until the conclusion of the trial. 4. Ch. Muhammad Akbar, Deputy Prosecutor General duly assisted by Mian Babur Saleem Advocate, learned counsel for the complainant has opposed the grant of bail to the petitioner contending that the petitioner and his brother belong to a ‘Mafia’ and that they deceive simpletons. They took a great deal of time to emphasize that the petitioner is the brain behind this racket and his brothers, Muhammad Younas and Muhammad Usman are just his agents. They befool the people and receive huge amounts from them on behalf of the petitioner. Learned counsel for the complainant, Mian Babur Saleem Advocate, was at pains to explain and expound the provisions contained in Section 22 of the Emigration Ordinance, 1979 to urge that the petitioner is neither a promoter nor has he obtained a license as an Overseas Employment promoter, and even so, he has indulged in the business of emigration on a large scale. According to him, the case of the petitioner is fully covered by the aforesaid provisions, which carry a penalty of 14 years’ imprisonment. He dubbed the petitioner as a dangerous man and implored that the petitioner be not admitted to bail; otherwise, other gullible people would fall a victim to his shenanigans, deception, misrepresentation and fraud. Crl.Misc. No.6094-B-13. 4 5. I have heard the learned counsel for the petitioner as well as the complainant and the DPG, besides going through the relevant record. 6. Except for the bald allegation that the complainant parted with an amount of Rs.3,50,000/- on the asking of the petitioner, there is no evidence whatsoever that he paid this amount directly to the petitioner. Furthermore, if at all the petitioner had held out an assurance to the complainant that he would get him a Visa of Dubai, the alleged pledge made by him stood redeemed in that the complainant went to Dubai on 8.9.2011. He remained there but as to when he returned to Pakistan is not clear from the record or the evidence collected by the Investigating Agency. Again, except for the ‘word’ of the complainant that the petitioner had given him an undertaking that he would give employment to him in his own Company, there is no evidence that the petitioner had actually opened Company in Dubai or that the Visa issued to the petitioner hinted at the employment of the complainant in the Company of the petitioner, as has been alleged in the FIR. It is also not clear from the record as to what job the complainant was hunting for. It has not been claimed by him either that he was a technical hand and/or that he was prevented by the authorities in Dubai to seek employment elsewhere other than the employment of the petitioner. All these circumstances call for further inquiry into the guilt of the Crl.Misc. No.6094-B-13. 5 accused. And it is too early to give an observation as to whether the alleged offence of the petitioner falls under Section 22 of the Emigration Ordinance, 1979. 7. For what has been stated above, the petitioner is admitted to post-arrest bail subject to the furnishing of bail bonds in the sum of Rs.1,00,000/- (Rupees one lacs) with one surety in the like amount to the satisfaction of the learned trial Court. (Mahmood Ahmad Bhatti) Judge APPROVED FOR REPORTING. JUDGE. *Zulfiqar*
]]></text></news-item>