<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-K2W1-JCB3-42NS"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Industry expert says fracking not linked to earthquakes</title><source>Pasadena Star-News (California)</source><author>Kevin Smith</author><text><![CDATA[One industry expert says it would be ludicrous to link Monday s 4.4-magnitude earthquake to hydraulic fracturing, but others insist there is a direct correlation.
Catherine Reheis-Boyd, president and CEO of the Western States Petroleum Association, said a motion presented Tuesday by Los Angeles councilmen Paul Koretz and Mike Bonin to explore that idea is both crazy and uninformed.
They are taking advantage of a political situation, she said. It s not fair to take the action they are taking when they have not taken a moment to understand the issue.
The practice of hydraulic fracturing, or fracking as it is more commonly known, has come under fire in recent months by environmentalists who also link it to increased air and groundwater contamination.
The temblor, which rattled Southern California early Monday morning, was centered near Westwood.
Reheis-Boyd said studies have shown there is no correlation between fracking and earthquakes.
She cited a 2012 hydraulic fracturing study of the PXP Inglewood Oil Field. In that report, Matheson Mining Consultants Inc. concluded that the hydraulic fracturing there did not induce seismic activity. Some minor spikes were noted, the study said, but they were imperceptible at the surface and could have been caused by local traffic.
Los Angeles Councilman Paul Koretz has been pushing for a citywide moratorium on fracking. His call for a review, he said, is based on research.
Experts in the field have made the connection between fracking and earthquakes, he said. We should be doing that work. To allow fracking in earthquake country is more likely to trigger an earthquake.
Koretz said he has been told the fracking process is being used at wells at the VA Administration land in West Los Angeles, near the suspected epicenter of Monday s temblor.
Earthquakes can be triggered if (fracking) is in that area or nearby, he said. We believe fracking is going on at the VA, which is pretty close and certainly, by location, could have been a trigger.
Koretz, Mike Bonin and Bernard Parks have asked the city departments of Emergency Management and Building and Safety to join with federal and state agencies to explore whether fracking could have been a factor in the occurrence of Monday s quake.
A study by three environmental organizations Earthworks, Center for Biological Diversity and Clean Water Action supports Koretz s concerns and concludes there is a direct correlation between fracking and seismic activity.
The study On Shaky Ground How Oil Companies Increase California s Earthquake Risk notes that 54 percent of the state s active wastewater wells lie within 10 miles of a recently active fault.
I would say there is a valid concern, said Andrew Grinberg, a program organizer with Clean Water Action who coauthored the study. We know there is oil and gas activity all over Southern California, and there is a wastewater injection well about eight miles away from where Monday s earthquake was centered.
Grinberg said about 16 barrels of water are extracted for every barrel of oil that is pulled from the ground. When the oil is taken away for processing, the leftover waste water is injected back into the ground under high pressure.
We took a look at the spatial relationships between active faults and wastewater injection wells that are used in fracking, he said. We ve seen evidence of huge increases in quakes in Oklahoma, Ohio and Texas.
Grinberg said there are huge gaps of knowledge about why, when and how wastewater injection can cause earthquakes.
It has not been established what distance (from an earthquake fault line) is safe or unsafe, he said. Our organizations are all calling for a moratorium on fracking in California.
The groups say fracking also produces groundwater contamination and increases greenhouse gas emissions.
Senate Bill 4, which was approved by the state Legislature last year, permits fracking in California but only under strict and stringent guidelines.
Reheis-Boyd said fracking can play an important role in increasing California s oil production.
We are the fourth-largest oil producer in the U.S. but we re only making 38 percent of what we need, she said. There are no crude oil pipelines that come into the state, so out-of-state oil comes in by water-borne tankers. Crude production in Alaska is down, so that leaves oil imports from foreign places that don t like us.
The National Academies of Science and other geologists have concluded the amount of energy involved in the process of hydraulic energy fracturing is far too small to trigger a felt earthquake, Reheis-Boyd said.
Jonathan P. Stewart, a professor of civil and environmental engineering at UCLA, offered his take on the issue via email.
My opinion is that the earthquake was not caused by fracking, Stewart said. I do not have information about where fracking may be occurring in Southern California, but I doubt it is occurring in the area struck by the recent earthquake. Moreover, the depth of the recent California event (reported by USGS as 9 km) is deeper than typical fracking depths. For both of these reasons, I believe the event was caused by the large tectonic-induced stresses in the crust in California, and is not due to any activity of people (fracking or otherwise).
Staff writer Rick Orlov contributed to this report.
]]></text></news-item>