<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-YCP1-JCBD-Y2J6"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>PROBE AFTER CARE WORKER JAILED</title><source>Press Association Mediapoint</source><author>Rod Minchin, Press Association</author><text><![CDATA[An independent investigation has been launched into how a care worker who raped three vulnerable women was not brought to justice nearly a decade ago.
Colin Stokes, 48, was jailed for 14 years after admitting attacking the victims - who all lived in supported accommodation in Gloucestershire - when he was supposedly looking after them.
Police branded Stokes a ``sexual predator'' who deliberately targeted his victims and said he had not shown an ounce of remorse for the damage he had inflicted upon them.
Following the shocking case Gloucestershire County Council commissioned a Serious Case Review to examine how Stokes was allowed to continue working as a carer after being investigated for alleged sex offences against a vulnerable woman in 2007.
``The county council was aware of a police investigation in 2007, but no charges were brought and the case was closed,'' a spokeswoman said.
``However, we have now asked the Safeguarding Adults Board to carry out a serious case review to understand exactly what happened in the past and to check we are doing all we can to keep our vulnerable people safe.''
The Crown Prosecution Service was presented with a file of evidence by police but decided there was insufficient evidence to secure a conviction.
In April last year a second investigation into Stokes began when one of his colleagues blew the whistle and reported what a resident had told them, Gloucester Crown Court heard.
Stokes, who had worked in the care industry for 13 years and in his current job since 2007, was immediately arrested on suspicion of rape and sexual assault and suspended.
Detectives used a specialist intermediary with Makaton cards to question residents who Stokes had been in contact with, after the first victim suggested there were others who had been abused.
Those inquiries found the second victim and forensic inquiries linked him to a third vulnerable adult.
Stokes, of St George's Road, Dursley, Gloucestershire pleaded guilty to three counts of rape, which were all committed between January 1 2012 and April 1 2013. He denied two offences of sexual assault and they were ordered to lie on file by the judge.
The mother of one of Stokes' victims wept in court as the horrific details of the case were read out.
Prosecutor Sarah Regan said the women, aged 32, 50 and 54, all have learning disabilities, difficulties communicating and require 24-hour care.
They were living in privately-owned supported accommodation, which cannot be identified in order to protect the identity of the victims, and Stokes' employers were contracted by the county council to provide care. The contract has since been cancelled.
The accommodation did not have to be regulated by the care watchdog, the Care Quality Commission - and ``fell through the regulatory trap'', Miss Regan said.
Stokes was employed to work the night shift, helping with day-to-day tasks but due to staff cutbacks worked alone.
Miss Regan said that Stokes had no previous convictions but complaints had been made against him previously
``In the time we are concerned with and despite those previous matters which should have caused them some concern, Colin Stokes was more often than not the member of staff that worked in the care home at night, which afforded him the opportunity to carry out the horrific acts that he did,'' Miss Regan said.
During police interviews, Stokes, who is married, denied the offences and explained why he enjoyed working with disabled adults.
``I like to help them because when you walk into a shop with them there are always people giving them nasty looks,'' he said.
``So why should they not be treated like everybody else? Treat people with respect.''
The court also heard moving statements written by relatives of the three victims.
The mother of one victim told the court that when her daughter was born she was advised by doctors she may not survive - but against the odds she did.
``I vowed as long as I live that no one would hurt her. How wrong I was. When we were told what happened to my daughter I felt numb with shock and physically sick,'' she said.
``We thought she would be safe and not come to any harm. Why didn't we see what was happening to her?
``The agony of not knowing how many times that evil man went into her bedroom and hurt her is unbearable.
``Sitting in court makes it all real. This evil man Colin has hurt our little girl in such a horrific way. Our guilt at putting our little girl there will never go away.
``It will be with us until the day we die.''
The sister of another victim branded Stokes a ``monster'' and described the last 10 months as ``horrendous''.
``This man was in a position of trust and he was there to look after her but it turned out he was a monster,'' she said.
``I will never get that monster's face out of my mind and it will stay with me for the rest of my life.''
Judge Jamie Tabor QC jailed Stokes for 14 years and told him he would serve another six years on licence. He also placed him on the Sex Offenders' Register for life.
``These offences are so depraved that they demonstrate that you have no moral boundaries whatsoever,'' the judge said.
``In short you have no moral compass at all.
``These three ladies had the bodies of adults but the minds of children and little children at that. They were every bit as vulnerable as little children and in some ways they were more vulnerable.
``Whereas a child may have later been able to explain what had happened to them when they had reached maturity, these three ladies will never be fully able to explain either what happened of how they feel.
``I have no doubt that you chose them as your victims because of their respective vulnerabilities.
``You had sex with each of them. Such behaviour was cruel and depraved. None of these ladies was capable of giving consent, as you well knew.
``Although they find it difficult to explain what happened there is no doubt that your behaviour has left them very disturbed and deeply upset.
``It is difficult to imagine a greater breach of trust than the taking advantage sexually of highly vulnerable persons entrusted into your sole care.''
As Stokes was led away to begin his sentence, members of the victims' families shouted at him from the public gallery ``Hope you suffer, you bastard'' and ``Rot in hell Stokes''.
After the hearing, the families of Stokes' victims issued a joint statement through police.
They said: ``Stokes was in a position of trust - he was there to look after and protect these women. Not only did he betray that trust in their own home; he turned out to be a monster.
``We would like to thank the police for the sensitive way they have handled this. But the fact is - this should never have happened.''
]]></text></news-item>