<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-SH01-DY7P-T00P"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Where in the World</title><source>The Sandspur: Rollins College</source><author>Lauren Waymire</author><text><![CDATA[Munich, Germany
Bayern Munich's Uli Hoeness has resigned as chairman and president of the German football club after being found guilty of massive tax evasion. The 62-year-old decided not to appeal his sentence for evading roughly $34 million in taxes. Reportedly, he had a Swiss bank account specifically for the purposes of avoiding investment income taxes. The new chairman and president of the top German club will be Adidas-Group CEO Herbert Hainer. Hoeness, who played for Bayern Munich throughout the 1970s and was a member of West Germany's winning World Cup team in 1974, will serve a sentence of three and a half years.
New York City, New York
Cleanup is still underway after a gas leak in East Harlem caused an explosion that demolished two buildings. At least seven people were killed and at least sixty others were injured. Tenants in one of the buildings began to notice the smell on Tuesday, but by the time a dispatch had been sent out after complaints of the smell on Wednesday, the buildings had already exploded.
The incident added to growing concerns over the dated infrastructure of the city. According to BBC News, many water and gas mains date back to the 1800s, and roughly 3,000 miles of old cast-iron pipes still deliver gas in the city.
Paris, France
Amidst growing concerns for the health of citizens due to rapidly rising smog levels, the French capital is offering free transportation to reduce the amount of drivers on the road. The head of the region and the regional public transport authority announced that public transportation would be free during peak times of air pollution.
The French government put the policy into place in 2011. The smog is considered dangerous when levels rise above 80 micrograms(mcg)/meter(m)³ of air, and on March 13 the levels reached 100mcg/m³.
Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia
Malaysian Airlines Flight MH370 disappeared on March 8 with 259 passengers on board in a flight from the Malaysian capital city to Beijing, China. The last known contact with the Boeing 777, a model with an exceptional safety record, was at 1:30 a.m. on the morning of the disappearance.
Initially considered pilot error or technical malfunction possibly resulting in a crash somewhere in the Indian Ocean, data is now suggesting that the plane may have been flown off course intentionally in a hijacking. Several theories are currently being investigated as multiple countries work together to solve this strange aviation mystery.
]]></text></news-item>