<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-T3M1-J9YR-G4XW"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Paperwork errors mean nearly half a million credit card and loan customers will receive £149m in compensation</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>THIS IS MONEY REPORTER</author><text><![CDATA[Nearly half a million credit card and loan customers are to be repaid £149million in interest and charges after banks and building societies failed to make mandatory disclosures in customer letters, it was announced today.
The Office of Fair Trading said 17 banks would return the money to 497,000 customers after they failed to send them some information about their credit agreements, such as statutory wording in statements and arrears notices, as required by the Consumer Credit Act.
Under the act, lenders are not entitled to default charges or interest for the period during which they have failed to comply with the requirements.
David Fisher, senior OFT director for Consumer Credit said these issues were not deliberate misconduct, but the institutions concerned should have ensured they were complying with the law.
He added: 'The OFT welcomes the proactive steps taken to return money to customers where it was incorrectly charged'.
The OFT said customers did not need to not contact their banks or building societies as the 17 lenders, who have not been named, would contact them directly in case of breach of regulation.
Some of the breaches date back as far as 2008 when new CCA rules came into effect, with lenders failing to provide the required wording or information in statements and arrears notices.
In some cases, they did not provide annual statements within 30 days of it being due, or had failed to inform customers of the amount they were in arrears within 14 days of default.
The OFT acted on the matter following similar errors made by Barclays, Northern Rock and The Co-operative Bank, with more than £370million already forked out in redress.
Northern Rock had to pay out £270million to more than 150,000 people after its documentation blunder emerged in December 2012.
In selected Northern Rock letters and customer account statements, certain paragraphs of mandatory wording were written incorrectly and compulsory information about the amount of credit was not included in the statements.
Meanwhile, Barclays said last September it was repaying interest and charges to as many as 300,000 customers after falling foul of the CCA rules, in what was expected to cost it around £100 million.
And Co-op Bank revealed in October that it had increased its provisions for customer redress, in part to cover 'an identified breach of the Consumer Credit Act'.
]]></text></news-item>