<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-9WJ1-DY37-C54F"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>With Crimea lost, West at loss; More sanctions eyed, but reining in Putin difficult</title><source>The Baltimore Sun</source><author>By Paul Richter, Tribune Washington Bureau</author><text><![CDATA[WASHINGTON -- Frustrated by the failure of Western sanctions and diplomacy to stop Russia from seizing Crimea, the Obama administration and its allies scrambled Wednesday to devise new and tougher economic penalties in hopes of preventing President Vladimir Putin from moving forces into Ukraine's eastern territory.
A day after Putin signed a treaty to annex Crimea to Russia, U.S. officials conceded that the breakaway region is lost to Ukraine. Pro-Russian forces seized control of two Ukrainian naval bases in the Black Sea peninsula Wednesday, including its naval headquarters in Sevastopol.
Ukraine's interim government in Kiev said it was making plans to evacuate its outnumbered troops from Crimea and to seek United Nations support to turn the disputed region into a demilitarized zone. U.N. Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon will meet Putin in Moscow on Friday before flying to Kiev.
Moscow's military takeover in Crimea has created a tense new divide between Europe and Russia, which appears increasingly isolated. U.S. and European officials worry that if they fail to halt Putin, long-term security and stability in Eastern Europe as well as parts of Central Asia with large ethnic Russian populations may be at risk.
President Barack Obama, who heads to Europe on Monday for a previously scheduled trip, said in a round of local TV interviews that he will not launch "a military excursion" in Ukraine. But Obama told KSDK in St. Louis that the United States and its allies are preparing "even more disruptive economic actions" against Russia.
"Obviously, we do not need to trigger an actual war with Russia," he said. "Nobody would want that."
Speaking to KNSD in San Diego, he added, "What we are going to do is mobilize all of our diplomatic resources to make sure that we've got a strong international coalition that sends a clear message, which is that Ukraine should decide their destiny."
U.S. officials aim to announce stiffer economic punishments as early as Thursday in response to what they called an illegal land grab by the Kremlin. European Union leaders will meet Thursday in Brussels, and they are likely to coordinate new sanctions with the White House.
Administration officials say they have legal authority to penalize officials up the chain of command in Moscow and are considering sanctions on Putin's inner circle of advisers, Russia's most important state-owned enterprises, the defense industry and banks.
"It's clear that sanctions against a few individuals didn't work," said a senior administration official, who asked to remain unidentified to discuss sensitive diplomacy. "We have to get much tougher to make sure Putin doesn't go further."
Europe appeared split in three camps. Poland, the Baltic states, Sweden and the Netherlands are deeply alarmed at Putin's moves and want strong action. Britain, France and Germany have strong economic ties to Russia but are leaning toward a tougher position, convinced inaction would set a dangerous precedent.
Economically strapped Greece, Spain, Italy, Cyprus and Bulgaria, which depend on Russian energy and trade, may resist stiffer penalties for fear they could cause pain at home.
Moscow has said any expansion of sanctions is "unacceptable and will not remain without consequences."
U.S. officials are considering providing limited military aid to Ukraine as a symbolic expression of support for the interim government, the administration official said.
However, a U.S. military official said he doubted the White House would approve arms shipments, because Russia could see that as highly provocative.
"I don't foresee any appetite for lethal (aid) right now," he said.
Both European and U.S. officials have been startled by Putin's indifference to their efforts to restrain his actions in Ukraine.
Obama and German Chancellor Angela Merkel, among others, have spent hours talking to Putin on the phone in recent weeks, urging him to pull his forces back in Crimea and promising Russia greater involvement in Ukraine as its new government takes shape.
Secretary of State John Kerry spent seven hours Friday with Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov in London, but Lavrov didn't have authority from Putin to negotiate on Ukraine.
Putin has ignored the entreaties, including pleas that he at least leave Crimea in a sort of legal limbo rather than moving to annex it two days after a referendum in the region had approved secession.
Russian news agencies on Wednesday cited Constitutional Court Chairman Valery Zorkin as saying the treaty signed by Putin was valid, thus clearing the way for Moscow to annex Crimea. The treaty requires ratification by the Russian parliament.
Putin's signing of annexation papers Tuesday was "a slap in the face," said Eugene Rumer, director of Russian studies at the nonpartisan Carnegie Endowment for International Peace in Washington. "He was saying, 'I'm doing a victory lap -- you can join me.' "
The Tribune Washington Bureau's Christi Parsons and Kathleen Hennessey contributed.
prichter@tribune.com
]]></text></news-item>