<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-2411-DXY3-01DY"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>INVESTOR ALERT: Investigation of Hyperdynamics Corporation Announced by Law Offices of Howard G. Smith</title><source>Business Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Law Offices of Howard G. Smith announces that it is investigating potential claims on behalf of investors of Hyperdynamics Corporation ("Hyperdynamics" or the "Company") (NYSE:HDY) concerning possible violations of federal securities laws. The investigation focuses on certain statements issued by Hyperdynamics concerning the Company's operations and financial prospects.
Hyperdynamics is an independent oil and gas exploration company engaged in the acquisition, exploration and development of oil and gas properties in the Republic of Guinea, Northwest Africa. The investigation is related to allegations that Hyperdynamics lacked adequate internal and financial controls, and that the Company obtained and retained oil and gas concession rights in violation of the U.S. Foreign Corrupt Practices Act and/or U.S. anti-money laundering statutes.
On September 30, 3013, the Company disclosed that in September 2013 it received a subpoena from the United States Department of Justice (DOJ) requesting that the Company produce documents relating to its business in Guinea, and that the DOJ investigation concerns whether "Hyperdynamics' activities in obtaining and retaining the concession rights and its relationships with charitable organizations potentially violate the U.S. Foreign Corrupt Practices Act or U.S. anti-money laundering statutes." Then, on March 12, 2014, Hyperdynamics' exploration partner, Tullow Oil Plc, halted activities in Guinea due to the DOJ and U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission investigations into Hyperdynamics' activities related to the concession rights.
If you purchased Hyperdynamics securities between November 8, 2012 and March 11, 2014, if you have information or would like to learn more about these claims, or if you have any questions concerning this announcement or your rights or interests with respect to these matters, please contact Howard G. Smith, Esquire, of Law Offices of Howard G. Smith, 3070 Bristol Pike, Suite 112, Bensalem, Pennsylvania 19020 by telephone at (215) 638-4847, Toll Free at (888) 638-4847, or by email to howardsmith@howardsmithlaw.com, or visit our website at www.howardsmithlaw.com .
http://www.businesswire.com
]]></text></news-item>