<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-W0V1-F03R-N0PB"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>One-Year Prison Term Given to Environmental Manager at a Plant That Knowingly Spewed Carcinogen</title><source>FairWarning</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 20, 2014 (FairWarning:http://www.fairwarning.org Delivered by Newstex) Citing 'singularly inexcusable' conduct, U.S. judge sentences industrial polluter in upstate New York. Tonawanda Coke Corp., whose plant near Buffalo, N.Y., knowingly released hundreds of tons of the carcinogen benzene into the air over a five-year span and improperly handled hazardous sludge, was fined $12.5 million. The judge also ordered the company to spend up to $12.2 million on two environmental studies and sentenced its former environmental manager, Mark Kamholz, to a year in prison. Tonawanda Coke and Kamholz were convicted of federal environmental crimes last year in a case that began with do-it-yourself air testing by neighbors of the plant. The plant, along the Niagara River, burns coal to produce coke used in steelmaking. The Associated Press[1], The Buffalo News[2]
America's electric cars are better for the environment, but they share a dirty little secret. The Chevy Volt, Nissan Leaf and Tesla Roadster all use a super-greenhouse gas known as HFC 134a as the refrigerant for their air conditioners. The liquid coolant is so potent that when it leaks into the atmosphere it traps 1,400 times more heat than carbon dioxide. For automakers and advocates of green transportation, it poses an uncomfortable truth: Vehicles touted as a solution to climate change carry a hairspray-sized canister loaded with a chemical that significantly contributes to global warming. Among 16 electric models on America's roads, only two—Chevy's newest model of its all-electric Spark and the Honda Fit—have ditched the super greenhouse gas for an alternative. InsideClimate News[3] Four of the 10 cities with the world's worst air pollution are in Iran. Figures from the World Health Organization list as No. 1 the small Iranian industrial city of Ahvaz, which has three times the concentration of pollutants as Beijing. Tehran, Iran's capital and the largest city in western Asia, fares better with a ranking of 82nd, but still has roughly four times the concentration of polluting particles as Los Angeles. Many Iranians blame U.S.-led trade sanctions that cut access to cleaner oil refining technology, but some experts also point to a soaring population, mismanagement and corruption. During bad air periods, school is cancelled for a week at a time; the sick and elderly are told not to leave home; and people are banned from driving on designated days. Separately, China is speeding development of a new type of nuclear power plant to reduce reliance on coal and cut pollution. Newsweek[4], The Guardian[5] Days after its ban is lifted, BP wins U.S. leases for deep-water energy exploration in the Gulf of Mexico. The Interior Department announced that it sold $872 million of Gulf leases to major oil companies, including BP's winning bids totaling $41.6 million for 24 lease blocks. It marked a milestone in BP's quest to recover from the 2010 Gulf blowout that killed 11 people and spilled millions of barrels of oil. BP reached an agreement a week ago with the Environmental Protection Agency that lifted a ban imposed in 2012 barring the company from new federal business. BP will continue to be monitored to ensure it is operating safely. But critics said the pact was too lenient for a company involved in not only the Gulf blowout but also a 2005 Texas refinery explosion that left 15 dead. The New York Times[6], The Washington Post[7] Alzheimer's disease takes a heavier toll on women. A report by the Alzheimer's Association said one in six women over 65 will get the irreversible neurological disorder during their lifetimes, versus one in 11 men. The report also said women in their 60s are twice as likely to develop Alzheimer's as they are to get breast cancer; blacks are twice as likely as whites to get Alzheimer's and more than 5 million Americans are living with the disorder — figure that will grow to 16 million by 2050. Separately, research by Harvard scientists suggests that the failure of a natural system that protects brain cells plays a key role in causing the disorder. The researchers found that people diagnosed with Alzheimer's, or the mild cognitive impairment that precedes dementia, had lower levels of a protective protein called REST. Time[8], The Boston Globe[9] Compiled by Stuart Silverstein [1]: http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/tonawanda-coke-manager-face-penalty-for-polluting/2014/03/19/5fa01026-af4e-11e3-b8b3-44b1d1cd4c1f_story.html [2]: http://www.buffalonews.com/city-region/federal-court/tonawanda-coke-to-pay-24-million-for-singularly-inexcusable-environmental-crimes-20140319 [3]: http://insideclimatenews.org/news/20140319/electric-cars-have-dirty-little-secret [4]: http://mag.newsweek.com/2014/03/28/air-pollution-iran-tehran.html [5]: http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/mar/19/china-uranium-nuclear-plants-smog-thorium [6]: http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/20/business/energy-environment/ban-lifted-bp-bids-42-million-to-win-gulf-oil-leases-in-us-auction.html?ref=us [7]: http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/interior-sells-850-million-worth-of-leases-to-major-oil-companies/2014/03/19/24f5c562-af83-11e3-95e8-39bef8e9a48b_story.html [8]: http://time.com/29680/women-at-higher-risk-of-developing-alzheimers-disease-than-men/ [9]: http://www.bostonglobe.com/metro/2014/03/19/harvard-team-discovers-protein-that-appears-protect-aging-brain-against-alzheimer/lxSkR25YrHx5zroLB7TUCP/story.html

]]></text></news-item>