<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-SKM1-F05M-K4C8"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Silicon Valley's toxic past: How tech waste contaminated Mountain View and beyond</title><source>Silicon Valley Business (California)</source><author>Lauren Hepler</author><text><![CDATA[Way back in the 1960s and 1970s, tech firms like Intel Corp. and Fairchild Semiconductor Corp. used toxic solvents to produce early computer chips. But that decades-old&nbsp;pollution has since led to additional environmental damage&nbsp;- and potential health threats - in Silicon Valley and other distant locales, according to a new report.
The Center for Investigative Reporting and the Guardian US conducted&nbsp; an in-depth study published this week on&nbsp;a government-designated environmental cleanup site in Mountain View that serves as a case study for 1,300 similarly toxic "Superfund" sites nationwide. The article found that costly clean up often creates more waste that goes beyond Silicon Valley and its residents.
The report follows the "toxic trail" of groundwater in Mountain View&nbsp;contaminated by cancer-causing solvents such as trichloroethylene and benzene, which were previously used by tech companies to degrease chips.&nbsp;
In an effort to limit harmful vapors wafting into nearby job and housing clusters - including massive tech campuses for companies like Google Inc. and Symantec Corp. - water is pumped out of the ground and sent to questionable treatment plants in places like Kentucky, Arizona or a separate plant in Silicon Valley. But that causes more concerns.&nbsp;
The CIR/Guardian report explains:&nbsp;
"Along the trail, contained toxic waste is turned into an array of uncontrolled and potentially worse problems that fan out across the U.S.&nbsp;
Often the original mess is almost untreatable. In Silicon Valley's case, it would take 700 years of continuous treatment to make the groundwater drinkable.'"
Read much more about the environmental mess - including the potential impacts on your food supply - in the full report.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Silicon Valley Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>