<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-JD11-DYX5-X3TH"><date>2014-03-21</date><title></title><source>The Japan News</source><author>The Yomiuri Shimbun</author><text><![CDATA[A Tokyo-based railway consulting company paid a total of about 130 million yen in kickbacks to foreign civil servants, in return for orders it received, to conduct projects involving Japanese official development assistance in their countries, according to sources familiar with the case.
The alleged illegal payments included about 100 million yen in kickbacks paid by Japan Transportation Consultants, Inc. (JTC) to public employees and others from Vietnam, Indonesia and Uzbekistan from 2008 to 2012, company officials told The Yomiuri Shimbun.
The payments, worth 100 million yen, came to light in the course of a tax inspection by the Tokyo Regional Taxation Bureau. During the inspection, JTC did not reveal the recipients of the money. As a result, the bureau concluded the payments must be treated as "concealed corporate expenditures." JTC was ordered to pay about 40 million yen in punitive taxes, equivalent to 40 percent of the kickbacks, in addition to ordinary corporation tax.
Furthermore, JTC is found to have continued similar payments even after the start of the bureau's tax inspection, the sources said.
JTC's payments likely violate the Unfair Competition Prevention Law, which prohibits business corporations from giving bribes to foreign government employees.
The kickbacks were paid from 2008 to 2012, with four ODA projects that totaled about 6 billion yen received in return.
The 130 million yen total includes 30 million yen in kickbacks that had not been identified through the tax inspection, which covered JTC's expenditures made during the seven-year period to December 2012. About one-third of the 30 million yen was paid after the start of the tax investigation by the bureau in April last year, according to the sources.
JTC was established in 1958 when construction began on the Tokaido Shinkansen line. Its main shareholders are the two wholly owned subsidiaries of East Japan Railway Co. and Central Japan Railway Co.
The company, which specializes in railway construction design and ground surveying, began expanding overseas in the 1990s. It has received 19 ODA projects totaling 25 billion yen since 2000, including orders it received while participating in joint ventures.
According to JTC and others, the four projects for which the company paid kickbacks related to railway construction design, construction surveillance and other services. They were all yen-loan-financed projects, with the orders received by joint ventures headed by JTC.
According to a source related to JTC, the company paid money to a senior official of an office responsible for project administration at Vietnam Railways, an official in a position of responsibility at the Directorate General of Railways at the Indonesian Transportation Ministry, and an official in charge of the relevant project at Uzbekistan Temir Yollari, a state-run railway company.
JTC first recorded the kickback total of around 100 million yen as a suspense payment, then later divided the money into smaller amounts and booked them as expenditures such as service charges. But the tax bureau recognized the payments disguised as charges and other expenditures as concealment of income. JTC has already submitted a revised tax return and paid outstanding taxes, including the penalty.
"We are considering ways to proceed without making such payments from now on," a JTC official told The Yomiuri Shimbun, after admitting having paid kickbacks. But concerning offers of payment made by the company to officials overseas, "it's not known to whom payments were made," the official said.
]]></text></news-item>