<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-VJ21-JC6P-C208"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Mercury clean-up closes Hood</title><source>Odessa American (Texas)</source><author>Lindsay Weaver, Odessa American, Texas</author><text><![CDATA[March 20--After 70 staff and students were transported to Odessa hospitals for exposure to mercury at John B. Hood Junior High on Tuesday, the school will remain closed through Friday for comprehensive testing of the air quality, Ector County Independent School District Superintendent Tom Crowe said.
It's not only a precautionary measure from ECISD, but hails from a federal order through the Environmental Protection Agency that gives instructions on what must be done to clear out mercury within a school facility.
"The safety of students and staff has been paramount in all the decisions we've made in dealing with John B. Hood Junior High," Crowe said during a news conference at the administration building Wednesday afternoon.
He later would say the decisions that ECISD has made is not an over-reaction.
"The process for remediation... has turned out to be more complicated and more lengthy than we anticipated," he said.
No one is allowed into Hood until Monday when Crowe expects classes to resume at the campus on East 38th Street. All personal belongings of staff and students will remain inside the school until they are tested and deemed safe, Crowe said.
"We want to ensure that all the mercury is gone, but also any vapors that were left that they're gone," Crowe said.
The clean-up became necessary after a Hood administrator discovered a ninth-grade student brought a half-ounce to 1 ounce of mercury in a water bottle and spilled out the heavy metal onto a cafeteria table on Tuesday morning, Director of Communications Mike Adkins said.
It's also believed the student and 20 or so other students were exposed to the mercury earlier in the day.
The result was a contamination of the school and quarantined treatment of those exposed.
ECISD contracted with Allied International Emergency, a hazmat cleaning company with an office in Midland, which has been on site since Tuesday to begin detection and decontamination operations, according to a written statement from Allied.
On Wednesday, the crew from Allied International Emergency remained at Hood locating and removing the contamination. After the clean-up, there is an eight-hour period they must wait before testing the air quality and deciding that the building is safe to reoccupy, Adkins said.
"Clearance samples will be based on the Environmental Protection Agency and Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry deadlines for mercury spills in a school. Normal school functions will resume when all clearance samples meet with these guidelines," according to their written statement.
To some who have questioned the purported overreaction of a quarantine of students and staff, Crowe stood behind their decisions.
"When this is deemed a hazardous material, we turn it over to (experts) to make that decision," Crowe said. "Things have changed in last 30 years. Things that weren't considered hazardous then are considered hazardous today."
On Wednesday, Hood Principal Wayne Squiers alerted parents via phone messaging system that students will return to classes today and Friday though not at Hood, but at New Tech Odessa on East 29th Street. Adkins said they made accommodations for all 650 or so Hood students to attend classes and to be transported to and from Hood by ECISD buses.
If a student normally rides the bus to Hood, students are instructed to get onto the same bus which will take them to New Tech Odessa on East 29th Street and Andrews Highway. If a student walks to Hood, a bus will transport students from the campus to NTO; students are asked to be on campus by 8:15 a.m.
Parents are asked to drop off their Hood students to the eastside entrance to NTO. Sack lunches will be provided to the students as well.
Career and technical classes that usually meet at NTO will remain at Odessa or Permian high schools through Friday and NTO's special education class will instead meet at Sam Houston Elementary School, Crowe said.
Adkins said the investigation by ECISD is ongoing. The possibility of punishment for the ninth-grade student who brought mercury on campus is still up in the air, Adkins said, though Crowe did curtly comment that the school was shut down for three days and punishment may be necessary.
Crowe wasn't certain how much this process is going to cost ECISD, he said on Wednesday at the news conference.
Crowe did thank parents for their patience and cooperation on Tuesday, the Odessa police and firefighters, food services staff, transportation and the district's nurses.
"We will make sure is safe for students and staff members before we reopen," Crowe said.
Nearly 70 people in all were exposed to the mercury, with 20 of them handling the actual substance and 49 having secondary exposure to it, Odessa Public Information Coordinator Andrea Goodson said. All were transported either to Odessa Regional Medical Center or Medical Center Hospital after being quarantined based on their exposure.
Police, firefighters and other emergency personnel were on scene at Hood by 10:18 a.m. Tuesday and within a few hours hundreds of parents gathered in front of campus to retrieve their children -- and answers.
Everyone who was transported to the hospital from Hood on Tuesday morning was released by Tuesday afternoon, according to the respective hospitals.
The substance was "elemental mercury" found in older thermometers, which is not easily absorbed by skin and is only harmful if it is in a gaseous state and someone inhales it, MCH physician Dr. Gregory Shipkey, director of the emergency room, said.
Symptoms in children range from rashes, hypertension, tremors, fever, nausea and vomiting, according to the Environmental Protection Agency.
The Poison Control Center covering the West Texas region was called for advice and its recommendation to Ector County medical and emergency professionals on Tuesday morning, Salvador Baeza said, the director of the center that is based in El Paso.
The center does not conduct testing or site visits, but rather gives advice from trained toxicologists such as Baeza, he said by phone on Wednesday.
"From what we gathered and what was shared, what was done was appropriate," Baeza said about how the quarantine was handled on Tuesday.
Calls to the center about mercury are not common in the least, Baeza said. Human exposure to mercury usually occurs from breathing mercury in the air (organic mercury is the most poisonous found in fungicide and in latex paints) or from ingesting fish that contains methylmercury, according to the Environmental Protection Agency.
Most often information requests to the Poison Control Center are about ingesting household products, medications or in the spring and summer about insects and snake bites, Baeza said.
Even still, interaction with heavy metals such as mercury shouldn't go unnoticed.
"The main way (to get mercury poisoning) is inhaling it. In this case there are little liquid beads that congeal and separate and are interesting to play with. But even at room temperature it could vaporize. The warmer it gets, increases the vaporization," Baeza said. "Inhalation of the mercury is our main concern."
As for students making up the lost time away from school on Wednesday, Adkins said they will consider applying for a waiver with the state since it was an emergency situation. That too, is still up for discussion.
--Contact Lindsay Weaver on twitter at @OAschools, on Facebook at OA Lindsay Weaver or call 432-333-7781.
___ (c)2014 the Odessa American (Odessa, Texas) Visit the Odessa American (Odessa, Texas) at www.oaoa.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>