<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSR-4HM1-DYG9-510V"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>DISEASE DEPLETES BROOK TROUT AS SEASON NEARS</title><source>Herald News (Passaic County, NJ)</source><author>Scott Fallon, Staff Writer; Email: fallon@northjersey.com</author><text><![CDATA[About 114,000 brook trout will be euthanized at a state hatchery after contracting a highly contagious disease that is not harmful to humans but could decimate the state's fish population, state officials said.
The discovery of the diseased fish comes just weeks before the opening of trout season and means several lakes and rivers in North Jersey will not be stocked this spring.
Recent tests found some of the 600,000 brook trout at the Pequest Trout Hatchery in Warren County were infected with furunculosis, a fatal bacterial disease that mostly affects cold water species of fish. The disease is harmful only to fish and is not transmissible to humans or other animal species, according to the state Department of Environmental Protection.
In order to protect healthy trout already in waterways across New Jersey, several waterways will not be stocked, including the Pequannock River, Saddle River, the lower Wanaque River, Green Turtle Pond in West Milford and Barbour's Pond in Woodland Park.
"You can still fish trout in those waters, but you're going to have to try a bit harder," said Larry Ragonese, a spokesman for the state Department of Environmental Protection.
"The last thing we want to do is kill trout, but this is about the safety of the species, long term," he said. "We don't want to put them in water to infect other trout or fish."
State workers will still release almost 500,000 healthy trout in about 200 ponds and streams statewide in time for trout season's opening day on April 5.
Fishing is one of the state's biggest outdoor industries, with almost 147,000 licenses issued in 2012. Freshwater fishing generated $242 million toward the state economy in 2012, through licensing, equipment sales and money spent on food, fuel and lodging, state officials said.
Trout fishing has seen a surge in popularity over the past decade in New Jersey. The state issued 89,590 resident and 5,528 non-resident trout stamps in 2012 - a 15 percent increase among resident stamps and a doubling of non-resident stamps over the past decade.
The diseased trout are being killed by introducing carbon dioxide into the water, essentially asphyxiating the fish.
"What they're doing is prudent," said Ross Kushner head of the Pequannock River Coalition, an environmental advocacy group. "They're being careful and that is what they should be when handling something like this."
Problems at the hatchery began last fall when 25,000 trout were euthanized after contracting furunculosis, the first outbreak in the hatchery's 31 years.
State officials believe osprey feeding on infected fish in the wild may have spread the disease by eating trout in the affected pool at the hatchery.
Laboratory tests last weekend confirmed the presence of the disease among brook trout in an upper portion of the concrete raceway system used to raise the fish for stocking.
The disease affects mostly brown and brook trout, which state officials may vaccinate in future seasons.
They also plan to increase the number of rainbow trout, which appear resistant to furunculosis, and are considering acquiring brown and brook trout that have been bred for resistance to the disease.
Email: fallon@northjersey.com
]]></text></news-item>