<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSS-GSD1-JCTS-G1Y4"><date>2014-03-20</date><title></title><source>The Star-Ledger (Newark, New Jersey)</source><author>STAR-LEDGER STAFF</author><text><![CDATA[Six states join review of Comcast-TWC merger
Comcast Corp.'s proposed acquisition of Time Warner Cable is being studied by at least six states that have joined a federal review of whether the deal violates antitrust laws.
The attorneys general of Florida, Ohio, Connecticut, Pennsylvania, Indiana and Maryland are reviewing the $45.2 billion deal that was announced last month, their offices said yesterday.
The Justice Department and the Federal Communications Commission are also reviewing the takeover, which would combine the two largest U.S. cable companies. Comcast plans to divest about 3 million subscribers of the combined company to keep its market share below 30 percent.
The attorneys general enforce state antitrust laws and can put pressure on the Justice Department to seek tougher conditions if they think the government isn't being aggressive enough.
Bloomberg News
FedEx blames winter for lower profit margin
FedEx cut its 2014 profit forecast after unseasonably harsh winter weather grounded flights and slowed shipments last quarter.
The company trimmed its profit forecast for the full year to a range of $6.55 to $6.80 a share, from $6.73 to $7.10 previously. That falls short of analysts' estimates of $6.90 a share, according to data compiled by Bloomberg.
FedEx is joining companies including Urban Outfitters, McDonald's and General Mills in reporting weaker results because of inclement weather. The term "weather" was mentioned at least once in 195 earnings calls over the last quarter, according to FactSet, a financial research firm.
Snow, ice and cold canceled more than 108,600 commercial flights, halted train service and slowed truck traffic.
Bloomberg News
BMW sales bolstered by new, refreshed models
BMW forecast "significant" gains in 2014 profit as new models like the 4-Series Gran Coupe propel higher deliveries.
Pretax profit this year will beat 2013's $11 billion, lifted by 16 new and refreshed models and lower development spending, the Munich-based company said yesterday. Sales gains should be stronger in the second half, helping BMW maintain its status as the best-selling upscale car brand. The shares gained the most in more than six months.
"We're viewing the business year 2014 with confidence," chief executive officer Norbert Reithofer said yesterday at a press conference at BMW's headquarters in Munich. "We are aiming to achieve a significant rise in sales volume."
Bloomberg News
]]></text></news-item>