<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSS-17M1-JBKN-B015"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Follow the roubles; The West's sanctions</title><source>The Economist</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[How America and Europe hope to put pressure on Russia
DURING the cold war, strategists in the West worried that their societies were at a disadvantage because they were less willing to put up with the inconvenience victory might require. Russia's return to disturbingly Soviet behaviour has brought with it a revenant of the same idea: that the West is too greedy for Russian money to pass meaningful sanctions against members of Vladimir Putin's government. For evidence, see the lack of a response to the murder of Alexander Litvinenko in a London sushi restaurant and to the war in 2008 between Russia and Georgia. Targeted measures taken after the annexation of Crimea have yet to banish this suspicion.
On March 17th, arguing that the pro-Russian referendum in Crimea had no legitimacy, the American government announced sanctions against 11 prominent Russians and Ukrainians. The European Union issued its own list, which though longer—21 people—was less aggressive in going after members of the Russian government. The American list includes the deputy prime minister, Dmitry Rogozin (who as ambassador to NATO liked to give AK-47s out as gifts) as well as members of the Duma, presidential advisers and Ukraine's ex-president, Viktor Yanukovych. The European list, by contrast, consists of members of the armed forces.
Those named will be unable to travel to America or the EU, and any assets they hold in either place will be frozen. American and European firms will be banned from doing business with them. The Treasury says this will hurt even those who do not have assets in America because they will be unable to use dollars in any transactions, and because international banks are wary of attracting the attention that might come from trading with them.
The greater caution of the European list reflects the EU's internal divisions. Poland, Sweden and the Baltic states are hawkish; Greece, Cyprus and Italy lead the doves. Cyprus, still in recession after the collapse of its offshore banking system, which caters heavily to wealthy Russians, says it expects to be compensated for any further losses. For Greece, desperately seeking new growth, the prospect of economic sanctions that might keep Russian tourists away is the cause of much worry.
Targeted sanctions can be hard to enforce: in the case of Libya some transactions slipped through the net simply because there are so many ways to spell Qaddafi. More than 100 lawsuits against targeted sanctions of various sorts have been brought in the European Court of Justice over the years, which has led to a tightening of procedures. Sanctions must be subject to due process and the EU must produce evidence to back its pursuit of specific people. This makes the commander of the Black Sea Fleet easier to target than a presidential adviser who may have much more influence, and more to lose, but whose links to Crimea are not so obvious.
Both the American and European governments say that their measures are just a start and can be extended, depending on what Russia does next. Even if the lists are lengthened to include the families of the main targets, the sanctions will fall far short of the chokehold on Iran's economy. Those sanctions were comparatively easy to put in place because the country was already cut off from the world economy. This is not the case for Russia. "Tough sanctions would mean saying to BP, Exxon, Chevron, Shell, Boeing and Siemens that they can't do business in Russia," says Fiona Hill of the Brookings Institution, a think-tank. This would not only damage Western companies, but also Western governments, Ms Hill says, which could expect embarrassing videos squirrelled away by Russian spies to start appearing on the internet.
Even so, at their summit which begins on March 20th, after The Economist went to press, European leaders were sure to feel pressure to come up with something stronger. One obvious possibility would be for France to suspend its delivery of two Mistral-class amphibious assault ships to Russia. The contract was controversial even in better times, and has since become an embarrassment. Britain's decision to suspend military sales and co-operation with Russia may be an attempt to nudge France towards this. Laurent Fabius, France's foreign minister, has said action on the ships would need to be matched by other countries: "I'm thinking of the British in particular to do something equivalent with the assets of the Russian oligarchs in London" (see next page).
For the moment, Western governments are unwilling to sacrifice much for Ukraine. Isolating Russia would do real harm to the world economy; registering a protest over Crimea does not yet seem worth that pain in Washington, Brussels or Berlin (see next page). Nor is there any certainty that tougher measures would change what Russia does next.
]]></text></news-item>