<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSS-BTR1-JBV1-X1K4"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>AFPTV-ADVISORY 2200GMT</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[LONDON, March 20, 2014 (AFP) - We will file the following videos:
-- TOP WORLD NEWS --
+ MALAYSIA AIRLINES SEARCH
Filed over last 12 hours:
KUALA LUMPUR: Malaysia says that two objects spotted by a satellite in the Indian Ocean are a "credible lead" in the search the missing jet. RAW. VID608777_EN
CANBERRA: Images from the Australian rescue centre coordinating the search for the plane. RAW. VID608672_EN
+ CRIMEA CRISIS
Coming up:
SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: Rolling news coverage of developments in Crimea as Russian-backed troops retain control of the Ukrainian naval headquarters. RAW. TBA
Filed over past 12 hours:
WASHINGTON: US President Barack Obama announces new sanctions on more Russian officials, threatens to directly target the Russian economy over Moscow's absorption of Crimea. RAW. VID608796_EN
BRUSSELS: EU leaders arrive for summit. RAW. VID608816_EN
- French President Francois Hollande says Europe's leaders will cancel a June summit with Russia and decide fresh sanctions against Russian figures. RAW. VID608839_EN
-German Chancellor Angela Merkel says EU leaders will discuss extending sanctions and visa bans to Russians over Crimea. RAW. VID608835_EN
-French president Francois Hollande meets German leader Angela Merkel. RAW. VID608909_EN
- British PM David Cameron says EU "must sign a new agreement" with Ukraine. RAW. VID608816_EN
- Luxembourg PM says OECD team should be sent to Ukraine. RAW. VID608887_EN
- Bilateral meeting between Chancellor Merkel and President Hollande. RAW. VID608909_EN
SEVASTOPOL, CRIMEA: Ukraine's defence ministry says about 20 gunmen have seized a Ukrainian warship in Crimea. STOCKSHOTS. VID606073_EN
MOSCOW: UN chief Ban Ki-moon meets with President Vladimir Putin. RAW. VID608872_EN
MOSCOW: Russia's lower house of parliament ratifies the treaty incorporating Crimea into Russian territory. RAW. VID608833_EN
SEVASTOPOL, CRIMEA: Russian flag flies over Bakhchisaray military base while Belbek remains under Ukrainian control. RAW. VID608885_EN
KIEV: US under-secretary for political affairs says US gives Ukraine its full support. RAW. VID608829_EN / VID608863_EN
SEVASTAPOL: Ukraine's defence ministry says around 20 gunmen seize a Ukrainian warship, the Ternopil, in the port of Sevastopol in Crimea. FILE. VID606073_EN
KIEV: Ukrainian parliament meets over Crimea, declares they will "never cease to fight to liberation of Crimea". RAW. VID608745_EN
SAINT-NAZAIRE, FRANCE: France resists pressure to suspend the controversial sale of two Mistral warships to Russia over the Crimea crisis, saying it will not make any decision before October. FILE. VID561280_EN
PEREVALNE, CRIMEA: Ukrainian soldiers are still in control of the military site in Perevalne but Russian soldiers surround the base in Crimea. RAW. VID608706_EN
SEVASTOPOL: Ukrainian servicemen leave navy headquarters after the base was seized by pro-Russia militants. RAW. VID608665_EN
KHARTSYZK, UKRAINE: The Donbas region is Ukraine's industrial heartland, but since the collapse of the Soviet Union the coal mining industry has fallen on hard times and dangerous illegal mines have sprung up to replace closing state pits. Many miners are in favour of joining Russia, believing a return to the fold could help them earn a decent and honest living. PKG. NSV - VID608802_EN/ VOICED - VID608803_EN
-- OTHER WORLD NEWS --
+ AFRICA
Coming up:
BANGUI: UN High Commissioner for Human Rights Navi Pillay holds a news conference at the end of a fact-finding mission to the Central African Republic. RAW. TBA
Filed over past 12 hours:
BANGUI: Head of the World Food Programme tells the world not to forget about the conflict in the Central African Republic, warns of malnutrition if food shortages are not addressed. RAW.
VID608685_EN
JUBA: The trial of seven former South Sudanese officials and politicians in connection with what the government describes as a 'coup attempt' resumes, despite the absence of the defendants now in Kenya. RAW. VID608931_EN
JUBA: The South Sudanese army says it's recaptured Malakal town, the capital of oil-rich Upper Nile state. RAW. VID608915_EN
JOHANNESBURG: South Africa's ruling ANC says controversial upgrades at President Zuma's residence were not for private dwellings, and says anyone involved in corruption should be prosecuted. RAW. VID608762_EN
PRETORIA: Oscar Pistorius will sell his upmarket Pretoria house where he shot dead his girlfriend Reeva Steenkamp last year in order to cover the legal fees for his murder trial. FILE. VID491274_EN
ABIDJAN: Ivory Coast says it will transfer Charles Ble Goude, the jailed right-hand man of former president Laurent Gbagbo, to the International Criminal Court. FILE. VID482
KAPIRI MPOSHI, ZAMBIA: A gay couple in Zambia begin their defence in their trial for sodomy. James Mwape and Philip Mubiana face 14 years in prison after being reported to the police by one of the men's relatives. FILE. VID605659_EN
KANO: South African retailer Shoprite opens its first outlet in northern Nigeria, as part of an aggressive expansion drive and defying wider concerns about security in the region. RAW. VID608987_EN
Still available:
NKANDLA, SOUTH AFRICA: As South Africa prepares to vote in May election, scandal rages around President Jacob Zuma's residence, threatening his support in the crucial polls. PKG. NSV - VID592252_EN / VOICED - VID592253_EN
+ LATIN AMERICA & CARIBBEAN
Coming up:
CARACAS: Protest following the arrest of two opposition mayors including one in the town of San Cristobal where the anti-govt protests started. RAW 2300 GMT
Filed over past 12 hours:
MONTEVIDEO: Uruguay said it had agreed to receive five prisoners of as yet undisclosed nationalities from the US war on terror prison camp in Guantanamo Bay. STOCKSHOTS of Montevideo VID577867_EN
HAVANA: The FARC guerrilla group condemns Colombian President Juan Manuel Santos' dismissal of Bogota's elected mayor, warning it undermined confidence in peace talks underway in Havana. RAW. VID608927_EN
+ NORTH AMERICA
Coming up:
WASHINGTON: US Secretary of State John Kerry meets with Slovak Deputy Prime Minister and Foreign Minister Miroslav Lajcak. On merit. TBC
+ MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
NETANYA, ISRAEL: Paul Bismuth, whose identity was usurped to open a second phone line for France's ex-president Nicolas Sarkozy to talk secretly with is lawyer, declares he wants his identity back. RAW. VID608774_EN / PHOTOS. VID608708_EN
WADI KHALED, LEBANON: Civilians and rebel fighters fleeing for Lebanon came under fire by the Syrian army as they crossed the river dividing the two countries RAW. VID608828_EN
CRAC DE CHEVALIERS, SYRIA: 11 rebels are killed fleeing 12th-century citadel of Crac des Chevaliers, a UNESCO heritage site. RAW. VID608766_EN / FILE. VID608701_EN
+ EUROPE
Filed over past 12 hours:
BRUSSEL: Diplomatic sources say all EU nations agree to combat tax evasion, during EU Summit talks in Brussels. STOCK SHOTS. VID432785_EN
OFF THE ITALIAN COAST: Italian navy rescues 1,000 migrants from the seas off Italy in the space of 24 hours. RAW. VID608662_EN
MADRID: Amnesty activists protest against EU's immigration policies which they say force migrants to take dangerous routes to reach the bloc. RAW. VID608726_EN
LISSE, NETHERLANDS: Keukenhof, the world's largest bulb garden opens for its 2014 exhibition. RAW. VID606212_EN
PARIS: French Prime Minister Jean-Marc Ayrault and Argentinian President Cristina Kirchner open the Paris Book Fair, at which Argentina is the guest of honour. RAW. VID608919_EN
PARIS: French 'Spiderman' Alain Robert climbs the 186-metre tall Total tower in La Defense. RAW VID608912_EN / VID608755_EN
NICE: A Rembrandt painting stolen from a French museum in 1999 and worth millions has been recovered in the southern city of Nice. RAW. VID608961_EN
+ ASIA-PACIFIC
Coming up:
BEIJING: Michelle Obama and her daughters visit China. RAW. TBC
Filed over past 12 hours:
MUMBAI, INDIA: An Indian court convicts four men over the gang-rape of a photographer last year. RAW. VID608695_EN
JALALABAD, AFGHANISTAN: Multiple suicide attack in east Afghan city kills at least 10 police. RAW. VID608782_EN
HONG KONG: The lawyer of Chinese human rights activist Cao Shunli, who died last Friday, calls for independent investigation into the death. RAW. VID608670_EN
-- SPORT --
Filed over past 12 hours:
VARIOUS BRITAIN: Having arrived at Arsenal Football Club in 1996, the club's manager Arsene Wenger will oversee his 1000th game on Saturday eighteen years later, as the Gunners take on Chelsea. FILE. VID608952_EN
-- FEATURES --
Filed:
WASHINGTON: Long a poor relation to West Coast cities like San Francisco and Los Angeles when it came to tech startups, Washington, DC is now attracting many of its own, drawing them in with readily-available talent and close links to government. PKG. NSV - VID607755_EN
/ VOICED - VID607756_EN
Contact:
London desk: +44 207 776 2768
Hong Kong desk: +852 2829 6216
Nicosia desk: +357 22 391 453
Washington desk: +1 202 414 0550
Montevideo desk: +598 2 900 5095 ext 257
For contact via email: afptv-en@afp.com
]]></text></news-item>