<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSS-GWN1-DXJR-H0DV"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>CBI to register PE in Rolls Royce case</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NEW DELHI: After receiving all the relevant documents from ministry of defence, the CBI has decided to register a preliminary enquiry in the Rs 10,000 crore scam involving Hindustan Aeronautics Limited and Rolls Royce for supply of aircraft engines.
It had received a complaint from the defence ministry earlier this month as it has been asked to look into the case. Defence Minister A K Antony had ordered a CBI probe into the allegations.
“We will co-operate fully with the regulatory authorities and have repeatedly made clear that we will not tolerate misconduct of any sort,” a Rolls-Royce spokesman had said.
Sources said the role of a London-based arms dealer Sudhir Choudhary, who had been probed by the agency in different cases, is also under scanner and if evidence of his role emerges, he might be made an accused in the case. Sources said the arms dealer, who is already in the list of ‘undesirable contacts’ issued by the agency to government officials, has been probed in the past but since no evidence had emerged the cases were closed.
The scandal relates to deal in the supply of engines for Hawk trainer and Jaguar fighter aircraft between 2007 and 2011 and an internal probe by the vigilance wing of HAL has prima facie established the charges, the sources said. The allegations surfaced after HAL received a letter claiming that bribes were paid to officials in the company and other departments to bag the contract.
Initial investigations by the CVO have found that the company allegedly violated several contractual obligations with HAL between 2007-11, when these bribes were allegedly paid. The company has supplied engines for the aircraft being manufactured by the HAL for the Indian Air Force.
The issue came to light after HAL issued guidelines to its vendors and suppliers to ensure probity in its transactions as part of its integrity pact signed with them. Rolls Royce, in a letter written to HAL in December last, had said it had employed a Singapore-based person identified as Ashok Patni and his firm Aashmore Private Limited as “commercial advisor” in India, providing sales and logistical support, local business support and “strategic advice.”
The firm also told HAL that it had severed ties with Aashmore and its owner in 2013. The commissions paid by the firm are in violation of the procurement rules in India which prohibits hiring of middlemen or commission agents while transacting deals with the defence ministry.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>