<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSS-DT91-DY7P-T0N2"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>New emails link state officials to Duke Energy</title><source>Old Gold and Black: Wake Forest University</source><author>Rachel Wallen</author><text><![CDATA[In the midst of investigations of the recent coal ash spill in the Dan river, emails have come to light that demonstrate coordination between Duke Energy and North Carolina state environmental officials.
Discussions with the energy firm over pollution began last year, when the Southern Environmental Law Center filed in its intent to sue Duke Energy for violations of the Clean Water Act in January of 2013.
As a result, the North Carolina Department of Environment and Natural Resources worked privately with Duke Energy lobbyists to reach a settlement and excluded citizen activist groups from participating in the deal, according to the emails discovered.
The proposed agreement was labeled a "sweetheart deal" by environmentalists, as it charged the company $99,111 for violations but included no requirements that it stop the pollution that was occurring.
After the spill began on Feb. 2, regulators faced harsh criticism from state environmental groups and quickly put the proposed deal on hold.
Environmentalists have long been suspicious of the level of cooperation between energy firms and the state, particularly since Gov. Pat McCrory worked for Duke Energy for over 28 years before beginning his run for governor.
Since the spill, officials from Gov. McCrory to Senate Leader Phil Berger have called for Duke to thoroughly clean up the spill and face severe ramifications for the damage.
Many environmental activists hope that an investigation on such a large scale will cause Duke Energy to make the chances necessary to clean up the pollution they have caused and prevent it from happening again.
"Duke Energy has been getting away with this pollution for too long," said senior Halston Kirkpatrick.
"There need to be enough consequences for this that they actually start complying with regulations."
Sophomore Bella Velasco agreed. "The pipeline break wasn't something they could necessarily have foreseen," she said.
"But I think [Duke Energy] should use the full extent of their resources to fix the problem they created to ensure that no one else is adversely affected by the spill," Velasco said.
Criminal investigations began soon after the spill. Since then, prosecutors have issued at least 23 subpoenas to various Duke Energy and state officials, seeking emails and reports related to the many spills that have occurred throughout Duke's 14 power plants in the state.
A grand jury has been formed to determine whether there was criminal activity involved in the spill.
They will hear evidence and decide future consequences for Duke Energy.
Presentations of the evidence commenced on March 18 at 9 a.m. and are set to run through at least Thursday, March 20.
]]></text></news-item>