<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSS-9PV1-JBF5-T371"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Appointment of New Chief Executive Officer and Chairman Of the Board of Directors</title><source>Market News Publishing</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[HUNTER BAY MINERALS PLC ("HBY-V;HTBNF-0") - Appointment of New Chief Executive Officer and Chairman - Of the Board of Directors
Hunter Bay Minerals plc ("Hunter Bay") announces Nico Civelli has resigned as Chief Executive Officer of Hunter Bay, effective immediately. To replace Mr. Civelli, the board of directors appointed Keith Minty as Chief Executive Officer. Mr. Civelli will remain as a director and Vice-President, Finance of Hunter Bay.
Hunter Bay also announces that Christopher Wilson will be stepping down as a director and Chairman of the board of directors once Hunter Bay files its audited financial statements for the fiscal year ended December 31, 2013. To replace Dr. Wilson, Hunter Bay's board of directors have approved the appointment of Matt Sutcliffe as a director and non-executive Chairman of the board of directors.
Hunter Bay wishes to thank Dr. Wilson for serving as Chairman and as a director of Hunter Bay including the facilitating of Hunter Bay's initial public offering and being responsible for acquiring Hunter Bay's Sela Creek Project.
Keith Minty. Mr. Minty has served as a member of Hunter Bay's board of directors since April 2012. Mr. Minty obtained a B.Sc. in Mining Engineering from Queen's University, Kingston Ontario, Canada in 1978. He has over 25 years of open pit and underground mine operational and project development experience in North America, Central America and in Africa. From 2008 to 2013, Mr. Minty was the Chief Operating Officer at Thani Dubai Mining Limited (Thani) where he was responsible for all project exploration and operation activities in Yemen and Egypt as well as new business development activities. Prior to joining Thani, he was the South African country manager for Hunter Dickinson Inc. Currently Mr. Minty is founding partner and Senior Vice President of Stope Capital Advisors Inc., a financial advisory firm that provides technical, commercial and financial advisory and capital sourcing services to the mineral resource industry and select other sectors. Mr. Minty has also served on the board of directors of Asanko Gold Inc. and Oremex Silver Inc.
Matt Sutcliffe. Mr. Sutcliffe holds a PhD in Mining Engineering at the University of Nottingham. In 1990, Mr. Sutcliffe worked in production management at an underground nickel mine in Northern Canada. He then moved into Investment Banking working in the City of London as a mining analyst and corporate financier focusing in the resource sector. During this time, Mr. Sutcliffe was a mining analyst at T Hoare &Co, head of mining at Williams de Broe and a director of corporate finance at Evolution Beeson Gregory (which is now part of Investec Bank). At Evolution Beeson Gregory, Mr. Sutcliffe advised a large number of public natural resources companies, as well as arranging a number of stock exchange listings for junior and mid-tier mining and oil and gas companies on the LSE- AIM market. Mr. Sutcliffe is currently Chairman and founder of Alexander Mining plc and a founding director of two private companies; Environmetals Ltd (NZ) and Global Oil Shales (Jersey) Ltd. Mr. Sutcliffe has previously served as chairman and/or director of junior listed mining and oil companies on AIM, TSX Venture and ASX.
About Hunter Bay
Hunter Bay is engaged in the acquisition, exploration and development of mineral resource properties located in South America and Canada. Hunter Bay's lead project is the Sela Creek Project, located in Suriname, in which Hunter Bay has an option to acquire up to an eighty percent (80%) interest. Hunter Bay also owns a one-hundred percent (100%) interest in the Great Bear Lake Properties located in the eastern side of Great Bear Lake, NWT, Canada.
NEITHER TSX VENTURE EXCHANGE NOR ITS REGULATION SERVICES PROVIDER (AS THAT TERM IS DEFINED IN THE POLICIES OF THE TSX VENTURE EXCHANGE) ACCEPTS RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ADEQUACY OR ACCURACY OF THIS RELEASE. TSX Venture closing price for HBY-V Date: 2014/03/10 Closing Price: 0.01
____________________________________________________________
(c)2014 Market News Publishing Inc. All rights reserved. Toronto:(416)366-8881 Vancouver:(604)689-1101 Fax:(604)689-1106
]]></text></news-item>