<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSS-DXK1-JCDS-Y2YD"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Latin America's continued prominent role in narcotics trade</title><source>Country Report Select</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A recent report by the US State Department found that 17 out of the 22 major identified drug-transit locations (countries that are either a significant direct source of illicit narcotic drugs that affect the US, or through which such drugs and illegal substances are transported) are located in Latin America and the Caribbean. The region plays a similarly prominent role as a major source of precursor, or essential chemicals, for the manufacture of illegal narcotics and as a destination for related money-laundering. Despite efforts put in place in most countries in the region to curb the illegal narcotics trade, it is likely to remain prevalent in the medium term, given its huge profitability and the continued institutional weaknesses in these countries.
The 2014 International Narcotics Control Strategy Report (INCSR), released on February 28th, analyses developments regarding the illegal drugs trade and related financial crimes during 2013, in particular whether countries are meeting the goals and objectives of the 1988 UN Drug Convention and other international treaties designed to combat these problems.
The INCSR points out that the illegal narcotics trade is significant in Bahamas, Belize, Bolivia, Colombia, Costa Rica, Dominican Republic, Ecuador, El Salvador, Guatemala, Haiti, Honduras, Jamaica, Mexico, Nicaragua, Panama, Peru and Venezuela-all considered major drug-transit locations. Inclusion on this list, however, does not reflect the level of commitment of governments to follow counter-narcotics operations, nor their degree of co-operation with US efforts. Rather, it results from a combination of geographic, commercial, and economic factors. Indeed, of these 17 countries, the INCSR includes only Bolivia and Venezuela as having failed to implement measures to combat the problem; the only other country in this category is Myanmar.
The report includes estimates of illegal crops and potential drug production based on satellite imagery and studies of crop yields. Its figures show that, while coca crops in 2012 were most extensive in Colombia, with 78,000 ha (followed by Peru, with 50,500 ha, and Bolivia, with 25,000 ha), Peru was the number-one producer of coca leaf in that same year, with 58,500 metric tons (mt), followed by Colombia (48,000 mt) and Bolivia (25,500 mt). Peru was also the main source of potential pure cocaine, with output of 290 mt, followed by Colombia (175 mt), and Bolivia (155 mt). The report contains no figures for 2013, except for potential pure cocaine production in Peru, which increased slightly, to 305 mt.
The Andean region has long been the main producer of cocaine worldwide, but, over the past few years, Mexico has become the third-largest producer of opium poppy-the main ingredient in heroin-after Afghanistan and Myanmar. In 2012 Mexico produced an estimated 219 mt of poppy, a slight decline from the 250 recorded in 2011 (compared to Myanmar's estimated 450 mt and Afghanistan's 4,400 mt the same year). In terms of surface area, Mexico is estimated to have had 10,500 ha of poppy crops in 2012, down from 12,000 ha in 2011 (one-third of Myanmar's 36,500 ha and a fraction of the 115,000 ha estimated to have been planted in Afghanistan in the same year). Mexico is also a major producer of cannabis worldwide, with crops covering an estimated 11,500 ha in 2012, down from 12,000 in 2011. However, the INCSR's volume figures for Mexico are only available until 2008 (estimated to have reached 21,500 mt) due to a lack of reliable crop-yield data.
The report also identifies countries considered to be major sources of precursor for the manufacture of illegal narcotics, both those derived from plants-such as cocaine and heroin-and synthetic drugs such as methamphetamine and 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA, popularly known as "ecstasy"). Although the geographical spread of this set of countries is much wider, Latin American locations also feature prominently. Out of a total of 33 countries, 10 are located within the region: Argentina, Bolivia, Chile, Colombia, Costa Rica, Dominican Republic, El Salvador, Guatemala, Honduras and Mexico.
Importantly, unlike illegal narcotics, chemicals used in their manufacture may have a legitimate and often widespread use within some countries, which makes their control much more difficult. Law-enforcement agencies, which are often ineffective and plagued by corrupt practices, have to prove that chemicals are intended for illicit drug production, making this a particularly challenging issue in the region. The INCSR highlights that criminal organisations in 2013 increasingly resorted to chemicals not listed under the relevant UN conventions. Similarly, drug-traffickers are increasingly seeking to manufacture chemicals in locations where illegal narcotics are also manufactured, in order to avoid international monitoring efforts.
The INCSR notes that, as Mexico has stepped up its interdiction and enforcement efforts, criminals have sought to procure precursors and move production to other areas with little experience in chemical control, such as Central America. Trafficking of ephedrine-one of the main precursors of methamphetamine-increased notably in both Mexico and Central America during 2013, while manufacture of methamphetamine and other synthetic drugs also grew significantly in Guatemala and Honduras. Argentina, Brazil and Chile also featured prominently as producers or importers of essential chemicals for the manufacture of illegal narcotics, as well as Canada and the US itself.
The trends recorded by the INCSR during 2013 confirm the prevalence of the so-called "balloon effect", where reducing the drug trade in one area leads to increased activity elsewhere. In particular, the report highlights concerns over a dramatic increase in US-bound drug-transit through the Caribbean, despite significant efforts by countries such as the Dominican Republic and assistance from US and multilateral agencies. Similarly, the deterioration of the situation in Central America, through which 90% of illegal narcotics from South America pass on their way to the US, is a particular cause for concern.
The report emphasises that international co-operation is central to achieving significant results against the illegal narcotics trade and related criminal activities. Importantly, it points out that the US agrees with other parties that new approaches need to be addressed, which are likely to take centre-stage in the UN General Assembly Special Session on Drugs in 2016. Ahead of this debate, the INCSR highlights that, in order to tackle successfully the illegal narcotics problem, law enforcement is insufficient, and admits that much remains to be done to reduce demand. Indeed, although the US has seen overall drug use fall by nearly one-third over the past 30 years-cocaine use has declined by around 40% since 2008-with almost 15% of its population over 12 years of age using drugs, according to the UN World Drug Report 2013, it remains one of the main markets for illegal narcotics.
After decades of limited success in curbing the production and trafficking of drugs, this debate is long overdue. Nevertheless, as long as the trade retains its enormous profitability, institutional weaknesses remain unsolved across Latin America-particularly within the law-enforcement and justice procurement spheres-and sections of the population continue to lack opportunities to access legal employment, it will be difficult to undermine the corruptive power of the illegal narcotics trade, which has repeatedly demonstrated its ability to adapt to changing circumstances.
]]></text></news-item>