<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSS-5621-F03R-N4GV"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>American taxpayers funding Russian companies, conservative group says</title><source>United Liberty</source><author>jpye</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 20, 2014 (United Liberty:http://www.unitedliberty.org Delivered by Newstex) The Club for Growth has waded into foreign policy, an unusual area for an organization that exclusively emphasizes free market policies, by urging on the U.S. Chamber of Commerce to join its call for an end to taxpayer-subsidized loans to Russian companies, amid escalating tensions between the United States and Russia[1]. In a statement on Wednesday, the Club for Growth[2] pointed to a January 2013 story from Reuters[3] on discussions between the Export-Import Bank and Gennady Timchenko, a Russian billionaire, for 'U.S. government-backed funding to buy luxury aircraft.' Timchenko was described as 'a long-time associate of Russian President Vladimir Putin.'
Another story highlighted in the statement was an August 2000 report from the Center for Public Integrity[4] which noted that the Export-Import Bank had 'guaranteed $489 million in credits to a Russian oil company whose roots are imbedded in a legacy of KGB and Communist Party corruption, as well as drug trafficking and organized crime funds 'We don't think that the Export-Import Bank should exist at all, let alone even consider giving loans and loan guarantees to Russian oligarchs and companies with ties to the Russian mob,' said Club for Growth President Chris Chocola[5]. The Club for Growth, which has long opposed the Export-Import Bank, issued key vote alert in 2012 against its reauthorization[6], noting that its 'actions are nothing more than market-distorting subsidies that pick winners and losers in the private sector.' The organization also highlighted some of the bank's shady beneficiaries[7]. Just last year, the Club for Growth backed legislation[8] introduced by Sen. Mike Lee (R-UT) and Rep. Justin Amash (R-MI) to repeal the Export-Import Bank. 'We have no idea what happened with the Export-Import Bank's discussions with Timchenko, ' said Chocola, 'but there's certainly no reason now why U.S. taxpayers should be footing the bill for subsidies to one of Vladimir Putin's biggest allies.' 'We hope the Chamber of Commerce will join us in asking the Export-Import Bank to immediately cease doing business with all Russian companies, and finally acknowledge that an agency that has given subsidies to everything from Enron to Mexican Drug Cartels to a company with ties to Russian organized crime should be completely eliminated,' he added. The U.S. Chamber of Commerce supported reauthorization of the Export-Import Bank[9] in 2012, claiming that it boosts American businesses and the fees it generates would reduce the federal budget deficit. [1]: http://www.unitedliberty.org/articles/17022-crimea-crisis-not-worth-taking-foreign-policy-risks [2]: http://www.clubforgrowth.org [3]: http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/07/31/us-timchenko-loans-idUSBRE96U0R720130731 [4]: http://www.publicintegrity.org/2000/08/02/3279/cheney-led-halliburton-feast-federal-trough [5]: http://www.clubforgrowth.org/news/?subsec=7id=1282 [6]: http://www.clubforgrowth.org/projects/?subsec=35chamber=houseyear=2012alert=15742 [7]: http://www.clubforgrowth.org/perm/?postID=15854 [8]: http://www.unitedliberty.org/articles/13949-mike-lee-justin-amash-introduce-legislation-to-repeal-export-import-bank [9]: https://www.uschamber.com/letter/letter-supporting-hr-2072-%E2%80%9Cexport-import-bank-reauthorization-act-2012%E2%80%9D

]]></text></news-item>