<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSS-2TH1-DXX7-H4VF"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Financial Results For The Year Ended December 31, 2013</title><source>Market News Publishing</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[SPY INC ("XSPY-L") - Financial Results For The Year Ended December 31, 2013
SPY Inc. announced financial results for the three months and year ended December 31, 2013.
Annual sales of our SPY(r) brand products were $37.7 million in 2013, an increase of 8% or $2.6 million, compared to $35.1 million in 2012. SPY(r) brand annual sales included slightly higher closeout sales of $2.8 million in 2013, compared to $2.6 million in 2012. Sales from our discontinued licensed brand products, which are no longer a focus of the Company, were less than $0.1 million in 2013, compared $0.5 million in 2012. Total Company net sales increased by 6% or $2.2 million, to $37.8 million for the year ended December 31, 2013, compared to $35.6 million for the year ended December 31, 2012, primarily as a result of increased sales of our snow goggle and optical products.
Fourth quarter sales of our SPY(r) brand products were $8.6 million in 2013, an increase of 7% or $0.5 million over the fourth quarter of 2012. The fourth quarter SPY(r) brand sales included higher closeout sales of $0.7 million in the fourth quarter of 2013 compared to $0.6 million in the fourth quarter of 2012, or a $0.1 million increase. Total Company net sales increased by 6% or $0.5 million, to $8.6 million in the fourth quarter of 2013, compared to $8.1 million in the fourth quarter of 2012, primarily as a result of higher sales of our snow goggle and optical products.
"With continued strong SPY(r) brand sales and an annual SPY(r) brand growth of 8% for 2013 over 2012, we are happy to once again generate annual growth and achieve our 11th quarter in a row of year over year growth of our SPY(r) brand products. What is also noteworthy is we had income from operations of $0.4 million during 2013 compared to an operating loss of $5.0 million in 2012," said Michael Marckx, President and CEO. "We not only managed to significantly reduce our operating expenses for 2013, but also increased our margin to 50% in 2013 from 46% in 2012, which is a dramatic positive shift for us. This directly reflects the strong demand for our product offering as well as the operational and manufacturing efficiencies that we have achieved over the past year. I'd like to mention that this is a definitive culmination of SPY's efforts to reduce costs, which has helped solidify our operating cost structure. Achieving operating profit along with our expanding portfolio of products, including our successful Happy Lens(TM) Collection, positions us well for 2014 as we continue to focus on disruptive strategies, driving sales, improving our product margins and managing our operating costs."
During 2013 the Company had income from operations of $0.4 million compared to a loss from operations of $5.0 million in 2012 or an improvement of $5.4 million. Our loss from operations was $0.4 million in the fourth quarter of 2013 compared to $0.6 million in the fourth quarter of 2012, or an improvement of $0.2 million.
We incurred an annual net loss of $2.9 million in 2013 compared to a net loss of $7.2 million in 2012. We incurred a net loss of $1.3 million in the fourth quarter of 2013 compared to a net loss of $1.2 million in the fourth quarter of 2012. The primary difference between the net loss and income and loss from operations was due to interest expense on our long-term debt.
SPY Inc. invites you to join the investor conference call on Thursday, March 20, 2014, at 1:30 p.m. PDT. The dial-in number for the call in North America is 1-866-515-2911 and 1-617-399-5125 for international callers. The participant pass code is 18230516. The call will also be webcast live on the internet and can be accessed by logging on at investor.spyoptic.com.
The results of our operations for the years ended December 31, 2013 and 2012 are more fully discussed in our Form 10-K for the year ended December 31, 2013, filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission on March 20, 2014.
SPY Inc.:
We have a happy disrespect for the usual way of looking (at life) and the need to SEE HAPPY. It is this mindset that drives us to design, market, and distribute premium products for people who "live" to be outdoors, pushing the boundaries in action sports, motorsports, snow sports, cycling and multi-sports. We actively support the lifestyle subcultures that surround these pursuits, and as a result our products serve the broader fashion, music and entertainment markets of the youth culture. Our reason for being is to create the unusual and this is what helps us deliver distinctive products to people who are active, fun and a bit irreverent, like us. Our principal products -- sunglasses, goggles and prescription frames -- are marketed with fun and creativity under the SPY(r) brand. More information about SPY may be obtained from: www.spyoptic.com, www.facebook.com/spyoptic, Twitter @spyoptic and Instagram @spyoptic.
Safe Harbor Statement:
This press release contains forward-looking statements. These statements relate to future events or future financial performance and are subject to risks and uncertainties. In some cases, you can identify forward-looking statements by terminology such as "may," "will," "should," "expect," "plan," "anticipate," "believe," "feel," "estimate," "predict," "hope," the negative of such terms, expressions of optimism or other comparable terminology. These statements are only predictions. Actual events or results may differ materially. Factors that could cause actual results to differ from those contained in our forward-looking statements include, but are not limited to lack of continuity and effectiveness of our management team, our ability to generate sufficient incremental sales of our core SPY(r) brand and new products to recoup our significant investments in sales and marketing, our ability to lower our expenses or otherwise reduce our breakeven point on an operating basis, our ability to maintain or increase the availability of our existing credit facilities and otherwise finance our strategic objectives, and the other risks identified from time to time in our filings made with the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission. Although we believe that the expectations reflected in our forward-looking statements are reasonable, we cannot guarantee future results. Moreover, except as required by law, we assume no responsibility for the accuracy or completeness of such forward-looking statements and undertake no obligation to update any of these forward-looking statements. //st SPY INC. AND SUBSIDIARIES CONSOLIDATED BALANCE SHEETS (Thousands, except number of shares and per share amounts)
December 31,
----------------------
2013 2012
---------- ----------
Assets Current assets Cash $ 686 $ 818 Accounts receivable, net 6,543 5,611 Inventories, net 5,872 6,274 Prepaid expenses and other current assets 680 770 Income taxes receivable 3 16
---------- ----------
Total current assets 13,784 13,489 Property and equipment, net 438 446 Intangible assets, net of accumulated amortization of $782 and $727 at December 31, 2013 and 2012, respectively 72 127 Other long-term assets 63 85
---------- ----------
Total assets $ 14,357 $ 14,147
========== ==========
Liabilities and Stockholders' Deficit Current liabilities Lines of credit $ 4,024 $ 4,591 Current portion of capital leases 77 49 Current portion of notes payable 16 15 Accounts payable 1,302 1,459 Accrued expenses and other liabilities 3,069 2,604 Income taxes payable -- --
---------- ----------
Total current liabilities 8,488 8,718 Capital leases, less current portion 92 102 Notes payable, less current portion 16 32 Notes payable to stockholders 21,452 19,078
---------- ----------
Total liabilities 30,048 27,930 Stockholders' deficit Preferred stock: par value $0.0001; 5,000,000
authorized; none issued -- -- Common stock: par value $0.0001; 100,000,000
shares authorized; 13,184,876 and 13,098,374
shares issued and outstanding at December 31,
2013 and 2012, respectively 1 1 Additional paid-in capital 45,331 44,403 Accumulated other comprehensive income 520 494 Accumulated deficit (61,543) (58,681)
---------- ----------
Total stockholders' deficit (15,691) (13,783)
---------- ----------
Total liabilities and stockholders' deficit $ 14,357 $ 14,147
========== ========== SPY INC. AND SUBSIDIARIES CONSOLIDATED STATEMENTS OF COMPREHENSIVE LOSS (Thousands, except per share amounts)
Three Months Ended Year Ended
December 31, December 31,
------------------ ------------------
2013 2012 2013 2012
-------- -------- -------- --------
(Unaudited) Net sales $ 8,627 $ 8,112 $ 37,782 $ 35,609 Cost of sales 4,571 4,545 18,921 19,189
-------- -------- -------- -------- Gross profit 4,056 3,567 18,861 16,420 Operating expenses: Sales and marketing 2,547 2,552 11,314 13,814 General and administrative 1,607 1,211 6,112 6,285 Shipping and warehousing 155 159 534 767 Research and development 158 222 502 587 Other operating expense - - - -
-------- -------- -------- --------
Total operating expenses 4,467 4,144 18,462 21,453
-------- -------- -------- -------- Loss from operations (411) (577) 399 (5,033) Other income (expense): Interest expense (737) (712) (2,966) (2,388) Foreign currency transaction gain
(loss) (116) 57 (290) 137 Other (expense) income (2) 21 (5) 50
-------- -------- -------- --------
Total other expense (855) (634) (3,261) (2,201)
-------- -------- -------- -------- Loss before provision for income
taxes (1,265) (1,211) (2,862) (7,234) Income tax provision - 8 - 8
-------- -------- -------- -------- Net loss $ (1,265) $ (1,219) $ (2,862) $ (7,242)
======== ======== ======== ======== Net loss per share of Common Stock
Basic $ (0.10) $ (0.09) $ (0.22) $ (0.56)
======== ======== ======== ========
Diluted $ (0.10) $ (0.09) $ (0.22) $ (0.56)
======== ======== ======== ======== Shares used in computing net loss per share of Common Stock
Basic 13,185 13,544 13,155 13,047
======== ======== ======== ========
Diluted 13,185 13,544 13,155 13,047
======== ======== ======== ======== Other comprehensive income (loss) Foreign currency translation
adjustment (107) (144) (239) (109) Unrealized gain (loss) on foreign
currency exposure of net
investment in foreign operations 118 177 265 132
-------- -------- -------- --------
Total other comprehensive income
(loss) 11 33 26 23
-------- -------- -------- -------- Comprehensive loss $ (1,254) $ (1,186) $ (2,836) $(7,219)
======== ======== ======== ======== OTCBB closing price for XSPY-L Date: 2014/03/19 Closing Price: 1.30
____________________________________________________________
(c)2014 Market News Publishing Inc. All rights reserved. Toronto:(416)366-8881 Vancouver:(604)689-1101 Fax:(604)689-1106
]]></text></news-item>