<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSS-8BP1-F05M-K534"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Green groups want to join NC suit against Duke Energy on Dan River coal ash regulation</title><source>Charlotte Business Journal</source><author>John Downey</author><text><![CDATA[Four regional environmental groups have filed requests to intervene in an N.C. lawsuit over coal ash pollution on the Dan River from a shuttered Duke Energy (NYSE:DUK) coal plant.
The lawsuit was filed last summer, and so it predates the Feb. 2 incident at the Dan River Steam Station that spilled up to 39,000 tons of coal ash into the river. But that spill brought more attention to the court case.
"The tragic Dan River spill and the revelations of uncomfortably close ties between Duke Energy and (the N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources) make it all the more important that citizens and local conservation groups have a seat at the table," said Frank Holleman, the senior attorney at the Southern Environmental Law Center who represents the groups in court. "We will work to make sure that the Dan River is protected and that Duke Energy cleans up the Dan River site."
The Dan River Basin Association, The Roanoke River Basin Association, the Southern Alliance for Clean Energy and the Waterkeeper Alliance want to participate in the case.
"This spill demonstrates the dire need to remove coal ash from impoundments adjacent to our lakes and rivers and into dry, lined storage," said Gene Addesso, president of the Roanoke River Basin Association. "We cannot allow these same negligent actions to continue polluting our water and putting at risk the citizens and businesses within the Roanoke River Basin that depend on this precious natural resource."
The suit against Charlotte-based Duke's Dan River plant is one of four enforcement actions filed last year by DENR.
All of the cases are before Wake Superior Court Judge Paul Ridgeway. He has allowed similar groups to intevene in cases involving Duke's coal ash sites at Riverbend Steam Station on Mountain Island Lake, Duke's Asheville Plant on the French Broad River near Skyland, and its Sutton Plant near Wilmington on the Cape Fear River.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Charlotte Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>