<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSS-5WB1-JDJN-62H8"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Creating interface between Inland Revenue Laws &amp; AML Act: necessary provisions to be introduced in Finance Bill</title><source>Legal Monitor Worldwide</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The government is conducting a study for creating an interface between Income Tax Ordinance 2001, Sales Tax Act, 1990, Federal Excise Act, 2005 and Anti-Money Laundering Act to effectively control the menace of money laundering to eradicate the chances of terrorism financing.  Sources told Business Recorder here on Wednesday that the necessary provisions would be introduced in the Finance Bill (2014-15) to create an interface between the Inland Revenue Laws and Anti-Money Laundering Act based on the findings of the study. At present, the AML Act, 2010 explicitly excludes 'Fiscal Offences' - Tax crimes) from its purview, which should be brought within its scope by allowing the FMU to have access to income tax information.  The proposal is to include serious tax offences under the said tax laws into the Anti-money Laundering Act. The criminal proceeds generated through the evasion of duties and taxes would be effectively checked through the Anti-money Laundering Law. According to the sources, the Financial Monitoring Unit (FMU) has requested the FBR to indicate serious tax crimes for inclusion as predicate offences in AML Act, 2010 schedule, and was also decided in the National Economic Council (NEC) meeting dated January 10, 2014.  The FBR initiated a study proposal with the objective that the FBR & FMU in the light of international bodies (FATF/Egmont Group/APG) guidance, should process the study for an interface between Inland Revenue Laws ie Income Tax Ordinance, 2001, Sales Tax Act, 1990 & Federal Excise Act, 2005 and the Anti Money Laundering Act, 2010 to effectively control Money Laundering and Terrorism Financing.
The views of Legal Consultant & FMU were dispatched to the FBR. Now partially revised study was again sent by the FBR to the departments concerned. The final recommendations of the study agreed it may be legislated by the Parliament by the end of the FY 2013-14 through Finance Bill.  As per sources, the queries raised in the study to seek clarity are: Tax evasion keeps on occurring but remains within, the ambit of tax laws, when does a tax evasion be liable for cognisance under the AML Act, which provisions of fiscal laws w.r.t tax evasion be considered as predicate offences under AML Act etc.  The FMU commented that the FATE designated 21 serious categories of offences including tax crimes. Whereas, the FBR independently conceived and moved the study proposal at its own after amending the Income Tax Ordinance 2001 that affected the ambit of AML Act, 2010 eg, section 165A(1)(e) of Income Tax Ordinance 2001 requires banks to provide copies of suspicious transaction reports (STRs/CTRs) to FBR. 
Study on improving compliance with fiscal laws and anti money laundering law is supported. However, clarity to the study contents/substantive aspects and precise objects to be met, are the prerequisites. When contacted, a tax expert said that tax evasion is primarily jurisdiction of IRS officials. If tax evasion is a money laundering offence, the investigation would be conducted by Inland Revenue. The question arises whether tax laws should be included in the AML or not? If the FBR wanted to include tax evasion cases in the AML, the Board will have to report such cases to the FMU as existing laws does not allowed such sharing of data/information. For instance, section 216 of the Income Tax Ordinance 2001 bars tax department from disclosure of information to any agency except provided under the law.  In case serious tax crimes are included in the AML Act, drastic changes in the existing laws are required. The income tax law is primarily based on civil recovery whereas AML Act is basically a criminal law. When civil and criminal laws are integrated under AML Act and tax laws, homework is needed on both the sides. If the FBR agrees to include tax offences in AML law, the competent authority has to specify certain sections of all the three tax laws which cover serious tax crimes.  Presently, it is only income tax law which contains provisions aiming at probing into sources of investment, expenditure, accusation of assets and transfer of funds. The income tax law directly dealing with the major cases of sources of investment/expenditure is out of the purview of the AML Act. Ultimately, money laundering regime cannot be completed without including tax laws regime particularly income tax law.  The FBR has reviewed the entire anti-money laundering law for inclusion of serious tax crimes (direct taxes and indirect taxes) in the Anti-Money Laundering Act 2010. The move would be instrumental in controlling money laundering involving duties and taxes evasion under Income Tax Ordinance 2001, Federal Excise Act 2005 and Customs Act, 1969.  In terms of Section 2(j) of the AML Act, 2010 DGI & I-FBR (Customs) has been notified as Law Enforcement Agency (LEA) vide Notification dated August 24, 2010. The fiscal offences have been defined in section 2(g) of the AML Act, 2010 as offences punishable under the Income Tax Ordinance, 2001, Federal Excise Act, 2005, Sales Tax Act,1990, and Customs Act,1969 except Section 2 (s),15,16, 32, 32A and 156 thereof and any other law as the Federal Government may notify. The section 41 of the AML Act, 2010 was given an overriding effect wherein fiscal offences were excluded from the ambit of the AML Act, 2010, experts added. 
]]></text></news-item>