<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSV-NHB1-DY15-S1JJ"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Huge Crackdown On Ansar Beit El-Maqdes</title><source>Egypt State Information Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Armed Forces and Police have dealt a fatal blow to the so called Ansar Beit el-Maqdes group and managed to preempt plans for launching a series of bombings in Cairo and Giza governorates concurrently with the demonstrations called for by terrorist Muslim Brotherhood (MB) organization.
A joint force of the army and police early on Wednesday 19/3/2014 launched a campaign on Arab Sharkas village, Qalyubia governorate and tightened the siege on a building where gunmen were entrenched following a shootout which lasted for six hours.
The campaign ended in the arrest of eight terrorists from Beit el-Maqdes and killing of six others.
However, two Armed Forces explosives experts, Brigadier Maged Ahmed Ibrahim Saleh and Col. Maged Ahmed Kamal Shaker, were killed. One officer from the special operations was injured.
Terrorists opened fire and threw explosive belts and bombs at the forces upon clamping the siege on the building where they were hiding.
The troops found a big quantity of the TNT explosive material, explosive belts and bombs which were enough to demolish a whole district. This pushed the attacking force to deal cautiously with terrorists in order to avoid the bombing of the building and demolishing the whole village.
Assistant Interior Minister for Public Security Sector Major General Sayed Shafiq told al-Ahram that public and national security officers managed to detect the members of this terrorist cell and pinpoint their hideout in the village.
He said information indicated that elements of the so called Ansar Beit el-Maqdes have turned a wood workshop into a factory for explosives and bombs to be used in attacks on vital facilities in both Cairo and Giza governorates together with a number of police stations.
The members of the terrorist group were also planning to carry out attacks concurrently with calls for demonstrations by terrorist MB.
Investigations by the Interior Ministry bodies indicated that elements of the cell who were hiding in Arab Sharkas village took part in attacking the Armed Forces bus in Mataria, the Military Police checking point in Mostorod,
They also participated in Cairo Security directorate bombing and assassination of Assistant Interior Minister Major General Mohamed el-Saeid.
Twenty five central security formations, 600 police officers, formations from the Armed Forces, explosives experts, special forces, public and national security personnel took part in the campaign.
Prime Minister Ibrahim Mahlab issued a statement in which he mourned the two martyrs who sacrificed their lives for saving the people against a big quantity of explosive materials the terrorists were planning to use for killing a large number of victims.
]]></text></news-item>