<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSV-TX51-DYJJ-P1DC"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>LPG plan could hurt residents near lake</title><source>Star-Gazette (Elmira, New York)</source><author>By, Paula Fitzsimmons</author><text><![CDATA[Remember the sense of shelter we felt living in the Finger Lakes? Natural disasters abounded across our country, and here we felt gratitude for escaping these burdens and tragedies.
But we all learned a new word, fracking, which changes all of that. I have poured time and energy into the fight against fracking because I live on a farm, we have vineyards and a winery, and it all depends on this magnificent microclimate, soil, air and water. The blood, sweat and tears we dedicated the last decade to create our business and become part of the explosion of the Finger Lakes onto the international wine and tourism scene has been thrilling. Two million visitors a year experience all we offer.
But now there is a threat even closer to home. Insidiously developing fracking's infrastructure, Inergy - the corporation now called Crestwood - plans to turn our region into a gas storage and transportation hub for the Northeast, storing liquefied petroleum gas (LPG) in the salt caverns underneath Seneca Lake. Are we forgetting that this lake makes it all possible?
I have practiced medicine in Schuyler County for 28 years. Each day, I see patients and develop plans and strategies to keep them well or to reduce the effects of their ills: diabetes, hypertension, heart disease and lung disease, among the usual problems. Through my involvement in the movement against fracking, I have watched medical societies and medical institutions across New York take a stand against fracking because of the health effects.
I realized I had an imperative in my county to act and advocate for the health of our residents. Inergy's plan poses grave threats to respiratory health (asthma and lung disease) because of both particulate matter and the unavoidable increase in ozone (a toxin to the respiratory tract), and possibly fetal health (air pollution is linked to pre-term births). Elderly and the young are at heightened risk. These are well-researched environmental topics with excellent predictor models, and the science is clear: air pollution is linked to increased mortality and a range of health effects. Yet, unfortunately, our governing bodies have paid little attention to the health risks or overall loss of quality of life.
Beyond the health effects associated with regular operating, catastrophic accidents could lead to problems of a magnitude that is difficult to fathom. Similarly, if the structural integrity of the caverns do not hold up - which geologic evidence suggests is a very real possibility - the water for 100,000 people could be poisoned. I look at our small hospital and shudder imagining what could come in the door.
These are among the health concerns that recently led many of my health professional colleagues to sign a letter asking all of the involved governing bodies to stop this project. Gov. Andrew Cuomo, the Department of Environmental Conservation and the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission should do right by the citizens of the Finger Lakes, our health and our thriving region by pulling the plug on this dangerous project.
Fitzsimmons is a Hector resident.
]]></text></news-item>