<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSV-TX51-DYJJ-P1CC"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>State official hurting jobless, senator says</title><source>Des Moines Register</source><author>By, William Petroski, and Jason Noble</author><text><![CDATA[A Democratic lawmaker on Wednesday accused the Republican head of Iowa Workforce Development of illegally pressuring the agency's administrative law judges to rule in favor of businesses and against workers in appeals involving unemployment benefits.
State Sen. William Dotzler of Waterloo accused Director Teresa Wahlert of harassing the judges - whom he described as working in a climate of fear - in an effort to reduce employers' costs for jobless benefits. He called on Republican Gov. Terry Branstad to ask for the resignation of Wahlert, whom he appointed. Dotzler also said he has asked for a federal investigation.
"In a legal dispute, everyone should be treated fairly and with respect. That's not happening," Dotzler said.
Wahlert issued a statement Wednesday saying her agency's administrative law judges are working diligently and doing their jobs properly while making improvements to the adjudication process. The improvements will ensure the state continues to receive federal money to administer the unemployment insurance program, she said.
Dotzler, who co-chairs the committee responsible for drafting the department's budget, said he sent a letter asking the U.S. Department of Labor to investigate whether Wahlert is violating federal laws requiring the fair and impartial administration of unemployment insurance benefits.
The Department of Labor did not respond Wednesday to a request for comment about Dotzler's letter.
Jimmy Centers, Branstad's communications director, criticized Dotzler, accusing him of "Washington, D.C.-style partisan attacks" that have no place in Iowa.
"The taxpayers expect their elected leaders to work in a bipartisan fashion to pass meaningful legislation, not engage in Senate Democrats' petty political theater," he said.
Main accusations, agency rebuttals
Dotzler, who said he has met with many current and former administrative law judges, held a news conference to voice his complaints against Wahlert. These included allegations that Wahlert:
Created a hostile work environment for administrative law judges who did not follow her "pro-employer, anti-employee philosophy." Wahlert's statement rejected that accusation.
Eliminated the chief administrative law judge's position, which had provided a buffer against politics, and made herself the direct supervisor of the administrative law judges.
Workforce Development spokesman Kerry Koonce said that in July 2013, several positions were eliminated in the department due to federal budget issues. The chief administrative law judge position was one of them. As that position was eliminated, the staff required a different supervisor, she said. As a result, Wahlert is supervising the staff, work flow and training for the Unemployment Appeals Bureau, she said.
"This is completely allowable under federal regulations ... as long as the director does not hear cases, which she doesn't," Koonce said. "The director does not participate in the hearings or review the decision before they are issued."
Directed the administrative law judges to become involved with "outreach to community and business leaders" and required them to develop "tip sheets" to help businesses win cases against their former employees. He said these actions interfered with the judges' ability to impartially weigh cases. He added that Wahlert did not ask judges to create tip sheets to help workers win appeals against their ex-bosses.
Koonce said it's untrue that judges were required to develop tip sheets to help employers while such sheets were not developed for ex-workers.
"There are a number of generic tip sheets on our website usable by employers and claimants," Koonce said. "Tip sheets are available for general fact-finding information, preparing a case, and for issues that come up frequently, such as what an employer or claimant should do if they refuse a job while receiving benefits, information on how cases are handled related to intoxication in the work place, off duty conduct, etc."
The documents reference both employers and claimants, she said.
Former chief judge echoes allegations
Joseph L. Walsh - the former chief administrative law judge identified by Dotzler - echoed the allegations against Wahlert in an interview on Wednesday.
Walsh, who has since taken another job with Workforce Development and stressed that he was speaking as a private individual and not in his official capacity, recalled Wahlert coming to him with complaints from employers and asking him to review and evaluate judges' decisions.
In at least one case when he found a judge had made the right ruling, she ordered him to write an "employer tip sheet" so other employers could avoid paying benefits in similar cases.
"The bottom line is she was not happy with what the law is with regard to unemployment. She doesn't like it. She wants it changed," Walsh said. "When I explained to her the process for changing the law, she didn't like that. So when she was really unhappy, the main thing that she would do is demand these employer tip sheets."
Wahlert said in a statement that the U.S. Department of Labor last week completed a routine monitoring visit to Iowa Workforce Development regarding its unemployment appeals process. The monitoring staff was very complimentary of the department's improvements and process changes, she said, adding she does not expect any negative findings.
Wahlert describes accomplishments
Wahlert said one of the primary measurements for the state's unemployment appeals program is a 30-day "timeliness data point." Since August 2013, Iowa has moved from the 47th lowest in the country to 12th place, she said.
"I'm extremely proud of the administrative law judges and staff who have worked diligently and brought forth a number of innovative ideas to improve our process," Wahlert said.
Since August, Wahlert added, the appeals unit has implemented new training opportunities, introduced technologies that have decreased processing times and clarified rules that create a better understanding of the process for customers.
Dotzler noted that in February, a federal investigation concluded that Maine Gov. Paul LePage, a Republican, and other Maine officials interfered with unemployment hearings in a way that could have swayed hearing officers to favor employers over claimants.
LePage has issued a statement denying any wrongdoing and has contended the federal probe was politically motivated by Democrats.
Dotzler's accusations against Wahlert and the Branstad administration quickly drew the attention of Democrats focused on defeating Branstad in his re-election bid this November. State Sen. Jack Hatch of Des Moines, the leading Democratic gubernatorial candidate, issued a statement Wednesday lumping the Workforce Development issue together with the revelation this week that Branstad's administration paid several secret settlements to fired employees and calling on the governor to answer questions on both matters.
"Is the governor unable to do a quick conference call with reporters and legislators to clear the air?" Hatch asked in a prepared statement. "If there's nothing to hide, stop hiding."
Branstad is out of state on a weeklong vacation in Arizona. Lt. Gov. Kim Reynolds is at a conference in Washington, D.C.
About Teresa Wahlert
Age: 65.
Title: Director of Workforce Development.
Hometown: Dubuque.
Career: Appointed director of workforce development in January 2011. Previously was president and chief operating officer of the real estate firm Mid-America Group and president and CEO of the Greater Des Moines Partnership. Before that, she spent 32 years in the telecommunications industry, including as a regional vice president.
Public service: Previous member of the Iowa Board of Regents; Wells Fargo of Iowa Community Board; Des Moines Art Center Board of Trustees; and Greater Des Moines Partnership Board of Directors. Iowa Business Hall of Fame inductee.
Education: Bachelor's degree from St. Mary's at Notre Dame; MBA from Creighton University; master's of science in business from Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
Source: University of Iowa
About Iowa Workforce Development
Iowa Workforce Development is the state's "economic security" agency.
Its responsibilities include managing the state's unemployment insurance benefits and workers' compensation system, investigating wage theft and worker misclassification, assisting in job searches and placements, compiling state labor data, enforcing workplace safety laws, and verifying the proper operation of everything from amusement rides to elevators to building boilers.
The agency had a $181 million budget in 2013.
Recent headlines about agency
Iowa Workforce Development has been in the news often since Gov. Terry Branstad returned to office and Teresa Wahlert became director in 2011.
Workers' Compensation Commissioner Chris Godfrey sued the state in 2011 alleging discrimination based on sexual orientation after Branstad reduced his pay by almost $39,000 a year. That litigation is ongoing.
Branstad closed 36 unemployment offices controlled by Workforce Development in 2011, replacing them with computer kiosks that in many cases did not work or were under-used. The Iowa Supreme Court later ruled Branstad exceeded his authority in closing the offices.
Thirty employees at the agency were laid off last July in a move Branstad administration officials said was forced by federal government budget cuts. Democrats and labor leaders criticized the move.
Workforce Development is now the agency at the center of Branstad's Home Base Iowa campaign, which is aimed at attracting military veterans to live and work in Iowa. The initiative is a top priority for the governor during the current legislative session.
- Jason Noble
Documents, video online
Go to this story at DesMoinesRegister.com to view documents Democrats released Wednesday about Iowa Workforce Development. Also find a video of Sen. Bill Dotzler speaking at a news conference regarding his concerns about the state agency.
]]></text></news-item>