<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSV-MB31-JCXB-225K"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>British Airways PLC BA Annual Report and Accounts -2-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[During the year BA has continued to maintain and operate its structure and processes to identify, assess and manage risks. The principal risks and uncertainties affecting the Group are further detailed for the year ended 31 December 2013 in the Annual Report and Accounts. The risks include consolidation and deregulation, competition, government intervention, infrastructure constraints, brand reputation, economic conditions, employee relations, failure of a critical IT system, pandemic, landing fees and security charges, safety/security incidents, events causing significant network disruption, debt funding, fuel price, currency and interest rate fluctuation, pensions, governance and compliance with Competition, Bribery and Corruption law Directors' responsibility statement The Directors as listed in the Annual Report and Accounts for the year ended 31 December 2013, confirm that, to the best of each person's knowledge:
-- The Group financial statements in this report, which have been prepared in accordance with IFRS as adopted by the EU, IFRIC interpretation and those parts of the Companies Act 2006 applicable to companies reporting under IFRS, give a true and fair view of the assets, liabilities, financial position and profit/loss of the Group; and -- The management report contained in this report includes a fair review of the development and performance of the business and the position of the Group, together with a description of the principal risks and uncertainties that they face. Ends Note to Editors: Certain statements included in this report are forward-looking and are subject to assumptions, risks and uncertainties that could cause actual results to differ materially from those expressed or implied by the forward-looking statements. Forward-looking statements can typically be identified by the use of forward-looking terminology, such as "expects", "may", "will", "could", "intends", "plans", "predicts", "envisages" or "anticipates" and include, without limitation, projections relating to results of operations and financial conditions and British Airways Plc (the 'Company') plans and objectives for future operations, discussions of the Company's Business Plan, expected future revenues, financing plans and expected expenditures and divestments. All forward-looking statements in this report are based upon information known to the Company at the date of this report as well as the Company's current expectations and beliefs concerning future events affecting the Company which involve a number of known and unknown risks and uncertainties. You are cautioned not to place any undue reliance on the forward-looking statements contained in this report which speak only as at the date of this report. The Company undertakes no obligation to publicly update or revise any forward-looking statement, whether as a result of new information, future events or otherwise, except as required by any applicable laws and regulations. It is not reasonably possible to itemise all of the many factors and specific events that could cause the Company's forward-looking statements to be incorrect or that could otherwise have a material adverse effect on the future operations or results of an airline operating in the global economy, though details of potential risks and uncertainties affecting the Company are described in the risk management and risk factors section of the report. Further information on the primary risks of the business and the risk management process of the Company is given in the Annual Report and Accounts 2013; these documents are available on www.iagshares.com. Investor Relations - 2 World Business Centre Heathrow, Newall Road, London Heathrow Airport, HOUNSLOW, TW6 2SF Tel: +44 (0) 20 8564 2900
TWELVE MONTH RESULTS 2013
OPERATING AND FINANCIAL STATISTICS
DISCONTINUED OPERATIONS
TOTAL GROUP OPERATIONS - CONTINUING OPERATIONS
TRAFFIC AND CAPACITY
FINANCIAL
TOTAL AIRLINE OPERATIONS - CONTINUING OPERATIONS
OPERATIONS
]]></text></news-item>