<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSV-TX51-DYJJ-P0VM"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>How Association of Africans impacts Vt.</title><source>The Burlington Free Press (Vermont)</source><author>By, Lynn Monty</author><text><![CDATA[Thato Ratsebe is the director of communications and health education at the Association of Africans Living in Vermont, which is a nonprofit serving refugee and immigrants. She moved from Botswana to the United States in 2001, and volunteered for the AALV for three years before becoming a full-time employee in 2012.
Thato, 36, of Shelburne has travel extensively in Africa and holds a bachelor's degree in journalism and mass communications and a master's degree in administration from St. Michael's College.
Ratsebe said the organization's name represents historical roots in the African resettled refugee community from 1999, however, the AALV today serves refugees and immigrants from all national groups.
"While the AALV was founded by primarily French-speaking West and Central African families to assist with resettlement and integration issues then, it opened its doors in late 2008 to the large number of refugees arriving in Vermont from all parts of the world," she said. "These groups include Iraqis, Burmese, and Bhutanese refugees."
BFP: How many people are served and how?
Thato Ratsebe: In 2013, we served 350 unduplicated adults, and children ages 10 to 19.
AALV's Project Integration employs bilingual and bicultural outreach workers to help refugees navigate the services, resources, and regulatory frameworks related to their social and economic integration in Vermont.
Outreach Workers help refugees with securing affordable housing, applying for and remaining compliant with their public benefits, securing gainful employment opportunities, registering for health insurance, seeking relief from family conflict and abuse, understanding the health care system, communicate with local schools, and connecting with elder and youth service providers.
AALV's Workforce Development program highlights self-sufficiency as the ultimate goal. Many refugees arrive in the United States with skills and ambitions that do not perfectly align with employment opportunities in the United States. Linguistically and culturally appropriate training, guidance with recertification, and job placement assistance are required.
Other programs are AALV's Health Education and Outreach, The New Farms for New Americans project, and AALVInterpret, an interpreter services program.
BFP: Does this organization help our local economy?
TR: Through our referral services and trainings, local businesses are able increase their labor by hiring both skilled and semi skilled refugees and immigrants.
BFP: Why is this association needed? How would Vermont be different without Association of Africans Living in Vermont?
TR: AALV existence is critical in assisting immigrants and refugees transition into their new environment and home. We also serve as a referral service agency to local service provider organization.
When households live in isolation, families falter. We need one another to emerge from poverty and become a member of the larger society. We connect our families to the resources they need to thrive in American society.
We add value to the existing service provider organizations by sharing our experiences and highlighting the needs, concerns and cultural backgrounds of the communities we serve.
BFP: Where did you grow up?
TR: I grew up in the central district of Botswana, between my home village of Serowe and Palapye, where I did my primary and secondary school.
BFP: How did you come to live in Vermont?
TR: Long story, but to make it short, I was very lucky to meet my host family, Bill Ryerson and Leta Finch of Shelburne. They played a huge role in my attaining education in the U.S. They parented me, still do, and groomed me to become the woman I am today. I came here in my early twenties, started school at the Community College of Vermont, transferred to St. Michael's College and started my career under their care.
BFP: What fuels your passion for AALV?
TR: Serving others, seeing people gain their independence and thrive is what makes me tick.
BFP: What hobbies did you have as a kid?
TR: I liked to sing and dance. I sang in church, choral music and did both ballroom and our traditional dance.
BFP: What did you want to be when you grew up?
TR: I have always wanted to be an investigative journalist. I thoroughly enjoy working with people. While I never had a dream to become a doctor or health professional in a traditional sense, I was always fascinated by the idea of helping communities understand the importance of public health through the media.
BFP: Best part of your job and biggest challenges?
TR: When I look back at how far clients come from, and how far they are, I consider that a major win. Seeing a client initiate a phone call to make a doctor's appointment, or write a check to pay their utility bill, or even an employer sharing their satisfaction about working with our clients simply make my day.
Biggest challenge: I wish I could solve everyone's problem. The reality of life proves this to be hard to do. Sometimes having boundaries can be tough, so, trying to strike a balance between my personal and work life can be challenging.
I find myself spending ungodly hours doing work - something I vowed to never do. But when you do this kind of work, it's hard not to go an extra mile. Fortunately I am surrounded by the most caring staff, and an incredibly supportive executive director who selflessly serve the community.
BFP: What sustains AALV?
TR: The AALV is a 501(c)3 non-profit organization registered with the Internal Revenue Service. We are supported by federal and state grants, individual donations as well as support from local foundations. We also have income revenue from our interpreter program that helps us cover some of our administrative expenses. We also work with volunteers in some of our programs and immensely value their contribution.
BFP: How is running a non-profit like this one different than running a for profit business?
TR: Striking a balance in working to meet people's basic needs, and sustaining the organization at the same time is complicated than running a for-profit business.
In the profit making world, you can make the decision to downsize the staff and programs when the business is not meeting the bottom line. We cannot simply drop clients because they are not making progress within a given time period. We have to consider the evolving needs of the community we serve.
Due to various experiences, some clients progress to independence quicker than others. We cannot compare this kind of progress to measure our success. We consider every step, small or big, taken by an individual or family as a positive towards gaining independence.
BFP: What are the current needs at Association of Africans Living in Vermont?
TR: Funding to sustain and grow our programs long term. This comes with hiring additional staff members. We cannot afford to do so without funding.
BFP: If you could do anything you wanted to innovate at Association of Africans Living in Vermont, with no barriers, what would you do? The sky is the limit.
TR: I would partner with other organizations in the community to develop a center in the old north end, showcase the rich different cultures that Chittenden County already possess by offering programs in the local schools, develop a vibrant program for cultural exchange and give local children an opportunity to learn more about each other by visiting different parts of the world.
Contact Lynn Monty at LynnMonty@FreePressMedia.com and follow her on Twitter at www.twitter.com/VermontSongbird.
Who they serve
According to AALV's records, they serve about 98 percent of the refugee community in Vermont. Based on calendar year 2013, about 60 percent were Bhutanese, 37 percent were African, and three percent were Burmese. Iraqis and other groups were also served.
AALV employs 10 full-time and three part-time bilingual staff from Bhutan, Somalia, U.S., Burundi, DR Congo, Botswana, Burkina Faso, Burma, Trinidad and Tobago.
For more information visit www.africansinvermont.org.
]]></text></news-item>