<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-4RN1-JCBF-S150"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>FITZPATRICK ON NOVA VISIT: WORK TO BE DONE ON ABUSE, HUMAN TRAFFICKING LOCAL LAWMAKERS, STAKEHOLDERS TALK STRATEGY FOR ADDRESSING CHILD ABUSE IN BUCKS CO.</title><source>States News Service</source><author>States News Service</author><text><![CDATA[The following information was released by the office of Pennsylvania Rep. Michael Fitzpatrick:
Congressman Mike Fitzpatrick (PA-8) joined Senator Pat Toomey (R-PA), local lawmakers and victims' rights advocates Thursday to discuss the need for a coordinated strategy to address abuse and human trafficking in the district.
"Tragically, human trafficking and abuse is an epidemic coming to light in our nation and in our neighborhoods - events like this, which connect officials on every level, help us push back against these heinous crimes," said Fitzpatrick. "Legislation alone isn't the solution to stopping abuse in Bucks and Montgomery counties - it's the continued interaction and sharing of ideas and needs that will ultimately help us address this problem from prevention, to counseling to prosecution."
The event, held at the Network of Victims' Assistance (NOVA) headquarters, allowed stakeholders - including Fitzpatrick - to highlight both areas of success and concern regarding abuse prevention and prosecution. Among those in attendance were NOVA personnel and members of the Bucks County Children's Advocacy Center who specifically highlighted efforts of local, state and federal leaders.
"NOVA staff had the opportunity to meet with Congressman Fitzpatrick and other community leaders to discuss issues related to victims of child abuse and human trafficking. We are grateful for his support in a bipartisan effort to release Victim of Crime Act (VOCA) funds for much needed victim services," said Julie Dugery, NOVA Volunteer and Community Outreach Coordinator. "Congressman Fitzpatrick was generous with his time, his sensitivity to victim issues, and his ongoing efforts to help victims in our community - we were honored that he came to visit our organization."
Fitzpatrick, a member of the Victims Rights Caucus, highlighted his efforts to bring a package of five anti-human trafficking bills to the House floor. Furthermore, he joined Toomey in laying out the need for legislation to stop the shameful process of "passing the trash' - in which a teacher or school employee suspected of child abuse is transferred between districts or across state lines without disclosure of the abuse. Fitzpatrick has successfully worked to add his Jeremy Bell Act language into a pair of education bills which passed the House this Congress. Toomey has introduced companion legislation in the Senate.
"The most vulnerable members of our communities deserve to be protected - both in their homes and their schools. Thankfully, our community is blessed with volunteers and organizations like those here today who work tirelessly on their behalf," added Fitzpatrick. "Be it on Capitol Hill and with legislation like the Jeremy Bell Act or VOCA, or making sure these neighborhood heroes have the tools they need, I'm glad to be a part of the solution."
"As the father of three young children, I am dedicated to strengthening laws to keep child predators away from our children," said Toomey. "Unfortunately, prevention is not enough. Too many of our children are preyed upon and need our help. I am proud that two pieces of legislation I have sponsored will assist organizations like the Bucks County Network of Victim's Assistance while simultaneously strengthening federal law to protect children."
Also attending the roundtable discussion: Barbara Clark, NOVA Executive Director; Kathy Bennett, NOVA Associate Director and Co-Chair of Bucks County Coalition Against Trafficking; Leslie Slingsby, Director, Bucks County Children's Advocacy Center; Al Sutter, NOVA Board Member/Office of State Senator Tomlinson; Congressman Mike Fitzpatrick; State Senator Stewart Greenleaf; David Heckler, District Attorney of Bucks County; Rob Loughery, Bucks County Commissioner; Charlie Martin, Bucks County Commissioner; State Representative Bernie O'Neill; Cathleen Palm, Center for Children's Justice; Senator Pat Toomey
]]></text></news-item>