<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-98H1-JBG1-8129"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Foster Wheeler Signs Agreement with Siemens Energy to Acquire Environmental Business</title><source>Business Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Foster Wheeler AG (Nasdaq:FWLT) announced today that a subsidiary of its Global Power Group has signed an asset purchase agreement with Siemens Energy, Inc. to acquire the Siemens Environmental Systems and Services business that supplies and services clean air technologies for use in power plants and industrial facilities. Closing of the transaction is subject to customary closing conditions, and is expected in the second quarter of 2014.
The Siemens Environmental Systems and Services purchase includes assets of the former Wheelabrator Air Pollution Control Company located in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania and the Advanced Burner Technology Company located in Branchburg, New Jersey.
Combined, these businesses design, engineer, retrofit and service a broad range of clean air technologies for power and industrial plants including: wet and dry flue gas desulfurization (FGD) and particulate control (fabric filters and electrostatic precipitators), acid gas control, mercury control, NOx reduction and combustion optimization systems.
"This is a strategic acquisition which expands our capability to offer clean air products and services to our clients in both the power and industrial sectors," said Gary Nedelka, Chief Executive Officer of Foster Wheeler's Global Power Group. "It complements our existing portfolio of clean-air products and allows us to provide our clients with a full array of solutions to meet both tightening environmental regulations and the growing demand for energy on a global basis."
As announced, on February 13, 2014 Foster Wheeler entered into a definitive agreement with AMEC plc ("AMEC") concerning a possible business combination of Foster Wheeler and AMEC. Foster Wheeler has informed AMEC of the Siemens transaction. Foster Wheeler does not expect the Siemens transaction to affect the timing of completion of the business combination of Foster Wheeler and AMEC.
Foster Wheeler AG is a global engineering and construction company and power equipment supplier delivering technically advanced, reliable facilities and equipment. The company employs approximately 13,000 talented professionals with specialized expertise dedicated to serving its clients through one of its two primary business groups. The company's Global Engineering and Construction Group designs and constructs leading-edge processing facilities for the upstream oil and gas, LNG and gas-to-liquids, refining, chemicals and petrochemicals, power, minerals and metals, environmental, pharmaceuticals, biotechnology and healthcare industries. The company's Global Power Group is a world leader in combustion and steam generation technology that designs, manufactures and erects steam generating and auxiliary equipment for power stations and industrial facilities and also provides a wide range of aftermarket services. The company is based in Zug, Switzerland, and its operational headquarters office is in Reading, United Kingdom. For more information about Foster Wheeler, please visit our website at www.fwc.com .
Safe Harbor Statement
Foster Wheeler AG news releases may contain forward-looking statements that are based on management's assumptions, expectations and projections about the Company and the various industries within which the Company operates. These include statements regarding the Company's expectations about revenues (including as expressed by its backlog), its liquidity, the outcome of litigation and legal proceedings and recoveries from customers for claims and the costs of current and future asbestos claims and the amount and timing of related insurance recoveries. Such forward-looking statements by their nature involve a degree of risk and uncertainty. The Company cautions that a variety of factors, including but not limited to the factors described in the Company's most recent Annual Report on Form 10-K, which was filed with the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission, and the following, could cause the Company's business conditions and results to differ materially from what is contained in forward-looking statements including: the timing and success of the proposed offer and acquisition of the Company by AMEC plc, the risk that the Company's business will be adversely impacted during the pending proposed offer and acquisition of the Company by AMEC plc, benefits, effects or results of the Company's redomestication to Switzerland, deterioration in global economic conditions, changes in investment by the oil and gas, oil refining, chemical/petrochemical and power generation industries, changes in the financial condition of its customers, changes in regulatory environments, changes in project design or schedules, contract cancellations, the changes in estimates made by the Company of costs to complete projects, changes in trade, monetary and fiscal policies worldwide, compliance with laws and regulations relating to the Company's global operations, currency fluctuations, war, terrorist attacks and/or natural disasters affecting facilities either owned by the Company or where equipment or services are or may be provided by the Company, interruptions to shipping lanes or other methods of transit, outcomes of pending and future litigation, including litigation regarding the Company's liability for damages and insurance coverage for asbestos exposure, protection and validity of the Company's patents and other intellectual property rights, increasing global competition, compliance with its debt covenants, recoverability of claims against the Company's customers and others by the Company and claims by third parties against the Company, and changes in estimates used in its critical accounting policies. Other factors and assumptions not identified above were also involved in the formation of these forward-looking statements and the failure of such other assumptions to be realized, as well as other factors, may also cause actual results to differ materially from those projected. Most of these factors are difficult to predict accurately and are generally beyond the Company's control. You should consider the areas of risk described above in connection with any forward-looking statements that may be made by the Company. The Company undertakes no obligation to publicly update any forward-looking statements, whether as a result of new information, future events or otherwise. You are advised, however, to consult any additional disclosures the Company makes in proxy statements, quarterly reports on Form 10-Q, annual reports on Form 10-K and current reports on Form 8-K filed with or furnished to the Securities and Exchange Commission.
http://www.businesswire.com
]]></text></news-item>