<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-V0P1-JC65-51D1"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>News briefs from around Kentucky at 1:58 a.m. EDT</title><source>Associated Press State &amp; Local</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Kentucky House panel halts 3 abortion access bills
FRANKFORT, Ky. (AP) - A Kentucky House panel has halted three Republican-sponsored bills that would regulate abortion access statewide.
Two of the measures would have required a woman seeking an abortion to undergo an ultrasound, without exemption for rape victims.
The third bill would have required a woman to be physically present during a consultation with an abortion provider instead of consulting over the phone.
Testifying on behalf of the bills were representatives from the Kentucky Right to Life Association.
Opponents of the bills included committee Chairman Tom Burch, a Louisville Democrat, and representatives from the Kentucky American Civil Liberties Union.
The bills were voted down along party lines in the committee after a contentious debate.
___
FRANKFORT, Ky. (AP) - Legislation aimed at having fewer children locked up in juvenile detention centers passed the Kentucky Senate by a wide margin Thursday, providing momentum for some of the biggest proposed changes in decades to the justice system for minors.
A major thrust of the measure would steer more young offenders toward community-based treatment as an alternative to detention.
Sen. Whitney Westerfield said his bill would bring needed updates to a system he called ineffective and costly.
"It is the first and best step in decades that Kentucky has taken to improve its juvenile justice system," the Hopkinsville Republican said.
The measure passed the GOP-led Senate on a 31-7 vote. It now goes to the Democratic-run House for consideration.
House Speaker Greg Stumbo called the measure a good idea and said it would get the attention of his chamber.
___
FRANKFORT, Ky. (AP) - Kentucky lawmakers wrapped up work Thursday on a long-sought measure that would allow local voters to decide whether to legalize alcohol sales at more state parks and golf courses.
The state Senate provided final passage, sending the bill to Gov. Steve Beshear for his consideration. The measure previously passed the House.
Most state park lodges and golf courses are situated in counties where alcohol sales are prohibited. The bill's supporters, led by House Speaker Pro Tem Larry Clark, said giving local voters the option to approve alcohol sales at those parks or golf courses would attract more visitors.
"We're optimistic this will give us some new opportunities to attract more guests ... and generate more revenue that can be used to support the parks," said State Parks Commissioner Elaine Walker.
The bill would allow residents to petition for the local-option elections. The ballot issue would be whether to allow alcoholic beverages to be sold by the drink at the local park or golf course.
Allowing alcohol sales would lure more people to eat at state park lodges and more business conferences to meet at them, Clark said.
___
FRANKFORT, Ky. (AP) - A proposal to let local governments charge a 1 percent sales tax is still alive in the Kentucky legislature after Democratic Gov. Steve Beshear convinced House Speaker Greg Stumbo to support it.
Stumbo announced his decision after a private meeting with Beshear on Thursday. He said the House could vote on the bill Thursday or Friday.
Louisville Mayor Greg Fischer has lobbied hard for the bill, saying it is the best way for Kentucky's local governments to pay for their own projects without asking the state for money. Kentucky retailers are opposed to the bill because it would raise their prices.
Kentucky already imposes a 6 percent sales tax, which brings in about $3 billion annually.
]]></text></news-item>