<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-MB41-F046-7331"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>US Flint Hills agrees to pollution controls at Port Arthur plant</title><source>Chemical News &amp; Intelligence</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[HOUSTON (ICIS)--Flint Hills Resources has agreed to control air pollution from industrial flares and leaking equipment at its chemicals plant in Port Arthur, Texas, the US Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) announced on Thursday.
"By working with EPA, Flint Hills has advanced new air pollution controls that will help EPA bring similar air quality improvements to other American communities," Cynthia Giles, assistant administrator with EPA's Office of Enforcement and Compliance Insurance, said in a statement.
The agreement is part of a settlement with the EPA and US Department of Justice, which requires Flint Hills to pay a $350,000 fine for Clean Air Act violations, to operate equipment to recover and recycle waste gases and to ensure flares are burned with 98% efficiency. The company has spent $16m to implement these required controls, the statement said.
When fully implemented, the company estimates it will spend $28m to reduce fugitive pollutant emissions. The company will also spend $2m on a diesel retrofit or replacement project and $350,000 to purchase and install technologies to reduce energy demand in low income homes, the statement said.
Flint Hills also agreed to make public its "fence line" monitoring data, a record of the benzene and butadiene (BD) levels at the boundaries of the facility, the EPA said.
The complaint, filed at the same time as the settlement, alleges that Flint Hills improperly operated its steam-assisted flaring devices, emitting excess volatile organic compounds (VOCs) like benzene. It also alleges violations of regulations designed to limit emissions from leaking equipment, the EPA said.
Once fully implemented, the EPA estimates the settlement will reduce VOCs and other hazardous air pollutants by 1,880 tons/year and will reduce emissions of greenhouse gases by 69,000 tons/year. The EPA did not specify if it referred to short tons or metric tonnes.
The consent decree, filed in the Eastern District Court of Texas, is subject to a 30-day public comment period and court approval. The decree is [1]available for viewing on line.
References
1. http://www.justice.gov/enrd/Consent_Decrees.html
]]></text></news-item>