<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-9371-DXKS-J201"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Vital Voices Global Partnership, the Avon Foundation for Women with Avon Foundation Global Ambassador Fergie, and the U.S. Department of State Launch New Initiative; Initiative Supports Victims of Extreme Forms of Gender-Based Violence and Creates Global Criminal Justice Responses in India, Mexico, Nepal, South Africa and other countries</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Global Partnership to End Violence Against Women, a collaboration of Vital Voices Global Partnership, the Avon Foundation for Women and the U.S. Department of State, today presented a new initiative to address gender-based violence: the Gender-Based Violence Emergency Response and Protection Initiative.

To view the multimedia assets associated with this release, please click:http://www.multivu.com/mnr/7137251-avon-foundation-for-women-vital-voices-global-partnership-with-fergie
In making the announcement, Vital Voices CEO Alyse Nelson said, "We are delighted to be part of this new initiative that leverages the knowledge and expertise of our global women leaders to rapidly and effectively identify and respond to the immediate needs of victims. From providing legal services to women who have suffered domestic violence, to creating viable employment opportunities for survivors of human trafficking these leaders know their communities and they have designed solutions that restore freedom and dignity. They are bringing us closer to a world free of violence."
The Gender-Based Violence Emergency Response and Protection Initiative is a first-of-its-kind global program dedicated to assisting victims of extreme forms of gender-based violence and harmful traditional practices around the world. The Initiative takes comprehensive steps to eradicate domestic violence, sexual assault, honor crimes and other forms of gender-based violence by providing critical support to survivors.  By providing short-term emergency grants to cover medical care, emergency shelter, legal assistance, and other related costs, the program allows victims in urgent situations to access life-saving services.
"Gender-based violence is a global epidemic and an affront to humanity," said Uzra Zeya, Acting Assistant Secretary of State for Democracy, Human Rights and Labor. "It is our privilege to join in launching the GBV Initiative, a unique partnership which aims to uphold the dignity and advance the human rights of women and girls around the world."
The Initiative takes a holistic approach to addressing these crimes by creating a global gender-based violence training program for law enforcement, judges, prosecutors, government officials, and NGO advocates - The Justice Institute on Gender-Based Violence.  Over the next two years, the program will work with criminal justice professionals and service providers in India, Mexico, Nepal, South Africa and other countries to develop and provide training that promotes a victim-centered approach to holding offenders accountable for their crimes.
Avon Foundation Global Ambassador Fergie said, "The new Justice Institute on Gender-Based Violence is designed to ensure that laws achieve their promise.  It will go even further to protect women who are victims of violence and secure justice for them. I am so proud to announce this pioneering new partnership of the Avon Foundation for Women, Vital Voices and the State Department."
Cindy Dyer, Vice President for Human Rights at Vital Voices Global Partnership and a former specialized domestic and sexual violence prosecutor, states, "We are honored to be part of these groundbreaking, comprehensive initiatives that will provide victims of gender-based violence not only with the critical services they need, but also with the justice they deserve."
Vital VoicesVital Voices Global Partnership is a leading non-governmental organization that identifies, invests in and brings visibility to extraordinary women around the world by unleashing their leadership potential to transform lives and accelerate peace and prosperity in their communities. Founded by former U.S. Secretary of State Hillary Clinton in 1997, the organization trains and mentors women leaders as agents of transformative change in economic development, human rights and political participation. The Vital Voices Global Leadership Network includes more than 14,000 leaders representing 144 countries who have trained and mentored 500,000 additional women and girls in their communities. Visithttp://www.vitalvoices.orgto learn more.
Avon Global PhilanthropyAvonis a global corporate leader in philanthropy focused on causes that matter most to women. Through 2013, Avon global philanthropy, led by the U.S.-basedAvon Foundation for Women, has donated more than $957 million in more than 50 countries. Avon's funding is focused on breast cancer research and access to care through theAvon Breast Cancer Crusade, and efforts to reduce domestic and gender violence through itsSpeak Out Against Domestic Violenceprogram. The company's global markets sell special products to raise awareness and funds for breast cancer and domestic violence, conduct hundreds of events for these causes, and educate women around the world through its global army of more than 6 million Avon Representatives. Visithttp://www.avonfoundation.orgto learn more.



To view the multimedia assets associated with this release, please click:http://www.multivu.com/mnr/7137251-avon-foundation-for-women-vital-voices-global-partnership-with-fergie
SOURCE Avon Foundation for Women
]]></text></news-item>