<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-NF61-JBF5-T3SF"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Asylum seekers may be resettled in Papua New Guinea within three months: Tony Abbott</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Prime Minister Tony Abbott says the permanent resettlement of asylum seekers in Papua New Guinea could begin within the next two to three months.
Mr Abbott has held formal talks with PNG's prime minister, Peter O'Neill, in Port Moresby.
Mr O'Neill says his country is committed to the agreement struck last year to resettle asylum seekers held at the Manus Island detention centre who had attempted to reach Australia by boat.
He says the talks have been constructive and that Australia and PNG will continue to "work together" on resettling asylum seekers.
"For PNG, we are committed to staying the course," Mr O'Neill said. "We have agreed to participate in this program that was signed by our former prime ministers.
"We will of course process those who have now been interviewed for processing and we will be dealing with them as quickly as possible in the coming weeks and months."
Mr O'Neill has indicated legislative changes will come before PNG's parliament in May and resettlement could begin soon after.
Mr Abbott, who arrived in Port Moresby earlier this morning for an official state visit and bilateral talks, says Australia and Papua New Guinea share a close relationship.
PNG's role in the Coalition Government's border protection policies is crucial and Mr Abbott says he knows "the course will be stayed".
He says he knows the resettlement of asylum seekers in PNG is a difficult issue for the country, but he appreciates the "mateship" shown to Australia.
"I'm extremely grateful for PNG's renewed commitment today to resettlement," Mr Abbott said.
"I accept that depending upon how many of those at Manus are found to be refugees, I accept that it might be hard for PNG to take all of them.
"But we're grateful for the fact that some of them will be here in PNG and we're continuing to work with other countries in our region to ensure that people don't come to Australia if they arrive illegally by boat.
"This is the bottom line: if you arrive illegally by boat in Australia, you will never permanently settle in Australia because as long as there is this prospect of permanent settlement in Australia, there is the risk that illegal boats will keep coming."
Mr Abbott's visit coincides with the first media tour of the detention centre on Manus Island since it reopened in November 2012.
Several media organisations, including the ABC, will visit the centre today with PNG judge David Cannings.
Recent violence at the detention centre saw one asylum seeker killed and around 70 injured.
Human rights groups have decried the living conditions inside the camp.
New economic treaty with PNG
In addition to the reaffirmation of the asylum seeker agreement, a new economic co-operation treaty has been signed during Mr Abbott's visit to PNG.
Mr O'Neill said the agreement would be the "cornerstone" of business and trade relations between the two countries.
The agreement includes annual leader-level talks.
PNG will host the APEC regional leaders summit in 2018, which Mr Abbott described as a "coming of age" for Australia's neighbour.
"It will demonstrate that PNG is not only a very big player in the Pacific but is increasingly a player in the wider world," Mr Abbott said.
The 16-page agreement recognises the "essential role" of private investment, both domestic and foreign, in fostering growth, creating jobs, expanding trade, improving technology and enhancing economic development.
"Each party shall, subject to its laws and regulations, accord nationals of the other party fair and transparent treatment with respect to matters in connection with their business, immigration and professional activities," the treaty states.
It also sets out new rules governing aid and development cooperation in PNG, including an exemption from income tax for Australian aid organisations.
]]></text></news-item>