<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-9371-DXKS-J16W"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Breitling Energy Wins Award for Excellence in Environmental Stewardship from Oil &amp; Gas Awards Gulf Coast</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Breitling Energy Corporation (OTCBB: BECC) (the "Company") announced it has been named the top honoree by the Oil & Gas Awards, earning the Aggreko Award for Excellence in Environmental Stewardship by an Exploration and Production Company. The award for the Gulf Coast Region was announced at the Awards Gala Dinner in Houston this week.
Also a finalist in the E&P Company of the Year and Corporate Social Responsibility categories, Breitling was recognized for its advances in environmental stewardship and outstanding achievements in the upstream and midstream sectors of the oil and gas industry. 
"We are very proud of the work we're doing at Breitling to minimize the environmental impact of exploration and production activities," said CEO Chris Faulkner. "Through our EnviroFrac(TM) and Social License Initiative programs, we strive provide an industry model for increasing public understanding and acceptance of fracking."
Under Breitling Energy's EnviroFrac program, hydraulic fracturing fluid additives are evaluated and eliminated if they are not critical to successful completion. Essential additives are replaced with food-grade alternatives. EnviroFrac is part of Breitling Energy's Social License Initiative outreach program, created to gain what Breitling calls the "Social License" by educating residents about fracking and sharing operation information through in-person town hall and one-on-one interactions within affected communities.
The company was also awarded in 2013 for E&P Company of the Year by the Oil & Gas Awards for the Southwest Region, named "Best North American Operator" by World Finance Magazine in 2011, 2012 and 2013, and to the "Dallas 100 List" in 2013, ranking fourth among the top 100 companies in the Dallas-Fort Worth area. Faulkner was named Industry Leader of the Year in 2013 by the Oil & Gas Awards for the Southwest Region, Oil Executive of the Year in 2013 by the American Energy Research Group, and recognized in the "Dallas Who's Who in Energy" in 2012 and 2013.
For more information on this and other activities of the Company, see the Breitling Energy Corporation web site athttp://www.breitlingenergy.com.
ABOUT BREITLING ENERGY
Breitling Energy Corporation is an oil and gas exploration and production company that acquires and develops lower-risk onshore oil and gas working interests and royalty interests in proven basins in the United States, such as the Bakken / Three Forks Sanish formations located in North Dakota and the Mississippi Lime and Hunton /Woodford / Cleveland formations located in Oklahoma and Kansas.
FORWARD-LOOKING STATEMENTS
Certain statements in this news release regarding future expectations, access to public capital markets, plans for acquisitions and dispositions, oil and gas reserves, exploration, development, production and pricing may be regarded as "forward-looking statements" within the meaning of the Securities Litigation Reform Act. They are subject to various risks, such as operating hazards, drilling risks, the inherent uncertainties in interpreting engineering data relating to underground accumulations of oil and gas, as well as other risks discussed in detail in the Company's periodic reports and other documents filed with the SEC. Actual results may vary materially.
Any number of factors could cause actual results to differ materially from those in the forward-looking statements, including, but not limited to, the volatility of oil and gas prices, the costs and results of drilling and operations, the timing of production, mechanical and other inherent risks associated with oil and gas production, weather, the availability of drilling equipment, changes in interest rates, litigation, uncertainties about reserve estimates, environmental risks and other risks and uncertainties set forth in Company's periodic reports and other documents filed with the SEC. The Company undertakes no obligation to publicly update or revise any forward-looking statements.
Contacts:
CONTACT: Traci Dakins, Stephenson Group, 253.306.4006INVESTOR RELATIONS CONTACT: Gilbert Steedley, Breitling Energy, 214.716.2060
Read more news fromBreitling Energy Corporation.
SOURCE Breitling Energy Corporation
]]></text></news-item>