<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-WNK1-DXY4-X0FT"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>North Carolina Says Utility Pumped Millions of Gallons of Wastewater in River</title><source>The New York Times</source><author>By MICHAEL WINES</author><text><![CDATA[Duke Energy, the electric utility whose massive spill of toxic coal ash into a river six weeks ago is part of a federal investigation, illegally pumped as much as 61 million gallons of coal-ash wastewater into a second river from September to last week, North Carolina regulators charged on Thursday.
Both the accidental spill and the deliberate releases occurred not far upstream from municipal drinking-water intakes.
The utility's officials have said that the pumping was part of preparations for routine maintenance of two settling ponds that hold ash, the remains of coal burned to generate power.
But regulators cast doubt on that claim on Thursday. ''The state's investigation revealed that the pumping activities ongoing at this plant far exceeded what would reasonably be considered routine maintenance,'' said Tom Reeder, the director of the water resources division at the state Department of Environment and Natural Resources.
A spokeswoman for the water resources division, Susan Massengale, noted that Duke had spent 31 days emptying 17.4 million gallons of water from one ash pond and 78 days releasing 44.4 million more from a second.
Peter Harrison, a lawyer for Waterkeeper Alliance, the New York-based environmental group that first uncovered the pumping, said Duke's explanation was ''absurd.''
''They've essentially simulated a terrible coal-ash spill by pumping the pond out,'' he said.
Duke briefly addressed the releases in a statement on Thursday evening, saying that ''water was being pumped to the existing, permitted outfalls and was being monitored according to the plant permit.'' The statement said Duke notified state officials before beginning pumping.
Both Duke and state regulators already have come under intense criticism for an early February pipe rupture that allowed as much as 82,000 tons of coal-ash slurry to empty into the Dan River just upstream from Danville, Va., a town of 43,000, and four other communities that take water from the stream.
Environmental activists have long asserted that state regulators were lax in their oversight of Duke, and particularly the coal-ash impoundments at 14 plants where the utility generates or once generated power. After the Dan River spill, a federal grand jury opened an inquiry into the relationship between Duke and the state, issuing at least 23 subpoenas so far to utility officials, current or former environmental regulators and the chairman of the State Utilities Commission.
The latest releases, at the decommissioned Cape Fear generating station near Moncure, N.C., were discovered only last week when members of Waterkeeper Alliance and a second group, Cape Fear Riverkeeper, photographed workers at the Cape Fear ash ponds while flying over the plant.
Photographs of one pond showed pumps diverting water into a canal that feeds the Cape Fear River. Waterkeeper officials informed state regulators, who found the pumps turned off when they visited the plant the next day.
Logs kept by the utility later showed that it had begun removing water from one pond last Sept. 30, and from the second pond on Jan. 13.
Since halting the pumping, Duke officials have said that they were lowering the ponds' levels to maintain two vertical pipes that jut above the surface and to reduce or prevent ash from leaking into groundwater. The pipes are essentially drains designed to keep the ash ponds from overflowing should heavy rains raise the water level too high.
The state permit covering the ash ponds allows water to be discharged during maintenance only if the release ''does not cause effluent limits to be violated.'' The permit also requires Duke to regularly sample water releases to gauge the level of pollution, but while the pumping log refers at one point to water samples, any test results that may exist have not been made public.
Releases that violate pollution standards are barred unless the utility has no other alternative, like sending divers into the pond, and conditions at the pond pose an imminent threat to people or property.
Coal-ash wastewater can contain dozens of toxic substances, including arsenic, selenium, lead and mercury.
The state notice of violation delivered to Duke says the utility could be assessed as much as $25,000 for each day that the permit was violated.
http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/21/us/north-carolina-says-utility-pumped-millions-of-gallons-of-ash-waste-in-river.html
]]></text></news-item>