<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-T4D1-J9YR-G3FM"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Qatar World Cup 2022 investigation: Jack Warner Profile; The Fifa kingmaker and ally of Sepp Blatter was forced out by persistent allegations of corruption</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Ben Bryant</author><text><![CDATA[Jack Warner was one of the most controversial members of the Fifa executive committee.
After sitting for 28 years, his duties came to an abrupt end in 2011 after he was embroiled in bribery allegations.
Seen by many as a kingmaker, Mr Warner was a close ally of president Sepp Blatter until he supported Mohamed Bin Hammam's campaign for the presidency.
Warner became president of the Confederation of North, Central American and Caribbean Association Football in 1990. He has also held several government roles in Trinidad and Tobago, including being chairman of the country's UNC party and Minister of National Security.
However, he is best known for his controversial role in Fifa, which he served as vice-president between January 1997 and June 2011. In Dec 2006, Mr Warner was caught selling 180 World Cup tickets for up to three times their face value.
He escaped dismissal and censure from his ally Mr Blatter, who commented at the time: "He should be more prudent and cautious when it comes to ticketing."
Fresh ticket touting allegations surfaced in 2010 as part of an investigation by the BBC's Panorama into alleged bribes paid to three members of Fifa's executive committee by International Sport and Leisure, the sports marketing company.
The programme said it had seen emails and an invoice which showed Mr Warner was involved in the purchase of $84,000 (£50,000) of 2010 World Cup tickets.
On May 10 2011, Lord Triesman, the former FA chairman, accused Mr Warner of asking for bribes in return for votes during England's bid. Mr Warner dismissed the claims and after he vowed to release a "tsunami" of counter-claims against Fifa, the organisation cleared him.
However, new corruption allegations emerged. Footage appeared to show Mr Warner telling members of the Caribbean Football Union to decide whether to accept "gifts" of $40,000 (£25,000) each, and urging them to vote for Mr Bin Hammam in Fifa's presidential elections.
Fifa launched an inquiry and Mr Warner was suspended. Mr Bin Hammam, meanwhile, pulled out of the presidential race, and Mr Blatter was re-elected.
Warner had switched allegiance to Qatar's Mr Bin Hammam during the election. He was later forced to deny that his vote went to Qatar instead of the US in the campaign to host the 2022 World Cup.
Eventually, on June 20 2011, Mr Warner resigned from Fifa and CONCACAF over the Caribbean bribery allegations.
A CONCACAF investigation, which was heavily critical of Mr Warner's tenure at the organisation, was released on April 19 2013. Mr Warner claimed the report was "baseless and malicious".
However, Kamla Persad-Bissessar, the prime minister of Trinidad and Tobago, said she was stunned by its contents, and on April 21 Mr Warner resigned as national security minister, before going on to resign as UNC chairman.
]]></text></news-item>