<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-0FS1-DXH0-K2VY"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>OSCE conference in Astana discusses fight against corruption</title><source>Central Asian News Services</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[An OSCE-supported conference on countering corruption in state institutions started in Astana on March 19.
More than 200 representatives from government institutions, law enforcement agencies and specialized academic and educational establishments from across the country attended the event, organized by the OSCE Centre in Astana in close cooperation with Kazakh Agency for fighting economic and corruption crimes, as well as with the Financial Police Academy.
The conference participants exchanged international best practices on anti-corruption measures and learned about the Swedish experience in preventing and mitigating corruption. Participants examined the relevance of European anti-corruption institutional set-ups and strategic planning for improving the national anti-corruption framework.
"The OSCE pays special attention to involving civil society to the promotion of a zero-tolerance attitude towards corruption," said Natalia Zarudna, Head of the OSCE Centre in Astana. "We do so through educational and training programmes, exchange of best practices for preventing and combating corruption, improvement of political and legal instruments." She stressed the importance of fully utilizing the potential of non-governmental organizations and co-operation between participating States in this field.
General Andrei Lukin, First Deputy Head of the Financial Police Academy, said: "Corruption is a systemic threat to national security. It impedes ongoing economic and social reforms and undermines the country's image on the international arena. An effective anti-corruption strategy should be based on a comprehensive system of administrative, legislative and information measures to be undertaken collectively by government agencies, NGOs, media and the public at large."
The event is part of the OSCE Centre's consistent efforts to support economic security and mitigate organized crime.
]]></text></news-item>