<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-MST1-DYT4-V42P"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>San Ramon Valley letters: Corporate criminals won't stop until forced to</title><source>Contra Costa Times (California)</source><author>Valley Journal</author><text><![CDATA[Business crime will not stop until forced to
Your editorial asking for an attitude change at Tesero understates the case. Attitudes will not change at Tesero unless the executives responsible for the stonewalling and cover-up related to the huge acid spill are arrested and prosecuted for the crime.
Similarly executives at General Motors who decided to hide a stall problem related to "too-heavy ignition key rings" can continue to commit premeditated murder with impunity. Executives at Chevron who decided not to replace the pipes at the Richmond refinery deserve to explain their actions in criminal court. Freedom Industries executives who sold the company a few weeks before the tanks leaked and contaminated the water supply for 300,000 West Virginians should face criminal charges. PG&E executives who decided they could not afford to properly maintain the San Bruno pipelines but had millions to spend on a stealth ballot measure to maintain their monopoly, should be charged with Murder One, as should culpable public servants at the Public Utilities Commission who let PG&E perpetrate the crime.
Sending a few executives to jail would deter others who do not want to join them from future criminal activities. Most of the people who work for the corporations mentioned are honest and have nothing to hide; they deserve better than executives who bring shame and dishonor to their organization. Most corporations are run honestly and put public safety before corporate profits; they too should be outraged that a few executives make the honest ones look bad. The public should not be satisfied with fines that turn into tax write-offs, are considered the cost of doing business and with executives who are rewarded with huge bonuses instead of jail time.
Ellis Goldberg
Danville
Vote out most members on BART board
No doubt many were as dismayed as I was to read the Times article reporting on the BART board meeting at which Board President Joel Keller presented his advisory measure aimed at preventing future strikes by BART employees.
The excuses of the board members for opposing this initiative were moronic. It is clear that a majority of the BART board are inmates running the asylum. But then, Tom Barnidge devoted today's column to pointing all this out. Kudos to Tom Barnidge! We need to throw the BART board rascals out, and elect board members who will represent the public who elected them and not represent the union bosses who contribute their members' dues money to BART election campaigns.
Rich Van Tassell
San Ramon
Freedom fast becoming rare commodity
It appears that every day I read the paper, watch the TV news or listen to the radio some bans on a legal product or conduct or some tax is being placed on the purchasing consumer. These range from food items, beverages, content, speech and numerous areas of daily activities us people engage in.
All from the federal, state and local level, unelected and elected persons are by fiat instituting laws that "we the people" never voted for or against. Where do they get this power? Neither the U.S. Constitution nor state constitutions grant this type of authority or legislation.
We are banned from consuming certain oils and foods, beverages with sugar, drinking water in plastic bottles, viewing controversial images on the news and films, teaching our children aspects of American history, placing religious symbols on private property, donning the American flag, honoring our veterans, the vehicles we drive and engaging in free speech whether it is spoken or printed.
There is no war on men or women. It appears to be a war on American ideals and freedoms. True freedom involves the individual right to make the right or wrong decisions and to deal with consequences -- good or bad.
The more we allow the government to abridge our private freedoms, the worse it becomes for our individual privacy and choices, civil rights, free speech and the collective interests.
Lisa Trapani
San Ramon
Tell the whole truth on guns, not just parts
If you want to spout statistics from articles that one reads on the Internet or in the news, make sure you include all the information contained therein, especially if one parrots. Allow me: yes, gun-related crimes have decreased by 56 percent. What one fails to mention is that gun-related crime has dropped across the nation as a whole. Other states that allow their citizens to own firearms and carry them on their persons whether concealed or not make the would be perpetrator think twice.
Have you seen the news? The sideshows in Oakland with the police just turning around for "safety" reasons. Yes, why endanger your life doing what you're sworn to do? That's rhetorical. All the shootings on the freeway. In the homes? All over the nation. Let's put other facts along with your statements so they can be well rounded. List all the data regarding "gun control."
Gun laws have only enabled the criminal to rob, murder and harm the public because we are not allowed to defend ourselves from the criminal that did not do a background check and the such to acquire the object used in the commission of that crime. We are made to be the criminal(s).
So please, do spout your opinion -- I am. But do include all the facts. Have you not looked at history? We are the same people with the same fears, wants, desires and hopes. There will always be those who want to take that. There's a blurred line between the "Gestapo" and the street criminal. Read between the lines sometimes. It's enlightening.
Michael Greene
Pleasanton
Memo to Lee: GOP doesn't run California
In response to U.S. Rep. Barbara Lee's editorial on March 9: Eldritch Cleaver, Martin Luther King, Jackie Robinson, Karl Malone, Dr. Ben Carson, Allen West, Princella Smith, Armstrong Williams, Angela Mcglowan, Condoleezza Rice, Lyn Swan, Don King, Jimmy Walker, Michael Steele. Colin Powell, Ward Connerly, Alan Keys, Richard Parsons and Clarence Thomas, to name a few black Republicans, must at present be wondering how it is that in a state that is more than 90 percent Democrat-led, a Democrat Congress member can blame Republicans for the plight of young black men in Oakland and other cities. I'm confused myself, unless in her editorial Rep. Lee meant white Republicans.
One would think that if someone were as concerned about young black men in Oakland, one would do something about it instead of blame the other guy who has no power to do anything anyway? Isn't it remarkable that one of Obama's biggest fans emulates him in every way; to include blaming someone else for the job they are NOT doing themselves?
Education, which includes learning the difference between right and wrong, begins at home, Rep. Lee. It is the parents' responsibility to guide the children, not the Republican Party's. And thank God it is also not the job of the Democrats.
Lord, do we ever need to clean house this election. Crying "racism" seems to be every one's crutch lately. Why don't you do something!
Michael K. Hurder
Livermore
]]></text></news-item>