<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-F081-JCBF-2492"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Biloxi attorney admits fraud, owes $7.7 million</title><source>The Biloxi Sun Herald (Mississippi)</source><author> ROBIN FITZGERALD; rfitzgerald@sunherald.com</author><text><![CDATA[GULFPORT -- A Biloxi attorney and businessman has admitted defrauding two banks and the U.S. Bankruptcy Court and has been told the government expects him to make restitution of more than $7.7 million.
Stephen Richard Colson, 48, pleaded guilty Wednesday to falsifying, concealing and covering up material facts in his business and legal dealings.
His sentencing is set for June 2 before U.S. District Judge Sul Ozerden. Aside from restitution, he faces up to five years in prison and a $250,000 fine.
Colson is free on an unsecured $25,000 bond.
The U.S. Attorney's Office charged him following an investigation by the FBI.
Colson is a settlement agent and closing attorney who owned Prestige Title Inc. and Advanced Title and Escrow. The businesses have headquarters in Biloxi and offices elsewhere in Mississippi and in Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Louisiana and Texas.
He also was an escrow agent for South Mississippi condominium developments.
As a settlement agent, he was required to set up trust accounts to disburse money from individual loans.
A federal probe revealed he took money from trust accounts and concealed the shortages in those accounts by co-mingling money from other accounts when he made payments to financial institutions, officials said in a press release from the FBI and U.S. Attorney's Office.
Officials said the scheme began in summer 2004 when Colson obtained a mortgage loan and used property titled in his name as collateral.
Colson issued a loan policy on that mortgage and later sold the property for cash but did not advise the bank that held the lien, the charging document said.
Documents show he continued to make the mortgage payment until the sale was discovered when he filed for bankruptcy in September 2009. He had sold the property for cash Sept. 15, 2005.
A title insurance company paid $133,600 to settle the claim.
Officials said Colson pleaded guilty to a larger scheme of using money from new real estate closings to pay off earlier closings.
He had served as the agent of a title insurance company that later changed hands, and an audit revealed his title companies had a shortage in money for settling real estate closings.
Officials said the title insurance company that took over was forced to pay 54 claims from lenders, borrowers and sellers, and won a claim against him in Bankruptcy Court. Its claim of $4.9 million, plus attorneys' fees and costs of litigation, are Colson's responsibility, officials said.
The Bankruptcy Court also determined the use of his trust account "was akin to a Ponzi scheme."
In a separate proceeding, the Bankruptcy Court denied his attempt to be released from a private investor's $2 million claim.
]]></text></news-item>