<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-0SF1-JDV5-F3SM"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Science on climate change unsettled</title><source>The Hamilton Spectator (Ontario, Canada)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Regarding Don McLean's piece on the National Energy Board's Line 9 decision, free speech is the foundation of democracy and we should cherish it. McLean is entitled to his opinions. The climate change conundrum is going to remain that way unless both sides listen to each other and acknowledge facts and other opinions regarding science. Using the Line 9 pipe as a lead-in to climate change is a cute tactic. But the theory of the cause and effect of burning fossil fuels, thus generating carbon dioxide thus warming the planet (now referred to as climate change) is getting weaker by the day.
The writer states: "The science is beyond doubt." This is simply not the case. Climate change science, once known as global warming science, is far from settled. The MET office, Britain's official weather office, has admitted that statistically "global warming" has stopped since 1997. Even the United Nations infamous IPCC in its latest report admits that warming has stopped, but implies that it is only a long-term pause. The UN IPCC is just a clearing house for scientific papers that validate its agenda. The IPCC often ignores any skeptical papers and name calls them "deniers." Recently, researcher Qing-Bin Lu at the University of Waterloo published a research paper in the International Journal of Modern Physics that postulated that chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs) are to blame for global warming since the 1970s and not carbon dioxide. Also, NASA's latest satellites have evidence showing the "sun's energy influences 1,000 years of natural climate variability in the North Atlantic." How can any rational person say that climate change science and/or global warming science and its causes are settled?
Recently we had Gideon Forman, executive director of the Canadian Association of Physicians for the Environment, weighing in on Ontario getting out of coal-generated electricity as a positive thing. Meanwhile, the U.S. is exporting coal at a record-breaking pace. So it is good for Ontario to walk and talk proud and not be like those Americans (tongue in cheek). It's also OK for President Barack Obama to drag his feet on the XL pipeline to appease the Hollywood enviro crowd by not approving a pipeline that is insignificant compared to the thousands of miles of pipelines that criss-cross the U.S.
It is simplistic and erroneous for the writer to state the economies of Ontario and Quebec have been damaged because of Canada exporting fossil fuel. The two economies are in dire straits because of a decade of mismanagement by provincial leaders.
Modern-day Western democracies are not addicted to oil. We need oil until we discover an alternative energy source. People become addicted to heroin, not oil. Using over-the-top metaphors to make a point serves no purpose.
Looking at the few suggestions the writer makes for change at the local level, we have:
Do not invest in oil or gas companies: We need oil to survive in Canada's cold climate and to power us around this vast country. If the oil companies are dramatically diminished, the federal government's revenues derived from oil will also be diminished. Thus services from Ottawa would have to be cut. That is not a pretty picture.
Oppose rubber stamping approvals: Read the report. The Line 9 approval was far from being rubber stamped.
Invest in alternative transportation: An $800-million-plus light rail is not going to pull Hamilton out of the economic doldrums. Hamiltonians need well-paying, full-time, meaningful jobs. Bike lanes are not the solution in a cold winter climate and they are an insignificant mode of transportation for moving people around Hamilton.
Reduce impermeable paved roads: If the Hamilton storm and sewer system was up to snuff, impermeable roads would not be an issue. Hamilton cannot even afford to fix the current potholes on its roads, let alone rip up parking lots and existing roads.
Obtain municipal electricity from renewable sources: Windmills, garbage incineration, solar? Fine, if it is affordable.
Freeze urban boundary expansion and reuse brownfields to protect local agricultural lands: This is a good and practical idea. But first, City Hall must become a lot more efficient in its zoning wars and court battles. City Hall cannot even seem to evict polluting landlords let alone let the Red Hill Parkway court case die a natural death.
So let's get those problems solved first. Then we can worry about saving the planet for our children (and their children) - which we are not having in droves.
]]></text></news-item>