<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-D271-JCRR-03D3"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Californians for Population Stabilization Says All of California's Population Growth Results from Immigration</title><source>Professional Services Close-Up</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[An analysis of Census Bureau and California statistics reveals that all of California's population growth results from foreign immigration.
According to a release, the demographic data-births, deaths, immigration, and interstate migration-reveals that foreign immigration, immigrants and their offspring, accounted for all of the state's growth from 2000 to 2010.
"This population growth is extremely destructive to the environment," said Jo Wideman, executive director of Californians for Population Stabilization (CAPS). "An increase in the human population results in more pollution and a greater strain on our limited resources. The current drought should remind us that we have exceeded the carrying capacity of our natural environment."
"From 2000 to today, the state has added 4.5 million people, the same as the entire population of New Zealand. That's a scary number for those of us who think we should save some space for the non-human critters in this wonderful land."
The analysis from CAPS examines Census information and data from California's Department of Public Health and Department of Finance. While in decades past, interstate migration contributed heavily to the state's growth, between 2000 and 2010 there was a net outflow from domestic migration. All of California's population growth of 3.4 million in the decade resulted from foreign immigrants and their offspring.
The increasing human population inevitably displaces other species. "Habitat loss is the leading threat to wildlife populations in California," according to the state's Department of Fish and Wildlife. There are over 300 animal and plant species designated as endangered, threatened, or rare in California.
The immigration bill passed by the Senate would effect a huge increase in immigration and population growth. The Congressional Budget Office said it would in 20 years increase the U.S. population by an additional 16 million beyond previous projections.
"If we want to save some of the biodiversity of this once-bountiful land, we must decrease population growth and decrease immigration," said Wideman.
((Comments on this story may be sent to newsdesk@closeupmedia.com))
]]></text></news-item>