<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-SP81-JCT2-K4PK"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Coalition mounts anti-shale tour of N.B</title><source>The Daily Gleaner (New Brunswick)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A new coalition of community groups and labour unions has formed the largest concerted effort to date in opposition to shale gas development and hydraulic fracturing in New Brunswick.
The group, which includes the New Brunswick Anti-Shale Gas Alliance - representing 22 community groups - the Council of Canadians, Unifor, and the Fredericton District Labour Council, has announced plans to visit every corner of the province to provide "public education about shale gas, clean jobs, and clean energy."
The Voice of the People Tour has 19 stops across New Brunswick already scheduled.
At least another seven others are in the works.
The coalition is also supported in the initiative by the Canadian Union of Public Employees, the New Brunswick Federation of Labour, the National Farmers Union, Green Party Leader David Coon and the province's conservation council.
"We will be asking the people in our communities several questions," said Jim Emberger, a spokesman for the anti-shale gas alliance.
"Do we know everything we need to know about shale gas? Is shale gas the only way to create jobs? What do you in your backyard?
"Over the past four years, there's been little or no public consultations or meetings initiated by the government or the industry, so people are organizing themselves."
He added: "In addition, the government of New Brunswick has failed to provide the public with peer-reviewed scientific evidence of the harmful effects of shale gas fracking and shale gas development. The people are not getting in the information that they need."
Premier David Alward stated in his state of the province address earlier this year that the province must take advantage of resource development on all fronts, taking shots at his critics who prefer to wait, stating that he didn't sign up for this job to "stand still and press pause."
"The decision before us is simple: do we listen to those who say 'no' to the very same opportunities that have created the strongest economies in North America, or do we finally say 'yes'?"
Alward said. "I am saying 'yes' to the development of domestic natural gas and 'yes' to the opportunities that will bring our people home, provide them with good jobs, and help us build a better tomorrow for our province.
"From where we stand, the cost of not moving forward on these initiatives is simply too great."
A study by auditing firm Deloitte states that each new shale gas well in New Brunswick will generate about $13 million in economic spinoffs and create roughly the equivalent of 21 full-time jobs, requiring 206 different skill sets over its life cycle.
Each well will also grow the province's gross domestic product by $9 million, according to the report.
The government has released rules to police the industry.
The New Brunswick Energy Institute also recently announced plans to spend more than $500,000 on research looking at well water quality in areas where industry wants to develop shale gas.
Emberger said the town hall-style meetings will provide an overview of scientific evidence on the effects of shale gas, specifically hydraulic fracturing.
He said a long-term health study from the University of Colorado's school of public health completed roughly two years ago will be presented. Newer studies from the University of Missouri and Colorado underscoring health impacts will also be reviewed.
Alternatives to the industry will also be brainstormed, namely clean energy initiatives.
Emberger cites a report by environmental alliance Blue Green Canada that states for the same investment there are seven times as many jobs with clean energy and building efficiency than there is with the oil and gas industry.
"We want to talk about economic development," said Jean Louis Deveau, chair of the Fredericton chapter of the Council of Canadians.
"Our premier is focused on the dig it out, cut it down and ship it out economy.
"We think there are all kinds of opportunities in clean energy that we haven't even started to talk about."
Grassroots groups say the consolidated effort against shale gas will ensure they are better heard.
"There are community organizations, but they weren't united with a strategic plan and an approach to dealing with both the industry and the government on this issue," said Water and Environmental Protection for Albert County spokesperson Roy Ries.
A first stop is scheduled for Fredericton on March 24.
]]></text></news-item>