<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-M1K1-JD6S-R2MD"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Fake guide dogs jeopardize legitimate rights</title><source>Rutland Herald: Blogs (Vermont)</source><author>Patty Minichiello</author><text><![CDATA[Photo & Story by Peter Crabtree
Eric Caron and his new guide dog, Ryan, recently ran into trouble with another dog whose owner was passing it off as a service animal.
Only an hour earlier, Eric Caron had said goodbye to Mae, his service dog of six years, as she was put down at the West Mountain Animal Hospital in Bennington.
Then, with his new guide dog, Ryan, leading the way, Caron went to the local CVS to do some shopping.
He would leave empty handed.
Caron, who is blind, encountered a barking, lunging dog that would not let him pass in the drugstore aisle. The animal was wearing a vest identifying it as a service dog. Only, Caron said, it was a fraud.
It was not the first time Caron had encountered a fake service dog in Vermont. And he is not alone nationwide, with states as far afield as California and Hawaii holding hearings and considering laws to curb the practice.
As the use of service dogs has expanded through the years - veterans with post-traumatic stress disorder and autistic children are among those who find the animals useful - so has the number of people who abuse the privileges accorded legitimate guide dogs and their handlers, report advocates for the disabled.
Their motives may include excessive devotion to their pets and, in the same way that some able-bodied drivers park in handicapped spaces, a sense of entitlement, critics say.
The problem leaves Caron deeply frustrated.
"Disabled people with skilled service dogs end up being denied service or are unable to enter a business because a fraudulent uncontrolled dog is already there," Caron said.
The 48-year-old guidance counselor at Mount Anthony Union High School in Bennington credits the three yellow Labradors that have served him since 1997 with giving him the freedom to live a full and satisfying life. They have, for example, helped him briskly navigate the halls of one of Vermont's largest high schools and led him up the stairs of the Eiffel Tower in Paris.
But fake service dogs, such as the one he encountered at CVS last month, threaten to rob him of his freedom, Caron said. He has come across them at the local Price Chopper, a Stewart's convenience store and a few years back, the Chelsea Royal Diner in Brattleboro, one of Caron's favorite spots.
Caron said an anxious waitress was reluctant to seat him. "She told me, 'I know your dog is great, but there is another dog here that I don't feel will be OK when you come in.'"
Eventually, the waitress found a way to sneak Caron and Mae "to a distant table far from where I would normally have enjoyed dinner," he said.
Beyond the personal inconvenience, Caron said he worried that continued abuses could roll back societal gains made by the disabled. Guide dogs have opened doors to jobs and business that once were closed.
But those doors "are likely to be opened less warmly and widely because of the abuses of people entering with vest-wearing pets demanding they be treated the same as real service dogs," he said.
The root of the problem, said Becky Barnes Davidson of Guiding Eyes for the Blind in Yorktown Heights, N.Y., is "a general attitude of entitlement" among Americans.
"People want to bring their pets with them and those who insist on doing that ... will stop at nothing, including buying equipment on line and trying to pass their pets off as a service dog," she said.
"The fact that (guide dog) harnesses are readily available online is appalling to those of who us have been through training and need these dogs," Davidson said.
Guiding Eyes for the Blind is part of the International Guide Dog Federation, which accredits and assesses its 80 member organizations. Although requiring guide dogs to be accredited might cut down on the prevalence of fake service dogs, the Americans with Disabilities Act contains no such mandate, Davidson said.
And forcing the legitimately disabled to produce proof of a dog's service pedigree would result in "a lot of pushback," said Davidson, the manager of consumer outreach and graduate support at Guiding Eyes for the Blind. Even if certificates were required, "it's just as easy to fake that as anything else," Davidson said.
Yet when it comes to a dog's behavior, it shouldn't be hard to distinguish the real from the fake, advocates say.
Guide dogs are bred for temperament and they undergo extensive training. That means they typically won't bark or lunge or make a general nuisance of themselves in public.
And while any dog might conceivably serve as a guide, German shepherds, Labrador retrievers and golden retrievers are the most commonly trained breeds.
When confronted with the barking dog at CVS, Caron asked questions of its owner that anyone may ask without fear of violating anti-discrimination laws: Is this a service dog? Who does it work for? What life function does it perform?
Yet Caron's questions were met with silence. Until, that is, an angry male voice responded, "What business is it of yours, anyway?"
Caron contends it is every citizen's right and responsibility to ask such questions, because any service animal - real or not - must be under the control of its handler. If not, the business owner or manager can ask them to leave the premises.
As for Davidson, she doesn't hold out much hope for a legal solution to the problem. Instead, she suggested that an "intensive public education campaign" might heighten awareness.
"I think the practice of passing off pets as service dogs is unethical," she said. "But there's very little you can do ... without damaging the rights of those of us who do have legitimate service dogs."
Beyond that, Davidson had a few words of caution for those who envy the disabled their right to be accompanied by service dogs.
"Be careful what you wish for," she said. "Do you want to be blind?"
]]></text></news-item>