<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-5TW1-JD3N-52PH"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Letters to the editor</title><source>Sydney MX (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Lotto luck with daily commute
There are two ways I try to earn money. One is going to work and the other is trying to win Tattslotto. I spend about the same weekly on my lotto ticket as I do daily on public transport, except that the lotto draw happens on time without fail. So, given the choice between going to work by train, or staying home and trying my luck in the lottery, I know which one is a lot easier to do.
Noel SCARED SICK: On Wednesday, I saw a young man on the train suddenly vomiting all over himself and on the floor. A man helped him off, but I'm concerned for his wellbeing and the possibility he had a highly contagious illness.
Terrified VILE SPORT: I was disgusted at the story about a decapitated goat being used as a ball in a traditional sport in Kyrgyzstan (mX, Wed). This could glorify animal cruelty.
Rebecca JAGGER BOMB: Mick Jagger (mX, Wed) has given the world a great rock star and some awesome tunes. He doesn't "need to give" anyone any private information to fill the gaps in their knowledge about his dead girlfriend.
Dani ANOTHER WORLD: Wilo (mX, Wed), try seeing what others see in our amazing city and you won't be such a "dead head" yourself. We live in a beautiful city. Soak it in while you can.
Open your eyes BACK TO ME: To the lovely person who found a wallet on the train on St Patrick's Day and returned it to my mailbox. You are a beautiful person.
So cool LOOK DAGGERS: Seriously (mX, Wed), how would you expect people to judge someone's character on Here's looking when they don't know the person yet? "I can see his dazzling personality bursting out of his body!" Is that what you want?
Sarcasm FOX POP: Is fox hunting legal in Australia?
Onewhonotices GRUMP TRUMP: Am I just a grump (mX, Wed), yeah, pretty much. I love hearing anything semi-personal from announcers. It helps to humanise our passionless, depressingly ritualistic, daily commutes which, frankly, lack any kind of humanity at all sometimes.
Whereisthelove IT NEVER CHANGES: Every time I've been to the shop by my station, you've given me less than the correct change.
Verycrossstudent LIB SERVICE: It was clear on the weekend everyone hated the pain that is coming to Australia. It's a riot watching the ICAC scandal unfold. When Labor gets caught with its fingers in the till, it's corruption, when the Liberals do, it's just doing business.
March on FOUL MOUTHS OF BABES: Shame on the parents of kids with signs and shirts saying "F… Abbott". Shows the types of people who oppose our elected government.
Glorenz WOE WOAH: Our Great Barrier Reef is about to have mud dredged all over it, Tasmania's World Heritage forest is to be cut down in size, jobs are being cut, people will be arrested for protesting and we're capturing, indefinitely detaining and torturing people in a country that isn't our own in the false assertion the mothers, dads, sons and daughters are terrorists due to skin colour.
Utter despair MEAN'S TESTED: To all those who use this to moan constantly, I don't give one stuff about your opinion of me or my habits. Disapprove, judge, I don't care. You and your thoughts mean nothing to me.
Misanthropic jerk TRADIE SHOVES A LADY: Offered my seat to an old lady, but a tradie stole the seat. I'm not even mad. Quite impressed at his catlike quickness.
NoSeats4Oldies BEG AND STEAL: Thief is brilliant as a stand-alone game.
Stealth mode OFFICE ROCKER: Do something productive (mX, Wed), it is completely unfair to say someone's job is less stressful because they work in an office. Everyone faces challenges.
Hardworkingnurse JUST DESERTS: I find it absurd so much money is spent on space exploration in the hope a planet suitable for human habitation will be found. Why not spend it making the deserts of Earth habitable?
Luna Ticks SHUT IT: To the guy who didn't stop talking on the train last Thursday. When your mate is reading and grunting, it's time to look out the window.
BreatheLess BUDDY RIDICULOUS: Eyeball away (mX, Wed), just WTF is a "schmuck"? And we don't use the word "buddy" in this country. Learn the lingo mate.
DoubleDutch STATING YOUR CASE: Publicschoolsrock (mX, Mon), my children go to a state school, which is an accredited international school, has a selective entry stream and is accredited to teach the International Baccalaureate.
GoStateSystem CLASS IS HALF FOOL: MGSWethebest (mX, Wed), your opinion reinforces opinions about privately educated folk. Money will never buy you class.
Private hell ESCALATE THE ROW: Rules (mX, Mon), escalators were not designed to let people move faster. They have a higher than standard step height, which is why they are barricaded when out of service.
PleasekeepmovingSMS 'VENT' and your message and name to 1999 9906. Texts cost 55c per 160 characters inc. GST. SMS support: 1300 737 728. Tweet @mxsydney or email sydtalk@mxnet.com.au
]]></text></news-item>