<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-YB01-DXH2-61JK"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>U.S. and Others Search for Flight 370 Debris in Indian Ocean</title><source>Fox News Network</source><author>Sean Hannity, Jennifer Griffin, Lt. Gen. Thomas McInerney</author><text><![CDATA[SEAN HANNITY, HOST: And welcome to "Hannity." And this is a "FOX News Alert." It is now day 13 of the greatest aviation mystery in history. Now, late last night, investigators found what they believe was their, quote, "best leads yet." Now, it came in the form of two objects spotted via satellite 1,500 miles off the coast of Australia.
Now, sadly, bad weather and the dark of night obstructed the initial search for the potential debris fields. Now, that is until now because at this hour, it is morning in the area where the objects are believed to be floating, and weather conditions are said to be much more favorable tonight.
And joining us now to tell us much more about this frantic search, live, from Perth, Australia, Sky News's Cameron Price. Cameron, welcome. Thank you.
CAMERON PRICE, SKY NEWS AUSTRALIA: Sean, the good news is, as you mentioned, the weather. The sun is out today making the search for the crews a lot easier. There was a lot of low-level cloud and rain around yesterday hampering efforts. Very different story today, seas not quite as -- not as large swells as what search crews had to deal with yesterday.
So it has resumed in earnest. The first of the five aircraft that will be searching that massive area of the southern Indian Ocean should be arriving in the next 10 to 15 minutes. The first aircraft is an RAAF Orion, an Australian air force plane. There are four others, including a U.S. Poseidon plane, that will be moving towards the search area over the next few hours to go through in a criss-cross pattern, trying to locate any sign of these objects that were picked up by an Australian satellite some four days ago.
Experts say, though, that those objects, possibly the debris field from the missing Malaysian airliner, could be up to 60 miles from where they spotted them because of the strong currents in the area. But the improved weather conditions are meaning that crews are able to get on with the search and are hopeful of an outcome over the next 24 to 48 hours -- Sean.
HANNITY: Cameron, good day to you, my friend. And thank you for joining us, 10:00 AM local time there.
Joining me now from Washington with the very latest on the investigation, FOX's own Jennifer Griffin tonight. Jennifer, welcome to the program.
JENNIFER GRIFFIN, FOX CORRESPONDENT: Thank you, Sean. Well, more evidence that the Malaysians sat on key leads in the initial days that may have delayed the search for flight 370. The British satellite company Inmarsat told Megyn Kelly just moments ago that it had evidence that the plane may have crashed in the Indian Ocean two days after it disappeared and shared it with the Malaysians on March 12th, who didn't acknowledge the information for three more days.
Commercial satellite companies are playing a huge role in the search. Not long ago, Digital Globe in Colorado released this new map and imagery, which gives us a more refined location of the possible wreckage off -- 1,500 miles from Australia. It comes from its World View 2 satellite. It gives us exact GPS coordinates for the images of what some say look like debris. Those images are from March 16th.
Digital Globe says the Australian government began combing through satellite photos in recent days and came up with this possible lead. Amidst the criticism that the U.S. military isn't doing more to help with the search, the Pentagon suggests they are using some assets we cannot see.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
REAR ADMIRAL JOHN KIRBY, PENTAGON PRESS SECRETARY: ... wouldn't get into the specifics of each and every one of those tools because, you know, some of those tools we don't talk about.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
GRIFFIN: Meanwhile, we've learned the U.S. Navy will be relying on its P-8 Poseidon again tonight. It is expected to be over the search field in the coming hours, and will remain for three hours, from 4:00 AM to 7:00 AM Eastern time. The U.S. Navy's P-3 Orion will not be flying today and is undergoing routine maintenance. The Navy says the nearest U.S. Navy ship is thousands of miles away and would take days to get there, if ordered.
The search is now being focused 1,500 miles off the coast of Australia, Sean, halfway between Australia and the Antarctic. That's how far away it is right now.
HANNITY: All right, Jennifer, great reporting. Thank so much for being with us. And joining us now to talk more about the role weather conditions are going to play in the search efforts, chief meteorologist, our friend from Weatherbell.com, Joe Bastardi is with us.
Joe, one thing that I thought of -- and I know there are big swells there, but every time we get on an airplane, aren't we told about our seats being flotation devices? Wouldn't they be floating at this point?
JOE BASTARDI, CHIEF METEOROLOGIST, WEATHERBELL.COM: Well, it's been a long time since this crash. And keep in mind that there's been a lot of variance in the weather conditions over the last 10, 12 days in the area where we suspect the crash to be.
So where could they possibly be? I mean, if you've had a couple of big storms going through there -- you got to remember that that area of the ocean is the equivalent of the north Atlantic and north Pacific, where you get these fantastic storms that go through with very high winds. And the wind blows out of the southwest and then shifts into the northeast right after. It could be almost anywhere right now, given how long that this has occurred.
HANNITY: Yes. Joe, let me ask you this. What are the weather conditions normally like there? I know we're told -- we just checked in with Australia. They say they're a little bit better. But from what I understand and people that I've spoken to and things I've been reading all day is usually, the swells are really, really, bad, really high. That makes, obviously, any search more difficult.
What can you tell us about the usual weather conditions?
BASTARDI: Well, usually, things get bad in their wintertime, and of course, now, they're the equivalent of where we'd be in September here in the northern hemisphere. So they're not quite as bad as what they get to be -- let's say, when we get to June or July in our months, things get very, very bad down there. There are a lot of big storms that go through. But in just checking, what we -- we have a wave watch chart. In other words, we can look at how high these wave are going to be over the next 8 to 10 days. There doesn't seem to be anything that is too outstanding coming at that general area right now...
HANNITY: How high, Joe?
BASTARDI: ... big 20 to -- well, the -- eight to twelve-foot waves, at the worst, and most of them between four and eight feet. But further south, you get these -- you know, you get 30, 40-foot swells down there off the north coast of Antarctica.
So right now, it's not nearly as bad as what it can be. But let's again keep in mind, this has been out there for 10, 12 days. It's -- who knows where it actually is winding up right now, given what's gone through there.
HANNITY: Eight to ten is still pretty big, though. I mean, I've spent enough time out on the ocean...
BASTARDI: Well, it is. It is. But for that area -- now, you're looking, relative to normal, let's say, that's what happens down there at that far south of latitude. It's like being up near 45, 50 north in the north Atlantic, you're going to get that type of thing. But we've had search and rescue operations in worse situations in the north Atlantic and north Pacific. So it's the variance of the weather, the back and forth of the weather that gets really tricky in there.
HANNITY: All right, Joe Bastardi, thanks so much for being with us, Weatherbell.com.
And joining me now with reaction are satellite imagery analyst from Globalsecurity.org Tim Brown, and retired P3-C mission commander Rick Burgess. Gentlemen, welcome to the program. Thanks for being with us.
Tim, let's talk about your site and the role that it's been playing here, and apparently, fairly pivotal and accurate. Tell us.
TIM BROWN, SATELLITE IMAGERY ANALYST: Well, the satellite imagery is -- the Australians caveat it as possible. They said "possible" several times, including the prime minister. So what that means is the imagery shows that there's possibly something there, but -- it's enough to send aircraft to do surveillance (INAUDIBLE) to make the case. They'll probably have to go back and research it and send more satellite imagery to see if there's anything there, if the storms haven't sunken whatever was floating.
HANNITY: All right, tell us about the process of downloading these images. Apparently, it takes time. And why the delay?
BROWN: Well, it takes -- first of all, the -- it comes off of satellite. Then it's bounced from another satellite to the ground station. Then it's processed. Then it's sent to the Australians. The Australians look at it by hand, by manually. And then it goes up the food chain until, finally, somebody decides it's worth -- there's something worth looking at. And then the politicians decide whether they're going to have a press conference or not. They slap a logo on it, and then they say "possibly."
HANNITY: Let me ask you one other question because you know a lot about satellites, too. One of the things that has amazed me in this entire process, now 13 days into this whole thing, is the fact that 777s don't go missing, that, you know, we live in an age that if you want to put a satellite GPS system in your car, you can pinpoint the location of that car, the speed of that car, in exact time, where that car is.
How did we lose a 777, a Boeing 777?
BROWN: Well, this is what I call the Diller (ph) factor. Basically, yes, you have Onstar for your car. We have GPS. But airplanes can go down in the middle of the south Indian Ocean, and they're not -- they're hard to find, especially if the guy turns off the transponder and he's in on it.
HANNITY: OK.
BROWN: So it's possible.
HANNITY: All right.
BROWN: That's why we're looking for it.
HANNITY: Rick, let's bring you into this. Let me get your thoughts on where we are with the investigation at this point. And any idea about how they go about the search? I would think even with eight to ten-foot swells, that that's difficult to do via the sea. So I assume it's going to be a lot of air flight.
RICK BURGESS, RETIRED P3-C MISSION COMMANDER: That's right. The patrol planes that they have in the theater there participating in the search, they're going to have a tough job because of the sea state. It's difficult to see an object that is not protruding above the water when you have whitecaps and the waves breaking over. And so it's a tough job visually and even also for the radar, as well.
HANNITY: Tell us more about the investigation, where you think it goes from here. And would it be possible, do you think, at this late date for this -- for us to find this debris?
BURGESS: Well, it's -- I think there's a good chance they'll relocate it by the mission planners as they calculate the currents, starting from where the satellite imagery detected the objects in the water. They'll be able to calculate approximately in which direction it traveled, as long as they have good hydrographic information on the currents. And they'll be able to plan a search pattern that, hopefully, will bring them into contact with the debris.
HANNITY: All right, we all got to hope and pray that -- well, we get some answers to this. Certainly, these families are dying to get it. Gentlemen, thank you both for being with us tonight.
And coming up on this breaking news edition of "Hannity," former military pilot Michael Kay is here and he's going to explain in detail just how and where investigators are searching for the missing jet.
Also tonight on "Hannity," coming up...
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
LT. GEN. THOMAS MCINERNEY, U.S. AIR FORCE (RET.), FOX MILITARY ANALYST: The only thing that I have seen that is starting to become verified is the LIGNET report that -- from Boeing saying that they believe the airplane was in Pakistan.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
HANNITY: Does Lieutenant General McInerney -- does he still stand by his analysis?
And then we'll also be heading over to the big board. We're show you possibilities about the exact locations where we're searching for this plane, this jet, tonight off the coast of Australia, as this breaking news edition of "Hannity" continues. Thanks for being with us.
HANNITY: This is a "FOX News Alert." As the search intensifies for the missing Malaysian jet, investigators are now focusing on an area 1,500 miles off the coast of Australia. Joining me now here at the big board to explain is the former adviser to the U.K. defense ministry, Michael Kay. Michael, thanks for being with us. Appreciate it, my friend.
MICHAEL KAY, FMR. ADVISER TO U.K. MINISTRY OF DEFENSE: Good to see you.
HANNITY: All right, now, 1,500 miles -- we're talking about a big distance. We just got the weather report, big swells, maybe eight to ten feet, makes it difficult by sea. Tell us what you think.
KAY: Yes, I mean, we've got basically just enough information here to create the basis for a search, but we don't have enough information to -- have empirical evidence to link this to Malaysian...
HANNITY: Right.
KAY: ... 370. So clearly, that involves a huge search. And the Australians are putting on an amazing effort at the moment. They're using P-3 Orion aircraft. That's a four-engine turboprop aircraft.
HANNITY: Right.
KAY: Travels at about 240 knots. That's about four miles a minute. Problem is, it's only got 13 hours endurance. That may sound a lot, however, this...
(CROSSTALK)
KAY: This here is a five-hour leg, five-hour leg back, that's 10 hours off. You got three hours on loiter. This area, Sean...
HANNITY: Wow.
KAY: ... is 100,000 square kilometers. That is a huge area for four aircraft to fly. Now, you've got satellites coming in. You've got the Poseidon aircraft, which is all very useful. And we know already from information reports today the Poseidon aircraft was concentrating in his area here. And unfortunately, all it's managed to turn up is a freighter and a couple of pods of dolphins. So as yet, we've got a long way to go.
You mentioned the weather -- hugely inclement weather there at the moment. Hopefully, that's getting better. But having done lots of search and rescue operations in my previous life, what I know is, is that when the weather comes down, the cloud base come down, the rain start falling, visibility comes right in. So you're traveling at four miles a minute, less than 5K viz (ph), incredibly complicated (INAUDIBLE)
HANNITY: You know, the hard part, too, is, again, we're going 15 (sic) miles out. You're talking about maybe maximum a three-hour window to actually search the area that is in question. And we don't even know if -- again, a good enough reason to search, but we don't have enough information or intel to tell us this is the location where they really believe it went down.
KAY: Yes, you're absolutely right, Sean. And you know, (INAUDIBLE) I've served on two boards of inquiry. And what we need to be doing is -- you know, this is the sort of area that they're looking at. But we shouldn't be putting all of our eggs in one basket. We shouldn't be living in the hope that soon we're going to get some evidence which is going to make this area conclusive.
HANNITY: Right.
KAY: So what we need to be doing is, we need to be looking at where was the last place that the transponder was actually located? Well, it was here. If we draw a line directly down, that's about seven hours. Now, the positive side of this is that that is on the edge of a Boeing 777's endurance. So you could say that if the crew was incapacitated in any way, then the flight director and the autopilot could have taken it down to this area, and that is likely where you would have run out of fuel.
HANNITY: But how do we explain that -- it was -- the flight path was put in manually into the airplane, when it made this turn, which took them off its path, and then they said good night after the path was changed?
KAY: Well, Sean, we only have part of that story. And what I mean by that is, is that the computer systems and the navigation systems on these airplanes, they have an ability to input waypoints. But then you have to input the waypoints into a route.
HANNITY: Right.
KAY: And so we don't know what the coordinates were of the waypoint. It could have been a diversion. So the aircraft could have got halfway across the South China Sea, and all the pilot might have been doing is he's changing a diversion airfield from Malaysia to Vietnam, but may not have put it in the route. And if he doesn't put it in the route, the flight director isn't going to follow it.
HANNITY: But also assuming starting here -- it's a relatively short flight to China, correct?
KAY: Absolutely. Yes.
HANNITY: All right. So that being a relatively -- so we can assume, too, that they had a full fuel capacity because all -- unless of course they might have filled it up because of the price of fuel. That could have been a -- we haven't gotten an answer on that 13 days in, which is insane because that would give us the maximum range of that airplane at that point.
KAY: Yes, more unknown information, Sean. I mean, you know, it's just proving how difficult it is. But what do we do -- what do we know? Well, look, if we do think that this is...
HANNITY: I didn't mean to mess up your board.
KAY: No, that's all right. We can clear that one and we can start again. So here was the last transponder. Here's where everyone's looking at the moment. Let's draw a line all the way down.
HANNITY: Right.
KAY: Now, the that I would be looking at if I was leading a board of inquiry is, is that in order for that aircraft to go from there, its last known point, down to here, it's got to cross Indonesian airspace and it's got to go across Singapore, which is one of the busiest airspaces in the world.
HANNITY: Plus, why wasn't -- why wouldn't it have been picked up? Great question, right?
KAY: Singapore...
HANNITY: Why do you doubt -- you're the only person I've heard cast any doubt on the computer input in flight before the good-bye. Why do you put doubt on that?
KAY: Again, only because I've familiarity with the way these systems work. And once again, like with many of these scenarios, we don't have enough pieces of the jigsaw to put enough together to be able to paint a picture. And so we're hearing about people knowing that some sort of information has been put into the flight navigation system, but we don't know what and we don't know whether there it was put in the route or not, and we don't know why it was put in. I mean, there could be perfectly logical explanations for it, such as diversions.
HANNITY: All right, now, you're going to stick around. Mikey's going to -- by the way, we're going to have "ask the experts" later. He's going to be here at the big board, and he's going to be taking your questions. On Twitter, it's @SeanHannity. Or you can go to my Facebook page.
Joining me now with more analysis on the search are former FAA official, U.S. Army pilot John McGraw (ph), along with pilot and former Navy officer Philip Holloway (ph). John let's start with you. You're -- well, let's -- look at this board and your thoughts on it.
JOHN MCGRAW, FORMER FAA OFFICIAL: Well, Sean, sorry, I can't see the board. Let me get it turned around here.
HANNITY: Well, what we were describing to you, and that is, really quickly here, that it made this turn, and it would be 1,500 miles, perhaps about here. We draw a straight line down -- that it went in that direction, the location where they're now searching off the coast of Australia.
MCGRAW: Well, you know, I -- I completely agree with the previous guest that you have to look at -- at every scenario at this point. We really don't have anything that we can rule out at this point. I think that the most probable outcome is that the airplane went south and continued south until it ran out of fuel. The satellite data that we have continued -- I think that's probably the best data we have. And so it's OK that they're focusing down south.
It does not mean that they should stop the rest of the investigation. That has to continue because there could be other answers for why the satellite continued to ping.
HANNITY: Michael is shaking his head. He agrees with you. Philip, let's get your input on that. What are your thoughts on this?
PHILIP HOLLOWAY, FORMER NAVY PILOT: Well, I actually -- I absolutely agree. You know, I've been a criminal lawyer for 16 years, and what I can tell you is that an investigation of any sort, especially one of this magnitude, must begin with facts, facts that have to be reliable, accurate and complete.
What we have not been getting are any facts that are accurate, reliable and complete. Only now, I think that a lot of the other countries, the United States and Australia and some other countries are getting involved. In fact, the FBI now has possession of the simulator found in the pilot's home. I think now we're going to start getting some answers.
But as Senator Chambliss said earlier tonight on this network tonight, these transponders were manually turned off. So that is a -- if that's a fact, that tells us something. We can draw an inference that a human being was involved in turning this airplane. The real question...
(CROSSTALK)
HOLLOWAY: ... is why.
HANNITY: But isn't it also ACARS and the transponder? And then, again, if you believe the information we're getting, the fact that they manually put in the computer new coordinates and a new flight path?
HOLLOWAY: Right, that means there's human involvement in this, which means to me it's a crime and it needs to be investigated as a crime. We have to be very thorough because if we're not and we don't get the answers to these questions as to who, what and why, this thing can happen again. And it can't happen again. This is too much of a big deal to ever happen again.
HANNITY: And we can add one other point to that. These families that have loved ones that were on that airplane -- they deserve answers. And we also need to know if this was an instance of terror because we've got to protect airlines not just in the United States, but worldwide.
Thank you, guys, gentlemen. Wish we had more time. Thank you for being with us.
And coming up next tonight right here on "Hannity"...
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
MCINERNEY: We may in the next 28 to 48 hours start hearing from either the Malaysian government or the Pakistani government. If the Pakistani government doesn't talk soon, they're going to be complicit in this.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
HANNITY: All right, so with the news tonight, does General McInerney -- does he stand by his prediction. He'll join us next. That and much more as this breaking news edition of "Hannity" continues. We're glad you're with us.
HANNITY: This is a "FOX News Alert." We have now confirmed tonight that the Malaysian airline pilot's home flight simulator is en route to the FBI headquarters. That's in Quantico, Virginia.
Joining me now to talk about this and much more, FOX News military analyst, Lieutenant General Thomas McInerney. General, welcome back to the program. Always good to see you, sir.
MCINERNEY: Thanks for having me, Sean.
HANNITY: You know, I know that you have a lot of sources. I know that you can't reveal them all to us. We had you on the program the other night, and it got a lot of interest from our viewers, your belief, that, in fact, this plane -- and sources that are -- that you're connected to are telling you that it may very well have landed in Pakistan. In light of this new information tonight, are your sources still confirming the same thing?
MCINERNEY: I can't say anything about that, Sean. all I can say is it would be nice, if we could identify it. But I think those passengers have the potential of still being alive.
HANNITY: How?
MCINERNEY: And I believe that airplane landed. I believe that airplane landed. And I've listened to a lot of aviation experts, and none of them know anything about radical Islam. And so I think that's one of the major shortcomings, to think, as well planned as this was -- and you just went through it with Mr. Kay on how the transponder was turned off, they said good night, ACARS went off, transponder -- take the line from the last transponder hit and then take the line from the Thai radar skin paint, and draw that line and see where it goes.
It heads straight for India. It doesn't go to the Indian Ocean and the south. Why would anybody be so clever to do that, and fly the airplane for seven-and-a-half hours and then let it flame out? I don't believe that.
HANNITY: You know, I know you're such a serious person. You make such a compelling case. You make me pause every time I talk to you, General. You turn the transponder off. You turn -- I'm looking at the timeline now. ACARS is off. Then we've got the computer manually. We've got the flight -- a new flight path put in. And then we say, "Good night." That doesn't fit. That doesn't fit.
I read a story today, somebody said, Well, it could have been a simple fire. The problem with that is you wouldn't have said "Good night" at that point. You would have contacted somebody. Again, looking at the timeline, transponder off, ACARS off. Then we have a computer shift in the flight path. That sounds to me -- I'm very strongly leaning that this plane was taken over by somebody.
MCINERNEY: Yes, I still maintain it was hijacked. And for anyone to say, Well, they had a fire or something -- look, we never heard a mayday. All the communications, the coms, the UHF/BHF satcom, to our knowledge were never turned off. And so they could have talked, if they wanted.
Yes, ACARS was turned off. Yes, the transponder was turned off. And so -- as was just pointed out, flying over Indonesia and Singapore -- I mean, there are not better radars along that whole route than through Indonesia and Singapore. Singapore's got the best air defense and the best pilots down in that whole region.
So that's why I have not seen one piece of compelling evidence, to include these satellite pictures, that tell me that that airplane is down there. Now, it could very well be...
HANNITY: Yes.
MCINERNEY: ... but I haven't seen any evidence.
HANNITY: General, without exposing any of your sources, is there any way, for our audience's sake, that you could shed light on what you believe to be the credibility of the sources that you obviously are talking to, because you're not making this up out of whole cloth.
MCINERNEY: No, but it is not my sources. It's the logic that goes into everything that has come up, explains and tracks with what I was talking about. How about the other day when we were on the radio and you talked to some of your very good friends in Boeing, and what did they say, Sean?
HANNITY: They said I can't talk about it, Because my question to Boeing is considering we know that the Boeing -- these 777s have really incredible, not only redundancy, but they have incredible communications where literally the engines are constantly sending back information at the exact function at any moment during the flight. So my question to my friend at Boeing was, tell me, what you know about these engines and what do you know about this plane? He said I can't talk about it. And that kind of surprised me.
MCINERNEY: It surprised me, too. And what have we heard from our own intelligence agencies about certain airfields, particularly the one near Quetta, Pakistan. As I mentioned the other day on the radio, the distance from Lahore to Beijing, excuse me, Kuala Lumpur to Beijing and Kuala Lumpur to Lahore, Pakistan, is 2,700 miles, equidistant. Isn't that a coincidence?
HANNITY: Finish your thought then I have a last question.
MCINERNEY: No, so all of those things track in the northern route. By the way, it is taking so long I'm not sure that that airplane landed in Pakistan that is still there. But we have not heard from the U.S. government of any substantive information. And they know a lot more than they're saying.
HANNITY: For the constraints of time that you have, you do have sources and you are of the belief that our government in particular has a lot more information. Can you confirm that you have sources that also are adding to your theory?
MCINERNEY: Not now, I can't. As you know I'm in the witness protection program right now.
HANNITY: OK, fair enough. I don't want to put you --
MCINERNEY: I'm a face to face person. Yes, and Rolls Royce, get Rolls Royce and get Boeing's comments. They know a lot about from that engine data, because if the Sat Com was working, the Sat Com was working because it was pinging, and the pilots talk on it.
HANNITY: Also the engines were trying to send back the data as to their performance. So that was also adding to the ping, and that was what? Seven hours into the flight they were pinging?
MCINERNEY: Exactly.
HANNITY: All right, this is bizarre to me. All right, general, good to see you, appreciate it.
MCINERNEY: Thanks, Sean.
HANNITY: And coming up next, we'll go back live to Australia. We'll get the very latest on where the search stands at this hour, literally 10:32 a.m. Australia time. And then our aviation experts will answer your questions including whether or not they think it is safe to fly in the wake of this apparent hijacking, and much more.
But first, we don't want you to miss an episode of HANNITY, so stop what you're doing, hope you'll set your DVR, record HANNITY the series so we're with you every night. We don't want to miss you at all. It would be lonely without you.
HANNITY: This is a FOX News alert, in just a few hours investigators will begin to search the Indian Ocean again for the two objects that were detected on the satellite images. And joining us live tonight from Canberra, Australia, with the very latest is Catalina Florez. Catalina, thank you so much for joining us. Tell us about the investigation. It's about 10:37 a.m. your time. What is going on?
CATALINA FLOREZ, NETWORK TEN, AUSTRALIA: Yes, Sean, it is actually 1:32 in the afternoon, and they're smack bang in the middle of the search. They sent about five aircraft from Australia, the U.S., and New Zealand to the area around 2,500 kilometers off the coast of Perth in the southern Indian Ocean. They're scouring an area around 23,000 kilometers, and we're told the ocean there is very deep, rough, and isolated.
The problem though, is, Sean, the images were captured by a U.S. satellite actually on Sunday, and because of the very tedious process it was only discovered and made public yesterday. That means that there is a high chance the debris has significantly moved from its original location.
Now, the search last night was unsuccessful because of poor weather conditions and today's search appears to be slowed again below cloud and rain. But we do understand a Norwegian merchant ship has reached the search area and we're hoping for information on that. But we've also been warned that it could be days before we get anything definitive. Sean?
HANNITY: Catalina, if I could ask you real quick here, one of the problems it is 1,500 miles out, then we have a five hour flight or thereabouts out to the location of the area, five hours back. The maximum in-air time is 13 hours. That only gives about three hours for each flight out there. Is that about right?
FLOREZ: Yes, that is right. The Australian Maritime Safety Authority has actually indicated to us they actually only have about a two-hour period to search that area. So it has limited -- the search capabilities. And, as I said, because of the poor weather conditions that will make the search even harder.
HANNITY: All right, Catalina, good afternoon to you, by the way. Sorry about my math being off ever so slightly. Appreciate you being with us.
And as the hunt for the missing Malaysian plane continues tonight, we are working to answer the questions that you, our viewers, want to know. You have been sharing your thoughts all day on Facebook and Twitter. And here with the answers tonight, aviation attorney Sal Lagonia is with us, and FOX News analyst Kathleen Bangs, and Michael, by the way, we have now renamed the big board the HANNITY board. He's over there and he's going to be answering your questions, going to the map when we need to.
Let's go to the first question. This is a really good question from Bobby Jones on Facebook earlier today. "He asked if the ELT, the emergency locater transmitter activated by submersion in water has not been located, why look in the ocean?" That is a really good question.
KATHLEEN BANGS, AEROSPACE JOURNALIST AND FORMER PILOT: That is a good question. And I think the main reason they're doing that is with the two satellite tracks that we think exist, one to the north and one to the south, I think the thought process is a lot of the governments say they have pretty strong radar and there is a good chance they would have seen the return from the 777. Ergo, let's look on the southern corridor. And I think that is why I think the search has been --
SAL LAGONIA, AVIATION ATTORNEY: And remember, the ELTs don't transmit from underneath the water. So ELTs if they're submerged aren't not going to five us any signals at all.
HANNITY: And where would you get the signal from the black orange box?
LAGONIA: If you could find the orange box we would get a perimeter around them.
HANNITY: Those days are running out, they have a 30-day max.
LAGONIA: Right, although we've seen them go longer, but, yes, 30 days is what they're supposed to operate at. But the ETL is not going to transmit underwater, and they ELTs are not perfect, either. They don't always go off.
HANNITY: Michael, let's go back to you. I guess we're calling this the HANNITY board, my staff is, and ask you, when we look at the location, and you know a lot about the search and rescue missions, in fact, would that have happened upon impact if it went down in the area?
MICHAEL KAY, FOX NEWS CONTRIBUTOR: Yes, obviously, it is clearly miles away from land, but I think to back up what the guys are saying, you have the tow ELTs which are triggered by salt water, which means if they land on hard ground it's going to go off. One thing we do know is that specifically the one in the tail is turned off by the pilots on landing because sometimes the landings can be hard. They don't want to inadvertently want to set off the ELT in the tail. So we don't know whether the ELT was actually turned on in the first place, once again yet another unknown.
HANNITY: You have to imagine the impact would be massive. I would think it would be a situation where it would go off, agreed?
KAY: Again, Sean, look at the air bus that landed on the Hudson. The two scenarios --
BANGS: If it was floating on the water, there is a chance, but underwater, no, we wouldn't hear anything.
HANNITY: But upon impact, Sal, you agree?
LAGONIA: Upon impact, absolutely. Anything over one g is going to set it off.
HANNITY: All right, let's go back to Facebook. Eden writes "How safe am I to get to my destination the next time I board a flight?" A lot of people are worried because if this was terrorism we need to know it, as well as the families, obviously.
BANGS: One of the downside of the coverage is it brings up a lot of people's worst fears about flying. But they have to know is it's exponentially safer than driving in their automobile. The changes of dying, one in 45 million on a United States carrier.
HANNITY: That is a great statistic, although it doesn't take away the fear of my wife. She is a queasy flier.
BANGS: You have to fly every day for 100,000 years one flight a day for your number to be up.
HANNITY: This is something I think is important. We go back to this, the Boeing 777 is one of the safest planes in the sky. It has a 20 year track record, only three fatalities happening when the pilot ran off the runway in San Francisco.
LAGONIA: And structurally, the Boeing products are just a great product, they have you always been. The 777 is one of their most advanced aircraft, absolutely have no fear of flying that.
BANGS: But you know, Sean, I think some of the people worry about, OK, we trust United States carriers, but what about flying globally? I think that is some of the concern. And even then the past couple of years the global standards have really gone up considerably.
HANNITY: I have questions about the safety, how people got on the plane, paying cash, one way tickets. Guys stay right there. Mike, hang in there. Don't go away. We'll have more with our aviation experts, your questions coming up after the break.
And then also tonight.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
ELLEN DEGENERES, TALK SHOW HOST: I apologize for doing it but I broke your re-tweet record.
(APPLAUSE)
BARACK OBAMA, (D) PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES: I heard about that. I thought it was a pretty cheap stunt myself.
(LAUGHTER)
(END VIDEO CLIP)
HANNITY: All right, a missing airplane and a crisis in Ukraine are not enough to stop our commander in chief from clearing his busy schedule for Ellen and his brackets. And his wife headed off to China. We're going to examine the growing list of misplaced priorities in the Obama administration tonight as HANNITY continues. Glad you're with us.
HANNITY: And welcome back to HANNITY, as we continue to answer your questions about the missing Malaysian jet with our aviation experts, Sal Lagonia, Kathleen Bangs, and Michael Kay is with us. Now, question number three, "If the plane landed could they put in a different transponder so they could try to pretend it's just another plane?" That is a pretty interesting question.
BANGS: They could, Sean, but all they really have to do is put in a different code. For the transponder you put in four numbers, all they do is put in the code, no reason to land.
LAGONIA: Absolutely. The transponder is just a radio receiver that retransmits radar data back to the air traffic control. They tell you what code to put in. We routinely change them in flight.
HANNITY: All right, I hope I'm pronouncing this right, how do we know the flight was reprogrammed, is the data transmitter. Michael, I'll throw that to you.
KAY: You have various ways of actually putting information into the computer. We talked about the waypoints. But as you put a waypoint in, you may want a diversion that is in Vietnam instead of Malaysia because it is closer, if you put it in it doesn't necessarily mean it is going on the route. It doesn't mean that the autopilot and the flight director is actually going to follow it. So again, you don't have enough information.
HANNITY: You said you had somebody asking you a question. You had one question.
KAY: I have had a number of these questions, thank you very much. Basically, a lot of people are asking why did the Orions have to come out two hours later and fly back again? Why can't they refuel? Well, the reason for that is the only barrier of the Orion that has that is the P3-F, and the Royal Australian Air Force doesn't have the P3-F. They've only got the P3-C.
HANNITY: Great question and great answer. Next question is from Allen McDonald, Facebook. "Is it possible for a plane this size to fly undetected and land without anybody's knowledge?" When I listen to General McInerney, he does make a compelling case. I have a note from my radio producer said he scares her.
BANGS: I know pilots who accidentally landed a Boeing 737 in an airport in Wisconsin, the wrong airport, and nobody knew it.
HANNITY: Seriously?
BANGS: They only way they got caught was the flight attendants reported them to the company.
LAGONIA: And that can happen. And you have this phenomenon known as shadowing. If you're near high terrain, the airplane can actually not be picked up because of the mountains or the hills behind it are going to cause radar not to pick up the airplane in front of it.
HANNITY: Mike?
KAY: Quickly, basic radar theory, primary and secondary radar, the transponder works on secondary. Transponder will only work out to about 200 miles. After that, transoceanic flights are dropped off the radar. And air traffic control has to use ACARS for synthetic air picture. Primary radar out to about 150 miles, and that is very primitive. It works by sending a pulse out, bounces off the fuselage, comes back again.
HANNITY: All right, back to our questions on Facebook. Jason Anderson asked a question, "Why can't they track the 200 cellphones the passengers had?" It's a good question especially in this day of GPS. If you put a GPS in your car you can find where that car is, time, and the speed it's moving at that moment.
BANGS: My suspicion is because this plane is in a very remote location or at the bottom of the ocean. There are no cell towers that can triangulate to try to find these cellphones. And that I believe --
HANNITY: That would be the same thing, going down?
LAGONIA: If it was over land where there is a bunch of cell towers, once you're above a certain altitude, cell towers aren't going pick up those signals anymore.
HANNITY: Would it have picked it up if it landed in Pakistan?
LAGONIA: If there is a cell tower within reach. But as we know, even in the United States we don't always have a cell tower.
HANNITY: You're landing bing, bing, bing, all your e mails start flying in there.
BANGS: If you text message once you're up to maybe 10,000 feet or 15,000 feet before they get going sometimes you'll get a text message.
KAY: Very quick one. Transoceanic flights, as we just discussed, primary radar, primary secondary, not a loss of about 200 or 150 miles. This bit here now relies on a synthetic air picture created from ACARS, so air traffic controllers procedurally track air craft crossing this ocean through a de-confliction using different numbers, using high de- confliction, and using information from the ACARS which we think was turned off.
HANNITY: All right, last question. Helen Willis, Facebook, "Do two pilots usually fly as a team?" They are usually not a regular team, right?
BANGS: We don't know if they have flown together in the past, but we know on the 777 they probably couldn't have because the co-pilot just got out of training about a month ago.
HANNITY: Good point.
LAGONIA: And Malaysia actually said these two pilots did not ask to fly together on the date of the fateful flight.
KAY: I completely concur. They fly with different people. I have a lot of friends flying for British Airways and Virgin, and a lot of them have never met and have been with the company for over 10 years.
HANNITY: They usually do have the one experienced pilot in the left seat and then the co-pilot in the right seat. Guys, really, really informative. Thank you for being with us. Thank you all for sending in your questions. And we're going to try to and do this every night until this plane is found.
Coming up, as America is embarrassed in the world stage by Russia's Vladimir Putin, you won't believe what interviews our commander in chief took time out of his busy schedule when he's not doing his brackets, when Michelle is not flying to China, the lowlights to this breaking news edition of HANNITY continues.
HANNITY: Welcome back to HANNITY. So as the world's sits on the verge of chaos, you have Putin calling the shots in Ukraine, no word on the missing Malaysian jet, you think your president would have his priorities in order. But that's not the case. Let's take a look at some of the things your commander in chief has taken time out of his very busy schedule to take part in recently. Take a look.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
ZACH GALIFIANAKIS, COMEDIAN: What is it like to be the last black president?
BARACK OBAMA, (D) PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES: Seriously? What is it like to be the last time you ever talk to a president?
GALIFIANAKIS: It must stink that you can't run three time.
OBAMA: Actually I think it's a good idea.
I've been unfairly maligned about my jeans. The truth is generally I look very sharp in jeans.
(LAUGHTER)
OBAMA: There was one episode like four years ago in which I was wearing some loose jeans.
UNIDENTIFIED MALE: North Carolina against Villanova, who do you like?
OBAMA: Nova will end up winning.
UNIDENTIFIED MALE: Arizona against San Diego State, they did play this season and Arizona won. What happens this time?
OBAMA: Arizona will win again.
DEGENERES: I apologize for doing it, but I broke your re-tweet record.
(APPLAUSE)
OBAMA: I heard about that. I thought it was a cheap stunt myself, getting a bunch of celebrities in the background.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
HANNITY: By the way, Ellen, not everybody loves Obamacare. All the people that are paying more, lost their doctors, and lost their plan. One other thing, Michelle, by the way, landed in China. Priorities.
That is all the time we have left this evening. Don't forget set your DVR. Record HANNITY the series because we want you to join us every night here at 10:00 eastern on the FOX News Channel. Don't forget to start your day with our friends, "FOX AND FRIENDS" in the morning, 5:00 to 9:00. Thanks for being with us. We'll see you back here tomorrow night. Have a great night.
]]></text></news-item>