<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-98H1-JBG1-81B1"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Proskauer Expands Antitrust Capabilities; Christopher Ondeck Joins DC Office as Partner</title><source>Business Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Global law firm Proskauer announced today that Christopher E. Ondeck will join the firm as a Partner in the Litigation Department and will serve as Vice-Chair of Proskauer's Antitrust Group, resident in the Washington, D.C. office.
Mr. Ondeck has significant experience handling civil and criminal antitrust litigation, representing clients in government investigations, and defending mergers and acquisitions before antitrust regulators. He handles antitrust matters for clients from a wide range of industries, including aerospace, agriculture (particularly regarding the use and application of the Capper-Volstead Act), defense, energy, financial services, industrials, medical devices, natural resources, pharmaceuticals and telecommunications. In addition, he serves as outside counsel to numerous trade associations and cooperatives.
"Chris's addition underscores our commitment to expanding the firm's presence in key markets and enhancing its bench strength in core practice areas," said Proskauer Chairman Joseph M. Leccese. "The broad spectrum of Chris's antitrust and regulatory capabilities will be a great complement to our seasoned team in D.C."
Over the past decade, Mr. Ondeck has worked on some of the largest corporate transactions and dispositions. Most notably, he advised United Technologies Corporation in its $18.4 billion acquisition of Goodrich Corp., the largest aerospace deal in history; represented Cardinal Health in an antitrust class action involving conspiracy and monopolization claims in the nuclear pharmaceutical distribution industry; and defended Potandon Produce LLC, the largest marketer of potatoes in the U.S., in nationwide multidistrict litigation.
Helene D. Jaffe, head of Proskauer's Antitrust Group, stated "Chris's vast experience across a full range of industry sectors and with various regulatory regimes enhances our depth in terms of geography and industries. His joining is an affirmation of our commitment to provide clients with comprehensive, world-class antitrust services. We welcome him to our team."
"Chris has a firm grasp on all aspects of competition litigation, which will be an invaluable resource not only to our diverse client base, but also to our litigators as a group. We are excited to have someone of Chris's caliber join Proskauer and look forward to working closely with him," said Litigation Department co-Chair Brendan J. O'Rourke.
Mr. Ondeck joins Proskauer from Crowell & Moring LLP, where he was co-Chair of the Trade Association Group and the past Vice-Chair of the Antitrust Group. He began his career at McDermott Will & Emery LLP, and holds J.D. and B.A. degrees from the University of Virginia. He serves as outside counsel to the American Gas Association, American Fuels & Petrochemical Manufactures, Communications Cable & Connectivity Association, National Institute of Nuclear Pharmacies, National Council of Farmer Cooperatives and American Iron & Steel Institute, among others.
Proskauer's Antitrust Group has extensive experience in antitrust litigation and counseling, both civil and criminal. The Group's lawyers have served as senior officials of federal enforcement agencies, including advisor to the Commissioner of the Federal Trade Commission (FTC) and Deputy Assistant Director of the FTC's Bureau of Competition.
About Proskauer
Founded in 1875, Proskauer is a global law firm serving clients' critical legal needs from offices in Beijing, Boca Raton, Boston, Chicago, Hong Kong, London, Los Angeles, New Orleans, New York, Newark, Paris, São Paulo and Washington, D.C. Additional information about the firm can be found at www.proskauer.com .
http://www.businesswire.com
]]></text></news-item>