<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-T4D1-J9YR-G2YN"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>BP would have been better off fighting Gulf of Mexico claims; Even by America's compensation-crazy standards, things have got out of hand</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Katherine Rushton</author><text><![CDATA[BP's chiefs would be forgiven for being tense on Friday morning.
At 9.30am in New Orleans, the company's lawyers will sit down to discuss the "penalty phase" of its drawn-out civil trial over the 2010 Deepwater Horizon explosion, which claimed the lives of 11 workers and wreaked billions of dollars of damage along the Louisiana coastline.
Those lawyers have already spent months debating the disaster - specifically who was responsible for the rig; whether BP acted fast enough to stem the damage; and just how many barrels of oil flowed into the sea. Now we are coming to the punch: the question of how much BP will pay.
Judge Carl Barbier, who is presiding over the case, will set out how the penalty phase will work, inching closer to the critical decision of whether BP was guilty of "gross negligence". Those are the two, loaded words that could raise BP's ultimate fine from $1,100 to up to $4,300 a barrel. If we accept the US government's claim that 4.2m barrels of oil leaked into the ocean, that's the difference between $4.6bn and $18bn.
BP has no choice but to put its trust in the US legal system, and hope that Judge Barbier does not automatically go for the biggest fine that he can. But keeping that faith must be becoming more and more difficult.
Last month, the oil giant lost a court appeal to clamp down on people making "absurd" claims for compensation. "Absurd" is BP's word, but it uses it advisedly.
In 2012, BP signed a catch-all compensation deal, to make it easier for victims to claim compensation without the expense of litigation. The contract was signed in good faith, but opened the floodgates to a slew of claims that were certainly not.
Lawyers in Louisiana have been trolling for business with brazen advertisements urging people to apply for cash, cheerfully telling them that they will be compensated for "losses unrelated to the spill".
To tens of thousands of small business owners still reeling from the recession, it was all the encouragement they needed. Claims have come in at a rate of up to 10,000 a month, many of them from companies hundreds of miles away from the disaster, which hadn't lost any money and were transparently unaffected.
Perhaps this greed is human nature. Perhaps people feel an oil company - a breed of corporation hardly known for its restraint - is fair game.
What is much more surprising is that the court-appointed committee in charge of BP's payouts is comfortable with the situation.
In one instance, it awarded $252,000 to a restaurant 180 miles from the Gulf Coast, never mind that its owner had shut up shop three months before the spill, and didn't reopen until 2011. In another instance, the committee awarded $9.7m to a construction company 200 miles away from the coast, which in 2010 enjoyed its best year ever.
BP argues that the compensation, though correctly worded, is being misinterpreted, and that claimants should have to demonstrate a link between the spill and any damage to their business before they are awarded a payout. BP's opponents argue that the company knew exactly what it was signing up to, and now has to live with the consequences.
Meanwhile, BP's estimate for total compensation payouts has climbed from $7.6bn to $9.2bn. There is no shortage of genuine victims in this sorry tale, of course, and BP deserves to be excoriated for its failures. But, even by America's compensation-crazy standards, things have got out of hand. With hindsight, it might seem obvious that BP should have bided its time and insisted on tighter wording in its compensation agreement. But at this juncture, there is little it can do.
That has not stopped the oil giant trying, of course. Earlier this week, it took out advertisements in The Wall Street Journal and The Washington Post, deriding the latest court judgment as bad for America. BP's payouts will discourage other businesses from accepting responsibility next time there is a corporate disaster, it argued. "Will the response be that it is better to deny, delay and litigate - with victims potentially waiting decades for compensation?"
As the company waits nervously for the final number, that advertisement hits a little too close to home. Executives must be asking themselves if, perhaps, they would not have been better off going down that route themselves. Trying to engender goodwill did not get them very far. Perhaps it would have been better off - in financial terms at least - denying, delaying and litigating.
New Yorkers pretend not to be fazed by much, but earlier this month a ripple of alarm spread through lower Manhattan that the city was about to clamp down on boozy brunches.
News channels and websites reported that restaurateurs had been blithely flouting long-standing laws against all-you-can-drink deals, and that those free-drinking days were over. After years of turning a blind eye, NYPD was going to start enforcing the ban.
The story eventually turned out to be a hoax - but not before a wave of outrage underscored just how much New Yorkers have turned bottomless mimosas into a weekend hobby.
During the week, however, it is quite a different story. Working lunches are almost always accompanied by iced tea or water. Ordering a glass of wine doesn't depend on whether you have a busy afternoon. It is simply taboo.
Sure, Martin Scorsese's Wolf of Wall Street might have been fuelled by liquid lunches (and plenty else besides), but these days the term is more likely to refer to some bile-coloured extract of kale than to booze. Even after-work drinks with colleagues have been turned into communal trips to the gym.
That might seem very sensible in one regard. Sober minds are likely to be more focused, after all. But all this puritanical behaviour overlooks three very important facts: that businesses are built on relationships; that relationships are built when people are relaxed; and that people are generally more relaxed with a glass of wine.
We are not talking about student-style carousing here. We are talking about grown-ups who actually want to do their jobs well. Having a glass of wine with lunch is a perfectly civilised thing to do for those who are not about to perform a surgical operation or fly an aeroplane.
New York may be hyper-efficient in many regards, but a total moratorium on lunchtime drinking? That's not one of them.
]]></text></news-item>