<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSW-8TB1-F031-X2J7"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Home insulation scheme placed intense pressure on staff, public servant tells royal commission</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A senior public servant involved in rolling out the former government's home insulation program has told a royal commission into the scheme that it placed intense pressure on government staff.
Ross Carter is the third bureaucrat to front the Brisbane hearing which is examining whether the Labor government and its staff failed to heed safety warnings before four workers died on the job in 2009 and 2010.
Mr Carter was asked about the pressure public servants were under when the scheme was rolled out.
He told the commission some staff were working until 9pm and 10pm on weekdays and on weekends.
Asked if human resource staff stepped in, he said no, but that he was concerned and tried to move staff into other areas if they were under too much pressure.
He said this made it challenging to stop knowledge being lost from the program teams.
Mr Carter says some staff are "still quite affected by the intensity of that time". Some had left the public sector, while others did not progress to management roles "because of the pressure and stress".
He told the hearing the idea the scheme might have "casualties" never crossed his mind before the workers died.
Yesterday the commission was told government staff were warned workers could die if the appropriate safety measures were not taken.
It was revealed an insulation industry representative warned bureaucrats at a planning meeting about the electrocution of insulation installers in New Zealand in 2007.
Three of the four tradesmen killed working on jobs linked to the Australian scheme were electrocuted.
Coroners in Queensland and New South Wales have previously identified deficiencies in the training given to the four insulation installers.
Workers were only required to attend a one-day general health and safety course.
The Brisbane hearing has been told staff from the Environment Department initially believed all new installers should complete more extensive installation training.
But on Thursday, Mr Carter said that recommendation was not heeded, as the Government wanted to minimise "barriers" to employment, and believed state-based safety rules were sufficient.
On Monday, public servant Mary Wiley-Smith told the hearing she and a colleague were given two days to plan and cost the scheme, which aimed to insulate more than two million homes.
She said she got a call from the Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet after 5pm on the Friday of the 2009 Australia Day weekend and was told she and another colleague had until Monday to have the details ready, including the risks involved.
The home insulation program was set up in 2009 by former prime minister Kevin Rudd and his environment minister Peter Garrett.
The scheme was intended to help ward off the effects of the global financial crisis by paying rebates to homeowners or installers of roof insulation.
During the roll-out of the $2.5 billion scheme, four men died and hundreds of house fires broke out, many of them in ceilings where foil insulation had been incorrectly installed.
]]></text></news-item>