<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-J2G1-JD3N-50J4"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Trophy site for over-50s</title><source>Homes Magazine</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A NEW luxury project on the Gold Coast is likely to lift expectations in the over-50s market.
The $60 million Halcyon Vision community will feature a selection of waterfront homes and a 52-berth marina.
The "trophy" 4.9ha site fronting the Hope Island Canal on Grant Ave will include a floating boathouse with function space, fitness centre, pool, spa, yoga room, media and massage room, and waterfront alfresco lounge area.
All of the new 88 residences will boast eight-star energy ratings. It is the second Hope Island project for the over- 50s developer, following its success with Halcyon Waters, which has now sold out.
Halcyon joint managing director Bevan Geissmann said he and business partner Paul Melville had decided to push ahead with Vision following completion of the 227-site Halcyon Waters.
"The success of Halcyon Waters has proved that we have a sought-after product in a wonderful location that meets the increasingly sophisticated needs of the over-50s buyer," he said.
The last home at Halcyon Waters was the flagship Paragon residence which sold off-the-plan for more than $1.1 million.
"It was a way for us to test the waters at the very top of the over-50s market and the result gave us the confidence to take our next venture to a new level of prestige," Mr Geissmann said. "Vision by Halcyon will epitomise our points of difference for the lifestyle-oriented retiree while setting a new benchmark for over-50s living.
"It will embrace the Hope Island marine lifestyle with all homeowners able to use the marina regardless of whether they own a waterfront home." Construction on the first of four stages is scheduled to start this month. Mr Geissmann expected the project to draw local buyers, including waterfront residents wanting to downsize without losing access to water and boating.
Designs include a new split-level dwelling along with the most popular and proven configurations from previous Halcyon communities.
The first release of 21 homes will include a mix of waterfront and non-waterfront lots with a variety of single, double and split-level layouts.
Prices start at around $500,000 and increase to $1.25 million for large waterfront dwellings.Halcyon does not charge exit or deferred management fees and buyers do not pay stamp duty on their purchase.
]]></text></news-item>