<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-9F81-DXY8-V17R"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Russia and U.S. trade sanctions over Crimea; Assets frozen and travel banned for officials, supporters</title><source>Chicago Tribune</source><author>By Kathleen Hennessey, Paul Richter and Henry Chu, Tribune Washington Bureau; Chu reported from London. David Cloud and Lisa Mascaro in Washington, and Sergei L. Loiko in Moscow, also contributed.</author><text><![CDATA[The U.S. and Russian presidents slapped sanctions on each other's top aides and other government officials Thursday as the dispute over Crimea intensified and the White House worried publicly that Moscow might be positioning its military to seize more of Ukraine.
Denouncing Russia's "illegitimate" annexation of Ukraine's Crimea region, President Barack Obama said the Treasury Department would freeze any U.S. assets of 20 prominent Russians, including several officials close to President Vladimir Putin, some of the country's wealthiest businessmen and a Moscow bank that financially supports the Russian leadership.
Saying the "world is watching with grave concern," Obama also warned he is prepared to take far harsher measures if Russian troops cross into southern or eastern Ukraine. Obama said he authorized penalties against "key sectors of the Russian economy," if necessary, warning that those sanctions could be "disruptive to the global economy."
Putin responded by banning nine U.S. lawmakers and White House officials from entering Russia, according to the Russian Foreign Ministry. The list includes House Speaker John Boehner, R-Ohio; Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid, D-Nev.; Sen. John McCain, R-Ariz.; and three top Obama aides.
Several of the U.S. lawmakers claimed they were honored to be singled out. "Proud to be included on a list of those willing to stand against Putin's aggression," Boehner tweeted. "I guess this means my spring break in Siberia is off," quipped McCain, who visited Ukraine last week.
The unusual back-and-forth came after the State Duma, the lower house of the Russian parliament, voted 443-1 to admit Crimea into the Russian Federation, defying Western complaints that it was approving what Washington and its allies consider an illegal land grab.
In Crimea, Russian flags flew over captured Ukrainian military bases and ships. Banks were closed and the Ukrainian Defense Ministry in Kiev said it was preparing to evacuate an estimated 25,000 military personnel and their families. In a sign that the new sanctions on Russia may sting, the Standard & Poor's credit rating agency downgraded its rating of Russia to "negative," warning of a possible outflow of capital and reduced investment. Still, polls show most Russians support Putin's actions so far.
Washington and the European Union jointly issued travel bans and asset freezes against about two dozen midlevel Russian and Ukrainian officials Monday.
EU leaders, meeting in Brussels, said they were prepared to blacklist more Russians as early as Friday.
But Europe is far more reliant than the United States on Russian oil and gas, and leaders fear disruptions to their fragile economies after years of a debilitating debt crisis.
German Chancellor Angela Merkel, the continent's most powerful leader, signaled that Berlin was not yet ready to seek economic and financial sanctions.
She insisted that, for now, widening the circle of Russian officials subject to travel bans and asset freezes was sufficient.
Samuel Charap, a senior fellow on Russia and Eurasia at the nonpartisan International Institute for Strategic Studies in Washington, compared Obama's executive order to putting major weapons on alert for possible use.
"This is the nuclear option," he said.
The U.S. sanctions target several Russian business tycoons who have profited from their ties to Putin. They include Arkady and Boris Rotenberg, billionaire brothers who received $7 billion in contracts related to the recent Sochi Olympics, according to a senior administration official, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
The blacklist also names Yuri Kovalchuk, who is known as Putin's personal banker. He and another Putin aide on the list, Andrei Fursenko, are primary owners of Bank Rossiya. The bank will be cut off from all U.S. business and find it "very difficult" to do business in dollars, the official said.
Sergei Zheleznyak, deputy speaker of the Duma, called the U.S. list "laughable and useless."
Government officials, he said, "are prohibited by law to have bank accounts and business assets abroad, and I don't have any real estate abroad either."
khennessey@tribune.com
ct14 0195 140321 N S 0000000000 00000802
]]></text></news-item>