<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-MKX1-DYR8-31MF"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Uganda; Bantariza Trial - UPDF Witness Contradicts Prosecution Claims</title><source>Africa News</source><author>The Observer (Kampala)</author><text><![CDATA[The fraud trial of the former director of the Kyankwanzi-based National Leadership Institute (Nali), Col Shaban Bantariza, was adjourned on March 11, after six months and several testimonies.
While prosecution accuses Bantariza of corruption and abuse of office, the former army spokesman claims he is being targeted by people his clean leadership may have denied avenues to perpetuate corruption. Here are some of the salient issues that have emerged in court so far.
Prosecution alleges that on February 3, 2011, at Akamba Uganda Ltd, Old Port Bell road in Kampala, Bantariza, using his position as head of Nali, received a tractor with registration number UAN 652Z and its accessories, donated to Nali by the ministry of Finance. The trial, before a seven-member panel chaired by Brig Moses Ddiba Ssentongo, started last October.
The three UPDF prosecutors are led by Capt Fredrick Kangwamu and the defence team is led by Frank Kanduho. One of the witnesses who have testified so far is Capt Edison Muhirwaha, a Nali finance and administration official. He told court that after his arrest and detention for one year by Brig [Moses] Rwakitarate, he was released on condition that he would testify against Bantariza.
Muhirwaha also confessed that he personally gave Shs 67m to Bantariza, which the latter used to purchase a tractor. He said he got the money from the office safe, contrary to evidence by another witness who said the money was withdrawn from the bank.
Prosecution contends that Bantariza did not buy the tractor, but it was a donation. However, Muhirwaha told court under oath that it was Bantariza's plan in the first place to purchase the tractor.
"On March 3, 2011, I removed Shs 67m from the safe and gave it to him [Bantariza] and he purchased the tractor and it is on the ground," Muhirwaha said.
Another witness, Warrant Officer (WO) I Henry Ssesanga, told court that he was not happy with Bantariza when he compared him to a dwarf because his (Ssesanga) shoe size is seven.
Describing Bantariza as a terrible officer who once bashed him for refusing to clean a toilet the colonel wanted to use, Ssesanga also accused Bantariza of refusing to give him Shs 100,000 for an eye operation.
"From March 2009 to April 2010, Afande Bantariza as Nali director on various occasions treated me unfairly and most times went personal with me when I was still at the lowest rank of a private to the extent that at one time when he found the toilet he wanted to use dirty, he abused and bashed... ," Ssesanga said.
He further told court that although he was a liaison officer who supervised fellow soldiers, he was not responsible for physically cleaning toilets. Ssesanga also said that on another occasion when a quartermaster , Sgt Twinomatsiko, failed to pass on mail from the National Forestry Authority (NFA), Bantariza blamed him instead.
On cross examination however, Ssesanga, a graduate of Makerere University, faltered a bit. He said he joined Nali as a lecturer in 1988 but received formal training for a lecturer much later.
He further told court that in 1991 he got army training but got an army number after seven years. Another witness, Maj Alfred Kamusala, said Bantariza opened an unofficial bank account in Stanbic bank - Kiboga branch, which he allegedly used to acquire Shs 500m from the president's office on Nali's behalf.
"He [Bantariza] was the chief signatory and he irregularly appointed another official as a co-signatory. I was a chief signatory to the old account that he [the accused] abandoned," Kamusala, a former Nali administration officer, said.
Bantariza faces other charges relating to conspiracy to defraud and mistreating his subordinates.
]]></text></news-item>