<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-N0T1-DYJJ-P4C2"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>STATE DIGEST; State board agrees to compensate 14 raped sex workers</title><source>The Californian (Salinas, California)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[SACRAMENTO - A state board on Thursday granted 14 rape victims who had been working as prostitutes the right to be compensated, the first such action since it reversed its policy on the issue last year.
The California Victim Compensation and Government Claims Board took the action on behalf of women whose claims had previously been denied. The victims' next step is to submit the amount of compensation they are seeking.
The decision follows a vote by the board in December to eliminate a policy that banned compensation for those who were attacked while working as prostitutes. The new rules allow victims of sexual assault who were engaged in an act of prostitution at the time of the attack to be reimbursed by the state for their medical costs and related expenses, including counseling, lost income and increasing home security.
The cases are confidential, but board chairwoman Marybel Batjer said in a statement that all 14 had been raped. All 14 cases "were earlier denied because of the victim's involvement in prostitution," she said.
Prostitutes had been excluded from receiving victim's compensation since 1999 because their activities are illegal.
California, which created the nation's first victim's compensation program in 1965, had also been the only state to specifically prohibit sex workers from being compensated if they were the victims of violent crimes.
Court upholds DNA swabs of arrestees
SAN FRANCISCO - A federal appeals court on Thursday upheld California's law requiring people arrested on suspicion of felonies to submit samples of their DNA to police.
The 9th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals in San Francisco said a 2013 U.S. Supreme Court ruling upholding a similar law in Maryland applies to California.
At issue is a law the voters passed in 2004 requiring that all people arrested in California on suspicion of committing a felony supply a DNA sample to police by way of a cheek swab. State Attorney General Kamala Harris and other law-enforcement officials say the law is a powerful tool used to solve thousands of "cold cases." The DNA sample is loaded into a state database and compared against samples collected at crime scenes.
Park service resists Mojave solar project
SAN BERNARDINO - The National Park Service says a proposed 6.5-square-mile solar development about a half-mile from the Mojave National Preserve would harm wildlife and should be built elsewhere.
Preserve Superintendent Stephanie Dubois submitted a letter critical of the plan to the U.S. Bureau of Land Management, which oversees the public land where the Soda Mountain solar project is planned, the Riverside Press-Enterprise reported Wednesday.
The eight-page letter accuses the BLM of failing to adequately examine the project's potential to harm groundwater and threatened and endangered species. The project would be detrimental to the desert tortoise, bighorn sheep and protected birds in the area and could reduce water supplies that support one of the few populations of an endangered fish, she wrote.
A subsidiary of Bechtel wants to put solar panels on both sides of Interstate 15 just outside the northwest corner of the preserve in the San Bernardino Mountains.
Obama will speak at UC Irvine graduation
IRVINE - President Barack Obama will speak at the University of California at Irvine commencement in June after students and staff delivered thousands of postcards requesting him, officials said Thursday.
Obama is looking forward to delivering the address marking the 50th anniversary of the dedication of the campus by President Lyndon B. Johnson, said Keith Maley, a White House spokesman.
Obama will speak at a unified ceremony for undergraduates, graduate and professional schools on June 14 at Angel Stadium, campus officials said in a statement.
Huge tech campus owner is a mystery
SAN JOSE - San Jose has approved a massive new office complex, but city officials and the developer aren't revealing the name of the technology company that will occupy it.
The city gave final OK to the project Wednesday, the San Jose Mercury News reported. Local real estate developers say it's one of the largest Silicon Valley office projects they have seen.
"This would be the proverbial granddaddy of them all," Jim Beeger, a senior vice president at Colliers International, told the Mercury News.
Whoever the tenant is, it is poised to become the second-largest private-sector employee in San Jos, behind Cisco Systems Inc., which had 13,000 as of workers last year.
The project is set to cover 2 million square feet spread out over 10 seven-story structures.
Construction is expected to start this year.
Worker arrested in $400,000 wine theft
NAPA - A Northern California man has been arrested on suspicion of stealing $400,000 worth of wine from the temperature-controlled warehouse where he worked.
The San Francisco Chronicle reports that Jose Pina, 31, was taken into custody Tuesday.
Police investigated the theft as an inside job after about 350 cases of wine - or 4,200 bottles - went missing last week from the American Canyon warehouse in Napa County.
At least 55 cases were eventually found at a Solano County barn. Clues from there led investigators to Pina's Vacaville apartment. There they found more of the stolen wine and $73,150 that they believe came from black-market wine sales.
Woman in chemical suicide identified
BERKELEY - A woman who used a toxic chemical to commit suicide in her room at a historic San Francisco Bay Area hotel and social club has been identified as a former professor at the University of California at Berkeley.
The San Francisco Chronicle reports that Sydney Kustu used sodium azide to kill herself Tuesday in her apartment on the third floor of the landmark Berkeley City Club. The newspaper says it was her 71st birthday.
Kustu was a professor emerita in plant and microbial biology at UC Berkeley's College of Natural Resources.
Kustu left a note warning authorities of the dangerous situation.
Sodium azide is commonly found in cars' air bags to make them inflate. It becomes a toxic gas when mixed with water.
Edison agrees to pay $24.5 million fine
LOS ANGELES - One of California's largest utilities has agreed to pay a $24.5 million penalty for safety violations uncovered after a 2011 windstorm left more than 400,000 customers without lights and a power-line failure electrocuted three family members, state regulators announced Thursday.
The proposed decisions by the California Public Utilities Commission staff said Southern California Edison also violated rules by failing to preserve evidence needed to investigate power-pole collapses that occurred in the storm.
]]></text></news-item>