<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-N0V1-DYJJ-P049"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>More tax breaks for Wall Street won't pay off</title><source>The Journal News (Westchester County, New York)</source><author>By, Michael Kink</author><text><![CDATA[Last week in Albany, Republican and Democratic state senators stood up to block a huge new $350-million-per-year package of special tax breaks Gov. Andrew Cuomo wants to give to Wall Street.
Good for them.
Wall Street doesn't need or deserve Cuomo's proposed tax breaks - and New York taxpayers can't afford to pay for them.
While so many New Yorkers and so many New York communities are struggling, the big banks are enjoying massive profits.
The six biggest banks in America - all of which have massive footprints and pay significant taxes in New York - earned more than $76 billion in profits in 2013.
And state Comptroller Thomas DiNapoli reported last week that the Wall Street bonus pool for executives rose 15 percent in 2013 to $26.7 billion.
New York's current tax policies aren't hurting Wall Street - they're making huge profits, and there's absolutely no need for new tax breaks. When profits, bonuses, CEO pay and share prices are sky-high, there's no reasonable case for new tax reductions or special deals.
Predatory lending and other abusive practices by the big banks devastated New York families and communities, destroying trillions in household assets during the 2008 financial crash and economic recession while scoring big profits for the financial services industry.
Federal and state regulators have brought dozens of enforcement actions against banks in New York for a wide range of illegal and abusive financial practices, from mortgage lending and servicing abuses - including wrongfully foreclosing on active-duty service members - to securities fraud, racial discrimination, manipulation of energy markets, money laundering, illegal payments in municipal bond deals, and criminal involvement in the Bernie Madoff scandal.
Rewarding Wall Street for bad behavior just doesn't make sense. If anything, we should be stepping up law enforcement and increasing tax rates to help pay the cost of rebuilding our communities.
Austerity cuts
Elimination of the bank tax and new, lower rates of taxation as proposed by Cuomo will cost between $250 and $350 million per year - and the governor admits that this new giveaway will be paid for with new austerity cuts elsewhere in the state budget.
We just can't afford to give out new tax cuts to Wall Street banks and millionaires. We should use that money to fund our schools, maintain services for our senior citizens and prevent tuition hikes at SUNY, CUNY and community colleges.
More tax breaks for Wall Street won't pay off. Investing in our people is the right growth strategy. The Assembly should join the Senate and reject Cuomo's special tax breaks for banks - and put the money toward education and services for all of us.
The writer is the executive director of the Strong Economy for All Coalition, strongforall.org.
]]></text></news-item>