<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-3201-JCG2-C37X"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Court ruling means couple can sue RBS for millions</title><source>The Plymouth Herald</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A PLYMOUTH businessman has won a landmark court ruling that means he can now sue the Royal Bank of Scotland for millions of pounds in compensation over an alleged mis-sold interest rate swap.
Michael Hockin, whose property empire was put into administration in 2012, believes it was the financial arrangement that cost him his business.
In a ruling that will give hope to thousands of other businessmen and women battling the banks, the High Court in London gave Mr Hockin, his wife Diane and their city-based company, London and Westcountry Estates, the right to pursue their case against the RBS. It also awarded them costs.
The legal action was taken against administrators Ernst Young, who refused to grant the Hockins a deed of assignment to sue the bank, forcing the couple, who live near Holbeton, to go to court.
But the judge's ruling in their favour allows the couple to press ahead with action to have the order putting their business into administration overturned and opens the way for a potentially massive compensation claim.
Mr and Mrs Hockin allege RBS sold them a complicated financial arrangement in 2008 that eventually left them unable to pay crippling interest rates on a £57 million loan.
A delighted Mr Hockin said: "This is fantastic news. I am almost in tears because it has been such a long journey and such a stressful time. It clears the way for us to sue the bank."
Mr Hockin, who has had to watch as administrators sold off the business parks in Plymouth and across the West Country that he and Mrs Hockin had built up over 30 years, hopes he can now halt any further disposals.
He wants the administration process to be suspended while he pursues the substantive legal action against RBS, claiming the bank was wrong to put his business into administration in the first place.
Mr Hockin said of Ernst Young: "They have fought us every inch of the way. If we had not had the money, the excellent solicitors and the sheer tenacity to keep up the fight we would have been dead.
"This has cost us £180,000 in legal fees so far but we are not giving up."
The couple's solicitor, Alison Loveday, of Manchester-based Berg, described the court ruling as "groundbreaking". She went on: "It's very unusual for a court to intervene in an administration case in this way."
She is now drawing up a writ to serve on RBS that must be served before July after which the claim will be officially out of time.
A spokesman for Ernst Young said: "Further to the hearing held on 12 March 2014 and judgment handed down on 19 March 2014, the administrators respectfully acknowledge the order and will act in accordance with the Court's judgement." They declined to comment further.
A number of banks, including RBS, have paid out a total of £300million in compensation for mis-sold swaps, with many more cases pending.
The vast majority that have received compensation, however, are businesses far smaller than the Hockins'.
RBS declined to comment on Wednesday's ruling.
Previously, the bank has said it has investigated the case and found "no evidence of wrongdoing by the bank".
The case, when it eventually comes to court, is likely to hinge on whether or not Mr and Mrs Hockin were considered 'sophisticated borrowers' able to fully understand the complicated terms of their interest rate swap or whether they were effectively talked into something they couldn't fully understand.
Mr Hockin said last year he was adamant they fell into the second category.
"We are not financial people - we are property people," he said. "Even the person who sold us this swap didn't understand it."
The Hockins have had strong support from Conservative MP for South West Devon Gary Streeter, who has publicly called for RBS, which has been owned by the taxpayer since the banking crisis, to "clean up its act" before it is re-privatised.
]]></text></news-item>