<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-MKX1-DYR8-31P1"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Nigeria; Hurdles for Contributory Pension Scheme</title><source>Africa News</source><author>Daily Trust (Abuja)</author><text><![CDATA[Born 2004, the contributory pension scheme now 9, has indeed witnessed exciting growth. A growth that is making Nigerians heave a sigh of relief that it has rested the pre-pension reform crisis where pension debts where over N2.6 trillion and retirees' die waiting for their pensions. Massive fraud and corruption characterised the defined benefit non-contributory scheme, thus making pension a nightmare for retirees.
But in the 9 years of the contributory pension scheme, operated by18 licensed Pension Fund Administrators (PFAs), 7 Closed Pension Fund Administrators (CPFAs) and 4 Pension Fund Custodians (PFCs) with the National Pension Commission (PenCom) as the regulator, has reached a record N4 trillion assets, said the Acting Director General of PenCom, Mrs. Chinelo Anohu-Amazu.
Under the scheme, employers deduct 7.5 per cent of individual workers monthly salary and contribute at least the same amount which is credited into the workers' Retirement Savings Account in any of the PFAs chosen by individual worker. The PFA manages the accumulated funds, which is under the custody of the PFC chosen by the PFA.
As at February, the pension assets stood at about N4 trillion from about 5.9 million contributors from the 20 Pension Fund Administrators operating in Nigeria, the Chairman of Pension Fund Administrators Misbahu Yola said in February.
He projected that the pension assets are projected to peak about N4.3 trillion by end December 2014 from a projected 6.2 million contributors.
Yola said "the growth rate of industry contributions nationwide is about $2 billion annually which is over N300 billion apart from market returns."
Reaffirming public confidence for the contributory pension scheme, NOI Polls Limited, one of leading opinion polling and research organisations in the country, said 73 per cent of Nigerians who have been contributing under the scheme were satisfied with the services of their PFAs while dissatisfied ones complained about not getting updates on their Retirement Savings Accounts (RSAs).
But even in the face of all these achievement and benefits, there are clogs in the wheel of the contributory pension scheme - the biggest threat coming from the fraud in the residual defined benefits non-contributory pension scheme.
Fraud in the administration of the residual defined benefits schemes have persisted while retirees under the schemes suffered hardships and various forms of dehumanising conditions.
This is robbing off negatively on the contributory scheme because some Nigerians still don't know the difference. They lump all the two different types of pension schemes together even though they are different.
While the residual scheme is fraud prone, the contributory pension scheme has in-built structures that make it almost impossible for individuals or organisations to divert or steal accumulated pension savings of workers.
Just last week, another pension scam was unraveled and just like the previous ones, it was erroneously reported to have taken place under PenCom.
The Chairman of the Independent Corrupt Practices and Related Offences Commission (ICPC), Mr. Ekpo Nta, was reported to have said ICPC apprehended a Clerk in PenCom who opened 50 different bank accounts with different names and signatures and banked about N500 million in these accounts.
Though this was a misrepresentation, as PenCom would later prove in its disclaimer, the report generated a lot of bad comments from Nigerians on PenCom.
The ICPC chairman later denied saying the culprit works in PenCom and clarified that the apprehended junior officer works in the civil service but, the damage on PenCom had been done.
Commenting on the misinformation, the Head of Communications Unit at PenCom, Emeka Onuora, stated emphatically that "the commission wishes to state categorically that no official of PenCom is involved in any form of looting of pension fund."
PenCom does not engage clerks and, as such, none of its employees goes by that designation even as it denied having been informed by any agency that its employee was being investigated or prosecuted for looting pension fund, Onuora added.
Onuora said contributors have unfettered access to any information relating to their accumulated pension savings.
In addition, PenCom has in place strict regimes, which include daily monitoring of the investment activities of PFAs and the institution of strict pay-out authorisation requirements.
The misrepresentation on PenCom underscores the need for a purpose-driven public awareness campaign with a view to making Nigerians see the differences between the residual defined benefits scheme and the budding contributory pension scheme.
Also, government should hasten to bring the residual schemes under the supervision of PenCom to ensure that all pension schemes in the country are under the same umbrella so that the water tight safeguards in the new scheme are extended to protect retirees under the residual scheme
]]></text></news-item>