<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-N771-DY15-S2DY"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>War in Lands - Row Between Nantaba and Ministry Officials Escalates</title><source>The Observer</source><author>Edris Kiggundu</author><text><![CDATA[The ministry of Lands, Housing and Urban Development has been sued 146 times largely because of the actions of its junior minister, Idah Nantaba, during the one and a half years she has been in the job.
Taxpayers could lose a lot of money in compensation claims as the embattled ministry moves to defend the activities of its officials, reliable sources have told The Observer.
This is in addition to 44 complaints registered against the ministry at the Inspectorate of Government relating to fraud, forgery, negligence and corruption. Most of the complaints are against registrars. Our sources told us that most of the lawsuits had been filed over the past one and a half years and relate to the work of Nantaba's land committee which went around the country between 2012 and 2013, resettling people who had reportedly been evicted illegally.
But Nantaba told us today that many of the complaints, specifically those to the IGG, came as a result of corruption by the registrars, not her actions. Since she was appointed minister in November 2012, Nantaba has gone about her work with lots of zeal, becoming the poster child of the campaign to stop illegal evictions.
While many people, especially the ordinary folk, are thankful for her efforts, others think she has been careless in her actions, which could cost government billions in legal suits. On March 4, 2013, real estate firm Zion Construction Uganda Limited sued Nantaba, alleging that she had trespassed on its vast pieces of land in Bulwanyi village, Wakiso district.
Through Ambrose Tebyasa and Company Advocates, Zion Construction alleged that Nantaba colluded with 10 other people and forcefully took possession of the land. The firm, which is demanding damages plus costs of the suit, attached certificates of transfer and land titles in its court documents to prove ownership
Then on April 5, 2013, Nantaba evicted a businessman Frank Twine from a disputed land in Kireka, Wakiso district, saying it belonged to a 77-year-old woman, Kevina Nantume. Nantume accused Twine of fraudulently grabbing the piece of land inherited from her late aunt, Mary Namagembe.
Nantaba ordered the removal of the iron sheets that the businessman had used to fence off the land. The poles that were used to erect the fence were loaded onto a truck and taken to an unknown destination. Twine took government to court. Another company rattled by Nantaba's activities is Riss Coffee Limited (RCL), which is embroiled in a land dispute with 43 families in Buikwe district.
Last year, Nantaba ordered the affected families to repossess the 158-acre piece of land. She told a meeting that the villagers had lobbied her, saying they had been cheated by the firm during the compensation process. The firm has since gone to court after efforts to settle the matter diplomatically, between Kampala and Copenhagen, reportedly failed.
There are many other individual suits, including those filed by Moses Karangwa, who owns large chunks of land in Kayunga, accusing the minister of trespassing on the land that is located in Bugerere, Block 26, Kiryantama. The legal suits come at a time when Nantaba and senior ministry officials are not on talking terms.
Nantaba accuses some officials in the ministry of being corrupt and engaging in fraudulent land practices that have earned the ministry a bad name in the eyes of the public. She wants at least 15 land registrars to be sacked. In turn, the officials accuse her of being aloof and ignoring their advice in the execution of her work, and point to the legal suits as evidence.
With neither side willing to budge, an impasse has been created, affecting the delivery of services to the public, sources told us. Daudi Migereko, the minister of Lands, Housing and Urban Development, the sources said, tried to intervene but failed after Nantaba accused him of siding with "corrupt officials" in the ministry.
'Sack Land officials'
The Observer has seen correspondences detailing accusations and counter accusations between the minister and various officials in the ministry. In August 2013, Nantaba wrote to the minister of state for Ethics, Simon Lokodo, saying that many land registrars had become unethical in their work and as a result there had been an increase in illegal land evictions. She wanted them to be punished.
In her letter dated August 13, 2013, Nantaba writes that Sarah Kulata, the commissioner for Land Registration, is the key architect of the scheme. Nantaba said Kulata, who had been interdicted before over abuse of office, is working in cahoots with land registrars across the country to fraudulently sell public land and issue fake land titles.
Besides Kulata, other registrars Nantaba wants sacked include Robert Nyombi (principal registrar-Wakiso), Madiina Nabukeera (Luweero), Diana Bobabaana (Hoima), Denis Musinguzi (district land surveyor-Hoima), Robert Mbaziira (Mukono), Ivan Serwamba (Bukalasa), Okia Yafeesi (Entebbe), Satya Mungusho (headquarters), Gilbert Kasozi (Wakiso), Okiriza (Masaka), Ahmed Ddamulira (registrar of titles), Ovason Arinaitwe (Mukono) and Yusuf Kakerewe (Jinja).
"The purpose of this letter is, therefore, to request you to take note of this grave issue and appreciate that non-action on such a subject has fuelled illegal land evictions out of fraudulently-issued land titles by these officers causing intolerable suffering to the citizens of this country," she wrote.
Nantaba said government continued to lose land and property such as hospital grounds, school playgrounds, and agricultural demonstration grounds because of such officers who fraudulently allocate the land to private individuals. Nantaba's letter was copied to President Museveni, the Prime Minister, the Inspector General of Government and the Attorney General, among others.
In a cabinet meeting held on February 5, 2014, the ministry of Lands was directed through a cabinet directive (CT 2014) to ensure that the registrars, including Kulata, face administrative action. Nantaba said such action can only be instituted by the Public Service Commission which can sack them, suspend them or caution them. However, this would require a long period of investigation.
Indeed three weeks later, on February 25, 2014, Irene Mulyagonja, the IGG, responding to the issues raised by Nantaba, wrote to Migereko saying that the investigations of the land registrars might not be easy citing section 75 of the Registration of Titles Act (RTA) which provides that registrars shall not be liable for acts done while exercising the powers given to them by the Act.
Mulyagonja advised the ministry to set up a commission of inquiry to resolve the numerous complaints. Nantaba told The Observer today that the biggest problem at the ministry was corruption and unethical practices of its officials, not land grabbing.
"I told the president when I met him recently that I do not see the need to go back in the field to fight land grabbers because the real problem is in the backyard [ministry]. We have people like Kulata who use money and connections with big people in government so they can do what they want. These are the people that should not be in the ministry," Nantaba said.
Kulata fights back
Last week, Kulata fought back. In a letter dated March 14, 2014, she wrote that Nantaba had in many cases given directives to the land registration department, which could not be implemented because they would be flouting the law. The letter is addressed to the first deputy Prime Minister and minister of Public Service and copied to Lokodo and Mulyagonja, among others.
"It should be noted and emphasised that when a technical opinion is not in tandem with the MSL (Minister of State for Lands) directive, she labels the officer a fraudster.
Unfortunately, most, if not all her directives are based on wrong premises, misinterpretation and understanding of the law, procedures, practices and techniques of land registration. If implemented, the directives of the MSL would plug the government into many legal cases and major financial losses," she wrote.
Kulata added that Nantaba's actions had helped aid "fraudsters or people with false, stale or outright illegal claims to dispossess rightful owners of land."
She further wrote that she had once told the Permanent Secretary in the ministry, Gabindadde Musoke, to organise a 10-day retreat to acquaint Nantaba and other officials with the process of land registration but this is yet to materialise.
Sought for an interview, Migereko did not return our calls.
]]></text></news-item>