<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-N111-DYJJ-P22X"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>N.Y. officials call for Rahway Arch probe</title><source>Home News Tribune (East Brunswick, New Jersey)</source><author>By, Bob Makin</author><text><![CDATA[CARTERET - Soil Safe got two bits of bad news recently.
The Maryland-based recycler plans to pay $15 million for remediation of the former American Cyanamid dump site, which is leaking cyanide-contaminated sludge into the Rahway River, by building a 29-foot-high landfill from which it, the property's current owner and the borough will profit. But that hasn't stopped environmentalists and officials from complaining about the project and property, both of which are known as Rahway Arch.
On Tuesday, federal, state and Staten Island officials filed a request with the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency to investigate concerns about the project, most of which are related to potential flood hazards.
That followed several state Department of Environmental Protection violation citations against Soil Safe's South Jersey site.
"This is the same company that NJDEP just granted a flood hazard rule waiver to develop a new facility in Carteret," said Debbie Mans, executive director of Keyport-based NY/NJ Baykeeper. "NJDEP needs to explain why in the space of two weeks, they issued a permit for a new facility for a company they just cited for multiple violations at an existing facility. It defies logic."
DEP spokesman Larry Ragonese said Soil Safe has had some violations at its Logan site, but they are not substantial problems that raise questions about the environmental integrity of the operation.
Soil Safe has been, and will continue to be, required to correct any violations and to comply with state regulations, Ragonese said.
In response to the Staten Island officials' letter to the EPA, he said, "We think Staten Island officials have gotten incorrect information on this project. We intend to reach out to officials in our neighboring state and make sure they fully understand the facts of the effort that is being undertaken at Rahway Arch. The project will stem the flow of contaminants now leaking into the Rahway River and offer a permanent solution to future contamination. It is designed to protect the environment."
Signed by Rep. Michael G. Grimm, R-N.Y., Staten Island Borough President James S. Oddo, six New York state legislators and two members of the New York City Council, the letter stated, "The proposed Rahway Arch project ... intends to establish a chemical waste repository on land along the Rahway River directly opposite of Staten Island. The land is located on what is considered a flood plain by FEMA, and the Rahway River feeds directly into our shared Arthur Kill waterway, which separates the Island from New Jersey.
"This soil recycling project calls for millions of tons of highly chemically contaminated soil to be trucked in and dispersed over the property to act as a cap over the acres of cyanide-contaminated sludge that American Cyanamid dumped there for over 50 years," the letter continued. "The site was completely flooded during Hurricane Sandy. ... We find it hard to rely on NJDEP's permitting in ensuring this project will not adversely impact the Staten Island shoreline and the waters of the Arthur Kill, the Kill van Kull and the Raritan Bay. We've concluded that a thorough investigation of the Rahway Arch project's environmental impact is both prudent and necessary."
The officials asked the EPA to examine how runoff from the proposed 29-foot cap will impact the water quality of the Rahway River and the Arthur Kill and how potential storm surges will affect the water quality. The EPA confirmed receipt and review of the letter.
The officials also claimed that the DEP issued conditional project approval last May before receiving engineering studies. Baykeeper has made the same claim, which convinced Rep. Donald Payne Jr., D-N.J. 10th District, in October to request the Army Corps of Engineers utilize federal Sandy relief funds to include Rahway Arch in its upcoming study of tidal flood conditions within the Rahway River.
The study is pending the Army Corps' draft of a partnership agreement with the DEP, an Army Corps spokesman recently said.
The DEP continually has disputed claims that the project will increase flooding, stating that Rahway Arch is within a tidal flood zone that floods because of ocean surge, not river flow impacted by rain.
Soil Safe response
Soil Safe spokesman Jonathan Jaffe described the officials' letter to the EPA as more tired rhetoric from individuals who have distorted the facts to generate support among lawmakers.
"The DEP has reviewed this permit with a fine-toothed comb, as repeatedly reported, and has deemed this project the best way to address the 85 acres of contamination on this property," Jaffe said.
"While these ongoing distortions are disturbing, what is more concerning is the fact these opponents have yet to suggest an option to deal with the seven tons of cyanide leaking into the Rahway River each year from this property. There is no option but to remediate it. That should be the concern of environmental groups and Staten Island officials, not baseless allegations."
The DEP has asserted repeatedly that clean fill will be used, under two sets of its rules, Jaffe said. The properly recycled Class B recyclables are clean fill under state solid waste regulations, he said, and the recycled product meets residential standards and/or the requirements of alternate fill for the remediation project.
But Mans said she remains concerned.
"NY/NJ Baykeeper supports the call for the investigation," she said. "These New York elected officials have shown leadership in addressing the concerns of their constituents about public health and flooding related to the proposed project. Unfortunately, NJDEP continues to move ahead with permitting the Rahway Arch project, heedless to the concerns of the community and now its neighbors in New York."
Staff Writer Bob Makin: 732-565-7319; bmakin@ MyCentralJersey.com
]]></text></news-item>