<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-8PH1-F03R-N19D"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Ten Things You Need to Know Today: Friday 21 Mar 2014</title><source>The Week UK</source><author>Tim Edwards</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 21, 2014 (The Week UK:http://www.theweek.co.uk Delivered by Newstex) SEARCH FOR MH370 'DEBRIS' CONTINUESAn international team is continuing its search for what may be pieces of missing Malaysia Airlines flight MH370, spotted on satellite images of the South Indian ocean, south and west of Australia. Australian PM Tony Abbott said the area was 'inaccessible' but added: 'If there is anything down there, we will find it.'
PETROL PRICES AT THREE-YEAR LOWPetrol is at its lowest price for three years, the Automobile Association says, with the cheapest tank in the country sold in Humberside and Yorkshire. The average price of a litre in March was 129.46p, compared to 138.42p last year. The group also predicts recent wholesale cuts could lead to a 2p price fall at the pumps. BEATLES JACKETS SELL FOR £115,000Cape-like jackets worn famously by George Harrison and Ringo Starr of The Beatles in their movie Help! have sold for £115,000 at auction. They were sold by the film's director, Richard Lester, now 82. Also sold was a grand piano used by Sir Paul McCartney and John Lennon to compose Yesterday and Help! CHINA: BABY BORN AS MOTHER DIES IN CRASHA baby born as his mother and father died in a motorbike crash has been hailed as a miracle in China. The parents were driving at top speed to a hospital after the mother felt abdominal pains on Tuesday morning when they collided with a truck. The baby, found lying nearby, is injured but said to be 'stable'. TURKEY BLOCKS 'SUBVERSIVE' TWITTERTwitter is investigating credible claims that its site has been blocked to users in Turkey, just hours after controversial PM Tayyip Erdogan threatened to 'wipe it out'. Users have been using the site to share documents and recordings they say show corruption among Erdogan's inner circle. He denies the claim. GAY-HATING CHURCH LEADER PHELPS DIESFred Phelps, who founded the 'church of hate', Westboro Baptist Church, in Kansas, whose adherents, largely composed of his own family, picket servicemen's funerals with signs saying 'God Hates Fags', has died at the age of 84. His church was brought to world attention by filmmaker Louis Theroux. WORTHING BIRDMAN FACES LEGAL COSTSA competitor in the 2009 Worthing Birdman competition who flew 99.86m, just missing out on the £30,000 prize for flying 100m, and who believed he had in fact hit the 100m mark, will have to pay £20,000 costs after unsuccessfully suing organisers of the light-hearted competition. Steve Elkins says he is 'devastated'. THIEVES DIG TUNNEL TO STEAL £80,000 CASHThieves in Salford got away with more than £80,000 after they built a 50-foot tunnel from nearby wasteland to a branch of Tesco where they stole cash boxes. They escaped by the same route. Police say they are looking for people covered in soil acting suspiciously. The tunnel may have taken months. MICROSOFT ADMITS READING HOTMAIL INBOXMicrosoft is caught up in a privacy row after it admitted reading the Hotmail inbox of a blogger to identify an employee it suspected of leaking information to him/her. The search was technically legal as Microsoft owns Hotmail, but the firm said it would take legal advice before repeating its actions in the future. HOT TICKET: PRISON DRAMA STARRED UPNew British drama Starred Up opens in UK cinemas today. Skins actor Jack O'Connell stars as a young offender who transfers to an adult prison, where he finds his counsellor and his father, who is also an inmate, want to change his violent destiny. "A great prison movie," says Empire.

]]></text></news-item>