<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-T201-JBHM-S0HJ"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Environmentalists Divided Over CPUC Plan For South State Power Supply</title><source>Inside Cal/EPA</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Major environmental organizations are divided over whether a new energy supply plan for southern California approved by state regulators last week for replacing electricity lost due to the closed San Onofre nuclear plant will result in unwanted construction of new natural gas-fired power plants in the polluted region. The disagreement boils down in part to interpretations of last-minute changes to the details of the plan.
Meanwhile, California Public Utilities Commission (CPUC) President Michael Peevey noted the division among the environmental organizations during testimony this week to state lawmakers, and said the plan allows utilities to make up the lost nuclear energy with 50 percent energy storage or "preferred resources" such as renewable power, energy efficiency, and 50 percent new natural gas-fired electricity. Peevey's comments appear to raise even more questions about the state's requirements for the power.
California's response to the permanent closure of the San Onofre nuclear plant - which is located between Los Angeles and San Diego and supplied about 2,200 megawatts (MW) to the region in previous years - has been the subject of increasing controversy over the past year. Some environmentalists are objecting to recent actions by local regulators to ease air permitting requirements to enable the construction of new power plants, and expect to oppose possible relaxation of the state water board's regulation phasing out once-through-cooling systems from coastal power plants.
Last week, CPUC approved a decision under its Long Term Procurement Planning (LTPP) proceeding that authorizes "long-term procurement for local capacity requirements" due to the permanent retirement of the San Onofre Nuclear Generating Station (SONGS). The decision is available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID: 2464973)
According to a March 13 CPUC press release, the decision directs Southern California Edison (SCE) and San Diego Gas & Electric (SDG&E) to procure energy supplies to meet the region's needs. SCE must procure between 500 and 700 MW and SDG&E must procure between 500 and 800 MW by 2022 to meet local capacity needs stemming from the retired SONGS, according to the press release.
CPUC says the decision "authorizes" SCE and SDG&E to procure up to 1,500 MW of new resources, at least 600 MW of which must be from preferred resources, such as renewable power, demand response and energy efficiency. The utilities can procure preferred resources to meet the entire 1,500 MW need, but are not expected to.
In addition, based on the details of prior CPUC procurement decisions for the region, SCE must provide a total of 1,900-2,500 MW to the Los Angeles basin; up to 60 percent of this amount may come from preferred resources, according to the CPUC press release.
SDG&E is required to procure at least 25 percent and up to 100 percent of new supply from preferred resources, according to CPUC decisions. SCE and SDG&E are also required to procure at least 50 MW and 25 MW, respectively, from energy storage, according to the CPUC press release.
CPUC's actions to date will offset the SONGS retirement and nearly 5,900 MW of electricity previously provided by coastal power plants with once-through cooling systems, according to CPUC.
But Earthjustice, the Sierra Club and California Environmental Justice Alliance charge that CPUC's decision last week contained late changes to the text of the order that allows the utilities to procure more natural gas-fired electricity to meet demand. "Ultimately, the final decision incorporated last-minute changes that will increase the odds that utilities will build gas plants instead of installing local, renewable energy sources," the groups state in a March 13 press release.
The groups claim that while the CPUC plan requires that a portion of the energy come from renewable sources, the utilities "will ultimately get to choose where the bulk of the energy comes from, which could include natural gas," the release states. "Leaving this choice in the hands of utilities could pave the way for new, gas-fired power plants that are often built in low-income communities of color. In fact, [SDG&E] has already begun to lay the groundwork for a new gas plant in Carlsbad. The utility could use that plant in the energy mix required by the CPUC to replace the San Onofre plant."
Evan Gillespie, representing the Sierra Club, says in the release that the final CPUC decision is a major step back toward a proposal made last year by the Brown administration, which envisioned about half of the new power coming from preferred resources and half coming from natural gas-fired power plants.
A source representing the groups says that the last-minute changes to the CPUC decision include authorizing SDG&E to increase its procurement by 100 MW, to a total of 800. In addition, CPUC altered the decision to allow SDG&E to procure natural gas plants first and to enter into bilateral contracts, the source says. "Allowing gas to go first appears contrary to the loading order," the source says.
However, the Natural Resources Defense Council (NRDC) applauded the CPUC's decision last week, saying it uses efficiency and preferred resources to "replace the vast majority of the lost SONGS generation," according to a March 13 press release. "Instead of turning to dirty gas-fired power to replace SONGS, this decision fills the gap left by SONGS with at least two-thirds of clean energy resources, and up to 100 percent clean energy."
The CPUC decision avoids "a significant number of fossil-fueled power plants, and those power plants' emissions that Californians are all too familiar with," the NRDC release says. It is notable that CPUC did not authorize any "additional mandatory gas-fired power sources because previously, the commission did enact mandatory gas requirements" in a 2013 decision, the group says. "This frees the utilities to appreciably, if not entirely, rely on clean energy resources to replace SONGS."
An NRDC source disagrees with Earthjustice and the other environmental groups that last-minute changes to the CPUC decision allow for more gas-fired power procurement. The final decision "does not authorize any mandatory gas, it only allows gas to compete," the source says. "The decision does not say that utilities can, should or must 'procure natural gas first.'"
The CPUC decision allows "any" resource to compete to fill about one-third of the total energy needed, the NRDC source adds.
Meanwhile, CPUC President Peevey appeared to contradict all the current interpretations of CPUC's decision by telling lawmakers during a March 18 hearing of the Senate Energy, Utilities & Communications Committee that utilities can comply by providing 50 percent preferred resources and 50 percent natural gas-fired electricity.
In response to a question on the issue by panel chair Sen. Alex Padilla (D-Pacoima), Peevey noted that "NRDC praised the decision" and "Sierra Club criticized the decision." He said NRDC applauded the commission for "going down the road" of 50 percent new gas-fired electricity and 50 percent preferred resources. He said CPUC did not place a big emphasis on new gas-fired plants in the order and is trying to strike the right balance on supplying the region with power.
Peevey also noted that CPUC can make "mid-course corrections" to the order in the years to come.
Last year, CPUC, the California Energy Commission and the California Independent System Operator issued a report, "Preliminary Reliability Plan for L.A. Basin and San Diego," which proposed that about 3,000 MW of new "conventional generation" be developed for the region. The plan consisted roughly of a 50-50 split between natural gas-fired electricity and preferred resources.
]]></text></news-item>