<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-R4X1-JCTS-G3VK"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>LUMPS OF COAL   OPPOSITION FAILS: Planning Commission approves Blue Creek Terminal. </title><source>Mobile Register (Alabama)</source><author>John Sharp z jsharp@al.com</author><text><![CDATA[coal . 6
More than six months after it first surfaced at Government Plaza, a coal terminal project south of downtown Mobile got the OK from the Mobile Planning Commission.
The commission, with a 4-2 vote, recommended planning approval for the Blue Creek Coal Terminal that is part of Walter Energy’s $1.2 billion, six-year mining project that affects mostly Tuscaloosa County.
“We are pleased with the vote that occurred today,” Tom Hoffman, spokesman with Walter Energy’s offices in Birmingham, said. “We’ve done a lot of work to get information into everyone’s hands.”
Voting in favor of the project were Commissioners John Williams, John Vallas, Carlos Grant and Don Hembree. Voting against were Terry Plauche and Roosevelt Turner.
Six other commissioners were either absent or abstained from voting: Victoria Rivizzigno, William DeMouy Jr., James Watkins, Scott Webster, Jarret Wingfield and Tracie Lee-Roberson.
The decision could be appealed to the Mobile City Council. The opposition, which includes concerned citizens and business owners within the Church Street East neighborhood and parts of downtown Mobile, has 15 days to file a request for tan appeal.
“We are disappointed,” said Greg Vaughan, an attorney who has spearheaded the opposition movement and helped lead a petition drive that compiled 1,680 signatures opposing the project. “We have had a coal problem for quite some time. We are trying to encourage people to move to downtown Mobile not leave and go to Baldwin County or west Mobile.”
A vote to overturn the commission’s decision will likely take a supermajority of five council members.
Hoffman described the project as an “outstanding” development located within a 25-acre lot that, for approximately 50 years, has been utilized for heavy industry.
“The only thing we’re doing different is getting rid of old equipment and putting in new equipment,” Hoffman said.
During the commission hearing — which featured 30 minutes each of presentations from Walter Energy officials and project opponents — the company cited its environmental protection measures it believes will keep dust and water pollution to a minimum.
Environmental consultant Allen Dittenhoefer of Birmingham, through a “comprehensive air quality impact assessment,” said the project will emit less particulate matter into the air than what many industrial uses already in Mobile currently allows.
“The impact of the terminal is extremely small,” he said. “The emission rates are extremely small compared to what’s currently emitted in the county.”
Dan Grucza, vice president of environment for Walter Energy, said that covered conveyors and fog control devices, including 16 water cannons to reduce air pollution, will keep the site’s dust pollution under control.
“We go above and beyond what is required and are committed to being a good neighbor and a responsible corporate citizen in your community,” he said.
Vaughan said he wasn’t convinced. He said that the company has not tested the equipment that will be installed into the Blue Creek facility. He said that the Mobile terminal is the first time Walter Energy is developing a project that includes the technology the company claims will reduce harmful pollution.
He also criticized the company’s track record in Birmingham, which he said resulted in a class-action lawsuit related to its use of street sweepers within the northern part of the city. A division of the company was included in an EPA investigation of past and current industries in the north Birmingham area for potential pollution violations.
Hoffman said the situation in Birmingham is “apples and oranges” compared to its project proposal in Mobile.
“It’s out of context,” he said. “We were (cleaning the area) not because we were generating so much dust to do that but because people are worried about dust in general.”
Vaughan also said that the company has shown little interest in exploring a potential dome structure over the coal stock piles it’s planning at the facility. Hoffman said at an estimated cost of $60 million, the dome is cost prohibitive especially since any of the dust pollution would take place through the transfer — not the storage — of coal.
Some residents who spoke before the commission said they were concerned about the development, while others said they were still seeking information.
Casi Callaway with Mobile Baykeeper said she has questions about stormwater management issues at the terminal site.
The company held an open house community meeting last week for the public to learn more about the terminal project. Walter Energy, which is one of Alabama’s largest companies, was criticized for not being more proactive months ago in discussing plans for the Mobile project.
“I think it is fair criticism that maybe we should’ve done this sooner,” Hoffman said. “Candidly, we made an assumption that was erroneous (that the project would be approved because) this was a site used for coal terminal for 50 years.”
Hoffman said he understands the neighborhood concerns.
“I don’t live there and they do and you have to respect their concerns and the emotional attachment to their neighborhoods,” he said.
coal From Page 1
]]></text></news-item>