<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-RXX1-JCBN-52K1"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Lax control causes worst loan scandal</title><source>Korea Times</source><author>By Kim Tae-jong</author><text><![CDATA[It was first thought that the worst-ever loan fraud involving 17 banks was a result of the personal misconduct of an employee at KT ENS, an affiliate of KT, and his accomplices.
But as the investigation is expanded, even murkier aspects of the crime are being discovered. A senior official from the nation's financial regulator was found to have been involved in the fraud, and bank officials are also being investigated for possible collusion.
KT ENS failed to detect its employee's wrongdoing for over five years - the man secretly used the company's official seal to forge sales documents to help the firm's subcontractors borrow money from banks.
The banks, for their part, did not take the necessary step to verify the authenticity of the submitted documents, before giving loans totaling 1.8 trillion won to the subcontractors over the lengthy period. The Financial Supervisory Service (FSS), which is required to regulate irregularities at financial firms, didn't detect the scam, either.
'This is not just a crime by a group of scammers or a few people,' Kim Sang-jo of Hansung University said. 'It rather stemmed from systematical problems at financial firms and the supervisory authorities.'
The crime is the result of deep-rooted corruption and irregular practices at all involved organizations, he said.
Plot for fraud
Then how were the financial firms so easily tricked for such a long time?
According to police, six subcontractors of KT ENS were so financially weak that they could not obtain legitimate loans from banks. So, they decided to manipulate sales documents to deceive the banks with the help of the KT ENS worker.
The KT ENS employee, surnamed Kim, helped forge loan-application documents for a special purpose company set up by the six subcontractors by stamping his company's official seal on fake documents.
The subcontractors were then able to receive loans from 17 lenders, including three major banks, after providing the fake collateral.
Police said the fraudulent loans were taken out between May 2008 and January this year. Outstanding repayments are estimated at 289 billion won.
The subcontractors used a large amount of the fraudulently received 1.8 trillion won to repay debts so that they could repeatedly take out new loans, police said.
Among financial firms, Hana Bank sustained the largest financial loss at 157.1 billion won, followed by NH Nonghyup and KB Kookmin with 29.6 billion won each.
Police have arrested heads of the subcontractors and the KT ENS employee, and are also seeking the whereabouts of a key suspect, surnamed Jeon, who is on the run abroad.
Officers said the suspects misused a large part of borrowed money for personal purposes - they were found to have purchased luxury cars and houses and paid for trips overseas. Some of the money was used to bribe officials.
Blame game
The banks that sustained massive losses claim KT ENS should be held accountable for the repayment of the outstanding loan, because its employee fabricated the documents with the company's seal.
They also expected KT to take moral responsibility, as it holds a 100-percent stake in KT ENS.
However, KT ENS has refuted such claims, saying the crime was committed by an individual, and had nothing to do with the company. It claims it is also a victim, because it has suffered a liquidity shortage since the scandal was made public.
'This has nothing to do with us, as KT ENS neither offered guarantees to the banks, nor permitted the use of the company's official stamp,' a KT ENS official said.
Amid growing criticism, the company filed for court receivership, citing a debt default. This move has made it even harder for creditors to collect on the fraudulent loans, because the assets of a company under receivership are frozen and debt repayments are at the discretion of the court.
The creditors strongly criticized the KT ENS move, arguing it made a hasty decision to dodge its responsibility in the loan scandal.
They also criticize KT on the grounds that it has tried to avoid taking responsibility by letting its affiliate file for court receivership without offering financial support.
'We granted massive loans largely because KT is the parent company of KT ENS, but now KT is trying to dodge its responsibility by allowing its affiliate to go into receivership,' an official from Hana said.
But the banks in trouble are not free from criticism because they offered massive loans to the subcontractors based on documents that they never attempted to verify for over five years.
Woori Bank and the Industrial Bank of Korea, which the scammers had also approached for loans, rejected their requests after examining the documents.
In this regard, the FSS suspects employees of the banks in question were also involved in the fraud.
'Illegal loans were taken out by subcontractors of KT ENS for five years, but the FSS and banks in question failed to detect them,' Financial Consumer Agency President Cho Nam-hee said Thursday, requesting the Board of Audit and Inspection to investigate the scandal.
Ethics at the FSS have also been called into question, as a senior official, surnamed Kim, is also alleged to be connected with the fraud. The official is suspected of help the key suspect Jeon flee abroad when the FSS started investigating the fraud case in January.
According to the FSS, Kim had allegedly received bribes, which may amount to billions of won, from the businessmen. He was immediately suspended after his actions were uncovered.
]]></text></news-item>