<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-3V81-JBKR-8138"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>U.S. promises more sanctions against Russia</title><source>The Star Phoenix (Saskatoon, Saskatchewan)</source><author>William Marsden, Postmedia News</author><text><![CDATA[In a marked escalation of tensions over the Ukrainian crisis, the United States has announced fresh sanctions against senior Russian officials and the "crony" bank that holds their assets.
More sanctions: U.S. President Barack Obama signed a new executive order Thursday allowing the Treasury Department to begin targeting sectors of the Russian economy for possible sanctions. This includes mining, engineering, banking, the arms industry and energy.
Obama's new sanctions add seven senior Russian officials and wealthy businessmen to a list that now totals 20.
It also sanctions Bank Rossiya, freezing the bank's American assets, and bars bank officials from travel to the U.S. "The world is watching with great concern as Russia positions its military in a way that could lead to further incursions to southern and eastern Ukraine," Obama said.
The sanctions, he said, will "not only have a significant impact on the Russian economy but could also be disruptive to the global economy. However, Russia must know that further escalation will only isolate it further from the international community."
Mounting criticism: Former U.S. national security advisers Zbigniew Brzezinski and Brent Scowcroft this week criticized Obama for not clearly describing to the American people the dangers posed by the Ukrainian crisis on world peace. "It is time for the president to tell the nation why a cooperative world order is in jeopardy due to Russia's unilateral actions," Brzezinski said in a tweet this week.
He repeated his observation Wednesday night during a panel discussion and added that Russian President Vladimir Putin's speech this week on Crimea was "terribly reminiscent of what Hitler was saying about Austria before the Anshluss.
"I think there is a spirit in Putin's speech that is vengeful and triumphalist at the same time and committed to this notion of a new union ... an empire with a capital in Moscow," he added.
Human rights concerns: A White House official said Russia has closed the border to Ukrainian goods. "This is unacceptable under their WTO (World Trade Organization) obligations." Citing reports of the arrest and beatings of journalists and activists, the official said the U.S. is concerned about human rights violations in Crimea since the Russian takeover.
"We have seen a serious worsening of the human rights situation in Crimea." She claimed Tartar houses have been marked in "a biblical fashion" and on Sunday the body of a Crimean Tartar man was found with signs of torture.
]]></text></news-item>