<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-MKX1-DYR8-322V"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Zimbabwe; Chinese, ZDF Firm Wreaks Havoc in Gwayi</title><source>Africa News</source><author>New Zimbabwe (London)</author><text><![CDATA[A CATASTROPHE is reportedly unfolding in the wildlife rich Gwayi Conservancy in Matabeleland North province where China Africa Sunlight Energy is accused of leaving a behind trail of environmental destruction.
The firm is one of the 20 companies controversially issued with special grants to explore and extract coal-bed methane gas in the area and has already completed an initial Environmental Impact Assessment
China Africa Sunlight Energy, a joint venture between Chinese conglomerate Shandong Taishan Sunlight and Old Stone Investments - an obscure local company linked to the Zimbabwe National Army (ZNA) - has already secured approval from the Environmental Management Agency (EMA) to mine despite serious environmental concerns raised by stakeholders in the area.
According to the Hwange/Gwayi Conservation and Tourism Association (HGCTA) and Gwayi Intensive Conservation Area, the Chinese's exploring activities have caused water aquifer bursts and massive pollution of rivers in the area.
"Before the commencement of the actual mining, the exploration process has already caused serious environmental damages. As I speak water is oozing from the ground at eight aquifers which have exploded because of drillings.
"The most affected are Chimwara and Good Luck farms," said Langton Masunda the chairperson of HGCTA who is also a safari operator in the conservancy in an interview with New Zimbabwe.com.
Mark Russell, the chairman of Gwayi-ICA, said his association and other stakeholders were side-lined from the assessment process.
"We are actual shocked that EMA gave this project a thumps up without our input. Gwayi ICA is the custodian of the land but surprisingly our members who have been affected by the exploration activities were ignored," said Russell.
Masunda said the area which the company wants to mine is a buffer zone for Hwange National Park and any mining activity would also have drastic effects on wildlife farming in the area.
"After a proper analysis, we have established that there is greater value in preserving the area as it is rather than allocating it for coal mining activities," said Masunda.
China Africa Sunlight Energy managing director, Retired Colonel Charles Mugari dismissed the concerns insisting the mining project would bring foreign direct investment of $2,1 billion in four years and create up to 4,500 jobs.
"This project will bring national benefits such as power generation, chemical and brick moulding plants. Only people who are not doing anything on their farms are most vocal about in opposing this project," said Mugari.
]]></text></news-item>