<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-6181-JCTS-G386"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Four women accused of stealing money from seniors </title><source>South Jersey Times (New Jersey)</source><author>Joe Green  nj.com/southjerseytimes</author><text><![CDATA[A prominent Atlantic County lawyer and the owner of an in-home senior care company are among four women accused of stealing millions of dollars from elderly clients.
Attorney Barbara Lieberman, 62, of Northfield, and Jan Van Holt, 57, of Linwood allegedly stole more than $2 million from at least 10 victims. They are charged with money laundering, conspiracy and theft by deception, authorities said.
Lieberman was arrested at her home on Northwood Court. Search warrants were executed there and at her Northfield law office. Bail was set at $300,000 full cash and about $5 million in her assets was frozen.
Holt, the owner of "A Better Choice," a company that claimed to offer seniors "custom designed life care and legal financial planning," was arrested at her home on West Vernon Avenue. Bail was set at $300,000 full cash.
Sondra Steen, 58, of Linwood and Susan Hamlett, 55, of Egg Harbor Township were each charged with theft by deception in connection with the alleged scheme.
Steen is Van Holt's sister, and Hamlett worked for "A Better Choice" as an aide for elderly clients, Acting New Jersey Attorney General John J. Hoffman said.
Authorities allege the women targeted elderly clients with substantial assets who typically did not have any immediate family, offering them non-medical care and assistance, including financial and legal services. They allegedly forged a power of attorney, added their names to the victims' bank accounts or transferred the victims' funds into new accounts they controlled. Holt then used that money to buy two Mercedes, a condo in Florida, pool supplies and health care for her pets. Lieberman allegedly used the money to pay off credit card debt.
The women allegedly went so far as to handle the wills of the elderly in order to continue to steal from their estates after they died.
Nine of the 10 victims have died since the scheme began, Hoffman said.
"These women allegedly preyed ruthlessly on elderly clients, most of whom were facing the end of life without family and with only their savings to ensure they would be cared for properly," Hoffman said. "We're supposed to honor our elders, but these women heartlessly exploited them, allegedly stripping them of their life savings and their ability to live out their final days in comfort, peace and dignity."
Hoffman added that anyone who thinks a loved one has been victimized by the four accused should call the state Division of Criminal Justice toll-free tipline at 1-866-TIPS-4CJ.
The investigation of the alleged thefts is ongoing, the Attorney General said.
Contact the South Jersey Times at 856-845-3300 or at news@southjerseymedia.com
]]></text></news-item>