<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-32C1-DYT4-K40P"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Artist reminds us that Kenyan road will threaten Serengeti migration</title><source>Business Day (South Africa)</source><author>CHRIS THURMAN</author><text><![CDATA[Artist reminds us that Kenyan road will threaten Serengeti migration
IF YOU have ever been a member of a writers' group, or submitted a manuscript to an editor, or signed up for a creative writing course, there is one piece of advice that you're sure to have heard: & Show, don't tell!& Don't tell readers that a character is nervous or scared; show us how he fidgets, how he smokes a cigarette. Don't tell us that a landscape is beautiful; show us the details of shape and light, of depth and height, so we can experience the perception of beauty.
It is repeated as a mantra to the extent that it almost loses its potency - almost, but never quite. For, simplistic as the show-don't-tell formulation may seem, the principle applies to practices of representation in a range of disciplines, from theatre to the visual arts.
There are, of course, times when it may be justifiably jettisoned. South African struggle literature was characterised by a propensity to show and tell in equal measure: to show readers what life was like under apartheid, to expose the grim spectacle of oppression, but also to tell them exactly how angry the poet or novelist was about it, to make explicit the moral of his or her text.
This is not to say, however, that all forms of & activist& art must involve telling. While an artist's statement can provide some necessary background and context to facilitate a viewer's engagement with an exhibition, it can also detract from the pleasure or provocation of this engagement. Sometimes images are more evocative when accompanied by a minimal amount of text.
A case in point is Georgia Papageorge's Serengeti Crossroads (at the University of Johannesburg Art Gallery until April 9). This exhibition records various aspects of Papageorge's environmental activism, protesting against the destruction of natural habitats in the Great Rift Valley: specifically, the Tanzanian government's desire to build a road from west to east across the country that will interrupt the famous Serengeti migration.
Papageorge points to a complex web of industrialisation and economic imperialism that has resulted in ecological damage to a & concentrated single region ... symptomatic of environmental loss throughout the world today& including the development of a soda ash plant that threatens the major breeding colony of the Lesser Flamingo, a hunting concession that will displace about 30,000 Maasai, and a Chinese-owned port in the historic stone town of Bagamoyo. One need not be a conspiracy theorist to sympathise with her distrust of the state's motivation for constructing the road.
The artist's & Shepherd Principle& Project is an ambitious and multivalent response. It invokes the & biblical idea of the good shepherd& the & African context& of the & herder& in this case of cattle) and a more celestial guide or protector: the Southern Cross constellation. Papageorge's plan was to recreate the geometry of the Southern Cross on a large scale using people from the area where the road is due to start, but was forced to abandon this.
Instead, she used red cloth against the stark, flat salt of the Makgadikgadi Pan in Botswana. Video footage, aerial photographs and mixed media paintings of the installation are testimony both to a grand vision and to careful execution by the artist and her team. This is suitably dramatic & showing& Other works in the exhibition give us a tangible sense of the terrain, its mapping and the potential damage that the road may cause. Road signs merge tragicomically with grasslands. Black volcanic ash from Kilimanjaro, white salt from the pans and blood-red Maasai blankets add vivid colour and texture to photographic panels and canvases. Photos of the flamingoes and of animal migration tracks by June Liversedge complement Papageorge's theme.
It is a pity, then, that the artist feels the need to & tell& us about the images, their provenance and their significance in a language that harks back to the ancient and archetypal, but is prolix and gauche. & Any installation of the Southern Cross must be seen as a benediction that blesses all those that it seeks to protect through its beneficial light and power,& we are told.
Show. Don't tell.
POINTING: Georgia Papageorge, Installation of the Southern Cross in the Makgadi-kgadi Pans, Botswana (May 2012, 2014). Mixed media on canvas.
]]></text></news-item>