<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-N111-DYJJ-P4C3"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Utility penalized for overpaying bosses</title><source>Journal and Courier (Lafayette, Indiana)</source><author>By, John Russell</author><text><![CDATA[INDIANAPOLIS - Indiana regulators said Wednesday that top executives at Citizens Energy are overpaid, and reduced the amount the company can raise rates on hundreds of thousands of water customers because of it.
The Indiana Utility Regulatory Commission also launched an investigation into the company's management practices, including how it runs its billing operations and call centers. The agency said that in some months, one out of four callers to the company hangs up prior to receiving service due to long wait times.
The action amounted to a stern rebuke by state regulators about the high salaries and incentives pocketed by Citizens executives after they acquired the city's water system, as well as the level of its customer service.
Citizens came under fire last summer after The Indianapolis Star reported that CEO Carey Lykins earned $2.9million in 2012 - nearly double what he made the previous year and more than triple what the leaders of other large municipal gas utilities earned.
Lykins had defended his pay, saying it was comparable to what executives made at similarly sized, primarily private utilities. But Indiana utility regulators later grilled him in a public hearing, strongly hinting that the executive compensation was out of line.
The regulatory commission said Wednesday that the multimillion-dollar salaries were excessive.
"Citizens Water's level of executive compensation was not appropriate for a municipal utility," the agency said in a statement.
It warned that it expects Citizens to realign compensation in its next rate case "so that it is more compatible with actual municipal-based expenses."
The utility took over the city's aging water and sewer systems in 2010 for nearly $2 billion, promising the keep rates lower than the city could have done on its own, and provide better service. Mayor Greg Ballard had strongly supported the deal.
Ballard's spokesman, Marc Lotter, said Wednesday that the mayor still supports the deal, and applauded the IURC as the appropriate mechanism to correct possible excesses or abuses.
"Rates were always destined to go up, because of the aging infrastructure, and the need to replace that," Lotter said. "But they were going up much less because of Citizens' management than they would have otherwise."
He said executive salaries at Citizens were a matter for the company's board and the IURC. "The mayor is focused on getting cleaner water, cheaper and faster, and that's where Citizens' energies are focused."
Citizens said it has already taken steps to address the compensation issue, and will continue to do so. In December, the company said it cut compensation for its top executives by an average 27 percent. Lykins saw his compensation slashed by more than a third, to $1.9 million last year.
The company requested last year to raise rates by 14.7 percent. It said the water system had 730 water main breaks last year and some sections date back to the 1800s.
But the agency, in its 102-page order on Wednesday, gave Citizens permission to raise water rates for its 300,000 Indianapolis-area customers by 9 percent. The company said that will translate to an increase of about $3 a month for the typical homeowner.
In addition, the IURC allowed Citizens to recover investment funds for infrastructure improvement up through 2015, which will save ratepayers an additional $2 million.
]]></text></news-item>