<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-MKX1-DYR8-3296"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Liberia; Sime Darby Responds to Fire Outbreaks</title><source>Africa News</source><author>The New Dawn (Monrovia)</author><text><![CDATA[Sime Darby Plantation Liberia Inc (SDPL) has confirmed that due to very dry weather that started in December 2013, there have been fire incidents in its Bomi, Matambo and Grand Cape Mount estates, affecting 214 hectares of land planted with oil palm. SDPL has been working with the local authorities and the Liberian government to manage these incidents.
In a press release, the company said measures taken include briefing communities on hazards surrounding fire outbreaks, requesting suspension of charcoal burning and burning related to farming.
Other measures are suspension of all charcoal burning and farming related burning within plantation areas until early June 2014; establishing a hotline to report fire outbreaks, increasing the number of staff involved in fire surveillance within the plantation area, planned radio broadcasts with Ministers, Senators and the local police to urge communities to cooperate with SDPL in ensuring that there are no fires within the estates.
SDPL also said it is working closely with the Liberian government to investigate the causes of these fires. It said media reports of local community dissatisfaction with SDPL are untrue, and suggestions that SDPL has entered into traditional land without consent is simply false.
"SDPL strictly observes the Free, Prior and Informed Consent process and this has been refined to include participatory mapping where community elders are involved in drawing the boundaries of areas considered as sacred or for farming, among others", the company clarified in a release.
SDPL said it has a good working relationship with Project Affected Community (PAC) and other key stakeholders. It said if the fires have been caused by arson, SDPL will work closely with the authorities to ensure the safety of all its employees and to protect the integrity of its investments.
"We have condemned this fire thing from the first day. What is happening is very bad. What we like to make clear is that the fire is not coming from the PAC residents. We have been with Sime Darby helping to create awareness in the communities. Sime Darby is our friend and we hope the fire incident stops soon so that the company can move ahead with its development," said Mustapha Foboi, chairman of the PAC.
Meanwhile, SDPL is calling on community residents to kindly assist with information regarding any fire throughout the plantation to ensure that it is managed effectively.
As a responsible long term investor, SDPL believes that the local communities are its biggest stakeholders, saying "This is why we are committed to providing medical care, educational facilities, access to drinking water and sanitation, and roads to the communities within our concession area."
Sime Darby has provided more than 2,900 jobs over the last three years and has the potential to provide 35,000 jobs once the project is fully operational.
]]></text></news-item>