<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-8K71-F05M-K0XW"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Cracks in the fracking boom: Is it under attack in North Texas?</title><source>Dallas Business Journal</source><author>Nicholas Sakelaris</author><text><![CDATA[aile Bush's suburban Denton home is under siege by hydraulic fracturing.
For years, the stay-at-home mother of two believed she had old water wells near her home, saying that's what her Realtor told her. But last summer she found out the hard way what they actually were - old abandoned vertical oil wells just a few hundred feet away from her home. And EagleRidge Energy had free reign to convert those wells into deeper, horizontal natural gas wells.
The drilling started in August. Then the fracking started in January.
"It was rows and rows and rows of trucks. Then they brought the silica sand in ... a known carcinogen," the 40-year-old Bush said. "The air was gritty. Once they actually started the actual fracking process it was the sound, the odors. The fear of not knowing exactly what they were doing."
With her back against the wall, Bush became an activist. She and her husband, Jason, a 38-year-old computer programmer, joined with 43 other Denton residents in a $25 million suit filed in February against Dallas-based EagleRidge, now tapping the Barnett Shale from underneath their homes in the Meadows of Hickory Creek development.
And she's leading a petition effort to force the City Council to either ban hydraulic fracturing outright or at least put a ban to a vote. Organizers have already collected the 571 signatures required to bring it to the city council.
One way or another, if Denton, which already has more than 270 natural gas wells, bans fracking it will be the first Texas city to have attempted such a bold move. This could lead other North Texas cities to follow suit, potentially delivering a crippling blow to the oil and gas industry in the midst of a fracking boom, which started in the Barnett Shale about 10 years ago.
In fact, fights between residents and oil and gas companies have intensified in North Texas over the past six months: They defeated Trinity East Energy's attempt to drill 60 wells in Dallas, which has led to a $30 million lawsuit against the city and a rancorous war of words.
More recently, the rattled citizens in and around the small Tarrant County city of Azle were radicalized after dozens of earthquakes rocked the community. They very vocally suspected that the cause was underground waste-water disposal from fracking and took their case to the state capital.
Could such unified, home-grown anti-fracking movements dish out serious damage? These battles have drawn headlines all over North Texas. Even casual observers would be hard-pressed to not see a trend.
Having natural gas wells so close to home has driven Bush to do things she never thought she'd do, like forbid her children from playing in their own backyard or installing a natural gas monitor for her 100 percent electric home.
"Not a day is going to go by that I'm not going to worry about their health," she said. "My son's sixth birthday was in January and he got one of those little scooters and he hasn't even opened it because he can't go outside. You don't know if something's going to explode or if there's going to be a leak."
But even if the fracking ban Bush and her neighbors hope for is successful, it could turn out to be a Pyrrhic victory.
"A city can do whatever they want, but then they are going to have to pay for that," said John Holden, a certified energy and mineral law attorney and partner with Jackson Walker LLP. "You're going to get an oil company suing the city saying, 'I'm damaged,'"
Sounds very much like the argument Trinty East is making against the city of Dallas. It's not as if efforts by the public to push back at the oil and gas industry have gone unnoticed by the state's energy companies.
Opposition to fracking cuts across political and socioeconomic lines - if the drill site is close enough. Right now, it seems to encompass rural communities and big cities. Rich and middle-income. Conservative and liberal.
Perhaps the strangest bedfellows of all: grass-roots efforts that have attracted the attention and resources of left-leaning anti-fracking heavy hitters: Sierra Club, Earthworks and even MoveOn.org.
"They're clear in saying that they are anti fossil fuel organizations, but the way they go about achieving their goals is by focusing on fracking," said Ed Ireland, executive director of the industry-funded Barnett Shale Education Council. "What these national organizations tend to do is take advantage of whatever situations come up."
Still, local protestors use the national groups for their funds and organizing prowess. For the national groups, the locals represent ready and willing boots on the ground. As these allies play out their rhetorical tag team, they're hoping for the same thing: that the Texas energy industry is finally on the ropes when it comes to fracking.
"If you can win in Texas," said Victoria Kaplan, a MoveOn.org organizer in California, "you can do it anywhere."
But there are no easy wins for Bush and her neighbors, where it may be too late.
"We may not be able to sell this house," she said. "Even if I wanted to get out, could I and where would I go?"
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Dallas Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>