<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-N0T1-DYJJ-P3MG"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Coachella Valley Water District, Desert Water Agency spotlight groundwater</title><source>The Desert Sun (Palm Springs, California)</source><author>By, Ian James</author><text><![CDATA[The Desert Sun
Jay Calderon/The Desert Sun
Wide-ranging discussions about water use on farms and golf courses, wastewater recycling and how to encourage conservation emerged as the Coachella Valley Water District and the Desert Water Agency led a tour of water infrastructure Thursday focusing on management of the area's groundwater.
Jay Calderon/Desert Sun
The water agencies offered the tour to participants in Thursday's symposium in Palm Springs focusing on drought and water scarcity. The group of government officials, water experts and local residents visited places including ponds on the outskirts of Palm Springs where imported water from the Colorado River flows in and seeps down to the aquifer.
"Fortunately, because of our amazing aquifer, we're able to sustain ourselves because we have a bank," said Jim Cioffi, vice president of the Desert Water Agency.
He and others noted that the drought has prompted state officials to announce they plan to deliver no water this year to the canals of the State Water Project. Flows have been reduced in recent years as federal regulators have sought to protect endangered Delta smelt in the Sacramento-San Joaquin River Delta, and the area's water districts are supporting the state's $25 billion plan to build huge water tunnels beneath the Delta.
"We're very concerned about the reliability of the State Water Project," Cioffi said. The canals and pipelines of the State Water Project don't reach the Coachella Valley, so the area's water districts trade their allotments to the Metropolitan Water District of Southern California for equivalent amounts from the Colorado River.
Colorado River water also flows into the valley through the Coachella branch of the All-American Canal. The tour stopped next to the canal overlooking farmland in Thermal.
John Powell Jr., president of the Coachella Valley Water District, explained how Colorado River water is used to irrigate 65,000 acres of crops in the valley.
Powell, who also is president and CEO of Peter Rabbit Farms, pointed out that 55 percent of the area's farms use drip irrigation and 28 percent use sprinkler systems for crops such as carrots. The remainder of farms use flood irrigation.
Passing fields with sprinklers spraying, Powell said the area has grown more efficient while producing high-value crops of winter vegetables.
As for the future supplies of water from the Colorado River, Powell said he hopes that parties along the river "work together to address the gap between supply and demand to avert a shortage, to avert cutbacks."
California has senior rights to water from the Colorado River, meaning that other states such as Nevada and Arizona would be required to make cutbacks before California would.
The group also visited Desert Willow Golf Resort in Palm Desert, one of the 51 courses in the valley that are receiving supplies of recycled water or Colorado River water. The Coachella Valley's remaining 73 courses rely on groundwater.
Desert Willow, which uses desert landscaping in much of the course instead of turf, has plans to further reduce its turf area by at least 20 percent, said Mike Tellier, golf course superintendent.
Such changes are the sorts of steps that various golf courses are planning to reduce their water use, said Keenan Barber, a cardiologist and board member of the Southern California Golf Association who was on the tour.
"I think all agree, almost to a person: we have to use less water," Barber said. "And the timing of that is not 10 years from now. It's now."
For many courses, he said, using less water means reducing the areas of green turf. A task force recently established by representatives of golf courses has set a goal of reducing water use by 10 percent in the coming years.
The state's serious drought and the area's declining groundwater levels raise a host of questions, said state Assemblyman V. Manuel Pérez, D-Coachella, who spoke to the group at the end of the tour.
"Are we over-pumping? And how serious are we about sustainability and water conservation?" Pérez said. "On a per-capita basis, residential water usage in the Coachella Valley stands out as being among the highest in the state of California, even more so than Phoenix and Las Vegas."
Pérez praised the local water districts for taking steps to use imported water to replenish the aquifer and for using programs to encourage conservation. Still, he said, "I think we can do more."
Pérez touted a proposed $8 billion state water bond that would provide money for a range of water projects. He also touted a new bill proposed by the Coachella Valley Water District that would give the agency legal backing to require that homeowner associations use non-potable water for irrigation when those alternative supplies of water are available.
Officials of the water district explained during the tour that valley-wide, about half of the area's sewage is being recycled and reused. Recycling more sewage for irrigation would require additional investments.
Riverside County Supervisor John Benoit, R-Bermuda Dunes, suggested that water pricing may ultimately play a large role in encouraging conservation.
"I think that there's plenty of water for all of us to have a good shower in the morning and not necessarily have quite as much grass. How do you enforce that?" Benoit said. "We've got to be maybe a little bit ahead of the game in realizing: Yeah, we've got enough water right now, but maybe we need to be charging a little bit more to make sure that people understand how critically short that resource is."
"I think that the criticality of the shortage eventually is going to drive prices that are more reflective of the critical nature and value of the water," Benoit said.
Powell, however, noted that Proposition 218, which was approved in 1996, places limits on what water agencies are permitted to do.
"We can only charge the cost to serve the water," Powell said. "We don't have the ability to arbitrarily raise that rate."
Barton "Buzz" Thompson, director of Stanford University's Woods Institute for the Environment, said that he came away from the tour impressed with the water agencies' efforts to manage groundwater, and that there is a great deal of potential to do more.
"There is still groundwater overdrafting occurring down here. We're still running down the groundwater," Thompson said. "You can still go a lot farther in terms of the amount of conservation and recycling that takes place, and most of the time that comes down to money."
Ian James can be reached by email at ian.james@thedesertsun.com and on Twitter at @TDSIanJames.
]]></text></news-item>