<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-0GF1-DXCW-D1CP"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Ireland: G3 Manager, Border Investigations, Border Policing Command, - Ref:1405842</title><source>European Union News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Crown commercial Service has issued the following news release:

Department National Crime Agency Business Area Operational Delivery Group Business Area - detailed Border Policing Command Number of Jobs Available 1 Location: Region North West Location: City/Town Manchester Warrington Location: Building/Site Warrington & Manchester Airport Grade Other Equivalent Departmental Grade G3 Type of Role Investigation Operational Delivery Job Description The NCA is a new organisation which leads the UK’s fight to cut serious and organised crime. This includes class A drugs, people smuggling and human trafficking, child sexual exploitation and sexual abuse, major gun crime, fraud, cyber crime, money laundering and the corruption that organised criminals use to facilitate these crimes. The CEOP Command within the NCA works with child protection partners across the UK to identify and tackle the main threats to children from sexual exploitation and abuse.
The CEOP Command is expanding its team of professional social workers in order to support growing numbers of referrals from industry and the public, and to play their part in multi-agency operations tackling child sexual exploitation and abuse. The NCA has statutory Children Act 2004 responsibilities to promote and safeguard the welfare of children in all its activities and CEOP Child Protection advisers have a key role in advising for officers undertaking a wide range of investigations. We expect our Officers to work to the highest standards of behaviour in everything they do.
Our values and behaviours are:
Flexibility – seeking continuous improvements to the way that we work, adapting to find solutions to difficult problems.
Integrity – acting with the highest standards of integrity and professionalism.
Respect – treating everyone with dignity and respect, valuing diversity, working in partnership, and sharing knowledge and best practice.
Serving the public – being proud to put the public interest at the centre of everything we do.
Transparency – being truthful, open and accountable for our actions.
Grade & Role Title: G3 Manager, Border Investigations, Border Policing Command Vacancy Reference Number: DP1533601JT
Open to: Substantive and External Staff on Lateral Transfer or Promotion, Permanent Location: Warrington & Manchester Airport Closing
]]></text></news-item>