<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-N771-DY15-S39P"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Bernard Kid Swing - Leymah Gbowee Labeled Divisionist</title><source>FrontPageAfrica</source><author>Wade C. L. Williams</author><text><![CDATA["How many Liberians are 17 years old that we are not using today to hold placards that they can't even read? And none of us must be satisfied in this country until we provide the space; like the President said that they can acquire that quality of education to make them competitive, not only in Liberia but anywhere else in the world. That's the crust of my presentation today." - Lewis Brown, Minister of Information
Monrovia - Liberia's President Ellen Johnson Sirleaf comes under the spotlight again for another wrong reason. Saddled by the crisis surrounding the government's spending of millions of dollars in lobbying fees to United States firms, the President is again being criticized for allowing what critics term as her zest for nepotism to overshadow Liberia's oil Dialogue.
The President and her siblings' key among them the Bernards (Jennie and Estrada Bernard) decision to allow the Bernard child to make a key presentation during the just ended oil dialogue is sending waves of anger across the country even leaving co-Nobel Laureate Leymah Gbowee to write her asking some frank questions.
But this letter has not gone unnoticed by the government's chief spokesperson, Information Minister Lewis Brown, who thinks that instead of criticizing the first family or the decision to allow the kid to speak at the oil dialogue, Liberians should be proud that a young boy of Liberian origin could use his time valuably unlike many of the kids back in Liberia who would rather wield placards around for politicians.
"The question is how many 17-year-olds can make such a presentation? That's the crust of the matter," said Brown at the Ministry of Information regular press stakeout.
"How many Liberians are 17 years old that we are not using today to hold placards that they can't even read? And none of us must be satisfied in this country until we provide the space; like the President said that they can acquire that quality of education to make them competitive, not only in Liberia but anywhere else in the world. That's the crust of my presentation today."
Brown chides Gbowee that she could not look beyond mere criticism and see that a young Liberian native no matter his parents could speak before a group of such nature, making the salient points that he made in terms of national ownership of the Liberia's oil resources drawing parallels on the margins of an oil producing country like Alaska in the United States of America.
"It should be of concern and it is such a concern that a distinguished citizen, none less than our esteemed Nobel Laureate drew attention, but if you read the letter, it is more about NOCAL and other transparency processes. That is why I'm bold enough to have heard and repeat what many are talking about without wanting to say what the real issue is," he said.
Continued Brown: "So here is the real issue that I think our Nobel Laureate is also and must also hopefully be concerned about. That is, that it should not matter in our country what your name is and if you want to be honest (and it's going to be hard in this political environment), that story would not have made your headlines if that was James Nagbe or Kolubah Bobolu, III. One of the issues that it was the issue is the fact that the young man name is Estrada Bernard, III."
Brown maintains that Gbowee concern is not that there was a problem with what the kid from Alaska said, but the fact that he is a Bernard and that is something that to him is very worrying considering Liberia's ugly past. "Let us not permit ourselves to be measured by our names; let us not permit ourselves to be measured by our gender; let us not permit ourselves to be measured by our religion," said Brown.
"These are divisive things that only pull society backwards and pull us down and I'm not saying it because I'm a government man; I'm saying it because I am a Liberian. I'm saying it because I saw the stinging effect of discriminating along those lines and measuring others along those lines." Brown said if Gbowee was so concerned about transparency as she claims in her letter to President Sirleaf, she should have raised the issues long ago as these consultations on Liberia's oil is not just beginning.
"The only thing that has happened in this oil reform process has not been this round table, I've not seen an open letter talking about the consultations in other parts of the country," he said.
Continued Brown: "When the legislature began this process, and went from place to place across this country, I didn't see any open letter published. I didn't see a guy in Saniquellie or Fissibu giving his view about oil being measured according to his name. Now a 17-year-old kid called Estrada Bernard, III and somebody want to frighten us; somebody wants to bring the ghost of our past to haunt us and rather than what was communicated which is the value of owning something together and how we must cherish what we own together and how we must leverage it so it benefits all of us; all of that is lost in the conversation. Somebody at such esteemable place, not just in Liberia but in the world is saying 'we must fear'."
Gbowee's Letter
Nobel Laureate Leymah Gbowee Slams Oil 'Experts' Credibility
Gbowee's open letter to President Sirleaf was unambiguous; about the negative ramifications of the President allowing her family to overshadow Liberia's oil reform process and to add insult to injury allow her grandnephew to address an oil round table.
"... It raises serious questions to learn that NOCAL entrusted your grandnephew Mr. Estrada Bernard, III, a South Anchorage High School student in the State of Alaska, USA, to make a presentation on the development of the National Oil and Gas Industry of Liberia, a country of three and a half million citizens," stated Gbowee in her letter which sent the government panicking.
"It is my understanding that Mr. Bernard did an internship with Malcolm B. Roberts & Associates, a firm in Alaska, through his participation in an extracurricular program, the Anchorage School District Gifted Mentorships. I am curious how the 90-day after-school program."
The co-Nobel Laureate maintains that in 2000, the National Legislature established the National Oil Company of Liberia (NOCAL) to hold "all of the rights, titles and interests of the Republic of Liberia in the deposits and reserves of liquid and gaseous hydrocarbons within the territorial limits of Liberia, whether potential, proven, or actual, with the aim of facilitating the development of the oil and gas industry and therefore the kids inclusion in a special spot at these consultations spells doom for Liberia.
"My concern is that the inclusion of Mr. Bernard without further clarity on his expertise undermines your stated efforts to build a transparent process to developing the oil and gas industry," she said.
"As your fellow Nobel Laureate, I supported your first and second term campaign platform to build an open, accountable government committed to rooting out corruption. Therefore, I join Liberians in keeping a keen eye on the NOCAL process."
Gbowee wants greater transparency on who is selected to speak at NOCAL roundtables adding that the expertise NOCAL brings will help buttress Liberians' faith that NOCAL is fulfilling its mandate.
"It is my hope that you will invest in greater transparency to alleviate concerns of all Liberians that NOCAL and every government entity is acting in their best interests," she said.
"Liberians are rightfully optimistic about the great benefits an accountable, effective management of Liberia's natural resources, especially the energy sector can bring to their lives--higher paying jobs, greater infrastructure development, and wider access to electricity and clean water among other benefits. The National Petroleum Policy report echoes this optimism."
The debate about the Bernard kid's participation in the oil roundtable will continue, but as it seems the government has no regret and it believes it was a move rightfully taken.
]]></text></news-item>