<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-Y8H1-F0JP-W2X7"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Caught in the vortex of NSW gutter politics</title><source>Weekend Australian</source><author>MARK COULTAN, BRAD NORINGTON</author><text><![CDATA[Arthur Sinodinos has questions to answer over his involvement with AWH
Sinodinos's real mistake was to get mixed up with a bunch of people who were trying to make a killing out of the public purse
THE NSW Independent Commission Against Corruption has been hot on the trail of Sydney Labor identity and businessman Eddie Obeid for two years. Its investigations have already resulted in seven inquiries and kept NSW Labor's standing with voters in the electoral basement.
This week the Obeid trail led to the door of a federal Coalition minister, Arthur Sinodinos, who has been forced to step aside as assistant treasurer while allegations swirl about what he knew or didn't know of corrupt dealings.
Sinodinos wasn't even under investigation by ICAC. Its main subjects of interest were three former Labor state MPs -- Joe Tripodi, Tony Kelly and, of course, Obeid -- and the possibly corrupt influence they wielded to benefit Obeid and his family.
Among other allegations, the investigation is focused on whether they altered a cabinet minute to recommend that the NSW government sign a multi-million-dollar deal with Australian Water Holdings, in which Obeid's family had secretly bought a 30 per cent stake.
Sinodinos, in the five-year interregnum between his career as long-time chief-of-staff to John Howard and his present post as an elected Liberal senator, set out to make some money as an investment banker with Goldman Sachs and National Australia Bank.
He also accepted a request in 2008 to join the board of AWH and in 2010 became the company's chairman.
So far no one has made any corruption allegation against Sinodinos. His main political crime is one of omission. He claims he didn't know almost one-third of the company he chaired was owned by a notorious figure from the other side of politics.
He claims he didn't know the company he chaired was a major donor to the Liberal Party, of which he was treasurer and then president. And therefore he didn't know that the donations were actually being billed back to the state government-owned Sydney Water, which meant that NSW taxpayers were in fact funding the Liberal Party.
Sinodinos received $200,000 a year as AWH chairman, plus 5 per cent of the shares of the company, rising to 7.5 per cent if he managed to get a public-private partnership signed with Sydney Water.
It was remarkably generous for a not-for-profit company with 10 staff that was set up to lay water and sewage pipes.
Sinodinos's real mistake was to get mixed up with a bunch of people who were trying to make a killing out of the public purse. In retrospect, it is obvious that political influence would be fundamental to the business plan because its entire success depended on a deal being cut with a state government authority.
Mixing political influence with his private businesses is what has got Obeid into so much trouble.
It is now clear that Obeid's influence was not limited to his right-wing faction of the NSW ALP. It was like a toxic plague throughout NSW politics. Whoever the Obeid family touches seems to end up damaged, destroyed or at least forced to endure the media walk of shame down Sydney's Castlereagh Street to the ICAC's inquisition room.
Obeid, the Lebanese family patriarch, businessman and politician who weaselled his way to become the most powerful factional warlord in the NSW ALP, has already been found corrupt by ICAC last year over the awarding of coal exploration licences on his family's Hunter Valley farm that netted them at least $30 million. But he is yet to be charged with any offence.
Obeid is also awaiting ICAC's report on three other investigations of improper influence related to his family's restaurant businesses at Circular Quay, water licences at his family farm and a health management company. He has been expelled from the ALP, referred to the NSW Crime Commission and faces possible confiscation of his assets under special legislation passed early this year.
Obeid's influence across party lines is enough to disillusion even the most partisan of political supporters, and suggests that money politics knows no party boundaries. As ICAC's counsel assisting, Geoffrey Watson SC, put it: ``In an uncharacteristic display of bipartisanship, the events cross political lines. It might be said -- re-adapting Shakespeare -- that corruption `acquaints a man with strange bedfellows'.''
Obeid's association with independent MP Richard Torbay caused his sudden resignation from state parliament, and a possible -- although yet to be made public -- ICAC investigation.
Evidence this week suggests Obeid also had an association with right-wing NSW Liberal factional chief and former minister Chris Hartcher to discredit a senior public servant. It seems the only party he hasn't infected, yet, is the Greens.
The Obeid family bought a one-third share in AWH when Sinodinos was chairman. The company was making large donations to the Liberal Party when Sinodinos had a senior executive role in the party as well.
Even if Sinodinos did not know about these dealings, AWH had almost no assets to its name, no free cash in the bank and its financial position was so ``acute'' that it needed an immediate injection of cash, according to an internal report around the time he left for the Senate.
He went along with this state of financial affairs as he and other executives from AWH lobbied hard to win a lucrative Sydney Water contract to lay water pipes in Sydney's outer west that would have transformed its fortunes.
Politics as it is played in the NSW business world seems to be more about who you know -- and who you give money to -- than how good you are.
From the start, the value of having Sinodinos on the AWH team was his political influence. He could get top politicians such as NSW opposition leader and later premier Barry O'Farrell to the phone with ease to lobby for the company's interests.
Australian Water Holdings had its origins in the 1988-92 administration of NSW Liberal premier Nick Greiner. It was the post-Thatcher era of privatisation. Suddenly the private contestability of what had traditionally been public provision of basic services such as water, electricity and transport was on the agenda.
The Greiner government wanted to shake up the sleepy old government-owned Water Board, and the paddocks around Rouse Hill in Sydney's northwest had been earmarked as a major growth area for the city's urban sprawl.
The Rouse Hill Investment Development consortium was formed between the government's developer, Landcom, and a group of private developers who owned land there. RHIC would be a not-for-profit vehicle to build a state-of-the-art water recycling and sewerage system.
The developers wanted to make a profit out of selling land, not laying pipes. As the years went on, and they sold their land, they lost interest in RHIC. Finally, all that was left were two staff members -- John Rippon and William MacGregor-Fraser.
Somehow -- and ICAC is still working out how this happened -- these two men inherited the company. MacGregor-Fraser paid $10 with a St George cheque for 50 per cent of the company.
The RHIC arrangement with Sydney Water was that the company should lay the pipes and bill Sydney Water for the cost. Things went along relatively uneventfully until about 2006 when Sydney lawyer Nick Di Girolamo joined the firm.
According to the counsel assisting the ICAC, Di Girolamo realised there was an easy way to make more money: simply raise everyone's salaries and bill Sydney Water, since it was paying the bills. Rippon's salary leapt from $720,000 to $1.69m even has he was doing less work for the company. MacGregor-Fraser's pay jumped from $430,000 to $750,000. Di Girolamo had joined the company with a $250,000 sign-on fee and handed himself a $1.1m annual salary as the chief executive.
Administration expenses billed to Sydney Water soared. Not surprisingly, Sydney Water started to ask questions, beginning a five-year fractious relationship.
Eventually Australian Water Holdings, as RHIC was renamed, sought to go over Sydney Water's head to its political masters. Evidence to ICAC suggests that Obeid pressured Labor's water minister Phil Costa to sack Kerry Schott, the tough head of Sydney Water, telling him to ``you need to sack that bitch''.
According to Watson, ICAC's counsel assisting, Obeid also said that it didn't matter if Costa didn't sack Schott: she was going to be the subject of a complaint to ICAC by Liberal MP Hartcher.
ICAC did get a complaint -- anonymously -- about Schott although it teased this week that it had actually found out the source. That will be another part of this inquiry: who made false allegations against Sydney Water executives who were standing in the way of AWH?
AWH desperately wanted to do a public-private partnership deal with Sydney Water. That would allow AWH is make real profits and get out from under the watchful eye of Sydney Water.
Di Girolamo, who is yet to give evidence, has emerged as the central figure in this tale of money politics.
He was a man who had worked his way up from legal intern to managing partner of one of Sydney's venerable law firms, Colin Biggers & Paisley.
He was a Liberal Party fundraiser, and had once been the campaign manager for one-time NSW opposition leader John Brogden. But, crucially, he had gone to St Patrick's School at Strathfield in Sydney's inner west with Obeid's youngest son, Eddie Jr.
The Obeid family paid $3m for a 30 per cent stake in the company. Eddie Jr also scored a job as director of strategic growth -- on $350,000 -- trying to drum up extra work in Queensland.
Now AWH had powerful friends on both sides of politics. But even that wasn't enough to get a deal.
When the NSW Premier's Department received the proposal, it engaged an outside expert, Brian McGlynn, to assess it. McGlynn came back with a unambiguous recommendation that it was a bad deal for the taxpayer. A NSW cabinet minute was drafted to refuse the deal.
But according to ICAC assisting counsel Watson, this cabinet minute was altered, either by or with the authority of Kelly, the Labor minister for planning: it went from refusal to a recommendation to enter ``direct negotiations'' -- public service code for an exclusive deal without tender.
Having been rumbled to the changes, Kelly then put the proposal to a budget subcommittee of cabinet. Again, this failed. Premier Kristina Keneally told him where to shove it.
ICAC even heard this week that, at one point, Obeid associate and former Labor minister Tripodi used his laptop computer to alter the disputed cabinet minute.
With a change in government in 2011, AWH threw its efforts into conservative politics. Up to five lobbyists with Liberal connections were employed. Di Girolamo suggested that Michael Photios, the leader of the Liberals' Left faction, be paid a $1m success fee if he could get the deal done. Sinodinos and Di Girolamo tried to again go over the head of Sydney Water to premier O'Farrell.
From opposition, O'Farrell had given AWH a letter of comfort but as premier he sent AWH back to unwelcome embrace of Sydney Water executives.
The irony of much of ICAC's proceedings on this matter is that the NSW public service is more resistant to influence and corruption than many would think.
Similar to last year's ICAC case involving the corrupt granting of coal licences, it was the secretariat of the Premier's Department that picked up the altered cabinet minute. Sydney Water and its senior executives were also resolute in defence of the public interest.
In the end AWH did get a deal with the government -- but limited to the role of project manager, and only after salaries and other excesses were slashed. Di Girolamo and other board members are gone, and ICAC agrees that the AWH commercial arrangement negotiated is fair and reasonable.
After AWH Holdings spent millions buying political connections with the Liberal Party, it took some straight-talk from the abrasive but astute Michael Costa, former NSW Labor treasurer and Sinodinos's successor as AWH chairman, to get the deal done.
That's how it goes in gutter politics, NSW style.
]]></text></news-item>