<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-Y8H1-F0JP-W2YV"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Corporate villains laughing all the way to the bank</title><source>Weekend Australian</source><author>ANTHONY KLAN</author><text><![CDATA[ASIC would love to have the clout of peer countries' regulators
ON Thursday evening - right on deadline and amid one of the biggest news stories of the year so far, the finding of possible MH370 debris - the corporate regulator released a report highlighting what shock jocks have been yelling about for years.
Australia is far too soft on corporate crime.
The Australian Securities & Investments Commission has compared how our penalties stack up with those in the US, Britain, Hong Kong and Canada.
And the answer isn't pretty.
The report, Penalties for Corporate Wrongdoing, found penalties, almost across the board, were a fraction of those of the peer jurisdictions.
In Australia, the maximum civil penalty for individuals involved in financial wrongdoing - including all of insider trading, market manipulation, disclosure and inappropriate advice - is just $200,000.
In Canada, the maximum was $1.05 million and unlimited in Britain.
In the US, the maximum penalty was three times the benefit gained by the wrongdoing, and in Hong Kong it was the greater of three times the benefit gained or $1.4m.
That Australian $200,000 cap hasn't changed since 1992, as it is not indexed to inflation, so it has effectively been shrinking each of the past 22 years.
ASIC chairman Greg Medcraft, who before taking the role had spent 17 years working in finance in the US, has been impressing on the federal government the need to bolster our laws; and the penalties report is his baby.
ASIC, long-derided by many as a "toothless tiger", wanted to be able to lift its game in penalising corporate crooks.
Late last month, before a Senate inquiry into ASIC launched because of perceived ineffectiveness of the regulator - Medcraft pressed his case.
"Penalties for white-collar crime need to be further strengthened, and I hope that the recommendations from the Senate inquiry into ASIC will reflect the community desire for this change," he told the Senate Economics Legislation Committee.
The committee raised one of the most recent high-profile cases of ASIC's alleged soft touch on corporate crime.
Gunns chairman John Gay was last year found guilty of insider trading, using insider knowledge to avoid a personal loss of $800,000 by selling some $3m of shares in the company.
That trade occurred between a director's report being drawn up, which showed the company had suffered a slump in revenue, and the release of that report to the public.
Gunns collapsed in 2012 owing creditors $560m.
Regarding the insider trading, Gay was charged just $50,000 - one 16th of the benefit gained - and restricted from running a company for five years.
The ASIC report repeatedly highlights the issue that financial wrongdoing penalties are often well below the profits made by the wrongdoing, offering a financial incentive for people to do the wrong thing, regardless of whether they are caught or not.
"In Australia, maximum civil penalties are relatively lower (than the comparison jurisdictions) and are set at fixed amounts," the report states.
"This means that it may not always be possible to ensure a wrongdoer does not profit from their conduct, since the maximum fine that may be imposed may be substantially lower than the financial benefit obtained as a result of the wrongdoing."
A key related concern is the issue of "disgorgement" - the removal of gains made by a person involved in financial wrongdoing.
Australia has no such laws, while each of the US, Britain and Canada do.
In the US, the disgorgement laws pertain to insider trading, market manipulation, disclosure, false statements, unlicensed conduct and inappropriate advice, according to ASIC.
In Britain, the laws pertain to each of those categories except for unlicensed conduct. Under Canadian law, they apply to each category except disclosure.
ASIC said that disgorgement orders could offer "significant deterrent value" by reducing the likelihood wrongdoers "can consider penalties to be merely a business cost".
The corporate regulator also highlighted the discrepancies between the maximum civil penalties that could be delivered by different Australian regulatory and enforcement bodies. The highest civil penalty ASIC could impose under the ASIC Act on an individual was just $340,000, one 10th of the $3.4m that could be handed down under the AntiMoney Laundering and CounterTerrorism Financing Act.
The maximum penalty for a company, group or "body corporate" was $1.7m under the ASIC Act and $17m under antiterrorism and money-laundering provisions.
Under the Competition and Consumer Act, an individual could be fined a civil penalty as high as $500,000 and corporations could be fined the greater of the three: $10m, three times the value of the benefits obtained by the wrongdoing or 10 per cent of the company's annual turnover. ASIC also noted that there were different penalties for the same wrongdoing under different acts.
"If we pursue an individual for providing unlicensed financial services under the Corporations Act, we could obtain at most a criminal fine of $34,000," the corporate regulator said.
By contrast, a person pursued under the National Credit Act for engaging in "unlicensed credit activity" could be forced to pay up to $340,000 in fines.
Regarding maximum prison terms for criminal penalties, Australia was largely in line with Britain and Canada, with the US and Hong Kong having the harshest penalties.
ASIC said its report would form the backbone of a submission to the federal government seeking reform.
The investing Australia public may well be hoping ASIC is better at lobbying the government over its wishes to grow teeth than it is at getting that message out to the public via the media.
]]></text></news-item>