<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-7BF1-JB1X-W1D2"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Down in the dumps</title><source>The Bangkok Post (Thailand)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Residents living near the 70-rai garbage dump in tambon Phraeksa which caught fire, spreading toxic smoke this week are hoping the disaster will prompt authorities into making sure pollution problems in their neighbourhood are a thing of the past.
They say they have endured foul smells from the site for over a decade and that repeated complaints have fallen on deaf ears.
Nongnuch Fumfook, 30, who works for a computer parts firm located near the garbage dump, said she and other residents had to endure air pollution from the site every day for years.
She hopes the fire which has burned for almost a week would be a wake up call for authorities to look into the the problems associated with the dump.
Ms Nongnuch said the smell from the dump affected local people physically and mentally.
Despite the staff keeping doors and windows at her workplace closed to keep the stench out it would always manage sneak in, she said.
According to police, the land belongs to a local businesswoman who leases out the plot to her son who runs the garbage dump.
He claims he was granted a licence to operate the waste management business but Tambon Phraeksa Administration Organisation denies this.
Ms Nongnuch is among thousands of Samut Prakan residents affected by the toxic smoke spewing from the burning dump site since Sunday.
She suffered eye irritation, coughing and chest pains after inhaling the toxic fumes.
She and her daughter are now staying at a temporary shelter set aside for evacuated residents at Phraeksa temple.
The company where she works has been closed since the dump fire broke out.
"This is not good for us since we have a lot of orders coming at the moment," she complained, adding other companies located in the area have also closed, meaning lost income for employees.
Despite the suffering the toxic smoke has brought, Ms Nongnuch was optimistic the incident would force authorities into solving pollution problems caused by the dump site once and for all.
"It's time some state agencies started taking care of us. We have been suffering for far too long," she said.
Panya Ard-harn, 46, a tambon Phraeksa resident, said he had been living in the area long before the land plot opposite his house became a dump site.
About 10 years ago, there were a few trucks dumping industrial waste into a pit each day.
But the number of trucks and the amount of waste increased over the years and the dump site expanded as a result, Mr Panya said.
The garbage dump operator is paid 1,500 baht for each truck dumping waste there, he said.
Fires have occurred at the site many times in the past, but they were small and were doused quickly, he said.
Mr Panya now suffers from skin irritation and respiratory ailments which he believes are a result of long-term exposure to air pollution from the dump.
Like Ms Nongnuch, Mr Panya hopes this week's blaze spurs authorities into looking into the legality of dump site activities as well as environmental and health impacts.
He said authorities should use this incident to force dump operators to overhaul garbage management practices in order to curb foul-smelling emissions, toxic gases, and contamination of wastewater into natural water sources.
Mr Panya recalled a fire at a garbage dump operated by Phraeksa TAO some years ago, saying the blaze forced authorities to improve garbage management at the site which saw a drastic reduction in pollution and complaints by the local community
Jirawat Eiamthoam, 17, a neighbour of Mr Panya, said he wanted the authorities to close the dump site permanently and prevent the landowner from using the land as a garbage dump again.
He said this week's fire had put the illegal site into the spotlight and had caused severe environmental and health impacts.
Shutting down the site would allow younger Phraeksa residents to grow up in a better environment, said the teenager who works at a Japanese restaurant in Samut Prakan.
Jirawat's family has been forced to flee their house near the garbage dump and are staying at a temporary shelter at the Phraeksa TAO office building.
Komsan Saengpleng, deputy mayor of Phraeksa municipality, said local authorities will discuss legal action against the dump site operator and strengthen regulations to better control the waste management business.
He said authorities were now focusing on putting out the fire and providing medical care for those affected by the toxic smoke.
]]></text></news-item>