<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-T201-JBHM-S0K3"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Upper Mississippi River States Craft Coordinated CWA Monitoring Strategy</title><source>Water Regulation Alert</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Five states along the upper Mississippi River have crafted an enhanced monitoring strategy that could help them coordinate and target Clean Water Act (CWA) management actions to address excess nutrient pollution and other issues, an effort that could help states respond to growing pressure from environmentalists to strictly regulate nutrients.
The monitoring plan, modeled after programs for the Chesapeake Bay, Ohio River and Delaware River, was approved Feb. 25 by the Upper Mississippi River Basin Association (UMRBA), which includes the member states Illinois, Iowa, Minnesota, Missouri and Wisconsin.
"There are considerable spatial gaps in monitoring and limited data available to assess the River's condition and to measure change," the strategy says. "Levels of monitoring effort also vary significantly among the states."
The states' monitoring effort could take on added significance as EPA steps up its fight against environmentalists' push to force the agency to take a strict regulatory approach.
UMRBA staffer Dave Hokanson says that while states have existing monitoring programs, the new effort would help harmonize those efforts across the basin, as well as create a program that is specifically geared toward CWA actions such as section 303(d) impaired waters listings and section 305(b) reports on the health of all state waters.
The program will allow "for the first time to have the five states' CWA programs speak with one voice," Hokanson says, adding that improved data will also allow states to better detect changes in the river in response to policy and management actions.
Though the program would review a range of pollutants and support the river's four designated uses of aquatic life, drinking water, recreation and fish consumption, Hokanson says "the big-ticket item is of course looking at what's happening with nutrient levels and nutrient effects on the river."
Creating a common biological assessment metric could be a key part of states' efforts on nutrients, as they have long argued that existing assessment factors, such as numeric nutrient criteria that measure the concentration of nitrogen or phosphorus, don't always fully characterize whether a waterbody is impaired.
UMRBA in 2011 crafted a guidance document intended to help states consider integrating biological information into their CWA programs, including a preliminary biological condition gradient for the Mississippi River. Findings from that work were incorporated into the monitoring plan.
"You kind of say, 'How are the fish?'" Hokanson says. "We have measures that are chemical, physical-based, but we're not always sure whether that is directly benefiting the thing we are really trying to protect, which is the aquatic life." Including biological assessments would allow states to "look for places where both biology and chemical [data] are giving us a signal" that a waterbody is not meeting its aquatic life use, he says.
Increasing Pressure
The new monitoring strategy comes as EPA and states are coming under increasing pressure from environmentalists to craft numeric nutrient criteria as a means to clamp down on nutrient pollution, though the regulators are pushing back against environmentalists' efforts.
The U.S. Court of Appeals for the 5th Circuit earlier this week granted an EPA request to stay a lower court's mandate requiring the agency to formally respond to environmentalists' petition seeking numeric nutrient criteria -- at least until the appellate court rules on the merits of EPA's appeal.
EPA is fighting the lower court order because issuing a formal denial of the petition would allow environmentalists to sue on the merits. As a result, the stay granted by the 5th Circuit in Gulf Restoration Network, et al. v. EPA preserves the agency's appeal of a case that officials had warned could undermine its water quality program and set an important procedural precedent.
While states in the Mississippi River Basin, most notably Iowa, are beginning to craft nutrient reduction plans, environmentalists argue they often rely on voluntary measures that don't do enough to reduce the amount of nitrogen and phosphorous that eventually travels to the Gulf of Mexico and creates a hypoxic "dead zone."
In a recent letter, environmentalists suggest the agency should "at least begin" to craft regulatory limits in some states in the basin, calling for a piecemeal approach to overcome agency concern about the time and resources needed to create standards for all 10 states.
An expanded monitoring effort could help show that states are serious about solving complicated nutrient issues even as many proceed slowly on creating numeric criteria, Hokanson says.
The expanded monitoring strategy will likely be implemented slowly at first, Hokanson says, with some states hoping to start pilot projects using existing funding within a few years. States will also retain ultimate decision-making authority over management actions such as which waters they list as impaired.
"The notion here is to lay out the desired monitoring framework" that states can then use to "either jointly or independently build up their monitoring programs," Hokanson says.
Initially, officials can use the plan as a filter to look at existing monitoring data from stations maintained by the Army Corps of Engineers, the U.S. Geological Survey or individual states.
He adds that other coordinated monitoring efforts, such as those for the Ohio River and Delaware River, have been around for longer and "have a little more institutional muscle" than UMRBA's effort. Those programs, for example, receive a dedicated source of CWA section 106 funding while Mississippi River Basin states have received only periodic grants.
"We are a little more dependent at this time on our states," Hokanson says. "If there comes a day where an additional increment of federal funding is available to cover those identified gaps, that would be hugely helpful." -- Lee Logan
]]></text></news-item>