<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-G5G1-F0JP-W4F8"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Howard's fixer tarred by his brush with Sydney sharpies</title><source>The Advertiser (Australia)</source><author>LAURIE OAKES THE NATION</author><text><![CDATA[AS THEY try to explain how Arthur Sinodinos got himself into such an unholy mess, his Coalition colleagues are homing in on the idea that Sydney is to blame.
Sidelined from his role as federal Assistant Treasurer while the NSW Independent Commission against Corruption (ICAC) investigates a company he once headed, Sinodinos is being talked about as a gullible victim of the Emerald City's urgers and shysters.
Under this scenario, the former Treasury official who came to prominence as John Howard's powerful and long-serving chief of staff was a naive innocent when he left Canberra in 2006, seeking a commercial career and a political role in the big smoke.
"In Arthur's former world he could make assumptions about probity and people's behaviour," says a Coalition MP.
"He could basically assume that processes had been followed. That's very public sector.
"But then he goes to Sydney. He doesn't have much experience and background in business. And he gets there at a time when, even by Sydney's terms, there's an ethical trough." The sharpies see him coming, and he is deceived and exploited by the inheritors of the Rum Corps traditions so pervasive in business and politics in the NSW capital.
"It's a Sydney thing," says a Liberal backroom operator in Melbourne. "They do it differently up there." The implication being that Sinodinos's sheltered Canberra background would have left him quite unprepared to handle Sydney's rogues.
Liberal Senate leader Eric Abetz used the naivety defence publicly after Sinodinos stood aside from the ministry pending his ICAC appearance.
Abetz told a television interviewer: "People with less honourable motives than Mr Sinodinos may well have sought to have involved him to provide their enterprise with a veneer of respectability." The theories illustrate the surprise in the Liberal Party - and outside it as well - that Sinodinos, regarded by just about everybody as a straight-shooter, has become the Abbott Government's first ministerial casualty.
For those who observed Sinodinos as Howard's shrewd right-hand man, the image of him as a naive fool does not sit well.
But nor does any other explanation for his involvement with the company, Australian Water Holdings, of which he was first a director and then chairman, before entering the Senate in 2011.
At the core of the current ICAC investigation, Operation Credo, are dodgy activities to do with the company's attempt to secure a private-public water infrastructure deal with the NSW Government.
It was revealed at ICAC that Sinodinos was getting $200,000 a year for 100 hours work plus 5 per cent of the company's shares at no cost, and would have reaped a $10 million to $20 million bonus if the public-private partnership deal had come off.
"It's quite transparent that Mr Sinodinos's true role in Australian Water Holdings was to open lines of communication with the Liberal Party and there will be evidence that he tried to do so," counsel assisting the inquiry, Geoffrey Watson SC, said on the opening day.
Watson has hammered the point that Sinodinos had no experience in water or sewerage infrastructure and was only useful to AWH because of the political influence he could bring to bear as the Liberals ousted Labor from office in NSW.
Sinodinos has said somebody should have told him that corrupt Labor powerbroker Eddie Obeid was associated with the company. But did he carry out no due diligence himself?
He has also said he was unaware the company was making donations to the Liberal Party (disguised as "administration costs" and, in a remarkable scam, charged back to the public utility Sydney Water) even though he was also the party's state finance director and later president.
Political donations were never discussed at company board meetings, according to Sinodinos.
But a witness told ICAC on Thursday that they were detailed in AWH management accounts available to the board.
ICAC announced on the first day of public hearings that several people had been cleared of any wrongdoing.
But Watson said of the stood-aside minister: "It's presently difficult to offer observations on the conduct of Mr Sinodinos. He has other involvements which will come under scrutiny in Operation Spicer." Operation Spicer involves AWH donations to a secret Liberal-associated slush fund that is being investigated for corruption.
So Sinodinos is required as a witness in two inquiries, not just one - almost certainly bad news for those who hope he will be able to make a quick return to the ministry.
Tony Abbott is letting it be known via proxies in the media that Sinodinos will be restored to the frontbench eventually, unless there is a clear finding of corruption against him - something no-one expects.
For anyone else, a comeback would almost certainly depend on how he performed in the witness box and the nature of the evidence to which Watson referred.
That is a clear indication of how important Sinodinos is to the Government. It needs his policy rigour and corporate memory.
Whatever happens, though, Sinodinos's brief association with Sydney's seamy side will leave him a diminished figure.LAURIE OAKES IS POLITICAL EDITOR FOR THE NINE NETWORK
]]></text></news-item>