<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-CCR1-JC8R-30JD"><date>2014-03-20</date><title></title><source>Pittsburgh Post-Gazette</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[CON ED PAYS 87 VICTIMS FOLLOWING NYC BLAST
NEW YORK - Con Edison has made compensation payments to 87 survivors and residents displaced by the fatal building explosion last week in New York City.
The utility says it began making the payments last Thursday, a day after the blast.
This week, federal investigators found a leak in the gas main near one of the two East Harlem apartment buildings that were leveled. Eight people were killed and more than 60 were injured.
Con Ed spokesman Robert McGee says most of the people in the effected buildings have already contacted the utility.
He declined to provide the average amount paid for each person who was injured or lost his or her home.
The payments were made after "one-on-one" meetings with the victims.
The cause of the explosion hasn't been determined. NUCLEAR WASTE MAY GO TO TEXAS
ALBUQUERQUE, N.M. - The operator of the nation's troubled nuclear waste dump in southeastern New Mexico wants to temporarily store waste from Los Alamos National Laboratory in rural West Texas until it reopens.
Waste storage at the Waste Isolation Pilot Plant near Carlsbad is halted because of a Feb. 5 truck fire and a Feb. 14 radiation leak that contaminated 17 workers. Nuclear Waste Partnership says it and the Department of Energy propose to ship Los Alamos waste to a Waste Control Specialists site in Texas' Andrews County.
The partnership says the waste would go to the New Mexico plant for final disposal once it reopens.
Los Alamos has promised the state it will get the last of thousands of barrels of plutonium-contaminated clothing, tools, rags and other debris off its campus by June. REPORT: CALIF. TOP CRIME TARGET
SACRAMENTO, Calif. - California is the top target in the U.S. for international criminal enterprises that operate from safe havens in Eastern Europe, Africa and China, according to a report being released Thursday.
Along with trafficking in drugs, guns and people, criminals are also turning to cybercrime to target wealthy, innovative businesses and financial institutions in the state, California Attorney General Kamala Harris said in the report.
"California is a global leader on a number of fronts and, unfortunately, transnational criminal activity is one of them," the report states.
Ms. Harris said the report is the first to outline the effects of international criminal organizations on California residents and businesses.
She was set to formally release the 181-page report during a news conference with other law enforcement officials in Los Angeles. It was obrained in advance by The Associated Press. It says California leads all states in the number of computer systems hacked or infected by malware; victims of Internet crimes and identity theft; and the amount of financial losses suffered as a result of online crimes.
The state also is particularly vulnerable to thefts of intellectual property because of its leading role in developing new technologies and mass-media entertainment. WESTBORO PASTOR DIES
TOPEKA, Kansas - The Rev. Fred Phelps Sr., the fiery founder of a small Kansas church who drew international condemnation for outrageous and hate-filled protests that blamed almost everything, including the deaths of AIDS victims and U.S. soldiers, on America's tolerance for gay people, has died. He was 84.
Daughter Margie Phelps told The Associated Press that Fred Phelps, whose actions drew international condemnation, died around midnight Wednesday. She didn't provide the cause of death or the condition that recently put him in hospice care.
Throughout his life, Phelps and the Westboro Baptist Church, a small congregation made up almost entirely of his extended family, tested the boundaries of free speech, violating accepted societal standards for decency in their unapologetic assault on gays and lesbians. In the process, some believe he even helped the cause of gay rights by serving as such a provocative symbol of intolerance.
Rev. Phelps believed any misfortune, most infamously the deaths of American soldiers killed in Iraq and Afghanistan, was God's punishment for society's tolerance of homosexuality. He and his followers carried forward their message bluntly, holding held signs at funerals and public events that used ugly slurs and read "Thank God for dead soldiers." God, he preached, had nothing but anger and bile for the moral miscreants of his creation. GUM LOSES ITS POP
NEW YORK- Gum seems as appealing as that sticky wad on the bottom of a shoe these days.
It's not that Americans still don't ever enjoy a stick of Trident or Orbit, the two most popular brands. They just aren't as crazy about chomping away on the stuff as they once were, with U.S. sales tumbling 11 percent over the past four years.
No one in the industry can pinpoint a single factor that's causing the decline - the theories include an unwillingness to shell out $2 or more for a pack in the bad economy or that advertising veered too far from underlining gum's cavity-fighting benefits. But the biggest reason may be that people simply have more to chew on.
From designer mints to fruit chews, candy companies have invented plenty of other ways to get a sugar fix or battle bad breath and anxiety. The alternatives don't come with gum's unpleasant characteristics either, like the question of whether to spit out or gulp the remains. They're also less likely to annoy parents, co-workers or romantic interests.
"You talk to someone and they're just chomping on gum," said Matt Smith, a 46-year-old who lives Albany, N.Y. and hates gum so much he refers to it only by its first letter. "If you substitute gum for any other food, like mashed potatoes, would you find that acceptable? It's disgusting."
The gum chewing habit dates as far back as the ancient Greeks but arrived in the U.S. in its modern form in the 1860s, according to Mars Inc., the No. 1 player in the market with its Wrigley unit.
]]></text></news-item>