<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSX-YV41-DYRD-S3W1"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>News briefing</title><source>Sun-Sentinel (Fort Lauderdale, Florida)</source><author>Tribune Newspapers and news services</author><text><![CDATA[Gunmen attack luxury hotel in center of Kabul
KABUL, Afghanistan -- Taliban gunmen attacked a luxury hotel Thursday in the center of the Afghan capital, Kabul, police said, and four of the assailants were killed in a shootout with Afghan security forces.
Interior Ministry spokesman Sediq Sediqi told Reuters all the gunmen were dead and security forces were in control of the hotel. He said he was not aware of deaths among the staff or guests, but checks were underway and Afghan special forces were on the scene.
The attackers appear to have entered the hotel around 6 p.m. local time with pistols hidden in their socks and waited three hours to start their attack, he said.
They fired on guests and then hid in bathrooms when security forces arrived, he said. The gunmen appeared to be under 18 years old.
Two guards had been wounded, he said. No other casualties were confirmed.
Taliban spokesman Zabiullah Mujahid claimed responsibility for the attack and said the attackers had fired at foreign and Afghan guests celebrating the Afghan new year.
Earlier Thursday, the Taliban attacked a police station in the southern city of Jalalabad with multiple suicide bombers and gunmen. At least 11 people were killed.
The Taliban have vowed to kill anyone associated with next month's presidential elections.
The April 5 polls should mark the first time one elected government hands power to another in the history of Afghanistan. Report: Gang caused mass displacement in Colombia
Human Rights Watch on Thursday blamed the Urabenos criminal gang for helping cause one of Colombia's worst humanitarian crises in years: the forced displacement last year of 19,000 people from the city of Buenaventura.
The displacements, representing 5 percent of the Pacific port city's population of 370,000, were only part of the mayhem perpetrated by the Urabenos gang members, the rights group said. Officials consider the gang the nation's biggest drug trafficker. 5 men are convicted in Mumbai rape cases
MUMBAI, India -- Five men were convicted Thursday for raping a photojournalist and a call-center operator in separate incidents that underlined India's problem of sexual violence.
A court in Mumbai found the men guilty of gang rape, destruction of evidence and other crimes in the attacks that occurred weeks apart last summer at an abandoned textile mill in the heart of the city. Three of the men were convicted in both incidents. Ala. lawmakers approve medical marijuana bill
BIRMINGHAM, Ala. -- A medical marijuana bill unanimously passed both the Alabama House and Senate on Thursday and is headed to the desk of Gov. Robert Bentley, who has said he will sign it into law.
The measure makes it legal to possess only a prescribed medical grade extract known as CBD or cannabidiol, which is nonintoxicating.
Congress in 1972 deemed the oil to have no accepted medical use. N.J. teen arrested for sneaking to top of WTC
A New Jersey teenager managed to wiggle through a security fence, then make his way past a guard to the spire atop 1 World Trade Center, the nation's tallest building, where he took pictures before he was apprehended, officials said Thursday.
The boy, whom authorities said was being treated as an adult, was charged with misdemeanor criminal trespass in the Sunday morning stunt and faces up to a year in jail if convicted. The Newsmaker Reid orders probe of alleged CIA hacking
Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid backed the head of the Senate Intelligence Committee on Thursday in a dispute with the CIA, ordering an investigation into what he called an "indefensible" breach of the panel's computers. N.C. cites Duke Energy for dumping coal ash
FAYETTEVILLE, N.C. -- North Carolina regulators cited Duke Energy on Thursday, saying the utility deliberately dumped 61 million gallons of toxic coal ash waste into a tributary of the Cape Fear River, which provides drinking water for several cities and towns.
The state Department of Environment and Natural Resources said the utility illegally pumped the ash from two ponds at its Cape Fear plant and into a canal flowing into tributaries of Cape Fear. Teens plead not guilty to murder of Aussie athlete
OKLAHOMA CITY -- Two Oklahoma teenagers charged with first-degree murder in the death of an Australian baseball player attending a university in the state pleaded not guilty at an arraignment on Thursday, a court clerk said.
The two are accused of shooting Chris Lane, 22, in the back as he was jogging in August 2013 near East Central University. Lane was a student on a baseball scholarship at the school. The teens will go on trial Aug. 18, the court clerk said. Vatican library plans to digitize its archives
VATICAN CITY -- The Vatican library began a project Thursday to digitize thousands of historical manuscripts, dating from the origins of the church to the 20th century, and make them available online.
Working with the Japanese technology group NTT Data, the library intends to scan and digitally archive about 1.5 million pages from the library's collection of manuscripts, which comprises some 82,000 items and 41 million pages.
]]></text></news-item>