<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-G831-JC8W-6534"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Bond trader fined £700,000 over ploy to exploit QE: FCA issues ban on former Credit Suisse director: Market rigged to profit from Bank's programme</title><source>The Guardian (London) - Final Edition</source><author>Press Association</author><text><![CDATA[A former Credit Suisse trader who saw the Bank of England's quantitative easing (QE) programme as "cake" to profit from has been fined nearly £700,000 after rigging the price of UK bonds.
Mark Stevenson, a bond trader with nearly 30 years' experience, was also banned from the industry by the Financial Conduct Authority (FCA) after his attempt to exploit the £375bn programme intended to help nurse the economy back to health.
The FCA found that he artificially ramped up the price of a £1.2bn holding in a set of gilts hours before he intended to sell them to the Bank. His unusual trading was reported within 40 minutes and officials at Threadneedle Street decided not to buy the gilts, which it had been due to buy as part of QE.
The FCA found the trading had the potential to affect taxpayers, since if the Bank had overpaid for the bond its losses would be shouldered by the Treasury.
Details of the episode in October 2011 surfaced publicly last summer when the Bank's executive director for markets, Paul Fisher, told MPs that claims about the "thoroughly reprehensible" allegations had been referred to the regulator.
Yesterday the FCA announced that Stevenson, who left Credit Suisse last December, had been fined £662,700 after qualifying for a 30% discount from a £946,800 fine because he agreed to settle early.
It is the first enforcement action for manipulation of the gilt market, and follows a series of market-rigging scandals.
Banks have been fined billions for manipulation of the Libor interbank lending rate and world regulators are investigating allegations of foreign exchange rate rigging that could be at least as serious.
Tracey McDermott, FCA director of enforcement, said: "Stevenson's abuse took advantage of a policy designed to boost the economy with no regard for the potential consequences for other market participants and, ultimately, for UK taxpayers.
"He has paid a heavy price for his actions. Fair dealing is at the heart of market integrity. This case sends a clear message about how seriously the FCA views attempts to manipulate the market."
The FCA described Stevenson's actions as "particularly egregious". It said the episode was the action of one trader on one day, and there was no evidence of collusion with other banks.
The FCA's findings described how the Bank of England had announced that its tranche of bond buying as part of QE would take place on 10 October 2011. Between 9am and 2.30pm on that day, Stevenson significantly increased his holding in the relevant gilt, accounting for 92% of its turnover that day.
"Given his significant market experience he was fully aware of the impact this would have - and traded with the express intention of increasing the gilt's price."
By 9.39am others in the market had notified the Bank of this unusual activity, saying the bond had been "squeezed" and "rammed". One trader said it appeared to be a deliberate attempt to push the price higher to sell later in the day.
The gilt's performance significantly outperformed others on the day but fell back after the Bank took the "unprecedented step" of announcing it would not be buying it. Had it gone ahead with the trade, Stevenson would have accounted for 70% of the £1.7bn allocated to QE that day, the FCA found.
The findings revealed details of a telephone conversation between Stevenson and a broker days earlier, in which he said "we've been loading up with QE trades for months" and described QE as "cake". The FCA concluded that he "was indicating his belief that QE was an opportunity to profit from selling gilts to the BoE".
"Mr Stevenson has stated he bought the bond because he believed it was cheap and not with the definite intention of offering to sell it to the BoE later that day." But the FCA concluded his trading was designed to move the price of the bond.
It also found Credit Suisse "stood to make significant sums of money" had the bond offer been accepted by the Bank, and Stevenson would have "indirectly benefited". Stevenson was a director on the company's London bond trading desk and was "able to trade with a large degree of autonomy".
The FCA said neither the firm nor any of its other employees were subject to criticism from the ruling.
Credit Suisse said: "We agree with the FCA's decision to sanction Mr Stevenson and are pleased to note that neither Credit Suisse nor any other employed individuals have been found at fault.
"The bank co-operated fully with the investigations into this matter by the Bank of England and Financial Conduct Authority."
Guilt-edged trading:
£1.2bn
Value of Stevenson's holding in the gilt that the Bank of England intended to buy on 10 October 2011
£331m
Amount of his holding that he bought between 9am and 2.30pm that day - thus inflating the price
70%
Proportion of the day's £1.7bn allocated for QE that would have gone to Stevenson if the sale had gone ahead
92%
Proportion of the day's trading in the bond accounted for by Stevenson
]]></text></news-item>