<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-TGK1-JC6P-C2FM"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>EDITORIAL: Execution and privacy -- Alabama shouldn't shield information about death penalty from public view</title><source>The Anniston Star (Alabama)</source><author>The Anniston Star, Ala.</author><text><![CDATA[March 21--Alabama's rush to hide the drugs used to execute prisoners is the perfect explanation of a state swimming against the tide of public opinion with a little crony capitalism tossed in for good measure. Granted, this is a familiar posture for Alabama.
Here's the background: It's becoming increasingly difficult for Alabama as well as other states that use capital punishment to acquire the drug or drugs used in lethal injections.
Why, you ask? Because manufacturers of these drugs (many of which are based in Europe, where capital punishment is banned) aren't anxious to have their products tied to state executions.
In the United States, public support for the death penalty is also dropping, from 80 percent approval in 1994 to 60 percent in 2013, according to Gallup. The number of death-penalty sentences is also dropping.
Compounding this perception problem is the uneven way in which the death penalty is applied. According to the Equal Justice Initiative, "Each year in Alabama, nearly 65 [percent] of all murders involve black victims, yet 80 [percent] of the people currently awaiting execution in Alabama were convicted of crimes in which the victims were white."
Of course, in the Alabama Legislature, support for the death penalty by the majority of its members is largely unmoved by this evidence.
State Rep. Lynn Greer, R-Rogersville, sponsored a bill that would make much of the information about how Alabama executes prisoners a secret. If his bill becomes law, any person or any company involved in the manufacture of death-penalty drugs would be shielded from the public.
"If a company is defined as a supplier of a drug, there could be some blowback against that company," according to Department of Corrections spokesman Brian Corbett last month.
Greer's proposal passed the House of Representatives and now awaits a vote in the Senate.
The state of Alabama is in a big-time rush to protect a few businesses from public scrutiny. We're left wondering what's happened to all those full-throated advocates of the free market in Montgomery.
Do they have duct-tape covering their mouths? That must be it.
Why else would they shield a few businesses from the public's right to know and possibly protest those companies' actions?
___ (c)2014 The Anniston Star (Anniston, Ala.) Visit The Anniston Star (Anniston, Ala.) at www.annistonstar.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>