<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-3MB1-DXKS-J3DR"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>New Technology Takes Water Out of Coal Separation; Mineral Separation Technologies Introduces New System</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Mineral Separation Technologies announced today that it has created a new product, the DriJet 100, that separates coal and ash without using water or chemicals.

The introduction of the DriJet 100 follows the recent chemical spill on the Elk River in Charleston, West Virginia. A liquid used for separating coal leaked from a storage containment tank into the river. The spill endangered more than 300,000 West Virginia residents.
"DriJet technology has many valuable practical applications. Perhaps the most important one is that it eliminates the possibility of a chemical spill such as the one that happened recently in Charleston," said Charles D. Roos, CEO of Mineral Separation Technologies. 
Mineral Separation Technologies, a Coal Center, Pa.-based company, recently received a patent for its DriJet technology, a process that uses x-rays to identify the atomic weight of coal particles and air jets to separate coal from ash. The DriJet 100 has been field-tested and is now available to coal companies nationwide.
"We remove the ash right at the mine face. Our technology means fewer coal trucks on the road and less coal waste in impoundments," Roos said. "It cuts the cost from mine to market. And it is much better for the environment than processes now in use."
DriJet requires low horsepower and has few moving parts. Operating costs, compared to other coal preparation technologies, are low.
"Simply stated, our technology is cleaner, portable and more reliable than traditional coal prep plants," Roos said.
Major components of the DriJet are manufactured in Beckley, WV. 
For more information, visit http://www.mineralseparationtechnologies.com.
Photo -http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20140321/NY88255
SOURCE Mineral Separation Technologies
]]></text></news-item>