<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-25J1-JD34-V0XN"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Building firms tax case finds crime figure link</title><source>The Age (Melbourne, Australia)</source><author>Nick Ralston, Nick McKenzie, Richard Baker</author><text><![CDATA[A Tax Office-backed Federal Court action to recover at least $1 million in unpaid tax from allegedly corrupt building industry figure George Alex has exposed his dealings with crime figures and union officials.
While much of the most explosive evidence from the Federal Court hearings in Melbourne and Sydney has been suppressed due to concerns that witnesses could be subject to underworld reprisals, evidence able to be reported includes allegations that:
"Mr Alex and his associate recently murdered standover man Joe Atoun, attempted to force several building industry identities to hand over millions of dollars in what some witnesses have alleged involve corrupt dealings or stand-over tactics.
"Mr Alex has allegedly helped to operate a network of construction companies across Australia using fronts to disguise his involvement.
"Mr Alex had close ties to the CFMEU, including a union official known as "Sparkles" - who Fairfax Media understands is NSW CFMEU secretary Brian Parker.
A business associate of Mr Alex, whose name Fairfax Media has decided not to publish for legal reasons, told the Federal Court on Friday morning that "Sparkles" had attended Mr Alex's house in Burwood.
Other details about the construction union's dealings with Mr Alex have been suppressed although building industry and legal sources said it is likely to be aired at the coming royal commission on unions.
Other witnesses in the proceedings have described how a range of underworld identities also conducted meetings at Mr Alex's home.
Fairfax Media has previously revealed Mr Alex is a crime figure allegedly involved in corrupt building industry dealings in Melbourne and Sydney, including scams to avoid paying his obligations to workers and the tax office.
Fairfax has also reported two senior CFMEU whistleblowers have claimed certain union officials turned a blind eye to Mr Alex's corrupt dealings - including non-payment of workers - and instead promoted his business in Sydney and Melbourne, where Mr Alex used underworld boss Mick Gatto as an industrial mediator.
Mr Parker has stated all his dealings with Mr Alex have been appropriate.
In bankruptcy proceedings against Mr Alex, solicitor Chris Rumore, who has appeared before the Independent Commission Against Corruption for his links to the Obeid family, said he had done work for Mr Atoun.
Mr Rumore, a senior partner at Colin, Biggers and Paisley, said he had no involvement with Mr Alex and a series of companies associated with him. He said he had no recollection of ever meeting him.
"I never considered him our client," Mr Rumore said. "I still don't."
Mr Rumore said he was approached by another legal firm that said it had some "good clients who had a series of complex commercial transactions" relating to the company.
Documents before the NSW Supreme Court allege Mr Alex, Mr Atoun and Mr Gatto persuaded Queensland businessman Kevin McHugh to sign over the labour hire firm to the trio.
Mr McHugh alleged Mr Alex and another man demanded he attend a meeting on the Gold Coast with Mr Gatto where he was threatened. Mr McHugh alleges Mr Gatto said he was speaking on behalf of others who had determined the companies were owned by Mr Alex. Mr McHugh alleges he was vulnerable and eventually signed over the companies.
]]></text></news-item>