<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-K7H1-DYT4-K2DJ"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>ANOTHER WEEK</title><source>Financial Mail (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ANOTHER WEEK
AFRICA
Al-Shabab fighters attack a hotel in the strategic central town of Bulo-burde in Somalia where African Union and army commanders were staying after the militants lost control of it last week.
A French court jails ex-Rwandan spy chief Pascal Simbikangwa for 25 years over the 1994 genocide.
Nigeria's president Goodluck Jonathan orders a forensic audit of the state oil firm following claims that US$20bn are missing.
Malawi is forced to withdraw from qualifying for the 2015 Africa Cup of Nations in Morocco because of a lack of funds.
A student is killed in clashes with police at Sudan's Khartoum University during a protest against violence in Darfur.
Libya's parliament dismisses PM Ali Zeidan after a tanker laden with oil from a rebel-held port broke through a naval blockade. Defence minister Abdullah al-Thinni is named interim prime minister.
Died: Ahmad Tejan Kabbah (82), Sierra Leone's ex-president and wartime leader.
ABROAD
The US and EU declare the referendum vote on Crimean secession illegal and impose travel bans and asset freezes on government officials in Russia and Crimea, which are dismissed by Moscow as ineffectual. Russian president Vladimir Putin tells parliament that Crimea had "always been part of Russia". US president Barack Obama asks G7 and EU leaders to attend a summit on the Ukraine crisis in The Hague.
As part of a radical shake-up at the Bank of England, governor Mark Carney names two new deputy governors: Ben Broadbent, responsible for monetary policy; and Nemat Shafik for markets and banking.
US regulator, the FDIC, sues 16 banks, among them Barclays, HSBC and Citigroup, for allegedly manipulating the London interbank offered rate (Libor).
Vodafone agrees to buy Spanish cable operator Ono for & 8364;7,2bn.
Chinese e-commerce giant Alibaba plans a flotation in the US to make it "a more global company".
El Salvador's electoral court confirms the victory of ex left-wing rebel Salvador Sánchez Cerén in a presidential run-off poll.
The US lifts a ban on oil giant BP that prevented it from bidding for US government contracts following the 2010 Gulf of Mexico oil spill.
Israeli warplanes strike 29 targets in the Gaza Strip in response to a rocket barrage from Gaza into Israel.
Six people die and several are missing after a gas leak sparked an explosion which razed two buildings in New York's Spanish Harlem district.
Sixty Shanghai maths teachers are to be brought to England to raise standards, in an exchange arranged by the department of education.
Died: Tony Benn (88), veteran British Labour politician.
PACT Russian president Vladimir Putin and Crimean leaders join hands after signing a treaty on the Ukrainian Black Sea peninsula becoming part of Russia, at the Kremlin on Tuesday, after 97% of voters in a referendum backed splitting away from Ukraine.
]]></text></news-item>