<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-5NY1-JCTS-G54D"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Oil companies may get more pipeline land rights </title><source>Flint Journal (Michigan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[URL: http://www.mlive.com/lansing-news/index.ssf/2014/03/oil_companies_may_get_tax_brea.html
By Jonathan Oosting
joosting@mlive.com
Oil and gas companies would receive tax breaks for reusing carbon dioxide to tap capped wells and have more power to obtain land for pipelines under legislation working its way to the desk of Gov. Rick Snyder.
The Republican-led state Senate approved the last measure in a four-bill package Wednesday in a 25-13 vote, sending it back to the House for concurrence.
The legislation would give companies incentives to invest in infrastructure needed for a process known as secondary or enhanced recovery, which involves flooding wells with carbon dioxide to bring previously unattainable oil or natural gas to the surface. It would not apply to hydraulic fracturing projects.
Supporters argue the tax break -- a 4 percent rate on the gross cash market value of total production, down from 5 percent for gas and 6.6 percent for oil -- would apply only to extractions that would otherwise be impossible. Critics say it would benefit big oil and gas companies who are doing just fine on their own.
"The bottom line is that this is about energy security, environmental protection and Michigan's economy," state Rep. Aric Nesbitt, R-Lawton, said on the floor last month before the lower chamber approved the package in a series of bipartisan votes.
One of the bills -- which would let companies try to condemn property through eminent domain in order to obtain right-of-way access for oil, gas or carbon dioxide pipelines -- got some blowback in the House, with a handful of Republicans joining several Democrats in opposition.
All 12 Senate Democrats, along with one Republican, voted against the tax break bill Wednesday.
(File photo)
An oil worker at a Napoleon Township drilling site.
@la-river @mlive-business @mlive-environment @mlive-news @mlive-politics @mlive-river aric nesbitt
]]></text></news-item>