<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-SV41-DYT8-R37P"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>MSHA cites company in coal slurry death</title><source>Charleston Gazette (West Virginia)</source><author>Ken Ward Jr., Staff writer</author><text><![CDATA[Mine management tried to expand a coal-slurry impoundment faster than was considered safe, and continued the work despite warnings that the site was becoming unstable, according to a new federal government report being issued this week.
U.S. Mine Safety and Health Administration investigators cited Consolidation Coal Co. for three alleged violations as a result of their investigation into the November 2012 collapse of a Harrison County slurry embankment that killed a miner, according to a report provided to family members on Wednesday.
Dozer operator Markel Koon, 58, of Shinnston, was swept into the impoundment shortly after noon on Nov. 30, 2012, in the collapse of a smaller "saddle dike, or a dam being built at a low spot in the surrounding topography.
Two other workers who ended up in the impoundment managed to survive. One of them swam to safety, while the other made it to a large slab of coal waste and was rescued by local firefighters. Koon's body, still inside his dozer, wasn't recovered for two weeks.
The incident occurred while the dike - constructed of coarse coal refuse piled on top of finer coal slurry - was being built as part of the expansion of the Nolan Run impoundment near Lumberport, so the site could continue to accept waste from the nearby Robinson Run Mine's preparation plant.
In its new report, MSHA concludes that the embankment was raised faster than the strength of the coal waste it was being built on top of could support.
Federal investigators said that the embankment was supposed to be built using a coal-waste "delta, involving a build-up of sediment that generally forms at the spot where slurry is discharged because of the larger particles settling sooner than the finer particles suspended in the slurry. MSHA said that because deltas are composed of the coarser portion of coal refuse, they are more permeable and have the ability to consolidate more rapidly than finer coal waste. In addition, the weight of the delta consolidates the underlying material, strengthening it, the MSHA report said. MSHA found, though, that the saddle dike was not placed on an exposed coal waste delta.
"The dike failure occurred because the load of the embankment exceeded the strength of the foundation materials, the MSHA report said.
Also, MSHA said that the mine operator waited too long to install a pressure gauge to get a baseline reading and allow proper monitoring of the stability of the site. MSHA said the pressure gauge, called a piezometer, was placed in the wrong location.
And even after the gauge was installed, the mine operator "continued to place fill on the saddle dike after additional stability analysis indicated a factor of safety lower than what was specified in the approved plan.
Pressure readings on Nov. 23 - a week before the collapse - and on the morning of the incident both showed excess pressures within the area where the embankment was being built, the MSHA report said. MSHA said the company ignored a requirement to report to the agency "a potentially hazardous condition concerning stability of the site.
The death occurred when the impoundment was operated by a subsidiary of Pittsburgh-based CONSOL Energy. In December 2013, a year after the impoundment collapse, the operation was purchased by Ohio-based Murray Energy. CONSOL referred questions about the MSHA report to Murray Energy. A spokesman for Murray Energy said in an email, "Murray Energy Corporation had absolutely nothing to do with the fatality or the report. We, therefore, have no comment.
Tim Bailey, a lawyer for the Koon family, said Thursday, "The family is extremely disheartened to learn that Mr. Koon's death was entirely preventable and that CONSOL's conduct violated mine safety regulations and the approved plans.
Reach Ken Ward Jr. at kward@wvgazette.com or 304-348-1702.
]]></text></news-item>