<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-BC51-DXHF-W1WD"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>City hints at 'canned hunting'</title><source>The Herald (South Africa)</source><author>Rochelle De Kock</author><text><![CDATA[Debacle over rates rebates for Bay game parks rages on in council THE Nelson Mandela Bay Municipality does not want to give annual rates rebates to the Kragga Kamma Game Park and Seaview Predator Park, saying it cannot be sure that the two game parks are not participating in "canned hunting".
The municipality claims the council would be seen in an extremely poor light if it was later discovered that the two tourist attractions were involved in "such unethical practices". Over the years, the policy has allowed the two game parks to receive a 75% discount on normal business and commercial property rates, but the rates policy was amended last year to include an ambiguous line that the parks should be used predominantly as game parks with the sole purpose of viewing of animals. The contradictory wording created confusion among municipal staff, who refused to grant any discounts to the two game parks because both have restaurants and/or curio shops. The metro ruled that this was not using the parks for the sole purpose of viewing animals. As a result, both parks have not received rebates, meaning they must each pay more than R10000 a month for rates, backdated to July last year. Earlier this month, the two businesses said losing the rates rebate meant they might be forced to close their gates, or hike their prices. At a joint mayoral and budget and treasury committee meeting yesterday, councillors said the proposal that game parks' rebates be revoked had to go out for public participation. Councillors also wanted to visit the two parks to see if there was any breeding and selling of game, and to see if the companies were not making a lot more money than was disclosed. In a report to the committee yesterday, signed by corporate services director Mod Ndoyana, it states the municipality must "treat property owners liable for rates equitably and any rebates must be fair". "A municipality may not levy rates which unreasonably discriminate between categories of non-residential properties; nor may a municipality grant relief to owners on an individual basis." The report adds that other businesses in the tourism industry could claim they were not being treated equally. "There have been numerous reports in the media regarding the unethical treatment of lions. There has been much media speculation in the past few years as to what happens to all the lions that are being bred in captivity. It has been suggested that many are being used for the controversial 'canned hunting' industry." David Cantor, co-owner of the Kragga Kamma Game Park, said he would challenge any insinuations that they sold animals or were allowing hunting to take place. "They say we are making a huge profit, but that's so untrue," Cantor said. "There is no hunting at our park; we focus on conservation. If we are going to be accused, they need to put some facts into place. "However, it is positive that the deputy mayor [Chippa Ngcolomba] suggested they come for a site visit. We welcome that." Seaview Predators Park owner Rusty Gibb could not be reached for comment. However, he previously told The Herald they bought and sold animals. He did not mention anything about hunting.
]]></text></news-item>