<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-K4G1-DY7P-S049"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Twin Liquors at risk of closing</title><source>Austin American-Statesman (Texas)</source><author>Gary Dinges American-Statesman Staff</author><text><![CDATA[Austin-based Twin Liquors could be forced to shut down by a Texas Alcoholic Beverage Commission investigation - and the company says the agency suspects it of having ties to notorious local nightclub operator Yassine Enterprises.
The claims, made in a newly filed lawsuit, are the first public confirmation that investigators are looking into links between Twin Liquors and Yassine Enterprises. Three members of the Yassine family were accused by federal agents of a variety of drug trafficking, money laundering and weapons charges in 2012 and are now serving time in federal prison.
In documents obtained by the American-Statesman, attorneys for Twin Liquors say the TABC is seeking to revoke the company's liquor permits because state and federal investigators believe Twin Liquors had dealings with Yassine Enterprises. Such a move could force the chain, which operates more than 20 area stores, to shut down, the lawsuit claims.
The suit, filed in Travis County District Court, contends that Twin Liquors has been denied access to documents, has been prevented from questioning witnesses and that the TABC has exceeded its statutory authority.
A joint task force composed of state and federal agents scoured Twin Liquors' Airport Boulevard headquarters in April of last year, questioning employees and carting off several boxes of records. At the time, spokesmen for the FBI and IRS told the American-Statesman they were "conducting official business," but they wouldn't elaborate.
The company's stores have remained open during the investigation.
TABC spokeswoman Carolyn Beck confirmed Thursday that the agency has a pending case against Twin Liquors and is seeking permanent revocation of the company's alcohol permits. She said she couldn't comment specifically on claims made in the pending suit, citing TABC policy.
A search of TABC records shows that many of Twin Liquors' locations in Austin and elsewhere across the state - including Bee Cave, Burnet, Cedar Park, Georgetown, Kingsland, Lakeway, Marble Falls, Pflugerville, Round Rock, San Antonio, San Marcos, Taylor, West Lake Hills and Wimberley - have permit renewal applications marked as "pending." Permits for a few other locations are listed as "expired."
A handful of those locations are shown as having alleged TABC violations, documents say, including prohibited relationships, inappropriate marketing practices, cash and credit law infractions, inducement and conspiracy to receive unlawful benefits, among other allegations.
Founded by members of the Jabour family, Twin Liquors dates to the 19th century, according to its website, twinliquors.com. David Jabour is listed as the company's current president, with Margaret Jabour identified as executive vice president.
Twin Liquors provided a written statement to the American-Statesman on Thursday: "Our attorneys filed a pleading in district court on March 18 concerning technical issues in an effort to further protect our constitutional rights to due process. To be frank, this investigation feels like a witch hunt. We believe we are innocent.
"We have no intention of shutting down and apologize to our staff and customers if anything in the court pleading sent a signal otherwise. TABC has not demonstrated anything that warrants the revocation of any of our permits. We don't agree with what they are doing, and we're vigorously defending ourselves.
"It is business as usual at Twin Liquors. Our customers, employees, wholesalers, and suppliers are our highest priority."
Twin Liquors says in its suit that its attempts to prevent its liquor permits from being revoked have been stymied by officials' refusal to provide copies of the documents that were seized and that permit revocation hearings have been delayed an inordinate amount of time.
"Without review of all documents and things seized by the joint task force and all documents produced by third parties to federal authorities or the TABC, Twin Liquors cannot effectively participate in any discovery process or prepare its defenses to the alleged administrative violations," the lawsuit says.
The company alleges that the TABC has exceeded its statutory authority and that attorneys for Twin Liquors have been unable to question witnesses who have been deposed - or are set to be deposed - by investigators, denying the company of its "statutorily and constitutionally protected due process right."
Twin Liquors also claims the State Office of Administrative Hearings, which typically hears TABC permit revocation cases, doesn't have the authority to hear some or all of the cases linked to the current state and federal investigations.
Attorneys are seeking, among other things, a stay of the proceedings. Failure to do so would cause Twin Liquors "significant harm" and "irreparable injury" and could potentially run afoul of the Fifth Amendment of the U.S. Constitution, which protects against government abuses, according to the suit.
"(T)he TABC now requests that the depositions of Margaret and David Jabour be noticed, and neither Margaret Jabour nor David Jabour can provide testimony without subjecting herself or himself to a real and appreciable risk of self-incrimination," the suit says.
A court date for Twin Liquors' suit has yet to be scheduled, records show.
The nine Yassine nightclubs - Pure, Spill, Kiss & Fly, Treasure Island, Hyde, Fuel, Malaia, Roial and Stack Burger Bar - closed for good the day in March 2012 that they, along with the Yassine Enterprises offices on West Fourth Street in downtown Austin, were raided by state and federal agents.
At a 2012 trial in federal court, prosecutors revealed they had enlisted a cousin of the Yassines as a government informant to assist in that investigation, gathering video and audio recordings used to help prove the government's case.
The cousin, Mo Yassine, was paid hundreds of thousands of dollars for his assistance.
Contact Gary Dinges
at 512-912-5987.
Twitter: @gdinges
]]></text></news-item>