<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-1MJ1-JC8C-21WN"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>Business briefing</title><source>Sun-Sentinel (Fort Lauderdale, Florida)</source><author>Tribune Newspapers and news services</author><text><![CDATA[States to join U.S. review of Comcast deal Florida and other states will join the Justice Department in seeking to determine if Comcast's plan to merge with Time Warner Cable is legal under U.S. antitrust law. "We are part of a multistate group reviewing the proposed transaction along with the U.S. DOJ Antitrust Division," the Florida attorney general's office said. It was not known how many states had joined the task force. Indiana officials were also looking at the deal to determine "the potential impact in Indiana." Pennsylvania, where Comcast is headquartered, was "reviewing the case independently," said Joe Peters, a spokesman for the state's attorney general's office. Comcast had no comment on the states' review of its proposed deal. Comcast has argued that the combination would not reduce competition because the two cable providers do not compete in any markets. The company pledged to divest 3 million subscribers, so the combined customer base of 30 million would represent slightly less than 30 percent of the U.S. pay television video market. A combined Comcast and Time Warner Cable would also have about a one-third share of the high-speed Internet market.
CEO Cook rips book on Apple
Apple CEO Tim Cook has gone out of his way to call a new book, which is focused on the state of his company since the death of Steve Jobs, "nonsense."
Wall Street Journal technology reporter Yukari Iwatani Kane released the book this week. It is titled "Haunted Empire: Apple After Steve Jobs."
"Steve Jobs's death raised one of the most pressing questions in the tech and business worlds: Could Apple stay great without its iconic leader?" the book's description reads.
Cook voiced his displeasure in a statement sent to CNBC. "This nonsense belongs with some of the other books I've read about Apple," Cook said. "It fails to capture Apple, Steve, or anyone else in the company."
Hershey must face Africa case Hershey, the nation's largest chocolate-maker, was ordered to face a lawsuit by investors seeking to force it to turn over records about cocoa from African farms that may use illegal child labor. A Louisiana pension fund raised legitimate questions about Hershey executives' knowledge of how much of the company's cocoa may have been produced by child slaves, a Delaware Chancery Court judge said Tuesday. He overruled a recommendation that the shareholders' request be denied. A Hershey spokesman said the judge ruled on a procedural issue and didn't find the company's West African cocoa-supply system was marred by child labor problems.
The bottom line Chewed-up napkins The alleged means of conveying tips in a new insider trading case. A Morgan Stanley stockbroker and a clerk at a major New York law firm were charged with insider trading in corporate mergers, in an alleged four-year scheme involving a middleman who would chew napkins on which he passed illegal tips at Grand Central Station. Steven Metro, 40, and Vladimir Eydelman, 42, were charged with securities fraud.
]]></text></news-item>