<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-Y9H1-DXDT-62RR"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Female sales executives who claim boss wanted a threesome are 'sex worker' and 'drug dealer's ex' in it 'purely for the cash', tribunal hears</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>RICHARD SPILLETT</author><text><![CDATA[Darren Scott hits back at women who accuse him of sexual harassmentDiana Nicholl-Pierson and Anna Mazover say he asked for a threesomeBut former boss Mr Scott says they are making up the claims to cash inHe says the two women live undesirable 'street-wise' lifestylesMs Nicholl-Pierson cries when she's accused of making up the claimsShe insists she has been treated unfairly and only wants 'justice'She says other men at the company are 'cowards' for not protecting her
A sales director accused of asking two female employees for a threesome has told a tribunal the women are only out to make money.
Sales executives Diana Nicholl-Pierson, 24, and Anna Mazover, 29, claim boss Darren Scott, 55, sexually harassed them during their time publishing firm Entico Corporation Limited
Ms Nicholl-Pierson said that along with Ms Mazover, she was 'subjected to constant sexual comments, sexual advances and sexual innuendos' on a daily basis by Mr Scott.
Mr Scott gave evidence today, telling the hearing the claims had been 'completely fabricated' and Ms Mazover had 'set out from day one' of her employment to take him to a tribunal.
Earlier in the day, Ms Nicholl-Pierson broke down in tears as she accused Mr Scott's male colleagues of 'cowering behind their desks' while she was being harassed.
Taking the stand for the first time, Mr Scott described the £108,000 being sought by the women as 'ridiculous' and branded them 'street-wise'.
He stated: 'Both these girls were out on the party circuit in Soho throughout the whole time they were employed by the company.
'They were both involved, from what I saw, in taking drugs and drinking to excess. There were rumours that (Ms Mazover) was a part-time sex worker and that (Ms Nicholl-Pierson) was going out with a drugs dealer.
'I don't know whether these rumours were true but certainly when I saw them out socially during this period, which I did a lot, they were certainly moving in those circles.
'I want the tribunal to be under no illusion that these are the type of claimants we are dealing with. They are street-wise girls and they are clearly bent on making as much money out of the company as possible.'
He wrote in his witness statement: 'I deny all the allegations against me and I feel very strongly that these claimants have acted dishonestly and maliciously.
'They clearly have conspired together to fabricate these claims in order to either get me the sack and/or try and save their jobs and/or simply try and make some money out of the company.
'I particularly resent the fact that they made a complaint to the police who found there was absolutely no evidence to support the allegations against me at all.'
During heated cross-examination, Mr Scott banged a fist on the table and, in a raised voice, told the claimants' lawyer, Michael McDonough: 'Get yourself some witnesses for the things you're accusing me of, and if you can't, p*** off'
Ms Nicholl-Pierson and Ms Mazover were both dismissed from the company last June, less than a month after they had started.
They are claiming compensation for sexual harassment, victimisation, race discrimination and poor treatment after whistleblowing at Central London Employment Tribunal.
Mr Scott told hearing that Ms Mazover had a poor record of punctuality, while Ms Nicholl-Pierson was 'simply unable to sell'.
He went on: 'Both claimants were actually pretty useless and they are not people we would have kept on in any event.'
In cross-examination, Mr McDonough, asked Mr Scott: 'Every single allegation that both of these women have made is 100% true, isn't that right?'
The respondent replied: 'No, it's 100% false.'
In his statement, Mr Scott described the office as open-plan and said that if he had said 'anything remotely inappropriate' it would have been heard by 'numerous other people'.
On the alleged suggestion of a threesome with the women, Mr Scott wrote that he 'never invited them to my home or to take part in any sexual activity', and claimed 'the only way they can prosper is by selling regularly'.
He told the hearing he had employed 'at least 4,000 people' in what was a 'tough environment'. He added that some employees only last 'for a few weeks'.
Earlier in the hearing, Ms Nicholl-Pierson cried when Mr Scott's lawyer, Adam Gadd, put it to her that 'your whole case is a lie' and she had made the claims 'for money'.
She replied: 'I want justice. The way they treated me is completely unfair.'
She added: 'What do you expect me to do when I've got no money and I want justice. I've been sacked and I'm unemployed. I'm not walking away.'
The claimant told the hearing that her former colleagues at the London-based company did not protect her.
'These men cowered behind their computers like idiots even though they have probably got children and wives,' she said. 'Do you think that is appropriate behaviour?'
Ms Nicholl-Pierson told the tribunal that she was not the only person at the company who believed there were issues with Mr Scott.
'A lot of people felt that Darren was perverted and strange. I think he knows this himself,' she said.
She said that when she went to complain to the publishing firm's director, James Ramsey, about Mr Scott's behaviour, he started crying.
Describing the meeting, she added: 'He (Mr Ramsey) burst out crying. He (Mr Ramsey) didn't protect me. He doesn't protect women, he stays there crying and does nothing.'
The two women started at the London-based company in May last year - Ms Nicholl-Pierson on May 13, and Ms Mazover on May 20 - and they were dismissed on June 14.
The hearing continues.
]]></text></news-item>