<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-TGK1-JC6P-C2W1"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Duke Energy cited for dumping 61 million gallons of coal ash wastewater into Cape Fear River tributary</title><source>The Fayetteville Observer (Fayetteville, North Carolina)</source><author>Amanda Dolasinski and Nathan Hardin Staff writers, The Fayetteville Observer, N.C.</author><text><![CDATA[March 21--State regulators cited Duke Energy Thursday after the utility pumped about 61 million gallons of coal ash wastewater into a Cape Fear River tributary last week.
The Division of Water Resources at the state Department of Environment and Natural Resources announced that it had issued a notice of violation of a wastewater discharge permit to Duke Energy. The utility has 30 days to respond to the violation, according to a news release from DENR.
Calls to Duke were not returned Thursday.
During a March 11 inspection, inspectors found that Duke Energy had been pumping wastewater from two coal ash basins. Pumping had been going on for several months, according to the violation.
State officials said Duke Energy told regulators the company was using a temporary pumping system to lower water levels in two basins at the Cape Fear plant to perform upcoming maintenance, according to the release.
Regulators estimated about 61 million gallons of wastewater was pumped, according to the violation notice. The dewatering to conduct maintenance on a plant and ash basin that is being decommissioned does not constitute essential maintenance, according to the notice.
"Certainly this is something we're very concerned about," said Drew Elliot, spokesman for DENR.
There have been no reports of high levels of toxins at intake points in Harnett County or Fayetteville, he said. The Cape Fear River is the source of drinking water for Fayetteville and Cumberland County, Fort Bragg, Harnett County and other downstream communities.
"In terms of dangers to public health, none of the downstream public water systems have reported any problems with treating water," Elliot said. "We don't have any drinking water impacts from that."
Regulators used the utility's log books to determine that about 17.4 million gallons of wastewater had been pumped from the 1978 coal ash basin over a period of 31 days since January. About 44.4 million gallons of wastewater had been pumped from the 1985 coal ash basin over a period of 78 days since September 2013, according to the violation.
The Water Division of DENR ordered Duke Energy to address the violations immediately, according to the notice. The current violations and any future violations are subject to a civil penalty assessment of up to $25,000 per day for each violation, according to the notice.
The March 11 inspection of the Cape Fear Steam Electric Power Plant was part of inspections of all Duke Energy's facilities with coal ash basins in the wake of the Feb. 2 coal ash spill at the Dan River plant, according to state regulators. There are 33 coal ash basins in the state, Elliot said.
Operations at Duke's Cape Fear plant ceased in September 2012. Since the coal ash basins are still at the plant, however, the company needs a wastewater discharge permit.
The permit allows the utility to empty coal ash basins when they become full, Elliot said. The permit, which is issued every five years, is valid through 2016.
Earlier this week, Waterkeeper Alliance released aerial photographs of the Cape Fear plant in Chatham County that showed workers pumping from the coal ash basins. The group, which advocates for waterways across the country, began investigating possible leaks at other Duke Energy facilities after the spill at the Dan River.
In the photographs, a man in a truck marked Duke Energy is parked next to a pump with hoses in the coal ash basin and in a storm drain. The drain connects to a canal that runs parallel to the Cape Fear River and eventually empties into it at several locations, according to officials at Waterkeeper Alliance.
"They were putting a cocktail of toxins into the river just above the drinking water intake for Sanford," said Kemp Burdette, Cape Fear Riverkeeper.
"If that is not the most criminal activity that I've ever heard of, I don't know what is," he said. "This issue is going to continue to affect people for a long, long time. Until every single one is cleaned up and coal ash is dried up and moved to a lined landfill away from waterways, that threat is going to be out there. We need to clean up these ponds, and we need to do it quickly."
Staff writer Amanda Dolasinski can be reached at dolasinskia@fayobserver.com or 486-3528. Staff writer Nathan Hardin can be reached at hardinn@fayobserver.com or 486-3509.
___ (c)2014 The Fayetteville Observer (Fayetteville, N.C.) Visit The Fayetteville Observer (Fayetteville, N.C.) at www.fayobserver.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>