<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-MD81-JCMN-Y34J"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Pesticide victims recount how 'Death is in the Meadow': Film screening, 27 March Brussels</title><source>EU Reporter</source><author>EU Reporter Correspondent</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 21, 2014 (EU Reporter:http://www.eureporter.co Delivered by Newstex) http://www.eureporter.co/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/IsZ7wN3Po83F6MsqJ2JgTQIaJCNXVkdnX4wFTXbaIL88uBn2tQu8za5cTLDOU8xCQklECJIyJ6VhEoCLUgyL1xInvmvVZn-cTisEs0-d-e1-ft.jpgOn the occasion of the 9th edition of Pesticide Action Week, the Health and Environment Alliance (HEAL), Générations Futures, Pesticide Action Network Europe (PAN) and Hiltrud Breyer MEP are inviting you to participate in this first-ever screening of the documentary Death is in the Meadow in Brussels. The film follows farmers, wine-makers and other individuals who have developed different cancers and Parkinson's from pesticide use. Director Eric Guéret aims to overcome the silence within the agricultural community on how pesticides have an impact on health.
Several of the farmers who share their personal stories in the film will also be present for the screening and discussion. In 2011, they created a association of victims of pesticides called 'Phyto-Victimes', which has become powerful in France. Those coming to Brussels are on its board. They are: President Paul Francois, who successfully sued US biotech giant Monsanto for poisoning him with a powerful weedkiller; Caroline Chenet-Lis, Vice President, who lost her husband to leukaemia; and, Jacky Ferrand, whose son died from bladder cancer, which is thought to be associated with pesticides used on vines. To register for this event please fill in the form available here.[1] The Health and Environment Alliance (HEAL) is a leading European not-for-profit organisation addressing how the environment affects health in the European Union (EU). Our broad alliance of more than 65 member organisations represents health professionals, not-for-profit health insurers, doctors, nurses, cancer and asthma groups, citizens, women's groups, youth groups, environmental NGOs, scientists and public health research institutes across Europe. For more information, click here. PAN Europe works to eliminate dependency on hazardous pesticides and to support replacement with sustainable alternatives. It brings together 34 consumer, public health, and environmental organisations and women's groups from Europe. More information: www.pan-europe.info[2] Pesticide Action Week is an annual and international event, open to everyone, with the aim to promote alternatives to pesticides. It was initiated and is coordinated by Générations Futures. More information: www.pesticideactionweek.org[3] [1]: http://heal.tttp.eu/sites/all/modules/civicrm/extern/url.php?u=7605qid=149018 [2]: http://heal.tttp.eu/sites/all/modules/civicrm/extern/url.php?u=7607qid=149018 [3]: http://heal.tttp.eu/sites/all/modules/civicrm/extern/url.php?u=7608qid=149018

]]></text></news-item>