<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-HJR1-JCF4-61X6"><date>2014-03-22</date><title></title><source>The Japan News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The president of a Tokyo-based railway consultant firm has admitted that the firm paid kickbacks to foreign civil servants in return for orders it received for official development assistance projects, The Yomiuri Shimbun has learned.
According to informed sources, Tamio Kakinuma, the president of Japan Transportation Consultants, Inc. (JTC), admitted the allegations during questioning by the special investigation squad of the Tokyo District Public Prosecutors Office. He reportedly signed a confession statement.
The prosecutors will conduct a criminal investigation into charges that the Unfair Competition Prevention Law was violated through payment of bribes to foreign government employees, sources said.
According to the sources, Kakinuma, 65, visited the Tokyo District Public Prosecutors Office voluntarily on Tuesday. During questioning, he reportedly admitted that JTC had paid money to civil servants in Vietnam, Indonesia and Uzbekistan, giving details such as when the firm had given them money and how much it had paid. The president is believed to have explained that he had not known about the situation.
The Tokyo Regional Taxation Bureau found illegal payments worth about 100 million yen made by JTC in the course of a tax inspection. Besides the 100 million yen identified through that process, JTC also made further illegal payments worth about 30 million yen. Of the additional 30 million yen, about 10 million yen was paid after the tax inspection was conducted in April last year, the sources said.
The firm's illegal payments were made on about 40 occasions from February 2008 to February this year, totaling 130 million yen, in relation to orders it received for five ODA projects.
The amount of each payment was determined according to the value of the orders received. For example, a total of 80 million yen was paid in return for an ODA project order worth 4.2 billion yen in Vietnam, while in Indonesia a total of 30 million yen was paid for three projects totaling about 2.9 billion yen. In Uzbekistan, the firm paid about 20 million yen in return for receiving an order worth about 700 million yen, according to sources.
The company is believed to have paid the kickbacks to five government employees, including a senior official of an office responsible for project administration at Vietnam Railways and an official in a position of responsibility at the Directorate General of Railways at the Indonesian Transportation Ministry.
]]></text></news-item>