<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-5NY1-JCTS-G55K"><date>2014-03-20</date><title>State first: Landfill miningproposed </title><source>Flint Journal (Michigan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[URL: http://www.mlive.com/news/flint/index.ssf/2014/03/possible_buyer_wants_to_mine_r.html
By Ron Fonger
rfonger1@mlive.com
The Clarkston company in line to buy the Richfield Landfill wants to mine it for recyclables that have been buried for decades, something that never has been tried in Michigan.
Representatives of the state Department of Environmental Quality said the proposed mining has not been detailed in writing but has been discussed in meetings with representatives of TerRenova LLC, which has offered $1 million for the shuttered property.
DEQ officials said TerRenova representatives also are talking about some type of waste-to-energy operation on the 272 acres that make up the landfill property off East Mt. Morris Road, north of Holloway Reservoir.
"We have discussed mining, but we have so few details. ... We're awaiting additional information from TerRenova," said Carrie Hardigan, an enforcement specialist for the Michigan DEQ. "Their interest is to see if they can reclaim any materials of value" in the landfill. "We don't know how they would go about doing that."
The Flint Journal/Mlive.com could not reach Andrew S. Alley, resident agent for TerRenova, which has been negotiating with a U.S. Bankruptcy Court trustee to buy the landfill, an unsold asset of Richfield Equities and related companies that filed for bankruptcy protection in September 2012.
Just the talk about disturbing waste at a property marked by environmental and management issues worries neighbors and township officials, who see potential fallout on
See landfill, A2
landfill
Holloway Reservoir, Buttercup Beach and the Flint River.
"I'm getting totally panicked calls from people around the area," said Julie Brandon, vice president of the Holloway Lake Association, who said she has found little reassuring information about landfill mining that has been done elsewhere.
Brandon fears mining garbage potentially will contaminate nearby waterways and send methane gas into the air.
"(This has) the potential to be the biggest environmental disaster in Genesee County," Brandon said. "We want to put up some caution signs and say, 'Let's proceed real slowly with this.'"
Landfill mining typically involves extracting waste from a landfill after that site has been closed and no longer is accepting waste, according to a report by the International Solid Waste Association.
Although other landfill mining operations typically are done once a landfill is closed, Richfield Township Supervisor Joe Madore said TerRenova officials have told him they plan to reopen the facility to fresh garbage.
Any mining would be done "during lulls" in planned sorting of fresh, incoming garbage, Madore said.
Madore said in a letter to landfill neighbors last month that there are "a lot of questions that need answers relating to this potential activity," including "odor, methane capture (and) leachate control just to name a few."
State regulators will have to address those questions with permits, licenses and new agreements that haven't been needed for typical landfills, a representative said.
"Our regulations don't address mining of landfills, so what we envision is a consent agreement," spelling out conditions for operating, said Margie Ring, state solid waste engineering coordinator.
Requirements for controlling odor and dust, as well as management of waste on site, would have to be a part of any such agreement, Ring said.
TerRenova applied Feb. 28 for a license to operate Richfield, and DEQ officials said that application is under review.
Permits, licenses and consent agreements at Richfield are complicated because of the history of the landfill, which was first licensed in 1966, which includes a cell that is closed and which generally was troubled in the years leading up to the last owner's bankruptcy filing.
Chief among the issues is development of a new plan for disposal of contaminated water -- or leachate, which is currently hauled off site for disposal.
If TerRenova can't satisfy state regulators with its plans, the DEQ is prepared to move ahead with a closure plan for the landfill, a process that already has started with the selection of a preferred bidder to seal the property.
The $4.4 million cost of closure would be paid for from a perpetual care fund that was build up by former operators of the landfill. The expense of closing the dump would nearly deplete the fund and leave an environmental scar, Hardigan said.
Brandon said she has asked elected officials for a public meeting as soon as possible to address questions about landfill mining and waste-to-energy plans.
Although methane already is captured at the landfill, Brandon said the new proposed uses raises new questions about the "health, safety and welfare of not only our members, but also every resident in our community for decades to come."
The landfill isn't the only environmental concern to surface in the township in recent months.
Residents also have been getting offers to sell the oil and mineral rights on their land, raising the potential for hydraulic fracturing, or facking, here.
Fracking is a controversial method of pumping high-pressure water, sand and chemicals thousands of feet below ground to free oil and gas from rock.
@fl-33 @fl-river @mlive-river @mm-business richfield township
]]></text></news-item>