<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BSY-73H1-F09T-F44T"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Oil industry expert says fracking not linked to earthquakes despite opponents' beliefs</title><source>Press - Telegram (Long Beach California)</source><author>Kevin Smith</author><text><![CDATA[Monday's 4.4-magnitude earthquake rattled Southern California and, for some activists and local lawmakers, it has confirmed one of their worst fears - that aggressive new oil-drilling methods are making the state vulnerable to increased seismic activity.
But at least one industry expert calls it "ludicrous" that hydraulic fracturing is legitimately threatening to further destabilize fault lines.
Fracking, as it is popularly known, is the practice of shooting high-pressure water and chemicals through underground drills to break up rocks and release trapped stores of oil and gas. Residents in cities that sit above oil fields - Carson, Wilmington, Hermosa Beach, Whittier, Long Beach and elsewhere - are raising concerns that the underground pressure is increasing the severity of earthquakes, and their elected representatives are sounding the alarm.
Earlier this month, the Los Angeles City Council imposed a moratorium on aggressive energy extraction methods like fracking, acidizing and gravel packing. On Tuesday, the Carson City Council placed a 45-day moratorium on any new or expanded oil and gas drilling projects in the city, effectively stalling an Occidental Petroleum Corp. proposal to install 200 new wells.
Los Angeles Councilmen Paul Koretz, Mike Bonin and Bernard Parks on Tuesday asked the city departments of Emergency Management and Building and Safety to join with federal and state agencies to explore whether fracking could have been a factor in the occurrence of Monday's quake centered in Westwood.
"Experts in the field have made the connection between fracking and earthquakes," Koretz said. "We should be doing that work. To allow fracking in earthquake country is more likely to trigger an earthquake."
Koretz said he has been told the fracking process is being used at wells at the VA Administration land in West Los Angeles, near the suspected epicenter of Monday's temblor.
"Earthquakes can be triggered if (fracking) is in that area or nearby," he said. "We believe fracking is going on at the VA, which is pretty close and certainly, by location, could have been a trigger."
Catherine Reheis-Boyd, president and CEO of the Western States Petroleum Association, said that idea is crazy and uninformed.
"They are taking advantage of a political situation," Reheis- Boyd said. "It's not fair to take the action they are taking when they have not taken a moment to understand the issue."
Association officials also criticized the vote by the Carson City Council saying there was no scientific basis for it.
"Hydraulic fracturing has been used safely and effectively to produce oil in California for more than 60 years without any harm to water supplies, air quality, or other environmental resources," said Colin Maynard, the association's senior communications coordinator, in a statement.
"It is unfortunate the City Council was persuaded to take the precipitous action by the outside advocacy groups using false and misleading information.
"It is even more alarming that the council acted to halt all oil and natural gas drilling, even that which does not utilize the hydraulic fracturing technology. The decision will deprive the city of the significant revenue it would otherwise receive from those prohibited activities, revenues that could have been used to support police, fire and other local services."
The U.S. Geologic Survey has published research showing that deep well fluid-injection operations have caused lots of tiny earthquakes for decades.
"Natural stresses put faults and fractures close to failure and then you inject water, any fluid, into the rock at depth, that forces the fluid along those fractures at high pressure and relieves what's called the 'effective stress' on the fault," said Bill Leith, associate coordinator of the USGS Hazards Program. "The fluid pushes the sides of the fault apart. (And) it allows that fault to slip more easily than it would have had it not been pressurized."
These induced earthquakes are typically less than magnitude 2, and there is a correlation between the volume of fluid that goes in and the magnitude of the quake, Leith said.
In 2008, USGS researchers recorded a large increase nationwide in small earthquakes because of well injections similar to a 2000 increase caused by coal-bed methane production.
Reheis-Boyd said studies have shown there is no correlation between fracking and earthquakes.
She cited a 2012 hydraulic fracturing study of the PXP Inglewood Oil Field. In that report, Matheson Mining Consultants Inc. concluded that the hydraulic fracturing there "did not induce seismic activity." Some minor spikes were noted, the study said, but they were "imperceptible at the surface" and could have been caused by local traffic.
A study by three environmental organizations - Earthworks, Center for Biological Diversity and Clean Water Action - supports Koretz's concerns and concludes there is a direct correlation between fracking and seismic activity.
The study, "On Shaky Ground - How Oil Companies Increase California's Earthquake Risk," notes that 54 percent of the state's active wastewater wells lie within 10 miles of a recently active fault.
"I would say there is a valid concern," said Andrew Grinberg, a program organizer with Clean Water Action who co-authored the study. "We know there is oil and gas activity all over Southern California, and there is a wastewater injection well about eight miles away from where Monday's earthquake was centered."
Grinberg said about 16 barrels of water are extracted for every barrel of oil that is pulled from the ground. When the oil is taken away for processing, the leftover wastewater is injected back into the ground under high pressure.
"We took a look at the spatial relationships between active faults and wastewater injection wells that are used in fracking," he said. "We've seen evidence of huge increases in quakes in Oklahoma, Ohio and Texas."
Grinberg said there are "huge gaps of knowledge" about why, when and how wastewater injection can cause earthquakes.
"It has not been established what distance (from an earthquake fault line) is safe or unsafe," he said. "Our organizations are all calling for a moratorium on fracking in California."
The groups say fracking also produces groundwater contamination and increases greenhouse gas emissions.
Senate Bill 4, which was approved by the state Legislature last year, permits fracking in California - but only under strict guidelines.
Reheis-Boyd said fracking can play an important role in increasing California's oil production.
"We are the fourth-largest oil producer in the U.S., but we're only making 38 percent of what we need," she said. "There are no crude oil pipelines that come into the state, so out-of-state oil comes in by water-borne tankers. Crude production in Alaska is down, so that leaves oil imports from foreign places that don't like us."
The National Academies of Science and other geologists have concluded the amount of energy involved in the process of hydraulic energy fracturing is far too small to trigger an earthquake that can be felt, Reheis-Boyd said.
Jonathan P. Stewart, a professor of civil and environmental engineering at UCLA, offered his take on the issue via email.
"My opinion is that the earthquake was not caused by fracking," Stewart said. "I do not have information about where fracking may be occurring in Southern California, but I doubt it is occurring in the area struck by the recent earthquake. Moreover, the depth of the recent California event (reported by USGS as 9 km) is deeper than typical fracking depths.
"For both of these reasons, I believe the event was caused by the large tectonic-induced stresses in the crust in California and is not due to any activity of people (fracking or otherwise)."
Staff writer Rick Orlov contributed to this report.
]]></text></news-item>