<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT0-G201-DXJR-H400"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Cong, BJP corrupt, says new AAP paper</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[JAIPUR: The state unit of AAP has released a 'white paper' accusing both Congress and BJP of involving in corruption over coal blocks allotted to the Rajasthan Rajya Vidyut Utpadan Limited (RRVUL) in 2006. The paper being distributed by AAP candidates said if existing irregularities are to be removed, 30% of the electricity bills can be slashed in Rajasthan.
Riding on the crest of such populist measures which paved the way for AAP's unprecedented victory in Delhi assembly polls, the state unit has asked the candidates to expose the government at both state and municipal levels on electricity, water and roads issues. The candidates have been told to disseminate the information to people during big public gatherings.
The paper said as coal blocks were allotted to the RRVUL was further allocated to private parties by both BJP and Congress parties since 2006. "The Union government allocated two coal blocks in Parsa East Basin and Kanti Basin in Sarjuga district in Chattisgarh to RRVUL to meet the coal demand for producing electricity," said Ravindra Singh, in-charge of the AAP unit in Pali.
In these circumstances, the rate of electricity bills would have been just 2/3 of what these companies are charging. The foul play comes when the coal blocks were re-allocated to Gujarat-based Adani Group by then chief minister Vasundhara Raje who was also the cabinet in-charge for the power department, he said. The government kept a meagerly 26% stakes while awarding 74% stakes to Adani Group, flouting the norm of mining which was to be carried out by the state owned company, Singh claimed.
The paper also said electricity companies have invested Rs 8,000 in the last few years to reduce wastage but still no improvement could be seen. Ironically, the wastage has shot up in many discoms, the paper, which is widely being circulated among the voters, claimed.
The AAP claimed that allegations its leaders are leveling on BJP and Congress are on the basis of evidences. "Neither our party is not into the business of leveling allegations based on biases nor do we encourage attacks on individuals," said Virendra Singh, who is contesting from Jaipur. He added that crores of rupees are being overcharged from the consumers should be returned by slashing the rates.
The AAP also questioned as to why the government has not executed the water policy in drought-hit areas by connecting by seasonal and perennial rivers. The state remained mute over the dispute arising among districts over distribution of water, the party claimed.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>