<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT0-58R1-F03R-N3CN"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Duke Energy caught intentionally pumping 61 million gallons of coal waste into North Carolina water</title><source>Freak Out Nation</source><author>Anomaly</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 21, 2014 (Freak Out Nation:http://freakoutnation.com/ Delivered by Newstex) On Thursday, North Carolina regulators cited Duke Energy saying the company illegally and deliberately dumped 61 million gallons of toxic coal ash waste into a tributary of the Cape Fear River, which provides drinking water for several cities and towns in the state.
Earlier this month we reported[1] that after contaminating 70 miles of the Dan River in Eden, North Carolina, Eden, N.C., dumping 39,000 tons of poisonous sludge and slurry on Feb. 2 — the third-largest such spill in U.S. history, Duke Energy expects its 3.2 million customers to pay the costs of closing its ash ponds, according to CEO Lynn Good. Image: LA Times That's right. Duke Energy wants consumers to pay for their mess, and some of it was created deliberately. The Los Angeles Times reports:[2]The state Department of Environment and Natural Resources said the giant utility, responsible for a massive spill from a different coal ash containment pond Feb. 2, had illegally pumped the ash from two coal ash ponds at its Cape Fear plant in Moncure, N.C., and into a canal that feeds into the Cape Fear River. Regulators said they caught Duke pumping the toxic ash March 11, one day after an environmental group took aerial photographs of what it said were pumps illegally dumping the waste. Environmental groups have accused the agency of coddling Duke Energy and allowing coal ash waste to seep for years from the utility's 14 coal-fired plants in the state. The state agency said Duke Energy had been getting away with the dumping by telling regulators it was part of routine maintenance. Regulators said inspectors had determined that 44 million gallons of toxic waste had been pumped from one pond for 78 days, and 17 million gallons pumped from a second pond at the site for 31 days.Duke is allowed 30 days to respond to the state's citation. After that, regulators could impose a fine of up to $25,000 a day for each violation, however, Duke is a $50-billion corporation. If a person deliberately poisoned our drinking water, that would be considered an act of terrorism. Corporations are not people, my friend.https://secure.repost.us/syndicate/create?url=http%3A%2F%2Ffreakoutnation.com%2F2014%2F03%2F21%2Fduke-energy-caught-intentionally-pumping-61-million-gallons-of-coal-waste-into-north-carolina-water%2F Tags: Duke[3], Duke Energy[4] [1]: http://freakoutnation.com/2014/03/09/duke-ceo-wants-customers-to-pay-cleanup-costs-after-company-spilled-39000-tons-of-poisonous-sludge/ [2]: http://www.latimes.com/nation/la-na-duke-coal-ash-20140321,0,1907269.story#axzz2wcLnurui [3]: http://freakoutnation.com/tag/duke/ [4]: http://freakoutnation.com/tag/duke-energy/

]]></text></news-item>