<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT0-7X11-DXKH-N45K"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Alpha Natural Resources climbs 4.6% on average volume</title><source>News Bites US Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Alpha Natural Resources, Inc. (NYSE:ANR), NYSE's 5th largest coal company by market capitalisation, climbed 19.50c (or 4.6%) to close at US$4.44, ending a three-day streak of losses. Compared with the S&P 500 Index which fell 5.6 points (or 0.3%) in the day, this represented a relative price increase of 4.9%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Alpha Natural Resources, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/00105196195031467
Bullish SignalsUptrendTop traded Alpha Natural Resources call options [volume of contracts in brackets; 1 contract is 100 shares]Exercise 6; Expires 19 Apr, 2014: 0.03 up 50.0% [37]Oversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The Relative Strength Index (RSI) of 26.2 has breached the oversold line of 30, suggesting the price decrease of 16.5% in the last 14 days is unusually high. - The stock is oversold according to the Williams % R indicator of -81.4, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day low of US$4.19. - The Money Flow Index [MFI] is 16.3 suggesting an oversold 14-day trend, being under 20. The Money Ratio of 0.2 suggests positive money flow was 0.2 times negative money flow. - The Stochastic indicator of 11.0 has pierced the oversold line of 20.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Sales of 0.2 [0.9]. - Price to Book of 0.3 [1.2]. We estimate Alpha Natural Resources stock is trading at a current year Price to Book of 0.1 and a forward year Price to Book of 0.1.Other Bullish Signals:- The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 63.6%.
Bearish Signals- In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week low four times, pointing to a downtrend. - The 5.8% premium to 12-month low of US$4.19 against the 48.7% discount to high of US$8.64 suggests the stock continues to push for new lows. - The present value of US$1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in Alpha Natural Resources is US$538, for a capital loss of US$462.
- Net Profit margin has seen consecutive falls and seems to be on a slippery slope in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]
- EBIT margin has shown signs of deterioration in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteBeta: the Beta of Alpha Natural Resources stock is 1.2. A Beta greater than 1 suggests this is a high risk, high return stock with volatility greater than that of the market.
FINANCIALSAnnual Report for the year ended December 31, 2013 (year-on-year comparisons with previous corresponding period)-Favourable Changes: EPS continued to be negative like in the previous year; however, there was an improvement from $US-11.06 in the previous year to $US-5.04.Unfavourable Changes: total revenue down 29.2% to $US4.9b; loss of $US1.1b; EBIT loss of $US1.1b; EBIT Margin of -21.9%; losses in 3 years out of the last 5 years; total debt to net tangible assets up from 81.2% to 95.1%; debt to equity up 23.5% to 0.8; total liabilities to total assets up 4.8% to 0.6; current ratio down 16.2% to 1.6; Net tangible assets per share down 13.8% to $US16.32; Working capital to total assets down 25.5% to 6.3%; total revenue to total assets down 21.5% to 0.4.Major Common Size Ratios: total current assets to total assets down from 17.8% to 16.9%; fixed assets to total assets down from 17.0% to 15.2%; cash to total assets down from 5.6% to 5.3%; intangibles to total assets down from 6.1% to 4.0%; other non-current assets to total assets up from 2.4% to 3.3%; cost of goods sold to sales up from 71.7% to 80.6%; depreciation to sales up from 14.9% to 17.5%; interest expenses to sales up from 2.8% to 5.0%; sales and marketing expenses to sales up from 3.0% to 3.2%; amortisation to sales down from 1.0% to 0.1%.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 05: Alpha Natural Resources Concludes Comprehensive Environmental Agreement[News Story] BRISTOL, Va., March 5, 2014 -- Alpha Natural Resources, Inc. (NYSE:ANR) today announced that it has entered into a consent decree with the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), U.S. Department of Justice (DOJ) and three states regarding claims under the Clean Water Act.The consent decree resolves a complaint by the EPA and state agencies alleging that the company's mining affiliates in Kentucky, Pennsylvania, Tennessee, Virginia and West Virginia exceeded certain water discharge permit limits.
February 21: Alpha Natural Resources to Participate in Upcoming Investor Conferences[News Story] BRISTOL, Va., Feb. 21, 2014 -- Alpha Natural Resources, Inc. (NYSE:ANR), a leading U.S. coal producer, announced that members of Alpha's management team plan to participate in several investor conferences, including: the BMO Capital Markets 23rdGlobal Metals & Mining Conference on Monday, February 24, 2014; the Simmons & Company International 14th Annual Energy Conference on Thursday, February 27, 2014; Barclays Metals and Materials Cross Asset Forum on Wednesday, March 19, 2014; and Howard Weil's 42nd Annual Energy Conference on Wednesday, March 26, 2014.
February 12: Alpha Natural Resources Announces Results for Fourth Quarter and Full Year 2013[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Usnyse/Stock/News/552317.htmlSource: Nasdaq Stock Exchange
February 10: U.S. Attorney Closes Upper Big Branch Non-Prosecution Agreement Following Full Compliance by Alpha Natural Resources[News Story] BRISTOL, Va., Feb. 10, 2014 -- Alpha Natural Resources, Inc. (NYSE:ANR), today announced that the United States Attorney's Office for the Southern District of West Virginia (USAO SDWV) has closed the Non-Prosecution Agreement (NPA) the company entered into on Dec. 6, 2011.On April 5, 2010, an explosion at the Upper Big Branch Mine (UBB), operated by a subsidiary of Massey Energy Co., claimed the lives of 29 miners.
February 06: Alpha Natural Resources Subsidiary to Open London Office; Vice President Named to Lead Effort[News Story] BRISTOL, Va., Feb. 6, 2014 -- In continuing efforts to enhance servicing of international customers and take advantage of expanding European markets, Alpha Natural Resources, Inc. (NYSE:ANR), a leading U.S. coal supplier, today announced that subsidiary Alpha Coal Sales International Limited will open a London office."Our intent is to build an export platform for U.S.
February 03: Alpha Natural Resources Recognized for Environmental Stewardship[News Story] BRISTOL, Va., Feb. 3, 2014 -- Alpha Natural Resources (NYSE:ANR), a leading U.S. coal supplier, is pleased to announce that four of its affiliate operations have been honored by the West Virginia Department of Environmental Protection and the West Virginia Coal Association for exemplary performance in protecting the environment, reclamation, reforestation, community outreach and enhancing post-mining land use.The awards were presented during the 41st annual West Virginia Mining Symposium Jan.
January 31: Awards for Safety Excellence go to 18 Alpha Natural Resources Affiliate Operations in West Virginia[News Story] 85 Operations across Company Record No Reportable Injuries in 2013BRISTOL, Va., Jan. 31, 2014 -- Alpha Natural Resources, Inc. (NYSE:ANR), a leading U.S. coal supplier, today announced outstanding safety performance for 2013, with 18 affiliate operations in West Virginia honored for safety achievements, including the top safety award for an underground mine.
ISIN: US02076X1028
N:ANR
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>