<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT0-G201-DXJR-H3FR"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Bribery case: Preliminary enquiry registered against Rolls-Royce</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Neeraj Chauhan</author><text><![CDATA[NEW DELHI: The CBI on Friday registered a preliminary enquiry (PE) against London-based Rolls-Royce, unknown officials of HAL and Ashok Patni, owner of Singapore-based firm Aashmore Private Limited, signalling the beginning of a formal probe into bribery allegations in the Rs 10,000 crore deal for supply of aircraft engines.
Top CBI officers say the agency is also probing role of defence ministry officials in the case. CBI sources say the sleuths would approach the British serious fraud office for details of the probe into Rolls-Royce.
The PE has been lodged to investigate alleged payment of bribe or kickbacks in the purchase of spare parts of helicopter the engines of the helicopters to the industrial and marine gas turbine division of HAL. CBI spokesperson Kanchan Prasad said, "PE has been registered against unknown officials of HAL, Rolls-Royce and the owner of Aashmore in the matter of alleged bribery of approximately Rs 18.8 crore in the supply of spare parts of helicopter engines to HAL."
The allegations surfaced after HAL recently received a letter, claiming that bribes were paid to officials in HAL and other departments concerned to bag contracts. Rolls-Royce had conducted an internal audit in which it was found that money had been paid to the commercial adviser of Aashmore Private Limited, allegedly as kickbacks to swing the deal in favour of the UK-based company.
CBI sources say, "The commission paid through Patni could be put in the category of bribe paid by a middleman and the PE would probe people in HAL and MoD who were in touch with him."
The allegation was that Aashmore provided "sales and logistics support, local business expertise and strategic advice" in dealings with HAL in the energy sector.HAL, through its Industrial and Marine Gas Turbine Division, buys and maintains gas turbines for ONGC and GAIL.
Ever since the controversy surfaced, Rolls-Royce has maintained that the company "will cooperate fully with the regulatory authorities and have repeatedly made clear that we will not tolerate misconduct of any sort."
Rolls-Royce, in a letter written to HAL in December last, had said that it had employed a Singapore-based person identified as Ashok Patni and his firm Aashmore Private Limited as "commercial advisor" in India, providing sales and logistical support, local business support and "strategic advice." The firm also told HAL that it had severed ties with Aashmore and its owner in 2013.
The commissions paid by the firm are in violation of the procurement rules in India which prohibits hiring of middlemen or commission agents while transacting in deals with the MoD.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>