<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT0-6KD1-JC92-P32P"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Ukrainian police arrest Naftogaz chief Bakulin (Part 2)</title><source>Russia &amp; CIS Business and Financial Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Ukrainian police arrest Naftogaz chief Bakulin (Part 2)
Ukrainian police have arrested Naftogaz of Ukraine chief executive Yevgeny Bakulin on Friday as part of an inquiry into corruption in the gas industry, Interior Minister Arsen Avakov wrote on Facebook.
"The actions of the criminal group cost the Ukrainian state around $4 billion on just three counts being probed by police investigators! And that is far from being a full list of dodgy schemes and operations which got under the scrutiny of our investigators," the interior minister said.
The inquiry "could lead to a discovery of colossal losses to the state and the involvement in them of famous personalities, including from the current political elite," Avakov said.
"I have decided to expand the team of investigators working in this area. I am warning politicians against meddling in the inquiry. I am warning that my response will be tough, including my public reaction to any attempts to put pressure on the investigators," the minister said.
The cynicism of theft in some of the probed schemes are glaring, Avakov said.
"This could only happen in an atmosphere of total permissiveness and connivance on the part of former top government, interior and prosecution officials. This inquiry is important not only for the sake of restoring justice and returning what was stolen. It is more important as a vaccination against corruption in the new government!" the interior minister said.
It was reported that Bakulin had led Naftogaz of Ukraine since March 2010. He led the company previously between March and December 2007.
Bakulin, born in 1956, spent more than 20 years working at Lisichansk Oil Refinery in the Luhansk region. Between July 2001 and May 2003 he led Lisichanskenefteorgsintez which operated the refinery. Between June 2003 and March 2005 and from September 2006 he led Urkgazvydobuvannya.
Naftogaz of Ukraine includes the country's largest oil and gas producing companies and holds a monopoly for natural gas transit and storage in underground facilities and for crude oil transportation through Ukrainian pipelines.
kk mk
(Our editorial staff can be reached at eng.editors@interfax.ru)
]]></text></news-item>