<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT0-7M41-JCPJ-W49G"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>NC drops coal ash settlement, says it will fight for cleanup in court</title><source>Charlotte Business Journal</source><author>John Downey</author><text><![CDATA[N.C. environmental officials have withdrawn a controversial court settlement of coal ash issues proposed last summer with Duke Energy and say they will now prosecute civil actions to force the cleanup of ash ponds at 14 sites across the state.
"We intend for our lawsuits against Duke Energy to move forward," says John Skvarla, secretary of the N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources. "We will continue to hold the utility accountable for the cleanup of its coal ash impoundments through the lawsuits, the reopening of the permits and our ongoing investigation."
Frank Holleman, a senior lawyer with the Southern Environmental Law Center, calls DENR's move "the most encouraging step they have taken so far."
"They done a complete reversal of their previous position and they have abandoned a settlement that would not have required any cleanup of coal contamination," he says.
The decision technically involves actions at just two of Duke's 14 current and retired coal plants. But DENR spokesman Drew Elliot says the basic approach applies more broadly to additional suits that DENR has filed against all of Duke's N.C. plants.
The decision to abandon the settlement is, in part, a response to the massive coal spill on the Dan River last month. On Feb. 2, a corroded metal stormwater pipe under the main ash pond at Duke's shuttered Dan River Steam Station broke and spewed up to 39,000 tons of coal ash into the river.
But Skvarla says the settlement also was based on an understanding of N.C. law concerning any required cleanup of groundwater contamination from coal ash ponds that has since been overturned.
Wake Superior Court Judge Paul Ridgeway ruled March 6 that state law requires Duke to take immediate steps to clean up groundwater contamination identified at any of its plants. He ordered DENR to enforce the law and this week denied a request from Duke to stay his order.
The settlement withdrawn Friday directly affects enforcement only in cases involving the Riverbend Steam Station on Mountain Island Lake in Gaston County, and the Asheville Plant near Skyland on the French Broad River. Those cases are also before Ridgeway.
In July, DENR and Duke agreed to a consent order to settle the cases. The settlement called for Duke to do additional testing and pay a $99,112 fine.
Holleman's organization represented environmental groups that participated in that case. And all of those groups condemned the settlement as lax treatment for Duke by friendly regulators
Catawba Riverkeeper Sam Perkins, a party to both of those suits, praised the decision to abandon the settlement.
"I'm glad that's off the table," Perkins says. "I really hope they will also realize that the solution they need to get out of the suit is simple and really the only safe solution, and that's to move the ash out from near the waterways."
He says the Catawba Riverkeeper Foundation hopes to work with state regulators as partners in any future settlement that might be worked out.
Staff writer Susan Stabley contributed to this report.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Charlotte Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>