<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT0-DD21-DXDT-63S1"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>'Ex-policeman filmed cage fighting just days after claiming he'd been involved in car crash which left him so injured he was unable to care for his child'</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>DAN BLOOM</author><text><![CDATA[Valerijs Trifonovs, 31, claimed £5,000 compensation after accident in 2010But a judge threw out damages bid after watching fight on TVLatvian claimed he was under pressure from his manager not to pull outHis lawyers say sporting history is full of people fighting on through painQuinn Insurance urged the judge to jail Trifonovs for contempt of court
An ex-policeman grappled in a televised professional cage fight just days after telling his car insurers he had been in a crash so serious he had to claim £5,000 compensation.
Valerijs Trifonovs, 31, could face jail after Quinn Insurance pursued him to the High Court over the 'contrived' accident in west London.
The Latvian national told the firm whiplash prevented him going to the gym, swimming or playing football for three months after the accident in the affluent King's Road, the court heard.
Scroll down for video
He was also said to have claimed he could not look after his son, lift heavy items, do DIY or 'manage his personal care' for a month.
But the former member of Latvian police and special forces soldier was brought to a civil court last year after a Quinn employee spotted he had taken part in a cage fight in Liverpool 13 days after the accident.
Judge Alistair Hammerton at Bow County Court watched the footage, ruling the crash 'probably never happened' and was 'a case of fraud'.
The insurance firm then pursued Mr Trifonovs to the High Court for contempt of court, where he appeared today.
The insurers' barrister, Marcus Grant, told Mr Justice Sweeney there was 'no bona fide accident', and 'the Honda insured by us could not have caused the damage to Mr Trifonovs' Toyota as he alleged'.
Mr Grant added: 'What made this particular fraud memorable was film of Mr Trifonovs engaging in a cage fight 13 days after the alleged accident.'
Mr Grant said he was 'caught out' by a vigilant Quinn employee scanning a newspaper, who 'saw a news story of a man by Mr Trifonovs' name and physical description engaging in a cage fight in Liverpool'.
He told Mr Justice Sweeney: 'Not only was there a report of the cage fight, there was a recording of it as it was broadcast on television.
'Mr Trifonovs lifted the opponent, Adam Parkes, off the ground, and Mr Parkes subsequently held him in a head lock and proceeded to hit him about the head'.
Today the High Court accepted requests by Mr Trifonovs' lawyers to adjourn the case until he could obtain full legal representation, organise his case, and secure a Russian interpreter.
Mr Trifonovs' barrister, Ian Bridge, insisted his client had suffered genuine whiplash in a genuine accident - adding that he had little option but to carry on with the cage fight as he needed the cash.
He said: 'Looking at this superficially it might bring a smile to your face due to the irony that a man should suffer a neck injury, bring a personal injury claim, and then find himself involved in a professional fight within a few days.
'But that does not take account of all the circumstances - not least the fact that it was his means for making a living.
'There was a purse available, tickets had been sold and a promoter had promoted him.'
Speaking after today's hearing, Mr Trifonovs said he had taken part in the fight as he needed to make some money.
'I swear on my children's lives that I had that accident,' he added.
His lawyers claimed his involvement in the cage fight was a testament to his stoicism.
They said: 'The annals of sporting history are full of those who have fought through injuries - from goalkeepers with broken skulls to outfield players with bloody heads.'
They also pointed out that Mr Parkes defeated him within one and a half minutes.
Mr Trifonovs, who said he did not have enough money for legal representation, was granted legal aid.
The case will return to the High Court later this year.
]]></text></news-item>