<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT2-SB91-DYTG-4183"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>BUDGET AS A FORCE FOR CHANGE</title><source>DAILY MAIL (London)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[COMMENT
BY ALEX BRUMMER CITY EDITOR
Early this week some commentators were asking: What is the point of the Budget?'
The answer is budgets provide a focus that forces government, via the Treasury, to make decisions that otherwise would not be made.
Savings reforms - the most radical for at least a generation - are a case in point.
The bumbling opposition response to pension and ISA changes, with the condescending suggestion that beneficiaries will head straight to the Porsche dealer, needs careful scrutiny.
Because retirement savers are being allowed access to their own money, pensions essentially are postponed wages, it does not mean they are going to blow them away.
Indeed, the evidence from the United States, Australia and Denmark is precisely the opposite.
In the US the 401K, the ability to build a pensions pot under the full control of the individual, has encouraged a high degree of financial sophistication, broader share ownership and turned successive Fed chairpersons into star turns on the speech circuit.
Similarly in Australia, the superannuation revolution, under which all citizens (with the exception of judges) are in the same boat, has spurred a financial expertise that didn't seem possible.
In many ways what the Chancellor has done makes the whole business of auto-enrolment - in which virtually the whole population will have a pension pot of their own - much more enticing as an option.
One of the reasons this has become a reality is because of the implementation, in an amended form, of Lord Turner's Pensions Commission proposals.
In the end Turner's proposal for a decent state pension and an end to the messy system of means tested pension credits has been adopted.
The improved state pension, with the inflation triple lock' (the higher of RPI, earnings growth and CPI) is the fall-back for those who have chosen the cruise, while they can still enjoy it, over wilting away on a park bench. There is a belief that what Osborne proposed was only for old people. Poppycock.
Auto-enrolment involved everyone. ISAs are for all ages and are extraordinarily popular with more than 24m subscribers. The new flexibility and higher upper limits (£30,000 for a two person household whether married or not) is terrific.
All of these place a huge new responsibility on the City.
For too long savers have suffered from the rapacious behaviour of providers in the shape of hidden commissions, upfront fees and over-egged management charges.
Companies such as L&G, with their ISA offerings, have tackled this with low-cost index funds.
Advisory supermarkets such as Old Mutual, Hargreaves Landsdown, St James's Place et al offer savers real choice.
Creators of savings products need to act with probity in providing a wide selection of suitable investment products that are easy to understand, cost efficient and are not blighted by hidden charges.
BEING the world's top economic policymaker is never easy.
Alan Greenspan's approach to the job of Federal Reserve chairman was to be as obscure as possible so that whatever he did, people thought he was a genius and they simply didn't understand.
Ben Bernanke went for a crisp new approach, under which monetary policy objectives were tied closely to precise economic guidance, so that misunderstanding was minimised.
Successor Janet Yellen, in her first public appearance in the role, looks to have forged a path between her two predecessors and in the process sowed confusion. The new Fed boss initially indicated she would not raise interest rates until the jobless rate had fallen to 6.5pc.
She added that the interest-rate setting Federal Open Markets Committee would also be adopting soft guidance', using a range of data including part-time working and financial conditions. A few moments later she let slip she expected US interest rates to start rising six months after quantitative easing (the buying of US government bonds) ended, which brought the date forward to mid-2015 from 2016 and temporarily sent the markets into paroxysm. It was not an impressive start. We may have to await her next press conference to know what she is really thinking.
ONE of the biggest problems for UK financial regulators and prosecutors in policing the City is gaining access to data, such as mobile phone traffic, at the highest levels.
During countless investigations into issues ranging from corporate bribery to Libor and Foreign Exchange Market rigging they have found that, mysteriously, the email traffic comes to halt at sales force level, or on the trading floor.
That is among the reasons it is always lower level employees or traders who pay the price, rather than senior executives.
It looks, however, as if prosecutors have decided to tap into the ultimate source at GCHQ to help them with their inquiries.
© Daily Mail
]]></text></news-item>