<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT2-XPX1-JB20-G0B2"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Latest on Malaysia Flight Search; US Government Denies Corporate Espionage Charges; Discussion of the Book by Alan Paul, One Way Out: The Inside History of the Allman Brothers Band</title><source>Imus Simulcast</source><author>Lori Rothman, Dagen McDowell, Nicole Petallides, Jo Ling Kent, Peter Barnes, Rich Edson, Don Imus, Connell McShane, Maria Bartiromo, Lou Rufino, Maria Molina</author><text><![CDATA[DAGEN MCDOWELL, FBN: Good morning, everybody.
The hunt for the missing Malaysia Airlines jet continues today. Search planes and ships scouring a remote part of the Indian Ocean so far have turned up nothing. Some officials say even if it was wreckage from the plane that was picked up by satellite, that debris has likely sunk by now, and we may never know what happened to flight 370.
In Kabul, Afghanistan, an attack on what was supposed to be the safest hotel in that city, leaving more than a dozen people dead. The Taliban stepping up its efforts to disrupt that country's upcoming elections.
And the nation's biggest banks get a clean bill of health as all but one of the 30 largest institutions pass the Federal Reserve's latest stress test. The result should be good news for investors and anybody with a bank account.
Good morning everybody, I'm here with Lori Rothman on this Friday, March the 21st on this best of Imus in the Morning.
LORI ROTHMAN, FBN: On the first day of spring, although, I'm not buying it. It's still freezing.
MCDOWELL: Hey, if it ain't snowin' and sleetin' outside, that does a start, right?
ROTHMAN: Well, my jacket has gotten more mileage this year. My boots? Forget it.
MCDOWELL: (inaudible) came into the studio with black, puffy coats on this morning. That says it all. And coming up, you're going to hear one of the Imus battles with Rob Bartlett over Hollywood and Vine, plus Imus's interview with author Alan Paul about the Allman Brothers. That is a great interview, and if you're here in New York, they're still playing the Beacon Theatre.
ROTHMAN: Are they still at the Beacon?
MCDOWELL: Yeah, they're still there.
ROTHMAN: Is this their last run?
MCDOWELL: With -- well, this is supposed to be Warren Haynes and Derek Trucks last run of Beacon shows, but you never know. They're not leaving. They'll be playing other shows throughout the year. Maybe we'll see it -- tickets are expensive.
And Lori, what are you looking at in terms of business news?
ROTHMAN: All right. Well, you know, it's a great week for the markets. U.S. benchmarks are poised to close out the week with two percent gains, even after Janet Yellen in her debut kinda rattled investors. Was she honest and that's fantastic? Or did she screw it up by saying, "interest rates, actually guys, are going to rise sooner rather than later," so we're kinda parsing that this morning, and the markets, I think, a day later, so you know, it's good to know the future.
MCDOWELL: And speaking of that, we'll just take a look around the world really quickly. Asia's markets already closed. Gains across the board with Japan not opening on this Friday. In Europe you have buying as well, the same stories here on the U.S. futures, and that's been the case all morning long. We're a little more than an hour and a half away from the opening bell. Oil and gold, your two major commodities we always focus on. Gold, found it a bid, big time.
ROTHMAN: All right. Let's get a closer look at the European markets, with Michael Hewson, chief market analyst at CMC Markets in London. And thank you so much for joining us. You just heard our chat about Yellen and the market reaction. It's already been two days, and it was interesting, right, that everyone ran for the exits initially, kinda fearful of a time table for interest rates.
MICHAEL HEWSON, CHIEF MARKET ANALYST, CMC MARKETS: Yeah.
ROTHMAN: But now, a day later, everybody's kinda coming back to the market. So what do you think is behind that?
HEWSON: I think just people are adjusting to it. I mean, I'm actually surprised at the reaction of the market to Mrs. Yellen's comments, because, all she was really reiterating, in my opinion, was what the dot (ph) charts were telling us, and the -- the you know, the policymakers' views of when interest rates could possibly rise, but I think, you know, people heard those three words, "around six months," but what they didn't hear, was all the other caveats that Mrs. Yellen talked about. It was data dependent. It was dependent on tapering continuing on its current path. So, I think once markets have sort of really adjusted to the whole of the speech, and that very good Philadelphia fed number yesterday, as well as those weekly jobless claims, I think they realized that they'd overreacted a little bit.
ROTHMAN: Now, will investors around the world continue to focus on these improvements in western markets and good economic data in the late part of the week, and the Federal Reserve, obviously, or will they return to concerns, tensions rising, between Russia and Ukraine? Obviously, the MICEX has had quite a rout this week. Russia downgraded. What do you think?
HEWSON: I think we're going to get markets focusing on these aspects in the background, but I think they are actually adjusting fairly well. If you actually look at European markets this week, they are -- they are mildly higher. The footsie has dragged a little bit because of concerns about China, and given the fact that the footsie is very heavily geared to the mining sector. There are concerns about that, and the real estate sector there, but even the footsie today is getting a little bit of a bid over a news story out of a Chinese news agency that suggested that maybe the Chinese authorities may look to underpin their GDP growth of cost (ph) target of 7.5 percent by actually easing monetary policy a little bit over the course of the next few weeks.
ROTHMAN: OK. Michael Hewson, thank you for your insight. Michael is with CMC Market.
HEWSON: Thanks.
ROTHMAN: And we've got more for you on what investors can expect to move markets today, from Nicole Petallides, who joins us from the New York Stock Exchange. Nicole?
NICOLE PETALLIDES, FBN: Well, stocks on Wall Street had a great day on Thursday. The Dow Jones Industrial's gained about 100, almost 109 points, closed at 16,331. The NASDAQ and S&P also had up arrows. The NASDAQ was up almost 12 points, closing at 4,319, and the S&P 500 up over 11 points, closing at 1872. So, gains across the board. The volatility still here for the year 2014.
And this week, no doubt, we've seen that. We actually, on Thursday, saw that we started off in the red and then a good Philly fed number pushed the markets into the green. Now, on Friday's trading, today, we'll be watching some action. Now, don't forget, the stock market's still doing well this week, up about 1.5 percent or more for all the major averages this week.
So we'll be watching some key things as well. The home builders, yesterday, dropped off, but today we'll see if they can turn it around, the existing home sales numbers, push those into the red. We're going to get a lot of fed speak today on the docket, including from the Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis President James Bullard, also from Dallas fed President Richard Fisher, so, we'll be watching to see if we get any news out of some of the fed speak today. Banks, many of which hit some record highs yesterday, JP Morgan, Wells Fargo, Bank of America, just to name a few, we'll be watching that group very closely. We did have Mark Newton over at Greywolf Execution Partners saying that he still likes the group in the short term, even naming some of the regional names in particular, such as Regions Financial, Zion, fifth third (ph), BB&T, are some of his favorites.
Not too much for economic news in -- in the docket for Friday. On the floor of the exchange, I'm Nicole Petallides, back to you.
MCDOWELL: Thank you, Nicole. And it looks like extreme weather hit another major U.S. company hard. Jo Ling Kent is in our news room with the details. Hey Jo.
JO LING KENT, FBN: Hey Dagen. Darden Restaurants reporting its third quarter results. A lot of analysts lowered expectations. The company, which owns Red Lobster, Olive Garden, and Longhorn Steakhouse chains posted an adjusted profit of 82 cents a share. Revenue coming in at $2.23 billion. That fell short of the estimate for $2.25 billion. Darden saying severe winter weather. Yet another company citing the bad weather hurt their sales and profit. Same restaurant sales fell 8.8 percent at Red Lobster, and they were down 5.4 percent at Olive Garden. Dagen?
MCDOWELL: Thank you, Jo. And Nike has issued a weak outlook. What's the main reason there?
KENT: You know, shares at Nike are lower in the pre-market after the company expressed concerns about weaker currencies in key emerging markets. The company says the devaluation of developing market currencies will be a significant drag on its profit growth, and meanwhile, Nike also reporting an unexpected third quarter of results. Take a look. The company posted an adjusted profit of 76 cents a share. That's four cents above the estimate. Revenue coming in at $6.97 billion, also beating expectations. Dagen, back to you.
MCDOWELL: Jo, thank you so much for that. Good to see you.
KENT: Good to see you, too.
MCDOWELL: And, good news from the Federal Reserve. Stress tests conducted on the nation's largest banks now show they could easily withstand a hypothetical economic meltdown even worse than the 2008 financial crisis. With more on that story, we go to Peter Barnes in Washington.
PETER BARNES, FBN: Well, all but one of the top 30 U.S. and foreign banks with major U.S. operations have passed the latest stress test from the Federal Reserve. These are the big banks, with more than $50 billion in assets. All of the top banks passed, as expected. Zions Bancorp was the only bank that would have less than the projected necessary capital by the end of 2015, but fed officials stressed that Zions still has time to fix this through its capital plans. The top performers under the stress test were State Street, Discover Financial, and Bank of New York Mellon.
Under Dodd-Frank fincial reform, the fed must estimate whether the biggest banks could survive and continue to operate in another terrible financial crisis and recession. So, the taxpayers don't have to bail them out again. The stress test this time around says they would lose $366 billion on their loans as a group through the end of 2015 under this difficult scenario, about $500 billion including trading losses. But despite that, as a group, they would survive the shock, the fed says, because they have been beefing up capital since the crisis. The 30 banks in aggregate would still end up with tier one common capital, the strongest form of shareholder equity of 7.6 percent. By the end of 2015, they will be required to have at least five percent tier one capital. Back to you.
MCDOWELL: And Lori has more business headlines related to that stress test.
ROTHMAN: I do indeed, especially if you happen to have shares of Discover. The credit card company, Discover Financial, is proposing a 20 percent increase in its dividends, and up to a $1.6 billion share buyback, so again, if you own shares of Discover Financial, that's great. Now, this comes as Discover easily passed its stress test. Discover still needs fed approval, though, for the moves. The company has benefitted from more rapid loan growth while expanding its lending offerings to student loans, mortgages, and home equity loans. Shares of Discover, no surprise, up in extended trading.
A deal to end the week. This broke just about an hour or so ago, Media General -- we are learning -- is buying Lynn Media, the price tag is $1.6 billion, so that breaks down to $27.82 a share. Add in the debt, and the deal has enterprise value of $2.6 billion. There you see Media General -- that's a nice chart over the last year or so.
Now, shares of Symantec though, different story, down in extended trading after the company fired its CEO, Steve Bennett. It's the second time in less than two years the security software maker dumped the CEO. Bennett, the former head of Quantum has been the CEO of Symantec since July 2012.
Well, the company's revenue declined each of the last two quarters, and the stock was down about 15 percent of the last 12 months.
And that about sums up our Friday morning business update.
MCDOWELL: I know.
And we have got more laughs coming up.
Look at how nice it is outside.
So if you have been watching "Imus in the Morning" lately you know there has been recent changes to the cast of the weekly segment, Hollywood and Vine. One of those now former members of the panel is Rob Bartlett who was not too happy about being replaced.
ROTHMAN: Poor Bob.
(BEGIN VIDEOTAPE)
(INTERVIEW WITH BOB BARTLETT)
(END VIDEOTAPE)
MCDOWELL: Always a good time.
Coming up the latest on the search for the Malaysian air flight 370, now becoming a race against time to find what actually happened to the missing airliner.
In an attack would on what was supposed to be a safest hotel in Afghan leaves nine dead, plus we will check on the markets and get a look at the weekend forecast.
Stay with us.
ROTHMAN: All right, checking out the markets for you this morning. It looks like we will wrap up this week on a high note.
Here's a look at Asia, higher across the board with the Shanghai and up nearly 3 percent, the Nikkei closed due to a holiday, by the way.
In Europe gains across the board as well, with the DAX up 39 points or nearly one half of 1 percent.
Here in the U.S. we are suggesting -- futures rather are suggesting a higher open after a sell-off yesterday care of brand new Fed chair, Janet Yellen, spooking investors saying interest rates will likely rise sooner rather than later.
And there's a look at commodities for you, crude oil flirting with $100 a barrel once again, and gold spiking up another $8 dollars an ounce this morning.
Now to some new stories making headlines, search crews far into the Indian ocean have sent the night looking for debris from missing Malaysia air flight 370. So far they've been unable to locate it.
Doug Luzader has the story for us, this morning, from Washington.
(BEGIN VIDEOTAPE)
DOUG LUZADER, FBN (on camera): One of the big problems here is just how remote this part of the world is. Search aircraft, for instance, that are taking off from Australia, that is about a 6-7 hour round trip out to the site of this search, and that leaves them precious little time to do any looking.
(voice-over): The U.S. Navy's most advanced sub hunter, the P8 Poseidon, is putting in some long hours. It and other aircraft are combing the Indian ocean for some sign of that debris that was spotted by a satellite five days ago almost 1,500 miles offshore from Australia. Australian officials say this is the best lead so far. One of those pieces measures nearly 80 feet, they think. But even Australia's prime minister says it's entirely possible this could be just another dead end.
AUSTRALIAN PRIME MINISTER TONY ABBOTT: It could just be a container that's fallen off a ship. We just don't know.
LUZADER: Meantime, tough questions for Malaysian officials who are managing the overall investigation. Why did they wait so long to pursue a lead that would eventually take search crews so far south? The company operating the satellite that continued to receive those signals from the plane for hours after it was otherwise lost says it turned over that data almost immediately.
CHRIS MCLAUGHLIN SENIOR V.P. INMARSAT: Saturday when the plane went missing, we were asked whether we had any data relating to the flight, and within three hours to four hours we had handed over the basic flight data information to the supplier of the avionics to the plane.
LUZADER: And that long delay could make finding any debris more difficult. Already search teams are battling spotty weather in the Indian ocean.
RICK (?): Today's flight into tomorrow's flight, weather is going to be looking pretty good at least for that visual observation, and then things change again for about another 48 hours as the next storm moves on in.
LUZADER (on camera): And weather may end up being a big factor here. These objects are not easy to spot even in these satellite pictures, and they may have moved a fair distance from when the pictures were taken.
For the Fox Business Network in Washington, I'm Doug Luzader, back to you in New York.
(END VIDEOTAPE)
MCDOWELL: Doug, thank you.
ROTHMAN: All right. Taliban gunmen killed nine people in an attack on a luxury hotel in Kabul Thursday night before being shot dead by security forces. The assault on the Serena hotel is the latest in a string of bold attacks by insurgents seeking to disrupt the presidential election on April 5th.
It started when four Taliban gunmen snuck past security and hid inside the hotel for hours before opening fire on diners inside the hotel's restaurant. Guests hid in rooms or fled to hotel bunkers. Some 18 U.N. staffers were inside the hotel at the time. They've all been accounted for. Police are investigating how the gunmen got into the heavily guarded hotel, which was considered the safest in that city.
President Obama has issued new sanctions against Russian president, Vladimir Putin, and his inner circle after Russia voted Thursday to annex the Black Sea peninsula of Crimea from the Ukraine. The new U.S. sanctions target 20 officials and one bank. The individuals named by the Treasury Include Putin's chief of staff and his personal banker.
Russia responded with its own list of sanctions targeting some U.S. Congressional leaders including House Speaker John Boehner, Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid and Senator John Mccain. After hearing the news, Senator Mccain Tweeted, "Guess this means my spring break in Siberia is off, Gazprom stock is lost and secret bank account in Moscow is frozen.
There you go, Senator Mccain.
ROTHMAN: Well, speaking of that whole ordeal, Vladimir Putin has officially made Crimea part of Russia. Putin signed a bill today completing the region's annexation from Ukraine, nearly two weeks after Russian troops had taken over Crimea.
Meanwhile, Russia's prime minister says, Ukraine owes Russia $11 billion for a defunct gas deal. That's what Mccain was referring to. Russia had agreed to provide cheap natural gas to Ukraine for its use of the Sevastopol naval base in Crimea.
However, now that Crimea and the city of Sevastopol are part of Russia, the deal is, "Subject to denunciation," and Russia can sue Ukraine. Meanwhile, Ukraine's ambassador to the U.N. says there are signs that Russia's preparing for further military intervention in the eastern region, a claim denied by Moscow.
And senior officials announcing yesterday that an intelligence leaker, Edward Snowden's' claims of U.S. industrial espionage are false.
With more on this story, we go to Rich Edson in our D.C. bureau.
EDSON: Well, a senior U.S. intelligence official denies the U.S. government spies on foreign countries and gives valuable information to American companies. This after National Security Agency leaker Edward Snowden charged the U.S. with corporate espionage.
A senior intelligence official tells Fox Business the U.S. will target foreign companies or executives for national security purposes, or targeting companies or executives as a way to broadly assess a country's economic capabilities and weaknesses. And one analyst says, there is a difference between that and what some governments in Europe and China do.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
CLAUDE BARFIELD, AMERICAN ENTERPRISE INSTITUTE: The key here is that it wasn't, I think, to pass on information -- competitive information to U.S. corporations as we strongly suspect the Chinese government does and some other governments have done. Its basically for some kind of intelligence operations.
RICH EDSON, FOX BUSINESS: The official also says US intelligence will target officials working in sanctions countries like Iran or North Korea, now Russia, and help determine which sanctions will be most effective or if they are working. Back to you.
DAGEN MCDOWELL, FOX BUSINESS: And did your bracket get broken? did your bracket get busted during the first full day of March madness? Well there were record four games that went to overtime and three major upsets, so a lot of people are weeping this morning.
First up was the battle for Ohio With Dayton stunning rival Ohio state 60 to 59. Then Harvard heavily which on top of heavily favored Cincinnati and the North Dakota state that shocked the Sinners in Oklahoma with an 80-75 win in overtime. Today's gains include number one seed's Arizona versus Weaver State out west. Virginia faces Coastal Carolina in the east and the only unbeaten team in the tourney which Cal State versus Cal Poly in the Midwest, so will the nerds win? Probably not.
And now let's get the latest on the weather from meteorologist, Maria Molina, in our weather center. Maria.
MARIA MOLINA, FOX BUSINESS WEATHER: Hi. Good morning. Hello, everyone. We have relatively warm temperatures today for the first full day of spring along many areas from Texas up into the northeast. You could see parts Del Rio, you're going to be in the middle 80s, 60s in Chicago, and into the 50s and places like New York City. But it all changes by the latter half of the weekend. We are expecting cooler temperatures moving into parts of the Midwest, like in Chicago where your high Zen are dipping down into the 30s, teens in Marquette, and by Monday, it gets even colder out here, temperatures only in the 20s for you in the city of Boston and also in Buffalo.
We do have several areas of snow and one of those areas is a cross parts of the upper Midwest early today. Winters for morning in effect out there. And several inches of snow expected along parts of northern New England today. That's it. Over to you.
MCDOWELL: Maria, thank you so much for that. And Lori's got business news.
LORI ROTHMAN, FOX BUSINESS ANCHOR: Yeah, let's do it! Here you go. These are your top business stories. Four members of the Federal reserve planning to give their own take on central bank policy. This comes two days after fed chair Janet Yellen made remarks that set stock markets reeling. Yellen suggested interest rates could rise sooner than many had expected. Now, the President of the Minneapolis Feds, St Louis Fed, Dallas Fed as well as Fed governor Jeremy Stein are all expected to speak today. We'll bring you headlines if they should come about.
In the mean time, Netflix CEO Reed Hastings said internet service providers should give content companies adequate network connections for free. This comes after Netflix reached a deal to take Comcast for faster online delivery for movies to TV shows. Hastings calls to see (ph) an arbitrary tax that the company would pay in certain cases to protect its customers' experience. Comcast says the fee has been an ample option to ensure customers enjoy optimal performance at a fair price.
Mt. Gox reducing the number -- the total number of missing bitcoin from 850,000 to a paltry 650,000. The Tokyo-based bitcoin exchange says it has found 200,000 bitcoin in a wallet that it no longer uses. I should checked my old jeans I guess.
(CROSSTALK)
ROTHMAN: Mt. Gox was shut down last month and the company did file for bankruptcy protection. Dagen.
MCDOWELL: That's exactly what it is. So, coming up. This is a great interview, author, Alan Paul, will stop by the program to chat with the I- man about his book, One Way Out: The Inside History of the Allman Brothers Band. You love sky dog, I love Sky dog. You don't want to miss it. Don't go anywhere.
(BEGIN AUDIO CLIP)
ALAN PAUL, AUTHOR: I was very excited to write about them, got to know them and then I sort of working in a guitar world and just one thing after another they liked the stories. They trusted me because I would primarily would talk about the music. When I would talked about the other things and I think it carries through to the book, it's about how it affected the music, I didn't really want to talk about gossip just for gossip sake.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
ROTHMAN: You're looking at Asian markets right now. Global markets rallied after a big sell-off the session before, care of the U.S. Feds. Still Kopi at 0.80 and Shanghai the index there - well, the Shanghai index is up about 3 percent. It's Friday, folks. It's been of long week there in Europe. Gains across the board. Let's see how the U.S. is shaping up.
U.S. Stock-Index Futures are pointing to a higher open after some good economic data and a day after Janet Yellen told us interest rates will rise sooner than we had earlier expected. Crude oil is just for a $100 a barrel and gold popping up today almost eight bucks an ounce to gain so far. $1338.60 is the price of gold.
MCDOWELL: Author Alan Paul recently joined us on IMUS IN THE MORNING to talk about his new book, One Way Out: The Inside History of the Allman Brothers Band, and here's some of that interview.
(BEGIN AUDIO CLIP)
IMUS: Let's please welcome to the program Alan Paul. Good morning, Mr. Paul.
PAUL: Good morning thanks for having me.
IMUS: How are you?
PAUL: I'm doing good. I'm not really used to being up and talking at this hour as you are.
IMUS: Yeah. All of these bands -- I'm just thinking about it, they all have problems. I mean, like I just watched a documentary about the Eagles. They all hate Don Faller and each other. I mean, I'm just saying is there any band that ever stayed together? I mean, I guess the Stones get along pretty much though.
PAUL: Oh no, not really.
IMUS: Oh, yeah?
PAUL: They have gone years without speaking with one another.
IMUS: So, the Allman Brothers are particularly interesting because everybody likes the Allman Brothers, even people who don't know much about them like me still like them, you know. How are you able to get access to them and get them agreed to do this?
PAUL: One step at a time. You know, I started covering the band in 1989, they had just reformed with the Warren Haynes I think a regular on your show
IMUS: I love him.
PAUL: Yeah, He was a hot young guitarist at the time when nobody knew coming up. And they had just reformed, I was just getting my career started I had always loved the band, going back to when I was 12 years old. I chose Duane Allman as my great American to write about in eighth grade social studies class, and so, I was very excited to write about them, got to know them. Then I started working at guitar world and just one thing after another. They liked the stories, they trusted me because I would primarily talked about the music and when I would talk about the other things and I think it carries through to the book, it's about how it affected the music. I didn't really want to talk about gossip just for gossip sake.
IMUS: They got back together in 89, was it?
PAUL: In 1989, yep. For 20th anniversary tour, they performed in 69.
IMUS: OK, so when did they break up?
PAUL: Which time? Yeah, they formed in 69. They broke up in 75-76. Then they got back together 79. They broke up in 82. That 79-82 run was really the only time that was sort of embarrassing, so nobody really knew what to expect.
IMUS: Why was it embarrassing?
PAUL: Well, you see, at one time when the music didn't stand up to the tradition of the music. I think a lot of it had to do with -- they did one pretty good album when they first got back together and the record company kind of flamed out, and they signed with Arista Records ran by Clive Davis also signed The Grateful Dead. They were sort in the process of trying to make all these great old bands sound new, you know. Why would you want to sound like you were from 1971. Let's get some synthesizers and get some pop songwriters
IMUS: Sure.
PAUL: And you know, it was sort of the normal stuff that is happening. The most embarrassing moment is when they appeared on Solid Gold, and you can watch Marilyn McCoo interview Greg Allman. It is pretty painful.
IMUS: When did Duane Allman die?
PAUL: Duane Allman died in 1971. So, he was only with the band for 2-1/2 years.
IMUS: How by the age 24 did he become such one of the phenomenal guitar players of all time, I guess?
PAUL: You know, the guitar playing is one thing. You know, you can listen to it, you can understand the music. There is no real explanation except that he was completely dedicated to it. From the time he was 16, he dropped out of school and was completely driven but what struck me in writing the book, I understood his musical legacy, was how vibrant person he was. You talk to these guys -- members of the band, but also these other people who were close to him, and it is if he walked out of the room a week ago or yesterday.
He remains such a guiding force for them and I think to this day, you go see them at the Beacon Theater, as I have been doing every night, three nights into a 49 run, I think Duane is still their guiding spirit. I think when they have to make a musical decision, it comes under what would Duane do.
IMUS: Talking with Alan Paul, his new book is called One Way Out: The Inside History of the Allman Brothers. They are at the Beacon Theatre. Derek Trucks Warren Haynes are leaving the band now after this?
PAUL: They've announced that they will no longer tour after 2014, so not at the end of the Beacon. You still have a few festivals coming up and they're gonna do something in the fall. They haven't announced what.
IMUS: Why are they leaving I wonder, other than what they said.
PAUL: You have to ask them.
IMUS: You should ask them, and then, tell me. What do you think they're leaving?
PAUL: You know, I think that they're both younger guys obviously. Derek is 32 and has his own band with his wife, Susan Tedeschi -- Tedeschi Trucks Band. Warren of course has government mule. He has Warren Haynes Band, and they dedicated a good chunk of their careers and lives to helping keep this great institution going and it obviously benefited their careers.
IMUS: Sure.
PAUL: And they are both at a stage in their lives they have kids, have their own band and want their own lives, and move on.
IMUS: Shocking to me how good Warren Haynes is. It's shocking.
PAUL: Warren is you know really a complete package. I mean, he's obviously a great guitar player and also a great singer and songwriter, and he really is the defacto band leader, and I think that's a skill -- again, if you go back to the unknown thing about Duane, what kept them going was that fire. Warren has this incredible ability to pull things together. I mean, you can take any one musician and throw them on the stage, Warren would be the guy you want conducting it.
IMUS: Do you think Greg still likes doing this?
PAUL: I do think Greg likes doing this, but I think Greg also really enjoys having his own band. I mean, Greg says to me in the book at one point that the difference between having the Allman Brothers Band and his own band is that he is the driver of his own band and with the Allman Brothers Band has four drivers punching each other in the head and sometimes, it gets a little frustrating.
IMUS: He has a great voice. Does he still has a great voice?
PAUL: He's still a great voice, and the thing that is amazing is there have been periods as recently as two years ago he was sick -- people at the Beacon, he missed the last show and a half, we were really worried about him. He sounded very diminished and he sounds fantastic now. I actually think he sounds better than he did in 1990-'91 when they got back together.
IMUS: Who caused all the problems? Dickey Betts -- is that the catalyst for all of this?
PAUL: Well, I'd say nobody has their hands completely clean, but Dickey clearly was a difficult guy to deal with. You know, it's no secret that Greg has really struggled with various addictions and so at times was sort of checked out, and that allowed Dickey just more and more take power. Dickey I think is an incredible musical presence. He was the guy who pulled it out the fire after Duane died, and nobody thought they would be able to continue and they ended up having their greatest success. He wrote Rambling Man, he wrote Jessica, great, great music in the void of Duane.
IMUS: Is he still a pretty good guitar player you think?
PAUL: Dickey is a fantastic guitar player.
IMUS: As good as Warren Haynes or better?
PAUL: You know, Imus, they are so different. It's really hard to compare. I'd say Warren is definitely more versatile. Warren you can throw in any situation, he would sound great. Dickey is much more of a stylist. He has his, but the style he created is so unique. It's relatively simple. You know, a lot of guitarists could play that way, but not with that touch, not with that tone. They didn't invented it, they didn't come up with that.
IMUS: What kind of guitar does he play?
PAUL: Dickey is a Gibson man. He mostly played -- he is most famous for Les Paul, but also SG which is what he plays now.
IMUS: What did warren play?
PAUL: Also a Gibson man. Am I getting anything from this? The Allman Brothers are very much a Gibson.
IMUS: They are?
PAUL: Derek plays a Gibson SG, Warren plays a variety a variety of Gibson, mostly Les Paul and 335.
IMUS: I remember -- I don't know if this has anything to do with the music but there was a time they all will turn on each other out of some cocaine deal. Tell me about that. What happened and when was it?
PAUL: Well, that was a big ugly story.
IMUS: Like when I was on cocaine. I used to do that all the time.
PAUL: Well, you know, it was in the air so to speak. That was all happening in 1975-76 in Machen, Georgia. Greg got caught up in a Federal sting, Butch Trucks, you know, founding drummer says that it was all about republican politicians in Georgia going after Jimmy Carter. I can't say if that was true or not, I didn't figure that one out. But there was a large sting of some pharmacies and other things that were selling pharmaceutical cocaine. They found someone who was the band's basically security man who is buying mass quantities supplying Greg. They put a serious pinch on Greg, and he testified to sort of save his own skin.
IMUS: Greg did?
PAUL: He did.
IMUS: Didn't Dickey wrapped (ph) somebody out or no?
PAUL: Oh, no. Dickey didn't know. It was all Greg. But what happened was, when that happened is that Butch, Jaymo (ph), and Dickey, the other surviving members all said they would never play with Greg again.
IMUS: Oh, that's right.
PAUL: And Greg became sort of notorious. You know, he had to have protection. He was getting death threats. He was called a snitch. You know, Greg says that Scooter, the guy he was testifying against, basically said there is no reason for you to take the fall, just do it. He was sentenced to a huge amount of time and so, that is the headline. They ended up appealing his case, and in fact, he ended up serving only about a year.
IMUS: Still a long time here.
PAUL: Yeah, I mean, who are we cast stones?
IMUS: Oh, I am not. Believe me, not me.
PAUL: Yeah, so, I think in retrospect everybody sort of feels what would you do if you're in Greg's situation? At the time, they were under tremendous strain. Frankly, I think the band was falling apart. That was the final straw and it is generally called the thing that broke the Allman Brothers up, but I think they were sort of crumbling at that point anyhow.
IMUS: So they reformed in '89.
PAUL: Yes.
IMUS: And they have been together since then?
PAUL: They have been. There have been changes. Obviously, in 2000, they parted with Dickey Betts after years.
IMUS: What is he doing now?
PAUL: Dickey is out with his own band. He has not performed nearly as much as the allman brothers. He did three shows in our metro area last week, so he still gets out and performs, has his own band, Dickey Betts and Great Southern.
IMUS: Do they speak or no?
PAUL: No, I don't believe so. There have been various outreaches to Dickey. I know he was invited in 2009 to the Beacon for their 42nd anniversary to play, and seriously considered it, ended up not even responding. I tried to figure out if there has been any direct contact now. This year, to the best of my knowledge, there hasn't been. Derek Trucks has been in touch with Dickey. We know that because Dickey played with his band, The Tedeschi Trucks Band in September at the Beacon. So, a lot of people are excited to see Dickey on stage with a member of the Allman Brothers, but not quite the same thing.
IMUS: I'm talking with Alan Paul whose book One Way Out: The Inside Story of The Allman Brothers. It sounds fascinating, you know. Any surprises even for you?
PAUL: Oh, yeah. There were a lot of surprises. I mean small surprises.
IMUS: Like?
PAUL: Warren Haynes never liked the first version of Soulshine that they recorded. There's a lot of little things like that, but in the bigger picture you know, I was taken by the vitality of Duane and the extent to which he still runs the show in so many ways being absent. I was also surprised to learn how close Duane Allman came to quitting the Allman Brothers in 1970 and running off with Eric Clapton, Eric and the Dominoes.
IMUS: They (inaudible) one time.
PAUL: Right. Duane really lit Clapton on fire in that whole album.
IMUS: Sure.
PAUL: Of course, I knew that but I didn't realize at the end of it, Eric Clapton gave him a very real offer to come off and join the band, and he very nearly accepted it.
IMUS: You get into these senior writers (ph) for Guitar World. You get into these conversations about who's the best guitar player and all that?
PAUL: No, I don't really believe in that. I got to be honest.
IMUS: I don't either.
PAUL: It's like who is the best radio host? It just depends on your taste.
(CROSSTALK)
PAUL: I mean, there is no best anything. What is the best restaurant? I mean, what do you like better, sushi or steak?
IMUS: There have been some great guitar players.
PAUL: There have been some great players. I think Duane Allman certainly has to be at the top of any...
IMUS: Stevie Ray of course. Do you like him?
PAUL: Of course, I like Stevie Ray, the fire, the passion. I think there's a lot of connection between Stevie Ray and Duane, but the thing about Duane is any session he walked into, he lit it on fire. When he was 21 years old, the second session he did was with Wilson Pickett. Wilson Pickett is one of the biggest stars in the country.
IMUS: On the Hey Jude record?
PAUL: Well, he was cutting other stuff, and they were unsatisfied with songs and Duane said, hey, man, we ought to do Hey, Jude. That was the idea.
IMUS: Oh, really?
PAUL: Yeah. The second session he has ever done, he was with the world super star and they laughed at him. Hey, Jude was number 4 on the chart with The Beatles. Why the heck would we do that? And Duane stuck to his guns. It says a lot about his musicality and his personality.
IMUS: Is this a true story? Because I played the end of Wilson Pickett's Hey Jude earlier this morning.
PAUL: Oh, good.
IMUS: Because that guitar solo at the end was apparently so impressive that somebody played it on the phone. Is that a true story?
PAUL: That's a true story. It is a true story that Clapton told me that he was driving and I picture him driving a big Rolls-Royce, he didn't give me that detail but he was driving his car, heard it on the radio, and they had to listen to it, and when he got home, he immediately called Atlantic and said his playing the guitar on Wilson Pickett's Hey Jude?
IMUS: The thing that irritated me about it was Wilson Pickett wouldn't shut up.
PAUL: Well, the other thing about Wilson Pickett apparently, he was singing Hey Jew.
(LAUGHTER)
PAUL: Tom Dow told me when Duane suggested it, Wilson said he won't let us record a song called Hey Jew. He definitely saying Hey Jew the first time through. It is the debate whether he did or redid it.
IMUS: Oh, man, well, whatever. Sounds like a fascinating book.
PAUL: Thank you. You know, there is no end of interesting stories.
IMUS: Oh, God. I imagine.
MCDOWELL: Oh, man, Sky dog. How missed he is. Coming up, we look at the markets, the Opening Bell, and of course some more great moments from the I-man. Stay with us.
ROTHMAN: Check on your markets around the world. I'm hoping for a good day here in the U.S. and certainly, it was that in Asia. Those markets closed, and of course, Japan closed, never traded today. Gains across the board in England, France and Germany and they've pared the gains some and there's green there. A little bit of a pullback in the Futures that we've seen. The Dow Futures up 27 points, and oil and gold also heading higher.
ROTHMAN: We're looking at 2 percent gains for the benchmark averages in the U.S. this week.
MCDOWELL: What else is going on? Deals?
ROTHMAN: A lot of things for investors to chew on this morning, probably will add to the positive sentiment this morning. Media General is buying Lin Media for 1.6 billion, which breaks out to $27.82 per share. It's a 29-1/2 percent premium to Lin's closing price. Shares of Lin are soaring on the news, add in the debt and the deal has an enterprise value of $2.6 billion.
And Darden Restaurant shares lower in the pre-market. And a third quarter profit lowered analyst expectations and trouble for Red Lobster and Olive Garden, and Long Horn Steakhouse chains, too, all posting an adjusted profit of just 82 cents a share, revenue at 2.23 billion, fallen short of the estimate. And Darden says severe winter weather hurt profits. Nobody one wanted to go for dinner, I guess. Same store (inaudible) restaurant sales down 8.8 percent at Red Lobster, nearly 5-1/2 percent down at Olive Garden Darden says it is sticking with its plan to spin off or sell Red Lobster.
OK. We're just moments away from the Opening Bell with Maria Bartiromo. Here's Maria with our preview.
MARIA BARTIROMO, OPENING BELL HOST: Hi, Lori. Thanks. Happy Friday. At the top of the hour on Opening Bell, banks flying high after the stress test results. Shareholders will certainly benefit from it. Vladimir Putin signs a law to make Crimea part of Russia. Ian Bremmer of the Eurasia group here with me to talk about it. Turkey Dance Twitter, Mark Zuckerberg at the White House and why history tells us that we are long overdue for a correction. Will it be right? That and a lot of more at the top of the hour on Opening Bell. Back to you, Lori.
ROTHMAN: All right. Busy week to wrap up today. Thanks, Maria.
MCDOWELL: That's right. So, you'll never know what you're going to get on IMUS IN THE MORNING but there's one guarantee, laughs are always here and here are some recent lighter moments.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
IMUS: Look what Carley did. She left her curling iron on. This morning -- it's not a curling iron, a hair straightener, right?
CARLEY NOELLE: Yes, I can't stop thinking about it.
IMUS: She left it on in her apartment.
MCSHANE: Right.
IMUS: And I said, well, do you want to go home and fix it? I was going to have Brandt take her, but then has to go and pick up Deirdre. So, I said take a cab and turn it off.
MCSHANE: An IMUS IN THE MORNING alert. If you live in Carley's building, evacuate now.
(LAUGHTER)
IMUS: That's right. If you live Carley's building, the place is going to blow up.
BARTLETT: We have a situation here (ph), straightener on fire.
IMUS: So, if you were gonna put somebody on Mt. Rushmore, we have Sinatra, Elvis and The Beatles.
KATHLEEN MCFARLAND: Sinatra, Elvis and The Beatles.
IMUS: You got to put somebody else up there. Who else would you put up there?
MCFARLAND: Maybe Bob Dylan.
IMUS: Not bad. You know we were talking about this the other day.
MCSHANE: That didn't come up.
MCFARLAND: Who would you have put up?
MCGUIRK: I'd push Dylan off Mt. Rushmore.
IMUS: I only say this, he is a friend of mine, but Little Richard I would put up there. I mean, a casual friend. It's not like we're buddies, but I might even go back, talking with Lou Rufino, make it go back with Robert Johnson. But got to put Dylan up there, don't you, Bernie?
MCGUIRK: No, absolutely not. I would just as soon push him off Mt. Rushmore than put him on there.
IMUS: You're a horrible human being.
RUFINO: Hey, Bernie, I'm falling, hey, hey.
(LAUGHTER)
IMUS: Oh, man, highway 61, come on, dude.
RUFINO: You gonna push me, Bernie or what?
]]></text></news-item>