<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT2-XSV1-JC85-N1SJ"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>A small town warily leading Japan's nuclear reawakening</title><source>International New York Times</source><author>MARTIN FACKLER</author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
To power his plans for Japan's economic revival, Prime Minister Shinzo Abe could soon return his nation to nuclear power for the first time since the Fukushima accident three years ago. But before he can, he will need the consent of the remote towns like this one that host Japan's idled nuclear plants.
All signs are that he will get it. In Japan's political world, local consent means getting the approval of the host communities' mayors, many of whom say they have suffered from loss of plant-related tax revenue and jobs that lifted living standards in their once-impoverished rural towns and villages. Ikata's mayor says local businesses are clamoring for a restart of their local plant, the Ikata Nuclear Power Station, built in 1977 on a narrow peninsula facing Japan's Inland Sea.
The mayor, Kazuhiko Yamashita, said in an interview that he would accept the plant's resuming operations if central government regulators proclaimed it safe. Political analysts say such a cooperative attitude has made Ikata likely to be near the front of the line when Mr. Abe's government turns on the first of Japan's 48 idled reactors, which could come as early as this summer.
But that does not mean all of Ikata's 10,700 residents are happy about leading their nation back into the atomic power age. Many confess to feeling deeply conflicted about the plant, located just north of the town center over a row of mountains covered with mandarin orange groves, Ikata's other economic mainstay.
While most were reluctant to say so publicly, many quietly expressed a mixture of resignation and dread about the prospect of restarting the plant. They said that while they know the town depends on it economically, they fear living with a new nightmare, of suffering the same fate as residents from the evacuated towns around the Fukushima Daiichi plant.
''The restart question gives us complex feelings,'' said Akihito Sakamoto, a town employee. ''We feel frightened by the plant, but we also know we need it.''
The town's angst is a microcosm for the indecision that has gripped Japan as a whole. Though it has idled its undamaged reactors because of post-Fukushima safety fears, it also frets about losing a vital source of energy for this resource-poor nation. Mr. Abe and his governing Liberal Democratic Party, which has close ties to Japan's powerful nuclear industry, have vowed to break through the logjam by restarting at least some reactors to provide low-cost electricity in hopes of keeping more factories and jobs in Japan.
This has led to growing political pressure on the newly created nuclear monitoring agency to speed through safety reviews of the 17 most modern Japanese reactors, including the newest of the three reactors at the Ikata power station, as a step toward turning them back on. Analysts and industry executives say the first approvals could come in May or June, possibly in time for peak summer use.
It would then fall on the host towns to give final approvals before Mr. Abe's government could restart the plants. Politicians and analysts say this will place intense pressure on local residents, including mayors, to swallow whatever misgivings they might have and say yes.
''The lack of a national consensus on nuclear power shifts the burden of decision to these local communities,'' said Motohisa Furukawa, a former minister in charge of economic and energy strategy. ''Towns will feel bound to serve the national interest.''
Ikata, on the western edge of Shikoku, the smallest of Japan's four main islands, is already feeling the pressure in a different form, the enormous financial losses caused by the idling of its plant.
Town officials say Ikata's overall annual tax revenue has plummeted by a third, or about $35 million, since the last of the plant's three reactors went off-line two years ago. The biggest reason, officials said, is the disappearance of revenue from a tax that host communities are allowed to place on all new nuclear fuel brought into the plants. Those shipments have stopped since the reactors have been turned off.
Since then, the mayor, Mr. Yamashita, has called for reducing Ikata's dependence on the plant by attracting more tourists to pick oranges or to fish in the Inland Sea. However, he also admits that it is impossible to replace the plant as the basis of the town's economic well-being.
''We know the plant has risk, but so does riding in an airplane or a car,'' Mr. Yamashita said. ''We want the national government to convince us that they are taking every measure to reduce that risk as much as possible.''
Nowhere is his town's economic dependence on the plant more evident than in the appearance of the town hall, much of it funded by plant-related income. The oversize seven-story structure dwarfs every building around it - except for an equally imposing one next door that houses the museum-style promotional center for the Ikata nuclear plant.
The two buildings are linked by an umbilical cord-like elevated walkway.
As is often the case in Japan's close-knit rural areas, many Ikata residents were reluctant to express opinions that could anger fellow townspeople, in this case by criticizing the plant that neighbors depend on for their livelihoods. Most offered only glimpses of their fears, and then only if assured they would not be identified by name.
Still, there has been an appearance of open, if limited, opposition to the plant, evident in the bright yellow hand-painted signs outside its gates that proclaim ''Absolutely No Nukes!'' A few townspeople also joined a lawsuit to shut it down permanently, though most of the 1,002 plaintiffs are from neighboring towns. The case, which was filed after the March 2011 Fukushima accident, is still in court.
''I think there is a deep layer of opposition to the nuclear plant, but those with money are using fear-mongering about damage to the economy to suppress it,'' said one of the lawsuit's leaders, Hideto Matsuura, 68, a retired manager at a machinery manufacturer who lives in a nearby city.
The plant's operator, the Shikoku Electric Power Company, has tried to allay these fears by spending $840 million on a four-year plan to bring the plant in line with tougher new safety standards. This has included assembling a small fleet of trucks carrying backup generators and water pumps on high ground, out of reach of large tsunamis like the one that ruined power and water-cooling systems at the Fukushima plant.
The company says it has posted annual losses every year since the plant was idled because of the $70 million monthly cost of importing extra fuel for its overworked coal-fired plants.
''When the central government cannot make up its mind,'' said Akifumi Nishizaki, a Shikoku Electric spokesman, ''the local economies suffer the consequences.''
]]></text></news-item>