<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT2-KS91-JCB3-C35N"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Czech police detain Rittig, other accused in tickets case</title><source>CTK National News Wire</source><author>hol</author><text><![CDATA[Czech police detained lobbyist and businessman Ivo Rittig and the other four accused in the case of tickets for the Prague Transport Company (DPP) today, Prague High State Attorney Lenka Bradacova has said.
The High State Attorney's Office also proposed that the accused be remanded in custody for fear of their escape abroad in reaction to the Prague Municipal Court's decision to return passports to them.
A district court will decide on the custody.
Rittig, his business partner Peter Kmet, Neograph printing offices former executive Jan Janku and lawyers David Michal and Marek Stubley, from the MSB Legal firm, were accused of money laundering in February.
They face three to eight years in prison and forfeiture of property if found guilty.
The state attorneys proposed in February that the passports be seized instead of remanding the accused in custody and a district court met the proposal. Rittig and the other defendants appealed the decision with the Prague Municipal Court.
The Prague Transport Company (DPP) signed a contract on tickets printing with Neograph, which was mediated by the Cokeville Assets company from the British Virgin Islands represented by Kmet.
According to investigators, Neograph, controlled by Rittig, Michal and Stubley, sent 0.17 crown from every sold ticket to Kmet's firm.
The Anti-corruption Endowment says the money probably ended in Rittig's hands. He filed a legal complaint against the endowment over the statements but the Prague Municipal Court rejected it last June. The verdict can yet be appealed.
The DPP terminated the contract with Neograph in 2011. Since 2012, the State Printing Shop of Stamps has supplied the tickets. It later won a five-year contract worth 170 million crowns on tickets supplies until 2017.
($1=19.975 crowns)
hol/dr/ms
]]></text></news-item>