<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT2-TCR1-F125-14P7"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Plains Midstream Canada expands maintenance approach after spills, audit</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[In the wake of major oil spills in each of the last three years, an Alberta pipeline operator is spending an estimated $311 million to prevent future disasters.
Chastised by provincial energy regulators for maintenance failings and slow spill response and faced with large cleanup bills and charges that it broke environmental protection laws, Plains Midstream Canada now admits its biggest worry may be an ongoing audit of the firm's ability to operate safely.
"Future proceedings could result in additional operational ... constraints that would not apply to our competitors," the company's publicly traded U.S. parent warned investors last month.
"Significant additional expenses could be incurred if new or more stringently interpreted pipeline safety requirements are implemented."
The Alberta Energy Regulator took the unprecedented step last year of ordering an audit of the company's emergency planning, pipeline integrity and risk assessment programs.
The AER said the company's history of non-compliance since it began operations in Alberta in 2001 - including 19 high- and low-risk deficiencies in the previous two years - made the extra oversight necessary.
Officials with the government agency said the audit results will be shared with PMC this spring.
Unless or until the order under Section 22 of the Oil and Gas Conservation Act is lifted, the AER said in a prepared statement, the company also remains in regulatory purgatory.
Even routine or minor applications and decisions involving PMC require approval by the agency's chief executive.
"Should the company fail to adhere to the terms of the order, or continued non-compliance occurs while the order remains in force, the company may be subjected to restriction of operations up to, and including, shut in of pipelines facilities," the statement said.
While PMC officials would not comment for this story, public filings by its American parent reveal the company's behaviour has changed in the aftermath of the additional regulatory scrutiny and negative media attention the spills garnered.
For example, an Alberta Energy Regulator investigation report this month found the 2012 release of 460,000 litres of oil into the Red Deer River happened because PMC had failed to properly inspect and maintain a vulnerable water crossing near Sundre.
Despite a high streamflow advisory issued prior to the break, the report faulted the company for not purging the pipeline to minimize the damage should water scour cause a leak to occur. After last summer's flood warnings, however, PMC shut down and emptied some sections of its Canadian transmission system, a move that meant $15 million in lost revenue over the rest of the fiscal year, according to public filings.
The parent company's 2013 annual report shows it spent $205 million in the three previous years and expected to spend a further $106 million this year on "required and elective activities" to make its pipelines in Alberta and Saskatchewan less likely to fail.
Greg Armstrong, chief executive of Plains All American Pipeline LP, explained the Houston-based company's capital spending on safety in Canada to analysts last August.
"We're actually going in and doing what we call high directional drills." said Armstrong, "to actually lower the pipe underneath those rivers to make sure we don't have the issue in the future and to protect the environment, quite candidly."
The cleanup bills for its Alberta releases and their impact on the company's bottom line may also have been a factor in its decision to increase maintenance spending.
After 3.3 million litres leaked from a remote section of its Rainbow Pipeline in 2011, it cost PMC $70 million to reclaim the contaminated wetlands in northern Alberta.
An AER investigation of that spill found the company had failed to fully assess the history of the pipeline and identify the risks posed by the application of sleeves used for corrosion repair.
Its report found the spill - the largest in Alberta in over three decades - was made worse by the fact control room operators at the company's Olds facility repeatedly ignored alarms and restarted the pipeline three times after the rupture.
Company filings show the release from its Rangeland Pipeline in central Alberta in 2012 cost $46 million to mop up and an 83,000-litre spill last spring on the company's Kemp River Pipeline in the province's northwest will result in a $15-million bill for remediation.
The company also faces the possibility of up to $1.5 million in civil fines from charges in connection with the Rainbow spill. Nearly a year after charges were laid by Alberta Environment and Sustainable Resource Development, the company has yet to enter a plea.
Investigators with both the federal and provincial governments have said they are also looking at laying charges in connection with the 2012 incident on the Rangeland Pipeline.
The parent company's filings said "it is possible that fines or penalties may be assessed in future against PMC" in connection with the spills, but it reassured investors the amounts "are not expected to be material."
The firm, ranked 77th in the Fortune 500 list of the largest U.S. companies, saw net income surge 24 per cent to $1.3 billion last year on revenues of $42.2 billion. PMC's president, David Duckett, has seen his annual compensation increase by more than one-third during the past three years to $6 million.
The parent company has a checkered safety record, including a settlement with the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency that required it to spend $41 million upgrading pipelines and pay a $3.25-million civil penalty in connection with repeated spills into waterways in Texas, Louisiana and Oklahoma between 2004 and 2007.
Alberta government briefing notes in the aftermath of PMC's first spill in 2011, obtained by Greenpeace under Alberta's freedom of information legislation, show government officials were aware of the company's problems south of the border.
"The company's track record in the U.S. is unfortunate," the May note to then energy minister Ron Liepert said.
"However, we haven't experienced the same issues with the company in Alberta."
Keith Stewart, a spokesman for the environmental advocacy group, said knowledge of the U.S. problems should have prompted a closer look at PMC's operations by Alberta regulators that might have prevented the company's spate of spills in the province.
"If there is no credible threat of enforcement of environmental regulations, then companies will cut corners," Stewart said.
"It is unfortunate that it takes a media spotlight on spills to get the government to force companies to invest in safety."
mmcclure@calgaryherald.com( mailto:mmcclure@calgaryherald.com )
© Copyright (c) The Calgary Herald
]]></text></news-item>