<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT2-XBC1-JCB3-431G"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Zuckerberg after White House meeting says Obama's NSA reforms are 'not enough'</title><source>San Jose Mercury News (California)</source><author>By Brandon Bailey bbailey@mercurynews.com</author><text><![CDATA[Emerging from a lengthy White House meeting that was aimed at soothing concerns about the government's Internet spy programs, Facebook CEO Mark Zuckerberg signaled Friday that he's not satisfied with President Obama's proposed intelligence reforms.
"While the U.S. Government has taken helpful steps to reform its surveillance practices, these are simply not enough," a Facebook spokesperson said after the Friday afternoon meeting. "People around the globe deserve to know that their information is secure and Facebook will keep urging the US Government to be more transparent about its practices and more protective of civil liberties."
The hastily arranged meeting between Obama and several top Silicon Valley executives, including Google's Eric Schmidt, came after several days of increasingly vocal complaints by tech leaders.
Zuckerberg personally phoned Obama last week to voice frustration over what he called "the damage the government is creating for all of our future," following a report that the National Security Agency had developed a method of installing spy software on individual computers by masquerading as a Facebook network server. Google CEO Larry Page also criticized the government's surveillance programs this week.
"It's tremendously disappointing that our government did this and didn't tell us," Page said at a technology and design conference this week, referring to NSA programs revealed by former government contractor Edward Snowden.
Schmidt and other tech executives declined to speak after Friday's meeting, however, and a White House spokesman only characterized the session as "part of a continuing dialogue" over issues of "intelligence, technology and privacy." Zuckerberg, meanwhile, added through the Facebook spokesman that he is "grateful" for the President's "continued personal engagement on this issue."
Since his first campaign for the White House, Obama has cultivated a strong relationship with the tech industry, while enjoying the financial backing and advice of key tech leaders including Schmidt. But leading Silicon Valley executives have complained the administration's support for NSA spying has weakened public trust in the Internet -- and, particularly, Internet companies based in the United States.
Along with concerns about their customers' privacy, executives worry that consumers and business clients will shy away from using the services of Silicon Valley firms, for fear they'll be subject to government snooping. Analysts say U.S. companies could lose billions of dollars in business to foreign firms that promote their services by claiming to be less vulnerable to U.S. spying.
In addition to discussing the NSA on Friday, Obama also used the meeting to provide an update for tech leaders on the administration's review of privacy issues related to "big data," or the use of data-mining programs and other sophisticated technology to analyze vast amounts of consumer data.
That's an issue that could put some tech companies on the defensive, since many Internet companies rely on analyzing user data to deliver targeted advertising. White House advisor John Podesta, who has led the review, attended Friday's meeting and is expected to report publicly on his findings next month.
Also attending on Friday were CEOs Reed Hastings of Netflix, Drew Houston of Dropbox, Aaron Levie of Box and Alexander Karp of Palantir, according to a White House spokesman. Yahoo CEO Marissa Mayer reportedly was invited but could not attend because of a scheduling conflict.
Hastings, Schmidt and Mayer had attended an earlier White House meeting with other leading tech executives and Obama in December. Since then, Obama announced some planned reforms in January, although the most significant are aimed at NSA collection of bulk telephone calling records. Attorney General Eric Holder is expected to issue a more detailed set of recommended changes next week.
Houston and Levie are rising stars in the Internet industry, as founders of successful companies that provide web-based data storage and other services. Karp is less well-known, but his company has thrived by providing data analysis for commercial and government clients -- including the NSA and other agencies.
While the tech industry has been voicing frustration since the first leaks by Snowden last summer, executives have increasingly chafed at recent disclosures.
Facebook security chief Joe Sullivan said this week that his company's current encryption measures would block the particular NSA scheme that was revealed by the Guardian newspaper. But another industry source said the notion that the government would co-opt a trusted web service to distribute malicious software is galling to all Internet companies, which spend heavily on efforts to prevent such hacking.
Yahoo, meanwhile, was buffeted by a report last month that said a British spy agency used some NSA technology to collected webcam images from millions of Yahoo users who thought they were engaging in private video chat sessions.
Google said this week that "due to last summer's revelations" -- a clear reference to the Snowden leaks -- the company is now automatically encrypting all messages on its popular Gmail service as they pass between users and Google's servers and as they move between Google's data centers.
Follow this reporter atTwitter.com/BrandonBailey orgoogle.com/ +BrandonBaileyOnline or on Facebook at http://on.fb.me/ULIOfb
]]></text></news-item>