<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT2-KJ51-JCXB-23M6"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Starwood European Real Estate Finan Preliminary -3-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[While the directors may seek to mitigate any discount to NAV per share through the discount management mechanisms set out in the Prospectus, there can be no guarantee that they will do so or that such mechanisms will be successful and the directors accept no responsibility for any failure of any such strategy to effect a reduction in any discount or premium. Please see the Corporate Governance Section for further information on the discount management mechanisms.
The board monitors investment strategy and performance on an on-going basis and regularly reviews the Objective and Investment Policy in light of prevailing investor sentiment to ensure the Company remains attractive to its shareholders. Interest Risk The Group is subject to the risk that the loan income and income from the cash and cash equivalents will fluctuate due to movements in LIBOR or EURIBOR. The loans in place at 31 December 2013 have been structured so that 51.2% of the loans are fixed rate which provides protection from interest rate movements to the overall portfolio. In addition whilst the remaining 48.8% is classified as floating, 30.2% are subject to LIBOR or EURIBOR floors such that the interest cannot drop below a certain level which provides significant additional protection against downward interest risk. When reviewing future investments the Investment Manager will continue to review such opportunities to protect against downward interest risk. Credit Risk The Group's investments are subject to risk of default where a borrower is unable or does not pay interest or principal as it becomes due. In the event of a default the Group is generally entitled to enforce security, but the process may be expensive and lengthy and the outcome is dependent on sufficient capital being available to meet the borrower's obligations. Some of the investments made would rank behind senior debt tranches for repayment in the event that a borrower defaults, with the consequence of greater risk of partial or total loss. In addition, repayment of loans could be subject to the availability of refinancing options, including the availability of senior and subordinated debt and is also subject to the underlying value of the real estate collateral at the date of maturity. The Investment Adviser undertakes detailed due diligence on each loan. Whilst the precise scope of due diligence will depend on the proposed investment, such diligence will typically include independent valuations, building and measurement and environmental surveys, legal reviews of property title and key leases, where necessary mechanical and engineering surveys, accounting and tax reviews and know your customer checks. The loan is first taken to the Investment Adviser's Investment Committee for consideration and if approved is then presented to the Investment Manager for consideration. The loan investments made are secured by way of a standard security package depending on the type of asset and jurisdiction. This will generally include, but not be limited to, a first ranking charge or mortgage over the property (or in the case of any mezzanine participations a second ranking entitlement or second ranking charge) and a charge or pledge over all other assets of the borrower accompanied, usually, by security over the shares of the borrower. The Investment Adviser, Investment Manager and board also manages these risks by ensuring a diversification of investments in terms of geography, market and type of loan. The Investment Manager and Investment Adviser operate in accordance with the guidelines, investment limits and restrictions policy determined by the board. The directors review the investment of the portfolio against these guidelines, limits and restrictions on a regular basis. The Investment Manager provides the board with management information including performance data on each individual loan in the underlying portfolio. The directors monitor the implementation and results of the investment process with the Investment Manager at each board meeting and monitor risk factors in respect of the portfolio. Investment strategy is reviewed at each meeting. Liquidity Risk The Group's investments primarily consist of loans secured on real estate assets. Such investments are often illiquid and may be difficult for the Group to sell, particularly at times of market stress, and the price achieved on any such realisation is likely to be at a discount to the face value of the relevant loan. The Group currently has sufficient cash to manage any liquidity issues. In addition, the Group has the ability to borrow up to 20% of NAV in order to manage any liquidity issues that may arise. The Company is currently engaged with two lenders with a view to arranging such a facility. Valuation Risk Real estate valuation is inherently subjective and uncertain. In addition, the value of underlying real estate and the rental income it produces may fluctuate as a result of factors which are outside the Group's control. The Group is and will be exposed to the residential and commercial real estate markets and if those markets enter a downturn it could materially adversely affect the Group's business and financial condition. Commercial mortgage loans are subject to the ability of the property owner to generate net income from operating the property/ies as well as the risk of delinquency and financial difficulty of the tenants. A major occupier or tenant of a property financed by the Group could default and / or seek to renegotiate terms during the course of a tenancy, which would lower the value of that property and may impact on the income to service the related loans provided by the Group. Loans on residential for sale are subject to the ability of the developer to complete the development and sell the individual residential units. If the developer is unable to sell the units at the price anticipated this may impact on the borrower's ability to repay the loan. The Investment Adviser meets with all Borrowers on a regular basis to monitor developments in respect of each loan and reports to the Investment Manager and the board periodically and on an ad hoc basis where considered necessary. The Group's loans are held at amortised cost and are reviewed quarterly for signs of impairment by the Investment Adviser. The results of the impairment review are discussed with the Investment Manager and the board. The value of investments in accordance with International Financial Reporting Standards ("IFRS") requires considerable judgement. Community, Social, Employee, Human Rights and Environmental Issues In carrying out its activities and in its relationship with the community, the Group aims to conduct itself responsibly, ethically and fairly, including in relation to social and human rights issues. The Group has no employees and the board is composed entirely of non-executive directors. As an investment company, the Group has no direct impact on the environment. However, the Group believes that it is in the shareholders' interest to consider environmental, social and ethical factors when selecting and retaining investments. The Group believes that high standards of corporate social responsibility ("CSR") make good business sense and have the potential to protect and enhance investment returns. In the forthcoming year, it is planned to adopt a more integrated approach to assessing and reporting corporate social responsibility risks. Sustainability risk will be included within the Group's risk management framework and it is intended that further integration will be evident in the reporting of these risks in future reports. This work will be conducted in conjunction with the audit committee to create a group assurance framework. Board Diversity The board considers that its members have a balance of skills, qualifications and experience which are relevant to the Company. The board supports the recommendations of the Davies Report and believes in the value and importance of diversity in the boardroom but it does not consider it is appropriate or in the interest of the Company and its shareholders to set prescriptive targets for gender or nationality on the board. The Company has no employees and therefore has no disclosures to make in this regard. Investment Manager's Report - Investment Highlights The Investment Manager during the period was Starwood European Finance Partners Limited, a company incorporated in Guernsey with registered number 55819 and regulated by the GFSC. The Investment Manager has been appointed pursuant to the Investment Management Agreement, which is summarised in note 4 of the financial statements. The Investment Manager has appointed Starwood Capital Europe Advisers, LLP ("the Investment Adviser"), an English limited liability partnership authorised and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authority, to provide investment advice, pursuant to an Investment Advisory Agreement which is summarised in note 4 of the financial statements. The Investment Manager and Investment Adviser are both part of the Starwood Capital Group, a leading global real estate investment group. Portfolio Statistics The board considers that the Group is engaged in a single segment of business, being the provision of a diversified portfolio of real estate backed loans. The analysis presented in this report is presented to demonstrate the level of diversification achieved within that single segment. The board does not believe that its investments constitute separate operating segments.
]]></text></news-item>