<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-H9J1-F11P-X3B8"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>'Amigos' Concourt challenge fails</title><source>Daily News (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA["AMIGOS" corruption trial accused Gaston Savoi and two co-accused have lost their Constitutional Court challenge and will have to face the music at trial for their alleged crimes.
Savoi, his company, Intaka Holdings, and co-accused Fernando Praderi launched a Constitutional Court appeal, challenging the constitutionality of sections of the Prevention of Organised Crime Act, in particular the "racketeering" laws under which they are charged.
Savoi, the main accused in the R144-million "Amigos" trial, claimed the racketeering laws were open to "personal and political manipulation" - and cited as evidence the withdrawal of charges against his former co-accused, ANC politicians Mike Mabuyakhulu and Peggy Nkonyeni.
Savoi and 12 others will be tried on racketeering, corruption and fraud charges relating to the supply of water purification and oxygen plants to the KwaZulu-Natal departments of local government and health.
Savoi contended that, having been charged under the act, his rights were being threatened because he would be forced to face a trial based on charges which would not survive constitutional scrutiny.
He submitted that, in terms of the act, the concepts of "pattern of racketeering activity" and "enterprise" were vague, and therefore unconstitutional.
Savoi and his co-accused |appealed to the Constitutional Court against a Pietermaritzburg High Court judgment by Judge Isaac Madondo, who dismissed all of the applicants' arguments, but found that the impugned paragraphs were |unconstitutional to the extent that they contained the words "ought reasonably to have known".
Yesterday, the Constitutional Court declined to confirm the declaration of invalidity handed down by Judge Madondo, in terms of which certain paragraphs of section 2(1) of the act were declared unconstitutional.
The Constitutional Court found that the definition of "pattern of racketeering activity" was quite clear, and thus not void for vagueness.
The court also found that a trial was not rendered automatically unfair purely because of the admission of evidence that is ordinarily inadmissible.
Whether or not the admission of otherwise inadmissible evidence will render a trial unfair is a matter best left to be determined by the trial court based on the material before it. Thus, the act did not limit the right to a fair trial.
Daily News © 1999 - 2014 Independent Newspapers (Pty) Limited. All rights strictly reserved.
]]></text></news-item>