<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-MNM1-JBTY-T0RR"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>2nd LD UN Security Council slams terrorist attack in Afghan capital</title><source>Xinhua General News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The UN Security Council on Friday strongly condemned a deadly terrorist attack on a hotel in Kabul, capital of Afghanistan, which left at least 20 people dead.
"The members of the Security Council condemned in the strongest terms the terrorist attack on 20 March 2014 at a hotel in Kabul, Afghanistan, which caused a number of deaths and injuries to Afghan civilians, including children, and international personnel, responsibility for which has been claimed by the Taliban," said a statement issued to the press here by the 15-nation UN body.
"The members of the Security Council reaffirmed that terrorism in all its forms and manifestations is criminal and unjustifiable, regardless of its motivation, wherever, whenever and by whomsoever committed, and should not be associated with any religion, nationality, civilization or ethnic group," the statement said.
Insurgents attacked the hotel on Thursday night, taking many hostages. Kabul's police chief said 15 civilians, including hotel guests, died. All five insurgents were killed.
The Taliban claimed responsibility for the attack, saying the hotel was used by wealthy Afghans and foreigners for "wild parties. "
"The members of the Security Council reiterated their serious concern at the threats posed by the Taliban, Al-Qaida and illegal armed groups to the local population, national security forces, and international military and international assistance efforts in Afghanistan, particularly in light of recent terrorist attacks elsewhere in the country," said the statement.
The members of the Security Council expressed their deep sympathy and condolences to the families of the victims, and to the people and Government of Afghanistan, as well as to those other countries whose nationals have been victims of this attack, and wished the injured a speedy recovery, said the statement.
Council members reiterated their steadfast support for the role of the United Nations and UN-affiliated organizations in Afghanistan, and underlined the need to bring perpetrators, organizers, financiers and sponsors of these reprehensible acts of terrorism to justice.
They also urged all states, in accordance with their obligations under international law and relevant Security Council resolutions, to cooperate actively with the Afghan authorities in this regard.
The Council reaffirmed the need and reiterated their determination to combat by all means, threats to international peace and security caused by terrorist acts.
"No terrorist act can reverse the path towards Afghan-led peace, democracy and stability in Afghanistan, which is supported by the people and the Government of Afghanistan and the international community," it added.
]]></text></news-item>