<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-H9J1-F11P-X2P4"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Rhoads defends workers' comp bill</title><source>Legal Monitor Worldwide</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[March 21--State Sen. Jerry Rhoads, a Democrat from Madisonville who represents residents in Muhlenberg, Ohio, Butler and Hopkins counties, said Senate Bill 137 would correct two major provisions in the current workers' compensation insurance law. Rhoads said comments from the Greater Owensboro Chamber of Commerce and others he has read in recent stories are misrepresenting the legislation.
"I read the Owensboro chamber spokesman's comment in the paper that the law isn't a benefit to its members," Rhoads said. "This law was enacted for employees, not employers. It's workers' comp, not employers' comp. But the trade-off is that workers' compensation shields the business from personal liability." The state chamber of commerce as well as the Owensboro chamber argue that SB 137 would add costs to all businesses by driving up workers' compensation premiums. State chamber officials have said the changes are being proposed "in order to appeal to the narrow special interests of lawyers who profit from our workers' compensation system." Senator Joe Bowen, an Owensboro Republican, said Monday that he opposes SB 137 because he sees it as another hardship on businesses. He, too, believes it was introduced by attorneys who stand to benefit. Rhoads, an attorney, said that is an unfair characterization of SB 137. The changes are overdue in large part because the current law is not fair to older workers, he said. Kentucky, like other states, had more workers who have either had to remain on the job longer or re-enter the work force because of the economy. SB 137 would correct discrimination in the current law that affects older workers by extending the eligibility age for workers' compensation coverage to 70 years or five years after the injury, Rhoads said. Under the current law, workers' comp insurance benefits are terminated when employees reach Social Security retirement age or two years from the date of last treatment. What this means, Rhoads said, is that if a 26-year-old worker is injured on the job today, he or she would probably draw benefits for 40 years, but if a 66-year-old is injured, he or she could only receive benefits for two years -- "even though that leg doesn't grow back or that person still can't see any more." And the person can't return to work. With older persons filling vital work force roles, the law needs to be changed, he said. The statements that have been made about the cost of the proposed changes to employers have been exaggerated, Rhoads said. The increased costs would be 1.1 to 1.4 percent of overall costs, according to the National Council on Compensation Insurance -- with costs spread across every employer in the state.
Rhoads said he has practiced workers' compensation law for more than 40 years. The proposed fee changes also are overdue, he said. Attorneys' fees, paid out of injured workers' case settlements, were reduced from $15,000 to $12,000 in 1996, he said. "I have no problem with statutory regulation of attorneys' fees; I just think it should be more fair," Rhoads said. "I can't think of another compensation that has been frozen for 18 years. It's unfair for attorneys' fees to be frozen for 18 years without an adjustment." The legislation would double the maximum attorney fees in original and reopened workers' compensation claims, from $12,000 to $24,000. Persons who are injured in 2014 draw more than they would have if they were hurt in 1996 since the compensation benefits are based on the state average weekly wage, he said. And there has been an annual adjustment in the death benefit. "We've had adjustments in benefits, but no adjustments in attorneys' fees," he said. "The idea that an increase in fees would increase claims is just not true. An attorney can't afford to take a case unless there is a significant impairment. If the case is severe enough, attorneys will take it any way." SB 137 did not get a hearing in the Senate Banking and Insurance Committee, and it was reassigned March 17 back to the Appropriations and Revenue Committee. Nearly all Kentucky employers are subject to the Workers' Compensation Act and are required to carry workers' compensation insurance or become self-insured, even if they have only one part-time employee, according to information from the Department of Worker's Claims in the Kentucky Labor Cabinet. There is an exemption for employers engaged exclusively in agriculture. Employees are entitled to certain benefits if they are injured on the job or get diseases from workplace exposure. Employees receiving these benefits give up their right to sue employers in civil court for damages from workplace injuries or illnesses. 
]]></text></news-item>