<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-8141-JC92-P1XR"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>China in a Catch-22 over LNG bunkering</title><source>Russia &amp; CIS Energy Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[China's ambition to fuel more ships on its rivers with LNG is caught in a Catch-22 - shipowners are refusing to use the fuel because of inadequate bunkering infrastructure, while a lack of end-users has discouraged the construction of bunker terminals, industry insiders have told Interfax.
"It will be impossible to make any real progress in using LNG in ships throughout the country by the end of 2015," a deputy general manager of a state-owned shipyard in Wuhan told Interfax.
"This is a new area, and so it's very difficult. There are applicable standards for LNG transfers internationally, but in an inland waterway... there are different hazards, especially when you're in close proximity to other neighbours and ships," said Michael Jones, business development director at Fortune Oil, which is involved in LNG bunkering.
Independent and state-backed LNG suppliers in China have targeted the transport sector as a potential market. To encourage shipowners to modify their existing diesel-powered fleets to also run LNG, the government and companies have touted potential fuel savings - up to 20% per year against diesel.
To spur greater LNG use in transport, Beijing singled out road vehicles and ships as 'preferred' users of gas in a policy issued in October 2012.
The Ministry of Transport has also issued several regulations and a set of guidelines over the past three years to promote the use of LNG in marine transport, while companies and local officials have made plans to build LNG-powered ships and bunkering infrastructure to service fleets.
Tepid growth
But growth in the use of LNG ships and development of bunkering infrastructure has fallen short of initial projections.
Experts at an industry event in the port of Ningbo in November 2012 had expected 1,610 ships to be using LNG by 2015, consuming 1.6-2 billion cubic metres of gas annually.
But just 14 diesel-fuelled vessels plying inland waterways have been modified to also run on LNG since August 2010, when the first ship started trials along the busy Beijing-Hangzhou Grand Canal. Only 10 have been approved by the transport ministry's Maritime Safety Administration to conduct trial operations.
The main problem is the dearth of small-scale LNG carriers to serve inland bunkering terminals, according to the shipyard manager.
China has no river-going LNG carriers, with shipbuilders so far shunning such technically advanced vessels because of the construction time and cost involved.
The lack of carriers has slowed construction of bunkering infrastructure, which in turn has discouraged shipowners from converting their fleets to use LNG. That leads to shipbuilders ignoring the small LNG carrier business. "It is a chicken-and-egg problem," said the manager.
"The government needs to address this," said Lin Boqiang, director of the China Centre for Energy Economics Research at Xiamen University.
"Tackling pollution and protecting the environment requires directives and incentives from the government. What companies care about the most is the economics," Lin told Interfax.
Retrofitting a ship to run on LNG costs around RMB 1 million ($160,000), while a bunkering terminal can cost RMB 30-40 million to build, said the manager. But a small LNG carrier can cost between RMB 70-80 million.
"We are companies and profit is critical for us. [LNG] use in the shipping sector is risky and what will happen ahead is unclear. We do not dare enter the sector without incentives from the government. Therefore, we'd like to watch and see," the manager said.
Industry caution
Shipowners are similarly cautious. A survey of the group by the China Waterborne Transport Research Institute found that more than half of respondents would continue to run their fleets on diesel if there was no financial support from the government for retrofitting ships.
Just 14% said they would install diesel-LNG dual-fuel engines whether or not state subsidies were available.
Vessel owners expecting state assistance are likely to be disappointed, as Beijing is more focused on curbing urban air pollution than marine emissions, according to Lin. "The government would rather give money to [encourage] road vehicle use of LNG or the use of wind and solar energies," said Lin.
China has looked abroad for guidance in developing its policy framework for LNG ships, an approach that some insiders have questioned.
"In the United States, there'd be more quantitative risk analysis (QRA) and understanding of the potential consequences of an incident or a scenario, whereas the Chinese model is to be more 'belt and braces' - the attitude is 'there's a safe distance, [so] let's double or treble it'," said Jones.
"They've been over-cautious [compared with] what I would have expected from experience in the US and European approach, where you'd get somebody to come in and do a QRA, understand the potential hazards and use that to set the level of risk," Jones added.
The circumspect approach was reflected in technology standards for pilot LNG ships released by the transport ministry in May 2012, which stated such vessels could be no more than 20 metres in length.
Although the ministry exempted ferries and oil and chemical tankers from the standards, the strict criteria still meant a large swathe of China's inland river fleet could not run on LNG.
Companies remain interested in the LNG bunkering market, and some of those making progress are from overseas.
Fortune Oil, for example, is helping China Changjiang National Shipping Group - one of the country's largest shipping firms - convert some of its ships to use both LNG and diesel.
Buoyant prospects
The two companies previously teamed up to retrofit a diesel-powered cargo ship to run on LNG using Fortune Oil's proprietary dual-fuel engine technology.
The Changxun 3 Hao was the first dual-fuel vessel on the Yangtze River, receiving certification from the transport ministry in October 2012 and beginning commercial operations two months later.
To serve the ship and other LNG vessels, Fortune Oil plans to build three refuelling stations along the Yangtze River, with the first under construction downstream of Chongqing.
It will source LNG from local liquefaction plants and is expected to start up in the third quarter, said Jones.
The other two stations, south of the Three Gorges Dam and in Nanjing, are in the planning and design phases.
China's first floating bunker station only started commercial operations at the end of September after passing government checks.
Located in Nanjing, it is jointly owned by local gas distributor Nanjing Towngas and Jiangsu Overseas Group, a government investment vehicle.
More recently, Rolls-Royce announced on Wednesday it would provide China National Offshore Oil Corp. with LNG-powered engines for two tugs by the end of this year.
cs tt aa
]]></text></news-item>