<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-TPV1-DY9P-N0KF"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Fraudster is jailed for 'callous and greedy' con</title><source>The Journal (Newcastle, UK)</source><author>Rob Kennedy</author><text><![CDATA[ABUSINESSMAN who fleeced investors out of £3m then spent the proceeds on the high life is today starting a six-year prison sentence.
David Reid ripped off more than 50 trusting people in the elaborate fraud, most of them elderly or seriously ill.
Victims lost their homes, pensions and savings as Reid tricked them into thinking they were securing their futures.
As the 50-year-old, who was close friends with some of those he ripped off, was jailed at Newcastle Crown Court, he was branded "greedy, callous and coldhearted". Many the investors were their Reid spent his ill-gotten gains on a boat, an Audi A8 luxury car, a Range Rover, a Mercedes, splashed out £14,000 on restaurants, hotels and clothing, £11,000 on skiing holidays, £6,000 on shooting and £1,000 on dog bills.
mature years ill The court heard he falsely passed himself off as a solicitor and even claimed to have competed in the Olympics in shooting.
Jailing him, Judge James Goss QC said: "The victims were cruelly deceived by your false veneer of professionalism and reassurances.
"There were devastating consequences for them and their families."
Reid, of St John's Mews, in Burnhope, County Durham, pleaded guilty to 22 counts of obtaining a money transfer by deception between 2001 and 2013 and one charge of participating in a fraudulent business.
The court heard police had passed a file on him to the CPS in 2003 but a decision was made not to take any action against him. That allowed him to continue defrauding people for another 10 years.
Prosecutor David Dixon told the court: "He was a plausible conman for more than 10 years, he set up a carefully-crafted, professionally-operated fraud."
Mr Dixon said Reid put the money people invested into a pot but by 2011 the money began to run out.
The barrister said: "Many of the investors were in their more mature years or in ill health.
"He knew he was taking funds from people who lacked capacity of or were in grave ill health and we say that was particularly cold-hearted, he was callous.
more "He would regularly take people's pension funds and say he had invested them but in reality it went in a pot and to whoever needed it, including himself.
"We say this is a clear case of greed."
or in " The court heard Reid would reassure the investors, lying that he was a solicitor and boasting he was an Olympian.
Mr Dixon said: "He said he was a solicitor and also said he was an Olympic competitor in the sport of shooting."
The son of one of his victims has special needs, which Reid knew, yet he still fleeced her, meaning she had to cancel a trip to Disneyland for the boy and has been left unable to support herself or her disabled son.
And a close friend of Reid lost his £300,000 inheritance after his wife died from cancer, money which was meant to secure the future of his child, who has Downs Syndrome.
Jamie Adams, defending, said Reid had tried to kill himself twice and was sorry.
Many of the investors were in their more mature years or in ill health
]]></text></news-item>