<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-2V51-JCDM-J4HM"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Sheriff: Domestic abuse is 'an everywhere problem'</title><source>Telegraph Herald (Dubuque, IA)</source><author>alicia yager TH staff writer alicia.yager@wcinet.com</author><text><![CDATA[domestic violence help * The Dubuque Community YMCA/YWCA runs the New Beginnings emergency shelter for domestic assault victims. CEO Sharon Covey said the shelter gives preference to Dubuque County residents and is supported mostly through community donations. Hotlines are 563-556-1100 or 800-332-5899, website dubuquey.org/programs/domestic-violence-shelter * Waypoint services is a state-funded organization that provides crisis counseling and support services to domestic assault victims in Dubuque and Delaware counties. Hotlines are 800-208-0388 or 319-363-2093, website waypointservices.org * Family Advocates Inc. offers domestic abuse victim services in the Grant County, Wis., area, including an emergency shelter and support services. Hotlines are 608-348-3838 or 800-924-2624, website familyadv.org * The Riverview Center serves Jo Daviess County, Ill., residents with an emergency shelter and support services. Hotlines are 815-777-3680 or 815-244-1320, website riverviewcenter.org
About one call per day for the Dubuque Police Department is related to a domestic assault report.
Over the past five years, reports of domestic assault in the city have ranged between 347 and 403 annually, according to statistics from Dubuque police. Lt. Mike Schmit added that many of those calls include the same people multiple times.
He added that it's safe to assume domestic assaults are underreported to the department.
"It's probably safe to double that number to show a real minimum," Schmit said.
But domestic assault isn't just a problem for Dubuque. Other area law enforcement agencies see similar patterns in their domestic assault cases. Galena, Ill., police, Platteville, Wis., police and the Dubuque County Sheriff's departments have fewer calls because of the smaller populations they serve, but the departments still take each case seriously.
"It's an everywhere problem," Dubuque County Sheriff Don Vrotsos said.
The way law enforcement in each of the three states handle domestic assault calls has evolved into a stricter approach. Schmit and Platteville police Chief Doug McKinley recalled that years ago, police responding to a domestic call would separate the people involved for a 12-hour "cooling off" period. Usually, no one was arrested.
Schmit said due in large part to lawsuits filed against law enforcement agencies, an Iowa law change in 1986 made it mandatory for police to arrest the primary physical aggressor in an assault with injury. If there are no injuries, arrests can be made at the discretion of an officer. Wisconsin and Illinois have similar mandatory arrest policies.
"If there are (injury) marks, somebody is getting arrested," said Galena Police Chief Lori Huntington.
Huntington and McKinley said their domestic assault incidents can go up and down from year to year. Huntington said domestic assault calls can be one of the most unpredictable situations for officers - there might be a fight in progress or a danger for officers, or the people involved might deny that anything happening.
Officers will give victims information on support services and help lines after any domestic assault call. One thing all departments see frequently is that victims will refuse to cooperate or change their mind about pressing charges.
"You'll see that a lot of times where they'll change their mind," Vrotsos said.
Schmit said when Dubuque officers respond to a call, they will use a quiet approach to hear and see any evidence of a tense or violent situation, because those involved in the incident might deny what happened. Officers also pay attention to signs of a struggle or injuries, and they will separate the two for questioning.
Schmit said it's common for victims of domestic abuse to deny abuse or change their minds because they are afraid of upsetting their significant other and making the situation worse. He added victims can also be afraid of losing financial support for themselves or their families because victims are usually dependent on their abusers. Most victims of domestic abuse are women, but men also are abused.
Schmit said it's common for victims to blame themselves and try to justify the abusive behavior."No one deserves to get hit," he said.
Anyone arrested for domestic abuse will be ordered not to have contact with the victim for a certain amount of time, or victims can take out their own no-contact order through civil court.
However, the departments will see a number of abusers violate those orders, or the victims themselves will invite the abuser over despite the order. Violating these orders will result in an arrest.
Schmit said although abusers can be apologetic after an incident and promise it won't happen again, domestic abuse is a cyclical behavior - it will keep happening.
]]></text></news-item>