<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-86S1-JBG1-82SY"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Research and Markets: Nanosatellite and Microsatellite (1kg to 10kg) Market Report 2014 - Worldwide Market Forecasts to 2019</title><source>Business Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Research and Markets ( http://www.researchandmarkets.com/research/l5mqxb/nanosatellite_and ) has announced the addition of the "Nanosatellite and Microsatellite (1kg to 10kg) Market Report 2014 - Worldwide Market Forecasts to 2019" report to their offering.
The Nano and Microsatellite market report constitutes of revenues from hardware, software and services required for the development and launch of such satellites. Overall market size is found by adding up the market size for two segments of satellites; namely 1kg to 10kgs (Nano satellites) and 11kgs to 100kgs (Microsatellites).
Though above two markets can exist independently, but the playing fields are the same. For example, there are applications in communication, earth observation, remote sensing, biological experiments, scientific research, academic training, space science and intelligence among various others. Among all applications of Nano and microsatellites, earth observations and remote sensing is expected to account for highest market share by 2019.
High growth markets include:
1. Software and data processing: Software packages as well as data processing suites that are required for accepting and extracting actionable information from the raw satellite data at the ground station
2. Nano satellites: Satellites in the range of 1kg to 10kgs
3. Earth observation and remote sensing: Disaster monitoring application such as cyclones, storms, floods, fires, volcanic activities, earthquakes, landslides, oil slicks, environmental pollution, industrial and/or power plant disaster among various others
4. Commercial: Nano and Microsatellites built and used for commercial purposes
Scope of the Report
Solutions
- Hardware
- Software and data processing
- Services
- Launch services
Mass
- 1kg-10kg
- 11kg-100kg
Applications
- Communication
- Earth observation and remote sensing
- Scientific research
- Biological experiments
- Technology demonstration and verification
- Academic training
- Reconnaissance
Verticals
- Defense and intelligence
- Government
- Commercial
- Civil
Companies Mentioned
- Clyde Space
- Geooptics
- Gomspace
- Lockheed Martin
- Northrop Grumman
- Planet Labs
- Raytheon
- Ruag
- Sierra Nevada Corporation
- Surrey Satellite Technologies Limited
For more information visit http://www.researchandmarkets.com/research/l5mqxb/nanosatellite_and
http://www.businesswire.com
]]></text></news-item>