<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-MMH1-JC65-5376"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>10 Things to Know: This Week's Takeaways</title><source>The Associated Press</source><author>The Associated Press</author><text><![CDATA[Looking back at the stories to remember from the past week:
1. PRESIDENT VLADIMIR PUTIN COMPLETES ANNEXATION OF CRIMEA INTO RUSSIA
He signed the legislation Friday that reclaimed the region from Ukraine despite sanctions imposed on the Russian leader's inner circle by the West. EU leaders also sought to pull the rest of cash-strapped Ukraine westward by signing a political association agreement with Kiev's prime minister. Besieged Ukrainian troops on the Crimean Peninsula faced a choice: leave, join the Russian military or demobilize.
2. MYSTERY OF MISSING MALAYSIA AIRLINES JET NOW TWO WEEKS OLD
The overall search for the lost Boeing 777 with 239 people aboard stretches from Kazakhstan in Central Asia to the southern Indian Ocean. Two days of searching in the ocean off the west coast of Australia - prompted by a reading of satellite imagery from earlier this week - has turned up nothing.
3. U.S. ARMY GENERAL SPARED PRISON IN SEXUAL MISCONDUCT CASE
Brig. Gen. Jeffrey A. Sinclair was originally brought up on sexual assault charges punishable by life in prison. But prosecutors dropped those charges in a deal in which he pleaded guilty to committing adultery with one woman and conducting inappropriate relationships with two others. Sinclair was reprimanded and fined $20,000 Thursday.
4. TALIBAN KILL 9 IN LUXURY HOTEL IN AFGHANISTAN'S CAPITAL OF KABUL
Among the dead from Thursday night's attack was a journalist from Agence France-Presse, his wife and two children who were shot in the head. The assault by four gunmen was a major embarrassment to government security forces less than two weeks before national elections and came on the heels of a rise in bombings and shootings targeting foreigners in the capital.
5. AT FIRST NEWS CONFERENCE, NEW FED CHIEF'S CANDOR CAUSES STOCKS TO FALL
Speaking Wednesday of when the Fed might raise short-term interest rates from their record lows, Janet Yellen was surprisingly specific - "around six months" - and the remark appeared to muddy her overarching message that rates are bound by no single economic indicator or time frame.
6. CHECHEN WARLOARD DOKU UMAROV REPORTED DEAD
The 49-year-old Islamic militant had claimed responsibility for some of Russia's deadliest terrorist attacks and had threatened to strike the Sochi Olympics. Umarov's death has been claimed before, but Tuesday's was the first report from the organization he headed, Kavkaz Center.
7. 'CHICKEN FROM HELL' DINOSAUR GETS A MORE SCIENTIFIC NAME
The bird-like creature that was 7 feet tall and weighed about 500 pounds was given a new name Wednesday: Anzu wyliei, which comes from a mythological feathered demon, plus the name of the grandson of a trustee of the Carnegie Museum of Natural history, where a replica of its skeleton has been displayed for nearly a decade.
8. ANTI-GAY PASTOR FRED PHELPS SR. DIES AT 84
The fiery founder of a small Kansas church led outrageous and hate-filled protests that blamed almost everything, including the deaths of AIDS victims and U.S. soldiers, on America's tolerance for gay people. Phelps, who died Wednesday, and his Westboro Baptist Church tested the boundaries of free speech, violating accepted societal standards for decency in an unapologetic assault on gays and lesbians.
9. MICK JAGGER REMEMBERS HIS LATE COMPANION, DESIGNER L'WREN SCOTT
In a poignant tribute, Jagger called Scott his "lover and best friend" and said he was struggling to understand why she might have taken her own life. The Rolling Stones canceled their tour of Australia and New Zealand after she was found dead Monday in her New York apartment.
10. EARLY EXIT: DUKE BOUNCED OUT OF NCAA BASKETBALL TOURNAMENT
Even though coach Mike Krzyzewski has won more NCAA tournament games than anyone in the history of men's basketball, his Blue Devils were knocked out by 14th-seeded Mercer. Other big early upsets included 11th-seeded Dayton beating sixth-seeded Ohio State, No. 12 Harvard knocking off fifth-seeded Cincinnati and No. 12 seed North Dakota outlasted fifth-seeded Oklahoma.
]]></text></news-item>