<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-1281-F197-501N"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Dofasco's coke ovens getting an $87m overhaul</title><source>The Hamilton Spectator (Ontario, Canada)</source><author>sarnold@thespec.com</author><text><![CDATA[ArcelorMittal Dofasco workers are getting the highest bonuses they've seen in a decade and neighbours are getting some welcome relief with an $87-million upgrade to the steelmaker's coke ovens.
The good news follows Friday's release of the parent company's 2013 financial results.
The coke oven upgrade, to be carried out over next five years, will be a major help in the struggle to solve polluting emissions from the steelmaker.
"This is part of our continual investment effort," said company spokesperson Tony Valeri. "It will improve the efficiency of our production and improve our environmental performance as well."
Valeri said the project will involve repairs and improvements to the flues and linings of the company's No. 2 and 3 batteries, helping to sharply reduce sooty emissions that have angered neighbours and landed the company in court on 13 environmental charges.
The steelmaker was charged last March with repeatedly spewing black smoke into the air, exceeding pollution standards more than 200 times. The next court appearance on those charges is set for March 27.
While the investment won't result in new jobs, Valeri said it adds to the security of the company's 5,200 current employees.
The oldest of the coke batteries is to be shut down in March 2015. ArcelorMittal Dofasco has already spent $175 million since 2010 updating its coke operations, including monitoring systems, emissions cameras, and repairs and rebuilds to ovens.
Coke is produced by heating coal in a series of ovens until it becomes a carbon mass used in blast furnaces to make iron.
The hope for cleaner air in the east end was warmly welcomed by Councillor Sam Merulla and Pat Thiessen, a member of the ArcelorMittal Dofasco Community Liaison Committee.
The steel plant is in Merulla's ward and Thiessen lives within sight of the factory.
"I applaud this investment of nearly $100 million not only from the economic development viewpoint but from the social mitigation standpoint as well," Merulla said.
"This is going to lead to a renewed and positive relationship with ArcelorMittal Dofasco."
For Thiessen, the new investment continues a company effort that is helping to clear the air in her neighbourhood.
"We still get a certain amount of fallout but it's a lot better than what it was," she said.
"I would call this investment very good news."
Employees were also told Friday they'll be getting the largest payouts they've seen since 2004 under the company's profit-sharing and variable compensation plans - averaging almost $20,000 each.
In addition to the coke oven upgrades, employees were also told Friday two other major investments in the plant will be completed this year - the $153-million Number 6 galvanizing line and the $33-million temper mill.
Combined, that's an investment of $273 million.
The temper mill sets the mechanical properties, thickness and surface texture of steel.
The galvanizing line produces the high-strength grades of steel demanded by the auto industry and other customers.
Friday's announcements for Hamilton followed the release of fourth quarter and year-end financial results by ArcelorMittal SA in Europe.
While the company does not release site-specific financial information, the Flat Carbon Americas division, which includes the Hamilton plant, reported an operating profit of $1 billion US, up from $852 million in 2012. Production was up to 23.9 million tonnes compared to 22.3 million last year and average selling prices rose to $854 per tonne compared to $818.
Operating income per tonne also rose to $45 per tonne compared to $38 last year.
Overall, the company reported a net loss of $3.3 billion for the year, but chairperson Lakshmi Mittal expressed confidence for 2014.
"The measures we have implemented to strengthen the business continue to yield positive results. In 2013, we delivered an 11 per cent underlying increase in EBITDA (earnings before interest, taxes depreciation and amortization), positive free cash flow and ended the year with net debt at the lowest level since the creation of ArcelorMittal in 2006," he said in a news release.
He said EBITDA for 2014 is expected to improve to about $8 billion.
Valeri echoed that positive outlook, saying while there are still challenges for the company, such as Canadian manufacturers moving offshore, there's also a new sense of optimism in the air.
"We are certainly seeing stronger automotive performance in North America and we are benefiting from that," he said.
"I think people are a little more confident today."
]]></text></news-item>