<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-8151-JCBD-Y4VT"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>FROM THE FIRST EDITIONS</title><source>Press Association Mediapoint</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[THE MIRROR
MOMENT PLANT FLEW INTO DEAD SPACE
As Flight MH370 left Malaysian airspace, controllers in Kuala Lumpur were expecting a simple handover to their Vietnamese counterparts.
PREGNANT ELEPHANT KILLED BY POACHERS
Conservationists called on Kenya's leader to declare poaching a ``national disaster'' after a pregnant elephant became
NORTON: I WISH I HAD KIDS
TV favourite Graham Norton has revealed his regret that he never started a family.
Sport:
MOYES: MY SHAME AT UTD DECLINE
David Moyes last night revealed his shame at Manchester United's woeful season.
MY 1,000TH GAME IS THE BIGGEST OF SEASON
Arsene Wenger said his 1,000th match in charge of Arsenal today is ``the game of the season'' for his team.
INDEPENDENT:
CRIME AGENCY IN CRISIS AFTER OFFICERS ARE CHARGED
The National Crime Agency is embroiled in its first controversy after two of its officers were suspended and charged with data protection offences following an investigation into criminals in Essex, The Independent can disclose.
RESTORED AT LAST (TO ITS RIGHTFUL OWNERS) - £20m MASTERPIECE WITH A SECRET NAZI PAST...
A £20m Henri Matisse painting that was once part of Luftwaffe chief Hermann Goring's private collection of looted art is being handed back to the family of a renowned Jewish dealer whose vaults were plundered by the Nazis.
CAMBRIDGE'S 'RACIST' MAY BALL - THE SECOND COURSE
Cambridge University officials have vowed to address complaints of ``racism'' which were made after the chanting of a pro-slavery song at the launch of a college's May ball.
City:
PRESSURE MOUNTING OVER £16bn NUCLEAR SITE FOR HINKLEY POINT
The Government's divisive plans for a new £16bn civil nuclear plant at Hinkley Point in Somerset have been dealt a double blow by the United Nations and a powerful group of MPs.
THERE'S A LONG WAY TO GO ON THE DEFICIT, OSBORNE WARNED
The latest public borrowing figures showed the Government remains on course to reduce the deficit over this financial year, but analysts have also warned that they underline the scale of the fiscal challenge still facing George Osborne.
TELEGRAPH:
LAST 54 MINS OF FLIGHT MH370
The last 54 minutes of cockpit communication aboard the missing Malaysia Airlines flight MH370 can be disclosed today by The Daily Telegraph.
BREAST CANCER PATIENTS GIVEN 'NEEDLESS' SURGERY
Half of women having mastectomies for an early form of breast cancer endure unnecessary surgery, a study suggests.
TREASURY IS PREPARING A MANSION TAX FOR NEXT YEAR, SAYS DANNY ALEXANDER
Treasury officials have begun work on a mansion tax that could be levied as soon as next year, a Cabinet minister discloses today.
City:
GOVERNMENT KEEPS TO BORROWING TARGET DESPITE SETBACK
The Government is still on track to meet its revised borrowing target this year, despite a slight worsening in the public finances.
EU TARGETS RUSSIA OVER FUEL SUPPLY BLACKMAIL
European leaders have rushed through plans aimed at breaking the Kremlin's grip on gas and energy supplies, marking a fresh escalation in the new Cold War between Russia and the West.
DAILY STAR:
CORRIE'S 6 SEXY NEW BABES
Six sexy babes will arrive on the Coronation Street cobbles when gorgeous Michelle Keegan leaves the hit ITV soap.
£55M CHARITY DOSH AND BECKS
David Beckham set Sport Relief on its way to a whopping £55million last night after joining the cast of Only Fools And Horses for a telly special.
AL-QAIDA FANATICS MAY BE PLANNING NEW 9/11 OUTRAGE
Military bases and other targets were on alert last night as it was feared the missing plane may still be ``out there''.
Sport:
LET'S BE EPIC
David Moyes has called on Manchester United to produce an epic display to give them hope of dethroning Bayern Munich.
STOP PICKING ON ME - JOSE
Jose Mourinho has claimed he is being singled out for unfair treatment by the authorities - and has vowed to fight his latest FA charge.
DAILY EXPRESS
HOUSE PRICES TO SOAR AGAIN
House prices are set to soar by up to 30% as savers raid their pension pots to invest in property instead.
PASSENGERS ON MISSING JET 'COULD STILL BE FOUND ALIVE'
Passengers on the missing Malaysian jet could still be found alive in the ``most inaccessible spot on the face of the earth'', search teams said yesterday.
100 NOT OUT... WE'RE LIVING LONGER THAN EVER BEFORE
Britons are living longer than before with record numbers reaching 100, according to figures.
Sport:
I'VE FELT ASHAMED
David Moyes last night suffered the double blow of losing Robin van Persie for six weeks and a Champions League pairing with Bayern Munich - after admitting he has felt ashamed of some of Manchester United's performances this season.
SHERWOOD IS TOLD TO CALM DOWN
Tim Sherwood has been warned by several senior English managers to calm down for the sake of the reputation of all young coaches in the country.
FINANCIAL TIMES
SANCTIONS BATTER OLIGARCHS' STOCKS
President Vladimir Putin's ``inner circle'' was feeling the pain of US sanctions yesterday as foreign banks and investors scrambled to reassess their dealings in Russia and investments held by some of the country's wealthiest oligarchs tumbled.
WORKAHOLIC EX-BANKERS IMPOSE THEIR LONG-HOURS CULTURE ON NEW COLLEAGUES
Bankers' punishing hours are no longer merely of concern to the families of financiers - the fallout of their all-consuming office culture is spreading as they take their hard-driving ways to new workplaces.
CHINESE IN FIGHT FOR PLACES AT TOP SCHOOLS
Packed into a grey minibus, 22 Chinese parents are trundling down a bumpy driveway towards Cobham Hall, a girls boarding school set in 70 hectares of Kent countryside.
Companies & Markets:
LI SCRAPS WATSONS IPO AS TEMASEK BUYS 6BN US DOLLARS STAKE
Asian tycoon Li Ka-shing will sell a near 25 per cent stake in his AS Watson health and beauty chain to Singapore's Temasek for 5.7bn US dollars rather than pursue a planned dual listing in Hong Kong and London.
INSURERS GIVE REPRIEVE TO ANNUITY CUSTOMERS
Five of the UK's largest life insurers have put customers' annuity applications on hold, in response to the radical shake-up of pension rules announced in the Budget this week.
THE GUARDIAN
DOCTORS' DOUBTS OVER STATINS 'MAY BE PUTTING LIVES AT RISK'
Doctors who worry about the safety of cholesterol-reducing statins are creating a misleading level of uncertainty that could lead to the loss of lives, one of the UK's leading medical academics has warned.
GOVERNMENT GOT MATHS WRONG OVER TUITION FEES - ADVISER
A former political adviser to the Tory universities minister, David Willetts, has called for a rethink of the tuition fees system and admitted the government ``got its maths wrong'' by overestimating the amount of student debt that will be repaid.
MEDIA BIGWIGS QUEUE UP FOR PART IN HIT TV SPOOF
In the new BBC mockumentary W1A he is known as ``his Tonyship, the Lord Director General'' and is as elusive as the Scarlet Pimpernel.
City:
BIG SIX BRACED FOR INQUIRY INTO COMPETITION
The big six gas and electricity suppliers are steeling themselves for a full competition inquiry beginning next week, against a background of accusations that the companies have used their market dominance to ramp up prices and make excessive profits.
BLACKBERRY FACES NEW BLOW - FROM OBAMA
Barack Obama is considering ditching his BlackBerry for a rival mobile phone brand, in what would be a symbolic blow to the struggling Canadian handset maker.
THE i
DOCTORS TELL HUNT: YOU'RE DAMAGING THE NHS
Jeremy Hunt's ``failure'' to grant doctors a 1 per cent pay rise has left the profession with ``a deep sense of outrage'', the leader of the doctors' union has said - warning that refusing to invest more in the NHS has put the future of the health service itself at risk.
BRITAIN FIRST COUNTRY IN WORLD TO OFFER MENINGITIS B JAB TO ALL BABIES
Every baby in Britain could be protected against meningitis B by the end of the summer, according to the company behind a vaccine the Government has announced will be offered on the NHS.
TWO CRIME AGENCY OFFICERS FACE DATA CHARGES
The National Crime Agency is embroiled in its first controversy after two of its officers were suspended and charged with data protection offences following an investigation into criminals in Essex, i can disclose.
City:
£16BN HINKLEY PLANT AT RISK AS UN AND MPS REJECT PLANS
The Government's divisive plans for a new £16bn civil nuclear plant at Hinkley Point in Somerset have been dealt a double blow by the United Nations and a powerful group of MPs.
OSBORNE WARNED OF CHALLENGES OVER DEFICIT
The latest public borrowing figures showed the Government remains on course to reduce the deficit over this financial year, but analysts have also warned that they underline the scale of the fiscal challenge still facing George Osborne.
DAILY MAIL
THE DEATH KNELL FOR TV LICENCE
The abolition of the BBC licence fee came a step closer yesterday when Downing Street backed plans to decriminalise non-payment.
AFTER ALL THAT RAIN, IT'S NOW OFFICIALLY A DROUGHT!
After the wettest winter on record, it might seem hard to believe. But many of us have been living through a drought for the last fortnight, weather experts revealed last night.
THE MET CORRUPTION FILES
This week saw the shocking revelation that a 'lorry-load' of documents compiled during a secret investigation into corruption in Britain's biggest police force was shredded in 2003.
Sport:
FLOORED
Manchester United's hopes of rescuing their season with Champions League glory were dealt a hammer blow last night when Robin van Persie was ruled out of both legs of the quarter-final with Bayern Munich.
WENGER: JOSE IS NO FRIEND OF MINE
Arsene Wenger and Jose Mourinho finally found something to agree on last night: that they cannot be friends.
THE SUN
KELLY'S I DO
Kelly Brook is to marry ex-gladiator Tornado after a whirlwind romance.
TORNADO A FAST MOVE
Former Gladiators star Tornado popped the question to a ``dumbstruck'' Kelly Brook after an 11-week romance.
KYLIE TURN OVER
Kylie Minogue has quit The Voice - in a major blow to the BBC1 talent show.
Sport:
ASHAMED
David Moyes admits he felt ``ashamed'' to face Old Trafford fans this season.
AARGHVP
Manchester United have been dealt a devastating blow with news that Robin van Persie's season could be over.
THE TIMES
BLOCK TV SIGNAL FOR LICENCE-FEE DODGERS
Television viewers who fail to pay the licence fee face having their BBC channels blocked under plans being considered by ministers.
DOCTOR IS FIRST TO BE CHARGED OVER FEMALE MUTILATION
A doctor and another man are to be charged in Britain's first prosecutions for alleged female genital mutilation.
MANSION TAX 'WOULD DENT HOUSE PRICES AND PROVE SELF-DEFEATING'
A mansion tax would dent house prices and slash the income from other taxes by as much as £4 billion within a decade, industry experts have warned.
City:
COMPETITION RULING DOOMS EUROTUNNEL FERRY SERVICE
Cross-channel ferry competition could be cut by a third this summer with a ruling that is expected to conclude that when it comes to the number of operators sailing between Dover and Calais, three is a crowd.
OBAMA MAY HANG UP ON BLACKBERRY
Since his election in 2008, when he was hailed not only as ``the first black President'' but also ``the first BlackBerry President,'' Barack Obama has been the best ambassador the ailing Canadian brand could have wished for.
]]></text></news-item>