<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-8151-JBV1-X373"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>AFPTV Agenda</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[We plan to file the following videos on Saturday. Please check the daily advisories for any additions and amendments:
-- TOP WORLD NEWS --
+ UKRAINE
KIEV/SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: Rolling news coverage of events in Ukraine and Crimea. RAW. TBA
KIEV: German Foreign Minister Frank-Walter Steinmeier holds talks with Ukraine's interim president Oleksandr Turchynov. RAW. 1500 GMT
PEREVALNE, CRIMEA: As the flags go down one by one on Ukraine's fleet in Crimea, Russian forces are laying siege to the few ships left in a strongly pro-Russian community that is hostile to the new government in Kiev. PKG. 1700 GMT
CHISINAU, MOLDOVA: Moldova, another former Soviet state with a restive Russian-speaking minority, fears events in neighbouring Ukraine will provide a blueprint for its own separatists. RAW / STOCKSHOTS. 0400 GMT
-- OTHER WORLD NEWS --
+ ASIA-PACIFIC
CANBERRA/KUALA LUMPUR/BEIJING: Monitoring the search for the missing Malaysia Airlines jet. RAW. TBC
+ EUROPE
ANKARA: Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan attends a campaign rally for municipal elections on March 30. RAW. 2000 GMT
VIENNA: The Westlicht gallery hosts an auction for the only camera to return from the Apollo missions to the moon. RAW. 1900 GMT
GENEVA: Hackers' fair with seminars on 'ethical hacking' and competitions on who can hack specially created websites the fastest. RAW. 1800 GMT
LYON, FRANCE: Polling station prepares for first round of municipal elections on Sunday. RAW. 1400 GMT
WARSAW: To celebrate the canonisation of John Paul II on April 27, every day a Polish horse rider will travel 70 km from the Polish capital to Rome. RAW. 1600 GMT
VARIOUS, CYPRUS: The discovery of gas reserves off the coast of Cyprus is giving renewed impetus to peace talks between the divided island's north and south and some optimism that natural gas will provide relief for the island's crippled economy. PKG. 0500 GMT
+ MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
ALGIERS: Campaign begins for April 17 presidential election. TBC
+ NORTH AMERICA
WASHINGTON: Ahead of 25th anniversary of the Exxon Valdez oil spill in Alaska, we speak to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's oil spill response chief, who witnessed the disaster. RAW/FILE. 0500 GMT
LOS ANGELES: Premiere of Disney animated adventure "The Pirate Fairy". RAW. TBA
+ LATIN AMERICA & CARIBBEAN
SALTA, ARGENTINA: Trial of three men charged with the murder of two French tourists found dead in the Quebrada de San Lorenzo national park in July 2011 starts Tuesday. FILE. 0300 GMT (investigation)
+ AFRICA
BISSAU: Campaign kicks off for Guinea-Bissau's presidential and legislative elections on April 13. STOCKSHOTS
-- SPORT --
MADRID: Pre-match training and presser ahead of Sunday's El Clasico clash between Real Madrid and Barcelona. RAW. 1600 GMT
Euro football coverage available to subscribers only:
MANCHESTER, UK: Post-match reax after Manchester City host Fulham in the Premier League. RAW. 2100 GMT
NAPLES, ITALY: Pre-match training and presser ahead of Napoli's match against Fiorentina on Sunday. RAW. 1700 GMT
Contact:
London desk: +44 207 776 2768
Hong Kong desk: +852 2829 6216
Nicosia desk: +357 22 391 453
Washington desk: +1 202 414 0550
Montevideo desk: +598 2 900 5095 ext 257
For contact via email: afptv-en@afp.com
afptv
]]></text></news-item>