<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-K6D1-JB4F-Y0H6"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>CDS Announces April Webinars on FRCP and Self Collection During eDiscovery</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Web Sessions Discuss Proposed Amendments to the FRCP (April 2nd) and Custodial Self Collection During eDiscovery (April 8th)
NEW YORK, NY - Complete Discovery Source (CDS/CDS Legal), the leader in eDiscovery, announced open registration for two upcoming April 2014 webinars:
Webinar - The Proposed Amendments to the FRCP: Will They Mark an eDiscovery Sea Change?
Wednesday, April 2, 2014 - 2:00pm Eastern; Duration: 1 Hour Hosted by CDS and Carahsoft
In August, the Committee on Rules of Practice and Procedure of the Judicial Conference of the United States disseminated several proposed amendments to the Federal Rules of Bankruptcy and Civil Procedure for public comment. The proposals represent the most substantial set of changes to the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure related to discovery since the 2006 amendments, and could have far reaching impacts on the modern practice of law. A mountain of public commentary has been submitted, public hearings have been held, and, if approved, these amendments would become effective on December 1, 2015.
Join Matthew Knouff, eDiscovery Counsel for Complete Discovery Source, as he moderates a discussion with the Honorable Judge David Waxse, Retired U.S. Magistrate Judge from the District of Kansas, Monica McCarroll, Partner at Williams Mullen, and Steven Bennett, Partner at Park Jensen Bennett LLP, to discuss how these changes could affect the various corners of the legal industry: plaintiff, defense, in-house, and the public-sector.
The panel will discuss several aspects of the amendments:
The landscape that precipitated the changes.
The Amendment Debate: The concerns and advantages of the amendments
What do these amendments mean for you as a practitioner?
What are the practical implications?
What should you be doing to prepare in case the amendments are approved?
Do the proposed amendments go far enough to address discovery challenges presented by the Digital Age?
Reserve your Webinar seat now at:
http://cts.vresp.com/c/?CompleteDiscoverySou/af40cc2ce0/TEST/94274e38a0
Webinar - Custodial Self-Collection During Discovery-Defensible Process or Spoliation Guaranteed? Tuesday, April 8, 2014 - 11:00am Eastern, Duration 1 Hour Hosted by CDS
Join us for an exclusive webinar on Tuesday, April 8th at 11am EST. This session complements a recent March NYCLA article on the complications associated with self-collection.
Matt Knouff, General Counsel and eDiscovery Counsel for CDS, will continue the conversation with Mark Sidoti, Director of Gibbons P.C.'s Products Liability and Business & Commercial Litigation Departments and Chair of the firm's E-Discovery Task Force, and Kevin Treuberg, former Counterintelligence Special Agent and current Director of Forensic Services at Complete Discovery Source.
Learn more about the oft-misunderstood practice that is self-collection. The discussion will include actual tactics and strategies for self-collection, sanctions cases such as Green v. Blitz USA, and how to avoid common mistakes, the proper documentation to create and maintain during a self-collection process, and more.
Reserve your Webinar seat now at:
http://cts.vresp.com/c/?CompleteDiscoverySou/af40cc2ce0/TEST/8e6191f608
click http://cdslegal.com/2014/03/21/cds-announces-april-webinars-on-frcp-and-self-collection-during-ediscovery/
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
14 January 2014: Complete Discovery Source: Webcast - Natural Language Processing: Converting Raw Data into Actionable Knowledge through Analytics - Hosted by Carahsoft and CDS Federal Services
Jan. 23rd Web Session Discusses the Use of Analytics Tools to Extract Knowledge from Big Data for Government WASHINGTON, DC - The online webinar will last approximately one hour. Synopsis: Big Data has become an obstacle for government entities. Combine data volumes, velocity, and variety with the limited manpower available and it is virtually impossible to identify the information needed to support critical initiatives without automated analytical applications.
click http://cdslegal.com/2014/01/14/webcast-natural-language-processing-converting-raw-data-into-actionable-knowledge-through-analytics-hosted-by-carahsoft-and-cds-federal-services/
]]></text></news-item>