<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-VF91-DXY4-X1S9"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>E.P.A. Agrees to Join North Carolina in Reviewing Spill</title><source>The New York Times</source><author>By MICHAEL WINES</author><text><![CDATA[The federal Environmental Protection Agency will join North Carolina regulators in addressing potential violations of the Clean Water Act at Duke Energy power plants, including a massive spill of toxic coal ash last month in the Dan River, state officials said on Friday.
The secretary of the state's Department of Environment and Natural Resources, John Skvarla, invited the federal agency's ''participation and coordination'' in a March 14 letter to the head of its regional office, the state department said in a statement. The regional administrator, Heather McTeer Toney, accepted the offer on Monday.
The statement left unclear the nature of the cooperation between the two agencies, but said they would ''pursue a joint approach to enforceable resolution of violations'' by Duke, the nation's largest electric utility.
State regulators and Gov. Pat McCrory have come under sharp criticism from environmental activists and others over regulation of Duke, which maintains coal ash ponds at 14 active and decommissioned power plants. The state pressed Duke to stop leaks from some of the ponds last year only after environmental groups pledged to file a citizens' suit over the leaks under a provision of the Clean Water Act.
After the Dan River spill, which spread as many as 82,000 tons of toxic ash over 70 miles of river bottom, a federal grand jury opened an investigation into relations between the state environmental department and Duke.
Under Mr. McCrory, a Republican who took office last year, relations with the E.P.A. have sometimes been less than warm. The state last year turned down a $582,305 federal grant to study streams and wetlands and monitor the impact on water quality of using fracking to drill for natural gas.
In Friday's statement, Mr. McCrory said he was pleased by the E.P.A.'s decision to join the state, adding that it would ''bring additional resources to help us resolve a difficult problem that spans more than six decades.''
Separately, the state said it was abandoning a consent order, sharply criticized by environmental groups, that would have fined Duke $99,000 for pollution violations at coal ash ponds near Asheville and Charlotte without requiring cleanups at the sites.
In a statement, regulators said they acted after a county superior court judge invalidated an interpretation of state groundwater law that was relied on in crafting the order.
http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/22/us/epa-agrees-to-join-north-carolina-in-reviewing-spill.html
]]></text></news-item>