<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-PWY1-DXMP-K1C1"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Jena denies ore charge</title><source>The Telegraph (India)</source><author>OUR CORRESPONDENT</author><text><![CDATA[Bhubaneswar, March 21: The BJD's nominee for Balasore Lok Sabha constituency Rabindra Kumar Jena today reacted to the Congress's accusation of chromite ores loot by Balsore Alloys, where he had worked as a manager.
Jena said: "I left the organisation two-and-a-half years ago. I have no involvement in this. Srikant babu could have raised the issue earlier as he is the MP from Balasore. By raising the issue now, he is violating the spirit of the model code of conduct."
Yesterday, state Congress campaign committee chairman Srikant Jena said the loot of chromite ores worth Rs 20,000 crore came to light after a case had been registered by Jajpur's sub-divisional magistrate, a state government official, in the court of the first-class judicial magistrate on March 12. The case was filed on the directions of the Union ministry of environment and forests.
Citing the case, Srikant Jena had demanded a CBI inquiry. According to the accusations, the scam had taken place between 2000 and 2010. At that time, Rabindra Kumar was an employee of the company.
Sources said the district administration had filed cases against 13 mining companies, including the state-owned Odisha Mining Corporation, in the court of the first-class judicial magistrate at Jajpur Road for allegedly violating environmental and other mandatory laws. The court has admitted the petitions and posted them for hearing, an official said.
"The cases were filed after chromite was found to have been illegally extracted from 12 mines in Sukinda Chromites Valley in the district," said Maheswar Panigrahi, Jajpur sub-collector, who is also the sub-divisional magistrate.
The mining operators, who have been found to be operating without mandatory environmental clearances, include Balasore Alloys, Odisha Mining Corporation, Ferro Alloys Corporation Ltd, Idcol, Misrilal Mines Pvt. Ltd, B.C. Mohanty and Sons, Jindal Stainless Ltd and Indian Metals and Ferro Alloys, official sources said.
]]></text></news-item>