<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-TPT1-DY9P-N3R8"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Goat meat 'was passed off as lamb'; Food suppliers accused of mislabelling offences</title><source>Daily Post (North Wales)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TWO men have been charged over the alleged mislabelling of goat meat.
Dafydd Raw-Rees, the owner and Food Business Operator of Farmbox Meats Limited in Aberystwyth and Colin Patterson, the company representative, are alleged to have been involved in the mislabelling of goat meat products intended for sale.
The case relates to an investigation that dates back to early last year. Proceedings have also started against the company, Farmbox Meats Ltd.
The two men will appear before Westminster magistrates in London to answer the charges next month.
Dafydd Raw-Rees and Sue Patten, Head of Fraud at the Crown Prosecution Service, said yesterday that the charges followed an investigation involving a number of agencies. She said: "Following a joint investigation by the Food Standards Agency, Dyfed Powys Police and Ceredigion Council, criminal proceedings have been instituted against two individuals and a company in relation to the alleged mislabelling of goat meat products intended for sale. It is alleged that on or about February 12, 2013, Dafydd Raw-Rees, the owner and Food Business Operator of Farmbox Meats Limited in Aberystwyth and Colin Patterson, the company representative, mislabelled goat meat as either lamb or mutton for the purposes of sale."
The suspects are to be charged with 19 offences contrary to s.15 (1) of the Food Safety Act 1990 and one offence of failing to comply with traceability requirements of meat sold by the company, contrary to regulation 4 of the General Food Regulations 2004.
Ms Patten said that the decision to prosecute was taken in "accordance with the Code for Crown Prosecutors."
She added: "It has been determined that there is a realistic prospect of conviction and that a prosecution is in the public interest."
The case was heard administratively yesterday morning but none of the defendants attended court.
Farmbox factory (above) They will appear before Westminster Magistrates Court on Monday, April 14.
Regulations in to the food industry indicate that a product should have traceability from the field of the farm the animal grazed on, right through to when it arrives on the plate of the final consumer.
The traceability principles indicate that at each stage of the process the Food Business Operator should be able to provide details of its movement.
]]></text></news-item>