<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-8151-JCBD-Y4VN"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>MURPHY BLASTS 'HUMAN RIGHTS ABUSES'</title><source>Press Association Mediapoint</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Bill Shankly's maxim that football is more important than ``a matter of life and death'' has come true in Qatar where workers building the infrastructure for the 2022 World Cup ``suffer squalid conditions and excessive hours'', according to Labour's shadow international development secretary.
Jim Murphy will use his keynote speech to Scottish Labour Conference today to demand the Scottish Football Association speaks out on the ``human rights abuses'' behind the 2022 World Cup.
The call comes 10 days before the East Renfrewshire MP travels to Qatar to meet construction workers.
``Next week I will travel to Qatar to meet some of the construction workers from Nepal and India building the infrastructure for the 2022 World Cup,'' he is expected to say.
``The treatment of these workers is the ugly secret of the beautiful game.
``Some are tricked into travelling thousands of miles under false pretences. Too many have their passports confiscated, work without pay, suffer squalid conditions, work excessive hours, and deal with staggering levels of debt.
``These abuses aren't one-offs - Amnesty International, Human Rights Watch have all made clear that these problems are pretty widespread.
``Bill Shankly was wrong when he said, 'Some people believe football is a matter of life and death - I am very disappointed with that attitude. I can assure you it is much, much more important than that.'
``But in Qatar today, the 2022 World Cup is becoming a matter of life and death for far too many. Hundreds have died, thousands are in danger. People don't have to die to bring us this or any sporting event; not a single worker died building the sites for the London 2012 Olympics.
``It's now time for the SFA to break its silence on the 2022 World Cup - Scotland and England gave football to the world and the SFA have a responsibility as custodians of the game.
``The World Cup must not be built on the backs of the forced labour and lost lives of thousands of working people.''
Mr Miliband began his speech by paying tribute to former Labour leader John Smith, who died 20 years ago, hailing him as ``Labour's lost leader, Scotland's lost leader, Britain's lost leader''.
He highlighted Mr Smith's commitment to social justice, and urged his party to win September's independence referendum to ``be true to his legacy''.
Mr Miliband said: ``That flame of social justice still burns, let us be true to the legacy of John Smith and let us win the fight to keep Scotland as part of the United Kingdom.''
With the vote on Scotland's future taking place later this year, he went on: ``This is no ordinary conference and no ordinary times. In 180 days Scotland will vote to determine its future.
``I want to be very clear, this is Scotland's decision and Scotland's decision alone. But all of us in this room, all of us in the Labour Party know that we are better together.''
He said he believed ``passionately'' that the ``right choice for Scotland is to stay in the United Kingdom'', telling activists that his party must ``focus on tackling injustice and inequality wherever we find it''.
He argued that ``if there was a border across the UK, England and Scotland divided, that would mean a race to the bottom because companies would be saying if you put in place that policy, we will move our company across the border''.
Mr Miliband went on: ``That is why we need fair rules across the United Kingdom, that is why we are better together.''
He said the SNP had ``no plans for social justice'' and had to be ``dragged kicking and screaming'' to act on the so-called bedroom tax.
Mr Miliband also criticised the Nationalists for failing to match Labour's plans to freeze electricity prices.
``They have no answer, they can't match us,'' he said.
Instead he said Mr Salmond's first priority in an independent Scotland would be to cut corporation tax for businesses.
``Once again, its about the race to the bottom,'' the Labour leader claimed.
``The SNP vision of an independent Scotland is the race to the bottom, David Cameron and Alex Salmond at the starting blocks.''
But he insisted: ``You can't build social justice if that is your approach, you can't be a narrow Nationalist and stand up for social justice, that is what we are showing in this referendum campaign.
``People should not believe the SNP argument there is a Tory England and progressive Scotland.
``There are millions of people across the country who believe in our vision of equality, social justice, and fairness.''
With his speech coming just two days after George Osborne's Budget, Mr Miliband also hit out at the UK Government for doing ``nothing to tackle the cost-of-living crisis that so many families are facing''.
He said it was a ``Tory Budget that did nothing to ease the squeeze on family budgets of people across Scotland''.
He also blasted a Conservative advert highlighting changes to beer and bingo taxes in the Budget as ``patronising'' and ``out of touch''.
The online advert said the 1p cut in beer duty and the halving of bingo duty would help ``hardworking people do more of the things they enjoy''.
Mr Miliband said: ``Did you see that advert? Have you ever seen a more condescending, patronising, haughty, complacent, out of touch, misconceived piece of nonsense?''
He claimed that the Conservatives' ``mask slips'' when talking about the ``hardworking people of Britain'', adding: ``The Tories say 'they', we say 'us'.''
Yes Scotland chief executive Blair Jenkins said: ``We agree with Mr Miliband's desire to create a country that is fairer, socially just and more equal.
``But the reality is that the UK is one of the most unequal countries in the developed world. That's happened not by an act of God, but from deliberate policy decisions of successive Westminster governments over many decades of failure.
``Growing numbers of Labour supporters are realising that Westminster isn't working for Scotland and hasn't been for a very long time. That has not diminished their desire to build a better and fairer nation which is as strong today as it was when John Smith was Labour leader.
``But as a new poll has just shown, Labour supporters are joining Yes in ever increasing numbers because they realise that putting Scotland's future in Scotland's hands is the best way to create the kind of country they want.''
SNP Westminster leader Angus Robertson said: ``Over a quarter of Labour voters are already voting Yes in September, and former Scottish Labour chairman Bob Thomson is calling on all Labour supporters to vote Yes - Ed Miliband can't even persuade his own members and supporters on the referendum.
``Therefore, instead of attacking the SNP, Ed Miliband would do better trying to understand why Labour are still so far behind the SNP in the polls, and why growing numbers of Labour supporters are voting Yes.''
Mr Robertson added: ``SNP policies are entirely based on what is best for Scotland - growing economic activity and jobs in Scotland, and investing in vital provision such as transformed childcare. Successive Labour and Tory governments at Westminster have made the UK a more unequal society, and we need the powers of independence to make Scotland fairer and more prosperous.''
]]></text></news-item>