<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT3-N391-DXXY-30GM"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Business roundup: Credit Suisse settles FHFA suits; FTC weighs in on privacy case</title><source>The Washington Post</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[BANKINGCredit Suisse settles lawsuits by FHFA
Credit Suisse Group agreed to pay $885 million to resolve claims by a U.S. regulator that the Swiss bank misled Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac into buying mortgage-backed securities that later went sour.
The settlement announced Friday would resolve claims in two lawsuits filed in New York by the Federal Housing Finance Agency, the conservator since 2008 for the government-controlled mortgage companies.
It is the ninth settlement that the FHFA has reached in litigation that began in 2011, when it filed 18 lawsuits over some $200 billion in mortgage-backed securities, an investment product that was at the center of the global financial crisis.
The accord resolves claims against Credit Suisse over $16.6 billion of securities sold to Fannie and Freddie.
The FHFA has recovered more than $10.1 billion from banks over similar securities.
- Reuters
In a move that could weaken Facebook's argument in a California district court suit over teen privacy, the Federal Trade Commission says the social network is misinterpreting a key children's privacy law.
The FTC filed a brief Thursday night to weigh in on a key point in the case Batman v. Facebook, also known as Fraley v. Facebook . The agency said Facebook is wrong in contending that, because the Children's Online Privacy and Protection Act protects the privacy of only children under 12, the law could be interpreted to keep states from enforcing their own laws on teen privacy.
This was a main part of Facebook's argument against those who objected to a 2012 settlement over "Sponsored Stories," which featured users' "likes" and check-ins in advertisements. The users say the $10 million settlement does not require teens to get explicit permission from their parents before agreeing to show up in advertisements, in violation of state teen privacy laws in seven states, including Virginia.
The state of California on Friday also filed an amicus brief affirming its right to enforce its state privacy law.
- Hayley Tsukayama
l General Motors, facing lawsuits in the United States and Canada over faulty ignition switches, was served with what may be the first wrongful-death suit since the company recalled 1.6 million vehicles in February, in a case involving two fatalities in a 2006 car crash. The lawsuit was filed in Hennepin County District Court in Minneapolis. Bob Hilliard, one of the lawyers who filed the suit, said it accuses the automaker of negligence in designing and manufacturing the switch.
l North Carolina regulators said they have asked a judge to withdraw a proposed settlement that would have allowed Duke Energy to resolve environmental violations by paying a $99,000 fine with no requirement that the company clean up its pollution. The order had been reached before a Feb. 2 spill from a coal ash dump in Eden coated 70 miles of the Dan River in toxic sludge and brought to light a history of Duke being cited for leaky, unlined coal ash dumps that were polluting groundwater. State officials said they will now partner with the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency to pursue joint enforcement against Duke for Clean Water Act violations related to the Dan River dump.
l A federal judge in Manhattan gave final approval to JPMorgan Chase's $218 million settlement to resolve class-action litigation accusing the largest U.S. bank of playing a central role in the huge Ponzi scheme of former client Bernard Madoff. The settlement was part of a $2.24 billion global resolution of Madoff-related matters by JPMorgan, which was Madoff's main bank for more than 20 years.
- From news services
]]></text></news-item>