<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-3181-DY2T-623V"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Our lives, our livelihood: why workplace mental health matters; With adults spending more of their waking hours at work than anywhere else, workplaces need more capacity to support the mental health of their employees. Luckily, such resources exist</title><source>National Post (f/k/a The Financial Post) (Canada)</source><author>Steve Horvath, National Post</author><text><![CDATA[Imagine working in a highly productive environment in which you feel safe, respected, and valued; the work is challenging; the demands of the job are reasonable; you have work-life balance; and your employer supports your involvement in your work and interpersonal growth and development. This is what is known as a mentally healthy workplace.
What is mental health?
The World Health Organization defines mental health not merely as the absence of disease, but also as a feeling of well-being in which the individual realizes his or her own abilities, can cope with the normal stresses of life, can work productively and fruitfully, and is able to make a contribution to his or her community. In the workplace, the traditional view of health and safety now includes a comprehensive approach that incorporates the total well-being and mental health of employees, also referred to as psychological health and safety. Psychological health and safety refers to the safeguarding of employees' psychological health, promotes employees' psychological (mental) well-being, and actively works to prevent harm due to negligent, reckless or intentional acts.
The most common psychological health problems in the workplace are anxiety and depression. Poor mental health in the workplace has far reaching negative impacts: hurting the individual, reducing employer profits, and costing the Canadian economy billions of dollars in losses each year.
What impacts employee mental health?
There are several issues that can greatly affect employee mental health that organizations should consider in their efforts to create a mentally healthy workplace. The comprehensive workplace guide "Guarding Minds at Work" identified thirteen psychosocial risk factors. These risk factors are elements that can impact employees' psychological responses to work and work conditions, potentially causing psychological health problems. These problems ultimately affect the health of the organization, individual employees, and the financial bottom line. They also impact the way in which work is done (including interactions and relationships with managers, coworkers, and customers) and the context in which work occurs.
Included are issues that affect mental health such as stigma and discrimination, presenteeism, job burnout, violence, harassment, bullying, and substance abuse.
Employers are required by law to protect the mental and physical health of their employees. Many provincial occupational health and safety acts have been expanded to include harm to psychological well-being in the definition of harassment. In jurisdictions that do not have explicit legislation dealing with psychological health in the workplace, the general duty clause would apply.
What employers can do to support mental health
Just as every workplace is different - from the size, to the people doing the work, to the work itself, to the leaders running the organization - there is no one "right way" to create a mentally healthy workplace. However, to effectively incorporate mental health at your workplace, commitment must start at the top with the involvement of all levels of leadership in the workplace including the board of directors, management, and finance and human resources departments.
editorial@mediaplanet.comSteve Horvath
]]></text></news-item>