<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-K0D1-F11P-X167"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Ban on Twitter criticized around the world</title><source>Cihan News Agency (CNA)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ANKARA (CIHAN)- The European Commissioner for Digital Agenda Neelie Kroes tweeted that the move to block Twitter in Turkey is "groundless, pointless [and] cowardly," following the block Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan imposed late on Thursday. "Turkish people and [the] intl [international] community will see this as censorship. It is," said Kroes on her Twitter account. Access to Twitter was blocked in Turkey on Thursday night shortly after Prime Minister Erdogan vowed to "root it out" in a rally on Thursday, only 10 days before local elections.
The Turkish prime minister also said that he does not care how the international community will react and that he will show the world the power of the Turkish Republic. In an interview with CNBC on Friday, Kroes also said that blocking access to Twitter is "not acceptable" and she would do her utmost to make sure the people of Turkey had freedom of speech. She also described the move by Erdogan as "embarrassing." "It's cutting down freedom of speech -- a value we're so proud of in the free world. He's going in the wrong direction. What we have to do is put it in plain language that it's not acceptable," said Kroes. Ban casts doubt on Turkey's commitment to European values Commissioner for Enlargement and European Neighbourhood Policy Stefan Füle also issued a statement on Friday, saying that "the ban on the social platform Twitter.com in Turkey raises grave concerns and casts doubt on Turkey's stated commitment to European values and standards. Freedom of expression, a fundamental right in any democratic society, includes the right to receive and impart information and ideas without interference by public authority." The statement continued, "Citizens must be free to communicate and choose freely the means to do it. This obviously includes access to the internet. Open debate promotes transparency and accountability and ultimately reinforces democracy; such debate needs to be strengthened everywhere, including in Turkey." Member of European Parliament (MEP) Marietje Schaake tweeted on her account, mentioning Erdogan's own remarks right after former president of Egypt Hosni Mubarek cut all access to the Internet in Egypt in 2011, when the Turkish prime minister said "No government can survive against the will of its people." European Parliament (EP) President Martin Schulz said on Friday that Erdogan is waging a campaign against media that he cannot directly influence or control. Twitter's 8th anniversary, no reason to celebrate in Turkey
"Today is Twitter's eighth anniversary. Yet, in Turkey, where Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan has promised to 'eradicate Twitter,' there is no reason to celebrate," said Schulz. "I strongly condemn the ban on Twitter in Turkey, which follows from PM Erdogan's previous threats against other social media," the EP president said, adding that "this authoritarian drive is a direct attack against freedom of expression in the country." Schulz said that Erdogan should guarantee freedom of press and freedom of expression "not as a favour to the international community, but because this is a right of Turkish citizens and an achievement of all advanced democracies." US expressed concern over Twitter ban The US also expressed deep concern over the blocking of Twitter in Turkey. Statement by the Press Secretary on Blocking of Twitter in Turkey: The United States is deeply concerned that the Turkish government has blocked its citizens' access to basic communication tools. We oppose this restriction on the Turkish people's access to information, which undermines their ability to exercise freedoms of expression and association and runs contrary to the principles of open governance that are critical to democratic governance and the universal rights that the United States stands for around the world. We have conveyed our serious concern to the Turkish government, urge Turkish authorities to respect the freedom of the press by permitting the independent and unfettered operation of media of all kinds, and support the people of Turkey in their calls to restore full access to the blocked technologies. CoE examining legal bases The Council of Europe's (CoE) Director of Communications Daniel Holtgen wrote in a twitter message: "Twitter blanket ban in Turkey is contrary to ECHR [European Convention on Human Rights] freedom of expression. CoE examining legal basis." Ria Oomen-Ruijten, rapporteur on Turkey for the EP, strongly criticized Turkey for blocking access to Twitter and expressed great concern about the issue, condemning the recent ban by saying in a statement that "blocking social media is unacceptable in a functioning democracy and rule of law. I call on the Turkish government to address this issue without delay. Turkish citizens should be able to express their opinion both offline and online." The EP's rapporteur went on to say that "Turkey is backtracking instead of taking steps forward. Measures that limit freedom for the citizens and the press have no place in a modern society and democratic rule of law." The recent developments and lack of constructive dialogue between the EU and Turkey have weakened the basis of the accession negotiations. "I have asked the Turkish minister for European affairs for a full explanation," the rapporteur added.
The vice-chairman of the Liberal Group in the EP, German MEP Alexander Graf Lambsdorff, called for the suspension of accession talks following the Twitter ban. Lambsdorff, who is also his group's shadow rapporteur on Turkey, said that negotiation with Erdogan is no longer necessary. Speaking to Today's Zaman, Lambsdorff said: "I am asking for the suspension of the accession process. Media freedom is a core European value. If Prime Minister Erdogan fails to understand that, there is no point in negotiating with him anymore. The EU must continue to engage with Turkish civil society, helping it to defend basic civil liberties." Hannes Swoboda, leader of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the EP, commented on the issue in a press release issued on the group's website. "Mr. Erdogan has lost all sense of direction and balance. Banning a social media network with 10 million users in Turkey is nothing short of a blatant attack on freedom of speech." "Turkey, as a country in the process of accession talks to join the European Union, has a duty to respect fundamental human rights. Freedom of speech is a core right of people and Erdogan's authoritarian oppression of it will not succeed. Mr. Erdogan may not care what the international community thinks about him, but the international community cares about the rights of the Turkish people. I recommend he takes a look at article 26 of the Turkish Constitution; emergency anti-terror legislation does not justify curtailing the rights of ten million people," the statement continued. Hélène Flautre, co-chair of the EU-Turkey joint parliamentary committee, called the ban "an absurd attack on fundamental rights and freedoms in Turkey. ... This latest anti-democratic manoeuvre only compounds concerns about the new Internet law, which finds here its first application. There was already major concern about the crisis hitting the democratic institutions in Turkey, with revelations of alleged intervention in media and the judiciary by the government. We would strongly urge the EU to engage immediately with the Turkish authorities to prevent further democratic backsliding ahead of the forthcoming elections," she added. Strong reaction from EU heavyweights "What we are hearing from Turkey does not comply with what we in Germany understand as free communication," German Chancellor Angela Merkel's spokesperson Christiane Wirtz said. "It doesn't fit with our idea of freedom of expression to forbid or block any form of communication."
The British Foreign Office made a statement on Friday, saying "The UK urges the authorities in Turkey to reconsider any ban on access to social media. Freedom of speech and expression is a fundamental right for all." "We are concerned about reports suggesting that access to Twitter from Turkey may be blocked. Social media has a vital role to play in a modern democracy, and helps to promote transparency and vibrant public debate. We have long supported Turkey's accession to the EU. As a candidate country, it is important for Turkey to promote the EU's core values of freedom of expression, democracy and the rule of law," according to the statement. Swedish Foreign Minister Carl Bildt said in a tweet on Friday that "Turkish PM Erdogan is not only damaging himself, but his entire nation by his latest threats against Twitter." (Cihan/Today's Zaman) CIHANCopyright © 2014 Cihan News Agency.
]]></text></news-item>