<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-HP51-JBM1-B35J"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>REPORT DETAILS THREATS TO STATE; Trafficking of guns, drugs, people cited</title><source>The San Diego Union-Tribune</source><author>ROXANA POPESCU, U-T</author><text><![CDATA[A surge in methamphetamine and prescription drug traffic, increasingly sophisticated foreign cyber bandits and more-devious trafficking methods for people, drugs and guns are some of the criminal threats facing Californians, according to a report issued Thursday by state Attorney General Kamala Harris.
The report describes the smuggling, financial and cyber crimes and concludes with a series of recommendations. They include establishing a new maritime task force to deal with smuggling along the coast and restoring funding to a special operations unit based in San Diego.
About 70 percent of the meth from Mexico comes through San Diego’s ports of entry. The amount of meth seized by U.S. border authorities tripled since 2009, reaching 6,200 kilograms in 2013, the report said. To obtain the meth statistic, the attorney general’s report cited a PBS NewsHour piece published last year.
Mexican cartels obtain the meth ingredients, like ephedrine and pseudo-ephedrine, from countries where chemical exports aren’t closely regulated.
After passing through San Diego, the drug’s most common destinations are Los Angeles and Merced counties. That’s where two-thirds of “ice” meth seizures took place from 2012 to 2013, the report states. “Ice” is a form of meth that looks like glass.
San Diego’s border outpaces Arizona and Texas for meth trafficking, the report says — a trend that has persisted since at least 2009.
Lauren Mack, a spokeswoman for Immigration and Customs Enforcement, offered several possible reasons: San Diego’s proximity to Mexico, its position on a major smuggling corridor, and its easy freeway access to points of high demand.
San Diego used to be a meth production hub, Mack added. Now that industry has moved south into Tijuana and Baja California, and the drugs are being brought into the U.S. from there.
Finally, she said, the Sinaloa cartel is involved in the meth trade, while previous cartels, which have lost control of Baja California and northern smuggling routes, dealt more in marijuana and cocaine.
The attorney general’s report cited a drop in cocaine smuggling.
San Diego County Deputy District Attorney Steve Walter, with the office’s narcotics division, confirmed there has been an increase in meth cases. “It’s difficult for me to say what the crossing rate or the frequency of importation is here in San Diego compared to other places,” Walter said. “Anecdotally, we are seeing a rise in meth cases.”
Drugs are increasingly being smuggled on boats and unmanned planes, as well as through traditional ground methods, the report also states.
Seizures of marijuana from panga boats, a type of fishing vessel, spiked from 3,800 pounds in 2008 to 120,000 pounds in 2012.
These boats are “fast … effective, and economical. Most importantly, due to their fiberglass construction and low profile, pangas are extremely difficult to detect by radar or night vision. This, coupled with the sheer size of California’s coastline, means that most panga discoveries are made either through tips or by happenstance,” the report said.
Unmanned aircraft that fly more than 70 mph have also been sending drugs north. These light machines resemble hang-gliders with single-propeller engines. As drug vehicles, they were first sighted in 2008. Since then there have been more than 200 incidents.
Still, the report calls them “an emerging trafficking threat” and not as big of a problem as boats and tunnels. That could change with drones.
The report also looked at financial and cyber crime, the characteristics and locations of perpetrators, how criminals are working together, and how they are getting more tech-savvy.
Among the findings:
•?Cyber criminals are targeting businesses, consumers and government databases and networks. Technology and mass media play such a large role here that “California is particularly vulnerable when its networks become infected and its intellectual property is stolen.”
•?Human trafficking is profitable because victims are seen as “renewable … ‘commodities’?” and penalties are not as severe as for drug smuggling. A sex trafficking victim can yield more than $100,000 in annual profits, and a forced laborer can yield an estimated $13,000 in annual profits.
•?Transnational crime organizations are stealing IDs with ATM skimmers and defrauding people online.
•?Prescription drug trafficking from Mexico into California has spiked. Mexican pharmacies issue drugs without a proper prescription. Those get moved into California and shipped to Internet buyers.
•?Budget reductions have resulted in fewer anti-crime task forces: from 55 in 2011 to 17 in 2013. The report concludes with a series of recommendations, including funding to restore defunct task forces.
•?Gang membership grew by 40 percent between 2009 and 2011.
]]></text></news-item>