<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-HP51-JBM1-B35K"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>ELECTRIC BUS GETS TEST DRIVE IN ESCONDIDO; Input from high school district could help TransPower refine its technology</title><source>The San Diego Union-Tribune</source><author>GARY WARTH, U-T</author><text><![CDATA[ESCONDIDO
One of the first electric school buses in the state is being taken for an extended test drive in Escondido this month as part of a statewide effort to protect children from harmful diesel emissions.
“It’s like driving the tram at Disneyland,” said Jacqueline Redman, a bus driver in the Escondido Union High School District who credits the smooth ride to the heavy batteries on either side of the vehicle. “It’s been very nice.”
Redman said her student passengers also have praised the bus, built by Poway-based TransPower in response to new regulations aimed at lowering harmful diesel fuel emissions at schools.
The company hopes to someday mass produce the bus, but first it is offering it on loan for a month to a few local school districts.
The vehicle is the only 48-seat electric school bus in the state built for potential mass production. An electric 32-seat bus was introduced at Kings Canyon Unified School District in Central California last month.
Both vehicles were funded in part by the California Air Resources Board to address new regulations aimed at reducing diesel fuel emissions at schools.
New regulations went into effect Jan. 1, but the Escondido district has been preparing for the deadline for years by buying new buses and installing diesel filters on some of its older buses, said Mike Simonson, district assistant superintendent of business services.
Aside from the quiet ride, bus number E-1 looks like any other yellow school bus in the district’s fleet.
Its hidden battery packs and electric motor, however, make it stand out from other vehicles in the 20-bus fleet at the Escondido Union High School District. More significant, the technology could cut the cost of a 40-mile trip from about $18 to about $9, district officials said.
The $280,000 electric bus is about twice as expensive as a diesel version, but the price is expected to go down if mass-produced, said Robert Berkstresser, director of transportation for the school district.
The electric bus is being used for special-education students going to Orange Glen High School and regular-education students at Del Lago Academy.
Berkstresser said the district, like many others in the state, has cut many of its bus routes to save money but has retained federally required routes for special-needs students. In Escondido, most routes are for special-education students, although regular-education routes still exist at San Pasqual High and Del Lago Academy, he said.
The electric bus only runs in the morning because it has a range of 40 or 50 miles and takes eight hours to recharge. Simonson said the test runs will help engineers studying the bus to make improvements to help reach the goal of going 250 or 300 miles between charges.
Rob Reider, deputy director of the San Diego Air Pollution Control District, said the electric bus is being tested locally because TransPower won a grant of about $500,000 from the California Air Resources Board to create the vehicle. TransPower had to work with the San Diego Air Pollution Control district as the local authority to apply for the grant, he said.
Berkstresser said the Escondido Union High School District volunteered to be the first to have the bus, which was leased for $1 from TransPower. Other costs to the school district came to about $800 to build a recharging station.
That expense could pay off in the future, however, if the district eventually acquires its own electric bus.
Joshua Goldman, an engineer and vice president of TransPower, said the bus has the capability of reverting power back to its source — a technology known as “vehicle to grid” — meaning the district can earn money by providing electricity to San Diego Gas & Electric when needed.
“It can power the equivalent of 12 homes for an hour and a half,” Goldman said. “If they had a fleet of buses, it would be a small power plant.”
In addition to helping engineers refine the technology, the local tests are helping expose the electric bus to other school districts, said Mike Watt, program coordinator with the San Diego Air Pollution Control District.
And aside from the cost savings, the real motivation is to create a cleaner environment, Reider said.
“Motor vehicles like buses are the largest source of air pollution we have in the county, and kids are most vulnerable because their lungs are still developing,” he said. “This seems like a win-win.”
]]></text></news-item>