<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-K491-F0NV-F3TR"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>EPA knew of faulty pipes at Dan River ash basin in 2009</title><source>Danville Register &amp; Bee (Virginia)</source><author>Taft Wireback (Greensboro</author><text><![CDATA[As federal officials convene a grand jury this week to investigate the Dan River coal ash spill, they might want to look in an unlikely spot before pointing fingers of blame.
The mirror.
The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency failed to seize an opportunity in September 2009 that might have prevented last month's disaster near the retired Dan River Steam Station in Eden, the third-worst coal ash spill in U.S. history.
The spill on Feb. 2 occurred after a drainage pipe ruptured under the ash basin for the closed coal-fired plant. It's one of two such pipes mentioned as potential problems in a detailed report prepared almost five years ago by an EPA consultant.
EPA later sent Duke Energy and state officials an "inspection letter" about the plant in Eden that never mentioned recommendations by its own consultant for both pipes to be checked regularly, said Steve McEvoy, North Carolina's chief dam-safety engineer.
That stymied state regulators, keeping them from addressing the pipes in their later examinations of the site, said McEvoy, whose program is part of the state Department of Environment and Natural Resources.
"As due diligence, we relied on a review of the EPA inspection letter that did not mention the storm drains, even though they were mentioned in the detailed report (by the federal agency's consultant)," McEvoy said in an email. "I do not know why the EPA did not consider the drainage pipes in their final recommendations."
McEvoy's office in January 2010 assumed supervision of the dams protecting coal ash ponds across the state, inheriting a job the N.C. Utilities Commission had held for 35 years. But the EPA serves as the ultimate regulator for the nation's environmental laws.
At least five other studies of Dan River for the state's utilities board between 1981 and 2006 also mentioned the pipes as a potential problem that deserved attention. Those reports, however, went to a utilities board whose members lacked expertise in dam-safety engineering. They turned informally to the DENR for advice in interpreting the reports and then relied on the various power companies to carry out any recommendations.
The EPA sent the inspection letter from its Office of Solid Waste and Emergency Response directly to Duke Energy on Sept. 14, 2009, about four months before ash-pond scrutiny passed from the utilities commission to McEvoy's office. McEvoy and his staff took the EPA letter as their marching orders for the site at Dan River, supervising work for several years to shore up the ponds' earthen dam walls, stop polluted water from seeping out and fend off burrowing animals.
In general, a consulting firm hired by the EPA, Paul C. Rizzo Associates of Columbia, S.C., rated the Dan River ash basin in good condition during 2009 "with a few areas of concern, chiefly seepage and shallow surface slides. ..."
But the report to the EPA that year apparently was the last comprehensive, public study of those ash ponds to register concern about the drainage pipes before the spill.
The EPA told the News & Record that it didn't single out the pipes for extra attention five years ago because the agency's engineering consultant believed they already were being checked adequately by Duke Energy, in line with "standard industry practice."
"Issues related to the structural stability of the two stormwater pipes that pass under the primary (ash pond) were assessed by the EPA's contractor and determined to be adequate at the point in time during which the assessment took place," EPA spokeswoman Enesta Jones said in an email.
EPA commissioned the 2009 study as one of many across the region after a catastrophe in December 2008 involving coal ash in Kingston, Tenn., the worst such accident in U.S. history. The Kingston spill happened when the walls of a dam holding back 1.1 billion gallons of coal ash slurry gave way.
Coal ash contains a variety of heavy metals and other toxic chemicals that can be harmful to people, wildlife and fish.
The Dan River ash basin includes two ponds where Duke Energy stores the remains of pulverized coal once burned to generate electricity at a shuttered plant that was replaced several years ago by one that runs on natural gas.
Decades ago, Duke engineers enlarged the old plant's main ash pond over the two drainage pipes designed to carry relatively clean stormwater from land behind the basin, beneath the basin of polluted ash water and then out to the river.
In addition to citing the submerged pipes as potential problems in 2009, Rizzo Associates found several shortcomings in the Dan River facility's earthen dam and its upkeep. Federal regulators included those items in their subsequent inspection letter, though not the submerged pipes, and McEvoy's state office supervised Duke Energy's efforts to deal with them, including the seepage of polluted water from the dam.
McEvoy reported to EPA last August that "final approval of the repairs" at Dan River had been issued by the state government.
His staff never checked the two stormwater pipes because EPA did not list them as items of concern and also because "historic drawings provided by Duke Energy described the pipes as reinforced concrete," he said.
In fact, part of the pipe that collapsed and caused the spill was made of less-durable corrugated metal, a factor in the collapse that Duke and government officials disclosed in the days immediately after the spill.
A check of the second drainage pipe after the spill on Feb. 2 showed that it also leaked in numerous places, allowing polluted water from the ash pond above to enter that second pipe and then flow out to the river.
Duke plugged both pipes last month.
Duke officials declined to comment on whether their company was careful enough in following recommendations in various past studies that suggested different ways of monitoring the two submerged drainage pipes.
But spokeswoman Paige Sheehan noted that Rizzo's report for the EPA recommended that the utility check water coming out of the pipes for "turbidity," cloudiness that would suggest they were leaking.
"We followed the recommendation," Sheehan said.
The EPA would not say whether U.S. Department of Justice prosecutors in Raleigh have subpoenaed any of its records in their coal ash probe, which apparently focuses on both the Dan River spill and whether state regulators cut Duke Energy too much slack generally in enforcing the anti-pollution laws that affect the utility's 30-plus ash ponds at 14 active and retired coal-fired plants across the state.
"EPA and the DOJ (Department of Justice) regularly coordinate our collective efforts to enforce environmental law and protect the public. Due to the ongoing investigation information shared between the two organizations is confidential," Jones said last week.
DOJ investigators from the U.S. Attorney's Office for Eastern North Carolina subpoenaed numerous coal ash documents and witnesses from the state DENR along with reports and other material from the N.C. Utilities Commission, mostly from the its last 15 years of ash-pond regulation. Duke Energy officials also have acknowledged having been served subpoenas, but they have declined to say who or what was summoned.
A spokesman for Rizzo Associates referred questions about the report to the EPA.
But Rizzo executive Conrad Ginther said in a recent telephone interview that none of the firm's data or documents related to the facility in Eden have been subpoenaed by the grand jury, which began its probe Tuesday.
"The EPA has all our records that were based in the report," Ginther said.
]]></text></news-item>