<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-07X1-F11P-X1SX"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Erdogan gov't deals new blow to rights, freedoms with Twitter ban</title><source>Cihan News Agency (CNA)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ISTANBUL (CIHAN)- In what came as a new development in a growing list of prohibitions against rights and freedoms in the country, Turkish courts on Thursday night -- apparently following an order by Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan -- blocked access to Twitter in a little over a week before the March 30 local elections.
The ban, which has drawn huge reactions both from Turkey and the world, came hours after the prime minister threatened to "root out" the social media network where wiretapped recordings have been leaked, revealing some Justice and Development Party (AK Party) government officials' hand in corruption and other forms of wrongdoing. Despite the ban, tech-savvy users managed to tweet links to the recordings on Friday. President Abdullah Gül was among those who circumvented the order, which he contested in a series of tweets. He wrote that complete closure of social media platforms is unacceptable. He also said only individual Internet pages should be blocked if a court ruled that an individual's privacy had been violated, adding that he hoped the current block would not last long. When vowing to block Twitter, Erdogan said he did not care what the international community had to say about it. "Twitter, mwitter!" he told thousands of supporters at an election rally in Bursa on Thursday, "We will wipe out all of these," Erdogan said. "The international community can say this, can say that. I don't care at all. Everyone will see how powerful the Republic of Turkey is," he said in a characteristically unyielding tone. The Prime Ministry, in a statement, said Erdogan was referring to what it called Twitter's failure to implement Turkish court orders seeking the removal of some links and that it may be left with no option but to ban the website all together. "If Twitter officials insist on not implementing court orders and the law ... there will be no other option but to prevent access to Twitter to help assuage our citizens' grievances," the statement said. Following the ban, the Communication Technologies Authority (BTK) said Twitter had been blocked by the courts after complaints were made by citizens that it was violating privacy. It said Twitter had ignored previous requests to remove content. Some users trying to open the Twitter.com website were taken to a statement apparently from the Telecommunications Directorate (TIB). The statement cited four court orders as the basis for blocking the site. It also accused Twitter of violating "personal rights and the confidentiality of private lives" and said access would be restored only when Twitter removes "illegal content."
San Francisco-based Twitter said that it was looking into the matter and had not issued a formal statement. Turkish Internet users were quick to come up with their own ways to circumvent the block. The hashtag #TwitterisblockedinTurkey quickly moved among the top trending globally. Some news sources said Twitter has sent its lawyers to Turkey to discuss the ban. News sources said the Twitter ban came due to a fake user. The Istanbul Chief Public Prosecutor's Office, in an attempt to refute claims that it had banned access to Twitter, said it made no decisions for the ban. The disruption sparked a virtual uproar, with many comparing Turkey to Iran and North Korea, where social media platforms are tightly controlled. The AK Party has already tightened Internet controls, particularly after recently passing amendments to the Internet law that have paved the way for greater control over the Internet and invasion of privacy. The party has also handed the government more influence over the courts and reassigned thousands of police and hundreds of prosecutors and judges. All followed a major corruption and bribery investigation that has implicated several AK Party government members and even the prime minister and his family members. The investigation has frustrated Erdogan, who claims his government is exposed to an international plot, supported by domestic collaborators. The investigation became public on Dec. 17 of last year when police detained the sons of three then-Cabinet ministers and businessmen close to the prime minister. The three ministers resigned a week later, while others were removed in a Cabinet reshuffle. Since Dec. 17, some anonymous Twitter users have been publishing voice recordings that allegedly belong to high-level officials. The recordings suggest those officials' involvement in corruption and bribery. The original source of the recordings is unclear. The Twitter ban was only the latest clash between the AK Party and social media companies including Google, Facebook and Twitter. Turkey in the past blocked access to YouTube, but it is the first ban on Twitter. Erdogan slammed Twitter as a "scourge" last summer after millions of anti-government protesters organized their activities via the site during the Gezi Park protests last summer. Earlier this month, Erdogan said Turkey could also ban Facebook and YouTube, which he says have been abused by his "enemies" after a stream of audio recordings purportedly revealing corruption in his inner circle emerged online.
But a senior official said on Friday there were no immediate plans to do so. Reuters quoted a senior government official, without citing his name, as saying: "The path was taken to block access within the framework of a court decision because of the failure to overcome the problem with the management of Twitter. At the moment there is no such decision for other social media like Facebook." In Samsun, the lawyer of a woman who had appealed against Twitter told the media that they did not ask for the blocking of Twitter. The lawyer said there was a fake user using the name and surname of his client and posting photos of naked women for a while. The lawyer, on behalf of his client, filed a lawsuit for the removal of that content and blocking the account of the fake user. "We have now learned that our suit has been used an excuse to block Twitter. We did not ask Twitter to be blocked," he said. The ban has drawn public outrage as well as international condemnation. There were also calls to take to the streets to protest, although some users equally called for calm. The US expressed deep concern about any move to introduce a ban on social media, highlighting the significance of freedoms. The Cihan news agency reported that former Transportation and Communications Minister Binali Yildirim, who is currently running for mayor of Izmir from the AK Party, filed a lawsuit against Twitter on March 18. The ex-minister argued in his suit that the platform has content that violates his personal rights. Deputy Prime Minister Ali Babacan said he expects the block on Twitter to be temporary and that he expects a mutual solution to be found. Lütfi Elvan, the minister in charge of transport and communications, said his office was merely obeying court orders. "Turkey is not a country that bans the Internet," he said. "We have to stand together against insults and unlawfulness." Bülent Arinç, also a deputy prime minister, became the first government official to violate the Twitter ban. He tweeted his schedule for March 21. He said he would be in his hometown of Manisa on Friday. His tweet came hours after access to Twitter was blocked. Arinç probably used a different proxy service to access the platform. Ankara Mayor Melih Gökçek, an enthusiastic Twitter user, also continued accessing Twitter on Friday. "I am able to post tweets thanks to my DNS settings. Access through this will probably be blocked tomorrow, too. I hope fake account holders and those who use Twitter to insult others will draw the necessary lesson," he said, putting the blame for the ban on users rather than the government.
Finance Minister Mehmet Simsek, commenting on the ban, said Twitter was not blocked due to a "pro-ban mindset." "If this was the case, then all other social media platforms would have been blocked. The Twitter issue is related to a court order," he argued during a TV program. Forestry and Water Affairs Minister Veysel Eroglu linked the Twitter ban to the approaching local elections, which he said could be marred by provocations. "The elections should be held in a healthy atmosphere. I think Twitter will be re-opened," he noted. AK Party deputy Yalçin Akdogan, also a chief advisor to the prime minister, blamed Twitter for what has happened. He also said there is not a ban on Twitter. "Access has been blocked," he said. Twitter ban sparks opposition uproar The opposition parties slammed the AK Party government for blocking Twitter, which they say is aimed at "banning any thought or opinion critical of the government." In an immediate reaction to the ban, the Republican People's Party (CHP) filed a legal challenge against a court decision to block access to Twitter. Akif Hamzaçebi, the party's parliamentary group deputy chairman, said the CHP would also file a criminal complaint against Prime Minister Erdogan on the grounds that he has been violating personal freedoms. He also said Turkey is being governed by a "bully." "This bully seeks to save himself [from corruption claims]. He has zeroed his dignity both in Turkey and abroad." CHP Chairman Kemal Kiliçdaroglu posted a tweet in which he said, "Despite the Twitter ban, tweet for your freedoms." He called on Prime Minister Erdogan to lift the ban. "A ban on thoughts will damage the reputation of Turkey," he cautioned. "The society wants freedoms, but you put pressure on the society. The society wants to talk freely, but you ban free speech. Turkey was supposed to be freer, what happened? People post tweets to express their thoughts. Why is Erdogan afraid? He is probably afraid of things he cannot explain [to the society]," the CHP leader said. CHP deputy Sezgin Tanrikulu submitted a parliamentary question in which he asked where the AK Party gets the authority to ban Twitter. "Doesn't blocking social media mean blocking freedom of thought and communication?" he also asked. CHP Deputy Chairman Haluk Koç said the AK Party blocked Twitter as it was unable to establish an "Alo Twitter" hotline. He was making reference to the "Alo Fatih " incident, which stands for the prime minister's exertion of influence to manipulate the editorial policy of some press outlets through appointments from among his reliable men. He also said the ban has come as an implicit confession by the prime minister that all claims of corruption and bribery leveled against him reflect the truth. "We are witnessing the last struggles of a lunatic dictator," he added.
Gürsel Tekin, a CHP deputy chairman, said Turkey wakes up to new bans every morning. "The Twitter ban will not be the last of the bans. We have been faced with hundreds of bans so far. The AK Party vowed to fight bans in 2001 during its election campaign. Why are they afraid of a bird now?" he asked, in reference to the bird symbol of Twitter. The CHP's candidate for mayor of Istanbul, Mustafa Sarigül, filed a lawsuit against the Twitter ban. He said the ban is a crime against humanity and a shame for democracy. Nationalist Movement Party (MHP) Deputy Chairman Sefkat Çetin said Erdogan is no different from dictators in North Korea and Syria. "It is never possible to cover up facts with bans or pressure," he stated. According to Çetin, Erdogan is probably worried that Twitter and other social media platforms will be used to make people learn about his other wrongdoings and this is why he opted to block access to Twitter. MHP parliamentary group deputy chairman Oktay Vural said his party will file a criminal complaint against the TIB on the grounds that it overstepped its authority with the Twitter ban. "The ban is a direct blow to the law and the rule of law in Turkey. The ban is against the law. The TIB has no authority to ban Twitter. The government does not have any authority for such a ban, either. Who are you [in reference to TIB and the government] to deprive the people of their right to information? I will file a criminal complaint against the ban. And we will see if there is a judge in Turkey to protect the rights of people," he stated. Independent deputy Ertugrul Günay, who recently parted ways with the AK Party, said the absurdity of the Twitter ban will soon be understood. "It is a source of sadness to see those who set off with a motto to fight bans are now seeking benefits in bans," he noted. (Cihan/Today's Zaman) CIHANCopyright © 2014 Cihan News Agency.
]]></text></news-item>