<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-WT31-JBSM-83T5"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>News Briefs: Regulators: Duke pumps coal ash into N.C. river; 2 Taliban Afghan attacks show dangers loom</title><source>Tulsa World (Oklahoma)</source><author>Wire Reports</author><text><![CDATA[Charlotte, N.C.: Regulators: Duke pumps coal ash into N.C. river
North Carolina regulators say Duke Energy illegally pumped 61 million gallons of contaminated water from a coal ash pit into the Cape Fear River, marking the eighth time in less than a month the nation's largest electricity company has been cited for environmental violations.
The pumping violated the terms of Duke's wastewater permit at its Cape Fear Plant, State Department of Environment and Natural Resources spokesman Jamie Kritzer said Thursday. Kritzer said the agency has issued Duke a formal notice of violation, which could result in hefty fines.
It wasn't immediately clear if Duke's efforts to empty the pond were related to a crack in the earthen dam holding back the coal ash. Inspectors are trying to determine the cause of the crack.
Kabul, Afghanistan: 2 Taliban Afghan attacks show dangers loom
Four gunmen with pistols stuffed into their socks attacked a luxury hotel frequented by foreigners in Afghanistan's capital Thursday, just hours after militants killed 11 people in an audacious assault on a police station in eastern Afghanistan.
All the assailants were killed in both standoffs, but made their point: Afghan forces face a huge challenge in securing upcoming elections in what will be a major test of their abilities as foreign troops wind down their combat mission at the end of this year.
The attacks show the Taliban are following through on their threat to use violence to the disrupt the April 5 vote, which will be the first democratic transfer of power since the 2001 U.S.-led invasion that ousted the Islamic militant movement.
Taliban spokesman Zabihullah Mujahid claimed responsibility for the assault on the Serena hotel and the earlier attack in Jalalabad, an economic hub near the border with Pakistan.
Houston: U.S. questions more than 100 from 'stash house'
U.S. immigration authorities on Thursday were interviewing more than 100 people presumed to be in the country illegally after they were discovered crammed into a small house in south Houston.
Five men also were in custody, two of whom were arrested after driving from the home on Wednesday. Authorities suspect it was a so-called stash house, a place where smugglers bring the people they've brought into the U.S. illegally and keep them until they or their family members pay a ransom.
Los Angeles: Microsoft: It snoops on Hotmail to track leak
Microsoft has skewered rival Google for going through customer emails to deliver ads, but it's acknowledging that it searched a blogger's Hotmail account to track down who was leaking company secrets.
John Frank, deputy general counsel for Hotmail's owner, Microsoft, said in a statement Thursday that the company "took extraordinary actions in this case." He says that in future, Microsoft would consult a former judge to determine if a court order would have allowed such a search.
The case involves former employee Alex Kibkalo, a Russian native who worked for Microsoft Corp. in Lebanon.
According to an FBI complaint against Kibkalo filed in federal court in Seattle on Monday, Microsoft found him in September 2012 after examining the Hotmail account of the blogger with whom Kibkalo allegedly shared proprietary Microsoft code.
Ankara, Turkey: Turkey blocks accessto Twitter over leaks
Turkey has restricted access to Twitter hours after Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan threatened to "root out" the social media network where wiretapped recordings have been leaked, damaging the government's reputation ahead of local elections.
Many users trying to access the network early on Friday were confronted instead with a notice from Turkey's telecommunications authority, citing court orders for the site's apparent closure.
On Thursday, Erdogan said the government would take steps against Twitter regardless of "what the international community will say."
The leaked recordings include one in which Erdogan allegedly instructs his son to dispose of large amounts of cash from a residence amid a police graft probe.
]]></text></news-item>