<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-3191-DY2T-D2VY"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>This land is your land, this land is their land; Private property deemed necessary for, say, a pipeline can be expropriated</title><source>The Vancouver Sun (British Columbia)</source><author>Kelly Sinoski, Vancouver Sun</author><text><![CDATA[If Kinder Morgan knocks on your door and wants to run a pipeline through your backyard, there's not much a resident can do besides negotiate reasonable compensation, according to an expropriation lawyer.
Several Fraser Heights residents told the Sun this week that they'd received a hand-delivered package from an agent hired by Kinder Morgan, advising them that some of their land might be needed for the new Trans Mountain Pipeline. Ted Hanman, a lawyer with Victoria firm Cox Taylor, says once the planning has been done and the alignment chosen for a particular infrastructure project, residents are usually at a loss to keep their land intact if they sit on a proposed right of way.
Several such cases have occurred recently across Metro Vancouver, including construction of the Canada Line project, the Golden Ears Bridge, the South Fraser Perimeter Road and Port Metro Vancouver expansion.
Here are some frequently asked questions about land expropriation: WHO CAN EXPROPRIATE LAND? Federal and provincial governments, municipalities, TransLink, BC Hydro, Metro Vancouver's water and sewer districts - any organization that requires land for "a linear taking" or connecting route from neighbour to neighbour. This could involve railways, highways, ports, pipelines and transit lines.
CAN HOMEOWNERS FIGHT IT? Yes, but in many cases the provincial or federal governments may state the project is deemed in the private good or national interest.
"Once the alignment is fixed, there's very little in the way of movement that's possible without going back to square one," Hanman said.
He noted most authorities are not trying to cause "grief or havoc" but will attempt to reach a mutual agreement with landowners to try to find the most effective and reasonable routes with the least disruption. He noted the South Fraser Perimeter Road has had a huge impact on individual properties but its intention is to reroute traffic and global goods overall.
"Each and every project, whether it's a water line or a gas line, has a consequence," he said, but added: "How many people can look at the Canada Line and say Vancouver can function without it?" WHO IS ELIGIBLE FOR COMPENSATION? Landowners who are directly affected by a project, such as running a pipeline through their backyard.
During the construction of the Golden Ears Bridge, for example, TransLink did not offer compensation to a couple whose home was under the bridge because their land was not considered to be needed for the project itself. The couple sued the South Coast B.C. Transportation Authority and the B.C. Transportation Financing Authority for the noise, pollution and invasion of privacy and eventually reached an out-of-court settlement with TransLink.
"There was no taking from that property but clearly there was an impact," Hanman said.
WHAT CAN RESIDENTS EXPECT TO RECEIVE? That depends, as each property affected is individually assessed. The standard rule of thumb usually involves market value for the land, damage to the remainder, and out-of-pocket expenses and disturbances, although landowners can advance a claim for higher entitlement through the courts.
"It's a balancing act of public interest and public benefit," Hanman said.
He noted money often isn't enough for some landowners, who may no longer want to live on their property with a Hydro line or pipeline running through it, and may negotiate for a total buyout of the land. BC Hydro in 2009, for instance, paid $62 million to purchase about 100 homes near a controversial Tsawwassen power line.
WHEN WILL THEY RECEIVE MONEY? Landowners must be compensated up front if an authority plans to expropriate their property. Before 1987, a piece of land could be dedicated but a landowner would have to make a claim for compensation.
ksinoski@vancouversun.com
]]></text></news-item>