<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-3M31-JC6P-C1R2"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Experts debate need for carbon emission regulation in power plants</title><source>Lubbock Avalanche-Journal (Texas)</source><author>R.S. Douglas, Lubbock Avalanche-Journal, Texas</author><text><![CDATA[March 21--Recent studies indicate that 97 percent of climate scientists and about 70 percent of Texans agree that global warming is not only a real phenomenon, but one that is escalating because of day-to-day activities of humans.
No firm plan to reduce mankind's carbon footprint exists, but the Environmental Protection Agency is taking a step toward solving the problem by considering regulations that would limit power plants' carbon emissions.
Those proposed parameters don't sit well with Rep. Randy Neugebauer, R-Lubbock, a senior member of the House Committee on Science, Space, and Technology, who spoke against the changes at a congressional hearing earlier this month.
Two regulations proposed by the EPA last year recommended that a "new source performance standard" be implemented, essentially requiring power producers to use carbon capturing and storage at all new plants and potentially current ones, Neugebauer said.
"The problem with that is that this technology has not been adequately demonstrated for full scale commercial use," he said. "I think there is a lot of concern that this will make it more difficult and more expensive to bring new power plants online."
Neil Marchbanks, Neugebauer's Democratic opponent in the upcoming election, said he couldn't disagree more. He compared this debate to two different responses regarding proposed standards to increase the fuel efficiency in cars. The punch line, Marchbanks said, is General Motors hired 100 new lawyers in response and the Japanese hired 100 new engineers. Not too much time passed before the Japanese were outselling General Motors, and the American company was going to Washington to ask for a bailout, he said.
"People have to keep up with the times and have to recognize when technology is moving on and adjust to it," Marchbanks said.
Local impact
Power plants release an estimated 40 percent of carbon dioxide emissions, a greenhouse gas believed to contribute to climate change.
Other than keeping records, no laws address carbon emissions, and there may not be if the EPA heeds the advice of many utility companies.
The agency's September proposal is still in the public comment portion of the process, and both Matt Rose, spokesman for Lubbock Power and Light, and Wes Reeves, spokesman for Xcel Energy, said the companies are actively opposing the new regulations.
Coal-powered plants are considered to release the most carbon dioxide, but even generation plants running on natural gas have carbon emissions, Rose said.
LP&L operates eight generation units in three locations, all of which run on natural gas, Rose said.
Xcel has two plants powered by coal, and because of its low cost those plants operate nearly year-round, Reeves said, speaking only on behalf of Xcel's operations in Texas and New Mexico.
Xcel owns more than 4,000 megawatts of generating capacity in Texas and New Mexico, including both coal- and natural gas-powered plants, Reeves said.
"Of that number, roughly half of the (generating capacity) is made up of those coal units," he said. "It's really important and it is also the least expensive generating resource we have."
The cost of the new technology that would be required to comply with the proposed regulations will ultimately be passed onto retail customers, Rose said. Still, the municipal utility is preemptively looking at ways to incorporate the costs into rate models, as most power companies are.
2019 and beyond
Because of the anticipated regulations hindering coal-powered plants, building new ones is considered too risky for many utility companies, an issue that is more difficult for other parts of the country than in West Texas, Neugebauer said.
As LP&L looks toward power generation for 2019 and beyond, Rose said coal-powered plants were initially considered, but they have been ruled nearly completely unviable by the board overseeing the decision.
Though coal is the cheapest alternative, Marchbanks said temporarily moving forward without it is the best option.
"We've got a time period here where we have plentiful natural gas that is inexpensive," he said. "We need to be using the natural gas and using the time period to improve the technologies for these other types of fuel such as coal ... and looking to add renewable energy sources to the mix, rather than relying on centuries-old technology."
Renewable energy
Renewable energy could become more attractive if the proposed policies are implemented, Rose said.
Currently wind and solar power are too expensive for the municipally owned utility to access because, as a government entity, LP&L does not benefit from renewable energy tax credits.
Still, the power company is moving forward with plans to increase the amount of renewable energy on the grid in 2019 when the city's contract with Xcel expires, Rose said.
Xcel, a company that can take advantage of the tax credits, is already entering into purchase power agreements with wind energy producers to add more renewable sources to its portfolio, Reeves said.
Current power plants
While the EPA proposal is directed toward new power plants, there is talk of regulating current operations as well. Neugebauer said he fears this could force some plants into early retirement.
Still, Xcel isn't raising the white flag yet,
"This is something that has taken place in some places around the country, but we have no plans at the present time to retire coal plants in Texas and New Mexico," Reeves said. "It would be speculative say which options are on the table for us should the EPA regulate existing sources."
It could be years before the EPA standards are implemented, but both LP&L and Xcel are preparing for the change by exploring options with renewable energy and ways to sell captured carbon to other companies, specifically those involved in horizontal fracturing.
Economic impact
More than just the cost of electricity, Neugebauer said he is concerned the economy will lose jobs, citing a study conducted by the Heritage Foundation, a Washington D.C.-based conservative think tank.
According to the report published on the organization's website, a projected 600,000 American jobs will be lost by 2023 because of the EPA's proposed policies, and Texas alone will lose 25,000 jobs.
Neugebauer also estimates that the 19th congressional district will lose more than 420 jobs -- nearly equivalent to the entire population of Ropesville. He did not cite how that number was reached.
"That is a combination of several things, one is direct jobs, but more importantly if you increase the cost of power ... it makes businesses less profitable and causes them to have to lay off people," he said.
rs.douglas@lubbockonline.com
-- 766-8742
Follow R.S. on Twitter @AJ_RSDouglas
___ (c)2014 the Lubbock Avalanche-Journal (Lubbock, Texas) Visit the Lubbock Avalanche-Journal (Lubbock, Texas) at www.lubbockonline.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>