<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-BXK1-JCCC-K35G"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Oil project has a bad Linc</title><source>Wyoming Tribune-Eagle (Cheyenne)</source><author>Staff</author><text><![CDATA[Wyomingites generally, and residents of Campbell County particularly, should attend a state Department of Environmental Quality hearing on Thursday regarding drinking water protection of the Fort Union Wyodak Aquifer.
DEQ proposes to exempt/reclassify a portion of the aquifer to enable Linc Energy's underground coal gasification experiment, which the Australian company hopes to expand into commercial production.
The public may speak at the hearing at the Wright Branch Library from 4-6 p.m. or send written messages to DEQ.
The agency based its decision on a 1983 agreement between the state and the federal EPA that sets parameters for underground injection control.
Linc's application, reproduced on the DEQ website, shows that test burns would cover an 80-acre portion of the aquifer at a depth of 1,100-feet. Coal would be ignited with oxygen and swamped with steam to convert the coal into "syngas." Linc plans to exhaust 1,000 tons of coal to produce about 1 million standard cubic feet of gas per day.
It says there will be no "adverse environmental impact" even though the syngas would be flared off. A million cubic feet of gas, burning daily, without adverse consequences?
After the test phase, Linc plans commercial production in Wyoming, though its Australian attempts have been problematical. A scientific panel studied the two companies, Linc Energy and Carbon Energy, that have undertaken trials in Queensland.
Its report notes failed wellheads; mechanical design problems relating to ignition and injection; and inadequate construction material for production wells. These were "lessons learned."
But unresolved issues remain: "downstream" contamination from underground temperatures of up to 1,500 degrees Celsius that produce "serious contaminants" when the chemicals escape into the surrounding environment.
The panel notes that Linc's assessments have been "retroactive," after a "hazard event" had occurred. As concerns risk assessment, no "core integrated framework" exists.
Site selection is crucial, the "single most important" aspect for risk-based evaluation. The panel says site selection should be based on geological surveys, hydrogeological modeling and assessment of community and environmental contexts.
Local residents' objections to Linc's Wyoming proposal will note that water needs in the area are increasing. Linc's application says the aquifer portion it seeks will not in future be used for drinking water because of its "mineral producing" potential: It contains hydrocarbons that may be "commercially producible."
Yet the Fort Union aquifer contains good quality water, and the formation is a commonly used water supply in the Powder River Basin. Even at depth of 1,000 feet or more, several aquifers within the Gillette area serve both the city and its subdivisions.
Linc's application states that DEQ requested a "demonstration project" prior to full-scale operations. The company says it has operated a demonstration facility in Queensland since 1999," where it continues to make synthetic crude "while maintaining environmental compliance."
But the panel says the Queensland facilities are "pilot" that never progressed to "demonstration" projects. While small-scale projects are manageable (barely), their expansions can become huge liabilities. Though the syngas industry has made strides in the past 30 years, progress has been limited.
Linc has been "unable to demonstrate" effective cleanup. The panel says "rubble from gasified coal (ash and tar)," from "collapsed overburden," and from "disturbed underburden" hinder decommissioning. It also notes lack of monitoring systems and "failure of infrastructure." Risk-based plans are not developed.
The panel recommended to the Queensland government that Linc continue for six months, provided the company "immediately propose, test and establish" a planning and action process that shows its commitment to cleanup.
Linc also must show environmental safety via "event-based milestones." Long-term critical risks also must be assessed, and besides, an underground cavity of "significant dimensions" must exist for "full comprehensive demonstration."
The panel cautions against further ignitions until long-term environmental safety can be demonstrated.
Clearly, before the Linc project goes any further in Wyoming, site selection needs scrutiny. Next Wyoming should wait until Linc has cleaned up its Queensland operation. That will give state and federal governments time to develop the guidelines recommended in the report.
DEQ does not accept emailed comments. I hand-delivered my comments to:
DEQ Water Quality Division
Kevin Frederick, administrator
122 West 25th St.
Herschler Building 4W
Cheyenne, WY 82002
Edith Cook
is a Cheyenne writer. Reach her at e104cook@aol.com or www.edithcook.com.
]]></text></news-item>