<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-3191-DY2T-D2XX"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Updating B.C.'s water policies is long overdue; A new law protecting our most precious resource is very welcome</title><source>The Vancouver Sun (British Columbia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Quick, what's British Columbia's most valuable natural resource? If your first response was natural gas, or metals, coal, timber or fish, you'd be seriously out of step with nine out of 10 of your fellow citizens.
Recent polling shows the vast majority of us believe fresh water to be our most valuable resource.
This is certainly congruent with attitudes in government, which is in the process of rewriting the province's dilapidated and outdated Water Act. The province acknowledges that water is the foundation of life itself and that without it, none of the other resources that so often dominate our social, economic and political agendas matter much. In fact, water often turns out to be the font of controversies over the two other great global issues of the 21st century, energy and food.
Indeed, water lies at the heart of a series of current domestic debates, which range from international jockeying about the future of the 50-year-old Columbia River Treaty to water as a feedstock for lucrative industrial activities.
One major mine development - Taseko Mine's New Prosperity open pit copper and gold project in the Chilcotin - has been spiked twice by Ottawa over concerns regarding possible damage to 27 square kilometres of surrounding watershed.
Environmental organizations are now in court disputing the way in which the oil and gas industry obtains access to short term licences for fresh water used in fracturing subterranean formations. The Western Canada Wilderness Committee and the Sierra Club of B.C. both allege that the BC Oil and Gas Commission has wrongly permitted withdrawal of millions of litres from lakes, streams and rivers, after which it's infused with chemicals and injected to smash up formations and release natural gas.
There's concern over groundwater contamination from agricultural run-off in the Fraser Valley and leaching from landfill sites in the Interior and on Vancouver Island and disputes about who gets what water for irrigation, whether wetlands deserve protection or development, whether a third hydroelectric dam should be installed on the Peace River, encroachment upon riparian zones by urban real estate developments, large-scale municipal sewage treatment projects, whether logging should take place in community watersheds supplying drinking water, and so on.
There's controversy about commercial extraction from an aquifer near Hope, whether pricing provides adequate compensation to the province and about the subsequent export of B.C. water as a bottled commodity - a development with which, polls show, many British Columbians remain deeply uncomfortable.
And there are rumbles of geo-political discontent on both sides of the border regarding the terms of the Columbia River Treaty by which B.C. receives hundreds of millions in revenue benefits from power generated by U.S. dams which themselves back-flooded large areas in Canada. The U.S. thinks it pays too much. B.C. thinks the U.S. doesn't adequately factor in downstream benefits from flood control above intensively cultivated agricultural regions and densely populated urban zones. Both sides are concerned about finding ways to restore salmon runs to the headwaters of an immense watershed that has been massively modified.
In this broader context, drafting a modern, up-to-date statute by which B.C. has the tools to properly manage this vital resource is clearly in keeping with what the people of the province desire.
The Water Act was first drafted more than a century ago at a time when the entire population of B.C. was 370,000 people, about 100,000 fewer inhabitants than now live in Surrey. Resources, including water, seemed endlessly abundant and there was little understanding of the ecological principles of sustainability - or even, in many cases, the complex, interdependent ways in which ecosystems function. A new act, addressing technologies, demands and environmental oversights that were barely imaginable when the first act was passed, is long overdue.
The new act, tabled in the legislature last week, promises among other things to bring previously unregulated - and in many cases unmapped - groundwater resources under provincial control, monitor and report on large-scale water use, permit government control of water management in response to climate events like drought, strengthen protection for aquatic environments, impose a modern pricing structure on water users both industrial and residential and to create a new framework to improve security of supply through conservation and efficiency.
All this is good news and goes a considerable distance toward meeting the concerns of environmental groups. The legislation under discussion isn't perfect - there are reasonable arguments that it doesn't go far enough and isn't aggressive enough in pricing for commercial extractions; that it's inadequate in addressing First Nations' interests in watersheds; that it fails to empower local communities in rejecting projects which affect water; that it doesn't establish basic access to clean water as a fundamental human right for every B.C. citizen rather than a property right for those who can afford it.
These are all fair points for discussion. We live in a democracy, after all, and government presents legislation for debate and amendment. Still, after a century of growth and change, it was high time to dust off the cobwebs and develop management protocols for what - if climate change predictions prove even modestly accurate - will certainly be among the most pressing resource issues of our time.
]]></text></news-item>