<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-T7D1-F12F-F39X"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Pakistan: Local drug makers oppose market access to India</title><source>Right Vision News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[LAHORE, March 21 -- Local drug manufacturers urged the government on Wednesday to rethink its decision of granting non-discriminatory market access to India as it would flood Pakistan with substandard medicines.
They said that the government should take a cue from latest bans by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) on Indian drug manufacturers exporting substandard medicines to US.
The FDA has imposed ban on numerous Ranbaxy plants operating in India for violation of good manufacturing practices, Amjad Ali Jawa, a former chairman of Pakistan Pharmaceutical Manufacturers Association (PPMA), said.
The Indian leading Ranbaxy is producing a number of generic replica of famous medicine brands of US.
Not only had it defrauded the consumers, but also manipulated the data about the efficacy of many of its generic drugs without actually performing the required quality tests.
Jawa said Pakistan lacks the equipment, technology and the drug auditing expertise available with the FDA.
If Indian drugs are allowed into Pakistan, patients would be at health risk, he said.
He added when Indian drug makers could hoodwink the most prudent regulator in the world, there wouldn't be any problem for them to dump substandard drugs in Pakistan where drug regulatory authority is much weaker.
Another former Chairman PPMA Dr Khalid Javaid agreed with this argument. Without carefully assessing all the outcomes, the government should not permit import of so-called cheap medicines from India, he said.
Dr Javaid said that the increasing number of quality issues and latest bans by the FDA in the recent years on the neighboring country's drug makers would call for a policymaker's attention to think about NDMA status, which would compromise the health of millions of people.
In addition to Ranbaxy, other pharmaceutical concerns of India, including Sun Pharmaceuticals and Wockhardt Ltd, met the same fate, he said.
The pharmaceutical business leader said that all the three firms were FDA-approved manufacturing facilities. These firms deviated from the best business practices after the approval, he said.
Wockhardt faced import restriction on its second plant in Chikalthana, Aurangabad for destruction of raw analytical data and samples.
Production Head and Vice President of the firm were reported to have lied to the FDA inspector, he added.
The firm maintained inadequate washing and toilet facilities, including urinals lacking plumbing.
This substandard arrangement, he added, allowed urine to flood the floor only 20 feet from the gowning area for the Sterile Formulation manufacturing facility, according to the drug manufacturer
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Right Vision News. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>