<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-K4D1-JD6S-R4JK"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Only one large bank fails Fed's stress test</title><source>Winston-Salem Journal (North Carolina)</source><author>JOURNAL STAFF AND WIRE REPORT</author><text><![CDATA[All but one of the nation's 30 largest banks are considered as better able to withstand a severe U.S. recession and global downturn than at any time since the financial crisis, the Federal Reserve reported Thursday.
Results of the Fed's annual 'stress tests' showed that only Zions Bancorp failed to meet the Fed's minimum level of capital to withstand a crisis. That hypothetical crisis would include a U.S. unemployment rate of 11.2 percent, a 50 percent plunge in the stock market and home prices declining by 25 percent over a 15-month period.
The 30 banks tested included BB&T Corp., Bank of America Corp., Citigroup, JPMorgan Chase, Wells Fargo & Co., PNC Financial Services Group Inc. and SunTrust Banks Inc.
Bank of America was listed among the banks at the bottom of the successful list, while BB&T, Wells Fargo, SunTrust and PNC were in the middle. The top-rated bank was State Street Corp.
'We are pleased that the results of the stress tests show BB&T's Tier 1 capital in the top quartile of all banks,' said Daryl Bible, the bank's chief financial officer. 'The results of the annual company-run stress tests demonstrate BB&T's continued strength. Under our and the Federal Reserve's calculations, BB&T's capital ratios remain very strong.' The Fed will announce March 26 whether it will approve plans by some of the banks to increase dividends or buy their own stock.
- The Associated Press, Richard Craver
Duke Energy CEO earns $6.5 million in 2013
Duke Energy Corp. chief executive Lynn Good earned nearly $6.5 million in 2013, more than doubling her previous pay as chief financial officer, The Charlotte Observer reported Thursday.
Good's pay last year reflects only six months as chief executive, a position she took on July. She was paid $929,000 in salary and about $5.3 million in stock awards and incentive pay.
As chief financial officer, Good had earned about $3.1 million in 2012.
Former chief executive Jim Rogers, meanwhile, took home $9.5 million in his final year at Duke. Rogers retired as chairman in December. Rogers was paid mostly through stock awards and options as Duke's CEO since 2006. He earned $8.7 million in 2012.
Stock owners will vote May 1 on a shareholder proposal that Duke disclose the company's political contributions, posting the information on its website.
Duke's political ties have been of public interest since the Feb. 2 spill of coal ash into the Dan River. Gov. Pat Mc-Crory, who was a long-time Duke executive, appointed the secretary of the state agency responsible for policing ash.
Duke's board of directors opposes the proposal, saying most Duke-linked political spending comes from political action committees or employee contributions, not the company itself.
- McClatchy Tribune
11 percent of long-term unemployed find jobs
WASHINGTON - A new study found that of Americans who have been unemployed for more than six months, just 11 percent of them will ever regain steady full-time work.
The findings by Princeton University economists show the extent to which the longterm unemployed have been shunted to the sidelines of the U.S. economy since the Great Recession.
During any given month from 2008 to 2012, barely more than one in 10 of the longterm unemployed had found full-time work. Their troubles were similar in states with high as well as low unemployment rates.
- The Associated Press
Starbucks to roll out beer, wine to more cafes
NEW YORK - Starbucks plans to turn more of its cafes into a destination for beer and wine in the evenings.
The coffee company says it is looking to expand alcohol sales to thousands of stores over the next several years. The chain first offered beer and wine at one of its Seattle cafes in 2010. This is now available in 26 cafes, with plans to reach 40 by the end of the year.
It is part of the company's push to boost sales after the morning rush hour when people are getting their caffeine fix.
- The Associated Press
]]></text></news-item>