<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-VRK1-J9XT-P242"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>TIP asks PM not to approve services contract for LNG terminal project at PQA</title><source>Daily The Pak Banker</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Transparency International Pakistan (TIP) has asked Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif to cancel the LNG service contract for terminal project at Port Qasim, as the contract-awarding process is full of massive violations of PPRA rules and that the terminal would also prove a catastrophe in case of any untoward incident at the port.
Transparency International Pakistan (TIP) in its letter written on Thursday on a subject of violation of Public Procurement Rules 2004 in Evaluation of ISGS tender No. ISGS/Proc/TE-FTLNG/2013 addressed to Mr Javed Aslam, secretary to prime minister, appreciates the declared policy of zero tolerance for corruption adopted by the government and application of rule of law in Pakistan. They are: Why did the ministry of petroleum insist in July 2013 on awarding unsolicited contract for Fast Track Engro Terminal Project at a cost of US $30-40 million? Why was SSGCL not allowed to invite bids? Why ISGS has invited bids? Why has the ECC approved the single bid of ETPL on Feb 2, 2014 when the ECC had rejected single bid of LNG terminal on 30-3-2013? Why has the Cost of Single bid submitted for approval of ECC in July 3013 increased to US $150 million in this tender? Why did SSGCL not approve the bid of ETPL, and why after the appointment of new chairman GCL, the board of SDSDGCL approved the bid? Why PQA (Port Qasim Authority), after it rightly refused to allow LNG Terminal at Engro and FOTCO Terminal in Oct 2013, after the new board members were nominated by federal government, in which one director is the brother of SSGCL chairman, has suddenly agreed to allow ETPL in Feb 2014 to set up LNG Terminal at Chemical Terminal Site? Why are the three exiting terminals at PQA, QICT, FOTCO and FAP challenging the ETPL LNG Terminal as high risk to their employees and establishment? Why is GoP agreeing to pay to EVTL, in case of non-availability of LNG, capacity payment of US $11-13 million per month, which comes to an average of US $144 million per annum, for a project costing in July 2013 US $30-40 million and, lastly, what is PQA royalty, which shall not be less than the latest royalty charged in the Cargo Terminal awarded by PQA, competitive royalty share to PQA is 40% of the total revenue of the terminal operators. The TIP also quoted a story, which appeared in a section of the process, according to which the prime minister has refused to approve award of the multi-million-dollar liquefied natural gas (LNG) terminal contract to Elengy Terminal Pakistan Limited (ETPL) and has instead told the ministry of petroleum and natural resources to seek the nod of the federal cabinet The Economic Coordination Committee (ECC) of the cabinet, in a meeting held on February 28, had approved, in principle, award of the contract to ETPL subject to getting the go-ahead from the prime minister. During the deliberations, the Law Division said Section 21 of the Ogra Ordinance 2002 empowered the federal government to issue policy guidelines to the Oil and Gas Regulatory Authority (Ogra). After the 18th Amendment to the Constitution, the definition of “federal government” had been changed and now the federal government or prime minister could give policy guidelines directly or through a federal minister, it said. ETPL, a subsidiary of Engro Corporation, had been declared the successful bidder as it quoted a tolling fee of 60 cents per million British thermal units (mmbtu). In the first phase, the government plans to import 200 million cubic feet of LNG per day (mmcfd) from November this year and increase the quantity to 400 mmcfd in 2015. According to officials, the price quoted by ETPL has been approved by the consultant. The price had been evaluated keeping in view the regional tolling rates for terminal handling and that’s why the federal cabinet was being asked to approve the contract. However, the ECC was upset about payment of million of dollars in capacity charges to ETPL on account of tolling fee by Pakistan State Oil (PSO) even if it (PSO) was unable to import LNG. The economic managers suggested that PSO should carry out due diligence before issuing a letter of comfort to Sui Southern Gas Company for LNG import from Qatar. “Since the federal government controls PSO, the letter of comfort would have a bearing on taxpayer money. Therefore, before issuing the letter, PSO should carry out due diligence,” the ECC said. ECC, according to TIP letter, also noted that the LNG services agreement was a commercial contract between two commercial entities including SSGC and ETPL and their boards of directors were competent enough to grant approval of the agreement. The letter says it has also been reported in the media that on February 28, 2014, the ECC meeting chaired by finance minister Senator Ishaq Dar agreed to give, in principle, its approval to the project after secretary petroleum argued that its disapproval by the ECC would send a negative message, which may create difficulties in terms of investor interest or financial support to the project. The letter also pointed out that in the name of Fast Track Project, and urgency due to energy shortage, ministry of water & power, in violation of PPRA Rules, had awarded RPP contracts in 2006 and in 2008 the capacity payments of over US $9 million per month, which were challenged by TI Pakistan. Also MNA Khawaja Asif had filed a petition in the Supreme Court of Pakistan. The ministry of water & power at that time had misguided the two prime ministers in 2006 and 2008, for awarding RPP Contracts without tendering or changes made in the tendered conditions, after the bids were opened. Three ex-ministers, 2 secretaries, and one PM are now facing corruption charges in NAB Accountability Courts only due to the contracts awarded on the wrong advice of the secretary, ministry of water & power. The Supreme Court in its judgment in Case No HRC 7734 G/ 2009 announced on March 30, 2012, declared all RPPs contracts null and void. On this procurement, ISGS tender No. ISGS/Proc/TE-FTLNG/2013, vide its letter dated 29-11-2014, minister of petroleum & natural resources TI Pakistan said: “The minister is informed that on TI-Pakistan letter dated 21st September 2013 objecting, FOTCO’s requests to PQA for use of chemical terminal for LNG handling, the PM office took notice, and vide their letter U.O. NO. 7(1) DS (E-11) 13, dated 26th September 2013, the secretary port and shipping was directed to submit report. Port Qasim Authority is the owner of the area on which the terminal is to be established, and has refused to allow both FOTCO and EVTL the use of chemical terminal (Engro Terminal) and FOTCO oil terminal site for LNG terminal, vide their letter 8th October, 2013, which confirms that the procurement should not have been commenced under Rule No. 11, which speaks about approval mechanism according to which all procuring agencies shall provide clear authorisation and delegation of powers for different categories of procurement and shall only initiate procurements once approval of the competent authorities concerned has been accorded. “This matter has been taken up by the Supreme Court of Pakistan under HRC NO 28368-S/2013,” says TIP letter. In fact ministry of petroleum & natural recourses, on the initiative of secretary MoP&NR first tried to award LGN terminal to Engro without going into tendering in July 2013 that ECC should allow exemption from PPRA. TI Pakistan vide its letter dated 19-7-22014(Annex-A) had warned the minister of petroleum and minister of finance to desist from violating PPRA Rules. Secretary MoP&NR’s proposal was that the three different projects for construction of terminals at Port Qasim for receiving, storage and re-gasification of LNG were approved by ECC, that include Fast Track Engro Terminal Project, which is likely to be completed between six to eight months at an estimated cost of $30-40 million and will have a capacity of 200 MMCFD modalities, and it will be finalised between the secretary finance and secretary petroleum. In August a company ISGS, and not SSGC (the procuring agency) invited tenders, opened them in October 2013, and only two bids were received. One bid was declared non responsive, and TI Pakistan in November 2013 informed the ministry that according to PPRA Rules, single bid can only be considered if the procuring agency has awarded a similar contract in current fiscal year, so that the competitive rates could be checked, and also that ECC in March 2013 decided to scrap a SSGCL single tender of LNG terminal at Port Qasim, and to invite bids again. The TIP in its letter urged the prime minister to uphold the rule of law and the spirit of maintaining zero tolerance for corruption.
]]></text></news-item>