<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-3181-DY2T-82DN"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Bulgaria's crisis may soon spill out beyond its own borders</title><source>Ottawa Citizen</source><author>Shannon Gormley, Ottawa Citizen</author><text><![CDATA[In Bulgaria, protests against corrupt government institutions have become something of an institution themselves. Every night, a motley crew of Bulgarians trudges purposefully down one of the main streets of the capital, Sofia, banging drums, blowing whistles, and shaking hands with the police officers, who are pretty nice to them. They're just a day's drive from Kyiv in Ukraine, where barricades still carve up Maidan.
While Ukrainians have protested for four months, however, Bulgarians have been doing it for nine - 10, if you count the February 2013 demonstrations that brought down their former government. Some protests number a mere hundred people, some have attracted tens of thousands; some protesters brandish European Union flags, others lean on canes; some demand that election rules be changed by means of a referendum, some beg the international community to intervene by any means necessary. Several have set themselves on fire. All march against the government.
Their concerns run deeper than their present coalition government though, just as they ran deeper than their previous right-wing one. Bulgaria is not only one of the most corrupt countries in the EU; it's also the poorest. Youth unemployment is at 30 per cent and rising. And though students have twice barricaded themselves into their university's main building, theirs is not a solitary economic catastrophe: the European Commission has reported that in recent years, half the population has been at risk of poverty or social exclusion; nearly half the population has experienced severe material deprivation.
The average salary in Bulgaria is the lowest among all EU member states: 393 euros, by the most recent statistics. The spectre of bankruptcy looms over the National Electric Company and the National Health Insurance fund.
While faith in public institutions plummets, xenophobic nationalism soars. A November poll revealed that 15 per cent of Bulgarians say they approve of violence against foreigners. During the same month, militias began stalking the streets of Sofia.
Bulgaria has entered a state of semi-permanent crisis. That much is clear. Considering Bulgaria's painful transition into a functioning democracy, it's also not entirely surprising. It is surprising, however, that Western states may have to start giving a damn. As nearby Greece, Ukraine and Turkey churn with crises of their own, their proximity to Bulgaria may rapidly make the country more strategically important to western nations in three ways: economically, militarily, and regarding the flow of people.
First, businesses are fleeing Greece in droves and seeking refuge across the border in Bulgaria. Bulgaria may offer its citizens little, but for businesses, taxes are low and labour is cheap. The Guardian reported this week that between 2010 and 2012, the number of Greek-owned firms registered in Bulgaria rose by a remarkable 75 per cent. Rising instability in Bulgaria may further destabilize relocated Greek businesses.
Second, Bulgaria, like Romania and Poland, may become more important to NATO as Russia consolidates its military buildup in nearby Crimea. While NATO has been monitoring Ukraine's airspace from Poland and Romania, it has conducted military drills in the Black Sea, which Bulgaria sits on. Two weeks ago, Bulgarian naval forces participated in exercises just a few hundred miles from the Crimean peninsula, alongside Romanian and US naval forces.
Third, neighbouring Turkey has become the world's second largest host to Syrian refugees; many of those refugees, having fled Syria to Turkey, are now fleeing Turkey to Bulgaria. They don't plan to stay long, especially after being effectively imprisoned for months in centres that forced up to 20 people to share a single room while they awaited asylum decisions. Many Syrians believe they will be able to move on further into Europe, although they can only travel temporarily within the EU as a refugee. Of the asylum-seekers who realize this, Boris Cheshirkov of the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees tells me, many plan to move to more hospitable EU countries and take their chances with being sent back.
Back on the streets of Sofia, protesters remain preoccupied with the government they don't want governing them. A 48 year-old protester named Ogi tells me, "We have protested. We have been to the streets. Now it is depend on you, the international community. We did our job."
He's advocating a foreign-backed military ouster of the government, which isn't going to happen. Nor should it. But when one of his fellow protesters, a professor, overhears, he lets out a laugh.
"This can't be possible according to our constitution," the professor says. "But this would be not a bad thing in my opinion."
Shannon Gormley is a Canadian journalist based in Beirut. She writes for the Citizen every Saturday about global affairs and the state of democracy and liberalism around the world.
]]></text></news-item>