<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-JV21-JB20-G1NB"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Malaysia Plane Mystery; Obamacare's 4th Birthday; Pelosi: Obamacare is a Winner</title><source>Fox News Network</source><author>Bob Beckel, Andrea Tantaros, Eric Bolling, Dana Perino, Greg Gutfeld</author><text><![CDATA[BOB BECKEL, CO-HOST: Hello, everyone. I'm Bob Beckel, along with Andrea Tantaros, Eric Bolling, Dana Perino, and Greg Gutfeld.
It's 5:00 in New York City. And this is THE FIVE.
(MUSIC)
BECKEL: It's been two weeks to the day since Malaysian Flight 370 went missing. Today's effort to find it in the Indian Ocean came up short.
Five surveillance aircraft will go out again at dawn. Conditions were good for international search teams earlier.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
UNIDENTIFIED MALE: We had a session today and had really good weather actually compared to what we saw yesterday. The visibility was great. We got a lot of hope and the conditions remain as they are, hopefully we'll find something soon.
UNIDENTIFIED MALE: It's certainly disappointing and I've got every confidence that if there is an object there, that we will find it. And every time we launch, we hold that hope. However, we're just going to keep going until we find it.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
BECKEL: But good weather may not be enough. Australia's prime minister says the possible debris they're looking for might not even be on the surface anymore.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
TONY ABBOTT, AUSTRALIAN PRIME MINISTER: Something that was floating on the sea that long ago may no longer be floating. It may have sunk to the bottom. It's also certain that any debris or other material would have moved a significant distance over that time.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
BECKEL: Whatever else you think about this story, this is the single biggest aircraft surprise and mystery we know since Amelia Earhart 75 years ago. The difference is, now you've got satellites and a lot of ways to trace these things. It didn't back then.
This is what we know for certain: that this plane took off at 12:41, on its way from Kuala Lumpur to Beijing. We know, in fact, that it turned around and headed west, exactly the opposite direction it was going in. We know that it flew for eight hours and the last connection with it was at 8:11 on the next morning, and it ran out of fuel at 8:40.
So, there are a lot of questions, a lot of possibilities, a lot of guesses, and that's what they are, guesses. But I'm fascinated by this because in this day and age, how do you lose something that big?
Go ahead, big boy.
ERIC BOLLING, CO-HOST: Well, that was really -- that was very impressive. That was nice.
DANA PERINO, CO-HOST: The best I heard all day.
BOLLING: Good summary, right.
So, here's the deal -- so, 5:00 in the evening now. I believe it's 12 hours later in Australia. The sun is going to start to come up. For the second day now, they're going to try to look for those same two pieces of debris. Now speculation, it was the same piece they just took another picture of, we don't know.
The problem is this, that we keep getting the emotions. The poor family members, they're getting close to getting closure. It looks like they have something, and then they don't. Now they can't find the debris for the second time.
I -- you know, we have to continue to cover it because we want to make sure the Malaysian and Thai authorities and everyone really stays on the issue so that these families get closure, but it's so hard with these emotional swings up and down.
BECKEL: Andrea, your brother is a pilot, I know a commercial pilot. You talked to him several times. The other things we do know, in fact, are that the two transponders were turned off in that plane at two different times. They weren't done at the same time, and that someone programmed into the computer of the plane to change directions of the plane going west.
Is that -- what does he say about that? Is that -- I mean, it's possible to do obviously because somebody did it.
ANDREA TANTAROS, CO-HOST: He just finds it to be very odd that if it was a fire or if there was an emergency landing, one, these pilots did not have any mayday call. There was no emergency communication there. He also said if the plane was going down, you're not going to stop and push in new waypoints.
You know, it is interesting that they did find today that the plane was carrying these highly flammable lithium ion batteries. That's a new development. That actually could play into the theory there was this spontaneous explosion and maybe that's why the ACARS system was left on. Maybe that wasn't exploded.
But I still don't understand, Bob, why, and this is what he said, why there was a deliberate turning off of the transponder. Not once but twice, no mayday call, and that deliberate turn west after they said good night very calmly. That does not add up in the minds of pilots.
BECKEL: Well, the other thing that happened here, Dana, is they looked into the background of virtually everybody on the plane, most of whom were Chinese, and they say that they found nothing exempt for two people who had phony passports that were issued in Thailand given to them, and the flights were paid for by an Iranian. But outside of that, there's nothing about the passengers or the pilots that we know now that says they were either radicals or they were in a suicide mode.
But if you're going to kill yourself, do you not just take the thing up and just bring yourself back down?
PERINO: Well, thankfully, I've never been in a position to do that, so it's hard for us to put ourselves in that position and to think about it.
But the flight simulator that the pilot had in his home just arrived today at Quantico, Virginia. So, the FBI will have a chance to look all the way through it.
One thing I really liked about what the Australians did today in their press coverage is they were very honest about what they know and what they don't know and how they might not find anything at all. And that is a different type of communication than you saw from what was happening in Malaysia over the 10 days, and I think that's good for the families. The Australians are not sugar coating it and you actually feel a sense of relief that they are in charge and they've got the materials and the resources and training to go out and try to find whatever they might find tomorrow.
BECKEL: You know, Greg, you made this point all week about the U.S. taking over. You have now the Malaysians who didn't do a very good job of reporting, you've got to get them somewhat of a break, there's a lot of information coming in.
But then we find out the Thai military has information that the plane did in fact make the return, and they said they reported it to the Malaysians within two days. We didn't hear about it for five days.
Now we do seem to have some semblance of order from the Australians.
But do you think this -- let me put it this way. Would they try to be cool by keeping control over the message of this thing, or were they overwhelmed or just not competent enough to do it?
GREG GUTFELD, CO-HOST: I think we needed their permission, right, to do anything? I think we were actually being respectful. I was pretty hard on the government for not taking charge. I might be wrong. I don't know.
But I still think that we should have been more forceful to get the stuff done because there are Americans onboard, and also, the end result could be an attack on America when you have a missing plane. That could be weaponized into some kind of, you know, weapon of mass destruction.
You know, the most successful word throughout this whole thing is the word "could". If you just put could in front of every sentence, you have a new story. Could the Tea Party in conjunction with the Koch brothers have taken the plane for an impromptu visit to Cuba?
BECKEL: That's exactly what it is.
GUTFELD: But I mean, the thing is -- there are a lot of people in the media who are criticizing the media for covering this. Now this is a "media on media' media commentary. People who are critical of wasting time on this probably tweet about "Scandal" while they're binge watching it. They're probably following a baseball team 162 games.
This is worth following because it's real and it could be really, really real in terms of terror later.
BECKEL: OK, Uncle Bill O'Reilly had comments about this very thing on his show, I believe last night. You want to take a look at that.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
BILL O'REILLY, FOX NEWS HOST: We can expect to hear massive speculation about the debris until it's found. That's because the media is running wild with the airline story, as you know, and there's a big reason why: money. The nation's newspapers are in dire trouble. They need bold headlines. The network doesn't want to cover important stories like the IRS and Benghazi, but they can cover the airliner without any political consequences.
Today, circulation of ratings dominate news coverage and unfortunately, so does ideology. The combination of cash and politics makes it exceedingly difficult for you to get the truth.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
BECKEL: O'Reilly being a little cynical here, Eric?
BOLLING: Well, look -- I'm going to take the other side of that argument, with all due respect, Mr. O'Reilly. I think the world is really tuned into it, they're clued into it. We're seeing ratings amongst all TV networks rise because everyone wants to know what's the new piece of news. Am I going to be right? Is it what I thought it was going to be?
I've been saying -- by the way, as soon as we find out what happened, I will guarantee 99.9 percent of the population will say, "aha, I told you", because everyone said everything. That's OK.
I think Bill O'Reilly is frustrated, as a lot of true journalists are. We need something more, we need more to go on rather than repeating the same thing.
Can I just throw this in quickly? Money is so important, when you talk about why the Thai government had it for a while and why the Australians are doing everything by the book and the Americans are waiting to take over -- again, this is a $280 million airplane. There are about 239 souls onboard. Technically, they throw a number around about $175,000 someone could be on the hook for per passenger, per fatality.
You're talking in excess of $320 million at stake. There's a lot of money at stake. I'm sure every one of these governments, insurance companies and airlines are going to do it exactly by the book.
BECKEL: Speaking of the lines that could, "The Daily Telegraph", (INAUDIBLE) used to live in London, says they now have the recordings between the tower and the copilot who did all the communications.
Now, I don't know what we learned from that very -- and how they got it is very interesting to me, if in fact they did get it, could they have gotten it? What were you going to say, Greg?
GUTFELD: Well, I was going to say, it's hard for anybody to say, to gauge the importance of the story because the story is not over. I talked about this with friends of mine.
If that plane were to suddenly show up again in the air and be asking to land in an airport in the New York area, what does America do? What do we do? If they're saying mayday and they want to land?
That's a big deal. It may never happen, but the fact is, if it's still an important news story until it's no longer important, until you have the facts and find out it's a tragic accident. But until we don't know that, it could be something far worse.
So, I don't know if you should be saying that there are other things like -- for example, we did a lot on the "Duck Dynasty" controversy. This is more important.
BECKEL: Yes.
Well, speaking about the passengers, Andrea, normally you see when these disasters happen, pictures of all the people onboard. I don't know about the rest of you, I have seen pictures of the pilots and copilot. I've never seen pictures of the engineers and I don't think I've seen pictures of any of the people who are on the plane except their family members who were in such huge distress.
TANTAROS: Well, I think this is hugely embarrassing to the country of Malaysia, which is why they don't release it.
Here in the United States, we're good about getting the names out and the personal stories behind it. But again, we're not in control of this thing. I think what's frustrating is that -- so, we got the tapes, the telegraph has these tapes. So far, we've learned there's nothing unusual about the tapes. Maybe we'll learn more.
We also spend yesterday talking about the debris. And today, the story was it could not maybe even be debris at all. It could be just light reflecting. So, we've talked 48 hours about that.
We also learned now that Malaysian authority are waiting for permission from Kazakhstan to start searching another area. So it's almost like we're back to square one on this.
And it's easy for Bill O'Reilly to, you know, go after the media on this, but Bill O'Reilly is the media on this. I mean, he acts like he's a citizen journalist who is doing this for free.
I mean, it's the most downloaded after "Not Cool" on my Facebook, post on Facebook. People have strong opinions. They care a lot or they don't care, but they care so little they're willing to get angry.
BECKEL: We've got to get out of here, but I understand one thing, if you had to grade how the Malaysians have handled this from a communications standpoint from A to F, where would you put them?
TANTAROS: D.
BECKEL: D?
PERINO: And I would say the brilliance of Bill O'Reilly is that he figured out a way to talk about the plane in a way that could still get him ratings, but he could criticize people talking about the plane. That's one of the reasons he's great at. It's one of the reasons he's number one -- for now.
GUTFELD: It has become, what the plane has become is like checking box scores, in the morning or checking stocks. It's like, so it becomes part of your regimen. Where is the plane today? And that's because we're curious about it. I think that's human nature.
BECKEL: It's a mystery. And it's one of the great mysteries of aviation history.
Next on THE FIVE, there's going to be a birthday party. And it's certainly going to be an interesting one. Stay tuned to find out why.
TANTAROS: Well, today, we observe a birthday, but it's far from celebration. Four years ago, Nancy Pelosi and the Democratically- controlled Congress rammed Obama's Affordable Care Act down America's throat. Pelosi, who once told us we have to read the bill to see what's in it is as proud of ever while former Obama political strategist David Axelrod said Dems should embrace the law.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIPS)
REP. NANCY PELOSI (D), CALIFORNIA: We just couldn't be prouder. I believe it's a winner. And by the way, it's called the Affordable Care Act. It's called the Affordable Care Act. I know you didn't intend any compliment or derogatory -- it's called the Affordable Care Act.
Affordable, there's a reason. Affordable. Affordable. Affordable. Affordable. Affordable.
DAVID AXELROD, FORMER OBAMA POLITICAL STRATEGIST: I think a lot of Democrats buy into this myth that the Affordable Care Act is doom and they should run from it. They should be proud of it. Democrats should embrace it.
(END VIDEO CLIPS)
TANTAROS: Affordable.
So as Americans lose their doctors and see their coverage cut and their premiums rise, we dedicate this beautiful cake to the minority leader.
Take a look, everybody. The Pelosi birthday cake. Maybe we should call it Pelosi-care.
What do you think, Greg? Because the recent poll --
PERINO: Affordable Pelosi care.
TANTAROS: Affordable Pelosi care. Affordable Pelosi care. Affordable.
Because actually a new poll said the more Republicans mention Pelosi, the better they do. She's the best gift the GOP has.
GUTFELD: Yes, it's a meat cake because it's full of baloney.
You know, it's kind of weird that she doesn't want to call it Obamacare. Is she a racist for not wanting to call it Obamacare? Because other people might call the right the same thing.
By the way, if you don't want to call it Obamacare, call it what it really is, the "you ruined my life" act.
(LAUGHTER)
TANTAROS: Dana, you said something while Pelosi was reminding us how affordable it is. President Obama said what's wrong with Obamacare? Didn't he want us to --
PERINO: Right. This started in the 1990s when Hillary Clinton tried to get something passed and it was called Hillary care. When Obama started down the road of trying to get the legislation passed, people are nicknaming it Obamacare.
And eventually, he came out and he said, call it Obamacare. You have my permission. But now all of a sudden, they don't like it anymore. It's like -- it's thing in Washington.
I remember when President Bush introduced the Clear Skies Act. And all the Democrats and the media would call it the so-called Clear Skies Act. So, it was a little bit of game playing, but actually, the underlying issues are very serious, and I think that the Democrats that are running for office are not listening to Pelosi and Axelrod. It's just noise in the background, because they know that their elections basically rest on this problem.
TANTAROS: Yes, Eric, we seem to be the only ones that are acknowledging this four-year-old bill. You know, we talked about the fact that the numbers haven't been there. You went through the numbers yesterday on the show.
Another fear, according to a "National Review Online" is that even people who may have started paying, a lot of them having paid yet, will eventually stop paying. That's an issue we haven't gotten to.
BOLLING: So, Nancy -- we rolled the sound bite, March of 2010, if I'm not mistaken, where she said affordable, affordable, affordable. Here we are four years later. And we -- that was yesterday, she said affordable yesterday.
So, even worse, because now we know that it's no longer bending the cost curve down for health care, which they promised it would. We found out that now the $2,500 per family it was supposed to save us is actually costing families $2,500 more prior to Obamacare. The rates have risen since the Affordable Care Act was passed in the -- I believe three or four years since it's become law, I guess, it now has exceeding the prior eight years before it was law in rate increases.
So, nothing affordable about this whatsoever. By the way, eight months after Nancy Pelosi was talking, she became the former speaker of the House -- seven great words: former speaker of the House, Nancy Pelosi -- because of that.
TANTAROS: Bob, can I play some of the pro-athletes have joined the cause. Athletes are getting involved. The Baltimore Ravens have been enlisted. Now, some very famous NBA players are coming out to help sell this as well. Take a look.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
LEBRON JAMES, NBA PLAYER: I want to tell you about the health insurance marketplace at healthcare.gov. You can go there to find an affordable health plan that's part of the health care law.
KOBE BRYANT, NBA PLAYER: It's a great cause and there's something that, particularly for athletes, it is extremely important thing for us to be a part of because we need health care.
UNIDENTIFIED MALE: Playing sports, it's important to make sure you have great health care because you never know when you're going to take a hit.
(END VIDEO CLIPS)
TANTAROS: King James, Kobe Bryant, these are some of the most popular guys in the NBA, Bob. Will it work?
BECKEL: Yes, I think it's going to work, but I also think that other people celebrating today -- let me make a point about a press release from the largest health insurance company in the country, WellPoint, which oversees Blue Cross and Blue Shield among others. They announced they're increasing their dividends to their taxpayers by 20 cents.
Their stock is soaring. The reason? One million to 1.3 million new insurance holders in their company because of Obamacare specifically. And they also said the cost of health care will begin to decline once this plays itself out.
This is WellPoint, this is the biggest one. They think it's great. They're making a lot of money out of it. A lot of people have joined, 1.3 million, that's one health care --
PERINO: You're happy the health insurance company is making money, Bob?
(CROSSTALK)
BECKEL: If you go to one source to figure out whether this is working, go to the devil. They'll tell you it's working.
GUTFELD: The thing is -- I mean, it's amazing how many -- if Obamacare is a winner, what does it take to be a loser? By using their definition, the Denver Broncos are winners from last year's Super Bowl. It makes no sense. What have you got to do?
BECKEL: What's your evidence that says it doesn't work?
(CROSSTALK)
BOLLING: Here's some evidence -- it was sold to the American people it was going to bend the cost curve down. That was -- that was a Democratic talking point. Obamacare or affordable Care will bend the cost curve down. It's raising the cost curve.
Premiums are spiking faster than they were before Obamacare.
BECKEL: But by your own admission, health care premiums have gone up every year before Obamacare. Now you're saying they're really spiking up?
BOLLING: But, eight years prior, they went X. The four years since, they have gone up x plus 40 percent.
(CROSSTALK)
BECKEL: Forty percent?
BOLLING: Forty percent, plus 40 percent.
TANTAROS: Bob, it's unbelievable.
BECKEL: Then when it plays itself out, enough people get in the market that you embrace so much, I assume all these people buying the health care, eventually the costs are going to go down.
BOLLING: What's the point? What's the point of doing this? Fewer people are covered. It's costing --
BECKEL: No, that's wrong. Fewer people are not covered.
BOLLING: There are fewer people covered in America today than before we started this process.
BECKEL: Wrong.
TANTAROS: That's absolutely true.
BECKEL: Boehner yesterday got four Pinocchios yesterday for saying that.
TANTAROS: We have to move to a topic that is blowing up social media right now. The first lady is in China. It was making headlines because it would not be covered by press, no press allowed, not even human rights would be discussed.
Greg, why do you think people are so fascinated by the first lady going to China with her daughters, no media, no talk of issues? A lot of people saying this is on our dime. Should people care?
GUTFELD: Yes, I don't -- I can't buy into the outrage over a trip that first ladies make. To me, I think it's good if she goes abroad, if she goes to China. When she goes home, she appreciates the country all the better.
When I'm away from home, I can't wait to get home. I say, boy, I love this city. Maybe when she gets home, she'll say, boy, I love America more.
TANTAROS: She said she's never been prouder. Can she get more prouder, do you think?
GUTFELD: That's my point. Yes.
TANTAROS: Dana?
PERINO: Well, OK, I have gone back and forth on this. I can understand if she wanted to take the girls and I think it's a great idea. I would have loved to have been able to have that experience to travel internationally when I was in high school and junior high, forming ideas and thinking things through. This is our spring break, it makes sense timing wise.
I think it's curious they're able to take press on every other thing they want to do, and they have photographs, right? But if she was going to practice some of the soft diplomacy, which I think is good for America, it helps, I don't understand why they couldn't have at least provided some opportunity for the press.
It would seem like the least they could do, and I think that proactively announcing you're not going to bring up human rights in China while you're having meetings and having your picture taken, because the Chinese are using that everywhere, we could have used it as an opportunity to raise a voice.
However, I think she wants to protect her girls from the press, and to a large extent, I don't think anybody who has violated that from the White House press corps standpoint.
BECKEL: Let's keep in mind. She's the single most popular political figure in America by far over everybody.
TANTAROS: I was going to say --
BECKEL: And it's not a bad idea to have her out there.
TANTAROS: But why not use her for a purpose?
BECKEL: Well, I mean, I think going to China serves a purpose.
TANTAROS: For what?
(CROSSTALK)
PERINO: If you want to have a personal trip, it's one thing. It's another thing to do these quasi-official events and have your trip paid for by the taxpayers.
TANTAROS: Eric?
BOLLING: Call me mean, rude, but I hear China is beautiful this time of year, but so are Texas and California.
BECKEL: What's the point?
BOLLING: My point is I don't think -- there's so much stuff going on. We have Russia, we have Vladimir Putin redrawing the global map. There's so many international things going on. I just -- I would rather have both of them --
TANTAROS: I don't -- I do not begrudge the first ladies traveling. However, when you're going to a place like China, it should have a purpose. She being so popular could deliver a message, especially on human rights and girls in China. That would be perfect for her. But --
GUTFELD: That's where the pandas are.
TANTAROS: Yes.
Coming up -- I thought your apartment was where the pandas are.
GUTFELD: Well, those are different pandas.
BECKEL: Those are stuff --
(CROSSTALK)
TANTAROS: How is a sneaky teen able to slip past security to get to the top of the Freedom Tower here in New York City? Well, it should be one of the most secure sites in the world.
Plus, a soul sister brings down the house on Italy's rendition of "The Voice." You've got the nun that everyone is talking about, up next.
(COMMERCAIL BREAK)
BOLLING: Welcome back, everybody, to the fastest 6 1/2. It's on fire today. Three vivid stories, 6 1/2 vigorous minutes and one voracious host.
Three stories today, three hot ones. Get ready for your heart to be tugged from an unusual place, Wal-Mart.
Check out this inspirational ad, a real Wal-Mart winner, but by the way, maybe they should loop this video in all the unemployment offices in America.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
UNIDENTIFIED MALE: One doctor said I had a condition that affected every part of me. My condition became so bad I lost feeling in my legs.
I learned to walk again. And when I wanted to work, I got a job. It's a struggle every day, but I still get up because work makes me feel that I'm reaching my goals.
My whole life, people have been telling me I have a learning disability. I guess they're right because I never learned how to give up.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
BOLLING: All right, Bobby, even you are going to be able to pat Wal- Mart on the back to that ad.
BECKEL: No, it doesn't tug me in the heart. It tugs me in another place.
The whole announcement, $250 billion of American products over the next 10 years which is a fraction of what they buy around the world, number one. Number two, taking advantage of this kid and putting an ad out, for Wal-Mart who put more businesses out of business than any other company in the history of the world, to do that is I think is just --
(CROSSTALK)
GUTFELD: Bob, can I ask you a question? What would you replace Wal- Mart with? Government --
BECKEL: Small businesses that they put out of business.
GUTFELD: That's what you would do. That's exactly the nature of progressivism. You don't even know what to replace it with -- small businesses.
BECKEL: The small businesses they put out of business.
GUTFELD: Please, they didn't put anybody out of business. They're the largest employer in the country, and you are actually upset they hired somebody with a disability. You might be the only person.
BOLLING: And very quickly, they also bring prices down to people who frankly probably need a break right now.
Let's talk about Wal-Mart and Patrick. Patrick is working through some disabilities. You have give him a pat on the back. And, frankly, I think Bob is wrong on this one.
PERINO: I think there's two audiences for Wal-Mart. One is the external audience, you and me.
The other is their internal audience and their employees. And I think that internal organizational communication is one of the most interesting areas from my perspective as a PR person, that you have to remind people why you work there. I think not only is it important for us to see it, but this is an investment that will pay off for Wal-Mart because if you read "The Wall Street Journal" everyday or "The New York Times," all the bad stories about Wal-Mart, watch Bob, then you'll have one perspective. Now, they have a chance to tell their own story.
BOLLING: Your thoughts?
TANTAROS: I don't think this issue is black and white. I do agree with Bob that it can hurt small businesses. I remember when they wanted to put a Wal-Mart in Trexlertown, Pennsylvania, my father was very upset. He joined together with a lot of small business owners and said this is -- this is going to hurt a lot of people.
However, it did bring a lot of people to an area that was not very populated to go eat in those restaurants that normally maybe you wouldn't travel out there.
I will say this when it comes to hiring people with disabilities. Obviously, I'm all for that and I will say Wal-Mart does put its money where its mouth is. They hire people with disabilities. They hire the elderly to be greeters. I mean, these are people who typically are turned away immediately. So, I do give them credit.
GUTFELD: They turned me away, though.
TANTAROS: Well --
BOLLING: We've got to go. We've got to go on the next one.
It's 16-year-old daredevil who has been known to post selfies hanging from various high buildings like this one in Hoboken, New Jersey. See the Freedom Tower in the backdrop. It turns out Justin Caskill (ph) slipped past security at Freedom Tower. He allegedly made it to the 104th floor.
Anyone else concerned with the schmuck daredevil teen looking for the viral selfie penetrating what really should be a secured area?
GUTFELD: You know, I've got three quick points to make. One, if he died, the family would sue.
TANTAROS: Yes.
GUTFELD: He might have done us a favor by showing us that it is possible to do something like that. I hate dare devils because we always have to bail them out.
The real daredevils in New York City are people who try to open up small businesses. They take a lot more grief.
And that's all I have, I think.
BOLLING: Thoughts? It's two-fold, the selfie and also breaking into the Freedom Tower.
TANTAROS: Yes, it could be a good thing, but then again, I hate when the media covers these stories because I feel like it gives our enemies an opportunity to go, oh, really, how many years later and they still don't have their act together?
And, again, if he would have fallen, it would have been, who was at fault? What security guard was asleep at the switch? And really, this is a kid who -- I mean --
BECKEL: It's the most video and sensitive security operation of any building in America, probably the world, and none of them were turned on.
PERINO: Incredible.
BOLLING: Good point. Dana?
PERINO: I was kind of speechless. I was thinking of a good explanation that would help us all understand it, but I think there's really no good excuse.
BOLLING: All right. That's leaves us with a little extra time for this one. I want to save some time. Watch this incredible performance from "The Voice" of Italy. Pay particular attention to the reaction of the judges when they find out exactly who was bringing the house down with her rendition of Alicia Keys' "No One."
(VIDEO CLIP PLAYS)
BOLLING: All right. Dana, let's start with you.
PERINO: I loved it. I loved watching "The Voice" here. I think it's an excellent show. Part of it is the judges' interaction and their reaction. It's great.
BOLLING: How about the singing nun?
GUTFELD: She's fine, but I have to disagree with Dana. This proves in every single country, the judges on these shows are complete tools.
PERINO: Why? How does it prove that?
GUTFELD: Look at them. They're tools. They're 49-year-old men dressed like 22-year-olds.
BOLLING: Like Red Hot Chili Peppers.
GUTFELD: Look at that. Come on, look at that.
BOLLING: Andrea, your thoughts on the singing nun?
TANTAROS: I wondered what they did all that time. They can't be praying. They have to do other stuff. Sister act, right?
(CROSSTALK)
BOLLING: Sister act -- Bob, you like it?
BECKEL: I liked it a lot. Who was that woman who did it on "Britain's Got Talent"? Who was it?
PERINO: Susan Boyle.
BECKEL: Yes, and that was -- remember the judges' reaction to that. They were just all shocked when she sang (INAUDIBLE)
GUTFELD: I'm tired of the shock. I don't care.
BECKEL: Well, we do. Boo!
BOLLING: All right, we're going to leave it there. They're saying, get out of here.
All right. Ahead, a lesson from Professor Gutfeld on what's cool and what's not cool in life. He spells it all out in his new book. He'll have the footnotes for us, coming up next.
GUTFELD: I always wonder why someone becomes an angry activist or a violent radical, but why do we become anything? To be liked or to be more precise, to be cool.
I can think of five stupid things I have done to be cool. They were all haircuts in the '80. But the desire to be cool always ends badly. For cool trumps the idea of good and evil. Cool things not be effective to be cool. See the White House.
This book tracks cool toxic effects as it permeates every part of our life. Whenever there's insecurity and weakness, cool will flourish.
Look at politics, media, pop culture, the work place, the college campus. There the cool try to subvert success, believing that chaos trumps character.
Progressive to its core, it's about undoing what came before, offering no alternative except surrender. Subversion is the prevailing wisdom of the media academic complex, Bob, and it's designed to undermine the thing they truly hate, which is American greatness.
My book attempts to expose this phenomenon and help you reclaim the real American ideal of cool, which is building businesses, protecting freedom at home and abroad, taking responsibility for your action and leaving other people alone to live at they damn well please.
That may be mocked by the currently cool, but this book is not for them, it's for you -- the decent person who must endure the cool's actions every day. You do it with dignity, making you far more cooler than they'll ever be.
BECKEL: Did you pay for advertising fee for that?
GUTFELD: Yes, I did, Bob.
PERINO: In blood.
GUTFELD: All right. So, Dana, you're interviewing me next week --
PERINO: Yes.
GUTFFELD: -- at the George W. Bush Library. So, you get the first question.
PERINO: OK. That would be next Thursday and I'm looking forward to it. You better be ready.
GUTFELD: I will be ready. I'll be done with this cough, I hope.
PERINO: OK, we have shared something this week.
I have a question -- this is your sixth book you have written.
GUTFELD: Yes.
PERINO: What you try to do is look at trends and then you tease it out like "Joy of Hate", now on "Not Cool". But could there be a trend of a backlash against being cool?
GUTFELD: I think so. When you think about the fact that the parents now -- parents are still trying to cling to being cool. Wouldn't the kids rebel against that? If your father is walking around in board shorts and a wallet chain and has tattoos all over his forearms and a nose ring, aren't you going to end up looking like Tucker Carlson? Your kid is going to be a little Tucker Carlson?
I hope so. We need more little Tucker Carlsons.
PERINO: With the bow tie.
GUTFELD: Yes.
Eric?
BOLLING: My question?
GUTFELD: Yes.
BOLLING: So, clearly, I'm not in the book. If the book is called "Not Cool", that's a good thing.
GUTFELD: Exactly.
BOLLING: Can I assume I'm cool then?
GUTFELD: Yes, you can. You can. But I don't like the word cool. I like good.
See, the whole point about, the bad thing about cool is that it negates the idea of good and evil because cool -- anything bad can be cool. So I would rather say you're good as opposed to cool.
BOLLING: Can I expand that a little bit? Hipsters are not cool, or the way they're acting is not cool, but don't the Republican -- doesn't the right need a cool -- to become cooler?
GUTFELD: Yes, they need a sense of humor. So they can go have fun and be less the moralistic Republican stereotype, I think. But I don't know if that -- again, that's not cool. That's just good.
BECKEL: But you -- you continue to support the free market system and all that.
GUTFELD: Yes.
BECKEL: The cool is -- makes a lot of money. Isn't that true? I mean, these cool trends, they sell a lot of things. They do a lot of these stars and stuff. They make a whole lot of money. I mean, it sort of runs a little counter, doesn't it, to where the markets are today?
GUTFELD: I don't -- I think, again, if you use the phrase -- if something good sells, then it's because it's good. There are a lot of things that are cool that sell that are bad. So you're right there.
BECKEL: Really?
TANTAROS: Wow.
BECKEL: I give you that point. Andrea.
TANTAROS: I would like to point out that I started chapter one, and I love it. I also believe that this doubles as a piece of artwork like the Mona Lisa. It looks like Greg, no matter where you put the book, is looking at you from any angle. So it's pretty amazing.
GUTFELD: And there's a microchip that records everything that's going on in your room. Anyway.
TANTAROS: OK, going to delete that last night.
OK, Greg. So how do we get back, then? Because when I think of cool, what's cool now -- facial hair and multiculturalism -- it reminds me of talking about these aging rock stars, right? They make a lot of money and then they look ridiculous, like the Madonnas of the world. Eventually, will it be cyclical? I mean, will we get back to hard work and the military being cool again? How do we do it?
GUTFELD: I think -- I think we have no choice. Because he only way that cool can exist is if the not-cool actually create successful things so they may survive. So sooner or later, they're going to run out of stuff, and it's going to be the not-cools that take over the world.
They're yelling at me.
TANTAROS: I like it.
GUTFELD: Coming up, Twitter turned eight today. And to celebrate its birthday, we're going to look back at each of our first tweets. Isn't that exciting? Bob is still trying to figure out how to send them out. That's next.
BECKEL: Quite true.
PERINO: Eight years ago today, Twitter was born. And to mark the blue bird's birthday, the social networking site has launched a new tool that allows users to find their very first tweet. So we're going to have some fun and look back on ours.
And I wanted to start with Eric, because you were the earliest adopter of all of us here to go on Twitter. October, 2008. But it's a strange message. You said, "Yes, well, what do you expect?"
BOLLING: Right.
PERINO: What were you talking about?
BOLLING: You just asked me, and I was trying to think back. What was happening October 2008. You know what was happening October 2008? We were about to elect Senator Obama, President Obama, so it was probably some commentary on something he was saying at the time.
TANTAROS: You had a premonition.
PERINO: Greg, yours is weird. It says, "I am playfully tugging at a pimple on my neck while it helps me find affordable auto insurance on the web," which is weird because you don't have a driver's license.
GUTFELD: I know. This was actually a secret code. You take every fourth letter and put it together, it's my exact address. Come on over.
PERINO: Andrea, yours was, "I'll be live blogging tonight. Obama press event." And then you had the little URL for that. And that was April of 2009.
TANTAROS: What a loser. Nothing better to do? No, I was helping FOX News Channel like a dedicated busy little bee, helping the dot.com try and launch those online chats.
PERINO: Mine kind of pathetic. It was a promotion of an article that I wrote for "National Review." It was called "NRO's The Corner: Glass Houses." And I went back and read that piece that I wrote. It was really terrible. I don't know what I was thinking; I don't know what I was writing.
TANTAROS: Nice title, though.
PERINO: Bob, yours was late. September 10, 2011, but it was done right here at the table of "The Five."
BECKEL: That's because you all taught me how to do it, because I had no idea.
PERINO: And it said, "FOX 'The Five' continues to grow audience. We thank you." Now, two years later, you could still write that, because we keep growing.
BECKEL: That's correct, and I wanted to put that marker down. And it continues to grow. It does continue to grow. Thank you all out there very much.
But I still -- the reason -- people say why don't you do more tweeties, whatever they're called. And I still don't -- I still don't know how to do it, but I don't, and I really don't that have much to say about it. And I'm glad the rest of you tweet.
TANTAROS: And that was the last time you tweeted, too? That was your first and your last?
BECKEL: One thing I did do, I tweeted a woman. I thought it was an individual one where you can tweet one person. I sent it out to the whole network.
PERINO: Oh, wow. Be careful with that, Bob.
BOLLING: That happens a lot.
PERINO: Ask Anthony Weiner.
Anyway, I was a reluctant tweeter, but I love it now. I found a way to make Twitter work for me.
GUTFELD: Good for you. We're so proud.
PERINO: Right. "One More Thing" is up next.
BECKEL: All right, time for "One More Thing" -- Andrea.
TANTAROS: Well, Eric Bolling got a haircut yesterday. And as I walked into the room where we get our hair done, it seems all the hair girls were talking about a look that he was going for. See if you can guess the look that Eric Bolling is going for. Is it, A, Jay Carney? Is it B, Harry Reid -- or John Boehner, I should say? Or is it C, Ronald Reagan?
PERINO: I like the Reagan one.
TANTAROS: What do you think? Tweet me your response, @AndreaTantaros. Whose hair does Eric Bolling look like?
BECKEL: All right. All right, Eric.
Speaking about something, answer your own question.
BOLLING: I know who I wanted to be like of those four. I clearly would be the Reagan one of them.
OK. Tomorrow morning, "Cashin' In," 11 a.m. Eastern. Big one tomorrow, we're going to talk about whether America is still a superpower or not. Is President O. doing everything in his power to make -- even the playing field globally, taking us away from superpower status? While President Putin is carving up the globe, President Obama is hanging out with, I don't know, basketball players.
BECKEL: Are you done with that -- Dana.
BOLLING: What the heck is that?
PERINO: Geez, Bob.
BECKEL: I got even with you.
PERINO: You remember the other day when I talked about Children's National, which is a hospital that Bret Baier and his son, Paul, are doing a big charity thing for. There's a celebrity auction. And it was a silent auction. You go online and you do it.
Well, there was a lunch with the "Special Report" panel. And that includes Charles Krauthammer, Juan Williams, Kirsten Powers and Jonah Goldberg. It was for $3,600 at the time. Twenty-four hours later, it closed at $26,000.
TANTAROS: Wow. That's awesome.
PERINO: And to show you how popular it is compared to other shows, "Morning Joe's" live broadcast, $2,000; Politico, a day with them, $1,000; and CBS "Face the Nation," behind the scenes, $1,050. So by 26 times.
BOLLING: Who overpaid for "Morning Joe"? That's ridiculous.
BECKEL: There you go. OK, Greg, what have you got?
GUTFELD: They thought it was something else. A thousand for the morning show. Oh, that's a talk show? I thought it was a massage.
Oh, tonight, I'm on "Greta" at -- between 7 and 8, and then "FOX & Friends tomorrow, pretty early, around the 7 a.m. -- 6:40, 7 a.m. And then I'm on Howie Kurtz's show, "Media Buzz," Sunday at 11 a.m., so I'm a busy little beaver this weekend.
BECKEL: OK. On this day, March 21, 1965, Dr. Martin Luther King led the march from Selma to Birmingham, which was the largest and most violent march to get civil rights -- voting rights for blacks in the south. I'm proud to say my dad was in that group.
But what's not known is the two marches that were held before Dr. King joined them. And the punks -- and the punks and the Gestapo from the police department down there beat people in some cases, killed a minister. They're bums. I hope you're all gone now.
But congratulations for Dr. King doing it. Congratulations. A year later, they signed...
PERINO: Happy Friday.
BECKEL: There you go -- OK, signed the bill. Happy Friday. DVR this show. What do you want? And Bret Baier is up next.
]]></text></news-item>