<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-BD01-F091-R4B7"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Vele accord 'too late as damage is done'</title><source>The Star (South Africa)</source><author> Sheree Bega</author><text><![CDATA[A BiODIVERSITY offsets agreement intended to minimise a controversial coal mine's effects on the sensitive landscape of Mapungubwe is a poor example for such accords because the environmental damage has been done.
This has been said by Jeff Manuel, who is developing the draft biodiversity offset policy framework for the Department of Environmental Affairs.
He was commenting on the agreement to be signed on Tuesday by CoAL of Africa, the department and SANParks, for the Vele colliery. The agreement was "retrofitting" the company's environmental effects.
"The less we look at the Vele colliery as an example of what good practice should be, the better," Manuel said.
"CoAL commenced mining illegally before their impacts could be properly assessed. Their application arose from a transgression.
"We'd ideally like to have pushed them to minimise their impacts on the environment first. But in this case, those impacts have already happened."
The Mapungubwe National Park, near Musina, is the site of the ancient Kingdom of Mapungubwe, which predates that of Great Zimbabwe.
Since 2010, in a protracted legal battle, the Save Mapungubwe Coalition has argued that CoAL's open cast coal mine - 6km from the borders of the park - and adjacent to the World Heritage Site, would destroy the unique and sensitive landscape in which Vele's mining area falls.
The biodiversity offset agreement is aimed at maintaining the integrity of the site, and ensuring that the negative effects of CoAL's activities are "avoided, minimised or remedied in the pursuit of sustainable development".
The SA National Biodiversity Institute (Sanbi) says biodiversity offsets involve offsetting, or compensating, for the unavoidable loss of biodiversity caused by some developments by securing equivalent biodiversity elsewhere.
Some experts say such agreements are a licence for developers to trash the environment. In November, more than 140 environmental and development organisations, including Friends of the Earth, stated that offsetting would not tackle biodiversity loss but could impoverish communities.
"Destroying one forest or river with a promise of protecting another fails to recognise they are part of a wider ecosystem and intrinsic to human and cultural landscapes."
Manuel, the deputy director of biodiversity policy advice at Sanbi, said although biodiversity offsetting agreements were a tool in their infancy in South Africa, the need for a regulated policy framework was urgent.
"Offsets are increasingly being authorised and implemented... The real test sits in compliance and enforcement.
"The capacity within government to do compliance monitoring and enforcement is weak.
"That is something we need to substantially invest in as a society if we're serious about maintaining a level of ecological integrity in our landscapes. It's also about making sure development happens in the socially, environmentally and ecologically responsible manner that we planned them to because otherwise we're investing a ton of money into doing assessments, but for what purpose?"
Melissa Fourie, director of the Centre for Environmental Rights, believes biodiversity offsets are "exceptionally open to abuse".
"We've seen cases in Mpumalanga where, as a mining company, you can get your authorisation here in this wetland, if you do an offset in a similar wetland close by, but there is no assessment of what is the appropriate offset, or whether an offset is even appropriate. You are salving your conscience by doing something for the environment."
In a letter to the Centre for Environmental Rights - which is representing the Save Mapungubwe Coalition - in December, Molewa said the agreement with CoAL was "complex... (as) biodiversity offsets are a relatively new area for the department. The department's view is that CoAL is not in non-compliance following the agreement recently reached."
Onno Huyser, senior programme manager at WWF-SA for the fynbos-succulent Karoo biomes, said biodiversity offsets should not be used in cases where unique or irreplaceable values were at risk.
"You can't replace pristine wetlands, which provide a unique hydrological function or flood prevention, or systems that have a unique population of insects, birds and wildlife. I think we should be much more strategic in securing these areas from the outset. These are areas where we should not be considering development or talking about offsets."
Biodiversity offsets were a legitimate and potentially valuable way to achieve balance between developments and biodiversity outcomes, "provided they meet certain criteria".
"The reality is that developers and mining companies are getting away with murder. We've had many examples where suspect authorisations have been made, or people have exceeded the conditions and got away with it."
]]></text></news-item>