<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-YH01-F08V-6201"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Lawyers studying potential effects of $1.2B Toyota penalty on lawsuit </title><source>Flint Journal (Michigan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[URL: http://www.mlive.com/news/flint/index.ssf/2014/03/too_soon_to_tell_if_toyotas_12.html
By Gary Ridley
gridley@mlive.com
Attorneys are working to evaluate whether a criminal charge and $1.2 billion penalty against Toyota over accusations it misled the public and investigators about unintended acceleration will have any effect on a Genesee County lawsuit stemming from the death of a 77-year-old woman.
The U.S. Department of Justice announced the charge and financial penalty against the auto manufacturer Wednesday, but attorneys for the estate of a Flint woman, who they claim died from a crash resulting from unintended acceleration, said it still is too soon to tell how the announcement will affect their case.
"We're grateful for the work the Justice Department did," West Virginia-based attorney Benjamin Bailey said. "We're studying and accessing if it will have an impact on the allegations in our case."
Bailey is one of a number of attorneys representing the estate of 77-year-old Guadalupe Alberto. The attorneys claim a sensor in Alberto's vehicle might have contained a "tin whisker" -- a small, electrically conductive outcropping -- that caused her vehicle to accelerate.
They also are exploring possible problems with the vehicle's software system.
The penalty announced by the Justice Department addressed only unintended acceleration caused by accelerator pedals being trapped by floor mats and mechanical problems that caused accelerators to be stuck in the depressed position -- not the vehicles' electronic systems.
Toyota denied tin whiskers played a role in any of the unintended acceleration cases.
2008 crash
Alberto's 2005 Toyota Camry careened at 80 mph down West Copeman Boulevard in Flint on April 19, 2008, weaving in and out of traffic before hitting a tree, sending her vehicle airborne. The car eventually smashed into another tree, hitting it 8 feet off the ground and killing her instantly.
Secretary of Transportation Ray LaHood said in 2011 that teams from NASA and the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration concluded there was no electronics-based cause for the high-speed acceleration in vehicles.
But the talk of tin whiskers picked up again after a separate team of NASA scientists published a study that said a tin whisker-induced short was responsible for the failure of an acceleration sensor in a 2003 Toyota Camry.
Sen. Charles Grassley, R-Iowa, also called for tin whiskers to be looked into in a letter he wrote to the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration in July 2012.
"So-called 'tin whiskers' are not a new phenomenon and do not represent a mysterious or undetectable problem in a vehicle's electronics," Toyota wrote in a statement following Grassley's letter. "Indeed, no data indicates that tin whiskers are more prone to occur in Toyota vehicles than any other vehicle in the marketplace.
"Further, no one has ever found a single real-world example of tin whiskers causing an unintended acceleration event, nor have they put forth any evidence of unintended acceleration occurring in a Toyota vehicle because of tin whiskers forming inside an accelerator pedal position sensor."
Record penalty
Toyota's $1.2 billion penalty -- the largest penalty of its kind levied against an automotive manufacturer -- stems from a charge Toyota defrauded consumers in 2009 and 2010 by issuing misleading statements about unintended acceleration issues in its vehicles.
Federal authorities said the auto manufacturer also took steps to hide the defects from National Highway Traffic Safety Administrator investigators.
"Toyota stands charged with a criminal offense because it cared more about savings than safety and more about its own brand and bottom line than the truth," U.S. Attorney Preet Bharara for the Southern District of New York said in a statement. "In its zeal to stanch bad publicity in 2009 and 2010, Toyota misled regulators, misled customers, and even misstated the facts to Congress.
"The tens of millions of drivers in America have an absolute right to expect that the companies manufacturing their cars are not lying about serious safety issues, are not slow-walking safety fixes and are not playing games with their lives. Companies that make inherently dangerous products must be maximally transparent, not two-faced. That is why we have undertaken this landmark enforcement action. And the entire auto industry should take notice."
The agreement between Toyota and federal authorities includes a stipulation that calls for prosecutors to dismiss the criminal charge if the auto manufacturer makes the required monetary payment, abides by the terms of the agreement and continues to cooperate with the government.
"At the time of these recalls, we took full responsibility for any concerns our actions may have caused customers, and we rededicated ourselves to earning their trust," Christopher Reynolds, chief legal officer of Toyota Motor North America, said in a statement. "In the more than four years since these recalls, we have gone back to basics at Toyota to put our customers first."
The case over Alberto's death is scheduled to proceed to trial May 6 in front of Genesee Circuit Judge Archie Hayman.
The Alberto family is suing Toyota Motor Company over this 2008 crash that killed Guadalupe Alberto, 77.
@crime-flintjournal @fl-river flint crime
]]></text></news-item>