<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT4-W1V1-DYBK-D29N"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>ISNR 2014 to Kick off early April</title><source>Emirates News Agency</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[WAM ABU DHABI, 22nd March, 2014 (WAM)--The 6th edition of the International Exhibition for Security and National Resilience (ISNR Abu Dhabi 2014) will kick off on 1st April, under the patronage of H.H. Sheikh Hazza bin Zayed Al Nahyan, National Security Advisor and Vice Chairman of Abu Dhabi Executive Council The event is organised by the Ministry of Interior in Abu Dhabi, in cooperation with REED Exhibitions at the Abu Dhabi National Exhibition Centre (ADNEC).
Major General Staff Dr. Obeid Al Kutbi, Deputy Commander-in-Chief of Abu Dhabi Police Chairman of the Higher Organising Committee, stressed that "ISNR Abu Dhabi 2014 is a prominent event on the calendar for global security and safety events in the MENA region. It provides public and private sector decision-makers with the most recent concepts and technologies in the field of security and protection of vital properties and facilities, in addition to the readiness and response to emergencies and hazard prevention." He added, "Abu Dhabi ISNR 2014 is an important platform to exchange ideas and experiences in the presence of the world's elite experts and specialists in this field, and to follow up with the latest achievements in the fields of security." Al Kutbi noted that this international biannual event, hosted by the UAE, has become an important platform to showcase state-of-the-art technologies and services in the fields of national security, protection of vital facilities, firefighting and emergency response, pointing out that the exhibition features 7 events, with the participation of more than 400 exhibitors from 40 countries.
It is also expected to host over 150 senior regional and international government buyers and official delegations from more than 20 countries. ISNR Abu Dhabi's 6th edition will also be hosting 60 international expert lecturers in the field of security and safety, who will be taking part in the first edition of the International Conference on Security Challenges (ICSC), the first edition of the Occupational Safety and Health Middle East (OSH ME) and in the 5th International Conference on Digital Forensics and Cyber Crime.
Major General Al Kutbi said that ISNR Abu Dhabi 2014 and the collocated exhibitions, namely the Fire and Emergency Middle East (FEME) and the Occupational Safety and Health Middle East (OSH ME), are expected to attract more than 15,000 visitors from the public and private sectors in the region.
For his part, Colonel Mohammed Al Zaabi, Chairman of the MoI Pavilion Committee stressed that the ministry's participation at the exhibition comes as a response to the directives of the police command. "It reflects the leadership's strong belief in the importance of taking part at international exhibitions, to display state-of-the-art devices, equipment, machinery and technology used by its various security authorities. This participation also underscores the Ministry of Interior's keenness to keep abreast of the latest developments in terms of advanced devices and equipment used in the fields of security and safety," said Al Zaabi.
He added, "In today's world, exhibitions have become a major source of information. Taking part at such exhibitions allows exhibitors and visitors alike to get acquainted with the latest equipment and techniques devised in the security industry. It also allows exhibitors to assess products of other competitors, given the significant development in security industries in developed countries, as well as technical development".
Captain Mohammed Obeid Al Obaidly, Vice Chairman of the MoI Pavilion Committee said that the pavilion will be showcasing the various services offered by the ministry to the public. It will also display its developed programs, plans, sophisticated equipment and modern mechanisms used by these bodies in the various areas of work.
"Free registration will be open to all on the e-gate throughout the exhibition. New systems will be showcased at the exhibition, most notably police monitoring and GPS security tracking. Training courses on the black points system will also be held, with a view to acquaint the public with the proper methods to reduce their black points tally. The workshops will be held in the Ministry of Interior's pavilion auditorium, along with other lectures aimed at raising awareness on the risks of using the Internet and social networking sites," said Captain Al Obaidly.
The conference will host members from the judicial authority as well as police and security agencies, university professors, law and IT students, legal advisors in governmental agencies and non-governmental organisations, governmental and private technical institutions, and social institutions.
Top-level lecturers from the Arab, local, and international levels are set to participate in the conference to discuss various legislative aspects, implementation of laws, exchange of ideas and topics related to IT crimes.
According to a study conducted by global industry analysts at Frost '&' Sullivan, "the information technology (IT) security market in the Middle East is set to grow nearly 18 per cent until 2018. The study also indicated that, with persistent cyber attacks that aim to access critical and confidential data, sectors such as banking, government and defense, oil and gas sectors, online retail, and social media websites were among the most vulnerable to such attacks in the Middle East.
It confirmed that regulatory compliance as well as systems and data protection will require more investment in information security products.
WAM/Majok

]]></text></news-item>