<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT5-R011-DYNS-32XN"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>State regulators approve Duke Energy's plan for dam repairs</title><source>The Fayetteville Observer (Fayetteville, North Carolina)</source><author>Gregory Phillips, The Fayetteville Observer, N.C.</author><text><![CDATA[March 22--SANFORD -- Water flowing into the water system serving Lee County is being tested every four hours for elevated levels of metal from a nearby coal ash spill.
Through Friday, no problems had been found, said Victor Czar, public utilities director for the city of Sanford.
"We haven't seen any change in that number in quite some time," he said, "so we're feeling pretty good."
The city utility serves about 50,000 customers in Lee and Chatham counties.
Its water comes from an impoundment off the Cape Fear River created by the Buckhorn Dam.
The intake is just upstream from where Duke Energy was cited Thursday for pumping about 61million gallons of coal ash wastewater into a Cape Fear River tributary canal from two impoundments at a coal plant that was closed in 2012.
"The best we know, that's the only place it discharged," Czar said.
Sanford usually tests its water for conductivity daily. The test helps detect metal in the water. The city will continue testing every four hours through the weekend, Czar said.
Since the illegal pumping was detected and stopped, "you would think that the most potential hazard has passed," Czar said.
The city has a 60 million-gallon reservoir that could supply its customers for just more than a week if tests required the city to stop using river water.
"We've taken the precautions, been on the forefront and staying abreast of what's happened," City Manager Hal Hegwer said. "We're trying to make sure we're ahead of the curve and being just as responsible as we can be."
State regulators approved Duke Energy's emergency plans to start repairing an earthen dam at one of the coal ash ponds from which the wastewater was pumped.
It was built in 1985, and the other has been in place since 1978, according to the violation report.
The impoundments hold water mixed with coal ash, the waste generated by the conversion of coal into electricity.
The utility reported Thursday afternoon that a crack had formed in the dam.
The emergency plan approved Friday would use a bladder to stop water from exiting the pond through a pipe, and excavate and stabilize the damaged part of the dam to prevent further ruptures.
The state will require that Duke Energy start long-term repairs once the emergency work is complete.
Duke Energy is required to respond within 30 days to the citation for pumping the tainted water toward the river.
Lee County Manager John Crumpton said he hasn't heard much concern from residents, although a couple of county commissioners who knew about the local coal ash ponds asked if there had been any problems just a day before the news broke.
"On Monday night, to the best of our knowledge, the answer was no, there were no problems," Crumpton said. "It was kind of ironic they even brought it up."
Staff writer Gregory Phillips can be reached at phillipsg@fayobserver.com or 486-3596.
___ (c)2014 The Fayetteville Observer (Fayetteville, N.C.) Visit The Fayetteville Observer (Fayetteville, N.C.) at www.fayobserver.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>