<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT5-B1V1-JDKC-R36M"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Pakistan: PIA facing 1,000 court cases</title><source>Right Vision News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[KARACHI, March 22 -- The Pakistan International Airlines (PIA) is facing up to 1,000 court cases, which is a record number of cases against any government institution. One-fourth of the petitions are filed by PIA employees, challenging promotions, transfers, postings and seniority matters, involving nepotism.
The increase in litigation has been registered over the last few months while the national flag carrier has to spend a hefty sum of money on account of fees of lawyers representing it in courts.
Sources said that over a few past months, the current administration of the PIA has made many controversial decisions regarding promotion, postings and seniority matters on the basis of favouritism which has set off a wave of unrest among the employees.
When the administration refused to listen to them, they went to courts, they said. The administration has not even acted upon many court orders and as a result, the national flag carrier has been issued at least six contempt notices. They said the PIA has to hire a private law firm in addition to lawyers of its own Legal Department to defend itself in courts. The sources said the litigations will cost the PIA millions of rupees annually.
PIA spokesperson Mashood Tajwar said most petitions were filed by the employees who were given contracts and were then regularised over the years. He said these employees have issues regarding their seniorities and the number of petitions from PIA employees is 250.
PIA DG Legal Asim Rauf was not sure about the exact number of lawyers, the PIA has hired but admitted that it could be between 100 and 150. He said they pay lower fees to lawyers and no legal firm has been hired to defend the PIA
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Right Vision News. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>