<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT5-WWH1-JD6S-R0TS"><date>2014-03-22</date><title></title><source>The Times Reporter (New Philadelphia, Ohio)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NC pulls deal with Duke on coal ash pollution RALEIGH, N.C. North Carolina regulators say they have asked a judge to withdraw a proposed settlement that would have allowed Duke Energy to resolve environmental violations by paying a $99,000 fine with no requirement that the $50 billion company clean up its pollution.
The state Department of Environment and Natural Resources said in a statement Friday that it would scuttle the proposed consent order to settle violations for groundwater contamination leeching from coal ash dumps near Charlotte and Asheville. The decision comes after a Feb. 2 spill at a Duke coal ash dump in Eden coated 70 miles of the Dan River in toxic sludge.
Obama meeting with Internet CEOs on privacy WASHINGTON President Barack Obama is meeting with CEOs from leading Internet and technology companies to discuss their concerns about privacy and National Security Agency programs. The White House said Obama hosted the leaders Friday in the Oval Office.
The meeting comes two months after Obama gave a speech proposing changes to NSA spying programs following public and industry concern.
Families in Wis. crash that killed two girls sue GM DETROIT The families of three teenagers killed or injured in a 2006 Wisconsin car crash are suing General Motors.
Natasha Weigel and Amy Rademaker died after the crash, which involved a Chevrolet Cobalt. Megan Phillips was injured.
Last month GM recalled 1.6 million Cobalts and other small cars to replace faulty ignition switches. The company has admitted knowing of the problem for at least 11 years.
The switches can slip out of the run position, shutting down the car's engines. That can cut off power-assisted steering and brakes and cause drivers to lose control. It also disables the air bags.
THE ASSOCIATED PRESS
]]></text></news-item>