<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT5-FX71-DYTG-255J"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Five killed in skydive plane crash</title><source>Canberra Times (Australia)</source><author>EAMONN DUFF, ANNE TARASOV; and RORY CALLINAN</author><text><![CDATA[Five killed in skydive plane crash By EAMONN DUFF, ANNE TARASOV and RORY CALLINAN The crash site.Photo: Channel Nine Flames engulf the wreckage of the light plane at the Caboolture airfield in southern Queensland. Photo: Seven News FOUR men and a woman were killed on Saturday in a fiery plane crash at a Queensland airfield.
A male pilot, two skydiving instructors and two customers died when the Cessna 206 plummeted to the ground shortly after taking off at Caboolture Airport, near Brisbane, about 11.30am.
Moreton police region Superintendent Michael Brady said numerous onlookers had seen the light plane crash and then burst into flames.
The plane belonged to local skydiving company, Adrenalin Skydivers Bribie Island, which specialises in offering spectacular skydives from 4200 metres on to a beach at nearby Bribie Island.
But airport safety officer Bryan Carpenter, of Aerodynamic Flight Academy Caboolture, told reporters the plane had lurched sharply to its left after failing to reach 60metres, then dived onto a cross runway. Witnesses had raced to the scene but because of the presence of high-octane fuel fire swiftly consumed the wreckage.
Superintendent Brady confirmed the impact of the crash had been "unsurvivable".
"It's a tragedy for all people involved, particularly loved ones and family and, of course, people on the scene," he said.
He added investigations were continuing into the cause. Both Queensland Police Service forensic investigators and the Air Traffic Safety Bureau combed the remnants of the plane for clues.
Authorities had not released the registration of the ill-fated aircraft on Saturday but confirmed the aircraft was a Cessna 206.
Civil Aviation Safety Authority records list Adrenalin Skydivers Pty Ltd as operating a 36-year-old Cessna model U206G.
A Caboolture Aero Club spokesman said: "The aircraft cannot be identified at this time - and I'm standing 50 metres from it."
The small Caboolture airfield is one hour's drive north of Brisbane and well-known to commuters on the Bruce Highway as aircraft can often be viewed just above the roadway as they take off or land.
Gliders, helicopters and light aircraft are regular fixtures at the site, which has only grass airstrips and is also used by instructors.
Five years ago the Professional Pilots Rumour Network forum featured a running post criticising the airstrip as the "crappiest airfield" in Australia.
The post alleged the airfield was plagued with overgrown grass, bog holes, narrow taxiways and unmarked culverts. It also claimed ibis and kangaroos caused a permanent hazard.
The same contributor also highlighted other potential issues, including the presence of trees and powerlines at the end of the south-east runway. Another expressed concern about crosswinds, while a different pilot suggested the airfield was "cheaper" for pilots to use than more developed runways in the region.
However, a Caboolture Aero Club spokesman said there was no suggestion the tragedy on Saturday could be tied to the airfield.
"It's an uncontrolled airport with unsealed runways and, yes, there are kangaroos and birds," he said.
He said the safety surveyor who assessed the field each year believed it was "the best airfield on the east coast".
]]></text></news-item>