<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT5-5PB1-JCVR-R2KW"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Long Beach, L.A. ports truck drivers win settlement after threats against union organizing</title><source>Press - Telegram (Long Beach California)</source><author>Karen Robes Meeks</author><text><![CDATA[CARSON >> Port truck drivers won a National Labor Relations Board settlement with a Carson-based company after allegations surfaced that drivers were threatened and interrogated over union organizing, officials announced Friday.
The settlement, which affects drivers who haul goods from the ports of Long Beach and Los Angeles for Pacific 9 Transportation Inc., applies to allegations involving the company's conduct last fall, "including threats to employees to close the business and loss of their jobs if the International Brotherhood of Teamsters were to succeed in its organizational efforts; and interrogating employees about their union sympathies," according to the agreement by the NLRB.
At a press conference in front of Pac 9, supporters of the drivers and Teamsters on Friday called this a win in the fight tothe misclassification of port truck drivers as independent contractors, which they say allows trucking companies to skirt labor laws.
The settlement is an acknowledgement by the board and the company that the drivers were indeed employees subject to labor laws and the right to organize, supporters said.
"The 30-year debate is over. The misclassification lie has been busted. The port drivers are, in fact, employees," said Eric Tate, secretary-treasurer of Teamsters Local 848. "The NLRB has said so. ... Pac 9 has said so. Now every port truck driver who wants totheir sweatshop conditions can bargain collectively to climb the economic ladder into the middle class."
In a statement, the Carson-based company expressed its disappointment in the "intentional misrepresentation of this settlement by out-of-town interests with an economic stake in keeping this dispute from resolving."
"The reality is that the settlement of these administrative proceedings is just that - a settlement with no finding of fault, penalties or fines. Those who suggest otherwise are clearly exploiting the situation to serve their own political agenda. PAC 9 will continue to service its customers hand in hand with its contractors and will not allow this orchestrated political event to detract from our core business of moving goods. "
Since deregulation some 30 years ago, trucking companies have been moving toward hiring independent contractors over employee drivers. Unions, who cannot organize independent contractors, have argued that many trucking companies use independent contractor designation to avoid paying for benefits for employees, such as workers' compensation, overtime and the right to unionize.
"This is truly a historic occasion," said Carson City Councilman Mike Gipson, who attended the press conference. "Employees' rights are civil rights and now you can come out of the shadows no longer the port drivers, sharecroppers on wheels. ... This settlement between the NLRB and Pac 9 is a wake-up call to all companies, not only here in Carson but throughout the state of California."
Contact Karen Robes Meeks at 562-714-2088.
]]></text></news-item>