<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT5-1241-F0HW-520B"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>GM CEO Mary Barra To Testify at Congressional Hearing on April 1; Nine Killed By Taliban Militants in Kabul Hotel Gun Attack; President Obama</title><source>Finance Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[DAGEN MCDOWELL, FOX BUSINESS ANCHOR: Good morning, everybody. The hunt for the missing Malaysia Airline's jet continues today. Search planes and ships scouring a remote part of the Indian Ocean. So far turning up nothing. Some officials say even if that wreckage formed was the plane that was picked up by satellite, that debris has likely sunk by now, we may never know what happened to Flight 370.
In Kabul, Afghanistan, an attack on what was supposed to be the safest hotel in that city leaving more than a dozen people dead as the Taliban sets up efforts to disrupt that country's upcoming elections. And the nation's biggest banks get a clean bill of health as all but one of the 30 largest institutions passed the Federal Reserve's latest stress test results. Those results should be good news to investors and anybody with a bank account. Friday, March, 21st, and this is THE BEST OF IMUS IN THE MORNING along with the fabulous Lori Rothman.
LORI ROTHMAN, FOX BUSINESS ANCHOR: Back at you. How are you doing?
MCDOWELL: How are you doing?
ROTHMAN: I'm fine, great. Finally, they actually letting us be in the same room together.
MCDOWELL: Good morning.
ROTHMAN: Good morning.
MCDOWELL: So, you never know what this search of the plane, we could be getting all the breaking news in the coming hours.
ROTHMAN: The wreckage could be actually deeper than the titanic wreckage was found, so it's very upsetting.
MCDOWELL: But we'll also going to get plenty of Imus coming up, including the Imus interview with Greg Gutfeld and a funny story about the cat that the I-man used to own. And Lori, what are you looking at in terms of business news?
ROTHMAN: Well, you know, it's interesting. I think there's still sort of a ripple effect from Janet Yellen. A lot of debate and discussion over whether she made a big mistake by telling us when interest rates are going to rise, or if this is a new era of transparency and honestly by the Federal Reserve, so. There's a holiday in Japan, but European markets are a little higher, facing up perhaps for higher open this morning.
MCDOWELL: And we'll going to dig into that as well. As Lori is talking about those markets, let's just give you an update on how the world did and is doing. Asia already closed. And you can see the three major markets that were open. Japan closed. We're all higher. I mean, Shanghai up almost three percent. Now over no Europe, we have gains across the board in England, France, and Germany, and here in the United States, the futures, does the picture look pretty? Yes, it does. Forty five point gain on the Dow futures, and then over to the two major commodities that we always watch, oil and gold, both heading higher, gold up almost $7 an ounce.
ROTHMAN: Let's get a closer look at Asia now. For that, we go to business reporter Rachael Ruble who's standing by for us in Beijing. Rachael, good morning to you. What's behind the rally there?
RACHAEL RUBLE, BUSINESS REPORTER: Hi, Lori, good morning. Well, the Asian markets moved higher today, but it was actually a pretty quiet day over here because, as you said, Tokyo was closed for a three-day weekend. Shanghai stocks ended positive lead from the U.S., all helped Asian markets recover from yesterday's sharp selloff. Shanghai made back all of its losses and then some closing up almost three percent back over the 2,000 mark. Now Hong Kong shrugged off concerns about weaker than expected earnings from several Chinese industries, industry giants, and slow down in the Chinese economy. The Hang Seng closing up more than one percent. Seoul up almost one percent. Tokyo, again, closed for the day because of the vernal equinox. Wait until Monday to see if they can make gains on the back of those rising U.S. stocks.
ROTHMAN: That's a holiday, huh? Who knew? You know, you have been reporting Rachael all week on Yuan and China expanding the trading range on the Yuan and its impacts, so it did fall pretty steadily in the wake of that happening, so how did the Yuan close out the week, and what should we expect for trade, really, in the week to come?
RUBLE: Yes, well, this was a really rough week for the Yuan. It's one of the worst weeks it had, I'm hovering now at a 13-month low, but you know, the people's Bank of China actually seems pretty comfortable with that. This morning, the Central Bank said the Yuan's midpoint weaker than yesterday's rate, and now, as you said, that on as of Monday, the daily trading ban is now two percent on either end of the daily pick things up from one percent. So, the fact that the Central Bank is setting in the midpoint to be lower actually shows that the Central Bank is pretty comfortable with the currency's fall. So, who knows, it might see a fall even further -- Lori.
ROTHMAN: Thank you so much, Rachael Ruble there for us in Beijing.
MCDOWELL: And for more on the European markets, let's go live to London where we're joined by Jan Randolph, director of Sovereign Risk at IHS Global. Jan, it's great to see you. What is the reason for the optimism that we are seeing in Europe today?
JAN RANDOLPH, SOVEREIGN RISK AT IHS GLOBAL DIRECTOR: I think it's on the back of U.S. news, but, also, there was some positive industrial numbers from Italy showing that the economy might be firming there, the recovery. But I think all eyes are really on Moscow and Russia today up the second round of sanctions yesterday to include a broader -- of Russian politicians and business elites, Moscow market was down, financing is a little bit more expensive, and some of the European-Russian stocks were hit despite the gains in Europe.
MCDOWELL: Why aren't we seeing more trepidation, if you will, in the broader European markets because of that? Like, are people ignoring potential problems?
RANDOLPH: Well, I think what's happening is, certainly, from western banks, preparing for the worst, by running off their loans and bonds to Russian counter parties, lowering their exposures, basically. Throughout the moments, sanctions are really at the political level affecting individuals and one or two banks, a study from the U.S. side in their sanctions, but it has not really affected underlying trade yet, and that's the key question. I think Germany's going through -- going to resist that until Russia de-escalates, or if they mount an invasion of Eastern Ukraine, that would take us into yet another round of sanctions to include economics.
MCDOWELL: Jan, it was great to see you, always great to talk to you, thank you so much for the insight as always. Have a terrific weekend.
RANDOLPH: Thank you.
MCDOWELL: Jan Randolph of IHS Global Insight.
ROTHMAN: And he's leaving, Dagen. You were talking earlier, and how we always bolt. He was ripping off the microphone.
MCDOWELL: Got to go, got to go, and you're, like, thanking him. Sorry.
ROTHMAN: Actually he paused before, you know --
MCDOWELL: I do not want to make fun of him because he will not come back on.
ROTHMAN: All right. Let's get you updated on the markets here in the U.S., what we should expect with the move today with Nicole Petallides, live for us at the New York Stock Exchange.
NICOLE PETALLIDES, FOX BUSINESS ANCHOR: Well, stocks on Wall Street had a great day on Thursday, the Dow Jones industrials gaining about 100 -- almost 109 points, closing at 16331, the NASDAQ and the S&P also had up arrows, the NASDAQ was up almost 12 points, 4319 and the S&P 500 up over 11 points closing at 1872. So, gains across the board. The volatility still here for the year 2014, and this week, no doubt, we've seen that. We actually, on Thursday, saw that we started off in the red, and then the good Philly Fed number pushed the markets into the green now.
On Friday's trading today, we'll be watching some action and don't forget, the stock market is still doing well this week, up about one and a half percent or more for all the major averages this week. So, we'll be watching some key things as well. The home builders, yesterday, dropped off, but, today, we'll see if they can turn it around, the existing sales home numbers pushed those into the red. We'll get a lot of Fed speaks today on the docket including from the Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis. President James Bullard and Dallas Fed President Richard Fisher, so we'll be watching to see if we get any news out of some of the Fed speak today.
Banks, many of which hit some record highs yesterday, JP Morgan, Wells Fargo, Bank of America just to name a few, we'll be watching that group very closely, and Mark Newton over at Greywolf Execution Partners saying he likes the group in the short term, even naming some of the regional names in particular, such as regions financial, Zion, BBNC (ph) as some of his favorites. But not too much for economic news in the docket for Friday. On the floor of the exchange, I'm Nicole Petallides, back to you.
MCDOWELL: Thank you, Nicole. For some good news from the Federal Reserve, the stress tests conducted on the nation's largest bank showed, they can now easily withstand a hypothetical economic meltdown, even worse than the one back in 2008. With more on those results, we go to Peter Barnes who joins us from Washington.
PETER BARNES, FOX BUSINESS ANCHOR: Well, all but one of the top 30 U.S. and foreign banks with major U.S. operations have passed the latest stress test from the Federal Reserve. These are the big banks with more than $50 billion in assets, all of the top banks passed as expected. Zion's bank corp was the only bank that would have less than the projected necessary capital by the end of 2015, but Fed officials stressed the giants still has time to fix this through its capital plans. The top performers under the stress test were State Street, Discover Financial, and bank of New York Melon. Under Dodd-Frank financial reform, the Fed must estimate whether the biggest banks could survive and continue to operate in another terrible financial crisis and recession.
So, the taxpayers don't have to bail them out again. The stress test, this time around, says they would lose $366 billion on their loans as a group through the end of 2015 under this difficult scenario, about 500 billion including trading losses, but despite that, as a group, they would survive the shock, the Fed says, because they have been beefing up capital since the crisis. The 30 banks in aggregate would still end up with tier one common capital, the strongest form of shareholder equity of 7.6 percent. By the end of 2015, they would be required to have at least five percent tier one capital. Back to you.
MCDOWELL: Thank you so much, Peter, and Lori Rothman now has some business headlines for us.
ROTHMAN: I do, indeed. Speaking of those stress tests, one bank is looking to take advantage right away. Credit card companies Discover Financial proposing a 20 percent increase in its dividend up to $1.6 billion in the stock buyback. This comes as Discover easily passed the stress test. Discover still needs Fed approval, however, for those moves. The company's benefited from more rapid loan growth expanding its lending offerings with student loans, mortgages, and home equity loans. Shares of Discover rose in extended trading.
That a couple of key earnings for you today. Let's get you to Darden Restaurants expected to report a profit of 82 cents a share on revenue of $2.2 dollars. Analysts estimate Tiffany will come in at $1.52 cents a share and 1.3 billion in revenue. We, of course, have those numbers for you as soon as they cross the wire. General Motors continue our coverage here, CEO Mary Barra set to testify now at a Congressional hearing, the date for that is April 1st as the House Energy and Commerce Committee continues its investigation into its GM's delayed recall related to faulty ignition switches. The company says, at least 12 people were killed in accidents linked to the problem. This week, Barra apologized for the deaths and named a new head of global safety. Dagen, that's it for now.
MCDOWELL: And of course, we have some I-man for you, the I-man's health, always a topic of conversation here on IMUS IN THE MORNING, and he thinks even if things got worse, his family would never put him on a home, but one particular day, Rob and Tony hinted that that might not be the case. What do we make of that? Listen to this.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
DON IMUS, HOST, "IMUS IN THE MORNING": So I'm talking to Rob and Tony, and they are threatening to -- that I'm going to wind up in a home.
CONNELL MCSHANE, FOX BUSINESS ANCHOR: Uh-huh. Right.
IMUS: And I said, Deirdre and Wyatt promised me that they would not out me in a home. And they won't. I can guarantee that.
MCSHANE: Yes.
IMUS: And we got to talking about Michael Lynn and Robert and Vinnie Andrews, who I have been with over 40 years. The Andrew Brothers handle the finances for me, Deirdre, the Imus ranch, and other stuff, but they're my age, and Michael Lynn is my age, couple years younger, so I won't have them there, but I -- as long as I have Deirdre and Wyatt -- well, here's what Deirdre gets out of that. I get this text from her, so you're debating whether you're paid employees, Andrews and Lynn, should be more trusted than me and Wyatt? No, no, who said that?
MCSHANE: I don't know.
IMUS: And if your wife who is part of the show, by the way, listens and watches this and can't get it straight, who can?
MCSHANE: I don't know. Wow.
IMUS: You know whose fault that is? Your fault, you two.
TONY POWELL, COMEDIAN: How?
IMUS: Because you suggested if they were both Deirdre and Wyatt were both going to stick me in a home.
BARTLETT: You assured us that that was not going to happen, and all we said was "Get it in Writing."
IMUS: What?
BARTLETT: Get it in writing.
IMUS: I don't need it and writing for Deirdre and Wyatt.
POWELL: So, I just asked you what you think Deirdre said, the Collins on the ride over to the vet's office that day, what do you think she told Collins? Oh, no, no, you're coming back home, you'll be fine. Don't worry about it. Just go in the box with the nice man. Was that the conversation?
IMUS: You're an evil bastard. Collins was my Himalayan blue point cat that I had for 18 years. What's the matter, Dagen?
MCDOWELL: This is just not going to end well, but go on with your bad self.
MCGUIRK: Tony suggesting that let's put you in a hole, instead of a home.
IMUS: When I was drinking vodka, and lived in Aster Place and the penthouse there, I was the only one who ever lived in the apartment. It was brand new. And I never left food out, ever, and I was lying there one night drinking vodka, reading, and I was reading -- in fact, and I looked up, and a mouse ran across the room. And I thought, I was not sure it was a mouse, but maybe I was drinking too much vodka.
(LAUGHTER)
So it was shortly after that that I got myself in such shape, but I had to go to rehab which I did, Hazelton down in West Palm Beach. This was July 17, 1987. So, I was gone six to eight weeks, and I got back to the apartment something fast-forward a week or two and I land there again reading something. But this time, I wasn't drinking any vodka. And I looked, and a mouse ran across the room. So, I bought Collins, a little kitty. I got Collins, and Collins got the mouse out of there, and Collins slept on my head for -- until I met Deirdre, and then Collins was so pissed off that Deirdre entered the equation, that she got under the bed and she came out about five years later, and then she ignored me for the rest of her life, and attached herself to Deirdre.
So, when she got to be 18 years old and she was -- couldn't walk, we took her out to see the worst veterinarian on God's earth, Bernadette Caster's (ph) hideous son-in-law, who --
ROB BARTLETT, COMEDIAN: Who folded the cat over one of the couches.
IMUS: And Deirdre took the cat out there, and they put the cat to sleep. And I buried the cat up in West Port. And they got a little gravestone for him and all that stuff, and I sold the property, praise God, and I know there's a God, and I sold it to a guy with a lot of money. He's going to need it. Anyway --
POWELL: Let me get this straight. So, when the cat got really old and couldn't walk, couldn't breathe, it was put to sleep?
IMUS: Right.
POWELL: How long does it take you to walk to the bathroom to here? I was just curious.
IMUS: Some days, I have to stop once, but Deirdre does everything she can to take care of me. Why do you think I'm able to battle success with this cancer? Because of her.
MCGUIRK: She took care of Collins too.
(LAUGHTER)
IMUS: No, the vet killed Collins. That was not Deirdre's idea.
POWELL: Oh.
WARNER WOLF, SPORTSCASTER: Hey, I-man.
IMUS: Yes.
WOLF: You know the headline of this whole story is?
IMUS: What?
WOLF: That first mouse may have saved your life. If you hadn't seen the mouse while you were drinking, who knows? Right?
MCGUIRK: Right.
WOLF: You said, you went to rehab after that.
(LAUGHTER)
IMUS: Well, no, I didn't go to rehab because I saw the -- here she is now. Now, here's an ugly text from her.
MCSHANE: That was really good.
IMUS: I did listen. You tend to be full of s, and why would you Tony or Rob even question it, and as far as Connell, the vet told you and me, she had complete kidney failure. Why didn't Deirdre call in? Doesn't she have a number?
MCSHANE: This is the modern way of doing it.
BARTLETT: She just realized we're not being serious, right?
IMUS: She says, I took the cat to the vet because you would not. Well, no because I felt bad about it.
MCSHANE: Yep.
IMUS: She said, when I met you I had to give up my dog and two cats.
MCGUIRK: That's in the all she had to give up.
IMUS: Well, this is going to be an ugly day today. Jesus, God!
BARTLETT: Two cats, a dog, and dignity.
IMUS: What an awful, I mean, get this, this is just not worth it.
MCSHANE: Off to a great start.
IMUS: Anyway, they're not going to put me in a home.
MCSHANE: OK.
BARTLETT: All right. Glad to hear it.
POWELL: OK.
MCSHANE: Settled that.
BARTLETT: Want to go for a ride, Don?
IMUS: She has no sense of humor. I have to deal with that. It's a joke!
All right. Please welcome to the program, Deirdre Imus.
MCSHANE: OK, good.
IMUS: Good morning, Mrs. Imus.
DEIRDRE IMUS, WIFE OF DON IMUS: Don't say "Good morning" now.
IMUS: What am I supposed to say?
DEIRDRE IMUS: Well, you just insulted me.
IMUS: How?
DEIRDRE IMUS: This -- I don't -- I don't even understand your train of thought, but maybe I do because it's very revealing.
IMUS: What did I say?
DEIRDRE IMUS: I mean, in Tony and Rob, they are just trying to be funny, of course.
IMUS: So am I.
DEIRDRE IMUS: But they are not funny, at all.
IMUS: Oh, that's nice. That's great.
DEIRDRE IMUS: I just really hope tonight because this helps the ranch too, I just hope they are funny. I really do.
(LAUGHTER)
MCSHANE: Great.
LOU RUFINO, PROGRAM ENGINEER: Have a good time, guys.
POWELL: Just trying to maintain that cover.
MCSHANE: I like it here.
DEIRDRE IMUS: I mean, this is just -- it's dreadful, and then you just go to the lowest of the low for what reason? Because you didn't even get any yucks out of it. You got nothing.
IMUS: What did I do?
DEIRDRE IMUS: I don't know. You have this bizarre -- like I just texted you back, I had to give up so much, just to be with you because you were -- you were a nightmare. I had to give up my two cats and my dog, and you go on about Collins who ended up loving me more than you.
IMUS: You're the one running around chasing me with a book full of naked pictures of yourself.
DEIRDRE IMUS: And you know what? Wyatt actually repeats that story because he thinks it's true.
(LAUGHTER)
You know, I hear his friends, and people come to the ranch, how did your mom and dad met? He says, oh, my mom was running around with a book full of naked pictures, and my dad thought she was cute.
IMUS: That's when you were a model, remember?
DEIRDRE IMUS: Don, I didn't have a book full of naked pictures.
IMUS: OK baby, whatever.
DEIRDRE IMUS: I had what they call a professional portfolio.
MCGUIRK: Tastefully Don.
IMUS: Tastefully Don. Yes, sure.
(LAUGHTER)
DEIRDRE IMUS: You're just awful.
IMUS: I love you, honey.
DEIRDRE IMUS: Well, OK. OK.
BARTLETT: Is that how you met Larry Flynt, I-man?
(LAUGHTER)
(END VIDEO CLIP)
MCDOWELL: Coming up, the very latest on this search for the Malaysia Flight 370 and an attack on what would supposed to be the safest hotel in Afghanistan leaves nine dead. A look at the markets and the weekend weather forecast is coming up from meteorologist Maria Molina. Don't go anywhere.
(COMMERCIAL BREAK)
MCDOWELL: Take a look at your markets around the globe. Japan closed with gains across the board in the three major markets that were open. Gains in Europe as well. We'll take a look at England, France, and Germany. Here in the U.S., futures are also pointing to a higher open, but we've got a ways to go, almost three hours from now, and then oil and gold are ticking up, by up $7.5 an ounce gain on gold now.
Some of the news stories, they're making headlines this morning. Search crews far into the Indian Ocean have spent the night looking for debris from missing Malaysia Air Flight 370, but so far, they have been unable to locate any. Doug Luzader has that story this morning from Washington.
DOUG LUZADER, FOX WASHINTON CORRESPONDENT: The one of the big problems here is how remote this part of the world is. Search aircraft, for instance, that are taking off from Australia, that is about a six to seven hour round trip out to the site of this search, and that leaves them precious little time to do any looking.
(BEGIN VIDEOTAPE)
(voice-over): The U.S. Navy's most advanced sub hunters, the P8 Poseidon is putting in some long hours. It and other aircraft are combing the Indian Ocean for some sign of the debris that was spotted by a satellite five days ago, almost 1500 miles offshore from Australia. Australian officials say, this is the best lead so far. One of those pieces measures nearly 80 feet. But even Australia's prime minister says it's entirely possible this could be just another dead end.
TONY ABBOTT, AUSTRALIAN PRIME MINISTER: It could just be a container that's fallen off a ship. We just don't know.
Meantime, tough questions for Malaysian officials who are managing the overall investigation. Why did they wait so long to pursue a lead that would eventually take search crews so far south? The company operating the satellite that continued to receive those signals from the plane for hours after it was otherwise lost says it turned over that data almost immediately.
CHRIS MCLAUGHLIN, SENIOR VP, INMARSAT: Saturday, when the plane went missing, we were asked whether we had any data relating to the flight, and within three hours to four hours, we have handed over the basic flight data information to the supplier of the avionics to the plane.
LUZADER: And that long delay could make finding any debris more difficult. Already search teams are battling spotty weather in the Indian Ocean.
RICH REICHMUTH, FOX NEWS METEOROLOGIST: Today's flight and to tomorrow's flight, weather is going to be looking pretty good for at least for that visual observation, and then things change again for about another 48 hours as the next storm moves on end.
(END VIDEOTAPE)
LUZADER: And whether may end up being a big factor here. These objects are not easy to spot, even in the satellite pictures, and they may have moved a fair distance from when these pictures were taken.
For the FOX Business Network in Washington, I'm Doug Luzader, back to you in New York.
MCDOWELL: Thank you, Doug. Taliban gunman killing nine people in an attack in a luxury hotel in Kabul Thursday night before being shot dead by security forces. The assault on the Serena Hotel is the latest in a string of bold attacks by insurgents seeking to disrupt the presidential election on April the 5th. It all started when four Taliban, gunman snuck past security and hid inside the hotel for three hours before opening fire on diners inside the hotel's restaurant. Guests hid in rooms or fled to hotel bunkers. Some 18 United States staffers were inside the hotel at the time of the attack and have all been accounted for.
Four of the nine people killed were from Canada, India, New Zealand, and Pakistan. Police are investigating how the gunman got into the heavily guarded hotel, which was considered the safest in Kabul. President Obama issuing new sanctions against Russian President Vladimir Putin and his inner circle after Russia voted Thursday to annex the Black Sea Peninsula of Crimea from Ukraine. The new U.S. sanctions target 20 officials and one bank. The individuals name by the treasury included Putin's chief of staff and his personal banker.
Russia responded with its own list of sanction targeting some U.S. Congressional leaders including House Speaker John Boehner, Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid, and Senator John McCain. After hearing the news, Senator McCain tweeted, I guess this means my spring break in Siberia is off. Gas from stock is lost. And secret bank account in Moscow is frozen.
As the crisis in Ukraine continues, the Russian prime minister is now saying Ukraine owes Russia $11 billion for a defunct gas deal. Russia had agreed to provide cheap gas to Ukraine for its use of those Sevastopol naval base in Crimea. However, on Thursday, Russia voted to admit Crimea in the city of Sevastopol into the Russian federation, making the deal, quote, "subject to denunciation and giving Russia the right to sue Ukraine."
Meanwhile, Ukraine's ambassador to the U.N. says, there are signs that Russia was preparing for further military intervention in the eastern regions, a claim denied by Moscow.
Senior officials announcing yesterday that the intelligence leaker Edward Snowden's claim of U.S. industrial espionage are false. With more on this, we turn to Rich Edson from our Washington Bureau.
RICH EDSON, FOX BUSINESS ANCHOR: Well, a senior U.S. intelligence official denies the U.S. government spies on foreign companies and gives valuable information to American companies. This after National Security Agency leaker Edward Snowden charged the U.S. with corporate espionage. Senior Intelligence official tells FOX News, the U.S. will target foreign companies or executives for national security purposes or targeting companies or executives as a way to broadly asses the country's economic capabilities and weaknesses. And one analyst says, there's a difference between that and what some governments in Europe and China do.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
CLAUDE BARFIELD, AMERICAN ENTERPRISE INSTITUTE: The key here is it was not, I think, to pass on information, competitive information, to U.S. corporations as we have -- as we strongly suspected the Chinese government does and some other governments have done. It's basically for some kind of intelligence operation.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
EDSON: The officials say U.S. intelligence will target officials working in sanctioned countries like Iran or North Korea, now Russia and help determine which sanctions would be most effective or if they are working. Back to you.
MCDOWELL: Thank you Rich, so much. You can hear the brackets break in during the first full day of March madness with a record four games going into overtime and three big upsets. First up, was the battle for Ohio with Dayton's stunning Ohio state, winning 60 to 59. Then came Harvard was toppled the heavily favored Cincinnati, and then North Dakota state shocked Oklahoma Sooners with an 80-75 win in overtime. Today's games include number one seed Arizona versus Weber State in the west.
Virginia takes on coastal Carolina in the east. And the only unbeaten team in the tournament, Wichita state, faces cal poly in the Midwest. And we'll be watching all of that. That's right.
So, let's get the latest on the weather from meteorologist Maria Molina in the FOX Business Weather Center. Hey, Maria.
MARIA MOLINA, METEOROLOGIST: Hi, good morning, hello, everyone. We have relatively warm temperatures today for the first full day of spring along many areas from Texas up into the northeast. You can see in parts of Del Rio, you'll going to be in the middle 80s, 60s in Chicago, and into the 50s in places like New York City. But it all changes by the latter half of the weekend. We're expecting cooler temperatures moving into parts of the Midwest like in Chicago where your highs then are dipping down into the 30s, teens in Marquette, and by Monday, it's even colder out here.
Temperatures only in the 20s for you in the city of Boston and also in Buffalo. We do have several areas of snow, and one of those areas is across parts of the Upper Midwest early today. Winter storm warnings in effect out there and several inches of snow expected along parts of northern New England today. Let's head over to you.
MCDOWELL: Thank you so much, Maria, and we have a lot more coming up, and particularly you're looking at business news right now?
ROTHMAN: That's my job this morning. Oh, look at that. I picked up the satellite. Oh, my goodness.
MCDOWELL: That's not good for you, but --
ROTHMAN: Keep it tuned here. We'll see if we both survive until nine o'clock. Shares of Nike, we are keeping an -- on shares of Nike because a trading lower in the premarket watching the shares because trading lower in the premarket after expressing concern about weaker currencies in key emerging markets. Now, the company says the devaluation of developing market currencies will be a significant drag on its profit growth.
Meanwhile Nike did report better than expected third quarter results. The company posted an adjusted profit of 76 cents per share so that was four cents better than the estimate. Revenue for Nike came in at $6.97 billion dollars, and that was also a beat.
All right. Four members of the Federal Reserve will give us their very own take on Central Bank's policy to, of course, two days after the Fed Chair Janet Yellen's remarks sent stock markets reeling. Yellen suggesting interest rates may rise sooner than a lot of us were expecting. The president of the Minneapolis Fed, St. Louis Fed, Dallas Fed as well as Fed Governor Jeremy Stein are set to speak today.
You'll also want to keep an eye on shares of Symantec which are down in extended trading after the company fired its CEO, guy named Steve Bennett. It is the second time in less than two years that the security software maker dumped its CEO. Bennett is the former head of Quantum, he had been CEO of Symantec since July of 2012. The company's revenue declined each past two quarters and its stock was down about 15 percent over the last 12 months.
All right. Dagen, that wraps it up for business this morning. We're looking at gains about two percent for the major averages in the U.S. this week, strong week despite all the volatility.
MCDOWELL: Yes, despite Janet Yellen --
Coming up, FOX News' Greg Gutfeld stops by IMUS IN THE MORNING to talk about his new book, "Not Cool."
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
GREG GUTFELD, AUTHOR, "NOT COOL": A lot of people become liberals and liberals tried to sustain their ideology by saying that their decisions are cool. That this are -- if you don't do this, if you don't agree with us, you'll be rejected, you will die alone if you're eaten by your own cats. We have this fear, we have this fear that we're going to be alone and so we decide to join things that would prevent that.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
(COMMERCIAL BREAK)
ROTHMAN: Welcome back to IMUS IN THE MORNING, BEST OF IMUS this morning. The I-man is away, the girls are here to play.
MCDOWELL: Two brunettes on TV at the same time.
ROTHMAN: How about that? On the FOX Network.
MCDOWELL: Who thought of that happening?
ROTHMAN: Hey, markets at the U.S. are poised for solid gains this week, as you pointed out, despite Janet Yellen possibly messing things up, but look at Asia, a big rally today. Japan was closed for holiday, but the Kospi, the Hang Seng up better than one percent. Look at the Shanghai index up nearly three percent in the last session. In Europe, trading underway there, and you see the positive sentiment extending to European bench mark indexes as well.
Here's the Dow, Dow futures are pointing to a higher open, so we're in good shape for a solid week here.
MCDOWELL: That's right.
ROTHMAN: There's a look at crude oil just below 100 bucks a barrel, and the price of gold is reversing course dramatically, up about eight bucks an ounce right now after seeing big gaps down earlier this week.
MCDOWELL: Big gainer this week. Well, this dude is a co-host of the popular FOX News show "THE FIVE" and he has his own show at night, I mean, well, early morning really, "Red Eye." Greg Gutfeld stopped by IMUS IN THE MORNING to talk with I-man about his new book "Not Cool." Here's some of that conversation.
(REPEAT INTERVIEW WITH AUTHOR GREG GUTFELD)
MCDOWELL: Coming up. We're going to check on the markets. Let's go to Maria Molina on the FOX Business Weather Center to see if spring has finally arrived, and a lot more great moments from the I-man and the whole crew. Stay with us.
(COMMERCIAL BREAK)
MCDOWELL: Take a look at your markets around the world. Japan closed, but gains in the other three markets that were open. Hong Kong, Shanghai, and South Korea, then England, France, and Germany all heading higher as well. Dow futures are pointing in the same direction. Commodities, oil and gold, are both up as well.
Lori Rothman has some business headlines right here right now. What's going on?
ROTHMAN: Hi there, Dagen. All right. So, we have breaking news for you, we have earnings from Tiffany, the jewelry company reporting an adjusted profit of a $47 per share. Now, the estimate was for a $57 in terms of bottom line, basically, that's a miss. Now, top line, 1.3 billion in revenue, the estimate was for 1.31 billion. So, revenue a little soft as well.
Another retailers to talk about here, shares of Nike are down in the premarket here, trading after the company expressed concern after weaker currencies and key emerging markets. That's the concern they are saying. So, Nike says the devaluation of developing market currencies will be a significant drag on its profit growth.
Meanwhile, Nike reported better than expected third quarter results. The company posted a profit of 76 cents a share, four cents better than estimate. Revenue came in at 6.97 billion and that was also a beat.
Credit card company, Discover Financial, proposing a 20 percent increase in its dividends, to add up to 1.6 billion in stock buybacks. This comes as discovered easily passed its stress test, now Discover still needs fed's approval for the moves, the company is benefited for more rapid loan growth while expanding its lending offerings with student loans, mortgages, and home equity loans. Shares of discover rose in extended trading. Let's go back to you, Dagen.
MCDOWELL: And we go from here to Maria Molina who is in the FOX Business Weather Center with your weather forecast. Hi, Maria.
MARIA MOLINA, METEOROLOGIST: Hi, good morning, hello, everyone. We have relatively warm temperatures today for the first full day of spring along many areas from Texas up into the northeast. You'll be in the mid-80s, 6os in Chicago, and into the 50s in places like New York City. But it all changes by the latter half of the weekend. We're expecting cooler temperatures moving into parts of the Midwest, like in Chicago where highs in are dipping down into the 30s, teens in Marquette, and by Monday, it gets even colder out here. Temperatures only in the 20s for you in the city of Boston and also in Buffalo. We do have several areas of snow, and one of those areas is across parts of the Upper Midwest early today, winter storm warnings in effect out there, and several inches of snow expected along parts of northern New England today. Let's head over to you.
MCDOWELL: Thank you, Maria, and a quick moment, let's check on a recent funny exchange with the I-man.
IMUS: When does the market open, 9:30?
MCSHANE: Most days, well, every day it's open, yes, 9:30.
IMUS: How would I know?
MCSHANE: I don't know. You've been here in a while, your stock markets opens at 9:30, closes at four. You know that.
IMUS: If I knew, I wouldn't ask you.
MCGUIRK: You rang the bell yourself on two occasions.
MCSHANE: What time was that at?
IMUS: I did?
MCGUIRK: Yes.
MCSHANE: There you go.
IMUS: Well, I didn't look at my watch when it was ringing.
MCGUIRK: That was after your drug-induced days.
IMUS: That was Dick Grasso was a chairman.
MCSHANE: What should I be there, Dick?
MCGUIRK: Around noon? On the way. You morons.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
MCDOWELL: Bernie and Connell always make me laugh. So, coming up, some more funny moments from the I-man and company. Also, Imus sits down with author and college basketball analyst, Seth Davis, to talk about his new book on John Wooden and the very latest on the missing plane when we come back.
(COMMERCIAL BREAK)
END
[Copy: Content and Programming Copyright 2014 Fox News Network, LLC. ALL RIGHTS RESERVED. Copyright 2014 CQ-Roll Call, Inc. All materials herein are protected by United States copyright law and may not be reproduced, distributed, transmitted, displayed, published or broadcast without the prior written permission of CQ-Roll Call. You may not alter or remove any trademark, copyright or other notice from copies of the content.]
]]></text></news-item>