<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT5-CS61-DXDT-650F"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>'Britain's FBI' rocked by allegations that two officers have been using their position to access secret documents and intelligence reports on criminals under investigation</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>SOPHIE JANE EVANS</author><text><![CDATA[Sheila Roberts and Brian Adair work for the UK's National Crime AgencySuspended from jobs after being charged with data protection offencesThey allegedly used positions to obtain sensitive documents and reportsIt is first major controversy for NCA, which was set up in October last yearAgency given £450million to tackle serious and organised crime in BritainKeith Vaz, MP for Leicester East, said he was 'astounded' by revelations
The National Crime Agency has been rocked by allegations that two of its officers have been using their positions to unlawfully obtain sensitive information, it has been revealed.
Sheila Roberts and Brian Adair, who work for the agency dubbed 'Britain's FBI', have been arrested and charged with data protection offences.
They are accused of using their jobs to access secret documents - including intelligence reports and personal files on suspects under investigation.
The allegations were revealed today after The Independent successfully overturned a court order banning any report or mention of the charges.
They have sparked the first major controversy for the NCA, which was set up in October last year in a bid to tackle serious and organised crime in the UK.
Since its launch, the agency has been given a staggering £450million budget to track down cyber criminals, drug barons and paedophile gangs across the country.
It has also acquired a reputation for secrecy - with only a tiny proportion of the 350 people it has arrested in the past five months receiving any publicity.
Roberts and Adair, who work alongside former Serious Organised Crime Agency (SOCA) officials, were taking part in a drug-trafficking investigation, which was set up by Home Secretary Theresa May at the end of last year.
But they have now been suspended from the agency and made subject to internal disciplinary proceedings after being charged with data protection offences along with Glyn Evans, a former superintendent from Norfolk Police.
Evans, who is alleged to have unlawfully obtained secret counter-terrorism documents, is believed to be co-director of Corporate Security Consultants (CSC), a firm that offers security to UK embassies across central America.
Keith Vaz, chairman of the Home Affairs Select Committee, told The Independent he was 'astounded' by the revelations - adding: 'This organisation was set up to provide a fresh approach to policing serious and organised crime.
'It is vital that all those who enforce the law act with the utmost integrity.'
Roberts and Adair are being prosecuted by the Information Commissioner, who enforces the Data Protection Act. 
Adair has been charged with unlawfully obtaining intelligence reports from a SOCA operation,
Meanwhile, Roberts is facing charges of three counts of unlawfully obtaining and disclosing sensitive information, including intelligence reports and information about people.
It comes just weeks after the Daily Mail revealed the NCA had refused to comment on its arrest of a top Number 10 aide.
David Cameron's trusted aide, Patrick Rock, was spirited away in the middle of the night when officers knocked on the door of his West London home.
But in an extraordinary move, senior NCA officials said they would not 'confirm or deny' the agency's involvement in any 'ongoing investigation'.
Their ultra-secrecy stands in stark contrast to every other police force in Britain and recently released official guidance.
A NCA spokesman said: 'The NCA expects the highest standards of professionalism from all of its officers, and has a zero-tolerance approach to corruption.'
Meanwhile, a CSC spokesman said the firm was 'unaware' Evans was involved in an ongoing investigation - and has since terminated his employment.
MailOnline has contacted the NCA for further comment.
]]></text></news-item>