<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT5-WF61-J9XT-P3PY"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Hawaii: Transparency Solomons Urges Police To Stop Illegal Logging</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Pacific Islands Development, The State of Hawaii has issued the following news release:
Senior police must ensure that orders to shut down illegal logging operations are enforced, according to Transparency Solomon Islands.
The corruption watchdog says it has learned of two logging operations, one in East Central Guadalcanal and the other in West Rennell, that are continuing to fell trees despite the Ministry of Environment and the High Court ordering them to stop. In both cases the landowners, who are clients of TSI’s Advocacy and Legal Advice Centre, believe that senior police have told their provincial officers not to interfere.
At Longu in East Central Guadalcanal, a logging operation being carried out by Sino Capital Limited was declared illegal in a ‘stop notice’ from the Ministry of Environment in January this year.
Police from Henderson and Tetere Police Stations visited Vila Point on February 2, to enforce the notice, but eyewitnesses have told TSI that the workers simply ignored the officers.
"The RSIPF have a duty to enforce criminal law. It is very difficult to understand why they are not doing so in this case," TSI Executive Officer, Daniel Fenua said.
A landowner, Gregory Awa, obtained an injunction in the High Court last weekend, but still the logging continues.
"I’m worried for my land, I don’t know what else to do," Mr Awa said.
"I have been advised that the Police do not need an enforcement order to stop this illegal operation on our land.
"We understand that they have all the powers they need under the Police Act".
Logging without a development consent is a criminal offence and carries a maximum one year jail term.
The Landowner’s Advocacy and Legal Support Unit (LALSU), the legal representatives for the landowners, praised the role of the Director of the Environment and Conservation Division in issuing the stop notice.
"Issuing a stop notice is the first step. However, the only body with the powers to enforce the order and to make arrests is the Police.
"The Ministry of Environment does not hold any powers of arrest," LALSU head, Martha Manaka said.
"The criminal investigation and prosecution of environmental crime is the next challenge for this country.
"Where laws are not enforced our country is sending a message to international companies that this is a place where poor environmental standards and illegal practices will be tolerated."
Attempts have been made to contact the directors and officers of Sino Capital Limited for comment but it is understood from their registered agents, Yam & Company, that their representative is overseas and unreachable.
In another case, a landowner from Tehakanagoku in West Rennell has told TSI that a logging company is continuing its operation on his land despite a stop notice and an injunction being in place.
On 13th September 2012, the High Court granted an injunction order restraining the licensee and the company, Samlinsan, from entering the land to fell trees or construct roads until further orders.
The landowners have told TSI that machines are still on the land, roads are being constructed and trees are being logged.
A penal notice has been issued meaning that if the injunction is not complied with, a crime has been committed.
ALAC’s client, Jonathan Tohuika, has sought assistance from local police only to be told that his complaint must be taken to Honiara to be actioned.
The client also says a group of senior Police officers visited the site in West Rennell in October last year but the police only met with the loggers and the licensee.
They left without enforcing the injunction or speaking to the group who had the court order made in their favour.
"Landowners are forced to spend huge amounts of money to pay private lawyers to obtain these court orders. But once the orders are obtained the Police must do their part," Mr Fenua said.
Two weeks ago TSI contacted the RSIPF Media Unit and asked a number of question related to these issues but to date "we have not receive their answer".
Anyone seeking legal advice on matters relating to corruption should contact TSI’s Advocacy and Legal Advice Centre on 20391
For further information please visit: http://pidp.eastwestcenter.org/
]]></text></news-item>