<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT5-T5R1-JCTS-G3YH"><date>2014-03-22</date><title></title><source>The Star-Ledger (Newark, New Jersey)</source><author>STAR-LEDGER STAFF</author><text><![CDATA[Turkey
Turkey's ban on Twitter springs corruption leaks
Turkey's attempt to block access to Twitter appeared to backfire yesterday with many tech-savvy users circumventing the ban and suspicions growing that the prime minister was using court orders to suppress corruption allegations against him and his government.
Turkey's telecommunications authority said it had blocked access to the social media network hours after Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan threatened to "rip out the roots" of the website. Tweets have proliferated with links to recordings that appear to incriminate him and other top officials in corruption.
Lutfi Elvan, Turkey's minister in charge of transport and communications, said Turkey was merely obeying court orders -- although an Istanbul lawyers group argued the court decisions were about blocking access to parts of websites deemed to be violating privacy -- not entire websites.
Hawaii
Sex with prostitutes just business, cops say
Honolulu police have urged lawmakers to preserve an exemption in Hawaii law that lets undercover officers have sex with prostitutes during investigations.
The notion has shocked advocates and law enforcement experts on the sex trade.
"I don't know of any state or federal law that allows any law enforcement officer undercover to "¦ do what this law is allowing," said Roger Young, a retired FBI agent who worked sex crimes out of Las Vegas for more than 20 years.
But Honolulu police said they need the exemption to catch lawbreakers in the act. Otherwise, they argued, prostitutes would insist on sex to identify undercover officers. The legislation was amended to restore the protection and the revised proposal passed the House and is now before the Senate.
Thailand
Political crisis deepens as election is nullified
Thailand's constitutional court yesterday nullified the Feb. 2 election won by supporters of Prime Minister Yingluck Shinawatra amid an opposition boycott, prolonging the country's 4-month-old political crisis and threatening a deeper toll on its tourism-dependent economy.
Opposition supporters celebrated the 6-3 court ruling that said the vote was invalid because not all polls were open to receive voters on the same day.
Anti-government protesters had blocked registration in 28 constituencies, forcing election workers to delay voting at the affected polls.
Yingluck's Pheu Thai Party rejected the ruling and vowed to take legal action against the protest leaders who obstructed the work of election commissioners, the government-run National News Bureau of Thailand reported.
The high court ordered that a new election be set but gave no time frame,.
WASHINGTON, D.C.
FBI agent cleared in mysterious shooting
A Florida prosecutor has cleared an FBI agent of any criminal wrongdoing in the fatal shooting of a Chechen man as he was being questioned about a Boston Marathon bombing suspect, two law enforcement officials with knowledge of the investigation said yesterday.
The officials, speaking on condition of anonymity yesterday because they weren't authorized to speak publicly, said State Attorney Jeff Ashton won't bring charges against the agent who shot Ibragim Todashev, a 27-year-old mixed martial arts fighter.
The circumstances surrounding Todashev's death have remained mysterious: Officials initially said the man had lunged at an agent with a knife while FBI agents were questioning him about his friendship with suspected Boston Marathon bomber Tamerlan Tsarnaev. Later, they said it was no longer clear what happened.
Star-Ledger wire services
]]></text></news-item>