<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT5-WWH1-F0NV-F13T"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>PCSO pulls down major meth network</title><source>Polk County Sun (Florida)</source><author>Compiled by Kathy Leigh Berkowitz; klberkowitz@heartlandnewspapers.com</author><text><![CDATA[A full scale investigation pulled down a major meth network, this week.
According to reports, as a result of an investigation begun in October, 2013, on Tuesday, March 18, 2014, Polk County Sheriff 's Office High Intensity Drug Trafficking Areas (HIDTA) Task Force detectives, along with members of the U.S. Drug Enforcement Administration Orlando District Office, Florida Attorney General's Office of Statewide Prosecution, and Lake County Sheriff's Office detectives, identified 25 suspects involved in an organized drug trafficking enterprise.
Reports say that through their investigation, detectives and agents learned the organized methamphetamine crime ring was responsible for the distribution of large amounts of methamphetamine in Lake, Orange, Osceola, Polk and Seminole Counties.
Investigators identified the organization's source of methamphetamine supply as Javier Flores, aka: "El Don." Flores resides in southern California and allegedly managed large scale methamphetamine shipments to Lakeland, Florida, Atlanta, Georgia, and Las Vegas, Nevada through southern California from Mexico. The organization included a network of couriers, managers, distributors and customers. In February, detectives intercepted a $200,170 cash delivery meant to pay for methamphetamine from a courier.
Investigators also learned Lopez and Flores consulted a Voodoo priest who would provide predictions, prophecies and readings regarding the organization's decisions and welfare, reports say.
On Tuesday, March 18, 2014, investigators intercepted 44 pounds of methamphetamine at Love's Truck Stop, 1800 Florida 559, in Polk City. The "uncut" street value of this amount is approximately $2 million. Also, on Tuesday, March 18, detectives arrested 13 suspects, seized tens of thousands of dollars, seven vehicles, approximately 100 weapons, bullet-proof vests, and thousands of rounds of ammunition. Two children, ages 1 and 3, were removed from a residence and placed into DCF custody.
Out of 25 suspects in the organization, 11 are currently receiving Federal/public assistance, and one has been deported, is back in the country illegally, and is currently receiving Federal/public assistance (Ma-Concepcion Lopez), according to reports.
During the course of the investigation, detectives and agents learned two of those involved in the methamphetamine network were Josh Widdows, 30, of 5339 Meadow Grove Trail, Lakeland, and TJ Scott, 25, of 7708 Glen Meadow Dr., Lakeland.
Reports say Widdows and Scott were known to associate with Matthew Tutt, the man responsible for shooting and severely injuring two PCSO deputies in June 2010. At approximately 2:30 a.m., Friday, June 25, 2010, Deputies Mike Braswell and Paul Fairbanks were patroling in the area of Plateau Avenue and Josephine Street in the Wabash area of unincorporated Polk County near Lakeland. There had been a number of burglaries in the area. During their encounter, Tutt pulled a gun from under his shirt and shot at both deputies. Tutt was killed when deputies returned fire. Now retired, Deputy Paul Fairbanks was shot three times, and Deputy Mike Braswell was shot four times. Both deputies recovered. Widdows and Scott bought Meth from Rojas and in turn were selling the meth on the streets of Polk County, according to reports.
Detectives with served search warrants at the following addresses:
2322 View Way, Lakeland (Lopez & Rojas' residence)
10910 Sportsman Trail, Lakeland (Lopez & Rojas' residence)
402 Wildlife Trail, Lakeland (Lopez & Rojas' residence)
3604 Glenoak Drive South, Lakeland - Joshua Widdows' residence
3839 NW 1st NW Street, Lakeland - Tyler Scott's residence
2015 Adair Road, Davenport - Rios residence
Arrested were:
· Jose Luis Rios, 47, 2322 View Way, Lakeland
· Ma-Concepcion Lopez, 38, 2322 View Way, Lakeland
· Luis Villafuerte Rojas, 39, 2322 View Way, Lakeland
· Joel Tapia, 30, 2015 Adair Rd., Davenport
· Debra Tapia, 49, 2015 Adair Rd., Davenport
· Tara Tapia, 29, 2015 Adair Rd., Davenport
· Maria Lopez Ontiveros, aka Mariana Alvear, 33, 2322 View Way, Lakeland
· Dioscelina Galaraza-Ozorio, 33, 2322 View Way, Lakeland
· Alfredo Ortiz-Hernandez, 26, 750 3rd Ave.
· Maria Widdows, 29, 3604 Glenoak Drive South, Lakeland
· Joseph Workman, 52, 18 West Bass Street Orlando
· Joseph Angelo Rinaldi, 34, 10811 Sienna Dr. Clermont
· Eugenia Lopez, 29, 402 Wildlife Trail Lakeland
Wanted Suspects:
· Javier Flores, unknown DOB, between 35-40 years of age, California; Flores is wanted for Engaging in a Continuing Criminal Enterprise, Conspiracy to Traffic in Methamphetamine over 200 grams, Conspiracy to Traffic in Methamphetamine over 200 grams, Unlawful Transportation of Currency $100,000 or More, and Unlawful Use of a Two-Way Communications Device to Facilitate the Commission of a Crime
· Hugo Lopez Esquivel, 33, 54 Pinetree Rd., Lawrencevill, GA. Lopez is wanted for Conspiracy to Traffic in Methamphetamine over 200 grams, Unlawful Transportation of Currency, $50,000 or More, Unlawful Use of a Two-Way Communications Device to Facilitate the Commission of a Crime.
· Eliezer Rodriguez Merced, 33, 54 Pinetree Rd., Lawrencevill, GA, Merced is wanted for Conspiracy to Traffic in Methamphetamine over 200 grams, Unlawful Transportation of Currency, $50,000 or more, Unlawful Use of a Two-Way Communications Device to Facilitate the Commission of a Crime.
· Joshua Widdows is currently receiving Federal/public assistance. Widdows is wanted for Conspiracy to Traffic in Methamphetamine over 14 grams, and Unlawful Use of a Two-Way Communications Device to Facilitate the Commission of a Crime.
· Tyler Scott is wanted for Possession of Methamphetamine, Sale of Methamphetamine, and Own or Rent Structure for Knowingly Selling Drugs.
· Demasco Candid Lugo, 30, 908 Ruth Ave., Lakeland; Lugo is wanted for Conspiracy to Traffic in Methamphetamine over 28 grams, and Trafficking in Methamphetamine over 28 grams
· Melinda Baker-Ruiz, 33, 908 Ruth Ave., Lakeland; Baker-Ruiz is wanted for Conspiracy to Traffic in Methamphetamine over 28 grams, and Trafficking in Methamphetamine over 28 grams.
· Danielle Campbell, 26, 9555 Kingsbury Ct., Windermere; Campbell is currently receiving Federal/public assistance and is wanted for Conspiracy to Traffic in Methamphetamine over 28 grams, and Unlawful Use of a Two-Way Communications Device to Facilitate the Commission of a Crime.
· Hector Sanyustiz, 39, 1254 Westside Dr., Winter Garden. Sanyustiz is currently receiving Federal/public assistance and is wanted for Conspiracy to Traffic in Methamphetamine over 28 grams, Trafficking in Methamphetamine over 28 grams, and Unlawful Use of a Two-Way Communications Device to Facilitate the Commission of a Crime.
· Laura Caton, 35, 2718 Sample St., Kissimmee, Caton is currently receiving Federal/public assistance, and is wanted for Conspiracy to Traffic in Methamphetamine over 14 grams, and Unlawful Use of a Two-Way Communications Device to Facilitate the Commission of a Crime.
· Jose Godoy, 22, 1108 Powerline Rd., Davenport. Godoy is currently receiving Federal/public assistance, and is wanted for Conspiracy to Traffic in Methamphetamine over 14 grams.
· Bryan Cumberbatch, 31, 1541 Goodyear Ave., Lakeland, Cumberbatch is wanted for Possession of Methamphetamine; Sell Methamphetamine; Own or Rent Structure/Vehicle Known to Sell Drugs, a second degree felony; and Possession/Use Narcotic Paraphernalia.
]]></text></news-item>