<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT5-CYS1-JCMN-Y0P8"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>District Attorney's Ethical Breach Printed in Wisconsin State Jounral</title><source>MAL Contends</source><author>MAL</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 22, 2014 (MAL Contends:http://malcontends.blogspot.com/ Delivered by Newstex) http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-3GOZhkFRsgk/Uy2f9O4Jb3I/AAAAAAAAIZU/apYk8osgX98/s1600/Katie+Kloth.jpgOn Monday, Iron County District Attorney Martin Lipske will attempt to overcharge and in an abuse of office typical of Lipske shut down and ultimately imprison a 20-something political protester, Katie Kloth.
The arraignment for Kloth[1] for actions at a protest last year is Monday, March 24.Lipske will be acting on behalf of GTac, or Gogebic Taconite for whom the corrupt Lipske works, with an eye out for its private security army, Bulletproof Inc., whom Lipske protected despite clear and repeated violations of Wisconsin statutes[2].Turns out the ethically challenged district attorney[3] has already committed a breach of the rules for ethical conduct for Wisconsin attorneys.Lipske violated Wisconsin Supreme Court Rule [SCR 20:3.6 Trial publicity[4]], stating: "(a) A lawyer who is participating or has participated in the investigation or litigation of a matter shall not make an extrajudicial statement that the lawyer knows or reasonably should know will be disseminated by means of public communication and will have a substantial likelihood of materially prejudicing an adjudicative proceeding in the matter."The violation occurred in Lipske's statement made to Steven Verburg of the Wisconsin State Journal[5] (July 17, 2013).The State Journal headline reads: "Details of harassment incident at mine show a troubling threat, prosecutor says."Here is Lipske's quote: '"The details on the [alleged criminal] incident (of Katie Kloth and a small group) help explain why the Gogebic Taconite mining company hired heavily armed security guards from Arizona who wore camouflage and masks, Lipske said," and "What is the appropriate response for the company? They don't want to spend hundreds of thousands of dollars in high-end security, but how much do they need to protect those people?" [1]: http://wcca.wicourts.gov/caseDetails.do;jsessionid=5A04487F88BFFA0843082E30BFD53BE1.render6?caseNo=2013CF000030countyNo=26cacheId=AD6183229DB63C3B90F7541E015BE0A8recordCount=1offset=0mode=detailssubmit=View+Case+Details [2]: http://eye-on-wisconsin.blogspot.com/2013/08/preferential-treatment-for-bulletproof.html [3]: http://malcontends.blogspot.com/2013/07/iron-county-da-has-history-of.html [4]: http://www.wicourts.gov/sc/scrule/DisplayDocument.html?content=htmlseqNo=102639#TrialPublicity [5]: http://host.madison.com/wsj/news/local/details-of-harassment-incident-at-mine-show-a-troubling-threat/article_440a2434-ef04-593b-b331-8e83fe3d5a3f.html

]]></text></news-item>