<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT5-DMC1-JDTY-44N4"><date>2014-03-21</date><title>Tribes in legal battle over hazardous waste; FMC accused of owing millions in unpaid storage fees</title><source>Idaho State Journal</source><author>O'donnell, Michael</author><text><![CDATA[FORT HALL --As FMC and the Environmental Protection Agency continue to move forward with cleanup efforts at the old elementary phosphorous plant west of Pocatello, a legal battle continues between the Shoshone-Bannock Tribes and FMC over millions of dollars in unpaid fees for hazardous waste storage.

The tribes contend that FMC owes $1.5 million a year in waste storage fees the company agreed to pay back in 1997. Those fees were paid to the tribes from 1998 until the plant closed in 2001.

"When they shut the plant down, they stopped paying," said Bill Bacon, general legal counsel for the tribes.

FMC's failure to continue to pay the waste storage permit fee led the tribes to file a lawsuit. Bacon said FMC originally agreed to pay the waste storage fees so the tribes could pay for observation and management of the Eastern Michaud Flats Superfund Site, which lies within the boundaries of the Fort Hall Indian Reservation in Power County. Bacon said the funds also allowed the tribes to establish a fund for possible mitigation expenses if necessary.

"The money is earmarked only for these purposes," Bacon said.

The original lawsuit was filed in tribal court and FMC argued the tribes lacked jurisdiction over the company. The tribal court ruled that, because FMC had entered into a consensual agreement with the Shoshone-Bannock Tribes, tribal jurisdiction did exist, according to the Supreme Court ruling in Montana v. U.S.

FMC appealed that ruling and lost in Federal District Court.

The Federal District Court found that because in 1998 FMC agreed to apply for tribal permits and pay fees for the storage of hazardous and nonhazardous waste the company had consented to tribal jurisdiction.

The tribes are now asserting that they have additional jurisdiction over FMC because the company's activities "threaten the health and welfare of the tribes." Bacon said that will be decided in tribal court beginning April 1.

Bacon said the tribes are seeking a judgment of more than $9 million in tribal court, but the main issue is to establish jurisdiction over FMC's

a. ctivities for two reasons -- the earlier consensual relationship and for the health and welfare of the tribes.

"The litigation of this case will be going for some time," Bacon said.

If the tribes win in tribal court, Bacon said he is certain that FMC will appeal that ruling and it will head to Federal District Court, then to the Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals and potentially the U.S. Supreme Court.

Bacon said at issue are 250,000 tons of slag, 16,000 tons of phosphorous in the soil at the old FMC plant site as well as hazardous chemicals in the old treatment ponds and groundwater contamination -- all located on reservation land.

However, the thrust of the legal argument being heard in tribal court next month will be whether the tribes have jurisdiction based on a threat to the health and welfare of the tribes, according to Bacon.

]]></text></news-item>