<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT5-85B1-F03R-N2N5"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>TopFinds: Searching for Flight 370, abuse found at turkey farms</title><source>Digital Journal</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 22, 2014 (Digital Journal:http://www.digitaljournal.com Delivered by Newstex) The hunt continues for debris and survivors of the Malaysia Airlines aircraft that went missing weeks ago. An investigation uncovered abuse at a Canadian turkey farm. A QA with Megadeth frontman Dave Mustaine. Welcome to this week's TopFinds.
As we do every week, we've collected the top news stories and compiled them on one page. Digital Journalists reported on important air-travel news, the latest sports analysis, insight into science features and much more.We also highlight some of the major topics Digital Journalists have been covering recently. Note you can see the trending topics at the top of any page on our news network, in the black bar. Hot topics on Digital Journal • Crimea news[1]• Obama news[2] Top Digital Journal Reports Review: Adam Lambert and Lea Michele impress on 'Barracuda' on 'Glee' (Includes first-hand account)[3] by Markos Papadatos[4] Adam Lambert and Lea Michele covered "Barracuda," the classic hit from rock band Heart on the reality television show "Glee." Interview with Dave Mustaine: Lead singer of Megadeth (Includes interview)[5] by Markos Papadatos[6] Iconic heavy metal group Megadeth will soon embark on a world tour in more than 25 countries across four continents starting in April. This Digital Journalist spoke to lead singer Dave Mustaine about the band's future.Review: Trisha Yearwood wows at the NYCB Theatre at Westbury (Includes first-hand account)[7] by Markos Papadatos[8] Country singer Trisha Yearwood performed at the NYCB Theatre at Westbury in Long Island, New York, on March 14. Rising country singer-songwriter Karyn Rochelle warmed up the stage. Girl's escape from Shining Path in Tomlinson's 'Lethal Dispatch' (Includes interview and first-hand account)[9] by AR Vasquez[10] Max Tomlinson, author of "Sendero" (awarded by Kirkus Reviews as the Best of 2012) is back with a new action thriller novel "Lethal Dispatch". Review: Foster The People shares Best Friend playlist on Spotify (Includes first-hand account)[11] by Kathleen Creighton[12] In anticipation of the release of their new album, Supermodel, on March 18th Foster The People shared another single on Spotify along with tracks from some of their best friends. Top Images In the MediaMissing airliner found off Australia? — Large debris found[13] by Paul Wallis[14] In what can only be described as a particularly bizarre twist to an already bizarre story, it is believed that debris located 2,000 km off the West Australian coast may be parts of the missing Malaysian Airlines plane which disappeared 10 days ago. Ottawa priest sentenced to one year in jail for defrauding church[15] by Arthur Weinreb[16] The former priest and pathological gambler was sent to jail for defrauding his parish of $130,000 over a period of five years ending in December 2010. Despite his crimes, he still has the support of many of his former parishioners. Ohio State has the mumps, all but one infected were vaccinated[17] by Jeannie Stokowski-Bisanti[18] On Tuesday, a city health department spokesman, Jose Rodriguez, said that mumps cases at Ohio State University have grown to 28 cases. Rodriguez said all but one of those infected had received at least one dose of the mumps vaccine. Op-Ed: Why Pacquiao should use speed more than power to beat Bradley[19] by Leo Reyes[20] Filipino boxing superstar Manny Pacquiao has been known for his speed and power inside the ring but boxing analysts and longtime supporters say that it would be better for Pacquiao to capitalize more on his speed than on his power punches. NBA News and Rumors: Chris Bosh headed to Chicago Bulls?[21] by Larry Seely[22] Despite some success this season without Derrick Rose, the Chicago Bulls could finish last in the NBA offensively for the second straight season, not exactly what a team needs to win championships. /sports/nba-rumors-josh-smith-headed-to-boston-celtics-this-summer/article/376827NBA Rumors: Josh Smith headed to Boston Celtics this summer? by /user/762796Larry Seely Boston Celtics General Manager Danny Ainge is looking toward this summer to add the necessary talent for this franchise to contend for another NBA Championship and a trade could be the key to getting the players this squad needs. /a-and-e/entertainment/video-japanese-anime-attack-on-titan-1st-english-dub-clip/article/376853Video: Japanese anime 'Attack on Titan' 1st English dub clip by /user/454492Can Tran The first English dub clip for "Attack on Titan" has been made available for streaming. The full preview will be available at this year's Anime Boston. /sports/nba-news-and-rumors-luol-deng-headed-to-la-lakers/article/376573NBA News and Rumors: Luol Deng headed to LA Lakers? by /user/762796Larry Seely One of the biggest names available this summer in the NBA is Cleveland Cavaliers forward Luol Deng. The former Duke star has already told Cleveland he won't return and rumors have already started on his possible destination. /news/world/op-ed-civilization-could-crash-in-15-years-nasa-study/article/376688Op-Ed: Civilization could crash in 15 years- NASA study by /user/195582Paul Wallis NASA's new study says the crunch time for civilization could be very near. Usually, when civilizations fall, it's a big deal. Whether or not anybody will even notice the fall of this particular civilization is highly debatable./news/world/group-exposes-horrific-turkey-abuse-at-hybrid-farms-canada/article/376494Group exposes horrific turkey abuse at Hybrid Farms Canada by /user/830467Kathleen Blanchard Mercy for Animals (MFA) has once again uncovered horrific animal abuse that seems to happen all too often on factory farms. In their undercover video, Hybrid Turkey workers in Canada throw, stomp and crush spines of turkeys. /news/politics/rob-ford-trashes-actor-kevin-spacey-on-ford-nation-youtube-show/article/376346Rob Ford trashes actor Kevin Spacey on 'Ford Nation' YouTube show by /user/654780Marcus Hondro Toronto Mayor Rob Ford, and his brother, Toronto councilor Doug Ford, unleashed a barrage of criticism at actor Kevin Spacey on their 'Ford Nation' YouTube show today. Spacey's biggest crime appears to be not posing for a picture with the mayor. This parrot is actually a woman posing in bodypaint[23] by David Silverberg[24] What looks exactly like a parrot perched on a stump is really the work of artist Johannes Stoetter, who lives in Italy. He spent four hours painting the woman's body using special breathable paint. Power Users Tim Sandle[25] W. Mark Dendy[26] [1]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/topic/crimea [2]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/topic/obama [3]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/a-and-e/music/review-adam-lambert-and-lea-michele-impress-on-barracuda-on-glee/article/376616 [4]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/user/274377 [5]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/a-and-e/music/interview-with-dave-mustaine-lead-singer-of-megadeth/article/377032 [6]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/user/274377 [7]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/a-and-e/music/review-trisha-yearwood-wows-at-the-nycb-theatre-at-westbury/article/376502 [8]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/user/274377 [9]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/a-and-e/entertainment/girl-s-escape-from-shining-path-in-tomlinson-s-lethal-dispatch/article/376653 [10]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/user/207462 [11]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/a-and-e/music/review-foster-the-people-shares-best-friend-playlist-on-spotify/article/376518 [12]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/user/269753 [13]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/news/world/missing-airliner-found-off-australia-large-debris-found-breaking-news/article/377305 [14]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/user/195582 [15]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/news/crime/ottawa-priest-sentenced-to-one-year-in-jail-for-defrauding-church/article/377316 [16]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/user/93201 [17]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/life/health/ohio-state-has-the-mumps-all-but-one-infected-were-vaccinated/article/377216 [18]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/user/995854 [19]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/sports/op-ed-why-pacquiao-should-use-speed-more-than-power-to-beat-bradley/article/376862 [20]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/user/87844 [21]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/sports/nba-news-and-rumors-chris-bosh-headed-to-chicago-bulls/article/377273 [22]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/user/762796 [23]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/a-and-e/arts/this-parrot-is-actually-a-woman-posing-in-bodypaint/article/376438 [24]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/user/899 [25]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/user/429626 [26]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/user/568433

]]></text></news-item>