<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT6-7DP1-JC3H-04VV"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Class-action suit targets stock's fall over recall</title><source>The Detroit News (Michigan)</source><author>By, David Shepardson , and Robert Snell</author><text><![CDATA[The Detroit News
Washington - A shareholder filed a class-action lawsuit against General Motors in Detroit on Friday, saying stockholders were defrauded by the Detroit automaker's failure to disclose ignition switch problems earlier.
"GM's illegal and immoral activities during (2010 through March 2014) effectively eviscerated GM's reputation for safety, quality, value and performance, said the lawsuit filed in U.S. District Court by New York-based law firm Pomerantz LLP and by Cafferty Clobes Meriwether & Sprengel LLP in Ann Arbor. "Moreover, the news of the company's recalls through a series of disclosures, and later reports of government criminal and civil investigations into the company, triggered a sharp decline in the company's share price, wiping out billions in shareholder value."
Last week, GM's stock fell by about 10 percent, wiping out about $5 billion in shareholder value after disclosures that the Justice Department is investigating GM's ignition switch recall in older Chevrolet Cobalts, Saturn Ions and other cars linked to 12 deaths and 31 crashes.
The suit also names GM CEO Mary Barra, former CEO Dan Akerson and other top officials including GM President Dan Ammann and North America Chief Alan Batey.
A separate class-action suit filed Friday in Detroit on behalf a Tennessee owner of a 2006 Saturn Ion in connection with the ignition switch recall said GM violated the warranty rights of owners of the recalled cars. Owners, the suit argues, would have paid less if they had known about the problem or might not have purchased them.
They are among a growing number of suits being filed nationwide in connection with the recall.
GM stock closed down 0.7 percent Friday to $35.01, off 25 cents a share.
GM spokesman Jim Cain declined to comment on the merits of the shareholder suit, saying the automaker will respond in due course. He said the company is focused on getting recalled cars fixed.
GM has repeatedly apologized and said it didn't handle the issue properly. GM has disclosed that as early as 2001 it knew of problems with a pre-production Saturn Ion and over more than a decade opted not to recall the vehicle, but bought back at least 13 cars from owners who reported severe stalling problems. "Despite being fully aware as early as 2001 of the severe and easily corrected defect in its cars, (GM) refused to engage the legally required recall and instead continued to sell millions of defective cars to U.S. consumers," the suit says.
Alan James, executive director of the Center for Global Governance, Reporting and Regulation at Pace University, said shareholders will also get hit at GM if the company pays massive fines.
"In the end, fines are paid by shareholders," James said.
He said huge fines on most firms result in a short range drop in the share price. "Recovery depends on whether the buyers think the stock is worthy of holding."
Shareholder suits are not uncommon after a major crisis results in a sharp drop in a company's stock price, but they face an uphill battle.
In November 2012, Toyota Motor Corp. agreed to pay $25.5 million to settle claims from shareholders who said they were harmed by the Japanese automaker's recall for unintended acceleration of millions of vehicles in 2009-10. The settlement covered all U.S. Toyota shareholders who bought stock between May 2005 and Feb. 2, 2010. The settlement said there were "tens of thousands" of people who purchased stock during the nearly five-year period. The company did not admit wrongdoing.
The negative publicity initially wiped out $30 billion in Toyota's market capitalization, lawyers for the shareholders said, so the settlement was just a fraction of the losses.
The shareholders claimed the automaker concealed problems with the vehicles and that they would not have purchased the automaker's stock had they known. Toyota stock, known as American Depository Shares, trades on the New York Stock Exchange.
Lawyers for the shareholders, who filed a series of suits in February 2010, reviewed more than 6 million pages of records and said the maximum shareholders could have recovered if the case went to trial is $124 million.
Old "GM" - the company that existed before new GM was created from the good assets of the automaker in a 2009 government-sponsored bankruptcy reorganization - paid $277 million in a 2008 settlement of claims by shareholders that it had overstated its income by billions of dollars over a six-year-period in an accounting scandal investigated by the Securities and Exchange Commission.
GM's auditor, Deloitte & Touche, paid $26 million as part of the GM shareholder settlement.
In 2008, Delphi settled shareholder lawsuits for about $284 million. Shareholders charged Delphi misled investors by not disclosing the extent of the company's financial woes and engaging in widespread accounting fraud.
The SEC filed financial fraud charges against Delphi and nine of its employees, charging the company with engaging in a pattern of fraudulent conduct between 2000 and 2004. Delphi settled the complaint without admitting fault.
dshepardson@detroitnews.com
]]></text></news-item>