<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT6-F801-DXJR-H0PC"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Complainant fined for bid to blackmail company</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[AHMEDABAD: A consumer court has slapped penalty of Rs 5,000 on a person for filing complaint against a multinational food company allegedly to extort money.
According to case details, Mahesh Tanna, a resident of Vadodara, had in May 2004 purchased two soft drink bottles of Slice from a shop in Makarpura area. He showed the shopkeeper that one of the bottles contained black plastic pieces inside. He, however, kept the bottle with him and slapped a legal notice to Slice Pepsico India Holding Pvt Ltd and the shopkeeper for selling adulterated food. He was not satisfied with the company's reply.
Tanna later moved the consumer dispute redressal forum in Vadodara and demanded that the company's manufacturing licence as well as the shopkeeper's business licence be cancelled. He also sought Rs 2 lakh from the company for selling adulterated and unhygienic stuff without proper quality check. He demanded Rs 20,000 towards mental agony he suffered.
During the hearing, the company maintained that it has got a sophisticated plant and maintained high standard of quality. It claimed that the complaint was false, frivolous and filed with a view to harassing the company. It also alleged that Tanna's intention behind the complaint was to blackmail the company.
After the procedure, the consumer forum came to a conclusion that the complainant might have tampered with the bottle, else there was no question of the bottle carrying foreign material. The court also observed that Tanna was not a food inspector. He did not make any panch-nama of the bottle, neither did he call any food inspector. He did not even took the soft drink bottle to any recognized laboratory for the purpose of tests.
Thus, in absence of any evidence to support his allegations, Tanna's complaint was seen as a means to extort huge money from the company. Since he could not prove any of his allegations, the court rejected his demands.
Six-month jail to shop owner
A metropolitan court punished a sweets shop owner with six-month imprisonment and imposed fine on him after he was found guilty of adulterating food items.
According to prosecutor Manoj Khandhar, a food inspector raided Ambeshwar Chavana & Sweets in Narol area during the Diwali festival in 2007. Food samples were collected and sent to a laboratory for test. It was found that certain food items were adulterated. Shop owner Gamnaram Prajapati was booked for selling adulterated food. After hearing the case, additional chief metropolitan magistrate J S Patel found the shop owner guilty and convicted him to six-month prison.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>