<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT6-CDB1-JCMN-Y21B"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Edward Snowden Leak: National Security Agency Spied on Chinese Firm Huawei</title><source>The Hinterland Gazette</source><author>Janet Shan</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 22, 2014 (The Hinterland Gazette:http://hinterlandgazette.com Delivered by Newstex) http://hinterlandgazette.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/huawei.jpeg Edward Snowden Leak: National Security Agency Spied on Chinese Firm Huawei EDWARD SNOWDEN LEAK: The National Security Agency is accused of spying on Chinese firm Huawei, according to New York Times article (@nytimes[1]). The NSA responded saying, 'As we have previously stated, NSA's activities are focused and specifically deployed against, and only against, valid foreign intelligence targets in response to intelligence requirements.'
But even as the United States made a public case about the dangers of buying from Huawei, classified documents show that the National Security Agency was creating its own back doors — directly into Huawei's networks. The agency pried its way into the servers in Huawei's sealed headquarters in Shenzhen, China's industrial heart, according to N.S.A. documents provided by the former contractor Edward J. Snowden. It obtained information about the workings of the giant routers and complex digital switches that Huawei boasts connect a third of the world's population, and monitored communications of the company's top executives. One of the goals of the operation, code-named 'Shotgiant,' was to find any links between Huawai and the People's Liberation Army, one 2010 document made clear. But the plans went further: to exploit Huawai's technology so that when the company sold equipment to other countries — including both allies and nations that avoid buying American products — the N.S.A. could roam through their computer and telephone networks to conduct surveillance and, if ordered by the president, offensive cyberoperations. Source: NY Times[2]The Edward Snowden leaks just keep coming but to whose benefit? I am pretty sure the Chinese are also spying on us. The Russians are also engaged in similar behavior, so I am not sure how these leaks will help Americans. Hinterland Gazette[3] [1]: https://twitter.com/nytimes [2]: http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/23/world/asia/nsa-breached-chinese-servers-seen-as-spy-peril.html?partner=rssemc=rsssmid=tw-nytimes_r=0 [3]: http://hinterlandgazette.com

]]></text></news-item>