<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT6-7DR1-JC3H-01J5"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Measure to ban fracking seems dead for session</title><source>The Daily News Journal (Murfreesboro, TN)</source><author>By, Duane W. Gang</author><text><![CDATA[NASHVIILLE - Bans on fracking and mountaintop mining in Tennessee appear dead for the year.
Three measures before state lawmakers aimed at adding those protections for Tennessee's natural resources failed to make it out of the Senate Energy, Agriculture and Natural Resources Committee March 12.
"I can't say I am really surprised by the vote. But I think they are important enough issues to keep talking about," said state Sen. Lowe Finney, D-Jackson, the sponsor of the bills.
"Regardless of what is going to happen with the bills, we got to keep some kind of conversation here going. That was the intent today."
For the first time, hydraulic fracturing or fracking is specifically addressed in state oil and gas regulations that took effect last year. Environmental groups say that is a good first step, but the regulations don't go far enough to protect Tennessee's natural resources and keep the public informed about drilling operations.
Lowe's Senate Bill 2064 would have banned fracturing in the state. The bill was sent to a subcommittee, meaning it is unlikely to get taken up again this session.
Mountaintop mining also has been an issue that Lowe has taken up in the past without success.
Senate Bill 1980 would have prohibited surface mining within 1,200 feet of a ridgeline. A similar measure, Senate Bill 1925, also by Finney, would have prohibited surface mining on ridges above 1,800 feet in elevation.
The two bills did not make it out of committee.
High-elevation surface mining does take place in Tennessee, but both sides of the debate differ on whether it constitutes "mountaintop removal."
Finney told the committee he understands that mining creates jobs. But he said he hoped to "figure out a way to preserve those jobs but at the same time in the years ahead find a way to protect the natural resources and, frankly, the beauty that we have in those mountain ranges across Middle and East Tennessee."
Meanwhile, the committee also halted a bill giving regulatory oversight of surface mining to the Tennessee Department of Environment and Conservation. The federal Office of Surface Mining currently regulates it.
Environmentalists praised that move. Ann League, Tennessee campaign coordinator for Appalachian Voices, said the committee took a "sound course of action today on this ill-conceived bill."
Chas Sisk contributed to this report.
Growth Projected
Shale gas is one of the most rapidly growing forms of natural gas. Unconventional gas production is forecast to increase from 42 percent of total U.S. gas production in 2007 to 64 percent in 2020.
- American Petroleum Institute
]]></text></news-item>