<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT6-7DP1-JC3H-03XV"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>NC bails on Duke coal ash deal, joins forces with EPA</title><source>The Asheville Citizen-Times (North Carolina)</source><author>By, John Boyle</author><text><![CDATA[jboyle@citizen-times.com
- The state agency charged with regulating coal ash pollution has asked a judge to allow it to withdraw from a proposed settlement with Duke Energy that would have allowed the utility to avoid a costly cleanup and pay a $99,000 fine.
The N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources issued press releases late Friday stating it now intends to move forward with its lawsuit against Duke, and that it will join forces with the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency to resolve violations associated with the massive Dan River coal ash spill.
DJ Gerken, an attorney with the Southern Environmental Law Center, which last year initiated legal action against Duke for pollution at the Lake Julian power plant in Arden, said Friday's news was welcome but tardy.
"Both of these things we wished would've happened a year ago," Gerken said. "I think it's driven by a few things: The Dan River ash spill, the intense media scrutiny and also by the judge's order a few weeks ago directing that Duke must take immediate action to stop its contamination."
One of the largest utilities in the country, Duke is a $50 billion company. Critics decried the $99,000 settlement proposal as a slap on the wrist.
DENR said Friday it would scuttle the proposed consent order to settle violations for groundwater contamination leaching from coal ash dumps near Charlotte and the Lake Julian plant.
The coal ash issue erupted anew in early February. The Feb. 2 spill at a Duke coal ash dump in Eden coated 70 miles of the Dan River in toxic sludge.
The proposed settlement was initially tabled last month, after an Associated Press story highlighted what environmentalists criticized as a "sweetheart deal" for Duke.
DENR Secretary John Skvarla said in the press release that the agency intends "for our lawsuits against Duke Energy to move forward.
"We will continue to hold the utility accountable for the cleanup of its coal ash impoundments through the lawsuits, the reopening of the permits and our ongoing investigation," Skvarla said.
The agency noted the terms of the consent order were negotiated "based on long-standing interpretation of the state's groundwater rules," and were based in part on advice from the state's Attorney General in a 2009 advisory memorandum and confirmed by the Environmental Management Commission in a 2012 ruling. The releases say that DENR is required to follow EMC rules and the commission's interpretation of the rules.
But a Wake County judge disagreed with that interpretation on March 6. The DENR release reads: "In view of the court's order, DENR believes the best course of action at this time is to withdraw its support for the current consent order."
The Southern Environmental Law Center had filed a notice of intent to sue in January of last year, but DENR then filed suit, superseding SELC's proposed legal action. Then, instead of pursuing its lawsuit, DENR offered the settlement proposal.
Gerken said Skvarla has not been diligent in forcing Duke to clean up its pollution or to seriously punish the utility.
It's clear, Gerken said, that DENR has opposed forcing a cleanup throughout its dealings with Duke and that the agency "was doing everything it could to keep the EPA out of the picture."
The release about joining forces with the EPA states that Skvarla invited the federal agency's participating in a March 14 letter.
"The state's goal is to clean up both the Dan River and to protect public health and the environment at the other Duke Energy facilities around the state, and we are pleased to announce that the EPA will join us as we address these important issues," Gov. Pat McCrory said in the release. "Participation by the EPA will bring additional resources to help us resolve a difficult problem that spans more than six decades."
The release notes the EPA has extensive experience with coal ash dating back to the devastating 2008 coal ash spill in Kingston, Tenn.
The Associated Press contributed to this report.
]]></text></news-item>