<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT6-7DR1-JC3H-017S"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>EPA seeks new funds for Lees Lane Landfill cleanup</title><source>The Courier-Journal (Louisville, Kentucky)</source><author>By, James Bruggers</author><text><![CDATA[The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency is going back to nearly two dozen companies it held responsible for pollution at the troubled Lees Lane Landfill, seeking their help in resolving lingering health and safety problems at the contaminated dump.
In letters to 22 companies provided to The Courier-Journal through a Freedom of Information Act request, the EPA said new problems have been found at the dump that closed in the 1970s, and EPA wants the companies to help pay to solve them.
On Friday it held a meeting and teleconference with the businesses, which made payments to the government in the 1990s under previous agreements to cover remediation costs. The agency says those businesses still have liability for toxic chemicals dumped and entombed decades ago along the banks of the Ohio River in the Riverside Gardens area of western Louisville.
MORE | State urges better security at landfill
A recent periodic EPA review of the conditions there identified "a number of technical issues that must be addressed" before the agency can determine the landfill's safety, John Sheesley, assistant regional counsel for the EPA, wrote to the companies.
"For example, the gas collection system at the site does not appear to be working properly, and data gaps exist concerning soil and groundwater contamination at the site," he wrote.
"In most of the settlement agreements, the United States reserved the right to seek reimbursement of future response costs, that is, those costs incurred by the United States after the date the agreements were lodged in court, from the parties," EPA spokesman James Pinkney said in a written statement.
He added that the EPA cannot yet estimate the costs associated with the new work.
EPA also plans to involve area residents in a community relations program, but said details have not been announced.
Those who were invited to participate in further cleanup activities include the Hofgesang Foundation, which owns the property. Also targeted are companies that at some point used the landfill, or companies that may have inherited liability through acquisitions.
The Metropolitan Sewer District, which agreed in a 1993 settlement to maintain the dump through 2020, participated in the meeting Friday, spokesman Steve Tedder said. Others sought by the EPA include such Rubbertown chemical companies as American Synthetic Rubber and Rohm and Haas (now owned by Dow Chemical), the Ford Motor Co., and Gannett, which bought the The Courier-Journal in 1986 and was part of the 1993 settlements.
Todd Mayman, a Gannett senior vice president and general counsel, said he intends "to learn what next steps (EPA) is proposing."
Waste Management Inc. also participated in Friday's meeting, said Jim Forney, an area director for the company. He said it was an "informational" meeting and the companies were told to expect further communication from EPA on potential additional studies and remediation activities.
The Hofgesang Foundation inherited the land from Joseph Hofgesang, who developed the landfill before dying in 1972. A lawyer for the foundation told The Courier-Journal in 2007 that it met its cleanup obligations through a separate settlement with the EPA in 1996 for $2.6million, largely depleting its assets.
Hofgesang Foundation Treasurer Elizabeth Kelton, of Lexington, said she could not attend or listen to Friday's meeting and declined further comment.
MSD's Tedder said after the meeting that the agency still isn't clear exactly what EPA wants MSD to do beyond what it agreed to in 1993.
"If they are asking for more, we will have to review it," he said.
The dump's problems first gained public attention in 1975, when methane caused flash fires in several Riverside Gardens homes, prompting officials to move seven families. Once on the nation's list of most toxic places, the 112-acre property has been fought over for decades.
The gas-collection system was first found to be working improperly in the 1990s, then again in 2007. The system was never overhauled when MSD contended it had spent all the money on the property agreed to earlier.
Then in 2012, with reports of once-buried waste making its way to the surface, EPA called for a new study of health and safety concerns.
Last year, state environmental officials discovered elevated levels of toxic pollution in new soil samplings. They urged that the public be kept out and no-trespassing rules be enforced to prevent people from using the old landfill as a park.
Those public access issues have not been resolved, even as a section of the Louisville Loop recreational trail has been developed next to the site.
Tim Hubbard, assistant director of the Kentucky Division of Waste Management, said state and federal regulations allow the government ask the so-called responsible parties to do more if an "approved remedy is not protective based on new data or changing site conditions."
He said state officials believe EPA has enough information to meet those requirements.
"Our goal is to ensure that the Lees Lane site is in a condition which is safe and protective of the citizens and the environment," Hubbard said.
Arnita Gadson, director of the Kentucky Environmental Quality Commission, said she has been working to find a future use for the property, so there could be a clear goal for any new cleanup activities.
Environmental attorney Tom FitzGerald, director of the Kentucky Resources Council, has said the original cleanup was never sufficient because much of the waste was left in place and only a small portion was covered with water-tight clay.
Friday, he praised EPA's decision to go back to the businesses and seek their help.
Reach reporter James Bruggers at (502) 582-4645 or on Twitter @jbruggers.
]]></text></news-item>