<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT6-7DP1-JC3H-03V5"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>5-year term for $565M theft from schools</title><source>Asbury Park Press (New Jersey)</source><author>By, Sergio Bichao</author><text><![CDATA[Michelle Pumilia, the former transportation manager for school districts in Piscataway and Hazlet, was sentenced Friday to five years in prison for stealing more than a half-million dollars from the districts.
Her live-in boyfriend, meanwhile, is facing separate charges of defrauding taxpayers.
Pumilia, 40, of Union Beach, pleaded guilty to the embezzlement charges, admitting that she signed off on purchase orders and issued school district checks to fake bus companies.
She stole about $336,570 from Piscataway and $229,202 from Hazlet, depositing the money in a join bank account she held with her mother, acting Attorney General John J. Hoffman said Friday in a news release.
"When a school official steals this amount of money, it does real harm to both students and overburdened taxpayers," Hoffman said. "The prison sentence Pumilia received should deter others who might be motivated by greed to selfishly exploit their public positions for personal gain."
Superior Court Judge Bradley Ferencz, sitting in New Brunswick, ordered Pumilia to pay back the money. She is barred from holding public employment and must forfeit all public pension and retirement benefits, officials said.
The state filed a forfeiture action in Superior Court in Freehold and obtained a court order to seize four of Pumilia's bank accounts and six vehicles.
Pumilia's scheme included providing district officials with false state business registration certificates for the fake companies.
Pumilia worked as a transportation manager for the Hazlet school system from July 2005 to August 2008. She then was hired in Piscataway in September 2008 and worked there until 2012.
Law-enforcement agencies were alerted after a Piscataway School District employee found suspicious invoices and both districts found irregularities during internal audits.
Charges against her mother, Virginia Lisay, have been dismissed.
Pumilia's boyfriend, Scott M. Callahan, 40, has pleaded guilty to third-degree theft by deception for underreporting his income from a part-time job in order to receive Social Security disability benefits and federal Section 8 housing subsidies. The Social Security benefits totaled $38,794 and the housing subsidies from the Middletown Housing Authority totaled $15,300 over 10 years, authorities said.
Sergio Bichao writes for the Home News Tribune: 908-243-6615; sbichao@mycentral
jersey.com
]]></text></news-item>