<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT6-7DP1-JC3H-0197"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>DNREC labels mulch firm a chronic violator</title><source>The News Journal (Wilmington, Delaware)</source><author>By, Jeff Montgomery</author><text><![CDATA["Designating a facility as a chronic violator is an enforcement tool of last resort to be used when all other regulatory authorities have failed to achieve compliance,"
Collin P. O'Mara
DNREC Secretary
A western Kent County recycling and mulch company has drawn the state's first environmental "chronic violator" label and a potential $8.3 million sanction along with a series of $10,000 per-day fines.
The sanctions come after what state officials said was repeated disregard of earlier cleanup orders and the abandonment of a contaminated site off Willow Grove Road west of Wyoming.
The Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Control said that Mike Davidson Enterprises "demonstrated an unwillingness" to follow state law and "engaged in a pattern of willful neglect and reckless disregard of regulations while taking in construction and demolition wastes for mulch and other uses.
The company's illegal waste stockpiles tripled after DNREC issued a second violation notice to the company in May of 2012 and eventually topped 100,000 tons.
Some of the illegally stored wastes exceed state toxic contamination limits for polychlorinated biphenyls(PCBs), arsenic and chromium. The company's abandoned waste piles caught fire at one point and smoldered for days.
The state's "chronic offender" action ranks as the first since state lawmakers directed the agency to develop more-stringent penalties for the state's worst environmental offenders.
That legislative action followed the explosion of a neglected tank of gasoline-laced sulfuric acid at the Delaware City refinery in 2001. One man died and several were injured in that incident, later traced to longstanding company failures while the refinery was owned by Motiva Enterprises.
"Designating a facility as a chronic violator is an enforcement tool of last resort to be used when all other regulatory authorities have failed to achieve compliance," said DNREC Secretary Collin P. O'Mara said in a written statement.
Attorney General Beau Biden said his agency would work with DNREC to hold the company accountable.
"Polluters cannot be allowed to treat fines as simply a cost of doing business," Biden said.
Problems with the company began in January 2010, two months after the company received a state resource recovery permit. By May 2012, DNREC had taken 14 non-compliance actions, and issued a cease and desist order in June 2012.
The company later appealed and lost, with its permit revoked in August.
Delaware's legal action noted that Davidson had failed to set aside financial reserves for eventual shutdown and cleanup, as required by law.
O'Mara said that the company appeared to have been generating enough revenues to meet its obligations. Davidson instead "has chosen instead to retain such funds for his own use, rather than make necessary investments in the business."
Contact Jeff Montgomery at (302) 463-3344 or jmontgomery@delawareonline.com
"Designating a facility as a chronic violator is an enforcement tool of last resort to be used when all other regulatory authorities have failed to achieve compliance,"
Collin P. O'Mara
DNREC Secretary
]]></text></news-item>