<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT6-F801-DXJR-H179"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Pollution a perennial problem in Old Town in Visakhapatnam South</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Sulogna Mehta</author><text><![CDATA[VISAKHAPATNAM: Visakhapatnam South constituency comprising some of the oldest areas of the Port City, stands out as one of the most diverse, polluted and neglected zones.
The constituency houses the Old Town that has at least a dozen heritage structures including century-old buildings and schools, an 800-year-old mosque and dargah, hilltop temples, churches, the 16th European cemetery and so on. It has the fishing harbour, the port and the biggest state-run hospitals in north coastal Andhra, including the century-old King George Hospital (KGH) and the Victoria or Gosha Hospital.
The main groups residing or working in these areas comprise fisherfolk, Muslims in the Old Town area, doctors and medical staff working in government hospitals and private clinics surrounding KGH. As per January 2014 data, there are more than 1,89,339 registered voters in the constituency.
Local residents point out that pollution has remained a perpetual problem and despite some efforts by the two-time sitting MLA Dronamraju Srinivas, things have failed to brighten up. Besides, there have been other issues such as sanitation to which civic authorities have turned a blind eye.
Septuagenarian Mohammed Ali Khan, president of Haji AbuSarang Mosque Committee and one of the community leaders said, "Over the past decade, D Srinivas, the Congress MLA representing the constituency, did build community halls and made some efforts to bring down pollution, but it's such a major issue that it remains unresolved. Even as coal and iron-ore dust continues to affect the health of all the residents, old heritage buildings remain neglected. Due to blasting activity (blasting of rocks for deepening of channels for ships) cracks have developed in the old mosque. Even though the MLA called up the authorities concerned, after a few days the high-intensity blasts resumed."
Pointing out that the Greater Visakhapatnam Municipal Corporation (GVMC) as well as Visakhapatnam Urban Development Authority (Vuda) should have shared the responsibility of heritage conservation, Khan said: "Certain government departments in connivance with the Vizag Port Trust are trying to destroy these heritage structures. Besides, no attention is being paid to sanitation."
So resigned are the residents to their fate that they feel that even if any other political party comes to power, there won't be any significant change in their situation. "At least the present MLA had been trying to do some work. Things won't get any better for us if other power-hungry parties come to power."
Similar opinions are expressed by a representative of the fishermen's community. There are around 12,000 people involved in fishing-related activities in the area. "Be it Congress, TDP, YSRCP, BJP or any other party, before the elections all of them make tall promises but forget everything later. We don't know who to trust," avers J D Naidu, secretary, Vizag Fishing Harbour and Workers' Union.
"Though we are getting benefits of certain central government schemes, the state government hasn't done anything for us. From mid-April to June 1, fishing holiday (no fishing activity in the sea) has been declared by the government without making any alternative arrangements for our livelihood. Though the MLA did visit us sometimes and also took back a memorandum on our problems to be submitted to the chief minister, nothing concrete came out of it. We didn't get 50 kg rice and Rs 200 per day for these 47 days of fishing holiday, nor is there any insurance for fishermen and trawler drivers. The port pollution has been affecting the fish catch but even that issue is not addressed," rued Naidu.
Apart from these two communities, several doctors who reside and work in areas under the Vizag South constituency were quite critical about the sorry state of affairs and lack of basic amenities at KGH. "Pollution has seriously debilitated nearly 50% of the Old Town residents in some way or the other while almost all the residents suffer from health problems associated with the 24x7 dust pollution. No arrangement has been made to cover the coal and iron-ore units near Convent Junction with tarpaulin sheets, which could have reduced the pollution to some extent," stated a government doctor.
Another doctor complained that local politicians were allowing encroachment of KGH land while no residential quarters for medical staff or drinking water or drainage facilities were being built inside the hospital. "Possibly TDP has a better chance to bargain this time but we don't think there will be any improvement to these government hospitals irrespective of whoever comes to power," concluded a doctor.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>