<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT6-F801-DXJR-H0K7"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Chopper scam: Recovering money paid to AgustaWestland looks difficult</title><source>The Economic Times</source><author>Dhananjay Mahapatra</author><text><![CDATA[NEW DELHI: Chances of India recovering Rs 2360 crore already paid to AgustaWestland for supply of 12 VVIP helicopters, a deal scrapped after delivery of three copters, appeared bleak as a Milan court stalled its move to encash 278 million bank guarantees given by the Italian firm.
In January, the defence ministry decided to encash bank guarantees given by Agusta through Deutsche Bank to recover its payments — around 45 per cent of the total contract value of 556 million euros — to the company.
MoD officials had said there were "enough safeguards" built into the integrity pact and the contract inked with AgustaWestland, the UK-based subsidiary of Italian conglomerate Finmeccanica, in February 2010 to "protect India's interests" and impose "punitive damages" on the company, said officials.
Within days of the MoD taking a decision to encash bank guarantees, Agusta approached two former Chief Justices of India — 77-year-old Justice GB Patnaik and 67-year-old Justice SH Kapadia — asking whether India would be legally entitled to encash its bank guarantees since it had part performed the contract by supplying 3 of the 12 AW 101 VVIP helicopters.
Both the advance bank guarantees had identical clause — "We, the (Deutsche) Bank, hereby undertake to pay the amount due and payable under this guarantee without any demur merely on a demand from the government stating that the amount claimed is due" because the seller breached the contract.
It further said, "Any such demand made to the bank shall be conclusive as regards the amount due and payable by the bank under this guarantee." Importantly the bank also promised — "We, the Bank, undertake to pay to the Government any money so demanded notwithstanding any dispute or disputes raised by the Seller in any suit to proceedings pending before any court or Tribunal relating thereto, our liability under this present guarantee being absolute and unequivocal."
The two CJIs appeared to ignore settled positions laid down by the Supreme Court and gave opinions that these bank guarantees could not be invoked by India.
Justice Kapadia said: "Agusta would be entitled to an interim order of injunction against invocation of the advance bank guarantees, the warranty bond and the performance bond by the government of India, ministry of defence till completion of arbitration proceedings. Till date, the tribunal is not constituted."
Justice Patnaik went into the reliability of evidence about bribery and middlemen. "The matter (bribery in procurement of deals for Agusta) is subjudice in Italian court and no conclusion has been reached by the competent court so far, those materials therefore may not be of sufficient" for the ministry to conclude that the contract was breached and invoke the bank guarantees.
But additional solicitor general Gourab Banerji extracted a series of Supreme Court judgments, especially since both the bank guarantees and performance bond expressly subjected themselves to Indian law, giving a contrary view to the opinion of the two ex-CJIs.
In Mahatma Gandhi Sakkare Karkhane case [2006 (7) SCC 470], the SC had said: "In our considered opinion if the bank guarantee furnished is an unconditional and irrevocable one, it is not open to the bank to raise any objection whatsoever to pay the amounts under the guarantee."
It also said: "The person in whose favour the guarantees is furnished by the bank cannot be prevented by way of an injunction in enforcing the guarantee on the pretext that the condition for enforcing the bank guarantee in terms of the agreement entered between the parties has not been fulfilled. Such a course is impermissible."
But, given the weight of opinion of two former heads of judiciary in India, there was little hesitation for the Milan court to grant an injunction to Deutsche Bank against encashment of its guarantees.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>