<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT8-K0D1-DYT5-335D"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Czech court releases all accused in public transport case</title><source>CTK National News Wire</source><author>hol</author><text><![CDATA[A Prague district court today released the remaining three accused of money laundering in the case of tickets for the Prague Transport Company (DPP) today.
The court rejected the state attorney's proposal for remanding lobbyist and businessman Ivo Rittig and lawyer Marek Stubley on Friday.
Today, Rittig's business partner Peter Kmet, Neograph printing offices former executive Jan Janku and Stubley's colleague from the MSB Legal firm, lawyer David Michal were released as well.
The police detained all the accused on Friday morning.
State attorney Adam Borgula, however, justified the proposal for custody by fears that the accused would escape abroad to avoid criminal proceedings.
They face three to eight years in prison and forfeiture of property if found guilty.
The state attorneys proposed in February that the passports be seized from the accused instead of remanding them in custody and a district court met the proposal. Rittig and the other defendants appealed the decision with the Prague Municipal Court, which found the seizure unlawful and unfounded.
The court decided similarly in the case of Kmet, Janku and Michal.
The accused criticised the attorneys' procedure and questioned the alleged reasons for their custody.
The DPP signed a contract on tickets printing with Neograph, which was mediated by the Cokeville Assets company from the British Virgin Islands represented by Kmet.
According to investigators, Neograph, controlled by Rittig, Michal and Stubley, sent 0.17 crown from every sold ticket to Kmet's firm.
The Anti-corruption Endowment says the money probably ended in Rittig's hands.
The DPP terminated the contract with Neograph in 2011. Since 2012, the State Printing Shop of Stamps has supplied the tickets. It later won a five-year contract worth 170 million crowns on tickets supplies until 2017.
($1=19.922 crowns)
hol/dr
]]></text></news-item>