<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT8-XJP1-JDV5-F43J"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Well owners uneasy about Line 9; Residents on their own to monitor private well water</title><source>Waterloo Region Record</source><author>Greg Mercer, Record staff</author><text><![CDATA[Patty and Robert Doud have lived at the corner of Lockie and Branchton roads for a quarter century. Line 9, just a few dozen metres away, has been there even longer.
You can stand on their front lawn and see the orange signs that mark the oil pipeline's underground route, cutting across the southern edge of Waterloo Region on its way to refineries in Sarnia.
For years, Line 9 has pumped thousands of barrels of crude oil past their house every day, largely out of sight and out of mind. But lately, the Douds and many of their neighbours have become uneasy about living so close to the buried fuel artery.
What has Ritchie and other people in this corner of North Dumfries concerned is a new plan by energy giant Enbridge, recently approved by the National Energy Board, to reverse the flow of oil and start pumping a higher volume through Line 9.
The problem is, the Douds, like most people along Lockie Road in North Dumfries Township, get their water from a private well. They say that means they don't have the same protection from the threat of oil spills as people who get their water from a municipal well.
"It's like we're second-class citizens," said Robert Doud. "I don't want some putz from the region eventually working his way down here saying, 'you know, you really shouldn't be drinking your water.' "
For township residents on municipal wells, it's a different story. Their water is monitored regularly for contamination, including from petroleum products, by regional staff, and people are alerted whenever there's a problem.
The township admits private well owners need to take precautions into their own hands.
"If you're on a private well, you're on your own," said Rodger Mordue, the chief administrator of North Dumfries Township. "You're supposed to look after your own water, and testing is up to you."
Private well owners can get free water tests for bacteria through the region's public health unit. But if they're worried about oil contamination, they're referred to private companies who charge about $250 a test.
Neil Ritchie, the township councillor who lives in Branchton where most residents are on private wells, says his neighbours deserve better protection than that. And with roughly 700 to 800 properties with private wells in North Dumfries, the issue could affect a lot of people, he said.
"My kids are drinking that water," he said. "If there's an underground spill, we have no expertise and we have no help."
Residents wonder if the Enbridge plan puts their water at greater risk of contamination from the nearly 40-year-old pipeline.
Patty Doud says the threat is high enough the region should start testing private well owners' water for oil on a regular basis - acting proactively before there's a problem.
But Eric Hodgins, the region's manager of water resources protection, said it's not the municipality's job to monitor private wells. He encourages people to get their water tested if they're worried - but says those best-equipped to proactively monitor for contamination are oil companies themselves.
"If some private owners are concerned about leaks from the pipe, then they should be checking their wells now, to get a benchmark," he said. "But our responsibilities are limited to the water supply we operate."
In the event of a significant spill where the province is involved, the region's public health unit would notify affected residents - including people on a private well, Hodgins added. But pre-emptive testing of private wells is simply not in their mandate.
Enbridge is also required to report any pipeline leaks it finds, but many here don't feel reassured putting their health in the hands of an oil company.
"It's very unsettling," said Deborah Mariano, who lives on Hughson Road, just up the street from Line 9. "It's not a matter of if there's a spill, it's a matter of when... "
Mariano says the company has a poor track record on preventing spills and can't be trusted to keep residents safe. She points to a Polaris Institute report that suggests Enbridge's vast network of pipelines has had 804 spills between 1999 and 2010.
She's worried about the plan for Line 9, which she says will put a more corrosive and acidic product known as diluted bitumen in the pipeline. Mariano says that makes it more vulnerable to leaks.
Despite a door-to-door public awareness campaign that was supposed to inform people living within 60 metres of the pipeline right of way, she believes many people were left in the dark about the plans for Line 9.
The Douds, and other residents, say they've never received a visit, a phone call, or a letter explaining what was happening to the oil pipeline just down their road.
"I think it's still below the radar. I don't think a lot of people are even aware of it," Mariano said.
Enbridge, meanwhile, says no one wants to prevent spills more than it does. In 2012 alone, it spent more than $800 million to protect the safety of its pipeline network.
While it has "no regulatory obligation" to test residents' wells as a precaution, according to company spokesperson Graham White, the responsibility lies fully on Enbridge if there is a problem.
"If there is a leak, it is fully our responsibility to inform landowners, residents and any other community members who may be affected," he said.
The company is also on the hook to provide clean drinking water to residents during the cleanup and must perform testing and monitoring afterward to ensure it's effective, White said.
Susan Bryant, a water expert with a local non-profit group's rural well testing program, says residents' concerns are justified. It wouldn't "take much oil to constitute a serious threat" to an aquifer, she said, and the Branchton area's sandy soil could make it more vulnerable to contamination.
The township's fire chief Robert Shantz says no one can guarantee there won't be a leak. But he points out there's never been a problem with the pipeline within the boundaries of North Dumfries.
"We've never had a spill in the township," Shantz said. "And we don't want a spill."
There have, however, been spills along the pipeline, and some not too far from the North Dumfries' boundary.
Enbridge has reported 12 spills along Line 9 since it was built in 1976. But an investigation by CTV's W5 program found the energy giant didn't report leaks that happened at company facilities attached to the pipeline.
If you include those, there's been 35 spills associated with Line 9 - including six spills at the Westover terminal, less than 10 kilometres from the Region of Waterloo border - according to Ministry of Environment records.
There was another 1,000-litre spill north of Hamilton in 1979, caused by a crack in the pipeline, the company said. Last summer, crews discovered damage in the pipeline near where it crosses Highway 8 south of Cambridge, which may have been caused by an excavator.
Ritchie says the township should be alarmed by this history of incidents. Branchton's wells all pull from the same bowl-shaped underground aquifer, and a spill in one area could affect a wide number of residents, he said.
"Our mayor hasn't taken this seriously," he said. "I don't see how anyone couldn't see this as a threat, when there's no protocols in place."
But the township's mayor, Robert Deutschmann, says he's just as concerned about his resident's safety as anyone.
"No concern is overblown when it comes to this issue," he said, in an email. "We certainly share the concerns of our residents. ... The Township, along with the region, is concerned about any potential impacts to the water supply of our residents."
Deutschmann says that "the issue of pipeline and rail delivery of crude is a concern" beyond just Line 9 - since there's a rail line running through Ayr and a shunting station in the neighbouring Township of Blandford-Blenheim.
He said that's why he pushed a motion at regional council that asked the National Energy Board to demand more integrity tests along Line 9 and a larger insurance fund available for any potential spills.
Shantz, the fire chief, admitted there were questions about the condition of the nearly 40-year-old pipeline. But he believes the strict rules around monitoring and inspections put in place by the National Energy Board will make the pipeline safer.
"The township does have a concern about that as it gets older," Shantz said. "But some of the directives from the National Energy Board address that, and they include many more inspections."
Shantz' fire department was one of several agencies that took part in a mock oil spill exercise last September around the W.D. Foulds Bridge in Glen Morris, where the pipeline crosses the Grand River.
And while the focus of that exercise was around containing a spill in the river, he says they're always ready in the event of a spill anywhere in the township.
With six pipelines that run across North Dumfries - three that carry natural gas, two for oil and one for refined products such as jet fuel - plus a rail line, the municipality has long been prepared for an emergency spill from any one of them.
"This isn't really anything new to us," he said. "Our mandate has always been to make the area safe."
In the event of a spill, Enbridge is responsible for any cleanup, Shantz said. Police and fire would focus on emergency response, such as evacuating people if necessary.
None of the other pipelines in the township are under the same scrutiny as the contentious Line 9, which has been carrying oil underground without a local problem since 1976, the fire chief added.
"Before this, they never realized the pipeline was in their neighbourhood," Shantz said.
But Ritchie says residents' concerns are being dismissed by township officials who he says are downplaying the risks of living in the shadow of the pipeline. People on private wells have a reason to be alarmed, he said.
"Chief Shantz is not a water expert," Ritchie said. "I'm concerned about the underground water, and we have no protection. I've had constituents call me up, and they're concerned, too."
gmercer@therecord.com, Twitter: @MercerRecord
]]></text></news-item>