<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT9-7R01-F0NV-F06R"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>LETTERS TO THE EDITOR</title><source>The Milford Daily News (Massachusetts)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Listen to the 97 percent
Sumner Weisman criticizes Ed Markey, Al Gore, and John Kerry for having an opinion about climate change without having graduate degrees in climate science ("Support for a climate change skeptic. March 18) It is silly to demand that a representative have an advanced degree in a topic before legislating on it. Does a politician need an art history degree to vote on funding the NEA?
Markey, Gore, and Kerry believe climate change is a grave danger because 97 percent of climate scientists believe climate change is a grave danger. Climate change deniers are labeled "flat earthers" mainly because they believe climate skeptics who have no expertise in climate science. For example, one of the lead skeptics is Steve McIntyre, a semi-retired mining expert who had a lead role in the "climategate" controversy which has since been discredited. Another highly public climate denier is Ross McKittrick, an economics professor who signed the Christian-fundamentalist sponsored Cornwall Declaration which states that climate change is an "unfounded or undue concern," even before he began attacking climate scientists.
The list of climate change deniers relying on specious logic is long, but 97 percent of legitimate climate scientists believe that our climate is approaching a crisis point. By listening to writers like Weisman we are wasting valuable time hashing over questions that are settled. We need to do something now to reduce carbon pollution. Putting a tax on carbon-polluting fuels would be a good first step.
JACK THORNDIKE
Boston
Those who helped Santa's helpers
We would like to thank the Ashland businesses and residents who made it possible for us to provide two absolutely wonderful holiday parties-one for special needs children and one for low-income families. Thank you for having faith in us and answering our wishes for these children during the holiday season.
We would like to send a special thanks to Santa who always makes it through for the children!
A thank you to Middlesex Savings Bank for their trust in us.
A thank you to Extra Space Storage. Without you, we would not have been able to store our donations.
A thank you to the town residents who supported us and called with ideas and trying to help our organization the best they could (there are so many of you). Some had just a kind word of encouragement, others jumped in happily and made sure these parties were a success.
A thank you to Chris at Papa Gino's for being there at the last minute and saving the day!
A thank you for one special lady. We really had no cash budget for the parties. In the checkout line, this very nice lady behind her asked why she was buying so much sugar at eight o'clock in the morning. Nicole explained that she was throwing a party for low-income children. The woman immediately said....I'm paying for your order. Thank you so much, for your faith in me and Stan, trusting my words (so many people thought we were scam artists), and for helping these kids.
Thank you all so much!
NICOLE L. KIDSON
STAN FEINBERG
Ashland
]]></text></news-item>