<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BT9-99X1-F12F-F48B"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Firm Manager Held for Rs 6.25 cr Tax Evasion</title><source>New Indian Express</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[BHUBANESWAR, March 22 -- The Central Excise, Customs and Service Tax Commissionerate has arrested the Regional Manager of East Coast Construction and Industries MT, Abubacker Ariff, for evasion of service tax to the tune of a whopping '6.25 crore.
The Central Preventive Unit of Central Excise, Customs and Service Tax's Bhubaneswar Commissionerate-I carried out the arrest and produced Ariff before the Chief Judicial Magistrate, Cuttack on Thursday. He has been sent to judicial custody for 15 days. This is the first ever arrest in service tax evasion in Odisha.
Acting on a tip-off, the Central Preventive Unit of the Commissionerate, headed by Assistant Commissioner (Preventive), conducted a search operation at the unregistered office of East Coast Constructions at Sahid Nagar on March 19. Though the company was found to have been registered since 2009, it had not filed any service tax returns for long.
The firm, Central Excise sources said, was involved in work contract and real estate business. Though it had been collecting service tax from its clients, East Coast Construction and Industries did not deposit the same with the department for the last four years.
Similarly, the company changed its office's location from the original registered premises to Sahid Nagar without intimating the department and was running from two floors of an apartment.
While the Preventive Unit seized huge volumes of incriminating documents relating to service tax evasion, the ongoing investigation is likely to bring more information about the company's dealings to the fore.
A case has been booked under Section 89 of the Finance Act, 1994 which is a cognisable offence and attracts imprisonment up to seven years. Since May 2013, about 20 such arrests have been made across the country. "We have lead on more companies which have evaded service tax and similar action will follow in the near future," said a senior official.
Fraudster Detained
Bhubaneswar: A man was detained on Friday for allegedly swindling '19,000 from a family in Balipatana.
He has been identified as Sarat Sahoo, a resident of Niali. Sahoo has been detained in connection with the case where the family was duped on the pretext of a business deal.
Sources said a CCTV footage from a bank led to Sahoo's arrest. The accused has also been charged with molesting a member of the family. ens
Published by HT Syndication with permission from New Indian Express. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>