<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTB-R8M1-DYX1-N0J2"><date>2014-03-23</date><title></title><source>Star-News (Wilmington, NC)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Another reason to oppose Titan
Your article about Duke Energy's "tweaking" of state law to circumvent future cleanup of areas contaminated by leaching from unlined coal ash dumps should be an eye-opener. The GOP-controlled legislature seems intent on weakening or dismantling most of our existing environmental protections with our governor manning the helm.
As a physician opposed to the proposed Titan Cement plant, this story gives me more reason to continue to oppose the project because of its risks to public health and the environment. If you think, as Titan executives are quick to say, that state law will protect you with existing regulations and they should be allowed to do business as proposed, read the article.
You will see exactly who the folks in Raleigh are going to protect.
Edgar O. Horger IV, M.D., Wilmington
Pricey parking at Wrightsville
General inflation has been running less than 3 percent for the past five years. However, Wrightsville Beach feels it's OK to raise the price of parking by 25 percent. Insane.
The least the town could do is provide the people of New Hanover County with the opportunity to purchase a yearly parking pass at a fixed price that can be purchased before the summer season.
I know I am tired of subsidizing the island's homeowners' property taxes.
Dan Carpenito, Wilmington
Crimea situation none of our business
Any claim by the European Union and our administration that the vote for secession by the residents of Ukraine's Crimea region violates international law is hypocritical. When South Sudan residents voted to split Sudan into two countries, the U.S. and the E.U. supported that action.
Numerous countries in Africa have been created over the last 20 years with our support, even without residents given the opportunity to vote on the action.
It is reasonable for Russia to be concerned about their area of influence and security in the area so critical to them, just as we were concerned about Cuba back in the 1960s. It seems the administration is simply exploiting a situation to take the focus off our domestic problems, and give the appearance of a strong foreign policy. President Obama tried that with Syria, and his pathetic "red line" statement.
Crimea's vote to back secession - and potential annexation with Russia - reflects a belief that politicians in Kiev are not concerned with the welfare of its majority-Russian population.
How can we, and the international community - with a straight face - claim that exercise of self-determination by the people of Crimea will not be recognized, merely because we wanted a different outcome?
I believe we should mind our own business, and stay out of something we have very little ability to have a positive impact on.
James W. Currin, Wilmington
]]></text></news-item>