<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTB-P8B1-JC3H-02P0"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Duke's coal ash pollution worries residents</title><source>The Asheville Citizen-Times (North Carolina)</source><author>By, Clarke Morrison</author><text><![CDATA[and John Boyle
View Duke Energy well contamination in a larger map
Cory Gibney lives a good four hours' drive from the spot where a ruptured stormwater pipe unleashed a torrent of coal ash slurry into the Dan River.
That spill from a Duke Energy power plant near Eden launched a statewide investigation into the utility's handling of coal ash and whether North Carolina regulators have been cozy with the company.
But Gibney's concern is far more local. A monitoring well at Duke's Lake Julian plant in Asheville sits about 200 yards from his condominium.
Evidence of a toxic metal has been found in that well, and Gibney fears he knows more about what happened in the Dan River than he knows about contamination happening near his own backyard.
Letters from Duke to state regulators show the utility has acted in a way that would allow the company to expand areas in which contamination can legally spread before forcing a cleanup, an expansion that has happened next to Lake Julian Trails, a newer complex of condominiums where Gibney lives.
"I have two children, a 2- and 3-year-old, and the last thing I want to worry about is contamination issues while they grow up," he said.
Progress Energy, which was acquired by Duke in a 2012 merger, bought 5.2 acres next to the Asheville plant for $1.1 million from Lake Julian Trails LLC.
That purchase in 2010 allowed the utility to dig a new monitoring well farther out from the utility's two coal ash ponds, which had already shown signs of spreading contamination. One pond was built in 1964 and the other in 1982.
Together they cover about 91 acres.
Each of Duke Energy's 33 coal ash lagoons across the state is surrounded by a "compliance boundary" beyond which groundwater contamination isn't supposed to be allowed to spread.
If toxins exceed state environmental standards, the company is supposed to take corrective action to stop it from spreading to neighboring properties.
Buying time, critics say
The $1.1 million Duke paid for Lake Julian Trails land is not out of line with other larger land purchases in the same timeframe, according to Buncombe County land records.
But the purchase and relocation of the well were all about buying time to avoid a costly cleanup, according to DJ Gerken, an attorney with the Southern Environmental Law Center in Asheville.
"I think they had every reason to believe the pollution was there, but moving the boundary well and insisting that they start over on the sampling, bought time," he said. "And everything Duke has been doing with respect to groundwater contamination is to buy time."
In a July 2012 letter to the N.C. Department of Environment & Natural Resources, Garry Whisnant, plant manager at Duke's Lake Julian power plant, proposed "a few changes to the groundwater monitoring plan for the ash ponds at the Asheville Plant." He cited an attached map that showed proposed locations for two new wells.
"Note that additional property has been purchased which results in a slight shift of the compliance boundary," Whisnant wrote, noting that the existing monitoring well was no longer in the compliance boundary.
That well had detected groundwater pollution from thallium, a bluish-white metal found in coal ash that can cause serious health problems, including nervous system issues and problems with internal organs.
The new well on the former Lake Julian Trails property, located about 300 feet from the well it replaced and not far from a nearby rental unit, also turned up excessive amounts of thallium.
A black fence with a locked gate now separates the land from the condominium complex.
But Gibney said children sometimes find their way onto the tainted land.
"They sneak through the fence on the back side over there," he said. "They should have their fences better secured.
"I think our entire neighborhood should have a better understanding as to the contamination issues. I'm sure if our neighbors knew that they would not let their kids over there at all."
A Duke spokesman on Friday did not respond to questions for this article.
The Feb. 2 spill of tens of thousands of tons of toxic coal ash into the Dan River from a Duke lagoon near Eden also worries Lake Julian Trails resident Scott Robinson.
"As far as I'm concerned (Duke) has a really bad track record - like what they did with the Dan River," he said. "If they messed up on that grand of scale, then what are they going to do here?"
To Robinson, 38, who lives in the subdivision with his mother, the utility's purchase of the former neighborhood property "sounds like another cover-up."
"It should definitely be researched and looked into," he said.
The neighborhood is on city water. But Donna Keiser, who has lived there for five years, said she's concerned about possible soil contamination. A sign hangs on the fence a few yards from her back door warning people to stay off the power plant's property.
"I'm afraid to grow any type of produce or vegetable," she said. "I buy bottled water out of fear."
Keiser also is disturbed by dust that periodically rains down on the neighborhood.
"I don't feel that it's a safe place to live," she said. "If there is a break in that coal ash dam, all of that waste material is going to run down toward the river."
Monitoring wells, boundary lines
Gerken said state environmental laws regarding water pollution have taken a relatively simple approach for decades: Stop groundwater pollution before it happens, but if it does happen stop it as quickly as possible.
"That's how our laws are put together and those are the laws Duke has been evading for years, by putting this off as long as possible and getting away with contaminating groundwater as long as possible," Gerken said.
In 2010 and 2011, the N.C. Division of Water Quality assisted Duke Energy and Progress Energy in developing groundwater monitoring plans for each of their coal power facilities with ash ponds.
DENR defines a compliance boundary as "a boundary around a disposal system at and beyond which groundwater quality standards may not be exceeded." For disposal systems permitted before December 1983, including the Lake Julian facility, the compliance boundary is established at a horizontal distance of 500 feet from the waste boundary, or at the property boundary, whichever is closer.
Gerken thinks DENR officials in Raleigh have been too accommodating to Duke, but he says local officials were trying to enforce the regulations as written. What Duke was trying to do was "reset that multiyear" water monitoring clock by putting a new well on the new land, a little farther from an area known to have pollution, he added.
"Duke said, 'Let's move (the monitoring well) out all the way to the edge of the new property line," Gerken said. "To which the state said, 'No, now the 500-foot limit is the closest point, so you can't go out further than 500 feet from the coal ash. The state did not agree to move that well as far as Duke wanted to move it, but it did get moved."
DENR spokeswoman Susan Massengale said the addition of land does not automatically change the compliance boundary. That would require a modification to Duke's permit, which is under review.
Gerken also contends that Duke has employed stalling tactics when it comes to excedences and acknowledging any violations. DENR needs "several years of groundwater monitoring data to have the statistical confidence that Duke had caused violation of standards," Gerken said.
That creates more doubt for Matthew Layer, who serves on the board of the Lake Julian Trails Homeowners Association. Layer said he wants to know more about possible contamination in the neighborhood and what will happen next.
"I'm not really sure what's happening," he said. "Is it in our water? How far is it spreading? What's going to happen it the next five years? It would be good to know."
Timeline on land purchase
2012
Dec. 10: Duke buys 5.2 acres from Lake Julian Trails LLC. The property is just south of its coal ash dumps and will ultimately accommodate a new monitoring well.
July 9: Duke proposes changes to groundwater monitoring plan for its ash ponds, including a new well on the former Lake Julian Trails property. The proposed site is farther from the ash ponds than the existing monitoring well.
Aug. 22: Asheville office of N.C. Departmennt of Environment and Natural Resources rejects proposal, noting that the site is too far from the ponds and existing monitoring wells. DENR also notes that the well to be replaced, as well as three other groundwater monitoring wells, have all exceeded acceptable levels for thallium, a toxic metal found in coal ash.
2013
Feb. 20: DENR sends letter to Duke stating "changes to groundwater monitoring," including the addition and use of the new well on the former Lake Julian Trails property, now meet requirements and are in effect.
Source: Letters between Duke, DENR
]]></text></news-item>