<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTB-JH01-JDKC-R3DH"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>CHEAPER THAN CATTLE</title><source>Hindustan Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Kolkata, March 23 -- Rubina appears much older than the 40 years she admits to. She does not look you in the eye; she is hardly audible, and often trembles. Her hut, on the outskirts of Guhana village in Haryana's Mewat district, is surrounded by garbage heaps and excreta. There is no water or electricity and the hut is filled with acrid smoke from the cooking fire. "This is how our stories end," she says, shooing away a stray dog.
Widowed three months ago, she was thrown out by her in-laws as she is a paro or molki ('molki' literally means 'one who has a price') - the terms used for women who have been purchased in other states and brought to the region. These are pejorative labels in Haryana, Punjab and western Uttar Pradesh where the skewed sex ratio and entrenched feudalism has resulted in a flourishing trade in women trafficked from the poverty-ridden villages of Assam, West Bengal, Jharkhand and Odisha. In this variant of modern slavery, the women, who are usually promised marriage, find themselves in places like Mewat where the go-betweens sell them - sometimes repeatedly - to men who cannot find local women. Cut off from their native states, they are forced to work as bonded labour or pushed into forced marriages or prostitution. The molki phenomenon is now so common that these areas even have common sayings that refer to the condition of these women - like the one that says it's impossible to find a paro's grave as she is passed on from man to man and so doesn't stay in one place for long. "We paros belong nowhere. We are treated like animals. If a man has to choose between leaving a local woman and one from outside, he kicks us out; if a man is in need of money, we are sold," said Rubina, originally from Assam, who was forced into marriage at 16.
A field study by the NGO Drishti Stree Adhyayan Prabodhan Kendra revealed that out of 10,000 households they surveyed in Haryana, over 9,000 married women were bought from other states.
Less than two hours drive from New Delhi, Mewat is one of the 21 districts of Haryana, which has the most imbalanced sex ratio in the country - 879 women for every 1,000 men against the national average of 927 to 1,000. "More than 30 per cent of men in Haryana between the ages of 15 and 44 are unmarried because of the skewed sex ratio. When they don't get women locally, they obtain them from other states," said Dr Prem Chowdhry, former fellow with Nehru Memorial Museum and Library, Delhi, who has worked extensively on shifting marriage patterns in north India.
Although HT visited Mewat, which has a large Muslim population, paros and their purchasers cut across community lines. "In Jind, I have come across Hindu and Christian women from Odisha, West Bengal and Jharkhand," said Susmita Guru, senior researcher with Indian Social Institute, Delhi.
Village heads in Mewat revealed that early marriages and economic factors add to the problem. Indeed, the trade in women is now accepted as normal in this area. "Families here don't give their daughters to men who are older than 20, poor, handicapped or widowed. If you belong to any of these categories, you will have to buy a bride," said Zakir Hussain, sarpanch of Luhinga Khurd village. "In every village, you will find at least 15 paros. It is common here," he added.
According to the 2011 census, about 72 per cent of the population in rural Haryana, including more than 60 per cent of the women, is literate. Nearby Gurgaon is an IT hub and hosts many automobile manufacturing units including Maruti Suzuki. But that's only part of the picture. 70 per cent of the state's population continues to be engaged in the agricultural sector.
Shafiq Ur Rehman, founder, Empower People, an NGO working with survivors of bride trafficking, said the practice is rooted in the history of the region. "North India, including Haryana, has been a battle ground. Polygamy, and the claiming of women with jewellery and property as war prizes, was common," he said. The National Crime Records Bureau report, 2012, shows that more than 22,000 girl children and women between the ages of 10 and 30 were kidnapped for marriage.
"The demand for 'marriageable age' girls is so intense that organised trafficking rackets have started operating in Haryana, Punjab and Uttar Pradesh," said a 2013 report commissioned by the United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime.
Ghausia Khan, bride trafficking survivor and a member of a district legal aid authority reveals that, on average, a girl is sold between two to five times. "You will never find a paro staying with the man who brings her here," she said. This is borne out by Rubina, who was sold twice before she settled with her husband.
In Kaithwada, a village in Rajasthan's Bharatpur, roughly 100 kilometres from Mewat, we met Mohammad Gulshan (45), who regularly procures women. "Assam and Kolkata are the two places which send girls in bulk," he said taking a break from working in his mustard field to reveal a few tricks of his part-time trade. "Poor people in these states find it difficult to get their daughters married as they cannot afford the dowry. If they send their girls to Haryana, they don't have to give any dowry. Plus, they get money in return. On the other hand, the men in Haryana get women, who are not locally available," he said. Gulshan's current wife, a native of Bihar, was bought for a mere
' 3,900. The trade relies on trust. "I have contacts in Bihar who can trust me and can easily send the girls with me," he said.
According to Shafique, the price of a paro varies between ' 5,000 and ' 30,000 depending on her age and features. "The only person who gets money in the process is the middle man," he said rejecting the notion that parents sell their daughters out of poverty.
Given her transformation into a commodity that can be bought and sold, the woman has no say in her fate. Whether she serves as a bonded labourer, a sex slave, a house maid, or will be accorded the status of a wife all depends on the inclinations and circumstances of her buyer. While some, like Rubina, are abandoned after the death of their husbands, others live with the humiliation of being a paro. Married or not, they are never treated at par with local women. "Sending local women out to work in the field is not considered good here. Paros serve as cheap labour," said Susmita Guru.
Most of the trafficked women were unwilling to talk as they fear being ostracized by the villagers. This poses a challenge to NGOs who cannot intervene unless a woman registers a protest or if a case of trafficking has been clearly established. As a result, much of their work is limited to case documentation. The authorities are similarly handicapped. "We are yet to get a single complaint where a girl alleges that she was bought. Even for suo-moto action, we have to follow some leads. But none exist," said Mewat SP Anil Dhawan.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from HT Kolkata. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>