<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTB-JHD1-JD3N-52D7"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>It's all getting a bit murky for the Libs</title><source>The Advertiser (Australia)</source><author>SAMANTHA MAIDEN COMMENT</author><text><![CDATA[WHEN Assistant Treasurer Arthur Sinodinos announced to a near empty Senate chamber that he was standing aside pending a NSW anti-corruption investigation, one man sat silently behind him.
It was Bill Heffernan. He is no small player in the controversy engulfing the Liberal Party involving the ICAC, Australian Water Holdings, the Obeid family, political donations and former NSW minister Chris Hartcher.
But his involvement has remained largely hidden.
Something of a law unto himself, Heffernan emerges from the story as a self-appointed corruption-buster who spent months chasing the mystery behind EightByFive, a suspected unauthorised Liberal Party slush fund that is now the subject of an ICAC investigation. What Heffernan didn't know in the beginning was that AWH, the company of which Sinodinos was the chairman, was also making payments to EightByFive for "public relations" reasons.
ICAC is investigating whether these regular payments were designed to ensure that "Christopher Hartcher MP favoured the interests of Australian Water Holdings Pty Limited and the circumstances in which false allegations of corruption were made against senior executives of Sydney Water Corporation." It will also probe whether MPs and others including a Hartcher staffer, Ray Carter, "solicited, received and failed to disclose political donations from companies including prohibited donors." There is no suggestion that Sinodinos knew that EightByFive might also being used to funnel political donations for an unauthorised Liberal Party slush fund. ICAC has made no allegation or finding of corruption against Sinodinos.
Heffernan even interrogated Sinodinos in NSW Liberal Party candidate review committee process in 2011 as a delegate of the Liberal leader.
His concern at the time was to ensure that Sinodinos's business interests did not yield any "surprises" for the party down the track according to witnesses. Good instinct. Two years ago, when Heffernan uncovered what he believed to be secret donations to a fund the Liberals HQ had never heard of, from a property developer who was prohibited from making donations, he acted.
A failed Liberal candidate, Matthew Lusted, mentioned he had donated to the Liberal Party.
Heffernan asked to see the receipt. When Lusted handed him a copy of the $5000 receipt, Heffernan informed him he would have to report it as he believed it breached electoral laws banning donations from property developers.
It also transpired the ABN number on the receipt was invalid but a GST component was charged. According to colleagues, Heffernan set out on a personal mission to find out what EightByFive was. Heffernan also rang the mobile on the EightByFive invoice. "Who are you?" he asked when a man picked up. The answer was Tim Koelma, a staffer in NSW minister Chris Hartcher's office.
Koelma and another Hartcher staffer, Ray Carter, were suspended while investigations began. The NSW Liberals referred it to electoral authorities and ICAC.
Some have suggested Sinodinos had relied on the factional support of Hartcher to get preselected.
Others maintain the claim that Sinodinos needed Hartcher, who is now a major focus of ICAC inquiry, is ridiculous.Ultimately, Sinodinos should have known better. In politics as in life, judgments are often made about the company you keep.
]]></text></news-item>