<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTB-P8B1-JC3H-04JV"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Proposed law would be blow to disabled and to whistleblowers</title><source>The Jackson Sun (Jackson, Tennessee)</source><author>By, Justin Gilbert and Wade Cowan</author><text><![CDATA[An important vote will be held in the Tennessee General Assembly this week that would restrict the rights of Tennessee whistleblowers and Tennesseans with disabilities. The bill is known as "House Bill 1954" or HB1954.
Tennessee whistleblowers take an ethical stand against wrongdoing, often at great risk to their jobs. National cases such as Watergate, Enron, Karen Silkwood, and Big Tobacco may come to mind. Currently, in Tennessee, whistleblowers are protected from being fired whenever they refuse to engage in illegal activity, or whenever they report it - orally or in writing.
HB1954 would change all that. Under this bill, job protection for whistleblowers would extend only to those who make a report of illegal activity by "electronic mail" or "in writing." Additionally, the report would fail unless it is sent to a government official or to a specified member of management: A corporate officer, a facility manager, or a human resources manager - supervisors do not count. Refusing to participate in the illegal activity is no longer good enough, either. There must also be a written refusal to one of the specified persons for the employee's job to be protected.
Of course, written reports are more often the exception than the rule, particularly with sensitive matters. For example, in the well-known Penn State case, the assistant coach orally reported Jerry Sandusky's showering with and fondling of little boys to his supervisor, head coach Joe Paterno. Had this occurred under current Tennessee law, the assistant coach could not be fired for reporting child abuse. But under HB1954, the assistant coach could be fired on-the-spot because his report was oral, not written, and it was not made to higher management. In this sense, the bill rewards a "fire 'em quickly" mentality.
If the letter of the law requires a "letter to the boss," this bill will exclude nearly half of all whistleblowers. The Ethics Resource Center (ERC) is a non-profit, nonpartisan center which studies organizational ethics in business; available at http://www.ethics.org/page/about-erc. Its landmark study, "Blowing the Whistle on Workplace Misconduct," found that 46 percent of all whistleblowers go to their supervisor, whereas only 29 percent go to higher management.
Whether it's unsafe drinking water, taxpayer waste, public wrongdoing, or other illegal actions, the laws protecting whistleblowers should remain strong. Otherwise, whistleblowers will be afraid to speak out and, over time, our state will be harmed. Instead of early prevention through robust reporting laws, illegal activities will fester until we experience a shared loss in areas like health, environment and finance.
HB1954 also negatively affects persons with disabilities. For persons who prove they were fired or discriminated against because of a disability, HB1954 puts a limit, sometimes as low as $25,000, on their recovery of non-economic damages. Even if a judge or jury wants to award more, it cannot do so. According to Evelyn Doxey, at the Disability Law & Advocacy Center of Tennessee: "This is an attempt to weaken, not strengthen, the law protecting people with disabilities who want to work and take their place in the broader communities in which they live. It also does not bring Tennessee law into alignment with the key federal requirement that employers provide reasonable accommodations that assist qualified people with disabilities in getting jobs and keeping jobs."
Fortunately, HB1954 is just being voted on, it has not yet passed. Among those persons voting on HB1954 is Rep. Jimmy Eldridge from Madison County. Eldridge deserves to hear from constituents as he, too, studies the serious consequences of the proposed bill.
The bill is available at http://www.capitol.tn.gov/Bills/108/Bill/HB1954.pdf, and Rep. Eldridge's public line in Nashville is: (615) 741-7475.
TENNELA is an organization devoted to protecting interests of employees, including whistleblowers and persons with a disability. Its members are responsible for several landmark cases before the United States Supreme Court including (1) protections for persons who report sexual harassment, in Crawford v. Metro. Govt. of Nashville and Davidson County, Tenn., 555 U.S. 271 (2009); (2) the scope and meaning of "retaliation" in Burlington Northern & Santa Fe Railway Co. v. White, 548 U.S. 53 (2006); and (3) psychological harm in sex and race discrimination cases, in Harris v. Forklift Systems, Inc., 510 U.S. 17 (1993).
Justin Gilbert and Wade Cowan are current and former presidents of the Tennessee Employment Lawyers Association (www.tennela.org). Contact them at Justin Gilbert jgilbert@gilbertfirm.com
]]></text></news-item>