<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTB-JFF1-DYRV-33MB"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Russian daily dismisses Western sanction threats, says other markets available</title><source>BBC Monitoring Former Soviet Union - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Text of report by Russian newspaper Trud on 21 March
[Trud economic columnist Aleksandr Protsenko report: "Eastern Delights. The West's Economic Sanctions Will Force Russia To Turn to Asia"]
Yesterday and today in Brussels leaders of the European Union countries have been discussing what kind of sanctions may be applied to Russia on account of the annexation of Crimea. Two countries have already taken the first steps, having suspended exports to Russia of military and dual-purpose products.
Germany has turned down the completion of the construction in Mulino (Nizhegorod Oblast) of the Ground Troops' digital computer centre. It was contemplated here on an already partially built proving ground 500 square kilometres in area with special electronic apparatus conducting the combat training of up to 30,000 warriors of mechanized brigades -with modelling of the tactical battlefield environment and laser return-fire simulation. And tank crewmen are already undergoing instruction in Mulino, what is more. And now the Germans have decided to annul the EUR100 million contract concluded with the Rheinmetall company.
Britain has suspended licenses for the manufacture in Russia of British sniper rifles and rounds and also of some aircraft and helicopter parts. The total value of the licenses is 80 million pounds sterling ($133 million).
France also has spoken of a possible suspension of deliveries to Russia of the Mistral helicopter carriers, which are already being built, but with a reservation: a final decision on the matter will be made in October, when the time of the handover to the Russians of the first ship, named the Vladivostok, is due. The reason for the indecision is clear: last summer France began the building of a second ship, which, by an irony of fate, has been given the name Sevastopol. The total value of the Mistral contract was EUR1.2 billion -this is a sizable sum and has already been partly spent, evidently. Deputy Premier Dmitriy Rogozin said that France should either honour its obligations or return the money. And the Russian United Shipbuilding Corporation threatened Paris as a follow-up with big punitive sanctions.
The cost of possible sanctions is altogether the biggest issue of the present summit in Brussels for Russia's commodity turnover with the European Union has in the past 10 years grown from $90 billion to $335 billion. And a considerable part of Russian exports to Europe is composed of raw material and energy sources, for which there would be a demand in other countries also. But in the event of a stoppage of the European commodity traffic to Russia, there is practically no one else to whom to supply it in appreciable quantities.
The picture is the same in trade with the United States, which occupies just over 3 per cent of Russia's foreign trade. Based on the 2013 results, over three-fourths (76 per cent) of Russian supplies to the Americans were composed of oil and petroleum products, fertilizers, aluminium in ingots and untreated palladium, pig iron and ferrous metal bars, titanium, synthetic rubber, and plywood.
From America we get in return automobiles and aircraft, medical equipment and construction machinery, and generators and pump and compressor equipment. High-technology goods, that is.
As a whole, the structure of the goods imported into our country from the far abroad is increasingly assuming an investment nature: machine-building products constitute more than one-half -50.1 per cent -food and agricultural raw material -12.5 per cent -mineral products -2.5 per cent -chemical products -15.3 per cent (including prescription drugs -3.3 per cent) - textiles and footwear -6 per cent -metals and their products -7 per cent -and miscellaneous goods -6.6 per cent.
But note: almost all this may now be purchased not only in Europe or the United States but also in Southeast Asia, which has already risen to a modern technological level. It would be easy for Russia, for example, to relinquish American household equipment and electric appliances in favour of Asian commodities. The expert Galina Gelfand, LogLab strategic development director, says that Chinese manufacturers will be dancing for joy in the vent of the imposition of sanctions against Russia and restrictions on our imports of American equipment. After all, Russians would try out Chinese counterparts and could satisfy themselves that they are not a bit worse than the brand-name models. This now applies to automobiles, electronics, and so forth. And where can the United States and Europe sell the 3 million automobiles which Russia purchases from them?
Asia already has very modern machine-tool building and other machine-building production also. But, which is even better, this sector is quietly reviving in Russia itself as well. Aleksey Likhachev, deputy head of the Ministry of Economic Development and Trade, says that in the past year of 2013 the proportion of raw-material goods in Russian exports declined, and of high-technology goods, increased. "Exports of machine-building products grew more than 4 per cent, of high-technology products, 14 per cent, and of innovation products, 4.2 per cent," the deputy head of the Ministry of Economic Development and Trade, affirmed. We take this information seriously: it is evidence of Russia getting past the most important inspector -the world market.
Russia is already beginning to sell overseas not only military aircraft but also An-148 and An-158 commercial aircraft (to Cuba). A plan for building in Angola a national space-based satellite communication and broadcasting system (Angosat) is being executed. Experts of facilities of the use of nuclear energy, primarily nuclear plants on a VVER-TOI platform, are developing successfully. The markets of Vietnam, Thailand, Indonesia, and other Asian countries have proven very promising for us in this respect.
Now is just the time to harness this trend, bolster government support of export-oriented and high-technology business, and increase the openness and transparency of administrative procedures and government-procurement procedures. A number of experts believes that tax holidays for enterprises geared to import-substitution in the high-technology sphere could be one of the most optimal modes of support for such business. The state would thus effectually advance loans for our manufacturers of high-technology products, which would enable them to lower the prices of their products, increasing competitiveness. And then new private investments in the sphere and a surge of business activity could be expected also.
And very much will depend more than ever on companies of Russia's fuel and energy complex, which was, is, and will remain the main support and foundation of our economy. And world business is certain of its firmness also. An interesting fact is proof of this: it was in the past two weeks, when there was a whiff of gunpowder in the air, that foreign exchange-traded funds investing in Russian shares of the fuel and energy sector recorded a net influx of funds amounting to $340 million. To compare: from the start of January through 1 March these funds recorded a net outflow of $425 million. The business world clearly understands, that is, that no political sanctions are capable of seriously harming these industries. And Russia, on whose coat of arms a two-headed eagle is depicted, could in the event of some obstacles appearing on one side re-direct the activity of its fuel and energy complex to another side. Western politicians also understand this, evidently, and are for this reason attempting to operate by the pinprick method - thinking up personal sanctions against senior politicians and businessmen of a country that does not buckle beneath foreign pressure.
Igor Sechin, head of Rosneft, the world's largest oil company, spoke about this as follows: "Threats, blackmail, and personal meanness are evidence of powerlessness. Which, generally speaking, is humiliating for self-respecting countries. But I would like to ask: what's the intent? To hurt our feelings? Pride goes before a fall. To browbeat? You have already done so. Or, perhaps, to make an offer that can't be refused? Based on the well-known blackmail -bribery -assassination threat arrangement? But such actions are in principle effective against one's own agents of influence. As far as an elite that is loyal to the country is concerned, sanctions have always and everywhere resulted in consolidation and the concentration of forces on countermeasures to outside pressure.... I recall Raul Castro's remark about Mr Obama's complaints that Cuba is pushing down insufficiently on the reform pedal. Raul responded: 'It is my foot on the pedal, not Obama's!' I have the feeling that they are once again confusing feet and pedals."
And about possible economic sanctions the head of Rosneft said that "from the business perspective, there are places to which Russian companies can move their activity. There is the global economy, a big world, in which it is long since Europe or America were the masters. And the very hysteria and busywork over these sanctions is obvious evidence of this."
P.S. The Moscow Economic Forum, at which businessmen, scholars, and politicians will gather, opens next week. Co-chairmen Konstantin Babkin and Ruslan Grinberg said ahead of it that the time had come to fundamentally reconsider economic policy.
"The neo-liberal course has long been the main impediment to our country's development. It is played out, but it continues to dominate economic theory and economic policy, the sphere of culture and science, and social policy and education. The supporters of this teaching are today trying to impress upon us that Russia's current condition is its lot for many years to come, that this is the norm and that nothing needs to be or can be changed. But we know and do not forget for one minute that our country has tremendous potential."
Voices
Pavel Grudinin, director of the Lenin Sovkhoz private corporation
If we imagine that they begin to ban imports of agricultural machinery and equipment, it will be worse for us. The Kharkiv Tractor Plant no longer exists, Belarusian tractors cannot compete with Western tractors. The best machines are made by the Deutz-Fahr and John Deere companies. But what's the point of them losing our market and money, I wonder?
Vadim Oleynikov, expert, doctor of sciences
Maybe I'm expressing a seditious thought, but I impatiently await sanctions. Because then the government will be forced to address such high-technology sectors as aviation industry. The authorities will, finally, stop incentivizing contracts for the purchase of overseas aircraft and their key-ready assembly. Return the Russian market to its own airliners, contend for the orders of eastern countries -this is possible. Now's the time to reconsider personnel policy also. "Effective managers" with a foggy idea of the specifics of the industry have infiltrated various spheres of the sector. Pretty good guys, perhaps, but not when it comes to this.
Musheg Mamikonyan, chairman of the board of the Meat Union
The sanctions weapon shoots all who pick it up. Russia today is fully self-supporting in poultry (96 per cent) and does not import, it already sells overseas, more than 20 million tons of grain a year. Russia now has a tremendous number of other meat suppliers aside from the EU and the United States. The biggest are Brazil and Mexico. And we import only 22 per cent of our meat. And international trade depends to a far greater extent than on embargoes, for example, on veterinary requirements. Imports from Europe of hogs are restricted at this time, for example, on account of African swine fever. This has already gone on for more than two months on the initiative of our veterinary service, but the consumers have not even noticed.
Source: Trud, Moscow, in Russian 21 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>