<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTB-SMS1-F091-R377"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>South Africa closer to search for black gold</title><source>Sunday Tribune (South Africa)</source><author> Fiona Forde</author><text><![CDATA[South Africa is about to be "fracked", as the government gives the go-ahead for shale gas exploration in the southern Karoo and elsewhere, a move it describes as a possible "game-changer" for the economy.
The Sunday Tribune can exclusively reveal that the final regulations for hydraulic fracturing - or "fracking", as the process is known - will be published in the middle of next month, after which the search for the new "black gold" will begin.
This is according to officials |in the Department of Mineral Resources earlier this week, and comes weeks after President Jacob Zuma told Parliament in his State of the Nation address that shale gas could be a "game-changer" for the economy.
"Having evaluated the risks and opportunities, the final regulations will be released soon, and will be followed by the processing and granting of licences," Zuma said.
Royal Dutch Shell is already on standby for an exploratory fracking licence in the Karoo, and is expected to pump more than R1 billion into the process and create a few hundred jobs.
In essence, Shell will be carrying out the exploration for the government, as any reserves they might tap into will remain the property of the state, as per the Mineral, Petroleum and Resources Development Act.
However if they find significant reserves, as they expect, they would be given preference for future commercial fracking rights.
The extent of the Karoo shale gas reserves is unclear, though.
In a study carried out by Econometrix a few years ago, the quantity was said to be 485 trillion cubic feet (tcf), but the Petroleum Agency of SA has since revised that figure to about 40tcf.
"The truth is that no one knows until the exploratory fracking begins," says Anthony Leiman, a professor of economics at UCT.
"This is about the value of information versus the price of ignorance. To determine the quantities, fracking is what needs to be done."
The go-ahead follows years of intense lobbying by Karoo residents, who believe fracking will wreak environmental havoc, as well as drain, and possibly contaminate, their scarce water supplies.
Although the amount of water required for exploratory fracking is not the key issue, the vast amounts that would be required for the later process of commercial fracking have raised concern.
How the fracking companies dispose of the contaminated water that will be returned to the surface is another bone of contention, and something Shell has not been entirely forthcoming about.
The Karoo residents' bottom line is that the economic benefits will not outweigh the detrimental environmental impact.
In a soon to be published paper in the Southern African Business Review, a number of academics have sided with the anti-fracking lobby, saying it will be the multi-national oil companies that will benefit most, and that it is the same companies who have controlled |the debate by commissioning studies that favour fracking and its |benefits.
To Page 2
]]></text></news-item>