<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTB-Y141-JD34-V1FJ"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Morwell will run its own inquiry</title><source>The Age (Melbourne, Australia)</source><author>Laura Banks</author><text><![CDATA[A community meeting in Morwell has heard new claims of health problems from the month-long fire that raged out of control at the Hazelwood open-cut coalmine.
About 100 emotional Latrobe Valley residents told their stories at the Voices of the Valley meeting and expressed anger at the state government for what they said was a failure to act adequately, as toxic smoke and ash from the fire continued to be dumped on those living in the region.
A teary John Biram, 78, told the group that he attributed the heart attack he suffered a week ago to the fire. "This is the worst my health has ever been; the stress of the stink and the ash has aggravated my health condition and that's it," Mr Biram said on Sunday.
Rachel Green sent her 18-year-old son to Melbourne six weeks ago when the fire erupted so his respiratory problems would not flare up. Her 15-year-old son is living with his girlfriend and her mother in Newborough to escape the smoke.
"I've never been this sick in my life and I've never had to take so many pills - I've had to buy a Webster pack like an old person so I can keep track of what I'm taking."
She said that before the fire she was active and went to the gym daily, but now she did not have the lung capacity to run her daily two kilometres on the treadmill.
Anecdotes of health deterioration, breathing problems, skin irritations, depression and anxiety were common among those who spoke, as were fears that long-term exposure to the smoke and ash would cause cancer.
The government released terms of reference for its inquiry ito the mine fire on Friday. Headed by Black Saturday royal commissioner Justice Bernard Teague, the inquiry will investigate government regulation of the Hazelwood mine, the emergency response, the role of mine operator GDF Suez and the adequacy of health information passed on to Morwell residents.
The terms of reference won praise from some groups concerned about how the response to the fire had been handled, including lawyers at the Environmental Defender's Office.
The fire burnt for 40 days after being ignited during bushfires on February 9.
Voices of the Valley president and Morwell resident Simon Ellis said the meeting gave people the opportunity to testify about how the fire had affected them, and their testimonies would go ito affidavits, which, Mr Ellis said, would be used in a citizens' inquiry.
He said the community did not trust the government and felt it had to conduct its own inquiry.
]]></text></news-item>