<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTB-RGF1-F08V-6007"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Dixie’s menagerie   famous animals: Alabama’s history is filled with furry and feathered celebrities. </title><source>Mobile Register (Alabama)</source><author>Kelly Kazek kkazek@al.com A surprising variety of animals have a</author><text><![CDATA[Lily Flagg, butter cow, Huntsville
Reminders of Lily Flagg, a cow made famous in the late 1800s, can be seen around Huntsville in the form of street signs, business and apartment names, and even a locally brewed beer. The Jersey cow’s full name was Signal’s Lily Flagg, born in 1884, who became the top butter producer in the world in 1892 when she produced milk to make 1,047 pounds of butter. Lily was owned by W. E. Matthews and Gen. Samuel H. Moore of Huntsville.
To celebrate Lily’s record year, Huntsville officials held a public reception.
Owner Samuel Moore would host another celebratory party July 21, 1892, at his Huntsville home. He painted the home butter yellow, built a dance platform and installed some of the region’s first electric lights.
As she aged, Lily was eventually sold and her date of death is unknown.
Matilda, world’s oldest chicken, Bessemer
Matilda, a Red Pyle chicken whose owners lived in Bessemer, lived to the ripe old age of 16, a record for chicken longevity, according to the Guinness Book of World Records. Matilda was hatched in 1990 and lived until Feb. 11, 2006. She was purchased by Keith and Donna Barton, who kept her as a pet and featured her in Keith’s magic act. After she was certified as the longest-living chicken, Matilda appeared with her owners on “The Tonight Show with Jay Leno” in 2004.
A veterinarian speculated Matilda outlived most hens because she never produced eggs and because she was an indoor chicken.
Miss Baker, monkeynaut, Huntsville
Miss Baker was a squirrel monkey, one of two monkeys who would become the first animals to be launched into space by the United States and be recovered alive. Miss Baker was born in 1957 and made her 16-minute space flight in 1959. She and Able, a rhesus monkey, returned to Earth healthy and were treated as celebrities. Able would die four days later from complications of surgery to remove electrodes embedded for her flight.
Miss Baker would appear on the cover of Life magazine later that year. In 1971, Ed Buckee of Huntsville headed an effort to have Miss Baker live at the U.S. Space & Rocket Center because of Huntsville’s work on the Jupiter rocket that launched the monkeys. At the museum, Miss Baker lived in a special habitat and would have three “husbands.” She was given strawberry gelatin with bananas for birthdays and special occasions.
She died of kidney failure Nov. 29, 1984, and, at 26, was one of the longest-living squirrel monkeys on record. She is buried on the grounds of the space center, where visitors sometimes leave bananas atop her grave.
Tiger, War Eagle VI, Auburn
Tiger is a golden eagle who gained fame as a mascot for Auburn University. Despite the fact that Auburn’s official school mascot is a tiger, an eagle has symbolized the college’s battle cry of “War Eagle!” since an injured eagle was first discovered and adopted by students in 1930. War Eagle VI came to Auburn in 1986 after being rescued from an illegal breeding operation when she was 6 years old. All eagles who now serve as mascots are birds that could not be released in the wild and are under the stewardship of the U.S. government because eagles are an endangered species.
During the 2000 football season, War Eagle VI began making flights from the top of Jordan-Hare Stadium, spiraling to the center of the field before games.
On February 8, 2002, War Eagle VI flew during the opening ceremonies of the Winter Olympics in Salt Lake City and was subsequently featured on the “Today” show. She officially retired from game flights in November 2006 when War Eagle VII, Nova, took over official game duties. War Eagle VI, who flew during four SEC-title seasons at Auburn, now lives quietly at the Southeastern Raptor Rehabilitation Center in Auburn.
Gucci, law-changing dog, Mobile
Gucci, a husky-chow mix who was abused as a puppy, would have a statewide impact when his case helped bring attention to animal abuse laws and eventually lead to stricter punishments. Gucci was hung from a tree in Mobile and set on fire by three young men in 1994 when he was only 3 months old. He survived the ordeal and was adopted by Doug James, a professor at Spring Hill College.
A campaign for tougher punishments for animal abuse led to Gucci’s Law, which made first-degree animal cruelty punishable by up to 10 years in prison and a $5,000 fine. Each of Gucci’s abusers was punished for animal cruelty and one would serve jail time.
Gucci died in 2010, but James told an AL.com reporter in 2013 he had a “great life.” Filmmakers came to Mobile last year to get footage for a feature-length documentary about animal-abuse laws called “A Dog Named Gucci.”
Zeke, healing horse, Wilsonville
Zeke was a sick and abandoned horse who gained new purpose in life when he was adopted by the Spirit of Hope Youth Ranch in Wilsonville, where he was given the task of helping abused children. Zeke suffered from Cushing’s disease and other ailments, but the members of the ranch created a special regimen of treatments and care to put the spring back in his step. At the ranch, Zeke provided emotional healing to the abused children who would stay there. His medical conditions caused him to grow a thick coat of fur that would lead to overheating. The children would spend lots of time brushing away Zeke’s extra layers, helping him stay cool.
Zeke died at the ranch in 2011 and is buried beneath his favorite tree.
Boo, movie-star reindeer, Huntsville
In 1987, a Southern reindeer answered a casting call that would make her an unlikely star. The reindeer named Boo had been brought from Alaska to be raised on Bobby Baldwin’s farm in Huntsville. Boo, who lived in an air-conditioned barn, traveled to Indiana, where film producers were looking for an animal to play the title role in a film called “Prancer” about an injured reindeer. Baldwin, who described Boo as high-spirited but gentle, noticed she had a special rapport with children, so he chose her from among his herd of eight reindeer to take to the casting call.
Boo would live seven more years on the Huntsville farm, dying in 1996.
Fred, the town dog, Rockford
Fred was a rather ordinary-looking mutt who managed to capture the hearts of an entire town, albeit one of fewer than 500 residents. In 1993, Fred wandered into Rockford in Coosa County in need of medical attention and some tender, loving care. After residents of the town nursed him back to health, Fred decided he liked the place and would call it home the rest of his life.
Fred belonged to no one and everyone, spending the majority of his time at Ken’s Package Store but from time to time deciding to nap right in the middle of the street. He gained notoriety when he began “writing” a column in the local newspaper about his activities in town. The town’s welcome signs were altered to say “Home of Fred the Town Dog” and Fred was featured on a TV show on the Animal Planet network.
Fred died on Dec. 23, 2002, and was buried behind the Old Rock Jail, a local tourist attraction.
Leo, UNA lion mascot, Florence
In 1974, Dr. Robert M. Guillot, president of the University of North Alabama, acquired a 35-pound lion cub to be the symbol of the college’s athletics. To this day, UNA is the only college in the country to have a live lion mascot living on campus. Although some animal rights groups such as PETA protest live mascots on college campuses, the current mascots at UNA live in a 12,764-square-foot specially made space called the George H. Carroll Lion Habitat.
Leo I lived on campus for 14 years, growing to a 540-pound symbol of pride at the university. He died Jan. 20, 1988, and a bronze monument was erected in his memory.
Leo II, a cub orphaned when its mother died, came to UNA in 1988 and died in 2000. Leo III and a female lion named Una, born in 2002, now live in the habitat and serve as UNA mascots.
Daniel, gas-chamber survivor, Florence
Daniel the beagle became a celebrity after an attempt to euthanize him in 2011 failed, and he was given a second chance at life. At 6 months old, Daniel was taken to Florence Animal Control, and when no one adopted him, he was placed in the gas chamber, a method of euthanasia some activists have protested as inhumane.
Daniel was adopted by Joe Dwyer of Nutley and became an award-winning “spokesdog” for an animal rights organization. In January, Daniel was a guest of honor on a float in the Rose Parade in Pasadena, Calif., riding along with other shelter dogs on a float sponsored by the Lucy Pet Foundation.
Troop, loyal coon dog, Tuscumbia
Troop, the faithful companion and hunting dog of Key Underwood of Tuscumbia, died in 1937, and a heart-broken Underwood decided to honor his pet by burying him in the woods where they had so often hunted together. In a grassy meadow in the woods near Tuscumbia, Underwood erected a monument over Troop’s grave.
Underwood didn’t know at the time, but Troop’s burial would make the site world famous. Other hunters decided to bury their coon dogs in the area, and it would become the Key Underwood Coon Dog Memorial Graveyard. According to the website coondogcemetery.com, “The burial spot was a popular hunting camp where coon hunters from miles around gathered to plot their hunting strategies, tell tall tales, chew tobacco and compare coon hounds. Those comparisons usually began and ended with Troop … he was the best around.”
One of the most-visited spots in the graveyard is Troop’s marker, made from a piece of chimney rock that Underwood chiseled with a hammer and a screwdriver.
Today, more than 185 dogs are interred at the site, all of them registered coon dogs, a requirement for burial. The cemetery is a popular tourist attraction and the only burial ground of its kind in the world.
Join AL.com reporter Kelly Kazek on her weekly journey through Alabama to record the region’s quirky history, strange roadside attractions and tales of colorful characters. Call her at 256-701-0576.
The following fields overflowed:
BYLINE = Kelly Kazek kkazek@al.com A surprising variety of animals have achieved “fame” in Alabama’s history. For this week’s Odd Travels, I featured 11 interesting animals.
]]></text></news-item>