<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTB-JD41-JD3N-5094"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>THEY NEVER HAD A CHANCE</title><source>The Courier Mail (Australia)</source><author>PETER HALL, THOMAS CHAMBERLIN, ANTHONY GOUGH, KAY DIBBEN, ROSE BRENNAN, DANIEL MEERS</author><text><![CDATA[THE skydiving firm involved in a fiery plane crash that claimed five lives at Caboolture was involved in a similar incident in 2010, when seven people cheated death.
Yesterday, five people - a pilot, two tandem instructors and two clients - died when a Cessna 206 operated by Adrenalin Skydivers crashed during takeoff at the airstrip, 50km north of Brisbane.
Witnesses say the aircraft inexplicably "headed left" during lift-off and was at very low altitude when it plunged into the ground and burst into flames.
There were no survivors.
Among the victims were experienced instructors Glenn Norman and Juraj Glesk, who had thousands of jumps under their belts.
Mr Norman, a husband and father of two young girls, was also a full-time firefighter as Station Officer at Woodridge, who friends said was -always there to help others.
Adrenalin Skydivers, promoted locally as Skydive Bribie, was running the ill-fated operation. It utilises Caboolture Airfield for pick-ups and conducts tandem jumps for tourists, who land on nearby Bribie Island.
The Sunday Mail can reveal that Adrenalin Skydivers Pty Ltd also was the parent company involved in an accident where an aircraft being used by Skydive Central Queensland crashed in August 2010.
The Cessna 206 plane was experiencing engine trouble on takeoff before it crashed near Gladstone Airport.
A father and two sons, three tandem jump instructors and a pilot were on board, Adrenalin Skydivers reported to media at the time. Five people were injured and airlifted to Gladstone Hospital.
The head of the company, Paul Turner, was unavailable for comment yesterday. The firm's Geebung headquarters, filled with skydiving signage and vehicles, were in lockdown yesterday.
Industry sources described the Caboolture crash as a -terrible tragedy. They said Mr Glesk had been working out of Bribie for about a year after previously being part of his brother Tibor's Caloundra-based operation.
Tibor Glesk, an industry identity, was too distraught to speak yesterday as he struggled to come to terms with his younger brother's death.
John Friswell, of Gatton-based Ripcord Skydivers, said he had known Mr Norman for many years.
He said his former employee and friend had juggled fire fighting and skydiving. "He was very much the gentleman skydiver, always caring towards his solo students. Glenn was a high quality instructor, skilled in solo and tandem jumps." Australian Parachute Federation chief executive Brad Turner told The Sunday Mail that the tight-knit industry had been left devastated.
Mr Turner said all thoughts were with the families of the victims. "They were very experienced sky divers … extremely good at their jobs, very well liked and very professional," he said.
Aero Dynamic Flight Academy managing director and Caboolture Airfield safety officer Bryan Carpenter said the aviation community was left shattered by the -tragic accident.
"We're devastated. You don't expect it to happen, not five deaths like that. That's pretty sad," he said.
Mr Carpenter said he had trained the pilot involved in the crash, who was a highly skilled and well-liked 24-year-old with around 600 hours under his belt as a sky-diving pilot.
"He was a very quiet unassuming sort of a lad, he was flying part time in order to pay for his degree," he said.
"He was very, very skilled in those sky-diving operations because that's what he'd been doing ever since he had his commercial licence, which is over two years now." Mr Carpenter said it was impossible to speculate as to the cause of the accident, but it could be anything from a bird going through the windscreen to a mechanical failure or a centre of gravity shift in the aircraft.
He said the Cessna had only risen 100 or 200 feet -before turning sharply and crashing on to the airfield.
Craig McKinlay, 41, was working at a neighbouring waste plant just 400m from where the plane hit the ground.
"I heard an enormous explosion and I turned around and a few seconds later … there was just this massive enormous red black fireball," he said, adding that white panels of the plane were flung 10m from the wreckage.
"It's just horrendous." Mr McKinlay said staff at the airfield ran to help.
"They could only get so close because of the intense heat and flame," he said. The Australian Transport Safety Bureau is investigating the crash. Additional reportingANTHONY GOUGH, KAY DIBBEN, ROSE BRENNAN, DANIEL MEERS
]]></text></news-item>