<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTC-S9C1-F08V-605B"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Newark  Watershed's legal counsel withdraws  Watchdog said law firm had a conflict of interest </title><source>The Star-Ledger (Newark, New Jersey)</source><author>David Giambusso, Star-Ledger Staff</author><text><![CDATA[In a move that is drawing applause from resident water advocates, the law firm Genova, Burns, Giantomassi and Webster has withdrawn as general counsel for the Newark Watershed Conservation and Development Corp.
"We believe it is in the NWCDC's best interest, at this time, to secure the services of another law firm," Angelo Genova wrote on a March 17 letter to the watershed agency's board of trustees.
The high-powered law firm includes Elnardo Webster, who was the watershed agency's general counsel during years when the state comptroller alleged there was rampant mismanagement and corruption at the agency that controlled all of the city's water infrastructure.
In March 2013, the city began the process of dissolving the agency by appointing new trustees to transfer the watershed's activities to City Hall. That process is still underway, but until last week, Genova's firm stayed on as the agency's general counsel, although Webster was no longer involved, trustees said.
Genova's involvement in the dissolution drew criticism from the Newark Water Group, a resident watchdog group that believed the firm had a conflict of interest.
"The water group is happy with this," said Dan O'Flaherty, one of the group members. "There are still big questions about what happens with the money."
Edwin Stier, one of the new trustees, said the point of keeping Genova on board until now was to save money. He said a new law firm would take time to familiarize itself with the minutiae of the watershed's finances.
He said the duties of the new trustees were twofold: to dissolve the watershed agency and hand over its responsibilities to the city, and to investigate what happened with the allegedly misspent funds.
"That (investigation) would have to come from a completely independent law firm," Stier said. With the dissolution now complete, he said it was a good time for Genova to withdraw.
"If you're going to do it, this is good time to do it," Stier said.
The city of Newark, pointing to $1 million remaining in the watershed's coffers, wanted to stop funding the agency, but last week Superior Court Judge Dennis Carey III ordered the city to pay $514,000 in back bills and continue funding the dissolution.
"The Court is not giving the NWCDC or the Provisional Trustees a blank check," Carey wrote in his order.
"Aside from any unfunded expenses up to the date of this Order, the Court agrees that there should be no duplicative investigation into the alleged past improprieties of the NWCDC."
Carey ordered the watershed trustees and the city to determine together if a new forensic audit of the agency's books is required.
David Giambusso: (973) 392-4178 or dgiambusso@starledger.com
]]></text></news-item>