<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTC-PC91-JC6P-C4TD"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>EDITORIAL: This is no time for DENR to spare the rod</title><source>The Fayetteville Observer (Fayetteville, North Carolina)</source><author>The Fayetteville Observer, N.C.</author><text><![CDATA[March 23--Duke Energy sought permission last year to conduct routine maintenance at its Cape Fear River plant in Chatham County. Officials with the N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources knew the company might adjust water levels in its coal-ash ponds.
State inspectors discovered a pumping operation last week that has dumped 61 million gallons of wastewater into the Cape Fear River over several months. Duke shrugged. It had permission, didn't it?
For once, DENR didn't budge, noting that 61 million gallons exceeds routine maintenance. The regulator has taken a bath in public opinion over its long, cozy relationship with Duke, especially under John Skvarla, an appointee of Gov. Pat McCrory, who is a former Duke employee.
Aspects of DENR's interaction with Duke, including a sweetheart settlement deal that fell apart after a major spill at Duke's Dan River plant in February, are the subject of a federal grand jury inquiry.
But DENR and the governor may feel their old friend insulted them, especially after this latest incident. Going easy on a company they trusted while it took care of business and kept the juice flowing was one thing. When it resisted cleaning up and threatened to charge customers for the privilege of having toxic waste removed, Duke was trying their patience.
Learning that the company intentionally dumped more wastewater into a half million people's water supply than the amount of coal-ash it accidentally spilled into the Dan, McCrory and Skvarla surely saw the scope of Duke's arrogance.
The tainted water does not pose the same level of hazard as toxic ash. But that doesn't change the shocking callousness of Duke's behavior.
Exasperation is is provoking suddenly stronger rhetoric from McCrory, who also commented Thursday on a crack discovered in the dam at the Cape Fear site: "This is the latest in a series of troubling incidents at Duke Energy facilities over the past few months, and it's time for Duke Energy to come out of the shadows and to publicly address this growing problem." The governor demanded explanations and promised appropriate action to enforce the law.
The same sense of betrayal could also explain DENR's sudden no-nonsense attitude toward Duke's abuse last week, with citations for dumping in the Cape Fear expected to bring hefty fines.
Whether McCrory and Skvarla do their duty out of anger with Duke or due to political pressure, their task of reining in the company remains clear. With its lame excuses, Duke behaved like a rotten young 'un; a trip to the woodshed is overdue.
___ (c)2014 The Fayetteville Observer (Fayetteville, N.C.) Visit The Fayetteville Observer (Fayetteville, N.C.) at www.fayobserver.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>