<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTC-67Y1-J9YR-G3J7"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Turkey defends Twitter ban: 'Social media companies must obey laws of Republic'; 'It is difficult to comprehend Twitter's indifference and its biased and prejudiced stance,' Turkish Prime Minister's office says in statement</title><source>Independent.co.uk</source><author>Tomas Jivanda</author><text><![CDATA[The Turkish government has defended its block on Twitter, accusing the social media company of allowing "systematic character assassinations" against Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan and members of his inner circle.
Ministers accused the company of refusing to comply with Turkish laws and court orders, citing this as the reason for the ban.
The country's communications minister, Lutfi Elvan said: "Whether it's Twitter, Yahoo or Google, all social media companies have to obey the laws of the Turkish Republic and they will."
The Turkish government attempted to clamp down on the access to Twitter after links to wiretapped recordings suggesting corruption were posted on the site, causing Mr Erdogan's government major embarrassment before local elections on March 30.
The effort to shut down the service backfired on Friday however, with many finding ways to continue to tweet and mock the government for what they said was a futile attempt at censorship.
Even President Abdullah Gul worked around the ban, tweeting that shutting down social media networks cannot "be approved".
Prime Minister Erdogan's office said in a statement the ban on Twitter had come in response to the company's "defiance" in failing to comply with hundreds of court rulings.
"Twitter has been used as a means to carry out systematic character assassinations by circulating illegally acquired recordings, fake and fabricated records of wiretapping," it said.
"It is difficult to comprehend Twitter's indifference and its biased and prejudiced stance. We believe that this attitude is damaging to the brand image of the company in question and creates an unfair and inaccurate impression of our country."
According to Mr Elvan, Turkey had made 643 content removal requests to Twitter since last January.
Speaking to the BBC, the country's finance minister further defend the ban: "The Turkish telecommunications watchdog has made a number of statements saying that they have asked Twitter on a number of occasions to remove some content on the back of court orders and Twitter has been refusing to comply."
"I don't think any global company, whether it's a media company, whether it's an industrial company, it shouldn't see itself [as being] above the law."
The minister did however add that it was looking like Twitter was working with Turkish authorities to have the ban lifted.
A senior Turkish government official told Reuters that talks with the social media company on resolving problem were going "positively".
The decision to block Twitter has sparked a wave of international criticism, as well as protests in the country.
Swedish Foreign Minister Carl Bildt used Twitter today to tell Turkey its efforts to block access to the social media network were "stupid." He said the blockade "isn't working and also backfiring heavily".
]]></text></news-item>