<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTC-P0R1-F125-13NP"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>The sides of Seeds</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Who has the forces of right on his side, David or Goliath? In fact, should the battle even be cast as a David and Goliath story?
Those are just a couple of the questions Montreal playwright Annabel Soutar tackles in her docudrama Seeds which plants itself at the National Arts Centre this week.
The play explores the high-profile legal battle between Saskatchewan farmer Percy Schmeiser and agricultural biotechnology giant Monsanto Canada Inc. Monsanto accused Schmeiser in 1998 of patent violation for growing its genetically modified canola without a licence. He fought back, saying that seeds had wound up on his property accidentally and that he had the right to use seeds harvested from those original, unintentionally sown plants. In 2004, Schmeiser lost in a 5 to 4 decision at the Supreme Court of Canada.
Soutar debuted her play the next year and has subsequently revamped and tweaked it multiple times as it tours. The show has been described as everything from an examination of how we want purity in both our food and our heroes to a debate about the ethics of owning the rights to a life form.
The play's backstory
Soutar, who had known next to nothing about GMOs (genetically modified organisms), says she was intrigued by the Monsanto/Schmeiser story. "I loved the idea that it was a farmer and a biotech company: it suggested very diverse perspectives and characters which I look as a documentary playwright. I liked that it had a national scope which at that point in my career as a Quebec playwright I was looking for. And I had an instinct that it had shelf life."
The process &; the people
As intrepid as the best investigative journalist, she spent a year researching the story and getting a balanced view by talking to lawyers, farmers and others across the country. She ploughed through legal documents and newspaper accounts. She stood in line on a freezing January morning to attend the Supreme Court hearing.
Soutar also interviewed Trish Jordan, Monsanto Canada's director of industry and public affairs. "She was at first sceptical of a playwright writing about this, but we spent two hours together," says Soutar. "She was anxious for me to hear their side of the story."
(Jordan joins Soutar on March 29 in a public interview with NAC English Theatre artistic director Jillian Keiley. The session is part of the NAC's Points of View series. See the NAC website for information).
The playwright also visited Schmeiser (played by Eric Peterson of Corner Gas and other television series) at his farm.
"He's very charismatic and frank, someone with a strong sense of justice. His attitude was, 'I've cultivated this property for 45 years. How dare someone tell me what I can or can't do on my own land.'"
Soutar wrote the first version of the play over five months, subsequently rewriting it to include herself (played by Christine Beaulieu) as a main character. "She guides us through the piece, holding the audience's hand so we're not overwhelmed by all the information. Although I was overwhelmed sometimes."
The University of Ottawa connection
Soutar's research included consulting with Illimar Altosaar, a professor of Biochemistry, Microbiology and Immunology at U of O on the mind-boggling complexity of GMOs. She would end up including him as a secondary character in the play.
There's little doubt where Altosaar stands on the continuing debate about the safety of GMOs. "Genetic modification has been a human activity since someone in the fertile crescent of Babylon or Mesopotamia first said, 'Wow, these little wheat seeds taste good. Could we get more and could they be bigger?'"
Is Soutar successful in presenting both sides of the corporation-versus-the-farmer picture?
"She presents a very interesting picture of food production all up and down the line," says Altosaar. "She doesn't really care about Monsanto winning or Schmeiser winning ... she's extremely philosophical."
The outcome
Seeds, especially in the first act, has been described as often dense and demanding in its exposition of biology and law. That level of detail is essential, says Soutar.
"A lot of policy makers and politicians and corporations kind of hope that no one cares about the details because that's where the devil is. But if we don't acquaint ourselves with details we won't understand what's going on."
Lighting, music, video, suspense: all these elements help audiences negotiate the play's thickets according to Soutar.
In any case, thinking is part of being an engaged citizen, she says. "We're saying to the audience, 'You have to do some of the work too. You have to come with us.'"
SEEDS
Where: NAC English Theatre
When: March 26-April 12 (previews March 26 &; 27; opening March 28)
Tickets: NAC box office, Ticketmaster outlets, 1-888-991-2787, nac-cna.ca
© Copyright (c) The Ottawa Citizen
]]></text></news-item>