<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTC-S9C1-F08V-6033"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>SALES TRICKS  HOW CHRISTIE TORE DOWN TESLA AND LET CAR DEALERS KEEP A STRANGLEHOLD </title><source>The Star-Ledger (Newark, New Jersey)</source><author>Julie O'Connor, STAR-LEDGER STAFF</author><text><![CDATA[direct from its store at the mall.
But no. Instead we are chasing Tesla out of New Jersey. Gov. Chris Christie's political minions at the Motor Vehicle Commission last week voted to revoke Tesla's license to sell cars, which the agency had issued under Gov. Jon Corzine.
That means Tesla will no longer be allowed to sell from its showrooms at the Mall at Short Hills and Garden State Plaza. It adds New Jersey to just a handful of states that ban direct car sales. So much for improving our state's business climate. Christie doesn't tell Apple how to sell its products. So why is he telling Tesla?
The governor has dodged responsibility by claiming he's bound by law to enforce this rule. That's bunk. He's referring to an outdated law that has long gone unenforced. It was intended to curb predatory behavior by car manufacturers and big dealerships that seek to devour smaller ones, not legitimate competition. If Christie doesn't like this statute, why hasn't he proposed changing it?
We've seen him change laws: dismantling tenure, capping property taxes, overhauling our state's pension system. His officials at the Department of Environmental Protection pushed through a powerful waiver rule to allow his administration to bypass regulations.
So what's stopping our hell-bent governor now?
In a word, money. You can bet he's acting at the behest of car dealers who want to protect their brawny monopoly and tossed big contributions into his political coffers. As Star-Ledger columnist Paul Mulshine pointed out, the hypocrisy is priceless. The very same governor who just complained that "government's trying to control the free market" is now stepping in to do so himself. And not only is Christie incurring the wrath of almost everyone on the political spectrum, he's ignoring the effect on the climate.
This we've seen before. Christie has dismissed climate change as "esoteric," and his administration is requiring everyone to tack on only a 1-foot margin of safety after Hurricane Sandy, even though nearby states are rebuilding higher. He also withdrew New Jersey from the Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative, which deprives our state of revenue that could be used for clean energy, and raided at least $1 billion from our state's clean-energy fund in order to balance his budget.
And let's not forget that sweeping waiver rule that lets his administration flout long-standing environmental regulations -- an open invitation to polluters.
To that growing list of climate crimes, we now add Christie's attack on Tesla.
Electric cars help reduce carbon emissions that contribute to global warming, and reduce our dependence on foreign oil. The Tesla is still too expensive to be a car for the masses, but with the electric car industry looking to expand, it could get a lot more affordable in the future. And the company has every reason to sell direct: Car dealers don't want to peddle Teslas because they don't require routine maintenance such as oil changes or tuneups, which is how the dealers make most of their money.
So for once, Christie's hit upon an issue that offends consumers, environmentalists and business people alike. Our governor should be supporting a successful American car company -- not getting paid to smother it.
]]></text></news-item>