<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTC-5NK1-F09T-F2KT"><date>2014-03-22</date><title>Board will receive report on Central Basin Water District's slush fund</title><source>Press - Telegram (Long Beach California)</source><author>Mike Sprague</author><text><![CDATA[COMMERCE >> A legal firm hired by a regional water district plans to deliver Monday its secret report on a $2.7-million slush fund that allegedly funneled cash to relatives, political allies and friends including a former assemblyman charged in a federal criminal case with money laundering.
It remains to be seen whether the report from Arent Fox, a legal firm hired by the Central Basic Municipal Water District more than a year ago, will be made public. Officials paid the firm $500,000 to do an investigation into the fund, linked to former Assemblyman Tom Calderon.
For now, the details of the report, which have been seen by one member of the board, remain secret.
"I can't talk about specifics," Director James Roybal said. "The lawyers are always clamping us down. They want me not to say anything. They're really strict on what I can say and I can't say."
Roybal said he's not even sure if the report will immediately be made public.
"I know some board members want it be public, but there might be legal issues, we have to be careful about it," Roybal said. "I don't know to what extent we can release the whole thing."
The report's contents haven't been shared with four other members of the board because all have conflicts of interest, Roybal said.
Two media law experts said the district needs to make the document available to the public.
"It's absolutely a public record under the Brown Act," said Gil Aguirre, a San Gabriel Valley open-government activist. "If they want to keep the report secret, they would have had to meet in closed session ... and then claim the report was prepared by attorneys for litigation," Aguirre said.
The report is listed for discussion on an open portion of the board's Monday agenda. The meeting, which is open to the public, begins at 10 a.m. at the agency's headquarters in Commerce.
Jim Ewert, general counsel for California Newspaper Publishers Association, said Arent Fox's work is subject to disclosure.
The slush fund under scrutiny was first brought to light as part of a whistle-blower lawsuit filed against the district by director Leticia Vasquez.
Vasquez said she plans to argue Monday for its immediate release.
"The public has a right to know what happened to the $2.7 million," Vasquez said. "We have a responsibility to the voters."
Vasquez claims the multimillion-dollar slush fund, approved by members Robert Apodaca, Art Chacon and Phil Hawkins, was created to design and manage a secret water-storage program.
Former General manager Art Aguilar, who was deposed in a separate civil suit, acknowledged the existence of the program.
The district has confronted several challenges in recent weeks. It was the subject of an FBI raid linked to a criminal corruption case against Calderon and brother state Sen. Ron Calderon. District officials also have come under fire for paying off $16,000 to a woman injured in a accident with Chacon. A resident of Commerce, Chacon has not had a driver's license for nearly a decade but continues to collect mileage and $600-a-month car allowance from the district.
Last week the district's insurance company said it was considering pulling Central Basin's policy due to dysfunction on its board.
Central Basin General Manager Tony Perez referred questions about the secret slush fund and the Arent Fox report to Ricardo Olivarez, Central Basin's house attorney.
Olivarez did not return calls seeking comment.
Three directors - Robert Apodaca, Art Chacon and Phil Hawkins - all voted on the appropriation of the $2.7 million, and Vasquez filed the lawsuit seeking to recover for the district the money that was paid to two legal firms.
Staff Writer Steve Scauzillo contributed to this story.
]]></text></news-item>