<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTC-B011-JC65-50CN"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Crews mopping up oil spill in Texas' Galveston Bay</title><source>Associated Press International</source><author>MICHAEL GRACZYK</author><text><![CDATA[TEXAS CITY, Texas (AP) - The cleanup of an unknown amount of thick, sticky oil that spilled into Galveston Bay blocked traffic Sunday between the Gulf of Mexico and one of the world's busiest petrochemical transportation waterways, affecting all vessels, even cruise ships.
A barge carrying nearly a million gallons (3.8 million liters) of marine fuel oil collided with a ship Saturday afternoon, springing a leak. Officials believe only one of the barge's tanks - which holds 168,000 gallons (636,000 liters), was breached, though Coast Guard Petty Officer Andy Kendrick said Sunday it wasn't clear how much oil spilled.
Crews were skimming oil out of the water and containment booms were brought in to protect environmentally sensitive areas of the Houston ship channel, Kendrick said. The ship channel is closed from the mouth of the Houston ship channel, between Galveston Island and Bolivar Peninsula, Coast Guard Lt. Sam Danus said.
"Unified command is aware of the situation and is communicating with the cruise ship companies," Danus said.
The area is also home to popular bird habitats, especially during the approaching migratory shorebird season, but Kendrick said there have been no reports of wildlife being impacted.
The Texas City dike, a popular fishing spot that goes out into the Gulf for a few miles (kilometers), is also closed. Lee Rilat, 58, owns Lee's Bait and Tackle, the last store before the access road to the dike, which was blocked by a police car on a breezy, overcast Sunday. If it weren't for the spill, Rilat's business would be hopping.
"This would be the first spring deal, the first real weekend for fishing," Rilat said. He says ships and barges have collided before, but this is the first time - at least this year - that someone has sprung a leak.
The collision was still being investigated, the Coast Guard said.
The captain of the 585-foot (178-meter) ship, Summer Wind, reported the spill just after noon Saturday. Six crew members from the tow vessel, which was going from Texas City to Bolivar, were injured, the Coast Guard said.
Kirby Inland Marine, which owns the tow vessel and barge, is working with the Texas General Land Office and many other federal, state and nonprofit agencies to respond to the spill, The Coast Guard said. Tara Kilgore, an operations coordinator with Kirby Inland Marine, declined to comment Saturday.
Jim Suydam, spokesman for the Texas' General Land Office, described the type of oil the barge was carrying as "sticky, gooey, thick, tarry stuff."
"That stuff is terrible to have to clean up," he said.
Richard Gibbons, the conservation director of the Houston Audubon Society, said there is important shorebird habitat on both sides of the ship channel. One is the Bolivar Flats Shorebird Sanctuary just to the east, which Gibbons said attracts 50,000 to 70,000 shorebirds to shallow mud flats that are perfect foraging habitat.
"The timing really couldn't be much worse since we're approaching the peak shorebird migration season," Gibbons said. He added that tens of thousands of wintering birds remain in the area.
]]></text></news-item>