<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTD-DFK1-DXJR-H3FF"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Man dupes flat buyers to the tune of Rs 2.50 crore</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Nishikant Karlikar</author><text><![CDATA[THANE: A 34-year-old person has been arrested for duping several persons to the tune of Rs 2.50 crore by promising them flats at a relatively lower rate.
According to the police, the accused, identified as Amit Devendra Singh, claimed that there were flats on sale that were 'seized by the bank'. Singh claimed that he had contacts with employees of local banks from the city and could get flats that were seized by banks for non-payment of loan amounts.
A 34-year-old person has been arrested for duping several persons to the tune of Rs 2.50 crore after he promised them to sell the seized flats of a bank at relatively lower price than market rates.
According to police, the accused has been identified as Amit Devendra Singh would operate from a commercial complex under the name of Bridgestone consultant located at the Anant Laxmi building located near B-cabin area of Naupada.
Explaining the modus operandi, Singh using his network of friends and acquaintances would spread the message of 'flats on sale seized by bank'. Singh claimed that he has internal contact with a local bank based in Thane and can give the seized apartments due to non-payment of the loan.
He would convince the victims that he could get flats at half the market rate in plush areas of the city, a police official said.
However, Singh ran out of luck when he duped Mohanlal Agrawal. Singh had taken Rs 75 lakh from Agrawal and had promised him a flat in the city that was lower than the market rate. After a few months when there was no sign of the flat, Agrawal lodged a complaint with the Naupada police.
''The accused has also asked victims to go to the registrar office but would never turn up and give some lame accuses,'' said a police official.
approached the Naupada police station and alleged that Singh had taken nearly Rs 75 Lakh from him and through Cash Demand draft, and cheque to his mother's account malti devendra singh and had promised to give him a flat at half of the market rate however, till date he has not given flat.
"The accused would tell them the registry would be done on a particular date and even called up several people to the registrar officer however, he himself never turned up and gave several excuses," said a police official.
Another victim, Ashok Ghag had also given Rs 39 lakh and Arun Sulakhe too had given the accused a sum of Rs 1. 03 crore and had not given the flats he had promised came forward and registered a case with the Naupada police station.
When the victims started demanding their money back, from the accused and pressure started mounting on him the accused hatched a plan and faked his death. wrote a suicide note in which he mentioned all the names of the victim as they were responsible for his death.
However, the police tracked him down and arrested him. and vanished for few days to which the victims got frightened however, the police officer swiftly tracked him and arrested the accused.
Further investigations are on and a case has been registered under Section 420 of the Indian Penal Code.
A police official informed that they are investigation the case and several other persons duped by the accused are coming forward and registering the case against the accused.
A case has been registered at Naupada police station under section 420 of the Indian Penal code.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>