<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTG-W4X1-DYR7-C2FC"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Worker Abuse at American Bases</title><source>International New York Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
Some 37,000 privately contracted workers, mostly from India, Nepal, the Philippines and Uganda, prepare meals, do laundry, sort garbage and provide other essential services to American military personnel abroad. These workers are paid as little as $150 to $500 per month and often work 12-hour days with little time off. Meanwhile, American contractors billed the Department of Defense an average of $67,600 a year per, or more than 10 times the top annual wages of the workers. All told, their services have cost American taxpayers $53.6 billion since 2001, with contracts awarded to just three major defense contractors: DynCorp Intercontinental, the Fluor Corporation and KBR.
Washington has made repeated attempts since 2006 to make sure that contractors respect American and international laws banning human trafficking and forced labor. But, in 2012, the American Civil Liberties Union, in concert with the Yale Lowenstein International Human Rights Clinic, published ''Victims of Complacency,'' an in-depth report on the problem of migrant-worker abuse on United States military bases. Then, in September 2012, President Obama issued an executive order strengthening protections against human trafficking in federal contracts, while Congress acted to ban unreasonable recruitment fees.
These steps, worthy as they are, have not halted abuses, according to a report broadcast on Al Jazeera's ''Fault Lines'' earlier this month. One major problem is that not a single contractor or subcontractor has been fined, suspended or terminated. Lip service to the rules in the form of sensitivity-training programs and stated ''zero-tolerance'' policies appears to suffice.
The root of the problem goes deeper, to the supply chain, a well-entrenched labor trafficking system centered in Dubai and other Gulf states. A villager in India or Nepal is trafficked just as easily through this system to work on building the new World Cup soccer stadium in Qatar as to serve food on an American base in Iraq or Afghanistan.
Last fall, the Federal Acquisition Regulation Council - a rule-making body - and the Department of Defense proposed new rules targeting some of the worst abuses. The rules take effect this year. But more rules will be of little use without enforcement. American military contractors need to know that they and their subcontractors will be audited regularly and that they will face serious penalties, including stiff fines and the loss of lucrative contracts, if abuses are found. It is high time to move beyond pious words and toothless warnings. Both workers and American taxpayers deserve a system that is fair and just.
]]></text></news-item>