<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTG-HY21-DYRX-X0C0"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Tory donor on trial for fraud leads radio deal: Alleged fraudster linked to Conservative grandee Media watchdog aware of imminent prosecution</title><source>The Guardian (London)</source><author>Juliette Garside</author><text><![CDATA[The takeover of London's biggest commercial Asian radio stations is being led by a former business associate of Tory grandee Cecil Parkinson who is awaiting trial for fraud at the Old Bailey.
Ketan Somaia, whose interests once included hotels, banking, motoring and media, is being prosecuted for fraudulently taking $23m (£14m) in a series of deals dating back to 1999.
At a trial scheduled to begin this month, he faces 11 counts of obtaining money by deception and two counts of perjury, but the Guardian has learned he is playing a leading role in the acquisition of four broadcasting licences formerly owned by the Sunrise radio group.
Somaia's involvement has been flagged to Ofcom, which has a duty to approve every change of ownership, though the media regulator is likely to delay any decision until the case has been heard.
The stations were acquired by Lyca Mobile, a UK firm which specialises in cut price international phone calls. The company says it has hired Somaia as a consultant on the venture. Ofcom must now judge whether the company is a fit and proper holder of a broadcast licence.
If he is convicted, Somaia's association with Lyca could prove embarrassing for London mayor Boris Johnson. The Lyca group donated more than £425,000 to the Conservative party in the year to October 2012, becoming one of its largest sponsors during the period. The support is understood to have gone largely to Johnson's campaign.
The Sunrise Radio Group, founded by the entrepreneur Avtar Lit, launched the UK's first 24-hour Asian radio station in 1989 and eventually reached millions of listeners each week broadcasting from Scotland to Slough. But it had been struggling in recent years and was put into administration in January after a £400,000 tax dispute with HMRC.
Four of the group's broadcasting licences covering London, Romford and Slough, and its studios in Romford, were bought in February by the Lyca group, in a deal arranged by administrators Grant Thornton.
While Somaia is not listed as a shareholder in Lyca Media II, the vehicle created to acquire the Sunrise assets, staff at the stations have described him as the public face of the new owners.
They say Somaia and Lycatel international development director, Anil Shetty, were introduced by two representatives from Grant Thornton as representing the new owners to surprised staff at the main Sunrise offices in Southall, west London, on 4 February.
One employee, who asked to remain anonymous, said: "We were called up to the fourth floor for a meeting and were introduced to Ketan Somaia and Anil Shetty. Ketan came across as the senior person."
Somaia did not respond to requests for comment. Speaking on behalf of Lyca, Shetty confirmed he had attended the Sunrise offices with Somaia on the day of the takeover, but said Somaia had no financial involvement with the venture.
"Mr Somaia acts solely as a consultant to Lyca Media II, in relation to the recent acquisition by Lyca Media II of assets of the former radio business Sunrise, as purchased from administrators Grant Thornton."
Of Indian origin but born in Kenya, Somaia made his fortune in Africa during the 1980s and 1990s from importing cars, owning hotels and securing government contracts. At its height his Dolphin business empire was chaired for eight years by Parkinson, a former Tory party chairman. Dolphin twice sponsored the Miss World beauty pageant, with Somaia presiding as a judge, and its assets included a chain of hotels, among them the Treetops Lodge in Kenya, where the young Queen Elizabeth spent her honeymoon.
But by the early 2000s, Somaia had lost control of many of his commercial interests. His Delphis bank, acquired from the remnants of the corruption-wrecked Bank of Credit and Commerce International, was wound down in Mauritius, Kenya and Tanzania.
The Old Bailey prosecution is being brought by Murli Mirchandani, an Indian businessman who made his first fortune trading between Germany and west Africa, and who is now based in Dubai.
Between June 1999 and May 2000, Mirchandani says he was persuaded by Somaia to hand over millions of dollars in a series of business transactions and loans.
The indictment lists several alleged money transfers from Mirchandani to Somaia including $7.5m for a 10% stake in Delphis Bank of Mauritius, $2.5m for a share in another company called Driscoll, $2.8m for half the shares in Diamond Mining Corporation of Liberia, $3m to help purchase a bank in Tanzania, and $1.85m for a share in the Block Hotels group.
Shetty said Lyca was unaware of the charges against Somaia.
Mirchandani, who during the last 15 years brought previous cases against Somaia in the civil courts, has hired one of the country's leading business crime lawyers, Michael O'Kane, of Peters & Peters.
Ofcom declined to comment on the progress of its scrutiny of the Sunrise takeover. A spokeswoman said: "Ofcom is assessing a licence transfer application relating to four radio licences, part of the Sunrise Radio group. The proposed licence transfers are subject to Ofcom's consent. Our decision on the application will be published on our website as soon as it has been reached."
Founded in the UK by Sri Lankan entrepreneurs Subaskaraan Allarajah and Milind Kangle, Lyca rents airspace from mobile networks and resells it for international calls. The brand was launched in 2005 and now has an estimated euros 1bn turnover, operating what it claims is the world's largest virtual mobile network.
Ketan Somaia's defunct business was chaired for eight years by former Tory
party chairman Lord Parkinson
]]></text></news-item>