<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTG-WCB1-DXDT-604V"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>First charges in the horse meat scandal after a year as slaughterhouse bosses are accused of breaking food chain rules</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>DAILY MAIL REPORTER</author><text><![CDATA[Peter Boddy and David Moss accused of breaching food regulationsFollows an investigation by Food Standards Agency in the wake of scandalNo one has previously been charged over the infiltration of horse meat into frozen beef products
Two slaughterhouse bosses have become the first people to face criminal charges relating to last year's horse meat scandal.
Peter Boddy, owner of an abattoir in Yorkshire, and David Moss, the facility's manager, are accused of breaching food regulations which state that the source of meat should be traceable from field to fork.
The charges follow a joint investigation by the Food Standards Agency, Dyfed Powys Police and Calderdale Council.
Boddy, 63, was arrested in February accused of fraudulently selling equine flesh for use in kebabs and burgers sold in Britain.
Under the law, operators of food businesses should be able to provide details of where the animal came from and to whom it was supplied at every stage of the process.
Sue Patten, head of fraud at the Crown Prosecution Service, said: 'Following a joint investigation by the Food Standards Agency, Dyfed Powys Police and Calderdale Council, criminal proceedings have been instituted against two individuals for failing to comply with the traceability requirements of horses slaughtered at and sold from premises in Todmorden, West Yorkshire.
'It is alleged that Peter Boddy, owner of a West Yorkshire slaughterhouse and game dealer, and David Moss, the manager of the slaughterhouse, failed to comply with traceability requirements for horses slaughtered at their premises.'
It is claimed that they each committed two breaches of Regulation 4 of the General Food Regulations 2004 between July 2012 and February 12 2013.
Moss is also charged with one count of forgery over claims that he faked an invoice for the sale of horse meat.
The pair are due to appear at Westminster Magistrates' Court on April 14. It is not being alleged that the horse meat was being sold as another meat.
Ms Patten said yesterday: 'The decision to prosecute was taken in accordance with the Code for Crown Prosecutors.
'It has been determined that there is a realistic prospect of conviction and that a prosecution is in the public interest.'
The scandal began in January 2013, when Ireland's Food Safety authority found horse DNA in burgers on sale in Tesco, Aldi and Lidl.
Sainsbury's, Asda and the Co-op also withdrew some frozen products as a precaution, but were not found to be selling contaminated food
It quickly spread to Britain and developed into a European-wide crisis, which saw ready meals taken off the shelves.
In addition to burgers, frozen spaghetti and lasagne meals, including those produced by Findus, were removed.
The investigation lasted for almost 12 months, with seizures of allegedly contaminated products continuing until December 2013.
]]></text></news-item>