<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTG-HY21-DYRX-X0F4"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Bosnia: War is over - now Serbs and Bosniaks fight to win control of a brutal history: Serbs accused of trying to create 'alternative reality' The word 'genocide' is removed from memorials</title><source>The Guardian (London)</source><author>Julian Borger Visegrad</author><text><![CDATA[After survivors and bereaved families put up a memorial to the mass slaughter in 1992 of Muslims in Visegrad, the response of the Serb authorities in the eastern Bosnian town was as unsubtle as it was symbolic. They ordered the word "genocide" chiselled off the stone monument.
A group of Visegrad widows soon restored the word in lipstick, only for it to be obscured by municipal white paint a few days later. This is a battle the town hall is not prepared to lose. When it sent a surveyor and workman into the town's Muslim cemetery with an angle grinder to erase the offending term on 23 January, they were accompanied by 150 policemen in riot gear. The message was clear.
The graveyard spat is a skirmish in a much bigger battle being fought in Bosnia - the continuation by bureaucratic means of the murderous four-year war of two decades ago. It is a struggle over collective memory and the power to write history.
"Those who committed the war crimes against us are still winning. They are killing our truth," said Bakira Hasecic, a Visegrad survivor who was raped multiple times by Serb paramilitaries at her home and in the local police station in 1992. Her sister was raped and killed. Her 18-year-old daughter was raped and had her head smashed by a rifle butt, but survived.
Hasecic now runs the Association of Women Victims of War. She and other Visegrad rape victims tried to protect the monument last month but failed because the town authorities turned up an hour earlier than announced, and in force.
"The police in their uniforms and caps brought back the memories of 1992. You relive those moments. My legs were shaking. When we arrived, we had no idea they had already done that to the monument. I couldn't bring myself to look at it."
However, the same morning and less than 200 yards away, Hasecic and other Bosniak survivors were successful in stopping another act of demolition. The Serb authorities want to knock down a house on Pionirska Street, where 59 Muslims were locked into a single room and incinerated on 14 June 1992. Relatives of the dead, with Hasecic's help, are trying to restore the house as a memorial.
The town council has countered by expropriating the building, claiming the road needs to be widened.
But no one in the neighbourhood believes the issue is about town planning. Serb nationalists are striving to suppress reminders of atrocities committed in the name of separatism, mostly against the country's Muslims (known as Bosniaks) and to construct an alternative history in which Serbs were the principal victims. Many Bosniaks and outside observers fear that this refusal to come to terms with the past means there are few guarantees that such acts will not be repeated.
Bosniaks and Croats have also been slow to allow memorials to civilian victims from other ethnicities, but it is in the Republika Srpska, the Serb-run half of Bosnia, where the scale of the killing was by far the greatest, and where the culture of denial is now the deepest.
Visegrad is a grim example. An eastern Bosnian town on the River Drina, it is home to Bosnia's best-known cultural artefact, the 16th century Mehmed Pasa Sokolovic bridge, a graceful span of 11 masonry arches made legendary by the Yugoslav Nobel laureate Ivo Andric.
In his 1945 novel, the Bridge on the Drina, it is silent witness to atrocities across generations. In 1992, it was spattered with blood once more. Serb paramilitaries calling themselves "The Avengers" and the "White Eagles" went on a killing spree through the town and surrounding villages, executing Muslims. Men, women and over a hundred children were slaughtered, many on the bridge itself, and their bodies dumped in the Drina.
The practice of barricading people into houses and setting them alight was reproduced several times. In another incident in nearby Bikavac, there were 60 victims.
A couple of miles outside Visegrad, young women and girls as young as 14 were held captive and repeatedly raped in the Vilina Vlas spa hotel. It was where the paramilitaries led by a pair of sadistic local cousins, Milan and Sredoje Lukic, made their wartime base. Muslim men were routinely tortured next door to where the women were raped and killed.
The estimates of the total number of victims in the Visegrad municipality range from 1,600 to 3,000. The rest of the area's Muslims fled; most made their way south to Gora&#382;de, which became a Bosniak enclave and survived a three-year Serbian siege. Before the war, the Visegrad municipality had a population over 21,000, two thirds Muslim. Now the population is 12,000, 1,500 of them Bosniaks.
Today's survivors are post-war returnees to the Visegrad outskirts, often living in villages or houses where loved ones were executed. Twenty years after the bloodletting they remain marginalised, routinely denied the meagre social benefits doled out by the authorities.
After an interregnum in which slightly more moderate parties held sway, the Serb Democratic Party (or SDS for Srpska Demokratska Stranka) regained control of the municipality in October 2012. The extreme nationalist party of Radovan Karadzic, which hacked out the Republika Srpska and oversaw the "ethnic cleansing" of Muslims and Croats, is back in charge in Visegrad and 24 other Serb towns with its own version of what happened between 1992 and 1995. Hence the municipal use of angle-grinders and bulldozers.
"With the old mayor we could co-operate much better. We had different opinions but it was discussed in a more civilised way," said Bilal Memisevic, the head of Visegrad's Islamic community council. Both his parents were murdered in 1992, when he was studying abroad. "Since the SDS came to power, they started ignoring us. They don't mention employment, or the economy. It's all about the war and the manipulation of 1992. They have built an alternative reality."
That alternative reality is visible everywhere in town. In the main square, there is large statue of a knight bearing a cross and a sword, dedicated to "the defenders of the Republika Srpska, with the gratitude of the people of Visegrad".
In mid-March each year, hundreds of Serbs parade through the town to commemorate Dra&#382;a Mihajlovic, the leader of the ultra-nationalist Chetnik movement during the second world war, who carried out a series of atrocities against Muslims in the Drina valley. They come as Chetniks, with long wild beards, fur hats, and black skull-and-crossbone flags. Many of the killers in 1992 dressed the same way. It is a terrifying annual spectacle for Visegrad's remaining Bosniaks.
The most powerful man in town now is Miroslav Kojic, a soldier and secret policeman for Republika Srpska during the war and now Visegrad's SDS representative in the Republika Srpska parliament.
He provides a legal defence of the municipality's actions, arguing that there have been no convictions at the Hague tribunal specifically for genocide that would justify the disputed memorial. (Visegrad was taken from the list of municipalities in Karadzic's genocide indictment to slim the charge sheet and speed up his trial, but the tribunal has declared the town was subjected to "one of the most comprehensive and ruthless campaigns of ethnic cleansing in the Bosnian conflict"). As for Pionirska Street, Kojic says the issue is a non-political town planning matter.
Of his own wartime role, Kojic - an energetic man with a piercing stare - is heated, launching into a strangely inverted version of Visegrad's wartime history, in which Bakira Hasecic supposedly tortured Serb policemen and soldiers, and Visegrad's Serbs withstood a brutal Bosniak siege in 1992 and 1993.
The narrative of Serb victimhood is pieced together from sporadic Bosniak acts of resistance during the war. After the former Yugoslav National Army bombarded Muslim areas of Visegrad at the outbreak of conflict in April 1992, a group of armed Muslims took some Serb policemen hostage and threatened to blow up a nearby hydroelectric dam if shelling continued. The dam was retaken by the army which then withdrew on May 19, handing the town over to Serb nationalists and paramilitaries that carried out the atrocities against Bosniak civilians.
In summer 1992, survivors of the concentration camps helped form a Bosniak First Visegrad Brigade which fought a guerrilla campaign for a year in the wooded hills on the west bank of the Drina, but never came close to surrounding or threatening the city. After surviving multiple rapes, Hasecic, did join the Bosnian army, but there is no evidence of her mistreating Serbs.
Today the Bosniak resistance effort is the justification for public memorials in central Visegrad for Serb soldiers and even Russian volunteer fighters on the Serb side, and the absence of equivalent monuments to Bosniak civilians. It is a pattern repeated around the Republika Srpska.
In Visegrad, the remaining Bosniaks have become accustomed to the official state of denial. Omar Bosankic and Elvedin Musanovic, two Muslim men in their mid-30s out strolling one recent afternoon on Visegrad's bridge, insist that relations with their Serb neighbours are fine as long as the war is not mentioned.
"No one wants to admit anything. They never want to talk about it," Bosankic said. As a 14-year-old boy, he helped fish bodies of murdered Muslims out of the Drina at night in his home village of Barimo, five miles downstream. "I still have images that come back all the time."
The two men are unimpressed by objections to the Bosniak memorial.
"What else happened here but genocide?" Bosankic asked. "Everybody who lives here knows what happened."
Captions:
Clockwise from top: a woman prays during the 2012 burial of Bosniak victims of a mass killing in Visegrad in 1992 - an incident which the town's Serbian authorities refuse to recognise amounted to genocide. Bosniaks fled the town in 1992 after a series of killings. Bakira Hasecic defends a house, where 59 people died, from demolition Main photograph: Elvis Barkucic/AFP
]]></text></news-item>