<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTG-PP21-JDJN-61F6"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Over 200 people fined in Dubai for fly-posting</title><source>7 Days (United Arab Emirates)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A clampdown launched after a surge of complaints from the public has resulted in more than 200 people booked for fly-posting in Dubai.
The municipality is getting tough on the problem in the emirate, issuing fines to those caught putting up posters without permission.
They have also seized half a tonne of posters and illegal adverts.
Abdul Majeed Saifaie, director of waste management at Dubai Municipality, said: "It has been recently noticed that many illegal random ads and posters have been spreading on walls, doors, parking areas and public squares, which negatively affect the hygiene and distort the appearance of the city.
"Such practices are a clear violation of Article 59 of Local Order No. 11 of 2003 and its regulations. The department has intensified the monitoring of offences by individuals and companies, resulting in the penalties on 226 violations after due notifications and removal of 500kg of paper ads and posters."
Saifaie said municipality workers use machines to strip the illegal adverts from walls to ensure no debris is left behind.
And he said the authority is also trying to get the message across to the public that fly-posting is an offence. Saifaie said: "Cleanliness and preservation of the city is an important part the municipality's work, and we are trying our best to communicate with all segments of society through available media channels and awareness campaigns in most common languages in Dubai," he said.
"The campaign came as a result of a large number of complaints from the public, and aimed to educate society about the negative impact of this phenomenon, both in terms of distortion of the aesthetic appearance of the city and damage to public property and facilities."
He said that the perpetrators are tracked down using information on the posters, such as addresses or telephone numbers.
"All types of unauthorised ads and posters contrary to the appearance, ethics and morals of the emirate will be fined and removed," he said.
He did not say how much the fine is, however it is thought to be about Dhs200.
Fly-posting can be reported to the municipality via the hotline 800 900.
news@7days.ae
]]></text></news-item>