<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTG-PHC1-DYJJ-P2MR"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Be a good customer and good service will follow</title><source>The Post-Crescent (Appleton, Wisconsin)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Life, liberty and the home delivery of barbecued chicken wings. Two of these are rights described in the Declaration of Independence, and one isn't.
Can you guess which one?
The Declaration of Independence says that Americans are endowed by their Creator with certain inalienable rights, including life, liberty and the pursuit of happiness. But, if your own pursuit of happiness includes the guaranteed home delivery of your favorite party food, you're going to be
disappointed. It's not
an inalienable
right.
Allow me to explain: Any business, including your local purveyor of chicken wings, can provide its products or services to you at its discretion. If the business wants to earn money, it will. But, the point is that it doesn't have to. I'm not talking about businesses being allowed to discriminate against
people because of
their race, religion,
sexual orientation,
etc. Thankfully, that
kind of discrimination
is illegal. However,
businesses do have
the right to refuse
service to "bad"
customers.
What is a "bad" customer? Recently, a consumer called the Better Business Bureau and wanted to file a complaint against a local restaurant that frequently delivered barbecued chicken wings to her home. She admitted that she was a picky customer. Sometimes she'd call the restaurant and complain that her wings were too saucy, or not saucy enough. At other times, they were too spicy or not spicy enough. She was as
hard-to-please as
Goldilocks. One time, she called the restaurant to complain that it hadn't given her enough napkins.
Finally, the restaurant put her on its "do not deliver to" list, meaning she'd have to find another source for her chicken wings. The basis of her complaint to the BBB was that she wanted to be removed from the restaurant's non-delivery list, and she wanted the BBB to compel the restaurant to serve her.
A lot of attention is paid to how businesses can provide good customer service. But good customer service is
a two-way street.
What about the
customer's role?
Here are six tips to
being a better
customer:
Remember the Golden Rule: Treat others the way you'd like to be treated. How would you feel if you were the store clerk getting yelled at by a customer?
Don't shoot the messenger: It's not the clerk's fault that the store has a no-return policy.
People are only human. Mistakes happen, but most of them are accidents and done without malice. If the screw-up was unintentional, cut him or her some slack.
Respect the
rules. Sure, you can
certainly ask if the
store will honor a
coupon that expired
last week. But don't
get mad if it
won't.
Keep your
expectations
reasonable. It's
reasonable to expect a good product and good customer service, but it's unreasonable to
expect the company to do whatever you want, whenever you want, and for as little as you're willing to pay.
If you're going to be difficult, be nice. If you have a penchant for liking things only your way and no one else's, find and politely ask for a solution that's mutually beneficial. Ask for your wings to be "naked" (no sauce), with sauce on the side that you can add yourself. Problem solved.
After all, don't you want to be a "good" customer? The good customers get the best customer service - and probably as many napkins as they want.
- Susan Bach is regional director of the Better Business Bureau for northeastern Wisconsin. She can be reached at sbach@wisconsin.bbb.org
or 920-734-4352.
]]></text></news-item>