<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTG-P5G1-JCBF-222M"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Be wary of gold mine proposal; Our view</title><source>The Herald (Rock Hill, South Carolina)</source><author>Rock Hill Herald Online</author><text><![CDATA[If residents of Lancaster County want the hundreds of jobs that could come with a giant new gold mining operation, the tradeoff could be costly: 1,100 acres of damaged wetlands and a scarred landscape.
For the past two years, Romarco Minerals of Canada has sought to reopen a long-closed mining site near Kershaw. The new mine would be on about 4,500 acres, more than half of which are expected to be used for gold extraction.
Many residents favor the mine as a boost to the local economy that would bring in as many as 420 new jobs during the peak of the mining operation. But critics say the environmental costs could be substantial – even higher than previously thought, according to a new study released this month by the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers.
Of the 1,100 acres of swamps, bogs and other wetlands compromised by the mining operation, 120 acres would be directly affected. That is one of the largest potential environmental impacts of any project under consideration in the state.
While those wetlands essentially would be destroyed, another 982 could be damaged indirectly – either permanently or temporarily – when miners lower groundwater levels to excavate gold, the report said. In addition, wildlife and plants that rely on those wetlands for habitat could be adversely affected over the proposed 15-year lifespan of the mine.
Romarco has pledged to try to minimize the environmental harm to the landscape. But some mining pits would be 800 feet deep, and the project also would create a toxic tailings pond and destroy nearly 5 miles of creeks.
Romarco has presented a proposal to mitigate the environmental damage, but it wouldn’t directly benefit Lancaster County in any way. The mitigation package would protect nearly 4,400 acres, mostly in Richland County on the Wateree River southeast of Columbia. The package includes public access and use of Cook’s Mountain, a rare land form.
While that is a worthy project, it does nothing to reduce the damage in Kershaw, which is more than an hour’s drive from the Richland County site. It sets up an unusual choice for residents of Lancaster County: Let us dig up a huge parcel of land containing fragile wetlands in your county and, in return, we’ll enhance a different piece of property in Richland County.
The environmental impact statement will be finalized after a public comment period and an April 24 hearing in Kershaw. The Corps then will use the 2,400-page report to decide later this year whether to issue Romarco a wetlands disturbance permit, which is vital to starting the mine.
We hope Lancaster County residents and other interested parties will study the details and think twice before getting behind this project. It has the earmarks of a devil’s bargain.
]]></text></news-item>