<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTH-PBN1-J9YR-G033"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Wikileaks reveals US concerns over 'Wales' independent streak causing friction within UK'; Cables posted on the whistleblowing website show a US ambassador telling Hillary Clinton Wales is 'not necessarily interested in producing energy/electricity for the rest of the UK'</title><source>walesonline.co.uk</source><author>By James McCarthy</author><text><![CDATA[US government officials feared Wales would experience a "Scottish- style devolution" that could lead to "intense struggle" between Wales and Westminster, secret documents reveal.
Cables posted on whistleblowing website Wikileaks, dating back to 2009, warned there was "considerable national pride among the Welsh". The missives were variously marked 'sensitive' 'confidential' and 'NOFORN' - which means 'no foreign nationals'
"Various contacts referred to Wales as 'our country' to embassy officials on multiple occasions," then US ambassador Louis Susman wrote to former American secretary of state Hillary Clinton.
He warned her that this could be problematic when it came to energy matters.
"The Welsh Government has already initiated a number of innovative energy programs, some of which could later be expanded to the UK level," Mr Susman said.
"On the other hand, Wales' independent streak may cause friction with the UK. Many Welsh think the UK has already 'milked' Welsh resources without providing anything in return."
Wikileaks 
The diplomat claimed Wales saw itself as "self-sufficient in renewable energy" and "not necessarily interested in producing energy/electricity for the rest of the UK".
"As its independent political power grows, the Welsh may look to exert their power and block projects seen as beneficial to the UK but harmful to Wales," Mr Susman said.
"It is possible that within two years Wales could have a Scottish-style devolution.
"While it still would not technically have the ability to control energy projects, it would have the power to legislate over the environment, which it might be able to use to block nuclear and other projects.
"If this occurs, HMG will have more difficulty in making country-wide decisions.
"Energy and environmental issues could become the focus of an intense struggle between London and Cardiff."
Plaid Cymru was "vehemently opposed to nuclear energy."
The American claimed Welsh Government energy advisor Dr Ron Loveland told the embassy that "even raising the issue of nuclear energy with Welsh Deputy First Minister and leader of Plaid Cymru Ieuan Wyn Jones is 'too sensitive.'" Mr Jones has since left those posts. "This negative attitude toward civil nuclear energy is pervasive in Wales, as several contacts echoed to ESTHOff similar concerns about nuclear waste."
ESTHOff refers to Environment, Science, Technology, and Health officers.
Mr Susman discussed conversations with former Tory leader Nick Bourne, now Lord Bourne.
The conservative "told the Ambassador that his party was very optimistic about UK general elections in 2010 and is hoping to increase their share from three of the 40 Welsh seats to double-digits."
"He said the Tories' overall move to the centre would attract new voters in Wales and said that Welsh voters are willing to switch parties for the first time in many years." Mr Susman said.
"Bourne's predictions are significant because Wales has been one of Labour's most reliable strongholds."
The ambassador claimed "Bourne also predicted that devolution would proceed quickly and Wales would have its own parliament before 2011."
"He suggested the US should open a consulate in Cardiff," Mr Susman said.
"The request for a consulate in Wales is a familiar refrain."
Lord Bourne this week said the refrain was "familiarly unheeded as well".
"I remember those conversations and I was not too far out with regard to the elections," he said.
"I think we got eight seats rather than double digits.
"I still think they should open a consulate in Wales and they still are not paying attention.
"I remember a very interesting conversation with Louis. He came to my office in the Bay and we had a long and interesting discussion."
He thought they should "keep plugging away" until Wales had a consulate. There might be a better chance if Hilary Clinton becomes president.
"She traces her family back to Tenby," Lord Bourne said.
The Welsh Government declined to comment.
A Plaid Cymru spokeswoman said: "It's true that we believe that Wales should benefit from our natural resources and energy production and believe these areas should be devolved."
]]></text></news-item>