<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTH-SPG1-F0CC-S46J"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Greencoat UK Wind PLC Final Results Announcement -3-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The portfolio assets have performed in line with management expectations in terms of energy production, operational expenditure and overall cash flow generation. A more detailed discussion of the individual project performance and a review of the business in the period is covered in the Investment Manager's Report. Key Performance Indicators The Board believes that the following indicators, which are typical for investment funds, will provide shareholders with sufficient information to assess how effectively the Group is meeting its objectives.
(2) GBP10.2 million of which was paid after 31 December 2013 Ongoing Charges The ongoing charges ratio of the Company is 1.46 per cent. for the period to 31 December 2013. This is made up as follows and has been calculated using the AIC recommended methodology.
The management fee and priority profit share paid to the Investment Manager are based on the Net Asset Value. If they were stated with reference to the Adjusted Portfolio Value (including acquisition debt, in line with a number of the Company's peers) then the annual management fee and priority profit share would be 0.96 per cent., assuming 20 per cent. medium term gearing (current gearing 12.5 per cent.). The Investment Manager is not paid any performance or acquisition fees. Corporate and Social Responsibility Environmental The Group invests in wind farms and the environmental benefits of renewable energy are widely known. The Group has in place an Environmental, Social and Governance policy. The policy outlines the Group's approach to responsible investing, as well as the environmental standards which it aims to meet. Responsible Investing Principles have been applied to each of the investments made. Employees and Officers of the Company The Company does not have any employees and therefore employee policies are not required. The Directors of the Company are listed in the annual report. Social, Community and Human Rights Issues The Company's Environmental Social and Governance policy also outlines the Company's aims in relation to social standards, covering the requirement to continue to meet legal standards and good industry practice. The policy requires the Company to make reasonable endeavours to procure the ongoing compliance of its portfolio companies with the policy. The Investment Manager monitors compliance at the investment phase and through their attendance at Board meetings. Gender Diversity The Board comprises four men and one woman. The Board is aware of the benefits of diversity and considers this when appointing board directors. The Investment Manager operates an equal opportunities policy and its partners and employees comprise fifteen men and eight women. Principal Risks and Uncertainties Under the Financial Conduct Authority's Disclosure and Transparency Rules, the Directors are required to identify those material risks to which the Group is exposed and take appropriate steps to mitigate those risks. In the normal course of business, each asset has a rigorous risk management framework with a comprehensive risk register that is reviewed and updated regularly and approved by its board. The key risks identified by the Board to the performance of the Group are detailed below. The purpose of the Group's risk management policies and procedures is not to eliminate risks completely, as this is not possible, but to reduce them and to ensure that the Group is adequately prepared to respond and to minimise their impact should they crystallise. Risks affecting the Fund Investment Manager The ability of the Group to achieve its investment objective depends heavily on the managerial experience of the management team within the Investment Manager and more generally on the Investment Manager's ability to attract and retain suitable staff. The growth of the Group depends upon the ability of the Investment Manager to identify, select and execute further investments which offer the potential for satisfactory returns. The Investment Management Agreement includes key man provisions which would require the Investment Manager to employ alternative staff with similar experience relating to investment, ownership, financing and management of wind farm projects should for any reason any key man cease to be employed by the Investment Manager. The Investment Management Agreement ensures that no investments are made following the loss of key men until suitable replacements are found and there are provisions for a reduction in the investment management fee during the loss period. It also outlines the process for their replacement with the Board's approval. The key men also have an equity stake in the Company and are incentivised through the management fee which is linked to NAV. Financing risk The Group will finance further investments either by borrowing or by issuing further shares. The ability of the Group to deliver enhanced returns and consequently realise expected real NAV growth is dependent on access to debt facilities and equity capital markets. There can be no assurance that the Group will be able to borrow or refinance on reasonable terms or that there will be a market for further shares. Investment returns become unattractive A significantly strengthening economy may lead to higher future interest rates which could make the listed infrastructure asset class relatively less attractive to investors. In such circumstances, it is likely that there will be an increase in inflation (to which the revenues and costs of the investee companies are either indexed or significantly correlated) or an increase in power prices (due to greater consumption of power) or both. Both would increase the investment return and thus would provide a degree of mitigation against higher future interest rates. Health and safety and the environment The physical location, operation and maintenance of wind farms may, if inappropriately assessed and managed, pose health and safety risks to those involved. Wind farm operation and maintenance may result in bodily injury or industrial accidents, particularly if an individual were to fall from height, fall or be crushed in transit from a vessel to an offshore installation or be electrocuted. If an accident were to occur in relation to one or more of the Group's investments and if the Group were deemed to be at fault, the Group could be liable for damages or compensation to the extent such loss is not covered under insurance policies. In addition, adverse publicity or reputational damage could ensue. Kevin McCullough has been appointed as Health and Safety Director to the Board and Quadriga Health and Safety Limited have been engaged to ensure the ongoing appropriateness of the Group's health and safety policies. Risks affecting investee companies Regulation A change in Government policy could lead to new renewable energy policies resulting in a change or abandonment of the Renewables Obligation. If these were applied retrospectively to current operating projects including those in the Group's portfolio, this could adversely impact the market price for renewable energy or the value of the green benefits earned from generating renewable energy. At the same time, such a policy change would be likely to halt further investment in new generating capacity, resulting in legally binding renewable energy targets being missed and adding to the already considerable security of supply concerns. The Government has evolved the regulatory framework for new projects being developed but has consistently stood behind the framework that supports operating projects as it understands the need to ensure investors can trust regulation. This principle of "grandfathering" was confirmed in the recently enacted Energy Act 2013. Electricity prices Other things being equal, a decline in the market price of electricity would reduce the portfolio companies' revenues. At present, the Group does not hedge its exposure to power prices; power prices have a natural floor whereas upside is uncapped. The Group's dividend policy has been designed to withstand significant short term variability in power prices. A longer period of power price decline would materially affect the revenues of investee companies. In general, independent forecasters expect European energy wholesale prices to continue to rise in real terms (in the short and long term), feeding into UK power prices, together with the ongoing phasing out of coal-fired power stations and the net reduction in nuclear capacity.
]]></text></news-item>