<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTH-PBN1-J9YR-G0KG"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>The boy who grew up to become a woman of terror; Debbie Vincent, one of Britain's leading animal rights extremists, has been found guilty of conspiracy to blackmail. But who exactly is Miss Vincent? Here we reveal her intriguing, and at times disturbing story</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Patrick Sawer</author><text><![CDATA[When former soldier Paul Rogers married his sweetheart in the fishing port of Falmouth 26 years ago their wedding guests might have hoped they would go on to lead a happy, and probably unremarkable life together.
In a few short years, however, Rogers would undergo a sex-change operation and adopt the name Debbie Vincent.
But in a sinister development, Vincent ended up as an obsessive supporter of animal rights, masterminding a campaign of harassment against pharmaceutical executives, culminating in the desecration of graves, the theft of a mother's ashes and arson.
Last week the 52-year-old was found guilty of conspiracy to commit blackmail following a three week trial at Winchester Crown Court, in what Scotland Yard described as "a significant milestone in a long-running investigation into criminal activity across Europe".
Working with other leading members of the notorious animal rights group Stop Huntingdon Animal Cruelty (Shac), Vincent helped organise a 10-year campaign of threats and intimidation against staff and executives at Huntingdon Life Sciences (HLS), a pharmaceutical research company involved in the development of new medicines, along with its suppliers, which they accused of animal exploitation and cruelty in its tests.
Now, for the first time the story can be told in full of how Vincent went from a loving husband and father who had served his country, to one of Britain's most feared and influential animals rights extremists.
It was certainly a long way from his roots in the Midlands town of Stafford, where Paul Vincent Rogers was born in 1962.
Vincent told the trial that his was a strict, 'Victorian' upbringing, so much so that at the age of 16 he joined the Royal Artillery to escape and, in the midst of the Cold War between East and West, was posted to Germany.
But Gunner Rogers' military career came to an abrupt end two and a half years later when Royal Military Police found women's clothes among his belonging while investigating the theft of his credit cards.
Rogers was exposed as a cross-dresser, in an age when tolerance for that lifestyle was in scarce supply in civilian life, never mind the Armed Forces.
Giving evidence Vincent tearfully told the jury how she had wanted to be a girl from the age of seven and had struggled with conflicted feelings as a teenager and young man.
However, in 1987, seven years after being discharged from the Army - after being offered electric shock treatment - Rogers married Tracy Green, who he had met in Cornwall, where her parents ran a dairy farm. The following year the couple had a son.
But Rogers, by now working as a marine electrician, was apparently unable resolve his conflicted sexual identity and, just two years after his marriage collapsed in 1990, he underwent a gender reassignment operation, becoming a woman and adopting the name Debbie Vincent.
Although his ex-wife agreed to give him some of the proceeds of the sale of the marital home to pay for his operation she remarried and Vincent has not seen their son for more than 20 years.
The marriage at an end, Vincent first became involved in animal welfare issues as a volunteer at a goat rescue centre in Devon. Over the following years she became more and more committed, but it was a protest against live animal exports at Plymouth docks, on a cold January day in 1995, which marked a key moment in her transformation.
As she padlocked herself by the neck to a lorry, eventually forcing it to turn back with its cargo of calves, she must have known she had taken a significant step along the road from legal protest to something far more dangerous.
Her spectacular act of protest at Plymouth docks in 1995 appears to have been her entry ticket to the radical wing of the animal rights movement. Soon after she joined the South West Hunt Saboteurs and was active in disrupting hunts across the region.
In September 1999 Vincent joined a counter-demonstration against a march by members of the Countryside Alliance outside the Labour Party conference, in Bournemouth, screaming "ban the hunt" at passing farmers and hunt supporters.
By 2002 she had turned her attention to the controversial question of the proposed badger cull, advocated by dairy farmers as the only way of stemming the spread of bovine TB across the south west.
A founder member of the Coalition of Badger Action Groups, Vincent had set up a website in 1999 called Badger Killers, which publicised the names and addresses of farmers and rural contractors accused of supporting any planned cull.
Her tactics led to several brushes with the law. In 2004, Vincent was among six protesters convicted by Sevenoaks Magistrates of intimidation against those they accused of being involved with HLS, for whom Shac's activists had developed an obsessive hatred.
Vincent, by that stage living in Nottingham, had been among a group of masked protesters who gathered outside people's homes in Kent. She was given 120 hour community punishment order and ordered to pay £450 costs.
The sentence did not appear to act as much of a deterrent.
When seven of Shac's founding members were imprisoned for Blackmail in late 2008, including Greg Avery, his first wife Heather Nicholson, and his second wife Natasha Avery, Vincent took on the mantle of leading the organisation.
Police intelligence showed that she had worked closely with Greg and Natasha Avery at a secluded cottage called Little Moorcote, near Hook, in Hampshire, using their computer to coordinate the group's illegal activities.
Following their imprisonment Vincent, who was subject to various court injunctions in a bid to curtail her activity, warned in an interview: "There will be more direct, what people call clandestine, action."
She was true to her word.
Alastair Nisbet, the senior crown prosecutor, told the Winchester trial: "Following the conviction of Shac's main leaders in 2008, Debbie Vincent's role within the organisation grew. She became the public face of Shac, but, behind a veil of respectability, she was involved in the criminal side of the organisation."
While Vincent took no part herself in the direct action campaign against HLS, the jury found she was "knowingly involved" with others in pursuing Shac's aims through "threatening and intimidating actions".
The court heard that between November 2001 and August 2011 Vincent conspired with others to blackmail businesses they believed were associated with HLS.
The campaign culminated in the targeting of Dr Daniel Vasella, the chairman of Novartis, a Swiss pharmaceutical company, in May 2009.
The grave of Dr Vasella's mother, in the Swiss village of Chur, was daubed with anti-HLS graffiti, the urn containing her ashes was stolen - it has never been recovered - and two crosses daubed in blood red paint placed in the ground nearby, one with the notional "date of death" of Dr Vasella's wife's Anne-Laurence.
At the same time Dr Vasella's holiday chalet, in the Tyrol region of Austria, was burnt to the ground.
On the back of threats of violence against Novartis employees, and the desecration of the Vasella family grave, Vincent travelled to Germany to meet the company's head of security in an attempt to 'persuade' the firm to cut its links with HLS.
Michael Bowes QC told her trial: "The threat was chillingly basic, companies were told they were on the [Shac] website until you publish your surrender and once we do we will very kindly take you off."
It mattered little that Novartis had not worked with HLS for several years, or that it had cut its use of animal testing by a quarter since 2003.
Vincent was arrested in July 2012, at the same time as her alleged co-conspirators, Natasha Simpkins, a British animal rights activist born in Germany, and Swiss-born Sven van Hasselt, who were detained in Holland and are awaiting extradition to the UK to face similar charges.
Vincent, who has been released on bail, will be sentenced on April 17 and has been warned she faces as much as 14 years behind bars.
Her defence was that neither she, nor Shac, had any idea who had carried out action against Novartis and that nothing they did was illegal or violent.
"The only thing I have ever been involved in is the lawful side. Any sort of illegality that might have happened between anybody was never discussed" she said, before last week's guilty verdict against her.
Such was Vincent's reputation that even now that she faces years behind bars, her victims are too scared to come forward for fear of retaliation by her friends and acolytes.
Novartis welcomed the outcome of the trial, stating: "We fully support the rights of individuals to freely express their opinions on the use of animals in research and engage in lawful protest. However, we will not tolerate harassment, intimidation or wilful destruction of property and condemn any crime committed against our associates and their families. Activism is legitimate, extremism is not."
HLS welcomed the verdict, and said it was "proud" of the role it had played in the development of safe and effective medicines.
One HLS director who, along with the company's managing director Brian Cass, was physically assaulted during Shac's long-running running campaign, expressed his relief at the outcome of the case
"People who suffered at the hands of Shac and their supporters want to put their experiences behind them. It ws a horrible chapter in all our lives that we'd rather not revisit, but frankly, the result of the trial is great," he said.
"It sends a powerful message to those people who still think they can get away with all sort of horrible behaviour without suffering the consequence that they can't, that in the end the law will catch up with them and they will be punished."
]]></text></news-item>