<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTH-W771-JB1X-W3R8"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Gulen breaks his silence, responds to allegations</title><source>Today's Zaman (Turkey)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Having stayed largely silent in the face of relentless attacks amounting to hate speech by beleaguered Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan, who was incriminated in a massive corruption scandal, Fethullah Gulen spoke to Today's Zaman and provided his account of how he sees the recent events in Turkey in his first interview with the Turkish media since Dec. 17.
The Turkish Islamic scholar, who has inspired a worldwide network active in education, charity and outreach programs, described the large-scale slander, pressure and oppression campaign his Hizmet movement is currently facing as worse than that seen during the military coup regimes witnessed by Turkey. He called on his supporters to remain patient and not to despair.
In an extensive interview that was published in Today's Zaman as a five-part series last week, Gulen gave his thoughts on the corruption investigations, the upcoming local elections, whether he would support any political party, the slander leveled against him, the voice recordings that have been leaked onto the Internet, the release of convicts from the Ergenekon trial, the settlement process with the country's Kurds, the rumors of a possible lawsuit against members of the Hizmet movement after the elections, Hizmet's alleged involvement in an effort to take over the Fenerbahce sports club, how he sees Turkey leaving the current crisis behind, his possible return to Turkey and other issues many have been wondering about. Gulen said his deep conviction of Islam will not allow him to turn a blind eye to the allegations of corruption, lamenting the fact that Erdogan's government has failed to take measures to tackle these allegations despite early warnings from state agencies. As for the wiretapping of phone conversations of unsuspecting citizens, Gulen said the authorities should investigate the illegal recordings, adding he had also been victimized as such. He said he was concerned by the government's moves in the last few years to cut back on fundamental rights and freedoms in Turkey, accusing the government of not addressing the demands of Alevis, Kurds and Gezi protesters.
March 15, Saturday
Police chiefs in Giresun, Mugla, Sivas and Van provinces were removed from their posts by the government. The removals come roughly three months after a wide-ranging corruption investigation, which implicated prominent bureaucrats and businessmen close to the ruling party, went public on Dec. 17. More than 8,000 police officers and about 130 prosecutors have been removed from their posts and reassigned since the corruption scandal broke out.
The ruling Justice and Development Party (AK Party) is no longer a negotiating partner in talks between the Turkish government and the Kurdistan Communities Union (KCK), according to a statement released by the KCK, an umbrella organization of the terrorist Kurdistan Workers' Party (PKK). The statement said that the Turkish government failed to take the necessary steps toward democratization and finding a solution to the Kurdish problem.
March 16, Sunday
A car carrying three women and a 5-year-old child fell from a car ferry in Istanbul's Sirkeci district. The child drowned. According to media reports, the car was caught on a ramp attached to the pier and was tipped into the sea. Ece Su Yilmaz, the child who lost her life in the accident, was suffering from leukemia.
Republican People's Party (CHP) leader Kemal Kilicdaroglu said during a public speech that Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan is trying to encourage separatism among Turkish people. He added that the CHP will embrace everyone, regardless of their ethnic identities or religious beliefs.
Nationalist Movement Party (MHP) leader Devlet Bahceli said via Twitter that Prime Minister Erdogan is trying to cover up the Dec. 17 corruption scandal through hate speech.
Ali Kurt, a Turk living in the German city of Cologne, went missing in the Rhine river after saving two Congolese girls ages 6 and 10 from drowning.
March 17, Monday
Turkey's unemployment rate declined by 0.1 percent in December year-on-year, reaching 10 percent, according to data released by the Turkish Statistics Institute (TurkStat).
President Abdullah Gul departed for an official visit to Denmark at the invitation of Denmark's Queen Margrethe II.
Besiktas President Fikret Orman vowed to finish building the club's new stadium "no matter what," amid claims of threats issued by Prime Minister Erdogan to halt construction. In a recent voice recording that was leaked on the Internet over the weekend, it was said that Erdogan was disturbed that Orman had not condemned the club's famous fan group, Carsi, for their role in the anti-government Gezi Park protests.
An Istanbul court accepted an indictment seeking up to 29 years in prison for 26 suspects who participated in protests linked to Gezi Park near Istanbul's famed Taksim Square.
A complaint was filed against Prime Minister Erdogan regarding his comments about Berkin Elvan, a 15-year-old boy who died after nine months in intensive care due to an injury sustained when he was shot in the head by a police tear gas canister during the Gezi Park protests last summer. During a party rally, Erdogan had accused Berkin -- whose funeral was attended by millions -- of being a terrorist and said that another slain youngster, Burak Can Karamanoglu, who was shot dead on the same day, was a "martyr."
March 18, Tuesday
The European Court of Human Rights (ECtHR) announced a ruling on an application filed by PKK leader Abdullah Ocalan, indicating that Turkey partly violated the European Convention on Human Rights (ECHR). It called on the country to create the possibility of conditional release for life sentences, or even abolish them completely. Ocalan, who was sentenced to life imprisonment, is currently jailed on Turkey's Imrali Island.
Whistle blower Twitter user Haramzadeler uploaded new audio recordings on YouTube which reveal that former EU Minister Egemen Bagis -- about whom a number of sound recordings have already been leaked documenting his purported involvement in a bribery network -- allegedly received $500,000 in a shoebox. Bagis was forced to leave his post during a Cabinet reshuffle after a graft probe went public on Dec. 17, 2013, rocking the government. Text accompanying the uploaded recordings claims that the audio was legally acquired through wiretapping and a man in them -- who can be heard having a phone conversation with another man, allegedly Iranian businessman Reza Zarrab -- is Bagis.
March 19, Wednesday
Parliament held an extraordinary session to address the summaries of proceedings on four former Cabinet ministers facing corruption allegations, following a call from the CHP.
Deputies from the ruling AK Party insisted on the secrecy of the investigation file concerning the four former Cabinet ministers, sparking huge criticism from opposition parties, which claim the government is trying to hush-up damning evidence from the corruption investigation. Deputy parliamentary speaker Sadik Yakut eventually decided not to read out loud the documents about graft claims and a parliamentary commission is to be established in order to handle the documents. Deputies currently do not have access to the documents, a result of the AK Party's efforts. The summaries of proceedings target former Economy Minister Zafer Caglayan, former Interior Minister Muammer Guler, former European Union Affairs Minister Bagis and former Environment and Urban Planning Minister Erdogan Bayraktar, who all resigned one week after the Dec. 17 corruption scandal went public. The four ministers were allegedly involved in corruption and bribery.
A former employee of TurkStat allegedly killed six people at the institute's building in Turkey's northeastern province of Kars in the morning, before committing suicide. The incident took place after the former employee was suspended as a result of an inspection. The individual reportedly went to the TurkStat building and took his former colleagues hostages, then killed them before committing suicide. Mehmet Tolon, the director of TurkStat in Kars, was among the victims.
Turkish Airlines (THY) issued a statement denying that the airline carried cargo suspected of being weapons to unknown groups in Nigeria, as had been alleged in a recently leaked audio recording.
Several CHP and MHP deputies protested the THY's decision to deny former AK Party deputy Muhammed Cetin the right to use seats reserved for lawmakers on a THY flight.
President Gul said that current developments in Turkey cannot be linked to external forces and that such claims put Turkey in league with third world countries, in a press conference during his visit to Denmark.
March 20, Thursday
Twitter was blocked late at night in Turkey after Prime Minister Erdogan vowed to "root it out," stirring harsh reactions across the country and around the world and putting the ruling party's reputation in jeopardy ahead of the local elections. Earlier in the day, Erdogan openly stated that he would ban the use of Twitter while speaking at a party rally in Bursa. Earlier this month the prime minister had said his government may shut down Facebook and YouTube, during a live TV broadcast.
Prime Minister Erdogan threatened to "ban a ban" imposed on his party's main campaign video after electoral authorities blocked it for misusing national symbols.
Two gendarmes and a police officer were killed after unidentified individuals fired rounds from a truck at a checkpoint on the Ulukisla-Adana highway in Nigde province.
A train collided with a minibus carrying commuters to work, killing 10 people and injuring four in the Mediterranean port city of Mersin.
A new recording uploaded by Twitter user Haramzadeler onto YouTube revealed that PKK leader Ocalan allegedly had secret surgery on Imrali.
March 21, Friday
Commenting on reports that Turkish Prime Minister Erdogan blocked the use of Twitter, Hélene Flautre, co-chair of the EU-Turkey joint parliamentary; CHP leader Kilicdaroglu; vice-chairman of the Liberal Group in the European Parliament, German MEP Alexander Graf Lambsdorff; EU Enlargement Commissioner Stefan Fule; President of the European Parliament Martin Schulz; leader of the Progressive Alliance of Socialists and Democrats in the European Parliament, Hannes Swoboda; and Turkish President Gul issued statements condemning the ban, regarding it as unacceptable. Meanwhile, Jack Dorsey, one of the founders of the popular social media site, told Turkish users that they could tweet via SMS by sending a message to 2444 on Avea and Vodafone, and to 2555 for those using Turkcell.
PKK leader Ocalan vowed to press ahead with efforts for a peaceful resolution of an insurgency that has killed tens of thousands of people since 1984. In a letter read to thousands celebrating the spring festival of Nevruz in the mainly-Kurdish city of Diyarbakir, Ocalan said, "We were not afraid of [fighting]; we won't be afraid of making peace."
]]></text></news-item>