<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTH-P9Y1-F0NV-F0TJ"><date>2014-03-23</date><title></title><source>The State Journal- Register (Springfield, IL)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Work toward clean energy
Monday marks 25 years since the Exxon Valdez spilled vast amounts of oil into Alaska's pristine Prince William Sound, devastating wildlife and the local economy.
Since then, numerous other dirty energy disasters have occurred, such as the catastrophic BP Deepwater Horizon explosion in April 2010 and most recently the release of toxic coal ash into North Carolina's Dan River in February 2014.
We are not immune from potential disasters in Springfield. For example, Sugar Creek is adjacent to and downstream from City Water, Light and Power's coal ash pond and runs into the Sangamon River.
Moreover, the cumulative impact of fossil fuel pollution is causing an even graver and long-term threat to civilization - climate instability. While no one weather event can be solely attributable to pollution-induced climate change, the combination of a major drought, repeated floods and destructive tornadoes experienced in just central Illinois in the last few years are persuasive evidence that something is amiss.
To address this looming problem, the EPA has begun the process of regulating the unlimited dumping of carbon into the atmosphere by our traditional power plants, which emit 40 percent of CO2 pollution in the United States. Illinois and every other state will be asked to develop a plan to reduce those emissions.
I implore all of our leaders to set aside their personal and political differences and work toward developing a comprehensive and, most importantly, effective plan. By promoting renewable energy sources, energy efficiency and energy conservation, we can hasten the day when we can enjoy a clean energy economy that will provide hundreds of thousands of new jobs without threatening our health and safety.
John Albers
Williamsville
Coaches overpaid, teachers underpaid
As reported in the Feb. 23 sports section, Minnesota football coach Jerry Kill gets a raise and an extension on his contract. He was making $1.2 million, the lowest in the Big Ten Conference. He will make $2.1 million.
In the March 7 sports section, Mizzou coach Gary Pinkel gets an increase from $2.8 million to $3.1 million, plus a $100,000 raise each season. His assistant coaches also receive a $540,000 boost to $3.2 million, and there are bonuses for the number of games won, but those numbers are enough to make me sick.
I like sports and have participated in some, but it seems that education has taken a back seat to sports, both in high school and college. How many of the teachers who are educating our future leaders make this outrageous amount of money? Except for the superintendents, who also are overpaid, our teachers deserve more consideration.
These are examples of only two schools out of hundreds, but no one who is coaching in our schools should be making this kind of money. The total spent in the U.S. schools would be staggering.
Pro sports is another subject - for example, $52 million for a six-year contract. Now I'm really sick.
Paul Rine
Mount Olive
Legalized 'vices' mean higher revenue
I disagree with Julian Reif's March 17 column, " Sin taxes won't save the Illinois budget."
If Illinois would follow some of the other states in capitalizing on a variety of sin taxes, we could draw in billions of dollars annually, as long as we didn't tack on a large cost of administration in legalizing these "sins," as we call them.
Apparently, a large number of residents would patronize "new" sins, such as marijuana, prostitution and drugs. How many decades has our law had to try and stop these? Billions of dollars are spent on them each year. Why not legalize these them as we have cigarettes, alcohol and gambling?
Look at Colorado, for instance. They legalized marijuana and now are taking in millions of dollars a month from their taxation. Why do we always have to be the followers? Why not be the leader for a change? We can't stop these drugs or we would have done it by now. We could save millions each year by not having to house prisoners convicted of drug trafficking.
We need more positive thinking by our polititions and bring in new, more liberal laws, along with younger lawmakers. Laws need to fit into the 21st century. We need to have the people's vote on these laws.
I personally am on Social Security and can't afford any of these vices anyway, but I would vote for change, mostly because what we have now just isn't working.
Ervin W. Stone
Beardstown
Republican candidates taking the wrong approach
For those of us who voted in the Republican primary, the period before the primary election was excruciating. The telephone calls were constant, seeking our vote for one candidate or another.
The vast majority were "robo-calls" from computers with prerecorded messages. These computers were sly, with originating numbers disguised so that your caller ID could not tell if it was coming from a campaign.
Since this evasive tactic shows that these campaigns know we really don't want these calls, why do they make them in the first place? Am I really more likely to vote for the candidate who is irritating me the most?
I don't mind it if an actual person takes the time to telephone me, but why should I waste my time listening to prerecorded messages?
In Republican primaries, the candidates also have increasingly adopted the position that we will vote for the person with the most extreme "tea party" views. Apparently, they believe we all think President Barack Obama is not just incorrect, but inherently evil and unAmerican. I guess we also are against all compromise with Democrats on any issue.
This is an unwise tactic, particularly in Illinois, where Republican politicians historically have been moderate and reasonable. I believe that for decades the Republican Party has offered the best state and local candidates.
My message to Republican candidates: please stop making campaign robo-calls and quit assuming we are all disciples of Ted Cruz and Ted Nugent. We aren't.
Edward Green
Springfield
]]></text></news-item>