<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTH-PD51-JBF5-T4W8"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Land Council claims mine is 'invalid'</title><source>ABC Regional News (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[More questions are being raised about the validity of a massive coal mine planned for the New South Wales Central Coast.
The biggest private landowner in the region, the Darkinjung Aboriginal Land Council, says plans for the Wallarah Two underground mine near Wyong are invalid, and it wants the development application withdrawn.
The Land Council's chief executive Sean Gordon says the mine's rail spur is over Darkinjung-owned land, and all access to it has been formally refused.
"I think it is quite risky for Minister Hazzard to be continuing with this project knowing that it is operating without any jurisdiction over our land," he said.
In a statement, the Planning Minister Brad Hazzard has referred to the matter as a 'commercial dispute' between the two parties.
The Planning Department defends the proponent, saying that since the proposal is considered a "public notification development", any consent to access the land is not required.
Mr Gordon says the development will be challenged in court.
"This company is 82 per cent owned by the Korean Government," he said.
"So you know, it's a real tester that a small aboriginal community of an Aboriginal Land Council are really taking on the Korean Government around protecting our rights and our interests."
This latest threat of legal action comes amid ongoing questions about the legitimacy of the proposal.
In February, the Planning Department backed the project, despite the Premier opposing it when in Opposition due to its potential impact on subsidence as well as the region's water supply.
At the time, the Opposition leader John Robertson said the Premier had broken a very clear election promise.
There are now calls to suspend approval of the development until the corruption watchdog completes its investigation into three local Liberal MPs, including former Resources Minister Chris Hartcher.
Fresh material for that inquiry has recently been referred to the ICAC by mine opponents, the Australian Coal Alliance.
Spokesman Allan Hayes says the information relates to Wallarah and the Liberal Government's changed stance on the issue.
The hearing is due to start late April.
The state's Planning Assessment Commission will hold a public hearing on the Wallarah mine project in early April before it makes a final determination.
]]></text></news-item>