<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTH-J6F1-JCF0-K53W"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Oil Spill in Texas</title><source>CTV Television, Inc.</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[SANDIE RINALDO: Another natural disaster is unfolding in Texas tonight. Crews are scrambling to clean up a massive oil spill after a barge loaded with oil collided with a cargo ship in Galveston Bay. The slick of heavy crude is now blocking a busy shipping lane and threatening wildlife refuge. CTV's Joy Malbon has more on the potential damage to the economy and the environment.
JOY MALBON (Reporter): You can see the oil slick from the air, clean-up crews scrambling to keep it from spreading laying thousands of kilometres of boom to protect the shoreline that's home to bird sanctuaries and migrating wildlife.
BRUCE CLAWSON (Texas City Emergency Management): There's a reasonable amount of oil in the water. I can't tell you if there's a substantial amount of oil in the water. That's certainly being, that's being assessed at this point.
MALBON: The barge was carrying six tanks of marine fuel, thick heavy crude, much of it being hauled away from the battered and partially submerged vessel, but not before one of the tanks carrying 636 litres of fuel was damaged, oozing oil into Galveston Bay after it collided with a ship on Saturday.
ADAM GUTIERREZ (Witness): Oh, my god.
MALBON: Adam Gutierrez shot this video as it happened.
GUTIERREZ: We saw that tanker come out of nowhere. I knew they couldn't change direction at that point. It was too close.
MALBON: Dozens of vessels, including three cruise ships blocked from using the shipping channel. Authorities don't want them tracking oil into open water, leaving many passengers stranded.
UNIDENTIFIED MAN: They told us we're delayed until probably tomorrow. We've got to get rooms now.
MALBON: And fishermen like Jeff Roberts told whatever he reels in, best not to eat it.
GEOFF ROBERTS (Fisherman): The first oil was going up the ship channel. And then a couple hours later now, it's coming around the backside of the dike.
MALBON: All this a little too close for comfort in the Gulf region, still recovering from the BP oil spill four years ago. Eleven workers died in a rig explosion while nearly five million barrels of oil continued to gush into the Gulf for months, polluting water, wildlife and crippling the economy. This spill is now contained, but what's not clear is just how much oil is in the water. The US Coast Guard calls it a significant spill. Now there's a massive effort underway to clean it all up. Sandie?
RINALDO: CTV's Joy Malbon. Thank you, Joy.
]]></text></news-item>