<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTH-PBN1-J9YR-G153"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Exxon Valdez - 25 years after the Alaska oil spill, the court battle continues; Exxon Valdez, a massive oil tanker, foundered on rocks as it sailed out of port in one of the worst environmental disasters in history - affecting one of the most beautiful, wildlife-rich spots in the world. 25 years on, Joanna Walters has spoken to the coastguard, campaigners and residents about their memories of March 24, 1989</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Joanna Walters New York</author><text><![CDATA[Mark Delozier remembers the crisp, clear night as if it was yesterday. He was a coastguard officer in Alaska when he got a call, just after midnight.
"You need to come in. The Exxon Valdez is aground on Bligh Reef and leaking oil," the message said.
It was March 24 1989, a quarter of a century ago on Monday. The massive oil tanker had foundered on rocks as it sailed out of port, and was about to unleash one of the worst environmental disasters in history upon one of the most beautiful, wildlife-rich spots in the world.
As Mr Delozier steered his small boat towards the stricken vessel, the stink of oil fumes filled the air and gurgling gobs of crude bubbled up and leapt four feet out of the sea.
"I thought that with a spark from our engine we could explode, then it occurred to me that the Exxon Valdez herself might blow," he told The Telegraph.
He kept going, however, boarded the tanker safely and encountered its captain, Joseph Hazelwood, in the wheelhouse.
"I could smell alcohol. Spirits. It was in his breath, coming into my face, very strong," said Mr Delozier, who later testified about it in court.
Minutes earlier Capt Hazelwood had put an unqualified junior officer at the wheel and left the bridge. The ship, steering wide to avoid ice, failed to turn back into the shipping lane in time - and slammed into the reef.
The Exxon Valdez's hull ripped open, hours after leaving its namesake port of Valdez in south-east Alaska, and more than 11 million gallons of black crude gushed into the pristine waters of Prince William Sound.
Oil reached beaches 650 miles away. Killer whales, eagles, otters, seals and thousands of sea birds died excruciating deaths while Alaska's famous salmon and herring were ruined. The pictures of distressed animals expiring and grief-stricken locals trying to scrub beaches coated with toxic filth shocked the world.
The event is still seared into the minds of those who witnessed it, even a quarter of a century later. But the Exxon Valdez has left more than memories.
On the anniversary, state senator Berta Gardner is pushing for Alaskan politicians to demand that the US government forces ExxonMobil Corporation to pay up a final $92 million (£57 million), in what has become the longest-running environmental court case in history. The money would primarily be spent on addressing the crippled herring numbers and the oiled beaches.
"There's still damage from the spill. The oil on the beaches is toxic and hurting wildlife. We can't just say we've done what we can and it's all over - especially with drilling anticipated offshore in the Arctic Ocean - this is significant for Alaska and people around the world," she told The Telegraph.
Richard Keil, a senior media relations adviser at ExxonMobil, said: "The overwhelming consensus of peer-reviewed scientific papers is that Prince William Sound has recovered and the ecosystem is healthy and thriving."
But federal scientists estimate that between 16,000 and 21,000 gallons of oil from the spill lingers on beaches in Prince William Sound and up to 450 miles away, some of it no more biodegraded than it was at the time of the disaster.
It's not immediately obvious. Tourists on boat trips from Valdez see breathtaking beauty. Furry sea otters floating in the bay distract from the sight of the oil tanks on shore, holding crude that has travelled 800 miles through the Trans-Alaska Pipeline from the frozen Arctic, ready to be pumped on to ships in port.
Then awed visitors sail on through clear blue waters, alongside snow-capped mountains and pine-wooded cliffs where eagles perch, safely past Bligh Reef, named after the famous future captain of the ship Bounty when he accompanied the British explorer, Captain James Cook, to Alaska in the 18th Century.
Seals bark, killer whales, porpoises and, in summer, humpback whales arc, puffins flit and icebergs sheer off glaciers with a spectacular crack.
But if you poke around on many beaches, Exxon Valdez oil remains .
Gail Irvine is a scientist with the US Geological Survey, based in Anchorage, Alaska, who analyses oil along the coastline up to 450 miles west of Valdez, including national parks and wildlife preserves. The beaches were ostensibly cleaned up, but oil loiters stubbornly among rocks and between tide marks.
"The oil mixes with seawater and forms an emulsion. It's like mayonnaise," she said. "Left out, the surface crusts over but the inside still has the consistency of mayonnaise - or mousse."
Residual oil in Prince William Sound itself is more liquid and quickly fills a hole dug in the beach. Researchers were amazed when tests showed the oil has barely broken down.
Mussels on the rocks contain traces of Exxon Valdez oil. Before the spill they were gathered for subsistence by local Inuit villagers. They are still eaten by oyster catchers, brightly-coloured harlequin ducks and sea otters, with the latter also digging for clams.
Rick Steiner, a University of Alaska marine adviser during the spill, said: "It's disgraceful. We didn't know it would still be toxic now and no one wants to admit it. Of 32 animal types, habitats and natural resources monitored, only 13 have recuperated fully. The ecosystem will never entirely recover."
A National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) report this year predicted that the residual oil would linger for decades - or even centuries.
The Exxon Valdez Oil Spill Trustee Council, a public body formed after the spill, will ultimately decide between leaving the oil alone or expensive removal.
Jeff Short, a former NOAA oil pollution researcher, said: "They should just post signs on beaches to warn people of the presence of Exxon Valdez oil - all that would cost would be red faces in the Alaska government and at Exxon."
In 1991, Exxon, now ExxonMobil, paid $1 billion damages to Alaska and the federal government. It also agreed to pay another $100 million later in the event of unforeseen "injury".
Despite a request from President George W Bush in 2006 for a total of $92 million for further research and recovery efforts, ExxonMobil refused and has argued in court ever since that Alaska has fully recovered.
As for Capt Hazelwood, he was fired and stood trial but was acquitted of most charges, including being under the influence. He was convicted of illegally discharging oil and given a $50,000 fine and community service that did not include cleaning up any of the oil.
After the spill, new laws required tankers in the region to be double-hulled, to reduce the risk of similar spills, all oil vessels to be escorted past Bligh Reef by tugboat, and alcohol tests.
Mr Hazelwood, 67, now lives with his wife on Long Island, near New York, in a comfortable, detached house painted primrose yellow, in the prosperous seaside town of Huntington.
He declined to comment when approached by The Telegraph. But when interviewed for a book in 2009 he offered "a heartfelt apology to the people of Alaska".
Mr Delozier, the coastguard, still cringes at how easily the disaster could have been avoided in a shipping channel more than six miles wide. He remains angry but, astonishingly, not with the captain.
"I forgive Hazelwood, as a human. We've all done things we regret. When I met him in the wheelhouse that night I knew he felt the pain of causing the disaster and it will haunt him for the rest of his life," he said.
"But I don't forgive Exxon."
]]></text></news-item>