<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-SPF1-DY0P-G4G6"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Groups Question California Plan For Oil Refinery GHG Credits Under LCFS</title><source>Carbon Control News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Oil industry officials and environmentalists are questioning California's plan to offer greenhouse gas (GHG)-reduction credits for refinery process changes as part of the state's low-carbon fuel standard (LCFS), with industry saying the plan shows the flaws in the LCFS while advocates fear refineries will be able to earn invalid credits.
The California Air Resources Board (CARB) is proposing a host of regulatory changes to the LCFS, in part to comply with an appellate court ruling last year as well as to improve the program's effectiveness, which are scheduled to be adopted in October. The LCFS -- seen as model for other states and regions -- is a key part of the state's strategy to reduce GHGs to 1990 levels by the end of 2020, as well as to meet a planned 2030 GHG-reduction target.
As part of the proposed revisions, CARB staff is floating a new amendment that would reward oil refineries LCFS credits for investing in projects that reduce GHGs, toxics and criteria pollution at the facilities.
"Refineries would submit a project plan to [CARB] for approval and staff would determine the difference between the refinery's baseline carbon intensity of their transportation fuel and the new carbon intensity of their transportation fuels with the project in place," according to a CARB concept paper. "The difference will be used to calculate credits for the refinery. These credits would be eligible for sale to other regulated parties."
Mike Waugh, CARB's lead staffer on the LCFS amendments, said during a March 11 workshop that board officials would evaluate the potential GHG reduction credits under the refinery concept on a "project-by-project basis."
But the plan is prompting questions from environmentalists due to concerns about invalid credits, and from oil company officials show say it is another effort by regulators to apply a fix to an infeasible program with no connection to the primary purpose of the LCFS -- increasing the use of cleaner alternative fuels. Industry officials are also reiterating longstanding calls for the air board to shelve or overhaul the program, arguing that it is broken.
David Stern, representing ExxonMobil Refining & Supply, at the workshop questioned whether the proposal would result in "double-counting" of GHG emission reductions because refineries are already subject to the state's GHG cap-and-trade program. Further, Stern questioned whether CARB has the resources and "accounting ability" to take on what could be a labor-intensive program to evaluate and verify such refinery projects under the LCFS.
Waugh responded that CARB officials "see this as an opportunity for an oil refinery to submit to us evidence that their GHG emissions have been reduced and therefore should receive some credit under the LCFS," and that CARB could shift more divisional staff to administer the program.
In addition, CARB staff does not believe the program would allow double counting of GHG reductions in part because the cuts will bring down the overall emissions inventory in the state and reduce a refinery's obligations under cap-and-trade -- something that benefits both the cap-and-trade and the LCFS programs, he said.
Simon Mui, representing the Natural Resources Defense Council, questioned whether CARB's plan can ensure that the GHG and other pollutant emission reductions at refineries under the credit proposal are truly "additional" as defined under the state's regulations, and that such projects would not allow "backsliding" in emissions from other parts of refineries. He said that in some instances refineries are facing the potential for backsliding in terms of GHG emissions mainly because they are using more energy to process heavier, high-sulfur crude oil.
Will Barrett, representing the American Lung Association in California, echoed Mui's concerns about backsliding, adding that any changes to the program should enhance market signals for the development of cleaner fuels going forward and ensure that California's LCFS remains a model for other jurisdictions.
Industry's Criticisms
Oil industry representatives argue more broadly that the refinery-credit proposal, as well as two options CARB staff is considering to provide "cost containment" under the LCFS by offering alternative compliance avenues for companies, expose the severe flaws of the program. At the workshop, they raised concerns -- as they have many times over the past three years -- that CARB must either shelve or totally overhaul the program, simply because there will not be an adequate supply of low-carbon fuels to meet the regulation in the coming years.
Stern said at the meeting that the proposed amendments by CARB, including a plan to relax compliance requirements in the 2015-19 time frame, change the original intent of the LCFS as a free market system to accelerate the production of low-carbon fuels. "All these options divert from the intended purpose of the LCFS, which is to try to encourage investment in and development of low-carbon-intensity fuels," he said.
Waugh responded, however, that he believes the proposed amendments will continue to drive investments in low-carbon fuel production.
Gina Grey, representing the Western States Petroleum Association, said the organization is "very concerned about the feasibility of the program and any possible consequences of staying the course as it is now." She said that the development of commercial-scale, ultra-low-carbon-intensity fuels, such as cellulosic ethanol, has been much slower than envisioned by state officials. "Our conclusion is that program revisions are needed to ensure the public's needs will be met in the transportation fuels market."
CARB's cost containment proposals are unacceptable substitutes for a feasible standard, added Bob Nelson, representing Shell Oil Co., who said board officials must make adjustments to the entire program to make it feasible. He said one of the options fails to provide certainty that there are enough credits available to supply gas and diesel to the California market. The proposal essentially grants "a second or third mortgage for a system headed for default . . . instead of addressing the real problem."
Under the proposal, CARB offers two options. The first is a "credit clearance," where regulated parties could carry deficits after purchasing their proportional share of credits. Companies holding excess credits could "pledge" credits they would like to sell to those parties that need to purchase additional credits at or below a pre-determined price, according to the proposal. Remaining deficits would add to a cumulative compliance obligation and incur interest to be repaid later, according to the CARB proposal.
The second cost containment option is a "credit window," where regulated parties can purchase and retire "compliance-only credits," according to CARB. Under this process, CARB would offer credits for sale at a pre-determined price. Regulated parties would purchase credits needed for that year's compliance. Funds collected from the sale of the compliance credits would be distributed to low-carbon intensity fuel producers to further incentivize production, according to CARB.
Ralph Moran, representing BP, said at the workshop that "we don't think the proper response if policymakers design an overly ambitious, infeasible regulation is to ask regulated parties to pay them money; it's not something we'd ever be comfortable with." He said this tack sends a "perverse message that the more infeasible the regulation, the more money is raised."
]]></text></news-item>