<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-HH81-DYJJ-P3V8"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Dumped fracking earns probation</title><source>The Cincinnati Enquirer (Ohio)</source><author>By, James F. McCarty</author><text><![CDATA[CLEVELAND - A former employee of a Youngstown oil- and gas-drilling company was sentenced this week to three years probation for dumping tens of thousands of gallons of fracking waste into a tributary of the Mahoning River.
Michael Guesman pleaded guilty in August to a federal charge of unpermitted discharge of pollutants under the federal Clean Water Act. In addition to the probation time, Guesman must perform 300 hours of community service work, and testify - if necessary - against his former boss at Hardrock Excavating, Benedict Lupo.
Guesman, 34, of Cortland, appeared in U.S. District Court where he apologized for his crimes to Judge Donald Nugent and explained he was only following orders from Lupo for fear he would lose his job if he failed to comply.
Guesman eventually lost his job after Hardrock Excavating went out of business and Lupo fired most of his employees, Assistant U.S. Attorney Brad Beeson said.
Lupo, 62, of Poland, is scheduled to appear at a hearing on Monday before Nugent, at which time he is expected to plead guilty to charges of violating the Clean Water Act.
Guesman said he acted on Lupo's orders when he ran a hose from the 20,000-gallon storage tanks to a nearby stormwater drain and opened the release valve, sending gushers of waste liquid into the Mahoning River.
The wastewater was a byproduct of Lupo's hydraulic fracturing - commonly known as "fracking" - consisting of saltwater brine and a slurry of toxic oil-based drilling mud, containing benzene, toluene and other hazardous pollutants.
Guesman admitted dumping into the drain on at least 24 occasions Nov. 1, 2012-Jan. 31, 2013. He always did the dumping under cover of darkness and after other employees had left, Beeson said.
Guesman said Lupo ordered him to lie if questioned about the dumping and to tell law enforcement officers he had emptied the waste tanks only six times.
The black fracking waste left a smelly, oily sheen on the Mahoning, located less than a mile away from the Hardrock facility and its 58 storage tanks, investigators said.
Ohio allows for disposing of fracking waste in state-permitted injection wells.
]]></text></news-item>