<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-J4N1-DYR8-30V0"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Kenya; Financial Crimes in Kenya Are On the Rise - Bichanga</title><source>Africa News</source><author>The Star (Nairobi)</author><text><![CDATA[With the increasing cases of fraud and other money-related crimes, there has been a need for a forensic investigations. Sosthenes Bichanga, is the CEO of OSullivan Associates International Co Ltd, founder member of International Institute of Certified Forensic Investigations Professionals Inc USA and the representative of the Forensic CPA Society of USA in Africa. He spoke to Star Reporter Nduta Waweru on the importance of forensic accounting.
Tell us what Forensic Accounting is all about.
Forensic accounting is one of the emerging branches of traditional accounting. The other branches are forensic audit and investigations. It is defined as the application of accounting principles to court issues. Forensic accountants or investigators present figures and other reports in the language of the court in support of litigation of financial crimes.
What does a forensic accountant look at specifically?
The forensic accountant looks at the figures and documents with a view to extract evidence that may support or dismiss an allegation of financial wrong doing. He or she also looks beyond numbers to gather qualitative information with evidential value. This is what makes a difference between a conventional accountant and a forensic accountant.
What kind of trainings do you carry out, and how many companies have you trained?
I organise short courses like workshops and conferences like the one that is coming up in April, 2014 and also long-term professional accreditation courses that lead to certified forensic investigation professionals. We have trained individuals not companies. The short courses are targeted refreshing and training working professional on investigative skills. The trainings delivered by the IICFIP experts are of world class standards.
I hope that the awareness we are creating about the significance of having staff who are well forensically trained will cause corporates to start having such training in their programs. Corporates always cite lack of budget for this kind of training but they sometimes find that the amounts they lose to fraud is usually higher than what they could have budgeted for training and strengthening of their internal controls and security systems.
What is the status on financial crimes in Kenya?
I have not done research on this but going by what reaches the media and becomes public knowledge, financial crimes in Kenya are on the rise. Financial crimes include wasteful application of resources by those in positions of power and also crimes like conning MPESA users.
Are there any regulations and rules guiding forensic accounting?
No. The International Institute of Certified Forensic Investigation Professionals Inc (IICFIP) is currently working on guidelines and standards that shall be followed by its members globally in all cases involving forensic investigation or audit. Hitherto forensic accounting/audit/investigation has always been done by those trained in accounting not investigation skills. The IICFIP has come to train all professionals interested in forensic investigation and audit to become Certified Forensic Investigation Professionals ( CFIPs) globally. CFIPs are professionals who use a mix of accounting skills, criminal investigations skills, auditing skills, fraud examination skills, investigation law, forensic accounting skills, and digital forensics in carrying out their assignments of financial crimes (white collar crimes) investigation.
Do you think there are enough policies that deal with cases of fraud and money laundering?
Yes, but I am not sure whether they are pro-actively applied. Organisations and government should continuously appraise whatever policies that are there with a view to amending them to pro-actively work to not only prevent but also detect the vices.
What is the impact of technology on what you do?
The impact of technology is huge. It is both a challenge and also a blessing in terms of providing intensive and extensive investigation tools since forensic investigators are not followers of the sampling methods of traditional accountants. A CFIP is expected to analyse almost every transaction in areas affected by financial irregularities in order to extra evidence. This can be possible only when using a very versatile investigative software in a large organisation with millions of transactions.
In your opinion, what is the future of forensic Accounting?
Very bright. Not just forensic accounting but professional forensic investigation.
Why is it important for firms to have forensic accountants?
CFIPs employed internally can not only act as internal intelligence agents to assist the organisation in discovering improprieties early before much loss is incurred but also thoroughly investigation all allegations, within the ambit of the law, to come up with findings that can be used in disciplinary or court proceedings. Vices like tribalism and nepotism are nice foundations for financial wrong doing in organisations. Where there is both of these vices, it is easy to collude and override controls and security systems. Organisations where you find that all heads of departments come from the same tribe or race or community and are deputised by the clan-mates are most likely to collapse due fraud and other malpractice since the wrong doers are in most cases protected. The CFIPs are trained to note this and report it to the top management/owners/shareholders.
Any advice to anyone who wants to be a forensic accountant?
Any individual interested in forensic investigation should undertake undergraduate degree in accounting, criminology, law, security or auditing and then join professionals institutes like the IICFIP to undertake professional training to become certified forensic investigation professionals.
What does your company do?
OSullivan Associates International Co Ltd is a firm that coordinates the services of various professionals and partners offering professional services in various fields that includes but not limited to Tax Consulting, investment consulting, financial and digital forensic investigations and other business advisory services.
History of Forensic Accounting By Nduta Waweru
While forensic accounting has become famous in the recent years, it has been around since the 1900s, but focused mainly on tax evasion in businesses that hid money in different states. Some of the most famous cases relating to forensic accounting include Al Capone's arrest in 1931. Capone was involved in illegal activities but the FBI was unable to convict him, but the forensic accountants were able to track the income he made from illegal activities, thus facilitating his arrest and conviction.
Families of OJ Simpson victims filed a civil suit to get financial compensation but Simpson claimed that he did not have any money. However, forensic accountants discovered that he had stashed away millions, and the families received $33 million settlement.
It was in 2001 that saw a case that forced a lot of companies to undergo audit, after the Enron scandal. Forensic accountants discovered that Enron, a company that was considered highly profitable, was hiding losses and debts in their financial records. Very few companies used to investigate and prosecute fraud cases successfully for the recovery of fraud loss. To make matters worse fraud involves concealment and destruction of evidential trail and that makes it an uphill task for the forensic accountants to exactly quantify the actual loss.This case saw a lot of firms, both private and public, use forensic accountants to detect fraud at early stages thus preventing serious financial losses.
Forensic accounting is not limited to detecting fraud; it has also been used in divorce proceedings. For example in the case of Paul McCartney and Heather Mills, where Mills claimed that McCartney had more money that he claimed. She hired the services of forensic accountants, who did not find any discrepancies in McCartney accounts.
]]></text></news-item>