<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-RN01-JD34-V2KS"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>ANZ set to sell Cambodian bank stake after scandal</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>James Eyers</author><text><![CDATA[ANZ Banking Group is looking to offload its majority holding in the Cambodian bank that was earlier this year embroiled in a scandal involving the financing of a Cambodian sugar plantation that employed child labour.
At a media briefing in Hong Kong on Monday, ANZ chief executive Mike Smith said the bank was looking to sell out of ANZ Royal, in which it holds a 55 per cent stake. The other 45 per cent of ANZ Royal is held by Cambodian company Royal Group.
Pointing to ANZ's 2012 sale of a stake in Vietnam's Sacombank, Mr Smith said: "We would like to do the same in Cambodia. I would much rather have a wholly owned business in these places."
After the child labour claims were revealed in January, corporate governance experts said the incident underlined difficulties for banks maintaining corporate governance standards when expanding overseas.
Mr Smith has said previously that some partial stakes in Asian banks could be problematic because ANZ received only a proportion of profits but had 100 per cent of its reputation invested in the holdings.
ANZ is also looking to scale up in other parts of the region. The bank's new head of Asia, Andrew Géczy, said on Monday the bank was looking to "strengthen its footprint" in Thailand and Myanmar and was awaiting a decision by regulators on whether it would win a banking licence in each country.
ANZ currently has representative offices in Thailand and Myanmar.
At the briefing, which followed the launch of a comprehensive new report on the future of the Asian financial system, Mr Smith reiterated comments made in January that ANZ would buy more of, or sell down, its 39 per cent holding inPanin Bank Indonesia.
He also suggested that valuations of banks in Hong Kong looked more attractive, as the market was not ascribing the potential for growth in yuan deposits held by Hong Kong banks as China's financial liberalisation gathered pace. ANZ considered a tilt at Hong Kong's Wing Hang bank last year but it is believed to have been put off by the elevated asking price.
Mr Smith said when looking at potential acquisitions in Hong Kong, the importance of the market "is not the domestic Hong Kong operations, it is what [a deal] potentially gives you in China. And I still feel banks in Hong Kong are generally valued on history - that is, the value of their Hong Kong dollar deposit base - rather than what they might provide by way of RMB deposits in the future."
Mr Smith said that when the bank was examining Asian deals, it always asked the question: does an acquisition create value for shareholders?
"That is what we have to work through. But we continue to look for opportunities," he said.
On the markets, Mr Smith said the United States Federal Reserve's withdrawal of stimulus would affect Africa and Latin America more harshly than markets in Asia, pointing to fiscal adjustments already made by Indonesia and India and Japan, which "is still pumping out a fair amount of liquidity and that has mitigated the withdrawal of capital going back to the US".
]]></text></news-item>