<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-SPF1-DY0P-G4FS"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>High Court Urged To Reject Appeal Of Landmark MTBE Liability Decision</title><source>Carbon Control News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[New York City is urging the Supreme Court to reject Exxon Mobil's push to reverse a landmark appellate ruling finding it liable $104 million in damages for contaminating groundwater with the fuel additive methyl tertiary butyl ether (MTBE), fighting Exxon's claim that the ruling is flawed because the Clean Air Act effectively mandated MTBE's use.
In a March 17 filing in opposition to the high court granting the company's pending petition for a writ of certiorari to hear the case, the city says Exxon's arguments that the air law preempts the claims are baseless. Lower courts have correctly found the company liable for spilling MTBE that contaminated groundwater in Queens, NY, and for failure to warn those to which it sold the additive its likelihood it could contaminate water, according to the city.
Exxon has argued that the government "made a judgment" that there would be air quality benefits to using MTBE, despite EPA's recognition at the time that use of the chemical could contribute to an increase in water contamination, Exxon says. Allowing the U.S. Court of Appeals for the 2nd Circuit's July ruling that awarded the damages to stand would hinder EPA's ability to make such policy calls in the future, Exxon warns.
However, New York City says in its opposition motion that the federal preemption claims offered by Exxon are "entirely insubstantial," as it notes that although the Clean Air Act Amendments of 1990 did set gasoline oxygenate requirements to improve air quality, it did not require the use of MTBE specifically.
The city instead says Exxon chose to use MTBE as the oxygenate for complying because it was "cheaper by a few cents a gallon" than adding ethanol. Further, the city says Exxon's scientists knew about the risks of MTBE and its propensity to cause costly groundwater contamination but that the company did not take steps to mitigate those risks at its own stations or to warn others to which it sold gasoline containing the chemical.
As such, the city says that the federal air act requirements cannot preempt the state damages, particularly because the jury that heard the case awarded damages for negligence in the handling of MTBE gasoline at its own service stations and failure to warn service stations about the chemical's risk, none of which New York says were caused by Exxon's decision to use MTBE to comply with federal law.
"[T]he jury did not find Exxon liable for 'using' MTBE," the city writes. "Rather, it found Exxon liable for additionaltortious conduct, including its own negligent handling of MTBE and its failure to warn of MTBE's dangers Ñ conduct for which Exxon does not even argue that federal law preempted state tort liability."
Exxon has faulted the city's suit as not being "ripe," as it says it is illegally being asked to pay for the future costs of removing MTBE from drinking water, even though the city has yet to build a pumping station at the Queens site. Exxon said it was being required to pay for damages that might never occur, creating a dangerous precedent.
'Unholy Alliance'
The free-market Washington Legal Foundation, in a Feb. 14 amicus brief, warned the ruling would create an "unholy alliance" between contingent-fee attorneys and large municipalities who would have incentives to try to recover "huge sums" for future damages that might never occur. It said the temptation for municipalities to "roll the dice" in hopes of obtaining awards for future damages would be "difficult for many elected officials to resist."
A coalition of trade groups that include the Chamber of Commerce also has urged the Supreme Court to take up the appeal, saying the 2nd Circuit impermissibly gave the city standing to sue on a "speculative chain of possibilities" and would "open the floodgates" to similar litigation against companies for "similar non-injurious conduct."
But New York rejects the arguments, saying in its filing that Exxon is attempting to take principles established by Article III of the Constitution on standing and "apply them to run-of-the-mill state-law claims for future damagesbased on tortious conduct that has already occurred. No prior ruling of this Court has even hinted at the calculation of state-law tort damages in federal court should be constitutionalized in this manner."
The city says the 2nd Circuit in its decision to reject Exxon's appeal last July "easily" found the city's claims were ripe and based on present injury, because the site on which the company had plans to build a drinking well had already been contaminated by MTBE. It adds that based on the "well established principles of tort law" that after having discovered the damages, it was allowed to recover past, present and future damages caused by Exxon.
To boost its claims that it needed to recover future damages, the city notes that under New York toxic tort law, it must bring a lawsuit within three years of discovering it had been injured by contamination, meaning that if it had waited to bring its lawsuit, "its claims would have been untimely under New York law."
The city says Exxon has failed to cite "any other precedent" of the Supreme Court that would support its claims that it could apply a ripeness test as a bar to future damages, "or even any precedent addressing ripeness in the context of a tort suit," adding that Exxon is attempting "to create a completely new doctrine that limits future damages available under state law in federal courts where Article III constraints apply." Ñ Chris Knight(cknight@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>