<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-SPF1-DY0P-G4K6"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Industry Wins Key Standing Ruling In NEPA Suit But Now Faces Merits Test</title><source>Water Policy Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Mining and other industry groups have won a novel ruling granting them standing to challenge a National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA) analysis that would bar their access to uranium mining on public lands near the Grand Canyon, one of the few times industry groups have won such a right in a NEPA case.
But the procedural decision only allowed the plaintiffs to overcome the Justice Department's (DOJ) procedural challenge to their suit and they must now overcome a higher legal bar to demonstrate their rights -- and potential injury -- on the merits, a test that DOJ is now asking the court to address.
Despite the new test facing the mining and other industry groups in this case, industry lawyers are nevertheless touting the ruling. This is "a small bright spot" for industry's attempt to assert that they have standing in NEPA cases, Susan Mathiascheck, who represents the industry groups in the case, said in a March 4 webinar,"Litigation Forecast 2014: Environmental Regulation and Litigation Risks," hosted by Crowell & Moring.
The issue is especially significant given the growing number of cases brought by environmentalists that pressure federal agencies to strengthen NEPA analyses as a means of blocking extraction and other projects, the law firm says.
As a result, Mathiascheck says, the court's preliminary ruling will help industry groups both when they seek to demonstrate standing to challenge NEPA decisions in their own right but also to give them leverage to push back against environmentalists as intervenors or defendants in NEPA suits.
NEPA is a procedural statute that requires federal agencies undertaking major actions that could impact the environment to review those actions in an environmental impact statement, and consider alternatives that would lessen the impact. Industry has had a difficult time bringing challenges to such reviews, since industry usually wants to take action that will have environmental harms and the statute is designed to protect the environment.
But in a ruling early last year in Gregory Yount v. S.M.R. Jewell, et al, a federal district court judge in Arizona rejected DOJ arguments that the mining and energy industry groups lacked standing to bring its claims because the alleged harm is "economic and thus falls outside the 'zone of interests' that NEPA, an environmental statute, protects." The ruling is available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID: 2464030)
Instead, Judge David Campbell, in his Jan. 13, 2013 order, agreed with the Nuclear Energy Institute (NEI), the National Mining Association (NMA) "have plausible alleged injury to an environmental interest that is sufficiently intertwined with the economic interests to bring them within NEPA zones of interests. Accordingly, the Court finds that these plaintiffs have prudential standing to assert their NEPA claims.
Campbell's ruling was based on legal arguments centering around DOJ's motion to dismiss, but DOJ Feb. 20 filed a cross motion for summary judgment, where it again challenges industry's standing in the case, an action that DOJ says must now be adjudicated on the record before the court. NMA and NEI claim that "the decision violates NEPA, yet they fail to demonstrate Article III and prudential standing to assert NEPA claims. These claims are non-justiciable and, in any event, contradicted by the record," the new DOJ brief says.
One environmentalists following the case says while it is true that industry cleared a procedural hurdle with the judge's order, the ruling's significance is limited because DOJ was "trying to dismiss early, and to survive a motion to dismiss is a lower threshold than dealing with standing on the merits." Industry has "cleared the low hurdle" of convincing the judge to not toss the case without looking at it. "Now we are at the merits stage," and industry is likely to fail, the source predicts.
In this case, which has been pending in U.S. District Court in Arizona since November 2011, the plaintiffs are seeking to challenge the withdrawal of 1 million acres of land that they want to access for uranium mining, and argue that the Bureau of Land Management (BLM) failed to consider their relevant information in the NEPA review, among other claims.
DOJ, on behalf of BLM, sought to dismiss the action, arguing in part that the industry groups lacked standing because their alleged economic harms fall outside NEPA's "zone of interest."
But the industry groups fought back, arguing that their claims fall within NEPA's realm. NEI and NMA also submitted a memorandum charging that denying the industry groups' right to intervene was inequitable. "Denying plaintiffs the ability to raise NEPA claims would yield absurd, or arbitrary, and inequitable results by refusing standing to the only plausible plaintiffs, effectively immunizing the agencies' NEPA analysis from conceivable challenge by industry, or any party likely to assert that environmental effects were grossly misstated in their EIS."
"The trade associations representing the uranium mining industry . . . are those most directly affected by the withdrawal. If NEI and NMA cannot challenge the withdrawal under NEPA, then no one can (save environmental advocacy groups who are highly unlikely to do so)," the memo said.
Campbell agreed and in a Jan. 8, 2013, order denied DOJ's motion to dismiss on the NEPA claims, finding that NMA and NEI had Article III standing and had satisfied "NEPA prudential standing by the environmental interest that they and their members possess in limiting the disruptive effects of uranium mining." And the judge found that their environmental interest were "sufficient . . . to bring them within the zone of interests of NEPA."
Mathiascheck told the webinar the declaration sought to show the industry interests were "precisely aligned with protecting the environment here" because "their interest is in fact to make sure they were mining in a way and in a place where they could minimize environmental impacts." Their analysis concluded that the places that BLM had withdrawn from access "were the best places to mine from the environmental standpoint," and the court found those environmental interests, intertwined with the company's financial interests, were exactly those that support standing in this case, she explained.
She also said she expected the standing decision to be appealed to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the 9th Circuit regardless of the outcome on summary judgment.
But the environmentalist warns that an appeal by industry is unlikely to succeed, citing "a long line of case law in the 9th Circuit that says the purpose of NEPA is to protect the environment. Your purpose cannot be to protect your pocketbook. And where what you are seeking to do would cause more environmental harm, you don't have standing. The mining companies say near the Grand Canyon is the best place to mine" because if they mine elsewhere it would do far more environmental damage.
The environmentalist notes that while some activists are intervening in the case on behalf of BLM, they are not
weighing in on the standing issue "mainly because we are often on the receiving end" of government lack-of-standing claims. "And our position is the courthouse doors should be open pretty wide."
Industry's response to DOJ's motion is due April 30. -- Dawn Reeves
]]></text></news-item>