<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-68C1-JCMN-Y18K"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>General Court Dismisses Appeals Against Commission Decision In Heat Stabilisers Cartel Case</title><source>Mondaq</source><author>Van Bael Bellis</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 24, 2014 (Mondaq:http://mondaq.com/ Delivered by Newstex) On 6 February 2014, the GC dismissed appeals brought by Arkema France, CECA SA, Elf Aquitaine SA and AC Treuhand AG against the European Commission's decision in the heat stabilisers cartel.
On 11 November 2009, the Commission fined 24 companies, from ten different corporate groups, a total of euro; 73,864,000 due to their involvement in cartels relating to plastic additives used as heat stabilisers (see VBB on Competition Law, Volume 2009, No. 11, available at www.vbb.com[1]). The Commission found that the companies concerned had fixed prices, shared customers, allocated markets and exchanged commercially-sensitive information in two separate cartels involving tin stabilisers (between 1987 and 2000) and ESBO/esters (between 1991 and 2000). Consultancy firm AC Treuhand was fined for its role as a facilitator of the cartel, even though it was not active on the markets concerned.Arkema France, CECA SA, Elf Aquitaine SA and AC Treuhand appealed to the GC against the decision. The companies argued that the Commission had erred in its assessment of the duration of the cartels and was, therefore, time-barred from imposing fines. The GC rejected this argument, recalling that, although the Commission must adduce precise and consistent evidence which is capable of demonstrating the existence of circumstances constituting an infringement, it is not necessary that every piece of evidence satisfy those criteria. It is sufficient that the body of evidence as a whole is capable of demonstrating, to the requisite legal standard, the existence of circumstances constituting an infringement. As cartels are regularly clandestine or secretive, the GC accepted that the existence of anti-competitive practice or agreements will often need to be inferred from a number of coincidences and indicia which taken together may, in the absence of another plausible explanation, constitute evidence of an infringement. Furthermore, the GC held that, if there is no evidence directly establishing the full duration of an infringement, the Commission should adduce evidence of facts sufficiently proximate in time for it to be reasonable to accept that the infringement continued uninterruptedly between two specific dates. In conclusion, the GC found no evidence that the applicants' participation in the infringements had come to an end on dates earlier than those stated by the Commission. In any case, the applicants did not specify the dates when, according to them, the infringements had come to an end.In addition Elf Aquitaine argued that the Commission had erred in attributing liability to it as the ultimate parent of Arkema and CECA. The Commission considered that Elf Aquitaine had exercised decisive influence and effective control over Arkema and CECA and so imputed liability to it. The GC recalled settled case law on this issue and held that where a parent company and its subsidiary form a single undertaking for the purposes of Article 101 TFEU, the Commission may address a decision imposing fines on the parent company, without having to establish its personal involvement in the infringement.Elf Aquitaine further claimed that the Commission had infringed its rights of defence by failing to inform it early in the investigation of the nature of, and the reasons for, the accusations made against it. The GC found, however, that provided an undertaking to whom a Statement of Objections is addressed is put in a position to submit its views effectively during the administrative procedure as to the reality and the relevance of the facts and circumstances alleged by the Commission, the Commission is not required as a matter of principle to address any measure of investigation to that entity before issuing a Statement of Objections.In addition, responding to pleas raised by AC Treuhand, the GC confirmed that a consultancy firm, which purposely contributes to a cartel, may be held liable as a co-perpetrator of an infringement. Any undertaking that has engaged in collusive conduct, including consultancy firms that are not active on the market affected by the restriction of competition, could reasonably have foreseen that the prohibition in Article 101(1) TFEU was applicable to it in principle.According to the GC, the level of fines imposed was appropriate, given the gravity of the unlawful conduct established in the Commission decision. The GC accordingly upheld the Commission's decision in its entirety.The content of this article is intended to provide a general guide to the subject matter. Specialist advice should be sought about your specific circumstances. Van Bael BellisVan Bael Bellis165 Avenue LouiseBrussels1050BELGIUM Tel: 26477350Fax: 26406499E-mail: Gdepril@vbb.comURL: www.vbb.comClick Here [2] for related articles (c) Mondaq Ltd, 2014 - Tel. +44 (0)20 8544 8300 - http://www.mondaq.com[3] [1]: http://www.mondaq.com/redirection.asp?article_id=300630company_id=1776redirectaddress=http%3A//www.vbb.com [2]: http://www.mondaq.com/search/relate.asp?article_id=300630online_host_id=0 [3]: http://www.mondaq.com/default.asp?online_host_id=22id=300630

]]></text></news-item>