<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-HP11-F11P-X334"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Proposed drilling a traumatic wakeup call for city residents</title><source>Global Data Point</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[I sincerely hope Goldenkey Oil Inc. will not be allowed to drill for oil and gas in west Lethbridge. We don't want to see pipelines, processing and storage facilities, plus a hazardous goods truck route along University Drive, toxic spills, noise, light pollution.
The scariest threat is the sour gas that could escape and drift towards homes and schools not far away. Hydrogen sulphide (H2S) targets the brain and lungs and starves them of oxygen. It can knock a person dead in levels as small as 700 parts per million (.007 per cent).I think back to the story of the Graff family near Vulcan. A huge flare nearby was ignited to dispose of waste gases and a noxious brew floated downwind, knocking Darrell down. He survived but with severe neurological damage. The Graff family fought for compensation but instead were further victimized, ridiculed and ignored.On top of the dizziness, nausea, nosebleeds, paralysis and seizures - symptoms of H2S poisoning - the Graffs lost 25 per cent of their calving herd and pigs miscarried in record numbers. A rancher on the Blood reserve, near wells being fracked, has also lost a large number of cattle. Howard and Nielle Hawkwood of Cochrane spoke to the No Drilling Lethbridge group and told them of their own horrors regarding fracking. She lost her hair and they have lost 10 per cent of their cow herd.The Alberta Energy Regulator is 100 per cent financed by the oil and gas industry and is in charge of allocating water for fracking. Did you know that it takes two to eight million gallons of water to frack a well? Where will they obtain this water in our semi-arid desert? Where will the toxic wastewater be dumped?When oil and gas companies are accused of destroying water wells, they deny, deny and ignore.The arrival of Goldenkey Oil Inc. has been a traumatic wakeup call for Lethbridge citizens. The local MLAs say they are making sure "our concerns are heard" but are they willing to put their jobs on the line and hound the Conservative government into changing legislation so that no drilling happens within the limits of any city or town in Alberta?© 2014 Global Data Point.
]]></text></news-item>