<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-RN01-JD34-V2MY"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>No room for error in Asia; Jennifer Hewett</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>Jennifer Hewett</author><text><![CDATA[Tony Abbott won't exactly be travelling light on his trip to Asia next month. He will be accompanied by a range of Australian business leaders and premiers as part of a massive trade mission that includes Japan and South Korea as well as China.
Balancing the diplomatic juggle - and the extreme political sensitivities - between three key trading partners is important for any Australian Prime Minister. That only becomes more crucial as the wealth and size of the Asian economies generally leapfrog those of the developed world.
But there's no doubt that managing the relationship with China, in particular, dominates Australian economic and political thinking - along with the aim of negotiating a free-trade agreement by year's end. A similar free-trade agreement with South Korea is due to be signed off during the trip, while an agreement with Japan is imminent.
Getting an agreement with China is more protracted and even more delicate, not least in calming voter concerns about the level of potential Chinese investment in Australia. And in gauging the response of the Chinese and what concessions are possible.
The well-choreographed visits by Abbott will leverage various activities occurring as part of "Australia Week in China" from April 8-11 - another element of Canberra's strong China focus. This timing neatly coincides with the Boao Forum in Hainan - the Asian equivalent of the world economic forum held in Davos each year. Abbott will (briefly) attend the forum, along with other leaders, before going on to Shanghai and other cities.China in conciliatory mood
Abbott registering a slightly off-key tone is an obvious risk given China's increasingly aggressive stance in dealing with Japan and the confrontational tone between China and the United States. Australian politicians expressing concern about "human rights" is by now almost rote - and meets a predictable response.
But after a rocky period under Kevin Rudd, relative disinterest in the relationship by Julia Gillard, and initial friction with the Abbott government, the Chinese will be keen to promote an image of co-operation and "trust". Abbott will also be keen on selling the mutual benefits of strong political and economic ties.
The Prime Minister is well aware that the ability to successfully restructure the Australian economy will be heavily dependent on China's growth, direction and willingness to liberalise its own economy. That includes constantly expanding Australian areas of potential trade and investment in everything from financial services to tourism, education and agribusiness, as well as the recent staple of resources.
The ANZ report released Monday on the transformation of the Asian financial system suggests the Chinese banking system may be larger than that of the US by 2020 and the financial sector twice as large by 2030.
The increase in New Zealand dairy exports to China since the signing of its FTA four years ago is another example. NZ dairy exports to China have grown by more than $2 billion since, compared to Australia's modest $60 million increase. A free-trade agreement is not the only reason, but it certainly helps.
And report after report talks about the potential for a new Australian boom in agricultural exports to meet the changing tastes and incomes of a rising Asian middle class.Foreign investment a hard sell
The corollary for Australia will be the enthusiasm of business and the public to back the implications of an FTA and China's ever bigger footprint on the neighbourhood. Much of Australian business has been slow to appreciate and take advantage of the rapid economic revolution occurring in Asia, in terms of export and investment opportunities offshore, and in searching out greater foreign investment in Australian operations.
In Australian domestic politics, the main issue is likely to involve managing the public reaction to the level of Chinese investment in Australian agricultural businesses and land and in residential real estate.
A parliamentary committee is currently looking at foreign investment in residential real estate, for example, including assessing the economic benefits and whether it is increasing supply and benefits to the Australian construction industry.
Those economic benefits are pretty obvious given the surge in residential apartment building - but concern about rising house prices and fears Australians are being "squeezed out" by Chinese investors is resonating loudly in the electorate.
That's going to require some careful political massaging - particularly given the obstacles facing Australian investment in China.
On purchases of agricultural land and businesses, it's more about the Liberals massaging the Nationals. Before the election, the Nationals managed to persuade their colleagues to reduce the threshold for references to the Foreign Investment Review Board on foreign purchases of agricultural land to $15 million, and to $53 million for agribusinesses.
For investments in non-sensitive areas of the Australian economy, China will get the same treatment as South Korea and the US, with a referral threshold of just over $1 billion. Any investments by state-owned enterprises (no names mentioned, of course) automatically get referred. But under the South Korea FTA, the Koreans agreed to these newly reduced thresholds for agricultural investments. The Nationals will want the same rules to apply to any FTA with China.
The ability of Trade Minister Andrew Robb to negotiate those sorts of pressures to finally conclude a free-trade agreement with China this year won't get the same public attention as various domestic squabbles. But the impact on Australia's economic future will be much more enduring.
]]></text></news-item>