<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-NP51-JBYM-Y46J"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Harlequin chief's son jailed for three years over £1.6m fraud</title><source>Citywire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The son of overseas property company Harlequin's chairman David Ames has been sentenced to more than three years in jail having been found guilty of a £1.6 million fraud.
Matthew Ames was sentenced to 40 months in prison at Isleworth Crown court last week having been convicted of two counts of fraudulent trading in February following a two-year investigation by the City of London Police.
Last month the court heard how Ames led investors into bogus carbon credit and teak tree investment schemes.
Between 2008 and 2010 Matthew Ames targeted investors through companies The Investor Club and Forestry for Life with the promise of high percentages and long-term returns on what he marketed as ethical, environmentally friendly enterprises.
Matthew Ames then used the money to cover company expenses and to support his lavish lifestyle of holidays in the Caribbean and driving a Lamborghini. His victims lost as much as £120,000 each.
The police said that Matthew Ames created the impression of success by using funds taken from later investors to pay out around £100,000 to his early investors 'in line with the classic 'Ponzi' style fraud'.
To legitimise the operation Matthew Ames recruited professionals with impressive CVs, including former civil servants and businessmen, the police said. However, these employees were kept at arm's length from the company finances and those that started to question the operating model were swiftly dismissed.
The Financial Services Authority launched an investigation into Matthew Ames in early 2011 after investors were having difficulty contacting him.
In September 2011, he was arrested by the City of London Police.
Detective constable Simon Cordell, who led the investigation, said this 'Ponzi fraud' played on people's conscience by tricking investors into a supposedly ethical investment scheme.
'Unfortunately it was all a pack of lies so he could live the high life at others expense, with no remorse shown for the damage caused to his victims' futures,' he said. 'I have little doubt that if we had not got to him when we did many more investors would have fallen into the same trap under a different company name.
'I hope this sentencing sends a clear message to anyone carrying out criminal activity and taking advantage of innocent people that City of London Police will find you and you will be prosecuted.'
There is no suggestion that David Ames or Harlequin were in any way involved.
]]></text></news-item>