<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-V7H1-F0JP-W241"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Union `cold cases' reopened CONSTRUCTION WATCHDOG CREATES NEW UNIT TO RE-EXAMINE PAST INVESTIGATIONS - EXCLUSIVE -</title><source>The Australian</source><author>EWIN HANNAN, INDUSTRIAL EDITOR</author><text><![CDATA[THE national building watchdog has established a ``cold-case'' unit to re-examine past investigations, with the federal government agency preparing to reopen the probe into alleged unlawful strike action by construction workers on Victoria's controversial desalination project.
In an extraordinary move that will inflame tensions between the Coalition and unions, the Fair Work and Building Construction director Nigel Hadgkiss has decided to set up the cold-case unit to re-examine the activities of the regulator under the previous Labor government.
The stand by Mr Hadgkiss, who returned to the agency in October, underlines the aggressive approach it intends to take against the Construction Forestry Mining and Energy Union.
The agency withdrew from legal action taken in the Supreme Court of Victoria in relation to five days of industrial action taken by CFMEU members at the Wonthaggi plant in June 2011.
``I ordered an internal inquiry as to why the decision was made to withdraw from a matter relating to the Victorian desalination plant,'' Mr Hadgkiss told The Australian yesterday.
``Preliminary findings are that the case should be reopened.''
Mr Hadgkiss would make no further comment but The Australian understands that the case is set to be reopened.
Employment Minister Eric Abetz last night welcomed the decision to set up the cold-case unit. ``The suggestion of a cold-case unit within FWBC to revisit past matters that may have been dropped without adequate reason is both concerning and welcome -- concerning that it is deemed necessary and welcome in that it will clear the air as to whether the FWBC was deliberately weakened and neutered under Labor,'' Senator Abetz told The Australian.
Dave Noonan, the national secretary of the CFMEU's construction division, last night accused Mr Hadgkiss of ``playing politics''.
``The use of terms like `cold-case units' demeans what are pretty serious investigations carried out by real police officers,'' Mr Noonan said. ``This is again very emotive language.''
He said he could not recall the specific action taken by the workers at the desalination plant that was set to be re-investigated. ``We'll deal with the matter if it comes before us,'' he said.
In pushing for the return of the Australian Building and Construction Commission, the Coalition and employers insist the former government significantly weakened the powers of the building regulator, including a reduction in the maximum penalties that could be imposed on unions and workers.
As well as the cold-case unit, Mr Hadgkiss revealed last week he was investigating complaints by contractors about the alleged conduct of head contractors on building projects.
He said it was a ``widespread practice'' for head contractors to strike agreements with unions and then require smaller contractors and subcontractors to sign up to the same agreement if they wanted work on the project.
Contractors have complained that the union agreements were significantly more generous than their existing legal agreements with workers but they missed out on the project work unless they agreed to them.
Mr Hadgkiss has also applied to have four union officials banned from construction sites, and moved to publish a national list of banned officials on his agency's website.
News of the agency's decision to set up the new unit came a day after the nation's builders urged the government to fast-track controversial changes to the construction industry code, warning that the intervention was needed to withstand union pressure to cave in to new enterprise agreements containing restrictive work practices. But Labor and the Greens have signalled they will not support passage of the code through the Senate, prompting
Continued on Page 6
Continued from Page 1
employers to accuse the opposition parties of condoning union coercion and intimidation.
The Weekend Australian reported Senator Abetz saying that he wanted to break the ``closed shop'' that existed between head contractors and the CFMEU by reviving the Work Choices era building code.
The code, to be released shortly by the government, will seek to prevent employers getting commonwealth work if they strike workplace agreements with ``restrictive'' work practices.
Based on the Howard government's controversial 2006 guidelines, the code will potentially force the removal of clauses in agreements that relate to outsourcing, contracting, use of labour hire and union rights.
Employers in Victoria said they hoped the code could be used to reduce the 20 rostered days off that apply across the state's construction sector, claiming the current 36-hour week industry calendar left the sector dormant for considerable periods of the year.
Labor and unions claim the move shows the government is engaged in underhand attempts to revive John Howard's Work Choices policy, despite the coalition promising the policy was ``dead, buried and cremated''.
]]></text></news-item>