<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-HD91-F0NV-F12V"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>BUSINESS MILESTONES</title><source>Winston-Salem Journal (North Carolina)</source><author>COMPILED BY CINDY HODNETT</author><text><![CDATA[. Jon Bowman has been named the president of PostMark Inc. Bowman was previously the company's vice president of business development and has been with PostMark for 20 years.
The position was previously held by PostMark founder and Bowman's father-in-law, Richard Vann. PostMark Inc. offers direct mail and data enhancement, including printing, fulfillment and mar­keting services.
. Novant Health Forsyth Medical Center , Novant Health Kernersville Medical Center and Novant Health Medical Park Hospital have earned Magnet recognition from the American Nurses Credentialing Center. The Magnet Recognition program recognizes excellence in three areas: nursing satisfaction, patient satisfaction and clinical performance. This is the third Magnet designation for Forsyth Medical Center and a first designation for Kernersville Medical Center and Medical Park Hospital.
Nationally, 401 health care organizations have earned Magnet status.
. Kilpatrick Townsend & Stockton has received 14 national first tier rankings from U.S. News Best Lawyers 2014 Best Law Firms rankings. The areas of practice for the first tier rankings include: antitrust law, construction law, employee benefits (ERISA) law, environmental law, franchise law, insurance law, litigation-antitrust, litigation-construction, litigationERISA, litigation-intellectual property, Native American law, patent law, technology law and trademark law. The firm also ranked nationally in the areas of advertising law, banking and finance law, bankruptcy and creditor debtor rights/insolvency and reorganization law, biotechnology law, commercial litigation, copyright law, corporate law, employment law-management, labor law-management, litigation-bankruptcy, litigation-environmental, litigation-patent, litigation-tax, mergers and acquisitions law, real estate law, securities/ capital markets law, securities regulation, securitization and structured finance law and tax law.
First-tier rankings for the Kilpatrick Townsend & Stockton Winston-Salem office include: antitrust law, commercial litigation, construction law, corporate governance law, corporate law, eminent domain and condemnation law, environmental law, insurance law, litigation-antitrust, litigation-construction, litigationenvironmental, litigationERISA, litigation-intellectual property, litigation-patent, litigation-securities, patent law, personal injury litigationplaintiffs, product liability litigation-defendants, trademark law. The Winston-Salem office received high rankings for: appellate practice, litigation-banking and finance, litigation-mergers and acquisitions, litigation-trusts and estates, personal injury litigation-defendants, securities/capital markets law and securities regulation.
. Business North Carolina named these attorneys from Kilpatrick Townsend & Stockton to the 2014 Legal Elite list: Paul J. Foley , business; Randall F. Avram , Richard D. Haygood , Corena A. Norris-McCluney and R. Sterling Perkinson , employment; Stephen R. Berlin and Steven J. Levitas , environment; Charles W. Calkins and Steven Gardner , intellectual property; Jeffrey A. Benson , real estate; John M. Moye , Young Guns (Best Under 40).
. Van Johnson has been named the incoming president of Triad Business Exchange.
Johnson was previously the business development manager for The Resource.
Triad Business Exchange is a nonprofit professional development, networking and business referral organization.
. R. Scott Tobin has been named a partner in the Raleigh office of Nelson Mullins Riley & Scarborough LLP. Tobin has practiced in the Greensboro area where he provided multistate merger and acquisition and corporate governance project support. He was also the chairman and chief executive of custom furniture manufacturer Wellington Hall Designs in Lexington. In his new role, Tobin will assist clients in North Carolina and beyond in corporate matters including venture capital and mergers and acquisitions.
He concentrates his practice in the areas of technology finance, mergers and acquisitions, corporate governance and business litigation.
. Four attorneys with Spilman Thomas & Battle PLLC have been recognized by North Carolina Super Lawyers magazine. Rayford K. 'Trip' Adams III was named to the Super Lawyers list, and Erin Jones Adams , R. Scott Adams and Nathan B.
Atkinson have been named as Rising Stars. Trip Adams has more than 30 years of experience in all aspects of bankruptcy matters and is board certified as a specialist in business and consumer bankruptcy law by the N.C.
State Bar Board of Legal Specialization. Erin Adams practices primarily in civil litigation, concentrating in the areas of employment law and electronic discovery. Scott Adams primarily practices consumer financial services law and has extensive experience in electronic discovery and in defending employers in complex workers' compensation matters. Atkinson focuses on litigation and trial work with an emphasis in natural resources law, toxic tort law and environmental litigation.
He is also a lead member of the Battle Group, Spilman's high-stakes litigation strike force and co-chairman of the firm's Shale Gas Group.
. Lori J. Prescott has been hired as the new executive director for the Winston-Salem Youth Chorus, a funded partner of The Arts Council of Winston-Salem and Forsyth County. Lori spent seven years in event planning and the last 16 years in advertising with The Woodbine Agency.
. Ten attorneys at the law firm of Bell, Davis & Pitt P.A. have been named North Carolina Super Lawyers for 2014 by North Carolina Super Lawyers magazine.
The attorneys are: Daniel C. Bruton , bankruptcy-business; D. Anderson Carmen , creditor debtor rights; John A. Cocklereece Jr. , business/corporate; Edward B. Davis , business litigation; William K. Davis , business litigation; James R. Fox , business litigation; Walter W. Pitt Jr ., bankruptcybusiness; Alan M. Ruley , business litigation; Robin J. Stinson , family law; and Kevin G. Williams , business litigation. William K. Davis also was named one of the state's Top 10 attorneys for 2014, and Stinson was named one of North Carolina's Top 50 female attorneys.
Five Bell, Davis & Pitt attorneys were named North Carolina Rising Stars for 2014 by the magazine.
Those attorneys are: Adam T. Duke , creditor debtor rights; Andrew A. Freeman , business litigation; Monica R. Guy , family law; Mark A. Jones , criminal defensewhite collar; and Michael A. Myers , banking.
. Henry Isaacson has received the Stanley Frank Lifetime Achievement award from Greensboro Partnership Economic Development.
Isaacson is a senior partner with Isaacson Isaacson Sheridan & Fountain LLP.
He has been a member of the Piedmont Triad Airport Authority board for 15 years, a director of First Flight Centennial Foundation, a trustee of the Weatherspoon Arts Foundation, director of the International Civil Rights Museum and local chairman of the National Conference of Christians and Jews. The Frank award is given to a member of the community who has dedicated years of service in support of improving Greensboro and Guilford County.
. A Baird public finance transaction has been recognized as a 2013 Deal of the Year by The Bond Buyer, a national daily newspaper that focuses on the municipal bond industry. The deal recognized was Harnett County, North Carolina's issuance of $20 million in limited obligation bonds to refinance the debt of its seven water and sewer districts. Baird served as senior managing underwriter to Harnett County on the transaction, which was recognized in the Southeast regional category. This is the sixth time since 2005 that a Baird public finance transaction has been honored by The Bond Buyer as a Deal of the Year.
. Allison Palmadessa has had an article accepted for publication in the Higher Education in Review Journal.
Palmadessa examines how academic capitalist efforts are damaging to higher education in 'Academic Capitalism and the Social Charter Between the University and the Public.' She is a 2003 graduate and an adjunct instructor of history at Greensboro College.
. Olga Topping , Tom Robinson and Michael Padjen have been named to the North Carolina District Export Council by U.S. Secretary of Commerce Penny Pritzker. Topping is with BB&T in Greensboro.
Robinson is with ERD Ltd. in Kernersville. Padjen works for Klaussner Home Furnishings in Asheboro.
Send submissions to business@ wsjournal.com.
]]></text></news-item>