<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-HH91-DYJJ-P0WH"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Oregon mid-pack on toxic pollution</title><source>Statesman Journal (Salem, Oregon)</source><author>By, Tracy Loew</author><text><![CDATA[Across Oregon, 276 facilities released 28.3 million pounds of toxic chemicals to the state's land, air and water in 2012, according to new data from the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency.
Oregon now ranks 35th in the nation for the total amount of toxic chemicals released to the environment.
The amount was about the same as in 2011.
Manufacturing, metal mining, electric utilities and hazardous waste facilities must report their release of toxic chemicals to the EPA each year.
The EPA then publishes an annual Toxic Release Inventory, listing information about chemical releases across the country.
Chemicals are placed on the list based on their potential to cause adverse effects to human health or the environment. However, the data does not quantify actual health exposure to the chemicals.
Two Oregon companies rank among the country's top 100 polluters.
Chemical Waste Management of the Northwest, located on 251 acres in Arlington, is the nation's 24th largest polluter and its second-largest hazardous waste landfill.
It accounted for 14 million pounds, or nearly half, of Oregon's chemical releases.
Cascade Steel Rolling Mills, in McMinnville, comes in at No. 87.
In Marion and Polk counties, eight companies released a total of 137,661 pounds of chemicals in 2012, a decrease of 6 percent from the previous year.
The biggest polluter locally remained Fiber-Fab in Gervais, which manufactures shower stalls and jetted tubs.
The most widely released chemical locally was styrene, used in the production of plastics and resins. It is a respiratory hazard that can affect the nervous system.
In Salem, three companies made the list: Akzo Nobel Coatings, Ennis-Flint and Riverbend Sand and Gravel.
Covanta's garbage incinerator in Brooks is not included in the report. EPA exempts municipal waste incinerators from reporting requirements.
Nationwide, releases of listed toxic chemicals decreased. Across the country, 3.6 billion pounds of toxic chemicals were released into the environment in 2012, an 11 percent decrease from 2011.
The state with the highest level of pollutants was Alaska, mainly due to mining.
It was followed by Nevada, Texas, Utah and Louisiana.
tloew@StatesmanJournal.com, (503) 399-6779 or follow at Twitter.com/SJWatchdog
Online
See this story at StatesmanJournal.com for more information about toxic releases.
Top polluters, Marion and Polk counties
Here are the Marion and Polk county companies that released the most toxic chemicals to the environment in 2012, along with pounds released.
Fiber-Fab, Gervais: 72,907 pounds
Marquis Corp., Independence: 17,473
Elkay Wood Products, Independence: 16,322
Akzo Nobel Coatings Inc., Salem: 13,050
Specialty Polymers Inc.,Woodburn: 13,004
Ennis - Flint, Salem: 4,852
Loxcreen Co. Inc., Woodburn: 17
Riverbend Sand & Gravel, Salem: 36
Top polluters, Oregon
Here are the Oregon companies that released the most toxic chemicals to the environment in 2012, along with pounds released.
Chemical Waste Management of the Northwest, Arlington: 13,964,080
Cascade Steel Rolling Mills, McMinnville: 5,003,635
Cascade Pacific Pulp Halsey Pulp Mill, Halsey: 1,354,311
Georgia-Pacific Toledo, Toledo: 1,113,280
Dyno Nobel-St. Helens Plant, Deer Island: 776,669
Georgia Pacific Consumer Products LP Wauna Mill, Clatskanie: 556,202
International Paper, Springfield: 535,191
Boardman Plant, Boardman: 484,928
TDY Industries DBA Wash Chang, Albany: 425,284
SP Fiber Technologies Northwest, Newberg: 370,633
Top pollutants, Marion and Polk counties
Here are the top toxic chemicals released by companies in Marion and Polk counties in 2012, along with pounds released and the chemical's potential impacts. All of the top 10 toxic chemicals released in the two counties are air emissions.
Styrene: 90,651
Breathing high levels may result in nervous system effects such as changes in color vision, tiredness, feeling drunk, slowed reaction time, concentration problems or balance problems.
Xylene: 20,320
High levels can cause headaches
Vinyl acetate: 10,101
Short term effects of breathing high levels include irritated eyes, nose and throat.
Toluene: 6,864
May affect the nervous system, causing tiredness, confusion, weakness, drunken-type actions, memory loss, nausea, loss of appetite and hearing and color vision loss.
Methanol: 4,058
Inhalation may cause neurological, gastrointestinal, ophthalmologic and other health effects.
Methyl methacrylate: 2,170
Acute and chronic exposure may result in respiratory and neurological symptoms.
Ethylbenzene: 1,029
Short exposures can cause eye and throat irritation and dizziness. Long-term exposure may cause irreversible damage to the inner ear and hearing. It is a possible human carcinogen.
N-butyl alcohol: 992
High concentrations can cause respiratory problems.
Butyl acrylate: 491
Heavy inhalation exposure can cause pulmonary edema.
Methyl acrylate: 481
Breathing can irritate the nose and throat.
Top pollutants, Oregon
Here are top toxic chemicals released by companies in Oregon in 2012, along with pounds released and the chemical's possible effects.
Aluminum: 5,478,966
Most of this chemical goes to the Chemical Waste Management hazardous waste landfill. A small amount is released to the air. High-level exposure may result in respiratory and neurological problems.
Methanol: 2,723,159
Inhalation may cause neurological, gastrointestinal, ophthalmologic and other health effects.
Lead compounds: 2,098,601
Most of this goes to the hazardous waste landfill. Some is released to the air. Lead can damage the nervous system, kidneys and reproductive system.
Asbestos: 2,014,580
All of this goes to the hazardous waste landfill. Exposure can cause serious lung problems and cancer.
Napthalene: 1,648,917
Acute exposure can cause liver and neurological damage.
Ammonia: 1,431,894
Exposure to high levels can cause irritation and serious burns on the skin and in the mouth, throat, lungs and eyes.
Nitrate compounds: 972,023
All of these releases are to water. Nitrate can cause blue baby syndrome and fetal development problems.
Manganese compounds: 587,637
High levels may affect the nervous system, lung irritation and reproductive system.
Hydrochloric acid: 461,581
Short-term inhalation exposure may cause eye, nose and respiratory tract irritation.
Barium compounds: 54,003
May cause gastrointestinal disturbances and muscular weakness.
Source: U.S. Environmental Protection Agency
]]></text></news-item>