<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-SPF1-DY0P-G4JT"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Advocates Advance Novel Suits On Clean Water Permits For Coal Trains</title><source>Water Policy Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Environmentalists are weighing whether to consolidate two novel cases testing whether train cars carrying coal and other pollutants are subject to Clean Water Act (CWA) discharge permits because they are "point sources" of pollution, litigation they hope will help them curb industry plans to construct new coal export terminals in the Pacific Northwest.
In a March 12 order, Judge John C. Coughenour, of the U.S. District Court for the Western District of Washington, rejected industry's motion to dismiss Sierra Club, et al. v. BNSF Railway Company, holding that the environmentalists have standing to bring the suit and that their claims give BNSF "sufficient information to figure out the nature of the violations for which it is being sued." Relevant documents are available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID: 2465143)
Coughenour's decision comes after BNSF's motion to dismiss a closely linked case in the eastern district of Washington, also titled Sierra Club v. BNSF, was rejected on separate grounds -- which an attorney working with Sierra Club on the suits says may allow the parties to consolidate the two cases for a single decision on the merits.
"Now that we have the ruling allowing our case to continue, the decision on whether to ask for consolidation will probably be made" before the end of March, the attorney says.
Judge Lonny R. Suko, who is presiding over the eastern district case, noted in a Feb. 19 scheduling order that environmentalists and industry had jointly "requested that the Court suspend the setting of a trial date and case schedule until a motion to consolidate with the nearly identical case, pending in the Western District of Washington, has been filed and ruled upon."
Both suits seek to establish that when coal and coal dust dislodged from open-top train cars during transportation falls into a jurisdictional waterbody, it is a "discharge of a pollutant" from a point source requiring a permit under the CWA.
"They're dealing with the same issue -- I think the main reason they haven't been consolidated already is because BNSF wanted to have two chances to get a dismissal," the attorney says.
If the cases are consolidated, however, it is not certain that the combined suit will reach a ruling on the merits. Environmentalists in the eastern district case are still awaiting the court's approval to file an amended complaint, crafted in response to Suko's Jan. 2 order that denied industry's motion to dismiss the suit but set a high bar for the plaintiffs to show that coal from the train cars follows "a confined, discrete conveyance" to protected waters -- a key characteristic of a point source as defined in the CWA (Water Policy Report, Jan. 13).
In its proposed amended complaint, Sierra Club cites specific bridges and crossings where it says coal trains have dropped debris directly into water. "For example, on Sunday, July 21, 2013, at approximately 8:05 a.m., a westbound
BNSF coal train, while crossing the point of confluence of the White Salmon River and Columbia River approximately one mile west of White Salmon, Washington, discharged a significant quantity of coal particles into and along the White Salmon and Columbia Rivers," it says.
The attorney says environmentalists are confident that if the court allows the amended complaint, it will survive Suko's "discrete conveyance" test. The complaint filed in the western district case uses similar language and was upheld despite BNSF's claim that it was not specific enough for the company to identify how the alleged discharges reached protected waters, the attorney says.
"We feel quite confident on that issue in light of the language that Judge Coughenour used" in his March 12 order.
"Plaintiffs explained that the violations allegedly occur at every location where BNSF's railcars pass over or near a protected waterway. While broad, this description is not necessarily lacking in specificity -- it provides BNSF with a method to determine the location of the violations: Where its trains go over or next to waterways. This is 'reasonably specific' and in accord with Ninth Circuit precedent," Coughenour says in the order.
Coughenour also says in his order that the environmentalists have shown a solid enough link between environmental harms and the railway's alleged failure to secure coal for transport to demonstrate standing -- which requires a plaintiff to show an injury that can be traced to misconduct by the defendant and is redressable by the court.
"Plaintiffs' allegations, while somewhat bare, are sufficient to state a plausible claim at this early point of the lawsuit," the order says.
If the court sides with Sierra Club, BNSF and other railways could be forced to seek discharge permits for coal trains, or even for individual train cars -- which could require them to cover the cars, seal leaks or take other potentially expensive measures to curb discharges, in addition to subjecting the companies to potentially high administrative costs.
The pending cases are part of a series of efforts by environmentalists against both greenhouse gas and conventional pollution from coal mining and related transport operations. They are especially concerned over plans by industry to build several new coal export terminals in Washington state and Oregon and, together with state and federal lawmakers, are calling for greater scrutiny of the climate change and other environmental impacts of the terminals.
"The implications of the case are monumental, as the Northwest has become ground zero in the fight to stop three proposed coal export terminals in Washington and Oregon," Sierra Club said in a statement. "The court's decision to move the case forward is a step in the right direction to stop coal -- and its toxic associates, lead, arsenic, and mercury -- from further poisoning our fish, our water, and our families."
Other recent instances of environmentalists targeting conventional pollutant emissions from coal mining or transport included a request by Sierra Club in February for Washington State to conduct a comprehensive review of air quality effects from coal transport in the state.
And in Alaska Community Action on Toxics (ACAT), et al. v. Aurora Energy Services, LLC, et al., which was due to begin briefing before the U.S. Court of Appeals for the 9th Circuit March 21, environmentalists are arguing that airborne coal dust that settles in jurisdictional waters is also a point source requiring permits (Water Policy Report, Aug. 26).
]]></text></news-item>