<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-MKK1-F0BC-M3R4"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Duke Energy to defend coal ash dumps in SC, NC; Watchdog decries contamination at Saluda River site</title><source>Anderson Independent-Mail (South Carolina)</source><author>Michael Eads</author><text><![CDATA[COLUMBIA — Duke Energy goes before the South Carolina Public Service Commission on Monday afternoon to address its coal ash dumping practices in North Carolina, as well as at its steam generation plant in eastern Anderson County.
Duke spokesman Ryan Mosier said the company asked for the appearance before the S.C. commission, set for 2 p.m. “Duke Energy requested the opportunity to give the commissioners the latest and best information not only on our ongoing activities in North Carolina, but specifically inform them about our coal ash facilities in South Carolina and answer any questions they might have on the topic,” Mosier stated in a email to the Independent Mail on Sunday.
A February 2014 spill from a coal ash dump in Eden, N.C., coated 70 miles of the Dan River in toxic sludge and brought to light Duke’s history of polluting groundwater with its leaky, unlined coal ash dumps, according to an Associated Press report. The Southern Environmental Law Center (SELC) has also requested time before the commission Monday to discuss Duke’s coal waste pond at the W.S. Lee Steam Station on the Saluda River near Williamston. Attorney Frank Holleman told the Independent Mail on Sunday that Duke is using the same methods in Anderson County that led to the Dan River spill. The SELC announced Friday that a 2006 study found elevated arsenic levels in the ground around the Lee station, which Greenville-based attorney Holleman blames squarely on what he calls Duke’s “antiquated” storage methods. “At its W.S. Lee facility, Duke is storing its coal ash just as it does in North Carolina — in unlined holes in the ground held back by a dike that leaks and contaminates the ground in the surrounding area,” said Holleman, who will be at Monday’s hearing. “Others, like Santee Cooper and SCE & G, are cleaning up these old coal ash dumps; Duke is the sole utility in the Carolinas that is sticking with this antiquated, toxic coal ash storage.” Holleman went on to say that leakage from the plant’s coal ash containment is being routed into stormwater sewers, which empty into the Saluda River. “If a dike there has even a minor leak, they have created a system that will shoot it into the Saluda River, similar to what happened at the Dan River,” said Holleman. Taking action against Duke in South Carolina could get tougher in the near future. State House members voted 80-30 earlier this month for a bill that would block lawsuits by citizens groups like the SELC under the state’s Pollution Control Act. The bill would apply to any company, but could be particularly advantageous to Duke and its coal ash dumps near Williamston and Darlington. “It is amnesty for polluters,” said Rep. James Smith, D-Richland. Holleman laughed when asked about the House bill, which is now before the state Senate for consideration. “It’s an outrageous example of illegal polluters protecting themselves by using lobbying and contributions in Columbia,” said Holleman, who noted that House members did strip criminal amnesty from the bill before its passage March 1. Duke has coal ash dumps at 14 power plants in North Carolina, all of which were cited last year for polluting groundwater. Following the Dan River spill, the company has been cited for eight more violations. North Carolina regulators said Friday that they have asked a judge to withdraw a proposed settlement with Duke Energy to resolve environmental violations by the company paying a $99,000 fine with no requirement that Duke clean up its pollution. North Carolina officials announced Friday they would partner with the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency to pursue joint enforcement against Duke for Clean Water Act violations related to the Dan River dump and new concerns about illegal releases at another Duke site. The U.S. Department of Justice has also convened a grand jury in Raleigh to investigate Duke’s coal ash dumping practices in North Carolina. Follow Michael Eads on Twitter @MikeEads_AIM The Associated Press contributed to this report.
]]></text></news-item>