<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-HD11-JD3N-52GN"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Have your say</title><source>The Advertiser (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Square is on track HAVING been contacted by a number of concerned residents and traders, I would like to add some context to the Henley Square Upgrade story from last week.
The headlines appearing in the Messenger and Advertiser and online included the words "Square Black Hole", "Projects could be scrapped", "$1 million over budget" and "Blowout to trim Square", and were quite misleading given the current stage of the project.
Council has not yet engaged a project construction contractor, nor have we received a final cost for the works.
Residents, traders and community groups have been working hard with Council through the Henley Precinct Community Reference Group (HPCRG) and the Henley Beach Business Association (HBBA) and have provided valuable feedback on various design elements and their priorities as part of the 30 per cent design review stage.
Unfortunately, these headlines made the project appear that it was in trouble when in fact council is very happy with the current progress of the project and with the input from the HPCRG and the HBBA.
On this basis Council has endorsed the project to proceed to final design with a budget of $8.4 million; this includes a $4 million contribution from the State and Federal Government. The next stage of the project will include a careful review of each element as part of a value management exercise with stakeholders.
At this stage there have been no decisions made by council to cut anything from the scope of works, and we will continue working with the community to ensure that their aspirations are reflected in the final design. Please do not hesitate to get in touch with council on 8408 1111, or email: kalexander@charlessturt.sa.gov.au if you have feedback or concerns.
(Mayor) KIRSTEN ALEXANDER, (Cr) Robert Randall (Henley Ward) and (Cr) Jim Fitzpatrick (Henley Ward).
United for search IT is heartening and reflective of our humanity that some 26 nations set aside their differences in a bid to resolve the mysterious disappearance of flight MH370 in the hope of ending the speculation and anguish for those who await the fate of there loved ones.
BRIAN COOMBES, Mannum.
Seen but not Hird METHINKS that Tania should be seen but not Hird.
GERRY GREENWAY, Netherby.
No solution given OUR legal system's lenient penalties for the perpetrators of sexual abuse against any child is appalling. Ali Clarke's column outlines this but doesn't offer a solution (The Advertiser, yesterday).
SUE PEARCE, Hawthorn.
Corruption bloom I REFER to the front page report in Saturday's Advertiser entitled "Paid Just $6/hour" in reference to international students working part-time in Adelaide. As a homestay provider for almost 30 years, this embarrassing scenario keeps popping up in my life.
I have seen a student working in a dumpling shop for $8/hour for months and was too terrified to point out to the proprietor that this was illegal.
Another Masters student was "lucky" to get a job in the sushi shop in the northern suburbs where they paid her around $8/hour.
When she found out through our family contacts that she should have been getting more than double that per hour she approached her boss who said that she was "lucky" to have a job and if she complained he would report her to Immigration and her visa would be cancelled because she had to work more than 20 hours a week as allowed.
And then, shortly after, he went bankrupt owing her $2000 back pay! Having a wide variety of contacts in the international student community I can assure you we have never heard of any overseas student being paid the correct wages from a small privately run enterprise. (No problems with big organisations like five-star hotels, supermarkets and the like).
Nothing would thrill me more than the see this exploitation and, indeed, corruption nipped in the bud ... even though the bud is now in full bloom.TONY ELLIOTT, homestay provider, Payneham.
]]></text></news-item>