<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTJ-SPF1-DY0P-G4GG"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Republicans Broaden Attacks On Climate NSPS Beyond CCS Concerns</title><source>Carbon Control News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[House Republicans appear to be broadening their attacks on EPA's proposed carbon dioxide (CO2) rule for new utilities beyond whether its carbon capture and sequestration (CCS) mandate is reasonable and lawful to fears that the rule, when combined with an EPA guidance on sequestering CO2, could discourage enhanced oil recovery (EOR).
The lower chamber's expanded line of criticism of the new source performance standards (NSPS) for newly constructed power plants comes as some Senate opponents of the rule are identifying new lines of attack against the rule. For example, several Senate environment panel GOP members are also questioning whether EPA should have consulted with other agencies on the rule's potential adverse impacts on endangered species -- a review the agency says it has not done.
Much of the debate so far over the rule has centered on EPA's proposal that future coal-fired utilities must install some CCS. The agency says that based on CCS projects that received federal funding and other data, CCS is "adequately demonstrated" as a viable technology for coal-fired power plants, meeting a Clean Air Act threshold for requiring it.
Critics counter that CCS is a highly costly technology that is not widely available, and say the rule will effectively bar construction of new coal-fired plants in favor of natural gas and renewable power sources that emit less CO2.
EPA has long worked to rebut those criticisms and defend the CCS mandate, but the agency is now having to also address a broader range of attacks over the rule, such as concerns about its impacts on EOR.
EOR operators have "made it clear" they will not purchase CO2 from utilities if it requires them to transition from a "Class II" well to a "Class VI" well, several industry groups recently warned EPA. The EOR guidance on obtaining underground injection control permits for CO2 sequestration could "have the effect of eliminating CCS as a viable compliance option" for utilities trying to comply with the NSPS, industry says.
At a March 12 joint hearing of the energy and science subcommittees on the House Science Committee, Republicans also warned that CO2 reporting requirements that are built into the utility NSPS, along with related agency guidance on the long-term sequestration of CO2, could hurt those who have injected CO2 to increase oil and gas production for decades and do not want to face new reporting and monitoring requirements.
"It would destroy the very thing that you were bragging about, the fact is it would put a whole new regulatory burden just to utilize this CO2 byproduct of coal production," Rep. Dana Rohrabacher (R-CA) said in response to comments Rep. Marc Veasey (D-TX) made about the benefits the rule could generate for EOR operators.
GOP Concerns
The Republicans' concern is that the oil sector would refuse to purchase captured CO2 from the power sector because it would come attached with "subpart RR" reporting requirements that the agency included in the utility NSPS in an effort to ensure captured CO2 is not released back into the atmosphere. Key EOR operators have suggested they would avoid CO2 regulated under subpart RR because of its reporting and monitoring requirements.
Rep. Randy Weber (R-TX) said the CO2 reporting mandate would "inject" the agency into processes that have been previously regulated by the states and that the reporting requirements on EOR operators would "make it prohibitive for these companies to use CO2 from future coal-fired power plants." Weber cited a paper from Texas-based oil company Denbury Resources that said the proposed NSPS "will foreclose, not encourage" their use of utility CO2.
Meanwhile, other Republicans offered concerns about an agency guidance document that outlines the process through which "Class II" underground injection control wells used by EOR operators would transition to more stringent "Class VI" wells the agency created for the geologic sequestration of CO2. EPA released the guidance late last year, saying if EOR operators switched from producing oil to mostly storing CO2, they needed to transition to Class VI wells.
Rep. Ralph Hall (R-TX) said at the joint hearing that he was concerned that under the guidance, existing Class II wells could be reclassified as Class VI wells, which he said was creating an "unnecessary level of certainty and risk," and called on EPA to take "immediate action to rectify the situation" created by the guidance. Despite EPA creating the Class VI program years ago, the agency has yet to approve a permit under the program.
Other House lawmakers continue to target the CCS mandate in the rule, with House Energy and Commerce Committee Chair Fred Upton (R-MI) and other Republicans in a March 12 letter to EPA announcing an investigation into the agency's "decision-making process" related to carbon capture technologies in the rule.
In the letter, they ask the agency to provide by March 28 a large number of documents, including those related to the Energy Policy Act of 2005, a statute that Republicans say prevents the agency from basing its NSPS on key government-backed CCS projects like Southern Company's pending Kemper project in Mississippi.
EOR Operations
EPA and supporters of the utility NSPS downplay the concerns about the rule and its development, and doubt it will have a negative affect on EOR operators, as they say the oil sector's threats that it would refuse the utility sector's captured CO2 if it came with the reporting requirements are not likely to come to fruition.
David Hawkins, climate programs director for the Natural Resources Defense Council and a witness at the March 12 joint hearing, said he didn't think that requiring EOR operators to report on what happens to injected CO2 under subpart RR would cause them to "refuse this business, we just don't think that washes."
Hawkins also said it was reasonable for EPA to require companies that want to permanently store CO2 underground to face new reporting and monitoring requirements under the Class VI well program, which he expected would increase public confidence in carbon sequestration.
EPA's Janet McCabe, meanwhile, said in response to a question at the hearing about endangered species concerns Ã first raised publicly by Senate Environment & Public Works Committee Republicans in recent weeks -- that the agency has not consulted with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service on the rule, though she added, "We will comply with all applicable requirements including that one if it is deemed applicable here."
McCabe at the hearing defended the utility NSPS and touted the long history of the Clean Air Act in helping to advance pollution control technologies that had not been widely in use but the agency found were adequately demonstrated. EPA officials have long said the rule will provide certainty for investors and within the utility sector on the types of investments they need to make to be able to build coal-fired power plants.
"When these requirements are put in place, it does drive the development . . . it becomes widespread and the costs go down and becomes part of the mainstream," McCabe said. -- Chris Knight (cknight@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>