<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-5WY1-DXHF-W4FH"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Zama Zamas on edge of danger</title><source>Sunday World (South Africa)</source><author>Boitumelo Tlhoaele</author><text><![CDATA[THREE illegal miners in Fochville have told Sunday World of the violence they face in their daily quest to make a living. A security guard who works in one of the mines in the west of Gauteng also described how men armed with AK-47s have rendered him and others around the mining fields powerless.
This comes after Sunday World reported recently that nine people died in one weekend at two informal settlements, Vuka Search and Mphahlwa Village, near the mining town. The three men, who did not want to be named, told of how they risked their lives to make up to R2000 a week from selling their gold dust to illegal dealers. During our visit two weeks ago, the men had stayed away from their daily activity because of tighter security measures now in place at Blyvoor. "It's tough lately because we can't work. The security guards are killing us, they're all over there," said one. A security guard, known only as Edward, who works for Western Deep Levels, confirmed the tighter security measures. Western Deep Levels is next to Blyvoor mine and is owned by Anglo Gold Ashanti. Edward said that because he worked so close to Blyvoor, he had witnessed a lot of "activity" at that mine. The security measures have forced the illegal miners, known as Zama Zamas or magomoshas in Fochville, to seek their fortunes elsewhere. "We now go to No 2 Shaft because we are here to try and make a living," said one. No 2 Shaft belongs to Sibanye Gold Mine, which lies behind the Vuka Search and Mphahlwa Village settlements. This mine is fully operational, unlike Blyvoor. James Wellsted, head of corporate affairs at Sibanye Gold, said they were aware of illegal mining taking place. "Sibanye Gold is affected with our Kloof Operation being targeted more intensely. [It is also] affected by regular intrusions by illegal miners on our surface areas such as surface rock dumps and tailings storage facilities." Wellsted said it appeared that the Zama Zamas were getting help from some of the mine's employees. "We have found to a smaller extent that employees are assisting illegal miners with safety equipment, food, medicine and batteries. We suspect that they also assist illegal miners to bring out amalgam or gold-bearing material." Wellsted said the Zama Zamas were part of larger syndicates . "We believe that illegal mining is a highly organised criminal activity and that illicit gold syndicates reach right into operations by compromising employees to assist," he said. Representatives of Blyvoor mine and Anglo Gold Ashanti could not be reached for comment. tlhoaeleb@sundayworld.co.za RISKY BUSINESS: Illegal miners in Fochville, in the west of Gauteng, say they risk their lives to make up to R2000 a week from selling their gold dust to illegal dealers. The mines are tightening security measures. Pictures: Tshepo Kekana
]]></text></news-item>