<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-NBB1-F05M-K0CK"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>JPMorgan China investment banking head to resign</title><source>New York Business Journal (New York, NY)</source><author>Staff</author><text><![CDATA[JPMorgan Chase & Co.'s chief executive of investment banking for China is resigning amid an investigation into the bank's hiring practices in Asia.
Fang Fang, 48, who also was vice chairman of investment banking in Asia, is retiring from JPMorgan (NYSE: JPM) after more than 12 years with the New York-based company, according to&nbsp; Bloomberg, citing an internal memo. Fang submitted his resignation last week, saying he wanted to spend more time with his family, sources told Bloomberg.
Fang was a key figure for U.S. investigators, who are looking into whether JPMorgan violated bribery laws by hiring people in Asia who were relatives of government officials. Investors were given e-mails written by Fang supporting the hiring of the son of the chairman of state-backed China Everbright Group,&nbsp; according to the Wall Street Journal.&nbsp;
In November, JPMorgan backed out of China Everbright Bank Co.'s Hong Kong $3 billion share sale because the investigation delayed an internal approval process, reports Bloomberg. In January, JPMorgan withdrew from Tianhe Chemicals Group's initial public offering due to questions over the company's previous employment of the daughter of Tianhe's chairman.
Fang joined JPMorgan in August 2001 and was a former vice president of Beijing Enterprises Holdings Ltd., an investment controlled by the government of China's capital, according to Bloomberg. He became head of JPMorgan's China investment-banking business in 2007 and was made vice chairman for Asia investment banking in 2009.&nbsp;
Frank Gong, vice chairman of JPMorgan's China investment banking, has been promoted to chairman, according to&nbsp; Reuters. Brian Gu and Jing Zhao will become co-heads of investment banking for China with Jing also continuing in her current role as head of the Financial Institutions Group for Emerging Asia.&nbsp;
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to New York Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>