<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-NBB1-F05M-K094"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>NSA reportedly hacked Chinese telecom giant Huawei's servers</title><source>Dallas Business Journal</source><author>Bill Hethcock</author><text><![CDATA[The U.S. National Security Agency hacked into telecom equipment maker Huawei Technologies servers and collected information to plant "back doors" on equipment from the Chinese networking manufacturer, according to reports published over the weekend.
Huawei's U.S. headquarters are in Plano. Bill Plummer, Huawei's vice-president of external affairs, said in a phone interview with the Dallas Business Journal that the company did not know it was an NSA target, and is seeking to confirm whether the activities alleged on the part of the NSA have taken place.
"To the extent that there's truth to it, and we're still trying to find out what's happening, Huawei certainly objects to any entity that steals proprietary information to then use to exploit other networks," Plummer said.
Huawei also sent a statement to the Dallas Business Journal saying the security of its corporate network and products are the company's highest priorities.
"Corporate networks are under constant probe and attack from different sources - such is the status quo in today's digital age," Huawei's statement says. "Huawei disagrees with all activities that threaten the security of networks and is willing to work with all governments, industry stakeholders and customers, in an open and transparent manner, to jointly address the global challenge of network security.
Huawei has for years faced opposition in the United States, where members of Congress have expressed concern that the company is too closely aligned with the Chinese government, posing a security risk. U.S. officials have contended that China's People's Liberation Army works with manufacturers and hacking groups to spy on U.S. companies and government agencies.
Documents leaked by former U.S. intelligence contractor Edward Snowden since last June have shown that the NSA has conducted surveillance of its own. New reports over the weekend from The New York Times based on documents leaked by Snowden indicate the NSA succeeded in penetrating equipment at Huawei's Shenzhen, China, headquarters as part of a plan to monitor the company's networking equipment worldwide.
The goal was to connect the alleged links between Huawei and the PLA, and to put "back doors" on Huawei equipment sold worldwide, according to the Times.
Covert operations against Huawei go as far back as 2007, the Times report said. The NSA also monitored communications of Huawei executives, the report said.
The NSA issued a statement in an attempt to distinguish its surveillance activities from those of China.
"We do not use foreign intelligence capabilities to steal the trade secrets of foreign companies on behalf of - or give intelligence we collect to - U.S. companies to enhance their international competitiveness or increase their bottom line," the NSA said in an emailed statement to news outlets on Sunday.
"It is important to note the overlay of law, regulation, policy, procedure, technical safeguards, training, culture, and ethos in the use of such tools; all of these things govern how NSA deploys various foreign intelligence techniques to help defend the nation," the NSA statement said.
Plummer told the DBJ that "the revelations of the last nine months have resulted in a rather alarming deficit of trust in global networks and data integrity."
"It is time now for information technology industry leaders to come together and set standards to raise the security bar across the industry ...," Plummer said. "We need to restore trust before the very fabric of the information society in which you and I live and work unravels."
"We're at a point now where this is not just about Huawei," Plummer said. "This is about the entire industry, and each successive revelation is one more chink in the armor of trust."
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Dallas Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>