<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-TT81-DXKP-J4YM"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>In the Hot Seat: More budget hearings</title><source>Washington Post BlogsIn the Loop</source><author>Colby Itkowitz</author><text><![CDATA[Congress is back from recess, and lawmakers will resume their round of Fiscal 2015 budget and appropriations hearings. As debate over a U.S. aid package to Ukraine is hashed out on the House and Senate floors this week, Defense Department officials will testify about military spending at hearings in both chambers. This week will also feature appearances by cabinet secretaries such as Veterans Affairs Secretary Eric Shinseki and Interior Secretary Sally Jewell.
SENATE
Tuesday, March 25
Who: Veterans Affairs Secretary Eric Shinseki Where: Senate Appropriations subcommittee on military construction, veterans affairs Why: 2015 appropriations
Who: Energy Information Administration Administrator Adam Sieminski Where: Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee Why: Reversing energy imports and job exports
Wednesday, March 26
Who: Secretary of the Navy Ray Mabus Where: Senate Appropriations subcommittee on defense Why: 2015 appropriations
Who: Interior Secretary Sally Jewell Where: Senate Appropriations subcommittee on interior, environment Why: 2015 appropriations
Who: Agriculture Secretary Tom Vilsack Where: Senate Appropriations subcommittee on agriculture, rural development, FDA Why: 2015 appropriations
Who: Environmental Protection Agency Administrator Gina McCarthy Where: Senate Environment and Public Works Committee Why: Fiscal 2015 budget
Who: Defense undersecretary Robert F. Hale Where: Senate Armed Services subcommittee on personnel Why: 2015 budget for military and civilian personnel
Who: Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern affairs Anne Patterson Where: Senate Foreign Relations Committee Why: U.S. policy on Syria
Who: Federal Trade Commission Chairwoman Edith Ramirez Where: Senate Commerce, Science and Transportation Committee Why: Protecting consumers' personal data
Thursday, March 27
Who: Secretary of Navy Ray Mabus Where: Senate Armed Services Committee Why: Authorization of defense programs
HOUSE
Tuesday, March 25
Who: Secretary of the Army John McHugh Where: House Armed Services Committee Why: Authorization of defense programs
Who: Transportation Security Administration Administrator John Pistole Where: House Appropriations subcommittee on homeland security Why: 2015 appropriations
Who: Secretary of the Navy Ray Mabus Where: House Appropriations subcommittee on defense Why: 2015 appropriations
Who: FEMA Administrator Craig Fugate Where: House Homeland Security subcommittee on emergency preparedness, response and communications Why: Fiscal 2015 Budget
Who: Interior Secretary Sally Jewell Where: House Appropriations subcommittee on interior, environment Why: 2015 appropriations
Wednesday, March 26
Who: Secretary of the Air Force Deborah Lee James Where: House Appropriations subcommittee on defense Why: 2015 appropriations
Who: National Institutes of Health Director Francis S. Collins Where: House Appropriations subcommittee on labor, health and human services, education Why: Biomedical research
Who: FEMA Administrator Craig Fugate Where: House Appropriations subcommittee on homeland security Why: 2015 appropriations
Thursday, March 27
Who: U.S. Army Secretary John M. McHugh Where: House Appropriations subcommittee on defense Why: 2015 appropriations
Who: Environmental Protection Agency Administrator Gina McCarthy Where: House Appropriations subcommittee on interior, environment Why: 2015 appropriations
Who: Veterans Affairs Secretary Eric Shinseki Where: House Appropriations subcommittee on military construction, veterans affairs Why: 2015 appropriations
]]></text></news-item>