<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-5H01-F125-10VX"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Law enforcement 'hyper-vigilant' in efforts to prevent meth epidemic</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Crystal meth use in Alberta is trending upward, but the epidemic feared by many when the drug first started appearing in the province has never materialized.
Despite a recent uptick, fewer addicts are reporting crystal meth use than 10 years ago, when easy access to the legal ingredients used to manufacture meth helped it spread rapidly through parts of the U.S. Authorities feared the same thing would happen here and moved to tighten controls on precursor substances, resulting in far fewer illegal meth labs in Alberta than there were a decade ago.
"We were fortunate to learn from what was happening in the States," said Sgt. Lorne Adamitz of the RCMP's serious organized crime unit in Calgary. "We took significant efforts to jump ahead of this."
In a five-year period between 2009 and 2013, the RCMP in Alberta responded to 12 illegal drug labs - eight of which were making meth.
The situation was more serious in 2002, when the RCMP in Alberta responded to 11 sites where someone was cooking crystal meth or had dumped toxic waste from a meth lab. The Mounties recorded nine meth lab calls the next year, in 2003.
While some of the cook operations were so-called "mom and pop" labs in homes, sheds or garages, some were "superlabs" capable of producing multiple kilograms of the drug in a single batch.
The trend was fuelled by a lack of controls on the stimulant ephedrine and its synthetic form, pseudoephedrine.
The stimulants have legal uses - particularly in cold medications - but can be made into crystal meth through a series of chemical reactions.
At the time, organized crime groups imported bulk quantities of ephedrine and pseudoephedrine from countries such as China and India with little scrutiny.
Mom-and-pop meth cooks, meanwhile, were getting their supply by buying or stealing large quantities of cold medication from stores.
From there, a cook can use a combination of household solvents and legally-bought chemicals to convert ephedrine and pseudoephedrine to meth.
In the early 2000s, authorities moved to stop these otherwise legal precursors from being diverted into meth production.
At the federal level, Health Canada introduced regulations requiring a licence to import or export bulk quantities of ephedrine and pseudoephedrine, as well as chemicals involved in making meth, such as hydriotic acid and red phosphorus. In Alberta, the provincial government required any cold medications with ephedrine or pseudoephedrine as its main ingredient to be moved behind pharmacy counters.
At the same time, authorities targeted workers in pharmacies, other retailers and the petrochemical industry with public awareness campaigns aimed at getting them to spot suspicious purchases and prevent theft of precursors.
"We put a full-court press on the issue," Adamitz said.
There may be far fewer meth labs in Alberta, but the drug is still a concern for police and workers who help addicts.
Crystal meth is highly addictive, and prolonged use has a number of dramatic physiological and psychological effects.
A binging meth user can stay awake for days, which not only places mounting stress on their bodies, but can lead to paranoia and psychosis as well.
"There's a lot more psychological damage," said Mark Cherrington, a veteran Edmonton youth worker.
Recent statistics from Alberta Health Services suggest the number of meth addicts is on the rise again.
In 2012-13, 2,621 adult clients seeking treatment reported using meth in the previous 12 months.
The number is higher than the annual average of 1,877 during the previous four years - but remains lower than 10 years ago.
In 2005, 2,912 adult treatment clients reported meth use in the previous year.
Meth use among younger people is on the rise as well, with 1,116 AHS treatment clients between 12 and 24 years old reporting meth use. The average during the previous four years was 767 clients in that age bracket.
"The use is up and it has been fairly parallel to crack cocaine," said Cherrington.
Although the number of young people reporting meth use is up, Cherrington observed the trend is more of a resurgence than a new peak.
Statistics from 2005 bear out his observation: in that year, 1,008 provincial treatment clients under the age of 18 reported meth use. That number isn't much lower than the 1,116 clients who reported using meth in the much larger 12 to 24 age group in 2012-13.
On the streets, police are encountering meth more frequently but still not in nearly the same quantities as marijuana and cocaine.
A provincial umbrella agency combining city police and the RCMP, Alberta Law Enforcement Response Teams, seized 7.5 kilograms of meth throughout the province in 2012-13 - a huge increase over 1.2 kilograms it found the previous year.
In comparison, ALERT seized 44 kilograms of cocaine, along with 267 kilograms of harvested marijuana and more than 36,000 marijuana plants in 2012-13.
The small number of lab busts demonstrate made-in-Alberta meth hasn't disappeared, but there's a consensus a lot of it is coming from elsewhere - particularly Mexico, where drug cartels make it in largescale labs.
"With the quality of methamphetamine we've seen, it was probably not manufactured locally and came from somewhere internationally," said StaffSgt. Martin Schiavetta of ALERT.
And federal licensing requirements haven't stopped ephedrine and pseudoephedrine from being diverted to meth production. With its coastline and remote border areas, B.C. is a destination for smuggled precursors that in turn supply illegal labs in that province, said Adamitz.
Even though the number of meth labs in Alberta has shrunk significantly over the years, Adamitz said they continue to pose a danger.
Making meth involves highly flammable and toxic chemicals, putting anyone nearby in jeopardy of being hurt by explosions, fires or exposure to harmful substances.
"We have to remain hyper-vigilant.
Even the smallest (labs) pose a significant, significant risk," Adamitz said.
jvanrassel@calgaryherald.com( mailto:jvanrassel@calgaryherald.com )( mailto:jvanrassel@calgaryherald.com ) Twitt er.com/JasonvanRassel
© Copyright (c) The Calgary Herald
]]></text></news-item>