<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-RV71-DYTB-Y46W"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Colombia leads LatAm environmental conflicts</title><source>Business News Americas - English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Colombia is the Latin American country with the highest number of environmental conflicts, followed by Brazil and Ecuador, according to a report that tracks environmental conflicts on issues ranging from fracking to mega-infrastructure projects.
The Environmental Justice Organisations, Liabilities and Trade (EJOLT) project, a European Union-funded initiative, has published a global atlas detailing 1,000 environmental conflicts around the world, with Latin America home to nearly one third of the disputes.
Colombia leads the regional ranking with 72 conflicts, landing in second place worldwide after India.
In Colombia, nearly half of the conflicts are related to coal and gold mining, with some 2.2% of the country's land involved in disputes of some kind. Gold mining in Dagua river and a lawsuit against oil and gas company BP alleging that the company had caused severe environmental damage are among the country's numerous conflicts.
Brazil, Latin America's largest economy, came in second place with 58 conflicts associated with the expansion of farming, mining, hydro power and oil exploration in the highland and coastal regions. Conflicts have also arisen between local communities and project developers over the construction of highways and railways.
"The atlas illustrates how ecological conflicts are increasing around the world, driven by material demands fed primarily by the rich and middle class subsections of the global population," said project coordinator Joan Martínez-Alier, a professor at the Universitat Autónoma de Barcelona.
Ecuador, Argentina, Peru and Chile also appear on the list with 30 or more open conflicts each.
In Ecuador, conflicts covered by the report relate to the production of commodities such as banana and shrimp, although the most controversial dispute regards a series of lawsuits brought against oil company Chevron alleging severe environmental contamination of land.
In Peru, disputes are focused on mining projects, including the US$4.8bn gold-copper project Minas Conga, which was halted after protests.
In Chile, meanwhile, one of the most noteworthy conflicts involved Barrick Gold's US$8.5bn gold-copper mine project Pascua Lama and its potential impact on glaciers.
http://www.bnamericas.com/story.xsql?id_sector=4&id_noticia=641691&Tx_idioma=I&source=
]]></text></news-item>