<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-RG41-F08V-64JN"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Christie, unions fight ongoing battle at town halls  Protesters seize on bridge scandal as chance to bring up long-held concerns </title><source>The Star-Ledger (Newark, New Jersey)</source><author>Matt Friedman, STAR-LEDGER STAFF</author><text><![CDATA[After protesters had interrupted his previous town hall meeting, Gov. Chris Christie was ready for the dozen or so who showed up last week in South River.
"Well, congratulations," Christie told the town hall crowd. "You have now seen the latest gift given to you by the public sector unions in the state of New Jersey."
Since January, when the George Washington Bridge scandal brought crisis to the high-flying Christie and his poll numbers began to plummet, a coalition of labor unions, liberal interest groups and college students have sprung into action and have followed the governor virtually everywhere he's gone in New Jersey.
They've stood outside town halls with placards, and infiltrated the events -- long a target of critics who have called them thinly veiled political rallies aimed more at helping Christie's career than answering constituents' questions.
They've protested at the George Washington Bridge and filed an ethics complaint against Christie confidant David Samson, the chairman of the Port Authority.
While the group of protesters is diverse, public-sector unions -- who have long fought with Christie -- have played a key role in organizing them, keeping the bridge scandal in the news as the governor works to put it behind him.
"Bridgegate opened the floodgates and got a lot of our members really fired up about what was going on," said Analilia Mejia, executive director of the New Jersey Working Family Alliance, which has played a lead role in the protests. "We've had this critique of the governor. His policy budget. Bullying and yelling at teachers and regular New Jerseyans for years."
The alliance, founded in 2007, includes 12 member groups, according to its website. Ten are labor unions, including the New Jersey Education Association, the largest public workers union in the state, and several locals of the Communications Workers of America, the dominant state workers union.
But Mejia said the alliance isn't just speaking for the unions, and that her organization has 40,000 individual members.
"Our intent is to promote and protect the rights of regular working families," Mejia said. "Our interest is to push to help regular New Jerseyans, who don't have access to high-priced lobbyists, have their voice, to be heard. To have the public interest taken into account."
Mejia and others behind the protests said that Bridgegate has put Christie under new scrutiny, giving them a louder bullhorn to talk about their longtime grievances on issues ranging from health care to Sandy recovery to judicial independence.
"We felt that because he's been so unaccountable, and because he hasn't made himself available to the average people we represent, or even to the press, these hearings were an opportunity to have our voices heard -- whether it's us directly or our members," said Phyllis Salowe-Kaye, executive director of New Jersey Citizen Action, a liberal advocacy group that is a member of the New Jersey Working Families Alliance.
PENSION CUTS
At least one political analyst thinks even more is at stake. Patrick Murray, a pollster at Monmouth University, noted that Christie, in his own attempt to change the conversation from Bridgegate, proposed further cutbacks to pension benefits for public workers despite spending the last three years trumpeting the effectiveness of revisions he and the Democrat-led Legislature pushed through in 2011. The protests make it more difficult for Christie to move beyond the bridge scandal, which has reduced his poll numbers and, with them, his political influence.
"The potential threats to pensions is really what these protesters are concerned about," Murray said. "They know he's in a weaker position as long as the cloud of Bridgegate hangs over him -- particularly when he proposes cuts to pensions, to make sure he's in a weaker position."
Asked for comment on the protests, Christie spokesman Kevin Roberts referred to the governor's words at the South River town hall, when the governor called the protests a "new and recent phenomenon "¦ brought to you by the Communication Workers of America."
"The state workers union has decided that one of their goals and missions in life is to recruit people to come here to the town hall meeting, and when you begin to ask questions they will stand up and start to scream and yell over you and over me," Christie said.
"They have spent tens of millions of dollars over the last four-and-a-half years trying to defeat me at the polls in 2009, tried to defeat me again at the polls in 2013, and they are zero for two," he said.
CHRISTIE FANS
But protesters say the reason Christie's town halls haven't seen much dissent is because they're often held in areas friendly to the Republican governor, naturally attract Christie fans and are always held during work hours when many of Christie's critics -- including state workers and teachers -- can't easily attend.
"We have lots and lots of members who aren't able to take off work at 11 in the morning and go say how they feel," said Salowe-Kaye.
Many of the protesters have been college students.
"These town halls are sort of political theater staged to make Christie look as good as he can. He always picks the same sort of people," said David Bedford, secretary of the Rutgers Student Union, who has taken part in some of the protests. "These town halls are typically in conservative, dominantly white towns during hours working people can't access."
Bedford said his group has coordinated with unions, in person and in conference calls, ahead of the town hall events. But he said the unions haven't always taken the lead, and that the students have sometimes been the driving force in organizing demonstrations.
Bedford said during the first couple of town halls, those likely to ask Christie tough questions were not being called on. So they decided to start interrupting and shouting questions.
"There's essentially two options here: We could be disruptive and flip the table on them, or sit at the table and play their game, with the resources they provide," Bedford said. "You're less likely to receive political backlash, but you're also less likely to get political attention."
Matt Friedman: (609) 989-0324 or mfriedman@starledger.com
]]></text></news-item>