<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-4511-JBXT-N0DW"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Residents rebuff mega gas stations</title><source>Tribune-Review (Greensburg, PA)</source><author>by TORY N. PARRISH</author><text><![CDATA[The gas station of yesterday is a shell of what it looks like today.
Gas stations are twice the size, with more pumps; some have full-service restaurants, small grocery stores and 24-hour operations.
More convenience stores sell gas, too "” a 14.2 percent increase to 126,658 locations from 2005 to 2014, according to the National Association for Convenience & Fuel Retailing in Alexandria, Va.
In some communities, these mega stations are hang-out spots for the post-nightclub crowd "” and they are attracting opposition in the planning stages from residents who are leery of more traffic, noise, crime and bright lights.
"It's unneeded. It's unwanted. It's unnecessary in this district," Moon resident Melissa Church said recently during a public hearing about Enon, Ohio-based Speedway LLC's proposal to build a gas station in an area zoned for residences and business.
She echoed sentiments voiced by residents in Delmont and Unity, who particularly opposed diesel-fuel pumps.
In Delmont, council rejected plans for a Speedway on Route 66 when residents criticized building a "truck stop" near homes on West Pittsburgh Street. The company has an outstanding zoning request.
Plans for a Speedway in Unity were pulled when more than 600 residents signed petitions opposing its location on Route 30 near the Inn at Mountain View.
"The convenience store model does nothing to beautify the gateway to our community," said David Nelson, president of the Charter Oak Civic Association.
Taking a stand
Push-back is not uncommon in projects of substantial size that affect neighborhoods, said John Rice, a land-use attorney with Grim Biehn & Thatcher in Bucks County.
What is changing is that people are pushing back more often, he said.
"They live there. That's the biggest investment they have," he said.
Church and her husband are among about 30 residents who hired an attorney to fight the Speedway gas station, which would have a 3,900-square-foot store and six fuel pumps. Moon supervisors will decide by May 9 whether to approve it.
A gas station that size, according to industry estimates, can be expected to generate about 3,000 total daily trips "” 1,500 entering and 1,500 exiting, PennDOT spokesman Steve Cowan said.
Fuel companies are getting more community push-back as gas stations move into more developed areas, said municipal planner Brian O'Leary, president of the American Planning Association's Pennsylvania chapter.
In towns with commercial zoning, municipal officials can require redesigns to restrict hours of operation, noise and other areas of concern, he said.
"I'd say in the majority of cases we've seen here that involve rezoning, the rezonings have gone through despite neighbor opposition," O'Leary said.
Some residents and business owners in Marshall claimed victory in January when the zoning hearing board denied O'Hara-based Giant Eagle Inc. three variances needed to convert a Kings Family Restaurant into a GetGo gas station.
Giant Eagle filed an appeal in Allegheny County Common Pleas Court on Friday. The company's attorney, William Sittig, declined to comment.
In 2012, some Forest Hills church members and neighbors objected to the potential traffic and disruption of a proposed GetGo gas station. The church refused to sell some of its parking lot to Giant Eagle.
Giant Eagle will open its first GetGo station in Indianapolis in 2015, spokesman Dick Roberts said. New GetGo locations are about 5,500 square feet and typically offer 16 fuel pumps and a variety of fresh food, Roberts said. "We work closely with local officials and other community stakeholders when planning a new store," he said.
Marathon Petroleum Corp. operates 1,480 Speedway stores in nine states, and all include gas stations. The company's growth strategy includes expanding into new contiguous markets, spokesman Jamal Kheiry said.
The company plans to build a 3,900-square-foot convenience station with 16 pumps on Route 130 in Penn Township near the Pleasant Valley Road intersection.
"We are actively acquiring real estate in Western Pennsylvania and Tennessee to be in a position to accelerate the pace of growth in these markets over the next several years," Kheiry said.
Money-makers
Gas stations are branching out because sales of in-store products are more profitable than gas sales, according to Santa Monica, Calif.-based market research firm IBISWorld Inc.
To make money from fuel sales, stations have to charge more per gallon or sell more gas at a lower profit, which is where having many fuel pumps comes into play, said Jeff Lenard, spokesman for the National Association for Convenience & Fuel Retailing.
People sometimes push back against new stores because of misconceptions about their impact on crime, noise, traffic and neighborhood tranquility, Lenard said.
"In a lot of these (public) hearings, the what-ifs play very well," Lenard said.
Tory N. Parrish is a staff writer for Trib Total Media.
]]></text></news-item>