<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-GKK1-JD46-G153"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>The fading power of labour unions</title><source>MINT</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[New Delhi, March 24 -- Last week witnessed the temporary lockout of two Toyota Kirloskar plants in Bidadi in Karnataka following wage disputes between the company's management and the labour union. With the management's decision on Thursday to end the lockout-imposed earlier citing worries over the safety of workers and management personnel-fears of violence have allayed. For the moment, the management has gained the upper hand by suspending 17 employees and not giving into the wage demands of the union. Quite naturally, the Toyota episode has brought back memories of the outburst of violence during labour disputes in the recent past.
In 2012, violence at Maruti's plant at Manesar led to the death of a member of the company's management. In 2009, a senior executive of Pricol in Coimbatore was killed in a similar bout of violence following the suspension of a group of workers. Not to forget the murder of the chief executive officer of the Indian unit of Graziano Trasmissioni in 2008 by employees who were fired. While white-collared workers have clearly been at the receiving end of violence in recent years, it has not been a clear one-way affair. In 2005, labour protests at a Honda plant in Gurgaon demanding the reinstatement of fired workers led to police excess on protesting workers. What is the reason for the spurt in violent industrial action in recent years? Two trends are visible on the labour front. One, the number of industrial disputes has fallen from over 1,800 (strikes and lockouts) in 1990-a year before the advent of reforms-to 345 in 2009, the year for which the Labour Bureau has published authoritative statistics. Two, the increasing number of contract labourers, in contrast to regular, unionized, workers employed in the private sector. Today, contract employees account for about 34% of the total workforce in India's top publicly traded companies that contribute to almost two-thirds of the total market capitalization of all listed companies. The share of contract workers in the total workforce is as high as 47% in the automobile sector which has witnessed the most labour-related disturbance in recent years. The preference of companies to employ contract labour is explained by India's restrictive labour laws. One such law is the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 that requires both compensation and prior permission from the government for retrenchment of workers in firms employing more than one hundred workmen. This, in turn, has led companies to hire labour through contractors, helping to keep many of their employees out of the regular payroll, thus escaping the provisions of the Act. Effectively, contract labour provided companies with the flexibility to hire or fire based on business conditions, while undercutting the power of the unions. This presented companies with a luxury they could not afford otherwise, but more importantly it brought into focus the relationship between regular and contract workers. Contract workers could cooperate-or effectively unionize-with regular workers and demand higher wages and benefits. Or they could compete with regular workers, forcing them to perform better, accept lower wages, or simply perish. During the Maruti episode, the demand to offer regular employment to contract workers formed an important part of the agenda of protesting workers. Both regular and contract workers colluded to take on the management. But in the Toyota episode, there does not appear to be the same kind of solidarity. In fact, according to some Toyota union members, the management continued to operate the plant during the lockout with the aid of contract workers-probably suggesting an undercutting of the power of the Toyota union. The advent of competition in the labour market with the entry of contract labour has coincided with greater uncertainty in the power of the unions. While there have been notable episodes of violence-some of which have also involved contract workers joining hands with the union-during this period, Toyota's story points to an underlying story of decreasing labour union power in a relatively open labour market. The greater-than-average prevalence of contract labour in the automobile sector is one reason for the conflict between the unions-who fear a decline in the bargaining power from an influx of contract workers-and managements. The relatively lower number of industrial disputes in other sectors indicates the sharpness of this conflict. Is India in urgent need of labour reforms? Tell us at views@livemint.com Published by HT Syndication with permission from MINT. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>