<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-XDK1-DYR7-T3GM"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Luna Gold Announces the Retirement of John Blake and the Appointment of Geoff Chater to the Position of President &amp; CEO</title><source>Marketwired</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Luna Gold Corp. (TSX:LGC) (LMA:LGC) (OTCQX:LGCUF) ("Luna" or the "Company") today announced the retirement of John Blake from the positions of President and CEO of Luna Gold effective March 20, 2014. Concurrently, the Company announced the appointment of Geoff Chater as President and CEO. Mr. Chater is a member of the Board of Directors.
"John will leave a lasting legacy at Luna. During his tenure gold production has grown from 15,800 ounces in 2010 to 79,229 ounces in 2013. Under his direction Luna has become a profitable gold producer and he has spearheaded the current expansion of the Aurizona mine and processing facility. Perhaps his most important contribution to Luna is the establishment of a strong management team who will continue the momentum created by John. We wish John the best in his retirement and all his future endeavours." commented Keith Hulley, Chairman of Luna Gold.
"Geoff will bring new energy to the Company. Luna is entering a period of complex decision making related to the growth of the Aurizona gold mine, the development of the Aurizona brownfields gold endowment and the exploration of the Aurizona greenfields concessions. Geoff brings complementary skills and experience to the existing executive team and will lead the team in the execution of Luna's strategic plan." commented Luis (Lucho) Baertl, Director of Luna Gold.
Geoff Chater has been a member of the Luna Board of Directors since February, 2013. Geoff has a degree in geology from Texas Christian University. He has over 25 years of experience in the mineral exploration and mining industries, operating in North America, South America, Europe and Africa. He has spent the majority of his career as a liaison between public companies and the financial industry, in particular with analysts and institutional investors. He is the principal of Namron Advisors, a capital markets consultancy he founded in 1998 that provides advice related to corporate strategy, transaction related business development and capital markets relationship development, financing and communications. He has held positions with Eldorado Gold Corporation, First Quantum Minerals, Fairbanks Gold, Greystar Resources, Ivanhoe Capital Corporation and Valley High Ventures. He is currently a Director of Great Panther Silver Ltd, Lara Exploration Ltd., and Reservoir Minerals Inc.
About Luna Gold Corp.
Luna is a gold production company engaged in the operation, expansion, and exploration of gold projects in Brazil.
On behalf of the Board of Directors
LUNA GOLD CORP.
Keith Hulley, Chairman of the Board
Website: www.lunagold.com
Forward-Looking Statements
This release contains certain "forward looking statements" and certain "forward looking information" as defined under applicable Canadian and U.S. securities laws. Forward-looking statements can generally be identified by the use of forward-looking terminology such as "may", "will", "expect", "intend", "estimate", "anticipate", "believe", "continue", "plans" or similar terminology. Forward-looking statements include, but are not limited to, statements with respect to future gold production and/or the results of analysis on gold production. Forward-looking statements are based on forecasts of future results, estimates of amounts not yet determinable and assumptions that while believed by management to be reasonable, are inherently subject to significant business, economic and competitive uncertainties and contingencies. Forward-looking statements are subject to various risks and uncertainties concerning the specific factors identified in Luna Gold Corp.'s periodic filings with Canadian Securities Regulators. These factors include the inherent risks involved in the exploration and development of mineral properties, the uncertainties involved in interpreting drill results and other exploration data, the potential for delays in exploration or development activities, the geology, grade and continuity of mineral deposits, the possibility that future exploration, development or mining results will not be consistent with the Company's expectations, accidents, equipment breakdowns, title matters, labor disputes or other unanticipated difficulties with or interruptions in production and operations, fluctuating metal prices, unanticipated costs and expenses, uncertainties relating to the availability and costs of financing needed in the future, the inherent uncertainty of production and cost estimates and the potential for unexpected costs and expenses, commodity price fluctuations, currency fluctuations, regulatory restrictions, including environmental regulatory restrictions and liability, competition, loss of key employees, and other related risks and uncertainties. The Company undertakes no obligation to update forward-looking information except as required by applicable law. Such forward-looking information represents management's best judgment based on information currently available. No forward-looking statement can be guaranteed and actual future results may vary materially. Accordingly, readers are advised not to place undue reliance on forward-looking statements or information.
SOURCE: Luna Gold Corp.
]]></text></news-item>