<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-NBB1-F05M-K06J"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Talks with county health department take on new urgency for Shenango Inc.</title><source>Pittsburgh Business Times</source><author>Justine Coyne</author><text><![CDATA[The owner of the Shenango Inc. coke battery plant on Neville Island said it expects&nbsp;to reach an agreement with the Allegheny County Department of Health in the next few weeks on additional steps that need to be taken to bring down emissions.
On Feb. 6, the Group Against Smog and Pollution issued a 60-day notice of intent to sue over the plant, citing violations of the Federal Clean Air Act and county health code violations. And on March 21, a 36-member coalition of residents, organizations and business owners sent a letter to Allegheny County Health Department Director Karen Hacker to comply with federal regulations or close the plant.
"At the time GASP issued the 60-day notice, DTE was already talking with the county about new steps the plant needs to take to improve emissions levels," said&nbsp;Randi Berris, a&nbsp;spokeswoman for DTE Energy, which owns the plant. "Since then, the negotiations with the county have taken on new urgency."
When DTE purchased the plant in 2008, the Ann Arbor, Mich.-based energy company inherited a 30-year history of air-pollution problems that have resulted in multiple federal and county consent orders. The facility has 26 coke ovens and 150 employees.
In its notice of intent, GASP cited that a review of recent Shenango compliance reports covering a 432-day period that show that on at least 330 of those days, one or more air violations occurred at the facility. There is no context provided for how long the plant was in violation on those days.
Acknowledging there is still work to do, Berris said DTE's goal is to be 100 percent compliant and the company is working to get the operation to that level as quickly as possible. In the past five years, DTE has&nbsp; significantly reduced visible emissions from the facility's combustion stack, using ceramic welding to seal oven wall joints.
Since 2010, when the plant contributed to Avalon having the dirtiest air in Allegheny County, Berris cited that the county's Avalon air monitor has been in compliance for the last three years.
"The air is better than it was a few years ago, but we are continuing to make improvements," she said.
Berris said the company is continuing to upgrade the facility and construction should speed up in the spring.&nbsp;
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Pittsburgh Business Times for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>