<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-5WY1-DXHF-W4FJ"><date>2014-03-23</date><title>Bidvest denies claims of fraud</title><source>Sunday World (South Africa)</source><author>Nkululeko Ncana</author><text><![CDATA[Company says job losses were inevitable, not due to merger THE Bidvest Group has been accused of acting in bad faith and possibly defrauding the Competition Tribunal as one of its subsidiaries intends on shedding 72 jobs.
Sunday World has learnt that the Competition Tribunal unconditionally approved the merger between Bidvest Group Limited and Mvelaserve in November based on undertakings from the two companies that no jobs would be lost as a result. But in an internal memorandum last week, Stamford (Pty) Ltd and Sprint Packaging - subsidiaries of Mvelaserve and Bidvest, respectively - announced that they were being forced to lay off 72 employees. Stamford and Sprint Packaging were merged under Bidvest Paperplus last month. The Bidvest Group, with over 130000 employees on four continents, is the largest food service business outside North America and has its hand in several other areas of business. The company, which also owns Premier Soccer League club Bidvest Wits, posted a revenue of R153-billion last year. The move by Bidvest Paperplus has outraged affected employees. In his memorandum, Bidvest Paperplus managing director Theo Ferreira said Stamford Johannesburg "has been making financial losses for a considerable period of time and this is a major focus area for the merged business". He also announced that they had lost distribution services of a massive retail chain. When approving the merger, the Competition Tribunal said: "The merging parties confirmed that the proposed transaction will not have any adverse impact on employment and that no retrenchments will result from the proposed transaction." Bidvest Group chief executive Brian Joffe told Sunday World that the Competition Tribunal was notified of Stamford's intention to shed jobs. "The commission and tribunal were fully aware of certain retrenchments at the head offices of Mvelaserve as a result of the merger and approved those. "They were also aware of significant financial difficulties at the Stamford Sales business of Mvelaserve. "At the time the merger was notified to the commission [during June last year] the commission was informed of financial difficulties being experienced within Stamford Sales. "The merging parties informed the commission that Stamford had, already then, taken the decision to close inland operations and focus on coastal regions." said Joffe. He said retrenchments were always a last resort and that the company had tried to save as many jobs as possible. Sunday World has learnt that a possible case of fraud will be made to the Competition Commission to investigate whether Bidvest and Mvelaserve had deliberately misled the Competition Tribunal to push the merger through, knowing well that people might lose their jobs. ncanan@sundayworld.co.za FACED WITH QUESTIONS: Bidvest Group chief executive Brian Joffe says the Competition Tribunal was notified of Stamford's intention to shed jobs. Picture: Raymond Preston
]]></text></news-item>