<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-4K01-DXX7-H50G"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>(2/3) Fourth Quarter and Full Year 2013 Financial and</title><source>Market News Publishing</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[SOUTHGOBI RESOURCES LTD ("SGQ-T") - (2/3) Fourth Quarter and Full Year 2013 Financial and - Operating Results
FINANCIAL POSITION AND LIQUIDITY
Liquidity and Capital Management
The Company has in place a planning, budgeting and forecasting process to help determine the funds required to support the Company's normal operations on an ongoing basis and its expansionary plans.
The Company anticipates that coal prices in China will remain under pressure in 2014, which will continue to impact the Company's margins and liquidity. Based on the Company's forecasts for the year ended December 31, 2014, the Company is unlikely to have sufficient capital resources and does not expect to generate sufficient cash flows from mining operations in order to satisfy its ongoing obligations and future contractual commitments, including cash interest payments due on the CIC convertible debenture. Therefore, the Company is actively seeking additional sources of financing to continue operating and meet its objectives.
The Company's consolidated financial statements have been prepared on a going concern basis which assumes that the Company will continue operating until at least December 31, 2014 and will be able to realize its assets and discharge its liabilities in the normal course of operations as they come due. While the Company is actively seeking additional sources of financing to continue operating and meet its objectives, there can be no assurance that such financing will be available on terms acceptable to the Company. If for any reason, the Company is unable to secure the additional sources of financing and continue as a going concern, then this could result in adjustments to the amounts and classifications of assets and liabilities in the Company's consolidated financial statements and such adjustments could be material.
While the Company intends to secure additional sources of financing as soon as possible, a continued delay in securing additional financing could ultimately result in an event of default of the $250.0 million CIC convertible debenture, which if not cured within applicable cure periods in accordance with the terms of such debenture, may result in the principal amount owing and all accrued and unpaid interest becoming immediately due and payable upon notice to the Company by CIC.
Cash Position and Liquidity
As at December 31, 2013, the Company had cash of $21.8 million compared to cash of $19.7 million and short term money market investments of $15.0 million for a total of $34.7 million in cash and money market investments as at December 31, 2012. Working capital (excess current assets over current liabilities) was $41.7 million as at December 31, 2013 compared to $120.4 million as at December 31, 2012. As at March 24, 2014, the Company had cash of $10.0X million.
As at December 31, 2013, the Company's gearing ratio was 0.19 (December 31, 2012: 0.14), which was calculated based on the Company's long term liabilities to total assets. As at December 31, 2013, the Company is not subject to any externally imposed capital requirements. 2013 Interest Payment Deferral
During the second quarter of 2013, the Company and the CIC mutually agreed upon a three month deferral of the convertible debenture semi-annual $7.9 million cash interest payment due on May 19, 2013. The Company and the CIC subsequently agreed to an additional deferral of one month, and the cash interest payment became due on September 19, 2013.
On September 19, 2013, the Company settled the $7.9 million amount, plus additional accrued interest of $0.2 million, as follows: -- The Company issued 1.8 million shares to the CIC for the November 19,
2012 1.6% share interest payment, where the number of common shares was
based on the 50-day volume-weighted average share price on November 19,
2012 of Cdn$2.16; -- In consideration of the common share issue, the CIC applied the $4.0
million in cash already paid by the Company in the first quarter of 2013
for the November 19, 2012 share interest payment against the amount due
on September 19, 2013; and -- The Company paid the remaining $4.1 million balance in cash.
The mutually agreed upon deferral of the cash interest payment, and subsequent settlement in cash and common shares of the Company, did not trigger an event of default and all other terms of the convertible debenture remain unchanged.
Mongolian IAAC Investigation
In the first quarter of 2013, the Company was subject to orders imposed by Mongolia's Independent Authority against Corruption (the "IAAC") which placed restrictions on certain of the Company's Mongolian assets. The orders were imposed on the Company in connection with the IAAC's investigation of the Company. The Mongolian State Investigation Office (the "SIA") also continues to enforce the orders on the Company.
The orders placing restrictions on certain of the Company's Mongolian assets could ultimately result in an event of default of the Company's CIC convertible debenture. Following a review by the Company and its advisers, it is the Company's view that this does not result in an event of default as defined under the CIC convertible debenture terms. However, if an event of default of the CIC convertible debenture occurs that remains uncured for ten business days, the principal amount owing and all accrued and unpaid interest will become immediately due and payable upon notice to the Company by CIC.
The orders relate to certain items of operating equipment and infrastructure and the Company's Mongolian bank accounts. The orders related to the operating equipment and infrastructure restricts the sale of these items; however, the orders do not restrict the use of these items in the Company's mining activities. The orders related to the Company's Mongolian bank accounts restrict the use of in-country funds. While the orders restrict the use of in-country funds pending outcome of the investigation, they are not expected to have any material impact on the Company's activities.
Ovoot Tolgoi Mine Impairment Analysis
Unchanged from the assessment made as at September 30, 2013, the Company determined that an indicator of impairment existed for its Ovoot Tolgoi Mine cash generating unit as at December 31, 2013. The impairment indicator was the continued weakness in the Company's share price during the fourth quarter of 2013 and the fact that the market capitalization of the Company, as at December 31, 2013, was less than the carrying value of its net assets.
Therefore, the Company conducted an impairment test whereby the carrying value of the Company's Ovoot Tolgoi Mine cash generating unit was compared to its "value in use" using a discounted future cash flow valuation model. The Company's Ovoot Tolgoi Mine cash generating unit carrying value was $416.6 million as at December 31, 2013.
Key estimates and assumptions incorporated in the valuation model included the following: -- Long term real selling price of $110 per tonne for semi-soft coking coal
FOB Australia; -- Life-of-mine coal production and operating costs; and -- A discount rate of 12.5% based on an analysis of market, country and
company specific factors
Key sensitivities in the valuation model are as follows: -- For each 1% increase/(decrease) in the long term real selling price of
semi-soft coking coal FOB Australia, the calculated fair value of the
cash generating unit increases/(decreases) by approximately
$34.0/($34.0) million; and -- For each 1% increase/(decrease) in the discount rate, the calculated
fair value of the cash generating unit (decreases)/increases by
approximately ($44.0)/$50.0 million.
The impairment analysis did not result in the identification of an impairment loss and no charge was required as at December 31, 2013. The Company believes that the estimates and assumptions incorporated in the impairment analysis are reasonable; however, the estimates and assumptions are subject to significant uncertainties and judgments.
REGULATORY ISSUES AND CONTINGENCIES
Regulatory Issues
Governmental and Regulatory Investigations
The Company is subject to investigations by the IAAC and the SIA regarding allegations against the Company and some of its former employees. The IAAC investigation concerns possible breaches of Mongolia's anti-corruption laws, while the SIA investigation concerns possible breaches of Mongolia's money laundering and taxation laws.
While the IAAC investigation into allegations of possible breaches of Mongolian anti-corruption laws has been suspended, the Company has not received formal notice that the IAAC investigation is completed. The IAAC has not formally accused any current or former Company employees of breach of Mongolia's anti-corruption laws.
A report issued by the experts appointed by the SIA on June 30, 2013 and again in January 2014 has recommended that the accusations of money laundering as alleged against the Company's three former employees be withdrawn. However, to date, the Company has not received notice or legal document confirming such withdrawal as recommended by the experts appointed by the SIA.
A third investigation ordered by the SIA and conducted by the National Forensic Center ("NFC") into alleged violations of Mongolian taxation law was concluded at the end of January 2014. The Company has received notice that the report with conclusions of the investigations by the NFC have been provided to the Prosecutor General of Mongolia. The Prosecutor General may undertake criminal actions against the three former employees for alleged violations of taxation laws and the Company may be held liable as "civil defendant" as a result of these alleged criminal actions. These actions could result in the investigation case being imminently transferred to a Court of Justice under the relevant Mongolian law. The likelihood or consequences of such an outcome or any civil action taken against the Company are uncertain and unclear at this time but could include financial or other penalties, which could be material, and which could have a material adverse effect on the Company.
The Company disputes and will vigorously defend itself against any civil or criminal actions. At this point, the three former employees remain designated as "accused" in connection with the allegations of tax evasion, and continue to be subject to a travel ban. The Company remains designated as a "civil defendant" in connection with the tax evasion allegations, and may potentially be held financially liable for the alleged criminal misconduct of its former employees under Mongolian Law.
The SIA also continues to enforce administrative restrictions, which were initially imposed by the IAAC investigation, on certain of the Company's Mongolian assets, including local bank accounts, in connection with its continuing investigation of these allegations. While the orders restrict the use of in-country funds pending the outcome of the investigation, they are not expected to have a material impact on the Company's activities in the short term, although they could create potential difficulties for the Company in the medium to long term. The Company will continue to take all appropriate steps to protect its ability to conduct its business activities in the ordinary course.
Internal Investigations
Through its Audit Committee (comprised solely of independent directors), the Company has conducted an internal investigation into possible breaches of law, internal corporate policies and codes of conduct arising from the allegations which have been raised. The Audit Committee has had the assistance of independent legal counsel in connection with its investigation.
The Chair of the Audit Committee has also participated in a tripartite committee, comprised of the Audit Committee Chairs of the Company and Turquoise Hill and a representative of Rio Tinto, which focused on the investigation of a number of those allegations, including possible violations of anti-corruption laws. Independent legal counsel and forensic accountants assisted this committee with its investigation. The tripartite committee substantially completed the investigative phase of its activities during the third quarter of 2013. The Company continues to cooperate with the IAAC, SIA and with Canadian and United States government and regulatory authorities that are monitoring the Mongolian investigations. It is possible that these authorities may subsequently conduct their own review or investigation or seek further information from the Company. Pending further reviews or questions from any of such government or regulatory authorities, the tripartite committee has been stood down and investigations have been paused.
The investigations referred to above could result in one or more Mongolian, Canadian, United States or other governmental or regulatory agencies taking civil or criminal action against the Company, its affiliates or its current or former employees. The likelihood or consequences of such an outcome are unclear at this time but could include financial or other penalties, which could be material, and which could have a material adverse effect on the Company.
The Company, through its Board of Directors and new management, has taken a number of steps to address issues noted during the investigations and to focus ongoing compliance by employees with all applicable laws, internal corporate policies and codes of conduct, and with the Company's disclosure controls and procedures and internal controls over financial reporting.
Withdrawal of Notice of Investment Dispute
On July 11, 2012, the Company announced that SGQ Coal Investment Pte. Ltd., a wholly-owned subsidiary of the Company that owns 100% of the Company's Mongolian operating subsidiary SouthGobi Sands LLC, filed a Notice of Investment Dispute on the Government of Mongolia pursuant to the Bilateral Investment Treaty between Singapore and Mongolia. The Company filed the Notice of Investment Dispute following a determination by management that they had exhausted all other possible means to resolve an ongoing investment dispute between SouthGobi Sands LLC and the Mongolian authorities.
The Notice of Investment Dispute principally concerned the failure by the Mineral Resources Authority of Mongolia ("MRAM") to execute the PMAs associated with certain exploration licenses of the Company pursuant to which valid PMA applications had been lodged in 2011. The areas covered by the valid PMA applications included the Zag Suuj Deposit and certain areas associated with the Soumber Deposit outside the existing mining license.
On August 22, 2013, the Company announced that it had withdrawn the Notice of Investment Dispute in recognition of the fact that the dispute was resolved following the grant of three PMAs on August 14, 2013 relating to the Zag Suuj Deposit and certain areas associated with the Soumber Deposit, and the earlier grant of a PMA on January 18, 2013 pertaining to the Soumber Deposit. Each of the PMAs was granted and executed by MRAM in accordance with Mongolian law.
Contingencies
Class Action Lawsuit
On or about January 6, 2014, Siskinds LLP, a Canadian law firm, filed a proposed securities class action (the "Ontario Action") against the Company, certain of its former senior officers and current directors, and its former auditors, Deloitte LLP, in the Ontario Superior Court of Justice in relation to the Company's restatement of financial statements as previously disclosed in the Company's public filings.
The plaintiff seeks leave to bring a claim under applicable Canadian securities legislation and seeks certification of a class action with respect to a class of persons who purchased shares of the Company between March 30, 2011 and November 7, 2013, alleging that the financial reporting of the Company during that period contained misrepresentations giving rise to liability at common law and under applicable Canadian securities legislation. The Ontario Action also seeks general damages against all defendants in the sum of Cdn$30 million, without particulars as to how such amount was determined, or such other amount that the Court deems appropriate. Assuming that leave is granted, the action is certified as a class proceeding, and there is a finding of liability, the actual quantum of damages will depend upon the evidence which is adduced in the court proceedings. Named in the Ontario Action as individual defendants are the Company's former Chief Executive Officer, Alexander Molyneux, the Company's former Chief Financial Officers, Messrs. Terry Krepiakevich and Matthew O'Kane, and the members of its Audit Committee, Messrs. Andre Deepwell, Pierre Lebel and Gordon Lancaster, each of whom held those positions during the period at issue.
The Company disputes and will vigorously defend itself against these claims through independent Canadian litigation counsel retained by the Company and the other defendants for this purpose. Due to the inherent uncertainties of litigation, it is not possible to predict the final outcome of the Ontario Action or determine the amount of any potential losses, if any. However, in the opinion of management of the Company, at December 31, 2013 a provision for this matter is not required.
PROCESSING INFRASTRUCTURE
Dry Coal Handling Facility
Following an extensive review that commenced in the fourth quarter of 2013, the Company concluded that it does not plan to either complete or use the DCHF at the Ovoot Tolgoi Mine in the foreseeable future. This conclusion constituted an indicator of impairment and the Company performed an impairment assessment over the DCHF. As a result of the impairment assessment, the Company recorded a $66.9 million non-cash impairment in other operating expenses to reduce the carrying value of the DCHF to its recoverable amount. The Company used a value in use cash flow model, with a discount rate of 10.4%, to estimate the recoverable amount. The total construction capital investment to date on the DCHF is $85.0 million and the DCHF had a carrying value of $78.1 million prior to the impairment assessment. Subsequent to the impairment charge, the DCHF has a carrying value of $11.2 million at December 31, 2013.
The first phase of the DCHF project comprised a coal rotary breaker intended to reduce screening costs and improve yield recoveries. On February 13, 2012, the Company announced the successful commissioning of the coal rotary breaker. The Ovoot Tolgoi Mine operations were curtailed during the second half of 2012 and resumed on March 22, 2013. The Company has not operated the coal rotary breaker since its announced commissioning. The second phase of the DCHF project included the installation of dry air separation modules and covered load out conveyors with fan stackers to take processed coals to stockpiles and enable more efficient blending. In 2012, the Company announced the suspension of the completion of the DCHF project to minimize uncommitted capital expenditures and preserve the Company's financial resources. On November 14, 2013, the Company announced that it was conducting a review of the DCHF project and its contribution to the Company's product strategy.
The review of the DCHF project was completed in the first quarter of 2014. The Company continues to focus on preserving its financial resources and has assessed, using updated operating cost assumptions and estimates, that it currently has the adequate equipment and capacity to efficiently meet its commercial objectives and execute its product strategy without the use of the DCHF. The use of mobile screens at stockpile areas closer to the pits has enabled the Company to realize a cost benefit compared to hauling the coal to the central DCHF and operating the rotary breaker. This provides a lower cost solution without adversely impacting the coal quality of the coal planned to be mined over the next year. As coal markets improve and production from the Ovoot Tolgoi Mine increases in line with its anticipated annual capacity of 9 million tonnes run-of-mine production, the Company will review the use of the DCHF as part of its existing assets and continue developing beneficiation capabilities to maximize value from its product.
Wet Washing Facility
In 2011, the Company entered into an agreement with Ejin Jinda, a subsidiary of China Mongolia Coal Co. Ltd to toll-wash coals from the Ovoot Tolgoi Mine. The agreement has a duration of five years from commencement of the contract and provides for an annual wet washing capacity of approximately 3.5 million tonnes of input coal. The facility is located approximately 10km inside China from the Shivee Khuren-Ceke crossing at the Mongolia-China border (the "Shivee Khuren Border Crossing"), approximately 50km from the Ovoot Tolgoi Mine. Ejin Jinda will charge the Company a single toll washing fee which will cover their expenses, capital recovery and profit. Ejin Jinda will also transport coal from the Ovoot Tolgoi Mine to the wet washing facility under a separate transportation agreement. Pursuant to the terms of the agreement, the Company prepaid $33.6 million of toll washing fees in 2011.
To date, commercial operations at the wet washing facility have not commenced. The Company identified the results of a trial sample from the wet washing facility and the delay in starting the commercial operations at the wet washing facility as indicators of impairment for the prepaid toll washing fees which are part of the contract with Ejin Jinda. Based on updated estimates and assumptions related to wash yields from the facility, a $30.2 million impairment loss on the $33.6 million of prepaid toll washing fees was recorded in the fourth quarter of 2013.
The Company's objective continues to be the implementation of an effective and profitable wet washing solution, and the Company is cooperating with Ejin Jinda in reviewing the utilization of the wet washing facility.
TRANSPORTATION INFRASTRUCTURE
On August 2, 2011, the State Property Committee of Mongolia awarded the tender to construct a paved highway from the Ovoot Tolgoi Complex to the Shivee Khuren Border Crossing to consortium partners NTB LLC and SouthGobi Sands LLC (together referred to as "RDCC LLC"). SouthGobi Sands LLC holds a 40% interest in RDCC LLC.
On October 26, 2011, RDCC LLC signed a concession agreement with the State Property Committee of Mongolia. RDCC LLC has the right to conclude a 17 year build, operate and transfer agreement under the Mongolian Law on Concessions. Construction of the paved highway was substantially complete by the end of 2013. Subject to the Company having available financial resources to fund its portion of the remaining construction costs, the remaining construction work and commissioning of the paved highway is expected to be completed by the end of the first half of 2014.
During the third quarter of 2013, a sub-contractor employee was fatally injured by a vehicle at the construction site. Following the fatality, additional safety training was carried out by RDCC LLC and its sub-contractors in order to reinforce compliance with safety protocols.
The paved highway will have an intended carrying capacity upon completion in excess of 20 million tonnes of coal per year.
PURCHASE, REDEMPTION OR SALE OF LISTED SECURITIES OF THE COMPANY
Neither the Company has redeemed, purchased or sold any of its own listed securities during the year ended December 31, 2013, nor any of its subsidiaries purchased, or sold any of the Company's listed securities during the year ended December 31, 2013.
COMPLIANCE WITH THE CODE ON CORPORATE GOVERNANCE PRACTICES
The Company has, throughout the year ended December 31, 2013, applied the principles and complied with the requirements of its corporate governance practices as defined by the Board of Directors and all applicable statutory, regulatory and stock exchange listings standards.
COMPLIANCE WITH THE MODEL CODE FOR SECURITIES TRANSACTIONS BY DIRECTORS OF LISTED COMPANIES
The Company has adopted policies regarding directors' securities transactions in its Corporate Disclosure, Confidentiality and Securities Trading policy that has terms that are no less exacting than those set out in the Model Code of Appendix 10 of the rules governing the listing of securities on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange. The Board of Directors confirms that all of the Directors of the Company have complied with the required policies in the Company's Corporate Disclosure, Confidentiality and Securities Trading policy throughout the year ended December 31, 2013.
OUTLOOK
Excess supply within the coking coal markets in 2013 continued with further growth from Australian producers and strong exports from North America and Russia also impacting global trade. Chinese domestic washed coking coal production increased in 2013 as a result of continued capacity expansion in Shanxi.
Coal prices in China declined progressively through 2013 before flattening out at four year lows in the third quarter and then improving slightly in the fourth quarter of 2013. However, prices remained well below the levels achieved over the last three years and the Mongolian coal industry faced strong competition from seaborne and domestic Chinese coal producers. These factors led to both lower prices and a reduction in market share of 16% for Mongolian coal producers in Chinese coking coal imports in 2013 compared to 2012.
The increase in sales volumes and the reduction in cash costs per tonne sold partially offset pricing pressures experienced in 2013 compared to 2012. The reduction in cash costs per tonne sold was driven by an improvement in mining equipment productivity and cost control measures. While the strip ratio was slightly higher in 2013 compared to 2012, it remained below long term trend. Cash costs were also favorably impacted by the depreciation of the Mongolian Tugrik versus the U.S. Dollar. The Company minimized capital expenditures and exploration expenses throughout 2013 to preserve its financial resources. As a result, despite difficult coal market conditions, the Company's cash position and liquidity(1) increased by $3.3 million in 2013 exclusive of $16.2 million of cash interest payments on the CIC convertible debenture. (1) Cash position and liquidity comprises cash and short term money
market investments
The outlook for Mongolian coal exports remains dependent on China. Demand at the beginning of 2014 has been seasonally weak with the impact of the Chinese New Year lasting longer than expected and prices have again declined after rising in the fourth quarter of 2013.
The Company anticipates that coal prices in China will remain under pressure in 2014, which will continue to impact the Company's margins and liquidity. The Company continues to strive for further cost reductions and where possible delay expenditures. However, based on its forecasts for the year ended December 31, 2014, the Company is unlikely to have sufficient capital resources and does not expect to generate sufficient cash flows from mining operations in order to satisfy its ongoing obligations and future contractual commitments, including cash interest payments due on the CIC convertible debenture. Therefore, the Company is actively seeking additional sources of financing to continue operating and meet its objectives.
The Company's consolidated financial statements have been prepared on a going concern basis which assumes that the Company will continue operating until at least December 31, 2014 and will be able to realize its assets and discharge its liabilities in the normal course of operations as they come due. While the Company is actively seeking additional sources of financing to continue operating and meet its objectives, there can be no assurance that such financing will be available on terms acceptable to the Company. If for any reason, the Company is unable to secure the additional sources of financing and continue as a going concern, then this could result in adjustments to the amounts and classifications of assets and liabilities in the Company's consolidated financial statements and such adjustments could be material.
While the Company intends to secure additional sources of financing as soon as possible, a continued delay in securing additional financing could ultimately result in an event of default of the $250.0 million CIC convertible debenture, which if not cured within applicable cure periods in accordance with the terms of such debenture, may result in the principal amount owing and all accrued and unpaid interest becoming immediately due and payable upon notice to the Company by CIC.
The Company is focused on securing additional sources of financing and continues to minimize uncommitted capital expenditures while preserving the Company's growth options.
Longer term, the Company remains well positioned, with a number of key competitive strengths, including: -- Strategic location -The Ovoot Tolgoi Mine is located approximately 40km
from China, which represents the main coal market. The Company has an
infrastructure advantage, being approximately 50km from a major Chinese
coal distribution terminal with rail connections to key coal markets in
China. -- Large resource base - The Company's aggregate coal resources (including
reserves) include measured and indicated resources of 533 million tonnes
and inferred resources of 302 million tonnes. -- Several growth options - The Company has several growth options
including an anticipated increase to 9 million tonnes annual run-of-mine
capacity at the Ovoot Tolgoi Mine as well as greenfield options with the
Soumber Deposit and Zag Suuj Deposit, located approximately 20km east
and approximately 150km east of the Ovoot Tolgoi Mine, respectively. -- Flexible product offering - Most of the Company's coal resources have
coking properties, including a mixture of semi-soft coking coals and
hard coking coals. The Company is currently studying options to supply
washed coal to the market to further improve its market position and
access to end customers.
Objectives
The Company's objectives for 2014 and the medium term are as follows. -- Drive operational excellence - The Company is focused on further
improving operational efficiency in delivering production to meet market
requirements and to further reduce operating and administrative costs. -- Continue to develop regional infrastructure - Subject to the Company
having available financial resources to fund its portion of the
construction costs, the Company's priority is to complete the
construction of the paved highway from the Ovoot Tolgoi Mine to the
Shivee Khuren Border Crossing as part of the existing consortium.
Construction of the paved highway was substantially complete by the end
of 2013 with the remaining construction work and commissioning expected
to be completed by the end of the first half of 2014. -- Deliver value through marketing by improving our access to market and
end customers and the overall quality of our product - Subject to
available financial resources, implement an effective business structure
and beneficiation process based on wet washing that is capable of
delivering a sustainable and profitable product mix to the Chinese
market and expand the Company's customer base further inland in China. -- Progress growth options - Subject to available financial resources, the
Company plans to further the development of the Soumber Deposit, while
staying compliant with all government requirements in relation to its
licenses and agreements. -- Operating in a socially responsible manner - The Company is focused on
maintaining our vigilance on health, safety and environmental
performance. -- Re-establish the Company's reputation - The Company's vision is to be a
respected and profitable Mongolian coal company. To achieve this, the
Company will continue to work on re-establishing good working
relationships with all external stakeholders.
NON-IFRS FINANCIAL MEASURES
Cash Costs
The Company uses cash costs to describe its cash production costs. Cash costs incorporate all production costs, which include direct and indirect costs of production, with the exception of idled mine asset costs and non-cash expenses which are excluded. Non-cash expenses include share-based compensation expense, impairments of coal stockpile inventories, depreciation and depletion of mineral properties.
The Company uses this performance measure to monitor its operating cash costs internally and believes this measure provides investors and analysts with useful information about the Company's underlying cash costs of operations. The Company believes that conventional measures of performance prepared in accordance with IFRS do not fully illustrate the ability of its mining operations to generate cash flows. The Company reports cash costs on a sales basis. This performance measure is commonly utilized in the mining industry.
The cash costs of product sold may differ from cash costs of product produced depending on the timing of stockpile inventory turnover.
Adjusted Net Income/(Loss)
Effective December 31, 2013, the Company discontinued the reporting of adjusted net income/(loss). The Company has determined that this non-IFRS measure no longer provides investors with useful information to evaluate the underlying performance of the Company. //st CONSOLIDATED FINANCIAL STATEMENTS Consolidated Statements of Comprehensive Income (Expressed in thousands of U.S. Dollars, except for share and per share amounts)
Note Year ended December 31,
----- --------------------------
2013 2012 Revenue $ 58,636 $ 78,061 Cost of sales 3 (112,627) (127,407) ---------------------------------------------------------------------------- Gross loss (53,991) (49,346) Other operating expenses 4 (126,040) (41,645) Administration expenses 5 (15,629) (24,637) Evaluation and exploration expenses 6 (1,169) (8,598) ---------------------------------------------------------------------------- Loss from operations (196,829) (124,226) Finance costs 7 (21,162) (15,385) Finance income 7 5,566 39,942 Share of earnings/(losses) of joint venture (53) 635 ---------------------------------------------------------------------------- Loss before tax (212,478) (99,034) Current income tax expense 8 (3) (354) Deferred income tax recovery/(expense) 8 (24,983) 1,886 ---------------------------------------------------------------------------- Net loss attributable to equity holders of the Company (237,464) (97,502) ---------------------------------------------------------------------------- Other comprehensive income/loss Reclassification of loss/(gain) on available-for-sale financial asset, net of tax 514 (16,559) ---------------------------------------------------------------------------- Net comprehensive loss attributable to equity holders of the Company $ (236,950) $ (114,061) ---------------------------------------------------------------------------- ---------------------------------------------------------------------------- Basic loss per share 9 $ (1.30) $ (0.54) Diluted loss per share 9 $ (1.30) $ (0.60) Consolidated Statements of Financial Position (Expressed in thousands of U.S. Dollars)
As at December 31,
Note 2013 2012
----- ---------------------------- Assets Current assets Cash $ 21,837 $ 19,674 Trade and other receivables 10 2,578 3,292 Short term investments - 15,000 Inventories 40,288 59,735 Prepaid expenses and deposits 11,506 47,432 --------------------------------------------------------------------------- Total current assets 76,209 145,133 Non-current assets Prepaid expenses and deposits - 16,778 Property, plant and equipment 399,395 521,473 Long term investments 30,602 24,084 Deferred income tax assets - 24,984 --------------------------------------------------------------------------- Total non-current assets 429,997 587,319 --------------------------------------------------------------------------- Total assets $ 506,206 $ 732,452 --------------------------------------------------------------------------- Equity and liabilities Current liabilities Trade and other payables 11 $ 31,241 $ 10,216 Deferred revenue 997 8,181 Current portion of convertible debenture 12 2,301 6,301 --------------------------------------------------------------------------- - Total current liabilities 34,539 24,698 Non-current liabilities Convertible debenture 12 94,302 99,667 Decommissioning liability 2,308 4,104 --------------------------------------------------------------------------- - Total non-current liabilities 96,610 103,771 --------------------------------------------------------------------------- - Total liabilities 131,149 128,469 Equity Common shares 1,067,839 1,059,710 Share option reserve 51,198 51,303 Investment revaluation reserve 514 - Accumulated deficit 13 (744,494) (507,030) --------------------------------------------------------------------------- - Total equity 375,057 603,983 --------------------------------------------------------------------------- - Total equity and liabilities $ 506,206 $ 732,452 --------------------------------------------------------------------------- - --------------------------------------------------------------------------- - Net current assets $ 41,670 $ 120,435 Total assets less current liabilities $ 471,667 $ 707,754
________________________________
_______________________________________________ TSX closing price for SGQ-T Date: 2014/03/21 Closing Price: 0.73
____________________________________________________________
(c)2014 Market News Publishing Inc. All rights reserved. Toronto:(416)366-8881 Vancouver:(604)689-1101 Fax:(604)689-1106
]]></text></news-item>