<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-90C1-DYTR-J2RX"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>TODAY IN HISTORY</title><source>The Southland Times (New Zealand)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Today is Tuesday, March 25, the 84th day of 2014. There are 281 days left in the year. Highlights in history on this date:
1634: British colonists under Lord Baltimore reach Maryland in North America.
1815: Austria, Britain, Prussia and Russia form new alliance against Napoleon Bonaparte after he escapes from confinement on Elba.
1821: Greek patriots begin revolt against domination of Ottoman Empire, an uprising that lasts 12 years and wins Greek independence.
1911: A fire at the Triangle Shirtwaist Co factory in New York City kills 146 immigrant workers; the tragedy galvanises America's labour movement.
1913: The home of vaudeville, the Palace Theatre, opens in New York City
1941: Yugoslavia joins Rome-Berlin- Tokyo Alliance in World War II.
1965: Rev Martin Luther King Jr leads 25,000 marchers to the state capitol in Montgomery, Alabama, to protest the denial of voting rights to blacks.
1969: Pakistan's President Ayub Khan turns power over to military after 11 years of leadership.
1971: Pakistani troops are deployed in East Pakistan, now Bangladesh, to quell rebels demanding an independent state.
1975: Saudi Arabia's King Faisal is assassinated in Riyadh by nephew with history of mental illness. Faisal's brother, Crown Prince Khaled, succeeds to throne.
1982: The Canada Act is signed , making Canada wholly independent of Britain.
1989: Heads of Egypt, Jordan and Palestine Liberation Organisation meet to co-ordinate Middle East peace strategy.
1990: Arson fire in illegal nightclub kills 87 in Bronx, New York; most of them Honduran and Dominican immigrants.
1992: Returning from a 10-month stay in space, cosmonaut Sergei Krikalev is given smelling salts when he learns that the Soviet Union has disintegrated while he was away.
1993: Gunmen storm the military compound of President Gnassingbe Eyadema in Lome, Togo, and kill his top military aide.
1994: American troops withdraw from Somalia after a 16-month humanitarian mission marred by fighting with Somali warlords.
1995: Two Americans who strayed across the Kuwaiti border into Iraq are tried by an Iraqi court and sentenced to eight years in prison.
2012: The US pays $50,000 in compensation for each villager killed and $11,000 for each person wounded in a shooting rampage allegedly carried out by a rogue American soldier in southern Afghanistan.
]]></text></news-item>