<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-DKR1-JC92-P330"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Daily Headline News for March 24, 2014</title><source>Russia &amp; CIS General Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Digest of headline news as of 3:30 p.m. Moscow time on March 24:
BUSINESS & FINANCE
*** ULYUKAYEV: ANNUALIZED INFLATION TO TOP 7% SOON, COULD DECLINE TO 5% BY YEAR-END
Russian inflation will swiftly rise above 7% on an annualized basis but will begin declining at the end of the second quarter and could finish that year the year at 5% or lower, Economic Development Minister Alexei Ulyukayev said.
"That is the target set by the Central Bank of Russia [5% inflation for full-year 2014]. In my view, we have every possibility of achieving that target. Right now of course, the situation is getting a little worse. We are going to hit 6.5% this month and will probably soon rise above 7% on an annualized basis. But as early as the end of the second quarter we expect the trend to reverse itself, for inflation to slow. The effect of the exchange rate shift will run its course and movement in the opposite direction will begin. On the other hand, measures in the area of tariff setting, trade and financial offers should have their effect. For that reason, I think that we will get close to the target by year-end," Ulyukayev said in an interview published on Rossiiskaya Gazeta's website.
*** GAS PRODUCTION IN CRIMEA SHOULD BE INCREASED AT LEAST 50% - MEDVEDEV
It is necessary to increase gas production in Crimea from up to 50% to 100% in the coming years, Russian Prime Minister Dmitry Medvedev said.
"According to expert assessments, this should be enough to cover Crimea's power needs," Medvedev said at a meeting dedicated to social and economic development of Crimea and Sevastopol on Monday.
*** MEDVEDEV SPEAKS OF VARIOUS OPTIONS OF ELECTRICAL POWER SUPPLY TO CRIMEA
Russian Prime Minister Dmitry Medvedev believes that electrical power can be supplied to Crimea by joining the peninsula to the Unified Energy System of Russia through the Kerch Strait and also by building generating facilities in Crimea.
"As to electrical power, there are options of joining Crimea to the Unified Energy System of Russia through the Kerch Strait and building generating facilities on the peninsula," Medvedev said at a meeting on the socio-economic development of Crimea and Sevastopol.
*** RUSSIAN RUBLE CAN NOW BE USED AS LEGAL TENDER IN CRIMEA
Starting today, the Russian ruble can now be used for purchases and settlements in Crimea.
Officials in Crimea say payments can now be made in Russian rubles and Ukrainian hryvna. Transition to the use of the ruble will be smooth, but quick, the authorities say.
Chairman of the Bank of Crimea Nikolai Barilyuk said the two currencies will be in use until January 1 of 2016. "The monetary system will be working both in rubles and the Ukrainian hryvna," he said.
*** VIETNAMESE PRESIDENT, ROSNEFT HEAD DISCUSS LONG-TERM OIL SUPPLIES
Rosneft (MOEX: ROSN) president Igor Sechin met with Vietnamese President Truong Tan Sang during his working visit to Vietnam.
They discussed the possibility of expanding cooperation between the Russian oil major and Vietnamese partners, including in the area of long-term oil supplies, Rosneft said in a statement.
Sechin and Prime Minister Nguyen Tan Dung discussed promising projects in the area of fuel supplies and offshore production.
*** RUSSIAN NUCLEAR FUEL EXPORTER SEES WEAK RUBLE BOOSTING REVENUE 500 MLN RUBLES IN 2014
TVEL, a nuclear fuel division of Russian state nuclear corporation Rosatom, expects to earn about 500 million rubles in additional revenue on exchange rate differences in 2014, the company told Interfax.
The company said that all foreign trade contracts with foreign partners for nuclear fuel supplies provide for payment in dollars or euros, so ruble revenues are expected to grow on the exchange rate difference.
*** URALVAGONZAVOD TO PRODUCE 1,500-2,000 CARS A YEAR IN VIETNAM - NEWSPAPER
Uralvagonzavod is set to manufacture 1,500 t0 2,000 cars a year in Vietnam, Vedomosti wrote on Monday referring to Uralvagonzavod General Director Oleg Siyenko.
Investment in the production of tank containers, LNG tank cars, open cars and mineral cars will stand at 40-50 million euro. The whole sum may be provided by the Vietnam-Russia Joint Venture Bank (owned by Russia's VTB at 50%), Siyenko said. A memorandum to the effect was signed during the Hanoi visit of Russian President Vladimir Putin.
*** ROSTEC ACQUIRES BLOCKING STAKE IN YOTA DEVICES
The state corporation Rostec has gained a blocking stake - 25.1% of shares - in the company Yota Devices, which sells Internet modems and YotaPhone smartphones.
Rostec's involvement in Yota Devices was envisioned at the moment the company was founded in 2011 and came about last December, a Yota Devices representative told Interfax.
After the deal with Rostec, the Yota capital stake of the investment fund Wooden Fish decreased to 74.9%. Wooden Fish represented the interests of the fund Telconet Capital, which is controlled 50/50 by Sergei Adonyev and Albert Avdolian.
*** TRANSNEFT MIGHT SELL STAKE IN NCSP TO SUMMA, BUY OUT OIL TERMINALS - PAPER
Transneft (MOEX: TRNF) president Nikolai Tokarev sent President Vladimir Putin a letter at the end of 2013 proposing several options for the development of Novorossiysk Commercial Sea Port (NCSP) (MOEX: NMTP), including a division of the assets of Russia's biggest port operator, national daily Kommersant reported on Monday, citing the letter.
The letter states that having several major shareholders, the largest of which are Ziyavudin Magomedov's Summa Group and Transneft, with different visions for the development of NCSP makes it impossible to agree on a common management strategy and negatively impacts economic performance.
POLITICS & SOCIETY
*** MEDVEDEV ORDERS DEVELOPMENT OF SPECIFIC STEPS ON INTEGRATION OF CRIMEA
All ministries and agencies should prepare a specific plan of action on the integration of Crimea into the state economic, financial, and legal systems of Russia in the nearest future, Russian Prime Minister Dmitry Medvedev said.
"We need to work out specific, consistent steps aimed at full-scale integration of Crimea and Sevastopol in the state, economic, financial, and legal systems of our country so that people in Crimea should have the same opportunities, rights and guarantees as all Russian citizens," Medvedev said at a meeting on the socio-economic development of Crimea and Sevastopol.
*** CRIMEA COULD RECEIVE STATUS OF SPECIAL ECONOMIC ZONE - MEDVEDEV
Crimea could be granted the status of a special economic zone, Russian Prime Minister Dmitry Medvedev said.
"We will need to provide additional preferences to the new Russian regions. I think that it is possible to consider the issue of establishing a special economic zone in Crimea," Medvedev said at a meeting dedicated to social and economic development of Crimea and Sevastopol on Monday.
During the transition period, which is scheduled for Crimea's integration in Russia's social and economic life and which will last until January 1, 2015, enterprises working in Crimea under Russian jurisdiction could be relieved of paying taxes, the prime minister said.
*** ALL CRIMEAN RESIDENTS TO RECEIVE RUSSIAN PASSPORTS BY SUMMER - MEDVEDEV
The procedure of issuing Russian passports to all people willing to receive one in Crimea should be completed by summer, Russian Prime Minister Dmitry Medvedev said.
"Crimean residents receiving Russian citizenship is of great importance. The federal migration service department plans to complete issuing Russian passports to all willing people by the summer," Medvedev said at a meeting dedicated to social and economic development of Crimea and Sevastopol on Monday.
*** FEDERAL MIGRATION SERVICE ISSUES OVER 2,500 RUSSIAN PASSPORTS IN CRIMEA
More than 2,500 Russian passports have been issued in Crimea, Federal Migration Service deputy head Sergei Kalyuzhny said.
"We have received over 20,000 passport applications from Crimean residents. More than 2,500 [identification] documents have been issued. This process has a acquired a regular basis - the number of accepted applications and issued documents will be growing each day," he told a press conference in Moscow on Monday.
*** LAVROV TO HOLD BILATERAL MEETINGS ON NUCLEAR SECURITY SUMMIT SIDELINES
The Russian delegation at the physical nuclear security summit (NSS) opening in The Hague on Monday is led by Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov.
Lavrov will hold a number of bilateral meetings on the sidelines of the summit, including, as expected, with United States Secretary of State John Kerry.
"The Lavrov-Kerry meeting is planned on the sidelines of the Hague summit. It will focus on the internal political crisis in Ukraine," a source in the Russian Foreign Ministry told Interfax earlier.
It is not ruled out that Lavrov will meet with his Polish counterpart Radoslaw Sikorski.
Ukraine is likely to be on the agenda of this meeting too.
*** GLONASS-M NAVIGATION SATELLITE REACHES TARGET ORBIT
A Soyuz-2.1b launch vehicle with a Fregat upper stage and a Glonass global navigation satellite aboard blasted off from the Plesetsk space center on Monday, Russian Aerospace Defense Forces spokesman Col. Alexei Zolotukhin told Interfax-AVN.
"The launch vehicle took off from the 43rd launch site of the northern spaceport at 02:54 a.m. Moscow time," he said.
That was the 500th launch done from that site.
*** ASW DIVISION TO BE RESTORED IN SEVASTOPOL - NAVY CENTRAL HQ
The division of anti-submarine warfare ships (ASW) will be restored in Sevastopol in 2015, a representative for the Navy Central Command told Interfax-AVN on Monday.
"Given the Navy's new objectives in the remote maritime zone, and the renewal of the Black Sea Fleet's ships, it has been decided to recreate within a year's time in Sevastopol the famous 'thirty' - the 30th division of anti-submarine ships, which will be based at its former location and under its former name. It will be a permanent-readiness formation," the source said.
*** UKRAINIAN TROOPS IN CRIMEA TO RE-DEPLOY - TURCHYNOV
The Ukrainian National Security and Defense Council (SNBO) has instructed the Defense Ministry to re-deploy its Crimean military bases, Ukraine's Acting President and Verkhovna Rada Speaker Oleksandr Turchynov said.
"The National Security and Defense Council has made the decision to instruct the Defense Ministry to conduct the re-deployment of the military units based in the Autonomous Republic of Crimea," Turchynov said at a conciliation board of the parliamentary faction leaders and committee chairmen.
*** SABOTAGE LIKELY CAUSE OF KRYVYI RIH ARMY BASE FIRE - DEPUTY MINISTER
Ukrainian Deputy Defense Minister Leonid Polyakov sees signs of sabotage in the case of the fire at a tank brigade base in Kryvyi Rih in Dnipropetrovsk region, in which two tanks burned down and three were damaged.
"Certain suspicions arise, these tanks were checked recently, everything was normal and suddenly they caught fire... This fits into the pattern of subversion or sabotage," he told a press conference in Kyiv on Friday.
Three tanks were damaged because of a fire at a tank brigade base in Kryvyi Rih in Dnipropetrovsk region, the regional police said earlier on Friday.
*** GEORGIAN DELEGATION FLIES TO GENEVA TO HOLD TALKS - FOREIGN MINISTRY
The next round of the Geneva talks will be held on March 25-26, Georgian Deputy Foreign Minister David Djalagania said at a briefing on Monday.
"Georgia will express strong protest once again amid the difficult situation, about the territories occupied in terms of security and human rights and the installation of wired fences and other artificial barriers along the occupation line," Djalagania said.
"At the same time, the Georgian delegation will pay attention to co-chairpersons to the instances of Russian helicopters violating air space controlled by the central Georgian authorities," the deputy minister said.
Of ar
]]></text></news-item>