<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTK-NG81-F0NV-F41N"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Group opposes town's input in solar farm proposal</title><source>Rutland Herald (Vermont)</source><author>BRENT CURTIS; STAFF WRITER</author><text><![CDATA[A battle over Rutland Town's right to participate in the review of a proposed solar farm in the community is playing out before the state's Public Service Board.
A proposed 9,000-panel solar project on 24 acres of land off Cold River Road prompted town officials last year to begin work on solar facility siting standards to adopt into the town plan.
The standards, which include setback and screening requirements, don't carry the weight of the law for energy projects, which need only a certificate of public good from the state utility board to move forward.
In a motion filed earlier this month, town officials asked for the right to participate in the Public Service Board proceedings to support the standards which have not yet been incorporated into the Rutland Town plan.
But Rutland Renewable Energy, the entity that owns the industrial land on Cold River Road, is opposing the town's participation on the grounds that the standards have yet to be incorporated into the town plan and have no force to compel utility projects under state law.
In the motion to intervene, Attorney Kevin Brown, representing the town, said the proposed solar farm was in violation of the proposed standards in a number of ways.
"(The project) thereby contravenes the substantial public interests of the town of Rutland," Brown wrote.
Among the violations Brown cited are the creation of a new road on the property and lack of sufficient setbacks.
GroSolar, the company that would build the solar farm, has proposed setbacks of 60 feet from roadways and 50 feet from wetlands on the property.
Those setbacks fall short of the proposed solar standards provisions, which call for a 200-foot setback from roadways and a 75-foot setback from wetlands. In addition, setbacks in the standards for historical properties would require the project to shrink up to another 1,000 feet from two historical properties that border the property.
The standards are also concerned with the preservation of prime agricultural soils. On the proposed site off Cold River Road, about 15 acres of fields would be occupied by solar arrays for at least the next 25 years, Brown wrote.
Aesthetic concerns - raised at prior public hearings in the town by neighbors whose properties look down on the proposed site - were also raised in the motion.
During a public hearing last year, GroSolar officials said the site would be screened from the road by a fence and an assortment of trees and shrubs.
But Brown wrote that the proposed plantings would represent a traffic hazard.
"The vegetative screening along Cold River Road... raises concerns regarding the adequacy of sight lines to ensure the safe flow of vehicular and pedestrian traffic," he wrote.
In a response to the town's motion to participate, Kimberly Hayden, an attorney for Rutland Renewable Energy, argued that the standards the town wants to govern the project haven't been adopted yet and are subject to further public hearings.
But even if they were in the town plan, she argued that municipal zoning and planning under state law are "advisory rather than controlling" under Act 248 - the law that regulates power utilities.
Hayden also argued that some of the town's concerns, including the protection of agricultural land and historic properties, are already being represented before the Public Service Board by the state Division for Historic Preservation and the Vermont Agency of Agriculture, Foods and Markets - both of which have found no problem with the project.
"(The Division for Historic Preservation), which has the expertise and responsibility for assessing the project's impacts upon historic properties... has already determined that the project will not in face result in an undue adverse impact," Hayden wrote.
But Brown said the interests of state agencies and the town can differ and he said Rutland Renewable Energy shouldn't be allowed to dismiss the weight of the town's standards simply because they don't carry the weight of law before the review board.
"The Legislature has not constructed a regulatory system in which the PSB renders its decision in a vacuum. Rather (the law) directs that the PSB hear and give due consideration to the recommendations of the Select Board of the town in which the proposed project is located," Brown wrote.
brent.curtis
@rutlandherald.com
]]></text></news-item>