<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTM-1WH1-JBG1-801C"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>CommScope Commences Secondary Offering</title><source>Business Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[CommScope Holding Company, Inc. (NASDAQ: COMM) announced today the commencement of an offering to sell 17,500,000 shares of its common stock by an affiliate of The Carlyle Group (the "selling stockholder"). The offering is being made pursuant to a registration statement on Form S-1 previously filed with the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission. The selling stockholder has also granted the underwriters a 30-day option to purchase up to an additional 2,625,000 shares of CommScope's common stock. CommScope will not receive any of the proceeds from the offering of shares by the selling stockholder.
J.P. Morgan, Deutsche Bank Securities and BofA Merrill Lynch are lead book-running managers for the proposed secondary offering. Additional book-running managers are Barclays Capital Inc., Credit Suisse Securities (USA) LLC, Goldman, Sachs & Co., Jefferies, Morgan Stanley & Co. LLC, RBC Capital Markets and Wells Fargo Securities. Co-Managers are Allen & Company LLC, Evercore, Raymond James, Mizuho Securities, SMBC Nikko and Drexel Hamilton.
Copies of the preliminary prospectus relating to the proposed secondary offering may be obtained from J.P. Morgan, Attention: Broadridge Financial Solutions, 1155 Long Island Avenue, Edgewood, New York 11717, telephone: 1-866-803-9204; Deutsche Bank Securities Inc., Attn: Prospectus Department, 60 Wall Street, New York, New York 10005, telephone: 800-503-4611 or email: prospectus.cpdg@db.com; and BofA Merrill Lynch, 222 Broadway, New York, New York, 10038, Attn: Prospectus Department or email: dg.prospectus_requests@baml.com
Important Information
A registration statement relating to these securities has been filed with the SEC but has not yet become effective. These securities may not be sold nor may offers to buy be accepted prior to the time the registration statement becomes effective. This press release shall not constitute an offer to sell or the solicitation of an offer to buy, nor shall there be any sale of these securities in any state or jurisdiction in which such offer, solicitation or sale would be unlawful prior to registration or qualification under the securities laws of any such state or jurisdiction.
Cautionary Statement Concerning Forward-Looking Statements
This press release and any other oral or written statements made by us or on our behalf may include forward-looking statements which reflect our current views with respect to future events and financial performance. These forward-looking statements are identified by their use of such terms and phrases as "intend," "goal," "estimate," "expect," "project," "projections," "plans," "anticipate," "should," "designed to," "foreseeable future," "believe," "think," "scheduled," "outlook," "guidance" and similar expressions. This list of indicative terms and phrases is not intended to be all-inclusive. These statements are subject to various risks and uncertainties, many of which are outside our control, including, without limitation, continued global economic weakness and uncertainties and disruption in the credit and financial markets; changes in cost and availability of key raw materials and manufactured parts and the potential effect on customer pricing; delays or challenges related to removing, transporting or reinstalling manufacturing equipment; the ability to retain qualified employees; customer demand for our products and the ability to maintain existing business alliances with key customers or distributors; competitive pricing and acceptance of products; industry competition and the ability to retain customers through product innovation; concentration of sales among a limited number of customers or distributors; customer bankruptcy; the risk that internal production capacity and that of contract manufacturers may be insufficient to meet customer demand or quality standards for our products; the risk that customers might cancel orders placed or that orders currently placed may affect order levels in the future; continuing consolidation among customers; possible production disruption due to supplier or contract manufacturer bankruptcy, reorganization, restructuring or manufacturing disruption; successful ongoing operation of our vertical integration activities; the possibility of further restructuring actions; possible future impairment charges for fixed or intangible assets, including goodwill; increased obligations under employee benefit plans; significant international operations and the impact of variability in foreign exchange rates; ability to fully realize anticipated benefits from prior or future acquisitions or equity investments; substantial indebtedness and maintaining compliance with debt covenants; income tax rate variability and ability to recover amounts recorded as value added tax receivables; changes in tax laws or regulations; product performance issues and associated warranty claims; ability to successfully implement major systems initiatives and maintain critical information systems; our ability to recover on a timely basis from natural or man-made disasters or other disruptions, including data or network security breaches; realignment of global manufacturing capacity; cost of protecting or defending intellectual property; ability to obtain capital on commercially reasonable terms; adequacy and availability of insurance; costs and challenges of compliance with domestic and foreign environmental laws and the effects of climate change; fluctuations in interest rates; the ability to achieve expected sales growth and earnings goals; the outcome of pending and future litigation and proceedings; changes in U.S. tax, health care and other major laws or regulations; authoritative changes in generally accepted accounting principles by standard-setting bodies; political instability; regulatory changes affecting us or the industries we serve; and any statements of belief and any statements of assumptions underlying any of the foregoing. These and other factors are discussed in greater detail in our Annual Report on Form 10-K and Form S-1. Although the information contained in this Press Release represents our best judgment at the date of this release based on information currently available and reasonable assumptions, we can give no assurance that the expectations will be attained or that any deviation will not be material. We are not undertaking any duty or obligation to update these statements as a result of actual results, new information, future events or otherwise.
http://www.businesswire.com
]]></text></news-item>