<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTM-FS91-DYX4-0380"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>The news in 5 minutes</title><source>The Straits Times (Singapore)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TOP OF THE NEWS
'Fatal crash' for MH370 flight
MALAYSIAN Premier Najib Razak has announced the MH370 flight "ended" its journey in the Indian Ocean, suggesting a fatal crash. He also suggested the finding was final as it was derived from a satellite data analysis method never used before.
Egypt sentences 529 to death
THE outlawed Muslim Brotherhood group in Egypt has called for the "downfall of military rule" after a court sentenced 529 of its members to death on charges including inciting murder and storming a police station.
ASIA/WORLD
Lessons from history
-- PHOTO: AGENCE FRANCE-PRESSE
JAPANESE Prime Minister Shinzo Abe (photo) promises to help ensure that human rights abuses in the 20th century are not repeated, and to pass on the lessons of history to the next generation, during his visit to the Anne Frank museum in Amsterdam. The visit comes in the wake of vandalism of copies of the diaries of Anne Frank in libraries in Japan.
Anger over toll booths
MANY road users in India view toll booths as "looting" by investors, and protesters in one state smashed up toll booths to convey their rage. But some think politicians are stoking the anger as polls loom.
Switching to Treasuries
FOREIGN buyers such as China may have cut their acquisitions of long-term interest-bearing US debt securities, but US investors have boosted their share to 33 per cent. US buyers have switched to Treasuries as yields from bonds of the most-creditworthy companies have dropped.
OPINION
Trouble in the region
JAPAN should stop its slanging match with China, and opt to be seen as a troubleshooter, not troublemaker, in the region, says associate professor of international relations Heng Yee Kuang.
CHINA'S GREAT URBAN PUSH
China has to grow its urban population and stimulate consumption so as to reduce dependence on exports for its growth. Developing the urban infrastructure and services to cater to the influx is a challenge that will call for careful planning.
SINGAPORE
Dry Songkran ahead
THE Thai new year will be a dry new year when it is celebrated in Singapore next month. Songkran, which takes place between April 13 and 15, is known for revellers splashing each other with water. However, the authorities here have cancelled such water-based activities to conserve water after the recent prolonged dry spell.
Suzhou wins LKY prize
THE Chinese city Suzhou boasts clear skies, an integrated migrant population and now, a Lee Kuan Yew World City Prize. It was selected for the title by Singapore's Urban Redevelopment Authority and the Centre for Liveable Cities.
MONEY
Shot in the arm for HSL
A TEMASEK Holdings-linked private equity firm has made its second investment in a home-grown company, pumping $15 million into marine civil engineering and construction firm HSL Constructor.
SPORT
Barca edge Real Madrid
Ronaldo scored a penalty in the Clasico but Real lost to Barca. -- PHOTO: AGENCE FRANCE-PRESSE
FOOTBALL star Cristiano Ronaldo slammed the referee's decisions in the Spanish Clasico, after Barcelona won a 4-3 thriller that put them just a point behind Real Madrid.
Lionel Messi made the title race even tighter - Atletico lead Real on goal difference - with his hat-trick.
LIFE!
Duo back for film fest
Mr Zhang (left) and Ms Yuni Hadi will helm this year's edition of the Singapore film festival. -- PHOTO: SGIFF
TWO former directors of the Singapore International Film Festival will return to helm the 25th edition this year. Ms Yuni Hadi will take the role of executive director, while her co-festival director in 2009, Mr Zhang Wenjie, will return as festival director and take charge of programming.
The festival will run from Dec 4 to 14.
Beethoven recital
ONE of the world's foremost Beethoven interpreters is to perform in Singapore for the first time.
Hungarian-born British pianist Andras Schiff will stage a solo recital on Monday at the Yong Siew Toh Conservatory of Music Concert Hall.
]]></text></news-item>