<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTM-33G1-JB5P-J05C"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Philippines: House leader asks Malacanang to certify Anti-Trust bill urgent to address cartels and monopolies</title><source>Thai News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[As the Philippines' climb to the sixth place in the recent Crony Capitalism Index, Valenzuela City Rep. Sherwin Gatchalian on Sunday expressed apprehension as he called on Malacanang to certify the Anti-Trust bill as urgent.
The country moved three notches up this year from No. 9 in 2007 in The Economist's gauge on countries where crony capitalism is still very much active, ahead of its Asian neighbors like India (9), Indonesia (10), and China (19). The Economist cited building cartels and lobbying for rules that benefit a firm at the expense of competitors and customers as cases of "rent-seeking."
Gatchalian moved for the urgent passage of House Bill 1133, to be known as the Philippine Fair Competition Act of 2013, filed by House Speaker Feliciano Belmonte, Jr.
According to the Valenzuela lawmaker, the measure will make playing fields even, eliminating the hold of cronies in crucial industries such as utilities and telecommunications. A fair business environment will sway foreign investors in setting up businesses here which in turn will create more jobs.
Cronies, cartels and monopolies still exist even after the Martial Law years, as shown by the crony-capitalism index. It is high time for this proposed law to be certified urgent. I call on President Aquino to make the bill a priority to ensure its passage in both Houses, said Gatchalian, who is also vice chair for the House committees on Metro Manila Development; Housing and Urban Development, and; Tourism.
He recalled that under the 1987 Constitution, the State is mandated to regulate or ban monopolies.
The proposed law fleshes out what the Constitution already provides. It expressly lists what acts will be prohibited as well as the penalties for violator firms, he pointed out.
The lawmaker said the bill will open the economy to more local and foreign players.
If passed into law, the Anti-Trust measure will give other enterprises a fighting chance to participate in sectors dominated by oligopolies like in utilities and telecommunications. It will also attract foreign direct investments that can create much-needed jobs for Filipinos. However, before foreign investors can set up their ventures here, they will need a business-friendly environment," he said. - PNA
]]></text></news-item>