<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTM-52Y1-F05M-K116"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Littleton homebuilder guilty of federal mortgage fraud</title><source>Denver Business Journal</source><author>Dennis Huspeni</author><text><![CDATA[The former president of a Littleton home buidling company, Peter V. Capra, was convicted Friday of federal counts of wire fraud, mail fraud and money laundering.
After an eight-day trial in U.S. District Court in Denver, a jury found 56-year-old Capra guilty of 14 counts of wire fraud, two counts of mail fraud and 10 counts of money laundering. He headed Golden Design Group Inc.
Capra faces up to 20 years in federal prison on each wire and mail fraud count, 10 years in prison on each money laundering count and hundreds of thousands of dollars in fines.
He was indicted by a federal grand jury in May of 2012.
The jury relied on evidence alleging that between January 1, 2005 and July 31, 2008, Capra "executed and attempted to execute a scheme to defraud mortgage lenders through the use of applications for residential mortgage loans and related documents associated with real estate purchases in the Denver Metro area," according to the U.S. Attorney's office.
In addition to being president of GDG - which built and sold homes in metro Denver - Capra was also the registered agent for Distinctive Mortgages LLC, which used GDG office space and provided mortgages for some of the purchasers of GDG houses. At the time of the indictment, the GDG website listed the company on its site, but the link led to a defunct web page.
Capra created Cambridge Real Estate Consulting LLC and Chateau Real Estate Investments LLC. Though paperwork filed through the Colorado Secretary of State showed the companies as independent entities, "Capra or his associate, a person with the initials R.P., directed all activities of Cambridge and Chateau and controlled their bank accounts," according to the indictment.
"As part of the scheme, Capra would structure transactions involving homes built and sold by GDG to allow buyers to receive substantial amounts of the lenders' money at the time of closing without the lenders' knowledge," evidence showed.
"He also sold a large volume of homes to otherwise unwilling or unqualified buyers," according to the U.S. Attorney. "The evidence at trial showed that Capra netted over $11,000,000 as a result of his scheme."
Capra was taken into custody at the conclusion of his trial.
Co-defendants Demetrious G. Gianopoulos, Brian Waring and Justin Knight were each charged and have pleaded guilty, according to the U.S. Attorney's office.
Gianopoulos pleaded guilty to one count of money laundering and was sentenced to five years' probation. Knight pleaded guilty to destruction of records in a federal investigation and was sentenced to 12 months of home confinement. Waring pleaded guilty to conspiracy to commit mail fraud, wire fraud, and money laundering and is scheduled to be sentenced on May 30, 2014, according to the U.S. Attorney.
First Assistant U.S. Attorney Robert Troyer and Assistant U.S. Attorney Mathew Kirsch tried the case.
Capra's bond hearing is scheduled for April 2 in U.S. District Judge R. Brooke Jackson's courtroom.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Denver Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>