<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTM-2S31-DYG3-317W"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Huawei condemns NSA for hacking its kit</title><source>Total Telecom</source><author>Nick Wood, Total Telecom</author><text><![CDATA[Huawei on Monday condemned the activities of the U.S. National Security Agency (NSA) after reports emerged that it hacked into the Chinese vendor's products.
Documents given to The New York Times and Der Spiegel by former intelligence contractor Edward Snowden reveal that the NSA gained access to servers at Huawei's Shenzhen headquarters so it could obtain information about its routers and switches, and spy on its high-ranking executives.
According to the NYT, the operation, code-named 'Shotgiant', aimed to find links between Huawei and the People's Liberation Army. The NSA is also alleged to have installed backdoors in Huawei's equipment so that when it is deployed in a network, the NSA can access and monitor traffic and even stage cyber-attacks.
"If the actions in the report are true, Huawei condemns such activities that invaded and infiltrated into our internal corporate network and monitored our communications," said Huawei, in a statement.
Over the years, Huawei has been unable to export its network products to the U.S. or acquire U.S. equipment vendors due to concerns about whether such a move would allow the Chinese government to access U.S. telecommunication networks.
It is perhaps unsurprising then that, if the report is true, the NSA would take an interest in gaining access to Huawei's products and corporate network. It is also ironic that the only backdoors in Huawei's equipment that the public know about are the ones allegedly installed by its accuser.
"We reiterate that Huawei disagrees with all activities that threaten the security of networks and is willing to work with all governments, industry stakeholders and customers, in an open and transparent manner, to jointly address the global challenge of network security," said Huawei. 
]]></text></news-item>