<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTM-2H81-F11P-X53R"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Financial advice rule changes on hold</title><source>Legal Monitor Worldwide</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Finance Minister Mathias Cormann has called a halt to the controversial watering-down of Labor's financial advice laws, less than a week after besieged colleague Arthur Sinodinos stepped down from the portfolio.
The move means the Abbott government's amended legislation will not be introduced to parliament this week. "I have decided to pause the process on the FOFA regulation for the time being to enable me to consult in good faith with all relevant stakeholders before pressing the go button on our changes," Senator Cormann told Fairfax Media. "We remain committed to implement the improvements to FOFA which we took to the last election as soon as possible." Advertisement The government had planned to introduce the regulations winding back the consumer protections in financial advice this Friday, after parliament rose for a six week break. The timing would have made it impossible for the parliament to immediately disallow the regulations. The change comes after months of criticism of the government's proposed changes to the Future of Financial Advice legislation, known as FOFA. It also comes in the first week after Senator Cormann took control of the policy following Senator Arthur Sinodinos's decision to step aside in the face of an Independent Commission Against Corruption inquiry in NSW. The legislation aimed at neutering Labor's financial advice reforms introduced on Wednesday was unlikely to pass the Senate. Legal advice prepared presented to the then assistant treasurer Arthur Sinodinos by Industry Super predicted chaos if the government proceed with its plan to amend the law by regulation. Prepared by the tax litigation specialist Arnold Bloch Leibler it said the regulations would be "invalid and susceptible to challenge in the courts". "A court declaration of invalidity would operate retrospectively," it said. "This means, for example, financial advisers who relied on the regulations could be found to have acted unlawfully." At issue was whether regulations could be used to nullify parts of an Act. "Regulations are usually only a management tool to implement the details of the day-to-day operation of an Act," the advice said. While Labor's law does include clauses permitting regulations that allow exemptions in "a particular situation" and in "prescribed circumstances" Arnold Bloch Leibler said those words could not possibly mean "in all situations", otherwise the words "particular" and "prescribed" would not have been used.
Introduced mid last year in response to a string of high profile financial collapses, Labor's Future of Financial Advice Act imposes an overarching requirement on financial planners to act in the best interests of their clients. It also prohibits them from obtaining sales commissions and other forms of conflicted remuneration. The Coaltion wants to remove the catch-all "best interests" provision, leaving in place the specific requirements that are at present backed up by the provision. They also would allow advisors and clients to agree to limit the scope of advice in a way that made clear there was no expectation the advisor would act in the client's best interests. The definition of "conflicted remuneration" would be narrowed to allow advisors to continue to receive payments in kind from product providers where the advice was general rather than personal.© 2014 Legal Monitor Worldwide.
]]></text></news-item>