<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTP-S9K1-JBG1-802S"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>SHAREHOLDER ALERT: Investigation on Behalf of Allied Nevada Gold Corp. Investors Announced by Law Offices of Howard G. Smith</title><source>Business Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Law Offices of Howard G. Smith announces that it is investigating potential claims on behalf of investors of Allied Nevada Gold Corp. ("Allied Nevada" or the "Company") (NYSE MKT: ANV), including purchasers in connection with the Company's Secondary Offering at $10.75 on May 17, 2013. The investigation concerns possible violations of federal securities laws and focuses on certain statements issued by the Company concerning Allied Nevada's business, operations and financial prospects. All persons or entities who purchased or acquired Allied Nevada shares in the Company's Secondary Offering may have special rights separate and apart from other purchasers of Allied shares.
Allied Nevada is a gold producer engaged in the mining, development and exploration of properties in Nevada. The Company operates the Hycroft Mine -- an open pit heap leach operation situated to the west of Winnemucca, Nevada. The investigation is related to the Company's statements concerning the Company's financial performance, mill construction at the Hycroft site, and additional drilling, lime and cyanide costs associated with the Lewis leach pad remediation project. In addition, on August 6, 2013, the Company disclosed that, as a result of continuing weak cash flow from operations, the Company would defer the construction of the mill at Hycroft until completing of a revised feasibility study. As a result of these disclosures, the price of Allied Nevada shares dropped from $5.90 per share on August 5, 2013, to a closing price of $3.73 per share on August 7, 2013, on heavy trading volume.
If you purchased Allied Nevada shares, including shares acquired in connection with the Company's May 17, 2013, Secondary Offering at $10.75, if you have information or would like to learn more about these claims, or if you have any questions concerning this announcement or your rights or interests with respect to these matters, please contact Howard G. Smith, Esquire, of Law Offices of Howard G. Smith, 3070 Bristol Pike, Suite 112, Bensalem, Pennsylvania 19020 by telephone at 215-638-4847, Toll-Free at 888-638-4847, or by email to howardsmith@howardsmithlaw.com, or visit our website at www.howardsmithlaw.com .
http://www.businesswire.com
]]></text></news-item>