<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTP-H2R1-DYTG-N1SR"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>JURY SELECTED FOR MINE DEATHS TRIAL</title><source>Regional Press Releases: Wales</source><author>Benjamin Wright, Press Association</author><text><![CDATA[Potential jurors have been selected for the trial of a former coal mine boss accused of causing the deaths of four employees.
Malcolm Fyfield was the sole survivor of the Gleision mining disaster near Pontardawe, South Wales, in 2011.
He managed to crawl out of a flooded mine shaft after a sudden deluge of water killed Charles Breslin, 62, Philip Hill, 44, Garry Jenkins, 39, and David Powell, 50.
Father-of-two Fyfield denies four counts of manslaughter, while MNS Mining Ltd, which operated the pit at the time, has pleaded not guilty to four charges of corporate manslaughter.
Fyfield and two representatives of MNS appeared at Swansea Crown Court today.
Judge Mr Justice Wyn Williams said the trial is set to last at least four months, and more than 90 witnesses are expected to give evidence.
The process of selecting 12 potential jurors and four reserves from an initial pool of 70 took more than two hours.
Mr Justice Williams said: ``When a jury summons is issued, it is expected that you come here to court and be involved in comparatively short cases and that jury service would take two to three weeks.
``The case that is going to be heard in this case is not going to take two to three weeks. It will probably take until the end of June and possibly beyond that.
``Jury service is a very important public service ... people are chosen from the electoral roll. They are expected to do jury service.''
Proceedings in Court One saw all 70 of those initially selected quizzed by Mr Justice Williams on their availability.
They were given a list of 15 questions such as whether they knew the defendant or the deceased, and if they knew the 91 witnesses in the case, including police officers, geologists, search and rescue teams and medical staff.
Finally they were asked to prove whether the length of time they would be expected to serve on a jury could cause them ``significant hardship''.
Proceedings were adjourned until tomorrow when it is expected a jury will be sworn in.
Fyfield is being represented by Elwen Evans QC.
Pranshant Popat is representing MNS.
The two directors who appeared on behalf of the company in court were Gerald Ward and Maria Seage.
]]></text></news-item>