<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTP-W311-JDK3-904K"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Woman takes Archidiocese of Ottawa before human rights tribunal</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[OTTAWA - A 59-year-old woman claims she was unceremoniously - and unlawfully - fired by the Archdiocese of Ottawa after her menopause and related depression caused her workplace performance to suffer.
Ginette Chaumont, the former administrative assistant to Archbishop Terrence Prendergast, has launched a human rights case in which she alleges that the archdiocese discriminated against her on the basis of age, sex and disability.
She was fired in November 2011 after 22 years of service.
Chaumont admits she was struggling in the workplace before she was fired, but contends those difficulties were a direct result of her menopause and depression.
She wants her job and insurance coverage reinstated, and the diocese to admit its mistake.
"I feel pretty devastated," Chaumont said in an interview Monday, on the eve of this week's hearing before the Human Rights Tribunal of Ontario.
"It wasn't just like losing a job; my whole life surrounded it. So I feel tossed aside, rejected, ostracized."
A spokesperson for the Archdiocese of Ottawa called the case "a termination of employment dispute."
"There is no foundation for a claim of discrimination on any basis," Sarah Du Broy said. "The archdiocese is prepared to defend its position before the Human Rights Tribunal of Ontario."
Chaumont, a devout Roman Catholic with a degree in canon law, said she was a loyal, conscientious and hard-working employee at the chancery for most of her adult life. She considered her co-workers at the administrative offices of the Ottawa diocese to be like family.
About 10 years ago, Chaumont was diagnosed with clinical depression. She told her employer about her condition and took some time off work, but with treatment, her symptoms subsided until 2011 when she began to experience menopause.
Chaumont's depression returned and with it came diminished energy and concentration levels.
Chaumont admits that her work suffered as a result. She was less organized, less efficient and made more mistakes.
"It is a very busy office and there was a lot of pressure," she said. "But when you're depressed and fatigued and you don't have a lot of energy, you have trouble keeping on top of things."
Chaumont worked unpaid overtime in an effort to compensate for her shortcomings. Despite her best efforts, however, she was called into a meeting on Nov. 18, 2011, and summarily fired. Prendergast had lost confidence in her work, she was told.
"I was in a state of shock," she told the Citizen. "I wasn't expecting it; it was very abrupt. I started laughing, and then crying, and then laughing again."
Chaumont later appealed to church officials for reinstatement, arguing that the church had a duty to accommodate her return since her work had been impaired by menopause and depression.
But the archdiocese rejected that overture, and its insurance provider subsequently cut off Chaumont's disability coverage.
Chaumont said she has applied for hundreds of jobs without success - a fact she blames on her age, health and a lukewarm reference letter from the archdiocese.
That situation, she said, exacerbated her depression. She was hospitalized for three weeks and doctors now recommend that she no longer work.
Without disability insurance, Chaumont has had to sell her house and car to make ends meet. She avoided church services for an entire year during her ordeal.
"I'd get ready for mass in the morning and then couldn't leave the house," she said. "I just couldn't do it."
The Ontario Human Rights Code imposes on employers "a duty to accommodate" the physical and mental health disabilities of their employees. Employers are required to make workplace adjustments until they impose "undue hardship" on an organization.
Under the code, an employee with a mental illness must be treated in the same way as someone with a physical disability.
Chaumont's lawyer, Alan Riddell, said the archdiocese "did not lift a finger" to accommodate his client after she began to suffer from the effects of menopause and depression.
The message from the archdiocese, he said, is "that you will be thrown onto the street faster than hell can scorch a feather at the first sign of disability that affects your workplace performance."
Lawyers for the archdiocese are expected to argue that Chaumont was not suffering from depression at the time she was terminated.
The case will be among the first in Canada to deal with the human rights implications of menopause-related problems in the workplace.
According to the National Institute of Mental Health, the hormonal changes involved in menopause can lead to an increased risk of depression. Even women without any history of depression are vulnerable.
aduffy@ottawacitizen.com( mailto:aduffy@ottawacitizen.com )( mailto:aduffy@ottawacitizen.com )
© Copyright (c) The Ottawa Citizen
]]></text></news-item>