<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTP-PCD1-F11P-X15S"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>United States : PLAN approved to decrease emissions from close to battery plant</title><source>TendersInfo</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Air quality regulators approved a plan to decrease arsenic emissions from the Exide battery recycling plant in Vernon that was cited and temporarily closed down in 2013 because of elevated levels of pollutants leaking from the plant, it was announced on 20 March 2014.Officials with the South Coast Air Quality Management District signed off on 20 March 2014 on a Risk Reduction Plan submitted by the company that includes measures to decrease emissions.According to Exide, the company will invest $5 million into many upgrades and other steps to be made in 2014, bringing the amount the company spent since 2010 on emissions-reduction measures at its Vernon facility to over $20 million.The company claims it decreased emissions by over 70% since 2010.The Exide plant has been under close scrutiny by local and state regulators over the past year. The plant was forced to temporarily close down in 2013 because of arsenic emissions, and the South Coast Air Quality Management District sued the company in January 2014 alleging numerous air quality violations.Residents living close to Exide learned from Department of Toxic Substances Control officials in March 2014 that higher-than-normal levels of lead were found in soil samples taken from the yards of 39 homes close to the plant.Residents who gathered at a hearing hosted on 19 March 2014, night by DTSC voiced their frustration at news of possible contamination from the battery recycling facility and criticized the regulators' ability to address the problems.DTSC officials said in 2013 that the battery recycling plant has been running under a temporary DTSC permit for 32 years and is the only facility left in the state that has not been fully permitted.The firm is one of only two lead-acid battery recycling plants west of the Rockies. The plant recycles 23,000 to 41,000 batteries daily and has been in operation since 1922.Copyright © Euclid Infotech Pvt. Ltd.
]]></text></news-item>