<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTP-P381-JC8S-D07M"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>RELIGION;Ousted Baptist missionary, family seeking asylum here;</title><source>The Houston Chronicle</source><author>By Allan Turner</author><text><![CDATA[Viktor Lim, a somber man with haunted eyes, considers himself a servant of God. Authorities in Kazakhstan, the former Soviet republic in which the Baptist missionary preached the gospel of Christ, view him as a subversive enemy. To the larger world, Lim simply is a man at a life-changing crossroads.
Above all, Lim, 38, deported from the west Asian nation for failing to register his ministry with the government, is a man without a country.
On Monday, he will meet with federal authorities in Houston, the first step in gaining asylum for himself, his wife, Radmila, 33, his daughter, Greis, 13, and sons Ilya, 7, and Maxim, 6. If successful, he hopes to resume his ministry in a new American home.
If he fails, Lim will be returned to Kazakhstan where - based on the fate that has befallen other ministers - he likely would be jailed.
Lim's attorney, David Baay, a partner at Sutherland Asbill and Brennan, believes the Russian-speaking missionary has a "good case." But, he said, "The process is difficult to predict. If he returned to Kazakhstan, there's little question in my mind he would face imprisonment in a state or psychiatric facility on some trumped-up charge."
Speaking through an interpreter, Lim called the near-decade of persecution he suffered at the hands of authorities "the worst moments of my life." In a period of seven years, he was twice arrested, his telephone was tapped, police raided his church services, spies infiltrated his congregation and government agents banged on his door to conduct searches of his home.
Last summer, Lim, a Uzbekistan native who was seeking Kazakhstan citizenship, was ordered to leave the country. He and his family arrived in Houston on tourist visas in August.
"Even though the government proclaims religious freedom and sponsors an interfaith conference, the facts on the ground show that it restricts religious freedoms," said Mihra Rittmann, a central Asian researcher with Human Rights Watch.
Only Islam allowed
"The Kazakhstan government cracks down on all religious communities," added Felix Corley, a London-based observer with the European religious rights group, Forum 18. "Only one form of government-approved Islam is allowed. Other communities that are especially targeted are Protestant Christians and Jehovah's Witnesses."
Late last year, Corley reported, a Polish cardiologist was fined and deported for preaching a Jehovah's Witness sermon. In January, a Baptist in the Kazakhstan city of Semey was sentenced to 10 days in jail for failing to pay a fine assessed for attending a worship service without state permission. In February, a retired Presbyterian pastor was given a four-year suspended prison term and ordered to pay $10,800 for "harming the health" of a church member - despite the congregant's assertion that she hadn't been harmed.
'A higher authority'
Kazakhstan embassy officials could not be reached by telephone or email Friday because of Nowruz, a spring equinox holiday.
Lim moved to Kazakhstan in 1993 to study mechanical engineering and, after encountering a religiously inclined relative, became a Christian two years later. "Even when I was an atheist," he said, "I felt there was a higher authority in this world. I had a lot of life difficulties, questions and concerns. God's work gave me a blessing and power and brought me solutions."
Lim preached as a lay minister then, in 2003, entered seminary.
Upon graduation, Lim was dispatched to Ushtobe, a city of about 25,000, to found a new congregation. His flock was a modest gathering of about 40 believers, but it soon came to the attention of worried authorities.
In 2008, Lim was charged with failing to register as a foreign missionary. Arguing that he had renounced Uzbekistan citizenship in an effort to become a Kazakhstan citizen and that his church was homegrown, not foreign, Lim was found not guilty.
Still, he said, his troubles had only begun.
In 2012, police attempted a search of Lim's home. When the missionary began videotaping the encounter, officers became angry and confiscated his passport. The next day he was fined because his residency papers had expired.
Ordered to leave
In March 2013, police visited the church, where they interrogated and "threatened" church members, Lim said. Authorities tapped his telephone, planted spies in the congregation and coerced Lim's neighbors to "make statements about our worship services."
"I could not feel certain of the safety of myself or of my family," Lim said. "I couldn't get help anywhere."
In May, Lim went to court on charges related to his ministry, notably, failure to register with authorities. After a 20-minute hearing in which he was denied legal counsel and the ability to call witnesses or make a statement, Lim was convicted, assessed a fine and ordered to leave the country within 15 days. After an unsuccessful appeal - the hearing lasted 10 minutes - Lim again was ordered to leave Kazakhstan.
"I was shocked," he said in an interview. "I thought I had been doing everything right. I didn't think Kazakhstan would do such a thing."
'I had nowhere to go'
In his filing with U.S. authorities, Lim explained, "I had nowhere to go. There was no country to receive me. The prosecutor said that this was not Kazakhstan's problem, only that I was deported." Lim was told that since his application for Kazakhstan citizenship had not been formally approved, he faced imprisonment on a criminal charge if he remained.
When U.N. refugee advocates were unsuccessful in finding a new home for Lim and his family - the missionary's wife and children are Kazakhstan citizens - the missionary turned for help to his local U.S. Consulate.
To his surprise, he said, the family was granted tourist visas.
"If I will be able to stay, to get asylum, I would still like to serve in the church. I would want to praise God, and teach and help other members, to try and help the people in this world who are seeking salvation."
allan.turner@chron.com
]]></text></news-item>