<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTP-PCD1-F11P-X15M"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Ukraine : OSCE special monitoring mission to Ukraine to operate in Ukraine</title><source>TendersInfo</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The OSCE Permanent Council today adopted a decision on deployment of an OSCE special monitoring mission of international observers to Ukraine.The mission is to contribute to reducing tensions and fostering peace, stability and security; and to monitoring and supporting the implementation of all OSCE principles and commitments. To this aim monitors will, in particular, gather information and report on the security situation in the area of operation; to establish and report facts in response to specific incidents and reports of incidents; to monitor and support respect for human rights and fundamental freedoms; to facilitate the dialogue on the ground in order to reduce tensions and promote normalization of the situation.The mission will coordinate with and support the work of the OSCE executive structures and cooperate with the UN, the Council of Europe and other actors of the international community.Consisting initially of 100 civilian monitors the mission will be deployed for a period of six months. Its mandate can be renewed if requested by Ukraine. Monitors will initially be deployed to 9 Ukrainian regions. The head office will be in Kyiv.Ukrainian delegation to the OSCE made an interpretative statement in relation to this decision, stressing that its adoption should be regarded as an emergency response of the Organization to the grave conflict around the Autonomous Republic of Crimea that stemmed from military aggression by the Russian Federation aimed at annexing this integral part of Ukraine s territory.In view of the current developments and reflecting upon the existing areas of concern, Ukraine proceeds from the understanding that the mandate of the mission covers the territory of Ukraine within its internationally recognized borders, including the Autonomous Republic of Crimea, and that the deployment of the mission must start from the eastern and southern regions of Ukraine that in the light of the situation on the ground require immediate attention.Copyright © Euclid Infotech Pvt. Ltd.
]]></text></news-item>