<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTR-RJG1-DYRR-900B"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>528 Muslim Brotherhood supporters sentenced to die; 700 more in Egypt face similar charges</title><source>USA TODAY</source><author>Sarah Lynch, Special for USA TODAY</author><text><![CDATA[Rights activists lashed out Monday at the death sentences handed down against 528 supporters of the Muslim Brotherhood as part of a government campaign to squash the Islamist movement.
More than 150 of 545 defendants stood trial on charges of killing a policeman and attacking police. The others were tried in absentia, Egyptian news agency MENA reported; 16 defendants were acquitted.
The court hearings that convicted the defendants lasted two days. Defense lawyers complained they never had a chance to present their case in the trial held in the city of Minya.
"This is the largest single batch of simultaneous death sentences we've seen in recent years, not just in Egypt but anywhere in the world," Hassiba Hadj Sahraoui, deputy director of the Middle East and North Africa Program at Amnesty International, said Monday in a report.
"Imposing death sentences of this magnitude in a single case makes Egypt surpass most other countries' use of capital punishment in a year," she added.
The verdict precedes another case set to open today in which nearly 700 defendants are facing similar charges.
"The trials are part of the raging battle between the military-led government and Muslim Brotherhood," said Fawaz Gerges, professor of international relations at the London School of Economics.
"What these trials tell us is that the government has been systematically trying to weaken the Muslim Brotherhood and force them to accept the road map set by the military government."
Egypt's Foreign Ministry brushed off the criticism, saying in a statement that the judiciary is "entirely independent and is not influenced in any way by the executive branch of government."
The government has outlawed the Brotherhood and branded it a terrorist group, a claim it denies. Thousands of Brotherhood supporters have been jailed.
Monday's ruling comes nearly nine months after the Brotherhood's Mohammed Morsi was ousted from the presidency. Egypt's army chief, Gen. Abdel Fattah al-Sisi, forced Morsi aside and called for fresh parliamentary and presidential elections, which could be held this year.
]]></text></news-item>