<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTR-VBM1-JC11-102K"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Criminal Complaint Filed Against Metal Recycling Facility Owner and Property Owner for Alleged Hazardous Waste Violations</title><source>Targeted News Service</source><author>Targeted News Service</author><text><![CDATA[The California Environmental Protection Agency's Department of Toxic Substances Control issued the following news release:
The Los Angeles City Attorney has filed a criminal complaint against a Sun Valley metal recycler and the facility's property owner. The criminal enforcement action resulted from a joint investigation by the Department of Toxic Substances Control (DTSC) and the Los Angeles County Fire Department, Health Hazardous Materials Division.
Named in the complaint are Jose Guadalupe Romero, owner of JGR Metal Recycling, Inc., located at 12278 Branford Street, and the property owners, the Istrin Family Trust; the Herman and Gertrude Istrin Family Trust; and Herman Istrin, a trustee for the Istrin Family Trust.
The complaint alleges that the defendants disposed of heavy metals including chromium, lead, cadmium, and zinc at JGR Metal Recycling, Inc., which is not authorized to receive these materials. In addition, the complaint alleges that the defendants failed to minimize the potential release of hazardous waste at the Sun Valley facility; properly train personnel to manage hazardous waste; make proper hazardous waste determinations; and to label and properly manage containers of hazardous waste. The complaint charges 14 misdemeanor counts for violations of the California Health and Safety Code and one misdemeanor count for a violation of the Los Angeles Municipal Code.
"This sends a strong signal to those who violate our hazardous waste laws," said Brian Johnson, DTSC Deputy Director of the Hazardous Waste Management Program. "DTSC supports the Los Angeles City Attorney's prosecution of the facility operator as well as the property owner of the site where the alleged violations occurred."
The collaboration between DTSC and the Los Angeles County Fire Department's Health Hazardous Materials Division is part of a Metal Recycling Enforcement Initiative that DTSC launched in the fall of 2012. The initiative focuses inspection and enforcement activities on metal recycling facilities and the threats they pose to surrounding communities. DTSC has conducted 14 investigations throughout the state since the start of the initiative.
Information about the Los Angeles City Attorney's criminal complaint filed against Jose G. Romero and Herman Istrin et al is available at dtsc.ca.gov
Contact: Tim Reese, 916/323-3396, treese@dtsc.ca.gov
Copyright Targeted News Services
CC AutoTriage5rn-140325-30FurigayJane-4677808 30FurigayJane
]]></text></news-item>