<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTR-5VH1-JB4P-V0P1"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>GSMA Announces Completion Of Mobile Energy Efficiency optimisation Project In Pakistan; New Technology Partners Join Programme to Deliver Optimisation Projects</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The GSMA today announced the completion of its second Mobile Energy Efficiency (MEE) Optimisation project, located in Pakistan, working in conjunction with mobile operator Warid Telecom and systems integrator Cascadiant. The project trialled innovative energy-saving technology in Warid's network and demonstrated significant energy savings of between 30 and 60 per cent. When the solutions are rolled out across Warid's network in Pakistan, the annual savings are expected to be more than US$6 million and 19,700 tonnes of carbon dioxide emissions.
The GSMA also announced that Eltek, Enertika, PowerOasis and Purcell Systems have joined the GSMA's MEE programme as technology partners. The companies are working with the GSMA to deliver MEE Optimisation projects for mobile network operators (MNOs) who wish to reduce their networks' energy consumption and cost, as well as carbon emissions.
"It is fantastic that this MEE Optimisation project in Pakistan has already successfully demonstrated significant cost savings and emissions reductions, and is clearly showing the benefits of the service to our members," said Tom Phillips, Chief Regulatory Officer, GSMA. "The GSMA is also delighted to welcome these four companies as MEE Optimisation technology partners to deliver real cost savings and environmental benefits for operators."
The project was conducted on ten cell sites across various geographies in Pakistan, and the technical solutions were trialled on four cell sites. These included Coolsure high efficiency telecom air-conditioners, GE's Sodium Nickel Chloride Durathon* battery and a Ballard methanol fuel cell back-up power system. Deployment of the solutions across Warid's network has already begun, with 200 DC (direct current) air-conditioners being installed.
"Energy efficiency and network quality are among the key focus areas for Warid Telecom to reduce energy costs and go green, with added reliability and availability of backup power. We are delighted to carry out this MEE Optimisation project, leveraging the innovative solutions from the partners and the GSMA's expertise. We now have clear visibility of the significant potential from the MEE Optimisation project and we hope to implement these learnings and solutions network-wide, not only to improve energy and cost efficiency, but also network availability and quality," said Muhammad Irfan Chaudhry, Chief Technology Officer, Warid Telecom.
"Cascadiant was honoured to be chosen to lead this project in support of the GSMA's MEE Optimisation initiative to make networks greener cost-effectively. Cascadiant shares the view with our partners that technologies exist today that will allow operators to significantly reduce a broad range of emissions and their carbon footprint, while at the same time to reduce their energy costs and greatly improve their networks' reliability," stated Marshall Towe, Founder and CEO, Cascadiant.
Launched in 2010, the GSMA's MEE Benchmarking service is a management tool that helps MNOs measure and monitor the relative efficiency of their networks. It identifies under-performing networks and quantifies the potential efficiency gains available, typically around 10 to 25 per cent across a MNO's portfolio. More than 35 MNOs, running more than 200 networks across 145 countries, are now participating in MEE Benchmarking. MEE Optimisation is an additional service that builds on the results from the GSMA's MEE Benchmarking tool. The service uses site audits to enable an analysis of the costs and benefits of specific actions to reduce energy and emissions, and equipment trials to deliver real performance data, which together will assist MNOs in selecting the solutions that will best address their requirements.
"As mobile use continues to grow dramatically, so does the demand for energy, particularly to support network infrastructure. The GSMA estimates that electricity and diesel consumed by mobile networks globally is responsible for around 70 million tonnes of carbon dioxide emissions annually and that MNOs spend up to US$15 billion on energy use each year," continued Phillips. "Given this, energy efficiency has become a strategic priority for operators globally, as our industry seeks ways to deliver services in a sustainable, cost-effective and environmentally-friendly manner. Our Mobile Energy Efficiency programme is squarely focused on addressing these pressing issues."
For more information about the GSMA's Mobile Energy Efficiency programme, please visithttp://www.gsma.com/mee.
Notes to Editors:
*Durathon is a trademark of the General Electric Company
About the GSMA
The GSMA represents the interests of mobile operators worldwide. Spanning more than 220 countries, the GSMA unites nearly 800 of the world's mobile operators with more than 230 companies in the broader mobile ecosystem, including handset makers, software companies, equipment providers and Internet companies, as well as organisations in industry sectors such as financial services, healthcare, media, transport and utilities. The GSMA also produces industry-leading events such as the Mobile World Congress and Mobile Asia Expo. 
For more information, please visit the GSMA corporate website athttp://www.gsma.comor Mobile World Live, the online portal for the mobile communications industry, athttp://www.mobileworldlive.com.
SOURCE GSMA
]]></text></news-item>