<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTR-WN91-F0BC-M00R"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>CHICAGO'S TOP 12 COMPANIES MASSIVE FRAUD CASE: WAS IT A SCAM OR JUST BAD LUCK?</title><source>Chicago Sun-Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Americans dining out more
Make a dinner reservation.It looks like Americans' love affair with eating at home is leveling off, according to new data from the NPD Group, a market research firm that tracks eating trends.About 80 percent of meals were prepared at home in November 2013, about the same as 2012, NPD data show. The percentage of meals prepared at home has risen steadily from 77.4 percent in 2008 at the beginning of the recession."The move back home for our meals looks to be over," says Harry Balzer, NPD chief industry analyst. Many people experienced a drop in income during the recession, and people lower their food costs by using restaurants less because restaurant meals cost three times more than meals made at home, he says."About 65 percent of women prepare at least one meal a day at home. It could be for themselves or their families. About 39 percent of all men will prepare at least one meal at home," Balzer says. "That could be me putting a Pop-Tart in the toaster."
-Gannett News Service Nokia, Microsoft phone deal delayed Nokia Corp. says the sale of its mobile phone unit to Microsoft will be delayed until next month because it is still waiting for approval from regulatory authorities in Asia. The Finnish company said Monday that the $7.3 billion deal announced in September and expected to be completed in the first quarter of 2014 has been approved by the EU and U.S. authorities but "certain antitrust authorities in Asia" were still reviewing the deal. -AP BY KIM JANSSEN Federal Courts Reporter It was dry, almost absurdly complicated and a month long. But one of the biggest fraud cases ever prosecuted in Chicago boiled down to three words, prosecutor Patrick Otlewski told jurors as Eric Bloom's $500 million fraud trial wrapped up Monday. "Oodles of money." That's what Bloom, 49, of Northbrook, allegedly made by conning investors in his North Shore investment firm Sentinel Management Group. More than six years after Sentinel collapsed, costing its clients hundreds of millions of dollars, the balding, bespectacled former CEO Bloom sat expressionless during closing arguments in federal court Monday. His attorneys argue that Sentinel collapsed as a result of the worldwide 2007 credit crunch, which they called a "tsunami . . . a one of a kind, 100-year financial crisis." But prosecutors said the market crash merely exposed weaknesses at Sentinel caused by Bloom's fraud. Though Sentinel boasted that in nearly three decades of business it had "never lost a dime" of its clients' funds, Bloom for years secretly used customer cash as collateral for huge bank loans that he in turn used to make risky leveraged bets for his family's benefit, they alleged. The New Trier High School graduate covered losses by "robbing Peter to pay Paul," deciding which clients should get larger returns and which should suffer based on his own interests, rather than the performance of each client's investments, Otlewski said. Even when it became clear in August 2007 that his bad bets would destroy Sentinel, he ignored legal advice and continued to accept deposits of more than $100 million, all of which was lost, Otlewski said. "Sentinel was sinking faster than the Titanic but he didn't tell the people on board - he didn't tell his customers," the prosecutor said. But defense attorney Terry Campbell said Bloom could not be convicted because he acted in "good faith." Though Bloom was in Africa on his honeymoon as the crisis deepened in the month leading up to Sentinel's collapse, "inattentiveness is not a crime," Campbell told jurors. "It's not a crime to lose money on investments," he added. Campbell blamed Sentinel's Chief Financial Officer, Charles Mosley, for wrongdoing, telling jurors that trusting Mosley was "Bloom's mistake." Mosley previously agreed to a plea deal under which he agreed to cooperate with prosecutors. Jurors are due to hear a rebuttal argument from prosecutors Tuesday morning before beginning their deliberations. If convicted, Bloom faces up to 20 years in prison on each of 18 wire fraud counts, up to five years for investment advisor fraud, plus a huge fine. Email: kjanssen@suntimes.com Twitter: @kimjnews Cisco to invest $1B in cloud computing NEW YORK - Cisco says it plans to spend more than $1 billion over the next two years to build up its cloud computing network. Cisco plans to use the money to expand its data centers for the new service to be called Cisco Cloud Services. The move makes the San Jose, Calif.-based networking company the latest to enter an arena that caters to the growing number of companies that would rather rent computing space than build their own. One of the biggest players in the market is Amazon.com. IBM Corp. said in January that it will invest $1.2B in its cloud computing operations. -AP Roadhouse 66 pledgesto be 40% restaurant Roadhouse 66 has pledged to increase food sales to prove to its new Wrigleyville neighbors it is a restaurant. Roadhouse 66 wants to reopen at 3478 N. Clark St. after a fire destroyed its previous building last year. Owners Matt Warner, Casey Bloemke and Drew Lynch agreed to aim for at least 40 percent of sales from food to get neighbors on their side. "They would be extremely stupid if they messed up this plan. They would lose their investment," the trio's attorney, Dimitrios Christopoulos, told DNAInfo.com. GrubHub boosts size of IPO Online delivery company GrubHub plans to raise up to $177.9 million from its initial public offering, increasing the offering's expected size from $100 million a month ago. GrubHub also disclosed in a regulatory filing on Monday that it anticipates selling about 7 million shares in the IPO, priced between $20 and $22 per share. The underwriters have the option to buy up to an additional 1.1 million shares. The company's filing in February did not include such details. The company was founded in 2004, making its name catering to college students and through its quirky social media activities. In August it completed a combination with rival Seamless for an undisclosed amount. Its other brands include MenuPages and Allmenus. The Chicago company connects more than 28,000 restaurants with diners in more than 600 U.S. cities. It had 3.4 million active diners at the end of the year. An active diner is considered a diner account that has placed an order in the last year. -AP Southwest adding Midway-to-Reagan flights Southwest Airlines will add flights later this year between Chicago's Midway Airport and Reagan National Airport outside Washington. New nonstop flights between Midway and Reagan National will be added in August and some one-stop flights will be added in September, the airline announced Monday. -Bill Ruminski Toppers Pizza to add Wrigleyville restaurant You don't need a business degree to know Toppers Pizza could work in Wrigleyville. The restaurant chain, which caters to college students with late-night hours and unusual toppings (tater tots, mac and cheese), is moving into the former Swan Cleaners at 3404 N. Sheffield in August. "We are 78 percent delivery, and one of our key differentiators is that we are open until 3 a.m.," said Chris Cheek, chief development officer for Toppers, which got its start in Champaign. "We are looking for areas with a lot of night traffic, foot traffic and nightlife." The location near Wrigley Field is one of eight stores set to open in the Chicago area this year. Toppers will take its first steps into the suburbs Monday, with a store set to open across from Randhurst Village mall in Mount Prospect. -Megan Platt Half Acre to open second brewery here Half Acre Beer Co. is opening a second brewery in Chicago. The company has bought a 60,000-square-foot space at 2050 W. Balmoral, which Half Acre touts as a five-minute walk from its brewery at 4257 N. Lincoln. The two buildings will complement each other. Half Acre said the extra space also will let the company expand its distribution throughout the Chicago area. -Bill Ruminski Apple, Comcast talking streaming TV: report Apple Inc. and Comcast Corp. might team up on a streaming TV service that could take a bite out of Netflix. The project being discussed by Apple and Comcast would use an Apple set-top box and get special treatment on Comcast's cables to ensure it bypasses congestion on the Web, the Wall Street Journal reports. The deal would mark a new level of cooperation and integration between a technology company and a cable provider to modernize TV viewing. Web storage provider Box unwraps $250M IPO Online storage provider Box is the latest rapidly growing Silicon Valley company seeking to strike it rich in the stock market. The Los Altos, Calif., company took its first step toward making its market debut with a Monday filing for an initial public offering. Box Inc. indicated it hopes to raise $250 million in its IPO, although that figure usually changes as investment bankers gauge investor demand. The documents didn't set a price range for the shares or how much stock will be sold. Those details usually emerge as the IPO nears completion, a process that often takes three to four months. Box says more than 25 million registered users store documents and other content on its service. The company lost $169 million on revenue of $124 million last year. -AP AT CHICAGOGRID.COM Whasdf chicagogrid.com Your morning business briefing DID YOU GETA NEW JOB? Let us know so we can share the news. Send details to people@suntimes.com, and come back to see who's making news. DID YOU GETA NEW JOB? Let us know so we can share the news. Send details to people@suntimes.com, and come back to see who's making news.
]]></text></news-item>