<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTR-PY41-DXH0-K015"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Rana Plaza compensation begins</title><source>United News of Bangladesh</source><author> UNBconnect</author><text><![CDATA[The much anticipated process for the compensation of the victims of Rana Plaza tragedy began on Monday following a fresh documentation of the victims by the newly formed Rana Plaza Claims Administration.
Rana Plaza Claims Administration is operating under the auspices of the recently formed Rana Plaza Coordination Committee, which is composed of the ILO as the lead agency, and of the government, factory owners, trade unions, buyers, retailers, national and international non-government organisations.
The collapse of Rana Plaza on April 24 last year turned out to be the biggest disaster in the readymade garment (RMG) sector of the country, killing 1135 workers, according to the latest official estimate.
The Administration, headed by former UN official Moitaba Kazazi as the executive commissioner, is expected to complete the claims processing and the payment within the next six months.
Injured survivors of the disaster will also be sent to the Centre for Rehabilitation of the Paralised (CRP) at Savar to go through a thorough medical check-up.
"Today we have started working, we will continue it for months," Kazazi told the Associate Press.
"But the whole process will be completed in six months," he added.
The fresh move by the high-profile Administration may fulfill its pledge to provide the proper compensation to the injured and the relatives of the dead in quick time, through a credible and fresh documentation process, but the fate of the relatives of hundreds of the `missing' workers as well as of those survivors who are living with a mental trauma after the collapse still remains undecided.
There is not a single day without the visit of some relatives of the `missing' workers to the ruins of Rana Plaza. Some of them even dare to break into the barbed fences put around site and look if there is anything identifiable with the lost member of the family.
Jannatul Sifat, 22, who was rescued on the third day of the collapse from the 6th floor of the building, lost her younger sister Shanta, who worked on the 4th floor.
Shanta is still `missing', and Sifat is still visiting the collapse site almost everyday to search for the remains.
Sifat has been chased away by the police several times, but she did not give up the search.
"Everyday, bones (human bones) are coming out from the site, but the police is repeatedly denying. You see they've hid some of retrieved bones into the water tank (a dysfunctional concrete-tank of the collapsed building)," she told UNB on Monday.
Asked about the condition of her family after the collapse, Sifat said, "My parents are too old to live with such a shock. My father is not physically well, but he is still earning by rickshaw-pulling."
Asked whether she is trying to get a job again she said, "I'm knocking on one office after another, or coming here in search of my sister almost everyday. I tried to find a job in the garments several times, but did not get it."
"Each time I enter into a high building, horror engulfs meâ(EURO)¦I run out," said Sifat.
"But I need a job too badly for my family," she said.
]]></text></news-item>