<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTR-HCK1-JCS0-D0SH"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Lloyds accused of short-changing PPI claimants; COVER STORY</title><source>i-Independent Print Ltd</source><author>Tom Harper INVESTIGATIONS REPORTER</author><text><![CDATA[One of Britain's biggest banks has cost victims of the payment protection insurance (PPI) scandal tens of millions of pounds by wrongly cutting their compensation awards, a new investigation claims.
Lloyds Banking Group, which is 33 per cent owned by the taxpayer, has been cutting payouts to victims who were mis-sold the notorious insurance policies intended to cover loan payments if borrowers found themselves unable to work. In many cases, the fine print meant that customers could never make a claim.
An investigation by the BBC has uncovered evidence to suggest the bank provided more than one in four PPI claimants with "alternative redress" - a loophole that allows Lloyds to assume victims who were wrongly sold single-premium PPI policies on credit cards or loans would have bought a cheaper regular premium PPI policy instead. Single premium policies involve one-off payments, rather than monthly outlays.
Over the last year, the bank has allegedly been often cutting the cost of the cheaper regular premium policy from the full payout it would otherwise have been required to pay.
Claims management companies told BBC Radio 4 that when they challenge Lloyds' reduced offers, the Financial Ombudsman has overruled the bank in every single case.
Cliff D'Arcy, an expert on the payment protection insurance scandal, said he believes Lloyds has banked tens of millions of pounds over the last year by wrongly deducting the payments. "What's happening here is a taxpayer-sponsored bank depriving taxpayers of their rightful compensation by using a loophole," he said. Research into the "alternative redress" loophole was conducted by the Professional Financial Claims Association (PFCA). It analysed more than 70,000 PPI offers and found more than 25 per cent of Lloyds claimants were being wrongly hit with the increased charges. It estimated that affected Lloyds customers were worse off by more than £1,100 on average.
In a statement, Lloyds Banking Group said: "There are a small number of loan customers who were eligible and suitable for PPI and who bought a single premium PPI policy...Since February 2013 and on this basis, we have offered comparative redress only on loans PPI complaints."
Britain's Biggest Banking Scandal is broadcast on Radio 4 tonight.
Lloyds Banking Group has set aside more than £10bn to deal with PPI compensation claims.
]]></text></news-item>