<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTR-J4W1-DY9P-N05S"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Co-op Bank shelves float and calls for £400m cash; New black hole of PPI and mis-selling costs pushes losses for year to £1.3bn Co-op bondholders wary of new capital raising</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Harry Wilson</author><text><![CDATA[THE Co-op Bank has admitted its plans for an imminent stock market flotation are probably over after being forced to launch a new cash call just months after a £1.5bn emergency recapitalisation.
The struggling lender said it needed to raise a further £400m from investors after revealing its losses for last year may be as high as £1.3bn, following the discovery of hundreds of millions of pounds of new compensation costs.
Niall Booker, the chief executive of the Co-op Bank, said the cash call probably meant plans for an initial public offering of the business were "some way off", adding that a series of reports into failure at the lender did not "present a perfect backdrop to an IPO".
The Co-op Bank had hoped to list this year, but the requirement to set aside the extra money for compensation claims related to payment protection insurance (PPI), interest rate swap mis-selling, mortgages misselling and "technical breaches" of the Consumer Credit Act have effectively killed this plan.
The new fundraising will be unwelcome news to the Co-op Group, which owns a 30pc stake in the bank, following last year's debtfor-equity swap that saw the troubled mutual give up control of the lender to its bondholders after a £1.5bn capital hole led to a race to save the business.
If the Co-op were to take up its full allocation of rights it would cost the organisation £120m, but because of its own financial problems it is far from clear whether it will play its full part in the capital raising. Mr Booker said the Co-op Bank had already planned with its advisers at UBS for the eventuality that its former parent was unable to take part.
"If the Co-op doesn't take up its share, UBS is pretty happy that it can be placed elsewhere," he said.
A spokesman for the Co-op said: "As a shareholder in the bank we will consider our position in relation to the proposed additional capital raising and make a further statement as and when appropriate."
The Co-op Bank had said its capital raising would take its core Tier 1 capital ratio, the main measure of a lender's financial strength, to just below 9pc, but the new provisions and losses mean it is expected to have ended 2013 at 7.2pc, close to the regulatory minimum of 7pc.
The lender will give more details of the cash call and its finances with the release of its annual report and accounts on April 8. Mr Booker said he was unable to guarantee there could not be further cash calls on shareholders, but he hoped the worst was behind the business. "Nobody is ever going to say there is not an outside possibility [of a further capital raising], but this is our best analysis," he said.
Talks have already been held with investors about the fund raising, though because of secrecy requirements none were given advance warning of the announcement.
Some of the bondholders who held debt at the time of the equity swap have already exited their positions amid fears over the bank's future. "I am wary of more land mines," said one former investor in THE Co-op Bank .
The Treasury Select Committee has held public hearings to question former directors, executives, and regulators on the lender's near failure. The Financial Conduct Authority and the Prudential Regulation Authority (PRA), the two main financial watchdogs, are conducting reviews. The PRA, run by the Bank of England, is not understood to have played a part in pushing the Co-op Bank to launch its new capital raising.
One of Japan's largest banks, Sumitomo Mitsui Financial Group, has reportedly approached Royal Bank of Scotland to buy its US retail business, Chapters, before its stock market flotation this year. Executives from the two banks met recently to discuss a potential deal, according to the Wall Street Journal. RBS declined to comment.
Comment: B2
]]></text></news-item>