<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTR-7WG1-F0JP-W35S"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Cocktails and cash splashed</title><source>Herald Sun (Australia)</source><author>JOHN MASANAUSKAS</author><text><![CDATA[A COCKTAIL party awards night for the federal human rights watchdog lost money despite $35,000 in sponsorship and most guests paying their own way.
Staff at the Australian Human Rights Commission were worried the $60,000 party last December would be seen as being too pricey.
And the lavish event on the Sydney waterfront did lose money, documents released to the Herald Sun under Freedom of Information laws reveal.
The "not to be missed" awards night at the Museum of Contemporary Art was dominated by problems such as -poverty, homelessness and disadvantage. However, guests -endured nothing of the sort as they nibbled on canapes such as seared marinated yellowfin tuna and fresh king prawns, while sipping on premium wine and beer.
Host Craig Reucassel from The Chaser was paid $2100 for his services plus $280 travel expenses, the documents show. Catering, room hire and "theming" at the human rights awards cost more than $33,000.
Commission staff had prepared a 16-page report on venue options, listing advantages and disadvantages of each.
The Museum of Contemporary Art was "perceived as expensive", but the harbour venue was chosen over the much cheaper option at Sydney's Government House.
The function made an $1800 loss, despite $10,000 in sponsorship from the Department of Social Services and $25,000 from other sponsors.
John Roskam, from free market think tank the Institute of Public Affairs, accused the commission of hypocrisy because it had previously complained it wasn't funded to pay for new human rights commissioner Tim Wilson - a former IPA employee.
"On the one hand they say they can't fund the salary for a commissioner but on the other hand they can spend $60,000 on an exclusive cocktail party," Mr Roskam said.
Commission president Gillian Triggs said that she and her colleagues had paid to attend the awards night, and most of the costs were covered by participants and sponsors.
"I really do take umbrage at the idea that somehow because you're a human rights body you've got to do things in some sort of shabby way," she said.
"We don't want to be in a village hall in Koo Wee Rup just because we haven't got a lot of money." Dr Triggs said the awards night was a chance to recognise the voluntary work of thousands of Australians.
john.masanauskas@news.com.au Watch video highlights of the party at heraldsun.com.au
Catering: $26,392 Audiovisual: $12,879 Room hire: $4200 Aboriginal welcome to country: $400Craig Reucassel's fee and expenses: $2380
]]></text></news-item>