<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTR-7WG1-F0JP-W362"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Hird denied justice</title><source>Herald Sun (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Hird denied justice THANK you, Mark Robinson ("Hird outcry old news", HS, Mar 22), for your balanced and timely comments.
The fact remains that James Hird has not been found guilty of anything. ASADA has charged no one at Essendon with any offence after more than a year of investigations.
On the lack of solid evidence presented so far, neither the AFL nor ASADA have successfully and independently found anyone guilty of anything in relation to this issue.
The failure of both the AFL and ASADA to even interview the key witness shows all the hallmarks of the denial of natural justice.
Peter Baulch, Baxter
Dollars drive roo cull THE announcement of a trial commercial kangaroo industry in Victoria is disappointing and disturbing, with serious questions left unanswered.
This "trial" will leave kangaroos vulnerable as there will be no tagging system to ensure only the authorised quota is shot, or scientific surveys to ensure the preservation of local populations. This is not just a matter of using shot kangaroos; this is a profit-driven industry, and a harshly cruel one.
There has been no consultation with the Victorian public or any independent animal welfare organisations. How can Victorians trust that animal welfare will be a priority now that kangaroos have dollar signs on their heads?
Nikki Sutterby, president, Australian Society for Kangaroos
Cyclists are road hogs I WORK in the CBD so drive there more than I want to.
Most of the formerly wide city streets Melbourne was famous for have been ruined over recent years and turned into single-lane bottlenecks. The solution to the problem of traffic and cyclists already exists and just needs to be enforced.
Swanston and Latrobe streets have basically been given to cyclists, so force them to use those streets.
Cyclists should be banned from Collins and Elizabeth streets (too narrow) and if they need to cross east-west, use the little streets (Little Collins, etc) and only be allowed to go in the correct direction of these one-way streets. There are already signs posted at each end of Bourke St banning cyclists.
Giving in to even more outrageous demands from these road hogs will only lead to further driver frustration and make the CBD a place no one will want to go to.
P. Otteraa, Pascoe Vale South
Knocked out by aggro AS a 50-plus cyclist who has only been riding in Melbourne for the past 18 months, I am surprised at the aggressiveness towards cyclists.
I have already been knocked off my bike by a car that went through a give way sign while I had the right of way and was in a bicycle lane, only to be told it was my fault.
What I find difficult to read is that we are "aggressive". Most of the time I feel totally vulnerable; there is nothing between me and the asphalt.
K. Young, Abbotsford
City's drivers rubbish ANY observation of road user behaviour in Melbourne will quickly reveal that ignorance, contempt and incompetence are common on its roads.
Yet in the "world's most livable city" you are far more likely to be caught and penalised for failing to touch on with your myki than you are for driving dangerously.
David Jones, Two Rocks, WA
Culture at a price MIKE Tyler's letter (YS, Mar 22) beggars belief. A $125 million cost for the Casey Cultural Centre will definitely incur increased rates for ratepayers.
He fails to explain how it will be funded - the inference is that it will be by loans and external funding.
Who will pay the interest? Who is contributing to the "external funding"?Arvo Talvik, Cranbourne
]]></text></news-item>