<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-0RH1-DY2T-F0HG"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>BoC looks at changes $10T rate; Cdor 'essential' to financial system, Bank of Canada deputy governor says</title><source>National Post's Financial Post &amp; FP Investing (Canada)</source><author>John Greenwood, Financial Post</author><text><![CDATA[Until recently the Canadian version of Libor was just an obscure acronym known only to a handful of traders, but it is "probably the most important benchmark" in the country and the Bank of Canada is taking steps to rein it in, one of the central bank's deputies said yesterday.
Cdor, short for the Canadian Dealer Offered Rate, is used to price an enormous amount of financial products, everything from plain vanilla consumer loans to complex interest rate swaps. This means it underpins a huge portion of the Canadian economy, over $10-trillion in total, Timothy Lane, deputy governor of the Bank of Canada said on Monday.
It was the first time an official from the Bank of Canada or any other regulator in this country has produced such an estimate.
"We will examine how these posted rates are currently used by market participants to see how any possible changes could affect market functioning," Mr. Lane said in a speech on Monday at York University's Schulich School of Business.
"Given Cdor's importance, making sure it is robust is essential to the whole Canadian financial system."
Since 2012, a string of international lenders such as Barclays PLC, Citigroup Inc., JPMorgan Chase &; Co. and the Royal Bank of Scotland have paid more than US$6-billion in settlements and fines over allegations they manipulated Libor. Now investors have begun launching civil suits and experts predict that by the time the dust settles, the total amount paid will be close to US$35-billion.
Like Libor the Canadian rate is calculated by a group of banks with scant regulatory oversight. After Libor was exposed, policymakers around the world started working together to shore up confidence on major financial benchmarks that are viewed as lynchpins of the financial system.
Still, concern is starting to spread to other benchmarks including foreign exchange and gold.
The London gold fix, used by miners, jewellers and investors to value bullion, may have been manipulated for a decade, claims a draft research paper by a professor from New York University's Stern School of Business that was obtained by Bloomberg.
The foreign exchange market is one of the biggest in the world and regulators are now looking into allegations that traders at some big international banks have been sharing client information in a bid to profit.
"The suspicion of such collusion - as suggested by some emails and chat-room discussions that have come to light - is being taken very seriously," Mr. Lane said.
Though the issues around benchmarks generally has sparked much worry in this country, it's Cdor that has the biggest potential for problems because, unlike the others, it's use is almost entirely restricted to the Canadian market.
Mr. Lane said it is used to price some $130-billion of floating rate notes, about US$9.3-trillion in Canadian-dollar interest rate swaps, and over $750-billion of exchange-traded derivatives.
The rate is set every morning at 10:15am, through submissions of provided by Canada's six big banks and HSBC Bank Canada. Unlike Libor, the rate at which a group of lenders think they can access funding, Cdor is more grounded in the market because banks are committed to lending based on Cdor. As a result it is "less likely" to be manipulated, Mr. Lane said.
However, he acknowledged that problems exist.
A review by the Investment Dealers Regulatory Organization of Canada published a year ago revealed a number of issues with Cdor including lack of clear regulatory oversight and "inconsistencies" among submitting banks in procedures used to calculate
Cdor. There was also "a failure in some cases to document those procedures," Mr. Lane said.
Now Canadian regulators are working together to fix those problems and the Office of the Superintendent of Financial Institutions - the top banking authority - has been tasked with overseeing the submissions processes of the banks involved.
Investors welcomed the action but for some it may not be soon enough. Nova Scotia recently announced plans to issue debt priced off a benchmark other than Cdor. The province recently announced plans to sell floating rate notes based on something called the Canadian Overnight Repo Rate, or Corra. One of the benefits of Corra, according to provincial officials, is that it's set by the Bank of Canada rather than "a group of individuals" at a bank. It was the first time any province had taken such a step.
Mr. Lane said the Bank of Canada is aware of the interest in the new benchmark.
The central bank "has begun to look at what changes may be needed to Corra given the new... [international] standards. I expect that, as it progresses, that work will need involvement from a range of stakeholders."
jgreenwood@nationalpost.com
]]></text></news-item>