<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-F8F1-F0JP-W2KT"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Going with the flow</title><source>The Courier Mail (Australia)</source><author>LIAM WALSH</author><text><![CDATA[THE water business at the centre of a NSW corruption inquiry pushed hard into Queensland, hiring corporate bluebloods with links to state utilities and politics.
Australian Water Holdings also spent thousands of dollars on both sides of politics and entertained Ipswich's mayor.
The company is at the centre of the inquiry by the Independent Commission Against Corruption, which is examining allegations including that AWH charged inflated expenses to a Sydney water utility.
The inquiry has not raised allegations of wrongdoing by Queenslanders or AWH's Queensland entities. Documents, from company and electoral records to council declarations, illustrate how AWH tried to garner a Queensland foothold.
AWH worked on water infrastructure for new developments. It hoped to expand, and the inquiry has heard Eddie Obeid Jr, son of former NSW Labor powerbroker Eddie Snr, worked for its Queensland business.
Electoral records state that in 2010 AWH paid $2200 to the Queensland ALP for a fundraiser. The ALP has asked ICAC to clarify if this was charged to the Sydney water utility, in which case it will be refunded.
AWH entities also either donated or spent $10,300 at LNP-linked events, such as Brisbane council fundraisers. The state LNP is returning the funds because of the AWH allegations.
AWH established a now-defunct subsidiary, Australian Water Queensland, whose executive chairman was Wayne Myers, a former director of state-owned energy retailer Ergon. He once had ALP ties through his friend, former state treasurer Terry Mackenroth.
Mr Myers said he was approached due to his utilities experience. "We tried to do some (public private partnerships) ... but we never got anywhere," he said.
Mr Myers said he had not been aware of what had allegedly occurred in Sydney, and had not seen anything inappropriate here. "I value my business reputation up here, (as) I'm sure do all the other people who were involved," he said.
Another AWQ director was Tony Bellas, a former Treasury bureaucrat, chairman of ERM Power among board roles, and former chief executive at state-owned energy companies. A third director was former Liberal senator Santo Santoro, now a lobbyist.
Neither returned calls.
AWH entities won a retainer with Sekisui House, a Japanese giant developing an Ipswich housing estate.
A register of interests by Ipswich Mayor Paul Pisasale listed six occasions when AWH entities provided hospitality such as dinner. But he said only a couple of times were for water business, with others listed because he met with AWH chief executive Nick Di Girolamo, but in Mr Di Girolamo's capacity as Italian Chamber of Commerce president. The chamber had provided flood support for Ipswich.
Cr Pisasale said AWH entities had approached Ipswich, and council looked at its NSW projects. "We never went ahead," he said.The inquiry has heard questions about whether AWH in NSW was funding some Queensland activities, but it also heard AWQ won two Queensland contracts worth $500,000.
]]></text></news-item>