<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-K201-F09T-F00D"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Company fined $230K for burying chemical waste at DeLand site</title><source>News-Journal (Daytona Beach, Florida)</source><author>Dinah Voyles Pulver, Dinah Voyles Pulver dinah.pulver@news-jrnl.com</author><text><![CDATA[State environmental officials on Monday notified a Utah-based chemical company that it would be required to pay more than $230,000 in penalties for improperly disposing of chemical waste products at a manufacturing facility on Hazen Road in DeLand and another in Palmetto, Fla.
In a letter to the Thatcher Company of Salt Lake City, Utah, on Monday, the Florida Department of Environmental Protection said the company also will be required to take immediate corrective actions and clean up the contamination. Department officials said they are also talking with law enforcement officials to determine whether criminal charges are warranted.
"When a business takes actions that are calculated, grossly negligent, and potentially harmful to the environment, we will pursue formal enforcement with maximum penalties," DEP district director Jeff Prather stated in a news release on Monday evening.
A call and email to Thatcher's Utah headquarters on Monday were not returned. According to its website, the Thatcher Company is a "major chemical supplier and distributor" with operations in seven states, supplying clients in the U.S., Canada, Mexico, Europe and the Pacific Rim.
Department officials stated the facility on Hazen Road in DeLand manufactures chemicals for use by water treatment plants and food production plants.
The department inspected the DeLand plant last August after receiving an anonymous complaint that chemicals were being buried on site, state documents show. Inspectors reported finding a "significant amount of waste and contaminated soil." Documents show inspectors discovered plant employees had buried ferric sulfate sludge in seven or eight pits, anywhere from six to 15 feet in depth, in a wooded area behind the site during 2010 and 2011.
The department stated the sludge is a byproduct of a production process that takes place at the plant.
In an email sent to the department just a couple of days after the initial inspection, Darren Bauer of Thatcher said the company's own internal investigation confirmed that sludge had been "disposed of improperly" at the DeLand site.
Bauer wrote the company had suspended the plant manager and was "committed to taking whatever steps are needed to resolve this situation."
The department eventually estimated the facility's staff had buried between 100,000 to 200,000 thousand pounds of ferric sulfate sludge. Department spokeswoman Christine Daniel said the company was advised last August to cease the improper activity and no other burying took place.
In subsequent inspections, department inspectors also found the facility had improperly discharged waste products at its facility in Palmetto, Fla., including discharging pollutants into a nearby stormwater management system.
State documents also conclude the company failed to train its employees in hazardous waste management, did not determine whether hazardous sludge was being generated, failed to notify officials of its hazardous waste activities and did not properly identify containers or minimize releases from "roll-off" containers.
In a warning letter and proposed consent order DEP sent to Thatcher on Monday, the department ordered the company to immediately comply with all department rules and begin correcting its earlier violations.
The department also directed the company to develop a contingency plan, employee training, an audit and evaluation of all the facility's practices and options for improvement.
The company was asked to respond within 20 days.
]]></text></news-item>