<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-14S1-JC6P-C40V"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Sequoyah County Agrees To Settle 19-Year-Old Sequoyah Fuels Lawsuit</title><source>Times Record (Fort Smith, Arkansas)</source><author>Mary L. Crider, Times Record, Fort Smith, Ark.</author><text><![CDATA[March 24--SALLISAW -- Sequoyah County commissioners agreed 3-0 Monday to accept a settlement offer in an almost 19-year-old tax lawsuit from officials representing the defunct Sequoyah Fuels uranium-processing plant at Gore.
Following a 23-minute executive session during which the commissioners conferred with Assistant District Attorney Stephanie Milburn, Sequoyah County Assessor Donna Graham and Gore Schools Superintendent Lucky McCrary, Commission Chairman Steve Carter said the commission "wooled" the matter around for a couple of years, and has now decided to accept Sequoyah Fuels' offer of 50 percent of everything in the escrow account.
No Sequoyah Fuels representatives attended the meeting Monday.
"Like I told them, it's like dumping sugar in the ocean. When you first put it there, it looks like a lot, then it's gone," Carter said.
District 3 Commissioner Jim Rogers said the Sequoyah Fuels-maintained escrow account has about $3.2 million in it. Carter said the county would also receive half the about $800,000 in accumulated interest earned by the account.
During the 1995-2011 tax dispute, the company deposited the amount of its property tax payments annually into the escrow account.
The uranium-processing plant was closed in 1993 for federal safety violations and contamination with radioactive materials. The county has contended the 1,800-acre property continues to hold value comparable to its value when it was operating. The company contended the 300 acres and materials deemed contaminated diminished its value.
In 2008, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, a federal regulatory agency, approved Sequoyah Fuels' $32 million cleanup plan. In November 2009, Sequoyah Fuels President John Ellis told the Times Record the entire cleanup process would cost about $65 million.
Gore Public Schools stands to benefit most from the settlement. In line with the way county tax revenue is distributed, the school district will receive a total of 67 percent of the ultimate settlement amount -- 52.3 percent for the school district's general fund, 6.7 percent for its building fund and 8 percent for its sinking fund, according to the county Commission and Assessor's Office.
McCrary said school officials will not know how the tax settlement will impact the district until the matter finishes playing out through the legal system.
In 2009, former Gore Superintendent Keith Kincaid said the tax dispute between the county and Sequoyah Fuels, the district's largest property-tax payer, was one of three main factors in the school district's financial woes then. Other factors were the recession economy and the state education budget cuts associated with the drop in revenues during the economic slump.
In 2010 under the leadership of then-Superintendent Monte Thompson, the county and the Gore community stepped up to help ease costs for the then-struggling school district, donating materials for needed maintenance and the means to haul it, donating labor. Volunteers filled cafeteria and office positions. Thompson himself worked from February through the June 30 end of the school year for a $1 a month salary.
Graham noted that the people who suffered most as the tax settlement case played out were the students attending school at Gore.
"It's time the school benefited from something," Graham said following the Commission's settlement vote.
___ (c)2014 Times Record (Fort Smith, Ark.) Visit Times Record (Fort Smith, Ark.) at www.swtimes.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>