<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-HRM1-DYJJ-P4F4"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>ELECTRONICS AFTERLIFE</title><source>Home News Tribune (East Brunswick, New Jersey)</source><author>By, Christina LoBrutto</author><text><![CDATA[Threatened by economic factors, local electronic waste (e-waste) recycling programs face cancellation, according to a statewide meeting sponsored by the Association of New Jersey Recyclerson March 4.
Representatives of local towns and counties that offer residents free collection of old computers and televisions met with private electronic processors and product manufacturers to discuss the problems affecting e-waste recycling and possible solutions.
"Cape May County has already canceled its e-waste collection events, and other counties and municipalities may follow if a solution isn't found," said Dominick D'Altilio, ANJR president. "A recycling company that handled all the e-waste collected in a number of South Jersey towns has already stopped taking the material and is requiring the collection sites to pay for pick up and recycling."
In 2010, the state's e-waste recycling law prohibited the disposal of TVs and computers in landfills. Shifting the cost of recycling residential electronic products from government to manufacturers, the law mandates that TV and computer makers cover the cost of the recycling of electronics that are turned in by individual owners and small businesses with less than 50 employees.
Guy Watson, director of the Department of Environmental Protection's Office of Recycling, said that 8 to 9 million pounds of e-waste were processed in 2010. By 2011, the total jumped to more than 40 million pounds.
Due to economic trends, a program that began with much success now faces difficult times. D'Altilio explained that the cost is shifting back to the government collection sites as manufacturers have pulled back from funding and collecting the worn-out electronics. He predicted that such economic factors could spread across the state.
"We know that many municipalities and counties are taking a hard look at funding their e-waste programs and some may decide to shut them down," he said.
According to ANJR board member Wayne DeFeo, an environmental consultant who facilitated the discussion, municipal and county e-waste recyclers are experiencing increased costs for labor, material handling, public education and event coordination.
"At the same time, the number of recyclers competing for a county or town's e-waste is decreasing and some who formerly paid for the material are now charging for it," DeFeo said. "As contracts with recyclers expire, governing bodies are going to be forced to make some tough decisions."
Private industry electronic processors say that manufacturers are paying them less to collect and process the products, and end markets for the material are disappearing. According to a manufacturer representative at the meeting, some recyclers are being paid less because the number of recyclers participating in the program is consolidating and television makers are experiencing fewer sales nationally.
Diana Vigilante, manager of Somerset County Public Works Solid Waste Management, says that the county is under contract with New Tech Recycling until July 2015. At that time, she understands that future contracts may change.
"I'm sure the economics will play a large part in any future bids that the county puts out for vendors handling our e-waste," Vigilante said. "Right now we're receiving a small amount of revenue in return for electronics. I was at the meeting and I understand South Jersey's concerns and how upsetting it is. Nobody wants it to run amok and cover the state of New Jersey."
New Tech Recycling, located in Somerset, services five counties: Somerset, Union, Hunterdon, Warren and Mercer. Jim Entwistle, president of New Tech, says he is one of the luckier vendors in the state.
"I've been very fortunate as a recycler to be covered by a manufacturer program," he said. "What that means is that I have a very strong relationship with manufacturer groups that look to me as a recycler to handle the processing of their allocated weight within the state."
Entwistle cites the use of brokers as middlemen as one of the factors in the current problems with e-waste programs.
"For example, a TV manufacturer will go to a middleman, or a broker, and that broker will then go to the marketplace and look for weight," he explained. "So they'll come to someone like myself and ask if they have weight that's available. In that case, I'm not dealing with a direct group. In essence I'm working with a middleman. These middlemen are driving the prices down that recyclers would get paid to handle the material."
The second problem, according to Entwistle, is the availability of weight.
"The essence of the problem is that where I have coverage and manufacturers come to me to seek out weight for their programs, other recyclers have not been approached by manufacturers," he said. "If they have, they've been approached at a very low rate, and the rate does not make it feasible to do the collection and proper processing of the material. Some of these other recyclers are being asked to recycle the right way, but they're not being fairly compensated. We all want to do the right thing. It's a very interesting time in our business."
In addition, Entwistle says some manufacturers are making use of out-of-state recyclers.
"It doesn't seem logical to me to see weight going to out-of-state recyclers who are not participating in the state or are not held to the same standards that we are in New Jersey," he said. "I think there needs to be firmer accounting by the manufacturers to the DEP as to where this material is coming from. Every manufacturer wants us to handle the material the right way. They just don't want to pay a lot of money for it, and I don't blame them. The economy is hurting them like it's hurting everybody else. If their new sales are down, they don't want to pay a lot of money recycling old TVs. Except at the same time, the law is the law."
Entwistle believes a modification to the current law may be a solution to some of the problems recyclers are facing.
"When you have a recycler who represents between seven and nine counties in a region and no manufacturer coverage, it raises the question as to why," he explained. "If these manufacturers are offering free and convenient collection, why aren't they covering someone who's doing the collection? I think the intent of the law is a good one and people are trying to do the right thing, but the implementation of the law really holds people up. It should be an unlimited type of law, meaning that whatever is collected should be under the law."
While no immediate solutions emerged at the meeting, ANJR Executive Director Marie Kruzan said that the meeting had started a "valuable discussion among all the stakeholders and the discussion will continue because the current system is unsustainable." In addition, ANJR has created a task force that is working to develop recommendations to keep e-waste recycling programs possible.
Editorial Intern Christina LoBrutto can be reached at clobrutto@njpressmedia.com or 908-243-6602.
]]></text></news-item>