<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-YW11-JB1X-W0J0"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Expert warns about upcoming massive power outages in Kyrgyzstan in 2014-2015 winter</title><source>Central Asian News Services</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The current water volume in the Toktogul dam is 9.2 billion cubic meters, which is for 2.2 billion cubic meters less than in the previous year, Head of the Research Institute for Use of Water and Energy Resources in Central Asia Ernest Karybekov said in its statement quoted by Tazabek.
"With the miserly export of electricity and rotational blackouts this summer by October 1, 2014, the dam will have only 14-14.5 billion cubic meters of water," the expert added.
This means that after the next heating season by April 1, 2015, the water level may drop to 6.5 billion cubic meters. "This is recurrence of the situation in the cold winters of 2007, 2008 and 2009," Mr. Karybekov claimed.
To keep water, power companies will have to practice wide power outages. Not rotational blackouts will be made, but massive outages. The accidents will occur in the grid and substations, he said.
Corruption and impunity led to disastrous situation in the energy system of Kyrgyzstan. The shortage of water in the Toktogul dam will affect the neighboring economies, Ernest Karybekov said, adding these are not threats, but mere calculations.
"The people of Kyrgyzstan need to prepare for the upcoming winter on their own. The top managers of the energy system are incapable of adopting measures other than power outages and raise of electricity tariffs," Ernest Karybekov emphasized.
He compared the current condition of the country's energy system with the British Titanic passenger liner.
"The blame for the terrible tragedy rests solely on the captain and his crew, who died. They were blamed for the high speed of the liner in the dangerous ice area not far from Newfoundland. Our energy system with its team of managers is also moving at a high speed right into the iceberg," he suggested.
Ernest Karybekov promised to suggest solutions of the problem some time later.
]]></text></news-item>