<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-H2X1-F0NV-F14P"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Exxon Valdez Anniversary: What Have We Learned and Are We Better Prepared?</title><source>Cordova Times (Alaska)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[March 24th is the 25th Anniversary of the Exxon Valdez oil spill disaster. For years, Exxon fought Alaskans in court to avoid paying their fair share of damages. Sean Parnell was a lobbyist for the firm representing Exxon while Exxon was trying to avoid paying Alaska fishermen for damages from Valdez. In an unprecedented decision, Exxon succeeded in avoiding most of the payments it should have made to Alaska fishermen whose livelihoods were damaged or destroyed.
The oil spill devastated families in this region. Yet our Governor helped Exxon avoid paying fishermen and their families for damages from the oil spill. For twenty years, Exxon fought against Alaskans in court to reduce compensation payments by 90%. As Exxon litigated against Alaskans, some of our fishermen who filed damages claims passed away. Exxon's long lawsuit against Alaskans was unconscionable.
While salmon stocks in Prince William Sound recovered, the Sound's herring fishery hasn't. The Valdez disaster and Exxon's attacks on Alaskans in court are a reminder that we need leaders who put Alaska first.
This is the perfect time for Alaskans to take stock of our ability to prevent and to respond to both man-made and natural disasters. Since the Exxon Valdez ran aground, the oil shippers, the State, and the Federal government have made impressive strides in preventing another large spill in Prince William Sound. The shipping lanes for trans-Alaskan oil are far safer now than twenty-five years ago. But the Arctic is warming and we will soon have shipping in the Bering Strait and along our Arctic Coast. We are not prepared to prevent or to respond to accidents in those difficult waters, but we should get prepared to ensure Alaska benefits from Arctic development
Since the State established an Oil and Hazardous Substance Prevention and Response Fund decades ago, it has allowed the real value of the monies going to prevention efforts in the Department of Environmental Conservation to be reduced substantially. The Spill Response Fund, intended to allow the State to respond quickly to catastrophic spills, is now barely half of what it used to be in real dollars, due to inflation. It is easy to allow preparedness to decrease when we are between emergencies, but protecting the public requires us to be ready at all times.
The State's Division of Homeland Security and Emergency Management has developed good advice for families and for communities on how to be personally prepared. But we know from 1989 and 1964 that we cannot allow the State's own prevention efforts, aimed at ships and other carriers of hazardous substances, to decline. And we cannot allow our ability to response with personnel, transportation, and advance planning and training to decrease when we are facing new challenges in the Arctic.
Recent legal battles, including Exxon's attempts to avoid paying Alaska fishermen from oil spill damages, are a reminder that we need a Governor who puts Alaska first. Sean Parnell worked as a lobbyist for the company representing Exxon while Exxon was trying to avoid paying what it owed to Alaskans. More recently, Parnell went to court on behalf of the Pebble Partnership, once again siding with Outsiders over Alaska fishermen.
Governor Parnell, for too long, has been working for Outside corporations-not Alaskans. Our governor should put Alaska first, not sell us out to well-funded special interest groups. We need a Governor who will ALWAYS fight for Alaska, and will never help Outside corporations fleece Alaska fishermen.
It is not a question of if, but when the next disaster strikes. Alaskans deserve a state government that leads the way in readiness. Without careful planning and solid preparations, Alaskans and Alaskan resources are put at risk, and we cannot afford that.
Mike Wenstrup, Chair of the Alaska Democratic Party, can be reached at michaelwenstrup@yahoo.com All opinions expressed are solely those of the author. Do submit a letter or opinion piece, email editor@thecordovatimes.com
]]></text></news-item>