<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-0261-DY9P-N1TN"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Airport safety was at fault ahead of fire chief's death</title><source>Gloucestershire Echo</source><author>Lisa Jones</author><text><![CDATA[COTSWOLD Airport's owners have been found guilty of health and safety breaches which led to the death of its fire chief.
Kemble Air Services was found guilty of two breaches of health and safety legislation that led to the death of Steven Mills on April 8, 2011.
Father-of-one Mr Mills, 45, died when a 5ft high, 10-stone high-pressure gas cylinder he was moving discharged and hit him on the head.
A safety pin was found in his hand.
Yesterday, a jury at Gloucester Crown Court found Kemble Air Services guilty of two breaches of health and safety laws.
The court heard the cylinders were used for fire suppression and were inside several containers acquired by the airport in Kemble from the army depot at Ashchurch, near Tewkesbury, in September 2010.
The prosecution said before anything was done with the containers and their contents, Kemble Air Services should have produced a full risk assessment.
But the company said that, at the time of Mr Mills' death, the point had not been reached when the company was required by law to risk assess those cylinders.
The jury decided Kemble Air Services had failed to make suitable and sufficient risk assessments of the danger to both employees and non-employees.
They believed the prosecution's case that, at the time of the accident, there was nothing at the airport to tell Mr Mills how to move the cylinder safely, and nothing to identify the hazards of the gas inside. Mr Mills' father Alan, who spoke to the Echo after the hearing on behalf of himself, his wife Marie, and Steven's brother and sister, said his son was a perfectionist in everything he did.
"His attitude was perfection in anything he undertook to complete," he said.
"No individual person is responsible for the death of my son. It was a series of minor irregularities, leading up to a major event resulting in accident.
"Nobody made a desperately bad mistake.
"Steve's death came as a bitter blow. He was a popular person.
"He was not only my son, but a good companion.
"He had many interests in life and worked hard.
"After his retirement as a firefighter, he planned to run the family farm in partnership with his brother Andrew.
" Mr Mills said Steven, who worked on the family farm in Minety, near Cirencester, was also a retained firefighter in Malmesbury. He added: "Time is a good healer, but Steven will be sorely missed for many years to come."
Prosecutor Simon Morgan said prosecution costs would exceed £104,000.
Judge William Hart said: "My sympathy goes out to the partner and family of Mr Mills." Sentencing was adjourned to a date to be fixed.
A four-day inquest in 2012 concluded that Mr Mills' death was an accident.
POPULAR: Steven Mills
"Steve's death came as a bitter blow. He was a popular person. He was not only my son, but a good companion. He had many interests in life and worked hard" Alan Mills.......................................
]]></text></news-item>