<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-H2X1-F0NV-F0H5"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Amid criminal investigation BVU nearly pulls $150,000 sponsorship of Bristol concert</title><source>CBS - 11 WJHL (Johnson City, Tennessee)</source><author>Nate Morabito, INVESTIGATIVE REPORTER</author><text><![CDATA[BRISTOL, VA (WJHL) - Bristol Virginia Utilities almost shut out the lights on a major concert planned for downtown Bristol, in part due to the ongoing concerns about the public utility's past.
BVU's board held its first public meeting Monday since our Community Watchdog investigation exposed thousands of dollars worth of past questionable credit card expenses at area restaurants. BVU remains under investigation by the Washington County Sheriff's Office and Washington County Commonwealth Attorney's Office for the alleged misuse of public funds.
At Monday's meeting the board briefly went into a closed executive session. However, when members returned they didn't talk about the ongoing criminal investigation at all.
Still, the increased public scrutiny the board is now under almost indirectly stopped a big outdoor concert in its tracks. Back in February, BVU's board approved a $150,000 loan to bring a major performer to Bristol later this year. BVU's OptiNet division, which provides cable, telephone and internet service, would foot the bill. The money, theoretically, would be repaid to OptiNet through ticket sales.
The idea is to bring a big time entertainer to Bristol for an outdoor concert, much like when Mumford and Sons performed downtown in 2012. Birthplace of Country Music Marketing Director Charlene Baker told board members the Mumford and Sons concert resulted in more than $1 million in ticket sales alone, not to mention its $5.6 million economic impact. According to Baker, that concert brought 17,000 to 20,000 people to downtown Bristol.
Baker told the board BCM is banking on BVU's support to secure another big name act, as well as supporting acts. Part of the goal is to spur more economic development.
However, several board members expressed concerns with the contract and the possible risk that comes along with it, especially considering the negative attention BVU has received recently. Board member Odell Owens said every person he's talked with has had a negative opinion of BVU helping fund this concert.
"BVU would probably be better off if its name was not on anything, because the public does not look at this favorably," Owens said.
At one point during the meeting the board pulled its sponsorship of the concert altogether. Board member Archie Hubbard said BVU needs to scour the fine print.
"I'm not taking anybody's word for anything (anymore)," Hubbard said. "We're not in the gambling business. They don't put us on this board to start rolling the dice."
Despite the concerns, after some heated debate the board again backed the concert by a 5-4 vote.
"It is a step to show the community that they are vital to what we do here and what we do here is for the community and I think it's a good step in that direction," BVU Board Chairwoman Faith Esposito said after the meeting. "We need to do something for the community and this is one way of us doing that."
Doug Fleenor, who has been the only board member publicly outspoken about BVU's past so far, was one of the four board members who voted against the sponsorship.
"I just didn't feel like it's OptiNet's place to be out promoting concerts," Fleenor said after the meeting.
Despite his displeasure with the idea, he suggested if Optinet makes any money from the concert after it recoups its loan, that money should be split evenly between the Washington County, Va. and Bristol, Va. school systems. That motion passed overwhelmingly.
"Let's designate that money instead of having it and potentially throwing it down the toilet or tube at a later point," Fleenor said. "If we can do this and it benefits the children and so forth, then I'm all for it."
Esposito says from here on out the board is committed to increasing its attention to detail.
"I think we're doing our very best to be as transparent and as attentive to everything that comes before us," Esposito said. "It's important for the public to trust us and to trust the name of BVU and that's what we're trying to restore here."
Copyright WJHL 2014. All rights reserved.
]]></text></news-item>