<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-0RH1-F125-10T3"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Daughter guilty of fraud, along with father</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Danielle Fast-Carlson will join her father in court in two weeks when both are scheduled to be sentenced for defrauding investors of millions of dollars.
She broke down in tears Monday in Saskatoon Court of Queen's Bench after listening to Justice Richard Danyliuk convict her of fraud and making false statements about the profitability of her father's company. The judge found Fast-Carlson, 38, not guilty of possessing proceeds of crime.
The charges relate to Marathon Leasing Corporation, a company founded by Ronald Jerry Fast, 70. The company was initially in the vehicle leasing business, but then was used in a Ponzi scheme to defraud investors of their money. The company promised high interest rates, but could only maintain the scheme with the infusion of money from new investors. It collapsed in 2008.
At the beginning of the trial in November, Fast pleaded guilty to all three counts of fraud, making false statements to investors and possessing the proceeds of crime. His daughter, an accountant who worked as a bookkeeper at the company in its last years, pleaded not guilty. Her trial took place in November and December.
As the judge noted in the opening words of his 115-page written decision, "This case is about unscrupulous business practices, criminal schemes to make money, greed and human nature."
Danyliuk did not mince words about why he found Fast-Carlson guilty. He didn't believe her when she said she didn't know Marathon was headed straight for disaster, he wrote.
"From the evidence before the court, it is clear that accounting training was not required to figure out this company was dying and that the only life support was from new investments. Anyone with common sense could figure that out. Had the accused not held her degrees and accounting designation, this court would have reached the same conclusion," Danyliuk wrote.
"For the accused to testify that with all her background and knowledge of this company, she could not see a bankruptcy coming is simply unbelievable, and the court unreservedly rejects her evidence in this regard."
Danyliuk referred to a phrase - calling it "perhaps ill-chosen" - that he used during closing arguments in December about how looking at the company's finances was like "getting hit in the face with a long-handled shovel."
After taking another long look at the case, he said those words were still pertinent.
"She simply cannot be believed when she says she did not see it coming. I do not believe her. No reasonable person, armed with the financial information entered into evidence, would believe her." A sentencing hearing for Fast is already scheduled for April 7 to 10. Danyliuk directed that Fast-Carlson's sentencing take place then as well.
© Copyright (c) The Regina Leader-Post
]]></text></news-item>