<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-X7W1-DXH0-K072"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Industrialists will be bound to reveal source of investment, PA told</title><source>Dawn (Pakistan)</source><author> Bhagwandas</author><text><![CDATA[The government plans to review the industrialisation policy under which investors will have to seek permission and disclose the source of investment for setting up industries, said Sindh Law and Parliamentary Affairs Minister Dr Sikander Mandhro on Monday.
He was responding to questions being asked by legislators during the question hour that pertained to the industries department in the Sindh Assembly. He was speaking on behalf of Chief minister Syed Qaim Ali Shah, who holds the industries portfolio and came late in the session, which began over an hour and a half behind the scheduled time of 10am.
Responding to a question asked by Pakistan Muslim league-Functional legislator Mahtab Rashdi that why no permission/ NOC was required for setting up industries and how the government would know if the funds being invested were legal or illegal, the minster said that the earlier governments, under pressure of the investors, had liberalised the industrial as well as investment policy under which neither the investors were required to obtain an NOC from the government nor did they intimate the investment incurred in the project.
He agreed with the legislator that the policy needed a review and that the government would also formulate laws so that the source of funds being invested be known and the investors took proper permissions. He said earlier the industrialists had raised objections and said that the government agencies/ officials harassed them, which was not totally baseless, as there could be some black sheep among officials. But keeping a check was necessary.
Replying to another of her questions regarding setting up of new industries during 2012-13, the minister said 355 new industries had been set up during that time.
Responding to a question from PML-N legislator Irfan Marwat that if industrialists did not seek permission from the government to set up new industries, how the number of 355 was being cited, the minister said the government received/ sought information indirectly. Explaining it, he said the labour department would register the workers so it would have the information, or various worker welfare departments also maintained records and registered the industries.
In reply to a question asked by Muttahida Qaumi Movement legislator Heer Soho regarding the establishment of new textile units, the minister said the number had more than doubled between 2002 and 2013, as currently there were 523 textile units and 282 of them had been set up during 2002-2013.
Responding to a question from the MQM's Zubair Khan regarding the state of expansion project of the industrial zone in Hyderabad and an update on it, Sindh information minister Sharjeel Memon, who had held the portfolio for some time earlier, said that over a decade back an expansion project was approved and Rs300 million was allocated for it and out of it over Rs150 million had also been given to a contractor, but despite lapse of over a decade no work had been done there. The government was investigating the issue and soon stern action would be taken against those found involved in it and the money given would be recovered, he added.
Responding to a question by MQM legislator Irum Farooqui regarding toxic and hazardous effluents and emissions being discharged from the industries which harmed air as well as water, the minister said no industry could be set up without obtaining an NOC from the Sindh Environmental Protection Agency, which monitored that environmental quality standards were maintained and also it took punitive action against the polluters. He, however, could not tell the legislator as to against how many polluters such actions had been taken and said that it was a separate question and also pertained to the environment department.
Responding to a question by Mr Khan regarding the use of industrial land for other purposes, he said land was allotted for specific purposes and land use was mentioned in the agreement. If anybody misused the land and used it for some other purpose like commercial or residential which was not mentioned in the agreement, it was illegal and if a specific case was pointed out, stern action would be taken against people involved in it.
In reply to another question by Ms Rashdi regarding setting up of industries in residential areas, he said all such units were illegal and if specific cases were pointed out, legal action would be taken.
Responding to a question by the MQM's Naheed Begum regarding the number of industrial estates functioning in the province, the minister said the Sindh Small Industries Corporation had set up 18 industrial estates while the Sindh Industrial Trading Estate had set up 13.
The PPP's Sohrab Sarki; Syed Hafeezuddin of the Pakistan Tehreek-i-Insaf and others also participated in the question hour.
]]></text></news-item>