<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-0RH1-DY2T-011P"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Quebec makes Sask. look sane</title><source>The Star Phoenix (Saskatoon, Saskatchewan)</source><author>Murray Mandryk, The Starphoenix</author><text><![CDATA[Hello, insanity of Quebec politics. Meet the insanity of Saskatchewan politics.
One realizes the two of you have never really got to know each other very well, that little problem with the language barrier and all. But you actually have a lot more in common than you realize, even though too much of it centres around the politically bizarre.
In fact, in all deference to other provinces in English Canada, no other comes as close as Saskatchewan to Quebec's brand of political crazy.
It's Saskatchewan that has produced the greatest divide between left and right, philosophical differences that have literally shut down government over everything from public health care to privatizing the publicly owned gas utility.
Three decades after the creation of the province came the creation of the Co-operative Commonwealth Federation - later to become the NDP - which dominated its politics for six decades between the 1944 and 2007. While not exactly establishing a distinct society, the CCF-NDP did define a chasm in politics wider than anywhere else except Quebec.
We've even had our own separatist party led by a former Progressive Conservative leader, Dick Collver, who announced his "Unionests" would have Saskatchewan join the United States. Fortunately, the only time Saskatchewan voters took Collver seriously was when he testified under oath that he heard Colin Thatcher - a former cabinet minister, son of a premier and sitting MLA at the time - say that he was contemplating killing his wife.
And then there's the little matter of the biggest political fraud case in Canadian history, at least in terms of the number of convictions, that stemmed from the abuse of the PC caucus communication allowances. Of course, it wasn't quite on the same scale of political crimes as the Quebec-based federal Liberal sponsorship or mayoral bribery allegations. But Saskatchewan had its own bribery charges levelled against executives of the provincial bus company buying new vehicles.
While Saskatchewan's left-right split has made for nasty politics over the decades, it has probably never come close to the cutthroat, high-stakes federalismversus- sovereignty fights in Quebec. And although Saskatchewan politics seems to have calmed down lately, the current election campaign in Quebec demonstrates that politicians there still opt for the bizarre.
The latest bit of crazy - one with a Saskatchewan connection - comes from Parti Quebecois Leader Pauline Marois, who told La Presse this about Saskatchewan Premier Brad Wall: "Un ratoureux qui essaie toujours de me faire trebucher."
The rough translation is that she called Wall either a type of cheese or foxlike - or rat-like, depending on who does the interpretation - or essentially a mischief maker who is always trying to trip her up. The context was interprovincial relations such as those involving premiers' conferences, which Marois insisted would turn any Quebecer into a separatist. Asked Monday what precipitated the comment, Wall said he didn't know, and that he and Marois actually have attended only one such conference together.
It's a bizarre way to do politics. It's usually taboo to drag into your domestic fights other first ministers with whom you'll have to work. But if you are in the business of refusing to work with other premiers - or actually the rest of country from which you desperately want to separate - you aren't particularly bothered by offending one of them.
Actually, this wasn't even close to the craziest thing to come out of Marois and the PQ in this campaign, or even this week. The latest is the peculiar claim that anglophone students from Ontario are about to steal the election by voting illegally. It is an allegation that even Quebec's chief electoral officer said is baseless, although that didn't stop reporters working for PQ star candidate Pierre Karl Peladeau's newspapers from repeating the nonsense.
The biggest debate in this election which will decide who will preside over this caring, sharing society, is whether public servants can wear religious garb or adornments. Of course, the PQ frames this as an issue of tolerance while it runs a candidate who actively expresses distaste for Muslims and another who expresses her distaste for Jews.
Meanwhile, the basket case that is Quebec's economy is hardly an issue to the PQ. Then again, Marois and the PQ won't commit to a separatism referendum either, even though that is their raison d'etre.
It all makes Saskatchewan politics look relatively sane.
]]></text></news-item>