<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-0RH1-DYWX-S0VT"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>NDP cites mill blasts in call for pursuit of employer prosecutions</title><source>Prince George Citizen (British Columbia)</source><author>Peter James, The Citizen</author><text><![CDATA[In the wake of the two fatal northern B.C. mill explosions in 2012, the B.C. NDP are calling on the provincial government to prosecute the executives and directors of companies if they're responsible for worker deaths. Labour critic Harry Bains introduced a motion during Monday morning's legislative sitting which he hopes will "hold those in authority accountable" if workers are killed on the job as a result of negligence by their employer.
"It is our duty to ensure workplace accountability by giving the tools needed for our investigators to collect evidence that will be acceptable to the Crown for successful convictions," Bains said in the legislature.
During his opening remarks Bains mentioned both the explosions at Babine Forest Products near Burns Lake and Lakeland Mills in Prince George. Two workers were killed in each blast and in the case of Babine there will be no charges because the Crown determined that the investigation techniques used by WorkSafeBC were inadequate and evidence collected may not hold up in court.
"Babine sawmill and Lakeland sawmill explosions killed four and injured 42 others very seriously," Bains said.
"In the Babine case no one has been held accountable so far."
In response, Prince George-Mackenzie Liberal MLA Mike Morris said that it's important to distinguish between the government's responsibilities and those of the Crown.
"It's not government's role to pursue prosecutions. That's why we have a Crown council agency," Morris said.
"That's why we have other agencies involved in the investigations of matters such as this."
Morris, a former RCMP officer, said that police attend work-place deaths to ensure that foul play does not lead to fatal injuries.
Morris also defended the government's actions in the wake of the explosions.
"It is, however, our role to ensure that we have effective agencies in place to monitor and investigate workplace safety," he said.
"This requires a working protocol, regular and consistent, between WorkSafeBC and mill owners with an unwavering focus on safer sawmills.
"Our government expects WorkSafeBC and mill owners to comply with safety practices."
NDP leader Adrian Dix joined the debate and said employers need to take responsibility for safety issues and that it's up to the government to hold them accountable.
"When you have Hampton in the Babine case doing a press release blaming the whole incident on WorkSafe and not taking responsibility, what message does that send?" Dix asked.
"Not a good one. What message does it send that 1,350 cases and zero charges - not zero prosecutions - are laid?" Morris said his government is committed to making sure workplaces are safe. "Every member of this House wants to make sure that when British Columbians go to work in the morning, they come home each and every night," Morris said.
"We sympathize with those who have lost loved ones in these tragedies.
"No legislation, findings or penalties can ever compensate for that loss."
]]></text></news-item>