<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-NG41-JCMC-P016"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>GC Titan head on stuation at Omsky Kauchuk</title><source>SKRIN Market &amp; Corporate News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[7 March 2014 Chairman of the Board of Directors of CJSC "Mikhail Sutyaginsky made a speech during a press-conference in the Government of Omsk Region. The topic of the press-conference was liquidation of consequences of an accident on the "Omsky Kauchuk" plant.
The press-conference was attended by headsof Chief Administration of the Ministry of Emergency Situations of Russia in Omsk Region, Administration of Russian Environmental Supervision in Omsk Region, Administration of Russian Consumer Supervision in Omsk Region, Ob’-Irtysh Hydrometeorology and Monitoring of Environment Administration, and also by Chairman of the Board of Directors of CJSC "GC "Titan" Mikhail Sutyaginsky.
The top-manager of the Group of Companies thanked all services of emergency response for the help, and also presented his apologies to residents of Omsk for troubles which were caused by the accident.
Information about the enterprise
Process of phenol-acetone production includes several stages. The accident happened on the first stage - the oxidation stage which does not contain ready product. During production process only one quarter of a 100 cu/m capacity column is filled with chemicals. The product of this stage from the point of view of toxicity can be compared with automotive exhaust gases.
It is reduced by 95 percent. Only black smoke which occurs during combustion of the product can cause concern. But worries, as those which are connected with black snow, have no ground. There will be no black snow even during changes in wind direction. As for the odor, phenol smells like gouache, and smell which is reported by residents has no connection with phenol.
Information about the cause of the accident
The cause of the inflammation is not yet discovered. A workers' cabin which was situated on the territory of the enterprise had been erected with observation of all norms. The "Sibmontazh" company which rendered services to the enterprise has necessary licenses and permits, its workers were dully attested.
The question of what happened in the cabin is now examined - was it negligence or inattentiveness. It was a sudden inflammation, which moved rapidly to the production facilities. Phenol-acetone workshop had been functioning for a long time, and this is the first such accident here. Yesterday a headquarters was created for liquidation of the accident, we are examining every detail connected with the accident, but, unfortunately, this process can take much time. I think that details of the accident will be determined soon.
Information about operative response
During the emergency situation the staff acted in accordance with instructions and took every necessary measure. In several minutes one conducted enormous amount of works: the power supply to the object was turned off, by the time of Ministry of Emergency Situations representatives’ arrival the laboratory conducted analysis of air samples in order to reduce radius of firefighters’ work, workers of gaseous emergency service responded operatively.
Information about casualties
There are two casualties who suffered from burns. We hope they will recover soon. Condition of others, as medics say, causes no concern. The majority of casualties have minor injuries. The blast wave destroyed windows, and workers were hurt by glass. Every casualty had already received medical help. If a need for compensation will be discovered, we will pay it.
Information about the inflicted damage
There was considerable damage, a unit which is quite important for us was put offline. Today we still cannot evaluate damage. Every institute which was engaged in designing of the unit will participate in this work, so as organizations which participated in its installation; we will examine every document, we will conduct survey of the unit’s condition, and after this we will compose an accurate report on financial charges. But, judging by the class awarded to the fire, we can say that the unit will not be working during the next six months.
According to the legislation, workers of the damaged workshop will be transferred to available vacancies in other workshops or they will be sent to idle mode.
Information about consumers of the products
No doubt, that it is a negative accident for our consumers. Each month our enterprise produced approximately 5000 tonnes of phenol and ca. 3000 tonnes of acetone, we had been working with 100% load, manufactured product of highest grade (A), and we received reclamations neither on phenol, nor on acetone. For the time being the consumers will have to reorient on other products.
Information about environmental safety of the enterprise
None of petrochemical and petroleum-refining enterprises excludes such situation. It all depends on conditions of use, approach and human factor. GC "Titan" is the only Omsk petrochemical enterprise which received certificates of management system in three standards: ISO 9001, ISO 14001 and OHSAS 180001. It suggests execution of all requirements, including the European ones, connected with industrial safety and protection of labor.
Our enterprise has minimal emissions into atmosphere. I can invite any expert agency in order to corroborate this fact. / Titan GK
]]></text></news-item>