<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-TFK1-DY8N-Y000"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Tribunal finds</title><source>The New Age (South Africa)</source><author>Michele Curling</author><text><![CDATA[MICHELE CURLING-HOPE
THE Competition Tribunal has, after 10 years, dismissed allegations that South African Breweries (SAB) engaged in any anti-competitive behaviour in its distribution. The tribunal yesterday dismissed the 2007 case brought by the Competition Commission against SAB and 13 SAB-appointed distributors.
The commission alleged that SAB's distribution system favoured its own appointed distributors to the detriment of independent distributors and, ultimately, consumers.
Yesterday the tribunal announced that the commission did not present sufficient evidence to prove that SAB's distribution system lessened "intra-brand competition" - competition between firms that distribute SAB-branded beer - as the commission had alleged.
SAB executive chairperson Norman Adami said the company welcomed the ruling and had always been confident that none of its practices were in breach of the law or competitive behaviour.
The commission's complaint alleged that SAB, which has a market share of between 89% and 90% in the production of clear beer, had contravened the Competition Act because it had appointed distributors and given them exclusive territories in which
to distribute SAB products.
The commission said this restricted competition between the various appointed distributors.
Other allegations included that SAB unfairly discriminated between the appointed distributors and independent distributors.
The commission said that appointed distributors were able to use a computer system that allowed them to charge a price set centrally by SAB.
These allegations were dismissed by the tribunal which pointed out that one of the problems with the commission's case was that it was entirely focused on the system of appointed distributors.
SAB's appointed distributors account for only 10% of its distribution.
Therefore, the tribunal said that there was no likely remedy that would impact on the market.
It said that if a remedy was imposed, SAB could easily make its distribution system conform to the remaining 90% of distribution which was not under attack from the commission.
In the original 2007 complaint referral, the commission also alleged that SAB's conduct was designed to induce retailers not to deal with SAB's competitors, in contravention of the Competition Act. Following an objection from SAB, the commission elected to commence with the case concerning the appointed distributors.
michelec@thenewage.co.za
]]></text></news-item>