<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-HVM1-JBJ4-20K6"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Political Parties Defraud State in Imported Vehicles Scam</title><source>Agencia de Informacao de Mocambique (English)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Mozambican political parties are abusing the customs exemptions they enjoy in order to import vehicles and sell them on to other people, thus defrauding the state of large sums in tax revenue, according to the anti-corruption NGO, the Centre for Public Integrity (CIP).
The law on political parties has enormous loopholes in terms of tax exemptions, for it does not specify how many cars or other goods can be imported duty free, and over what period. Parties which have no offices, no publications, few votes and fewer members, and which are completely unknown to most of the Mozambican public, are using the exemption clause to import and then sell vehicles.
What has repeatedly happened, according to CIP in a lengthy article is its latest newsletter, is that dishonest customs brokers tell people who wish to import cars that the cheapest way to do so is via a political party.
The cars in questions are often second hand Japanese cars, purchased directly from Japan, or via companies in South Africa. If the CIF (Cost, Insurance and Freight) price of a Toyota Corolla imported from Japan is 4,550 US dollars, by the time customs duties (20 per cent), value added tax (17 per cent) and specific consumption tax (35 per cent) are added, the price to the Mozambican customer rises to almost 7,850 dollars (plus 20,000 meticais - 655 dollars - for port costs).
The customs broker then tells the client that he should resort to a political party, which is 100 per cent exempt from the taxes and duties. The client will than pay the party half of what he ought to have paid in taxes. In other words, the party has illegally sold on its exemption, and pocketed a substantial sum for itself.
A senior party official - the president or general secretary - then sends a letter to the General Director of Customs, asking for the exemption on the vehicle in question. When the vehicle arrives, it is registered in the name of the political party, but is handed over to the real buyer. So that no awkward questions are asked if he is found driving the vehicle, he is given a party membership card, or a credential authorizing him to use the vehicle.
Customs did seem to be aware of this type of fraud in 2012, when six luxury vehicles imported by political parties and sold on to third parties were seized and shown to the press. They were a Volvo S40, two Range Rovers, two Land rovers, and a Toyota Fortuner.
CIP found that the two Land Rovers had been imported by PIMO (Independent Party of Mozambique - which is a disguised Islamic party) and MONAMO (Mozambique Nationalist Movement). PIMO stands in elections, but with derisory results. MONAMO was once a member of the Renamo-Electoral Union coalition, but this was wound up in 2009. Since then MONAMO has disappeared from sight.
CIP did not find out what parties had registered the other four vehicles, but it was confirmed that the ownership deeds had been illegally altered. In all, the six vehicles should have paid the state taxes and duties amounting to over 14 million meticais (about 460,000 dollars).
According to the southern regional directorate of customs, in 2012 political parties imported 210 cars. PIMO and the Ecologist Party imported 35 each, the National Reconciliation Party imported 28, the Green Party 27, while several others, including the Patriotic Movement for Democracy (MPD), the Labour Party (PT), the MDM (Mozambique Democratic Movement) and the Mozambique National Union (UNAMO) imported less than ten.
With the exception of the MDM, which is now the third force in Mozambican politics, none of the others have any representation anywhere - not in parliament, and not in the municipalities. From one election to the next, nothing is heard of them, and they do no campaigning - so why do they need so many cars?
In 2013, the pace of the imports stepped up. The Green Party imported no less than 234 cars, PARENA 120 and the Mozambican Socialist Party (PSM) 73. No-one has ever seen a car bearing the insignia of any of these parties. These figures only refer to Maputo province, and not to Maputo City - CIP was unable to obtain the data for the city.
Leaders of the parties contacted by CIP admitted that the vehicles are not for party work as such, but for party members. “There are people who join the party so that they can then seek exemption in importing cars”, they said.
The parties ask these people to pay their membership fees - and then they benefit from customs exemptions not only on cars, but also on computers, furniture and other goods.
CIP found that the PSM had imported vehicles via Namaacha, on the Swazi border, on 20 February this year, and a fortnight later, on 5 March, they were already illegally registered in the names of other people.
CIP says it has the documents which prove that a Toyota RAV4 car and a Hiace minibus entered the country in the name of the PSM, but on 5 March they were registered in the city of Matola in the names of Evonne Mbewe and Anibal Machava. To achieve this customs documents and receipts had been forged.
In one case, vehicle imports led to an uproar inside the party concerned. This was the MDM which, in 2009 and 2010, shortly after its foundation, imported 13 luxury vehicles, which should have paid customs and duties of 26.4 million meticais (close to a million dollars at the exchange rates of the time). These imports, CIP says, led to a dispute in the MDM leadership, and the resignation of its then general secretary, Ismael Mussa, who claimed that he was not consulted.
CIP says the current whereabouts of these vehicles is unknown, except that “they were delivered to a well known car importer to be sold”.
The CIP investigation uncovered several other ways in which the state is defrauded of taxes in vehicle imports. One of these involves under-invoicing by three companies in the South African port of Durban, Quest Royal Investment, Mansoor Motors and Jan Japa, Mozambican car dealers go there, not only because the prices are relatively cheap (they bring in large shipments of cares at a time from Japan), but because they are willing to issue false invoices, mentioning prices way below what was really paid, in order to reduce the Mozambican importer's tax liability.
The CIP team, who pretended to be interested in importing a car, visited Quest Royal in Durban. Here they were told that on the sale of a car for 5,500 dollars, they would be given an invoice for only 3,000 dollars.
The CIP would-be buyers were assured that the vehicle would not be revalued by Mozambican customs. They were put in contact with a Mozambican dealer who told them “Pay for the car, go back to Maputo and I'll deal with the rest. If I submit the papers to customs, it won't be revalued. I've been doing this for five years”.
CIP suggests there is a web of corruption involving customs officials, brokers, car dealers, and officials in the licensing and registration authorities, which results in depriving the state of millions of dollars in the tax revenue that should be paid on imported vehicles.
]]></text></news-item>