<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-HVM1-JBJ4-217F"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Henry Costa Gets Bail, Released From South Beach Prison</title><source>FrontPageAfrica</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The freedom or let's say temporary freedom of radio talk show host Henry Costa came late Monday evening at about 5pm, after lawyers were able to secure a bond of an undisclosed amount. Friends, well wishers and sympathizers of Costa flooded the grounds of the temple of justice early Monday morning hoping to see him a free man before midday but that was not to be so.
Lawyers were seen moving back and forth at the Monrovia City Court trying to secure a valid bail bond for the terroristic threat charges that has been brought upon Costa by the court in favor of the head of the National Security Agency, Fomba Sirleaf, who happens to be the son of President Ellen Johnson Sirleaf. Many who assembled at the court in support of Costa expressed dismay that the head of the NSA would bring such charges against an ordinary citizen.
"We are here in defense of Henry Costa, that was arrested arbitrarily taken to the Monrovia Central Prison, not under the direct time of the supervision of the court because we have come to realize that you cannot go to jail after 6pm," said Janjay Baipkeh a civil rights activist.
"The court violated the rights of Mr. Henry Costa, by sending him to jail after 6pm. This is a signal we want to send to Madam Sirleaf and her people; we don't want selective justice in this country."
Baipkeh criticized the first family for bringing frivolous lawsuits against individuals who disagree with them or the government's policies. "We have come to say to Madam Sirleaf and her children, this country does not belong to the Sirleafs, it belongs to each and every one of us," he said.
"We went to war because of injustice and selective justice, so we have come to inform the court; this judge who in his wisdom can refuse to sign a proper bond filed by the defense team of Henry Costa on grounds that he did not pay this bond fee in United States Dollars."
Costa on his release from the Monrovia Central Prison told a crowd of supporters who had promptly trooped there after hearing that the legitimate bond had been secured, expressed gratitude for the support adding that he will not cower into submission. "My brothers and sisters, I thank you very much from the bottom of my heart, for the support that you showed me," he said.
Continued Costa:"It has not been an easy thing, but to know that you stand with us matters more than anything else. It has given me and us a renewed conviction that what indeed we are doing has a purpose because it is appreciated by you, you gave your time, you were in the sun, you were out there for us and I am just overwhelmed, what I have seen has given me conviction that indeed the majority of the people of this country means good."
The talk show host who claims not to be a journalist said he believes Liberia has a great future in terms of promoting that freedom that many Liberians like himself are standing up for. He said his imprisonment has cost the Ellen Johnson Sirleaf-led government more harm in terms of image than good.
"Some of us are nothing but mere instruments, an insignificant Henry Costa you putting me in jail to do what? You lose so much of your image, you place our cause, it is not about me, it is about the cause, I stand for something," said Costa.
"I am an opposition to corruption, an opposition to nepotism, cronyism, to bad governance and certainty to the poor justice system we have in our country, I will forever remain resolute and convicted and to preach for that, nothing." Costa said he is prepared to go to jail any time adding that he is not afraid of being imprisoned based on his conviction.
"In fact, I am going to secure an open ended bond, which mean I am going to prepare a bond that will never take me to court, I will present my bond and we ill keep testing the system, we will keep testing," he said.
If it were not for you perhaps, I would not be standing here today, it is because of your presence, you intimidated them by that and we need to do more of that and when we do that, I believe we will change this country."
Costa did not mince his words in expressing his dislike for President Sirleaf and her family members who he says he holds responsible for his imprisonment. "One day, we will take our country back, thank you very much, thank you very much," he said.
"This country does not belong to Ellen Johnson Sirleaf, it does not belong to Robert Sirleaf, does not belong to Fombah Sirleaf and we want to say to them that we are not afraid of them, we are not afraid."
Although Costa has stated on several occasions that he is not a journalist, the umbrella organization governing journalists in Liberia, the Press Union of Liberia (PUL) through its President Abdullai Kamara issued a statement late Sunday evening condemning the arrest and prosecution of Costa, terming it an action, which effectively undermines the government's commitment to decriminalize speech in Liberia.
"When we met this week to further our conversations about the way forward in repealing speech laws, the Press Union was determined to laud the commitment of the government to repeal these laws, but as it now stand, we are seriously reconsidering whether that is the way to go," said Kamara.
"Agreeing to decriminalize speech offenses mean that high public officials must accept comments, criticism and innuendos that could even be considered derogatory and reckless. The truth in this is if we cannot accept such unfettered criticism, then we are not prepared to allow a civil discussion of our stewardship of public resources."
The Union maintains that given Mr. Sirleaf's strategic role, family connection, affluence and influence, it is not reasonable to accept that an utterance by Mr. Costa could really threaten his standing.
"By all accounts, this will simply translate into misuse of power, and no pretense of going to court will convince an already susceptible public otherwise," PUL Kamara. "The best way out of this situation is for the government to unconditionally drop the charges and allow Mr. Costa to go about his business."
President Sirleaf at the weekend during the one-year review of the government's Agenda for Transformation expressed concern over the widespread pretrial detention in the country. The President said it is a major problem and it is too easy for people to get put in jail in Liberia because of a system that allows it to be so.
"The justice and the rule of law, I know that the judicial reform as Associate Justice Ja'neh had said is ongoing, but pretrial detention is still a major, major problem, our prisons are full of people, it is too easy to be put in jail in this country, too easy", said President Sirleaf.
"That means the Justice Ministry working with the court system, particularly through the Supreme Court need to find a way to stop a system where somebody can just go to a magistrate and pay $25 and somebody gets put into jail, and sometimes you don't even know they are there."
She challenged the Justice and Rule of Law pillar of the AFT to work beyond resource constraints in getting the country's judicial system on the right path.
"So there are some of these things that I ask the pillars to get practical when they sit down to discuss these issues, resource is a constraint, no doubt, but we still have to go beyond the resource constraint and look at some of the systems and the processes and the procedures and see how we can change some of them to be able to achieve the objectives", said President Sirleaf.
Costa's detention and the judge refusal to grant him bail on a statutory fee left many to wonder whether there is justice for the poor in Liberia.
]]></text></news-item>