<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-HGK1-JC8C-2007"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>News briefing</title><source>Sun-Sentinel (Fort Lauderdale, Florida)</source><author>Tribune Newspapers and news services</author><text><![CDATA[Crews try to contain oil spilled in Texas waters
Oil spilled from a barge in Galveston Bay, blocking the busy Houston ship channel and threatening some birds at a nearby wildlife sanctuary, officials and environmentalists said Sunday.
Coast Guard officials said up to 168,000 gallons of oil may have spilled.
The spill was reported at 12:30 p.m. Saturday by the captain of a 585-foot Liberian-flagged ship, Summer Wind, that collided with the barge, Coast Guard officials said. The cause of the crash was under investigation.
Michael Lambert, spokesman for Galveston County Office of Emergency Management, called it a "significant spill," but not based on the amount of oil.
"The real issue is that it's in the ship channel, near environmentally sensitive areas. So there's an economic impact and an environmental impact," he said.
On Sunday, crews were skimming oil and laying absorbent booms to contain the spread of the spill, which occurred in the channel that runs between Galveston Island and the Bolivar Peninsula, Lambert said. Containing the spill could take days, he said.
Coast Guard port Capt. Brian Penoyer said at a Sunday news briefing that oil had been spotted a dozen miles offshore in the Gulf of Mexico.
He said the spill blocked about 60 vessels, including cruise ships, from transiting the channel, one of the world's busiest petrochemical transport routes.
Penoyer said the remaining oil had been removed from the damaged barge Sunday, and the barge had been taken out of the channel. He did not say when the channel would reopen.
Iran: U.S. aircraft carrier replica part of movie set
A replica of a U.S. aircraft carrier spotted near the coast of Iran is merely a movie set, the Iranian media said Sunday.
The New York Times, quoting U.S. intelligence sources, said last week that the Iranians were building a mock-up of a U.S. nuclear-powered aircraft carrier, possibly so they could blow it up for propaganda purposes.
Satellite photos showed what looked like one of the Navy's Nimitz-class aircraft carriers rising near the port of Bandar Abbas.
Palestinian crowds rally to show Hamas support
GAZA CITY, Gaza Strip -- Tens of thousands of Palestinians demonstrated Sunday in Gaza to show support for their Islamist Hamas government, which has long been at loggerheads with Israel but is now shunned by Egypt as well.
The military-backed government that toppled the Muslim Brotherhood, Hamas' ideological kin, in Cairo last year deems the Palestinian faction a security threat. An Egyptian court this month banned Hamas activities in the country.
Israeli diplomats strike, forcing embassy closings
JERUSALEM -- Israeli diplomats launched a strike Sunday, forcing the closings of embassies around the world as they escalated a pay dispute, officials said.
The action has already threatened to postpone a visit by Pope Francis to Israel planned for May -- one of 25 trips by foreign officials affected by a work slowdown the diplomats began March 5, when wage talks broke down. The strike is the first by the diplomatic corps since the country's establishment in 1948.
Syrian president's cousin killed in fight with rebels
A cousin of Syrian President Bashar Assad was killed Sunday in battles with Islamist rebels near the border with Turkey, activists and state media said.
The Syrian Observatory for Human Rights said Hilal Assad, local head of the National Defense Forces militia, and seven of his fighters were killed in clashes with Al-Nusra Front and other Islamist brigades. State television confirmed his death. The National Defense Forces is a militia set up to support the army.
<hl2 style="briefs_subhead">The Newsmaker
Chinese firm responds
Chinese telecommunications and Internet company Huawei said Sunday it would condemn any infiltration by the National Security Agency. The New York Times and Der Spiegel, citing documents leaked by former security contractor Edward Snowden, said the NSA got sensitive data.
Guinea moves to contain outbreak of Ebola virus
CONAKRY, Guinea -- Health officials fighting an outbreak of Ebola in Guinea on Sunday dispatched specialized medical equipment, imposed restrictions on funerals and sought to contain panic to prevent the fever from spreading.
There have been 29 confirmed deaths from the hemorrhagic fever among 59 people killed by a mysterious illness in southern Guinea since February, international charity Doctors Without Borders said.
Avalanche kills 2 women at Sochi resort in Russia
MOSCOW -- Two people were killed Sunday when an avalanche swept down a slope at the Sochi ski resort where the 2014 Winter Olympics alpine events were held, Russian officials said.
Rescuers found the bodies of two women beneath the snow after the midday avalanche on a slope at Rosa Khutor, the resort said on its website.
"Despite all efforts to revive them, they could not be saved," it said. The Russian Emergency Situations Ministry confirmed two people were killed.
<hl2 style="briefs_subhead">Austrian tourist killed by shark in South Africa
An Austrian tourist was killed by a shark while swimming in South Africa's Eastern Cape province, the National Sea Rescue Institute said Sunday.
The 72-year-old man received fatal wounds in the attack Saturday at Second Beach in Port St. Johns, where he and his wife were part of a tour group, the institute said in a statement. It did not name the victim. Underwater fences have been erected at popular swimming spots for protection.
]]></text></news-item>