<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-0VD1-JC11-10SC"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Minnesota Power Put On Notice for More Than 12,500 Clean Air Act Violations</title><source>Targeted News Service</source><author>Targeted News Service</author><text><![CDATA[The Sierra Club issued the following news release:
Today the Sierra Club is putting Minnesota Power on notice (https://docs.google.com/a/sierraclub.org/file/d/0B99rOgSuwtDyTWxGUUpnLU1WZlE/edit) that the utility is accountable for 12,774 violations of the federal Clean Air Act at its Clay Boswell, Taconite Harbor, and Syl Laskin coal plants over the last five years, threatening public health. Although the Sierra Club first filed its notice of intent to sue Minnesota Power last year, the three plants continue to neglect clean air safeguards.
The Sierra Club found that, according to data collected by Minnesota Power itself, the three plants have violated their limits on "opacity" more than 10,000 times. Opacity is a measurement of the degree to which light passes through a smoke plume; it is used as an indicator of particulate matter emissions, or soot. Soot pollution from burning coal can contribute to lung and heart disease, can exacerbate asthma problems, and has recently been linked to cancer (http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/iarcnews/pdf/pr221_E.pdf) by the World Health Organization. In addition, Minnesota Power has committed hundreds of violations of legal requirements related to the operation of its pollution control equipment, including mercury controls, since 2009.
"These serious violations call into question whether Minnesota Power is willing or able to operate its plants within the national safety guidelines for public health," said Michelle Rosier, Sierra Club Campaign and Organizing Manager. "Minnesota Power should immediately bring its plants within clean air standards and announce plans for how it will eventually replace its coal plants with cleaner sources of energy."
Newly released 2012 data from The Clean Air Task Force estimates that the Clay Boswell, Taconite Harbor and Syl Laskin coal plants contribute to 367 asthma attacks, 36 heart attacks, and 23 premature deaths per year. The elderly, children and people with respiratory and heart disease are most at risk.
"I am deeply concerned for the children of Cook County and our beautiful, but fragile environment," said Gordy Dodge, who lives in Schroeder, Minn. "Minnesota Power's clean air violations make clear the need to plan for the responsible transition beyond dangerous coal plants."
Minnesota Power draws over 80 percent of its power from burning coal. Last May, a Peak Campaigns poll (http://sc.org/MNPowerPoll) found that two-thirds of voters in Minnesota Power's service territory are concerned about the health risks associated with coal pollution. An even greater 74 percent of voters in Minnesota Power's service area support replacing coal plants with clean energy.
Contact: Alison Flowers, 303/246-6297, alison.flowers@sierraclub.org
Copyright Targeted News Services
TNS 24HariRad-140325-30FurigayJane-4678252 30FurigayJane
]]></text></news-item>