<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-H9J1-DYR8-30PF"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Nigeria; 20 Standing Committees Announced</title><source>Africa News</source><author>Daily Trust (Abuja)</author><text><![CDATA[The National Conference has proposed setting up 20 committees as it begins deliberations yesterday after a week's recess.
A document obtained by Daily Trust showed that committee on devolution of power is top on the list.
This committee has the following items: fiscal federalism (comprising revenue sharing, resource control and sharing formula), policing, local government administration and role of traditional rulers and institutions in governance.
This is followed by the committee on political restructuring and forms of governments. It comprises items such as federalism, regionalism, state creation, geo-political zones, forms and content of government (presidential and parliamentary), and legislature which includes bicameral, unicameral and part time/full time.
There are also committees on National Security, comprising the armed forces (civilian oversight and review of the Armed Forces Act); reform of the Nigerian Customs Service; Road Safety Corps; terrorism/counter- terrorism; armed robbery; kidnapping; small arms proliferation; communal violence; election violence; illegal violence; sea piracy; organized/transnational crime (money laundering, human trafficking, drug trafficking, terrorism financing); and cybercrime.
Others are committees on environment; politics and good governance; law, judiciary human rights and legal reform; social welfare; transportation; science and technology and development; and agriculture.
Other committees include those on civil society, labour and sports; electoral matters; foreign policy and diaspora matters; land tenure matters and national boundary; trade and investment; energy; religion; public finance and revenue generation; and Immigration.
According to the draft work plan, these committees whose memberships and chairmanship would be determined by the delegates this week, would work for two weeks, beginning from April 7 to 17.
The plenary would begin deliberation, and voting on the various committees reports by April 21. The plenary would spend three weeks, starting from April 21 to May 9, considering the reports of the committees.
Thereafter, the conference secretariat would spend two weeks drafting the final report, beginning from May 12 to May 22.
Also, the plenary, according to the work plan, would spend another two weeks to consider and adopt the report, from May 26 to June 5.
The final week of the conference, June 7 to June 10, would be used for the production and signing of the final report.
]]></text></news-item>