<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-0261-DY9P-N33T"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Co-op Bank facing £400m hole to pay for legal costs</title><source>Metro (UK)</source><author>CHERYL LATHAM</author><text><![CDATA[THE Co-operative Group's debt laden banking arm needs to raise an additional £400million to cover legal costs, it revealed yesterday.
Extra funds are needed for legal documentation related to the mis-selling of payment protection insurance and technical breaches of the consumer credit act, the bank said.
Full-year results, which were due to be revealed tomorrow, were expected to show losses of up to £1.3billion for 2013. Publication has been delayed until next month.
The bank's chief executive Niall Booker said: 'The proposed capital raise would enable us to reset this starting point and continue with the execution of our original business plan.' Co-op group's former chief executive Euan Sutherland branded the organisation 'ungovernable' and resigned earlier this month after his £6.6million pay deal was leaked.
The Co-op Bank is now under the control of bondholders as part of last year's refinancing deal to fill a £1.5billion hole in its balance sheet.
Its latest update means the starting capital position of the bank for its four to five-year recovery is weaker than when last year's rescue plan was announced.
Continuing reviews of processes, procedures and documentation had produced further conduct and legal issues, the bank said.
In addition, one-off costs associated with the separation of the bank from the Co-operative Group have proved more costly, time-consuming and more complex than anticipated.
Its capital ratio, a measure of its fi-nancial strength, is now expected to be about 7.2 per cent, against the regulatory minimum requirement of seven per cent.
Mr Booker added: 'The new executive team brought in just nine months ago is continuing to review aspects of the Co-operative Bank's legacy operations, assets and liabilities. 'As a result of this continuing review, we are unearthing a range of issues which the new executive team is having to address.' Staff numbers have been reduced by 1,000 in the past year, which is equivalent to 14 per cent of its workforce, as part of a planned 15 per cent cut in branches.
]]></text></news-item>