<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-MH61-JD34-V03B"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Harassment case thrown out of court</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>Angela Macdonald-Smith</author><text><![CDATA[Former senior EnergyAustralia executive Kate Shea has lost her unfair dismissal case against the country's third-biggest electricity and gas retailer and had her credibility and reliability openly questioned.
In a 219-page decision released in Melbourne on Tuesday, Federal Court Justice Julie Dodds-Streeton said Ms Shea was "not, in my opinion, an impressive, persuasive or reliable witness".
Ms Shea had alleged she was sacked from her almost $500,000-a-year position in February 2012 because she had complained of sexual harassment by another executive during a work trip to Hong Kong two years earlier.
But the judge concluded that EnergyAustralia had shown that none of the alleged complaints by Ms Shea was a material factor that led to the decision to make her position redundant.
During the trial last year, Ms Shea, the former corporate affairs director at EnergyAustralia, then known as TRUenergy, was accused of acting against the chief executive Richard McIndoe.
Energy Australia, owned by Hong Kong-listed CLP Group, argued Ms Shea was dismissed as part of a company restructure and that she brought the harassment case in a bid to damage Mr McIndoe's reputation.
Mr McIndoe was described by Judge Dodds-Streeton in her decision as "an impressive, conscientious and credible witness".
She found "no reasonable basis" for Ms Shea's allegations of misconduct by Mr McIndoe and then human resources manager David Purvis to whom Ms Shea made complaints about the conduct of then chief financial officer Kevin Holmes.
Mr McIndoe is set to leave his position at EnergyAustralia by June, after tendering his notice just before Christmas in order to lead an unidentified Hong Kong-based energy technology business.
Counsel for Ms Shea argued in October that she deserved more than $6 million in compensation for unfair dismissal, to cover past and estimated future losses.
EnergyAustralia had argued the compensation claim was not warranted partly because it incorrectly assumed the company would be publicly listed by 2015.
Judge Dodds-Streeton said the compensation claim was inflated by excessive assumptions about salary increases, and said a public listing by 2015 could not be assumed.
She also said five years was too long for Ms Shea to assume she would be without similar employment and suggested two years would be more appropriate. She said Ms Shea had failed to mitigate her loss by more actively seeking alternative employment.
The judge said Ms Shea's reinstatement would be "inappropriate" and pointed to a break-down in trust and confidence between Ms Shea and the company.
Ms Shea left the court without commenting. Her lawyer, Katrina Raymond, couldn't be reached.
Energy Australia said it was "pleased" with the decision.
"We believe this validates our strong view the business acted with integrity and respect at all times during the handling of Ms Shea's redundancy," it said.
"It has been extremely disappointing to hear and read the claims made about individuals and our culture all of which the court has today dismissed," the company said, adding it had a "robust code of conduct" for employees.
Ms Shea had alleged that a lewd culture prevailed at EnergyAustralia in which denigration of women and sexual harassment was pervasive and condoned.
Ms Shea is now a part-owner of Brisbane-based sub-metering business Smart Building Services, which provides developers and apartment buildings with metered utility services in electricity and water.
With Nassim Khadem
]]></text></news-item>