<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-B771-DYG2-R01M"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Kirk, Cornyn Target Gangs that Target Children</title><source>Targeted News Service</source><author>Targeted News Service</author><text><![CDATA[The office of Sen. Mark Kirk, R-Ill., issued the following news release:
U.S. Sens. Mark Kirk (R-Ill.) and John Cornyn (R-Texas) were joined today by Cook County State's Attorney Anita Alvarez and Cook County Sheriff Tom Dart to demonstrate how the Justice for Victims of Trafficking Act (S. 1738) will change the way the U.S. prosecutes child sex traffickers.
"Organized crime is a major driver of sex trafficking--especially as it pertains to the victimization of children," Sen. Kirk said. "The Justice for Victims of Trafficking Act, of which I am an original cosponsor, improves the federal racketeering statutes by allowing law enforcement to prosecute anyone who knowingly assists or facilitates organized crime organizations in human trafficking. The federal government can and should work to end the act of gangs profiting from modern-day slavery."
The nation's Racketeer Influenced Corrupt Organizations (RICO) statutes are widely recognized as law enforcement's most potent weapons against organized crime. The Justice for Victims of Trafficking Act applies RICO's principles to organized sex trafficking and improves the national, state and local responses to victims of human trafficking.
"The scourge of human trafficking is far too prevalent, especially in Texas," Sen. Cornyn said. "I look forward to working with my colleagues on both sides of the aisle to pass legislation that ends modern-slavery and delivers justice for the victims of this crime."
"Senate Bill 1738 would provide exceptional enhancements for those of us fighting human trafficking at the local level by providing our domestic victims with equal footing under federal law and granting crucial victim support for programs and services," said Cook County State's Attorney Anita Alvarez. "I am extremely pleased to be supporting Senator Kirk and others in working to bring new and important federal penalties and resources in our ongoing efforts to attack human trafficking here in Cook County and throughout jurisdictions across the country."
"Senate Bill 1738 would provide exceptional enhancements for those of us fighting human trafficking at the local level by providing our domestic victims with equal footing under federal law and granting crucial victim support for programs and services," said Cook County State's Attorney Anita Alvarez. "I am extremely pleased to be supporting Senator Kirk and others in working to bring new and important federal penalties and resources in our ongoing efforts to attack human trafficking here in Cook County and throughout jurisdictions across the country."
"Trafficked individuals - the overwhelming majority of whom were forced into the sex trade as juveniles - have been violated in nearly every conceivable way, enduring rape and slavery-type conditions," said Cook County Sheriff Tom Dart. "The services proposed in this bill represent an integral step in providing victims with a renewed sense of dignity and a second chance at life."
In addition to Sens. Kirk and Cornyn, the bill's original cosponsors are Sens. Amy Klobuchar (D-Minn.), Marco Rubio (R-Fla.), and Ron Wyden (D-Ore.)
Senator Kirk worked to include language in Justice for Victims of Trafficking Act that would improve federal racketeering laws by giving law enforcement the ability to prosecute those who assist in human trafficking, not just those who are part of the operation or management of a ring. This provision would also allow for prosecution of those giving financial assistance to a criminal network's activities.
The bill will increase the maximum penalties for human trafficking-related offenses including enticement into slavery, obstruction of a human trafficking investigation, and repeat child exploitation offenses.
"All levels of government need to work together to combat this victimization of the most vulnerable among us," Sen. Kirk said. "That's why Sen. Cornyn and I are glad to have the support of local leaders like Sheriff Dart and State's Attorney Alvarez. Together, we can prosecute and end the practice of trafficking."
Sens. Kirk and Cornyn also worked together on the Stop Exploitation Through Trafficking Act (SETT--S. 1733), which also aims to combat sex trafficking.
More information on Sen. Kirk's efforts to end child sex trafficking can be found here.http://www.kirk.senate.gov/?p=end_child_sex_trafficking
Copyright Targeted News Services
TNS 30TacordaCheng-140325-4677678 30TacordaCheng
]]></text></news-item>