<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-HVM1-JBJ4-205J"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Private Sector Eyes Stake in Growing Oil, Gas Subsector</title><source>Tanzania Daily News</source><author>Finnigan Wa Simbeye</author><text><![CDATA[TANZANIA Private Sector Foundation (TPSF) Chairman, Reginald Abraham Mengi and Chief Executive Officers (CEO) roundtable Chairman, Ali Mufuruki, are bitter people.
Since the government announced the Fourth Round of Oil and Gas blocks allocation exercise last October, the two business leaders have opposed the move, arguing that the country needs to put a legal framework first before the blocks allocation can proceed.
While addressing a news conference last October, Mr Mengi said mistakes done with the mining sector where the country earned peanuts, while multinationals reaped windfall profits should not be repeated.
"Justice among our people is necessary for the promotion of peace, tranquility and social stability that has characterised our society should be backed by proper allocation of resources.
"Unfortunately, the National Economic Empowerment Act was not implemented in the manner that would have empowered Tanzanians in the mining sector," Mengi who is also IPP Group Executive Chairman, said.
Mr Mufuruki added his voice by arguing that without a national gas policy and an up-to-date oil and gas law, the government is simply repeating mistakes made in the mining sector.
"It's an issue of putting the cart before the horse, we seem not to have learnt from past mistakes," argued the Infotech Group CEO and Chairman.
Energy and Minerals Minister, Prof Sospeter Muhongo and President Jakaya Kikwete have on different occasions reassured the nation that all is well and that mistakes made in the past relating to the mining sector, will not be repeated.
"Under the current arrangement, our national interests are more than safeguarded with TPDC as our representative," President Kikwete said last October when he officially kick-started the Fourth Oil and Gas licensing round.
Mr Kikwete said signed Production Sharing Agreements (PSA) allow investors to earn between 25 and 35 per cent of revenue once commercial production starts, while the government through Tanzania Petroleum Development Corporation (TPDC) gets the remaining 75-65 per cent.
"This is an expensive area to invest in, hence we will allow companies to recover their costs before sharing the profits," President Kikwete pointed out as he dismissed elements of the society which are portraying his administration as not taking care of national interests.
In a paper presented at an Oil and Gas conference held in Dar es Salaam last year, Mr Mengi argued that what the private sector wants is not buying shares from TPDC at a later stage but rather have local content clearly stipulated through a legal framework.
"The most successful countries that have achieved a national content level of 40 - 80 per cent include Brazil, Malaysia, the United Kingdom and Norway.
In its effort to ensure local participation by Angolan suppliers in the oil and gas supply chain, Angola has identified a number of products and services which Angolan suppliers have competence in and this group has been categorised as opportunities for Angolan suppliers only," he argued.
One of such areas where locals are losing out is insuring assets being used by multinationals in oil and gas exploration and extraction.
It's an area worth billions of shillings which the local insurance industry cannot do without. In one example, Norwegian state owned Statoil has so far spent about 1bn US$ (over 1.6trn/-) on exploration work and plans to spend US$ 30bn in partnership with ExxonMobil.
Statoil Executive Vice President responsible for Development and Production International, Lars Bacher said recently in Dar es Salaam that locals will benefit from the investment. Local insurance companies are already excited about developments in their field.
There is big hope that by next June, local insurers will get a stake in underwriting property and services being offered by multinational oil and gas exploration companies. Association of Tanzania Insurers (ATI) Chairperson, Ms Maryanne Mugo said low capitalisation which has kept most local insurance firms away from joining the lucrative sub-sector, is being addressed.
"Plans are underway and hopefully before the end of the first half of the year the arrangements will be in place," Ms Mugo said, pointing out that the main reasons which have kept local companies out of the business include low capitalisation and lack of underwriting capacity and skills.
She said the country's insurance industry is in the process of forming a consortium to underwrite risks in oil and gas sub-sector, which grosses in billions of dollars due to the nature of equipment used and services provided.
"Currently, a lot of discussions and lobbying are going on with all stakeholders to ensure that the local insurance industry benefits from the oil and gas sectors," Ms Mugo who is also General Manager of First Assurance Tanzania Limited, noted.
With a gross premium estimated at over 400bn/- per annum, the country's insurance industry has failed to benefit from the lucrative oil and gas sub- sector for over a decade but now stakeholders want a share of the market. Through Tanzania National Reinsurance Corporation Limited (TAN-RE), insurance companies hope that they can underwrite up to 20 per cent of oil and gas sub-sector.
TAN-RE CEO, Mr Rajab Kakusa, said recently that due to the size and scale of the capital involved, the risks posed by oil and gas extraction cannot be carried by a single insurance company alone. Given the country's lack of experience in the oil and gas sector, Mr Kakusa noted that TAN-RE has sought consultants from abroad with experience in oil and gas extraction, to help advice the domestic industry.
"Working together can enable us get a bigger stake in this business," Mr Kakusa said recently while delivering a paper on oil and gas sub-sector in relationship with insurance industry.
Experts estimate that with booming oil and gas extraction, the country's annual gross premium will peak 2trn/- in the next five to 10 years.
Recently, the government was advised to ensure the energy policy being formulated contains a clause that demands oil and gas businesses to be insured by firms registered in Tanzania.
The Commissioner of Insurance, Mr Israel Kamuzora, told this paper at the time that the strategic clause was crucial to ensure national interests were vigilantly protected.
]]></text></news-item>