<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-0261-DY9P-N11P"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Aldi sausage rolls taken off shelves over food safety</title><source>Irish Daily Mail</source><author>Sandra Mallon</author><text><![CDATA[ALDI has been forced to remove a brand of sausage rolls from its shelves after the food preservative sulphur dioxide was not declared on the label.
The Food Safety Authority of Ireland has asked the German grocery giant to remove Kelly's pork sausage rolls from shelves for fear it could cause an allergic reaction to consumers.
Sulphur dioxide and sulphites are generally used for their preservative effects in foods but they can cause reactions, especially in asthmatics.
The packets affected include Kelly's eight premium mini pork sausage rolls, Kelly's 16 premium cocktail pork sausage rolls, and Kelly's four jumbo pork sausage rolls.
In a statement on its website last night, the FSAI said: 'Sulphites were not declared on the label of all batches of the sausage rolls listed above.
'This may make them unsafe for consumers who are allergic to or intolerant of sulphur dioxide or sulphites. These products were sold in Aldi stores.' The supermarket said it had taken prompt steps to protect consumers and apologised for any inconvenience caused.
In a statement to the Irish Daily Mail last night, Aldi said: 'Aldi Stores (Ireland) takes the quality of all our products extremely seriously and demands the highest standards from our suppliers.
'In addition, Aldi carries out regular independent testing of all products we sell.
'Aldi can confirm that routine product testing highlighted a labelling issue in relation to our Kelly's sausage roll products.
'We immediately informed the Food Safety Authority of Ireland of the matter and removed the products from sale.
'We are now investigating the issue with our supplier. Customers who have purchased this product should return it to their nearest Aldi store for a full refund. We apologise for any inconvenience and thank customers for their co-operation. 'No other Aldi products are affected by this issue.' Sulphur dioxide and sulphites are permitted in a wide range of foods - including dried fruits, breakfast sausages and burger meats. However, they are considered allergy-sensitive and can cause reactions in certain people, especially asthmatics.
The most common reaction is wheezing, tightening of the chest and a cough.
Severe allergic reactions to sulphites (anaphylaxis) have been reported but are very rare. Some people with urticaria, a type of skin rash, can also experience worsening of symptoms after eating food with sulphites.
Therefore, for pre-packaged meal, their presence in a food or beverage must be indicated on the label, by its full name, where the level exceeds 10mg/kg or 10mg/L. Other foods that contain sulphites include bakery goods, soup mixes, jams, canned vegetables, pickled foods and vinegar, potato crisps and sparkling grape juice.
Tea, fresh or frozen prawns and guacamole also contain sulphites. A spokesman for Kelly's could not be contacted for comment last night.
Last June, Aldi was forced to recall all batches of Duneen Chocolate Yoghurts, as soya was not declared on the ingredients list or on the allergen warning box. These yoghurts may be unsafe for consumers who are allergic or intolerant to soya.
Last month, the FSAI revealed there were 13,269 queries and complaints to it last year. Up to 2,846 related specifically to complaints by consumers about food and food premises - up 12.5 per cent on 2012.
Meanwhile, 10,429 complaints involved requests for advice across a range of food-related areas - up 9 per cent on 2012.
Consumer complaints ranged from reports of food unfit to eat, to inaccurate labelling.
There were 1,190 complaints on unfit food, 566 complaints on suspect food poisoning, 587 complaints on hygiene standards, and 192 on incorrect information on food labelling. Contamination of food with foreign objects was frequently reported by consumers, including food contaminated with plastic, metal and glass fragments, as well as other foreign objects.
Edel Smyth, information manager for the FSAI, said last month: 'On the one hand, more food businesses are contacting us, seeking to raise their foodsafety standards while, on the other, consumers are increasingly vigilant and aware of the need to report bad practice or experiences they've had where food safety is compromised.
'We continue to encourage anyone who has had a bad experience in relation to poor hygiene or food-safety standards to report the matter to us so that the issue can be investigated directly. Consumers are entitled to the highest standard of food safety and hygiene in every food establishment and across every food product they purchase.
'It is the responsibility of food businesses across the country to ensure that they provide food which does not compromise the health of anyone who eats it.' sandra.mallon@dailymail.ie
'Sulphites were not declared'
'Routine testing highlighted issue'
]]></text></news-item>