<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-5381-DY37-900W"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Protesters target GEO chief; Activists in Boca express solidarity with hunger strikers in corporation's centers.</title><source>Palm Beach Post (Florida)</source><author> By John Lantigua   Palm Beach Post Staff Writer </author><text><![CDATA[Human rights activists staged a protest Monday outside the gated community of the president of a private prison company, expressing their solidarity with hunger strikers currently being held in private immigration detention centers.
About a dozen protesters gathered around a fountain just outside the Royal Yacht & Country Club community, one of whose residents is George Zoley, president of GEO Group of Boca Raton.
GEO operates immigration detention centers in Tacoma, Wash., and Conroe, Texas, where over the past two weeks inmates have staged hunger strikes, protesting both the federal government's deportation policies and conditions at the facilities.
"George Zoley is a bad neighbor," read one sign held by the demonstrators.
"George Zoley, corporate greed, crimes against humanity," was one of the chants they sang during an hour long, rain-drenched protest.
With immigration reform legislation hung up in the U.S. House, activists nationwide have turned their attention to the Obama administration's continuing detention and deportation of undocumented immigrants.
Between people captured just inside the border and others detained in the interior of the country and deported, the administration has expelled some 2 million illegal immigrants. It has deported people at a higher rate than any other administration in history.
GEO runs eight immigration detention centers holding 8,500 beds. GEO spokesman Pablo Paez responded to the protest in an email to The Palm Beach Post.
"Our company has had a long-standing, public-private partnership with the federal government that dates back to mid-1980s. GEO's facilities, including the Northwest Detention Center (in Tacoma), provide high quality services in safe, secure, and humane residential environments, and our company strongly refutes allegations to the contrary.
"Our facilities adhere to strict contractual requirements and standards set by U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE)," Paez wrote.
He said the facilities also provide office space for ICE personnel, immigration attorneys, immigration court judges, nongovernmental organizations and other constituent groups "who have unfettered access to each facility."
GEO's total revenues last year were $1.5 billion. But its facilities -- both its prisons and its immigration detention centers -- have also been cited by courts for human rights violations over the years, and GEO has lost multimillion-dollar judgments . Some states have also responded by canceling contracts with GEO .
The latest accusations have come from the Texas and Washington facilities.
The Texas center, named the Joe Corley Detention Facility, has a capacity for 1,517 inmates. A lawyer who saw a client there last week told The Palm Beach Post that as of then about 120 inmates were participating in the hunger strike.
The Tacoma facility has a 1,575-inmate capacity, and it was estimated by sources there that at one point, 1,200 inmates were participating before it shrank to just a few inmates last week. Neither of those figures could be confirmed with the Immigration and Customs Enforcement, which oversees the centers.
The strikers in both prisons were demanding an end to deportations and overcrowding of cells, better food and medical care, and reduced costs for phone calls, which they say are exorbitant.
"We're here today to amplify the demands of people who are behind bars," said Britni Hiatt, 23, a graduate student at Florida Atlantic University and an organizer of the Boca Raton protest.
She said all the issues raised by the Texas and Washington detainees also applied to detainees at the Broward Transitional Center, an immigration detention center run by GEO in Pompano Beach.
Another issue for the protesters is the federal "bed mandate," a $2 billion program approved by Congress that dictates that 34,000 beds in immigration detention centers be filled at all times.
The mandate was added to Homeland Security Department budget in 2009 at the behest of Sen. Robert Byrd, D-W.Va., although its defenders today are mostly Republicans.
The protesters called for an end to the mandate, as did U.S. Rep. Ted Deutch, D-Boca Raton, who has sponsored legislation to end it.
"I understand why they are out there with those signs," Deutch said in a phone call from Washington.
Deutch said the mandate caused many undocumented immigrants who are not threats to society to be locked up, which costs U.S. taxpayers more than $1 billion each year.
He said that ICE would better use that money to fight human trafficking, child pornography and other crimes.
Staff writer Pat Beall contributed to this story. jlantigua@pbpost.com
Detention center incidents
Among the reported incidents in GEO's detention facilities were:
In 2008, an undocumented immigrant died in solitary confinement after an epileptic seizure; he had been placed on a cheaper and less effective anti-seizure medicine after arriving at the GEO center in Reeves County, Texas, and had been experiencing frequent seizures as a result. Inmates rioted after seeing his body removed and then rioted again a few months later, claiming substandard medical care.
Undocumented immigrant Miroslava Rod­riguez-Grava was placed in a GEO-run detention center pending deportation in 2006. She was refused psychiatric medication and soon began deteriorating mentally, at which point guards took her crutches, and had her placed naked in an isolation cell.
A year earlier, an Army veteran diagnosed with schizophrenia had been detained and not given previously prescribed medication. When his mental state deteriorated, he was moved to solitary. Both sued.
In 2009, a GEO hiring supervisor admitted that she hired 92 guards at an immigrant detention center without background checks.
]]></text></news-item>