<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-SC11-JD34-V1C4"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Tension rises in reality pawn show</title><source>The Age (Melbourne, Australia)</source><author>Ben Pobjie</author><text><![CDATA[In the history of reality TV, there have been a few truly seismic moments, moments that changed the landscape forever. The premiere of Big Brother, for example, or the production in a secret lab of Simon Cowell.
But has any discovery been more exciting than that of some genius producer who found that the word "pawn" sounds the same as the word "porn"? It has created an industry, and one of television's most storied rivalries: Pawn Stars versus Hardcore Pawn (7mate, 8.30pm).
They are pretty easy to distinguish: Pawn Stars is the one about a family of pawnbrokers who are all shaped like space hoppers and agonise over whether to buy first-edition Dickens novels and autographed baseballs.
Hardcore Pawn is the one about a family of pawnbrokers who scream at each other and have their security guards escort angry people off the premises.
In this, the ninth episode of the ninth series (I know, right?), one such furious gentleman is expelled after banging on the bulletproof glass in response to Ashley's request that he spell his girlfriend's name. It's a long story, but basically he did not want to spell his girlfriend's name, and so he gets bounced. Much more amicable are the creepy guys who come in to American Jewellery and Loan to buy chainsaws to defend themselves against the imminent zombie apocalypse.
It sounds ridiculous, but is a lot more plausible after looking at the pawn shop's average clientele. It's not so much a place of business as a daytime fight club with guitars on the walls.
But the main narrative isn't the brawling or the zombies - it is the attempts made by Les to sell the 40,000 watchbands that he previously, inexplicably, accepted as payment in place of money. Les doesn't really have a head for business: he got ito the pawn game mainly for the yelling and fistfights. As his desperation grows, and the people of Detroit demonstrate a powerful reluctance to buy watchbands from a scary old man who shouts at them, tension in the Gold family intensifies and the beeps on the soundtrack become ever more vehement.
Nobody will ever be proud of watching Hardcore Pawn, but somehow it is human nature to want to watch insane people threaten violence over how much their disgusting fur coat is worth.
The stakes seem so much higher on Sons of Anarchy (ONE, 9.30pm), although they're really much lower, given everyone on the show is made up.
However, the gravelly portetousness of Charlie Hunnam's voice-over makes you believe this is damn serious stuff.
Everything's always serious in the charmingly titled Charming, California, and Wednesday's episode has Jax looking to bring the club ito a new business venture, while enduring the heat from a series of home invasions being blamed on the Sons, and fighting with Irishmen. This is one intense show - it could only be more intimidating if the bikers shopped at Hardcore Pawn.
]]></text></news-item>