<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-HRM1-DYJJ-P160"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>In Cold Spring, the race to find water is on</title><source>St. Cloud Times (Minnesota)</source><author>By, Jennifer Vogel</author><text><![CDATA[Inside Cold Spring Brewing, the concrete floors are scattered with pallets of industrial-sized bags of barley, wheat and other beer-making ingredients.
An extremely aromatic room is dedicated to hops for flavoring brews such as Bitter Neighbor Black IPA. Elsewhere, more pallets contain the makings for energy drinks, including Monster and Rockstar, which the brewery custom mixes on contract.
What all these ingredients have in common is that in order to become what they are designed to become, they need water, millions of gallons of water.
"We are a beverage manufacturing facility and a craft brewery," said Brent Neisinger, Cold Spring's director of environmental control. "Water is our business in essence."
And yet the wells from which the brewery has drawn water for a century - it was founded in 1874 - have become a source of contention. The state's Department of Natural Resources wants Cold Spring Brewing to find a new source of water to protect a slender, 1.7-mile-long trout stream that runs through town and along the brewery's property. The stream is fed by the same aquifer that supplies the brewery wells.
The new source will likely come from the city of Cold Spring, which has been digging test wells in search of a clean, self-replenishing pocket of water.
The city is eager to help the brewery, which provides 250 local jobs, but so far has been unsuccessful. Eventually, the brewery expects to pay around $200,000 per year for municipal water to replace what it has essentially always gotten for free or very little.
Water scarce
These are the kinds of conundrums people across the state are grappling with as groundwater, once thought to be endlessly bountiful in Minnesota, becomes scarce in some areas, contaminated in others, and in need of reallocation in still others.
People are casting a critical eye on the state's aquifers and the land that surrounds them, which means some cities and businesses have to operate differently.
In the case of Cold Spring, the issue is that as the brewery has expanded and added products such as energy drinks, it has taken more water from the ground. A state permit allowed it to take 24 million gallons in 1984, but that cap has been raised twice since. Last year the brewery used 114 million gallons, Neisinger said. That was down slightly from 2012, when Cold Spring added a state-of-the-art facility called Third Street Brewhouse.
He said the company has emphasized water conservation and efficiency. "We want to continue to grow the business," he said.
In the state's view, drawing so much well water pulls flow from Cold Spring Creek, increasing sediment and harming a struggling population of trout.
"The aquifer and the stream here are connected," said Dan Lais, a DNR hydrologist and central region district manager who has been working on this case since at least 2009. "That is a picture that I want to make sure I'm painting. They are not disconnected."
Yet, Lais said, "it's not just about people versus trout or beer versus trout." The state as a whole is trying to manage groundwater more effectively, which means considering not only the needs of cities and businesses, but ecological issues, too.
What lurks beneath
It's hard to know exactly what's going on underground, Lais said. It's difficult to gauge how resilient a particular water supply might be, or how it might move. So, when a problem becomes evident above ground, like when a trout stream doesn't have enough water in it, it's important to act.
"We're trying to find the tipping point before it happens," he said. "If it's obvious, like you turn on the tap and no water comes out, you have crossed the threshold. We want to discover how to manage the system much before we get to that point."
But in many people's eyes, the tussle over the brewery's water supply has pitted a small trout stream against the fortunes of a major local business. The brewery was given until late February to stop or significantly reduce its well use, but it was granted an extension to Dec. 31, a deadline likely to be extended again.
"This is the biggest thing on the company's plate," Neisinger said. "Our brewing water is excellent quality water. That is a big deal to us."
Looking for water
Nobody has to tell Paul Hoeschen, Cold Spring's public works director, how hard it is to know what's going on underground. He's been digging test wells, looking for an aquifer that can provide three things: good water quality, proximity to the city and decent recharge.
"I've drilled 10 different wells so far trying to find another quality water source," he said. "They were all failures, for multiple reasons."
Inside his office, Hoeschen pulled up a map on his computer. He pointed to five areas he has tried and described the shortcomings of each. Once a suitable source is found, Cold Spring may spend millions more installing pipe and building a treatment plant.
There is an element of alchemy to the search process. You can look at geology, read drilling logs, take samples from wells and listen to experts. "A lot of times, you listen to two experts and get two different kinds of advice," Hoeschen said.
The city has hunted for water before. In the early 2000s, it closed two wells because of high nitrate levels. It found new wells outside of town and addresses lingering nitrate issues by blending water from various sources. Hoeschen hopes the current search will turn up an aquifer without nitrate problems, because they are expensive to fix.
He'll find it because Cold Spring Brewing matters to the city.
"They pay a lot of taxes," he said. "They employ a lot of people. They are supporting the surrounding businesses, the hardware store and on and on. When they need water, we spend money to get it to them, maybe a million dollars. But they will have to pay monthly bills to buy that water. Eventually the brewery will reimburse us for it."
Hoeschen said the brewery's yearly water bill might be $150,000 to $200,000, depending on whether the DNR closes or reduces the use of the stream-adjacent wells.
Neisinger hopes the DNR will allow the brewery to continue to tap some well water.
"We are trying to negotiate through it to see if we can come to an agreement," he said.
Meanwhile, the December deadline looms. Representatives from the city, the brewery and the DNR met last month to discuss progress. At that meeting, said Hoeschen, they talked about extending the deadline, though no time frame was established. He counted the conversation as "a success."
www.mprnews.org
]]></text></news-item>