<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-0261-DY9P-N2H7"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Co-op Bank woes continue with a £400m cash call; Manchester mutual says it has'unearthed'issues relating to PPI, interest rate swaps and other matters</title><source>Manchester Evening News</source><author>Shelina Begum</author><text><![CDATA[THE Co-operative Group's beleaguered banking arm needs to raise another £400m to cover the cost of past misconduct issues.
The Co-op Bank, which prides itself in ethical lending, said it had 'unearthed' a host of liabilities linked to payment protection insurance, interest rate swaps and breaches of the Consumer Credit Act.
The business, set to report full-year losses of up to £1.3bn for 2013, is now under the control of bondholders as part of last year's refinancing to fill a £1.5bn hole in its balance sheet.
The bank said continuing 'root and branch' reviews of processes, procedures and documentation had produced further conduct and legal issues.
In addition, one-off costs associated with the separation of the bank from the wider Co-operative Group have proved more costly, time-consuming and more complex than anticipated.
Its capital ratio - a measure of its financial strength - is now expected to be around 7.2 per cent, compared with previous guidance of near nine per cent and against the regulatory minimum requirement of seven per cent. The bank's results for 2013 are expected to be announced on or before April 8. The bank said it was focused on improving its capital position and on community banking through retail and small business (SME) customers.
Chief executive Niall Booker added: "The new executive team brought in just nine months ago is continuing to review aspects of the Co-operative Bank's legacy operations, assets and liabilities. As a result of this continuing review, we are unearthing a range of issues which the new executive team is having to address."
Mr Booker said there were some early indications of progress in its turnaround plan.
He added: "We have started to simplify the business, reduce costs and de-risk assets as we drive the change needed to return to our roots as a bank focused on our retail and SME customers.
"There remain signifi-cant challenges ahead."
Staff numbers have been reduced by 1,000 in the last year, as part of a planned 15 per cent cut in its branch estate.
]]></text></news-item>