<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-TRF1-DXDT-609V"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Lloyds accused of shrinking payouts to PPI victims by tens of millions of pounds using a legal loophole</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>RACHEL RICKARD STRAUS</author><text><![CDATA[Payments made using 'alternative redress' - sometimes cutting compensation by thousands of poundsPractise branded a 'scandal coming out of a scandal'Lloyds claims two per cent of PPI victims had payouts with alternative redress applied
Lloyds Banking Group has shrunk payments to PPI victims by tens of millions of pounds by using a legal loophole, an investigation has claimed.
The part state-owned bank was accused of short-changing customers who were mis-sold payment protection insurance policies using an obscure regulatory provision called 'alternative redress'.
Alternative redress allows a bank, in certain circumstances, to assume a customer who was mis-sold PPI would have bought a cheaper, regular PPI policy instead.
It can then subtract the cost of the regular policy from the compensation it pays out - which can amount to thousands of pounds.
PPI expert Cliff D'Arcy told the BBC Lloyds had saved more than £60million over the past year by cutting compensation.
Mr D'Arcy, who previously worked at HBOS's PPI operation, told BBC Radio 4 that the practise was a 'scandal coming out of a scandal'.
'What's happening here is a taxpayer-sponsored bank is depriving taxpayers of their rightful compensation by using a loophole'.
He added: 'Frankly I'm amazed that this problem has existed throughout the last year and hasn't emerged into the light'. 
A large survey of compensation offers undertaken by the Professional Financial Claims Association (PFCA), a trade body representing claims management companies, claimed that in some months of last year Lloyds were applying alternative redress to over 25 per cent of their PPI offers.
Lloyds, which has already set aside £10billion for compensation payouts, strongly disputes the BBC figures.
It claims 98 per cent of its customers who received a PPI compensation payout received full redress - just two per cent alternative redress.
It added that it followed FCA procedures to the letter when applying alternative redress.
A spokesperson said: 'The numbers that have been provided to the BBC by the claims management companies, are incorrect and deeply misleading. Over 98 per cent of upheld PPI claims have been paid with full redress. For less than 2 per cent of claims, we have used a formula agreed with the FCA to offer comparative redress to customers.
The FCA handbook is very clear that in these specific circumstances, the provider should give redress that puts the customer in the position they would have been in had the customer taken the regular premium policy.'
The BBC programme, Britain's Biggest Banking Scandal, cites the case of care worker Veronica Rayner, who had two loans from Halifax, now part of Lloyds Banking Group.
Mrs Rayner told the BBC she received £2,300 compensation from Lloyds after she claimed she had been unaware the bank had sold her PPI policies when she took out the two loans.
However when her case was taken to the Financial Ombudsman Service, Lloyds was told to pay her an additional £1,200 because it had applied alternative redress to her claim.
'I don't think it's very fair. I think they should just offer people the right amounts and get it done. It's cheating people in a way,' Mrs Rayner said.
Claims management companies suggested Mrs Rayner is just one of many PPI victims who have successfully challenged alternative redress.
They told the BBC they have routinely been challenging alternative redress offers from Lloyds by referring them to the Financial Ombudsman Service.
Martin Baker at Renaissance Easy Claim told the BBC the ombudsman had so far ruled on more than 100 of its clients' cases.
'In every single case our challenge has been upheld, and clients will now be entitled to full redress,' he said.
But Lloyds disputed this suggestion. A spokesperson added: 'The numbers for overturn rates are again misleading. The overturn rate for loans claims is the same whether it is for comparative redress or for other reasons.'
They added that any customers with concerns about their PPI payout can get in touch.
]]></text></news-item>