<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-X7W1-DXH0-K05V"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Raja summoned for indictment in RPP scam references</title><source>Dawn (Pakistan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Accountability Court has summoned former prime minister Raja Pervez Ashraf on April 9 to initiate indictment proceedings against him in three references relating to the Rs22 billion Rental Power Projects (RPP) scam.
The court also issued similar notices on Monday to others nominated in the references. Judge Mohammad Bashir heard the case.
It was expected that the former premier and other accused would be indicted, but the court did not do so, apparently because of the absence of the accused.
Mr Ashraf has been accused of misusing his authority as water and power minister while awarding contracts for the projects to some companies in violation of procurement rules.
The National Accountability Bureau (NAB) has been investigating 12 RPP cases, according to which, nine firms received over Rs22bn mobilisation advance from the government to commission the projects but most of them failed to set up plants.
Of the 12 cases, three references relating to Naudero-II, Sahuwal and Piraghaib power projects have been filed in court.
Mr Ashraf appeared before the court as principal accused on Jan 3, with the request that he should not be indicted until the Lahore High Court announced a decision on stay orders obtained by two other accused in the case.
Mr Ashraf's counsel, Farooq Naek, claimed that corruption of Rs7.5 million had been found in a shipment for Naudero power plant which had nothing to do with his client.
NAB filed a supplementary reference in the Naudero-II project case in the court on Nov 7, 2013.
It is expected that Mr Ashraf will face eight more references relating to the RPP scam. Four references have been prepared and are ready to be filed in the court. NAB is working on four others.
Mr Ashraf, whose name has been placed on the Exit Control List, has been accused of obtaining kickbacks and commissions from nine firms for awarding contracts for rental power projects in 2008.
He has also been accused of preparing a misleading summary and submitting it to the federal cabinet, pleading for an increase in the mobilisation advance for the companies from seven to 14 per cent. The summary was approved and authorised for submission to the Executive Committee of the Cabinet on Aug 17, 2009.
Mr Ashraf served as prime minister for nine months in the last PPP government after his predecessor Yousuf Raza Gilani was removed on the orders of the Supreme Court.
]]></text></news-item>