<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-MH61-JD34-V027"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Sinodinos seeks to limit ICAC probe</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>Geoff Winestock</author><text><![CDATA[Arthur Sinodinos's lawyer has told the Independent Commission Against Corruption to stop investigating possible breaches of directors' duties or commercial contracts involving the former assistant treasurer because they have nothing to do with corruption.
ICAC is looking ito allegations of corruption in relation to contracts awarded by state-owned Sydney Water to Australian Water Holdings, a firm where Mr Sinodinos was a director and chairman before joining the Senate.
Tom Bannon, SC, questioned the relevance of evidence from Rod de Aboitiz, an investor who lost money in AWH, who last week told ICAC he warned Mr Sinodinos in 2010 about excessive expenses and donations to the Liberal Party paid by AWH.
The inquiry has heard these expenses were then charged back to Sydney Water under a contract to deliver sewage to north-west Sydney.
Mr Bannon said this was a commercial dispute involving AWH, Sydney Water and its investors with no evidence of corruption involving Mr Sinodinos. "This inquiry is not directed to alleged breaches of directors' duties. It's not a Corporations Act case nor is it a commercial dispute between Sydney Water and AWH," Mr Bannon said.
Megan Latham, ICAC commissioner, allowed Mr de Aboitiz to be recalled to the inquiry saying: "The suggestion is Mr de Aboitiz specifically drew to Mr Sinodinos's attention the possibility that donations to the Liberal Party were within, were within the ambit of the expenses."Smear campaign
The inquiry has heard AWH paid lobbyists, the Liberal Party and a company called EightbyFive linked to Tim Koelma, a Liberal staffer. Mr Koelma has been linked to a smear campaign against Sydney Water executives including former managing director Kerry Schott who questioned AWH's expenses and opposed a proposal for a much bigger, more lucrative contract for AWH. Dr Schott was on Tuesday asked about evidence she gave on Monday that she had told Mr Sinodinos that AWH might be "dishonest".
Mr Bannon asked why she had said this even though Sydney Water had not said anything about dishonesty in the course of its long-running dispute with AWH over expenses and contracts.
"It was a personal warning to Mr Sinodinos who I thought very highly of," Dr Schott said. She said it was a "friendly comment" and she "admired him."
The inquiry also heard from Peter Phillips, a consultant for Sydney Water who had the job of checking whether AWH expenses complied with its contract with Sydney Water.
Mr Phillips said that when he questioned the expenses in 2008, a finance manager at AWH Vass Kuznetsov, said that NSW Right MPs including Eddie Obeid and Joe Tripodi were "making a move" on then premier Morris Iemma and once the premier was removed part of the pay-off for that would be that AWH would be given a bigger water contract. Mr Phillips said when Mr Iemma was forced to resign six to eight weeks later it was "sobering".
The inquiry heard that Mr Obeid took a $3 million investment in AWH and Mr Tripodi was involved in a plot to fake a cabinet minute about a contract for AWH. Mr Sinodinos has denied knowing of the Obeid's investment.
The inquiry has heard that Mr Obeid told then Water Minister Phillip Costa to "sack the bitch" referring to Dr Schott and warning a corruption allegation would be made against her.
The inquiry has heard that an anonymous allegation was made against Dr Schott to ICAC. Dr Schott said on Tuesday that another allegation of corruption was made to the premier's department about her decision to award a consulting contract to Ron Quill, a senior Sydney Water executive, a few months after she retired.
Dr Schott said the premier's department had investigated the allegation and dismissed it. She said she had cleared the payments with Sydney Water's board. READ NEXT: Abbott dodges questions on Sinodinos appointment Sinodinos was warned over 'dishonest' AWH
]]></text></news-item>