<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-HVM1-JBJ4-206F"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Auditor Probes Tanzania Power Contractor Account</title><source>East African Business Week (Kampala)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The controversial payment saga of the Tegeta Escrow account is undergoing investigation by the Controller and Auditor General (CAG) as Prevention and Combating of Corruption Bureau (PCCB) probes the entire process of the Independent Power Tanzania Limited (IPTL) deal with PAP.
Tegeta Escrow account was opened following a dispute between the government through its ministry of Energy and Minerals and IPTL on modalities of paying capacity charges.
The account which held by the Bank of Tanzania (BoT) acts as a financial instrument held by a third party on behalf of the other two parties in a transaction.
According to the agreement the funds are held by the escrow service until it receives the appropriate written or oral instructions or until obligations have been fulfilled.
PAP, the Pan Africa Power Solutions (T) Limited is the company that has acquired IPTL in a deal that has been highly questioned by some legal experts who raised a concern on how a once liquidated company becomes the assignee, and assigned its shares to a new investor.
IPTL, the independent power producers, who sale electricity to Tanzania Electricity Supply Company (Tanesco) has agreed with the Ministry of Energy and Minerals to authorize the payment of $122.2 million and Tsh161.4 billion ($98.63 million) to the IPTL project's new owner, PAP.
Meanwhile, there is another company called Mechmar, a Malaysian firm that used to own 70% of IPTL before it was liquidated, and it wasn't known if it signed any agreement to sell its shares to PAP as claimed or not.
According to BoT Governor, Prof Benno Ndullu, they have already transferred the funds to PAP account between November 28 and December 8, last year.
This has raise fear to Public Account Committee (PAC). The committee has decided to order CAG office and the PCCB to investigate the saga so as to know in and out.
The PAC Chairman, Zitto Kabwe said in Dar es Salaam last week that they have decided to conduct special auditing on the whole issue.
]]></text></news-item>