<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-HVM1-JBJ4-208F"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Yet Another Probe</title><source>This Day (Lagos)</source><author>Shola Oyeyipo</author><text><![CDATA[Probes instituted into the death of the 19 people, who passed on during the immigration recruitment exercise do not seem to excite many.
In the views of many Nigerians, all efforts must be put in place to unravel those behind the criminal negligence that led to the untimely death of 19 job seekers at the various venues of the interview for job placement at the Nigerian Immigration Service (NIS) penultimate weekend. The incident has generated outcry from the people, many of whom are seeking appropriate punishment for those involved. For instance, the National Human Rights Commission (NHRC), Citizens Advocacy for Social and Economic Rights (CASER), opposition All Progressives Congress (APC), Nigerian Labour Congress (NLC), the Trade Union Congress (TUC), Champions for Nigeria and a host of other persons and groups have called on the Attorney-General of the Federation as well as the Inspector-General of Police together with the Director-General of State Security, to launch a joint criminal investigation into the avoidable deaths of the job seekers.
Since the development penultimate week, Nigerians have been asking questions with a view to finding answers to some of the questions agitating their minds. Many people, for instance, will like to know who ordered that the entire recruitment exercise is conducted the same day. Why the number of job seekers was not pruned down in view of the last experience? Which of the agencies of government provided security and coordinated the activities as well as those who represented the Comptroller-General, the Civil Defence, Fire Immigration and Prison Service Board (CDFIPB) of the Ministry of Interior at each of the venues? It is also imperative to know when the police, the civil defence, the Federal Road Safety Corps (FRSC) and other government agencies were informed about the recruitment exercise. Did the concerned agencies meet prior to the exercise to anticipate the magnitude of such a crowd and develop a strategy to manage the applicants, considering the staggering figure of those expected at the venues? How many officers of what agencies were deployed at each scene? Was any agency specialised in crowd management deployed to the venue? Such questions are critical in order to determine what went wrong on the tragic day. If Lagos State postponed the same exercise due to insufficient preparations and why was the exercise not suspended in other centres to avoid the consequences of the poor management? Why was there no prompt information and effective coordination that could have provided ease of documentation of casualties, injured and missing persons until about 24 hours later? Was there any agency assigned to provide psychological support to the injured and relatives of the deceased as first responders? These are some of the questions that people have been pondering on. Indeed, prominent Nigerians have continued to ask that Minister of Interior, Mr. Aba Moro and the NIS Comptroller-General, Mr. David Parradang, be dismissed.
Those who have called for their dismissal include Chairman, NHRC, Mr. Chidi Odinkalu; former Minister of the Federal Capital Territory, Nasir El-Rufai; lawyer and human rights activist, Ayo Obe (SAN); former presidential candidate of the defunct National Republican Convention, Bashir Tofa; novelist, Lola Shoneyin and Yemi Candide-Johnson. There among the dismissal advocates are Ayesha Imam, Jibrin Ibrahim, Ishyaku Mohammed, Olusegun Adeniyi, Hussaini Abdu, Femi Edun, Abubakar Siddique Mohammed, Abba Kyari, Kole Shettima, Maryam Uwais, Ebere Onwudiwe, Nasir Ahmed El-Rufai, Yusuf Tuggar, Tajudeen Fola Adeola, Waziri Adio, Bashir Yusuf Ibrahim, Iniruo Wills, Yunusa Yau, Nasir Ladan, Aliyu Modibbo and Jeremy Weate, amongst others. They are all of the views that the two lead characters should be relieved of their jobs as quickly as possible. To them, their negligence was partly responsible for the death of the job seekers. Another issue the incident has brought to the fore was the allegation of corruption that manifested in the alleged extortion of the hapless 700, 000 youths competing for 4,500 job openings. The entire exercise was carried out with impunity and disregards for the directive by the House of Representatives which ordered agencies of government to desist from charging applicants fees for taking part in recruitment exercise. A pathetic aspect of the incident was an attempt by the minister to place the blame on the victims rather than take responsibility. He thought the victims were: "impatience" and that "they did not follow the laid down procedures spelt out to them before the exercise". With this statement, many castigated him and thought he had no regard for life. Already, the two chambers of the National Assembly have commenced investigation into the deaths. While the Senate, last week, commenced public investigation into the deaths, the House of Representatives mandated a multi-committee probe. Likewise, the federal government is setting up a probe panel. But Nigerians are not quite excited but disenchanted. They have no trust in the fact that the probe would produce a meaningful result. This mindset is premised on the piling records of inconclusive and fruitless probes in the country. It is common place in Nigeria that when an event takes place, probe panels are set up to investigate the cause and recommend appropriate actions. But their reports are dumped on the shelves to gather dust. For example, nothing has been heard since the probe panel set up to investigate the killing of some members of the National Youth Service Corps (NYSC) in the North submitted its report. Many are therefore tempted to ask: "Of what use are these probe panels" when it is unlikely to yield result.
Among probe panels whose reports have not been implemented are the recent fuel subsidy probe and several others such as the Human Rights Violations Investigations Panel (Oputa Panel) June 1999; Justice Obiora Nwazota Panel on NAL management, September 1999; Senate probe of Nigerian National Petroleum Commission (NNPC) under Gaius-Obaseki, 2003; Maritime Workers Union probe (Pats-Acholonu Panel) October 2001; Nigerdock management probe panel, September 2001 and the Bola Ajibola Panel on Jos disturbances of 2010. There were such others like the Mike Okiro Panel on Halliburton scam; House of Representatives probe of energy sector, 2008; Senate probe of FCT Minister, El-Rufai, 2008; House probe of Railway project; federal government import duty waiver probe, 2010; Senate probe of Jos crisis, December 2008; House probe of Finance Ministry over 2007 budget, 2008 as well as the federal government probe of oil blocks and petroleum importation between 1999 and 2004. There was the House probe of the Jos crisis; January 2009; House probe of Customs scam, January 2009; Senate probe of Obasanjo and Yar'Adua on solid minerals special account, February 2009; National Assembly probe of World Bank Aviation loans of 2006 in March 2009; Senate probe of federal government sale of houses in Lagos and Abuja; House probe of sale of Nigerian House in New York, February 2010; Senate probe of lead poisoning in Zamfara, 2010 and federal government probe of NAICOM boss in March 2007.
President Goodluck Jonathan, of course, has made efforts at dousing the public outrage that attended the incident. He devoted the entire session of last Wednesday's cabinet meeting to console the families of those who died as a result of the stampede and immediately directed the cancellation of the recruitment exercise and ordered that a fresh one should be conducted. To compensate the bereaved, he offered each family of those that lost their loved ones three slots each and the injured, automatic employment. Even with that, the call for a closer look into the matter was not suppressed as many are seeking appropriate sanctions as deterrent to others. As it is, there is growing pessimism whether the NIS death probe panels will serve any purpose on the long run.
]]></text></news-item>