<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-N951-JCW9-X0MY"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Brent Batten: Some things better left unsaid, but they aren't</title><source>Naples Daily News (Florida)</source><author>BRENT BATTEN</author><text><![CDATA[Imagine how quiet things would be around here if everyone adhered to the adage, “If you can’t say something nice about someone, don’t say anything.”
Republican candidates for Florida’s U.S. House District 19 seat and their proxies are filling the airwaves with negative ads about each other at a rate that makes even Billy Fuccillo’s media presence seem, well, not so huge.
Academic studies of negative advertising in politics are a mixed bag, with some showing them effective when used in moderation and others indicating they may hurt the sponsor more than the target. But candidates and their consultants obviously believe they work because the three best-funded candidates in the race, with the help of the Super PACs supporting them, are investing heavily in dirt. A new round of filings by the Liberty and Leadership Fund shows the group, which shares an address with a political committee formed by candidate Lizbeth Benacquisto, is dumping another $70,000 into attacks on Curt Clawson, the self-proclaimed outsider for the seat. Meanwhile, Values are Vital, a Super PAC funded by friends of candidate Paige Kreegel continues to spend from its war chest in excess of $1 million on attacks against Benacquisto and Clawson. Clawson, without a Super PAC to boost his cause, is using some of his own money to buy ads attacking Benacquisto and Kreegel. His campaign staff also takes pains to on one hand decry the attacks against him and on the other point out damaging information about his rivals. Some of the recent activity in the race includes: Expenditure reports filed with the Federal Elections Commission on Wednesday, Thursday and Friday of last week show Liberty and Leadership Fund spending an additional $70,000 on anti-Clawson TV ads and mailers. All told, Liberty and Leadership Fund has spent more than $200,000 with various ad agencies and consultants. Still unfiled with the FEC is a financial disclosure form showing the source of Liberty and Leadership Fund’s funds. The same three days brought three new filings from Values are Vital showing anti-Benacquisto advertising buys. One item arriving in mailboxes will be an “ethics violation” mailer targeting Benacquisto, the reports suggest. The flyer apparently highlights the charge leveled at Benacquisto accusing her of using money from her state senate campaign to build name recognition for her current run for Congress. Benacquisto said the money was spent as part of her senate campaign before she filed papers to run for Congress on Feb. 3. Values are Vital’s total spending in opposition to Benacquisto and Clawson totals more than $600,000 to date. The Clawson camp has been busy as well. Last week, the campaign sent out an email questioning whether Kreegel was working in tandem with Values are Vital, something not allowed under federal election law. The basis of the charge was a voice mail Kreegel left with Clawson informing him that Values are Vital was preparing to launch negative ad campaigns against Clawson and Benacquisto. “If you don’t already know, I just read or heard that the PAC people are going to spend so much negative on her and so much negative on you. It’s not something I wanted, and not something I can prevent. Anyway, that’s the way it is.” The Clawson campaign characterized the call as a “threat” and wondered how Kreegel came to know about the PAC’s plans. Kreegel says he found out by checking the FEC website, which contains information on the amount spent, the form of advertising and the target. Also last week, Clawson’s aides circulated a story from the Charlotte Sun newspaper, which covers an area outside the 19th Congressional District, about Kreegel’s departure from the medical practice he worked at until early this year. The story implied Kreegel left without telling his boss and without giving his patients a way to access their medical records. Kreegel says the doctor in charge of the practice, Dr. John Jancik, told him on Jan. 3 he could no longer work there while a candidate for Congress. Office manager Roxanna Ingle says she was in the office during the conversation between Kreegel and Janick and remembers Janick telling Kreegel he’d have to leave the practice. Once he was booted from the practice, he had no access to his patients’ contact information or to their medical files, which were the property of the physicians’ group. Kreegel called the March 19 story a “hatchet job” and questioned why a doctor leaving a medical practice would constitute front-page news, especially nearly three months after it happened. Clawson’s aides also responded to a Liberty and Leadership ad recounting a 2003 worker death that occurred while he was the CEO of Hayes Lemmerz an auto rim manufacturing firm. “How low must Benacquisto go?” asked David James, spokesman for the Clawson campaign. The answer, it appears, is pretty low and it applies not just to Benacquisto, but to all three candidates and their allies. None of the attack ads have made a compelling case that the target is guilty of something that would disqualify him or her from office. All of them represent money spent that could otherwise be used communicating coherent solutions and building trust. Michael Dreikorn, the fourth Republican candidate in the special primary election, hasn’t the money, or one would hope, the will to enter the negative ad fray. As for the others, well, perhaps it’s best just to say nothing. (Connect with Brent Batten at bebatten@naplesnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>