<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-0RJ1-DY2T-21BM"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Solar firm closes as customers wait; Dozens out of pocket more than $2M as cops investigate</title><source>Windsor Star (Ontario)</source><author>Dave Battagello, The Windsor Star</author><text><![CDATA[The owners of a Windsor solar power company have shut down their headquarters and stopped taking on new customers, leaving dozens of people out-of-pocket more than $2 million, according to the Better Business Bureau of Western Ontario.
Certified Solar Inc. remains under investigation by the Windsor Police Services and Ontario Provincial Police. The Better Business Bureau revoked its accreditation last year after receiving over four dozen customer complaints about the company.
The solar firm continues to exist, despite recently closing down its headquarters in the 2700 block of Deziel Drive near E.C. Row Expressway, vicepresident Gord Simmons said
Monday.
"We had a two-year lease and sublet the building. The lease expired and the rent went up.
"We don't have space anywhere, but we are still taking calls.
"We have stopped taking new customers. We are focusing our attention on satisfying and installing what we promised to our existing customers. We are going through that process and all projects should be cleaned up by the end of 2014."
The company installs solar panel systems at a cost of between $40,000 and $100,000. Homeowners are then supposed to be connected to Ontario's hydro grid and eligible to receive a monthly cheque of about $500 for supplying solar power.
Several customers told The Star they gave Certified Solar cheques for up to $50,000 for the installation of solar panels.
They were among dozens who did not receive panels or were not hooked up to the power grid. Repeated calls to the company are being ignored, they say.
Simmons said there are "between 50 to 100 customers" with issues that need to be resolved.
Simmons said there are "between 50 to 100 customers" with issues that need to be resolved.
Sgt. Matt D'Asti of Windsor police said the company is under investigation. The financial fraud department is trying to determine whether the company's conduct is a civil or criminal matter.
"The complication is they have their business in Windsor, but we are hearing from (alleged) victims in other jurisdictions," D'Asti said. "We are encouraging these people to contact their local law authority to file their complaints. It's something ongoing for us, but we haven't received complaints from any victims in Windsor who have come forward."
Const. Stephanie Moniz, of Essex OPP, said the detachment in Aurora will lead the investigation for the provincial police.
Certified Solar's phone is answered by a recording telling customers to hold for assistance. Messages can be left.
There have been a dozen new complaints against Certified Solar over the last two months, said Deborah Brady, president of the Better Business Bureau of Western Ontario. That's on top of over four dozen it had on file as of the end of last year.
"I urge consumers to do research, talk to the Better Business Bureau and make sure they are dealing with a trustworthy business," she said. "They need to read their contracts and make sure the business has a commitment date on what they will do and when. Most of all, be careful putting any money up front."
Brady said she is concerned Certified Solar executives are attempting to do more business through a company named Citi Solar.
Several sales job postings for Citi Solar in locations across Ontario - including Mississauga, Oakville, Barrie, Midland and Orillia - were posted on Kijiji in recent weeks.
The listings give a mailing address in a Mississauga business park.
Simmons said the only connection he and his partner Craig O'Brien have to Citi Solar is they provided it with software.
"We are not shareholders," he said.
He and O'Brien are involved in Windsor-based Pure Data Flow, which Simmons said provides software to many businesses across Ontario, primarily in the solar industry.
The Better Business Bureau was contacted by a former Certified Solar employee, Brady said. The Star spoke with the employee, who asked not to be named and provided records of his job as a salesman at the solar company.
He joined the company last summer, believing there was a solid business model. Then he started hearing from his angry customers.
"Emotionally and financially I was seeing what a burden it was to (customers)," he said. "I grew frustrated with the company and gave them my resignation (late last year).
"I still have people calling my cellphone on a daily basis asking me why they are not connected to the grid or being rescued. Unfortunately, I don't have answers for them."
Marco Belperio of Schomberg - about 25 kilometres west of Newmarket - said he is out a $30,000 deposit he gave to Certified Solar in August 2012 for a system costing $86,000. He can't get a refund despite repeated attempts.
"They said they needed the money up front for the equipment to get the job going," said Belperio, a single father who operates a small indoor pool business. "I was too trusting. But who takes $30,000 and doesn't do the job? I'm at the point now where I'm at the brink of losing my home because of what they did.
"I've written all kinds of letters, gone to the Ontario Ombudsman, Ontario Power Authority, talked to police, but nothing positive has happened. I've never worked so hard for $30,000 in my life, but how can you just walk away from that much money. I would never be happy about that again."
Another unhappy customer is Brian McAuley of Courtice, just outside Oshawa.
He handed over a $23,000 deposit for a $36,000 solar panel system in October 2012 and has not seen any equipment from Certified Solar or been able to get his money refunded. He did hear back from a company rep a few weeks ago after repeated calls.
"I told them 'I don't have any trust left in you,'" said McAuley, who works in technology sales. "I just want this resolved amicably and move on. I understand how business works and people can get in over their heads.
"It seems like a business that oversold and can't deliver. I don't understand what the issue is in refunding my deposit ... I'm disappointed they have not kept their commitments. It's been excuse after excuse, so I just feel exasperation."
Simmons said provincial hydro regulations keep changing and have hindered the ability to fulfil contracts with customers.
He said there used to be 1,000 solar panel applications in Ontario hooked to the grid bi-weekly, but that's down to "only 85 in the last two weeks."
dbattagello@windsorstar.com
]]></text></news-item>