<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTS-HRN1-DYJJ-P0GD"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Duke: No plan for SC coal ash ponds</title><source>The Greenville News (South Carolina)</source><author>By, Tim Smith</author><text><![CDATA[If Duke filled a dump truck every three minutes with ash and ran the trucks 12 hours a day, it would still only remove 750,000 tons in one year.
Duke Energy coal ash ponds in Anderson and Darlington counties are being studied closely by the utility in the wake of a giant spill last month at a North Carolina plant that dumped millions of gallons of coal ash water into the Dan River, Duke officials are telling utility regulators.
But they are offering no detailed plan of how or whether they will remove the toxic ash, saying they are waiting for expected federal environmental rules to be issued later this year before acting.
A Greenville lawyer for an environmental group told members of the South Carolina Public Service Commission on Monday that Duke remains the only utility in the state that hasn't committed to emptying its ash ponds and moving the contents to safe, dry storage away from waterways.
"What we see here is a tremendous risk to the public and the ratepayers," Frank Holleman, a senior attorney for the Southern Environmental Law Center, told members of the Public Service Commission.
The law center last week released details of a report that found elevated levels of arsenic and chromium in the ground at the site of Duke's W.S. Lee coal plant near Williamston in Anderson County, which is located near the Saluda River.
Duke officials told the PSC on Monday that they were aware of elevated levels of iron and manganese at the site but not of any other contaminants.
Duke briefed the PSC on Monday on the North Carolina spill and what actions it is taking to prevent problems at its other facilities. Officials say Duke has 33 coal ash ponds in North Carolina and three in South Carolina.
"We have a lot of political and media attention focused on us right now to make sure we move quickly," George Everett, director of environmental and legislative affairs for Duke, told the PSC.
Holleman said his briefing was designed to fill in pieces of the story that Duke omitted.
But the PSC heard the briefings only as information. Neither Holleman nor Duke have any request concerning the coal ash issue before the commission.
In North Carolina, the Dan River spill has spawned the convening of a federal grand jury and state officials have accused the utility of violating state environmental laws, Holleman said.
The issue of coal ash ponds have caused such controversy in North Carolina that Duke took out full-page newspaper ads Sunday to reassure the public.
Coal ash is a byproduct of coal-fired power plants. For decades, utilities have moved the waste to retention ponds. But many of those ponds are located near waterways and environmentalists worry about some of the elements in the ash, such as mercury, selenium, arsenic, chromium, iron and manganese, leaking from the ponds and contaminating ground water or nearby waterways.
Everett said a collapsed 48-inch metal storm sewer pipe running just underneath a pond at Duke's plant near Eden, N.C., was responsible for sending tons of coal ash and millions of gallons of water from the pond into the Dan River nearby in early February.
He said no other coal ash pond at a Duke facility in either state has storm water pipes underneath, though all have discharge pipes at the base of the dikes that are being inspected.
Asked by PSC's chairman if the coal ash spill poses any hazardous risk, Everett replied he doesn't think it does.
"The water quality in the river has only been minimally impacted, initially after the spill, that's my assessment," he said. "We don't expect to see long-term, water-quality or fish-tissue issues. But I reserve judgment just like everybody else will."
Duke officials say the utility has formed a special team to look at each of its sites and ponds throughout its system to see which ponds can be closed and how, giving priority to ponds at closed plants. While most of Duke's plants are in the Carolinas, some are in other states.
"We will have to look at a number of factors at each site," Everett said. "How close are we to a river or lake, what's the status of groundwater at the site, what other disposal options do we have?"
Everett said the utility has accumulated 100 million tons of wet ash and 50 million tons of dry ash at its coal-fired sites, 14 of which are in North Carolina. If Duke filled a dump truck every three minutes with ash and ran the trucks 12 hours a day, it would still only remove 750,000 tons in one year, he said.
At the utility's largest site, it could take 30 years, Everett said.
"It is a lot of material," he said. "It is a task that is going to take a lot of time."
Mike Ruhe, who directs environmental affairs for Duke, told the PSC that elevated levels of iron and manganese have been detected at the Anderson County plant site, but he said both elements are "indicative of Piedmont soils" and the state's environmental and health agency hasn't been alarmed at the findings or ordered any action.
He said two of the coal-fired units at the site are scheduled to be retired next year, while the third unit is supposed to be converted to gas later this year. The units were built in the 1950s.
A 55-acre pond developed for a now-closed coal-fired unit near Hartsville and Lake Robinson is mostly dry, he said. Duke is scheduled to provide a plan to close the pond to state officials in the next three years, he said.
Holleman said he doesn't think it will take 30 years to remove the ash, especially in Duke's South Carolina sites.
He described Duke's ponds as "primitive" because they are unlined and the earthen dikes that surround them are aging and in some cases "seeping."
The coal ash ponds over 64 acres at Lee are held back by dams that the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency said pose a "significant safety hazard" and have showed signs of seepage over the past several years.
Duke maintains that the dams are safe. An official said Monday that Duke engineers are studying the seepage.
If South Carolina's two other major utilities are willing to remove the ash in their ponds to dry, safe storage, why can't Duke, Holleman asked the PSC.
"If you set up a system where you are storing coal ash in unlined pits next to rivers in antiquated, dug-out facilities that have been there, in some instances 80 years, you are setting up a situation where any minor human error can result in a catastrophe," he said.
Holleman said maps show streams running through the Anderson County ponds and he said dikes around the Anderson County ponds have been leaking for many years. Seepage, he said, is being directed into a storm water system that eventually flows into the Saluda River.
"They've constructed a system to make this about as dangerous as you could," he said.
Holleman said waiting for the federal environmental rules is "another excuse." He said the state's other utilities haven't waited for any rules to begin emptying and moving their ponds.
If Duke filled a dump truck every three minutes with ash and ran the trucks 12 hours a day, it would still only remove 750,000 tons in one year.
]]></text></news-item>