<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-YVD1-F0J6-J00H"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>"Water contamination prompts demand for licence withdrawal Renewed call to ban fracking</title><source>Camden Advertiser</source><author>Anne Tarasov</author><text><![CDATA[REVELATIONS that coal seam gas operations in the Pilliga Forest contaminated an aquifer with uranium have led Macarthur's anti-CSG activists to renew their calls for the state government to revoke mining licences which cover residential suburbs in the area.
Stop CSG Ingleburn spokeswoman Marina Farid said the expansion of the AGL Camden Gas Project could include operations in Ingleburn, Varroville, Kearns and Denham Court.
The Environment Protection Authority fined energy company Satos $1500 after elevated levels of uranium, lead, aluminium, arsenic and other chemicals were found in an aquifer, 11 metres below the surface.
Ms Farid said the incident showed how dangerous CSG mining was to the environment.
"And here AGL want to mine very close to residential areas," Ms Farid said
"AGL has continually ignored community requests to cancel its application to drill for coal seam gas in Ingleburn and the Scenic Hills and the company's record of dealing with community concern over issues including contaminated waste water is abysmal.
"The NSW government announced that coal seam gas would not be allowed within two kilometres of residential areas but coal seam gas exploration licences remain over the Sydney metropolitan area including the south-west."
An AGL research paper released recently found NSW could experience up to 21 days of gas supply shortages from the 2016 winter.
AGL's head of economic policy and sustainability Tim Nelson said the finding reinforced the need to explore and produce gas in NSW, for NSW.
"NSW is the only state which is not self-sufficient in gas, with only five per cent of the state's needs currently being produced at AGL's Camden Gas Project," Mr Nelson said.
"We need to increase our local gas supplies to ensure security of gas supply for the state."
]]></text></news-item>