<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-9J51-JCXB-21DH"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>HSBC Holdings PLC Annual Financial Report - 38 of 60</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[RNS Number : 1618D HSBC Holdings PLC 25 March 2014 Corporate Governance
Corporate Governance Report The statement of corporate governance practices set out on pages 329 to 415 and information incorporated by reference constitutes the Corporate Governance Report of HSBC Holdings. The reports of Board Committees are contained within the Corporate Governance Report. Letter from the Group Chairman Dear Shareholder During 2013, your Board has taken positive steps to enhance the Group's corporate governance framework globally, in part to reflect the heightened expectations of all of our stakeholders. We believe that a robust and transparent corporate governance framework is vital to the sustainable success of HSBC. The Board has a critical role in overseeing the transformation agenda which is underway to simplify the way we run the Group, making it easier to manage and control. Management's focus on the transformation agenda reflects HSBC's three strategic priorities: to implement Global Standards, grow the business and to simplify and streamline processes. At each of its meetings and through its Committees, the Board reviews progress made on implementation of this agenda and challenges management over the speed of delivery and options considered. Strengthening our corporate governance framework to support the successful implementation of our Global Standards programme, which includes enhancement of compliance-related controls and standards relating to financial crime risk, is a continuing priority focus within the Board's agenda. As an early indication of the Board's commitment to support the transformation agenda, at the start of 2013 we established the Financial System Vulnerabilities Committee ('FSVC') chaired by Rona Fairhead. Throughout the year this committee has overseen our progress in achieving enhanced standards and has provided valuable input in connection with the controls and procedures adopted to underpin them. It has also, with the support of its advisers, worked to identify emerging risks, such as cyber security, and challenged management on its plans to address such risks. A key element of its work in 2013 has been on bolstering 'Know Your Customer' and 'Enhanced Due Diligence' procedures, recommending to the Board revisions and enhancements to existing practices. In January 2014, the Board approved and adopted revised Global Sanctions and Global Anti-Money Laundering Programme Policies, to facilitate implementation and assurance of globally consistent practices. Adherence to these enhanced standards is vital to ensure we adopt globally the high behavioural and compliance standards consistent with our brand and which meet all of our commitments under the deferred prosecution agreement entered into with the US Department of Justice in December 2012 as well as associated legal and regulatory undertakings. The emphasis we place on adhering to high behavioural standards and 'doing the right thing' has led us to establish a further new Board Committee, the Conduct & Values Committee ('CVC'), which will be chaired by Rachel Lomax. The CVC, which incorporates much of what was previously done in the Corporate Sustainability Committee, will, with a much expanded role, oversee the design and application of our policies, procedures and standards to ensure that we conduct business responsibly and consistently adheres to HSBC Values. The CVC will focus on the key themes that underpin our commitment to meeting societal expectations of the banking sector; treating customers fairly and openly, doing business with the right clients, doing business the right way, being a responsible employer, acting responsibly towards the communities in which HSBC operates and treating all stakeholders fairly. We recognise, and are preparing for, the specific challenges resulting from continuing regulatory and legislative changes, such as the corporate governance aspects of the EU's Capital Requirements Directive IV, proposals for a senior persons regime now contained in the 2014 Banking Reform Act and support for the establishment of a professional standards body for banking in the UK. Ensuring we have a diverse balance of skills, knowledge and experience on the Board is a fundamental aspect of successful corporate governance. In my statement to shareholders on pages 3 to 5, I welcomed Kathleen Casey, who will join the Board on 1 March 2014, bringing extensive experience of financial services regulation. Sir Jonathan Evans, who joined the Board on 6 August 2013, has added considerable insight on emerging risks and threats and will take over the chairmanship of the FSVC during the second quarter of this year. The Board has also been strengthened by the appointment of Marc Moses, Group Chief Risk Officer, as an executive Director with effect from 1 January 2014. This reflects the criticality of the Risk function. On behalf of the Board and with the very capable leadership of its new and existing committees, I can assure you that your Directors remain committed to establishing and maintaining the highest standards of corporate governance wherever we operate. This is key to the Group's ability to capitalise on the opportunities arising from successful implementation of our strategic priorities. D J Flint, Group Chairman 24 February 2014 Directors Douglas Flint, CBE, 58 Group Chairman Skills and experience: Member of the Institute of Chartered Accountants of Scotland and the Association of Corporate Treasurers. Fellow of The Chartered Institute of Management Accountants. Extensive governance experience gained through membership of the Boards of HSBC and BP p.l.c.; considerable knowledge of finance and risk management in banking, multinational financial reporting, treasury and securities trading operations; honoured with a CBE in recognition of his services to the finance industry. Joined HSBC in 1995 as Group Finance Director. Appointed Group Chairman: 2010 Appointed to the Board: 1995 Current appointments include: A director of The Hong Kong Association and Chairman of the Institute of International Finance. A member of the Mayor of Beijing's International Business Leaders' Advisory Council as well as the Mayor of Shanghai's International Business Leaders' Advisory Council; a member of the International Advisory Board of the China Europe International Business School, Shanghai; an independent external member of the UK Government's Financial Services Trade and Investment Board since 20 September 2013, and by invitation from the Prime Minister a British Business Ambassador from January 2014.
]]></text></news-item>