<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-G5D1-JC86-10SF"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Madoff aides convicted in securities fraud trial</title><source>The Virginian-Pilot(Norfolk, VA.)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[By
Erik Larson, Patricia Hurtado and Bob Van Voris
Bloomberg News
Five former aides to Bernie Madoff, who spent decades working for his firm, were found guilty of helping run the biggest Ponzi scheme in U.S. history, a $17.5 billion fraud exposed by the 2008 financial crisis.
The three men and two women, hired by Madoff with little financial experience, were convicted on all 31 counts. The defendants failed to convince a federal jury in Manhattan that they were ignorant of the fraud despite being part of the inner circle at Madoff's New York-based firm.
Sentencings are set for July.
Monday's verdict, after five months of testimony and four days of deliberations, is a major victory for the U.S. government, coming in the only criminal trial brought in the five years since the scam was revealed. Madoff refused to cooperate with prosecutors.
Some clients learned they lost their life savings after Madoff's confession and arrest on Dec. 11, 2008, leading to criticism of regulators who repeatedly overlooked the scam. Madoff, 75, pleaded guilty the next year and is serving 150 years in a North Carolina prison.
Prosecutors began probing Madoff's highest-ranking employees soon after his arrest.
The defendants are Annette Bongiorno, who ran the investment advisory unit at the center of the fraud; Joann Crupi, who managed large accounts; Daniel Bonventre, the ex-operations chief of Madoff's broker-dealer; and computer programmers George Perez and Jerome O'Hara, accused of automating the scam as it grew rapidly in the 1990s.
The convictions "demonstrate what we have believed from the earliest stages of the investigation: This largest-ever Ponzi scheme could not have been the work of one person," Manhattan U.S. Attorney Preet Bharara said in a statement. "The trial established that the Madoff fraud began at least as far back as the early 1970s, decades before it came to light."
The defendants were accused in the indictment of conspiring to use millions of fake account statements and false trade confirmations to trick customers into believing they owned shares in the world's biggest companies. Instead, prosecutors said, the victims' money was used to enrich the firm's wealthiest clients, give conspirators exorbitant pay and bonuses and keep the Ponzi scheme afloat.
the trial
Five former aides to Bernie Madoff failed to convince a jury that they were ignorant of a $17.5 billion fraud exposed by the 2008 financial crisis. The defendants were convicted on all 31 counts.
]]></text></news-item>