<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-5JB1-JB5P-J17N"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Former Executive of Miami-Based Ocean Bank Sentenced to Serve 37 Months in Prison for Participating in Bribery Scheme and Filing False Tax Returns</title><source>Thai News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Wednesday, April 4, 2012
WASHINGTON - A former executive of Ocean Bank, a financial institution headquartered in Miami, was sentenced today for participating in a scheme to accept bribes and for failing to report income on federal income tax returns, the Department of Justice announced.
Danilo P. Perez, a former vice president of Ocean Bank, was sentenced today in the U.S. District Court in Miami by District Judge Donald L. Graham to serve 37 months in prison followed by one year of supervised release.
On Jan. 25, 2012, Perez pleaded guilty to one count of conspiracy to solicit or demand money and other things of value to influence an employee of a financial institution and three counts of tax offenses. The charges against Perez stemmed from his accepting nearly $500,000 in cash and other items from co-conspirators in connection with his supervision of certain customer business with the bank. As vice president, Perez generally oversaw Ocean Bank's lending relationships with corporate customers of the bank.
Perez admitted to accepting bribes, including payments for expensive watches, Super Bowl tickets and other items for his personal use, as well as substantial amounts of cash. Perez accepted the payments intending to be rewarded and influenced in connection with his role in approving Ocean Bank's issuance of letters of credit, loans and overdraft privileges to his co-conspirators. Perez also admitted that he failed to report income from those bribes for tax years 2005, 2006 and 2007, resulting in lost tax revenue of approximately $91,000 to the federal government.
The investigation was conducted by the Antitrust Division's Atlanta Field Office and Internal Revenue Service-Criminal Investigation in Atlanta and Miami, with assistance from the U.S. Attorney's Office for the Southern District of Florida. Anyone with information concerning anticompetitive conduct in the banking industry is urged to call the Antitrust Division's Atlanta Field Office at 404-331-7100 or visit www.justice.gov/atr/contact/newcase.htm.
Source: U.S. Department of Justice
]]></text></news-item>