<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-66V1-DXHF-W010"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Tourist dies in 8th PSJ shark attack</title><source>Daily Dispatch (South Africa)</source><author>Sikho Ntshobane; Vuvu Vena</author><text><![CDATA[Port St John's beach now world's most dangerous Suddenly people started screaming and rushing towards the shore. The next thing there was blood in the water By A 72-year-old Austrian tourist this weekend became the eighth shark attack victim in just five years, fast making Second Beach in Port St Johns among the deadliest in the world.
Eastern Cape Parks and Tourism (ECPT) CEO, Luxolo Rubushe, confirmed that Port St Johns was becoming the beach with the highest number of shark attack-related deaths in the world. The latest victim was among many people swimming in fairly shallow water just metres from the crowded beach. Beachgoers watched helplessly and in horror as the man, the member of a tour group with his wife, was attacked in front of his companions. Siphesihle Mangcotywa said the tourist had been swimming with three other people at the time of the incident. "Suddenly people started screaming and rushing towards the shore and the next thing, there was blood in the water next to the man," said Mangcotywa. "He did not even scream but tried to swim towards the shore. His three companions were about a metre away and watched helplessly. But then they also ran to the shore." The water had been dirty and rough, but people had gone in to swim anyway to cool off from scorching temperature. The man's body is believed to have been carried out to sea by the strong currents, but was found washed up onto nearby rocks about an hour and half after the attack. National Sea Rescue Institute (NSRI) spokesman Craig Lambinon confirmed that the NSRI's Port St Johns volunteer sea rescue duty crew had been called out at around 3pm on Saturday. "On arrival at the scene they found the body of the man who had been fatally wounded by a shark," Lambinon said. He said the species of the shark could not be confirmed, but it is speculated that it was a Zambezi shark. These occur in their numbers in the area and have been responsible for attacks in the past. Port St Johns police spokesman Captain Mduduzi Godlwana declined to name the victim until his family had been notified, but said an inquest had been opened. Despite its dangerous history, Second Beach remains a popular destination for both locals and tourists. Signs warning beachgoers about shark attack dangers have done little to deter bathers. Port St Johns resident John Costello, who was part of the volunteer crew said surprisingly other beachgoers went back into the water just 30 minutes after the man's body had been retrieved. "The problem is the attitude of people. People are not disciplined and many do not understand the dangers of the sea," he said. The beach reportedly has no lifeguards currently as the Port St Johns municipality failed to renew their contracts. Costello said a critical study and analysis of the beach needed to be done urgently to establish why so many people had been attacked by sharks in the last few years. Rubushe said a study was under way. He said the ECPT had partnered with the municipality and community in the area, as well as commissioning the Natal Sharks Board to conduct research into the reasons for so many attacks happening on that beach. One assumption was that traditional healers who conducted traditional ceremonies at the seaside and slaughtered animals there were attracting the sharks. "Because sharks can smell blood from kilometres away, they swim closer to the shore to feed off the slaughtered animals," he said. The second assumption was that the species of shark found on the Wild Coast area were not confined to the sea alone but could breed up river in the Mzimvubu River. A team of experts from the KwaZulu Natal Shark Board was expected to arrive in Port St Johns today to establish what kind of a shark had attacked the man. Municipal authorities in Port St Johns could not be reached for comment before going to print yesterday. - sikhon@dispatch.co.za / vuyiswav@dispatch.co.za
]]></text></news-item>