<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-9J51-JCXB-21FK"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>HSBC Holdings PLC Annual Financial Report - 43 of -2-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Directors, through the GRC and the GAC, have conducted an annual review of the effectiveness of our system of risk management and internal control covering all material controls, including financial, operational and compliance controls, risk management systems, the adequacy of resources, qualifications and experience of staff of the accounting and financial reporting function and the risk function, and their training programmes and budget. The review does not extend to joint ventures or associates.
The GRC and the GAC have received confirmation that executive management has taken or is taking the necessary actions to remedy any failings or weaknesses identified through the operation of our framework of controls. Statement on going concern The financial statements are prepared on a going concern basis, as the Directors are satisfied that the Group and parent company have the resources to continue in business for the foreseeable future. In making this assessment, the Directors have considered a wide range of information relating to present and future conditions, including future projections of profitability, cash flows and capital resources. HSBC's principal activities, business and operating models, strategic direction and top and emerging risks are described in the 'Strategic Report'; a financial summary, including a review of the consolidated income statement and consolidated balance sheet, is provided in the 'Financial Review' section; HSBC's objectives, policies and processes for managing credit, liquidity and market risk are described in the 'Risk' section; and HSBC's approach to capital management and allocation is described in the 'Capital' section. Employees At 31 December 2013 we had a total workforce of 263,000 full-time and part-time employees compared with 270,000 at the end of 2012 and 298,000 at the end of 2011. Our main centres of employment are the UK with approximately 46,000 employees, India 31,000, Hong Kong 29,000, Brazil 22,000, mainland China 19,000, Mexico 18,000, the US 16,000 and France 9,000. In the context of the current global financial services operating environment, a high performance and values-led work force is critical. We encourage open and honest communication in decision making. Employment issues and financial, economic, regulatory and competitive factors affecting HSBC's performance are regularly shared with our employees. Reward Our approach to reward is meritocratic and market competitive, underpinned by an ethical and values based performance culture which aligns the interests of our employees, shareholders, regulators and customers. Employee relations We negotiate and consult with recognised unions as appropriate. The five highest concentrations of union membership are in Argentina, Brazil, mainland China, Malta and Mexico. It is our policy to maintain well-developed communications and consultation programmes with all employee representative bodies and there have been no material disruptions to our operations from labour disputes during the past five years. Diversity and inclusion HSBC is committed to building a values-driven high performance culture where all employees are valued, respected and where their opinions count. We remain committed to meritocracy, which requires a diverse and inclusive culture where employees believe that their views are heard, their concerns are attended to and they work in an environment where bias, discrimination and harassment on any matter, including gender, age, ethnicity, religion, sexuality and disability are not tolerated and where advancement is based on objective criteria. Our inclusive culture helps us respond to our diverse customer base, while developing and retaining a secure supply of skilled, committed employees. Our culture will be strengthened by employing the best
]]></text></news-item>