<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-7V71-DY2D-J044"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>'Bernie was the mastermind - they were loyal &amp; he rewarded them nicely'</title><source>Daily News (New York)</source><author>BY DANIEL BEEKMAN, BARBARA ROSS and DAREH GREGORIAN NEW YORK DAILY NEWS</author><text><![CDATA[BERNARD MADOFF is getting some company in the big house.
Jurors found five former employees guilty Monday of acting as the soldiers used to carry out his massive $65 billion scam.
The flimflam five - Daniel Bonventre, 67; Annette Bongiorno, 65; Joann Crupi, 52; Jerome O'Hara, 51, and George Perez, 48 - knew exactly what they were doing as they assisted Madoff with the biggest scam in U.S. history, jurors said after convicting the quintet on all 31 counts.
"He was the mastermind. They were his soldiers. They were loyal and he rewarded them nicely," juror Sheila Amato told reporters.
"They hurt a lot of lives," the art teacher said.
The defendants showed little emotion as the eight-man, three-woman jury returned the verdict that could put them behind bars for the rest of their lives.
Bongiorno calmly tallied the guilty counts with a pen while nodding her head ever so slightly. Crupi clasped her hands in front of her mouth and stared straight ahead blankly. The three male defendants appeared grim.
Afterward, the disgraced former employees - who were allowed to remain free on bail pending their sentencing - hugged friends and family. Bundled up against the cold, they hurried out of court and declined to answers questions shouted by reporters.
They face a maximum of 78 to 220 years in prison, but are unlikely to receive such lengthy sentences, experts said.
Bonventre, Bongiorno and Crupi were charged with tax evasion in addition to the fraud counts they all faced.
"We're disappointed," said Bonventre's lawyer Andrew Frisch. "The list of Bernie Madoff's victims now includes these five former employees."
Bongiorno's lawyer, Roland Riopelle, said he planned to appeal the verdict.
"I'm certain that Bernard Madoff being the de facto lead defendant was not helpful for the other defendants," he said.
Madoff, now 75, was sentenced in 2009 to 150 years in prison for running a multibillion-dollar scam a judge called "extraordinarily evil."
Prosecutors said the crooked quintet cooked the books at Madoff's firm, making up phony securities trades and lying to help trick auditors.
"For nearly 40 years, (Madoff) ran one of the largest frauds in history . . . and each of these defendants played a crucial role," Assistant U.S. Attorney John Zach said in Manhattan Federal Court during his closing arguments.
"These defendants told an avalanche of lies."
The employees claimed they were clueless to what was going on during their lengthy tenures with Madoff, as their bank accounts got fatter and fatter.
Bongiorno, a Howard Beach, Queens, native hired straight out of high school as a firm secretary, wound up becoming a manager in the investment advisory unit with an $80 million Madoff investment account.
For decades, she built bogus investor accounts records via "cut and paste," an underling testified.
Bongiorno testified that she didn't know she was doing anything wrong because she trusted Madoff completely.
She said she kept a picture of Madoff on her desk with the words "my hero" on it.
"I believed what he told me. I never even thought of the word 'illegal,' " she testified.
She also told jurors she saw nothing strange about the $80 million in her own Madoff investment account because she rarely withdrew cash to pamper herself.
Bongiorno and Bonventre both took the stand in their own defense, a tactic jurors said backfired.
"I don't think it was a good move on their part. It was very scripted when their lawyers were asking them questions, and then (they were) hesitant when the prosecutors were asking questions. It made them look like they were hiding something," Amato said.
Juror Nancy Goldberg said she couldn't buy the defense assertion that the five were the master manipulator's unwitting dupes.
"I think they were having a good time" and didn't care about the people they were hurting, she said.
"There were a lot of charities and good people, trusting people, who were swindled, bamboozled and taken advantage of," Goldberg said.
Manhattan U.S. Attorney Preet Bharara said the convictions show "what we have believed from the earliest stages of the investigation: this largest-ever Ponzi scheme could not have been the work of one person."
Each of the five "played an important role in carrying out the charade, propping it up, and concealing it from regulators, auditors, taxing authorities, lenders and investors" over a period of decades, Bharara said.
The jurors deliberated for just over 20 hours after sitting through a five-month trial that had testimony from more than 40 witnesses. A 12th juror was excused during deliberations because of illness.
Norma Hill, 73, who lost $2 million to Madoff, appreciated the jurors' hard work.
"I feel grateful to the jury," she said.
"I'm not a vengeful person, but when I heard the verdict, I was happy to know that after years of living in the lap of luxury, these people will now be punished for the crimes they committed.
"To go to work every day and draw these monumental salaries and then claim they didn't know what they were doing, that's pathetic. They must have considered the rest of the world pretty stupid if they thought the jury was going to believe that."
Abby Frucht, 56, whose mother and father were ruined in 2008 when Madoff's house of cards collapsed, said, "I hope (the five) get a long time in jail to think about it."
Goldberg said she was confident her verdict was just, but it still made her feel "sad."
"It was the right decision, but it still makes me sad. Their lives are over," she said.
The jury foreman, who asked not to be identified, said he's ready to move on.
"It was a long trial. I'm just glad it's over and we can get on with our lives," he said.
The five are expected to be sentenced in late July.
In addition to the five flunkies convicted Monday, nine defendants charged in connection with the Ponzi scheme have pleaded guilty and one more, accountant Paul Konigsberg - who worked with but not for Madoff - is awaiting trial..
220 YEARS*
Daniel Bonventre, 67
Title: Operations manager
Counts convicted of: 23
Bonventre worked for Madoff from 1968 until 2008. Responsible for back-office records.
Prosecutors said the unassuming number-cruncher secretly cooked the books to hide the fraud from regulators and obtained huge loans for Madoff using stolen investor bonds as collateral.
175 YEARS*
Joann Crupi, 52
Title: Investment manager
Counts convicted of: 13
Hired in 1983, Crupi managed hundreds of millions of dollars in bogus investment accounts.
The mild-mannered desk worker said she was snookered by Madoff and his right-hand man, Frank DiPascali. But records showed she oversaw the daily activity of the slush fund bank account where Madoff stashed billions of dollars in Ponzi scheme funds. Crupi went wild outside the office, using her company-paid credit card on cruises, Las Vegas vacations and copious amounts of wine.
100 YEARS*
Jerome O'Hara, 51
Title: Computer programmer
Counts convicted of: 8
O'Hara, along with his programmer buddy George Perez, built and maintained the software programs and computer systems that kept the scheme going as it became more and more complicated over the years, prosecutors said.
His code helped Madoff crank out false records that looked real enough to fool regulators and investors. Hired in 1990, O'Hara said he and Perez confronted their boss in 2006 with concerns about their work. But prosecutors said the men wound up taking raises to keep quiet, even asking for the hush money in the form of diamonds
100 YEARS*
George Perez, 48
Title: Computer programmer
Counts convicted of: 8
Perez, hired in 1991, worked with O'Hara on complex computer programs that automated the scheme and its fake trades. The "computer guys," who regularly chowed down together at expensive restaurants after work, made it easier for Madoff and his minions to hoodwink the rest of the world, prosecutors said.
That meant the band of crooks had more time to spend partying or at the beach. They said they were no different than other computer workers at the firm - but their salaries were much higher.
78 YEARS*
Annette Bongiorno, 65
Title: Manager
Counts convicted of: 10
Madoff hired Bongiorno straight out of high school 1968. To hear the pint-size Howard Beach, Queens, native tell it, she learned nothing despite decades in the financial industry.
Bongiorno played dumb at trial, telling the jury she blindly did what Madoff told her to do because he was her hero. But prosecutors showed handwritten notes linking her to the scam, records showing how she backdated phony trades and a photo of the Bentley sedan she splurged on while making millions of dollars.
]]></text></news-item>