<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-K861-DYRV-3011"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Programme summary of Afghan Ariana TV news in Dari 1530 gmt 25 Mar 14</title><source>BBC Monitoring South Asia - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A. News headlines
B. Home news
1. 0030 A group of assailants attack an Independent Election Commission (IEC) office in Kabul, killing two employees, one provincial election candidate, two policemen and wounding two others. IEC employees say 40 employees trapped in a basement for hours until the Afghan forces rescued them. [Video shows IEC employees, interior ministry spokesman talking to camera, the incident site.] (Covered)
2. 0320 Suicide attack kills five people and wounds 20 others on buzkashi playing field in northern Konduz Province. Reportedly, the main target of the suicide attack was Mir Alam Khan, former jihadi commander who survived the attack. [Video shows map of the province.] (Covered)
3. 0405 Lower house of parliament approves Mohammad Yunos Qanuni as the first vice-president. President Karzai says the April election is crucial for Afghanistan. Qanuni says he will make every effort to ensure a transparent election and address security problems in the country. [Video shows Karzai saying Qanuni is capable of fulfilling government responsibilities, Qanuni speaking to journalists.]
4. 0800 National Directorate of Security blame Pakistani spy agency for masterminding the attack on Serena Hotel. NDS Spokesman Lotfollah Mashal says some employees of the hotel cooperated with the attackers. [Video shows archive CCTV footages, Lotfollah Mashal speaking to journalists.]
5. 1005 Defence Ministry Spokesman Gen Zahir Azimi says national army casualties increased in comparison to last year. He says the reason for the increase is because Afghan forces now leading almost all military operations across the country. [Video shows Gen Zahir Azimi and some other officials speaking.]
Adverts
6. 1640 Presidential candidate Zalmay Rasul promises residents of northern Konduz Province to seriously fight irresponsible armed men and corruption in this province. Rasul's first running mate calls on the people to vote in the April polls. [Video shows Rasul, an MP speaking at a gathering, correspondent reporting from the site.]
7. 1850 Hezb-e Wahdat Meli of Afghanistan voiced support for candidacy of the presidential hopeful Zalmay Rasul. [Video shows the leader of party, Mohammad Akbari people speaking in gathering.]
Adverts
8. 2240 Presidential candidate Abdorrab Rasul Sayyaf travels to Herat Province and says he will ensure shari'ah law implemented and Islamic and jihadi values are respected. Mohammad Esmail, Sayyaf's first running mate calls on the people to vote for them. [Video shows Sayyaf, Mohammad Esmael speaking at a huge gathering, supporters raising banners, flags.]
C. Economic news
9. 2830 Delays in signing the bilateral security between Kabul and Washington resulted in decrease in construction projects funded by the West. Owners of construction companies voice concern over the issue and urge the government to support them. The minister of economy, Abdol Hadi Arghandiwal, says government will channel construction projects through domestic companies. [Video shows minister and some officials speaking.] (See separate report)
Source: Ariana TV, Kabul, in Dari 1530 gmt 25 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>