<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-4S01-F05M-K05W"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Omnicare settles hazardous waste allegations</title><source>Cincinnati Business Courier (Ohio)</source><author>Barrett J. Brunsman</author><text><![CDATA[Cincinnati-based Omnicare Inc. has agreed to pay nearly $300,000 to settle a lawsuit filed by New Hampshire that alleged hazardous waste violations.
The state had alleged that Omnicare failed to identify hazardous waste shipped to facilities that weren't authorized to accept it. Most of the waste was in the form of pharmaceuticals disposed of through a product return program.
Omnicare (NYSE: OCR) provides pharmaceutical services to long-term care institutions such as nursing homes and assisted living centers as well as people with complex diseases such as multiple sclerosis or rheumatoid arthritis.
A subsidiary, Omnicare of New Hampshire, operates mail-order pharmacies that primarily service group living facilities, including jails.
"In order for waste pharmaceuticals to be properly managed as hazardous waste, they must be identified by the pharmacy at time they are discarded ... in order to prevent harm to human health or the environment," according to a statement released by New Hampshire's attorney general, Joseph Foster.
The alleged violations, as well as Omnicare's failure to follow certain hazardous waste management requirements, were discovered during an October 2011 inspection by the New Hampshire Department of Environmental Services, according to state officials.
"Omnicare quickly corrected the problems once identified by DES and was cooperative throughout the investigation," according to Foster.
The company agreed to pay $290,000 by this week to the state's Hazardous Waste Cleanup Fund, as well as $8,100 to the Northeast Environmental Enforcement Project.
"The company agreed to settle the matter in order to avoid continued litigation and to focus on its mission of helping to ensure the health of seniors and other patient populations in a cost-effective manner," an Omnicare spokesman said. "The settlement is not an admission of liability, and Omnicare continues to deny that there was any wrongdoing.
"Omnicare is committed to ensuring that it remains in strict compliance with all applicable laws, regulations and standards in each of the markets and jurisdictions in which it operates," the company spokesman said.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Cincinnati Business Courier for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>