<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-BP41-JCG2-C0M3"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Gleision trial 'could last four months'</title><source>Carmarthen Journal</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[POTENTIAL jurors have been told the trial of the manager and owners of a mine where four men died could last more than four months.
Mine manager Malcolm Fyfield, aged 58, from Caerhenllys, Cwmllynfell, is on trial alongside MNS Mining Limited, who ran the Gleision Colliery in the Swansea Valley, where the four miners died.
They have denied the charges against them and their trial started on Monday at Swansea Crown Court.
Philip Hill, aged 44, Charles Breslin, aged 62, David Powell, aged 50, and 39-year-old Garry Jenkins all died in the Swansea Valley Colliery in September 2011.
Fyfield denies four charges of manslaughter by gross negligence and the company denies four charges of corporate manslaughter.
The jury are yet to be sworn but 70 potential jurors were called into the court room and spoken to by the judge, Mr Justice Wyn Williams.
Each of the potential jurors were given a list of questionnaires detailing people involved in the case and the names of the witnesses expected to be called have also been read out to them.
More than 90 people, including some relatives of the dead men, are expected to give evidence.
The others include people who worked at the mine, police, a cave diver, staff from the Mines Rescue Service, machine operator and an underground mechanic.
The pool of jurors were then asked if they had any connection to the mine or the defendants and whether they or their families had any connection to groups including the police, Mines Rescue Service, Crown Prosecution Service, the Health and Safety Executive, the Coal Authority, MPs Peter Hain and Hywel Francis or Neath Port Talbot County Borough Council.
They were also asked if they lived in the Swansea Valley, Cilybebyll, Ystalyfera, Pontarddulais and Ystradgynlais. From the possible group, 16 people available to hear the case were asked to re-consider overnight and check their availability before they are formally sworn, which expected to be today.
The trial continues.
]]></text></news-item>