<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-5JB1-JB5P-J0VR"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Justice Department Resolves Allegations of Discrimination with Onward Healthcare in Connecticut</title><source>Thai News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Wednesday, March 28, 2012
WASHINGTON - The Justice Department reached a settlement agreement today with Onward Healthcare, a healthcare staffing company based in Wilton, Conn., resolving allegations that the company posted discriminatory job advertisements on its home page and third party websites that limited its jobs to U.S. citizens.
According to the department's investigation, over a one year period, thousands of Onward Healthcare's job postings impermissibly limited applications to U.S. citizens, even though work-authorized immigrants, such as lawful permanent residents, asylees and refugees, should have been allowed to apply as well. The Immigration and Nationality Act (INA) generally prohibits employers from discriminating on the basis of citizenship status unless required by law, regulation or government contract. The department determined that the company had no legal basis for its stated citizenship preference.
Federal law protects people who are authorized to work in the United States from facing discriminatory barriers when they are seeking employment, said Thomas E. Perez, Assistant Attorney General for the Civil Rights Division. Employers should ensure that their online job postings do not violate the anti-discrimination provision of Immigration and Nationality Act.
Under the terms of the settlement agreement, the company has agreed to pay $100,000 in civil penalties, to change its internal policies and manuals to reflect the INA's protections, and to be subject to reporting and compliance monitory requirements for a period of three years. This case was handled by Justice Department Attorney Liza Zamd.
The Office of Special Counsel for Immigration-Related Unfair Employment Practices (OSC) is responsible for enforcing the anti-discrimination provisions of the INA, which protect U.S. citizens and certain work-authorized individuals from citizenship status discrimination. The INA also protects work-authorized individuals from national origin discrimination, over-documentation in the employment eligibility verification process and retaliation.
For more information about protections against employment discrimination under the immigration laws, call 1-800-255-7688 (OSC's worker hotline) (1-800-237-2525, TDD for hearing impaired), 1-800-255-8155 (OSC's employer hotline) (1-800-362-2735, TDD for hearing impaired), sign up for a no-cost webinar at www.justice.gov/crt/about/osc/webinars.php, email osccrt@usdoj.gov or visit the website at www.justice.gov/crt/about/osc/.
Source: U.S. Department of Justice
]]></text></news-item>