<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-5JB1-JB5P-J1CP"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Barrio Azteca Gang Member Pleads Guilty in Texas to Racketeering Conspiracy</title><source>Thai News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Wednesday, January 18, 2012
WASHINGTON - A Barrio Azteca (BA) gang member pleaded guilty today for his participation in a racketeering conspiracy, announced Assistant Attorney General Lanny A. Breuer of the Justice Department's Criminal Division, U.S. Attorney Robert Pitman for the Western District of Texas, FBI Assistant Director of the Criminal Investigative Division Kevin Perkins and Administrator Michele M. Leonhart of the U.S. Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA).
Ricardo Gonzalez, 44, aka Cuate, of El Paso, Texas, pleaded guilty before U.S. District Magistrate Judge Norbert J. Garney in the Western District of Texas, El Paso Division, to racketeering conspiracy. A sentencing date has not yet been set by the court. At sentencing, Gonzalez faces a maximum penalty of life in prison.
According to court documents, the Barrio Azteca gang began in the late 1980s as a violent prison gang and has expanded into a transnational criminal organization. The BA is primarily based in West Texas; Juarez, Mexico; and throughout state and federal prisons in the United States and Mexico. The gang has a militaristic command structure and includes captains, lieutenants, sergeants, soldiers and associates - all with the purpose of maintaining power and enriching its members and associates through drug trafficking, money laundering, extortion, intimidation, violence, threats of violence and murder.
According to court documents, members and associates of the BA have engaged in a host of criminal activity committed since Jan. 1, 2003, including drug trafficking, extortion, money laundering, kidnapping and murder, including the March 13, 2010, murders in Juarez of U.S. consulate employee Leslie Ann Enriquez Catton, her husband Arthur Redelfs and Jorge Alberto Salcido Ceniceros, the husband of a U.S. consulate employee.
The BA profits by importing heroin, cocaine and marijuana into the United States from Mexico. Gang members and associates also allegedly charge a street tax or cuota on businesses and criminals operating in their turf. These profits are used to support gang members in prison by funneling money into prison commissary accounts of gang leaders and to pay for defense lawyers or fines. The cuota profits are also allegedly reinvested into the organization to purchase drugs, guns and ammunition.
According to information presented in court, Gonzalez was a BA member who distributed cocaine, marijuana and heroin on the west side of El Paso. Additionally, he collected extortion fees from drug dealers operating on BA turf and knew those fees were funnelled to jailed BA leaders.
Thirty-five members and associates of the BA gang, including Gonzalez and 16 others who have pleaded guilty, were charged in a third superseding indictment unsealed in March 2011 with various counts of racketeering, murder, drug offenses, money laundering and obstruction of justice. Trial is set to begin April 6, 2012.
The case is being prosecuted by Trial Attorney Joseph A. Cooley of the Criminal Division's Organized Crime and Gang Section, Trial Attorney Brian Skaret of the Criminal Division's Human Rights and Special Prosecutions Section and the U.S. Attorney's Office of the Western District of Texas - El Paso Division. The U.S. Attorney's Office for the District of New Mexico provided significant assistance in this case, including Assistant U.S. Attorney Sarah Davenport. Valuable assistance was provided by the Criminal Division's Offices of International Affairs and Enforcement Operations.
The case was investigated by the FBI's El Paso Field Office. Special assistance was provided by the DEA; the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives; Immigration and Customs Enforcement; the U.S. Marshals Service; U.S. Customs and Border Protection; Federal Bureau of Prisons; U.S. Diplomatic Security Service; the Texas Department of Public Safety; the Texas Department of Criminal Justice; El Paso Police Department; El Paso County Sheriff's Office; El Paso Independent School District Police Department; Texas Alcohol and Beverage Commission; New Mexico State Police; Dona Ana County, N.M., Sheriff's Office; Las Cruces, N.M., Police Department; Southern New Mexico Correctional Facility and Otero County Prison Facility New Mexico.
Source: U.S. Department of Justice
]]></text></news-item>