<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-HN11-F12F-F0TX"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Fresh ultimatum to ensure compensation for victims</title><source>The Financial Express (Bangladesh)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Bangladesh, March 25 -- The apparel leaders Monday gave fresh ultimatum to the government to ensure compensation for the Rana Plaza victims before the first anniversary of the world's worst industrial tragedy.
They made the announcement at a protest programme held in front of the debris site at Savar on the outskirts of the capital. Bangladesh Garments Sramik Sanghati (BGSS) Monday organised the demonstration to realise their demands.
The protestors also strongly demanded declaration of April 24 as the 'Labour Safety Day' making it general holiday for the apparel makers. Among others, BGSS convener Taslima Akhtar, labour leader Firuz Ahmed and Dipok Roy addressed the rally.
BGSS convener Taslima Akhtar said that the survivors of the tragedy and the deceased's families are yet to get the promised compensations except some emergency financial grants for medical treatment.
Ms Akhtar urged the government to announce the missing apparel workers as 'dead' and give compensation to the victims' family members, so that they could at least survive.
Criticising the bail of the Rana Plaza owner Sohel Rana in a case lodged for flouting the building construction law, the labour leaders reiterated their demand for exemplary punishment to the owner who is responsible for the biggest industrial tragedy.
"A number of accused including Mr Rana, who is responsible for the world's worst heartbreaking industrial disaster, unfortunately got bail," the speakers said.
They also expressed grave concern over the existing working safety arrangements for the readymade garment (RMG) workers who contribute significantly to the national economy.
The eight-storey Rana Plaza, which housed five apparel factories and a market, collapsed on April 24, 2013, leaving more than 1100 people, mostly female apparel workers killed and over 2500 injured.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from The Financial Express. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>