<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-BP41-JCG2-C042"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Politicians to air fears with new energy firm</title><source>Carmarthen Journal</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[POLITICIANS are set to meet with the company that is hoping to bring an "incinerator" to the Gwendraeth Valley.
Local MP Jonathan Edwards and AM Rhodri Glyn Thomas are to meet with Clean Energy on Friday, March 28.
Clean Energy is the company which has applied for planning to Carmarthenshire Council to bring a photovoltaic solar array and energy recovery centre, which will be made up of a pyrolysis plant and an anaerobic digestion facility, at New Lodge Farm on Pontarddulais Road, Cwmgwili.
Since plans were made public residents have raised concerns about the application and fears that the "incinerator" would create pollution and add a further 120 lorries on Carmarthenshire roads.
Meeting
Earlier this month, more than 100 people attended a meeting to discuss the plans.
Mr Edwards MP said: "Rhodri Glyn Thomas AM and I will be meeting with representatives of Clean Energy on Friday when we will put directly to them the concerns of our constituents.
"We've been out speaking with residents of Cwmgwili and we have collected a catalogue of questions which have to date been unanswered.
"It's only right and proper that my constituents are given all of the information they require before any decision is made on the application."
Cwmgwili resident Stephen Jeacock said he hoped everyone could work together for the people of the county.
He said: "As a member of the local Labour Party and a resident of Cwmgwili, it was nice to see Jonathan Edwards and Plaid Cymru join the Labour Party in supporting local residents in their opposition to the proposed building of an incinerator off the A48 in a recent edition of the Carmarthen Journal.
"The public meeting that Jonathan attended had actually been called by Labour MP, Nia Griffith. She had been present at the original consultation meeting last year.
"Also present, was Labour's Parliamentary candidate, Calum Higgins.
"It was my wife Sheryl who first brought this matter to the public's attention and from day one I have supported her and the action group both as a husband and as a member of the Labour Party.
"I have provided advice throughout and was instrumental in communications which resulted in an extension of the date to lodge objections.
"Clean Power's proposal to build this site at New Lodge is something that we should all be opposing.
"The company itself have admitted that the toxins that will be produced are very dangerous to both animals and humans.
"What they are asking of us, is that we trust them when they say that they will deal with these toxins in a safe and controlled manner.
"Unfortunately, the fact that from the very start they have tried to pass this development off as a solar park rather than an incinerator severely undermines that trust.
"I really do hope that on a political level, we can all work together on this one in order to put the interests of the people of Carmarthenshire first."
A Clean Power spokeswoman said: "We are grateful to all residents and community representatives that have taken time to comment on our plans.
"All feedback has been analysed and responded to in a consultation report that can be viewed as part of our planning submission.
"As well as contributing to the UK's renewable energy targets, the energy recovery element of this project will help provide Carmarthenshire with a much needed alternative to the landfilling of non-hazardous waste produced by the region from everyday life."
]]></text></news-item>