<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-9NW1-J9YR-G012"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Andrew Lloyd Webber and Tim Rice's choirmaster friend accused of sustained campaign of child abuse at George Osborne's old school</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>MARTIN ROBINSON</author><text><![CDATA[Allegations made about Alan Doggett and 5 others who worked at St Paul'sPupils accuse management of 'hushing up' abuse over two decadesDoggett helped Rice and Lloyd Webber with first performance of JosephChoirmaster was member of notorious Paedophile Information Exchange5 others named as alleged abusers but they have never been prosecuted
A choirmaster friend of Andrew Lloyd Webber and Tim Rice has been named as one of six teachers at George Osborne's former school who allegedly abused boys as young as ten over at least two decades.
The staff all worked at the prestigious St Paul's School in London - or its prep school Colet Court - between 1960 and the mid-1980s.
Alan Doggett helped launch the careers of Lloyd Webber and Rice and later conducted recordings of Joseph and the Amazing Technicolor Dreamcoat, Jesus Christ Superstar and Evita.
But the choirmaster is believed to have been a serial abuser while teaching at Colet Court - even making sex attacks part of his choir's audition process for some boys - but was allowed to quietly resign his post when a string of indecent assaults came to light.
Doggett was also an active member of the Paedophile Information Exchange (PIE), an infamous pro-child-sex group who wanted the age of consent lowered to ten.
After he left Colet Court he was given a job at the equally prestigious City of London School but threw himself under a train when he was charged with the indecent assault of a ten-year-old boy in 1978.
One of Doggett's alleged victims today accused St Paul's and Colet Court of 'hushing up' historic sex offences.
He said despite teachers being accused of abusing several pupils none of the four separate police investigations were never instigated by the schools.
Andrew Lloyd Webber told the Mail in 2012 he and Tim Rice were young struggling composers who 'got a call from Alan Doggett, who had taught Julian, my brother'.
Doggett asked them to 'write something for the kids' end of term concert' and they chose the biblical story of Joseph, which had its first performance at Colet in March 1968. Four months later it was recorded at Abbey Road with the help of Doggett and the Colet boy's choir.
After Doggett's suicide in 1978, The Magpie, the Paedophile Information Exchange's magazine for members, advertised a memorial service for him and said he should be remembered for his 'friendliness, integrity and loyalty'.
PIE's links to several leading members of the Labour party were revealed by the Mail last month, after it emerged the notorious group had extraordinary ties with the National Council for Civil Liberties - now known as Liberty.
WHAT THE SIX PRIVATE SCHOOL TEACHERS ARE ACCUSED OF
Alan Doggett - choirmaster: Allowed to resign from Colet Court after being accused of abusing boys. Killed himself in 1978 after being charged with child sex offences at another school. Was member of Paedophile Information Exchange.
'Alex Alexander' - housemaster: Accused of beating boys for sexual pleasure. Police never involved and believed to be dead.
Patrick Marshall - rowing master: Arrested last month over alleged abuse of 15-year-old boy in late 1970s. He denies the allegations and has been bailed.
Rev Paul Topham: Accused of abusing boys but police inquiry in 2000 led to no prosecution. He denied all allegations and died in 2012.
Unnamed teacher: Allowed to leave school for 'family reasons' after violent porn found in room and register of boys he had beaten was discovered.
Unnamed teacher: Arrested in 2000 for abuse in late 1980s. No further action after CPS said there was a lack of evidence.
Today the St Paul's High Master Professor Mark Bailey backed calls for a new police investigation and said: 'All such allegations must be properly and fully investigated' and 'subjected to the proper processes of justice'.
An investigation by The Times has today shed light on historic abuse involving five other staff who may have assaulted dozens of boys at St Paul's or Colet Court over 20 years.
St Paul's and Colet Court are considered among Britain's most prestigious schools.
Chancellor George Osborne and Attorney General Dominic Grieve QC were there at the time of the alleged abuse but there is no suggestion either were victims.
Luke Redmond said from the age of 12 he was attacked by three teachers who touched him inappropriately or beat him for sexual pleasure.
He is now 59 and married with children and says he needed to speak out about his ordeal at school for 'closure'.
The allegations made by him and others involve Alan Doggett and five other staff, The Times' Chief Investigative Reporter, Andrew Norfolk has said.
The most recent claims were made about Patrick Marshall, a geography and rowing tutor at St Paul's, who was arrested in February over the alleged abuse of a 15-year-old boy in 1979 and 1980. He was bailed and denies the allegations.
Former Colet Court teacher Paul Topham, was accused of groping at least one child in his bed and forcing others to swim naked while he would touch them.
He went on to become an Anglican priest, but a 2000 police inquiry into sexual abuse allegations never led to a prosecution and he denied all the allegations. He died in 2012 aged 80.
Another teacher at Colet, known as 'Alex' Alexander,  would allegedly beat boys in his office with their trousers down and and then sit them on his knee 'until his face went very red', one boy said. He is presumed dead.
The fifth teacher - another unnamed member of staff - was caught with a stash of sado-masochistic pornography in his office and a register of boys he liked to spank. He was allowed to leave for 'family reasons', The Times said today.
The sixth and final teacher, also unnamed, was investigated by police and arrested in 2000 after allegations of historic abuse in the late 1980s were made. But the Crown Prosecution Service decided there was insufficient evidence. 
In a statement St Paul's said: 'The allegations do not relate to any pupils or staff currently at the Schools.
'Any sexual abuse of children by an adult-and particularly a teacher-is abhorrent, a serious violation of trust, and an affront to the values of any caring community. 
'Suspects should be investigated and subjected to the proper processes of justice'.
]]></text></news-item>