<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-03X1-JD6S-R071"><date>2014-03-24</date><title>Resources: Where to go, how to help mudslide victims</title><source>The Daily Herald (Everett, Washington)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Red Cross donations
If you wish to help victims of the Oso mudslide, cash donations are preferred. The American Red Cross is no longer collecting items. Go to the Red Cross of Snohomish County to donate. People also can text "RedCross" to 90999 to make a $10 donation. Free counseling is available from the Red Cross around-the-clock at 800-985-5990 or text "TalkWithUs" to 66746.
------------
Banks collecting donations
------------
* A disaster relief account for Oso landslide victims has been set up at Union Bank in downtown Arlington, 525 N Olympic Ave. The account is through Cascade Valley Hospital Health Foundation, and checks should be addressed to that organization.
* The Coastal Community Bank is accepting donations for slide victims at all branches: Darrington, Camano Island, Everett, Monroe, Stanwood, Sultan, Silver Lake, Smokey Point, Snohomish and Whidbey Island.
Reminders
------------
* If you have missing loved ones or need to get in touch to confirm you are OK, call the Snohomish County Department of Emergency Management at 425-388-5088 or go to www.safeandwell.org.
* A new email has been set up in addition to the hotline. People with missing loved ones also can send info to DEMcallcenter@snoco.org They should provide as much information as possible, including pictures and descriptions of identifying features, such as tattoos.
* The Darrington and Arlington school district schedules are affected. Make sure to follow changes to school hours and bus routes.
Other fundraisers
------------
* The Arlington Domino 's Pizza plans to donate 100 percent of sales from Thursday to the victim relief fund. 3704 NE 172nd Ave. 360-659-1120.
* The Pazzaz Hair Design salon on N. Olympic Avenue downtown is giving money from each haircut to victims. 360-435-2975.
* Olympic Place Retirement and Assisted Living is planning a spaghetti feed from 4 to 7 p.m. on Thursday. Proceeds are expected to go to the American Red Cross and the families affected by Saturday's mudslide. Tickets cost $8. The event is set to take place at 20909 Olympic Place in Arlington
* The Spring Fling Fashion Show in Darrington now will be a fundraiser for the slide victims. The event is set for 5:30 to 8 p.m. April 12 and is $5 per person. Darrington youth will model fashions alongside an auction. Snacks and non-alcoholic drinks will be served. For tickets, call 425-320-6996.
Prayers
------------
* The Arlington United Church plans a prayer service at 7 p.m. Monday, 338 N. McLeod Ave. Childcare will be available. The church bells will ring at 9 a.m., noon and 3 p.m. to remind people to pray for those affected.
* The Oso Community Chapel was working Monday to get reopened to provide a safe gathering place for people. A public meeting is planned for 7 p.m. Wednesday at the church, 22318 Highway 530.
Access to Darrington
Highway 530 is closed and the town of Darrington is cut off from direct access to I-5. The Department of Transportation says drivers in Darrington will need to go north on Highway 530 to Highway 20 in order to avoid the closure. People can reach Darrington by going east on Highway 20 and south on Highway 530. Crews are working to open the Mountain Loop Highway as an alternate route.
------------
Key links:
------------
* Red Cross of Snohomish County
* Snohomish County 530 slide resources
* DSHS emergency programs
* Mudslide info and relief effort Facebook page
* Follow us on Twitter for updates as this story develops: @EverettHerald
]]></text></news-item>