<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-BP31-JCXB-21KW"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>HSBC Holdings PLC Annual Financial Report - 53 of -7-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Further details of legal proceedings and regulatory matters are set out in Note 43. Legal proceedings include civil court, arbitration or tribunal proceedings brought against HSBC companies (whether by way of claim or counterclaim) or civil disputes that may, if not settled, result in court, arbitration or tribunal proceedings. Regulatory matters refer to investigations, reviews and other actions carried out by, or in response to the actions of, regulators or law enforcement agencies in connection with alleged wrongdoing by HSBC. In December 2012, HSBC made payments totalling US$1,921m to US authorities in relation to investigations regarding inadequate compliance with anti-money laundering and sanctions laws. Further details of the agreements reached with the US authorities are set out on page 558. Customer remediation refers to activities carried out by HSBC to compensate customers for losses or damages associated with a failure to comply with regulations or to treat customers fairly. Customer remediation is initiated by HSBC in response to customer complaints and/or industry developments in sales practices, and is not necessarily initiated by regulatory action. Payment protection insurance An increase in provisions of US$756m was recognised during 2013 in respect of the estimated liability for redress regarding the mis-selling of payment protection insurance ('PPI') policies in previous years. Cumulative provisions made since the Judicial Review ruling in 2011 amount to US$3,153m, of which US$1,138m was paid in 2013 (2012: US$957m). At 31 December 2013, the provision amounted to US$946m (2012: US$1,321m). The estimated liability for redress is calculated on the basis of total premiums paid by the customer plus simple interest of 8% per annum (or the rate inherent in the related loan product where higher). The basis for calculating the redress liability is the same for single premium and regular premium policies. Future estimated redress levels are based on historically observed redress per policy. A total of approximately 5.4m PPI policies have been sold by HSBC since 2000, generating estimated revenues of US$4.1bn at 2013 average exchange rates. The gross written premiums on these polices was approximately US$5.0bn at 2013 average exchange rates. At 31 December 2013, the estimated total complaints expected to be received was 1.5m, representing 29% of total policies sold. It is estimated that contact will be made with regard to 1.9m policies, representing 35% of total policies sold. This estimate includes inbound complaints as well as HSBC's proactive contact exercise on certain policies ('outbound contact'). The following table details the cumulative number of complaints received at 31 December 2013 and the number of claims expected in the future:
1 Excludes invalid claims where the complainant has not held a PPI policy. 2 Claims include inbound and responses to outbound contact.
]]></text></news-item>