<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-MTG1-F05M-K076"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Survey: Duke Energy has too much pull in state, blocks strong regulation</title><source>Charlotte Business Journal</source><author>John Downey</author><text><![CDATA[Duke Energy (NYSE:DUK) and N.C. environmental officials fare poorly in a poll of registered voters in North Carolina commissioned by the Sierra Club on environmental issues and the massive coal ash spill on the Dan River.
The poll shows that 57 percent of the respondents believe stronger state enforcement could have prevented the spill. And 69 percent of those interviewed believe "other serious incidents like this one will occur unless some action is taken to prevent them."
Grace McRae, the public opinion research manager for the Sierra Club, called on Duke to take steps supported by vast majorities in the poll to protect the state from future spills. She noted 90 percent of the respondents say Duke should clean up the spill and improve safety at its other coal plants. Eighty-eight percent think Duke should be required to move coal ash storage to lined landfills far from rivers and lakes.
Duke declined to comment on the poll. State regulators in charge of coal ash issues were studying the poll and had no immediate comment.
Hart Research Associates, based in Washington, D.C., conducted the survey. The firm interviewed 600 registered voters March 10-13. Hart says the poll has a margin of error of plus or minus 4 percentage points.
The firm reports 39 percent of the respondents were Democrats, 31 percent were Republicans and 17 percent were registered as independents. Fifty-four percent of the respondents were female, and 46 percent were male.
Seventy percent of the respondents hold Duke entirely or mostly responsible for the Feb. 2 accident that sent 39,000 tons of ash from the Dan River Steam Station. Large pluralities also believe Charlotte-based Duke has too much influence on N.C. Gov. Pat McCrory's administration and stands in the way of "strong standards and enforcement to protect clean air and water and public health."
N.C. officials did no better on the survey. Sixty-three percent of the respondents said state officials are not doing enough to protect North Carolina's river and streams. Respondents say by 52 percent to 35 percent that officials do not do enough to protect "public health from pollution and other environmental hazards." And by a margin of 50 percent to 37 percent, they say officials do not do enough to protect North Carolina's environment in general.
The N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources takes a direct hit.
The poll asked respondents to rate the job DENR specifically is doing at "protecting the quality and cleanliness of water in the state." Thirty-one percent said DENR is doing an excellent or good job.
Sixty-three percent said the department was doing "just a fair job" or a poor job.
The poll shows that 75 percent of respondents had heard a lot or some about the spill, and 68 percent of all respondents said they were pretty concerned or extremely concerned about it.
The Sierra Club emphasized that 83 percent of those interviewed thought coal ash should be treated as a hazardous substance and should be regulated. And that response was held by large majorities in all parties - 91 percent of Democrats, 85 percent of Independents and 75 percent of Republicans.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Charlotte Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>