<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-XTV1-DYRW-R041"><date>2014-03-26</date><title></title><source>South China Morning Post</source><author>Name Name name.name@scmp.com</author><text><![CDATA[Guangdong
A man in Guangzhou was arrested by police for using women he had seduced as drug mules, the New Express reports. After starting up a relationship with the women, he would convince them to transport drugs, the report said. Customs officers had alerted local authorities to the illegal activity after tracing seized drugs back to the city. It was unclear how many women were involved or what drugs were trafficked.
Zhongshan city has launched a libraries-on-wheels programme in 20 districts and towns to improve access to reading material, People's Daily reports. Vans carrying a total of 5,000 titles will stop in designated areas so residents can browse items or sign them out. Registration with the mobile service will also allow residents to use public libraries in the area.
Guangxi
Police are cracking down on a popular strip in Nanjing city where elderly men visit inexpensive prostitutes for sex, the National Business Daily reports. The customers and the prostitutes, who are mostly middle-aged, reportedly have sex in broad daylight, using public benches by a lake next to Yanxi Road in Jiangning district. The women charge between 20 yuan (HK$25) and 60 yuan. Authorities are continuing their investigation.
The education department in Liuzhou has told middle and elementary schools to hold monthly emergency drills for disasters or acts of terrorism, the Nanguo News reports. While the fire, earthquake and terror drills have been practised before, the department wants them to be held more regularly as it sees the risks increasing.
Henan
A free breakfast programme has motivated thousands of students in Zhengzhou University to start doing exercises early in the morning, the Dahe Daily reports. The school offered a 3-yuan breakfast voucher, which can be redeemed at campus restaurants, for early birds who can run 800 metres around an exercise yard before 7am. The university said the policy had worked well so far.
The provincial government has prohibited the use of internet slang in government documents or textbooks for public servants, the Henan Business Daily reports. Officials are worried that using popular internet catchwords such as diaosi, or "loser", will diminish the seriousness and solemnity of official documents. Officials have published guidelines on writing reports to ensure that standards are maintained.
Hubei
A 26-year-old man in Wuhan was so heavily in debt that his parents had to intervene, the Wuhan Evenings News reports. The man, who held odd jobs but had five credit cards, reportedly squandered his money on clothes and fancy restaurants, ending up 100,000 yuan in debt, including interest charges. His parents tried to pay back their son's debts, but in the end they could only request that bank authorities reject any applications he sent for cards.
More than 200 writers in Wuhan who became popular on an online literary forum were given a career boost after being admitted to a local writers' association, the People's Daily reports. The writers owe much of their success to the Yangtze Literature Forum, a budding platform which has helped amateur writers publish poems, essays and novels for several years. The writers' association makes it easier for members to get hired to work for print publications.
Hunan
A husband committed suicide after killing his wife and in-laws after she spread news about his alleged impotence, the China Economic Weekly reports. The couple married last year but the relationship deteriorated. After the husband allegedly beat her, the wife fled to her parents' house. The man followed her and broke into the home, killing the woman, her parents and her brother. He later drowned himself in a river in Xiangyin village near Yueyang city.
Residents in Shimen county near Changde city are demanding authorities shut down mines they say have been dumping toxic chemicals into a river and poisoning the community, the Beijing Youth Daily reports. The mines for orpiment, an arsenic sulphide mineral used in semiconductors and fireworks, are accused of polluting the river with arsenic-laced waste water for 20 years. Residents blame the pollution for the deaths of 157 villagers.
Jiangsu
A husband and wife in Huaian filed a complaint with city authorities after their home was torn down and their elderly parents were allegedly beaten up by demolition workers, the Yangtze Evening Post reports. Their flat was in a three-storey building which was razed by a demolition company with whom they had refused to sign a land deal. They said the eviction happened while they were away.
A woman in Muyang county was found to have committed bigamy after her late husband's ex-wife sued her, the Yangtze Evening Post reports. The defendant was with the man for 40 years and they had four children. They wed in 1994 but only received their marriage certificate in 2004. This year, after he died, the ex-wife sued her, claiming she never divorced him.
Liaoning
A man, 29, was arrested for fatally stabbing his girlfriend after she tried to break up with him, the Shenyang Evening News reports. The victim, who grew up with the man in the same hometown, wanted to end the relationship after she began attending Shenyang University. But the man refused and visited her last weekend. He lured her to the suburbs, where he pleaded with her not to break up with him. When she refused, he stabbed her in the chest.
A hospital in Shenyang is under investigation for suspected participation in an illegal trade in fetuses, the Liaoshen Evening News reports. The newspaper received a tip-off and sent an undercover reporter to pose as a buyer. He discovered a group was buying fetuses from the hospital and selling them for about 300 yuan each. Some believe fetuses have medicinal benefits, and in powdered form have shown up in "stamina" pills.
Shaanxi
Shaanxi province has launched a crackdown on the illegal dumping of hazardous waste, the Shaanxi Daily reports. The policy will target 119 factories that deal with chemicals and electronics. The authorities vowed to penalise those who dumped chemicals into rivers or mixed their waste with ordinary rubbish.
A hotpot restaurant was shut down after it was found to have used stale cooking oil in food, the Huashang Daily reports. Empty barrels of reused oil were found on the premises. The Provincial Food and Drug Administration has launched an investigation. Old oil can be tainted with bacteria that can cause food poisoning. Unsafe cooking oil has been a persistent problem on the mainland.
]]></text></news-item>