<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-PPS1-JCTS-G0MH"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Fracking owner pleads guilty   He had ordered toxic pollution dumped to river </title><source>Plain Dealer (Cleveland, OH)</source><author>James F. McCarty jmccarty@plaind.com</author><text><![CDATA[The owner of a Youngstown oil- and gas-drilling company pleaded guilty today to ordering an employee to dump tens of thousands of gallons of fracking waste into a tributary of the Mahoning River.
Benedict Lupo, 63, of Poland, Ohio, could be sentenced up to three years in federal prison and be ordered to pay restitution of more than $3 million, plus fines of up to $1 million for his crimes.
U.S. District Judge Donald Nugent scheduled sentencing for June 16.
There was no plea bargain. Lupo pleaded guilty to the indictment, which charges him with the unpermitted discharge of pollutants under the federal Clean Water Act.
Assistant U.S. Attorney Brad Beeson said he would seek the maximum penalty of three years in prison for Lupo, plus an as-yet undetermined amount of fines and restitution.
Defense attorney Roger Synenberg said Lupo is extremely ill and Synenberg would ask the judge to take that into consideration when sentencing his client.
Beeson said there is still a chance of reaching a sentencing agreement with the defense prior to June 16.
Nugent sentenced Lupo’s former employee, Michael Guesman, 34, of Cortland, to three years probation last week after he pleaded guilty to the same Clean Water Act crime as his boss.
Guesman, a worker at Hardrock Evxcavating, testified that Lupo ordered him to run a hose from the 20,000-gallon storage tanks to a nearby storm-water drain and dump the polluted waste water, which eventually reached the Mahoning River.
The wastewater was a byproduct of Lupo’s hydraulic fracturing operations — commonly known as “fracking” — consisting of saltwater brine and a slurry of toxic oil-based drilling mud, containing benzene, toluene and other hazardous pollutants.
Guesman said he was afraid of losing his job if he failed to comply with Lupo’s orders.
Guesman lost his job anyway after Hardrock Excavating went out of business and Lupo fired most of his employees, Beeson said.
Guesman admitted dumping the polluted water into the drain on at least 20 occasions between Nov. 1, 2012, and Jan. 31, 2013.
And Guesman said Lupo ordered him to perform the secret dumping under cover of darkness and after all of the other employees had left the facility.
Guesman said Lupo ordered him to lie if questioned about the dumping and to tell law enforcement officers he had emptied the waste tanks only six times.
]]></text></news-item>