<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTT-NVX1-JB4P-V4XG"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Business Leaders Endorse Proposed New EPA Clean Water Rule</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Today, the American Sustainable Business Council (ASBC), which with its member organizations represents more than 200,000 businesses across the U.S., announced its support for the Environmental Protection Agency's (EPA) new proposed rule for water safety. The rule clarifies the EPA's regulatory power under the Clean Water Act, after two recent Supreme Court decisions threw some protections into legal jeopardy.
In a statement, ASBC said it supports the proposed rule because it will give the business community more confidence that streams and rivers will be protected, and provide a consistent regulatory system based on sound science. The following may be attributed to Richard Eidlin, Co-founder and Policy Director for ASBC:
"American business has always depended on the availability of clean water for its success, and EPA's regulation in this area historically has been a prime example of the vital partnership between business and government. Whether a company is a food producer, a high tech manufacturer of silicon wafers, outdoor recreation guide or a beer manufacturer, businesses rely on clean water to produce high quality and safe products. Ever since the passage of the Clean Water Act in 1972, the EPA has been charged with ensuring that our water supply remains safe.
"Today, we applaud the Agency for taking steps to clarify that small streams, wetlands and other tributaries are protected by the Act. Degradation and loss of wetlands or small streams can increase the risk of floods, threatening businesses. Moreover, dirty, polluted water creates unnecessary and sometimes very difficult economic challenges for communities and businesses alike. Today's action by the EPA is good for the environment and good for business."
The American Sustainable Business Council and its member organizations represent more than 200,000 businesses nationwide, and more than 325,000 entrepreneurs, executives, managers and investors. The council includes chambers of commerce, trade associations and groups representing small business, investors, microenterprise, social enterprise, green and sustainable business, local living economy and women and minority business leaders. ASBC informs and engages policy makers and the public about the need and opportunities for building a vibrant and sustainable economy. http://www.asbcouncil.org
Contact: Bob Keener, 617-610-6766,bkeener@asbcouncil.org
SOURCE American Sustainable Business Council
]]></text></news-item>