<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTV-DFY1-JCDS-Y022"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Mercosur-EU trade deal progresses slowly</title><source>Country Report Select</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Technical talks on a long-awaited free-trade agreement (FTA) between the EU and the Mercado Común del Sur (Mercosur, the Southern Cone Customs Union) took place on March 21st in Brussels, but failed to produce a calendar for further negotiations, mainly reflecting the continued lack of cohesion among the Mercosur countries on the deal's content and timeframe. Despite the slow pace of negotiations, there is clearly some renewed momentum for achieving a deal, particularly on the part of the Brazilian government, as it seeks to regain preferential access to Europe and improve its competitiveness, and further gradual progress is a possibility in the rest of the year.
The FTA, which has been in the pipeline since 2000, has repeatedly stalled owing to a failure to reach agreement on tariff reductions by both sides, with Mercosur countries wary of exposing their industrial sectors to competition from EU imports and the EU hesitant to crowd out its agricultural sector with competition from foreign farmers. A growing tendency towards trade protectionism in Mercosur's two largest member countries, Brazil and Argentina, has also been an obstacle. Argentina, in particular, has resisted any negotiation until recently, and has, on top of this, become embroiled in a number of trade disputes with EU members, resulting in formal complaints being made to the World Trade Organization (WTO).
However, the deterioration of global conditions has changed the economic landscape for both sides, giving renewed impetus to negotiations. Another driving force has been the global shift towards trade liberalisation outside of the WTO, prompted by the body's failure to produce global agreements before its ninth ministerial conference, which took place in Bali in December 2013. Probably most important has been the expiry in January of the Generalised System of Preference (GSP) agreements between the EU and Argentina, Brazil and Uruguay (who were among the 32 countries to have their trade preferences eliminated at the start of 2014 on the basis of their increasing per-head incomes). Paraguay maintains its trade preferences under the GSP, but is nevertheless keen to participate in the trade deal; Venezuela will not, reflecting continuing political turbulence and economic difficulties.
Brazil's president, Dilma Rousseff, has become a staunch advocate of the deal and has pushed in recent weeks for faster progress. Her stance reflects increasing pressure from domestic industry groups, which are fearful of losing competitiveness as other trade deals (including an EU-US FTA) gain momentum. This issue has been intensified by growing competition from cheap Chinese exports, which are increasingly threatening domestic trade. If the deal is delayed much longer, doubts could arise over the benefits for Brazil of its membership of Mercosur. This sentiment has been echoed by Carlos Abijaodi, head of the industrial development department of the Confederação Nacional da Indústria (CNI, the national industry confederation), who has made it clear that Brazil's industrial sector is keen to sign trade deals with different countries at a quicker pace than that of its Mercosur peers, saying that, otherwise, the country is in danger of failing to advance in new global markets.
Ms Rousseff's determination to secure a deal was underlined at the 7th annual EU-Brazil summit in Brussels on February 24th. During the summit, Ms Rousseff met with the head of the European Commission (EC), José Manuel Barroso, to discuss the deal's progress. Following the meeting, both sides made positive sounds regarding the status of the agreement, with Mr Barroso remarking that he had seen "progress on the Mercosur side" and that a deal would be reached in the "foreseeable future". For her part, Ms Rousseff confirmed the interest of other Mercosur countries-particularly that of Argentina, which has been repeatedly cast in doubt-and said that a deadline of May had been set for completion of the first draft of the deal.
As the two smaller economies in Mercosur, both Paraguay and Uruguay have a lot to gain from the deal. In Paraguay, the recently inaugurated president, Horacio Cartes, has openly promoted his administration's goal of opening the country's economy to foreign investment and strengthening trade ties. A recent study carried out by Desarrollo de Negocios Internacionales, a consultancy firm, showed that Paraguay was the country in South America that had shown the greatest increase (731%) in exports over the past ten years-although much of this has been the result of spikes in prices for key commodities exports, such as soybeans. This is mainly propelled by the country's export-oriented agricultural sector, which accounts for 20% of GDP. The signing of an agreement would boost exports further still, which would have a positive impact on the country's growth outlook.
Uruguay, meanwhile, continues to press for further trade liberalisation, as it seeks to diversify its exports away from Argentina, and to express its frustration with trade protectionism on the part of Brazil and, especially, Argentina in recent years. There is growing criticism in Uruguay that this protectionism has narrowed the country's opportunities for strengthening ties with the US, the EU, Asia and the rest of Latin America, and the government of José Mujica has in response embarked on its own push to diversify trade and investment partners in recent months. Mr Mujica recently visited both China and Europe with the aim of boosting exports and attracting foreign investment for the development of Uruguay's infrastructure. The government has also formally expressed a desire to join the Alianza del Pacífico (Pacific Alliance) free-trade zone (FTZ) as a full member as soon as possible. However, under Mercosur rules, Uruguay is in fact barred from negotiating free-trade agreements (FTAs) outside of Mercosur; it has, therefore, been extremely keen to convince its larger neighbours, especially Brazil, of the benefits of an EU-Mercosur FTA.
While Brazil appears to have been convinced of the benefits of an FTA with the EU, resistance from Argentina continues, and remains the biggest obstacle to the deal's completion from the Mercosur side. This was underlined by Uruguay's minister of foreign affairs, Luis Almagro, who said at a press conference in January that Brazil, Paraguay and Uruguay had agreed an ambitious "offer list", which would see import tariffs lifted on around 90% of European goods. However, Argentina, he said, had less ambitious plans, and this was holding back the deal. Mr Almagro at that point suggested the possibility of a two-speed deal, which would see the three countries push ahead and leave Argentina free to negotiate its own deal separately.
However, on March 14th the Brazilian minister of development, industries and trade, Mauro Borges, suggested that, after meeting in Argentina's capital, Buenos Aires, with his Argentinean counterpart, Débora Giorgi, along with the Argentinean economy minister, Axel Kicillof, a deal between Mercosur and the EU was closer than ever. Mr Borges went on to say that Mercosur was heading towards a "very competitive" presentation to the EU, but did not elaborate on the details of the offer, or how the issue of Argentina's resistance had been resolved.
The proposals are clearly not final. An EC statement made after the Brussels talks indicated only that there was an exchange of information and clarification of several issues surrounding the proposals, and that consultations would continue, with a view to exchanging proposals formally in coming months. This puts the May deadline in doubt. With the EC keen to advance its trade deals before the end of the term of the current commissioner for trade, Karl De Grucht, at year-end, a deal for all members could still be finalised. For this to happen, however, Argentina will have to demonstrate increased flexibility on tariff-reduction proposals. If it does not, and even with the strong impetus to complete a deal from Brazil, Paraguay and Uruguay, the deal will remain on hold.
]]></text></news-item>