<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTV-4C51-JCPJ-W0T1"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Wisconsin residents to split $3M from e-book settlement</title><source>Milwaukee Business Journal (Wisconsin)</source><author>David Schuyler</author><text><![CDATA[A national settlement regarding the alleged price-fixing of electronic books is expected to result in at least $3 million in distributions to injured consumers in Wisconsin.
Wisconsin Attorney General J.B. Van Hollen said Tuesday that the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of New York has now approved the $166 million in settlements of the lawsuit brought by the Wisconsin Department of Justice and the attorneys general in 32 other states against e-book publishers Hachette Book Group Inc., HarperCollins Publishers LLC, Simon & Schuster Inc., Holtzbrinck Publishers LLC (d/b/a Macmillan), and Penguin Group (USA) Inc. An account credit or check will be issued based on the number of eligible e-books purchased by a consumer during the claims period of April 1, 2010, to May 21, 2012.
Apple Inc. of Cupertino, Calif., was also sued but did not agree to settle. After a three-week trial in June 2013, U.S. District Judge Denise Cote found that Apple played a central role in facilitating and executing a conspiracy to eliminate retail price competition in order to raise e-book prices, in violation of federal and state antitrust laws. A second trial to determine the amount of damages Apple must pay for that violation has been tentatively scheduled for May. If successful, additional account credits or checks will be distributed to Wisconsin consumers in the future.
"Consumers are entitled to a fair, open and competitive marketplace," Van Hollen said in a press release. "When a company is found to have violated the antitrust laws, as Apple did here, consumers who have suffered as a consequence of that violation are entitled to compensation. At the upcoming damages trial, Wisconsin, along with Connecticut, Texas and New York, will be working on behalf of our partner states to obtain substantial, additional monetary compensation for consumers, as well as civil penalties for the state."
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Milwaukee Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>