<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTX-SKX1-DYT4-V4BG"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Sustainable abalone: Monterey company wins plaudits from environmentalists</title><source>San Jose Mercury News (California)</source><author>Nicholas St. Fleur nstfleur1@mercurynews.com</author><text><![CDATA[MONTEREY -- Trevor Fay grabs a fistful of fresh, crisp kelp and crams it into a large steel cage hidden within a dim, wooden cavern beneath Municipal Wharf No. 2, just a few hundred feet from where tourists browse gift shops and book whale-watching trips.
It's feeding time for more than a thousand baby abalone that line the cage in the "nursery section" of the Monterey Abalone Co.
Since 1992, the iridescent-shelled abalone have thrived in the company's cages, which hang suspended in Monterey Bay's waters from a barnacle-covered platform under the pier. A trapdoor at the end of the commercial dock serves as the entrance to an underworld that smells like brine and rings with the sounds of sea lions roaring and metallic gears cranking up cages.
Hordes of abalone once coated the rocks and sea floor of Monterey Bay. But because of overharvesting throughout most of the 20th century, wild abalone now are scarce.
State regulations prohibit the commercial harvesting of abalone, but they allow them to be farmed. The Monterey Abalone Co. is one of only two California aquaculture operations that use environmentally safe methods to cultivate red abalone in the same waters the species has populated for millennia.
Fay, the son of a marine biologist and a Salinas rancher, manages the aquaculture operation with his business partner, Arthur Seavey.
"They are feeding the abalone what they usually eat where they usually eat it," said Michael Graham, a scientist at Moss Landing Marine Labs. "They've pretty much taken all of the negatives out of aquaculture."
Most of the criticism of aquaculture, commonly called "fish farming," stems from the practices of the giant salmon-farming industry. Environmentalists fear that the practices pollute surrounding bodies of water with excess feed, potentially spreading diseases and threatening to create genetically different species when the farmed fish escape into wild populations.
Most abalone farms are land-based, such as the one in Davenport, north of Santa Cruz. The only other underwater abalone farm in California, Pacific Abalone Farms, grows the tasty mollusks in cages suspended off a raft in Monterey Harbor.
Seven species of wild abalone inhabit California waters, and each is fiercely protected by state regulations. Only red abalone can be farmed.
Feeding time
For the underwater farmers, sustainability begins at feeding time with hand-harvested kelp.
Every week a few of the company's eight employees make four boat trips to Monterey's abundant kelp patches, lean over their 22-foot flat-bottom aluminum skiff and wield butcher knives to chop several tons of the plant from its canopy.
Harvesting kelp, Fay said, is a sustainable step in the operation because the sea grass grows 14 to 18 inches every day. "It's just like cutting the grass in your frontyard," he said. "That top is going to come right back."
Kelp, which is regulated by the California Department of Fish and Wildlife, can only be legally harvested with a permit.
"The practice of feeding abalone is no more complicated than cutting hay and feeding it to a cow," said Randy Lovell, the department's aquaculture coordinator.
It takes the abalone nearly a week to devour the 10 to 40 pounds of kelp packed in their cages. But because there are hundreds of cages, feeding the farm's abalone army seems like a never-ending task for workers.
"By the time they finish, it's time to start at the other end," Fay said. "It's like painting the Golden Gate Bridge."
Workers also feed the abalone red algae, which give the mollusks their red appearance. Red algae are abundant where wild abalone grow, but not every farm incorporates it into the sea snail's diet. That's a mistake, Fay said, because omitting the algae leaves the abalone with pale shells and a bland taste. The algae also increase the abalone's growth rate by 25 percent, he said.
Monterey Bay Abalone sells abalone directly to local restaurants and consumers as an expensive entree -- more than $60 -- that is often grilled, pan-fried or sauteed and served in a garlic, butter or lemon sauce.
"The end result of all our work is an abalone that looks and tastes like a real wild abalone," Fay said.
The farm raises abalone from broodstock it receives from a hatchery that holds more than 9 million larvae. But the survival rate for the larvae is extremely low. Little more than 1 percent, or about 100,000, get to the farm.
A week after birth, the abalone develop their shells. At about nine months, they can start eating kelp. The abalone munch on the sea grass using two teeth-like mouthpieces called radula, which interlock to rasp away kelp.
"It's like having a zipper to rub against kelp and grind off pieces into their stomach," said Jim Covel, director of interpretation at the Monterey Bay Aquarium.
The company partitions its farm into three sections that grow abalone of different shell sizes and ages. Every section holds about 60 cages that can each support hundreds of older abalone with 6-inch shells to thousands of juvenile abalone with 2-inch shells.
The company sells abalone when they are between 3 and 6 inches. Regulations aimed at protecting the species and the bay dictate what size of abalone the company can sell, as well as the conditions in which the farm is operated.
Because of its feeding methods, the company's abalone gets a "green light" from the Monterey Bay Seafood Watch Program, said Peter Bridson, the program's aquaculture research manager. The program uses a traffic-light rating system to denote sustainable seafood options.
He said the Monterey Bay Abalone Co. runs a particularly sustainable operation because there are no significant concerns about chemical waste or feed waste -- or fear of the abalone escaping.
Seavey acknowledges that his operation's image is sometimes tainted by the widely criticized practices of salmon farming. However, he thinks the comparison is unfair.
"It's like saying all of agriculture is bad because people don't like industrial farming," Seavey said. "We hope that we can be an example of sustainable aquaculture -- not just environmentally, but economically, too."
Contact Nicholas St. Fleur at 408-920-5064. Follow him atTwitter.com/SciFleur .
ABALONE RULES
Though abalone were once numerous off the California coast, overharvesting in the past century has caused their numbers to drop so low that California regulations now prohibit commercially harvesting them in the wild.Recreational diving for the mollusks is legal anywhere north of the Golden Gate, but as of April 1 sport fishers can take only 18 a year -- and only nine off the coast of Marin and Sonoma counties.
]]></text></news-item>