<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTX-G8X1-JCXB-24HF"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>HSBC Holdings PLC Annual Financial Report - 41 of 60</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[RNS Number : 1641D HSBC Holdings PLC 25 March 2014 regulatory change in 2013 has led to increased scrutiny by the GRC of the Group's risk appetite profile and management actions to mitigate risks and exposures. We have set out in the report below further information on the role and activities of the GRC during 2013. On behalf of the Committee I should like to thank John Coombe, who will be stepping down as a Director with effect from the 2014 Annual General Meeting, for his valuable contribution. Joachim Faber Chairman, Group Risk Committee 24 February 2014 Role and members The GRC is responsible for advising the Board on high-level risk-related matters and risk governance and for non-executive oversight of risk management and internal controls (other than financial reporting).
1 All members are independent non-executive Directors. . With effect from the conclusion of the 2014 Annual General Meeting, John Coombe will retire as a Director and member of the GRC. 2 Appointed chairman of the Committee on 24 May 2013. 3 Retired as a member and chairman of the Committee on 24 May 2013. John Trueman, a non-executive director of HSBC Bank plc and Chairman of its risk committee, and Robert Herdman, a non-executive director of HSBC North America Holdings Inc. and HSBC Bank USA have both attended meetings of the GRC by invitation during 2013. Their experience of risk-related matters in the financial services industry is valued by the Committee. Governance All of HSBC's activities involve, to varying degrees, the measurement, evaluation, acceptance and management of risk or combinations of risks. The Board, advised by the Committee, requires and encourages a strong risk governance culture which shapes the Group's attitude to risk. The Board and the Committee oversee the maintenance and development of a strong risk management framework by continually monitoring the risk environment, top and emerging risks facing the Group and mitigating actions planned and taken. The Committee monitors the effectiveness of the Group's risk management and internal controls systems other than over financial reporting, which are monitored by the GAC. The governance structure for the management of risk is set out in the following table. Each major operating subsidiary has established a board committee with non-executive responsibility for oversight of risk-related matters and an executive committee with responsibility for risk-related matters. Governance structure for the management of risk
]]></text></news-item>