<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTX-M8N1-JCBG-S01M"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Indophil says ready to take over mine</title><source>BusinessWorld</source><author>Imee Charlee C. Delavin</author><text><![CDATA[AUSTRALIA's Indophil Resources NL is prepared to take over a major mining project in central Mindanao - deemed potentially the country's biggest foreign investment to date - should its key partner abandon the venture, according to a company spokesman yesterday.
Gavan Collery, Indophil's vice-president for corporate affairs, said Indophil could take over the stake of Anglo-Swiss firm GlencoreXstrata should the latter divest its interest in Sagittarius Mines, Inc. (SMI), which has the rights to develop and operate the $5.9-billion Tampakan copper-gold project.
GlencoreXstrata and Indophil hold 62.5% and 37.5% interests, respectively, in a 40% controlling stake in SMI. The remaining 60% is held by Tampakan Mining Corp. and Southcot Mining Corp.
"One of Indophil's best options is to talk with Glencore with the view of Indophil taking over... the project," Mr. Collery told reporters over lunch in Quezon City, admitting that status quo and even Indophil's own divestment remain scenarios.
"The reason I sought to have chit-chat with you is to let you know there's every reason for Indophil to continue with the project," he stressed.
"It's fair to say that we're looking at the three options. But at the end of the day - in my head - I'm thinking you'll see more of Indophil in the picture," Mr. Collery continued.
"Should Glencore decide to divest from the project, Indophil is more than willing to push through with the... share takeover."
Mr. Collery admitted that GlencoreXstrata has given Indophil "several indications that it is not inclined to go [on] with the project and every indication that, at some stage, they're going to divest their interests in this project."
Tampakan was one of two projects - the other being the Las Bambas copper mine project in Peru - being considered for possible sale by GlencoreXstrata to meet a requirement to sell its copper stakes that was imposed by China as a condition for approving the takeover of Xstrata last year.
The Tampakan project covers an area of around 10,000 hectares straddling Tampakan, South Cotabato; Columbio in Sultan Kudarat; Kiblawan in Davao del Sur; and Malungon in Sarangani. Value of mine production has been placed at $37 billion over 20 years.
South Cotabato's imposition of a ban on open-pit mining - the technique SMI says is needed by the project - has held back development. SMI had said in 2012 it would defer start of commercial operations to 2019 from 2016, with construction to "potentially commence in 2015" due to the ban.
The company adopted a new work plan in August last year due to this and other obstacles "with the aim of securing government support on key bottleneck issues before proceeding to final valuation and possible development," Mr. Collery recalled.
"Should we secure all needed approvals, construction based on our timeline will commence 2016 and first production target by 2019 although first production date remains subject to government approvals not yet obtained."
The government had issued a conditional environmental compliance certificate for the Tampakan project in February last year.
Mr. Collery said Indophil has welcomed national government moves to help Tampakan surmount project obstacles. The Mining Industry Coordinating Council last year formed an interagency working group to recommend measures to address these problems, including conflicts between certificate of land ownership awards and Tampakan mining tenements, potential liabilities for environmental damage arising from project operations, the open-pit mining ban, as well as securing free and prior informed consent of affected indigenous communities.
"What we need to see are hurdles being overcome. The open-pit ban is a hurdle. In our eyes, it is still not being resolved and we seek the intervention of the national government to resolve that hurdle... in the very near future," Mr. Collery said.
]]></text></news-item>