<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTX-THP1-JDJ4-M01K"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Broker jailed for 6 years for conning clients out of £3m</title><source>Mortgage Strategy</source><author>Devraj Ray</author><text><![CDATA[A Northumbria-based mortgage broker has been jailed for six years after conning over 50 his clients out of £3m.
Northumbria Police charged David Reid, 50, with 23 counts of obtaining a money transfer by deception, with the offences spanning a period of 12 years. Reid was also charged with participating in a fraudulent business dating back to January 2007.
He appeared at Newcastle Crown Court on February 17, pleading guilty to all charges. He was sentenced to six years in prison on 21 March.
The offences related to Reid advising clients of his firm Washington Mortgage Centre to place their money in a higher-interest paying offshore account. Clients were supposed to receive these interest payments directly to their bank accounts but these payments stopped in November 2012.
When clients made enquiries with their banks it emerged the offshore account did not exist and supporting documentation had been falsified.
Northumbria Police Major Crime Team investigated the claims and subsequent search warrants led to the seizure of information on Reid's clients and business interests.
Reid was arrested in March 2013 as part of the ongoing investigation.
Northumbria Police DCI Christina Barrett says: "Reid gained the trust of his victims, so much so that he persuaded people to cash in existing investments, insurance and pension premiums on his advice to make investments in his scheme.
"The financial advice Reid provided to his clients was false and misleading and forged documents appear to have been used to reinforce the fraud, convincing clients to participate in the scheme.
"He deceived people out of millions of pounds and left many of his victims suffering significant financial hardship. These people put their trust in Reid and his actions are nothing short of disgusting. The impact on these individuals cannot be underestimated with generations of families' inheritance stolen by Reid."
]]></text></news-item>