<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTX-TV41-JCB9-7195"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Anglo American resumes operations at Los Bronces following protest</title><source>Business News Americas - English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[London-based Anglo American (LSE: AAL) has resumed operations at its Los Bronces copper mine in central Chile, following a day of protests and blockades by subcontracted workers.
Anglo American was forced to shut down operations at Los Bronces late Monday (Mar 24) to secure the safety of its workers, the company said in a release.
However, operations at the mine had stopped completely since the early hours of Monday as well as at other Anglo operations in the country, including the El Soldado and Mantoverde divisions, Manuel Ahumada, president of the subcontracted mining workers federation CTC told BNamericas.
Anglo American resumed operations at Los Bronces in the early hours of Tuesday. The company is expected to carry out a full evaluation of the damage caused during the protest, a separate statement said.
REASONS
The protest began in the early hours of Monday over alleged anti-union practices, including layoff threats and harassment of union leaders, Ahumada said.
Subcontracted workers have been trying to reach an agreement with miners that will give them some of the benefits that company workers have, including labor and safety benefits, as well as non-discrimination policies, the CTC leader said.
"We have first and second-category workers in fundamental areas such as transport. For example at [Anglo's smelter and refinery] Chagres, subcontracted workers have to get there using public transport or their own means, while for in-house workers the company provides transportation."
"We think this is arbitrary discrimination. Such practices are unacceptable in the year 2014," Ahumada told BNamericas.
The situation is similar at other mining companies that have subcontracted workers. At state copper giant Codelco, CTC workers staged a strike in the early 2010s which resulted in the company adopting a non-discriminatory approach, as we are demanding from Anglo American, the union leader said.
Ahumada said the union expects to resume negotiations with Anglo American representatives soon, and did not rule out future protests if an agreement is not reached. The last talks between both parties took place on February 6.
Copper production at Los Bronces in 2013 was 416,300t. The mine is 50.1% controlled by Anglo American, while Codelco holds a 24.5% stake. Japanese conglomerates Mitsui and Mitsubishi hold the remaining share.
http://www.bnamericas.com/story.xsql?id_sector=7&id_noticia=641816&Tx_idioma=I&source=
]]></text></news-item>