<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTY-5061-JB4P-V0VR"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Candidate Selection for Clinical Trials, Financial Results, and Patient Enrollments for Phase I Study - Analyst Notes on Synta, Ziopharm, Aastrom, Agios, and OncoMed; Editor Note: For more information about this release, please scroll to bottom</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Today, Analysts Review released its analysts' notes regarding Synta Pharmaceuticals Corp. (NASDAQ: SNTA), ZIOPHARM Oncology, Inc. (NASDAQ: ZIOP), Aastrom Biosciences, Inc. (NASDAQ: ASTM), Agios Pharmaceuticals, Inc. (NASDAQ: AGIO), and OncoMed Pharmaceuticals, Inc. (NASDAQ: OMED). Private wealth members receive these notes ahead of publication. To reserve complementary membership, limited openings are available at:http://www.AnalystsReview.com/register
--
Synta  Pharmaceuticals  Corp.  Analyst  Notes
On March 11, 2014, Synta Pharmaceuticals Corp. (Synta) and QuantumLeap Healthcare Collaborative jointly announced that Synta's lead drug candidate, the Hsp90 inhibitor ganetespib, has been selected for study in the I-SPY 2 TRIAL (Investigation of Serial Studies to Predict Your Therapeutic Response with Imaging And moLecular Analysis 2). "The selection of ganetespib for the I-SPY 2 program is important validation of the potential for ganetespib in breast cancer," said Dr. Iman El-Hariry, Vice President of Clinical Research at Synta. "This study represents a new standard for efficient, cutting edge collaborative research, and has already yielded promising new findings, such as those announced for investigational agents veliparib and neratinib. We look forward to participating in the trial." The Companies informed that they expect enrollment in the ganetespib arm of I-SPY 2 to begin in 2014. The full analyst notes on Synta Pharmaceuticals Corp. are available to download free of charge at:
http://www.AnalystsReview.com/03252014/SNTA/report.pdf
--
ZIOPHARM  Oncology,  Inc.  Analyst  Notes  
On March 3, 2014, ZIOPHARM Oncology, Inc. (Ziopharm) reported its Q4 2013 and full-year 2013 financial results. The Company reported Q4 2013 net loss of $8.9 million or $0.09 per basic and diluted share, compared to $30.2 million or $0.37 per basic and diluted share in Q4 2012. Full year 2013, net loss was $57.1 million or $0.66 per share, compared to $96.1 million or $1.22 per share in full-year 2012. Ziopharm informed that it expects to file several investigational new drug (IND) applications for novel, multigenic gene therapies through 2015. The full analyst notes on ZIOPHARM Oncology, Inc. are available to download free of charge at:
http://www.AnalystsReview.com/03252014/ZIOP/report.pdf
--
Aastrom  Biosciences,  Inc.  Analyst  Notes
On March 13, 2014, Aastrom Biosciences, Inc. (Aastrom) reported its Q4 2013 and full-year 2013 financial results. For the quarter, the Company reported net loss of $2.9 million or $0.65 per share, compared to 6.7 million or $3.60 per share in Q4 2012. For full year 2013, net loss was $15.6 million or $6.95 per share, compared to $29.5 million or $16.25 per share in full-year 2012. According to Aastrom, the substantial decrease in net loss during both the periods on YoY basis is primarily due to decreases in research and development and general and administrative expenses and the non-cash change in the fair value of warrants. "With the completion of a number of operational and financial initiatives in 2013, we are well-positioned to continue to build on our momentum in advancing our ongoing ixmyelocel-T clinical programs, exploring new indications for ixmyelocel-T and pursuing promising new business opportunities in 2014," said President and CEO Nick Colangelo. The full analyst notes on Aastrom Biosciences, Inc. are available to download free of charge at:
http://www.AnalystsReview.com/03252014/ASTM/report.pdf
--
Agios  Pharmaceuticals,  Inc.  Analyst  Notes
On March 19 2014, Agios Pharmaceuticals, Inc. (Agios) announced the enrollment of the first patient in its Phase 1 Study of AG-120 in patients with Advanced Hematologic Malignancies with an isocitrate dehydrogenase-1 or IDH1 Mutation. According to the Company, AG-120 is an orally available, selective, potent inhibitor of the mutated IDH1 protein, making it the first targeted therapeutic candidate to treat patients with cancers that harbor the IDH1 mutation. David Schenkein, M.D., CEO of Agios commented, "Initiation of this study also represents a significant milestone for Agios, as we have exclusive U.S. rights for the IDH1 program, as well as for our partner Celgene, who has an option on IDH1 program rights in the rest of the world. Most importantly, we believe this program has the potential to change the treatment of cancer and help patients." The Company informed that AG-120 is a part of Agios' global strategic collaboration with Celgene Corporation. The full analyst notes on Agios Pharmaceuticals, Inc. are available to download free of charge at:
http://www.AnalystsReview.com/03252014/AGIO/report.pdf
--
OncoMed  Pharmaceuticals,  Inc.  Analyst  Notes 
On March 18, 2014, OncoMed Pharmaceuticals, Inc. (OncoMed) reported its Q4 2013 and full-year 2013 financial results. For the quarter, revenues totaled $19.0 million, compared to $6.9 million in Q4 2012. Net loss during the quarter remained unchanged from Q4 2012 at $4.3 million. Net loss per diluted share was $0.15 in Q4 2013, compared to $4.01 per diluted share in Q4 2012. For full year 2013, revenues increased to $37.8 million from $24.7 million in full year 2012, primarily attributable to collaborative revenues in the form of milestone payments from Bayer associated with the vantictumab and OMP-54F28 program received in Q4 2013 and the amortization of upfront payments from OncoMed's agreements with GSK, Bayer and Celgene. Net loss was $26.1 million or $1.93 per diluted share in full year 2013, compared to $22.2 million or $21.30 per diluted share in full year 2012. The full analyst notes on OncoMed Pharmaceuticals, Inc. are available to download free of charge at:
http://www.AnalystsReview.com/03252014/OMED/report.pdf
--
About  Analysts  ReviewWe provide our members with a simple and reliable way to leverage our economy of scale. Most investors do not have time to track all publicly traded companies, much less perform an in-depth review and analysis of the complexities contained in each situation. That's where Analysts Review comes in. We provide a single unified platform for investors' to hear about what matters. Situation alerts, moving events, and upcoming opportunities.
--=============
EDITOR  NOTES:
This is not company news. We are an independent source and our views do not reflect the companies mentioned. Information in this release is fact checked and produced on a best efforts basis and reviewed by Nidhi Vatsal, a CFA charterholder. However, we are only human and are prone to make mistakes. If you notice any errors or omissions, please notify us below. This information is submitted as a net-positive to companies mentioned, to increase awareness for mentioned companies to our subscriber base and the investing public. If you wish to have your company covered in more detail by our team, or wish to learn more about our services, please contact us at pubco [at] AnalystsReview.com. For  any  urgent  concerns  or  inquiries, please contact us at compliance [at] AnalystsReview.com. Are you a public company? Would you like to see similar coverage on your company? Send us a full investors' package to research [at] AnalystsReview.com for consideration.
COMPLIANCE  PROCEDURE
Content is researched, written and reviewed on a best-effort basis. This document, article or report is prepared and authored by Analysts Review. An outsourced research services provider represented by Nidhi Vatsal, CFA, has only reviewed the information provided by Analysts Review in this article or report according to the Procedures outlined by Analysts Review. Analysts Review is not entitled to veto or interfere in the application of such procedures by the outsourced provider to the articles, documents or reports, as the case may be.
NOT  FINANCIAL  ADVICE
Analysts Review makes no warranty, expressed or implied, as to the accuracy or completeness or fitness for a purpose (investment or otherwise), of the information provided in this document. This information is not to be construed as personal financial advice. Readers are encouraged to consult their personal financial advisor before making any decisions to buy, sell or hold any securities mentioned herein.
NO  WARRANTY  OR  LIABILITY  ASSUMED
Analysts Review is not responsible for any error which may be occasioned at the time of printing of this document or any error, mistake or shortcoming. No liability is accepted by Analysts Review whatsoever for any direct, indirect or consequential loss arising from the use of this document. Analysts Review expressly disclaims any fiduciary responsibility or liability for any consequences, financial or otherwise arising from any reliance placed on the information in this document. Analysts Review does not (1) guarantee the accuracy, timeliness, completeness or correct sequencing of the information, or (2) warrant any results from use of the information. The included information is subject to change without notice.
CFA® and Chartered Financial Analyst® are registered trademarks owned by CFA Institute.
SOURCE Analysts Review
]]></text></news-item>