<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTY-5401-JBG1-80TY"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Baron and Budd Files Lawsuit Against GM Regarding Recent Faulty Ignition Recall; Recall May Affect More Than 1.6 Million GM Vehicles, Linked to 12 Deaths</title><source>Business Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Baron and Budd, along with co-counsel, has filed a lawsuit against automobile manufacturer GM regarding the company's recent recall of more than 1.6 million vehicles that are believed to have faulty ignitions. According to news reports, the faulty ignitions may cause certain GM vehicles to stall or suddenly turn off, or even cause the air bag system to fail during an accident. The faulty ignitions have already been linked to 12 deaths, according to reports inTheNew York Times. Baron and Budd is working with Grant & Eisenhofer, P.A., The Cooper Firmandothers in the lawsuit, including the former Chief Justice of the Missouri Supreme Court and the former U.S. Attorney for West Virginia.
Roland Tellis (Photo: Business Wire)
The lawsuit, filed yesterday in the U.S. District Court for Northern California, states that GM knew its ignition system may have created an increased risk of injury as early as 2001, but failed to take the necessary steps to correct the issue. GM has also publicly stated that the keys in the affected vehicles could accidentally slip out of the "run" position while the car's engine was running.
As reported inThe New York Times, GM has told federal regulators that the company may have known about the defectiveignitionswitches as early as 2001, during testing of the Saturn Ion. According to GM, if the faulty ignition is bumped or weighed down by a heavy key ring, it could shut down the vehicle completely and disable the air bags.
"The real question here is why GM waited for so long to issue this recall," saidRoland Tellis, alawyer at Baron and Budd. "Quite simply, we filed this case to hold GM accountable to its loyal customers." Tellis added: "Old GM was financially bankrupt; I hope new GM is not morally bankrupt."
The recall has already sparked a government investigation.
The vehicles affected by the recent recall include: the 2005-2010 Chevrolet Cobalt, the 2006-2007 Chevrolet HHR, the 2006-2007 Pontiac Solstice, the 2005-2007 Pontiac GS, the 2003-2006 Saturn Ion and the 2006-2007 Saturn Sky Vehicle.
To learn more about the GM faulty ignition recall lawsuit, call Baron and Budd at 818-839-2320 or visit our website here: http://baronandbudd.com/ .
About Baron & Budd, P.C.
With a history of over 35 years "Protecting What's Right" for individuals, communities, and governmental entities, Baron and Budd is a well-established law firm devoted to making a positive difference. With offices in Dallas, Austin, Los Angeles and Baton Rouge, Baron and Budd is able to take on complicated and expensive cases within the realms of dangerous drugs and medical devices, asbestos-related illnesses, consumer fraud, water contamination, the Gulf oil spill and fraudulent financial practices.
Photos/Multimedia Gallery Available: http://www.businesswire.com/multimedia/home/20140325005942/en/
http://www.businesswire.com
]]></text></news-item>