<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTY-4XK1-F0NV-F0VC"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>IN BRIEF</title><source>Daily Messenger (Canandaigua, New York)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NY extends comment period on high-speed rail
The state Department of Transportation has extended the public comment period on plans for high-speed rail service between New York City and Upstate New York.
The comment period was originally supposed to end Monday. Officials have received about 250 comments and held six public hearings across the state that attracted more than 500 people.
Transportation Commissioner Joan McDonald says comments will be accepted through April 30.
The state's draft environmental impact statement lays out five alternatives for higher speed passenger rail service along the 463-mile Empire Corridor, from New York City to Niagara Falls.
Comments may be submitted through the DOT's website or emailed to empirecorridor@dot.ny.gov
- The Associated Press
ITHACA
Cornell's looking for bird nest watchers
As birds wing their way north from their wintering grounds, the Cornell Lab of Ornithology is recruiting volunteers for its annual NestWatch citizen science project.
Participants map any nest or birdhouse location on the NestWatch website (www.NestWatch.org ). Then they report the species of nesting bird, when eggs are laid, how many hatch, and how many fledglings leave the nest.
Sometimes NestWatchers see something that surprises scientists. Last year, participant Gerald Clark reported twin bluebirds hatching from one egg. NestWatch leaders say it was so unusual it was written up in a scientific journal.
This spring, researchers are asking NestWatchers to be on the look-out for nesting Eurasian collared doves. The non-native species has rapidly colonized most of North America but little is known about its breeding habits.
- The Associated Press
ALBANY
NY asks feds to update oil spill plans
New York officials asked the Environmental Protection Agency on Monday to update a contingency plan for dealing with oil spills amid the rapid expansion of rail shipments of crude oil from North Dakota across New York to coastal refineries.
State Department of Environmental Conservation Commissioner Joe Martens sent a letter Monday to EPA Administrator Gina McCarthy. He said under the Oil Pollution Act of 1990, the EPA is responsible for creating Inland Area Contingency Plans to improve preparedness for oil spills.
A review of crude oil rail safety ordered by Gov. Andrew Cuomo in January found immediate action was needed by the EPA to update contingency plans and develop response plans for environmentally sensitive areas, Martens said.
Cuomo directed state agencies to do a comprehensive review of safety procedures and emergency response preparedness related to shipments of crude from the Bakken oil fields in North Dakota in light of a series of rail disasters last year, including one in Quebec that killed 47 people. The agencies are to report by the end of April on their findings.
- The Associated Press
BUFFALO
Buffalo gets grant to improve Erie water
The city of Buffalo is receiving a $500,000 federal grant to improve water quality in Lake Erie.
The award was announced Monday by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency. EPA officials say it will fund green infrastructure projects that will help prevent storm water from carrying contamination into the lake.
The city of Buffalo and the Buffalo Sewer Authority will use the grant, along with $500,000 from Empire State Development, to install porous asphalt, storm water planters and rain gardens along a one-mile section of Niagara Street along the Niagara River, which flows from Lake Erie.
Authorities say the projects will control up to 4.9 million gallons of storm water runoff per year and reduce the amount of road salt, oil and sediment flowing into the river.
- The Associated Press
]]></text></news-item>