<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTY-N1K1-DXXV-301P"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>THE NATION; Channel partly reopens after oil spill; As cleanup continues, it is uncertain when ship traffic will fully resume at the seaport near Houston.</title><source>Los Angeles Times</source><author>Michael Muskal</author><text><![CDATA[One of the nation's busiest seaports partially reopened to ship traffic Tuesday after a weekend oil spill near Houston, the Coast Guard announced.
Traffic resumed through the Houston Ship Channel about 1 p.m., Coast Guard Petty Officer Manda Emery said. There was no estimate of when the channel would fully reopen or how long it would take to clear the backlog of more than 100 vessels waiting to get through.
The channel was closed Saturday after a collision between an oil barge and a ship, which led to a spill of up to 168,000 gallons of oil into the waters used by ships serving refineries.
"The cleanup operations progress is to the point that there is minimal danger of contamination to the commercial maritime traffic and allowing limited transit during daylight hours," Coast Guard Capt. Brian Penoyer said in a statement.
More than 71,000 feet of containment boom has been deployed on waters surrounding the incident site and along environmentally sensitive shorelines, the Coast Guard said.
The oil spill is a mere fraction of more well-known environmental disasters such as in 1989 when the Exxon Valdez let loose more than 11 million gallons of oil into Prince William Sound off Alaska. The Deepwater Horizon disaster in 2010 resulted in more than 200 million gallons of oil spewing into the Gulf of Mexico.
Officials said they believed that most of the oil spilled Saturday was drifting out into the gulf, which should limit the damage to bird habitats around Galveston Bay and on the beaches. Officials from the Texas General Land Office, the lead state agency, said they were optimistic.
Experts from the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and the Texas Parks and Wildlife Department also have responded to the spill. So far, there have been 18 birds confirmed captured and 10 dead, officials said.
But environmental groups said those numbers underestimated the impact.
"The number of birds affected is definitely going to be higher" than the count so far, said Iliana Pena, director of conservation for Audubon Texas. She said there were already 50 to 60 birds that had been oiled.
--
michael.muskal@latimes.com
]]></text></news-item>