<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTY-K7T1-JC1N-W0M2"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>IN BRIEF</title><source>Dayton Daily News (Ohio)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[COURTS
E-Book settlement for Ohio consumers
A lawsuit over e-book price fixing, could mean more money in some Ohioans' wallets. Ohio Attorney General Mike Dewine announced Tuesday that consumers will begin receiving checks or credits this week from a settlement in a 2012 lawsuit.
Dewine and attorneys general from 32 other states filed the suit against Apple Inc., and e-book publishers Hachette Book Group Inc., Harper Collins Publishers LLC, Simon and Schuster Inc., Holtzbrinck Publishers LLC, Macmillan, and Penguin Group (USA) Inc. The suit claimed that companies conspired to fix the price of electronic books.
The publishers settled the claim for $166 million dollars and $4.7 million of that will be distributed to Ohioans who purchased e-books from the publishers, Dewine said.
People who purchased an e-book between April 1, 2010 and May 21, 2012, may be eligible to receive part of the settlement. Call 866-621-4153 or go to www.ebookags ettlements.com for more information. STAFF REPORT
MANUFACTURING
GE Aviation to invest in Indiana plant
A report says GE Aviation plans to invest $92 million and create 200 jobs at a jet-engine manufacturing plant in Lafayette.
The Indianapolis Business Journal reports the board of the Indiana Economic Development Corp. discussed the company's plans during a meeting Tuesday.
GE Aviation has invested $17 million in three Dayton-area sites in the past five years and has partnered to add a $51 million facility on the University of Dayton campus. STAFF REPORT
JOBS
Meijer to hire for Marysville store
Meijer is conducting interviews to complete hiring for more than 270 positions in all departments for its new Marysville store scheduled to open this summer. Open positions include clerks and cake decorators to customer service, cashiers, receiving and meat cutters. Starting pay will be based on experience level and specific skills. STAFF REPORT
]]></text></news-item>