<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTY-XFB1-JC8S-C0RT"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Russian regulator strips three more regional banks of licence in clean-up drive</title><source>BBC Monitoring Former Soviet Union - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Russian Central Bank has revoked the licences of three mid-sized regional banks and a non-banking credit organization in the latest move to clean up the national banking sector, Russian privately-owned news agency Interfax reported on 26 March.
The Yekaterinburg-based Sberegatelniy and Investitsionniy bank (Sberinvestbank), which is ranked 509 in terms of assets, lost its licence over the non-compliance with the Russian federal laws regulating banking activity and multiple violations of the law on combating money laundering.
"(Sberinvestbank - Interfax) pursued a high-risk borrowing policy, and it did not create reserves that were adequate for the risks for possible loan losses," Central Bank's statement said.
Sberinvestbank's volume of dubious transactions amounted to R4.6bn (about 129m dollars at the current exchange rate) in 2013.
Two more banks that have been stripped of licences are Ufa-based Moy bank. Ipoteka, the clients of which will be taken over by Rossiyskiy Kredit bank, and Moscow-based Sovinkom bank, the dubious transactions of which amounted to R6.8bn (about 191m dollars) in 2013, Interfax said in a later report.
According to Russian state-run news agency RIA Novosti, Moy Bank. Ipoteka started experiencing difficulties following a revocation of the banking licence of Moy Bank, which was in the same banking group. In February, temporary administration was appointed to run the bank and to reorganize it, but it was later decided that the reorganization of the bank was impossible.
"The analysis of the financial condition of Moy Bank. Ipoteka has revealed that the bank lost its own funds and also could not restore its financial solvency," RIA Novosti quoted the Central Bank as saying.
The non-banking credit organization called "Rasschetniy tsentr 'EnergoBusiness'" was stripped of its banking licence over violations of the accounting procedure and the inability to carry out appropriate internal audit, as well as over violations of the Central Bank's regulations on combating money laundering, RIA Novosti said in a later report.
The organization's volume of dubious transactions reached R4bn (about 112m dollars) in 2013.
The Deposit Insurance Agency will start reimbursing Sberinvestbank, Moy Bank. Ipoteka and Sovinkom banks' depositors no later than 9 April 2014, RIA Novosti reported.
Sources: Interfax news agency, Moscow, in Russian 0310 and 0452 gmt 26 Mar 14; RIA Novosti news agency, Moscow, in Russian 0320, 0528 and 0546 gmt 26 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>