<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTY-5GK1-JC65-52HH"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>2 who helped slain Texas cop among Carnegie Heroes</title><source>Associated Press State &amp; Local</source><author>JOE MANDAK, Associated Press</author><text><![CDATA[PITTSBURGH (AP) - Two employees who disarmed and subdued a shoplifter who fatally shot a police officer at a Texas Wal-Mart were among 22 people being honored Wednesday with medals and cash awards from the Carnegie Hero Fund Commission.
Five of those honored for various rescue attempts died in the process, so their families will receive the awards in their name.
One Pennsylvania man, 44-year-old Sanatoga bartender Kurt Buchler, was among those honored for his efforts last March to save a 19-year-old woman from an attack by three dogs. Buchler wound up being hospitalized for six days and missed three months' work.
Wal-Mart employees Lincoln LeMere and Archie Jordy were honored less than a month after the man they subdued, Brandon Daniel, 26, was sentenced to death for shooting Officer Jaime Padron on April 6, 2012, in Austin, Texas.
LeMere, 35, of Pflugerville, the store's retail manager, Jordy, his 42-year-old assistant, of Round Rock, intervened after the officer tackled Daniel as he was running out of the store.
Daniel pulled a gun and shot the officer twice before the employees were able to help.
LeMere reportedly pinned Daniel to the floor, while Jordy grabbed for the gun, which Daniel was able to fire once more - striking the ceiling - before Jordy was able to step on the suspect's hand to make him release the weapon. Jordy then called for help over the stricken officer's radio while LeMere held Daniel down until other officers arrived.
A jury took only an hour to return a guilty verdict Feb. 21, then sentenced Daniel to death a week later after prosecutors presented evidence that Daniel was overhead laughing by witnesses, who also heard him say, "I killed a cop."
The Carnegie Hero awards are named for the Pittsburgh industrialist and philanthropist, Andrew Carnegie, who was inspired by stories of heroism during a coal mine disaster near Pittsburgh that killed 181 people, including a miner and engineer who died trying to rescue others.
The commission investigates stories of heroism and awards medals and cash grant several times a year. The commission has given away more than $36 million to 9,675 awardees or their families since its inception in 1904.
]]></text></news-item>