<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTY-N431-J9YR-G37K"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>British Gas boss faces calls to give up £400,000 bonus; Energy giant's top five executives expected to be awarded £6.6m pay pot for 2013 amid pressure on British Gas boss Chris Weston to follow lead of Centrica chief Sam Laidlaw and forgo annual bonus</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Emily Gosden Energy Editor</author><text><![CDATA[The boss of British Gas faced calls to give up his bonus on Tuesday as it emerged he was in line for a £400,000 payout - amid allegations the energy giant rips off its loyal customers.
The bonus is expected to have pushed Chris Weston's total earnings for 2013 to in excess of £1m as part of a £6.6m annual pay pot for the top five executives at parent company Centrica.
British Gas raised household energy prices for its 10 million customers by 9.2 per cent in November and has been singled out for criticism by energy secretary Ed Davey, who has suggested it makes too much profit and may need to be broken up.
The details of Centrica's pay were leaked to Sky News ahead of a formal announcement scheduled for Thursday - the same day regulator Ofgem is expected to refer the energy sector for a full competition probe.
Centrica chief Sam Laidlaw is expected to have been awarded a total pay package of about £2m, including a £1m base salary, but has already pledged to donate his annual bonus to charity.
Mr Weston and other senior executives including Centrica finance chief Nick Luff have so far refused to do the same.
Caroline Flint MP, Labour's shadow energy and climate change secretary, said: "Hard-pressed families and pensioners struggling to pay their gas and electricity bills will be rightly outraged if British Gas awards its bosses bumper payouts - on top of their salaries - just months after it imposed huge price hikes on its customers.
"If the energy companies want to win back their customers' trust they should forego their bonuses and use the money to help freeze people's bills instead."
Centrica's total payout for its top executives has fallen significantly since 2012 - when it stood at £16.4m - because it is understood the company's performance failed to match up to targets for long-term bonus schemes.
The company's 2013 profits came in lower than had been expected, while its share price has fallen heavily in the wake of Ed Miliband's pledge to freeze energy prices if Labour is elected in 2015.
These factors are expected to mean that the executives did not receive any long-term bonus payouts vesting this year.
In addition, pay for former British Gas boss Phil Bentley will be much lower than in 2012 as he quit Centrica mid-way through 2013.
The four remaining senior executives are likely to be awarded large numbers of shares that could vest in future years depending on its performance.
However, Mr Luff has already resigned and plans to leave the company in coming months while Mr Laidlaw is known to be planning his own exit.
Mr Laidlaw took colleagues by surprise in November when he announced he was giving up his annual bonus. "Bonuses are independently set by our remuneration committee but in this environment there is a case for leadership," he said at the time.
"Just to continue in this world where households are under pressure, and assume it is business as normal, is not the way thoughtful remuneration committees think about it."
Ofgem is currently undertaking its first annual competition review of the energy sector and is expected to suggest the sector be referred for a full probe by the new Competition and Markets Authority.
Last month, Mr Davey wrote to Ofgem saying that "British Gas, the company with the largest share of the gas domestic supply market, has tended to charge one of the highest prices over the past 3 years, and has been on average the most profitable".
He said the regulator should consider "whether this is prima facie evidence of an issue in the market and so whether it merits a market investigation reference with the whole gamut of potential remedies that could follow including a break up of any companies found to have monopoly power to the detriment of the consumer".
Labour has accused companies including British Gas of overcharging loyal customers , saying those that had never switched from Britain's former monopoly gas supplier paid on average £75.50 more for their gas each year.
Separate analysis by think-tank the IPPR on Tuesday suggested the company charged its most loyal customers £89 a year more than those who had switched supplier.
]]></text></news-item>