<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTY-P8G1-JB4F-Y4RS"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Aldridge Minerals will appoint President</title><source>News Bites Canadian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Aldridge Minerals will appoint Han Ilhan as President. The effective date is April 07, 2014.
Resignation:
Recent TradingAldridge Minerals (AGM.TSXV) MCap is CAD22.9 million (US$20.4 million) at the last price of 27.0c. The value of CAD1,000 invested one year ago is CAD587 [vs CAD1,152 for the S&P/TSX 60 Index], for a capital loss of CAD413. The total return to shareholders for 1 year is -41.3%.
Original AnnouncementAldridge Announces Appointment of New President and CEOTORONTO, March 25, 2014 - Aldridge Minerals Inc. (TSX Venture: AGM) ("Aldridge" or the "Company") is pleased to announce the appointment of Han Ilhan as President and Chief Executive Officer, effective as of April 7, 2014.Mr. Ilhan is a highly regarded mining executive with capabilities spanning the entire mine life cycle from scoping, exploration, feasibility, licensing & permitting, design, construction, supply chain, commissioning, financial management, management of operations, maintenance, and reclamation. Mr. Ilhan joins Aldridge from an international mining company with operations in Turkey where he served as Vice President of Projects and Country Manager of Turkey Operations.Mr. Ilhan is a professional engineer and earned his Bachelor of Civil Engineering from Bogazici University in Istanbul, Turkey and Master of Geotechnical Engineering at Oregon State University. Prior to his most recent position, Han spent 26 years in progressive engineering, management, and leadership roles at URS Corporation ("URS"), a leading provider of engineering, construction, and technical services for public agencies and private sector companies around the world. Mr. Ilhan was most recently the Vice President and Director of Global Mining Business at URS, where he provided engineering and environmental services to the mining industry in over 20 countries. His experience includes project identification, evaluation, planning, and development, with a strong emphasis on environmental risk minimization and sustainable development. His specific technical expertise in the mining industry includes engineering, environmental, social risk management, and technical planning in the design and construction of heap leach facilities, water supply and diversion systems, pollution prevention measures, waste storage facilities, and mine closure and reclamation projects."The Board was committed to finding an executive that not only brought extensive industry experience with a history of building and operating mines, but also had particular expertise with mine development in Turkey. After conducting an exhaustive search process, the Special Committee of the Board concluded that Han brings a unique skill set to the Company and is ideally suited to lead Aldridge through its critical next phases of development," said Barry Hildred, Chairman of Aldridge."I am honoured to have the opportunity to lead Aldridge, a company I have known and admired for many years," said Mr. Ilhan. "This is an exciting time for the Company and I look foreword to working with the management team and Board to unlock the significant value of the Yenipazar Project."Mr. Ilhan, who is fluent in both Turkish and English, will be based in Ankara, Turkey.Source: TMX Group
Currency Conversion: Canadian dollar CAD1= US$0.892 [or US$1=CAD1.12]; Against the US$ the CAD strengthened 8.98 basis points (or 0.1%) for the day; declined 0.9% for the week; weakened 0.8% for the month; dropped 7.5% in the past year. CAD1 = 100c.
ISIN: CA0144301029
V:AGM; CVE:AGM; CN:AGM;
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>