<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTY-HG91-JBVM-Y19J"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Will we body-conscious Brits worship at the altar of Lululemon?</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Celia Walden</author><text><![CDATA[Bottoms. A wall of bottoms. From my vantage point at the back of my Yogilates class in Beverly Hills, that's all I can see. They range from tight, sculpted and boyish to shelflike and Latina, and as they effect a series of sinuous movements to the left and to the right - surely pornographic in any other context - some are more graceful than others. They all, however, have one thing in common: a little white insignia, not dissimilar to a pert derriere, on the waistband. Out here in LA, Lululemon isn't just a sportswear brand: it's a status symbol, a lifestyle choice - a statement of intent.
Quite how you can state your intent with superior Silverescent Spandex is anyone's guess, but in La La Land ambitions begin and end with the relative tautness of your gluteus maximus. And nobody showcases that quite like Lululemon. Presumably this is why the Canadianborn heavyweight company with a market value of $7.1 billion (£4.3 billion) has chosen to open its first European outlet - a 3,100 square foot store in Covent Garden - this Friday in London, a city where bottoms have yet to be presented in their full glory.
Now, we Brits may be more fashion-conscious in our health-consciousness than ever before, shelling out up to £60 at Sweaty Betty for a pair of yoga pants, but are we really willing to upgrade to a pair of £108 "sweat-wicking two-way stretch and breathable" work-out trousers to walk the runway at our local Virgin Active? Tara Poseley, the chief product officer at Lululemon - who prefers to think of her customers as "guests" - thinks so. "Our guests lead busy, active lives," she says. "They're that friend who you count on for the best new coffee shop, restaurant, fitness class, and band. Their busy lifestyle means they value functional fashion and are looking for technically beautiful clothing that takes them from studio to street and back again."
Indeed Lululemon, founded in 1988, is a trailblazer in the kind of fitness wear that doesn't look any more out of place at brunch, on the terrace of the Ivy in LA, than it does at cocktail time in the snug at Chateau Marmont. I may find knocking back gin slings in a £45 neon "Power tank" and a pair of £52 "Hotty Hot Shorts" wrong on a quasi-moral level (I'm also not sure I can see it taking off at the Coach and Horses), but Lululemon's female and male devotees (the company's menswear is doing so well that it is to expand its line over the next two years) are the religious zealots of the work-out community. Sanctified by gym and yoga marathons earlier in the day, their outof-studio Lululemon gear is a testament to the purity of the lifestyle they uphold. After all, a little pair of gold dumbbells on a chain around one's neck isn't as agreeable to wear as the best-selling Luon leggings.
Like any religious following, Lululemon wearers like to feel that puritan living has earned them the privilege of belonging - and, also, wearing a premium product.
When, last July, the company was hit with a US lawsuit, accused of defrauding shareholders by hiding defects in batches of yoga pants so sheer that they led to a recall, Chip Wilson, Lululemon's billionaire founder and then chairman, sparked feminist fury by attributing the problem to deficiencies in his customers' bodies. "Quite frankly, some women's bodies just actually don't work," said the notoriously abrasive Canadian. "It's about the rubbing through the thighs, how much pressure is there over a period of time and how much they use it."
Because Wilson doesn't make leggings larger than a size 12 (a UK 16), his comments were deemed exclusionary. A writer for Time magazine swiftly informed Wilson that "if you keep espousing the philosophy that only skinny people can buy your pants, you're going to lose a lot of money". However, this, Forbes magazine pointed out, "was a bit like warning BMW that if it continues selling cars only to rich people, it's going to lose a lot of money".
With an aspirational brand like Lululemon, profits were never going to be adversely affected by a little elitism. Although sheer leggings may no longer be a problem (to the general upset of women in my Beverly Hills Yogilates class, who don't spend three hours a day honing a body part only for it never to be seen) and Wilson no longer in situ as chairman, the Lululemon ethos remains the same: "elevating the world from mediocrity to greatness". I can only hope we Brits prove worthy.
Celia Walden
]]></text></news-item>