<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BTY-HG91-JBVM-Y3SF"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Want the kids to be a success? Then don't give them a penny</title><source>The Western Mail</source><author>ABBIE WIGHTWICK</author><text><![CDATA[THE youngest has a job walking a friend's dog, a service he sometimes contracts out to his older sister who sub-contracts to her younger sister.
Somehow, in the complexities of this arrangement, the pooch gets a stroll and everyone gets a sum of money they're happy with.
No-one gets extra tips for clearing up if the dog messes on the verge, it's just one of those things.
If you want to earn a crust, you have to take the rough with the smooth and keep focused on the money - not a bad lesson for any 11-year-old.
The sub-contractors have other business lines of their own.
The oldest babysits for enough cash to make the job appealing to an adult. Who wouldn't watch television and eat biscuits for four hours for £30 while two well-behaved small children sleep upstairs? The middle one volunteers in a charity shop, which everyone said was very noble of her, until she let slip it was to gain retail skills with a view to getting a well-paid weekend job as soon as she is old enough to do so.
She has her eye on various clothes shops with dim lighting whose stock is too pricey for her parents, more often to be seem modelling Matalan's latest. Another good reason to make more money than them.
Whatever the reason, I'm glad they all have hard-bargaining genes.
I credit their Scots-born father who has, for years, failed to convince them not to make unfair generalisations about people's birth place and attitude to cash.
I've long since ducked out of the annual pocket money claims.
With negotiations currently under way, the youngest was modelling himself on the late Bob Crow, who impressed him with a recent radio interview just before his recent, untimely, passing.
The son's current claim runs along the lines of - you can't discriminate against people because they are younger but do the same job.
The job, he explained, was being the pocket money-payer's child, a role that bore equal weight whether you were 11, 14 or 16, especially as the 16-year-old slams more doors, fills the dishwasher less often and uses more hot water, while the 14-year-old eats more biscuits and plays two musical instruments, twice the price of his one.
Acting as mediator, spiritual adviser and squash-pourer, I sit in smokey rooms - toast always gets forgotten and burns during negotiations - and try pouring oil on troubled waters.
"My client believes it is irrelevant that his sisters will leave home before him and he'll get pocket money for longer," I say with one hand on the lemon squash, another on the son's shoulder.
"He points out that as he is five years younger than the oldest and three years younger than the second, who were young during rosier economic times, he should get proportionately more as inflation is running at 4%, if you read the right news items online.
"Since he was born the economy has suffered the dot com crash and the gloom of austerity Britain. The price of football magazines, cards and other soccer-related paraphenalia has risen by a greater percentage than the rise you are offering, which would leave him at a disadvantage and worse off than those who went before him.
"Do you want him to hold his own during schoolyard discussions on the January transfer window, or would you rather he had his head kicked in? No, that is no exaggeration, don't you know it's tough out there?" Occasionally rival companies (his sisters) pop in to stake their claims which centre on the mounting cost of being a teenager under George Osborne's financial regime.
"We can't vote so it must be your fault," they shriek, risking electrocution trying to dig burning embers from the toaster with knives."
It's no use pointing out we exist on burned offerings thanks to Mr O, who didn't get his job thanks to us. The masses are unstoppable.
This entrepreneurial spirit and political awareness may be tiring, especially after a day at the keyboard face, but at least it shows we must be doing something right.
A wealthy doctor friend recently complained his children don't have the hunger he did, as a working class son of a miner, to do well.
We're not miners but we're not doctors either, so the kids will need to be a bit peckish, which judging by knives lost down the toaster they are.
So, good luck to super-rich 'Kitchen King' John Roberts who has told his children he's leaving his £500m www.AO.com fortune to charity for their own good.
Roberts, CEO of www.AO.com, made £500m when he sold the electronics business he co-founded.
Since the company was founded it has risen to take a 24% share of the online market for major domestic appliances in the UK and was valued at £12bn when listed on the London Stock Exchange last month.
Roberts, a 40-year-old, who left school with no qualifications (shh, don't tell the kids), says his five children will get nothing and he wants them to be 'happy' and 'normal' in whatever careers they choose.
He's leaving the money to charity as an inheritance of millions could have a bad affect on his children's careers and how others view them, he believes.
I'll leave them to argue that one among themselves, but I bet it'll involve a few of his toasters being thrown, not to mention knives.
Other parents wanting their off-spring to make their own way include Bill and Melinda Gates who have vowed not to leave their £46bn Microsoft fortune to their teenage children and actor Sean Connery, who says son Jason won't inherit any of his www.millions.TV chef Nigella Lawson is also reported not to want to pass her fortune on to her brood and Body Shop founder Anita Roddick died in 2007 without leaving her fortune to her daughters. What did they all do wrong? Viewed from their position, I am a financial failure as I'll be happy to pass on whatever is under the mattress when I turn my toes up (a few odd socks and a ball of cat fur at the last count).
If money prevents happiness and normality, why don't all these rich people give away their cash now? I'll risk misery and abnormality if any of them want my bank account number.
]]></text></news-item>