<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-HN01-DYJJ-P565"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Cleanup of oil spill will be 'tricky,' expensive</title><source>The Cincinnati Enquirer (Ohio)</source><author>By, Staff Report</author><text><![CDATA[Cleanup continues this week after crude oil spilled from an underground pipeline into a stream and marshy pond in a western Colerain Township nature preserve March 17.
The spill didn't injure anyone and has been contained to the spill site.
State and federal EPA officials are overseeing the cleanup of an estimated 10,000 gallons of crude oil from the 20-inch Mid-Valley pipeline, which has been shut down.
Colerain Township Safety Services Director Dan Meloy says the township is assisting. The command center for the agencies was set up at nearby Dravo Park, which means the soccer fields are not available for use. Colerain Fire Capt. Steve Conn is serving as an information officer for the incident, and updates from the daily 10 a.m. briefings are posted on the Colerain Township website at www.colerain.org and on the township's Facebook page.
"We want to make sure information is available for our residents," he said.
The pipeline was laid in the mid-1950s, well before the land was identified as one of four "conservation areas" owned and operated by Great Parks of Hamilton County, which has pieced together the preserve over recent decades. Great Parks' website describes the 364-acre park as "rugged hills with a rich diversity of native trees, shrubs and wildflowers."
A spill "could definitely have been worse later in the spring when all of our wildlife is coming out of hibernation," said Bob Mason, stewardship manager with Great Parks. "Plus, now the ground is still hard, still somewhat frozen, so that helps."
After springing from the earth, the oil ran about half of a mile down a stream into a marshy pond, just west of East Miami River Road.
Even if some of the "sweet crude" - a lighter, thinner oil than sour crude - makes its way into the nearby Great Miami, regional drinking water will not be threatened because water treatment plants are located upstream on the Great Miami in Fairfield and upstream on the Ohio River from where the Great Miami feeds into it, said Greater Cincinnati Water Works spokeswoman Michele Ralston.
Hamilton County Public Health Department spokesman Mike Samet said the water samples taken from wells in the area showed there was no oil contamination to the drinking water. The health department will monitor the water sites while operations continue at the spill site.
Residents who have questions concerning the quality of their drinking water are encouraged to contact the Hamilton County Public Health Department on their hotline at 513-946-7808.
Steve Renninger from the US Environmental Protection Agency said March 20 that a repair plan has been formulated by Sunoco Logistics and will be submitted to the Department of Transportation for approval. The DOT provides oversight for the investigation and the agency's approval is needed before repairs can be made at the site.
Federal records show inspectors last checked the pipeline in 2011; the records do not include any current or ongoing inspections.
The leak was discovered by Gary M. Broughton, who was driving down East Miami River Road about 8 p.m. March 17 and smelled a "fuel, oily smell." He got out of his vehicle and saw oil spread across the marshy pond.
"It's absolutely terrible," Broughton told the 911 dispatcher. "It made me sick when I saw it."
Nearby residents later told authorities they had smelled a fuel-like odor, but neither the Hamilton County Dispatch Center nor the Southwest Ohio Air Quality Agency received reports of the smell prior to Broughton's call, officials said.
Ron and Sharon Worsley live on a 55-acre farm next to the nature preserve.
Sharon Worsley said she has smelled the oil since the end of last week but thought it was from her husband pouring diesel into his tractor. The smell hasn't bothered her much, she said.
Her husband said he thought the smell seemed stronger Tuesday morning. The couple said they don't have any concerns about the pipeline leak.
"I wouldn't want to be swimming in it," Ron Worsley said, "but these things happen."
Who's involved?
A Unified Command has been established with U.S. EPA, Ohio EPA, Colerain Township, Great Parks of Hamilton County and Sunoco Logistics/Mid-Valley.
State and local agencies which are providing assistance during the emergency include the Hamilton County Department of Environmental Services, the Hamilton County Emergency Management Agency, the Hamilton County Public Health Department and the Ohio Department of Natural Resources.
]]></text></news-item>