<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-RSW1-JDN8-20MR"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Medicine for the soul; Q&amp;a with Dustin Thomas</title><source>The Daily Mercury and Rural Weekly (Mackay, Queensland)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[YOUR debut album, Mountain High, is dedicated to the Fukushima nuclear power plant disaster. How do you ensure the album is still uplifting?
Hope is all about facing hardships.
When I think about the millions of gallons of nuclear wastes streaming into our oceans, I don't think of it with fear or panic, but as an opportunity for mankind to start engaging this beautiful planet with harmony, and using our resources and energy to purify these waters and save our oceans and coasts.
The few tricked the hearts of the many, and many of us forgot that water is life and that the ocean and her creatures are crucial to our human existence on this planet. Now there is no more time for compromise.
Awareness can bring activation. Let's see what humankind can actually accomplish.
All I can speak of is what I've seen and experienced. This world is beautiful, her potential is limitless but the future of her creatures and resources are in peril and need protection.
Through music and an open heart I've had the opportunity to travel to many countries and encounter all sorts of different people. The one theme I can always speak to is this: people are naturally prone to love and look out for each other.
If given the chance, people want do the right thing. If given the tools and education, people would do everything in their power to maintain peace and make this world better
This current paradigm of separation and fear that is perpetuated by world media and corporately-purchased governments preys on the natural vulnerability of the people with separation, lies and illusion. Music is a key to unlock the doors or aggression, complacency, and sorrow.
Since I've been gifted this audience to travel and sing, I feel it is my obligation to speak to the people of Earth on the things I've seen.
Forgive all debts. Hire the brilliant scientists of the world to find solutions to manage resources and purify our waters and lands.
We're so excited. I'm sure anyone watching will feel us frothing. As far as sounds and songs that will be shared, people can expect to see my brother Nahko in full power, sharing stories of consciousness and empowerment, backed up by world music rhythms held down by our percussionist Hope Medford and epic guitar riffs from Australian-raised Chase Makai. I'll be holding down the bass grooves and all four of us sing. Rumour has it another Aussie native might join us on drums. The only guarantee is musical medicine.
I'll be touring with Medicine for the People in Australia and then heading back for a USA summer tour in mid-May. We will then be planning our next Australian tour sometime in late 2014/early 2015.
]]></text></news-item>