<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-YH91-DYS4-D0T0"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Human Rights Ombudsman in Kazakhstan concerned about social tensions in ArcelorMittal Temirtau</title><source>Kazakhstan General Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Kazakhstan's Office of Human Rights Ombudsman recommends the management of ArcelorMittal Temirtau to act on preventing social tensions within the company.
"Given the current situation, the national human rights institution has drawn the attention of ArcelorMittal Temirtau management to "the need of taking further measures to prevent social tensions in line with constitutional rights and interests of workers," said the office in a Wednesday statement.
The statement refers to media reports about the unresolved labor relations and discussions about the staff reduction.
Thus, according to the press release, "First Vice Minister of Industry and New Technologies Albert Rau said in the Parliament that the discriminatory actions of the company's management, in particular, a pay discrimination among workers of different categories and cancellation of free summer camps for workers' children lead to social unrest."
In 2013, the Office of Ombudsman together with the Zhaktau Trade Union and employees studied the situation at the plant and found evidences of the violations of workers' rights such as personnel cuts on the back of a discrepancy between the staffing table and actual number of workers and failures to meet requirement for heath and safety requirements and working hours.
"According to the recent information, it is obvious that many of the pointed out problems have not been resolved yet, which is not helpful to easing social tensions at the enterprise," said the office in the statement
The institution of the Ombudsman, though, agreeing on the need to maintain a balance between economic aspects and labor rights, reminded of the priority of basic human rights established by the Constitution.
ArcelorMittal Temirtau (formerly Ispat Karmet), the largest steel plant in Kazakhstan, is part of Arcelor Mittal, the world's largest steel company. The group acquired the Kazakh plant in mid 1990s and made it a fully integrated metal combine. The company owns 8 coalmines in the Karaganda Region and 4 metal ore mines in the Karaganda, Akmola and Kostanai regions.
]]></text></news-item>