<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-Y6W1-JDK3-90F7"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Kelly McParland: B.C. Speaker is sorry for helping herself to the public trough. Sort of</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Speaker of British Columbia's provincial legislature isn't sorry she billed the province to fly her husband to South Africa, business class, where she photographed him petting a giraffe.
She is sorry if helping herself to the public treasury upset anyone. Or, as she put it( http://www.canada.com/business/Speaker+Linda+Reid+billed+taxpayers+thousands+business+class+flights/9660116/story.html ) Tuesday, "If this has caused anyone any consternation I sincerely apologize."
Similarly,Louise Mailloux,( http://news.nationalpost.com/2014/03/14/jewish-group-accuses-parti-quebecois-candidate-of-spreading-kkk-anti-semitic-conspiracy-theory/ ) who is a Parti Quebecois candidate in the Montreal riding of Gouin, isn't sorry for suggesting Jews and Muslims were part of a secret cabal to cheat people by charging a phony fee to declare food either kosher or halal. But she did express regret if identifying Jews and Muslims as thieves offended anyone.
"I never wanted to offend or hurt anyone," she said after her bizarre claim started getting her in trouble. "If that has happened, I very sincerely apologize."
@ReidforBC, TwitterGuess what folks: You're paying for this.
Who's next in line, Vladimir Putin? "Look, I never intended to upset people by seizing the Crimea, chasing out the Ukrainians and arbitrarily declaring it to be part of Russia. I don't plan to give it back, but if that offends anyone, I sincerely apologize. Not."
The case of the B.C. Speaker, Linda Reid, bears obvious similarities to the disgrace and fall( http://news.nationalpost.com/2014/03/19/alison-redford-resigns-as-premier-of-alberta/ )of Alberta Premier Alison Redford. In Reid's case, the South African trip was to attend a meeting of the Commonwealth Parliamentary Conference. The Commonwealth is a collection of states with historic links to Britain that is sometimes disparaged as a pleasant but largely anachronistic social club. Prime Minister Stephen Harper skipped( http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/harper-s-sri-lankan-boycott-includes-swipe-at-commonwealth-1.1928342 ) the most recent Commonwealth summit, in Sri Lanka, to protest that government's human rights policies. The Queen also( http://www.cbc.ca/news/world/prince-charles-gets-higher-commonwealth-role-as-queen-stays-home-1.1342380 ) bowed out, pleading age, sending Prince Charles in her place.
Reid, like Redford, evidently likes to travel, as long as it's not on her own dime. Since becoming Speaker in April 2013, according to the Vancouver Sun,( http://www.canada.com/business/Speaker+Linda+Reid+billed+taxpayers+thousands+business+class+flights/9660116/story.html ) she has visited London, Scotland, Ottawa, California, Oregon and Washington, all at public expense. When the Sun started asking questions about the South African trip, and her husband's bills, she went into full evasion mode, much as did Redford.
First, the Sun reported, she suggested there was no problem taking a passenger along if it didn't increase the overall cost of the trip. Two hours later she called a snap press conference, admitted she'd also claimed for her husband's hotel and other expenses, and had flown business class despite an order by Finance Minister Mike de Jong. She said she'd repay $5,500.
Even then she tried to excuse her actions.
"The policy that we're hopefully going to have some more conversation about at finance and audit [committee] says if you can take a second person for the price of a single ticket, that has been the practice here for a long, long time," she told The Sun.
Right. Hey look, other people have been doing this forever. So why shouldn't I?
THE CANADIAN PRESS/Chris YoungRob Ford: maybe I should just apologize in advance, for anything I might get up to tonight.
It's not news that political figures have immense problems keeping their hands out of the cookie jar. Mr. Harper spent most of last year trying to dodge, denounce or explain away the rapacious approach several of his Senate appointees took towards their perceived entitlements. We have yet to receive a sincere apology from any of those figures either, though we've heard much from them about how badly they've been treated by a government that washed its hands of them after discovering it couldn't sweep them all under some convenient rug. We did get an apology( http://www.timescolonist.com/news/national/so-sorry-etc-a-partial-list-of-rob-ford-s-apologies-1.844928 ) from Toronto Mayor Rob Ford; several, in fact - for cursing out reporters, for smoking crack cocaine, for getting "hammered" a lot and threatening to kill people, for almost trampling a fellow council member and for suggesting a city hall reporter was a pedophile, among other things - but that didn't stop him from carrying on in much the same vein. He's just sorry it bugs people.
Sincere regret appears to be outside the skill set of most politicians. Maybe they fear voters wouldn't know how to react if they actually confessed to having acted foolishly, and accepted the blame. "What an idiot - I should never have taken my husband along on a freebie to South Africa. Wasting money on an unnecessary junket for myself was bad enough; I shouldn't have compounded it by trying to slip him in on the public dime. I made a mistake. I'm sorry."
Are they afraid we'd all fall over dead from the shock? OMG look, a semi-honest politician. Quick Muriel, fetch the smelling salts.
We'll likely never find out. I apologize if that offends anyone.
National Post
]]></text></news-item>