<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-8VH1-JD6S-R2SF"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Disability suit filed in Madelia woman 's case; Staples Enterprises denies allegations</title><source>The Free Press (Mankato, Minnesota)</source><author>Josh Moniz, JMONIZ@MANKATOFREEPRESS.COM</author><text><![CDATA[ST. JAMES - A Madelia woman has filed a lawsuit accusing Staples Enterprises and Staples Oil Co., both of Windom, and their owner Brent Staples of discriminating against her because of her disability.
According to the complaint in the lawsuit, Brenda Mosser has epilepsy but she was still capable of fulfilling her work duties as the customer service representative for the Madelia convenience store purchased in 2009 by Staples.
In August 2010, she tripped on a carpet and suffered a workplace injury, resulting in a laceration on her right elbow. The complaint alleges Staples believed the fall was caused by Mosser's disability, despite her assertion it was a normal accident and a lack of medical evidence. According to the suit, Staples allegedly told Mosser's manager "Why do we have a person with such a messed up life working here?"
The company has filed a response the suit denying the allegations.
Mosser allegedly told hospital staff she was concerned Staples would fire her if she filed a workers' compensation claim. She alleges Staples tried to impede her from filing a claim by sternly suggesting she submit her medical bills to her own insurance.
In September 2010, the store was merged with another Madelia store. During that month, Mosser was terminated after being allowed to return to work for a few days. She was the only employee fired from the store during the merger, with "lack of work" cited as the reason for the firing, despite the company subsequently hiring two new employees, according to the complaint.
The complaint alleges the two new hires were less experienced than Mosser and that Staples failed to cooperate with the Minnesota Department of Human Rights investigation in the experience level of the new employees.
Mosser filed a complaint with the department in August 2011. The department concluded its investigation in January 2013, concluding there was probable cause for Mosser's discrimination claim.
According to the department investigation report, Staples said the two new employees were hired based on their experience on the day he purchased the merged store. When asked to detail the experience of the new hires, Staples told the investigator the employee records from merged store's former ownership were unavailable.
When asked how he was able to verify their experience without records, Staples representative allegedly refused to answer any further questions. The report also noted that information provided by Staples refuted his statements on when he hired the new employees.
Mosser's lawsuits charges Staples and his businesses with violating the Minnesota Human Rights Act and the Minnesota Workers' Compensation Act. She is seeking damages in an amount greater than $50,000 and punitive damages as deemed appropriate by the court.
In the response filed by Staples this month, he denied both Mosser's allegations and the conclusion of the Minnesota Department of Human Rights. He also asserted that Staples Enterprises owned the convenience store, but denied that he and Staples Oil Co. owned the store.
]]></text></news-item>