<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-Y0H1-DY37-401N"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Discord over sex traffic victims</title><source>Sarasota Herald Tribune (Florida)</source><author>J. DAVID McSWANE and ZAC ANDERSON Staff Writers</author><text><![CDATA[LEGISLATURE: Bills aimed at protecting children worry reform advocates
TALLAHASSEE -- The debate over how Florida should rescue and treat child sex trafficking victims is now sharply focused in the state house, where two competing bills could profoundly change how police and child welfare agencies place and treat victims.
Both bills call for more safe houses and new protocols for police and child welfare agencies, but despite those widely supported changes, both bills are likely to face opposition by the very advocates who have been calling for reform.
The major sticking point for child welfare advocates: The bills would allow the state to place some victims in so-called "secure facilities," heavily monitored and restrictive placements akin to those that keep many of Florida's juvenile offenders.
Those in support of a so-called "lockdown" approach point to cases in which children who developed psychological bonds with the traffickers ran away from safe houses or foster homes to return to their abusers. Prosecutors across the state have said they have lost cases because of the difficulty of keeping key witnesses safe, while the Department of Children and Families has faced political backlash when children under its care ran away.
"We want to cocoon them in treatment," said Rep. Gayle Harrell, R-Stuart, chair of the House Healthy Families Subcommittee, which drafted and passed its bill earlier this month.
Another trafficking bill, filed by Rep. Erik Fresen, R-Miami, calls for an automatic five-day confinement of children found to be victims of sex trafficking. During that assessment period, HB 1071 would require mental health specialists and case workers to determine if children should be placed in a less restrictive home.
There is broader bipartisan support behind the committee bill. That bill, HFS 14-02, calls for a small subset of victims with extreme symptoms and needs -- those who could not be treated by specialized foster homes or safe houses -- to be placed in a secure facility as part of a pilot program.
The bill's sponsors say the pilot program will be monitored by the DCF and the Department of Juvenile Justice to see if it could be a viable long-term solution.
"It is not incarceration by any stretch of the imagination," Harrell said. "They will receive therapy. They will receive a warm, loving environment."
The flurry of anti-trafficking bills filed this year are a direct response to advocates who, in recent years, have said the state fails to protect children who were manipulated, coerced and forced into the sex trade -- systematically treating them as criminals instead of victims.
The need for change
The need for systemic changes have been increasingly evident even after the 2012 passage of the landmark Safe Harbor Act, which established the need for safe houses and re-identified so-called "child prostitutes" not as delinquents, but as victims.
But some advocates say placement in a secure facility is tantamount to a jail sentence, which would further victimize trafficked children.
"It mirrors what happened to her in trafficking," said Lawanda Ravoira, president and CEO of the Delores Barr Weaver Policy Center, a Jacksonville-based child advocacy group.
"When we involuntarily place her, we tell her that she can't trust adults. It reinforces what the trafficker told her, that if you tell, you're going to get locked up.
"Florida is really going backwards if this passes."
Ravoira was among those advocates who helped stall an identical committee bill in the Senate, in which members of the Children, Families and Elder Affairs committee expressed concerns over locking up victims.
The committee tabled its bill, leaving it up to House sponsors to make changes and muster support in the Senate.
Sen. Nancy Detert, R-Venice, says she is struggling to strike a balance between ensuring victims can be stabilized under state care, but also ensuring victims are not further harmed by their care.
"It's a hard decision because these kids are kind of brainwashed, and they run away and go right back to the same lifestyle," Detert said.
"Child advocates think it's terrible that we're locking up kids, and it certainly sounds bad. But we've had some bad experiences where they've recruited other kids, just some bad experiences."
Detert says she expects leaders in the House to make amendments to appease advocates and legislators skeptical of secure facilities, but she expects those will be minor language clarifications to ensure the pilot program is carefully monitored.
Trudy Novicki, a former state prosecutor who authored the Safe Harbor Act, said she shares the fears of advocates that secure facilities could do more harm than good.
But Novicki says she sees the need for some special type of center or home for chronic runaways and children wracked with immense psychological trauma.
"Some of these children do need a secure psychiatric bed," said Novicki, director of Kristi House, a child advocacy center in Miami that specializes in treating trafficking victims.
"I think the advocates that I've talked to that are just totally opposed to the bill; their point is that it's a slippery slope," she added. "And if you start with it, it's just going to keep snowballing into a secure facility approach."
The fear of widespread incarceration of child victims has galvanized some advocates who are lobbying legislators to toss the bills entirely.
Among them is the Tallahassee-based Children's Campaign, whose policy letters are calling the bills a "Return to Unsafe Harbor."
Lynn Osgood, the campaign's spokeswoman, says her group sees the issue in simpler terms: these children are child abuse and rape victims.
"In Florida, we don't lock up child abuse victims or rape victims," she said.
ONLINE:
To read the Herald-Tribune's special report about sex trafficking in Florida, go to http://thestolenones. heraldtribune.com.
]]></text></news-item>