<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-XBK1-JBF5-T1GB"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>FRACK PROTESTERS 'NON-COMPLIANT'</title><source>Regional Press Releases: London</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Demonstrators were passive, non-compliant and had to be physically taken away from where they were sat after being arrested during anti-fracking protests, a court heard at the trial of several people, including one from north-east London.
Ruth Jarman, one of the defendants on trial alongside Green MP Caroline Lucas, refused to comply with an officer's instructions when she was arrested, ``went limp and lifeless'' and had to be carried away, Brighton Magistrates' Court was told.
Lucas, from Brighton; Jarman, from Hook, Hampshire; Ruth Potts, from Totnes, Devon; Josef Dobraszczyk, 22, from Bristol; and Sheila Menon, 42, from north-east London, all deny wilful obstruction of the highway and breaching Section 14 of the Public Order Act.
Footage showed Jarman, 50, refusing to respond to police requests when she was separated from a group of people who had linked arms and were sat in the emergency entrance to Cuadrilla's exploratory drilling site in Balcombe, West Sussex.
The court heard from Pc Alan Harris, a Sussex Police officer who said he arrested Jarman and 39-year-old Potts.
He told the court he had spoken to several protesters and had given them time to discuss whether they were going to move to an area designated by police for protest.
Pc Harris said he explained the offences they might be committing and added that if they did not comply they risked arrest.
He said Potts was arrested and did not say anything as she was escorted away, although police footage showed her saying: ``We have not come to a decision yet.''
The court also heard Pc Harris's description of Jarman, which was different to her appearance on the police DVD.
Leon Jennings, health, safety, security and environment director for Cuadrilla, said drilling activities were halted during the height of the protests because police advised that the firm was unlikely to get vehicles on and off the site.
He told the court that even though there was a reduction in Cuadrilla staff, there were 27 security staff on site and police officers who needed to be provided with fresh food and water and toilet facilities, and that deliveries of fresh supplies still needed to be made.
He said he and his staff were subjected to ``intimidation'' and ``scaremongering'' by some of the protesters throughout their time at the site but that he did not have a problem with anyone making a peaceful protest.
Tom Wainwright, representing Lucas and Potts, said: ``You were thoroughly fed-up ... certainly by the end of the operation in September, with the fact there were protests going on outside.''
Mr Jennings said: ``Peaceful protest is a human right and we accept that. As soon as we start to get abuse to staff it's a different situation, and staff were intimidated and upset by that.''
Mr Wainwright said: ``You have exaggerated the behaviour of those protesting because of how you feel about them, haven't you?''
Mr Jennings replied: ``Not at all.'' end
]]></text></news-item>