<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-D8X1-JD3N-53T4"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Have your say</title><source>The Advertiser (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Blinkered view TAKE off your blinkers for a moment Nicolle Flint ("Week free of meat will cut industries to the bone", The Advertiser, 25/3/14), and consider the facts.
People who don't eat meat still have to eat and will be supporting Riverland fruit growers, Eyre Peninsula wheat growers, Virginia market gardeners - the list goes on.
We support these farmers wholeheartedly, as well the people who harvest, transport and sell this food. It is a fact that high meat consumption causes ill-health.
Only a few days ago the Body and Soul liftout of the Sunday Mail (23/3/14) featured an article entitled "Ditch meat to reduce blood pressure".
It was based on a study in the Journal of the American Medical Association, surely a more reliable source of information than Sam Kekovich, as quoted by Ms Flint.
A United Nations report on climate change calculated that livestock are responsible for one-fifth of all human-generated greenhouse gases - more than all transport sectors combined.
Eating less or no meat is the environmentally responsible option. A plant-based diet is better for us and the planet, and still needs farmers to produce food.
SUZANNE POPE, St Morris.
Not just money WHAT a heartless opinion piece by Nicolle Flint (The Advertiser, 25/3/14). Animal protection society Voiceless is totally justified in asking consumers to think about how eating meat impacts on animals.
This is because animals are not blocks of stone; they are living, feeling beings with the same capacity for suffering as ourselves.
Cows, sheep, pigs etc don't want to be violently and prematurely killed any more than we do.
What's more, they don't deserve to be, because humans are not natural carnivores and thus have absolutely no need of animal flesh in their diet.
As a vegan of 35 years I can vouch for this.
Ms Flint urges us to eat meat this week because it will enable the animal exploiters to make more money.
Well, if life is simply about making money, this would make sense. But if we have a higher goal - to treat all beings with respect and compassion - it makes no sense whatsoever.
JENNY MOXHAM, Monbulk, Vic.
Direct action JESSICA Irvine ignores a host of inconvenient facts (The Advertiser, yesterday). Despite the large increase in the amount of greenhouse gases entering the atmosphere, overall world temperatures, as measured by a range of instruments and reported in the last IPCC Report, have been stable for about 17 years. In fact some data show a slight cooling.
There have been record hot spells in Australia, but there also have been record cold spells and severe blizzards in the Northern Hemisphere over the past five years.
The year 2013 saw the coldest temperature ever recorded at Antarctica. The models did not predict these widespread and severe cold conditions and no adequate explanation has been offered.
Jessica does not mention that the funding of direct action is capped at less than $1 billion per year and unlike a carbon tax has environmental advantages, including improvements in farm soils and extensive tree planting.
STEPHEN TURNER, Mannum.
Underpaid I READ with interest the letter "Corruption bloom" (The Advertiser, 25/3/14) and wholeheartedly agree. Our Chinese niece was recently offered employment at a city dumpling cafe for $8/hour. Sensibly, she turned it down.
I hope that the Fair Work inspectors continue to visit these establishments to ensure employers meet their legalrequirements towards employees.
JULIE HOUSE, Brompton.
Crusader Abbott WILL Tony Abbott reintroduce jousting and crusades for his new knights?TONY QUICK, Sellicks Beach.
]]></text></news-item>