<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-5DG1-JBG7-419Y"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Bankruptcy shields GM from lawsuits; Despite admitting to fatal defect, firm protected from liability in pre-insolvency crashes</title><source>Chicago Tribune</source><author>By Jerry Hirsch, Tribune Newspapers; Tribune Newspapers' David Undercoffler contributed.</author><text><![CDATA[Margie Beskau would seem to have a strong lawsuit against General Motors for millions in damages.
Eight years ago, her 15-year-old daughter, Amy Rademaker, died in a Chevrolet Cobalt -- one of the cars the automaker has now admitted had a deadly safety defect.
A faulty ignition switch shut off the car on a Wisconsin road, leaving its teen driver without power steering, brakes or air bags.
But Beskau probably will never collect in the civil courts, legal experts say, because GM has been absolved of all responsibility for crashes before the automaker's 2009 bankruptcy and federal bailout. That's despite the automaker's public apologies and its recall of 1.6 million vehicles to fix ignition switches.
GM has acknowledged 12 deaths were caused by the problem. But the Center for Auto Safety, an advocacy group, estimates that number could be more than 300.
More than half those wrecks occurred before GM's 2009 bankruptcy, according to an analysis the center performed.
"They should be liable for Amy's death," Beskau said. "They lied to everybody; they covered up the problem. They put anybody who bought the car or who -- like my daughter -- rode in the car at risk."
The automaker confirmed that the post-bankruptcy GM bears no liability for accidents before its legal reinvention. Bankruptcy and product liability experts agree.
As in many corporate bankruptcies, GM's legal slate was wiped clean. The U.S. government brokered the transaction as part of a historic bailout to save the company from collapse. "GM completely threw all product liability claimants under the bus," said Steve Jakubowski, a Chicago bankruptcy attorney.
The crash that killed Beskau's daughter and another teen, Natasha Weigel, took place on a Wisconsin road in 2006. The ignition switch in a 2005 Cobalt driven by 17-year-old Megan Phillips slipped out of the "on" position, shutting off the power steering, power brakes and air bags. Phillips lost control of the car, striking a telephone junction box and two trees. The air bags failed. The passengers were killed and Phillips suffered lasting injuries.
Only recently -- as GM recalled cars during the past six weeks -- did Beskau and the families of the other victims in the accident become aware that GM knew of the problem and had failed to fix it.
The families filed a wrongful death and injury suit against the automaker last week, after learning about federal investigations into GM's actions -- and documents showing the automaker knew about the ignition switch problem before the bankruptcy. But it hinges on convincing the original bankruptcy judge that the company defrauded the court by withholding information about the safety defect.
The case is a long shot, attorneys said. "They just won't do it," Jakubowski said. "I can't fathom a bankruptcy court now saying it would have any interest in revisiting the judgment to alter it or revoke it."
There's another way to force GM to pay the claims, said Sen. Richard Blumenthal, D-Conn. The federal government should pursue criminal charges against GM, he said.
"Bankruptcy provides no immunity from criminal prosecution," Blumenthal said. "The Department of Justice has enormous leverage to require the establishment of a fund for compensating victims, just as it did with Toyota."
GM has disputed the estimate of more than 300 deaths.
"Without rigorous analysis, it is pure speculation to attempt to draw any meaningful conclusions," the automaker said in a statement.
jhirsch@tribune.com
ct14 0022 140326 R S 0000000000 00007392
]]></text></news-item>