<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-RSW1-JDN8-20J2"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>creating a sustainable future</title><source>The Northern Star and Rural Weekly (New South Wales)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[IS THE future looking bright for your children? Will they be able to live out their lives with plenty of food and water, good health and all those creature comforts we associate with modern life?
And what of their children? Will they look back in indulgent fashion grateful for the choices of their forebears or will they shake their heads with incredulity and anger wondering how we were able to muck it all up in such brilliant fashion?
The stark reality is that should we insist on continuing down this path where we are too lazy to recycle, can't be bothered about buying local, are happy to fill our homes with energy-gobbling electronic devices and turn a blind eye to waste, then it will be impossible for history to judge us kindly.
Natural resources such as water, minerals, oil and soil are finite entities - they can and will be depleted if care is not taken to aid their longevity. By 2050 the world will have to support and feed more than 9 billion people but how do you accomplish that in an environmentally friendly way when as it stands agricultural practices already make up 24% of global greenhouse gas emissions?
We need to look at the way we build our homes and cities, the way we manufacture motor vehicles and electronic goods, our farming methods and the way we plunder natural resources.
We need to pay more attention to conserving water, cutting down on energy use while securing alternative sources and empowering Third World nations so they can meet their own needs.
Global warming and climate change have been the buzzwords for the past decade with environmentalists, conservationists and scientists pushing the need for change to ensure long-term survival.
Research shows us that the world is warming at a rate unprecedented in human history and that changing global temperatures, humidity and rainfall patterns cannot be explained without the rise in greenhouse gases especially carbon dioxide caused by human activity.
Australia is one of the largest polluters on a per capita basis at four times the world average with energy use, transport and direct fuel combustion our major areas of concern.
We already face major challenges here in being the driest continent on Earth, in having limited water resources, in having a mostly coastal dwelling population and in having food production severely impacted on by extreme heat and drought. We are also the caretakers of some of the most important and vulnerable ecosystems in the world.
So the news from climate change scientists that by 2030 Australia will face up to 20% more drought, a further 1 degree warming in temperatures, a 25% increase in days of very high or extreme fire danger and increases in storm surges and severe weather events certainly does not bode well.
Of course there are climate change sceptics who dispute these findings saying that a warmer Earth is a natural process and not the cause of human activity but I for one am not willing to take the risk.
While the Australian Government cools its heels on taking any real effective measures to combat climate change, concerned individuals can make simple everyday choice to affect change.
Educate yourself about what it takes to live sustainably, grow your own vegetables if you can, source your food locally, recycle, invest in energy-saving appliances and turn them off at the plug when not in use, take shorter showers, use a fan instead of an air-conditioner, car pool, say no to plastic bags"¦
Small things can make a big difference - your children will thank you for it.
]]></text></news-item>