<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-GRW1-F11P-X4JK"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Contract-seeking IT boss faces R5m bribery charge</title><source>Daily News (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[An executive director of Pinnacle Holdings has been charged with offering a bribe to a senior police official in an attempt to win a contract, the police said yesterday, the news sending the company's shares down 25 percent.
The JSE said it was investigating whether Pinnacle violated rules on timely disclosure by waiting 20 days to announce the arrest of executive director Takalani Tshivhase.
"We are investigating the issue and will be posing some questions to the company," John Burke, the exchange's director of issuer regulation, said.
In the US, technology firm Net 1 UEPS Technologies has said it was being investigated by the US Department of Justice and the FBI over whether it made "corrupt payments" to South African government officials to win a contract with the national welfare agency.
The SAPS said Tshivhase allegedly offered the R5 million bribe to a lieutenant general in the police service to secure a multi-million rand contract for devices used in police investigations.
The 59-year-old, who has denied the charges, was arrested by the police's anti-|corruption unit earlier this month and released on bail the same day.
His court case has been postponed until April 24 to allow for further investigation, the police said.
Pinnacle confirmed the arrest in a statement yesterday, and said there was no reason |to doubt the veracity of Tshivhase's denial, based on the evidence available to it.
The announcement of the charges against Tshivhase came just days after Tshivhase sold R4 million worth of his Pinnacle shares.
The JSE declined to comment on whether it was investigating the timing of the sale.
Shares in Pinnacle, which manufactures and distributes information technology hardware and software, tumbled in the stock's biggest one-day fall for almost 11 years.
"It's very surprising that management thought this information was not relevant to shareholders," Nic Norman-Smith, chief investment officer at Lentus Asset Management in Johannesburg, said.
"On top of that, the close timing between quite a significant stock sale and the release |of the regulatory announcement is not helping sentiment."
Pinnacle chief executive Arnold Fourie said the charges against Tshivhase were based on a "huge misunderstanding".
Fourie said in an interview he also did not believe the company had breached rules on timely disclosure.
The company had waited until after Tshivhase had appeared in court on Monday before informing the market, Fourie said.
"He only appeared (in court) yesterday (Monday), so we could only get the details of |the charges after that," Fourie said.
"There was no information that would affect the company - the company's performance - and therefore it was not necessary" to disclose earlier, he said.
Fourie said he knew of Tshivhase's plans to sell shares before his arrest, and did not believe it constituted insider trading.
Police spokesman Paul Ram-aloko said Tshivhase allegedly offered the bribe to win a contract to supply the police force with electronic handheld devices used in police work.
The devices, which sell for R55 000, allow police in the field to check whether a person has |a criminal record.
They are also equipped |with fingerprint scanners, he said.
The SAPS were looking to acquire 3 000 of the terminals, Ramaloko said, which would value the contract at R165m.
"This arrest should serve as a reminder to companies doing business with the government that corruption is not an option in securing business deals," Anwar Dramat, the head of the police's anti-corruption unit, said. - Reuters
Daily News © 1999 - 2014 Independent Newspapers (Pty) Limited. All rights strictly reserved.
]]></text></news-item>