<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-RSW1-JDN8-20GX"><date>2014-03-27</date><title></title><source>The Northern Star and Rural Weekly (New South Wales)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Gas rebuttal
I WISH to respond to the misleading claims made by Metgasco in last Saturday's Northern Star.
In response to the claim it has been "without a reportable incident": in 2012 Metgasco was found to have been illegally dumping water from their drilling program into the Casino sewage treatment plant and was fined by the State Government regulator for breaches of their exploration licences.
In response to the claim they are drilling for conventional gas: it is known the gas is held in tight sands, which requires horizontal drilling and water-intensive fracking using chemicals known to be hazardous to human health.
In addition, the groundwater that Rous Water wants to use to supplement our water supply is in danger of contamination.
In response to the claim "many" in the community are concerned about the gas industry as the result of a scare campaign: the fact is a plebiscite in Lismore showed 87% of those who voted opposed the industry and the percentage of opposition is even higher in most of the surrounding rural villages.
The so-called scare campaign consists only of scientific findings and verifiable information, which is published on websites such as those of Lock the Gate and the National Toxics Network.
In response to the claim communities in Queensland have benefited from the industry: it is a fact water tables have dropped, cattle have been contaminated, forests have been fragmented and human health has suffered in the Tara gas fields.
The use of fly-in, fly-out workers housed in man-camps that meet their every need means communities have had little economic benefit from the industry.
The industry does not create as many jobs as it claims. In August 2013 the entire oil and gas industry employed 20,700 people, which is 0.2% of the workforce. To put this figure into context, Bunnings employs 33,000 people.
In response to the claim the industry will provide a clean energy supply: it is a fact the emissions involved in producing the gas, plus the environmental damage created by the expansion of gas fields means any greenhouse benefits of gas over coal or other fossil fuels may well be cancelled out.
Furthermore, as a recent report by The Australia Institute showed, the production of unconventional gas will do nothing to reduce domestic gas prices.
Jill Garsden,
Goonellabah.
]]></text></news-item>