<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-K381-JBM5-C0M2"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Landfill fire odors go on unabated Neighbors keep up online log.</title><source>St. Louis Post-Dispatch (Missouri)</source><author> By Blythe Bernhard bbernhard@post-dispatch.com 314-340-8129 </author><text><![CDATA[Last May, Kathy Bell and her husband took advantage of an offer to stay in a hotel for a few weeks to avoid odors from work being done on the Bridgeton Landfill. The day they got back, she said the stench was worse than before and had seeped inside their house in the Spanish Village neighborhood.
"It was the first time we had ever smelled it inside, and this was after the fix," Bell said. "It's totally changed our quality of life."
An underground fire has been smoldering at the Bridgeton Landfill for more than three years. The fire has stirred up noxious odors as well as concerns about the proximity of radioactive waste dumped at the adjacent West Lake Landfill. A year ago, Missouri Attorney General Chris Koster sued the landfills' owner, Republic Services, for environmental violations. Under a court injunction, Republic Services agreed to place a plastic cap on part of the landfill by Labor Day 2013 to help lessen the odors and tamp down the fire.
Nearby residents and workers say that after an initial improvement last fall, the smell got progressively worse during the winter. There have been no more offers of free hotel stays. The Attorney General's office has not imposed any fines against Republic Services, although an agreement allows for $10,000 a day if odor deadlines are not met. Residents think their only recourse is an odor complaint log maintained by the state Department of Natural Resources.
Bell has logged the most complaints, with 52. She said it was because she lives and works within one mile of the landfill.
"I don't believe it's doing any good. I'm just doing it because I want a record of it," she said.
The log, obtained through a public records request, contains 378 odor complaints since the smoldering was first reported in late 2010. That includes 335 that were entered after the cap was placed in August and as more people learned of the log. The complaints come from about 200 people, including 30 who are anonymous. They reflect that the stench has moved beyond an inconvenience to being blamed for nosebleeds, sore throats, headaches, nausea and asthma attacks. A sampling:
• Oct. 30, 2013: As soon as I got out of my car at work the stench nearly knocked me over. I still feel like I am on the verge of vomiting.
• Jan. 5: I have to shovel the driveway while breathing in this toxic cocktail. When will this end??!!
• March 8: My child looked at me and said "why do we live here? why can't we move?" How do you sell a condo with these horrendous odors?
Complaints came in on Halloween, Christmas Eve, New Year's Day and from as far away as Creve Coeur and St. Charles. There were nine complaints on Valentine's Day. The department was flooded with 39 complaints on Jan. 8, when an odor alert was in effect as workers made repairs to the landfill's gas extraction system. Cold temperatures delayed that work, according to Republic Services. Nine odor complaints came in during the first weekend of March.
Some of the complaints "may be part of a determined attempt to keep public attention on the site," said Richard Callow, a spokesman for Republic Services. Residents urge one another on a Facebook page dedicated to West Lake Landfill to fill out the online complaint form when they post about smelling the odor.
Monitors placed by the state Department of Natural Resources have recorded light, moderate and strong odors from various sites near the landfill in the last year. The odors peaked last April through June and spiked again in July, August and October before leveling off. There were a few days with odors above the environmental standard in December and early January, the latest available data. A spill of liquid runoff and extreme cold that compromised the flare system were blamed.
Several residents say the odors in March are the worst they can remember. Various maintenance issues have caused Republic Services to issue seven alerts for potential odors this month, including three on weekends.
"Obviously, the odors have gotten worse, and they're coming more frequently," said Karen Nickel, who lives near Pattonville High School in Maryland Heights and has logged 24 complaints. "What was supposed to be better has just become worse."
Nickel has lupus and said she was recently diagnosed with chronic sinus disease.
"As sick as I've been lately my doctor told me to stay away," Nickel said. "You try to avoid the area, but you can't avoid your home."
Federal and state health officials maintain that the odors pose no health risks beyond headache, nausea and fatigue. The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency repeatedly offers assurances that it is safe to live and work around the landfill. The state Department of Health and Senior Services reports no increase in emergency room visits linked to the landfill. The health department also reviews carbon monoxide and gamma radiation, which have remained at safe levels. Unhealthy levels of sulfur dioxide, hydrogen sulfide and benzene have not been detected since early last year.
Each odor complaint gets a response and is shared with Republic Services and the Attorney General's office, according to a spokeswoman for the Department of Natural Resources. Koster, the attorney general, has said he doesn't think fining Republic Services would be productive while the fire still burns. In a statement Friday, a spokeswoman for Koster said Republic Services would be assessed for public nuisance damages when the case is resolved.
In a similar situation in Ohio, state environmental regulators have fined Republic Services $10 million for violations related to underground fires at the company's Countywide Recycling and Disposal Facility. Neighborhoods around that landfill received $3 million for civic projects. The rest of the money went into an environmental protection fund to clean up abandoned landfills across the state.
Callow, the spokesman for Republic Services, said the company understood residents' frustrations and had spent "tens of millions" of dollars to tame the odors at the site. The cap has been successful in reducing odors by capturing more gas, he said.
An additional cap was placed, old pipes were removed and 40 new wells were installed to capture gas. Residents can expect further relief as the weather warms and a runoff treatment facility is completed, according to Callow.
Christen Commuso of Maryland Heights said she would continue to log odor complaints just as she has when smelling the landfill at home, inside her car and on several visits to her daughter's school, Rose Acres Elementary.
"It makes me sad. This is where I grew up. I wanted to raise my daughter here," she said.
]]></text></news-item>