<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-1SJ1-DYT4-K03N"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Kebble still plagues R&amp;E shareholders</title><source>Business Day (South Africa)</source><author>Dave Marrs</author><text><![CDATA[COMPANY COMMENT
Kebble still plagues R& E shareholders
IT HAS been years of legal strife for those holding shares in Randgold & Exploration (R& E), a company plundered by its then CEO, Brett Kebble. And the struggle continues as the incumbent directors try to recover monies and value stolen or destroyed by Kebble and others at the company.
Two battles remain that R& E and its shareholders have to fund. One is with PwC, the auditors at the time Kebble was siphoning R1bn or more from the JSE-listed company. The second wrangle involves Gold Fields, which bought Western Areas, a mining company that was also headed by Kebble.
Estimates of the theft from R& E vary from R1.2bn to nearly R20bn, depending on the method used to measure the loss of Randgold Resources shares and other assets. R& E has said shares it owned but were stolen by Kebble included 26.6-million London-listed Randgold Resources shares as well as JSE-traded DRDGold, Simmer & Jack and Aflease Gold shares. R& E has said these shares were sold by JCI, also headed by Kebble, to fund liabilities and continuing operations and to maintain financial stability.
The scale of the theft is astonishing, and it takes up much of the time and focus of R& E's directors. They see the company's assets as its cash of R201m and the pending legal claims, which could obviously be worth far more. R& E is selling off its prospecting rights because it cannot give them the attention SA's mining laws require. This raises the question of what R& E will become once the legal processes have run their course and there are few or no mineral rights left.
This is a tale of unfettered greed, corruption and theft on a scale that defies belief. And sadly, there is no end in sight.
NEWLY appointed Capitec CEO Gerrie Fourie will present the bank's results for the first time today. But the full-year figures Capitec releases should not be used to judge his performance at the Stellenbosch-based bank.
Mr Fourie's term as CEO and successor to Riaan Stassen only started in January. It is now up to Mr Fourie to articulate what he intends to do at the bank.
The market will want to hear about progress in delivering the promised virtual banking facilities, and how far the bank is from launching its mobile application.
Mr Fourie is now in charge of a bank that is no longer growing from a low base. He will need to explain that to the market, so that expectations can be managed. For instance, earnings are no longer growing above 20%, which had become the expectation.
Today the bank will release earnings growth figures of 12%-16% for the year ended February.
Mr Fourie will also have to give some guidance on how Capitec is likely to grow. The super high growth rates have now been left to new and smaller banks such as Finbond.
& 8226; edits Company Comment (marrsd@bdfm.co.za)
]]></text></news-item>