<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-78M1-DYRS-T02P"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>PG SUPPORT FOR THE DEER LAKES LEASE IS PREMATURE</title><source>Pittsburgh Post-Gazette</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[To paraphrase "Casablanca's" Captain Renault, I was "shocked, shocked" to read that the PG editorial board in its editorial "Prudent Drilling" (March 24) had determined that "The county has a good deal at Deer Lakes Park" and that "this lease . is carefully crafted and worthy of approval by county council." Unfortunately, given the economic realities of today's newspaper business, no regular reader of the PG should be surprised by this editorial.
However, as a member of Allegheny County Council - the body which according to the home rule charter has ultimate responsibility for all of the county's land use decisions - I can say categorically that as of Tuesday, neither I nor any of my colleagues had received legislation from the chief executive related to Deer Lakes Park, nor have we seen a lease. We have received a one-page press release which bears a striking resemblance to the PG's editorial. To be blunt, I wonder how you've made the determination that the lease is "carefully crafted" without actually having seen the lease? As with the deal between the Allegheny County Airport Authority and Consol, the details are important. The press release put forth by the county executive and his team needs to be fleshed out via a careful and thorough review by county council and the public hearing process.
To say I am disappointed in the PG would be an understatement. Perhaps next time the PG can simply reprint the chief executive's press release and place it as an insert into my morning newspaper.
BARBARA DALY DANKO
Council Member, District 11
Allegheny County Council
Regent Square
Imprudent position
Regarding fracking at Deer Lakes Park: Really? The Post-Gazette thinks it's "prudent" to blast millions of gallons of chemical-laced frack fluid beneath a publicly owned county park with a lake that people fish in ("Prudent Drilling," March 24)? How many advertising dollars from the oil and gas industry did it take to arrive at that "prudent" opinion?
And what happens if a water test reveals that radium-226 (with a half-life of 1,600 years) has been released underground from fracking and has reached the lake water? Will the county executive's office post signs with skulls and crossbones, Mr. Yuk and the county seal alongside the lake? That sure would be the prudent thing to do.
BOB ZILLER
Wilkinsburg
Helmet cams help
I read with interest that some local politicians are expressing concerns about firefighter helmet cams - concerns about privacy, about lack of control of where the video goes, etc. ("Cameras on Fire Helmets Raising Privacy Concerns," March 22). Yet many of these same municipalities have no issue with having "dash cams" or "lapel cams" on their police officers "for their protection" or putting cameras or GPS devices in other vehicles. There is also the unpopular "speed" and red light cameras that are becoming darlings for communities that want to raise revenue under the guise of promoting safety.
Being a retired firefighter after more than 40 years, I think the cameras are great safety features. Some even transmit pictures back to a command post so the chief can see what's going on inside in real time.
Yes, your wife may be in her negligee or important papers might be scattered around, but if firefighters were really concerned with those issues they would just pull out a phone and take video and that cannot be regulated. Same with incidents that happen outside the home: As firefighters, we cut clothes off, and people are herding around videotaping it for the 6 p.m. news. So I would suggest that these politicians come out against all video surveillance, or accept that in today's world no privacy can be guaranteed.
RAY STEFFENS
Norfolk, Va.
Coal-use concerns
Syd S. Peng misleads readers in his Perspectives commentary championing clean coal as a viable route for reducing greenhouse gases ("Champion Clean Coal: The EPA Is Stifling Realistic Climate-Change Policies," March 18). For one thing, "clean coal" refers to methods of burning that reduce pollutants and particulates but have nothing to do with reducing carbon dioxide emissions. He pooh-poohs CO2 sequestration as being nonviable and makes the childish claim that since everyone else is burning coal, we should, too. He even claims that burning coal with 50 percent greater efficiency will reduce fuel use by half. No, it would take a 100 percent increase to reduce usage by half, and if a plant can get 50 percent more efficiency, it won't take government policies to induce foreign plants to be built that way. The money they save will be inducement enough.
No, coal just doesn't have the carbon efficiency to solve our climate problem, so the best way we can lead the world is to stop using it.
Another opinion piece a couple of weeks ago scorned the Senate climate caucus for wasting time discussing the problem in an all-night session ("Liberals Put Out-of-Touchness on Display" by Jennifer Rubin, March 12). Instead, it said people want more focus on the economy and jobs. Yes, those are more pressing concerns, but how else should this country join in a discussion of climate change? It may be a longer-term threat than today's unemployment rate, but it could be a much more dire one.
If there's just a 10 percent chance that the energy path we are on today will wreak havoc 100 years from now, don't we owe it to our grandchildren to at least discuss the problem? I, for one, think we should be acting much more forcefully than we are now, but I'm appalled that our society seems unable to even contemplate it.
CHRIS MULLIN
Mt. Lebanon
]]></text></news-item>