<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-S0Y1-DXMP-K1X2"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>7 Million Died in 2012 due to Air Pollution: WHO Report</title><source>News Tonight</source><author>Daphney Choshi</author><text><![CDATA[World Health Organization has released a report linking 7 million deaths in 2012 to indoor and outdoor pollution. The pollution leads to many health ailments, including heart disease, stroke and breathing related issues. As per latest stats from WHO, one is eight deaths globally could be blamed on pollution.
The pollution also leads to long-term health issues as impaired cognitive functions and birth defects have been linked to air and water pollution. In poor nations, nearly 4.3 million deaths have been attributed to indoor air pollution, mainly due to use of wood and coal for cooking. WHO report also blames outdoor pollution, caused by diesel engines for 3.7 million deaths globally.
Southeast Asia is more prone to health ailments caused due to pollution. The WHO report found higher instances in India, China, Philippines and Indonesia. In poor nations, more than 2.9 billion people use wood or coal for cooking and heating.
WHO report added, "Many people are exposed to both indoor and outdoor air pollution. Due to this overlap, mortality attributed to the two sources cannot simply be added together, hence the total estimate of around 7 million deaths in 2012."
Carlos Dora, WHO Coordinator for Public Health, Environmental and Social Determinants of Health said that it is necessary to check air pollution. Transport, energy and waste management industries are major cause of air pollution.
WHO report puts the number of deaths in Africa at 680,000, in Middle East 400,000, in European region 287,000 and in Latin America at 131,000.
China has been in the news for air pollution and heavy smog in major cities. The Chinese government has planned to take strict action to reduce emissions and pollution. The air filtering industry has grown fast in China during the past few years. However, the outdoor pollution still continues to impact the health of individuals. As per reports, more than 500,000 premature deaths are caused in China every year, due to air pollution.
]]></text></news-item>