<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-HN11-DYJJ-P0R6"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Fracking smacks a partisan wall</title><source>The News-Press (Fort Myers, Florida)</source><author>By, Mary Wozniak</author><text><![CDATA["Right now, fracking is in limbo." Matthew Schwartz
A bill that would require oil companies to disclose the chemicals used in a controversial drilling process called fracking has hit a partisan brick wall, its sponsor says.
Rep. Ray Rodrigues, R-Estero, doesn't think House Bill 71 will pass. The chilly reception is due to partisan politics in an election year, Rodrigues claims.
"Last year we had bipartisan support probably through the whole process," he said. "With a subject as controversial as this, it really needs a broader range of support."
Fracking, formally known as hydraulic fracturing, is controversial because it involves injecting a well with water, chemicals and sand at high pressure to fracture rock and access previously untapped reserves of oil and gas.
Fracking is not occurring in the state now, but Rodrigues said his research indicates that fracking is a real possibility in Florida's future, particularly Southwest Florida. He wants the state to be prepared. Rodrigues' disclosure bill would put a regulatory process in place so the state Department of Environmental Protection can have a registry of chemicals, "should fracking take place in the state," he said.
When Rodrigues filed the same bill in 2013, it proceeded smoothly through legislative committees and passed the House by a large majority. However, the legislative session ended without the bill reaching the Senate floor.
Opponents say the problem is a companion bill, House Bill 157, which would allow companies to withhold some chemicals used in the fracking cocktail if they were considered trade secrets. The same companion bill was proposed by Rodrigues last year, but he said it did not have enough support to generate the required two-thirds vote to pass the House.
The energy industry says fracking is safe, does not put the water supply at risk, creates jobs, provides billions in revenue and will help make the country energy independent.
Critics claim fracking threatens freshwater supplies because companies must drill 2 miles or more beneath the Earth's surface, passing through aquifers that supply fresh water on the way. Some of the fluid is recovered at the surface, stored in tanks or pits, recycled, injected into underground storage wells or taken to waste treatment plants.
They also claim the disclosure bill is simply window dressing so the oil industry can look like it's being transparent if and when fracking comes to Florida, while keeping some chemicals secret.
There are 750 chemicals companies can use in fracking, 29 of them carcinogens, regulated under the Safe Drinking Water Act or listed as hazardous air pollutants under the Clean Air Act, according to a 2011 congressional study.
The bills are confusing, said Matthew Schwartz, executive director of the South Florida Wildlands Association.
"One bill calls for full disclosure and another one for exemption," he said. "On the surface on the face of it, having companies disclose the chemicals utilized is a good thing. Allowing companies to also hold back information is a bad thing." Having fracking in some of the most sensitive environmental lands in Florida is bad, period, he said.
"Right now fracking is in limbo," Schwartz said. "I think that these two bills taken as a whole are to advance fracking in Southwest Florida if they were to go through."
Rodrigues admits the companion bill is contentious. But it falls in line with an already existing state trade secrets law, as well as federal law, he said. The Uniform Trade Secrets Act has been adopted in some form by at least 45 states. Florida's law was adopted in 1988.
Rodrigues said his companion bill is different from disclosure laws in several other states where fracking occurs, because a company would have to tell the state DEP every chemical it used in fracking, even those considered trade secrets. Then a company would say which chemicals are trade secrets and ask that they be exempted. If a person or entity files a public records request asking for a list of trade secrets, the state DEP would inform the company, which would decide whether or not to go to court to block the request.
In the meantime, any trade secret chemicals exempt from public disclosure would still be listed in state records, he said. would "The DEP would know exactly what was put in the ground and know exactly what to look for if there were problems," he said.
If the bills die in this session, Rodrigues is determined to bring them back for a third time next year.
"Right now, fracking is in limbo." Matthew Schwartz
]]></text></news-item>