<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-FJ71-DXDT-64FH"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Malaysia Airlines Mhl70: March 25 as it happened; Air and sea search called off due to bad weather as Chinese relatives of passengers onboard Mhl70 stage protest in Beijing.</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Lucy Kinder, Hannah Strange, Arron Merat and Bonnie Malkin</author><text><![CDATA[· Suicide mission theory of Mhl0 investigators · Air and sea search called off due to bad weather · Relatives of Chinese passengers stage protest · Australian plane spots two objects; HMAS Success on way to retrieve · Chinese plane spots two "relatively big" white objects in the ocean · 'My heart is broken' says mother of passenger · Wooden pallet and "straps" spotted in Indian Ocean · Revealed: the final 54 minutes of communication from Mhl0 · Investigators focus probe on 'deliberate act' by pilots . · The theories - from the plausible to the ridiculous· Air France investigator warns of 'colossal' task· In pictures: The hunt for Mhl0
00.00 We are closing this live blog now, the latest developments in the search for Mhl0 can be found here .
23.50 AMSA announces there are now four planes and 2 ships searching for debris from the plane.
Twitter: AMSA News - Four aircraft have now departed Perth for the #Mhl0 search area. HMAS Success and Xue Long now in search area. http://t.co/exA8Aqqv5a
23.20 The Mail Online has a story suggesting that one of the pilots flew the plane at a deliberately extreme altitude to knock out the passengers .
Shortly after the last voice communication from the cockpit of the plane on March 8 it was tracked by military radar flying between 43,000 and 45,000 feet.
The source, who wished to remain anonymous, told MailOnline: 'It was tracked flying at this altitude for 23 minutes before descending. Oxygen would have run out in 12 minutes [in a depressurised cabin], rendering the passengers unconscious.'
23.00 Tony Abbott, the Australian prime minister, has told the Nine Network the search for the missing airliner will not be abandoned lightly, but "is absolutely not open ended".
He said there was a lot of debris in the area and Australia would keep searching until there was no hope of finding anything.
"We are just going to keep on looking because we owe it to people to do everything we can to resolve this riddle," he said.
22.13 The search for wreckage of crashed Flight Mhl0 has resumed after the weather improved, with Chinese ships and Korean planes joining the hunt over a vast stretch of the Indian Ocean.
Gale force winds, rain and big waves prevented any sorties being flown on Tuesday but 12 aircraft will be in the air on Wednesday while Australia's HMAS Success plans to conduct a surface sweep of an area where two objects were spotted this week.
China's polar supply ship Xue Long was also due in the area, with other Chinese vessels on their way, as the search intensifies for the Malaysian Airlines jet that crashed into the sea after vanishing on March 8 with 239 passengers on board.
"Today's search is split into three areas within the same proximity covering a cumulative 80,000 square kilometres," said the Australian Maritime Safety Authority, which is coordinating the search.
"AMSA has tasked a total of 12 aircraft today to search for possible objects in the search area."
22.00 Jonathan Pearlman in Kuala Lumpur reports the crashed Malaysia Airlines flight gave one last unexplained signal eight minutes after its final "ping", possibly the result of the plane entering its "catastrophic phase" as it plunged into the Indian Ocean.
21.33 Tom Phillips reports on how China's controversial one-child policy means the disappearance of Malaysia Airlines Flight Mhl0 was particularly excruciating for Chinese parents - many of whom lost their only child.
19.32 As we will report in tomorrow's paper, the crashed Malaysia Airlines flight gave one last unexplained signal eight minutes after its final "ping", possibly the result of the plane entering its "catastrophic phase" as it plunged into the Indian Ocean, investigators has said.
Thomas Withington, a defence electronics analyst, told The Telegraph: "It sounds like the aircraft began to squawk a message and for some reason this was curtailed. It could be because the aircraft was at a catastrophic phase of its flight - that something was causing it to crash - or there could be some atmospheric disturbance."
17.38 This photo shows staff at satellite communications company Inmarsat work in front of a screen showing subscribers using their service throughout the world, at their headquarters in London.
Inmarsat used a wave phenomenon discovered in the nineteenth century to analyse the seven pings its satellite picked up from Malaysia Airlines Flight Mhl0 to determine its final destination.
The new findings led Malaysian Prime Minister Najib Razak to conclude that the Boeing 777, which disappeared more than two weeks ago, crashed thousands of miles away in the southern Indian Ocean, killing all 239 people on board:
17.03 Malaysia Arlines has offered $5,000 of compensation to the passengers of flight Mhl0.
According to CNBC, insurance experts have warned of "divergent" compensation claims, with the families of U.S. passengers potentially receiving millions more than their Asian counterparts.
Under a multilateral treaty known as the Montreal Convention, the airline must pay the families of those on board around £107,000 per passenger.
But relatives can also sue for further damages - and it is these further pay-outs that experts warn could vary widely.
16.59 Yesterday Malaysia Airlines defended its use of text messages to inform the families that the plane had crashed into the sea- saying that it was an additional contact method and that as many family members had been contacted by phone or in person as possible.
There are still many accounts of families finding out the devastating news by text message. Sarah Bajc, the partner of American IBM executive Philip Wood, found out this way.
The relatives of Australian couples Rodney and Mary Burrows and Bob and Cathy Lawton also heard via the 26 word text message.
According to the Sydney Morning Herald Mr Lawton's brother David was asleep when his wife, Rhonda, was woken by the text. She waited until the morning to tell him. ''I wanted him to get a good sleep,'' she said.
16.15 Chinese President Xi Jinping ordered a special envoy, Vice Foreign Minister Zhang Yesui, to Kuala Lumpur to deal with the case. Deputy Foreign Minister Xie Hangsheng told Malaysia's ambassador that China wanted to know exactly what led the Malaysian prime minister to announce that the plane had been lost, a statement on the ministry's website said.
16.10 Students attend a prayer ceremony in tribute to passengers and crew onboard missing Malaysia Airlines flight Mhl0:
16.00 China and Malaysia have had some terse communications today. China has demanded that Malaysia turn over the satellite data which was used to conclude that the plane has crashed in the Indian Ocean.
Ealier today in a press conference Malaysia's acting Transport Minister criticised China's role in the search. When asked by a Chinese journalist why Malaysia had taken so long to release the satellite data, he said
"Can I also remind you that we received satellite data from China involving 'sightings' in the South China Sea, which made us detract ourselves from the search and rescue to search areas we already searched, and it was found to be negative."
15.11 James Wood, the brother of missing MH 370 passenger Philip Wood, has spoken to CNN about receiving the news there were no survivors.
14.55 Crew members of the Australian Navy ship, HMAS Success, use a spotlight as they look for debris in the southern Indian Ocean during the search for the missing flight:
14.50 The Sydney Morning Herald reports that the cluster of suspected debris from Malaysian Airlines flight Mhl0 has been sighted above a giant undersea chain of volcanoes whose complex terrain has barely been charted
14.44 A relative grieves for the passengers of missing Malaysia Airlines flight Mhl0 during a protest outside the Malaysian embassy in Beijing
14.34 The daughter of Mhl0 chief steward Andrew Nari has been tweeting since the flight disappeared:
Twitter: î€£. - Physically and mentally tired. It has been a hectic day since last night. I am still hoping for a miracle, but..., hm. Goodnight, daddy. :')
14.19 The Washington Post reports that plainclothes appeared to brief relatives of Mhl0 passengers on how to protest at the Malaysian embassy:
While the crowd included many relatives, several also appeared to be Chinese government agents in plain clothes whose mission seemed to be not only to guide the protest but also to keep it under control.
Some relatives said they believed authorities were giving them a way to release their anger for fear it could turn back on the Chinese government.
13.56 According to the Wall Street Journal, an online Sina poll found that 77% of more than 38,400 Chinese respondents said the incident had influenced whether they'd be likely to travel to Malaysia in the future:
More than 3/4 of Chinese polled say #Mhl0 has influenced whether they'll visit Malaysia http://t.co/9AgvjiNeT4pic.twitter.com/gglU81HPT9
- Wall Street Journal (@WSJ) March 25, 2014
13.21 Grieving Chinese relatives of passengers on missing Malaysia Airlines flight Mhl0 try to remove a police barricade blocking journalists as they gather to protest outside the Malaysian embassy in Beijing:
AFP/GETTY
13.18 A concert to mark Malaysia's Formula One Grand Prix weekend which was set to feature Christina Aguilera has been cancelled due to the jet crash, its sponsor said.
State oil company Petronas, which sponsors the Mercedes F1 racing team and the annual concert, said it called off the show as "a sign of respect to the families and next-of-kin of the crew and passengers of flight Mhl0".
Formula One organisers are meeting to discuss a possible tribute to victims at this weekend's event.
13.06 Paramilitary soldiers in anti-riot gear march around the Malaysian embassy while family members of passengers onboard Malaysia Airlines Flight Mhl0 stage a rally in front of the embassy in Beijing:
12.57 Here is an explanation, given by Malaysian authorities, of how British satellite company Inmarsat managed to narrow down the search area for flight Mhl0:
In recent days Inmarsat developed an innovative technique which considers the velocity of the aircraft relative to the satellite. Depending on this relative movement, the frequency received and transmitted will differ from its normal value, in much the same way that the sound of a passing car changes as it approaches and passes by. This is called the Doppler effect. The Inmarsat technique analyses the difference between the frequency that the ground station expects to receive and that actually measured. This difference is the result of the Doppler effect and is known as the Burst Frequency Offset.
The Burst Frequency Offset changes depending on the location of the aircraft on an arc of possible positions, its direction of travel, and its speed. In order to establish confidence in its theory, Inmarsat checked its predictions using information obtained from six other B777 aircraft flying on the same day in various directions. There was good agreement.
While on the ground at Kuala Lumpur airport, and during the early stage of the flight, Mhl0 transmitted several messages. At this stage the location of the aircraft and the satellite were known, so it was possible to calculate system characteristics for the aircraft, satellite, and ground station.
During the flight the ground station logged the transmitted and received pulse frequencies at each handshake. Knowing the system characteristics and position of the satellite it was possible, considering aircraft performance, to determine where on each arc the calculated burst frequency offset fit best.
The analysis showed poor correlation with the Northern corridor, but good correlation with the Southern corridor, and depending on the ground speed of the aircraft it was then possible to estimate positions at 0011 UTC, at which the last complete handshake took place.
12.33 Suwarni the mother of Sugianto Lo, who was onboard the Malaysia Airlines plane Mhl0 with his wife Vinny, shows her son's family portraits at her residence in Indonesia:
AP
12.23 Malaysia Airlines Chairman Mohammed Nor Mohammed Yusof said this morning that it may take a long time before the families of passengers get the answers they want:
"This has been an unprecedented event requiring an unprecedented response," he said. "The investigation still underway may yet prove to be even longer and more complex than it has been since March 8th."
He added that even though no wreckage has been found, there was no doubt it had crashed.
"This by the evidence given to us, and by rational deduction, we could only arrive at that conclusion: That is, for Malaysia Airlines to declare that it has lost its plane, and by extension, the people in the plane," he said.
12.14 Former Navy pilot Dr Simon Mitchell says the mystery surrounding missing Malaysia Airlines Flight Mhl0 is "tearing up rule book in terms of how to start looking for an aircraft":
12.07 Australia's deputy defence chief, Air Marshal Mark Binskin, has said of the search: "We're not searching for a needle in a haystack - we're still trying to define where the haystack is,"
11.45 Malaysian officials have released a statement detailing the technical information given to them by the UK's Air Accidents Investigation Branch (AAIB) which helped them determine flight Mhl0 had crashed in the Indian Ocean based on satellite analysis:
If the ground station has not heard from an aircraft for an hour it will transmit a 'log on / log off' message, sometimes referred to as a 'ping', using the aircraft's unique identifier. If the aircraft receives its unique identifier it returns a short message indicating that it is still logged on. This process has been described as a "handshake" and takes place automatically.
From the ground station log it was established that after ACARS stopped sending messages, 6 complete handshakes took place.
There is evidence of a partial handshake between the aircraft and ground station at 0019 UTC. At this time this transmission is not understood and is subject to further ongoing work.
No response was received from the aircraft at 0115 UTC, when the ground earth station sent the next log on / log off message. This indicates that the aircraft was no longer logged on to the network.
Therefore, some time between 0011 UTC and 0115 UTC the aircraft was no longer able to communicate with the ground station. This is consistent with the maximum endurance of the aircraft.
11.29 Chinese relatives of flight Mhl0 pssengers sit on a bus waiting to go to the Malaysian embassy in protest in Beijing.
11.23 Here is a video of families in Beijing staging protests as Malaysia Airlines officials say it may take time for further answers about the fate of flight Mhl0 to become clear:
11.16 This from Jonathan Pearlman in Kuala Lumpur:
Malaysian authorities have provided more details about the satellite tracking of Mhl0 and the analysis that established its landing point in the Indian Ocean.
The details are complex and only now being released.
But, as the last two weeks unfolded, the analysts appear to have gradually refined their inquiry, focusing on the frequency of the "handshakes" issued by equipment aboard the missing plane and considering how the frequency might change depending on the velocity of the aircraft relative to the satellite. They then tested their findings against six aircraft which took off from Kuala Lumpur on the same day as the missing flight (March 8) and whose routes were known. They concluded that their new assumptions were accurate and that the plane - as feared - had landed in the southern Indian Ocean.
Hishammuddin Hussein, Malaysia's acting transport minister, says an international team is being put together to try to work out exactly where the plane has ended. He also revealed that the findings have allowed the search area to be narrowed down to a zone of 469,407 nautical square miles compared with a previous zone of more than 2 million square miles.
11.11 As the deadline to find the Malaysian Airlines jet's black box approaches Australian officials suspend the search for flight Mhl0 due to gale force winds in the southern Indian Ocean:
10.54 This from Malcolm Moore in Beijing:
A hundred relatives of the Chinese passengers on board Malaysia Airlines flight Mhl0 hurled water bottles and stood chanting outside the Malaysian embassy in Beijing for two hours, calling for "proof" of the plane's demise.
Outside the embassy gates, the relatives called for the ambassador to come down and address them, only to be told he was not inside.
When they caught sight of Malaysian diplomats taking photographs of them through the floor-to-ceiling windows, they lobbed water bottles angrily.
"They are liars!" said Mr Wang. "They hide everything. We just want the truth but they are hiding so many things. There is no proof. Why did the officials not come to see us," he added.
After two hours, a senior diplomat arrived to receive a letter of protest, after which the relatives boarded buses back to the hotel.
There, the Malaysian ambassador did arrive, only to face another volley of abuse. After he made a speech with tears in his eyes, he was told: "Tell us the truth, or go **** your mother."
Here is the full story.
10.32 The Malaysian Transport Minister's press conference following the announcement that there was no longer any doubt that Flight Mhl0 went down in the southern Indian Ocean:
10.15 Still no real information about why the plane went down, Malaysian officials refusing to speculate.
10.11 According to China's Xinhua news agency, Chinese President Xi Jinping has ordered to send a special envoy to Kuala Lumpur to consult with Malaysia and deal with the matter of missing Malaysia Airlines Flight Mhl0.
10.09 The Malaysian Air Force will set up an enquiry into what happened to Mhl0. Malaysia will also set up a royal commision into what happened.
10.01 Malaysia's Transport Minister agrees that until debris is found, it will be very difficult for the families to have closure. He says that he is an optimisitc person and will do 'whatever it takes' to find the plane. He reminds press that they have managed to narrow the search area form millions of nautical miles to hundreds of thousands. It is still a big area though.
09.58 Malaysian officials say that they have had regular meetings with the search team from the Air France crash in 2009.
09.54 He says that the exact location of the plane is still being determined. Six Chinese ships are currently in the search area and will arrive at the point of Mhl0's last known position tomorrow morning. This includes the icebreaker Xuelong.
09.50 Hishammuddin says that searches in the northern corridor and the northern part of the southern corridor have now been stopped. All search efforts are focused on the southern point of the southern corridor.
09.47 Malaysia's acting Transport Minister Hishammuddin Hussein says that the challenge is now technical and logistical. He is currently explaining how satellite company Inmarsat managed to track the plane into the Indian Ocean.
09.43 The Malaysian press conference has just begun. The Malaysian government said that they remain focussed on narrowing the search area.
08.25 A representative of the Chinese community in Perth, Australia has said volunteers will help out when relatives of the 239 passengers fly to the city when the search resumes. Sammy Yap of Perth's Chung-Wah Association said the representatives would provide physical, emotional and spiritual support to grieving visitors. The Australian government will designate a reception centre to co-ordinate the visit.
08.01 A concert to mark Malaysia's Formula One Grand Prix weekend which was set to feature US star Christina Aguilera has been cancelled due to a passenger jet crash, it has been announced.
Petronas, the state oil company that sponsors the Mercedes F1 racing team and the annual concert, said it called off the show as "a sign of respect to the families and next-of-kin of the crew and passengers of flight Mhl0".
The concert was to be held Friday and Saturday at the Kuala Lumpur Twin Towers and feature Aguilera, Korean star Rain and R&B musician Craig Davis.
07.20 Reports have come in that relatives of the passengers gathering outside the Malaysian embassy in Beijing have clashed with police. Among the flight's 239 passengers, 153 were Chinese nationals, making the incident a highly emotional one in the Chinese capital.
Nearly 100 relatives and their supporters marched to the embassy in the late morning, wearing white T-shirts that read "Let's pray for Mhl0" as they held banners and chanted for about three hours.
"Tell the truth! Return our relatives!" they shouted.
06.05 Jayden Burrows, the son of Australian passengers Rod and Mary Burrows, has spoken to journalists in Queensland, asking for privacy.
The love and compassion that they shared and their priority of putting their family first will help us get through this together.
We're heartbroken this stage of their life has been cut short. They worked hard to reap the rewards of their retirement so they could travel and spend time with their family and friends.
We're extremely grateful for all of the love and support from our friends and families.
Our family appreciate all the well wishes and prayers but now we ask for privacy and we request that our wish for family solitude be respected at this time.
05.40 Our correspondent Jonathan Pearlman was at the press conference in Kuala Lumpur. He reports:
The airline said family members have been offered 24-hour counselling and $US5,000 each - as well as hotel and food requirements - and will be offered continuing financial and counselling aid.
"We feel enormous sorrow and pain," said Mr Ahmad Jauhari, the airline's chairman.
"As a parent... my heart breaks at the unimaginable pain suffered by the families."
The airline offered to bring families of passengers to the crash zone but said Australia has refused to grant visas until clear evidence of the plane is found.
Mr Ahmad Jauhari said the crash was an "unprecedented event in aviation history" and the airline had already changed procedures to boost safety and security. He said all had been done to support the families and to provide support and information.
The airline revealed little more about the cause of the crash, saying the Malaysian government was responsible for the investigation. But it said it had little choice but to accept the "painful reality" that its plane had crashed without survivors.
05.15 The press conference has wrapped up. Over in Beijing it looks like the protest staged by families of the passengers is also drawing to a close.
Twitter: malcolmmoore - Bus has arrived at Malaysian embassy. Relatives protest about to end Mhl0
Chinese authorities normally keep a very tight rein on any protests in Beijing, but this one was allowed to go ahead, with demonstrators shouting slogans including "The Malaysian government are murderers" and "We want our relatives back".
04.50 Reporters are now asking questions. One has asked whether the Malaysia Airlines chief will resign:
Will I resign? it's a personal question, we will tackle it later.
Another reporter asks if Malaysia Airlines has been "heartless" towards the relatives.
Depending who you speak to you will get a different version...the thought is to provide some comfort.
04.35 Malaysian authorities are now giving a press conference in Kuala Lumpur, defending the way in which they broke news that the flight was now considered to be lost to the families of passengers. The Malaysia Airlines group chief executive said text messages were used "as a last resort".
He goes on to detail how 900 relatives are being supported by the airline, including financial assistance.
"We don't know why, we don't know how this terrbile tragedy happened, but the Malaysia Airlines family are all praying for the passengers and crew of Mhl0."
04.26 Air Marshal Mark Binskin, vice chief of the defence force, says he hopes the weather will improve in the coming days.
"This is a highly complex search, it will develop in the coming days."
04.20Defence minister David Johnston is speaking in Perth thanking crews and teams involved in the search.
"This is an amazing example of international cooperation especially between militaries," he says.
But he has reiterated that there has been no physical confirmation that the items spotted in the sea relate to the missing plane.
"Until we recover and positively identify a piece of debris, everything is speculation."
04.15 The Australian defence minister is due to give a press conference on Mhl0 shortly.
04.08Malcolm Moore reports that relatives of the passengers have arrived at the Malaysian embassy.
Twitter: malcolmmoore - These chaps have just turned up - embassy guards? http://t.co/VkcMThkSxu
Twitter: malcolmmoore - Mhl0 relatives now raging, shouting, chanting
Twitter: malcolmmoore - Relatives now in a closed police pen outside the embassy, media on other side of police lines Mhl0
04.00 China's heavily controlled media has also reacted furiously to last night's announcement about the fate of Flight 370. Chinese newspapers carry a series of very strongly worded and suspicion-filled editorials this morning that give a taste of the anger.
"This is not the end," writes the Beijing Times. "One day, we will find out what happened on Mhl0 during those final seven hours and why some people did not want us to know."
"We need the truth," argues the Economic Observer. "The families of the 154 Chinese passengers have the right to know the truth. In their eyes, the Malaysian [government] is the actual executioner of their loved ones."
03.45 China is demanding that Malaysia turn over satellite data used to conclude that Mhl0 was lost in the southern Indian Ocean with no survivors.
China's official Xinhua News Agency quoted Deputy Foreign Minister Xie Hangsheng as telling the Malaysian ambassador to Beijing that China wanted to know the specific facts that led Malaysia to announce Monday night that the plane had been lost.
There was no immediate response from the Malaysian side.
03.30 Here is more from Malcolm on the protest by families of the passengers:
Twitter: malcolmmoore - This is the scene outside the Malaysian embassy but no sign of relatives' buses yet http://t.co/4jMdgaFsHp
Twitter: malcolmmoore - 3-4 public buses, with police on board, are ferrying relatives to the Malaysia Embassy Mhl0
02.44Malcolm Moore, our correspondent in Beijing, reports that a big group of relatives has just streamed out of the hotel, carrying placards and wearing t-shirts saying "Save Mhl0" and they are heading for the Malaysian embassy by bus.
Twitter: malcolmmoore - The relatives are on their way to Malaysian embassy, with about 50-60 police waiting Mhl0 http://t.co/1CsNOK8vkT
02.08 Tony Abbott, the Australian prime minister, has made some comments about the news that the plane has been declared lost with all onboard. Speaking in Canberra, he said it has been a "desperately difficult time" for thousands of people, particularly in China and Malaysia. He said Australia would welcome the families of any of the victims that want to come to Australia as the search for the wreckage continues.
01.40 Here is the striking and sombre front page of the New Straits Times from today.
01.00 Tom Phillips, our correspondent in China reports:
CCTV is reporting live from the Lido hotel in Beijing this morning. That is where many furious and distraught Chinese relatives of Flight 370's missing passengers recieved the news last night that authorities believed nobody could possibly have survived.
The CCTV reporter says families there are now already gathering to watch a live feed of this morning's scheduled press conference in Kuala Lumpur by Malaysia's Prime Minister.
Some people are demanding the Malaysian ambassador comes to their hotel while others are already vowing to take "action" and receiving legal advice, CCTV says.
00.20 Warren Truss, Australia's deputy PM, has said that the Malaysian government will take over the investigation in the southern Indian Ocean for lost flight Mhl0, according to a report by Australian Associated Press. Mr Truss said confirmation by Malaysian Prime Minister Najib Razak that the plane had crashed killing all on board moved the investigation into a new phase, with Malaysia taking control under the Chicago Convention on international civil aviation.
"The announcement by the Prime Minster that Malaysia believes that the aircraft is lost and that there will be no survivors does move the search to a new phase," he said.
"It moves it to a stage where we are now investigating an accident, a loss of an aircraft and some new decisions will have to be taken now about the direction of future operations.
"Malaysia needs to take control under the Chicago convention of those investigations.
Mr Truss said the HMAS Success had been in the area of ocean where sightings potentially related to Mhl0 had been made but officers had not recovered a single piece that might be associated with the aircraft.
He said the Malaysian government's announcement was based purely on the satellite imagery and calculations available "so it's really a long, long way away before much can be done by way of physical examination".
"It's still important for us to try and find as much of the aircraft as possible.
"The ideal would obviously be to locate as much of the wreckage as possible.
"That will require sophisticated equipment, some of which we do not have in Australia.
"It is also a priority to recover the flight box recorder on the aircraft.
"Again, we don't believe we will have the technology to be able to work at those depths and to be able to recover the equipment, so we'll need assistance from countries like the US to actually be able to undertake that kind of an operation."
23.45 Here is the AMSA statement on the suspension of the search in full:
The Australian Maritime Safety Authority's search for any signs of the missing Malaysia Airlines flight Mhl0 has been suspended for today due to poor weather conditions in the search area.
Due to rough seas, HMAS Success departed the search area early this morning and is now in transit south of the search area until seas abate. A sea state ranging between 7 to 8 is forecast today with waves up to two metres and an associated swell of up to four metres.
The area is also forecast to experience strong gale force winds of up to 80km/h, periods of heavy rain, and low cloud with a ceiling between 200 and 500 feet.
AMSA has undertaken a risk assessment and determined that the current weather conditions would make any air and sea search activities hazardous and pose a risk to crew. Therefore, AMSA has suspended all sea and air search operations for today due to these weather conditions.
AMSA has consulted with the Bureau of Meteorology and weather conditions are expected to improve in the search area in the evening and over the next few days. Search operations are expected to resume tomorrow, if weather conditions permit.
HMAS Success will return to the search area once weather conditions improve. Last night, HMAS Success attempted to locate objects sighted by a RAAF P3 Orion aircraft. The objects
were spotted visually in the search area by the RAAF P3 Orion about 2.45pm (AEDT).
Drift modelling was undertaken to assist search efforts. HMAS Success was unable to relocate the objects.
In light of the statement by the Malaysian Prime Minister Najib Razak overnight, AMSA offers its deepest sympathies to the families of the passengers and crew of flight Mhl0.
AMSA intends to recommence search activities for any signs of the aircraft once weather conditions improve in the search area.
23.25 Some more detail on the bad weather: The AMSA statement said strong gale force winds of up to 80 kilometres per hour (50 miles per hour) were whipping the area along with heavy rain and low cloud with a ceiling between 200 feet (60 metres) and 500 feet.
23.15 Bad weather has forced the Australian Maritime Safety Authority (AMSA) to announce that the air and sea search for the missing plane has been suspended for the day. The deteroriating conditions come at a crucial time for the recovery mission, when a naval vessel was hoping to recover items spotted in the ocean over the past few days.
"AMSA has undertaken a risk assessment and determined that the current weather conditions would make any air and sea search activities hazardous and pose a risk to crew," a statement said.
"Therefore, AMSA has suspended all sea and air search operations for today due to these weather conditions."
The search will resume tomorrow if weather permits.
23.00 Reuters reportsthe United States is sending an undersea Navy drone capable of exploring waters nearly 15,000 feet deep to potentially help search for any sunken wreckage.
The Pentagon announced the US is pre-positioning the sonar-equipped Bluefin "autonomous underwater vehicle" in Australia to help pinpoint the plane.
"We have more than 200 families out there that are grieving right now. They just got some stark news today from the Malaysian government," said Pentagon spokesman Rear Admiral John Kirby, adding the "the whole world grieves with them."
The Bluefin drone is just over 17 feet (5 meters) long and weighs 1,764 pounds (800 kg), according to a Navy factsheet. Kirby said it can operate for more than a day at slower speeds.
The undersea Navy drone was flown out of a New York airport on Monday and were expected to arrive in Perth, Australia on Tuesday, the Pentagon said.
Ten American civilian personnel and uniformed members of the military were also flying to Australia to operate or prepare the equipment, it said.
But the Pentagon cautioned that the US technology would only be employed once the search area was significantly narrowed.
"In order for this technology to be useful, you have to have an identified area on the sea bottom that you want to go take a look at," Mr Kirby said.
"You have to be able to go give it some parameters - and right now we're just not there."
22.25 Our reporters Gordon Rayner and Nick Collins explain how Britain finds itself at the centre of the blame gameover crucial delays in the search for the missing plane.
22.04 The Wall Street Journal (£) has an interesting piece on the difficulties of searching for a black box at sea .
21.08 Our correspondent Jonathan Pearlman reports from Kuala Lumpur quoting well-placed sources that no malfunction or fire was capable of causing Mhl0's unusual flight and it in fact went down over the southern Indian Ocean in an apparent suicide mission .
The team investigating the Boeing 777's disappearance believe no malfunction or fire was capable of causing the aircraft's unusual flight or the disabling of its communications system before it veered wildly off course on a seven hour silent flight into the sea. An analysis of the flight's routing, signalling and communications shows that it was flown "in a rational way".
An official source told The Telegraph that investigators believe "this has been a deliberate act by someone on board who had to have had the detailed knowledge to do what was done ... Nothing is emerging that points to motive."
Asked about the possibility of a plane malfunction or an on-board fire, the source said: "It just does not hinge together..... [The investigators] have gone through processes you do to get the plane where it flew to for eight hours. They point to it being flown in a rational way."
20.37 Blog post by the New Yorker entitled ' The End of the Beginning of the Mhl0 Mystery ' on the false closure experienced by the relatives of the dead.
We will no doubt hear that, for those whose loved ones vanished without explanation sixteen days ago, this moment represents some intimation of that elusive quantity known as closure, however painful its arrival. But that conclusion seems doubly false: too much about how and why their relatives died remains to be determined, and even that knowledge, when it eventually surfaces, will still feel insufficient to the scale of their losses. But, whatever closure consists of, it describes a process rather than a point; today, at least, that process can begin.
20.22A video by the Guardian shows how Australian prime minister Tony Abbott has confirmed that a navy ship is on its way to recover the two new objects detected by a search plane.
20.13According to the Daily Mail, an Australian horror film that sees China-bound flight crash into the ocean and survivors fight off giant sharks is shelved after Mhl0 tragedy.
Out of sensitivity to the Malaysia flight situation, we've decided to put it on pause for now,' managing director Gary Hamilton said
19.33 The US Navy has said that it was moving a black box locator to the region in case a debris area was located.
The TPL-25 Towed Pinger Locator System is able to locate black boxes on downed Navy and commercial aircraft down to a maximum depth of 20,000 feet anywhere in the world. Commercial aircraft pingers are mounted directly on the flight recorder, the recovery of which is critical to an accident investigation.
The Pinger Locator is towed behind a vessel at slow speeds, generally 1-5 knots, depending on the depth. The tow array carries a passive listening device for detecting pingers that automatically transmit an acoustic pulse.
19.28 As Malaysia announced that flight Mhl0 crashed in the southern Indian Ocean, questions have emerged as to what will happen next. Our correspondent Henry Samuel endeavours to answer the six major ones here .
1. How they will be able to pinpoint the plane crash site?
2. How will they find the wreck itself?
3. Will finding debris, or the main wreck, be conclusive in saying what happened to plane?
4. If they do recover the black boxes, will they be working?
5. If they do find the wreck, what are they likely to see?
6. Will it be tricky to recover parts from the ocean floor?
19.10 Chinese Deputy Foreign Minister Xie Hangsheng has told Malaysia's ambassador in Beijing that China was demanding Malaysia hand over all relevant satellite data analysis on the missing Malaysian airliner, the Foreign Ministry said.
Xie met the ambassador after Malaysian Prime Minister Najib Razak, citing new satellite data, said Malaysia Airlines Flight Mhl0 had crashed in the southern Indian Ocean.
18.50 Despite today's news, there will be no let up in efforts to locate the wreckage and the black box of the Mhl0. David Millward, Telegraph US correspondent, has this report on the US deployment of a towed pinger locator, excerpts of which are below:
"In the event a debris field is located, we're moving some specialised locator equipment into the area," said Cmdr. Chris Budde, US 7th Fleet operations officer.
"The Towed Pinger Locator has some highly sensitive listening capability so that if the wreck site is located, we can hear the black box pinger down to a depth of about 20,000 feet.
"Basically, this super-sensitive hydrophone gets towed behind a commercial vessel very slowly and listens for black box pings.
"This movement is simply a prudent effort to pre-position equipment and trained personnel closer to the search area so that if debris is found we will be able to respond as quickly as possible since the battery life of the black box's pinger is limited."
18.28 The families gathered in Beijing have delivered a scathing denunciation of Malaysia Airlines and the Malaysian government, branding them "the real executioners" of the Mhl0 passengers:
"At 10pm on March 25, the Malaysian prime minister sent a statement to the families of Mhl0 passengers without any direct evidence that Mhl0 crashed in the south Indian ocean and no people survived.
"From March 8 when they announced that Mhl0 lost contact to today, 18 days have passed during which the Malaysian government and military constantly tried to delay, deceive the passengers' families and cheat the whole world.
"This shameless behaviour not only fooled and hurt the families of the 154 passengers but also misguided and delayed rescue actions, wasting a large quantity of human resources and materials and lost valuable time for the rescue effort.
"If the 154 passengers did lose their lives, Malaysia Airlines, the Malaysian government and military are the real executioners who killed them. We the families of those on board submit our strongest protest against them.
"We will take every possible means to pursue the unforgivable crimes and responsibility of all three."
18.07 Read The Telegraph's interview with Chris McLaughlin, senior vice president of external affairs at Inmarsat, who explains how the British satellite data company tracked down the Mhl0:
"We worked out where the last ping was, and we knew that the plane must have run out of fuel before the next automated ping, but we didn't know what speed the aircraft was flying at - we assumed about 450 knots," said Mr McLaughlin. "We can't know when the fuel actually ran out, we can't know whether the plane plunged or glided, and we can't know whether the plane at the end of the time in the air was flying more slowly because it was on fumes."
17.52 The Telegraph's Nick Collins has been talking to Dr Stephen Wright, an aviation lecturer at Leeds University, who said the co-pilot's inexperience could have left him ill-equipped to cope with emergencies such as a possible terrorist attack:
"You've got one guy that's got 45,000 hours of flight time - this is somebody very experienced - and at the other end of the spectrum is this chap," he said. "They haven't told us when the first officer got his commercial license for some reason, which is unusual.
"When you roster two pilots where is a minimum experience level, they must put a new guy with an older pilot by law. The co pilot is not going to have the confidence or experience to deal with many types of incident.
"If it were an emergency occurence such as a decompression or a fire, both crew members would be expected to react as per their training. But if it was something other than that, such as a form of terrorism, sabotage, persons entering the flight deck that should not enter, then the young guy is potentially not going to have the experience to deal with this.
"At this time it is a hypothesis but what needs to happen now is they must recover the cockpit voice recorder. As soon as they have got it they will be able to find out who said what, and what other noise is going on in the background."
17.34 Despite today's announcement, many relatives of the Mhl0 are struggling to accept the news that there are no survivors from flight Mhl0. Sarah Bajc, partner of the passenger Philip Wood, said the lack of physical evidence made it difficult to come to terms with. Others have been demanding further information as to why authorities have reached their conclusion. "No confirmed wreckage, so no real closure," Ms Bajc said in a statement .
17.07 Our correspondent Malcolm Moore in Beijingreports on the grief and denial that beset relatives as they were told the plane had been concluded lost via a text message:
When the news came, at 9.46pm in Beijing, it was not face to face, or even in a language the relatives could understand.
Inside the conference room at the Lido hotel, phones began to beep with text messages in English, not Chinese.
After 16 days of doubt and mistrust, and heavy criticism of the calamitous misjudgements of the Malaysian authorities, the text message was a final insult.
Its vague wording brought no sense of closure for the scores inside the room, some of whom continued to cling on to hope even after the window for optimism had long closed.
There was no hard evidence of flight Mhl0's demise, simply an "assumption beyond all doubt" that all aboard had been lost.
At first there was silence. Then at 10pm, as the Malaysian prime minister appeared on the television screens inside the room to confirm the news, the screaming started.
16.54 Amid confusion and disbelief among the families of Mhl0's Chinese passengers, Beijing has demanded Malaysia hand over the data that has led to today's grim conclusion, CCTV America reports:
Twitter: CCTV America - #Mhl0 : Chinese Foreign Ministry Spokesman Hong Lei demands Malaysia to provide all data and information that indicated the crash.
16.29 From The Telegraph video team:
It was the news they feared. The relatives of passengers and crew of missing flight Mhl0 were in shock after after the prime minister of Malaysia confirmed that the missing Malaysia Airlines plane went down hundreds of miles off course in the southern Indian Ocean, with no hope of finding survivors:
16.09 The BBC has been hosting a Twitter Q&A with Piers Applegarth, a pilot from the British Airline Pilots Association and Richard Westcott, BBC transport correspondent. You can read an edited transcript here. One user asks Applegarth about the theory that a fire incapacitated the pilots:
Question from Colin via email: If fire incapacitated pilots, can cabin crew enter cockpit? #AskBBCRichard
Piers answers: Cabin crew can enter cockpit. If pilots conscious they could stop door opening. #AskBBCRichard
15.55 This graphic from The Telegraph indicates the suspected flight path of Mhl0 and the location of the past week's debris sightings and searches:
15.36 Read the full report from our correspondent in Kuala Lumpur, Jonathan Pearlman, on today's announcement that the plane has been lost:
Following a seventeen-day global hunt to locate the vanished aircraft, Najib Razak, Malaysia's prime minister, confirmed the worst fears of the families of the 239 passengers. He said new analysis by Britain's Air Accidents Investigation Branch team and British satellite telecommunications company Inmarsat revealed that the plane ended its baffling eight-hour flight in the deep, remote waters of the Indian Ocean, about 1500 miles from Perth.
"This is a remote location, far from any possible landing sites," he said. "It is therefore with deep sadness and regret that I must inform you that, according to this new data, flight Mhl0 ended in the southern Indian Ocean."
The cause of the crash remains a mystery. Mr Najib said Malaysian officials will release further details on Tuesday, but it has long been thought that the flight's most likely endpoint was in the southern of two possible trajectories; the northern trajectory was above land and would almost certainly have been picked up by radar.
But the plane remains missing and the search for the wreckage of the aircraft - and its black box - will continue.
15.20 French investigators have said it is too soon to consider launching undersea searches for the wreckage of Mhl0.
France's BEA accident investigation service, which had sent three investigators to Kuala Lumpur, said the "extremely vast areas (involved) do not make it possible at this stage to consider undersea searches", AFP reported.
14.59 There is considerable consternation emerging over the decision of Malaysia Airlines to inform families of the deaths of their loved ones via text message. Richard Quest of CNN says the relatives had been prepared to receive such news in an SMS, but nevertheless, many of those commenting on social networks are questioning the decision to use such an impersonal method.
14.54 Inmarsat says it passed the relevant analysis to the UK Air Accidents Investigation Branch (AAIB) yesterday. More details from the UK satellite data company as we have it.
14.36 Following the news that satellite data analysis from UK company Inmarsat has helped conclude that Mhl0 ended in the southern Indian Ocean, read The Telegraph's interview with Inmarsat's chief operating officer and senior vice president of external affairs on what the data from the flight tells us.
14.27 Our correspondent Jonathan Pearlman reports from Kuala Lumpur on the confirmation that Mhl0 has been lost in the southern Indian Ocean:
The search for Mhl0 is over - and hopes for survivors crushed - after the plane was confirmed to have crashed in the south Indian Ocean.
Following a seventeen-day global hunt to locate the vanished aircraft, Najib Razak, Malaysia's prime minister, confirmed the worst fears of the families of the 239 passengers.
Mr Najib confirmed that the plane ended its baffling eight-hour flight in the deep, remote waters of the Indian Ocean, about 1500 miles from Perth.
The cause of the crash remains a mystery.
A 26-nation search has focussed on a remote stretch of the Indian Ocean after satellites from the United States, China and France all detected floating objects believed to be debris from the plane. In recent days, numerous objects have been spotted floating in the water.
Malaysian authorities were preparing to brief families of the passengers - most of whom were Chinese - in Beijing and Kuala Lumpur.
14.22 The operation to retrieve the wreckage of Malaysia Airlines Mhl0, using the various physical and satellite sightings over the past week. Here's a graphic showing the locations of the detected objects:
14.20 Beijing authorities are providing medical assistance to relatives at the Lido Hotel, where some have collapsed at the news that the plane went down in the southern Indian Ocean:
14.18 Watch the press conference with Najib Razak, the Malaysian prime minister, as he announces that Mhl0 went down in the southern Indian Ocean:
14.13 Our correspondent Malcolm Moore is at the Lido Hotel in Beijing, where scenes of grief and distress have broken out as the worst fears of passengers' families are confirmed:
Twitter: malcolmmoore - Terrible screaming and wailing here of families in grief Mhl0 #Beijing
Twitter: malcolmmoore - One relative just came out of the conference room weeping, pursued by photographers and fell down the escalator Mhl0
14.09 Here is the full statement from Malaysian Prime Minister Najib Razak on investigators' conclusion that Mhl0 ended in the southern Indian Ocean and that no one on board survived:
PM NAJIB RAZAK'S PRESS STATEMENT ON Mhl0
This evening I was briefed by representatives from the UK Air Accidents Investigation Branch (AAIB). They informed me that Inmarsat, the UK company that provided the satellite data which indicated the northern and southern corridors, has been performing further calculations on the data. Using a type of analysis never before used in an investigation of this sort, they have been able to shed more light on Mhl0's flight path.
Based on their new analysis, Inmarsat and the AAIB have concluded that Mhl0 flew along the southern corridor, and that its last position was in the middle of the Indian Ocean, west of Perth.
This is a remote location, far from any possible landing sites. It is therefore with deep sadness and regret that I must inform you that, according to this new data, flight Mhl0 ended in the southern Indian Ocean.
We will be holding a press conference tomorrow with further details. In the meantime, we wanted to inform you of this new development at the earliest opportunity. We share this information out of a commitment to openness and respect for the families, two principles which have guided this investigation.
Malaysia Airlines have already spoken to the families of the passengers and crew to inform them of this development. For them, the past few weeks have been heartbreaking; I know this news must be harder still. I urge the media to respect their privacy, and to allow them the space they need at this difficult time.
14.07 Relatives at the Lido Hotel in Beijing are currently being briefed by authorities. A team of police has just entered the building and an ambulance is parked outside the doors, our correspondent Malcolm Moore in Beijing reports.
14.00 BREAKING: The Malaysian prime minister is speaking. He says from new analysis of satellite data, investigators have concluded that Mhl0 "flew along the southern corridor and that its last position was in the middle of the Indian Ocean west of Perth. This is a remote location, far from any possible landing sites. It is therefore with deep sadness and regret that I must inform you that according to this new data, flight Mhl0 ended in the southern Indian Ocean."
Najib Razak says Malaysian authorities will be holding a press conference tomorrow, and that the airline has already informed the families of passengers and crew of these developments. "For them, the past few weeks have been heartbreaking; I know this news must be harder still," says.
13.56 The families of passengers have received a text message from Malaysia Airlines with the following statement:
"Malaysia Airlines deeply regrets that we have to assume beyond any reasonable doubt that Mhl0 has been lost and that none of those on board survived. As you will hear in the next hour from Malaysia's Prime Minister, we must now accept all evidence suggests the plane went down in the Southern Indian Ocean."
13.52 BREAKING: The families have been told that Mhl0 went down in the Indian Ocean and that "no one on board survived". More to follow.
13.50 Malaysian authorities are briefing passengers' families as the country's prime minister prepares to hold an emergency press conference, a government official has said. There are unconfirmed reports that relatives are being booked on flights to Australia.
13.36 As you await the press conference with the Malaysia PM in 25 minutes, take a look at this interactive by the AP newswire on the search the inconclusive leads to date.
13.13 An emergency meeting has been called with the families of passengers in Beijing, to be held in the next hour, Sky News reports. There is no word as yet on what might be announced.
13.08 The last aircraft has departed the search area without any further sightings, the Australian Maritime Safety Authority has said.
Twitter: AMSA News - Last aircraft has departed the search scene without any further sightings. See the interview with AMSA's John Young http://t.co/wplAtbjbmU
13.05 The Royal Australian Air Force P-3 Orion has dropped smoke markers at the locations of the objects sighted this morning:
12.56 From Chinese state news agency Xinhua comes this image of the objects sighted this morning by an Australian Air Force plane:
12.54 We've just heard that the Malaysian prime minister is to hold a press conference at 10pm local (2pm GMT) on "developments" on the missing plane, according to the country's Star newspaper, which cited a government official.
12.45 Watch the latest video from the Telegraph on the sighting of objects in the search area by an RAAF plane today. "It's been the first time that we've actually certified that we've seen something and got photographs". says Flight Lieutenant Captain Josh Williams of the Australian Air Force:
12.17 Read the latest report from Jonathan Pearlman in Kuala Lumpur on the revelation that Fariq Abdul Hamid was on his first outing as a co-pilot on the Boeing 777 without a "check co-pilot" supervising him:
Malaysia Airlines has revealed that Fariq, who joined the airline seven year ago, was just starting to pilot the Boeing 777 and that the ill-fated flight to Beijing on March 8 was only his sixth in the cockpit of a 777 - and his first without a check pilot overseeing him.
"The first five flights, the co-pilot normally flies with what we call the check co-pilot," said Ahmad Jauhari Yahya, the airline's head at a press briefing.
"He actually passed the first five flights. We do not see any problem with him."
12.05 Andrew Thomas of Al Jazeera English was on the RAAF plane that spotted the objects. He reports via Twitter that five objects were seen, four of which were deemed confirmed - seen by two or more people - and two of which were photographed. At least three of the objects were one metre long or more. He says that the first sighting took place around an hour into the search part of the flight and then came at a regular pace for another 1.5 hours.
Twitter: ANDREW THOMAS - I have seen the images of 2 of the objects. Impossible to say what they are Very indistinct in photos. One white and circular
Twitter: ANDREW THOMAS - We saw smoke flares dropped, gps locators too. HMAS Success was v close and will be trying to find and bring inboard objects now #mhl0
11.58 HMS Echo is scheduled to arrive in the southern corridor overnight, joining a number of Chinese and Malaysian ships which have also arrived in the corridor though have not yet reached the search area itself. As HMAS Success is currently the only vessel in the Australian search zone at present, HMS Echo and the others can't arrive a moment too soon.
11.30 As AMSA says the last plane will depart the search area at 11pm tonight, that means there is only half an hour left for today's air efforts. However the HMAS Success will continue to try to retrieve the sighted objects overnight, officials have said.
11.21 Bevan Shields of the Sydney Morning Herald reports that the RAAF plane which spotted the objects in fact saw more items, though only two were photographed:
Twitter: Bevan Shields - Flight Lieutenant Josh Williams has also told media four items were spotted by crew aboard RAAF plane, not two. #mhl0
A news crew on board the RAAF plane reportedly shot footage, which we are working to obtain.
11.05 More than 30 relatives of Mhl0 passengers have been forced to move out of their hotels in Kuala Lumpur to make way for Formula one teams and fans arriving for the Malaysian Grand Prix, Telegraph Sport reports:
Thirty-two family members, including Chinese nationals, have decamped from two hotels near Kuala Lumpur's international airport, which is also close to the Sepang racetrack, hotel and airline officials said on Monday.
"The rooms have been pre-booked before this event happened," one hotel official said. A Malaysian Airlines spokeswoman also confirmed the relatives were moved.
10.56 The moment the Malaysian prime minister, Najib Razak, received a call from Tony Abbott, his Australian counterpart, informing him a spotter plane had located two circular and rectangular objects:
10.33 200kg of lithium batteries was among the cargo onboard Mhl0, Malaysia Airlines has said; it has emphasised however that the batteries were properly packed and stored and posed no danger. The cargo manifest also includes fruit and electrical equipments such as Malaysia-manufactured radios.
10.25 Malaysia Airlines says Fariq Abdul Hamid was on his first flight on a Boeing 777 as a copilot. He had previously passed 5 practice flights with a check pilot.
10.14 Another Malaysia Airlines flight suffered technical problems this morning - the Mhl6 from Kuala Lumpur to South Korea's Incheon forced to make an emergency landing in Hong Kong after an electrical generator malfunctioned. The plane's auxiliary power unit continued to supply electricity, and the plane "landed uneventfully", Malaysia Airlines said. While it may not have any bearing on the disappearance of Mhl0, it may refocus attention on the possibility of mechanical failure.
10.06 Watch today's briefing from the Malaysian Transport minister, at which he announced that an Australian spotter plane had located two objects in the search area:
10.03 Today's sightings hold out particular promise in the search because they are in real time, aviation experts are saying. Whereas the previous sightings by satellite had occurred a few days before they were confirmed, the latest objects were located today, meaning they should be much easier to reach.
Mr Hussein said it was hoped the objects would be retrieved in the next few hours - or, as night is now falling in the search area - tomorrow morning.
09.57 Here's the Malaysian government's press statement from this morning in full:
Mhl0 PRESS BRIEFING BY HISHAMMUDDIN HUSSEIN,
MINISTER OF DEFENCE AND ACTING MINISTER OF TRANSPORT
Introductory statement
The search for Mhl0 continues. Over the past few days, new leads from satellite data have focused our search and rescue operations in the southern corridor. Our partners continue to deploy assets to assist us, as we work to narrow the search areas.
Operational update
Yesterday, 18,500 square nautical miles were searched in the Australian search area.
Two orange objects approximately one metre in length and one white coloured drum were sighted by search aircraft, but remain unidentified and have not been conclusively linked to Mhl0.
HMAS Success detected two radar targets within the search area, but could not locate the targets on further investigation of the area.
Earlier today, a Chinese search plane reportedly sighted objects in the Australian search area. These objects are not in the vicinity of those which were identified by the Australian authorities last week.
A few minutes ago the Prime Minister received a call from the Prime Minister of Australia, who informed him that an Australian search aircraft had located two objects in the Australian search area, one circular and one rectangular.
HMAS Success is in the vicinity and it is possible that the objects could be received within the next few hours, or by tomorrow morning at the latest.
Three search areas, totalling approximately 20,000 square nautical miles, have been identified for operations today. RCC Australia anticipates that 10 aircraft will be used.
HMAS Success remains the only vessel in the search area. A number of Chinese vessels are expected to commence arriving within the search area on 25th March.
3 aircraft - 2 from Japan and 1 from the UAE - have already departed from Subang today and are en route to the southern corridor.
6 Malaysian ships, with 3 ship-borne helicopters, are now in northern part of the southern corridor. 10 Chinese ships are in the southern corridor, carrying out search and rescue operations. HMS Echo is currently refuelling in the Maldives and will be sailing to the southern corridor this evening.
In the northern corridor, Turkmenistan have confirmed they have not had any sightings of Mhl0 on their radar. Each piece of information we receive from our partners in the northern corridor helps us to continuously narrow the corridor.
Satellite images
New leads into Mhl0's possible location have come from satellite data. This was one of the four tools we identified that could narrow the search area, along with surveillance radar data, increasing surface and air assets, and bringing in more technical experts.
The most recent images were obtained by French satellites, which captured radar images of potential objects in the vicinity of the southern corridor on 21st March. These images were received by Malaysia on the evening of the 22nd March, and were relayed to RCC Australia on the morning of the 23rd March, as they are leading the search in that particular area of the southern corridor.
This morning we have received a further set of images from French satellites, this time captured by cameras. These images were taken yesterday and have been relayed to RCC Australia.
Family briefings
Yesterday, the high-level team met with families in Beijing for more than eight hours.
The families asked many questions, and made detailed requests for radar readings and other data. Some of these questions could not be answered, and some of the data they requested was still being held by the investigation, as is standard procedure in investigations of this sort.
After meeting with the families for a total of more than twelve hours, and taking hundreds of questions, the high-level team has returned to Kuala Lumpur to discuss the matters raised at the meetings. They will return to Beijing tomorrow to continue.
The briefings in Kuala Lumpur over the last two days went smoothly, and the families responded as positively as could be expected, with the families engaging with representatives from the relevant authorities.
It has always been our intention to keep the families as fully informed as possible. We continue to do so.
Specific questions
There are a few specific questions I would like to respond to.
On the police investigation, we can confirm that the police have interviewed more than a hundred people, including families of both the pilot and co-pilot.
As far as the transcript is concerned, the technical committee is considering releasing it and we will keep you informed about the decision.
The Inspector General of the Police will attend tomorrow's press conference to answer further questions on the investigation.
We can also confirm that Mhl0 was carrying wooden pallets. However, there is as yet no evidence that these are related to the wooden pallets reportedly sighted in the Australian search area.
Concluding remarks
The search for Mhl0 has taken us halfway around the world. At the moment there are new leads, but nothing conclusive. Our thoughts continue to be with the families who are still waiting for news. In the meantime, we are grateful for the on-going co-operation shown by our partners in this multinational search.
09.51 The Malaysian transport minister is addressing the cause of Mhl0's disappearance. He says that parallel investigations are ongoing and that both mechanical failure and a deliberate act are still being considered.
09.48 Here's the full statement from the Australian Maritime Safety Authority (AMSA) on this morning's sighting of two objects. The agency says the first object was grey or green, and circular, the second orange and rectangular.
The Australian Maritime Safety Authority can advise objects have been located by a Royal Australian Air Force P3 Orion.
HMAS Success is on scene and is attempting to locate the objects in the search for missing Malaysia Aircraft flight Mhl0.
The objects were spotted in the search area about 2500 kilometres south-west of Perth by the RAAF Orion about 2.45pm (AEDT).
The crew on board the Orion reported seeing two objects - the first a grey or green circular object and the second an orange rectangular object.
The objects identified by the RAAF Orion are separate to the objects reported by the Chinese Ilyushin IL-76 to AMSA earlier today.
The objects reported by the Chinese were also within today's search area.
The US Navy P8 Poseidon aircraft sought to relocate the objects reported by the Chinese aircraft but were unable to do so.
The US Navy P8 is remains in the search area, while a second RAAF P3 and a Japanese P3 are en route to their assigned search areas.
The last of these aircraft will depart the search area about 11pm (AEDT).
09.43 Aviation experts on the BBC are discussing what these orange objects might be - could they be life rafts? Or the emergency exit slides, which could have inflated on impact with the water?
09.42 More detail on the objects spotted by a Chinese plane this morning. The IL-76 plane saw "white, square floating objects" and was able to take photographs, according to a Chinese foreign ministry spokesman, Hong Lei, says. China is "rushing to analyse" the images, he said.
09.37 The Malaysian transport minister, Hishammuddin Hussein, is giving a briefing in Kuala Lumpur. He has announced that a circular and a rectangular object have been detected by planes in the Australian search area and that ships are currently trying to reach them. The two objects are said to be orange in colour.
He has also confirmed, as was suggested by an anonymous Malaysia Airlines official yesterday, that Mhl0 was carrying wooden pallets. But, he added: "There is as yet no evidence that these are related to the pallets reported in the Australian search area"
09.22 We are waiting for various press conferences to update us on the latest in the search for Mhl0. Meanwhile the Associated Press (AP) gives us a bit more on the US Pacific command's black box locator that is being sent to the search area.
The Towed Pinger Locator, which is pulled behind a vessel at slow speeds, has highly sensitive listening capability so that if the wreck site is located, it can hear the black box pinger down to a depth of about 20,000 feet (6,100 meters).
Cmdr. Chris Budde, a U.S. Seventh Fleet operations officer, said in a statement: "This movement is simply a prudent effort to preposition equipment and trained personnel closer to the search area so that if debris is found we will be able to respond as quickly as possible since the battery life of the black box's pinger is limited."
The ocean depth in the search area ranges between 1,150 meters (3,770 feet) and 7,000 meters (23,000 feet).
An Australian defence official said an Australian navy support vessel, the Ocean Shield, was also moving into the search zone and would arrive in three or four days. The ship is equipped with acoustic detection equipment that can search for the missing plane's black box.
08.33 We are still waiting for any confirmation on exactly what the Chinese aircraft may have spotted. Reuters though says that a U.S. Navy P-8 Poseidon, the most advanced search aircraft in the world, had been unable to find objects spotted by the Chinese.
An Australian Maritime Safety Authority spokeswoman said in an emailed response: "A US Navy P-8 Poseidon aircraft was tasked to investigate reported object sightings by the Chinese aircraft made at 33,000 ft. The objects were spotted by the Chinese aircraft as it was heading back to Perth. Drift modelling was undertaken on the sighting. The P-8 was unable to relocate the reported objects."
07.41 News just in: Another Malaysian Airline flight was diverted to Hong Kong this morning for emergency landing after experiencing electrical problems. The airline says the diversion was caused by 'an inoperative aircraft generator, which supplies normal electrical power'
07.37 The latest update from Tom Phillips in Shanghai and Jonathan Pearlman in Kuala Lumpur: a Chinese ship has been sent to an area in the south Indian Ocean where a Chinese search team spotted "suspicious objects" believed to be debris from the missing Malaysia Airlines flight.
As new reports indicated the plane flew low before disappearing, crew aboard a Chinese IL-76 plane saw "two relatively big floating objects" and "many" smaller white objects "within a radius of several kilometres", according to a reporter from Xinhua, China's official news agency, who was on board.
06.10 To recap on the main developments over the last few hours:
A Chinese plane crew has spotted a white, square-shaped object and other items in an area identified by satellite imagery as containing possible debris from the missing Malaysian airliner, Xinhua News agency said. A Chinese ship was headed toward the area to investigate.
The US Pacific command said it was sending a Towed Pinger Locator to the region. The equipment, which is pulled behind a vessel at slow speeds, has highly sensitive listening capability that can detect pings from a plane's so-called black box down to a depth of 20,000 feet (6,100 meters).
05.55 The Australian Bureau of Meteorology has emailed over a report on the weather conditions in the search zone:
A rain band moving through the search area today will see increased winds, low cloud and a reduction in visibility. Tomorrow, a cold front is forecast to move through the search area from the west, also bringing showers, low cloud and a reduction in visibility.
Tropical Cyclone Gillian will not have an impact the search area. Tropical Cyclone Gillian is forecast to weaken to a tropical low over the next few days
05.22 China has diverted its icebreaker ship, the Xuelong, or Snow Dragon, toward the location where the debris was spotted. From 10,000 metres (33,000 feet), the spotters saw two larger floating objects and some smaller, white debris scattered over several square miles, the report said.
05.10 Australian search authorities have said they have been advised about objects spotted by Chinese aircraft hunting for any sign of a missing Malaysian airliner and will be trying to locate them in the remote southern Indian Ocean.
Official Chinese news agency Xinhua earlier reported the crew of a IL-76 aircraft spotted two "relatively big" floating objects and several smaller white ones dispersed over several kilometres.
"AMSA advised about reported objects sighted by Chinese aircraft. Reported objects in today's search area. Attempts will be made to relocate," the Australian Maritime Safety Authority (AMSA) said on its Twitter feed.
04.40 As we await more news on the "suspicious objects" spotted by a Chinese plane, here is a breakdown of the aircraft currently involved in the search:
AUSTRALIA
Four military P3 Orion planes; four non-military jets; the navy supply ship HMAS Success.
CHINA
Two Ilyushin IL-76 planes; warships Kunlunshan, Haikou and Qiandaohu; icebreaker Snow Dragon.
JAPAN
Two P3 Orion planes.
NEW ZEALAND
One military P3 Orion plane.
UNITED STATES:
One military P8 Poseidon plane.
04.23 Xinhua says the "white and square" objects were spotted by searchers aboard a Chinese Ilyushin-76 plane.
"The crew has reported the coordinates - 95.1113 degrees east and 42.5453 south - to the Australian command centre as well as Chinese icebreaker Xuelong, which is en route to the sea area."
04.21 A little bit more information on the sighting is emerging on Twitter:
Twitter: Michael van Poppel - Xinhua: Chinese plane spotted "a number of white floating objects" in southern Indian Ocean
04.10 Tom Phillips, our correspondent in Shanghai, has a bit more detail on the sighting:
That sighting seems to have been made by a Chinese IL-76 aircraft which took off from Perth earlier today. It is flying in an area around
2,500 km west of Perth, says Xinhua, which has a reporter on board. The plane is flying at a height of just over 1,000 ft.
China has sent two of these IL-76 planes to the search zone.
04.05 Breaking news from Chinese news agency Xinhua:
FLASH: CHINESE AIRBORNE Mhl0 SEARCHERS FIND SUSPICIOUS OBJECTS IN S. INDIAN OCEAN
04.00 The US Navy has said it is sending a black box locator to an area of the southern Indian Ocean being scoured for the missing Malaysian jet, following a cluster of possible sightings of debris over the weekend.
The navy called the move a "precautionary measure" in case those sightings confirm the location of the aircraft which disappeared on March 8 with 239 people on board.
"If a debris field is confirmed, The Navy's Towed Pinger Locator 25 will add a significant advantage in locating the missing Malaysian aircraft's black box," Commander William Marks, a spokesman for the US Seventh Fleet, said in a statement.
The locator system relies on acoustic signals to help find flight recorders - also known as black boxes - on downed navy and commercial aircraft to a maximum depth of 20,000 feet (6,000 metres), he added.
However, the statement cautioned that the deployment did not mean the missing jet's location had been confirmed.
"Please note that movement of the Towed Pinger Locator into the region is not an indication that we have confirmed a debris field," it said.
"It's a precautionary measure so that if we do find debris, we'll be ready to deploy the equipment to listen for the black box."
03.30 CNN reports that authorities have released new details on what may have happened in the plane's cockpit :
Military radar tracking shows that the aircraft changed altitude after making a sharp turn over the South China Sea as it headed toward the Strait of Malacca, a source close to the investigation into the missing flight told CNN. The plane flew as low as 12,000 feet at some point before it disappeared from radar, according to the source.
The sharp turn seemed to be intentional, the source said.
The official, who is not authorised to speak to the media, told CNN that the area the plane flew in after the turn is a heavily trafficked air corridor and that flying at 12,000 feet would have kept the jet well out of the way of that traffic.
02.55 US news website ABC has a moving story about the girlfriend of an American passenger aboard missing Malaysia Airlines Flight 370 who has been writing a series of love notes to her boyfriend on her Facebook page.
Sarah Hamil Bajc has used the notes to tell Philip Wood about the things he has missed since the plane disappeared March 8.
Dearest Love ... This is the second Saturday of your disappearance. I cannot remember much of the first, but I have spent today remembering you. I have scrolled through a very long rolodex of happy memories ... we have so much fun together. And so much peace together. And so much love. You have become a permanent part of me.
02.20 An AMSA spokesman interviewed by Reuters has said that AMSA is still examining French radar images showing potential floating debris and have not yet shifted the search for a missing Malaysian jetliner in the southern Indian Ocean further north to look for the objects.
We only recently got this information and we are still examining it.
We are taking it into account but at this stage we are still focused on the same search area. We are taking every bit of information seriously and examining it and cross-referencing it with every other bit of information.
01.40 An aviation expert has told Australian news website news.com.au that there is no reason why Malaysia Airlines should keep the cargo onboard flight Mhl0 a secret . Strategic Aviation Solutions chairman Neil Hansford said:
To me, there is no reason why they wouldn't declare the cargo manifest unless you've got something to hide.
There is no reason you wouldn't have given it to AMSA (the Australian Maritime Safety Authority) on the first day of the search.
01.00 AMSA has released a chart of the planned search area for the day .
00.30 Acting Australian PM Warren Truss has been speaking to ABC Radio about the progress of the search.
He said the latest potential sighting of debris, by a French satellite, was about 850 kilometres north of where aircraft and ships have been looking since Thursday.
"Certainly the area where debris has been picked up by satellites is of particular interest, and they're the focus of a lot of the searching.
"The French sighting is I guess a piece of new material because that is in a completely different location. That is about 850 kilometres north of our current search area.
"So we need to check that out as well."
While Malaysian authorities initially said the latest data came in the form of images, France's foreign ministry clarified this, saying it came in the form of "satellite-generated radar echoes".
A radar echo is an electronic signal that contains information about the location and distance of the object which bounces the signal back.
Mr Truss cautioned that "we still don't know for certain that the aircraft is even in this area".
"We're just, I guess, clutching at whatever little piece of information comes along to try and find a place where we might be able to concentrate the efforts," he added.
He said Sunday's search proved "fruitless" and warned of deteriorating weather, stirred up by Tropical Cyclone Gillian which is expected to track at least 1,000 kilometres north of the search area.
"Clearly it won't be cyclonic when it gets down into the freezing waters that we're dealing with with this search," Mr Truss said.
"But certainly it could stir up less favourable weather." '
00.05 The Australian Maritime Safety Authority (AMSA), the body coordinating the search for the missing plane, has announced that today's search is now underway with 10 aircraft scouring the southern Indian Ocean for any sign of potential debris. Here is their latest statement in full:
The search for the missing Malaysia Airlines aircraft in the Australian Search and Rescue Region has resumed this morning, with further aircraft joining the operation out of Perth.
The Australian Maritime Safety Authority (AMSA) reiterates this is a challenging search operation. The flight has been missing since March 8 and AMSA continues to hold the gravest of concerns for the passengers and crew on board the missing flight.
AMSA is using all satellite imagery and information available in its search area development. Both civil aircraft engaged by AMSA and military aircraft from Australia, New Zealand, the United States, China and Japan are all assisting in the ongoing search operation to provide the best chance of locating objects captured by satellite imagery with the naked eye.
AMSA has tasked a total of 10 aircraft today to search for possible objects in the search area about 2500 kilometres south-west of Perth.
The weather forecast in the search area is expected to deteriorate with rain likely.
Today's search is split into two areas within the same proximity covering a cumulative 68,500 square kilometres.
Three civil aircraft will be involved in search activities today. These are two Bombardier Global Express planes and an Airbus aircraft.
A total of 20 State Emergency Service (SES) volunteers from Western Australia will again be air observers on board the civil aircraft. Ten volunteers will be on board the Airbus, and five volunteers will be on each of the Bombardier Global Expressaircraft.
All three civil aircraft will also have an AeroRescue Aviation Mission Coordinator on board. Aerorescue is AMSA's contracted provider of dedicated search and rescue services from locations across Australia.
Two Ilyushin IL-76 aircraft from China have been tasked by AMSA to join today's search, together with two P3 Orion aircraft from Japan. The two Chinese aircraft are now en route to the search area.
The United States Navy P8 Poseidon will also be a part of today's search activities, along with two Royal Australian Air Force (RAAF) P3 Orion aircraft.
Departure times of aircraft will be provided later today.
HMAS Success remains in the search area. A number of Chinese ships are en route to the search area to assist in the location of objects possibly related to the search.
00.00 Hello again and welcome to our live coverage of the search for Mhl0. To recap yesterday's events, here is our main story on the woman whose anguish over her missing son captured the agony of families of those onboard the plane and news of a French satellite spotting more potential debris .
Also in the Telegraph today is a piece by novelist Guy Walters about why the world is so fascinated with the fate of Mhl0 :
What is the source of our fascination with Mhl0? There are of course some easy answers. These might include a need to help the grieving process, and a practical wish to improve safety. A more complicated answer would involve that word "closure", a desire to see how the story ends, to follow a narrative arc through to the very end.
When I was writing my first thriller, my editor was insistent that I tied up all the loose ends in the final chapter. To do so, she argued, would bring the type of ending that was satisfying for the reader. At the time, I baulked - and I still do - because I do not think it necessarily the job of writers to bring satisfaction. But her point was fair. People do want closure, and they want it badly.
]]></text></news-item>