<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-MW81-F0JP-W3K2"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Newman man linked to Obeid - EXCLUSIVE -</title><source>The Australian</source><author>MICHAEL McKENNA, QUEENSLAND POLITICAL EDITOR</author><text><![CDATA[QUEENSLAND'S top public servant went into business last year with the Obeid family and Australian Water Holdings directors after it had already emerged that his fellow company owners were at the centre of a NSW corruption inquiry.
Premier Campbell Newman's hand-picked director-general of the Department of Premier and Cabinet, Jon Grayson, was one of six shareholders -- including the son and nephew of disgraced Labor powerbroker Eddie Obeid and then boss of AWH, Nick Di Girolamo -- in Gasfields Water and Waste Services when it was incorporated in May.
The company was set up after the NSW Independent Commission against Corruption had already raised questions about the dealings between AWH and the state-owned Sydney Water, as well as raising links to the Obeids.
The company's only director is Dennis Jabour, Mr Obeid's nephew, who has also worked in a senior role with AWH.
In August, Mr Di Girolamo and Eddie Obeid Jr -- the son of the former NSW MP -- transferred their shares to Mr Jabour.
Last year, Mr Jabour gave evidence at the ICAC hearings after it was revealed his uncle had lobbied successive NSW ministers to renew leases for the Jabour family restaurants at Sydney's Circular Quay, without telling them that his family owned the businesses.
Mr Grayson remains one of only four shareholders in the company, which also includes Tony Bellas, a former chief executive at state-owned energy companies in Queensland, and Wayne Myers, a former energy sector executive with ties to Queensland Labor.
The ICAC hearings have heard how AWH had began expanding into Queensland in 2009, with the creation of Australian Water Queensland, using Sydney Water funds to cover many of their expenses.
Mr Myers and Mr Bellas were both directors of Australian Water Queensland, which was deregistered last December.
It is the second time that Mr Grayson has been linked with the Obeid family, which ICAC alleges has a secret shareholding in AWH.
Last year, The Australian revealed that Mr Grayson owned 25 per cent of Gasfields Water Management, a Queensland coal-seam gas services business, with AWH holding the remaining 75 per cent.
A spokesman for Mr Newman said last night that the new company had been created in May as a result of a restructure of Gasfields Water Management to ``exit from the affairs of Australian Water Holdings''.
Gasfields Water Management was not deregistered until December.
``This company came about through a restructure of Gasfield Water Management Pty Ltd, and it has been disclosed in his declaration of interest and to the integrity commissioner,'' the spokesman said.
``It is on the public record that both Eddie Obeid and Nick Di Girolamo are no longer shareholders.''
]]></text></news-item>