<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-MW81-F0JP-W3JC"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>It's the law of unintended consequences - EXCLUSIVE -</title><source>The Australian</source><author>CHRIS MERRITT, LEGAL AFFAIRS EDITOR</author><text><![CDATA[BARRING a sudden reversal by the Abbott government, Federal Court judge Mordecai Bromberg is about to enter an exclusive club: he will soon become one of the few judges whose rulings have led to the destruction of a body of law.
Before his 2011 ruling against News Corp Australia columnist Andrew Bolt, hundreds of claims of racial vilification had been quietly processed over 20 years using a procedure that favoured those who claimed they had been vilified. It was mostly done behind closed doors at the Australian Human Rights Commission, with only about 5 per cent of respondents braving a hearing before a court.
After Justice Bromberg's ruling against Bolt, the notoriety of the case and the clarity of the judgment meant a much wider audience became aware of the nature of the law governing racial vilification.
That culminated in this week's release by Attorney-General George Brandis of a draft plan that would introduce a system that would oblige the courts and the Human Rights Commission to adopt a procedure that gives priority to community standards.
The Brandis plan says liability for speech that vilifies or intimidates people because of their race is to be determined ``by the standards of an ordinary reasonable member of the Australian community, not by the standards of any particular group''. This would reverse two decades of legal practice in which community standards had limited relevance. The potential liability of those accused of racial vilification was being judged from the perspective of a reasonable representative of those claiming they had been vilified. Legal academic Simon Rice has no doubt the Bolt judgment is responsible for the push to change the law.
``It lit the match -- and it took off and ran,'' said Professor Rice who is co-author of Anti-Discrimination Law in Australia.
This is not the first time rulings by Justice Bromberg have had an impact. In December he determined that Toyota workers
Continued on Page 2
Continued from Page 1
should not be allowed to vote on whether they wanted to consider changes to their workplace agreement. Soon after, Paul Sheehan wrote in The Sydney Morning Herald that Justice Bromberg had ``probably signed the death warrant of the Australian vehicle manufacturing industry''.
In February, Toyota announced it would close its Melbourne manufacturing operations from 2017.
Like some others who joined the Federal Court during the Rudd-Gillard years, Justice Bromberg has strong Labor credentials. He sees the judiciary as a way of delivering what he describes as social justice.
He joined the court in 2009, eight years after failing in an attempt to secure Labor Party preselection for a federal seat.
At his ceremonial welcome to the bench he listed the reasons he had accepted judicial appointment. They included ``my impassioned commitment to the rule of law and to the continued contribution this court makes to upholding the law as an instrument of social justice''.
He started his legal career at Slater & Gordon, Julia Gillard's old firm, where his contemporaries included Bernard Murphy, who joined the Federal Court in 2011.
The judge yesterday declined an invitation to discuss section 18C and the government's proposed changes. Professor Rice, who has criticised the government's proposed changes, said Justice Bromberg's ruling was ``within bounds'' and there was good authority to support his approach in determining liability based on a hypothetical reasonable representative of ``the target group''.
Legal academic Spencer Zifcak -- who was one of the first to call for section 18C to be changed -- said it was wrong to see Justice Bromberg's decision as a departure from the pattern of previous decisions. The judge had merely applied the law as set down in the Racial Discrimination Act.
Professor Zifcak had one caveat. ``Bromberg made one fundamental error and that was to give some weight to the fact Bolt had expressed himself in inflammatory terms,'' he said.
``But apart from that, it is a good judgment overall. But that doesn't mean the statute was good. It just means the decision, under the terms of the statute, was a reasonable decision.''
Professor Zifcak, who is based at the Australian Catholic University, is a former president of Liberty Victoria. He provided a briefing on Monday for the Coalition backbench and presented a paper on the operation of section 18C.
The draft plan outlined by the government on Tuesday would simplify the defences to section 18C by eliminating the requirement for ``reasonableness'' and ``good faith''.
In the Bolt case, these requirements meant Justice Bromberg believed he was required to examine the tone of Bolt's articles and to question the absence of material the judge believed should have been included in the articles.
The ability of judges to impartially assess this requirement for ``reasonableness'' has been subject to criticism in the US, according to Mirko Bagaric, dean of law at Deakin University. In remarks on the US research, not the Bolt case, Professor Bagaric said that whenever legislation contained a requirement for reasonableness ``it introduces the capacity for judges to decide matters on the basis of their pre-existing sentiments''.
``There is an enormous amount of evidence in the US regarding the unconscious biases and prejudices judges bring to the task when they make discretionary decisions,'' he said.
``They are affected by their political views, their religious views, and impacted by things such as whether they make a decision before lunch or after lunch.
``When you have such a broad brush as this, it is quite easy for two judges to reach opposite conclusions, and that is often informed by their implicit biases.''
]]></text></news-item>