<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-G2Y1-F0NV-F3GM"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>How safe is new Fayette pipeline?</title><source>Herald-Standard (Uniontown, Pennsylvania)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Relative to Marcellus Shale natural gas development, the major concern involves accidents at gas well sites, gathering lines and the interstate transportation of hazardous materials.
(Editor's note: This is the second column in a two-part series)
Relative to Marcellus shale natural gas development, the major concern involves accidents at gas well sites, gathering lines and the interstate transportation of hazardous materials.
Because a pipeline failure could pose a significant risk to the people and the sensitive environment, increased public awareness of pipeline safety and appropriate regulation is needed. Complicating the onset of a new pipeline network to meet demands are problems with the existing pipeline infrastructure, it's old and inadequate having been installed anywhere from 100 years ago in some areas of Fayette County.
In 2008, the Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration studied proximity of structures next to pipelines. The result created advisory standards for new development around existing pipelines.
Pipeline Informed Planning Alliance (PIPA) was put in place and suggested that extra precautions be taken and extra planning to be done if buildings are within 660 feet to 1,000 feet on either side of a pipeline. The pipeline blast radius is the distance that the fire from an explosion consumes, measured in feet from the epicenter to the outer edge of the burned area.
The rupture of a high pressure natural gas pipeline can lead to outcomes that can pose a significant threat to people and property in the immediate vicinity of the failure location. The dominant hazard is thermal radiation from a sustained fire and estimate of ground area affected by the heat intensity associated with rupture failure of the pipe where escaping gas is assumed to feed the fire that ignites very soon after pipeline failure.
For example; An accident involving a 30-inch pipeline in Louisiana burned an area of 1,450 feet long by 350 feet wide with (furthest fire extent of 950 feet) while operating at 1016 PSI which claimed five lives within 65 feet and 23 serious injuries within 800 feet.
Fear of explosion from this new 36-inch Spectra high pressure pipeline is well placed given the nationwide pipeline accidents resulted in on average, a death every three weeks, injures or burns more than once a week.
Private companies such as Spectra Energy and Texas Eastern own and operate the pipelines and lease it to Chevron for interstate transmission. These companies do not pay a specific tax associated with the right-of-way/easements and the actual transportation of the Marcellus Shale gas. Pipeline companies do not pay impact fees. Property owners are left paying taxes on land that is rendered useless.
There is a safety issue with Spectra Energy. The PennDOT pipeline division and PHMSA inspectors cited Spectra for 17 inadequacies in its pipeline safety operations and procedures in the classes 2-4. The inspection uncovered problems with pipeline surveillance, emergency plans and welding procedures. Class 1 is exempt from these types of inspections.
Texas Eastern, a subsidiary of Spectra Energy that proposes to build the new pipeline in Fayette County received the federal Environmental Protection Agency's (EPA) seventh highest federal penality assessment on record for PCB contamination.
Our area is classified as Class 1, so we would be excluded from all of the above safety issues as they do not apply to Class 1. Spectra Energy would operate and maintain the newly constructed pipeline and facilities in the same manner as they currently operate and maintain their existing systems. Class 1 will not be covered by the rules that govern the other classes.
Did you know that Spectra Energy is excluded from regulations of the "Clean Air and Clean Water Acts"? Given Spectra's past history, this is an assurance not of safety but of calamity.
Cyndi Kumor is a resident of Menallen Township.
.
]]></text></news-item>