<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-5SW1-JCW9-X2K2"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Mudslide warning given 15 years ago</title><source>Chicago Sun-Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ARLINGTON, Wash. - A scientist working for the government had warned 15 years ago about the potential for a catastrophic landslide in the fishing village where the collapse of a rain-soaked hillside over the weekend killed at least 16 people and left scores missing.
Rescue workers late Tuesday said they believe they found eight additional bodies. Word of the 1999 report raised questions about why residents were allowed to build homes on the hill and whether officials had taken proper precautions. "I knew it would fail catastrophically in a large magnitude event," though not when it would happen, said Daniel Miller, a geomorphologist who was hired by the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers to do the study. "I was not surprised." Patricia Graesser, a spokeswoman for the Army Corps in Seattle, said it appears that the report was intended not as a risk assessment, but as a feasibility study for ecosystem restoration. Asked whether the agency should have done anything with the information, she said: "We don't have jurisdiction to do anything. We don't do zoning. That's a local responsibility." Kuala Lumpur, malaysia Relatives of Flight 370 victims protest in China Frustration over the fate of Flight 370 mounted Tuesday, with gale-force winds delaying the search in the rough and remote seas off western Australia, and angry relatives shouting "Liars!" in the streets of Beijing about Malaysia's declaration that the plane went down with all aboard. washington Birth control rule seemsto divide Supreme Court Seemingly divided, the Supreme Court struggled Tuesday with the question of whether companies have religious rights, a case challenging President Barack Obama's health overhaul and its guarantee of birth control in employees' preventive care plans. Peppering attorneys with questions in a 90-minute argument, the justices weighed the rights of for-profit companies against the rights of female employees. Mexico city Prosecutors: Pimp holding kids forced moms into prostitution Mexican prosecutors say they have freed two children held by pimps who used their hold over the children to force their mothers into prostitution in the United States. The raid announced Tuesday appears to confirm one of the most chilling allegations about the prostitution trade operated by organized gangs in central Mexico: that some women are forced into sex for hire because they fear their children will be harmed if they rebel or attempt escape. The Hague, netherlands Obama concedes Russia unlikely to leave Crimea President Barack Obama acknowledged for the first time Tuesday that Russia is unlikely to surrender control of the strategically important peninsula it annexed from Ukraine, conceding that Western condemnations have had little effect on Vladimir Putin. Obama insisted the international community would never recognize Russia's takeover of Crimea. But he and European leaders said a military response against Moscow was unlikely. The leaders focused much of their attention on keeping Russia from expanding elsewhere in Ukraine. Copenhagen, denmark Zoo that killed healthy giraffe kills 4 lions A Danish zoo that faced protests for killing a healthy giraffe to prevent inbreeding says it has put down four lions, including two cubs, to make room for a new male lion. Citing the "pride's natural structure and behavior," the Copenhagen Zoo said Tuesday that two old lions had been euthanized as part of a generational shift. It said the cubs were also put down because they were not old enough to fend for themselves and "anyway would have been killed by the new male lion." Phoenix Judge spares life of dog that mauled child A Phoenix judge has spared the life of a pit bull after it mauled a 4-year-old boy last month and touched off a polarizing Internet debate on mercy, blame and animal violence. Municipal Court Judge Deborah Griffin ruled Tuesday that the dog named Mickey must be neutered, defanged and microchipped. The Feb. 20 attack left 4-year-old Kevin Vicente with a broken eye socket and jaw. Caracas, venezuela Venezuelan leader sayscoup plot generals arrested Venezuelan President Nicolas Maduro has added three generals to the growing list of people and entities he accuses of plotting against him. Maduro announced Tuesday that his socialist administration had brought three air force generals before a military tribunal on charges of plotting a coup amid the anti-government protests wracking the country.
]]></text></news-item>