<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-RFK1-DYRV-303K"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>EU slaps seafood trade ban on Belize over illegal fishing</title><source>BBC Monitoring Latin America - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Text of report by Caribbean Media Corporation news agency website
BRUSSELS, Mar 25, CMC -The European Union in one of its toughest move to eradicate illegal fishing, has blacklisted Belize and two other countries, effectively banning their products from the world's most valuable seafood market.
The EU said that the decision, which also targeted Cambodia and Guinea, resulted from those countries "acting insufficiently against illegal fishing.
"EU states will now be required to ban their fish imports and EU vessels required to stay out of their waters," the EU said in a statement.
EU's Fisheries Commissioner Maria Damanaki described the decisions as "historic" adding "I want EU citizens to know that the fish they consume is sustainable, wherever it comes from".
Damanaki said illegal fishing is estimated to account for 15 per cent of world catches, or an estimated Euro10 billion (One Euro = 1.29 dollar cents) annually.
She said the EU imports 65 per cent of its seafood.
The EU said the three countries were among eight nations warned in late 2012 to take action against illegal fishing or face such action.
The European Commission considered that the five other nations warned - Panama, Fiji, Togo, Sri Lanka and Vanuatu - had made "significant progress, but the Commission is continuing to monitor the situation".
Another three countries - South Korea, Ghana and Curacao - received warning "yellow cards" in November and are currently being evaluated, the EU said.
Meanwhile, the EU's decision has won swift praise from environmental groups.
"Illegal, unreported and unregulated fishing depletes fish stocks, damages marine ecosystems, puts legitimate fishers at an unfair disadvantage and jeopardises the livelihoods of some of the world's most vulnerable communities," said the World Wide Fund for Nature (WWF), Oceana, the Pew Charitable Trusts and the Environmental Justice Foundation in a joint statement.
Source: Caribbean Media Corporation news agency website, Bridgetown, in English 1350 gmt 25 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>