<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-PC51-JCBD-K0N9"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>EU regulators raid Faurecia, Eberspacher, Tenneco in price-fixing probe</title><source>IHS Global Insight</source><author>Ian Fletcher</author><text><![CDATA[European Union (EU) regulators have raided several automotive exhaust systems suppliers yesterday (25 March), in relation to allegedly violating antitrust rules, reports Reuters. The European Commission said in a statement that it could confirm that "officials undertook unannounced inspections at the premises of companies active in the automotive exhaust systems industry in several Member States." It added that it "has concerns that the companies concerned may have violated EU antitrust rules that prohibit cartels and restrictive business practices and/or abuse of a dominant market position (Articles 101 and 102 respectively of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union)." Faurecia, Eberspacher and Tenneco have all confirmed that they were included in the raids, with the latter stating that as well as the EU regulator raiding its Edenkoben (Germany) administrative facility it has also received a related subpoena from the US Department of Justice (DOJ).
Significance:The unannounced investigation is a preliminary step into suspected anti-competitive practices, although the commission added that raids do not mean that these suppliers are guilty of anti-competitive behaviour. Nevertheless, antitrust regulators in major automotive markets such as Japan, South Korea, Europe and the United States have stepped up investigations on price-fixing in auto parts industry. Last week, the European Commission found six companies as being involved in fixing prices of automotive bearings, and imposed a combined fine of EUR953 million (USD1.32 billion) on five suppliers while the sixth was let off without a fine for blowing the whistle on the cartel. In the United States, the DOJ has charged 23 companies and 26 executives. These companies and executives have agreed to pay a total of USD1.8 billion in fines. As a part of plea agreement, some executives have even agreed to serve prison terms in the United States. Noting the growing issue, earlier this year EU Competition Commissioner Joaquin Almunia said that price-fixing among auto suppliers had "attained an unbelievable magnitude, affecting virtually any part a car was made of". He reiterated this last week, stating, "we will not stop here. We are still investigating suspected cartels for airbags as well as lighting systems of cars, to mention a few examples."
]]></text></news-item>