<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-W2H1-DXH0-K31V"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Graft, plunder charges filed vs present, former HGC execs</title><source>Business Mirror (Philippines)</source><author> Jovee Marie N. dela Cruz</author><text><![CDATA[A LAWYER on Wednesday filed graft and plunder charges before the Ombudsman against present and former officials of the Home Guaranty Corp. (HGC).
In a seven-page complaint, lawyer Alan Paguia said HGC President Manuel Sanchez and his immediate predecessor, Gonzalo Benjamin Bongolan, violated Republic Act (RA) 7080, or The Anti-Plunder law, and RA 3019, or the Anti-Graft and Corrupt Practices Act, which resulted in "huge financial losses" by HGC. Sanchez was appointed to the HGC by President Aquino in September 2010. He replaced Bongolan.
HGC performs a vital role in the implementation of the country's housing program by providing risk coverage or guarantees and fiscal incentives to banks and financial institutions to grant housing development loans and home financing to qualified Filipinos.
Paguia cited the annual report by the Commission on Audit (COA) on the HGC's financial and management performance from 2009 to 2011 as basis in pointing to the alleged specific acts of mismanagement and questionable financial decisions made by Sanchez and Bongolan as HGC top officials.
"I was compelled to file this case because I was worried that these abuses happening at the HGC may end up forgotten and neglected," Paguia said after filing the complaint.
"Everyone seemed focused on the abuses of the pork-barrel fund to the neglect of other public officials also being found by the COA to have committed grave abuse of discretion and authority for personal gain," he added.
HGC is mandated by its charter, RA 8763, or the Home Guaranty Corp. Act of 2000, to operate a credit guaranty program in support of the government's effort to promote housing ownership by providing risk guarantees and fiscal incentives for housing credits coming from financial institutions.
Based on COA reports, Paguia listed alleged specific acts of abuse of power and authority committed by Sanchez in 2010 and specific violations of the law allegedly committed by Bongolan in 2009.
Investments in stocks and bonds
ON the part of Bongolan, the COA auditors took him to task for, among others, increasing HGC's investment in private shares of stocks and bonds from P3 million to P734 million contrary to Section 22 of its charter and the provisions of the 2009 General Appropriations Act, Paguia said.
The lawyer said Bongolan then allegedly made a turnaround and used the portion of the interest income from these investments to reward himself and other HGC officials some P9.3 million in "monetary incentive awards."
The COA said it is contrary to civil service rules, Section 5 of Presidential Degree 1597 and Memorandum 20 signed by then-President Gloria Macapagal- Arroyo, mandating clearance from the Office of the President for such expenses, Paguia added.
He added that contrary to the said laws, Bongolan authorized the use of P22.2 million for the HGC's motor vehicles purchase plan for its officials.
P415-million retirement plan
THE COA, Paguia noted, also questioned and disallowed more than P415 million disbursed by the HGC for its retirement plan for being contrary to Teves Retirement law (RA 4968).
He said the HGC allegedly lost some P247 million over the sale of three so-called Apec villas and 52 quadruplex units when these were sold for a measly P41.5 million and P48 million, respectively.
The COA said the villas were worth more than P133 million, while the quadruplex units have a recorded cost of more than P204 million.
During Bongolan's watch, the HGC also piled up losses reaching P9.8 billion as of 2009, Paguia also said.
In the case of Sanchez, Paguia said the HGC's accumulated deficit ballooned further to P12.7 billion as of 2011, which "cast doubt on its ability to provide a viable shelter program for the homeless."
The COA said HGC's liabilities of more than P6.1 billion also exceed its current assets of P3.1 billion by some P2.9 billion by the end of 2011.
Like Bongolan, the COA also questioned the HGC's retirement plan approved by Sanchez totaling some P120.7 million. The commission said this is also violative of RA 4968.
The amount represents the bulk of P149.7 million in total disallowances by the COA for 2011. The car plan for HGC officials amounting to P28 million was also questioned by the COA.
The lawyer, citing the COA, also said titles of HGC-acquired assets worth P7 billion were not consolidated in the name of HGC, "thereby depriving the HGC of the opportunity to sell and recover from these properties."
House investigation
AT the House of Representatives, Party-list Rep. Jonathan de la Cruz of Abakada Teacher filed a resolution directing the House Committee on Good Government and Public Accountability to summon anytime, when session resumes on May 5, for a panel hearing Bongolan and Sanchez to explain the status of the HGC.
Dela Cruz said HGC officials, during the hearing, are expected respond to the demands of COA and the Government Corporate Council, the agency in charge of government-owned and -controlled corporations.
De la Cruz said the massive losses hamper HGC's ability to perform its mandate of providing guaranty to the government mass housing projects and contribute to the government's fiscal problems, amid repeated calls from the COA in the last five years for HGC to fix its finances.
]]></text></news-item>