<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-G331-F0NV-F4W0"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>RICO charges draw re-indictment; Criminal, civil charges pursued in chicken fighting ring</title><source>The Moultrie Observer (Georgia)</source><author>Alan Mauldin, THE MOULTRIE OBSERVER</author><text><![CDATA[MOULTRIE - A Norman Park man accused of running a chicken-fighting operation was re-indicted by a Colquitt County Grand Jury last week as prosecutors continue civil as well as criminal cases.
Wallace Gene Hurst, 59, 4391 U.S. Hwy. 319 N., was indicted on two counts each of commercial gambling and keeping a gambling place, violation of the Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organizations Act -- better known as "RICO" and cruelty to animals.
In July 2012 law enforcement agencies raided Hurst's property, where they said chicken fighting was going on, about a mile and a half off Highway 256.
Hurst and 31 other people were arrested. All but Hurst only were charged with misdemeanor offenses and all have pleaded guilty in Colquitt County State Court. Those who entered guilty pleas are required, as a condition of sentencing, to testify in any trials that result.
In addition to the criminal charges, Hurst also faces the loss of the land where the alleged chicken fights were held. The civil case also filed by the Colquitt County District Attorney's office seeks more than 350 acres of land.
The Colquitt County Sheriff's Office described the facility on Hurst's land as "elaborate," with a glassed enclosure for chicken fights with an arena and stands.
Tifton attorney Joe Kunes, who is representing Hurst in both the criminal and civil matters, said Tuesday that he had not yet been made aware of the new criminal indictment.
"I haven't seen it, so I can't comment on it," he said.
He said prosecutors informed him late last year that they intended to dismiss the first indictment from September 2013.
"I assume I will do the same as last time: review the indictment and file any motions that need to be filed," he said.
There were issues with the first indictment, necessitating presenting a new one to a grand jury, Assistant District Attorney Brian McDaniel said Tuesday.
The initial criminal case was presented to a grand jury last year after all of the other defendants had entered guilty pleas, he said.
"By pleading, they've all admitted they were participating in gambling," he said.
McDaniel said he did not know when the criminal case could go to court if no plea agreement is reached prior to any potential trial. No negotiations have taken place so far between the parties.
It is possible that a plea deal could be constructed that would settle both civil and criminal cases.
In several recent civil court sessions the feeling among all involved seemed to be that the civil issue will not be taken up until after the completion of the criminal case.
Most of the 29 men and two women arrested along with Hurst in 2012 lived outside of Colquitt County, with some traveling as far as from Douglas, Ga.
At the time, law enforcement said that spectators paid a $20 fee to enter the property and that the entry fee to fight birds was $100 for each chicken.
About 40 live chickens were removed from the property and six dead birds were found, the sheriff's office said in the day after the raid. A variety of metal spurs attached to roosters' legs for fighting also were found at the site as were a pistol and a shotgun.
The civil case seeks 356 acres of land, along with the weapons and an ATV. If the civil suit is successful, the property would be forfeited to the sheriff's office as the agency that made the case.
]]></text></news-item>