<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-3HS1-DYPV-N1RH"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Sinteza - Daily Overview, Top Business Stories, Mar 26, 2014</title><source>Emerging Markets Brokers Reports - Southeast Europe</source><author>SeeNews</author><text><![CDATA[Sinteza Invest Group Ltd.
Belex
Serbian share indices rise, turnover doubles - The share indices of the Belgrade bourse gained ground on Tuesday as total daily turnover doubled, bourse data indicated. The blue-chip BELEX15 index, which tracks the most liquid shares on the Belgrade Stock Exchange, added 0.16% to 563.79 points after losing 0.05% on Monday.
(To view the full report please click here:
http://reports.aiidatapro.com/brokers/Sinteza/26-Mar-2014,BelexDailyOverview.pdf)
The broader BELEXline index was up 0.07% to 1,121.48 after gaining 0.03% in the previous trading session. The joint SRX index of the bourses in Belgrade and Vienna edged up 0.01% in euro terms at 174.44 after ending 0.02% lower on Monday. Total turnover surged to 41.1 million dinars ($491,000/355,000 euro) from 20.3 million dinars in the previous session. Komercijalna Banka [BEL:KMBN] generated Tuesday's largest turnover of 9.9 million dinars, closing flat at 1,680 dinars. Language courses provider ISJ [BEL:INSJ] led the session's gainers, rising 4.43% to 9,000 dinars in a volume of just two shares. Aluminium rolling mill Impol Seval [BEL:IMPL] paced the decliners, closing 13.67% lower at 1,023 dinars with 56 shares changing hands. (Sinteza Invest Group, SeeNews)
Serbia's NIS unit gets anti-trust nod to buy 11 petrol stations in Bulgaria - Bulgaria's competition regulator said on Tuesday it gave the go-ahead to locally-registered fuel retailer NIS Petrol to acquire 11 petrol stations from OMV Bulgaria, Bultrance Oils and Light Commerce. NIS Petrol is a wholly-owned subsidiary of Serbian oil and gas company NIS [BEL:NIIS], which in turn is majority-owned by Russia's Gazprom Neft.
The deal is expected to increase competition on Bulgaria's fuel retail market to the benefit of end-users, the Commission for Protection of Competition said in a statement. The petrol stations which NIS Petrol will acquire are located in the capital Sofia, the towns of Stara Zagora, Burgas, Bansko, Haskovo, Velingrad, Ruse,  Parvomai and Dimitrovgrad, and the villages of Kostievo and Krepost. (SeeNews)
Serbia sells 8.9 bln dinars (76.9 mln euro) in 2-yr T-bonds - Serbia sold on Tuesday 8.9 billion dinars ($106.4 million/76.9 million euro) in two-year amortized Treasury bonds, equal to 88.75% of its offer, the finance ministry's public debt agency said. The debt agency said in a statement it sold a total of 887,500 T-bonds with a coupon equal to the central bank's reference rate plus a fixed spread of 1.49%. The government paper will mature on March 27, 2016. (SeeNews)
Bambi products to feature Non-GMO icon - Bambi will become the first food company in Serbia to feature a non-GMO icon on its products, which are all GMO free. "Given the huge amount of information coming from consumers concerning the use of genetically modified ingredients in food products, we have decided to show clearly that our products do not contain GMO. All the products from the Bambi company will bear the 'non-GMO' icon on their packaging," the company said. Bambi is present in all confectionery segments, manufacturing everything from hard biscuit to chocolates, and it is one of the largest and most profitable companies in Serbia. The company was founded in 1967, and right from the start, it was focused on making biscuits from domestically grown grains with an emphasis on food healthiness. In 1997, the company was the first in the country to receive the ISO 9001 international certificate for the standard in quality management in food industry. (Tanjug)
Serbia
Strategic partnership approved between Air Serbia, Etihad - The United Arab Emirates' (UAE) national airline Etihad Airways announced on Tuesday that required official approvals had been ensured that confirm a strategic partnership between Air Serbia and Etihad Airways. On August 1, 2013, the Serbian government signed a long-term strategic partnership agreement with Etihad Airways and announced a plan for Air Serbia's recovery worth USD 200 million, Etihad stated in a statement. Etihad Airways President and CEO James Hogan said that, based on the received confirmation, the initial USD 40 million loan to Air Serbia will be turned into equity. "I am pleased to confirm Etihad Airways is now the shareholder of 49 per cent of Air Serbia. This investment represents an important partnership with the Government of Serbia, as we work together to build Air Serbia into the leading airline in the region," the company quoted Hogan as saying. Serbia's First Deputy Prime Minister Aleksandar Vucic said: "We are pleased to have closed the transaction with Air Serbia's strategic partner, Etihad Airways." "Air Serbia is the only major airline in the region to have successfully partnered with a leading global airline, Etihad Airways. We are proud the national airline of Serbia now stands shoulder-to-shoulder with the best in the world," the release quotes Vucic as saying. Air Serbia CEO Danny Kondic said that Air Serbia has "a strong business plan, and a clear Government mandate, to be a safe, best-in-class and profitable airline". "We have already achieved a remarkable transformation of the national airline of Serbia and are looking forward to the journey with our new shareholder and strategic partner, Etihad Airways," Kondic said. (Tanjug)
Region
Tourism contributes directly 12% of Croatia's 2013 GDP - Croatia's tourism and travel industry contributed 35.07 billion kuna ($6.33 billion/4.58 billion euro) directly to the country's economy in 2013, equivalent to 12.1% of its gross domestic product (GDP), the World Travel&Tourism Council (WTTC) said. The direct GDP contribution of the country's tourism and travel industry is forecast to rise 6.0% in 2014, the WTTC said in its Travel&Tourism Economic Impact 2014 report on Croatia. Travel and tourism investment in Croatia in 2013 was 6.61 billion kuna and the WTTC expects it should rise by 1.7% in 2014. Leisure travel spending - inbound and domestic - in Croatia totaled 69.2 billion kuna last year and is expected to grow by 6.0% in 2014. Business travel spending in the Adriatic country totalled 5.8 billion kuna in 2013 and is seen up by 4.6% in 2014. Croatia's travel and tourism sector generated 138,000 jobs directly in 2013 and this is forecast to rise by 4.8% in 2014. The WTTC expects the country to attract 11.9 million international tourist arrivals in 2014. (SeeNews)
Tourism contributes directly 9.8% of Montenegro's 2013 GDP - Montenegro's tourism and travel industry contributed 348.7 million euro ($482.1 million) directly to the country's economy in 2013, equivalent to 9.8% of its gross domestic product (GDP), the World Travel&Tourism Council (WTTC) said. The direct GDP contribution of the country's tourism and travel industry is forecast to rise 12.6% in 2014, the WTTC said in its Travel&Tourism Economic Impact 2014 report on Montenegro. Travel and tourism investment in Montenegro in 2013 was 208.3 million euro and the WTTC expects it should rise by 14.3% in 2014. Leisure travel spending - inbound and domestic - in Montenegro totaled 781.6 million euro last year and is expected to grow by 7.8% in 2014. Business travel spending in the tiny Adriatic country totalled 94.5 million euro in 2013 and is seen up by 13.3% in 2014. Montenegro's travel and tourism sector generated 14,500 jobs directly in 2013 and this is forecast to grow by 14% in 2014. The WTTC expects the country to attract 1.55 million international tourist arrivals in 2014. (SeeNews)
****
Copyright: Sinteza Invest Group a.d, All rights reserved.
For further Information please contact: Novi Belgrade, Jurija Gagarina 32, 11070, Serbia
Phone: +381 11 2099500; Fax: +381 11 2099 577   
web: http://www.sinteza.net/
e-mail: info@sinteza.net
http://www.sinteza.net/
]]></text></news-item>