<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-9DK1-F12F-F3JG"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Pakistan: CJ takes notice of underpass construction near Karachi temple</title><source>Right Vision News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[KARACHI, March 26 -- Chief Justice (CJ) of Pakistan, Justice Tassaduq Hussain Jillani on Monday took notice on press reports regarding the structure of Hindu temple that is threatened due to construction of an underpass and flyovers at Clifton.
The chief justice also directed the Sindh chief secretary and Karachi Metropolitan Corporation administrator to file detailed reports within two weeks with respect to the environmental assessment studies and the potential threat, if any, to the more than 150-year-old Sri Ratneswar Mahadev temple located at Clifton, few meters away from one of the underpasses.
The Human Rights Commission of Pakistan (HRCP) had sought the intervention of the Chief Justice of Pakistan to protect an old Hindu temple in Karachi that is threatened by the construction of underpasses and flyovers at Clifton.
In a letter sent to the chief justice, the HRCP chairperson noted that business interests in complicity with the KMC officials had started construction of multiple flyovers and underpasses around the Clifton seafront without any prior notice.
She noted that such a major venture, "which would vandalise the very face of a historical part of the city, has not undergone the Environmental Impact Assessment (with public hearings) mandated by law". The chairperson highlighted HRCP's deep concern over the adverse impact that this project could have on the more than 150 years old Sri Ratneswar Mahadev temple. She noted that every year thousands of Hindu and Sikh devotees visit the temple located in a cavern under the Jehangir Kothari Parade.
"Ground vibrations from excavation and from the eventual high-density traffic running so close to the temple could cause collapse of this irreplaceable place of worship," the HRCP chairperson added.
She said that the Hindu community in Sindh had been experiencing escalating human rights
violations over the past few years. "The Laxmi Narayan Mandir, located at Native Jetty, near the Jinnah Bridge on M A Jinnah Road, had its access, privacy and environs severely affected a few years ago by another commercial project, Port Grand." The letter called upon the chief justice to summon KMC officials to explain the matter and ensure that all necessary steps were taken to protect the temple.
It is pertinent to mention here that the Supreme Court also took up issues related to access of Hindu community at pre-partition era dharmshala at Tando Adam and Hindu Gymkhana. The court had also directed the Larkana district and sessions judge to hold inquiry regarding attack on Hindu temple and desecration of Holy Quran pages incidents in the district. The court also directed the Evacuee Trust Board secretary to submit a detailed report regarding use of many evacuee trust properties by various other departments and commercial activities
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Right Vision News. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>