<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-HNN1-JC3H-016J"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Marion County restaurant inspections; Pure Decadence Pastries</title><source>Statesman Journal (Salem, Oregon)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Details: 4740 Liberty Road S, Salem; (503) 584-1534
Date/type of inspection: Jan. 22; Semi-Annual
Score: 100
VIOLATIONS
Priority violations: None
Core violations: None
Quiznos Sub #5138
Details: 5133 River Road N, Keizer; (503) 559-2296
Date/type of inspection: Jan. 22; Semi-Annual
Score: 97
VIOLATIONS
Priority violations: Hand towels or a hand drying device is not provided at the handwashing sink, specifically: No paper towels at the front hand wash sink. Required correction: Correct immediately. Point deductions: 3.
Core violations: None
Sonic Drive In
Details: 220 Lancaster Drive SE, Salem; (503) 362-1279
Date/type of inspection: Jan. 22; Semi-Annual
Score: 100
VIOLATIONS
Priority violations: None
Core violation:
The establishment is not cleaned as often as necessary or at a time when the least amount of food is exposed, specifically: Flooring and wall is soiled behind the beverage-syrup boxes near the ice machine. Fan guard inside the walk-in refrigerator is starting to build up dust.
The Firehouse
Details: 5782 Portland Road NE; Salem; (503) 393-4782
Date/type of inspection: Jan. 22; Semi-Annual
Score: 100
VIOLATIONS
Priority violations: None
Core violation:
Physical facilities are not maintained in good repair, specifically: Metal floorboard coming up in the walk-in refrigerator.
Muchas Gracias
Details: 4940 Commercial St. SE, Salem; (503) 559-0480
Date/type of inspection: Jan. 22; Semi-Annual
Score: 91
VIOLATIONS
Priority violations: Ready-to-eat food is not properly date-marked, specifically: Cooked Fish and shredded chicken not dated in walk-in cooler. Food-contact surfaces are not clean, specifically: Wire slicer for cheese stored as though clean but still has cheese on it. Reach-in prep cooler has black build up on fan guard. Hand towels or a hand drying device is not provided at the handwashing sink, specifically: Batteries dead in paper towel dispensers at drive through and in back kitchen. Unable to get towels out. Required correction: Correct immediately. Point deductions: 9.
Core violations, 7, including:
Food is not stored to prevent contamination, specifically: Shelf holding spices above hand sink is sticky to touch. Trays of chips uncovered in dry storage area.
Nonfood-contact surfaces subject to splash or spillage are not properly constructed, specifically: Wire shelving rusting beneath three compartment sink.
Temperature measuring devices are not provided, or are not easily readable, properly located, or accurately scaled in hot or cold food storage units, specifically: Unable to find thermometer in drive-through refrigerator.
Surfaces of utensils and equipment contacting food that is not potentially hazardous is not cleaned as necessary, specifically: Stored can opener blade and holder dirty. Inside shield in ice machine has black build up. Ice chute on coke machine has green build up.
Taco Del Mar
Details: 1920 Turner Road SE, Suite C, Salem; (503) 362-3333
Date/type of inspection: Jan. 23; Semi-Annual
Score: 100
VIOLATIONS
Priority violations: None
Core violations, 4, including:
Surfaces of utensils and equipment contacting food that is not potentially hazardous is not cleaned as necessary, specifically: Ice chute at beverage dispenser near drive through window has some brown growth.
Nonfood-contact surfaces are not cleaned at an adequate frequency, specifically: Shelving racks inside the walk-in refrigerator have build-up.
Outer openings and windows in the establishment are not constructed or protected to prevent the entrance of insects and rodents, specifically: Back door propped open but is not protected to prevent entrance of pest.
Subway #26049
Details: 2535 Jori Lane NE, Keizer; (503) 949-1174
Date/type of inspection: Jan. 23; Semi-Annual
Score: 100
VIOLATIONS
Priority violations: None
Core violation:
Handwashing sinks are not kept clean, or are not properly maintained or used, specifically: sponge used to wipe down toaster stored inside front hand sink.
Korner Post Restaurant
Details: 110 S Detroit Ave., Detroit; (503) 854-3735
Date/type of inspection: Jan. 23; Semi-Annual
Score: 90
VIOLATIONS
Priority violations: Food employees do not use the proper cleaning procedure for washing their hands, specifically: employee washed hands improperly. Raw or ready-to eat food is not properly protected from cross contamination, specifically: back freezer has raw animal items not stored according to cooking temperature. Required correction: Correct immediately. Point deductions: 10.
Core violations, 2:
Utensils are not maintained in good repair or condition, air or water temperature measuring devices or water pressure measuring devices are not maintained in good repair or accurate, specifically: interior of freezer is damaged and food is directly on shelves.
Physical facilities are not maintained in good repair, specifically: ceiling damaged.
Carl's Jr. #7453
Details: 5130 River Road N, Keizer; (503) 390-9227
Date/type of inspection: Jan. 23; Semi-Annual
Score: 100
VIOLATIONS
Priority violations: None
Core violation:
Nonfood-contact surfaces are not cleaned at an adequate frequency, specifically: Wire racks in the walk-in refrigerator are soiled and have debris.
Jamba Juice
Details: 2555 Jorie Lane NE Suite 104, Keizer; (503) 810-5354
Date/type of inspection: Jan. 23; Semi-Annual
Score: 100
VIOLATIONS
Priority violations: None
Core violation:
Equipment is not maintained in good repair or according to manufacturer's recommendations or cutting parts of can openers are not kept sharp, specifically: reach-in refrigerator door gaskets damaged.
Round Table Pizza #964
Details: 6055 Ulali Drive NE, Keizer; (503) 393-2150
Date/type of inspection: Jan. 23; Semi-Annual
Score: 92
VIOLATIONS
Priority violations: Poisonous or toxic materials are not properly separated or located, specifically: red bucket of sanitizer stored above food, chemical spray bottles stored with soda syrups. A test kit is not provided or is not accurate enough to measure the concentration of sanitizing solutions, specifically: no test paper for Quat sanitizer. Required correction: Correct immediately. Point deductions: 8.
Core violation, 3:
Warewashing machines, sinks used for warewashing, food preparation or wiping cloth laundering, or drainboards are not cleaned at an appropriate frequency, specifically: interior of dish machine has buildup.
Food-contact surfaces of cooking equipment and pans are not kept free of encrusted grease deposits and other soil, or nonfood-contact surfaces are not kept clean, specifically: Can rack soiled.
A handwashing sign is not posted at all handwashing sinks used by food employees, specifically: Hand wash reminder signage missing at hand sinks in kitchen.
Restaurant inspections are compiled from the Marion County Health Department database by business reporter Elida S. Perez
About restaurant inspections
These are a synopsis of restaurant inspections conducted by the Marion County Health Department. To read the full inspection report with corrective measures, go to http://apps.co.marion.or.us/RIS.
Marion County has more than 700 licensed restaurants. Restaurants receive two unannounced routine inspections a year to determine compliance with the Food Sanitation Rules. Inspections focus on food temperatures, food preparation practices, worker hygiene, dishwashing and sanitizing, equipment and facility cleanliness.
What the scores mean: A restaurant that receives a score of 70 or higher is considered to be in compliance. Any cited "critical violations" are corrected immediately or an approved alternative procedure implemented. A restaurant that receives a score below 70 fails to comply and must have a full re-inspection within 30 days or be subject to closure or further administrative action. Follow-up inspections are conducted on any facility where a public health risk is identified. A placard on the restaurant entrance indicates whether a facility passed the last routine health inspection.
About violations: The inspection score is based on 100 points. Critical violations, called priority violations and priority foundation violations, deduct between 1-5 points. Core violations do not have point deductions, but must be corrected. If the same violation is cited on consecutive semi-annual inspections, the points deducted will double.
]]></text></news-item>