<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-F281-DXMP-K0HC"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Astec Lifesciences declines on receiving order to temporarily shut Dombivili Plant; Astec Lifesciences is one of the 22 companies which have received the order from MPCB regarding contamination of the Ulhas River</title><source>Accord Fintech</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Astec Lifesciences is currently trading at Rs. 34.50, down by 3.45 points or 9.09 % from its previous closing of Rs. 37.95 on the BSE.
The scrip opened at Rs. 37.10 and has touched a high and low of Rs. 37.95 and Rs. 34.50 respectively. So far 97729 shares were traded on the counter.
The BSE group 'B' stock of face value Rs. 10 has touched a 52 week high of Rs. 43.15 on 11-Mar-2014 and a 52 week low of Rs. 14.45 on 30-Apr-2013.
Last one week high and low of the scrip stood at Rs. 40.00 and Rs. 36.30 respectively. The current market cap of the company is Rs. 63.93 crore.
The promoters holding in the company stood at 58.05% while Non-Institutions held 41.95%.
Astec Lifesciences has received order from Maharashtra Pollution Control Board (MPCB) for temporary suspension of operations at Dombivili Plant. Astec LifeSciences having its plant at Plot No- F-39, MIDC, Phase II, Dombivili, District- Thane is one of the 22 companies which have received an order for temporary suspension of operations.
National Green Tribunal (NGT) based on an appeal filed by NGO Vanashakti, has been seeking clarifications from MPCB regarding contamination of the Ulhas River.
Astec LifeSciences is a producer of agrochemicals and pharmaceutical intermediates. The company manufactures a wide range of Agrochemical active ingredients and pharmaceutical intermediates.
DISCLAIMER: Accord Fintech provides the Content on "AS IS" basis without any express or implied warranties. Accord Fintech does not warrant the accuracy, timeliness, completeness, adequacy, merchantability, or fitness for a particular purpose of the Content, and Accord Fintech shall not be liable to Licensee or to any third party with respect to any actual or alleged inaccuracy, untimeliness, incompleteness, inadequacy, unmerchantbailty or unfitness.
]]></text></news-item>