<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV0-GDT1-JC11-1033"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Senate Panel to Examine Efforts to Curb Medicare Fraud</title><source>Targeted News Service</source><author>Targeted News Service</author><text><![CDATA[The Senate Special Committee on Aging issued the following news release:
The U.S. Senate Special Committee on Aging will hold a hearing on Wednesday to examine federal efforts to combat Medicare fraud.
In recent years, federal authorities have significantly ramped up efforts to curb healthcare fraud, resulting in a record recovery of $4.3 billion in taxpayer funds last year. The government's Medicare Fraud Strike Force also set a new record for prosecutions last year, having charged 345 people, and obtained 234 guilty pleas and 46 jury trial convictions. The Southern District of Illinois (East St. Louis) and the Southern District of Florida led the nation in prosecutions, according to data obtained by researchers at Syracuse University.
During the hearing, lawmakers will get a first-hand account of federal anti-fraud efforts in Florida from one of the government's leading health-care fraud investigators. The committee will also hear from the director of the CMS Center for Program Integrity, the CEO of the National Health Care Anti-Fraud Association, a Senior Medicare Patrol Coordinator and a fraud victim from Michigan.
While Medicare fraud is estimated to cost taxpayers $60 billion to $90 billion each year, it is difficult to measure the true cost of these crimes. What is known is that today's fraudsters have become more organized, sophisticated and better able to allude authorities. Tactics commonly used include paying kickbacks to recruiters for finding patients, providing medically unnecessary services and hiding ownership interests in companies that bill Medicare, among others.
For example, a physician in Michigan was arrested last year bilking $225 million from Medicare by falsely telling patients they had cancer so that he could bill for expensive chemotherapy treatments. In Florida, a federal judge sentenced to prison the former owner of a Miami-based company, Health Care Solutions Network (HCSN), for submitting more than $63 million in false Medicare and Medicaid billings for mental illness therapies that often consisted of nothing more than patients watching movies, playing bingo and having barbeques. The owner was a convicted cocaine trafficker who entered the Medicare business in the mid-2000s.
In addition to highlighting the human and financial cost of Medicare fraud, the hearing will also examine: the government's use of new technology aimed identifying suspect claims before they are paid out; how current and potential providers are screened; and, ways to improve anti-fraud efforts.
UNITED STATES SENATE SPECIAL COMMITTEE ON AGING
HEARING: Preventing Medicare Fraud: How Can We Best Protect Seniors and Taxpayers?
2:15 p.m., Wednesday, March 26 2014
Dirksen Senate Office Building, Room 562
WITNESS LIST
Shantanu Agrawal, MD, Deputy Administrator and Director, Center for Program Integrity, Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services
Bettie Hughes, Senior Medicare Patrol Coordinator, The Senior Alliance (Area Agency on Aging 1-C)
Accompanied by: Patricia Gresko, Medicare Fraud Victim from Romeo, MI
Brian Martens, Assistant Special Agent in Charge, Miami Office of Investigations, Department of Health and Human Services Office of the Inspector General
Louis Saccoccio, Chief Executive Officer, National Health Care Anti-Fraud Association
Copyright Targeted News Services
TNS 30FurigayJof 140326-4680469 30FurigayJof
]]></text></news-item>