<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV1-5851-JB4P-V3NW"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>ProfNet Experts Available on Earth Day, Malaysia Airlines, Copyright Act, More; Also in This Edition: Jobs for Writers and Media Industry Blog Posts</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ Below are experts from theProfNetnetwork that are available to discuss timely issues in your coverage area. If you are interested in interviewing any of the experts, please contact them via the contact information at the end of the listing. To receive these updates by email, send a note toprofnet@profnet.comwith the industries you cover, and we'll add you to the appropriate edition. 
If you are in need of additional experts, you can alsosubmit a queryto the hundreds of thousands of experts in our network. You can filter your request by institution type and geographic location to get the most targeted responses. The best part? It's free! Just fill out thequery formto get started.
If you have any questions or need assistance with any aspect of ProfNet, please drop us a note atprofnet@profnet.com
EXPERT ALERTS
Smokey and the Copyrights Malaysia Airlines Families May Turn to Courts Texas' Energy Boom Engulfs Enforcement Efforts Tesla Pushes for Dealership Sales Model Change Terrestrial and Aquatic Ecological Studies Spill Response and Natural Resource Damage Assessment
EXPERT ROUNDUP
Earth Day (34 experts)
MEDIA JOBS
Reporter - Baltimore Business Journal (MD) Reporter - The Dallas Observer (TX) Editor - Santa Monica Daily Press (CA)
OTHER NEWS & RESOURCES
Protecting Yourself As a Freelancer Writer Media 411: Ways Journalists Can Use Facebook Grammar Hammer: Comma Placement in Quotes
EXPERT ALERTS:
Smokey and the CopyrightsJeffrey O. AndersonFamily Law AttorneyMcCurley Orsinger McCurley Nelson & Downing, L.L.P. in Dallas"Music legend Smokey Robinson's former wife may be in line for half the future profits from his Motown catalog under the terms of a divorce that took place nearly 30 years ago. Mr. Robinson recently filed suit under the Copyright Act to recapture the rights to his hit catalog and to be named as the sole beneficiary. However, in their 1985 divorce agreement, his former wife was awarded half of all copyrights and royalty rights based on the music created during their 27-year marriage. If the court awarded her half of these copyrights in the divorce, she owns them. They are hers to market, reconstitute - in the modern sense of the industry term - or let them be. However, if there is a great deal of work required in the reclamation of the royalties, and she offers no assistance, then his position that she should not benefit is on firmer ground."Media Contact: Amy Hunt,amy@androvett.com
Malaysia Airlines Families May Turn to CourtsMark S. WerbnerAttorneySayles Werbner in DallasThe March 8 disappearance of Malaysia Airlines flight 370 has confounded international investigators while many of the 239 passengers' relatives have remained at a Beijing hotel waiting on answers. Related lawsuits are a threat, and depending on what any potential evidence shows, legal liability could be shared by everyone from the airline to the Malaysian government to the pilots themselves. The passengers' families are still coping with the disappearance of their relatives and holding out hope for their safe return, but it won't be long before they begin taking official action on their loved ones' behalf, and that likely will come in the form of lawsuits."Media Contact: Bruce Vincent,bruce@androvett.com
Texas' Energy Boom Engulfs Enforcement EffortsSteven C. LairdPersonal Injury AttorneyLaw Offices of Steven C. Laird, P.C. in Fort Worth, Texas"Texas' rosy employment picture has been sullied by reports that workers in the state's energy patch have been dying in alarming numbers. There's no doubt that the energy industry has contributed heavily to Texas' low 5.7 percent unemployment rate, but recent media reports show that the rush to jobs in the Eagle Ford Shale and other energy-rich areas of the state has resulted in poor worker training and, as a result, hundreds of casualties. Despite this, the oil and gas industry - which is overseen by the federal Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) - has historically enjoyed remarkable immunity to the enforcement of safety standards and penalties. In fact, state safety fines have often been insultingly low."Media Contact: Dave Moore,dave@androvett.com
Tesla Pushes for Dealership Sales Model ChangeJohn ShackelfordAttorney for Auto DealersShackelford, Melton, McKinley & Norton, LLP in Dallas"New Jersey is the latest state to bar electric vehicle maker Tesla from direct sales to consumers. The upstart car company is now telling Texas and other states vying to secure a $5 billion next-generation battery factory that would employ more than 6,000 workers that they may improve their chances to attract the project if they loosen long-standing laws related to direct sales. These laws have been in place for a reason. The primary reason is to protect the existing retail auto distribution network. Although Tesla's sales are relatively small, dealers fear allowing Tesla to sell direct to consumers will open the floodgates to other manufacturers doing the same and eventually eliminate the dealer model."Media Contact: Robert Tharp,robert@androvett.com
Terrestrial and Aquatic Ecological StudiesRob FiorileSenior ScientistMatrix New World Engineering"Volunteers will be planting over 1,000 plants to restore a local coastal marsh, which is a type of intertidal habitat that is critical to aquatic and terrestrial wildlife. This restoration effort is part of a pilot project that will be the first in the Northeast to use an innovative and patented restoration technique that has been successfully employed in the Gulf region. The purpose of the project is to demonstrate that this technology can be successfully adapted to local conditions in order to facilitate use on a much wider regional scale to restore and protect this valuable habitat."Fiorile has a background in the various types of terrestrial and aquatic ecological studies/surveys such as: watershed management plans, wetland delineations, seagrass surveys, shellfish surveys, dredge material sampling, acid soils surveys and seagrass and wetland mitigation/restoration. He can specifically address the groundbreaking eco-environmental, engineering pilot program occurring in Cattus Island County Park in Toms River, New Jersey.ProfNet Profile:http://www.profnetconnect.com/robfiorileWebsite:http://www.matrixneworld.comMedia Contact: Amy Delman,amydelmanpr@verizon.net
Spill Response and Natural Resource Damage AssessmentLawrence MalizziVice PresidentMatrix New World Engineering"Volunteers will be planting approximately 500 plants to restore a coastal marsh along the Chesapeake Bay, which is a type of intertidal habitat that is critical to aquatic and terrestrial wildlife. This restoration effort is part of a pilot project sponsored by the Chesapeake Bay Environmental Center (CBEC), the Chesapeake Potomac Regional Chapter of the Society of Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry (CPRC SETAC), Matrix New World Engineering (Matrix), and the Restore the Earth Foundation (REF). Bay Saver Bags, a patented restoration technique developed by REF, will be used and have been successfully employed in the Gulf region. The purpose of the project is to demonstrate that this technology can be successfully adapted to the Chesapeake Bay, and similar environments, in order to facilitate use on a much wider regional scale to restore and protect this valuable habitat."Malizzi has a background in spill response, natural resource damage assessment (NRDA), geology, hydrogeology, due diligence and remediation. He can specifically address the groundbreaking eco-environmental, engineering pilot program in the Chesapeake Bay, Maryland area.ProfNet Profile:http://www.profnetconnect.com/lawrencemalizziWebsite:http://www.matrixneworld.comMedia Contact: Amy Delman,amydelmanpr@verizon.net
****************
EXPERT ROUNDUP: Earth Day
Following are 34 experts who are available for quotes on various topics related to Earth Day, April 22. If you need additional experts, you can alsosubmit a query, and can filter your request by institution type and geographic location to get the most targeted responses. The best part? It's free! Just fill out thequery formto get started.
Matt CrenshawPresidentMother Nature Network"It used to be that green was a color. It then evolved into what we buy, eat and drive. But no one is talking about green -- hybrid cars, fair-trade coffee, farmers markets.  We're talking about green 2.0. Whole Foods has increased same-stores sales by nearly 10 percent year over year, but who are these people?  There's a whole so-called green lifestyle that has emerged that no one has quite put their finger on. Look at the boom of aforementioned farmers markets, where the numbers across the country has jumped near threefold from 2000 to 2012, from 2,863 to 7,864. Many people want to get back to a more simple life. There is a new definition of living well... Blame it on fear and finances, but self-sufficiency is rising.  'Seven Things You Can Make Instead of Buying' has become MNN's top shared image on Pinterest.  A casual Facebook post on how to make your own soap  -- "Your Great-Grandparents Knew How -- You Could Learn Too" -- and 40,000+ readers have clicked on to see how it works.  A guy who has 3 million miles on his Volvo starts a massive discussion among readers on fixing your own car. There is no media company for that kind of person. There is no Oprah. There is no Martha Stewart. There's just this social movement."Mother Nature Network, is the world's most visited environmental website, founded in 2009 by Chuck Leavell, a noted conservationist who doubles as longtime Rolling Stones keyboardist and musical director. An Atlanta native, University of Georgia grad with a Harvard MBA, Crenshaw is recognized as one of the more influential principals in Web analytics, and thus his principal role at Mother Nature Network is to provide an analytics vision and roadmap. A Web old-timer at 36, Crenshaw maintains a deep knowledge of the digital ecosystem, but he's also a garrulous storyteller with a self-deprecating air and keen sense of the absurd.  He's all the things most senior execs are not:  super-grounded, unassuming and scary-smart in all things "eco."Media Contact: Dan Beeson,dbeeson@mnn.com
George BasileSenior Sustainability Scientist and Professor of PracticeArizona State University, Tempe"I see sustainability as a huge opportunity space for how we do business - and everything else - better. The first step is to educate yourself on how your everyday decisions can make a difference -- especially in helping to build the future you want, more sustainably. There are literally a zillion things you can do [to be more sustainable]. Everything you do every day, you can try to do it more sustainably.  For example, water is a big challenge right now in California and Arizona. You can and should just use less water, of course, but everything is connected.  So, for example, if you replace a pound of beef with a pound of rice and beans, that saves about 2,500 gallons of water. Or, use less energy. We use about 40 percent of our water in the U.S. to make steam to make electricity. There are great resources on things like water conservation, energy conservation, etc."Basile is an expert on green business practices, strategic leadership, strategic sustainability, entrepreneurship, emerging technologies, biotechnology, sustainability science. He is widely published and is a sought-after speaker focusing on creating strategic alignment between business drivers and emerging market needs. He has held teaching positions at Arizona State, Berkeley, and Stanford, and helped develop Green MBA programs in the United States and Sweden. He currently serves on the boards of nonprofit organizations and new ventures, and advises Fortune 500 clients on sustainable business practices and integrated operational and marketing strategies.Media Contact:michelle.schwartz@asu.edu
Tony JuniperSenior Associate, Programme for Sustainability LeadershipUniversity of Cambridge"The monetary value of nature can, and has been, measured. In fact, the services nature provides -- water, pollinating plants, generating oxygen, pollinating insects that produce nearly all of our food and much more -- have an estimated value every year of around double the global gross domestic product (GDP). Yet this colossal contribution to human welfare and prosperity is hardly ever mentioned when countries consider how to create future growth. Politicians cannot afford to ignore the cost of these 'natural' services."Juniper is a campaigner, writer, sustainability adviser and a well-known British environmentalist. He is also special adviser to the Prince of Wales Charities' International Sustainability Unit and senior associate with the University of Cambridge Programme for Sustainability Leadership (CPSL). His book, "What Has Nature Ever Done for Us?" was published in July 2013 by Synergetic Press. He is available to discuss the economic value of nature.Website:http://www.tonyjuniper.comMedia Contact: Elena Meredith,elena@prbythebook.com
Dr. Mark NelsonFounding Director, Chairman, CEOInstitute of Ecotechnics"We are wasting the world's dwindling supplies of fresh water by flushing away a very valuable resource, our own human waste!"In the EPA's 2015 FY budget, $581 million was cut from a fund that helps states build wastewater and drinking water projects -- the same kind of projects Nelson is working on in Iraq and China. He consults on wastewater reuse and recycling using wastewater gardens. He is one of the original Biosphere 2 crew and author of "The Wastewater Gardener: Preserving the Planet One Flush at a Time" (Synergetic Press, June 2014).Bio:http://www.synergeticpress.com/authors/mark-nelsonWebsite:http://www.ecotechnics.eduMedia Contact: Elena Meredith,elena@prbythebook.com
Jeffrey Bennett, Ph.D.Astronomer, Teacher, WriterRegarding this year's Polar Vortex, Bennett says: "Perhaps you've heard some people claiming that 'global warming has stopped.' Well, as I like to say, it's easy to argue endlessly as long as you don't let any actual facts get in the way. But the facts are clear, and anyone who claims the data point to a cessation of global warming is simply ignoring the obvious. Consider what you will say to your children and grandchildren who will be living in a world with far worse weather problems unless we act now to do something to help."Bennett was the first author to send his books to the International Space Station as a part of Story Time From Space, a new reading program created by astronauts and educators. He is an expert on teaching climate change.Website:http://www.jeffreybennett.comMedia Contact: Elena Meredith,elena@prbythebook.com
Meghna TareDirector, Office of SustainabilityUniversity of Texas at ArlingtonTare is available to explain what institutions of higher education (and similar large organizations) can do to become more sustainable and has written columns and been interviewed about a variety of sustainability issues. In a recent interview with the website TriplePundit, Tare explained that UT Arlington's commitment to sustainability was about more than cost savings. She said: "We tap into the 'moral imperative,' based on the concept that everything is part of the puzzle. Students attending a university that places high value on sustainable operations are more likely to take this mindset to their future places of employment where they can help shape the future of environmentally friendly companies." She also talked about the importance of collaboration in that interview: "I have learned from experience that university campuses that tie together multiple areas of sustainability into a comprehensive, holistic plan or roadmap tend to be more successful -- at getting buy-in from the community, funding various initiatives and achieving results and recognition."Bio:http://www.linkedin.com/in/meghnatare Media Contact: Traci Peterson,tpeterso@uta.edu
Scott HiteHead of Architecture and DesignTD BankHite has enterprise-wide responsibility for both retail and corporate design standards in the U.S. and Canada. He also manages the real estate sustainability team that has designed and constructed TD Bank's new energy-efficient locations.  He can speak to anything related to green/sustainable building and real estate, such as material selection decisions (e.g., roofing); electrical power, plug load and management; lighting choices; forward-looking planning and establishment of success metrics; and consumer and employee education.Media Contact: Ben Murray,bmurray@cooperkatz.com
Kaayla T. Daniel, Ph.D., CNNVice PresidentWeston A. Price FoundationDr. Daniel is vice president of the Weston A. Price Foundation and on the board of directors of the Farm-to-Consumer Legal Defense Fund.  She is known as "The Naughty Nutritionist" because she outrageously and humorously debunks nutritional myths. One of the biggest myths she'd like to debunk is that veg-centric diets are the best for personal and planetary health. She is available to discuss: why the true threat to our environment is not animals, but the globalization and industrialization of agriculture; why animals play critical roles in restoring our soil and growing nutrient-dense vegetables and fruits; how only 11 percent of the planet is well-suited to agriculture; why meat, butter, and other animal products are wrongly blamed for the diseases of modern civilization and why the true culprits are sugar, corn syrup, white flour, liquid and partially hydrogenated vegetable oils, artificial flavorings, preservatives, and other known health hazards of processed, packaged and fast foods; why low-fat diets are neither healthy nor eco-conscious; how the low-fat message serves Big Agra and leads to increased food consumption, more packages, more products, higher profits, ill health and environmental destruction; what people eat when they give up or minimize meat (almost always soy and other vegetarian foods grown and transported from a distance); and what to do instead of Meatless Mondays (commit one day a week to menus in which everything is local, a day of being a "non-barcode" person.Dr. Daniel's book, "The Whole Soy Story: The Dark Side of America's Favorite Health Food (2005)," has been endorsed by leading health experts, including Drs. Russell Blaylock, David Brownstein, Larry Dossey, Nicholas Gonzalez, Joseph Mercola, Kilmer McCully, Doris J. Rapp, JJ Virgin, and Jonathan Wright. She is coauthor (with Sally Fallon Morell) of "Nourishing Broth: An Old-Fashioned Remedy for the Modern World," scheduled for Fall 2014 publication. She has been a guest on "The Dr. Oz Show," PBS' "Healing Quest," NPR's "People's Pharmacy," ABC's "View from the Bay," and Discovery Channel's "Medical Hotseat," and has shared the stage with Dr. Mark Hyman, JJ Virgin, Gary Taubes, Charles Poliquin, Dr. Joseph Mercola, Joel Salatin, David Wolfe and other prominent health experts.Website:http://www.drkaayladaniel.comExpert Contact:Kaayla@DrKaaylaDaniel.com
Joe CarterCEOSnyder Environmental, Inc.Snyder Environmental, an environmental remediation company based in North Little Rock, Ark., provides the safe and compliant remediation of environmental issues, including asbestos abatement and lead paint removal for commercial businesses. Thus, Carter would be perfect to address the environmental hazards that can be found in the workplace and how to protect yourself from them. He has more than 12 years of entrepreneurial experience in building and leading companies. Under his leadership, Snyder Environmental has twice been named to Inc. Magazine's 500 fastest growing, privately held, for-profit companies in the country. Founded in 2007, Snyder Environmental has done more than 1,600 jobs including marine and maritime asbestos abatement in the south, throughout the U.S. and overseas. He graduated from the University of Arkansas and is currently attending the Harvard Business School's Owner/President Management (OPM) program.Website:http://www.snyderenvironmental.com Media Contact: John Goodman,john@johnlgoodman.com
Maya van RossumDelaware Riverkeeper NetworkRossum is the spokesperson for and leader of the Delaware Riverkeeper Network (DRN), a 501(c)(3) nonprofit environmental organization and vital force in the preservation, protection, and restoration of the Delaware River Watershed. Rossum heads a team of dedicated staff and volunteers who monitor the river throughout the Watershed's four states --  New York, Pennsylvania, New Jersey, and Delaware -- and who advocate, educate, and litigate for protection, restoration, and change. Rossum is a powerful force in protecting the river against threats, including shale fracking and drilling, dredging, dumping, pollution and detrimental construction. As the Delaware Riverkeeper, she organizes concerned citizens, testifies before state and national governing bodies, overseas all litigation, and keeps a close watch on the Delaware River and all of its tributary streams. She is a lead advocator and litigator against Marcellus Shale drilling and other environmental hazards to the four-state area watershed. She is available to discuss conservation, water, and natural resource preservation.Website:http://www.delawareriverkeeper.org Media Contact: Paige Wolf,paige@paigewolf.com
Paige WolfOwnerPaige Wolf Media and Public RelationsWolf is a publicist, author, and green-living expert who uses her media savvy and personal moxie to promote manageable eco-chic living. She is the owner ofPaige Wolf Media and Public Relations, a B Corporation certified eco-friendly PR firm focused on sustainable clientele, and the author of "Spit That Out! The Overly Informed Parent's Guide to Raising Children in the Age of Environmental Guilt." Wolf regularly appears on television as a green-living expert, and she has been featured in publications including Boho, People.com, The Huffington Post, MSN.com, and Forbes.com. She frequently speaks at green-living conferences and expos and has written about green living for several publications.  She is available to discuss realistic green parenting and how to make green living more practical, manageable and affordable.Expert Contact:paige@paigewolf.com
Robert ReileyProfessor, Environmental StudiesKaplan University School of Legal StudiesReiley has 20 years of experience as an environmental attorney in the government and private sector. His specialties include environmental policy, legal counseling, regulatory development and litigation. He is available to discuss: ways to encourage your employees to participate in Earth Day; daily steps we can take to be more environmentally conscious; causes of environmental issues; the importance of Earth Day.Media Contact: Stephanie Schwartz,stephanie.schwartz@rbbpr.com
Steve SullivanSenior Curator of Urban EcologyPeggy Notebaert Nature Museum, ChicagoSullivan studies the nature in our own backyards. He is the primary investigator of Project Squirrel, one of the museum's signature award-winning citizen science initiatives. When he's not out in the field, you can find him at the museum doing taxidermy for the academy's collection or interacting with members. In fact, trying to "Stump Steve" is a staple of the museum experience. He is a member of the Ecological Society of America, American Society of Mammalogists, Society for the Preservation of Natural History Collection, Chicago Herpetological Society, North American Native Fishes Association, American Society of Ichthyologists and Herpetologists, and the Boy Scouts of America. He is available to discuss how climate changes are shaping the landscape of local flora and fauna, how various species and habitats are coping in today's environment, and what people can do lives to foster a true connection with nature.Media Contact: Marissa Ellenby,mellenby@pcipr.com
Doug Taron, Ph.D.Curator of Biology, Vice President of Conservation and ResearchPeggy Notebaert Nature Museum, ChicagoTaron has been responsible for all living materials on the grounds at the museum; he manages the internationally renowned Judy Istock Butterfly Haven; oversees the management of the academy's collection; and leads the museum's insect conservation biology research. He is director of the Illinois Butterfly Monitoring Network and president and co-steward of Friends of Bluff Spring Fen. He serves on the Board of International Association of Butterfly Exhibitors and Suppliers and Mayor's Committee for Nature and Wildlife in Chicago. He is a member of the Lepidopterists' Society, The Sonoran Arthropod Studies Institute, The American Association of the Advancement of Science, and the America Alliance of Museums. He is available to discuss how climate changes are shaping the landscape of local flora and fauna, how various species and habitats are coping in today's environment, and what people can do lives to foster a true connection with nature.Media Contact: Marissa Ellenby,mellenby@pcipr.com
Laurence LaniganGeneral ManagerSol Providers, Wappinger's Falls, N.Y.Lanigan grew up in NYC and moved to the Hudson Valley as a teen. Upon graduating from Marist College, he worked as an executive with the largest export management company in the United States until he left that position in order to spend time with his newborn daughter. Then he began working for CSI, revitalizing and transforming it into a dynamic and successful telecommunications construction company. Four years ago, Lanigan built Sol Providers as the solar and wind installation arm of parent company CSI. He is available to discuss solar energy.Website:http://www.SolProviders.comMedia Contact: Carol Bloom Stevens,carol@msco.com
Jay BlackDirector of SustainabilitySL Green Realty Corp.As the first director of sustainability for SL Green Realty Corp., New York City's largest commercial landlord, Black brings to the post a professional and personal passion, dedication, and focus. Beginning in 2007, he established a market-leading program for carpet and ceiling tile recycling throughout SL Green's construction projects, which has diverted to date more than 3.2 million square feet of materials, totaling 1050 tons of debris from landfills. Other programs include installation of more than 23,000 high-efficiency LED lights at 32 properties; installation of electric vehicle charging stations at suburban offices; and an event for last year's Earth Day to plant 76, 10-foot trees on Randall's Island in conjunction with Bloomberg's "Million Tree Program." For Earth Day this year, SL Green, in conjunction with the Urban Air Foundation and New York Restoration Project, will host "Tenant Action Day," providing stewardship to Highbridge Park's 119-acre urban forest in Northern Manhattan.A regular on the speaking circuit, Black has presented at Columbia University, NY University's Shack Institute, Cornell University, Yale, Temple Pace Law, IREM, BOMA - NYC and Bisnow. He participates in REBNY's Sustainability Committee and was formerly active in Westchester County Climate Change Action Committee, White Plains Sustainable & Environmental Enhancement Committee, and the Port Chester Architecture Board of Review. His dedication permeates his personal life -- he completed three Ironman triathlon competitions (2.4-mile swim/112-mile bike/24.6-mile run) and he gives back, through triathlons, by raising money for the National MS Society, for which he has raised more than $40,000 since 2008.Media Contact: Melanie Keenan,mkeenan@rubenstein.com
Brian Trimble, P.E., LEED APRegional VP, Engineering Services and Architectural OutreachBrick Industry Association (BIA), Reston, Va.Trimble is an accredited professional in Leadership in Energy & Environmental Design, and has more than 25 years' experience in the masonry industry, assisting design professionals in the design of brick and masonry structures. He is a frequent lecturer to local, regional and national construction industry groups, and has authored many articles and papers on various masonry subjects. He has worked at BIA for more than 19 years, serving in various positions. In addition to his long tenure at BIA, he has worked for a brick manufacturer and the International Masonry Institute. He now leads architectural and builder outreach in the 17-state Midwest/Northeast Region for BIA. Trimble's extensive technical experience includes serving as chairman C12.03 of ASTM International and a past institute director for the Construction Specifications Institute. He is available to discuss building/green building topics, including residential/home building, commercial and industrial building, and green building practices.Website:http://www.gobrick.comTwitter: @bricktrimbleMedia Contact: Lorelei Harloe,lh@ascendcomm.com
Dr. Stephen "Mitch" WagenerProfessor of Biological and Environmental SciencesWestern Connecticut State UniversityWagener teaches ecology, entomology and related courses at WCSU. His research interests include the ecology of soil and aquatic invertebrates, the ecology of our changing climate, and the impact of historical events on the environment. Currently, his research focuses on the ecologies of Lakes Candlewood, Lillinonah and Zoar (in Connecticut), with particular interest in invasive species infesting these lakes. Wagener began life in the Midwest, growing up a barefoot boy in the Ozarks and attending high school in Branson, Mo. -- before it became so famous. After graduating from the University of Missouri with a degree in fisheries and wildlife, he moved to Fairbanks, Alaska, to attend graduate school. He received a master's degree in stream ecology and a doctorate in soil ecology during his 13 years in Alaska. Areas of expertise: the ecological effects of climate change; environmental concerns in local lakes, especially invasive zebra mussels; historic stone walls in New England.Media Contact: Sherri Hill,hills@wcsu.edu
Dr. Laurie WeinsteinProfessor of AnthropologyWestern Connecticut State UniversityWeinstein received her Ph.D. from Southern Methodist University. She is passionate about teaching anthropology and researching the indigenous peoples of the Americas. She has edited or written many books and articles on such diverse topics as New England Indians and Indians of the Southwest, and women in the military. She can address Native American relationships to the earth, including Native American horticulture. She is currently running the Jane Goodall Center at WCSU, which maintains active ties to the Jane Goodall Institute in Washington, D.C.  The JGC, working with the Connecticut Northeast Organic Farmers Association and permaculture guru Ryan Harb (UMass, Amherst), is embarking on a project to plant a community permaculture garden. She can discuss Native American horticulture, along with permaculture and her work with Jane Goodall.Media Contact: Sherri Hill,hills@wcsu.edu
Paige GoffVice President, Sustainability and Business CommunicationsDomtar Goff is responsible for managing sustainability communications for Domtar, the world's most sustainable pulp and paper company. The key to her role is understanding and applying the current trends and strategies related to environmental, regulatory and social sustainability to Domtar's business practices and products, while managing the relationships among environmental non-governmental organizations (NGO) and customers. Goff has 14 years' experience in the paper industry and joined Domtar in 2004. She has a master's degree in business administration. She is available to discuss the importance of knowing where your paper comes from, and the environmental and social impacts that result; Domtar's industry-leading sustainability platform, designed to increase sustainability throughout the organization; responsible sourcing; partnership engagement; NGO relations (key Domtar partners include the Rainforest Alliance and the WWF); sustainable supply chains and the importance of transparency; sustainable forestry; how Forest Stewardship Council certification supports environmental responsibility; the state of American agriculture; and issues facing small landowners.Bio:http://www.triplepundit.com/2013/10/women-csr-paige-goff/ Expert Contact: Jessica McHugh,Jessica.McHugh@ogilvy.com
Tom SzakyFounder and CEOTerraCycleAs a college sophomore, Szaky left Princeton University in 2003 to found TerraCycle, a company that enables consumers to collect non-recyclable waste, from used juice pouches to used cigarettes, to be reused, upcycled or recycled into thousands of various products and materials. TerraCycle has won over 200 environmental and social awards for its work, and the company has grown in size every year since its inception, making the Inc. 500 list for the fastest-growing companies in America three times. Today, TerraCycle has partnerships with virtually all major CPG companies, from Kimberly-Clark to Kraft Foods; operates in 25 countries; has over 50 million people engaged in its waste collection programs; collected over 5 billion pieces of non-recyclable waste; and donated over $8 million dollars to charities. Szaky is a seasoned interviewee, having been featured in virtually every major media outlet, including "60 Minutes" and "Oprah," and he blogs for Treehugger, Huffington Post and the New York Times, among others.  He has personally won more than 50 awards for entrepreneurship, and in 2007 he published his first book, "Revolution in a Bottle," and is publishing his second, "Outsmart Waste," in early 2014. He is also the star of the National Geographic Channel TV show "Garbage Moguls," and will soon be seen in the reality series "TerraCycle," which will air in the fall of 2014 on Participant Media's Pivot TV cable network. He is available to discuss top sustainable packaging trends in 2014; top recycling and waste management trends in 2014; challenges with getting people to recycle; consumer tips on how to throw away less and recycle more; barriers to expanding recycling systems; finding ways to recycle almost anything, even cigarette butts; why modern packaging creates a waste dilemma; and how companies can prepare for packaging taxes or extend producer responsibility laws.Media Contact: Albe Zakes,albe.zakes@terracycle.com
John VucetichAssociate Professor of Wildlife EcologyMichigan Technological UniversityVucetich leads the wolf-moose predator-prey study at Isle Royale National Park, the longest running predator-prey study in the world (began in 1958). He opposes wolf hunts and favors repopulating the inbred and dying wolf population of Isle Royale, an extremely controversial stand that the National Park Service has delayed weighing in on. He is available to discuss wolves of Isle Royale National Park, wolf hunting, public policy on repopulating national parks with wolves, endangered species listings.Website:http://www.mtu.edu/newsMedia Contact: Jennifer Donovan,jbdonova@mtu.edu
W. Charles KerfootProfessor of biological sciencesMichigan Technological UniversityKerfoot has studied invasive quagga mussels in Lake Michigan and the ecology of lakes large and small. He is credited with founding the new specialty of "resurrection ecology." He heads the Lake Superior Ecosystem Research Center and won Michigan Tech's Research Award for 2013. He is available to discuss invasive species in the Great Lakes.Website:http://www.mtu.edu/newsExpert Contact:wkerfoot@mtu.eduor +1-906-487-2791Media Contact: Jennifer Donovan,jbdonova@mtu.edu, +1-906-487-4521 or cell: +1-906-281-7530
Andrew StorerProfessor and Insect Ecologist, School of Forest Resources and Environmental ScienceMichigan Technological UniversityStorer is leading research and prevention efforts to find environmentally sustainable ways to combat the emerald ash borer, an invasive Chinese beetle that is killing ash trees in 13 states and Canada. He is available to discuss the emerald ash borer.Website:http://www.mtu.edu/newsMedia Contact: Jennifer Donovan,jbdonova@mtu.edu
David ShonnardRobbins Professor of Chemical Engineering, Director of Sustainable Futures InstituteMichigan Technological UniversityShonnard heads several bioenergy initiatives, including international ones funded by the National Science Foundation. His work led Michigan Tech to be named a Center of Energy Excellence by the State of Michigan. He has researched ethanol and biodiesel made from woody biomass, as well as the "life cycle" of bioenergy -- from growing and harvesting the right plants to conversion processes, transportation and distribution. He is available to discuss bioenergy, biofuels from trees and other woody biomass.Website:http://www.mtu.edu/newsMedia Contact: Jennifer Donovan,jbdonova@mtu.edu
Sharon H. KneissPresident and CEONational Waste & Recycling Association"Americans are doing tremendously well in growing recycling into a mainstream, effective system of handling resources. Yet, we need to balance our desire to continually grow recycling participation rates with the emphasis that Americans need to recycle "smarter" -- they need to be educated on recycling the right items in order to keep our nation's recovery systems efficient and make sure quality commodity products that can be sold at market (the whole point of recycling in the first place!) is the end result of our curbside recycling programs."Kneiss has more than 30 years of business, management and advocacy experience relating to environmental policy at the federal and state levels. She served as vice president, products division with the American Chemistry Council (ACC); in a management capacity at the American Forest & Paper Association; and in policy advocacy roles at Chevron Corporation, Hercules Inc. and the American Petroleum Institute. She has a bachelor of science in chemistry from the University of Scranton and a master of business administration from the University of Pittsburgh. The National Waste & Recycling Association, formerly known as the Environmental Industry Associations, is the national trade association representing America's private sector waste and recycling industry.Kneiss is available to speak to any sustainability issues for which reporters will need the perspective of the waste and recycling industry.Website:http://www.wasterecycling.orgMedia Contact: Parker Wishik,pwishik@kellenadams.com
Anne GermainDirector, Waste and Recycling TechnologyNational Waste & Recycling Association"As many Americans engage in the annual ritual of Spring Cleaning, questions may arise on how to best dispose of some items in your home that seem too dangerous to simply toss in a trash can-paint and chemicals, medication, batteries and even fluorescent light bulbs. While modern landfills are designed to accept these materials, a better option may be available in your community.  These could include household hazardous waste disposal, pharmaceutical take back programs and battery and electronic waste recycling."Germain has two decades of technical experience in the field and previously served as the international president of the Solid Waste Association of North America and the engineering and technology chief for the Delaware Solid Waste Authority. The National Waste & Recycling Associations, formerly known as the Environmental Industry Association, is the national trade association representing America's private sector waste and recycling industry.Germain is available to discuss spring cleaning and how to safely and effectively dispose of "helpful" hazardous waste from your home.Website:http://www.wasterecycling.orgMedia Contact: Parker Wishik,pwishik@kellenadams.com
Chaz MillerDirector, Policy and AdvocacyNational Waste & Recycling Association"The waste stream continues to evolve, getting lighter as products and packaging get lighter. Disposal, however, has been in a slow but steady decline for two decades. Does new data presented by the EPA, which indicates recycling volume is down, really mean that recycling participation is on the downswing? In actuality, the latest numbers tell us more about changes in the materials we use in our daily lives-and the impacts of those changes on what we do with our stuff when we don't want it anymore-than they do about Americans' recycling habits."A longtime industry veteran, Miller has worked at the Environmental Protection Agency's Office of Solid Waste, the glass packaging industry, and this association on a variety of waste and recycling issues. The National Waste & Recycling Association, formerly known as the Environmental Industry Associations, is the national trade association representing America's private sector waste and recycling industry.Miller is available to discuss how the composition and makeup of America's waste stream has changed over time, and the impact of these changes on waste management and recycling rates.Website:http://www.wasterecycling.orgMedia Contact: Parker Wishik,pwishik@kellenadams.com
Mick DalrympleSenior Sustainability Scientist, Global Institute of SustainabilityPractice Lead, Sustainability Solutions Services, Walton Sustainability Solutions InitiativesArizona State University, TempeDalrymple is a seasoned leader, manager, communicator, and educator in the sustainability movement. Since 2001, he has shaped national programs, standards, public policy and public awareness regarding green building and sustainability. He frequently authors articles and serves as a media source and public speaker on sustainability topics. The Business Journal of Phoenix named him Green Pioneer in 2009 for his national and local contributions to the sustainability movement. He is available to discuss energy efficiency, zero net energy, energy codes, STAR community index, sustainability planning.Media Contact: Michelle Schwartz,michelle.schwartz@asu.edu
Emily TalenSenior Sustainability Scientist, Global Institute of SustainabilityProfessor, School of Geographical Sciences and Urban Planning, College of Liberal Arts and SciencesArizona State University, TempeDr. Talen is a published author, focused on new urbanism and sustainable cities. She is the founding co-editor of the Journal of Urbanism and serves on the editorial boards of Open Urban Studies Journal and Urban Morphology. She teaches urban design, principles of urbanism, mapping urbanism, urban geography and new urbanism. She is available to discuss urban design, walkable cities, new urbanism, sustainable cities, urban codes, urban development, urban infrastructure, urban form.Media Contact: Michelle Schwartz,michelle.schwartz@asu.edu
Mark BowlesFounder and Co-InventorecoATMBowles is the founder and co-inventor of the revolutionary technology behindecoATM, the first and only nationwide network of automated electronic recycling kiosks located in shopping malls and select Walmart stores. By providing cash payments for unwanted mobile phones, tablets and MP3 players that would otherwise end up in landfills, ecoATM has recycled more than 500,000 pounds of devices in its four-year history -- that includes more than 2 million individual devices, 70,000 pounds of copper and over 1,500 pounds of silver.Bowles, a successful green entrepreneur, is available to discuss the recycling of electronic waste, and the expansion of the green movement from recycling paper and plastic to the modern-day need for e-cycling. He can also provide advice to consumers and businesses on easy, eco-friendly ways to dispose of devices such as mobile phones and tablets.Media Contact: Natasha Ratliff,natasha.ratliff@edelman.com
Mark LeChevallier, Ph.D.Director of Innovation and Environmental StewardshipAmerican Water, Voorhees, N.J."No one would argue that water conservation isn't a good thing. Yet, in the U.S., water pollution has typically been more of an issue than supply -- until now. Unbelievably, an estimated 36 states could be facing water shortages as early as next year. Climate change, and population growth and redistribution to arid areas, are two reasons. Plus, despite a reduction in household consumption, overall usage in the U.S. is increasing, and people continue to take water service for granted. Case in point: The average American uses 135 gallons of water per capita per day -- 3-4 times that of a German or British citizen."Dr. LeChevallier is known around the industry for his talent for making complex scientific concepts more easily understandable to the general public. He has been dedicated to advancing the science of water for more than 30 years through participation in national research foundations, including conducting nearly $1.5 million of research on the topic of water reuse and planning. He has also served as principal investigator or co-investigator on nearly 60 research grants totaling over $25.5 million. Additionally, he has served on a variety of professional committees at the local and national level, including several for AWWA and U.S. EPA. He is available to discuss such issues as: key impacts on our water resources and supply; the need to change our nation's mindset on the value of water; how water can either enable or limit economic development; how everyone can help reduce daily water use through simple measures.Media Contact: Adam Leiter,aleiter@stargroup1.com
Karin WadsackProject Director, Institute for Sustainable Energy SolutionsNorthern Arizona UniversityWadsack serves as project director for NAU's Institute of Sustainable Energy Solutions and has more than 10 years of experience in renewable energy, climate change and environmental policy, as well as international development, business and project management. She can speak to anything related to utility-scale renewable energy, energy education and state/tribal/federal environmental policy.Media Contact: Jessica Chen,jchen@cooperkatz.com
Adam WerbachCo-founder and Head of ProductYerdleWerbach is an environmental activist, author and entrepreneur. He became the youngest person ever elected as national president of the Sierra Club at the age of 23 in 1996 and is the author of the books "Act Now, Apologize Later" and "Strategy for Sustainability: A Business Manifesto." He is a frequent contributor to The Atlantic, serving as the magazine's online "sustainability expert," and he can provide valuable insight on the green movement. His most current project, yerdle, is a new type of store where users can give and get things for free. Accessible via the iOS app, the store houses thousands of items all donated by other yerdle users or brand partners, like Patagonia, and are available to other members in exchange for yerdle credits, instead of cash. Yerdle's mission is to eliminate 25 percent of new merchandise sales by making it easy for people to find what they need from others willing to lend it or give it away.Media Contact: Emily Pomilio,yerdle@grayling.com
***************
MEDIA JOBS:
Following are links to job listings for staff and freelance writers, editors and producers. You can view these and more job listings on our Job Board:https://prnmedia.prnewswire.com/community/jobs/
Reporter- Baltimore Business Journal (MD)Reporter- The Dallas Observer (TX)Editor- Santa Monica Daily Press (CA)
See more listingshere.
*****************
OTHER NEWS & RESOURCES:
Following are links to other news and resources we think you might find useful. If you have an item you think other reporters would be interested in and would like us to include in a future alert, please drop us a line atprofnetalerts@prnewswire.com
PROTECTING YOURSELF AS A FREELANCE WRITER. It is important for freelancers to be able to generate new story ideas, but it is as equally important for freelancers to know how to protect their own work. In a recent #ConnectChat, Randy Dotinga, freelance writer and vice president of the American Society of Journalists and Authors, discussed what freelancers should look for in a contract, the meaning of copyright, as well as information about ASJA'a annual conference:http://prn.to/1mhG9chMEDIA 411: WAYS JOURNALISTS CAN USE FACEBOOK. As a journalist, you may be familiar with how Twitter can be helpful in your writing. But did you know that Facebook can be beneficial to journalists as well? Here's a list of the top 10 best ways that writers can use Facebook:http://prn.to/NxOedRGRAMMAR HAMMER: COMMA PLACEMENT IN QUOTES. Do commas go inside or outside the quotation marks? According to Cathy Spicer, this is one of the most common mistakes that people make with their writing. She breaks it all down in this week's Grammar Hammer:http://prn.to/1g8ywSd
*****************
PROFNET is an exclusive service of PR Newswire. To submit a request for experts:http://bit.ly/findexperts  To search the ProfNet Connect experts database:http://www.profnetconnect.com  To contact ProfNet by phone: +1-800-PROFNET, ext. 1  To share a thought on Expert Alerts:profnetalerts@prnewswire.com
SOURCE ProfNet
]]></text></news-item>