<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV1-KR51-F05M-K24W"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Greenpeace protests strike P&amp;G again</title><source>Cincinnati Business Courier (Ohio)</source><author>Barrett J. Brunsman</author><text><![CDATA[Procter & Gamble was targeted again today by the environmental advocacy group Greenpeace, whose activists rappelled down the side of P&G's office tower in Jakarta, Indonesia, to unfurl a protest banner in a fashion similar to a publicity stunt earlier this month at the company's headquarters in Cincinnati.
Protests were also staged in:
The Philippines at the P&G facility in Cabuyao, Laguna (south of Manila);Belgium at P&G's Brussels Innovation Center in Grimbergen;India outside the Wella Professionals Salon in New Delhi;And at an industry conference in Manchester, England, attended by P&G employees.
A spokesman for Procter & Gamble (NYSE: PG) didn't immediately respond to a request for comment on how security might have been breached at its Jakarta headquarters or whether any property had been damaged.
On March 4, nine activists with Greenpeace rappelled from the 12th floor of the 17-story twin towers of the Procter & Gamble headquarters in downtown Cincinnati and unfurled two enormous banners to protest deforestation linked to palm oil.
The so-called "P&G 9" were arrested and charged with felony counts of burglary and vandalism. The Hamilton County prosecutor's office reported that those protesters apparently used fake IDs to enter the building and caused about $17,000 in damage. A Greenpeace activist questioned whether the building had actually been damaged.
Earlier this month, Greenpeace protested outside the London office of an advertising agency that works with P&G.
Today, 20 activists were involved in unfurling a banner with the message "Head & Shoulders: 100% rainforest destruction" from the top of P&G's office tower in Jakarta, a Greenpeace spokeswoman told me. Some protested at the building's entrance in tiger costumes.
Greenpeace claims that palm oil used in P&G brands such as Head & Shoulders shampoo, Gillette shaving gel and Olay skin care products is connected to the deforestation of an area of Indonesia that is home to endangered Sumatran orangutans and tigers.
"These protests come in the wake of fresh evidence that a palm oil producer linked to Procter & Gamble's supply chains is destroying primary forest in the Indonesian region of Papua," spokeswoman Kat Clark said. "Greenpeace released the evidence today, documenting large-scale clearance ... in the districts of Sarmi and Jayapura, Papua Province.
"Landsat images showed clearing in areas mapped as primary forest on the Indonesian Ministry of Forestry's 2011 land cover map," Clark said. "The group (responsible) sells palm oil to Cargill, a supplier to P&G."
Clearing rainforests to cultivate palm trees is not only pushing the animals closer to extinction but also speeding climate change, Greenpeace claims. The group wants Procter & Gamble to suspend trade with any producer involved in deforestation.
A P&G spokeswoman previously told me that the company agrees that deforestation is a significant issue and takes seriously any allegation of impropriety by its suppliers.
However, "from India to Belgium to the Philippines, people are demanding that P&G starts taking rainforest destruction seriously," said Joao Talocchi, a Greenpeace spokesman.
"P&G says it's working on sourcing sustainable palm oil, but it's doing this by relying on a certification scheme which has failed to prevent destruction of endangered Sumatran tiger habitat, or reduce the huge amount of carbon pollution that's being released," Talocchi said. "Consumers around the world today are asking P&G to do better."
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Cincinnati Business Courier for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>