<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV1-3SW1-F031-X0BG"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Legal advice about CSG contamination of food not disclosed</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author>Sarina Locke</author><text><![CDATA[To date, there has been no contamination of meat by the coal seam gas sector.
But legal experts warn it's only a matter of time before such an issue comes to court.
Just who is liable for damages, if a consumer falls ill and traces it back to petroleum exploration, is not clear.
The cattle industry attempted to find out last year, but the findings are not allowed to be released due to professional legal privilege.
"I think we have to be clear here," said Dugald Gordon, chief executive of the Australian Lot Feeders Association (ALFA).
"We got Safe Meat to look at this issue and whether it would pose a risk to producers, and they determined the risk is negligible, so we have to be careful about the language we use.
"Our markets are very sensitive on issues such as residues.
"Certainly we need to maintain a watching brief over this issue."
The story has emerged this week, in a Beef Central report, that the Cattle Council and ALFA funded a project, managed by Meat and Livestock Australia, for legal advice on who in the supply chain is covered and who is liable.
But the detailed report has not been released. What's in the public domain is little more than a summary.
Mr Gordon says the issue is complex, and so landowners should monitor their bores.
"We've got consumer law, environmental law, water legislation, contract law and we've got common law and they vary between states.
"So it's complex and we'd have to be careful making general statements.
"It's important landowners monitor their bores. The CSG is expanding and we're aware of that, so let's do the work."
The Basin Sustainability Alliance (BSA), a group representing landholders and rural communities, wants Meat and Livestock Australia to release the report, saying it's shocked it's been kept from cattle producers for 12 months.
Meat and Livestock Australia has released a summary of the legal advice on the MLA website.
MLA says the law firm prepared the report on the basis that it would not be made public, a common practice for legal advice.
Peter Shannon, partner in Shine Lawyers, at Dalby on the Darling Downs, says it's the MLA that is claiming legal privilege in not releasing the advice.
"Legal Privilege is the client's privilege, not the lawyer's privilege, so the client can waive that privilege.
"So if you think about it, the advice is to the MLA. It's unlikely the MLA will be directly involved in court action. It will be a producer, or an organisation producing beef, that would be involved.
"So I think the circumstances in which that privilege are pretty guarded. And in any event, the purpose of getting the advice is to stimulate discussion and lobbying and to understand where producers sit.
"There's absolutely no doubt there's potential for contamination and the extent and potential ramifications are something that should be agitated."
Peter Shannon says he has been involved in 'incidents' where "fracking ponds have overtopped or issues like that have been involved, and generally those get negotiated with the companies. But we are only very early into the production phase in Queensland".
"When we move into the sustenance of the production we'll see an explosion of issues that will bubble up."
On the legal advice, Mr Shannon says there are two issues.
"Initial contractual liability rests between the buyer and the producer, but in negligence where you fail to take reasonable standard of care, to protect against damage, that liability might be both the producer and the CSG company.
"In that circumstance, the producer might sue the CSG company depending on what is in the (CSG company's) access agreement (to the farm).
"And the CSG company might argue contributory negligence by the landholder as to whether he should have done more to protect himself.
"But I think the price of admission of CSG companies onto the properties should mean the landholder is not out of pocket at all."
Ian Coleman, a Senior Counsel, says the miner has a duty of care.
"It's strongly arguable that a coal miner or CSG producer has a duty of care not to do things that pollute waterways or damage the land.
"The most obvious point for landholders is if it's damaging the aquifers.
"There is so much material of a scientific nature, suggesting the risks of damage to aquifers either by polluting them or damaging the aquifer physically so that it ceases to be available, so that it is strongly arguable, (that) they have a duty of care to the water resources and those who they know depend on those aquifers for their livelihood.
"But from there it becomes a matter of proof, in terms of causality, and whether the miner or CSG extractor took reasonable steps."
Meanwhile, the gas industry says it's highly regulated.
Rick Wilkinson, from the Australian Petroleum Production and Exploration Association, expects to meet the same standards as any other industry.
"We have to report to very rigorous reporting regimes. I'm sure farmers are very familiar with them, and we meet those or exceed them."
He says studies by the CSIRO and by the companies into the aquifers are important parts of the final approval for CSG drilling.
]]></text></news-item>