<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV1-TCJ1-JD6S-R4P4"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>YOUR VIEW: PTO Mom: Don't privatize Bristol's school cafeterias</title><source>The Bristol Press (Connecticut)</source><author>Staff Writer</author><text><![CDATA[Dear Mayor Cockayne and the Board of Education: My name is Michele Roalf, born and raised in Bristol and a 1988 graduate of Bristol Eastern High School. I have two boys, a junior at BEHS and a third grader at Ivy Drive School. I am actively involved in the PTO, my third year as secretary at Ivy Drive, and committee chair for several school events and fundraisers.
I am writing this letter because I respectfully disagree with the Bristol Board of Education's decision to pursue privatizing our school cafeterias. My primary concern is for the children attending our public schools.
I have read many articles regarding the lunch vendor, Whitsons. I am horrified by the incidents I have read about in several other states that have occurred. Students were forced to throw away their lunches by the cafeteria staff because the balance in their pre-paid accounts were too low. Whitsons' cafeteria workers' intentions were to humiliate and upset the students; parents said that students were crying, and went home hungry. How dare Whitsons' employees force children to go hungry simply because they don't have enough money for food?
Other complaints are regarding the quality of the food served; either it is under- or over-cooked. They sometimes sell expired milk which has caused some students to get sick. This is appalling; no child should go hungry or be demeaned. A hungry child cannot learn.
Whitsons settled a lawsuit for $1.6 million for being in direct violation of contracts as well as federal and state regulations. Whitsons Culinary Group received savings from the food vendors it worked with and did not pass those savings on to schools.
To quote New York Attorney General Eric Schneiderman, "These are difficult financial times for New Yorkers and our state. For a company to profit off of sweetheart deals, while over-charging our schools is simply unconscionable." Attorney General Schneiderman stated that from the 2002-03 school years through the end of 2010, Whitsons received rebates from its food vendors but failed to pass those savings on to the schools. "Recovering taxpayer dollars is exactly what the Tax Payer Protection Bureau was established to do - and today's announcement sends a clear message that those who seek to defraud New York taxpayers will be held accountable."
These are difficult financial times for the citizens of Bristol. We are being financially paralyzed by paying high taxes, oil and gas prices, food and electricity, the basic necessities to live. If the cost of hot lunch goes up, which seems to be the trend with Whitsons, my boys will no longer purchase hot lunch, as well as most students attending Bristol Schools.
Throughout the 2013 municipal campaign, four of our six city councilors, Ellen Zoppo, Mary Fortier, Calvin Brown, and Richard Meiznichowski, as well as our mayor, all spoke out against the privatization of the cafeteria workers.
I would like to also mention the dedicated cafeteria staff that is currently employed. What kind of sense does it make to hire a company that does not provide health care benefits and will cut their pay checks to minimum wage? I can personally vouch for the two women who run the Ivy Drive cafeteria. They know all the children by their names. They cook and serve the food in a professional manner and they keep a very clean kitchen.
Most importantly, they give a student a cheese sandwich and some milk because they care and have compassion about each and every student and would not let them go hungry, no matter what the financial status is with their account.
Some of these employees have worked in the Bristol school cafeterias for over 20 years, and are now going to lose their jobs to a barbaric food service provider. As far as I am concerned, these people are as critical to the school system as the teachers and I as well as many, many other parents consider them as vital members of our Ivy Drive community family.
Privatizing school lunches here in Bristol will turn out to be a disaster at the expense of our children.
On behalf of the students, parents and taxpayers, I strongly urge the Board of Education members who are pursuing the route of privatizing our cafeteria workers to reconsider.
Michele Roalf
Bristol
]]></text></news-item>