<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV1-NW91-F08V-620G"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Hickory Hills hearing stopped REQUEST ON PROPANE SAFETY will be refiled, attorney says.Jurisdictional questions Residents' concerns </title><source>Eastern Express Times (Pennsylvania)</source><author>TOM SHORTELL The Express-Times</author><text><![CDATA[EASTON | The attorney for Hickory Hills residents withdrew their request Tuesday for a Northampton County judge to appoint a third party to oversee the propane system at the troubled Moore Township mobile home park.
During a hearing before Judge Jennifer Sletvold, attorney Jamie Sutton acknowledged residents had flaws in their motion seeking an emergency order to grant Moore Township temporary administrative authority over the property.
Sutton said Moore Township does not want that authority, and the complaint would have to be amended. Hickory Hills residents created the legal document themselves before he was retained, he said.
He intends to file an amended complaint in the next week or so, he said. The residents instead want the park operator to pay for a third-party engineering firm to oversee repair work on the system to ensure its safety, he said.
&The residents did the best job they could to bring this before you, Your Honor,& Sutton told Sletvold.
The residents have concerns over Hickory Hills' centralized propane system after an explosion Feb. 14 killed William Neith Sr. A subsequent investigation by the state found the 30,000-gallon propane tank is not up to code and management has not taken corrective actions.
Continental Communities LLC, which owns the property, was never served notice of the residents' court filing, said Mark Malkames, Continental's attorney; also, Hickory Hills MHC Management, the management firm listed in the complaint, does not exist. They only learned of the hearing last week by reading an article in The Express-Times, he said.
&There's no possible way we can address issues that were not brought to our attention,& he said.
Sletvold cited concerns of her own that would make the proceedings difficult. Many of the safety violations cited by the state inspectors fall under the purview of the Pennsylvania Department of Labor & Industry or the Public Utility Commission.
&I'm not clear at all if I have jurisdiction over that,& Sletvold said.
Sletvold assured the dozen or so residents present that she understood their concerns over the system but the procedural challenges would limit her ability to hear their complaints.
&I don't want to do anything that would prejudice your rights or, for that matter, the defendants,'& she said.
During the hearing, Malkames said there soon would be no need to have the court intervene. Nearly all of the residences are no longer getting fuel through the underground system, he said, and it will be offline by April 4.
Continental still has until later this month to fix the problems cited by the state, he said.
But Sutton said residents still have valid concerns about how the well the system was shut down and how individual systems were connected to each home.
Some of the homes' setups appear to be improperly installed, he said, with systems resting on cinder blocks with little shelter.
Sutton also claimed some residents reported a second explosion days after the Feb. 14 disaster, as Hickory Hills employees started to make repairs. He questioned whether a map of the mobile home community's pipe system exists, because some residents believe contractors are randomly digging holes searching for pipelines.
&My clients are extremely concerned that the work that was done was not done correctly,& Sutton said. &They are extremely concerned it was done by unlicensed workers.&
Malkames denied any other explosion has occurred and said it's unclear whether any faults in the community system led to the explosion.
If a problem develops on a gas line connecting a household to the community system, it's the responsibility of the resident to fix it, not management, he said. He said Continental was disappointed that residents were spreading misinformation.
&We're not aware of any issues in that community that constitute a threat to anyone in that community,& he said.
Moore Township Police Chief Gary West said he has received no reports of a second explosion at Hickory Hills. Klecknersville Rangers fire Chief John Mann could not be reached for comment.
Reporter Tom Shortell can be reached at 610-258-7171, ext. 3456, or tshortell@express-times.com Follow @TShortell on Twitter.
]]></text></news-item>