<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV1-KR51-F05M-K220"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Without Keystone, 1B barrels of oil stay in the ground, professor says</title><source>Dallas Business Journal</source><author>Nicholas Sakelaris</author><text><![CDATA[The argument that Canada's oil sands will be produced with or without the Keystone XL Pipeline has been challenged by an energy professor from the University of California at Berkeley.
"I think that even under the best-case scenario in terms of supply, where all other pipeline projects are approved and built, not permitting Keystone XL will leave 1 billion barrels in the ground by 2030," said Maximilian Auffhammer, a George Pardee associate professor of international sustainability at UC Berkeley.
Of course, Gary Doer, Canada's ambassador to the United States, had a very different opinion when he spoke at the Texas Energy Council's 26th annual symposium on March 6. Even without the Keystone,&nbsp; Canadian oil moves into the United States via rail and that will continue, he said.
"The theory that the oil would stay in the ground if a pipeline's not built is falling like a house of cards every day with every fact," Doer said.
But Auffhammer said the 830,000-barrel per day Keystone would play a critical role. Relying only on rail-assuming no new pipelines are built-the amount of oil left in the ground could be as high as 10 billion barrels by 2030.
The controversial pipeline from Alberta to Nebraska has been waiting for approval from President Barack Obama since he took office. It needs approval because it cross an international border.
Recent reports have said a decision could come in the next few months. The CEO of TransCanada, the company that proposed the pipeline, has said construction could start this summer if it's approved.
But environmentalists have made their case to Obama while the state of Nebraska is again challenging the route through that state.
If Keystone isn't built, there will be a "binding transport constraint" by 2024, Auffhammer argues.
He goes on to say that "not permitting Keystone 'buys time' for alternative transportation fuels and climate policies to develop."&nbsp;
If that's true, that means the Keystone XL Pipeline does contribute to carbon pollution, which was&nbsp; Obama's main test for approving the project.&nbsp;
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Dallas Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>