<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV1-M8K1-JC6P-C2KT"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>State residents will benefit from $3 million e-book lawsuit</title><source>The Day (New London, Connecticut)</source><author>Lee Howard, The Day, New London, Conn.</author><text><![CDATA[March 26--A settlement related to price-fixing allegations against Apple Inc. and five publishers of e-books will put $3 million into the pockets of Connecticut residents.
Attorney General George Jepsen said Tuesday that Connecticut consumers who claimed to have over paid for the electronic versions of books should check their email or mail to see whether they have received account credits or checks related to the price-fixing suit filed in 2012. Connecticut and 32 other states brought the action.
The partial settlement of the case nationwide totaled $166 million and was recently approved by the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of New York. Payments will be based on e-books purchased between April 1, 2010 and May 21, 2012.
"Consumers are entitled to a fair, open and competitive marketplace, and consumers who have suffered as a consequence of violation of antitrust laws are entitled to compensation," Jepsen said in a statement.
District Court Judge Denise Cote, after a three-week trial last June, ruled that Apple had facilitated a conspiracy to eliminate price competition, resulting in consumer overcharges. Apple is contesting that decision.
A brief filed on behalf of Apple by economists Bradford Cornell of the California Institute of Technology and Janusz Ordover of New York University has argued that Cote never considered that Apple's entry into the e-book market facilitated competition "by diminishing Amazon's power as a retail monopolist."
The five major e-books publishers, however, have decided to settle. The companies involved are Hachette Book Group Inc., HarperCollins Publishers LLC, Simon & Schuster Inc., Holtzbrink Publishers LLC (doing business as Macmillan) and Penguin Group Inc.
"At the upcoming damages trial, Connecticut -- along with Texas and New York -- will be leading the effort on behalf of our partner states to obtain substantial additional compensation for consumers as well as civil penalties for the state," Jepsen said.
For more information about settlements, visit www.ebookagsettlements.com.
l.howard@theday.com
___ (c)2014 The Day (New London, Conn.) Visit The Day (New London, Conn.) at www.theday.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>