<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV1-1TX1-DXKS-J0TN"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>McGuire Memorial Hosts Celebrity Golfers At Two Prestigious Courses; The 22nd Annual McGuire Celebrity Golf Classic is largest charity golf outing in Western PA</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[(http://www.mcguirememorial.org) McGuire Memorial, providing comprehensive services to children and adults with intellectual and physical disabilities, including those on the autism spectrum, is hosting its 22nd Celebrity Golf Classic on June 2, 2014.  The event has grown to be so popular that the tournament is held on two of the area's most prestigious golf courses.  The courses enjoyed by the celebrities and golfers will be Treesdale Golf and Country Club, designed by Arnold Palmer and Diamond Run Golf Course, designed by Gary Player. The McGuire Celebrity Golf Classic is the largest charity golf outing in Western Pennsylvania and continues to grow. The day long outing includes food and beverages along the courses and an awards dinner to be held at the Pittsburgh Marriott North in Cranberry Township.
Former Pittsburgh Steelers, Mike Merriweather and Ernie Mills, and Jim Osborne, formerly of the Chicago Bears will be returning to play the Classic.  Shorty Pit Boss Rossi, of the Animal Planet network program Pitt Boss, will also be playing in this year's Classic. Local media celebrities will include Bill Hillgrove, Paul Alexander and Bob Pompeani.
Sister Mary Thaddeus Markelewicz, the President and CEO of McGuire Memorial, states, "Our golf outing supports McGuire's programs, including our state-of-the-art school, adult day programs as well as our employment option center, community homes and residential campus. The work our caring staff does inspires hope and fosters growth for hundreds of God's most vulnerable and fragile children and adults. We are thankful for the generosity of our sponsors and numerous celebrities. Through their participation, they become part of our caring community, one that respects the dignity of life in every individual." 
James, a resident at McGuire, is the 2014 Honorary Co-Chairperson of the event.  James has been with McGuire since he was 8 years old. After graduating from the School at McGuire, James went on to attend the Adult Training Facility where he puts his unique skills to work.  James hosts the morning announcements at McGuire, where he acts as the "resident meteorologist" giving the weather forecast for each day.  He also advocates for not only himself, but others as needed. James is one of the very special "Entrusted Treasures" who makes McGuire an inspirational community.
Premier Transportation and The Hughes Group are perennial Diamond Sponsors, once again leading the way in support for this year's event.  Blackburn's Pharmacy has committed to the Platinum level, with Cranberry Dental Care, ESB Bank and Huntington National Bank supporting with a Gold sponsorship package. Silver sponsors are BASF, CentiMark, McCarl's, Inc., McCarl's Services, Professional Medical, the Reno Brothers and the Total Equipment Company.  Sponsorships are still available should a company want to participate.
"Our sponsors are critical to the success of the Classic," says Dennis Sabatini, Executive Director of the McGuire Memorial Foundation. He continues, "Their steadfast commitment to helping our "Entrusted Treasures" demonstrates how very philanthropic our community-at-large really is and how deeply the business leaders of our region believe in the McGuire Ministry. We are profoundly grateful for the prodigious corporate support during the past 21 years and are hopeful for continued support for this year's 22nd Annual McGuire Celebrity Golf Classic."
The kick-off for the golf event starts the night before, June 1st, with McGuire's Ramblin' Gamblin' Monte Carlo Night held at the Pittsburgh Airport Marriott. The master of ceremonies will be Andrew Stockey, of WTAE-TV, anchorman and sports director. Stockey will keep the evening moving with fun and laughter. Featuring casino-like games dinner and prizes, the evening sets the stage for a successful golf outing. Visits from the celebrities, residents and students of McGuire will round out the Monte Carlo Night. Individual tickets and sponsorships are still available for this exciting evening.
For more information about the Monte Carlo Night or the McGuire Memorial Golf Classic, please call the McGuire Memorial Foundation office at 724-843-0365 or visithttp://www.mcguirememorial.org. 
About McGuire Memorial
McGuire Memorial is a co-sponsored ministry of the Felician Sisters of North America, Our Lady of Hope Province and the Diocese of Pittsburgh. Forming a joy-filled community of Christian believers, McGuire Memorial is committed to providing comprehensive services to people with mental and physical disabilities that may include complex medical conditions and offers supportive services to their families and caregivers.
SOURCE McGuire Memorial
]]></text></news-item>