<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV1-FWB1-JBRX-8008"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Fraud sentence 2 years for ex-financial adviser $228,606 due elderly client, others</title><source>Arkansas Democrat-Gazette (Little Rock)</source><author>LINDA SATTER ARKANSAS DEMOCRAT-GAZETTE</author><text><![CDATA[A former Little Rock financial adviser was sentenced Tuesday to two years in prison, and ordered to pay $228,606 in restitution, for admittedly defrauding an elderly client who was descending into dementia.
The sentence, which includes five years of probation, was imposed by U.S. District Judge Susan Webber Wright for Christopher "Kit" Williams, 33, now of Bryant, who in December pleaded guilty to a bank-fraud charge. Williams admitted at his plea hearing that he had secretly transferred funds from the account of former University of Central Arkansas physical-therapy professor Joe Finnell into other accounts for his personal use.
Finnell, then 86, was Williams' client at the Charles Schwab investment firm, which fired Williams on June 14, 2012.
Authorities said Williams then began visiting Finnell's home on the pretext of helping him clean, unearthing financial documents during the "cleaning" and using them to access Finnell's bank account online.
Finnell's family attorney, C. Brantly Buck, told the judge that Finnell now lives in a nursing home. He said he thinks the discovery of the fraud hastened Finnell's decline into dementia, noting that the retired professor had been "spry and active" until that point, while relying on Williams' expertise for his financial matters.
Buck also told the judge that the Schwab firm, once alerted to its former employee's actions, was able to prevent an attempt by Williams to transfer $1 million out of Finnell's Schwab account into an e-trade account.
Standing at a courtroom lectern Tuesday morning beside defense attorney Richard Hughes of Little Rock, Williams told Wright that it would be impossible for the judge to impose a sentence that would "teach me more of a lesson" than the day in December 2012 when Charles Briscoe, a special agent with the Social Security Administration's Office of the Inspector General, arrested him in the fraud case and took him away from his young son in handcuffs.
Williams said he was remorseful for his actions. Hughes said he thinks Williams initially had good intentions after Finnell called him for assistance, but "before long, it got out of hand." Assistant U.S. Attorney Alex Morgan argued against Hughes' request that the judge sentence Williams below the 21- to 27-month penalty range suggested in federal sentencing guidelines because of the former broker's military service as an on-call diver with the Navy.
Morgan said Williams - who has also admitted improperly charging more than $5,400 of personal items on a Navy credit card after his guilty plea - already benefited from a reduced penalty range through his plea negotiations. Morgan noted that the plea agreement included the dismissal of other charges of aggravated identity theft and bank fraud, which could have left Williams facing up to 65 months in prison. Morgan also asked Wright to impose the maximum term of probation - five years.
In addition to accessing Finnell's bank account online, Williams tricked the elderly man into signing personal checks made payable to third-party organizations under Williams' control, such as the Arkansas Freeride Society, and opened credit cards in Finnell's name for Williams' personal use, authorities said.
The restitution that Wright ordered Williams to pay is due to Finnell personally as well as to Chase Card Services, Bank of America, the Navy, Citibank and American Express.
Wright ordered Williams, who is divorced, to begin serving his prison sentence May 5.
This article was published 03/26/2014
]]></text></news-item>