<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV1-NW91-F08V-61X9"><date>2014-03-26</date><title></title><source>Plain Dealer (Cleveland, OH)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Copley
Hedge fund operator pleads guilty
A Copley man Tuesday pleaded guilty to charges he operated a fraudulent investment scheme that caused his investors to lose about $1.8 million. Anthony Davian, 34, was charged with 14 counts of securities fraud, mail fraud, wire fraud, and money laundering. He is scheduled to be sentenced July 2. According to charging documents, from 2008 to 2013, Davian used his hedge fund, Davian Capital Advisers LLC, to promote and sell securities to at least 20 investors across several states, resulting in $1.8 million in overall investor loss. Davian purported to sell securities in the form of shares in the various funds he created and controlled, including Davian Capital, Rubber City Gravity, Rubber City Pure Alpha, Cleveland Precious Metals Fund, and others. Instead, he used the investors’ money to pay back earlier investors, to enrich himself, and to pay off personal expenses, such as the purchase of an Audi Q7 Prestige, and the construction of a luxury home, according to the information.
Gambier
Kenyon helps create ‘green cemetery’
Kenyon College, in association with a land trust, plans to convert a golf course into a nature preserve and green cemetery. The Philander Chase Corp., a nonprofit land trust associated with the college, purchased the 51-acre Tomahawk Golf Course in Knox County in 2013. Nine of the 18 holes will remain and be leased. Converting about 30 acres into a nature preserve for natural burials – to be known as the Kokosing Nature Preserve – protects the land and meets the demand of families interested in an environmentally friendly final resting place, the college said. It said it is the only college in the country with a land trust. Through the use of agricultural and conservation easements, the land trust has helped preserve about 5,000 acres since its founding in 2000. The land trust is seeking certification from the national, nonprofit Green Burial Council, which has certified 38 cemeteries in the United States, including four in Ohio.
higher education
Most veterans graduate, study shows
Just over half of veterans who sought a higher education from 2002 through 2013 under the GI Bill completed schooling ranging from vocational training to post-graduate, according to an unprecedented review of nearly 800,000 college records, according to USA Today. The research, to be presented by the Student Veterans of America service organization, is the first in-depth look at how those who fought in Iraq and Afghanistan are performing in college. While analysts say results could be better, the numbers appear to refute reports that most of these veterans are dropping out or failing in college, the newspaper said. About one in three of the veterans earned a bachelor’s degree or higher. “I’ve heard it over the last few years about the disaster of these students. That it’s terrible, [that] they’re just flunking at huge rates,” Shelley MacDermid Wadsworth, a Purdue University professor and director of the Military Family Research Institute who studied the report, told USA Today. “That’s not right.” The completion rate for these veterans of 51.7 percent is lower than the four-year graduation rate for younger, non-veteran peers, which was 59 percent in 2011. “Looking at the obstacles and the issues that student vets have to deal with ... I think we’re doing quite well,” says Wayne Patterson, a former Army command sergeant major and now president and CEO of Student Veterans of America. The most sought-after undergraduate degrees by veterans were in business, social sciences, homeland security, law enforcement and firefighting, and computer and information services, the report said.
Ohio
Common Core off to a strong start
The first day of testing out the new Common Core exams that Ohio and other states will start using for real next year went well Monday, according to Ohio’s testing partnership and the state. The Partnership for Assessment of Readiness for College and Careers (PARCC) — the testing partnership Ohio joined along with 16 other states — reported Monday that more than 40,000 students took the tests. “It has gone more or less as we expected – some glitches, but overall fairly smooth,” PARCC said on its website. About 120,000 Ohio students will test drive the new standardized exams that Ohio plans — tentatively — to start using in 2015. Ohio is in the process of shifting toward the new Common Core standards for each grade shared by 45 states.
cleveland
Service academy seminars scheduled
U.S. Senators Sherrod Brown and Rob Portman are co-hosting 10 U.S. Service Academy Seminars across the state in April and May. The information sessions are designed for students who are interested in applying for the Air Force Academy, Military Academy at West Point, Naval Academy and Merchant Marine Academy. The seminar in Cleveland will be held April 26 at the Horizon Science Academy, 6000 South Marginal Road, from 10 a.m. to noon. Student applicants are reviewed by a committee of active and retired military and community leaders, and provided with the required congressional recommendation upon applying for admission. Participants are asked to RSVP if planning to attend a seminar. Contact the academy coordinators at (1-800-205-6446) or (1-888-896-6446 then press 1). Other seminar dates are as follows. All seminars are scheduled for 6-8 p.m.
April 2, Zane State College, Zanesville.
April 8, Mills Morgan Tower, Beavercreek.
April 9, North Central State College, Mansfield.
April 10, Center for Business Services, Lima.
April 15, Youngstown State University.
April 16, Ohio State University, Columbus.
April 17, Scripps Center, Cincinnati.
April 23, Jackson City Library, Jackson.
May 8, University of Toledo, Toledo.
]]></text></news-item>