<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV1-FWB1-JBRX-8005"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Progress cited as anniversary of Mayflower oil spill nears</title><source>Arkansas Democrat-Gazette (Little Rock)</source><author>AZIZA MUSA ARKANSAS DEMOCRAT-GAZETTE</author><text><![CDATA[MAYFLOWER - At least once a week, Faulkner County Judge Allen Dodson visits the Northwoods subdivision to check on the neighborhood's progress.
And at least two to three times a week, Dodson monitors the oil sheens that pop up in Lake Conway's Dawson Cove - remnants of the Exxon Mobil pipeline rupture on March 29, 2013.
"We've made a lot of progress," he said during a news conference Tuesday, just four days before the anniversary of the spill. He added that officials should "be mindful" of those who were affected by the rupture. "At the same time, we have a duty to take stock of where we are after a year," he said.
The roughly 850-milelong Pegasus pipeline, which runs from Illinois to the Gulf Coast of Texas, burst in the Northwoods subdivision, spilling an estimated 210,000 gallons of heavy crude oil into the area. The spill prompted the evacuation of 22 homes. Many residents still haven't moved back, and the cleanup continues.
On Tuesday, the oil giant's representatives walked through the subdivision with local officials as landscapers tended to mulch and bushes in front of an empty home.
A curb once stained black that runs the course of North Starlite Road has been replaced and the road redone. Fresh fences and new mailboxes have been installed.
Although Dodson said he hadn't heard from the former neighborhood residents, he said he assumed they were still digesting the events of the past year.
"My hope is they've moved on with their life," he said.
The neighborhood and protecting the values of property within it are among Exxon Mobil's priorities going into the second year, officials said during the news conference Tuesday.
Karen Tyrone, an Exxon Mobil Pipeline Co. vice president, said the testing of thousands of samples - including from the Arkansas Department of Environmental Quality and a third-party laboratory chosen by the oil company but approved by the state agency - confirmed there was no "ecological risk" in the cove, connected channels or the neighborhood.
However, the Environmental Quality Department recently told Exxon Mobil that it must do more to correct oil-related contamination in the cove and three drainage ditches leading to it.
The Arkansas Game and Fish Commission has also said the oil giant's statements "regarding the presence or absence of adverse effects or risk to ecological receptors are worded in too definitive a manner." Ecological receptors refer to nonhuman, living organisms that environmental contamination can harm. Such receptors include plants and bloodworms.
Last week, the Environmental Quality Department approved Exxon Mobil's report that assessed the extent and severity of lingering oil contamination. The approval allowed the company to move forward with plans to reduce oil sheening by excavating up to 1 foot of affected soil and sediment from a channel of water leading into the cove and capping the sheens with sand and clay.
The company still needs to submit to the state department a Mitigation Action Plan, but the oil giant's officials said they were working on a "pre-design study" to develop that plan.
"There's a remnant of a small visual impact, and we're going to address that," Tyrone said, adding that there's an "intermittent sheen in a limited" part of the cove. "It's not a widespread problem. You have to go find it," she said.
The company, she said, will take "appropriate action" under the Environmental Quality Department and will continue to monitor the oil sheens weekly.
Exxon Mobil also has until April 7 to turn in a Remedial Work Plan to the federal Pipeline and Hazardous Materials Safety Administration. Officials plan to meet with stakeholders and agencies including Central Arkansas Water later this week before handing in the remedial plan, Tyrone said, adding that she wouldn't yet disclose what the oil company's "findings" were after a year.
"[The Pipeline Administration] will be the key in determining if the plan is appropriate and what the next steps are," she said, adding that Exxon Mobil needed to "prove the integrity of the pipeline" before moving forward.
The federal agency hadn't given the oil company approval to reopen any part of the pipeline as of Tuesday, Exxon Mobil spokesman Aaron Stryk said.
In the meantime, part of the company's focus is to begin drawing potential buyers to the neighborhood.
After meetings with company officials, lenders, real estate agents and brokers, Exxon Mobil has sent in crews to repaint, change flooring and make upgrades to some of the empty homes, said Garret Smith, regional commercial manager for the oil company's environmental services division. He added that five or six families have returned.
The company has retained "a couple dozen" of the subdivision's homes and has opened an information center and a model home there. The goal, Smith said, is to maintain the subdivision's pre-spill property values, but the company doesn't want to compete "too much" with those who have stayed in the neighborhood.
The company hopes to launch the open houses and showings in late April, he said.
Mayflower Mayor Randy Holland said he has started receiving calls from some interested in moving to the town.
"I see it getting a lot of better going forward," he said. "I'm ready for Mayflower to move forward. It's time."
This article was published 03/26/2014
]]></text></news-item>