<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV1-P4S1-DYTB-Y17V"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Netline sues Chilean operators for US$118mn in market entry barrier compensation</title><source>Business News Americas - English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Chilean MVNO Netline is to sue Chile's main operators - Movistar, Entel and Claro - for almost US$118mn in compensation for what it alleges to be barriers to market entrance put in place by the telcos, according to a release by consumer association Conadecus citing local business publication Diario Financiero.
Netline previously filed a lawsuit with anti-trust body TDLC claiming that the telcos have not honored a ruling from two years ago that fined operators for obstructing the entrance of MVNOs into the market.
Without the barriers to market entrance put in place by the main operators, Netline would have entered the market as an MVNO in 2007, prior to the arrival of other MVNO's such as Virgin Mobile.
In 2006 mobile penetration in Chile reached just 75%, suggesting that there was still growth potential in the market.
If the company had been able to enter the market in 2007, it would have gained a share of around 40% of the MVNO market, Netline alleges.
This claim will no doubt be questioned, however, by the established telcos in the country. As it is, Netline entered the Chilean market in the middle of 2012, reaching just 3,263 subscribers as of June 2013 following 12 months of operations.
Meanwhile, fellow MVNO Virgin entered the market in April 2012, and reached 166,277 subscribers as of the end of 2013, according to telecoms regulator Subtel's statistics.
Leading retailer Falabella launched its own MVNO operation in September last year and had reached 54,822 subscribers by the end of December.
Such statistics may make it tempting for established players to argue that a lack of competitive advantage, as oppose to barriers to market entry, have impeded Netline's success.
The three leading telcos have, however, found themselves increasingly questioned over the lack of competition in the industry, as new operators in Chile have gained only limited market share.
Consumer association filed a complaint with competition watchdog TDLC against the three main telcos in the country over alleged spectrum hoarding, and previously requested the suspension of the recently concluded 700MHz auction.
http://www.bnamericas.com/story.xsql?id_sector=2&id_noticia=641885&Tx_idioma=I&source=
]]></text></news-item>