<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV1-DY51-DYG5-4029"><date>2014-03-25</date><title>Veterans end lobbying on asbestos bill | Groups upset to hear Walker plans to sign limits on lawsuits</title><source>Milwaukee Journal Sentinel (Wisconsin)</source><author>PATRICK MARLEY, pmarley@journalsentinel.com Milwaukee Journal Sentinel, Milwaukee Journal Sentinel (WI)</author><text><![CDATA[Madison - Veterans opposed to a bill curtailing asbestos lawsuits are standing down on their efforts to persuade Gov. Scott Walker to reject the measure after an aide to the governor told a leader of a veterans group there is no way to stop it.
"We're extremely disappointed," said Jason Johns, the legislative officer for the Military Order of the Purple Heart of Wisconsin. "We're not necessarily going to forget about it."
Many veterans remain adamantly opposed to the business-backed measure because they have found the majority of plaintiffs in asbestos lawsuits have served in the military. Asbestos, which has long been used for insulation and fireproofing, can cause cancer and respiratory illnesses.
On Friday, a day after the Assembly sent the bill to the governor, Johns sent an email urging veterans to call Walker's office to oppose the bill.
Less than two hours later, Johns sent a follow-up email telling them to back off, because he said Walker policy adviser Waylon Hurlburt had told another veteran that Walker was committed to signing the bill.
In an interview Monday, Johns said he was passing on information Hurlburt had told Kenneth Rynes, commander of the American Legion of Wisconsin. "Continuing to put pressure on the Gov to veto, will not make a difference and will only irritate him," according to Hurlburt, Johns wrote in his email.
"'Retreat' is not in my nature, but for the interest of the (Military Order of the Purple Heart's) future veterans fights, and not wanting to risk affecting those endeavors in pursuit even further of this bill that is going to be signed no matter what. So as a result, I recommend (although I am not happy about it) that we inform everyone to 'Stand Down' on" the bill.
In addition to his role with the Military Order of the Purple Heart, Johns is a lobbyist for the Wisconsin Asbestos Victims Network. A former deputy secretary of veterans affairs in Walker's administration, Johns received a Purple Heart in 2011 for injuries he received in Iraq in 2003.
In the interview, Johns called stopping the asbestos bill the top priority of veterans this legislative session. Lawmakers from both parties for years have been good to veterans, he said. But when it came to the life-or-death matter of asbestos lawsuits, Republicans in the Legislature chose businesses over veterans, Johns said.
The drafting file for the bill shows lobbyist Andy Cook had a hand in writing the bill. Cook's clients include Wisconsin Manufacturers & Commerce, the state's largest business lobby, and the Wisconsin Civil Justice Council, an alliance of major industries that advocates for limiting lawsuits.
Many of the companies that produced asbestos created trust funds to pay claims as they filed for bankruptcy protection.
Victims can file claims with the trusts and can also sue companies that are still in business. The bill approved last week would require plaintiffs to disclose any actions against trusts that they have filed or plan to file.
Double-dipping?
Supporters say the measure aims to prevent people from trying to collect twice. Opponents say the bill makes it harder for victims to get fully compensated. The bill would help businesses when they are sued because they could point out to the jury that the plaintiffs had filed claims against trusts. That could bolster their arguments they were not to blame for the asbestos exposure at issue.
Walker's Democratic opponent, former state Commerce Secretary Mary Burke, opposes the bill.
"For politicians beholden to special interests to stand in the way of holding companies accountable and making it harder for those affected to seek compensation for legitimate claims is unacceptable to me," Burke said in a statement.
Walker spokeswoman Laurel Patrick said the governor is evaluating the bill, but she did not address if Hurlburt had said Walker plans to sign it no matter what.
Patrick stressed that the Department of Veterans Affairs never took a position on the bill.
"This bill is about ensuring transparency in the lawsuit process to stop trial lawyers from double dipping," Patrick said in a statement. "Preventing double dipping will help make sure there will be resources available for the truly injured down the road."
Veterans groups have railed against the measure. The Wisconsin American Legion, Wisconsin Veterans of Foreign Wars and Wisconsin Military Order of the Purple Heart issued a joint state- ment last week condemning Assembly Republicans for passing the bill.
Renee Simpson, commander of the Wisconsin Veterans of Foreign Wars, said in that statement that Assembly members had "turned their backs" on veterans and their families. Simpson's father died of asbestos exposure.
"After months of good faith negotiations, I am extremely disappointed that (the bill) lacked much needed language to ensure veterans and their families are not left bearing the burden created by the asbestos companies that poisoned them," Rynes said in the joint statement.
Another veterans group, Wisconsin AMVETS, came out in support of the legislation in January, arguing that the bill would protect funds for asbestos victims.
In a statement, Walker's veterans affairs secretary, John Scocos, said his agency took no stance on the measure because it does not specifically target veterans for their military service.
"There are many varying opinions on this topic in the veteran community," he said in his statement.
The Assembly passed the bill 55-38, with all Republicans in favor of it and all Democrats against it. The Senate approved the bill 17-16 earlier this month, with Sen. Dale Schultz (R-Richland Center) joining all Democrats in opposing it.
Twitter: twitter.com/patrickdmarley
Copyright 2014, Journal Sentinel Inc. All rights reserved. (Note: This notice does not apply to those news items already copyrighted and received through wire services or other media.)
"I am extremely disappointed that (the bill) lacked much needed language to ensure veterans and their families are not left bearing the burden. "Kenneth Rynes Commander, American Legion of Wisconsin "This bill is about ensuring transparency in the lawsuit process to stop trial lawyers from double dipping." Laurel Patrick Scott Walker spokeswoman
Copyright, 2014, Journal Sentinel, All Rights Reserved.
]]></text></news-item>