<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV2-3H41-JCPJ-W23B"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Charlotte Mayor Patrick Cannon arrested on federal corruption charges</title><source>Jacksonville Business Journal</source><author>Jen Wilson</author><text><![CDATA[Charlotte, North Carolina Mayor Patrick Cannon was arrested by FBI agents on Wednesday for alleged violations of federal public corruption laws.
A criminal complaint filed in U.S. District Court in the Western District of North Carolina charges Cannon&nbsp;with theft and bribery, wire fraud and extortion,&nbsp;accusing him of accepting bribes from undercover FBI agents on five separate occasions.
According to the charging documents and affidavits filed by law enforcement, the FBI began investigating Cannon, a Democrat, in or about August 2010, after receiving a tip that he was potentially involved in illegal activities associated with his position as an elected official.
The complaint and affidavit allege that during the course of that investigation, Cannon solicited and accepted money bribes and things of value from undercover agents who were posing as commercial real estate developers and investors wishing to do business in Charlotte, in exchange for the use of his official positions as mayor, mayor pro tem and as a Charlotte City Council member.
The documents state that on Feb. 21, the most recent occasion, Cannon allegedly accepted $20,000 in cash in the mayor's office. And the documents allege that between January 2013 and February 2014, Cannon accepted $48,000 in cash, airline tickets, a hotel room and use of a luxury apartment.
In the criminal complaint, the FBI cites Cannon's dealings with an unnamed "prominent local businessman." The complaint states that Cannon alluded to an undercover agent that he had "assisted and intervened in a major project - using his official position - on behalf of (a) prominent local businessman."
An affadavit from FBI special agent Eric Davis states that Cannon accepted $6,000 in cash and an all-expense-paid trip to Las Vegas for him and his wife in July 2013. The purpose was to tell foreign investors about his ability to make projects get through regulatory process in Charlotte, the affidavit says.
Read the links below or&nbsp; the full report from the Charlotte Business Journal here.&nbsp;
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Jacksonville Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>