<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV2-4SP1-JC8H-P0HK"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Taseko files second judicial review on New Prosperity</title><source>Canada NewsWire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[VANCOUVER, March 26, 2014 /CNW/ - Taseko Mines Limited (TSX:TKO; NYSE MKT:TGB) ("Taseko" or the "Company") today applied for a second judicial review in respect to the federal government's recent decision on its proposed New Prosperity Gold-Copper Mine Project.
Russ Hallbauer, President & CEO of Taseko stated that the New Prosperity project, and specifically Taseko's plan to save Fish Lake, was not evaluated in a fair, open and transparent manner.  "We will seek to rectify both the failed process and the decision that stemmed from it in a court of law, the only reasonable option open to us."
Taseko maintains it had a legitimate expectation that if any third-party representations were made to the federal government concerning the project after the Panel Review was complete that Taseko would be afforded an opportunity to make responses to those submissions.  The Company was never given that opportunity.
Among Taseko's claims are that government officials held inappropriate closed door meetings with opponents of the proposed mine without Taseko's knowledge or informing the Company of the content of those meetings.
"We believe that the final government decision failed to consider critical information submitted by the Company and thus failed to fully understand our commitment and ability to protect the environment," added Mr. Hallbauer. "We were never given a fair opportunity to correct any misrepresentations about the project, nor were we allowed to clarify any misunderstanding on our plan to save Fish Lake."
Taseko is asking the Federal Court to set aside decisions by the CEAA, the Minister of Environment and the Governor in Council because of "a failure to observe the principles of natural justice and procedural fairness."
Russell Hallbauer President & CEO
No regulatory authority has approved or disapproved of the information contained in this news release.
CAUTION REGARDING FORWARD-LOOKING INFORMATION
This document contains "forward-looking statements" that were based on Taseko's expectations, estimates and projections as of the dates as of which those statements were made. Generally, these forward-looking statements can be identified by the use of forward-looking terminology such as "outlook", "anticipate", "project", "target", "believe", "estimate", "expect", "intend", "should" and similar expressions.
Forward-looking statements are subject to known and unknown risks, uncertainties and other factors that may cause the Company's actual results, level of activity, performance or achievements to be materially different from those expressed or implied by such forward-looking statements. These included but are not limited to:
For further information on Taseko, investors should review the Company's annual Form 40-F filing with the United States Securities and Exchange Commission www.sec.gov and home jurisdiction filings that are available at www.sedar.com.
SOURCE Taseko Mines Limited
]]></text></news-item>