<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV2-B0S1-DXJR-H02H"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>After Honda &amp; Maruti Suzuki, Toyota faces labour unrest in India; Are Japanese cos insensitive?</title><source>The Economic Times</source><author>Naren Karunakaran</author><text><![CDATA[Osamu Suzuki, chairman of Suzuki Motor Corporation (SMC) has always emphasised on and tutored his Indian managers that cost reduction and improvement is a continuous process. It’s the reason why Japan has emerged as the lowest-cost manufacturer of cars in the world. On a particular occasion, he told RC Bhargava, now chairman of Maruti Suzuki India, that back home in Japan, they were veritably wringing water out of a dry towel. By comparison, the Indian towel, he added, was dripping!
The dripping towel metaphor for Indian manufacturing is perhaps apt. We are nowhere near Japanese benchmarks on costs, shop-floor practices, and their unique approaches to doing things—the ken for hard work and perfection, discipline and consensual decision-making. “They will invariably nudge and push any activity to the nth degree of excellence,” says YH Gharpure, president of the Pune–based Indo-Japan Business Council (IJBC), an industry association focused on strengthening business ties between India and Japan.
If this celebrated ‘Japanese way’ is indeed the ideal, why then are so many of the Japanese ventures in India—Honda, Suzuki and, at present, Toyota—facing recurrent labour strife? Why are they often caught in swirls of controversies? How can one, for instance, explain Suzuki’s insistence on setting up a new manufacturing subsidiary in Gujarat, rendering, as analysts fear, Maruti Suzuki into a mere marketing outfit?
Is it something to do with the peculiar Japanese way of thinking or our inability to comprehend them? It’s both, according to Ravi Kamat, also of IJBC and managing director of Softbridge Solutions, a software and training company that has been hand holding a bevy of Japanese companies with a view to bridge the socio-cultural abyss between Indians and the Japanese. Given Japanese predilections, their desire to improve upon the business objective by a certain degree every year is par for the course. It fits neatly into the continuous improvement framework. And if, at some point in time, a complete overhaul of the management system is necessitated to achieve that objective, so be it.
“Suzuki has invested money for a return they are expecting,” explains Kamat. “And if they know the market is capable of giving them those returns, they will keep pushing, relentlessly. That is, till people across the table say: thus far, and no further. Theirs is a very different way of looking at, and executing opportunities,” he says. This ‘continuous improvement’ paradigm has borne fruits in India over the years.
At Maruti Suzuki, which is poised to regain 50 per cent market share, it has enabled the company to not only meet overwhelming customer demand for its cars over the years, barring blips, but also churn out light and fuel-efficient cars. How did it happen? Among other things, by painstakingly reducing the weight of car components by as little as a few grams a year —year after year.
It is the same mindset that is constantly pushing for ways to enhance intellectual property, ratchet royalty or increase profits for the parent company. “They abhor static situations,” says Kamat, who is among the few Indians with a firm understanding of the Japanese psyche. How does the labour turmoil at Japanese plants in India then fit into the narrative? Can it be attributed to the constant wringing of the cost towel?
Or, is it possible that the Japanese are exporting the stress and trauma of work conditions back home in Japan to their overseas operations, in India, and elsewhere?
 
‘Karoshi’ and ‘Karojisatsu’
In 2005, an American who worked with the Toyota system in Japan wrote a book on his experiences that stung the Japanese. While Darius Mehri lauded the yearning for efficiency and innovation in his book, titled ‘Notes from Toyota-Land: An American Engineer in Japan’, he was appalled by the human cost it engendered. The punishing work ethic, unyielding deadlines, the widespread practice of unpaid overtime, the oppressive ‘culture of rules’ was highlighted.
Japanese society continues to battle deleterious issues related to the workplace and workers. The situation has even given rise to a condition called karoshi (death by overwork) and karojisatsu (suicide due to overwork and stress). This disturbing pattern among Japanese workers has been of concern to the government there for the estimates are unnerving: over 10,000 incidents of karoshi deaths and over 31,000 suicides annually, according to a journal of the Asian Network for the Rights of Occupational and Environmental Victims.
According to the old order, a Japanese worker was ensured lifetime employment and was expected to be loyal to his employer by putting in long hours. Complaining was seen as dishonourable and there was little notion of any life beyond work. It is only now, reacting to the crises at the workplace, the government is implementing a new ‘work-life balance charter’.
This tradition is, however, giving way and the younger generation do not subscribe to warped notions of loyalty and sacrificing oneself for the employer. “Youngsters aspire for a better life, and are beginning to think and act differently,” says Yoshihisa Hatta, a 23-year-old business executive, who is in India on a short internship.
The Japanese managing director of a large Japanese electronics company in India, who spoke on the condition of anonymity, agrees and maintains that people like him, with 30 years of a service in a single company, will be a rarity. He also attributes the painful churn in society to the pretty long economic downturn in Japan; it’s a reason why labour strife has aggravated. Japanese companies, facing intense global competition and the pressure to reduce costs, have little choice but to exploit the workforce; unpaid overtime is rampant.
The problems also manifests in the rising number of contract, or non-regular workers, in Japan. It stands at 18.13 million, almost a third of the total workforce and a jump of 57 per cent since 1997. Cultural Differences Contract workers are also growing in numbers in India. Between 2008 and 2013, the number of contract workers has grown by 39 per cent, according to a recent study by industry chamber Assocham, titled ‘India’s Workforce Goes Casual’.
In 2007, when Maruti Suzuki built a swanking new plant at Manesar, in Haryana, the Japanese naturally gravitated towards this low cost, flexible option and populated the plant with an army of contract workers, hired through contractors. “They did it like they did it elsewhere in the world,” says Bhargava. “They had no clue about local ethos and cultural mores.”
 
Youngsters from Haryanvi farming families were picked up and pushed into pressure- cooker assembly-line situations of high production efficiency. Leave requests were disregarded, and even toilet breaks were frowned upon; something the simple rustic minds couldn’t comprehend. “They stretched the idea of anushasan (discipline) to stupefying limits,” says Kuldeep Janghu, general secretary of the Maruti Udyog Kamgar Union (MUKU), the union for the Gurgaon plant. (Leaders of the Manesar Union are in jail following the violence of 2012 and the workers at that plant are represented by an ad-hoc committee instituted by the Labour Commissioner.) The typical Indian worker, with high family attachments and responsibilities, expect leave of absence when necessary.
This is unlike typical Japanese workers, who display their love for family by immersing themselves at work for the family’s sake. “Indian workers want to be with family; to mourn, to celebrate,” says Pawan Kumar, president, MUKU. All of this didn’t occur to the Japanese managers at Maruti Suzuki.
Suzuki always wanted the Manesar plant to be akin to the one in Kosai, Japan, with all the best practices the Japanese had to offer. The idea of it as an extension of the Gurgaon plant, with a certain degree of the Indian way perhaps didn’t fit in. The Manesar plant was to be Osamu Suzuki’s exemplar in “better productivity, lower costs, and higher quality.” The start of the Manesar plant also coincided with a 25 per cent spurt in demand for cars in India.
“The maximum pressure naturally was on us at Maruti Suzuki,” says SY Siddiqui, COO, administration, Maruti Suzuki. The Manesar plant churned out the hugely in-demand Swift and Dzire models. “We did what we shouldn’t have: ensure high levels of attendance and discipline by diktat,” concedes Bhargava of Maruti Suzuki. It was a disaster waiting to happen, and it did in July 2012, when workers went berserk at the plant, leading to the death of an HR manager.
“The Japanese had taken absolute control of the Manesar plant,” insists Janghu. “It was as if they wanted to prove a point and demonstrate their way of doing things.” To ensure that the lines rolled without a squeak, a host of unsavoury measures were imposed. “The practice of knocking off the incentives earned by a worker if he took leave was wrong,” concedes Siddiqui. And of course, the wage gap between contract workers and regulars simmered.
 
Communication Gap
As the Japanese went about stamping the Japanese way, a serious “listening gap” emerged in the absence of structured communication channels between the management and workers. The Japanese, in India, usually shy away from interacting with overseas workers. Why? “Because they are scared of doing something wrong,” says the Japanese MD of the electronics firm.
A Japanese MD is usually on overseas contract for a couple of years.It perhaps stems from the fear of jeopardising their career for any crisis means a shameful recall to headquarters. It also has something to do with the Japanese upbringing. “It’s a culture that tells them you cannot commit a mistake,” says Kamat, who is always telling the Japanese under his tutelage that it’s okay to commit a mistake.
The Japanese MD was like any of his peers till his stint in Mexico, where he broke the mindset barrier. He is now engaging with his Indian workers directly by brushing aside interlocutors. “The trust deficit that existed at my plant is now seeing a remarkable thaw,” he says. The crisis in Japanese companies outside Japan can also be attributed to the manner in which operations are structured and the way they work. The Japanese spend an enormous time in planning and seeking consensus on issues. But once the project plan is frozen, then it’s on to execution, which is a song, as every little aspect has been considered. The chance of going back to the plan or tweaking it is remote.
The mandate of a Japanese MD is to execute as per plan. He has little freedom to act on his own even when situations outside the plan emerge. Therefore, they are often seen as rigid and obstinate. “All the thinking is done in Tokyo,” says Kamat. “They work this way because they don’t like working with too many variables. It impinges on quality.” So, there are learnings for the entire pack of Japanese companies in India. “Standard operating procedures from Japan can’t be implanted here,” says Vishnu Mathur, director general, Society of Indian Automobile Manufacturers (SIAM). This is especially true while dealing with workers. “A degree of empathy for workers is desirable,” he adds.
Are the Japanese to be blamed squarely for worker unrest in their Indian factories then? Kamat is certain that the Indian managers are also to be held responsible as they are the interface to Indian workers. They go into meetings merely to nod their heads. It’s also a cultural issue: Indians are unable to say no to their bosses.
“Why didn’t the Indian managers at Maruti Suzuki provide the right feedback to the Japanese about brewing workers unrest?” asks Kamat. Bhargava agrees. “Unfortunately, the Indian managers just followed what the Japanese wanted. So, it’s our fault also.” Again, the cultural thing: the Indian inclination to say “ho jayega” (it will be done) or “no problem”, when the ground realities are quite different. Whenever, the articulate, breaking-themould Japanese MD hears those two words—no problem —during the course of his work, he knows it’s the Indian habit of exaggeration, and is immediately on his guard. The Japanese are learning, quickly.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>