<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV2-B0S1-DXJR-H00X"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Panel suggests allowing mining in Goa with production cap</title><source>The Economic Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NEW DELHI: In what may eventually help in further relaxing the Supreme Court's iron ore mining ban in Goa, an expert committee set up for the macro environmental impact assessment (EIA) study has submitted its interim report to the court suggesting that mining may be permitted at the level of an annual cap of 20 million tonnes once the state sets up an adequate regulatory and monitoring mechanism.
Emphasizing on the need to strictly regulate mining activities in Goa, the report, filed through amicus curiae A D N Rao, said the regulation would ensure minimum damage to ecological systems.
The apex court had on October 5, 2012 banned mining of iron ore and its export, acting on a PIL following a report of irregularities by the Justice MB Shah Commission. The PIL was filed by Goa Foundation, a non-governmental organization (NGO).
In its 11-point recommendation, the six-member committee, said, "It may not be desirable to start fresh extraction without adequate regulatory and technological measures that ensure restoration of degraded landscapes and ecosystems and minimize future damage to the environment".
It suggested that the monitoring and regulation can be done by the department of mines and geology and Goa State Pollution Control Board in consultations with Indian Bureau of Mines and ministry of environment and forests.
It said that such monitoring should continue for mining activity, as directed by the Supreme Court, till the scientific study of the committee is completed. The committee feels that the scientific study may take minimum 12 months.
The other recommendations include exploring an option by the state to set up a mineral corporation or a government public limited company. The committee feels that this option may not only break the monopoly of private miners but also maximize state's earnings.
Setting up multi-disciplinary ecological centre in Goa by imposing a cess on the mining activity and creating 'permanent fund' for promoting sustainable development are other two key suggestions of the committee.
The report of the committee will be taken up the court on its next date of hearing. Though the matter was listed for Monday, the hearing could not take place as one of the judges on the three-judge bench was not available.
Besides filing the report of the six-member committee, the amicus curiae also submitted yet another report of a different committee which provided details on the e-auctioning of the excavated iron ore by the Goa government.
The second report said that the state government had e-auctioned a quantity of 545369 MT (metric tons) of iron ore on February 17. "The total value realized through the e-auction of the ore was Rs 93.82 crore approximately", it said.
The Supreme Court had recently allowed a relaxation in its earlier mining ban order by allowing the state government to conduct e-auction of iron ore, extracted prior to ban, under a monitoring committee set up by the court.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>