<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV2-B0S1-DXJR-H02R"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Reliance Industries Limited confirms cooperation with CAG under production sharing contract terms to the Supreme Court</title><source>The Economic Times</source><author>Samanwaya Rautray</author><text><![CDATA[NEW DELHI: Reliance Industries Limited (RIL) on Wednesday rejected an allegation made by a public interest petitioner that the company had vigorously resisted a Comptroller and Auditor General (CAG) inquiry, instead said it had offered all cooperation warranted under the production sharing contract (PSC) with the government.
"The CAG report says RIL has cooperated. It says others didn’t cooperate. I want to clarify that CAG summoned RIL on the basis of the PSC and we cooperated under the PSC,” senior advocate Harish Salve, who is representing RIL, told the Supreme Court during hearings on two petitions challenging the legality of the PSC with the government. He was responding to allegations by Colin Gonsalves, senior advocate for CPI leader Gurudas Dasgupta, that RIL’s replies to CAG were "ambiguous” and there was "very large scale opposition to the audit from RIL".
At the outset, Gonsalves demanded the court’s intervention to order a CAG audit of books for the Krishna Godavari (KG) D-6 block. Justice BS Chauhan wondered if there was anything in the law to stop him, prompting GonGonsalves to claim that RIL was not cooperating. Salve interrupted him to claim that RIL had cooperated with the CAG under the PSC.
Both Gonsalves and Prashant Bhushan, lawyer for NGO Common Cause, are relying on a CAG report of September 2011, to accuse RIL of underproduction, over invoicing and refusal to relinquish areas already explored. They also want ongoing arbitration proceedings between the government and RIL to be suspended if allegations of collusion between RIL and officials were proved.
"Is it possible that an honest adjudication is possible when two parties are colluding? We have demonstrated various examples of previous and present ministers and officials colluding," he argued. He urged the court to cancel RIL’s contract, take over the fields and auction it to another party. Bhushan on his part invoked the Niira Radia tapes to claim that both the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) and the United Progressive Alliance (UPA) had colluded with RIL to defraud the exchequer.
Bhushan referred to new BJP entrant NK Singh’s conversation with the BJP about replacing Arun Shorie with Venkaiah Naidu during a discussion on the 2009 Finance Bill, which had a clause to give retrospective tax benefits to one company, to support his contention.
RIL has consistently under-produced and over-estimated costs but no one wants to do anything, he argued. He also accused RIL of moneylaundering through a Singaporebased company and showed a letter from the High Commission there to the government, urging a probe into it. RIL had on earlier occasions strongly denied any wrong-doing and has produced documents showing the investment by the Singapore-based company was funded by loans from ICICI Bank.
The bench, comprising among others by Justice Jasti Chelameswar and Justice Kurian Joseph, then asked the government if they had investigated the issue. "This just creates a doubt. There may be wrong doing, but has it been investigated?" Justice Chauhan sought to know. SG Mohan Parasaran promised to file a report. Arguments in the case will continue on Thursday.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>