<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV2-4SP1-JBV1-X0NJ"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>AFPTV Advisory 2200 GMT</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[We will file the following videos:
-- TOP WORLD NEWS --
+ MALAYSIAN PLANE
Coming up:
RESTON, VIRGINIA: Research company Metron Inc. was instrumental in finding the downed Air France Rio flight, using statistical models to narrow down the most likely search areas. They discuss possible search techniques for Malaysia Airlines flight 370. RAW. 1700 GMT
Filed over past 12 hours:
KUALA LUMPUR: Malaysia's government says that in time, it will be judged favourably over its much-questioned handling of the crisis over missing flight MH370. RAW. VID610888_EN
BEIJING: Frustrated relatives of Chinese passengers aboard missing flight MH370 demand answers from the Malaysian ambassador for a second consecutive day. RAW. VID610955_EN
+ US LANDSLIDE
Coming up:
SNOHOMISH COUNTY, WASHINGTON: Monitoring efforts to locate victims of a devastating landslide. TBC
Filed over past 12 hours:
DARRINGTON, WASHINGTON: The death toll is still expected to rise following a landslide in Washington state. RAW
- NASA before and after satellite images. VID611066_EN
- Images of roadblocks. VID610728_EN
- Family members say they're ignoring search and rescue restrictions. VID611029_EN
- Soundbites on rescue efforts. VID610772_EN
+ UKRAINE
Filed over past 12 hours:
SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: Local residents in the Crimean port of Sevastopol have demonstrated against corruption in Crimea. RAW. VID611058 EN
LONDON: Ukrainian presidential contenders Petro Poroshenko and Vitali Klitschko pledge to work together for the future of their crisis-hit country. RAW. VID611091 EN
BRUSSELS: On his first ever visit to the European Union headquarters, US President Barack Obama says that Russia stands "alone" on the Ukraine crisis. RAW. VID610948_EN, VID611078 EN
KIEV: EU Enlargement Commissioner Stefan Fuele says the EU stands united with Ukraine. RAW. VID611025_EN
KIEV: Poland's foreign minister Radoslaw Sikorski visits the Ukrainian capital, says the country had paid a very high price to be closer to European Union. RAW. VID910968_EN
-- OTHER WORLD NEWS --
+ NORTH AMERICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
NEW YORK: Bank of America will pay $9.3 billion to settle US charges that it sold bad mortgage-backed securities to mortgage giants Freddie Mac and Fannie Mae ahead of the housing bust. FILE. VID479744_EN
NEW YORK: Rupert Murdoch announces that his son Lachlan will assume key roles at News Corp. and 21st Century Fox, the two companies that make up his media-entertainment empire. FILE. VID525792_EN / VID610931_EN
NEW YORK: King Digital, the maker of the wildly popular video game Candy Crush, falls below its IPO price in initial trading on the New York Stock Exchange. FILE. VID610951_EN
+ LATIN AMERICA & CARIBBEAN
Coming up:
CARACAS: Venezuelan opposition politician Maria Corina Machado travels home from Peru, daring the govt to arrest her for allegedly inciting protest marches. TBC
Filed over past 12 hours:
SALTA, ARGENTINA: Trial continues of three men accused of murdered two French tourists in 2011. RAW. VID611105_EN
+ EUROPE
Coming up:
PARIS: State dinner in honour of Chinese President Xi Jinping. RAW 2300 GMT
BERLIN: South Korean President Park Geun-Hye meets with German Chancellor Angela Merkel. RAW. 2200 GMT (joint presser)
Filed over past 12 hours:
PARIS: Paris mayoral candidates Anne Hidalgo and Nathalie Kosciusko-Morizet go head-to-head in televised debate. RAW. VID611099 EN
GENEVA: Georgia and Russia hold a new round of peace talks brokered by the international community. RAW. VID611068 EN
PARIS: Ceremony at the Invalides in Paris in honour of Chinese President Xi Jinping. RAW. VID611016_EN
GENEVA: UN monitor warns of a deepening human rights crisis in the Central African Republic. RAW. VID610913_EN
GENEVA: UN rights chief Navi Pillay urges the international community to launch a probe into alleged war crimes in Sri Lanka in 2009 and ongoing violations in the country. RAW. VID610973_EN / FILE. VID337039_EN
BARCELONA, SPAIN: Catalonia's president Artur Mas vows that the region's drive for independence from Spain will continue despite Spanish judges overruling its claims of sovereignty. RAW. VID610944_EN
MARCY L'ETOILE/LYON, FRANCE: Chinese President visits diagnostics firm and Franco-Chinese institute ahead of journey to Paris. RAW. VID610898_EN / VID610862_EN
ISTANBUL: Turks vote in local elections on Sunday, in a poll which could be heavily influenced by recent high-profile corruption scandals. Campaigning is intense for control for Istanbul, which has been governed by the ruling AKP for nearly 20 years but which has seen almost continuous anti-government protests since June. FILE. VID610627_EN / VID610558_EN
ISTANBUL: One of the key issues in Turkey's local elections this Sunday is urbanisation. Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan's Justice and Development party (AKP) has run Istanbul for nearly 20 years, and has undertaken a series of huge transport projects which have divided many in the city. PKG. NSV - VID608702_EN / VOICED - VID608703_EN
BASEL, SWITZERLAND: Media day at Baselworld, the world's biggest watch fair. RAW. VID611045_EN, VID611141 EN
ROME: Italy will on Thursday mark the 30th anniversary of the death of former Communist Party leader Enrico Berlinguer with the release of a new documentary. RAW. VID611008_EN
LONDON: A virtual changing room is now available to fashion-lovers in London that uses body mapping software to superimpose items of clothing onto the customer's body so that they can try different styles, without having to change clothes. RAW. VID610946_EN
+ MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
Coming up:
AMMAN: US Secretary of State John Kerry meets King Abdullah of Jordan and then Palestinian president Mahmud Abbas for talks on the Middle East process. RAW. TBC
Filed over past 12 hours:
AL-BASSIT, SYRIA: Syrian government forces intensify their shelling of positions seized by rebels in the coastal province of Latakia. RAW. VID611104_EN
CAIRO: Egypt army chief Abdel Fattah al-Sisi announces he will run for president. RAW. VID611117_EN. FILE. VID532064_EM
JERUSALEM: Relatives of Israeli victims of Palestinian militant attacks protest against the planned release of 26 veteran Arab prisoners. RAW. VID611024_EN
CAIRO: Deadly clashes erupt between police and student supporters of Egypt's deposed president Mohamed Morsi. RAW. VID611044_EN
AMMAN: US Secretary of State John Kerry arrives in Jordan for meetings on the Middle East peace process. RAW. VID610957_EN
KUWAIT CITY: Annual Arab summit calls for political solution to Syria conflict. RAW. VID610922_EN / VID610826_EN
RAFAH, PALESTINIAN TERRITORIES: Two Palestinians are wounded when Israeli navy vessels destroy two Gaza-bound boats smuggling cigarettes and tobacco from Egypt. RAW. VID610831_EN
BETHLEHEM, PALESTINIAN TERRITORIES: Palestinian activists urge Rolling Stones to cancel concert in Israel. RAW. VID610905_EN
Still available:
OUARGLA, ALGERIA: Algerian presidential candidate Ali Benflis slams the record of Abdelaziz Bouteflika. VID610749_EN
+ AFRICA
Coming up:
CONAKRY: Guinea battles to contain an Ebola epidemic threatening neighbouring countries. RAW. TBA
Filed over past 12 hours:
GENEVA, SWITZERLAND: In a debut report, UN monitor warns of a deepening human rights crisis in the Central African Republic. RAW. VID610913_EN
+ ASIA-PACIFIC
Coming up:
KABUL: A vigil is held in Kabul in memory of Sardar Ahmad, an AFP journalist who was killed with his wife and children during last week's attack on the Serena Hotel in Kabul. RAW. TBA
Filed over past 12 hours:
NEW DELHI: Congress party campaigns ahead of legislative elections that begin on April 7, which the party is slated to lose. RAW. VID610841_EN
NAYPYIDAW: President Thein Sein stresses the importance of a modern and strong military in a speech to mark the anniversary of taking power. RAW. VID610770_EN
-- SPORT --
Filed over past 12 hours:
KUALA LUMPUR: Formula One world champion Sebastian Vettel and swim star Missy Franklin are named Laureus sportsman and woman of the year. RAW. VID610977_EN
MUNICH, GERMANY: Bayern Munich return home triumphant after winning the German Bundesliga title with seven games to spare. RAW. VID611011_EN / FILE. VID605477_EN
PARIS: Official presentation of the 2015 Dakar Rally which, for the 7th year running, will take place in South America. RAW. VID610815_EN
WASHINGTON: The hugely popular March Madness college basketball tournament is underway. The games make millions for the universities which host them, but the players -- while receiving scholarships -- don't make any actual money, prompting some to call for a fairer deal. PKG. NSV - VID610698_EN / VOICED - VID610700_EN
HONG KONG: Teams train ahead of this weekend's Hong Kong 7's, round seven of the World Series. RAW. VID610802_EN
Euro football coverage available to subscribers only:
DORTMUND, GERMANY: Post-match reax after 0-0 derby between Borussia Dortmund and Schalke. RAW. EFT121_EN
-- FEATURES -
Filed:
NOBSIN, BURKINA FASO: Between half a million and 700,000 adolescents and younger children are caught up in the mining sector in Burkina Faso, according to Unicef. Some not even teenagers, they plunge deep into artisanal mines in the deeply poor west African nation, risking their lives for gold. PKG. NSV - VID609352_EN / VOICED - VID609353_EN
MUMBAI: A handful of fed-up residents in one of the world's noisiest cities have taken on a daunting challenge: persuading Indian drivers to stop honking their car horns. PKG. NSV - VID610774_EN / VOICED - VID610775_EN
Contact:
London desk: +44 207 776 2768
Hong Kong desk: +852 2829 6216
Nicosia desk: +357 22 391 453
Washington desk: +1 202 414 0550
Montevideo desk: +598 2 900 5095 ext. 257
For contact via email: afptv-en@afp.com
]]></text></news-item>