<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV2-2651-JCB3-41F5"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Nuclear safety official: WIPP accidents were 'near misses'</title><source>Carlsbad Current-Argus (New Mexico)</source><author>By Zack Ponce zponce@currentargus.com @zackponce12 on Twitter</author><text><![CDATA[CARLSBAD >> The recent truck fire and radiation release from the Waste Isolation Pilot Plant, located 26 miles east of Carlsbad, were "near misses" at a facility whose workers proved unprepared to respond to the emergencies, the head of an independent oversight agency said.
Defense Nuclear Facilities Safety Board Chairman Peter Winokur also said the Feb. 5 underground truck fire at the nuclear waste repository was preventable, and that the initial response to a radiation release that contaminated 17 workers nine days later was unsatisfactory.
"As a result, the internal contamination level of workers, although minor, was nevertheless greater than necessary," Winokur wrote Friday in response to a query from New Mexico Sens. Tom Udall and Martin Heinrich. "The local WIPP Emergency Operations Center was ineffective, and the DOE (Department of Energy) emergency center at headquarters in Washington, D.C., was never notified, as would have been appropriate."
Udall and Heinrich requested the assessment from Winokur, who is head of the independent federal agency charged with overseeing public health and safety issues at Department of Energy defense-related nuclear facilities.
Nuclear Waste Partnership, a government contractor that oversees operations at WIPP, hired Bob McQuinn two weeks to replace Farok Sharif as the president and project manager of the organization just two days before the Department of Energy Accident Investigation Board released a 187-page report that placed a majority of the blame for the fire on NWP.
The buildup and mixing of either hydraulic fuel or diesel fuel with the salt hauler truck's catalytic converter were to blame for the fire that ravaged the 29-year-old vehicle referred to as 74U006B, according to the DOE. The board also found "significant buildup" of engine and hydraulic oil on other mining equipment underground, including on an identical vehicle known as 74U006A which was found with a large puddle of hydraulic fluid underneath the carriage that was not reported on daily maintenance checklists.
The DOE investigation board also said that NWP was not following many of the recommended maintenance procedures suggested by the vehicle service manual, including routine checks of the air intake vacuum, exhaust brake pressure, front and rear suspension bolt torques and changing the wheel end oil and differential oil every 1,000 hours.
NWP was also found to be performing many suggested 125-hour maintenance checks and repairs after 500 hours, including the washing of the vehicles which the board states was done solely with compressed air and not water. The salt hauling truck that caught on fire was also found to be operating on standard oil instead of a fire resistant fluid in the hydraulic oil system according to its design.
WIPP removed its vehicle prewash station around 2004 and that action likely contributed to the poor maintenance of the equipment, according to DOE Accident Investigation Chairman Ted Wyka.
"We need to sort of figure something out because we require that vehicles be washed every 100 hours so it's difficult to get rid of the washers," he said during a town hall meeting held at the Carlsbad City Council Chambers on March 13.
Winokur said his agency has sent four letters to the DOE since 2010 raising concerns about flaws in WIPP's fire-prevention program and that the culture must change at the nuclear waste disposal facility.
"Significant improvements in the safety strategy for the dump are warranted to address design basis accidents that lead to radiation releases," Winokur said, acknowledging that a cause for the escape of plutonium and americium must still be determined.
The DOE has targeted the coming weekend for manned entry into the underground at WIPP, although an official date and time has yet to be announced.
Jeri Clausing of the Associated Press contributed to this report.
Reporter Zack Ponce can be reached at (575) 689-7402.
]]></text></news-item>