<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV2-7XX1-JCDS-Y4K7"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>South Africa's public administration bill aims to curb graft</title><source>Country Report Select</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[South Africa's Public Administration Management Bill appears well-intentioned. It contains several measures intended to improve public-sector performance and clamp down on corruption. However, concerns have been raised about the prospect of central government interference in the provincial and municipal arenas, and about the watering down of a key anti-corruption provision contained in the original June 2013 draft. Instead of establishing a new anti-corruption bureau within the Department of Public Service and Administration, the final bill has downgraded this to a technical assistance unit. The rise in corruption, attested to by several sources, is a serious impediment to socioeconomic development and business activity.
Among the positive aspects of the bill-which was adopted by the National Assembly on March 12th (a day before its pre-election recess)-and is now awaiting assent from the president, Jacob Zuma-is a bar on public servants (who number about 1.6m in total) conducting business with the state, although this will be difficult to police. The bill also requires officials to disclose their financial and business interests (and those of close family members) and strengthens the disciplinary process in cases of wrongdoing. The legislation seeks to streamline standards and norms across all three levels of government (national, provincial and municipal) and allows for the secondment of personnel between the different levels. This will, in theory, allow local-level skills gaps to be plugged, but has raised concerns in local government, and in Western Cape province (which is controlled by an opposition party, Democratic Alliance), about being forced to comply with secondment orders. Such action could amount to unwarranted interference and may give rise to a Constitutional Court challenge. In addition, the bill provides for an Office of Standards and Compliance (to oversee the process) and a National School of Government (to promote skills development). According to the bill's sponsor, the public services minister, Lindiwe Sisulu, the legislation is geared to building a capable state, in line with the requirement of the National Development Plan. However, critics, such as the Democratic Alliance (the official opposition), believe that the bill has been rushed through and that the refusal of the ruling African National Congress (ANC) to allow a final debate contravened parliamentary procedures.
The bill's potential effectiveness in tackling corruption will be diminished by the dropping of plans for an anti-corruption bureau (which was to be modelled on Tanzania's version) in favour of an Ethics, Integrity and Discipline Technical Assistance Unit. Compared with the bureau, the unit will less authority to investigate wrongdoing and launch disciplinary action and will therefore be less successful in tackling graft, according to Corruption Watch, a non-governmental organisation. Another valuable provision in the original draft-that would have required state employees to a have a 12 months "cooling off" period before taking employment in private firms to which they had awarded contracts-has also been dropped in the final version. The negative changes from the original draft no doubt reflect lobbying by vested interests and heighten fears that, despite the rhetoric, the government is not truly committed to fighting graft.
Corruption appears to be on the increase, based on evidence from several sources, including South Africa's Public Protector, Thuli Madonsela, who has written a series of highly critical reports including, most recently, on taxpayer-funded improvements to Mr Zuma's private residence in Nkandla. Other recent targets include the agriculture minister, Tina Joemat-Pettersson, in January, because of irregular tendering, and the head of the Independent Electoral Commission, Pansy Tlakula, in August 2013, because of a questionable property lease. Mrs Madonsela's annual report for the 2012/13 financial year (delivered last August) noted that the number of complaints about corruption had risen by about 23% from the previous year to 33,777. The Corruption Perceptions Index produced by Transparency International, a non-governmental organisation, also shows a steady deterioration in South Africa's relative standing. The country's global ranking fell from 54th in 2010 to 64th in 2011, 69th in 2012 and 72nd in the latest 2013 index, which also showed South Africa falling to joint ninth place in Sub-Saharan Africa (alongside São Tomé and Príncipe), behind Botswana, Cape Verde, Seychelles, Rwanda, Mauritius, Lesotho, Namibia and Ghana.
South Africa has a number of anti-corruption agencies, including the Special Investigating Unit (an autonomous public entity), the "Hawks", formally known as the Directorate of Priority Crime Investigation (which is part of the police force) and the aforementioned Public Protector. However, despite the various initiatives, the problem appears to be getting worse, partly because of a lack of capacity and a shortage of skills. Moreover, although weaknesses at a local level are widely acknowledged, the central government's record is little better (and may be worse) as highlighted by the Nkandla scandal and the appearance in the ANC's electoral lists of several candidates linked to corruption. The public administration and management bill is broadly positive but, especially after the withdrawal of key clauses, is unlikely to make a significant impact on the scourge of corruption.
Retrieve Image
]]></text></news-item>