<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV2-3RH1-JB4F-Y18G"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Abercrombie &amp; Fitch Class A keeps sliding: down 4.9% in 3 days</title><source>News Bites US Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Abercrombie & Fitch Co. (NYSE:ANF), NYSE's 29th largest retailing company by market capitalisation, extended its slide Wednesday, shedding an additional 55.70c (or 1.4%) to close at US$38.13. The shares have sunk US$1.98 (or 4.9%) over the past three trading days. Compared with the S&P 500 Index which fell 13.8 points (or 0.74%) in the three days, this represented a relative price change of -4.2%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Abercrombie & Fitch Class A, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/0010519610003148
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- The stock dropped to a one-month low.- Open interest hit a two-month low.
- In the NYSE Short Selling market of 2967 stocks, short selling as a % of issued shares ranked 96th and within the top quartile of stocks. This means it was higher than market average of 0.4%, a bearish indicator. - The current short volume is 1.6 times its own historical average of 1.1%. It lifted 2.2% from the previous day, a bearish indicator.Top three traded Abercrombie & Fitch Class A put options [volume of contracts in brackets; 1 contract is 100 shares]Exercise 37; Expires 19 Apr, 2014: 0.72 up 53.2% [213]Exercise 36; Expires 19 Apr, 2014: 0.44 up 18.9% [144]Exercise 39; Expires 19 Apr, 2014: 1.27 up 7.6% [138]- The price decreased 0.3% in the last month. The stock has been exacerbated by firm volume of 1.2 times average for the month. - The present value of US$1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in Abercrombie & Fitch Class A is US$842, including a capital loss of US$170 and dividend reinvested of US$13.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Return on Equity 13.0% [17.1%].Other Bearish Signals:- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity of 13.0% is lower than sector average of 17.1%. This is computed as net profit margin of 5.3% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 1.5 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 1.6.- Net Profit margin has shown signs of deterioration in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]

Bullish SignalsOversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The Relative Strength Index (RSI) of 22.9 has breached the oversold line of 30, suggesting the price decrease of 7.5% in the last 14 days is unusually high. - The stock is oversold according to the Williams % R indicator of -90.2, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day low of US$37.71. - Open interest tumbled -8.3% from 236162 a week ago while the stock dropped -3.2% from US$39.38 a week ago, suggesting a strong weekly trend.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Earnings of 13.3 [23.4]. - Price to Book of 1.7 [6.9]. - Year-on-Year Earnings Growth of 77% [12.4%].- Return on Assets 7.9% [6.2%].Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 1.8 is comfortably below 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 20.4%. - Interest cover defined by EBIT/I is 51.3 times. This indicates it is less leveraged. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 1.1. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- Over the last 3 years average annual compound growth rate of earnings per share was 19.5%. This is considered moderate.- Net Profit margin, EBIT margin and EBITDA margin are positive and have seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 1,360,000 shares worth US$51.9 million traded. Trading volume was 32% lighter than average. Beta: the Beta of Abercrombie & Fitch Class A stock is 1.9. A Beta greater than 1 suggests this is a high risk, high return stock with volatility greater than that of the market. - Abercrombie & Fitch Class A is at a discount of 31.0% to its 12-month high of US$55.23 on 22 May, 2013. It is also at a premium of 22.4% to the 12-month low of US$31.14 on 18 Dec, 2013.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Parity:- Price/Sales of 0.7 [0.7]. - Return on Capital Employed 16.3% [17.8%].- Dividend yield of 1.6% [1.5%].
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 20: Abercrombie & Fitch Class A insider sells; shares at a seven-day highAbercrombie & Fitch Class A (NYSE:ANF) insider Jonathan E. Ramsden sold 2,775 shares worth approximately US$109,280 on March 18, 2014. The selling price was USD39.38. The shares hit a seven-day high on the day.
March 19: Abercrombie & Fitch Class A insider buys; shares at a seven-day highAbercrombie & Fitch Class A (NYSE:ANF) insider Perrin Charles R bought 10,000 shares worth approximately US$395,000 on March 18, 2014. The purchase price was USD39.5. The shares hit a seven-day high on the day.
March 06: Abercrombie & Fitch To Pay Assistant Manager Thousands of Dollars In Improperly Withheld Overtime Wages[News Story] RYE BROOK, N.Y., March 6, 2014 -- Klafter Olsen & Lesser LLP; Kellogg, Huber, Hansen, Todd, Evans, & Figel, P.L.L.C.; and Berger Attorney, P.C. announce that Abercrombie & Fitch Co. and Abercrombie & Fitch Stores, Inc. (NYSE:ANF), have offered to pay $4,075.96 to one Assistant Manager for failing to pay proper overtime wages from May 16, 2010 to present, in connection with a lawsuit filed in the Eastern District of New York, Hepler, et al.
March 06: Klafter Olsen & Lesser: Abercrombie & Fitch To Pay Assistant Manager Thousands of Dollars In Improperly Withheld Overtime Wages[News Story] RYE BROOK, N.Y., March 6, 2014 -- Klafter Olsen & Lesser LLP; Kellogg, Huber, Hansen, Todd, Evans, & Figel, P.L.L.C.; and Berger Attorney, P.C. announce that Abercrombie & Fitch Co. and Abercrombie & Fitch Stores, Inc. (NYSE:ANF), have offered to pay $4,075.96 to one Assistant Manager for failing to pay proper overtime wages from May 16, 2010 to present, in connection with a lawsuit filed in the Eastern District of New York, Hepler, et al.
March 04: Abercrombie & Fitch Class A insider sellsAbercrombie & Fitch Class A (NYSE:ANF) insider Michael S. Jeffries sold 50,000 shares worth approximately US$1,975,000 on February 28, 2014. The selling price was USD39.5.
February 28: Abercrombie & Fitch To Present At The Bank Of America Merrill Lynch 2014 Consumer & Retail ConferenceNew Albany, Ohio, February 28, 2014: Abercrombie & Fitch Co. (NYSE:ANF) today announced that Jonathan Ramsden, EVP, Chief Operating Officer & Chief Financial Officer will present at the Bank of America Merrill Lynch 2013 Consumer & Retail Conference on Tuesday, March 11, 2014 at 9:40 AM, Eastern Time.The audio portion of the presentation and the accompanying slides will be available to the general public on the "Investors" section of the Company's website at www.abercrombie.com at approximately 9:40 AM, Eastern Time on Tuesday, March 11, 2014.Source: Nasdaq Stock Exchange
February 26: Abercrombie & Fitch Promotes Jim Bierbower to Executive Vice President, Human Resources[News Story] New Albany, Ohio, February 26, 2014: Abercrombie & Fitch Co. (NYSE:ANF) (the "Company") today announced the promotion of James N. Bierbower to Executive Vice President - Human Resources, effective immediately.Mr. Bierbower, 49, joined Abercrombie & Fitch in 2006 as Vice President - Organizational Development.
ISIN: US0028962076
N:ANF
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>