<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV2-3B61-DY2M-W322"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Bank of America to Pay $6.3 Billion to Settle Mortgage Securities Suit</title><source>The New York Times Blogs(DealBook)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Bank of America is paying $6.3 billion to settle a lawsuit arising out of troubled mortgage-backed securities it cobbled together and sold to Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac in the run-up to the financial crisis.
The bank agreed to pay that sum to settle a lawsuit filed on behalf of the two government-sponsored mortgage finance firms by their regulator, the Federal Housing Finance Agency. As part of the settlement, Bank of America will also repurchase mortgage securities from Fannie and Freddie that are valued at about $3.2 billion.
The settlement covers so-called private label mortgage backed securities sold by Bank of America and its affiliated entities like Countrywide Financial and Merrill Lynch. The settlement with the housing finance agency is the latest in a string of deals that regulators have reached with big banks that sold mortgage securities backed by subprime mortgages, which quickly soured during the financial crisis and housing bust.
The settlement came on the same day as Bank of America and its former chief executive officer, Kenneth Lewis, reached a deal to resolve another lawsuit arising from the financial crisis.
Mr. Lewis, who stepped down in 2009, agreed on Wednesday to pay a $10 million penalty to settle a civil lawsuit arising out of the bank's acquisition of Merrill Lynch at the height of the financial crisis.
Officers of companies often have insurance policies to cover their actions if they lead to litigation.
The settlement between Mr. Lewis and New York's attorney general, Eric Schneiderman, also bars the former bank executive from serving as an officer or a director of a public company for three years. Mr. Lewis, a Wall Street deal maker who also oversaw Bank of America's acquisition of the troubled mortgage lender Countrywide Financial, has kept a low profile since stepping down as chief executive at the end of 2009.
Bank of America also reached a settlement with Mr. Schneiderman's office in which the bank will pay $15 million. The bank also agreed to institute a number of corporate governance changes, including the creation of a corporate development committee to monitor acquisition activities for the next five years.
The lawsuit, filed by Gov. Andrew Cuomo of New York when he was still the state's attorney general, charged that Mr. Lewis and other bank executives misled Bank of America shareholders about the financial problems facing Merrill Lynch when the acquisition was announced in September 2008. The lawsuit said shareholders were not told that Merrill Lynch was facing up to $9 billion in losses, most of it tied to write-downs on the value of collateralized debt obligations backed by troubled mortgage securities.
The deal to acquire Merrill Lynch was announced on Sept. 14, 2008, the same day that Lehman Brothers filed for bankruptcy and panic began to ensue across Wall Street.
The settlement with Mr. Schneiderman's office was first reported by Reuters.
The ill-timed deal has led to much litigation and pain for Bank of America. Last year, Bank of America agreed to pay $2.4 billion to settle a securities class-action lawsuit over the merger brought on behalf of the bank's shareholders. In 2010, the bank reached a $150 million settlement with the Securities and Exchange Commission to settle similar allegations that it had misled shareholders about the Merrill Lynch transaction.
"Today's settlement demonstrates a major victory in our continued commitment to applying the law equally to individual as well as corporations," Mr. Schneiderman said in a prepared statement. "I would hope this closes on chapter of our ongoing efforts to ensure the frauds that occurred in and around the financial crisis are not forgotten."
Mr. Schneiderman's office said it had not reached a settlement with Joe L. Price, the bank's former chief financial officer, and intended to file a motion for summary judgment against him.
Banks Seek to Overturn Judge's Ruling in Critical Mortgage CaseU.S. Accuses Bank of America of a 'Brazen' Mortgage Fraud
]]></text></news-item>