<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV2-B0S1-DXJR-H0K9"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Suspended mines department draftsman held in mining case</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[PANAJI: Robert Gonsalves, the alleged mastermind in the Hussain Khan murder case, and a suspended draftsman at the directorate of mines and geology, was arrested by the special investigative team (SIT) in an illegal mining case, on Wednesday.
The is the second arrest by the SIT in the Frost International Ltd case. The company was allegedly involved in exporting iron ore with forged documents.
The accused has been arrested for his alleged involvement in hatching a conspiracy and issuing fake documents to Frost International Ltd for exporting iron ore from the state. The accused was produced before the special court and he has been remanded to three days police custody.
Gonsalves was arrested at Sada sub jail, Vasco. Gonsalves is in custody since March 21, 2013, for murdering his business partner Khan. Gonsalves is a suspended mines department official. He was suspended after the Shah Commission report on illegal mining was tabled in Parliament.
Gonsalves had allegedly hired the ‘supari’ killers to murder Khan after the dissolution of a business partnership with the victim and his inability to repay 1.30 crore taken from customers promising them flats in return at Canca, Mapusa.
Last week, the SIT had made two arrests in a mining case. First, the SIT arrested Frost International Ltd’s operation manager Subroto Barik, 39, of West Bengal. Barik was arrested at a hotel in Gandhidham in Gujarat, where he was staying for the last 18 months.
The SIT had also arrested Prashant Sahu, a director of Magnum Pvt Ltd, for alleged impersonation of the revenue secretary.
The directorate of mines and geology (DMG) had lodged a complaint with the crime branch of Goa police alleging that officials and directors of Frost International had exported 1,35,000 metric tonnes of ore to China using forged documents resulting in a loss of revenue to the state exchequer to the tune of 1.17 crore.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>