<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV2-0CC1-DY2D-K0P7"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Spill Could Have Been Worse</title><source>THE DALLAS MORNING NEWS</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[For a calamitous incident, the collision Saturday at the entrance to the Houston Ship Channel between a cargo freighter and a barge carrying 924,000 gallons of bunker fuel oil, could have been much worse.
Yes, about 170,000 gallons of oil spilled into Galveston Bay and Gulf of Mexico waters, 10 birds were killed and 50 more needed treatment. The impact on fish is yet to be determined. But compare that with the environmental devastation caused by the 11 million gallons of oil from the Exxon Valdez, which ran aground on a reef in Prince William Sound 25 years ago Monday: 250,000 seabirds lost, 2,800 sea otters, 300 harbor seals, 250 bald eagles and 22 killer whales.
The oil industry and the agencies charged with its oversight learned from the Exxon Valdez. Stricter standards, better emergency procedures and the growth of the environmental cleanup industry grew from that spill. This is how the free market is supposed to work. Here in Texas, the Exxon Valdez spill also helped prompt the creation of the General Land Office's Oil Spill Prevention and Response Division. Funded by a tax on crude oil loaded or offloaded in Texas ports, the division plans for such accidents, including pre-positioning equipment along the coast.
In the Houston Ship Channel spill, work began almost immediately, with the U.S. Coast Guard offloading most of the remaining oil out of the barge. Four skimmers were quickly deployed, along with miles of containment booms. By Monday, more than 380 people and 27 boats were involved in the cleanup. By 10 a.m. Tuesday - less than three days after the spill, sooner than it took for cleanup to even begin after the Exxon Valdez spill - the channel was at least partially open for business again.
And we should all be thankful for that. The Port of Houston is one of the world's busiest; its economic impact in 2012 alone was estimated at $178.5 billion. Eight refineries, producing nearly 12 percent of U.S. refining capacity, use the ship channel. If the 53-mile waterway had been shut for an extended period, it could have caused gas prices to rise.
The successful response can be attributed to a number of factors:
The spill's location - an area familiar with petrochemicals and disasters, with significant resources nearby.
The Coast Guard's immediate all-hands-on-deck response.
A fast and full acceptance of responsibility - and a dogged focus on cleanup rather than blame - by Kirby Inland Marine, owners of the barge and the boat that was towing it.
That cooperation and acceptance of responsibility will be needed as the investigation into what happened truly begins. State and federal agencies need to determine the cause as soon and as thoroughly as possible. And those found responsible need to pay, not just for cleanup but also for restoration of our water, shoreline and natural resources.
]]></text></news-item>