<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV4-GPV1-DY15-S322"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>ANHRI Gets an Acquittal for a Number of Elbadil Online Newspaper Journalists [press release]</title><source>Arabic Network for Human Rights Information</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Basateen Misdemeanor Court, during its session on March 25, issued a ruling over the lawsuit No. 23368/2013 (Basateen misdemeanor). The court acquitted Assem Abdel-Moati Seliman- former deputy at Central Auditing Organization (CAO) and head of Egyptian Center for Transparency and Anti-Corruption (E.C.TAC)- and two journalists: Mohamed Al-Ashwal- ElBadil newspaper journalist- and Mohamed Zeyad- editor-in-chief of ElBadil newspaper and its news portal, in addition to Mohamed Ali Rezk- ElBadil executive editor- Mohamed Al-Saban, ElBadil newspaper and website chairman of the board, together with Mahmoud Lotfy Al-Sakka- a clerk at Commercial International Bank (CIB)- of the lawsuit filed by a clerk at CIB; charging all the aforementioned with defamation.
The clerk has brought a lawsuit, in which they all were accused of defamation against the backdrop of an article written by Mohamed Al-Ashwal and published on ElBadil website. The complainant alleged that the article contained defamation of officials and clerks in CIB; accusing them of aggression on public funds and covering up indecent and immoral acts inside the bank.
The case's proceedings date back to 19 September, 2013, when the complainant directly filed a lawsuit against ElBadil online newspaper journalists with others; charging them with defamation in light of an article entitled " a warning to the central bank governor" that was published on 20 June, 2013, on ElBadil news portal, which holds the slogan "the voice of the vulnerable".
Noteworthy, a number of clerks at the bank have filed lawsuits included the same accusations against the defendants. The Arabic Network for Human Rights Information was managed to get three acquittals, while the fourth case was set for adjudication. Furthermore, a number of lawsuits in many other governorates were filed against the same defendants over the selfsame accusations. Three clerks at the bank in Mansoura governorate filed three direct lawsuits, while other three clerks at Port Said branch filed other three lawsuits. Additionally, two clerks in Luxor branch filed two lawsuits, whilst one lawsuit was filed in Alexandria against the defendants. On top of that, the bank's chairman himself has filed a lawsuit against the defendants. ANHRI has got a lack of jurisdiction verdict from Dokki Court, which referred the case to Kasr Al-Nile Court.
ANHRI's lawyers elaborated that four clerks at the bank's branch in Giza, among those who filed lawsuits against the defendants, alleged that they are the chairmen of the board of CIB bank; the matter that proved the falseness of filing the lawsuit by the bank's chairman of the board himself.
The lawyers, in their defence, referred to the inadmissibility of the proceedings, as they were filed by irrelevant plaintiffs, as well as the defendants have no relation to the facts, in addition to the absence of any phrases that insult the bank and its officials.
]]></text></news-item>