<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV4-T981-J9YR-G2XF"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Death toll in Washington mudslide 'rises to 24' with dozens still missing: Hope fades that any survivors will be found as rescuers recover two more bodies and believe they have located eight others 'underground'</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>JAMES NYE and LOUISE BOYLE IN DARRINGTON, WASHINGTON</author><text><![CDATA[Landslide tore through Snohomish County 55 miles north of Seattle, Washington state, on Saturday at 11amThe likely death toll from a devastating weekend landslide in Washington state rose to 24 on TuesdayNumber of missing still stands at 176 people - although rescuers do not expect that to be the final figureAround 200 crews searching for survivors; teams using search dogs, sonar devices, hover craft, and air supportRecover efforts have been hampered by mud and debris that is up to 15-feet deep in some placesPresident Obama spoke from his tour of Europe and asked the nation to pray for the communitySeveral people critically injured, around 50 homes destroyed, debris blocked one-mile stretch of State Route 530Geologists Daniel Miller and Lynne Rodgers Miller reveal they warned of 'potential for catastrophe' in 1999 reportBut Snohomish County Department of Emergency Management told press conference: 'it was considered very safe'Further rain over next few days expected to hamper rescue effortsList of the missing is expected to be published on Wednesday morning
The death toll from Saturday's devastating landslide in Washington is expected to rise to 24 after increasingly desperate rescuers slogging through debris recovered two bodies and believed they had located eight more, the local fire chief said on Tuesday.
The official death toll rose to 16 with the discovery of the additional victims as crews searched under drizzly skies for survivors amid fading hopes that anyone could still be plucked alive from the massive pile of mud-soaked rumble.
'Unfortunately we did not find any signs of life today, we didn't locate anybody alive, so that's the disappointing part,' local fire chief Travis Hots told a media briefing.
'It's unimaginable, the conditions out there they're dealing with,' Hots said.
SCROLL DOWN FOR VIDEO
The grim discoveries came three days after the collapse of a rain-soaked hillside about 55 miles north of Seattle.
Searchers had warned they were likely to find more bodies in the debris field, which covered a neighborhood of 49 structures. Authorities believe at least 25 were full-time residences.
Authorities believe that the mudslide destroyed 35 homes, as well as 13 manufactured homes, including RVs, and at least one cabin.
As many as 176 people remained listed as missing three days after the slide on Saturday, tumbling over a river, across a state road and into a rural residential area where it swallowed dozens of homes near the town of Oso.
Officials said they were hoping that number would decline as some of those listed as missing may have been double-counted or were slow to alert family and officials of their whereabouts. Eight people were injured.
But the disaster already ranks as one of the deadliest landslides in recent U.S. history. In 2005, 10 people died when a hillside gave way and engulfed homes in La Conchita, California.
'We're all still hoping for that miracle but we are preparing for the other possibility,' Washington State Patrol spokesman Bob Calkins said Tuesday afternoon.
And as the rain still fell on Tuesday night, about 200 people gathered in the cold at a park in Arlington to pray for the victims, friends and family of those lost.
'Hug each other. Wipe away each other's tears,' said Pastor Chad Blood with the Lifeway Foursquare Church in Arlington.
'People are just responding,' he said. 'When a need arises they just come and take care of it until we have to turn them away. I'm speechless at times, and so very proud of out community.'
Though authorities have said the chances were low of finding any more survivors in the cement-like mud blanketing the landscape, Hots said some 50 more searchers had been brought in to sift through the disaster zone in hopes of a miracle.
'This makes up over 200 responders that are here on site working very hard to locate victims and hopefully find somebody that is still alive. That is still our number-one priority out there,' he said.
WHY IS THE NUMBER OF MISSING CHANGING SO MUCH?
Officials are compiling the list from calls from worried family members, friends and locals. Snohomish County Emergency Management Director John Pennington said the number of potential missing likely includes duplicate names as people phone in reports about the same person. Authorities are working through the list, being extra cautious before they make conclusions.
'What we're finding is these vehicles are twisted and torn up in pieces.'
'It's amazing the force and magnitude what this slide has done.'
Another obstacle has been the chaotic nature of the debris field itself. In some places, the ground is covered by 15 feet of rubble.
'It's muddy in areas, it's like quicksand,' said Hots. 'One of the folks out there told me, "Chief, sometimes it takes five minutes to walk 40 or 50 feet".'
Searchers are also running into gasoline and septic discharge and dealing with ground that geologists warn remains unstable.
At one site in a square-mile zone of devastation that once contained a meandering river surrounded by rural homes, the landslide pushed a house onto the highway, leaving nothing intact but its cedar shake roof.
Operators of excavators with clawed buckets dug through the debris, and chaplains stood by to comfort searchers and families of the missing. Hots said dogs also were being used to identify potential buried bodies, which were dug out in some cases with bulldozers or other heavy equipment.
President Barack Obama, who was in Europe for a meeting with world leaders, signed an emergency declaration ordering U.S. government assistance to supplement state and local relief efforts, the White House said.
Speaking at The Hague, where he was attending a summit, Obama began a news conference on Tuesday by addressing the disaster in Washington state and asking Americans to 'send their thoughts and prayers' to those affected by the disaster.
'We hope for the best, but we recognize this is a tough situation,' he said.
The president also called Washington Governor Jay Inslee on Tuesday to discuss the mudslide, according to Inslee's office.
Compounding the sense of urgency was a fear of flooding as water levels rose behind a crude dam of mud and rubble that was dumped into the North Fork of the Stillaguamish River by the slide.
DON'T AUTHORITIES KNOW HOW MANY PEOPLE LIVED IN THE COMMUNITY?
The information-gathering process has been complicated by the nature of the rural area 55 miles north of Seattle where the slide hit Saturday morning. Pennington said officials have determined it included 49 parcels containing some kind of structure - including manufactured homes, a cabin and vacation properties. Not every structure was occupied full time. Some were only used sporadically. Complicating matters further is the fact that it's believed some nonresidents were working in the area and some victims may have been driving through the state highway that was also covered by mud.
The river was rising with rain on Tuesday, but had cut a channel through fresh mud and debris, lessening the chance of flooding, officials said.
A volunteer was injured Tuesday when he was struck by debris blown by a helicopter's rotor. The man was transported to a hospital for evaluation, but the injuries appear minor, Snohomish County sheriff's spokeswoman Shari Ireton said in a statement.
Near the southern perimeter of the slide, volunteers from a logging crew gathered to help move debris with chain saws, excavators and other heavy equipment.
Gene Karger said he could see six orange flags in the debris field, marking bodies they would be pulling out. Karger, a logger most of his life, said it was the first time he was involved in this kind of rescue work.
'You see parts of their bodies sticking out of the mud. It's real hard. It's that bad,' Karger said. 'There are people out there we know.'
Hots said about 200 responders using everything from heavy equipment and search dogs to their bare hands were working through the debris field Tuesday in rainy, wet conditions.
'We didn't locate anybody alive,' he said. 'We haven't lost hope that there's a possibility that we can find somebody alive in some pocket area.'
More than one mile of rain-soaked hillside collapsed onto the remote town, which is just five square miles in size, at 11am on Saturday.
Three days on, hundreds of rescue workers with dogs, aircraft and sonar equipment remain scouring the wreckage for survivors in the slide which has swamped a fifth of Oso's land.
But amidst the devastation, experts have revealed they predicted this would happen in 1999.
In a report filed with the US Army Corps of Engineers, geologists warned of 'the potential for a large catastrophic failure' 15 years ago.
'We've known it would happen at some point, we just didn't know when,' co-author Daniel Miller told The Seattle Times.
Geological reports warning the hill is in imminent danger of collapse date back to the 1950s.
WHY IS IT TAKING CREWS SO LONG TO FIND MORE PEOPLE?
The debris field is a huge, dangerous mess - 15 feet thick in some places. 'It's muddy, in areas it's like quicksand,' said Snohomish County Fire District 21 Chief Travis Hots. "One of the folks out there told me, 'Chief, sometimes it takes five minutes to walk 40 or 50 feet.' Searchers are also running into gasoline and septic discharge and dealing with ground that geologists warn remains unstable.
But the alerts, issued by experts every ten years, went unnoticed.
And in a press conference following Saturday's slide, the head of Snohomish County's Department of Emergency Management, John Pennington, said 'it was considered very safe'.
Mr Miller said he was shocked to see houses being built around the danger zone weeks after a slide in 2006.
The slide, which was thought to be caused by heavy rain, formed a new channel along the cliff-side, but carpenters immediately set to work erecting homes along it.
'Frankly I was shocked that the county permitted any building from across the river,' Mr Miller told the paper.
In fact, the area has long been known as the 'Hazel Landslide' because of landslides over the past half-century. The last major one before Saturday's disaster was in 2006.
'We've done everything we could to protect them,' Pennington said.
Patricia Graesser, a spokeswoman for the Army Corps of Engineers in Seattle, said it appears the report was intended not as a risk assessment, but as a feasibility study for ecosystem restoration.
Asked whether the agency should have done anything with the information, she said, 'We don't have jurisdiction to do anything. We don't do zoning. That's a local responsibility.'
No landslide warnings for the area were issued immediately before the disaster, which came after weeks of heavy rain.
Tragic stories of those who have reported lost loved ones and are waiting on any news:
Keenan Parks and his wife Chery, who live in Darrington, told MailOnline that they drive that road daily and had passed that way just the night before.
Their son darin and his wife Martha live on the edge of the devastating slide but survived.
The couple work as firefighters and the Park's said that tears poured down the couples faces as they described finding bodies in the rescue operation, some with clothes blown off from the force of the slide.
Their son described being up to his waist in mud during the recovery effort.
Still exhausted from their ordeal were on their way to check on an elderly man they are acquainted with but had not seen since Friday.
They said that they know the man, called Kurt, lived in the area of the slide but were not sure if he was home at the time.
Missing: 13-year-old Jovon Mangual,(holding his sister Brooke) stands alongside his Kaylee Spillers and brother Jacob (in blue t-shirt) who managed to escape their Oso, Washington home on Saturday and was returned to his mother Jonielle Spillers (right) Missing: 13-year-old Jovon Mangual,(holding his sister Brooke) stands alongside his Kaylee Spillers and brother Jacob (in blue t-shirt) who managed to escape their Oso, Washington home on Saturday and was returned to his mother Jonielle Spillers (right) Father and his children: Jovon Mangual (left in blue and right in blue), Kaylee (as a tiger and right in pink) Brooke (pumpkin) and Jacob as a bumblebee pose for a picture on Halloween - and right with Billy Spillers - who is also missing Father and his children: Jovon Mangual (left in blue and right in blue), Kaylee (as a tiger and right in pink) Brooke (pumpkin) and Jacob as a bumblebee pose for a picture on Halloween - and right with Billy Spillers - who is also missing
Mr Park said that he believes the man has sons but that they don't live in the area. They also were concerned for the cattle that he raised on his land.
Cory Kuntz and several volunteers worked Monday with chain saws to cut through the roof of his uncle's house, which was swept about 150 yards from its previous location. Kuntz said his aunt, Linda McPherson, was killed. He and the others pulled out files, his aunt's wallet and a box filled with pictures and slides.
McPherson was branch manager of the Darrington library and served for about 15 years on the local school board.
Indeed, Linda McPherson and her husband, Gary 'Mac' McPherson were sitting down to read the newspaper on Saturday morning at home when the landslide hit.
They were separated only by a living room table when trees tore through their house and simply ripped Linda and the side of the house she was sitting in 150 feet southwards away from Gary.
Gary, 81, awoke covered in mud and began to dig himself out until he was rescued by passers-by.
It was then that they discovered the body of his wife just nearby.
'When you look at it, you just kind of go in shock, and you kind of go numb,' he said, adding that there were more people out helping Sunday. On Monday, they couldn't get through roadblocks.
'They are all eager to get down here, but unfortunately they can't. It just shows how tight this community is,' he said.
Jonielle Spillers, a nursing assistant fears that she may have lost three of her four children and her husband - while her youngest boy managed to barely escape the slide.
Her son Jovon Mangual, his half-sisters Kaylee Spillers, 5, Brooke Spillers, 2 and Jonielle's husband Billy Spillers are all missing.
According to Jovon's father, Jose Mangual, a staff sergeant in the US Army, the Spillers moved from Seattle to Oso two years ago.
He said that he had spoken to Jovon's 4-year-old half-brother Jacob Spillers who described the terrifying scene when the landslide struck.
According to Jacob, Billy Spillers - a chief petty officer in the Navy - was watching television with the three missing children when the land gave way.
Jacob said that he was on the second floor of the house and manged somehow to get away.
On her Facebook profile, Jonielle thanked everyone for their support and said she was 'not giving up and I know they will find my babies and husband....please pray for us.'
Other family members of the missing such as Pete Bellomo, of Bellevue spent the day trying to find out any information on his daughter Shelley and her partner Jerry Logan.
He did not hold out hope they would be found alive.
TOLL OF THE MUDSLIDE: NAMES OF THOSE FEARED DEAD:
The names below are of those whose families have reported them unaccounted for to the media - The official list has still to be released:
Navy Commander John Regelbrugge 49, and wife Kris, 44Mark GustafsonAmanda LennickSummer RaffoLarry and Sandy MillerAlan Bejvl and his fiancee Delaney WebbThomas and Marcy SatterleeSteven HadawaySteve NealBrandy WardTom DurnellBonnie GulliksonWilliam 'Bill' WelshDenver HarrisShane, Katie, Hunter and Wyatt RuthvenSanoah HuestisChristina JefferdsAdam FarnesJulie FarnesGloria HalsteadJerry HalsteadSteve HarrisTheresa HarrisLon SlausonRonald deQuilettesNavy Chief Billy Spillers, Brooke Spillers (2), Kaylee Spillers (5) and Jovon (Jojo) Mangual (13)Joseph R. MillerShelley BellmomoJerry LoganLinda McPherson
'No, no, I don't think there's any chance of that... but I haven't been informed of anything yet,' he said to the Seattle Times.
Thomas Durnell, 65, was at home when the landslide piled into his house and is missing according to his daughter Pam Keller.
Caroline Neal hopes her missing father, Steven, 52, will still be rescued. He's a plumber who was on a service call when the land gave way.
'My dad is a quick thinker, and he is someone who takes action in an emergency,' Neal told CNN affiliate KING. 'If he had any warning at all, we just have to think he is somewhere and he's safe and they just can't reach him right now.
'None of us feel like he's gone,' his wife Brenda Neal said.
Her daughter, Sara, agreed: 'I think if anyone had a chance to getting through, it would be him.'
The waiting also came to end on Tuesday for the family of U.S. Navy Cmdr. John Regelbrugge, 49, whose body and that of his beloved dog were found by his brothers, his sister-in-law, Jackie Leighton, told CNN.
Still missing is Regelbrugge's wife, she added.
One retired lumber mill worker, Reed Miller, told Seattle television station KOMO-TV that his riverfront house was demolished by the slide, and that his 47-year-old son, Joseph. with whom he shared the home, was probably swept away with it.
The younger Miller, an avid fisherman and photographer, was alone in the Oso mobile home he shared with his father Saturday morning when the mudslide ran through it.
'Well, he was at home. As far as I know he's gone,' said Miller, who was at a grocery store in town at the time. 'There's no official (word) that he's been found yet, but he could be buried. I just don't know.'
Doug Reuwsaat, who grew up in the area and was also helping in the search, said authorities had told people to stay away.
'We're related to a lot of these people from around here. So that's why we're here,' he said.
Among those who are missing are the wife and granddaughter of Oso firefighter Seth Jeffereds.
He and his stepdaughter were out collecting errands when the landslide began according to him.
Christina Jeffereds, 45, was at home babysitting 4-month old Sanoah Huestis when the earth began to move.
They were joined by Doug Massingale, Christina's ex-husband.
He said he had dashed down from Sedro-Woolley, Washington, to help his 26-year-old daughter search for Sanoah and his ex-wife, who was with their granddaughter when the slide hit.
'They're still looking for her. 'I think it's going to be a long search. Big area and a little body.'
Also, Barbara Welsh, who spoke to reporters at a news briefing on Monday said that she hadn't seen her husband, William Welsh since Saturday.
Frustrations were growing as family members and neighbors waited for official word on the missing and the dead. Elaine Young and her neighbors uncovered several bodies Sunday and had to contact authorities to get them removed.
They also found a chocolate Labrador named Buddy alive, and helped pull the dog from the rubble, leading her to wonder if other survivors could be out there, desperate for help.
'If we found a dog alive yesterday afternoon that we cut out of a part of a house, doesn't that seem that maybe somebody could be stuck up under part of a house and be alive too?' asked Young, whose home survived the slide but was on the edge of the devastation.
Nichole Webb Rivera told the Seattle Times she frantically called and texted her parents, her daughter and her daughter's fiance when the massive hillside collapsed.
Rivera said her parents, Thom and Marcy Satterlee, lived near the center of the slide, and she doesn't believe they made it out.
She said her 20-year-old daughter, Delaney Webb, and Webb's fiance were visiting the older couple at the time.
Rivera lives in Houston but has traveled to Washington following the slide. She said Monday after visiting the area: 'We've lost four.'
Ronald DeQuilettes is an electrician who was working at Larry and Sandy Miller's house when the wall of mud came crashing down on them - they are all missing.
Also missing is 14-year-old Denver Harris, who may have been hiking when the mudslide came crashing down.
Missing: In this undated photo provided by Nichole Webb Rivera, her daughter, Delaney Webb, (left), and her fiance, Alan Bejvl, (left), who are missing as a result of the huge landslide are shown Missing: In this undated photo provided by Nichole Webb Rivera, her daughter, Delaney Webb, (left), and her fiance, Alan Bejvl, (left), who are missing as a result of the huge landslide are shown while (right) Thom and Marcy Satterlee who are also missing are shown Searching: Married grandfather Steve Neal, 52, is also reportedly among the missing Christina Jefferd Granddaughter Sanoah Huestis Among the missing: Summer Raffo's family says she is still unaccounted for and may have been trapped in her vehicle
Also among the missing are Steve and Theresa Harris.
Their niece, Emily Christoph, one of many worried family members, holding on to the hope they will be found alive.
FIRST STEPS TO HELP AFFECTED
As the search continues for survivors of the deadly mudslide, the first steps in helping those affected have already begun.
Gov. Jay Inslee has declared a state of emergency that could bring in long-term federal money beyond the assistance President Barack Obama ordered to supplement local rescue efforts. Various groups are also collecting donations for victims of the disaster.
Sen. Patty Murray, D-Wash., told her colleagues on the Senate floor Monday that 'it's impossible to describe the scope of this devastation'.
'In the coming weeks and months and even years, if that's what it takes, all of us need to stand with the people of Oso and Darrington and Arlington and provide the federal resources they're going to desperately need in this recovery and rebuilding operation,' she said. 
'I didn't know what to do. I was numb. I couldn't believe it. It's like you don't ever think your family would be involved in something like this,' said their niece Emily Christoph.
Also reported missing were former Alaska residents Julie Farnes and her son Adam, who were believed to be home on Saturday morning.
Her youngest brother, Richard Urton said he was losing hope. 'She was just the best sister a guy could ask for,' he said to the Anchorage Daily News.
Another sad addition to the list of people missing is Brandy Ward who was home with her husband, Tim at the time of the landslide.
Tim Ward was taken to Harborview Medical Center in Seattle with a fractured pelvis, and Brandy Ward is still missing.
Ron Thompson, whose home was destroyed, stopped by the evacuation shelter at Post Middle School in Arlington to find out if his friends turned up alive. 'We lost a lot of good kids. I don't know what else to tell you. It hurts,' he said before driving away.
Also among the missing was a group of girls who had been having a slumber party, according to a resident interviewed by The Seattle Times.
Retired firefighter Gail Moffett, who lives in Oso, said she knows about 25 people who are missing, including entire families with young children.
'It's safe to say I'll know everyone affected or who they are,' Moffett said. 'There's so much pain going on in the community right now.'
Among the injured were a mother and her baby. Amanda Skorjanc, 25, was in satisfactory condition at Harborview Medical Center in Seattle, spokeswoman Susan Gregg said.
Her son, 22-week-old Duke Suddarth, remained in critical condition and was improving, Gregg said. Three other men were in serious condition.
The search for victims resumed under partly cloudy skies on Monday after treacherous quicksand-like conditions forced rescue workers to suspend their efforts at dusk on Sunday. Some workers, mired in mud up to their armpits, had to be dragged to safety.
]]></text></news-item>