<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV4-RM61-F03R-N2WC"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>What does freedom in business mean?</title><source>The Hindu Business Line</source><author>Dov Seidman</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 26, 2014 (The Hindu Business Line:http://www.thehindubusinessline.com/ Delivered by Newstex) A successful organisation is one that offers individual freedom without losing its sense of direction No matter where you are on the political spectrum, for capitalists, free enterprise is sacred and an inherent good. But what if we looked at free enterprise another way and asked: What is the role of freedom in the corporate setting? And how do levels of freedom affect the bottom line?
Freedom is widely accepted as a basic human right in our societies. Yet while strategists and organisational experts have explored many forces that drive success, they have paid too little attention to the impacts and implications of freedom.Research into how freedom affects business performance reveals that the right kind of freedom can indeed underpin competitive advantage, across different measures of financial performance, innovation and long-term success. This is not an abstract notion. There is a clearly defined structure — 'freedom from' and 'freedom to' — through which companies need to approach the quest for freedom.'Freedom from' is a necessary condition for success in life, society and business. It speaks to the liberation of individuals from hierarchy, oppression and stultifying rules, whether from a tyrannical government or from a top-down corporate management style. Relationships created by 'freedom from' have the potential to be open and two-way because power is appropriately distributed, information is shared and decision-making is inclusive. 'Freedom from' can shape the space for multiple actors to make broad contributions.We need moreBut 'freedom from', in and of itself, is not sufficient; while empowering to individuals, it doesn't establish moral and ethical frameworks in which to operate. 'Freedom from' needs to be followed by a meaningful journey towards 'freedom to' — the shared condition where we are inspired to act in the common interest. 'Freedom to' is alignment towards shared objectives and mutually positive outcomes.The breakdown of traditional power structures is leading to a rise of 'freedom from', leaving behind a power vacuum as old controls wither. We see it in West Asia — where the Arab Spring was a manifestation of the powerful drive for freedom — but also in the startup culture, among millennials who want freedom from conventional corporate trappings. But how do we contend with — and benefit from — this abundance of newfound freedom?Companies need to fill that vacuum with 'freedom to' if they are to create a competitive advantage. For example, organisations can increase employees' choices about what projects to work on and reward high performers with additional responsibilities in their areas of interest. In so doing, leaders can relocate freedom from something conferred externally to a force that arises organically.Organisations need to start viewing relations with all stakeholders — employees, customers, supply chain partners and even communities — through this lens of 'freedom from/freedom to'. Business, after all, is about relationships — relationships with employees, customers, supply chain partners and other stakeholdersFreedom on the marchToday, freedom — particularly 'freedom from' — is on the march. The interdependencies of today's business, culture and communications expose us to the freedom of others, increasing our demand for the newfound freedoms we see others exercising. Technology is a great liberator, powering interactivity and commerce that support the rise of 'freedom from' in our business and personal lives as never before.No organisation can ignore that change is under way, any more than a government could ignore the uprising sparked by a Tunisian fruit vendor in 2010. Companies that swim against the tide of history, that invest in more powerful controls and erect walls to keep freedom at bay, will find their smartest minds, most loyal customers and most valuable partners drift away to seek freedom with others.On the other hand, those enterprises that devote themselves to fostering 'freedom to' will be best suited to generate sustainable growth that is resilient over the long term. It won't come easily. But the only option that can inspire behaviour that underpins organisational growth and resilience at the same time is unshackling superfluous controls to foster 'freedom from' — then embedding and scaling the human values that animate 'freedom to'.The writer is the founder and CEO of LRN Corporation

]]></text></news-item>