<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV4-MBN1-JC8S-D0PS"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>As channel opens, cleanup shifts west;New focus: Oil is expected to hit Matagorda Peninsula;</title><source>The Houston Chronicle</source><author>By Harvey Rice</author><text><![CDATA[TEXAS CITY - Traffic in the Houston Ship Channel, which ground to a halt for three days because of an oil spill, resumed Tuesday as authorities prepared for a new cleanup effort on the Matagorda Peninsula southwest of Galveston.
Crews on some 70 vessels worked furiously before weather worsened Tuesday to skim as much oil as possible remaining from a collision in the channel Saturday that poured as much as 168,000 gallons of thick fuel oil into Galveston Bay.
Enough oil had been cleared to allow ships to begin moving again through the section of the Ship Channel affected by the spill. Barges resumed their journeys on the Intracoastal Waterway.
The wind and current pushed a portion of the spill into the Gulf of Mexico, where it was about 10 miles off the coast and moving south, said Capt. Brian Penoyer, captain of the port for Houston/Galveston. The oil is expected to land as tar balls on the Matagorda Peninsula, Land Commissioner Jerry Patterson said.
Patterson said crews were arriving in Mata­gorda County in preparation for cleanup efforts.
Bad weather with swells as large as 9 feet in the Gulf was expected to make recovery operations difficult Wednesday, said Richard Arnhart, an official with the Texas General Land Office oil response team.
The major cleanup operation is expected to continue for at least several more days, and smaller cleanup efforts will likely continue for weeks, Penoyer said.
Effect on coastline
The oil so far has soiled about 15.5 miles of coastline as a result of the collision between the Liberian-flagged bulk vessel Summer Wind and a barge carrying 900,000 gallons of heavy bunker fuel oil. Because of wind and currents, the areas stained with oil were limited to the Texas City Dike, a small area on the western tip of the Bolivar Peninsula, Pelican Island, the Port of Galveston and the eastern end of Galveston Island.
None of the oil has penetrated environmentally sensitive marshes so far, authorities said. Nine dead birds have been reported. Eight soiled birds still alive were moved to a rehabilitation center in Baytown.
Skimmers have scooped about 165,000 gallons of oil-and-seawater mixture and crews picked up 852 bags of oily debris and sand, but it's hard to know exactly how much oil is in the mix, Penoyer said.
More than 71,000 feet of containment boom has been placed to protect sensitive areas, and 232,600 feet of boom is ready for use. Some of that boom surrounds the 1877 barque Elissa, the official Texas tall ship, in its berth at the Texas Maritime Museum in Galveston. Oil in Galveston Harbor forced the postponement of the ship's first outing after two years of repairs, said W. Dwayne Jones, Galveston Historical Foundation executive director.
The oil is also soiling the environmentally sensitive Big Reef area on the eastern end of the island, a habitat for birds that have just begun a migration across the Gulf from Mexico into the U.S.
Unseasonably cold weather may have kept the oil from affecting two types of endangered turtles, green and Kemp's ridley, said Kimberly Reich, director of the Trophic Ecology and Sea Turtle Biology Lab at Texas A&M University in Galveston. Green turtles, which all but vanished before making a comeback in Galveston Bay, typically feed near the Texas City Dike, and the Kemp's ridley nesting season normally begins about this time of year. But few turtles have been seen in the area, and Reich believes the cold weather may be keeping them away.
A few tar balls appeared on Galveston beaches facing the Gulf of Mexico on Monday and were picked up quickly. Craig Brown, chairman of the Galveston Park Board, said Seawolf Park on Pelican Island remained closed, but the beaches most frequented by tourists were open.
The vessels that have begun moving through the Ship Channel are under strict supervision that could keep traffic from returning immediately to normal levels, Penoyer said. Vessels carrying products needed to keep refineries operating safely would likely be given priority, he said.
Pump prices stable
Gasoline prices have been largely unchanged in the days since the channel closure prompted worries that lower refinery output might reduce fuel supplies and force up the price at the pump.
Nationally, unleaded gasoline sold for an average of just over $3.53 per gallon Tuesday, according to AAA, up less than a penny from the day before the spill. Houston-area gasoline sold for $3.38 per gallon, similarly unchanged.
Refiners haven't said much about how their operations were affected by the waterway's closure. Officials with Shell Oil and Valero Energy declined to say whether the channel's shutdown affected their production. A spokesman for Exxon Mobil Corp. said it had reduced production rates at its Baytown refining complex but declined to say by how much.
Texas A&M University at Galveston scientists took water samples from the reopened channel Tuesday. The samples will provide clues about how the oil affected marine life, particularly phytoplankton, the base of the bay's food chain.
"If there are problems with the phytoplankton, there will be consequences higher up the chain," said marine biologist Antonietta Quigg, who has taken monthly water samples from the bay since 2005.
A key concern is whether the oil reached the bottom of the bay, where problems can linger. Oyster reefs, for example, still haven't recovered from the pounding of Hurricane Ike in 2008.
But fish can swim away from the oil. A good sign: Three dolphins jumped from the waters near where the oil spill began. A common sight in the spring, dolphins had not been seen since Saturday.
The sighting means that "the cleanup is going well or the currents are pushing it out," Quigg said.
Lawsuit filed
Meanwhile, charter fishing businesses and others filed a class action lawsuit in federal court in Galveston against the owners of the two vessels.
The suit, filed Monday, names Kirby Inland Marine, owner of the towboat Miss Susan, and Cleopatra Shipping Agency, owner of the 585-foot bulk carrier Summer Wind. It claims the vessels' owners failed to ensure that the oil would be contained in the immediate vicinity in the event of a collision.
The spill has had a "wide and devastating effect on Galveston Bay, the Gulf of Mexico and the people who use and depend on it," according to the lawsuit, which seeks unspecified damages.
A top Kirby Corporation official declined comment on possible causes of the accident, which remains under investigation by the U.S. Coast Guard.
Kirby chairman and CEO Joe Pyne said company officials regret the accident and the effect it has had on the environment.
"Houston is our home, and the bay is a cherished resource that the Houston community, including our employees and their families, enjoy," Pyne said.
Matt Woodruff, the company's director of government affairs, described the Miss Susan, built in 1995, as a towboat of average age with no recent safety issues. Though the ship has had 17 reported incidents to the U.S. Coast Guard in the last dozen years, there have been no reports of accidents or mechanical problems since December 2010, records show.
Chronicle reporters Matthew Tresaugue, Ryan Holeywell and Carol Christian contributed to this report.
harvey.rice@chron.com
twitter.com/harveyricechron
...
Good news for birds
>> Feathered patients: Wildlife experts are relieved that the number of oil-soaked birds brought in for cleaning and rehabilitation is lower than expected. B1
]]></text></news-item>