<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV4-FDP1-F0CC-S4MK"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Royal Bank of Scotland PLC Final Results -14-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[include members of the RBS Group Board, or other key employees, and it may suffer if it does not maintain good employee relations.
-- The RBS Group is subject to a number of regulatory initiatives which may adversely affect its business, including the UK Government's adoption of the Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013, the US Federal Reserve's new rules for applying US capital, liquidity and enhanced prudential standards to certain of the RBS Group's US operations and ongoing reforms in the European Union with respect to capital requirements, stability and resolution of financial institutions, including CRD IV and other currently debated proposals such as the Resolution and Recovery Directive (RRD).
Risk factors
-- The RBS Group's ability to meet its obligations including its funding commitments depends on the RBS Group's ability to access sources of liquidity and funding. The inability to access liquidity and funding due to market conditions or otherwise or to do so at a reasonable cost due to increased regulatory constraints, could adversely affect the Group's financial condition and results of operations. Furthermore, the RBS Group's borrowing costs and its access to the debt capital markets and other sources of liquidity depend significantly on its and the UK Government's credit ratings which would be likely to be negatively impacted by political events, such as an affirmative outcome of the referendum for the independence of Scotland.
-- The RBS Group's business performance, financial condition and capital and liquidity ratios could be adversely affected if its capital is not managed effectively or as a result of changes to capital adequacy and liquidity requirements, including those arising out of Basel III implementation (globally or by European, UK or US authorities) as well as structural changes that may result from the implementation of ring-fencing under the Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013 or proposed changes of the US Federal Reserve with respect to the RBS Group's US operations. The Group's ability to reach its target capital ratios in the medium term will turn on a number of factors including a significant downsizing of the Group in part through the sale of RBS Citizens.
-- The RBS Group is, and may be, subject to litigation and regulatory and governmental investigations that may impact its business, reputation, results of operations and financial condition. Although the RBS Group settled a number of legal proceedings and regulatory investigations during 2013, the RBS Group is expected to continue to have a material exposure to legacy litigation and regulatory matter proceedings in the medium term. The RBS Group also expects greater regulatory and governmental scrutiny for the foreseeable future particularly as it relates to compliance with new and existing laws and regulations such as anti-money laundering and anti-terrorism laws.
-- Operational and reputational risks are inherent in the RBS Group's businesses.
-- The RBS Group is highly dependent on its information technology systems and has been and will continue to be subject to cyber attacks which expose the RBS Group to loss of customer data or other sensitive information, and combined with other failures of the RBS Group's information technology systems, hinder its ability to service its clients which could result in long-term damage to the RBS Group's business and brand.
-- RBSG or any of its UK bank subsidiaries may face the risk of full nationalisation or other resolution procedures, including recapitalisation of RBSG or any of its UK bank subsidiaries, through bail-in which has been introduced by the Financial Services (Banking Reform) Act 2013 and will come into force on a date stipulated by HM Treasury. These various actions could be taken by or on behalf of the UK Government, including actions in relation to any securities issued, new or existing contractual arrangements and transfers of part or all of the RBS Group's businesses.
-- As a result of the UK Government's majority shareholding in RBSG it may be able to exercise a significant degree of influence over the RBS Group including on dividend policy, the election of directors or appointment of senior management or limiting the RBS Group's operations. The offer or sale by the UK Government of all or a portion of its shareholding in RBSG could affect the market price of the equity shares and other securities and acquisitions of ordinary shares by the UK Government (including through conversions of other securities or further purchases of shares) may result in the delisting of RBSG from the Official List.
Risk factors
-- The actual or perceived failure or worsening credit of the RBS Group's counterparties or borrowers, including sovereigns in the Eurozone, and depressed asset valuations resulting from poor market conditions have led the RBS Group to realise and recognise significant impairment charges and write-downs which have adversely affected the RBS Group and could continue to adversely affect the RBS Group if, due to a deterioration in economic and financial market conditions or continuing weak economic growth, it were to recognise or realise further write-downs or impairment charges.
-- The value of certain financial instruments recorded at fair value is determined using financial models incorporating assumptions, judgements and estimates that may change over time or may ultimately not turn out to be accurate.
-- Recent developments in regulatory or tax legislation and any further significant developments could have an effect on how the Group conducts its business and on its results of operations and financial condition, and the recoverability of certain deferred tax assets recognised by the Group is subject to uncertainty.
-- The RBS Group is required to make planned contributions to its pension schemes and to compensation schemes in respect of certain financial institutions, either of which, independently or in conjunction with additional or increased contribution requirements may have an adverse impact on the Group's results of operations, cash flow and financial condition.
26 March 2014 Board of directors
Forward-looking statements Certain sections in this document contain 'forward-looking statements' as that term is defined in the United States Private Securities Litigation Reform Act of 1995, such as statements that include the words 'expect', 'estimate', 'project', 'anticipate', 'believe', 'should', 'intend', 'plan', 'could', 'probability', 'risk', 'Value-at-Risk (VaR)', 'target', 'goal', 'objective', 'will', 'endeavour', 'outlook', 'optimistic', 'prospects' and similar expressions or variations on such expressions. In particular, this document includes forward-looking statements relating, but not limited to: the RBS Group's and the Group's restructuring and new strategic plans, divestments, capitalisation, portfolios, net interest margin, capital ratios, liquidity, risk-weighted assets (RWAs), profitability, cost:income ratios, leverage and loan:deposit ratios, funding and risk profile; discretionary coupon and dividend payments; implementation of legislation of ring-fencing and bail-in measures; sustainability targets; litigation, regulatory and governmental investigations; the Group's future financial performance; the level and extent of future impairments and write-downs; and the Group's exposure to political risks, including the referendum on Scottish independence, credit rating risk and to various types of market risks, such as interest rate risk, foreign exchange rate risk and commodity and equity price risk. These statements are based on current plans, estimates and projections, and are subject to inherent risks, uncertainties and other factors which could cause actual results to differ materially from the future results expressed or implied by such forward-looking statements. For example, certain market risk disclosures are dependent on choices about key model characteristics and assumptions and are subject to various limitations. By their nature, certain of the market risk disclosures are only estimates and, as a result, actual
]]></text></news-item>