<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV4-MTS1-JC3H-03YV"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>In video, Braley slams Grassley as farmer without a law degree</title><source>Des Moines Register</source><author>By, Jennifer Jacobs</author><text><![CDATA[Video shot at a private fundraiser of Democratic U.S. Senate candidate Bruce Braley that shows him belittling Republican U.S. Sen. Chuck Grassley as "a farmer from Iowa who never went to law school" created a firestorm on Tuesday, and later drew an apology from Braley.
Republican operatives on Tuesday circulated the footage of Braley at a Texas fundraiser in January warning fellow lawyers that Grassley might become the next Judiciary Committee chairman if they didn't contribute money to help elect Braley.
The remarks by Braley, a trial lawyer and Iowa congressman who is running in the high-stakes open race for retiring U.S. Sen. Tom Harkin's seat, quickly caught fire on Twitter and national news sites. Some politics watchers predicted that this incident will bruise a campaign that they've been confident would see victory in November.
Grassley's staff pulled no punches in responding on Tuesday - National Agriculture Day, when a statue of an Iowa ag hero was unveiled at the U.S. Capitol.
"If you help me win this race," Braley says in the video, posted online by a donor after the Jan. 23 fundraiser in Corpus Christi, Texas, and released Tuesday by the conservative America Rising political action committee, "you may have someone with your background, your experience, your voice, someone's who's been literally fighting tort reform for 30 years in a visible and public way on the Senate Judiciary Committee.
"Or you might have a farmer from Iowa who never went to law school, never practiced law, serving as the next chair of the Senate Judiciary Committee," Braley says. "Because if Democrats lose the majority, Chuck Grassley will be the next chair of the Senate Judiciary Committee."
Longtime Iowa political columnist David Yepsen watched the video, then told The Des Moines Register: "This is bad for Braley, and it will hurt him. Chuck Grassley is a political icon."
In response to the Braley video, Grassley spokeswoman Beth Pellett Levine said: "By the logic expressed on this recording, a trial lawyer shouldn't be involved in policymaking about agriculture, or energy, or health care."
Pellett Levine noted that Grassley, the ranking member on the Judiciary Committee, has a strong record of work that has stopped fraud, reformed the bankruptcy code, protected whistle-blowers, exposed illegal gun trafficking and dealt with other matters for the public good.
Grassley is one of only two working family farmers in the U.S. Senate, she said.
Braley's biggest donors this election cycle to date are lawyers and law firms, according to OpenSecrets.org. They've funneled $1.12 million into his campaign.
In a statement Tuesday afternoon, Braley said: "I apologize to Sen. Grassley and anyone I may have offended. I respect Sen. Grassley and enjoy our working relationship even though we disagree on some issues."
Braley said his parents both grew up on Iowa farms during the Great Depression, which "deeply influenced who they are and who I am, and gave me a profound appreciation for what farmers do for the world."
He added that one of his grandfathers was a charter member of the Iowa Farm Bureau, and that he himself grew up in rural Iowa doing farm jobs and working at a grain elevator.
Yepsen said Iowans who watch Braley's candid remarks to a friendly audience might find them grating.
"There are a lot of people who don't have law degrees. It comes off as elitist," Yepsen said.
Braley's situation is reminiscent of other red-faced politicians who were caught on tape at fundraisers - including President Barack Obama's guns-and-religion jibe and Republican Mitt Romney's 47 percent remark, Yepsen said.
It's too early in the 2014 campaign for something like this to be fatal for a candidate, he said, but it will give new hope to Republicans who didn't think they had a chance against Braley and were instead focusing on the Iowa governor's race and 3rd District congressional race.
"The biggest effect will be to energize Republicans," he said. "This will be a bloody shirt that they wave in front of GOP audiences from here on out."
Four of the Republican U.S. Senate candidates seeking the chance to take on Braley in November issued statements Tuesday afternoon skewering Braley.
And the right-leaning Priorities for Iowa released a statement Tuesday that blasted Braley for scoffing at the notion of a farmer as the committee's chairman, and for telling out-of-state trial lawyers that he would be their voice in Washington.
"Bruce Braley is putting his values, and this Senate seat, up for sale," said Sara Craig, director of Priorities for Iowa.
She added: "Maybe Bruce Braley doesn't realize that today we celebrate 'just an Iowa farmer' Norman Borlaug's statue unveiling in the United States Capitol. Makes you wonder what he could have achieved if he'd gone to law school."
Hundreds of tweets about Braley's comments made the rounds on Twitter.
"Big unforced error on Braley's part," wrote NBC News political analyst Chuck Todd. "Not just elitest but un-Iowan to attack another Iowan the way he did."
And CBS News political director John Dickerson, referring to the bottles of liquor visible next to Braley in the video, wrote: "Come for the huge farm state gaffe, stay for the selection on the nearby bar cart."
What they said
The conservative America Rising political action committee on Tuesday released video taken by and posted online by a donor invited to Democratic U.S. Senate candidate Bruce Braley's Jan. 23 fundraiser in Corpus Christi, Texas. The audience at the fundraiser was a group of trial lawyers.
WHAT BRALEY SAID IN THE VIDEO: "If you help me win this race, you may have someone with your background, your experience, your voice, someone's who's been literally fighting tort reform for 30 years in a visible and public way on the Senate Judiciary Committee. Or you might have a farmer from Iowa who never went to law school, never practiced law, serving as the next chair of the Senate Judiciary Committee. Because if Democrats lose the majority, Chuck Grassley will be the next chair of the Senate Judiciary Committee."
GRASSLEY'S REACTION, via spokeswoman Beth Pellett Levine: "By the logic expressed on this recording, a trial lawyer shouldn't be involved in policymaking about agriculture, or energy, or health care. Sen. Grassley has served on the Judiciary Committee since he was first elected to the Senate, and he's got a strong record on the committee. Grassley-authored amendments to the False Claims Act have recovered nearly $40 billion for taxpayers that would otherwise be lost to fraud. He's the co-author of laws to curb class-action lawsuit abuse and to reform the bankruptcy code. Sen. Grassley is unmatched in his legislative and oversight work to protect whistleblowers, both in and out of government, who speak up about wrongdoing for the public good. He coauthored the Whistleblower Protection Act and numerous updates to laws protecting whistleblowers, including national security and on Wall Street. Sen. Grassley's work on the Judiciary Committee exposed the illegal gun-trafficking operation known as Operation Fast and Furious. It was Sen. Grassley's persistence that pressured the current administration to provide Congress with the legal rationale for using drones on American citizens. Alongside that, Sen. Grassley's one of only two working family farmers in the United States Senate, where he brings Iowa common sense to work for ag, anti-trust, transportation, environmental, energy, trade, health care, communications, national security, and tax policy that works for all of America."
BRALEY'S APOLOGY: "I apologize to Sen. Grassley and anyone I may have offended. I respect Sen. Grassley and enjoy our working relationship even though we disagree on some issues. But there is a clear choice in this race between Mark Jacobs and my other opponents who support policies that are bad for Iowa farmers, and the work I've done hand in hand with Iowa farmers to grow Iowa's farm economy and create good paying Iowa farm jobs. My parents both grew up on Iowa farms during the Great Depression. It deeply influenced who they are and who I am, and gave me a profound appreciation for what farmers do for the world. One of my grandfathers was a charter member of the Iowa Farm Bureau. I grew up in rural Iowa, doing farm jobs and working a grain elevator. I have tremendous respect for Iowa farmers and appreciate how important they are to our state, and I'm grateful to have the support of hundreds of farmers across Iowa."
]]></text></news-item>