<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV4-RXW1-F125-13V9"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>André Boisclair lands in Montreal offices of Recyc-Québec</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[QUEBEC - André Boisclair, who gave up his position as Quebec's representative in New York to defend his name in a lawsuit, has landed in the Montreal offices of Recyc-Québec, the Quebec government's agency to encourage recycling, on President Kennedy Ave.
In his new position as president of Comex, a joint Quebec-Cree committee created under the James Bay-Northern Quebec Agreement to evaluate the environmental impact of proposed developments in the James Bay region, Boisclair receives the same $175,608 salary he was granted when Pauline Marois named him Quebec's delegate general to New York in November 2012.
He replaced Pierre Mercier, a retired senior Quebec civil servant, who was paid $375 a day to preside over Comex.
The cabinet decree, naming him to his new position for a two-year term, specifies Boisclair will work in the Montreal office of Comex.
But Comex, based in Quebec City, has no Montreal office. Questioned by reporters in Montreal Wednesday, Marois said his office was with Recyc-Québec.
But, mysteriously, to reach Boisclair's telephone number, callers must go through the Université du Québec à Montréal switchboard.
In September, Boisclair stepped down temporarily from his position as Quebec's delegate general in New York after Jacques Duchesneau, a former Montreal police chief and the outgoing Coalition Avenir Québec MNA for Saint-Jérôme, questioned Boisclair's admitted use of cocaine in the past and his association with Paul Sauvé, a construction entrepreneur. While renovating Montreal's St. James United Church, Sauvé had a business partner named Normand (Casper) Ouimet.
Ouimet, a Hells Angels gang member, previously convicted of cocaine trafficking and charged with 22 murders, was recently sentenced to 27 years in prison.
Boisclair has denied the allegations against himself and is suing Duchesneau, CAQ leader François Legault and the CAQ for $200,000 in damages.
In December, former Radio-Canada journalist Dominique Poirier was named to replace Boisclair in New York. Poirier is also paid $175,608 a year.
In a statement, Quebec's environment department said that since Boisclair lived in Montreal, a Montreal office with the necessary equipment for him to do his job, was found for Boisclair, at no extra cost to taxpayers. The environment department was already paying for the Recyc-Québec office.
Geneviève Lebel, the environment department media relations officer, said in an email reply that Boisclair does not give interviews as president of Comex since "that is not part of his duties."
Boisclair was environment minister in the PQ government of Bernard Landry, resigning his National Assembly seat in 2004 to do a master's degree in public administration Harvard University's John F. Kennedy School of Government.
When Landry resigned as PQ leader in 2005, Boisclair sought and won the party leadership with 54 per cent of the vote, beating Marois, his nearest rival.
Boisclair led the PQ into the disastrous 2007 election campaign, which saw the party place third behind Mario Dumont's Action démocratique du Québec. Faithful to the PQ program, Boisclair promised a new sovereignty referendum.
After the election, Boisclair resigned and Marois was acclaimed PQ leader.
Boisclair became a Concordia University lecturer and a consultant, whose clients included Alberta gas and oil companies.
After Marois won the 2012 election, she named Boisclair to the coveted New York post, which includes a penthouse apartment across from the Museum of Modern Art.
kdougherty@montrealgazette.com( http://mailto: )( mailto:kdougherty@montrealgazette.com )
Twitter:doughertykr
© Copyright (c) The Montreal Gazette
]]></text></news-item>