<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV4-Y8N1-JDK3-9481"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Portland Hotel Society spinoff companies set off 'alarm bells' after audit</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[One of the key concerns raised in audits of the beleaguered Portland Hotel Society is at least eight spinoff companies that owe the non-profit nearly $500,000.
PHS created the corporations - which do everything from clothes washing to pest control - to provide services to their buildings and, in some cases, to give jobs to vulnerable Downtown Eastside neighbourhoods.
But damning audits released last week reveal the companies have a history of financial losses and many are owned, run or overseen by people with links to PHS - either as society employees, members or board directors.
The companies "present an elevated risk of fraud, corruption and abuse," says a 126-page KPMG audit completed last July for the provincial government, one of PHS's main funders.
The audit found the board of directors had "insufficient recognition" of the associated risks, potential contractual problems and governance issues, and recommended PHS try to stop doing business with its friends and staff.
A 2014 audit for Vancouver Coastal Health, another key PHS funder, found eight spinoff companies owed the non-profit society $481,000 in outstanding cash advances as of October 2013, putting public funds "at risk."
"The rationale for setting up these companies initially is questionable as well as the lack of an ongoing assessment process to determine the continued benefit of operating them," says the VCH audit.
PHS managers told the auditors Bugs Be Gone pest control, for example, was created to provide timely bug treatment by people willing to work in challenging environments. It had to be a separate legal entity in order to buy the chemicals required, they said.
PHS managers did not respond to interview requests. The Sun was also unable to reach the owners or directors of the eight companies.
The revelation that PHS was essentially contracting services to itself was one of the main reasons the government recently axed the executive and asked the board to resign, said B.C. Housing Minister Rich Coleman.
"It is suspect. There should be arms-length transactions. That was one of the alarm bells that came up as we went through this," he said.
"Some of this work could be tendered out to people. If it is a company owned by the society, then the perception is that nobody else gets to bid for the work."
Coleman said the new board will determine whether the companies provide social and financial value, and if they will be continued.
Because PHS is mainly supported by government grants, most of the companies therefore receive a large portion of their revenue from taxpayer dollars, the audits found.
Any losses or gains from these companies reverted to PHS, not the legal owners, because they were largely "controlled by PHS," the KPMG audit found. It found no proof, however, of any PHS managers double-dipping - that is, receiving income from both PHS and the affiliate companies.
The VCH audit found a conflict of interest, though, when a PHS manager, who is also the shareholder of Bugs Be Gone, approved a $13,887 payment from PHS to the firm. "Allowing the shareholder of a company PHS uses for services to authorize PHS payments creates the risk of erroneous invoices being approved," the audit says.
It was PHS policy to provide loans to the companies to help with cash flow. As such, the audits found PHS was owed significant amounts of money from some, including $161,783 from DTES Maintenance, $117,945 from Our Community Security, and $96,999 from Bugs Be Gone.
Auditors uncovered other financial curiosities.
Andy Bond, a PHS employee who also owns DTES Janitorial Services, purchased wholesale cleaning supplies on his personal credit card, and then sold them back to PHS for markups averaging 30 per cent.
PHS management said the markups reflected Bond's costs of sourcing, purchasing, collecting, storing and delivering the supplies. Bond used his personal card because PHS had a limit on corporate cards it could obtain, managers said.
From 2010 to 2012, auditors found Bond charged $535,000 in expenses back to Janitorial Services that were largely for cleaning supplies. He also filed hefty expense claims to two other companies: $185,788 to Bugs Be Gone and nearly $5,000 to Mop Squad.
Phong Lam, a PHS employee and owner of three of the companies, filed $34,263 in expenses to DTES Maintenance from 2010 to 2012.
PHS frequently charged the affiliates for accounting, payroll, and other administrative services, but the fees were largely based on the companies' ability to pay, the audits found. For example, Bugs Be Gone paid $24,000 to PHS in 2010 but nothing in 2012.
The auditors raised concerns that in 2012, six of the eight companies paid PHS $162,000 in fees but only $125,000 was recorded as revenue in PHS books.
Four of the eight companies also paid rent to PHS for some or all of the three years audited, ranging from $12,000 to $24,000 annually.
PHS managers told the auditors they were in the process of moving these affiliates into a Community Contribution Company, a new hybrid corporate model that would allow PHS to own the shares.
With research by Sun librarian Kate Bird and files from Matthew Robinson
lculbert@vancouversun.com( mailto:lculbert@vancouversun.com )
rshaw@vancouversun.com( mailto:rshaw@vancouversun.com )
The PHS-affiliated companies that concern auditors:
1. Bugs Be Gone Pest Control
Owner: Phong Lam, PHS employee who oversees maintenance and emergency response, and is the brother of PHS senior accountant Theresa Lam
Board member: Brad Doherty, PHS controller
Outstanding loans owed to PHS: $96,999 (as of March 2012)
Fees paid to PHS for administrative services: $24,000 (2010), $24,000 (2011), $0 (2012).
Payments, in addition to salary, mainly to reimburse expenses (2010-2012): $185,788 to Andy Bond
2. DTES Community Janitorial Supplies
Owner: Phong Lam, PHS employee who oversees maintenance and emergency response, and is the brother of PHS senior accountant Theresa Lam
Board member: Brad Doherty, PHS controller
Fees paid to PHS for administrative services: $0 (2010), $48,000 (2011), $60,000 (2012).
Payments, in addition to salary, mainly to reimburse expenses (2010-2012): $535,383 to Bond
This company lost money in 2010 ($3,215) and 2012 ($966), but made $1,557 in 2011.
3. DTES Maintenance
Owner: Phong Lam, PHS employee who oversees maintenance and emergency response, and is the brother of PHS senior accountant Theresa Lam
Board member: Brad Doherty, PHS controller
Outstanding loans owed to PHS: $161,783 (as of March 2012)
Fees paid to PHS for administrative services: $48,000 (2010), $0 (2011), $0 (2012).
Payments, in addition to salary, mainly to reimburse expenses (2010-2012): $34,263 to Lam
Audit found PHS pays this company a regular monthly amount but is given no details of the specific cleaning it does or in which buildings.
4. The Mop Squad Cleaning
Owner: Andy Bond, PHS employee who oversees social housing buildings
Board member: Brad Doherty, PHS controller
Fees paid to PHS for administrative services: $12,000 (2010), $30,000 (2011), $90,000 (2012).
Payments, in addition to salary, mainly to reimburse expenses (2010-2012): $4,879 to Bond
5. Radio Station Cafe
Owner: Edmond Wolf, identified in the audit as a PHS member
Board member: Brad Doherty, PHS controller
"Loss subsidies" claimed by PHS: $-4,000 (2010), $-63,000 (2011), $-64,000 (2012).
Audit found that unlike many of the other companies, its customers are external rather than directly from PHS.
6. Our Community Security
Owner: Andy Bond, PHS employee who oversees social housing buildings
Outstanding loans owed to PHS: $117,945 (as of March 2012)
Fees paid to PHS for administrative services: $29,600 (2010), $0 (2011), $0 (2012).
7. Wishy Washy Laundry
Owner: an inactive company owned by Russell Cullingworth, a former PHS employee
Board members: Brad Doherty, PHS controller, Tom Laviolette, PHS's director of properties and facility development
Fees paid to PHS for administrative services: $2,000 (2010), $1,000 (2011), $12,000 (2012).
8. DTES Community Development
Owner: Tom Laviolette, PHS's director of properties and facility development
Fees paid to PHS for consulting expenses: $32,000 (2010), $62,000 (201), $5,000 (2012).
Source: Vancouver Sun corporate record searches, KPMG audit, VCH audit
© Copyright (c) The Vancouver Sun
]]></text></news-item>