<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-PP31-JBV0-D00F"><date>2014-03-27</date><title></title><source>The Tampa Tribune (Florida)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[- Charlotte Mayor Patrick Cannon, who has been in office less than six months, resigned Wednesday, just hours after he was arrested and accused of taking more than $48,000 in bribes from undercover FBI agents posing as businessmen who wanted to do work with North Carolina's largest city.
Cannon, 47, is charged with bribery and public corruption. The Democrat took cash, airline tickets, a hotel room and the use of a luxury apartment as bribes and solicited more than $1 million more, according to a criminal complaint from the U.S. Attorney's office.
Train driver dozed off before Chicago crash
- The operator of a Chicago commuter train that crashed at O'Hare International Airport acknowledged she dozed off before the accident and told investigators she had fallen asleep at the controls one other time recently, even overshooting a station platform, a federal investigator said Wednesday.
In Monday's accident, which injured more than 30 people, she woke up only as the eight-car train jolted onto the platform and barreled up an escalator leading into the airport.
The accident occurred about 3 a.m., as the driver was nearing the end of her shift.
The woman had an erratic work schedule and investigators were looking to see whether that played a role in her evident fatigue.
North Korea launches 2 missiles in protest
- North Korea test-fired two medium-range ballistic missiles Wednesday, South Korea and the U.S. said, a defiant challenge to a rare three-way summit of its rivals Seoul, Tokyo and Washington that focused on the North's security threat.
The launch of the Rodong missiles for the first time since 2009 violates U.N. Security Council resolutions and marks an escalation from a series of shorter-range rocket launches the North has staged in recent weeks to protest ongoing annual military drills by the U.S. and South Korea that Pyongyang claims are invasion preparation.
The missiles flew off North Korea's east coast. It wasn't immediately clear where the missiles splashed down.
House OKs bill to limit national monuments
- The House on Wednesday approved a Republican bill to limit the president's ability to designate new national monuments, a step President Barack Obama and other presidents have taken to protect historic or ecologically significant sites.
The bill, sponsored by Utah Rep. Rob Bishop, would require an environmental review, including a public hearing, before designation of monuments larger than 5,000 acres.
Only one monument per state could be created in a president's term. The legislation is unlikely to pass the Senate.
Judge throws out Okla. execution law
- An Oklahoma judge ruled the state's execution law unconstitutional Wednesday because its privacy provision is so strict that it that prevents inmates from finding out the source of drugs used in executions, even through the courts.
Under state law, no one is allowed to disclose the source of drugs used in a lethal injection.
From wire reports
]]></text></news-item>