<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-3X01-DY93-M1P1"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>AFPTV Agenda</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[We plan to file the following videos on Thursday. Please check the daily advisories for any additions and amendments:
-- TOP WORLD NEWS --
+ MALAYSIA PLANE
CANBERRA/PERTH, AUSTRALIA; KUALA LUMPUR; BEIJING: Monitoring the ongoing investigation into Malaysia's missing jet. RAW. TBA
+ US LANDSLIDE
SNOHOMISH COUNTY, WASHINGTON: Monitoring efforts to locate victims of a devastating landslide. TBA
+ OBAMA VATICAN/ITALY VISIT
VATICAN CITY: President Obama wraps up the European leg of his overseas trip with a visit to the Vatican to meet Pope Francis for the first time. RAW. 1100 GMT
ROME: Obama meets Italy's Prime Minister Matteo Renzi and then goes on a private guided tour of the Colosseum. RAW. 1700 GMT (Obama/Renzi presser) 2100 GMT (Coliseum visit)
-- OTHER WORLD NEWS --
+ ASIA-PACIFIC
MANILA / MINDANAO, PHILIPPINES: Philippine government and Moro Islamic Liberation Front to sign peace accord at presidential palace. RAW. TBA
NAYPYIDAW: Myanmar's powerful military conducts a show of strength in the former junta-run nation in the country's annual Armed Forces Day celebrations. RAW. TBA
TOKYO: Spring officially arrives as Japan's weather agency announces the start of the cherry blossom season. RAW. TBA
MACAU: Movie stars attend the annual Asian Film Awards. RAW. 2000 GMT
KEMUSUK, INDONESIA: As voters gear up for legislative elections, nostalgia is growing for the rule of former dictator Suharto, even though he headed a deeply corrupt and brutal regime. PKG. 0500 GMT
+ AFRICA
THE HAGUE: Charles Ble Goude, right-hand man to Ivorian ex-president Laurent Gbagbo, makes his first appearance before the International Criminal Court to face four counts of crimes against humanity. RAW. 1400 GMT
CONAKRY: Monitoring as Guinea battles to contain an Ebola epidemic also threatening neighbouring countries. TBC
PRETORIA: South African Reserve Bank Monetary Policy Committee decides on whether to maintain its main interest rate at 5.5%. STOCKSHOTS. 0300 GMT
+ EUROPE
KIEV/SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: Rolling news coverage of events in Ukraine and Crimea. RAW. TBA
THE HAGUE: Charles Ble Goude, right-hand man to Ivorian ex-president Laurent Gbagbo makes his first appearance before the International Criminal Court to face four counts of crimes against humanity. RAW. 1400 GMT
ISTANBUL: Hearing in absentia in the high-profile trial of four ex-Israeli military commanders over the killing of nine Turkish activists on board a Gaza-bound aid ship. FILE. 1000 GMT
ISTANBUL: US-exiled influential Muslim cleric Fethullah Gulen is accused by Turkey's Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan of using his influence in the country's police and judiciary to instigate a corruption probe to topple his AKP government. As the probe overshadows Sunday's municipal elections, AFPTV looks as Gulen's Hizmet movement which used to be an important backer of the AKP. PKG. 0400 GMT
FRANKFURT, GERMANY: German airports brace for major disruption and hundreds of flight cancellations as ground staff, baggage handlers and maintenance workers plan a strike over pay. RAW. 1300 GMT
LONDON: Amnesty International publishes its annual report on death sentences and executions worldwide. RAW. 0001 GMT
BERLIN: Chancellor Merkel hosts Canadian PM Stephen Harper for talks expected to focus on Ukraine. RAW. 1500 GMT (joint presser)
GENEVA: UN Human Rights Council begins two days of voting on dozens of resolutions spotlighting crisis situations around the globe, with attention centred on a call to probe alleged war crimes in Sri Lanka and extend an inquiry on Syria. RAW. TBA
PARIS: Chinese President Xi Jinping continues his official visit to France to mark 50 years of diplomatic relations. RAW. TBA
NANTERRE, FRANCE: Verdict in privacy breach case brought by Francois Hollande's lover Julie Gayet against Closer magazine. RAW. 1800 GMT
PARIS: Campaigning ahead of second round in French local elections winds down. TBC
BASEL, SWITZERLAND: News coverage of World Watch and Jewellery Show. RAW. TBA
+ MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
LATAKIA, SYRIA: Fierce battles rage in Syria's coastal and Turkish border province. RAW. TBC
DOHA: Verdict in the trial of US couple accused of killing their adopted child to harvest her organs. RAW. 1100 GMT
+ NORTH AMERICA
WASHINGTON: The Senate votes on a bill that allows the United States to guarantee one billion dollar loan to Ukraine. RAW. 1800 GMT
UNITED NATIONS: The UN General Assembly considers a draft resolution supporting the territorial integrity of Ukraine and not recognizing a referendum in Crimea. RAW. 1500 GMT
WASHINGTON: US quarterly GDP results released. STOCKSHOTS. 1300 GMT
SAN FRANCISCO: First press conference of new Microsoft head Satya Nadella. RAW. 1900 GMT
+ LATIN AMERICA & CARIBBEAN
RIO DE JANEIRO / SAO PAULO: Monitoring anti-World Cup demonstrations called in some Brazilian cities. RAW. TBA
-- SPORT --
RIO DE JANEIRO : FIFA secretary general Jerome Valcke gives news conference as part of his latest World Cup inspection tour. RAW. TBA
-- FEATURES --
BUDAPEST: Before the economic crisis many Hungarians rushed to take out loans in foreign currencies, especially in Swiss francs. Unable to pay off the loans as the forint crashed, many have seen their homes repossessed and have now found refuge in a controversial new government housing project in the central Hungarian town of Ocsa. PKG. 0400 GMT
ACCRA: An inventor and church leader who calls himself the "Star of Africa" is hoping to transform manufacturing in Ghana with a series of home-grown consumer goods he believes will reduce the country's reliance on foreign imports. PKG. 0400 GMT
Contact:
London desk: +44 207 776 2768
Hong Kong desk: +852 2829 6216
Nicosia desk: +357 22 391 453
Washington desk: +1 202 414 0550
Montevideo desk: +598 2 900 5095 ext 257
For contact via email: afptv-en@afp.com
]]></text></news-item>