<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-YHM1-JBM5-J01W"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Hickory Hills residents in court over fatal propane tank blast;  Management installing individual tanks, but tenants say they still don't feel safe.</title><source>Morning Call (Allentown, Pennsylvania)</source><author>Riley Yates Of The Morning Call</author><text><![CDATA[After an explosion killed one of its residents, a Moore Township mobile home park has been paying to install new individual propane tanks for all of its tenants, with most already hooked up, an attorney for Hickory Hills said Tuesday.
But residents remain worried about their safety, believe the work being done is substandard, and don't trust the park's management to ensure it is up to code, countered James Sutton, a lawyer for the tenants.
The comments came after a Northampton County Court hearing over a lawsuit by the residents seeking to wrest control of the propane system from the company that owns Hickory Hills, Illinois-based Continental Communities.
The suit, prepared by the residents before Sutton was hired, was withdrawn by their attorney after Judge Jennifer Sletvold warned that it had serious flaws. Sutton said he will prepare an amended complaint that better makes the tenants' case, in which they will seek to have an independent engineer appointed to oversee health and safety issues at the park on Route 512.
On the night of Feb. 14, a blast at Hickory Hills killed 65-year-old William D. Neith while he was in his home. State police determined the cause was a liquid propane leak, with Neith's death ruled accidental.
The park had provided propane to its tenants through an underground distribution system similar to a natural gas distribution system. But the system for the 300 homes was operating in violation of state rules, regulators say.
According to the state Department of Labor and Industry and the Pennsylvania Utility Commission, the propane system was not registered with the PUC as required by state law, and inspectors found 18 maintenance and operational violations.
A Labor and Industry Department report compiled after an inspection Feb. 24 said the 30,000-gallon propane tank's fill piping was not properly protected from vehicles, various valves could not be read due to paint coverage, and emergency shut-off valves were not installed to code.
Mark Malkames, Hickory Hills' lawyer, said all but roughly 10 homes are now on individual propane tanks that were installed free of charge. By April 4, he said, the underground distribution system will be decommissioned.
"The long and short of it is that the system that is there is being eliminated," Malkames said.
Sutton said his clients remain "extremely concerned" about the work that has been done. He said they believe it has been jury-rigged by unlicensed workers and isn't up to code. Even after the explosion that killed Neith, residents report there was a smaller blast several days later as repair work was starting, Sutton said.
"They want somebody who knows what they're doing," Sutton said.
In the days before Neith's death, multiple residents had complained of smelling propane in the neighborhood. Employees at the park have said the complaints were investigated, but the source of the odor could not be found.
Malkames said it has not been proven that Hickory Hills' system was to blame. He said the blast could have been caused by an unnoticed leak from piping in Neith's home.
"I'm not trying to minimize what happened, but we don't know what happened," Malkames said.
Sutton said before the blast, management never attempted to contact fire officials or other authorities about the odors the tenants had brought to their attention.
"This wasn't an isolated incident," Sutton said. "What we do know is there was a problem with gas leaking in the community that was known about."
riley.yates@mcall.com
Twitter @riley_yates
610-253-5751
]]></text></news-item>