<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-G6N1-DY9P-N1BN"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Millions paying too much for energy; Ofgem criticises Big Six companies amid allegations of profiteering on power bills</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Emily Gosden</author><text><![CDATA[MILLIONS of households may be paying too much for their gas and electricity, the energy regulator is expected to say today, in a report that is likely to order an investigation into alleged profiteering by the Big Six suppliers.
Ofgem is expected to refer the energy sector to the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) after finding that the leading firms have a case to answer over rising bills. The two-year inquiry could result in the Big Six - British Gas, SSE, Npower, EDF, Scottish Power and E. ON - being broken up.
It comes despite yesterday's pledge by SSE, Britain's second biggest energy supplier, to freeze energy prices until 2016.
Ofgem can refer a sector to the CMA if it finds that "the structure of the market or the conduct of suppliers or customers is harming competition". It is believed to have particular concern over the treatment of customers inherited by the big suppliers after privatisation, who have faced some of the biggest price rises.
Industry sources said they were also braced for questions over whether some of the Bix Six, which control 95 per cent of the market, are stifling competition by selling gas supplied by their own wholesale arms, and whether power generators could be deliberately increasing wholesale prices by withholding supplies.
The Big Six all raised their prices last winter by as much as 11 per cent despite wholesale prices rising by only 1.7 per cent in a year, according to Ofgem. Average dual fuel energy bills rose from £570 in 2003 to £1,267 last year, government figures show. Ofgem began its first competition review into the energy sector in the autumn and will publish its initial findings today.
A referral could see the CMA begin a two-year review in the summer.
Coalition ministers hope the move will "shoot Labour's fox" by scuppering Ed Miliband's plans for a review and reform of the market.
Ed Davey, the Energy Secretary, has suggested that any review may need to consider breaking up Britain's largest energy supplier, British Gas. Labour has accused the Big Six companies of ripping off loyal customers in areas where they enjoyed a monopoly pre-privatisation.
SSE said yesterday that it would unconditionally freeze electricity and gas prices for its five million household customers until 2016. The announcement came six months after the company attacked Labour's pledge to freeze energy prices for 20 months after the general election.
At the time SSE claimed "price freezes ... will lead to unsustainable loss-making retail businesses". Yesterday it said the move was possible by reducing profits, implementing a cost-cutting programme including 500 job losses, and because of the Government's cuts to green levies on bills. It was labelled a "cynical move to pre-empt a competition investigation" by energy price campaigners.
Both Labour and the Government and sought to claim credit for the SSE price freeze yesterday. Mr Miliband told the Commons: "Week after week [Mr Cameron] denounced Labour's call for an energy price freeze to help families and businesses. What is clear is that his argument against the freeze has been totally demolished today." Mr Cameron hit back: "What we have done is reduce the cost of energy charges so that companies are able to cut their bills."
Most major energy suppliers now support a CMA investigation, believing it could deliver a clean bill of health for the industry and halt political interventions.
SSE's chief executive, Alistair Phillips-Davies, told The Daily Telegraph: "If a CMA investigation were to come about, if it were to lead to additional trust and confidence in the market for consumers and deliver greater certainty for investors, we would clearly support it."
He said the energy market was already "highly competitive".
Editorial Comment: Page 23
]]></text></news-item>