<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-XYK1-JBKR-G1FD"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Take male/female choice off ID, transgender girl's mother says</title><source>National Post (f/k/a The Financial Post) (Canada)</source><author>Jen Gerson, National Post, Postmedia News</author><text><![CDATA[Saskatoon mother Fran Forsberg believes schools, libraries and the government shouldn't need to know the gender of her child. In fact, she'd like to see the designation removed from all government-issued ID altogether.
"I don't think it's anybody's business what gender you are," she said on Wednesday. "I have to show a birth certificate when I register at a school. Why do they need to know her gender? We have to show that even to get a library card."
Ms. Forsberg has launched a complaint with the Saskatchewan Human Rights Commission over her six-year-old daughter's birth certificate, because the provincial government has refused to switch the "M" to "F.' Renn was born with male genitalia, but has identified as a female for three years.
Ms. Forsberg said Renn started to express self-destructive behaviour at the age of three, banging her head against the wall repeatedly, and it only let up when she allowed Renn to identify as a female.
"When we allowed her to express herself the way she wanted with her clothing, she was a much happier child, not selfdestructive," the mother said.
Ms. Forsberg said she continually runs into problems. When she enrolled Renn in a local Catholic school, she had a hard time encouraging officials to let the child use the girl's washroom. She fears Renn will face other barriers every time she has to pull out a piece of government-issued ID.
Ms. Forsberg said she wanted Renn's birth certificate changed so the girl wouldn't face confusion or discrimination. The government refused: sex can be changed on ID only after a person has undergone sex reassignment surgery.
Ms. Forsberg noted Ontario has removed the surgery requirement; she filed a complaint with the Human Rights Commission in May, but has heard nothing in almost a year. Ultimately, she said she wants government to stop recording gender altogether.
Demographer David Foot of the University of Toronto said previous decisions to remove race from government documents has made it much more difficult for governments to assess whether those groups are succeeding or failing relative to the rest of the population. Likewise, Mr. Foot said removing gender from birth certificates and the like could prevent governments from implementing policies that could help women and transgender people.
"It's understandable at the individual level, and the individual point of view, but if we want to have good social policies we need to get the information to develop those policies," he said. "It's a bit like removing age. Age discrimination is a concern in the workplace in particular, but on the other hand if we don't have information, we can't develop policies to help combat that sort of discrimination."
Provincial Justice Minister Gordon Wyant said the government will wait for the rights commission to do its work before acting.
"We know that there's been some things that have been done in others provinces. Certainly that will be something that the commission will look at when they're doing their deliberations," he said.
Susan Antosh, CEO of eHealth Saskatchewan, took no position on the issue but noted it's important medically to be able to quickly identify a person's sex. For example, women and men may present different symptoms during a heart attack. Sex is also a "primary attribute used for identification purposes," Ms. Antosh said.
David Arnot, chief commissioner of the province's human rights commission, said he was not able to comment specifically on Ms. Forsberg's complaint.
"I can say a few things: One, we recognize the issues faced by the trans community and we're sympathetic to the vulnerabilities that that group [has]. We know that there's discrimination against trans-people in Saskatchewan and we're very confident that the human rights code in its current form protects trans-people."
The commission has taken three complaints over the last two years involving allegations of discrimination against transgender people, he said.
Ms. Forsberg said she and her family have come under heavy criticism. Call-in shows have blasted her parenting and called Renn an "it."
"I don't care about me, but when they attack a child like that, it's such cowardice," she said.
Renn's older brother, Tana, is also "gender fluid," Ms. Forsberg said.
"Tana is not a transgender child, Tana is what we call two-spirited. He's in touch with his male and female side," she said.
Ms. Forsberg said gender is much more fluid than most people believe, and some children live along a spectrum.
"My children don't have an issue.
Society has an issue. People need to educate themselves," she said.
jgerson@nationalpost.com Twitter.com/jengerson
]]></text></news-item>