<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-3Y51-DYN6-W33H"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>AP Weekly News Calendar</title><source>Associated Press International</source><author>The Associated Press</author><text><![CDATA[?Thursday, March 27:
MANILA, Philippines - The Philippines and the country's largest Muslim rebel group end a decades-long war by signing a peace deal that aims to turn them into allies to confront the deep poverty, despair and lawlessness that continue to breed other Islamic radicals in the resource-rich south.
NEW DELHI - India is formally declared polio-free. The milestone means that the World Health Organization now considers the entire southeast Asia region, home to a quarter of the world's population, to be free of the disease.
ROME - U.S. President Barack Obama visits.
THE HAGUE, Netherlands - Former youth leader Charles Ble Goude makes his first appearance at the International Criminal Court where he faces crimes against humanity charges linked to deadly postelection violence in Ivory Coast. 1100 GMT.
BERLIN - Canadian Prime Minister Stephen Harper meets German Chancellor Angela Merkel. News conference at about 1210 GMT.
WASHINGTON - House Resources Committee hearing on advances in earthquake science.
NEW YORK - Amnesty International releases its annual roundup of death penalty trends around the world, finding executions around the world rose almost 15 percent in 2013 and the United States was among the five countries putting the most people to death.
PARIS - Chinese President Xi Jinping visits France, holding business and diplomatic meetings as France tries to expand business in China but keep its own companies from sending too many jobs abroad. Also attending special opera at Versailles with French President Francois Hollande. 1600 GMT.
FRANKFURT, Germany - Germany's main public-sector union has called ground workers at Frankfurt, Munich and other major German airports out on strike to raise pressure in a pay dispute.
WASHINGTON - Senate Health, Education, Labor and Pensions Committee hearing on the federal student loan program.
STOCKHOLM - Fashion retailer H&M releases Q1 results.
WASHINGTON - Labor Department releases weekly jobless claims, 8:30 a.m. (1230 GMT); Commerce Department releases fourth-quarter gross domestic product, 8:30 a.m. (1230 GMT); Freddie Mac, the mortgage company, releases weekly mortgage rates, 10 a.m. (1400 GMT); National Association of Realtors releases pending home sales index for February, 10 a.m. (1400 GMT).
NEW YORK - Fashion retailer H&M reports quarterly results.
?Friday, March 28:
SARAJEVO, Bosnia-Herzegovina - British, Austrian, Croatian and Hungarian foreign ministers are taking part in a conference on wartime sexual violence.
BERLIN - Chinese President Xi Jinping meets with German Chancellor Angela Merkel, delivers speech to foreign policy think tank in the evening. Joint news conference with Xi and Merkel after 1515 GMT. Xi think tank speech scheduled for 1630-1730 GMT.
NEW YORK - U.N. Security Council consults on the Syrian civil war.
TALLINN, Estonia - Members of Russian punk collective Pussy Riot attend opening seminar of the annual Tallinn Music Week. The band, including two of its most vocal members Nadezhda Tolokonnikova and Maria Alyokhina, join discussion forum at 0900 GMT.
WASHINGTON - Commerce Department releases personal income and spending for February, 8:30 a.m. (1230 GMT).
TORONTO - Blackberry Ltd. reports quarterly results.
?Saturday, March 29:
BRATISLAVA, Slovakia - Prime Minister Robert Fico faces businessman-turned philanthropist Andrej Kiska in a runoff ballot to become Slovakia's next president.
HAVANA - Cuba holds an extraordinary session of parliament to consider a new law that seeks to rewrite the rules governing foreign investment and attract more of it.
LONDON - The first same-sex marriages are held in England and Wales, capping a long - but in many ways remarkably rapid - journey from official discrimination to marriage equality for gay people in Britain.
CURITIBA, Brazil - The delayed Arena da Baixada stadium in the southern Brazilian city of Curitiba is scheduled to be inaugurated in front of limited attendance.
HAVANA - A semiprofessional team of Cuban boxers is set to square off against a U.S. squad in Miami, the hotbed of the Cuban exile community. It's the first time in 19 years that the Cold War rivals, who don't have full diplomatic relations, face each other in the sport.
?Sunday, March 30:
PARIS - Voters across France choose mayors and city councilors in the second round of nationwide municipal elections. Two women are vying to run Paris City Hall, in a first, and far right candidates are hoping for a strong showing in the local votes amid deep disillusionment with President Francois Hollande's Socialist leadership.
LONDON - Archaeologists reveal the results of tests on 25 skeletons found in a "plague pit" uncovered by work on the Crossrail train line in London. They are thought to be victims of the Black Death that wiped out half the city's population in the 14th century.
?Monday, March 31:
THE HAGUE, Netherlands - The United Nations' highest court rules on Australia's appeal against the legality of Japan's annual whale hunt. 1200 GMT.
VIENNA - Israeli President Shimon Peres talks to the media during his state visit to Austria. 1100 GMT.
BRUSSELS - Inflation figures for the eurozone and wider EU are released by Eurostat, the statistics agency. Markets will be monitoring for any further drop in inflation that might put more pressure on the European Central Bank to loosen its monetary policy. 1000 GMT.
PARIS - France's national statistics agency posts definitive GDP data for the last quarter of 2013. 0900 GMT.
SAO PAULO - Sao Paulo Fashion Week. Through April 4.
TOKYO - Japan economic data for February released.
?Tuesday, April 1:
BERLIN - Germany's Federal Labor Agency releases March unemployment figures for Europe's biggest economy.
BRUSSELS - Unemployment is expected to remain near a record high for the eurozone when the Eurostat agency releases its latest estimates on Tuesday.
TOKYO - Japan's sales tax rises to 8 percent from previous 5 percent in a hike needed to help narrow the country's huge public debt but risky for the economic recovery.
?Wednesday, April 2:
TOKYO - Japan economic outlook from Bank of Japan.
]]></text></news-item>