<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-4BK1-DXY3-01P2"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Faruqi &amp; Faruqi, LLP Investigates The Proposed Sale of the Company to Media General Inc.; Faruqi &amp; Faruqi, LLP, a leading national securities firm headquartered in New York City, is investigating the Board of Directors of LIN Media LLC</title><source>Business Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Juan E. Monteverde , a partner at Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP , a leading national securities firm headquartered in New York City, investigates a possible challenge of the Board of Directors of LIN Media LLC ("LIN" or the "Company") (NYSE:LIN) actions as they relate to their recommendation and agreement of the sale of the Company to Media General Inc. (MEG) for approximately $1.6 billion, or $2.6 billion including debt of $968 million. The Company's stockholders are offered to receive a mixed of stock or cash worth $27.82, or 1.5762 shares of the Media General Inc. for each share of LIN common stock they own. A complaint has been filed against the Company.
Click here for more information: www.faruqilaw.com/LIN . There is no cost or obligation to you.
The investigation focuses on whether LIN's Board of Directors breached their fiduciary duties to the Company's stockholders by failing to conduct a fair sales process and whether and by how much this proposed transaction undervalues the Company to the detriment of LIN's shareholders.
Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP is a national law firm which represents investors and individuals in class action litigation. The firm is focused on providing exemplary legal services in complex litigation in the areas of securities, shareholder, antitrust and consumer litigation, throughout all phases of litigation. The firm has an experienced trial team which has achieved significant victories on behalf of the firm's clients. To keep track of the latest securities litigation news, follow us on Twitter at www.twitter.com/MergerActivity or on Facebook at www.facebook.com/FaruqiLaw .
If you own common stock in LIN and wish to obtain additional information and protect your investments free of charge, please visit us at www.faruqilaw.com/LIN or contact Juan E. Monteverde, Esq. either via e-mail at jmonteverde@faruqilaw.com or by telephone at (877) 247-4292 or (212) 983-9330.
Attorney Advertising. (C) 2014 Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP. The law firm responsible for this advertisement is Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP ( www.faruqilaw.com ). Prior results do not guarantee or predict a similar outcome with respect to any future matter. We are happy to discuss your particular case.
http://www.businesswire.com
]]></text></news-item>