<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-3WV1-DY91-H0SD"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Oversight board calls U.S. nuke dump incidents "near misses"</title><source>Xinhua General News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[An independent oversight agency criticized the safety procedures of a nuclear waste plant in the U.S. state of New Mexico where a radiation leak contaminated 17 workers and a truck fire prompted evacuations, calling the incidents "near misses," U.S. media reported Tuesday.
Defense Nuclear Facilities Safety Board Chairman Peter Winokur made the assessments in a letter sent to New Mexico Senators Tom Udall and Martin Heinrich, local TV KRQE reported.
Winokur said in the letter the Feb. 5 underground truck fire at the Waste Isolation Pilot Plant was "preventable," and that the plant' s initial response to a radiation release which happened nine days later was "unsatisfactory."
He said neither the contractors nor the federal workers were prepared for the emergencies, even calling the events "near misses." Winokur went on to say emergency notifications were not done like they should have been. He also found other faults with the plant' s safety procedures.
The two Senators requested the assessment from Winokur, who is head of the independent federal agency charged with overseeing public health and safety issues at the Department of Energy's defense-related nuclear facilities.
Operators of the country' s only underground nuclear dump has been under mounting critiques as the facility appeared to face an open-ended closure, which forced Los Alamos National Laboratory, a nuclear weapons manufacturing facility in New Mexico which used to store its refuse at the repository, to relocate its radioactive waste to Texas.
The U.S. Department of Energy said employees with the WIPP have undergone training simulations before re-entry into the underground dump, but didn' t give out a detailed timetable.
The cause of the radiation leak still remains unknown. A truck fire was reported at the underground site on Feb. 5 and prompted evacuations, but officials said the fire was in a different part of the site and did not seem related to the leak.
The repository stores "transuranic waste" leftover from nuclear weapons research and testing from the nation's past defense activities, according to the Energy Department website. The waste includes clothing, tools, rags and other debris contaminated with radioactive elements, largely plutonium.
]]></text></news-item>