<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-4211-DXKH-N34D"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Progressive lifts 2.0%</title><source>Global Round Up - Bonds</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[BONDS
Progressive Corp (N:PGR.GG) bond lifted US$2.18 (or 2.0%) from its last traded date of September 27, 2013 to close at US$110.0.
ISSUE DETAILS
COUPON & DATES
RELATIVE VALUATION INDICATORS [RVI] TECHNICALS- The price dropped 3.3% in the last week. % Discount to high: progressive is at a discount of 6.0% to its 12-month high of US$116.99 traded on 03 Jun, 2013. - The present value of US$1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in Progressive is US$984, for a capital loss of US$16. The total return to investors for 1 year is -1.6%.

PRICE UPTREND (or YIELD DOWNTREND)- In the global market of 1,863 bonds traded today, the bond's relative price strength percentile is rising at 69 for 6 months, 72 for 3 months and 85 for 1 month. Rises to Falls in the past month: the number of rises outnumbered falls 7:2 or 3.5:1. The bond traded in 9 of the 20 trading days.
CREDIT RATING SUMMARY
DESCRIPTIONThe Progressive Corporation is an insurance holding company. Its insurance subsidiaries provide personal and commercial automobile insurance, and other specialty property-casualty insurance and related services throughout the United States. The Company's Personal Lines segment writes insurance for private passenger automobiles and recreational and other vehicles. The Commercial Auto segment business writes primary liability and physical damage insurance for automobiles and trucks owned by small businesses. The Company's other indemnity businesses primarily include writing professional liability insurance for community banks, principally directors and officers liability insurance. Its service businesses include providing insurance-related services, primarily for the commercial auto insurance procedures/plans (CAIP).
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 5 company announcements are:March 20: Progressive Snapshot Reaches 10 Billion Mile Mark[News Story] MAYFIELD VILLAGE, Ohio-- Progressive(Registered) Insurancehas collected over 10 billion miles of driving data with Snapshot(Registered), its Pay As You Dr.ve(Registered) program, since introducing its first wireless device in January 2008. Progressive leads the usage-based insurance (UBI) industry with the most miles collected and two million vehicles that have participated in the program.
March 17: Progressive® Insurance and GOOD Launch Search for Everyday Progress Makers[News Story] The Progress is GOOD Challenge will shine a light on one innovative individualMAYFIELD VILLAGE, Ohio-- Often times, progress-makers go unnoticed, moving the world forward with little fanfare or recognition. Progressive(Registered) Insurance and GOOD are looking to change that for one forward-thinking individual. The Progress is GOOD Challenge, which will accept entries from March 17, 2014 at 12:00 p.m.
February 20: Progressive Announces Investor Relations Conference Call[News Story] MAYFIELD VILLAGE, OHIO - February 20, 2014 - As previously announced, The Progressive Corporation will host a one-hour conference call on Friday, February 28, 2014, beginning at 9:00 a.m. eastern time. On February 26, 2014, Progressive expects to file its Annual Report on Form 10-K with the Securities and Exchange Commission and post its Shareholders' Report, including the Letter to Shareholders from Glenn Renwick, President and CEO, to its website at www.progressive.com/annualreport.
December 20: A.M. Best Affirms Ratings of The Progressive Corporation and Its SubsidiariesOLDWICK, N.J.-- A.M. Best Co. has affirmed the financial strength rating (FSR) of A+ (Superior) and issuer credit ratings (ICR) of "aa" of the members of Progressive Agency Pool,Progressive Direct Pooland ProgressiveCommercial Auto Group (collectively known as Progressive). A.M. Best also has affirmed the FSR of A (Excellent) and ICR of "a+" of National Continental Insurance Company.
December 11: Progressive Receives Perfect Score in 2014 Human Rights Campaign's Corporate Equality Index[News Story] Foundation's twelfth annual scorecard recognizes top companies for LGBT workplace equalityMAYFIELD VILLAGE, Ohio-- Progressive(Registered) Insurance has earned a 100 percent score in the 2014 Corporate Equality Index (CEI). This was the fifth time Progressive scored 100 percent on the survey. The CEI is a national benchmarking survey and report on corporate policies and practices related to LGBT workplace equality, administered by the Human Rights Campaign Foundation."Progressive is committed to building a diverse workforce and inclusive culture," said John Hoppes, Progressive's National Recruiting Director.
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>