<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-M841-DXDT-651Y"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Wrexham: Controversial gas drilling test plans unlikely to impact underground mines; Plans to test drill for coal bed gas on land near Borras look set for approval despite concerns from councillors</title><source>dailypost.co.uk</source><author>By Steve Bagnall</author><text><![CDATA[Controversial plans to test drill for  underground gas would be "highly unlikely" to impact a vast network of  mines a report said.
GP Energy Ltd has submitted proposals to test drill for coal bed gas on  land near Commonwood Farm, Borras,  Wrexham, which have been recommended for the go-ahead.
They were deferred at a previous  planning meeting after councillors expressed concerns whether they would  impact the area's vast network of underground mines.
Councillors were also worried it  could affect the tombs of the hundreds  that died in the 1934 Gresford Mining  Disaster.
But after inquiries from Wrexham  council planners with the Coal Authority, a report said the borehole  would be more than 1km from the  nearest point of the abandoned mine  workings.
A report by Wrexham council's head  of community and wellbeing,  Lawrence Isted, said: "Since the borehole is only to be drilled vertically with  no laterals following the coal seam  horizons, the Coal Authority have confirmed that the proposed borehole is  highly unlikely to impact in any way  with the Gresford mine workings."
Councillors have also expressed concerns, if this application is granted, it  could lead to mass drilling to get gas out  across a large area of Wrexham.
Other concerns included its impact  on the environment, the pollution of  water courses with toxic chemicals,  greenhouse gases being emitted into  the air, subsidence and sink holes appearing.
Council planning chiefs have insisted the application should be judged  on its merits alone and not on the basis  of any future applications.
The proposals will be discussed by  councillors at a Wrexham council planning committee meeting on Monday  evening.
Protestor Luke Ashley said: "The fear  is, it is not this application, but the ones  that come after to drill for gas.
"Once they get a foot in the door, it is  hard to get rid of them and there are  also major concerns over radioactive  materials that get pumped into the  ground. If this gets the go-ahead there  will be protests."
Underground gas drilling has been shrouded in controversy across the world.
One process is called fracking where water, sand and chemicals are injected into the rock at high pressure to allow gas to flow out to the head of a well.
Some countries have banned it, including France, and others have halted the technique for further information on its affects, such as Germany.
GP Energy had said they would prefer to use a different method of extraction - horizontal wells, where water is actually pumped out of the coal to depressurise the seam and remove the gas through gallons of water.
This month Happy Monday Dancer Mark Berry, better known as 'Bez', joined other anti-fracking campaigners at Marsh Lane, Farndon, just across the border from Holt, where a controversial test drill is going ahead.
]]></text></news-item>