<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-6661-JCRR-013V"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Crown Equity Holdings and Zaman &amp; Co. File Claim Against EQCO2, Inc.</title><source>Professional Services Close-Up</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Crown Equity Holdings, Inc. announced that in conjunction with Zaman & Co., and Mike Zaman; an individual, has filed a lawsuit in the Superior Court of the State of California, County of Los Angeles - West District against EQCO2, Inc. (F/K/A Cleantech Transit, Inc.), Discovery Carbon Environmental Securities Corp.; William Barnwell, an individual; Arnold F. Sock, an individual; Shad Sullivan, an individual; ROE Individuals 1-10 and DOE Entities I-X, inclusive.
According to a release, the complaint is for; Breach of Contact (the Exchange Agreement); Breach of Implied Covenant of Good Faith & Fair Dealing; Fraud; Constructive Fraud; Breach of Fiduciary Duty; Breach of Duty of Loyalty; Negligent Misrepresentation; Declaratory Relief; Conversion; Unjust Enrichment; Compelling Annual Shareholder Meeting; and Violation of Business & Professions Code Section 17200.
The company noted that in its complaint, the plaintiffs seek a jury trial.
Further, in addition to the above filing, a Temporary Restraining Order and Order To Show Cause Re: Preliminary Restraining Order was also filed, which the Judge ordered that a Temporary Restraining Order be issued restraining and enjoining all Defendants, their officers, directors, successor in interest, agents, employees, attorneys in fact, and all persons acting in concert or participating with them, or any of them.
Crown Equity Holdings Inc., together with its digital network of Websites, offers advertising branding and marketing services as a worldwide online multi-media publisher.
More information:
crownequityholdings.com/Crown_Equity_VS_Billy_Barnwell_EQCO2_TRO_Superior_Court.pdf
www.crownequityholdings.com/Crown_Equity_Holdings_Inc_ percent20vs_EQCO2_Inc_Cal.pdf
www.crownequityholdings.com/.
((Comments on this story may be sent to newsdesk@closeupmedia.com))
]]></text></news-item>