<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-F5C1-DY37-G027"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>DEC SEEKS PORT OIL DETAILS</title><source>The Times-Union (Albany, NY)</source><author>BRIAN NEARING</author><text><![CDATA[Albany
The path ahead for a proposed crude oil terminal expansion at the Port of Albany got steeper Tuesday when the state demanded answers to questions about fire risk, evacuation plans, spill response and insurance coverage for accidents.
A letter from the state Department of Environmental Conservation posed more than two dozen questions to Global Companies, which wants permission to heat crude oil from rail cars to make it easier to ship down the Hudson River. DEC also warned it could rescind a November ruling that the project would have no negative impact on the environment -- which could result in a detailed review.
A second DEC letter to Global raised similar questions over the company's planned expansion of its terminal on the Hudson in New Windsor, Orange County, to accept oil from rail cars for transfer onto river transport vessels.
DEC appealed in a third letter to the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency to strengthen its decades-old, land-based oil spill response plan for the state.
"DEC will make no final determination until we receive more information about (Global's) operations and only after the impacted communities are provided meaningful opportunities to learn about and comment on the proposals," DEC spokeswoman Emily DeSantis said.
Albany's port has become a major shipping route for crude oil moving eastward in mile-long trains from the Bakken fields of North Dakota. Waltham, Mass.-based Global and Buckeye Partners of Houston have state permission to handle 2.8 billion gallons a year of crude oil at the port.
"As we always have, we will be responsive and provide the information," according to a statement from the company. To address public concerns, the company has created a website, mailed statements to neighbors and scheduled community meetings.
In his letter to Global, DEC Regional Permit Administrator William Clark said DEC wants further evidence that Global is taking "measures to prevent and respond to a potential release of crude oil," as well as planning to protect and evacuate people in the event of a "large-scale disaster" at the port.
DEC also is extending a public comment period on an air pollution permit required for the crude heating project by two months -- through June 2 -- according to Clark's letter. This is the second time it was extended; the permit has drawn considerable neighborhood concern.
Bakken crude is highly flammable, and the aging DOT-111 tanker cars predominantly used to carry it have proved to be prone to rupturing in derailments. There have been four such derailments in New York since last year. None involved explosions or spills. Blasts from derailments have occurred in Quebec, where 47 people died last year, and in Alabama and North Dakota.
Tuesday, EPA spokeswoman Mary Mears said it will review DEC's request to revisit land-based oil spill planning. "We are actively enhancing our prevention and response efforts including conducting inspections of oil storage facilities," Mears said.
Scenic Hudson President Ned Sullivan praised DEC, saying a surge of crude shipments could "subject Albany, the Hudson River and communities and coastal resources along the route of tanker ship and rail transport to devastating spills and accidents." He urged DEC Commissioner Joe Martens to revoke its earlier finding on Global's crude heating project and to require a full environmental review of the company's Orange County proposal.
In 2012, when the Times Union reported on the Hudson oil spill plan in the wake of the oil tanker Stena Primorsk grounding on its maiden voyage from the port, the Coast Guard, which updated its plan in 2011, said there was no need to revisit the issue. DEC agreed at the time.
Last week, Global modified its plans at the port to put oil-heating equipment, meant to make crude easier to pump out of rail tankers into land storage tanks, into an existing building rather than a new structure. Such a step could limit jurisdiction by the Albany Planning Board, which has been directed by Mayor Kathy Sheehan to "supersede" DEC authority.
Tuesday, Global held a meeting at an Albany hotel meant to inform people living around the port on the project, but aside from environmental groups opposed to the project no members of the public showed up. Monday night, a similar meeting drew about a dozen people.
Last month, DEC ordered Global to hold such meetings as part of an outreach plan under state guidelines meant to ensure "environmental justice" for predominantly poor and minority communities, like the South End that encompasses the port.
"People want to know how they are going to be safe if something goes wrong," said Common Council President Carolyn McLaughlin, who attended Monday's meeting. "Global's answer is that 'we have a plan,' but then they could not give any details on the what the plan is."
Local media outlets were not informed of the meetings. Joan Gerhardt, a Global spokeswoman, said the firm did not want residents to be intimidated.
County Legislator Lucille McKnight, who represents the South End, criticized Global for shifting the location of the Monday meeting at the last minute to "make it more difficult for people to participate."
McKnight called Global "bullies ... who feel they don't have to take the people in the community seriously. I welcome having the media at all these meetings, which should be open to the press, open to all in the community."
Albany County Executive Dan McCoy, who has declared a county moratorium on the crude heating project based on county health law, called the Global meetings "lip service" meant to give the illusion of community input. He said officials "sidestepped" questions on such critical issues as advance evacuation planning in the event of a spill-induced conflagration.
Global has already threatened to sue over the moratorium, claiming the county lacks jurisdiction.
Tuesday, city Conservative Party Chairman Joe Sullivan said objections by McCoy and Sheehan to crude oil trains were politically motivated, and called for a refinery to be built in the port to process crude. "Residents of the city and Capital District will benefit from high-paying jobs, and lower costs for gasoline and home heating oil," he said.
bnearing@timesunion.com - 518-454-5094 - @Bnearing10

]]></text></news-item>