<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-XYK1-JBKR-R1H3"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Taseko learned of extra meetings through Facebook; Miner seeks new review of B.C. project</title><source>National Post's Financial Post &amp; FP Investing (Canada)</source><author>Peter Koven, Financial Post</author><text><![CDATA[Taseko Mines Ltd. is taking the federal government to court for the second time in four months, claiming its rejection of the New Prosperity project was based on a highly unfair process that included inappropriate meetings with opponents of the mine that it only learned about through Facebook.
The Vancouver-based miner said these meetings were documented in Facebook posts by a First Nations chief. It claims the government declined to talk about them or let Taseko respond to what was discussed.
Taseko filed an application for judicial review on Wednesday to try to force the government to reconsider New Prosperity, based on its belief Ottawa did not run a fair process. It launched a separate judicial review in federal court in December, claiming there was a key technical error in a review of the B.C. project that influenced Ottawa's decision. "The process was flawed," said Brian Battison, Taseko's vice-president, corporate affairs. "The findings were wrong and the decision to deny the project was certainly wrong. We expect to prove that in court."
The $1.5-billion New Prosperity has been controversial from the start.
The government of British Columbia approved the mine in 2010, but Ottawa blocked it later that year, citing concerns about environmental damage due to Taseko's plan to drain nearby Fish Lake. Taseko came up with a new plan that would save Fish Lake at an additional cost of $300-million. Ottawa blocked that proposal last month after a federal panel warned of "significant adverse environmental effects" from the mine. Stephen Harper called the panel report "damning" at a conference earlier this month.
Last summer, the Canadian Environmental Assessment Agency (CEAA) held hearings around Taseko's updated mine plan for New Prosperity. Stakeholders around the project made numerous submissions.
Taseko alleges that there were further meetings between government officials and opponents of New Prosperity that took place far after those hearings ended, during a critical period in which the government was reviewing the mine. The company claims that beginning in October, there were discussions between Tsilhqot'in National Government (a First Nations group fiercely opposed to New Prosperity) and high-level federal officials, including environment minister Leona Aglukkaq. These were documented on the Facebook page of Chief Roger William.
Taseko said that when it asked the government about them, it was given no opportunity to respond to what was discussed.
The company "had a legitimate expectation that if third-party representations were made to the minister or her staff and advisors after the close of panel hearings, then the minister would advise Taseko of those submissions and afford Taseko the opportunity to make response submissions," the miner said in the complaint.
Taseko also claims that when it responded to the federal panel's concerns around New Prosperity, the CEAA did not post the comments on its registry. The company found this baffling, as a vast number of other comments were posted. It is also upset about lack of detail from Ottawa when it made its decision to reject the mine.
While Taseko's second judicial review request is focused on the alleged unfairness of the process, the first one is built around its view that the federal review was fatally flawed. The company believes the only reason the panel found "significant adverse environmental effects" is that it missed Taseko's plan to build a thick liner in its tailings pond that would prevent seepage.
That case should be decided this year.
pkoven@nationalpost.com
]]></text></news-item>