<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV5-F2H1-DY2M-W0C9"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Airline Buckles to Pressure From PETA on Monkey Cargo</title><source>The New York Times Blogs(Sinosphere)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[After years of protests by animal rights crusaders, a Chinese airline has said it will no longer transport monkeys and other primates used for laboratory experiments.
China Southern Airlines, a state-owned carrier, has decided to "stop transporting live primates for laboratory experiments on all flights," Chen Qiuhua, the airline's chief manager of special cargo transportation, told the animal welfare organization People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals.
The decision was effective immediately, Mr. Chen wrote in an email to PETA on Friday. "We truly request PETA to stop protests against China Southern Airlines," it said.
PETA was quick to celebrate.
"PETA is thrilled that China Southern Airlines has finally recognized that cruelty shouldn't fly," Justin Goodman, director of PETA's Laboratory Investigations Department, said in a statement.
Helen Han, the airline's cargo manager at O'Hare International Airport in Chicago, where the animals were delivered to the United States, confirmed on Wednesday that the shipments had been terminated.
For years PETA has campaigned aggressively against international airlines transporting monkeys and other primates for use in laboratory experiments. Protesters in chimpanzee costumes have startled travelers at airports in North America and Asia.
About four months ago, PETA purchased shares of China Southern Airlines so its representatives could attend shareholder meetings and directly lobby company executives, said the organization's laboratory campaigns manager, Jeremy Beckham, in a telephone interview. However, China Southern announced its policy change before PETA had a chance to apply its shareholder's leverage on the company.
Putting pressure on airlines is an effective tactic because it makes it harder and more expensive for laboratories to obtain experimental animals, Mr. Beckham said.
"Laboratories in the States and the E.U. want to get their hands on monkeys who were bred in the squalid monkey factory farms in China and Vietnam," he said. If PETA can close off China, he said, "it may create an incentive" for the laboratories to find alternatives to conducting experiments on live animals because they won't be able to "get their hands on as many cheap monkeys."
The use of animals in laboratories is unlikely to end soon in China, however.
"To say animal testing is totally unnecessary is just not telling the whole story," said Huang Ren, director of the Guangdong Laboratory Animals Monitoring Institute, a government-run inspector of the breeding and use of laboratory animals in Guangdong Province. "We don't really have an alternative to testing on nonhuman primates for the purpose of gaining new knowledge and advancing human health."
"If we had enough data to build computer models," he said, "we might be able to simulate functions that we now observe in animals. But we are not there yet, and even when we are, we still have to take virtual studies into the physical world for testing. Do you want to test them on humans or on animals first?"
The treatment of experimental animals in China is supervised by the Ministry of Science and Technology. A national regulation revised in 2011 by the State Council, China's cabinet, requires that animals be supplied with clean food and water, and it forbids "abusive treatment."
Chinese public opinion is divided over testing on live animals, as well as on PETA's tactics. On Guokr.com, a Chinese chatroom frequented by scientists, some commenters praised PETA's efforts to promote animal welfare, but more dismissed it as an "extremist animal protection organization" and accused it of putting the well-being of animals before that of humans.
Mr. Beckham acknowledged that not everyone supported PETA's campaign to stop animal testing. "Our purpose is not to make enemies," he said. Still, "if we have to make enemies to achieve goals that result in less animal suffering and less animal exploitation, then we will do that."
Animal testing is still mandatory for any cosmetics or body-care products manufactured or marketed in China. However, the China Food and Drug Administration has said it plans to drop this requirement for domestic brands of shampoo, soap and certain skin products starting in June, apparently heeding calls to end unnecessary cruelty to animals. Foreign brands sold in China will still have to undergo testing on animals.
China Southern's decision to give up the primate transport business leaves Air France as the last major airline on PETA's list, and Mr. Beckham offered a blunt warning.
"We are doubling down on Air France," he said. "We will be unprecedented. If I was Air France right now, I would be very worried."
Grandmothers Call for Protection of Children After Kindergartners Are Fed DrugsStranded Travelers Start 'Riot' at AirportRegulations Will Increase Commercialization of Wild Animals, Experts SayQ. & A.: Rory Medcalf on the Meaning of China's Air Defense ZoneChina Eases Rules on the Coveted Pilot's License
]]></text></news-item>