<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-FYC1-JC86-C02B"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Liberia; U.S. Hits Liberia Hard Again</title><source>Africa News</source><author>The New Dawn (Monrovia)</author><text><![CDATA[The United States Ambassador to Liberia, Deborah Malac says there is slow progress on the development side here because incompetent officials and workers used Liberia's resources perhaps in the past, not for the country's benefit, but for their own benefit.
"So we hear from the young people when I go and talk to them, that they are concerned about issues like corruption and mismanagement. And simply in some cases, people fail to do their jobs for whatever reason; and you the young people of Liberia are resolute not to follow to this stride, because you can see that it does not contribute positively to the growth of the country, and what we need is energy and dedication," she told graduates of the President's Young Professional Program Wednesday.
Launched by President Ellen Johnson-Sirleaf in 2009, the President's Young Professionals Program or PYPP is said to be one of Liberia's most competitive programs for leadership in civil service.
Delivering the keynote address, at the C. Cecil Dennis Auditorium at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, the US envoy said government workers have the training and the skills they need, but yet they are not committed to their jobs or they are probably corrupt.
But she told the PYPP Class Three graduates that they came into the program, understanding that they have something to offer to help built Liberia, telling them "You are an answer... to that capacity challenge. And you as I said before have a vital role to play."
Ambassador Malac said the graduates made it through the process because they are some of the best graduates of Liberia's colleges and universities, reminding them that their academic achievements were exactly what Liberia needs to raise the overall level levels of professionalism as civil servants.
"Finally you have also seen the ... of the incompetent officials and workers who have used Liberia's resources perhaps in the past, not for the benefit of the country but for their own benefit. As a result, we have slow progress on the development side," she concluded.
Meanwhile, President Sirleaf told the graduates that she expects that they be absorbed by the civil service, having congratulated them for their professionalism.
But late at the commissioning of four government officials of integrity institutions here also graced by diplomats and the US Ambassador Malac, President Sirleaf said in 2006, her administration pledged and dedicated itself to fight corruption despite the debt and pervasiveness and systemic problems here.
In her statement before commissioning Liberia's new Auditor General Yusador S. Gaye and her Deputy Foday G. Kiazolu; Independent National Human Rights Commission Chair Gladys Johnson and Liberia Anti Corruption Commission Chair James N. Verdier, President Sirleaf argued that her government's stance to take on corruption fight was not because it is politically correct, but because it is a fight which time has come.
Further, she said her government took on the fight not because it is easy, but because it is necessary, adding that quite simply, her government took on the fight because the Liberian society can no longer continue to accept the ... manifestation of corruption as a normal way of doing business.
She said the fight also meant that each citizen's duty owed to the state would be defined, while importantly also, the fight requires government to shift the moral compass of the society requiring everyone.
She said government knows that the progress it seeks may be gradual and in some instances the results would seem slow in coming as efforts would be initially resisted and politically criticisms would be loud, her government remains firm in its resolve. Finally President Sirleaf vowed that in the fight against corruption, there is no turning back in her administration.
]]></text></news-item>