<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-83X1-F0NV-F1W6"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Mankato woman pleads guilty to human trafficking; Former nails shop owner forced woman to work at Pho Saigon</title><source>The Free Press (Mankato, Minnesota)</source><author>The Free Press, THE MANKATO FREE PRESS</author><text><![CDATA[MANKATO - A Mankato woman pleaded guilty to forced labor trafficking for smuggling a woman into the country and forcing her to work in her son's Pho Saigon restaurant.
Tieu Tran, 59, pleaded guilty Tuesday to one count of forced labor trafficking in the U.S. District Court for the District of Minnesota, the Justice Department announced Wednesday. Tran is the former owner and manager of Nails By Jordan in Mankato.
According to evidence, in 2008 Tran recruited a woman from Vietnam and convinced her to come to the U.S. under "false promises" of gaining a high-paying job and legal immigration status.
The Justice Department said that Tran smuggled the victim and two other Vietnamese nationals across the U.S.-Mexico border and "imposed a significant debt" on the victim and then forced the victim to work at Tran's son restaurant, Pho Saigon, in Mankato to pay off the debt.
The owner of Pho Saigon reached Wednesday by The Free Press declined to comment on the case.
During the plea hearing, Tran admitted to making the victim work long hours using a "scheme, plan and pattern of non-violent coercion," the Justice Department said.
Tran faces a maximum sentence of 20 years in prison and a $250,000 fine. Tran agreed to remove all debts owed by the victim as part of the plea agreement, Similar debts on seven others suspected to be under the same circumstances were also to be dismissed as part of the plea agreement.
The case was investigated by the FBI.
The Justice Department said Tran "used manipulation of debts, isolation and verbal intimidation to hold the victim in fear, knowing that the victim was without legal status and money, did not have the ability to speak English, feared losing her family home in Vietnam to creditors and had nowhere else to turn for subsistence."
"This defendant preyed on vulnerable victims and exploited them for her profit," Acting Assistant Attorney General Jocelyn Samuels for the Civil Rights Division, said in a statement.
The case is being prosecuted by Attorney William Nolan of the Justice Department's Civil Rights Division Human Trafficking Prosecution Unit and Assistant U.S. Attorney for Minnesota David Steinkamp.
]]></text></news-item>