<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-XPC1-JBF5-T2VJ"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>'IT FAILURE' CAUSED MET FILES LOSS</title><source>Regional Press Releases: London</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A ``catastrophic'' IT failure was to blame for the loss of files on police corruption within the Metropolitan Police, the force's deputy commissioner has said.
Craig Mackey said files from an anti-corruption intelligence exercise called Operation Othona were shredded after they were transferred on to an electronic database which ``corrupted and collapsed'' in 2005.
The Met deputy was appearing before the London Assembly's Police and Crime Committee after revelations about the destruction of police corruption files were published in Mark Ellison QC's damning review of the Stephen Lawrence investigation.
Mr Mackey told the committee at London's City Hall that a retired member of the Directorate of Professional Standards (DPS) revealed in an interview last month that Operation Othona files from 1994 were entered on to a database and the original documents were destroyed.
He said the force was investigating whether all the Operation Othona files were transferred to the database which ``suffered a catastrophic failure in 2005''.
``Some of the intelligence may still exist,'' Mr Mackey said.
He told the committee that eight people within Scotland Yard knew about Operation Othona when it launched in 1994.
There remained ``two big risks'' of police corruption in 2014 which were ``access to information and abuse of position'', he said.
``I don't think corruption has gone away. It doesn't go away,'' Mr Mackey said.
He told the committee he was now more worried about corruption within ``borough-based investigations''.
``Corruption has changed slightly,'' he said. ``Corruption now is much more about trying to corrupt an individual. That might be a member of police staff or a police officer.''
Mr Mackey said he accepted Mr Ellison's criticism of a review he commissioned into police corruption in 2012 which he described as ``ill-judged''.
The deputy commissioner said he told the Home Office in 2012 that the force could not find files gathered under Operation Othona.
Another 12 months was needed for ``full forensic drains up'' review before it was published, he said.
In an angry exchange with the committee, London mayor Boris Johnson said he was ``content'' that the Met had a ``grip'' on undercover police operations.
``I've heard quite enough tripe from people who are seeking to undermine what I think is a vital part of policing,'' he said,
``What I find disgraceful is the constant sniping and slurring at Metropolitan Police officers who are doing a fantastic job in bringing down crime.''
Mr Johnson said the use of undercover officers to infiltrate the Lawrence family was ``reprehensible'' but he was ``utterly fed up of reading attacks'' on police officers in London.
Mr Lawrence, 18, a would-be architect, was stabbed to death by a group of up to six white youths, in an unprovoked racist attack as he waited at a bus stop in Eltham, south-east London, with a friend on April 22, 1993. It took more than 18 years to bring two of his killers to justice.
In the wake of the Ellison Review's publication, Commander Richard Walton was temporarily removed from his post as head of the Met's counter-terrorism command SO15 over his links to the undercover operations.
An undercover officer - known as N81 - held a meeting in 1998 with Mr Walton, who was then an acting detective inspector working on Scotland Yard's Lawrence review team, responsible for making submissions to the Macpherson Inquiry. end
]]></text></news-item>