<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-FJN1-F0NV-F1BB"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Tonawanda Coke ordered to pay $25 million in fines</title><source>Ken-Ton Bee (New York)</source><author>NAOMI SPENCER Editor</author><text><![CDATA[A federal judge last week ordered Tonawanda Coke to pay fines totaling $25 million, with about half of them going toward two in-depth environmental studies of the area surrounding the River Road business.
(See editorial on page four)
Mark Kamholz, the former environmental controls manager for the company, was sentenced to one year in prison. Kamholz, 66, of West Seneca, was also sentenced to 100 hours of community service and fined $20,000.
The fine, according to the United States Department of Justice, is one of the largest ever levied in an air pollution case involving a federal criminal trial.
"This sentencing holds Tonawanda Coke and its environmental control manager accountable for one of the most egregarious environmental pollution crimes in the area's history," said William Hochul Jr., attorney for the Western District of New York, adding, "The environmental regulations designed to protect our citizens also place trust in industry not to choose pollution over profit. Tonawanda Coke Corporation betrayed that trust."
Last year, a federal jury convicted the company on 11 counts of violating both the Clean Air Act and Resource Conservation Recovery Act.
According to the evidence presented at trial, the company released coke oven gas that contained a toxic chemical - benzene - into the air. This was done through an unreported pressure relief valve. Additionally, among other violations, a coke-quenching tower was being operated without baffles, a mandated pollution control device.
U.S. District Judge William M. Skretny ordered the company, located at 3875 River Road, to pay fines of $12.5 million for disregarding the toxic chemicals being spewed into the air.
Another $12.2 million will fund two environmental studies. The first study, which will cost $11 million, will be conducted by the University at Buffalo's School of Public Health and Health Professions. It will study the effect toxic chemicals have had on the communities surrounding the company. The second study, which will cost $711,000, is an in-depth soil and air study on particulate matter from the company's foundry emissions.
Jackie James-Creedon, director of the nonprofit Citizen Science Community Resources, has led the community in its fight for clean air. She said she's pleased with the outcome of the sentencing, especially that it will fund two studies. She had reservation, she said, on whether Skretny would make Tonawanda Coke fund the two community projects. She's thrilled he did.
"This definitely sends a message," she said. "It sends a message loud and clear to industries not only in Tonawanda but across the country."
State Sen. Mark Grisanti, who represents the Ken-Ton area, said he agrees with the sentence given by Skretny.
"Although the maximum sentence was not imposed against Tonawanda Coke, I applaud the decision by the court to force Tonawanda Coke to fund two separate environmental studies for the benefit of the Tonawanda comm unity," he said. "These studies will help prevent future health concerns for the residents who were affected by this terrible act."
Rep. Brian Higgins, who represents District 26, said he credits an "engaged, enraged and educated" community with the sentencing decision.
"The fines," he said, "could never be steep enough for the cost to this community and its residents, but we are pleased that Tonawanda Coke will be made to pay for their negligence and more than $12 million in fines will be kept there where the psychological, physical and property damage occurred."
Higgins said it was the residents who should be credited with beginning the effort to get state and federal agencies to take note of what they were witnessing in the vicinity of the plant.
He credits Skretny for hearing the community's call for fines to be reinvested in community service projects.
]]></text></news-item>