<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-3TT1-JC17-F2GK"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>National Park questions LG plan</title><source>Northern Valley Suburbanite (Bergen, North Jersey)</source><author>Stephanie Simone</author><text><![CDATA[ENGLEWOOD CLIFFS - Pressure continues to build in a campaign to force LG Electronics to reduce the height of its planned 143-feet Northern American headquarters that would be visible above the tree line along the Palisades Cliffs.
The head of the National Park Service is the latest in a series of preservationists to decry LG's plans for 111 Sylvan Ave.
In a letter released on March 13 by Protect the Palisades, a coalition of preservationists trying to block construction, Park Service Director Jonathan B. Jarvis said the building would threaten "the nationally significant, historic scenic integrity of the Palisades in a major way" and "introduce a massive incompatible feature that will be visible for miles along the river and from vantage points along the west side of Manhattan" as well as from the George Washington Bridge.
"Given the size of the property in question, it seems entirely possible for the development to achieve its needs and conform to the borough's existing zoning regulations," Jarvis wrote in the letter to the chairman of the borough's Planning Board.
The Palisades Interstate Park and its recreational trails are designated national landmarks, but the National Park Service has no authority over the South Korean company's planned headquarters.
Six Northern Valley towns also came out against the project last month and wrote a letter to LG's corporate officials stressing the need to lower the building's height.
Closter officials passed a resolution on March 12 opposing the height and urging LG to lower it because it will have a "detrimental impact" on the Palisades.
"I am pleased the Closter Council has joined the chorus of protest against LG's threat to visually pollute this iconic New Jersey landmark," Councilman John Kashwick said. "If we, as a community, allow LG to build their 143-feet high corporate tower - four times above the traditional 35-feet limit in the area adjacent to the Palisades Interstate Park north of Fort Lee - we will have failed in our duty to keep safe for our children and our nation this geologic and historic treasure."
Opponents of the project continue to argue that allowing LG to build a high rise that would be visible above the tree line along the Hudson River cliffs would undo a century of conservation efforts and allow for more development north of Fort Lee.
Jarvis' letter comes as the Englewood Cliffs Planning Board awaits a report that could amend its master plan - allowing the borough to codify the rezoning changes that were granted for the project. Prior to the rezoning changes, a variance had exempted the project from the borough's 35-feet height limit.
The Borough Council asked its current planner, Paul Phillips, to review the rezoning in response to a claim in the lawsuit that the borough's former municipal planner, Burgis Associates, had a potential conflict of interest because it represented LG when it was granted the variance.
If Phillips affirms the rezoning, the Planning Board would amend the master plan to reflect the taller height limit for buildings on larger parcels, such as LG's 27-acre property, Borough Attorney Michael Kates said. If Phillips doesn't back the rezoning, the Borough Council could still enact a new ordinance allowing buildings of this height, according to the attorney.
Mayor Joseph Parisi defended LG's plans to build during a council meeting on March 12 where he outlined the economic benefits the project would bring to the borough including a lower tax rate for residents and hundreds of jobs for the area. He also added that since the location is on a slope, the building won't be noticeable along the Palisades and LG is building according to strict environmental standards.
"I've been an advocate of the LG project from day one," Parisi said. "When the project is done if no one in the County, Englewood Cliffs, or New York is happy with the results, please don't vote for me. That's how strongly I feel about this. They've been great corporate citizens and they've been contributing to this town in every little aspect. If LG lowered the building it would cost LG $3 to $5 million dollars just to design the change and they have to go through the whole process again."
Borough attorney E. Carter Corriston also defended LG's intention to build saying if the electronics giant decided to completely relocate because of all the pushback, the borough would have to quickly decide what to do with that land - which includes considering affordable housing to comply with Council On Affordable Housing obligations.
While LG and borough officials have engaged the community over the past four years with multiple public hearings and meetings with local community groups, preservationists are rallying at the eleventh-hour after a campaign by the Rockefeller family-aligned Natural Resources Defense Council (NRDC) outlined how "damaging" the construction would be to the Palisades.
LG was initially granted a variance to build and, after that was challenged by two residents in April 2012, a rezoning ordinance was approved exempting it from Englewood Cliffs' 35-feet height limit on buildings in October 2012.
A Superior Court judge upheld the variance and a coalition of preservation groups filed a lawsuit to appeal the decision in August 2013. That lawsuit has yet to be ruled on.
The NRDC and New Jersey Conservation Foundation moved to join the appeal but on March 5 the New Jersey Court of Appeals denied the motion to intervene.
Work is already underway at the construction site. LG is confident that it can win additional challenges, according to John Taylor, Vice President of Public Affairs and Communications.
The Englewood Cliffs Planning Board has set a public hearing for April 30 on the master plan.
]]></text></news-item>