<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-RS91-DYN2-33P0"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Gleision mine disaster survivors heard deafening rush of water, court hears</title><source>guardian.co.uk</source><author>Steven Morristheguardian.com</author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
Survivors of a Welsh colliery disaster that killed four men heard an explosion like a jet engine followed by the deafening sound of rushing water as the mine flooded, a jury has been told.
The manager of Gleision mine, Malcolm Fyfield, who is charged with manslaughter over the deaths at the colliery near Pontardawe in 2011, was one of seven working in extraordinarily cramped conditions in a warren of tunnels.
Fyfield managed to crawl out of the mine through sludge and dirt and told paramedics: "They've gone, there is no hope for the others", Swansea crown court heard on Thursday.
The bodies of Charles Breslin, 62, Philip Hill, 44, Garry Jenkins, 39, and David Powell, 50, were eventually found.
Fyfield denies manslaughter and MNS Mining, which ran the mine, denies four charges of corporate manslaughter.
Gregg Taylor, prosecuting, described how the men's jobs involved crawling on hands and knees through small tunnels and extracting coal from the 100-year-old drift mine using explosives.
Taylor said the height of some tunnels was just 77cm (30in), almost 20cm lower than a standard kitchen worktop.
"Men worked this space by crawling on their hands and knees. It's not modern with machines, tracks and trains. This is a very historical practice."
Taylor said that at around 9am on 15 September 2011, the miner David Wyatt told colleagues he was going to "fire the shots" to blast the coal from the seam. "They heard an explosion that sounded like a jet engine followed by the sound of rushing water."
Wyatt, his colleague Nigel Evans and Fyfield managed to get out and the emergency services were called. Fyfield later told police that he tried to give Powell and Hill mouth-to-mouth resuscitation before fleeing as the water rose around him.
Taylor said post-mortem examinations of the men found their lungs and airways were blocked with water contaminated with coal and silt.
He described Fyfield as a very experienced miner who had owned and run a number of collieries. "As a mine manager, Mr Fyfield was very well regarded in the industry and by the mines inspectorate."
The jury heard Fyfield had been working as the manager of Gleision, near Pontardawe, for 10 weeks before the disaster happened.
The trial continues.
]]></text></news-item>