<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-FYX1-JC3H-013M"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Madison Hospital could have to pay $2.5M</title><source>The News-Star (Monroe, Louisiana)</source><author>By, Scott Rogers</author><text><![CDATA[Madison Parish Hospital could face a financial emergency if the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services require reimbursement of $2.5 million in overpayment that was the result of fraudulent billing by the hospital's former administrator.
Hospital CEO Scott Barrilleaux and Hospital Service District Chairman Thomas Williams provided the state fiscal review committee an update on the hospital district's corrective action plan after years of fraud and misuse of public funds decimated hospital finances.
The fiscal review committee is composed of the legislative auditor, state treasurer and attorney general.
Michael Cragin, senior adviser for the Louisiana legislative auditor, said the reimbursement to the centers is the biggest challenge facing the hospital.
Originally the legislative auditor identified $5 million in possible fraudulent billing by the hospital's former administrator, but further investigation revealed approximately $2.5 million was billed fraudulently, with the proceeds split among former administrator Wendell Alford, Tech Solutions LLC agent Casey Hughes and insurance agent Russell Ham of Insurance World.
Alford was sentenced to 37 months in prison and three years supervised probation and is responsible for $1,383,874 in restitution.
Hughes was sentenced to spend 12 months in prison and ordered to pay $566,874 in restitution.
Ham will serve 14 months in prison and was ordered to pay $817,000 in restitution. Hughes and Ham will have three years supervised release following their prison terms.
It is unknown if the three men will be able to pay any of the restitution or fines imposed on the three men, Cragin said.
According to Barrilleaux, the hospital could be expected to pay back $2.5 million in June. Over the next several weeks, hospital officials will meet with CMS to determine how the hospital can pay back the money.
If the hospital does not make the repayment, CMS will stop Medicare and Medicaid reimbursements to the facility until it is paid in full.
"Barring any type of repayment plan, we could be saddled with a $2.5 million payback. At that point we go negative, and we will stay negative for the rest of the year. That would be devastating. If we have to cut a check for $2.5 million, it would shutter us," Barrilleaux said.
The hospital has hired an outside CPA firm to manage finances as required by the corrective action plan.
"The hospital has never had a chief financial officer, which may explain some of the past problems. They now have this firm to give financial advice and prepare monthly financial statements until staff can be brought up to speed and manage the hospital's accounting department," Cragin said. "They've had to rely heavily on outside resources because they just don't have the expertise in house in many of the key areas in accounting. There also has been a good bit of turnover in the accounting department, so they've had their challenges."
According to the most recent audit, released in December 2013, Madison Parish Hospital Service District ran a $2.2 million deficit and racked up 36 deficiencies during the 2012 fiscal year.
The audit provided few surprises to the Legislative Auditor's Office, considering the district has dealt with financial problems from activities of its former chief executive officer to defraud the district.
According to the audit, total revenue in 2012 was $12.8 million while expenses totaled $15 million, resulting in the $2.2 million loss from operations. At the close of the fiscal year, the hospital district had $3.7 million in total cash available after the deficit spending.
Follow Scott Rogers on Twitter @lscottrogers.
]]></text></news-item>