<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-FYX1-JC3H-00TG"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Bluegrass Pipeline project loses case</title><source>The Courier-Journal (Louisville, Kentucky)</source><author>By, Tom Loftus</author><text><![CDATA[FRANKFORT, Ky. - Developers of the controversial Bluegrass Pipeline do not have the legal authority to condemn land to pipe natural gas liquids across Kentucky, a judge ruled Tuesday.
In an 18-page order, Circuit Judge Phillip Shepherd granted a summary judgment in favor of the group Kentuckians United to Restrain Eminent Domain, or KURE, which has fought the pipeline project.
Shepherd ruled that a private corporation would need an "undeniably clear mandate from the legislature" before being able to seize citizens' property rights: "There has been no such clear and explicit delegation of this power to Bluegrass."
Penny Greathouse, a cattle farmer from Franklin County and member of KURE, said, "I'm elated that the judge stood up for landowners. It's what we were hoping for."
A spokesman for Williams Co., one of two companies that comprise Bluegrass Pipeline Co., said it will appeal.
"While we disagree with today's ruling ... we continue to purchase easements through face-to-face negotiations with individual landowners, a successful process whereby we've acquired nearly 70 percent of the route needed in Kentucky," said Williams spokesman Tom Droege.
At issue are Bluegrass' plans to run about 150 miles of 24-inch diameter pipe through Kentucky, carrying natural gas liquids from Pennsylvania to the Gulf Coast.
Natural gas liquids include a variety of hydrocarbons including ethane, propane, butane, isobutane and pentane. They are used in the production of everything from plastic bags and antifreeze to synthetic rubber and gasoline.
Critics have expressed concerns of the possibility of explosion and environmental damage caused by any leak. But Droege has said the pipe will engineered to the latest safety standards and closely monitored.
The line would cross the Ohio River at Bracken County, run southwest through the Bluegrass region and on to Larue County, where it would turn west to Breckinridge County and link with an existing pipe that would be repurposed.
Bluegrass Pipeline has contended that Kentucky law gives it the power to condemn the property of landowners who decline to voluntarily sell easements through their property, though it has not yet attempted to invoke the power.
But Shepherd ruled the project can not condemn land because the legislature has not granted that authority for this type of project. The judge said the pipeline does not serve the energy needs of Kentuckians and would not be regulated by the Kentucky Public Service Commission.
"Bluegrass is a private, for-profit, unregulated entity" that plans to use the pipeline to ship natural gas liquids to the Gulf Coast to be processed and sold in Louisiana, Shepherd wrote. The purpose of the line, he said is "to have NGLs - a mixture of highly dangerous chemicals - running through Kentucky farmland and forests and near rural communities."
The judge also stated that Bluegrass can not even suggest to landowners who do not want to sell that it has eminent domain power. "Landowners ... are entitled to know that the law does not support Bluegrass' assertion of the power of eminent domain."
Greathouse said: "That part of the ruling is important because it lets people not interested in selling feel OK about saying no."
Meanwhile, legislation that would expressly prohibit the use of condemnation for natural gas liquids pipelines is running out of time in the 2014 legislative session. The bill, House Bill 31, passed the House 75-16 Friday but has not moved in the Senate.
"I have no clear sense of what the Senate intends to do with it," said Tom FitzGerald, director of the Kentucky Resources Council and the attorney who represents KURE.
Wednesday is the 54th day of a legislative session that can last no more than 60 days and must adjourn by midnight April 15.
Reporter Tom Loftus can be reached at (502) 875-5136. Follow him on Twitter at @TomLoftus_CJ.
LOCATION MAP THAT SHOWS THE PROPOSED BLUEGRASS PIPELINE ROUTE (SEE LIBRARY MICROFILM OR LIBRARY PDF PAGES)
]]></text></news-item>