<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-G381-JBWH-P0PF"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Jebel Ali Port Turning Off Non-Essential Lighting For Earth Hour 2014</title><source>Emirates News Agency</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[WAM Dubai, 27th March 2014 (WAM): - DP World today announced that its flagship Jebel Ali Port will join thousands of businesses and millions of people across the globe in reducing resource consumption for Earth Hour, the world's largest public action for the environment.
For the fifth year in a row, unnecessary controlled lights will be switched off at Jebel Ali and other DP World, UAE Region Terminals, from 8:30 pm to 9:30 pm (Dubai Time) during the event which will take place this year on Saturday 29 March,.
During this week, a series of awareness campaigns were held at the port encouraging employees to switch off all non-essential lights and unplug non-essential equipment in their offices and at home with free Earth Hour kits being distributed to participants.
Mohammed Al Muallem, Senior Vice President and Managing Director, DP World, UAE Region, said: "Earth Hour has become a global campaign and we are proud to be part of it, raising awareness of energy conservation and how to operate businesses in the most environment friendly way possible. We have a responsibility to operate our business in a manner that does not harm the environment or deplete limited natural resources for future generations." Mohammed Ali Ahmed, Chief Operations Officer, DP World, UAE Region, said: "Being a 24/7 operation, light at our terminals cannot be totally switched off. Yet, non-critical items can be turned off temporarily without compromising individual safety, terminal security or operational efficiency. Port users can be confident that we are committed to exceptionally high standards which have been internationally recognized." Last year, Jebel Ali Port saved thousands of kilowatts by replacing the lighting system in its 175 hectare terminals with a custom-designed Green Generation Lighting system.
Reducing kilowatt usage by 72% as well as lowering maintenance costs, the project won the "Light Middle East Award" in "Sustainable Lighting Project of the Year" category held last November in Qatar.
WAM/tfaham

]]></text></news-item>