<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-M3D1-JBHM-S18Y"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>CASAC Members Aim To Boost Case For Novel 'Secondary' Ozone NAAQS</title><source>Inside EPA Weekly Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Members of EPA's Clean Air Scientific Advisory Committee (CASAC) are trying to bolster the case for the agency to pursue a novel distinct "secondary" ozone standard to protect the environment, highlighting insufficient scientific justification for the separate standard that industry critics could potentially use to fight a secondary limit.
During a March 25-27 meeting of CASAC's ozone review panel in Chapel Hill, NC, panelists reviewed documents for EPA's pending revisions to its ozone national ambient air quality standard (NAAQS). The agency last updated the standard in 2008, tightening the "primary" health-based limit to 75 parts per billion (ppb), down from the prior level of 80 ppb set in 1997. EPA in the 2008 rule opted against setting a separate secondary ozone standard.
Environmentalists sued the agency over that decision, and the U.S. Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit in a July 23 ruling remanded to EPA for better explanation its reasoning for not setting a distinct secondary NAAQS. The agency's response to the remand is expected to be included in the ozone NAAQS review.
The Clean Air Act mandates that EPA reassess its NAAQS every five years, and the agency has acknowledged it is behind schedule on the ozone review. But it has released key scientific and policy documents to inform the review, including a draft risk and exposure assessment (REA) of exposures and associated risks to human health and the environment, and a policy assessment suggesting options for revising the stringency of the NAAQS.
CASAC's ozone review panel during this week's meeting assessed the various documents, and members said that they support a distinct secondary limit, with a different form and indicator than the primary limit, as the most appropriate way to protect the environment. But they also cautioned that the REA shows little reduction in risk from using such a novel standard. Industry is making a similar argument to oppose a novel secondary NAAQS.
Panelists further argued for a "more balanced" presentation of scientific uncertainties in the REA, and ideally a quantitative uncertainty analysis rather than the qualitative approach now used. Whereas the qualitative analysis merely describes uncertainties in general terms, a quantitative analysis would seek to measure them.
If the REA does not unambiguously show benefits of a distinct secondary standard, EPA will face a difficult choice on whether to adopt the alternative methodology suggested by EPA staff to set a secondary NAAQS using a method called W-126, which measures ozone-season, or summertime, ozone in parts per million-hours (ppm-hrs).
Panelists said they will not call on EPA to issue a third draft of the REA, but in a forthcoming letter to EPA Administrator Gina McCarthy will call for changes to the document to take their concerns into account. While the panel will "re-affirm" its support for the W-126 metric, the suggested changes -- also to include an analysis of any adverse effects from using a distinct secondary NAAQS -- would render the REA more "defensible," they said.
CASAC member Peter Woodbury, of Cornell University, noted that within the range of 7-15 ppm-hrs that EPA analyzed in the REA, a lot of options for the secondary NAAQS when modeled appear to have similar benefits to the existing 75 ppb NAAQS. He suggested this may be in part because of EPA's methodology, which is based on nine regions. EPA needs to demonstrate the risk reductions achieved by W-126 at a local level to show site-specific impacts, he said.
Woodbury added that in describing uncertainty in the REA, "we don't want to overemphasize the noise and lose the signal," and that he is "more concerned about bias than uncertainty," responding to strong argument in favor of quantitative uncertainty analysis from fellow panelist Armistead Russell of the Georgia Institute of Technology.
Panelist Daniel Jacob of Harvard University suggested an analysis of the benefits of a distinct secondary NAAQS down to the county level is necessary, as the standard will be implemented at the county rather than national level. Counties typically form the basis for areas designated as "attainment" or "nonattainment" with the NAAQS. EPA staff said that the choice of nine regions was based on a technical limitation in computational power.
However, the power sector Utility Air Regulatory Group (UARG) in public comments presented to the panel said that EPA has failed to demonstrate that meeting a distinct secondary welfare-based standard would provide any more protection than meeting the current primary standard. At 15 ppm-hrs, the REA shows that the benefits to the environment are "virtually identical" to meeting the 75 ppb primary NAAQS, UARG says.
Georgia Murray of the environmentalist Appalachian Mountain Club countered that EPA's "robust analysis" shows a need for the W-126 metric, and a NAAQS level of 7 ppm-hrs. She said EPA should expand its focus from daytime, 3-month exposures to cover nighttime, year-round exposures to capture the true impact of ozone on plants.
CASAC members said they remain concerned about two other important aspects of the review, impacting the fate of both the primary and secondary ozone standards.
Background ozone, which originates from abroad or from natural processes, remains problematic, especially in the West. Also, EPA's focus in the document is on reducing nitrogen oxides (NOx) -- which are precursor gases to ozone -- rather than volatile organic compounds (VOCs), which are also precursors that react to form ozone.
State and local regulators cannot reduce background ozone, and so may be able to unable to meet the NAAQS if background levels climb too high, making reductions in local emissions ineffectual. Failure to attain the NAAQS means regulators must impose tougher and more expensive pollution controls on industry, or face the ultimate sanction of losing federal highway funds.
EPA staff at the CASAC meeting took the position that EPA cannot consider implementation costs or feasibility when setting either primary or secondary NAAQS.
Despite this, CASAC's Jacob said "I am fundamentally concerned about the intermountain West," where high background ozone levels are often recorded. He suggested that a federal strategy to try to reduce ozone stemming from other countries, or efforts to reduce domestic methane emissions, could be beneficial in lowering background ozone.
Jacob said that EPA's focus on NOx might be particularly misplaced in the West, where ozone chemistry is more poorly understood and other factors such as VOCs or stratospheric intrusions are at play. Russell agreed, saying that the sole focus on reducing NOx needs to be better justified.
The background and NOx issues also arose in discussions over the adequacy of EPA's primary NAAQS during the meeting. CASAC has twice unanimously recommended tightening the standard to a level within a range of 60 ppb to 70 ppb, and then-EPA Administrator Lisa Jackson advocated a 70 ppb limit in a 2011 rulemaking that was ultimately blocked by the White House.
Industry and environmentalists continue to spar over whether EPA's science supports strengthening the standard, with industry arguing that the evidence is too weak, and some environmentalists saying it is strong enough even to support a standard as strict as 55 ppb -- the level supported by the American Lung Association.
Allen Lefohn, of consultancy A.S.L. & Associates, said that in the West and also the Northeast, background ozone often makes up 70 percent of the total ozone measured. While some of this might be reduced by international initiatives or curbs on methane leaks, some of it is related to natural phenomena, Lefohn said.
Several industry speakers cited research by consultancy Gradient, which frequently works for major industry groups such as the American Petroleum Institute, suggesting there are no statistically significant effects on health from ozone at levels below 70 ppb, and no true harm at levels below 80 ppb.
However, CASAC panelist Frederick Miller said, "I take issue with your statement that there is no adversity at 70 ppb." The meeting is scheduled to conclude March 27. -- Stuart Parker
]]></text></news-item>