<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-3PV1-JBF5-T1NM"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Crocodile safari hunting plan rejection angers Northern Territory Government</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Northern Territory Government is angry its plan for crocodile safari hunting has been rejected by the Federal Government.
The NT Government wanted fee-paying safari hunters to be able to take a total of 50 large saltwater crocodiles each year, as part of a trial.
That has been rejected by Federal Environment Minister Greg Hunt.
"My view is that there was a risk of cruel and inhumane treatment. That was, in my view, inappropriate," Mr Hunt said.
"There have been a series of ministers, both on the Coalition side and on the other side, that have periodically rejected this.
"So no crocodile safaris in the Northern Territory."
The Territory Government has labelled the decision "a total load of croc".
NT Minister for Land Resource Management Willem Westra van Holthe says safari hunting would have provided valuable income and jobs for remote Indigenous communities.
"Territorians best know how to manage the crocodiles up here in the Northern Territory," he said.
"I don't think Greg Hunt has any idea how to manage crocodiles in an area that he has little idea about.
"I'm sure if he had crocodiles in his swimming pool or his backyard, he'd want them managed."
Government 'frightened of animal welfare lobby'
A leading crocodile scientist is also disappointed by Mr Hunt's decision.
Professor Grahame Webb, who runs Crocodylus Park in Darwin, said the Federal Government was not prepared to stand up to animal rights activists.
"They're frightened of the animal rights and animal welfare lobbies down in Canberra, I don't think they care too much about landowners and crocodiles up here," he said.
"I would say they're being lobbied by people who just think this is outrageous."
Jida Gulpilil from the Gupulul Marayuwu Aboriginal Corporation says safaris could have provided much-needed economic development.
"It's another feather in the Government's hat when you are talking about taking away the rights of Aboriginal people," he said.
"For the Federal Government to come in under the Crown lawlessly, and take away the rights of Aboriginal people to continue hunting and gathering through this modern day and age that we all live in and have evolved through, is unfair and it's unjust."
The majority of saltwater crocodiles are found on Aboriginal lands and waterways.
The Territory Government wanted to trial the hunting for two years.
Mr Westra van Holthe says the 50 crocodiles each year would have been part of the existing crocodile management plan, which allows for up to 500 crocodiles to be harvested from the wild each year.
He says the safari hunts would have been conducted in a humane way.
The Territory's Parks and Wildlife Minister, Bess Price, says Federal Minister Greg Hunt's decision came as a shock.
"We had talks and I thought the talks were a great opportunity for us as the Northern Territory to be able to work with Greg Hunt," she said.
The Environment Department said it received hundreds of formal submissions from industry groups and environmental organisations, including Humane Society International.
Society spokeswoman Alexia Wellbelove said there was no significant economic benefits for Indigenous communities and a real risk of destroying other tourism brands.
"[It] rewards very few or benefits very few people," she said.
"We believe very strongly that there is far more potential in the remote areas of the Top End in ecotourism than there are for elitist safari hunting activities."
]]></text></news-item>