<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-RTC1-DY8N-Y00D"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Directors 'broke rules'</title><source>The New Age (South Africa)</source><author>MICHELE CURLING-HOPE</author><text><![CDATA[PINNACLE Holdings' internal shareholders pocketed millions before the company's share price tanked on Tuesday, in contravention of the JSE listing requirement to disclose "material price-sensitive information to shareholders".
On March 14, CEO Arnold Fourie sold 1.2 million shares for R23m. On March 12 and 13, executive director GJ Wiehahn disposed of 80000 shares for about R1.6m and on March 19, executive director Takalani Tshivhase sold 200000 shares worth R4m.
Tshivhase was arrested on March 5 for allegedly offering a R5m bribe to a senior policeman.
Two days later the company presented its interim results and made no reference to the arrest.
Under the heading, "General obligations of disclosure", a requirement for JSE-listed companies in respect of material price sensitive information includes: "... an issuer must, without delay... release an announcement providing details of any development(s) in such issuer's sphere of activity that is/are not public knowledge and which may, by virtue of its/their effect(s), lead to material movements of the (share price)."
Tshivhase was arrested at the company's head office in Midrand and charged with attempting in January to bribe a senior police manager with R5m to secure a multimillion-rand contract for devices used in police investigations.
On Tuesday, 20 days after the arrest, Pinnacle released a statement saying it was aware of the accusations. Pinnacle's share crashed by 25% soon after the announcement and a further 24% yesterday.
Shareholder activist Theo Botha told The New Age it was clear that internal shareholders looked after their own interests, selling off shares before disclosing the information to other shareholders.
He said that the internal shareholders involved must have known that news of Tshivhase being accused of bribery would cause the company reputational harm and hurt the share price.
"We know this for sure now after the share price tanked on the day the announcement was made."
Botha said the company had the opportunity to inform its shareholders of the arrest when it released its interim results a few days later.
Hawks spokesperson Paul Ramaloko said Tshivhase's appearance had been postponed to April 24 for further investigation.
The JSE's director of issuer regulations, John Burke, said: "We are investigating."
The findings are expected to be handed over to the Financial Services Board. In a statement on Tuesday, the JSE-listed technology company said Tshivhase denied all allegations.
According to Pinnacle Holdings' 2013 annual report, Tshivhase held 4705851 shares at the time, which translated into about 3% of the total issued shares of the company.
Pinnacle describes itself as "one of Africa's largest providers of ICT products and services".
Pinnacle board chairperson, Daphne Mashile-Nkosi was recently named CEO of the Year at the Africa CEO Forum event in Switzerland.
Pinnacle did not respond to requests for comment.
michelec@thenewage.co.za
]]></text></news-item>