<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-FYB1-JC86-C4K6"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Nigeria; Vandalised Crude Pipeline in Agip's Oil Field Pollutes Ikarama Community in Bayelsa</title><source>Africa News</source><author>Premium Times (Abuja)</author><text><![CDATA[There is uncontrolled discharge of crude from three spots in the Ikarama oil fields located in Yenagoa Council Area of Bayelsa, causing great harm to the environment, an environmental organisation has said.
Two of the spots are said to be discharging crude into the environment, while one has been discharging gas since March 21, 2014. The discharge is believed to be caused by the activities of suspected oil thieves on Agip's pipeline.
According to a field report by Environmental Rights Action/Friends of Earth Nigeria, ERA/FoEN, the spills occurred on two different pipelines within the oil field operated by Agip in the area.
In the report signed by Alagoa Morris, the Head of Field Operations of ERA/FoEN in Bayelsa, the organisation noted that the oil thieves had excavated the earth to expose the pipelines which they abandoned after their illicit act.
According to ERA/FoEN, an environment focused Non-Government Organisation, the spill was reported to it by members of the community; after which it dispatched its field monitors to the spill location.
"The spills were discovered on the 21st of March 2014, by Mr. Washington Odoyibo from Ikarama community while he was going to assist a friend on a fishing expedition.
"He promptly called the Yenagoa office of Environmental Rights Action (ERA/FoEN) to complain of the predicament that has befallen their people and ERA/FoEN mobilised to site and returned with these findings," the report stated.
The ERA/FoEN expressed concerns over the negative impact of the ongoing pollution of the environment by both crude oil and gas leaks and urged the management of Agip to urgently clamp the leak.
It further recommended a prompt clean up and remediation of the spill on the impacted site while the oil firm should take steps to secure its facility from vandals.
When contacted, Tajudeen Adigun, the spokesperson of Agip, declined comment.
]]></text></news-item>