<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-9XG1-DY9P-N50W"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Families fuming at gas drill plan; Firm wants to extract methane from site</title><source>The Sentinel (Stoke)</source><author>PHIL CORRIGAN</author><text><![CDATA[GAS could be extracted from a borehole just yards from families' homes - for up to 25 years. Alkane Energy has lodged plans to drill for methane behind Mossfield Road Industrial Estate in Longton. The company hopes to use coal mine gas from the former Mossfield Colliery to generate two megawatts of electricity at the site.
It wants drilling to take place 24 hours a day, seven days a week, until around 2040.
According to the plans, once up and running the 'energy park' would be generally unmanned and have minimal impact on its surroundings.
But residents in nearby streets have expressed concerns over noise and pollution.
Nottinghamshire-bassed Alkane already runs 24 similar gas-to-power plants around the country, including those at Hem Heath and Florence.
The company's application states: "The design of the site is based upon a tried and tested model which has evolved over the 16 or so years Alkane Energy has been developing coal mine methane extraction and electricity generating sites throughout the UK.
"The site is designed to operate automatically without the need for people to be on site except for maintenance or repair.
"Our aim is to provide a compact 'green' energy facility with minimal impact on the surrounding environment."
The plans explain that a borehole would be drilled from the surface to evaluate whether there are 'commercially extractable quantities' of methane in the abandoned mine. If this is successful, a gas engine within a single-storey prefab container would then assembled at the energy park.
An 11ft-high acoustic screening would be erected on the southern and eastern boundaries of the site.
Access to the site would be via Mossfield Road, with traffic normally limited to two vans and three cars a week.
But residents living close to the site are still concerned about the plans, despite the company's attempts to reassure them.
Sharon Lockett, aged 44, of Bambury Street, said: "This is going to be just yards from our back gate.
"I called the company and asked the man there how he'd like it if one of these was built just behind his house.
"My husband has had four heart attacks, the last one just last year. That's why we moved here.
"There was never any suggestion that anything like this would happen.
"We've already lodged our objections to the plans. But hundreds of people objected to the one at Florence, and that still went ahead, and it's still there now.
"The company knows that as long as they keep within the maximum sound and pollution levels they'll be fine.
"But we've heard of cases where gas has leaked at other drill sites."
'METHANE GAS IS ONLY A QUICK FIX': READ THE FULL STORY AT www.thesentinel.co.uk
]]></text></news-item>