<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-DK91-F0JP-W23P"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Costa shock at AWH pay levels and pole dancing</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (Australia)</source><author>Amy Dale</author><text><![CDATA[POLE dancing was included in the outlandish expenses of Australian Water Holdings, with former Labor state treasurer Michael Costa revealing to the corruption watchdog yesterday his "horror" at the company's spending.
Mr Costa, who served as chairman of AWH after federal Senator Arthur Sinodinos stood down from the role, said he was "shocked" to learn that personal assistants were on salaries of more than $100,000 and a desperate $5 million cash injection was partially spent backpaying some of the directors.
"The costs were out of control," Mr Costa said of his findings upon replacing Mr Sindinos in November 2011.
"I was completely shocked ... limousines, I think (current AWH chairman Peter Canaway) did mention pole dancing, I didn't know what that was all about." The inquiry has seen the expenses of Australian Water Holdings, which were billed back to Sydney Water under a longstanding and "poorly drafted" deed meant to cover administration costs for an infrastructure project. Also being investigated by ICAC are claims a cabinet minute was falsified to help AWH secure a lucrative public-private partnership with the government, and allegations politicians from both sides corruptly intervened in the company's interest.
It is alleged the Obeid family hold a secret 30 per cent stake in AWH, with the inquiry also hearing evidence yesterday from Dennis Jabour, Eddie Obeid's nephew, who was paid $150,000 to produce "nothing" as its land development manager.
Mr Costa, who is not accused of any wrongdoing and resigned from the company after a year, described one of AWH's directors, John Rippon, as "extremely greedy".
Mr Costa was preceded in the witness box by former premier Kristina Keneally, who described the allegedly doctored cabinet minute as "bad policy" and a proposal which she left "dead in the water, at least as far as (my) government was concerned".
Mrs Keneally said she was lobbied by Eddie Obeid, Joe Tripodi and Tony Kelly about the AWH proposal but that she eventually "drove a stake through (its) heart"."At no point did anyone raise with me concerns about ownership of the company, authorship of the minute, donations being made to the Liberal Party. That information was not available to me," Mrs Keneally said.
]]></text></news-item>