<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-SY61-JC8C-21WS"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Boca bar vows to fix problems; Mayor criticizes 101 Cantina's reputation for rowdiness.</title><source>Sun-Sentinel (Fort Lauderdale, Florida)</source><author>Brett Clarkson and Anne Geggis, Staff writers</author><text><![CDATA[A student nightspot criticized by residents as being a magnet for out-of-control rowdiness and underage drinking should be closed down if it doesn't clean up its act, Boca's outgoing mayor said.
"We want the place either to follow the law and act and be responsible, or we want it shut down," Mayor Susan Whelchel said Wednesday.
Meanwhile, a representative of 101 Cantina responded publicly for the first time to the controversy, saying during Tuesday night's City Council meeting that the Gainesville-based company that manages the bar takes residents' concerns "very seriously" and has made changes in an effort to fix problems associated with the bar.
"Our goal is to make sure that we have solutions to these issues," said Ryan Prodesky, vice president of marketing for 101 Management Group LLC, which manages 101 Cantina. "We believe that we do, and our job is to implement those and make sure that those issues are over."
The public debate over the establishment, at 133 SE Mizner Blvd., has ramped up since March 16, when two separate fights broke out at the bar in the wee hours.
After the brawls, Boca Raton police released numbers that showed there had been 98 arrests at the bar between its grand opening in June 2013 and March 17. Of those arrests, 78 were for possession of alcohol by a minor.
Police spokeswoman Sandra Boonenberg described the arrest numbers as unusually high.
At Boca Raton City Hall on Tuesday night, downtown resident and businessman Mark Seigel, who lives close to the bar, asked city officials to take action.
"It has assaulted our community with obnoxious music, intoxicated customers, and violent situations that have required significant police intervention," Seigel said.
Whelchel agreed with the sentiment, saying of the bar, "I don't want it to be there. Nobody up here wants it to be there."
Seigel said Wednesday the situation has "caused me to reconsider whether I want to continue to reside in the neighborhood."
City Manager Leif Ahnell said in the meeting that the city has been exploring its enforcement options and has been working with state regulators who oversee the establishment's licenses to sell alcohol and operate as a restaurant.
The establishment's retail beverage license showed an unspecified enforcement action effective Wednesday, online DBPR records showed.
An email request made to the Florida Department of Business and Professional Regulation for current information about 101 Cantina's license status Wednesday afternoon was not answered by Wednesday evening.
Boonenberg said police haven't had any calls involving the establishment since last Monday, with the exception of a burglary Monday morning in which 101 Cantina was listed as the victim.
"We're continuing to monitor it along with several other local establishments," Boonenberg said.
bsclarkson@tribune.com, 561-243-6609 or Twitter @BrettClarkson_
INFORMATIONAL BOX:
Cash taken
Police arrest suspect in Monday burglary at 101 Cantina. Page 3B
]]></text></news-item>