<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-TK71-JD34-V507"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Morwell fire inquiry focuses on public health</title><source>The Age (Melbourne, Australia)</source><author>Darren Gray Rural Affairs Reporter</author><text><![CDATA[Public health issues such as the impact of the Hazelwood open-cut coalmine fire on people's health, and the effectiveness and timeliness of health warnings issued in response to the fire, will be a prime focus of the independent inquiry ito the long-running blaze.
During a visit to Morwell on Thursday, the inquiry's head, Justice Bernard Teague, said he expected hundreds of submissions would be made and hundreds of people would attend about six community consultation sessions, likely to start in about two weeks. The sessions would help guide the inquiry on what matters were important to locals and what should be examined, he said.
"We want to find out what the local community thinks in relation to the various issues that are of concern to them," he said.
At a media conference, Justice Teague said: "My primary objective is to work out from a health point of view what are the things that need to be done, that will mean that the kind of health problems that have arisen won't happen again."
The three-member board of inquiry includes John Catford, a former chief health officer of Victoria, and lawyer Sonia Petering. Professor Catford said it was possible international health experts could be asked to participate.
"Obviously there have been some serious concerns about a number of individuals being affected by the outcome of the fire. And clearly the public health responses indicate that that was taken seriously. The question for me is - was the response appropriate - and particularly how can we learn from the Morwell experience to make sure that we minimise future problems," he said.
"Were the actions taken the right ones, were they done in the right sequence and timing, and was there effective public communication about those actions," he said.
While respiratory issues associated with the smoke and ash have received media focus, Professor Catford raised another area of health to be considered. "There are mental health dimensions as well. This has been a very harsh experience for this community. So I think we need to go beyond pure, immediate physical impacts to broader issues," he said.
For many days in the weeks after the mine fire ignited on February 9, Morwell and its 14,000 residents were blanketed by strong-smelling smoke and ash. Residents on the south side of town - where some houses are just a few hundred metres from the mine - bore the brunt of the smoke and ash. Some residents complained about the level of health information and warnings they were given, or that they were confused by the messages. Many complained of headaches, nausea, sore eyes and sore throats which they blamed on the smoke and ash.
Under its terms of reference the inquiry will investigate the origin and circumstances of the fire, the adequacy of the mine's regulatory regime, the emergency response, the role of mine operator GDF Suez and the adequacy of health information passed on to residents.
Justice Teague said the inquiry would be able to look at the issue of the health of firefighters who fought the blaze, describing this as a "health matter".
Public hearings are expected to be held in June. The board of inquiry has been asked to submit a report to the state government by August 31.
]]></text></news-item>