<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-H8T1-JCBD-Y182"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>MINERS HEARD BANG 'LIKE JET ENGINE'</title><source>Press Association Mediapoint</source><author>Benjamin Wright, Press Association</author><text><![CDATA[Miners working at a coal mine where four men died following flooding heard an explosion ``like a jet engine'' moments before the sudden whooshing sound of water, a jury has heard.
Pit boss Malcolm Fyfield was one of seven people working inside the Gleision drift mine, near Pontardawe, South Wales, when a shaft flooded in 2011.
He survived after crawling out through sludge and dirt.
As he was being treated by paramedics, Swansea Crown Court heard he told paramedics: ``They've gone. There is no hope for the others.''
Following hours of searches, the bodies of Charles Breslin, 62, Philip Hill, 44, Garry Jenkins, 39, and David Powell, 50, were discovered.
Father-of-two Fyfield has pleaded not guilty to four counts of manslaughter.
MNS Mining Ltd, which ran the mine at the time, denies four charges of corporate manslaughter by failing to ensure a safe system of work was in place.
Prosecutor Gregg Taylor said coal was extracted from the 100-year-old drift mine using explosives.
Conditions in the mine were said to be cramped, with the ceiling height at just 77cm, almost 20cm lower than a standard kitchen work top.
Mr Taylor said: ``Men worked this 2ft space by crawling on their hands and knees.
``It's not modern ... with machines, tracks and trains. This is a very historical practice.''
Mr Taylor said that at around 9am on September 15, a mine worker called David Wyatt told colleagues he was going to ``fire the shots'' - to blast the coal from the seam.
Mr Taylor said: ``They heard an explosion that sounded like a jet engine and their reaction was to shout 'run'.''
The jury was told the ``deafening sound'' of rushing water followed.
Mr Wyatt and a colleague called Nigel Evans managed to flee up the main shaft with the water hot on their heels.
A frantic 999 call was then made by the late Mr Powell's son, who also worked at the mine.
]]></text></news-item>