<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-4VX1-DXX7-H0WJ"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>LUCAS 'DIDN'T REACT' TO WARNING</title><source>Regional Press Releases: South East</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Green MP Caroline Lucas ``made absolutely no reaction'' and ``looked away'' when she was warned she risked arrest during anti-fracking protests in West Sussex, a court has heard.
The Brighton Pavilion MP was asked by Inspector Rachel Carr, a Sussex Police protest liaison officer who was drafted in to negotiate with demonstrators, to move to an area which had been designated by police for protesters.
Insp Carr told Brighton Magistrates' Court that she had recognised Lucas as being one of a group of protesters who were sat down and had linked arms at the entrance of Cuadrilla's exploratory drilling site in Balcombe on August 19 last year.
She said she was tasked, with two other officers, to explain to everyone in the group about the section 14 Public Order notice which had been issued and that if they did not move they risked being arrested, the court heard.
The officer said as she crouched down the group had started singing and raising their voices.
She said each person was issued with a copy of the notice with a map on the back marking the designated area for protest, and that she had placed it in the laps of those she spoke to so they could clearly see it, the court was told.
She said: ``I spoke to Caroline Lucas in relation to the section 14. The group was sitting in a circle, directly in front of the main gate and Caroline Lucas was on the left hand side close to the grass verge area.''
Insp Carr continued: ``Initially, she was not doing anything but as I started speaking to her the whole group began to sing.''
The officer said she advised the MP that there was a section 14 direction in place and that by sitting where she was she was breaching the order.
Insp Carr said Lucas gave ``absolutely no reaction at all''. She continued: ``She was looking away from me when I spoke to her.''
Prosecutor Jonathan Edwards said: ``Was there any reaction when you placed the notice in her lap?''
Insp Carr replied: ``I think she looked at it when I placed it in her lap but there was no speech.''
The officer told the court she went on to warn another four or five people about the section 14 notice.
Demonstrators were passive, non-compliant and had to be physically taken away from where they were sat after being arrested, the court was told.
Ruth Jarman and Josef Dobraszczyk two of the defendants on trial alongside Lucas, refused to comply with officers when they were arrested, and went limp and had to be carried away.
Footage showed Jarman, 50, and Dobraszczyk, 22, holding hands with a third man before they were arrested and refusing to respond to the officers who were speaking to them, the court heard.
Pc Alan Harris, a Sussex Police officer who said he arrested Jarman and another defendant, 39-year-old Ruth Potts, told the court he had explained the offences they might be committing and added that if they did not comply they risked arrest.
He said Potts was arrested and did not say anything as she was escorted away, although police footage showed her saying: ``We have not come to a decision yet.''
The court also heard Pc Harris's description of Jarman, which was different to her appearance on the police DVD.
A fifth defendant, Sheila Menon, 42, was also warned she was breaching the section 14 order but turned her head away from the officer talking to her, the court was told.
Leon Jennings, health, safety, security and environment director for Cuadrilla, said drilling activities were halted during the height of the protests because police advised that the firm was unlikely to get vehicles on and off the site.
He told the court that even though there was a reduction in Cuadrilla staff, there were 27 security staff on site and police officers who needed to be provided with fresh food and water and toilet facilities, and that deliveries of fresh supplies still needed to be made.
He said he and his staff were subjected to ``intimidation'' and ``scaremongering'' by some of the protesters throughout their time at the site but that he did not have a problem with anyone making a peaceful protest.
He claimed that some protesters had called him a ``baby killer'', as well as asking him ``how do you feel working for a company that's going to give everyone cancer?'', the court heard.
Tom Wainwright, representing Lucas and Potts, said: ``You were thoroughly fed-up ... certainly by the end of the operation in September, with the fact there were protests going on outside.''
Mr Jennings said: ``Peaceful protest is a human right and we accept that. As soon as we start to get abuse to staff it's a different situation, and staff were intimidated and upset by that.''
Mr Wainwright said: ``You have exaggerated the behaviour of those protesting because of how you feel about them, haven't you?''
Mr Jennings replied: ``Not at all.''
Lucas, from Brighton; Jarman, from Hook, Hampshire; Potts, from Totnes, Devon; Dobraszczyk, from Bristol; and Menon, from north-east London, all deny wilful obstruction of the highway and breaching Section 14 of the Public Order Act. end
]]></text></news-item>