<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-FYB1-JC86-C4KD"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Tanzania; To Attain 'Water for All' Target, We Must Protect Sources</title><source>Africa News</source><author>Tanzania Daily News (Dar es Salaam)</author><text><![CDATA[LAST week, Tanzania joined other countries in the world to mark the International Water Week (March 16-22) despite the government's popular appeal "water for all" remaining a distant dream.
Access to safe drinking water is a major problem in most communities in developing nations where a substantial percentage of the population depends on unsafe sources to meet their needs.
The World Health Organization (WHO) estimates that about 1.1 billion people rely on unsafe drinking water sources in developing countries and that the lowest drinking water coverage rates of 58 per cent are in sub- Saharan Africa.
The situation becomes more pronounced in the dry season as only a handful of people have access to potable water in the form of boreholes and hand-dug wells. In most cases, the majority of people living in the rural areas depend on sources which are contaminated and also susceptible to waterborne diseases.
WHO estimates that water-related health problems kill more than five million people annually with children under five years being the most affected victims.
It is, therefore, irrefutable that Tanzania must step up efforts to achieve Goal Seven of the Millennium Development Goals (MDGs) which aims at halving by next year the proportion of people without sustainable access to safe drinking water and basic sanitation.
This means that there is the need to create the political will, partnership and resources to manage water, especially in the growing urban centres to help reduce to the barest minimum water-borne diseases with their attendant consequences on socio-economic development.
Health experts say safe drinking water is that precious fluid containing microbial, chemical and physical characteristics that meet the WHO guidelines or national standards on drinking water quality. It is against this background that all hands ought to be on deck to investing in systems that address the needs of the people.
The solution to the water crisis isn't simple since it's a big problem requiring a big answer. The water crisis is only going to end when all of us work together with each other, with other NGOs and with the communities that government seeks to serve.
In Tanzania, experts in the Ministry of Water say that in the past two decades, the country has experienced increased pressure on available water resources. They say demand for the indispensable liquid has increased considerably due to increased population and socio-economic activities.
Currently, the country's urban and rural water supply coverage is about 73 per cent and 53 per cent respectively, for domestic use.
This means that three in 10 urban residents have difficulty in accessing clean and safe water, while one in two of their rural counterparts has a similar experience. However, Minister of Water Prof. Jumanne Maghembe says that the government is committed to realising its vision of improving water supply to reach 90 per cent of the population, under the National Development Vision for 2025.
He says that without availability of water for domestic and other use, the country cannot achieve the UN's Millennium Development Goals as well as the National Strategy for Growth and Poverty Reduction (MKUKUTA).
The nation's water policy targets are to raise the proportion of rural population that has access to safe and clean water from 53 per cent to 60.5 per cent by this year and for the urban population from 73 per cent to 90 per cent.
There is also pressure from the agricultural and energy sectors, where growth depends on increased supply of water for irrigation and hydroelectric power generation.
However, plans for rural and urban water supply and sewerage services are only achievable if secure water resources are available, protected and used sustainably - a factor that is now a matter of serious concern.
There are cases where pastoralists and farmers have invaded riverbeds leading to destruction of ecosystems and water supply to dams feeding hydropower generation plants.
Environmentalists in Tanzania and elsewhere in East Africa are concerned with the perilous rate of deforestation that has disturbed climatic trends.
They say the "climate impasse is rooted, not simply in our dependence on a fossil fuel economy, but more broadly, in our love affair with mass consumption, made possible by global capitalism, and in our faith in Progress--that science and technology will forever improve the conditions of human life."
For us in Tanzania, our most important task as far environmental issues are concerned, is to protect our water sources to enable them protect us.
]]></text></news-item>