<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-GVN1-F0BC-M3R6"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Exxon exec. talks at ACU about challenges in oil, gas industry (w/video)</title><source>Abilene Reporter-News (Texas)</source><author>Mark Smith mark.smith@reporternews.com 325-676-6720</author><text><![CDATA[A senior executive for an oil and gas giant was in Abilene on Wednesday to speak at a college’s luncheon about the industry’s challenges, as well as emphasize to students that leadership doesn’t begin with a title.
Mark W. Albers, senior vice president of Exxon Mobil Corp., was the spring speaker for Abilene Christian University’s Distinguished Speakers Series luncheon. He compared the current oil boom in Texas to other discoveries and waves in the industry’s past. “We’re in one of those waves now,” Albers said in his speech at ACU’s Hunter Welcome Center. “(There’s an) enormous development of unconventional oil and gas development, all started by a Texas businessman, George Mitchell of Mitchell Energy. “It’s an exciting time,” said Albers, a Texas A&M grad with a degree in petroleum engineering. But it’s also a time when the world is facing several large-scale challenges that can involve the oil and gas industry, “when the world is dealing with a number of fundamental issues.” He said many developing economies are struggling to get on their own two feet, “and that’s leading to conflict among nations.” He said two other issues economies around the world are facing are raising the standards of living for those in poverty and possible climate change. “I think energy provides a pretty special thread as a possible solution to dealing with all this,” Albers said, adding that oil and gas companies should rise to the challenge to provide affordable energy to developing countries, allowing residents to “enjoy the same standards of living you and I enjoy, and to do that in a way that reduces greenhouse gas emissions.” Monday was the 25th anniversary of the Exxon Valdez oil spill in Prince William Sound in Alaska that, at the time, was the largest oil spill in U.S. waters. Before the luncheon, Albers said Exxon Mobil used what he called a “tragedy” as a learning opportunity. “I think we really learned from and used that to develop the whole way we approach operations integrity,” he said. In the last half of his speech, Albers encouraged those in the audience, especially the small number of students, to use their strengths to be good leaders who have influence on others. “The leader is the one with courage, not title,” he said, illustrating his point with the biblical story of David and Goliath, saying David was confident and used his strengths to lead his people and defeat their enemy, Goliath.
]]></text></news-item>