<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-RBS1-F15H-C3CJ"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Milton Keynes animal lab dogs and kittens born to die</title><source>Milton Keynes Citizen</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Dozens of puppies and kittens are literally being born to die at a laboratory in the heart of Milton Keynes.
An investigation has revealed that animals have been experimented upon then killed at MSD headquarters in Walton.
Ironically the company specialises in animal health, producing vaccines and drugs for vets and governments all over the world.
But inside the modern industrial building "sickening" practices are taking place, say the Anti-Vivisection Coalition which cites the undercover investigation carried out by the British Union for the Abolition of Vivisection.
A female scientist from the latter group worked undercover at MSD for eight months, taking secret film footage of employees in action with the animals.
An example of this footage can be viewed {http://www.buav.org/undercover-investigations/born-to-die/ | here | } but it carries a warning that it's highly distressing and NOT suitable for younger viewers.
The content includes an MSD worker dismembering a dead Beagle puppy and quipping, "Right, now I am going to do something gruesome", before tipping the intestines into a bin.
It reveals how puppies are taken away from their mothers to be used for experiments. The mothers are killed minutes later and the puppies are given a lethal injection after a few weeks.
We are also providing a link to the scientist's diary, which is equally harrowing.
MSD is not breaking the law in any way, but the AVC is now campaigning strongly for legislation to be changed to abolish animal experiments completely.
AVC spokesman Sophie Kennerley said: "MSD has a responsibility to listen to the public outrage and release these animals for rehoming."
The AVC is organising a protest demonstration outside the MSD building at 1pm tomorrow (Friday).
A spokesman for MSD told the Citizen the company was committed to advancing the health of animals and preventing deadly diseases such as parvovirus, feline leukaemia and myxomatosis.
He added: "We adhere to all regulatory standards of testing and development of vaccines and our standards for animal care meet or exceed applicable local, national and international laws and regulations."
He said MSD strove to use the fewest number of animals, minimise any discomfort they feel and "whenever possible" tried to find homes for them.
For more information visit the {http://www.buav.org/undercover-investigations/born-to-die/investigators-diary/ | BUAV website | }
]]></text></news-item>