<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-JXY1-JCW9-X32H"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>Bill would make California first state to require drug-makers to fund disposal program</title><source>Ventura County Star (California)</source><author>Timm Herdt</author><text><![CDATA[SACRAMENTO — Saying that unused and expired medications piling up in household cabinets are creating a serious public health problem by contributing to prescription drug abuse and contaminating drinking water, Sen. Hannah-Beth Jackson on Wednesday pushed a bill “asking the pharmaceutical companies to join us in tackling the problem.”
The measure, which was approved on a party-line vote by the Senate Environmental Quality Committee, would require prescription drug manufacturers to create and manage a take-back system to allow consumers to return unused medications so they can be safely destroyed. Lawmakers have struggled with the issue of disposal of in-home medications for years, establishing a patchwork system of local collection programs in 2007 and directing the Department of Resources Recycling and Recovery to develop model guidelines. Programs range from one-time “take-back” days, such as one scheduled for April 26 in Ventura County, where collection bins will be deployed at police stations in every city, to an ongoing pilot program in San Francisco that involves the participation of 13 neighborhood pharmacies and all 10 city police stations. But the patchwork of local efforts, Director Caroll Mortensen told the panel, have been largely unsustainable and expensive for local governments to run. The number of collection sites has dropped from about 300 statewide in 2010 to about 275 today, she said. A panel convened by the department has endorsed the idea of converting to a model called “extended producer responsibility,” similar to existing programs that involve manufacturers in the collection of discarded consumer items such as tires, motor oil, car batteries and mattresses. Jackson, D-Santa Barbara, seeks to make California the first state in the nation to require the pharmaceutical industry to fund a program to facilitate the disposal of unused drugs. “People don’t know what to do with them,” she said. “What do we do in California? We flush them in the toilet. We dump them in the garbage.” Operators of wastewater systems say their treatment processes are designed to deal only with biological waste, and that traces of drugs that are flushed into sewers inevitably end up in waterways, creating potential environmental dangers for people and wildlife. Law enforcement groups are also pushing for a more convenient take-back system, one that they believe could reduce the availability of addictive prescription drugs that are increasingly being abused by teenagers. Erin Loback, an Alameda County deputy district attorney, said the state needs “a safe and structured way to dispose of highly addictive prescriptions, and it has to be relatively convenient. We are asking that pharmaceutical companies step up and take responsibility for the product they created.” The industry strongly opposes Jackson’s bill, and a representative told senators she believes the extent of the problem is being overstated. “Prescription medications are intended to be used. We think patients should be taking all medications prescribed,” said Marjorie Powell, an attorney for the Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America. “When used as expected, there is no pharmaceutical waste.” Powell and other industry lobbyists recommend that unused pills be disposed of by mixing them with kitty litter or coffee grounds, placing the mixture in a plastic bag and tossing it in the trash. “We are advocates of in-home disposal,” Powell said. “You don’t have to wait. You can get rid of it immediately after you don’t need it.” She said that if California is to adopt a program, the responsibility for funding it should be shared by other parties, including pharmacies. “This applies only to manufacturers,” Powell said of Jackson’s bill. “It would exempt everyone else in the distribution system.” Chairman Jerry Hill of San Mateo, who joined the panel’s four other Democrats in supporting the bill, advised Jackson that he may not vote for it in the future unless she broadens responsibility for funding the program to include retail pharmacies. “This puts the responsibility at the top of the chain, and there’s no responsibility for anyone else,” he said. Sen. Fran Pavley, D-Agoura Hills, said her vote was based on her growing concern over what she called an epidemic of prescription drug abuse. “There’s a growing epidemic with teenagers and young adults with what they call ‘medicine-cabinet parties,’” Pavley said. “Once addicted, they are switching to heroin. I live in a small community of 400 homes. Two kids died last year of drug overdoses.” The bill next goes to the Business, Professions and Economic Development Committee. -- Disposal Bin Locations Call your local police department for safe, confidential drop-off bins. According to Ventura County Behavioral Health, here are a few locations in Ventura County: Camarillo Police Department, 3701 East Las Posas Road, 388-5100 East County Patrol Station, 2101 East Olsen Road, Thousand Oaks, 494-8260 Fillmore Police Department, 524 Sespe Ave., 524-2233 Headquarters Patrol Station, 800 South Victoria Ave., Ventura, 654-2304 Moorpark Police Department, 610 Spring Road, 532-2700 Ojai Police Department, 402 South Ventura St., 646-1414 Oxnard Police Station, 251 South C St., 385-7740 Port Hueneme Police Department, 250 North Ventura Road, 986-6530 Simi Valley Police Department, 3901 Alamo St., 583-6950 Ventura Police Department, 1425 Dowell Drive, or at the Westside Resource Center, 110-K N. Olive St., Ventura, 339-4400 The National Prescription Drug Take-Back Day will be held from 10 a.m. to 2 p.m. April 26. Locations will be available Tuesday. For more information about disposing of prescription and over-the-counter drugs, go to http://tinyurl.com/lp5pcs8.
]]></text></news-item>