<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-7631-JBF5-T032"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Crocodile safari hunting: Environment Minister Greg Hunt scuppers NT plan</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Plans for crocodile safari hunting in the Northern Territory have been rejected by Federal Environment Minister Greg Hunt.
The Territory Government wanted to trial trophy hunting of large saltwater crocodiles.
The Federal Environment Department has been consulting with traditional landowners, environmental groups, industry stakeholders and animal rights groups about the proposal.
Today Mr Hunt said the plan would not be allowed to go ahead.
"My view is that there was a risk of cruel and inhumane treatment. That was in my view, inappropriate," Mr Hunt said.
"There have been a series of ministers, both on the Coalition side and on the other side, that have periodically rejected this.
"So no crocodile safaris in the Northern Territory."
A leading crocodile scientist said he was disappointed with Mr Hunt's decision.
Professor Grahame Webb, who runs Crocodylus Park in Darwin, said the Federal Government was not prepared to stand up to animal rights activists.
"They're frightened of the animal rights and animal welfare lobbies down in Canberra, I don't think they care too much about landowners and crocodiles up here," he said.
"I would say they're being lobbied by people who just think this is outrageous."
Jida Gulpilil from the Gupulul Marayuwu Aboriginal Corporation says the decision is unjust.
He says safaris could have provided much-needed economic development.
"It's another feather in the Government's hat when you are talking about taking away the rights of Aboriginal people," he said.
"For the Federal Government to come in under the Crown lawlessly, and take away the rights of Aboriginal people, to continue hunting and gathering through this modern day and age that we all live in and have evolved through, is unfair and it's unjust."
The majority of saltwater crocodiles are found on Aboriginal lands and waterways.
The Territory Government wanted to trial the hunting for two years, with up to 50 of the large protected crocodiles killed annually.
The Environment Department said it received hundreds of formal submissions from industry groups and environmental organisations, including Humane Society International.
Society spokeswoman Alexia Wellbelove said there was no significant economic benefits for Indigenous communities and a real risk of destroying other tourism brands.
"(It) rewards very few or benefits very few people," she said.
"We believe very strongly that there is far more potential in the remote areas of the Top End in ecotourism than there are for elitist safari hunting activities."
]]></text></news-item>