<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-YW11-JCG2-C25J"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Inspectors praise support for victims</title><source>Nuneaton News</source><author>Claire Harrison</author><text><![CDATA[DOMESTIC abuse victims across Nuneaton, Bedworth and North Warwickshire officially have access to a 'good' service.
That is according to the findings of HM Inspectorate of Constabulary (HMIC) report which says that Warwickshire Police provides a 'good' service to those who suffer at the hands of domestic abuse.
HMIC inspectors also reported that the public can have confidence that the local police force is 'working well' with partners to tackle domestic abuse and keep victims safe.
But the report did state that while dedicated to tackling domestic abuse, there is still room for improvements and it outlined areas where the force could further strengthen its response.
On the whole, the good news is being celebrated not only by the local police force, but also the many organisations it works with to help tackle incidents of domestic abuse, which is particularly high across Nuneaton and Bedworth.
Speaking about the findings of the HMIC report, Warwickshire's Deputy Police and Crime Commissioner Eric Wood said: "I particularly welcome the fact that those who commit domestic abuse in Warwickshire are more likely to be charged or cautioned than in many other parts of the country.
"Victims of domestic abuse in Warwickshire should feel confident that the police and their partners are skilled and committed to providing an effective service.
"The safety of victims is paramount and I am determined to ensure we continue to build on this good work."
Police and partners including Warwickshire County Council and support agencies work together, under the banner of 'Warwickshire Against Domestic Abuse', to encourage anyone affected by domestic abuse to seek help.
Sue Ingram, domestic abuse manager at the county council, explained: "In Warwickshire we believe that agencies must work together if we are to effectively support those affected by domestic abuse and prevent future harm.
"Warwickshire Police is central to our partnership and we are delighted that HMIC recognise the good service they provide.
"However, this outcome would not be possible without the hard-work and commitment from many agencies, notably Warwickshire's specialist domestic abuse services, and this positive inspection outcome is testament to what can be achieved when working together."
Police say that their links with their partner agencies, as well as using new powers, such as the Domestic Violence Disclosure Scheme also known as Clare's Law, all help to provide what they have described as a 'robust response' to domestic abuse across the whole of the county.
The force also has a policy of taking positive action in all domestic abuse incidents. For every 100 domestic abuse crimes recorded, there were 63 arrests in the county.
It also says that the checking of children who are present when officers respond to reports of domestic abuse is routine practice across the force.
But it is not simply about arresting and prosecuting offenders.
All of the partners involved in tackling domestic abuse are keen to ensure that victims do not suffer in silence.
People are being urged to visit www.talk2someone.org.uk to find out more about domestic abuse.
Extra information about domestic abuse is available for victims, perpetrators, friends and family, and young people by visiting www.talk2someone.org.uk or by calling the Warwickshire Against Domestic Abuse helpline on 0800 408 1552.
The helpline is open 9am - 9pm Monday to Friday and 8am - 4pm on Saturdays.
Outside of these hours, people can call 0808 2000 247, the freephone 24 hour National Domestic Violence Helpline, run in partnership between Women's Aid and Refuge.
]]></text></news-item>