<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-BN21-JC92-P4CD"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Moscow press review for March 27, 2014</title><source>Russia &amp; CIS Energy Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The following is a digest of Moscow newspapers published on March 27. Interfax does not accept liability for information in these stories.
POLITICS & ECONOMICS
The Russian government plans to spend the whole anti-crisis reserve of the federal budget, formed with the frozen pension savings of Russians, on Crimea. The Black Sea peninsula could get more than 240 billion rubles this year alone. This does not include the cost of infrastructure development in the region, so the government might have to cut other spending (Vedomosti, p. 1).
The Russian delegation to the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council Europe might suspend its participation in the organization's work at the April session if the assembly decides to hold a vote to strip Russia of voting rights or accreditation. European deputies are proposing such measures in response to Russia's policy in regard to Ukraine and Crimea (Kommersant, p. 1).
The World Bank forecasts that Russian economic growth will slow to 1.1% in 2014 if the impact of the geopolitical crisis over Crimea does not last long, but that Russia's economy could contract by 1.8% this year if the political tensions and uncertainty linger or deepen. Even the forecast of growth implies a technical recession in the first half (Vedomosti, p. 4).
The middle class in Russia grew from 27% to 60% of the population from 2001 through 2010 thanks to growth of wages and pensions, a new World Bank study shows. But the economic slowdown is expected to stall this growth. The expansion of the middle class will depend on the success of government policies to create new jobs for young people, women and the older generation (Kommersant, p. 2).
OIL & GAS
U.S. President Barack Obama has said that the United States can fully replace Russia on the European gas market. Gazprom, whose share of the European and Turkish gas markets reached a record 30.07% in 2013, dismissed the statement and said it would not affect the gas giant's negotiating position. The U.S. will only be able to really challenge Russia on the European market after 2020, one expert said (Vedomosti, p. 1).
Novatek's board is supposed to approve the sale of a major asset worth at least 20 billion rubles on Monday. Market players believe Russia's biggest independent gas producer might sell 9.8% of SeverEnergia to Gazprom Neft. This would enable Novatek to restore parity ownership at the oil and gas venture with Gazprom Neft, which was upset last year in the fight for this asset with Rosneft (Kommersant, p. 7).
BANKING, FINANCE & INSURANCE
The Economic Development Ministry is proposing to allow Russia's Export Credit and Investment Insurance Agency to offer 100% guarantees on export credits. This means the agency would be able to provide full coverage on export credits for Sukhoi SuperJet 100 airliners and the construction of the South Stream gas pipeline (Vedomosti, p. 10).
DeltaCredit, one of Russia's leading mortgage lenders, placed bonds at 12% on Wednesday, 3.5 percentage points higher than its previous offering. The higher cost of borrowing could push up mortgage rates, analysts said. Some state banks have already begun raising rates, and if the situation on the market does not change in the next two months rates could jump at least 1.5-2 percentage points (Kommersant, p. 7).
RETAIL & CONSUMER MARKET
Along with Crimea's tourism industry, the Russian authorities are preparing to save the region's winemaking industry. Authorities in the Moscow Region, Moscow and St. Petersburg are asking major retail chains to support Crimean wines by allocating separate shelf space and organizing tastings. Crimean companies are hoping retailers will at least offer a "flexible price policy in regard to payment for sales promotions" (Kommersant, p. 1).
A1, the investment arm of Russia's Alfa Group, is selling its Formula Kino chain of movie theaters. One of the suitors is Russia's biggest chain, Cinema Park, which is owned by Vladimir Potanin's Interros group. Market players value Formula Kino at $250 million to $350 million (Vedomosti, p. 10).
Russia's Federal Anti-Monopoly Service has found a new source of revenue for retail chains - fictitious services. For some suppliers such services, which usually fall under the umbrella of marketing services, can total up to 50% of turnover. The regulator intends to focus on this issue in its next phase of inspections of food retailers (Vedomosti, p. 11).
Russian government officials have stopped using Apple iPads for work, and have instead switched to the tablets of South Korea's Samsung. This is because the Samsung devices offer better protection from hackers, not because of U.S. sanctions against Russia, the communications minister said (Vedomosti, p. 11).
TELECOMMUNICATIONS, MEDIA & TECHNOLOGY
The CEO of Russia's Channel One on Wednesday urged Ukraine to reverse a decision to suspend transmission of four Russian channels because it contradicts the "standards of international law and the interests of subscribers." A Kyiv court will begin hearings Thursday in a lawsuit brought by Ukraine's National Council of TV Broadcasters against satellite company Torsat. The suspension could result in financial losses for both the Russian channels and their distributors in Ukraine (Kommersant, p. 1).
Internet resources that systematically commit piracy need to be shut down and legislative amendments have to be made to allow this, Russia's culture minister said Wednesday. However, this would not solve the problem of piracy as resources can move to another domain and open under a different name (Kommersant, p. 1).
Vp ak
(Our editorial staff can be reached at eng.editors@interfax.ru)
]]></text></news-item>