<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV6-FYW1-JC3H-045R"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Report recommends D.M. scrap its human rights commission</title><source>Des Moines Register</source><author>By, Jason Clayworth</author><text><![CDATA[Des Moines would relinquish its human rights investigations under a controversial proposal to be considered tonight during a special meeting.
The city's fiscal hawks have long argued investigations into illegal discrimination are being duplicated by both the city and a state agency located just blocks apart in the capital city. They question why Des Moines taxpayers spend $300,000 to $400,000 annually for the commission when its functions could be shifted to a state agency already doing much of the same work.
Human rights advocates contend the commission is far more valuable than fiscal savings, and a practical understanding of how it works is missing from the debate.
The commission has legal authority to investigate, fine and pursue prosecution of illegal discrimination in Des Moines based on such things as race, sexual orientation and mental or physical disabilities that occur in employment, housing, municipal practices and public accommodations. It is one of 26 city or county civil rights or human rights commissions in the state.
The statewide Iowa Civil Rights Commission also conducts investigatory work and frequently takes on Des Moines cases.
Supporters of the Des Moines commission point out the state has had a backlog of investigations in previous years, forcing some people to wait years for justice and pushing many to simply give up. Local investigators also have knowledge and community relationships that help to quickly resolve complaints, they argue.
"Would you favor dismantling Des Moines Police in order to fund only the Polk County Sheriff, state patrols or the FBI? Probably not," said Rudy Simms, director of the Des Moines Human Rights Commission.
The Register investigated the 63-year-old Des Moines commission last fall as part of a review of the state's civil rights complaints. That review found the Des Moines commission closed or resolved 33 complaints in the fiscal year that ended June 30. The Iowa commission, a statewide agency, processed 306 complaints from Des Moines during that same time.
Des Moines' cost per case based on its entire budget was $10,333. The state commission's cost - after handling 2,182 cases statewide in the fiscal year that ended June 30 - was about $595 per case.
Simms noted the per-case cost comparisons fail to take into account other activities by his commission, such as community education or outreach. He likened the comparisons to judging a fire department by the number of calls it receives.
City Councilwoman Christine Hensley said her interest in transferring investigations to the state goes beyond finances.
"When you look at the numbers, I don't think we have a track record that would support continuing to do it," Hensley said, noting the state is already investigating more cases in Des Moines than the city commission. "It's already happened without us actually being part of it because people are going to the state on their own."
Strategic plan questioned
Concerns about the commission's effectiveness promoted the city to hire Resource Development Consultants - a business owned by Sen. Matt McCoy of Des Moines - to help create a strategic plan. That plan, which cost about $12,000, recommends that the agency focus on investigations starting in 2015.
Under the plan, Des Moines' commission would still in most cases receive between $250 to $500 in federal money per case turned over to the state, the report shows. The report also notes the state's staff of 28 far outnumbers Des Moines' three employees.
David Meeks, a former civil rights specialist for the state, criticized the study. He said it lacks testimonials from local commissions and didn't adequately review results-based data.
Meeks plans to speak at tonight's special meeting against shifting the Des Moines commission's investigations to the state.
"You can't take this lightly," Meeks said. "This has to be based on reliable results-based data, not comparing the Iowa Civil Rights Commission with local numbers."
The Iowa Civil Rights Commission currently has agreements with 11 local agencies to provide services. In West Des Moines, for example, all complaints filed with its human rights commission are transferred to the state for investigation. The local commission's $5,500 annual budget is used almost exclusively for education purposes.
Beth Townsend, director of the Iowa Civil Rights Commission, has declined to comment about Des Moines' study, saying it's a local decision. But she has disagreed with comments insinuating the state's investigations are inferior to the investigations by local commissions.
Assessing the commission's work
Unlike local agencies, where a commission's staff generally makes key decisions about innocence or guilt, the state issues "probable cause" determinations through a system using the review of an administrative law judge not associated with the case. The state commission also relies on an assistant attorney general to represent it in hearing and court matters, Townsend said.
Des Moines Mayor Frank Cownie said Wednesday that he isn't yet convinced the city should drop its human rights investigations. Cownie would like the city in the next month to adopt an operating plan that - at least for the next few years - would allow the commission to continue its investigative duties.
Such a plan must, however, include aggressive goals and a fair way to assess the city commission's work, Cownie emphasized. Much of the intimate details of the commission's work is, by law, closed to the public, making an assessment of the city or the state's work difficult, he noted.
"We have a responsibility to take care of these issues in a responsible way," Cownie said. "If this was your family member who was discriminated against and was making a complaint, you would want to make sure it's handled appropriately. That's what we all want."
ONLINE
Read the city's 119-page report that recommends scrapping the Des Moines Human Rights Commission's investigations online with this article at DesMoinesRegister.com
About the Des Moines Human Rights Commission
The Des Moines Human Rights Commission was created in 1951 - the first human or civil rights commission in Iowa. That was 14 years before the 1965 Iowa Civil Rights Act passed the state Legislature.
Today, the overarching purpose of the commission is to investigate complaints of discrimination in Des Moines based on age, ancestry, color, creed, physical/mental disability, familial status, gender identity, national origin, race, religion, sex or sexual orientation.
The commission reviews complaints in the area of employment, public accommodation, housing and municipal practices. It completes complaint investigations, resolves complaints through mediation and conciliation, interprets civil rights and aspects of diversity, and offers educational opportunities.
The commission has three employees, fewer than half what it had in the late 1980s and early 1990s. It processed 33 complaints in the latest fiscal year that ended June 30, when its total budget was $368,272.
TALK ABOUT IT
WHAT: A special public meeting between the Des Moines City Council and the Des Moines Human Rights Commission
PROPOSAL: To end the commission's investigatory work
WHERE: Des Moines City Hall's council chambers, 400 Robert D. Ray Drive
TIME: 5:30 p.m.
]]></text></news-item>