<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-4FG1-JB4P-V4PJ"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>SHAREHOLDERS ALERT: Pomerantz Law Firm Investigates Claims On Behalf of Investors of InterCloud Systems, Inc. - ICLD</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Pomerantz LLP is investigating claims on behalf of investors of InterCloud Systems, Inc. ("InterCloud" or the "Company") (NasdaqCM: ICLD) (CUSIP: 458488103).  Investors are advised to contact Robert S. Willoughby atrswilloughby@pomlaw.comor 888-476-6529, ext. 237.
The investigation concerns whether InterCloud and certain of its officers and/or directors have violated Sections 10(b) and 20(a) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934.
On March 13, 2014, an article published on the Seeking Alpha website, cited emails sent by John Mylant, a professional Options trader, which disclosed that John Mylant, was a paid promoter who worked closely with the companies that employed him to publish favorable articles while falsely stating that he was independent of the companies he promoted.   One of the Company's Mylant was allegedly employed to promote was Intercloud. 
On this news, shares of InterCloud fell $1.19 to $11.91, or more than 9.08%, on unusually heavy trading volume, on March 13, 2014. 
The Pomerantz Firm, with offices in New York, Chicago, San Diego, and Florida, is acknowledged as one of the premier firms in the areas of corporate, securities, and antitrust class litigation. Founded by the late Abraham L. Pomerantz, known as the dean of the class action bar, the Pomerantz Firm pioneered the field of securities class actions. Today, more than 70 years later, the Pomerantz Firm continues in the tradition he established, fighting for the rights of the victims of securities fraud, breaches of fiduciary duty, and corporate misconduct. The Firm has recovered numerous multimillion-dollar damages awards on behalf of class members. Seehttp://www.pomerantzlaw.com.
CONTACT:Robert S. WilloughbyPomerantz LLPrswilloughby@pomlaw.com 
SOURCE Pomerantz LLP
]]></text></news-item>