<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-60C1-JB2D-54M2"><date>2014-03-26</date><title>EC liquor wholesaler loses case</title><source>Daily Dispatch (South Africa)</source><author>Siya Miti</author><text><![CDATA[SAB welcomes tribunal verdict By Business Reporter EASTERN Cape liquor wholesaler Big Daddy's lost its 10-year battle of anti-competitive pricing and distribution against beer giant South African Breweries (SAB) on Monday.
SAB welcomed the ruling by the Competition Tribunal, which was heard between 2010 and last year. The anti-competitive pricing case was referred to the Competition Tribunal in 2007after an investigation into allegations related to SAB's distribution system and pricing activities. The original complaint lodged by Big Daddy's head Nico Pitsiladis with the Competition Commission alleged that SAB charged the Big Daddy's group as a wholesaler the same price as the company charged to retailers, thereby preventing Big Daddy's from earning a fair margin on its sales to retailers. The case that was presented by the Competition Commission before the Competition Tribunal related to SAB's distribution system; an alleged practice of minimum resale price maintenance; an allegation of price discrimination and broad, diffuse allegations relating to abuse of dominance. The abuse of dominance allegations were previously separated from the "distribution" case and may proceed separately although the commission has taken no further steps on this part of the case. Queries by the Daily Dispatch were referred to Peter Pitsiladis, who could not be reached for comment. SAB executive chairman Norman Adami said the company had always been confident that it had not breached competition laws. "SAB has structured its business to serve retailers and consumers and strongly believes that all businesses have the right to distribute their products in the manner that best serves their needs," he said. One of the problems with the commission's case was that it focused entirely on the system of appointed distributors, which accounted for only 10% of SAB's methods of beer distribution. "Given this, no remedy was likely to have a great impact on the market and, even if a remedy was imposed, SAB could easily make its distribution system conform to the remaining 90% of distribution, which was not under attack from the commission," the tribunal found - Additional reporting by BDLive BATTLE FOR CUSTOMERS: The complaint by Eastern Cape wholesaler Big Daddy's in 2004 that it was unable to make any profit on the distribution of SAB products has been dismissed by the Competition Tribunal Picture: FIONA KRISCH
]]></text></news-item>