<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-DJV1-DYR7-R0T3"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Accused of taking bribes, Charlotte mayor resigns</title><source>The Virginian-Pilot(Norfolk, VA.)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[By Mitch Weiss
The Associated Press
CHARLOTTE, N.C.
Charlotte Mayor Patrick Cannon, who has been in office less than six months, resigned Wednesday, just hours after he was arrested and accused of taking more than $48,000 in bribes from undercover FBI agents posing as businessmen who wanted to do work with North Carolina's largest city.
Cannon submitted his resignation letter to City Manager Ron Carlee and City Attorney Bob Hagemann, Charlotte spokesman Keith Richardson said in an email. Cannon, 47, is charged with bribery and public corruption. The Democrat took cash, airline tickets, a hotel room and the use of a luxury apartment as bribes and solicited more than $1 million more, according to a criminal complaint from the U.S. Attorney's Office.
Cannon said in his resignation letter that the pending charges "will create too much of a distraction" for the business of the city to go forward. He said it was effective immediately.
"It is my hope that by my taking this action, the members of our City Council and the staff of the City will continue to move the City forward," he wrote. "The City is fortunate to have officials and staff who are competent, loyal and committed to advancing the interests of all of our people. I regret that I have to take this action, but I believe that it is in the best interest of the City for me to do so."
Telephone messages left for Cannon were not immediately returned. He had an initial court appearance Wednesday and was released on a $25,000 unsecured bond.
While working with the undercover agents, Cannon touted his close relationship with Republican Gov. Pat McCrory and a trip to the White House to meet with President Barack Obama and other administration officials, according to the complaint.
At one point, an undercover agent said to Cannon: "You're operating at quite a level, Patrick."
If convicted on all the charges, Cannon faces up to 50 years in prison and more than $1 million in fines.
Cannon, a longtime radio show host and the founder of E-Z Parking, a parking management company, was elected mayor in November, replacing Anthony Foxx, who was named Transportation Secretary by Obama.
According to the complaint, FBI agents posing as commercial real estate developers paid Cannon on five occasions between January 2013 and February 2014. Cannon accepted cash in exchange for access to city officials responsible for planning, zoning and permitting.
On the last occasion, Cannon accepted $20,000 in cash in the mayor's office, the complaint said.
U.S. Attorney's Office spokeswoman Lia Bantavani said the investigation was ongoing. She declined to comment further.
]]></text></news-item>