<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-S681-F0NV-F419"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>--- MISSING HEADLINE</title><source>Vincennes Sun-Commercial (Indiana)</source><author>Staff Writer</author><text><![CDATA[Coast Guard: BP let  9 to 18 barrels of oil in lake
INDIANAPOLIS - An initial assessment of a Lake Michigan oil spill shows between nine and 18 barrels of crude oil entered the lake following a malfunction at BP's sprawling northwestern Indiana refinery, a U.S. Coast Guard spokesman said Wednesday.
Coast Guard spokesman Chief Petty Officer Alan Haraf said the estimate comes from the Coast Guard's initial visual assessment Tuesday of the spill scene at BP's Whiting refinery some 20 miles southeast of downtown Chicago.
One barrel of oil contains about 42 gallons, meaning the estimate indicates between about 378 and 756 gallons of crude oil were released into the lake.
Haraf said a more accurate figure likely will be released later this week on how much oil entered the lake, where crews for BP continued their cleanup work Wednesday.
Brothers charged in 2011 slaying
ALBION - Authorities have charged a Fort Wayne man with murder in connection with the June 2011 death of a woman whose body was found in northeastern Indiana lake.
Noble County Prosecutor Steve Clouse said Wednesday that 35-year-old Andres Gonzalez Jr. was charged in the death of 36-year-old Erin Ruth Justin of Fort Wayne. His brother, 32-year-old Victor Gonzalez of Fort Wayne, is charged with assisting a criminal.
Court records state Andres Gonzalez attacked and killed Justin in the garage of his home and his brother helped him dump her body in Bartley Lake near Albion, about 25 miles northwest of Fort Wayne. Two fishermen found her body the following month.
Both men were being held Wednesday in the Noble County Jail in Albion. Information wasn't available on their attorneys.
Pence approves adoption, veterans measures
INDIANAPOLIS - Gov. Mike Pence has signed legislation designed to promote adoption, assist Indiana veterans and promote Indiana agriculture.
The governor approved a measure supporting production of industrial hemp Wednesday and a program promoting Indiana-grown products.
He signed into law Tuesday a new tax credit to promote adoption. He also approved the creation of a program for women veterans and a measure encouraging veterans to become teachers.
The signatures come as Pence is running up against the state's deadline for signing a measure, vetoing it or allowing it to become law without his signature.
Pence also signed a measure allowing central Indiana counties to vote on a mass transit system.
Turner: No violation of House ethics rules
INDIANAPOLIS - A powerful Indiana Republican lawmaker says he didn't violate ethics rules during a nursing home battle this past session.
House Speaker Pro Tem Eric Turner said Wednesday he's confident the House Ethics Committee will determine he didn't break any rules.
House Speaker Brian Bosma has called for an ethics review following reports that Turner had lobbied in private against a nursing home ban that would have hurt his family's business.
House Ethics Chairman Greg Steuerwald said the committee could meet as soon as the second week in April to consider Turner's case.
Turner's son develops nursing homes throughout the state and his business would have suffered under a construction moratorium that was under consideration. The ban died in the final days of the session.
Company to appeal proposed fine in mill death
EAST CHICAGO - A Gary construction company plans to appeal a proposed state fine of $3,500 for not alerting employees to unsafe conditions before a nearly 4-ton steel plate fell, killing one worker and injuring two others.
Pangere Corp. Vice President Bill Rathjen said Wednesday the company disagrees with the findings by the Indiana Occupational Health and Safety Administration.
A safety order issued by the agency March 11 cited Pangere for a serious violation for not warning employees they were working in front of an unsecured, 7,300-pound steel plate at ArcelorMittal's sprawling steelmaking complex in East Chicago. The plate fell Nov. 13, killing 39-year-old Michael Samuelson of Valparaiso and injuring two other workers.
The Lake County Coroner's Office ruled Samuelson died from blunt force trauma and that the death was accidental.
GE Aviation plans $100 million Indiana engine plant
WEST LAFAYETTE - GE Aviation officials said Wednesday that a $100 million jet engine manufacturing factory that it's building in Lafayette will be a key in producing its new-generation engine for passenger airliners.
The company already has orders for more than 6,000 of its new LEAP engine that's now undergoing development testing and will have its final assembly at the Lafayette factory, said David Joyce, the president and CEO of GE Aviation.
"So we're kind of in a hurry," he said. "With that backlog in sales, we've got to move fast so we hope to break ground this year in Lafayette. We hope to hire in 2015."
The company expects the factory will open in 2016 in a Lafayette industrial park and have more than 200 workers within five years. The new engine will be used by passenger jets built by Airbus, Boeing and Chinese company Comac for airlines worldwide, according to GE Aviation, which is based in suburban Cincinnati.
Indianapolis Opera calls off show amid money woes
INDIANAPOLIS - The Indianapolis Opera has called off its fourth and final production of the season because of what its leaders call financial challenges.
The opera company was scheduled to present "Albert Herring" on the weekends of April 25-27 and May 2-4 at the Basile Opera Center on the city's north side.
The Indianapolis Business Journal reports that opera officials said they started the 2013-14 season with a plan to resume putting on four productions, but decided against risking "further financial strain."
The Indianapolis Star reports the opera's last publicly available tax filing shows it had $613,000 in assets at the beginning of 2011. By the end of that year, those assets had dwindled to about $75,000.
Cummins plans new office in downtown Indianapolis
INDIANAPOLIS - Engine maker Cummins Inc. announced plans Wednesday to build a $30 million headquarters for its global distribution business in downtown Indianapolis
The company said it expected about 400 people to eventually work in the new building at the site of the former Market Square Arena while keeping its corporate headquarters in the central Indiana city of Columbus.
Cummins now has about 100 employees at two Indianapolis office locations in areas such as communications, information technology and investor relations.
The new complex, expected to open in late 2016, will include ground-floor retail, public greenspace and a parking garage, according to the mayor's office.
Cummins officials said the new office will help employee collaboration and accommodate business growth and wasn't a sign of lessening its involvement in Columbus. It has some 8,000 headquarters and factory workers in that city and nearby communities.
Arts center proposed for Indiana city's mall
COLUMBUS - Part of a central Indiana shopping mall could be converted into an arts center with a 1,200-seat auditorium.
The concept outlined to Columbus officials targets a new use for the space in the downtown Commons Mall that will be vacant after Sears closes its store there this spring.
An architect estimated it could cost about $30 million to convert the store to include the performance area and the Indiana University Center for Art + Design, along with convention and office space.
Mayor Kristen Brown tells The Republic a combination of tax money and private donations could be used for the project but that no decisions have been made.
Renovations are also being considered for the nearby 135-year-old Crump Theatre so it could host community theater and musical events.
Fire forces about 50 from Evansville restaurant
EVANSVILLE - A fire inside an Evansville restaurant forced more than 50 customers and employees to evacuate the building.
The fire broke out Tuesday night at a Logan's Roadhouse restaurant on the city's east side.
Fire officials tell the Evansville Courier & Press and WFIE-TV that the fire was contained to a wall near the restaurant's entrance. No injuries were reported.
The fire caused smoke to fill the restaurant. The cause of the fire wasn't immediately known.
IU researcher getting grant for 'machine learning'
BLOOMINGTON - An Indiana University computer scientist has received a $1.4 million federal grant to help make machines smarter.
IU says Chung-chieh "Ken" Shan will receive the funding over 46 months from the U.S. Defense Department's Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency. Shan is an assistant professor in the School of Informatics and Computing on the Bloomington campus.
Shan's work will focus on helping machines handle uncertain information so they can tackle larger, more complex data and allow more people to create such programs. It's called "machine learning."
This type of programming is used in smartphone personal assistants and self-driving vehicles.
One group of researchers is already using machine learning to develop "smart drugs" that can automatically detect, diagnose and treat a variety of diseases using a mixture of chemicals.
]]></text></news-item>