<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-JRC1-JDK3-90SF"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Four court cases that changed Alberta</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA["It punched above its weight," said Eric Adams, law professor at the University of Alberta. "The Alberta Court of Appeal had not only a tremendous impact on Canadian constitutional law, but an impact above and beyond what you might expect given Alberta's population and size."
In the 1970s, for example, the court recognized the value of the work women do in the home, transforming how property is divided during divorce.
After the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms came into effect in 1982 (as the introduction to Canada's repatriated Constitiution) the Court of Appeal helped shape it into the powerful tool it is.
LEWIS
If the government doesn't obey the law, who will? That's a question that arose in 1918 when the Court of Appeal of Alberta (then called the Alberta Supreme Court, Appellate Division) and the federal government butted heads over a case, resulting in a standoff at the Sarcee Barracks in Calgary.
Three years after Canada entered the First World War, the federal government passed the Military Service Act to deal with a soldier shortage. Some men were protected from conscription, including farmers and other Canadians in vital occupations. But a year later, when the government became even more desperate for troops, cabinet withdrew that protection and many of the people who had previously been exempt were drafted. One of them was a 21-year-old Alberta farmer named Norman Lewis, who stood up against the government and claimed he was being detained by the military against his will. His lawyer, R.B. Bennett, who would later become the 11th prime minister of Canada, argued that because the law had been changed by cabinet alone and not passed by Parliament, it was invalid.
"I don't know whether or not I would have done that at 21," said Mary MacDonald, the registrar for the Court of Appeal. "That's a brave thing to do, but then I guess if you're confronted with being conscripted and going off to war, you may have additional gumption."
In 1918, four out of five justices ruled in Lewis's favour, saying the government had acted unlawfully, and ordered that he be released from military service. But the military and the government wouldn't give up that easily. The military defied the court order and attempted to block Lewis's release by setting up machine guns at the entrance of the barracks. The government tried to move those who had been illegally drafted out of the province, where they would no longer be under the Alberta court's jurisdiction.
The one justice who had dissented, Chief Justice Horace Harvey, refused to let the federal government defy the court. He sent the sheriff to retrieve the men, resulting in a standoff. Eventually, the military relented and the government honoured the court's decision until it could be resolved by the Supreme Court of Canada.
"At the end of the day, we don't have armies to enforce our decisions; what we have is respect by Canadian citizens for the rule of law and the recognition that the government has to abide by that," Chief Justice Catherine Fraser said recently about the case. "Because if it is not prepared to abide by the law, why should any of the rest of us?"
The SCC ended up ruling in the federal government's favour, but by that point, the war was almost over. However, what the decision by the Alberta court proved was that even in precarious circumstances like war, no one - not even the government - is above the law.
TRUEMAN
Today, if you get a divorce, it's expected and taken for granted that property will be fairly divided between you and your partner. This wasn't always the case. Back in 1971 when a farm wife (known only to us as Mrs. Trueman) was getting a divorce from her husband, it was decided that because her husband bought the property and it was in his name, it was technically his. She argued that she should be entitled to her fair share because she did work that hired hands would have done, indirectly helping her husband purchase the farm. The Court of Appeal recognized the ultimate fairness of her claim and overturned the trial court's decision. She was granted half of her husband's property.
Before this ruling, divorce often put many women in a very economically precarious position. The Trueman case shines as an early example of the courts trying to level the playing field and protect women made vulnerable by divorce.
"Even if their contribution is not a financial one, their labour alone, whether it's on the farm or on the ranch or even caring for children, is something that has to be accounted for in thinking about how property should be divided," said Jennifer Koshan, a law professor at the University of Calgary.
The case helped spark legislative reform that recognized and valued the equal contributions that women make in a relationship. In 1978, Alberta's Matrimonial Property Act was enacted; it assumes an equal division of all matrimonial property, including investments, cars and household goods.
There is still some controversy surrounding the Matrimonial Property Act because it applies only to married spouses and not common law spouses, Koshan said. But, she added, while the law may seem to discriminate against common law couples, the Supreme Court of Canada has said that because they chose to be in that kind of relationship, the courts must respect that those couples may not want to be bound by the provisions of matrimonial property legislation.
"To me it's interesting in the way that law evolves and progresses over time. It took until the late 1970s for married women to be fully recognized as equal partners in the sharing of property, but that wasn't the end of the story. And there's still some potential injustices in the legislation that arguably need to be changed," Koshan said.
BIG M DRUG MART
Sunday has become one of the most important days of the week to do business in Alberta.
"Not only do we do about 25 per cent of our weekly sales on Sunday, but this is also a good day for marketing our business, as a lot of new customers come from new areas to check out Whyte Avenue," said Louise Dirks, the owner of gravitypope, a boutique shoe shop in Edmonton. "And sometimes, depending on the weather and the time of year, our Sunday sales, in six hours of being open, can surpass our Saturday sales."
Had gravitypope existed before 1982, under the Lord's Day Act it wouldn't have been allowed to do business on Sunday. That year, a drugstore in Calgary was charged for selling goods on Sunday. At the trial court, Big M Drug Mart argued that the Christian-based law, which had been in effect since 1905, infringed on its rights under the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms. The trial court agreed that it was unconstitutional for one religion to dictate the rules of all society, so it acquitted the drugstore.
"It's an early case of the court actually giving some meaning to the charter and being bold enough to actually strike down legislation because its purpose and effect were contrary to freedom of religion," said Mona Duckett, a criminal defence attorney and partner at Dawson Stevens Duckett &; Shaigec Barristers, in Edmonton.
But the case didn't stop there. It was appealed at the Court of Appeal and the Supreme Court of Canada, which both sided with the drugstore, in the end profoundly influencing national public policy by allowing Sunday to become an important money-making day across Canada.
"Freedom of religion protected the freedom not to be compelled to observe somebody else's religious holidays," Koshan said. "I think we saw a huge change and shift in the commercial landscape as a result."
HUNTER VS. SOUTHAM
A legal battle between the federal government and the Edmonton Journal that was fought all the way up to the Supreme Court of Canada in the 1980s helped the courts define a section of the charter and protect citizens from unreasonable search and seizure.
In 1982, three days after the charter became law, government officials entered and searched the newspaper's office. They seized business files and books from the publisher's office under suspicion that the Journal was violating federal legislation by engaging in unfair trading and anti-competitive business practices. Government officials were allowed to search not only the newspaper's office in Edmonton, but any of the Southam chain's locations across Canada.
The Journal sought a court order to stop the search. The matter ended up before the Court of Appeal, which ruled that the search was unreasonable and a violation of privacy and property rights under the charter. It also found that the warrant government officials had used was not authorized by a judge and therefore was invalid. The Supreme Court of Canada upheld the Court of Appeal's decision.
"Hunter vs. Southam remains the root of all search and seizure law in Canada to this day," Allan Lefever, the Journal's lead counsel on the case, said in 2003. "It has the broadest application for anyone in this country accused or suspected of a criminal offence."
"For every one of us, this is recognition that we have a right to be left alone by the government in terms of our privacy, and any government step which is intrusive on our privacy requires justification by an independent and a judicial authorizer," defence attorney Duckett added.
KEY TERMS
Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms: Recognizes and protects citizens' fundamental rights and freedoms, including the right to equality, freedom of expression and Aboriginal peoples' rights. The charter came into effect as part of the Constitution Act 1982, which came about as a result of the repatriation of the Canadian Constitution. The charter is entrenched in the Constitution, which is considered Canada's highest law. Any new law has to be consistent with the charter.
Court of Appeal of Alberta: The court of last resort for Albertans. It deals with appeals from the provincial court, the Court of Queen's Bench and several administrative tribunals. A panel of justices will make a finding of law, which then applies to the case being appealed and to similar cases throughout the province.
Supreme Court of Canada: The top court in the country. If a person were to appeal a decision made by the Court of Appeal of Alberta, that appeal would have to go to the Supreme Court of Canada in Ottawa. The court deals with appeals that have to do with an important question of law or issues of national importance.
Our six-part series on the Court of Appeal in Alberta continues next week:
April 3: People of the court
April 4: Chief Justice Catherine Fraser
April 10: Demystifying/understanding the court
April 11: The changing face of the court
© Copyright (c) The Edmonton Journal
]]></text></news-item>