<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-SCK1-J9YR-G09R"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Energy firms face probe at last: Regulator launches investigation into Big Six over soaring profits, blocks on competition and 'co-ordinated price hikes'</title><source>MailOnline</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Ofgem asks Competition and Markets Authority to launch investigation into the energy market dominated by Big Six suppliersRegulator finds the firms' profits have been soaring over the past few yearsMarket is blocked to new entrants because of the price of infrastructureMove comes one day after SSE announces prize freeze amidst political row 
Energy firms face a crackdown from the regulator Ofgem after it announced a full investigation into their business and stiffer financial penalties for breaking the rules.
A report issued today found that the Big Six gas and electricity companies have shut out smaller challengers, leading to a fall in the number of people switching energy suppliers.  
Ofgem accused the big firms of 'tacit co-ordination' in announcing price hikes at the same time, and pointed out that their profits have grown even though there is no evidence the industry has become more efficient.
The regulator plans to ask the Competition and Markets Authority to launch an investigation which will 'consider once and for all whether there are further barriers to effective competition'. 
If the investigation is approved, it will be the biggest probe into the energy market ever, and could see the Big Six forced to break themselves up in order to boost competition.
The news comes just one day after SSE, one of the six firms which dominate the market, vowed to freeze its prices for the next two years in response to pressure from customers and politicians.  
Labour has threatened to impose a compulsory price freeze on all energy companies if the party comes to power after next year's election.  
Ofgem's decision to recommend an investigation follows a probe into the 'state of the market' released this morning, which concluded that fewer customers were switching suppliers amid widespread distrust of all the big firms.  
'Profit increases and recent price rises have intensified public distrust of suppliers and highlight the need for a market investigation to clear the air,' the regulator said.  
As well as the proposed investigation, Ofgem announced a 'substantial increase' in the level of fines levid on energy firms which fail to comply with its guidelines.   
The 'state of the market' report found that the main energy firms - SSE, British Gas, EDF, E.on, npower and Scottish Power - had seen rising profits in recent years as gas and electricity bills soared.   
On average, they made profits of £3.7billion in 2012, up from £3billion in 2009, despite 'no clear evidence' of efficiency gains which might explain the companies' increased profitability. 
Overall retail profits - from supplying gas and electricity to homes and businesses - increased from £233million in 2009 to £1.1billion in 2012.  
At the same time, the average dual-fuel energy bill rose from £1,095 to £1,232, with the portion going straight to energy firms in profit soaring more than six times. 
According to Ofgem, 43 per cent of consumers do not trust energy companies to be transparent - which could deter them from actively seeking out the best tariffs and switching suppliers.  
'This low level of consumer engagement is not consistent with a competitive market,' the regulator warned. 
Recent research carried out by The Big Deal found that the number of people switching suppliers in any given year had fallen by more than 20 per cent over the past decade.
Ofgem pointed the 'incumbency advantages' enjoyed by the Big Six, which allow them to charge higher prices to loyal customers who are unlikely to switch suppliers.  
In addition, because the large companies own infrastructure such as power stations and gas pipelines, it is difficult for smaller challengers to enter the market on the same terms.  
While the regulator said there was no evidence of 'explict collusion' between the Big Six, it did point to 'possible tacit co-ordination' in the fact that the companies frequently announce price rises around the same time.  
'Although tacit co-ordination is not a breach of competition law, it reduces competition and worsens outcomes for consumers,' Ofgem said.
Ofgem divided households into three different groups - 'sticky' customers who have never changed suppliers, users on conventional dual-fuel with the Big Six, and online shoppers who are more likely to use smaller energy comanies. 
'The effect of this "three-speed market" is that the "stickiest" customers, who are more likely to belong to vulnerable groups, pay higher prices for their energy than those that are able and willing to switch supplier for a better deal,' the regulator said.  
It added that surveys had shown nearly two thirds of customers did not recall ever having switched suppliers.  
37 per cent of households are still being supplied by the company which took over their local electricity board during the market's liberalisation 15 years ago, while 40 per cent are still customers of the former monopoly, British Gas.  
Ofgem said a typical Big Six single-fuel customer could save nearly £100 a year by switching to the best-priced single-fuel tariff of other large suppliers. 
Chief executive Dermot Nolan said: 'Ofgem believes a referral offers the opportunity to once and for all clear the air and decide if there are any further barriers which are preventing competition from bearing down as hard as possible on prices. 
'The CMA has powers, not available to Ofgem, to address any structural barriers that would undermine competition. Now consumers are protected by our simpler, clearer and fairer reforms, we think a market investigation is in their long-term interests.  
'I want to make sure that consumers are put at the heart of this market, so we will continue to take action to help consumers.  
'This includes from today putting the industry on notice that any new serious breach of the rules which comes to light will be likely to attract a higher penalty from Ofgem.' 
Critics suggested that the probe would not stop fuel bills rising, denouncing it as a political move intended to deflect criticism of Ofgem and the Government.
The GMB union said the investigation would be 'bad for jobs in the UK, bad for investment and it will do nothing for consumers apart from maybe delay the relentless rise in energy bills until after an election'.
HOW TO SAVE MONEY ON FUEL: AN EXPERT GUIDE BY THIS IS MONEY
1) Regular meter readings. Make sure you check every time you receive a bill, rather than relying on an estimate by your energy provider's estimate.
2) Change to online bills. You could save up to 10 per cent.
3) Avoid prepayment meters if you can, and swap to a billed meter. Even if you have to pay to get one, it's probably worth it for the savings you'll gain.
4) If you're in financial trouble some companies offer special deals, which help ease any difficulties you might be facing. But don't just assume this will be the cheapest option - make sure you still do your homework.
5) Dual fuel (gas and electricity from the same supplier) is not always the cheapest option.
6) Monthly direct debit payments could save you five to 10 per cent as companies are more confident that customers won't default and earn interest on any overpayments. Check any extra payments are refunded at the end of the year.
7) Move beyond the Big Six. Some of the best tariffs are now offered by smaller providers such as First Utility, Ovo Energy and Spark Energy. In a recent survey, Good Energy and Ecotricity topped the table for best service with 82 per cent customer satisfaction.
Martin Lewis, founder of consumer website MoneySavingExpert.com, told ITV's Daybreak: 'Why now and not five years ago when it could have made a difference? 
'I think the hope is a more fluid market will mean relatively lower prices - but don't expect to see your bills coming down by 20 to 30 per cent, that isn't going to happen.'  
He added: 'There's visceral anger that some people in this country have to choose between heating and eating, so I'm glad to see it happen but I do have a little bit of annoyance that there's nothing in this report we didn't know. Why has it taken so long?'
Ed Miliband tweeted: 'Today's announcement shows that the energy market is broken. That's why the next Labour govt will freeze energy bills until 2017.'
Caroline Flint, the shadow energy secretary, added: 'Yesterday's price freeze from SSE showed that a price freeze is possible. Today's confirmation that the energy market is broken shows that it's needed for all customers.  
'That's why the next Labour government will freeze gas and electricity prices until 2017 and reform the market to break up the big energy companies and make tariffs simpler and fairer.'
But Energy Secretary Ed Davey said: 'This is tough action based on a detailed independent expert assessment of the state of competition in Britain's energy markets - leading to the first ever market reference for the energy markets. 
'This is just too important for people to rely on guesses about how to fix the energy markets. If we get it wrong, consumers will pay the price.' 
British Gas owner Centrica welcomed an independent review 'free from political interference', but said competition in the market was already 'intense' and rejected the suggestion there might have been 'tacit co-ordination' with rivals.  
Chief executive Sam Laidlaw also voiced fears that a lengthy probe could damage confidence at a time when investment is needed.  
'Anything that clears the air and helps rebuild trust in the industry must be a good thing,' he said.  
'Britain's energy market is highly competitive and we believe that a full independent review by a respected regulatory authority would demonstrate precisely that. 
Which? executive director Richard Lloyd said: 'It is the right decision to refer the energy market to a full-scale investigation and a hugely important step towards restoring trust in an industry that has lost the confidence of its own customers.  
'This investigation must work quickly to expose what is really happening in the energy market and confirm where competition is lacking.  
'It is make or break time for the energy suppliers, who should not wait to be forced into action but instead start now to put customers first, keep costs as low as possible and trade transparently.'
A spokesman for uSwitch.com called for an emphasis on empowering individual customers, saying: 'Many of us lack both the information and the confidence to participate in this market. 
'We need a simple, straight talking education programme that enables consumers to make the market work for them.' 
Citizens Advice chief executive Gillian Guy added: 'Households have been bearing the brunt of a failing energy market for too long. We've been calling for a competition inquiry since 2007.
'It's important this long-awaited investigation gets to the root cause of rising prices and results in a competitive and transparent market that works for all consumers.  
'Prices are up 33 per cent since 2010, seven times the increase in annual earnings. Bad service, mis-selling scandals and rising prices have all meant that trust in the industry is almost non-existent.' 
]]></text></news-item>