<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-W131-DXMP-K4PX"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Is it time to scrap IPL?; SC suggests CSK and RR be dropped this year. This is only the most recent in a series of damning indictments on the way IPL is run. Corruption, betting and nepotism are rampant. Can the system be cleansed or...</title><source>DNA</source><author>dna, &amp; Derek Abraham</author><text><![CDATA[New Delhi/Mumbai: Enough is enough - face the music now. That's the stern message the Supreme Court (SC) is sending out to the BCCI and its bullheaded president N Srinivasan.
Utterly convinced that the BCCI is not serious about cleaning up the IPL mess, the SC on Thursday proposed far-reaching changes, including replacing Srinivasan with former India skipper Sunil Gavaskar or any other "seasoned or respected cricketer", as BCCI chief. It also recommended that Chennai Super Kings and Rajasthan Royals - two franchises whose owners/officials/players were arrested for spot-fixing/betting-related activities - be suspended from participating in the upcoming edition of the league. What's more, the SC also proposed that no employee of India Cements Ltd - owned by Srinivasan - should be part of the BCCI set-up.
India skipper MS Dhoni's name was also dragged into the court. Senior lawyer Harish Salve, who represented the petitioner, Cricket Association of Bihar (CAB), slammed Dhoni for lying to the justice Mukul Mudgal committee. "Mr MS Dhoni, Mr N Srinivasan and officials of India Cements took the stand that Mr (Gurunath) Meiyappan had nothing to do with the cricketing affairs of Chennai Super Kings and was a mere cricket enthusiast supporting Super Kings," Salve said, quoting the report. He said Dhoni was pressurised into lying by Srinivasan. Dhoni is senior vice-president in India Cements Ltd.
The bench, comprising justices AK Patnaik and FM Ibrahim Kalifulla, said the detailed interim order will be passed on Friday. The final order is expected to be passed on April 16, the day the IPL is set to kick-off.
However, there are serious doubts over the league's credibility and a section of the board - especially the politicians who are busy with the elections - does not want the league to take place this year. Some reckon that the IPL be reduced to a six-team affair, sans CSK and RR. The rest, who swear by Srinivasan, are hoping that the BCCI's lawyers manage to convince the court to spare the erring franchises as their suspension could sound the death knell for the league.
The question is do we really need a league mired in corruption? From CSK to RR, from Sahara Pune Warriors to Kochi Tuskers Kerala (both scrapped), from fixing to betting, the IPL gives us reasons to doubt its credibility every year. It's less about cricket and cricketers, and more about muck and money, much of it through illegal means. Yes, it's a money-spinner and a source of livelihood to hundreds, but filth and falsity is fundamental to the IPL.
Kirti Azad seconded dna's opinion. "There should not be any second thoughts about scrapping the IPL in the current form. Any form of cricket which compromises with integrity and discipline should not be allowed to continue. The tournament itself should not make money by corrupt means," the cricketer-turned-politician said.
Meanwhile, the BCCI and CAB were asked to respond to the court's propositions by Friday. Salve contended on the colossal 'conflict of interest' allegation against Srinivasan, who did all he could to defend Meiyappan. Salve suggested the names of Gavaskar and another former captain, Bishan Singh Bedi, to replace Srinivasan.
At the beginning of the hearing, BCCI counsel Ariama Sundaram handed over a proposal, saying the board will initiate disciplinary proceedings against the persons named in the justice Mukul Mudgal committee report. He said Srinivasan was ready to 'step aside' (not 'step down') and that any other BCCI functionary could handle the day-to-day affairs till disciplinary proceedings were completed.
Asking Salve to place his submissions, justice Patnaik said: "We will have to think very hard whatever is in the interest of cricket," adding the court would consider the BCCI's proposals later. Salve submitted that the Mudgal committee's report clearly proved the conflict of interest allegation against Srinivasan and that there was sufficient evidence to remove him from the post.
LITANY OF WOES
2013: Three Rajasthan Royals players arrested for spot-fixing. Also, two co-owners arrested for betting-related activities
2013: Sahara Pune Warriors terminated for not honouring franchise agreement
2012: Players caught taking bribes during a sting operation by a TV channel
2011: Kochi Tuskers Kerala terminated for not honouring franchise agreement
2010: IPL founding chairman Lalit Modi sacked for misappropriation of funds
2009: IPL officials pulled up for DEMA violations to the tune of Rs283 crore
MONEY-SPINNER AND GAME-CHANGER
Rs396.8 crore Amount PepsiCo shelled out for title rights (2013-17), almost double of what DLF paid for the first five seasons (2008-12)
Rs8,200 crore What Multi Screen Media (formerly Sony) agreed to pay BCCI to be the IPL's official broadcast partner for nine years (2009-17)
Rs14 crore Amount Royal Challengers Bangalore shelled out for India cricketer Yuvraj Singh at the auction last month, making him the costliest player ever
Rs1,900 crore What Sahara Group paid to buy the Pune team in 2010 for a 10-year period. The franchise was terminated after IPL-6
Rs30 crore Total prize money for IPL 2014 - Rs13 crore for champions, Rs8 crore for runners-up, Rs5 crore for the third place and Rs4 crore for fourth place
]]></text></news-item>