<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-GXK1-JBJ4-22WC"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Summit Delegates Say Africa a Promising Destination for ICT</title><source>The Daily Observer (Banjul)</source><author>Alieu Ceesay</author><text><![CDATA[Delegates attending the ongoing three-day 12th Innovation Africa Digital Summit in Banjul have been speaking about the continent's enormous potentials in Information Communication and Technology, saying the gains registered so far are promising for the region.
The Summit, currently underway in Kololi under the theme "Towards Service Excellence, an integral part of the ICT sphere", seeks to support the most pressing agenda facing stakeholders in the development of the ICT sector, anchored on the need to improve quality of service, from policy to regulation in terms of networks to content management, while promoting the understanding of the needs of the very diverse African market.
This gathering brought together key stakeholders, potential investors including policymakers, regulators, service providers, major end-users, vendors and international agencies from across Africa along with International Solution Providers to share knowledge and experience in the ICT Industry.
"It has created the awareness and exposure for us as delegates because Africa seems to be a very promising destiny for technology," said Kebba Bojang, director of Customer Service at Gamcel. "The summit has also created the platform for networking and the theme is very apt. To have the technology is something but to deliver the service as expected is another thing," he noted.
Also speaking to the Daily Observer, the chief executive officer of Insist Global, a local software engineering company, Seedy Omar Bensouda, said the Summit has been quite interesting with delegates brainstorming on topical issues surrounding the development of the ICT sector. "It is an opportunity to network and hopefully there will opportunities to direct investment in the country," he noted.
He said he was particularly interested in the topics dealing with 'finance' and 'exchange' as without that it will be difficult to sustain or start businesses.
Bensouda opined that one of the biggest things that the ICT sector in the country can benefit from is the 'quality of service", something he noted is a catalyst to business. "It is important that we take on this issue if we are to be more competitive and especially if we are to create competitive products that can be exported," he stressed.
Quizzed on the issue of cyber security, Bensouda said it is a very critical topic given the potential impact it could have not only on the industry, but the country at large.
The representative of the East Africa Belgium-based Antaser Afrique bvba company, Monique Mukuna, said her company attaches great importance to the summit, noting that the good turnout is a manifestation of the importance Africa attaches to ICT. Mukuna, whose company specialises in electronic cargo traffic system, providing online import data to counter tax evasion and gives reliable import statistics for security purposes, stressed the need for Africans to use ICT wisely.
]]></text></news-item>