<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-T0C1-DYT8-R1B2"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Man sues Airgas over Putnam blast</title><source>Charleston Gazette (West Virginia)</source><author>Ryan Quinn, Staff writer</author><text><![CDATA[A man who says he was seriously and permanently injured in last May's explosion at the Airgas USA facility in Putnam County sued the company this week, alleging it exposed him to an "extremely unsafe working condition.
William Lee Parrigan's complaint, filed in Putnam Circuit Court on Tuesday, said he was "severely injured in and about his head, back, neck, hands, left leg, ears, and face, and that he "suffered first and second degree burns, scarring, hearing loss, ringing and clicking in ears, as well as Post Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD) causing him to experience nightmares, sleeplessness, and anxiety attacks.
The Winfield resident claims that even though he worked in the company's hydrogen department, superiors regularly required him to "bleed out tanks containing acetylene gas by opening their valves to allow it to escape. The suit states this was performed "without attaching any of the cylinders to a manifold system in order to prevent the release of the highly flammable acetylene gas into the atmosphere, and that requiring Parrigan to work in these conditions violated federal and state regulations and industry standards.
J. Barrett Strzelec, Airgas' director of investor relations and corporate communications, wrote in an email that the company doesn't comment on pending lawsuits.
Acetylene gas is commonly used for welding and for torches that cut metal.
Airgas' website states it has "the highest flame temperature of any common hydrocarbon and burns at 5580 degrees Fahrenheit.
In his suit, Parrigan says he and a co-worker were ordered to "bleed out about 150 overfilled tanks. About 10 minutes and 48 cylinders in, Parrigan said there was a loud and violent explosion, and he "remembers everything going black before he was immediately engulfed in flames.
Parrigan says that even though he was severely burned, he ran to get a fire extinguisher because he thought his co-worker was still in the fire. But the first cylinder explosion had set off a chain reaction that eventually blew up perhaps more than 50 tanks. Two employees were injured in the explosion.
The federal Occupational Safety and Health Administration investigated the acetylene gas explosion and cited Airgas for six violations, four of which were classified as "serious and carried a total of $19,000 in proposed fines. OSHA lists violations as serious if "there is substantial probability that death or serious physical harm could result from a hazard about which the employer knew or should have known.
U.S. Department of Labor spokeswoman Joanna Hawkins wrote in an email that Airgas is contesting the violations and is in settlement discussions with OSHA. Airgas shuttered its Putnam County facility, located off W.Va. 62 in Black Betsy, in August.
Parrigan's attorney, Rich Holtzapfel, said Parrigan is still receiving treatment for PTSD and has severe anxiety.
"They had a manifold right there that they could've emptied those cylinders into safely, but time means you can't make money off those cylinders while you're waiting to refill, Holtzapfel said. He called the explosion "a classic case of putting profits before people.
Parrigan is seeking compensatory and punitive damages.
Reach Ryan Quinn at ryan.quinn@wvgazette.com or 304-348-1254.
]]></text></news-item>