<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-44N1-JBM5-R1B3"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>MCDONNELLS REQUESTING SEPARATE TRIALS, DISMISSAL {SUMMHD} In a flurry of legal motions, former first couple adds detail to vows of innocence</title><source>Daily Press (Newport News, Virginia)</source><author> By Travis Fain  tfain@dailypress.com</author><text><![CDATA[Former Gov. Bob McDonnell and his wife, Maureen, asked for separate trials or outright dismissals Tuesday on most of the federal corruption charges filed against them.
In a flurry of motions, the former first couple again declared their innocence of criminal wrongdoing in the gift scandal that rocked the last year of McDonnell's administration.
They asked for dismissals not just because of that innocence, but argued that prosecutors overstepped the law by a wide margin, seeking to criminalize modern politics.
As of early Wednesday afternoon, the U.S. attorney's office responses to these motions had not been filed in the federal court system's online database.
The McDonnells also asked for separate trials and said Maureen McDonnell would take the 5th Amendment in her own defense, but testify in her husband's trial.
McDonnell attorneys asked for a particularly thorough jury selection process, too, given the case's high profile nature and jurors' potentially "strong views about Mr. McDonnell's political positions, as well as about politicians and public corruption generally."
These motions aren't unusual for a case of this sort, and the dismissal request repeats many of the arguments McDonnell and his attorneys have made since he was indicted in January.
"Federal law does not prohibit state officials from accepting gifts from political patrons or friends," the McDonnells' attorneys argue in a 38-page motion explaining their push for dismissal.
"The government's indictment alleges five 'official acts' in support of its claim that Mr. McDonnell corrupted the office of Governor of Virginia," it states. "But even if the Government's allegations were true (which they are not), none of these actions -- which involve arranging or suggesting meetings with government officials or attending or hosting events -- are 'official acts.'"
That's in line with what McDonnell has said many times: That he's guilty of bad judgment, but not corruption. He and his wife accepted more than $160,000 in gifts and loans from Jonnie R. Williams Sr., now the former CEO of Star Scientific, a Virginia company that once made tobacco products but has since moved into dietary supplements.
The indictment against the couple makes it clear that Maureen McDonnell catalyzed much -- but not all -- of the couple's contact with Williams. But, her attorneys argue, she's not a public official, making it impossible for her to perform the "official acts" prosecutors must prove to make the charges against her stick.
Among other things, Williams sent the family on golf outings, a lake house vacation and at least one spin in his Ferrari, the indictment alleges. In return, prosecutors say, Williams met repeatedly with the McDonnells in an effort to lend their legitimacy to his company's products.
At one point -- a few weeks after nailing down the details of a $50,000 loan Williams gave him -- the governor asked a cabinet secretary who oversaw state employee health plans to meet with Star Scientific about a dietary supplement it produced called Anatabloc.
He took some out of a pocket and told the official that the product was beneficial and that he used it himself, the indictment states.
McDonnell has said many times that he didn't do anything out of the ordinary for Williams, and some of the state officials Williams met with rebuffed him. His company didn't get any state contracts, or a hoped-for sign off to use one of its products in a study involving state employees.
Prosecutors are far too broad in defining the "official acts" they accuse McDonnell of performing, or promising, the defense argues.
"Arranging meetings without attempting to control their outcomes does nothing more than provide access and is therefore not corruption," the memorandum states, quoting case law.
"Public officials routinely refer supporters and other constituents for meetings with other government officials."
It's an interesting argument, and the case may have some wide-ranging ramifications, according to Peter White, a former assistant U.S. Attorney for the Eastern District of Virginia, which is where the McDonnell case sits.
"I think what makes it unusual is there's a certain extent to which this is politics as usual," said White, now a partner at a Washington, D.C., law firm. "The idea that a politician is doing an 'official act' ... if they're holding a reception for a big contributor at the governor's mansion -- that's problematic for how politics is done these days."
The motion to dismiss focuses on most of the charges against the McDonnells, which include several charges of wire fraud, a conspiracy charge and extortion. It requests a hearing, and the federal judge overseeing this case will decide whether to hold one.
If convicted of all, or even most, of the counts against them, the McDonnells could face decades in prison and seven figures in fines.
Fain can be reached by phone at 757-525-1759.
]]></text></news-item>