<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-X6D1-JD34-V1BF"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>STAWELL - The Environment Effects Statement relating</title><source>Ararat Advertiser &amp; Stawell Time</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[STAWELL - The Environment Effects Statement relating to the proposal by Stawell Gold Mines to open cut mine Big Hill has been released to the public.
Stawell Gold Mines put the Environment Effects Statement on public display today.
The EES is a comprehensive set of documents covering all aspects of SGM's proposal to mine two open cut pits at Big Hill over a four-to-five year period.
In launching the EES today, SGM general manager Troy Cole said the documents would be on public exhibition for 30 business days to allow residents and other interested people an opportunity to assess the proposal and to make submissions to the government.
"We encourage all Stawell residents to take the opportunity to peruse the EES as it covers a wide variety of subjects that are pertinent to the future of the Big Hill Project and to Stawell itself," he said.
The EES contains details of the project along with studies looking at a variety of associated subjects including environmental, cultural, noise, air pollution and health impacts.
"The Big Hill Enhanced Development Project is a real positive for Stawell. This project will at least partly mitigate the downturn from the imminent closure of our underground mine by providing 80 to 100 jobs for its lifespan of four to five years," Mr Cole said.
"SGM and our parent company Crocodile Gold are committed to this project and to the needs of the Stawell community."
"While we have been consulting closely with the Stawell community about the project, the EES holds answers to many of the questions people have been asking during the past 12 to 18 months and which we could not answer until the studies were completed," Mr Cole said.
If it proceeds the project will provide employment for 80 to 100 people and involve up to four years of mining activity, with a further year allowed for the full reinstatement and rehabilitation of Big Hill.
Stawell Gold Mines has been consulting with the Stawell community to ensure Big Hill becomes a significant community asset at the conclusion of the Project.
The EES is available for viewing during normal business hours at:
Northern Grampians Shire Council, Town Hall, Main Street, Stawell. Tel: (03) 5358 1274.
Stawell Library, Sloane Street, Stawell (restricted hours Tuesday - Friday 10am to 5.30pm, Saturday 10am to 12 midday, Sunday 3pm to 5pm) Telephone (03) 5358 8700.
Regional Development Victoria, Grampians Region, 111 Armstrong Street North, Ballarat VIC 3350. Tel: (03) 5327 2800 .
Victorian Government Bookshop, Level 20, 80 Collins Street, Melbourne VIC 3000. Tel: 1300 366 356.
The statement, including the technical appendices, is available for viewing online at the SGM website: www.crocgold.com/bighill.
Free copies of both the EES Summary Brochure and a DVD of the complete EES Main Report and Technical Reports are available from Stawell Gold Mines. To access a copy email: SGM.enquiries@crocgold.com.au or call 1800 771 729.
A number of printed copies of the EES Report and EES technical appendices are available for loan from the Stawell Library.
There are limited hard copies of the EES Main Report and Technical Reports for purchase.
]]></text></news-item>