<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-D521-JC60-C2B9"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Gleision mine manager gives evidence over flood deaths of four colleagues</title><source>guardian.co.uk</source><author>Steven Morristheguardian.com</author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
A colliery manager accused of being responsible for the deaths of four colleagues in a mine disaster crawled out of the flooded pit and told rescuers: "There's no hope for the others," a court heard.
Malcolm Fyfield, an experienced manager, was working with his team 100 metres underground when they heard the "deafening" sound of water rushing into the Gleision mine.
A jury at Swansea crown court was told there was a shout of "Run!", but four men were trapped. Fyfield, 58, is said to have tried to give two of them mouth-to-mouth resuscitation but had to flee as the water rose around him.
On the first day of Fyfield's trial, the court was given an insight into the extraordinarily cramped conditions the men endured in a warren of tunnels at the 100-year-old drift mine in south Wales.
Gregg Taylor, prosecuting, described how the men's jobs involved crawling on hands and knees through small tunnels and extracting coal using explosives.
Taylor said the height of some tunnels was just 77cm (30in). They continually had to pump water out to gain access to the seams of coal.
"Men worked this space by crawling on their hands and knees. This is a very historical practice."
Fyfield denies the manslaughter by gross negligence of Charles Breslin, 62, Philip Hill, 44, Garry Jenkins, 39, and David Powell, 50. MNS Mining, which ran the mine, denies four charges of corporate manslaughter.
Taylor said that at around 9am on 15 September 2011, miner David Wyatt told colleagues he was going to "fire the shots" to blast the coal from the seam. But the blast freed thousands of gallons of water that had been held in old mine workings for years.
Wyatt, another miner called Nigel Evans and Fyfield managed to get out and the emergency services were called. Fyfield later told police he tried to give Powell and Hill mouth-to-mouth resuscitation before leaving them.
Taylor said post-mortem examinations of the men found their lungs and airways were blocked with water contaminated with coal and silt.
He described Fyfield as a very experienced miner who had owned and ran a number of collieries. "As a mine manager, Mr Fyfield was very well regarded in the industry and by the mines inspectorate," he said.
The jury heard Fyfield, of Cwmllynfell, near Swansea, had been working as the manager of Gleision, near Pontardawe, for 10 weeks before the disaster.
He is suffering from severe post traumatic stress disorder and the jury was told he would need frequent breaks. His wife, Gillian, was allowed to sit alongside him.
The trial continues.
]]></text></news-item>