<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-60C1-JB2D-54KN"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Police officer grilled by Bizos over Marikana</title><source>Daily Dispatch (South Africa)</source><author>Niren Tolsi</author><text><![CDATA[By POLICE at Marikana acted contrary to their policies, with "malice of forethought" and with disproportionate force two years ago when they killed 34 striking miners, said veteran human rights lawyer George Bizos.
Bizos was questioning Lieutenant-Colonel Salmon Vermaak before the commission investigating the circumstances surrounding the deaths. He suggested that following a confrontation between police and striking miners on August 13 - where two miners and two policemen where killed - the police leadership did not follow proper procedure. This, he said, heightened the "wrong assumption" that "the crowd was the enemy [of the police]." Vermaak, who was the police air wing unit commander on the day, confirmed to Bizos there was no debriefing of police after the events of August 13, contrary to the South African Police Service's Standing Order 262. The order requires that "debriefing take place after each event or gathering and that record is kept thereof". It also requires a "thorough evaluation" to be conducted. Vermaak said this did not happen. Bizos suggested this oversight could have led to an increasing sense of animosity among police members against the striking miners: "Was there information given to you that these deaths were not to condemn the 3000 people protesting for a better wage? Was this relayed to you ... that this was a labour issue, not war talk?" said Bizos. Vermaak maintained the strike had been described among police "as a difference between employer and employee" rather than anything personal - despite the deaths of policemen on August 13. But Bizos was relentless in his interrogation of the police leadership at Marikana and their "flagrant disregard of the provisions of the standing order" including that senior police officers were not present at the first scene so that they "don't have to take responsibility" for the deaths that occurred there. Following the theme that a re-militarised police force had been given licence to "shoot to kill" by previous public utterances by police minister Nathi Mthethwa and former police commissioner Bheki Cele, Bizos questioned whether police acted according to the "principle of proportionality" - required by the standing order - when responding to the striking miners. "Many miners were shot in the back or side," said Bizos. "Do you think the actions taken by police in killing and injuring so many people in the manner that the documents [autopsy reports] show - do you think the proportionality called for in Standing Order 262 was observed?" Vermaak said he was "not in a position to comment" as he was in the air.
]]></text></news-item>