<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-DGW1-JC86-4187"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>MNI Spotlight:US Senate Approves Ukraine Loan,Russia Sanctions</title><source>The Main Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[* In a rare display of bipartisan unity, the Senate approved Thursday a Ukraine loan package while the House passed a narrower bill imposing sanctions on Russia for its incursion into Crimea. The Senate voted 98 to 2 to approve the main elements of a bill drafted by the Senate Foreign Relations bill as an amendment to a House bill. The Senate then passed by voice vote the underlying bill, sending it to the House. The Senate bill provides $1 billion in loan guarantees to Ukraine and imposes an array of sanctions on Russia. It directs the Obama administration to assist the Ukrainian government to identify, secure and recover assets linked to acts of corruption by former Ukraine President Viktor Yanukovych, members of his family, or other former or current Ukrainian government officials. [13:07 ET]
* President Barack Obama Thursday said the Eurozone has been successful in tackling its banking crisis, but actions to spur domestic demand by export-oriented countries such as Germany are needed to pull the region out of its "very slow" economic growth path. Strong coordination among euro area countries, and "smart action" by the European Central Bank, means "the financial situation has stabilized," Obama said during a joint press conference with Italy Prime Minister Matteo Renzi after a bilateral meeting in Rome. This does not mean region's recovery is complete, Obama cautioned, noting that "Europe's growth is still very slow and its unemployment rate is still very high." [13:28 ET]
* The International Monetary Fund hopes to finalize a $14-18 billion loan program for Ukraine by the end of April, once the government completes necessary "prior actions," and all the components of a total $27 billion financing package are worked out, an IMF spokesman said Thursday. While there are "no hard rules for a timeline" for approving the IMF's standby loan following the staff-level agreement announced in Kiev early Thursday, "We hope to wrap things up in April," deputy spokesman William Murray told reporters at the regular biweekly press briefing. [10:30 ET]
* The National Association of Realtors said Thursday the number of contracts signed to purchase a home in the United States, but not yet closed, declined for the eighth straight month February, but the housing market appears to be stabilizing. The NAR said that its Pending Home Sales index fell 0.8% in February to 93.9, which is down 10.5% from February of last year when it was 104.9. While contract activity is far off last year's mark, NAR Chief Economist Lawrence Yun said "the market appears to be stabilizing" as contract signings have "been little changed" over the past three months. [10:00 ET]
* Initial claims for U.S. state unemployment benefits fell more than expected in the March 22 week, decreasing by 10,000 to 311,000, the Labor Department reported Thursday. The last time initial claims were lower was November 30, 2013 when initial jobless claims were 305,000. Expectations for this week's report was for a claims level of 323,000 which would have been an increase of 3,000 from the previously reported 320,000 level. That week was revised up slightly to 321,000. The initial claims seasonally adjusted 4-week moving average fell 9,500 to 317,750 in the March 22 week, which is the lowest since the September 28, 2013 week when the 4-week moving average was 305,000. [08:30 ET]
* The final revision of U.S. Q4 GDP showed growth of 2.6%, with the only surprise that new services data altered the landscape to show more consumption, back closer to the original estimate. In the latest GDP revision, services components partly offset. Consumption, exports, and investment continued to push growth higher. Governments remain a problem as Federal spending fell 12.8% on defense cuts and budget reductions elsewhere. State and local spending was unchanged. Overall consumption was up 3.3%, its best showing since Q4 2010. [08:30 ET]
* Cleveland Federal Reserve Bank President Sandra Pianalto Thursday said the low inflation readings of the past year is a sign the economy is "not firing on all cylinders" and that the central bank is "falling short" on their jobs and price stability mandates. "To put it simply, even though we are making some progress, we are still falling short of achieving our objectives for maximum employment and 2% inflation," Pianalto said in remarks prepared for a speech at the University of Dayton in Ohio. The Cleveland Fed president, who will be replaced by Loretta Mester, currently executive vice president and director of research at the Philadelphia Fed, said the FOMC "will take into account a wide range of information in determining how long to keep the target federal funds rate low." [08:30 ET]
* France's Socialist President Francois Hollande is prepared to react quickly next week if, as expected, his party's stinging losses in nationwide municipal elections are confirmed in the second round of voting on Sunday. "The President's response to these results should be very quick," one French government official told MNI. Hollande "will show the voters that he has heard their message," said the official, who declined to provide details. It is widely speculated that Hollande will aim to appease unhappy voters with a tax cut focused on the poorest households and a major cabinet reshuffle intended to reduce the size of his government to 15 to 20 ministers from the current 37. [11:03 ET]
* Greece's Prime Minister Antonis Samaras said Thursday that the country's return to the bond market is next on the agenda while the debt restructuring debate will come after that and reiterated that no additional austerity measures will be needed. Speaking to journalists on the sidelines of the negotiations for a multi-part reform bill set to be tabled to parliament for debate Friday and voted Sunday, in remarks broadcast on Greece's DT TV, Samaras appealed to lawmakers to approve the bill. "Now, return to the markets is next and debate for the debt will follow. This way we will start our final exit from the crisis and the bail-outs," he added. [12:46 ET]
* A senior Brazil Central Bank official insisted Thursday that monetary policy is still effective against inflation and will bring the rate down, even if a long tightening cycle so far has failed to do so. "Monetary policy is doing its part and will continue to do its part. We expect that inflation indices will respond," Economic Policy Director Carlos Hamilton Araujo said at a press conference to discuss the quarterly inflation report released early Thursday. The report showed the central bank raised its 2014 inflation forecast to 6.1% from 5.6% and its 2015 forecast to 5.5% from 5.4%. [12:44 ET]
* Maxine Waters, the ranking member of the House Financial Services Committee, Thursday introduced her own plan for housing finance reform with a bill that embraces House Democrats' "core principles" for overhauling the mortgage market while also building on proposals already introduced in the Senate. Waters' proposal, called the Housing Opportunities Move the Economy Forward Act, creates a risk sharing plan and giving smaller lenders access to a "cash window." [12:28 ET]
* Standard & Poor's Thursday said the Federal Reserve's rejection of Citigroup's plan to return capital to investors, derailed by what the central bank called "a number of deficiencies" in its capital planning process, will not have an impact on the banking giant's credit rating. "We continue to assess Citi's risk position as 'adequate' because we believe Citi has improved and streamlined its risk management practice from where it was before the crisis and has made significant progress in shedding riskier assets," S&P said of the financial services institution that required a multi-billion dollar bailout from the U.S. government in 2008. [10:54 ET]
* Growth in Tenth District manufacturing activity increased in March, and producers' expectations were mostly stable at solid levels according to the Kansas City Fed's manufacturing survey Thursday. Some contacts attributed improved activity to better weather conditions. Many firms cited difficulties finding qualified workers with some additional pressure on wages. Most price indexes were stable or slightly higher. The month-over-month composite index was 10 in March, up from 4 in February and 5 in January. The composite index is an average of the production, new orders, employment, supplier delivery time, and raw materials inventory indexes. [11:00 ET]
* Freddie Mac Thursday released the results of its Primary Mortgage Market Survey, showing the 30-year fixed-rate mortgage averaged 4.40% for the week ending March 27, 2014, up from last week when it averaged 4.32%. The 15-year FRM this week averaged 3.42%, up from last week when it averaged 3.32%. [10:00 ET]
* The European Commission launched a package of new measures Thursday aimed at bolstering lending to the real economy at a time when banks are deleveraging ahead of the European Central Banks comprehensive asset review. As part of the package, the Commission will study ways to channel funds toward long-term investment projects by lowering the capital requirements on securitized products, reviving capital markets, issuing European-wide covered bonds and improving the quality of corporate governance and reporting standards inside financial companies. [08:33 ET]
]]></text></news-item>