<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-JYF1-JCPJ-W013"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Less than two years after illegal pesticide case, Scotts exits U.S. wild bird food business</title><source>Columbus Business First (Ohio)</source><author>Tom Knox</author><text><![CDATA[Scotts Miracle-Gro Co. has sold its wild bird food product line to a Seattle company.
The sale comes less than two years after the Marysville-based company was slapped with hefty fines after pleading guilty to illegally applying pesticides to its wild bird food products.
Scotts' subsidiaries agreed to pay $12.5 million in criminal and civil penalties for that and for falsifying pesticide registration documents,&nbsp; as we reported.&nbsp;
Here's what the&nbsp; Department of Justice said in announcing that fine: "In the plea agreement, Scotts admitted that it applied the pesticides Actellic 5E and Storcide II to its bird food products even though EPA had prohibited this use. Scotts had done so to protect its bird foods from insect infestation during storage.&nbsp;Scotts admitted that it used these pesticides contrary to EPA directives and in spite of the warning label appearing on all Storicide II containers stating, 'Storcide II is extremely toxic to fish and toxic to birds and other wildlife.' Scotts sold this illegally treated bird food for two years after it began marketing its bird food line and for six months after employees specifically warned Scotts management of the dangers of these pesticides. By the time it voluntarily recalled these products in March 2008, Scotts had sold more than 70 million units of bird food illegally treated with pesticide that is toxic to birds."
The divestiture marks a quick exit for the gardening megapower. Just nine years ago, Scotts (NYSE:SMG) spent $77 million to&nbsp; buy a bird seed maker based in Lafayette, Ind. That company, Gutwein & Company Inc., was the largest player in the wild bird seed market at the time.
Global Harvest Foods Ltd. is buying the product line for an undisclosed sum. Brands of note it is acquiring from Scotts include Songbird Selections, Morning Song and Country Pride.
The company will now operate Scotts bird seed manufacturing plants in Indiana, South Dakota and Texas.
"While we have made a strategic decision to exit the U.S. wild bird food business, Global Harvest stands out as a leader in the industry when it comes to the core values of quality customer service and producing the finest in seed and bird food products," Mike Lukemire, Scotts executive vice president,&nbsp;chief business operations officer, said in a statement.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Columbus Business First for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>