<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV7-C931-DYT4-V0HM"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Veteran prosecutor challenges San Bernardino County District Attorney Michael Ramos to three public debates</title><source>Inland Valley Daily Bulletin (Ontario, CA)</source><author>Joe Nelson</author><text><![CDATA[SAN BERNARDINO >> San Bernardino County District Attorney candidate Grover Merritt has challenged incumbent District Attorney Michael A. Ramos to three public debates to be sponsored by the county s three regional state bar associations.
The citizens of San Bernardino County deserve a District Attorney who is open, accessible and engaged. We are not getting that from Mr. Ramos, Merritt said in a news release Wednesday. These debates will give Ramos an opportunity to stop hiding behind his Orange County political consultant and start answering questions about his record in an open public forum.
The Orange County political consultant which Merritt refers to is David Ellis, Ramos longtime political consultant.
Ellis said in a statement Wednesday that Merritt continues drowning in ethical quicksand and that his acceptance of campaign contributions from the brother and business partner of a defendant in the high profile Colonies corruption case has raised ethical questions.
The contributions Ellis cites are from Phillip Burum, brother of Rancho Cucamonga developer and Colonies defendant Jeff Burum, who on March 19 gave $1,000 to Merritt s campaign, and a $4,000 contribution from Upland Realty Equities V, Inc., a bar owned by Burum s business partner Mark Davidson.
Burum and Davidson own the Second Avenue Saloon in Upland.
Ramos welcomes the opportunity to debate Merritt, said Ellis, but Ramos must first determine if such a debate would compromise the integrity of the Colonies case given the monetary contributions Merritt has received from Burum s friends and supporters.
Ramos Public Integrity Unit and partner in the prosecution, the Attorney General s office, will be consulted, Ellis said. Mike will never jeopardize the integrity of any pending case, or the D.A. s office for a political stunt.
Merritt said he sees nothing wrong with accepting the contributions, who he said are from taxpaying citizens not charged in any criminal case.
Jeff Burum and three former county officials stand accused of conspiring to settle a nearly 5-year-old lawsuit between Burum and the county for $102 million, in Burum s favor, in November 2006. Prosecutors allege the settlement was tainted by bribery and blackmail.
All four defendants deny any wrongdoing. Also charged are former county Supervisor Paul Biane, former Assistant Assessor and labor union president Jim Erwin, and Mark Kirk, former chief of staff for Supervisor Gary ovitt.
Merritt said in his news release that the debates would be sponsored by the San Bernardino County Bar Association, the High Desert Bar Association and the Western San Bernardino County Bar Association. He says morale at the District Attorney s Office is at an all-time low. Instead of going to bat for crime victims at trial, plea agreements have become epidemic, he says.
Ramos, 56, of Redlands was elected District Attorney in 2002 and claims to be a staunch advocate of crime victims and a tough-on-crime prosecutor, especially gang and prostitution solicitation crimes. He and his office staff helped raise public awareness on human trafficking in the county with a documentary film and its Stop the John Project, posting the names and photographs of individuals convicted of soliciting young girls working as prostitutes.
Merritt is a veteran county prosecutor who headed the District Attorney s Appellate Services Unit for 13 years and led a 43-month grand jury investigation into political corruption that resulted in multiple prosecutions and convictions, according to his campaign consultant, Chris Jones.
To date, Merritt has received $23,549 more in campaign contributions than Ramos.
Since January 1, Merritt has received a total of $67,048 in contributions, made expenditures totaling $42,393.31 and has $19,815.94 cash on hand. In the same time period, Ramos has received $42,499 in contributions, made expenditures totaling $64,555.55 and has $171,613.33 cash on hand, according to campaign finance reports.
Ellis wasn t sweating the numbers. He said Merritt has bigger obstacles to overcome.
The friends of Burum are wealthy, Ellis said. But for the ethical mountain Grover has to climb, $66,000 is not enough.
]]></text></news-item>