<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV8-2MN1-F05M-K2PF"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Mudslide death toll likely to rise soon as victims are identified</title><source>Puget Sound Business Journal (Seattle)</source><author>Terry Tazioli</author><text><![CDATA[The number of confirmed deaths in the Snohomish County mudslide remained at 16 Thursday morning, the same as it has been for several days, but local&nbsp;officials expect that number to rise significantly - and soon, perhaps by the end of the day.
County officials John Pennington, emergency management director, and&nbsp;Travis Hots, Fire District 21 chief,&nbsp;have said they are&nbsp;waiting for the county's medical examiner to process the bodies of more victims&nbsp;who&nbsp;have been recovered from the slide but whose identities have not yet been released.&nbsp;
Hots acknowledged that families and friends have been frustrated by the lack of speedier identification, but said the county has to follow protocol and make sure it's accurate in its findings, given the number of victims and those missing.
The county also confirmed Thursday that the number of missing has been set at 90, down from the 176 reported unaccounted for earlier this week.
Recovery efforts continue at the site at Oso, east of Arlington, with local, county and state crews, bolstered by a huge group of volunteers, still searching for victims. The crews have an eye on a weather forecast that includes more rain, which may hamper efforts. Geologists are monitoring the hillside where the slide occurred in case of further movement.
Media coverage of the mudslide is widespread, and is growing as the scope of the disaster unfolds. Local coverage, including&nbsp; The Herald in Everett and &nbsp;The Seattle Times, has been nonstop, including coverage of years-old warnings about slide potential.
Donations are pouring into the stricken area daily.&nbsp; Washington tribes and local and national corporations are giving large amounts of money to the relief effort. In the nearby towns of Arlington and Darrington, residents are volunteering by the score and businesses are opening their doors to community needs.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Puget Sound Business Journal (Seattle) for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>