<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV8-96S1-DXJR-H4P2"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Firm's capacity to process medical waste on radar</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Abhijeet Patil</author><text><![CDATA[KOLHAPUR: The new firm that the the civic body wants to appoint for the processing of bio-medical waste generated in the city does not have the "capacity" to do it, reveals a report prepared by the by the Maharashtra Pollution Control Board (MPCB) after the Pune bench of National Green Tribunal (NGT) on March 14 directed the pollution watchdog to assess the potential of the Ichalkaranji-based firm.
After the termination of the earlier contract with the Satara-based Nature in Need, the civic administration had appointed S S Enterprises, an Ichalkaranji-based firm. But the plan did not move forward as Nature in Need moved the NGT, alleging that the termination was illegal and should be cancelled. Taking cognizance of the civic administration's efforts to dispose the waste properly, the NGT directed the MPCB to examine the potential of the Ichalkaranji-based firm to treat the waste.
The report prepared by the MPCB, which will be produced in the court during the hearing scheduled on Friday, reads that S S Enterprises "is not capable to dispose of the BMW generated to the tune of 1 tonne per day. "The firm does not have the capacity and resources to treat the waste according to Bio-Medical Waste (Management and Handling) Rules, 2011," adds the report.
During the assessment of the firm, the MPCB visited its processing unit, machineries available with it, transport facility and the number of employees as well. The KMC had given the contract of processing biomedical waste to the Satara-based firm at a royalty cost of Rs 1.5 lakh per month. The establishments have been charged from Rs 500 to Rs 1,200, depending on the number of beds available with those.
The report is likely to create trouble for the civic administration, as it had pleaded to the court during the last hearing to give the permission for the appointment. The earlier firm, too, had taken the objections over the appointment of the new firm.
A KMC official, who agreed to talk to TOI on the condition of anonymity, said, "We have not received the report prepared by the MPCB. However, it is up to the court to decide on the matter. At present, the earlier firm is collecting the waste as per the orders of the court till the new firm is appointed. But if the court dismisses our stand, we will continue with the earlier firm and float a tender for the appointment of the new firm and complete the process ."
Bio-medical waste is generated during diagnosis, treatment or immunization of human beings or animals in research or during production or testing of biological products, including all categories of infected and toxic waste that is a potential threat to human beings and the environment.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>