<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BV8-96S1-DXJR-H43D"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>ED files chargesheet in Rs 28cr NMCE fraud case</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[AHMEDABAD: The enforcement directorate (ED) has filed a chargesheet against former chairman of National Multi-Commodity Exchange of India Ltd (NMCE), Kailash Gupta, and three of his family members in the Rs 28 crore money laundering case. In the chargesheet filed in the ED special court here on Thursday, the agency has charged Gupta, his wife Anjana Gupta, daughter Poonam Gupta and son Amit Gupta with siphoning off Rs 28 crore from NMCE.
According to ED officials, Gupta bought 33% of shares in NMCE by illegally routing the money through the companies registered in the name of his family members. Later, the shares were bought in the name of Neptune Overseas Ltd (NOL) whose director was Gupta.
"Gupta purchased a trading platform software from the city-based Mantissa Infotech Private Ltd for Rs 33 lakh but in the books of NMCE the cost was shown as Rs 28 crore," said an ED official. The money was then transferred to companies like ATSPL, Kushal Enterprise and ATSLLC.
He transferred Rs 25 crore to Aero Total Solutions Private Ltd (ATSPL), Rs 2.75 crore to Kushal Enterprise, and Rs 1 crore to US-based ATSLLC owned by his son Amit. The total amount was then moved to NOL. Gupta then used this money to buy 33% of NMCE shares. Gupta had also bought tickets from All Four Season Travels for ATSPL but later cancelled the tickets and got the refund transferred to NOL.
In 2011, commodity market regulator Forward Markets Commission (FMC) had found Gupta guilty of defrauding the NMCE and abusing his position to favour his family-run companies. Gupta, NMCE's founder, was vice-chairman of the exchange at that time. The FMC had then asked NMCE to recover Rs 36 crore and any other illegal payment from him.
Gupta was managing director and CEO of NMCE from its inception in 2003 till May 2010. Thereafter, he served as executive vice-chairman till February 2011 and was later appointed chairman of the country's fourth largest commodity exchange.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>