<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVB-DNY1-JC8W-61BG"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Miliband calls for new curbs on energy bills: Big six firms face competition inquiry as Labour seeks further price freeze: Miliband calls for fresh price curbs as big six face competition inquiry</title><source>The Guardian (London)</source><author>Patrick Wintour Terry Macalister</author><text><![CDATA[Ed Miliband will today propose fresh controls over energy prices, brushing aside angry claims by the big six companies that his call for a freeze on bills has prompted a wide-ranging competition inquiry that will chill investment for two years and possibly lead to the lights going out.
The Labour leader will reject suggestions that the coalition has shot his fox by engineering a referral of the distrusted industry to competition authorities, and he plans to keep up the pressure by calling a Commons vote next week demanding an immediate price freeze for business and domestic customers.
In a speech today he will also try to broaden popular support for the 20-month price freeze announced at the Labour conference by saying it is a business-friendly measure that could save small businesses over £5,500 a year. "The profiteering of the big six has been at the expense of hardworking business people," he will say.
He will also tell the Federation of Small Businesses that he wants to create an open market economy where small businesses can grow and make bigger profits.
Miliband, determined to secure the credit for the scrutiny being imposed on the industry, will criticise the limits of the price freeze announced by SSE energy corporation this week, pointing out it excludes small businesses.
The Labour leader will say: "We have to mend the broken energy market and freeze bills up to 2017 not just for the customers of one company but all the customers of all the energy companies."
Labour said the timing of the inquiry announced yesterday by the energy regulator, Ofgem, would broadly dovetail with its own price freeze, and provide a Labour government with the detailed advice it needs to break up the big six energy firms, end vertical integration of the industry and also strengthen the future powers of the regulators.
The party also promised to give Ofgem new powers to enforce a ban on energy suppliers rolling firms over on to more expensive tariffs without their consent, or crippling them with expensive back-billing for periods of longer than a year. They will use an opposition day debate on Wednesday to force a vote to expose party lines on the issue.
Ofgem's decision to launch the deepest ever investigation into the big six power suppliers by the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) followed pressure from the energy secretary, Ed Davey, and the government's inability to defuse the politics of the energy prices issue.
Ofgem, which has been under fire for failing to monitor the energy sector properly, said it felt compelled to act after its own review alongside the Office of Fair Trading and the CMA confirmed soaring corporate profits and plunging public confidence. It also reflects a change of the top team at Ofgem.
The latest Ofgem review had found only 43% of customers trusted the large energy companies to be open and transparent while their retail earnings had rocketed from £233m in 2009 to £1.1bn by 2012.
The new probe could lead to recommendations for the big six such as British Gas and SSE to be broken up in an attempt to make inroads on their 95% market share.
"Ofgem believes a referral (to the CMA) offers the opportunity to once and for all clear the air and decide if there are further barriers which are preventing competition from bearing down as hard as possible on prices," said Dermot Nolan, the new chief executive of Ofgem.
The regulators insist that they acted alone and not as a result of political pressure, but Davey recently sent a letter to them urging a deeper inquiry, particularly into the gas sector.
The watchdog admitted the review might take two years but promised in the meantime to increase penalties to "tens of millions of pounds" on any firms found guilty of breaking their licence conditions.
Sam Laidlaw, chief executive of British Gas parent group Centrica, immediately claimed that the inquiry would increase uncertainty and damage investment "at a time when Britain's energy security is being seriously challenged".
The former Lib Dem energy secretary Chris Huhne predicted a nailbiting time ahead as capacity margins are cut. He predicted that electricity rationing in the winter of 2015 was possible.
Huhne said that when in office he had rejected a competition inquiry because the semi-judicial process would create uncertainty. He added: "That is the big downside here - that there is a greater risk of the lights going out precisely because inevitably the shareholders, the directors and the managers of the big six are bound to invest less than they would have otherwise done."
Consumer bodies gave a sceptical response to the parcel-passing by the regulators, especially since they will not report until 2016, with any reforms expected the following year.
Ann Robinson, director of consumer policy at uSwitch.com, said: "What is clear is that there is no cavalry coming to the rescue any time soon."
Henry de Zone, co-founder of ThisIsTheBigDeal.com and a former aide to the education secretary, Michael Gove, said: "All this decision does is push the issue further down the road. It will take years to report, and even longer to implement. Meanwhile, the energy companies will be delighted to continue business as usual."
The Tory energy select committee chairman, Tim Yeo, said there was a case for just directly breaking up the big six, saying that Ofgem had been sitting on its hands for six months.
The claims were dismissed by Davey as "absolutely, totally wrong". There were 14 power projects in the pipeline covering the next 15 years, he said. Michael Fallon, the energy minister, said: "It's important this is taken out of politics. People make claims, and Labour have been all over the place on whether it's right to have vertical integration or whether the profits are too large. Let's have it properly investigated out of party politics."
Leader comment, page 40 >=
43%
Proportion of customers who trust the big six power firms to be transparent, accord
ing to Ofgem's
latest review
6-7>=
13>=
Continued on page 2 >=
continued from page 1
]]></text></news-item>