<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVB-KH31-JC3H-00DT"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Paper companies, cities reach $54 million settlement for PCB contamination in Fox River</title><source>Green Bay Press-Gazette (Wisconsin)</source><author>By, Duke Behnke</author><text><![CDATA[| Gannett Wisconsin Media
File/Gannett Wisconsin Media
Four paper companies, the city of Appleton and the Neenah-Menasha Sewerage Commission agreed Wednesday to pay $54.1 million to settle federal, state and tribal claims for the decades-old discharge of polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) into the lower Fox River.
File/Gannett Wisconsin Media
In return, the companies and municipalities will receive protection against the claims of nonsettling parties NCR Corp. and Appleton Papers Inc.
According to federal court documents, U.S. Paper Mills Corp. will pay $14.7 million for the cleanup of PCBs and natural resource damages. Menasha Corp. will pay $13.7 million, WTM 1 Co. will pay $12.2 million, and CBC Coating Inc. will pay $3 million.
Appleton and the Neenah-Menasha Sewerage Commission each will pay $5.2 million. In addition the state will pay $100,000.
The settlement must be approved by U.S. District Court Judge William Griesbach after a 30-day comment period.
In a separate settlement, Kimberly-Clark Corp. agreed to pay $1.35 million. In a third action, the federal and state governments made claims of $1.16 million against NewPage Wisconsin System Inc., but because NewPage filed for bankruptcy protection, actual payments "may be as little as $50,000," according to court documents.
Damage claims were brought by the federal and state governments, Menominee Indian Tribe of Wisconsin and Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin. The $54.1 million payment and individual shares were negotiated with the help of a mediator, U.S. District Magistrate Judge Aaron Goodstein.
"The settlement is the result of many months of negotiations between many parties, and reflects the settling parties' strong desire to resolve all claims and support the cleanup and restoration of the Fox River site," said J.P. Causey Jr., vice president of WTM 1. "This milestone could not have been reached without the able assistance of Judge Goodstein."
The $54.1 million is in addition to previous contributions by the settling parties toward site remediation and restoration. The settlement follows several others between the governments and other municipalities, paper companies and the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, all of which have been approved by the federal court.
Neenah City Attorney Jim Godlewski said the cities of Neenah and Menasha each will be on the hook for $262,500, or half of the sewerage commission's $525,000 insurance deductible.
"The rest of it ($4,675,000) is covered by the commission's insurance carriers," he said.
NCR and Appleton Papers could appeal the settlement to the U.S Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit, but if it's upheld, it would end the parties' liability.
"It's very good news," Godlewski said. "It's a very significant settlement."
The settled claims relate to discharges of PCBs into the Fox River originating from the manufacture of carbonless copy paper from 1954 to 1971 by Appleton Coated Paper Co. and NCR, and from the recycling of that paper by some paper mills throughout the Fox River Valley.
A statement from Quarles & Brady, a Milwaukee law firm representing WTM 1, said the paper recyclers and the municipalities that treated the companies' wastewater didn't know the paper being recycled contained PCBs.
- Duke Behnke writes for Post-Crescent Media of Appleton.
What are PCBs?
Polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) are long-lasting, manmade chemicals once used in the production of carbonless copy paper. Paper companies discharged about 700,000 pounds of PCBs into the lower Fox River between 1954 and 1971, when their use was discontinued.
PCBs in river sediments enter the food chain, causing reproductive failure and birth defects in some fish-eating birds and mammals. PCBs are considered a probable human carcinogen and have been linked to developmental problems in children whose mothers ate contaminated fish.
The Environmental Protection Agency and Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources ordered the paper companies responsible for the pollution to carry out a $92 million cleanup of Little Lake Butte des Morts. The work occurred from 2004 to 2009 and involved dredging, dewatering and landfilling PCB-contaminated sediment and the placement of sand and gravel caps over low-level PCB deposits where dredging was difficult.
A much larger and more costly cleanup of the lower Fox River is underway downstream in the Green Bay area.
]]></text></news-item>