<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVB-RYR1-DYR7-C01F"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>When China bends the rules</title><source>International New York Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
Several years ago, China began restricting exports of rare earth minerals, which are used in cellphones, wind turbines and various industrial products, making them more expensive on the world market. American, Japanese and European companies and officials rightly complained that China, the dominant producer of many of these minerals, was manipulating the market to benefit Chinese businesses.
On Wednesday, a World Trade Organization panel found that China's export restrictions on two minerals - tungsten and molybdenum - violated international trade rules. The decision is important because it sends a clear message to officials in Beijing that they cannot engage in protectionism without consequences. China has about two months to appeal the decision. Under W.T.O. rules, if China does not comply with the final decision, its trading partners can impose sanctions like quotas and duties on raw materials imported by China. Chinese export controls, which included export taxes, quotas and limits on which businesses can export the materials, created a two-tier market for rare earth minerals. Domestic businesses and foreign-owned companies located in China could buy rare earth minerals with few restrictions and at cheaper prices than users of the materials located in other countries.
The Chinese government had argued that the export restrictions were justified to conserve ''exhaustible natural resources'' and protect the environment. Rare earth mining is often a dirty business, especially in China where officials have a poor record of cracking down on pollution. The W.T.O. panel concluded that those arguments did not justify export restrictions because China cannot treat foreign and domestic businesses differently. Under commitments China made to join the W.T.O. in 2001, it has the right to protect the environment and to enact policies designed to conserve natural resources. But that is not the issue in this case.
China has benefited greatly from international trade. But if it wants to be part of the global trading system, it has to play by the rules.
]]></text></news-item>