<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVB-XXD1-F12F-F2T3"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>MAJORITY AGAINST AMERICA - GL</title><source>Daily News (Sri Lanka)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Sri Lanka, March 28 -- External Affairs Minister Professor G.L. Peiris yesterday said the outcome of the vote on the U.S sponsored resolution at the UN Human Rights Commission reflects that more countries are against the U.S at the Human Rights Council in Geneva.
The United Nations Human Rights Council (UNHRC) yesterday passed the US sponsored resolution against Sri Lanka with 23 countries in favour and 12 against with 12 abstentions. This brought the voting tally to 23 for, and 24 against the resolution. Pakistan, Cuba, China and Russia, strong allies of the country voted against the resolution.
India abstained from voting for the resolution against Sri Lanka at the UN Human Rights Council for the first time citing that the resolution is against the principles of the United Nations Human Rights Council.
Prof. Peris stressed that the US resolution was voted for with a majority of 25 last year and it has dropped to 23.
The number of countries that do not support the resolution are greater than those supporting it, he said. He made these observations at a press conference at Peacock Hotel, Hambantota yesterday. Professor Peiris said that another development is that India which voted for USA during the last two years, abstained from voting this year. The External Affairs Minister said only one out of 13 countries in the Asian region and four out of 13 countries in the African region voted for the resolution.
"The resolution has not gained the support of the Asian region whereas 33 of the 36 countries that co sponsored the resolution are from Europe."
He added that the result does not reflect the opinion of the entire world. The minister said Sri Lanka asked for a separate vote on the operative paragraph 10 of the resolution which proposes to handover the investigation to Human Rights Commissioner Navaneetham Pilley.
"However our suggestion to divest her of responsibility in this regard got 14 votes in favour whereas 23 against. Ten abstained from voting, meaning that the number of countries that did not support the resolution are greater than those supporting it."
Prof. Peiris said the UN Human Rights Commissioner has no legal powers or budget to conduct such an investigation and questioned if she got funds from the countries that co sponsored the resolution.
He added that Sri Lanka opposes her being given powers to conduct an investigation, as she has no mandate.
The External Affairs Minister said the international community knowing that they cannot bring about a regime change in the country by means of democratic means, was attempting to achieve their objectives through external means with the support of opposition and other inimical forces in Sri Lanka.
Meanwhile, Permanent Representative of India to the U.N. Offices in Geneva Dilip Sinha said unlike the resolutions in 2009, 2012 and 2013, this resolution asks the United Nations Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights (OHCHR) to "investigate, assess and monitor" the human rights situation in Sri Lanka which was an "intrusive" approach that undermines national sovereignty.
"It has been India's firm belief that adopting an intrusive approach that undermines national sovereignty and institutions is counterproductive. Any significant departure from the core principle of constructive international dialogue and cooperation has the potential to undermine efforts of Human Rights Council for promoting universal respect for the protection of human rights and fundamental freedoms," he said.
Observers say the results of yesterday's vote on the US sponsored resolution of Sri Lanka shows that division within the United Nations Human Rights Council over the issue of Sri Lanka.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Daily News Sri Lanka. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>