<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVB-XRF1-F03R-N412"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Left Tries To Make Christianity A Farce And Fails</title><source>The Constitution Club</source><author>Cultural Limits</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 27, 2014 (The Constitution Club:http://constitutionclub.org Delivered by Newstex) http://constitutionclub.files.wordpress.com/2014/03/christianity.jpg http://constitutionclub.files.wordpress.com/2014/03/religious_liberty.jpg Hence why it is such a threat. Christianity has been in the news quite a bit this week:'Comedian' Laura Levites tweeted that she would like to castrate every male conservative Christian she can find[1]. Two corporations owned by Christians argued before the Supreme Court that due to the Freedom of Religion guaranteed by our first amendment, they should not have to pay for certain forms of contraception that are known to kill very early stage babies, as their faith dictates that all human life is sacred and forgoing financing these products is a matter of practicing that religion. A former president who had his own arguments with the branch of Christianity in which he grew up blamed it and the Catholic Church for all the world's ills related to poor treatment of women and human trafficking. Today, the Occupier of the Oval Office went to Vatican City to talk to the Bishop of Rome, the man the world knows as Pope Francis, first among equals of the world's bishops. This pope may be popular, but make no mistake, he hadn't changed Church teaching on any topic. Can't, actually, but that's another story. It's rumored they talked about religious liberty, abortion, human trafficking.
Sex seems to be a big theme in leftist - Christian dealings. Hmmm…… To a person who lives life with no convictions or one believing that man is just one of many within the animal kingdom, the idea that sex is part of living religion might be a little strange. Even the idea that 'contraception' that really acts as an abortifacient since conception has already taken place and any baby dies as a result of the drug or element might be a little out there. But that does not give anyone in this country the right, the justifiable force, to tell another person or group that they MUST follow a law that violates their conscience in that regard. This should not be difficult to understand. After all, these are the same people who support conscientious objectors to war. It also does not give a man, no matter how well-perceived in his own mind or anyone else's, to make up convenient 'facts' about other Christians. Jimmy Carter might well be an advocate against human trafficking, but so is the Catholic Church among other people and entities. In fact, a number of Catholic anti-human trafficking agencies have closed[2] rather than comply with Obama-era rules regarding providing contraception to the victims. Within the pantheon of services provided by Catholic bishops and stressed as human rights violations, human trafficking is a focus.* What does not seem to penetrate to the people of the left is that Christianity isn't simply something to do on Sunday - for any of us. It is a way of life. Kathryn Jean Lopez[3] described Catholic submission this way:Christianity isn't a private thing, permission to be merely personally opposed to evils. It's evangelical, mandating an all-in. It's a work in progress for those who believe, always, but it's a radical surrender.We would hope that our Brethren in Christ would do the same. That is why Christianity is not a life 'style.' It is a life choice. We choose to live this way and will not accept those imposing law forcing what we consider to be objectionable on us. By the founding documents of this country, that is one of our rights. If the left can protest and fight for made up rights, why should we Christians who are in the objectification hairs of the Alinskyites not be allowed to do the same for rights which actually exist. *As for the treatment of women within the Church, not being a Southern Baptist, this writer will not comment on that society. But being a Catholic since the age of 22 days, abuse of women be it physical, verbal or mental is not acceptable in the culture - at least not in the one where I was raised. In fact, if any of the three surfaces after a wedding, they are all grounds for annulment. I've known women who have been granted annulments for all three. Wives and daughters are to be cherished, not abused. That doesn't mean that men can't be difficult, but there's a difference between actual abuse and just living with a difficult person. We also believe that Christ passed the priesthood to the men at the Last Supper, and have maintained that continuity. This does not make the men of the Church anti-woman, necessarily. As complements to each other, women do work that men don't. We are two sides of the same whole.‹ Harry Reid's Obamacare Failure Theory[4]Categories: Freedom[5], Religion[6] Tags: abortion[7], alinsky[8], Barack Obama[9], bishop of rome[10], Catholic Church[11], Christian[12], Christianity[13], conestoga wood[14], Contraception[15], Hobby Lobby[16], human trafficking[17], human traficking[18], jimmy carter[19], Leftist[20], lifestyle[21], pope francis[22], religious liberty[23], Sex[24] [1]: http://newsbusters.org/blogs/tim-graham/2014/03/27/funny-feminist-id-personally-castrate-every-male-conservative-christian [2]: http://www.ncregister.com/daily-news/hhs-ends-contract-with-church-program-for-trafficking-victims-stressing-nee/ [3]: http://www.nationalreview.com/corner/374333/no-roman-holiday-pope-and-president-meet-kathryn-jean-lopez [4]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/2014/03/27/harry-reids-obamacare-failure-theory/ [5]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/category/freedom/ [6]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/category/religion/ [7]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/abortion-2/ [8]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/alinsky/ [9]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/barack-obama/ [10]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/bishop-of-rome/ [11]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/catholic-church/ [12]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/christian/ [13]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/christianity/ [14]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/conestoga-wood/ [15]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/contraception/ [16]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/hobby-lobby/ [17]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/human-trafficking/ [18]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/human-traficking/ [19]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/jimmy-carter/ [20]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/leftist/ [21]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/lifestyle/ [22]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/pope-francis/ [23]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/religious-liberty/ [24]: http://theconservativecitizen.com/tag/sex/

]]></text></news-item>