<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVB-DMJ1-JCXB-22J2"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>GKN PLC Annual Financial Report -2-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[could result in reduced sales and profit margins and potentially lost growth opportunities in high growth markets. An inability to secure new business on major programmes could significantly impact future growth, cash flow and profitability.
Changes during 2013
Strong competition has continued throughout 2013 with growing price pressures across the supply chains of our key markets. In automotive, competition continues to increase in high growth markets such as China and South America, and in aerospace a number of new entrants and consolidations within the market have also further increased competition. This includes the emergence of government-backed manufacturers, with OEM support, in countries with growing aviation industries.
See the strategic report (page 11) for more information on the trends in each of our markets.
CUSTOMER CONCENTRATION
The insolvency of, damage to relations, or significant worsening of commercial terms with a major customer could have a material adverse impact on the Group's future results, and could result in loss of market share and future business opportunities, asset write-offs and restructuring actions.
Changes during 2013
There have been no significant changes in the OEM customer landscape with the proportion of business from the Group's top 10 customers remaining stable during 2013. No individual customer accounts for more than 10% of Group revenue.
See page 11 of the strategic report for more information on key customer trends and page 141 (note 19c) on Credit Risk.
LAWS, REGULATIONS AND CORPORATE REPUTATION
Potential impact
Non-compliance could expose the Group to fines, penalties, damage to reputation, suspension or debarment from government contracting or suspension of export privileges.
Changes during 2013
The Group is exposed to an ever more stringent governance and regulatory environment and has again expanded its presence in territories where ethical standards may not be as well established as in other markets. Whilst there has been little new regulation in the year, enforcement activities by the authorities in relation to existing regulations have increased. The acquisition of the aero engine division of AB Volvo in October 2012 increased the proportion of Group's business subject to export control regulations.
See pages 52 to 54 and 67 to 68 for more information on governance policies and procedures.
OPERATING IN GLOBAL MARKETS
Changes during 2013
In general, the commercial aerospace and global automotive markets have grown during 2013, however the construction, mining and industrial markets remain challenging and government spending cuts continue to impact military aerospace demand.
Further commentary on the recent trends and outlook for each of our markets is set out in the Chief Executive's review on pages 12 to 14 and the Business Context on pages 10 and 11. For further details on the Group's Financial Risk Management processes regarding foreign currency exposures see page 140.
JOINT VENTURES
Changes during 2013
Whilst relationships with our joint venture partners remain strong, as the amount of revenue generated through joint ventures continues to increase, this potential risk has been included as a principal risk for the first time. During the year GKN Driveline further extended its long-standing joint venture in China to cover the complete range of GKN Driveline products.
]]></text></news-item>