<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVB-SF41-JDKC-R3KB"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Cong MP Darda charge-sheeted in coal scam</title><source>Hindustan Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[New Delhi, March 28 -- The CBI on Thursday filed a charge sheet against Congress' Rajya Sabha MP Vijay Darda, his son, a Nagpur-based company, AMR Iron and Steel Pvt Ltd, and others for misrepresenting facts to acquire coal blocks.
If found guilty, Darda will not only lose the membership of the House but will also be banned from fighting elections for at least six years.
Filing its second charge sheet in the scandal that has caused a great deal of embarrassment to the outgoing UPA government, the investigating agency said Darda, the owner of the Lokmat newspaper g roup, his son Devendra Darda, AMR directors Arvind Kumar Jaiswal, Manoj Jaiswal and Ramesh Jaiswal conspired to acquire a coal block in Bander, Maharashtra. The FIR also mentions unknown officials of coal ministry.
The accused have been charged with corruption and cheating. Special CBI judge Madhu Jain fixed May 1 to consider the second charge sheet in the scandal which has come to be known as Coalgate and according to the Comptroller and Auditor General of India, cost the exchequer ' 1.86 lakh crore.
The CBI, which is looking at allocations made between 1993 and 2009, said AMR failed to disclose in its application that five blocks had been allocated to its group companies previously.
In its first charge sheet filed on March 10, the CBI named Navabharat Power Pvt Ltd and its two directors P Trivikrama Prasad and Y Harish Chandra Prasad. But due to some procedural delays, the court will take it up on May 2.
The agency lodged two more cases on Thursday against Central Collieries Co Ltd, Nagpur and Delhi-based Prakash Industries. The Nagpur firm allegedly sold coal in the open market illegally, while the one in Delhi inflated its net worth to be eligible for allocation.
The CBI, however, filed a closure report in the case against Kamal Sponge, Steel and Power Ltd, sources said, adding two more closure reports were expected. The agency may seek more time to file charge sheets in two other cases, they said.
A total of 18 cases have been filed in the scandal after the chief vigilance commissioner forwarded a complaint to the CBI in June 2012. The first FIR was filed in September 2012.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Hindustan Times. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>