<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-KFR1-DXDT-636C"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Gleision Colliery trial: Court told of moment explosion 'like jet engine' left water flooding into mine; Trial opens at Swansea Crown Court of Gleision manager Malcolm Fyfield, who is accused of the manslaughter of Charles Breslin, Philip Hill, Garry Jenkins and David Powell</title><source>walesonline.co.uk</source><author>By Robin Turner</author><text><![CDATA[The trial of a mine manager accused of causing the death of four colliers through gross negligence has heard how water rushed into the Gleision Colliery after workers in pit heard an explosion which sounded "like a jet engine".
At Swansea Crown Court, the manager, Malcolm Fyfield, 58, of Caerhenllys, Cwmllynfell, denies the manslaughter of colliers Charles Breslin, 62, of Cwmllynfell, Philip Hill, 44, of Resolven, Garry Jenkins, 39, of Rhiwfawr and David Powell, 50, of Godre'Graig.
The four died when water burst into the Gleision drift mine they were working in near Cilybebyll, Pontardawe, on September 15, 2011.
The company which owned the colliery, MNS Mining Ltd, represented in court by Gerald Ward and Maria Seage, denies four counts of corporate manslaughter.
Opening the prosecution case today, Gregg Taylor QC, described how miners were preparing to blast into new workings and shortly after underground fitter David "Jake" Wyatt and Garry Jenkins, who was standing next to him, heard the explosion.
He said: "The reaction of them both was 'run!'.
"David Wyatt got onto a conveyor belt and went as fast as he could, Garry Jenkins was behind him. Around half way along the heading he was able to jump off and go as quickly as he could. There was a deafening sound of rushing water, Garry Jenkins was behind him in the darkness."
The court heard as Mr Wyatt sprinted to the mine entrance with the water rushing behind him, another mine worker, conveyor belt operator Nigel Evans who was only on his fourth day at the pit, helped him up as he collapsed near the surface.
They then called on men on the surface to call for the emergency services and the desperate call "men trapped in flooded mine" was given at 9.21am.
The court heard Mr Wyatt and Mr Evans went back into the mine to see if they could get the others out but found a massive amount of water.
Mr Taylor said Malcolm Fyfield, who had been with the men in the blasting area got out of the pit via a section known as the Old Top Road.
He said: "He was in a terrible state, cold, shaking and he had a cut to his head. He was helped to an ambulance where he had oxygen but before he got in he said: 'They've gone'.
"He was taken to Morriston Hospital for treatment and on the way he was able to tell paramedics: 'There's no hope for the others.'"
He remained in hospital until September 27 and Mr Taylor told the jury today: "It's an agreed fact Malcolm Fyfield is suffering from severe post traumatic stress disorder as a result of his experience in the incident.
"He will require breaks during the course of the day and may need to leave the courtroom on occasions."
Opening the case this morning, Mr Taylor said: "On Thursday, September 15, 2011, men left their homes in the valleys to go to work in the Gleision Mine near Cilybebyll close to Pontardawe, by 9am that morning four men died."
He explained Garry Jenkins lived with his partner and her three children and had two sons of his own and was an experienced miner who had worked in a quarry for ten years before going back to mining at Gleision in August 2011.
David Powell, who lived with his wife, was also an experienced collier who had worked "on and off" at Gleision since 2008.
Philip Hill had previously worked at the Bettws mine in Ammanford and had been at Gleision since April 2011 while Charles Breslin, who had worked most of his life underground had worked there since May 2011.
The court heard MNS Mining had been set up in 2009 by Maria Seage who worked in the office at Gleision Colliery while her brother Gerald Ward, also a director of the company, was involved in loading and selling coal from the pit.
Mr Taylor said: "Gleision was run its managers."
He said Mr Fyfield, a qualified shot firer and experienced mine manager who was well thought of in the industry was in charge in September 2011.
The jury have been shown diagrams, maps and pictures of the mine and the Rhondda No 2 coal seam the men were working and the court also has an electronic model of the pit and the surrounding valley.
Mr Taylor explained the Gleision Colliery had been worked for around 100 years and that it had a sandstone "roof", a thick layer of sandstone rock above the coal seam.
Mr Taylor said: "One of the big problems all miners have is water - sandstone is strong but it also porous, in other words water can trickle in through it from the hillside, rainwater can permeate through it and so on. As the mine is worked water is constantly dripping through the roof."
He explained as the pit's lower levels were worked, the water had to be pumped out, sometimes to a container in upper levels where other pumps would take the water out of the mine.
The case continues.
]]></text></news-item>