<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-3331-JBV1-X1P4"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>AFPTV Agenda for the week ahead</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[We plan to file the following videos over the coming week. Please consult the daily advisories for additions and amendments.
-- SATURDAY, MARCH 29 --
AFRICA
YAMOUSSOUKRO: Press conference after ECOWAS elects new president to take over from Ivorian President Alassane Ouattara. RAW
NIAMEY: Protest against government and French nuclear giant Areva to denounce lack of clarity in deals surrounding Niger's uranium mines. RAW. TBC
ASIA-PACIFIC
BANGKOK: Thousands of anti-government protesters take to the streets to keep up pressure on the Thai PM. RAW
SINGAPORE: Spider-Man 2 cast lead worldwide celebrations of Earth Hour. RAW
EUROPE
ISTANBUL/ANKARA: News coverage of Turkey's local election on the eve of the vote. RAW
ISTANBUL/ANKARA: Refile of pre-election package of stock shots, file images, profiles and packages on Turkey's local elections. FILE/STOCKSHOTS/PKG
BUDAPEST: Hungarian "Peace March", a show of force by supporters of Prime Minister Viktor Orban before April 6 election. RAW
LONDON: Same-sex marriage becomes legal in England and Wales. RAW
BRATISLAVA: Second round run-off of Slovakia's presidential election. RAW
KIEV/SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: News coverage of events in Ukraine and Crimea. RAW
PARIS: France observes Earth Hour. TBC
MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
BEIRUT: Hezbollah Chief Hassan Nasrallah addresses supporters. RAW. TBC
BAGHDAD: Campaigning hasn't officially opened yet but candidates contesting Iraq's parliamentary polls are pressing ahead with unofficial, and illegal, campaigning. PKG
RAMALLAH/GAZA CITY, PALESTINIAN TERRITORIES: Israel scheduled to release a final tranche of 26 veteran Palestinian prisoners under commitments to the US connected to the peace talks. RAW. TBA
RAFAH, PALESTINIAN TERRITORIES: Reopening of the Rafah border crossing between Gaza and Egypt. RAW. TBA
NORTH AMERICA
CHICO, CALIFORNIA: As reform of the American immigration system stalls in Congress, one undocumented California man has been awarded a license to practice law - even though his presence in the country is technically illegal. PKG
-- SUNDAY, MARCH 30 --
AFRICA
ADDIS ABABA: Teff, a grain mostly grown in the Horn of Africa, is a key part of Ethiopia's heritage and a crucial food staple. It is now gaining interest abroad among health aficionados seeking a nutritious, gluten-free alternative to wheat and farmers hope it can earn them some much-needed cash. PKG
JOHANNESBURG: Stockshots of the South African stock exchange and economy. STOCKSHOTS
ASIA-PACIFIC
MYANMAR: Myanmar starts its first census in 30 years. RAW
BANGKOK: Thais vote in Senate elections as anti-government protests continue. RAW
TOKYO: New terminal opens at Haneda Airport, one of the world's busiest. RAW
KATHMANDU: Nepal celebrates Ghode Yatra traditional horse racing festival. RAW. TBC
EUROPE
ISTANBUL/ANKARA: Turkey holds key local elections. RAW
KIEV/SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: News coverage of events in Ukraine and Crimea. RAW
VARIOUS LOCATIONS, FRANCE: Second round in French local elections, seen as a major test for President Francois Hollande. Rolling news coverage.
HENIN-BEAUMONT, FRANCE: Far-right National Front mayor Steeve Briois takes office. RAW
BRUGELETTE, BELGIUM: Chinese President Xi Jinping visits pandas Xing Hui et Hao Hao at Pairi Daiza zoo. RAW. TBC
THE HAGUE: The International Court of Justice rules on Monday in case brought by Australia alleging that Japan's annual Antarctic whale hunt is a business disguised as science. FILE
MIEDZYRZECZ, POLAND: An awe-inspiring Nazi defence line in western Poland has taken on a new role in peacetime as home to tens of thousands of bats in what is Europe's largest artificial roost. PKG
MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
OUARZAZATE, MOROCCO: Once dubbed the "Mecca" of the film industry, the studio facilities in this southern Moroccan location are in the doldrums and need fresh winds to get moving again. PKG
GAZA CITY, PALESTINIAN TERRITORIES: Palestinians celebrate Land Day. RAW. TBA
NORTH AMERICA
CAPE CANAVERAL, FLORIDA: Third SpaceX commercial resupply mission delivers cargo to the International Space Station (delayed from March 16). RAW
SPORT
Euro football coverage available to subscribers only
LONDON: Post-match reax after Arsenal host Manchester City in the Premier League. RAW
STUTTGART/DORTMUND, GERMANY: Post-match images after Stuttgart take on Borussia Dortmund in the Bundesliga on Saturday. RAW
-- MONDAY, MARCH 31 --
AFRICA
PRETORIA: News coverage of the Oscar Pistorius trial. RAW
ASIA-PACIFIC
POHANG, SOUTH KOREA: South Korean and US forces in joint exercises. RAW
ISLAMABAD: A special tribunal hearing in landmark treason case against Pakistan's former military ruler Pervez Musharraf. TBC
YOKOHAMA: The UN's International Panel on Climate Change presents final version of report for policy-makers, which looks set to be its darkest yet. RAW
AYODHYA, INDIA: Fears of a post-election Hindu nationalist agenda are growing among many in Ayodhya. The city is India's most notorious religious flashpoint and saw 2,000 people killed in 1992 over a disputed religious site. PKG
EUROPE
THE HAGUE: The International Court of Justice rules in case brought by Australia alleging that Japan's annual Antarctic whale hunt is a business disguised as science. RAW
BRUSSELS: Chinese President Xi Jinping visits EU institutions for the first time. RAW
NICOSIA: Greek-Cypriot and Turkish-Cypriot leaders meet for reunification talks. RAW. TBA
VARIOUS LOCATIONS, FRANCE: Reactions to second round in French local elections. PKG. TBA
KIEV/SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: News coverage of events in Ukraine and Crimea. RAW
MADRID: State funeral for Spain first post-Franco prime minister Adolfo Suarez. RAW
METZ, FRANCE: Condemned serial killer Francis Heaulme, in jail for 11 murders, goes on trial for another double murder. RAW
PARIS: Carlos the Jackal, imprisoned for terrorism, on trial for alleged anti-semitic insults. TBC
PARIS: The Eiffel Tower is 125. FILE.
BUDAPEST: The economy is at the centre of Hungary legislative election on Sunday. On paper, Prime Minister Viktor Orban's government has created many jobs but in reality many are precarious and badly paid. PKG
LONDON: Sinking a pint below towering wooden arches, living in a bell tower or paying for shopping as stained glass saints look on, falling numbers of parishioners and tightening purse strings are seeing a number of Britain's churches sold off as pubs, flats and supermarkets. PKG
LATIN AMERICA & CARIBBEAN
RIO REAL, BRAZIL: Brazil is the world's biggest orange producer with more than 4.3 million farms. STOCKSHOTS
ACAJUTIBA, BRAZIL: Once an artisanal profession, Brazil's coconut producers are modernising to incorporate more industrial methods. STOCKSHOTS
MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
TEL AVIV: Court hands down verdict in trial of former Israeli premier Ehud Olmert who was accused of receiving bribes in connection with a major property development in Jerusalem. RAW / FILE
SPORT
BARCELONA: Pre-match training and pressers ahead of Tuesday's Champions League first leg quarter final between Barcelona and Atlectico Madrid. RAW
MANCHESTER, UK: Pre-match training and pressers ahead of Tuesday's Champions League first leg quarter final between Manchester United and Bayern Munich. RAW
Euro football coverage available to subscribers only
NAPLES, ITALY: Post-match reax after Juventus play Napoli in the Serie A on Sunday. RAW
-- TUESDAY, APRIL 1 --
AFRICA
PRETORIA: News coverage of the Oscar Pistorius trial. RAW
As part of our special package ahead of the 20th anniversary of the Rwandan genocide, we will file the following videos:
KIGALI: It's been 20 years since at least 800,000 Rwandans were massacred in one of the worst genocides of the 20th century. And yet as the country prepares to commemorate its darkest days, the fight to bring those responsible to justice still continues. PKG
KESHO, RWANDA: File images of the genocide memorial at Kesho where 1,400 Tutsis were killed. FILE
ASIA-PACIFIC
MANILA: Catholic Church opens an exhibition of Pope John Paul II's relics. RAW.
TOKYO: Japan's sales tax increase from 5 to 8%. RAW.
TOKYO: Japan reacts to the verdict of the International Court of Justice on whether the country's whaling practices contravene international law. RAW
EUROPE
BRUGES/GHENT, BELGIUM: Chinese President Xi Jinping gives a speech on EU-China relations and visits a Volvo factory. RAW
BRUSSELS: NATO foreign ministers meeting (to 2). On merit. RAW. TBC
KIEV/SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: News coverage of events in Ukraine and Crimea. RAW
BUDAPEST: Profile of Hungary's controversial Prime Minister Viktor Orban ahead of Sunday's legislative election. PKG
PARIS: Bill Gates visits to lend support global health initiative Unitaid. TBC
NORTH AMERICA
WASHINGTON: GM CEO Mary Barra testifies before Congress on the recent recall of 1.6 million cars. RAW
SPORT
BARCELONA: Post-match reax after the Champions League first leg quarter final between Barcelona and Atlectico Madrid. RAW
MANCHESTER, UK: Post-match reax after the Champions League first leg quarter final between Manchester United and Bayern Munich. RAW
MADRID: Pre-match training and pressers ahead of Wednesday's Champions League first leg quarter final between Real Madrid and Borussia Dortmund. RAW
PARIS: Pre-match training and pressers ahead of Wednesday's Champions League first leg quarter final between Paris Saint-Germain and Chelsea. RAW.
-- WEDNESDAY, APRIL 2 --
AFRICA
PRETORIA: News coverage of the Oscar Pistorius trial. RAW
BANGUI: File of the conflict in Central African Republic as EU and African leaders discuss the crisis at a summit in Brussels. FILE
As part of our special package ahead of the 20th anniversary of the Rwandan genocide, we will file the
following video:
KIGALI: The dead have been buried for 20 years but the mental trauma left behind by Rwanda's genocide is still very much alive among the survivors. PKG
ASIA-PACIFIC
AMETHI, INDIA: Hit by a weakened economy and various corruption scandals, India's incumbent Congress party is facing its worst ever results in the national election that starts on April 7. While Congress vice-president Rahul Gandhi has promised to overhaul the party's mechanics, its sagging popularity is unlikely to dent the appeal of the party's all-powerful Nehru-Gandhi dynasty brand. PKG
ANGKOR WAT, CAMBODIA: Cambodia's Angkor Wat is digitally mapped for the first time, allowing web-users to travel through the temple complex using Google Street view. PKG
EUROPE
BRUSSELS: EU-Africa summit (to 3). RAW
BRUSSELS: Final day of NATO foreign ministers meeting. On merit. RAW. TBC
KIEV/SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: News coverage of events in Ukraine and Crimea. RAW
BERLIN: Press preview of major exhibition by Chinese dissident artist Ai Weiwei which opens on Thursday. RAW
BUDAPEST: News coverage of the campaign for Hungary's legislative election on Sunday. RAW. TBC
GENEVA: International Invention exhibition opens, showcasing wild and wonderful ideas from the world over. RAW
PARIS: Game of Thrones fans get a sneak peak at the fourth season. RAW.
LATIN AMERICA & CARIBBEAN
SAN JOSE: Costa Rica holds Sunday a second round of presidential elections. STOCKSHOTS of San Jose. FILE candidates.
NORTH AMERICA
WASHINGTON: IMF chief Christine Lagarde previews IMF/World Bank Spring meetings and discusses the state of the global economy and Ukraine. RAW
WASHINGTON: "Marvin," a bistro and bar named after Washington DC native Marvin Gaye, celebrates what would have been the music legend's 75th birthday with family members and a special performance by his original band, The Marquees. RAW
SPORT
MADRID: Post-match reax after Champions League first leg quarter final between Real Madrid and Borussia Dortmund. RAW
PARIS: Post-match reax after Champions League first leg quarter final between Paris Saint-Germain and Chelsea. RAW
-- THURSDAY, APRIL 3 --
AFRICA
PRETORIA: News coverage of the Oscar Pistorius trial. RAW
As part of our special package ahead of the 20th anniversary of the Rwandan genocide, we will file the following video:
KIGALI: Two decades after Rwanda's genocide, the country's economy is still in tatters. RAW
ASIA-PACIFIC
DELHI: India, the world's biggest democracy, prepares to start the first of round of voting in parliamentary elections expected to see the opposition Hindu nationalists led by hardliner Narendra Modi come to power. PKG
EUROPE
ROME/VATICAN CITY: Queen Elizabeth II meets President Giorgio Napolitano and visits Pope Francis. RAW
KIEV/SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: News coverage of events in Ukraine and Crimea. RAW
BUDAPEST: News coverage of Jobbik, Hungary's third biggest party and far right grouping. RAW
PARIS: From symphonic maestro to amateur pianist: celebrated Korean conductor Myung-Whun Chung has recorded his first-ever piano solo CD with relatively simple beginner's pieces, dedicated to his grandchildren. PKG
LATIN AMERICA & CARIBBEAN
MEXICO CITY: Stockshots illustrating Mexico's economy. STOCKSHOTS
NORTH AMERICA
WASHINGTON: As Afghanistan prepares to elect a new president, Americans are being forced to reflect on the minimal gains made in the country after 13 years of bloody intervention. PKG
MARYLAND: Chesapeake Bay oysters are on the rebound in US restaurants after a major public-private effort to re-establish them as a quality food product and a tool against water pollution. PKG
SPORT
Euro football coverage available to subscribers only:
LYON, FRANCE: Lyon plays Juventus Turin in the Europa League. RAW.
-- FRIDAY, APRIL 4 --
AFRICA
PRETORIA: News coverage of the Oscar Pistorius trial. RAW
KIGALI: Vox pops from Rwandans ahead of the 20th anniversary of the Rwandan genocide. RAW
KIGALI: Rwanda hosts an international conference, "After Genocide: Examining legacy, taking responsibility". RAW. TBC
ASIA-PACIFIC
THAILAND: Pro-government Red Shirts are expected to hold a mass rally. TBC
KABUL: First round in presidential election in Afghanistan. RAW.
EUROPE
BUDAPEST: Hungary votes in legislative election on Sunday. STOCKSHOTS
KIEV/SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: News coverage of events in Ukraine and Crimea. RAW
AIX-EN-PROVENCE, FRANCE: Verdict in the trial of Patrick Salameh, accused of killing three prostitutes. RAW
BRUSSELS: European unions call for anti-austerity protest. On merit. RAW. TBC
LYON, FRANCE: James Ellroy is guest of honour at the Lyon crime thriller festival. RAW
PARIS: Sweet tooth delights as Sugar Paris, a fair for pastries, opens. RAW
MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
ALGIERS: With Algeria's election campaign in full swing, ailing President Abdelaziz Bouteflika is conspicuous by his absence. PKG
NORTH AMERICA
WASHINGTON: Tunisian PM Mehdi Jomaa visits the White House. RAW
WASHINGTON: US unemployment figures released. STOCKSHOTS
-- SATURDAY, APRIL 5 --
AFRICA
KIGALI: Ahead of a week of official mourning to commemorate 20 years since the genocide, refile of special package. RAW / FILE / STOCKSHOTS / PKG
EUROPE
KIEV/SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: News coverage of events in Ukraine and Crimea. RAW
BERLIN: The conservative Christian Democratic Union holds a party congress ahead of European elections. RAW
BRUGELETTE, BELGIUM: Pandas Xing Hui and Hao Hao are presented to the public for the first time at the Pairi Daiza zoo. RAW
PARIS: Paris city council due to elect mayor after local elections. TBC
MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
CAIRO: Trial resumes of deposed president Mohamed Morsi over charges of inciting the killing of protesters during his presidency in 2012. TBC
NORTH AMERICA
SEATTLE: 20th anniversary of Kurt Cobain's death. RAW
-- SUNDAY, APRIL 6 --
AFRICA
KIGALI: From Monday, Rwanda begins a week of official mourning to commemorate the 20th anniversary of the Rwandan genocide. RAW. TBC
EUROPE
BUDAPEST: Hungary parliamentary election. RAW
KIEV/SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: News coverage of events in Ukraine and Crimea. RAW
PARIS: Frenchman Denis Josselin attempts to cross the Seine on a 150-metre long cable. TBC.
LATIN AMERICA & CARIBBEAN
SAN JOSE: Second round of presidential election in Costa Rica. RAW
MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
KHIRBET AIN KARZALIYA, JORDAN VALLEY: For Atiya, a 50-year-old Bedouin shepherd, it is the third time that he and his extended family have had their homes levelled as the Israeli army steps up the pace of demolitions in the Jordan Valley. PKG
SPORT
PARIS: More than 50,000 runners meet for the Paris marathon, the world's fifth-largest marathon event. TBC
Contact:
London desk: +44 207 776 2768
Hong Kong desk: +852 2829 6216
Nicosia desk: +357 22 391 453
Washington desk: +1 202 414 0550
Montevideo desk: +598 2 900 5095 ext 257
For contact via email: afptv-en@afp.com
aftpv
]]></text></news-item>