<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-FWY1-DY9P-N1JD"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>'They've gone... others'.",' Gleision there's no hope for the boss told paramedics</title><source>The Western Mail</source><author>Robin Turner</author><text><![CDATA[THE trial of a coal mine manager accused of causing the death of four colliers through gross negligence heard yesterday the noise of an explosion before water gushed into the Gleision pit was "like a jet engine".
Experienced pit manager Malcolm Fyfield, 58, of Caerhenllys, Cwmllynfell, denies the manslaughter of colliers Charles Breslin, 62, of Cwmllynfell; Philip Hill, 44, of Resolven; Garry Jenkins, 39, of Rhiwfawr; and David Powell, 50, of Godre'Graig.
The four underground workers died when a vast amount of water suddenly burst into the Gleision drift mine they were working in near Cilybebyll, Pontardawe, Swansea Valley, on September 15, 2011.
The company which owned the colliery, MNS Mining Ltd, represented in court by Gerald Ward and Maria Seage, denies four counts of corporate manslaughter.
Opening the prosecution case yesterday at Swansea Crown Court, Gregg Taylor QC, described how miners were preparing to blast into new workings and, as they did so, underground fitter David "Jake" Wyatt and Garry Jenkins, who was standing next to him, heard the "jet engine" explosion.
Mr Taylor said: "The reaction of them both was 'run!'.
"David Wyatt got onto a conveyor belt and went as fast as he could, Garry Jenkins was behind him.
"Around halfway along the heading, he was able to jump off and go as quickly as he could. There was a deafening sound of rushing water, Garry Jenkins was behind him in the darkness."
The court heard that as Mr Wyatt sprinted to the mine entrance with the water rushing behind him, another mine worker, conveyor belt operator Nigel Evans, who was only on his fourth day at the pit, helped him up as he collapsed near the surface. They then called on men on the surface to call for the emergency services. The desperate call "men trapped in flooded mine" was given at 9.21am.
The court heard that Mr Wyatt and Mr Evans went back into the mine to see if they could get the others out, but found a massive amount of water.
Fyfield, who had been with the men in the blasting area, got out of the pit through sludge and mud via a section known as the Old Top Road.
Mr Taylor said: "He was in a terrible state, cold, shaking and he had a cut to his head. He was helped to an ambulance where he had oxygen but before he got in he said: 'They've gone.' .
"He was taken to Morriston Hospital for treatment and on the way he was able to tell paramedics: 'There's no hope for the others'."
He remained in hospital until September 27 and Mr Taylor told the jury yesterday: "It's an agreed fact Malcolm Fyfield is suffering from severe posttraumatic stress disorder as a result of his experience in the incident.
"He will require breaks during the course of the day and may need to leave the courtroom on occasions."
After his release from hospital care, Fyfield told police he had discovered David Powell's body after the "in-rush" of water. He told officers he tried to give him mouth-tomouth resuscitation at the scene but discovered there were no signs of life and added at the time it was not possible to take his pulse or to move his body.
Soon after, he saw a light attached to Mr Hill. He told police he went towards him and again tried to give mouth-to-mouth resuscitation, but again he found there were no signs of life.
All the time, the court heard, the water in the mine was still rising. He said he tried to move Mr Hill's body but was unable to do so.
Mr Taylor said post-mortem operations revealed the cause of death of all four miners was drowning, each of the men having been found with silt and coal contaminated water in their mouths and windpipes.
Mr Hill also had other injuries, including internal bleeding.
Opening the case, Mr Taylor said: "On Thursday, September 15, 2011, men left their homes in the valleys to go to work in the Gleision Mine near Cilybebyll close to Pontardawe; by 9am that morning four men died."
He explained Garry Jenkins lived with his partner and her three children and had two sons of his own and, an experienced miner, had worked in a quarry before going back to mining at Gleision in August 2011.
David Powell, who lived with his wife, was also an experienced collier who had worked "on and off" at Gleision since 2008.
Ex Bettws, Ammanford miner Philip Hill and had been at Gleision since April 2011 while Charles Breslin, who had worked most of his life underground had been there since May 2011.
The court heard MNS Mining was set up in 2009 by Maria Seage who worked in the colliery office, while her brother Gerald Ward, also an MNS director, was involved in selling coal from the pit.
Mr Taylor said: "Gleision was run by its managers."
He said Fyfield, who was well thought of in the industry was in charge in September 2011.
Mr Taylor explained that the 100-year-old Gleision Colliery had a sandstone "roof", a thick layer of rock above the coal seam and miners quite often only had 2ft-6ins in which to move, the height of the average kitchen sink.
"Men worked this space by crawling on their hands and knees," he said.
The prosecutor added: "One of the big problems all miners have is water - sandstone is strong but also porous, water can trickle in." Yesterday, the jury was told a former Gleision Colliery manager, Brian Amber, encountered a "pocket of water" while working the pit at a time when Charles Breslin and David Powell were at the mine.
The case continues.
TIMELINE September 15 2011 0920 South Wales Police officers, along with fire and ambulance crews, are called to the colliery after four people were trapped. Seven people were initially in the mine at the time, three of them got out - with one taken to hospital. The families gather at Rhos Community Centre where they are kept informed.
1500 Superintendent Phil Davies says emergency services are conducting a "difficult rescue operation". 1630 First Minister Carwyn Jones says "my thoughts and prayers - and those of the people of Wales - are with the trapped men and their families".
1700 It emerges that the miner who was taken to hospital is in a "critical condition". Mr Davies also says water is flowing into the mine.
2130 The missing miners are named by South Wales Police as Philip Hill, 45, Charles Breslin, 62, David Powell, 50, and Garry Jenkins, 39.
Friday September 16 0830 Police say the body of a miner has been located but has yet to be identified.
1330 Police say a second body has been found and that the first has now been recovered.
1510 Police confirm a third body has been found 1800 Chief constable Peter Vaughan confirms fourth and final body found in mine.
September 17, 2011 Inquiry into the disaster is jointly launched by South Wales Police and Health and Safety Executive (HSE).
September 28, 2011 Inquests into the deaths of the four coal miners are formally opened. Funeral of Charles Breslin takes place. Three other funerals follow soon after.
October 19, 2011 Pit boss Malcolm Fyfield arrested on suspicion of gross negligence August 28, 2012 Swansea Valley Miners' Appeal Fund set up after the tragedy announces it has raised £1m for the victims' families.
January 18, 2013 Malcolm Fyfield is charged with four counts of gross negligence manslaughter. The company which owns the colliery, MNS Mining Ltd, is charged with counts of corporate manslaughter.
December 16, 2013 In court Malcolm Fyfield denies four charges of manslaughter relating to the men's deaths.
March 25, 2014 A jury is sworn in for the trial of Malcolm Fyfield.
]]></text></news-item>