<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-RFW1-DYRG-W3TH"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>PG&amp;E bracing for criminal case; Deadly San Bruno explosion and fire likely to lead the U.S. attorney's office to file charges, utility says</title><source>The San Francisco Chronicle (California)</source><author>David R. Baker</author><text><![CDATA[Pacific Gas and Electric Co. expects to face criminal charges from the federal government over the 2010 San Bruno pipeline explosion that killed eight people and leveled a neighborhood, the company reported Thursday.
The U.S. attorney's office investigating the blast will probably charge the utility with violating the federal Pipeline Safety Act in areas related to record-keeping and pipeline maintenance, PG&E said. The utility's parent company, PG&E Corp., made the prediction in a filing Thursday to the Securities and Exchange Commission.
The company maintains that its employees did not intentionally violate federal law and that criminal charges are unwarranted. The company has committed to spending $2.7 billion of its shareholders' money on upgrading its vast natural gas network in response to the accident, which destroyed 38 homes and damaged 70 more.
"San Bruno was a tragic accident that caused a great deal of pain for many people," said Tony Earley, CEO of PG&E Corp., in a prepared statement. "We're accountable for that and make no excuses. Most of all, we are deeply sorry. We have worked hard to do the right thing for victims, their families and the community, and we will continue to do so."
PG&E, based in San Francisco, already faces the prospect of paying up to $2.5 billion in fines and penalties from California regulators over the blast. But some public officials have pushed for criminal charges as well, blaming the explosion on years of negligence and greed.
"I am so excited that we'll see justice," said state Sen. Jerry Hill, D-San Mateo. "There's clear evidence that they diverted hundreds of millions of dollars from safety and operations to bonuses for executives. That's why they didn't have good record-keeping. That's why they didn't have good maintenance. They didn't want to pay for it."
The Sept. 9, 2010, explosion of a large natural gas transmission line shook San Bruno with such force and torched so many homes that it was at first mistaken for a plane crash. Investigators determined that a faulty weld from the 1950s - one that shouldn't have even passed inspection when it was installed - had finally ruptured.
PG&E records indicated that section of pipeline didn't have a weld. An investigation by the National Transportation Safety Board concluded that the utility's shoddy record-keeping and an organizational culture that didn't emphasize safety led to the blast.
State and local officials considered filing their own criminal charges, but failed to do so before their three-year statute of limitations passed last fall. Federal authorities, however, have a five-year statute of limitations and continued pursuing the case.
"The City of San Bruno commends the diligence of the U.S. Attorney's Office for its investigation of Pacific Gas & Electric Company's gross negligence in the explosion and fire," Mayor Jim Ruane said in a prepared statement Thursday. The move, he said, "will hopefully help bring closure to this devastating tragedy created by the negligence of PG&E. San Bruno, its citizens, and state and local elected leaders are monitoring the outcome closely."
To those whose lives were upended by the explosion, criminal charges are cold comfort.
"It doesn't help," said Gayle Masunu. She and her mother, Loretta Groulx, survived the blast, but they both suffered burns, and their home was seriously damaged.
"We're all still kind of down and everything," Masunu said.
In its filing, PG&E did not indicate why it believes criminal charges are imminent. A spokeswoman for the U.S. attorney's office in San Francisco declined to comment.
The California Public Utilities Commission is still weighing a proposal to levy a mix of fines and penalties that could cost up to $2.5 billion, total.
But Hill and other critics have accused the commission and its president, Michael Peevey, of being hesitant to penalize PG&E, saying the regulators have grown too close to the company. The city of San Bruno even sued the commission last month seeking documents city officials say could expose a "cozy" relationship between the commission and PG&E.
"We certainly could not expect to see justice from the PUC under Michael Peevey, but we'll see it in the federal courts," Hill said Thursday.
Peevey has repeatedly rejected those accusations. And a spokeswoman for the commission said Thursday the commission had shared all of its own investigative materials on San Bruno with the U.S. attorney's office.
PG&E has at times warned that a steep fine could cripple the company, although its critics consider those comments scare tactics. But the financial uncertainty raised by the incident has weighed on the company's stock. In its filing to financial regulators Thursday, the company warned that criminal charges could lead to more fines and penalties, and cause investors to lose confidence.
"If criminal charges are filed, PG&E Corporation's and the Utility's reputations would suffer," the filing said.
]]></text></news-item>