<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-DWY1-F025-P1C6"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>McDonnell calls wife's testimony pivotal</title><source>Richmond Times Dispatch (Virginia)</source><author>JIM NOLAN AND OLYMPIA MEOLA</author><text><![CDATA[The key to Bob McDonnell's defense may be the testimony of his alleged partner in crime -- his wife.
The former governor's lawyers say former first lady Maureen McDonnell's testimony on his behalf would reveal a "strained" marital relationship. They say it would dispel the federal government's notion that the McDonnells conspired to use the state's highest public office to assist Jonnie R. Williams Sr., then Star Scientific Inc.'s CEO, in exchange for gifts and loans.
"Far from acting in concert, they had no such agreement and he had no timely knowledge of many of her interactions with Williams," the former governor's attorneys assert.
But that testimony will not take place if the McDonnells are tried together, the lawyers state in their motion to sever the public corruption case against the former governor from the case against his wife.
The 28-page memorandum in support of the motion to split the trials was part of an avalanche of defense documents the McDonnells' lawyers filed Tuesday night in U.S. District Court in Richmond. The filings included motions to dismiss 12 of the 14 counts against the McDonnells, to sever their trials and to allow an expanded jury-selection process.
The federal government is expected to object to the motions, which U.S. District Judge James R. Spencer will consider during a hearing in May. Legal observers say motions to dismiss are rarely granted in such cases.
But theunusual circumstance of standing criminally accused with one's spouse offers openings for pretrial legal challenges.
"Where the co-defendants are also husband and wife, the long-recognized 'adverse testimony' and 'confidential communications' privileges present potential grounds to sever" the McDonnells' trials, said Charles E. "Chuck" James Jr., a former federal prosecutor and chief deputy Virginia attorney general who is now a partner at the Williams Mullen law firm.
"Mr. McDonnell's attorneys recognize that their defense strategy is dramatically different depending on whether Mrs. McDonnell is also a defendant in the same trial," James added.
The former governor's lawyers argue that, "in essence, the government has chosen to put a 38-year marriage and the entire McDonnell family" on trial.
His defense attorneys say allowing the former first couple to be prosecuted together would "severely constrain" the former governor's ability to introduce "relevant, admissible and exculpatory evidence at trial."
Maureen McDonnell is willing to testify on his behalf, but does not intend to testify in her own defense, according to Bob McDonnell's legal team.
Further, in a joint trial Maureen McDonnell would invoke a marital communications privilege if the former governor takes the stand in his own defense and attempts to testify about confidential conversations he had with his wife, according to the filing.
The former governor's attorneys argue Maureen McDonnell is the "key figure" in the government's narrative. They say that because she frequently communicated with Williams alone and because she is "uniquely equipped" to repudiate the government's account by refuting each allegation, including gifts, trips and cash the first couple received.
The former first lady would testify that her relationship with her husband "was strained for a number of reasons, including Mr. McDonnell's demanding work and travel schedule," according to the court filing.
The former governor's lawyers argue the government provides no specific allegation of an agreement between the McDonnells, but appears to be "inferring a conspiracy" solely by virtue of their marriage.
"Her testimony would, in turn, clearly exonerate her husband," the lawyers state.
McDonnell and his wife face a 14-count indictment stemming in part from more than $165,000 in gifts and loans they accepted from Williams. The McDonnells have pleaded not guilty to all charges.
Spencer has set a July 28 start for a joint trial that was expected to last five or six weeks.
"Judge Spencer will review the pleadings and seek a balance between the understandable desire to preside over only one trial and the compelling need to ensure both defendants a fair trial," James said.
In other filings Tuesday night, the former governor and the former first lady asked the judge to dismiss the corruption counts against them, arguing that the U.S. government is trying to stretch the boundaries of federal bribery laws.
The former governor's lawyers on Tuesday did not ask the judge to dismiss the two other counts against him, charges alleging that he knowingly made false statements on financial documents.
Lawyers for the former first lady argued that the corruption counts against her do not apply because she was a private citizen, albeit one in the public eye.
"In short, a first lady has no public office to corrupt."
Maureen McDonnell's lawyers also asked the judge to toss the additional charge against her, in part, because the indictment "fails to identify the official proceeding Mrs. McDonnell allegedly obstructed" and "fails to allege Mrs. McDonnell intended to obstruct an official proceeding."
Lawyers for the former governor also asked the judge for a thorough jury selection process, citing extensive pretrial publicity.
Among other things, McDonnell wants prospective jurors to fill out a lengthy questionnaire -- at the courthouse -- two weeks ahead of the trial. In the case of a joint trial he wants each defendant to get 10 "strikes" of prospective jurors to the federal prosecutors' six. He also wants jurors to be able to take notes.
The former governor says that in the absence of such a thorough process, the only reasonable alternatives are more burdensome -- to sequester the jurors for five weeks away from smartphones and computers, or to move the trial out of Richmond to someplace where pretrial coverage of the case has not been so extensive.
"This case has and will likely continue to raise novel issues," James said.
jnolan@timesdispatch.com
(804) 649-6061
Twitter: @RTDNolan
omeola@timesdispatch.com
(804) 649-6812
Twitter: @omeola
]]></text></news-item>