<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-RFT1-JBKR-N0PD"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Bibeau fires back at allegations</title><source>The Gazette (Montreal)</source><author>SUE MONTGOMERY, The Gazette</author><text><![CDATA[In the latest salvo in an increasingly nasty election campaign, the Liberal party fundraiser under Jean Charest denied recent Parti Québécois allegations that he raised $428,150 at one event.
Earlier this week, the Parti Québécois filed a complaint with the province's chief electoral officer about the sum raised by Marc Bibeau, but the same day confirmed its director general and director of finances and administration met with provincial anti-corruption investigators in February.
During what the PQ called an "informal" meeting, two UPAC investigators questioned the directors about the party's financing and organization.
According to a statement released by the PQ, the meeting was intended to be confidential, but the party chose to release information after details of the meeting were leaked to the media.
"The Parti Québécois chose to make public all information on this subject, in order to avoid confusion with the situation of the Liberal party," the PQ said.
Bibeau shot back with his own statement Thursday, saying that the $428,150 was not the result of one event but rather the cumulative amount of individual donations over a period of months and within the guidelines established for the funding of political parties.
The province's anti-corruption squad raided Liberal party headquarters last July, which led them to Bibeau's businesses, Schokbéton and Saramac, which were raided in November.
Among the items listed in the search warrants are emails concerning envelopes given to Schokbéton. Some of the material seized revealed $428,150 was raised at one event, yet that amount doesn't appear in the Liberals' financial statements, the PQ charges.
In December, anti-corruption squad officers raided Bibeau's luxury home on des Érables St. in Laval. No arrests have been made as a result of any of the searches connected to Bibeau.
On Wednesday, Quebec Liberal Leader Philippe Couillard responded to allegations about the amount raised, vowing that if anyone in his party committed "reprehensible acts, they will be punished."
In 2012, former construction entrepreneur Lino Zambito testified before the Charbonneau Commission examining corruption and collusion in the construction industry that Bibeau was the Quebec Liberal Party's "big financial boss" in 2007.
Zambito alleged he met with Bibeau and Liberal organizer Violette Trépanier in the fall of 2007 to arrange a fundraiser for then-municipal affairs minister Nathalie Normandeau. The tickets for that event, according to Zambito, were priced at $5,000 apiece, and the dinner raised $110,000. Elections Québec's records, however, show tickets were $1,000 and that only $77,500 was raised.
smontgomery@montrealgazette.com Twitter: MontgomerySue
]]></text></news-item>