<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-XF11-JCBD-104N"><date>2014-03-27</date><title></title><source>City News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A proposed settlement reached today would relieve customers of Southern California Edison and San Diego Gas & Electric of paying $1.4 billion in utility charges related to steam generators that caused the shutdown of the San Onofre Nuclear Generation Station.
The settlement agreed upon by The Utility Reform Network, state Office of Ratepayer Advocates and the two utility companies still needs approval from the state Public Utilities Commission.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - A leak of toxic fumes forced the evacuation of a building at the University of California San Diego today and sent three people to a hospital, authorities reported.
An employee of a private contractor was in a ground-floor laboratory at Jacobs School of Engineering shortly before 9:30 a.m., servicing the structure's ventilation system, when he accidentally cut a duct that carries a caustic gas, according to Lee Swanson, an information officer for the San Diego Fire-Rescue Department.
SPRING VALLEY (CNS) - A 73-year-old missing Spring Valley woman diagnosed with Alzheimer's disease and dementia was found safe today in the Clairemont area, authorities said.
World Luz Loper left her home in the 9500 block of Upland Street on foot about noon Wednesday and was found safe at Balboa and Genesee avenues at 8:20 a.m., according to the San Diego County Sheriff's Department.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - A woman accused of shooting and killing a former boyfriend inside his Imperial Beach apartment after stalking and harassing him for a year is mentally competent to stand trial on a murder charge, a judge ruled today.
A mental competency trial was scheduled for Vegas Bray, but both sides stipulated to a doctor's findings that the defendant understood the charges against her and could assist her attorney at trial.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - A gang member who fatally shot a member of his own gang in broad daylight, because the victim supposedly wasn't following orders from gang leaders, was sentenced today to 50 years to life in state prison.
Aron Franklin, 21, was convicted of first-degree murder in the Jan. 3, 2013, killing of 20-year-old Julius Batiste in Lincoln Park.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - Mayor Kevin Faulconer and City Council President Todd Gloria said today they will unveil plans tomorrow for a scaled-down version of a celebration of Balboa Park's centennial next year.
Plans for a yearlong series of events that would draw national and international visitors collapsed after a citizen's group failed to attract enough private investment. Balboa Park Celebration Inc. is in the processing of disbanding amid questions of what the city got in return for its $2.6 million investment.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - The rate of pertussis infections in San Diego County is running far ahead of last year's pace, the county Health and Human Services Agency reported today.
The 10 new cases logged last week brings to 154 the number of patients diagnosed with the disease -- also known as whooping cough -- so far this year, compared to 33 at this time last year, according to the HHSA.
CARLSBAD (CNS) - The $1.7 million Kia Classic women's golf tournament began today with several players saying the course at the Park Hyatt Aviara Golf Club in Carlsbad is in better shape than last year.
"The fairways are not rolling out so much, the greens are not rolling out so much," Stacy Lewis said.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - A 19-year-old who allegedly made a failed attempt to rob a Rancho Bernardo gas station near Stoneridge Country Club while wielding a large knife that resembled a machete pleaded not guilty today to an attempted robbery charge.
Alexander Scott Brill was ordered held on $75,000 bail, despite an argument from defense attorney Peter Liss that the defendant needed to be released immediately so he could be treated for mental health issues.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - An group of about 400 mayors who support same-sex marriages announced today that San Diego Mayor Kevin Faulconer has been named one of its seven directors.
Faulconer is following in the footsteps of former San Diego Mayor Jerry Sanders, who helped start Mayors For The Freedom to Marry.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - A man who held up eight gas stations in San Diego and Lakeside over a 12-hour period -- and was dubbed the "I'm Sorry Bandit" because he apologized to his victims -- pleaded guilty today to robbery charges.
Ryan Tyler Morris' crime spree began with a robbery at a Mobil gas station on Rancho Penasquitos Road off Interstate 15 at 7:45 p.m. on Feb. 25, said Deputy District Attorney Roy Lai.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - An expensive bulldog claimed without authorization last week from a North County kennel business, where the puppy had been brought after getting lost, was reunited with his owners today.
The man who took the 5-month-old English bulldog, named Schroeder, from the boarding center in the 900 block of West San Marcos Boulevard returned him to his rightful home just down the block this afternoon, according to sheriff's officials.
ENCINITAS (CNS) - The Encinitas Union School District was one of two districts honored today in the state Department of Education's Green Ribbon Schools Program.
The state program mirrors the federal Green Ribbon Schools initiative to honor energy efficiency, education on sustainability, and student health and wellness improvements.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - San Diego State's men's basketball team faced Arizona tonight in the Aztecs' first Sweet 16 appearance since 2011.
The game at Anaheim's Honda Center is rematch of a Nov. 14 game won by Arizona, 69-60.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - San Diego airport officials celebrated today's reopening of a nearly 2,000-space parking lot on the north side of Lindbergh Field.
The entrance on Pacific Highway at Sassafras Street was closed, and the lot was moved a short distance to make room for a rental car center.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - The April 10 deadline to pay the second installment of property taxes is approaching and only 30 percent of the bills have been remitted, San Diego County Treasurer-Tax Collector Dan McAllister said today.
Of the nearly 982,000 invoices that were sent out last September, 590,000 second installments have gone unpaid, with a total value of $1.68 billion, McAllister said.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - A young man was arrested today on suspicion of trying to steal a woman's backpack at a Valencia Park transit station, prompting a brawl during which he suffered a minor stab injury.
David Monegro, 22, allegedly confronted two women waiting for a trolley at the depot in the 6200 block of Imperial Avenue shortly before 9:30 a.m. and grabbed one of their backpacks, according to San Diego police Officer Frank Vali.
VISTA (CNS) - A 21-year-old who stole a jar of cash from Girl Scouts selling cookies outside an Escondido supermarket pleaded guilty today to misdemeanor charges of petty theft and resisting arrest and was sentenced to 240 days in jail.
David Betancort will be on probation for three years.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - An influx of sewage-fouled waters out of Baja California prompted a beach pollution advisory today along several miles of ocean coastline just north of the U.S.-Mexico border.
The warning stems from waste that entered the surf out of the Tijuana River in the area of Border Field State Park, according to the San Diego County Department of Environmental Health.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - A San Diego man who admitted hacking into a website associated with an Israeli-based business was sentenced today to 15 months in prison.
Jonathan Cowden, 29, was sentenced in U.S. District Court in St. Louis, Mo., where he formerly lived, according to the Department of Justice.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - A 25-year-old San Diego man was jailed early today for allegedly shooting a man in his 30s in Mountain View, sending the victim to the hospital with life-threatening wounds, police said.
The shooting in the 3800 block of Franklin Avenue was reported at 9:17 p.m. Wednesday, according to San Diego police Acting Lt. Manuel Del Toro.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - The average price of a gallon of self-serve regular gasoline in San Diego County rose today to its highest amount since Sept. 18, increasing nine-tenths of a cent to $4.023.
The average price has risen six of the past seven days, including three- tenths on Wednesday, according to figures from the AAA and Oil Price Information Service.
SAN DIEGO (CNS) - Strong winds were forecast to continue to blow through the mountains and deserts of San Diego County today, meteorologists said.
Fairer weather is expected for Friday and Saturday, though some wind and a slight chance of light showers is possible Saturday night into Sunday, according to the National Weather Service.
]]></text></news-item>