<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-D8J1-JBM5-S0NS"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>ANOTHER POLLUTION FINE FOR SI GROUP</title><source>The Times-Union (Albany, NY)</source><author>BRIAN NEARING</author><text><![CDATA[Rotterdam
One of the Capital Region's largest chemical plants has been hit with its fourth state pollution fine in three years, this time for polluting the Mohawk River.
SI Group, which operates its plant at Main Street in Rotterdam Junction, agreed to a $75,000 fine under the federal Clean Water Act, according to a consent order signed with the state Department of Environmental Conservation this month. Of that amount, $10,000 will be forgiven if the company takes steps to prevent problems from recurring.
The plant makes chemical resins, used in a variety of manufactured products, and part of the fine stemmed from dumping of untreated waste water into the river in September 2013. The discharge contained phenol, a corrosive chemical that can irritate eyes, skin and respiratory tract.
Other violations last year included releasing into the Mohawk excessive amounts of cyanide and oxygen-consuming waste that depletes oxygen from river water and can kill aquatic life, based on test reports given to DEC. Other required reports on pollution discharge levels for other substances were missing, according to the agreement signed by DEC Regional Director Eugene Kelly and SI Vice President Daniel Tilley.
With the latest fine, the plant owners have been fined a total $275,000 by DEC since March 2011 for a myriad of air and water pollution violations in four separate cases.
"We take these allegations very seriously and, to be clear, we were proactive and self-reported the deviations from our permit requirements. We're doing what is necessary -- such as engaging two reputable engineering consulting firms to help ensure these incidents are not repeated," said company spokeswoman Brooke Manrique on Wednesday.
Under the terms of a December 2011 agreement over pollution in the river, SI agreed to file an evaluation of its wastewater system that would show areas of potential improvement. The report was initially to be filed by December 2012, and DEC later extended that deadline to December 2013. SI did not file the report by that deadline, and part of the latest fine reflects that failure.
In March 2013, the company agreed to a $112,500 fine after air pollution control equipment exploded the previous fall due to improper operation and workers "improperly engineered" a release of flammable vapor. DEC gave the company permission to produce resin for four days with no pollution control equipment in place after the company claimed the mishap was an equipment malfunction, rather than an operator error.
In December 2011, the company admitted that the plant exceeded pollution standards 18 times between March 2009 and August 2011 for waste water entering the Mohawk and paid a $73,000 fine. In March 2011, the company paid a $25,000 fine for failing to keep accurate records of air pollution emissions.
SI Group, formerly Schenectady International, employs about 200 people at its Rotterdam factory and another 200 at its headquarters and laboratory in Niskayuna. It has 20 factories around the world.
SI factories make resins used in 80 percent of the automobile tires made throughout the world, and many of its chemicals are used as raw materials to make products ranging from inks to fuel additives and plastics.
bnearing@timesunion.com - 518-454-5094 - @Bnearing10

]]></text></news-item>