<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-RFW1-DYRG-W3T4"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Scandal dismays Sunset neighborhood; DISTRICT'S REACTION</title><source>The San Francisco Chronicle (California)</source><author>Kale Williams</author><text><![CDATA[Fallout from the news of state Sen. Leland Yee's arrest was swift and severe in his home district this week, with many of his constituents expressing shock that a man whom many considered to be one of the "good guys" could be implicated in such a far-reaching scandal.
Yee, a Democrat who represents half of San Francisco and most of San Mateo County, was one of 26 people ensnared in a five-year federal investigation that also targeted notorious Chinatown gangster Raymond "Shrimp Boy" Chow.
An outspoken advocate of gun control and open government, Yee was arrested Wednesday and charged with conspiring to traffic in firearms as well as scheming to defraud citizens of honest services. While Yee has yet to comment on the allegations, people who live in his district were quick to offer their opinions.
"You tend to think of the Sunset District as this quiet, sleepy little backwater," said Charles Burch, a 63-year-old dispatcher for an alarm company who has lived in Yee's district since 1979. "And then to hear that he could be involved with Chinatown gangs and the sale of guns overseas - it's hard to believe."
For some, Yee's troubles were just another black eye for a political system that they feel increasingly fails to represent them.
"It's like, who can you trust?" said Christopher Mei, 62.
Mei, who works at the California Public Utilities Commission and lives in the Sunset, thought Yee should resign immediately.
"He has completely violated the public trust," he said. "In his case, he should quit while he's behind."
While many expressed shock at the extent of the allegations leveled against Yee, some weren't surprised to hear of yet another politician implicated in scandal. Two high-profile state Democratic state senators from Southern California - Ron Calderon of Montebello and Roderick Wright of Inglewood, both in Los Angeles County - recently also found themselves embroiled in legal troubles.
"It's horrible, but it's not that surprising," Ed Kanoti said from behind the counter of Eddy's Liquors in the Sunset District. "Politicians tell you one thing when they're running for office, but then once they're elected, they tell you something completely different."
Others took Wednesday's revelations more personally.
"It's a slap in the face to the Asian community," said Billy Shen, a 53-year-old graphic designer who also calls the Sunset home.
The dismay felt by Shen extends beyond Yee's district. Breanne Winfield lives in the Bayview, outside Yee's senate district, but works in the Sunset at a boutique near Ninth Avenue and Judah Street. As the mother of a young child, Winfield said she wonders more than ever where her kids are supposed to find role models.
"Who is our younger generation supposed to look up to?" she asked.
Amid the avalanche of criticism, at least one Sunset resident was skeptical of the case against the senator.
"To me, it smells like entrapment," said Ron Robinson, who has lived around the corner from Yee's residence for roughly 30 years. "If it is true, I don't think he was taking the money for himself - it was all for his campaign. We all need to wait and see how this thing shakes out."
One consistent theme in the reactions of Yee's constituents was frustration with the role that money plays in politics.
"It's amazing the actions people can rationalize when they're trying to retire these massive amounts of debt," Burch said in reference to the roughly $70,000 that Yee owed after an unsuccessful run for San Francisco mayor in 2011.
"I'd love to see this lead to some kind of campaign finance reform. The amount of money it takes to run for office these days means that some people are going to reach out to questionable sources. When you have to constantly be raising funds instead of doing the work of the people, this type of thing is bound to happen."
]]></text></news-item>