<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-32H1-JCM0-61VH"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Former union boss receives prison time in fraud case</title><source>ABC Transcripts (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TANYA NOLAN: First though, former union boss Michael Williamson has been sentenced to seven-and-a-half years in prison for what has become one of Australia's most notorious cases of union fraud.
Williamson had pleaded guilty to funnelling almost a million dollars from the Health Services Union (HSU) to businesses in which he had an interest.
For more Lexi Metherell joins me now from the Downing Centre District Court in Sydney.
Lexi, this prison term comes as no surprise to Williamson and his legal team. What are the details of the sentence?
LEXI METHERELL: Yes, he and his team have certainly been waiting for this. He was put in jail a couple of weeks ago after his bail was revoked and all of the four counts that he was facing carried jail time. They include two counts of defrauding the union, one of publishing false invoices and one of recruiting someone to hinder a police investigations.
Now he's been sentenced to seven-and-a-half years jail with five years non-parole so he's due to be out at the earliest in 2019, in March 2019 when he'll be about 65 years old.
The fraud he was found, or he pleaded guilty to actually, included setting up a company via which he paid his wife around $300,000 and the judge said today that payment was made for effectively very little work. She was meant to be helping record the, make records of the company's files and there was very little evidence that that was actually done properly.
The other count of fraud was related to $600,000 worth of fraud which involved invoices being inflated to a publishing company. So he was taking money off the top of these invoices.
Now Judge David Frearson described Williamson's conduct as arrogant and brazen. He said he leeched funds from the union when he was already handsomely paid and these remarks went on for almost an hour, it was quite a long sentencing and he spoke about Williamson's motivations a bit.
Williamson has said he was motivated by wanting to provide a better life for his children than he had when he was growing up, but the judge said today that was really nonsense because Williamson was already being paid very well and was in a position to do that. So he said that it was pure greed that motivated Williamson to commit this fraud.
TANYA NOLAN: And has there been any reaction from Williamson's legal team yet?
LEXI METHERELL: We haven't heard from Williamson's legal team. I believe some of his family members were in court today for the hearing, but also in the court were members of the Health Services Union, including the national secretary Kathy Jackson, who was the whistle-blower in this case and also Marco Bolano who's also with the HSU.
She spoke outside after the court. She said today is a victory for the union but she still has concerns about the HSU. She's very much in favour of the Royal Commission and she says there are still questions to be answered.
Now also...other people who were here today included members of the HSU. Out the front there were a number of signs, you know, talking about the hurt that they suffered as a result of Williamson's actions.
So there was a lot of interest in this case today and there was a fully packed public gallery in the court today.
TANYA NOLAN: And what are the chances of the new leadership of the HSU recovering that stolen money?
LEXI METHERELL: Well, it has been agreed that there was $5 million that has gone missing or been stolen from the HSU. Michael Williamson only pleaded guilty to four that was worth about $1 million, but the HSU's lawyers have already had one settlement with Williamson in which they agreed that he would pay back $1.7 million.
The lawyers are still pursuing a number of other avenues, including Williamson's former mistress who was Cheryl McMillan, who was also the purchasing manager at the HSU for funds that she gained by this fraud and also another former supplier to the union, Alfred Downing, he was the one who was involved, collaborated in inflating invoices.
It's a very tangled web. Michael Williamson has declared bankruptcy, so there is a bankruptcy trustee also pursuing this case.
It's going to be a very hard road for the union to recover the rest of that $5 million but the lawyers say they are hopeful of at least getting something.
TANYA NOLAN: Lexi Metherell at the District Court in Sydney. Thank you.
]]></text></news-item>