<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-PJJ1-JC65-54DR"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>FEATURE: Radiation physician trying to pass on lessons from Fukushima crisis</title><source>Japan Economic Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[FUKUI, Japan, March 28 - Physician Hironobu Tokunaga says it is his mission to pass on to younger generations the lessons he has learned from his involvement in medical work following the nuclear crisis at Tokyo Electric Power Co.'s Fukushima Daiichi power plant.
Tokunaga, 42, was sent to Sendai, Miyagi Prefecture, from the University of Fukui Hospital in Fukui Prefecture as a member of the Disaster Medical Assistance Team immediately after the magnitude 9.0 earthquake hit the northeastern Japan region of Tohoku on March 11, 2011. Two days later, he was assigned to the Fukushima prefectural government's disaster headquarters.
Tokunaga dealt with a flood of questions from nearby hospitals about radioactive contamination. "Even doctors and nurses lacked sufficient knowledge of radioactive contamination and exposure to radiation," he said.
More than 100 medical teams were formed across the country to examine residents' exposure to radiation in Fukushima, but only around 20 of them actually arrived there as many staff members turned down the assignment for fear of radioactive contamination.
About a decade earlier, an emergency system to treat people exposed to radiation was established in Japan following a critical accident at a nuclear fuel plant operated by JCO Co. in Tokaimura, Ibaraki Prefecture, in September 1999. Under the system, local governments with nuclear power plants within or near their jurisdictions have conducted drills for treatment and other countermeasures on a regular basis.
But "interest (in radioactive contamination) among participants in the drills had been extremely low until the Fukushima accident," said Hidekazu Terasawa, 62, professor at the medical school of the University of Fukui, who served as a lecturer under the system.
As nuclear power plants are usually located in depopulated areas facing an acute shortage of doctors, it was very difficult to make preparations there for the emergency treatment of exposure to radiation, Terasawa said.
Terasawa, one of the emergency room physicians in Fukui Prefecture who accept any type of patients, recognized the importance of urgent treatment for radiation casualties due to an accident at Kansai Electric Power Co.'s nuclear power plant in the Fukui Prefecture town of Mihama in August 2004. In the accident, five workers were killed and six others injured as a result of hot steam leaking from a broken pipe at its No. 3 reactor.
Terasawa and other physicians were unable to collect information on the workers' conditions -- whether they were exposed to radiation -- and other results of the accident in a timely manner.
"There is no absolute safety of things people produce and operate in the long run," Terasawa said.
As Fukui has the largest number of reactors among all of Japan's prefectures, Terasawa has been working to create a system that enables local physicians to study emergency treatment for radiation exposure at the University of Fukui and specialized institutions in the United States.
Tokunaga began to learn such treatment from Terasawa 10 years ago. In the prefectural city of Tsuruga, home to many nuclear power plants, Tokunaga has been teaching the treatment to other doctors and nurses at Municipal Tsuruga Hospital since the Fukushima crisis.
He also gives lessons to firefighters, police officers and school teachers and workers. When requested, he works at the ER facility created next to the front gate of the Fukushima Daiichi plant.
The Fukushima crisis has raised public fears about radioactive substances. But as they are widely used in medical treatment, agriculture, industrial production and various other fields, Tokunaga said, "In modern society, people cannot live without radioactive substances and rays."
Given this reality, Tokunaga said it is his "mission" to pass on what he learned through his work since the crisis began.
]]></text></news-item>