<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-3PJ1-JD6S-R1NF"><date>2014-03-27</date><title></title><source>The Arlington Advocate (Massachusetts)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[METCO an important program
In yesterday's Arlington Advocate there was a special opinion by Charles Foskett and Cindy Starks basically citing what they say are the costs to Arlington for the METCO program and saying that "It is time for Boston to start paying the real costs of this program. And it is time for Arlington to decide if we can afford to stay in a program with such a hefty price tag."
While I do not have the "costs" I do know that you cannot just straight line what it costs to educate Arlington students and directly cite that as the cost for the METCO students. In most cases, the children are accepted when young to fill "available" seats and much of that cost would be the same with or without the METCO program.
I will concede it probably is costing us some financial price but there is a moral cost as well. I know that Arlington was very brave in the late 60s when it was one of the original communities that voted to receive METCO students. This was during the Civil Rights Era. While we may not have been the "South" the North had its own type of segregation.
Growing up in Arlington there was barely a person of color - they stopped at the Cambridge and West Medford lines. Yes, Arlington had redlining and it took many years of courageous work of a small group of people to stop that. It took much longer to change curriculum to include black history and even longer, as it continues today, to make inroads to change cultural bias.
Without our METCO students, our own students education would be deficient in preparing them for their adult years. Furthermore our state, let alone our country, depends upon all of us finally overcoming race issues and cultural bias.
Please ad your voice to the public discussion and to your elected School Committee officials. - Janice Bakey, Fountain Road, Arlington
METCO more than money
In the commentary "Boston should pay more METCO costs" (March 13, 2014) Cindy Starks and Charlie Foskett make a compelling case for questioning the financial viability of Arlington's participation in the METCO program. The article concludes with "...it is time for Arlington to decide if we can afford to stay in a program with such a hefty price tag." Before our community engages in a debate about affordability, however, we need to first ask ourselves some bigger questions. Why are we involved in the program? What value does it bring to our schools? How does our involvement advance the town's goals and honor its principles? In short, the financial costs need to be considered in tandem with the program benefits.
In 1966, Arlington was one of the first towns to participate in METCO, a voluntary school integration program intended "to eliminate racial imbalance in the sending district" and, as the law states, "to help alleviate racial isolation in the receiving district."
As U.S. Federal District Court Judge Nancy Gertner said in regards to school integration efforts, "Without meaningful social contact, talk of tolerance and cooperation is nothing but an abstraction."
If our community believes that the goals and ideals of the METCO program are still a priority, then let's make sure that any discussions about its future include both the funding and the value that it brings to our town.
Above all, we should not lose sight of the fact that Arlington currently hosts 71 children in the METCO program whom we have invited into our schools. They, too, are members of this community. We must recognize that our collective discourse around this issue has a direct impact on their lives.
For more information about the METCO program, we encourage you to visit doe.mass.edu/metco.
Christine Carney, Stacy Davison and Mel Goldsipe are current members of the Arlington Human Rights Commission (AHRC). The views expressed in this letter are solely personal and are therefore not intended to represent an official AHRC position. - Laurie "Duck" Caldwell, Christine Carney, Stacy Davison, Mel Goldsipe, Anna Watson, Riley Watson, all of Arlington.
Thanks for honoring Bill Twomey
We would like to extend our thanks to the Arlington community for all that was done to honor our beloved husband and father, Bill Twomey, at his memorial gathering. We cannot express enough our gratitude to Cindy Curran and the entire Arlington Hockey Club-directors, coaches, players, and families-Captain McCormick and the hockey players who participated in the walk by, the Sons of Italy, DeVito Funeral Home, and our many Arlington friends and former neighbors. While we are devastated that Bill is no longer with us, all that you have done to honor Bill has been a great source of comfort and support to us.
Even though we moved away a few years ago, we still consider Arlington our "home." A case in point is the fact that "Coach Twomey" would never have considered coaching hockey anywhere else. In the last few weeks, many wonderful people have expressed to us how dedicated Bill was to the hockey program, and to Arlington in general. It should be noted, however, that Bill felt that he got back just as much as he gave, and that he was truly blessed to be part of the Arlington community. Given the generosity of spirit shown to us over these last few weeks, we would agree. - Roberta Klix, Patrick Twomey, and Liam Twomey
Buckley for School Committee
I'm writing in support for Michael Buckley for Arlington School Committee. I've known Mike and his family since our older daughters entered kindergarten at Dallin School, four years ago. Over these years, I've been impressed by Mike's down to earth and well-informed perspectives in education, and by his strong commitment to high quality education for the children in Arlington.
Mike has been a high school teacher for more than a decade. In the last few years, he has become a school administrator as a department head for social studies at the Minuteman High School in Lexington. This first-hand experience as an educator has allowed him to get a true sense of what works in schools. Teaching has enabled Mike to develop a sharp understanding of what really helps schools improve, what helps teachers be more effective, and a great deal of knowledge about the kind of policies and programs that support excellence in schools. His leadership roles in schools have made him a great listener, mentor and negotiator bringing divergent perspectives to a core goal: the wellbeing and successful learning of the students.
I believe that the Arlington School Committee would benefit from the experience and perspectives that a seasoned educator can provide. - Carolina Buitrago, Standish Road, Arlington
Tosi for selectman
It is with great confidence that we endorse Bob Tosi in his campaign for election to the Arlington Board of Selectmen.
Bob's experience is extensive and encompasses diverse town groups. His most known endeavors include being a Town Meeting member for 27 years, a member of the Arlington Finance Committee for 12 years and a member of the Council on Aging for nine years, there years of which he served as chairman.
What might not be as well known is Bob's commitment to the people of Arlington through is volunteer efforts associated with Arlington Boys and Girls Club, the Arlington Food Pantry, the Housing Corp. of Arlington, St. Vincent de Paul Society, the Arlington Historical Society, the Friends of Robbins Library, the Knights of Columbus and the churches of St. James, St. Camillus and St. Agnes. All of these experiences uniquely allow Bob to reach across generations and perspectives to view concerns from multiple vantage points, and to find solutions that respect all of Arlington’s citizens.
Bob is a man of impeccable integrity, steadfast dedication, caring compassion and tireless energy. The only special interest group that Bob represents is the town of Arlington and all of its members.
Thus, we respectfully ask your consideration in casting one of your two votes for selectmen for Bob Tosi on April 5. - Larry and Susan Greco, Dodge Street, Arlington
Tosi for selectman
I'm writing in support of Bob Tosi for Arlington's Board of Selectmen. Bob is a tireless worker with an impressive list of community service: 27 years as Town Meeting member, 12 years on the Finance Committee, 9 years with the Arlington Council on Aging all while volunteering his time at the Arlington Food Pantry, the St. Vincent de Paul Society and with the Special Needs Association. That's just to name a few, the list goes on.
Bob is a man of integrity who will listen to his constituents. You can be sure his actions will be in support of all Arlington citizens. He will definitely not cater to special interests, that's not in his character.
Bob is committed to maintaining high standards in our school system and in serving the needs of Arlington's senior citizens. I'm confident he'll do a great job as selectman and I ask you to join me in voting for Bob Tosi on April 5. - Pete Kenney, Cutter Hill Road, Arlington
Dunn for selectmen
I write in strong support of Dan Dunn for Selectman. Of the three candidates, he brings the best analytical skills and financial acumen, talents he has used to aid our town through the past several years.
From my political vantage point is as a School Committee member, it is on the Long Range Planning Committee where Dan really shines. He has chaired the group for the past two years. He brings to this job the same talents he displayed while a member of the town Finance Committee: an even-handed approach, a desire to understand the details and a push to ensure that all in our town see the rewards of our mutual efforts. He actively solicited discussion around the growing school enrollment and was instrumental in working out a responsible solution, while ensuring that Arlington maintains financial health as long as possible.
He has dealt with the complex issues surrounding Minuteman Regional Vocational High School and Arlington High School in the same way. With both he has fostered a thorough discussion of the options. With Minuteman he has explored different ways we can achieve our vocational-technical education goals while decreasing the burden on our taxpayers. With AHS he has been on the forefront learning why and how we as a town will need tackle this rebuilding project.
I urge you to join me in voting for Dan Dunn on April 5, so that he can continue his calm leadership to benefit Arlington into the future. - Kirsi Allison-Ampe, Governor Road, Arlington
Dunn for selectman
I first encountered Dan Dunn through his Town Meeting blog, which beautifully illustrates why Dan is such an asset to Arlington and why I am enthusiastically voting for him for selectman. In the blog, Dan provides a succinct, objective and thorough account of what happens at Town Meeting, while also clearly explaining his own thoughtful positions. The blog mirrors Dan's approach to everything he does: he listens carefully, pays close attention to the issues, and develops his own opinions, then works hard to come up with effective, well-grounded solutions to problems and challenges.
What does this mean practically? It means that Dan has played an essential role in creating a workable budget for Arlington that is helping us achieve our goals without draining our coffers. He helped craft a flexible and responsive funding plan to meet education needs. He has brought his considerable professional expertise to the task of moving Arlington forward technologically. He collaborates respectfully and effectively with colleagues, on the Board of Selectmen, School Committee, the Finance Committee and other town bodies.
Not only that, he's also warm, likeable, funny and a fantastic ambassador for Arlington. I am proud to support Dan Dunn, and I hope you will join me in voting for him on April 5.
Rebecca Steinitz, Cleveland Street, Arlington
Gilligan for treasurer
Readers who do not follow town politics closely should understand the background for this year's treasurer's race and why they should re-elect Stephen Gilligan.
Arlington's selectmen have been eying the takeover of the treasurer's office for years, but they haven't been able to get Town Meeting to agree. They and others invited the state Department of Revenue (DOR) to conduct a study, instead. The DOR told the selectmen what they wanted to hear, recommending a consolidated finance department for the town with the treasurer under the selectmen's control.
At Candidate's Night on March 20, Mr. Gilligan's opponent stated her support for the DOR report without reservation. So it should come as no surprise that selectmen are falling all over themselves to support her. They want to have a treasurer under their control, and she apparently agrees.
What is wrong with that? The role of the treasurer is to represent the broad financial interests of the town, not the narrow political interests of the selectmen.
The financial damage the selectmen caused when they pushed the Redevelopment Board to insert their favorite developer into the Symmes project demonstrates why we need a Treasurer who can act independently. The selectmen cost the town a lot of money with their meddling when their favored developer paid the town only a fraction of the fair market value for one two-acre parcel. In the treasurer's office, the stakes are much higher.
Stephen Gilligan understands the need for checks and balances in town government and the appropriate roles and responsibilities of town officials, boards, and committees. He was a selectman himself for 9 years. He has the independence, experience, and ability to continue to get the job done.
Please join me in voting to re-elect Stephen Gilligan to Treasurer on April 5. - Christopher Loreti, Adams Street, Arlington
Dunn for treasurer
Arlingtonians ask me two things about the upcoming town elections.
1. Is Julie Dunn, who is a candidate for treasurer, related to Dan Dunn, an incumbent seeking re election as selectman? The answer is no.
2. Why vote for Julie Dunn as treasurer?
Well where do I begin! Julie is finance person. She is a trained professional.
She will collaborate to modernize the office of the treasurer and help it work with all town offices, including the schools. She will streamline accounting practices by implementing the same software that all town offices use. How can it be that the treasurer's office uses outdated software that does not "talk" to any other town offices?
Julie will run an efficient office of the treasurer. For too long we have held on to old ways. As we limit the hours that town hall can be open, and citizens work hours expand, online payments are essential. This is the 21st century! The treasurer works for the voters, and as such should have as a priority improving services to citizens of the town.
She will look for opportunities and follow through to bring in new sources of revenue. One example of an untapped resource is the municipal parking. Arlington needs to be proactive in exploring a new, more expansive parking collection system and replace the faulty collection system we have.
I have known Julie for 15 years, and worked alongside her for several years in the Arlington Public School; she in cost containment and I, as grant writer and program manager. She tackles problems tenaciously. She looks for the facts, clarifies them for people to understand then works collaboratively to find a solution.
Julie has a unique ability to see the "big picture" and share that vision clearly.
Vote for Julie Dunn for treasurer and help her be part of a modern solution for Arlington's growing needs. - Judi Bohn, Arlington
Gilligan for treasurer
I'm writing to endorse Stephen Gilligan for Treasurer.
Since being elected treasurer in 2006, Mr. Gilligan has proved extremely effective in performing the duties of the office, and has done so with the highest degree of integrity.
The job of the treasurer is to collect taxes, manage borrowing, refinancing, and oversee Arlington's 103 trust funds and scholarships. In each of these areas Mr. Gilligan has delivered exceptional results for the Town.
In 2007 Arlington was upgraded by S&P to the highest rating of AAA, and has managed to maintain that rating through nine successive bond issues led by Mr. Gilligan. Arlington is one of only 20 municipalities in Massachusetts to hold an AAA rating. Mr. Gilligan has led the Town through three refinancings for a combined saving of $1.5 million, plus additional savings each year of over $250,000 in borrowing costs - all due to the superior credit rating of the town of Arlington.
As manager of the town's funds, Mr. Gilligan led the effort to change our outside portfolio advisors and fund managers. Since then, the collective return on all funds has averaged over 9% a year.
Lastly, as collector of taxes, Mr. Gilligan and his team have quietly and effectively collected 100% of all revenue owed the Town - every year. This, in addition to numerous other actions by the Treasurer, has kept Arlington at the highest level of financial soundness and stability.
Like many other people in Arlington, I value Mr. Gilligan's performance both professionally and personally. I urge you to consider him for Treasurer on April 5. - David Leone Jr., Bartlett Avenue, Arlington
Mahon for selectman
I have been an activist and an advocate for East Arlington for thirty years and I am voting for Diane Mahon for re-election to the Board of Selectman.
Diane has stood with us publicly, when few others would. Diane continues to work with residents to preserve the Mugar property as open space.
Diane continues to work with us to eliminate the dumping of raw sewage into Alewife Brook from the Combined Sewer Overflows of neighboring towns.
Diane has spoken out on numerous occasions calling for state agencies to take action to alleviate flooding conditions in sections of East Arlington.
Diane is a friend not only of the residents of the East but of all the residents of our town.
I am honored to be able to cast a vote for Diane Mahon for re-election to the Board of Selectmen. Please join me in voting for Diane! - George Laite, Lafayette Street, East Arlington
Dunn for treasurer
Julie Dunn has earned my admiration and support, and I hope you will join me on
Saturday, April 5, in electing her as Arlington's Treasurer. I have known Julie for over 20 years, and we have shared many common interests as Arlington residents, parents, church members and finance professionals. She has demonstrated her commitment to the town over many years and was a key force in making the Arlington Education Fund a success in raising funds to support public education in Arlington. She is past board chair and trustee of the First Parish Unitarian Universalist congregation. Of particular importance in her current campaign is her broad experience working with the schools and the town on budgets, securing grants and financial management.
Her credentials and accomplishments only tell part of the story. Julie is extremely smart, thoughtful and open-minded. She is an excellent communicator and hears and responds to different views diplomatically. She does her homework, and understands what change involves. She approaches any task with energy, enthusiasm and a positive attitude. She is a true team player, and at the same time understands the responsibilities of leadership.
As residents and taxpayers, we want to stretch our resources for the maximum possible impact in our community. Having strong financial management and systems is critical to that goal, and Julie Dunn is the right leader for the task. - Kay Snowden, Norfolk Road, Arlington
Susse for School Committee
Jennifer Susse has a keen understanding of complex issues, a passion for Arlington's children, and a long-term commitment to our schools. She is an ideal candidate for the Arlington School Committee, and I urge friends and neighbors to vote for her on Saturday, April 5.
Jennifer already serves Arlington by volunteering in our schools, serving on Town Meeting and leading a Girl Scout troop. A graduate of public schools, she has a Ph.D. in philosophy and taught at the university level for many years. Her resume is top notch, and we would be lucky to have someone of Jennifer's caliber serving on the School Committee.
School Committee members need to challenge one another, listen respectfully and keep open minds. We must also be willing to change course when presented with new information, master financial issues, and understand educational nuances. In addition to regular School Committee meetings, members put in hours of service on subcommittees, meetings with constituents, and researching complex educational issues.
Jennifer Susse has an ideal background for the work done on a board that oversees the largest budget of any department in Arlington. Jennifer will help the Arlington School Committee to continue doing great work serving the students of our town's public schools. - Jeff Thielman, Arlington School Committee member, 2003 to present
Susse for School Committee
I am writing in enthusiastic support of Jennifer Susse for Arlington School Committee. I first met Jennifer six years ago when her children first attended Thompson School, where my children were also students. A member of the Thompson PTO Board at the time, I was immediately impressed with her strong desire to jump in and become a contributing member to the group. Jennifer recognized the inherent needs unique to the Thompson community and worked tirelessly with others in the PTO to implement creative ideas and solutions, such as the Arlington Community Card. Her drive, vision and collaborative skills were a driving force in the success of this program, thus enabling the PTO to further its goal of providing educational enrichment opportunities to the entire Thompson student body.
Since that time I have seen Jennifer put the same amount of enthusiasm and dedication into all of her endeavors. Whether it be her commitment as a Town Meeting member, an activist in local and national political campaigns, a producer and volunteer with Arlington Children's Theatre, or her obligations as a Girl Scout volunteer, Jennifer can always be counted on to work tirelessly and competently.
Through her extensive volunteer work, Jennifer has had the opportunity to converse with a wide array of people and groups in town. She has gained a keen insight into the concerns held by members of our community, and has an understanding of the complex issues facing our schools. With her educational background, strength of character, and ability to analyze, listen and reflect, Jennifer is superbly qualified to serve as a member of the School Committee.
I am thrilled that Jennifer is running for this position, she is smart, committed and insightful. Please join me in voting for Jennifer Susse for School Committee on April 5. - Suzanne Leone Lindner, Winter Street, Arlington
Mahon for selectmen
As a long time Arlington coach and supporter of youth sports, I enthusiastically endorse Diane Mahon for re-election to the Arlington Board of Selectmen.
From the playing fields to the selectmen's boardroom, Diane has tirelessly advocated for the youth of our community.
Several years ago, Diane worked with parents and the town's state senator to secure state funds to pay for lights on the Warren A. Pierce field at Arlington High School. Our teams were able to play night games under the lights for the first time.
As a current Arlington High Cheer coach, Diane continues to work for our children. I'm voting for Diane Mahon for re-election to the Board of Selectmen and urge you to do the same. - Bob Geribo, Forest Street, Arlington
Dunn for selectman
Sitting in the audience on Thursday night at the League of Women Voters debate, I was struck once again by Dan Dunn's command of his job as selectman. Dan is knowledgeable and experienced. He is comfortable dealing with the issues that arise on an every day basis.
He understands that his primary task for the taxpayers is to keep the town on solid financial footing. He works well with his colleagues, the Finance Committee, and our new Town Manager. He can handle the other selectmen tasks well too, whether it isinitiating fair taxi-cab regulations, handling parking issues or dealing with licensingissues. He listens, is even-handed, and lets his sense of humor shine through whennecessary.
As a former selectman, I know how important his intelligence and strategic thinking is in stretching the three-year plan into a seven-year plan. I want him on the board to help unravel the complications of the Minuteman agreement before we deal with the cost of rebuilding that school. I want him to help deal with the Arlington High School rebuild in the same thoughtful, fair way.
I hope you will join me in voting for Dan Dunn for Re-Election on April 5. - Clarissa Rowe, Herbert Road, Arlington
Sheri Baron asks for TM vote
Election Day is just around the corner. I am asking the citizens of Precinct 7 to please consider giving me one of your votes for Town Meeting member. I have been a Town Meeting member for
17 years. I take my responsibility to represent my constituents very seriously. I have lived in Arlington for nearly 37 years and raised my family here.
I believe that my greatest achievement for the town has been the change in beer and wine policy. Following a request at Town Meeting more than 20 years ago from a restaurant owner whose patrons were asking for wine with their excellent meals, I (with another Town Meeting colleague) spearheaded the campaign to allow the service of beer and wine in local restaurants. This economic change has transformed Arlington from "the sleepy little known with a vaguely colonial past" into a fine dining and shopping destination (and soon tourism, as well).
I have also been active on a number of committees and commissions, including Vision 2020, the Arlington Human Rights Commission (20 years), the Massachusetts Avenue Corridor Project Advisory Committee, and the Master Planning Advisory Committee. I have an M.B.A. and a M.Ed., and work as a professional, nonprofit fundraiser, for organizations such as The American Red Cross of Eastern Massachusetts and The Greater Boston Food Bank. I have also taught in the public schools and worked as an Early Intervention Specialist with children with communication disabilities.
I care about our town and the well being of its residents. I value Arlington's diversity and want to keep working on making this town a welcoming and safe place for all those who live and work here. I respectfully ask for your vote on Saturday, April 5 for Town Meeting member in Precinct 7 (vote at Chestnut Manor). Thank you very much. - Sheri Baron, Raleigh Street, Arlington
Gilligan for treasurer
Steve Gilligan is honest, intelligent, humorous, the easiest person to work with that I've met in a decade of Town Meeting service.
And, he's every bit the expert in municipal finance and technology his résumé proves (although Steve is the last person to flaunt his résumé in front of anyone.)
So what? You can't put a number on Steve's personal qualities or his eminent professional qualifications. But, you can grade his results as Arlington's treasurer, if you are Standard & Poor's, and your business is rating towns' credit worthiness.
And S&P gives Steve a grade of AAA. Not A or AA, perfectly respectable scores, but its highest rating of AAA, awarded to fewer than 10% of Massachusetts towns. Triple-A. The town has received that rating every year since 2008.
Steve's money-management skills have saved Arlington millions of dollars. He won't flaunt that fact, but I will.
Please join me in re-electing Steve Gilligan our treasurer on April 5. - Michael Ruderman, Precinct 9 town Meeting Member, Alton Street, Arlington
Gilligan for treasurer
I am supporting Stephen Gilligan for many reasons. Stephen has proven that over the past eight years, he has the knowledge, experience and training to be reelected our treasurer. He achieved and maintained our AAA rating during his tenure, and saved thousands in interest charges. Stephen always assembled a team of senior town managers to present Arlington's issues.
On Stephen's watch, there has been a 100 percent collection rate for property taxes. Also, he initiated reimbursement for our schools, when other departments responded slowly to the urgent need for funds.
Statements that Stephen is not a team player or does not collaborate with other departments lacks credibility, and has no basis in fact. I have a difficult time understanding these statements, because for the past eight years the treasurer's office has issued 100 billing cycles on time.
On Stephen's watch he has worked directly and professionally, with the assessors, comptroller and other town departments to achieve this solid record of responsibility to the people of Arlington.
As a homeowner, business owner and town meeting member, I trust Stephen as our treasurer.
Please vote for good government. Please vote for the reelection of Stephen Gilligan. - Maria Romano, Bates Road, Arlington
Tosi for selectman
Bob is very involved in the community as evidenced by his participation in over 15 different public and private organizations in Arlington including: Boys and Girls Club, Council on Aging Board, Finance Committee, Food Pantry, Historical Society, Housing Corporation, Land Trust and Vision 2020. I believe, with all the years that Bob has spent in organizational leadership roles, his experience makes him a fine candidate for the office of selectman. Further Bob has practical understanding of working with the elderly due to his employment with Minuteman Senior Services as a care manager. Bob will work hard for more services for the elderly and the community in general. Bob also supports the need for the town to address the status of Arlington High School, which is in disrepair.
Please join me in voting for Bob Tosi for Selectman on April 5. - William J. Logan, Esq., Town Meeting Member Precinct 2, Arlington
Gilligan for treasurer
I'm writing to support Stephen Gilligan for Arlington Town Treasurer. Stephen has shown his commitment to the town over the years through his public service and volunteerism. His education and professional background is well suited to the treasurer's job, and he's worked hard to make sure the town's tax revenues are collected to their fullest - not the easiest thing in the down economy we've seen over the past several years. Thanks to Stephen, the town's borrowing costs are as low as they can be and he's not been shy about chasing the state for money it owes the town. Stephen's financial expertise has served the Town well. Let's keep Stephen working for Arlington!
Jeanne Leary, Summer Street, Arlington
]]></text></news-item>