<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-3H21-F072-41YV"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>BBC neglecting youth for elite arts, say producers</title><source>The Independent (London)</source><author>IAN BURRELL MEDIA EDITOR</author><text><![CDATA[Two of the most senior figures in British television comedy have accused the BBC of turning its back on younger audiences in favour of courting the high-arts establishment.
In comments which are damaging to the corporation's Director-General, Tony Hall, Jimmy Mulville, the co-founder of Hat Trick Productions and the producer of some of the BBC's most popular comedies, said the broadcaster had "embarked on a mission focused on making itself irrelevant in 10 years' time".
In interviews to the magazine Broadcast, Mr Mulville and Ash Atalla, the producer of The Office, criticised the timing of a star-studded event convened this week in which Lord Hall offered BBC positions to arts grandees.
The pair criticised the initiative, which saw roles offered to Tate's Sir Nicholas Serota and the National Theatre's director, Sir Nicholas Hytner, days after the announcement of the closure of the youth-oriented BBC Three. Mr Mulville said: "The message to young people is: we don't want to serve you culturally, we want to serve the high arts."
Mr Atalla, the founder of the production company Roughcut TV, compared the closure of BBC3 as a television channel, while pouring added resources into the arts, to an old man objecting to a nightclub's music so he could "hear more Mozart next door".
He said: "You can't argue against the arts per se; that would be absurd. But you can when their promotion comes after a direct cut to youth, to comedy, to diversity. This is a daylight land-grab by a metropolitan élite. I was right - the Mozart has been turned up."
Lord Hall is in a difficult position as he leads the BBC into the next round of negotiations for its royal charter funding. He is anxious to underline the broadcaster's public-service remit, but in moving BBC Three solely on to iPlayer his executive has come under fire from a noisy constituency.
]]></text></news-item>