<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-X301-DY2T-02RC"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Trio develops care facility software</title><source>The Star Phoenix (Saskatoon, Saskatchewan)</source><author>Scott Larson, The Starphoenix</author><text><![CDATA[Curtis Chapman says visiting his grandmother in a seniors care facility was one of the factors that led him and two colleagues to develop new software.
Chapman, Scott Kopelchuk and Henry Fernandes make up Avocado Applications, which has created careoperations.com, software geared toward helping manage seniors care facilities more efficiently and also improve residents' quality of life.
"My grandmother was in a care home in rural Saskatchewan, so I would call in on her," Chapman said. "What mattered to her in these care homes has shaped some of these features that we've built into the software. It's little things like the type of tea my grandmother liked."
Chapman said the key to the software is the ability to track residents' information.
Features include resident profiles, messaging for staff, tracking activities and care home management. The software can be used in longterm care facilities, care homes, retirement communities and group homes. Fernandes said the web application is available 24 hours a day, eliminates duplication, saves time and reduces administrative costs. "It is very easy for homes to use and there is no installation required," Fernandes said, adding clients pay a monthly fee for the service.
At many facilities there is no overlap between shifts, so a messaging system lets staff communicate with each other.
Kopelchuk said with the software there is one central record for each resident which allows all staff access to the information in a secure way.
And family members can also find out what has been happening as there is a historic record of what has been communicated about each resident.
There is also the ability to track what activities residents have participated in, Kopelchuk said.
"Communicating those little things about residents between staff allows them to provide a higher level of care," Chapman added.
The trio, all University of Saskatchewan grads, have been working on the project for about 18 months. The initiative gained traction when they placed in the Top 3 at last year's U of S Industry Liaison Office (ILO) Tech Venture Challenge.
That won Avocado consulting services ongoing support from the ILO, helped write the business plan and also connect with the local startup community.
They have a few facilities using the software, which is still evolving.
"As we get feedback we are making it stronger and more robust," Chapman said.
"We are trying to make sure we have the right features so that it has value for the customers," added Kopelchuk. "We want to do it in a traditional way where we provide someone with a good amount of value and they pay us a bit of money. That way the business model is sustainable long-term." Go to careoperations.com for more information.
Careoperations.com features
Resident profiles The profiles keep data of residents all in one place. Profiles includes the residents' photos and health information, It can also list things such as if they are married, their religion, hobbies etc. It also has family contact information.
Messaging Staff are able to communicate with one another about resident care, and with everything recorded it is easy to track communication about residents.
No more note pads, sticky notes, or messy communication logs.
Careoperations.com's messaging system ensures personal health information is kept private.
Activities This feature lets the facility schedule activities, track participation and print out reports showing attendance. Chapman said family can see what a resident has been doing at the facility. Staff can see if activities have fallen off for a resident. It also shows what activities are the most popular or effective. Resident participation makes planning for care conferences with family members much easier.
Care home management The management feature shows information about your facility on a single screen where you can manage employee accounts and departments or multiple facilities.
]]></text></news-item>