<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-VV01-JC8S-C397"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Turkey bans YouTube, steps up pressure on media ahead of local elections</title><source>BBC Monitoring Europe - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Text of report in English by Turkish newspaper Today's Zaman website on 27 March
27 March 2014, Thursday /Istanbul, TODAYSZAMAN
(Todays Zaman) -The embattled Justice and Development Party (AK Party) government, which has been the subject of graft allegations, on Thursday [27 March] banned access to YouTube shortly after banning Twitter, cancelling the nationwide broadcasting license of one station and issuing a record number of penalties to another.
The Telecommunications Directorate (TIB) on Thursday afternoon blocked access to popular video sharing platform YouTube hours after a leaked voice recording allegedly featuring the voices of Turkey's foreign minister, intelligence chief and a top army general discussing the developments in neighbouring war-torn Syria was uploaded onto the site.
In the voice recording, Foreign Minister Ahmet Davutoglu, National Intelligence Organization (MIT) Undersecretary Hakan Fidan, Foreign Ministry Undersecretary Feridun Sinirlioglu and Deputy Chief of General Staff Gen. Yasar Guler are heard discussing a possible intervention in Syria and potential reactions from the world.
The ban comes a week after Twitter was blocked by the TIB in a move widely seen as a response to leaked voice recordings posted on the micro-blogging site that seem to implicate Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan, his close family members and some members of his government in large-scale corruption. However, Twitter's block might be lifted soon, according to Deputy Prime Minister Emrullah Isler.
The 15th Ankara Administrative Court on Wednesday issued an injunction on Turkey's Twitter ban, saying it runs "contrary to the principles of the rule of law." The ban had not been lifted as of Thursday, but Isler said in televised remarks: "To my knowledge, Twitter has carried out the demands of TIB and there are only a few remaining issues. When those issues are resolved, Twitter will be completely unblocked."
The YouTube ban comes only one day after the Radio and Television Supreme Council (RTUK) cancelled the nationwide broadcasting license of the KanalTurk television station. KanalTurk, owned by Ipek Media, will now only be allowed to broadcast in the Marmara region. Reports said the five AK Party members of RTUK voted for the cancellation, while Republican People's Party (CHP) members Ali Oztunc and Suleyman Demirkan and Nationalist Movement Party (MHP) member Esat Ciplak objected to the body's decision.
The RTUK penalty came days after Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan vowed to finish off the Hizmet movement - inspired by Turkish Islamic scholar Fethullah Gulen - and its associates, including Samanyolu Haber TV.
Ipek Media Group head Fatih Karaca, who is also a former chairman of RTUK, said the decision was against the law. "I have never spoken about any RTUK action since I left as chairman of the board in July 2005, but I have to enlighten the public on this," he said on KanalTurk's afternoon news programme.
He said before KanalTurk was bought by Ipek Media in 2008, there was a lawsuit ongoing regarding KanalTurk's nationwide broadcasting rights launched in 2007. In 2011, after changes to the RTAoeK law, the new management of KanalTurk went to court, winning decisions in its favour from the 2nd Administrative Court and later the Council of State. "The decision [to cancel the national license] is based on a trial from eight years ago based on a law that is no longer in force."
He said he hoped the decision was the result of a misunderstanding but also noted it had been taken without a statement in writing from the RTUK Legal Undersecretariat and apparently in haste. "I was notified at 12:40 a.m. this morning," he said.
Karaca said the nationwide broadcast license only relates to analog land frequency broadcasts which account for less than 1 per cent of the station's audience. He said the license does not concern digital, cable or satellite broadcasts but noted that there was an attempt to create a misunderstanding.
He said news stories that KanalTurk can now only be accessed in the Marmara region were untrue, adding that an advertising agency had e-mailed companies this false information as well. He said the company, which he did not name, and the RTUK board will be held legally responsible for any financial losses KanalTurk might incur due to the wrong perception created by the decision.
Karaca also said KanalTurk has filed an application for a review, and he believes the decision will be reversed after RTUK reviews it.
The move to cancel KanalTurk's license comes shortly after RTUK issued 36 broadcast suspension penalties for several programmes of the Samanyolu Haber TV news station.
Commenting on the recent developments, Nationalist Party Movement (MHP) Ankara deputy Ozcan Yeniceri said recent developments, such as the ban on Twitter and leaked recordings allegedly proving that Erdogan dictated the headlines of the HaberTurk daily through government press commissioner Fatih Sarac, clearly demonstrate the prime minister's attitude towards society's access to news.
Yeniceri further noted: "RTUK meting out a deluge of penalties to networks that are not part of the chorus that broadcasts all of the prime minister's speeches uninterruptedly is a sign of a one-man regime. The pressure and intimidation on some of the media is reminiscent of [Josip] Tito's Yugoslavia. He is trying to find excuses to disable the institutions that he cannot shut down."
"As the single-party and one-man mentality is out there, his allies and the bureaucrats that are helping Erdogan are also responsible for what's going on. At a time when freedoms are under threat and the principles of democracy and human rights are being destroyed, it is impossible not to expect to step up pressure on the media. But with these actions Erdogan and his accomplices are losing legitimacy."
Republican People's Party (CHP) Deputy Chairman Gursel Tekin said the government is ready to risk a war with Syria in an attempt to minimize the corruption scandal. "Unfortunately in this state of emergency they have started, the rule of law has been suspended. It is obvious that the AKP, which is enforcing its own laws, will prevent information from being disseminated to the public."
He said punishing networks that broadcast the news against "hired people who disseminate propaganda for Erdogan" is an indication that a "one-man regime" is in place. "There is no legal basis or convincing reason for cancelling the license of a national network," Tekin said.
CHP Konya deputy Atilla Kart, who is a member of the parliamentary Constitution Commission, said: "We are faced with an administration that is prepared to carry out any illegality to make sure that graft evidence doesn't make its way to the public. We are faced with a government that doesn't hesitate to manufacture evidence in order to prevent people from receiving information. All these illegal actions are being carried out for personal and political interests."
He said Kanal Turk is making an effort to ensure that the public is properly informed. "Intolerance towards publishing and broadcasting in line with the principles of journalism has become the motto of the government." He described the point Turkey has reached as "extremely worrying" in terms of societal and regional peace, claiming the government has shown it will not hesitate to go to war with Syria to protect its own interests.
Meanwhile, in a statement regarding the penalties, Samanyolu Media Group head Hidayet Karaca said, "These incredible penalties issued against our institution just ahead of elections which are taking place amidst graft and illegality scandals have a special meaning."
Thirty-six suspension penalties - all related to broadcasting about the local elections - is a record number of penalties in the history of Turkey's television broadcasting, according to a tweet from Samanyolu Haber TV Editor-in-Chief Metin Yikar, who also noted that the news programme at Samanyolu Haber TV - whose broadcast has been suspended - would be broadcasted on Samanyolu TV.
Hidayet Karaca said: "With this last decision, RTAoeK has clearly shown the kind of instrument of pressure on the media it has turned into at the hands of the government. The purpose of the penalties is clearly understood by the people." He said the Samanyolu Media Group will continue broadcasting honest and impartial news but said those who are behind the illegal actions of today will be remembered as "dark stains" on the country's democracy.
MHP Deputy Chairwoman Ruhsar Demirel said the government was finding new ways of censorship. "The government, which is increasing pressure in every sphere, is doing all that it can to limit freedom to access news and information. It is demonstrating that it won't hesitate to resort to all kinds of illegal actions," she said.
She noted that the cancellation of licenses and suspensions not only violate fundamental rights, but also intervene in free trade. "Can these illegalities that local businesses are subjected to attract foreign investors? Erdogan doesn't care about the league of countries that Turkey, isolated from the rest of the world to such an extent, has fallen into. He has other targets. People close to him are also complicit in this."
Source: Zaman website, Istanbul, in English 27 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>