<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-KFR1-DXDT-655C"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Turkey blocks access to YouTube</title><source>standard.co.uk</source><author>Martyn Landi</author><text><![CDATA[Turkey has blocked access to YouTube just a day after a court ordered the government to lift a ban on Twitter imposed by the Prime Minister.
The Turkish telecoms authority TIB said today it has taken an "administrative measure" against the Google-owned video site.
Prime minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan singled out the video-sharing website for criticism on Tuesday after previously accusing Twitter of trying to undermine the personal privacy of those within his government.
"What is this thing called Twitter anyway?" he said on state television. "It is a company, involved in communication, social media, et cetera. Now, you look at it and actually see YouTube behind this. They do not have a representative here, but work with the lawyers of YouTube." Twitter had hired the same law firm YouTube has used during a dispute with Turkish authorities in 2008, when the site was also banned.
Mr Erdogan promised to "rip out the roots" of social network Twitter after a series of tweets appeared on the site that appeared to incriminate him and other top officials in relation to corruption. The site was banned last week, however Turkish users began changing internet settings in order to get around the block.
London-based Turkish journalist Figen Gunes said: "It was only a couple of hours ago the YouTube ban was announced but already in Google when one makes a search by writing 'YouTube ban' in Turkish, the second suggestion that comes up is about 'how to bypass the YouTube ban'. The previous YouTube ban and the recent Gezi movement in Turkey showed how the young generation is tech-savvy and still proves to be.
"The main opponent CHP's president Kemal Kilicdaroglu says Mr Erdogan has been scared of 140 characters so that's why Twitter has been banned.
"Now, the YouTube ban informs us that Erdogan is striving to hold on to power regardless of international pressures reminding him of the importance of the rule of law. The YouTube ban is against the freedom of expression and it should be overturned immediately."
Yesterday a Turkish court overturned the ban on Twitter, ordering the government to restore the service. It was unclear whether an appeal would be lodged, but more court action is now likely following the new YouTube ban. The block had caused uproar within Turkey, with the Turkish bar association and journalists' union bringing the court action citing a breach of freedom of expression.
]]></text></news-item>