<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-VV11-JCB2-W0SJ"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Wonga SA dismisses talk of a credit bubble</title><source>Business Day (South Africa)</source><author>MARVIN MEINTJIES</author><text><![CDATA[Wonga SA dismisses talk of a credit bubble
London
WONGA SA CEO Kevin Hurwitz is not sweating over changes to SA's National Credit Act.
He sat down with Business Day in London to explain why, and why he hates alarmist talk that SA is heading for a credit bubble.
From April 1 credit bureaus will have to remove data listing debt judgments against people who have since paid off their loans. Some credit providers have said this will negatively affect their ability to assess loan applications.
Mr Hurwitz, cousin of Wonga co-founder Jonty Hurwitz, says he thinks the focus on changes to the National Credit Act may be & slightly politically motivated& given there is an election on the horizon. But Wonga, he says, has already factored this in. & We know the removal of adverse credit information has already been passed,& he says.
& That's not going to affect our business in a major way. I don't think it's a good thing. Generally we work in a very strong data culture and I don't think we should be removing data generally, on principle. There are other ways to solve a problem than removing 1.5-million records.& But how will this not affect Wonga SA, if others are complaining? & Right now let's say someone is blacklisted; we get that info from the bureau and are totally reliant on it and for the most part it's accurate. We would immediately decline that person. So all that's going to happen now is they're going to go through the risk engine. I have huge confidence and faith in the risk engine (the complex algorithms Wonga uses to assess loan candidates).
& They'll get declined if they aren't the right customers. So that's what's going to happen for the most part.
& For credit providers that rely purely on credit bureau information it's going to be a little bit more difficult. It's going to take time to get the modelling around the removal of that information accurate again.
& We don't just rely exclusively on credit bureau information ... they're a part of the puzzle, we use their information hugely but not exclusively, so we've built that (removal of the data) in already.& So, with that risk dealt with, what are the chances of listing Wonga in SA? There were rumblings of a possible UK listing. Then a possible US listing. The answer: & No. The media spoke of a listing; at some point there might have been a thought. But it's never been something on top of the agenda internally. Our focus is on building the business.& The company has had its hands full dealing with bad PR over its practices in the UK, where the country faces a cost of living crisis.
& This is not a Wonga issue in the UK. It's because Wonga was early to market in this space, people might think of it as a bit of a poster boy. The reality is that this is a UK consumer credit issue and it's affecting every credit provider that transacts in a certain space. So it's a UK regulatory issue, as simple as that.
& We are absolutely determined ... to be co-operative and compliant with all the changes being made. This is a good thing.& Wonga has found itself in a highly charged political debate in the UK, where over-indebtedness has been rising, and to a lesser extent in SA.
& Again, we have to be very clear. The first debate is whether you believe credit is a vital part of the economy. For most people who have some kind of intelligence on economic matters, there will be very few who say credit is not a vital part of economic growth. So that's the starting point. The fact we have a regulated environment (in SA) is a huge plus. Again, our issues are with those companies that are noncompliant....
& We've done economic studies. We don't have an over-indebtedness problem in SA. I see it's in the media again. Some American said we're headed for a credit bubble. Our household debt-income ratio is 74%-75%. In the UK it's something like 140%. In SA it's dropped over the last three years. For me, and many economists, we need to have a fast-growing economy to even consider a bubble and we just don't have that.& That is a macro issue. Mr Hurwitz says macro issues have been confused with micro issues - that risky lending practices by individual companies have been interpreted as macro issues for the country.
Wonga's default rate is & single digit& as a percentage of loans granted. & We have a really good arrears rate. We also only accept on average 25% of first-time applicants.& He laughs when asked the size of his loan book. & It's a significant business,& is all he will say.
I have huge confidence and faith in the risk engine ... they'll be declined if they aren't the right customers
Kevin Hurwitz, chief executive of Wonga SA
]]></text></news-item>