<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-DWY1-F025-P1C5"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>300 show upto debate taxes in Chesterfield; Residents are split during meeting on raising rates</title><source>Richmond Times Dispatch (Virginia)</source><author>JOHN RAMSEY</author><text><![CDATA[At least 300 people packed Chesterfield County's public meeting room Wednesday for a lengthy public hearing that highlighted split opinions on whether the Board of Supervisors should raise property taxes.
The Board of Supervisors is considering a 3-cent property tax increase for schools and a 1.5-cent increase (reduced from 1.6 cents) to help pay for federally mandated stormwater reductions.
Of the crowd's members, 84 signed up beforehand to speak directly to the board concerning the proposed budget. Several more stood up to speak once the meeting began.
Nearly all the speakers who addressed the tax increase -- whether for or against it -- were applauded by members of the audience who shared their opinion. Outside the room, a crowd sat watching on a small TV, unable to get inside the packed meeting.
"When it comes to government, smaller is definitely better," county resident Fred DeMay said. "Taxes hurt people, ladies and gentlemen. Higher taxes hurt people more."
Each extra penny on the tax rate would generate about $3 million for the county and add $20 to the annual bill for a $200,000 home.
Before the meeting began, special-interest groups handed out materials in favor of and in opposition to the property tax increase.
Teachers and others who wore red to indicate solidarity in their support of more schools funding said higher taxes are necessary to restore a faltering school system to excellence.
"If the board does not now act responsibly to increase revenue, we all lose," county resident Doug Scheibe said. "When the school district becomes substandard, that will lead to diminishing property values."
Of the 44 people who spoke specifically about the proposed tax increase, 24 were in favor and 20 were opposed.
Chesterfield has cut more than $50 million from its budget and eliminated 618 full-time jobs since 2009. The school system's budget dropped by $60 million, and it lost about 500 employees during that time frame.
Those cuts in schools have meant larger classes, fewer offerings of electives and increased workloads for the remaining teachers. Spending per student dropped from $9,066 in 2009 to $8,225 in 2012, nearly three times the average cuts across the state's public schools.
The cuts left Chesterfield near the bottom of the pack in Virginia; only nine school divisions spend less per student. The county also ranks near the bottom of the state in class sizes, with larger classes than all but 15 Virginia school systems.
Residents opposed to the tax increase said the government needs to look at other ways to pay for what it wants without further burdening property owners.
Clayton Rhodes said people who would never try to use his home also think it's OK to allow the government to take his money for projects they support.
"People like me ask one thing of government: Let me keep more of what I earned," Rhodes said. "We don't have the extra money to spend, so don't spend it. If you don't have the money, that's the lesson we teach our kids, don't spend it."
Others who opposed the increase said people can't afford to pay the county more because of the still-struggling economy.
Part of the Board of Supervisors' debate centers on how any extra revenue raised for schools would be spent.
Originally, 2 cents of the proposed tax rate increasewas slated to help pay for completing within seven years the $304 million in school renovations approved by voters in November.
The county hoped a 2 percent meals tax included on the same November ballot would pay for the projects by raising about $8 million a year, but voters rejected the idea. Some speakers Wednesday night said the defeat of the meals tax should show county leaders how its residents feel about a tax increase.
The other penny of the proposed tax increase is expected to go toward the schools' pay-as-you-go renovations.
But the board has been debating whether to shift some or all of the money raised for schools toward hiring more teachers. The School Board supports the idea, even though it would push the voter-approved school projects to a nine-year completion window instead of seven. The plan would allow the school system to hire 250 teachers during the next five years.
The Board of Supervisors is also considering a list of 30 potential cuts totaling $17.8 million that was developed last week by county staff members after elected leaders asked for cost-savings measures that could negate the need for a tax increase.
The new menu of cuts includes delaying the opening of a fire station, forgoing raises for employees, getting rid of some property-tax exemptions, reducing tourism contributions, and eliminating county-funded programs such as the drug court.
Supervisor Dorothy Jaeckle said the board will have a difficult job identifying which potential cuts may be the most harmful because of the tight timetable it now faces. The board plans to adopt its budget at a meeting April 9, just two weeks away.
"It would've been nice if as each department presented, if there's a proposed group of cuts, if we as a board had an opportunity to ask them about what the ramifications of the cuts are," Jaeckle said. "We don't know the ramifications of some of these cuts and we have to decide by April 9."
The proposed $771 million budget includes fee increases such as adding $10 to the cost of vehicle registration fees to help pay for transportation improvements in addition to the proposed tax increase. Of the 4.8 percent spending increase proposed in County Administrator James J.L. Stegmaier's budget, 75 percent is dedicated to schools and public safety.
The conservative group Americans for Prosperity -- founded by billionaire brothers David and Charles Koch -- has also been involved in the debate.
Leading up to Wednesday's public hearing, the group paid for robocalls and sent members door to door to encourage residents to show up in opposition to the tax increase. People in green Americans for Prosperity shirts handed out pamphlets Wednesday to people who entered the meeting room.
The county's two leading business organizations have signaled at least partial support for a property tax increase. The Chesterfield Business Council signaled full support for the proposed tax increases. The Chesterfield Chamber of Commerce said it would endorse a 2-cent increase to pay for the voter-approved school projects but would have to further evaluate its position if the money were instead used to hire more teachers.
Laura Lafayette, chief executive officer of the Richmond Association of Realtors, said Wednesday that she also favors the tax increase because unfunded mandates and the effects of the recession have left the county with needs it can't otherwise afford.
"At this point, the county can cut its way to mediocrity, but not prosperity," Lafayette said.
jramsey@timesdispatch.com
(804) 649-6911
Staff writer Louis Llovio contributed to this report.
]]></text></news-item>