<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-MV81-JBVM-Y04J"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>BLACKOUT OF ORDER; ENERGY RIP-OFF SCANDAL: PROBE WILL TAKE TWO YEARS! Ofgem orders full inquiry into industry over rocketing prices at cosy Big Six firms Centrica chief's shameless threat to leave Brits in dark branded 'blackmail'</title><source>Daily Mirror</source><author>GRAHAM HISCOTT</author><text><![CDATA[FATCAT Centrica boss Sam Laidlaw has been slammed for "holding a gun" to customers' heads after claiming a probe into the rip-off energy market could trigger blackouts.
The chief executive, whose company owns British Gas, warned an investigation ordered yesterday into competition would delay investment in new power plants.
Asked if the lights would go out, he said: "There is an increasing risk."
It came as regulator Ofgem was blasted for taking too long to protect consumers after it emerged the new probe could take 18 months.
Critics accused loaded Mr Laidlaw of scaremongering by criticising the investigation, which could lead to cheaper energy bills for hard-up customers, but lower profits for the suppliers. MP John Robertson, who sits on the Energy Select Committee, fumed: "It's blackmail. But if he thinks he can hold a gun to the heads of customers, he has picked the wrong people."
Business Secretary Vince Cable waded into the row by branding Mr Laidlaw's comments "overdramatic". And Energy Secretary Ed Davey said: "He is absolutely, totally wrong, I can prove it.
"We have 14 contracts for power generation [in the pipeline] over the next 15 years. What we are seeing in Britain is a big investment in energy."
Mr Laidlaw had claimed Ofgem's review could hit investment, just when the UK was facing an energy crunch with a number of polluting power stations due to shut. He told Today: "If this competition market review is going to determine whether we should [divest], obviously our enthusiasm for investing in that space is going to be much less."
He added that the review could set the building of new gas-fired stations back from four years to six. Mr Laidlaw's comments came as Centrica revealed he had bagged a near £2.2million pay and perks package last year, including a £950,000 salary, although he gave an £851,000 bonus to charity.
Meanwhile, figures revealed millions of families were struggling to keep the power on.
Jenny Saunders, chief executive of charity National Energy Action, said: "4.5 million UK households are in fuel poverty - on low incomes and with unaffordable energy bills."
It followed revelations in the UK Fuel Poverty Monitor that VAT from bills could be used to bring all UK housing occupied by lowincome families up to the standard of a new home.
The row between Mr Laidlaw and Labour's Mr Robertson erupted after energy regulator Ofgem referred the industry to the new Competition and Markets Authority for a full investigation.
The move, expected to cost millions of pounds, was triggered by a slump in customer confidence in energy companies, a 24% surge in prices since 2009 and a big jump in suppliers' profits, from £233million in 2009 to £1.1billion in 2012.
Ofgem said there was no proof the 372% surge in profits was due to suppliers being more efficient and cutting their costs and questioned the industry's argument that a 5% profit margin was "fair".
The watchdog also highlighted the cosy relationship between the Big Six suppliers - British Gas, SSE, npower, EDF Energy, ScottishPower and E.ON - which control 95% of the domestic energy market.
British Gas still has a 40% share of the gas industry more than 20 years after privatisation.
Ofgem said its investigations found no evidence of any "explicit collusion" between the suppliers.
But in a damning assessment it said: "There is evidence of possible tacit co-ordination reflected in the timing and size of price announcements and new evidence that prices rise faster when costs rise than they reduce when costs fall.
"Although tacit co-ordination is not a breach of competition law, it reduces competition and worsens outcomes for consumers."
The report also slammed suppliers for charging loyal customers more than new households they wanted to sign up. Ofgem chief Dermot Nolan said firms "haven't treated consumers well enough". He added: "If competition was working effectively it should be pushing profit margins down."
But Ofgem came under fire itself for taking until now to refer the market to the competition authorities. Stephen Fitzpatrick, founder and managing director of small supplier Ovo Energy, said: "It is a shocking indictment of Ofgem's performance over the past 15 years. We have heard time and time again that the market is not working in the interests of most customers and yet the regulator has done almost nothing to bring the Big Six to task.
"It is likely we will see a much more dramatic shake-up of the sector now and that can only be good news for energy customers and the industry as a whole. However this is going to take time and we won't see the benefit for at least two years.
"And in the meantime the Big Six are still charging the most they can get away with." Will Straw, of think tank the IPPR, added: "Our research shows that there is no justifiable reason for the profit margins of 5% which energy companies enjoy. Meanwhile, the Big Six have been guilty of overcharging their loyal customers. It is indicative of the problem that every region in the country still has a monopoly supplier of electricity."
The new competition inquiry could lead to energy giants, which have both power generation and energy supply businesses, being broken up.
Investment bank Morgan Stanley warned the probe would "likely stop almost all generation investments" by the Big Six, adding fuel to Mr Laidlaw's threats of a blackout reminiscent of those in the 1970s. But many energy firms backed the probe, claiming it would clear the air.
On Wednesday, SSE announced it was freezing its prices for two years - a boost to Labour's vow to do the same with all gas and electricity bills until 2017 if the party wins the general election.
Shadow Energy Secretary Caroline Flint said: "SSE showed that a price freeze is possible. Today's confirmation that the energy market is broken shows that it's needed for all customers."
graham.hiscott@mirror.co.uk
VOICE OF THE MIRROR: PAGE 8
THE FATCAT
SAM Laidlaw had a privileged background as the son of an ex-BP chairman.
Educated at Eton, he went on to read law at Cambridge. But despite qualifying as a solicitor, he decided to go into business instead.
He has worked in the energy industry for more than 30 years and became the chief executive of Centrica in 2006.
The 58-year-old dad of four earned a basic £950,000 last year, but gave his £851,000 bonus to charity after criticism over soaring prices.
He has a posh home in Chelsea, a country mansion and is sitting on more than £6million worth of Centrica shares.
If he thinks he can hold a gun to the heads of customers, he has picked the wrong people FURIOUS MP JOHN ROBERTSON on mr laidlaw's threats
]]></text></news-item>