<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-XC61-DXKH-N0KS"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Africa Oil Provides Operational Update and Year-End Results</title><source>News Bites Canadian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[[News Story] VANCOUVER, BRITISH COLUMBIA--(March 27, 2014) - Africa Oil Corp. (TSX VENTURE:AOI)(OMX:AOI) ("Africa Oil" or the "Company") is pleased to provide year-end financial results and an update on its operations in Kenya and Ethiopia.
Seven rigs are currently active on the Company's blocks including four rigs on Blocks 13T and 10BB in the Tertiary Lokichar Basin in Western Kenya, one rig on Block 9 in the Cretaceous Anza rift in Northern Kenya, one rig in the South Omo Block in the Tertiary basin in Southern Ethiopia and one rig in Block 8 in the Jurassic/Triassic basin in the Somali region of Ethiopia.
In the Lokichar Basin, two rigs are drilling exploration/appraisal wells and two rigs are conducting testing operations. Africa Oil Kenya BV holds a 50% working interest in these blocks along with partner Tullow Oil plc who holds the remaining interest and is operator.
The Weatherford 804 rig has completed drilling operations on the Emong prospect. The well was located approximately four kilometres northwest of the Ngamia-1 field discovery and was drilled to a total depth of 1,394 metres. It encountered oil and gas shows while drilling, however the Auwerwer sandstones that are the primary reservoirs in the Ngamia field were thin and poorly developed in Emong-1 and the well was plugged and abandoned. It is believed that the reservoir was poorly developed due to its proximity to the basin bounding fault and its location within what appears to be a local isolated slumped fault margin. The results are not expected to impact the thickness and quality of reservoir throughout the main Ngamia field area. This rig will now move to the Ekunyuk prospect on the eastern flank play which is on trend with recent discoveries at Etuko and Ewoi.
The Sakson PR-5 rig is continuing drilling operations on the Twiga-2 updip appraisal well and is expected to be completed in mid-April. This rig will then move to drill a downdip appraisal of the Amosing discovery, which appears to have high quality reservoir and may be one of the largest discoveries in the basin to date.
Testing operations have been completed on the Ekales-1 well using the SMP-5 rig and have confirmed this significant discovery. Two DST's were completed and flowed a combined rate of over 1,000 barrels of oil per day from a combined 41 metre net pay interval. The upper zone had a very high productivity index of 4.3 stb/d/psi. This rig will next test the Agete discovery.
The Etuko-2 well was drilled by the PR Marriott 46 rig as an exploration well to test the upper Auwerwer sands overlying the previously announced Etuko discovery. The well penetrated a potential significant oil column identified from formation pressure data and oil shows while drilling and in core, with good quality reservoir, but flowed only water on drill stem test. The results are considered inconclusive and analysis is underway to consider further options to evaluate this reservoir. This rig will next drill the Ngamia-2 appraisal well.
The Great Wall 190 rig is drilling ahead on schedule and budget at the Sala prospect in the Cretaceous Anza graben. This well is operated by Africa Oil Kenya B.V. which holds a 50% interest and operatorship with partner Marathon Kenya Limited B.V., a subsidiary of Marathon Oil Corporation holding the remaining 50%. The well is currently at approximately 1500 metres depth and drilling ahead. Results of this well are expected to be announced in the second quarter.
The Shimela prospect in the South Omo Block in Ethiopia is expected to spud before the end of March and will target a new basin in the Tertiary trend, the Chew Bahir Basin. Numerous potential hydrocarbon indicators have been observed on seismic in this basin and if this well is successful in proving up an active petroleum system and thus "opening" the basin, numerous other prospects identified in the basin will be de-risked. This rig will next drill the Gardim prospect in the southern portion of the basin. Both wells are basin bounding fault prospects similar to the Ngamia/Amosing/Twiga discoveries in the Lokichar basin.
The El Kuran-3 well, in the Somali region of Ethiopia, has reached a total depth of 3,528 metres and is currently undergoing logging and evaluation prior to taking a decision on the way forward on the well. There have been numerous oil and gas shows in the well which is a follow up to a discovery made by Tenneco in the 1970's. There appears to be a significant amount of oil and gas in several intervals and the primary issues are the quality of the reservoir and potential commerciality given the remote location.
Keith Hill, President and CEO of Africa Oil, commented, "We are very pleased that all wells in the Lokichar Basin continue to find hydrocarbons indicating a very rich prolific source rock. We continue to gather key reservoir data through drilling and testing, with particular emphasis on understanding the distribution of the most productive reservoirs in the basin. This understanding should be enhanced with the addition of the 3D seismic survey which should allow us to develop a comprehensive reservoir model which will be essential for moving the Lokichar basin into development. We are on track to drill six very exciting potential basin-opening wells in 2014 including wildcat wells in the Chew Bahir, West Turkana, and South Kerio Basins, and along the eastern flank of the Anza Basin in addition to at least three additional exploration targets in the Lokichar Basin."
The Company is also actively pursuing pre-development studies in the Block 10BB/13T area including commencement of the front end engineering design (FEED) and environmental and social impact assessment (ESIA) studies for the pipeline, export terminal and field facilities. It is the goal of the partnership to conclude these studies and achieve project sanction by the end of 2015/early 2016.
http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Canada/Stock/News/495998.html
Source: TMX Group
Recent TradingAfrica Oil (AOI.TSXV) MCap is CAD2.3 billion (US$2.1 billion) at the last price of CAD7.50.
Currency Conversion: Canadian dollar CAD1= US$0.9046 [or US$1= CAD1.11]; Against the US$ the CAD advanced (or 1.4%) for the day; rose 0.6% for the week; rose 0.6% for the month; dropped 6.9% in the past year. CAD1 = 100c.
ISIN: CA00829Q1019
V:AOI; CVE:AOI; CN:AOI;
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>