<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-3351-JCM0-62FP"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Sugarloaf spill prompts park improvement plan</title><source>ABC Regional News (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The mining company behind a major subsidence incident and a botched clean up job in the Sugarloaf Conservation area near Newcastle has agreed to pay $100,000 for park improvements.
The New South Wales government has released its inter-agency investigation report into the damaging incidents, which caused major land slips in the park and left a 250 metre long cement grout spill down a creek bed.
Planning Minister Brad Hazzard yesterday told parliament the company responsible for the grout spill, Orica is being prosecuted.
"The Environment Protection Authority and the Office of Environment and Heritage commenced proceedings in the Land and Environment court last Friday," he said.
"This prosecution sends a very clear message that the New South Wales Government will prosecute on behalf of the community where we believe any mining company or any company associated with a mining company has broken the law, whether it does it intentionally or not."
"While coal mining is vital to our state's economy, the New South Wales government sets the rules for the good of the community and the environment and those rules must be followed."
The report reveals the government considered prosecuting mining giant Glencore, but instead opted to seek compensation for the damage.
Glencore has agreed to provide $100,000 in park improvements, which could include installation of park signage, pest management or improving walking tracks.
It has also covered the cost of remediation works in Sugarloaf and has significantly scaled back its mining activities.
Independent Lake Macquarie MP Greg Piper welcomed the government's decision to release the report publicly, but he is not completely satisfied with its findings.
Mr Piper says the report has skirted the issue of why government agencies approved mining in the area against expert advice and failed to properly inform the public about the damage.
"And I think these are questions people would have been expecting a rather forensic investigation and report should have dealt with," he said.
"They just seem to be missing.
"Certainly there doesn't seem to be any ongoing or recommendation into how such an issue or incident would be handled into the future.
"So I want to look further at that and I will be following up many of these questions with the relevant Minister."
The report concludes that government agencies should have advised the mining company to issue a public statement about the subsidence and the later grouting spills.
It states that the responsibility to publicly report such incidents rests with the mining company, but if it refuses to comply, it would then be up to government agencies to ensure the public is notified.
]]></text></news-item>