<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-FWY1-DY9P-N1JC"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Energy's Big Six facing break-up in new probe</title><source>The Western Mail</source><author>Darren Devine</author><text><![CDATA[AN ENERGY market probe could see Britain's Big Six firms broken up amid concerns over "tacit" price co-ordination.
Regulator Ofgem said soaring bills highlighted the need for an investigation by the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) on whether the Big Six are making excess profits - after they quadrupled to more than £1bn in three years.
But British Gas owner Centrica warned the two-year inquiry could create uncertainty and threaten billions of investment needed in new infrastructure to keep the lights on.
Older people's charity Age Cymru pointed to a 50% increase in preventable, cold-related deaths in 2012/13 and said many would welcome the inquiry.
Spokesman Iwan Rhys Roberts said: "The winter of 2012/2013 was the winter that older people in Wales were more likely to have to cut back on their heating and eating than those anywhere else in the UK. The fact that older people are risking their health because they are afraid to turn up their heat is clear evidence we are failing them."
Families in Wales face the largest fuel bills in the UK. In 2011 the Department of Energy and Climate Change (DECC) found Cardiff's energy customers pay most.
Around 386,000 households in Wales (about 30%) are estimated to be living in fuel poverty - meaning they spend more than 10% of their income on heating.
Concerns have centred round the big six effectively selling energy to themselves as they not only sell it to households, but also produce it.
On Wednesday, watchdog Consumer Futures questioned whether the market's "very structure" fails consumers. Critics will be hoping the "vertically integrated" firms selling to themselves will be broken up.
Bruce Davis, a marketing director with renewable energy investors Abundance Generation, has called this self-supply a "secret" and "murky world", with behind-closed-doors trading desks and prices charged by generation arms to supply arms left unpublished.
He said: "It's about 10% of the market that has published data and unfortunately that's what the regulator uses to say whether wholesale prices reflect retail prices."
The Big Six - Centrica, SSE, E.ON, npower, RWE and EDF - control 95% of the UK energy market.
They also own around 70% of generating capacity - though only Centrica has significant gas production capability as part of its UK group.
It also has nearly 40% of the gas retail market, through British Gas, leaving it vulnerable to action to break up dominant players.
Retail profits increased from £233m in 2009 to £1.1bn in 2012, Ofgem said. It found prices had risen by 24% over the period, well ahead of the rate of inflation at 13.8%.
Plaid Cymru's Shadow Energy Minister Llyr Gruffydd, who maintains his party would create a publicly-owned not-for-profit energy firm for Wales to compete with the Big Six, said: "Energy prices have spiralled out of control over recent years, and there is little help for customers struggling to pay the inflated prices. Something needs to be done to rebalance the energy market in favour of the customers."
Ofgem said a probe would "clear the air" amid concerns that switching between suppliers had fallen with claims those who never switch, many of them vulnerable customers, are being ripped off.
It also said it found evidence of "possible tacit co-ordination" between companies on the timing and size of price announcements, but stopped short of accusing them of explicitly colluding in an illegal cartel.
Umbrella body Energy UK says the industry is "increasingly competitive" with three-and-a-half million households switching suppliers last year and it has "nothing to hide".
Analysis: Page 30 » EXECS SHARE £2M IN BONUSES Executive pay at British Gas parent Centrica was slashed by two-thirds last year, but bosses were still awarded annual bonuses worth more than £2m despite falling profits and a customer exodus.
The group's annual report showed pay for the top five executives dropped to £6.7m from £18.6m in 2012 as long-term share bonuses awarded three years ago were wiped out due to disappointing results and a plunging share price.
Annual bonuses worth £2.3m were still awarded to the top bosses, including £851,000 for chief executive Sam Laidlaw - although he has already pledged to donate the payout to charity in an effort to calm public anger over rising energy bills.
Executives were also awarded £5.3m of bonus shares under a long-term incentive scheme that could see Mr Laidlaw pick up a potential 200% of his salary - or £1.9m - in April 2016 if performance and share price targets are met.
]]></text></news-item>