<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-VV11-JCB2-W0VK"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>NPA revokes bribery charges for Malema's business associates</title><source>Business Day (South Africa)</source><author>SETUMO STONE</author><text><![CDATA[NPA revokes bribery charges for Malema's business associates
Political Correspondent
THE National Prosecuting Authority (NPA) has discharged the case against alleged business associates of Economic Freedom Fighters (EFF) leader Julius Malema, its spokesman Nathi Mncube said yesterday, but Mr Malema is not off the hook yet.
The NPA had re-evaluated evidence and decided not to separate the cases, Mr Mncube said.
The connection between Julius Malema and the case that was & discharged& by the Mokopane regional court yesterday was that the three co-accused in the case were alleged to have paid a bribe to gain a tender for On-Point Engineering, a company with links to Mr Malema.
His Ratanang Family Trust had shares in On-Point Engineering.
A discharge verdict meant that the Mokopane three could not be charged again.
Mr Malema last year made representations to the NPA, seeking to have the charges against him dropped. A decision on the matter was still pending.
If the NPA declined Mr Malema's plea, then the trial was expected to start in September.
Mr Mncube told Business Day yesterday that the Mokopane three - Selby Manthatha, his wife Helen Moreroa and his brother Makgetsi Manthatha - were initially arrested with Mr Malema and two others.
But the prosecution, after evaluating the evidence, decided to separate the cases of Mr Malema, Lesiba Gwangwa and Kagiso Dichabe from the corruption charges of the Mokopane three.
Mr Malema and company are facing charges of racketeering, money laundering and fraud.
Mr Mncube also said the party that was alleged to have received the bribe, On-Point Engineering, was also not charged in the same case as the Mokopane three.
This decision seemed to have hints of the Schabir Shaik corruption trial in 2005, where President Jacob Zuma was alleged to have received a bribe from Mr Shaik, but the two were charged separately.
The arrangement, after Mr Shaik was convicted, prompted speculation in political circles that the NPA's motive was to find Mr Zuma guilty of corruption in absentia.
Mr Mncube said it would have amounted to & malicious prosecution& to have Mr Malema and company tried together with the Mokopane three, which explained why the cases were separated.
Mr Malema's EFF would for the first time this year contest the general elections, after being formed last year. However, a final sequestration order in May, a few days after the elections, may prevent Mr Malema from getting a seat in Parliament because of a pending tax bill.
Mr Malema has claimed criminal charges against him were intended to block his political career. He was Mr Zuma's close ally until the fallout between the two saw him expelled from the African National Congress in 2012 and removed as president of its youth wing.
stones@bdfm.co.za
IN THE HOT SEAT: The NPA has discharged the case against alleged business associates of EFF leader Julius Malema. Picture: SUNDAY TIMES
]]></text></news-item>