<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-3PH1-JD6S-R4S0"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>natural gas; Proposed gas site questioned</title><source>The Evening Times (Little Falls, New York)</source><author>Rob Juteau Times Staff Writer</author><text><![CDATA[DOLGEVILLE - Boston-based Xpress Natural Gas' proposed compressed natural gas filling site continues to raise questions in the town of Manheim and beyond.
"I have not been pleased with the way I have witnessed the town representatives being led to expedite this dangerous direction for our region from which there is no return," St. Johnsville resident Lia Marrero said during Tuesday evening's town council meeting. "There are many false rumors. New York state provides us with the ability to say no to development that is counter to the comprehensive plan of a community, but if we make the mistake of saying yes we will not be able to regulate this dangerous industry."
Xpress Natural Gas and landowners Leon and Rebecca Newswanger have asked the town's Planning Board to approve a subdivision of property at 5366 state Route 167.
If approved, a 6.7-acre parcel would be created from the Newswanger's existing 113-acre parcel of farmland to house a filling site that will draw from the Iroquois Pipeline.
Natural gas pulled from the pipeline will be dried, compressed, cooled and delivered to customers via a company tractor-trailer, according to the proposal before the planning board. The proposal also includes the construction of a 2,000-square-foot facility surrounded by pine trees that will be operational 24 hours a day, seven days a week.
Xpress Natural Gas expects to hire six full-time employees who will work at the site in shifts and anticipates indirect jobs such as truck drivers will also be created.
"We know better, the question is do we have the spine to reject this wrong direction for our town's, region's and planet's well being," asked Marrero.
Questions posed during Tuesday evening's meeting included why the town's renewed moratorium on hydraulic fracturing and related activities was not filed with the state and who will benefit from the proposed compressed natural gas filling site.
Town Supervisor John Haughton said it is too early to tell how the town will benefit from the project. "We haven't even reached that point in the discussions," he said.
Haughton added the town's Planning Board and Zoning Board of Appeals, which Xpress Natural Gas must deal with if the subdivision is approved, as well as the town council, will do their "due diligence" when it comes to researching the project.
"The planning board and the zoning board has a series of meetings scheduled, all of which will be open to the public," he said. "The company's plans are available for anyone to come in and review. All anyone has to do is make an appointment with the town clerk. The town is being open. Nothing is being hidden or kept from the public."
Haughton said two members each of the town council, planning board and zoning board, as well as Dolgeville Fire Chief Randy Tenant, will travel to Dover, N.H., where Xpress Natural Gas makes equipment for compressed natural gas shipments on April 6 and 7.
"We will also visit a compressed natural gas filling site in Vermont that is similar to the site that is being proposed in Manheim," he said. "We are being as through as we can."
As for the moratorium to prohibit natural gas and petroleum exploration activities, underground storage of natural gas and the disposal of natural gas or petroleum extraction, exploration and production wastes in the town, Haughton said the council unanimously voted to renew it in June 2013 and it was forwarded to David Slottje, executive director and senior attorney at the Community Environmental Defense Council.
"We learned the moratorium was never filed with the Department of State," he said, adding Ken Ayers, the attorney representing the town in the establishment of the filling site, provided the council with a legal opinion that said the moratorium would not apply to the Xpress Natural Gas project because it does not call for exploration activities, underground storage of natural gas or the disposal of natural gas or petroleum wastes.
"The moratorium would not prevent someone from filing an application for a subdivision of land or from filing an application for a special use permit," said Haughton. "That is what has happened here. An application for a subdivision has been filed."
Asked if the town would correct the error and file the moratorium, Haughton said the council would address the issue at a later time. "Right now, the state Department of Environmental Conservation is not issuing permits of any kind for hydraulic fracturing anywhere in the state," he said. "It's not something that is being allowed."
Dolgeville resident Donna DeLucco asked the town to consider the air and noise pollution created by the site and the possibility of spills and explosions, and Bronner Road residents Adam Riddle and Kim Hergert said the thought of having the gas industry setting up in their backyard has them feeling "extremely unsettled."
Having both recently lived in southeastern Ohio and southwestern Pennsylvania, Riddle and Hergert said they have seen with their own eyes the damage the gas industry can do.
"No amount of money can every buy back clean water, air and the sanctity of an untouched area like Central New York," said Hergert. "... We are very concerned with the amount of activity that would be going on around this aging pipeline and how fast this project seems to be moving. We would like to see further impact studies and environmental studies done before the board considers this proposal."
]]></text></news-item>