<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVC-3321-JCBD-Y28T"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>SCRUTINY OF UK'S ENERGY MARKET</title><source>Press Association Mediapoint</source><author>John-Paul Ford Rojas, Press Association City Staff</author><text><![CDATA[The first full-scale competition probe into the energy market could result in a radical shake-up of the industry - but is likely to take two years to produce its final report.
Plans to refer the sector to the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) will subject the workings of the so-called Big Six suppliers to unprecedented levels of scrutiny.
But despite the clamour for action amid soaring bills and company profits, it cannot begin in earnest until after a consultation lasting several weeks has been completed and is not expected to issue a definitive report until after the 2015 general election, when the political landscape is likely to have been transformed.
The probe could result in the breaking up of the major firms with large market shares or force them to split from their ``upstream'' arms producing gas and electricity.
Less drastic measures will also be available to regulators, depending on whether they judge that the market is not operating competitively for consumers, and what action needs to be taken to fix it.
Industry insiders point out that the sector has been scrutinised on numerous occasions over the past 15 years, including an energy supply probe launched in 2008 and a retail market review in 2010 resulting in changes only now coming into effect.
But some including E.ON chief executive Tony Cocker have welcomed the prospect of a CMA investigation to restore public trust.
Others say the lengthy probe will add to uncertainty, threatening to hold up investment in UK power production needed to keep the lights on.
It would represent a major step up in scale from previous regulatory reviews. The CMA, which is taking on responsibilities previously held by the Competition Commission, has sweeping powers including tough measures to impose fines on firms that do not comply.
British Gas, owned by Centrica, looks particularly vulnerable should a break-up of suppliers be on the cards, given its dominant position in gas supply, with 38% of the market share - one which has been highlighted by Energy Secretary Ed Davey.
Recent reforms to energy supply have included new rules designed to make it easier for consumers to compare energy deals with those offered by rivals, and cutting back the number of different types of tariff available.
But political pressure on the sector has intensified in the last few months amid public anger over soaring household bills and fat energy company profits - at a time when real-term wages have been falling.
Labour has pledged to freeze tariffs in 2015 if it wins the general election.
Suppliers have blamed rising costs of buying and delivering wholesale energy as well as so-called ``green levies'' by the Government on bills, designed to pay for energy-saving measures in low-income households.
David Cameron announced in October that levies would be rolled back, resulting in tariff hikes by suppliers being scaled down. But he also signalled a review of competition in the energy markets by regulators including Ofgem.
In February, Mr Davey urged Ofgem in a leaked letter to ``think radically'' as it considered whether to refer the sector for a full CMA probe and raised the prospect of a break-up of suppliers ``if they have been shown to abuse their market power''.
The Liberal Democrat minister also drew attention to British Gas's dominant position in the gas supply market and cited figures showing it generated a profit margin of 11.2% on domestic supply in 2012.
It was far above the margins of around 5% - which include gas and electricity - usually cited by suppliers when they attempt to justify bill increases.
British Gas is one of the Big Six companies that dominate the energy market, along with SSE, E.ON, EDF, npower and Scottish Power.
Some insiders argue that the market is already intensely competitive, with 19 suppliers and 11 switching websites.
Figures from Centrica's annual results last month showed British Gas lost more than 360,000 gas and electricity customer accounts in 2013.
The CMA investigation into the sector will not be able to begin until after a consultation expected to last several weeks and industry insiders expect it will not produce a final report until the middle of 2016.
It will be expected to begin with requests to suppliers for a raft of data, followed by the authority producing an ``issues statement'' on the terms of its investigation.
The process is likely to include calling in industry figures for private oral hearings. Provisional findings should be produced by the middle of 2015 with possible details on the type of remedies needed to improve the market.
These would be fleshed out in the following months followed by a final report which it is expected should be issued two years after the start of the probe.
While radical break-up plans could feature, other solutions might include further measures to improve consumer awareness and choice.
There could also be reform to the relationship between suppliers and their upstream arms that stops short of full splits, which could take the form of a ``legal separation'' of different parts of the company of the sort just announced by SSE - in an apparent attempt to forestall the probe's findings.
A break-up of suppliers to reduce their market share might follow an example of the banking industry, and the spin-off of the revived TSB brand from taxpayer-backed Lloyds Banking Group, which was forced by EU rules on state aid.
But there is no certainty on how this would work in the energy sector, and there is an argument that having large suppliers is an important part of maintaining security of supply as Britain becomes increasingly reliant on imports.
It is pointed out that only these large companies have big enough balance sheets to be able to commit to buying tens of billions of pounds of energy from abroad years in advance.
]]></text></news-item>