<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-FM21-DYJJ-P3N4"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>top workplaces: the winners</title><source>Rochester Democrat and Chronicle (New York)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Aerotek Staffing Agency
Ranking: Sixth, small company category.
Founded: 1983.
Employees: 35 locally, 4,000 overall.
Line of work: Recruiting and staffing.
Revenues: $5.1 billion.
Local: 100 Corporate Woods, Brighton.
Job openings: http://www.aerotek.com/employment-agency/staffing-company.aspx
Local community support: Taken part in such community events as Make A Stride Against Breast Cancer, the Salvation Army's Project Bundle Up, and career fairs at the Veterans Outreach Center and Rochester Rehabilitation through the Al Sigl Center.
Recent events: Recently invited prospective and current clients to an open house in order to showcase office culture as well as the recruitment process.
Of note: Aerotek has more than 200 offices nationwide and has placed more than 100,000 workers with its clients. The staffing firm was named one of the top military-friendly employees in the nation by G.I. Jobs and Military Spouse magazines in 2014.
Benefit Resource Inc.
Ranking: 19th, small employer category.
Founded: 1993.
Employees: 78 locally, 94 overall.
Planned hiring: 10 positions over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Employee benefit plans third-party administration.
Local: 245 Kenneth Drive, Henrietta.
Job openings: benefitresource.com/about-us/career-opportunities/
Employee benefits: Eligible employees receive health insurance, term life insurance, short- and long-term disability, dental coverage, accidental death and dismemberment coverage, paid personal time off, and health savings and flexible spending accounts.
Bonadio & Co. LLP
Ranking: Fourth, midsize employer category.
Founded: 1978.
Employees: 213 locally, 377 overall.
Line of work: Accounting and payroll services, business advising.
Local: 171 Sully's Trail, Perinton, and offices in Batavia and Geneva.
Job openings: bonadio.com/apply-online
Revenues: $54.2 million.
Local community support: The firm has teams that participate in walkathons, corporate challenges and other group fundraising events. Some employees teach at-risk youth through Junior Achievement's "JA in a Day," while others might help to sort/inventory food at local food pantries as part of United Way's Day of Caring.
Of note: The firm closes at noon on Fridays in the summer, and other staff appreciation days off may be given in celebration of a successful year.
Brand Networks Inc.
Ranking: 15th, small employer category.
Founded: 2007.
Employees: 76 locally, 175 overall.
Recent hiring: 30 in the past 12 months.
Line of work: Custom software development and digital advertising.
Local: 61 Commercial St. Suite 200, Rochester.
Job openings: brandnetworksinc.com/who-we-are/#careers
Employee benefits: Full health and dental coverage. Starting employees receive 15 days of paid time off. Also provides kegs of Yuengling beer on tap, foosball and Waffle Wednesdays.
Of note: Rochester office is located in a historic trolley repair station in High Falls. It has an annual company outing to Cape Cod.
Brighton Securities
Ranking: Eighth, small employer category.
Founded: 1969.
Employees: 37 locally, 40 worldwide.
Recent hiring: 15 in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 10 over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Financial planning and 401(k) administration.
Local: 1703 Monroe Ave., Brighton, and offices in Gates and Batavia.
Job openings: brightonsecurities.com/careers/
Employee benefits: Package includes medical and dental insurance covered by a 50 percent firm contribution, 401(k) with a match, and profit sharing. Hourly staff receive "flex time" paid time off that can be used in hourly increments. Advisers receive firm-funded budgets of up to $10,000 to be used on community outreach.
Local community support: Workers can earn additional pay for volunteerism.
Of note: Brighton Securities has had the same name and Monroe Avenue location since its founding in 1969. Two of its client service associates have been with the company for 30 years or more.
Bristol ID Technologies
Ranking: 21st, small employer category.
Founded: 1975.
Employees: 75 locally.
Line of work: Maker of tags, badges and RFID cards.
Local: 1370 Route 15A, Lima, Livingston County.
Job openings: BristolID.com
Employee benefits: Package includes a health savings account with company contribution; a 401(k) with company match; choice of life insurance, critical illness insurance, accident insurance and short-term disability insurance providers; and membership in the Rochester Regional Area Recreation and Employee Services Association. The company also regularly puts on such events as bowling nights, monthly luncheons and the Bristol Bucks Program that rewards workers for such achievements as years of service or particular work outside their job description.
Recent events: During summer, will have local ice cream shop set up in its parking lot, serving employees sundaes at shift's end.
Broadstone Real Estate LLC
Ranking: Seventh, small employer category.
Founded: 2006.
Employees: 52 locally, 55 globally.
Recent hiring: Eight in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 13 in the next 12 months.
Line of work: Commercial and residential real estate investment trust.
Local: 530 Clinton Square, Rochester, plus numerous commercial properties and rental homes across the region.
Job openings: broadstone.com/about/careers/
Employee benefits: Package typically includes performance bonus plan; corporate success profit sharing plan for eligible employees; choice of medical, dental and vision coverage; health savings account with employer contributions; flexible spending account; 401(k) with matching contributions; health and wellness benefits; paid parking; and company-provided beverages and snacks.
Of note: Broadstone manages more than $850 million in properties nationwide. Most Broadstone employees were referrals from other employees. Two of its founders, CEO Amy Tait and her husband, Bob, raise alpacas.
Butler/Till
Ranking: Ninth, small employer category.
Founded: 1992.
Employees: 75 locally, 76 globally.
Line of work: Advertising and marketing.
Revenues: $8.7 million.
Local: 1565 Jefferson Road, Suite 280 in Building 200, Henrietta.
Job openings: butlertill.com/contact/?jobOpenings
Local community support: Through its Charity Committee, Butler/Till has donated $11,000 and 200 hours of time in the past year to organizations including the West Webster Fire Department, Special Olympics, Colon Cancer Alliance, American Cancer Society, United Way, The Strong National Museum of Play and FoodLink.
Of note: Participants in the Employee Stock Ownership Program own 51 percent of Butler/Till's shares.
Clark Patterson Lee
Ranking: 30th, small employer category.
Founded: 1975.
Employees: 90 locally, 227 worldwide.
Line of work: Architecture and engineering.
Revenues: $30 million.
Local: 205 St. Paul St., Suite 500, Rochester.
Job openings: clarkpattersonlee.com/people/join-our-team.aspx
Local community support: Participated in such events as the American Heart Association Heart Walk, Making Strides Against Breast Cancer, Can-Struction, and Chase Corporate Challenge.
Of note: An intern was selected as 2013 American Institute of Architects New York State Intern-Associate of the Year.
CooperVision Inc.
Ranking: Fourth, large employer category.
Founded: 1980.
Employees: 1,091 locally, 7,000 worldwide.
Recent hiring: 90 in the past 12 months.
Line of work: Soft contact lens manufacturing.
Revenues: $1.27 billion.
Local: Operations in Scottsville, Henrietta and Perinton.
Job openings: coopervision.com.my/about-us/careers
Employee benefits: Include a 401(k) with company match, a pension plan, medical plans with health savings accounts, flexible savings accounts, vision insurance with a contact lens discount, life insurance, and tuition assistance, as well as an employee wellness program.
Local community support: A corporate sponsor of the American Heart Association Heart Walk, it also is sponsoring the association's Lifestyle Change Award.
Recent events: In 2013, CooperVision's wellness program saw its Rochester-area workforce lose 4,344 pounds and an average total body fat reduction of 5.8 percent.
Dawnbreaker Inc.
Ranking: 28th, small employer category.
Founded: 1989.
Employees: 51 locally, 70 overall.
Line of work: Strategic planning, market research, training, and marketing communication services to advance national technology innovation initiatives of government agencies and advanced technology firms.
Revenues: $7.5 million.
Locall: 3161 Union St., Chili.
Job openings: dawnbreaker.com/about/employment.php
Local community support: Supports Toys for Tots, Rochester Business Alliance.
Of note: A woman-owned business.
Dick Ide Family of Dealerships
Ranking: Second, midsize employer category.
Founded: 1970.
Employees: 129 locally, 130 overall.
Recent hiring: Added roughly 50 jobs in the past 18 months.
Line of work: Auto dealerships.
Local: Three dealerships in Penfield and East Rochester.
Job openings: dickidehonda.com/jobopp_listing.asp
Local community support: Many employees have participated in Tour de Cure in the past several years.
Recent events: A year-end celebration for employees, which took place in the Honda building, featured food and prizes.
Of note: The Ide family is involved in day-to-day operations: Mitch Ide is the company president, Rich Ide is vice president, Anne Ide is chief financial officer, and Stephanie Ide works in marketing and accounting.
Dorschel Automotive Group
Ranking: Fifth, large employer category.
Founded: 1952.
Employees: 487 locally, 491 overall.
Recent hiring: 15 added in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 15 over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Auto dealerships.
Revenues: $292.8 million.
Local: Eight new vehicle franchise locations in Henrietta, plus two Upstate Auto Credit dealerships in Henrietta and Rochester.
Job openings: dorschel.com/section/secondary/careers/
Employee benefits: Comprehensive medical, dental and vision plans; 401(k); employee recognition programs, tuition reimbursement; discount on parts, services and vehicle purchases.
Of note: Dorschel is a third-generation, family owned, multi-franchise automotive dealership. Some employees have been with it for more than 30 years.
East House
Ranking: Seventh, midsize employer category.
Founded: 1966.
Employees: 134 locally, 143 overall.
Line of work: Private nonprofit rehabilitation agency providing mental health and substance abuse services.
Revenues: $10 million.
Local: Nine facilities locally.
Job openings: easthouse.org/careers/
Employee benefits: Package includes medical and dental coverage, 401(k), paid time off, medical spending and dependent care reimbursement accounts, life insurance, short-term and long-term disability, and an employee assistance program.
Recent events: Puts on its Hope & Recovery Luncheon each September. The 2013 event, with guest speaker Patrick Kennedy, raised more than $54,000 with 425 guests in attendance.
eHealth Technologies
Ranking: 25th, small employer category.
Founded: 2007.
Employees: 93 locally, 102 overall.
Planned hiring: 24 over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Electronic medical records technology.
Local: 250 Thruway Park Drive, Henrietta.
Job openings: ehealthtechnologies.com/about-us/careers
Employee benefits: Offers medical and dental coverage, 401(k) options, life insurance, a casual dress code for most employees, and an on-campus health facility.
Local community support: Frequently runs donation drives for local causes. This past holiday season the company collected and donated items to Lollypop Farm, Alternatives for Battered Women, Cure for Childhood Cancer, and Job Path. Supports Cancermission2020 and a variety of other local and regional charities.
Of note: Recently built its company headquarters in Henrietta designed to house a rapidly growing workforce.
Federated Clover Investment Advisors
Ranking: Fourth, small employer category.
Founded: 1984.
Employees: 40 locally, 1,432 overall.
Line of work: Investment management.
Local: 400 Meridian Center, Suite 200, Brighton.
Job openings: clovercap.com/public/OurFirm/EmploymentOpportunities.aspx
Local community support: Supports such organizations as SeniorsFirst, Rochester Museum & Science Center, Rotary Club and Camp Good Days & Special Times.
Of note: Federated Clover gets its name from its parent company (Federated Investors) and the street where it was originally located (Clover Street in Pittsford).
Frontier Abstract and Research Services Inc.
Ranking: 10th, small employer category.
Founded: 1999.
Employees: 43 locally, 49 overall.
Recent hiring: Nine over the past 12 months.
Line of work: Property title searches and insurance.
Local: 30 W. Broad St. Suite 100, Rochester.
Job openings: frontierabstract.com/career.aspx
Employee benefits: Package includes group medical and dental plans, 401(k) plan with a company match, paid time off, summer appreciation time off, parking cost assistance and eight paid company holidays annually.
Local community support: All full-time employees are given a minimum of eight hours of paid time off annually for use for volunteer work in the community.
Of note: Marking its 15-year anniversary this year with some events, such as its annual St. Patrick's Day celebration for employees and clients with a performance by a local children's dance troupe.
Hammer Packaging
Ranking: Second, large employer category.
Founded: 1912.
Employees: 421 locally, 428 overall.
Line of work: Packaging printing.
Revenues: $106 million.
Local: 200 Lucius Gordon Drive, Henrietta; and 234 Wallace Way, Building 9, Rochester Technology Park, Gates.
Job openings: hammerpackaging.com/about-us/employment
Employee benefits: Hammer Packaging offers medical and dental benefits along with profit sharing, a 401(k) and paid time off. Employees making efficiency or performance suggestions can earn "Hammer Bucks" that can be redeemed for paid time off or company apparel.
Local community support: Backs numerous programs, including the National Center for Missing and Exploited Children, Junior Achievement, and Camp Good Days and Special Times. CEO James E. Hammer is a member of various boards for local businesses and community programs and recently stepped down from the board at Mary Cariola Children's Center after 20 years of service.
Of note: Privately held through five generations.
Hilton Central School District
Ranking: Third, large employer category.
Founded: 1949.
Employees: 754 locally.
Recent hiring: 70 in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 70 over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Pre-K through grade 12 public education school system.
Revenues: Budget of $72.3 million.
Local: 225 West Ave., Hilton, plus a high school, a middle school and three elementary school buildings.
Job openings: secure.myschooljobs.org/hilton/
Local community support: Employees have contributed time and funds to such community events as Books for Len - which has helped raise about $20,000 in the past 13 years for Northwood Elementary School - and Cadet Cupboard, a food pantry for Hilton students.
Recent events: Staff members are recognized through retiree celebrations, teacher of the year awards and more.
Of note: The Health and Wellness Committee organizes involvement in such events as Eat Well, Live Well; Corporate Challenge; and the Ride for Missing Children.
iCardiac Technologies
Ranking: Second in small employer category.
Founded: 2006.
Employees: 49 locally, 70 overall.
Line of work: Cardiac safety assessment for pharmaceutical research.
Local: 150 Allens Creek Road, Brighton.
Job openings: icardiac.com
Employee benefits: Along with health and dental coverage, life insurance and a matching 401(k), iCardiac offers an employee stock option plan and such paid days off as birthdays, charitable work days, and "summer fun hours" of half days on Friday during the summer.
Local community support: In 2013, recognized as a Rising Star by the United Way for its charitable giving efforts. During the 2013 holiday season, the company "adopted" a family designated by Alternatives for Battered Women and provided Christmas gifts to the children.
Recent events: Regularly puts on company-wide social events such as a clam bake, bowling lunches, its own softball team, and Red Wings and Amerks nights.
Of note: Twice chosen for the Science Coalition 100, a national list highlighting the best success stories of companies that have commercialized university research.
Insero & Co.
Ranking: Third, small employer category.
Founded: 1973.
Employees: 71 locally, 79 overall.
Recent hiring: Nine in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 12 over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Accounting and business advising.
Local: 2 State St. Suite 300, Rochester.
Job openings: inserocpa.com/career/index.html
Employee benefits: Provides three to five weeks of paid time off based on level, a summer hours program of 48 hours worth of extra time off, a 401(k) with employer match, profit sharing plan, CPA exam reimbursement and CPA bonus, tuition reimbursement, staff and management bonuses, a travel bonus program, and employer-provided parking. If an employee opts out of company-provided medical insurance, Insero provides $4,000 in opt-out dollars.
Recent events: Frequent sponsor of employee events such as its formal holiday party, rappelling off a 21-story building, and two indoor volleyball teams. Recently held a Star Wars-themed lunch where employees dressed up as characters from the films and made a video called "Quest for the Highest Standard of Client Service."
Of note: In 2012 and 2013, Insero & Co. made the "Best Accounting Firms to Work For" list compiled by Accounting Today and WorkplaceDynamics.
KJT Group Inc.
Ranking: 17th, small employer category.
Founded: 2007.
Employees: 32 locally, 40 overall.
Recent hiring: 12 over the past 12 months.
Line of work: Life sciences industry market research and consulting.
Revenues: $7.2 million.
Local: 6 East St., Honeoye Falls.
Job openings: kjtgroup.com/careers/current-seeking-positions/
Employee benefits: Offerings include bonus vacation time that has, in the past, included a week off for the July Fourth holiday. Set up an employee stock ownership plan in 2013, giving each employee a stake in the business.
Local community support: Involved with Meals on Wheels, supports the local Boy Scouts in their annual popcorn sale and participates annually in the Light the Night Walk and SBC Cares Thanksgiving Appeal.
Recent events: Regularly holds staff potluck lunches, company-sponsored lunches and happy hours. During December, the staff enjoyed a holiday party featuring a catered meal, as well as a potluck lunch, which included a gift exchange. KJT Group's annual summer picnic for employees and their families is a full-day, off-site event.
LaBella Associates D.P.C.
Ranking: Sixth, midsize employer category.
Founded: 1978.
Employees: 190 locally, 255 overall.
Recent hiring: 40 over the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 25 planned over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Architecture, engineering and planning.
Revenues: $31 million.
Local: 300 State St. Suite 201, Rochester.
Job openings: labellapc.com/LaBella/Careers
Employee benefits: Package includes tuition reimbursement, medical and dental coverage, 401(k) retirement plan, paid holidays and leave time, a wellness program and license fees and certifications.
Local community support: LaBella in the Community is a committee that promotes and provides community service activities for employees and clients. Takes part in Adopt A Highway with a mile stretch of Interstate 490 near Bushnell's Basin.
Recent events: Fiscal 2013 marked the opening of LaBella's first international office, in Madrid.
Of note: Has doubled in size over the past five years.
Lakeland Equipment
Ranking: 27th, small employer category.
Founded: 1983.
Employees: 45 locally, 150 overall.
Recent hiring: Four in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: Four over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Agricultural and lawn and garden equipment retailer.
Revenues: $72 million.
Local: Six locations across the Rochester region.
Job openings: lakelandequipment.com/employment-opportunities
Employee benefits: Package includes health, dental, vision, life insurance, 401(k) with company matching offered after a year of employment, and company-provided uniforms.
Of note: Started when two former John Deere employees, Marty Phillippe and Gene Roling, purchased Dickens Bros., an active John Deere dealership. In order to provide parts, service and sales to a larger region a customer service representative was hired. The "VanMan" operation prompted Deere to encourage similar operations across the nation.
Manning Squires Hennig Co. Inc.
Ranking: Fifth, midsize employer category.
Founded: 1958.
Employees: 130 locally.
Recent hiring: 10 in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 10 over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Construction general contractor.
Revenues: $70 million.
Local: 8426 Seven Springs Road, Batavia, Genesee County; and 936 E. Main St., Rochester.
Job openings: mshco.com
Recent events: Had two employees receive Lifetime Achievement Awards from the Rochester Builders Exchange.
Of note: More than half of Manning Squires' employees have been with the company more than 10 years - and several have been with it more than 20 years.
Martino Flynn LLC
Ranking: 20th, small employer category.
Founded: 1997.
Employees: 51 locally.
Recent hiring: 16 in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: Three over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Marketing and communications.
Revenues: $15 million.
Local: 175 Sully's Trail, Suite 100, Perinton.
Job openings: martinoflynn.com/about/careers/
Local community support: Main sponsor of Jerry Flynn Golf Classic to support Gilda's Club. Also supports the Breast Cancer Coalition of Rochester, Literacy Volunteers of Rochester, and Junior Achievement.
Of note: Won a Rochester Area Business Ethics Foundation Ethie
Award in 2013.
Massage Envy Spas of Rochester
Ranking: 26th, small employer category.
Founded: 2010.
Employees: 105 locally.
Recent hiring: 30 in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 40 over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Massage and spa services chain.
Local: Locations in Pittsford, Greece, Webster and Victor.
Job openings: massageenvycareers.com/
Employee benefits: Along with traditional health, dental and vision coverage, there is an employee discount at the spas; ability to enroll in such additional coverage as life insurance, hospital indemnity, accident insurance, cancer protection and supplemental short term disability. Eligible employees receive paid time off and holiday pay. Offers a continuing education reimbursement benefit for annual licensing re-certification and a 401(k) with employer contribution.
Local community support: National sponsor of the Arthritis Foundation's Arthritis Walk events throughout the country and hosts "Healing Hands for Arthritis," a one-day, in-clinic nationwide event.
Of note: The company was recently ranked 88th in Franchise Times magazine's Top 200, 81st in Entrepreneur magazine's 2013 Franchise 500 and 29th in its Fastest Growing Franchise rankings.
MassMutual Financial Group
Ranking: 14th, small employer category.
Founded: 1851.
Employees: 60 locally, 10,000 overall.
Recent hiring: 14 in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 15 over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Financial services.
Local: Financial Architects, 700 Bausch & Lomb Place, Rochester.
Job openings: massmutual.com/careers
Local community support: Ninety-five percent of people who work for Financial Architects in some capacity volunteer regularly with local community groups.
Mirror Show Management
Ranking: 22nd, small employer category.
Founded: 1993.
Employees: 56 locally.
Recent hiring: 17 in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: Six over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Exhibit and display design.
Revenues: $21 million.
Local: 855 Hard Road, Webster.
Job openings: mirrorshowmanagement.com/contact-us/careers/
Employee benefits: Has an on-site fitness center. Is 49 percent owned by employees through an employee stock ownership plan.
Local community support: Has a "Give Great" program to encourage employee contributions. Every employee receives a United Way Gathering to Give gift card for their birthday that they can redeem on the Gathering to Give website.
Recent events: In 2013, it marked its 20th anniversary with a variety of events including a celebration where the first ESOP stock certificates were handed to employees.
Monroe Tractor
Ranking: 23rd, small employer category.
Founded: 1951.
Employees: 85 locally, 196 overall.
Recent hiring: Five in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: Five over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Agricultural and construction retail, rental and service.
Local: Headquartered at 1001 Lehigh Station Road in Henrietta, with 11 upstate locations including Batavia and Canandaigua.
Job openings: monroetractor.com/CompanyInfo/career-opportunities.aspx
Employee benefits: Offerings include health, dental and life insurance, disability, 401(k) with match and an employee stock ownership plan.
Local community support: For a number of years has provided construction equipment to Habitat for Humanity in the building of their homes, and donated equipment to build community baseball parks and playgrounds. Also offers scholarships to college students who pursue careers in agriculture or construction.
Optimax Systems Inc.
Ranking: Ninth, midsize employer category.
Founded: 1991.
Employees: 205 locally.
Recent hiring: 30 in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 20 over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Precision optics manufacturing.
Revenues: $20 million.
Local: 6367 Dean Parkway, Ontario, Wayne County.
Job openings: optimaxsi.com/careers/
Employee benefits: Optimax provides up to 100 percent tuition assistance, membership to the Optimax Beach Club (that being its CEO's personal condo), a profit-sharing plan that distributes 25 percent of company profits to employees on a monthly basis, and a free tie-dyed T-shirt, which is the corporate uniform.
Local community support: Offers internships, mentoring donations and volunteer time at local higher educational institutions. President Mike Mandina is a founding member and president of the workforce development group Finger Lakes Advanced Manufacturers' Enterprise.
Of note: Placed in the top 20 of the 2010 "Top Small Company Workplaces Competition" put on by Winning Workplaces and Inc.
Paris-Kirwan Associates Inc.
Ranking: 18th, small employer category.
Founded: 1926.
Employees: 38 locally, 41 overall.
Recent hiring: Three in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: Two over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Independent insurance agency.
Revenues: $5.5 million.
Local: 1040 University Ave., Rochester.
Job openings: www.paris-kirwan.com
Employee benefits: Paid individual health insurance policy, group term life, short and long term disability and paid vacation.
Recent events: A "pig out day" where all employees bring in their favorite foods and eat all day.
Partners + Napier Inc.
Ranking: 13th, small employers category.
Founded: 2004.
Employees: 125 locally, 135 overall.
Line of work: Advertising, marketing and brand strategy.
Revenues: $24 million.
Local: 192 Mill St., Suite 600, Rochester.
Job openings: partnersandnapier.com/contact
Employee benefits: Employees get birthday off paid. Partners + Napier picks up the tab for the weekly "Beer Friday" and hosts regular ice cream socials and agency breakfasts.
Local community support: Pro bono support for businesses and causes including The Little Theatre, WallTherapy and the High Falls Film Festival. Supports organizations including Catholic Family Charities and Open Door Mission.
Regional International Corp.
Ranking: 29th, small employers category.
Founded: 1989.
Employees: 110 locally, 170 overall.
Line of work: Commercial truck and trailer dealership.
Local: Locations in Henrietta, Geneva, Batavia and Dansville.
Job openings: www.regionalinternational.com
Local community support: Has supported Boy Scouts of America, various fire departments and police departments, and Golisano Children's Hospital.
Recent events: Ride and Drive event, to test trucks, at Canandaigua Motorsports Park.
Roberts Communications Inc.
Ranking: Fifth, small employers category.
Founded: 1971.
Employees: 50 overall.
Line of work: Advertising and public relations.
Revenues: $51 million in capitalized billings.
Local: 64 Commercial St., Rochester.
Job openings: robertscomm.com/jobs/
Local community support: Pro bono developed and launched local "don't text and drive" campaign.
Recent events: Ran second annual 24-hour Day of Innovation for employees.
Of note: Only Rochester-area advertising agency named to Ad Age's 2012 "Best Places to Work" list. "Carrot parties" and quarterly bonuses for all employees.
Sage Rutty & Co. Inc.
Ranking: First, small employer category.
Founded: 1915.
Employees: 53 locally.
Recent hiring: Five in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: Five over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Financial services.
Revenues: $10.2 million.
Local: 100 Corporate Woods Suite 300, Brighton.
Job openings: sagerutty.com/Careers.aspx
Employee benefits: Makes annual contributions into profit-sharing accounts; waives annual IRA fees; extra time off for staff during summer and holidays; and has such employee wellness offerings as weight-loss support groups, flu shots for employees and significant others, and experts who come to talk about anything from chiropractic care to how to create a professional social media page.
Recent events: Sponsors an event each fall to celebrate the support staff - the most recent being an appreciation dinner at Zeppa Bistro in the South Wedge. Prior to drinks and dinner, the staff wandered around different stores in the South Wedge, and there were pre-arranged gifts waiting for them in the different shops.
Of note: Sage Rutty was ranked 18th Best Small & Medium Place to Work in the country by Great Place to Work. It offers employees access to chair massages, BJ's memberships, Keurigs and dry cleaning.
Scott Miller
Ranking: First, midsize employer category.
Founded: 1985.
Employees: 145 locally.
Recent hiring: 21 in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 25 over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Beauty and hairstyling salons.
Local: 3340 Monroe Ave., Pittsford; and 980 Ridge Road, Webster.
Job openings: scottmillerstyle.com
Employee benefits: Offerings include continuing education in cut, style, color, skin care, makeup, spa treatments, client relations and customer service as well as group health plans and a 401(k).
Local community support: Has a dedicated donations coordinator and customer service team.
Recent events: Sent three stylists and creative team members backstage to New York Fashion Week for the spring/summer 2014 collections to work eight shows.
Systems Management Planning Inc.
Ranking: 12th, small employer category.
Founded: 1997.
Employees: 53 locally, 64 overall.
Recent hiring: 14 in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 12 over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Information technology services.
Revenues: $60 million.
Local: 1020 John St., Henrietta.
Job openings: smp-corp.com/careers
Employee benefits: The Henrietta headquarters is on 28 acres of wilderness and hiking trails, with a full-size gymnasium and an on-staff wellness director. A variety of exercise classes are offered weekly. The company also encourages employees to compete in outside endurance events and sponsors a variety of marathons, canoe races and triathlons.
Recent events: Each month it hosts themed technology events and sessions such as Casino Night, SMP Flying Circus and Oktoberfest.
Stewart Title Insurance Co.
Ranking: 24th, small employer category.
Founded: 1987.
Employees: 51 locally, 250 overall.
Line of work: Title and closing services.
Local: Five offices in the Rochester region.
Job openings: stewart.com/careers
Employee benefits: Include multiple medical insurance options, dental, life insurance, and disability, flexible spending accounts, employee stock purchase program, 401(k), 529 college savings plan, paid time off, title reimbursement program, and corporate discounts.
Recent events: In fall of 2013, hosted a continuing legal education seminar for attorney clients on such topics as oil and gas leases, manufactured housing, and ethics, and lunch seminar on the basics of title insurance for paralegals.
Tompkins Financial Corp.
Ranking: Third, midsize employer category.
Founded: 1836.
Employees: 297 locally, 1,067 overall.
Recent hiring: 38 in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 17 over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Financial services holding company.
Revenues: $253 million.
Local: 23 locations across the Rochester area.
Job openings: tompkinsfinancial.com/
Employee benefits: Along with the traditional benefits, has a wellness program that reimburses such expenses as gym/health club memberships, exercise programs as well as quit-smoking programs. It also has profit sharing that is paid in company common stock.
Local community support: Supported more than 750 charitable organizations in 2012 through donations and time.
Of note: Tompkins' local banking affiliate, The Bank of Castile, was founded in 1869 in Castile, Wyoming County, with $500.
Transcat Inc.
Ranking: 10th, midsize employer category.
Founded: 1964.
Employees: 126 locally, 368 overall.
Line of work: Test and measurement equipment and calibration services.
Revenues: $112.3 million.
Local: 35 Vantage Point Drive, Ogden
Job openings: transcat.com/about/employment.aspx
Employee benefits: Health and dental insurance, profit-sharing plan, 401(k), stock purchase plan, dry cleaning service, enhanced insurances, transfer opportunities.
Recent events: President Lee Rudow was named CEO in July 2013.
Of note: Close to 25 percent of employees are former military. Periodically holds such events as holiday parties, Cinco de Mayo, and bringing in of an ice cream truck.
Unity Health System
Ranking: First, large employer category.
Founded: 1975.
Employees: 5,500 locally.
Line of work: Health care.
Revenues: $557 million.
Local: Nine area locations.
Job openings: unityhealth.org/jobs
Employee benefits: Flexible scheduling; night- and weekend-shift differential; paid time off plus six paid holidays; comprehensive health benefits; 403(b) tax-deferred savings plan; company-paid pension plan; free life insurance policy; short- and long-term disability; flexible spending account; on-site child care center, with employee discounts; reward and recognition program; and tuition reimbursement plan.
Local community support: Major sponsor of such events as the Flower City Challenge, Chase Corporate Challenge, Total Sports Experience, Xerox Rochester International Jazz Festival.
Of note: Has 1,145 volunteers who donate more than 137,000 hours per year. Unity Hospital is ranked among the top 100 hospitals in the country for its National Community Value Index score, based on service and value to community.
Valley Manor
Ranking: 16th, small employer category.
Founded: 1971.
Employees: 77 locally.
Recent hiring: 16 in the past 12 months.
Planned hiring: 16 over the next 12 months.
Line of work: Senior citizen housing and adult day care services.
Revenues: $5 million.
Local: 1570 East Ave., Rochester, and 254 Alexander St., Rochester.
Job openings: seniorsfirst.com/employment.htm
Local community support: Collaboration with WXXI for resident programs; Valley Manor Art Gallery supports local artists; and takes part in a mentoring/tutoring program with Rochester School 20.
Of note: First independent living senior community of its kind built in New York state, Its Adult Day program was named Innovative Program of the Year by the New York Association of Homes and Services for the Aged.
Vance Metal Fabricators Inc.
Ranking: 11th, small employer category.
Founded: 1880.
Employees: 82 locally.
Recent hiring: Two in the past 12 months.
Line of work: Metal fabricating and welding.
Local: 251 Gambee Road, Geneva, Ontario County.
Job openings: vancemetal.com/content/view/job-opportunities.html
Local community support: Lead sponsor for the Boys & Girls Club of Geneva and a major sponsor of the Musselman Triathlon held each July in the Finger Lakes.
Of note: Employee owned. Gov. Theodore Roosevelt stopped there in 1900 while campaigning for vice president on the McKinley/Roosevelt ticket, and a photo of the event hangs in Vance's offices.
Webtitle Agency
Ranking: Eighth, midsize employer category.
Founded: 2005.
Employees: 167 locally.
Line of work: Property title and closing services.
Local: 500-A Canal View Blvd., Brighton, and 36 W. Main St. Suite 51, Rochester.
Job openings: webtitle.us/employment/
Employee benefits: 401(k) with company match, health/dental/eye insurance, vacation days, flex time.
Local community support: Awarded the 2011 Corporate Volunteer Organization of the Year by the Federation of Social Workers for charitable endeavors.
Of note: According to Webtitle, the ownership group is also very open to providing life advice to workers to the point where President John Nitsche is referred to as "Papa John."
]]></text></news-item>