<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-XTR1-JB1X-W1V5"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Maritime sector of Pakistan is crucial for sustenance and development: Vice Chief of Naval Staff - Press Note issued by Pakistan Navy</title><source>Pakistan Press International</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[March 28, 2014 (PPI-OT)
Following is the text of press note issued by Pakistan Navy
Quote
The 2nd National Maritime Seminar was held on 27th March 2014 to discuss the policy and regulatory framework governing the maritime sector of Pakistan. National Centre for Maritime Policy Research (NCMPR), a constituent unit of Bahria University organized this enlightening event at the Bahria University Karachi Campus.
Vice Chief of Naval Staff, Vice Admiral Muhammad Zakaullah HI(M) and Chairman Pakistan National Shipping Corporation (PNSC) Mr. M Siddique Memon graced the occasion as chief guests. The seminar was attended by officials from Government, Pakistan Navy, academia and maritime industry.
The seminar was divided into two sessions which comprised of presentations and interactive question answer sessions. The first session addressed the environmental laws as the marine life along the coastal belt of Pakistan is under serious threat due to marine pollution. Dr. Shahid Amjad, HoD, Environmental and Energy Management of Institute of Business Management (IoBM) apprised the audience on national laws for marine pollution and protection of coastal areas.
He stated that degradation and encroachment of coastal zones will result in loss of important resources and make us more vulnerable to natural disasters. In this regard citizens, industry and officials should abide by the environmental laws. Likewise, Mr. Fayyaz Rasool, Manager Marine Pollution Control Department from Karachi Port Trust discussed the implementation of global environmental standards for port operations in Pakistan.
Other speakers reviewed the existing national laws and policies pertinent to the maritime sector. Although Pakistan being a responsible maritime nation is signatory to important international laws but a need to continuously rationalize national regulations and mechanisms for best practices still exists. Commander Omer Farooq impressively elaborated the role of Pakistan Navy and Pakistan Maritime Security Agency in maintaining the safety and security at sea.
With reference to the presentation on Maritime Labour Convention, Advocate Aga Zafar Ahmed touched upon the important aspects. Moreover, Commander Retd Muhammad Azam Khan talked about the Maritime Doctrine of Pakistan and revealed that this is still a work in progress.
Chairman PNSC Mr. Siddique Memon in his speech, lauded the organizers of the event for providing a unique opportunity to all stakeholders, to sit together and work out the way forward for an integrated approach towards a sustainable and developed maritime sector.
Speaking on the occasion Vice Chief of Naval Staff, Vice Admiral Muhammad Zakaullah HI (M) emphasized that the maritime sector of Pakistan is crucial for sustenance and development. Therefore, regularization and effective implementation of maritime sector is important. He highlighted that Pakistani seafarers qualify the international standards for the training and education set by IMO. In this regard, the government of Pakistan should adapt dynamic policies to open up job opportunities for our seafarers as this sector can earn revenue up to US$ 500 million per annum.
Director General NCMPR Vice Admiral Asaf Humayun HI (M) thanked the esteemed chief guests and speakers for their presence at the seminar. He appreciated the speakers for making such informative presentations.
NCMPR at Bahria University serves as Think-Tank for study and analysis of maritime affairs. The Centre's mandate includes promotion of maritime education, research and public awareness on the issues related to maritime sector.
For more information, contact:Lieutenant Commander Shakeel AhmadAssistant DirectorDirectorate of Public RelationsPakistan NavyTel: +9221 2006 3210Cell: +92333 217 1764 and +92300 217 1038
Unquote
]]></text></news-item>