<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-WMR1-JDK3-94HV"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Class-action suit over credit card fees charged to merchants gets green light in B.C</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[VANCOUVER - A class-action lawsuit challenging the fees paid by merchants on credit card transactions has been approved to go ahead in a B.C. court.
The two B.C. law firms that launched the action, Branch MacMaster LLP and Camp Fiorante Matthews Mogerman, say the Supreme Court of British Columbia granted the class action status on Wednesday.
The lawyers filed the suit in 2011 on behalf of Mary Watson, a Vancouver furniture store owner, who accuses the major credit card companies of a price fixing conspiracy, charging excessive fees on merchants when they process credit card transactions.
Named in the suit are credit card companies Visa Canada Corp. and MasterCard International Inc., as well as Canada's largest banks: Royal Bank of Canada, Toronto-Dominion Bank, BMO Financial Group, the Bank of Nova Scotia, Canadian Imperial Bank of Commerce, National Bank of Canada and the Federation des caisses Desjardins du Quebec.
At issue in the proceedings are approximately $5 billion in fees paid by merchants annually to accept Visa and MasterCard credit card transactions, the firm says.
Parallel proceedings are underway in Ontario, Quebec, Saskatchewan and Alberta, but were being held in abeyance pending the decision in British Columbia.
"The claims advanced in the other jurisdictions are very similar and were designed to collectively capture the claims of all Canadian merchants," said Reidar Mogerman, of Camp Fiorante Matthews Mogerman, in a statement.
"We hope that this positive decision will result in the Canadian banks, Visa and MasterCard responding to merchants' concerns about how high these fees are set. Changes have already occurred in many other countries to address this problem, and we believe it is time for Canada's banks to respond as well."
A settlement has already been negotiated with Bank of America, which will now be forwarded to the B.C. court for approval.
The claims have not been proven in court.
The class action seeks to represent all Canadian merchants who processed a credit card payment dating back to March 2001.
ticrawford@vancouversun.com( mailto:ticrawford@vancouversun.com )
© Copyright (c) The Vancouver Sun
]]></text></news-item>