<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-GW91-DXCW-D15T"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Tennessee: Training Officer, Fire Department</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[City of Spring hill, The state of Tennessee has issued the following job vacancy:
Training Officer, Fire Department
Under limited supervision, is primarily responsible for providing subordinate officers and personnel with mandated training and instruction, which involves determining the specific training needs of departmental personnel, developing course content, administering course, and evaluating the students; performance. Arranges classes for new recruit training and orientation and conducts the forty hours of recurrent training mandated by the State of Tennessee Commission on Firefighting; arranges for personnel to take classes through various other agencies or learning institutions as required. Handles employee concerns and problems related to training issues. Remains responsible for all training of departmental personnel, which involves performing a needs assessment, designing and developing course content, administering the course to department staff, and evaluating the work of each student. Reviews any existing safety deficiencies within the fire stations and employee accident reports, and reports such safety violations to the Fie Chief for corrective action to be taken. Reviews all departmental motor vehicle accident reports to determine whether the accident was due to operator error or a lack of proper training; works to ensure these types of situations are not repeated by ensuring that all personnel receive the necessary training to successfully complete job duties. Qualifications
Five years of supervisory experience; or any equivalent combination of education, specialized training, and experience which provides the requisite knowledge, skills, and abilities for this position. Must be state certified as Firefighter II, Instructor I, Fire Officer I and 2 Must possess an E.M.T. or Paramedic license and have extensive knowledge in hazardous materials operations (Hazardous Material Technician is preferred). Prior to selection, applicant must have a record free from felony crime, or a misdemeanor involving theft or giving false information, be in good physical condition as determined by NFPA medical examination and meet minimum physical fitness requirements of the Fire Fighter Professional Qualification Code as published by the National Fire Protection Association, and possess a valid Tennessee Driver's License with excellent driving history. Must possess thorough knowledge of City geography and related laws, ordinance, rules, and regulations. Special Requirements
This position is FULL TIME, M-F, 40 hours per week. Miscellaneous Information
Applications MUST be submitted online at www.springhilltn.org. Resumes and supplemental materials may also be submitted through the provided link on the City's employment site.
For further information please visit: http://www.springhilltn.org/Jobs.aspx
]]></text></news-item>