<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-4321-JCXB-23NP"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Manroy PLC Preliminary Results -14-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Key estimates and judgements are applied to the fair values of assets acquired on acquisitions and these have been included the valuation of intangible assets. The financial statements reflect the fair value of intangible assets acquired based on estimates and judgements of the discounted rates of return of the cash generating units of those assets and the weighted average costs of capital.
Tangible assets Key estimates and judgements are applied to the fair values of assets acquired on acquisitions and these have been included the valuation of tangible assets. The financial statements reflect the fair value of tangible assets acquired based on independent valuations and market values appropriate to such classes of asset. Basis of consolidation The consolidated financial statements incorporate the financial statements of the Company and its subsidiaries up to 30 September 2013. Subsidiaries are those entities that are controlled by the Company. Control is achieved where the Company has the power, directly or indirectly, to govern the financial and operating policies of an entity so as to obtain benefits from its activities. The results of subsidiaries and associated companies acquired or disposed of during the year are included from the effective date of acquisition or up to the effective date of disposal, as appropriate. Inter-company transactions, balances and unrealised gains on transactions between Group companies are eliminated. Unrealised losses are also eliminated. Where necessary, adjustments are made to the financial statements of subsidiaries and associated companies to bring the accounting policies used into line with those used by the Group. Associated companies Associated companies have been accounted for under the equity method of accounting whereby the investment is initially recognised at fair value and adjusted thereafter for the post-acquisition change in the Group's share of the fair value of the net assets of associated companies. The profit or loss of the Group includes the share of profit or loss of associated companies after tax. Segmental reporting A business segment is where a group of assets and operations are engaged in providing services that are subject to risks and returns that are different from other business segments. The Group has only one class of business and a summary of revenue by geographical market is set out in note 2. The results of the Company's Associated Company, MUSA, are included as share of results of Associated Company in the Income Statement. Revenue recognition Revenue represents income recognised by the Group in respect of goods and services supplied, royalties from third parties using the Group's intellectual property and management expertise, exclusive of trade discounts and Value Added Tax. Revenue is recognised on dispatch of completed goods, except in the case of bill and hold sales where revenue is recognised when the risks of ownership have passed to the customer concerned. Under bill and hold arrangements, customers request the Group to hold products in Section 5 secured facilities until collection by their secured carriers has been undertaken. Royalty income is accrued during the period then reconciled to royalty cash receipts on a periodic basis. Pre-contract costs Pre-contract costs are carried as an asset where there is reasonable certainty that the contract will generate future economic benefits against which the costs will be recovered. Share options For equity-settled share-based payment transactions, the Group measures their value in accordance with IFRS 2, with the corresponding increase in equity, by reference to the fair value of equity instruments granted. The fair value of equity instruments is measured at the date of grant using the Black Scholes method. The expense is apportioned over the vesting period of the financial instrument and is based on the numbers which are expected to vest and the fair value of the financial instruments at the date of grant. If equity instruments vest immediately, the full expense is recognised immediately. Foreign currencies Monetary assets and liabilities denominated in foreign currencies are translated into Sterling at rates of exchange ruling at the date of the statement of financial position. Transactions in foreign currencies during the year are translated into Sterling at the rate ruling on the date of the transaction. Exchange gains and losses arising on transactions are recognised in the consolidated income statement in the year they arise. For the purpose of presenting consolidated financial statements, the assets and liabilities of the Group's foreign operations are translated at exchange rates prevailing on the date of the statement of financial position. Income and expense items are translated at the average exchange rates for the period, unless exchange rates fluctuate significantly during that period, in which case the exchange rate at dates of transactions are used. Exchange differences arising on the translation of assets and liabilities of the Group's foreign operations at exchange rates prevailing on the date of the statement of financial position are recognised in other comprehensive income. Leasing and hire purchase Assets obtained under hire purchase contracts and finance leases are recorded as tangible fixed assets. Assets acquired by finance lease are depreciated over the shorter of the lease term and their useful lives. Assets acquired by hire purchase are depreciated over their useful lives. Finance leases are those where substantially all of the benefits and risks of ownership are assumed by the group. Obligations under such agreements are included in current and non-current liabilities net of finance charge allocated to future periods. The finance element of the rental payment is charged to the consolidated statement of total comprehensive income so as to produce a constant periodic rate of charge on the net obligation outstanding in each period. Operating leases Operating leases and lease payments are recognised as an expense in the income statement over the lease term on a straight-line basis, unless another systematic basis is more representative of the time pattern of the user's benefit Benefits received and receivable as an incentive to sign an operating lease are recognised on a straight line basis over the period until the rent is expected to be adjusted to the prevailing market rate. Dividends Interim dividends paid are recognised in the year in which the payment is made. Final dividend payments in respect of a financial year are recognised as a liability in the year in which the dividend payment is approved by the Company's Shareholders. Goodwill Business combinations are accounted for using the acquisition method. On acquisition, the assets, liabilities and contingent liabilities of a subsidiary are measured at their fair values at the date of acquisition. Any excess of the purchase price over the fair value of the assets and liabilities acquired is recognised as goodwill. Goodwill is not amortised but is reviewed for impairment at each date of statement of financial position.Gains, arising when the price paid for an acquisition is less than the fair value of its net assets are determined as negative goodwill; these gains are taken immediately to the Income Statement. Intangible assets The Group has valued intangible assets using the income approach and relief from royalty methodology. Useful economic lives have been determined for specific assets as follows:-
]]></text></news-item>