<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-TPV1-JD34-V10H"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Political theatre</title><source>Sydney Morning Herald (Australia)</source><author>Michaela Whitbourn and Kate McClymont</author><text><![CDATA[AWH was about lots of money and not much work, write Michaela Whitbourn and Kate McClymont.
It says a lot about the extravagance of the corruption alleged in an inquiry that a $150,000 salary for a job involving "no specific work" sounds like loose change.
There was barely an eyebrow raised when a nephew of corrupt former Labor powerbroker Eddie Obeid, Dennis Jabour, admitted this week he was "employed in a position which never actually produced anything" for him to do.
"Of course I worked," the former Australian Water Holdings employee huffed indignantly at the Independent Commission Against Corruption.
It was just that his job description didn't reflect the work he ended up doing, he explained.
Jabour was a small fish at the end of a big week at the ICAC. The inquiry ito Australian Water, a company linked to the Obeid family, had already heard sensational allegations of forged cabinet minutes, political knifings and whopping salaries charged by the company to the state-owned Sydney Water.
Hours before Jabour took the stand, former Labor premier Kristina Keneally had swept ito the ICAC witness box and declared of a dodgy cabinet document favouring AWH: "This was the cabinet minute that wouldn't die, until I drove a stake through its heart."
The minute was allegedly doctored by Obeid's political allies, Joe Tripodi and Tony Kelly, to support AWH's proposal in mid-2010 for a lucrative public-private partnership.
The inquiry has heard the Obeids had a secret stake in AWH and stood to make up to $60 million if the PPP went ahead.
Following Keneally's theatrical lead, former NSW treasurer Michael Costa, a one-time chairman of AWH, told the inquiry he felt like "that bloke in the Pulp Fiction movie, Winston Wolfe" - a sharply dressed fixer and cleaning specialist.
Costa is said to have played a "positive role" at AWH in trying to clean up its financial mess.
He and Keneally delivered made-for-TV testimony - even if the latter borrowed her evocative phrase from a bureaucrat - and escaped the witness box unscathed.
Former premier Morris Iemma, who is expected to give evidence on Monday, is expected to fare equally well.
Iemma was added to the all-star witness line-up after the inquiry heard jaw-dropping claims this week that Obeid and Tripodi agreed to oust him as premier in 2008 in exchange for a favourable deal for AWH.
Other politicians face a tougher time in the ICAC hot seat.
Liberal senator Arthur Sinodinos, who preceded Costa as non-executive chairman of AWH, will give evidence as early as Wednesday.
All eyes were on the former Liberal Party president after former Sydney Water boss Kerry Schott told the inquiry she warned him as early as 2009 he could be keeping "dishonest" company on the AWH board, and that the company was billing exorbitant expenses to the public utility.
Sinodinos remained on the AWH board until November 2011, when he resigned to take up a Senate position.
His barrister, Tony Bannon, SC, fuelled the media frenzy when he called another witness, disgruntled AWH investor Rod De Aboitiz, a "smart arse" after he referred to Sinodinos as the "former" assistant federal treasurer.
Sinodinos is expected to face heated questioning about the steps he took, if any, to rein in ballooning costs at AWH and to inform himself of how the money was being spent.
The inquiry has heard allegations Sydney Water was unwittingly paying thousands of dollars for chauffeur-driven limousines, donations to the Liberal Party and legal fees.
The public utility had contracted AWH to manage the roll-out of water and sewerage infrastructure in the north-west and agreed to cover its costs under a badly drafted agreement signed in the early 1990s.
Jabour's $150,000 salary at AWH, and the millions of dollars paid to the company's top executives, were allegedly "bundled up" in the company's expenses and billed to Sydney Water.
So too was the $200,000 salary paid to Sinodinos. (The inquiry heard Costa was offered $150,000 when he took over as chairman).
Counsel assisting the commission, Geoffrey Watson SC, had previously claimed that Sinodinos did about 100 hours' work a year.
But when Bannon objected to questions this week about his client's pay, Watson shot back: "I said 100 hours a year, I tallied it up, I was trying to be kind, it's about 50."
Sinodinos will be grilled about his "true role" at AWH, which the inquiry has heard was to "open lines of communication with the Liberal Party".
He was appointed chairman of the company in November 2010, four months before the 2011 election which swept the Keneally government from office and delivered a landslide victory to the Barry O'Farrell-led Coalition.
The inquiry has heard that Obeid and his allies were touting the Liberal credentials of AWH almost a year before the election.
Keneally told the inquiry she had a "very clear memory" of Tripodi assuring her there were Liberal Party figures involved in AWH, so she "didn't need to worry about the opposition kicking up a fuss if we approved this minute".
She said Obeid had also assured her that there were "Liberals involved with the company".
"His view was that the company shouldn't be barred from putting a proposal forward because there were people with political connections involved," Keneally said.
The company's links to the Liberals became more pronounced after the March election, when AWH shifted its focus to securing a PPP with the new Coalition government. A string of Liberal-aligned lobbyists were retained, including powerbroker Michael Photios, who is also expected to give evidence next week. Just what Sinodinos knew, and when, will be the main game next week.
Costa said it was clear to him when he joined the board of AWH in late 2011 that the company's expenses were "out of control".
He said that AWH director Peter Canaway, who inherited the company in a financially parlous state, had told him that pole dancing was also among the company's "staggering" expenses.
"I couldn't believe the salaries," Costa said. "The managing director of Sydney Water's salary, he was on about $650,000 ... or $700,000 and we had three executives that were either on that or higher in a company that had limited resources and limited scope of operation."
]]></text></news-item>