<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-PY71-DYN2-32XX"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Street Child World Cup kicks off in Brazil to tackle global problem</title><source>guardian.co.uk</source><author>Jonathan Wattstheguardian.com</author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
It's Brazil, it's 2014 and players from around the world are waiting for kick-off, but there will be no galacticos on the pitch or Wags at local boutiques during the tournament this weekend in Rio de Janeiro.
Instead, the Street Child World Cup will bring together some of the most disadvantaged youths from 19 nations for 10 days of football, art, sightseeing and workshops - putting a spotlight on an issue that many people choose to ignore.
They include street children from Karachi in Pakistan and Mwanza in Tanzania, Indian children who sought refuge in Chennai station after escaping from domestic abuse, and Brazilian youths who are trying to break free from the cycle of poverty, drugs and violence that claims so many lives in Rio before the age of 20.
The dangers have been all too apparent in the runup to the tournament. Last month, Rodrigo Kelton, one of the players in the Brazilian boys' team was killed on his 14th birthday in an apparent revenge attack for a robbery he committed before signing up for the event.
Other participants say they still feel at risk. Francesca Santos (whose name has been changed to protect her identity) has spent much of her young life living on the streets, begging for food and working as a drug mule for one the biggest gangs in Rio.
Until three months ago, she was smuggling drugs from Paraguay - a job the gang wanted her to continue, until her grandmother interceded. As well as pressure from the traffickers, she says her lover's former partner - also a gangster - has threatened to kill her. Playing football is a rare opportunity to escape from these worries.
"Football takes me away from my problems. I've always loved it," she says, during a training session with teammates in the Penha area of Rio. "The Street Child World Cup is a really great opportunity. I've never had anything like this."
Organisers say the 10-day event - backed by Save the Children and also endorsed by David Beckham, Sir Alex Ferguson, Gary Lineker and Archbishop Desmond Tutu - is about a lot more than football. As well as the boys' and girls' competitions, the 230 or so participants will take part in a festival of arts, visit Rio's most famous sights and engage in a conference on children's rights. By the closing ceremony, they are expected to produce a "Rio rights declaration" of actions countries should take to help street children.
"Street Child World Cup is calling on governments, businesses and the wider community to invest in frontline responses, legislate and implement policies that protect street children and listen to street children so they are no longer blamed, ignored or victimised," said organiser Joe Hewitt.
After the first such tournament, in Durban, South Africa, the organisers said the city government was compelled to end the practice of "street sweeps" - an often indiscriminate rounding-up of youths for largely cosmetic reasons. This year, the goal is to prompt the Brazilian government to introduce a comprehensive policy on street children.
Activists in poor communities say the event should help to raise public awareness, but some are cautious about the long-term benefits.
"It's never bad to put the kids in the media spotlight and bring together teams from around the world," said Yvonne Bezerra de Mello of the Uerê Project in the Maré community. "But people will say it is just marketing. They'll put them out for a short while then they'll go back to the streets."
De Mello started the Uerê education programme soon after the 1993 Candelária massacre, when eight Rio street youths were murdered by police death squads.
Since then, she said, little has changed. Despite the passage of a law to protect street children, she said the number on the streets is about the same as it was 20 years ago, shelters are filled with crack addicts and middle-class resentment and fear is as bad as ever. There has been a recent spate of cases in which vigilantes have chained street youths to lampposts and railings with bicycle locks.
"One day another massacre will occur," said De Mello. "It's inevitable. Everyone wants to ignore the situation - not just in Brazil, but in the world."
Supporters of the tournament do not claim that the event will lead to the salvation of the participants, but they say it is worthwhile for its symbolism, profile, and as a driver for small but important changes in the lives of the participants.
Philip Veldhuis, who runs the Favela Street NGO in Penha, said football helps to take drug soldiers off the streets. "We educate them with sport. We try to train them to be trainers on the soccer pitch so that they can become role models."
The participants seems to agree that it offers at least a temporary escape. Eighteen-year-old Jessica Maria Nogueira, one of the coaches of the Brazilian team, said many former players had drifted back to the streets and drugs, but the tournament inspired her to dream of better things.
"I'm really looking forward to it. We're representing Brazil. This is a really big thing in my life," she said. "My dream is to play for my country."
Additional research by Charlotte Livingstone
]]></text></news-item>