<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-DYH1-DYR8-328T"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Nigeria; Lagos Laws Do Not Cover Toll Collection On Lekki-Ikoyi Bridge, Court Rules</title><source>Africa News</source><author>Premium Times (Abuja)</author><text><![CDATA[Conceived in 2008, the 1.35 kilometre Lekki-Ikoyi link bridge was opened to the public in May 2013 amid controversies.
Justice Saliu Seidu of a Federal High Court, Lagos, Thursday ruled that the Lagos State Government does not have an existing law permitting it to collect tolls on the newly constructed Lekki-Ikoyi Bridge.
Delivering judgment on a suit filed by Ebun-Olu Adegboruwa, a lawyer and human rights activist, against the Lagos State Government over collection of toll on the bridge; the judge held that the state can only make a law to that effect, before it can collect tolls on the bridge.
Joined as first and second respondents are the Attorney General of the Federation and the National Inland Waterways Authority, NIWA.
Ade Ipaye, the Attorney General of Lagos State, and the Lagos State Government are the third and fourth respondents respectively.
Justice Saidu said that he would consider the case based on its merit rather delving into technical issues raised in the addresses of both the applicant's and respondents' counsels.
"The further counter affidavit of the third and fourth respondents, and the response of the first and second respondents, have answered most of the questions before this court," the judge said in his ruling.
"The second respondent (NIWA) is the only Federal Agency to form and regulate Navigable Waterway in the country, in line with the NIWA Act.
"The applicant did not contest this issue, but only goes further to raise the issue of collection of toll from the subject matter.
"The third respondent tried to justify the collection of such toll in paragraph 26 of their counter affidavit, by stating that when the bridge is erected, its proceeds will be applied to the consolidated revenue fund of the Lagos State government.
"The question now is, has the Lagos State government made the appropriate law to enable her collect such toll on the bridge?
"The third respondent only cited sections 27, 28, and 29 of the Lagos State Public Private Partnership Law 2011 as making provision for the collection of revenue.
"There is nothing before me to show that the subject matter in this case was as a result of any Public Private Partnership law, to enable the law of 2011 be extended.
"The fact before this court is that the bridge was built with the third respondents' money.
"I agree and uphold the construction of the bridge, and the power of the Lagos State government to generate revenue there from, but the existing laws does not cover it.
"I therefore hold that the third respondent can only make a law to that effect, before it can collect tolling on the Lekki-Ikoyi bridge," the judge added.
Mr. Adegboruwa had filed the suit in November 26, 2012, for a declaration that the Lagos State government had no authority to erect a bridge, on the Lagos Lagoon which is categorized by law as federal navigable waterways.
He had also sought a determination of court as to whether there existed any law in Nigeria, authorizing the collection of such tolls, tax or fee, from citizens.
Mr. Adegboruwa wanted the court to declare that the imposition of such tariff on road users, is an illegal form of taxation and is inconsistent with the Constitution of the Federal Republic of Nigeria.
Conceived in 2008, the 1.35 kilometre Lekki-Ikoyi link bridge was opened to the public in May 2013 amid controversies.
A Lagos Tolling Company, set up to be in charge of the concession of the bridge, would retain 27 per cent of the gross revenue from the toll, while 73 per cent goes to the state government, a move frowned upon by the State House of Assembly.
The bridge, constructed by Julius Berger Plc, is suspended from a 91 metre high pylon and provides the 9 metre headroom above water level to allow for maritime traffic.
According to the state government, salon cars are required to pay N250 toll to use the suspension bridge; motorcycles with 200cc capacity and above - N100.00; mini-vans, SUVs and light pick-up trucks - N300.00; while non-commercial buses with a maximum seating capacity of 26 persons will pay N400.00 each way.
Restrictions were placed on commercial motorcycles (also known as Okada), tricycles (also known as Keke Marwa), commercial buses including danfos and high capacity buses (commercial buses exceeding a maximum seating capacity of 26), and heavy duty trucks, articulated trucks, lorries and other vehicles.
]]></text></news-item>