<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-SDG1-JC65-507M"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>BC-Japan-N Korea UPDATE3</title><source>Japan Economic Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TOKYO, March 28 -
Prime Minister Shinzo Abe said Friday he will make all-out efforts to completely resolve the issue of North Korea's past abductions of Japanese citizens.
Abe's government has decided on its approach in Japan-North Korea intergovernmental talks starting Sunday at which Tokyo will urge Pyongyang to reinvestigate the abductees' whereabouts, Japanese government sources said.
"I'll make utmost efforts to resolve the issue totally while I'm in office," Abe told a meeting with the families of Japanese abducted by North Korean agents in the 1970s and 1980s, adding Japan will keep using "dialogue and pressure" to achieve that goal.
Abe made the pledge after a Cabinet minister said that Tokyo could ease its sanctions against the North if it deals with the issue properly. "We sense there is a chance to resolve the abduction issue and hope (the government) will not miss it," Shigeo Iizuka, who heads the group of families, told Abe at the meeting.
Keiji Furuya, minister in charge of the abduction issue, told a press conference earlier in the day, "If North Korea shows sincere, positive moves toward resolving the abduction issue, it is possible (for Japan) to gradually lift its unilateral" sanctions.
Government sources also later said the Japanese government plans to tell North Korea during the two-day talks that it is ready to consider gradually lifting sanctions if Pyongyang reinvestigates the abduction cases.
As part of easing sanctions Japan imposes on North Korea, Tokyo could partially ease entry of North Korean nationals into Japan and allow chartered flights from the North to Japan, they said.
Following a 16-month hiatus, the two countries will resume formal talks Sunday in Beijing to address bilateral issues of concern, most notably the kidnappings, which have prevented them from normalizing their diplomatic ties.
Japan will also call on North Korea to honor its 2008 promise to reinvestigate the fate of Japanese abductees, and look into the cases of missing Japanese who are not on the government's official list of abductees, the sources said.
Japan has imposed sanctions since a missile launch by Pyongyang in July 2006. It has banned port calls by a vessel used to transport North Korean residents of Japan between the two countries and prohibited North Korean officials from visiting Japan.
After Pyongyang repeatedly fired missiles amid a lack of progress on the abduction issue and its nuclear program, Tokyo took additional steps, expanding the port call ban to cover other North Korean vessels and blocking all trade between the countries. Analysts say the measures have hit the already fragile North Korean economy.
Japan has also taken steps coordinated by the international community to punish North Korea.
Any unilateral moves by Japan to soften its stance against North Korea would come in contrast to international pressure on the country over its nuclear and missile development programs in violation of U.N. resolutions. They could also irk the United States, Japan's main ally.
On issues other than abductions, Tokyo will protest against Pyongyang over its launch of Rodong medium-range ballistic missiles Wednesday, calling the action a "clear violations of U.N. Security Council resolutions," a Foreign Ministry source said.
Japan will also tell North Korea it will take sincere steps to "settle its past," or address the suffering of the Korean people under Japan's 1910-1945 colonization of the Korean Peninsula, the government sources said.
Furuya said whether Japan lifts the unilateral sanctions "basically depends on negotiations," suggesting Tokyo will only act in response to steps taken by North Korea to address the abductions. "We must make North Korea understand that it will become unable to stand unless it makes progress on the abduction issue."
Foreign Minister Fumio Kishida expressed hope that the upcoming intergovernmental talks will raise prospects for addressing the abduction, nuclear and missile issues comprehensively.
"We will respond with patience," Kishida told a separate press conference.
North Korea admitted in 2002 to having abducted 13 Japanese nationals and later returned five of them to Japan, claiming the remaining eight were dead.
Japan believes North Korea has yet to provide credible evidence regarding the fate of those eight abductees while Pyongyang has repeatedly said the issue has been resolved. Tokyo has identified 17 Japanese abductees while also believing there are more cases.
]]></text></news-item>