<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-1RV1-DYN6-W4XY"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Japan to revise ODA guidelines for strategic use</title><source>Japan Economic Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TOKYO, March 28 - The government will revise guidelines for Japan's official development assistance to use ODA more "proactively and strategically" for global peace and prosperity, as well as Japan's national security and economic revival, Foreign Minister Fumio Kishida said Friday.
The Foreign Ministry has set up a panel of experts to promote debate on the first revision in 11 years of the ODA Charter, created in 1992 and revised in 2003, and plans to compile a new charter by the end of this year, Kishida said in a speech.
The eight-member panel, chaired by Taizo Yakushiji, a professor emeritus at Keio University, will hold its first meeting on Monday. It plans to present a report to Kishida around June.
The new charter will reflect views from business leaders, nongovernmental organizations and civil groups, as well as opinions from the public.
Based on Prime Minister Shinzo Abe's policy of proactively contributing to peace, Japan will assist countries that share fundamental values such as freedom, democracy, human rights and the rule of law as it deploys ODA strategically as a diplomatic tool, Foreign Ministry officials said.
ODA will address not only poverty elimination but other development and global issues such as international health, disaster prevention and narrowing the gap between the rich and poor, the officials said.
Japan will make greater contribution to the growth of developing countries through use of ODA for areas such as infrastructure exports and support for small and midsize companies, which in turn would lead to the growth of Japan's economy, they said.
The charter will call for increased coordination between ODA and non-ODA finance such as private funds in promoting development in recipient countries.
In an ODA white paper released in February, Japan called for increased ODA to Asia and Africa, saying aid to the Association of Southeast Asian Nations has been an effective "investment in the future" for the 10-nation region and Japan.
In 2012, Japan's ODA totaled about $10.60 billion, down 2.1 percent from the previous year, ranking fifth after the United States, Britain, Germany and France, according to the paper.
Vietnam was the largest recipient of Japanese ODA with $1.64 billion, followed by Afghanistan with $873 million, India with $704 million and Iraq with $360 million.
]]></text></news-item>