<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-FCH1-DY15-S3TJ"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Crime Rate Declines By 24 Percent</title><source>The New Times (Kigali)</source><author>Didace Ndamira</author><text><![CDATA[Security situation in the country has improved tremendously with crimes reducing by 23.9 per cent in the past three months, the Inspector General of Police, Emmanuel K. Gasana, has said.
IGP Gasana was speaking during an interactive session between Rwanda National Police (RNP) and the media fraternity at the Force's headquarters in Kacyiru on Wednesday
The session, held quarterly, brings together Police and media to discuss issues aimed at strengthening cooperation in fighting crime.
The Police chief cited assault, theft, gender violence and drug abuse among the major crimes that were reported.
The IGP also said traffic-related offences decreased by about 13 per cent since December last year.
"The decrease was due to increased awareness and partnership with various stakeholders such as the general public and local government officials," IGP Gasana said.
"Rwanda is safe and the citizens should concentrate on development," he added.
The Force also signed partnership agreements with all the 30 districts in the country, trained over 100,000 community policing committee members and established anti-crime clubs in schools to improve security in the country.
The Police chief also said that the Force established an anti-corruption unit, and is working closely with other institutions like Transparency International and the Ombudsman's office to fight graft in the Force and in the country.
Gasana explained that those responsible for the recent grenade attacks in Musanze District were arrested.
"These are terror acts coordinated by FDLR and the likes of Kayumba Nyamwasa and company. Anyone involved in these criminal acts will face the consequences," he said.
IGP Gasana said RNP had strengthened cooperation with regional and international police forces to combat cross-border crimes and apprehend suspects who flee their home countries after committing crime. Gasana appealed to the media to always be fair and objective in their reporting and to partner with RNP to sensitise and educate the public on crime prevention.
He also appealed to the public to report anything that might cause insecurity, especially during the upcoming Genocide commemoration period.
During the meeting, it was agreed that journalists be trained in crime reporting and that a monthly talk-show be aired on private and public radio stations to sensitise the public about crime.
Prof. Anastase Shyaka, the Chief Executive Officer of Rwanda Governance Board (RGB), said the partnership between police and the media is an indication of good governance and transparency.
He pledged support in organising periodic interactions and monthly talk-shows.
]]></text></news-item>