<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-DJC1-F0NV-F231"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>UPDATE: Court tells GPC: Pay up and clean up</title><source>Muscatine Journal (Iowa)</source><author>Jason Liegois 5632620525 Jason.Liegois@muscatinejournal.com</author><text><![CDATA[Update: 8:30 p.m
MUSCATINE, Iowa - It's a fine for the record books, and that will be just the start for Grain Processing Corp.
The office of Iowa Attorney General Tom Miller announced Thursday afternoon that GPC, located in Muscatine, will pay a $1.5 million penalty for pollution violations.
The penalty, assessed Thursday by District Court Judge Mark D. Cleve, is the highest ever state penalty for environmental violations. It is part of a consent decree which settles a lawsuit Miller filed against GPC in 2011, which alleged the company was responsible for multiple instances of air and water pollution. GPC processes grain into ethanol and various other feed, industrial and food products.
On top of the penalty, GPC will be required to fully convert its coal-fired boilers used at its Muscatine operations to natural gas usage by July 15, 2015. Miller's release stated that the move, which his office termed "unprecedented," would reduce air pollution emissions by more than 12,000 tons annually.
Conversion of the boilers to natural gas was a specific goal of Clean Air Muscatine Inc. (CLAM), which had intervened in Miller's lawsuit.
"This is a comprehensive and historic resolution of an environmental enforcement action," Miller said in the release. "This outcome will go far toward ensuring GPC's environmental compliance and improving air quality in Muscatine."
Other requirements of GPC by the decree include:
* Installing ten additional air pollution control systems, resulting in additional reductions of at least 700 tons of air pollutant emissions per year, according to the attorney general's office.
* Implement an ongoing environmental management system.
* Conduct, through an approved third party, a comprehensive environmental audit of its corn processing facility, and correct any environmental hazards or violations found as part of that audit.
Geoff Greenwood, communications director for Miller's office, said Thursday evening that Miller was confident that GPC would follow through with the requirements of the consent decree.
"If they violate this decree, they would face a hefty penalty," Greenwood said.
According to the consent decree, every individual violation of the agreement would cost GPC as much as $10,000 per day for as long as the violation took place.
The company estimates that implementing terms of the consent decree will cost $15-17 million in capital expenses, $1 million per year in operating costs, and $4-12 million per year in increased fuel costs.
In a news release from Kent Corp., the Muscatine-based parent company of GPC, the company said these efforts will be in addition to $100 million in environmental sustainability efforts already begun by GPC. The statement said that the agreement will allow GPC to "focus on the future" and that the company's actions will help Muscatine County to reach its pollution reduction goals set in the state's five-year implementation plan.
"The amended petition from the AG's office provided an opportunity for GPC and the DNR to collaboratively develop specific plans to address the full scope of concerns," said Gage Kent, CEO and Chairman of Kent Corp. "GPC has and will continue to make a huge commitment of resources to deliver on the promise of air quality improvement."
It's a bill far more expensive than previous environmental penalties the company has paid. In April 2013 it paid $129,000 in fines to the federal Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) for a violation of the Clean Water Act. Back in 2006, there was a $538,000 civil penalty for air pollution control violations, awarded after a previous Miller lawsuit.
In a statement issued by CLAM president Sandy Stanley Thursday night, Stanley said her group was celebrating a "historic day for the people of Muscatine," adding that the record penalty was "befitting for a corporation that, unfortunately, has become one of Iowa's all-time-record air polluters."
While some have criticized proponents of stronger pollution controls for GPC, alleging that such efforts would cost jobs, CLAM rebuked that claim. "GPC can - and will -do better environmentally," Stanley said in the statement, "without any loss in the quality of the products its workers make or the number of jobs that those workers enjoy."
Stanley said the improvements that GPC must make will put the company on a more level playing field with grain manufacturers "who already are playing by the environmental laws of our state and nation."
Stanley said Thursday's actions would not have happened without the public's vigilance, adding that the judge's ruling was an important first step.
"CLAM will remain vigilant to ensure GPC complies with this court order," said Stanley.
]]></text></news-item>