<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-77P1-F0JP-W4RH"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Flight Centre hit with $11m fine</title><source>The Courier Mail (Australia)</source><author>Anthony Marx</author><text><![CDATA[FLIGHT Centre has been slapped with one of Australia's largest fines for price-fixing.
The nation's biggest travel agency network was ordered yesterday to pay $11 million for repeatedly attempting to prevent three airlines from undercutting it on airfares between 2005 and 2009.
Federal Court Justice John Logan also placed injunctions on the Brisbane-based company, banning it from making any pricing deals with any international airlines for three years.
Justice Logan noted that Flight Centre chief executive Graham Turner "had direct, personal involvement" with one of the five breaches of the Trade Practices Act.
He harshly criticised the "flagrant conduct by a major, profitable public company enjoying a significant market share" and said the fines would have been higher if the price- fixing attempts had succeeded.
"It is only to be expected that the making of orders as to penalty will be attended with considerable and unwelcome publicity for Flight Centre. It is unlikely to wish to repeat that experience in the future," Justice Logan wrote.
Flight Centre plans to appeal the decision and said yesterday it may also appeal the penalties for its attempted collusion with Singapore Airlines, Malaysia Airlines and Emirates.
Mr Turner (pictured) described the ruling as "disappointing" but said it "has not created a need for fundamental changes within our business".
He said the fine, which must be paid within 45 days, would be partially offset by an unrelated one-off gain and Flight Centre still expected pre-tax profit to swell by at least 8 per cent this year.
The Australian Competition and Consumer Commission, which sued Flight Centre in early 2012 over the alleged breaches, welcomed the ruling.
But ACCC chairman Rod Sims said it was "disappointing" that Justice Logan had rejected a submission that the maximum penalty for each of four breaches was 10 per cent of Flight Centre's turnover rather than $10 million.
The case has been widely seen as the first significant test of new price-fixing laws that came into effect in 2010.
Cardboard manufacturer Visy was hit with a $36 million fine for price-collusion in 2007, while 15 airlines paid a record $98.5 million for price-fixing on fuel surcharges in 2012.
Flight Centre expects the court to hear the appeal in 2014/15 but will book the cost in the current financial year.Flight Centre shares lost 11¢ yesterday to close at $52.02. The stock has jumped almost 55 per cent in the past year.
]]></text></news-item>