<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-NXY1-JDN8-2424"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Earth hour</title><source>Daily Examiner (Grafton, New South Wales)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TODAY millions of people in more than 5000 cities across 130 countries and territories will switch off their non-essential lights. For one hour, from 8.30-9.30pm local time, people around the world will offer a symbol of their commitment to the planet to show that hope can spring from the darkness.
The Eiffel Tower will be blacked out as will the Empire State Building, Las Vegas, the Pyramids of Giza, the Petronas Towers in Malaysia and even the International Space Station as people power gets a chance to shine.
It is difficult, despite the naysayers, to ignore the effect climate change is having on our world. The planet is battling with the demands of an ever growing population and the gluttony of commercialisation and while the need for food and water grows so does the drive for natural resources.
Earth Hour, which started in Sydney in 2007, shows that people across the world recognise the plight of our planet and there is a willingness to make a change. Some people dismiss the enterprise as a publicity-seeking exercise saying it has no effect in the long run, but organisers are adamant change starts in small increments.
"People from all walks of life, from all nations around the world, are the lifeblood of the Earth Hour interconnected global community," said Earth Hour CEO and co-founder Andy Riley.
"They have proven time and time again that if you believe in something strongly enough, you can achieve amazing things. These stories aren't unique, this is happening all over the world."
There is little doubt we are failing to live in a sustainable fashion and Earth Hour gives individuals a chance to demand change from government and big business.
To date those 60 minutes have been successful in trying to combat deforestation in Uganda by planting 500,000 trees during the first Earth Hour Forest.
In Russia a long-awaited law to protect the country's seas from oil pollution was passed after hundreds of thousands of citizens protested during Earth Hour and in Argentina grass-roots action during that hour resulted in 3.4 million hectares of sea being protected, raising the level of protection of that country's seas from 1% to more than 4%.
This year all eyes are on the Great Barrier Reef, with a new report showing the natural wonder will suffer irreversible damage by 2030 if steps are not taken immediately to reduce carbon emissions.
Warming waters weakens the reef as the coral are unable to reproduce, are more susceptible to disease and die off.
At the current rate of global warming summer maximum temperatures will increase by 4C, making it impossible for the coral and reef to survive.
In June Unesco will decide whether to put the Barrier Reef on its endangered list with conservationists adamant it is under threat from climate change, development, dredging and pollution.
More information at www.earthour.org.au.
]]></text></news-item>