<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-FM31-DYJJ-P2H1"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Israel boycott rejected at U-M</title><source>The Detroit News (Michigan)</source><author>By, Detroit News staff and wire reports</author><text><![CDATA[Ann Arbor - The University of Michigan student government rejected a proposal Wednesday calling for an anti-Israel boycott following hours of debate and a weeklong sit-in by students.
The 25-9 vote came after more than five hours of debate and discussion at a meeting that began Tuesday night.
The proposal before Central Student Government had been tabled without action last week, leading boycott supporters to stage a sit-in at the government's offices in the Michigan Union. With the meeting, the sit-in ended.
In a statement Wednesday, university officials urged restraint and mutual respect, saying some students felt subjected to a backlash after speaking up.
"A core value of the University of Michigan is respect for diverse ideas and viewpoints. Intolerance has no place at Michigan," said the statement, released by E. Royster Harper, vice president for student life, and Laura Blake Jones, dean of students. "However, individual behaviors can fall short of our common expectation."
The statement continued: "Because of the strong feelings on all sides of this issue, some students have told us they feel targeted for their religious or cultural identities or for their involvement in this issue ... Today we call on every member of that community to recommit to this effort to ensure that our university is a place for strong views and opposing viewpoints offered in a culture of mutual respect."
The resolution, backed by a group called Students Allied for Freedom and Equality and using the hashtag #UMDivest on Twitter, would have urged the university to sell holdings in companies that are accused of enabling Israeli human rights violations.
Student government representative Jacob Ruby called the resolution a one-sided attack on Israel disguised as a human rights resolution.
"Not only is this resolution regarding an issue that is only peripherally related to campus life, the issue is incredibly divisive and greatly contributes to animosity between groups on this campus," he said.
Advocates of the resolution argued that Israel's continued occupation of the West Bank oppresses Palestinians.
Sam Molnar, a student government representative in favor of the resolution, said the world's future depends on building a nonviolent movement to end human rights violations.
"I support #UMDivest out of a love for my four little cousins who live in an illegal settlement in the West Bank," he said.
Suha Najjar, a senior who was one of the original authors of the resolution, said while it wasn't the outcome members of SAFE wanted, she was happy their voices were not silenced. "I am upset. I am disappointed. But more so, I am very proud of what we've accomplished," she said.
]]></text></news-item>