<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-NXY1-JDN8-24GM"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Big payout as miner suffers spinal injury</title><source>The Daily Mercury and Rural Weekly (Mackay, Queensland)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Mark Sleeman
mark.sleeman@dailymercury.com.au
A FORMER mine truck driver who was 23 when she seriously injured her neck and back in a workplace accident has been awarded a payout of more than $1.4m.
Jodie Maree Martin, who is now studying in Townsville to be a school teacher, sued her former employer Golding Contractors Pty Ltd over the 2009 accident at Ensham Mine, near Emerald.
Her solicitor Craig Worsley, a partner at Taylors Solicitors in Mackay, said yesterday it was one of the largest payouts to a miner, with Ms Martin's young age having a bearing.
"I know of only one other comparable,'' he said.
"That was a motor vehicle accident where he (the plaintiff) happened to be a miner. He had quite extensive injuries to his arm.
"This (Ms Martin's) would be one of the highest awarded to someone who is a miner who has sustained a spinal injury."
The judgement, handed down by Justice David North in the Townsville Supreme Court, includes $700,000 for future economic loss, as well as $330,000 for past economic loss and $90,000 for pain and suffering.
The compensation for future economic loss takes into account what she would have earned in the mining industry, less an amount she hopes to earn as a teacher.
The court was also told the daily back pain Ms Martin suffers had previously made it difficult for her to work as a teacher's aide, so there were misgivings as to whether she would be able to work full-time as a teacher, should she qualify.
Golding's contract at Ensham Mine ended in 2010, but it was successfully argued that Ms Martin's trade qualifications meant she would have had no problem obtaining employment in the coal mining industry with another operator.
At the time of the accident, Ms Martin was reversing a large mining dump truck to manoeuvre it into a position where it could be loaded by a digger.
"I was still moving backwards when I felt a huge impact to the rear of the truck,'' she said in evidence.
"The force of the impact caused the whole of my back and neck to be firstly slammed into the back of the seat and then thrown forwards in the seat."
Among her injuries were disc prolapses causing severe cervical spine pain and headaches and lumbar spinal pain.
Mr Worsley said Ms Martin was relieved the court case was over. "It's been traumatic for her and her family. They've been dealing with this for five years."
]]></text></news-item>