<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-P4W1-DYR7-V1JW"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Brazil Analysts: Rousseff Reelection No Longer a Sure Thing</title><source>The Main Wire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Brazil President Dilma Rousseff's popularity is dropping: her government's approval rating has fallen to 36% from 43% in December, according to a CNI/Ibope poll released Thursday, and markets suddenly have begun to look on her reelection as less than a sure thing.
The market reaction to Rousseff's political troubles has been euphoric: after the poll was released Thursday, the dollar/real exchange rate fell 1.73% to 2.268, the strongest for the real since November 2013, while the stock market surged 3.5%.
David Fleischer, professor of political science at the University of Brasilia, told MNI analysts must wait for a poll of voting intentions, due next week, to see if the drop in popularity is translating into fewer votes, but Thursday's poll was "an ominous sign."
"She is still ahead right now, but this election may be competitive," Fleischer said.
Elections will be held October 5. If no candidate wins more than 50% of the valid votes, a second round will be held October 26.
Even though polls still show Rousseff a lead of more than 20 points over her two main opponents, Aecio Neves from the center right PSDB party, and Eduardo Campos from the center left PSB, Fleischer said more bad news may be coming for Rousseff.
"If we have a electricity blackouts in May and June, it will be horrible for her, and if we have another wave of violent protests in June, her approval will go below 30," he said.
An ongoing drought is threatening to cause shortages in Brazil's predominantly hydro-electric power grid, and the World Cup in June may cause a redux of last year's demonstrations, sparked by criticism of the amount of money spent on the World Cup instead of on transportation and other public services.
The opposition also has opened a congressional inquiry into allegations of corruption at Petrobras, the state petroleum company run by Rousseff's proteges.
Fleischer said the campaign still has not really begun, as Neves and Campos have not begun advertising and have little name recognition, but it is already clear that Rousseff will have a harder time this year than in 2010, when she rode the wave of popularity of outgoing President Luiz Inacio "Lula" da Silva and an economy growing at a 7.5% pace. But that was before the global crisis hit Brazil.
Rafael Cortez, political analyst with the Sao Paulo consultancy Tendencias, told MNI the widespread dissatisfaction with the current administration has not yet translated into support for an opposition candidate, but that could soon change.
Cortez noted that Rousseff at the start of her term staked her legacy on economic growth and implemented ambitious, heterodox changes in macroeconomic policy and regulations, but she has failed to deliver.
This year the economy may struggle to grow 2% while inflation exceeds 6%, and even though unemployment is at historic lows while interest rates continue to rise, polls show Brazilians are expressing anxiety about their economic future.
"It is a very difficult scenario for Rousseff. If an opposition candidate runs a strong campaign, he could win," Cortez said.
Cortez said the market is probably right to prefer a victory of either Aecio Neves, whose political base is in the business community, or Eduardo Campos, a former ally of ex-President Lula, Rousseff's political mentor.
Cortez said both appear to be more pragmatic than Rousseff and will have political incentives to reverse some of her policies, such as her antagonistic relationship with the market, her use of state-owned companies to further government policies, and her sudden modifications of regulatory environments without consulting business.
Gabriel Gersztein, head of Latam FX and IR strategy at BNP Paribas in Sao Paulo, told MNI the political news was important for the markets, but it also "accelerated a movement that had already been happening for several days."
With local players holding large positions short the real, any positive sign for Brazil was enough to trigger stop loss orders and major movement in an overcrowded trade, he said.
"The poll helped, but it was not the only factor," he said, citing S&P's recent indication it would keep Brazil at investment grade for now despite the ratings cut, and capital inflows that were "nothing extraordinary, but better than the market had expected."
Gersztein said the real could strengthen further in the near time, since "right now the carry trade here is the best in the world," but later this year the currency should weaken as monetary policy normalizes in the U.S. and since Rousseff is still favored to win reelection.
** MNI - Sao Paulo **
]]></text></news-item>