<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVD-VJ81-JB1X-W15P"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>All stakeholders to be consulted for new textile policy, NA told</title><source>The Financial Daily</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The National Assembly was informed Thursday that various short and medium term schemes have been introduced for the promotion of textile industry.
Minister for Textile Industry Abbas Khan Afridi told the House during question hour that the government will initiate consultations with the stakeholders to formulate textile policy 2014-19.
He said Karachi Garment City project is also being implemented as part of efforts to boost up textiles exports.
Commerce Minister Khurram Dastgir Khan told the House that the government is working with the business community to give a quantum jump to exports by improving the standard and quality of different products.
Minister for Inter-Provincial Coordination Riaz Hussain Pirzada said facilities are being developed for the promotion of different sports including Hockey, Cricket and Squash. He said a sports village is being set up in Islamabad with the cooperation of Australia.
Commerce Minister Khurram Dastgir said the government desires to normalize trade relations with India and use land as well as sea routes for the purpose.
He said intensive consultations have been held with domestic stakeholders from both public and private sectors to protect the local industry in case of imports surge from India.
Most of the concerns would be addressed by including these industries' products in the sensitive list.
Meanwhile, Responding to a call attention notice, Minister of State for Information Technology Anusha Rehman said that the latest equipment has been installed to check grey trafficking.
She said Pakistan Telecommunication Authority in cooperation with Federal Investigation Agency (FIA) has conducted raids against those involved in the illegal activity and confiscated 391 illegal gateways.
She said SIMs involved in grey trafficking have also been blocked.
]]></text></news-item>