<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-CFH1-JC85-N2HW"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Concerns on bribery case send Alstom shares lower; French firm disputes report that it faces major fine to settle U.S. inquiry</title><source>International New York Times</source><author>DAVID JOLLY</author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
Shares of Alstom, a French industrial conglomerate, fell nearly 5 percent in Paris trading on Thursday after a news report that the company was facing a large fine in the United States to settle a corruption case.
But the company disputed the report's characterization of the Department of Justice investigation and the contention that a large fine was ''likely.''
Discussions with the Justice Department ''have not evolved to the point of negotiating a potential resolution of any claims,'' the company said in a statement from one of its Washington lawyers. ''Any effort to estimate the size of any possible fine is sheer speculation, as would be any comparison with other cases that have recently been resolved.''
Peter Carr, a Justice Department spokesman in Washington, declined to comment. Two people close to the Justice Department investigation confirmed that it was continuing, but they declined to comment on the report, by Bloomberg News.
Bloomberg said court documents showed that Alstom had ''hindered the U.S. investigation of possible bribery in Indonesia.''
As previously reported by news organizations, the Justice Department has brought criminal cases against several Alstom employees in the Indonesian case, including a former executive at Alstom's Connecticut subsidiary. According to prosecutors, the employees bribed a member of the Indonesian Parliament and high-ranking members of Perusahaan Listrik Negara, Indonesia's state-owned electricity company, in exchange for help in securing a $118 million contract for an electricity project.
Alstom, which based in Levallois-Perret, near Paris, competes in many of the same markets as Siemens, the German industrial giant. Siemens agreed in 2008 to pay about $1.6 billion to the United States and European authorities to settle charges that it had used corrupt means to win contracts. Siemens paid $450 million to the Justice Department and $350 million to the Securities and Exchange Commission, one of the largest such penalties ever paid by an industrial company in the United States.
The statement Thursday from Alstom was attributed to Robert Luskin, a lawyer for the company at the Washington law firm of Patton Boggs. ''Alstom is cooperating closely, actively and in good faith with the D.O.J. investigation,'' the statement said, in part. ''In the course of our regular consultations, the D.O.J. has not identified any ongoing shortcomings with the scope, level or sincerity of the company's effort.''
Christine Rahard, an Alstom spokeswoman, declined to comment further.
Alstom noted in the registration document for its 2012-13 annual report that it was ''subject to procedures for alleged anti-competitive practices,'' and noted that it was being investigated in the United States, France and Britain ''with respect to alleged illegal payments.''
]]></text></news-item>