<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-WKT1-JDJN-64GG"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Lawyers adapt to a Competition Bureau that's willing to flex its muscles</title><source>Legal Monitor Worldwide</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Lawyers say they have seen a major change in enforcement at Canada's Competition Bureau under Commissioner John Pecman. Mr. Pecman, who was appointed in June 2013 after 10 months as interim commissioner following the resignation of Melanie Aitken, has resurrected the s. 11 subpoena powers of the Competition Act. That means when investigating a conspiracy, price fixing or misleading advertising case the Bureau can compel a person to be examined under oath or produce documents and records.
"It's an old school kind of enforcement," says Paul Collins, head of the competition and foreign investment group at Stikeman Elliott LLP, who is ranked as a Band 1 practitioner for competition and antitrust law in Chambers Global 2014. Lawson Hunter, another Stikeman lawyer and a former competition commissioner, receives Chambers' highest accolade, the rank of "senior statesman." Mr. Hunter says the s. 11 power was historically a "very common investigatory tool" that fell into disuse in the early 1990s. Its return, he says, is being met with mixed emotions. Mr. Lawson says it's a "powerful tool" that aids in getting at information. "From a private sector point of view, it adds cost and time." Mr. Pecman, an economist, is the first non-lawyer to head the Bureau, after spending 29 years holding various positions within the Bureau. Lawyers say appointing someone from within the Bureau, rather than reaching into the justice department or private bar, as has been the practice, has boosted morale. As with any regime change, cultures shift. Mr. Hunter says Mr. Pecman "is willing to be more flexible or creative in how to resolve things on the merger side." Cal Goldman, co-head of the competition, antitrust and foreign investment group at Goodmans LLP and a Band 1-ranked practitioner, says that Mr. Pecman "is very much focused on making sure that any and all decisions made by the commissioners office are fully and properly formed." The shift to greater s. 11 use doesn't surprise him. Mr. Pecman, he says, has "a tremendous degree of enforcement experience," and "has seen the repercussions ... that occur when decisions aren't fully and properly formed." Knowing the nuances about regulators and being able to spot trends and marshal major deals through the intricacies of Canada's investment review and competition regimes is critical to law firms and the clients that hire them. It's a practice area that continues to grow in importance. Brian Facey, chair of Blake, Cassels & Graydon LLP's competition, antitrust and foreign investment group and a Band 1 ranked practitioner, says competition law is becoming increasingly global in nature.
There are more than 100 competition regimes around the world. "Pretty much every country has a competition regime" and regulators are increasingly co-ordinating their efforts, Mr. Facey says. That's creating a virtual network among law firms around the world as they co-ordinate client activities abroad. "I see that trend continuing and increasing." In Canada, Mr. Facey says there are a number of competition issues emerging. One is the increasing interface between regulators dealing with competition-related issues. For example, when Maple Group sought to buy TMX, the Bureau and the Ontario Securities Commission were heavily involved. The Bell-Astral merger involved the Bureau and the CRTC. Mr. Facey says that Mr. Pecman is "becoming an advocate for competition in the regulated world" and working with other regulators to help them understand these issues. In terms of mergers, lawyers say regulators are also flexing their muscles more. Oliver Borgers, a McCarthy Tétrault LLP partner who is ranked as a Band 1 practitioner for his knowledge of Canada's investment review regime, says the government "has made it clear they are going to look very carefully at commercial motives and underpinnings of SOE [state-owned enterprise] investors." As well, deals touching on assets involving national security will also be highly scrutinized. It's an "opaque process," he says. "When it comes to national security, a lot of what is relevant is not known to the public or advisors who don't have security clearance. [Companies] need to think about potential issues and pitfalls ahead of time." Lawyers say that recent court rulings are also changing Canada's competition landscape. Richard Annan, a Band 3 ranked practitioner who is co-head of the competition group at Goodmans LLP, notes the Supreme Court of Canada has ruled Canadians can sue someone from a price-fixing cartel outside of Canada for indirect purchases. That sets Canada apart from the U.S. and will "open the pathway for more class action lawsuits," he says. Adam Fanaki, a Band 2 ranked practitioner in the competition and foreign investment review practice at Davies Ward Phillips & Vineberg LLP, says the Supreme Court will soon hear a contested merger case - a rarity in Canada. The deal involved only $6-million and had already closed, showing that the Bureau is willing to challenge mergers of any size and reminding businesses that it can also seek to dissolve a deal after the fact. Mr. Fanaki says everyone is also watching how the federal government plans to tackle concerns about the price gap in goods sold in Canada versus the U.S. The federal budget suggested the government will do this using competition law. "There's a concern among competition law purists that it's not really an area that's appropriate for competition law enforcement," Mr. Fanaki.
In its annual review of Canadian law firms, influential legal publisher Chambers and Partners, acknowledges nine firms for their competition strengths. Band 1 Blake, Cassels & Graydon LLP Davies Ward Phillips & Vineberg LLP Band 2 Osler, Hoskin & Harcourt LLP Stikeman Elliott LLP Band 3 Bennett Jones LLP McCarthy Tétrault LLP McMillan LLP Torys LLP Band 4 Fasken Martineau LLP Norton Rose Fulbright © 2014 Legal Monitor Worldwide.
]]></text></news-item>