<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-DW91-JCBF-S2Y6"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>MISSOURI LEGISLATORS HOLD SECOND HEARING ON COAL ASH WASTE RESOLUTION COAL ASH DISASTERS ACROSS THE COUNTRY SPARK FEARS FOR MISSOURI RESIDENTS ABOUT TOXIC COAL ASH DISPOSAL</title><source>States News Service</source><author>States News Service</author><text><![CDATA[The following information was released by the Sierra Club:
Today, the Tourism and Natural Resources Committee of the Missouri House of Representatives held its second hearing on HCR 28, a resolution on disposal of toxic coal ash waste produced by coal-fired power plants across the state of Missouri.
The resolution urges the Missouri Department of Natural Resources (DNR) to require groundwater monitoring immediately at all new and existing coal ash ponds in Missouri, and require cleanup at all coal ash ponds found to be leaking toxic chemicals.
Coal ash is full of heavy metals, like mercury, lead and arsenic, which can cause cancer and brain damage in humans and are harmful to fish and wildlife.
Unlike neighboring states like Illinois, Missouri does not require groundwater monitoring near coal ash ponds, many of which have leaked toxic chemicals for decades.
"People deserve clean drinking water. Missourians living near coal ash dump sites are more than justified in receiving that assurance," said Rep. Jeanne Kirkton of Webster Groves, a sponsor of HCR 28. "This year's major coal ash spill in North Carolina taught us that inaction can lead to disaster. We can't let that happen in Missouri."
This is the second in a series of hearings on coal ash after the major coal ash spill in North Carolina, which left local drinking water at risk from nearly 82,000 tons of toxic coal ash dumped into the Dan River.
Missouri's lax approach to coal ash disposal presents risks for communities across Missouri. In eastern Missouri, Ameren is attempting to build dangerous coal ash landfills on top of already leaking coal ash ponds.
"We've got a severe coal ash waste problem here in the state of Missouri," said John Hickey, Chapter Director of the Missouri Sierra Club. "Across the river in Illinois, polluters are held accountable for the toxic waste they place near groundwater. We're simply asking for the same protections in our state."
In Labadie, where utility company Ameren has done preliminary testing around a proposed coal ash landfill site, arsenic has been detected at six times the federal drinking water standard. The resolution language also acknowledges the DNR is aware that the coal ash pond at the Labadie coal plant is known to leak 50,000 gallons of toxic metal-laden water daily since 1992.
Next week, the Missouri Public Service Commission (PSC) will hold a series of hearings in Jefferson City on Ameren's controversial proposed coal ash landfill.
"The dangers of coal ash in Missouri are finally being recognized by our state leaders," said Patricia Schuba, President of the Labadie Environmental Organization. "Polluters aren't going to take the initiative to clean up on their own. We need action from Missouri's leaders to protect our water."
Elsewhere in the state, KCPandL in Kansas City sends coal ash to an abandoned mine for underground pumping. City Utilities in Springfield used Missouri legislation to avoid an environmental review process of potential coal ash waste disposal sites.
Last month, the Sierra Club and the Labadie Environmental Organization delivered a letter to Governor Jay Nixon urging a halt to the permitting of all proposed coal ash dumps in Missouri until the state conducts a thorough investigation of groundwater impacts.
]]></text></news-item>