<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-HYV1-F125-11GB"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Kinder Morgan: The long road to earning the public's trust over pipelines</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Gordon Hoekstra
Vancouver Sun
British Columbians have been skeptical of major pipeline proposals such as Enbridge's $6.5-billion Northern Gateway project and Kinder Morgan's $5.4-billion expansion of its Trans Mountain system. Kinder Morgan has set about to earn the public trust and influence attitudes toward its pipeline with its president in Canada, Ian Anderson, leading the charge. The Vancouver Sun talked with Anderson.
Q There is a considerable amount of resistance to more pipelines in B.C., particularly the increased tanker traffic it will bring. Your project will bring about another 350 tankers into the Salish Sea and Burrard Inlet. How do you convince the public you should be allowed to build it?
A There is a process to go through that will involve lots of study, research, evidence and so forth that will be publicly examined. But beyond that we know we don't just need the permits, we need the permission. So, to get the permission we are spending a lot of time making sure we understand what the issues and concerns are. Some of them are founded in fear, some of them are founded in, I think, that people view that risks can't be managed. And our view would be that ships have been sailing in these waters for decades without incident and we think that the safety regime around them is such that we'll be able to operate safely into the future.
Q I understand you've spent a considerable amount of time talking to people on the ground - I think that people say that's a different approach. Why are you doing it that way?
A It's just the way that I believe, and my company believes, business should be done. We should spend time talking to the people, talking to the parties that are affected by something. So, right from Day 1, regardless of what others were doing, or what other companies' approaches were, we charted a course that would be grassroots, that would be local.
Q Can you give an example of that?
A I think over the course of the last 18 months, personally, I've had in excess of 200 or 250 meetings. That can be with individuals, it might be a business operator, it might be a land owner, it might be a farmer whose land we cross. It might be a special interest group that has concerns about the watershed. It might be with salmon foundations or stream keepers. It could be with First Nations' chiefs and their council and their community. I was meeting with a group of accountants in Victoria last week. I'm meeting with a group of biologists the week after next in Victoria.
Q How much of your time do you spend doing that?
A I'm on the road every week. I'm in Vancouver every week. I am in the Interior, whether that's Kamloops, Merritt, Hope, North Thompson Valley, every couple of weeks. A First Nations group, chief, community, it might be every other week. I made the choice to make this somewhat personal - I think people appreciate a personal face, a personal approach to the issues. And we've tried to build the trust and confidence along with the personal approach.
Q Is your approach working?
A I think it is. I think if nothing else, the public appreciate our openness and honesty about the issues. We don't shy away from what an issue is. We don't pretend to say: nothing can ever happen, don't worry. So, we try to be realistic. We are diligent and we are patient and we have thick skins, and we are just trying to continue to convince British Columbians that we can do this safely.
Q The public also has concerns about pipeline spills, for example, in light of the Burnaby spill in 2007. How do you convince them that tripling your capacity is a good idea?
A One of the first things we do is we are very transparent about our historical operating record - what has happened on that pipeline over the course of the last 60 years. What incidents had occurred, what caused them, what did we learn from them and what has changed. We are very, I think, open about consequences. When you talk about risk, you are talking probability and consequence. So, the probability of a major incident is very, very low. The incident we had in Burnaby when a third-party excavator hit the line was a terrible event. I was here. It was a beautiful day. It was a horrific sight. But we repaired that community. We put it back together. We didn't point fingers, we didn't lay blame, we didn't talk about liability or responsibility. We fixed it. And that's the reputation we have.
Q In British Columbia, people also have concerns about increases in greenhouse gas emissions from the Alberta oilsands. What do you say to people you are trying to build support with about that, how do you tackle this global concern?
A The pipeline brings all of those concerns, issues and observations to the forefront. Some of them in my control, and some not. We are not controlling emissions and water use and so forth. But we have used, I think, as much as anybody can, the profile of the pipeline to influence as much as we can both upstream and downstream. So we are hugely active with all players on the marine side. Upstream, similarly, I'm talking to (oil) producers all the time about what we are hearing on the ground: their image, their investments in new technology, about changes they need to be thinking about longer term in order to increase their public-permission profile if you like. So, we are not shying away from any of those conversations.
Q Your $5.4-billion Trans Mountain expansion will triple capacity. Why do you want to build this pipeline?
A It's about market demand. It's about producers looking for more markets for the products they have to sell. So, it's about responding to growing production needing to access markets, and that's what we are in the business to do. We have long-term commitments from 13 customers to do that for the next 20 years, and the pipeline is the missing piece right now.
Q Is that market Asia? Some people have suggested that if Kinder Morgan is going to expand the pipeline, do that across Sumas to U.S. and then an increase in tankers is not needed.
A Asia is where the producers want to get, too, mindful of the fact that today, 80 per cent of the tankers that leave Burnaby end up in California. So, that's still a market that producers will continue to want to get to simply because Alaska North Slope crude continues to be in decline. But the growing market, however, is China.
Q People in Alberta appear confident that pipeline projects benefit them economically. That's not necessarily the case in British Columbia. How do you convince people here there are benefits for this province and what are they?
A The whole economics behind fossil fuels are kind of viewed to be an Alberta thing, a Canadian thing beyond that. So, what we try to do is a couple of things: make sure the national and provincial picture around benefits are clear. But then we work hard to translate that locally. Municipally, we'll double the property taxes we pay - $23 million a year to north of $40 million a year to municipalities in British Columbia. While the project doesn't bring a large number of permanent jobs - there's probably 40 or 50 in British Columbia long term - it will bring lots of contracting opportunities for the project. We are going to spend roughly two-thirds of that $5.4 billion in British Columbia.
Q Aside from the few jobs and increased taxes, are there other ways the company might help communities?
A Most definitely. Whatever is important to the community. And I don't pretend to judge what is and isn't.
© Copyright (c) The Vancouver Sun
]]></text></news-item>