<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-4RW1-F143-42K9"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>&gt;&gt;&gt;ANSA/ Trial requested for ex-Vatican Bank executives; Case against former chief Gotti Tedeschi dropped</title><source>ANSA English Media Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[(ANSA) - March 28 - Rome prosecutors on Friday requested that the former general manager of the Vatican Bank, Paolo Cipriani, be sent to trial for allegedly breaking Italy's laws against money laundering.
They also requested Cipriani's former deputy, Massimo Tulli, be indicted.
The case is related to a probe that in 2010 led to the freezing of 23 million euros over two cash transfers involving the bank that were deemed suspicious.
Earlier on Friday a Rome judge upheld a request from prosecutors for a probe into the former head of the Vatican Bank, Ettore Gotti Tedeschi, over the same case to be shelved.
Gotti Tedeschi resigned from the bank in May 2012 following a no-confidence vote by the supervisory board, amid reported disagreements on efforts to get the Vatican on the white list of financially transparent countries.
The trial requests are fresh blows to the image of the bank, whose official name is the Institute for Works of Religion (IOR), after a series of scandals over the years.
Italian banks effectively stopped dealing with the IOR in 2010 after the Bank of Italy ordered them to enforce strict anti-money-laundering criteria to continue working with it.
From January 1 to February 12 last year the Bank of Italy froze all credit-card and ATM transactions inside the Vatican City over its failure to fully implement international anti-money-laundering standards.
The Vatican has made several reforms to introduce greater financial transparency and fight money laundering since Pope Francis was elected to the helm of the Catholic Church last year.
In June Francis nominated a pontifical commission to make proposals on the future of the bank and he has even openly expressed the possibility of abolishing it.
In December the Council of Europe's Moneyval agency, a monitoring group of financial experts, praised the Vatican's progress, as it seeks to get on the list of countries with strong credentials on combatting financial crime.
But it also stressed that more work needed to be done.
In January the Vatican Bank said it was ready to resume normal relations with Italy after making progress in measures to prevent money laundering and other financial crimes.
There have been many allegations that the IOR was used to launder money, most notably by 'God's Banker' Roberto Calvi, the former head of Italy's biggest private bank, whose body was found hanging under Blackfriar's Bridge in London in 1982, a suspected victim of the Sicilian mafia.
The IOR was also named in kickbacks probes stemming from the 1990 collapse of public-private chemicals colossus Enimont, part of the Clean Hands investigations that swept away Italy's old political establishment.
In recent years there have been a series of Italian TV reports and a best-selling book claiming to show how individuals used the IOR to squirrel away money, dodging Italian regulations.
]]></text></news-item>