<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-XKM1-JC92-P0T8"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Daily Headline News for March 28, 2014</title><source>Russia &amp; CIS General Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Digest of headline news as of 7:00 p.m. Moscow time on March 28:
BUSINESS & FINANCE
*** ULYUKAYEV: REASONABLE TO INCREASE 2014 BUDGET DEFICIT BY 1% OF GDP TO COMPENSATE FOR CAPITAL OUTFLOW
Increasing the 2014 federal budget deficit by around 1% of GDP would be reasonable in order to compensate for large capital outflow, Economic Development Minister Alexei Ulyukayev said at an interactive seminar with state authorities.
He said it was important to include a procedure to support the budget's independence from capital outflow. "If capital outflow is very large, like it was this year, then [we] must compensate. The way I see it, an additional 1 percentage point of GDP of the budget deficit would be a mechanism that compensates for capital outflow figures that exist this year," Ulyukayev said.
*** ECON MINISTRY AGREES WITH WORLD BANK ON RUSSIAN ECONOMY CONTRACTING 1.8% IF CAPITAL OUTFLOW IS $150 BLN - ULYUKAYEV
Russia's Economic Development Ministry is in agreement with the World Bank forecast that if capital outflow from Russia is more than $150 billion this year Russia's GDP will contract 1.8%, Economic Development Minister Alexei Ulyukayev said during an interactive seminar with state authorities.
"If outflow goes past $150 billion [this year], we will have negative growth. We will have around minus 8% investment and minus 1.8% economic growth," he said.
*** RUSSIA, N. KOREA TO SWITCH TO RUBLE PAYMENTS - MINISTRY
Russian Minister of Far East Development Aleksandr Galushka and North Korean Foreign Trade Minister Ri Ryong Nam signed a protocol for development of bilateral cooperation in Pyongyang, the Russian Ministry of Far East Development said in a press release.
"The parties deemed it expedient to bring their mutual trade to a totally new level with an increase of up to $1 billion (per year) by 2020, by facilitating the transition to mutual payments in rubles and the resolution of inter-banking interaction problems," the press release said.
*** NO ALTERNATIVE TO RUSSIAN GAS IMPORTS - GERMAN MINISTER
There is no reasonable alternative to European imports of Russian natural gas, said German Vice-Chancellor, Economic Minister Sigmar Gabriel.
An erroneous thesis of "the availability of numerous energy supply options" is being suggested in the debate on the possible independence of Europe from Russian oil and gas, but this is not so, the Deutsche Welle radio cited Gabriel as saying at an energy forum on Friday.
The vice-chancellor said Europe should not stir up panic or fear the possible termination of supplies from Russia.
*** NOVATEK OPTIMISTIC ABOUT PROSPECTS FOR YAMAL LNG ON KOREAN MARKET
The head of the management board at Russia's independent gas producer Novatek (MOEX: NVTK), Leonid Mikhelson, has said he sees promise in dialog with Korean liquefied natural gas importers.
"I had a meeting with the Kogas President [this week] and he spoke about the company's strategy as regards this matter. Their position is that working with one or two suppliers is wrong," Mikhelson said on the sidelines of the Gastech 2014 conference in Seoul. "They want to build up and diversify their portfolio of long-term contracts and bring in different manufacturers from various regions. We have been informed Korea's energy strategy is currently being revised. The country intends to increase consumption of gas which means we have a topic for discussion," he said.
*** TOTAL WILL CONTINUE TO BUY NOVATEK SHARES - MIKHELSON
The French energy company Total will continue to buy stock in Russia's independent gas producer Novatek (MOEX: NVTK) after the first of next month, a timeframe set by the partners earlier for Total to increase its stock interest in Novatek to 19.4%
Total became a Novatek shareholder in April of 2011, when it bought 12.09% of the company's shares. The agreement between the two companies involved the French company increasing its stake to 19.4% before April 1 this year.
*** NOVATEK CHIEF SEES NO RISKS FOR CO. AND YAMAL LNG FROM U.S. SANCTIONS VS. TIMCHENKO
The head of independent gas producer Novatek (MOEX: NVTK), Leonid Mikhelson, has said he does not see any risks for the company emerging from the imposition of sanctions on company stockholder Gennady Timchenko by the United States.
"I don't see any potential risks to our company in connection with this situation. There have been too much PR activity on this subject and that's why the market is now facing investor uncertainty, which has led to the high volatility of the market. I think this is temporary," Mikhelson said during an interview with several news agencies in response to an Interfax question.
*** NOVATEK WON'T EXCEED BUYBACK ALLOCATION TO AVOID REDUCING SHARE LIQUIDITY - MIKHELSON
Novatek (MOEX: NVTK) has so far spent only a fraction of the total allocation for its ongoing buyback program, but it will not risk a reduction in share liquidity by exceeding that amount, Novatek chief Leonid Mikheslon told journalists.
"As you know, our company has started a buyback program. I'm buying shares myself and I'm glad there are new investors, who buy shares at current prices and see prospects for capitalization growth for Novatek," Mikhelson said.
*** GAZPROM MULLS JOINING PROJECT TO BUILD POWER PLANT IN TURKEY
Gazprom (MOEX: GAZP) is discussing the possibility of buying the 890-MW Eurostar combined cycle power plant that is being built in Turkey, a source familiar with the progress of the negotiations told Interfax.
The seller - the MetCap group is being represented in the deal by Raiffeisen Zentralbank. It is offering to sell 100% of the special purpose vehicle Verbena Enerji Sanayii ve Ticaret A.S.
For the buyer, payment for joining the project will be compensation for historical costs - several tens of millions of euros - and subsequent independent financing of the project, which amounts to more than half a billion euros.
*** RUSAL EBITDA FALLS 29% TO $651 MLN IN 2013
Russian aluminum company UC Rusal saw its adjusted earnings before taxes, depreciation and amortization (EBITDA) decline 28.9% to $651 million in 2013, the company said in a financial statement.
Analysts polled by Interfax had put the company's 2013 EBITDA at $745.5 million, an 18.5% decline. Goldman Sachs provided the most accurate forecast of $646.6 million.
EBITDA in the fourth quarter fell 54.3% to $101 million from the previous quarter's $221 million. According to the consensus forecast, EBITDA was expected to fall in Q4 by 52% to $105.7 million.
*** FIRST TRANCHE OF IMF LOAN FOR UKRAINE COULD TOTAL AROUND $3 BLN - MINFIN
The International Monetary Fund (IMF) could begin carrying out its $14-18 billion stand-by agreement with Ukraine by issuing the first $3 billion tranche of the loan, Ukrainian Finance Minister Alexander Shlapak told journalists in Kyiv on Friday following a governmental meeting.
"We have not yet come to a final agreement with the IMF. There was a promise in the draft. [...] They are now ready to talk about the first tranche for around $3 billion," he said.
The IMF's mission reached a working-level agreement on March 27 with Ukrainian leadership on opening a two-year credit of between $14 billion and $18 billion.
POLITICS & SOCIETY
*** PUTIN SUBMITS PROPOSAL TO TERMINATE RUSSIAN-UKRAINIAN AGREEMENTS ON BLACK SEA FLEET TO STATE DUMA
A proposal to terminate a number of Russian-Ukrainian agreements, in particular on the Black Sea Fleet, has been submitted to the Russian State Duma.
Russian President Vladimir Putin was the one to submit the proposal to terminate the agreements, the Kremlin posted.
Deputy Foreign Minister Grigory Karasin and Deputy Defense Minister Nikolai Pankov have been appointed official presidential representatives for considering the issue by chambers of the Federal Assembly.
*** EVENTS IN CRIMEA DEMONSTRATE RUSSIAN ARMY'S NEW CAPABILITIES - PUTIN
Russian President Vladimir Putin has said that the events in Crimea have demonstrated a high level of readiness of the Russian Armed Forces and he thanked the military service members stationed in the peninsula for their stamina and professionalism.
"The recent events in Crimea were a serious test. They demonstrated both the completely new capabilities of our Armed Forces and the high morale of the personnel," the president said at a ceremony introducing the top officers on the occasion of new appointments and rank awarding.
*** NEXT STAGE OF RUSSIAN ARMED FORCES DEVELOPMENT SHOULD INCLUDE GROUP IN ARCTIC - PUTIN
Next stage of the Russian Armed Forces training should include developing a combat group in the Arctic region, Russian President Vladimir Putin said.
"Next is the further development of the combat personnel of our armed forces, including in the Arctic region," Putin said on Friday at a ceremony introducing the top officers on the occasion of new appointments and awarding of ranks.
*** RUSSIAN FOREIGN MINISTRY SAYS RESTRICTIONS IMPOSED BY BERN ON BILATERAL TIES ARE "COUNTER-PRODUCTIVE"
Moscow has expressed regret over the position taken by Bern in response to the events in Ukraine and has described the latest restrictions imposed on Russian-Swiss bilateral cooperation as "unfounded".
"We express our regret over the unilateral position assumed by the government of Switzerland in relation to the events in Ukraine that ignores the realities and the explanations given by the Russian side more than once," the Russian Foreign Ministry said in a commentary on Friday.
"We consider the restrictions imposed by Bern on a number of spheres of bilateral cooperation unfounded and counter-productive," it said.
*** MOSCOW POINTS OUT TO OBAMA THAT NO INDEPENDENCE REFERENDUM WAS HELD IN KOSOVO
The Russian Foreign Ministry is surprised by U.S. President Barack Obama's statement regarding an independence referendum in Kosovo.
"Moscow has taken note of the fact that U.S. President Barack Obama, in rationalizing 'independence' of Kosovo and Metohija (Serbia) declared in circumvention of UN Security Council resolution 1244 in his speech in Brussels on March 28, mentioned some referendum on this issue allegedly held in coordination with the UN and the neighboring countries," the Foreign Ministry said in a statement available on its website.
"This allegation by the U.S. president causes perplexity, as no plebiscite, not to mention one agreed upon with the international community, was held on Kosovo's independence. The decision on secession from Serbia was made by the so-called 'parliament' in Pristina in 2008," it said.
*** RUSSIA CRITICIZES U.S. STANCE ON MILITARY COURTS, TRIBUNALS
The Russian Foreign Ministry is deeply disappointed by the decision of the United States to vote against the Russian-proposed draft resolution of the United Nations Human Rights Council (UNHRC) titled "Judicial System Integrity" and points to Washington's active attempts to hinder the passage of the document.
"At its 25th session on March 27 the UN Human Rights Council passed the Judicial System Integrity resolution submitted by the Russian Federation on behalf of over twenty co-authors. As a result of the voting held at the request of the U.S. delegation, the document was backed by 27 nations, with 19 abstaining, including the European Union, and only the U.S. voted against it," the ministry said in a statement posted on its website.
*** MARGELOV: AFRICAN STATES OVERWHELMINGLY REJECT ANTI-RUSSIAN RESOLUTION AT UN
Special Representative of the Russian President for Cooperation with African States Mikhail Margelov has welcomed the refusal of most African states to back the UN General Assembly resolution on Ukraine.
Margelov recalled that 31 out of 47 African countries said "no".
"It is easy to imagine what pressure the West has put on these countries and what conditions have been set for their approval of the anti-Russian resolution. But the West failed to achieve unity and consolidation," Margelov, who is also the Chairman of the Federation Council International Affairs Committee, told Interfax.
*** MOSCOW TO HOST INTL SECURITY CONFERENCE IN MAY
A high-level international security conference will be held in Moscow in May.
Pursuant to the Russian government directive posted on the official legal information portal, the Russian Defense Ministry will set up the organizing committee and approve its members.
Deputy Defense Minister Anatoly Antonov has been appointed to the post of organizing committee chair. "The Russian Foreign Ministry shall issue visas in the established procedure at the request of the conference organizing committee without levying visa issue fees," the document runs.
*** RUSSIAN POPULATION GROWS BY 320,000 IN 2013 - TOPILIN
Russian population numbers rose by 320,000 in 2013, including through the net migration gain, Labor Minister Maksim Topilin said.
"The Russian population grew by 320,000 over the year. This indicator takes net migration into account," Topolin said at an expanded session of the Ministry's collegium on Friday, which focused on the 2013 results and 2014 plans.
In 2013, Russia registered a natural population increase - of almost 23,000 people - for the first time since 1991, the minister said.
*** SOYUZ SPACECRAFT WITH 3 CREWMEMBERS DOCKS WITH ISS
Russia's Soyuz TMA-12M spacecraft with three crewmembers onboard has docked with the Poisk multirole module of the International Space Station (ISS).
"The manned spacecraft has docked with the Poisk module of the ISS. All systems are operating normally," according to an announcement made at the Mission Control Center, located in the town of Korolyov outside of Moscow, an Interfax-AVN correspondent has reported.
*** UKRAINIAN PARLIAMENTARY COMMISSION TO PROBE SASHKO BILY'S DEATH
The Ukrainian parliament has created a provisional investigations commission to investigate the circumstances of the death of Right Sector coordinator Oleksandr Muzychko (nicknamed Sashko Bily).
A total of 232 of 279 parliamentarians voted for that decision.
The commission will be led by parliamentarian Yuriy Derevianko. The commission will be comprised of representatives of all factions and three representatives of public organizations.
*** DELEGATION OF U.S. DEPARTMENT OF STATE AND PENTAGON TO VISIT CHISINAU
U.S. Assistant Secretary of State for European and Eurasian Affairs Victoria Nuland will visit Moldova on Sunday, March 30.
A spokesman for the Moldovan Ministry of Foreign Affairs and European Integration told Interfax that during her trip, Nuland would be accompanied by Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense Evelyn Farkas and Director of the U.S. European Command Director of Strategy and Policy Maj. Gen. Randy Kee.
"This visit comes as a follow-up to the strategic dialogue between Moldova and the U.S. that was launched during a recent official visit to the U.S. by Moldovan Prime Minister Iurie Leanca," the spokesman said.
Of ar
]]></text></news-item>