<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-C9N1-JC13-D3JK"><date>2014-03-27</date><title>Settlements would add to cleanup of Fox | $56 million proposed for project</title><source>Milwaukee Journal Sentinel (Wisconsin)</source><author>LEE BERGQUIST, lbergquist@journalsentinel.com Milwaukee Journal Sentinel, Milwaukee Journal Sentinel (WI)</author><text><![CDATA[Six companies and two units of government in the Fox Valley on Wednesday proposed settlements totaling $56 million to pay for a portion of a massive cleanup of contaminated sediments in the Fox River in northeastern Wisconsin.
The settlements, which must still be approved by a federal judge, would settle claims against the eight parties in an expensive and longstanding legal dispute over financial responsibility for removing sediments tainted with toxic chemicals known as polychlorinated biphenyls.
The cost of the project - the largest cleanup of PCBs in the United States - is estimated at more than $1 billion. Work will begin for the 2014 construction season early next month, according to the Department of Natural Resources. PCBs had many uses in manufacturing, including the production of carbonless paper manufactured between 1954 and 1971. The chemicals, which can be found in the tissue of fish and can cause health problems in humans eating the fish, were discharged into the river and settled in the sediments of the Fox and Green Bay. Upstream, Little Lake Buttes des Morts also was affected.
Judge William C. Griesbach must still review the proposals.
The companies and government units said in federal court records that they had reached settlements with state and federal authorities and the Menominee and Oneida Indian tribes after months of negotiations with a mediator, U.S. Magistrate Aaron E. Goodstein.
Reaching settlements totaling $54 million were the City of Appleton, the Neenah- Menasha Sewerage Commission, CBC Coating Inc., Menasha Corp., U.S. Paper Mills Corp. and WTM 1, formerly known as Wisconsin Tissue Mills.
In separate court filings, Kimberly-Clark and New-Page Corp. indicated settlements of about $2 million. Wednesday's filing did not include two other companies that have already spent millions of dollars on the cleanup to date: NCR Corp and Glatfelter Co.
The latest settlements by the city and sewerage district and CBC Coating, Menasha Corp., U.S. Paper Mills and WTM 1 also don't include past payments of more than $130 million, according to J.P. Causey Jr., vice president of WTM 1. "This has been a big issue that we have been working on, and we've made a lot of progress," Causey said. "This is a step in the process."
Causey said if the judge approves the settlements, the companies and government units would be released from claims that they were partially responsible for polluting waters.
Beth J. Olson, who is overseeing the cleanup for the DNR, said work on the river should restart in the second week in April.
According to the EPA, an estimated 14 million cubic yards containing more than 51, 000 cubic yards of the PCBs were dumped in the river. An even larger volume of toxic waste lies in Green Bay and will not be removed, The EPA says several hundred million cubic yards of sediments and 154, 000 pounds of PCBs have floated into the bay.
The project is about 65% complete, Olson said, with 2.8 million of an estimated 4.3 million cubic yards of sediments of sediment now removed from the river.
The parties paying for the cleanup are expected to remove 675, 000 cubic yards of sediments this year, she said.
The plan is to complete the cleanup in 2017, according to Olson.
Copyright 2014, Journal Sentinel Inc. All rights reserved. (Note: This notice does not apply to those news items already copyrighted and received through wire services or other media.)
Copyright, 2014, Journal Sentinel, All Rights Reserved.
]]></text></news-item>