<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-91S1-DYTG-203H"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Rescuers fear the worst in Oso</title><source>Canberra Times (Australia)</source><author>Jonathan Kaminsky; in Darrington, Washington</author><text><![CDATA[Rescuers fear the worst in Oso By Jonathan Kaminsky in Darrington, Washington NO RESPITE: Rescuers cross floodwaters on Highway 530 as searching continues for survivors of the Oso mudlside. Few expect any to be found. Photo: Reuters 'It really doesn't hit you until the day's over. It's just take it day by day, chunk by chunk of debris.'
Search team member Rescuers searching for 90 people still missing five days after a massive Washington state mudslide said they expected the death toll to climb sharply soon, even as they clung to hope of finding a miracle survivor.
At least 25 people are known to have died when a rain-soaked hillside collapsed without warning on Saturday, unleashing a wall of mud that engulfed dozens of homes in a river valley near the rural town of Oso, about 90 kilometres north-east of Seattle.
Only the first 16 victims recovered and examined by coroners have so far been officially counted as dead, although district fire chief Travis Hots said that figure would soon rise. Nine bodies have been found since. "In the next 24 to 48 hours, as the medical examiner's office catches up with the difficult work ... you're going to see these numbers increase substantially," he said.
Snohomish County officials said that about 90 people remained missing or unaccounted for, down from an earlier estimate that was nearly twice that.
About 180 people lived in the path of the landslide.
Authorities have acknowledged there is little chance of finding any more survivors in the 2.5 square kilometre heap of mud-caked debris and muck left by the landslide, and that the remains of some victims may never be recovered.
Everyone discovered alive was rescued by helicopter within the first few hours. Rescuers have not found further signs of life, officials said.
"We're not changing the pace of this. And we're going to exhaust all options to try to find somebody alive," Mr Hots said. "If we find just one more person that's alive, to me, that's worth it."
As the days wore on, emotions were running raw.
Jessica Neal, 30, said she found comfort from Wednesday's recovery of the body of her father-in-law, Steve Neal, a water-heater installer who was working at a house hit by the slide, and in learning that he apparently did not suffer long.
Shayne Barco, 37, a search team member, said he had laboured to keep his emotions pushed to the side while he worked. "It really doesn't hit you until the day's over," he said. "It's just take it day by day, chunk by chunk of debris."
Many area residents have voiced a sense of anger that local officials refused to allow volunteers to join the frantic search for victims immediately after the slide, when chances for finding survivors were greatest.
State police spokesman Bob Calkins said conditions were simply too dangerous.
"We wish they could have helped, too," Mr Calkins said. "It would not have been safe, and we'd have had more victims."
Community members from Oso and nearby towns assembled late Wednesday to offer prayers for the missing. "We know, and most of us, I think, are accepting that many of our people are not going to make it," Megan Fanning, 41, said at the gathering in Darrington, not far from Oso. "But please, we need a miracle.
Just one. One little miracle would be wonderful."
The casualty count has pushed the Oso mudslide into the history books as one of the deadliest, said Josef Dufek, a professor at Georgia Institute of Technology who studies natural cataclysms.
The 1980 eruption of Mount St Helens in Washington killed 57 people, and a 1969 landslide in Nelson County, Virginia, killed 150.
Many valley residents have channeled their collective trauma into acts of comfort for the bereaved and support for searchers.
Stores in nearby Arlington posted hand-painted signs calling for solidarity and donations, Boy Scouts collected food outside a market, and a bowling league offered to donate tournament prize money towards relief efforts.
Injured survivors include a 22-week-old baby rescued with his mother. The baby was in critical condition but was improving. The mother and three other survivors remained hospitalised. Reuters
]]></text></news-item>