<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-WKT1-JDJN-64G6"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Chinese export quotas for rare earth metals violate world trade law</title><source>Legal Monitor Worldwide</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A World Trade Organization panel said that China has broken international trade law by restricting the export of rare earth elements and other metals opens the possibility that Beijing will face trade sanctions from the United States, which brought the case and the European Union and Japan.
The panel ruled against China's arguments on all counts. While it did not rule that nations may not impose quotas to protect scarce resources, it argued that once a commodity is extracted from the ground it should be treated in accordance with the global rules. China produces more than nine tenths of the global supply of the strategically important metals, which are essential to a host of modern applications including smartphones, wind turbines, industrial catalysts and high tech magnets. Prices soared in 2010 after Beijing cut export quotas by about 40%, to just over 30,000 tonnes saying the restrictions were necessary on environmental grounds. But critics said the quotas gave an unfair advantage to China's domestic manufacturing industries. Members of the WTO panel considering the case in Geneva agreed with that assessment. The United States, which is almost totally dependent on China for the metals, filed the case in March 2012 and the European Union and Japan joined on Washington's side soon after. They challenged the export restrictions on 17 rare earths, as well as two metals used in steel alloys, molybdenum and tungsten. An interim report by the WTO panel last October had indicated that China would be found in violation of trade law in the case. The dispute has attracted worldwide attention, as it has been framed by some as pitting a sovereign government's right to regulate destructive environmental practices against global trade rules. China has amply demonstrated the damage caused at each step of the production process, from mining and refining of the metals to disposal of the waste and Beijing has been shutting down some of the worst offending producers among them criminal enterprises. The soil in parts of China is scarred from the concentrated acids used to leach the ores, making farming impossible, while giant tailing ponds full of toxic and sometimes radioactive chemicals attest to the fact that the recovery of every pound of rare earth metals entails the creation of hundreds or thousands of pounds of waste. China had also argued that the export quotas were justified under an exception made where such steps relate to the conservation of exhaustible natural resources. But the complainants argued that the restrictions were inconsistent with China's obligations under the rules of the World Trade Organization, which it joined in 2001, because they were handled in a manner that is not uniform, impartial, reasonable, or transparent distorting the market in favor of China's domestic industry.
World trade rules do not prohibit export taxes. The agreement China signed with other countries when it joined the WTO allowed for only a limited number of such duties and did not include rare earths. Critics have argued that despite the claims of environmental damage, China was using its monopoly to create a cost advantage for companies operating within its borders; since the price was lower for domestic users, foreign companies also had an incentive to set up shop in China to be competitive, creating local jobs and transferring technology.© 2014 Legal Monitor Worldwide.
]]></text></news-item>