<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-WKT1-JDJN-64KR"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Regulatory lawyers seek to unplug the 'ponderous' pipeline approval process</title><source>Legal Monitor Worldwide</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Building pipelines in Canada used to be a sleepy business. Not any more, says lawyer Kemm Yates, a partner with Blake, Cassels & Graydon LLP in Calgary. "There's a great deal of activity," says Mr. Yates, who is ranked as a Band 1 practitioner for oil and gas regulatory matters in Chambers Global 2013. Blakes is ranked as a Band 1 firm for oil and gas.
There are more than a half-dozen key projects at various stages of the regulatory process. As well, there are a number of smaller pipelines proposed around the Alberta oil sands that will move crude into the system. Pipeline projects are increasingly in the cross-hairs of environmental and anti-fossil fuel groups, who are turning up the heat on the National Energy Board, the main regulator in charge of green lighting projects. It comes at as time when Canada's energy producers are bringing into production more heavy oil and shale gas and looking to diversify the markets in which they sell their product. "Canada has always been an energy exporting nation," says Laurie Smith, a Band 1 regulatory practitioner in Calgary at Band 1 oil and gas firm Bennett Jones LLP. Canada's main market has been the United States, but that country is nearing energy self-sufficiency with the shale gas boom, Mr. Smith says. "It's an absolute imperative that Canada get long-term reliable access to a more diverse mix of markets. For that reason, all these pipelines are important for both the east and the west." He says moving oil and gas to the Canadian coasts would make it easier to ship to foreign markets, such as Asia, India and Europe. It also reduces Canada's reliance on U.S. consumption. Pipelines have a long history in Canada and have at times been controversial, stemming back to the mid 1950s, when then Liberal prime minister Louis St. Laurent allowed TransCanada to build a gas line to central Canada. It became political fodder in the House of Commons and contributed to his defeat at the hands of Conservative John Diefenbaker. Other controversial pipelines include the 3,700-kilometre Alliance pipeline moving natural gas from Western Canada to Chicago built in the 1990s, and the proposed Mackenzie Valley pipeline, first proposed in the 1970s and seems stalled since receiving approval in 2011. Richard Neufeld, a Band 2 regulatory practitioner at Band 2 oil and gas firm Dentons Canada LLP in Calgary, says of today's projects that the "profile is higher now than it has been in the past." This is due to a number of factors. First, the duty to consult with aboriginal groups is evolving in the courts. Mr. Neufeld says a project like Northern Gateway involved 50 Aboriginal groups. "Trying to chart a way that's fair to everybody and gets to the intended goal can be complicated."
Second, lawyers say activists are using the pipeline-approval process to attack fossil fuel development, which is wreaking havoc on the NEB. For example, protesters disrupted the Line Nine hearings, forcing the NEB to stop the proceedings because of security concerns and resort to written submissions. The NEB noted in its decision the "lack of decorum and disruptive conduct" by some individuals attending the Montreal and Toronto hearings. In determining if a pipeline project should proceed, the NEB normally considers things like the economic, technical and financial feasibility of a project and its environmental and socio-economic impact. Industry lawyers say anti-fossil fuel lobbyists have been unable to stop oil sands projects from moving forward, so they are debating the use of hydrocarbons as part of a deliberate strategy to drag out pipeline hearings. "I do not believe the future of hydrocarbon development is a legitimate issue on a pipeline application," Mr. Smith says. He said the process is becoming "ponderous" and it shouldn't take years to approve a pipeline. At each hearing, lawyers are often "re-proving" technology and methods that are "well accepted," Mr. Smith says. "We have to find a way to tighten up the timelines. Our approval process is putting us at a serious disadvantage relative to other suppliers seeking out the same markets." Keystone XL: a $5.3-billion, 1,800-kilometre pipeline proposed by TransCanada Corp. It would move 830,000 barrels per day of Alberta oil to refineries in the Midwest and Gulf Coast. It has been approved in Canada, but is awaiting presidential approval in the U.S.Northern Gateway: an 1,100-kilometre, $7.9-billion pipeline that would move 525,000 barrels of Alberta oil to a terminal in Kitimat, B.C. The NEB has recommended that the Enbridge Inc. project go ahead and it is awaiting Cabinet approval.Energy East: a $12-billion, 4,600-kilometre pipeline that would move 1.1 million barrels of oil from Alberta and Saskatchewan to marine terminals in Quebec City and Saint John. The TransCanada project involves converting a gas pipeline and building new lines in six provinces.Line Nine Reversal: a $110-million Enbridge project between Montreal and Sarnia, which has been approved by the NEB. It will see 300,000 barrels a day flow from Sarnia to Montreal.Mainline expansions: A $2.1-billion multi-stage expansion of Enbridge's mainlines. It includes adding pumping capacity to its Alberta Clipper line that serves the U.S. Midwest and will eventually see that line boosted to 1 million barrels per day.Trans Mountain: a Kinder Morgan project that would see the reactivation of a 193-kilometre pipeline and the construction of 987 kilometres of new pipeline between Alberta and Burnaby, B.C. It's expected to cost $5.4-billion and move 890,000 barrels per day.In its annual review of Canadian law firms, influential legal publisher Chambers and Partners, acknowledges nine firms for their competition strengths:
Band 1Blake, Cassels & Graydon LLPDavies Ward Phillips & Vineberg LLPBand 2Osler, Hoskin & Harcourt LLPStikeman Elliott LLPBand 3Bennett Jones LLPMcCarthy Tétrault LLPMcMillan LLPTorys LLPBand 4Fasken Martineau LLPNorton Rose Fulbright © 2014 Legal Monitor Worldwide.
]]></text></news-item>