<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-GRJ1-DYRV-31B2"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Austrian opposition urge more transparency in talks on EU-US free trade deal</title><source>BBC Monitoring Europe - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Text of report by Austrian newspaper Wiener Zeitung on 27 March
[Unattributed report: "The Freedom To Know What Is Being Negotiated at All"]
Vienna - At a Nationalrat [National Council, or lower chamber of the Austrian Parliament] session on Wednesday [26 March], MPs called for transparency in the negotiations about the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership, TTIP, between the EU and the United States.
The Greens highlighted the issue of the TTIP at "Question Time." Greens floor leader Eva Glawischnig stressed that the agreement concerned 800 million people in Europe and the United States. "All these people are deprived of an essential freedom, the freedom to know what is being negotiated at all." She accused the federal chancellor [Werner Faymann] of "secret-mongering."
Glawischnig has a sense of foreboding about the agreement because it probably serves, above all, to enforce commercialization interests of the agriculture and food production industry prevailing in the United States. It was to be feared that companies with a special right to sue could bring action to recover investment losses to the detriment of the people. In addition, for example in the chemical sector, the US risk principle could prevail over the European precautionary principle, she said.
It was urgently necessary to disclose the contents of the planned agreement. Therefore, in order to shed light on the issue, the Greens Parliamentary Group had used a new political tool, she pointed out. It had filed a request for documents to call on the Federal Government to provide information on the TTIP. Although the deadline would expire on Friday, they had not received a single page. The lack of transparency at all levels was highly problematic in terms of democracy policy, she argued.
Federal Chancellor Werner Faymann stressed his commitment to a transparent information policy and asserted that Austria would not agree to a "deal that would worsen conditions."
Faymann tried to pacify the critics. In fact, Europe, and in particular Austria, had considerably higher standards than the United States as far as social and environmental issues were concerned, which indeed needed to be protected, he stressed. The issue of investment protection must by no means be a hidden backdoor to privatize water supply and lower environmental protection standards and social conditions, he stated. "More market and more opportunities for Austrian companies is a goal that must not be incompatible with our social and environmental criteria."
As far as the Greens' concrete demands were concerned, he would ask his officials to review which documents could be handed on. He went on to say that he also shared the view that the discussion should be as transparent as possible. For that reason, Faymann also expressly welcomed the current suspension of the negotiations on the issue of investment protection in order to allow intensive public discussion with non-governmental organizations, social partners, and employees' representatives.
No Chlorine Chickens
In the SPOe [Social Democratic Party of Austria] Parliamentary Group, consumer protection spokeswoman Elisabeth Grossmann warned of pitfalls for the environment and employees. "We certainly do not want chlorine chickens, hormone meat, and genetically modified corn in Austria." Deputy floor leader Cap, however, did not share the Greens' criticism, rejecting their "gloomy comments." He called for a more objective discussion because it did not make sense to paint apocalyptic pictures. Rather, it would be helpful to back the federal chancellor to strengthen his position in the negotiations.
According to [former Agriculture Minister] Nikolaus Berlakovich (OeVP [Austrian People's Party]), the fears are justified; hence - just like the chancellor - he welcomed the partial suspension of the TTIP negotiations for public consultations on investment protection. However, there were also positive aspects, the former agriculture minister stated, referring to the size of the common economic area.
Other opposition groups also expressed criticism of the TTIP. Harald Vilimsky (FPOe [Freedom Party of Austria]) even called on Faymann to use his veto in the negotiations, accusing him of "acting like a rabbit in the headlights" at present. Ulla Weigerstorfer (Team Stronach) expressed concern and suggested holding a working meeting on the issue. "Alarm bells start ringing in my head when I hear the name Monsanto," she stated with reference to the interests of US agriculture companies.
"Neither on the national nor on the European level will we support a TTIP along the proposed lines," said Angelika Mlinar of the Neos, stressing at the same time the advantages of free trade.
Source: Wiener Zeitung, Vienna, in German 27 Mar 14 p 3
]]></text></news-item>