<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-CY91-JB4F-Y3H7"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Cohen Milstein Sellers &amp; Toll PLLC Announces the Investigation of Immunomedics, Inc.</title><source>News Bites US Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[[News Story] WASHINGTON - Cohen Milstein Sellers & Toll PLLC is conducting an investigation to determine whether Immunomedics, Inc. ("IMMU" or the "Company") and certain of its officers and directors made false and misleading statements and/or omissions in violation of Sections 10(b) and 20(a) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934.
A class action lawsuit was filed in the U.S. District Court for the District of New Jersey by another law firm on behalf of purchasers of the common stock of Immunomedics, Inc. (NASDAQ:IMMU) between May 9, 2013 and October 9, 2013, inclusive (the "Class Period").
The complaint alleges that IMMU and certain of its officers and directors ("Defendants") made numerous positive statements about Veltuzumab and its related development with IMMU partner Takeda-Nycomed (the "Agreement"), while in fact the Company and Takeda-Nycomed were actually embroiled in an on-going dispute regarding the same. On May 14, 2013, just after the beginning of the Class Period, IMMU provided Takeda-Nycomed with a formal notification that, as a result of the delays in the development in Veltuzumab, it considered Takeda-Nycomed to be in "material breach" of the Agreement and that the Agreement would terminate if the breach remained uncured.
The Class Period ends on October 9, 2013 with IMMU's announcement that its development Agreement with Takeda-Nycomed had been terminated. The announcement was made after the market close on October 9 and Immunomedics shares fell from $5.60 to $5.56 on October 10.
Cohen Milstein encourages all investors who purchased IMMU common stock between May 9, 2013 and October 9, 2013 or former employees with information concerning this matter to contact the firm.
If you are an IMMU shareholder and would like to discuss your right to recover for your economic loss, you may, without any cost or obligation, call Cohen Milstein's Managing Partner, Steven J. Toll at (888) 240-0775 or (202) 408-4600, or email him at stoll@cohenmilstein.com If you wish to serve as lead plaintiff, you must move the Court no later than April 28, 2014 to request that the Court appoint you as lead plaintiff. A lead plaintiff is a representative party acting on behalf of other class members in directing the litigation. To be appointed lead plaintiff, the Court must decide that your claim is typical of the claims of other class members, and that you will adequately represent the class. Your share in any recovery will not be enhanced or diminished by the decision whether or not to serve as a lead plaintiff. Any member of the proposed class may retain Cohen Milstein Sellers & Toll PLLC or other attorneys to serve as your counsel in this action, or you may do nothing and remain an absent class member.
Cohen Milstein Sellers & Toll PLLC has significant experience in prosecuting investor class actions and actions involving securities fraud. The firm has offices in Washington, D.C., New York, Chicago, Philadelphia and Palm Beach Gardens, and is active in major litigation pending in federal and state courts throughout the nation.
The firm's reputation for excellence has repeatedly been recognized by courts which have appointed the firm to lead positions in complex multi-district or consolidated litigation. Cohen Milstein Sellers & Toll PLLC has taken a lead role in numerous important cases on behalf of defrauded investors, and has been responsible for a number of outstanding recoveries which, in the aggregate, total over one billion dollars. Prior results do not guarantee a similar outcome. For more information visit www.cohenmilstein.com.
If you have any questions about this notice or the action, or with regard to your rights, please contact either of the following:
Steven J. Toll, Esq. Jordan Hill Cohen Milstein Sellers & Toll PLLC 1100 New York Avenue, N.W. West Tower, Suite 500 Washington, D.C. 20005 Telephone: (888) 240-0775 or (202) 408-4600 Email: stoll@cohenmilstein.com; jhill@cohenmilstein.com
Source: NASDAQ Stock Exchange
Recent TradingImmunomedics (IMMU.NASDAQ) MCap is US$372.2 million at the last price of US$4.50. The value of US$1,000 invested one year ago is US$1,860 [vs US$1,277 for the NASDAQ-100 Index], for a capital gain of US$860. The total return to shareholders for 1 year is 86.0%.
ISIN: US4529071080
O:IMMU;
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>