<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-R8M1-DXCW-D02T"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Georgia: UPSCALE SECURITY OFFICER / SECURITY GUARD (ATLANTA</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Department of Labor, The State of Georgia has issued the following job opportunities:
Job Location Months ofExperienceRequired Years ofEducationRequired Salary Job Type Job OrderNumberAtlanta, GA 12 12 $10.00 to $10.00 Per Hour Permanent Part Time GA8167154Atlanta, GA 12 12 $10.22 to $10.22 Per Hour Permanent Part Time GA8167159Job Number GA8167154Job Title UPSCALE SECURITY OFFICER / SECURITY GUARD (ATLANTAJob Location Atlanta, GAMinimum Skills See job description.
12 Month Experience 12 Years Education
Preferred Skills None GivenJob Description The world s leading private security organization, G4S, has an immediate job opportunity for an Upscale Security Officer. G4S is a security provider for the United States government, fortune 500 companies, nuclear power plants, oil and gas companies, airport, ports, banks, hospitals, factories, warehouses, commercial facilities, residential communities and much more. G4S offers job security, excellent pay and benefits, and career opportunities. We offer entry level careers, management careers, sales careers and executive careers across the United States and internationally. Perform security patrols of designated areas on foot or in vehicleWatch for irregular or unusual conditions that may create security concerns or safety hazardsSound alarms or call police or fire department in case of fire or presence of unauthorized personsWarn violators of rule infractions, such as loitering, smoking or carrying forbidden articlesPermit authorized persons to enter property and monitors entrances and exitsObserve departing personnel to protect against theft of company property and ensure that authorized removal of property is conducted within appropriate client requirementsInvestigate and prepare reports on accidents, incidents, and suspicious activitiesProvide assistance to customers, employees and visitors in a courteous and professional manner. Education, Licenses and Certifications Required: Must possess a high school diploma or equivalent. Must be able to pass any State-required training or other qualifications for licensing. Pass a State licensing test if driving a company-owned or client-provided vehicle. Type and Length of Specific Experience Required: Must possess one or more of the following; Associate's degree or higher in any discipline. Service in the active duty military, military reserves or National GuardService in auxiliary police or police cadets. Meaningful and verifiable work history. Minimum of one year verifiable and successful security experience. Skills Required: Ability to operate radio or telephone equipment and/or console monitors. Ability to interact cordially and communicate with the public.Effective oral and written communication skills, active listening skills. Ability to assess and evaluate situations effectively. Ability to identify critical issues quickly and accurately. Attention to detail. Must be at least 18 years old or the minimum age required by the State. Must have access to reliable transportation. Must not use illegal drugs. Must be able to pass a drug test with negative results (except when undergoing documented medical treatment). Must be able to pass an extensive background check, including criminal history, personal references, employment and education verifications, and Department of Motor Vehicle and credit checks if applicable. Must be able to provide, upon job offer, a DD214 discharge document with discharge status indicated.Salary $10.00 to $10.00 Per HourJob Type Permanent Part Time First Shift JobYou must possess all of the Minimum Skills required to request a referral to this job.Request a referral to this jobView same catergory of jobs in the County this Job is LocatedJob Number GA8167159Job Title UPSCALE SECURITY OFFICER / SECURITY GUARD (ATLANTAJob Location Atlanta, GAMinimum Skills See job description.
12 Month Experience 12 Years Education
Preferred Skills None GivenJob Description The world s leading private security organization, G4S, has an immediate job opportunity for an Upscale Security Officer. G4S is a security provider for the United States government, fortune 500 companies, nuclear power plants, oil and gas companies, airport, ports, banks, hospitals, factories, warehouses, commercial facilities, residential communities and much more. G4S offers job security, excellent pay and benefits, and career opportunities. We offer entry level careers, management careers, sales careers and executive careers across the United States and internationally. Perform security patrols of designated areas on foot or in vehicle. Watch for irregular or unusual conditions that may create security concerns or safety hazards. Sound alarms or call police or fire department in case of fire or presence of unauthorized personsWarn violators of rule infractions, such as loitering, smoking or carrying forbidden articlesPermit authorized persons to enter property and monitors entrances and exitsObserve departing personnel to protect against theft of company property and ensure that authorized removal of property is conducted within appropriate client requirementsInvestigate and prepare reports on accidents, incidents, and suspicious activitiesProvide assistance to customers, employees and visitors in a courteous and professional manner. Education, Licenses and Certifications Required Must possess a high school diploma or equivalentMust be able to pass any State-required training or other qualifications for licensingPass a State licensing test if driving a company-owned or client-provided vehicleType and Length of Specific Experience Required Must possess one or more of the following:Associate's degree or higher in any disciplineService in the active duty military, military reserves or National GuardService in auxiliary police or police cadetsMeaningful and verifiable work history.Minimum of one year verifiable and successful security experience. Skills Required Ability to operate radio or telephone equipment and/or console monitorsAbility to interact cordially and communicate with the publicEffective oral and written communication skills. Active listening skills. Ability to assess and evaluate situations effectivelyAbility to identify critical issues quickly and accurately. Attention to detailOther Must be at least 18 years old or the minimum age required by the StateMust have access to reliable transportation. Must not use illegal drugs. Must be able to pass a drug test with negative results (except when undergoing documented medical treatment). Must be able to pass an extensive background check, including criminal history, personal references, employment and education verifications, and Department of Motor Vehicle and credit checks if applicable.Must be able to provide, upon job offer, a DD214 discharge document with discharge status indicated, if prior militaryUpon acceptance of a job offer, must be able to pass the following:MMPI - PsychologSalary $10.22 to $10.22 Per HourJob Type Permanent Part Time First Shift Job
For further information please visit: http://www.dol.state.ga.us/
]]></text></news-item>