<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVF-DV21-JBJ4-22BK"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Cosatu Alarmed At Developments At Blyvooruitzicht Mine and Blyvoor Community [press release]</title><source>Congress of South African Trade Unions</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Congress of South African Trade Unions fully shares the concern and anger of its affiliate, the National Union of Mineworkers (NUM), that the workers at the Blyvooruitzicht Mine in Carletonville and the surrounding communities “are facing a bleak future”.
The situation is becoming as bad as the humanitarian tragedy which unfolded between 2011 and 2013 at the Aurora gold mines at Orkney and Grootvlei, where 700 workers were left unpaid for more than two years.
Those two mines, formerly owned by the liquidated company, Pamodzi Gold, were sold to Aurora Empowerment Systems, which was allowed to manage the mines, but who never paid the workers in full despite numerous promises, and sold removable items, while workers and other creditors went unpaid.
Now, at the Blyvooruitzicht mine, none of the 1746 workers have been paid since September 2013, nor received any retrenchment payments. Thomas Wilkes, a banksman who has worked for Blyvoor for 12 years, told the Financial Mail that he is owed R280 000 in retrenchment. Workers doing essential services work are not being paid as promised.
On 10 March 2014 workers in two security companies working for Goldrich, embarked on a protest demanding their salaries. This matter was temporary resolved by the newly appointed business rescue practitioner who promised to take up their complaint as he claimed to be in charge.
Blyvooruitzicht gold mine's former owner used to employ almost 2000 people. But the company went into liquidation in 2013 and the mine was sold to Goldrich for R70m. It has however defaulted on the second payment and on 27 February Goldrich applied for “business rescue”, which led to the appointment of a business rescue practitioner to take over the running of the company.
Events there are starting to look like a re-run of the Aurora mines saga. The Chairperson of Goldrich Holdings, Thulani Ngubane, was a former Aurora director, and the company is advised by Fazel Bhana, who also advised Aurora.
Liquidator for the former owners, Leigh Roering of Harvard Corporate Recovery Services, who is pursuing court action to cancel the sale agreement, say they were not aware of the same people being involved in Goldrich and Aurora until the day the agreements were signed, but concedes that “the individuals associated with Goldrich were involved in the Pamodzi liquidation and were responsible for asset-stripping through Aurora, and the liquidators want to avoid a recurrence of what transpired on that estate.”
The liquidators are now pursuing court action to cancel the sale agreement and have filed two urgent applications in the high court, firstly to nullify its sale agreement with Goldrich and to evict it from the mine premises, and secondly to interdict Goldrich from removing and selling any assets from the mine.
It is not only the workers who are in peril. About 6000 people live in the Blyvoor village community, where 1000 houses were recently sold to a property developer for the equivalent of R17000 each and residents are now being charged R3500 a month for water and electricity, which no-one can afford, given that most of the residents have been without jobs and salaries since September 2013.
About a month ago water and electricity supply became intermittent and the municipality is providing a stand tap, which means a daily trek with buckets and bottles. The company has also threatened to talk to Eskom to stop power supply if residents cannot pay the R3, 500 per month.
On top of all this the people of Blyvoor are living in fear as ‘zama-zamas' (‘illegal miners') knock in their doors during the night demanding money and if this is not given they resort into robbing, raping, and threatening to kill the occupants. Residents told the Financial Mail that they hear shooting at night and at least 20 people are reported to have been killed in clashes between ‘zama-zamas' and security staff employed by Goldrich.
The liquidators also believe that asset-stripping has been going on. Roering says: “It was brought to my attention during the course of the evening of February 28 2014 that assets of Blyvoor were being stripped and carted off the Blyvoor property.”
AngloGold Ashanti (AGA) informed him that Goldrich “was flame cutting AGA's assets which were on the Blyvoor property”, notably a winch shaft “worth millions” that had already been sold by the liquidators to AGA, and that “three borer mills belonging to Blyvoor, which are functional pieces of equipment and not redundant, were being cut up into scrap metal and loaded on to a truck.”
The affidavit concluded that: “It is apparent from Goldrich's conduct that it holds the entire judicial process in contempt and that it is attempting to realise as much cash as possible before being evicted from the mine … The respondent's ¬conduct is reprehensible.
“There is a real fear that the assets of Blyvoor, including the gold concentrate and even gold nuggets, will be illegally removed and sold. I have been advised that the respondent is panning gold dust, producing gold and transporting it to refineries… which heightens the concern that the material assets of Blyvoor are disappearing without any accounting to the liquidators.”
On 10 March two senior managers appeared in the Carletonville magistrate's court after they were arrested by the Hawks on charges of theft and the illegal possession of gold. Police allegedly found 1.3kg of gold nuggets in their possession, which has a value of between R400 000 and R500 000.One of them faces two extra charges for fraud and defeating the ends of justice.
The company's mismanagement also poses a threat to surrounding mines and communities owing to the disrupted pumping of toxic water by AGA because of Goldrich's non-payment of R5 million per month for water pumping services. This has led to the flooding of two levels at Blyvoor number five shaft. If this is not stopped it could flood the whole shaft and possibly spread to other nearby mines.
COSATU backs the NUM's call for the liquidators to take decisive action on the Blyvoor situation, bearing in mind that thousands of the workforce are currently in a dire situation. Richgold must be brought to justice.
We cannot tolerate the looting of our nation's mineral wealth while workers and communities face destitution. That is why the mines must be nationalised and placed under the democratic management of the workers and the local communities, so that the wealth under our soil is exploited for the benefit of the majority and not for the enrichment of a handful of greedy capitalists.
Patrick Craven (National Spokesperson), Congress of South African Trade Unions
]]></text></news-item>