<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVG-5C51-F03R-N215"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>BofA Heading to Possible Victory Over U.S. in Mortgage Case (DOJ Looking For A Great White Shark, Catches A Minnow Instead)</title><source>Confounded Interest</source><author>tonysanders</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 28, 2014 (Confounded Interest:http://confoundedinterest.wordpress.com/ Delivered by Newstex) Bank of America may win a lawsuit with the U.S. Department of Justice about false statements with regard to $850 million in mortgage-backed securities (MBS).
March 28 (Bloomberg) — Bank of America Corp. should win dismissal of a U.S. Justice Department lawsuit accusing it of misleading investors about the quality of loans tied to $850 million in mortgage-backed securities, a judge said. The government’s claim that the bank made false statements wasn’t properly supported, U.S. Magistrate Judge David Cayer in Charlotte, North Carolina, said yesterday in a recommendation to dismiss the case. The U.S., which filed a notice that it will object, has a chance to challenge the recommendation before a district court judge and appeal any dismissal. Dismissal of the case “will represent a significant setback for the government’s legal efforts and likely mark the beginning of the end for crisis-era litigation,” Isaac Boltansky, a policy analyst at Compass Point Research Trading LLC in Washington, said today in a research note. The proposal comes as the U.S. seeks to punish companies for wrongdoing that helped trigger the financial crisis. The case and others like it allege violations of a law that is a relic of the savings-and-loan crisis of the 1980s, allowing civil suits to reach back further in time to target bad behavior and seek larger damages in court. If the case is dismissed, it will be a first for about a dozen companies that have been targeted under the Financial Institution Reform, Recovery and Enforcement Act of 1989, known as FIRREA, which allows the government to sue an individual or group, rather than charge them with a crime, for fraud that affects a federally insured financial institution. So, the Magistrate in this case realized that starting in 2008, unemployment skyrocketed and real median household income sank, leading to a surge in seriously delinquent loans (causality). Plus, this information was available to investors at the time of purchase of MBS. http://confoundedinterest.files.wordpress.com/2014/03/loanhpothers1.png Clearly, the magistrate thinks that the alleged misreporting of information was not sufficiently substantiated. I have read through many Prospectus Supplements for RMBS offerings and never understood what the DOJ was fishing for. DOJ was hoping to land a Great White Shark, but caught a Minnow instead. http://confoundedinterest.files.wordpress.com/2014/03/coconutradio.jpg

]]></text></news-item>