<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVG-8BG1-JB3N-T2YS"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>CBI chargesheets Congress MP Vijay Darda, son in coalgate</title><source>The Economic Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NEW DELHI: In an embarrassment to the Congress ahead of the 2014 polls, the CBI on Thursday charged Rajya Sabha MP of the Congress and owner of the Lokmat group, Vijay Darda in the coal block allocation scam along with his son, Devender Darda. In an action packed Thursday, just a day before a hearing on the coal scam matter in the Supreme Court, CBI has also closed two other coal scam cases and lodged two new FIRs.
Along with Darda, CBI has charged mining baron and Director of AMR Iron and Steel , Manoj Jayaswal, in the case regarding allocation of Bander Coal block in Maharashtra to the company in 2009. The charge-sheet was filed by the CBI in a Delhi Court on Thursday. The allegations are that Jayaswal’s company had concealed and misrepresented facts that its group firms had already been allocated five coal blocks earlier and also falsely claimed that it was financially eligible to get the block.
The CBI’s allegations are that in order to prove financial eligibility to acquire the block fraudulently, Jayaswal’s company claimed that it was a proposed special purpose vehicle with Lokmat Group. Vijay Darda owns the Lokmat Group while his son Devender Darda is the Managing Director and the Dardas and Jayaswal are said to have close business links.
CBI has charged the Darda father-son duo and Jayaswal for cheating, conspiracy and corruption. No government servant has been named in the said charge-sheet. CBI has also started to close certain coal scam cases. CBI has filed closure reports on Thursday citing the “lack of prosecutable evidence” in cases registered earlier in 2012 against Vikas Metals Ltd and Kamal Sponge and Power. In more action on the coal scam front, CBI also registered two fresh cases on Thursday -- one against the Promoter of Prakash Industries, Delhi, Ved Prakash Agrawal along with unknown public servants and another FIR against GD Daga, the owner of Central Collieries Nagpur. In the first case, CBI said then members of 35th Screening Committee committed irregularities in respect of allocation of Fatehpur Coal Block in Chhatisgarh to the company which alleged misrepresented on aspect of net-worth to get coal block.
“The Screening Committee deliberately did not follow the guidelines and showed undue favour to the company,” the CBI said. Regarding the Nagpur-based company, CBI said it got a coal block at Chandrapur (Maharashtra) by furnishing false information as the company was non existent at the time of allocation. “Central Collieries was allocated coal block in the year 1998 for captive use of the coal in their proposed power plant.
Though the policy was that the coal blocks would be allocated for captive use only, the mining lease deed executed by the company with the Government of Maharashtra did not incorporate the condition of captive consumption of the coal. The mine plan was forged which facilitated the non captive use of coal.
Mining started since the year 2000 without setting up of the proposed power plant and the coal extracted from the block was sold in the market.
This led to an alleged misappropriation to the tune of Rs10 crores,” the CBI said, saying this meant selling coal by the company in the open market against the concept of captive allocation of coal blocks for specified end use product.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>