<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVG-8BG1-JB3N-T31Y"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Mukesh Ambani globally celebrated, AAP attacks absurd: Anand Sharma</title><source>The Economic Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NEW DELHI: Commerce Minister Anand Sharma has come to the defence of Reliance Industries chairman Mukesh Ambani saying vested interest may have provoked the Aam Aadmi Party’s attacks on the “globally acknowledged and celebrated” industry leader.
Separately, Reliance Industries also lashed out at the Aam Admi Party, saying its leader Arvind Kejriwal, had ordered a “completely illegal” FIR against Ambani and Central ministers. In a video uploaded on YouTube on Thursday, RIL alleged Kejriwal was not actually interested in fighting corruption, but had an eye on the elections.
Kejriwal has attacked Ambani regularly in his election rallies. He has alleged that Ambani had influence on both Congress and the Bharatiya Janata Party.
Sharma rubbished the allegations against Ambani and said it was absurd to say Ambani was running the Congress. “It is all nonsense. It is absurd. How come they (AAP) are targeting only the industry leader who is globally acknowledged and celebrated. You are talking of big industry leaders of India. For anybody to say that Congress is run by ‘A’ or ‘B’, it’s unfair. It’s actually an insult not only to the industry leader Mukesh Ambani in this instant case but to the entire Congress,” he told ET NOW.
“Do not forget that they (AAP) have vested interest in the corporate world ... How do you attract attention — if you do something which is shocking, if you say something which is shocking,” the minister said. Sharma pointed out that industry had a right to present its views to the government. Kejriwal had ordered an FIR against Ambani, oil minister Veerappa Moily and former oil minister Murli Deora, alleging collusion to raise gas prices. He also urged the Election Commission to stop the notification of higher gas prices. The poll authority subsequently asked the oil ministry to defer the increase in gas prices.
Commenting on the EC decision, the commerce minister said the poll authority had “overreached”.
“I have no hesitation to say (that they are) going for an overreach every time. They have a constitutional mandate to ensure the conduct of free and fair elections. There is an extended mandate which is not a part of constitution which is because of the consensus and concurrence of the political parties. Now it cannot be extended on a daily basis. You have a government in office and a new government will assume office ...but the state has not come to a standstill,” he said.
Meanwhile Reliance, which has countered Kejriwal’s attacks with strong statements in recent days, questioned Kejriwal’s intentions on Thursday. In a video uploaded on YouTube, Reliance spokesman Upadhyay speaks to former Secretary General of Lok Sabha, Subhash Kashyap, and begins the interview saying: “The FIR relating to gas contracts filed by former Delhi Chief Minister against the Union Government was completely illegal. The Constitution clearly spells out the division of power between and Centre and State very unambiguously. ”
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>