<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVG-2CG1-F03R-N4H3"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Malayan Insurance Co. Inc. : Company Profile and SWOT Analysis</title><source>SBWire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 28, 2014 (SBWire:http://www.sbwire.com Delivered by Newstex) Naperville, IL -- (SBWIRE[1]) -- 03/28/2014 -- Reportstack, provider of premium market research reports announces the addition of Malayan Insurance Co. Inc. : Company Profile and SWOT Analysis[2] market report to its offering This report is a crucial resource for industry executives and anyone looking to access key information about "Malayan Insurance Co. Inc."
The report utilizes a wide range of primary and secondary sources, which are analyzed and presented in a consistent and easily accessible format. World Market Intelligence strictly follows a standardized research methodology to ensure high levels of data quality and these characteristics guarantee a unique report.Scope Examines and identifies key information and issues about "Malayan Insurance Co. Inc." for business intelligence requirements. Studies and presents the companyaposs strengths, weaknesses, opportunities (growth potential) and threats (competition). Strategic and operational business information is objectively reported. The profile also contains information on business operations, company history, major products and services, key employees, and locations and subsidiaries.Reasons to Buy Quickly enhance your understanding of "Malayan Insurance Co. Inc." Gain insight into the marketplace and a better understanding of internal and external factors which could impact the industry. Increase business/sales activities by understanding your competitors businesses better. Recognize potential partnerships and suppliers.Key HighlightsMalayan Insurance, Co., Inc. (Malayan Insurance) is a non-life insurance company based in the Philippines. It offers a range of non-life insurance products such as fire insurance, motorcar insurance, aviation insurance, engineering insurance, marine insurance, personal accident insurance and surety bonds. The company also offers property insurance, general liability insurance, hospitalization insurance, household employee insurance, golfer insurance, glass insurance, livestock insurance, poultry catastrophe insurance, errors and omissions insurance, boiler, pressure and vessel insurance, photographer insurance and fidelity guarantee. It operates through a network of more than 30 branches in the Philippines. The company is a member of Yuchengco Group of Companies. Malayan Insurance is headquartered in Manila, the Philippines.Companies MentionedMalayan Insurance Co. Inc. To view the table of contents for this market research report please visit http://www.reportstack.com/product/150986/malayan-insurance-co-inc-company-profile-and-swot-analysis.html[3] Contact: Roger Campbell contactus@reportstack.com Naperville Illinois United States Ph: 888-789-6604###For more information on this press release visit: http://www.sbwire.com/press-releases/malayan-insurance-co-inc-company-profile-and-swot-analysis-483733.htm[4] Media Relations Contact Roger Campbell Director of Marketing Email: Click to Email Roger Campbell[5] Web: http://www.reportstack.com[6] [1]: http://www.sbwire.com/?utm_source=ntutm_medium=feedutm_campaign=distribution [2]: http://www.reportstack.com/product/150986/malayan-insurance-co-inc-company-profile-and-swot-analysis.html [3]: http://www.reportstack.com/product/150986/malayan-insurance-co-inc-company-profile-and-swot-analysis.html [4]: http://www.sbwire.com/press-releases/malayan-insurance-co-inc-company-profile-and-swot-analysis-483733.htm?utm_source=ntutm_medium=feedutm_campaign=distribution [5]: http://www.sbwire.com/press-releases/contact/483733?utm_source=ntutm_medium=feedutm_campaign=distribution [6]: http://www.reportstack.com

]]></text></news-item>