<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVG-1Y11-F05M-K387"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Reports: Trenna Cannon, wife of former Charlotte mayor, loses job at Allen Tate</title><source>Charlotte Business Journal</source><author>Jen Wilson</author><text><![CDATA[Local TV news reports indicate Trenna Cannon, the wife of former Charlotte mayor Patrick Cannon, has been let go from her job as a real estate agent with the&nbsp;Allen Tate Cos.
In an internal email obtained by WBTV and other stations, Allen Tate Chief Operating Officer Pat Riley said the company surrendered Trenna Cannon's license to the state after learning of the ongoing federal investigation of her husband, according to multiple published reports.
A spokesman for the N.C. Real Estate Commission told WBTV the statement about surrendering the license is not accurate, and that Trenna Cannon's real estate license is still valid in North Carolina. However, she no longer works at Allen Tate's Ballantyne office, according to that report.
Reached by the Charlotte Business Journal, the company said it cannot comment on personnel matters, and that Riley himself has not sent any emails to media outlets. But a listing for Trenna Cannon on&nbsp;the Allen Tate website has been removed.
Patrick Cannon was&nbsp; arrested by the FBI on Wednesday on charges of public corruption, sending shockwaves through the Queen City. Hours later, the former Charlotte City Council member resigned as mayor, a post he held for just 114 days.
The ex-mayor, a Democrat, is accused of soliciting and accepting bribes in exchange for the use of his various official positions as mayor, mayor pro tem and as a city councilman. Court filings allege he received more than $48,000 in cash, plane tickets, a hotel room and use of a luxury apartment from undercover agents.
Trenna Cannon has not been charged with any crimes. But she is mentioned multiple times in the court documents, including statements in an affidavit that detail an all-expenses paid trip to Las Vegas for the Cannons, plus spending money.
"Trenna Cannon personally thanked [the undercover agent] for the $1,000 cash payment that was provided to the Cannons the previous day," the affidavit states.
Patrick Cannon is represented by Charlotte attorney James Ferguson.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Charlotte Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>