<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVG-7671-F125-12S2"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Pauline Marois promises new Quebec French language charter to bring 'new lift' to speakers, bolster use in workplaces</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[MONTREAL - Parti Québécois leader Pauline Marois promised if elected to create a new French language charter to bolster the language in the province and halt what she called the decline of the French language at work caused in part by the Liberal government's refusal to act.
She was accompanied by former minister and Rosemont riding candidate Jean-François Lisée, who said he was "pessimistic" about the chances of Quebecers opting for a referendum in the next four years, much to his disappointment.
"I'm pessimistic about having one in the mandate," he said. "But of course we want to keep the option open, in case (the voters) change their minds. But we know if the Liberals are there, the option is not there to change their minds.
Related
Graeme Hamilton: With PQ confidence evaporated, Marois reduced to slinging mud at Couillard( http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2014/03/27/graeme-hamilton-with-pqs-confidence-evaporated-marois-reduced-to-slinging-mud-at-couillard/ )
Pierre Karl Péladeau re-emerges to blame Liberal referendum 'boogeyman' for PQ's falling fortunes( http://news.nationalpost.com/2014/03/27/pierre-karl-peladeau-reemerges-to-blame-liberal-referendum-boogeyman-for-pqs-falling-fortunes/ )
McGill student rejected as voter in Quebec election despite living in province since 2009( http://news.nationalpost.com/2014/03/26/mcgill-student-rejected-as-voter-in-quebec-election-despite-living-in-province-since-2009/ )
"All sovereignists want a referendum before yesterday, it's sure. But we are realists and we see the signals sent by the Quebecers."
Lisée said he was surprised by Quebecers majority refusal to support a referendum in recent polls. "The message was much stronger than I had thought - so we have to respect that."
Neither Marois nor Lisée would say what minimum support of Quebecers would be needed to justify holding a referendum.
Short on details about what exactly would be in the new charter, Marois mentioned more programs to teach immigrants French, and more English courses at French CEGEPs to entice francophone students instead of going to anglophone CEGEPs to learn English. The measure would help English students who are having difficulty getting into crowded anglophone CEGEPs, Marois said. The new charter would not formally restrict francophone students from attending English CEGEPs, as had been previously mandated under Bill 14.
"For more than 400 years, the Quebec nation lived, grew and flourished under French," Marois said. "French is the precious heritage bequeathed to us by our fathers and mothers. It is one of our greatest riches. ... "Our language, our collective identity, our identity, deserves more than the refusal to act of the Liberals," she said. "It's the Parti Québécois that gave the province its French Language Charter 37 years ago. It is more than time to bring a new lift to the French language."
The Canadian Press / Ryan RemiorzQuebec Liberal leader Philippe Couillard speaks to the media while campaigning at a window manufacturing plant Friday, March 28, 2014 in Blainville, Que. Quebecers will vote in a provincial election April 7, 2014
Former minister Diane de Courcy criticized Liberal leader Philippe Couillard for failing to protect the French language and speaking in favour of bilingualism in the workplace.
"It was very clear from M. Couillard last night that everyone must speak English at work in the case a foreign company visits a factory and asks a question in English," she said. "I couldn't believe my ears. What a decline. A decline to the 1950s. A refusal to see the Quebecers flourish in French."
The PQ has long advised that if elected it would toughen up language laws and bring back the controversial Bill 14, to strengthen the French Language Charter. The bill proposed extending Bill 101 rules for French in the workplace to companies with between 25 and 50 employees, and imposing stricter rules on access to English education and bilingual municipalities. The party dropped its initial proposal to restrict francophone students from attending English CEGEPs in the face of widespread disapproval among French and English students.
The PQ was forced to abandon Bill 14 last year because it lacked support from opposition parties, who in particular objected to a clause that would restrict the children of military personnel from attending English schools.
In February, then-minister de Courcy said Quebec must stop the "unacceptable slide" into institutional bilingualism, expressed in part in the habit of downtown Montreal sales staff of greeting shoppers with "Bonjour-Hi."
Dario Ayala / MONTREAL GAZETTEJean-François Lisée
Marois' announcement came the day after Quebec's political leaders clashed in their second televised debate in a week, with the possibility of an independence referendum figuring prominently.
During the debate, Couillard accused Marois of failing to come clean with Quebecers on the referendum issue.
Polls repeatedly suggest that a majority of Quebecers do not want a plebiscite and Couillard's strategy was similar to his approach in last week's debate: try to cast the PQ as a party that fosters political uncertainty at the expense of economic prosperity.
"People know you're going to have a referendum," he said in a heated exchange with the premier.
Marois countered with the argument she repeatedly used last week - that there will be no such vote until Quebecers are ready for one.
"The election is all about choosing a government," she said."
"You know very well, Mr. Couillard, that I am a determined woman but that I am a woman who can listen to Quebecers."
Couillard reiterated the Liberal mantra that Quebecers don't want a referendum and that their priorities are jobs, health care and education.
That prompted Marois to accuse her rival of being soft on the national question.
"Yes, Quebecers want jobs but they also want a Quebec that stands up for itself."
With an opinion poll this week suggesting the Liberals were leading in popular support, Marois, Coalition Leader François Legault and Québec solidaire's Françoise David made a point earlier in the debate of ganging up on Couillard on integrity issues.
Couillard was grilled extensively about his ties to Arthur Porter, a former hospital administrator who now faces fraud charges in connection with a scandal-plagued contract to build a large Montreal hospital.
He and Porter were appointed by Prime Minister Stephen Harper to the committee that monitors Canada's spy agency, and they also ran a consulting business together.
Couillard took issue with being mentioned in the same breath as Porter.
"He's someone I knew but to associate me in any way whatsoever with what he's accused of doing is unacceptable, unacceptable," the Liberal leader said.
"I wasn't even around him when the contract was handed out."
David then went after Couillard following a Radio-Canada report that he placed $600,000 in an offshore tax haven while practising as a neurosurgeon in Saudi Arabia well before embarking on his political career.
Couillard repeated there was nothing illegal about the account at a branch of the Royal Bank of Canada based in Jersey, in the Channel Islands between England and France.
"I respected all the tax laws," he said. "Upon my return to Canada, I paid all the requisite taxes."
With files from the Canadian Press
]]></text></news-item>