<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVJ-R451-F125-140D"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Victoria woman who claimed cash was from wealthy suitors convicted of defrauding charity</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A Victoria woman has been convicted of defrauding the Capital Families Association of $204,000, despite her defence that she had money because she dated wealthy men and also had a cash box at home that contained "thousands and thousands of dollars."
B.C. Supreme Court Justice Geoff Gaul found that Anita Dunkers, the 56-year-old former bookkeeper for the association, wrote 270 Capital Families cheques to herself and deposited them in her bank account between January 2008 and January 2010.
"I am satisfied you used falsehoods and deceitful action to fraudulently deprive the CFA of more than $200,000," Gaul said Thursday. "I find you guilty as charged."
Outside court, Prairie Escallier, former executive director of Capital Families, said she didn't know whether to laugh or cry at the end of the saga.
"I think justice has been served," Escallier said. "I knew she was guilty. Everybody knew she was guilty. I'm thankful that the judge believed the witnesses."
Dunkers' fraud sparked the demise of Capital Families, which closed March 31, 2011, after providing child, youth and family programs on the West Shore for 34 years, Escallier said.
It had a $1-million budget, up to 25 employees and contracts with the provincial Ministry for Children and Family Development.
"That broke my heart. It broke my spirit. It was more than I could handle," said Escallier, wiping away tears. "We're heartfelt people who cared about the families in that community and believed for all we were worth in what we were doing. It didn't just break my heart. It broke many hearts."
In January 2010, Capital Families was on the verge of bankruptcy, Gaul said. Programs, staff hours and services were being reduced or cut. In mid-January, Dunkers resigned after a dispute with Escallier. Soon after, Dunkers' replacement, Ashley Xu, discovered that a number of cheques, listed in records as being paid to Capital Families employees and contractors, were actually made payable to Dunkers.
Dunkers testified that she would often use her personal funds to make payments on behalf of Capital Families, then submit expense claims.
But Escallier, who had been with Capital Families for more than 20 years, testified that Dunkers was not authorized to incur any expenses for the society and that she did not sign any cheques to reimburse Dunkers. Four other Crown witnesses, former members of the board, testified they did not sign expense cheques for Dunkers.
"They were all consistent in their evidence that the accused would have no reason to have an expense file," Gaul said.
Dunkers testified that she never signed anyone else's names on Capital Families cheques. She maintained they were reimbursements for legitimate expenses. She said she often bought groceries and office supplies and always had cash on hand.
"The accused said she dated wealthy men and had a cash box at home that contained thousands and thousands of dollars," Gaul said. "She said she never kept track of how much money was in the box."
Gaul found Dunkers' evidence contrived and her explanation of her spending and banking practices unconvincing.
Defence lawyer Tim Russell asked Gaul to order a pre-sentence report because Dunkers has no criminal record. Her sentencing hearing is expected to be held in June.Capital Families lost funding after the B.C. Gaming Commission heard about the embezzlement, Escallier said. The commission refused further funding, a loss of $65,000 to $95,000 from the budget. Major contracts with the Ministry of Children and Family Development were not renewed because of below-standard bookkeeping, which meant the loss of up to $350,000 in grants.
ldickson@timescolonist.com( mailto:ldickson@timescolonist.com )
Read more stories from the Times Colonist.( http://timescolonist.com )
© Copyright (c) The Victoria Times Colonist
]]></text></news-item>