<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVJ-CT61-F0CC-S236"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Tawa PLC Annual Results Announcement -5-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[HIR is a small German reinsurer. On 20 December 2013 Tawa announced the sale of HIR and PIR. During the year HIR made a loss of $2.5 million (2012: profit $1.4 million) which was mainly attributable to a Group IFRS pension adjustment. Discontinued risk carrier business On 16 April 2013, the Group disposed of its risk carrier KX Re and its direct subsidiary OX Re. The business of KX Re comprised a collection of mature portfolios of long-tail liabilities, including exposure to asbestos, environmental and other latent claims. OX Re was a small London market company which had been in run-off since 1994 and was acquired by Tawa as a strategic investment in 2011. The Group's objective for KX Re was to reduce the company's liabilities by accelerating the natural run-off of the portfolio to enable the extraction of capital with regulatory approval. This was achieved and since acquisition Tawa extracted capital of $75.0 million from KX Re by way of dividends to the holding company. The sale of KX Re and OX Re was part of the Group's active investment management program with a view to volatility reduction. The loss on sale is considered a corporate activity and the results are disclosed within discontinued operations.
PXRE is mainly comprised of catastrophe exposures. In 2013 the investment return for PXRE was in line with the discount unwind (2012: in line with the discount unwind). During the current year capital of $13 million (2012: $nil million) was extracted from PXRE by way of dividends to its holding company. Since acquisition Tawa has extracted $47.8 million (2012: $34.8 million). This reflects the significant progress made in reducing the volatility, achieved by de-scaling the liability portfolios in this risk carrier. During the year PXRE made a loss of $2.4 million (2012: profit $4.1 million) which was largely attributable to costs incurred. Island Capital Group ("ICG"), which comprises ICL and ICE, is an insurance group with a specialist underwriting portfolio of trade credit and political risk insurance business, which went into run-off in November 2008 following the sale of its trade credit and political risk insurance underwriting platform. ICG made a profit of $0.3 million during the year (2012: profit $1.0 million). As at 31 December 2013 there were $16.3 million of subrogation recoveries included in assets held for sale due to Island Capital Limited. These remain subject to judicial proceedings and the process is taking longer than originally expected. Notwithstanding this, management continue to see progress and still anticipate realisation of the booked value. The associate CX Re has a book of reinsurance contracts written prior to August 2001, when the company ceased underwriting new business. The company has consistently maintained a portfolio of highly rated, readily realisable assets which broadly matches the duration and currency of the liabilities, plus a substantial tax asset, the recovery of which depends on the satisfactory resolution of pending litigation with HMRC. In 2013 the investment return for CX Re was $1.1 million in excess of the discount unwind (2012: $2.0 million in excess of the discount unwind). CX Re made a profit of $0.9 million in the year (2012: loss of $0.2 million), including the Group IFRS adjustment to the risk carriers debt purchase portfolio of $1.8 million (2012: $nil). The table below illustrates all the risk carriers' assets and liabilities:
Corporate division results This division incorporates corporate costs and Group overheads, incubator costs for STRIPE(R) , acquisition activities and financing resulting in a loss of $11.1 million (2012: $5.6 million). The share of results in associate Asta are discussed in the service business section.
]]></text></news-item>