<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVJ-GFR1-JB4P-V4S6"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Faruqi &amp; Faruqi, LLP Encourages Investors Who Suffered Losses In Excess Of $100,000 Investing In Coty, Inc. To Contact The Firm</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP, a leading national securities law firm, reminds investors in Coty, Inc. ("Coty" or the "Company") (NYSE: COTY) of the April 14, 2014 deadline to seek the role of lead plaintiff in a federal securities class action lawsuit filed against Coty, certain executives and directors of Coty, and the underwriters of the Company's Initial Public Offering ("IPO").

A complaint has been filed on behalf of all persons who purchased or otherwise acquired Coty securities pursuant and/or traceable to the Company's June 13, 2013 IPO in the Southern District of New York.
The complaint alleges that the Company and its executives violated federal securities laws with respect to its disclosures concerning its business, operations, and prospects.
Specifically, the action alleges that Defendants made false and/or misleading statements and/or failed to disclose that during the quarter prior to the IPO: (i) consumption of Coty's products was materially declining to the point that products were being returned from retailers and (ii) Sally Hansen and the Company's other nail products had experienced a material decline leading to the sales of those products being flat and were negative in July 2013.  Additionally, Coty failed to disclose that mass retailers were not refilling inventory, or were restocking a smaller amount of inventory, which was a material negative trend that would indicate a material decline in the Company's revenue.
Since the IPO, Coty's common stock price dropped $4.67 per share, or over 26%, hitting a low of $12.83 per share on February 5, 2014.
Request more information now by clicking here:http://www.faruqilaw.com/COTY.  There is no cost or obligation to you.
Take Action
If you invested in Coty stock or options pursuant and/or traceable to the Company's June 13, 2013 IPO and would like to discuss your legal rights, visithttp://www.faruqilaw.com/COTY.  You can also contact us by calling Richard Gonnello or Francis McConville toll free at 877-247-4292 or at 212-983-9330 or by sending an e-mail torgonnello@faruqilaw.comorfmcconville@faruqilaw.com Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP also encourages anyone with information regarding Coty's conduct to contact the firm, including whistleblowers, former employees, shareholders and others.
Faruqi & Faruqi, LLPis a national law firm which represents investors and individuals in class action litigation.  The firm is focused on providing exemplary legal services in complex litigation in the areas of securities, shareholder, antitrust and consumer litigation, throughout all phases of litigation.  The firm has an experienced trial team which has achieved significant victories on behalf of the firm's clients. To keep track of the latest securities litigation news, follow us on Twitter athttp://www.twitter.com/MergerActivityor on Facebook athttp://www.facebook.com/FaruqiLaw.
Attorney Advertising.  The law firm responsible for this advertisement is Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP (http://www.faruqilaw.com).  Prior results do not guarantee or predict a similar outcome with respect to any future matter.  We welcome the opportunity to discuss your particular case.  All communications will be treated in a confidential manner.
FARUQI & FARUQI, LLP369 Lexington Avenue, 10th FloorNew York, NY 10017Attn:  Richard Gonnello, Esq.rgonnello@faruqilaw.comFrancis McConville, Esq.fmcconville@faruqilaw.comTelephone: (877) 247-4292 or (212) 983-9330
Logo -http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20120119/MM38856LOGO
SOURCE Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP
]]></text></news-item>