<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVJ-K411-F03R-N4FG"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>SEC Says $65 Million 'Cloud' Scheme Hot Air</title><source>Ponzi Clawbacks</source><author>Michael Hackard</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 28, 2014 (Ponzi Clawbacks:http://ponziclawbacks.com/ Delivered by Newstex) http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/files/2014/03/Care-Bears.jpg DiC The SEC has levelled civil action[1] against a far-flung technology marketing scheme that has burned through $65 million in just one year. World Capital Markets, also known as WCM777, is the subject of the agency's complaint over allegations that the company funneled at least $28 million of investor funds to bank accounts in Hong Kong. While the exact number of WCM777 investors is as yet unknown, it is reported to be in the 'tens of thousands.' The alleged Ponzi was said to target Asian and Hispanic American communities with claims of easy money at little risk.
The man behind WCM777 is Phil Ming Xu, a resident of Temple City, CA. From March of 2013 until the SEC filed its suit, Xu has purported to sell 'cloud' technology services in what can only be called a multi-level marketing pyramid, promising mind-blowing returns of 100% in 100 days. In addition to that, WCM777 clients could acquire 'points' that would be converted into stock in up-and-coming tech companies. These points could also be traded, Xu claimed, in a secondary market worth $890 million. Federal regulators contend that far from generating any profit bonanza, Xu was recycling investor principal through WCM777 to pay out fictitious interest. He also is accused of misappropriating his clients' funds to purchase real estate properties (including two golf courses) and to play the stock market. According to authorities, money was also diverted to PMX Jewels, a Hong Kong diamond merchant. Along with a freeze on Xu's activities with WCM777, the SEC is demanding disgorgement of all funds - much of which is said to be hidden away in Hong Kong - and penalties. PHIL MING XU Company: WCM777 Job: Cloud Marketer Alleged Scam: Multi-Level Marketing Profits: 100% in 100 days Ponzi Time: 2013-2014 Victims: 'Tens of Thousands' Amount of Fraud: $65 million SEC Complaint: Multiple Counts of Fraud, Money Laundering Location: Los Angeles, CA Court: US District Court, Central District of CA Ming Xu SEC Complaint[2] Michael A. Hackard[3], Meriam Hansen, Nou Lee and Jeremy Rutledge are experienced in prosecuting civil actions against Ponzi scheme perpetrators as well as defending and resolving clawback cases filed by Bankruptcy Trustees and SEC Receivers. If you have been a victim in a Ponzi scheme and face legal action, contact Hackard Law[4] today. [1]: http://www.sec.gov/News/PressRelease/Detail/PressRelease/1370541324305 [2]: http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/files/2014/03/Ming-Xu-SEC-Complaint.pdf [3]: http://www.avvo.com/attorneys/95655-ca-michael-hackard-226264.html [4]: http://www.ponziclawbacks.com/contact/

]]></text></news-item>