<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVJ-CT61-F0CC-S327"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Public Power Corporation S.A. Annual Financial -36-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Tangible assets are initially recognised at their acquisition cost which includes all direct attributable expenses for their acquisition or construction. Subsequent of their initial recognition, tangible assets (with the exception of mines and lakes which are valued at cost minus accumulated depreciation and eliminations) are valued at their fair values minus accumulated depreciation and eliminations. Estimations of fair values are performed periodically by independent appraisers (every three to five years) in order to ensure that fair value does not differ significantly from the net value of the asset. The last assets' evaluation was completed December 31(st) 2009. Any valuation increase is credited to the revaluation surplus net of deferred taxes. At the date of revaluation, accumulated depreciation is offset against pre depreciation accounting values and net amounts are restated according to restated amounts.
Any decrease is first offset against an earlier valuation increase in respect of the same fixed asset and thereafter charged to the income statement. Upon disposal of revalued tangible asset, the relevant portion of the revaluation surplus is released from the revaluation surplus directly to retained earnings. Repairs and maintenance are charged to expenses as incurred. Subsequent future expenditures are capitalized when they increase the asset's useful life, improve its productivity or decrease its operational cost. For all assets retired or sold, their acquisition cost and related depreciation are removed from the accounts at the time of sale or retirement, and any gain or loss is included in the statement of income. Borrowing costs From January 1(st) , 2009, borrowing costs that are directly attributable to the acquisition, construction or production of a qualifying asset that needs a substantial period of time to get ready for its intended use or sale, is capitalised as part of the cost of the relevant assets. The new accounting policy is implemented on fixed assets recognized from January 1, 2009 herein (new constructions). All the remaining borrowing costs are recognized as expenses in the period in which they are incurred. 3.4. PRINCIPAL ACCOUNTING POLICIES (CONTINUED) Depreciation Depreciation is calculated on a straight-line basis over the average estimated remaining useful economic life of the assets. The useful lives (in years) applied for the calculation of depreciation, have as follows:
Buildings and Civil Works
Mining activities The Parent Company owns and operates open-pit lignite mines. Land acquisition (mainly through expropriation) and initial (pre-production) development costs relating to mines are capitalized and amortized (upon commencement of the mines' commercial operation) over the shorter of the life of the mine and 20 years. Exploration, evaluation and ongoing development costs are charged to the cost of lignite production as incurred. A provision for land restoration is established for the Group's estimated present obligation for restoration and is calculated based on the surface disturbed to date and the average cost of restoration per metric unit. It is accounted for at the present value of the related obligation to restore land back to a beneficial use and is included both in fixed assets (mines) and in provisions. Investments in subsidiaries In the separate financial statements, investments in subsidiaries are accounted for at cost less any impairment losses. The spin off and contribution of an activity from the Parent Company to a wholly owned subsidiary in exchange for shares, is accounted for as a transaction between companies under common control. In cases of such transactions the shares received are recognised as an addition to the cost of investment in the subsidiary with a value equivalent to the carrying value of the net assets contributed at the transaction date. Investments in associates These are entities in which the Group has significant influence and which are neither a subsidiary nor a joint venture of the Group. The Group's investments in associates are accounted for under the equity method of accounting. The investments in associates are carried on the balance sheet at cost plus post-acquisition changes in the Group's share of net assets of the associate, less possible provisions for any impairment in value. The income statement reflects separately the Group's share of the results of its associates, while amounts that are registered by the associates directly to their equity are recognized directly to the Group's equity. Non - realizable profit or loss resulting from the transactions of the Group with said associates are eliminated to the extent of the interest in the associates. The associates' accounting principles are adjusted, when necessary, in order to comply with those adopted by the Group. In the separate financial statements such investments are accounted for at cost less any accumulated impairment losses. 3.4. PRINCIPAL ACCOUNTING POLICIES (CONTINUED) Investments in joint ventures The Group has interests in joint venture which are jointly controlled entities with other companies with which the Group has a contract. In the consolidated financial statements, investments in joint ventures are accounted for under the equity method. The investments in joint ventures are carried on the balance sheet at cost plus post-acquisition changes in the Group's share of net assets of the associate, less any impairment value. The consolidated statement of income reflects the Group's share of the results of its joint ventures while amounts that are registered by the joint ventures directly to their equity are recognized directly to the Group's equity. Non - realizable profit or loss incurring from the transactions of the Group with those joint ventures is eliminated to the extent of the interest in the joint ventures. The joint ventures' accounting principles are adjusted, when necessary, in order to comply with those adapted by the Group. In the separate financial statements such investments are accounted for at cost less any impairment losses. Impairment of assets The Group assesses at each reporting date whether there is an indication that an asset may be impaired. If any such indication exists, the Group makes an estimate of the asset's recoverable amount. An asset's recoverable amount is the higher of an asset's or cash generating unit's fair value less cost to sell and its value in use and is determined for an individual asset unless the asset does not generate cash inflows that are largely independent of those from other assets or groups of assets. Where the carrying amount of an asset exceeds its recoverable amount, the asset is considered impaired and is written down to its recoverable amount. In assessing value , the estimated future cash flows are discounted to their present value using a pre-tax discount rate that reflects current market assessment of the time value of money and the risks specific to the asset. The fair value of sale (after the deduction of sales costs) is determined, in each case, according to the implementation of a revaluation model. Impairment losses of continuing operations are recognized to the income statement, except if the particular asset is valued in fair values and then the impairment loss is recognised as a decrease of the already recognised surplus value. An assessment is made at each reporting date as to whether there is any indication that previously recognized impairment losses may no longer exist or may have decreased. If such indication exists the recoverable amount is estimated. A previously recognized impairment loss is reversed only if there has been a change in the estimates used to determine the assets' recoverable amount since the last impairment loss was recognized. If that is the case, the carrying amount of the asset is increased to its recoverable amount. That increased amount cannot exceed the carrying amount that would have been determined, net of depreciation, if no impairment loss had been recognized for the asset in prior years. Such reversal is recognized in profit and loss unless the asset is carried at revalued amounts in which case the reversal is treated as a revaluation increase. After such a reversal the depreciation charge is adjusted in future periods to allocate the asset's revised carrying amount, less any residual value, to be divided equally to future time spans on a systematic basis over its remaining useful life. Fair value measurement The Group measures financial instruments, such as, derivatives, and non-financial assets such as investment properties, at fair value at each balance sheet date. Also, fair values of financial instruments measured at amortised cost are disclosed in Note 20.4. Fair value is the price that would be received to sell an asset or paid to transfer a liability in an orderly transaction between market participants at the measurement date. The fair value measurement is based on the presumption that the transaction to sell the asset or transfer the liability takes place either: In the principal market for the asset or liability, or In the absence of a principal market, in the most advantageous market for the asset or liability The principal or the most advantageous market must be accessible to by the Group.
]]></text></news-item>