<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVJ-T6J1-JDKC-R4XN"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Air force jolted by C-130J crash, five crew members die</title><source>Hindustan Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[New Delhi, March 29 -- Five crew members were killed when an Indian Air Force transport plane crashed near Gwalior on Friday, jolting the world's fourth-largest air force and exposing cracks in its safety standards.
Barely an hour after it took off from the Agra airbase on a training mission, the IAF's US-built C-130J Super Hercules aircraft went down 75 miles west of Gwalior along the Madhya Pradesh-Rajasthan border at around 11.30 am.
The crash comes a little over three years after the IAF inducted the first of its six C-130J planes, configured for special operations and airborne assault.
The IAF identified the dead as Wing Commander Prashant Joshi (captain), Wing Commander Raji Nair (co-pilot), Squadron Leader Kaushik Mishra ( additional pilot), Squadron Leader Ashish Yadav (navigator) and Warrant Officer KP Singh (systems operator).
The crash sent shockwaves across the air force. Former IAF chief Air Chief Marshal Fali Major described it as "absolutely shocking" as the aircraft had the "best safety record" of any military plane worldwide. "The news has bombed the hell out of me," he said.
IAF chief Arup Raha said such crashes were "painful reminders" of the risks air force personnel faced on a daily basis. He said the IAF had exploited the C-130J's capabilities during the Uttarakhand floods and the historic landing at the world's highest airstrip at Daulat Beg Oldie in north-eastern Ladakh last August. "The best pilots are chosen to fly these planes," he said.
A probe has been ordered into how the newly-acquired aircraft could have crashed during a training exercise involving two C-130J planes. Attacking the government over the crash, the BJP asked it to take responsibility for the recent mishaps in the military.
The crash comes a month after Admiral DK Joshi stepped down as navy chief accepting moral responsibility for a string of accidents involving leading Indian warships.
India had signed a $962 million contract with the United States for buying six C-130J planes. Six more aircraft are in the works. Built by US aerospace major Lockheed Martin, the C-130J can carry out precision low-level flying, airdrops and landing in blackout conditions.
The aircraft can be used for a range of missions such as combat delivery, peacekeeping, low-intensity conflict, search and rescue, disaster relief and humanitarian missions. It was also involved in the hunt for the missing Malaysia Airlines flight MH370.
The plane comes with major system improvements over the previous variant ( C- 130 Hercules). Pakistani dictator General Zia- ul- Haq and US ambassador to Pakistan Arnold Lewis Raphel perished in a C-130 Hercules (older variant) crash in August 1988.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from HT Kolkata. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>