<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVJ-JVB1-JC3H-03GT"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Grain Processing must pay $1.5M pollution penalty</title><source>Des Moines Register</source><author>By, Matthew Patane</author><text><![CDATA[A Muscatine County judge has ordered Grain Processing Corp. to pay a record $1.5 million civil penalty for violating pollution control laws.
The attorney general's office said Thursday that the penalty was the "largest ever paid to the state for environmental violations." GPC has 10 days to pay the penalty, according to the order.
District Judge Mark Cleve ordered GPC, based in Muscatine, to pay the penalty and meet certain conditions to reduce the company's output of air pollutants.
Among the conditions, GPC must:
Convert its boilers from coal-fired to natural gas-fired.
Install 10 additional air pollution control systems.
Implement an ongoing environmental management system.
Conduct, through a third party, a comprehensive audit of its corn-processing plant and take corrective action, if necessary.
The order, which was issued Thursday, resolves a lawsuit the state had filed against the company in 2011. In the lawsuit, the Iowa Department of Natural Resources alleged that the company was a major source of hazardous air pollutants, such as methanol and formaldehyde.
The attorney general's office also said GPC had estimated that implementing the terms of the order would cost between $15 million and $17 million in expenses, $1 million in annual operating costs, and between $4million and $12 million a year in increased fuel costs.
Separately, GPC said it had already undertaken steps to lessen its emissions of air pollutants.
"Today's announcement provides GPC with the ability to focus on the future," the company said in its statement. "The projects already completed and the many improvements that will be implemented have been approved and supported by the DNR."
The Muscatine company must also take steps to reduce its emissions.
]]></text></news-item>