<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVJ-CVG1-DYRX-X1M5"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Animal rights campaigner: 'I'm a scapegoat'</title><source>The Guardian (London)</source><author>Steven Morris</author><text><![CDATA[An animal rights campaigner convicted of taking part in a conspiracy to blackmail the research company Huntingdon Life Sciences (HLS) told the Guardian she is a "scapegoat" targeted because detectives cannot catch the "real culprits" who have terrorised the company and its suppliers.
Debbie Vincent, who faces up to 14 years in prison when she is sentenced next month, insisted she is a lawful and peaceful campaigner who had been found guilty of "nebulous" charges that are increasingly being used to clamp down on legitimate protest against vivisection.
In her only interview since her conviction, Vincent also criticised the way the Metropolitan police counter-terrorism command, SO15, planted an undercover police officer in meetings she had with healthcare company Novartis over its relationship with Cambridgeshire-based HLS.
Vincent freely admits she carried out work for Stop Huntingdon Animal Cruelty (Shac), which has long fought to close down the HLS animal testing laboratories. But she maintains she had never taken part in acts of terror. She said: "I have been persecuted by the police. I am a public, lawful campaigner. I am being scapegoated because the police have not been able to catch or identify many of the real culprits."
During her trial at Winchester crown court the prosecution gave a string of examples of crimes carried out against HLS suppliers and customers on continental Europe, ranging from sending incendiary devices to falsely accusing staff of being paedophiles and even digging up the urn of the mother of a senior executive at Novartis. It claimed one of Shac's main tactics was to publish the names of possible targets, laying them open to illegal acts of intimidation and violence by extremists.
The prosecution accepted that Vincent, 52, had not herself committed direct action offences, but the jury clearly believed she was part of a wider conspiracy that enabled crimes to take place. Vincent denied the suggestion that she was a leader of Shac, arguing her work there was just part of her campaigning. Vincent said: " I do strongly believe that all I did was be involved in lawful campaigning against HLS."
She said the use of conspiracy laws was having a "chilling effect" on campaigning. It meant, she claimed, that legitimate protesters could be convicted just because they had links to those who carried out attacks.
She said: "A conspiracy is nebulous and hard to grasp. The issues go further than me and could affect countless campaigners and protesters across the UK."
Vincent, who is based in Bristol, is angry at what she sees as a smear campaign by rightwing media, who she believes used her sexuality against her.
The Daily Mail and Telegraph made much of the angle that Vincent was born male, left the army after military police found women's clothing among the young soldier's belongings and has undergone gender reassignment. In its headline, the Mail branded Vincent the "Sex-change soldier who became an animal rights terror commander".
But the depictions of Vincent in the court and in the media do not tally with the woman who emerges in dozens of letters from people who have provided references to her legal team. Farmers, vets, bosses of animal shelters and leaders of community projects spoke of a gentle, peaceful woman who was kind to both animals and humans.
The Met called Vincent's conviction a "significant milestone in a long-running, proactive investigation into criminal activity across Europe".
It said that the investigation, which was led by SO15, established that Vincent had acted as a representative of Shac and had been involved in blackmail campaigns.
But Vincent told the Guardian: "In some ways I'm really not surprised I was found guilty as I don't believe anyone can get justice when faced with a political conspiracy charge and the huge resources of the state and multinationals against me. I will always have hope and will continue to try to make the world a better place to all."
Debbie Vincent, who denies any involvement in criminal activity, could be jailed for up to 14 years next month
]]></text></news-item>