<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVJ-CVG1-DYRX-X1GF"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Street children make a pitch to be heard: As the World Cup draws ever closer, Brazil plays host to a more sobering tournament</title><source>The Guardian (London)</source><author>Jonathan Watts Rio de Janeiro</author><text><![CDATA[It's Brazil, it's 2014 and players from around the world are waiting for kick-off, but there will be no galacticos on the pitch or Wags at local boutiques during the tournament this weekend in Rio de Janeiro.
Instead, the Street Child World Cup will bring together some of the most disadvantaged youths from 19 nations for 10 days of football, art, sightseeing and workshops - putting a spotlight on an issue that is widely ignored.
They include street children from Karachi in Pakistan and Mwanza in Tanzania, Indian children who sought refuge in Chennai station after escaping domestic abuse, and Brazilian youths trying to break free from the cycle of poverty, drugs and violence that claims so many lives in Rio.
The dangers have been all too apparent in the runup to the tournament. Last month, Rodrigo Kelton, one of the players in the Brazilian boys' team, was killed on his 14th birthday in an apparent revenge attack for a robbery he allegedly committed.
Francesca has spent much of her young life living on the streets, begging for food and working as a drug mule for one the biggest gangs in Rio. "Football takes me away from my problems. I've always loved it," she says, during a training session with teammates in the Penha area of Rio. "The Street Child World Cup is a really great opportunity. I've never had anything like this."
Organisers say the 10-day event - backed by Save the Children and also endorsed by David Beckham, Sir Alex Ferguson, Gary Lineker and Archbishop Desmond Tutu - is about a lot more than football. As well as the boys' and girls' competitions, the 230 or so participants will take part in a festival of arts, visit Rio's most famous sights and engage in a conference on children's rights. By the closing ceremony, they are expected to produce a "Rio rights declaration" of actions countries should take to help street children.
"Street Child World Cup is calling on governments, businesses and the wider community to invest in frontline responses, legislate and implement policies that protect street children and listen to street children so they are no longer blamed, ignored or victimised," said organiser Joe Hewitt.
After the first such tournament, in Durban, South Africa, the organisers said the city government was compelled to end the practice of "street sweeps" - an often indiscriminate rounding-up of youths for largely cosmetic reasons. This year, the goal is to prompt the Brazilian government to introduce a comprehensive policy on street children.
Activist Yvonne Bezerra de Mello started the pioneering Uere education programme soon after the 1993 Candelaria massacre, when eight Rio street youths were murdered by police.
Since then, she said, little had changed. Despite the passage of a law to protect street children, she said the number on the streets was about the same as 20 years ago, shelters were filled with crack addicts, and middle-class fear was as bad as ever. There had been a recent spate of cases in which vigilantes chained street youths to lampposts and railings with bicycle locks.
"One day another massacre will occur," said De Mello. "It's inevitable. Everyone wants to ignore the situation - not just in Brazil, but in the world."
Additional research by Charlotte Livingstone
Captions:
A boy shows off his skills in a Rio favela occupied by police ahead of this summer's World Cup Photograph: Mario Tama/Getty
]]></text></news-item>