<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVJ-CTY1-DXKS-J348"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Top 20 Cyber Security Companies 2014</title><source>PR Newswire Europe</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ - M&A, Competitor Positioning & New Market Opportunities 
The global cyber security marketis highly competitive and substantially fragmented.The 20 leading companies in the marketare primarily US based IT and defence companies, with the rise of defence contractors one of the key recent developments in the market's competitive landscape. Leading US defence contractors have emerged as a powerful group in the market, primarily as a result of their expertise in the wider defence and security sectors. Other crucial trends shaping the competitive landscape of the market include: the ever-increasing proliferation of cyber attacks and threats; the development of new technologies and emergence of new companies.
This new report fromvisiongainanalyses these key market dynamics to reach fresh conclusions on the competitive landscape of the cyber security market. Crucially, it finds that the cyber security market is likely to be characterised by diverse security requirements; the advent of new technologies and disruptive innovation from new market entrants. Leading players will seek to address the demands of providing security across the entire cyber domain by expanding their capabilities through strategic acquisitions. These factors will result in significant changes in the competitive landscape of the cyber security market and the composition of the leading companies.
Why you should buy the Top 20 Cyber Security Companies 2014: M&A, Competitor Positioning & New Market Opportunities 
What is the future competitive landscape of the cyber security market? Visiongain's comprehensive analysis contains highly quantitative content delivering solid conclusions benefiting your analysis and illustrates new opportunities and potential revenue streams helping you to remain competitive. This definitive report will benefit your decision making and help to direct your future business strategy.
To see an exec summary of this report please email Sara Peerun onsara.peerun@visiongainglobal.com
We guarantee that you will receive key information which will benefit you in the following way 
·     View global market share data for the leading companies in the global cyber security market in 2014 to keep your knowledge ahead of your competition and ensure you exploit key business opportunities-     The report provides detailed analysis of the leading 20 companies in the cyber security market, the competitive landscape, and the commercial drivers and restraints allowing you to more effectively compete in the market. In addition to current market shares for the leading companies, our report contains original critical analysis, and revealing insight into commercial developments·    Why struggle to find key market data? Why miss crucial information? Our comprehensive report provides instant market insight-    Our 196 page report provides 170 tables, charts, and graphs; 152 contracts and 556 companies and other organisations mentioned. Let our analysts present you with a thorough assessment of the current and future prospect for leading companies in the cyber security market.-    This analysis will achieve quicker, easier understanding. Also you will gain from our analyst's industry expertise allowing you to demonstrate your authority on the cyber security sector·    Visiongain is one of the few business intelligence companies that provides full transcripts of primary research company interviews. Be part of this knowledge. Learn what industry thought leaders are thinking. Leaders hold critical information-    By reading the full transcripts of exclusive expert opinion interviews contained in the report you will keep up to speed with what is really happening in the industry. Don't' fall behind. You will gain a thorough knowledge on the cyber security market sector finding strategic advantages for your work and will learn how your organisation can benefit - allowing you to assess prospects for investments and sales. Read our interview with:-    Symantec Corporation·    Discover sales analysis and market share breakdowns for the leading companies in 2014-    What are the dynamics of the cyber security industry? How will the sector expand? Which companies will generate the most revenue? Use our analysis and expert insight to grow your business and give you more industry influence. Find where you can gain and how your organisation can succeed. Avoid falling behind.·    Explore the factors affecting product developers, and everyone within the value chain. Learn about the forces influencing market dynamics.-    Explore the social, technological, economic and political (STEP) and strengths, weaknesses, opportunities and threats (SWOT) issues in the cyber security market. Discover what the present and future outlook for business will be. Learn about the following business critical issues --    Research and development (R&D) strategies-    Capital expenditures-    Technological innovations-    Disruptive innovation from new market players-    Competition from new product types-    Evolving threats and threat landscape-    Expanding expertise among leading companies-    Increasing industry consolidation and the acquisition of new technologies.-    Advances in product quality-    Analysis of barriers to entry·    Identify who the leading companies are in the cyber security market-    Our report reveals the technologies and companies which hold the greatest potential. See where the expected gains will be. Prospects for advances in the cyber security market industry are strong, and from 2014 it holds many opportunities for revenue growth. View Visiongain's assessment of the prospects for established competitors, rising companies, and new market entrants. Our work explains that potential, helping you stay ahead. Gain a thorough understanding of the competitive landscape with profiles of 20 leading cyber security companies examining their positioning, capabilities, product portfolios, R&D activity, services, focus, strategies, M&A activity, and future outlook. The leading companies are:-     BAE Systems PLC-     The Boeing Company-     Booz Allen Hamilton Inc-     Cisco Systems Inc-    Computer Sciences Corporation-    Dell Inc-     Finmeccanica SpA-     General Dynamics Corporation-     Hewlett Packard Company-     International Business Machines Corporation (IBM)-     Intel Corporation-     Kaspersky Lab-     L-3 Communications Holdings-    Leidos-     Lockheed Martin Corporation-     Northrop Grumman Corporation-     Raytheon Company-     Symantec Corporation-     Thales Group-     Trend Micro Inc
To see an exec summary of this report please email Sara Peerun onsara.eerun@visiongainglobal.com
Discover Information found nowhere else in this independent assessment of the leading companies in the cyber security market 
The Top 20 Cyber Security Companies 2014: M&A, Competitor Positioning & New Market Opportunities report provides impartial cyber security market analysis. With the independent business intelligence found only in our work, you will discover where the prospects are for profit. In particular, our new research provides you with key strategic advantages: Our informed forecasts, independent and objective analysis, exclusive interviews and revealing company profiles will provide you with that necessary edge, allowing you to gain ground over your competitors.
With this report you are less likely to fall behind in knowledge or miss crucial business opportunities. You will save time and receive recognition for your market insight. See how you this report could benefit and enhance your research, analysis, company presentations and ultimately your individual business decisions and your company's prospects.
What makes this report unique? 
Visiongain consulted widely with leading industry experts and a full transcript from an exclusive interview with Symantec Corporation is included in the report. Visiongain's research methodology involves an exclusive blend of primary and secondary sources providing informed analysis. This methodology allows insight into the key drivers and restraints behind market dynamics and competitive developments. The report therefore presents an ideal balance of qualitative analysis combined with extensive quantitative data including company market shares; market revenues and capital expenditures in 2014.
Why choose visiongain business intelligence? 
Visiongain's increasingly diverse sector coverage strengthens our research portfolio. The growing cross-sector convergence of key verticals and the interplay of game changing technologies across hitherto unrelated industries are creating new synergies, resulting in new business opportunities for you to leverage.
As such, visiongain's team of London based in-house analysts offer a wealth of knowledge and experience to inform your strategic business decisions. Let visiongain guide you.
How the Top 20 Cyber Security Companies 2014: M&A, Competitor Positioning & New Market Opportunities  report can benefit you 
Visiongain's report is for anyone requiring analysis of the cyber security industry. You will discover market shares for leading companies, technological trends, predictions and expert opinion providing you with independent analysis derived from our extensive primary and secondary research. Only by purchasing this report will you receive this critical business intelligence revealing where revenue growth is likely and where the lucrative potential market prospects are. Don't miss this key opportunity to gain a competitive advantage.
If you buy our report today your knowledge will stay one step ahead of your competitors. Discover how our report could benefit your research, analyses and strategic decisions, saving you time. To gain an understanding of how to tap into the potential of this market and stay one step ahead of the competition you must order now our report the Top 20 Cyber Security Companies 2014: M&A, Competitor Positioning & New Market Opportunities. Avoid missing out -order our report now.
To request an exec summary of this report please email Sara Peerun atsara.peerun@visiongainglobal.comor call Tel : +44(0)20-7336-6100
Or click onhttp://www.visiongain.com/Report/1228/Top-20-Cyber-Security-Companies-2014
Companies Listed in this report: 
3001 International Inc3Di Technologies LLC42Six Solutions LLCABB GroupAccenture LtdAccenture PLCACSAdcorp Holdings LtdAdobe Systems IncAdvanced Laser Systems Technologies IncAdvanced Micro Devices (AMD)Aerient LLCAffirmTrustAirborne Technologies IncAirbus GroupAlion Science and Technology CompanyALON IncAMSEC LLCAmor GroupAppAssureApplied Physical Science CorporationApplied Signal TechnologyApplied Visions IncArcSight IncAreva SAArgon STARINC Engineering Services LLCARINC IncARINC Inc, Defense Systems Engineering and SupportAssured Information Security IncAT&T IncAutonomy CorporationAvast Software ASAVG TechnologiesAvio SpAAvineon IncAxsys Technologies IncAxxonSoftAydin CyberSecurityAyon CyberSecurity IncBAE AustraliaBAE Cyber & IntelligenceBAE DeticaBAE Electronic SystemsBAE IndiaBAE Intelligence & SecurityBAE Land and ArmamentsBAE Regional AircraftBAE Saudi ArabiaBAE Shared ServicesBAE Support SolutionsBAE Systems Applied IntelligenceBAE Systems PLCBAE Systems Technology Solutions and Services IncBBN TechnologiesBenchmark Capital LLCBigFix IncBlueWater Technology SolutionsBoeing CapitalBoeing Commercial AirplanesThe Boeing CompanyBoeing Cyber Engagement Center (CEC)Boeing Defense Space and SecurityBoeing Engineering Operations and TechnologyBoeing Information SolutionsBoeing Intelligence Systems GroupBoeing Shares Services GroupBooz & CompanyBooz Allen Hamilton Engineering Holding Company LLCBooz Allen Hamilton Engineering ServicesBooz Allen Hamilton IncBooz Allen Hamilton State & Local Government Transit ConsultingBreakingPoint SystemsBringaBusiness Computers Management Consulting Group LLCByres Security IncCACI IncCamber CorporationCap Gemini SAThe Carlyle GroupCDW Government LLCCGI Group IncCH2M HILLCheck Point Software Technologies LtdChemring Group PLCCinvenCisco Systems IncCloudShield Technologies IncCM Equity PartnersCognitive SecurityComputer Sciences Canada IncComputer Sciences CorporationComputer Sciences Corporation, Enterprise Systems IntegrationConsul Risk Management IncContext ISCorero Network SecurityCosentini AssociatesCreative Computing Solutions (CCSI) IncCredant TechnologiesCubic XDCustom Computer Services IncCyberlabs SrlCyberoam TechnologiesCyber Integration & Innovation Centre (Thales)Cyber Operations IncDedagroup SpADef-Logix IncDell Federal Systems LPDell IncDell Services Federal GovernmentDeloitte Consulting LLP.Deloitte Touche Tohmatsu LimitedDenali Holding IncDenim Group LtdDetica Group PLCDiebold IncDigital Info Security CompanyDigital Receiver Technology IncDigital Risk LLCDMIDRC SystemsDRS Technical Services IncDRS Technical Services, Global Enterprise Solutions InternationalDRS Technologies IncDRS Technologies Inc, Network and Imaging SystemseGlobalTechElsag DatamatEMC CorporationEmiraje SystemsEnerNexEngility Holdings IncEnterprise Information ServicesEquifax IncESETETI A/SEuropean Aeronautic Defence & Space Company (EADS)Exelis IncExidaeXMeritus IncExperian PLCExtraQuestFederal Management Systems IncFiberlink CommunicationsFidelis Cybersecurity SolutionsFinmeccanica SpAFireEye IncFiretideFortify SoftwareFortinet IncFoxGuard Solutions IncF-Secure CorporationFulcrum IT Services LLCGalileo AvionicaGeneral Dynamics Advanced Information SystemsGeneral Dynamics Armament and Technical ProductsGeneral Dynamics Bath Iron WorksGeneral Dynamics C4 SystemsGeneral Dynamics CorporationGeneral Dynamics Electric BoatGeneral Dynamics European Land SystemsGeneral Dynamics Information Technology LimitedGeneral Dynamics Land SystemGeneral Dynamics NASSCOGeneral Dynamics One Source LLCGeneral Dynamics Ordnance and Tactical SystemsGeneral Dynamics United Kingdom LimitedGeneral ElectricGentex CorporationGideon TechnologiesGlobal Defence Technologies and Systems IncGlobal InfoTek IncGnostech IncThe Goldman Sachs GroupGoogle IncGS Capital PartnersGuardianEdge Technologies IncGulfstream Aerospace CorporationHarris CorporationHauri IncHawker Beechcraft CorporationHenggeler Computer Consultants IncHewlett Packard CompanyHewlett Packard Enterprise Security ProductsHewlett Packard Enterprise Services LLCHiflex Software GmbHHoneywell IncHoneywell Technology Solutions IncHRL Laboratories LLCHuawei Symantec Technologies Company LtdHuawei Technologies Company LtdHuntington Ingalls IndustriesHyTrusti2 Algorithmics IncIBM Global ServicesIBM Global Technology ServicesIBN Internet Security SystemsIBM Watson GroupICF InternationalID/DataWebIdentum LtdIndustrial DefenderInjazat Data SystemsInternational Business Machines (IBM) CorporationIntel CorporationIntel Federal LLCIntel SecurityIntelliDyne LLCInternet Security SystemsIntrusion IncIPKeys Technologies LLCIron Bow Technologies LLCISC8 IncItaltel SpAITOCHU CorporationITOCHU Techno-Solutions CorporationITT ExelisIxiaJohnson Controls IncJuniper Networks IncKACE NetworksKaspersky LabKestrel Technology LLCKEYW CorporationKForce Government SolutionsKnowledge Consulting Group (KCG)Kratos Defense and Security Solutions IncKtech CorporationKylmar LimitedL-3 Aeromet IncL-3 ASA LtdL-3 Communications ComCeptL-3 Communications Holdings IncL-3 Communications Systems EastL-3 Communications Systems EastL-3 Crestview AerospaceL-3 Integrated Optical SystemsL-3 Integrated SystemsL-3 KEOL-3 MASL-3 National Security SolutionsL-3 Services IncL-3 STRATISL-3 TCS IncLacoon Mobile SecurityLeidosLockheed Martin AeronauticsLockheed Martin AustraliaLockheed Martin CanadaLockheed Martin CorporationLockheed Martin Cyber Security AllianceLockheed Martin Electronic SystemsLockheed Martin Global Training and LogisticsLockheed Martin Information Systems & Global SolutionsLockheed Martin InternationalLockheed Martin Missiles and Fire ControlLockheed Martin MS2Lockheed Martin Security Intelligence CenterLockheed Martin Simulation Training and SupportLockheed Martin Space SystemsLockheed Martin UKLookingglass Cyber Solutions IncM5 Network Security Pty LtdMacAulay-Brown IncMainline Information SolutionsMandiantManTech International CorporationMcAfee IncMcLaren GroupMEI TechnologiesMerlin InternationalMessageLabsMi5 NetworksMicrosoft CorporationMicrotech SystemsMitsubishi Heavy Industries LtdMobile ArmorMphasiS LimitedNarus IncNational Flood Services IncNational ICT AustraliaNational Interest Security Company LLCNetApp IncNetWitness CorporationNew York TimesNICTA (formerly National ICT Australia)NitroSecurityNorthrop Grumman Aerospace SystemsNorthrop Grumman CorporationNorthrop Grumman Corporation M5 Network SecurityNorthrop Grumman Cyber Security Operations CenterNorthrop Grumman Electronic SystemsNorthrop Grumman Information SystemsNorthrop Grumman Systems CorporationNorthrop Grumman Technical ServicesNukonaOasis SystemsOdyssey SoftwareOnex PartnersOpen Kernal LabsOpenPagesOracle CorporationPAE Government Services IncPalo Alto Networks IncPanda Security SLPanda SoftwareParadigm Technologies IncPaxusPayPal IncPerot SystemsPerot Systems Government Services IncPGP CorporationPikewerks CorporationQ1 LabsQantas Airways LtdQantas Defence Services (QDS)QinetiQ Group PLCQuantum SecureQuest SoftwareRackspace IncRadiance Technologies IncRandomStorm LtdRaytheon Advanced ProgramsRaytheon Air & Missile DefenceRaytheon Aircraft CompanyRaytheon Applied Signal TechnologyRaytheon AustraliaRaytheon Combat & Sensing SystemsRaytheon CompanyRaytheon Cybersecurity SolutionsRaytheon ELCAN Optical TechnologiesRaytheon Environmental SolutionsRaytheon Fed ITRaytheon Homeland SecurityRaytheon Integrated Comms SystemsRaytheon Integrated Ground ControlRaytheon Integrated SensorsRaytheon Intelligence and Information SystemsRaytheon Missile SystemsRaytheon OperationsRaytheon Secure Information SystemsRaytheon Security & Transport SystemsRaytheon SI Government Solutions IncRaytheon Teligy IncRaytheon UKRaytheon Vision SystemsRaytheon Visual Analytics IncRed Hat IncRockwell Collins IncRSA Security IncRSA Security LLCSafeNet IncSafeNet Inc Government SolutionsSagemSalient Federal Solutions (SFS)Sandia CorporationSAP AGSaudi Arabian Oil Company (Saudi Aramco)Scale Venture PartnersScanSafeSchneider Electric SAScience Applications International Corporation (SAIC)Science, Engineering and Technology Associates CorporationScientific Research CorporationSecure ComputingSecure Digital IncSecureTechSecureWorks IncSelex CommunicationsSelex ElsagSelex ESSelex GalileoSelex Sensors and Airborne SystemsSelex Sistemi IntegratiSentrigoSerco Group PLCSiemens AGSiemens EnergySIFTSI Government Solutions IncSilver Lake PartnersTata Consultancy Services LtdThe SI OrganizationSM Consulting IncSofradirSoftScanSojitz CorporationSolana Networks IncSolutions Made Simple IncSonicWall IncSony CorporationSophos PLCSotera Defense Solutions IncSourcefire IncSperry MarineSpirent Communications PLCSRA International IncStoneRiver IncStonesoft OyjStrataviaSTRATISStratsecSTS GroupSymantec CorporationTaia Global IncTampa MicrowaveTasc IncTechnica CorporationTelecommunications Systems (TCS) IncTeligy IncThales CommunicationsThales Communications & SecurityThales Critical Information Systems and CybersecurityThales Cyber SecurityThales GroupThales Information SystemsThales Raytheon SystemsThales Secure Communications and Information SystemsThales SecurityThird BrigadeTrend Micro Australia Pty LtdTrend Micro (EMEA) LimitedTrend Micro IncTrend Micro Inc (Taiwan)Trend Micro Inc (Australia)Tripwire IncTrusteer IncTT Government Solutions IncTWD & Associates IncTwitter IncTZ LimitedUnicorn Government IncUtriUXC ConnectVangent Holding CorporationVangent IncVanguard Integrity ProfessionalsVASCO Data Security International IncVCE Company LLCVega Group PLCVenafi IncVeriSign IncVeritas CapitalVertica Systems IncVirtuataVisionixVisual Analytics IncVMware IncVodafone Group PLCVodafone McLaren MercedesVulnerability Research LabsWatchfire CorporationWaterfall Security Solutions LtdWill Electronics IncWorld Wide Technology IncYahoo! Inc
Government Agencies and Other Organisations Mentioned in this Report
Alabama Agricultural and Mechanical (A&M) UniversityBattelle Memorial InstituteCanadian National Insurance Crime Services (CANATICS)Centers for Medicare and Medicaid (USA)Central Intelligence Agency (CIA)Centre for the Protection of National Infrastructure (CPNI) - USACyber Crime Center (USA)Cyber Security Research Alliance (CSRA)Czech Technical UniversityDefence Research and Development Organisation (DRDO) - IndiaDefense Advanced Research Project Agency (DARPA) - USADefense Information Systems Agency (DISA) - USADefense Information Systems Agency, Enterprise Services Directorate - USADefense Intelligence Agency (DIA) - USADefense Technical Information Center (DTIC) - USADefense Threat Reduction Agency (USA)Elderwood GroupFederal Bureau of Investigation (FBI)Federal Government of the United StatesForeign and Commonwealth Office (UK)General Services Administration (GSA) - USGeneral Services Administration, Managed Service OfficeGeorgia Tech Applied Research CorporationGovernment of CanadaGovernment Communications Headquarters (GCHQ)Government Communications Headquarters (GCHQ), Communications Electronics Security Group (CESG)Government of GeorgiaGovernment of KuwaitGovernment of the Republic of EstoniaGovernment of the Russian FederationGovernment of Saudi ArabiaGovernment of the United KingdomGrid Protection AllianceHer Majesty's Revenue and Customs (HMRC) - UKIndian ArmyIndo-Tibetan Border PoliceInternal Revenue Service (IRS) - USA    Joint Improvised Explosive Device Defeat Organization (USA)Ministry of Commerce and Industry (Kuwait)Ministry of Commerce and Industry (Saudi Arabia)Ministry of External Affairs (India)Ministry of Home Affairs (India)Ministry of Justice (UK)National Aeronautic and Space Administration (NASA)National Geospatial Intelligence Agency (USA)National Reconnaissance Office (USA)National Security Agency (NSA)National Security Agency (NSA) High Performance Computing Infrastructure GroupNational Security Agency (NSA) Maryland Procurement OfficeNew Zealand Department of Internal AffairsNorth Atlantic Treaty OrganisationOffice of the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Homeland Defense and Americas' Security AffairsParliament of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern IrelandPeople's Liberation Army (PLA) - ChinaRoyal Saudi Naval ForcesSandia National LaboratoriesScottish GovernmentSpace and Naval Warfare Systems Command (SPAWAR) - USASpace and Naval Warfare Systems Center AtlanticSpace and Naval Warfare Systems Center PacificSpace and Naval Warfare Systems Command Program Executive Office Enterprise Information SystemsState of Ohio Computing CenterUnion Defence Force (armed forces of the UAE)US Air ForceUS Air Force 33rd Network Warfare SquadronUS Air Force 35th Intelligence SquadronU.S. Air Forces Central Command (USAFCENT)US Air Force Research LaboratoryUS Air Force Space CommandUS Air National GuardUS ArmyUS Army 160th Signals BrigadeUS Army Accessions CommandUS Army Communications Electronics, Research, Development and Engineering Center (CERDEC)US Army Information Technology AgencyUS Army Material CommandUS Army Program Executive Office Command Control Communications - Tactical (PEO C3T)US Army Redstone ArsenalUS Army Research, Development and Engineering Command (RDECOM)US Central Command (CENTCOM)US Central Command, Control Communications and Computers DirectorateUS Cyber CommandUS Defense Industrial BaseUS Defense Industrial Base Cyber Security Task ForceUS Department of DefenseUS Department of Defense, Chief Information OfficeUS Department of EnergyUS Department of Homeland Security (DHS)US Department of Homeland Security (DHS), Office of the Chief Financial Officer (OCFO)US Fleet Forces CommandUS Fleet Forces Command, Navy/Cyber ForcesUS Marine CorpsUS Marine Corps Forces Cyber CommandUS National Cybersecurity Center of Excellence (NCCoE)US Naval Supply Fleet Logistics Center NorfolkUS Naval Surface Warfare CenterUS NavyUS Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC)US Southern Command (USSOUTHCOM)US Special Operations Command (USSOCOM)WikiLeaks
To see an exec summary of this report please email Sara Peerun onsara.peerun@visiongainglobal.com
]]></text></news-item>