<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVJ-RJG1-DXDT-61GD"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>CBI claims Darda received coal 'kickback': Chargesheet reveals Congress MP got facilitation fee from Jayaswal</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>ABHISHEK BHALLA</author><text><![CDATA[The coal block allocation scam has blackened another big name.
Congress leader and media baron Vijay Darda received a kickback of Rs 24 crore from the Jayaswal Group to facilitate the allotment of a coal block, the Central Bureau of Investigation has alleged while exposing the link between the Rajya Sabha MP and mining baron Manoj Jayaswal in a chargesheet.
The CBI has claimed it has evidence that Darda accepted gratification from the Jayaswal group and used his influence to lobby government officials.
Top sources said the money was allegedly transferred from a company owned by the Jayaswal Group to another company in which Darda has a big stake.
The transfer came after AMR Iron and Steel Limited of the Jayaswal Group bagged a coal block in Maharashtra.
CBI Director Ranjit Sinha told Mail Today that the link regarding the kickback has been established. "We have evidence that money was transferred," he said.
"Officials from the state governments and the Centre who were part of the decision-making process are under the scanner and are being investigated," he added.
Charged by CBI Repeated attempts to get a reaction from Darda, the chairman of Lokmat Media Group, made no headway.
Darda has been charged under Section 9 of the Prevention of Corruption Act that deals with taking gratification for using personal influence with government officials.
SUPREME COURT DIALS CVC FOR HELP
By Mail Today Reporter
The Supreme Court on Friday sought assistance from Chief Vigilance Commission (CVC) to examine all cases in coal blocks allocation scam in which there were divergent views between the investigating officer and the CBI's head office on filing chargesheets.
It asked the Chief Vigilance Commissioner and two Vigilance Commissioners to give their suggestions whether the cases can be closed or the CBI can go ahead with the filing of charge sheets in them.
The apex court passed the order after it was informed that the agency had filed its closure report in two cases despite there being differences of opinion among the CBI officials.
The CBI also informed the court that there are till date 20 such cases where officers differ on what further action needs to be taken.
A bench headed by Justice RM Lodha directed the agency to place the documents of all 20 cases within five days before the CVC for its perusal and the corruption watchdog will file its report in four weeks.
Darda is the first politician to be charged by the CBI in the coal scam which, according to the Comptroller and Auditor General, caused a loss of Rs 1.86 lakh crore to the exchequer.
The CBI has also charged AMR Iron and Steel Private Limited, its directors Manoj Jayaswal and Vijay Darda's son Devendra for cheating and criminal conspiracy. The company was allocated the Bander coal block in Maharashtra on May 29, 2009.
Mail Today had reported in October 2012 - based on an internal communication within the Jayaswal family (see box) - that the CBI was probing kickbacks allegedly paid to Darda by the Jayaswal Group in return for coal blocks allocated.
A letter written by Manoj Jayaswal to his father and brothers said, "AMR has been allocated a coal block because of the efforts of the Lokmat Group and hence commitments made have to be honoured in true spirit. I convey that 26 per cent free equity be allotted immediately to Lokmat Group without any further delay and Lokmat Group nominees be appointed as Chairman and Director."
Darda, his son Devendra and his brother Rajendra were directors in Nagpur-based JLD Yavatmal, which had a Jayaswal connection, and in which Manoj Jayaswal was one of the directors.
The CBI is also probing possible links between Darda and former junior coal minister Santosh Bagrodia.
According to the FIR registered against AMR Iron and Steel, representatives of the company attended a meeting in Bagrodia's chamber on July 18, 2008.
The CBI's FIR states that the group was allocated five coal blocks on the date of application but they concealed this while applying for the Bander coal block.
Sources said Darda also wrote a letter to the Prime Minister's Office, asking for a coal block to be allocated to AMR even though the company was not eligible for the allocation.
The letter written by Manoj Jayaswal also mentioned that the settlement of ownership of the remaining 14 per cent shares was be decided by "Shri Shriprakashji".
Coal Minister Sriprakash Jaiswal, however, has denied that he had anything to do with the matter.
He said he was never made an offer to arbitrate nor did he enter into any such agreement with anyone.
The CBI registered a case against AMR in September 2009 in the first batch of five FIRs in the coal scam.
Since then, the agency has registered 16 cases, while closure reports have been filed in two.
The CBI has also has filed chargesheets in two cases.
]]></text></news-item>