<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVJ-CT61-F0CC-S2JS"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Manroy PLC Preliminary Results -22-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Under section 408 of the Companies Act 2006, the Company is exempt from the requirement to present its own profit and loss account. Under Financial Reporting Standard 1, the Company is exempt from the requirement to prepare a cash flow statement in respect of its own operations, on the grounds that the consolidated cash flow statement included in these published consolidated financial statements includes the cash flow of the Company. The Company has taken advantage of the exemption in FRS8, "Related Party Disclosures" from the requirement to disclose related party transactions on the grounds that it has presented this in its consolidated financial statements.
Results of the Company The loss for the Company during the year ended 30 September 2013 was GBP6,595,000 (2012: profit GBP97,000). Going concern review The provisions of the Combined Code require directors to confirm whether, after making appropriate enquires, they have reasonable expectations that the Company has adequate financial resources to continue in operational existence for the foreseeable future. As part of their regular financial management of the Company, the Directors review the detailed cash flow projections of the Group. These cash flow projections include the net cash flows arising from operations, capital expenditure proposals and the financial effect of planned business expansion and disposals. The projections take into account all bank and other financing facilities available to the Group and assess the cash flow adequacy of the Group on a month by month basis for a fifteen month forward period. After making such enquiries as they consider appropriate, the Directors consider that there is a reasonable expectation that the Group has adequate cash and related financial resources to continue in business for the foreseeable future. The Directors have therefore adopted the going concern basis in the preparation of the financial statements for the year ended 30 September 2013. Revenue recognition Revenue represents income recognised by the Company in respect of management fees and services charged to other Group companies, exclusive of trade discounts and Value Added Tax. Foreign currencies Monetary assets and liabilities denominated in foreign currencies are translated into Sterling at rates of exchange ruling at the balance sheet date. Transactions in foreign currencies during the year are translated into Sterling at the rate ruling on the date of the transaction. Exchange gains and losses arising on transactions are recognised in the consolidated income statement in the year they arise. For the purpose of presenting consolidated financial statements, the assets and liabilities of the Company's foreign operations are translated at exchange rates prevailing on the balance sheet date. Income and expense items are translated at the average exchange rates for the period, unless exchange rates fluctuate significantly during that period, in which case the exchange rate at dates of transactions are used. Exchange differences arising on the translation of assets and liabilities of the Company's foreign operations at exchange rates prevailing on the balance sheet date are recognised in other comprehensive income. Operating leases Rentals under operating leases are charged on a straight line basis over the lease term. Benefits received and receivable as an incentive to sign an operating lease arerecognisedon a straight line basis over the period until the rent is expected to be adjusted to the prevailing market rate. Dividends Interim dividends paid are recognised in the year in which the payment is made. Final dividend payments in respect of a financial year are recognised as a liability in the year in which the dividend payment is approved by the Company's Shareholders. Carrying value of payables and receivables Receivables and payables are recorded initially at fair value. Subsequent measurement is stated at amortised cost. In most cases trade receivables and payables are stated at the amount expected to be paid or received, although any trade payables or receivables held for a significant period may be discounted. Cash and cash equivalents Cash and cash equivalents consist of cash balances, deposits held at banks and other short-term highly liquid investments with original maturities of three months or less, and bank overdrafts. Bank overdrafts are shown within bank loans in current liabilities on the balance sheet. Bank overdrafts that are repayable on demand and which form an integral part of the Company's cash management are included as a component of cash and cash equivalents in the consolidated statement of cash flows. Financial liabilities and equity Financial liabilities and equity instruments are classified according to the substance of the contractual arrangements entered into. An equity instrument is any contract that evidences a residual interest in the assets of the Company after deducting all of its liabilities. Taxation Current tax is based on taxable profit for the year and is calculated using tax rates that have been enacted or substantially enacted. Taxable profit differs from net profit as reported in the income statement because it is adjusted for items of income or expense that are taxable or tax deductible in other years (temporary differences) and items that are never taxable or deductible (permanent differences). Temporary differences principally arise from using different balance sheet values for assets and liabilities than their respective tax base values. Share options For equity-settled share-based payment transactions, the Company measures their value in accordance with FRS20, with the corresponding increase in equity, by reference to the fair value of equity instruments granted. The fair value of equity instruments is measured at the date of grant using the Black Scholes method. The expense is apportioned over the vesting period of the financial instrument and is based on the numbers which are expected to vest and the fair value of the financial instruments at the date of grant. If equity instruments vest immediately, the full expense is recognised immediately. Investment in subsidiary and associated undertakings The interest of the Company in shares of subsidiary and associated undertakings is stated at fair value less provision for impairment. The carrying values of fixed asset investments are reviewed for impairment if events or changes in circumstances indicate the carrying value may not be recoverable. Impairment is recognised by comparing the carrying amount to the higher of the recoverable amount and value in use. 29. Directors' emoluments
G. P. Bottomley was the highest paid Director of the Company, and received GBP198,000 (2012: GBP198,000) inclusive of pension contributions during the year ended 30 September 2013. Further details of Directors' emoluments are provided in the Report on remuneration of Directors. 30. Investments
All subsidiaries and associated undertakings of the Company are wholly owned, are registered in England and Wales and are incorporated and operate in the United Kingdom. The subsidiaries and associated undertakings of the Company at 30 September 2013, after reflecting the adjusting post balance sheet events referred to in note 22, were as follows:-
]]></text></news-item>