<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVK-PK61-DXY4-X40J"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Warning: Gas Leaks and Aging Pipes</title><source>The New York Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[To the Editor:
Re ''Beneath Cities, a Decaying Tangle of Gas Pipes'' (front page, March 24):
The recent deadly explosion in East Harlem reminds us of the danger of our crumbling natural gas pipeline infrastructure, and should serve as a call for rapid replacement of leaky lines. But smaller, nonexplosive leaks are not ''harmless'': methane, the main ingredient of natural gas, is also a potent climate pollutant.
New York is not alone. Recent studies in Boston and Washington have detected thousands of gas leaks around each city, further indicating the vast magnitude of the problem. Leaks from these unreliable pipes nationwide harm the climate as much as all the carbon dioxide from power plants in New Jersey.
Upgrading this aging infrastructure can reduce methane emissions by 95 percent. This is a matter of national public safety, a priority for protecting the climate and an opportunity to create jobs, and must be immediately addressed at all levels -- by state utility regulators, by the Environmental Protection Agency and by other federal agencies.
ARMOND COHEN Exec. Director, Clean Air Task Force Boston, March 24, 2014
To the Editor:
One way to increase vigilance in spotting gas leaks is to look for damaged vegetation like dead trees, dead grass and dead shrubs.
As an undergrad at Boston University in 2011, I went on several gas-leak surveys with my professor and a gas industry expert. I learned that it was often possible to identify a gas leak just by examining the nearby plants.
Leaking methane in the ground deprives the soil of oxygen, which the flora need to absorb nutrients. In addition to recognizing the smell of gas, we should make people more aware of this information so that they can spot the signs of a potential leak.
Furthermore, utilities should routinely screen for leaks by identifying areas with dying vegetation. Of course, as those of us without green thumbs can attest, distressed vegetation can have many causes, but it's better to be safe than sorry.
COURTNEY CARROLL New York, March 24, 2014
The writer is a graduate student studying environmental health at the Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University.
http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/29/opinion/warning-gas-leaks-and-aging-pipes.html
]]></text></news-item>