<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVK-FKW1-DY9P-N10C"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Gleision rescuers saw after explosion freed water up to roof flood, court told</title><source>The Western Mail</source><author>Robin Turner</author><text><![CDATA[AROUND 650,000 gallons of water, more than in an Olympic swimming pool, engulfed the Gleision Colliery in just a few seconds, Swansea Crown Court court heard yesterday.
Gregg Taylor QC, prosecuting, said the fatal "inrush" happened when mine manager Malcolm Fyfield and his men blasted through a 2m-thick seam of coal on the morning of September 15, 2011, in an attempt to break through to old workings so a better ventilation system could be opened up in the 100-year drift mine near Pontardawe in the Swansea Valley.
The cascading water flushed away pit props and even crushed a heavy, metal coal conveyor - known as a panzer - against the pit roof.
Rescue workers found water up to the roof of the mine.
But Mr Taylor said Fyfield, 58, of Caerhenllys, Cwmllynfell, who denies manslaughter through gross negligence of the four colliers who died in the inrush, along with other workers, had "got it into their heads" there was only a small amount of water in the old workings they were blasting into.
A day earlier, he explained, the men had made a small drill hole into the old workings and according to one worker, David "Jake" Wyatt, what came out was like a "tap turned half-on" but the prosecutor said the large volume of water in the old workings, which had built up since 1984, was heavily silted and the silt had blocked water on the other side from bursting through the narrow drill hole.
He said it gave the impression there was not a lot of water on the other side.
Earlier, the jury was shown mine maps which clearly indicated "underground water" in the old workings the men were blasting into.
Colliers Charles Breslin, 62, of Cwmllynfell; Philip Hill, 44, of Resolven, the shot firer who detonated the charges which led to the inrush; Garry Jenkins, 39, of Rhiwfawr; and David Powell, 50, of Godre'Graig, died when the water burst into the area they were sheltering in.
Mr Taylor also claimed yesterday the men were not far enough away when the charges were detonated.
He told the jury explosives regulations dictated they should have been at least 100m away when the "shots" into the 2m coal seam were fired. The stall (working area), where some of the men remained including the mine manager himself when the charge was detonated, was only 60m away. Mr Taylor said: "On a day like this, which the prosecution say is a special day, where they knew they have made contact with older workings and on the other side of the coal seam there was a place where there was water, these regulations should have been compiled with exactly."
Fyfield escaped from the mine going through mud and sludge and suffering cuts, while Mr Wyatt managed to run to the mine entrance with water "following behind him".
Mr Wyatt saw Garry Jenkins behind him but the water overtook Mr Jenkins at a point 60m along a mine roadway.
The dead men's bodies were discovered a day later.
Mr Taylor said: "It seems they'd got it into their heads there would be very little water there."
But, referring to the exploratory drill hole they made, he said: "The small amount of water they saw coming through was because the narrow hole was blocked by silt. It would appear Malcolm Fyfield took the small flow to mean there was very little water there."
The world's media focused on the incident as attempts were made to rescue the men. The company which owned the colliery, MNS Mining Ltd, is also denying four counts of corporate manslaughter.
The firm denies causing the death of the four miners by failing to ensure a safe system of work was in place.
Yesterday the jury heard workers at the pit had expressed concern at the plan to break into the old workings during "canteen talk".
And the jury was told a previous manager of the pit, Ray Thomas, said if the Mines Inspectorate had learned of the scheme to enter the old workings without a system of drilling advance boreholes, it would have been stopped. Mr Taylor, continuing his opening of the Crown's case against Fyfield and MNS, said: "Daniel Giles, a surface worker at the pit, the son of David Powell, and others all had conversations about where they were going, there was talk in the canteen about the old workings and it was thought they would not get through to them because they were filled with water and would need to be pumped out."
Mr Taylor has told the jury "advanced boreholes" should have been used when the men were close to breaking through the coal seam to the old workings using long drill bits so they could assess how much water was ahead.
But instead, he said, smaller "ordinary drills" were used.
Mr Taylor said: "On October 18, 2011, Mr Fyfield told police he had not been advance drilling, all he was doing was drilling through to the old workings to determine how thick the coal seam was before getting to the old workings, he would know how far he'd have to go then."
Later, Mr Taylor explained how Fyfield took over as Gleision Colliery manager early in July, 2011, and had a three-day "hand-over" session with former manager Ray Thomas.
Mr Taylor said: "Mr Thomas told him, if it needed telling, that the old workings were full of water and if they were to be connected with the old workings would have to be 'de-watered'.
"Mr Thomas said advance boring would be needed with long holes to test if there was water behind where you needed to get to and he said if the Mines Inspectorate knew he intended heading towards the old workings without advanced bore holes he would have stopped it." The court heard, after taking over as manager, Fyfield asked mine surveyor John Brosnan if he could mine coal in a so-called precautionary area.
He was told he could, but that he would need two things in place, a water management scheme involving electric pumps to take water out of the area and a Precautions against Inrush Scheme (PAI) scheme, both of which would have required approval from the Mines Inspectorate.
The court also heard yesterday of a meeting between Fyfield and Neath Port Talbot Council planning officer Alan Rees a month before the inrush.
Mr Taylor said: "Mr Rees asked if he had in place the PAI scheme and he said he had and he was asked if he'd contacted the Mines Inspectorate and he said he had."
The case continues.
]]></text></news-item>