<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVK-2961-DYRK-D0XT"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Identity Theft and Payment Card Fraud Bankroll Other Crimes</title><source>Canada NewsWire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Fraud Prevention Remains Top Priority for Police and Financial Services
ORILLIA, ON, March 28, 2014 /CNW/ - As part of Fraud Prevention Month, the Ontario Provincial Police (OPP) believes greater awareness can help prevent consumers from becoming victims of fraud through identity theft and payment cards.
Typical identity theft cases include situations where government documents -- such as drivers' licences, health cards, Social Insurance Number (S.I.N.) cards and birth certificates -- have been unlawfully obtained or forged. Criminals can use your stolen identity documents to:
According to the Canadian Anti-Fraud Centre (CAFC), in 2013 there were 6,275 complaints of identity theft in Canada. Of those complaints, 4,898 victims were identified and their combined financial losses exceeded $11-million.
The consequences of having your identity compromised can have lasting effects on your life including potential employers, individual finances and credit ratings, and your dealings with government and other agencies.
The OPP Organized Crime Enforcement Bureau - Identity Crimes Unit also makes use of stronger legislative tools with which to charge criminals for possessing the personal information of others and prevent it from being used for fraud or theft.
If you or someone you know has been a victim of identity or payment card fraud, contact your local police service or Crime Stoppers at 1-800-222-8477 (TIPS).
FRAUD Recognize it Report it Stop it.
QUOTES
"Criminals are able to convert your stolen personal information into documents and other tools to further support other crimes. Managing your personal information wisely and cautiously can help prevent identity theft."                          - Deputy Commissioner Scott Tod, OPP Investigations and Organized Crime Command
"Knowledge is power. Consumers can take some basic steps to better protect themselves from becoming a victim, such as never giving out personal information over the phone or over the internet if you are not sure with whom you are dealing, or by only carrying the identification documents that you need."                          - Detective Inspector Paul Beesley, OPP Anti-Rackets Branch
FAST FACTS ABOUT FRAUD
LEARN MORE
OPP - March is Fraud Prevention Month
OPP Crime Prevention Section -- Tip Sheet
The OPP Identity Crimes Unit has a number of tips and contacts to help you avoid becoming a victim of identity theft at this link.
Canadian Anti-Fraud Centre (formerly Phonebusters) - Identity Theft
For a Canadian Anti-Fraud Centre Identity Theft Victims' Guide, click here (PDF file)
MEDIA NOTE: This is the last of four weekly OPP media releases on various criminal activities as part of Fraud Prevention Month.
SOURCE Ontario Provincial Police
]]></text></news-item>