<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVK-JJY1-DXDT-629C"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Gleision Colliery trial: Trapped miners were engulfed by 650,000 gallons of water in seconds, court hears; The resulting explosive "inrush" of water, more than that in an Olympic swimming pool, flushed away pit props and even crushed a metal coal conveyor against the mine roof</title><source>walesonline.co.uk</source><author>By Robin Turner</author><text><![CDATA[The miners who died in the Swansea Valley Gleision Colliery tragedy were engulfed by 650,000 gallons of water "in a few" seconds,  Swansea Crown Court heard today.
Gregg Taylor QC, prosecuting, used a DVD animated representation to describe how mine manager Malcolm Fyfield and his men blasted through a 2m thick seam of coal on the morning of September 15, 2011, in an attempt to break through to old workings so a circular ventilation system could be opened up in the 100-year coal mine near Pontardawe.
The resulting explosive "inrush" of water, more than that in an Olympic swimming pool, flushed away pit props and even crushed a metal coal conveyor known as a panzer against the mine roof.
But Mr Taylor alleged Fyfield, 58, of Caerhenllys, Cwmllynfell, who denies manslaughter of the four colliers who died through gross negligence, along with other workers, had "got it into their heads" there was only a small amount of water in the old workings they were blasting into.
A day earlier, he explained, the men made a small drill hole into the old workings and according to one worker, David "Jake" Wyatt, what came out was like a "tap turned half on" but the prosecutor said the large volume of water in the old workings, which had built up since 1984, was heavily silted and the silt blocked water on the other side from bursting through the narrow drill hole.
Earlier, the jury was shown mine maps which clearly indicated "underground water" in the old workings the men were blasting into.
Colliers Charles Breslin, 62, of Cwmllynfell, Philip Hill, 44, of Resolven, the shot firer who detonated the charges which led to the inrush, Garry Jenkins, 39, of Rhiwfawr and David Powell, 50, of Godre'Graig, died when the water burst into the area they were sheltering in.
Mr Taylor also claimed today the men were not far enough away when the charges were detonated.
He told the jury explosives regulations dictated they should have been at least 100m away when the "shots" into the 2m coal seam were fired. The stall (working area), where some of the men remained including the mine manager himself when the charge was detonated, was only 60m away.
Mr Taylor said: "On a day like this, which the prosecution say is a special day, where they knew they have made contact with older workings and on the other side of the coal seam there was a place where there was water, these regulations should have been compiled with exactly."
Mr Fyfield escaped from the mine going through mud and sludge and suffering cuts while Mr Wyatt managed to run to the mine entrance with water "following behind him". Mr Wyatt saw Garry Jenkins behind him but the water overtook Mr Jenkins at a point 60m along a mine roadway.
Mr Taylor said: "It seems they'd got it into their heads there would be very little water there."
But, referring to the exploratory drill hole of they made, he said: "The small amount of water they saw coming through was because the narrow hole was blocked by silt. It would appear Malcolm Fyfield took the small flow to mean there was very little water there."
The world's media focused on the incident as attempts were made to rescue the men whose bodies were later found in the mine.
The company which owned the colliery, MNS Mining Ltd, is also denying four counts of corporate manslaughter.
The firm denies causing the death of the four miners by failing to ensure a safe system of work was in place.
The case continues.
]]></text></news-item>