<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVK-DWJ1-DYTG-N3C3"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>WHAT THE PAPERS SAY</title><source>Press Association Mediapoint</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EXPRESS:
MISSING PLANE: DRAMATIC NEW TWIST
The first wreckage from the missing Malaysian airliner could be recovered today after a dramatic switch in the area of the search.
FIRST SAME-SEX MARRIAGES TAKE PLACE IN BRITAIN
Gay couples last night raced to tie the knot in Britain's first ever same-sex wedding ceremonies in what David Cameron called ``an important moment for our country''.
STARR LAWYERS HIT OUT AT POLICE
Freddie Starr's lawyer attacked Scotland Yard yesterday after the comedian was bailed by police for the ninth time.
Sport:
WITH THIS LOT FERGIE WOULD STRUGGLE
David Moyes claims even Sir Alex Ferguson would have struggled to turn Manchester United into Premier League title contenders this season.
SHERWOOD SAYS SPURS MUST LOOK CLOSER TO HOME
Tim Sherwood has told Daniel Levy he needs to ditch his foreign policy to get the players Tottenham need to break into the top four.
i:
BISHOP: CHILDREN ARE 'GOING TO SCHOOL HUNGRY'
Children growing up in poverty are going to school hungry each day, struggling to concentrate and falling behind in their lessons, one of Britain's leading churchmen has claimed.
ONLY 6% OF BEDROOM TAX TENANTS FOUND SMALLER HOME
Just a fraction of the people affected by the so-called ``bedroom tax'' have moved to a smaller home as a result of the policy, a survey of councils and housing associations has concluded.
INQUIRY INTO UNION ACTIVITIES CURTAILED
The Government has scaled back a review into allegations of union intimidation following an internal row.
City:
LEAK INQUIRY OPENED AFTER BILLIONS WIPED OFF INSURERS
The City's most powerful watchdog last night humiliatingly launched an independent inquiry into a briefing one of its directors gave to a newspaper that wiped billions off the value of stock exchange-listed insurance companies.
SALES RISE AT STAMP DEALER
Stanley Gibbons, the rare stamp dealership, enjoyed a 16 per cent rise in sales to £42m last year.
TELEGRAPH:
CABINET MINISTER ABUSED EXPENSES
The Culture Secretary abused the parliamentary expenses system by over-claiming for her mortgage and then failing to co-operate fully with an investigation into her conduct, The Daily Telegraph can disclose.
GAY PRIESTS URGED TO DEFY THE CHURCH
Homosexual clergy should follow their conscience and defy the Church of England's restrictions on same-sex marriage, a prominent bishop said last night as the first ceremonies took place today.
'PLANNING MAFIA' RUINING RURAL AREAS
Mafia-style behaviour in the planning system is 'traumatising' the English countryside, the chairman of the National Trust has suggested.
City:
FAMILIES RAID SAVINGS AS COST OF LIVING RISES
Households across the UK are increasingly raiding their savings to fund spending as wage growth continues to lag behind increases in the cost of living.
INVESTORS FLIGHT KNOCKS £2.4BN OFF VALUE OF INSURERS
Investors took fright at the prospect of a regulatory review into Britain's life insurance industry yesterday, knocking about £2.4bn off the market value of the biggest insurers.
GUARDIAN:
INDEPENDENT SCOTLAND 'MAY KEEP POUND'
A currency union will eventually be agreed between an independent Scotland and the remainder of the UK to ensure fiscal and economic stability on both sides of the border, according to a government minister at the heart of the pro-union campaign.
FIRST IT WAS GLACIERS, NOW YOUR COFFEE FACES CLIMATE THREAT
Rich western urbanites expecting to dodge the impacts of climate change should prepare for a jolt: global warming is leading to bad, expensive coffee.
REVENUE ORDERED TO HAND £1.2BN TO BARCLAY BROTHERS AFTER VAT DEFEAT
HM Revenue & Customs has been ordered by the high court to pay £1.2bn to the business empire of Sir Frederick and Sir David Barclay in order to settle a dispute over a VAT error dating back over 40 years.
City:
FCA FACES LEGAL INQUIRY AS ZOMBIE FUNDS ANNOUNCEMENT SENDS SHARES PLUNGING
The Financial Conduct Authority faces a legal inquiry into its bungled announcement of an industry investigation into 30m pension and investment policies, which saw shares in leading British insurers tumble yesterday.
UK CURRENT ACCOUNT DEFICIT HITS £22BN AND RAISES ALARM OVER RECOVERY
Britain was warned over the sustainability of the recovery yesterday after official figures showed the country's trading position was much worse than expected and separate data suggested consumers were running down their savings.
TIMES:
BANKS MUST GIVE FRAUD VICTIMS THEIR MONEY BACK
Hundreds of thousands of victims of card fraud wrongly denied refunds could finally get their money back in a crackdown on banks that try to wriggle out of paying compensation.
UNION LEADER FACES RE-ELECTION INQUIRY AFTER 'GHOST' VOTE CLAIM
The head of Britain's biggest trade union is to face a formal hearing over claims that his re-election to his post was unfair.
REDUCE NIGHT-TIME WARD MOVES, ORDERS NHS BOSS
Moving patients around hospitals in the middle of the night strikes at the heart of NHS efforts ``to treat all patients with respect and compassion'', health chiefs have been told.
City:
INSURERS FORCE REGULATOR INTO 'ZOMBIE' FUNDS CLIMBDOWN
The City regulator was forced into an humiliating climbdown yesterday after it was accused of creating a ``disorderly market'' in the shares of Britain's biggest pensions and insurance providers.
TRY, TRY AND TRY AGAIN, OSBORNE TELLS FIRMS
Britain must get rid of the stigma surrounding business failure and become more like America, according to the Chancellor, as he pledged to look into the problem of credit histories preventing businesses from moving banks.
SUN:
TUBERCULOSIS REX
A child has caught tuberculosis from their pet dog - in the first case of its kind ever seen in Britain.
OUR TOP FAN IS 6 FEET SUNDER
A devoted Sun reader has finally made headline news - with a mocked-up front page on his grave.
CAM: GAY MARRIAGE MAKES THE UK BETTER
Gay weddings became legal at midnight - and make Britain a ``better country'', the PM said.
Sport:
FERGIE LEFT ME WITH OAPS
David Moyes last night insisted he inherited a bunch of OAPS from Alex Ferguson.
JOSE: IT'S YOUR FOY-LT
Jose Mourinho risks further FA trouble after insisting ref Chris Foy will be to blame if Chelsea lose the title race.
MAIL:
I CAUGHT TB FROM MY PET KITTEN
A teenager told last night of her horrific ordeal of catching TB from her pet kitten.
DOCTORS SNAPPED MY UNBORN BABY'S ARM IN TWO... TO SAVE HER LIFE
A baby who was so big she became trapped during birth was saved by medics who broke her arm.
MILLIONAIRE OFFERED WIFE £83 PAYOUT... THEN HANDED £250K TO POLE DANCER LOVER
A businessman accused of trying to deprive his former wife of a huge payout gave his pole dancer girlfriend £250,000-worth of shares in his company.
Sport:
FERGIE WOULD HAVE FAILED
David Moyes last night fuelled the debate on his dismal Manchester United season by insisting even Sir Alex Ferguson could not have done better.
'SCHOLES KNOWS NOTHING'
Arsene Wenger has hit back at Paul Scholes after the former Manchester United midfielder claimed Arsenal are 'a million miles away from winning the title'.
INDEPENDENT:
THE MOST EXPENSIVE FREE SCHOOL IN BRITAIN?
The Education Secretary, Michael Gove, has approved a plan to spend £45m on a free school, making it almost certainly the most expensive in the country even though it has just 500 students, The Independent has learnt.
OFFICERS UNDER INVESTIGATION OVER 'MASSAGED' CRIME STATISTICS
Four police officers were under investigation last night after a criminal claimed he was falsely persuaded to accept responsibility for 500 burglaries, in the latest crime recording scandal to hit the country's biggest force.
GOVE'S APPROACH TO CRITICS IS 'REMARKABLY UNINTELLIGENT'
Two years on and Sir David Bell, Michael Gove's first Permanent Secretary at the Department for Education, is not afraid to speak out about the way the country's education system is being run.
City:
BARCLAY BROTHERS EMPIRE INFLICTS 'BIGGEST EVER' DEFEAT ON TAXMAN
The billionaire Barclay brothers, owners of the Telegraph newspapers, are set for a £1.2bn payout from the British taxpayer for their Littlewoods mail order business after winning a landmark court victory yesterday.
WATCHDOG ACCUSED ON WIMPING OUT ON NEW LOAN RULES
MPs and consumer groups have criticised the City watchdog for being toothless ahead of it taking over responsibility for payday lenders from Tuesday.
MIRROR:
I'VE LIED TO SAVE REAL MURDERER
Serial killer Joanna Dennehy has claimed she took the rap for a murder she did not commit.
KATE'S NOT WITHERING
Tickets for Kate Bush's first live shows in 35 years sold out in less than 15 minutes yesterday.
BBC FACES £1M FIGHT OVER JEZZA 'RACISM'
An actress is threatening to sue the BBC for £1million after Jeremy Clarkson allegedly used a racist word on Top Gear.
Sport:
FERGIE WOULD LOSE WITH THIS LOT
David Moyes says even Sir Alex Ferguson would have had difficulty making Manchester United competitive this season.
YA GOING TO WIN THE LOT
Manuel Pellegrini has backed Manchester City's free-scoring midfield colossus Yaya Toure to be crowned player of the year.
STAR:
INVASION OF ZE GERMAN RATS
Mutant German super rats with massive fangs have Britain in their sights after terrorising a town within striking distance of the Channel Tunnel.
£250k TO AID SINGLE FAMILY
Taxpayers have forked out £250,000 to help just one problem family under a Government scheme.
KYLIE'S LIPS ARE A POUT TO EXPLODE
Pop star Kylie Minogue horrified fans as she debuted a new trout pout.
Sport:
FERGIE WOULD HAVE FLOPPED WITH THIS LOT
David Moyes last night claimed even Sir Alex Ferguson would be struggling as Manchester United manager this season.
WENGER WON'T PICK TOP GUN
Arsene Wenger last night insisted that he will not be picking his successor.
]]></text></news-item>