<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVK-JJY1-DXDT-631C"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Gleision Colliery trial: 'Workers had expressed concerns at plans during 'canteen talk''; Trapped miners were engulfed by 650,000 gallons of water in seconds, Swansea Crown Court has been told</title><source>walesonline.co.uk</source><author>By Robin Turner</author><text><![CDATA[Workers at a colliery where four miners died after 650,000 gallons of water cascaded into the pit in a few seconds during an operation to link up with flooded old workings had expressed concern at the plan during "canteen talk", Swansea Crown Court has heard today.
And the jury was told a previous manager of the pit, Ray Thomas, said if the Mines Inspectorate had learned of the scheme to enter the old workings without a system of drilling advance boreholes, it would have been stopped.
Malcolm Fyfield, 58, of Caerhenllys in the Swansea Valley, who was the manager of Gleision Colliery when the fatal "inrush" of water happened, denies the manslaughter through gross negligence of experienced colliers Philip Hill, 44, Charles Breslin, 62, David Powell, 50, and Garry Jenkins, 39.
They died on September 15, 2011 as they blasted through a coal seam to the old workings.
Gregg Taylor QC, prosecuting, told the court the idea of linking with the old workings had been to create a second mine exit and to improve ventilation throughout the 100-year-old pit.
Mine owners MNS Mining Ltd also deny four counts of corporate manslaughter.
Mr Taylor, continuing his opening of the crown's case against Fyfield and MNS, said: "Daniel Giles, a surface worker at the pit, the son of David Powell, and others all had conversations about where they were going, there was talk in the canteen about the old workings and it was thought they would not get through to them because they were filled with water and would need to be pumped out."
Mr Taylor has told the jury "advanced boreholes" should have been used when the men were close to breaking through the coal seam to the old workings using long drill bits so they could assess how much water was ahead.
But instead, he said, smaller "ordinary drills" were used. Mr Taylor said a small amount of water came through the narrow test holes like "a tap turned half on" but he said the water on the other side of the seam was heavily silted and the narrowness of the holes prevented it gushing through leading Fyfield and the miners to believe there may not have been a large amount of water on the other side.
Mr Taylor said: "On October 18, 2011, Mr Fyfield told police he had not been advance drilling, all he was doing was drilling through to the old workings to determine how thick the coal seam was before getting to the old workings, he would know how far he'd have to go then."
Later Mr Taylor explained how Fyfield took over as Gleision Colliery manager early in July, 2011, and had a three-day "handover" session with former manager Ray Thomas.
Mr Taylor said: "Mr Thomas told him, if it needed telling, that the old workings were full of water and if they were to be connected with the old workings would have to be 'de-watered'.
"Mr Thomas said advance boring would be needed with long holes to test if there was water behind where you needed to get to and he said if the Mines Inspectorate knew he intended heading towards the old workings without advanced bore holes he would have stopped it."
The court heard, after taking over as manager, Fyfield asked mine surveyor John Brosnan if he could mine coal in a so-called precautionary area.
He was told he could, but that he would need two things in place, a water management scheme involving electric pumps to take water out of the area and a Precautions against Inrush Scheme (PAI) scheme, both of which would have required approval from the Mines Inspectorate.
The case continues.
]]></text></news-item>