<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVK-CJ81-DXKH-N175"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Gibney, Anthony &amp; Flaherty, Llp: Immigration Spotlight: The Biggest EB-5 Visa Scam in History- United States Securities and Exchange Commission v. Anshoo Sethi, A Chicago Convention Center, LLC and Intercontinental Regional Center Trust of Chicago, LLC</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
The biggest EB-5 Visa scam in history became front and center news in February 2014 when the United States Securities and Exchange Commission ("SEC") filed a complaint with the U.S. District Court in Illinois against Anshoo Sethi and the two companies he owned, A Chicago Convention Center, LLC, and Intercontinental Regional Center Trust of Chicago, LLC. The claim- Mr. Sethi used the above-mentioned companies to develop and undertake a large-scale investment scheme to exploit the EB-5 visa program and defraud investors seeking to obtain a legal path to U.S. permanent residency.
Mr. Sethi's fraudulent plan involved luring and soliciting investors in China, seeking a route to U.S. permanent residency through the EB-5 visa program, by selling them securities, interests in one of his companies, under the guise that their funds would be helping to finance and build the 'World's First Zero Carbon Emission Platinum LEED certified' hotel and conference center in the Chicago area. Mr. Sethi sold more than $145 million in securities and collected $11 million in "administrative fees" from more than 250 investors for this project. Mr. Sethi misled the investors, providing false assurances that several major hotel chains had signed on to the project, that all necessary permits to begin construction had been received, and purporting that the project was likely to generate over 8,000 jobs. Despite the fact that Mr. Sethi claimed that the "administrative fees" collected were refundable to an investor, in the event of a U.S. visa denial, it was found that he had already spent over 90 percent of these fees collected and that some of the misappropriated funds had been directly sent to Mr. Sethi's personal bank account in Hong Kong.
On March 17, 2014, the United States District Court for the Northern District of Illinois presented its ruling; The Defendants were required to put an immediate stop to the project and pay civil penalties to the SEC in the amount of $3.9 million and administrative fees to the investors to the tune of $11.5 million. Having collected close to $158 million at the time of this ruling, it is questionable whether the penalties in this case were harsh enough.
The EB-5 visa program has been quite successful, with nearly 9,000 cases approved between 2005 and 2012, an approval rate of 81% on average. Nonetheless, this serves as an important reminder to EB-5 investors to do their due diligence before investing in an EB-5 project. Investors should be attuned to any suspicious activity, stay actively involved in the project in which they are investing, ask the responsible EB-5 project leader a plethora of questions, and seek the assistance and advice of EB-5 experts.
For more information on the EB-5 visa program please visit http://www.gibney.com/practice-areas/immigration/eb-5-program. If you have any questions, please contact your designated Gibney representative at immigrationalerts@gibney.com
click http://www.gibney.com/news/read/dc169849c6130deaa2a7edc9dd5c462757cf6d5e
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
26 March 2014: Gibney, Anthony & Flaherty, Llp: Immigration Alert: United States Citizenship & Immigration Services Announces Premium Processing Delay for H-1B CAP FY 2015 Cases
In anticipation of a large volume of H-1B cap FY 2015 filings, United States Citizenship & Immigration Services (USCIS) announced that the fifteen-calendar day period for adjudication of cap petitions filed via premium processing will not begin later than April 28th. The mandated cap on H-1B visas FY 2015 is 65,000, although 6,800 of these visas are set aside each year for the H-1B1 program.
click http://www.gibney.com/news/read/bc82f8e4f30c97b71d8f017f67cbd93f0f9fd615
23 March 2014: Gibney Professionals to Participate in Totally Expat Show 2014 in New York City
Gibney Immigration Partners Stephen J.O. Maltby and Ellen Poreda and Gibney Senior Counsel, Deborah Davy, will be attending the 2014 Totally Expat Show, held by the Forum for Expatriate Management (FEM), at the Metropolitan Pavilion. Ms. Davy will be speaking, along with other field experts, as part of an immigration panel entitled, "What you need to know about the latest compliance changes." The panel discussion will focus on current trends and the latest changes in immigration compliance around the world. Mr.
click http://www.gibney.com/news/read/f61fb27a2d2e9d3be318f84e7b6ffa63244b87a5
11 March 2014: Gibney, Anthony & Flaherty, Llp: Immigration Alert: Projections on U.S. EB-5 Visa Availability
According to the latest update from Charlie W. Oppenheim, Chief of Immigrant Control & Reporting of the State Department, visa availability in the Employment-Based Fifth Preference Category (EB-5) will stay "Current" for the foreseeable future. Mr. Oppenheim further stated that because the EB-5 category is presently underutilized by about 15%, sudden and unanticipated changes in demand are not likely to cause retrogression.
click http://www.gibney.com/news/read/f02c99e5befdc74455da67e8ff7faed16a5ff0c3
11 March 2014: Gibney, Anthony & Flaherty, Llp: Global Alert- Israel: Work Sanctions Abruptly Stop Visa Processing at Israeli Consulates
On March 4, 2014, the Israeli Ministry of Foreign Affairs stopped all visa processing at Israeli Consulates due to a year-long labor dispute with diplomats. Israeli diplomats may no longer engage with foreign representatives or make official visits of any kind, nor may they provide any consular services including adjudications of visa applications. It is uncertain when the Israeli Consulates will resume consular services and visa processing.
click http://www.gibney.com/news/read/85184397ba17b1bed8ad3df8670bf1870d646415
10 March 2014: Gibney, Anthony & Flaherty, Llp: Immigration Alert: April 2014 Visa Bulletin Released
The U.S. Department of State (DOS) has published the April 2014 Visa Bulletin. As we saw in the March Visa Bulletin, the EB-2 category for China has advanced by approximately one month, while the EB-2 visa priority cut-off date for India remains unchanged. Similarly, the EB-3 category shows slight movement by approximately a month, for most countries, while the visa priority cut-off date for India remains September 15, 2003.
click http://www.gibney.com/news/read/2075b7bf84e592e3d7236379988aad0c224aeeff
]]></text></news-item>