<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVK-2VC1-F0NV-F1SD"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Union formed, paychecks next?</title><source>Coldwater Daily Reporter (Michigan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Wednesday's ruling by a Chicago-based Regional National Labor Relations Board said that the Northwestern University football team can bargain with the school as union represented employees. The question is, will this change the way college (amateur) sports operate?
Maybe, maybe not.
The main demands by the Colter-led push included financial coverage for sports-related expenditures once their playing days are over - much like what NFL players receive; concussion experts at every game; and an education trust to fund former players to graduate. Those are great things that the athletes should have, and the NCAA could take action on that by expanding insurance policies.
While Northwestern will appeal the ruling, it's very hard to predict what may or may not happen in the future for the NCAA. But one thing is clear: this is the start of endless litigation.
The ruling couldn't have come at a worse time, after news of an $18,000 bonus that Ohio State athletic director Gene Smith received after an OSU wrestler won a national title; as well as Billy Donovan's recent raise to coach basketball at Florida.
No wonder the big talk has been about paying "student" athletes.
The NCAA Tournament and football bowl games account for a near estimated $18 billion dollars, so why not give the kids a piece? A recent story by MLive said that the University of Michigan football program brought in $82 million bucks in 2012-13 - 57 percent of U-M athletic department funds. It only cost $23 million to operate the program, meaning $58 million went to the other 30 teams at U-M.
If this recent call to unionize turns into paying student athletes, one problem will arise. How much does an Appalachian State football player make compared to a player from the University of Alabama? An MSU men's basketball player compared to an MSU women's player? What about a gymnast compared to a hockey player?
There are many other comparisons that could be made, but the point is, there is no real equitable way to do it.
And if one thinks there are problems and scandals now, wait and see what happens if they start paying athletes. Bribes, illegal gambling, even throwing games could become the norm in collegiate athletics.
It's all the NCAA's fault for making college athletics the big business that it is. Not that business is a bad thing, but the argument is that the athletes are the ones that do the work that brings in the big money. While that statement is true, the NCAA and its member schools could end a lot of this discussion very quickly.
Walk away from the television rights.
Walk away from the billions.
Collegiate athletics today have nothing to do with the game(s); it's all a fancy backdrop for filling the coffers.
And the kids know it.
Gary Baker is the sports editor for The Daily Reporter. He can be reached at gbaker@thedailyreporter.com or on twitter at @TDRsports.
]]></text></news-item>