<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVK-FKV1-DY9P-N2HV"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Will new energy inquiry finally mean lower bills?; Energy bills The grip of the "big six",' is to be closely scrutinised, Sophie Christie explains why, and how to act now</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Sophie Christie</author><text><![CDATA[Households are to find out "once and for all" whether they are really being ripped off on energy bills because of a lack of competition.
That is the promise being made after the regulator, Ofgem, concerned about the grip of the "big six", referred the energy market for a full competition investigation.
Now, the Competition & Markets Authority (CMA) will examine the reasons for the dominance of these firms - British Gas, SSE, npower, EDF, Scottish Power and E.On.
The background
In 2008 Ofgem conducted a study that concluded the market wasn't perfect but that there was "no evidence of a cartel, and retail price rises could be justified by wholesale costs". But as prices have continued to rise since then amid a wider squeeze on the cost of living, political pressure has grown.
Ofgem cites "declining consumer confidence", with 43pc of people saying they don't believe energy companies are being open and transparent.
Last year, Labour sparked controversy by suggesting it would freeze energy prices for 20 months if it won the general election next year.
What is the problem?
The CMA, which from Tuesday will replace the Competition Commission, will look at many areas of the market, but one of the focuses will be on "self supply". The big providers supply the customer-facing parts of their businesses with energy. Meanwhile, most of the smaller energy providers, the challengers, buy energy from the big six. The CMA will also examine whether it is right that customers who never switch pay a higher price.
It will look too at barriers to entry. Ironically, one of the reasons for the failure of more suppliers to enter the market is the controversy around bills and uncertainty over political interference.
The number of people switching supplier is also an issue. While it rose rapidly until 2008, it has been in decline since then. One possible explanation is that the savings are not as big as they were previously, although Ofgem said people could still save, on average, £250 a year by switching.
Regardless of what happens, the best tool open to every household today is to switch supplier, something they should then repeat each time their special tariff comes to an end.
This can be done easily and free of charge, online or by phone, through one of the many switching companies. (The Telegraph offers a switching service at www.telegraph.co.uk/moneydeals.)
The savings, which are shown in our table (see above), are considerable.
Look up your existing supplier in the top half of the table and compare it with the cheapest deals in the second half.
Standard tariffs and the cheapest dealsTariff Annual average cost (direct debit) 'Big six' standard prices EDF Energy £1,164 E.On £1,169 British Gas £1,193 SSE £1,186 Scottish Power £1,199 npower £1,205 Cheapest tariffs First:Utility iSave Fixed May 2015 £1,013 Ovo Energy Cheaper Energy Fixed £1,015 Spark Energy Direct Debit Advance 4 (variable) £1,058 Green Star Energy No Worries 12 Months Fixed 1311 £1,086 M&S Energy Fixed Price May 15 £1,130 Standard tariffs and the cheapest deals
]]></text></news-item>