<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVK-45S1-F0JP-W3B9"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Parents' decade-old quest finally delivers some painful answers</title><source>The Advertiser (Australia)</source><author>SALLY BROOKS</author><text><![CDATA[FOR 12 years Brian and Helen Gitsham had been forced to live without answers to the most important question in their lives: When their son was allegedly sexually abused as a student attending St Ann's Special School in the 1980s, what did the authorities do about it?
David, a student at the school for intellectually disabled young people, had likely been an abuse victim between 1986 and 1988, but it wasn't until 1995 that his behaviour began to change.
It was another six years, in 2001, before the Gitshams learned about allegations of sexual abuse at the school.
It was then that they began to think David was likely a victim of paedophile Brian Perkins, who was jailed in 2003 for sexual offences against three other students at St Ann's. Their view that David was -abused was based on his deteri-orating behaviour, school reports and physical symptoms.
Their focus then moved to question the response of institutions and authorities to the sexual abuse claims. The Royal Commission into Institutional Responses to Child Sexual Abuse fits well with the Gitshams' line of inquiry.
The commission's first public inquiry in Adelaide into the handling of sexual abuse claims at St Ann's lasted six days and heard from 13 witnesses.
On the first day, the couple sat together in the witness box as Mrs Gitsham read an emotion-charged 36-page statement. They then attended the inquiry each day.
It was a profound experience. They were finally discovering what they had been seeking for 12 years. "In those answers, it gave us a greater understanding of why things happened and what was happening, which we knew nothing about," Mr Gitsham said.
The Gitshams' quest began in 2001 when they were first made aware of the abuse allegations. They became embroiled in meetings, letter exchanges and conversations between different authorities.
Eventually, in 2004, Archbishop Philip Wilson offered to meet them. He asked them to submit discussion topics for the meeting, so they sent him a list of 35 questions. Many were based on why the Towards Healing protocols had not been implemented. There were also questions about an inquiry commissioned by the church authorities, which became known as the Hayes inquiry. They asked about "gift" payments, which had been made from the archdiocese to victims and their families.
On receiving the questions, the archbishop cancelled the meeting. "I didn't feel confident enough on what I knew at the time to be able to engage with Mr and Mrs Gitsham about these matters. So I asked for the meeting to be postponed," he told the inquiry.
Instead, an offer of a pastoral meeting was made, which wasn't what they wanted. Seven months later, they received a letter in response to their list of 35 questions, but still no proper answers.
Their son David, now 36, died two weeks later from stomach cancer. The questions to the archbishop was partly prompted by a gift payment to the Gitshams in 2003. They agonised over whether to accept the $50,000. But it would help David, so they did. The archdiocese paid $2.3 million to families involved with Perkins and St Ann's.
The Gitshams and other victims and families learnt at the inquiry that the gift payments were part of the church's group approach to dealing with the St Ann's abuse victims, instead of an individual response as outlined in the -Towards Healing protocols.
The church's Professional Standards Office director, Susan Cain, told the inquiry she decided on this approach for several reasons, including not wanting to cause alleged victims more distress by putting them through another assessment process.
For nearly a decade, the Gitshams had also been asking about the limited scope of an inquiry, commissioned by the archdiocese. In 2002 they received terms of reference for the inquiry, outlining 12 areas. But when the inquiry report came back, it was restricted to only three areas.
Counsel assisting the royal commission Sophie David quizzed Archbishop Wilson about the report and who made the instruction on limiting the terms of reference.
"I can't remember exactly the details, but it would have been ultimately my responsibility," he replied.
Ms David continued: "The report was prepared on the basis of written interviews but not any evidence or any oral testimony. What was the basis for making that decision?" He replied: "I don't know." "Were any of the families invited to submit any submissions or the like?" she asked. "I don't think so," he said.
"Did you consider the report a satisfactory inquiry into what had taken place at St Ann's?" she asked. "I did at the time," the Archbishop replied.
"Do you now?" Ms David asked. "I can see now, from what you've been saying to me, that a specific report in relation to the terms of reference could have been more helpful," he said.
"The report was somewhat limited, wouldn't you agree?" she asked. "I agree," the archbishop replied.
The Gitshams said the royal commission made clear the failure of institutions, in particular the Catholic Church, to engage with them.
"We provided a series of questions but the Catholic Church failed to respond appropriately. It was a golden opportunity for them to engage with us and they failed to do that. They refused to do that," Mr Gitsham said.
His wife agreed. "When they did finally give us an opportunity, it was going to be only on their terms," she said.
The inquiry was also a cathartic process, they said, which has left them feeling vindicated."There were some times during the hearing when we heard truth that we found difficult to deal with but we had to accept that that's the truth. And we needed to hear that, whether it was good, bad or indifferent," Mr Gitsham said.
]]></text></news-item>