<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVK-28N1-JCBD-Y31F"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>FRACKING PROTEST IMPORTANT - LUCAS</title><source>Press Association Mediapoint</source><author>Tom Pugh, Press Association</author><text><![CDATA[Green MP Caroline Lucas defended her decision to join campaigners at an anti-fracking protest, telling a court: ``It felt important to serve the right to peaceful protest.''
The Brighton Pavilion MP was arrested after linking arms with protesters outside energy firm Cuadrilla's exploratory drilling site in Balcombe, West Sussex.
She is on trial with four co-defendants who all deny obstructing a public highway and breaching an order under Section 14 of the Public Order Act last August 19.
Lucas, 53, told Brighton Magistrates' Court that she felt it was important to protest about fracking in a bid to prevent the UK being locked into using more fossil fuels.
She said: ``I'm haunted by the idea that my children and my children's children will turn round to me and say, 'What did you do about this overwhelming threat?'
``And I want to do all I can do peacefully to address that before it's too late.'' Lucas said governments were failing to urgently address the issues surrounding climate change.
And she said she felt the protest outside Cuadrilla's main entrance gate was a ``legitimate'' and ``appropriate'' way of sending a message to Government about fracking concerns.
Lucas said she attended Balcombe the day before her arrest to take part in a march as the community was ``at the frontline of this whole new fossil fuel industry''.
The following day she joined protesters outside the main gate of the Cuadrilla site, which she said was not operating on those days.
She said it felt important and ``symbolic'' to be based outside the gate during the protest, which lasted around five hours from around 10.15am.
Lucas added: ``If this protest hadn't been effective it would have been made harder to persuade the Government to stop fracking and go down cleaner energy routes.''
Police approached her, pointing out a Section 14 notice under the Public Order Act had been issued, but Lucas denied being told of a designated protest area elsewhere.
She said: ``I couldn't see any reason why we couldn't continue our peaceful protest.''
Lucas said discussions were being held among the protesters at the time about wrapping up the protest before officers moved in.
The court heard that her son, who was sat next to her in the circle of protesters who had linked hands, was held by police.
``I was aware that the police tactics looked disproportionate,'' Lucas said. ``I was aware that my son was in pain and I was very upset about it.''
Pc Robert Staplehurst, of Sussex Police, approached Lucas, told her there was a Section 14 notice and asked whether there was anything he could say to move her, the court heard.
Lucas - who was elected as the Green Party's first MP in the 2010 General Election - replied no and she was then arrested.
She went on: ``If we had another 10 to 15 minutes we could have come to an agreement to end it and dispersed. We weren't doing anything different than we were in the previous five hours.''
Lucas, from Brighton; Josef Dobraszczyk, 22, from Bristol; Ruth Jarman, 50, from Hook, Hampshire; Sheila Menon, 42, from north east London; and Ruth Potts, 39, from Totnes, Devon, all deny wilful obstruction of the highway and breaching Section 14 of the Public Order Act.
Lucas added: ``I couldn't see any obvious reason why we should be arrested as we weren't providing any kind of obstruction.
``However, I am aware that peaceful protests are becoming criminalised. I could see (getting arrested) was a possibility, but I couldn't see any objective reason why it should happen.''
Under cross-examination from prosecutor Jonathan Edwards, Lucas said she did not believe the protest would have had the same impact if it had taken place away from the main gate.
Mr Edwards said that as an MP Lucas' presence was ``significant'' and that she would have attracted more interest than ``ordinary demonstrators''.
Lucas said it would have been clear to the police that discussions among the demonstrators to move on were happening.
She added: ``I couldn't see any reason why the protest could not continue as it had been for the last five hours.
``There were already discussions about moving on of our own accord. I was fairly certain that we would be able to do that.
``I believe that people have a right to peaceful protest and that we were not causing an obstruction, and that we had a right to protest in that area.''
Lucas said that the police did not mention to her at any point a requirement for emergency access to the site.
She was also questioned about whether the singing of ``We shall not be moved'' was an indication of defiance of the police.
Lucas said: ``It was more the fact that we were singing together rather than the words we were singing. It's a song of strength.''
The case was adjourned to April 17 when verdicts will be given following the evidence of the final defendant, Ruth Jarman.
]]></text></news-item>