<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVK-JJY1-DXDT-61W9"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Why whinge, UK energy costs are among the cheapest in Europe?; Government figures show Britain is the fifth cheapest market for electricity and second cheapest for gas in Europe</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Andrew Critchlow</author><text><![CDATA[Official figures show that Britons enjoy some of the cheapest gas and electricity costs in Europe so why are we obsessed about the price of our energy bills?
According to figures from the Department of Energy & Climate Change (DECC), the UK is the fifth cheapest market of 15 major European nations, excluding Spain, in terms of electricity prices. In terms of gas prices, Britain is the second cheapest market in Europe after Finland.
The facts would seem to challenge the claim made by Ofgem chief executive Dermot Nolan that "prices have risen more than they should have, we believe, over the last few years."
High energy costs are the reason given by Ofgem for refereing the "Big Six" to the competition watchdog for an expensive review into the industry. However, Mr Nolan's attack ignores the fact the Britain is no longer self sufficient in terms of natural gas, or oil.
Although, regulators and politicians have the power in the UK to impose price freezes on private company they cannot enforce the same draconian approach to markets on our international energy suppliers such as Qatar.
Interactive chart: Domestic electricity prices compared (IEA* + USA)
Perhaps a greater emphasis should be placed on developing new reliable and cheap sources of natural gas in the UK by fracking shale deposits instead of ordering a "witch hunt" against utlities. Look what a similar apprach has done in the US. America is the cheapest of any OECD nation in terms of the price of electricity and gas. Washington's decision to open up the US to widespread shale fracking has revived the world's largest economy with cheap energy and severed its dependence on Middle East oil.
Instead of focusing our administrative energies on creating the right environment for companies to get fracking in the UK we seem obsessed with the negative politics of blaming business instead of creating the kind of low cost environment that would see manufacturing and industry thrive as it is in America.
Interactive chart: Domestic gas prices compared (IEA* + USA)
All of this talk about rising electricity prices does, however, raise the question of just how much energy does the UK need. According to the US Energy Informational Adminsitration (EIA), not that much.
The EIA's research on global energy consumption shows that Britain is roughly using the same amount of "total energy" - a basic measure of the use of energy as a source of heat or power, or as a raw material to a manufacturing process - as it did 30 years ago. This contrasts with the US, which has seen a 24pc increase over the same period. Total energy consumption in China, now the world's second-largest economy, has quintupled since 1980. Even the French are using more energy than they did in the Eighties, according to the EIA.
Britain has stood still not because its economy has fallen far behind it major competitors but instead it has grown more efficient. Energy generated from fossil fuels, such as oil and natural, is a finite resources and will only gain in value of the long run. If Britain is to thrive we need to continue being smart with our energy. It's greater efficiency that drives down prices in free-market economies, not enquiries.
]]></text></news-item>