<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVK-TV21-DY9P-N133"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>'There's enormous potential here, right under our feet'; Barton Moss has become a byword for controversy after anti-fracking campaigners began camping there to protest about test drilling work being carried out by energy firm IGAS. Here reporter Dan Thompson gets the first look around inside the site</title><source>Manchester Evening News</source><author>Dan Thompson</author><text><![CDATA[FROM the road, it looks ominous, a fortress in a field created out of 10ft high fencing and barbed wire.
The level of security at the site is understandable, however.
Energy company IGas has been test drilling at Barton Moss for three months - a £7m operation to explore potential reserves of unconventional gas underground - and this has proved to be one of Greater Manchester's biggest controversies of 2014 so far.
IGas has drilled 6,000ft beneath the site in Eccles, Salford, to collect samples to test for levels of gas in the coal bed and shale rock formations.
The process to extract the shale gas is hydraulic fracturing - or fracking - and this is why there is a protest camp a few hundred yards away on Barton Moss Road.
Opponents have several concerns about the frack-k ing process - not least fears it can lead to the contamination of water supplies with cancercausing chemicals. But last year a Public Health England report concluded it anticipated fracking would be a low risk to safety if properly operated and regulated.
IGas, a London-based company, has made no secret of its desire to exploit the gas at Barton Moss - if the levels are commercial viable and if the company can get the relevant planning permission and permits.
John Blaymires, the company's chief operating officer, says he is certain they could drill for and develop the gas safely.
He adds: "I'm confident about our ability to do that. I've been doing this all my life.
"We are incredibly highly regulated. The UK regime and the Norwegian regime are seen to be global examples. And we can't afford not to do it properly. We want to build public trust."
The M.E.N. was invited to take a look round the IGas plant at Barton Moss as part of this drive towards transparency.
The site is 6,000 square metres, about the size of a football pitch, and around 25 people work the day shift here.
At the centre of the site sits a huge, white carousel which houses the drill pipes.
The company's operations manager, Dave Kerr, says that the hole drilled is about 200 cubic metres - which means that around 200,000 litres of water has been needed in the test drilling process.
Chemicals have also been needed to give the water a thicker consistency, which, according to Mr Kerr, means there is a 'very small risk' of contamination.
The chemicals, water and other items needed in the process are brought onto site by trucks, which are routinely held up by protesters who walk in front of them along Barton Moss Road.
Mr Kerr says that the journey along the road should take three minutes - but has taken up to four hours because of the protest. The disruption has added weeks onto the operation, at a significant cost to IGas.
The test drilling has just finished at Barton Moss and analysis of the samples should text six months. IGas will then decide if it wants to exploit the coal bed methane, which it has planning permission for, or the shale gas, which it does not.
There is little doubt that if IGas does find shale gas here, and gets permission to frack for it, then it will be lucrative for the company. But it would also be a massive benefit to the whole region, according to Mr Blaymires.
"We could establish this region as the centre for shale expertise then start exporting it to France and Germany and Europe," he says. "This area could become the Aberdeen of the shale world - actually build colleges, have apprenticeships, train people. There's enormous potential, literally underneath our feet."
]]></text></news-item>