<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVM-CXG1-JC3H-035P"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>NJ fights back against illegal trash dumping</title><source>The Daily Journal (Vineland, New Jersey)</source><author>By, Kirk Moore</author><text><![CDATA[WOODLAND - Hidden cameras in the woods and criminal prosecution are part of a new campaign by state environmental and parks officials to fight trash dumping on public lands - a perennial problem that has defied cleanup and enforcement efforts for decades.
Prosecutors are bringing a new hammer into play: the state Solid Waste Management Act that provides for fines up to $50,000 per day for major violations. Lesser offenders still will face criminal fines of up to $5,000, civil penalties up to $1,500 and confiscation of their vehicles, said Michele Siekerka, an assistant commissioner at the state Department of Environmental Protection.
The newest enforcement measure is motion-activated automatic cameras on forest roads that lead to frequently used dumping spots. The cameras will transmit their images and "our compliance folks will be checking those daily," Siekerka said.
Like automatic cameras that catch bank robbers, law enforcement will use those images to get public help finding dumpers.
The new website www.stopdumping.nj.gov will post images from the cameras - and mug shots of people convicted of dumping.
"If you are caught dumping on our state lands, you will be on this website," Siekerka said Thursday at Brendan Byrne State Forest in Burlington County.
The idea grew out of the DEP's recent Barnegat Bay Blitz cleanups, when workers found lots of illegal dumps on state land in Ocean and Burlington counties, said Katie Barnett, a public education specialist in the agency's water resources section.
"At Brendan Byrne, we pulled out 100 tires," Barnett recalled.
Along with its own parks police and wildlife conservation officers, the DEP will work with state and local police and county prosecutors to make arrests and get convictions, said John Giordano, the DEP assistant commissioner for compliance and enforcement.
"We'll use whatever means necessary," said Giordano, a former federal prosecutor.
He indicated the biggest penalties could fall on businesses that use woodland dumping to escape paying tipping fees at landfills.
"They're looking at it from a purely business standpoint, and creating an unlevel playing field. We're not going to allow that," Giordano said.
Byrne State Forest Superintendent Leigh Germann said the tract is plagued by what appears to be commercial castoffs - one pile of building debris obviously came out of a commercial dump truck - but workers commonly find household trash, from plastic bags of leaves to paint cans.
DUMPING PENALTIES
An aggressive new campaign by the state will apply much stiffer penalties to people caught illegally dumping on public lands, including:
Civil penalties up to $1,500
Criminal fines up to $5,000
Fines up to $50,000 per day, under the state Solid Waste Management Act, for the most serious offenses
]]></text></news-item>