<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVM-D361-DY15-S298"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Beira Council Fines Chinese Company</title><source>Agencia de Informacao de Mocambique (English)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Beira Municipal Council has fined a Chinese company, Biworld, 550,000 meticais (about 18,030 US dollars) for operating in violation of the terms of its licence, reports the Beira daily paper “Diario de Mocambique”.
Biworld was storing clinker in the Beira neighbourhood of Munhava - but the licence issued by the Municipal Council only authorised it to use the space as a car park, and not as an open air warehouse.
The matter first came to the paper's attention earlier this month when Munhava residents complained of the harmful effects of the dust raised in the handling of the clinker. A team from the Provincial Environment Directorate (DPCA) then went to the Biworld site and carried out an environmental audit. It seems that, without the Municipal Council's knowledge, the company had sent an Environmental Management Plan for the storing of clinker to the DPCA, which had then approved it.
The conclusions of the team's report were damning, since the company was paying no attention to the Environmental Management Plan. The team found that the solid waste produced there is deposited locally, without any selection, and then taken to the municipal landfill “with all the dangers this represents for the environment, since it contains non-biodegradable material, with polluting components”.
It added that “the effluent consisting of organic material and chemical products used in cleaning and washing, flow into a nearby drainage ditch, which is linked to the municipal drainage channel, which passes through the community without any specific treatment”.
Biworld's emissions “are another acute environmental problem”, the report said, “since there is no monitoring of the emissions which result from the circulation of heavy vehicles unloading bulk clinker in the open air”.
Furthermore, there was no sign of any environmental education, and the work force knew nothing about the Environmental Management Plan. The report also noted a poor relationship between the company and the local residents.
Pf/ (323)
]]></text></news-item>