<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVM-CDC1-F12F-F0HY"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Bicol police chief seeks MGB deputation to halt illegal mining in CaMarchnes Sur town</title><source>Philippines News Agency</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[LEGAZPI CITY, March 28 -- ' Chief Supt. Victor P. Deona, Philippine National Police (PNP)-Bicol regional director, has asked the Mines and Geosciences Bureau (MGB) of the Department of Environment and Natural Resources to deputize lawmen to stop the illegal small-mining activities in the island-village of Gota, Caramoan, CaMarchnes Sur.
Deona has sent members of the Caramoan Municipal Police Office and the Regional Public Safety Battalion to maintain peace and order in the area following the massacre of four small miners by armed members of Sagip-Kalikasan, which created fear among the villagers.
He also replaced Senior Supt. Ramiro Bausa as provincial director of CaMarchnes Sur Provincial Police Office and placed Senior Supt. Arnold Albis, his deputy for operations, as acting officer in charge of the office.
Engr. Theodore Rommel E. Pestano, MGB Bicol regional director, told the PNA in a text message that he had signed the deputation letter and was being delivered to Deona's office.
Four persons were killed by members of the Sagip-Kalikasan group in the premier tourist destination on Sunday evening.
Joint operatives of the CMPO and the RPSB arrested seven suspects in the massacre at about 4 p.m. Monday at the Gota Village, Barangay Ilawod, on tip of residents.
Deona identified the suspects as Angelo Refran, Servillano Espares Jr., Luis Palaganas Jr., Saetiel Pielago, Jonah Bolima, Florencio Vargas and group leader Francisco Tria III -- all members of Sagip Kalikasan.
Victims Julio Lobiano, Rene Lobiano, Salem Virtuz and Jesse Brondia ' all miners and residents of Barangay Gota ' have already been buried.
Deona, who personally went to the area right after he heard the news on the massacre, said the suspects were arrested at about 4 p.m. Monday after the police received information that the men they were after were going to Caramoan.
He said no person or organization was authorized by the MGB to conduct mining operations, small- or big-scale, in the area.
Pesta'o confirmed this, saying the MGB has not issued a mining permit to anybody and adding that the agency has a plan to allow small miners through the 'Minahang Bayan' program of the government in order for the villagers to benefit from the natural resources of the area.
He said Republic Act (RA) 7076 otherwise known as An Act Creating A People's Small-Scale Mining Program and for Other Purposes and Its Implementing Rules and Regulations (IRR) embodied in the DENR Administrative Order (DAO) No. 34, series of 1992, provide for the procedures on how the Provincial Mining Regulatory Board (PMRB) and a Minahang Bayan or the People's Small-Scale Mining Area (PSSMA) are created and established.
The PMRB, known as the 'Board' in RA 7076 and its IRR, is designated as the implementing body by the DENR in the identification of a Minahang Bayan.
Pestano added that it is composed of the MGB regional director as chair; the provincial governor, or his/her authorized representative, as vice-chair; and members composed of duly appointed representatives from the small-scale miners; large-scale miners and non-government organization with environmental concerns.
The PMRB has the authority to declare and set aside People's Small-scale Mining Areas or Minahang Bayan in sites on-shore suitable for small-scale mining operations subject to review by the DENR secretary through the regional executive director, who, in Bicol, is Gilbert Gonzales.
Gonzales has ordered his men in CaMarchnes Sur to closely coordinate with the MGB in enforcing DENR's covering laws in the area.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Philippines News Agency. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>