<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVM-CCH1-JD6S-R3C2"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>There 's a silver lining in the cloud</title><source>Muscatine Journal (Iowa)</source><author>Jason Liegois 5632620525 Jason.Liegois@muscatinejournal.com</author><text><![CDATA[MUSCATINE, Iowa - Local government and business leaders voiced their support for Grain Processing Corp. and its parent company, Muscatine's Kent Corp., following news Thursday that the company had been ordered to pay a record penalty for environmental violation.
Those same leaders expressed their hopes that the consent agreement reached between GPC and the Iowa Department of Natural Resources would be a way for the company to put past problems behind them.
Muscatine Mayor DeWayne Hopkins, who has been in Washington, D.C. for the past two days, declined comment on the consent agreement, saying he had not had a chance to read it or any of the reports about it.
City Administrator Gregg Mandsager said "GPC is a valued partner and economic driver for our community," adding that "yesterday's settlement will allow GPC to put these issues behind them and move forward with their project here in Muscatine. This latest investment demonstrates GPC's ongoing commitment to a strong local economy and environmental stewardship."
As part of the consent agreement, GPC, which is located in Muscatine and processes grain into ethanol and various other feed, industrial and food products, will pay a $1.5 million penalty for pollution violations. In addition, it will be required to fully convert its coal-fired boilers used at its Muscatine operations to natural gas usage by July 15, 2015, which the state hopes will reduce pollutants by as much as 12,000 tons per year.
The company estimates that implementing terms of the consent decree will cost $15 million-$17 million in capital expenses, $1 million per year in operating costs, and $4 million-$12 million per year in increased fuel costs. This is on top of an estimated $100 million the company says it has already spent on environmental sustainability efforts.
Failure to comply or follow the consent decree could result in fines as much as $10,000 per day per individual violation. It settles a lawsuit Iowa Attorney General Tom Miller filed against GPC in 2011, which alleged the company was responsible for multiple instances of air and water pollution.
Muscatine County Board of Supervisors Chairman Robert Howard said that he hadn't had a chance to read the decree, but did have the chance to review previous environmental efforts of the company.
"Overall, I've been very pleased at the efforts of GPC to try and meet of its guidelines," Howard said. "We're looking forward to it (the new program) coming to a successful conclusion."
"Kent Corp. has long been a vital part of our community," said Greg Jenkins, president and CEO of Greater Muscatine Chamber of Commerce and Industry. "I see this [consent decree] as a clear commitment to the future of Muscatine."
]]></text></news-item>