<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVM-BY51-JB4F-Y055"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Lifescript: Massachusetts bans sale of FDA-approved Zogenix painkiller</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
WASHINGTON (Reuters) - Officials in Massachusetts have blocked sales of Zogenix's controversial but U.S.-approved painkiller Zohydro, prompting the drugmaker to criticize what it called an "unprecedented action."
The state's ban "only serves to unfairly restrict patient access," the company said in a statement late Thursday. "Ultimately, the ban on the prescription medication will add to patient suffering in the state," it added.
Massachusetts Governor Deval Patrick announced the Zohydro ban in a speech on Thursday, formally declaring a public health emergency resulting from the abuse of opioids in the New England state.
It is the latest salvo in the ongoing battle over Zohydro's launch as the U.S. grapples with a wave of abuse of opioids, a class of drugs that includes not only powerful prescription painkillers but also heroin.
The federal Food and Drug Administration approved Zohydro last year over the objections of its advisory panel, which expressed concerns about the potential for abuse.
The drug has since come under further scrutiny from members of Congress, dozens of state attorney generals, medical groups and drug treatment experts seeking to block the drug even as the FDA's top official has defended its action.
While the FDA approves drugs for sale in the United States, it does not guarantee their availability. For example, health insurance companies can exclude certain medications from their formularies.
Zohydro is a form of hydrocodone that, unlike rival products such as AbbVie Inc's Vicodin or UCB's Lortab, does not contain acetaminophen.
The company has defended the drug as a necessary option for pain patients who cannot tolerate acetaminophen, a nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug linked to liver damage and stomach bleeding.
But critics worry that with no built-in abuse deterrents, Zohydro will be a draw for addicts looking for an easy fix. Rival Purdue Pharma has said it is working on a hydrocodone-only drug that will be resistant to abuse, something Zogenix has also pledged to do.
"Once/if the Purdue product is approved, possibly in 2015, FDA could then rule that Zohydro is not as safe as the abuse-deterrent product and either pull the drug's approval or ask Zogenix to withdraw it voluntarily," Rob Cox, an analyst with Capital Alpha Partners, said earlier this week.
Zogenix, in its statement, said it would "review the safe use measures already in place" with Massachusetts officials.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/28/massachusetts_bans_sale_of_fda-approved_zogenix_painkiller.aspx
COMPANY BACKGROUND
ACTIVITIES
LifeScript is a online publishing company based in Mission Viejo, CA.
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
28 March 2014: Lifescript: Mild head injuries linked to risk of death years later
NEW YORK (Reuters Health) - Adults hospitalized with mild head injuries have almost double the risk of dying in the next 15 years compared to similar people with no history of head injury, according to a new UK study. It's not clear whether lifestyle before and after a head injury is to blame for the increased risk, if the injury itself has lingering effects, or both, researchers say. "There is evidence in the study that points to lifestyle factors and health before and after the head injury," said lead author Tom McMillan, of the Institute of Health and Wellbeing at the University of Glasgow. High rates of death in the year following a severe head injury have been well documented, McMillan and his colleagues write in the Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery and Psychiatry.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/28/mild_head_injuries_linked_to_risk_of_death_years_later.aspx
28 March 2014: Lifescript: Guinea seeks to stem spread of deadly Ebola virus in capital
CONAKRY (Reuters) - Authorities in Guinea scrambled on Friday to halt the spread of Ebola in the capital Conakry, after the death toll linked to an outbreak of the deadly virus in the West African country hit 66. Officials said on Thursday that five cases of Ebola had been detected in Conakry, a city of more than 2 million people, some 300 km from the previous infections in the remote southeast.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/28/guinea_seeks_to_stem_spread_of_deadly_ebola_virus_in_capital.aspx
28 March 2014: Lifescript: Pot-smoking style linked to addiction risk
NEW YORK (Reuters Health) - Marijuana smokers' behavior is more important than the potency of their pot or how much of the psychoactive ingredient THC they take in for predicting who will become dependent, according to a small new study. Researchers have debated whether smokers of high-potency cannabis varieties are at greater risk of addiction because they get more THC, or if they compensate for the pot's strength by using or inhaling less of it. That doesn't really matter, say the authors of the new report.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/28/pot-smoking_style_linked_to_addiction_risk.aspx
28 March 2014: Lifescript: U.S. court finds fault with federal water transfer regulation
WASHINGTON (Reuters) - A U.S. judge on Friday threw out a federal regulation that allowed government agencies to transfer water between different water bodies, such as rivers and lakes, without needing to safeguard for pollution. U.S. District Judge Kenneth Karas of the Southern District of New York ordered the U.S.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/28/us_court_finds_fault_with_federal_water_transfer_regulation.aspx
28 March 2014: Lifescript: U.S. wants at least $1 billion from drugmakers who delay generics
WASHINGTON (Reuters) - The U.S. Federal Trade Commission seeks a settlement of $1 billion or more from pharmaceutical companies it has sued for delaying the sale of cheaper medicines after patents on brand-name drugs may have expired, an FTC official told a legal conference on Friday. The antitrust agency alleges that the way drugmakers settle patent-related lawsuits hurts consumers by making drugs more expensive.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/28/us_wants_at_least_1_billion_from_drugmakers_who_delay_generics.aspx
]]></text></news-item>