<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVM-4J01-JCV0-11K5"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Conflicts plague adviser to large pension funds; Your retirement savings could be in a fund that gets investment advice from financial services group Riscura, |about which troubling conflict-of-interest issues have come to light, |with questions being asked by |major players in the financial services |industry. Bruce Cameron reports</title><source>The Independent on Saturday (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[In a case of clear and avoidable |conflicts of interest, financial services company Riscura, which, among other things, advises major retirement funds on investments, has raked in millions of rands from asset managers it has recommended in the past. It has also advised retirement funds to invest in a portfolio that it partially manages and from which it earns fees.
The Financial Services Board (FSB) confirmed last week that, since last year, it has made inquiries to Riscura about possible conflicts in its business structures.
And a Personal Finance investigation reveals that, by ignoring conflicts of interest, retirement fund trustees are often misled by Riscura.
The consequence of these multiple conflicts of interest could potentially be lower benefits for fund members - many of whom belong to major funds, with assets under management totaling about R1 trillion.
The FSB inquiries have been |confirmed by the FSB's newly appointed deputy chief executive in charge of financial advice, Caroline da Silva, who says the FSB will |continue to engage with Riscura |on some of the issues raised by Personal Finance.
Personal Finance's investigation into Riscura followed its failure in a number of instances to spot and protect retirement fund members from high-risk investments, including:
u Potential losses of millions of rands in the collapse of one of South Africa's biggest privately owned companies, First Strut;
u Potential losses running into millions in the Rocklands fiasco, |in which undeveloped sand dunes on the Cape Flats shot up in value from a purchase price of R36 million in 2007 to R890 million in |December 2010 without a single |sod being turned; and
u Exposure, through a fund of hedge funds managed by Edge Capital, to Evercrest, a R200-million hedge fund that collapsed in 1997 when it took a wrong-way geared bet on Sanlam shares. Riscura not only advised retirement funds on investments in Edge but also provided risk assessment services to Evercrest.
Increasingly, questions are being asked by major players in the financial services industry about the business practices of Riscura, which are seen as anti-competitive.
The Personal Finance investigation into Riscura has revealed the following:
u Multiple conflicts of interest
Riscura has significant and serious conflicts in the multiple services it provides to retirement funds, including some of the country's largest funds, such as the Government Employees Pension Fund (GEPF), the mining industry's Sentinel Retirement Fund, and funds for |the employees of Telkom, Eskom, Johannesburg municipality, the University of the Witwatersrand, Imperial Group, the printing industry, and Mercedes Benz.
The investigation shows that Riscura does not seem to avoid or manage its own conflicts of interest, as it is required to do in terms of Financial Advisory and Intermediary Services Act, and does not insist that retirement funds avoid conflicts of interest. This is despite having a subsidiary company that advises funds on good governance, which includes avoiding conflicts |of interest.
Riscura advises retirement funds on which asset managers to use, but it has very close relationships with most of the asset managers it recommends, particularly Investec Asset Management and funds of hedge funds manager Edge Capital, from which it earns significant fees.
These conflicts exist despite Riscura stating in its code of ethics for its staff that "all Riscura staff must recognise their responsibility to conduct themselves ethically and avoid any conflicts of interest".
And in proposal documents, |such as one to the Johannesburg municipality's retirement funds, Riscura claims: "We are an independent company, free from any potential conflicts of interest."
The potential conflicts are highlighted in an email from Riscura's chief executive, Jarred Glansbeek, to staff in which he refers to R1.2 million "just in direct income" if the company wins the Printing Industry Pension Fund business.
According to Riscura's income statements that Personal Finance has seen, only about 25 percent of Riscura's income was, at one stage, from consulting to retirement funds on investments. The bulk of its income was from various services provided by its subsidiary companies, such as Riscura Analytics, |to asset management companies and from switching retirement |fund assets between asset managers. This "indirect" income enables Riscura to submit lower quotes |for consulting services to retire-ment funds.
Asset managers interviewed by Personal Finance do not agree on whether the services offered by Riscura Analytics (see "Riscura group's interlinked activities", |page 19) are required. And not all who manage money from retirement funds advised by Riscura use Riscura Analytics. Fund managers that do not use the subsidiary |company say these are functions that an asset manager should |and can perform itself.
However, Personal Finance has evidence that Riscura demanded from at least one asset manager (which does not want to be identified at this stage) that, on its appointment as manager to a |major retirement fund, Riscura Analytics be appointed to undertake risk management at an annual fee |of 0.1 percent of the fund's assets under management.
In a letter to the asset manager, Riscura also claims that its clients (mainly retirement funds) that "are invested in [the asset manager's] funds have requested that certain reports be made available to them regarding the funds".
Riscura states in the letter: "We will provide these within their reporting service where required, based on Riscura's reporting |and standards."
The asset manager later discovered that no such instruction had been issued by the retirement fund.
Riscura charges different amounts for its services to asset managers. These include, as in this case, payments as a percentage of assets under management, rather than a rand amount.
u Individual conflicts
The conflicts of interest are further bedevilled by the fact that both Riscura and Edge Capital have |provided freebies to key members (and their spouses) of large retirement funds to which Riscura provides asset management consulting.
They include Eric Visser, the principal officer of one of the country's largest self-administered funds, the Sentinel Retirement Fund.
Visser has endorsed Riscura. In his endorsement, Visser claims, among other things, that the trustees of the Sentinel fund are very comfortable that "Riscura has always been open and transparent regarding direct and indirect charges earned by all Riscura services and business units. This includes their transition offering and their risk services division, which provides risk support to unregulated asset classes."
In an email, Glansbeek gives his staff an instruction that Visser's Riscura reference be used "as a standard in all presentations".
No response has been received from Visser or the Sentinel fund chairman, André le Grange, to questions from Personal Finance about the freebies and the Riscura reference and whether these were approved by the fund's trustees.
Personal Finance also has spreadsheets produced by Riscura listing the birthdays of hundreds of people in the retirement fund industry and stating who should and who should not receive gifts, with some people, such as former Springbok coach Harry Viljoen of Edge Capital and Visser listed for "premier" gifts. Some of the premier gifts have been Riscura-branded golf bags.
Personal Finance has the names of a number of other retirement fund trustees who have accepted luxury trips and gifts, including a person associated with the GEPF. (That person is not the GEPF's |principal officer, John Oliphant, who has been suspended for several months for reasons that have not been made public.)
u Lack of checks and balances
Riscura companies check on each other in a number of instances. This has led to questions by competitors, for example, over whether Riscura-advised retirement funds are adhering to prudential investment requirements in terms of the Pension Funds Act, particularly when investing in derivatives, currency options and futures.
Riscura recommends the funds it is advising to invest significant amounts in hedge funds, which use these instruments.
This means that Riscura is both recommending investments and then checking that these investments comply with the law, without any independent assessment. Often the asset managers recommended to retirement funds by Riscura pay Riscura for compliance checks, creating a further conflict of interest.
u Lack of transparency
Despite Riscura's claims that it provides comparative asset performance and risk analysis figures, it does not, particularly with |managers of funds of hedge |funds, publish comparative performance data.
Most of the portfolios Riscura recommends for retirement |funds are structured specifically for that fund. The more usual |practice is to place the money of individual retirement funds into |pooled portfolios.
Edge Capital's funds of hedge funds also seem to be secretive, with only a few of these funds included in the public Alexander Forbes funds of hedge funds quarterly survey.
internal communications
Included in the thousands of intra-office emails to which Personal Finance has had access, there is |evidence that Riscura actively attempts to mislead trustees of retirement funds or keep them in the dark.
In a document titled "Questions & Answers", Riscura deals with questions that trustees might ask. In it, Riscura states that it arranges guarantees for a certain investment that it suggests are stronger than bank guarantees.
In an email to a Riscura staffer accompanying a draft of a document compiled for the trustees of the Post Office retirement fund, Glansbeek says: "Sorry, please |read my email carefully ... I DON'T want this to look like a Riscura |document ..."
In another email, dealing with a proposal to the Tshwane municipal retirement fund, a Riscura client manager suggests to Glansbeek that all references to the names of asset managers should be removed from |a performance scatter graph, "as I don't think the 36-month [performance] looks great at all".
And being kept in the dark is not limited to trustees. At one stage, financial advice company Acsis |asks Riscura for data for modelling it is doing on an aspect of asset management. Glansbeek is informed |by his staff that the information |is available on the Riscura web-|site archive.
He responds: "Don't give them anything yet please. And also don't do any extra work here ... and can we please make sure that we only keep the last two or three surveys on the [web]site from now on."
u A draft of this and other reports was sent to Riscura and Edge Capital last week. No response had been received by the end of this week.
]]></text></news-item>