<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVM-Y8P1-F0BC-M2T1"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Duke cited over Williamston steam plant</title><source>Anderson Independent-Mail (South Carolina)</source><author>Michael Eads</author><text><![CDATA[State regulators cited Duke Energy last month for problems with its steam plant near Williamston.
South Carolina Department of Health and Environmental Control staff visited the W.S. Lee steam station Feb. 24 and found the earthen dam intended to hold back one of the coal ash lagoons showed signs of erosion and had “trees and other deleterious vegetation taking hold near the toe drain directly below where seepage is daylighting from the dam embankment and foundation.” The dam also showed signs of visible water seepage that need to be repaired.
A Notice of Violation dated Feb. 27 was sent to Duke officials in Charlotte, informing them of the problems. It said Duke wasn’t in compliance with reporting requirements of the National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit for the plant. The permit, required by the federal Clean Air and Clean Water acts, is issued and enforced by DHEC with oversight from the Environmental Protection Agency. In addition, the plant appears to have had problems with the Clean Water Act requirements of its permit since mid-2011. EPA records posted at http://echo.epa.gov/detailed_facility_report?fid=110004937864 show problems keeping up with reporting requirements. Frank Holleman, attorney for the Southern Environmental Law Center, would like to see DHEC take a much closer look at the earthworks holding back those coal ash dumps. “One of those dams is leaking,” said Holleman. “Duke is gathering the water and trying to move it away with the stormwater drains, due to concerns about the dam’s stability.” Duke Energy the only utility in the Carolinas that stores its coal ash in unlined pits, according to Holleman. The ash is typically captured from coal smoke, then mixed with water and dumped into the pits. The company announced last year that it plans to quit burning coal and switch to natural gas to heat the boilers at the Lee plant. Duke has not, however, indicated any plans to remove the coal ash from the site or replace the unlined pits. Duke Energy spokesman Ryan Mosier did not respond to a request for comment late Friday, but he defended the company’s operation of the plant in an email to the Independent Mail earlier this week. “The coal ash facility at the W.S. Lee steam station is safe and inspected regularly by the company and outside agencies,” Mosier said Tuesday. Follow Michael Eads on Twitter @MikeEads_AIM.
]]></text></news-item>