<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVM-CCH1-JD6S-R392"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>WORTHY CAUSES</title><source>Gloucester Daily Times (Massachusetts)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[PARENT MENTORS SOUGHT: Pathways' Cape Ann Families is seeking men and women to volunteer as parent mentors. The Cape Ann Families Parent Mentor Program has been running for 20 years, serving parents of the Cape Ann community who are experiencing stress or isolation. The program is looking for volunteers to participate in its five-week spring parent mentor training, after which each volunteer will be matched with a parent, beginning a year-long mentorship/friendship. Contact Teby Wammack at 978-281-2400, ext. 110, or twammack@pw4c.org
CAPT. JENNIFER J. HARRIS, USMC MEMORIAL SCHOLARSHIP: Capt. Jennifer J. Harris, a native of Swampscott, graduated from Swampscott High School in 1996 and from the United States Naval Academy in 2000. She was the first female helicopter pilot assigned to the famed Marine Corps squadron HMM-364 "Purple Foxes," served three tours of duty in Iraq flying casualty evacuation missions, and was killed in action on Feb. 7, 2007 when the helicopter she was piloting was shot down. An educational trust continues Captain Harris's legacy of serving others and offers scholarship opportunities for Gloucester and other North Shore communities. JROTC Scholarship: $500 to be awarded to one North Shore JROTC student, to support college or military expenses. Returning Veterans: $500 to be awarded to one North Shore veteran to support college expenses. For information, eligibility requirements and applications, www.jjharrisscholarship.com. Contributions may be sent to the Capt. Jennifer J. Harris, USMC Memorial Scholarship Fund, Eastern Bank, 405 Paradise Road, Swampscott, MA 01907 or online at www.jjharrisscholarship.com.
CAPT. HARRY "PINT" JOHNSON SCHOLARSHIP: A scholarship in memory of Capt. Harry "Pint" Johnson is available to graduating seniors from Cape Ann who will be entering a trade school, maritime arts school or the emergency services field. Send contributions to Speedwell Engine Co. 2, c/o Phil Tanson, 15 Prospect St. Rockport, MA 01966.
JOHN W. ORLANDO SCHOLARSHIP: Johnny Orlando was a teacher, mentor and friend to countless students during his many years as a carpentry teacher at Gloucester High School's vocational school. A native of Gloucester, Orlando was a fixture around town, especially on the Boulevard where no one passed by without a greeting or kind word. A $500 scholarship in Orlando's name will be awarded to a graduating senior accepted at a college of higher education or an accredited technical school. Tax-deductible donations in his memory may be sent to: John W. Orlando Scholarship Fund, C/O Gloucester Scholarship Foundation, Cape Ann Savings Bank, 109 Main St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
JAMES EASON SCHOLARSHIP: A scholarship in memory of James A. Eason has been established. Applicants must plan to pursue a career in the trades or be seniors enrolled in automotive, electrical or machine technology, carpentry or cabinetmaking at Gloucester High School. Applicants must be committed to giving their best at all times, have integrity and strength of character, and not allow adversity to slow them down. Strong academics are not a requirement. To donate, send contributions to the James A. Eason Memorial Scholarship Fund, c/o Rockport National Bank, Railroad Avenue, Gloucester, MA 01930, Attn: Cathy Ketchopolus. Call Joan Dallin at Gloucester High School for more information.
FOSTER FAMILIES NEEDED: Dare Family Services, a private, nonprofit social services agency that specializes in providing intensive foster care to children and teens that have been abused or neglected, is recruiting foster parents in all areas to provide homes for local foster children. Call 978-750-0751 or visit www.darefamily.org.
L. DEXTER WOODMAN SCHOLARSHIP FUND: The L. Dexter Woodman Scholarship Fund was founded in 1988 with a donation from the Woodman family of Essex in honor of Dexter Woodman, a well-known benefactor of young people in his community. Woodman scholarships have helped send 61 young men and women to college, with awards of $510,000. The fund also gives to students chosen annually by the Essex Lions, the Cape Ann Chamber of Commerce, and the Massachusetts Restaurant Association. Every year the fund also sponsors 25 Honors Scholars through the North Shore Chamber of Commerce. Woodman scholarship recipients are seniors at Manchester Essex Regional High School, or high school seniors who attended Essex Elementary School. Applicants are judged on character and service to the community as well as academics, extracurricular activities, and need. Donations to the fund may be made at any time and should be mailed to: Woodman Scholarship Fund, P.O. Box 81, Essex, MA 01929. For application information, email scholarship@woodmans.com
CONSERVATION COMMISSION: The Gloucester Conservation Commission seeks environmentally conscious volunteers. The purpose of the Conservation Commission is to protect environmental resources and the adjoining uplands from adverse impact by enforcing the Massachusetts Wetlands Protection Act and the city Wetlands Ordinance. The commission also advises other city boards on environmental matters and encourages public outreach on conservation issues. It meets the first and third Wednesday of the month. Anyone who is interested should send a letter to the Conservation Commission, 3 Pond Road, Gloucester, MA 01930.
ROGER J. PARADY JR. SCHOLARSHIP: A scholarship has been established in memory of Roger J. Parady, for a graduating senior of Gloucester High School who has been accepted by Salem State College, and is pursuing a career in the field of education. Parady was very proud to have graduated from Salem State College which educated and prepared him to go on and become a successful and dedicated teacher of history for more than 33 years. His passion for teaching was evident by the number of students, who, when reflecting upon past teachers, regarded Parady as their "best teacher ever," a teacher who respected each one as an individual, instilling his confidence that each one had the potential to become successful with hard work and staying in school. Parady often spoke of his appreciation to the city of Gloucester for giving him the opportunity to teach in this community that he loved. Those wishing to donate to his memory may do so by sending their donation to: Roger J. Parady Jr. Scholarship Fund, c/o Cape Ann Savings Bank, 109 Main St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
RED CROSS: The American Red Cross of Northeast Massachusetts is a humanitarian organization that assists disaster victims and helps community members prevent, prepare for, and respond to emergencies. The organization relies on the generosity of its dedicated volunteers and is always eager to welcome more. Call 978-922-2224.
MARGARET F. PARSONS SCHOLARSHIP: A scholarship in memory of Margaret F. Parsons, former office nurse for Cape Ann OB-GYN, Dr, Lawrence Ross and Dr. Hamer Lacey, is awarded to a graduating senior of Gloucester High School who plans to major in the medical sciences and has demonstrated good character, dependability and self-help skills. Applicants must show financial need. Grades are not a determining factor. Send applications and donations to: Margaret F. Parsons Scholarship, c/o Patricia Sargent Burleson, 600 Washington St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
CATHOLIC CHARITIES: Help your Cape Ann neighbors by providing a donation to the local Catholic Charities Gloucester Office for basic needs - food, utility and rental assistance - during these difficult economic times. Send donations, with "Basic Needs" written on the memo line, to: Catholic Charities North, Attn: Sarah Gindel, 60 Prospect St., Gloucester, MA 01930. Call 978-283-3055 for more information.
HAWC VOLUNTEER TRAINING: HAWC (Healing Abuse Working for Change, www.hawcdv.org), is seeking volunteers for a 24-hour hot-line service to help end family violence. Volunteers must complete 30 hours of training on evenings and Saturdays. Training provides volunteers with the information needed to answer the 24-hour hot-line, which can be answered from your home. Email info@hawcdv.org
PAT ROY SCHOLARSHIP: The board of directors of the Cape Ann Chamber of Commerce has established a scholarship in honor of past President Pat Roy, the first woman leader in the organization 's history. The scholarship will be awarded each year to a young woman pursuing business courses in college. The chamber will provide an annual endowment of $500 and welcomes additional contributions from those wishing to honor Roy's accomplishments as a key member of the Woodman family business and in strengthening the business and civic climate of the region. Send checks to the Pat Roy Scholarship Fund, c/o Cape Ann Chamber of Commerce, 33 Commercial St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
CAROLYN O'CONNOR SCHOLARSHIP: The Carolyn O'Connor Scholarship has been established by the Cape Ann Chamber Businesswomen. The $1,000 scholarship, named in honor of the group's first chairwoman, will be awarded annually to a Cape Ann woman looking to change careers or re-enter the work force. Each applicant must have a high school diploma or its equivalent, be a legal resident, and be accepted into an accredited college, university or job training program. Applications are available at the chamber office or by calling 978-283-1601. Contributions, made payable to Businesswomen's Scholarship Fund, may be sent to Chamber Businesswomen's Division, Cape Ann Chamber of Commerce, 33 Commercial St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
ELDER VOLUNTEERS SOUGHT: The Rose Baker Senior Center and the Council on Aging (COA) needs friendly visitors and shoppers to provide weekly shopping and home visits to home-bound elders. The Gloucester COA has many other volunteer opportunities also available. Call Lydia at 978-281-9765, ext. 14.
ASHLEY RICHARD SCHOLARSHIP: The Ashley Richard Memorial Scholarship, created by family and friends in her memory, is awarded each year to a deserving Gloucester High School senior who has participated in Junior ROTC. The student must demonstrate the leadership, citizenship and perseverance to strive to make things better. Qualified students must be accepted at an accredited school of continued learning. To donate, send a check payable to the Ashley Richard Memorial Scholarship, c/o Cape Ann Savings Bank, 109 Main St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
RAYMOND R. ANDERTON SCHOLARSHIP: The Raymond R. Anderton Scholarship Fund has been established by family and friends to honor his life. The scholarship is awarded to a deserving Gloucester High School senior who has been accepted at an accredited school of continued learning. The recipient must demonstrate a commitment to community service and social change through activities, school-sponsored and otherwise. Applicants should possess a strong character, unique interests and an eagerness to "think outside the box." Scholarship applications may be picked up at the Gloucester High School guidance office. To make a contribution, send a check payable to the Raymond R. Anderton Scholarship Fund, c/o Cape Ann Savings Bank, 109 Main St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
VOLUNTEER OPPORTUNITIES: North Shore Elder Services, 152 Sylvan St., Danvers, seeks volunteers willing to make a difference in the life of an elder by joining its Money Management Program, Ombudsman Program or At Your Side Medical Advocates Program. Contact Amy Bens at 978-624-2288, Gene Doughty at 978-624-2288, or visit www.nselder.org.
ROBERT K. MULLOY SCHOLARSHIP: A scholarship fund in memory of Robert K. Mulloy has been established for a Manchester Essex Regional High School senior who exhibits Rob's strength of character, positive attitude, vibrant personality, strong academic performance, sense of humor and athletic excellence. Tax-deductible donations may be sent to the Manchester Education Fund, f/b/o Robert K. Mulloy Scholarship, c/o Cape Ann Savings Bank, Attn: Gail Ramos, 109 Main St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
KATHERINE E. "RENEE" NUTBROWN: The League of Women Voters of Cape Ann awards three $500 scholarships to graduating seniors of Gloucester, Rockport and Manchester Essex high schools. The scholarship is named in honor of Katherine E. "Renee" Nutbrown, a longtime League of Women Voters member and community activist, who died in 2007. For those wishing to honor Nutbrown and the league's commitment to the next generation of citizens, tax-deductible contributions may be sent to: June Michaels, P.O. Box 244, Rockport, MA 01966. Checks should be made payable to LWVCA, with "scholarship" written on the memo line.
DAVID L. BENJAMIN MUSIC SCHOLARSHIP: Donations are being accepted for the David L. Benjamin Music Scholarship. The $500 scholarship is awarded annually to a Gloucester High School senior who is active in the instrumental or vocal music programs at Gloucester High School. Checks may be sent to: David L. Benjamin Music Scholarship, c/o Maureen Klopotoski, 169R Magnolia Ave., Gloucester, MA 01930.
STEPHEN B. ROSS SCHOLARSHIP: Stephen Ross was a Gloucester High School freshman who was struck and killed by a drunk driver while walking home one night in 1993. This scholarship is given to deserving Gloucester High School seniors every year. To donate, send contributions to Bob Gillis at the Cape Ann Savings Bank, 109 Main St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
CHARLIE THOMAS SCHOLARSHIP: The family of Charlie Thomas has established a scholarship in his memory to be awarded each year to a graduating Gloucester High School student. Charlie Thomas was a dedicated teacher who was devoted to his profession and enjoyed teaching students not only in the classroom, but also through extracurricular activities and sports. Students planning a career in education will be given preference. Send donations to the Charlie Thomas Scholarship Fund, c/o Mary Thomas, 90 Langsford St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
NEIL G. RAMSDEN ACADEMIC ACHIEVEMENT AWARD: Donations are being accepted for this memorial award given by the Essex teachers. This award is given to Essex seniors who are also graduates of Essex Elementary School and are enrolling in at least a two-year program of study. It is awarded on the basis of academic achievement, citizenship and service. Donations may be made in the form of a check made out to the Manchester Federal Credit Union, c/o Susan Hardy, Essex Elementary School, 12 Story St., Essex, MA 01929.
WELLSPRING HOUSE: Wellspring House is looking for volunteers for its ESOL (English for Speakers of Other Languages) and ALI (Adult Learning Initiative) programs. Call 978-281-3558.
LINDA WIEDITZ SCHOLARSHIP FUND: Donations are being accepted for the Linda Wieditz Scholarship Fund. A scholarship, given in memory of the much beloved music teacher in the Rockport Public Schools, is presented at the Rockport High School graduation each year to one or more graduates pursuing music studies in higher education. Checks, made payable to the "Linda Wieditz Memorial Scholarship," should be mailed to: Linda Wieditz Memorial Scholarship, P.O. Box 191, Rockport, MA 01966.
GLOUCESTER EDUCATION FOUNDATION: The Gloucester Education Foundation (GEF) supports innovation and excellence in the Gloucester Public School District. GEF funds educational programs and initiatives across all district schools, grade levels and disciplines that have real impact on teaching and learning. Visit www.thinkthebest.org. Financial contributions may be made online or by mail to: GEF, 33 Commercial St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
VOLUNTEERS NEEDED: RSVP of the North Shore is a volunteer network for people ages 55 and over, and offers a full range of volunteer opportunities with many area nonprofit organizations. RSVP is part of the Corporation for National and Community Service and is sponsored locally by SeniorCare Inc. Call 978-281-1750 or 1-866-927-1050, or visit www.seniorcareinc.org/rsvp.html.
HAWC VOLUNTEER TRAINING: HAWC (Healing Abuse Working for Change, www.hawcdv.org), is seeking volunteers for a 24-hour hot-line service to help end family violence. Volunteers must complete 30 hours of training on evenings and Saturdays. Training provides volunteers with the information needed to answer the 24-hour hot-line, which can be answered from your home. Email info@hawcdv.org
ELDER VOLUNTEERS SOUGHT: The Rose Baker Senior Center and the Council on Aging (COA) needs friendly visitors and shoppers to provide weekly shopping and home visits to home-bound elders. The Gloucester COA has many other volunteer opportunities also available. Call Lydia at 978-281-9765, ext. 14.
PAT ROY SCHOLARSHIP: The board of directors of the Cape Ann Chamber of Commerce has established a scholarship in honor of past President Pat Roy, the first woman leader in the organization 's history. The scholarship will be awarded each year to a young woman pursuing business courses in college. The chamber will provide an annual endowment of $500 and welcomes additional contributions from those wishing to honor Roy's accomplishments as a key member of the Woodman family business and in strengthening the business and civic climate of the region. Send checks to the Pat Roy Scholarship Fund, c/o Cape Ann Chamber of Commerce, 33 Commercial St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
PAT ROY SCHOLARSHIP: The board of directors of the Cape Ann Chamber of Commerce has established a scholarship in honor of past President Pat Roy, the first woman leader in the organization's history. The scholarship will be awarded each year to a young woman pursuing business courses in college. The chamber will provide an annual endowment of $500 and welcomes additional contributions from those wishing to honor Roy's accomplishments as a key member of the Woodman family business and in strengthening the business and civic climate of the region. Send checks to the Pat Roy Scholarship Fund, c/o Cape Ann Chamber of Commerce, 33 Commercial St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
SCHOOL LIBRARIES SEEK DONATIONS: Many of Gloucester's public school libraries welcome donations of books suitable for student borrowing. Books should be new or gently used and published within the past 10 years. Please do not donate old encyclopedias, damaged or musty-smelling books. Monetary donations to be used toward the purchase of books are also welcome. Donations may be dropped off at the schools. For more information, email Mary Saunders at Gloucester High School at msaunders@gloucester.k12.ma.us; Maureen Foster at O 'Maley Middle School at maureen.foster@comcast.net; Diane Bevins at Beeman Memorial School at dojbessex@juno.com; Sharron Cohen at Plum Cove School at sharronster@gmail.com; Cathy Lake at West Parish Elementary School at cathy@lakesinmagnolia.com; and Cherylann Parker at Veteran 's Memorial School at cparker@gloucester.k12.ma.us
NURSING HOME VOLUNTEERS: SeniorCare seeks volunteers who want to make a difference. Volunteers must be willing to spend 10 hours per month advocating for patients or residents as they live their lives with dignity and respect at a nursing facility or rehabilitation center. Volunteers will also work with the residents and staff to resolve concerns about residents ' rights and quality of life and care. A one year commitment is necessary after a local three day training class. To schedule an interview, call SeniorCare at 1-866-927-1050 (toll free) or 978-281-1750, Ext. 336. To learn more, visit: www.seniorcareinc.org.
SCHOONER ADVENTURE: The schooner Adventure needs volunteers for office support, exhibit development, event organization, photography, public relations and the ship's store. The Gloucester Adventure Inc., a nonprofit historic preservation and educational organization, was established to restore the schooner Adventure as a historic community resource and living classroom. Volunteers help year-round with vessel restoration, educational programs, events and fundraising. Visit www.schooner-adventure.org. Send donations to the Gloucester Adventure Inc., P.O. Box 1306, Gloucester, MA 01931. Contact Joanne Souza at 978-281-8079 or jsouza@schooner-adventure.org
ROBERT K. MULLOY SCHOLARSHIP: A scholarship fund in memory of Robert K. Mulloy has been established for a Manchester Essex Regional High School senior who exhibits Rob 's strength of character, positive attitude, vibrant personality, strong academic performance, sense of humor and athletic excellence. Tax-deductible donations may be sent to the Manchester Education Fund, f/b/o Robert K. Mulloy Scholarship, c/o Cape Ann Savings Bank, Attn: Gail Ramos, 109 Main St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
KATHERINE E. "RENEE" NUTBROWN: The League of Women Voters of Cape Ann awards three $500 scholarships to graduating seniors of Gloucester, Rockport and Manchester Essex high schools. The scholarship is named in honor of Katherine E. "Renee" Nutbrown, a longtime League of Women Voters member and community activist, who died in 2007. For those wishing to honor Nutbrown and the league's commitment to the next generation of citizens, tax-deductible contributions may be sent to: June Michaels, P.O. Box 244, Rockport, MA 01966. Checks should be made payable to LWVCA, with "scholarship" written on the memo line.
TRUSTEES OF RESERVATIONS: The Trustees of Reservations needs adult volunteers for its Show-n-Go work crew. The crew meets on the first Tuesday of every month, April to November, at the Coolidge Reservation in Manchester, from 9 a.m. to noon. Learn stewardship skills and work side-by-side with The Trustees staff for hands-on work on our Cape Ann conserved lands. Work includes trail clearing, building boardwalks, painting, mending fences and performing resource management care. Call 978-921-1944, ext. 4013, or visit www.thetrustees.org.
TRANSPORT DRIVERS FOR SENIORS NEEDED: RSVP Volunteers of the North Shore seeks volunteer medical transportation drivers. SeniorCare is in need of volunteers from Gloucester and Rockport for local and out-of-town appointments. Volunteers choose when and how often they drive. Drivers are compensated. Call 978-281-1750.
CAPE ANN ANIMAL AID: Cape Ann Animal Aid, 4 Paws Lane., a no-kill, nonprofit organization dedicated to finding appropriate placement for adoptable animals, seeks donations of cleaning and office supplies, animal toys and treats, collars and leashes. CAAA also seeks volunteers to help care for the shelter dogs and cats and to help with special fundraising events. All volunteers must attend an orientation before starting. Visit www.CapeAnnAnimalAid.com or call 978-283-6055.
VOLUNTEER OPPORTUNITIES: North Shore Elder Services, 152 Sylvan St., Danvers, seeks volunteers willing to make a difference in the life of an elder by joining its Money Management Program, Ombudsman Program or At Your Side Medical Advocates Program. Contact Amy Bens at 978-624-2288, Gene Doughty at 978-624-2288, or visit www.nselder.org.
DRIVERS NEEDED: SeniorCare Inc. seeks volunteers to deliver Meals on Wheels in East Gloucester on Tuesdays and/or Wednesdays. Call 978-281-1750.
KESTREL EDUCATIONAL ADVENTURES: Kestrel Educational Adventures, a nonprofit organization, brings hands-on science education to schools in Gloucester, Rockport, Manchester, Essex, Beverly and Salem. Entering its sixth year, Kestrel is launching its first fundraising and membership campaign which will support programs such as Forest Connections and Ponds in the Classroom, as well as the Animal Care and Conservation Afterschool Clubs. Kestrel focuses on bringing students out to explore local wild lands and bringing live animals into the classroom. Follow-up materials are provided for teachers and students to encourage the continued exploration of nature. Kestrel is looking for volunteers to join its board of directors or assist with many projects throughout the year. Visit www.kestreleducation.org or call 978-633-7100.
DAVID L. BENJAMIN MUSIC SCHOLARSHIP: Donations are being accepted for the David L. Benjamin Music Scholarship. The $500 scholarship is awarded annually to a Gloucester High School senior who is active in the instrumental or vocal music programs at Gloucester High School. Checks may be sent to: David L. Benjamin Music Scholarship, c/o Maureen Klopotoski, 169R Magnolia Ave., Gloucester, MA 01930.
STEPHEN B. ROSS SCHOLARSHIP: Stephen Ross was a Gloucester High School freshman who was struck and killed by a drunk driver while walking home one night in 1993. This scholarship is given to deserving Gloucester High School seniors every year. To donate, send contributions to Bob Gillis at the Cape Ann Savings Bank, 109 Main St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
SCHOOL LIBRARIES SEEK DONATIONS: Many of Gloucester's public school libraries welcome donations of books suitable for student borrowing. Books should be new or gently used and published within the past 10 years. Please do not donate old encyclopedias, damaged or musty-smelling books. Monetary donations to be used toward the purchase of books are also welcome. Donations may be dropped off at the schools. For more information, email Mary Saunders at Gloucester High School at msaunders@gloucester.k12.ma.us; Maureen Foster at O 'Maley Middle School at maureen.foster@comcast.net; Diane Bevins at Beeman Memorial School at dojbessex@juno.com; Sharron Cohen at Plum Cove School at sharronster@gmail.com; Cathy Lake at West Parish Elementary School at cathy@lakesinmagnolia.com; and Cherylann Parker at Veteran 's Memorial School at cparker@gloucester.k12.ma.us
TRUSTEES OF RESERVATIONS: The Trustees of Reservations needs adult volunteers for its Show-n-Go work crew. The crew meets on the first Tuesday of every month, April to November, at the Coolidge Reservation in Manchester, from 9 a.m. to noon. Learn stewardship skills and work side-by-side with The Trustees staff for hands-on work on our Cape Ann conserved lands. Work includes trail clearing, building boardwalks, painting, mending fences and performing resource management care. Call 978-921-1944, ext. 4013, or visit www.thetrustees.org.
VNA CARE NETWORK & HOSPICE VOLUNTEERS: VNA Care Network & Hospice, a nonprofit home health care, hospice and wellness agency, needs volunteers to provide practical and emotional support to terminally-ill patients and their families on the North Shore, Cape Ann and Merrimack Valley. Volunteers receive training, supervision and support. Call Nancy Barcelo at 1-888-663-3688, ext. 4271. Visit www.vnacarenetwork.org. or call 1-800-728-1862.
MELANOMA EDUCATION FOUNDATION: The Melanoma Education Foundation seeks volunteers to help raise melanoma awareness. Volunteers should preferably have two or more weekdays per month available and be willing to plan and organize fundraising events in their area in memory of a loved one or friend whose life was lost to melanoma. Examples of fundraisers are races, raffles, dinners and auctions. For details, call 1-800-259-1633, email MEF@skincheck.org or visit www.skincheck.org.
GARDEN VOLUNTEERS NEEDED: Essex County Greenbelt needs garden volunteers for Cox Reservation, 82 Eastern Ave., Essex. The construction of Greenbelt 's new "green" headquarters is complete, and now its focus has shifted to the landscaping and perennial gardens around the Cox house. Experienced gardeners are needed to help plan and execute a simple landscape and garden design. This will require attendance at meetings and regular correspondence with Greenbelt and other garden volunteers. Anyone who is interested in volunteering some amount of time (weekly/bi-weekly) to maintain the perennial gardens at the Cox Reservation are also needed. Volunteers should be physically fit for some strenuous activity and lifting. Contact Kate Walton at kwalton@ecga.org or 978-768-7241, ext. 15.
BUSTING BREAST CANCER: The Essex County Busting Breast Cancer Initiative needs volunteer workshop leaders from Essex, Gloucester and Manchester, as well as a fundraising administrator and a publicity coordinator. During 2012 the National Breast Cancer Prevention Project/Know Breast Cancer, based in Manchester, will teach Essex County women three safe, inexpensive and healthy ways to help stop breast cancer before it can start. NBCPP/Know Breast Cancer is a 5-year-old nonprofit educational organization. Visit www.knowbreastcancer.net, email info@knowbreastcancer.net or call 978-526-8702.
SOCIAL DAY CARE PROGRAM: The Gloucester Council on Aging 's Social Day Care Program is looking for enthusiastic, responsible volunteers to assist the program coordinator with stimulating activities for 10 frail seniors. Shifts are available on Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays between 9 a.m. and 3 p.m. Call Christie Parker at 978-281-9765, ext. 20.
LISA BETH CURCURU SCHOLARSHIP: A memorial scholarship has been established to remember Lisa Beth Curcuru. All proceeds go directly to an annual scholarship awarded to a Gloucester High School student. Donations may be made to the Lisa Beth Curcuru Scholarship Fund, c/o Cape Ann Savings Bank, 109 Main St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
PATHWAYS VOLUNTEERS: Pathways for Children needs volunteers to help out, either for one time only or on a weekly basis, working with support staff in the classroom, sharing a special interest or skill or assisting with homework. Pathways has opportunities working with all ages, beginning with infants and toddlers in the Young Families Initiative, Head Start preschool program, and School-Age Care, which provides after-school programs for children up to age 12. There are also some opportunities available outside the classroom. Call Laura Trainor at 978-281-2400, ext. 320 or email dfoster@pw4c.org
CAROLYN O 'CONNOR SCHOLARSHIP: The Carolyn O'Connor Scholarship has been established by the Cape Ann Chamber Businesswomen. The $1,000 scholarship, named in honor of the group's first chairwoman, will be awarded annually to a Cape Ann woman looking to change careers or re-enter the work force. Each applicant must have a high school diploma or its equivalent, be a legal resident, and be accepted into an accredited college, university or job training program. Applications are available at the chamber office or by calling 978-283-1601. Contributions, made payable to Businesswomen's Scholarship Fund, may be sent to Chamber Businesswomen's Division, Cape Ann Chamber of Commerce, 33 Commercial St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
GARDEN VOLUNTEERS NEEDED: Essex County Greenbelt needs garden volunteers for Cox Reservation, 82 Eastern Ave., Essex. The construction of Greenbelt's new "green" headquarters is complete, and now its focus has shifted to the landscaping and perennial gardens around the Cox house. Experienced gardeners are needed to help plan and execute a simple landscape and garden design. This will require attendance at meetings and regular correspondence with Greenbelt and other garden volunteers. Anyone who is interested in volunteering some amount of time (weekly/bi-weekly) to maintain the perennial gardens at the Cox Reservation are also needed. Volunteers should be physically fit for some strenuous activity and lifting. Contact Kate Walton at kwalton@ecga.org or 978-768-7241, ext. 15.
BUSTING BREAST CANCER: The Essex County Busting Breast Cancer Initiative needs volunteer workshop leaders from Essex, Gloucester and Manchester, as well as a fundraising administrator and a publicity coordinator. During 2012 the National Breast Cancer Prevention Project/Know Breast Cancer, based in Manchester, will teach Essex County women three safe, inexpensive and healthy ways to help stop breast cancer before it can start. NBCPP/Know Breast Cancer is a 5-year-old nonprofit educational organization. Visit www.knowbreastcancer.net, email info@knowbreastcancer.net or call 978-526-8702.
SOCIAL DAY CARE PROGRAM: The Gloucester Council on Aging 's Social Day Care Program is looking for enthusiastic, responsible volunteers to assist the program coordinator with stimulating activities for 10 frail seniors. Shifts are available on Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays between 9 a.m. and 3 p.m. Call Christie Parker at 978-281-9765, ext. 20.
LISA BETH CURCURU SCHOLARSHIP: A memorial scholarship has been established to remember Lisa Beth Curcuru. All proceeds go directly to an annual scholarship awarded to a Gloucester High School student. Donations may be made to the Lisa Beth Curcuru Scholarship Fund, c/o Cape Ann Savings Bank, 109 Main St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
PATHWAYS VOLUNTEERS: Pathways for Children needs volunteers to help out, either for one time only or on a weekly basis, working with support staff in the classroom, sharing a special interest or skill or assisting with homework. Pathways has opportunities working with all ages, beginning with infants and toddlers in the Young Families Initiative, Head Start preschool program, and School-Age Care, which provides after-school programs for children up to age 12. There are also some opportunities available outside the classroom. Call Laura Trainor at 978-281-2400, ext. 320 or email dfoster@pw4c.org
VOLUNTEER DRIVERS NEEDED: The American Cancer Society 's Road to Recovery program needs volunteers to drive local cancer patients to and from chemotherapy and/or radiation treatments. Drivers use their own vehicles. The schedule is flexible, and treatment appointments take place weekdays, primarily during business hours. Call 800-ACS-2345 or visit www.cancer.org.
CAROLYN O'CONNOR SCHOLARSHIP: The Carolyn O'Connor Scholarship has been established by the Cape Ann Chamber Businesswomen. The $1,000 scholarship, named in honor of the group's first chairwoman, will be awarded annually to a Cape Ann woman looking to change careers or re-enter the work force. Each applicant must have a high school diploma or its equivalent, be a legal resident, and be accepted into an accredited college, university or job training program. Applications are available at the chamber office or by calling 978-283-1601. Contributions, made payable to Businesswomen's Scholarship Fund, may be sent to Chamber Businesswomen's Division, Cape Ann Chamber of Commerce, 33 Commercial St., Gloucester, MA 01930.
MAGNOLIA HISTORICAL SOCIETY: Historically-minded volunteers are needed to help with digitizing the collection, filing, helping with grants and other related work. Someone with computer experience would also be a big help. Call Lisa at 978-290-3005.
ADDISON GILBERT VOLUNTEERS: Addison Gilbert Hospital in Gloucester seeks applicants to join its team of enthusiastic and professional volunteers. The Emergency Department, Surgical Day Care Unit and Adult Unit need volunteers to give directions, assist with activities, transport patients within the hospital, and help serve refreshments. Opportunities are also available for clerical assistance and sales positions in the gift shop for morning, afternoon and evening shifts. Training, free parking and meal vouchers for the hospital's cafe are provided. Call 978-922-3000, ext. 2307.
ADULT FOSTER CARE: A volunteer is needed to be rep payee for a disabled adult to handle monthly deposit and a few checks. Free training. Volunteer must be 'squeaky clean' and organized. Call 978-281-2612 or email cbjorlie@adultfostercarens.com
LIBRARY VOLUNTEERS: Manchester Public Library depends on volunteers to keep up with a busy schedule. Shelving books, processing materials, data entry, homework center coach, are just some of the tasks performed by volunteers. If you have an hour or two a week consider joining the library community. Call 978-526-7711.
LISA SPARACO SCHOLARSHIP: Donations are being accepted in memory of Lisa Sparaco, who was killed in a drunken driving accident. A scholarship will be given to an Ipswich High School senior who needs assistance to attend college. Send donations to the Lisa Sparaco Scholarship Fund, c/o First National Bank of Ipswich, Attn: Jenny, 31 Market St., Ipswich, MA 01938.
VOLUNTEERS NEEDED: The Council on Aging needs volunteers to drive seniors to and from medical appointments. Mileage reimbursement is offered. Volunteers are also needed for the Friendly Visitors program. Volunteers visit homebound elders for one to two hours per week with the goal of providing a supportive friendship and, in some cases, light grocery shopping. Training and support are provided. For more information, call Claire or Peg at the Rose Baker Senior Center at 978-281-9765.
PLANT COMMITTEE: The Gloucester Plant Committee is seeking volunteer gardeners to help care for public spaces in Gloucester. No experience necessary. Committee meets Wednesdays, 6 to 7 p.m., at perennials gardens on Stacy Boulevard, near Fishermen 's Wives Memorial. Gardening begins mid-April. Email Susan Kelly at susan@generousgardeners.org for information.
GHS ALUMNI SCHOLARSHIP FUND: The Gloucester High School Alumni Scholarship Fund was initiated in 1975 by the Class of 1925. It is the responsibility of the Trustees to raise and distribute scholarship monies each year. In the spring of 2014, four $1,500 Alumni Scholarships and one $2,000 Founders Scholarship will be awarded. These amounts will be enhanced if fundraising allows. Trustees are committed to choosing students who best exhibit the requirements of each scholarship. Candidates must show proof of financial need, academic success and self-help to justify investment in their future. Investing in GHS graduates is a way of investing in Gloucester 's future. Send tax-deductible donations to: GHS Alumni Scholarship Fund, P.O. Box 1226, Gloucester, MA 01930; or visit www.ghsalumni.org.
SCORE VOLUNTEER BUSINESS COUNSELORS: SCORE needs volunteers with business ownership or management experience to provide free confidential business counseling to local people who want to start a business, buy or sell a business, or improve the performance of an existing business. SCORE N.E. Massachusetts has 34 business counselors with varied business backgrounds that met with more than 2,000 clients last year in Gloucester and 11 other regional locations. Nationwide there are more than 12,400 SCORE volunteer counselors. Visit www.scorenemass.org, email membership@scorenemass.org or call Jack Clauson at 978-973-8948.
MAB COMMUNITY SERVICES: Donate your old car to MAB Community Services, formerly the Massachusetts Association for the Blind, which provides services and programs to the blind and vision-impaired community of Massachusetts. Free tow and quick pickup are available. Old cars, boats, trailers, campers, motorcycles, Jet Skis and snowmobiles may be donated. Call 888-613-2777.
ROCKPORT EDUCATIONAL FOUNDATION: The Rockport Educational Foundation, a nonprofit corporation, raises funds from private sources to improve and enrich the Rockport educational system. Donations are used to support projects in the schools for which there are insufficient funding. For more information, contact the Educational Foundation for Rockport, c/o Superintendent 's Office, 24 Jerden's Lane, Rockport, MA 01966; or visit www.rockportedfoundation.org.
]]></text></news-item>