<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVM-Y8P1-F09T-F2DV"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Unsavory private-eye 'pretexting' a flash point in $102 million San Bernardino corruption case</title><source>Redlands Daily Facts (California)</source><author>Joe Nelson</author><text><![CDATA[When a prestigious El Segundo-based private investigations firm was hired to investigate the key witness in a major San Bernardino County corruption case, they subcontracted the work - or at least part of it - to a rural Alabama woman who had no license and a spotty criminal record.
That woman, according to court documents, used information provided by the El Segundo firm Thomas Dale & Associates to impersonate the witness and illegally gain access to his phone records.
While the incident has become a flash point in the San Bernardino County case, the practice of hiring independent contractors to develop potentially illegal information is not all that unusual, according to experts.
"It goes on all the time," said Rob Douglas, a former Washington D.C.-based private investigator of 20 years and nationally recognized identity theft and information security expert. "It is frequent enough that I believe for hundreds of private investigators across the country, it's a routine way of doing business."
No charges have been filed against the woman, Theresa C. Speer, aka Theresa C. Paul, of Fairhope, Ala., or Thomas Dale & Associates, the company that subcontracted her services, but prosecutors say the investigation, which began three years ago, is ongoing. They say Speer hijacked the phone records of former San Bernardino County Supervisor Bill Postmus, a key witness in the ongoing criminal investigation into the county's $102 million legal settlement with Colonies Partners LP.
Stephen P. Jones, the attorney representing Thomas Dale & Associates, declined to comment for this story.
According to court documents, Speer was hired by Thomas Dale & Associates, which touts on its website a client base that includes NBC Universal, Paramount Pictures and CNN. TDA was hired by attorney Stephen G. Larson, a retired U.S. District Court judge-turned- defense attorney who now represents Colonies co-managing partner Jeff Burum, who is charged with bribing public officials to settle his partnership's legal case.
Speer could face up to a half-dozen felony charges, including criminal conspiracy and illegally accessing a computer network, according to a search warrant affidavit filed in San Bernardino Superior Court.
The San Bernardino County case is similar to other high-profile incidents in which investigators obtained private information under false pretenses - a strategy so common it's been given a name: pretexting.
The most noteworthy of these is the spying scandal at Hewlett- Packard in which HP executives hired private investigators to help determine who was leaking confidential company information to the press.
In October 2006, the state Attorney General's Office charged HP Chairwoman Patricia Dunn, who launched the investigation into the news leak, HP's former chief ethics officer Kevin Hunsaker, and three outside private investigators with four felonies. Dunn maintained her innocence, testifying before Congress she had believed the actions of the private investigators were legal. All charges against her were subsequently dropped.
Hunsaker and two of the private investigators, under a plea agreement, pleaded guilty to one count of wire fraud and were sentenced to 96 hours of community service, and the third investigator, Bryan Wagner, was convicted of the federal offenses of wire fraud and identity theft and sentenced to three months in federal lockup.
Though laws have been passed to protect consumers and deter such activity, prosecutors have had a hard time making cases. Douglas notes that in many cases, private investigators are hired by large firms with deep pockets, and pursuing a pretexting case can be complex and very expensive.
"It is the major law firms in this country that are hiring these people," Douglas said.
FALSE PRETENSES
The investigation into Speer and Thomas Dale & Associates sprouted from San Bernardino County's Colonies corruption case, in which Rancho Cucamonga developer Burum and three former county officials stand accused of conspiracy and bribery. Prosecutors allege Burum, former county Supervisor Paul Biane, former Assistant Assessor and labor union president Jim Erwin, and Mark Kirk, former chief of staff for supervisor Gary Ovitt - conspired to facilitate a $102 million legal settlement between Burum's real estate investor group, Colonies Partners LP, and the county for $102 million in November 2006.
In exchange for shepherding the settlement in Colonies' favor, presecutors contend, Burum gave each of the other defendants $100,000, which was funneled into phony political action committees secretly controlled by the supervisors who voted in favor of the Colonies settlement.
All four defendants deny any wrongdoing.
Postmus, initially a defendant in the case, has admitted taking a $100,000 bribe from Burum in exchange for voting in favor of the settlement in 2006 while serving as chairman of the Board of Supervisors. As part of a plea bargain with prosecutors, Postmus has become a key witness in the ongoing case.
Burum's attorney, Larson, has acknowledged hiring private investigators to tail Postmus, an admitted methamphetamine addict, to see if he was still abusing the drug, but those services were terminated after Postmus realized he was under surveillance, according to court documents.
Larson also declined to comment for this story. Postmus became concerned that someone had hacked his phone when he received a text message from his carrier, AT&T, informing him that his account information had been changed. He alerted prosecutors, who began an investigation. They ultimately learned that Speer had contacted AT&T and used information about Postmus provided by TDA to route his phone records to a Yahoo! email account she had set up.
On Jan. 31, 2013, district attorney's investigators served a search warrant at TDA's office as part of their investigation.
Larson is alleging in a court motion that investigators and prosecutors in the Colonies case conducted the search at TDA in an effort to "raid the defense camp" and seize privileged attorney- client information to gain an upper hand in the Colonies prosecution.
In an interview with law enforcement investigators at her doublewide in Fairhope, Ala., Speer said she has owned "Lookout Resources" since 2008 and that she is hired by private investigators, bail bondsmen and attorneys to locate people. She told investigators that the firms that retain her services provide her basic information about a search subject, such as his or her name, Social Security number, birthdate and last known address.
According to the search warrant affidavit, Speer would use this information to determine what companies provided phone, Internet or utility service to the individual in question. Then she would call those companies and pretend she was assisting a client with their account.
"Using the information provided by the client, Speer would then trick the proper company representative into giving her private information on the person she was hired to locate," San Bernardino County district attorney investigator Eric Bremner wrote in his affidavit.
Speer who according to Baldwin County, Ala. court records has misdemeanor convictions for domestic violence, being drunk in public and driving on a suspended license, could not be reached for comment for this story.
PLAUSIBLE DENIABILITY
California's Private Investigator Act prohibits private investigators from committing "any act constituting dishonesty or fraud," said Los Angeles lawyer John Caragozian, whose 2004 article, "Private Investigators in California: Analysis of the PIA and Case Law" has circulated widely in legal publications and online.
"Private investigators have no more rights to access people's personal information than any other citizen, beyond what a reporter has or any other citizen has," Caragozian said. "If it would be illegal for a private person to do something, chances are it's illegal for a private investigator to do it."
Private investigators subcontract with people like Speer to insulate themselves from potential criminal culpability, experts say.
It creates plausible deniability, said Chris Jay Hoofnagle, director of information and privacy programs at the Berkeley Center for Law & Technology. Hoofnagle has written extensively in the fields of information privacy and deceptive practices including pretexting, and was at the forefront of a 2005 push to get the federal government to establish stricter rules surrounding the dissemination of a consumers' personal phone records.
He submitted a petition to the Federal Communications Commission, which revised its policies, Hoofnagle said.
"In my 2005 investigation of the field, we found many examples of firms that said they could get phone records, but would not disclose their specific methods," Hoofnagle said. "These were pretexting firms, but with a nod and a wink, they created deniability for the clients who hired them."
The more distance created between the private investigators and subcontractor, the more plausible the deniability, said Stan Goldman, a criminal law professor at Loyola Law School.
"It's a perfectly plausible reason why you would have somebody else do your dirty work for you," Goldman said.
Douglas said individuals hired by private investigators for such services, such as Speer in the Postmus case, are known in the field as "information brokers."
The information brokers typically live and work on the margins of the private investigative world.
"A lot of them are wannabees. They wanted to be a cop or they wanted to be private investigators themselves," Douglas said. "It's kind of a fraternity of players.
Oftentimes, the so-called information brokers display the characteristics of a sociopath."
"There is no line for them. They can't see the line," Douglas said. "In many cases, they truly believe they are the good guys, and what they're doing is good."
UNSAVORY PRACTICE
Douglas said the method in which Speer is accused of accessing Postmus' phone records is one of the most common and popular ways of obtaining the information under false pretenses because the information is easily available online, so long as a few pieces of personal information from the actual account holder are available.
"What we found was that this was so easy. The information brokers would go to these (online accounts). It was the first thing they would look at because it was so easy," said Douglas.
He cited the case of Adam Yuzuk, former president of a New York leather accessories company, who in 2006 discovered someone had used his social security number and a fake email address to set up his online Cingular Wireless account to view his calling records.
Yuzuk had been involved in a legal dispute with his former partners of the firm, and he learned that they had paid a private investigator to dig up information on him, including paying the PI $300 to access Yuzuk's phone records.
Yuzuk's case was featured at a Congressional hearing in June 2006.
Perhaps the worst case of pretexting is that of 20-year-old Amy Boyer, who was shot and killed in October 1999 by a man who had obtained her work address from an online company called Docusearch, which employed New York subcontractor Michelle Gambino to place a pretext call to Boyer and trick her into giving up her workplace address, according to published news reports.
Many, however, have argued that pretexting is a tried and true method of developing information in an investigation, especially useful in collecting debts, tracking down bail jumpers or locating parents in arrears on child support.
Goldman likens the practices to that of the classic fictional English sleuth Sherlock Holmes and his employment of knowledgeable street kids, known as the Baker Street Irregulars, to track people down.
"Maybe this is the same kind of thing - it's the 21st Century version of the Baker Street Irregulars," Goldman said.
]]></text></news-item>