<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVM-4J01-JCV0-11MY"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Unclear who ordered Marikana tear gas barrage</title><source>Cape Argus (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[THE IDENTITY of the police officer who ordered the firing of tear gas at Marikana that led to a fatal clash on August 13, 2012, is still unclear.
Yesterday the chairman of the Farlam Commission of Inquiry, retired Judge Ian Farlam, sought greater clarity on this from North West air wing commander Salmon Vermaak.
Vermaak was one of the senior police officers present at the Lonmin labour unrest.
"Your affidavit, which you made on January 21 this year, doesn't coincide with what you say in your information note handed to this commission," Farlam said in Pretoria.
"You said the instruction from General (William) Mpembe that tear gas and stun grenades must be thrown triggered the assault on the SAPS (by protesters).
"You said Mpembe denied giving the instruction and only after Captain (Samuel) Thupe said he was next to the general when the instruction was given... only after that General Mpembe admitted that it was him."
Major-General Mpembe is North West deputy provincial police commissioner.
Farlam said Vermaak's affidavit said Mpembe initially denied giving the instructions. He later conceded he might have given the orders, but he had forgotten.
Vermaak responded: "At first he denied it, after Captain Thupe directly confronted him about it. General Mpembe then said if it was him, then he doesn't remember it."
Judge Farlam said there was still no clarity over who gave the instruction.
On August 13, 2012, the police were monitoring a group of miners moving from a railway line towards a koppie. They had refused to surrender their weapons and started moving as Mpembe instructed them to disarm.
As the protesters altered their route, heading towards an informal settlement, some police officers have testified that an instruction was given to fire tear gas. In response, the miners then charged at police and allegedly killed two officers. Three miners were killed.
When Mpembe testified at the inquiry last year, he said a Warrant Officer Kuhn had fired tear gas at the mine workers, but he was unaware who had instructed Kuhn to do so.
"I told the provincial commissioner, that Kuhn himself could not say who he got the instruction from," Mpembe told Michelle le Roux, for the SA Human Rights Commission. - Sapa
]]></text></news-item>