<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVN-4WB1-DYTR-J0MG"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Fraud investigation at Mighty River Power</title><source>The Sunday Star-Times (Auckland, New Zealand)</source><author>By MATT NIPPERT</author><text><![CDATA[A SENIOR Mighty River Power manager has been dismissed and the Serious Fraud Office is investigating after alleged procurement fraud at the recently-listed energy giant.
A spokeswoman for MRP confirmed a senior manager had been dismissed in late 2012 and a related fraud complaint was made to police in February 2013.
"It then got handed to the SFO and they've yet to make a decision on whether to prosecute," the spokeswoman said.
The SFO confirmed receipt of the MRP complaint but under a new media policy refused to answer any other questions.
"We are not in a position to make any further comment at this time," a spokeswoman said.
The SFO is charged with investigating fraud involving losses of more than $5 million, or where the case is too complex for police, or where public officials or funds are involved.
The amount stolen in the alleged fraud has not been disclosed.
MRP was the first state- owned energy company to be part-sold under the Government's mixed ownership model policy, debuting on the NZX in May last year.
The Sunday Star-Times understands the timing of the fraud allegation caused consternation at MRP and internal debate took place over whether political or market demands required it to be publicly announced.
The MRP spokeswoman defended the nondisclosure and said the losses due to the alleged fraud did not require notification to the NZX.
"There was not a material loss, and they have been historic," she said.
The spokeswoman said changes had been enacted after the episode.
"What we can say is we have implemented changes to inventory management and procurement processes. And we've had them audited."
The case is the latest in a growing trend of commercial and public sector procurement fraud and corruption being tackled by the SFO.
Last week the trial of former Auckland Blues chief executive Peter Scutts was confirmed to take place in the High Court in November this year.
Scutts, who has pleaded not guilty, is charged with taking $64,000 in kickbacks from a supplier during his time heading the NZX-listed New Zealand Wine Company.
Also last week Jimmy Miu was found guilty in the Auckland District Court of defrauding his employer, McKay Shipping, of over $1 million through the purchase of nonexistent or overpriced computer products.
In October last year Hemant Maharaj and Suresh Din were respectively sentenced to prison and home detention following the payment of $849,000 in council funds for road and berm projects that were never completed.
An SFO investigation into several individuals responsible for issuing roading contacts at Auckland Transport is ongoing.
Investigator Mark van Leewarden, of Warden Consulting, said the high-profile prosecution of former MP Taito Phillip Field for corruption had helped dispel some misconceptions.
"There's probably been a bit of latent comfort based on the fact that we think we're clean and green and that corruption doesn't exist," he said.
"If you see that type of conduct happening at the highest levels, there's no doubt - and you must assume - it's happening further down the chain."
Leewarden said the rise in investigations and prosecutions of procurement fraud and corruption showed organisations were now focused on rooting out financial crime.
--------------------
CAPTION:
Mighty silence: The SFO confirmed receipt of the MRP complaint but refused to answer any other questions. Above is a scene from the advertisement inviting people to invest in the public share offer.
]]></text></news-item>