<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVN-HJ11-JC8W-62W0"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Saturday: Low spirits at the bar: With pub landlords coming bottom in a new survey of job satisfaction, we sent Pete Brown to pull pints in the Rose and Crown - and find out how to cheer them up</title><source>The Guardian (London) - Final Edition</source><author>Pete Brown</author><text><![CDATA['Can you go round and check there's no dead bodies in the toilets, Pete?" asks Will, who has been showing me the ropes. "Flush anything nasty away and then lock them with the bolts at the top." As Petra, another member of the team, finishes mopping the floors, and Andrew, the shift manager, cashes up the tills in the office downstairs, I slump on to a bar stool, knackered. It's 12.30am.
It's not that my first shift behind a bar for over 20 years has been physically arduous. It's just that I'd forgotten what it was like to be alert and on duty at a time when I'm normally nursing a pint on the other side of the bar or thinking about going to bed.
And make no mistake - I've been lucky. Tonight was a quiet night in a good pub in a pleasant part of London.
"I once worked in a pub in the City," says Petra, "I lasted a week. No please or thank you, just 'Guinness', and the money thrown at you."
I haven't had to face anyone like the man who threatened to call the police when he decided his card had been cloned after sharing three bottles of wine with his wife, or the drunk woman who became violent and announced that she was a solicitor who was going to get this fucking place shut down - two customers Andrew had to deal with on the same night.
It's not just football supporters or stag nights that can make a bartender's life hell.
Last time I worked behind a bar I was a university student in St Andrews. It was mostly OK, apart from when alcoholic Old Course caddies threatened to kill me for being an English bastard, or possibly for being a 19-year-old with a stupid indie haircut.
Even then, I was lucky enough to avoid the tribulations faced far too often by my friend Emma, manager of the BrewDog bar in Camden. Despite brilliant support from her employers, there invariably seems to be more than she bargains for when she has to check the toilets.
"Why do men who need to be sick always do it in the urinal?" she asks. "The only way to clear it out from there is to scoop it by hand. And it's a law of pub nature that pub toilets only get blocked on a Friday or Saturday night when you can't get a plumber. Then it's a bin bag up to your shoulder, fisting the toilet bowl."
This is why my Twitter and Facebook feeds - which consist mostly of people who brew, sell or drink beer - are scornful when I announce I'm working a one-off shift in the Rose and Crown, in Stoke Newington, north London.
"Will you help pay the business rates and other bills? The beer bit is the easy bit! You need to be there for a few days taking part in deliveries, paperwork and cleaning to get a better idea," say Matt Wickham and his wife Karen, who run the Evening Star in Brighton.
I've done this shift to explore why working behind a bar is the ninth most miserable job in the UK, beaten by happier call centre workers, window cleaners, fork-lift drivers, and almost 300 other jobs, according to a survey published last week.
But if you work or have worked behind a bar and are nodding along, spare a thought for your boss. Rooted to the foot of the survey's table of results, below debt collection and "elementary construction occupations", is publican or manager of a licensed premises.
The regulars at the Rose and Crown have a hard time believing this. "Standing there pulling pints and having a natter is easy! And they always look happy enough," says one.
Martin Harley, who grew up working in the Rose and Crown for his parents and now runs a small chain of pubs, smiles in recognition. "Everyone has this idealised vision of how brilliant it would be to run a pub. People often tell me they're thinking about (doing) it and I always try to dissuade them."
Dawn Hopkins, who runs the Rose in Norwich, explains why. "Whatever kind of pub you run, you work very long hours for little reward. And the expectations are huge. As well as knowing your way around a beer cellar, you have to be a host, cook, cleaner and manager. You have to be good at marketing, social media, personnel management and finance."
Harley says: "I occasionally still jump behind the bar and pull a few pints and the regulars go, 'Oh look, he's working!' That's not work, that's the glory bit! The rest of the time I'm dealing with VAT returns, personal licences, designated premises supervisor licences for the shift managers, Environmental Health, Customs and Excise, the police. Today I had to go to the council offices to sort out a separate licence for the tables and chairs outside. And all that time, you're the landlord, they expect to see you in the bar. Even on your days off, people expect to be able to have a pint with you."
Kirsty Valentine, formerly of the Alma in Newington Green, north London, used to relish the challenge. But it took its toll. "To me, a 60-hour week would be quiet, like a 35-hour week for anybody else. Normally I'd be on 70 or 80 hours, more when there was a bank holiday or event. The upside is that when you're working with a great team, and the customers are friendly and you're giving them what they want and making them happy, it's brilliant. But when everyone else is off work, that's when you're busiest. You work weekends, bank holidays, Christmas and Easter. I used to manage one week's holiday a year, but I'd have to work extra hard and plan very carefully in the six weeks running up to it to make it happen."
Everyone I speak to tells me that to do the job well, you have to be fit - both physically and mentally. Most publicans are not. A recent survey by pub trade magazine the Publican's Morning Advertiser (PMA) revealed that 63% of licensees are overweight and unhappy about it, and more than half admitted to drinking more than the recommended 21 units of alcohol a week. A third said they do no exercise - not surprising when 60% of them work more than Valentine's "quiet" 60 hours a week.
All this makes the job hard enough. But throw in the context in which publicans are working, and it starts to look decidedly grim. On average, 28 pubs are closing for good every week. Despite relentless headlines about Britain's binge drinking problem, in reality alcohol consumption is in long-term decline. The beer market has shrunk by 23% over the last decade - and beer makes up 61% of the average pub's revenue.
While income is falling, costs are going up. Last week's alcohol duty freeze in the budget brings to an end a period where duty increased by 42% in five years. A third of the price of every pint is handed over to the government. And yet, another PMA survey showed the effect of duty increases is dwarfed by the impact of cheap supermarket pricing and soaring utilities costs.
But among the publicans I spoke to, one factor dominated conversations: the structure of the industry.
Over 22,000 pubs are owned by the pub companies (pubcos), large property businesses that emerged to absorb the pubs that breweries were barred from owning when the anti-monopolistic 1989 Beer Orders came into effect. It's difficult to write anything about the state of the industry these days without critics of the two largest pubcos, Punch and Enterprise, insisting that they are the biggest problem.
The pubco issue is fiendishly complicated, but a few common themes emerge. Many licensees feel they are misled about the leases they sign, and the conditions thereof. "I signed a lease that said I was liable for the full cost of repairs," says former Enterprise licensee David Montgomery. "Then they hit me with a bill for statutory compliance - £45,000, including the replacement of all the fuse boards in the building, some of which went back to the 1960s. I spent £120,000 on repairs in five years." Montgomery is unsure of his future, and undergoing counselling.
Peter Swanson is one of many who felt that he wasn't given the full picture when he signed his lease. "It soon became obvious the pub just wasn't viable. We poured money in, tried different menus, different beer ranges, nothing worked. When we spoke to Enterprise, they simply said, 'You signed the lease,' and that was it. We had to carry on paying rent that was based on much higher turnover than we were getting. We poured all our savings into it. It was meant to be a partnership, but when we said we couldn't carry on, they asked if we had any assets we could sell. Or any friends or family we could borrow money from?"
Swinson was eventually able to renegotiate his lease. But he admits that at the height of the crisis, he considered suicide. He says the rent reduction he was given was "too little, too late", and now, at 56, he faces bankruptcy and is looking for employment in his former trade, engineering.
Simon Townsend has inherited the situation after taking over as CEO of Enterprise Inns when the company's founder, Ted Tuppen, retired last year. (CEOs came second from top in last week's survey, which Townsend attributes to them being "driven".)
Townsend knows he has a role to play in improving landlords' lot. "It is beholden on people like me to try to improve the conditions for licensees, to help improve the situation around taxation and regulation, and to offer support. That is my responsibility."
He finds it "disturbing" if publicans are giving the impression of unhappiness to customers, but doubts they are. "Publicans are very good at separating their public personas from their private concerns. They're good at presentation. The industry would be in far greater difficulty if they were visibly unhappy."
This is perhaps why the regulars at the Rose and Crown in London find it impossible to accept that the people serving them might be miserable.
Tony Leonard, co-owner of the award-winning Snowdrop Inn in Lewes, Sussex, is not so sure this separation is healthy. He and his partner, Dom McCarten, recently emerged from a bruising battle with Greene King about the terms of other pub leases.
"The constant fear of losing everything if we faltered put a huge strain on our mental health and our relationship," he says. "Keeping up a cheerful appearance in front of customers when you're under siege from your 'business partner' doesn't help, and emphasises the disconnect between your role and your state of mind, which probably isn't healthy. It would have been indescribably worse if we had children depending on us, and I can easily understand why many people going through similar situations have suffered from depression, breakdowns, illness, alcoholism, family break-up and self-harm as a result."
There are happy pubco tenants - and unhappy publicans in freehouses. Even the happier ones freely admit that the job is tough. So what can be done to improve the wellbeing of the British publican?
From the CEO of the UK's biggest pubco to the staff at the Rose and Crown, the answer is unanimous: they want to be busier, to see more people come through the door. Sadly, that's not an easy ask. As the economy recovers from recession, the pub industry - always the pit canary for forthcoming financial woe - is significantly off the pace. Market analysts CGA Peach predict we'll lose another 8,000 pubs by 2018. "It's not that people aren't going out," says CGA's Scott Elliott, "but when they do, they want to eat food. The traditional wet-led boozer is suffering, while food-led pubs and restaurants are growing.
"Expectations are very high," he adds. "Things like WiFi, charging points and good quality or branded coffee have very quickly gone from nice-to-have to must-have."
Rob Willock, PMA editor, compares publicans to clergy, the profession that in last week's survey took the top spot.
"It's funny that they're at opposite ends of the table when so much of what they do is similar," says Willock. "They attract the congregation, dispense bread and wine, listen to people confess their sins and offer emotional support."
The difference being, one will be contemplating the promise of eternal life this weekend, whole the other could well be wrapping their arm in a bin bag, preparing to fist a toilet.
Captions:
Beer trouble
Pete Brown talks to a customer in Stoke Newington Photograph: Graham Turner for t he Guardian
'The upside is when you work with a great team and customers are friendly'
]]></text></news-item>