<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVN-H8H1-DYNS-34VG"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Lodi pollution clean-up on track for completion</title><source>Lodi News-Sentinel, Calif.</source><author>Wes Bowers, Lodi News-Sentinel, Calif.</author><text><![CDATA[March 29--Lodi's interim City Manager Steve Schwabauer and Public Works Director Wally Sandelin said this week that the project to clean up underground pollution discovered in Downtown Lodi more than two decades ago is on track to being complete by 2038.
"With the exception of the central plume, we are done with any heavy action or remediation," Sandelin said. "We expect we won't do any physical treatment, but just some monitoring. (TCE/PCE levels) are pretty low in the other plumes, and if contamination reaches any of the water wells, we'd treat that."
The central plume, or leak into the groundwater, is located in an alley south of Pine Street between Church and Pleasant streets, and extends about a mile south. Public Works crews have removed 17,520 pounds of PCE from that plume, Sandelin said.
Perchloroethylene, or Tetrachloroethylene, more commonly know as PCE/TCE, is a colorless liquid or vapor commonly used for dry cleaning.
The contamination was first discovered in the late 1980s while crews were pumping water into a Locust Street tank. The Public Works Department then shut down the wells in Downtown.
The State Department of Toxic Substances Control began testing the soil and measuring toxins in an area ranging from Turner Road to Kettleman Lane, just west of Highway 99 and east of Ham Lane.
The chemicals were believed to have leaked into the city's groundwater from companies such as dry-cleaners and metal shops.
The City of Lodi filed a suit in 2000 against 15 Lodi businesses to force their insurance companies to clean up sites contaminated with TCE and PCE.
Two companies named in the suit included Guild Dry Cleaners, located at 17 S. Church St., and Busy Bee Laundry and Cleaning, located at 110 E. Elm St. in the city's Central Business District. The Lodi News-Sentinel was also named in the suit.
After nine years of legal battles and attorney's fees that reached nearly $30 million, the city was awarded $6.3 million in a settlement from the Regional Water Quality Control Board. The city then abandoned its lawsuit and began the pollution cleanup itself.
During that time, Busy Bee Laundry also chose to clean the pollution in a plume along East Elm Street -- dubbed by the city as the Busy Bee plume -- on its own.
The company hired an outside contractor to begin monitoring the groundwater in 2003. Two remediation systems, including 29 soil vapor extraction wells and 38 groundwater extraction wells, were installed and began operating on the property in 2008.
By 2012, the Regional Water Quality Control Board determined that Busy Bee Laundry could discontinue the extractions because they had cleaned the plume as much as they possibly could.
Busy Bee spent $600,000 to clean the pollution, and removed 110 pounds of PCE/TCE, Schwabauer said.
The city was responsible for the central, northern, southern and western plumes.
Crews have been monitoring and removing pollution from the central plume for three years with 50 groundwater monitoring systems at 50 wells, along with a groundwater extraction system and nine vapor extraction systems at 211 W. Oak St.
A vapor system pulls the chemicals through the ground and into treatment systems. The vapor is then run through three carbon filters to remove the PCE/TCE before it is discharged into the air.
A groundwater extraction system pulls groundwater from 100 feet below ground level and runs it through carbon filters. The city then discharges the filtered water into the sewer.
The western plume contains just PCE, and is located under the neighborhood at the southwestern corner of Lodi Avenue and Hutchins Street.
The southern plume, which contains both PCE and TCE, is located at Kettleman Lane and Sacramento Street, and extends to Sycamore Street, according to city documents.
Sandelin said nine additional watering wells will be constructed in three different locations at the southern and western plumes. But he said it is unlikely the city will need to treat any water, as pollution levels are very low in those plumes. He said staff will continue to monitor the wells, however.
The northern plume, located between Elm Street and Turner Road, contains just TCE, according to city documents.
Only one groundwater monitoring well will be constructed there, as Sandelin said contamination levels are also very low.
Schwabauer praised the city on spending less than $10 million on the cleanup so far. The project was originally estimated to cost $19.9 million over 30 years.
There is currently $15.9 million in the project's funds, and Schwabauer is confident that will be all the city needs to complete the cleanup. He and Sandelin stressed that the proposed water and wastewater rate increases to be discussed in June will not be used to pay for the pollution cleanup.
"I think the council and myself did a really great job at solving our litigation (in this case)," Schwabauer said. "But Wally (Sandelin) took that step and hammered it out of the park that this needs to be cleaned. And he turned this into something we are now fixing."
Duncan Austin, the clean-up program manager with the Central Valley Regional Water Quality Control Board, said the city has been responsible in reporting its progress, even though it is not on a strict reporting timeline.
"We've been satisfied with how they've been working pretty diligently to clean up the contamination and report their findings to us," he said.
Mostly found in dry cleaning businesses, PCE/TCE enters the body when contaminated air is inhaled or when contaminated food or water is ingested, according to the Environmental Protection Agency.
Chronic PCE exposure can cause damage to the liver, kidneys and central nervous system. It may also lead to an increased risk of developing cancer.
Inhaling PCE/TCE for short periods of time can cause dizziness, fatigue, headaches, sweating and unconsciousness. Contact irritates the skin, eyes, nose and throat.
Inhalation over longer periods of time can cause liver and kidney damage in humans.
Workers repeatedly exposed to large amounts of the chemicals in the air can also experience memory loss and confusion, according to the EPA.
Contact reporter Wes Bowers at wesb@lodinews.com
___ (c)2014 the Lodi News-Sentinel (Lodi, Calif.) Visit the Lodi News-Sentinel (Lodi, Calif.) at www.lodinews.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>