<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVN-84D1-F0BC-M43S"><date>2014-03-28</date><title>Contraceptive fight more about ACA than religious rights</title><source>Evansville Courier &amp; Press (Indiana)</source><author>Evansville Courier &amp; Press</author><text><![CDATA[The following editorial originally appeared in the Philadelphia Inquirer
For the last half-century, millions of American women have been digging into their purses to pay for birth-control pills and other contraceptive methods that weren't covered by their health insurance plans.
Unfortunately, that won't change if the Supreme Court, following arguments in the latest high-profile challenge to the Affordable Care Act, decides to void provisions that increase birth control coverage. The court is considering two cases, one brought by a cabinetry business, Conestoga Wood Specialties, whose Mennonite owners say it would violate their religious beliefs to help pay for employees' birth control. The Affordable Care Act does exempt churches and other religious employers from providing birth control coverage, but not for-profit companies like Conestoga or the other challenger, Oklahoma Citybased retail giant Hobby Lobby, whose owners are evangelical Christians. It's more than interesting that Hobby Lobby previously provided coverage for two birth control methods that it now seeks to drop. That religious conversion smacks of the Republican-driven effort to dismantle Obamacare at any price. As the high court sorts through the case, it must beware of setting a dangerous precedent. If these companies were granted the right to bar insurance coverage of the pill, any business might well be able to raise objections to other types of medical care that its owners contend violate their faith tenets. That could derail the entire landmark health care reform and set back the nation's necessary efforts to cover millions of people with inadequate or no health insurance. These court challenges appear to be the latest salvo from conservative forces trying to scuttle Obamacare, even as it's become clear that the law is putting affordable, quality health insurance coverage within reach of millions. Sign-ups have passed the 5 million mark. It appears the White House's target of 7 million enrollees by April may not be reached, but that's partly due to unresolved glitches. For example, a Philadelphia Inquirer analysis revealed last week that the Healthcare.gov website may be incorrectly calculating poverty levels and wrongly telling thousands of families who should qualify for insurance subsidies that they are ineligible. But even that apparent misstep doesn't diminish the positive impact Obamacare is having. Millions of young adults have retained insurance coverage under their parents' plans, seniors are getting more help paying for drugs, and insurance companies can no longer deny coverage due to pre-existing conditions. Were states like Pennsylvania to sensibly expand Medicaid, as Obamacare allows, the ranks of the insured would swell by millions more. As for the insurance market - long reduced to a virtual monopoly in many regions - a number of states say they are seeing more robust competition. The right path for the nation's well-being is clear. By keeping Obamacare intact, the Supreme Court can discourage other rear-guard efforts to cripple the health care reform that is helping so many.
]]></text></news-item>