<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVP-7GX1-DXJR-H292"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Competition panel probe into Google may end in three months</title><source>The Economic Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[BANGALORE: The Competition Commission of India (CCI), which slapped a Rs 1 crore fine on Google for non-cooperation in an ongoing investigation of the search company’s practices, could conclude the probe in the next three months, said people with direct knowledge of the matter.
If the allegations that Google favoured its own business in its eponymous searches, which triggered the investigation, are found to be true, India’s competition watchdog could demand a formal settlement with the company. That could potentially involve a heftier penalty and changes to some of Google’s search practices, the people said.
“The investigation is in the final stages. The CCI could come out with a final report anytime now, after which Google can contest the decision by defending its practices,” a person briefed on the matter told ET on condition of anonymity. The probe isn’t expected to go beyond six months the person added.
Google didn’t provide information and documents, the CCI said on March 27, ordering the penalty and clarified the fine was meant for the non-cooperation and not related to the findings of the probe. The two-year investigation is looking into online search and advertising practices alleged to favour Google’s own products and services.
The California-based company, by far the most dominant search provider on the Internet, has faced similar investigations in the United States and Europe.
Another person with direct knowledge of the Indian investigation said the director general’s office at the CCI is currently examining Google’s online search practices, specifically whether it has adopted anti-competitive and discriminatory practices to favour the company’s own products and services over those of rivals.
The CCI probe began in August 2012 after advocacy group Consumers Unity and Trust Society (CUTS) claimed that Google was abusing its monopoly position in India. India has nearly 200 million Internet users today according to the Internet And Mobile Association of India.
Separately, match-making portal Bharatmatrimony.com had filed a complaint against Google earlier that year alleging Google engaged in unlawful practices relating to its AdWords platform. Google was selling keywords relating to its websites to rival sites such as Shaadi.com, and Jeevansathi.com, the matrimonial site alleged in its complaint.
AdWords is Google’s online advertising channel that sells keywords to advertisers and creates online ads on its search screen. Google, which has a nearly 90 per cent market share in India’s search engine market, gets over 90 per cent of its revenues from advertisements.
Officials at the CCI declined to comment, but Uday Mehta, an associate director at CUTS said the commission, a quasi-judicial body, is expected to summon both the Google spokesperson and the complainants before publishing the final report. “We hope the CCI director general completes the probe as quickly as possible.”
An email to Murugavel Janakiraman , founder and chief executive of Bharatmatrimony.com did not elicit a response at the time of print. A Google spokesman acknowledged that the Rs 1 crore penalty is due to delay in submission of some documents and the company is reviewing the development in detail. Google has said that its products and services are compliant with competition law in India and that it was cooperating with the CCI in the ongoing investigation.
Some legal experts said there could further delays in the investigation if Google fails to provide adequate information and documents to the CCI.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>