<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVP-7GX1-DXJR-H2J0"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Sons wait to enter Coal India rolls as VRS for women becomes a reality</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Debjoy Sengupta</author><text><![CDATA[Champa Yadav (name changed) was given a job at Coal India on compassionate grounds after her husband died in a mining accident some 12-years ago. As she was uneducated, she was absorbed as a general labourer in a CIL colliery far away from her home. A rule in Coal India requires a family member to be offered employment in case an employee dies in an accident or is rendered unfit for work. Now 51, Champa finds the job taxing on her health. For ten years now, her only son Sonu, has been accompanying her to work and helping her in her daily tasks.
Champa does not have the luxury to stop working because her job pays her between 20,000 – 29,000 per month. But Sonu and Champa have entered into an unwritten agreement with the manager that Sonu will do the actual physical work, while Champa will just be present. However what Champa really wants is to opt out and let Sonu be absorbed by CIL in her place. This has been done before. Prior to 2002, every five years, CIL used to absorb the sons of women employees after they turned adult. But, the management stopped the practice as Coal India was overstaffed and there has been no such recruitment in the last 12 years. This is not just the story of Champa and her son Sonu. There are some 26,000-odd women who make up 7% of Coal India's 3.57 lakh strong workforce. A large chunk of these women have been appointed on compassionate grounds and are asking their sons be absorbed by CIL in their place. "With age, we are losing our ability to continue with the physical work. In a large number of cases, the mothers are accompanied by their sons to the workplace," said Namita Bhowmick, a general labourer at Amrapatra Colliery 4 in Jharkhand. While this helps the women retain their jobs, it stops sons from exploring employment opportunities.
"Sons are not able to do an independent job and add to the family income," said Nirmala Rai, another employee. A recently announced voluntary retirement scheme by the CIL management was, in fact, the result of an effort which took at least 8-9 years to materialize. The VRS (Female) Sangathan, a loose group of women and sons like Namita and Subhendu, approached almost all the officials of Coal India including the unions to take up their case. The Indian National Mine Workers’ Federation then took up the issue and convinced the management to declare a VRS scheme. "We have been in talks with the management for years and it is only last week that the scheme was announced after it was passed by the board a couple of weeks ago,” said SQ Zama, secretary general of the federation. In fact, during the time the government was planning to divest an additional stake in the company, the workmen threatened to go on strike and the female VRS scheme was included in the list of demands to which the management agreed.
Limited benefit
But the VRS Sangathan is not happy with the scheme in its present form. "After years of effort, the scheme announced by CIL will render a majority of the women employees ineligible under any of the three conditions set by the management. CIL has introduced a condition that a woman opting for VRS will require to have put in 10 years of service at CIL, yet be less than 50 years of age. Their sons will also have to be a matriculate or an ITI certificate holder. Not every son would be eligible," says Shubhendu Bhowmick, general secretary of the Sangathan. "We have been asking for an option for the mothers to opt out of the job and the sons be employed instead. But this VRS scheme does not at address all our issues. Of the 26,000 women, only 400 are likely to be eligible under the scheme in its present format," says Shubhendu. Members of the VRS Sangathan now plan to take up the issue with the management along with the Indian National Mine Workers’ Federation so that the scheme is tweaked to include a larger number of women employees. "The objective behind offering the wife a job is to help the family tide over the financial crisis following the bread earner’s death. Prior to 2002, every five years, sons of the female employees used to be absorbed after they attained 18 years of age. But this VRS is virtually of no use," he said. While CIL has employed women on compassionate grounds there are a host of problems associated with this. The Mines Act of 1952 stipulates that women employees cannot be deployed in underground mines and need to be relieved from open-cast mining jobs before dark.. Since most CIL mines are underground, the appointees are employed as general labourers, peons, sweepers and para medical staff but there are more employees than posts. “They cannot be employed gainfully," a senior CIL official admitted. Then here are other problems.
"Women employees have a tendency to resist transfers and cannot be posted in areas where exploration is underway since most such locations are deep inside forests with hostile terrain," he explained. Women employees say if the sons are employed, it would be a win-win for both CIL and the employees. "CIL would get young blood who can be sent to mines, while the mother gets relieved from hard toil which a large number of them are not capable of," said Kranti Devi, yet another beneficiary of the job after her husband died in a mine accident.
Hazardous occupation
At Coal India, the world’s largest producer with production slated to cross 500 million tonnes in 2014-15, 80% workmen still toil in underground mines to produce only about 10% of coal. The company operates some 470-odd mines in 21 major coalfields across eight states, including 163 open cast mines, 273 underground mines and 34 mixed mines (which include both open cast and underground mines). Mishaps are common. On 6th September 2006, the roof of the Bhatdee coal mine at Jharkhand collapsed after an explosion – the result of a spark that ignited a patch of dense methane. Fifty people were killed. On 6th May 2010, a gas explosion at the Anjan Hill underground coal mine in Chattishgarh, killed 14. Bhatdee, under Bharat Coking Coal, is considered a Degree 3 mine on the basis of its high methane content per tonne of coal. It's a dark and damp underground cavern where one would gasp for air.
Yet, miners have been braving this scary environment and entering the tunnels of this obsolete mine for the last 60 years. Rescue experts say its just a matter of luck that it has been operational for so long, without an accident. At Anjan Hill, under South Eastern Coalfields, mine workers arriving for the early shift were asked to wait while a team of mine rescuers were assessing the safety of the mine deep inside its belly. A gas leak was detected two days earlier and mining operations were suspended. Suddenly, the ground shook, and scorching hot gas erupted from within the depths, blowing open three gaping holes in the mountain side and charring everything.
Beams and pillars caved in. On the surface, the fired-up gas exploded through the shaft, instantly injuring 31 miners. According to figures compiled by DGMS, between 2001 and 2011, as many as 1,137 mine workers lost their lives in some 919 coal mine accidents due to inundation, explosion, fires, spontaneous heating, or strata failure in the mines. According to data compiled by CIL, average fatalities at CIL mines between 2000-04 was 82 every year for the five years. Between 2005 and 2009 the average was 80 which declined to 66 between 2010-12. Although the rate is declining accidents are a way of life at mines. As late as last year in 2013, 54 employees died in some 50 accidents. CIL’s rule of employing a family member will lead to more women being employed and the issue will continue to haunt Coal India unless, accidents stop.
Fact box
Coal India operates 470 mines in 21 major coalfields across 8 states. This includes 163 open cast mines, 273 underground mines and 34 mixed mines. 26,000 women make up 7% of its 3.57 lakh strong workforce. 1,137 miners died in 919 coal mine accidents between 2001 and 2011.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>