<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVP-7GX1-DXJR-H2DW"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Mumbai: Worker killed, 7 others fall ill following gas leakage in factory</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Pradeep Gupta</author><text><![CDATA[AMBERNATH: A worker was killed and seven others were taken ill following leakage of Ammonia gas in Ambernath Ice Factory situated in Ambernath on Saturday early morning.
Those who fell ill are rushed to the Sion hospital in Mumbai where they are now out of danger.
Following to the incident, the Ambernath police have registered negligence led to death case against factory owner Ashok Bhojwani.
The Ambernath fire officials said that incident took place on Saturday morning at around 1 am in Morivali MIDC area, when wall of the Ammonia gas plant started leakage due to which labour Shambhu Nepali,35, working close to wall fell unconscious on the spot. Shambhu was rushed to the Central hospital in Ulhasnagar where doctor declared him dead.
The leakage imapct was so wide that three others workers working in plant and four of their family members living in same factory premises fell ill.
All seven were rushed to the Central hospital in Ulhasnagar, where from doctor reffered them to Sion hospital in Mumbai.
"After getting call from company our fire officials team rushed on the spot and switch off supply of gas into wall due to which leakage was stopped otherwise neighboring plant staffs may also affected" said R V Patil, Chief Fire officials Ambernath Fire office.
Following the incident, the Ambernath police have registered case under section 304A ( Causing death by negligence ) of Indian Penal code against owner Ashok Bhojwani of the company.
An official from Ambernath police station said that prima facies suggest that company owner negligence who do not conducted proper maintenance work due to which incident happened but further probe is on.
However talking to TOI, factory owner Bhojwani claimed that he is innocent and whatever happened it is just an accident.
This is second mishap in last one week in factories situated in Morivali MIDC Ambernath. On Tuesday a major fire was broke out in Hanaka Organics Pvt Ltd company killing one of its directors and leaving four others injured.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>