<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVP-7GX1-DXJR-H2Y8"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Bribery cases on the rise, revenue department tops the list</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Santosh Sonawane</author><text><![CDATA[NASHIK: The Nashik anti-corruption bureau (ACB) has registered 56% more bribery cases this year compared with the corresponding period in 2013, with the maximum number of traps laid against the officials from the revenue department.
Till March 26 this year, the ACB had laid 36 successful traps as against the 23 traps laid last year. ACB officials attributed the rise to increasing awareness among citizens. More people are coming forward to lodge complaints against government officials and employees and people's representatives. ACB officials said.
Among the five districts in the division, Nashik tops the list with 10 traps this year, followed by nine traps each in Jalgaon and Ahmednagar, five in Nandurbar and three in Dhule. Nashik topped the list last year too with 11 cases, followed by six in Ahmednagar, three each in Dhule and Jalgaon. No traps were laid in Nandurbar.
Superintendent of the ACB, Nashik, Shashikant Mahavarkar said, "People should come forward without any fear if there is a demand of bribe from them. We are putting our best efforts to bring awareness among the general public."
As per the instructions of Director General of the ACB, Praveen Dixit, officials have started visiting various government departments to check if any bribe demands have been made from the people.
"Our officials are speaking to the people to see if they are facing problems in government offices and if there is a demand of bribe. All such things have resulted into the rise in the number of successful traps this year," Mahavarkar said.
A total of 44 people were booked through the 36 traps this year, in which seven are Class I officers, five Class II officials, 25 Class III officials and two Class IV staff. Five others, who accepted the bribe on behalf of government officials or employees, were also booked.
The revenue department continues to top the list of bribery cases with 11 traps against its officials. Four traps were laid against police department personel, five of the Maharashtra State Electricity Distribution Company Ltd (MSEDCL), two of Nashik Municipal Corporation, one of Zilla Parishad, three of Panchayat Samiti, one of municipal council, one traps related to the cooperatives, two of land survey department, one of the registrar office, one of Mahatma Phule Backward Class Welfare Board, one of Tribal Welfare Department, one of the education department and two of the judiciary department.
Among the major cases in Nashik this year, a block development officer and a branch engineer were arrested while accepting a bribe of Rs 1.7 lakh at the panchayat samiti office in Sinnar in January. A contractor, who had done works under the Employment Guarantee Scheme, was requesting approval of his bill of Rs 34 lakh. However, the block development officer demanded Rs 70,000, while branch engineer had demanded Rs 1 lakh for clearing the bill. The aggrieved contractor approached the ACB, which laid a trap at the panchayat samiti office. The two were arrested while accepting the bribe of Rs 1.7 lakh.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>