<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVS-N2R1-JCB3-43JW"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>INSPECTIONS: 5 businesses out of compliance in food inspections</title><source>The York Dispatch (Pennsylvania)</source><author>By STAFF REPORT 505-5425/@yorkdispatch</author><text><![CDATA[The state Department of Agriculture conducts annual inspections of food-serving businesses to ensure public safety and safe food-handling practices. Schools are inspected twice per year, according to the Bureau of Food Safety and Laboratories.
Whether an establishment is considered compliant or non-compliant is the discretion of the inspector. There are, however, several violations for which inspectors should automatically consider establishments non-compliant. Called "critical violations," they include food temperature issues, issues with chemicals and how they're handled, and employee hygiene.
Depending on the severity of the situation, inspectors and their supervisors could file citations or close an establishment.
Below is a list of establishments listed as out-of-compliance for inspections conducted March 20 - March 25.
OUT OF COMPLIANCE
Burger King, 490 Loucks Road, York
Action: Violations included an excess of chlorine sanitizer at the three-bay sink; managers not wearing hair restraints while handling food; liquid eggs stored above ready-to-eat foods in the walk-in refrigerator; inside of warmer was not clean; a pink substance inside the ice chute; soda nozzles not clean to sight and touch; underside of a cutting board was not clean to sight and touch; underside of the milkshake machine contained food residue; dumpster lids were not closed; floors were not being cleaned properly.
Comment: A manager said she had "no comment on anything" and hung up on a reporter.
Chili's, 370 Eisenhower Drive, Hanover
Action: Violations included thermometer not available or readily accessible in numerous refrigeration units; deeply scored cutting boards not resurfaced or discarded as required; accumulation of food and debris inside the dishwasher; food and dirt residue on nacho unit; food debris on slicer units; pink, slimy substance inside the ice machine; old encrusted food debris on pots, pans, plates, scoops, ladles and lemon-lime slicer; clean dish racks stored on the floor in the dishwashing area; clean food equipment and/or utensils stored wet in a manner that did not allow for draining or air drying; condensation around freezer entrance door and floor area of walk-in freezer; old unused equipment stored in the bar area that should have been removed from the restaurant; large amounts of static dust on ceiling vents in rear and dining areas of the restaurant.
Comment: A manager said all violations been corrected and the restaurant is waiting on its follow-up inspection.
Hanover V.F.W. Post 2506, 19 S. McKinley Ave., Hanover
Action: Violations included visible evidence of insect contamination inside one liquor bottle of Inver House Scotch; loose caulking and ice accumulation at the walk-in freezer; large crack on wooden pizza paddle; thermometers for ensuring proper temperatures of beer was not available at the reach-in cooler; pink slime residue on the ice-deflector plate; excess dust and grime on the soda cluster valves; clean tubs stored on the floor; slime residue found at the end of the soda gun reservoir drain; women's restroom was not provided with covered trash can for sanitary napkins; drain to the soda gun was disconnected at the public-access bar; loose caulking inside grill hood; broken equipment in the kitchen area that needs to be removed.
Comment: An employee who answered the phone said, "No comment, thank you," and hung up on a reporter seeking information about the violations.
Sbarros Italian Eatery, 2899 Whitford Road, York
Action: Violations included various refrigerated and frozen products stored at room temperature and unattended where there could be possible contamination; restaurant not properly storing food deliveries.
Comment: A manager said the restaurant has corrected its storage violation.
Suburban Bowlerama, 1945 S. Queen St., York
Action: Violations included possible cross contamination, as raw eggs were stored above ready-to-eat or cooked foods inside the reach-in refrigerator; food employee donning single-use gloves without a prior hand wash; heavy accumulation of mold-like growth covering a large portion of deflector plate inside bulk ice machine; an old accumulation of food debris under a shelving unit holding kegs of beer inside the walk-in refrigerator.
Comment: Manager Jimmy Plessinger said all violations have been corrected, and a state inspector said some violations were corrected at the time of inspection.
IN COMPLIANCE
Bamboo Garden, 205 S. Sherman St., York City.
Baum's Mini Mart, 302 S. George St., York City.
Bob's West End News, 639 W. Market St., York City.
Challenge Academy, 200 E. Princess St., York City.
Cheri Anne, 48 W. Philadelphia St., York City.
Christian School of York, 907 Greenbriar Road, York.
CPC - Jefferson School, 226 E. College Ave., York City.
Crazy Tomato, 1738 Filbert St., York.
Crimson American Grill, 1839 S. Queen St., York.
Early Learning Center, 101 Webster Ave., York.
El Sol Mexican Store, 1628 W. Market St., York.
Kreutz Creek Elementary School, 50 N. Lee St., Hellam.
Luther Memorial Church, 1907 Hollywood Drive, York.
North Salem Elementary School, 5161 N. Salem Church Road, Dover.
Staples, 965 Loucks Road, York City.
Sunoco A-Plus, 260 N. Sherman St., York City.
]]></text></news-item>