<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVS-N2R1-JCB3-43PY"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Residents air concerns at environmental review meeting for Marinwood Plaza project</title><source>Marin Independent Journal (California)</source><author>By Megan Hansen Marin Independent Journal</author><text><![CDATA[Marin residents have a catalog of concerns about the effects of a proposed mixed-use development at Marinwood Plaza, but all agree the project's environmental impact report needs to be thorough.
Dan Carraher said he and other Marinwood residents feel as if they haven't been heard during the planning process and want their worries addressed in the report.
"I believe a lot of the contention created at these meetings is the recreation of trust is needed," Carraher said. "We can rebuild trust if the document truly addresses these concerns."
Carraher was one of about 160 people who attended a scoping session Saturday at Lucas Valley Community Church in San Rafael to voice concerns about the Marinwood Village's impact on its surroundings. The hottest topics were effects on traffic, impacts to the Dixie School District, the project's proximity to Highway 101, access to public transportation, impacts to the Las Gallinas Creek watershed and toxins at the plaza's former dry-cleaning and gas station sites.
For resident Courtney Fischer, having a clear report and accurate descriptions of the materials that would used to build the development are the most important elements.
"It should be a readable and easily understood document," Fischer said. "The aesthetic visual portion of the EIR is often short and vague. I request the aesthetics be considered."
Bridge Housing Corp. of San Francisco has proposed erecting commercial and residential buildings at the five-acre Marinwood Plaza site currently owned by Marinwood Plaza LLC. The Marinwood Village plan, which was filed in June, includes building 72 low-income and 10 market-rate apartment units on the northern and southern portions of the site. The southern lot would have the most apartments, with a density of 29 units per acre.
San Francisco-based Environmental Science Associations, an environmental science and planning firm, has been hired by the county to develop an environmental impact report for the project. Bridge Housing will pay the planning firm's $368,914 bill for the report, which is anticipated to be finalized early next year.
Residents said they're worried the tax-exempt developer won't pay property taxes, hurting the Dixie School District's bottom line. The district is largely funded through property taxes as opposed to revenue limit districts that rely on a larger amount of state funding. But that could change under Proposition 30, making it so the district receives funding based on average daily attendance.
Resident JoAnn Hastings said opponents of the project have used the school issue to spread fear throughout the community. She said it needs to be made clear exactly how the district will be affected if children living at Marinwood Village start attending the district's four schools.
"This has become a rather emotional issue," Hastings said. "I'd like the report to clearly state the future of how the schools are funded."
Locals are also uneasy about the fact that trichloroethylene, a chemical used at the former dry cleaner site, has contaminated groundwater within 550 feet of a drinking water well at nearby Silveira Ranches, according to the San Francisco Bay Regional Water Quality Control Board. The board has ordered the property owner to create a cleanup action plan by Jan. 1, 2016.
Resident Mike Ralston said he supports the project, but wants more information about the toxins.
"Please provide an objective analysis of contamination leftover from the dry cleaners," Ralston said.
Residents Justin Kai, a Marinwood Community Services District director, and Bill McNicholas also raised concerns about the presence of benzene in the air at the site.
An April 2012 report from San Francisco-based environmental consulting firm Geologica to the water board shows there are high concentrations of the petroleum-based chemical in the air. The report states the chemical is likely present because of the site's proximity to the highway.
Resident Mark Albers said he's concerned about pollutants and doesn't support the project as it's drafted.
"My primary concern is creating a healthy environment there for people to live," Albers said.
San Rafael City Councilman Damon Connolly, who is vying for Supervisor Susan Adams' seat, said he'd like to see the impact report include a risk hazard assessment for the air next to Highway 101.
He said he's against the project and wants a range of alternatives.
"I oppose the project as currently proposed. I do not believe the current plan reflects the community vision process that took place during the mid-2000s," Connolly said. "Improvements to the center should be focused on retail in a way that serves the community's needs and serves as a convenient gathering place."
Supervisor Susan Adams, who attended the meeting, said she's been working with constituents on rehabilitating Marinwood Plaza for years and was pleased to hear many of the 48 speakers say they support the project.
She said while the proposal from Bridge Housing isn't 100 percent in line with the county's 2006 conceptual master plan for the plaza, it's overwhelmingly close.
"I don't know why Damon made the comment that there's been no community engagement," Adams said. "I think as we address concerns, more and more people will find things to like about the project."
People have until 4 p.m. April 7 to submit written comments concerning the project's environmental impacts to http://blogs.marinij.com/bureaucratsandbaking.
]]></text></news-item>