<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVT-1CB1-DXKH-N2DJ"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Digital Look Ltd: Three former ICAP brokers to be charged in Libor rigging probe</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[British fraud investigators said on Friday they would charge three former ICAP brokers as part of a Libor inter-bank rate rigging probe.
The Serious Fraud Office (SFO) said it had begun criminal proceedings against three former employees at ICAP, Danny Martin Wilkinson, Darrell Paul Read and Colin John Goodman, in connection with the manipulation of Libor.
It is alleged they conspired to defraud between August 8th 2006 and September 7th 2010, the SFO said in a statement.
"This brings to nine the number of people facing charges in respect of Libor. The investigation continues," the SFO added.
click http://www.digitallook.com/dl/news/story/21573631/Three_former_ICAP_brokers_to_be_charged_in_Libor_rigging_probe.html?&username=&ac=
COMPANY BACKGROUND
ACTIVITIES
Digital Look is a financial media and technology company providing online advertising opportunities and a complete suite of financial information solutions to leading organisations throughout the UK.
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
28 March 2014: Digital Look Ltd: Canary Wharf's Songbird says occupancy at highest since credit crunch
Companies taking up more property space at London's Canary Wharf financial centre helped its developer to unveil better than expected annual results. Songbird Estates, whose main operating arm is Canary Wharf Group, said occupancy in its property portfolio increased to about 97%, which it said was the highest since the financial crisis. Songbird's adjusted net asset value per share rose by 38.1% to Pound2.90 at December 31st, although underlying pre-tax profit fell to Pound22.4m from Pound23.3m a year ago.
click http://www.digitallook.com/dl/news/story/21573664/Canary_Wharf_s_Songbird_says_occupancy_at_highest_since_credit_crunch.html?&username=&ac=
28 March 2014: Digital Look Ltd: Ferrum Crescent receives funding for South African iron project
AIM-listed metal explorer Ferrum Crescent on Friday received the first tranche of funding from an investor for an iron ore project in South Africa. The payment, which totalled $500,000, follows Anvwar Asian Investment's agreement to vest at 35% interest in the subsidiary company holding the Moonlight assets for a total of Pound10m. The next payment is due by the end of April. Ferrum said it would use the funds to progress a feasibility study at the Moonlight magnetite iron ore project. Ferrum Crescent Managing Director, Tom Revy, said: "As funds are being secured for the company through the AAI agreement, we are simultaneously planning the next stage of the Moonlight bankable feasibility study.
click http://www.digitallook.com/dl/news/story/21573620/Ferrum_Crescent_receives_funding_for_South_African_iron_project.html?&username=&ac=
28 March 2014: Digital Look Ltd: Repsol tries to fend off hostile take-over from PEMEX
Repsol has increased the number of votes needed to break-up its up-stream and downstrean assets, in a bid to fend off such an attempt by Mexico's state-owned PEMEX, which owns a minority stake in the Spanish oil major. At the company's annual shareholder's meeting held in Madrid, on Friday, the company's boss, Antoni Brufau, made an agggresive case in favour of keeping the firm whole.
click http://www.digitallook.com/dl/news/story/21574008/Repsol_tries_to_fend_off_hostile_take-over_from_PEMEX.html?&username=&ac=
24 March 2014: Digital Look Ltd: WPP to acquire marketing services agency XMKT
In what is so far proving to be an acquisition-heavy week for the group, WPP announced it has agreed to acquire XMKT Group, a marketing services agency specialising in customer experience management. The firm, whose clients include Diageo and Uniqlo, is headquartered in Shanghai and employs approximately 253 people. "This acquisition marks a further step towards WPP's declared goal of developing its networks in fast-growth markets and sectors," the FTSE 100 company said. Founded in 2010, XMKT has four main divisions, Events, Retail, Entertainment and Digital. Source: Company Website
click http://www.digitallook.com/dl/news/story/21562099/WPP_to_acquire_marketing_services_agency_XMKT.html?&username=&ac=
24 March 2014: Digital Look Ltd: C A Sperati begins trading on AIM
C A Sperati, supplier of buttons, buckles, trimmings and accessories to the clothing and allied trade, began trading on the London Stock Exchange's AIM market on Wednesday. Shares declined 12.50% to 5.25p each at 16:10 from the opening price of 5.50p. Executive Chairman, Jason Drummond, said: "The board, advisors and I have worked hard to bring C A Sperati to AIM where it belongs, and will be able to thrive. "The business has been trading for over 150 years and now we look forward to working with Jonathan Rowland and all the shareholders to create significant value and build our business through acquisitions and organic growth." Source: Company Website
click http://www.digitallook.com/dl/news/story/21561315/C_A_Sperati_begins_trading_on_AIM.html?&username=&ac=
]]></text></news-item>