<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVT-84Y1-DY9P-N1XS"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>India's biggest battle to play out in court; Nation awaiting naming of six players who stand accused of match-fixing, writes Jonathan Liew</title><source>The Sunday Telegraph (London)</source><author>Jonathan Liew</author><text><![CDATA[For a country that has registered three comfortable wins and looks well placed to claim a fourth global trophy in three years, there is a dazed, bloodshot look to Indian cricket at the moment. Victory against Bangladesh on Friday night sealed passage to the World Twenty20 semi-finals with a game to spare. And yet, the joyless, functional character of their progress perhaps reflects a deeper truth: that the real game is being played elsewhere.
A sense of paranoia pervades throughout. Mahendra Singh Dhoni, the India captain, has been conspicuously absent from the team's post-match press conferences. When he finally appeared on Friday, the team's media officer warned that questions not relating to the match or the tournament will not be answered.
The Indian Premier League spot-fixing affair, which is threatening to engulf the world's most powerful cricketing nation, has become the elephant in the room.
At the centre of this web of intrigue lies the mysterious envelope. This envelope, believed to be in the possession of India's Supreme Court, contains the names of six players, all current or recent India internationals, who are mentioned in conversations between bookmakers caught on police tapes. As yet, no names have been named, and no wrongdoing has been proven. But if nobody is under suspicion that means nobody is above it, either.
It is a predicament that goes to the very top of Indian cricket, and thus to the top of world cricket as well. This week, the Supreme Court of India ordered Narayanaswami Srinivasan to step down while it investigates allegations of corruption at the Chennai Super Kings.
Srinivasan has been replaced on a temporary basis by Sunil Gavaskar, but will still represent the Board of Control for Cricket in India at an executive meeting of the International Cricket Council, paving the way for him to take over as chairman as scheduled in July. In a few months, a man who has been forced to step away from his own board following a corruption scandal may be in charge of world cricket.
Srinivasan's company India Cement owns the Chennai franchise. His son-in-law Gurunath Meiyappan, a former team principal at Chennai, was arrested last year for alleged links to illegal bookmakers. The captain of Chennai is Dhoni, who also happens to be a vice-president of India Cements.
The key player in all this is Srinivasan, a ruthless and unsentimental operator who has been accused by his own son of having him beaten up because he is gay. Srinivasan made his fortune in the aftermath of the state's deregulation of cement prices, building his empire in the late 1980s and early 1990s with a series of hostile takeovers.
Like most Indian cricket administrators, he is a man with many fingers in many pies: president of the Tamil Nadu Cricket Association, the Tamil Nadu Golf Federation, the All India Chess Federation. A few months after he bought Chennai franchise, Srinivasan used his influence at the BCCI to remove a clause preventing administrators from owning teams. The result was a monumental conflict of interest, a scandal waiting to happen. At times, Indian cricket can be its own worst enemy.
If Srinivasan has most to explain, then it is Dhoni, the captain of India and hero of a nation, who has most to lose. Questions still linger over what he knew about Meiyappan's role at Chennai. He told a court-appointed inquiry that Meiyappan was merely a fan and close friend of the team, despite the fact that he sat in the dugout during matches. With the interrogation showing no sign of abating, reports suggest he has offered to stand down from the Chennai captaincy and his role at India Cements in order to preserve his reputation.
The seventh season of the IPL will begin in a fortnight. Calls from former administrators to scrap it were always optimistic: KPMG estimate that it would cost around £2billion in lost revenue. For the BCCI, a tainted tournament is clearly better than no tournament at all. But it will begin under a cloud of suspicion and a climate of fear.
For while Indians expect their politicians to be bent, players are held to a higher standard, which is why the world awaits the opening of the envelope. The revelation that senior players in the sport's biggest domestic competition were on the fix would be a blow that would tarnish cricket for generations. For now, the show goes on. But the game will be following developments with bated breath.
]]></text></news-item>