<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-D8N1-JCTS-G0NJ"><date>2014-03-30</date><title></title><source>Mobile Register (Alabama)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Commissioners need to fight for Mobile’s drinking water.
Mobile Baykeeper filed a lawsuit challenging a permit issued by the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers for the Plains Southcap LLC pipeline on Jan. 24. This project was permitted by the Corps without the proper review or consideration of the pipeline’s close proximity to Mobile’s drinking water intake. In August, the Mobile County Commission wrote an extensive letter to the Corps outlining multiple problems with the Corps’ permitting of this pipeline in the watershed. Commissioner Jerry Carl expressed his outrage to the media over this federal permit. Commissioner Connie Hudson told the media “there were too many gaps in this process.”
The county was so alarmed that they demanded the Corps revoke this permit. Mobile Baykeeper applauded their efforts at the time, but hasn’t seen the county take action to protect Mobile’s drinking water since. In fact, the county penned another letter last month to the Corps completely reversing its stance on the issue. We want to know what information was provided to the county since this summer that caused our commissioners to backtrack.
In August, Hudson said on the record, “There’s too much at stake here, in terms of protecting our drinking water.” On behalf of the 250,000 citizens who drink water in Mobile, we need to understand why Hudson and the other commissioners are no longer protecting the drinking water.
Pumping millions of gallons of crude oil every day so close to Mobile County’s drinking water puts your constituents’ at severe risk. Recent events in West Virginia and North Carolina only accentuate this point, and it has been proven that putting private profit over protection of our drinking water resources does not pay. It costs us down the road. Just a few months ago, the county would have said the same.
The commissioners need to explain why they retracted their original letter to the Corps and gave up on fighting for our drinking water.
Casi Callaway
Mobile
MAWSS let everyone down.
Thirty pieces of silver was the going rate in biblical times, now it appears it only costs $2.7 million to sell out people’s lives and livelihood.
Mobile Water and Sewer Board let everyone down, including themselves as our very lives are now ticking time bombs, knowing the best water supplies available in coastal Alabama will eventually be spoiled or destroyed. Big Creek Lake has been placed in jeopardy because of wimpy politicians, lawyers and our MAWSS board of directors. Everyone in elected office refused to demand an injunction which would have stopped this mindless action in the first place.
This group of self-serving individuals gave up as it would be too costly to battle the petroleum industry. There is a billion-dollar investment being threatened and going down the drain. Our legal system tends to lean toward supporting the oil industry, not just locally, but statewide. It appears there is little faith in this system protecting our very lifeblood for municipalities throughout coastal Alabama. There are more than 350,000 people depending on Mobile for their clean, great tasting water.
Water is arguably the most essential nutrient there is. We can go without food for 40 days and more, but without water it would all be over in three to five days. To stay in optimum health, it is absolutely essential that you drink enough water. This is vital information but what isn’t said is the fact drinking spoiled oiled water wouldn’t be healthy in any manner and the MAWSS didn’t have the guts to continue battling for us.
The Corps of Engineers Nationwide Permit given to Plains All American, in my opinion, is illegal and no one took immediate legal steps demanding this permit be rescinded and the process redone. A proper evaluation of the environmental and human threats would require an Environmental Impact Statement with a public hearing. There is a belated legal action filed by Southern Environmental Law Center, so let us hope some real thrust is taken and very soon.
Myrt Jones
Mobile
]]></text></news-item>