<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-BV71-DY9P-N230"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Energy firms price-fix probe</title><source>Daily Mirror</source><author>ZENA ALLI</author><text><![CDATA[The the energy regulator Ofgem has finally got tough with the big six providers and referred them for a full competition investigation. So what does this actually mean and how will it affect you? What is a competition investigation? It is an investigation by the Competition And Market Authority (CMA), into whether a particular market or industry is "anti-competitive".
Why are the big six being referred? Ofgem investigated and found "possible tacit co-ordination" on the size and timing of price rises by British Gas, EDF, E.on, Npower, Scottish Power and Scottish and Southern Energy (SSE).
This seems a perfectly reasonable concern when you consider that these big six suppliers dominate 95 per cent of the energy market - and history tells us that when one supplier increases prices the others follow like sheep.
Ofgem therefore concluded that the only way to remove the uncertainty in the energy market was to refer it to the CMA for an investigation because it has greater power to tackle the issue if their concerns prove to be correct.
How long will the investigation take? It is likely to begin in June and is expected to take around 18 months to complete. There will then be a further six months for any changes to be brought in.
What could the outcome be? One possible outcome is that the big six will be broken up, allowing smaller suppliers to gain a foothold in the market. More suppliers in any market means it becomes more competitive - and you would expect prices to fall as a consequence.
How will I be affected? Firstly, we will find out once and for all if consumers have been ripped off over their energy bills because of a lack of competition in the market.
Hopefully, the main impact will be that the market becomes more competitive, with more deals and offers becoming available which would lead to cheaper bills.
Even before the investigation we have seen a sign of this with SSE announcing that it will freeze prices until 2016. Will the rest of the sheep now follow? My thoughts... There is no doubt the investigation, which should have been commissioned years ago, is good news for consumers. I only hope it tackles the real issues thoroughly - and finally makes our energy market fair, trustworthy and transparent.
QI just found out that a DVD player I bought was stolen by the seller, can I keep it? Anonymous DEAN SAYS: The short answer is no. When goods are stolen the original owner retains legal right of ownership Q:I have been given bad financial advice what can I do? Keith Carpenter, via email DEAN SAYS: If you have already complained to the advisor and they have failed to deal with the complaint you can go to www.financialombudsman.org.uk
]]></text></news-item>