<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-CJV1-DYJJ-P0GN"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Mr. Speaker</title><source>Courier News (Bridgewater, New Jersey)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Government must play a role in helping give people a leg up and help them make it to the middle class.
Vincent Prieto, 53, a former bodybuilder and plumber, was sworn as New Jersey's 170th Assembly Speaker in January, replacing Sheila Oliver of Essex County. Prieto, D-Hudson, who emigrated to the United States with his mother when he was 11, has been in the Assembly since 2004, where he represents the 32nd Legislative District. He is a construction code official in Secaucus, where he was a member of the Planning Board.Prieto attended Middlesex County College and Bergen Community College.We asked him some questions pertaining to issues, his background and the influence his background had on his governing philosophy:
What personal qualities do you think will serve you best as Assembly speaker?
I consider myself to be a fair-minded, independent person who is able to listen to all sides of an argument and reach the kind of compromises that benefit our state. During my 10 years in the Assembly, I have forged strong relationships with my fellow members on both sides of the aisle and these friendships help me find the common ground necessary to get things done. I always say that in Trenton you don't want great legislation - you want good legislation because that is how you build the consensus necessary to pass bills and move our state forward.
How will you differ, in style - and substance, if at all - from your predecessor, Sheila Oliver?
Sheila Oliver is a close friend and someone I have great respect for. Working with her was a true privilege, especially in the last two years as the Assembly budget chairman. I hope to build on her success in fighting for progressive values like looking out for working families and investing in education. At the same time, I believe that more can be done to make sure that the Assembly is an equal partner along with the Governor's Office and State Senate in making the decisions that determine the future of our state. In my short time as Speaker, I believe that I have shown a desire to be at the table and have a strong voice in what legislation makes it to the governor. I will continue to do so to make sure that the People's House is getting its due and helping to shape the important legislation coming out of Trenton.
The day you were sworn as Assembly speaker in January, you said lowering property taxes would be the Assembly Democrats' top priority. How, exactly, do you propose doing so?
Property taxes are the most difficult problem facing our state, and I believe the only way to solve the problem is to look outside to what other states are doing to successfully lower the burden on homeowners. That's why I have proposed setting up a commission to study effective methods to control property taxes, and we are working to establish this group now. We do not yet have the answers, but my goal is to find these answers and then implement them to the best of our ability.
Would you support a revenue-neutral plan to reduce the reliance on property tax by increasing income taxes or expanding goods and services subject to the sales tax?
I am committed to reducing the property tax burden on New Jersey residents. We are not quite there yet on specific ideas and strategies, and I do not like to deal in hypotheticals, especially when it comes to something as crucial to the future of our state. What we need to do is look at what is working in other states and begin an honest dialogue among the many stakeholders in this issue on how to improve the situation. The residents of our state need relief, and I am committed to working to provide it.
What are your other top two or three legislative priorities this session?
Coming from a blue-collar background as a construction code official and former plumber, I firmly believe that we must invest more in career and technical education. Not everyone is cut out for college, and there are good-paying middle-class jobs available to people who have the right skills and are willing to work hard. I recently participated in the launch of the New Jersey Employer Coalition for Technical Education, and I am working on legislation to expand career and technical education. I am also committed to passing a comprehensive earned sick leave bill to remove the dilemma that many New Jersey families face of either working while sick or losing pay. Earned sick leave would not only benefit employees but would also be a positive development for employers in increased morale and productivity and for consumers in lower risk of illness.
Do you believe there is a need for further public employee pension and/or health care reforms?
Public workers made sacrifices when the reform legislation was passed - now it is time for the state to do its part. New Jersey's problem is not only expenses but revenue, and we cannot continually lay the blame on the backs of public employees. We must do more to grow the economy and create jobs to increase our tax receipts and solve our revenue issues. The Legislature passed a full package of bills designed to create jobs and improve the economy in 2011, only to see it vetoed by the governor. We are willing to revive these programs that we know will improve the situation at any time, but it is up to the governor to act on them.
Would you support an increase in the gasoline tax to fund improvements to New Jersey's transportation infrastructure?
I have been outspoken in my belief that we must raise the gas tax to fund vital transportation infrastructure needs. New Jersey has the third-lowest gas tax in the country and it has not been increased in decades. This has led the Transportation Trust Fund to become so badly underfunded that it can no longer finance new projects and is only paying off debt on previous work. Raising the gas tax would create thousands of construction jobs, help our economy and let us fix our crumbling infrastructure. If we don't act soon, we will be in much bigger trouble when more and more of our roads and bridges become structurally deficient.
On what major policy issues do you believe there is common ground among Democrats, the Republican legislative leadership and Gov. Christie?
Everyone wants to lower the property tax burden on residents, and that is an area where we should be able to find common ground moving forward. It is extremely important to forge bipartisan compromise like we did recently with the Dream Act bill, which granted in-state college tuition to the children of undocumented immigrants who grew up here in New Jersey. This was a common-sense bill that needed to be passed, and I was happy to see the governor sign it. There are always opportunities for compromise, and one of my main missions is to find them.
How, if at all, has your background as a Cuban immigrant influenced your views on the proper role of government?
When I came here from Cuba as a boy with my mother, we had very little and had to strive to improve our lives. I worked very hard, but I would not have gotten to where I am now without strong support from family and friends in the neighborhood as well as the educational opportunities provided by government. This has shaped my governing philosophy in that I believe government must play a role in helping give people a leg up and help them make it to the middle class and the American Dream. One clear area is public education, which I am a firm believer in and I believe must be a priority for our state.
Who have been your most important political mentors? In what ways have they helped shape your governing philosophy?
My main political mentor has always been my running mate, state Sen. and North Bergen Mayor Nick Sacco. He has been an incredible guide into state politics over the last decade and remains someone that I go to for counsel and advice. The main value he taught me is that for politicians to be successful, they must always keep their word. I follow that goal every day in the Statehouse and it has served me very well. He also showed me that you don't necessarily have to speak loudly and grab headlines to be well respected, and that often times the person who gets less attention is the one who is really getting things done for their constituents.
I also have great admiration for U.S. Sen. Bob Menendez. Being a fellow Cuban immigrant and Hudson County resident, he in many ways paved the way for me and showed us that a person new to this country and with limited means can make a difference in their community and rise up to important positions in our government.
As a state assemblyman, your focus was on Hudson County. What have you done as Speaker to better familiarize yourself with the issues facing suburbanites and residents living in the central and southern parts of New Jersey?
While I represent Hudson County predominantly, my hometown of Secaucus is much more of a suburb than a city, and I also represent parts of Bergen County. No matter where you are in New Jersey, we all face many of the same obstacles - high property taxes, high cost of living, stagnant wages and a sluggish state economy. I am fighting to invest in our middle class and to promote programs that will better train our children to work the high-tech jobs of the future, rein in property taxes and promote economic fairness and opportunity. I think of these as universal values that apply to every part of our state.
Given the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey's history of patronage, lack of transparency and testy relationships among appointees from the two states, what kinds of reforms do you believe are appropriate?
This is an issue that we are studying, and there have been bills proposed by members of the caucus that could do tremendous good in making the Port Authority more accountable. The entire reason that the Legislature is still investigating the controversy over the George Washington Bridge lane closures is to find out exactly what happened and why it did, so we can install reforms and safeguards to prevent it from happening again. Until the investigation is over we may not know exactly what must be done, but we will continue to pursue it because New Jersey residents deserve a Port Authority that treats them with respect and not as pawns in a political game.
Government must play a role in helping give people a leg up and help them make it to the middle class.
]]></text></news-item>