<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-BM11-F12F-F01Y"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Acted Firm on Graft Charges: Antony</title><source>New Indian Express</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[THIRUVANANTHAPURAM, March 30 -- Union Defence Minister A K Antony has said that his ministry had acted firmly on charges of corruption in the defence sector and never ignored them.
The Defence Ministry had ordered inquiries into corruption charges whenever they came up and had never ignored such complaints, Antony told a meet the press programme here on Saturday.
"I have blacklisted world's prominent companies and cancelled global contracts. The main criticism against me is that I'm not kneeling before the arms dealers,''he said. "At the same time, there is no let up in the modernisation of the forces,'' he asserted.
The Defence Minister said that an inquiry has been ordered into the crash of Indian Air Force's C-130J Super Hercules aircraft near Gwalior airbase the other day. Holding his ground on the criticism that mishaps and deaths have become a common affair in the armed forces while he remained at the helm, he said that he did not want to jump into any conclusions. "Accidents occur now and then. There is a procedure for inquiries in the Armed forces. Let the investigation be completed,'' he said, and added that in India, procurement of arms and equipment is not based on political decisions. "There is a system in our forces. The main concern is on quality and pricing,'' he said.
'No Leadership Role'
On whether he will return to state politics in the event of UPA failing to form the next government, Antony said that he will never have a leadership role in the party or the government in the state in future.
"My leadership role in the party or government here is over. Permanently, he asserted. "I'll play only a complimentary role,''he added. He said that the people in Kerala have already taken a decision to back UDF and UPA in the Lok Sabha polls and reiterated that the UDF will better the 2009 tally of 16 seats, by at least one seat.
He pointed out that the CPM is even scared to field candidates on its own symbol.
"Five out of the CPM's 15 candidates are independents .It shows that it has lost its mass base heavily. The party has become outdated by following obsolete policies and programmes. The CPM is not ready to change according to the times," he said. "People of the state detest political killings. Earlier, people suffered in silence but now they have begun to react," he said.
Asked how he viewed the adverse remarks passed by the High Court against the Chief Minister's office, Antony evaded a direct reply and said that the government was for a CBI probe as ordered.
"It is for the government to comment on the remarks,'' he said. However, Antony maintained that Chandy needn't step down.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from New Indian Express. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>