<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-CJV1-DYJJ-P11V"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Asbestos issues won't impair air quality, official says</title><source>Des Moines Register</source><author>By, Jason Clayworth</author><text><![CDATA[The smoldering ruins of the former Younkers building are considered to be an asbestos contaminated site and will require specialized removal, an inspector said Saturday.
And while proper cleanup is critical to public health, inspector Tom Wuehr of the Iowa Department of Natural Resources said it's unlikely that downtown workers or people viewing the site have been or will be exposed to harmful levels of the cancer-causing materials.
"We can't say categorically that you didn't breathe an asbestos fiber or two," Wuehr said. "But in the Midwest, we all have asbestos fibers in our lungs. It's the matter of degree of exposure we have. We don't generally see health problems from people unless they've really had heavy exposure for a long period of time.
"Generally speaking, you wouldn't expect health consequences from a one-time event. And it would appear to me that the levels of exposures here would be relatively light, if anyone was exposed."
The floors of the former department store building were believed to have had asbestos felt between them, Wuehr said. In addition, pipes and other areas of the building had asbestos. Asbestos is an airborne fiber, but the large amounts of water used by firefighters would have helped contain the material, Wuehr said.
Crews had been in the process of removing the asbestos, and bags of the material had been taken out of the building and properly disposed of Friday, Wuehr said.
The building also contained lead paint, a poison when inhaled or ingested in large amounts. Toxic fumes that include lead may be inhaled when the paint is burned or melted. Lead may be inhaled when dust that contains lead becomes airborne.
Steve Weil of the Lead and Environmental Hazards Association in Maryland said the most dangerous periods would likely have been when the flames were at their peak and debris was flying.
Weil recommended people be cognizant of the risk and stay away from the debris. The site is currently sectioned off from the general public and will remain so until the dangers are cleared, Wuehr noted.
Probe into asbestos will continue, state promises
Investigations into whether contractors had illegally disposed of hazardous waste as part of the Younkers building renovation will continue despite the structure now being a giant pile of rubbish, a state inspector said Saturday.
The investigations began earlier this year after executives at RedNet Environmental Services of West Des Moines alleged in a letter to state officials that workers at the site were being told to throw away materials presumed to have asbestos without any testing.
Officials from the Hansen Co., a Johnston-based construction contractor in charge of overseeing renovations at the site, have categorically denied the accusations. They have filed a lawsuit against RedNet owners Rob and Lynn Knudsen alleging multiple counts of libel.
State and city officials initially dismissed the complaints. However, new asbestos and lead investigations were launched after The Des Moines Register reported that the state and the city had failed to review key documents that the Knudsens claimed showed improper cleanup.
Iowa Department of Natural Resources asbestos inspector Tom Wuehr said Saturday that his review will continue despite the fire.
]]></text></news-item>