<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-CJV1-DYJJ-P36V"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Poor health hurts our economy</title><source>Pensacola News Journal (Florida)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[If there was any silver lining to last week's gloomy survey of Escambia County's poor health, it was the economic wake-up call sent to local businesses and health care providers.
The message is relatively simple: The vitality of a community's economy is directly related to - and affected by - its overall healthiness.
More about that later in this column.
Conducted by the University of Wisconsin and the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, the health survey showed that between 2010 and 2012 the overall healthiness of Escambia's 300,000-plus residents deteriorated, falling from 55th worst in Florida to 57th.
What's more, Escambia held on to its dubious title of having the worst overall healthiness of any of Florida's 26 urban counties.
The main factors pushing Escambia further down the list were tobacco and alcohol use, obesity and chronic poverty among various segments of the population.
In stark contrast to Escambia, its next-door neighbor Santa Rosa County ranked sixth best overall in the state.
Of course, this latest survey did not fall on deaf ears.
The Partnership for a Healthy Community, an alliance of health care providers and businesses, is addressing the problem head-on.
By working with local businesses, the partnership is developing programs to promote healthy lifestyles, reduce obesity and strongly discourage tobacco use.
And the partnership is making progress, getting the attention of local business owners bearing the adverse financial effects of an unhealthy workforce and community.
And the costs are staggering, said Baptist Hospital's David Sjoberg, who also serves as executive director, along with partnership President Nora Bailey.
Obesity alone is costing local businesses $500 million a year in additional health insurance costs, lost productivity and absenteeism. Couple those costs with tobacco use and abuse of alcohol, and the loss figure soars to more than $1 billion annually.
Some business owners are reworking their business plans to include tools that promote and reward healthy lifestyle changes, while others are implementing more aggressive tactics, such as hiring only non-smokers.
The task of moving the community's needle in a positive, healthy direction is a daunting one.
By focusing on a few of the contributing factors that drag down the community's health, Sjoberg and Bailey think progress is possible.
The alternative - accepting deteriorating community health - is unacceptable and injurious to the area's overall economic health.
]]></text></news-item>