<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-C1X1-DXDT-61VW"><date>2014-03-29</date><title>Petro Poroshenko, the billionaire chocolate baron hoping to become Ukraine's next president; Officially declaring his bid for the presidency on Saturday, Petro Poroshenko declared he would steer Ukraine firmly out of Moscow's orbit and into Europe's, writes Colin Freeman</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Colin Freeman Kiev</author><text><![CDATA[In the huge protests that toppled Ukraine 's pro-Kremlin government last month, crowds endured freezing temperatures, water cannon, and the constant threat of police violence as they demanded President Viktor Yanukovych's downfall.
They did not, however, want for high-quality chocolate.
For wandering among the crowds handing out morale-boosting bars of Madascan Vanilla and Dominican Dark was Petro Poroshenko, a pro-Western billionaire whose Roshen chocolate brand is Ukraine's answer to Green and Blacks.
In a land where good chocolate used to be as hard to come by as denim jeans and pop music, it was no great surprise that a man who began importing cocoa beans 20 years ago should become one of its richest men.
What was remarkable, though, was how he risked his entire business empire to support the protests, broadcasting their grievances via his private television station, Channel Five.
Now, having already had the Kremlin ban his products and shut one of his Russia-based factories, the 48-year-old has emerged as the front-runner to become Ukraine's new president in elections in May.
Officially declaring his bid on Saturday, he declared he would steer Ukraine firmly out of Moscow's orbit and into Europe's - a move he believes Ukraine should have started making two decades ago.
Mr Poroshenko warned that Ukraine was "in serious danger", both from the military threat from Russia and from economic meltdown.
He also called for new security guarantees from the West, pointing out that the 1994 Budapest Memorandum, which America, Britain and Russia all signed to guarantee Ukraine's borders, had failed to prevent Moscow's invasion of Crimea.
"We should have a special treaty that replaces the memorandum, which provides an absolutely clear mechanism as to how we can provide not only Ukrainian, but European and global security," Mr Poroshenko, a fluent English speaker, told The Sunday Telegraph.
He also vowed to use his business nous to tackle Ukraine's rampant corruption problems, which have helped push the country to bankruptcy and are a serious obstacle to his ambitions for European Union membership.
"We know how to use Western experience to fight corruption and demonstrate zero-tolerance," he said. "We need financial help, yes, but we must tackle the corruption first."
Mr Poroshenko was speaking just two days after a flying visit to London, where he and other opposition leaders met with the Foreign Secretary, William Hague. Also with him was Vitaly Klitschko, the heavyweight boxer who was also a prominent figure in the recent protests, and who has also declared a bid for the presidency.
True, a boxer and a chocolate baron may not seem the obvious candidates for the formidable challenges ahead. But both have an advantage that goes beyond the street cred they enjoy with the protesters in Kiev's Independence Square. As wealthy men already they are deemed less susceptible to the corruption that has crippled so many other Ukrainian governments.
And in a country where even the reputations of even the most promising politicians seldom survive the challenges of elected office, the simple fact of never having held the top job before is also a boon.
That is a problem already confronting Yulia Tymoshenko, the blonde-haired heroine of Ukraine's 2004 Orange Revolution, who also declared her candidacy last week. For many, the ex-prime minister is much part of the failed "old guard" as Mr Yanukovych, and is current trailing in the polls."Poroshenko is seen as the best of a generally poor bunch, as the stars of the established politicians start to fade," said Andrew Wilson, a Ukraine expert with the European Council on Foreign Relations.
"Then again, while his lack of a big party machine behind him will be an attraction to some, that may mean it is difficult for hin to get things passed in parliament. He is in effect, just a 'brand' - rather like his chocolate."
All the same, he seems to be a brand people like. While many voters are as yet undecided, recent polls gave Mr Poroshenko 24.9 per cent of the vote, compared to nine per cent for Mr Klitschko and eight per cent for Ms Tymoshenko. Mikhail Dobkin, who was on Friday adopted as Mr Yanukovych's replacement candidate by the pro-Russian Party of Regions, is also on eight per cent.
"Poroshenko is a smart guy and he was very good at helping people during the protests, negotiating with police to get people freed and so on," said Elena Suvchenko, 60, as she stood in Independence Square week. "On the other hand, he didn't try and be centre stage all the time. I will vote for him."
So who exactly is the man known as the Chocolate King? Born near the port of Odessa in south-west Ukraine, the former economics graduate was one of post-communist Ukraine's very first business consultants. As Ukrainian firms opened up to free trade for the very first time, he advised them on the vary basics of commerce, from how to draft a letter of credit or contract through to getting goods cleared by customs.
In the 1990s, he snapped up several state-owned sweet firms, replacing the papery-tasting Soviet chocolate - which often lacked any actual cocoa beans - with a much superior product. Today, his business empire also includes car plants, a shipyard, and Channel Five television, which gave rather more favourable coverage to the protests than state television did.
While the risk of government reprisals to his businesses were considerable, most of his interests lie outside of heavy-industry, where the Ukrainian state wields most control.
Not that Mr Poroshenko, who is worth around £1.1bn, is a complete novice to politics. A serving MP, he has worked with both sides of Ukraine's political divide, having served as foreign minister alongside Ms Tymoshenko, and for part of 2012 as trade minister for Mr Yanukovych.
A sign, however, that he and Mr Yanukovych no longer saw eye to eye came last July, when Russia suddenly banned all imports of Roshen chocolates. What was ostensibly a purely technical row about labelling standards was in fact a none-too-subtle campaign to remind Ukrainian businesses how dependent they were on the Russian market, and to bully Kiev out of a planned trade association agreement with the European Union.
In November, Mr Yanukovych duly did scrap the agreement, sparking the start of the anti-government protests and dismaying Mr Poroshenko, who has long been staunchly pro-European.
Unlike many of Ukraine's oligarchs - who prefer to pull strings from behind the scenes - he made no secret of his involvement. Channel Five hroadcast the protests from a massive makeshift stage in Independence Square, and Mr Poroshenko frequently used his influence to help injured or arrested demonstrators. When Dmytro Bulatov, an opposition activist, was abducted and badly tortured, Mr Poroshenko paid him a special visit him in hospital, telling Channel Five: "His body has been beaten, but Dmytro's spirit is strong."
Already, though, his support for the protests has earned him enemies. A fortnight ago, Kremlin officials closed his factory in the southern Russian city of Lipetsk, alleging an obscure trademark violation. And last month, during what was supposed to be a peacemaking visit to the breakaway region of Crimea, he was forced to flee through the streets after being chased by angry pro-Russian mob.
That, though, will be nothing compared to the problems he will face if elected, running a country at risk of bankruptcy, separatist turmoil and possible further invasions by Russia.
Supporters hope he will bring the same skills has acquired as a businessmen to the job of president, improving the balance sheet, keeping the work force happy, and outmanoeuvring rivals. But no amount of chocolate is likely to keep things sweet for long.
]]></text></news-item>