<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-CD11-F03R-N1YJ"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>﻿Expert urges oil spill action</title><source>The Bangkok Post</source><author>prf.admin</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 28, 2014 (The Bangkok Post:http://feeds.feedblitz.com/prorssbp Delivered by Newstex) Better oil spill prevention measures are needed to protect Thai waters from chemical pollution, Chulalongkorn University's engineering faculty says.
Lecturer Pisut Painmanakul said authorities have failed to learn any lessons from last year's PTT Global Chemical oil spill crisis off the coast of Rayong. 'We have not adopted any measures to create more efficient prevention measures, and have not succeeded in the environmental remediation process,' he said. He was referring to the pipeline operated by PTTGC Plc which burst while transferring oil to a tanker on July 27 last year. An estimated 50,000 litres of crude leaked into the sea near Map Ta Phut. The incident was one of at least 10 oil spills reported in Thailand since 1997, said Mr Pisut, who is also a member of the National Committee on the Prevention and Combating of Oil Pollution. He said a major oil spill disaster could happen again if government agencies did not devise effective prevention measures. Mr Pisut said the large amount of oil stains found on Bang Saen beach in Chon Buri province on March 15, and the appearance of oil and tar lumps on Sichon beach in Nakhon Si Thammarat recently, were the latest cases of oil pollution in domestic waters. Calling for action, he said both recent oil pollution cases most likely came from the illegal dumping of used oil from ships or fishing vessels. The leading causes of oil pollution are a lack of law enforcement, and inefficient monitoring systems and prevention measures, Mr Pisut said. He called for the establishment of an oil spill emergency response system and a fund, contributed to by state and private sectors, to use in the cleaning up of hazardous waste-related pollution. The Natural Resources and Environment Ministry should also set up an environmental remediation department to specifically deal with oil spills and other environmental disasters, he said.

]]></text></news-item>