<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-BRM1-F0JP-W1SX"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>AROUND THE TRAPS</title><source>The Courier Mail (Australia)</source><author>PETER CAMERON</author><text><![CDATA[Molhoek defends office ASSISTANT Minister Rob Molhoek has defended his charity record as Labor prepares to go on the attack over LNP fundraising.
Despite guarantees there will not be a state election before March 2015, Newman Government ministers have reminders to keep themselves available to assist LNP MPs striving to raise campaign war chests. Some LNP stalwarts fear party organisers are dragging the election chain.
Mr Molhoek (pictured with Gold Coast Imam Imraan Husain) said $8000 plus was raised at his charity golf day on the Gold Coast last week.
"$5000 went to Bravehearts and $3000-plus for the Musgrave Hill Special School. We're trying to raise enough money for their school bus," the Southport MP said.
Mr Molhoek, assistant to Development Minister Jeff Seeney, came into Labor's sights over his endorsement for the coffee table publication Southport Towards Twenty 18. Up to 50,000 copies of the book were touted with ad prices ranging from $7500 to $30,000. At those figures it could have raised more than $200,000.
Labor wants to know if two fundraising entities set up last August used Mr Molhoek's Chirn Park office and staff as a contact point.
"I did not receive a cent and the book was published at no cost to Government. It was commissioned by a Gold Coast ad agency. Not only did I obtain permission from the Clerk of Parliament to write a foreword but also I put money in myself," Mr Molhoek said.
Labor gets the chance to put up or shut up when Parliament resumes on Tuesday. BUYING FAVOURS REINTRODUCTION of Dame Edna (pictured) awards in Canberra sparked memories about the Nationals selling knighthoods in Queensland in the '70s. The idea was pinched from former British PM Lloyd George but old Joh and his cunning "yes men" refined the Pineapple Plutocracy skinner to new levels.
Up to $165,000 (whew!) was the NP going rate but Joh's fundraising sugarbag "Top-Level Ted" Lyons sometimes failed to deliver. One bloke paid $100,000 but shifty Lyons, who had a secret escape door in his city office, left him lamenting.
power wins honour MOVIE producer Des Power was honoured for his screen achievements in Washington last week.
Australian Ambassador Kim Beazley was on hand to laud Power (pictured above left, with Chinese filmmaker Huang Jianxin), who launched Brisbane's annual Asia Pacific Screen Awards. Power cut his screen teeth as a foreign correspondent and boneshaking boss of current affairs at Channel 9, Brisbane in the 1980s.
GOING TO THE DOGS DARLING Downs cockies complain dingoes are being trucked from coastal regions by government contractors to be released up isolated tracks before terrorising their paddocks. But our hairsplitting George St spy says: "They are not dingoes but wild dogs." "Unlike purebred Fraser Island dingoes which are protected, there is not any protection for wild dogs." REBELS SIGN COVERED BIKIE-busting A-G Jarrod Bleijie should be safe to travel north. Packs of bikies seem to have been eliminated from byways in the Bowen Basin. The "Rebels" sign at their old clubhouse on the western side of Mackay racecourse is obscured in black plastic and duct tape.
FURNER IN SEAT SIGHTS DEFEATED Labor Senator Mark Furner, a right-wing Christian, is in the centre of a factional tug-of-war which may see him secure endorsement for the state seat of Ferny Grove held by LNP's Dale Shuttleworth.
SEND IN G-MEN TO HIT BETTING RACKETS AUTHORITIES may need to send betting G-men (and girls) to the Philippines if they want to clean up betting rackets.
Around the Traps revealed last week that racing stipes in Queensland and New South Wales were aware of suspicious betting trends featuring mostly unsuccessful horses who firmed fast on TABs.
Hard to trace when there are up to four betting exchanges operating in Asia outside Australian jurisdiction including a Singapore-owned Philippines exchange.
Australian greyhound betting figures in the racket with some favourites fed three tablespoons of patent infant tonic to cause racing cramps.
NEWMAN REALLY IS A PARTY MAN ON TRADING HOURS POLICE are reserving judgment on Premier Campbell Newman's refusal to reduce liquor trading hours.
Mr Newman (pictured) stood firm this week that he was not about to be a narc against late-night partying.
It would not make sense in the 12 months before an election. Police were mollified when Mr Newman provided extra funding for overtime on the "grog shifts", plus more Drink Safe street precincts and stiffer laws for drunken violence.
If a liquor review next year finds alcohol problems are as bad as ever, you can bet police will demand reduced trading hours.
PEARL SHINES HER WAY TO BIG CHAIR PUMICESTONE pearl Lisa France looks a special for Cabinet promotion in the Newman Government. The Assistant Minister for Natural Resources and Mines shone as MC when Premier Campbell Newman gave his state report to Qld Inc at an Ekka banquet last Tuesday. Praises for the mother-of-three gushed down the microphone from Mr Newman and LNP godfather Bruce McIver.
TIQ SHAKE-UP ON CARDSFORMER Peter Beattie chief of staff Rob Whiddon gained second wind as a big shot at Trade and Investment Queensland when the LNP arrived. A TIQ shake-up is tipped before May.
]]></text></news-item>