<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-H721-JDPF-N1DF"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Results give software firm the Edge</title><source>Motherwell Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Bellshill firm Edge Testing Solutions announced strong end of year results, achieving revenues of £3.6 million and operating profit of over £400k.
Over the past 12 months Edge, the UK's fastest growing and largest independent software testing company, has created 22 new jobs and exceeded its growth target of £3m.
The Strathclyde Business Park company now aims to reach a £5.1m turnover in 2014 with a three-year plan for organic growth of £10m by 2016.
As the company grows it is competing for and winning larger contracts.
Last year Edge won its first £1m contract in direct competition with global IT organisations, and customers now include Heineken, Historic Scotland and Ignis Asset Management.
Expanding into the rest of the UK, Edge opened its first office in England in late 2012, and the company has grown by at least 40 per cent year on year since inception in 2007.
Managing director Brian Ferrie said: "Today software testing is very much part of mainstream business thinking.
"The services we provide are vital to businesses and organisations across all sectors.
"As consumer expectations rise, testing is critical not only to provide a rich and relevant online experience for customers but also to ensure that banks, retailers and governments don't fall victim to damaging software failures that so often hit the headlines."
Edge's success has been fuelled by the impact of technological risk' and its increasing threat to the digital economy, particularly in the financial services sector.
Brian added: "Traditionally we provided testing of back office systems for large corporations, but are now living in a digital age where consumers demand more online services are available 24 hours a day.
"It's critical websites work, respond quickly, support high volumes of users and provide a rich user experience."
]]></text></news-item>