<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-BPX1-JC6P-C4NP"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Stericycle-North Salt Lake divorce picking up speed</title><source>Standard-Examiner (Ogden, Utah)</source><author>Cimaron Neugebauer, Standard-Examiner, Ogden, Utah</author><text><![CDATA[March 30--First of two parts
SUNDAY: Stericycle is looking forward to Tooele County and has finally begun using a public relations strategy.
MONDAY: How it started in North Salt Lake. Who was there first, and what did that mean?
NORTH SALT LAKE -- Stericycle is planning to move to Tooele County far away from homes -- and North Salt Lake is doing everything it can to help it get there as soon as possible.
"We totally understand, [residents] are scared," North Salt Lake assistant city manager Ken Leetham told the Standard-Examiner. "Incineration of trash right next to homes is really not good from a land compatibility standpoint."
Stericycle agrees that operating next to residents wasn't in their plans, especially 25 years ago when it opened.
"I don't think it's an ideal situation for either one of us," said Selin Hoboy, Stericycle president of Legislative and Regulatory Affairs.
Changing its image
After months of not commenting, the company recently reached out to the Standard-Examiner and offered a tour of its facility and explained in-depth what goes on inside. They want to repair their image by clearing up misconceptions and being more open with the public, especially their new neighbors in Tooele.
Stericycle hopes to change the company image by offering two public tours in April and May to let Tooele County residents come see what the facility does and educate them. North Salt Lake residents are also invited, but space is limited and by reservation.
Foxboro neighborhood resident Whitney Brady says a tour of its facility is "too little, too late" of a gesture for her family. They are already looking for another place to live primarily due to Stericycle.
Brady's 5-year-old daughter's asthma condition has worsened instead of growing out of it since they moved into the area two years ago. The girl is now on daily medication and an inhaler.
"We want to go away and see if that helps," she said.
Stericycle executives admit they haven't been as available to the public as they could have when concerns arose about the company last fall because its emission violation came to light.
"We learned a big lesson from Salt Lake City," said Jennifer Koenig, Stericycle vice president for Corporate Communications as she referred to the public relations fiasco that happened when angry residents weren't getting answers about repeated emergency bypass events.
"That's just how Stericycle has operated for years. We have been a very quiet company. We didn't have P.R. people," she said. "We weren't readily available."
A state-of-the-art facility
The new location in Tooele County will be on 40 acres of School and Institutional Trust Lands Administration property and about 11 miles away from the nearest house.
"We won't likely, in our lifetimes, run into an issue like this where we are up against neighbors," Koenig said.
The actual date of when Stericycle will move is unknown because of the permitting process and obtaining water rights for a well to provide water to the facility. In the best case scenario the company estimates it could move 1 1/2 -- 2 years from now.
The new location will actually cost the company more money than just staying in North Salt Lake. Just to maintain the facility with the new EPA regulations beginning in October it will spend over $1.5 million by installing a new generator and upgrades. The new regulations will be even more strict by cutting current limits by about 90 percent. When the company moves it will start building from scratch again like it did in 1989; it won't be salvaging all the old parts, because there are stricter requirements for new buildings.
Critical reports
Recent scientific reports from the Erin Brockovich environmental team showed more concentrated levels of dioxin surrounding the homes closest to the plant. Stericycle hasn't seen the very critical Brockovich report, but understands it compares dust samples and not solely soil samples like the state recently tested. They say the unfavorable report from the Brockovich team doesn't prove anything since it was such a small sample size and other variables.
"We can't be certain it is necessarily material that is coming from our facility," Hoboy said. "What they were comparing -- the attic versus what's in the soil, is like comparing apples to oranges. They are not related."
A Utah Department of Health report in February showed increased levels of pollution directly around the facility. The levels were estimates based on emission data and weather patterns, since Stericycle doesn't have a way to measure particulate matter airflow.
Regulation and violation
Since the 1980s, the federal Environmental Protection Agency went from not regulating thousands of incinerators at all to now requiring constant monitoring and pollutant emission standards.
Stericycle received a notice of violation in December 2011 when it had an emergency bypass event and a recorded 616 dry standard cubic meters of unsafe dioxin was emitted into the air around homes. The normal range is 125.
Stericycle is still fighting the violation in an appeal process, but is said by the state Division of Air Quality to currently be in compliance with operations. According to the DAQ, other violations collected into the one notice of violation were: emissions exceeding permit limits for hydrogen chloride and nitogen oxides on multiple occasions. The company also failed to report these issues to DAQ in the expected time frame. It failed to keep consistent operating conditions during the December 2011 stack test and failed to include test results showing the violating levels in its annual and semi-annual reports.
Hoboy said Stericycle's contribution to air pollution in the southern end of Davis County has been "so small, so minimal" since it has been here.
"In reality if you were to move Stericycle out of the state altogether, we are not going to have a huge impact on air quality because our emission standards are set so low to begin with."
The company's motto is "Protecting people. Reducing Risk," and that is what they believe they are doing. They said they have done everything they can to be a good neighbor including putting up a concrete wall between the homes and switching to quieter eco-friendly electric trucks. It has also contributed money to community baseball teams, held public tours back in 2006 and hand sanitation events, Koenig said.
"We are trying to get better."
Contact reporter Cimaron Neugebauer at 801-625-4231 or cneugebauer@standard.net Follow him on Twitter at @CimaronNews.
___ (c)2014 the Standard-Examiner (Ogden, Utah) Visit the Standard-Examiner (Ogden, Utah) at www.standard.net Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>