<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-CJV1-DYJJ-P072"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>fight against slaughter</title><source>Asbury Park Press (New Jersey)</source><author>By, Jennifer Merkel</author><text><![CDATA[Barely a month ago, Amy Zeidman Horowitz found herself having dinner with a group of fellow vegans, talking about her choice not to eat meat, her passion for animal rights and her idea to raise awareness for the conditions in which animals are bred for food. On Saturday, her vision became a reality as more than 30 people lined the rain-soaked sidewalk in front of the Catelli Bros. slaughterhouse, holding signs that read, "Honk if you love animals," and "Meat, dairy and eggs are murder."
"Our goal is for people to start realizing what goes on in a factory ... to put glass walls on slaughterhouses," said Horowitz, founder of the group NJ Farm Animal Save. "Animals are not living out their lives on the grass."
The demonstration, meant to "bear witness to the suffering of animals killed for food," was held in front of a slaughterhouse that had been accused of animal cruelty.
In January, the U.S. Department of Agriculture suspended operations at Catelli Bros. on allegations of inhumane treatment of calves. Around the same time, a secret video from the Humane Society of the United States surfaced on YouTube, showing conscious calves being slaughtered and one calf -unable to walk - being dragged by workers.
The veal company, which is based in Camden County, reopened its Shrewsbury plant in February after agreeing to oversights and a series of conditions to improve conditions.
"Compassion starts on our plate," said Horowitz, 48, of East Brunswick, who became a vegan three years ago. Vegans do not consume any food that comes from an animal, such as meat, dairy or eggs.
She cited examples of animal cruelty in food production, such as veal crates, which are banned in eight states, though not in New Jersey. In veal crates, calves are taken within hours of being born, tethered by their necks and confined to tiny crates too small for them to move around in until they arrive at their destination and killed for food.
"These animals are innocent victims," Jason Wicker, 41, of Brick said as water poured down his rain slicker. "We are here to say stop exploiting them."
He said he saw many people driving Saturday along Broad Street react to the pro-animal signs the demonstrators paraded over their heads. "You can see their faces - you can see their expressions. It's powerful. There is some anger, but there's a lot of compassion, too."
Holding a sign that read, "Being vegan is clucking awesome," Maureen Rocco, 50, of Brick said she stopped eating meat two years ago while participating in a 21-day vegan challenge during Lent.
"You can eat and be healthy and live better without animal protein," she said. "You have to find out where your food comes from - and it's ugly," she said.
Horowitz said Saturday's event was the first of many she hopes to hold. Her goal is to have a vigil once a month and informational gatherings every few weeks, where she hands out leaflets on veganism and the conditions of animals that are bred and slaughtered for food.
"I don't preach," she said. "People get defensive when they hear I'm vegan. But the whole basis of being vegan is that every living thing has a right to be free."
Wicker agreed, saying, "There was the Bill of Rights, civil rights, women's rights ... now it's time for animal rights."
Speaking out
Scan the QR code to watch a video from Saturday's protest.
]]></text></news-item>