<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-BMB1-JC1N-W001"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>DP&amp;L seeks OK to charge extra fees; IN-DEPTH COVERAGE ECONOMY</title><source>Dayton Daily News (Ohio)</source><author>By Laura A. Bischoff</author><text><![CDATA[COLUMBUS - Dayton Power & Light customers may be on the hook for millions of dollars in extra fees on their monthly electric bills if the Public Utilities Commission of Ohio grants requests that consumer advocates say are related to maneuvering done to minimize the effects of deregulation.
The Ohio Consumers' Counsel, which acts as the lawyer for Ohio's residential consumers, is fighting DP&L's requests, saying what's good for the utility's stockholders isn't necessarily what's good for its Ohio customers.
DP&L's corporate communications officials declined comment to the newspaper, saying it would respond to the OCC remarks in filings before the PUCO.
The issue concerns the transfer or sale of DP&L's electric generation assets, such as power plants, mandated as part of a 1999 law that ushered in utility deregulation in Ohio. In one of the contentious issues, DP&L seeks to charge customers for environmental clean-up or other expenses tied to the sale of its generation assets.
The deregulation law required electric utilities to transition from state regulated monopolies to businesses that vie for customers in a competitive market. The thinking was that competition brings lower prices, which benefits consumers.
However, the switch to a competitive market has taken far longer than initially expected, and OCC is accusing DP&L of purposely causing delays in order to collect more fees.
The big electric utilities used to own all three levels of the business: generation, transmission and distribution. The new system required them to spin off or sell their generation assets so they are no longer vertically integrated monopolies.
In its filings before the PUCO, DP&L says it is working on transferring or selling its generation assets, which have a book value of about $1.57 billion.
The filings also argue that the diverstiture of those assets potentially puts the utility in a precarious financial position. It is under a legal mandate to perform environmental investigation and remediation activities in connection with the transfer of those facilities, the utility says, and should be able to "recover all prudently incurred costs" associated with any environmental clean-up.
It also says the divestiture of the generation assets was ordered without regard to market conditions, and that those conditions have deteriorated.
"Given current poor market conditions, DP&L could sustain a serious, continuing financial loss," the utility warned in arguing for approval to continue collecting $110 million a year from customers as a "service stability rider."
In a response filed with the PUCO last week, the Ohio Consumers' Counsel accused DP&L of dragging its feet as a business strategy.
"DP&L wants the PUCO to protect it from 'poor market conditions,'" the OCC wrote. "Having denied its Dayton-area customers of the benefits of low market prices that it finds to be poor conditions for its own profit, DP&L seeks to prolong the pain of its customers with more delay to market.
"Basically, DP&L is asking the PUCO to delay its full transition to market until it can make more profit and have its customers pay more. That's a bad idea for Ohioans."
Pocketbooks affected
The tug-of-war being played out before the PUCO, the state's regulatory body that serves 4.5 million residential utility customers as well as business owners, shows how behind-the-scenes wrangling can dramatically affect consumer pocketbooks.
DP&L, which is owned by AES Corp., serves more than 500,000 retail electric customers including 456,000 residential customers in 24 counties in west central Ohio. It is the electric company for all or parts of Montgomery, Miami, Greene, Clark, Champaign, Preble and Darke counties.
In its Dec. 30 application, DP&L told the PUCO it is working toward transferring its power generation assets to a new company by May 31, 2017, but it had a number of complex issues to work out.
It seeks permission to:
? Continue collecting $110 million a year from customers as a "service stability rider" so that the company gets a reasonable return on equity through May 2017 - even if that goes past when the company sells or transfers its generation assets;
? Charge customers for business costs associated with the sale or transfer of its generation assets since the state is requiring the company to do so; and
? Charge customers for future clean-up costs on generation properties, even after those assets are sold off.
The consumers' counsel is crying foul on all these requests. DP&L should not be allowed to charge customers for earnings that fall short on the generation side of the business after the utility sells off those generating assets, according to the consumer advocacy group. And it says DP&L is the first Ohio utility to propose charging customers for future clean-up costs associated with assets that it plans to sell or transfer to an unregulated entity.
"Other Ohio electric utilities have apparently recognized that such a proposal neither would, nor should, pass the proverbial 'smell test,'" the OCC wrote in filings with the Public Utilities Commission.
Some of the generation assets include long-ago shuttered plants that require extensive clean-up. According to the consumer council, utilities in other instances made the new owners assume those liabilities.
Having DP&L's customers pick up the tab for the environmental clean-up costs means DP&L can sell of its generation assets for more money, the OCC alleged in its filing. DP&L customers, it said, have already paid $441 million in "stranded" costs tied to generating assets no longer in use.
"There is no valid reason to ask the customers of DP&L to pay twice for the same environmental liabilities," the OCC said in the filing.
Deregulation slow to occur
The DP&L case is being closely watched by those in the industry, and it generated a flurry of filings last week from more than 10 customer groups and utilities.
The PUCO staff has recommended against several of DP&L's requests, saying in part that there are too many unanswered questions and requests for special treatment. Jason Gil-ham, a PUCO spokesman, said the agency staff is still reviewing DP&L's application and the comments from interested parties. There is no time table yet for when the PUCO might decide the case, he said.
DP&L's residential customers paid on average $113 a month for electric service in 2012, up 18.9 percent from $95 in 2007, according to the OCC. Roughly 32 percent of DP&L's residential customers in 2012 struggled to pay their electric bills, according to OCC records. A utility rate survey by the PUCO in March 2014 shows that Dayton customers pay the second highest rate in the state.
The deregulation implementation process should never have taken so long, OCC spokesman Marty Berkowitz said, and as a result, customers are paying more than they should.
"It is taking DP&L a long time since the 1999 deregulatory law
- too long for customers - to complete the transition to pricing electricity based on the energy market," Berkowitz said. "Instead of benefitting from recent lower market prices, DP&L customers have paid a succession of above market charges for such things as DP&L's 'stability.' It seems that DP&L wants to avoid pricing electricity generation at the market until the market prices go higher and consumers will pay more. In this regard, Ohioans are paying higher electricity rates on average than residential consumers in 32 other states."
Contact this reporter at 614-224-1624 or email Laura A..Bischoff@coxinc.com
]]></text></news-item>