<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-CJV1-DYJJ-P1J5"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Fact Check: Critics question Clawson's actions at Hayes Lemmerz</title><source>The News-Press (Fort Myers, Florida)</source><author>By, Heather Wysocki</author><text><![CDATA[Curt Clawson has been the topic of more attacks than his opponents in the race for the 19th Congressional District seat. Anti-Clawson television ads and mailers have totaled over $340,000 since March 1, according to Federal Election Commission filings.
And while a few have poked fun at his early ad about his Purdue basketball career, the majority have focused on his time at Hayes Lemmerz, an automotive wheel manufacturer.
1 Claim: Clawson took a government bailout
What did happen during Clawson's tenure: two Chapter 11 restructurings, in 2001 and 2009; the closure of seven U.S. plants that eliminated over a thousand jobs between 2001 and 2007; the death of a factory employee in 2003; and members of the board of directors and management team making millions in the years after bankruptcy.
Clawson and former board members don't deny those claims but have explanations for each.
But what didn't happen? A government bailout.
The company did work with a government agency to cover nearly $100 million worth of employee and retiree pensions. But that agency doesn't use tax money.
"No money whatsoever came from the U.S. government or the state government," said Jim Chapman, a former Hayes Lemmerz board member.
Hayes Lemmerz came out of its first Chapter 11 in 2003 and experienced a period of growth, according to Securities and Exchange Commission filings.
The company entered a second Chapter 11 in 2009, and as part of it company stakeholders wanted Clawson and his board to look at how to reorganize the massive amounts of pensions the company was responsible for.
For years, Hayes Lemmerz paid into the Public Benefits Guarantee Corp., an agency createdto help companies pay for their employees' pensions, according to a PBGC document.
The PBGC is a government agency. But it's funded by the premiums companies pay into it, according to its website - and under law, it cannot use taxpayer money to help companies cover pensions.
2 Claim: Clawson eliminated jobs
Between Clawson's start at the company and 2007, seven domestic plants closed, according to Hayes Lemmerz's website. Each had between 150 and 300 employees, Clawson said.
Several other plants that made things other than aluminum wheels were sold.
About 160 people were employed at a Howell Township, Mich., plant closed by Hayes Lemmerz in 2004, according to information from the Howell Chamber of Commerce. That made it just one employer among many in the town, including a large health system and several other manufacturers that closed, according to the township's website. Howell Township had 6,702 residents at the 2010 census.
Officials in several other towns where Hayes Lemmerz closed plants either did not return calls seeking comment or did not remember the closures.
In that same period, nine plants opened overseas, including in Thailand, Brazil, India, Russia, Germany and South Africa. In one instance, a Georgia plant was closed and moved to Mexico. But Clawson rejects the idea his company was involved in moving jobs outside the U.S. only to ship back cheaper parts from overseas.
That plant was losing around $20 million a year and employed a small number of people, he said. Wheels created overseas did not, for the most part, return for sale in the U.S.
3 Claim: Clawson dropped the ball on safety
When Clawson took over in 2001, there were no safety managers in the plants, said Donald Walton, who in 2002 joined Hayes Lemmerz as director of operational excellence for the North America wheel group.
By 2003, management had begun rolling out an "operational excellence initiative," but the changes weren't yet drastic, Walton said.
In October of that year, employee Shawn Boone was killed, and two other employees severely injured, in an explosion, according to the federal Occupational Health and Safety Administration.
Two other people were killed in overseas Hayes Lemmerz facilities, according to OSHA. The company was fined $42,000.
The federal Chemical Safety Board found the factory had "inadequate housekeeping" in the foundry area and "insufficient maintenance" of the chip processing equipment, leading to the dust accumulation that led to the explosion.
Company leaders were not aware of the specific issue with dust, which caused the explosion, or the machines themselves, Clawson said.
The company immediately set out to learn more about the equipment used at the facilities.
Hayes Lemmerz became safer over the next few years. Boone's was the only U.S. death, and while OSHA inspections found some serious violations, there were no repeat or willful ones.
4 Claim: Clawson donated to a Democrat and used a lobbyist
According to fliers and television ads attacking Clawson, his tenure at Hayes Lemmerz included giving to a Democratic senator who supported the Affordable Care Act and using a Washington, D.C., lobbyist firm to help his company during bankruptcy.
Those claims are true. Clawson says those moves were made while he was CEO and before he considered running for office.
"It's my fiduciary responsibility to go see anybody and everybody that could potentially ... you know, my board is saying to me, 'Go see everybody you can,' which they should," he said.
Clawson gave U.S. Sen. Debbie Stabenow of Michigan $1,000 in May 2009. That was before she voted in favor of the Affordable Care Act.
The donation, given at a fundraiser, "was the quickest way to get in to see the senator," he said.
Clawson visited other political leaders where Hayes Lemmerz operated and hired a Washington, D.C., firm to get time with them.
"It's the only way to get in quick," he said.
5 Claim: Clawson benefited while the company went bankrupt
Opponents and ads have criticized Clawson's earnings as a CEO. And it is a lot of money - even Clawson agrees. "I made a lot of money. I feel very blessed," said Clawson.
Clawson's base pay ranged over the years from about $750,000 to about $900,000, about a third of his overall pay, according to Hayes Lemmerz proxy statements.
In 2006, Clawson was paid about $1.3 million in salary and bonuses. It was one of his smallest paydays.
In 2003, the year Hayes Lemmerz came out of bankruptcy, Clawson made, on paper, about $11 million. About $5.2 million of that was in stock options.
But much of that money is stock options and performance-based bonuses - or performance pay that, in Clawson's case, was based on safety ratings, customer satisfaction and the company's financial state.
So when the company entered Chapter 11 in 2001 and again in 2009, Clawson lost much of that. He did a $1.6 milion bonus after re-emergency from the first bankruptcy, in 2003.
He didn't walk away destitute when a Brazilian wheel company, Iochpe-Maxion, bought Hayes-Lemmerz in 2012. When the sale closed, the stocks Clawson and other managers earned after the company came out of its second restructuring converted to cash.
]]></text></news-item>