<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-BPX1-JC6P-C4NM"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Even in 1989, bitter opposition to medical waste incinerator</title><source>Standard-Examiner (Ogden, Utah)</source><author>Cimaron Neugebauer, Standard-Examiner, Ogden, Utah</author><text><![CDATA[March 30--Second of two parts
SUNDAY: Stericycle is looking forward to Tooele County and has finally begun using a public relations strategy.
MONDAY: How it started in North Salt Lake. Who was there first, and what did that mean?
NORTH SALT LAKE -- It's better to have one regulated medical waste incineration plant taking care of our waste than more than a dozen unregulated hospitals doing it, said the North Salt City Council in 1989.
Not everyone agreed, though.
"If [my constituents] don't want it, I don't want it either," said then-council member Carlin Jacobson.
Most of the land around the proposed area zoned for manufacturing were undeveloped and open fields. Despite concerns that burning toxins may be detrimental to other business owners, the community's air quality and its safety, the city council approved the build of the Stericycle plant as it was assured it would be a state-of-the-art facility that would comply with the strictest regulations.
How it started
Controversy began in 1989 when the North Salt Lake Planning Commission approved a conditional use permit for BFI Medical Waste, which was acquired by Stericycle in 1999, to open for business in the North Salt Lake Industrial Park. The commission felt BFI was properly placed in a light-industry zoned area. Residents and business owners couldn't have disagreed more. The city council held a non-required public hearing to allow residents to vent their concerns about the already issued green light for BFI.
Signed petitions with about 760 names opposed the plant, along with many phone calls to the city. One resident's letter stated approval of the plant, but the city "sentiment of the responses received [were] overwhelmingly against it," according to 1989 city council minutes.
At one meeting, Richard Harvey with Davis County Environmental Health spoke highly of the burn plant and told the city council he believed it would "be a very clean high-tech operation." When a city council member pressed him if he would be afraid to live next to the facility he said, "I would prefer not to live next door to a pollution producing plant."
One business owner told the city if the plant was built, large amounts of medical waste would be trucked into the community from other states to keep the plant operating at full capacity, and he was right.
Out of 7,200 tons of waste burned at the North Salt Lake facility in 2011, nearly 85 percent of it came from outside the state, according to a February report from the Utah Department of Health. Stericycle said the Utah plant disposes medical waste from about eight other states.
After a lengthy public debate lasting most of the year, that city council 25 years ago decided by a 3-2 vote to stand behind the original decision the planning commission had made.
'Who was here first?'
In 1992, BFI Medical Waste built the facility at 90 N. 1100 West. Seven years later it was bought out by Stericycle. It wasn't until about a decade after the plant first began burning medical waste that a residential home developer approached the city about a planned development known as Foxboro.
In 2003, the city grandfathered in Stericycle and rezoned the area surrounding the plant for mixed use. Young families looking for inexpensive and affordable land began building starter homes a few hundred feet from Utah's only regulated Hospital Medical Infectious Waste Incinerator.
It wasn't until 2012 that the city rezoned the entire undeveloped area to general commercial as part of its new master plan. The city was planning to have a future corridor that revolves around Center Street, including on- and off-ramps to Legacy Parkway.
"It was an attempt to really begin to make some changes in that portion of the city," North Salt Lake assistant city manager Ken Leetham said.
Contact reporter Cimaron Neugebauer at 801-625-4231 or cneugebauer@standard.net Follow him on Twitter at @CimaronNews.
___ (c)2014 the Standard-Examiner (Ogden, Utah) Visit the Standard-Examiner (Ogden, Utah) at www.standard.net Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>