<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-BNW1-J9YR-G00V"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Revolution within the revolution: Former Maoist rebels in Chhattisgarh talk about their hopes, fears and aspirations</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>ABHISHEK BHALLA</author><text><![CDATA[Armed with an INSAS rifle, Kamlu Ram Nureti alias Navin fled from the darkness of Abujmarh in Chattisgarh, a Maoist fortress, on the night of February 12, 2013 and reached Narayanpur.
His idea was to break free from a movement, which he joined at the age of 16, with a dream to change people's lives.
Though not a part of the rebel outfits military wing, he stole the rifle, as he knew it would fetch him Rs 1 lakh at the time of surrender.
His wife, also a Maoist, surrendered with him.
More than a year later, the 31-year-old rebel has turned into a family man: the couple has two daughters and a son and works closely with the police, providing valuable information on the activities of his former parent group, all the while fearing a brutal vengeance attack on his family.
The situation is the same for Ganda Ram alias Vinod and his wife Jaymati, another rebel couple who defected from the group as recently as January this year.
While Vinod was responsible for the group's cadre management, his wife was a part of the women guerilla squad. "We are scared for our lives. If they (Maoists) want, they can hunt us down," he explains.
Class divide
The fear-laden accounts of these former rebels reveal the inside story of a movement that is riven by internal differences, power struggle and a widening chasm between the leadership and foot soldiers, even as it mounts incessant guerilla warfare on the country's security forces.
Defected rebels like Navin have now become lead actors in the state's fight against the violent Maoist ideology, which is showing signs of internal rift.
"The top leadership look down upon the locals and consider them inferior. This is creating a class divide," he says. Signaling in the direction of Abujmarh, a hilly forest area, where the Gond tribals live, he says: "Adivasis are simple people and are being exploited by the big Naxal leaders."
Navin, who used to be the area secretary of the Maoists and also the president of its area jantana sarkar (revolutionary people's committee), claims that he can help the police in nabbing the Maoist master mind Ganapati.
"He is quite unassuming and roams around without a gunman. I can help them nab him," he says. Navin denounces the group's shady financial sources. "There is no accountability on the funds generated. While an amount of Rs 1 crore was raised from Abujmarh alone, more money is pouring in from other Indian cities and abroad," he says.
A statement attested by government estimates, which show that Maoists generate an annual revenue of Rs140 crore by way of extortion and illegal taxes. Accounts of differences within the movement have also been corroborated in the latest central committee report of the Maoists.
RK Vij, Additional Director General, Anti Naxal Operations, Chhattisgarh Police says interrogation of the surrendered and arrested rebels reveal disgruntlement within the ranks.
Growing might
The police are assisted in their operation by the renegade rebels.
Thirty-year-old Lachu Potai, Navin's former comrade, who claims to be a part of the Maoists guerilla contingent that ambushed the Border Security Force in 2011, provides inputs on rebel tactics to the cops.
According to Potai, the strategy of the Maoists is to outnumber the security forces through a combination of shock and surprise.
"Heavy firing followed by an explosion using an improvised device is the tactic that has been most successful," he says.
The rebels also loot weapons from the security forces and a nearby arms factory in Abujmarh apart from purchasing supplementary stocks from other insurgent groups across the country. Inter-state alliances between rebel outfits are common.
Potai was once assigned to take part in a high-level meeting in Kolkata. Arun Deo Gautam, IG, Bastar range, believes that the military capability of the rebels is increasing.
"They have sophisticated arms and are experts in making IEDS," he warns.
While the surrendered rebels are helping the police in anti-Naxal operations, the collective view among them is that the menace cannot be weeded out by bullets alone.
"The police should use us to win the confidence of the locals who trust us and educate the children," they say. Gaining local support remains the key in winning the regions war against the red rebels.
Carrot and stick to win over rebels
Covered by thick forests and spread across 1,500 square kilometers spanning over 200 villages, Bastar region in Chhattisgarh is regarded as a Maoist den with restricted entry for more than three decades.
However, with 13 rebels surrendering in Narayanpur district in the last one year and villagers from the region voting for the first time in several years during last year's assembly polls, the local administration has plenty to cheer about.
There have been close to 25 surrenders in the Bastar region in the last one year.
Amit Tukaram Kamble (pictured), an IPS officer of the 2009 batch has started a drive to ensure that the rebels lay down their arms. Pamphlets with happy faces of former rebels who lead a normal life after renouncing the path of violence is circulated in the region.
The happy faces are contrasted with gory images of rebels killed in police operations.
"The idea is to show them the dichotomy of life," says Kamble. Referring to a Marxist theory he says, "Arrest is only a victory over the body. But getting them to surrender means we have won over the spirit. There cannot be a more satisfying feeling," the young officer says.
Pointing at the picture of Sarita, one of the slain rebels, the SP said he recovered a copy of the pamphlet from her bag after she was killed.
"Perhaps she was thinking of laying down arms," he says.
Kamble calls this a "psychological warfare."
In order to make the surrender more attractive, Abujmarh Vikas Pradhikaran, a local agency is building 100 houses for the families of surrendered Maoists.
In January this year, a senior Maoist leader from Chhattisgarh GVK Prasad surrendered with his wife Santhoshi in Andhra Pradesh.
A senior leader can get economic incentives of up to Rs 20-25 lakh, combining the amount offered by the state and central governments.
While every state has different economic incentives, the centre enhanced the economic packages for the surrendered Maoists, last year.
The amount given was increased from the Rs 10,000 to up to Rs 2.5 lakh along with a bonus of Rs 25,000 for handing over sophisticated weapons.
There is also a monthly stipend of Rs 4,000 on offer for a period of three years.
The amount is in addition to what the Naxal-hit states are offering.
A total of 1,538 Maoists have surrendered so far, according to the union home ministry. H
owever, last year's surrender figure of 283 was lower than the previous years.
In 2012, 445 Maoists surrendered and in 2011 the number was 394.
In addition to housing and economic incentives, efforts are also on to rehabilitate the surrendered Maoists by providing them jobs.
]]></text></news-item>