<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-C411-F0JP-W34C"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Letters to the editor</title><source>The Australian</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TALKING POINT The difference between harmful acts and opinion As a personal addendum to the excellent pieces by Gabriel Sassoon, Brendan O'Neill and the editorial ("Smothering free exchange of ideas a dangerous path," 29-30/3), I am grateful to my parents for bringing me here after suffering under Nazi and then Soviet totalitarian regimes in Hungary.
In my youth I valued freedom of speech above all other values. Although a Jewish Holocaust survivor, I opposed the criminalisation of statements by Holocaust deniers.
Now in my old age, I am disturbed by the efforts of those who wish to criminalise rather than just ridiculing and shaming so-call hate speech. A robust freedom of speech distinguishes criminal acts from abhorrent opinions. Australians who ignore the difference between harmful acts and mere opinions, eroding freedom of speech will unwittingly create a velvet totalitarianism in our society.
John J. Furedy, Darling Point, NSW
THERE are many areas of our society where unfavourable comment can give offence and on occasion that offence can be very hurtful. The problem with section 18C is that offence can range to the trivial to the extreme. Some of the best comedians are Jewish and they make jokes about Jewish society - which could give offence to some - but would never consider a joke relating to the Holocaust.
Section 18C paints a picture that is either black or white where, in fact, there are many shades of grey. Where offence is directed to hurt an individual, such offence is wrong. An offence directed at an entire community is equally wrong.
There is surely a middle ground where individuals receive some protection from offence and there are some subjects which are beyond the pale and may need to be defined.
John Downing, Ringwood North, Vic
IF the Abbott government's new broad provisions of the Racial Discrimination Act will prohibit the incitement of racial hatred and threats of physical harm, will it also prohibit the incitement to hatred of non-believers, infidels and crusaders, and threats of death to those who do not follow the Islamic teachings?
D. Thompson, Middle Ridge, Qld
MELBOURNE University law professor Mark McMillan, one of the nine Aborigines who successfully had two of my columns banned by the Federal Court, says of the reaction: "I was accused of being a pedophile, and these were not just responses of Andrew Bolt ("Act failing to stop black-on-black racism" (29-30/3.) This is grossly offensive and utterly false. I have never made any such accusation and would condemn anyone who did. I have in the past publicly attacked prominent journalists, authors and politicians who tried to smear gays as closet pedophiles, and I find it outrageous that a professor of law would defame me by falsely suggesting I did something so vile myself.
Andrew Bolt, Melbourne, Vic
THIS argument is not about Andrew Bolt ("A free and vigorous debate would be the best avenue for Bolt's detractors", 29-30/3), it was always about a government entitlement system being allegedly rorted, for that is what Bolt was indicating.
The fact that debate has been effectively stopped by legislation should be a worry for everyone. Those involved in this "solution" will first look to legislation to silence every other criticism of government policy. Legislation to prohibit debate is obviously not democracy.
Neville Wright, Kilcunda, Vic
IN urging the repeal of all hate speech laws, Brendan O'Neill has made easily the best contribution yet in the freedom of speech debate. The idea that bigotry can be legislated away is absurd. Look at how much taxpayers' money is wasted on this nonsense - just to appease a minority of politically correct devotees.
Like many others, I have been reviled from time to time but it causes me no loss of sleep. My attackers have every right to express an opinion on my views, just as I have the right to express one on theirs.
Richard Congram, Mosman, NSW
Titles could devalue the significance of future Order awards I FIND myself in accord with your editorial ("Restoring knights and dames", 27/3), in criticism of Prime Minister Tony Abbott's rash move to restore archaic titles in 21st-century Australia. Even his mentor John Howard showed more sense than to take this kind of nostalgic step, and reportedly now sees it as unwise.
Taken with little consultation even within the Coalition, this decision will confuse and devalue the significance of our Order of Australia award system, and future recipients of such new titles may become embarrassed at the disdain and satire with which they could be treated.
Geoff D. Bolton, Nowra, NSW
THE anti-knights and dames crowd mistake titles as the adoption of a certain class structure. It is more to do with achievement, not social status, and the titles are not inherited, but awarded. So there's no need to panic about antiquated titles for our gentry.
Like Gerard Henderson, I voted for an Australian republic in 1999, believing that although the Queen does a magnificent job for Britain, we should have an outstanding Australian as our head of state.
That's just as long as we don't start handing them out willy-nilly to footballers, pop stars, politicians and others in the business of self-promotion.
Robin Southey, Port Fairy, Vic
A better way on boats IT doesn't matter how many boats have or haven't arrived ("New phase as 100 days pass without boat", 29-30/3. That doesn't make what the government is doing right. And the Labor Party is no better on this issue.
We need a better way to deal with asylum-seekers instead of the cruel and racist policies we have had for several years.
If these people were fair-skinned and blue-eyed, we wouldn't be locking them up as we are now.
Margaret Ludowyk, Brunswick, Vic
A HUNDRED days without an illegal boat reaching our shores - now that's something to crow about. But don't expect any accolades from the Labor Party. It is too embarrassed to acknowledge this initial success which is just the first of many achievements to come from the Abbott government.
George Fishman, Vaucluse, NSW
Loss of wheat edge TRADE Minister Andrew Robb says the grain sector is benefiting enormously from market deregulation ("Robb tries to smooth waters on ADM deal", 29-30/3). In recent media reports, Neoh Soon Bin, managing director of Southeast Asian flour miller Soon Soon group, puts forward a different view.
He says that with the loss of our single desk, Australian wheat is cheaper, our quality is inconsistent, there is less reliable supply for customers and there is no unified information on crop quality or technical support for buyers.
In other words, Australia has lost its marketing edge due to the treachery of the Rudd government and the Liberal Party which abolished the single desk in June 2008 against the wishes of the majority of growers.
Jock Munro, Rankins Springs, NSW
Back to the Dark Ages THERE has been talk of Australia taking backward steps into medieval history. Perhaps the most striking example of this is Earth Hour, where participants forgo an hour of electrical lighting and step back into the Dark Ages in an effort to curb carbon dioxide emissions.
As with all forms of slacktivism, Earth Hour allows participants to feel good about doing something without the inconvenience of having to do anything. Rather than sitting in the dark, Australians should remind themselves of the advances in living standards delivered by technological progress, and recognise that solutions to environmental challenges can be found through research, development and innovation.
Luke Hughes, Redland Bay, Qld
Cricket's sternest test RELEGATED to the weather page was a most important cricket article ("CA backs the wrong man as cricket faces its sternest test", 29-30/3). The stars, their salaries, the tournaments and matches will amount to nothing unless the conduct of the game is given priority.
Gideon Haigh's thoughtful piece, following his previous work on governance and corruption in cricket, will be worth reflecting on in the years to come when cricket as we know it becomes a distant memory. Corrupt cricket will not be cricket at all unless it's addressed now.
Phillippa Power, Leura, NSW
LAST POST I'm completely pomped out for the foreseeable future This infusion of other-worldly splendour is much too rich for my peasant taste. A little bit of proper warning next time please, Mr Abbott.
David Hall, Labrador, Qld
At the rate of four knights a year, King Tony Abbott should have just enough for a round table by the end of his government's term.
Brian Sanaghan, West Preston, Vic
A right royal welcome to our prospective knights and dames. I write from London where some of my friends - having seen and heard Moonie Ponds's own Dame Edna and former cultural attache Sir Les Paterson - were under the mistaken belief that such estimable titles had never been abandoned downunder. They will be reassured.
John Kidd, Auchenflower, Qld
It seemed to me the knightly jousting target was actually Bill Shorten. A jocular response to a bizarre idea, with him ending up as the butt of the joke. The acceptance of the anachronistic title by his mother-in-law may deliver the punchline.
David Sankey, Alfords Point, NSW
I'm looking forward to Sir Boof Lehmann and Sir Grumpy Border to take their place among the pantheon of great Australian cricketers such as Sir The Don.
Deric Davidson, Bunbury, WA
There is little doubt that Labor recently ran one of the most dysfunctional governments in Australian history. Now that Labor is in opposition, the best it can do is play such childhood games as bait the Speaker.
Greg Kater, Sydney, NSW
Fairfax Media and our ABC seem unaware that convicted fraudster Michael Williamson was national Labor Party president in 2009-10 and a longstanding board member of the ACTU. A notable omission given the blanket coverage of Liberal MP Arthur Sinodinos appearing as a witness before ICAC with the commissioner indicating no adverse finding is likely.
John Shailer, East Lindfield, NSW
In Ross Fitzgerald's entertaining article ("Goodwill gets a side only so far - it's hatred that counts", 29/3), there is no prediction about which Collingwood player will be the first to receive a knighthood.
P.A. Smith, Mt Archer, Qld
Our submarines have sensitive sound detection equipment making them an ideal choice in the search for MH370's black box. Assuming some of our subs are in working order, they should be used now.Peter de Lepervanche, Clontarf, Qld
]]></text></news-item>