<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-CNS1-DYJJ-P3X0"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Guest Column: Hobby Lobby case about power, not faith</title><source>The Montgomery Advertiser (Alabama)</source><author>By, Gene Robinson</author><text><![CDATA[In 2003, I prepared for my consecration as a bishop by donning a bulletproof vest beneath my religious robes because of death threats from "good, religious people" who still believed that homosexual people are despicable in the eyes of God.
As an openly gay man, elected as an Episcopal bishop, I was reviled even by other bishops in my own church. I know something about religion-based discrimination.
A decade later, I am watching a remarkable phenomenon: Followers of Jesus pleading with the government to allow them to shun those they regard as "sinners." Arizona's recent attempt to make it a religious right to discriminate, and similar efforts in other states, would give businesses the right not to serve almost anyone, for almost any reason, as long as it involved a seriously held religious belief. Services of all kinds could be denied to anyone whom the provider judged to be living an immoral life, according to their brand of religion.
Jesus of Nazareth taught his followers to go the extra mile and to turn the other cheek. Imagine that same Jesus casting his gaze on many of his followers who are seeking the government's permission to discriminate against people of whom they disapprove, to narrow their rights, and to place themselves above the laws meant to protect the vulnerable. The shortest verse in the Bible comes to mind: "Jesus wept."
Gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender people know who the crafters of these laws have in mind. We know that those who oppose the full and equal rights of LGBT people seek to reclaim the right to discriminate that they are losing at the ballot box, in courts and in public opinion polls.
Christians are not refusing to cater weddings of adulterers or gossips (condemned by name in Scripture), nor are they claiming that their religious beliefs are offended by photographing the wedding of someone who is greedy or a legislator who cuts food stamp funding. But bake a wedding cake for two people of the same gender, who love each other and are willing to take on the life-long commitment of marriage? This kind of Christian is not only offended but also claims to be a victim.
That argument should sound familiar. Last week, the Supreme Court heard arguments by Hobby Lobby, a nationwide chain of craft stores, asking the court for the right to discriminate against their employees who are entitled to reproductive health care under the Affordable Care Act. I know that Hobby Lobby's owner family, the Greens, are deeply religious people, and I respect their beliefs.
They object to certain forms of birth control, claiming they constitute abortion (a "fact" disputed by much of the medical community). The Greens claim that corporations, through their owners, have freedom of religion - a very slippery slope. But should the entire company and its 14,000 employees be held hostage by the beliefs of its owners?
We know that most American women, regardless of what religion they are, use contraception at some point in their lives. As a pastor, I have seen firsthand what a gift it is to be able to control when and whether one has a child. It offers women some measure of control over their lives.
Sometimes, even for a bishop, it's embarrassing to be a Christian. Not that I'm embarrassed by Jesus, whose life was spent caring and advocating for the marginalized, and whom I believe to be the perfect revelation of God. I'm just sometimes embarrassed to be associated with others who claim to follow him.
The Jesus I follow always stood with the poor and powerless - and trust me, this struggle is about power. Whether the issue touches women or gays and lesbians, our religion should be about more love, not less; more dignity, not less.
The Supreme Court's rulings on gay rights, with Justice Anthony Kennedy's leadership, have been on this path for more than a decade. The court has made great strides in recognizing the worth and dignity of women and LGBT Americans. A decision in favor of Hobby Lobby would change that direction.
It would not be a victory for religious freedom, but a victory for discrimination and a repudiation of the vital progress the court has made in securing equal justice for all.
Gene Robinson is the IX Episcopal bishop of New Hampshire.
]]></text></news-item>