<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-CWG1-JD3N-54JS"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Appalled by Pell</title><source>Herald Sun (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[THANK you, Wendy Tuohy, for your succinct and damning article on Cardinal George Pell ("Pell makes it so hard to forgive", Opinion, Mar 27).
Having sat for almost five hours recently while Cardinal Pell was questioned by the royal commission, I was amazed by his cold indifference to the evidence presented.
This week he offered an apology to one of the victims of this Australian horror story.
He can now trundle off to Vatican City to take control of the inestimable wealth of the Catholic Church - safe and protected from the questions and criticism of our media and all those victims left in the wake of paedophile priests.
Edwina Green, St Kilda
End child detentions THE Australian Human Rights Commission's findings from its national inquiry into children in immigration detention are as heartbreaking as they are unsurprising.
Children do not belong in prison.
Jesuit Social Services has many years experience supporting young people and adults leaving prison, and even for adults, the prison experience is dehumanising and often terrifying.
It offends every principle of decency and humanity that we would inflict this harm on children. How we treat children is surely the test of our nation's character and soul.
We call upon our Government to release all children from detention into the community immediately.
Julie Edwards, CEO, Jesuit Social Services
Dons' queries remain REVELATIONS concerning Essendon Football Club employees being the subject of undocumented injections of an unknown substance in the workplace in a systematic program of assumed performance enhancement caused me to contact the Victorian WorkCover Authority.
After nearly three months of persistent inquiry, having pursued this matter with the VWA, my local member of Parliament, the State Attorney General and the Premier, an answer from the Assistant Treasurer was finally forthcoming.
It would appear that the VWA has abrogated its statutory responsibilities, preferring to wait for the outcome of the ASADA investigation before "considering ASADA's findings when available".
Clearly there is a distinction to be made between sports doping and systemic breaches of the Occupational Health and Safety Act 2004. ASADA has confirmed in writing that there is nothing in the ASADA legislation that precludes any investigation by a state-based workplace OH&S authority.
I wonder if pressure has been applied by either the AFL and/or timid politicians to the VWA to preclude appropriate investigations into this matter.
Greg Angelo, Balwyn North
Blame AFL for crowds ROUND 1 AFL crowds were their lowest in nearly 20 years.
No "blockbusters" were scheduled in the split round and a total of 245,301 attended. Last year, the Round 1 total was just under 366,000. In a game that is growing and is in a healthy financial state, this figure was pathetic.
Andrew Demetriou must take responsibility.
W. De Lacy, Ringwood East
Tania Hird impresses I WAS offended that Paul Little said James Hird should "control those around him". I was delighted when Tania Hird said she found it offensive to suggest she would be "hauled" before anyone, i.e. the Essendon board. She is her own person and will not be pushed around.
Diane Parker, Warrnambool
Stand by your man FREE speech, when defending your husband, is one thing that should never be taken away. Marriage vows mean sticking by each other, in good times and in bad.
Graham Palmer, Seymour
HWT code of conduct The Herald and Weekly Times, publisher of the Herald Sun, aims for the highest editorial and ethical standards. All editorial staff are required to act in accordance with a strict code of conduct.
This has been updated and can be viewed on heraldsun.com.au. Just scroll down the right-hand side of our homepage to find it.
For the record The Herald Sun  is committed to accurate, fair and fearless publication of news and commentary. But we acknowledge and aim to promptly correct errors when they occur. Corrections, clarifications and explanations the newspaper wishes to make will appear in this space. If you are aware of an error in this newspaper contact editor@heraldsun.com.au The Herald Sun  is bound by the Standards of Practice of the Australian Press Council. If you believe the standards may have been breached, you may approach the Herald Sun itself or contact the council by email atinfo@presscouncil.org.auor by phone (02) 9261 1930.
]]></text></news-item>