<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVV-DWB1-DXY4-X0XV"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>The Mines Have Shut Down. The Miners Haven't.</title><source>The New York Times</source><author>By DANNY HAKIM. Maciek Nabrdalik and Jacek Rutkowski contributed reporting.</author><text><![CDATA[Down a homemade mine shaft in southwestern Poland, a would-be comedian sang in the faint glowing light.
The strains of ''Ob-La-Di, Ob-La-Da,'' in rhythm with a pick ax, rose up from eight yards underground.
The song stopped.
''A huge chunk of coal has fallen on my finger!'' the miner yelled up the shaft. ''Now I can't pick my nose!''
The sky was black and the stars blazed, especially the constellation Orion. In the nearby city of Walbrzych, the bells had just tolled. It was 9 p.m., the temperature was below freezing, the wind bitter. But for many miners here, in a region known as Lower Silesia, work was just beginning.
The practice of digging coal illegally is often called ''rathole mining.'' It is better known in places like India, or in South Africa, where illegal mining accidents recently killed five men. But it's also common in Lower Silesia, near the Czech border.
Poland is Europe's largest producer of hard coal, and both black and brown coal mines flourish in other parts of the country, from abundant mines in Upper Silesia to the north, to the giant open pit mine in Belchatow, in the east.
But while Germany, Europe's largest overall coal producer, is aggressively trying to encourage renewable energy sources, Poland has shown far less interest in finding alternatives. More than 88 percent of its electricity is powered by coal, and many people still use it to heat homes.
That dependence means that mining never stopped in Lower Silesia, despite the shuttering of industrial mines in the late 1990s. The mines were deemed to be unprofitable, as well as dangerous. Coal seams are found at steep angles in the region, making machinery hard to use. And hundreds of years of mining tapped out reserves.
''We started to make the switch from a communist economy to a market economy, and these places were not efficient enough for businesses to be interested in them on an industrial scale,'' said Pawel Mikusek, a spokesman for the state environmental ministry.
Those kinds of efficiencies helped make Poland an economic model of sorts among its post-Soviet neighbors, and countries like Bulgaria and Ukraine look at its growth rate over the last two decades with envy. But they also cost jobs in places like Walbrzych, where the mayor estimated the unemployment rate at about 15 percent. So unemployed miners continue to dig for black coal on their own. And for younger men here, rathole mining is the only kind of mining they have ever known.
Activists estimate that as many as 3,000 men are engaged in illegal mining in Lower Silesia, though local officials say they believe that the number is much lower. And while coal in Poland is relatively cheap, buying it on the black market here can be 30 or 40 percent cheaper than buying it legally.
A walk in a hilly area outside of town on a recent February night was treacherous. Makeshift mine shafts were all around, waiting to swallow up those unfamiliar with the terrain.
At least four groups of miners were working, one group of five just getting started around 11 p.m. Cars and trucks drove in, often with their lights off, to collect 30 sacks of coal at a time.
The men cracked jokes and told tales, like the one about a woman who for two sacks of coal will keep a miner warm at night. ''Is it worth the coal?'' one miner asked another.
At the same time, it was clear that this was tough work for often desperate men, and boys. Because it is illegal, and because many of the miners have been caught by the police and fined, they generally gave only their first names, if any at all.
''The whole of Walbrzych is being dug up,'' said Konrad, 22, who mined a hole that was remote enough that he could work it during the day. It was a little more than four yards deep, the walls about a yard apart, braced by about 20 birch logs. At the bottom, a light was powered by a car battery.
All of Konrad was covered in a soft brown dirt and black soot -- from his close-cropped blond hair to his once-white Asics sneakers.
Konrad, who grew up in an orphanage and did not get very far in school, worked with Tomasz, who was 17. Tomasz was down in the hole, hacking coal from the side of shaft. Then he loaded the coal into a plastic bucket tied to a rope, which Konrad pulled to the surface.
Tomasz was asked if he feared that the hole might collapse.
''You should just pray,'' he said. ''I do it every day.''
No Uniforms, No Parades
For about 15 years, Roman Janiszek, 51, worked in the coal mines of Walbrzych. He started mining when he was 20 or 21, in the early 1980s.
''Everybody had jobs and the town was full of coal mines and coking plants, and the industry was big,'' he said. ''What was nice about the good old days is that we were all respected.''
There were festivities on Dec. 4 to celebrate St. Barbara, the patron saint of miners. The miners wore fancy uniforms with plumed hats. During an interview at his small apartment, Mr. Janiszek insisted on putting on his old black uniform with a white-feathered cap. ''Lots of orders were pinned to our chests,'' he explained. ''We all wore them with pride.''
Then the mines closed.
''We all lost our jobs, thousands of people, just like that, onto the street,'' Mr. Janiszek recalled. ''There was this idea that the coal mines were not profitable. The decision came from Warsaw; they all did it in haste.''
He hit the road. He picked grapes in Austria, harvested nuts and watermelons in Greece, worked on a pig farm in Switzerland. Eventually, he was deported back to Poland, penniless. He ran into an old apprentice who was working in the illegal rathole mines.
''He says, 'Well, Roman, come with us and see what it looks like, see how it's done,' '' Mr. Janiszek recalled. ''And I said to him, 'O.K., I'll do it.' ''
So began a second life as a miner. There were no uniforms this time, and no parades. After a few years, he became an activist who organized protests on behalf of the miners. He wants the local police to stop harassing the miners and has hopes to make the work legitimate again. He was co-founder of an activist group with Grzegorz Walowski, 34, a former rathole miner who is now a doctoral student. Mr. Walowski studies advanced technologies like coal gasification, which can turn coal into gas without even taking it out of the ground.
''I can see a special role for the miners working now,'' Mr. Walowski said. ''They have an expert knowledge of where the coal is, and this is not so easy.''
It is unclear if such technologies will be cost-effective, but with Poland's hunger for coal exceeding its production, the central government recently licensed an Australian company, Balamara Resources, to conduct research in Lower Silesia to determine whether mines could be reopened. The project is expected to take another couple of years to complete.
During a tour of the city, Mr. Janiszek stopped at an old slag pile. He has tried his hand at acting, and he has a theatrical flair.
Standing atop the pile, the city stretching out in the distance, he held up a piece of coal.
''This piece of coal testifies to the fact that there used to be coal in Walbrzych, there is coal in Walbrzych and there will be coal in Walbrzych,'' he said. ''Life goes on and we basically do the same thing we've always done. We just do it differently.''
''There will just be memories. There will be pictures. There will be photos and uniforms. Life goes on,'' he said. ''Amen.''
Chasing the Diggers
There is another man named Roman in Walbrzych. He is Roman Szelemej, the city's mayor. And he, too, has experience in the mines, but as a doctor. Dr. Szelemej is a cardiologist who started his medical career in a clinic in one of the mine complexes. He is a former hospital executive with a view of the wider world. A sister lives in New Jersey, and he has two daughters in London. Since taking office in 2011, he has been trying to address a fundamental question: What do you do with a coal town where coal mining is no longer legal?
Walbrzych, a city of about 120,000, sits in a part of Lower Silesia that belonged to Germany before World War II. Coal mining has been going on for hundreds of years here. It's a town that looks better from afar, nestled among woodlands, than up close. Downtown, you can find old men carrying buckets of coal up flights of stairs to heat their flats.
Dr. Szelemej is adamant that the city needs to look beyond coal. And he lamented the ''P.R. problems'' brought by ''the diggers,'' as he called them.
''This is why you are coming here,'' he told me. ''I am happy to have you here, but you are here because of diggers, not because you are interested in the personal career of the mayor of Walbrzych being a cardiologist, no way, so it's a price we still pay because of the history of this city. We are trying not to forget these problems. We know it exists. We try to solve it, but it's part of the image we would like to change.''
The mayor is focused on bringing new business to an economic development zone where Toyota and a number of auto suppliers have plants.
He sat in his office at City Hall, a three-story stone building with decorative turrets in a small town square; the noise of a jackhammer outside his window testified to the kind of development he is trying to bring to the town. There was a grandfather clock, a crucifix on one wall and his well-worn medical bag in a nearby chair.
After he took office, he visited some of the illegal mines and even talked to one of the miners. He described them as uneducated with an attitude ''typical for those people who simply prefer to be, let's say, free.''
''It's much easier than to go to the Toyota factory and work from 7:30 up to 5:30 or 6:30, regularly, day after day,'' he said. Mining was hard work, he said, but also easier in a way than staying with a steady job.
Wojciech Suwala, a professor at the AGH University of Science and Technology in Krakow, said that ''the income from this mining is very high,'' relatively speaking. He said he had heard that middlemen who take coal from these miners could make 10,000 zlotys a month, or about $3,300, though the miners themselves make much less than that.
''This is a good opportunity for the men to earn money, and there is no burden of social security, health care, etc., and it's quite well organized,'' Mr. Suwala said. ''And the punishment is low, and it's not preventing them from doing it.''
Dr. Szelemej, however, is committed to putting a stop to it.
''It's dangerous. It's criminal. It's illegal. It's destroying forests, destroying nature,'' he said, adding: ''There is no future for the coal industry here. It is closed. No more.''
But Dr. Szelemej acknowledges that there are limits in his administration's efforts to chase off the diggers. His predecessors all tried to stop it, and he said he had redoubled efforts. Still, he said, ''I can't use the whole police force.'' There are other problems to address in the city: car accidents, drugs, domestic violence. And so the digging goes on.
'I Have to Work Here'
Back out at the mines, Konrad and Tomasz are still at work as the sun fades in the sky. ''I work here, I kind of like working here, but I have to work here,'' Konrad said. ''It's definitely better working here than going and stealing something.''
They have been digging this hole for three or four months. Sometimes it caves in, and so they dig again.
''After a heavy rain, the whole thing may collapse,'' Konrad said, ''and then we spend up to two weeks just excavating it back.''
There are other setbacks. Two months ago, Konrad was caught by the police and fined 550 zlotys, or about $180, which amounted to a week's work. But if you do not pay, you are jailed.
They can dig out two metric tons of coal per day, surrounding the hole itself with a wall of sacks. Who buys it? ''Everybody,'' Konrad says. The miners sell either to middlemen, or directly to townspeople. Between hauling bags, Konrad fielded a call from an elderly customer on his cellphone.
Down in the hole, meanwhile, Tomasz said there was a certain peace to the work, despite the risks and the narrow escapes from cave-ins. ''It's like a retreat. It's so quiet, calm,'' he said. ''You're here, on your own.''
http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/30/business/energy-environment/the-mines-have-shut-down-the-miners-havent.html
]]></text></news-item>