<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVW-JP01-F08V-60WS"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Law firm that cleared Christie thrives on tax dollars  It's one of several with ties to Gov. flourishing on his watch, records reveal </title><source>The Star-Ledger (Newark, New Jersey)</source><author>Christopher Baxter, STAR-LEDGER STAFF</author><text><![CDATA[The private law firm that conducted an internal review of Gov. Chris Christie's office in response to the George Washington Bridge scandal raked in $3.1 million from state taxpayers last year to represent the administration in its uphill battle to legalize sports betting, records obtained by The Star-Ledger show.
Gibson, Dunn & Crutcher was the second-highest paid law firm by the Attorney General's Office in 2013, according to the records. Topping the list was Jackson, Gilmour & Dobbs, of Houston, which took home $6.1 million for its work on the Passaic River cleanup.
The Los-Angeles-based Gibson, Dunn & Crutcher, which on Thursday cleared Christie of wrongdoing in the bridge scandal and has reportedly been paid more than $1 million for that review, was among several law firms with ties to the governor that have thrived under his administration, the records show.
McElroy, Deutsch, Mulvaney & Carpenter, which has been home to several Christie allies, collected $1.9 million to rank third, the records show. Wolff & Samson, the law firm of David Samson, who resigned as chairman of the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey on Friday, ranked 10th with $568,738. The governor's former firm, Dughi, Hewit & Domalewski, ranked 12th with $531,433.
In total, private law firms banked $29 million from taxpayers last year, the most since at least 2008 and the third-straight increase, according to records provided under the state Open Public Records Act.
The Attorney General's Office has long hired private firms to supplement its hundreds of civil attorneys to help with everything from medical malpractice claims to complex financial deals when it has a conflict of interest, needs special expertise or doesn't have the manpower.
The use of Gibson, Dunn & Crutcher under Christie began last year, when the governor, with the support of leaders of the Democratic-controlled Legislature, made a major push to defend a state law legalizing sports betting, which could be the key to revitalizing Atlantic City.
Christie is close friends with a partner at the firm, Debra Wong Yang, who, like Christie, was appointed a U.S. attorney by former President George W. Bush. The two have gone on vacation with each other's families, and Christie steered Yang a lucrative contract while U.S. attorney.
Another attorney with the firm, Theodore Olson -- a former U.S. solicitor general who represented Bush during the 2000 Florida presidential recount -- took the lead on defending the law allowing sports betting against a challenge by the NCAA and the major pro sports leagues.
But the law was blocked by a federal judge early last year, and that ruling was later upheld on appeal. The state has petitioned the U.S. Supreme Court to take up the case, but a decision by the court has not yet been made.
BRIDGE SCANDAL
Work for Gibson, Dunn & Crutcher continued into this year when the firm was hired by the state Attorney General's Office on behalf of Christie to conduct an internal review of his office, determine who was involved in the September George Washington Bridge lane closings and make recommendations.
A report issued Thursday by the firm concluded Christie played no role in the scandal and neither did anyone in his office other than Bridget Anne Kelly, a former deputy chief of staff whom he fired after an email emerged from her stating, "Time for some traffic problems in Fort Lee."
Assemblyman John Wisniewski (D-Middlesex), co-chairman of the legislative committee investigating the lane closures, said in light of Gibson, Dunn & Crutcher's lucrative new arrangement with the state, "they're certainly going to be very careful about biting the hand that feeds them."
When asked about his past relationships with lawyers for Gibson, Dunn & Crutcher at a Statehouse news conference on Friday, Christie said: "After seven years as U.S. attorney and nearly five years as governor, there's probably not a major law firm in this country that I don't have some relationship with. ... No matter who I chose to do this, questions would be raised from some quarters as to some people's objectivity."
The lawyer who led the review, Randy Mastro, on Thursday said the firm's prior work for the state had no influence on its conclusions in the bridge matter.
A spokesman for the Attorney General's Office, Leland Moore, said in a statement that "private law firms are selected based on many factors including experience, what size firm is needed and where the case is venued, to name a few."
A 2012 Star-Ledger analysis showed firms with ties to Christie had thrived in the first half of his first term, while those with ties to his predecessor, former Democratic Gov. Jon Corzine, had seen their work fall off dramatically.
Moore said the amount paid last year for help from private attorneys would have been similar to 2012 without the sports betting litigation and a push to resolve a Passaic River pollution case, which brought the state two settlements totaling about $165 million. "Sometimes it takes money to make money," he said.
The Passaic River case boosted the amount of money the office won through litigation last year to more than $300 million, the most since at least 2006.
OTHER LAWSUITS
The records also show the Attorney General's Office paid out $77.7 million in 2013 -- the most since at least 2006 -- to resolve lawsuits filed against the state.
Medical malpractice topped the list of payouts by the state in settlements and judgments last year, records show.
The largest, $7.5 million, went to Elda and Leovardo Martinez of New Brunswick, who sued in 2010 claiming their infant son suffered brain and other injuries as a result of inadequate care in 2004 while at Robert Wood Johnson University Hospital. The state paid out $5 million in each of two other cases alleging malpractice by doctors and others with the University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey.
The state also paid $3.47 million to Christopher Sarao of Sandyston, an NJ Transit worker who was driving a train that struck a tree that had fallen on tracks in 2008, as well as $2 million to Jason Cartwright of Willingboro, who was also injured while working for the agency.
And the state paid $3 million to Natasha Aeriel of Newark and the parents of Iofemi Hightower, Dashon Harvey and Terrance Aeriel, who sued in 2008 claiming the state failed to properly secure and guard the schoolyard at Mount Vernon Elementary School in Newark. Hightower, Harvey and Terrance Aeriel were murdered "execution style" there in 2007, and Natasha Aeriel was shot in the head but survived.
Moore said payouts in lawsuits against the state's departments, agencies and employees were dictated by the number of cases resolved last year and the facts of each dispute, noting the office closed "a number of cases that had been pending for several years" as well as several new cases. Most of the cases resolved were from 2010-12, records show.
Christopher Baxter: (609) 989-0322 or cbaxter@starledger.com
]]></text></news-item>