<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVW-N6P1-JD6S-R259"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Water summit in Lynchburg looks toward raising the level of commitment to James River</title><source>The News &amp; Advance (Lynchburg, Virginia)</source><author>Alex Rohr</author><text><![CDATA[On the bridge above on a not-quite-cold weekday afternoon, walkers, joggers and runners traverse the James River Heritage Trail near downtown Lynchburg while snow melts slowly beneath their feet, creating puddles on the wood path.
Below on one of the bridge's ballasts, a rabbit with X's over its eyes and "2014" are spray-painted in pink over faded black graffiti.
As time and weather wear the paint, it will bleed into the waterway. So will the puddles above, a piece of blue tarp in the nearby mud and an empty Capri Sun packet left on the bank. Floating in the James, the refuse will join discharge from wastewater treatment plants, storm water from city streets and animal excrement from farms upstream.
Efforts to handle the variety of waste in the James, its effect on the river, and the future of drinking water in the region were highlighted at the Lynchburg Water Summit held Saturday at Lynchburg College.
The event - organized by the Central Virginia Master Naturalists, the local chapter of a nonprofit conservation group - started as the organization's annual lecture to follow last year's engagement on sustainable landscaping.
After deciding on New York Times-bestselling author Charles Fishman to speak about his book "The Big Thirst" for the yearly lecture, the idea spouted streams that converged into the summit, which included talks by state and local officials, nonprofit conservation groups and scientists.
"The Big Thirst" examines the difficulties faced throughout the world from diminishing water sources as climate conditions change, and what can be done to address individual problems.
Fishman said the water summit - along with disasters such as California's ongoing four-year drought, the January chemical spill in West Virginia's Elk River and the Dan River coal ash spill in February - are opportunities to discuss dwindling clean water resources.
"The whole point is that when something significant happens that causes people to pay attention to water, it's a great moment for people who are paying attention to the water system to say, 'let's take advantage of this and change peoples' habits,'" Fishman said in an interview.
As clean water sources fade, he said, there is a need to change people's "water consciousness" even in area's such as Lynchburg that have plenty of water.
"A community like Lynchburg, I suspect some people actually know where their water comes from ... It's remarkable, most people in the country turn on the tap and have no idea where that water came from and they have no idea where it goes when it leaves," Fishman said.
He said while Lynchburg is "relatively water wealthy" - with the Pedlar Reservoir in Amherst County as its main source and the James River as a steady backup - compared to many cities, its residents should be looking at the water in terms of protecting its quality and using the resource.
"There's plenty of water around. That does not mean you should not pay attention to water. It means you should pay attention to it in a different way," he said in the interview.
In water-wealthy areas, he said, residents should be concerned less with conserving water, but they should concentrate on how to best use the water.
Throughout the summit, public officials, academics, nonprofits and private citizens mingled to discuss water-related interests, which included efforts to ban hydraulic fracturing as a method of extracting oil and gas and working to nurture and plant trees in the city. Organizers hope discussion would lead to progress.
"It's not just about getting knowledge in your head, it's about doing something," said Bea Stryker, of the Central Virginia Master Naturalists.
One idea speakers mentioned throughout the event was the responsibility each person holds to those upstream and downstream to maintain a viable ecosystem.
"The James River is really a reflection of all the streams and creeks that flow into it. If we have an unhealthy James River, it means we have some problems in the tributaries," said Bill Street, the chief financial officer of the James River Association, in an interview.
Street spoke Saturday about the "State of the James River," a report released every two years by the association. It analyzes the river's overall health by examining benchmarks in wildlife, habitat, pollution and river protection, and restoration.
The report, last released in October, gave the James a "C" grade or 53 percent, up 2 percent from 2011.
"There are two key conclusions from the report. One is that we have made some tremendous progress and the commitment and investment that has been made in addressing wastewater is really showing some results and certainly Lynchburg is a key part of that. So that's showing some great benefits for the health of the river and how communities are able to enjoy it," said Street in a recent interview on the phone from his office in Richmond.
"The other piece is that we still have a good long ways to go, particularly when it comes to sediment pollution and other pollution that runs off the land."
Sediment pollution occurs when storm water washes exposed dirt into the river.
For example, last week at Percival's Island across from downtown Lynchburg, snow and ice melted on the banks of the James. Some of that water will drain into the river, but much of it is naturally soaked up by the trees and brush, called a riparian buffer.
In areas in which the buffer is removed - such as land being developed or a field left fallow, that water and whatever dirt, chemicals or trash it drags with it, end up in the river.
The report gave sediment pollution a score of 4 percent for the length of the James and its tributaries. The score hasn't improved in 20 years, according to the report.
Street said the James River is at a significant transition point since the river was shut down to fishing of any sort for 13 years starting in the late '70s.
"We've made a lot of progress in those regards and the river now is much healthier than where it was. Communities are starting to see it as a major emphasis and an asset for their region. It's at a time where we really need to figure out a way to make greater progress."
New storm-water regulations aim to decrease runoff, so precipitation soaks into the dirt. Soil and plants can act to cleanse the precipitation before it soaks deeper to become groundwater. State and local grants have also been developed to help farmers voluntarily prevent agriculture runoff and pollution from animal waste.
With a ways to go in developing more sustainable utility and environmental practices, attendees said the summit was a good opportunity to share problems and solutions from the individual perspective to the international.
Street summed up that ideal in the relation to the James River that begins with the headwaters of the Cowpasture and Jackson rivers in Bath and Highland counties and flows by Richmond and into the Chesapeake Bay.
"What we need to realize is anyone who lives on or around the James, we're all part of the problem, but we all can be part of the solution as well."
]]></text></news-item>