<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVW-9SX1-DYR7-C010"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Women charge bias and harassment in suit against jeweler</title><source>International New York Times</source><author>SUSAN ANTILLA</author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
Among glittering diamonds and shining gemstones, Dawn Souto-Coons loved being in what she called ''the business of romance,'' selling engagement rings to smiling couples at a Jared jewelry store in Florida.
But her passion for the job crumbled one day in 2005. As she filed a form, she came across paperwork for a recently hired co-worker. She found the new salesperson, a man who had no retail jewelry experience, was making $15 an hour - over $1.50 more an hour than the woman who was the store's top seller.
She checked another file, and then another, until she had reviewed the records of each of the dozen or so sales staff members. Almost all of the men, recalled Ms. Souto-Coons, then an assistant manager, were making more per hour than the women.
''I was so mad,'' she said. ''It was just an old boys' club.''
Today Ms. Souto-Coons, 55, is among 12 women in a suit against Sterling Jewelers, parent of 12 chains in the United States, including Jared the Galleria of Jewelry and Kay Jewelers. Sterling, the largest retail jewelry company in the United States by sales, is accused of gender discrimination in its pay and promotion practices since 2003.
And the accusations go further, portraying a workplace where sexual harassment and vulgar behavior left some plaintiffs feeling violated.
If the class is certified, about 44,000 current and former Sterling sales employees, from store managers to sales associates, would be offered the chance to join the plaintiffs' case, seeking back pay and punitive damages.
While the group would not be as big as the 1997 gender case against Publix Supermarkets, which included more than 100,000 women and was settled for $81.5 million, it would eclipse the 2004 gender case against Boeing, which included 29,000 women.
Even if the women are certified as a class, they must pursue their case against Sterling privately. According to company policies, employees must deal with cases through arbitration, not the courts.
For one plaintiff, Maria House, a former saleswoman at a Kay store in California, day-to-day life became grueling. After she would close a big sale, she said, an assistant manager would announce that he had a ''reward'' for her, opening his legs and telling her to sit on his lap.
''It used to bring me down to the point where I'd take a break to go outside in the mall and cry,'' said Ms. House, 56.
Sterling is fighting the case. David Bouffard, a Sterling spokesman, said in a statement that the company had investigated the claims in pay discrimination lawsuits by the plaintiffs and the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission.
''We believe that the facts show that they are without merit,'' he said.
As for the allegations of sexual harassment, Mr. Bouffard said that Sterling investigated and took action when employees raised concerns. He added that Sterling had disciplined employees who violated discrimination and harassment policies.
The case dates to 2005, when a saleswoman filed a pay complaint with the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission. The commission charged that Sterling had paid its female retail employees less than men and that it had denied women promotion opportunities. On March 10, a related lawsuit, first brought by the commission in 2008, was dismissed by a federal judge, who said the agency had not conducted a wide enough investigation of Sterling. The commission said it was disappointed and was considering its options.
Several months after Ms. Souto-Coons, who now operates a farm in Maryland, uncovered the pay information, she quit, taking copies of the records with her. Largely through word of mouth, plans for a lawsuit spread to upstate New York and California.
Sterling, based in Akron, Ohio, has 1,400 stores in 50 states and is a subsidiary of Signet Jewelers, which is based in Bermuda and has 500 stores in Britain. Signet agreed last month to purchase the rival jewelry chain Zale.
Since 1998, Sterling has required employees to agree to take disputes to private arbitration as a condition of employment. Companies are increasingly demanding that employees agree to arbitration, said Cliff Palefsky, an employment lawyer in San Francisco. More recently, firms are including clauses that prohibit bringing class-action complaints to arbitration, he said.
Sterling employees can get to arbitration only after they have filed a claim with its in-house resolution program. It received 474 complaints from 1998 to 2010. In that time, according to plaintiffs' legal filings, only two moved to an arbitration decision.
In their complaint, the plaintiffs said that grievances about pay and harassment were not taken seriously. Ms. Souto-Coons said in an interview that her boss once asked her to write out a complaint for the company about sexual harassment of women in the store by a male employee, but two days later, she learned the report had been watered down. Two weeks later, the man was promoted, she said.
Beyond the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission inquiry, in 2009 the civil rights division of the Department of Law and Public Safety in New Jersey found probable cause of discrimination at Sterling after a sales associate complained that a manager had rubbed up against her. Another employee told similar stories to company officials. Sterling told investigators that it had not been able to corroborate the allegations. But the state examined company officials' notes, and concluded that they ''knew or should have known'' about the harassment and that the company's harassment policies were ineffective.
In the pending case, the plaintiffs refer to sexual affairs involving the chief executive, Mark Light, and subordinates, and describe a company meeting when Mr. Light jumped into a swimming pool with female managers who were ''in various states of undress.''
Without referring to any specific employee, Mr. Bouffard, the Sterling spokesman, said that some of the allegations ''relate to personal, consensual relationships with individuals who have never raised a concern with the company, or involve situations that already have been thoroughly investigated and addressed.'' He did not respond to written questions about Mr. Light.
In their filings, the plaintiffs include a report from an expert who says that lower-level male employees may have modeled their behavior after that of senior executives. Upper management, the expert writes, created a ''climate and culture'' that devalued the work of female employees.
One situation noted in the complaint involves a rape case. A manager was assaulted by another manager in a Florida hotel room during an annual meeting in 2003. In the wake of that case, a third manager, the victim's hotel roommate and a witness, was fired, accused of withholding information from company management, according to a complaint she filed.
The dispute with the company is described in the roommate's 2004 lawsuit against Sterling. Months after the assault, the roommate was called to the firm's headquarters, 200 miles from where she worked, and asked personal questions about her sex life, according to her suit. Eight days later, she was fired. The woman sued for invasion of privacy and wrongful termination. Sterling won a court fight that kept her case in private arbitration. The case went to mediation and was settled.
Mr. Bouffard said that the company immediately fired the suspect. The man was convicted of rape and appealed. He later pleaded no contest to sexual battery.
Beyond the pay and harassment concerns, Mr. Bouffard said that women were well represented at Sterling, making up more than 70 percent of Sterling's sales force and assistant manager positions, and 60 percent of store manager positions.
''Fairness, equal opportunity and respect for our female employees - and all employees - is central to who we are,'' he said. Last week, Sterling announced that a woman, Denise Shaffer, would take on the newly created role of Signet treasurer.
In their case, however, the plaintiffs say women are in the minority in the most powerful jobs at Sterling. Since 2002, 24 people have held the title of vice president for regional operations, meaning they oversee store operations. Only six have been women, they say.
Lisa McConnell, a plaintiff and former manager at a Kay store in Indiana, said she was hopeful that the case would make a difference for women still at Sterling.
''There's a hole in my heart - I don't know if it will ever be filled - for the way I was treated,'' she said. ''But the purpose we are here for is to make sure this stops. We're working just as hard as the men, so give us our due.''
]]></text></news-item>