<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVW-0NF1-DXDT-600M"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Think your energy bills are a rip off? Britain's gas and electricity are actually among the cheapest in Europe</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>JON REES, FINANCIAL MAIL ON SUNDAY</author><text><![CDATA[New probe by Competition and Markets Authority into our billsEnergy firms warn squeeze could kill investment and spell blackoutsAverage dual fuel bill is £1,300 - up 24 per cent on 2010But Britain's gas and electricity bills are among Europe's cheapest
Energy bosses, the Government and consumers are at loggerheads over our gas and electricity bills.
Customers furious at years of rising prices have fought back by ditching big suppliers, MPs have sought to claim kudos with promises of taking on the energy firms, yet the big suppliers claim they are not profiteering.
So how expensive are our bills, why are they rising and will a crackdown on energy firms really lead to the threat of the lights going out? We take a look.
Energy bosses sound warning to the PM
Energy firms and the City are demanding the Government acts fast to make sure vital investment isn't withdrawn from the industry after last week's announcement of a competition review into prices.
Angela Knight, head of trade body Energy UK, said the Government had a two-month window during the consultation period before the inquiry formally begins to issue reassurance that investment in new power stations would not be at risk.
Meanwhile leading City analyst Peter Atherton warned that controversial claims by British Gas owner Centrica that delays in investment could put Britain at risk of power shortages were 'entirely correct'.
Knight said: 'We simply cannot afford to miss a beat in investment. There is planning permission for enough power stations to produce 23 gigawatts to be built right now in the UK, but only one is actually being built. That's due to uncertainty.'
In 2012, demand for electricity in the UK was 36GW on average, rising to 58GW at peak times. The Government reckons it needs £100 billion in investment to switch to a low-carbon, renewable energy market.
Sam Laidlaw, boss of Centrica, warned last week that the UK could stop building power stations and the gap between supply and demand could see lights go out - a claim which has led to him being accused of blackmailing the public.
City experts say the political row over energy has already affected investment, with Centrica's shares falling by 20 per cent since the issue exploded in September last year.
Calls for a vote on a price freeze, despite energy bills probe
Hopes that the review to be carried out by the Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) would take the heat out of the debate have proved forlorn, with Labour calling for a Parliamentary vote this week on an energy price freeze.
Shadow energy secretary Caroline Flint believes that the case for a freeze has strengthened after SSE announced last week it would put its standard prices for energy on hold until 2016.
But Knight insisted the actions of one firm did not mean all could or should freeze prices, adding that worst hit could be smaller firms who are being counted on to provide more competition.
'When SSE said it would freeze its prices by cutting investment in offshore wind and making hundreds redundant, that is a company making a decision based on its own circumstances,' she said. 'But an edict from on high that "one size fits all" is different. The big energy firms will find ways to hedge the cost of freezing prices, but the small firms will have problems doing that.'
Why are bills rising and could they fall?
The rising level of other costs which make up a bill must be looked at too, Knight said.
She added: 'Less than 40 per cent of a bill is made up of the wholesale cost of electricity. The rest is other costs like green levies, distribution costs etc. That must be looked at by the review.'
Atherton, an analyst with Liberum Capital, is also exasperated by political interference.
While agreeing with Laidlaw that Britain faces a long-term energy squeeze, he says in the past six months wholesale prices have fallen, meaning short-term prices could fall.
He added: 'Labour's call for a price freeze is absolutely bonkers. Don't they realise the wholesale price of gas has fallen and if anything they should be calling for a reduction not a price freeze? Labour wants to freeze prices at the top of the market.'
While the wholesale price of gas may be falling now, the long-term trend has been upwards. The wholesale price of gas has risen 240 per cent in the past decade while electricity has increased by 140 per cent according to regulator Ofgem.
A typical dual fuel bill stands at £1,300 a year, up 24 per cent since 2010. Wholesale prices account for about half the cost of an annual bill.
While concerned at the uncertainty created by the review, energy firms believe the CMA is the right body to carry out an investigation, as they consider Ofgem tainted by its close relationship with the Government.
One senior energy executive said: 'Ofgem is in conflict because it is charged with driving through decarbonisation of the economy. It cannot talk about the cost of green energy because they are the people who must deliver it. The CMA is less afraid.'
Will the CMA uncover a scandal? Is the energy market a cartel run by multinationals on their own behalf? Not if last week's market assessment is anything to go by, energy bosses say. They argue Ofgem itself said there was as yet no evidence of a breach of competition law.
One energy executive said: 'What were the barriers to entry for new entrants to the energy market? Not the Big Six, that's for sure.'
And through it all the industry likes to highlight the fact that Britain has just about the lowest energy bills in Europe.
It may just not feel like that.
]]></text></news-item>