<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVW-Y7Y1-JCDH-0009"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Six big questions that the British energy industry must answer: The prospect of unpopular electricity generators being taken to task by no fewer than three regulators has been widely welcomed. But as Terry Macalister reports, there are hard truths to tackle beyond ever-increasing utility bills</title><source>The Observer (England)</source><author>Terry Macalister</author><text><![CDATA[This is the biggest investigation of the British energy markets since privatisation and deregulation began in the 1980s. But the inquiry, triggered last week by a trio of watchdogs led by Ofgem and to be undertaken by the new Competition and Markets Authority (CMA) immediately sparked dire warnings that go to the heart of Britain's energy policy paralysis.
British Gas owner Centrica and a raft of analysts said a probe that could last two years will freeze investment in much-needed power stations and make blackouts more likely. Ofgem and energy and climate change secretary Ed Davey countered that a proper and full investigation would clear the air and rebuild trust among consumers.
But it will take more than a competition probe to restore faith in British energy policy. There are six questions the energy industry needs to answer as it tackles the wider issue of how Britain can modernise and decarbonise its power industry without pushing up prices and driving vast numbers of people into fuel poverty.
What do we do about the big six?
It is highly unlikely that Margaret Thatcher, the political cheerleader for deregulation and privatisation, envisaged a world where the state-owned Central Electricity Generating Board (CEGB) and the 12 regional English electricity boards would end up almost entirely in the hands of the largely foreign-owned companies we now know as the big six.
She would surely have blanched at the idea that a state-owned French company, Electricite de France (EDF), would hold major stakes in the supply sector and own most of the former CEGB's nuclear power stations.
British Gas was privatised in 1986 and has remained in UK hands but nearly 30 years later still controls 40% of the gas market, plus a further 25% of the electricity supply.
The privatised firms took over an industry which had seen plenty of investment, so the new owners felt able to concentrate on cost-cutting and neglect the building of new plants. This continued until they were encouraged to "dash for gas", building plants that eventually undermined the coal- and nuclear-powered stations to a point where the privatised British Energy - now part of EDF - had to be given a £ 3bn state bailout.
Power generating companies are no longer strictly separate from energy suppliers, which has allowed the big six to colonise and dominate both sectors, and stop new entrants expanding, say independent suppliers.
Regulator Ofgem has only recently begun trying in earnest to reform the sector, fining companies for breaking their licence agreements, be it for mis-selling, poor handling of complaints, or overcharging.
In the meantime a key measure of a healthy market - customers switching from one supplier to another - has failed to take root, while collective prices - and profits - have risen.
Customers have been infuriated by ever higher bills - pushed up by rising wholesale power prices, plus the cost of subsidising low-carbon energy projects such as windfarms - and politicians have been goaded into promises of action.
The Big Six have always argued that they are working harder than ever to increase efficiency, keep bills down and provide good customer service. They largely attribute the collapse in customer trust to others. They see themselves as an easy media whipping boy and the scapegoat of successive governments' unwillingness to explain to the public that the need to modernise and decarbonise the energy industry means higher prices whoever runs it. Some of them now see the competition inquiry as a chance to tell their side of the story.
How do we ensure energy security?
Most observers agree there is a need for more power stations in this country, be they gas-, nuclear- or wind-powered - gas plants have been mothballed or closed even as surplus capacity has dwindled.
The Department of Energy and Climate Change has spoken of the need for £ 100bn of new investment to cope with the coal-fired power stations that are being driven offline by new environmental regulations, or the many nuclear facilities which are coming to the end of their lives.
The state-owned CEGB, praised in 1983 by then-parliamentary under secretary of state the Earl of Avon as a "success story", could perhaps stand accused of overengineering and overcautiousness. It used to keep many power plants on standby and at one stage had 25% surplus capacity margins. That figure is now down to just 5%, which has led to fears about blackouts.
The need to tackle climate change means carbon-intensive oil and coal-fired stations must be phased out unless a largely unproven and expensive system of carbon capture and storage (CCS) can be rapidly introduced.
Meanwhile wind, solar and nuclear systems still require heavy subsidies to make them competitive, at a time when the country foresees huge future demand for electricity as it tries to move transport away from petrol-powered to electric cars. And all of this is comes at a time when our own North Sea oil and gas production is in fast decline.
But the best way of reducing the scale of the action needed is by reducing demand for power. Energy-efficiency can do this via well-insulated domestic households or less energy-intensive ways of doing business.
To frack or not to frack?
Hardline environmentalists would rule out shale gas extraction, on the grounds that it would keep Britain dependent on fossil fuels and stifle investment in low-carbon power. But many observers believe locally produced and lower-carbon shale would increase energy security and could be used to buy the time required move away from oil and coal.
Successful shale gas exploitation has had a dramatic impact on the energy scene in America, driving down domestic gas prices and triggering a new manufacturing boom. But Britain is at a very early stage, with little knowledge yet about how easy or lucrative it would be to get at the reserves that are believed to lie beneath regions such as Bowland, Lancashire.
David Cameron said last week that a shale gas industry could beat off any threat by Vladimir Putin to use Siberian gas as a political weapon. But it could take years to get a UK shale industry running profitably, and even Lord Browne, chairman of shale pioneer Cuadrilla Resources, believes it would have little impact on prices.
What about the nuclear option?
Nuclear power plants should be able to run at full capacity almost all the time - unlike wind or solar, which are weather-dependent. A number of new investors have come forward with plans to build new reactors on the sites of existing plants.
Hinkley Point C, proposed by EDF in Somerset, would generate 3,200MW, single-handedly supplying almost 7% of the country's electricity. That compares with 630MW of intermittent energy from the world's biggest offshore wind farm, the London Array off the coast of Kent. But EDF has been granted huge subsidies to build the low-carbon plant, which may yet be deemed in breach of competition policy by the European Commission.
The building of new reactors in France and Finland is running way over time and budget, and the issue of radioactive waste remains unresolved.
Will the lights go out?
The list of organisations and business leaders who have warned that Britain is heading for an energy crunch somewhere between now and 2020 is long and distinguished and includes Ofgem, the National Grid and, most recently, Centrica.
People have been predicting power failures for more than 10 years, but Sam Laidlaw, chief executive of the British Gas parent group, repeated the warning last week as the CMA inquiry was announced.
Ofgem and Ed Davey insist that the competition investigation will make investment easier, because it will come to a clear conclusion about whether the energy companies have been profiteering, and how a market that appears to keep new entrants out - or at least stop them expanding - can be restructured.
So will there be blackouts
this time around?
What is more likely is higher prices, as Dieter Helm, professor of energy policy at the University of Oxford and a former government adviser, told parliament in 2006: "People think insecurity of supply means will the lights go off, but that is not the issue. It is what happens just before the lights go off. It is volatility and sharp price rises."
Even if the big six are found guilty of profiteering and face fines, break-ups or other sanctions, the fact remains that the private sector will not invest in new low-carbon plants without significant subsidies.
It is unsustainable to keep loading the cost directly on to consumers through energy bills, as this hits the lowest-paid and most needy. The taxpayer is the obvious candidate to foot more of the bill, but this requires the government to be more open about the challenge ahead, and adjust its spending priorities accordingly.
Captions:
Margaret Thatcher stands on top of newly opened Torness nuclear reactor in 1989.
Hinkley Point A, right, and Hinkley Point B power station - soon to be joined by Hinkley Point C? Photograph
by Matt Cardy/Getty

]]></text></news-item>