<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BVW-N8H1-F12F-F002"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>An 'Arab Spring' scenario in Pakistan</title><source>Columnists India/Pak</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Islamabad, March 30 -- I am travelling, mother; blame is pointless. I am lost on a road not of our making. Forgive me for disobeying you. Blame the times, not me. I am leaving, and there is no return" were the final words written in a short note by Mohammed Bouazizi, an unemployed university graduate, who had been denied a permit to run a small fruit and vegetable stall. He set fire to himself - an act of defiance that sparked demonstrations and rioting throughout the country and eventually brought down the Government of Tunisia.
As usual the State treasury in Pakistan is reported empty; the country is at the edge of bankruptcy. Social welfare (even food supplementation for poor children and healthcare) has been gutted, and debt and inequality is unprecedented. And inflation? Don't worry. Nobody talks about it-a sudden silence. After all, common people are no longer able to buy anything. Pakistan has a remarkably high percentage of people living in what is called "deep poverty". It's always very sad when you see a lot of poor sick about their lives, how difficult it is, how difficult they are coping, looking after their families and so on. Millions are starving and suffering from hunger and malnutrition, millions are destitute, millions of men, women and children are steeped in ignorance; millions of people need schools, hospitals, and homes, millions need two time meal only to survive. People protesting peacefully against the rising cost of living state corruption and bad living conditions too are regularly beaten up and bloodied. Liberalization has also brought its own challenges which have created complex problems for families. We are continuing to hear of layoffs in factories and business houses, employees losing their jobs, companies downsizing. The industry is increasingly putting pressure on the workers to work long hours in order to compete globally. Materialism is driving more and more people to work harder and harder in order to achieve the desired standard of living. People will continue to lose their jobs, their friends and sometimes their families. Without a livelihood and with no hope for a better future, many people are finding themselves isolated in a society that values money over everything else. The divorce rate is constantly on the rise as parents fail to maintain a healthy balance between their work commitment and family lives.
For most of the poor people, the answer for their survival is crime or violence. People are forced to steal food, to break into each other's homes, or to somehow find a way to survive outside of the normally acceptable means of earning, or to commit suicide. We are able to trust each other less and less, become even more disconnected and fearful, and this will result in more policing, more military force being used against us as the Pakistani people become increasing violent and dangerous to each other. And the more threatening we are to each other, the less threatening we are to the corrupt and tax evader wealthy ruling elite who have created this mess in the first place. Here, money flows to the rich, as the needy borrow and pay the interest and pay huge indirect taxes. The people are forced to pay more to get less, just to maintain a basic standard of living with food, utilities, and gasoline. People aren't spending money on goods - they are spending it on essential items and services. The economic collapse has occurred quietly and stealthily.
This economic catastrophe is unprecedented in the history of independent Pakistan. The rulers of this poor country stand their luxurious properties with big villas, garages, golf and tennis courts, lakes, parks, even private zoo and helipads, which use to be the most guarded and secretive places in Pakistan. Their earnings are without effort; they get money merely by means of previous holdings. While the masses look as if they are living in the Stone Age, our rulers are enjoying extra luxurious life. Their self-defence as well as state agencies are guarding them. Regular visitors and common people are not allowed inside. We, the people, ultimately prevail, and those in power are afraid of us. Yes, they are very much afraid.
One can only wonder how many years worth of taxpayers money the gold-plated toilets, sinks and towel racks cost Pakistan. The obscene amount of money spent on luxurious decor is a good illustration of the scale of waste and embezzlement, which takes place during their rule. Luxury cars and other items are imported when ordinary people can hardly pay their water, electricity and gas bills. Yes! Rulers, after all, are the rulers. The poor, after all, are the poor. We have totally unaccountable rulers that wouldn't listen and wouldn't care. How much money do they need, anyway? is however a big question. They were born with money, they continue to make more money and yet they hoard their money. Most of it goes nowhere, just sits in bank accounts, trust funds, stocks, bonds, etc. Still they live in constant fear of losing even a mere penny of it. What a sad life they lead. They own several cars, houses, mansions, private planes, servants, etc., but they are never satisfied. It's just never enough for them. According to Islamic teachings, how can rulers live in luxury while people suffer? they have never thought about.
Revolutions are caused not by poverty alone, but by thousands of accumulated injustices; when the breaking point is reached, even the smallest can ignite the firestorm. Our rulers should remember neo-liberalism, staggering unemployment, high inflation rendering everyday items like food harder to buy, the graft and nepotism practiced by Ben Ali's family in Tunisia were the main causes of anti-government anger which ousted the regime after young Tunisian fruit seller publicly lit himself on fire and died in the hospital later.
The Tunisian people did not need more reasons to protest when they took the streets. The revolution in Tunisia was not motivated by any ideology or religion, nor was it pro or anti-democracy. Its only catalyst was the desire of millions of Tunisians for social justice, dignity, the right to work, and to live free of fear and poverty. Our rulers need to learn from history and have sensible policy about rule of law, ending corruption, wealth distribution through fair taxation, ensuring at least two time meal for everyone, and access to real justice to everyone before it is too late.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Columnists. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>