<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW0-VVJ1-JCRR-00NM"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>UNS Energy Updates on Acquisition by Fortis</title><source>Professional Services Close-Up</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Shareholders of UNS Energy Corp. voted overwhelmingly to approve the proposed acquisition of the company by a subsidiary of Fortis Inc.
According to a release, the votes were tabulated at a special meeting for shareholders at UNS Energy's Corporate Headquarters in Tucson. Approximately 97 percent of the ballots cast supported the company's acquisition by Fortis, the largest investor-owned gas and electric distribution utility company in Canada.
"Today's vote is a positive step toward a new partnership that will provide benefits for shareholders, customers, employees and the communities we serve. Joining Fortis will provide additional financial strength to help us maintain safe, reliable service throughout Arizona," said Board Chair and CEO Paul J. Bonavia.
The merger agreement provides that Fortis will acquire all of the outstanding common stock of UNS Energy for $60.25 per share in cash. The $4.3 billion transaction, which includes the assumption of approximately $1.8 billion in debt, would provide additional capital and new resources for UNS Energy's subsidiaries, including Tucson Electric Power (TEP) and UniSource Energy Services (UES). Both companies will remain headquartered in Tucson under local control with current management and staffing levels and no planned changes to existing operations or rates.
Joining the Fortis family of companies would improve UNS Energy's access to capital to fund the ongoing diversification of its generating fleet as well as investment in other infrastructure improvements. Upon closing, Fortis will inject $200 million of equity into UNS Energy.
The merger is subject to the approval of regulators, including the Arizona Corp. Commission and the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission; the expiration or termination of the applicable waiting period under the Hart-Scott-Rodino Antitrust Improvements Act of 1976, as amended; and the satisfaction of customary closing conditions. UNS Energy anticipates the transaction will be finalized by the end of 2014.
Fortis is an investor-owned gas and electric distribution utility in Canada.
More information:
uns.com
fortisinc.com
((Comments on this story may be sent to newsdesk@closeupmedia.com))
]]></text></news-item>