<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW0-FYT1-DYX4-0047"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Truck runs over worker, killing him</title><source>The Straits Times (Singapore)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A FOREIGN worker was killed on Saturday after he was run over by a tipper truck - the third worksite accident reported here over the past week.
The police and Singapore Civil Defence Force (SCDF) were alerted to the incident - which took place at the entrance of a worksite located at the junction of Tampines Avenue 10 and Tampines Industrial Avenue 2 - just before 3pm.
The victim, a 27-year-old worker from India, was trapped under the front wheel of the truck when SCDF rescuers arrived.
He was pronounced dead by SCDF paramedics after his body was extricated by the rescuers.
The 33-year-old driver, also an Indian national, was arrested for causing death by a negligent act.
Officers from the Ministry of Manpower (MOM) Occupational Safety and Health Inspectorate were on site to investigate the accident, said a spokesman.
Peng Chuan Engineering Construction, the occupier of the site, has also been ordered by the MOM to stop all work.
Chinese evening daily Lianhe Wanbao reported yesterday that the victim started working in Singapore about half a year ago.
He had just finished unloading some cargo and was taking a rest by the site's entrance when tragedy struck. A witness reportedly saw him being dragged by the truck for a few metres after being knocked over.
This is the third worksite accident reported here over the past week.
On March 23, a 23-year-old Indian worker died after he was pinned between a boom lift and a crawler crane at a worksite in Joo Koon Road in Jurong.
Last Tuesday evening, a crane toppled over at a worksite between Robinson Road and Cecil Street in the Central Business District, but no one was injured.
There have been at least 13 workplace fatalities since the start of this year, with a spate of at least seven construction accidents in January alone.
That month, Acting Minister for Manpower Tan Chuan-Jin said his ministry would review two existing workplace safety programmes to "make sure we heighten sensitivity to safety".
But he added that the Manpower Ministry and the construction industry must review and prevent lapses in the building process.
YEO SAM JO
]]></text></news-item>