<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW0-RGK1-JB3N-T01Y"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>CIL May Stop Hiring Women on Compassionate Grounds</title><source>Economic Times (E-Paper Edition)</source><author>DEBJOY SENGUPTA KOLKATA</author><text><![CDATA[Coal India,the world's biggest coal miner,may stop employing women under compassionate grounds as most of them are illiterate and cannot be deployed for mining purposes.It is instead planning to give a lump sum.36,000 every month to the family of the worker who dies at the mines."We are in discussion with the unions to implement this scheme in lieu of the existing one because we are looking at reducing the number of female workforce in the company because they cannot be sent to mines or remote locations for coal exploration," a senior CIL official said on condition of anonymity.Accidents at CIL mines are common and until now the company is following the system of offering job to one member of the family in case of death of an employee.The practice of employing widows of its workers in the company is on since 1974.The number of such women employees has reached 26,000."This segment is surplus at the moment and we have offered a voluntary retirement scheme for them," a senior CIL official said.The Indian Mines Act does not allow women to be sent to underground mines,neither could they be made to work in opencast mines after dark.This has forced the PSU miner to make them do the jobs of general mazdoors,peons,sweepers and paramedical staff."Now we would like to stop recruiting any more women on compassionate grounds and are in discussions with the unions," the official added."CIL,however,is open to offer a job a male member of the family,provided he qualifies and has attained the legal age to work.But,every affected family may not have a male member eligible to work," he said.The company is working out a package which would be offered in lieu of the job to the widow in case there are no male members in the family."We plan to offer a monthly contribution of.16,000 each month to the family member till the time the employee was to reach 60 years," he said.For example,if an employee dies in a mine accident at the age of 45,his family would be offered a monthly contribution of.16,000 per month for the next 15 years - the period in which the deceased employee would have turned 60 - the age for retirement."In addition,the family will also receive a pension of around.20,000 per month on average,totaling the package to.36,000 per month," he said.

]]></text></news-item>