<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW0-BPF1-JCBN-000B"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>@HD2 New Briefs head;Missing from US landslide down from 90 to 30</title><source>The Nation (Thailand)</source><author>The Nation</author><text><![CDATA[@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;The number of people listed as missing from a monster US landslide has dropped from 90 to 30, while the confirmed death toll rose by one to 18, an official said yesterday.
Another body has been located but not formally identified, said Jason Biermann of the Snohomish County Department of Emergency Management, a week after a wall of mud and debris crashed down onto the town of Oso in the state of Washington.
At least eight other bodies are believed to have been located earlier in the week, making the expected death toll from the tragedy at least 27
.
@HD2 New Briefs head;Poll; Women in revealing clothes deserve rape
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;In Brazil, the land of mini bikinis and voluptuous carnival dancers, most people say a woman who shows off her body deserves to be raped, according to a poll that has triggered outrage.
Of the 3,810 respondents of both sexes who responded to the government's Institute of Applied Economic Research (IPEA) survey, about 2,480 – 65 per cent, justified raping women who wear "clothing that shows off the body".
Journalist Nana Queiroz launched an online protest event on Facebook that invited women to take pictures of themselves topless while covering their breasts accompanied with the phrase; "I don't deserve to be raped."
Queiroz, 28, said she received several threats of rape while she led the protest online.
"The most surprising thing is that it is permissible to walk naked in the Carnival, but not in real life," Queiroz said.
@HD2 New Briefs head;Men try to deposit fake bonds in Vatican bank
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;Vatican police on Saturday apprehended an American and a Dutch man who were trying to deposit billions of euros and US dollars in fake bonds in the Vatican bank.
The men were stopped by the police when they approached one of the guarded gates at the Vatican and asked to be let through to the Institute for Religious Works as the bank is formally known, Vatican spokesman Federico Lombardi said.
The bonds were discovered in a briefcase they were carrying and the men were handed over to Italy's financial police, who found false passports and other fake documents in their hotel rooms.
The haul came a day after Italian prosecutors said two former top executives at the Vatican bank will go on trial for money laundering. – AFP
@HD2 New Briefs head;CNN sorry for accidentally announcing Pele's death
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;The CNN news organisation has apologised for accidentally announcing the death of 73-year-old Brazilian soccer legend Pele via Twitter.
"Pele representative tells CNN he is alive and very well," tweeted the CNN show "New Day". The Twitter account of the show also said it deleted the earlier erroneous tweet about the soccer player.
"We regret the error and thank our followers for the feedback," the tweet reads, apologising to its 54,000 followers for the mistake. #124– DPA
]]></text></news-item>