<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW0-CNN1-JC65-50FG"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Monday, April 7</title><source>Associated Press International</source><author>The Associated Press</author><text><![CDATA[Today is Monday, April 7, the 97th day of 2014. There are 268 days left in the year.
Highlights in history on this date:
1509 - France declares war on Venice.
1652 - The Dutch under van Riebeeck settle Cape Town in South Africa.
1897 - Turkey declares war on Greece.
1933 - A purge of Jews, socialists and democrats in public office begins in Germany, with the Nazis coming to power a month earlier.
1936 - Cape Parliament passes native representation bill permitting natives to elect three Europeans to represent them in Union Parliament in South Africa.
1939 - Italy invades Albania.
1941 - British forces under Archibald Wavell evacuate Benghazi, Libya, during World War II.
1945 - U.S. aircraft carrier planes sink Japan's largest battleship, the Yamato, in World War II.
1948 - The United Nations World Health Organization is established to research and prevent disease and improve public health worldwide.
1953 - Dag Hammarskjold, Swedish diplomat, is elected secretary-general of United Nations.
1957 - New York City's last electric trolley completes its final run from Queens to Manhattan.
1961 - Milovan Djilas, former Number Two man of Tito regime in Yugoslavia, is arrested.
1966 - U.S. hydrogen bomb lost from bomber is recovered in Mediterranean Sea off coast of Spain.
1969 - U.S. Supreme Court unanimously strikes down laws prohibiting private possession of obscene material.
1974 - Major oil producing countries meeting in Geneva decide to set up fund for developing nations hit hard by higher petroleum prices.
1976 - China's Deputy Prime Minister Deng Xiaoping is deposed and Hua Guofeng named prime minister.
1987 - U.S. President Ronald Reagan announces that American diplomats will not occupy the new embassy in Moscow until he is sure that it is secure from Soviet eavesdropping.
1988 - Iran and Iraq bomb each other's capitals and other towns, killing and wounding scores of people.
1990 - Former U.S. national security adviser John Poindexter is convicted of conspiracy, obstruction and lying in Iran-Contra scandal; China enters satellite-launching business by putting U.S.-made telecommunications satellite into orbit.
1991 - U.S. military planes begin taking off from a southern Turkish air base to drop food and water to besieged Kurdish refugees stuck at the border.
1992 - Air strikes by Yugoslav jets kill at least six people in Bosnia.
1993 - Macedonia, a former republic of Yugoslavia, is allowed to enter the United Nations after a compromise with Greece over the name of the country.
1994 - Rampaging troops kill Rwanda's acting premier and 11 Belgian U.N. soldiers and a civil war erupts in Rwanda, a day after a mysterious plane crash claimed the lives of the presidents of Rwanda and Burundi.
1995 - U.N. peacekeepers square off against Bosnian Serb troops on a key Sarajevo road as the Serbs block access to the besieged city and keep their guns trained on a suburb.
1996 - Russian forces attack rebel positions in southern Chechnya, using artillery and air raids in an effort to uproot the guerrillas.
1997 - Government soldiers in Lubumbashi, Zaire's second largest city, lay down their arms and join the cause of rebels advancing on the city.
1998 - Indonesia and the International Monetary Fund agree on the third package of measures in six months to get a US$43 billion bailout package on track.
1999 - Yugoslav authorities seal off Kosovo's main border crossings, preventing ethnic Albanians from leaving as the wave of refugees approaches the half-million mark.
2000 - Iqbal Masih, a slain Pakistani boy who rose from virtual slavery at a carpet factory to become a symbol of the fight against child labor, is named the winner of the first World's Children's prize.
2001 - Armed police break up protests in several Turkish cities after the lira falls sharply and prices soar. Thousands of laid off workers and citizens call for the resignation of Prime Minister Bulent Ecevit and his government.
2002 - Costa Ricans in a runoff election choose Abel Pacheco of the ruling right-of-center Social Christian Unity Party as their next president.
2003 - An audio tape purportedly made by Osama bin Laden, the fugitive leader of the al-Qaida terrorist organization, is delivered to The Associated Press urging Islamic followers to devote themselves to "martyrdom," by engaging in suicide attacks against the U.S. and Britain.
2004 - The French government says that 550 new research posts will be created in France, easing tensions within the elite research community that took to the streets in angry demonstrations to denounce a lack of funding and posts.
2006 - Gunmen attack a convoy of customs agents traveling through the desert in southern Algeria, killing 13 and wounding eight others.
2007 - A Russian rocket carrying the U.S. billionaire Charles Simonyi and two cosmonauts blasts off on a 13-day trip en route to the international space station. Simonyi, the fifth paying space tourist to make the trip, paid $20 million.
2008 - A coroner's jury in London rules that Princess Diana and boyfriend Dodi Fayed were unlawfully killed through the reckless actions of their driver and paparazzi in 1997.
2009 - Israel successfully tests an anti-missile system designed to protect the country against Iranian attack, the Defense Ministry says, perfecting technology developed in response to failures of similar systems during the 1991 Gulf war.
2010 - Thousands of protesters furious over corruption and spiraling utility bills seize internal security headquarters, a state TV channel and other levers of power in Kyrgyzstan after government forces fatally shoot dozens of demonstrators and wounded hundreds.
2011 - A gunman roams the halls of an elementary school in Rio de Janeiro and kills 11 children, lining them up against a wall and shooting them in the head at point-blank range.
2012 - Mali's parliamentary head, who was forced into exile after last month's coup, returns to the West African nation in crisis, marking the first step in Mali's path back to constitutional rule.
2013 - A fierce battle between U.S.-backed Afghan forces and Taliban militants in a remote corner of eastern Afghanistan leaves nearly 20 people dead, including 11 Afghan children killed in an airstrike and an American civilian adviser.
Today's Birthdays:
St. Francis Xavier, Jesuit missionary (1506-1552); William Wordsworth, English poet (1770-1850); Sir David Low, New Zealand cartoonist (1891-1964); Billie Holiday, U.S. jazz singer (1915-1957); Francis Ford Coppola, U.S. director (1939--); David Frost, British television personality (1939-2013); Jackie Chan, Hong Kong movie star (1954--); Russell Crowe, Australian actor (1964--).
Thought for Today:
Real generosity toward the future consists of giving all to what is present - Albert Camus, Algerian-born French writer (1913-1960)
]]></text></news-item>