<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW1-TVX1-DXX7-H1S8"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>CFMEU fined $1.25m over Grocon protests in Melbourne</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Construction, Forestry, Mining and Energy Union (CFMEU) has been fined $1.25 million for illegal blockades at Melbourne construction sites in 2012.
The union organised a four-day protest, in defiance of a court order, at the Grocon Emporium site in Melbourne's CBD.
The protests sparked clashes with mounted police who were called in to escort non-union workers into the site on August 28.
The union was fined $1 million for contempt of court over the Emporium blockade and $250,000 for protests at two other Grocon sites.
Supreme Court Justice Anthony Cavanough ordered the union to pay Grocon's court costs.
The judgement says according to financial figures submitted as part of the case that the union can afford to pay the fine because it has "substantial financial means."
The union does not dispute that but lawyers for the union have asked for 30 days to pay the fine.
Federal Employment Minister Eric Abetz says the size of the penalty is unprecedented and shows the union's behaviour is unacceptable.
"[It] reflects the ongoing actions of a union's disregard for the rule of law and standards of behaviour that apply to everyone else," he said.
"It is unacceptable to blockade a building site, intimidate staff, threaten and vilify employees and engage in battles with police in CBD streets.
"It is equally unacceptable to deliberately defy orders of the highest court in Victoria."
Victorian Planning Minister Matthew Guy says the fine is proof that Labor leader Daniel Andrews should cut ties with the union.
"Today is the day that Andrews needs to stand up and sack the CFMEU, from the Labor Party and stop backing them," Mr Guy said.
"If he doesn't, it's a sign of weak leadership."
Mr Andrews says he will not take advice from Mr Guy.
No place for intimidation - Grocon
In a statement, Grocon said the company welcomed "what is a defining moment for the construction industry and the rule of law."
"It should be clear to the Victorian CFMEU that old-style bullying and intimidation has no place in a modern workplace or the broader union movement," the statement said.
"The construction industry must take a stand to eradicate this sort of lawless behaviour and require all players to simply obey the law."
Grocon is continuing to pursue separate civil cases seeking damages against the CFMEU to recover the "significant costs" of the blockades.
At the time, the CFMEU maintained it was fighting for its right to have union representation on Grocon worksites and to have safety and shop stewards picked by the rank and file.
Mounted police and hundreds of officers in riot gear were called in to break the blockade to escort non-union workers into the site on August 28, causing gridlock during the morning peak in central Melbourne.
Grocon said the dispute cost the company over $300,000 a day and went to the Supreme Court seeking orders to end the dispute, which the union ultimately ignored.
Eventually after about three weeks the union backed down and lifted the blockade.
]]></text></news-item>