<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW1-B2B1-J9YR-G1HJ"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>World Cup workers' death toll in Brazil hits eight</title><source>Daily Star Online</source><author>Marc Walker</author><text><![CDATA[BRAZIL'S World Cup stadia death toll has soared to eight after a worker plunged 30ft at a jinxed ground.
The horror fall is the third fatal accident at São Paulo's Itaquerao arena, which is due to host the opening game on June 12.
Work at the site is behind schedule after two deaths from a crane collapse.
Latest victim Fabio Hamilton da Cruz died from head injuries while helping install seats at the venue, where Brazil and Croatia will kick off the tournament.
Medics said that he was pronounc- ed dead before he could undergo emergency surgery.
Fifa secretary general Jerome Valcke tweeted he was "deeply saddened by the tragic loss of a worker".
Valcke, 52, has previously slammed preparations, claiming the competition would be the "worst ever" with key deadlines missed by organisers.
The governing body and the local World Cup organising committee said they were waiting for an official report on the death.
It was the eighth fatality at World Cup venues so far, the seventh in accidents.
Three workers died in the Arena da Amazonia in Manaus, where England play crucial group games, including a 55-year-old killed in a crane accident. Another died of a heart attack.
In 2012, a worker died at the construction site of the stadium in the nation's capital Brasilia.
The city Porto Alegre, which is due to host three group games and a last 16 match, is set to pull out of the tournament because it has run out of cash to complete essential facilities.
Meanwhile, Brazilian special forces yesterday stormed one of Rio's largest slums in a controversial "clean-up operation" ahead of this summer's action.
The mission was to rid Complexo da Mare, home to more than 130,000 residents, of violence and drug gangs.
Brazilian police have attracted widespread criticism following the use of violence.
Related articles SNAPPED: England's home and away World Cup kits revealed Forget football, Jay Z and Beyoncé just want to party in Brazil for World Cup 2014 England fans outraged after World Cup flights are suddenly scrapped World Cup host city Brazil have no cash to finish stadium building
]]></text></news-item>