<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW1-B2B1-J9YR-G1KR"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Brilliant Putin is the leader I most admire, says Nigel Farage; Ukip leader cites former KGB officer Vladimir Putin as the statesman he most admires</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Matthew Holehouse Political Correspondent</author><text><![CDATA[Nigel Farage has named Vladimir Putin as the statesman he most admires.
Mr Farage, the leader of the UK Independence Party, said he disapproved of Russia's annexation of the Ukraine but hailed President Putin, a former KGB officer, as an "operator".
Russia's contribution in the Syrian Civil War has been "brilliant", he added.
He was interviewed by Alistair Campbell, Tony Blair's communications director, for GQ magazine.
Asked which current world leader he most admired, Mr Farage replied: "As an operator, but not as a human being, I would say Putin.
"The way he played the whole Syria thing. Brilliant. Not that I approve of him politically. How many journalists in jail now?"
Mr Putin has been blamed by the West for prolonging the bloodshed in Syria and propping up the Assad regime by supplying arms including helicopter gunships to the Assad regime, and repeatedly blocking moves to censure or sanction him at the United Nations. Russia regards its port at Tartus on the Meditarranean as vital.
However, Russia was widely seen to have outwitted the US last year when he brokered a deal under which Damascus agreed to give up its chemical weapons, derailing a push in Washington to launch air strikes against the regime.
Two Russian journalists who have criticised the regime are currently in jail. Others, such as Anna Politovskaya, have been murdered after criticising the regime.
Mr Farage last week offered a sympathetic interpretation of Russia's invasion of Ukraine during his debate with Nick Clegg, saying the European Union had "blood on its hands" for supporting the EuroMaidan protests in Kiev which triggered the downfall of the Moscow-aligned president Viktor Yanukovych.
He added later: "If you poke a Russian bear with a stick he will respond."
The Liberal Democrats characterised that position as "I agree with Vlad" and accused Mr Farage of "taking his talking points straight from the Kremlin".
Russia regards the European Union with increasing hostility, and Ukraine was integral to President Putin's plan to build a rival trade bloc, the Eurasian Union.
Mr Farage is understood to have met the Russian ambassador to the UK, Alexander Yakovenk, several times.
Mr Putin has attracted admiration in some conservative quarters in Europe for his opposition to gay marriage, with his time in office marked by a rise in attacks on homosexuals.
However, Mr Farage's interpretation of the Ukraine crisis is shared by a number of Conservative MPs, who regarded the EU's bid to "europeanise" Russia's backyard as foolhardy.
Asked by Mr Campbell to say "something nice" about the three major party leaders, the normally garrulous Mr Faragewas almost lost for words, describing each of them as "nice".
Mr Cameron is "a perfectly nice fellow who stands four-square for nothing," Mr Miliband a "nice chap, not very worldly - I would love to see him in a working men's club in Newcastle", while Liberal Democrat leader Nick Clegg - who took on Mr Farage in a TV debate last week - was a "very nice guy, just wrong".
Mr Farage said there was "absolutely no doubt at all" that the Prime Minister decided to offer an in/out referendum on Britain's EU membership because of pressure on his party from Ukip, adding: "It was the last thing he wanted to do. He was Mr No, No, No."
He added he "don't give a damn" who wins the next election, and said he has a "yearning" to work in radio on leaving politics.
"Potentially I would be very interested in being a shock jock, though Ofcom might be tricky. Some of the American stuff is appalling, wild stuff, crazy conspiracy theories."
]]></text></news-item>