<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW1-DD71-JCXB-2057"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Quindell PLC Preliminary Results -5-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[In October 2013, we announced that the Group has reached agreement with 10 key brands of varying sizes for over GBP150 million of revenue per annum as well as a GBP50 million per annum contract win with Direct Line Group the largest retail general insurer in the UK. This new hire contract was significant from day one, being worth over GBP150 million during its three year period and followed a competitive market evaluation, rigorous due diligence and selection process by Direct Line Group. Of these GBP200 million additional annual run rate revenues, circa GBP150 million per annum commenced in Q4 2013 and circa GBP50 million commenced as from Q1 2014.
Solutions Division The Group's Solutions Division has similarly experienced a positive year. Revenues totalled GBP80.4 million during 2013 (2012: GBP30.1) with GBP39.5 million, GBP33.8 million and GBP7.1 million coming from Europe, North America and the Rest of the World respectively. Adjusted EBITDA was GBP51.4 million, a margin of 64% (2012: GBP24 million at 80%) representing a contribution of approximately 37% of the Group's Adjusted EBITDA in the year, and with a particularly strong cash generation profile. Quindell's Solutions Division is recognised in the industry by both financial and trade analysts as number one in P&C insurance claims technology in Europe. Quindell is a global technology supplier of P&C complete insurance ERP solutions, a global technology supplier in telecoms with expertise in OSS/BSS, and have unique expertise in online/social media sales and service. In addition we are seen as the global leader for 'Black Box Telematics' Usage and Behaviour Based Insurance. As a result, the Division has experienced rapid expansion in North America with acquisition of iter8 and establishment of Quindell Solutions Inc., and signed multiple new technology contracts and extensions across key markets and geographies including major contracts in telematics. Quindell was recognised among the leading European providers of Insurance Claims Systems in Celent Claims Systems Vendors: European General Insurance 2012 and we now believe the Group, with its market leading ICE Challenger software suite of Policy, Claims, Analytics and Napier cloud based rating engine, is the clear market leader for European insurance technology by a significant margin, having delivered more deals in the first six months of 2013, including SaaS implementations, than Guidewire, SAP and Accenture together are accredited by Celent to have won in claims software over the last two years. Significant new deals with the RAC, Ageas, and one other of the top ten UK motor insurers, being amongst the highlights for Quindell. In April 2013, the Group marked its expansion into the North American Insurance market and the formation of Quindell Solutions Inc with its acquisition of Iter8 Inc, a company specialising in providing SaaS based solutions to the direct insurance and broker channels. At the time of the acquisition of Iter8, the Board stated its confidence that Quindell would be able to replicate its UK growth rate in insurance technology sales in North America, and performance to date, together with the growing sales pipelines in this region, particularly for telematics based solutions, for the Group continue to justify the Board's confidence that the Group's technology market leadership, already proven in Europe, is replicable in the North American market. In May 2013, the Group acquired Quindell Property Services, a newly formed group bringing together a number of businesses owned by the vendors, related to the supply of outsourced property services and SaaS based enabling technologies. This transaction also enabled the Group to increase its shareholding in 360GlobalNet Limited from 19% to 60%. The Group's SaaS based technology and outsourcing property solution 'with you in five' was recently highlighted in the financial results presentation of one of the largest, innovative and influential direct insurers in the UK market. The Group is also now starting to develop what we expect will soon become a significant pipeline of opportunities in a number of the largest insurance markets around the world for this solution. Connected Car and Telematics The Board believes that the scale of the opportunity of this Division is not fully reflected in current market expectations, particularly with regard to telematics led contracts which in 2013 already represented approaching GBP40 million of high margin, cash generative revenue for the Group and with more than half from North America. For Quindell, our charter clients for telematics, including our associate ingenie, were more than simply car insurance for young drivers and represented more than 'niche' segments of the market. Rather, they represented a whole new approach to motor insurance, and one that in time has the potential to become mainstream as a result of the superior underwriting results it offers to insurers and the access to reduced premiums that insured drivers can enjoy. Telematics and the concept of a learning solution which enables the insurer to offer reducing premiums is revolutionary for car insurance, but the technique is now accepted, and a tipping point in its application is being reached. This change, we feel, is as significant as telephone sales were for the insurance industry and the resultant success of Direct Line Group. Globally, the Group's strong positioning is supported by the findings of Ptolemus Consulting, which in its 2013 Global Study into Usage Based Insurance the Quindell/Himex proposition was the only solution out of the 77 providers surveyed that was listed in the top three in all categories: black box, OBD dongle and smartphone. The Group has previously highlighted the opportunity to build a 10 million subscriber base each paying between $5 to $15 per month, equating to $600 million to $1.8 billion per annum in high margin recurring technology revenues in the medium to long term. This is led by the Group's telematics insurance and its other Connected Car initiatives. The Group's position in insurance based telematics is already well advanced in the UK where Quindell currently enjoys a dominant market share. Over the last year, the UK market has seen a growth in the number of telematics policies sold by circa 116,000, with ingenie representing approximately 20% of black box insurance growth. Further, in combination with its other clients, the Group is providing technology to leading brands in the telematics space that in combination represent approximately 80% of the growth over the last year in the UK. In July 2013, the Group announced its 19% investment in Himex Limited, a business focused on delivering disruptive insurance technology solutions enabling game changing usage based insurance propositions that leverage the full insurance value chain. Himex is primarily focused on the US market and this provides significant synergies with Quindell as each business can cross fertilise use of both sets of their technologies to maximise on the global opportunities during this period of land grab and as telematics reaches a critical tipping point in its adoption cycle for insurance. Quindell had been working with Himex to implement an outsourced support service centre in Canada and on certain telematics related supply arrangements supporting the current and future implementations for a number of top-twenty US insurers. Quindell was also appointed during 2013 as Himex's sole and exclusive distributor of Himex's gamification UBI products in the UK, Canada, Brazil and across South America. Leveraging its unique market position in telematics, the Group negotiated a number of significant contracts for its usage and behavioral based insurance solutions in combination with Himex technology in our exclusive territories. Of particular significance was the agreement that was reached with the Insurance Brokers Association of Ontario ("IBAO") for telematics technology. Quindell will provide the technology for all of the IBAO's telematics initiatives to its membership base representing circa 12,000 brokers who directly or indirectly along with their insurance partners provide approximately 60% of auto insurance policies in Ontario, representing over 6 million policies. The agreement is valued at over C$6 million by the end of 2014 and implies more than C$20 million of technology revenues over the minimum five year exclusive contract term, although the full potential from this agreement to Quindell could be substantially in excess of the C$20 million. At the end of October 2013, we announced that RSA and Gore Mutual are first movers for broker-owned telematics in Canada. RSA and Gore Mutual are amongst first movers to the Insurance Brokers Association of Ontario broker-owned telematics offering which is supported by Quindell's technology and outsourcing solutions. In November 2013 we announced a telematics and outsourcing win with CAA and CAA Insurance, covering circa 1.9 million members in Southern Ontario and with sister organisations across Canada covering a combined 5.8 million members. The contract represented the second of several contracts for Quindell's telematics offering and to date the largest North American deal for Quindell. Based on a 10% to 30% telematics take-up in Canada with automobile association members, there is revenue potential of C$79m to C$237m per annum. CAA South Central Ontario (CAA SCO), has also contracted with Quindell to provide their auto club members and insurance customers with new telematics technology and services. Acquisitions and Strategic Investments Acquisitions represent a smaller part of the Group's growth strategy in 2014 than in any prior period when compared to the size of the enlarged Group, with any acquisitions during the remainder of the financial year typically being small relative to the size of the Group and likely to be of a tactical or in-fill nature. As previously announced the Group's criteria for acquisitions continues to be as follows:
]]></text></news-item>