<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW1-B2B1-J9YR-G1MD"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Tax uncertainty stops multinationals moving to UK, says Deloitte chief; David Sproul says negative rhetoric surrounding corporation tax paid by UK-based companies is the "number one" reason why firms defer decisions to strengthen their presence in Britain</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Szu Ping Chan</author><text><![CDATA[Endless criticism of the amount of tax paid by multinational companies has stopped at least a dozen corporations from moving their headquarters to the UK, according to the head of one of Britain's "Big Four" accountancy firms.
David Sproul, the chief executive of Deloitte, said negative rhetoric surrounding corporation tax paid by UK-based companies was the "number one" reason why they had deferred decisions to strengthen their presence in Britain.
"The notion that companies need to pay their fair share of tax, businesses absolutely accept that," he said. "They just like to be certain about what that 'fair share', is and then they can operate in that environment." Mr Sproul said several companies in the US and Japan had expressed interest in moving their headquarters to the UK, but decided to delay because of uncertainty about tax rules.
"Certainly there are multinationals we know that have deferred a decision until there isn't quite such a degree of rhetoric about international businesses based [here] being perceived to be taking advantage of tax and tax regimes."
Multinational companies, including Amazon and Google, have been criticised by MPs for a lack of transparency over tax. The Government is working with the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development to reform the system, and Mr Sproul said it was their responsibility to clarify tax rules.
"The sooner there's certainty on where that's going, the better," he said, adding that uncertainty over Britain's membership of the EU was the second most frequently cited reason for businesses delaying UK investment.
Despite these hurdles, Deloitte expects a resurgence in business investment over the next two years. Companies are expected to invest around £90bn this year, rising to £107bn in 2015, according to its survey of 132 senior executives.
Most investment is expected to come from private companies, as listed businesses choose to prioritise returning cash to shareholders who suffered reduced or axed dividends in the financial crisis.
A separate survey by the Confederation of British Industry showed business volumes at financial services firms continued to grow at a steady pace in the three months to March.
]]></text></news-item>