<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW1-0M01-JBV1-X08Y"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>AFPTV Advisory 1600 GMT</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[We will file the following videos:
-- TOP WORLD NEWS --
+ MALAYSIAN PLANE
Filed over past 12 hours:
SUBANG JAYA, MALAYSIA/ INDIAN OCEAN, AUSTRALIA: Almost 30 relatives of Chinese passengers on a missing Malaysia Airlines flight arrive in Kuala Lumpur to demand answers about the plane's fate. PHOTOS. VID612151_EN
+ TURKEY ELECTION
Coming up:
ISTANBUL/ANKARA: Rolling news coverage of Turkey's key local elections. RAW. (Erdogan voting) 2000 GMT (reax to exit polls) TBA
Filed over past 12 hours:
ISTANBUL: Turkey's Premier Recep Tayyip Erdogan, hit by protests and a graft scandal, voices confidence as he votes, predicting "the people will tell the truth". RAW. VID612176_EN.
- Opposition Republican People's Party (CHP) candidate for Istanbul mayor Mustafa Sarigul votes. RAW. VID612116_EN (images). VID612161_EN (soundbites)
- Voter voxpops. RAW. VID612114_EN / VID612079_EN
+ UKRAINE CRISIS
Coming up:
PARIS: US Secretary of State John Kerry meets his Russian counterpart Sergei Lavrov for talks on the crisis in Ukraine. RAW. 1900 GMT
Filed over past 12 hours:
KIEV: Ukraine's presidential, military and national orchestras and choirs join forces to perform the European anthem in airports around the country, in a show of unity with the EU. RAW. VID612172_EN.
LVIV, UKRAINE: A Crimean football team is greeted with nationalistic chants as the players take on Lviv in western Ukraine. RAW. VID612074_EN
-- OTHER WORLD NEWS --
+ EUROPE
Coming up:
MADRID: Spanish journalists Javier Espinosa and Ricardo Vilanova greet colleagues and loved ones on returning to Spain after being freed following six months in the hands of Al-Qaeda-linked kidnappers in Syria. RAW. 2000 GMT
VARIOUS LOCATIONS, FRANCE: Rolling news coverage of second round of France's local elections. RAW.
BUDAPEST: Hungarian opposition holds rally one week ahead of legislative election. RAW. 1900 GMT
HENIN-BEAUMONT, FRANCE: Far-right National Front mayor Steeve Briois takes office. RAW.
Filed over past 12 hours:
VARIOUS LOCATIONS, FRANCE: France holds a second round of voting in local elections that are set to result in a breakthrough by the far right and trigger a reshuffle of the beleaguered Socialist government. RAW. VID612154_EN
THE HAGUE: The International Court of Justice rules on Monday in case brought by Australia alleging that Japan's annual Antarctic whale hunt is a business disguised as science. FILE. VID504628_EN
ROME: Franciscan monks have launched an appeal for private funding in order to renovate the tiny cell where St Francis sleep when he came to Rome to visit the pope. RAW. VID611914_EN
BASEL, SWITZERLAND: Switzerland's recent vote to curtail immigration from the European Union could seriously impact the Alpine country's booming watch trade, industry insiders warned this week. RAW. VID611623_EN
BASEL, SWITZERLAND: Watches that connect to your smartphone or even a satellite to ensure perfect time, regardless of where you are in the world, or alert you if you leave your phone behind? RAW. VID611680_EN
SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA : Crimea to set clocks to Russia time. RAW. VID612040_EN
BRATISLAVA: Political newcomer and millionaire Andrej Kiska wins a landslide in presidential run-off. RAW. VID612067_EN
+ AFRICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
CONAKRY: Guinea races to contain a deadly Ebola epidemic spreading from its southern forests to the capital Conakry, as neighbouring Senegal closes its border. RAW. VID612134_EN (MSF in Conakry). STOCK SHOTS. VID401715 (Senegal)
JOHANNESBURG: Stockshots of the South African stock exchange and economy. STOCKSHOTS. VID611375_EN
BRAZZAVILLE: Congo's streets of Brazzaville have taken on a more stylish appearance thanks to the presence of "sapeurs", a sartorial subculture of colourful Congo dandies inspired by -- but not always faithful to -- the world's great couturiers. RAW. VID611726_EN
+ ASIA-PACIFIC
Coming up:
KATHMANDU: Nepal celebrates Ghode Yatra traditional horse racing festival. RAW. TBA
Filed over past 12 hours:
TAIPEI: Tens of thousands of Taiwanese protesters take to the streets in Taipei against a trade pact with China. RAW. VID612094_EN
BANGKOK: Thailand holds elections for the upper house of parliament that could hold the key to the fate of the prime minister. RAW. VID612042_EN
MYANMAR: Myanmar starts its first census in 30 years. RAW. VID612050_EN
TOKYO: New terminal opens at Haneda Airport, one of the world's busiest. RAW. VID612054_EN
AT SEA, SOUTH CHINA SEA: A Philippine re-supply ship evaded a Chinese coastguard blockade in the South China Sea Saturday to reach Filipino soldiers based on a remote reef claimed by both countries. RAW. VID612060_EN
KABUL: Taliban insurgents attack the Afghan election commission's heavily-fortified headquarters in Kabul on Saturday, one week ahead of voting and after a series of bloody attacks in the city. RAW. VID612052_EN
+ MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
GAZA CITY, PALESTINIAN TERRITORIES: Palestinians and Arab Israelis commemorate Land Day with rallies remembering six of their number who were shot dead during a 1976 demonstration against land seizure. RAW. VID612182_EN / VID612163_EN
ZOUK MOSBEH, LEBANON: Sattar Saad from Iraq wins the Arabic version of the reality-TV show "The Voice", which featured 100 participants from across the Arab world. RAW. VID612058_EN
ARSAL, LEBANON: A suicide car bomber explodes his vehicle at an army checkpoint in eastern Lebanon near the border with Syria, killing at least three soldiers and wounding four. RAW. VID612027_EN
+ LATIN AMERICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
CARACAS: Anti-government protests that have paralysed Venezuela continue on the streets of Caracas with police firing teargas and rubber bullets. RAW. VID612188_EN / VID612038_EN
RIO DE JANEIRO: More than 1,000 police occupy the vast Mare favela near Rio's international airport as authorities step up efforts to quell violence ahead of the World Cup. RAW. VID612157_EN
+ NORTH AMERICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
CHICAGO: The World Clown convention wraps up. RAW. VID612089_EN
-- SPORT --
Euro football coverage available to subscribers only
LONDON: Post-match reax after Arsenal host Manchester City in the Premier League. RAW. 1700 GMT
STUTTGART/DORTMUND, GERMANY: Post-match images after Stuttgart take on Borussia Dortmund in the Bundesliga on Saturday. RAW. 1900 GMT
-- FEATURES --
Filed:
CHOLISTAN, PAKISTAN: Cheered on by tens of thousands of spectators, 4x4s tear through Pakistan's deserts in the 9th edition of the Cholistan Desert Rally. PKG. NSV - VID609454_EN / VOICED - VID609455_EN
ADDIS ABABA: Teff, a grain mostly grown in the Horn of Africa, is a key part of Ethiopia's heritage and a crucial food staple. It is now gaining increased interest abroad among health aficionados seeking a nutritious, gluten-free alternative to wheat and farmers hope it can earn them some much-needed cash. NSV - VID611095_EN / VOICED - 611096_EN
Contact:
London desk: +44 207 776 2768
Hong Kong desk: +852 2829 6216
Nicosia desk: +357 22 391 453
Washington desk: +1 202 414 0550
Montevideo desk: +598 2 900 5095 ext 257
For contact via email: afptv-en@afp.com
]]></text></news-item>