<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-M581-JBHM-S01S"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>EPA To Review Options For Regulating Oil And Gas Methane Emissions</title><source>Clean Energy Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EPA is launching a formal review of oil and gas industry sources of the greenhouse gas (GHG) methane to help it decide by this fall on how to best control such releases, a key part of President Obama's just-released plan to curb methane emissions and which could result in first-time regulations of the pollutant for the energy sector.
Although the White House's plan released March 28 indicates a strong preference to regulate both methane and volatile organic compound (VOC) emissions in any future policies, some parts of the oil and gas development process only release methane and therefore methane-specific rules may be necessary. And EPA is also suggesting it might pursue stand-alone new source performance standards (NSPS) for oil and gas methane.
The American Lung Association and League of Conservation Voters were among the group who in response to the plan cheered the potential for direct regulation of methane, saying that new regulations are vital.
But industry and some Republican lawmakers were more critical of the plan and the potential for precedent-setting GHG rules for the sector. Sen. James Inhofe (R-OK) said the possibility of such rules reflects Obama's "war on fossil fuels" and is designed to "appease extreme environmental groups," while the American Petroleum Institute (API) said the industry is already voluntarily reducing methane emissions and new rules are not necessary.
The White House's Interagency Methane Strategy document, a part of the administration's Climate Action Plan, is a joint effort including EPA, the Energy Department (DOE) and the Interior Department (DOI). The document also says that DOI's Bureau of Land Management will later this year propose requirements for reducing emissions from flaring and venting from drilling on public land, and that DOE and EPA will use the agency's voluntary Natural Gas STAR program to identify voluntary opportunities for achieving methane cuts from downstream sources.
But EPA's formal review of methane from the sector has the most potential for new regulations to curb emissions, building on the agency's 2012 NSPS for oil and gas operations. The rules targeted VOCs and not methane despite advocates' push for such limits, instead cutting methane indirectly through VOC controls.
However, the agency in the methane strategy plan says it is reassessing the need for potential regulation of oil and gas methane emissions. "This fall, the EPA will determine what if any regulatory authorities, including setting standards under section 111 of the Clean Air Act or issuing Control Techniques Guidelines under section 182 of the Act, the agency will apply to emissions from these sources," a White House fact sheet says.
"If the agency determines to follow a regulatory course of action, it will undertake a schedule that will ensure that both rulemaking and any ensuing regulatory requirements for the states are completed by the end of 2016."
To launch its process, the agency is preparing a set of white papers for release this spring evaluating "emerging technical information" on effective control technologies that target five sources from the sector, according to recent legal filings and the White House documents describing the white papers.
The white papers, which EPA will float for public comment and peer review by an independent panel, are aimed at helping "solidify" EPA's understanding of whether the source, which are liquids unloading, oil and co-producing wells, leaks, pneumatic devices and compressors, are "potentially significant sources of methane," according to President Obama's March 28 climate action plan document, "Strategy to Reduce Methane Emissions."
"This robust technical understanding will allow the agency to fully evaluate the range of policy mechanisms that will cost-effectively cut methane waste and emissions," the fact sheet says.
Methane Emissions
EPA recently noted the development of the white papers in a Feb. 24 court filing in litigation over the NSPS. That lawsuit, pending in the U.S. Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit, was filed by industry groups who say the rules are too strict, and environmentalists who oppose the lack of GHG controls.
The suit is on hold pending an EPA administrative reconsideration of some provisions of the rules, and in the filing EPA said it will issue a "number of white papers on emerging technical information" on methane.
During a March 27 House Appropriations Committee environment panel hearing on EPA's fiscal year 2015 budget proposal, agency Administrator Gina McCarthy also said, "You'll be seeing some white papers come out but not direct regulation." Her comments were in response to questioning from Rep. David Joyce (R-OH) on whether the agency is planning new rules for the natural gas industry within the next two years.
The existing NSPS issued in 2012 set first-time control requirements for VOCs stemming from several aspects of the drilling and production process, most notably requiring drillers to install so-called green completions technologies in order to reduce VOC emissions from hydraulic fracturing and other drilling wells by 95 percent.
But the agency delayed a review of whether to set direct control requirements on methane, a potent GHG. Instead, EPA said it would continue to evaluate the appropriateness of direct methane limits and take additional steps if necessary, but cited controls for VOCs and other pollutants that have the co-benefit of also reducing methane emissions.
The White House document says, for example, that when the rules fully take effect in 2015, EPA estimates that the control requirements will cut methane by 33 million tons per year of carbon dioxide equivalent per year.
But environmentalists have charged that the rules, while a good first step toward managing emissions from the sector, leave a number of substantial sources at oil and natural gas sites uncovered, including those that emit low levels of VOCs but high amounts of methane, including liquids unloading and oil wells.
A coalition of Eastern states, led by New York and including Delaware, Connecticut, Maryland, Massachusetts, Rhode Island and Vermont, threatened to sue EPA Dec. 11, 2012 alleging it violated the Clean Air Act when it deferred a determination of whether direct methane limits would be "appropriate" in the NSPS.
In response to the new methane strategy plan, New York Attorney General Eric Schneiderman (D) said, "It is clear that methane from the oil and gas industry contributes substantially to climate change pollution. At the same time, it is clear that well-established and cost-effective measures to control these emissions are available."
Oil-and gas-producing states, however, including Oklahoma, Texas, North Dakota and others have sought to dissuade EPA from entering negotiations with the Eastern states on the issue, saying in a May 2 letter that the Eastern states' argument lacks merit because the provision of the air law governing such reviews is more "permissive" than the Eastern states portrayed.
The Environmental Council of the States is at its March 31-April 2 spring meeting in Sausalito, CO, to discuss a coordinated interstate approach for curbing releases of methane from the oil and gas sector. A key component of the state effort, which includes participation from industry groups and environmentalists, is to share best practices on reducing methane emissions under EPA's current regulations to control the sector's VOC emissions.
In its final NSPS, EPA acknowledged concerns about wells drilled in principally oil-rich plays that may also be used for natural gas extraction, but cited a lack of sufficient data on VOC emissions during completion of hydraulic fracturing at oil wells to support control requirements for those wells.
Regulatory Options
While the white papers will apparently serve as the template for future agency policy measures on controlling methane, the administration is leaving options open for how EPA may opt to address the issue.
However, the strategy document does say that the white papers should focus on controls that can target both VOCs and methane, signaling a possible expansion of the NSPS rather than stand-alone rules, and that any regulation EPA decides to issue should be completed by the close of 2016.
Environmentalists in recent meetings with EPA officials over the pending D.C. Circuit litigation have urged the agency to consider a path similar to the agency's climate NSPS for the utility sector under Clean Air Act section 111(d), including issuing direct methane standards and setting a schedule for finalizing regulation.
Other options EPA could consider, one environmentalist says, include achieving greater emissions cuts that would also capture methane through state implementation plans to achieve ambient air standards for ozone Ð for which methane is a precursor and also generates a greater amount of ozone than other precursors because it is a GHG -- or in section 112 of the air law, which governs hazardous air pollutants.
Addressing leaks along the natural gas pipeline under the NSPS is particularly tricky, the source says, because "a lot of the leaks are just methane Ð once gas leaves the wellhead, there's no legal justification for controlling emissions" because the NSPS only mandate controls for VOC emissions.
In the litigation, which consolidates both industry and environmentalist petitions for reconsideration, EPA filed a Feb. 24 motion to stay further proceedings pending its reconsideration, saying after release of the white papers "the Agency intends to take additional actions as appropriate."
But it is not entirely clear from recent administration officials' remarks whether the agency will opt for a direct regulatory approach. The strategy document emphasizes the importance of preserving states' primary role as regulators of the oil and gas industry, but also says, "Going forward, the EPA will deploy a carefully selected combination of policy tools to maximize cost-effective methane and VOC reductions from the oil and gas sector."
And top White House officials told reporters March 19 that the overall low-carbon benefits of natural gas continue to outweigh the GHG emissions stemming from methane releases.
"The basic story on methane . . . is that the emissions are definitely big enough to be worth reducing, but they're not big enough to imperil the advantage that natural gas has over coal as a way to generate electricity," White House science advisor John Holdren told reporters March 19. -- Bridget DiCosmo (bdicosmo@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>