<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-BGH1-DYR8-302K"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Tanzania; Nuclear Families Now Care Less for Children</title><source>Africa News</source><author>Tanzania Daily News (Dar es Salaam)</author><text><![CDATA[RECENT history, unfortunately, has seen various communal settings caring less for their children. Surprisingly, children do not thrive well even in nuclear families.
It is also apparent that wealthy families are rarely concerned about the children of other people. Clearly, this is a departure from the traditional African culture that requires that care for all children be a responsibility of every member of the society.
In towns and cities the once closely-knit extended family is now fragmented. In some places it has ceased to exist. What we now see is a proliferation of fragile families that live acrimoniously and single parent households, many of which are headed by women or older children. Neglect and abuse of children are common phenomena in our urban centres.
This sorry spectacle has given rise to a preponderance of juvenile delinquents. These underage children often engage in petty offences such as theft and possession of or peddling of narcotic drugs. The majority of children who live in extreme difficulties live in the developing world. More than a million of them live in Tanzania.
There are about 2.2 billion children in the world. At least 1.9 billion of them live in the developing world where the quality of life is bleak. Some slog it out for a living in the worst form of labour. Failure to protect children from any form of strenuous labour amounts to child abuse.
Some parents defend this situation saying: "The children are acquainting themselves with the rudiments of earning a living. "Children must work alongside parents or on their own so they develop the talents, mental capabilities and physical abilities to their fullest potential," some Tanzanian parents say.
So, you find in towns under-age quarry stone crackers, shoe-shine boys, fitters, cart pushers, sand miners, prostitutes, domestic hands, farm helps and even factory labourers.
In rural areas you find land tillers, cattle minders, cutters of hut construction poles, firewood collectors and even hunters of wild animals, some of which are vicious. Socially disadvantaged children have been seen working in fishing vessels on the high seas.
Welfare officers say exploitation of child labour has become so commonplace in Tanzania that the average person no longer sees it as a serious offence. The ILO says without really playing the blame game, it should be the responsibility of every government in the world to ensure that children are given a chance to live decent lives.
What troubles the ILO and the UNICEF is that half the world's children are growing up hungry and unhealthy. Some children live in a world where schools have become targets in armed conflicts. And in some regions AIDS is emptying whole villages.
In Tanzania, Makete and Muleba districts are a case in point in this regard. Governments should be ashamed for failing to deliver on the promise of childhood. The consequences of not paying attention to the problems of children do not need to be overstated.
Already, UNICEF is warning that meeting the Millennium Development Goals depends on reaching vulnerable children throughout the developing world. In Tanzania some destitute children have gone out of their way to become budding criminals. Historically, adult outlaws are known to have committed crimes for many centuries.
Unfortunately, modern society sees an increase in criminal acts committed by children. One school of thought, however, asserts that children are not criminals by nature.
However, the plight of disadvantaged children who live on mean streets without legal means to earn a living drives them into the criminal underworld. Some of these unfortunate children are neglected orphans who miss parental supervision.
A number of street boys in Dar es Salaam, Iringa and Dodoma, who eat from garbage cans and sleep in the dank alleys, find the business of living insurmountable. They say that life is not worth living. A few blame their "cruel" parents in particular and society in general for their predicament.
Some of the children interviewed (names withheld) sleep in abandoned kiosks, smelly shacks or on verandahs. Others sleep in junked boats, dilapidated vehicles or on the open beach or in hovels, especially in Dar es Salaam. Many do not trust anyone.
They are security sensitive and always carry knives for self-defence. Welfare officers say it is these needy children who usually engage in criminal activities for reasons of sheer survival. Some of these delinquent children may have been brought up by parents who have no respect for the rule of law or who are criminals themselves.
It is natural that children who grow up in a family of outlaws, without any adult role model, are likely to consider criminal activity as an acceptable way of living.
Juvenile delinquents are young offenders -- that is children aged between seven and sixteen years -- who commit repeated criminal acts, which would be punishable as crimes if committed by persons over the statutory age of sixteen as set by the juvenile courts.
The police in this country consider street children to be an army of future hardcore criminals who must be hammered severely when cornered. Probably it is this misbegotten belief that instigates the frequent abuse of street children by the smart "boys in khaki".
Some of the street children speak grimly about a number of confrontations with police officers. The children allege on-the-spot torture and extortion. Many of the interviewed girls claim to have been arrested and released without charge several times.
One girl, who was sleeping on the beach "one sinister night", was accosted by a patrol police officer who demanded sexual favours (in exchange for release from arrest) with threats. When the girl resigned to her fate the cop laid his rifle in the sand and went into carnal business "in earnest."
This is an atrocity that is punishable by law. The assaulted girl says the cop didn't even remember the cardinal sexual rule that calls for discreet use of a condom. "He must have been the daredevil type," she says.
"After the illegal sexual attack the cop dusted his uniform, fumbled around for his rifle and wandered on along the beach feeling good! Cops with this kind of lewd conduct should wind up in jail. Sexual assaults of this kind compound the suffering of socially disadvantaged street girls," she laments.
]]></text></news-item>