<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-MF81-F0J6-J059"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>War veteran, 92, among mine protesters arrested</title><source>Sydney Morning Herald (Australia)</source><author>James Robertson</author><text><![CDATA[Sixty protesters have been arrested for blockading construction of a mining site in a state forest in north-western NSW.
About 80 people walked oto the Maules Creek mine, about 50 kilometres north of Gunnedah, before sunrise on Monday and blocked or chained themselves to machinery.
A protest organiser, Helen War, said the protest aimed to draw attention to the new assessment report from the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change.
"We're looking at mass extinction," she said. "We can't continue burning coal."
She said those protesting included farmers, doctors and Bill Ryan, a legally blind 92-year-old Kokoda veteran, who was among those arrested.
Clearing of part of the Leard State Forest began in January to make way for Whitehaven Coal's $750 million open cut mine.
Statements to the Australian Stock Exchange suggest the mine would double Whitehaven's coal production by 2017. The company said no work was disrupted by the protest.
Murray Drechsler, a long-time Maules Creek protester, said disruptions would continue until Whitehaven released a report ito how carbon emissions from the mine were being offset by the company. "We have no choice. We believe they should be transparent."
The company says it has provided its report on carbon offsets to government regulators and plans to release it on an unspecified date.
A NSW Police spokeswoman said: "Police will not tolerate breaches of the peace or criminal offences committed by persons who attend unauthorised demonstrations."
The NSW Minerals Council said the disruption was dangerous.
The protesters were charged with entering and remaining on closed land and hindering mining equipment. They will appear in Narrabri Local Court on April 29.
Meanwhile up to 2000 people gathered to blockade the path at another mining site at Bentley, about 15 kilometres north of Lismore, early on Monday morning.
Protesters said numbers at a camp had grown tenfold in the expectation that Metgasco, the company with rights to drill an exploratory gas well on the site, would begin moving on Monday.
Protesters say the miners will employ environmentally damaging fracking techniques.
Numbers at Bentley fell to a few hundred after police attended the mining site but made no arrests and work did not begin.
Organisers said the numbers would surge again on Tuesday morning.
Metgasco said it will begin its operations at Bentley in the next two weeks.
]]></text></news-item>