<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-WD01-F08V-603V"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>Drilling in store? </title><source>Flint Journal (Michigan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[By Ron Fonger
rfonger1@mlive.com
Hikers, mountain bikers and horseback riders might have to make way for a new activity at Richfield County and Holloway Regional parks: drilling for oil and gas.
A company that is buying up mineral rights from private property owners around eastern Genesee County also is interested in oil and gas beneath the surface of more than 90 acres of land in the two parks, according to filings with the state Department of Natural Resources.
The DNR said Western Land Services asked the state to include 25 acres in Richfield County Park and 67 acres in Holloway Regional Park near Wolverine Campground in a May 1 oil and gas lease auction.
No final decision has been made on whether the land will be included in the auction -- something DNR Director Keith Creagh will determine in coming days.
After recent protests from the county about fears of wells sprouting up on parkland, the DNR already has changed the classification on the land, taking away the winning bidders' ability to construct drilling wells on the surface of the land.
The state controls access to oil and gas on the properties as a result of previous DNR grants that required the transfer of those rights from the county to the state, but the state is accepting public comments on the possible leases until Friday.
The county Board of Commissioners, Parks and Recreation Commission and Sierra Club Nepessing Group are among those rallying against the proposal.
Even though drilling on the surface of the land would not be allowed in the parks, there is the potential for drilling or fracking on adjacent property and for mining oil or gas underground, said Mary Uptigrove, Michigan DNR manager of mineral rights management.
The potential for increased drilling or fracking is quickly becoming a hot-button issue in county, where Western has been active in
See drilling, A5
Drilling
offering mineral leases and where hundreds of residents have turned out, looking for answers at meetings in recent weeks.
"I don't think a park is the ideal place for an oil" drilling operation, said Robert Young, a volunteer with Richfield Park BMX, a group that hosts bike competitions there three or four times a week from May through October. "I hate to see that area ruined."
The Flint Journal/MLive.com could not reach Brian Benson, senior project manager for Ludington-based Western, which has landmem working in Genesee and Lapeer counties.
Landmen or companies can nominate property where the DNR owns mineral rights for inclusion in the agency's twice-yearly lease auctions. Those auctions generate royalties, rent and bonuses that have amounted to more than $750 million in the past 10 fiscal years, according to the state.
'It's surprising'
That cash has helped boost the Michigan State Parks Endowment Fund and the Game and Fish Protection Trust Fund, but the money isn't worth losing people's unrestricted use of the land, county Parks Director Amy McMillan said.
The county Board of Commissioners has authorized McMillan to request the state make the mineral rights on the park properties "nonleasable" or to initiate talks aimed at purchasing those rights to protect the land in the future.
"This seemingly sudden interest is curious. It's surprising," said McMillan, who added this is the first time county parkland has been proposed for inclusion in an oil and gas auction since she became director in 1999.
"These areas are legitimately and actively used for recreation purposes. They aren't in the middle of nowhere," she said. "This (could) absolutely interfere with the public use of (that land)."
Uptigrove credited McMillan and county attorney Andrew Thompson with having successfully lobbied to change the classification of the parks' land nominated for the auction so wells could not placed on the surface.
Others have been speaking out, as well.
Landowners, local government officials and environmentalists have said they are concerned -- particularly by the potential for fracking, the method of pumping high-pressure water, sand and chemicals thousands of feet below the ground to free oil and gas from rock.
Environmental groups claim the process might harm groundwater and cause seismic disturbances while proponents of fracking say it is safe and is done thousands of feet below the aquifer.
Linda Berker, a member of the executive committee of the Sierra Club Nepessing Group, said anyone who enjoys parks should complain about the potential for opening them to drilling.
"The smell of an oil and gas well is really not what you want to smell when you're recreating," Berker said. "(That's) a nuisance that can cause ... negative health effects."
Other counties involved
The DNR said nominated land for which the state owns mineral rights might be finalized in advance of the April 10 meeting of the DNR Commission, a seven-member public body whose members are appointed by the governor.
Even if the rights to drill for oil and gas are purchased, companies also must meet Department of Environmental Quality requirements before that activity can start, Uptigrove said.
"We (are) working with the county. (Its representatives) are submitting information," said Upigrove, who called this a "preliminary stage" of discussion.
In addition to the county parkland in Genesee County, land under consideration for oil and gas leasing in the May 1 auction is in Barry, Cheboygan, Clare, Crawford, Genesee, Grand Traverse, Isabella, Jackson, Kalkaska, Lapeer, Lenawee, Mecosta, Midland, Montcalm, Oseola and Sanilac counties.
Western has become a known name in Genesee County recently as landmen have been offering five-year leases to private property owners at $35 per acre plus a 12.5 percent royalty.
Those offers have been out of the ordinary for the county, for which no oil or gas permits have been issued since 1995.
The DNR website said mineral leases with the state prohibit drilling within wetlands, habitat defined as critical to the survival of an endangered species, and drilling within 1,320 feet of any lake or stream.
Michigan has allowed leasing of oil and gas rights on state-controlled land since the late 1920s.
]]></text></news-item>