<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-MHH1-JDK3-900S"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Rural pot farms spark concern over crime</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[When is a farmer's crop no longer just another crop? When it's marijuana.
Starting Tuesday, new regulations will allow commercial growers to legally supply medical marijuana to more than 40,000 users authorized by Health Canada.
Dozens of companies across the country - including several in Alberta - are vying to fill that demand and have applied for a licence from Health Canada.
But while growers see medical marijuana as a potentially lucrative cash crop sanctioned by the federal government, its long history as an illicit drug has made local lawmakers and their rural constituents wary about allowing it in their communities.
Last week, Rocky View County outside Calgary changed its land-use bylaw to restrict medical marijuana operations to business and industrial areas. Neighbouring Mountain View County in central Alberta did the same earlier this month.
"There's a difference between cucumbers and marijuana," said Bob Barss, president of the Alberta Association of Municipal Districts and Counties.
"Because it's new, people are going to proceed with some caution."
The association, which represents 69 counties and municipal districts, doesn't have a position on medical marijuana, but Barss said local governments have the right to weigh the pros and cons of the industry and dictate where it operates.
Health Canada decided to contract medical marijuana distribution to commercial growers in response to health and safety concerns about the old system, which allowed licensed users to cultivate their own plants or designate a small-scale grower to provide their supply.
The government decided to scrap that system over concerns legally grown marijuana could be diverted to the criminal market and that home-based operations posed increased fire and safety risks.
A Federal Court injunction granted two weeks ago will allow patients to continue growing their own marijuana while a constitutional challenge to the new regulations goes through the courts.
The new system, which is unaffected by the court ruling, is supposed to eliminate those problems by requiring licence applicants to pass criminal background checks and build their facilities to strict specifications, with intrusion alarms and closed-circuit surveillance.
Yet some rural residents have been just as concerned about the new system's potential to attract crime, saying commercial grows could become targets of thieves trying to steal marijuana.
At recent public hearings in Mountain View and Rocky View, residents also voiced concerns over other issues, such as fire protection and smell.
The issue came up in Mountain View after a local consortium, ReLeaf Inc., announced it had applied for a Health Canada licence and planned to build a 50,000 square-foot greenhouse in the county.
Mountain View approved ReLeaf's development permit because it met the definition of permitted horticultural uses at the time, but has since rewritten its land-use bylaw.
"There were some people in the area who said they weren't opposed to the concept, but they weren't happy with the location," Mountain View Reeve Bruce Beattie said.
The amended bylaw will apply to any future medical marijuana growers seeking approval in Mountain View, but ReLeaf will be able to go ahead without relocating or applying to have its existing property re-zoned.
"We're not going to make those regulations retroactive," said Beattie.
In neighbouring Rocky View County, the municipal council found itself in a similar situation when a local company, Sundial Growers, applied for a Health Canada licence last year and began renovating a greenhouse on its land west of Airdrie.
Sundial owner Stan Swiatek previously grew cucumbers on the land and said medical marijuana complied with Rocky View's specifications for horticultural land use when the company began work last fall.
Rocky View council voted unanimously last week to amend its land-use bylaw to restrict medical marijuana grow operations to business and industrial areas, but Swiatek said the move won't stop his plans.
"It's business as usual," he said.
It's not known whether Rocky View will try to require Swiatek to apply for a re-zoning application: the county refused to comment for this article.
In addition to Sundial, Rocky View's amended bylaw could also affect two additional companies seeking to set up medical marijuana operations in the county.
An industry representative said municipalities risk driving jobs and tax revenue elsewhere if they're too strict about medical marijuana operations.
"If Alberta doesn't get its share because of these impediments then as an industry we will suffer a lot," said Mohyuddin Mirza of the Alberta Greenhouse Growers Association.
ReLeaf spokeswoman Elise Coppens said the company will be capable of supplying up to 6,000 medical marijuana users and its facility will provide up to 20 full-time jobs once it's complete later this year.
The company will comply with Health Canada rules mandating air scrubbers to eliminate odours and will go "over and above" requirements in many other areas, Coppens said.
Medical marijuana operations aren't supposed to have any visible signage for security reasons, but Coppens said ReLeaf will take that requirement a step further.
"We're getting (the property) landscaped and making it look aesthetically pleasing for our neighbours or anyone passing through their community," she said.
jvanrassel@calgaryherald.com( mailto:jvanrassel@calgaryherald.com )
Twitter.com/JasonvanRassel
© Copyright (c) The Calgary Herald
]]></text></news-item>