<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-BT41-DYBK-D000"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Rule of Law and Anti-Corruption Centre Hosts A Workshop on Anti-Money Laundering</title><source>Qatar News Agency</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Doha, March 31 (QNA) - A workshop on Anti-Money Laundering and Financial Crimes for official from the Qatari Justice Sector began here on Monday at the Rule of law and Anti-corruption Center. The event due to continue until next Wednesday, is organised in cooperation with the U.S Embassy Doha and the United States Department of Justice.
The workshop is a 3-day program which will include presentations from national and international experts in the fields of anti-money laundering, anti-corruption, and financial investigation techniques. Some of the topics that will be presented are Money Laundering Basic Concepts, Money Laundering Prosecution, Basic Financial Investigation Techniques, International Standards on Corruption, and Challenges in Conducting International Investigation.
Attendees include official, from the Qatari Public Prosecution Office, the Qatari Financial Information Unit, the Ministry of Interior, the Supreme Judiciary Council, the National Anti-Money Laundering committee and the Qatar Central Bank.
This workshop brings together practitioners and experts from eth United Sates and Qatar to discuss investigation techniques tailored to financial crimes, including money laundering and corruption. These crimes are not limited to any individual country.
It has become widely recognized in the past several years that crime has no borders, because money can be moved instantly and under layers of sell companies, trusts and beneficial ownership schemes that hide a criminal or leader's identity in order to effectively combat financial crimes and the illegal and dangerous flow of money, investigators and prosecutors must learn new techniques for tracing the flow of illegal money as it moves through the world banking system. (MORE)
MD
QNA 1157 GMT 2014/03/31

]]></text></news-item>