<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-9N51-JD6S-R3R1"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>16-year-old accused of 20 car break-ins</title><source>Winston-Salem Journal (North Carolina)</source><author>JOURNAL STAFF AND WIRE REPORT</author><text><![CDATA[A 16-year-old is being charged with breaking into 20 vehicles in Winston-Salem.
Officers with the Winston-Salem Police Department arrested Roland Wayne Pinnix III, of 1212-A W. Fourth St., Friday afternoon. Pinnix is charged with 20 counts of auto breaking and entering.
Police were responding to a report of an auto break-in on the 400 block of Horace Mann Avenue when they found Pinnix nearby. Police said he was interviewed and gave officers a statement about break-ins to approximately 20 vehicles through unlocked doors. No items were taken from the vehicles. A second suspect fled on foot and was not found, according to police reports.
Pinnix was placed in the Forsyth County Law Enforcement Detention Center under a $15,000 secured bond. His court date is April 17.
The investigation is ongoing. The Police Department requests that anyone with information regarding this crime contact Crimestoppers at 727-2800.
- Arika Herron
Authorities arrest 27 people in drug investigation
YADKINVILLE - Authorities have arrested 27 people and charged them with 172 drug offenses in a 12-month investigation called 'Operation Clean Sweep.' The suspects were arrested Thursday and Friday in Yadkin, Davie, Davidson, Wilkes and Forsyth counties, the Yadkin County Sheriff's Office said.
Among those arrested were Roy Lee Myers, 54, of Yadkinville, charged with five counts of trafficking in opiates and other offenses; Dennis Church Jr., 29, of Wilkesboro, charged with eight counts of trafficking in opiates and other offenses; and Harold Salmoms, 37, of the Hamptonville community, charged with the three counts of trafficking in opiates, the Sheriff's Office said.
Nino Robinson, 34, of Hamptonville was charged with four counts of trafficking in cocaine and other offenses, the Sheriff's Office said. Marilyn Alizabeth Rose Long, 22, of Winston-Salem was charged with two counts of conspiracy to traffic in cocaine and other offenses, the Sheriff's Office said Robert Wall Jr., 22, of Lexington was charged with five counts of trafficking in opiates and other offenses, the Sheriff's Office said.
- John Hinton
N.C. Zoo marks 40th anniversary with new exhibits
ASHEBORO - The North Carolina Zoo is celebrating its 40th anniversary in 2014 and has scheduled a series of weekend events to mark the milestone.
'Bugs: An Epic Adventure' is a new zoo attraction opening this weekend and continuing through the end of October. The exhibit features 13 giant, animatronic bugs created by Billings Productions of Allen, Texas. That's the same company that produced the popular 'Dinosaurs' exhibit featured at the zoo over the past two years.
Also opening this weekend will be the 'kidZone.' It provides a stream, mud café, rope bridge treetop experience, stone maze, live animal presentations and other educational programs designed especially for children.
- The Associated Press
Shots .red into a Greensboro home, no one injured
GREENSBORO -Police are investigating a reported shooting into a home Saturday afternoon.
At about 1:36 p.m., police were called to a home at 830 Terrell St. for the reported shooting.
Police said no one was injured when two to three shots were fired into the home.
No description of a possible shooter or a motive was given.
- News & Record
State Briefs
Duke Energy to begin cleanup in Danville
DANVILLE, Va. - A North Carolina power company will begin cleaning up a large coal ash deposit from the Dan River in Danville next week.
A park along the Dan will be closed Tuesday so Duke Energy can begin removing the toxic sludge from a massive spill upriver in North Carolina.
Danville officials say Duke expects the work to end in July.
The (Danville) Register & Bee reported that Duke crews and contractors will use the park as a staging area. The park includes a boat access ramp and a boathouse. The city will be compensated for revenue losses related to the closing.
Duke officials said the deposit spans 350 yards by 20 yards and is about a foot deep.
City, federal and state officials have said treated city water exceeds safedrinking standards.
Police: Man killed in shootout first shot wife
LINCOLNTON - Lincolnton police say the man they killed during a shootout admitted during a two-hour standoff that he fatally shot his estranged wife hours earlier.
Police say 40-year-old Anthony Ray Osburn of Lincolnton was killed in a blaze of gunfire early Friday. Authorities say he admitted to shooting 39-year-old Tara Lynn Osburn during negotiations for his surrender.
After a delivery driver discovered the woman's body outside a home east of Lincolnton on Thursday, an officer who stopped Osburn's pickup in the apartment complex where he lived reported being fired on.
A SWAT team eventually fired tear gas into his apartment. Authorities say Osburn walked out and again traded gunshots with officers. He was pronounced dead at the scene.
The SBI is investigating according to policy in officer-involved shootings.
Forest officials offer advice on ramp collection
ASHEVILLE - With warmer weather approaching, visitors to the Pisgah and Nantahala national forests will turn out to collect ramps.
But officials with U.S. Forest Service are asking people to avoid collecting too much.
Gary Kauffman, botanist with the National Forests in North Carolina, said there's been a decline in populations of ginseng and other forest products such as ramps. Kauffman said if their numbers get too low, the Forest Service may have to shorten the harvest season or ban the harvest altogether.
- The Associated Press
]]></text></news-item>