<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-0H21-JC17-F00D"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>EPA discusses updating its thresholds for fumes</title><source>Suburban Trends (Morris, North Jersey)</source><author>Leslie Scott</author><text><![CDATA[The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) announced that a proposal to modify the vapor intrusion work plan for the borough's contaminated Plume area is being considered by state and federal agencies.
This was announced at the public information session the EPA held March 19 to discuss updates on the cleanup for the area of contamination in the borough known as The Plume, where toxic vapors emanating from groundwater are entering into the homes above.
Some residents were not thrilled to hear that if the proposal is approved, the work plan to deal with the intrusion of toxic vapors could change.
In March 2013, the NJ Department of Environmental Protection (DEP) modified the screening levels for soil gas, ground water, and indoor air.
The EPA is currently looking at a proposal from DuPont, the company responsible for The Plume contamination. This proposal would allow the vapor intrusion program to be in line with the new screening guidelines.
EPA Project Manager Perry Katz said DuPont submitted a revised vapor intrusion work plan to the EPA and DEP in December 2013.
"We approved the (DEP) comparison levels but we didn't approve the revised work plan because there were a lot of details about the implementation that needed to be worked out," said Katz.
Once a decision regarding the proposal is made, Katz said the public will be made aware of the changes.
"We hope very soon we will come to terms with that work plan and communicate it to the community," said Katz.
Some residents at the meeting expressed that they were not happy to hear that there is a proposal to modify the vapor intrusion work plan.
Resident Jefferson LaSala said DEP officials assured the local environmental groups that the new vapor screening guidelines would not impact Pompton Lakes.
"That was said with the DEP present at CAG (Community Advisory Group) meetings multiple times," said LaSala.
At the meeting EPA officials said they were not aware this was promised to residents.
"I know that there is language in the documents regarding the vapor intrusion program that talk about if there were changes in the program that DuPont would have the ability to come back to the state and EPA and to basically put a proposal in to change the program consistent with the numbers," said Katz.
Plume resident Lisa Riggiola said, "Perry (EPA project manager Katz) you are talking about this like it's a done deal. I hear what you're saying, you're already saying, 'Oh, we're going to do this.' Well guess what, we don't want you to do this."
Councilman Mike Serra asked if the new numbers could change the configuration of The Plume.
Katz said he did not want to evaluate everyone's situation and that The Plume itself "doesn't change."
EPA officials said they did not want to go into details on how The Plume would be impacted because the proposal was not finalized.
"When we start to go out with this, that's all we are going to talk about [is this program] and hopefully we will have DEP and DuPont available to discuss where we are going with the program," said Katz.
Screening level changes
Screening levels are set help the EPA and DEP evaluate the cleanup of contamination sites.
DEP spokesperson Bob Considine said the screening levels were modified "due to changes in toxicity values and risk-based equations based on the most recent EPA Regional Screening Level Tables."
Under the its new groundwater screening levels for residential properties, the DEP increased the level of concern from 1 to 31 micrograms per cubic meter (ug/m3) for tetrachloroethylene (PCE) and from 1 to 2 ug/m3 for trichloroethylene (TCE).
The residential screening levels for indoor air increased from 3 to 9 ug/m3 for PCE and remained at 3 ug/m3 for TCE.
The screening levels for soil gas increased from 34 to 470 ug/m3 for PCE and it remained at 27 ug/m3 for TCE; however, according to DEP officials, DuPont has a site-specific soil gas screening level of 11ug/m3 for TCE in Pompton Lakes.
DuPont and the DEP declined to comment on the proposals being requested in the modified work plan.
"No changes to it have been approved to date. We don't typically comment on plans while they're under review," said Considine.
Background
DuPont operated the Pompton Lakes Works facility from 1902 to April 1994. Products manufactured at the facility included explosive powder containing mercury and lead, detonating fuses, electric blasting caps, metal wires, and aluminum and copper shells.
The manufacturing operations and waste-management practices contaminated soil, sediment, and ground water both on and off-site.
Lead and mercury from its operations were released into Acid Brook, which flows through the eastern part of the facility and discharges into the Acid Brook Delta of Pompton Lake.
DuPont's operations also contaminated the ground water with chlorinated volatile organic compounds, such as PCE, TCE, cis 1,2-dichloroethylene, and vinyl chloride.
In 2008 the community was made aware that the groundwater below 439 homes was emitting high levels of TCE and PCE vapors into the air.
Since this time the company has been make arrangements with every homeowner in the affected area, to test the air and install a system that would remove these vapors from the home.
]]></text></news-item>