<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-M581-JBHM-S03J"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Georgia High Court Eyes Easing Class-Action Threshold For Toxic Tort Suits</title><source>Superfund Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Georgia Supreme Court is weighing whether to uphold a lower court ruling certifying an environmental tort case involving a variety of property owners as a class action, a move that major industry groups say would be counter to U.S. Supreme Court precedent and numerous other federal and state courts and make Georgia an "outlier jurisdiction."
While the court has not yet ruled in Georgia-Pacific Consumer Products LP v. Ratner, et al., several justices during oral arguments last month appeared skeptical that the original plaintiffs in the case could be certified as a class, an action that creates large groups of plaintiffs that can seek heftier damage awards than if they pursue individual cases.
According to a video recording of the Feb. 17 arguments on the Georgia Supreme Court website, the state high court justices repeatedly questioned the plaintiffs' attorney John C. Bell Jr. on what common element linked the plaintiffs such that they could be certified as a class.
In the case, four homeowners sued Georgia-Pacific Consumer Products for nuisance, trespass and negligence over the release of hydrogen sulfide gas onto their properties from the company's nearby Savannah River Mill, which makes bath tissue, paper towels and napkins.
They asked the state trial court to make the case a class-action lawsuit, with a class consisting of 65 additional properties neighboring the plant, in order to seek monetary damages for the hydrogen sulfide releases.
The trial court certified the class and the state appeals court upheld the ruling, "finding that the trial court's definition of the class 'is unambiguous and the members of the class are readily identifiable from public records,'" according to a summary of the case written by the Georgia Supreme Court Office of Public Information (OPI).
Under Georgia law, "a class action is authorized if the members of the class share a common right and common questions of law or fact predominate over individual questions of law or fact," the appellate court ruled. "The character of the right sought to be enforced may be common although the facts may be different as to each member of the alleged class."
Georgia-Pacific appealed the case to the state supreme court, arguing the lower courts erred in certifying the class, in part because the claims of the named plaintiffs and the class cannot be resolved with common answers. The property owners are at varying distances to the plant and include owners of residences, industrial sites and forest land, resulting in very individualized claims, the company argues.
Unless reversed, the appeals court decision "will have grave adverse consequences for the integrity of class litigation in Georgia," Georgia-Pacific's attorneys contend, according to the OPI summary. "The Court of Appeals analysis 'puts Georgia out of step' [with other states and federal courts] . . . making class litigation the default instead of the exception.'"
The U.S. Chamber of Commerce, together with a coalition of Georgia industry groups, make similar arguments in a joint Feb. 7 amicus brief. The brief is available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID: 2465810)
"The decisions below are aberrations in class-action law that, if upheld, will endanger Georgia's manufacturing, chemical, and agricultural companies," the brief says.
The industry groups note that Georgia's class-action provisions, which are modeled on federal judicial rules, require members of a class to demonstrate both that common questions will predominate in the litigation over individual questions and that a class action is superior to other available procedures, such as consolidation or joinder of individual cases.
Numerous state and federal courts have repeatedly held "that these requirements are all but impossible to satisfy where, as here, plaintiffs claim that pollutants have caused a variety of adverse effects, over a number of years, on diverse and differently situated and exposed property holdings and on the health of individual owners," the brief says.
Court rulings to this effect have only increased in the wake of two recent class de-certifications by the U.S. Supreme Court -- the 2011 ruling in Wal-Mart Stores, Inc. v. Dukes and the 2013 ruling in Comcast v. Behrend.
The industry groups note that Georgia courts have denied class certification when individualized inquiries are needed to establish an element of plaintiffs' claims. "Until the decisions below, Georgia courts had refused to open an escape hatch from this rigorous analysis for class representatives who offer to defer individualized damages determinations to some later phase of the proceedings."
The groups cite several state and federal rulings that have relied on Dukes and Comcast to reject class certifications. "In short, the 'overwhelming majority' of courts that have rebuffed environmental tort class actions has grown since Dukes and Comcast. This Court should prevent Georgia from breaking ranks and becoming an outlier jurisdiction," the brief says.
During the Feb. 17 oral arguments, the plaintiffs' attorney faced multiple questions from the justices on how the plaintiffs could prove the commonality necessary to be considered a class. "How are you going to prove causation in a common way?" Justice David Nahmias asked, according to the video recording.
"First of all from their admissions this stuff is toxic. Second of all through experts," Bell responded.
"That's liability. That's not causation," Nahmias said.
Justice Harold Melton asked whether it wouldn't be better for the plaintiffs to seek class certification based on the type of property owned, such as residential, timber, commercial properties or vacant lands. "Aren't those disparate groups?" Melton asked.
Bell responded that the trial court has discretion at the damages phase to make those distinctions. There could be a unified damages awarded to the class, which later would be divided up based on individual injury by a court master, he said.
But Melton appeared unsatisfied with the answer, asking at least three more times some variation of the question "How do you get to commonality?"
Nahmias suggested that a divvying up of a large award was better suited to a settlement rather than a judicial judgment. "When you settle, you can do it however you want," he said.
But Bell said there is nothing to prohibit the trial court from making property-specific damages calculations. "I've seen it done, and it has worked smoothly," he said. -- Lara Beaven
]]></text></news-item>