<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-9NM1-JC3H-015M"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Teen's street plays tackle sexual abuse in India</title><source>The Detroit News (Michigan)</source><author>By, Shawn D. Lewis</author><text><![CDATA[The Detroit News
Bloomfield Hills - Home for Rohun Dhar is an affluent subdivision of sweeping estates stretched along winding hills.
Dad is a chemical engineer who owns an alternative energy company. Mom is a filmmaker.
But the Detroit Country Day School senior prefers trekking through remote villages across India, tackling the taboo subject of sexual abuse through free street plays he writes, composes and directs.
"I'm blessed to have all these resources, and it makes no sense not to maximize the potential," said Rohun, 17, a first-generation Indian-American. "A lot of us go to a privileged school, and enjoy a privileged life, but some are not really doing anything with it."
Sexual abuse is a tough subject to broach, especially in India's patriarchal culture, so Rohun engages audiences using vivid Bollywood-style song and dance in his productions, which average about 10 minutes. Some audiences who watched his plays last summer in India were receptive, while others were loath to expose secrets.
"I pass a microphone throughout the crowds following each performance, and some would tell me I shouldn't be talking about such things in public," Rohun said. "Surprisingly, it felt good, because that was what I was trying to do - open a dialogue."
He has visited his parents' homeland every year since he was 5 years old.
Speaking with The Detroit News at his family's home, Rohun was comfortably barefoot in his white-carpeted home recording studio, along with his younger brother, Amman Dhar, 15, a 10th-grader at Detroit Country Day. Rohun plays keyboards and Amman plays guitar. There's also a drum set in the room.
"I can tell you we have a very hush-hush nature about sexual abuse, because it's really not talked about in homes," said Rohun. "Children are not able to speak freely about it."
Reports indicate the number of rape cases in India's capital, New Delhi, have almost doubled since the gang rape and murder of a 23-year-old physiotherapy student on a bus Dec. 16, 2012. The incident grabbed international headlines, triggered protests and provoked a national debate about violence against women.
Much less is known about sexual abuse of children, according to an 88-page document, "Breaking the Silence: Child Sexual Abuse in India," produced by Human Rights Watch.
It says studies suggest more than 7,200 children, including infants, are raped every year in India; experts believe many more cases go unreported.
Enter Rohun Dhar and his mission.
He and his team of collaborators are completing a video of last summer's performances. (
His mother, Shailja Dhar, and sister, Raeshem Nijhon, were producers. Rohun tapped his uncle Vidhu Vinod Chopra of Mumbai (formerly Bombay), a film director and producer, to be executive producer for his future street plays. Chopra's 1978 documentary "An Encounter With Faces" was nominated for an Academy Award.
For now at least, Rohun is relying on the Internet to promote his campaign against sexual violence.
Rohun has posted two videos to YouTube - the trailer previewing last summer's shows, and one introducing Chopra. "The videos we have up on YouTube work only to spread awareness of the project, and are not necessarily built with a message or audience in mind," he said.
Last summer's play depicts a man's visit to relatives, including his nephew, a small boy. After being abused by his uncle, the boy tells his mother, who initially rejects his claims. She eventually believes her son, and the uncle is banished from the family.
Rohun said the internationally publicized gang rape and murder in December 2012 served as his impetus to delve deeper into sexual abuse, with an emphasis on children, especially after one of his friends revealed he had been sexually abused by an uncle.
"I was shocked and couldn't believe it," said Rohun. "Then I began researching it and knew I had to do something about it."
Aswin Punathambekar, a University of Michigan associate professor and expert on South Asian cultures, said Rohun's street plays can be "safe, but effective, communicative spaces for raising thorny and sensitive issues, and get a discussion going that is difficult to do in other contexts."
Rohun's mentor at Detroit Country Day agrees.
"Rohun possesses a great imagination, he understands the power of his speech, and his discipline is flawless," said Jeffrey Nahan, the school's executive director of fine, performing and communication arts. "... Rohun understands his responsibility to humanity. He strives to make a difference."
Rohun's parents expect nothing less of their son.
"Rohun has stepped beyond the normal boundaries of academic accomplishments to fight against and increase awareness of child abuse in our society; his approach to addressing this issue through art and music has provided a platform uncharted before. ... He makes me extremely proud," said his father, Subhash Dhar.
slewis@detroitnews.com
(313) 222-2296
Online: To watch a trailer of the video and interviews, go to www.detroitnews.com/oakland.
]]></text></news-item>