<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-G5K1-J9YR-G042"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Government braced for damning report into  Royal Mail privatisation than saw taxpayer lose out on £1bn</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>MATT WEST</author><text><![CDATA[The government and investment banks are bracing themselves for what is likely to be a highly critical assessment from the National Audit Office of the privatisation of Royal Mail.
The NAO will give its verdict of the £1.32billion stock market flotation of the 500 year old institution tomorrow.
The float, which took place six months ago, is already thought to have cost taxpayers more than £1billion.
The NAO is expected to add its own damning verdict of the privatisation to that of the Business, innovation and skills select committee of MPs, which has already conducted its own inquiry.
In what is likely to be a difficult week for Royal Mail it pushed through stamp and parcel price rises today.
Consumer groups criticised the move claiming the former monopoly was trying to profit from its market dominance.
The cost of a first class stamp is increasing by 2p to 62p and second class stamps are rising by 3p to 53p.
Royal Mail said it had 'thought carefully' about the impact on customers and its business before announcing the decision last month, pointing out that the last rise was two years ago.
It added its prices remained among the cheapest in Europe, and the company had the highest service standards of any major European country.
The average for a first class letter in Europe is 67p and 60p for second class.
A large letter first class stamp up to 100g increases by 3p to 93p, while a large second class stamp will go up by 4p to 73p.
Consumer Futures said the 3 per cent rise in first class and 5 per cent increase in second class stamp prices were above the current inflation rate
Since 2009, prices have increased by 59 per cent for first class and 77 per cent for second class, it said.
Dimitris Hiotis of pricing specialists Simon-Kucher & Partners, added: 'Consumers and businesses can expect price increases above inflation as long as Royal Mail has market power in letters and small packages, and the regulatory framework allows it.
'As Royal Mail is now a publically traded company with profit targets to meet, we expect the market to demand they maximise their ability to raise prices on an ongoing basis, particularly if transformation efforts are slower or cost more than expected and profits aren't delivered.
'The larger price increase on second-class stamps indicates consumers and businesses switch to second class as a result of price increases.
'Royal Mail wants to limit this switching down, and consumers can expect the gap to continue to close in future price rises to prevent this, probably until Royal Mail reaches the regulatory price cap on second-class of 57p.
'Consumers should stock up on first and second-class stamps prior to these annual price rises to avoid the price increases.'
Business Secretary Vince Cable and Michael Fallon, the minister in charge of postal affairs, have previously been accused of selling Royal Mail on the cheap.
The stock market flotation raised £2 billion, while postal workers shares equal to 10 per cent of the company's value. The Treasury retains 30 per cent.
The government has been criticised for relying too heavily on investment banks Lazards and Goldman Sachs, their advisers.
Evidence that 21 banks in the City on average valued the business at between £3.9billion and £4.8billion, with one institution saying it would be worth as much as £8.6billion, emerged after the sale.
Private investors who subscribed for £750-worth of shares, and who kept them, are sitting on a £525 profit.
This morning Royal mail shares were higher by 0.2 per cent at 565.5p.
]]></text></news-item>