<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-B2T1-JDKC-R0K0"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Pakistan: Erdogan implores voters to 'Ottoman slap' his foes</title><source>Right Vision News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ISTANBUL, April 1 -- Turkey's Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan lashed out on Saturday at his political enemies over a spate of damning online leaks, in passionate speeches on the eve of crucial local elections.
"They are shameless," he bellowed at one of five events in Istanbul to wrap up a marathon campaign, referring to followers of his declared nemesis, the reclusive US-based Muslim cleric Fethullah Gulen.
He has accused the 73-year-old imam and his loyalists in the Turkish police force and justice system of being behind a spate of wiretaps and social media leaks exposing corruption, and of going after Erdogan's political and business allies.
Erdogan and his Islamic-leaning party, in power for over a decade, face the first electoral test since being hit with the twin crises of mass protests and corruption allegations spread via Twitter, Facebook and YouTube.
"The vote you will cast tomorrow will expose this ring of treachery," Erdogan told a sea of flag-waving and chanting conservative supporters, some of whom climbed trees to catch a glimpse of the man they call the "sultan".
Erdogan urged voters to support his party and deal his foes an "Ottoman slap at the ballot box tomorrow" - a reference to an open-handed blow to the head said to have been a combat technique of Turkey's former imperial troops.
Although Erdogan's name won't be on the ballot in the mayoral and local assembly polls, he has campaigned tirelessly with multiple daily speeches to support candidates of his Justice and Development Party (AKP).
Erdogan, 60, was forced to cancel two campaign events on Friday - reportedly on doctors' orders to avoid permanent damage to his vocal cords - after his voice went alternately hoarse and squeaky earlier this week.
Undeterred, he resumed his punishing schedule Saturday with five municipal campaign events in Istanbul, the megacity of more than 15 million where he was once mayor.
In the latest YouTube leak, which the government has labelled "an act of espionage", participants in an apparently high-level security meeting are heard discussing plans to fabricate a pretext for military action in Syria.
Turkish police briefly detained Onder Aytac, an author on security issues who had claimed on TV before the YouTube leak that Turkey was preparing for a military operation in Syria
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Right Vision News. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>