<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-SN01-JB5M-W0RT"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Steel Authority of India Business Insight on Partnership, Corporate Crime, Capacity Expansion (March 22-28)</title><source>India Public Sector News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Partnership: Steel Authority of India (SAIL) has inked a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) with CII-Triveni Water Institute for improving water efficiency and maintaining better water management at its plant sites. Under the MoU, CII-Triveni Water will resolve all the issues related to water management of the company that includes water audits, rainwater harvesting and waste water treatment and purification.
Corruption/Scam: SAIL's manufactured TMT bars fake branding has led the Enforcement Directorate to seize Rs 70 million assets of two Chhattisgarh steel plants Pankaj Ispat Ltd and Alankar Alloys. It has been alleged that the two firms have used SAIL's trademark without having its authorisation, which is in violation of the Trade Marks Act. The public sector unit had registered a case in this regard in April 2013.
Partnership: SAIL has entered into an agreement with Siemens Ltd for a period of 3-year in order to increase the technical skills of its employees. It is the third consecutive MoU (Memorandum of Understanding) signed by the PSU with Siemens. As per the agreement, SAIL's workforce will be trained by Siemens in projects and other technical assessment of plants.
Management Quote: Manas Panda, Executive Director (HRD), SAIL spoke on partnership:
"We are in the process of modernizing our plants with newer installations. Through this agreement we aim to upgrade the competence of our work force and bring them up-to-date with the latest innovations and technologies."
Operation Expansion: SAIL's capacity expansion plan at its four plants Bokaro steel plant, Burnpur, Rourkela Steel Plant and Durgapur plant will be completed by September 2014. With the increase in capacity of these plants, SAIL hopes to take its annual steel output to 23 million tonnes from the current 14 million tonnes. Beside, the capacity expansion plan at Rashtriya Ispat Nigam (RINL) is expected to be wrapped up by the same period.
]]></text></news-item>