<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-RXP1-DXMS-80M2"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Philippines: BIR files P194.47-M tax evasion raps vs. Cedric Lee's firm</title><source>Thai News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Bureau of Internal Revenue filed on Thursday before the Department of Justice a P194.47-million tax evasion case against businessman Cedric Lee, his company, Izumo Contractors Inc., and two of its top officials.
Aside from Izumo Contractors Inc. and Lee as its president/chief executive officer, the two other respondents were the company's operating officer John K. Ong and chief financial officer Judy Gutierrez Lee.
In a press conference, BIR Commissioner Kim S. Jacinto-Henares said that they charged the respondents for willful attempt to evade or defeat tax and deliberate failure to supply the correct and accurate information in the annual Income Tax Return (ITR) for taxable years 2006, 2007, 2008 and 2009 in violation of Sections 254 and 255 of the National Internal Revenue Code.
Izumo is registered with the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) as a general contractor located at 8th Floor Galeria Corporate Center, EDSA corner Ortigas Avenue, Quezon City.
The case arose from a confidential information received by the BIR denouncing Izumo for tax evasion committed through non-declaration of income realized from its business.
Certifications showed that Izumo received a total amount of P302.63 million in income payments from 2006 to 2009 such as P80.64 million from the city governments of Butuan; San Juan City - P59.76 million; Pasay City - P12.36 million; provincial government of Davao del Sur - P113.33 million; and municipal government of Tagudin, Ilocos Sur - P36.54 million.
Investigation showed that Izumo declared in its ITR the amounts of P5.54 million in 2006, P9.14 million in 2007, P21.34 million in 2008 and P40.50 million in 2009.
Henares said that a comparison of the gross income declared by Izumo in the four years as against the income it received from its clients showed that it deliberately failed to declare its correct taxable base by substantially underdeclaring its taxable income by P88.79 million or 1,602 percent in 2006; P36.93 million or 404 percent in 2007; P9.49 million or 44 percent in 2008; and P91.20 million or 227 percent in 2009.
She added that Izumo was charged for a total tax liability amounting to P194.47 million for deficiency income taxes, inclusive of surcharges and interests such as P89.77 million for 2006, P33.78 million for 2007, P8.27 million for 2008 and P62.65 million for 2009. - PNA
]]></text></news-item>