<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-3631-F091-R52D"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Hawks boss implicated in R2m bribe scandal; Complainant alleges he 'made fraud and theft cases disappear'</title><source>The Star (South Africa)</source><author> ANGELIQUE SERRAO |AND LERATO MBANGENI angelique.serrao@inl.co.za lerato.mbangeni@inl.co.za</author><text><![CDATA[ALLEGATIONS of corruption and interference in criminal investigations have been levelled against the head of the Hawks in Gauteng, Major-General Shadrack Sibiya.
In a case before the Johannesburg High Court by Africa Cash 'n Carry chief executive Edrees Ahmed Hathurani, Sibiya, provincial head of the Directorate of Priority Crime Investigation, is accused of receiving bribes amounting to R2 million to make cases of fraud and theft Hathurani had opened against the company's director, Cassim Aysen, three employees and a supplier, disappear.
Hathurani wants the court to interdict Sibiya and Lieutenant General Anwa Dramat, national head of the Directorate of Priority Crime Investigation, from "interviewing, consulting or investigating any criminal matters pertaining to the applicant", and to order them to hand over dockets pertaining to the applicant to the minister of police. He wants an independent investigative unit assigned to the case.
Police Minister Nathi Mthethwa and National Director of Public Prosecutions Mxolisi Nxasana are cited as respondents.
Hathurani's affidavit and annexures, including a forensic audit, indicate the business lost R168m due to the alleged fraud.
The papers also contained affidavits from an employee who confirmed the criminal activity and admitted to being involved in the allegations.
Hathurani said the cases he had opened followed the normal course of arrest, detention, investigation and prosecution, "until the intervention of the second respondent (Sibiya)".
The papers say Sibiya convened a meeting in August between a Brigadier Magson, from the Specialised Commercial Crime Unit; Brigadier Ronnie Rajin, from the Joburg Central police station; and a Brigadier De Bruin, the cluster commander for Joburg.
"The second respondent (Sibiya) emphatically stated the conduct of Aysen did not constitute a criminal offence/s and it was a civil matter that did not warrant the attention of a criminal court."
The affidavit goes on to describe visits by SAPS and Hawks members to his business he said were intimidatory.
There were two affidavits alleging Sibiya had been paid to make the Africa Cash 'n Carry cases go away. One affidavit alleged a bribe of R2m.
Hathurani said Sibiya went to the police station with Aysen and collected all the dockets related to Africa Cash 'n Carry.
"I pause to mention that, as a lay person, I find it suspicious and unnerving that a high-ranking general would accompany an accused person to a police station and attempt to convince other members of the SAPS that a case is civil in nature and should not be prosecuted," the affidavit said.
Sibiya referred The Star to Hawks spokesman Paul Ramaloko, who said the State had responded to the allegations in responding papers which would be filed in court this week.
Ramaloko indicated the State would refute the allegations.
The case was brought before Judge Fayeeza Kathree-Setiloane, who said this was "a very important and serious matter". The matter was, however, not fully heard last week because State advocate Naomi Manaka said she'd not had time to file responding papers.
Arguing on behalf of the applicant, senior counsel Max Hodes agreed to remove the matter from the court until next week, but asked the judge make an interim protection order because the applicant's attorney Saleem Ebrahim's life and his family's lives had been threatened.
Hodes said the order should ban Hawks officers from communicating with the accused or Ebrahim.
The judge granted the interim order.
]]></text></news-item>