<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-9NM1-JC3H-0242"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>E-book buyers get refunds in $166M settlement</title><source>Palladium-Item (Richmond, Indiana)</source><author>By, Justin L. Mack</author><text><![CDATA[About 370,000 e-book buyers in Indiana will receive more than $2.6 million in refunds thanks to settlements reached between publishers and 33 state attorneys general.
The refunds are the result of a multistate price-fixing case involving five major U.S. publishers, according to Indiana Attorney General Greg Zoeller.
Refund amounts will range from about 73 cents to $3.17 per e-book, with the higher amounts for books on the New York Times best-seller list.
"Customers were ultimately the ones harmed by the decision made by Apple and these publishers to set e-book prices in order to knock out competition," Zoeller said. "Many states and the federal government worked diligently together to hold the parties responsible and ensure consumers were refunded."
The U.S. Department of Justice and 33 states filed lawsuits against Apple Inc., Hachette Book Group Inc., HarperCollins Publishers L.L.C., Penguin Group Inc., Simon & Schuster Inc., and Holtzbrinck Publishers LLC d/b/a Macmillan in 2012.
A news release from Zoeller's office states the suit was filed over allegations the companies conspired to artificially raise the retail prices of e-books.
In July 2013, Apple Inc. was found to have violated antitrust laws, and the company is appealing the decision, according to the release.
The U.S. District Court for the Southern District of New York approved the settlements with the publishers in December 2013.
A total of 23 million e-book customers nationwide will receive more than $166 million as a result of the settlements, according to the release.
The refund amount will be applied either as an account credit or made out in the form of a check and will be based on the number of eligible e-books a consumer bought between April 1, 2010, and May 21, 2012.
Comment on this story at palitem@pal-item.com
Find free e-books and help with e-readers
Several local libraries are subscribing to e-book services and some offer classes on how to use e-readers. Contact your local library about those services.
For instance, Morrisson-Reeves Library in Richmond is offering upcoming e-book classes. On April 10, classes include: 9:15 a.m., Kindle; 10:30 a.m., non-Kindle ebooks; and 11:45 a.m., audiobooks. Classes are also offered on May 15: 3:30 p.m., Kindle; 4:45 p.m., non-Kindle ebooks; and 6 p.m., audiobooks. Classes are free but registration is required at the Audio-Visual department, at http://www.mrlinfo.org/events-computer-classes.html or (765) 966-8291, ext. 111. Registration begins no earlier than two weeks before the class. Classes are limited to 14 participants.
]]></text></news-item>