<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-NNY1-JCDN-4009"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>A duty to Danville</title><source>The Roanoke Times (Virginia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Battles pitting economic and environmental interests provide standard fodder for political debates, but more often the two are complementary.
Roanoke Valley economic development leaders have long recognized the symbiotic relationship and incorporated the region's natural assets into their sales pitches. Likewise, Danville has banked on its river to lead the city's evolution from a tobacco and textile town to a hub for technology and tourism.
Entrepreneurs brainstorm in red brick warehouses along the Dan River in the revitalized downtown, while visitors can stroll the river walk that feeds into a mountain bike trail, or plunge into the water for a canoe trip.
"In Danville, we're intimate with the river," said City Manager Joe King in an interview last week. "I'm sitting in my office looking at the river right now."
But after working hard to secure "scenic river" status for a stretch of the waterway, city leaders watched helplessly last month as its currents turned gray. A stormwater pipe burst beneath a 27-acre coal ash pond 25miles from Danville, dumping 39,000 tons of power plant waste and coating 70 miles of riverbed in a sludge laced with arsenic, mercury and lead.
A spokeswoman for Duke Energy, owner of the earthen pond, told The Associated Press, "We are responsible for costs directly related to this spill."
King said he is hopeful that the North Carolina utility will make good on its promises, saying, "We are going to hold Duke to its word." He'd be wise to make a mental note of the word "directly."
Danville officials are preparing three studies to assess the impact of the spill on their city while acknowledging the impossibility of full compensation. The negative publicity puts them at a disadvantage in competing for new businesses, some of which they are aware of and others that may dismiss the city without making contact.
King said the city's reputation and economic wellbeing will be factored into damage assessments, along with more easily quantified variables such as overtime for workers at the water treatment plant who have put in extra effort to keep drinking water safe. Although communities can and have bounced back from even more extreme disasters, he said, "We'll be on everybody's coal spill map forever."
"We don't see this as a payday," he added. "We wish it had never happened."
Danville's most immediate need is for Duke to take visible and prompt steps toward remediation. A 300-by-50-yard deposit of coal sludge near the city's water treatment plant is scheduled for removal within the next week or two, a crucial signal for residents as well as business prospects. A longer-term cure will require removal of the remaining ash from the spill site and financial relief for affected communities.
Danville leaders must be vigilant. The Dan River stretches between two states, neither possessing a stellar record on environmental protections. Indeed, environmental groups had sued Duke after North Carolina officials failed to address groundwater contamination from other ash ponds, only to have the state intervene with a paltry $99,000 fine. State officials yanked that slap-on-the-wrist settlement, which didn't even require Duke to remove ash from leaky ponds, after the February spill.
The Dan River debacle should be a lesson to both states that "business-friendly" is no longer a code word for tolerating dirty and dangerous environmental abuses. Twenty-first century businesses and their communities are demanding clean and safe places to work and live. Those who don't get with the program should expect to pay for their mess.
]]></text></news-item>