<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW2-M581-JBHM-S01T"><date>2014-03-30</date><title>SEAB Seeks Broader Disclosure Of Fracking Chemicals Despite Trade Secret Fears</title><source>Clean Energy Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[An Energy Department (DOE) advisory panel has unanimously approved a draft report urging regulators to strengthen disclosure requirements for chemicals used in hydraulic fracturing operations, brushing aside industry concerns that the panel's advice would violate trade secret protections contained in federal environmental laws.
At a March 28 meeting of the Secretary of Energy Advisory Board (SEAB) task force slated with examining FracFocus 2.0, the latest iteration of a voluntary, state-run database of chemicals used in fracking, key members of the panel acknowledged industry concerns that their call for broader disclosure of fracking chemicals could threaten trade secrets.
But the panelists nevertheless urged regulators to strengthen disclosure requirements, saying they must "balance" the industry concerns with the need to gain public confidence that fracking is safe. The final report reflects a "judgment that balances the potential of sacrificing trade secrets with benefits to public and industry of getting public confidence about chemicals," said John Deutch, chair of the SEAB task force.
Deutch acknowledged that concerns raised by industry that one of the report's key recommendations Ð making the database more searchable so that data could be mined and aggregated by environmental groups, industry, regulators and the public Ð could give some companies competitive advantages.
"I don't think that's a trivial matter, but we have to weigh" that consideration against concerns from communities about the level of disclosure from oil and gas companies that drill in their region, Deutch said. "There's a balance."
During the meeting, the panel unanimously approved its report, which recommended that regulators use the State Review of Oil and Gas Regulations (STRONGER) -- a federal and state board created by EPA to evaluate the adequacy of state energy production oversight -- to craft and facilitate adoptions of "stringent criteria" for trade secret exemptions and a process for determining compliance with that criteria, including a mechanism for third parties to challenge trade secret assertions. The report marks the latest call for regulators to strengthen disclosure requirements, though many efforts so far have been stymied due to policymakers' difficulties balancing competing industry concerns over disclosure of trade secret and environmentalists' fears over inadequate disclosures.
The SEAB group was created in response to concerns from then-Senate energy committee Chairman Ron Wyden (D-OR) and environmentalists who were alarmed that the Obama administration and many states were planning to allow operators to report their chemicals to FracFocus in lieu of disclosure to regulators, potentially eliminating data regulators may need as well as any enforcement mechanism.
The FracFocus database, launched in April 2011, is a key source of data that EPA is using in its massive study on the impact of the drilling practice on water quality, slated for submission to Congress in 2016. Since its launch, nearly a dozen states have passed laws or adopted rules that either require drillers to disclose their chemical usage to the database or allow disclosure to FracFocus in lieu of or in addition to disclosure to the state.
States that mandate disclosure to FracFocus include Texas, Utah and North Dakota while states that allow disclosure to the database include Colorado, Louisiana and Montana.
Industry Concerns
At the time that Wyden sought the panel, the Bureau of Land Management (BLM) was also considering using the database as a disclosure mechanism in its upcoming rules for drilling operations on federal lands, though the SEAB report says the proposed BLM rules "do not yet meet the high disclosure standards that [a prior SEAB] Subcommittee recommended that BLM adopt."
But industry groups have challenged some components of the draft report, saying that the recommendations to list chemicals without their associated volumes may not actually prevent reverse engineering, that developing a standard for verifying trade secret claims would be duplicative and unnecessary and may conflict with existing federal laws, and other criticisms.
"We do not believe the idea that 'trade secrets can be protected by reporting the raw chemicals separately from the additive products they go into' is consistent or compliant with other Federal legislation," including the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide & Rodenticide Act and Toxic Substances Control Act, Nalco Champion, a chemical manufacturer, says in March 25 comments on a draft version of the report.
Nalco says that competitors in the oil and gas industry are aware of the classes of chemicals used for specific applications, and providing the information publicly can "significantly enhance" the ability of a competitor to reverse engineer. "Although development work would have to be conducted to come up with a usable formulation, knowing a specific chemical is being used in fracturing operations gives competitors a jump-start in cloning proprietary technology," the comments say.
And in joint comments on the draft report filed March 25 by the Independent Petroleum Association of America, American Petroleum Institute, America's Natural Gas Alliance and American Exploration & Production Council, the trade groups raise similar concerns. The groups say that trade secret laws already outline clear rationale that the "primary policy consideration underlying trade secret protection is the desire to encourage research and development by providing protection to the originator of business information," citing a 1974 Supreme Court ruling,Kewanee Oil Company v. Bicron Corp.
The groups also point out that trade secret laws at federal and state levels already exist Ð including penalties for making false claims -- and that courts have "generally held that the law allows companies to protect any information that is valuable and that provides a potential economic advantage over others who do not possess the information."Moreover, the groups say they do not support a "one-size-fits-all regulatory approach to state disclosure requirements."
Despite the industry concerns, the SEAB report pushes for a series of additional steps to strengthen disclosure requirements. For example, the report urged FracFocus to list chemicals claimed as trade secrets separately from the related additives to allow for greater disclosure while still preventing reverse engineering and expanding it to include disclosure of water quality data for water used as the base in fracking mixtures.
The report also urges DOE to conduct a four- to six-month study on a range of issues related to trade secret claims within the oil and gas industry, including trends, the percentage of wells with one or more fracking chemicals claimed as trade secrets, and other issues, in coordination with BLM and EPA.
And it further states that any trade secret exemptions BLM allows in its rules should include a "rigorous process" for making claims, verifying claims and allowing for third-party challenges. -- Bridget DiCosmo(bdicosmo@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>