<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW3-M311-F125-1018"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Emissions-area families hope regulator's report will call for pollution controls</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EDMONTON - Brian Labrecque, his father and brother are waiting anxiously Monday to see if the Alberta Energy Regulator will take steps to clean up smelly bitumen fumes that forced the farmers off their land south of Peace River.
The report from January 's public inquiry into hydrocarbon emissions that residents say are causing serious health problems was originally scheduled for release Monday though the regulator declined to confirm a release date.
"We're hoping the AER will call for new regulations to cover tank top emissions from this CHOPS production method," said Labrecque.
In the CHOPS (Cold Heavy Oil Production with Sand) method, oilsand is augered up into huge surface tanks where it is heated to separate the oil and sand and melt the bitumen for shipping.
The fumes from heating the bitumen, when released into the air, are causing health problems including dizziness, headaches, fatigue, cognitive impairment, among farmers near the Reno field operated by Calgary-based Baytex, the unprecedented public inquiry heard.
Labrecque said it's been a two-year battle with Baytext to get some pollution controls on the tank top fumes, so the sooner the report is released, the better.
"It's very upsetting to wait. Can they not see Baytex is the reason we had to move off our land?" said Labrecque.
Baytex Energy, which operates 86 heated tanks near the Labrecque land, does not use pollution control equipment on all tanks.
Baytex spokesperson Andrew Loosely said the company is committed to the promise it made at the inquiry to install the vapour control equipment on all tanks.
"We're going ahead to get all he permits required," he added.
The inquiry heard that the regulator does not have the authority to order such equipment be installed - though companies operating in the area, such as Shell, already use tank top vapour control devices to contain the fumes.
Even if the inquiry report recommends new regulations to cover tank top emissions, it will likely be months before they are put into force, says Keith Wilson, lawyer for the area landowners.
With this report, the regulator has a chance "to move ahead toward its goal of responsible energy development" if it does the right thing, says Wilson.
"If the AER takes no action, it will send a signal about their lack of commitment to responsible development and a signal to other companies about putting profit over responsible development," said Wilson.
"These are hard working Alberta families not opposed to the industry and they've been harmed."
Wilson has also applied for an injunction in Peace River to order a halt to production until control equipment is installed to contain the fumes.
Meanwhile, Monday also marks the official transfer of responsibility for environmental protection of laws in the oilpatch from Alberta Environment to the regulator.
The new regulator, officially started last June, is designed to make it faster to get new energy projects approved and put enforcement of environment laws over air, water and public land with the industry-funded regulator.
spratt@edmontonjournal.com( mailto:spratt@edmontonjournal.com )( mailto:spratt@edmontonjournal.com )
© Copyright (c) The Edmonton Journal
]]></text></news-item>