<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW3-15H1-DY91-H000"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Norwegian gov't urged to further cut greenhouse gas emissions</title><source>Xinhua General News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Norwegian government was urged by environmentalist groups to take tougher actions to cut greenhouse gas emissions after the IPCC published its second report on climate change and global impacts on Monday.
The new report issued by the United Nations' Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) should make everyone do more to cut greenhouse gas emissions, said the Friends of the Earth, Norway's oldest environmentalist organization set up in 1914.
Lars Haltbrekken, chief of the Friends of the Earth, called on Norwegian politicians, businesses and the general public to seriously tackle the issue, which he said affects all people on our planet, especially the poorest.
"This is quite unfair," Haltbrrekken said, arguing that the rich part of the world has created the climate problem.
Countries like Norway must take a leading position in resolving the problem, said Haltbrekken.
The Young Friends of the Earth Norway, another influential environmentalist group in Norway, said that the latest IPCC report should serve as a "wake-up call" for the Norwegian government.
Stronger and more frequent extreme weather events, food and water shortages are some of the things which are in store for human beings if the trend continues, said the youth organization, which called Norwegian politicians to act.
The Green Party in Norway said that the Norwegian government needs to take concrete steps to reduce emissions of greenhouse gases, according to local media reports.
"There is only one solution to this is to cut greenhouse gas emissions. Norway must do it and do it quickly," said Rasmus Hansson, a member of parliament from the Green Party.
The greenhouse gas emissions have increased over the past 20 years in Norway as a result of a massive focus on oil business and the failure to take concrete measures for emission reductions, Hansson charged.
Bellona, a foundation in Norway devoted to finding sustainable solutions to meet climate change challenges, said that the IPCC report is expected to put more pressure on the current Norwegian government to correct what is seen as a passive climate policy Norway has adopted over the years.
The IPCC is scheduled to publish its third report next month in Berlin, Germany.
]]></text></news-item>