<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW3-F381-DYTG-S02V"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>EPA looked askance at DENR’s proposed coal ash settlement with Duke</title><source>The News &amp; Observer (Raleigh, North Carolina)</source><author> Craig Jarvis; cjarvis@newsobserver.com</author><text><![CDATA[The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency thought North Carolina regulators were too lenient when they came up with a settlement with Duke Energy over coal ash plants that imposed a relatively small fine.
The EPA’s questioning of the proposed settlement in 2013 surfaced in thousands of emails and other records that the state Department of Environment and Natural Resources recently made public in response to numerous records requests by the news media, advocates and others.
The records also portray the tensions among state regulators, their superiors and utility companies over the past four years as North Carolina began paying more attention to coal ash storage ponds, in the wake of the catastrophic spill of the material in Tennessee in 2008.
A far smaller spill – although the third largest in U.S. history – occurred at Duke Energy’s plant in Rockingham County on Feb. 2, polluting the Dan River with coal ash sludge and wastewater. The spill occurred when a metal pipe running beneath the dam collapsed.
A federal grand jury is investigating that spill and taking a close look at all 14 of the utility’s plants with coal ash ponds. Inspections had raised warnings about that pipe as far back as 1986, but Duke only monitored the water flowing out of the pipe rather than the recommended sending video cameras into them to check for leaks.
The EPA, in comments submitted to DENR on the proposed settlement last year, questioned the size of the penalties of $51,500 for the Asheville plant and $36,000 for the Riverbend plant in Gaston County, in addition to cost reimbursements bringing the total liability to $99,111.
That amount “seems low considering the number of years these facilities are alleged to have been out of compliance,” the EPA response says. However, since the federal agency didn’t have information that DENR had incorrectly applied its penalty policy, it would be difficult to challenge the fines, the response says.
The EPA also thought more testing and monitoring for pollution should be required. DENR says the settlement was appropriate, and that the main thrust of it required Duke to clean up and monitor the sites.
Jarvis: 919-829-4576; Twitter: @CraigJ_NandO
]]></text></news-item>