<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW3-FJW1-JD6S-R3NR"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>VGS touts safety record</title><source>Rutland Herald (Vermont)</source><author>Bruce Edwards; STAFF WRITER</author><text><![CDATA[A gas leak and subsequent explosion that killed eight people in New York City earlier this month has again raised questions about the safety of the nation's natural gas infrastructure.
In Vermont, the state's only provider of natural gas has been serving residents and businesses in Chittenden and Franklin counties for nearly 50 years with one significant incident during the past 11 years.
Vermont Gas Systems operates 70 miles of gas transmission lines and 733 miles of distribution lines. It's the distribution lines that feed gas directly to the company's 40,000 customers in 17 communities in the two counties.
According to the Pipeline & Hazardous Materials Administration of the U.S. Department of Transportation, between 2004 and the end of last year, there were no reported incidents involving VGS.
The last major incident occurred in 2003.
William Jordan, director of engineering at the Department of Public Service, said Wednesday the incident occurred Feb. 2, 2003, in Williston. A fire broke out after a mass of ice fell from a roof of an apartment building, damaging the gas regulator/meter. There were no injuries, but damage was assessed at $216,682.
(The Department of Transportation defines a significant incident as one involving a fatality, injury or damage in excess of $50,000 in 1984 dollars.)
In 2011, the Public Service Board approved a settlement between VGS and the Department of Public Service related to 31 alleged violations of federal gas fire code safety standards.
In return for having the alleged violations dismissed, VGS agreed to notify contractors and customers of the need to paint customer-owned piping and gas meter assembly components.
Safety record
Since 1994, the DOT reported 1,893 incidents nationwide involving gas transmission lines resulting in 41 fatalities, 195 injuries and $1.6 billion in property damage.
Over that same 20-year period, there were 2,604 incidents involving gas distribution lines resulting in 264 fatalities, 1,086 injuries and $963.5 million in property damage.
The 10-year average is 138 incidents, 11 fatalities, 43 injuries and $74.3 million in property damage.
Vermont Gas Systems, a subsidiary of Gaz Metro of Montreal, has embarked on an aggressive expansion. The company recently received state approval to extend its pipeline south from Chittenden County to Middlebury.
Phase II of the Addison Rutland Natural Gas Project would take a westerly route from Middlebury to Five-Mile Point in Shoreham and across a 5,000-foot section of Lake Champlain to serve the International Paper mill in Ticonderoga, N.Y. Phase III would bring the pipeline farther south to Rutland.
It's the industry's overall safety record that concerns Paul Burns of the Vermont Public Interest Research Group. Burns said gas leaks and explosions across the country happen all too often and should be of concern to Vermonters.
"Nobody is suggesting it's going to be a daily occurrence but it is a very real risk that I think homeowners, who are anywhere near this, need to be aware of," said Burns, VPIRG's executive director.
VGS: Safety First
"Safety is job one for us. Our customers are our most important focus and we take significant steps to keep them safe," said company spokesman Steve Wark.
Because VGS only entered the Vermont market in 1965, Wark said the pipeline infrastructure is more contemporary than found in other states.
He said VGS has no bare or cast iron in the ground. It was an old cast iron main that was blamed for the recent New York City explosion.
Wark explained that the steel transmission lines are coated against corrosion. In addition, he said there is a zinc ribbon attached to sections of the pipe that serves as a sort of corrosive magnet.
He said the company does experience minor leaks from time to time.
Citing DOT figures, Wark said the national average for gas leaks - both large and small - is 28.12 per 100 miles compared to six leaks per 100 miles for VGS.
"Our system is significantly tighter than anything you would see in the national average," he said.
Wark also said VGS has a policy of fixing leaks immediately, which isn't always the case with other gas companies.
He said the company has a rigorous inspection routine that includes round-the-clock pressure monitoring, monthly aerial inspection to locate any physical encroachment that could cause a breach, system-wide ground inspections twice a year to detect possible leaks, and special winter inspections of the distribution network every two weeks.
Wark said the system is more susceptible to leaks during the winter because of the freezing and shifting of the ground.
Jordan of the Department of Public Service said with only one reportable incident in more than 10 years, VGS has a good safety record.
"They go above and beyond the federal code in a number of ways," he said.
Jordan said unlike other companies VGS fixes all leaks that it discovers. He also said VGS has a system "that is relatively new and so the material that's in the ground is not some of the problematic material that other companies have that are very old such as cast iron, wrought iron or bare steel."
Lake crossing
Under Lake Champlain, Wark said, a steel 10-inch pipe would be buried 30 feet under the lake bed using what's called horizontal, directional drilling.
In opposing the pipeline project, VPIRG has raised concerns about the continued use of fossil fuels and the importation of natural gas from Canada that's extracted using hydraulic fracking.
But VPIRG has also expressed concern about the safety record of natural gas.
Burns said the Lake Champlain leg of the project presents its own set of potential problems. Buried under the lake bed, he said it raises the issue of the pipeline's life span and what happens if the steel deteriorates over time.
"Will the material they're using now, hold up better 50, 70, a hundred years from now?" Burns asked. "I mean who's to say. And the danger underneath the lake is not only it jeopardizes a precious natural resource but that it is incredibly hard to get to in terms of fixing it."
It's one reason why Burns said VPIRG want the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission to retain jurisdiction and not accede that to the state Public Service Board. VGS has filed for a waiver with FERC to allow the PSB to oversee the permit process for Phase II.
Wark said any leak under the lake could be repaired quickly, starting with shutting down the flow of gas.
But he also said the chances of a leak are remote with the pipeline designed to withstand corrosion and seismic movement of the lake bed. And because it's under the lake bed, he said there's little likelihood the line would be damaged by a third party, which is often the case when pipelines are damaged or breached on land.
VGS already runs transmission lines under the Winooski, Lamoille and Missisquoi rivers. Wark said the company has never encountered a leak.
Old pipes
A DOT report, "The State of the National Pipeline Infrastructure," found: "In spite of its gradually improving safety performance, some pipe has been in the ground for a long time."
More than 50 percent of the nation's pipelines were built in the 1950s and 1960s (and some even earlier) "during the creation of the interstate pipeline network built in response to the huge demand for energy in the thriving post-World War II economy."
Gas transmission pipelines are made from steel while distribution lines are built from cast iron and newer lines from plastic.
The old cast-iron lines in place are a concern because of they're prone to stress from the ground's movement.
Weld failures, corrosion and excavation damage are the major causes of significant incidents involving gas transmission lines.
Incidents involving the smaller distribution lines are most often the result of damage from motor vehicles not engaged in excavation (outside force damage), excavation damage, corrosion and the largest cause, "all other causes," which make up 43 percent of all significant incidents. The latter category includes "incidents caused by deterioration of the pipe material."
In the distribution system, there was approximately one leak for every eight miles of main and one leak for every two miles of service line.
But even the new plastic distribution lines are a cause for concern.
"The National Transportation Safety Board reported that plastic pipe installed in natural gas systems from the 1960s through the early 1980s may be vulnerable to brittle-like cracking resulting in gas leakage and potential hazards to the public," the DOT report concluded.
All 733 miles of VGS distribution lines are made from high density polyethylene plastic. "These are designed to meet or exceed the current specifications," Wark said.
Bur he also acknowledged that plastic is not foolproof.
"There is no perfect material," he said. "And that's why the inspection processes are so important."
bruce.edwards
@rutlandherald.com
]]></text></news-item>