<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW3-B291-JCMN-Y0P8"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Congressional Investigators Find That Regulators Twice Declined to Investigate GM’s Ignition Switch Flaws</title><source>FairWarning</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 31, 2014 (FairWarning:http://www.fairwarning.org Delivered by Newstex) New details bolster contention that both regulators and GM ignored or dismissed warnings about deadly defect. U.S regulators decided not to open an inquiry on the ignition switches of Chevrolet Cobalts and other cars even after their own investigators reported in 2007 that they knew of four fatal crashes, 29 complaints and 14 other reports showing that the problem disabled air bags, according to a memo[1] from a House subcommittee. In 2010, regulators with the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration again came to the same decision after receiving more reports that air bags weren’t deploying. Congressional panels beginning hearings this week will press NHTSA and General Motors on why they missed several opportunities during the past decade to alert the public to the dangers. The Wall Street Journal[2], The New York Times[3]
Questions persist a year after a broken pipeline spilled an estimated 210,000 gallons of oil into an Arkansas neighborhood. The most critical mystery yet to be resolved for the public: What caused ExxonMobil’s Pegasus pipeline to break apart while the line was running well below its maximum approved pressure? All the public knows now is that a metallurgical report completed last July concluded that substandard pipe-making methods left tiny cracks near the lengthwise seams on the 1940s-era pipe. Those micro-cracks grew into dangerous “hook cracks,” and then something—or a combination of things—caused at least one hook crack to open up a 22-foot gash in Mayflower, Ark. There’s been no news about the cause or the pipeline’s condition since. Exxon has said only that it is conducting additional tests. InsideClimate News[4] Australia asks five countries challenging its tobacco plain packaging law to speed their complaints. Indonesia, Ukraine, Cuba, Honduras and the Dominican Republic have launched complaints at the World Trade Organization to overturn Australia’s law, which bans corporate logos and requires cigarettes to be sold in drab green packs. Australia hopes its laws will reduce smoking, and other countries have said they may follow suit, based on the WTO case’s outcome. An Australian diplomat told the WTO that the legal challenges were having a “regulatory chilling” effect on other countries. As FairWarning has reported[5], tobacco companies have tried to use international trade agreements to thwart the toughest anti-smoking rules and have paid legal fees for countries taking Australia before the WTO. Reuters[6], The Guardian[7] Report accuses tobacco companies of promoting scare stories claiming that plain packaging spurs smuggling. T[8]he assessment[9], published in the journal Tobacco Control, urges skepticism in evaluating industry claims about the potential impact of rules under consideration in the United Kingdom requiring cigarettes to be sold in plain packages. The peer-reviewed assessment also found that there are credible allegations that the industry has been complicit in fostering illegal trade in its products. ”Tobacco industry data on the illicit trade is totally unreliable,” said one of the report’s authors, Anna Gilmore, of the University of Bath. “Their methodology is never fully transparent. Their misleading claims … should be seen for what they are -– a desperate bid to prevent plain packaging from being implemented.” The Guardian[10] U.S. report estimates that some form of autism afflicts 1 in 68 children. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention has regularly raised its estimates since setting up a surveillance system more than a decade ago. The last estimate, in 2012, was 1 in 88, up from 1 in 110 two years before that. As in the past, researchers could not say what is driving the increase. While the role of environmental factors remains an open question, rising awareness of the disorder, greater detection and improved access to services have all been significant factors. To make estimates, CDC researchers comb through health and education records for hundreds of thousands of 8-year-olds, looking for indications of autism — either a formal diagnosis or symptoms of the disorder. Los Angeles Times[11] Compiled by Stuart Silverstein [1]: http://docs.house.gov/meetings/IF/IF02/20140401/102033/HHRG-113-IF02-20140401-SD002.pdf [2]: http://online.wsj.com/news/articles/SB10001424052702304157204579471613766178646?mg=reno64-wsjurl=http%3A%2F%2Fonline.wsj.com%2Farticle%2FSB10001424052702304157204579471613766178646.html [3]: http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/31/business/us-regulators-declined-full-inquiry-into-gm-ignition-flaws-memo-shows.html?rref=businessmodule=Ribbonversion=originregion=Headeraction=clickcontentCollection=Business%20Daypgtype=article [4]: http://insideclimatenews.org/news/20140328/one-year-after-exxons-arkansas-spill-8-crucial-questions-still-unanswered [5]: http://www.fairwarning.org/2012/11/as-nations-try-to-snuff-out-smoking-cigarette-makers-use-trade-treaties-to-fire-up-legal-challenges/ [6]: http://www.reuters.com/article/2014/03/27/us-wto-tobacco-idUSBREA2Q0T520140327 [7]: http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/mar/27/indonesia-granted-right-to-challenge-australias-plain-packaging-laws [8]: http://tobaccocontrol.bmj.com/content/early/2014/03/10/tobaccocontrol-2013-051397.abstract [9]: http://tobaccocontrol.bmj.com/content/early/2014/03/10/tobaccocontrol-2013-051397.abstract [10]: http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2014/mar/30/tobacco-cigarette-smuggling-scare-plain-packs [11]: http://www.latimes.com/science/sciencenow/la-sci-sn-autism-prevalence-cdc-20140327,0,2274205.story

]]></text></news-item>