<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW4-40J1-DYWV-N00P"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Gas price hike deferred</title><source>Country Report Select</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Event
The Election Commission has asked the government to defer a hike in gas prices that was scheduled to come into effect from April 1st until after the general election in mid-May.
Analysis
India is the world's fourth-largest energy consumer and has largely maintained gas prices below global price levels. Gas producers, including state-run ones, say that this discourages them from investing in gas exploration and production. Under the current policy, gas prices have been fixed at US$4.20 per million British thermal units since 2009. This pricing policy expires on March 31st 2014 and in June 2013 the government approved a new pricing formula for the next five years that would come into effect in April 2014. The new pricing policy is based on the simple average of the price of Indian gas imports and the weighted average of gas prices at major trading hubs in the UK, US and Japan. The new formula could almost double the price of domestically produced gas.
According to the government, the increase in gas prices would ensure higher returns for government-operated and private firms and encourage investment in exploration. However, according to critics, the move to raise gas prices would benefit energy major, Reliance Industries, India's largest private corporation and the only significant private gas producer. Several petitions against the hike are pending in India's Supreme Court. Meanwhile, the Aam Aadmi Party, which made an impressive debut in state elections in Delhi in 2013 on an anti-corruption platform, had asked the Election Commission (EC) to stay the gas price hike until after the general election. The EC has the authority to direct the government and political parties on matters that could unfairly influence electoral outcomes when the code of conduct is in force (the code of conduct comes into effect as soon as the election schedule is announced).
In late March the EC wrote to the Ministry for Petroleum saying that the price hike could be deferred. The newly elected government, which will take charge in mid-May, will reconsider the gas pricing formula.
Our inflation forecasts have incorporated an increase in gas prices in the second quarter of 2014. In light of the deferral of the gas price hike we will will be revising our inflation forecasts down.
]]></text></news-item>