<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW4-5B81-DYN6-W17X"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Panel discusses Mayflower oil spill effects</title><source>Associated Press State &amp; Local</source><author>CHRISTINA HUYNH, Associated Press</author><text><![CDATA[LITTLE ROCK, Ark. (AP) - A year after a major oil spill in a small Arkansas town, a congressman says that while communities believe they are ready for a disaster, there's always something else to do to prepare.
The Clinton School of Public Service invited public officials to its campus in Little Rock on Monday to discuss what they may have learned from the March 29, 2013, spill in Mayflower.
"You're never as ready as you think you are," said Rep. Tim Griffin, R-Ark., whose district includes the town. "You're never as ready as you need to be."
More than 200,000 gallons of heavy crude spilled from ExxonMobil's Pegasus pipeline beneath Mayflower, soiling a neighborhood and threatening Lake Conway, a popular place to fish. The spill has triggered more than a dozen lawsuits, including one by the state.
Faulkner County Judge Allen Dodson, the chief administrator for the county where the spill occurred, said residents don't want to suffer through a similar incident.
"To state the obvious, the No. 1 lesson learned with the Pegasus pipeline rupture is that we do not need another rupture," he said.
ExxonMobil has blamed a manufacturing defect in the 65-year-old Pegasus pipeline.
Most of the areas contaminated by the oil leak have been cleaned, however some oil remains in Lake Conway's Dawson Cove. State regulators have approved a plan to clean up those areas.
The pipeline, which runs about 850 miles from Illinois to the Texas Gulf Coast, was closed following last year's spill. The U.S. government has approved a plan to restart a section of the pipeline in Texas. But in Arkansas, the company has only submitted a plan to rehabilitate it, the Log Cabin Democrat newspaper of Conway reported Monday.
About 20 lawsuits have been filed against ExxonMobil, many seeking damages due to health problems or reduced property values.
Arkansas Attorney General Dustin McDaniel also has filed a joint lawsuit with U.S. Attorney Christopher Thyer. ExxonMobil has asked that the lawsuit be dismissed.
]]></text></news-item>