<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW4-5B81-F03R-N4X3"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>﻿Passing the waste dump hot potato until it explodes</title><source>The Bangkok Post</source><author>prf.admin</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 28, 2014 (The Bangkok Post:http://feeds.feedblitz.com/prorssbp Delivered by Newstex) There is something smelly about the open garbage dump that caught fire and spewed toxic fumes across several districts in Samut Prakan and Bangkok. First of all, the officials who should know didn't know whether the dump contained industrial waste even though it is situated near the Bang Pu Industrial Estate.
The director-general of industrial works didn't know. The chief of Praeksa Tambon Administration Organisation, which has jurisdiction over the dump site, didn't know. Reporters didn't ask the Samut Prakan governor whether he knew because they knew he didn't know. Every one of them said in interviews that the dump held mainly household garbage but was reluctant to say whether it also contained industrial garbage. Secondly, this dump had been operating for over 10 years, and official accounts are murky whether it had the required permits for operation. Some accounts said the operators once had a landfill operating licence, which had expired or been revoked years ago. Other accounts said they had a permit for fertiliser production. How can you have garbage-laden trucks going in and out of a huge garbage dump site for over 10 years without attracting any curious inquiries from the authorities? The garbage dump has drawn many complaints from local residents who must endure foul smells and the rumbling noise of garbage trucks day, in day out. To avoid being accused of dereliction of duty, the local authorities had taken action by penalising the landfill operators with a fine of 2,000 baht a couple of times. But it's odd that the complaints failed to pique officials' curiosity to investigate the legality of the dump site and determine whether toxic waste had been dumped there since it was so close to a major industrial estate. Thirdly, even granted that most of the garbage in the dump was actually household garbage, isn't it also odd that no officials had inquired as to its origin or the reason it was dumped there? As we know, local authorities — whether tambon administrations, municipalities or cities — are responsible for household waste management. The usual means of disposal is landfilling, so they find a piece of land and build a landfill site according to engineering and environmental principles to ensure it does not contaminate the environment. If they deem it necessary, they may outsource the task to private companies. But they remain responsible for ensuring that the private operators comply with all relevant rules and regulations and that their facilities are up to standard. We have to assume that no one in his right mind would simply open up their land to take in garbage without the promise of financial returns. We have to assume then that the Phraeksa dump site operators ran their facilities with official blessing in the form of contracts from some local authorities. So far no one has claimed ownership of the garbage there. Why? If a dump site for household waste could kick up so much stink, imagine what a stink it could cause if toxic industrial waste were discovered there. Officials tiptoe around the question, saying coyly that they would rather wait for lab results to clarify the issue. Most people have, however, made up their mind that toxic waste is in the garbage mix. The business of industrial waste disposal is like the twilight zone. It's a dirty and lucrative business. Proper disposal is expensive. So many industrialists cut corners by hiring 'private disposal companies' to take care of their waste. Like most people, the industrialists don't care to know where the waste goes once it leaves their premises. Everyone involved knows what has been happening. For years officials have known that much of the waste — 60%, according to the Industrial Works Department — had been dumped illegally. They know it's a huge problem. As the country becomes ever more industrialised, the volume of toxic waste increases. Officials know that, without proper management, the untreated waste would inevitably wreak havoc with the environment, posing health threats to animals and humans alike. Studies were done and recommendations made. Implementation of a simple tool called Pollutants Release and Transfer Register, for example, would provide easy access to key environmental data from industrial facilities, including the amounts of pollutants released into the air, water and land as well as off-site transfers of waste. Environmentalists have also called for public disclosure of raw materials and chemicals used by each industrial plant. The information would help in identifying sources of waste and in determining emergency responses. Officials, seemingly paralysed by the magnitude of the problem, have chosen instead to sit on their hands, leaving the problem to fester. On second thought, maybe they were not paralysed by the problem but by something else. It is an open secret that the lucrative underground business of toxic waste disposal is dominated by people with influence, including local politicians, moneyed landowners and businessmen. These people command respect from local residents and officials in the same way a mafia don commands respect. Many of them are in a position to 'make an offer that you can't refuse'. While the memory of it is still fresh, the dump fire at Phraeksa should be seized as an opportunity to set things right. The public should put pressure on the government to implement recommendations that increase transparency and strengthen the public's role in the licensing and monitoring of garbage dump sites and waste management in general. The fire may have been a shocking experience for the people of Bangkok and Samut Prakan but it was by no means a surprise. It was simply a time bomb that exploded. The problem is there are many such bombs ticking away around the country and any one of them could explode without warning any time with untold consequences. It's time that politicians and officials acted to defuse them or face the public's wrath.

]]></text></news-item>