<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW4-40J1-DYWV-N010"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Garment shift</title><source>Country Report Select</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Recent developments in Asian garment manufacturing point to continued expansion and diversification. Although China still dominates the industry and will do so for the foreseeable future, better environmental enforcement, higher labour and production costs, and an appreciating renminbi are making "Made in China" garments more expensive. Many producers and buyers are turning their attention to South-east Asia and South Asia-attracted in part by these countries' trade preferences in relation to developed markets-but concerns persist about inadequate safety and labour standards.
The main production platforms outside China are now in Bangladesh, Cambodia, Indonesia, Vietnam, India and Pakistan. Other countries are about to join the club, such as newly liberalising Myanmar. Since the EU granted preferential trade access for garments in 2013, Myanmar's garment industry has been growing rapidly. It exported garments worth more than US$1bn in 2013-around 20% of the total for Cambodia.
Trade aid remains key to the success of garment manufacturers in almost all countries in developing Asia. The EU, the biggest buyer of garments, grants Bangladesh, Cambodia and Myanmar the same extensive trade preferences under its Everything But Arms (EBA) initiative for countries defined by the UN as least developed countries. Richer developing countries, such as China, India and Vietnam, are treated slightly less generously under the EU's standard Generalised System of Preferences (GSP), but some countries enjoy an enhanced version of this system called GSP+. Sri Lanka's GSP+ status was suspended in 2010 because of human rights violations. In late 2013 the EU announced, along with certain changes to the GSP system, that Pakistan would be granted GSP+ status and that China would lose its GSP status in January 2015.
Asia's garment industry is highly diverse. Some countries, such as Cambodia, rely heavily on the import of inputs including fabrics, buttons and zips. Others, like Bangladesh and Pakistan, produce some of the inputs domestically. In Bangladesh, Pakistan and Sri Lanka, local entrepreneurs own the factories and often suppliers. In Myanmar and Cambodia, on the other hand, the industry is almost entirely owned by foreigners-Koreans, Taiwanese and Chinese.
Sources of comparative advantage differ across countries and products, but low wages and the ability to ramp up production at short notice remain crucial in the labour-intensive and fast-moving garment industry. In Bangladesh, for instance, the minimum wage has been raised repeatedly, but implementation and enforcement have been erratic. Unions are either ineffective or do not exist at all, and they have only limited wage-bargaining power. By contrast, there are around 1,300 registered trade unions in Cambodia, where single factories typically have multiple trade unions. In Cambodia strikes are frequent, as in Bangladesh, but tend to be more disruptive.
India's rigid labour laws have kept its garment industry small relative to its vast labour force. In broad terms, there are two distinct garment industries in India. In the northern states, such as Uttar Pradesh and Rajasthan, small-scale cottage industries produce garments of relatively high value. In the south, around Bangalore, garment manufacturing occurs on an industrial scale. But unlike in neighbouring Bangladesh, manufacturers in south India are faced with labour shortages, partly reflecting the fact that local jobs in the automotive and services sector are more attractive and there is only limited internal labour migration to fill the gap.
Wages in Bangladesh are generally lower than in China, India, Cambodia or Vietnam, its main competitors. However, productivity and safety standards are also low. Some 4m workers produced garments with an export value of around US$20bn in Bangladesh in 2013. Cambodian factories employ 450,000 workers, who produced around US$5bn (data vary) in exports in 2013. The diverse and largely unregulated industry in Bangladesh has come under scrutiny following the collapse of a factory, Rana Plaza, that left at least 1,100 workers dead. The catastrophe triggered attempts by brands and retailers, mostly from Western countries, to improve safety and working standards in Bangladeshi factories. Given that such efforts could raise operational costs, many observers predicted an exodus of orders from Bangladesh to Vietnam, Cambodia and Indonesia. However, recent trade figures show that Bangladesh's garment exports have been largely unaffected by the catastrophe.
Buyers' economic rationale for sticking with Bangladeshi factories is compelling. First, Bangladesh's production capacity, with around 5,000 factories, is vast. It is nearly on a par with the total combined capacity of its main competitors in South-east Asia. According to McKinsey, a consultancy, there are 2,500 factories in Indonesia, 2,000 in Vietnam and 260 in Cambodia. Second, wages are lower in Bangladesh. Although the monthly minimum wage was raised to US$68 in 2013, to keep costs down factories can hire new workers or not promote existing staff-or increase sub-contracting to the shadow economy, where wages are lower than in the formal sector. Still, even at the going rate, labour is cheaper than in Cambodia, where the monthly minimum wage rose to US$100 in February 2014. Third, there is no substitute for Bangladesh when it comes to producing cheap garments. Buyers place orders outside Bangladesh to spread risk, not because they could not source more from Bangladesh. For many retailers and brands, sourcing from Bangladesh provides the highest margins and is therefore essential to their business success.
Despite Bangladesh's seemingly dominant position in Asian garment manufacturing (excluding China), the collapse of Rana Plaza has not been entirely without consequence. The Accord on Fire and Building Safety in Bangladesh, a legally binding five-year initiative by retailers and brands, may force necessary improvements on factories. Some Bangladeshi manufacturers are concerned, arguing that none of their competitors abroad is coming under equivalent pressure and negative attention. But although the initiative may increase costs, it will also allow Western buyers and brands to deflect reputational damage, ensuring Bangladeshi manufacturers' continued access to their biggest markets.
]]></text></news-item>