<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW4-5YY1-DXJR-H0CN"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Pollution in Chanda a grave issue, but not during polls</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Mazhar Ali</author><text><![CDATA[Chandrapur: Chandrapur district known for its high mineral deposits, green cover and tiger population, has earned a dubious distinction of being one of the most polluted places in the country during recent years. While pollution has escalated respiratory and skin related diseases among the citizens, it is also adversely affecting crops around the industrial areas.
Industrial clusters like Chandrapur, Ghugus, Ballarpur and Tadali, transport hubs in Wani, Gadchandur and Padoli, and areas surrounding over 40 coal mines in the constituency are faced with particularly intense pollution. Though pollution menace is of a matter of grave concern for citizens, the issue is missing in the poll campaigns in Chandrapur Lok Sabha constituency.
Congress has fielded cabinet minister Sanjay Deotale in the fray. Despite being a guardian minister and minister for environment for more than three years, he has done little for controlling pollution in Chandrapur. His apathy towards the heavy pollution caused by Chandrapur Super Thermal Power Station (CSTPS) had brought him bitter criticism from environmentalists and social organizations. Now that he is running for parliamentary elections, the key issue of pollution control appears to be missing from his campaign.
BJP candidate and sitting MP, Hansraj Ahir has always been vocal about heavy pollution, but has failed to pressurize the government agencies to act against the polluting industries during his three terms as Member of Parliament. Though he boasts of being an advocate of control of pollution, the issue is missing from his poll campaign speech.
The third major contender in the fray is AAP candidate Wamanrao Chatap. Even as pollution is adversely affecting the crops in this industrial belt, the Shetkari Sanghatana strongman and farmer leader Chatap too has spoken little about pollution during his poll campaign. He is apparently relying more on national issues taken up by AAP, while grave issue of pollution here has taken back seat.
"People in Chandrapur are more conscious about the local issues concerning them. Pollution has posed a grave threat to public health and agriculture in the district. While national issues of inflation, corruption, good governance, women's security etc are important, candidates taking up issue of pollution and environment in Chandrapur would appeal to voters most," said Suresh Chopne, president of NGO Green Planet Society that works for environmental protection.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>