<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW4-41F1-DYT5-300F"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Czech ex-PM denies corruption offer was made in Tatra case</title><source>CTK National News Wire</source><author>hol</author><text><![CDATA[Former prime minister Mirek Topolanek ruled out in his testimony in court today that then deputy defence minister Martin Bartak had asked for a bribe to solve problems with the Tatra lorries' supply for the Czech military at a meeting in the United States.
U.S. representatives of the Tatra lorry maker came unexpectedly to the meeting at a shooting range in Centerville, USA, with the aim to lobby, Topolanek said, adding that their behaviour was unusual.
According to the charges, Bartak in his capacity as then first deputy defence minister attempted to influence the contract on the supply of several hundred Tatra off-road vehicles.
The charges also say Bartak, a member of the PM's delegation, demanded a five-million-dollar bribe from Tatra's supervisory board head William Cabaniss, former U.S. ambassador to the Czech Republic, to settle the firm's dispute with Prague that threatened Tatra's lucrative order, during his business trip to the United States in 2008.
"I completely rule out that Martin (Bartak) made a corruption offer during this conversation," Topolanek told the Prague Municipal Court today.
He added that the Tatra representatives were trying to lobby and they addressed him at a shooting range as they feared to lose the contract over a dispute with Praga, a subcontractor of axles.
The axles were breaking and this is why Tatra terminated its contract with Praga and the firms found themselves in a lawsuit.
Topolanek said the then government had taken no steps to withdraw from the contract.
In spite of it, Tatra should have agreed with and compensated the Czech firm for the loss it suffered, Topolanek added.
Cabaniss and then Tatra manger Duncan Sellars gave their testimonies in court previously. They both said Bartak had asked for a bribe in the United States.
Another defendant in the case is lobbyist Michal Smrz, owner of the MPI Group arms firm.
He is charged with an attempt to extract money from Tatra representatives by pretending influence on and contacts with high-ranking government and Defence Ministry officials.
In January 2008, Smrz allegedly promised then Tatra director general Ronald Adams to arrange a personal meeting with the prime minister (Topolanek) for money.
Both Bartak and Smrz plead innocent. They call the charges absolute nonsense and an expediently fabricated construct.
($1=19.928 crowns)
hol/dr/ms
]]></text></news-item>