<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW6-KRC1-JCBG-S186"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>TO TAKE A STAND; Heads up, eyes on the ball!</title><source>BusinessWorld</source><author>Rafael M. Alunan III</author><text><![CDATA[AN IMPORTANT forum will be held tomorrow, April 2, at the Asian Institute of Management on "Understanding 21st Century China: All Under Heaven?" Speaking before a "by invitation" crowd are Prof. Marwyn Samuels from Beijing University; ADB economist Liping Zheng; and China expert Chito Sta. Romana. They will tackle China's geopolitics, economy, demographics and people-to-people relations in these dangerous times. It comes a few days after we filed our "Memorial" (legal brief) before ITLOS (International Tribunal for the Law of the Sea) on March 30.
It's also timely at the eve of Cold War 2. We're seeing the return of old enemies challenging each other. The vanquished - China, Russia - plus their satellites and allies (North Korea, Iran and non-state actors) seek to fill a gradually widening vacuum, as the great powers (US, UK, Europe and Japan) are believed to be in steady decline and retreat. They are estimated to be weakening economically and waning in their resolve to use force globally to hold the line as budgets shrink and as the costs of war weigh down on their publics.
The belief that economic interdependence deters war is being severely tested. Vladimir Putin seems to have confirmed suspicions of the West's weakness when Russia took over Crimea in blitzkrieg fashion. NATO hasn't responded militarily although the US has imposed sanctions that Putin boasts Russia will be able to withstand. China has obviously backed Russia's territorial grab. For years China's been annexing the South China Sea, albeit in gradual or "salami slice" fashion. Will interdependence hold the peace in the face of resurging aggression, revenge and ambition?
China is the rising hegemon in our part of the world, subjecting us and other countries in the region to its uncouth brand of imperialism as it gradually annexes the entire South China Sea in pursuit of its geopolitical and economic interests. We're defenseless for now, having been betrayed by our political leaders and their cronies who ignored national interests, hijacked public policies and diverted public monies for their vested interests, some in collaboration with China.
Today, we're feeling the winds of war stretching from the Pacific to the Indian Ocean, with the South China Sea in the center. Our coveted strategic geographical location is both boon and bane: bane because that makes us a natural target and front-line state in a hot regional conflict; boon because we can leverage that with our allies to control the seas enveloping our archipelago. Our location is our best asset to an alliance out to deter China's illegal expansion via its 9-dash line (now 10, used to be 11) and first/second island chain strategies, by providing them safe harbor and vital services.
Providing access invites opportunities to strengthen our national security across-the-board: our economy from beneficial regional trade arrangements; internal security from collaborative intelligence efforts; and external defense from access to affordable weapons, systems and technologies. If the country is to be shielded from China's hostile intent to grab our territory and resources in partial fulfillment of their grand design to rule the region and control the world, we must address the imperatives of national security.
While we're still in the process of building our external defenses, we must do everything we can to prevent our backyard from being taken over by a hostile nation that has a clear edge in terms of its military might and capacity to ruin a country's internal affairs. We need to clear the decks of infiltrators, Trojan horses and potential saboteurs. We must settle the socioeconomic and cultural differences that divide us to stand united. And we must end our culture of corruption and impunity if we are to survive at all.
We must hurry because we're at risk. China has threatened us with consequences should we file our "Memorial" in ITLOS, which we did. Its Foreign Ministry spokesman said it would damage bilateral relations. Would? Our ties are already damaged by China's:
We filed our Memorial on March 30 as a free and sovereign country to challenge China's spurious historical claim of the South China Sea without legal proof. It thinks it can bully small nations into submission and fool the world into accepting its unworthy say-so as it flouts international law, i.e., the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea (UNCLOS) that it co-signed. As its Foreign Minister remarked last year: "China's a big country and yours is small." The middle finger would be too polite a response, don't you think?
Instead of joining us in ITLOS to peacefully resolve the dispute that China itself created, it has threatened retaliation instead. That could take the form of expanded economic sanctions, the sabotage of vital infrastructure and continued subversion of the government, society and economy. As to when and how exactly - simultaneously or sequentially, gradually or suddenly - depends on China's timing considerations. Who knows? It could start today, April Fool's Day.
One thing is certain - China has a track record of carrying out its threats sooner or later. Vigilance is essential; it is the price we pay for freedom. We need a "whole of nation" approach to mitigate the clear and present danger that China poses to our human, economic and ecological security. All that require leadership, a clear national security policy and strategy to guide our government, military, and citizenry in the dangerous years ahead.
]]></text></news-item>