<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW6-YV61-DYS4-D09K"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Yesterday in Brief for March 31, 2014</title><source>Russia &amp; CIS Business and Financial Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Digest of headline news from March 28 to 11:30 a.m. Moscow time on March 31:
BUSINESS & FINANCE
*** DOLLAR, EURO DECLINE AGAINST RUBLE IN EARLY TRADING
The dollar and euro declined against the ruble in early trading on the Moscow Exchange on Monday.
The dollar was averaging 35.67 rubles/$1 after the first minute, 11 kopecks below the close on Friday and 2 kopecks below the official exchange rate.
The euro began the day at 49.06 rubles/EUR1, 10 kopecks lower than the close on Friday but 1 kopeck above the official exchange rate.
The bi-currency basket ($0.55 and EUR0.45) started the day at 41.7 rubles, 10.5 kopecks above Friday's closing value.
*** RUSSIAN STOCKS OPEN HIGHER ON MONDAY
Russian stock indexes opened 0.1% higher on Monday amid easing tensions over Ukraine and gains on exchanges abroad.
The MICEX index was up 0.1% to 1,345.59 points and the RTS index was up 0.1% to 1,187.24 as of 10:01 a.m. Moscow time.
The blue chips posted gains of as much as 1%.
*** ULYUKAYEV: REASONABLE TO INCREASE 2014 BUDGET DEFICIT BY 1% OF GDP TO COMPENSATE FOR CAPITAL OUTFLOW
Increasing the 2014 federal budget deficit by around 1% of GDP would be reasonable in order to compensate for large capital outflow, Economic Development Minister Alexei Ulyukayev said at an interactive seminar with state authorities.
He said it was important to include a procedure to support the budget's independence from capital outflow. "If capital outflow is very large, like it was this year, then [we] must compensate. The way I see it, an additional 1 percentage point of GDP of the budget deficit would be a mechanism that compensates for capital outflow figures that exist this year," Ulyukayev said.
*** RUSSIA, N. KOREA TO SWITCH TO RUBLE PAYMENTS - MINISTRY
Russian Minister of Far East Development Aleksandr Galushka and North Korean Foreign Trade Minister Ri Ryong Nam signed a protocol for development of bilateral cooperation in Pyongyang, the Russian Ministry of Far East Development said in a press release.
"The parties deemed it expedient to bring their mutual trade to a totally new level with an increase of up to $1 billion (per year) by 2020, by facilitating the transition to mutual payments in rubles and the resolution of inter-banking interaction problems," the press release said.
*** MILLER, DVORKOVICH TO HOLD GAS TALKS IN BEIJING ON APRIL 9
The next round of Russian-Chinese consultations on deliveries of Russian gas to China will be held in Beijing on April 9, several sources familiar with the situation told Interfax.
The Russian delegation to the talks will be led by Gazprom (MOEX: GAZP) CEO Alexei Miller and Deputy Prime Minister Arkady Dvorkovich.
A spokesman confirmed that Dvorkovich would be in Beijing on April 9.
*** LUKOIL STARTS OIL PRODUCTION AT WEST QURNA-2 FIELD IN IRAQ
The Russian oil company Lukoil has started oil production at the West Qurna-2 oil field in Iraq, an Interfax correspondent reported from the first oil ceremony on Saturday.
Russian President Vladimir Putin said in a greeting message to Iraqi Prime Minister Nuri al-Maliki, which Deputy Prime Minister Arkady Dvorkovich read out at the ceremony, that the launch of this major project by Lukoil is an important step in the development of mutually beneficial practical cooperation between the two countries.
*** LUKOIL CONFIRMS INTEREST IN NASIRIYA PROJECT IN IRAQ
Russian oil company Lukoil (MOEX: LKOH) has confirmed its interest in the Nasiriya project in Iraq.
"We managed to handle the risks at West Qurna 2 that analysts and investors were concerned about. Now we have opened up opportunities for new projects in Iraq and will step up negotiations on new Iraqi projects," Lukoil vice president and head of Lukoil Overseas, the operator of the company's international upstream projects, Andrei Kuzyaev told reporters on Saturday.
*** ROSNEFT SHOWS INTEREST IN SEVERAL PROJECTS IN IRAQ
Rosneft takes interest in several projects in Iraq, Russian Vice Premier Arkady Dvorkovich has told journalists.
"Rosneft has interest in projects in Iraq. In fact, there are several of them. I must point out that our companies operate in line with the laws of the countries of their presence. All Russian companies respect the rules spelled out by the government of Iraq," he said at a joint press conference with Iraqi Vice Deputy Prime Minister for Energy Affairs Husayn al-Shahristani.
Al-Shahristani said that the Iraqi Cabinet had notified Russian companies that operations in Kurdistan should be authorized by the Iraq government.
*** NOVATEK OPTIMISTIC ABOUT PROSPECTS FOR YAMAL LNG ON KOREAN MARKET
The head of the management board at Russia's independent gas producer Novatek (MOEX: NVTK), Leonid Mikhelson, has said he sees promise in dialog with Korean liquefied natural gas importers.
"I had a meeting with the Kogas President [this week] and he spoke about the company's strategy as regards this matter. Their position is that working with one or two suppliers is wrong," Mikhelson said on the sidelines of the Gastech 2014 conference in Seoul. "They want to build up and diversify their portfolio of long-term contracts and bring in different manufacturers from various regions. We have been informed Korea's energy strategy is currently being revised. The country intends to increase consumption of gas which means we have a topic for discussion," he said.
*** TOTAL WILL CONTINUE TO BUY NOVATEK SHARES - MIKHELSON
The French energy company Total will continue to buy stock in Russia's independent gas producer Novatek (MOEX: NVTK) after the first of next month, a timeframe set by the partners earlier for Total to increase its stock interest in Novatek to 19.4%
Total became a Novatek shareholder in April of 2011, when it bought 12.09% of the company's shares. The agreement between the two companies involved the French company increasing its stake to 19.4% before April 1 this year.
*** NOVATEK CHIEF SEES NO RISKS FOR CO. AND YAMAL LNG FROM U.S. SANCTIONS VS. TIMCHENKO
The head of independent gas producer Novatek (MOEX: NVTK), Leonid Mikhelson, has said he does not see any risks for the company emerging from the imposition of sanctions on company stockholder Gennady Timchenko by the United States.
"I don't see any potential risks to our company in connection with this situation. There have been too much PR activity on this subject and that's why the market is now facing investor uncertainty, which has led to the high volatility of the market. I think this is temporary," Mikhelson said during an interview with several news agencies in response to an Interfax question.
*** NOVATEK WON'T EXCEED BUYBACK ALLOCATION TO AVOID REDUCING SHARE LIQUIDITY - MIKHELSON
Novatek (MOEX: NVTK) has so far spent only a fraction of the total allocation for its ongoing buyback program, but it will not risk a reduction in share liquidity by exceeding that amount, Novatek chief Leonid Mikheslon told journalists.
"As you know, our company has started a buyback program. I'm buying shares myself and I'm glad there are new investors, who buy shares at current prices and see prospects for capitalization growth for Novatek," Mikhelson said.
*** GAZPROM MULLS JOINING PROJECT TO BUILD POWER PLANT IN TURKEY
Gazprom (MOEX: GAZP) is discussing the possibility of buying the 890-MW Eurostar combined cycle power plant that is being built in Turkey, a source familiar with the progress of the negotiations told Interfax.
The seller - the MetCap group is being represented in the deal by Raiffeisen Zentralbank. It is offering to sell 100% of the special purpose vehicle Verbena Enerji Sanayii ve Ticaret A.S.
For the buyer, payment for joining the project will be compensation for historical costs - several tens of millions of euros - and subsequent independent financing of the project, which amounts to more than half a billion euros.
*** FIRST TRANCHE OF IMF LOAN FOR UKRAINE COULD TOTAL AROUND $3 BLN - MINFIN
The International Monetary Fund (IMF) could begin carrying out its $14-18 billion stand-by agreement with Ukraine by issuing the first $3 billion tranche of the loan, Ukrainian Finance Minister Alexander Shlapak told journalists in Kyiv on Friday following a governmental meeting.
"We have not yet come to a final agreement with the IMF. There was a promise in the draft. [...] They are now ready to talk about the first tranche for around $3 billion," he said.
The IMF's mission reached a working-level agreement on March 27 with Ukrainian leadership on opening a two-year credit of between $14 billion and $18 billion.
POLITICS & SOCIETY
*** LAVROV: RUSSIA, U.S. TO WORK TOGETHER WITH UKRAINIAN GOVT, PEOPLE ON CRISIS SETTLEMENT
Russia and the United States have agreed on the joint work with the Ukrainian government and people on the resolution of the Ukrainian crisis, Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov said.
"We have agreed to work with the Ukrainian government and the Ukrainian people in a more comprehensive manner and insist on measures towards the achievement of such primary goals as the rights of national minorities, language rights, the accomplishment of tasks of the disarmament of paramilitary forces and provocateurs, the inclusive process of the constitutional reforms, and a free and fair election consistent with objective international criteria," the minister said in Paris early on Monday morning after four-hour negotiations with U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry.
*** LAVROV: U.S. WON'T LIFT BAN ON MANPADS DELIVERY TO SYRIA
The United States does not intend to lift the ban on MANPADS deliveries to the Syrian opposition, and U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry has reaffirmed that, Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov said.
"We have asked about media reports concerning the discussion of MANPADS deliveries to the Syrian opposition during President Obama's visit to Saudi Arabia," he replied to an Interfax question early on Monday morning after four-hour negotiations with the U.S. secretary of state.
*** LAVROV REPORTS PENDING 5+2 CONSULTATIONS ON TRANSDNIESTRIA
Transdniestrian settlement consultations in the 5+2 format, involving Russia and Ukraine, will be held shortly, Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov said.
"Actually, ten to twelve days from now consultations will be held in the 5+2 format, in which Russia and Ukraine are the guarantors, the OSCE is the intermediary, Transdniestria and Chisinau are the conflicting sides and the United States and the European Union are the observers," he told reporters in Paris.
*** RUSSIAN FOREIGN MINISTRY SAYS RESTRICTIONS IMPOSED BY BERN ON BILATERAL TIES ARE "COUNTER-PRODUCTIVE"
Moscow has expressed regret over the position taken by Bern in response to the events in Ukraine and has described the latest restrictions imposed on Russian-Swiss bilateral cooperation as "unfounded".
"We express our regret over the unilateral position assumed by the government of Switzerland in relation to the events in Ukraine that ignores the realities and the explanations given by the Russian side more than once," the Russian Foreign Ministry said in a commentary on Friday.
"We consider the restrictions imposed by Bern on a number of spheres of bilateral cooperation unfounded and counter-productive," it said.
*** MOSCOW POINTS OUT TO OBAMA THAT NO INDEPENDENCE REFERENDUM WAS HELD IN KOSOVO
The Russian Foreign Ministry is surprised by U.S. President Barack Obama's statement regarding an independence referendum in Kosovo.
"Moscow has taken note of the fact that U.S. President Barack Obama, in rationalizing 'independence' of Kosovo and Metohija (Serbia) declared in circumvention of UN Security Council resolution 1244 in his speech in Brussels on March 28, mentioned some referendum on this issue allegedly held in coordination with the UN and the neighboring countries," the Foreign Ministry said in a statement available on its website.
"This allegation by the U.S. president causes perplexity, as no plebiscite, not to mention one agreed upon with the international community, was held on Kosovo's independence. The decision on secession from Serbia was made by the so-called 'parliament' in Pristina in 2008," it said.
*** RUSSIA CRITICIZES U.S. STANCE ON MILITARY COURTS, TRIBUNALS
The Russian Foreign Ministry is deeply disappointed by the decision of the United States to vote against the Russian-proposed draft resolution of the United Nations Human Rights Council (UNHRC) titled "Judicial System Integrity" and points to Washington's active attempts to hinder the passage of the document.
"At its 25th session on March 27 the UN Human Rights Council passed the Judicial System Integrity resolution submitted by the Russian Federation on behalf of over twenty co-authors. As a result of the voting held at the request of the U.S. delegation, the document was backed by 27 nations, with 19 abstaining, including the European Union, and only the U.S. voted against it," the ministry said in a statement posted on its website.
*** MARGELOV: AFRICAN STATES OVERWHELMINGLY REJECT ANTI-RUSSIAN RESOLUTION AT UN
Special Representative of the Russian President for Cooperation with African States Mikhail Margelov has welcomed the refusal of most African states to back the UN General Assembly resolution on Ukraine.
Margelov recalled that 31 out of 47 African countries said "no".
"It is easy to imagine what pressure the West has put on these countries and what conditions have been set for their approval of the anti-Russian resolution. But the West failed to achieve unity and consolidation," Margelov, who is also the Chairman of the Federation Council International Affairs Committee, told Interfax.
*** MOSCOW TO HOST INTL SECURITY CONFERENCE IN MAY
A high-level international security conference will be held in Moscow in May.
Pursuant to the Russian government directive posted on the official legal information portal, the Russian Defense Ministry will set up the organizing committee and approve its members.
Deputy Defense Minister Anatoly Antonov has been appointed to the post of organizing committee chair. "The Russian Foreign Ministry shall issue visas in the established procedure at the request of the conference organizing committee without levying visa issue fees," the document runs.
*** UKRAINIAN PARLIAMENTARY COMMISSION TO PROBE SASHKO BILY'S DEATH
The Ukrainian parliament has created a provisional investigations commission to investigate the circumstances of the death of Right Sector coordinator Oleksandr Muzychko (nicknamed Sashko Bily).
A total of 232 of 279 parliamentarians voted for that decision.
The commission will be led by parliamentarian Yuriy Derevianko. The commission will be comprised of representatives of all factions and three representatives of public organizations.
*** KAZAKH FM TO NEGOTIATE IN MOSCOW
Kazakh Foreign Minister Yerlan Idrisov will soon pay an official visit to Russia, the Kazakh president's Central Communications Service spokesman Altai Abibullayev said.
"An official visit of Kazakh Foreign Minister Yerlan Idrisov to the Russian Federation is scheduled for April 3," he told a press briefing in Astana on Monday.
According to Abibullayev, the sides will discuss the current status and prospects of Russian-Kazakh cooperation, political, cultural and humanitarian contacts and a variety of other issues, including global affairs.
Of ar
]]></text></news-item>