<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW6-YVB1-DYN6-W26T"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>FEATURE: Back on track: Sanriku Railway's long road to recovery</title><source>Japan Economic Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[OFUNATO, Japan, April 1 - A little over three years after a devastating earthquake hit northeastern Japan, coastal communities shattered by the ensuing tsunami are slowly returning to normal. Shops that were destroyed are gradually opening back up. Residents forced to evacuate to distant parts of Japan are returning to their hometowns.
And soon, communities along the coast of Iwate Prefecture will take another step toward recovery; Sanriku Railway Co. is set to restart full-scale operations on its South Rias and North Rias lines.
Operation is set to resume on a 15-kilometer stretch between Yoshihama and Kamaishi stations on the southern line on April 5, and on a 10.5 km stretch between Omoto and Tanohata stations on the northern line on April 6.
Covering most of Iwate's coastline on the Pacific Ocean, Sanriku Railway's two train lines were a central part of life for many local residents prior to the March 2011 earthquake and tsunami.
But the railway was crippled by the tsunami, its train cars flooded beyond repair and sections of the tracks swallowed whole.
"Seeing the state the tracks were in (after the tsunami), I thought we would never recover from that," said Shoichi Kumagai, a 30-year veteran at Sanriku Railway.
Recalling the earthquake, he said, "It seemed like the world was about to break apart."
"Immediately following the disaster, everyone was just trying to survive," he said. "But as soon as things settled down, I had people come up to me and ask, 'Can we ride the train yet?'"
With roads destroyed or blocked by rubble, the people at Sanriku Railway knew they had to act quickly. The North Rias line resumed operation just five days after the quake, carrying passengers free of charge across the small portion of its tracks that was undamaged.
The South Rias line, however, was more severely damaged and it was more than two years before partial operations were resumed.
It was not just the trains and tracks that needed to be repaired. Station buildings and bridges were also hit hard, and the South Rias line's main office in the city of Ofunato was flooded by the tsunami.
"The seawater filled the first floor, so all of the employees fled to the second floor office," Kumagai said.
Many of Sanriku Railway's employees were themselves victims of the disaster. Taiki Sato, 28, had been working at the company as an engineer for less than a year when the quake and tidal wave hit.
"My wife was pregnant then, and her parents' house got washed away in the tsunami. We both lived out of our workplaces after that, on constant standby."
"Now that all operations are going back online, it's really hitting home that things are returning back to normal," Saito said.
For the past three years, Sanriku Railway has worked with the government-backed Japan Railway Construction, Transport and Technology Agency to rebuild the damaged facilities.
The roughly 10 billion yen rebuilding costs were originally to be shared by Sanriku Railway, the Iwate prefectural government and the central government. But the central government ended up shouldering the entire cost.
The railway company also received support from outside Japan. Kuwait donated roughly 40 billion yen in crude oil to the three northeastern prefectures most heavily hit by the disasters, and Iwate used part of its share to buy five new train cars for Sanriku Railway.
Local residents along the train lines are more than eager for their local trains to be fully-restored.
"I used to take my children on the southern line all the time when they were little," said Kuniko Minawa, 65. "It was sad having train tracks but no train running on them. Once it starts back up, I'd like to take the train to see my husband's old house."
Haruka Mori, 18, said "I always use Sanriku Railway to come to Ofunato to hang out. I want to ride the entire length of the southern line when it starts up again."
"There's still a lot of rebuilding to do, but the Sanriku lines resuming makes me think the progress is becoming more visible," Mori said.
Starting full-scale operations is only the first step in Sanriku Railway's rebirth, however. Like many other small regional train lines, the North Rias and South Rias lines suffer from a dearth of regular local users. Populations in the countryside are on the decline and more and more people use cars to get around.
Sanriku Railway has worked to cover those losses by attracting tourists from other prefectures, operating special event trains such as the "Disaster Education Train," which has company employees lecturing passengers on the damage the 2011 earthquake and tsunami did on train lines and the surrounding areas, and the "Omiai Train," on which passengers sit face to face in search of a potential marriage partner.
The number of tourists riding the Sanriku lines received a boost from the North Rias line's cameo in the hugely-popular TV drama "Amachan," with the line featured in the storyline and opening credits.
But with the show ending six months ago, it remains to be seen whether the local lines can sustain their current popularity.
"We received kind words and support from people all over Japan, and I think the only way we can show our thankfulness is to show that we have more passengers now than ever," said Sanriku Railway's Kumagai.
"Of course we want local passengers, but we want to plan all kinds of events so that people from outside Iwate will visit disaster-struck areas."
]]></text></news-item>