<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW6-YT81-DY93-M0K3"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>AFPTV-Advisory 2100GMT</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[LONDON, March 31, 2014 (AFP) - We will file the following videos:
-- TOP WORLD NEWS --
+ UKRAINE
Coming up:
PARIS: French Foreign Minister Laurent Fabius meets with Russian counterpart Sergei Lavrov. RAW. TBA
Filed over past 12 hours:
KIEV: Interim Ukrainian president Oleksandr Turchynov is to oversee creation of a new 'national guard', made up of volunteers in response to Russia's annexation of Crimea and military build-up to the east. RAW. VID612668_EN
SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA Crimea's Tatars voted to push for self-rule in their historic homeland following its annexation by Russia, but remained torn on how to engage with the new authorities. RAW. VID612682_EN
SIMFEROPOL, CRIMEA: Russian PM Dmitry Medvedev visits Crimea, the first Russian leader to travel to the Black Sea region after Moscow seized it from Ukraine. RAW. VID612519_EN
PARIS: French and Russia Foreign Ministers continue talks about Ukraine. RAW. VID612486_EN
PARIS: The US and Russia fail to reach a deal on Ukraine but Russian FM Sergei Lavrov says talks with US Secretary of State John Kerry have been "constructive" and will continue. RAW. VID612372_EN
PARIS: US Secretary of State John Kerry calls on Moscow to pull back its forces. RAW. VID612377_EN
PARIS: Images of Kerry-Lavrov meeting. RAW. VID612228_EN
PARIS: John Kerry meets French FM Laurent Fabius. RAW. VID612218_EN
+ CLIMATE CHANGE REPORT
Filed over past 12 hours:
YOKOHAMA, JAPAN: Ignorance is "no longer a good excuse" says a UN panel in a landmark report on climate change. RAW. VID612396_EN
VARIOUS: Stockshots to illustrate climate change and natural disasters. STOCKSHOTS. VID381815_EN
+ TURKEY ELECTION
Filed over past 12 hours:
BEIT LAHYA, GAZA STRIP: Hamas militants in the Gaza Strip welcome Erdogan's victory in local elections in Turkey. RAW. VID612752_EN
ISTANBUL/ANKARA: Reactions to Sunday's local elections. RAW. VID612564_EN (Istanbul residents reax) VID612531_EN (newspapers) / VID612578_EN (analyst)
ANKARA: Turkey PM appears on the balcony at party HQ, claims victory. RAW. VID612410_EN, VID612458_EN
ANKARA: Supporters celebrate after Turkey's Premier Recep Tayyip Erdogan claims victory for his Islamic-rooted party. RAW. VID612387_EN
+ FRANCE ELECTION
Filed over past 12 hours:
PARIS: French President Francois Hollande appoints popular Interior Minister Manuel Valls as his new Prime Minister. RAW. VID612732_EN/ FILE. VID612650 (Valls) / VID612527_EN (Images of Elysee Palace)
- French President Hollande replaces the current Prime Minister and reshuffles the cabinet. FILE. VID610895_EN/ VID610887_EN
- Jean-Marc Ayrault resigns as French Prime Minister. RAW. VID612674_EN
-French President Francois Hollande reshuffles his cabinet after the government suffered humiliating losses in local elections in which the far-right National Front made historic gains. PKG. NSV VID612482_EN/RAW. VID612483_EN
-French National Front leader Marine Le Pen says her party will show that it is worthy of voter trust after a breakthrough in local elections, and predicts that the National Front could come out on top in forthcoming European elections. RAW. VID612455_EN / VID612487_EN (Marseille reax)
-A Socialist party spokesman says the message from voters has been received 'loud and clear' and that he expects an early announcement of 'strong and significant responses'. RAW. VID612580_EN
-French press highlights Socialist local vote defeat. RAW. VID612405_EN
-- OTHER WORLD NEWS --
+ EUROPE
Coming up:
LONDON: Natural History Museum opens annual butterfly exhibition. RAW. TBA
Filed over past 12 hours:
THE HAGUE: The UN's top court orders Japan to end its annual Antarctic whale hunt. RAW. VID612478_EN, VID612549_EN / FILE. VID504628_EN
BRUSSELS: Chinese President Xi Jinping begins a ground-breaking European Union visit. RAW. VID612408_EN (Jinping with Van Rompuy), VID612414_EN (roundtable), VID612441_EN (Barroso handshake), VID612446_EN (Barroso roundtable), VID612462_EN (Martin Shultz meeting), VID612498_EN (leaders' wives meet), VID612536 EN (Jinping visits pandas)
ATHENS: After Greece's parliament narrowly approved an omnibus bill of reforms tied to the country's next tranche of loans, radical leftist Alexis Tsipras tells AFP "these procedures convert a sovereign country into a protectorate that is constantly blackmailed by its leaders". RAW. VID612717_EN
MADRID: International dignitaries crowd into Madrid's Almudena Cathedral for a solemn state funeral to honour Adolfo Suarez, the statesman who led Spain to democracy after the Franco dictatorship. RAW. VID612750_EN/ VID612775_EN
NICOSIA: Greek and Turkish Cypriot leaders continue their talks on reunifying the island. RAW. VID612585_EN
PARIS: Lufthansa, Germany's biggest airline, says it will be forced to cancel most of its flights later this week, grounding as many as 425,000 passengers, due to a pilots' strike. FILE. VID583168_EN
METZ, FRANCE: Condemned serial killer Francis Heaulme, in jail for 11 murders, goes on trial for another double murder. RAW. VID612528_EN
PARIS: Carlos the Jackal, imprisoned for terrorism, on trial for alleged anti-Semitic insults. FILE. VID612434_EN
PARIS: The Eiffel Tower celebrates its 125th birthday. FILE. VID612514_EN
+ AFRICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
GUINEA Aid organisation Doctors Without Borders says an Ebola outbreak suspected of killing at least 78 people in Guinea was an "unprecedented epidemic" that had spread across the west African nation. RAW. VID612647_EN
BANGUI: Chadian soldiers sent to repatriate their compatriots from the Central African Republic killed at least eight civilians when they opened fire on crowds in Bangui, the African peacekeeping force MISCA said Sunday. RAW. VID612654_EN
BANGUI: The President of the Red Cross in the Central African Republic, Antoine Mbao Bogo, presented on Saturday an overview of attacks and the death toll in the city of Bangui since 5 December. VID612565_EN
KIGALI: On every last Saturday of the month, Rwandans participate in the mandatory 'Umuganda' community service work, put in place after the genocide by President Paul Kagame in order to rebuild the country. RAW. VID612728_EN
+ MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
Coming up:
RAMALLAH, PALESTINIAN TERRITORIES: US Secretary of State John Kerry meets with Palestinian leader Mahmoud Abbas. TBC
Filed over past 12 hours:
JERUSALEM: US Secretary of State John Kerry meets with Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu. RAW. VID612758_EN
DAMASCUS: A Syrian artist sets the Guinness record for the world's largest mural made of recycle materials. VID612609_EN
RAMALLAH: Palestinians reject an Israeli proposal to extend peace talks. VID612715_EN
TEL AVIV: US Secretary of State lands in Tel Aviv in a bid to save crumbling peace talks. VID612695_EN
TUNIS: Trial resumes of two Tunisian policemen accused of raping a young woman in 2012. RAW. VID612581_EN
ARSAL, LEBANON : This small border town has turn into a refuge for scores of wounded fighters from Syria. RAW. VID612421_EN
TEL AVIV: A court finds former premier Ehud Olmert guilty of bribery. VID612465_EN; VID611620_EN (Images of Holyland); VID390469_EN (FILE of Olmert)
+ NORTH AMERICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
DARRINGTON, WASHINGTON STATE: With bodies still being recovered following a massive landslide, the affected rural community in Washington State is doing its best to deal with the disaster's aftermath. PKG. NSV: VID612621_EN / VOICED: VID612623_EN
+ ASIA PACIFIC
Coming up:
WUKAN, CHINA: A Chinese village that held landmark democratic elections after it rebelled against Communist Party officials heads to the polls again. RAW. TBA
Filed over past 12 hours:
BEIJING: A top Malaysia Airlines official tells relatives of Chinese passengers on board flight MH370 that there is "no guarantee of success" in the search for the missing aircraft. RAW. VID612597_EN
ISLAMABAD: A Pakistani court indicts former military ruler Pervez Musharraf for treason on charges relating to his 2007 imposition of emergency rule. RAW. VID612437_EN / FILE. VID505189_EN
+ LATIN AMERICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
CHILE: President Michelle Bachelet sent Chile's Congress a bill Monday that would raise corporate taxes to fund a sweeping overhaul of the country's education system. RAW. VID612764_EN
-- SPORT --
Coming up:
BARCELONA, SPAIN: Pre-match training and pressers ahead of Tuesday's Champions League first leg quarter final between Barcelona and Atlectico Madrid. RAW. TBA
Filed over past 12 hours:
MANCHESTER, UK: Pre-match training and pressers ahead of Tuesday's Champions League first leg quarter final between Manchester United and Bayern Munich. RAW. VID612532_EN
MUNICH, GERMANY: Bayern Munich coach Pep Guardiola on Monday warned against reading too much into Manchester United's domestic struggles ahead of the first leg of their Champions League quarter-final on Tuesday. RAW. VID612768_EN
-- FEATURES --
Filed:
LONDON: Sinking a pint below towering wooden arches, living in a bell tower or paying for shopping as stained glass saints look on, falling numbers of parishioners and tightening purse strings are seeing a number of Britain's churches sold off as pubs, flats and supermarkets. PKG. NSV - VID611278_EN / VOICED - VID611279_EN
ALMASFUZITO, HUNGARY: Hungary experienced its worst-ever chemical disaster in 2010 when a reservoir of toxic red mud burst, killing 10 people and polluting the surrounding area. Four years later and environmental groups are sounding the alarm about another reservoir on the banks of the Danube where toxic mud from the communist era remains. PKG. NSV - VID611278_EN / VOICED - VID611744_EN
Contact:
London desk: +44 207 776 2768
Hong Kong desk: +852 2829 6216
Nicosia desk: +357 22 391 453
Washington desk: +1 202 414 0550
Montevideo desk: +598 2 900 5095 ext 257
For contact via email: afptv-en@afp.com
]]></text></news-item>