<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW6-PNR1-DXJR-H4P6"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>BMC blacklists firm that supplied 'expensive' fire-fighting equipment</title><source>Times of India (Electronic Edition)</source><author>Bhavika Jain TNN</author><text><![CDATA[Mumbai: The civic body has blacklisted Technotrade Impex,promoted by Bimal Agarwal,which had supplied fire-fighting equipment in 2009-10.Subsequently,Agarwal moved the Bombay high court against the blacklisting and for non-payment of dues.The BMC had bought 1,642 mutli-purpose safety belts for Rs 10,743 each,though similar belts were sold to the state police for Rs 1,980 each.This disparity was brought to the notice of then BMC chief Subodh Kumar by senior IPS officer P K Jain."The specifications of the police belts and BMC belts were different,hence,the cost difference.The BMC has been using the belts for two years,but has not yet paid me Rs 27 crore," Agarwal told TOI.Agarwal is also facing an EOW probe for alleged irregularities in the supply of bomb suits to the police.Meanwhile,an anti-corruption bureau report has indicted four civic officials for alleged financial irregularities in the procurement of the equipment.The report,which has been submitted to BMC chief Sitaram Kunte,has recommended action against former chief fire officers Uday Tatkare,Arvind Sawant,Pramod Karguppikar and director of the BMC Anil Shrote;blacklisting the supplier and lodging a police complaint.While Tatkare died of a heart attack on duty,Sawant retired four years ago.The EOW has closed the inquiry for lack of proof."The BMC has given an application wherein we conducted a preliminary enquiry.It claimed Agarwal had sold them multi-purpose belts costlier than the police.But it is not a crime as the BMC had fixed the price,floated the tender and awarded it to Agarwal," said an EOW official.Following the ACB report,the BMC has started its own departmental inquiry.The BMC has also blocked the firm's vendor ID,so that no money can be paid to it.The firm is currently executing a Rs 45-lakh renovation project in the Byculla zoo.

]]></text></news-item>