<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW6-YTV1-JCM0-600D"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Forbes Council pleads guilty to effluent overflow</title><source>ABC Regional News (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Forbes Shire Council will have to find more than $200,000 (AUS) to pay fines and legal costs imposed on it for water pollution.
The council pleaded guilty in the Land and Environment Court to the breach which happened between June 23 and July 9, 2012.
The Council pumped water from an effluent dam at the Central West Livestock Exchange, which had been overflowing, onto an irrigation area and adjoining land.
The effluent then flowed across a paddock, along a drainage line and into three livestock dams on a neighbouring property.
The Environment Protection Authority launched proceedings against the council which then pleaded guilty in the Land and Environment Court.
The Court heard there was potential for cattle on the adjacent land to become infected with Bovine Johnes disease by drinking contaminated water.
The council was fined $130,000 for the water pollution and $35,000 for failing to notify the EPA of the incident immediately once it became aware of it.
The Shire has also been ordered to pay $47,000 in legal costs.
The Council's General Manager, Brian Steffen, says the pollution was due to a combination of human error and rain causing an effluent dam to overflow.
Mr Steffen says since then the council has introduced a pollution response plan, a waste water action management plan and an effluent re-use scheme.
"We've got travelling irrigators that will travel across the licensed area where we irrigate that deluded effluent it sits in and mixes with the water and then we'll irrigate that to our licensed area," he said.
He says the council will now look at how to foot the bill, including whether insurance could cover it.
"It's a lot of money and it's what the court felt was fair for the offence.
We're reviewing that but certainly will make a dent in the budget. We'll need to make some operational savings in the budget but my objective will be not to reduce any services in the community," he said.
Mr Steffen says there was the potential for cattle on the neighbouring property to be affected by contaminated water but that didn't happen.
"The EPA biological expert and ours agreed that there was no actual harm to the environment but a real risk," he said.
"There was only the potential for harm and that's a very serious potential but there was no actual harm to the drinking water or cattle."
The EPA says anyone who has concerns about pollution in their local are should contact its 24 hour Environment Line on 131 555.
]]></text></news-item>