<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW6-9C91-DYN2-31WJ"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Why Target's anti-union video is no joke</title><source>guardian.co.uk</source><author>Ucilia Wangtheguardian.com</author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
Even as the debate over raising the minimum wage gains public attention and the disparity between the rich and poor continues to grow, US membership in unions has continued what Philip Jennings, general secretary for UNI Global Union, calls "an alarming plunge", hitting a 97-year low last year.
The recent leak of Target's latest anti-union video highlights how effective corporate campaigns have been in undermining unionization efforts. It isn't the first anti-union video from Target: Gawker also posted a heavily panned video back in 2011, when the United Food and Commercial Workers International Union (UFCW) were attempting to unionize Target employees in Valley Stream, New York.
Had UFCW succeeded, that store would've become the first union shop among Target's 1,750 stores. UFCW told Salon, which first wrote about the most recent video, that it wasn't planning to seek another vote from Target employees to unionize.
It's easy to make fun of both videos for the characters' performance, the script or special effects. But the quality of the videos is beside the point, said John Logan, an associate professor in the San Francisco State University's labor and employment studies department. Both videos present essentially the same talking points, and the main message is this: Job security is at stake if you unionize because a union will undermine Target's competitiveness in a cutthroat business.
"If you see the video in isolation, it seems comical. But in the context of power dynamics that exist in the workplace, these statements are quite effective at dissuading employees," Logan said. "Employers can fire people for no reason. We shouldn't underestimate the degree people are fearful about what the employers say."
Corporate social responsibility includes the proper treatment of workers. That invariably affects a company's fortunes in the long run. The most shocking stories - and the ones that embarrass a company enough to force change - seem to come mostly from exposés about overseas factories, however. Think of Apple's attempt to address stories of workers' abuse at the giant campus of its supplier, Foxconn, in China.
What's happening elsewhere in the world - the terribly unsafe working conditions, paltry wages and ungodly long working hours - also used to exist in the United States. Those conditions gave rise to stronger labor protection laws at federal and state levels during the last century, when unions' influence also rose. Gallup polls in 1937 found that 72% of those surveyed approved of unions.
In recent years, however, Americans by and large no longer view unions any more favorably than they view businesses. In fact, their opinions tend to dip for both when the economy turns sour and go back up when the economy improves, according to Pew Research Center surveys.
Unions' power has fallen considerably in the past few decades. Changes in federal and state laws have made it more difficult to organize unions, and penalties against companies that illegally interfere with unionization campaigns aren't serious deterrents, especially for large companies with resources to fight. Gallup polls found the approval rating for unions dropped to 48% in 2009.
Union membership also has fallen from about 20% in 1983 to 11% in 2013, according to the US Bureau of Labor Statistics. About 35% of the public-sector workers belonged to a union in 2013, compared with only roughly 7% for private-sector employees.
Unionized workers on average make 30% higher wages and benefits than non-union workers, said Kent Wong, director of the Center for Labor Research and Education at the University of California at Los Angeles. "There's tremendous incentives for corporations to intimidate the workers from joining the unions," Wong said.
Anti-union messages don't have to come from companies to be effective. The failed unionization effort by the United Auto Workers at a Volkswagen plant in Tennessee last month serves as an example. The German automaker was actually open to having the union at its plant. But Republican lawmakers campaigned against it and threatened to withhold tax incentives.
Could the public sentiment towards unions change? In recent years, the public has paid more attention to the rising disparity of incomes between the rich and the poor.
The Occupy Wall Street movement in 2011 and its slogan of "We are the 99%" highlighted the huge economic inequality. Edward Wolff of New York University found that the richest fifth of US families control about 89% of the country's wealth.
While the public attention is welcome, it won't likely translate into changes in labor laws that favor unions, said Kathy M Newman, an English professor at Carnegie Mellon University who is writing a book about labor, media and culture in the 1950s.
"I think American business is at its most productive and powerful at the time when there was a high percentage of unionized workers," Newman said. "When workers have a democratic voice and given an avenue for their ideas to be heard, the companies perform better."
Target responded to multiple requests for comment about the latest video with the following line: "We communicate with our team members through a variety of channels, including videos."
]]></text></news-item>