<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW6-YVB1-DYN6-W2C8"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>FOCUS: Fate of Japan's whaling looks uncertain due to ICJ ruling</title><source>Japan Economic Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TOKYO, March 31 - A ruling on Monday by the International Court of Justice that orders Japan to halt whaling in the Antarctic is likely to deal a major blow to all of the country's whaling as anti-whaling nations are certain to turn up the heat against the practice.
Japan has three channels to carry out whaling -- research whaling in both the Antarctic Ocean and Northwest Pacific, as well as coastal whaling of smaller species including dolphins which are not subject to control by the International Whaling Commission.
Their respective catches are assumed to be 992 tons, 1,564 tons and 431 tons in 2012, according to Japan's Fisheries Agency.
While the ruling in the U.N. court could reduce by roughly 20 percent the whole supply of whale meat to Japan, it also raises the possibility that whaling in the Northwest Pacific Ocean would be halted.
The strongly held views by both the anti- and pro-whaling sides have made it almost impossible to resolve the issue through dialogue.
"Sustainable use of living resources is indeed at the very heart of the Japanese ethos precisely because Japan has scarce resources and has always relied for her survival on what nature can provide," said Koji Tsuruoka, who represented Japan in the case, in the opening statement at the court last July, maintaining Japan's basic stance towards whaling.
Japan also maintains that each country's dietary culture and habits have been formed through their environment, and mutual understanding should be respected.
However, anti-whaling countries including Australia oppose killing whales, citing that they are intellectual, friendly to people or "sacred" animals, Japanese experts said.
An anti-whaling trend spread between the 1960s and 1970s in the United States and Europe, helped by an increasing sense of environmental and animal welfare, they said.
In recent years, Japan's long-held custom came under intensified pressure by anti-whaling nations and groups in the wake of the 2010 Academy Award-winning documentary film "The Cove" depicting dolphin hunting in the whaling town of Taiji, Wakayama Prefecture, partly through the use of hidden cameras.
In January, U.S. Ambassador to Japan Caroline Kennedy expressed her concerns on Twitter about dolphin hunting at Taiji, spurring a fresh international controversy.
"Deeply concerned by inhumanness of drive hunt dolphin killing. USG (the U.S. government) opposes drive hunt fisheries," she wrote.
Immediately after, U.S. State Department Deputy Spokesperson Marie Harf said Kennedy expressed "our view that we've made public for a long time."
While international pressure on Japan's whaling is likely to strengthen further, the domestic industry also appears to stand at the crossroads.
Whale meat was once regarded as an important source of nutrition amid food shortages in Japan following the end of World War II, typically served in school meals nationwide.
However, demand for whale meat has been decreasing year by year in the country due to a wider variety of tastes for food. The stockpile of whale meat in Japan at the end of 2012 surpassed the assumed domestic consumption volume for the year, according to the Fisheries Agency.
Japan may be able to increase import volume from other whaling countries including Norway and Iceland even if the domestic supply falls short of demand.
But even in Japan, some pundits question the need for the research whaling, which has been aided by a large amount of public funds amid sluggish demand for the meat.
]]></text></news-item>