<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW6-9K41-JBRC-V0NC"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Protection in a cyber world</title><source>Chicago Daily Herald</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Almost everyone heard the news that Target stores was the victim of a criminal data breach that resulted in over 110 million confidential customer records falling into the wrong hands.
While retailers and e-commerce sites are often victims of cyber crime, hackers also attack other businesses or organizations that accumulate confidential information. A health care provider in Georgia recently reported a data breach that may have exposed 410,000 patient records to data thieves.
The costs to companies experiencing a data breach can be devastating. The Target data breach was widely reported during the holiday shopping season last year. Many customers avoided the retailer. Target reported significant earnings reductions as a result. Federal and State laws now mandate specific reporting requirements and notification to customers who have their data stolen. Some breaches require the business to provide credit monitoring for affected customers. The notification and monitoring costs for large scale breaches can easily reach into the millions.
The insurance industry is responding to these risks by developing new products and coverage forms to protect businesses from hackers and the theft of data. Just five years ago, this coverage was offered by only a handful of insurance carriers and was difficult for ordinary businesses to obtain. Today, many insurance companies now offer some form of "cyber liability insurance". Cyber liability insurance can be purchased as a stand- alone policy, or it may be bundled together with other lines of traditional business insurance. As more insurance carriers enter the marketplace for cyber liability coverage, the underwriting requirements have been streamlined and premiums have dropped.
The insurance coverage provided by cyber liability policies varies significantly from carrier to carrier. There is not one standard policy. However, the coverage typically pays third parties for damages they sustain as a result of negligence by the insured business in failing to secure data. An example of a third party would be a patient in a doctor's office. The doctor's office has a duty to secure the confidential medical files of its patients. If a patient's medical records were published on a website, the cyber liability insurance would both defend the doctor's office against patient lawsuits and pay the patient any monetary damages for violating the patient's privacy.
Some cyber liability insurance will also provide first party coverage. This coverage is intended to reimburse the insured business for costs that it may incur as a result of a cyber attack. An example would be a manufacturing firm that maintains its extensive inventory data and product quality control records on an internal server network.
A hacker is able to bypass the network firewall and launches a harmful virus that renders the network inoperable. The cyber liability policy would pay for a computer consultant's time to diagnose the damage, repairs to the computer system, and time and expense necessary to restore or recreate the damaged data. The policy will respond to any loss of business resulting from the breach.
There are many other types of cyber liability claims. Coverage can be provided for the insured's negligence in infringing on copyright, trade mark, or plagiarism of website content. If an insured business is required to notify customers of a data breach and provide credit monitoring, cyber liability policies will pay these expenses. The average cost of notification is more than $200 per record, so even a breach of several hundred records can quickly overwhelm a small business. Some cyber liability policies provide coverage for cyber extortion, where a hacker threatens to disable a website or a critical business process if payment is not received.
Every business owner should consider if cyber liability poses a significant risk to their business. A discussion of cyber liability and insurance alternatives should be part of every business insurance review. The statistics on cyber crime are alarming. It is estimated that nearly one in four businesses will sustain a serious data breach within the next five years.
* Edward J. Boltz is the founding partner of Prime Meridian, a Foundation Insurance group member. Foundation Insurance has offices in six locations in Illinois.
in the manufacturing, technology and construction sectors.
]]></text></news-item>