<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW6-PNR1-DXJR-H4V5"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>'Indian domestic helps of diplomats in UK abused'</title><source>Times of India (Electronic Edition)</source><author>Kounteya Sinha TNN</author><text><![CDATA[London: Indian domestic workers in the UK have for the first time come forward to reveal how they are being subjected to serious abuses,including forced labour and low or no salary.The report was launched by Human Rights Watch.Neha R,an Indian domestic worker employed by a diplomat,has told Human Rights Watch that she worked seven days a week looking after her employer's children,cooking and cleaning for which she was being paid a paltry xA3150 (Rs 15,000) per month.Her salary has not increased since she started working for her employer 12 years ago.She told Human Rights Watch,"My family is very poor.I send them xA3100 every month." Neha said she supported her mother,father,sister,and her sister's two children back home.Another Indian domestic worker Anita L has revealed her employers didn't pay her for three years,including the three months she spent working for them in the UK.She said she worked from 6am to 11pm with no breaks and no days off.She wasn't allowed to step out alone and slept in a room with the kids."They said they would transfer money to my account but they didn't," she said."I called home in India once per month,I wasn't allowed a mobile.'' Till October 2013,the national minimum wage for workers over the age of 21 was xA36.31 per hour.In 2012,it was xA36.19 and in 2011 xA36.08.Employers can only charge up to xA34.91 per day,or xA334.37 per week for accommodation,which includes rent,gas and electricity and laundry.This reveals that Indian workers weren't even being paid the minimum wage.A report launched on Monday by Human Rights Watch revealed that migrant domestic workers accompanying their employers to the UK are being subjected to serious abuses.The UK government,they said,is doing far too little to protect vulnerable workers and recent changes to UK immigration rules make it harder for workers to flee abuse.The 58-page report documents the confiscation of passports,confinement to the home,physical and psychological abuse,extremely long working hours with no rest days,and very low wages or non-payment of wages.In April 2012,the UK abolished the right of migrant domestic workers to change employer once they are in the UK,against the recommendations of parliament.Under the terms of the new 'tied visa' overseas domestic workers cannot legally leave their employer and find new work,meaning those abused can become trapped."Workers who are mistreated now face a horrendous choice: either endure the terrible abuse,or escape and become undocumented migrants,where of course they are much more vulnerable to further abuse and exploitation," said Leghtas.

]]></text></news-item>