<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW6-T8R1-JC8Y-804N"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Swiss raise stakes in forex manipulation probe</title><source>The Irish Times</source><author>Daniel Schafer, James Shotter</author><text><![CDATA[The sprawling probe into alleged manipulation of foreign exchange markets intensified yesterday when two European regulators stepped up their efforts to root out the rigging of crucial financial benchmarks.
Switzerland's competition watchdog became the first regulator to confirm it had uncovered signs of illegal activity as it announced an investigation into possible forex manipulation. Meanwhile, Britain's financial regulator said it was examining the controls investment banks have to prevent traders from rigging benchmarks.
Switzerland's Wettbewerbskommission said it had launched an investigation into four domestic lenders - UBS, Credit Suisse, Julius Baer and Zürcher Kantonalbank - and four foreign banks - Barclays, JPMorgan, Citigroup and Royal Bank of Scotland
"There are indications that these banks went into anti-competitive agreements to manipulate price rates in foreign exchange trading," Weko said.
Its focus on whether banks broke antitrust laws raises the prospect of bankers' biggest fear: multibillion-dollar fines for violating competition rules. The European Commission and the US department of justice are also looking at potential infringements.
Incriminating evidenceOne person familiar with the preliminary probe told the Financial Times banks have been queueing up to provide incriminating evidence "of startling quality" in an attempt to secure leniency. More than a dozen regulators on four continents are investigating whether traders at more than 15 banks colluded to manipulate the $5.3 trillion-a-day currency market.
Weko's announcement follows a review launched in September and widens the number of banks under scrutiny. It said it could not rule out the involvement of even more banks and interdealer brokers.
Credit Suissesaid it was "astonished" and "The press release contains incorrect references to Credit Suisse AG." - (Copyright The Financial Times Limited 2014 )
]]></text></news-item>