<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW6-HMB1-JDK3-927Y"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Opinion: 'We have not been properly consulted on impacts of Northern Gateway'</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Imagine if an oil pipeline was built through your backyard, across your local park or at your church, or alongside your desk at work without consultation and without your consent.
It sounds far-fetched, but it is the potential reality facing a number of communities across British Columbia, including one of the longest continually inhabited territories in North America, the Gitxaala Nation.
We, the Gitxaala Nation, are vehemently opposed to Enbridge's proposed Northern Gateway pipeline project because of the disastrous effects the shipment of heavy oil through our territory would have on our traditional way of life, economy, spirituality, and governance system.
As Gitxaala, known as People of the Saltwater, we rely on our territorial waters for 80 per cent of our food. There are serious concerns the Enbridge project will jeopardize our traditional harvesting territory.
What's especially concerning is that our people have not been properly consulted about the impacts of the Northern Gateway Project, despite openly participating and co-operating with the federal joint review panel process. We went out of our way to participate in Canada's regulatory system, yet our rights have been completely ignored.
For thousands of years, Gitxaala has been governed by a system of clans and houses tied to specific territories and waters that determine our survival and success. The Gitxaala Nation is not a signatory to a historic treaty and is not currently in the modern-day B.C. comprehensive treaty process.
Just as Canadians are governed by the laws of their municipalities, provinces and federal government, so too are the Gitxaala. We have our system that existed thousands of years ago, long before contact with Europeans.
Fifteen of the 21 Gitxaala reserves are in the vicinity of the proposed Northern Gateway project tanker routes. Extensive sections of the heavy oil and condensate tanker routes would be located within our traditional territory. The very presence of huge tankers will have enormous negative impacts on our community.
This isn't news to the people at Enbridge or the JRP that held hearings on the proposed project and released its recommendation along with 209 conditions in December.
Gitxaala's concerns were submitted to the JRP in 7,500 pages of written evidence, oral testimony from 27 community members and nine expert reports including critiques of the proponent's risk assessment methodology, oil spill modelling and fate and behaviour of spilled bitumen.
Throughout the JRP process, Gitxaala raised concerns the Northern Gateway project would adversely affect our constitutionally protected Aboriginal rights including adverse impacts on our Aboriginal title and self-governance.
Still, we were shocked the JRP appeared to ignore and summarily dismiss all of our concerns in its report.
We played by the rules, but our concerns were ignored. Now the government is giving us just three days this month to talk about the JRP's recommendations.
Meanwhile, what we still haven't discussed is our rights and concerns around the project itself. Those are the issues we plan to bring to the table on Wednesday.
Canada has a duty to consult and accommodate First Nations when it comes to development that will have a negative impact on their territories. The Supreme Court of Canada has recognized this in a number of decisions. These rulings have found consultation and accommodation are constitutional obligations that must take place before important decisions affecting First Nations are made.
To ensure government actions - such as permitting an oil pipeline, terminal project or related marine traffic - do not contravene constitutional requirements, the Crown must consult meaningfully and at an early stage.
It's not as if we haven't tried. To date, despite repeated requests, Canada has refused to talk with Gitxaala about the real issues at stake, which are Aboriginal rights and title and the potential impacts from the project.
Proper consultation would show this project cannot be approved without breaching our constitutionally protected rights and Canada's constitution. Canada cannot ignore this reality by relying on a failed JRP process and refusing to properly consult.
This is what the Gitxaala and other First Nations opposed to Northern Gateway demand to be on the agenda. Until that happens, no other conversation will be possible.
Clarence Innis is acting chief of the Gitxaala Nation.
© Copyright (c) The Vancouver Sun
]]></text></news-item>