<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-9DM1-J9YR-G0TR"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>FCA to review rate rigging controls; Thematic review is one of a number announced in the regulator's 2014/15 Business Plan</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Telegraph Staff</author><text><![CDATA[The Financial Conduct Authority (FCA) is to consider how banks can reduce the risk of traders manipulating key benchmarks such as Libor.
The thematic review is one of a number announced on Monday in the regulator's Business Plan for 2014/15.
Regulators around the world have been investigating allegations of manipulation of Libor, the London Inter-Bank Offered Rate which is used to price trillions of pounds of loans and financial products across the world, and a number of individuals are facing charges.
The review will assess whether firms have learned lessons from the Libor rigging scandal and other recent controversies and ask if adequate controls on traders behaviour and activity are now in place to prevent future manipulation of benchmarks.
Martin Wheatley, the chief executive of the FCA, said: "Following widespread attempted manipulation of Libor, firms should ensure that traders are not able to act in this way in the future. We are determined that firms need to take the matter of manipulation of any benchmark seriously and will be working with firms to seek out any issues that may remain."
Others thematic reviews included a look into the conduct of wholesale banking and investment management firms.
In investment banking, the FCA will look at the issues surrounding conflicts of interest and a separate look into the way firms ensure that confidential information received in one part of the business is not abused by a different part of the business.
It will also examine the behaviour of asset managers, "focusing both on how firms ensure that trading activity is consistent with expectations of market conduct and how asset managers are acting as good agents and taking proper account of investor interests".
Mr Wheatley said: "Over the next year we will increase the intensity with which we supervise wholesale conduct to ensure that transactions undertaken by these firms do not have a harmful impact on market integrity."
Alongside reviews of the wholesale market, the regulator will assess competition issues in wholesale markets which could lead to further reviews.
This year the FCA takes on regulation of consumer credit, which "effectively doubles the number of firms" regulated by the watchdog.
"Using our new power we want to tackle harm to consumers who are most at risk and our work will focus on protecting vulnerable consumers," Mr Wheatley said.
Other areas of focus for the next year outlined in the Business Plan include using the FCA's consumer protection objective to undertake a programme of work ensuring that consumers are being treated fairly.
The FCA also said its annual funding requirement for 2014/15 had risen to £446.4m, from £432.1m the previous year, driven by the costs of establishing the new competition team. Minimum fees charged to the industry by the FCA remain unchanged at £1,000 for the fifth year in a row, with only 42pc of firms pay the fee.
Mr Wheatley said: "We have worked hard to ensure that the small firms we regulate pay the least ... the increases will be borne mainly by larger and more complex groups which pose the most risk and are costliest to regulate."
]]></text></news-item>