<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-9DM1-J9YR-G0V9"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>'Our deaths are cheap': Qatar World Cup 'slaves' speak out amid new controversy</title><source>Daily Star Online</source><author>Cyrus Engineer</author><text><![CDATA[THE QATAR World Cup has become embroiled in yet more controversy after an investigation revealed as many as 1,200 "slaves" have been worked to death in the oil-rich state.
Migrant workers are being forced to live in horrific and inhumane conditions as the Gulf nation prepares for the 2022 World Cup with a £39bn construction operation.
One worker told the Mirror: "We are treated like slaves and our deaths are cheap."
Fifa is under fresh pressure to take the tournament away from Qatar following multiple revelations of corruption, mass death and exploitation of workers.
Campaigners fear up to 4,000 workers could be killed as they toil in 40C heat without proper water for just 57p an hour.
A Nepalese carpenter
Many of the labourers are recruited from Nepal. They are promised safe working conditions and decent pay to send home to their family.
However the truth is far different. One carpenter said: "We're treated like slaves. They don't see us as human and our deaths are cheap. They have our passports so we cannot go home. We are trapped."
Last summer a Guardian investigation into the World Cup revealed that workers were dying at a rate of almost one a day, many of them young, healthy men.
Those who do not die are routinely denied their wages, have their passports and ID confiscated and are denied water even in the extreme desert heat.
Two MPs who witnessed the appalling conditions in Qatar have promised to raise the issue in Parliament.
Chris Williamson, MP for Derby North, said: "I was sickened by what I saw. Fifa is under a moral obligation to press the Qatari authorities to end the exploitation."
Following the Guardian's report the energy-rich country, one of the wealthiest on the planet, promised to crackdown on exploitative private building firms.
But it appears nothing has been done with the situation and it again raises the real possibility of the World Cup being taken away from Qatar.
Fifa President Sepp Blatter is sending lawyer Dr Theo Zwanzieger to the country next month.
Related articles Qatar World Cup 2022: Shocking revelations that 185 construction workers died in 2013 FIFA play down Valcke comments FIFA confirms Qatar World Cup switch FIFA concerned by preparations
Qatar's World Cup has been plagued by problems ever since they were awarded the tournament in December 2010.
Due to the intense heat many have claimed the tournament cannot be held in the summer.
A winter World Cup has been proposed but that would mean heavily disrupting the European club season.
There have also been multiple allegations of bribery which have seen several prominent members of Fifa suspended.
Qatar's officials have consistently denied any impropriety in their bid.
]]></text></news-item>