<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-36D1-F0JP-W4WV"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Caltex asked, please explain</title><source>Southern Courier</source><author>Laura Suckling</author><text><![CDATA[Residents are demanding answers from Caltex after last week's oil spill into Botany Bay.
The petrol giant had to clean up oil released from its Kurnell refinery on Monday, stating the heavy rain caused a "small release of oily water" into Botany Bay, resulting in a light sheen.
On Tuesday Caltex and Sydney Ports Corporation, inspected Botany Bay by boat and foot and "all beaches were reported clean".
The Recreational Fishing Alliance said the smelly oil slick spread across to the northern side of the bay and through its headlands.
Fisherman Mike Hill has been fishing at Botany Bay for eight years and said the marine environment needed to be better looked after.
"There is a safety issue. It's not like it hasn't rained like that before and won't ever again. Caltex needs to come out and say what happened," he said.
"Take the bull by the horns and openly communicate what happened and what is being done to prevent it happening again." Botany resident Wendie McCaffley was walking through Botany Bay National Park on Monday when she was stopped in her tracks by an oil smell which was "unbearably strong".
She said Caltex's action, including no community notice, was inadequate. "That's the problem with having the port so close to the city, but it's why the industries have to be so vigilant. There is a high residential area around it and we don't want to live in a polluted harbour." Tell us what you think: Email news@southerncourier.com.au
THE response ■ Caltex said it did not produce a media release as the issue arose on Monday afternoon and was resolved shortly after. "Caltex has pollution reduction programs and works with the regulator to improve the environmental performance of operations" ■ The NSW Environment Protection Authority will investigate how the spill happened and ways to prevent it in the future■ The NSW Food Authority said there was no food safety issues regarding fishing in Botany Bay, following the oil release
]]></text></news-item>