<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-0JD1-F06S-P0B8"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Cigna and Penobscot Community Health Care Introduce Initiative with Focus on Oral Health</title><source>Health &amp; Beauty Close-Up</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Cigna and Penobscot Community Health Care, a Maine based community health center, announced that they have launched an initiative to help improve the oral health of those patients that have certain chronic medical conditions such as heart disease or diabetes.
According to a release, research has demonstrated a link between oral health and overall health, and there is evidence that good oral health may contribute to reduced risk of heart disease, stroke and diabetic complications.
Cigna will help Penobscot identify patients who might benefit the most from proactive educational outreach and enhanced preventive oral health services. Treating an individual's condition with an integrated dental and medical approach can help decrease the likelihood of health complications which, in turn, can enhance the patient's quality of life while reducing costs.
"When we use all the tools and resources at our disposal, like the kind of information and data that Cigna can provide in this initiative, it allows us to provide more effective and impactful coordination of medical and dental services. We are excited to be working with Cigna on this quality of care initiative because we believe it will make a real difference in the health and well-being of our patients with chronic illnesses," said Dr. Noah Nesin, chief quality officer at Penobscot Community Health Care.
"Oral health education is a critical component to the success of this initiative. The work we are doing with Penobscot Community Health Care to help patients with certain chronic conditions understand how the right oral health care, along with regular medical treatments, can improve their overall health is expected to drive better health outcomes, better service experiences and better savings," said Miles Hall, D.D.S., chief clinical dental director for Cigna.
The companies noted that a value-based compensation model is incorporated into this initiative. Cigna will increase Penobscot Community Health Care's dental fee schedule for successfully meeting targeted measurements with regard to its educational outreach, increase in customer use of preventive services and increase in customer satisfaction.
In addition to participating in Cigna's Dental PPO network, Penobscot Community Health Care participates in Cigna's collaborative accountable care initiative for physician practices. These programs focus on expanding patient access to health care, improving care coordination, and achieving improved health, affordability and patient experience. Collaborative accountable care is Cigna's approach to accomplishing the same population health goals as accountable care organizations, or ACOs, with a focus on high-risk individuals, including people with chronic health conditions such as diabetes or heart disease.
Penobscot Community Health Care is a non-profit organization governed by a board of community volunteers, incorporated in 1997. It provides access to patient-centered integrated health care services regardless of ability to pay. Focusing on the health of every patient, Penobscot Community Health Care offers a medical home with access to many health services in addition to primary health care, such as dental, integrated mental health, pharmacy, physical therapy, case management, health and nutrition education, chronic disease management, speech and audiology services, and many medical specialists.
Cigna Corp. is a global health service company with products and services including an integrated suite of health services, such as medical, dental, behavioral health, pharmacy, vision, supplemental benefits, and other related products including group life, accident and disability insurance.
More Information:
pchcbangor.org
cigna.com
((Comments on this story may be sent to newsdesk@closeupmedia.com))
]]></text></news-item>