<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-8HB1-DXCW-D2DT"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Manju for cementing regional bonds to cut disaster risk</title><source>Bangladesh Government News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The official news Agency of Bangladesh (BSS) has issued following news release:
Environment and Forests Minister Anwar Hossain Manju today stressed the need for cementing regional cooperation through sharing knowledge and experiences to minimize disaster risk in South and South-east Asia.
Due to geographical location, Bangladesh and other South and South-east Asian countries are particularly vulnerable to naturalcalamities, he told a symposium on 'Coastal community resilience'at a city hotel.
The Mangroves For the Future (MFF) National Coordinating Body(NCB) of Bangladesh and the MFF Secretariat, Bangkok organized the symposium.
Chief conservator of Forests Md Yunus Ali, senior advisor of Mangroves For the Future (MFF) Don Macintosh, country representative of the International Union for Conservation(UICN) Ishtiaq Uddin Ahmad, among others, addressed the inaugural session of the symposium with Environment and Forest Secretary Md Shafiqur Rahman Patwari in the chair.
Executive director of Centre for Natural Resources Studies(CNRS) M Mokhlesur Rahman and executive director of Bangladesh Centre for Advanced Studies Dr Atiq Rahman presented separate keynote papers at technical secession.
Bangladesh is one of the most disaster-prone countries in the world, Manju said adding the country is exposed to different natural disasters including flood, cyclone, drought, salinity intrusion as well as human induced disaster almost every year.
The government has taken massive initiatives to boost disaster management preparedness for minimizing losses of life and property, he said adding "We are taking multiple measures to strengthen disaster management capacity to face different disaster events."
Bangladesh is the worst victim of climate change and adequate measures should be taken to fight the climate change impact, Dr Atiq said. He warned that 20 to 25 million people of Bangladesh will become victims of climate change if adaptation measures are not taken immediately.
Adverse impact of climate change will increase frequency of natural disasters -- cyclone, flood, drought and river bank erosion -- in different costal countries like Bangladesh, Dr Atiq said adding, "We have to take adaptation measures to face climate change challenges to make Bangladesh a disaster resilient country."
Other speakers said coastal communities in many parts of Asia are particularly vulnerable to the impacts of climate change, with increased severity of extreme weather events directly affecting their lives and the resources they rely on for everyday survival.
Taking an ecosystem-based approach which includes healthy mangroves and other coastal ecosystem can make a major contribution to coastal community resilience, they added.
﻿
]]></text></news-item>