<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-R2G1-F11P-X184"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Ukraine's recruiting foreigners to restore order may be attempt to suppress civil protest - Moscow</title><source>Yerepouni Daily News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Media reports claiming that the Ukrainian leadership wants to recruit personnel from private foreign military companies "in order to maintain law and order" may suggest that the Kiev regime wants to suppress civil protest and discontent, the Russian Foreign Ministry said. "Anyway, one can state that in the absence of support from the Ukrainian population, the Maidan government has only one option if it wants to remain in power - to mobilize any support possible from foreign sponsors, including foreign mercenaries," the Russian Foreign Ministry said in a commentary.
"Among the candidates for the role of gendarme is the company Greystone Limited, registered in Barbados, which is integrated with the Academi corporation," it said.
"It is an analogue, or, probably, an affiliate body of the Blackwater private army, whose soldiers have been accused of committing rigorous and regular human rights abuses in troubled regions," the ministry said.
"It looks as though this practice, if it really is implemented, goes against the Ukrainian laws that ban foreign citizens from working with private security companies," it said.
"Such initiatives demonstrate that those who have conquered their place in power in Kiev cannot guarantee minimal order or even their own security," the Foreign Ministry said.
"The question arises, what the price of this plan is and where the money will come from. To what extent will the burden of spending on highly-paid foreign specialists be shifted to ordinary Ukrainians who, in connection with the painful tax increase, including taxes on gas as the precondition for securing loans from the International Monetary Fund, will have to tighten their belts even stronger?" it said.
Putin talks with Angela Merkel, calls for constitutional reform in Ukraine
Russian President Vladimir Putin has called for constitutional reform in Ukraine in order to ensure the legitimate rights and interests of its people. Putin was holding a telephone conversation with German Chancellor Angela Merkel on Monday, March 31. He called the chancellor to discuss "various aspects of the situation in Ukraine, including possible international assistance for the restoration of stability in the country", the presidential press service said.
"Discussing various aspects of the situation in Ukraine... Putin stressed the importance of holding constitutional reforms" in Ukraine, the Kremlin said in a statement.It added they also discussed Moldova's largely Russian-speaking breakaway region of Transdniestr bordering Ukraine and Putin raised "the need to take effective measures aimed at lifting an effective blockade from the outside of this region."
Russian President Vladimir Putin also said a series of effective measures must be taken to lift a de-facto blockade of Transdnestria by Moldova and Ukraine. Putin pointed out at the situation around Transdnestria.
]]></text></news-item>