<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-NJM1-DYT4-K019"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Fight for justice persists, 20 years into democracy</title><source>Business Day (South Africa)</source><author>Setumo Stone</author><text><![CDATA[Fight for justice persists, 20 years into democracy
talks to apartheid case lawyer Ntsebeza about why the suit in the US remains relevant
THE injustices that still bedevil SA due to its apartheid past are captured in the continuing apartheid lawsuit case before the high courts in the US.
The case, instituted by survivors of apartheid abuses in 2002, remains relevant two decades into democracy, says their lawyer, Dumisa Ntsebeza. & For as long as there is evidence that shows that these companies were working hand in hand (with the apartheid regime) in the gross violation of human rights and the international human rights law, then those cases are still justified.& The plaintiffs allege that these corporations, among them US car maker Ford and the world's biggest technology service provider, IBM, aided and abetted SA's oppressive former government in the gross violation of the victims' human rights.
In February this year, the plaintiffs filed fresh papers before the courts, arguing that while the US Supreme Court, which is the equivalent of the Constitutional Court in SA, ruled that German companies Daimler Chrysler and Rheinmetall could not be sued in America, the local groups were not off the hook.
The critical question now before the US courts is whether or not corporations, in the same way as natural persons, can be held liable under the Alien Torts Claims Act on the basis of the liability standard of aiding and abetting apartheid. & If the court says yes, companies, like natural persons, can be held liable, then we are still in the game.
& But if not, meaning that you cannot charge corporations, then that will be the end of the road,& Mr Ntsebeza says.
He says the companies being sued never came forward during SA's Truth and Reconciliation Commission (TRC).
Amnesty, according to the Promotion of National Unity and Reconciliation Act of 1995, which created the TRC, would be granted only to parties that voluntarily appeared before the commission to confess their wrongdoing.
At one point, the view of the South African government was that the case ran counter to the spirit of reconciliation, evident when former justice minister Penuell Maduna, under former president Thabo Mbeki, urged the US court in a letter to dismiss the case.
Mr Ntsebeza, also a former commissioner and head of investigations in the TRC, disagrees. & You can't just be forgiven when you have not come up with the truth,& he says. & Those who did not come forward exposed themselves to future criminal prosecution and civil claims. It is therefore false to bring up the reconciliation argument.& Big business largely snubbed the TRC. Few companies applied for amnesty, or disclosed their involvement in providing support to the apartheid regime.
The alleged apartheid crimes include the torture and extrajudicial killings of those who threatened the regime's grip on power. There were abductions and other incidents that qualify as crimes under international human rights law.
Mr Ntsebeza says that in some cases, the & management& of the companies insisted the victims co-operate with the police or lose their jobs. & That was the liability basis on which we began to sue,& he says.
Although they were just corporations engaged in making money, & they also became part and parcel of the machinery of the apartheid regime& Mr Ntsebeza says he can only speculate that big business did not come forward because it did not think there was an obligation on it to do so.
He says many individuals - such as the generals in the security police - also ignored the TRC. & Many of them are now roaming the streets, having tortured and killed our people. They are never chased by the National Prosecuting Authority even though evidence was there.& Is there political will or not, Mr Ntsebeza asks rhetorically.
But why has the matter been heard in the US? According to Mr Ntsebeza, most of the companies the plaintiffs are suing are US companies or companies based in the US. The act on which the plaintiffs' case is premised, the Alien Torts Claims Act, dates back to 1789.
Mr Ntsebeza says it was historically aimed at piracy, seen as a crime against the law of nations. & It meant that if you could find a defendant anywhere in the world, who was guilty of violating the law of nations, the defendant could be brought to a court in the US and the court could use this piece of legislation to hold them accountable and order them to pay damages.& The US Supreme Court last year ruled the Alien Torts Claims Act was not intended to be of extraterritorial application, effectively dismissing the case against Daimler Chrysler and Rheinmetall. However, Ford and IBM, as US companies, can be held accountable.
On the plus side, Mr Ntsebeza says, there is now political will on both sides, with the governments of both Jacob Zuma and Barack Obama voicing support for the case to go ahead.
stones@bdfm.co.za
For as long as there is evidence showing these companies were working hand in hand (with the apartheid regime) in the gross violation of human rights, those cases are still justified
Those who did not come forward exposed themselves to future prosecution and civil claims
Advocate Dumisa Ntsebeza, left, is determined to wring justice from companies that snubbed the Truth and Reconciliation Commission, right. Pictures: SUNDAY TIMES, SOWETAN
]]></text></news-item>