<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-07Y1-F15H-C04S"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Illegal workers found in Rothesay restaurant raids</title><source>The Buteman</source><author>Newsdesk</author><text><![CDATA[Six immigration offenders were caught during Home Office Immigration Enforcement action in Rothesay on Friday.
The men were found following an operation targeting four restaurants in the town - the India Pavilion in Argyle Street, Bute Asia in High Street, Jade Garden in Gallowgate and Shonar Gaon in Victoria Street.
Officers spoke to staff working at the restaurants to establish whether they had the right to be and work in the UK. All were found to be in the country illegally.
They included a 32-year-old Indian at India Pavilion, a 42-year-old Argentinian and a 23-year-old Indian at Bute Asia, a 36-year-old from Myanmar at Jade Garden and two Bangladeshi nationals, aged 24 and 51, at Shonar Gaon.
All are currently in Home Office detention while steps are taken to remove them from the country.
The owner of each business will be issued with a notice of potential liability of up to £10,000 per illegal worker employed. The Bute Asia and Shonar Goan both face penalties of up to £20,000 each and the Indian Pavilion and Jade Garden face a penalty of £10,000 each.
Iain Stewart, from Home Office Immigration Enforcement, said: "Illegal working undercuts honest employers, defrauds the public purse and cheats legitimate job hunters out of employment opportunities.
"We are happy to work with employers to explain the simple checks that need to be carried out to establish a person's right to work in the UK.
"The message to those who choose to ignore the rules is clear. We will find you and you will face a heavy financial penalty.
"I would ask anyone with specific and detailed information about suspected illegal working to get in touch."
Employers unsure of the steps they need to take to avoid employing illegal workers can visit www.gov.uk/check-an-employees-right-to-work-documentsor they can call the Employers Helpline on 0300 123 4699.
Anyone with information about suspected immigration abuse can contact www.gov.uk/report-immigration-crime or call Crimestoppers on 0800 555 111.
]]></text></news-item>