<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-T8V1-F0JP-W4BN"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>CFMEU fine spurs push for watchdog</title><source>The Australian</source><author>Rick Wallace</author><text><![CDATA[THE building industry has demanded the ALP and Greens allow the return of the construction watchdog after a Supreme Court judge fined Australia's main building union a record $1.25 million over an ugly blockade of two of builder Grocon's Melbourne sites.
Master Builders Australia chief executive Wilhelm Harnisch said the hefty fines imposed on the Construction Forestry Mining and Energy Union sent an unambiguous message to parliament of the -urgent need for the return of the Australian Building and Construction Commission and its strong oversight powers.
"It is a clear rebuttal to those who choose to deny or defend the underlying culture of intimidation of the CFMEU," Mr Harnisch said.
"It's a message to the Labor Party and to the Greens that this culture of intimidation can't be allowed and can't be supported and there must be an early -return of the ABCC and its -powers." Mr Harnisch said the verdict would embolden other builders to fight the union's attempts to seize control of their sites, but not all had the resources of Grocon to fight such a long and costly court battle.
"Had the ABCC or its powers existed at the time there would have been early intervention and it would have been stopped," he said of the 2012 protests.
The CFMEU was found to have committed four counts of criminal contempt over a series of blockades it instituted on the Emporium building and one other site in Melbourne's CBD in April 2012. The blockade was launched in retaliation for the company's decision not to bow to the union's pressure to gain control over its building sites -by appointing its own shop stewards.
In handing down a $250,000 penalty for each count, judge Anthony Cavanough said the CFMEU's disregard for the court's orders convinced him to impose criminal rather than civil contempt offences.
The judge penalised the union a total of $250,000 more over two further counts of contempt involving the blocking of shipments of precast concrete components from two Grocon suppliers last year, but ruled these were civil rather criminal contempt offences.
Late yesterday, the CFMEU issued a statement in the name of secretary John Setka claiming the dispute was about safety, saying 23 workers had died on building sites since 2012 and workers needed stewards who represented their interests rather than someone "hand picked by the boss".
"The union is not seeking to be above the law," Mr Setka said. "We want to save lives." Grocon has been the sole major builder in Australia prepared to stand up to the CFMEU in its stronghold state of Victoria and keep union delegates from controlling its sites. As a result, it has suffered considerable disruption from the Continued on Page 6 From page 1 union, whose leadership reportedly says it wants to "smash" Grocon. The company issued a statement yesterday hailing the Supreme Court's decision as "a defining moment for the construction industry and the rule of law".
"Today's decision should send a clear message to the CFMEU leadership that they can no longer operate outside of the law with impunity," Grocon said. The company is continuing to pursue a civil case against the unions for the millions of dollars of losses it suffered as a result of the blockades.
In deciding on the record fine, Justice Cavanough noted that the CFMEU had significant financial resources and its Victoria-Tasmania branch had set aside $2m for legal settlements.
On top of the $1.25m fines, the case is expected to cost the CFMEU at least another $1m in legal costs. However, the powerful, ultra-militant union has vast financial resources comprising more than $12m in cash and assets of more than $50m, according to documents tendered in court.
Workplace Relations Minister Eric Abetz said yesterday's decision made it clear it was unacceptable for the CFMEU to blockade a building site, intimidate staff, threaten and vilify employees and engage in battles with police.
At the height of the blockades, police had to use horses to try to safely allow Grocon employees access to the site to go about their work.
Senator Abetz called on the ALP and the Greens to allow the stalled bill to re-establish the ABCC through the Senate.
"Today's penalty is yet one more reason why Bill Shorten and Labor must stop running a protection racket for union bosses engaged in illegal and unlawful behaviour," he said.
Master Builders Association of Victoria chief executive Radley de Silva said it was "time the union threw out its outdated playbook tactics of chaos, fear, intimidation and lawlessness".
"Our industry and the community were held to ransom by the CFMEU for weeks during this blockade," Mr de Silva said. "Victorians deserve better than having to foot the bill when unions force delays and cost blowouts on construction sites." Victorian Planning Minister Matthew Guy said state Opposition Leader Daniel Andrews should now demand the disaffiliation of this "rogue" union from the Labor Party in Victoria.
Mr Andrews labelled the illegal CFMEU blockade appalling and said the union should pay the fine promptly.
Documents tendered to the court show the CFMEU Victorian-Tasmanian branch had the means to pay the hefty fine.The judge has given the CFMEU 30 days to decide whether it will appeal against the judgement or pay the fines.
]]></text></news-item>