<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-B871-DY9P-N185"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Gas test drill proposals thrown out; Councillors reject plans over environment fears</title><source>Daily Post (North Wales)</source><author>STEVE BAGNALL</author><text><![CDATA[CONTROVERSIAL plans to test drill for gas were last night thrown out by councillors.
GP Energy Ltd had submitted proposals to test drill for coal bed gas on land near Commonwood Farm, Borras, Wrexham, which had been recommended for the go-ahead.
But at a Wrexham Council planning committee meeting last night councillors decided to reject the plans amid concerns over its impact on the environment.
The proposals had been deferred at a previous planning committee after councillors expressed concerns whether they would impact on the area's vast network of underground mines.
There were also fears it could disturb the tombs of the hundreds of miners who died in the 1934 Gresford Mining Disaster.
But after inquiries from Wrexham council planners with the Coal Authority, a report said the borehole would be more than 1km from the nearest point of the abandoned mine workings, according to records held by the CA.
A report to the planning committee last night said the test borehole was: "highly unlikely to impact in any way with the Gresford mine workings."
Last night councillors expressed serious concerns over the proposals. Cllr Dave Kelly was worried, due to the geology of Wrexham, it could lead to a gas escape and said: "We are drilling into the unknown here."
Cllr Ronnie Prince said: "I cannot support this application, it is a precursor to fracking, which could be this generation's asbestos."
Cllr Andrew Bailey said it went against Welsh planning policies, drilling in a rural area which was not acceptable.
When the decision was made there were cheers from the public gallery from protestors, who had earlier staged a demonstration outside.
Councillors had also expressed concerns, if the application was granted, it could lead to mass drilling to get gas out across a large area of Wrexham.
Other concerns have included its impact on the environment, the pollution of water courses, greenhouse gases being emitted into the air, subsidence and sink holes appearing.
]]></text></news-item>