<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-TB31-JD3N-541V"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Hanlong chief faces life in jail</title><source>The Australian</source><author>SCOTT MURDOCH, CHINA CORRESPONDENT</author><text><![CDATA[HIGH-profile Chinese business figure Liu Han, the founder of the Hanlong Group, is facing life in jail after his murder and corruption trial began in China yesterday.
Liu, who has major stakes in Australian companies, is one of 34 people facing trial in the Hubei province, in China's central region, after they were charged for being part of a major organised crime ring.
It was alleged in court yesterday that Liu ordered the deaths of a number of his business rivals in the province.
Liu allegedly ordered the execution of his rivals, often in public places like tea houses, to reinforce his power and help Hanlong maintain its dominance as a mining company.
Hanlong remains the largest shareholder of ASX-listed miners Moly Group and Sundance Resources, after it launched an ambitious overseas expansion plan that focused on Australia and Africa.
A $1.3 billion bid for Sundance collapsed last year after the Chinese group could not -secure finance.
Xinhua, China's official news agency, said Liu tried to offset his alleged mafia rule by being one of Sichuan's most generous -philanthropists.
He famously built a new -elementary rural school campus after an earthquake in 2008 devastated the province.
Liu Han's brother Liu Wei faced court yesterday also charged with corruption and murder and being part of a "mafia-style" group.
A photograph of Liu Han in the court's dock, flanked by -policemen, was published on Chinese state and social media.
It has been speculated that Liu will spend the rest of his life in jail, given court sentences are usually negotiated in China -before the trial starts.
The case has captivated China given Liu's high profile and ranking as one of the richest men in the country.
Liu, who is reportedly worth at least 40bn yuan ($6.97bn), has had his assets seized as part of the police investigation. "His business empire was backed by menace," Xinhua wrote last month.
It said that Mr Liu and his gang "have accumulated enormous wealth in property, mining, and electricity" via illegal means.
Sichuan is one of the powerbases of Zhou Yongkang, China's former hugely powerful security chief, who is at the centre of rumours about a corruption investigation.State media have hinted that Liu Han's gang had political connections to central government officials.
]]></text></news-item>