<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-10G1-DYMS-S0KX"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Former tycoon on trial for murder</title><source>Shenzhen Daily</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A FORMER Sichuan Province mining magnate went on trial yesterday over charges including murder after being accused of leading a 36-member gang on a crime spree spanning two decades.
Liu Han, former chairman of unlisted Hanlong Group and once ranked the 230th-richest person in China, faced trial in Hubei Province along with the other members of his mafia-style gang, Xinhua said. Xinhua said Liu, who was arrested last year, was facing charges ranging from murder to gun-running and extortion for crimes carried out in Si-chuan. His gang was responsible for nine murders, Xinhua said, without giving details. Hanlong Group, the biggest private enterprise in Sichuan, made headlines when it tried to take over Australia’s Sundance Resources. Its proposed US$1.29 billion deal for Sundance, a West Africa-focused iron ore explorer, was called off a year ago after Hanlong missed funding deadlines. Hanlong still has a majority stake in Australian-listed iron ore miner Moly Mines and remains the biggest shareholder of Sundance Resources. Police launched an investigation last year into Liu and his younger brother, Liu Yong — also known as Liu Wei — on suspicion of criminal activities, media has said. Prosecutors in Hubei said the two set up the gang in 1993, along with 34 others, and “carried out a vast number of criminal activities.” “The ring allegedly led by former mining tycoon Liu Han and his brother, Liu Wei, in Sichuan Province, is the largest mafia-style criminal group under trial in recent years in the country,” Xinhua said. The probe into Liu marks one of the highest-profile cases against a private businessman since President Xi Jinping took power last year and vowed to crack down on corruption. The police investigation into the activities of Liu and his associates eventually covered more than 10 provinces and cities, including Beijing, Xinhua has previously said. Liu founded Hanlong Group, a conglomerate spanning solar energy to real estate and infrastructure, in 1997. (SD-Agencies)
]]></text></news-item>