<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-TB31-JD3N-541D"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>CFMEU fine spurs push for watchdog</title><source>The Australian</source><author>Rick Wallace</author><text><![CDATA[THE building industry has demanded the ALP and Greens allow the return of the construction watchdog after a Supreme Court judge fined Australia's main building union a record $1.25 million over a blockade of two Grocon sites in Melbourne.
Master Builders Australia chief executive Wilhelm Harnisch said the hefty fines imposed on the Construction Forestry Mining and Energy Union sent an unambiguous message to parliament of the urgent need for the return of the Australian Building and Construction Commission and its strong oversight powers.
"It is a clear rebuttal to those who choose to deny or defend the underlying culture of intimidation of the CFMEU," he said. "It's a message to the Labor Party and to the Greens that this culture of intimidation can't be allowed and can't be supported and there must be an early return of the ABCC and its powers." The verdict would embolden other builders to fight the union's attempts to seize control of their sites, but not all had the resources of Grocon to fight such a long and costly court battle.
The CFMEU was found to have committed four counts of criminal contempt over a series of blockades on the Emporium building and another site in 2012. The action was launched after the company decided not to bow to union pressure to gain control over building sites by -appointing its own shop stewards.
In handing down a $250,000 penalty for each count, judge Anthony Cavanough said the CFMEU's disregard for the court's orders had convinced him to impose criminal rather than civil contempt offences. He penalised the union a total of $250,000 more over two further counts of contempt involving the blocking of shipments of precast concrete components from two Grocon suppliers last year, but ruled these were civil rather criminal contempt offences.
Late yesterday the CFMEU -issued a statement in the name of secretary John Setka claiming the dispute was about safety, saying 23 workers had died on building sites since 2012 and workers needed stewards who represented their interests rather than someone "hand picked by the boss".
"The union is not seeking to be above the law," Mr Setka said. "We want to save lives." Grocon has been the sole major builder in Australia prepared to stand up to the CFMEU in Victoria and keep union delegates from controlling its sites. As a result it has suffered considerable disruption from the union, whose leadership reportedly says it wants to "smash" Grocon.
The company issued a statement yesterday hailing the -court's decision as "a defining moment for the construction industry and the rule of law".
"Today's decision should send a clear message to the CFMEU leadership that they can no longer operate outside of the law with impunity," Grocon said. "The company is continuing to pursue a civil case against the -unions for the millions of dollars of losses it suffered as a result of the blockades." In deciding on the record fine, Justice Cavanough noted the CFMEU had significant financial resources and its Victoria-Tasmania branch had set aside $2m for legal settlements.On top of the $1.25m fines the case is expected to cost the CFMEU another $1m in legal costs. The powerful union has vast financial resources comprising more than $12m in cash and assets of more than $50m, according to documents tendered in court.
]]></text></news-item>