<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-7NK1-DYX2-90KW"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Climate Change Report</title><source>CTV Television, Inc.</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[LISA LAFLAMME: Good evening. The threat of climate change reached a whole new level today for the entire world. Hundreds of scientists have delivered the most complete judgment ever, a 2,000-page report filled with startling predictions and alarming language. The summary uses the word "risk" 230 times alone. It talks about hot spots of hunger, poverty, and economic shock, along with severe, pervasive, and irreversible impacts. CTV's Omar Sachedina now with more on a massive call for change.
OMAR SACHEDINA (Reporter): Not only is global warming very real, the report warns, the worst is yet to come.
DR. RAJENDRA PACHAURI (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change Chairman): Nobody on this planet is going to be untouched by the impacts of climate change.
SACHEDINA: 310 scientists from 73 countries, including Canada, say the political and financial consequences are dire. More risk of violent conflicts as food, land and water become more scarce, soaring prices for produce, even higher insurance rates as fierce natural disasters strike with greater intensity.
ANDY ATKINS (Friends of the Earth Executive Director): Unless we cut our greenhouse gas emissions very rapidly, we will be inflicting disaster on ourselves and generations to come.
SACHEDINA: For Canada, the report comes after one of the worst winters in decades and following a catastrophic summer of floods in Alberta and Ontario. The message - get used to more extreme weather.
DEBRA DAVIDSON (University of Alberta): For all of Canada, even relative to other parts of the world, on average our temperatures are going to increase at a greater rate.
SACHEDINA: Debra Davidson was one of the report's lead authors. She says those wild swings in weather will hurt farmers. Two years ago, almost 90 percent of Ontario's apple crop was devastated after a sudden spring heat wave followed by a big chill. Davidson expects more of that.
DAVIDSON: Non-average years, years in which we're going to be in drought situations or in extreme weather situations or simply more unpredictable weather.
SACHEDINA: The opposition accuses the Conservatives of dragging their feet on climate change. Seven years ago, for example, the Harper government promised environmental regulations for the oil and gas industries but, Lisa, they still haven't delivered.
LAFLAMME: Okay, Omar. Thank you for this tonight from Ottawa.
]]></text></news-item>