<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW7-MDX1-JBKR-43ST"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Former theatre manager pleads guilty to fraud</title><source>The Leader-Post (Regina, Saskatchewan)</source><author>Hannah Spray, The Starphoenix</author><text><![CDATA[The former general manager of the Saskatchewan Native Theatre Company admits she lied to the federal government about how grant money was being used.
Donna Heimbecker, 53, pleaded guilty Monday in Saskatoon provincial court to defrauding Human Resources Skills Development Canada (HRDC) of an amount exceeding $5,000.
The charge arose out of an examination of the 2006 and 2007 financial records of the local non-profit organization. SNTC received a $250,000 grant for capital expenses related to renovations, but Heimbecker used most of that money ($211,000) for operating expenses.
The misuse of the money, in itself, wasn't necessarily criminal; the fraud charge arises from Heimbecker's misrepresentations to the government about the use of the money, Crown prosecutor Darren Howarth said in court.
Heimbecker asked a construction company to provide her with an invoice showing how much money would have been spent, if a certain amount of work was performed. She then passed that invoice on to the government as if it was real, to make officials believe the capital grant was being spent properly.
Her actions were not discovered until after she left SNTC in 2010.
Heimbecker founded SNTC with her then-husband, but as it grew, managing it became more complicated, defence lawyer Darren Winegarden said.
Since the charges were made public, Heimbecker's career has been in shambles, he said.
She accepts full responsibility for her role in misusing the money, but Winegarden said she wasn't alone in the action.
"She did receive some direction from a bookkeeper and an accountant for how to do this," Winegarden said in court.
Heimbecker said she's proud of the theatre company and she's "very sorry" for what she did.
"I would just like to say that this has been really difficult for me, personally and professionally," she said. "I'm very embarrassed by what's happened and I'm trying to find the strength to take responsibility for what I've done."
It was difficult for the Crown to quantify the amount of the loss, Howarth said. Normally, a $200,000 fraud would attract jail time, but this case was unique because Heimbecker didn't pocket the money. Rather, the money was used to keep the theatre company operating. She drew a salary from the organization, but there's no direct link between the fraud and her employment, Howarth said.
"Who was out the money was (the government), but of course it was a grant to start out with," he said. "They aren't out of pocket, but they didn't get what they paid for, what they contracted for."
The Crown and defence jointly submitted a one-year community-based sentence, consisting of a three-month conditional sentence order followed by nine months of probation, during which Heimbecker must perform 100 hours of community service work.
Judge Shannon Metivier accepted the recommendation, commenting that the real victim was the theatre company's reputation.
"I think the damage is to the very entity you created. I think that's the very saddest thing, that's the legacy," Metivier said.
SNTC's current general manager, Alan Long, attended Heimbecker's sentencing and said outside court that the company has eliminated its debt and moved on.
]]></text></news-item>