<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-6601-F08V-61XV"><date>2014-04-01</date><title></title><source>South Jersey Times (New Jersey)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[To the Editor:
We already know that there is misinformation about natural gas as a safe "alternative energy" source.
Politicians say that building the Keystone XL pipeline will bring jobs. This is one of the biggest ways politicians fool people. It is important to understand how they came up with a tens-of-thousands-of-jobs fallacy.
Russ Girling, CEO of pipeline owner TransCanada Corp., has said that the construction project would create 13,000 U.S. jobs. But Girling has explained that this calculation uses the "one-person, one-year" method, which means that one person working for two years on the pipeline counts as "two" jobs.
A 6,500-job figure is in line with U.S. State Department projections and most independent estimates. Anything that creates jobs should be considered, but had the recent federal payroll tax holiday been extended past 2012, it would have spurred more jobs than the pipeline.
Also, most of the Keystone XL jobs would be temporary, low-paying, manual-labor jobs. Apparently, politicians think creating a few thousand such jobs for a pipeline through America's agricultural heartland is more important than helping 160 million American working families. A spill from the pipeline has the potential of destroying wildlife, and environmentalists claim it could pollute groundwater for 2 million Americans.
There is no good outcome for the American people in building the pipeline, but politicians are so intent on adding to the oil/gas industry's perpetual high profits that they feel justified in rewarding the industry with subsidies from U.S. taxpayers.
The same spin has been put on the 22-mile natural-gas pipeline through the Pinelands that has been proposed by South Jersey Gas Co. (The Pinelands Commission has rejected the pipeline, but its backers want the panel to reconsider it.)
Remember when makers of cigarettes, now deemed as cancer-causing, advertised that nine out of 10 doctors recommend smoking and even smoked themselves? Watch what is spent on spin doctors and promotion.
Tino Rosso
Vineland
LoBiondo impressive on a rainy Saturday
To the Editor:
Saturday, March 29, saw the arrival of U.S. Rep. Frank LoBiondo, R-2nd Dist., at the Highland Firehouse in Pitman to meet citizens in this part of his district.
Although I did not see mention of this in the press, I'd like to note that LoBiondo came out in the pouring rain to listen to what we everyday folks had on our minds: the economy, jobs and health care. I spoke to him about Congress doing more for active military families and our military veterans.
I was also impressed with the fire company members and want to publicly thank them for their service to Pitman and surrounding communities. They are dedicated volunteers who deserve our respect and admiration for the important job they do.
I heartily endorse LoBiondo (who is running for re-election) and the continuing great job performance by the Pitman Highland Chemical Engine Co.
Josephine Ladd
Mantua Township
Good to see Minor running for Congress
To the Editor:
I am thrilled that Logan Township Mayor Frank Minor is running for the First District congressional nomination in the June 3 Democratic Primary.
As a township resident, I know how much he cares about the people he represents and how hard he works for them. Residents feel comfortable calling him at his home or dropping by his house whenever they have a problem.
Minor does not just listen to your problem, but immediately gets started trying to solve it. He also follows up until the problem is resolved. Residents also appreciate his efforts in keeping our municipal property taxes low.
I know that Minor can help many more people as a congressman. He is willing to take on big challenges and does not lose sight of who he is working for.
Mayor Minor puts the interest of residents first, which is why he is absolutely the best person to represent our district.
Sheriese Coy-Armour
Logan Township
]]></text></news-item>