<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-SDN1-J9YR-G0G1"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Watchdog criticises BT rural broadband 'monopoly'; All of the £490 million of state subsidies for delivery of rural broadband has gone to BT</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Sophie Curtis</author><text><![CDATA[The government has failed to deliver meaningful competition in the procurement of its £1.2 billion rural broadband programme, leaving BT in a monopoly position, according to a new report by the Public Accounts Committee (PAC).
The Broadband Delivery UK (BDUK) scheme is designed to help get broadband to hard-to-reach areas where commercial broadband infrastructure providers currently have no plans to invest.
The PAC raised concerns in September 2013 that over half of the 44 contracts to deliver this had been awarded to BT. Of the nine suppliers initially bidding within the BDUK framework, most had dropped out and the only other - Fujitsu - was largely inactive. Since then, however, all remaining contracts have gone to BT as well.
"Despite our warnings last September, the Department for Culture, Media and Sport has allowed poor cost transparency and the lack of detailed broadband rollout plans to create conditions whereby alternative suppliers may be crowded out," said, the Rt Hon Margaret Hodge MP, Chair of the PAC.
"We see the lack of transparency on costs and BT's insistence on non-disclosure agreements as symptomatic of BT's exploiting its monopoly position to the detriment of the taxpayer, local authorities and those seeking to access high speed broadband in rural areas."
Ms Hodge said that, some communities can still not access the detailed data they need to understand whether they will be covered by BT's scheme in their area. She warned that other broadband providers might be squeezed out of the rural market by BT's actions.
She called on the Department for Culture, Media and Sport (DCMS) to collect, analyse and publish data on deployment costs in the current BDUK programme, to inform its consideration of bids from suppliers under the next round of funding, and work with local authorities to ensure there is real competition and value for money.
"If we don't hear that the Department is making significant progress on our recommendations we will require a further hearing to find out why it is not improving its approach to protecting public funds," she warned.
Responding to the PAC report, a BT spokesperson said the criticism of BT was "inaccurate and unjustified".
"It is frustrating that the committee continues to try and pick holes in the programme rather than recognise the wider value and benefits it is delivering," he said.
"BT was the only company willing to accept the challenging terms on offer and make a significant investment in rural areas. This was at a time when others walked away when they realised easy pickings weren't to be had. Claims that BT is a 'monopoly' are simply inaccurate given more than 100 ISPs are offering fibre across BT's open network."
Earlier this year, DCMS announced an acceleration of the government's rollout of superfast broadband to rural communities in the UK. The number of properties able to access speeds of more than 24Mbps reached 273,731at the end of December, up from 111,968 at the end of September.
DCMS estimates that more than 300,000 UK premises can now access superfast speeds due to the programme, and the number of homes and premises gaining access will rise from 10,000 per week to 40,000 per week by the summer.
Communications minister Ed Vaizey said: "The government's nationwide broadband rollout is ahead of schedule; multiple robust safeguards are already in place to ensure value for money, and thousands of homes and businesses up and down the country are already getting the benefits."
]]></text></news-item>