<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-TB31-JC17-G0S0"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Pay college athletes</title><source>Pittsburgh Tribune Review</source><author>By Peter Morici</author><text><![CDATA[The National Labor Relations Board determination that Northwestern University football players are employees and may form a union, along with other lawsuits moving through the courts, has the potential to end the exploitation of young athletes by universities, coaches and fans.
The advent of cable television gave universities vast opportunities to profit from football and basketball, and the large and most lucrative programs have consolidated into five major conferences. Those programs dominate the national championship tournaments and earn huge sums.
Universities monopolize the market for athletes' services through the NCAA, which stipulates that players are amateurs and can't be paid salaries. This denies them the value they create with their labor and unique talents.
Coaches earn millions, universities use profits to subsidize other activities and the fans get cheap entertainment. Universities twist admissions standards and faculty bend grades to deliver winners and appease wealthy donors.
In exchange for scholarships for tuition, room and board, and limited expenses, student athletes are expected to train year-round and work 40 to 60 hours per week during the season. Their lives are tightly controlled and often this impairs their development into fully capable adults.
Most athletes will not enter a pro league, but instead leave college with a degree in a soft major that has little value in today's tough job market or no diploma at all. Many leave with medical conditions from injuries but no financial assistance to pay for care.
Northwestern football players are not necessarily seeking salaries as much as better opportunities to complete degrees and additional health insurance. However, if upheld on appeal, the NLRB decision will greatly aid plaintiffs in two pending antitrust suits that seek to break NCAA rules prohibiting salaries and permitting universities to use player images and names in endorsements and promotions without compensation.
Those suits have the potential to do to college sports what free agency did to professional football, baseball and basketball after the courts struck down owners' monopoly practices similar to current NCAA rules.
The top 30 or 40 programs in each college sport will be able to pay top dollar to attract the best athletes, and the other universities will not be able to effectively compete. The solution may be to permit the top 30 or 40 universities to form football and basketball teams "affiliated" with their institutions and a major pro franchise, but require those to be self-financing based on game-day revenues and contributions from the professional teams.
Pay the athletes, offer them the opportunity to earn a degree over five or six years, but don't require them to enroll if they are not capable or are simply disinclined. By disengaging university-sponsored athletics from academic programs, the potential to corrupt admissions and faculty would be greatly reduced and a broader range of gifted young athletes would have the opportunity to participate.
Then all the other universities could have walk-on programs for genuine amateurs, and those programs, in a manner similar to the Ivy League schools and military academies, could compete at a level that complements a decent university education.
After all, a quality education is why young people should go to college.
Peter Morici is an economist and professor at the University of Maryland Robert H. Smith School of Business.
]]></text></news-item>