<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-KR81-JDK3-9343"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Ewart: Encana finding its focus</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Almost five years after the breakup of Canada's largest oil and gas producer to create two "highly focused energy companies," Encana chief executive Doug Suttles is delivering on that pledge.
It hasn't gone entirely according to plan - Encana abandoned the original idea of being a pure-play natural gas producer - but shareholders of the increasingly smaller company are starting to reap the benefits of Suttles' less-is-more strategy.
Encana shares hit a 52-week high of $23.77 on Toronto Stock Exchange Monday after the company announced the widely expected sale of its once-prized Jonah gas field in Wyoming as part of sweeping changes in strategy, management and assets since Suttles was hired last June.
It was just days after Suttles' appointment that Encana's stock bottomed out at $17.40 per share. In the nine months since, Encana has cut its dividend, shed 20 per cent of its employees, closed offices, focused on key assets - and seen its market capitalization surge by $4.6 billion.
The $1.8-billion US sale of the Jonah gas field in Wyoming won't be the last property off-loaded in the strategy that, as CIBC World Markets said in a research note Monday, "ultimately supports the transition to a higher liquids-weighted production base."
Encana announced in December it would focus the bulk of its 2014 spending, about $2.5 billion, on five oil and liquids-rich plays; B.C.'s Montney, the Duvernay in Alberta, DJ Basin in Colorado, San Juan Basin in New Mexico and Tuscaloosa Marine Shale in Louisiana and Mississippi.
"This transaction is consistent with our strategy ... allowing our teams to focus on our five core growth areas," Suttles said in a statement Monday.
With 90 per cent of production in gas, even as its focus shifts to high-value gas liquids and oil, the turnaround at Encana remains a work in progress.
It's proceeding with plans to package its large tract of fee title lands in Alberta where its collects royalties on production - its Clearwater business unit - as a new company through an initial public offering by summer. Encana will retain an ownership stake in Clearwater, which industry analysts have said may be worth as much as $3 billion.
Chief financial officer Sherri Brillon has also said the 300 million cubic feet a day Deep Panuke gas project off Nova Scotia "doesn't really fit our portfolio."
Suttles, a former executive with BP, has put profitability ahead of production in Encana's turnaround.
At one time, Jonah, one of North America's largest natural gas fields, was a critical part of EnCana's strategy to focus on unconventional gas plays in the U.S. and Canada. The field has about 1,500 active wells and accounted for about 12 per cent of Encana's gas production in 2013.
The sale doesn't include Encana's operations at Pavillion, Wy., where the Environmental Protection Agency is investigating the company's fracking practices following complaints about contaminated drinking water. Encana refuted the EPA's claims and a report from the agency is expected in September.
Encana acquired its first stake in the field in 2000, when it was still Alberta Energy Company. It emerged as a self-styled global super independent with the merger of AEC and PanCanadian Energy in 2002. By 2008, a plan was announced to split the corporate behemoth into a pair of "highly focused" independent companies - one a gas producer, Encana, the other an oil company, Cenovus Energy.
At the same time, the proliferation of fracking created a gas supply glut in North America that drove prices to uneconomic levels - $2.26 a gigajoule in Alberta in 2012 and $3.01 last year - and Encana's business strategy and share price tanked, too.
Chief executive Randy Eresman resigned last January as the beleaguered gas producer's problems mounted.
Soon after Suttles arrived at Encana he complained the company's operations were spread too far afield - "we have something like 28 or so different asset opportunities every single one of them are being funded" - and let it be known he would narrow the focus to the best assets.
Encana needed "radical change," Suttles said in announcing his new strategy in November.
More than 1,000 employees - about a quarter of its workforce - were let go in 2013 and about 100 more will leave with the Jonah sale.
The resurgence in gas prices with the frigid winter has boosted the fortunes of producers, but it was Suttles who did as much as anyone to dampen the enthusiasm of investors when he cautioned this year that prices would stay "range bound" at $3.50 and $4.50 over the next three or four years.
If anything, Suttles' caution is a reality check that Encana must continue to be "highly focused" going forward.
Stephen Ewart is a Calgary Herald columnist.
sewart@calgaryherald.com( mailto:sewart@calgaryherald.com )
© Copyright (c) The Calgary Herald
]]></text></news-item>