<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-8MC1-JC1N-W00K"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>2 men die in separate workplace accidents; OSHA: Multiple fatal accidents in same area uncommon.; PERSONAL SAFETY</title><source>Dayton Daily News (Ohio)</source><author>By Nick Blizzard</author><text><![CDATA[Two local men died in separate area workplace accidents in a 24-hour span - a rarity, according to the Occupational Safety & Health Administration.
Having two fatal workplace accidents in the same area occurs "very infrequently," said Bill Wilkerson, area director for OSHA's Cincinnati office.
James L. Mitchell of Vandalia was killed likely late Sunday night in an industrial accident at Certified Heat Treating in West Carrollton, while Greene County employee Jeremy Lovely of Fairborn died late Monday morning while operating a backhoe in Beaver-creek, authorities said.
OSHA is investigating Mitchell's death but does not have jurisdiction over the Greene County accident because it involves a local government employee, Wilkerson said.
Mitchell, 48, was killed at the business at 4475 Infirmary Road. He was apparently working with a furnace as part of a the heat-treating process, got caught in "some sort of door" that "apparently closed on him while he was doing some work," Wilkerson said.
Mitchell was alone at the time and his body discovered later, he said.
Attempts to contact Certified Heat Treating officials Monday were unsuccessful. The company ceased operations on Monday so employees could grieve, Wilkerson said.
He said the business has no history of OSHArelated complaints.
An autopsy of Mitchell's body was scheduled for Monday afternoon. Preliminary results may be released today, according to the Montgomery County Coroner's Office.
OSHA has visited the premises and talked with managers.
Wilkerson said OSHA plans to talk with the foreman and employees who perform similar work as Mitchell.
Wilkerson said his agency will respect the employees' grieving process, but would like to talk with them while information is "still pretty fresh in their minds and they don't forget details that may be important to us."
OSHA's Cincinnati office will review the information and prepare a report that will be reviewed by OSHA's regional and national offices. OSHA then would issue its findings, Wilkerson said.
The process may take three to six months, he said.
Meanwhile, Lovely, 34, was killed while operating a Bobcat to dig a hole near Kemp and Beaver Valley Road around 11 a.m. Monday, said Det. Chris Moore of the Greene County Sheriff's Office.
A switch was inadvertently flipped on the machine, causing a function that led to Lovely's death, Moore said. He said Loving was pronounced dead at the scene.
A crew of workers was in the area, but no other injuries were reported, he said. Moore said the sheriff's office has no reason to believe foul play was involved.
Lovely's body has been sent to Montgomery County. An autopsy is scheduled to be performed today, officials said.
Yuna Lee of WHIO contributed to this report.
]]></text></news-item>