<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-F621-JCPJ-W031"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Patton Boggs woes mount with defections, Chevron ruling</title><source>Washington Business Journal</source><author>Tucker Echols</author><text><![CDATA[Patton Boggs has more woes than Job these days. In addition to&nbsp; seeking solutions to its financial situation,&nbsp; downsizing&nbsp; and&nbsp; exploring a merger, the&nbsp;Washington law firm and lobbying powerhouse has suffered a major legal setback and the defection of&nbsp;six former partners who&nbsp;will form&nbsp;the foundation of a&nbsp;new McGuireWoods LLP&nbsp;office in Dallas.&nbsp;
In&nbsp; announcing the expansion,&nbsp;McGuireWoods managing partner Tom Cabaniss hailed new arrivals&nbsp;Jon Finger, Akash Sethi, J. Kevin Boardman,&nbsp;David McLean, Darren Collins and Robert Hilton as a&nbsp;"talented and entrepreneurial group" that would swiftly grow the Dallas office.
Back on the East Coast,&nbsp;A New York federal judge delivered another blow,&nbsp;ruling that Chevron can pursue claims against Patton Boggs for allegedly committing fraud while trying to enforce a multibillion-dollar judgment in a marathon case over environmental damage in the Ecuadoran Amazon,&nbsp; The Washington Post reported.
U.S. District Judge Lewis Kaplan said Chevron could sue Patton Boggs for fraud, malicious prosecution and making false statements to the New York court during the&nbsp; epic&nbsp;legal battle with&nbsp;the U.S. oil giant.
"We look forward to litigating Chevron's counterclaim against Patton Boggs and holding that firm accountable for its role in trying to enforce this travesty of justice in Ecuador," said Randy Mastro, Chevron's outside counsel and a partner at Gibson, Dunn & Crutcher.
Patton Boggs, which has&nbsp; gone on the offensive itself&nbsp;during the long-running legal feud,&nbsp;&nbsp;issued a statement saying the charges "are baseless and unlikely ever to proceed to litigation on the merits." The statement added the firm believes it "acted ethically and properly in assisting these communities" in Ecuador.
Mastro did not say what amount Chevron would claim in damages against Patton Boggs, but Kaplan said it could seek compensatory and punitive damages.
On March 18, in the Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organizations case it recently won, Chevron filed an application for $32.3 million in damages from Steven Donziger, the lawyer who has pursued the environmental case against the energy company for two decades. That amount would cover 36,837 hours billed by Gibson, Dunn & Crutcher and 139,747 hours billed by the Huron Consulting Group and Merrill Communications.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Washington Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>