<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-MX01-JC8C-202C"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Global warming threat escalated in U.N. report</title><source>Sun-Sentinel (Fort Lauderdale, Florida)</source><author>Reuters</author><text><![CDATA[-- Global warming poses a growing threat to the health, economic prospects, and food and water sources of billions of people, top scientists said in a report that urges swift action to counter the effects of carbon emissions.
The latest report from the U.N. Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change said the effects of warming are being felt everywhere, fueling potential food shortages and natural disasters and raising the risk of wars.
"The world, in many cases, is ill-prepared for risks from a changing climate," the IPCC said Monday.
More warming increased the chance of harsh, widespread effects that could be surprising or irreversible, it said.
The report projected that global warming may cut world economic output by 0.2 to 2.0 percent a year if mean temperatures rise by 3.6 degrees Fahrenheit, an estimate many countries say is too low.
"Over the coming decades, climate change will have mostly negative impacts," said Michel Jarraud, secretary-general of the World Meteorological Organization, citing cities, ecosystems and water supply as being among the areas at risk.
"The poor and vulnerable will be most affected," he said.
The IPCC was set up in 1988 by the World Meteorological Organization and the United Nations Environment Program.
The report emphasized the risks, portraying cuts to greenhouse gas emissions as an insurance policy for the planet.
"Climate change is really a challenge of managing risks," said Christopher Field, co-chair of the IPCC group preparing the report. The risks ranged from death to disrupted livelihoods in low-lying coastal zones and small islands, because of storm surges, coastal flooding and sea-level rise, the report said.
Immediate action is needed, says the report, which follows a warning that humans are probably responsible for global warming thought to cause droughts, colder weather and rising sea levels.
"Unless we act dramatically and quickly, science tells us our climate and our way of life are literally in jeopardy," U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry said in a statement. "Denial of the science is malpractice."
Still, many governments have pleaded for greater scientific certainty before making billion-dollar investments in everything from flood barriers to renewable energies.
Global warming will worsen health threats, reduce crop yields and bring floods, according to the report. It could also deepen poverty and worsen economic shocks at the heart of conflict.
The report was the second in a four-part IPCC series meant to guide governments that have promised to agree a pact in 2015 to slow climate change. The first, in September, raised to at least 95 percent the probability that most global warming is man-made, from 90 percent in 2007.
The panel's credibility faces scrutiny after one of its reports, in 2007, exaggerated the melt of Himalayan glaciers, but reviews said the error did not undermine key findings.
Climate scientists say they are more certain than ever that mankind is the main culprit behind global warming and warned that the impact of greenhouse gas emissions would linger for centuries.
The report pulled together the work of hundreds of scientists, but skeptics have been emboldened by the fact that temperatures have risen more slowly recently, despite rising emissions.
One of the authors, professor Richard Tol of the University of Sussex in England, pulled out of the writing team last week, saying he thought the report was too alarmist.
]]></text></news-item>