<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-KRJ1-JBTM-700P"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Blyvoor mine workers face bleak future</title><source>The New Age (South Africa)</source><author>LUYOLO MKENTANE</author><text><![CDATA[THE National Union of Mineworkers (NUM) is worried that hundreds of workers at Blyvooruitzicht mine in Carletonville face a bleak future after going for months on end without wages.
And if the matter is not addressed, the union fears it could reach the proportions of the Aurora mines saga where mine workers were left unpaid for more than two years.
Aurora's Orkney and Grootvlei operations, formerly owned by the liquidated Pamodzi Gold company, were sold to Aurora Empowerment Systems which reportedly failed to pay its creditors and workers.
Blyvooruitzicht or Blyvoor was sold to Goldrich for R70m after its former company went into liquidation last year.
Cosatu said none of the 1746 mine workers had been paid "nor received any retrenchment payments" since September last year.
Cosatu national spokesperson Patrick Craven said events at Blyvoor were starting to look like a "re-run of the Aurora mines saga".
"The chairperson of Goldrich Holdings, Thulani Ngubane, was a former Aurora director, and the company is advised by Fazel Bhana, who also advised Aurora," he said.
"Liquidator for the former owners, Leigh Roering of Harvard Corporate Recovery Services, who is pursuing court action to cancel the sale agreement, say they were not aware of the same people being involved in Goldrich and Aurora until the day the agreements were signed, but concedes that the individuals associated with Goldrich were involved in the Pamodzi liquidation and were responsible for asset-stripping through Aurora, and the liquidators want to avoid a recurrence of what transpired on that estate.
The liquidators are now pursuing court action to cancel the sale agreement and have filed two urgent applications in the high court, firstly to nullify its sale agreement with Goldrich and to evict it from the mine premises, and secondly to interdict Goldrich from removing and selling any assets from the mine."
Cosatu said it was not only the workers were in peril regarding the Blyvoor situation as about "6000 people live in the Blyvoor village community, where 1000 houses were recently sold to a property developer for the equivalent of R17000 each and residents are now being charged R3500 a month for water and electricity, which no-one can afford".
"About a month ago the water and electricity supply became intermittent and the municipality is providing a tap, which means a daily trek with buckets and bottles.
"The company has threatened to talk to Eskom to stop power supply if residents cannot pay the R3500 per month."
Craven said they supported union affiliate NUM's call for the liquidators to take decisive action on the Blyvoor situation.
Mammburu said: "NUM will keep fighting for members who have not been paid since September. We have raised the issue with the liquidators but they can't do anything because the issue is now in court.
luyolom@thenewage.co.za
]]></text></news-item>