<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-KRD1-DY2K-G01S"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>News briefing</title><source>Orlando Sentinel (Florida)</source><author>Tribune Newspapers and news services</author><text><![CDATA[
Ex-Israeli PM convicted in corruption scandal
JERUSALEM -- Former Israeli Prime Minister Ehud Olmert was convicted Monday of accepting bribes in a case called one of the nation's largest corruption scandals, ending an intense two-year trial and most likely his political career.
Tel Aviv District Court convicted Olmert and nine other defendants -- including real estate developers, a former mayor, a former city engineer, a former bank chairman, and former councilmen and aides -- of accepting or taking bribes. Three other people were acquitted.
Olmert was acquitted of two counts of bribery but convicted of two others. One count involved about $140,000 in a series of postdated checks given to Olmert's financially distressed brother, Yossi Olmert, by a third person who turned state witness and then died during the trial.
Ehud Olmert is the first former prime minister to be convicted, although he joins a growing list of former Israeli politicians convicted of crimes.
The Holyland scandal, named after the towering real estate project dominating one of Jerusalem's hilltops, broke in 2010 with the arrests of businessmen and Jerusalem city officials suspected of pushing through the widely disputed project with bribery as well as financial and bureaucratic misconduct.
The investigation revealed an intricate web of corruption and a massive mechanism of bribes, money laundering and mutual favors exchanged between entrepreneurs, City Hall and others.
The scandal involved cutting corners and bending zoning laws to secure permits.
Fukushima-area residents can go home after 3 years
For the first time since Japan's Fukushima nuclear disaster more than three years ago, residents of a small district 12 miles from the wrecked plant are about to be allowed to return home.
The Miyakoji area of Tamura, a northeastern city inland from the Fukushima nuclear station, has been off-limits for most residents since March 2011, when the government ordered evacuations after a devastating earthquake and tsunami triggered a triple meltdown at the power plant.
China charges military officer with corruption
BEIJING -- China has charged former senior army officer Gu Junshan with corruption, Xinhua News Agency said Monday, in what is likely to be the country's worst military scandal since a vice admiral was jailed for life for embezzlement in 2006.
Gu has been charged with corruption, taking bribes, misuse of public funds and abuse of power, Xinhua said on one of its official microblogs. He will be tried by a military court, it added.
Ugandan president dismisses donor cuts
KAMPALA, Uganda -- President Yoweri Museveni told a rally of religious leaders, politicians and supporters on Monday that Uganda could live without aid that Western donors suspended in protest of an anti-gay bill that became law in February.
Donors have halted or re-directed $118 million in aid since Museveni signed the law, which toughened rules against gays and prescribed life in jail for what it called "aggravated homosexuality."
U.N. court: Antarctic whaling by Japan illegal
The United Nations' highest court on Monday ruled that Japan's Antarctic whaling operations are not for "scientific purposes," as Tokyo claims, and ordered an immediate halt to the practice.
In a 12-4 ruling, the International Court of Justice said Japan failed to demonstrate during a trial last year that its claimed right to harvest about 1,000 whales each year was for research.
Tokyo said it was disappointed but would abide by the decision.
THE NEWSMAKER
U.S. ambassador resigns
Nancy Powell, the U.S. ambassador to India, has resigned following a row over the arrest of a junior Indian diplomat in New York that pushed relations between the world's biggest democracies to their lowest ebb in more than a decade; however, a State Department spokeswoman denied Monday the resignation was related to ongoing tensions.
Hollande names new PM after election defeat
PARIS -- President Francois Hollande named centrist Interior Minister Manuel Valls as his new prime minister Monday, replacing Jean-Marc Ayrault, who quit after ruling Socialists were trounced in local French elections.
Hollande vowed to pursue cuts in labor charges for business but also promised tax cuts, insisting European Union partners take his reform efforts into account in judging whether France had respected commitments to Brussels.
Trial starts in stiletto death of woman's beau
HOUSTON -- A woman charged with beating her boyfriend to death with a stiletto heel after a night of drinking faced a Texas jury Monday as opening arguments began in a trial expected to take about a week.
Prosecutors say Ana Trujillo, 45, stabbed University of Houston professor Stefan Andersson, 59, several times in the head with her spiked-heel shoe after the pair returned to his upscale Houston condominium from a night out.
hl2 style="briefs_subhead">Congress approves bill to avert Medicare cut
WASHINGTON -- The Senate gave congressional approval Monday to legislation to avert a pay cut for doctors who participate in the Medicare insurance program for the elderly and disabled.
By a 64-35 vote, the Democratic-led Senate sent the measure, approved last week by the Republican-led House of Representatives, to President Barack Obama to sign into law. The bill would give doctors a one-year reprieve from a 24 percent cut set to kick in this week.
]]></text></news-item>