<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-X9T1-JCKG-J005"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>President Obama's NSA Reforms May Not Go Far Enough</title><source>USNEWS.com</source><author>Brad Bannon</author><text><![CDATA[
The National Security Agency was cruising for a bruising and President Barack Obama tried to come to the rescue when he announced his reform plan for domestic surveillance last week. In the months since Edward Snowden disclosed the existence of the NSA's spying programs, the pressure on the president to make changes to the program has been building.
A clear sign of the public's displeasure with domestic spying is public approval of Snowden's actions. A majority (57 percent) of Americans described Snowden as a whistleblower, while only one in three (34 percent) called him a traitor in a January national survey by Quinnipiac University. Last week, former President Jimmy Carter announced that he didn't use email because the NSA could be spying on him. A month ago, Sen. Dianne Feinstein, D-Calif., chair of the Senate Intelligence Committee and a long time supporter of the CIA, charged that the agency was monitoring a congressional investigation. Meanwhile, Kentucky Republican Sen. Rand Paul, a 2016 presidential prospect, campaigns against domestic spying on college campuses across the country.
Last year, a federal district court judge in Washington, D.C., described the domestic surveillance program as "Orwellian" and ruled that the program violated the Fourth Amendment which "protects the right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses and effects against unreasonable searches and seizure." Public concern is boiling over too. A clear majority of Americans (57 percent to 39 percent) believes the government collects too much personal information, according to the same survey by Quinnipiac.
[ See a collection of editorial cartoons on the NSA.]
Feeling the heat, the president announced a set of modest reforms in the domestic surveillance program. He asked Congress to increase judicial scrutiny of NSA activities and also proposed limits on the collection of so-called "metadata."
The president dropped the biggest hot potato on the phone companies. The most controversial part of the current system concerns the program that allows NSA to collect and scrutinize batches of phone records for five years with hardly any judicial scrutiny. Now according to the president's plan, the phone companies will instead hold the data, and for only 18 months. The government will be able to access it with a federal court order. The problem with this proposal is that the telecom industry doesn't want to hold the data because it fears the wrath of customers for invading their privacy.
A lot of people besides telephone company executives don't think the president went far enough last week. The president's recommendations don't go as far as the proposals that his own blue ribbon commission developed a few months ago. The president's reform plan does not apply to social media. This is sure to inflame the blogosphere and antagonize the high tech companies who don't want any part of the program. Some opponents of the program want to end metadata spying entirely. Snowden said that the president's proposals were a "turning point," but didn't go far enough.
[ Check out our editorial cartoons on President Obama.]
Don't expect quick congressional action on the president's proposals. Section 215 of the Patriot Act, which created the program, is not up for reauthorization until next year. The big data program will have a tough fight for survival when Congress takes up Section 215. Feinstein will take the lead on reauthorization in the Senate if Democrats retain control of the body, and she undoubtedly will take a close hard look at the surveillance program. Last year the in the House of Representatives, a coalition of liberal Democrats and conservative Republicans came within 12 votes of completely shutting the program down.
The NSA still watches the public and the public looks to Washington to protect them and the Bill of Rights.

]]></text></news-item>