<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-FXW1-DXH0-K4KV"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Philippine media a reflection of society</title><source>Philippines Daily Inquirer</source><author> ROWENA C. PARAAN</author><text><![CDATA[The National Union of Journalists of the Philippines is concerned about the allegations of media corruption reported by the Inquirer, specifically how pork barrel funds were supposedly funneled through the National Agribusiness Corp.
We will withhold comment on the specific allegations to allow those accused the opportunity to present their side, as well as for the Inquirer to present more definitive evidence to back up the allegations raised.
Nevertheless, we acknowledge that probably the most common criticism against the Philippine media always had to do with the perceived lack of ethics and professionalism among journalists. In fact, some quarters have gone so far as to cite this shortcoming to explain, if not justify, why media killings persist, as if corruption deserved a death sentence.
Nevertheless, it is perhaps time that the
issue of ethics and professionalism-or the lack thereof-in Philippine media was discussed openly and honestly, and, more importantly, addressed decisively.
However, we hope that any discussion of ethics and professionalism shall encompass all aspects of the media industry as a whole and not be limited only to weeding out individual offenders.
After all, for all its virtues and faults, Philippine media is a reflection of the society from which it springs and which it claims to serve.
Thus, any examination of ethics and professionalism should take into account as well the ownership and management patterns that exist in the media and how these, more often than not, play a major role in why journalists-from beat reporters to editors-fall astray. This is as true in Metro Manila, where practitioners earn substantially more, as in the provinces, where many journalists toil under difficult working conditions for wages below even the legal minimum.
We also fervently hope that the discourse on ethics does not descend into a mindless witch-hunt or be exploited by the enemies of a free and independent press to tarnish a profession that, for all its blemishes, still remains one of the Filipino citizens' strongest defenses against those who habitually abuse their powers and privileges.
]]></text></news-item>