<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-9BS1-JC3H-00XR"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>State cost for secret settlements tops $500,000</title><source>Des Moines Register</source><author>By, Jason Clayworth</author><text><![CDATA[The cost of Iowa's secret settlements with former state workers climbed to $516,245 late last week, and the controversy facing Gov. Terry Branstad's administration doesn't show any sign of fading.
The Des Moines Register first revealed the secret payments March 16. The Register's investigation now shows more about what the state attempted to keep confidential, details that have ignited a quest from state lawmakers for answers.
The cost to taxpayers could continue to climb as new information about the state's 24 settlements with former workers becomes public.
Some settlements made public by the administration Friday had large sections of information blacked out, which means the public may never know what actions employees took or the full terms of what state officials agreed to.
The first secret settlements were made in 2011, but administration officials continued to make confidential deals with outgoing state workers until Feb. 28, less than two weeks before the Register contacted the governor's office about the practice.
Former state workers who received secret settlements are scheduled to testify before the Iowa Legislature's oversight committee this week.
Lawmakers from both parties are calling on Branstad's administration to testify about who approved the payments and why.
Most of the recipients of the first six secret settlements identified in the Register's March 16 report accused the Republican Branstad administration of firing them for their ties to Democrats, according to interviews and public records.
Additionally, Pat Mullenbach, the former chief financial officer of the Iowa Department of Administrative Services, said she sat in meetings where merit-based employees - workers who are legally protected from political discrimination in employment - were identified as being an "R" or a "D."
Branstad said he wasn't aware of the settlements until he read about them in the Register. He has vehemently denied that his administration's actions were politically motivated, saying some job cuts were tied to reorganizations. Top state officials who signed off on individual agreements included eight state directors and two assistant attorney generals.
Branstad last week was unable to say why the agreements were made in secret.
"I don't know what the motives are," he said. "I just know that it's wrong to have confidentiality agreements."
State explains why
records are redacted
The cost to taxpayers is at least $100,000 more than state officials reported last week, a Register review of the settlements shows. The additional cost comes from records that show the state paid thousands of dollars more in agreements to provide back pay to some of the ex-employees or allowed some to convert unused sick time into cash.
And while Branstad spokesman Jimmy Centers says no more secret settlements will be unveiled from the governor's current term in office, the total cost could grow.
That's because the administration late Friday released the final four of 24 agreements made since Branstad took office in 2011. While those four documents do not indicate lump-sum payments, sections of them were redacted, and it was not immediately clear whether there were costs taxpayers had to pick up as part of those agreements.
Additionally, it was not always clear last week how much some of the confidential settlements cost taxpayers. Multiple cases, for example, indicated employees would be provided back pay but didn't outline those costs. Answers to the Register's questions about those costs were not immediately available Friday from the Iowa Department of Administrative Services.
A statement from the Iowa attorney general's office - which advised state agencies what to black out - stated that the redacted information was being kept secret under a provision in Iowa law related to personnel records.
Iowa public records advocates have previously said that exemption can and sometimes is interpreted so broadly that even basic information is kept hidden from the public. They have been concerned that the specific actions that led to a state employee's firing are kept secret rather than disclosed.
The attorney general's office Friday cited a 2012 Iowa Supreme Court case concluding that "discipline records and information regarding discipline are nothing more than in-house job performance records or information," which the attorney general said should be confidential.
The newly released blacked-out documents still disclose "all essential terms of the settlement agreement," according to Geoff Greenwood, a spokesman for the attorney general. "Rather than withholding the documents in their entirety, the state is releasing the settlements with limited redactions under the law."
Branstad has said he disagrees with such secrecy because redacted information can help alert the public to potential harm that the employee's actions may have caused.
"The governor's office would welcome legislation regarding Iowa Code 22.7(11) that would increase transparency for the taxpayers of Iowa, allowing them to fully understand why an employee is no longer working for the state," Centers said Friday.
2 days of hearings set for this week
Meanwhile, pressure is mounting for explanations about why the administration signed those secret settlements with 24 former state employees.
Sen. Janet Petersen, D-Des Moines and Senate chairwoman of the Legislature's oversight committee, will hold two days of public hearings about the secret settlements this week. She will be joined by Republicans, including Sen. Sandra Greiner of Keota, who said last week that she wanted more details about the issue and would not end this year's legislative session until she found out.
Petersen has made multiple public records requests of the administration, yet said she's still in the dark about key questions.
Petersen has received some records from the governor's office about the settlements, but other requests have so far not been met. That includes a request for a list of employees or directors who specifically authorized or OK'd each settlement and a list of what accounts the state used to pay them.
In at least some of the cases, the state did not dip into general fund money to make the secret settlement payments, which allowed them to avoid public disclosure before the State Appeal Board.
The governor's office has said it does not have those records and directed Petersen to other state departments March 18, the same day she made the requests. Those state agencies continue to work on those requests, Centers said Friday.
Petersen said she found it surprising that the governor's office didn't readily have the budget information she requested.
"The fact that the governor's staff was able to conduct their investigation makes me think they have to have had this information compiled for him to come to a conclusion," Petersen said. "I'm at a loss to why that information hasn't been provided yet."
Ken Thornton, a former administrator of operations and design services for the state's administrative department, said that at the oversight hearings, he plans to "specifically talk about following the law."
Thornton refused to sign a contract with a confidentiality clause, unlike other employees - one of whom told the Register she accepted $5,000 more in exchange for a secrecy agreement.
The state nonetheless paid Thornton almost $25,000 in 2012. He said the payout was partly to settle a complaint that illegal employment practices allowed Branstad officials to cover their nepotism under the guise of reorganization.
"There's a reason we have the merit system, and that's so cronyism isn't incorporated into the state," Thornton said.
Documents obtained by the Register, as well as interviews with multiple secret settlement recipients, suggest the agreements were made to hide allegations of illegal or unethical accounting procedures, such as failure of the transportation department to obtain competitive bids; accusations of unlawful hiring practices; and embarrassing employee actions, such as drinking on the job.
Newly obtained records of deals include sections that have been blacked out by state officials.
ABOUT THE REGISTER'S INVESTIGATION
The Des Moines Register's March 16 report on secret settlements made over a three-year period to former state workers revealed:
PAYOUTS: Six former state employees received a total of $282,000 after they lost their jobs and then filed grievances.
STATE'S REQUESTS: All six were asked to sign documents that would have made the settlements confidential. Four signed; two declined. One former employee said she was paid an additional $5,000 in exchange for agreeing to the confidentiality clause.
POLITICAL MOTIVES? All six workers were either registered Democrats or had ties to state initiatives opposed by Republicans or Gov. Terry Branstad's administration.
NOT ENFORCEABLE: The Iowa attorney general's office said it thinks the confidentiality clauses are not only bad policy but also are unenforceable, since Iowa government settlements are, by law, public records.
LATEST DEVELOPMENTS:
MARCH 17: Lt. Gov. Kim Reynolds says she didn't know about the settlements until reading The Des Moines Register's investigation. The Branstad administration appoints a work group to review the issue.
MARCH 18: The administration says the work group will not hold any public sessions.
MARCH 21: Branstad returns to Iowa following a vacation in Arizona. He declines to answer questions when approached by a Register reporter at the Des Moines airport but repeats Reynolds' assertion that he previously knew nothing about the secret settlements.
MARCH 24: Branstad signs an executive order making secret settlements to state employees illegal and vows such secrecy won't happen again or "heads will roll."
MARCH 26: The Register publishes the names of eight directors or agency officials of the Branstad administration who signed some of the secret deals. Also, the Register reveals that two members of the attorney general's staff signed the agreements.
TODAY: The Register reports that the total costs of the settlements exceed $500,000 and that the practice of making secret settlements was ongoing through February 2014.
About the oversight hearings
WHAT: Hearings about secret settlements before the Legislature's Government Oversight Committee.
WHEN: Wednesday and Thursday, starting at 11 a.m. both days.
WHERE: The Legislative Dining Room, located in the basement of the State Capitol.
DETAILS: On Wednesday, multiple recipients of the secret settlements will speak. On Thursday, key Branstad appointees, including Mike Carroll, the director of the Department of Administrative Services, are expected to testify.
]]></text></news-item>