<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-55T1-JD3N-54X9"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Whales saved by a growing awareness of environment</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (Australia)</source><author>Troy Lennon, History Editor</author><text><![CDATA[Music and films helped awaken the world to the fate of the ocean giants
In the 1970s the words "Save the whales" adorned millions of T-shirts, car bumper stickers and badges around the world. It became something of a -cliche, often used to mock the concern of environmental -activists for animals that seemed remote from humanity and should have been big enough to fight their own battles.
But today few question the value of the campaign to stop the Japanese catching and killing whales in the Southern Ocean for scientific research. Although the Australian case against the Japanese in the International Court of Justice in The Hague will not stop Japanese whaling in the north Pacific, it is seen as another milestone in the long running campaign to save whales from extinction.
For thousands of years people hunted the leviathans, sometimes for meat but also for a multitude of other resources. As people devised better ways to harvest whales they found the population of the creatures close to shore began to thin out, forcing whalers to venture further and further out to sea to find their quarry.
In the 19th century the hunting of whales was conducted on an -industrial scale, with steam-powered ships and powerful harpoon guns. Whales were hunted for their oil for use as lighting fuel, lubricants and other things vital to an increasingly industrialised and mechanised world. This large scale harvesting resulted in a collapse of global whale populations.
Had it not been for the development of petroleum alternatives -humanity may well have pushed whales over the brink before World War I. By the 1920s there were discussions within the scientific community and the whaling industry about the need for the conservation of particular species. In the 1930s scientists were beginning to use the catchphrase "save the whale" but it would be decades before it became a bumper sticker. The introduction of the Geneva International Convention for the Regulation of Whaling (which took effect in 1934) resulted in bans on hunting of several species of whale but was pointedly ignored by some countries including Japan.
The establishment of an International Whaling Commission in 1946 and the introduction of quotas on the number of whales killed helped bring whales back from -extinction. But while the IWC was intent on protecting whale species it was formed primarily to save the whaling industry from extinction.
In the 1960s attitudes toward whales began to change, helped by books and films depicting dolphins, orcas and whales as intelligent and peaceful animals.
In 1967 researchers Scott McVay and Roger Payne discovered whales sing to each other to communicate. McVay's 1971 prediction that many species of whales were destined for extinction only increased people's interest in these creatures.
Popular music reflected this fascination with the dying whaling -industry with songs such as the 1971 single Nantucket Sleigh Ride (a term referring to harpoon boats being pulled along by a whale) by the band Mountain, and The Whale by Terry Fielding and Fred Dyer in 1972. Both songs emphasised the cruelty of the industry to men and whales.
By then environmentalists were protesting against whaling, creating "Save the whale" petitions to lobby governments to ban whaling. In 1974 the group Friends of the Earth launched project Jonah (named after the Biblical character who lived inside a whale) planning to buy shares in Cheynes Beach Whaling Company in Albany, Western Australia, to shut it down.
In 1975 Greenpeace, noted more for its antinuclear protests, launched its first anti-whaling campaign. On June 1, 1975 Greenpeace took its first direct action against a whaling vessel when a Canadian expedition headed by journalist Bob Hunter confronted a Russian whaling fleet. While they couldn't stop the slaughter the -images they captured raised indignation around the world.
The "Save the whale" slogan became a popular catchcry. Rock music continued its interest in whales. On their 1977 album Out Of The Blue, Electric Light -Orchestra played an instrumental titled The Whale with simulated whale song noises. On their 1978 album Tormato, Yes had a song called Don't Kill The Whale.
Protests against Cheyne's Beach, along with the fact it was increasingly unprofitable, shut down our last whaling station in 1978.
In 1982 the IWC announced a moratorium on whaling worldwide. While people have defied the moratorium the 1970s Save the Whale campaign had helped -ensure that whales would not vanish from the world's oceans.
troy.lennon@news.com.au
]]></text></news-item>