<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-NTM1-JD34-V35Y"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>ASIC to quiz Leighton witnesses; 'Too late' - Watchdog accused of about-face - Exclusive</title><source>The Age (Melbourne, Australia)</source><author>Nick McKenzie, Richard Baker</author><text><![CDATA[Australia's corporate watchdog is preparing to use its Star Chamber powers to quiz witnesses and suspects over possible corporate offences arising from allegations that Leighton Holdings paid multimillion-dollar bribes to win contracts overseas.
Australian Securities and Investments Commission chief Greg Medcraft told a Senate estimates committee last Friday that earlier this year the watchdog "opened a formal investigation so we can use our compulsory powers" to probe Leighton Holdings.
ASIC's compulsory powers enable it to order a person to attend an examination and hand over documents and answer questions.
Labor senator Sam Dastyari, who quizzed Mr Medcraft about the development on Friday, said it amounted to a backflip by the corporate regulator.
ASIC was criticised last year for not launching its own inquiry ito a raft of potential corporate offences exposed by a Fairfax Media investigation ito Leighton Holdings' international operations.
Last October, ASIC defended its failure to investigate Leighton in connection to corporate offences allegedly linked to the bribery scandal, claiming it had to wait until federal police referred the case to the regulator, and that legal issues created problems for ASIC if it launched a parallel inquiry.
Before launching its own formal probe this year, ASIC seconded an officer to the federal police's criminal investigation, which began in late 2011, ito whether any Leighton Holdings staff had breached Australian Foreign Bribery laws.
Senator Dastyari told Fairfax Media on Tuesday that "while the ASIC investigation is welcomed, it is coming two years too late".
"This should have begun in 2011 - not 2014," he said.
"The allegations against Leighton are serious. It should not have taken ASIC being pursued by the media and politicians for this investigation to get under way."
Mr Medcraft told the Senate hearing that in launching its own probe, ASIC was mindful of the need not to get "timed out". ASIC only has six years from the date of an alleged corporate offence to begin a prosecution.
Senior ASIC officer Chris Savaundra also told the committee the AFP's probe was not limited to allegations of foreign bribery but included an examination of whether any senior company officers had breached the Corporations Act.
"They [the federal police] are looking at Corporations Act matters from a criminal perspective. We are looking at it from a civil perspective," Mr Savaundra said.
The revelations are likely to alarm several former top Leighton managers who may have had no direct knowledge of alleged bribe payments but whose failure to conduct appropriate due diligence may have enabled corruption.
In October, Fairfax Media revealed how Leighton's international business was facing multiple corruption and kickback allegations, and that several top former executives, including Leighton International managing director David Savage, were implicated.
]]></text></news-item>