<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-SP71-DYG9-50NM"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>FOUNDER RECEIVES PROBATION FOR FRAUD</title><source>Herald News (Passaic County, NJ)</source><author>John Brennan, Staff Writer; Email: brennan@northjersey.com Blog: northjersey.com/brennan Twitter: @BergenBrennan</author><text><![CDATA[All but one of 11 criminal charges against Meadowlands EnCap founder William Gauger were dismissed by a federal judge on Monday in a Newark courtroom as part of a plea deal with prosecutors, seemingly bringing to an end the last of the federal corruption investigations related to the controversial golf course and housing project in Lyndhurst, Rutherford and North Arlington.
Gauger was sentenced to one year of probation and a $5,000 fine by U.S. District Court Judge Claire Cecchi for admitting to defrauding North Carolina-based Cherokee Investment Services of $299 by receiving a reimbursement in that amount for a plane ticket. That March 2007 flight was canceled because of a snowstorm, and Gauger received a refund from the airline.
The submission of the fraudulent expense report was "sloppy, stupid, and ultimately criminal," Gauger told the court in brief comments just before sentencing. "I pledge never to be here again."
The EnCap development was embroiled in controversy almost from the beginning, and it swept up lawmakers and attorneys as the project fell apart.
The plan, first approved by the state in 1999 as a way to bring economic development to an undeveloped area, moved forward quickly once James McGreevey took office as governor in 2002. But after the developers were granted $300 million in low-interest and no-interest loans toward cleanup of the site, state Inspector General Mary Jane Cooper launched a yearlong investigation in January 2007.
A bid later that year by real estate mogul Donald Trump to revive the project failed, and state taxpayers were left on the hook for more than $50 million when project executives filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection in 2008.
The failed EnCap plan resulted in two indictments.
Former state Sen. Wayne Bryant was acquitted in August 2012 of fraud allegations. The judge concluded that the government did not prove beyond a reasonable doubt that the $100,000-a-year retainer paid by EnCap developers to Bryant's South Jersey law firm "for little or no work" was directly related to Bryant's legislative support for the project.
A co-defendant in that case, former project attorney Eric Wisler, died in August 2011 with the case against him unresolved.
A January 2012 indictment of Gauger alleged that EnCap was falsely billed $20,000 by Gauger's brother-in-law in 2005 for a review of concept plans for a train station at the site.
The core of that indictment, however, featured assertions by the government of an alleged shakedown by Gauger of a former friend for $100,000 as the result of an Asbury Park real estate deal. The friend was a banking executive referred by Gauger to the developer, who wound up paying the friend nearly $1 million in consulting fees for helping raise funding for the project.
But all five of those counts -- including one count of extortion -- as well as the EnCap-related charge were among those slated to be dropped as part of a plea deal last fall that led to Monday's sentencing.
Laurence Shtasel, Gauger's attorney, told the judge before the sentencing that Gauger -- who has no criminal background -- had led "an exemplary life" as a husband, father, and active community volunteer other than the lone charge before the court.
The attorney noted that since a state investigation of the failed Meadowlands EnCap condo and golf course development began in 2007, Gauger's life "has been on hold in some ways." Shtasel added that Gauger's employment opportunities had been curtailed, and that "financial stresses" and "community shame" had arisen because of the nature of the charges.
"This is a bad mistake that will not be repeated," Shtasel said of his client.
Email: brennan@northjersey.com Blog: northjersey.com/brennan Twitter: @BergenBrennan
]]></text></news-item>