<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-P091-JCF2-2000"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Olmert in; Pollard out?</title><source>Mideast Mirror</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Israeli newspapers lead their Tuesday editions inevitably with the conviction of former Prime Minister Ehud Olmert on charges of bribery. One has to go deep into the inside pages to find a story that isn't about Olmert, his former bureau chief or any of the other people who were involved in the case.
At the verdict reading on Monday, Tel Aviv District Court Judge David Rozen delivered a sharp, at times cynical, decision, slamming Olmert's testimony. The judge said that the former prime minister had tried repeatedly to pass the blame and ridicule others, instead of taking responsibility upon himself. The judge told the court that the case exposed 'governance that grew more corrupt and rotten over the years.'
Also convicted were former Jerusalem Mayor Uri Lupolianski, former Bank Hapoalim chairman Dan Dankner, Olmert's former chief-of-staff Shula Zaken and, in total, 10 out of the 13 individual defendants. An Olmert spokesman said after the court hearing that the final word had not yet been said, presumably a reference to the intention to appeal.
The one story that does stick out, however, is the resurfacing of a report that the United States is so desperate to keep the Israeli-Palestinian peace talks going that it might even be willing to free Jonathan Pollard, the naval intelligence officer who was convicted of spying for Israel. According to Maariv, senior sources in Israel have confirmed that the American administration has agreed to discuss the possible release of Pollard from his life sentence as an incentive to unblock the stalled negotiations. But the sources said they think the chances of his release are not high.
Haaretz adds that American sources said the Pollard issue would advance only if significant understandings are reached regarding the continuation of the Israel-Palestinian peace talks. According to other reports, which cited sources close to the talks, one proposal could see Pollard freed before the Passover holiday, later this month. In exchange, Israel would release the final batch of prisoners as well as another group of detainees, and the sides would agree to extend the negotiations.
The Associated Press cited sources close to the talks cautioning that such a release is far from certain and discussions are continuing. White House spokesman Jay Carney on Monday declined to discuss any possible deal. He told reporters that Pollard is a person who is convicted of espionage and is serving his sentence. Carney said he does not have any updates on his situation.
Meanwhile, U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry met for a second time in the space of a few hours with Prime Minister Binyamin Netanyahu Tuesday morning, in a bid to save the talks. Kerry flew to the region from Paris on Monday to push both sides to resolve the lingering dispute over Palestinian prisoners, which is threatening to derail the negotiations ahead of an April 29 deadline. Following the meeting this morning, Kerry flew to Brussels, to attend a meeting of NATO ministers on the Ukraine crisis. Kerry and Netanyahu met for several hours on Monday night, but a late-night meeting scheduled between Kerry and Palestinian President Mahmoud Abbas was cancelled. Instead, Kerry held talks in Jerusalem with chief Palestinian negotiator, Saeb Erekat, and Palestinian intelligence chief Majed Faraj.
On Monday night, Palestinians warned that if the crisis over the prisoner release is not immediately resolved, they will renew as early as Tuesday efforts to secure international recognition through United Nations institutions. Palestinian legislator Mustafa Barhgouti told French news agency AFP that if the Palestinians do not receive an answer from Kerry on the prisoners, they will begin to ask for membership in all UN agencies beginning today.
Abbas, for his part, spent most of Monday in a key leadership meeting to discuss the standoff. Palestinian sources told the French news agencies that the leadership agreed at the Ramallah meeting that there would be no extension of peace talks with Israel without a 'comprehensive' freeze on Israeli settlement construction. According to Israel Radio, American sources say that a formula could be found to extend the negotiations by several months - and to that end Israel will release several hundred prisoners.
BUILDING MAKES IT OUR FAULT: Writing in Maariv, Ben-Dror Yemini says that, despite the obvious fact that the Palestinians are refusing to make peace with Israel, the international community rightly places the blame at Israel's doorstep because of its policy of settlement expansion.
"Over the weekend, a senior Israeli official expressed satisfaction that 'we have proven that it's the Palestinians who are peace rejectionists.' This proof relies on the fact that Israel agreed to free prisoners, but that the Palestinians were not willing to commit to continued negotiations.
But this senior official and others like him need to cool their heels. In the sphere in which Israel is operating, there is almost no proof for anything. After all, the Americans have already put pressure on the Palestinians and, in the end, after a lot of cajoling; Yasser Arafat uttered the words 'Jewish state.' But don't forget that when Arafat was a guest at the White House, the Americans (along with the Saudi Arabians, the Egyptians and many other Arab states) pressured him to say yes to Bill Clinton - and he ended up saying no. And when Palestinian President Mahmoud 'Abbas visited George W. Bush in the White House and was urged in the strongest terms to agree to Ehud Olmert's proposals, he, too, insisted on saying no. Somehow, the Palestinian propaganda machine, with the generous help of the media and academics, has managed to turn Israel into the rejectionist. So why does anyone think that, because of a trifling matter like the fourth stage of a prisoner release, the international community will suddenly decide to pin the blame on the Palestinians. That's just naïve.
It's true that the Palestinians refuse to make peace and that their demands are unacceptable to 90 percent of Israelis, including those who vote for Meretz. And it's true that Israel has not managed to show these demands for what they really are - a fantasy that is merely an impediment to a peace deal. But Israel has an Achilles Heel which dulls or even erases entirely the Palestinian rejectionism.
When Israel insists on expanding settlements and building 'new neighborhoods,' our stubbornness dwarfs Palestinian rejectionism. This is something that goes far beyond anti-Semitism or anti-Israeli sentiment. Even our closest allies, who support the demand that the Palestinians recognize Israel as the national homeland of the Jewish people, find it hard to understand this stubbornness.
Most of the Israeli public supports the idea of the two-state solution. Expanding settlements hurts the chances of an agreement. But Israel is ruled by a minority. In the Knesset and among members of the general public, there is a majority in favor of making painful concessions. But there is a minority in the Knesset, which has a powerful hold over the ruling coalition that manages to dictate policies that will result in a one-state solution and which play straight into the hands of the anti-Israel boycott.
This new Palestinian rejection of continued negotiations, therefore, is small change compared to the expansionist policies that are being spearheaded by Housing Minister Uri Ariel. It doesn't matter that construction is, for the large part, limited to the large settlement blocs, which, in any case, will remain part of Israel. And it doesn't matter that each new building is accompanied by a dozen declarations. That's exactly the issue: that is exactly what opponents of the peace process want. Even if the construction itself does not prevent an agreement being reached, the media noise and the never-ending declarations about renewed construction mean that Israel bears responsibility for the failure of negotiations.
The last few months are very much part of this march of folly. There was real movement on the part of Prime Minister Binyamin Netanyahu, who is serious and genuine. But the Israeli right insisted on expanding settlements and the Israeli left insists that Netanyahu's demand that the Palestinians recognize Israel as the Jewish state is the only obstacle to peace. Together they have managed to move the pendulum from faint hope to disappointment. So, while it is true that the Palestinians have given us yet another master class in rejectionism, that's no use to anyone. Israel's stupid policy of settlement expansion means that we are responsible for the failure of this round of talks."
ABU MAZIN IS THE WINNER: Writing in Maariv, Shalom Yerushalmi says that Palestinian President Mahmoud 'Abbas is the big winner from this latest round of peace talks and urges Justice Minister Tzipi Livni to get more involved.
"Let's admit the truth: Palestinian President Mahmoud 'Abbas is the big winner from the negotiation process, which will either end in the coming days or will be given a new lease of life with a fourth round of prisoner release. So far, Abu Mazin has welcomed with open arms no fewer than 78 Palestinian terrorists. He has held festive receptions for them in Ramallah, Nablus and Hebron.
Israeli citizens saw the buses carrying these terrorists as they pulled out of Ofer Prisoner and bit their lips. The families who lost loved ones in terror attacks committed by these freed terrorists held protests - they still are, in fact - right outside of the home of Prime Minister Binyamin Netanyahu. It was all in vain, however, and more terrorists were allowed home.
Abu Mazin was gifted these prisoners and did not give anything in return - other than a vague promise that he would not turn to the United Nations to demand unilateral recognition of the Palestinian state (a state which, of course, the Palestinians fully deserve). Abu Mazin took full advantage of the political weakness and lack of leadership of our prime minister. Netanyahu's decision to free terrorists was fundamentally cowardly, rather than brave, as others have claimed. Netanyahu was afraid to confront his coalition partners on the right and the ministers from his own Likud party, so he opted to free prisoners rather than impose a settlement construction freeze.
Abu Mazin jumped at the opportunity to record a tangible achievement. We were left to bemoan our fate. That was inexplicable. Abu Mazin also did not feel any need to give Israel anything in return - such as a compromise over security arrangements in the Jordan Valley, or an end to anti-Israeli incitement or recognition of Israel as the national homeland of the Jewish people. Nothing!
The Palestinian leader managed to send the ball back into Netanyahu's court - even after Israel freed prisoners. The prime minister played right into Abu Mazin's hands. After all, Netanyahu does not really want to partition the Land of Israel and establish a Palestinian state with East Jerusalem as its capital. The international community has known this for years. That is why any reticence on Netanyahu's part - no matter how justified - is seen by Abu Mazin, the Americans and the Europeans as institutionalized rejectionism.
This time, Netanyahu has decided that he's not going to be anybody's sucker any more. He has decided not to free the 26 Palestinian prisoners, who were due to be released as part of the fourth batch, without getting something in return. This is a total reversal of his government's prior decision. If we get something in return, he said, I will seek cabinet approval.
The Americans and the Palestinians have already responded with great annoyance. Even President Shimon Peres has warned of the dangers of the talks failing. Peres, whose political views I agree with, does not understand that nothing good will come of these negotiations, because of Abu Mazin and because of Netanyahu. Therefore, we are constantly being asked to give, give and give - because we hold all of the assets at the moment.
So what can be done? If I were the prime minister, I would try to turn back time. I would say to the international community: 'Fine. I don't want the negotiations to end in failure. I proved that by freeing dozens of terrorists from Israeli prisons. But I am not willing to free any more of them, because we're not getting anything in return. In any case, I am willing, as a gesture of good will, to declare a settlement construction freeze for three months. I am making another effort to ensure the success of the talks. Let's see what the Palestinians are willing to do in return.'
And here's a footnote: Where is Tzipi Livni in all of this? Why have we not heard from her? Livni only joined the government to advance the peace process. She is the head of Israel's negotiating team. In the past few months, she has hinted that there has been progress in the talks and pooh-poohed reports (including by yours truly) that we were heading for a terrible crisis. This is the time for Livni to get involved, to come up with some creative initiative and to fight to keep the process alive. She has to do something to justify her continued presence in the Netanyahu government."
THE END OF ISRAEL: Writing on the News 1 website, Amos Arika warns against the danger of agreeing to free Israeli Arab terrorists, which, he says, would be the beginning of the end of the State of Israel.
"In the next few days, it will become clear whether the State of Israel has fallen in the trap set by the Palestinian Authority, with the help of U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry. Palestinian President Mahmoud 'Abbas is about to get the gift of his life, when Israel presents him with its own head on a silver platter. Anyone who thinks that I am being hyperbolic or engaging in deliberately exaggerated rhetoric should read the following lines with extra care.
Once again, this small and whiny man has managed to turn himself into an accomplished conjurer, whose trickery has once again succeeded. Rather than holding an olive branch in his outstretched hand, he is holding a sharpened dagger. Given the complicity of the United States in this malicious move, Abu Mazin is engaged in a sophisticated sting. After all, the international community is asking itself, what do the Palestinians want? All they are asking is that Israel includes 14 of its own citizens, convicted of terror acts, in the fourth batch of prisoners to be freed. Why can't Israel just agree? But to agree would be tantamount to swallowing poison.
Indeed, agreeing to this latest Palestinian demand would be suicide; it would kill the dream of generations and all because of the stupidity of the government of Israel and its leader, Binyamin Netanyahu. This prime minister will go down in history as the leader who oversaw the destruction of Zionism and who allowed it to be replaced by a terrible monster known as 'the culture of the Jewish ghetto.' Now - if the government indeed plans on doing something totally illogical by freeing Arab citizens of Israel who committed heinous crimes - it would be tantamount to ceding sovereignty. And we all know that if you have no sovereignty you have nothing. Sovereignty is freedom.
Making such a concession so easily and without, it seems, giving it a second thought, the government of Netanyahu would be making a mistake of terrifyingly humungous proportions - a mistake that will help Abu Mazin make a mockery of Israel's wholly justified demand that the Palestinians recognize the State of Israel as the national homeland of the Jewish people. Moreover, it would grant him the greatest victory of all: the victory of the Palestinian narrative over the Jewish one.
Abu Mazin stands stubbornly by his refusal to recognize Israel's Jewish character - a demand that some idiotic or naïve Israelis reject as unimportant. 'What does it matter?' they ask. 'If the Palestinians don't want to recognize the Jewish state, so what? Peace is more important!' These people, to my great regret, ignore the indisputable fact that by refusing to accept the Jewish character of the State of Israel, Abu Mazin is clinging on to the Palestinian dream of a Middle East without Israel. But by claiming to be the representative of the Arab citizens of Israel, he is turning everything on its head and trying to make the Palestinian narrative the basis for the Zionist narrative.
The moment that Israel agrees to the Palestinian demand to free Israeli Arabs, we open the door to the Palestinian demand for the so-called right of return to within the State of Israel. This trap was created by the current government, which swallowed the bait that Abu Mazin, John Kerry and their lackeys put out for us. We have to remember that the moment we free even a single Arab Israeli, the dream is over - even if the Palestinians subsequently recognize Israel as the national homeland of the Jewish people. From that moment on, Abu Mazin will be recognized by the international community as the sole representative not only of Palestinian refugees, but also of Israel's Arab citizens. And then any agreement that we may reach with him will be utterly meaningless."
WHAT THE HELL WAS HE THINKING?: Writing in Haaretz, Amos Harel says that Ehud Olmert should have stepped down as prime minister immediately after the Second Lebanon War, rather than wait until he was indicted for corruption.
"The machinations behind the Holyland affair, the real estate corruption scandal that resulted in a bribery conviction for former Prime Minister Ehud Olmert on Monday, began in the second half of the 1990s and stretched into the early years of the previous decade. It turns out that while Jerusalem was racked by terrorism, the city's mayor was involved in other things - and not just the payoffs that gave rise to the Holyland apartment complex.
The other tortuous corruption scandals that Olmert managed to get out of by the skin of his teeth - the Investment Center breach of trust case (conviction but no jail time), the Rishon Tours fraud case and the $150,000 in cash from U.S. businessman Morris Talansky (acquittals in both), and the allegations that he tried to influence the sale of the state's controlling interest in Bank Leumi (no charges filed) - took place in the same period, when Olmert was a public figure serving in various government positions: mayor of Jerusalem, industry and trade minister, finance minister.
In other words, Olmert was suspected of being corrupt long before Ariel Sharon was incapacitated by a stroke, which ushered Sharon's second-in-command into the Prime Minister's Office in January 2006. This timeline raises one question: What the hell was Olmert thinking?
Court documents indicate that he made inappropriate political appointments and, despite a clear conflict of interest, acted to expedite his friends' projects at the government-run Investment Center, and accepted large sums of money from an American businessman. (He was acquitted not because there was doubt over whether he took the cash but because the court was not convinced he took it for personal gain.) And it has now become clear that he accepted large sums of money to approve construction plans. Olmert, of course, knew all about his own exploits when he took Sharon's place as prime minister.
As it was, Olmert took the job without much of a defense background, a hole in his resume that was painfully prominent during the Second Lebanon War. When he took the most important job in Israel, wasn't Olmert concerned that he could have been subject to blackmail? That too many people had information about him that could cost him his job? Looking back¸ it seems there is a point at which a person must say: Thank you for the honor, but the truth is this job is too much for me.
Israeli prime ministers from the past generation have not exactly been pure as snow. None of them seem to be models of ethical behavior and good governance. Ehud Barak, Ariel Sharon and Binyamin Netanyahu have all been under investigation. Olmert presumably knew he was in deeper trouble than any of them. As long as it isn't overturned by the Supreme Court, Olmert's conviction on Monday proves that his appointment as prime minister in 2006 was fundamentally improper.
There's another depressing element here. For at least a decade, there has been a communications empire that praised Olmert's leadership skills and political moderation to the heavens, and dismissed media investigations of his actions. These are the lawyers and public relations experts who were paid for their efforts, along with some journalists and friends who did it for free. The Tel Aviv District Court's decision yesterday eliminated the smokescreens that had deliberately been placed around the Holyland affair.
Let's also say a word about the second dubious achievement for which Olmert will be remembered, aside from being the first (former) Israeli prime minister to be convicted of bribery: the war of the summer of 2006. Despite the claims that Olmert and his supporters have made since then, the Second Lebanon War was conducted terribly. The Israeli leadership embarked on the war boastfully and thoughtlessly, without understanding the significance of the decisions it made. The government zigzagged on its positions during those 34 days, while sending out Israel Defense Forces units without a clear objective. And in the final, most critical phase of the war, a foolish decision was made to approve the army's advancement - a move that cost the lives of 35 soldiers in 60 hours, without a single real achievement to show for it.
The quiet that has prevailed on the Lebanese border for nearly eight years is not the result of Olmert's brilliant leadership, but of the destruction Hizbollah and Israel caused each other. Both sides came to understand fully well what the enemy's firepower could do, and since then both have been wary of another conflict. In addition, assisting the Assad regime in Syria has kept Hizbollah busy for the last three years.
It could well be that Olmert acted wisely when it came to the bombing of the Syrian nuclear facility in September 2007, an act that has been attributed to Israel. It could even be that he's a born manager and a warm and beneficent person, as almost everyone who has worked with him is ready to swear. But Olmert shouldn't have waited until March 2009, when the Talansky affair proceedings pushed him to resign, before he left office. And we didn't need the Holyland conviction to show us that he's not fit for public office. He should have resigned on August 14, 2006, the day on which the cease-fire he agreed to, at a delay that cost so much, went into effect.
Since Olmert was found guilty of bribery in the Holyland case, I cannot stop thinking about two IDF company commanders I wrote about who were killed during that cursed month in Lebanon. What would they have thought about the man who sent them to war had they known about the skeletons in his closet?"
ONE GAME IN TOWN: Writing on the I24 website, Yossi Melman bemoans the downfall of a leader whom he describes as a daring leader in war and peace; who was undone by corruption.
"What a pity. One of Israel's best prime ministers ever was convicted of accepting a bribe. Ehud Olmert might be the first Israeli prime minister to be sent to jail following one of the biggest and most severe fraud scandals ever exposed in Israel.
There's no doubt. Olmert, who served as prime minister for three and a-half years, until July 2009, deserves to be punished, and punished severely. Israel, which already has a former President (Moshe Katsav) serving time for sex crimes, a former finance minister (Avraham Hershson) who did time for fraud, and dozens of Knesset members and public officials who have been suspected and/or convicted of corruption, needs to send a clear and strong message that corruption is intolerable.
Olmert, never a popular figure in his Likud party, was nonetheless recognized as an ambitious and sly politician. After serving for a decade as mayor of Jerusalem, he was re-elected to the Knesset and was named Deputy Prime Minister. When Prime Minister Ariel Sharon fell into a coma in January 2006, from which he never recovered, Olmert took over for a short interim period, after which he was elected prime minister.
He proved himself to be a competent leader, ready to take tough and sometimes risky decision for Israel's national interests. It was Olmert who in 2007 had the guts, despite the uncertainties and fears of a major escalation, to order the Israel Air Force to bomb a nuclear reactor being built in Syria, before it became radioactive and operational. And it was Olmert who cleverly formulated the decision to keep silent about the operation, neither confirming nor denying responsibility, thus helping Syrian President Bashar al-Assad swallow his pride and not retaliate.
In his memoirs, 'Decision Points,' President George W. Bush wrote that Olmert had first asked him for the U.S. to bomb the facility. Olmert ordered the attack only after Bush refused and said he would prefer diplomatic action and sanctions.
The decision to destroy the Syrian reactor was taken despite the unforgiveable opposition of Olmert's Defense Minister, Ehud Barak. In retrospect it was one of the most important strategic decisions in Israel's history, along with the similar daring decision taken in 1981 by Prime Minister Menachem Begin to bomb and destroy Saddam Hussein's nuclear reactor near Baghdad.
Four months after the destruction of the Syrian reactor, Olmert approved another daring operation - instructing the Mossad to kill Imad Mughniyeh, Hizbollah's 'defense minister' and one of the most wanted terrorists in the world. Mughniyeh was gunned down in Damascus. The gunmen left no traces.
Even the two controversial wars launched during Olmert's premiership - one in the summer of 2006 against Hizbollah in Lebanon and the second in December 2008 against Hamas in Gaza, proved in retrospect very effective and helped Israel maintain its deterrence in relation to the two terror groups.
As a member of Sharon's government, and subsequently as Prime Minister, Olmert's world view and ideology underwent a dramatic change. He realized that his right-wing, sometimes extreme right-wing opinions, with which he grew up (his father was a right-wing Knesset member), in support of Jewish settlement in the West Bank and rejection of a Palestinian state, were not compatible with reality.
Olmert became deeply involved in negotiations with the Palestinians, forming a personal and professional friendship with Palestinian President Mahmoud Abbas. With the concessions he was willing to make, his ambition and drive, and above all his pragmatic flexibility, if Olmert had remained in power Israel would have achieved an agreement with the Palestinian Authority.
Now, following his conviction, Olmert's political career is over. There is no chance, not even the slimmest one, that he can stage a comeback. Many Israelis, who are disappointed with Prime Minister's Binyamin Netanyahu's rigid and uncompromising policies, were hoping to see Olmert return. With Olmert possibly on his way to a prison cell, and no other candidate in sight, the peace camp is left with no serious candidate and no match for Netanyahu. Israel is left with the notion that there is only one game in town - Bibi's."
]]></text></news-item>