<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-TB31-JC17-G10W"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Fault found in VA review</title><source>Pittsburgh Tribune Review</source><author>by BILL VIDONIC</author><text><![CDATA[The Department of Veterans Affairs failed to properly check the qualifications of the former developer of an outpatient center in Butler County, according to a highly critical report by the VA's Office of Inspector General released Monday.
The report says the VA improperly calculated that a 20-year lease with Westar Development Co., valued at $157 million, would be cheaper than the VA building and owning the $75 million outpatient center on its own.
"While it is undisputed that Westar made false and misleading representations to the VA, our findings and conclusions supported that the VA failed to perform appropriate, required verification steps and failed to follow up on key statements made in Westar's proposal," wrote Maureen Regan, counselor to the inspector general.
The Inspector General's Office allowed the VA to respond to the report before it was released publicly. In a March 7 response, Reagan wrote, the VA's Office of Acquisition, Logistics and Construction disagreed with several of the report's findings, claiming that it "conducted due diligence when vetting ownership of Westar and (offshoot developer) VA Butler Partners."
The VA said it has taken steps to beef up its leasing procedures, including having a contracting officer take an active role in projects and not abdicate responsibility to a project manager or real estate broker. It will get more proof of company ownership before awarding a contract. The inspector general said Westar officials falsely claimed veteran-owned status, giving it a leg up in the bidding process.
"VA is committed to delivering this project as quickly as possible, while complying with all federal procurement laws and regulations," spokesman Mark Ballesteros said on Monday.
Westar beat out five other companies in May 2012 to win a contract to build the outpatient center on Deshon Woods property adjacent to the Butler Township VA campus. The inspector general said the VA improperly dismissed a protest by another developer of the award.
The report says that Westar gained an unfair advantage through owning the Deshon Woods property that the VA favored, though the VA denies any preference.
Nearly a month before the April 2013 groundbreaking, the inspector general "received allegations that Westar was actually conducting business for entities created and managed by Michael Forlani that were suspended by VA in December 2011," according to a memo obtained in September by the Tribune-Review.
In April 2013, a federal judge in Ohio sentenced Forlani of Cleveland to 97 months in federal prison when he pleaded guilty to nine conspiracy charges that included racketeering, bribery and fraud. Federal prosecutors said Forlani bribed public officials to get contracts.
The VA terminated the Westar lease on Aug. 9. The VA reopened the bids last year and expects to award a bid in late spring.
U.S. Rep. Mike Kelly, R-Butler, who has been critical of how the lease project was handled, said in a statement, "The most recent VA Inspector General report continues to paint a very troubling picture. I am still reviewing the report but this continues to be a disaster of complete negligence at best."
Kelly said federal investigators gave information to the U.S. attorney in Cleveland about the Butler project in September. A spokesman for the office could not be reached on Monday.
Bill Vidonic is a staff writer for Trib Total Media. He can be reached at 412-380-5621 or bvidonic@tribweb.com
]]></text></news-item>