<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-W5G1-DYY4-315N"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Buyer sought as copper business put up for sale</title><source>Leek Post and Times</source><author>Leslie Jackson</author><text><![CDATA[LONG established Staffordshire Moorlands copper manufacturer Thomas Bolton Ltd has gone into administration.
The Froghall-based firm, which makes copper products for the power industry, employs 110 people.
Manchester based advisory and restructuring specialist Zolfo Cooper LLP has now been appointed to try to find a buyer for the business.
The news comes three weeks after the Post & Times reported an explosion at the factory, which residents claimed shook their houses and led to clouds of orange smoke appearing over the site. It was also reported last week that the company has been fined £19,050 plus £10,361 in costs for a separate incident after pleading guilty to single breaches of the Management of Health and Safety at Work Regulations 1999, the Health and Safety at Work Act 1974 and the Provision and Use of Work Equipment Regulations 1998, at Stafford Magistrates' Court.
The court case came after a 63-year-old worker suffered life-changing injuries when he was hit on the head by a metal peg.
In a statement to the Post & Times, Zolfo Cooper LLP said that Graham Wild, Andrew Palmer and Anne O'Keefe, were appointed Joint Administrators over Thomas Bolton Limited (the Company) on March 24.
The company will continue to trade while the administrators market the business for sale as a going concern.
The Joint Administrators said they were appointed due to the company experiencing short-term cash flow difficulties and administration was the only option which would allow the business to continue to trade and to retain its employees, while the business is marketed for sale.
Graham Wild, Partner at Zolfo Cooper, said: "We believe the company is an attractive proposition to a range of potential buyers given its expertise and excellent product range.
"We welcome expressions of interest from third parties to acquire the business as a going concern.
"We would also like to thank the staff for their continued support and professionalism during this process."
One worker told the Post & Times: "We have been told that the administrators are now running the company and that the business has been put up for sale.
"Everyone is concerned but we have been told nothing else.
"There are orders, but we have no copper and therefore can't complete them.
"This is a long established company and most people do not want to see it close."
District councillor, Linda Malyon, said: "This is probably the only copper works left in the country and is needed to produce the products industry requires.
"The company also provides proper jobs for local people.
"I have written to our MP Karen Bradley asking if she can help in any way."
Thomas Bolton has been trading for over 200 years and is the sole British producer of specialist copper and copper alloys to a number of major electrical industries worldwide.
It has an extensive product range, skilled workforce and diverse customer base.
Churnet Valley Masterplan agreed: Page 12
]]></text></news-item>