<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-JH81-DYRV-30RV"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Russian TV attacks Ukrainian presidential candidate Tymoshenko</title><source>BBC Monitoring Former Soviet Union - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Russian Gazprom-owned NTV channel has continued its latest character-assassination series about Ukrainian politicians the Kremlin finds objectionable with a feature report about former Prime Minister Yuliya Tymoshenko. The programmes come out under the brand of an earlier cancelled programme called "Profession Reporter", though unlike its previous reincarnation, where each edition was made by one of the channel's well-known correspondents, the new format leaves the authors of the programme and the narrator anonymous.
Disloyalty towards Russia
The 29 March instalment in the series, entitled "Princess at the slop pail", accused Tymoshenko of disloyalty, hypocrisy and financial corruption, among other things. The programme, which ran for just under 30 minutes, started the attack on Tymoshenko by slamming her for changing her position towards Russia.
Over archive video, the narrator contrasted what he said was Tymoshenko asking for Russia's help in freeing her from prison "with tears in her eyes" and stressing her "loyalty to friendly relations" with Russia and "unlimited love for the brotherly nation" with what he said was her "true face", or "bared-teeth grin", that was supposedly revealed by a recording of a telephone conversation between her and Ukrainian MP Nestor Shufrych.
In an audio recording over Tymoshenko's photo, a female voice, allegedly belonging to Tymoshenko, said that she would raise the whole world as soon as she could so that not even "scorched earth" was left of Russia. "Even Western partners froze in indecisiveness when Tymoshenko confirmed the authenticity of the recording," the narrator said, over a photo of a tweet allegedly belonging to her and saying that a certain conversation had taken place but a portion of the recording had been doctored.
The narrator wondered what could have prompted Tymoshenko's "aggressive hysteria", while political scientist Aleksandr Dugin was shown saying that she had been illegally freed from prison "by a gang that took power in Kiev".
A certain Andrey Kovalenko, captioned as leader of a Eurasian Youth Union, alleged that Tymoshenko had always "lied that she was trying to improve relations with Moscow and Putin personally", that the telephone conversation had shown her "true face" and that she was now forced to rely on a "radical electorate".
Different excerpts from the recording were repeatedly played at various points in the programme.
Accusations of corruption
The programme also attempted to ascribe a long history of financial corruption to Tymoshenko and accused her of allegedly ordering the murder of MP Yevhen Shcherban in 1996, a charge she has repeatedly denied.
The programme traced Tymoshenko's alleged history of financial violations from a 1995 incident when she was detained by customs for attempting to take 26,000 dollars out of the country to the 2001 charges of smuggling attempts and forgery of state documents to the 2011 criminal case on charges of exceeding authority when signing gas agreements with Russia's Gazprom in 2009.
The narrator also recalled accusations against Tymoshenko, which remained inconclusive since the relevant case against her was dropped, that back in 2001 she tried to bribe a judge; the allegation was made over black and white footage of what the narrator said was Tymoshenko talking about bribing a judge.
After accusing Tymoshenko of fraud and financial corruption, the narrator suggested that she decided to move to "big politics" so as to save her "cash account".
The programme also contrasted Tymoshenko's mansion in Ukraine to what he said were her claims of living a modest life and suggested that she also owned an expensive flat in Miami. The narrator made some unsubstantiated claims about the size of Tymoshenko's fortune, citing, among other things, a figure of 12bn dollars.
Attack on Tymoshenko's character
In an attack on her character, the programme also suggested that Tymoshenko's relations with male politicians, including former Ukrainian Prime Minister Pavlo Lazarenko, former President Viktor Yushchenko, Interim President Oleksandr Turchinov, and MP Nestor Shufrych, went beyond just business or political dealings.
The programme also found fault in what it said was Tymoshenko's lack of principles in working in different political camps such as that of ousted President Viktor Yanukovych and former President Viktor Yushchenko.
The narrator also poked fun at Tymoshenko's image, which, he said, changed suddenly at different points of her career. After starting her own political party, Tymoshenko, a brunette and a native of Dnipropetrovsk who only spoke Russian, turned into a blonde and learned to speak Ukrainian, he said. "Her formal dress style of a businesswoman was replaced by the image of a mother," he said, linking the transformation to American PR experts "close to State Department".
Over archive footage, the programme further mocked Tymoshenko's supposed attempts to pretend being on her "deathbed" after she was jailed in 2011.
A certain Yuliya Abaplova, captioned as Tymoshenko's former cellmate, claimed that the latter had used her as a servant and said that Tymoshenko, despite her claims of being seriously ill and unable to walk, was able to perform various physical exercises, including some strenuous ones. She further alleged that Tymoshenko had intimate relations with her visiting lawyer over an unclear video of a man and a woman appearing to be hugging and kissing in a small room.
"On the hook of the US secret service"
In the early 2000s, the FBI launched a probe against Lazarenko and, "according to analysts", they received access to data about all of Tymoshenko's finances, the narrator said. She thus "became caught in the hook of the US secret services", he concluded. He went on to say that almost the whole of political elite in Ukraine were under the control of the West, including "oligarchs who financed the Maydan and who are now close to the new authorities".
The programme also questioned Tymoshenko's alleged close ties with US financier George Soros and senator John McCain.
It concluded with a warning about what it claimed were Tymoshenko's ties with radical far-right groups. Moreover, the narrator wondered how Tymoshenko could be "flirting with fascist thugs" while forgetting her father's "Jewish roots".
Pro-Kremlin political scientist Yevgeniy Satanovskiy was shown saying that the current authorities in Kiev were composed of revolutionaries who had been partly approved by the USA and the EU and partly come to power thanks to the Maydan protest movement, of oligarchs and people close to the criminal world and those who controlled gangs and private armies or those leaning on "semi-Fascist structures".
"However, would Tymoshenko's Western patrons like these changes in her image? The Orange Princess is already being warned that such behaviour will not bode well for her. Pursuing its own interests, the West is indeed ready to have a dialogue with unprincipled but sane politicians. By all accounts, the recent convict who, together with nationalists, is calling for shooting Russians everywhere does not fall into that category," the narrator concluded over video of violence in Kiev and meetings between European and Ukrainian politicians.
Source: NTV, Moscow, in Russian 1420 gmt 29 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>