<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-4HV1-DYG2-R44V"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Public Comments Sought on Clean-Up Proposal for Oak Grove Water Conveyance Trestles</title><source>Targeted News Service</source><author>Targeted News Service</author><text><![CDATA[The U.S. Department of Agriculture's U.S. Forest Service unit - Mt. Hood National Forest - issued the following news release:
The Clackamas River Ranger District is seeking comments on a proposal for clean-up activities at the Oak Grove Hydroelectric Project Water Conveyance Pipeline Trestle sites. This project is part of an ongoing program in the Forest Service to address impacts associated with hazardous materials on National Forest lands.
The Oak Grove Hydroelectric Project (Project) is located approximately 22 miles southeast of Estacada in Clackamas County, Oregon. The 6.4-mile-long water conveyance pipeline conveys water that is diverted from Lake Harriet, north to the Oak Grove Hydroelectric Powerhouse (Powerhouse) for the generation of electricity. Trestles are present across surface water bodies to support the pipeline. The Trestles are at three different locations along the pipeline between Lake Harriet and the Powerhouse at Pint and Canyon Creeks. Contaminated soils were discovered when PGE re-painted the pipeline trestles. The soil became contaminated with lead and other metals during sand blasting in the late 1960's and early 1970's. This removal action addresses the risk posed by the presence of these soils.
Under the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act (CERCLA) of 1980, proposed clean-up activities are designed to minimize risks to human health and the environment from contamination associated with hazardous substances found at the site. A site investigation (SI) was performed between 2008 and 2013 to assess the nature and extent of metals in soils at the Trestles. The results indicate that arsenic, chromium, and lead are present in soils beneath the Trestles. The investigation results indicate that contamination at the Trestles is limited to surface or near-surface soils. While metals are present in soils near Canyon, and Pint Creeks, they were not detected in sediment or water samples collected from the creeks.
"This clean-up project will allow us to reduce the threat of hazardous substances being released into Canyon, and Pint Creeks," said Mike Chaveas District Ranger for the Clackamas River Ranger District.
The Engineering Evaluation/Cost Analysis (EE/CA) and related documents constituting the Administrative Record for this response are located at the Clackamas River Ranger District, Mt. Hood National Forest,and are available for public review during regular business hours. The office is located at 595 NW Industrial Way, Estacada, OR. These documents are also available for viewing on the Internet at: http://www.fs.usda.gov/detail/mthood/landmanagement/?cid=STELPRD3791926
The public spokesperson for this action is Laura Pramuk, Public Affairs Specialist, Mt. Hood National Forest at 16400 Champion Way, Sandy, Oregon 97055, phone: 503-668-1791. The On-Site Scene Coordinator for the Removal Action is Jonathan Heyl, stationed at the PNW Region 6 Office of the US Forest Service, phone: 503-808-2171. Written comments may be mailed to Mr. Heyl at USFS Region 6 - Engineering, Jonathan Heyl: 1220 SW 3rd Avenue, Portland, OR 97204 at or e-mailed to jheyl@fs.fed.us
Contact: Chris Bentley, 503/668-1776
Copyright Targeted News Services
TNS 18DejucosGrace-140401-30FurigayJane-4686845 30FurigayJane
]]></text></news-item>