<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-F9M1-DXDT-60RR"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Audit Office delivers damning verdict of 'botched' Royal Mail sell off that saw 16 'priority' investors pocket millions in profits</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>MATT WEST</author><text><![CDATA[16 institutional investors allowed to buy shares valued at £728mThey agreed to hold the shares for the long termBut  most sold all or part of their shares as share price skyrocketed 75%Retail investors were limited to shares allocations valued at £750
The government's privatisation of Royal Mail short-changed the taxpayer by £1billion a report found today in a damning indictment of the way in which the 500 year old company was floated on the London Stock Exhchange.
The National Audit Office found 16 priority investors reneged on a gentleman's agreement to hold their investments for the long term, instead selling their shares at a massive profit within weeks.
Only the Government of Singapore and Children's Investment Fund Management were named out of the group of 16. Each retain over 3 per cent of total shares in Royal Mail.
The NAO said the remaining 14t sold either all or most of their stakes in Royal Mail within weeks after its share price sky rocketed by 38 per cent, to 455p, on the first day - representing a first day in value of £750million for the new shareholders - and continued to head north.
The NAO revealed six priority investors sold all their shares within weeks of trading, while a further six sold part of their holdings, and four others increased their holdings.
The 16 priority investors were allocated £728million worth of shares, while another 94 institutions were given £570million worth.
The news will anger retail investors who were limited to share allocations worth £750 each, while the group of institutional investors given priority by the government were able bank millions of pounds in profits from the meteoric rise in Royal Mail's share price in the weeks that followed is London debut.
Limits were imposed on the number of shares retail investors could buy on Royal Mail's initial public offering after it emerged the shares listing was over-subscribed by some 24 times the expected level.
Critics said the level of interest showed Royal Mail was significantly undervalued within a share price range of 260p to 330p, even at the top of the range.
Almost a month before the shares listing analysts at stockbrokers Panmure Gordon were warning the company was undervalued by as much as £1billion.
Business Secretary Vince Cable dismissed the rocketing share price - at one stage Royal Mail shares were 75 per cent higher than their stock market debut - as 'froth.'
Despite this shares in Royal |Mail remain significantly above the original offer price. They were higher today by 0.04 per cent at 563.25p.
The Business Secretary said the report showed that the government achieved is aim of securing the future of the universal delivery service through a successful sale.
But critics of the privatisation said the spending watchdog's report providing damning evidence that the government sold off the country's family silver 'on the cheap'.
The NAO said Mr Cable's department took a 'cautious' approach to a number of issues which led to shares being priced at a level 'substantially below' the initial trading price.
Amyas Morse, head of the NAO said: 'The Department was very keen to achieve its objective of selling Royal Mail, and was successful in getting the company listed on the FTSE 100. Its approach, however, was marked by deep caution, the price of which was borne by the taxpayer.
'The government retained 30 per cent of the company. It could have retained even more and allowed the taxpayer to participate further in the rapidly increasing share price and thus limit the cost to the taxpayer.'
The government could have retained 110 million more shares, worth £363million, at the offer price, while still privatising the business, said the report.
Surplus properties with a market value of more than £200million were disclosed in the privatisation prospectus, but the NAO said it did not believe the basis on which the company was sold recovered this value.
The NAO also criticised the government's 'reliance' on professional advisers, in this instance Lazard's investment bank which pocketed £12.7million from the Royal Mail sale.
Mr Cable defended the government's decision to sell the Royal Mail, effectively at a discount.
He said: 'We secured the future of the universal postal service through a successful sale of a majority stake in Royal Mail, predominantly to responsible long term investors.
'Achieving the highest price possible at any cost and whatever the risk was never the aim of the sale.
The report concludes there was a real risk of a failed sale attached to pushing the price too high, and a failed sale would have been the worst outcome for tax payers and jeopardised the operation of Royal Mail going forward.
'The report also comprehensively demolishes the argument that the government should have relied on the price valuations of some banks who were pitching for the contract to sell Royal Mail.
'The NAO confirms we have protected taxpayers from the risk of needing to offer ongoing support to the company as well as safeguarding the vital six day a week service that customers and businesses around the country rely on.'
But shadow business secretary Chuka Umunna said the NAO had delivered 'a damning verdict on the government's botched Royal Mail fire sale' and had left the taxpayer disgracefully short changed by hundreds of millions of pounds.
'We now know definitively that far better value for taxpayers could have been possible had ministers adopted a different timetable for the sale. The NAO could not be clearer: the inflexible timetable set by ministers for Royal Mail's privatisation resulted in the public losing out,' he said.
'When Royal Mail was privatised, Vince Cable described the huge rise in its share price as 'froth', but since then it has continued to rise. He and David Cameron have serious questions to answer on the hundreds of millions of pounds they have lost British taxpayers and cannot duck responsibility for what has happened.'
Business Minister Michael Fallon said a loss-making public corporation had been transformed into one of the top 100 British companies.
He told the BBC Radio 4 Today programme: 'So, this was a success and the Audit Office report actually recognises that we achieved our objectives.'
Mr Fallon said there had been difficult market conditions and 'challenging' industrial relations at the time which meant that some priority investors would not have paid more than 310p.
He added: 'Hypothetically, we could have got a higher price but we would have taken a bigger risk of the public not subscribing for shares, of the whole transaction falling apart and Royal Mail's value - and the NAO recognises that in their report - collapsing. It would have been worth far less if we'd had a damaging transaction that didn't receive public support.'
]]></text></news-item>