<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-G7X1-JD34-V2JN"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Obeids 'aimed to take full control of Sydney water'; Corruption hearing - Banker tells of meetings</title><source>Sydney Morning Herald (Australia)</source><author>Kate McClymont, Michaela Whitbourn</author><text><![CDATA[The family of crooked Labor kingpin Eddie Obeid was scheming to "effectively control all of Sydney's water" and make $100 million in the process, the Independent Commission Against Corruption has heard.
Gardner Brook, a former Lehman Brothers banker, told the inquiry on Tuesday that in 2008 Moses Obeid had told him the water deal "eclipsed" the family's plans for a coal venture.
Mr Brook was the ICAC's star witness at a previous inquiry where the Obeids were revealed to have reaped $30 million from a corrupt coal deal involving former mining minister Ian Macdonald.
The commission is investigating allegations the Obeid family owned a secret 30 per cent stake in Australian Water Holdings and stood to make up to $60 million from a proposed public-private partnership with the state government.
In a statement to the commission, Mr Brook said Moses Obeid told him his family had "an ownership in Australian Water" as well as "great influence over it".
Mr Brook also said Moses Obeid had confided that "the company was looking ito a privatisation deal where they could effectively control all of Sydney's water".
Mr Brook said he had previously met Moses Obeid and AWH chief executive Nick Di Girolamo at his Lehman Brothers office in July 2008. The inquiry has heard that Mr Di Girolamo is a prominent Liberal Party fund-raiser and associate of the Obeid family. At the time, Mr Brook understood Mr Di Girolamo was the Obeids' business partner.
A month later, Mr Brook said he attended a meeting at Moses Obeid's Elizabeth Bay residence. Former Labor minister Joe Tripodi was already there and Mr Obeid senior arrived later, Mr Brook said.
They spoke about AWH for up to half an hour before switching to proposed electricity privatisation.
Mr Brook understood that Moses Obeid was hoping to get a cut by brokering the sale of the government's electricity assets.
Other evidence given at the inquiry revealed that when Arthur Sinodinos left AWH at the end of 2011, the company was in dire financial straits. Financial records submitted at the inquiry show that as of September 2011, AWH owed the Tax Office $720,000.
Despite having no funds, AWH continued to pay monthly retainers, some worth more than $5000, to several Liberal Party lobbyists.
It was around this time the Obeid family, through a trust, injected $400,000 ito the business to keep it afloat.
In other evidence, Ian George, an accountant who signed off on the expenses billed to Sydney Water by AWH, told the inquiry that some of the expenses must have been certified "in error".
"What I've got is a whole bundle of what might be described as errors," Geoffrey Watson, SC, counsel assisting the inquiry, said.
Showing a bill from a luxury hotel, Mr Watson said, "it strikes me you couldn't have been looking too closely if you let the Sofitel in Cairns go through".
"I can only assume that it's a mistake," Mr George said.
Payments to lobbyists also appeared to have been approved, along with a $2000 gala dinner at the Italian Chamber of Commerce and limousine charges worth $880. Mr Watson asked jokingly if there were sewerage pipes at the back of the limo.
Paul and Moses Obeid are expected to give evidence on Wednesday; Senator Sinodinos on Thursday.
]]></text></news-item>