<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-F391-DY2M-W52W"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>A Whale of an International Court Ruling Against Japan</title><source>The New York Times Blogs(Dot Earth)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Japan has agreed to abide by a ruling from the International Court of Justice that its whaling expeditions to the Southern Ocean are not scientific research and thus forbidden under a longstanding moratorium.
A Facebook comment by John Taylor, a Coloradan with a passion for ocean conservation (which I saw via the filmmaker Louie Psihoyos), succinctly summarized the significance of this decision:
Today, we evolved some, became a better, more human species.
There's plenty of wiggle room in the ruling, particularly in that it only applies to Japan's whaling in the waters around Antarctica. Read this article in The Australian for more. And of course Norway and Iceland have not lost their appetite for whale meat.
But the court ruling is a big step forward, nonetheless. The news story in The Times has lots of context, including this:
Japan's whaling program has struggled financially in recent years, as more Japanese consumers turn up their noses at whale meat and as environmental activists chasing whaling boats make the hunts more difficult. Hunts in recent years have relied on public subsidies, including money drawn from funds earmarked for Japan's post-tsunami reconstruction.
Some critics said that Monday's decision presented Japan with an opportunity to bow out of a practice that has become a drain on its finances, as well as a blow to its image abroad.
"This might be a good time to quit," said Toshio Kasuya, an early collaborator on Japan's research program who has since become one of its harshest critics. From early on, it became clear to researchers that the program did not prioritize scientific discovery, he said.
"The system is bankrupt," Mr. Kasuya said.
Whaling is defended by some Japanese, however, who feel unfairly singled out by international criticism and who argue that the hunts are a Japanese tradition. These supporters make little pretense that whaling is carried out for science.
"Some people eat beef, others eat whale. We should respect all cultures," said Komei Wani, who leads the Group to Preserve Whale Dietary Culture, based in the whaling town of Shimonoseki. "As long as there are enough whales to go around, why can't we hunt a few?"
A Chat With Greenpeace's Departing U.S. Chief on Old and New EnvironmentalismScientists See Cruelty in Killing Method Used in Japan's Dolphin RoundupBluefin Tuna Sold for Record $1.76 Million in Tokyo 'Auction'*Paul Watson Recalls Civil War's Whale WarsU.N. Climate Report Authors Answer 11 Basic Questions
]]></text></news-item>