<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-MX01-JC8C-2009"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Polluted lake may get break; Federal judge's ruling could block pumping of contaminated water into Okeechobee</title><source>Sun-Sentinel (Fort Lauderdale, Florida)</source><author>Andy Reid, Staff writer</author><text><![CDATA[Lake Okeechobee may no longer be the dumping ground for polluted water that washes off South Florida sugar cane fields and other farmland, after a federal judge's decision Friday.
Environmentalists are declaring a key win in their long-standing legal fight to stop "back-pumping," the controversial flood-control practice that pumps polluted stormwater runoff from South Florida farms north into the lake.
The result of the federal judge's decision on Friday could be that South Florida back-pumping as well as other kinds of "water transfer" of polluted water elsewhere in the country can be considered a violation of the U.S. Clean Water Act.
Back-pumping opponents contend that it flushes damaging fertilizers, pesticides and other pollutants into Lake Okeechobee, sacrificing the lake's health in order to hold onto water that later gets tapped mainly by the sugar industry for irrigation.
Fish kills, toxic algae blooms and threats to drinking water are among the consequences of the "giant sickly plumes" that can come from back pumping into the lake, said David Guest, attorney for Earthjustice, which is waging the legal challenge.
"These are real serious, horrendously bad impacts [for] using a lake to store contaminated water for the sugar industry," Guest said.
But sugar industry representatives and the South Florida Water Management District defend back-pumping as a valuable flood-control tool that helps farms and communities stay dry, while also holding onto stormwater for future needs instead of dumping it out to sea.
"It's an appropriate management tool," said Barbara Miedema, vice president for the Sugar Cane Growers Cooperative of Florida. "Without water in the lake ... everybody would be in jeopardy. It's not just for farms."
Sugar industry representatives and the water management district contend that the judge's decision doesn't necessarily mean an end to back pumping. The district is still evaluating whether it will file an appeal, spokesman Randy Smith said Monday.
During 2013, about 8 billion gallons of water were back-pumped into the lake between June 6 and 12, according to the district.
"Back-pumping is very rare and it is used primarily for health and human safety uses during flood-control operations," Smith said. "Over the years the district has greatly reduced the frequency and also the volume of back-pumping."
Lake Okeechobee water once naturally overlapped its southern shores and flowed south to replenish the Everglades, until farming and development got in the way.
Now, South Florida's vast system of levees, canals and pumps manipulates water levels for flood control needs and uses the lake as a backup to boost water supplies. Much of the water that once fed the Everglades now gets drained out to sea for flood control.
Back-pumping into the lake is a practice that environmental groups have fought for decades, arguing that it brings an influx of phosphorus, nitrogen and other nutrient-rich pollutants that result from farming, leading to fish kills and lake water quality problems.
Lake Okeechobee already suffers from polluted stormwater that drains in from the north, washing in pollutants from agricultural land, roads and neighborhoods between the lake and Orlando.
The federal court decision on Friday that affects back-pumping came from U.S. District Judge Kenneth Karas in the Southern District of New York. Karas has been hearing a case involving regulations for "water transfer" practices across the country.
The result of his decision, if it holds, could end an exemption that allows the South Florida Water Management District to avoid federal water quality standards when pumping water back into Lake Okeechobee.
If the back-pumping ruling holds, South Florida would need to take more steps to clean up the water that flows off farms in order to keep pumping that water into Lake Okeechobee.
"If they actually cleaned their act up, they wouldn't need a [back-pumping] permit at all," Guest said.
abreid@tribune.com, 561-228-5504 or Twitter@abreidnews
]]></text></news-item>