<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-8T11-JBHM-S00G"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Court Orders New Jersey To Address Flaws In RGGI Withdrawal Process</title><source>EnergyWashington Week</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[New Jersey's Superior Court is ordering the state to address what it says are flaws in how the state went about withdrawing from the Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative (RGGI) climate cap-and-trade program, agreeing with environmentalists that officials erred by not pursuing a formal rulemaking to withdraw from the program.
Environmentalists say the March 25 ruling, combined with what they say are economic and environmental benefits of RGGI in the remaining participant states, should push New Jersey to reassess its decision to leave it. But the court case that resulted in the ruling did not challenge the legality of the withdrawal -- only the process the state used to withdraw. The state could now craft a rule to formalize its withdrawal and satisfy the terms of the ruling.
RGGI applies among several Mid-Atlantic and Northeast states. The program is seen as a model for other states, and RGGI members have said they should receive credit for participating as a compliance option in EPA's upcoming greenhouse gas (GHG) rule for existing utilities, which will set an overall GHG limit and defer to states on how to meet it.
RGGI imposes an overall GHG emissions cap for the affected region, which states implement by issuing their own rules to participate in the system. Under RGGI, which only regulates power plants, companies are required to purchase emission credits equivalent to their GHGs. RGGI's website says, "States sell nearly all emission allowances through auctions and invest proceeds in energy efficiency, renewable energy" and other programs to cut GHGs.
New Jersey previously adopted rules to implement a state carbon dioxide (CO2) budget trading program to satisfy RGGI requirements, but after Gov. Chris Christie (R-NJ) took office he decided to pull out of RGGI.
The state's Department of Environmental Protection then posted a notice on its website saying that as the state had withdrawn from RGGI as of Jan. 1, 2012, it would not implement the trading program rules for the regulatory period beginning on that date. The notice prompted Environment New Jersey and the Natural Resources Defense Council (NRDC) to sue the state, claiming it cannot scrap the trading program except through rulemaking.
A three-judge panel of the New Jersey Superior Court heard oral arguments earlier this year in the case, In re: Regional Greenhouse Gas Initiative, and observers said the judges were skeptical of the state's RGGI withdrawal process -- though they also appeared uncertain on what remedy they could grant to environmentalists.
Court's Decision
Subsequently, the court in its March 25 ruling says that although the state CO2 trading program rules were intended to implement RGGI, they were "sufficiently broadly worded to allow for implementation of a program independent of RGGI,"and so it is remanding the issue to the environment department to resolve.
New Jersey environmental officials must now initiate a state Administrative Procedure Act rulemaking to repeal or amend the rules within 60 days of the opinion.
New Jersey's environment department should have taken action to repeal the state CO2 trading program rules or amend them to clarify they do not create a stand-alone trading program, the court says. On remand, the state should either repeal the rules or clarify they apply only when New Jersey is a participant in a GHG trading program. Enforcement of the state trading program rules is stayed pending the remand process.
Although New Jersey could satisfy the court's decision by issuing a rule to repeal or otherwise amend the state CO2 trading program policy, environmentalists say the state should now rejoin RGGI.
"Today's court decision -- together with the substantial economic, environmental and public health benefits the program has demonstrated in neighboring states -- should compel New Jersey to give RGGI another look," said NRDC's Energy and Transportation Program Director Dale Bryk in a March 25 statement.
Bryk also noted the benefit of participating in RGGI as a compliance option for EPA's upcoming CO2 new source performance standards for existing power plants. "In all likelihood the EPA will consider RGGI to be an appropriate compliance mechanism," Bryk said, noting that RGGI states have asked the agency for such an approach.
"Soon, every state in the country is going to have to crack down on their dirty fossil fuel powers plants -- why not do it with a program that's proven to create jobs, lower bills and boost your local economy?" said Bryk. -- Anthony Lacey (alacey@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>