<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW8-42K1-J9YR-G4DK"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Mum's the word when the spooks are hiring; Female double agents, and especially mothers, are said to be deadlier than the male. We discover why</title><source>telegraph.co.uk</source><author>By Judith Woods</author><text><![CDATA[If you want something done, ask a busy woman, so the old adage goes. After all, she's already juggling career and children and elderly in-laws and cooking dinner every evening, so taxing the car and worming the dog shouldn't prove too much of a stretch.
But what if you want to counter the new and polymorphous threat of state-sponsored terrorism? Engage in politically explosive surveillance of allied nations? Or carry out morally dubious acts of sabotage against shadowy foes? Well, it would seem for this sort of thing the person you really need on speed dial is - also a busy woman.
According to an anonymous female MI6 officer who has spoken out as part of a subtle but active recruitment drive, women make "bloody good spies" thanks to their emotional intelligence, empathy and ability to park their egos and work closely in a team. Moreover, for once, having children is regarded as a plus, and not just because men in general and terrorists in particular tend to underestimate the critical faculties of anyone with a handbag crammed with wet wipes.
"Being a mother and a spy can also be an advantage because it enables you to connect with a whole range of people from terrorists to political leaders," says our unnamed spy, who claims, with admirable matter-of-factness, to have "made the world a safer place" as part of her job, which brings with it "a strong moral reward".
"I'm less of a threat than a single female," she says. "They, the terrorists, have mothers, sisters, daughters."
It is a sentiment echoed by Baroness Neville-Jones, former minister for security and counter-terrorism, now a member of the House of Lords with a position on the National Security Strategy joint committee. "Though I have had a lot to do with the intelligence world, I have never been a member of any of the agencies and have no personal experience of their working environment," says the Baroness. "I do think, based on my own experience of government, that women are often better than men at ploughing through detail in pursuit of policy outcomes. Since a good deal of modern intelligence work is on sifting vast amount of material and making connections, this attribute is especially powerful."
Female spies, of course, have long captured the public imagination in film and literature. But until recently, their skillset has always been seen in terms of their sexuality. Mata Hari, the Dutch exotic dancer and courtesan who was accused of spying for Germany in the First World War and shot for espionage, was the embodiment of the devious femme fatale.
Ian Fleming's philandering female spies fed the appetite for state-sanctioned seduction. They might have been able to deploy
hi-tech gadgetry and high-kick like cage fighters, but it was usually while wearing bikinis. And having extracted secrets from their high-ranking lovers, they would get their comeuppance from a smirking 007.
These days, however, female security agents have come into their own, as attested by the fact that Melissa Rosenberg, the screenwriter behind the blockbusting Twilight series, is working on a script featuring an all-female spy ensemble. The result is bound to be more Bourne trilogy than Charlie's Angels, as contemporary portrayals of female spies have been more complex - and all the more compelling for it.
Claire Danes in Homeland is a case in point; a driven manic-depressive, her formidable talents are never in doubt. In the British series, Spooks, Keeley Hawes, Hermione Norris and Miranda Raison played pivotal operational roles in MI5. It was abundantly clear that they had reached their positions by merit rather than any window-dressing demanded by gender quotas.
In the Oscar-winning Zero Dark Thirty, about the hunt for Osama bin Laden, Jessica Chastain's intense analyst, Maya, was based on a real-life CIA operative, whose identity may be unknown but whose character has attracted as many detractors as admirers. While others in the agency had wavered during the hunt for the man behind the 9/11 atrocities, the real-life Maya repeatedly declared that she was "100 per cent" certain bin Laden was hiding at the compound in Abbottabad, Pakistan, where he was eventually killed in 2011.
When an email was sent around the agency announcing that she was among a group of officers who were to be decorated for their triumph, "Maya" is said to have clicked "reply-all" and unleashed a tirade. "You guys tried to obstruct me," was the gist, according to one recipient. "You fought me. Only I deserve the award."
No female self-deprecation there. Yet it is typically female traits that make women so well-suited to security operations, not least their ability to abide by rules and suppress the impulse to broadcast their achievements. The code-breaking women who worked at Bletchley Park spent half a lifetime batting off "What did you do in the war?" questions with inconsequential anecdotes that bore no resemblance to the truth, which was protected by the Official Secrets Act.
Just as Silent Witness, starring Emilia Fox, and its US equivalent CSI, sparked a boom in forensic science degrees, interest in careers in security operations is on the rise at home and abroad. Lindsay Moran, a former CIA officer and author of Blowing My Cover, My Life As a Spy, is today giving a talk to undergraduates at her alma mater, Harvard, on being a spy.
Moran, 44 (above), now married with two children, concurs that women in general and mothers in particular are extraordinarily well suited to fieldwork. "Many of techniques I was being trained in came so naturally to me that they were already second-nature," says Moran.
"The first was attention to personal security. Long before I was a spy, I had an instinct about who was suspicious and who might be following me. Like any woman entering a dark parking lot, I would have my keys threaded through my fingers and have a contingency plan about what I would do if someone approached me. Men just don't think the same way."
Another important trait is the ability simply to sit and listen, at length, to another person. Women have a lot of practice at this, observed Moran wryly. "You need to be able to assess and read people, understand their motivations and what makes them tick," she says. "Security services tend to attract people with healthy egos, and confident men are so used to jammering on about themselves they aren't prepared to stop and let someone else do the talking."
Men are more likely to open up to a woman and are much less likely to suspect she is an intelligence officer. "A man will complain about how he's being treated at work, and when a woman says, 'That sounds terrible,' he'll just keep speaking."
The modern world of spying is less about scaling walls and assassinating the enemy with poison-tipped umbrellas than seeking ways to infiltrate terror organisations. So-called soft skills employed by intelligence operatives are used to gain the confidence of disillusioned members or affiliates of various groups.
A rapport is built up, then once trust has been established, the spy reveals their true identity - or at least a version of it - to the person, who then agrees to become an agent and the relationship takes on a monetary dimension.
"It's actually a relief once you break cover and reveal you work for the US government," says Moran. "Then you can move away from any ambiguity, particularly regarding the issue of sex, because most men assume that if a single woman wants to spend time with them and listen to their woes she must be attracted to them.
"Being a mother is useful, because it gives you a different status, and a middle-aged woman with kids is 10 times less likely to arouse suspicion. It also helps engender a certain protectiveness towards your agents in the field."
It is this maternal duty of care - coupled with steely pragmatism - that characterises James Bond's handler, M, who was later played by Dame Judi Dench.
But the often conflicting demands of bringing up children while defending the realm can take their toll. Moran concedes she couldn't have brought up her sons, aged nine and seven, while living a double life.
Britain's most famous spy, the former MI5 director, Dame Stella Rimington (above) - who combined national security with child-rearing, albeit with the help of nannies - last year admitted her regret that she didn't spend enough time with her children. She may have been defending Queen and country, but she was none the less "wracked with guilt" over the sports-day and school-play milestones she missed. Her offspring had no idea what mummy was really doing when she was a no-show.
Men, meanwhile, know the women in their lives are adept at juggling roles, and let them get on with it. But the exact nature of those roles often remains a mystery.
In his morose commentary on creativity, Cyril Connolly famously observed that the pram in the hallway represented a "sombre enemy of good art". These days it signals your wife is quite possibly working for MI6.
]]></text></news-item>