<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW9-2FW1-JCBN-V20W"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Car dealer fined over repo scam</title><source>Waikato Times (Hamilton, New Zealand)</source><author>Josh Martin</author><text><![CDATA[A Mount Maunganui car salesman convicted of assaulting a Fair Go reporter investigating his activities, has been fined for breaching the Fair Trading Act.
In Auckland District Court yesterday morning, Mount Auto Court director Alan Spiers and his finance company MAC Warranties were fined a total of $65,000.
Spiers pleaded guilty in January to 11 charges of breaching the act after a three-year Commerce Commission investigation into his repossession practices. MAC Warranties was convicted of 17 breaches of the act.
Spiers was yesterday fined $23,000 and his company fined $42,000.
The court was told MAC Warranties would repossess cars from defaulting borrowers and sell them to Mount Auto Court at a low value. The car yard would then resell the vehicles for a large mark- up.
Judge Phillipa Cunningham heard how one repossessed vehicle was valued by Spiers at $800, but later sold at Mount Auto Court for close to $7000. She said "the disadvantage [to the loan defaulter] is obvious".
The Commerce Commission and Spiers negotiated a reduced fine which Judge Cunningham approved. It came more than three years after the commission began investigating the car salesman's dealings.
Judge Cunningham said Spiers' case was about consumer protection and his system of repossessing cars and vehicles from often low-income or welfare- dependent clients, who often did not know their rights or exercise them, was "reckless".
She said she hoped the fine would be a deterrent to other potential cases in the car industry, but it was discounted due to a guilty plea and a compensation plan that MAC Warranties had started.
Prosecution lawyer Alysha McClintock earlier submitted a $110,000 to $120,000 starting point penalty for the Fair Trading Act offences.
"This business made and broke its own rules . . . in terms of how it was going to approach vehicle valuations for repossessed vehicles."
Defence counsel Jenny Stevens said both her clients acted in a "careless" way.
Spiers had voluntarily enacted a compensation scheme for victims, that was worth $180,000, refunding some and crediting the accounts of others.
Fair Go host Gordon Harcourt, who was assaulted while filming at Spiers car yard in July 2011, said outside the court, that Spiers had caused "a high degree of real harm" to people who used MAC Warranties, when buying used cars from Mount Auto Court.
]]></text></news-item>