<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW9-DRW1-JBKR-R3S5"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>It's time policymakers realize pipelines, not railcars, are the cheapest and safest way to ship oil</title><source>National Post's Financial Post &amp; FP Investing (Canada)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[This article appears in the April 2014 edition of the Financial Post Magazine. Visit the iTunes store to download the iPad edition of this month's issue.( http://itunes.apple.com/ca/app/financial-post-magazine/id414091878?mt=8 )
Trains were never meant to replace pipelines as oil transportation workhorses. Yet that's where we are, the result of a paralysis by policymakers reluctant to pick sides in the energy security versus climate action debate, while oil industry opponents jam pipeline regulatory reviews to frustrate proponents amid a North American oil production boom.
It's a bad situation that begs for a return to common sense: Let oil from long-life reserves such as Alberta's oil sands move through pipelines-starting with the approval of Keystone XL in the United States - and let trains get back to what they do best, including clearing the backlog of grain waiting for a ride in Western Canada.
Even veteran railroader Hunter Harrison, CEO and president of Canadian Pacific Railways Ltd., recognized the mismatch between oil and rail. "I don't get really excited, necessarily, about getting crude. I am excited about moving lumber and paper and other stuff that railroads were built on," he said in February. "We've got to haul the crude, I'm going to do as good a job as we can do, as safely as we can do, but I am not going out there lobbying to get rules changed and making it easier for crude. That's notmygame."
No improvement of rail tracks, tank cars, emergency response or labelling of flammable oils can change the fact that pipelines are simply safer because they are fixed, underground and highly regulated, while trains are less safe because they move, are above ground, and we are just beginning to implement regulation for oil cargoes. Besides, hauling oil by train puts the environment at greater risk - including generating more greenhouse gases-than moving it by pipelines, making the green campaign against oil-sands pipelines counterproductive.
If the 10 rail accidents that have already occurred in North America since 2008 -from oil spills to explosions such as the one at Lac-Mégantic, Que., that claimed 47 lives - aren't motivation enough for a big rethink, a look at the aggressive growth projections of oil by rail if pipelines continue to be stalled should be a wake-up call.
Related
Oil sands development held back by 'blunt and flawed' investment barriers aimed at state-owned firms, report says( http://business.financialpost.com/2014/03/26/oil-sands-state-owned-investment/?__lsa=c5c7-807f )
Former Obama adviser: Rejecting Keystone XL pipeline would make Vladimir Putin's day( http://business.financialpost.com/2014/03/13/keystone-xl-pipeline-obama-adviser/?__lsa=bdb3-b150 )
Clinton's Keystone-pipeline dodge causes donors to rethink support( http://business.financialpost.com/2014/03/11/clintons-keystone-pipeline-dodge-causes-donors-to-rethink-support/?__lsa=bdb3-b150 )
Oil sands foes ignore the facts as cancer claims dealt a blow by study( http://business.financialpost.com/2014/03/24/oil-sands-foes-ignore-the-facts-as-cancer-claims-dealt-a-blow-by-study/?__lsa=bdb3-b150 )
An extensive study of the growth in the oil-by-rail transportation business in North America done by the U.S. State Department, as part of its recently released Final Environmental Impact Statement on the proposed Keystone XL project, revealed that approximately 180,000 barrels of Canadian oil was moving on rail every day by the end of 2013. Two years ago, that figure was zero.
Industry in Western Canada is spending billions to increase rail-loading facilities, and there is already capacity to load 700,000 barrels of oil per day, increasing to more than 1.1 million b/d by the end of 2014, the report says. By contrast, pipeline capacity out of Western Canada is 3.7 million b/d.
The ramp-up in rail can replace KXL, which could move 830,000 b/d, if it's further delayed or turned down by U.S. President Barack Obama, who has promised a decision by April. To be sure, it's more expensive to move oil by rail.The State Department study estimates it costs US$8 to US$10 a barrel to move oil through pipes from Alberta to the U.S. Gulf Coast, and US$12 to US$24 a barrel to cover the same distance by rail. But the higher rail cost is not enough to suppress oilsands production, which is driven by global oil demand rather than by any single project.
Indeed, the availability and flexibility of rail to fill oil transportation gaps is a major reason the study concludes oil-sands growth will continue with or without KXL, or any other proposed pipelines. But just because it's available doesn't make it right. It feels like a dare that's gone too far.
]]></text></news-item>