<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW9-DX21-JD6S-R3SG"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>At 35, memories of TMI accident still fresh</title><source>Delaware State News</source><author>Dr. Samuel B. Hoff</author><text><![CDATA[As an undergraduate student at Susquehanna University in Selinsgrove, Pa., in March 1979, I didn't worry about where the electricity in my dorm came from. By April of that year, everyone at SU - less than 50 miles from the Middletown [Pa.] location of the Three Mile Island nuclear power plant - and, I dare say, a good portion of people in the world, probably thought twice about the safety of nuclear power. As we commemorate the 35th anniversary of the TMI accident, it is appropriate to assess the ramifications of that event and subsequent ones, together with the future direction of nuclear power.
By now, the facts which led to the most serious nuclear power accident in U.S. history are clear. A pump controlling coolant flow at the TMI plant failed, leading to the automatic opening of a pressure-relief valve which flooded the Unit 2 reactor and, eventually, the entire containment area. Human error added to the crisis when a technician reacted to contradictory water-level readings by increasing the flow, a mistake which was not corrected for some 80 minutes.
The temporary loss of reactor coolant led to a partial meltdown of the Unit 2 reactor. There is evidence that a buildup of hydrogen gas caused a small explosion in the Unit 2 containment area, although a much-more-destructive discharge was avoided. Due to the uncertainty at various points in the crisis, as many as 140,000 people within a 20-mile radius of the TMI plant were evacuated, though most returned within three weeks.
Although the Unit 1 reactor at the plant was undamaged, the entire plant ceased operation for six years after the accident. TMI's Unit 2 reactor has been decommissioned and is permanently shut down, with most radioactive waste having been removed to another site for storage.
Certainly, the cost to the nuclear power industry as a result of TMI debacle was devastating. First, public confidence in nuclear power as a safe method of generating electricity significantly declined in the 1980s, to which the 1986 Chernobyl nuclear disaster in the Soviet Union also contributed.
Anecdotal evidence of adverse health effects from the TMI accident includes increases in infant mortality, certain cancer rates and leukemia in the vicinity of the plant.
Second, although U.S. nuclear power output increased threefold from 1979 until 2013, not one nuclear power plant was constructed or came online during that span. Third, the financial cost of the TMI accident must be recognized.
Cleanup of the Unit 2 reactor began immediately after the 1979 accident and lasted through 1993 at a cost of $1 billion. Additionally, the TMI plant operator and its insurance company paid out a total of $100 million in compensation and settlements for health claims, evacuation expenses, and lost business income, although a separate $25 million class-action suit was unsuccessful in the courts. The TMI plant operator likewise paid a fine for falsifying records of a previous safety visit.
Following the TMI accident, a number of improvements and safety checks were put in place, starting with technician training and simplification of control-room design. Still, there were seven serious nuclear power plant accidents in the U.S. between 1985 and 2010.
The Nuclear Regulatory Commission, the federal independent agency with regulates civilian nuclear-power industry, ordered reviews of all American nuclear plants following the Chernobyl disaster in1986, after the terrorist attacks of Sept. 11, 2001, and after the devastating Fukushima nuclear plant catastrophe in Japan in 2011.
Partly due to these measures, the nuclear power industry has experienced a renaissance over the last few years. For example, construction of new nuclear plants resumed in 2013, with five new plants scheduled to be online by 2020.
Two ongoing issues with nuclear power - which accounts for 19 percent of electricity used in the United States - are evacuation plans in case of an accident and storage of radioactive waste emanating from nuclear power plants. While most plans for evacuation are at least feasible, one that was not was the Shoreham nuclear power plant on Long Island. Fully 10 years into construction of that plant, county government rejected the evacuation plan as not possible.
It took another six years to close the plant, sell it, and decommission it, with the $6 billion cost passed on to electricity customers. That fi-asco convinced plant owners of the importance of a suitable evacuation plan in case of emergency.
Transport and storage of spent nuclear fuel and other residual waste of nuclear power is of concern, as well. Though most U.S. nuclear power plants are in the eastern part of the country, the storage facilities are in the western section, meaning that road and rail transport of material is necessary. Ensuring that such dangerous cargo reaches its destination and is safely stored is a permanent obligation of the nuclear power industry, one that is gaining more scrutiny as some western states create and compete for storage.
Given the current fixation with fracking to extract natural gas, attention to nuclear power has somewhat diminished. However, until the United States develops a comprehensive national energy policy, nuclear power will continue to be a vital source of electricity, and thus, power for millions of citizens.
Even with the lessons learned from the events of late March 1979, Americans should hope that real life will not mimic Hollywood again as it did when the TMI crisis occurred less than two weeks after the release of "The China Syndrome," a movie about a fictional nuclear power accident.
Dr. Samuel B. Hoff is George Washington Distinguished Professor of History and Political Science and Law Studies Director at Delaware State University. A native of Pennsylvania, he was a 21-year-old senior in college when the Three Mile Island accident occurred in March 1979 and was a Ph. D. student at SUNY-Stony Brook on Long Island during the controversy over the fate of the Shoreham nuclear power facility.
]]></text></news-item>