<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW9-MMC1-JD6S-R1NY"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Florida must decide on its energy issues; Editorial</title><source>The Key West Citizen (Florida)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Florida has an uneasy relationship with energy issues. As a state whose economy rests largely on tourism and agriculture, Florida's economic welfare depends on its white beaches and its abundant supply of freshwater. That's why, thanks to pressure from Florida, there is no drilling in federal waters off the Panhandle or the state's west coast. That's why the state bans drilling in state waters.
Though it appears to have significant energy resources offshore and on land, Florida ranks only 30th nationally in total energy produced.
Yet Florida continues to be a major consumer of carbon-based fuels. According to the U.S. Energy Information Administration, which compiles energy statistics and analysis, Florida ranks fifth nationally in natural gas consumption, fourth in petroleum consumption and third in retail electricity sales. Translation: We want our air conditioners running and our highways full of tourists who drive or fly to our state. The price of fuel has been shown to affect our outlook. When gas prices were climbing and "drill, baby, drill" was a national phrase, there were serious efforts to lift Florida's offshore drilling ban. The BP oil spill cooled those intentions, but only briefly. An effort by then-Gov. Charlie Crist to add a constitutional amendment banning drilling went nowhere, and a year later, polls found Floridians again leaning toward offshore drilling.
Which now brings us to fracking. Hydraulic fracturing, or fracking, is a method of getting natural gas and oil from rock deposits. Water and chemicals are forced into the formations, with the gas and oil then squeezed out.
Depending on your point of view, and maybe where you live, fracking is a miracle that helps us lower our energy costs and clean our air by increasing the availability of natural gas. Or it's a nightmare that can forever poison groundwater. In Southwest Florida, there are limestone deposits that may lend themselves to fracking. So when state Rep. Ray Rodrigues, R-Estero, introduced two bills this session related to fracking - H.B. 71, which would set requirements for drillers to list the chemicals they are using, and H.B. 157, which would offer exemptions for "trade secrets" - there was an uproar.
Rodrigues is pessimistic that H.B. 71 will pass, blaming partisan politics in an election year. But it's worth paying attention anyway; the bill passed easily in the House last year and surely will be back next year.
Some opponents say it would open the door to drilling in Florida. Some proponents say this is an honest attempt to regulate fracking, which is right now is unregulated. Neither is entirely correct.
There already are 162 wells operating in Florida, most in the southern part of the state. And the state Department of Environmental Protection says fracking definitely is not unregulated. It's covered in state rules as a "workover operation," and as such would have to undergo review and conform to safety and environmental standards.
H.B. 157, offering exemptions for trade secrets, is a bad idea. The Consumer Energy Alliance, which advocates an "all of the above" strategy on energy diversity, supports both bills. Still, CEA President David Holt, in a meeting with the Democrat last week, acknowledged that the national trend seems to be toward full disclosure.
So, what does this all mean? It means Floridians need to get busy.
They need to become informed on fracking and drilling. It's not enough to just say no. Floridians need to know the benefits - to the state's economy and to energy independence -as well as the dangers. They need to pressure lawmakers to support alternative energy. For example, a bill backed by Agriculture Secretary Adam Putnam that would give a tax exemption for renewable energy devices on commercial buildings is being blocked in the house. State Rep. Ritch Workman, R-Melbourne, says he is tired of subsidizing solar power.
They need to realize that they can't continue to reap the benefits of advances in carbon-fuel production - cheap energy to heat and cool our homes, fuel to bring our tourists here by car and plane, fertilizers for our all-important agriculture - while refusing to contribute somehow.
In the end, Floridians need to decide whether they want to help our nation by being an energy producer or by being a leader in conservation and alternative energy.
- Tallahassee Democrat
]]></text></news-item>