<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW9-7GX1-DXMP-K01R"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>CVC to conduct inquiry against Pune's Divisional Commissioner</title><source>Money Life</source><author>Vinita Deshmukh</author><text><![CDATA[RTI activist Vijay Kumbhar, who unearthed Prabhakar Deshmukh's land scam and acquisition of wealth in gross violation of service rules, filed a complaint to CVC, which will now conduct an inquiryOver and above the 300 acre agricultural land scam in Jambhe village of Satara district of Pune's Divisional Commissioner Prabhakar Deshmukh,details of which are here (http://www.moneylife.in/article/pune-div-commissioner-prabhakar-deshmukhs-land-scam-exposed/36456.html), owns several properties in his family's name. Right to Information (RTI) activist Vijay Kumbhar unearthed other properties of Deshmukh in the name of his wife and other family members. The case of owning such assets is in gross violation of All India Services (Conduct) Rules. A formal complaint was sent to the Central Vigilance Commission (CVC) Delhi last fortnight. The CVC has acknowledged the complaint that would lead to investigation in this matter against Deshmukh.
In his complaint to the CVC, Kumbhar has alleged "corruption and favouritism", stating that Prabhakar Deshmukh (IAS), presently Divisional Commissioner of Pune, Maharashtra, "is a very influential officer in Maharashtra. In his entire tenure, he has hardly been posted out of Pune Division and since last more than ten years he has been posted in Pune only". Kumbhar, who rigorously used Section 4 to bring out the scandal, says he has sent "substantial evidence" against Deshmukh. His complaint reads thus:"Although there are several allegations against Mr Prabhakar Deshmukh, I am citing only those cases for which there is concrete documentary evidence. There is violation of All India Services (Conduct) Rules especially Sections 9, 11, 13, 14 and 16, Maharashtra Agriculture Land Ceiling Act and the nature of these acts is unbecoming of an IAS Officer. All details of Jambhe land scam here* Mrs Anuradha Deshmukh, wife of Mr Prabhakar Deshmukh in October 2006, purchased a plot in Mundhwa area of Pune admeasuring 593 Sq. m. from a real estate management company named Abhay Property Management Pvt Ltd, at a cost of Rs4.75 lakh, almost 75% less than the ready reckoner cost, which was Rs16.04 lakh. Normally, such transactions are always at prices that are more than the ready reckoner price. Mrs Anuradha Deshmukh signed an agreement regarding the property for a project floated as Eastern Ranges by Phadnis Properties. The cost of the above-mentioned property escalated to Rs60.28 lakh from Rs4.75 lakh. The ready reckoner price had come to Rs41.44 lakh. Mrs Phadnis has been signing other documents in the name of Phadnis Properties. This is evident because she also had a development agreement with Phadnis Properties.
* Mrs Deshmukh has purchased agriculture land at Wakhari in Daund Tehsil of Pune district. Here too, she purchased a property of which ready reckoner rate was Rs36.40 lakh by paying just Rs12.26 lakh to poor farmers
* In 2006, Mrs Deshmukh's father purchased three acres of agricultural land for a mere Rs8 lakh. The father then generously gifted this land to Mrs Deshmukh. On the setting up of the Integrated Township Project, Mrs Deshmukh sold this plot at an unknown price. However, the cost of this land shown in the Immovable Property Return (IPR) of Mr Deshmukh is Rs95 lakh.
* Mr Deshmukh himself, wife Anuradha, son Mayuraj and daughter Harshada purchased land at Nanded Township in Pune city and here also a huge integrated township has come up and all purchasers have signed joint venture agreement with the developer.
* One Sindhu Naik-Nimbalkar gifted two plots at Akluj in Solapur district in September 2010 admeasuring 311.40 sq. m. and 290.4 sq. m. (In IPR only one plot is shown) to Mr Deshmukh's son Mayuraj and in April 2011, he sold these plots for Rs35 lakh.
* Mr. Deshmukh's family has floated four companies. None finds a mention in his IPR. These companies are (a) Ornate Graphics Private Limited, 11, Pushpanjali Apts., 20/100 Gidney Park, Salisbury Park, Pune (b) Kernel Ornate Private Limited, 11, Pushpanjali Apts., 20/100 Gidney Park, Salisbury Park, Pune (c) Dream Social Foundation, Sadamangal Co-op Hsg society, S. no. 103, flat no 10, bldg no 3, Shastri Nagar, Yerawada. One of these companies has purchased about 5,000 sq. ft. commercial office in Magarpatta city, a huge and prime township in Pune. Obviously, this is not shown in IPR of Mr Deshmukh
* Mrs Deshmukh is director in a company named Subodh Industries Private Ltd, 11, Pushpanjali Apts., 20/100 Gidney Park, Salisbury Park, Pune since 2004. This Company possesses many immovable properties. This too is not mentioned in IPR of Mr Deshmukh
* Many companies are registered at 11, Pushpanjali Apts., 20/100 Gidney Park, Salisbury Park, Pune. In some of these companies relatives of either Mrs Deshmukh or Mr Deshmukh's are directors. Moreover most of the directors of these companies have purchased huge immovable properties in prime locations of Pune.
* In Ornate Graphics Pvt Ltd, there was one director named Sangram Zunjarrao Deshmukh. This gentleman is also a director in Anupriya Sugar Pvt Ltd. In Anupriya Sugar, there is another Director Sangram Khanajirao Jadhav. Mr Jadhav is the one who has sold land in Nanded city to Prabhakar Deshmukh.Kumbhar says, "This is just the tip of the iceberg. If you investigate the matter in totality, you will find more and more such misdeeds. I have already lodged complaint with Government of Maharashtra. MP Kirit Somaiya has lodged a complaint with Anti Corruption Bureau (ACB) of Maharashtra. It is also said that ACB has asked sanction for public inquiry in this case. However, the Government of Maharashtra has not given such permission. Please investigate the matter and take appropriate action as per law as soon as possible."To add to this, Ajit Pawar, the deputy chief minister of Maharashtra, had gone on public record stating that after hearing a few conversations on phone (phone tapping?), he has concluded that all the accusations are invalid
]]></text></news-item>