<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW9-M3G1-JDKC-R4KJ"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Pakistan: Two pharmaceutical companies' stocks seized</title><source>Right Vision News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ISLAMABAD, April 2 -- Federal Inspector of Drugs on Tuesday seized
stocks of all those products of two pharmaceutical companies which they were
selling on prices more than the prices fixed by the federal government.
According to official sources, on the direction of Minister of State
for National Health Services, Regulations and Coordination, Saira Afzal Tarar, Federal Inspector raided the warehouses of two Islamabad based pharmaceutical companies namely M/s Wislon's Pharmaceuticals, Islamabad and M/s Scottmann Pharmaceuticals, Islamabad.
During the inspection, the companies were found overcharging the
prices of few drugs. Further legal action will be taken under the Drugs Act, 1976 and rules framed there under, they added.
Earlier, on the directives of the Prime Minister, Minister for
National Health Services, Regulations and Coordination Saira Afzal Tarar took strict notice of reports of unilateral and illegal price hike by certain pharmaceutical companies.
The minister, in an emergency meeting here, directed that stern
action be taken against violators of the government's pricing regime."There
will be zero tolerance against those deceiving the government and hurting
public interest," she warned.
She said a three-member committee headed by Chief Executive Officer
of Drug Regulatory Authority of Pakistan (DRAP), has been constituted to monitor the market and report any violation of the pricing regime.
"Strict action under the law will be taken against companies found
violating the law and overpricing", she said.
The minister said some companies after resorting to illegal price
hike sought restraining orders from the court to avoid action by DRAP.
She said 18 drug companies had enhanced the prices illegally in
the year 2012-2013 and DRAP took legal action against them. The companies
approached the Sindh High Court, which granted them stay.
DRAP is pursuing the case vigorously in the Supreme Court to get
the stay order vacated, she added.
On September 17, 2013, the DRAP filed an application in the Supreme
Court against all companies, who have increased prices without approval of the federal government and after obtaining stay orders from various courts,
mostly from the Sindh High Court.
The Supreme Court in hearing of the case of March 20, fixed case
of un-authorized price increase by the pharmaceutical companies for 3rd
week of April and directed DRAP to submit a comprehensive report on the
matter. The court further directed to issue notices to all such companies
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Right Vision News. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>