<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW9-81G1-DXH2-6364"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>GM CEO Mary Barra Apologizes for Ignition Switch Defect; Senate Subcommittee Holds Hearing on Caterpillar's Tax Strategy; Facebook CEO Reaps Slow Gain From Stock, Options in 2013</title><source>Imus Simulcast</source><author>Don Imus, Lori Rothman, Connell McShane, Warner Wolf, Dagen McDowell, Bernard McGuirk, Maria Molina, Lou Rufino, Rob Bartlett, Tony Powell, Tom `Bigfoot' Bowman, Carley Shimkus, Michael Gunzelman</author><text><![CDATA[DON IMUS, HOST, "IMUS IN THE MORNING": This is the IMUS IN THE MORNING program on the FOX Business Network. Now, here's Lori Rothman.
LORI ROTHMAN, FOX BUSINESS ANCHOR: And a very good morning, everyone. Our top story, the CEO of General Motors is apologizing for that ignition switch defect that's been linked to at least a dozen deaths leading to the massive recall. Mary Barra is due to testify today before a House Subcommittee about the problem and she's expected to face tough questions from lawmakers on why GM waited more than a decade to recall vehicles due to faulty switches and problems with air bags and brake parts. Federal regulators will also be on the hot set.
According to preliminary findings, Congressional investigators found the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration twice failed to investigate complaints and crash reports about GM cars. Bar is also due to testify before the Senate tomorrow which is holding its own hearing on the matter. Late yesterday, GM announces recalling 1.3 million vehicles to fix the problem with the power steering. The auto maker is recalling a total now of more than 6.3 million vehicles.
Checking the markets following yesterday's rally, here in the U.S., futures are pointing to a higher open, ahead of the latest ISM report and auto sales figures.
Asia finished the day higher after a report showed a mixed picture for China's manufacturing sector. For details, there she is, business reporter Rachael Ruble in Beijing. Hi, Rachael.
RACHAEL RUBLE, BUSINESS REPORTER: Oh, hi Lori, as you said, Asian stocks were modestly higher today following the latest PMI data out of China and that strong lead-in from the U.S. Beijing's official Purchasing Managers Index rose slightly in March right in line with expectations and showing mild growth. However, separately HSBC's final reading was lower and showing a slow down. Now the mixed results didn't seem to weigh too heavily on the markets here as investors seems to be weighing on Beijing to make moves to stimulate the economy.
Shanghai closing up seven-tenths-of-one percent and Hong Kong rising a little over one percent. Now the Bank of Japan's quarterly look at business sentiment was worse than expected ahead of today's increasing the sales tax. Well, the Nikkei didn't take to kindly to those results as -- from a solid gain and pre-markets up futures to close out the session lower. That's going to do it from Beijing. I'm Rachael Ruble, Lori, back to you.
ROTHMAN: Great, Rachael. Thanks so much for that. Let's take a closer look now on what's moving the European markets with Craig Erlam, market analyst at Alpari in London. Craig, always great to see you. Markets higher this morning, carry-over what you say from the enthusiasm generally from Janet Yellen's most recent common on interest rates?
CRAIG ERLAM, ALPARI MARKET ANALYST: Yes, I think that's what really the key drive this morning, that's what is driving European markets higher, we also saw the majority impact on U.S. markets yesterday but U.S. futures are quarterly around 1/10th of a percent this point higher. So maybe a contributing to that as well. And we have also had some encouraging data in Europe this morning, we've had things like unemployment rate for the Eurozone falling to 11.9 percent. The unemployment rate is well in Germany, also falling a little bit as well. So, then it's a few things really feeding into the markets this morning and helping to drive European and U.S. future highs as well.
KELLY: 11.9 percent Eurozone unemployment is good news. I mean, I guess it's all in perspective right about where you're coming from. So, what is the expectation in terms of improvement in these labor figures over the time to come?
ERLAM: Well, listen, I think we have to view 11.9 percent really as a positive, especially when you take a look at the past few years where we've seen those persistent rises in the unemployment rate until it reached a 12.2 percent mark. In the last six months or so, we have seen it stabilize around that region and is gradually creeping lowest. So, as long as we've start continue to see it, gradually moving lower in any other direction, I think it's got to be view there's a positive that the only next question now is how the ECB going to respond?
KELLY: We shall see, it is a big week for that. Craig Erlam, market analyst at Alpari, thank you much.
ERLAM: Thank you.
KELLY: A Senate subcommittee back in the U.S. holding a hearing today on Caterpillar's tax strategy this after a report says, Caterpillar's avoided paying 2.4 billion in U.S. taxes since 2000 by shifting profits to an affiliate in where? Switzerland. The report also says Caterpillar paid accounting from price water house coopers $55 million to develop this tax strategy. Representatives from Caterpillar and the accounting firm are scheduled to testify.
And Apple and Samsung in federal court today in California for opening statements in their latest legal battle. Apple accuses Samsung of infringing on spy's patents on smart phones and tablets but Samsung claims Apple stole two of its ideas to use on iPhones and iPads. The two companies have been litigating around the world for nearly three years. If Apple prevails in this case, the cost of Samsung could reach $2 billion. And we like to track oil and gold prices for you. Oil is trading at $101 a barrel and gold is up $3.60 cents to 12.87 per ounce.
IMUS IN THE MORNING continues right now on FOX Business giving you the power to prosper.
ANNOUNCER: Ladies and gentlemen, IMUS IN THE MORNING.
IMUS: You know, the sports phrases that I use most, I believe during the '70s and maybe even the '80s was Yankees win, Mets lose. And I believe I have said that over the past 42 years and -- on the air hair. I bet I've said that more often than not. Yankees win, Nets lost, and of course the Mets, their general manager or somebody said well, we'll going to win 90 games this year. Well, they're still going win 90 because they didn't win yesterday and they blew it with two out in the ninth.
WARNER WOLF, SPORTSCASTER: Two outs in the ninth. And then two outs in the tenth. The Bullpen died. Forget the Bullpen, that's it, man.
IMUS: Yes. I did not watch a milli-second of it.
WOLF: No. They booed the mayor throughout the first pitch --
IMUS: Throughout the first pitch from in front of the mound.
MCSHANE: Yes, come on.
IMUS: That is really weak.
WOLF: Yes, lame. Oh, man!
IMUS: I have decided to -- that I went home yesterday and watched the Might Be Elvis on the program and I'm going to keep it.
CONNELL MCSHANE, FOX BUSINESS ANCHOR: Oh.
IMUS: Because it's good.
MCSHANE: Very nice.
IMUS: But you know who was the best, Trevor.
MCSHANE: Hey, Trevor.
IMUS: Now Trevor, he is not a television performer, he's a --
MCSHANE: Audio guy.
IMUS: He's an audio guy engineer. And he's a guitar player. He's an outstanding guitar player. But for him to be better than Dagen --
MCSHANE: Oh, here we go.
IMUS: And Tony who are seasoned performers, I mean, come on. And Rob was good.
(LAUGHTER)
MCSHANE: So, that's what it's about.
IMUS: So I'm going to keep Might Be Elvis because it was funny and entertaining except I'm changing the request song requirement now. The song requirement now is --
MCSHANE: Everybody listen in.
IMUS: The goal is to get something to find songs that we can put in the power rotation Lou, on the IMUS IN THE MORNING program, stuff we like. We discover stuff all the time, like years ago, Todd Snyder for example, and even Bob like the bowling for soup to deal or outside, I discovered Uncle Tupelo and get back to the key to my heart. I mean, so that's the goal.
MCSHANE: OK.
IMUS: And then, so, we'll do that. And one would hope that Dagen would come up with something better than these funeral dirges that she's been, so.
MCSHANE: There's no is no restrictions in other words.
IMUS: No, there's not.
MCSHANE: Could be on the charge.
IMUS: Could be the number one song in the country, pop song in the country, simply we're not playing that and if you pick that, you're suggesting that we should be playing it, so.
MCSHANE: Oh, OK.
IMUS: And then somebody asked, some make-up person asked Deirdre, she was on Hannity last night. How people like Nat and Trevor get on the program? How does that happen?
MCSHANE: All right, well, like.
IMUS: Or like Guns. Well, here is how it happens because if you talk to people around here, you find and I have found this forever, is that there are many talented people behind the cameras as they are in front.
MCSHANE: Absolutely.
IMUS: But most of the time they don't ever get a chance because nobody talks to them. You find out all kinds of stuff, like Guns. Guns was -- Warner had his foot on Guns, his neck and poor Guns, he wasn't going to get anything. Warner was keeping him down and so was the Levin and who rescued Guns on obscurity?
MICHAEL GUNZELMAN, SPORTSCASTER: -- did that.
IMUS: Why did I?
MCSHANE: I'm not sure.
IMUS: Well, because somebody said, can Guns fill in when Warner went somewhere.
BERNARD MCGUIRK, PROGRAM PRODUCER: I think that was me.
IMUS: Bernard McGuirk.
(LAUGHTER)
MCSHANE: I met a guy in --
IMUS: Let me tell you something else, you know how -- this is how this all started, how I recognized this. Back when I was at FAN, over in Queens, my brother God bless him, was up there on the Superstition Mountain, I remember I was going to take a dust buster up there to see if I can find him because I didn't know what was going on.
(LAUGHTER)
It's too much. Anyway, he came to visit me once, so he went to work with me in the morning and he was sitting in the studio with Bernard and Lou.
MCSHANE: Uh-hm.
IMUS: And he said, and after their show he said to me, he said, you ought to turn their mics on. Their mics in there for some reason.
MCSHANE: Right.
IMUS: He said, where their mics in there at the time, Lou?
MCSHANE: Yes, I'm sure there were mics in there, for extra guests?
IMUS: So Fred said, you had to turn their mics on. Said they'll scream about the stuff they said all morning.
MCSHANE: He was right about that.
IMUS: Now, look at them. Bernard is a huge star.
RUFINO: Oh my God, you can't even measure it.
IMUS: As is Lou.
MCGUIRK: Pull my car around.
IMUS: So that's how that happened.
(LAUGHTER)
Bernard McGuirk here, McGuirk, McGuirk. Ten minutes after the hour, so KT McFarland is coming up. We'll talk to her about --
The guy who found Guns.
(LAUGHTER)
MCSHANE: Bernard McGuirk, the guy who discovered Gunzelman.
IMUS: And then Hollywood and Vine with Imogen Lloyd Weber, Dagen McDowell and Michael Reidel, he's back and then we'll talk with Juan Williams. And Rob interviewed, what's his name?
MCSHANE: Russell Crow.
IMUS: Russell Crow.
MCSHANE: An exclusive interview.
IMUS: So, we'll have that coming up.
MCSHANE: Great.
IMUS: And well, Rob interviewed Russell Crow. Let's leave it at that.
MCSHANE: Yes. One-on-one.
IMUS: So, that will be coming up and Dice is here this morning as well, so.
MCSHANE: Yes good.
IMUS: Let's check into the green room and see how they are.
MCSHANE: All right.
IMUS: Oh, yes, there they are.
TONY POWELL, COMEDIAN: This is how we look.
ROB BARTLETT, PROGRAM PRODUCER: We're over here now. We used to be over there but we're over here now.
(LAUGHTER)
IMUS: Right.
BARTLETT: KT McFarland is here.
MCSHANE: She's over there.
IMUS: How is the booking going for that vintage, Tony?
POWELL: It's going well.
IMUS: OK.
POWELL: We could use some help but well.
IMUS: Tony is going to be appearing in Uncle Vinny's at Point Pleasant in New Jersey, is it this weekend?
POWELL: This weekend, Friday, Saturday.
IMUS: Two big nights.
POWELL: Uh-hm.
IMUS: OK. If you want tickets, you can call the Box Office at Uncle Vinny's in Point Pleasant. I could give you the number but there's no possible way you would write it down. Is there any other way to get tickets?
POWELL: I think that would be the best way. We'll show up at the door.
IMUS: Yes.
POWELL: I think it's 1-800-Uncle Vinny's, I don't know. This Uncle Vinny's, it's really easy to Google.
MCSHANE: It's a way to promote yourself well, Tony.
IMUS: Yes, Tony, the act is better than that. All right. Twelve minutes past the hour. Let's do some news and here with that is Connell McShane, good morning, Connell.
MCSHANE: Hey, good morning, I-man. We'll start with healthcare in the news this morning because seven million was this magic number we kept hearing that they had to get the seven million people signed up. And government officials are saying by the deadline last night, ObamaCare indeed was on track to get that. Seven million signed up and this despite a number of problems, though, reported throughout the day yesterday. Lisa Larsen running to some website issues and then stopped by a center that was set up in Chicago where applicants were being shown how to get on board with the new law.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
UNIDENTIFIED WOMAN: It's just one click. It's just not working.
UNIDENTIFIED WOMAN: So, what do I do?
UNIDENTIFIED WOMAN: Well, you have done what you've needed to do, which is, you have this process started on the day the deadline.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
MCSHANE: Long waits around the country, some people had to leave email addresses for people to get back to them later on but again the governments go to the White House celebrating this seven million number that they say that they have reached.
IMUS: It's actually cost us money at the Imus Ranch for Kids with Cancer because we have to give people off because they try to get an appointment to get their insurance and it's been slammed, and it's almost impossible. Plus, like with Edward and Gozola, who Edward worked at the ranch since -- in fact, Edward was part of the construction crew that built the ranch.
MCSHANE: Right.
IMUS: And there we hired him. And he's been there ever since. And their insurance is going to cost some $1,000 a month. I mean, that's a huge amount of money for anybody, but particularly for them.
MCSHANE: Right. I mean that was what we talked about initially. A lot of people have to pay a lot more.
IMUS: We pay half of it.
MCSHANE: Half of it, right.
IMUS: But we're a public foundation, I mean, come on. But this is just been a disaster, just on that level, on the ranch level, I'm trying to get everybody insured.
MCSHANE: A lot of small businesses and others going through the same --
IMUS: It wasn't the ranches in a fact.
MCSHANE: Essentially a small business. Right. So here is Governor Christie, meantime. Governor Chris Christie talking about a president --
IMUS: We didn't think you meant Governor Bob Christie.
MCSHANE: Right. Well, you know.
IMUS: How many other Governor Christies are there?
MCSHANE: I don't even have a respond, it could be the former sacramental king Doug Christie. I have no idea.
IMUS: That's a basketball player.
MCSHANE: Right.
IMUS: Governor Christie, then you say Chris Christie as though, we thought you meant someone else.
MCSHANE: It could be a basketball player --
IMUS: No, no, no, no, no.
MCSHANE: Look at concern Kevin Johnson, Bill Bradley.
IMUS: No Bill Bradley.
MCSHANE: You said Governor Christie.
IMUS: And then you said Chris Christie as though we were going to confuse that, I mean --
MCSHANE: It's Not Doug Christie, remember him be, a pretty good shooter --
RUFINO: A bench guy.
MCSHANE: He was a valuable asset on your club.
RUFINO: Defensive guy.
MCSHANE: So Governor Christie was talking about a presidential run on Megyn Kelly's FOX News show last night. And Kelly told Chris Christie that it, you know, seemed like he was a little closer to running this time around than he was in 2012. Here is how it went.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
GOV. CHRIS CHRISTIE (R), NEW JERSEY: Well, I think I'm older and more experienced and it is certainly something that I have said to everybody that I'll consider.
MEGYN KELLY, FOX NEWS HOST: But you've had too much baggage.
CHRISTIE: No.
KELLY: You had so little baggage last time. This time was different.
CHRISTIE: I'm older. And you know, what? If you don't have baggage they'll create baggage for you. That's politics in America today. That's the way it goes. In the end, you know what people -- people don't judge you on that kind of stuff. People look into your eyes and they try to decide what's in here. And that's how they vote. They vote for what they believe is in your heart.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
MCSHANE: Chris Christie, there you go. So in terms of the investigation to the bridge scandal, the latest development there, the state legislative committee continues to investigate plans to subpoena documents from the internal investigation that was released the other day by Christie's lawyer. They want to see some of those documents.
MCGUIRK: It is.
IMUS: Speaking of people behind the scenes whenever Nat is gone --
MCSHANE: As he is today.
IMUS: I'm stuck with either Nick.
MCSHANE: Nick, terrific job.
IMUS: No, he doesn't do a terrific job.
MCSHANE: Oh, he doesn't.
IMUS: No, because my headphone, my ear monitors now are pulling on my, every time I turn my head and Nat is able to somehow fix that so that doesn't happen.
MCSHANE: He's a genius, no doubt about it.
DAGEN MCDOWELL, FOX BUSINESS HOST: He was doing great though, setting up that ring of fire around you with the space heater.
MCSHANE: Really, it's unbelievable.
IMUS: Ring of fire.
MCDOWELL: Yes, ring of fire. You will spontaneously combust, as you enter the ring of fire, it is so hot where you sit. He's doing a good job, though.
IMUS: Well, the thing is that it's cold in the studio because I don't know why it is. So then I have a space heater on either side of me because I'm cold. Well, not all the time but --
MCSHANE: Most of it.
IMUS: But Nick, is there something we can do because every time I turn my head for my ear monitors not to pull out of my ears.
MCSHANE: Nick, he'll have you hung by those ear monitors by the end of the day probably.
IMUS: Probably not.
MCSHANE: Yes.
IMUS: It doesn't make any difference.
MCSHANE: No, it doesn't.
IMUS: Seventeen after the hour. Let's do business news sponsored by -- I have no idea. I probably should check, while I'm checking, here is Dagen McDowell. Good morning, Dagen.
MCDOWELL: Good morning, sir. The Dow was up 134 pounds yesterday wrapping up the first quarter. Futures are higher this morning but the blue chips are still down so far this year. And today, General Motors CEO Mary Barra will testify in front of a House Subcommittee over that faulty ignition switch recall. 2 p.m. Eastern Time is the hearing. She says --
MCSHANE: Well, they're going to testify -- she has to testify on why GM knew that these things were faulty and it was killing people and then didn't do anything about it?
MCDOWELL: Well, she says in recent testimony, I can't tell you why it took years for a safety defect to be announced.
IMUS: And we're sorry all of those people died in our stupid cars that we knew there was something wrong with and did nothing about.
MCDOWELL: And speaking of that, she privately met with 22 family members of those killed who have come to Washington for that hearing.
IMUS: Hope she had a checkbook with her.
MCDOWELL: Well, the lawsuits are piling up separately. GM has again recalled a million and a half vehicles over a power steering defect. There you go.
IMUS: Michael Lewis, the guy who wrote money ball, blind slide, I mean, it's a wonderful writer, even better than that. And a very nice guy, too. Good interview and all that. He's written a new book called the flash boys. There was a feature on "60 Minutes" about it. He himself has written, perhaps, as an excerpt in the "New York Times" magazine and there's a review of the book, which I have already read in this morning's "New York Times." So, it makes they feel as though I should read it. Should I Dagen or Connell?
MCDOWELL: Yes.
MCSHANE: I've been always been a big fan of his stuff. He gets a lot of criticism all the time from people inside the industries he examines.
IMUS: Well, of course.
MCSHANE: And that's this case this time but he's a great writer. No doubt.
IMUS: So it's a brilliant approach to all of this and how did he get wind of this, I wonder?
MCSHANE: You know, I was thinking that this morning. I don't know. But he clearly found -- because he finds a great story but then great characters, whether it's the blindside or money ball.
IMUS: But how did he find out that they were doing this on Wall Street?
MCSHANE: I wouldn't be surprised if the Canadian guy contacted him. They don't say in the "60 Minutes" piece, I watched online last night but I would not be surprised if that's the Canadian guy who exposed all of this said, how do I get it out there and he went to Michael Lewis.
MCDOWELL: Well, because they've also set up their own exchange so they would be looking for publicity for that as well.
MCSHANE: Right. And he has a lot of connections in the industry and yes, Bernie is right, somebody connected the two of them. He said, yes, he wants to talk to Lewis.
IMUS: Seemed like something that Matt Taibbi have to find out, doesn't it?
MCGUIRK: A lot of people. Yes. You think about it.
IMUS: Well, no, no. Not a lot of people who has written more extensively about the underbelly of Wall Street than Matt Taibbi.
MCGUIRK: Yes. But this is really the -- inside stuff, Taibbi's pretty much on the superficial companies like Goldman Sachs ripping people off but this is high tech rip-off stuff.
IMUS: It was brilliant, just uncovering it.
MCGUIRK: Yes.
IMUS: And it was brilliant trying to figure it out. My question about -- well, I'm sorry.
MCGUIRK: The Canadian and the Irish do pretty much figured it all out?
IMUS: And my question about trying to read it is, will I be able to understand it.
MCSHANE: You will if Lewis runs it.
MCDOWELL: Yes. Exactly.
MCSHANE: And that's always been the key for him, you know?
IMUS: He's really pretty good. I'll tell you what else I started to read, Wyatt got a copy of it, Seth McFarland, family guy and all of that, he's written a western novel called a million ways to die in the west.
MCSHANE: Yes.
IMUS: That's so stupid funny that I guess it's been out about a month or so. It hasn't done anything really but it's a scream.
MCSHANE: It's right up your alley.
IMUS: Well, I mean, it's dumb funny but he's funny.
MCSHANE: No, he's hilarious.
IMUS: I mean, you know, everybody thinks they can write a novel but it's not bad but it may be laugh out loud.
MCSHANE: There you go.
IMUS: That Wyatt, he ordered two books, he ordered that and a biography of Axel Rose for some reason.
MCSHANE: Oh, well --
IMUS: He just finished Kirk Monogan's (ph) hocus focus. The Monogan's fan. And so, these books arrived from Amazon yesterday and I just thought I would look at this Seth McFarland book and then now I can't get it back. Going on some funny to read, but I mean, the opening deal is that these two guys that will have a gun fight at high noon out in the middle of the street, you know?
MCSHANE: Right.
IMUS: A western in the 1880s. One of the guys is admittedly a coward and the other is a gunslinger, you know? So the one guy shows up late, the gunslinger, he gets there at 12:15.
MCSHANE: Oh, man. So much for high noon.
IMUS: So the other guy, the coward, reprimand him for being late. He said, you know? I mean, it's just -- talking about it, it's not going to help it but it's really funny. Oh man, it's a scream, so. It's 22 after the hour and particularly if you're raised in the west and on a cattle ranch as I was, that stuff just seems funny.
MCSHANE: Uh-hm.
IMUS: Anyway, time for sports. We're getting way behind here, Warner. We don't have a lot of time because we have a lot of stuff to talk to KT McFarland about.
MCGUIRK: Oh, that's important.
IMUS: And going on about Seth McFarland and Michael Lewis, well, that's just two books you ought to buy.
MCSHANE: Yes, Warner.
IMUS: So, you definitely should buy Seth McFarland's book. One million ways to die in the west it's called, and you should buy Michael Lewis. Lewis doesn't need any help but McFarland does, so do that.
Anyway, here with sports is Warner Wolf sponsored by Peerless Boilers. Good morning, Warner.
IMUS: Good morning, I-man. Baseball 13 games yesterday including a full house, 42,000 at City Field, the Nats with one in the ninth with two outs, four in the tenth with two outs and beat the Mets and just the Met Bullpen never showed up and the Nats win at nine to seven. Here was the big hit, the tenth inning call by Charlie Slowes, WJFK Washington.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
CHARLIE SLOWES, BROADCASTER: Pitches and Rendone smacks one high in the air to deep field, Erick Young back to the warning track, to the wall, it carries on out, a three-run homer for Anthony Rendone. It busted it open. Anthony Rendone sets Mets fans to the exits.
(LAUGHTER)
WOLF: Oh, man! The Pirates beat the Cubs.
IMUS: Color guy blurt or some over -- there.
MCSHANE: Yes, moron.
IMUS: God, they're awful. Why you insist on playing these local announcements? I have no idea.
WOLF: Oh, because --
MCSHANE: Oh, man!
WOLF: Yes. We were looking for it.
MCSHANE: No, they only gave us the met highlights. It's a losing game, come on.
(LAUGHTER)
IMUS: Come on. OK, we're way behind.
WOLF: The Pirates beat the Cubs on Neil Walker's lead-off homer in the tenth. Is that a walker-off homer and by the way, in this game, a safe call on the pick-off attempt by the Cubs and the tenth was reversed to an out with videotaped replay taking two and a half minutes.
MCSHANE: OK.
WOLF: The Brewers beat the Braves disgrace left fielder Ryan Fraud after returning from a 65 game suspension and lying about the urine tester received the standing O from the walking fans. Wait until he hits the road. And --
IMUS: Doesn't the guy deserve a second chance or this guy doesn't?
RUFINO: Not what he did to the tester.
WOLF: No, that was disgraceful. It really was.
IMUS: This guy is a creep.
RUFINO: No, he's not a good guy.
IMUS: OK.
WOLF: And finally, I-man, the --
IMUS: Lou says he's not a good guy. And Warner, he's not a good guy.
WOLF: No.
IMUS: You know, what about -- we don't have any time. Didn't you understand? We have no time.
WOLF: OK.
IMUS: So I mean, just give me the scores. Important stores and then we'll move on.
WOLF: All right. Knicks win and the Hawks win.
IMUS: OK, thank you very much.
WOLF: Yes.
IMUS: Bernie, what's coming up in the briefing?
MCGUIRK: Colbert responding to Ching Chong ding dong for Orientals or whatever.
IMUS: OK. Twenty six after the hour here on the IMUS IN THE MORNING program.
KT McFarland already going to be late for her. We're already going to be late.
No time to do anything. Because there are too many stupid e-fing commercials.
(MUSIC PLAYING)
ANNOUNCER: IMUS IN THE MORNING.
MCSHANE: Good morning, everyone. Checking the markets following yesterday's rally looks like we could see an extension of buying once regular session gets underway here in the U.S. Futures are pointing to a higher open ahead of the latest ISM report and auto sales figures. Speaking of those auto sales, we will get those March numbers today.
Kelley Blue Book is a looking for a two percent increase from a year ago to a seasonally adjusted annual rate of 15.7 million. So, some good news here. The damage done to the industry by that bad winter weather likely over. Now Chrysler is expected to lead the pack with an increase of 11.1 percent according to Edmunds. The only major brand predicted to have a double digit gain. Sales at Ford expected to rise 1.6 percent while the estimate for GM sales is for only an increase of one-half-of-one-percent.
Here is a look at oil and gold prices this morning. Crude oil is trading at $101 a barrel and gold is a little change at $1285 an ounce.
IMUS IN THE MORNING continues right now on FOX Business giving you the power to prosper.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
IMUS: So, you didn't know I called Bigfoot just Foot.
DEIRDRE IMUS, WIFE OF DON IMUS: I couldn't stop laughing, I was crying. You reduced it where you're saving your breath because you just call him Foot.
IMUS: Yes.
DEIRDRE IMUS: I mean, I couldn't believe it. I mean, that's crazy. It's so crazy it's hilarious.
IMUS: It's not that funny.
DEIRDRE IMUS: Yes, it is. It is hilarious. I have to come up with one for you Lis.
LIS WIEHL, FOX NEWS LEGAL ANALYST: You can't shorten my name anymore than it already is.
IMUS: What about cheap skate.
(LAUGHTER)
WIEHL: This is just not right.
DEIRDRE IMUS: How about just skate?
IMUS: How about what?
DEIRDRE IMUS: Skate. You can't say the whole world anyway.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
IMUS: All right. It is 32 past the hour and way behind already KT McFarland is coming up. And I mean, I don't know how we do this. So, anyway, this portion of the IMUS IN THE MORNING program sponsored by Cars for Kids. That's cars with a k, donate your car. Well, they'll sell them and they'll probably give the money to the children, we would hope.
MCSHANE: Let's hope.
IMUS: This portion of the program is sponsored by the Hackensack University Medical Center, a place where medicine meets innovation. It's time now for a Bernie briefing and that sponsored by MyPillow, go to MyPillow.com, type in the code word Imus and get a bunch of stuff off. Good morning, Mr. McGuirk.
MCGUIRK: Good morning, Mr. Imus. We'll get to Stephen Colbert later because we're so late boss, because let's go to Jon Stewart talking about Governor Christie and his report exonerating well, himself. Well, take a listen to Jon Stewart from last night.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
JON STEWART, STAND-UP COMEDIAN: By the way, Christie is not responsible for this Bridgegate, who is?
UNIDENTIFIED WOMAN: The internal review heaped all the blame for shutting down lanes on former Port Authority official David Wildstein and Christie's former top aide Bridget Ann Kelly.
UNIDENTIFIED MAN: They said, quote, "There is about Bridget Kelly, she seemed emotional, she was actually concern about she was perceived by the governor. A boyfriend had ended a relationship portraying Miss Kelly as duplicitous weeping frequently and dependent on men for approval and stability.
STEWART: That also explains very clearly why the official report was titled. That would be crazy, right?
(LAUGHTER)
(END VIDEO CLIP)
MCGUIRK: And here's your briefing, boss. You don't know now with you know.
IMUS: Thirty three after the hour, KT McFarland is next. She has Elvis on her musical Mount Rushmore.
(MUSIC PLAYING)
IMUS: I'm a man of the people.
ANNOUNCER: The bail-out program for boring radio. IMUS IN THE MORNING.
IMUS: This is the IMUS IN THE MORNING program on the FOX Business Network. Now, here is Lori Rothman.
Good morning, everybody. Facebook CEO Mark Zuckerberg got this, got $3.3 billion, a gain, a $3.3 billion gain last year by exercising stock options in the social networking company. Meanwhile, Facebook paid him about $650,000 in 2013, including a base salary of just a dollar so all of that down 67 percent from 2012, because Zuckerberg decline to participate in the bonus plans for the year. Now, in 2012, Zuckerberg received a total package about two million from Facebook. On to the weather, has spring finally sprung?
Here's meteorologist Maria Molina in the FOX Business Weather Center. Hi, Maria.
MARIA MOLINA, METEOROLOGIST: Hi, good morning, Lori. And hello everyone. Temperatures warming up out there across the eastern half of the country. We're going to be in the upper 50s in New York City, middle 60s in Cleveland, and wide-spread high temperatures into the 70s across parts of the southeast. There will be some issue though with these warm temperatures because we'll going to start to see the severe weather risk ramping up farther off towards the west across the center of the country.
Today, cities like Abel in Kansas City could be looking at severe weather but as we head into Wednesday and also on Thursday, that severe weather risk does expand and we are looking at the risk for large hail, isolated tornadoes and even some damaging wind gusts from some of these thunderstorms today. So, if you live out here, have a way to get those warnings over the next several days. Lori, back to you.
ROTHMAN: Thank you, Maria. Futures are pointing to a higher open. Let's get you back now to IMUS IN THE MORNING continuing right now on the FOX Business Network, giving you the power to prosper.
IMUS: All right. It is 21 until the hour here on the IMUS IN THE MORNING program. KT McFarland who is a frequent guest on this program and a foreign affairs expert working in the State Department.
KT MCFARLAND, FOX NEWS NATIONAL SECURITY ANALYST: Never the State Department, Pentagon White House.
IMUS: She's only been here about 50 times. You think I would know by now. Anyway, good morning, Miss McFarland.
MCFARLAND: Good morning. Happy April Fools' Day.
IMUS: I guess, yes. Here is her Musical Mount Rushmore, it was just, I don't know, Louis Armstrong, if you're going to put a -- player on, put -- song. That's one.
MCSHANE: Here we go.
IMUS: Then Frank Sinatra, Elvis and Bob Dylan, well, I can live with those three.
MCFARLAND: Well, thank you very much for that compliment.
IMUS: But then Lou says to me, why do I ask people for their Musical Mount Rushmore and then argue with them about it? I don't know why I do. So do you want to talk about Ukraine?
MCFARLAND: Sure, whatever you would like to talk about.
IMUS: Well, I don't want to talk about that but I mean, that's on some people's minds. But the latest, at least in my head, here is the latest information that I think I have. Is that the Russians, that would be Putin are amenable to working at some sort of diplomatic arrangements, is that right?
MCFARLAND: Yes, and usually you get right to the key question, are they amenable to a diplomatic solution? I think they assume that Ukraine is now going to fall into their lap because of economic reasons. Yesterday, this weekend, the prime minister of Russia went to Crimea, you know, the new area they've annexed. And he's start handing out the goodies, he's, you know, raising pensions, he's cancelling loans. They're going to do a lot of good things for Ukraine and the rest of Ukraine is going to look and say, hmm, you know, we're not getting that good stuff. And six months from now, when I think the economic pain is pretty pronounced in Ukraine, they may look over at Russia. I think that's what Russia is assuming. But also they're going to have 33,000 troops on the border.
IMUS: What diplomatic solutions are they amenable to?
MCFARLAND: Well, you know, what is a diplomatic solution? They're not giving back Crimea. And everybody understands --
IMUS: We're not even trying.
MCFARLAND: We're not even trying. We talked about it a couple of weeks ago but, you know, we've put another red line, there are going to be serious consequences.
IMUS: Well, if you would ask, Secretary Kerry or the President, what's your goal here? What would they say?
MCFARLAND: Well, they probably throw up their hands.
IMUS: They don't know? Well, what is our goal?
MCFARLAND: Well, I think what our goal should be is to say that the Russians, you're not going to retake a lot of countries which have won their freedom the hard way, that all of these countries from the Baltics all the way down, would include, Georgia, Crimea, Moldova, and maybe even Poland, Hungary, Czech Republic and the Baltics. These guys had won their freedom the hard way. They want to be part of Europe and you're not going to reclaim them. And with the reason you're not going to reclaim them is not, because we're sending them in the marines. We're going to use economic power that we have and you are losing, and we're going to resolve the situation that way.
IMUS: But it's only going to be America's economic --
MCFARLAND: Yes.
IMUS: Not going to be Europe. Because Europe is not going to act in concert with this, are they?
MCFARLAND: You know, I think Europe is not in a position where they can act into a large extent because they're so dependent on Russian energy that it would be very difficult for them to do the kind of severe sanctions we might do but I don't think we will do.
IMUS: So how effective?
MCFARLAND: Not very.
IMUS: So what's to dissuade Russia?
MCFARLAND: You know, very little. What's to dissuade them is they certainly don't want to like move tanks and didn't have guerilla war fares in these places, and I think Putin has spent15 years on this plan. I went back and I look at this -- he talked about when Russia was on its knees, he talked about how to rebuild Russia and he said he use oil, used natural gas, get political dependency from Europe, be able to blackmail them, and build up the new Russia and that's what he has done for 15 years. He's where he wants to be right now and now is when he wants to reclaim a lot of the sort of the band of ethnic Russian states and ethnic Russians along Russia's border. I think he also is more ambitious, I think he would like to see Nato dissolve.
IMUS: You think he's trying to recreate the old Soviet Union?
MCFARLAND: Yes. But differently. Not in the sense of recreating like Russian troops are going to occupy I think recreating in the sense of political dominion over them. But I think he's even more ambitious in a lot of ways, that he would like sort of have a new relationship with China, new relationship with India and at the same time --
IMUS: United with China against us?
MCFARLAND: Economically, you know, China needs oil. Where will they going to get the oil? If they get the oil from Russia, there's Eastern Siberia, they would love that to have access to that oil. India needs oil. Russia has a lot of oil. Russia has a lot of natural gas. So there's a trade relationship that might take place.
IMUS: Why are we tougher with China?
MCFARLAND: Yes, I agree.
IMUS: I mean, I subscribe to the philosophy of don't laugh of Donald Trump because I think he's right about China. I think we have a tremendous economic influence over them, would buy so much from them, that they could ask for their money back because they're not given it to you, now what they're going to do about it. Nothing.
MCFARLAND: Nothing. And I would take it even a step further, which is the oil.
IMUS: And threaten them.
MCFARLAND: Well, suddenly threaten them. Yes, I would absolutely --
IMUS: Why don't we do that?
MCFARLAND: Well, I'm not going to explain the Obama foreign policy.
IMUS: Well, no, but why don't we think we don't do it. That's why you're here.
MCFARLAND: The Obama --
(CROSSTALK)
That's a good, thank you. I think this president doesn't see America's role in the world as the previous presidents have. He believes leading from behind, he believes in international cooperation, the international community which he talks about all the time.
IMUS: Right.
MCFARLAND: And I don't think he sees America's role as being, you know, leader of the free world in the sense that we have use it before. So, what you're seeing then is, when you lead from behind, there's a power vacuum up front and others are rushing to fill it.
IMUS: I'm not kind of, I am naive about these kinds of things and so I look at the administration and I look at the president and I don't think that -- I think he's wrong, but I don't think he's evil.
MCFARLAND: No, I don't think he's evil.
IMUS: And I think he just has an idea that is not write, that's not workable.
MCFARLAND: Yes. And you know, you've said it, that's just the perfect thing. He is committed to his idea what the world should be like. When he talks to Putin about, oh, you're so 19th century, you know, 21st century, countries don't invade each other. He has this world image that he's committed to, his people are committed to and they're not going to change it, no matter what the reality of the situation.
IMUS: I mean, he's entitled, the President to his own policy and his own opinions about all of these, but probably not at the expense of diminishing the stature of American in the eyes of the world.
MCFARLAND: Absolutely.
IMUS: Both practically and even philosophically.
MCFARLAND: Yes. I completely agree. His role is to do what President has always sounds which is to promote America's best interest. He's not the world's best interest. He is the President of the United States, not the president of the world.
IMUS: And I would suspect if one were to ask him, and I believe he is interested in promoting the strength of the United States, and thinks he has a better idea of doing it but it's not working and you would think, he's probably a smart guy, that somebody would be able to reason with him and say, look, what has happened here and it's not working here. And I'm not one of those people who think Putin has made a fool of him but was pretty close.
MCFARLAND: Yes.
IMUS: Many look kind of goofy. Not goofy but --
MCFARLAND: Well, I mean, first I used to think it's a learning curve thing. I figured it out. And they haven't figured it out. I mean, to the point, even last week, the President is lecturing Putin about your best interests are, you don't understand that Russia should be best served. They say the same thing about Iran and Israel. No, other countries don't have to share your world. They have a different world view. A very different objectives. And I think if there is any one failure I point too, on the part of this President and this administration, it's their inability to sort of learn from their mistakes.
IMUS: Yes, digressing a little bit about North Korea and South Carolina, they're shooting at each other.
MCFARLAND: Yes.
IMUS: I thought that was yesterday we thought it was good. Well, he didn't think it was good. I did simply because if somebody gets killed, I mean --
MCFARLAND: Yes.
IMUS: Idiotic I am. Well, it just seems like it was, that's cool.
MCFARLAND: Well, they do it every Spring. It's like cherry blossoms in Washington. North Korean crisis. Now, the reason they do it is there's always in the spring, there's a U.S. South Korean military exercise.
IMUS: There's still 40,000 troops --
MCFARLAND: Yep, on the 39,000 in the border between North and South Korea --
IMUS: Forty thousand troops in Korea since I was in high school.
MCFARLAND: Yes.
IMUS: That's insane. Even before that.
MCFARLAND: Well, that's why a lot of people have encouraged the South Koreans to have a more stronger stand that maybe the United States wouldn't need to. Here's the problem with this, if North Korea does this every spring, because they're running out of food. They don't make enough food to feed their people and by spring, cupboards are bare, so they provoke a crisis, the world comes running, says, ho, ho, you guys have nuclear weapons, what can we do to stop you? And then we give them the food, we give them the aid and the crisis dissolves until next year.
IMUS: Yes. The haircut idea is a good idea. Would you think?
MCFARLAND: The haircut?
IMUS: Yes, little schmuck, what's his name?
MCFARLAND: Kim Jong-un.
IMUS: Yes, apparently he had ordered -- but he had ordered all of the college students, male college students in the country and perhaps all male --
MCFARLAND: I didn't hear this.
IMUS: -- to get his hair cut.
MCFARLAND: Oh, to get his haircut. Not to have their head shave. But to get the Kim Jong-un haircut.
IMUS: Right.
MCFARLAND: Well, I guess that's one way to be a fashion center.
IMUS: Well, as Bernard pointed out, it's fine if you have a fat little round face like his but if you're emaciated, North Koreans starving to death, with sunk in cheeks like one of these skulls hanging from a mirror of your 55 Chevy, it probably won't even look that great. So, anyway, thanks for coming in. It's always nice to see you.
MCFARLAND: It's always a joy.
IMUS: Eleven minutes now until the hour.
ANNOUNCER: IMUS IN THE MORNING.
IMUS: Good morning, everyone. Let's check the markets starting in Asia where markets finished the day mostly higher with the exception of the Nikkei. Data on China's manufacturing sector showed a mixed picture. The official Purchasing Managers Index for March came in higher than in February. However, the final HSBC PMI reading dame in at an eight-month low indicating contraction. Japan's Nikkei was lower after the Bank of Japan's Tankan survey showed, Japanese companies are cautious on the economic outlook as a three percentage point sales tax hike went into effect today.
Over to Europe, Eurozone reactivity slowed slightly this month and there was a pick-up in France and Italy, Spain and Ireland but slowdowns recorded in Germany and Austria. Still stocks are higher across the benchmarks there in Europe.
Here in the U.S., futures are pointing to a higher open in extension of the selling that wrap -- I'm sorry, buying that the Wall Street investors enjoyed yesterday, big rally yesterday. And Dow futures with a gain of 45 points signal that sentiment will extend into today's session. So investors are gearing up for earning season but the Wall Street Journal says, they should be ready for some disappointing results.
According to facts that profits among S&P 500 companies are expected to fall by six-tents-of-a-percent by the first quarter from last year. The Journal says that would be the first decline in our interest, the third quarter of 2012 and a sharper reversal from an estimated increase of more than four percent at the start of the year. The fact says, 93 companies have issued profit warnings, it's not a record. Commodities quickly, oil prices trading around $101 a barrel and the price of gold is up slightly to 1285 and 40 cents an ounce.
IMUS IN THE MORNING continues right now on FOX Business, giving you the power to prosper.
IMUS: All right. Coming up next hour, Hollywood and Vine with Michael Riedel, Imogen Lloyd Webber, and Dagen McDowell. And well, we have some good topics and I don't have time to get into what I want to attack Dagen for but I will in a minute. Five until the hour.
ANNOUNCER: IMUS, IMUS, IMUS IN THE MORNING.
IMUS: Is Bigfoot back today?
MCSHANE: He's got an e-mail.
TOM `BIGFOOT' BOWMAN, PROGRAM PRODUCER: Where else will I be?
IMUS: Well, you weren't hear yesterday.
BOWMAN: Where else would I be?
MCSHANE: He has a mouth full.
IMUS: His mouth is full.
MCSHANE: Holy God!
(LAUGHTER)
He's literally has a moth full.
MCGUIRK: It's funny.
IMUS: You know who did a pretty good job yesterday is that Jessica woman.
MCSHANE: All right, Jessica.
BOWMAN: He's great.
IMUS: But what happened to Jule (ph)?
BOWMAN: Jule went on to another job. He's working for Channel 5 here in New York during the mornings.
IMUS: Doing what?
BOWMAN: He's producing.
IMUS: Is that that show with --
MCSHANE: It's a great Kelly thing, right?
BOWMAN: Yes.
IMUS: You know, they do pretty well in the ratings, are you aware of that?
BOWMAN: I think they win in New York City.
IMUS: They do?
BOWMAN: Yes. I think they'd beat Good Morning America and Today Show in New York City.
MCSHANE: Now they have Jule, forget about him. Look out.
IMUS: Well, Jessica, where will we get her?
BOWMAN: She's been on the show for a couple of years now.
MCSHANE: Promoted.
BOWMAN: Yes.
IMUS: She was pretty good. I mean, she, well, she was pretty good. Let's leave it with that. Hey, Rob --
MCSHANE: Rob?
IMUS: Where's Rob?
MCSHANE: In the greenroom. Should be. Here he is.
BARTLETT: Sir?
IMUS: I looked at that -- thing, it's OK.
BARTLETT: OK. How can we make it better?
IMUS: You weren't good in it. You weren't, you know, the idea is funny but just -- you weren't good. Clumsy amateur is we have asking the questions which is not the point. It could have been a lot better. That's my only point. That's looking good.
]]></text></news-item>