<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW9-P0M1-F15H-C161"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Tulip Tandoori faces £40k bill after raid</title><source>Spalding Guardian</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Four workers from Spalding's Tulip Tandoori restaurant were detained for questions following a swoop by Home Office Immigration Enforcement and police.
The Pinchbeck Road business was handed a warning notice that it faces a civil penalty of up to £40,000 - £10,000 for each illegal worker - unless it proves appropriate right to work checks were carried out.
This is the second Home Office Enforcement raid on Indian/Bangladeshi restaurants in the district within a month - five illegal workers, all from Bangladesh, were found at Quadring's Curry Inn on March 6.
Home Office Immigration Enforcement and police officers visited Tulip Tandoori at 6.30pm on Thursday to question employees to check their rights to work in the UK.
Officers arrested four Bangladeshi men, aged between 22 and 30.
The Home Office says one man had overstayed his visa, two had entered the UK without leave and one student was suspected of working in breach of his visa conditions.
Yesterday one man was still detained and two were on immigration bail. The student received a police caution.
Alsion Spowage, assistant director of East Midlands Immigration Enforcement, said: "This is a warning to businesses which either deliberately employ people with no right to work or fail to carry out the legally required checks on their staff.
"We will catch up with you and you should expect to face heavy financial penalties.
"Illegal working is not victimless. It defrauds the taxpayer, undercuts honest employers and cheats legitimate job seekers out of employment opportunities.
"I would urge members of the public with information about suspected immigration abuse to get in touch."
The Curry Inn and Tulip Tandoori have continued trading following the raids.
Three men arrested at Quadring were taken to immigration detention pending their removal from the UK. Two others had outstanding immigration applications that did not entitle them to work in the UK, although they were entitled to reside here.
Following the Quadring raid, a Home Office Enforcement spokesman said: "We are happy to work with businesses to let them know what checks need to be done on staff, but those who choose to break the law will face heavy financial penalties."
l Home Office Immigration Enforcement says anyone with information on suspected immigration abuse can contact www.gov.uk/report-immigration-crime or call Crimestoppers, anonymously, on 0800 55511.
]]></text></news-item>