<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW9-V371-F11P-X42X"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Focus on Marikana bargaining</title><source>Daily News (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Bargaining arrangements in the platinum mining sector were under the spotlight at a seminar yesterday organised by the Farlam Commission of Inquiry into the Marikana shootings.
The Department of Labour's director of collective bargaining, Ian Macun, said in Joburg that workers had been expressing their grievances in protests that were not organised and led by a trade union.
"Workers may choose to bypass their unions, where they become dissatisfied with their unions and the organisers. There was clearly an element of this at the strike at Lonmin that led to the August (2012) shootings."
Macun was speaking at the University of Witwatersrand, where the Farlam inquiry held its first fact-finding seminar, on the theme "Bargaining arrangements in platinum".
"In analysis of the Marikana (strike), the sheer size of the workplace in mining complicates communication bet-ween unions and members. There are different reasons |for workers to bypass trade unions.
"There has been an increase in the past two to three years in unprocedural strike action."
The commission has been mandated by President Jacob Zuma to investigate the circumstances leading to the deaths of 44 people during the strike at Lonmin's platinum mine at Marikana, near Rustenburg, North West.
Police opened fire to disperse a large crowd, killing|34 people, most of them striking miners, and wounding 70 on August 16, 2012. They arrested 250. In the preceding week, 10 people, including two policemen and two security guards, were killed.
The inquiry is also examining the causes of violence in the mining sector.
The second phase of the inquiry, which has held public hearings since 2012, is to involve public seminars.
These are expected to enable the commission to obtain information and advice from experts, and open matters for public debate.
Professor Sakhela Buhlungu, dean of the faculty of humanities at the University of Cape Town, said unions had "done a decent job" in improving working conditions and wages in post-apartheid South Africa.
"Before Marikana, the bulk of the workforce was represented by one large union, the National Union of Mineworkers. It had a virtual monopoly on that segment of the workforce. But it becomes a problem once the union does not function optimally. It becomes a problem for workers because they have nowhere else to go."
Following the Marikana violence, the Association of Mineworkers and Construction Union became the dominant union at several platinum mining companies, including Lonmin.
The head of the inquiry's evidence leaders, Geoff Budlender, said the second phase would be different from the first, which was dominated by court-style hearings.
"We have broad topics the commission is interested in, not in an abstract sense, but because they may be related to the events of that week in August 2012."
North West's police air wing commander Salmon Vermaak is expected to be on the stand when the hearings resume in Pretoria today.
He is to be cross-examined by the police's lawyers. Unlike other officers, whose testimony has been led by SAPS lawyers, Vermaak'shas been led by evidence leaders.- Sapa
Daily News © 1999 - 2014 Independent Newspapers (Pty) Limited. All rights strictly reserved.
]]></text></news-item>