<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW9-DX21-JD6S-R384"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>NY seeks to be heard on pipeline</title><source>The Times Argus (Barre-Montpelier Vermont)</source><author>Bruce Edwards; STAFF WRITER</author><text><![CDATA[MIDDLEBURY - Ticonderoga, N.Y., home to the International Paper mill that is the town's economic engine, wants a say in the second phase of a proposed natural gas pipeline that would help cut the mill's energy costs.
R. William Grinnell, Ticonderoga town supervisor, wrote the Addison County Regional Planning Commission for an opportunity to weigh in on Phase II of the Addison Rutland Natural Gas Project, which would extend the pipeline from Middlebury west and under Lake Champlain.
On Monday, the town of Ticonderoga and the Essex County Board of Supervisors voted unanimously (with one person absent) to endorse the project and urged the Addison County commission to do the same.
Ticonderoga will be given the opportunity to address the commission at its next meeting April 9. At that time, the commission is expected to vote on whether to endorse Phase II of the Vermont Gas Systems project.
In his March 24 letter, Grinnell noted the economic impact in his community and Vermont of the IP plant. In Ticonderoga, the IP mill has 600 employees, with an additional 600 landowners and loggers dependent on the mill for their livelihood, he said. Across the border, he estimated, the mill spends "more than $3 million on goods and services provided by Vermont businesses, in addition to the $2.5 million spent for wood and fiber and over $1 million in wages and benefits paid to Vermonters working at the mill."
In addition, he said, Vermont benefits from Ticonderoga residents' taking the bridge across the lake to buy goods and services.
"From shopping to professional services, the impact of the money these employees spend in Vermont is significant. In short, the Ticonderoga mill is a significant economic driver for our entire region," Grinnell wrote.
Because New York and Vermont share greenhouse gas reduction goals, Grinnell said, converting the mill from No. 6 fuel oil to natural gas will cut greenhouse gas emissions by 25 percent to 30 percent.
According to Grinnell, converting to natural gas is expected to result in an estimated 40 percent to 50 percent savings in the mill's energy bill.
He wants the opportunity for the Ticonderoga Town Board and other interested parties in the Champlain Valley to weigh in on the project before the Addison County Regional Planning Commission makes its recommendation to the Vermont Public Service Board.
Grinnell said Monday during a phone interview that he has serious concerns about the fairness of the process on the Vermont side of the border.
"Like everything else, there are two sides to every story, and I feel completely disappointed in the side that's being presented in Vermont," he said, "and the fact that the other side is being nearly completely overlooked, and I have a lot of difficulty with the honesty and the forthrightness of that type of approach."
He said extending the pipeline from Vermont is the only way the IP mill could access natural gas.
"There's natural gas in Plattsburgh (N.Y.), but to bring it down the west side of Lake Champlain through the Adirondack Park is a show stopper," Grinnell said.
Opponents argue that extending the pipeline will only increase reliance on fossil fuels and exacerbate global warming. They also have targeted the source: Canadian natural gas in Alberta extracted using the hydraulic fracking process.
Grinnell forwarded a copy of the resolution to the Addison County Regional Planning Commission, which Ticonderoga wants included in the official record.
The commission has extended an invitation to Grinnell and Ticonderoga to attend its meeting April 9, said Adam Lougee, the commission's executive director.
"Our meetings are public meetings. Our process is an open, public process," Lougee said Monday.
In his letter, Grinnell reminded Lougee that under Vermont law the commission is required to take into consideration a project's impact on communities in other states.
Lougee said Grinnell made a good case of tying the common economic interests of both sides of the border to the IP plant as well as the air quality issues.
At the April 9 meeting, Lougee said, he expects the commission will vote whether to endorse Phase II of the pipeline.
He said the commission has spent a good deal of time vetting the project.
"We have had Vermont Gas to two of our commission meetings," Lougee said. "We have had basically members of the public that oppose the project at a third commission meeting. I have had four committees taking a look at this project."
Grinnell said he would make every attempt to attend the meeting and he expects other representatives from New York to be present as well.
The commission endorsed Phase I of the project, which would extend the pipeline south from Chittenden County to Middlebury. The PSB approved that segment of the pipeline in December.
Phase II would extend the pipeline south and west to Shoreham and under 5,000 feet of Lake Champlain to the IP plant. IP is paying $62 million of the $64.2 million cost.
A third phase would run the pipeline south to Rutland.
Vermont Gas Systems spokesman Steve Wark said given the importance of the IP mill it makes sense for Ticonderoga to weigh in with the regional planning commission.
In similar hearings involving Vermont Yankee, Wark said, neighboring states were given the opportunity to voice their views on the nuclear plant's operations.
Because the gas project crosses state lines, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission has jurisdiction. However, Vermont Gas Systems has asked for a waiver from FERC to give the state Public Service Board jurisdiction. Wark said the New York State Public Utilities Commission would also have a role in the proceedings.
The Vermont Public Interest Research Group and Conservation Law Foundation, which oppose the project, are against the waiver, arguing that only FERC has the ability to thoroughly review the project.
bruce.edwards
@rutlandherald.com
]]></text></news-item>