<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW9-06R1-DY0P-G002"><date>2014-03-31</date><title>Novel Suit Seeks To Mandate EPA Review Of Seismic Risks For UIC Permits</title><source>Carbon Control News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Residents and officials in Brady Township, PA, are challenging an EPA underground injection control (UIC) permit in a novel administrative suit that could provide a new legal basis to require the agency to consider potential seismic risks when permitting disposal of oil and gas wastewater on the grounds that it may threaten drinking water sources.
The Environmental Appeals Board (EAB) suit, In re: Windfall Oil and Gas comes as an EPA-state work group has issued long-awaited final recommendations for how permit writers can assess and manage potential seismicity risks on a site-specific basis -- though the advice would be implemented on a voluntary basis.
The report, "Minimizing and Managing Potential Impacts of Injection-Induced Seismicity from Class II Disposal Wells: Practical Approaches," finds that regulators should make an effort to consider and take steps to minimize seismic risks early in the siting and permitting process. "If the UIC Director does not identify a suitable approach to address seismicity concerns, conditions may not be suitable for disposal operations at that location," the report says.
But the report, completed by the UIC National Technical Workgroup (NTW) Jan. 17 and obtained by Inside EPA in a Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) request, finds that the agency is "unaware" of any contamination of underground sources of drinking water (USDWs) resulting from seismicity related to underground injection.
EPA and states have been closely examining potential seismic risks associated with UIC wells used to dispose of wastewater from hydraulic fracturing operations in recent years, as a series of earthquakes in Ohio, Arkansas, and Texas were linked to increased volumes of injected wastewater from booming oil and gas development.
While EPA says it has no evidence that such injection activity is responsible for contamination, the agency is facing criticism from environmentalists and others who allege its regulations governing the wells are inadequate because they do not require consideration of potential seismic risks.
They have argued that the problem lies in EPA's decision to permit such disposal wells under Safe Drinking Water Act (SDWA) rules for Class II UIC wells, which unlike regulatory categories for hazardous waste, carbon capture and sequestration, and other types of injections, do not explicitly require extensive review of potential seismic risks.
Environmentalists' Petition
The Natural Resources Defense Council (NRDC) in 2010 petitioned EPA to recategorize the wastewater as a hazardous waste, a petition that if granted would force regulators to permit the disposal under Class I rules for hazardous wastes, which require industry to demonstrate that the injection will not cause seismic activity or regulators can force the well to be moved.
By contrast, Class II rules do not impose similar burdens on industry nor is an EPA permit review required to specifically address induced seismicity, though the agency must generally consider whether the geological conditions of the formation will prevent endangerment to underground sources of drinking water.
EPA, however, has not acted on the NRDC petition and the Government Accountability Office has indicated that any reclassification of the waste would require legislative action.
But attorneys for the Brady Township petitioners in the EAB suit -- who are challenging EPA Region III's Class II permit for Windfall -- are now proposing a new basis for considering potential seismic risks.
Rather than seeking to recategorize the wastewater, they are arguing that EPA's failure to weigh the risks is at odds with SDWA's requirement to prevent harms to USDWs. In their March 14 petition, the township officials charge that the agency's decision to grant the permit, as well as the permit conditions, are not sufficient to ensure that the permitted injections will not endanger drinking water sources because they do not adequately consider potential seismic risks.
"With regard to pressure and seismicity, EPA's permit decision and the permit conditions related to maximum injection pressure and operations restrictions . . . do not meet the endangerment standard regarding the potential for induced seismic events caused by the authorized wastewater injection," says the petition, which was filed on behalf of landowners by University of Pittsburgh School of Law Environmental Law Clinic.
The pending EAB suit is likely to test EPA's approach outlined in the NTW report, as well as in a voluntary framework developed by Region III and applied when regulators crafted the Windfall permit.
The report is based on four case studies of seismic activity at Class II UIC wells in Texas, Arkansas, Ohio and West Virginia, where EPA is aware of seismic activity though the agency says none has so far resulted in contamination.
Case Studies
In reviewing the case studies, EPA found that the magnitude of the earthquake activity may increase over time, that injection into fractured disposal zones overlaying certain types of rock may increase seismic risks, and that some deep disposal wells were thought to have conduits to known faults, posing additional risks.
The case studies also showed that while disposal "commonly" occurred in zones known to have naturally fractured reservoir characteristics, operating the wells below certain pressures could offset related risks, though identifying appropriate pressure rates would require additional testing.
While the report is not agency guidance and does not identify specific policy procedures, it is intended to "provide the "UIC Director with considerations for addressing induced seismicity on a site specific basis, using Director discretionary authority."
The report offers a "decision model" to be used in assessing specific sites for determining whether there exists pressure buildup from pre-existing injection activities, "faults of concern," or those with potential for significant seismic risks, and a pathway for the increased pressure to "communicate" with the fault.
The decision model, specifically to Class II wells, poses three questions: whether any seismicity concerns have been identified in new or existing wells, whether site considerations remain following further review data and whether an approach can successfully be used to address identified risks.
The report, which says that the model can be used for existing disposal wells and for siting assessment with proposed or planned wells, may help bring clarity to permitting decisions over UIC wells where seismicity risks are believed to be an issue, given that a major sticking point in In re: Windfall is that the agency has not clearly identified its rationale either for setting permit conditions it says are protective against seismic risks.
EPA's Response
For example, in EPA's summary response to comments on the permit, the agency says that it considered factors "relevant to seismic activity such as the existence of any known faults and/or fractures and any history of, or potential for, seismic events in the area of the Injection Well."
EPA says in the summary response that it followed its "Region III framework for evaluating seismic potential associate with UIC Class II permits," updated last year.
According to a copy of the framework document, the region uses operating conditions in Class II permits to expressly limit the injection pressure to prevent cracking of rock in the injection zone, where the region finds that it is necessary to minimize conduits for potential contamination to USDWs. This approach appears to have been applied in the Windfall permitting process.
The Region III document also emphasizes that "Of the hundreds of thousands of injection wells operating in the United States, EPA is not aware of any case where a seismic event, whether naturally occurring or induced, caused an injection well to contaminate a USDW.
But the EAB suit is likely to provide a key test of the agency's position, outlined in the summary response, that it is not required under SDWA to review seismic risks before issuing a permit for a Class II well -- though the region says it does routinely include such risks in reviewing permit applications based on the framework document.
"Although EPA must consider appropriate geological data on the injection and confining zone when permitting Class II wells, the SDWA regulations for Class II wells do not require specific consideration of seismicity, unlike the SDWA regulations for Class I wells used for the injection of hazardous waste," the summary response says.
In the Windfall permit suit, the petition charges that although the Class II regulations do not explicitly require seismicity to be addressed, "When issuing a permit, the permittee must satisfy EPA or the delegated state agency that its injection will not endanger USDWs, and the permitting authority is required to proscribe such permit conditions as may be necessary to ensure that no risk of endangerment is present." -- Bridget DiCosmo(bdicosmo@iwpnews.com)
03-27-2014
]]></text></news-item>