<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW9-PVF1-DY37-30MK"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Ameren, environmental groups square off on coal ash landfill</title><source>St. Louis Post-Dispatch (Missouri)</source><author> By Jacob Barker jbarker@post-dispatch.com 314-340-8291 </author><text><![CDATA[JEFFERSON CITY • Trucking coal ash from its Labadie power plant to a remote landfill would cost Ameren Missouri - and ultimately ratepayers - $100 million more than keeping it nearby, the utility says. But critics worry Ameren's preferred site invites an environmental catastrophe that could cost a whole lot more.
The first day of Missouri Public Service Commission hearings on the utility's proposal for a coal ash landfill near its largest power plant started Monday, marking the beginning of the end for the utility's years-long bid to add new waste storage.
The site next to the Franklin County plant, though, is in the Missouri River floodplain, and while Ameren says it will build a berm to withstand a 500-year flood, environmentalists worry that an unprecedented flood event could overwhelm any man-made defense.
Whether the PSC should take those considerations into account, though, is disputed. The regulator typically deals with rate-setting, the balance between a reasonable profit for investor-owned utilities and the lowest burden for customers. Environmental concerns, Ameren's attorney James Lowery argued, should be handled by the Missouri Department of Natural Resources, which is already reviewing the company's application for a construction permit.
Pressed by PSC commissioners, Lowery said there may not be a prohibition against looking at environmental factors when determining whether to issue a certificate to build the landfill. But because the law spells out the DNR's responsibility in the process, he said the commission should leave those questions to the other agency.
"You may literally have the discretion to look at it here, but it's my position that it's not appropriate here," Lowery said.
The PSC's own staff and the Office of the Public Counsel appeared to agree. The commission looks at environmental issues "from a very high level," said Nathan Williams, an attorney on the PSC's staff. But its role is to regulate utilities, not look out for environmental hazards, he said.
But Missouri Public Counsel Lewis Mills, whose office advocates for ratepayers before the commission, said the concerns raised by critics of the plan seemed to fall within the DNR's regulatory realm.
"If there is a vacuum there and no other agency is evaluating health and safety, then your role should be greater," Mills said.
Opposing parties in the case - the Sierra Club and the Labadie Environmental Organization, a local group - argue that the PSC should take environmental factors into account because costs from remediating contaminated groundwater or the river could ultimately hit ratepayers.
But ratepayers have been held harmless after disasters before. When Ameren rebuilt its Taum Sauk reservoir following its collapse, it wasn't allowed to recoup costs from customers.
Still, even if a condition was added to prevent Ameren from passing on any cleanup costs to ratepayers, representatives for the environmental groups said the risk of contamination at the proposed site was too great not to consider.
"This site is not well situated," said Giles Howard, who helped represent the environmental groups through the Interdisciplinary Environmental Clinic at the Washington University School of Law. "The proposed site presents risk of catastrophic failure that Ameren has not taken into account."
Beyond flooding, chief among their concerns are groundwater contamination and the prospect of further pollution in the Missouri River, a water source for thousands in the St. Louis region.
Ameren Missouri's managing supervisor of hydroengineering, Craig Giesmann, said the company was going "above and way beyond" the safety features required by environmental regulators.
The proposed landfill would include a concrete liner to prevent leaks, and the site would be able to hold waste from the power plant for the remainder of its 20 to 30 years of "useful life."
Storing the waste elsewhere would be pricey. Ameren estimates it would cost roughly $351 million through 2058 to store the coal ash off-site - nearly $100 million more than it anticipates spending to manage it nearby.
That's conservative, Lowery said, because it doesn't take rising fuel costs into account and Ameren estimates it would take 160 trucks every workday to haul the ash. The company expects that to rise to 200 trucks per day in the early 2020s, after it installs new coal scrubbers in the plant to comply with federal rules.
Hearings on the proposal are expected to continue through Wednesday, and the commission likely won't make a decision before late May. Ameren expects the DNR to issue a construction permit by June 1.
]]></text></news-item>