<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BW9-T9G1-JB4P-V1VM"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>SHAREHOLDER ALERT: The Law Firm of Levi &amp; Korsinsky, LLP Launches an Investigation into Possible Securities Fraud Violations by the Board of Directors of Tenneco Inc.</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ Levi & Korsinsky, LLP is investigating Tenneco Inc. ("Tenneco") (NYSE: TEN) in connection with possible violations of federal securities laws.

To get more information, click here:http://zlk.9nl.com/tenneco-ten. There is no cost or obligation to you.
On March 25, 2014, shares of Tenneco stock fell after the Company confirmed that authorities in Europe and the United States have requested information as part of a global antitrust investigation concerning multiple automotive suppliers. The Company recently received a subpoena from the U.S. Department of Justice. Shares of Tenneco fell from a close of $59.00 per share on March 24, 2014, to a close of $55.24 per share on March 25, 2014.
If you own common stock in Tenneco and wish to obtain additional information, please contact Eduard Korsinsky, Esq. either via email atek@zlk.comor by telephone at (212) 363-7500, toll-free: (877) 363-5972, or visithttp://zlk.9nl.com/tenneco-ten.
Levi & Korsinsky is a national firm with offices in New York, New Jersey, Connecticut and Washington D.C. The firm's 26 attorneys have extensive expertise in prosecuting securities litigation involving financial fraud, representing investors throughout the nation in securities and shareholder lawsuits. For more information, please feel free to contact any of the attorneys listed below. Attorney advertising. Prior results do not guarantee similar outcomes.
CONTACT:   Levi & Korsinsky, LLPEduard Korsinsky, Esq.30 Broad Street - 24th FloorNew York, NY 10004           Tel: (212) 363-7500Toll Free:  (877) 363-5972Fax: (866) 367-6510http://www.zlk.com
Logo -http://photos.prnewswire.com/prnh/20120409/MM84375LOGO
SOURCE Levi & Korsinsky, LLP
]]></text></news-item>