<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWB-5401-JB3N-T055"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Irrigation scam probe fails to name Ajit Pawar</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Nauzer K Bharucha</author><text><![CDATA[MUMBAI: The Chitale committee which probed the multi-crore irrigation scam in the state has found “major irregularities” in the way project costs were increased through revised administrative approvals (RAA) and recommended “strict action” against officials involved.
The Special Investigative Team (SIT) headed by Madhav Chitale found that RAAs for 27 projects in Vidarbha, Tapi and Godavari-Marathwada were illegal. The state finance department was kept in the dark when these RAAs were sanctioned by various irrigation corporations between October 7, 2006, and August 20, 2009. “That the government did not know this is difficult to digest and cannot be accepted. These officers must be identified,” it said.
But the committee did not investigate the core issue of corruption, including arbitrary increase in tender costs, awarding additional works to contractors without inviting tenders and involvement of senior ministers in the scam, saying the issues were beyond its mandate.
The man at the centre of the controversy, the then water resources minister Ajit Pawar who briefly resigned following a TOI expose in September 2012, finds no mention in the report. TOI had reported how Pawar had issued circulars which circumvented the mandatory approval of the state finance department and were directly responsible for jacking up tender rates. The report has apportioned the blame on officials.
The report mentioned that “these core issues were riddled with grave irregularities which require deep and thorough investigation by a competent authority”.
The report, going into more than 1,300 pages and divided into two volumes, concluded that there were major “policy flaws” in the irrigation sector. “Projects got entangled in the vicious circle of contractors. (The thinking seemed to be) Spend as much as you want and take as much time as possible,’’ said the report.
The investigative team further found “major faults” in projects due to change of design. “Of the 61 projects examined, costs of 28 projects were high because of design change. In fact, work on these projects commenced on incomplete information. The actual design was known much later, which led to massive changes and resulted in huge cost escalation as the construction cost increased,” it added.
“There are a lot of grey areas in policy matters. If rules were followed, a lot of mistakes could have been avoided. Major changes will improve the department in the long run,” the committee said.
Interestingly, between January and August 2009, Ajit Pawar had granted RAA to 38 projects worth Rs 17,700 crore. But the three-member Chitale panel put the entire blame on respective chief engineers. “The executive director and chief accounts officer of the irrigation corporation must be held liable in projects where excessive expenditure was incurred,” said the report, which was submitted to the state government last month but has still not been made public.
“In four projects, no RAA was granted, but excess expenditure was incurred beyond the original approval. This is a serious lapse. There is total financial irregularity; action must be taken against top project officers related to expenditure control of the project,” said the report.
It put the onus on the chairman of the governing council of the irrigation corporation (minister) for allowing these additional expenditures beyond the sanctioned amount.
The probe team also found that projects began without adequate funds. It asked the state cabinet to examine if the executive director and chief accounts and financial officer had informed the governing council about unavailability of funds.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>