<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWB-5401-JB3N-T013"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>SpiceJet floats Re 1 ticket, DGCA shoots it down</title><source>The Economic Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NEW DELHI/ MUMBAI: SpiceJet’s Re 1 ticket offer earned the carrier a stern cease-and-desist warning from the aviation regulator, which said the offer was predatory, a malpractice and deceptive to boot.
The carrier shot back that the offer can’t be predatory as it has only a 20% share of the market and that it clearly told customers that seats were limited and that such offers have been made before in India and overseas.
The launch of the Re 1 fare scheme on Tuesday was reminiscent of similar campaigns by GR Gopinath’s Air Deccan that kicked off the aviation boom in India. The Directorate General of Civil Aviation (DGCA) said SpiceJet’s move was “anti-competitive”.
The offer created a rush on the website as eager travellers shopped for bargain fares. “While we planned for high response, our website was at times unable to cope with the high traffic that was generated due to the high booking activity that was taking place simultaneously as customers took advantage of the market-stimulation fares,” the airline said in a release.
SpiceJet said it had responded to DGCA’s letter. “This kind of low-fare market stimulation and inventory management (if done properly) is essential for the LCC (low-cost carrier) business model, and is a key part of the strategy for low-cost airlines such as Air Asia, RyanAir, Southwest, EasyJet, etc globally, and benefits the wider travel industry and economy at large due to the stimulation and ‘economic multiplier’ effect,” the carrier said.
The DGCA move was under rules relating to tariffs and state that these should be set with regard to cost of operations, characteristics of service, reasonable profit and generally prevailing charges. The director general can ask the airline to revoke tariffs found to be predatory or excessive.
SpiceJet defended itself vigorously. “As a low cost airline in a market where demand is currently soft in a market where costs are structurally high, amongst the highest in the world, we are trying our best to be innovative and adopting best practices from global LCCs in order to attract more customers and improve our revenue performance.”
The regulator said the carrier will need to decide what to do with the tickets already sold. “We have asked them to withdraw the scheme immediately," a DGCA official told ET. The carrier launched the offer for travel between 1 July, 2014, and March 28, 2015 with tickets to be booked between Tuesday and Thursday. Taxes will be added but some tickets won’t carry a fuel surcharge.
While the regulator usually cracks the whip when prices go up, this is the second time DGCA has reacted this way. In the middle of January last year, SpiceJet offered 1 million tickets at Rs 2,013 apiece. DGCA immediately asked CEOs of all airlines not to follow SpiceJet as it would damage their financials.
Some of SpiceJet's fares under the current scheme were 50% cheaper than those on IndiGo, GoAir and other competitors. Delhi-Kolkata return tickets were available for Rs 2,051 on Spice-Jet while the average price on other airlines was around Rs 7,500 after the advance purchase discount.
SpiceJet has already sold out its Re 1 inventory and is close to doing that on its Rs 799 inventory. "The only thing that is left is the Rs 1,499 inventory," said a person affiliated to SpiceJet. The decision of the DGCA does not impact passengers who have already booked tickets, this person said.
DGCA had asked Spice-Jet to explain the rationale of the scheme. “The airline gave an explanation for the rationale of launching the scheme saying that it will stimulate the demand but only 1.7% of their inventory is available as per this scheme and we don't see how it will stimulate demand in the industry,” the official at the regulator’s office said.
“These fares will allow families to plan their vacations and weekend trips at fares lower than train fares with joy and freedom, now that the pressure of March school exams is finally over. But they need to move fast as seats are limited," said Kaneswaran Avili, SpiceJet's new chief commercial officer.
"There's a misinformed propaganda about all low fares affecting the margins of an airline," said Gopinath, founder of Air Deccan, which was acquired by the now grounded Kingfisher Airlines in 2007.
"In the low-fare model, it’s a crime to fly empty planes. You have to stimulate the market with attractive fares. For example, Ryan Air sells 80 million seats every year out of which 25% is for free. Its revenue per passenger is 39 euros while its competitor Easyjet's is 59 euros," said Gopinath.
Go Air slashed fares on its website although it didn't match the Re 1 fare. SpiceJet airline started the first fare war of the year on January 21 by announcing 50% off on tickets for travel till April 15.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>