<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWB-5401-JB3N-T002"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Green activists offer plan for new environment regulator</title><source>The Economic Times</source><author>M Rajshekhar</author><text><![CDATA[NEW DELHI: Even as the ministry of environment met its March 31 deadline to submit a plan to the Supreme Court for a new environment regulator, a set of academics, activists and environmental lawyers have weighed in with their own design.
Concerned that the ministry version “would not meet the minimum standards of an independent regulatory authority”, this set, called Watchdog and Action Group for the Environment, have proposed an authority that has greater powers and independence than the design outlined by the ministry.
According to Shekhar Singh, an RTI activist who leads the group, the ministry had not shared with the public any of its thinking behind the proposed authority. “We felt we had no other option but to draft our own set of recommendations and try and ensure that these are considered and, as far as possible, incorporated in the new bill,” he said in an email response.
The group submitted its plan last week to the ministry and to the central empowered committee that advises the SC on forest matters. The group is also considering becoming a party to the SC case on the new authority.
The group’s blueprint for the authority is different from that of the ministry on many counts. For inconomystance, while the ministry only wants the authority to appraise projects, the group wants it to also approve and reject projects.
Speaking on the condition of anonymity, a senior official at a leading industry federation said the authority as proposed by the group -- it chooses who studies a project, it evaluates that study and gives a verdict -- could become a law unto itself. “It may once again lead to centralisation of power,” the official said. Counters Singh: “All decisions can be appealed in the National Green Tribunal (the courts that settle environment disputes). This would make it as accountable as most other independent institutions.”
Another sizeable difference is whether the authority should be created under the existing Environment Protection Act, as directed by the SC, or through a new law, as both the ministry and the group want. “We have to be within the SC decision,” says a senior official in the ministry, not wanting to be named. “However, for the sake of greater independence and the ability to levy financial penalties, etc, we do need a bill for the regulator.”
William Lockhart, emeritus professor of Law at the University of Utah’s SJ Quinney College of Law, who has been studying the environment clearance process in India, feels that just creating a regulator is not enough. The planners also need to reconsider “specific aspects of the present design that encourages slapdash or dismissive treatment of environmental issues”. For example, he adds, the exclusion of project-affected people from the process that defines the parameters along which project impact has to be studied.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>