<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWB-77W1-DYTD-90KX"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Whistleblowers Are Cashing In On Fraud; Government shells out huge sums to uncover corporate malfeasance</title><source>Investor's Business Daily</source><author>CIARAN MCEVOY</author><text><![CDATA[Aggrieved employees wreaking vengeance on their bosses is one common workplace fantasy, but the federal government is making it increasingly possible -- notably in financial services -- to cash in on exposing potential wrongdoing by their employers.
Keith Edwards, a former JPMorgan Chase employee, was awarded $63.8 million last month for helping the government in its quest to force the nation's largest bank into a $614 million settlement. The case involved mortgage-lending practices that allegedly violated the False Claims Act, a Civil War-era law banning businesses from making false claims for payment from the government.
Last October, a jury found Bank of America liable for fraudulent loans that its Countrywide unit sold Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac in 2007 and 2008 -- a case based in part on information from a former insider at Countrywide. Other whistleblowers have reaped millions of dollars after going public with allegations that banks "robo-signed" foreclosure notices, scammed veterans and committed other skullduggery.
Bad Deeds Raise Suspicion
The Enron and WorldCom scandals of a decade ago spurred Congress to pass the Sarbanes-Oxley Act, and Time magazine to award its 2002 Person of the Year honor to "The whistleblowers."
But the 2008 financial crisis, spurred in part by a banking sector encouraged by the federal government to write subprime loans that unintentionally overheated the housing market, has caused the federal government to seek out whistleblowers more aggressively to punish wrongdoers and perhaps save face for the government.
Whistleblowers can save investigators money and, more importantly, give them access to inside information they ordinarily wouldn't have in terms of corporate malfeasance.
"Congress has been impressed with this model of enforcement," said Kathleen Clark, a professor at Washington University School of Law. "It's kind of a private-public partnership."
Rewards For Good Tips
The Dodd-Frank Act rewards people who volunteer original information leading to a successful action resulting in a recovery of $1 million or more by the U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission. Such whistleblowers are eligible to receive 10%-30% of the overall amount.
The SEC received 3,238 whistleblower tips and complaints in fiscal 2013, up nearly 8% from a year before. Six whistleblowers have been paid under the Dodd-Frank Act, which created the SEC's Office of the whistleblower. A $14 million payout was issued last October in one investor-fraud case.
Meet A Friendly Prosecutor
An executive branch that is friendly to whistleblowers -- outside the national security sector, that is -- also has contributed to more aggressive enforcement, experts said.
"The SEC is really encouraging them to file their submissions and assuring them that they will be vigorously investigated," said Eric Havian, a San Francisco-based lawyer who practices whistleblower law. "You're going to see a lot of financial fraud coming to light that had been buried for many years."
Spurred on not only by banking cases but also by fraud involving health care, defense contracts and shady pharmaceutical billing, the Justice Department recovered $3.8 billion from lawsuits brought under the False Claims Act in its fiscal year ended Sept. 30, 2013 -- the second largest such annual recovery ever under the statute.
About $17 Billion Recovered
Total recoveries since January 2009 have totaled $17 billion, nearly half the total amount recovered since the False Claims statute was amended to allow whistleblowers to sue alleged wrongdoers. State and federal governments can decide to join in those complaints and award a percentage of the recovery to the whistleblower, as in the Edwards case.
Although the Edwards case against JPMorgan drew headlines, it remains only one part of an overall anti-fraud landscape.
"It's possible we'll see many more False Claims Act cases along the lines of the JPMorgan case, but it depends on how much fraud there was and whether there was a federal government nexus (for claims)," Clark said. "I would anticipate many more whistleblower awards by the SEC under its Dodd-Frank program."
The False Claims Act's 10-year statute of limitations also means that the public may not have heard the last of it being used against the banking sector.
Contractors Covered Too
Bolstering whistleblowers further was the Supreme Court's March 4 decision that Sarbanes-Oxley's protections extend to subcontractors who do business with publicly traded companies.
The SEC's continued public statements make it clear that whistleblower protections will be broadly viewed.
"They're not going to sit by and twiddle their thumbs," said Meyer Eisenberg, a professor at Columbia Law School and former SEC deputy general counsel.
The potential of hefty financial awards may increase the likelihood of exposing fraudsters such as Bernard Madoff at an early stage, preventing other investors from getting swindled.
"Now, everyone in Madoff's organization would have an incentive to come forward and blow the whistle," Havian said.
]]></text></news-item>