<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWD-8M41-F125-150X"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Locke oil company ordered to clean well site</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[CALGARY - An eight-year struggle over reclamation of an abandoned oil and gas well south of Calgary has resulted in an environmental protection order against a private junior oil company headed by the owner of the Lake Louise ski resort.
Alberta Environment and Sustainable Resource Development said in a news release on Tuesday it decided to issue the order after failing since 2006 in numerous attempts to have the well site cleaned up, first with Stampede Oil and then with Locke Stock &; Barrel after it acquired the site from a receiver in 2009.
It said the department has made many requests for a plan with an implementation time frame but "no substantial steps were undertaken to deal with remaining contamination."
The order demands that Locke Stock &; Barrel reclaim the site and remediate contamination before the end of March next year.
It is to undertake soil and groundwater sampling and submit a final report summarizing all work that has been undertaken before April 30, 2015, then apply for a reclamation certificate for the well before Dec. 31, 2016.
In an interview, president Charlie Locke said his company hired an environmental contractor "several years ago" for the project and will be able to complete it in the time allotted.
"It's an ongoing process which is normal industry standard in these situations where you do your environmental work first, then you proceed to reclaim the site," he said. "That's where we're at."
He said last year's heavy flooding caused some of the delays, pointing out the well was actually a "dry hole" that never produced economic quantities of oil or gas.
Sarah Jackson, a spokesman for ESRD, said the order gives more force to the department's previous efforts.
"Should this company not follow the deadlines as laid out, we can actually then pursue it further which can be fines, it can go all the way up to prosecutions," she explained.
The release and the order say that several complaints have been registered by the landowner, Malcolm McPherson, that no reclamation activities at the well site had occurred, despite meetings with the company.
In August of last year, ESRD issued "directions of an inspector" giving details on activities that need to be completed so that the company can apply for a reclamation certificate. But the landowner complained in January that nothing had been done, it said.
dhealing@calgaryherald.com
© Copyright (c) The Calgary Herald
]]></text></news-item>