<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWD-M5B1-F0JP-W3PD"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Standing up to miner</title><source>Central Coast Express Advocate (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Legal proceedings against the Wallarah 2 coal project have been initiated in the Land and Environment Court by the Darkinjung Local Aboriginal Land Council.
They will challenge the validity of a development -application for the proposed mine, due to be considered at public hearings by the -Planning Assessment Commission (PAC) today, April 2.
"Over recent days Darkinjung has been vilified repeatedly by Wallarah 2 spokespeople who are accusing us of 'extortion', 'blackmail' and of making a 'cash grab', simply because we are standing up for our legal rights," Darkinjung's chief executive officer Sean Gordon said.
"These are rights that we have under the planning laws of NSW, both as private landholders and as a part of the NSW Aboriginal land rights Act.
"Our people have been attacked for decades for allegedly living off government welfare and not looking after ourselves.
"Now when we do stand up to protect our social and economic values, we get vilified for that too.
"It is laughable that a powerful mining company backed by the government of a wealthy nation like Korea would accuse a small local land council of -extortion.
"Wallarah 2 are proposing to use our land for their own purpose and offer an insulting tonnage rate of just 4 cents. Darkinjung has no choice but to pursue our legal rights in the Land and Environment Court.
"We filed proceedings on March 27 against Wallarah 2, the Minister for Planning and Infrastructure and the Planning Assessment Commission, seeking declarations that the development application is invalid and an injunction preventing the minister or the PAC from determining it."
PAC hearingThe Australian Coal Alliance is urging people to attend today's (April 2) Planning and Assessment Commission hearing at Wyong Golf Club from 9.30am. Alliance spokesman Alan Hayes said the hearing would be the last chance for people affected by the Wallarah 2 mine proposal to have their voice heard.
]]></text></news-item>