<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWD-BVP1-DYX4-003H"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Freight forwarding firms 'engaged in price-fixing'; Watchdog finds they have engaged in 'cartel activities' for Japan-S'pore shipments</title><source>The Straits Times (Singapore)</source><author>Grace Leong</author><text><![CDATA[ELEVEN freight forwarders along with their Singapore subsidiaries have allegedly engaged in cartel activities to fix prices of air freight services for shipments from Japan to Singapore.
The Competition Commission of Singapore (CCS) has provisionally found that the parties infringed Section 34 of the Competition Act by collectively fixing certain fees and surcharges, and exchanging customer and price information for freight forwarding services for shipments on the Japan-to-Singapore route.
The Singapore competition watchdog yesterday issued a proposed infringement decision, a written notice setting out the facts on which the CCS makes its assessment and gives reasons for arriving at the proposed decision.
The parties include Deutsche Post; DHL Global Forwarding Management (Asia Pacific) and its subsidiary DHL Global Forwarding (Singapore); "K" Line Logistics and its subsidiary "K" Line Logistics (Singapore); Nippon Express and its unit, Nippon Express (Singapore).
When contacted yesterday, a CCS spokesman said: "At this stage, CCS won't be able to reveal what are the exact fees and surcharges that were collectively fixed by the 11 freight forwarding companies and their subsidiaries."
The CCS began investigations after one of the parties involved in the alleged cartel filed an application for immunity under the CCS Leniency programme. The leniency initiative gives cartel members an incentive to come forward and give evidence on their cartel activities.
In the course of its investigation, the CCS found that the parties, who were meant to be competitors, attended meetings in Japan where they exchanged information, discussed and agreed on the amount of certain fees and surcharges in relation to air freight forwarding services involving the Japan-Singapore route.
The parties have up to 35 working days to make representations to the CCS, which will then take their information and any new evidence into consideration before it decides whether to issue a final decision.
The CCS spokesman added: "Should CCS issue an infringement decision, information about successful leniency applicants, and any associated reduction in penalties, would be contained in the decision."
Cartels are defined as groups of businesses or executives that, instead of competing against each other, secretly agree to work together to increase their individual profits.
The practice is not just anti-competitive but also harms the local economy by making consumers and other businesses pay inflated prices for goods and services.
gleong@sph.com.sg
]]></text></news-item>