<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWD-Y8V1-JB4P-V373"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Adelaide Environmental Renews GSA Contract, Will Continue Post-Hurricane Sandy Remediation Efforts</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Adelaide Environmental Health Associates, Inc., (Adelaide) an Environmental Consulting firm based in New York State announced that they have secured a 5-year renewal of theirGSA Schedule 899 Contract. Adelaide continues to lead the mold, lead paint, asbestos investigations and remediation planning and monitoring for buildings affected by hurricane Sandy, including numerous schools and churches run by the Archdiocese of New York.
"Hurricane Sandy exposed serious environmental hazards in older and historic buildings and we're working with property owners to ensure compliance, safe removal and remediation of hazardous materials including mold contamination, older lead paint and exposed asbestos insulation," states Stephanie Soter, President at Adelaide Environmental Health Associates, Inc.
Adelaide remediation services have been required in key renovation projects for Veteran Affairs hospitals located in Albany & Bath, NY. They have provided environmental consulting services to governmental organizations and helped guide numerous facility managers through safe renovations of older properties. Ms. Soter adds: "We're looking to expand our governmental portfolio as many of their older properties will require significant repairs and we expect that they will present environmental challenges similar to those encountered while supervising renovations at the VA."
Retail, corporate, residential, and industrial property owners use Adelaide's consulting services for pre-construction, pre-demolition, and abatement monitoring. Adelaide is a trusted provider of abatement planning, design, and monitoring in New York's schools. In the public sector, Adelaide regularly consults at state-run facilities from Buffalo to the Bronx, including hazmat investigation and project monitoring at the New York State Capitol, an architecturally significant building on the National Register of Historic Places.
About Adelaide Environmental Health Associates, Inc.:A Woman Owned Small Business (WOSB), Adelaide is an approved consultant on the New York State Office of General Services roster, now servicing their fifth consecutive term contract with OGS. They are also well known and well received by government agencies such as GSA, USPS, DOT, DOD, DASNY, NYPA, and numerous others for whom they have completed a wide variety of projects as a term, prime, or sub-consultant. Adelaide also acts as an abatement design firm as well as the monitoring and final inspection team, providing owners with a seamless, well-coordinated operation where requirements are understood and adhered to. For more information, visithttp://www.adelaidellc.com.
Contact for Adelaide Environmental Health Associates, Inc.:Stephanie Soter, President at (845) 278-7710
SOURCE Adelaide Environmental Health Associates, Inc.
]]></text></news-item>