<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-XKK1-JB20-G4P2"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>IMUS IN THE MORNING</title><source>Imus Simulcast</source><author>Lori Rothman, Lauren Simonetti, Don Imus, Connell McShane, Rob Bartlett, Bernard McGuirk, Dagen McDowell, Lou Rufino, Warner Wolf, Tom Bowman, Maria Bartiromo</author><text><![CDATA[LORI ROTHMAN, FOX BUSINESS: Good morning. Our top story, the CEO of General Motors is apologizing for an ignition switch defect that's been linked to at least a dozen deaths leading to a massive recall.
Mary Barra is due to testify today before house subcommittee about the problem. She is expected to face tough questions from lawmakers on why GM waited more than a decade to recall vehicles due to faulty switches and problems with air bags and brake parts.
Federal regulators will also be on the hot seat according to preliminary findings. Congressional investigators found the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration twice failed to investigate complaints and crash reports about GM cars.
Barra is also due to testify before the senate tomorrow which is holding its own hearing on the matter. Late yesterday, GM announced it is recalling 1.3 million vehicles to fix problem with power steering.
So the automaker is recalling a total now of more than 6.3 million vehicles. A senate subcommittee holding a hearing today on Caterpillar's tax strategy.
This after report says Caterpillar avoided paying $2.4 billion in U.S. taxes since 2000 by shifting profits to an affiliate in Switzerland.
The report also says Caterpillar paid accounting firm PricewaterhouseCoopers $55 million to develop this strategy.
Representatives from Caterpillar and the accounting firm are all scheduled to testify. Checking the markets following yesterday's rally here in the U.S., Futures are pointing to another higher open ahead of the latest ISM report on manufacturing and auto sales.
Also playing into the market this morning, the latest manufacturing reports out of China. The official report from the government showed an increase over February, however the final HSBC PMI reading, as they call it, came to an eight-month low indicating contraction.
Asian markets finished the day mostly higher with the exception of the Nikkei which lost ground. And in Europe, Euro zone factory activity slowed slightly this month.
There was a pick-up in France however as well as in Italy, Spain and Ireland. Slow-downs recorded in Germany and Austria, stocks though shrugging that news off and posting slight gains right now across the board for the European benchmarks.
And it looks like Yahoo is in the market for an online video service. Straight to Lauren Simonetti now in the newsroom with more. Hi, Lauren.
LAUREN SIMONETTI, FOX BUSINESS: Hey, good morning, Lori. The "Wall Street Journal" is reporting that Yahoo is in talks to buying "News Distribution Network" for about $300 million.
The paper says the deal could boost Yahoo's online video programming and its video advertising revenue, right? Everybody is watching video on TV these days.
"Ndn" is a syndication service, it works with newspapers as well as online publishers, Yahoo has not come onto the -- on the story and the "Journal" does point out that this deal could still fall through.
ROTHMAN: Hewlett-Packard paying up to settle a shareholder lawsuit, give us the details --
SIMONETTI: Yes --
ROTHMAN: On this one --
SIMONETTI: Absolutely, $57 million, that's what HP is paying to settle the suit which accused the PC maker's former management team of defrauding shareholders by abandoning a business model it had long praise.
Now the lawsuit was filed after former CEO Leo Apotheker shocked investors back in 2011 when he announced plans to refocus the company on its business services and its business products.
Apotheker also revealed plans to scrap web OS whose right HP had obtained when it bought Palm back in 2010 and pay more than $11 billion for the British software company Autonomy.
The purchased software only forced HP to take a huge charge for accounting problems, Lori.
ROTHMAN: And that sums it up, thank you so much, Lauren, see you soon --
SIMONETTI: Sure, bye.
ROTHMAN: Well, Microsoft is in the news, it has taken the crown once again for the world's top software company.
According to Gartner, Microsoft remained in the number one spot last year with revenue of about $65.7 billion.
But in a significant shift Oracle bumped IBM out of second place with 29.6 billion, compared with "big lose" 29.1 billion.
Now the company reported weaker-than-expected quarterly results two weeks ago although some analysts saw signs of improvement in the company's business.
Overall software, revenue climbed about 5 percent from 2012 to just over $407 billion. Breaking news about the auto sales number for the latest month from Chrysler.
Chrysler saying sales rose 13 percent last month compared to this month a year ago, the estimate was for a gain of 11.1 percent according to Edmonds.
Chrysler saw an 11 percent increase in February, so some good news there for Chrysler. All right, Apple and Samsung in federal court today in California for opening statements in their latest legal battle.
Apple accusing Samsung of infringing on five patents on its Samsungs and tablets. But Samsung claims Apple stole two of its ideas to use on iPhones and iPads.
The two companies have been tangling with all this litigation all around the world now for nearly three years. If Apple prevails, this time around the cost of Samsung could reach $2 billion.
Here is a look at commodities, crude oil is trading at $101 a barrel and the price of gold is up slightly trading at 12.85 even per ounce. IMUS IN THE MORNING continues right now on Fox Business, giving you the power to prosper.
DON IMUS, HOST, IMUS IN THE MORNING: All right, here is what I can decide --
CONNELL MCSHANE, IMUS IN THE MORNING: OK --
IMUS: There're no big news by the way, the Mets suck --
MCSHANE: They do, yes --
IMUS: The mayors about a half a Pinnochio --
MCSHANE: Obamacare stuff and --
IMUS: Well, so Rob e-mails me this morning and says, you know these press junket videos they send out to people?
Like if you're a -- let's say you have a little TV station in Huntsville, Texas, you're not going to get -- Russell Crowe is not going to come to your TV station to do your local news, you think, you see --
MCSHANE: Right --
IMUS: Even if they have one, I'm not so much sure. So they send out these pre-taped interviews from Mr. Crowe and somebody interviewing him.
So we got one of them, somehow Rob got his hands on one of them and so he cut out the questions that were being asked Mr. Crowe and he came up with his own questions.
MCSHANE: Sure --
IMUS: And he puts this together, so if I don't do it now we're not going to get to it and it begins by Rob introducing himself. So roll that, Bigfoot.
MCSHANE: Oh, here we go.
(BEGIN AUDIO CLIP)
ROB BARTLETT, IMUS IN THE MORNING: Rob Bartlett here without a context interview, we're very lucky today to have the incredible Russell Crowe.
Star of Box Office hit "Noah"; the very controversial "Noah", I think that our audience probably would like one of the biggest questions answered.
What is the difference between you singing "Folsom Prison Blues" on the "Tonight Show" with Jimmy Fallon and the sounds of a yak being sodomized by a much larger yak?
RUSSELL CROWE, ACTOR: Well, you know, that's an interpretive thing, you know, you're making a rush or something, I wouldn't think that it is any different.
(LAUGHTER)
But these are not necessarily sure that it is so vastly different at all, I mean it's just an interpretation.
BARTLETT: Yes, well, you killed --
(LAUGHTER)
Definitely. Moving on, the subject that everyone seems to be obsessed with, you've seen big Roy, Imus' penis --
(LAUGHTER)
What were your first impressions?
CROWE: Well, the first time I saw it, it was from the air --
(LAUGHTER)
I went into that particular location by helicopter because we'd come in from Ireland -- Iceland and that was the fastest way to get there.
So it was kind of breath-taking to come over the top of that -- of that set and see the style of it, you know.
And it gives you a lot -- I mean if we were just pouncing about on the sounds station in front of the green screen, that just wouldn't have been the same feeling, you know.
MCSHANE: Oh --
CROWE: To be able to stand on the interior set on the ground level and look up to the three-storey and feel the scale and the weight of the bird and I think it was -- you know, it brought a lot to it, without it, it would have been a very different experience.
BARTLETT: A very different experience, indeed. Russell Crowe here with us on out of context interviews, I'm Rob Bartlett.
(END AUDIO CLIP)
MCSHANE: All right, yes, Rob --
BERNARD MCGUIRK, EXECUTIVE PRODUCER, IMUS IN THE MORNING: Yes --
MCSHANE: That's good --
IMUS: I think it's funny, isn't it?
MCSHANE: Very --
DAGEN MCDOWELL, IMUS IN THE MORNING: Very --
(LAUGHTER)
IMUS: All right, well, we're talking about this morning a couple of books, one, "Flash Boys" --
MCSHANE: Michael Lewis, yes --
IMUS: Great title for a book by the way.
IMUS: And he is the same guy, he's an enormously talented writer --
UNIDENTIFIED MALE: Good to play --
IMUS: Who comes up with great ideas. He wrote "Moneyball", the Oakland Athletics deal, he wrote "The Blind Side", they made it a movie, that makes you -- I'm sure it was, and a number of other books he's written.
MCSHANE: Yes, "Liar's Poker", the first one is probably a lot more --
MCGUIRK: Let "The Big Short".
MCSHANE: That was after the financial --
MCGUIRK: Yes --
MCSHANE: Collapse, that's --
MCGUIRK: All right --
MCSHANE: That's the last time you had him on --
MCGUIRK: That's the one you had him on for --
IMUS: Yes --
MCGUIRK: You're right --
IMUS: So he's a charming guy and very affable and gregarious and so now he's written this five books which is about what?
MCSHANE: It's about high frequency trading on Wall Street where essentially according -- and again I haven't read this.
So I have to read the book but the "60 Minutes" piece basically said that these -- according to Mr. Lewis and it was his quote, "the stock market is rigged because of these high frequency traders."
IMUS: Right, and people like Neil Cavuto and others who do know something about it by the way --
MCSHANE: Yes --
IMUS: Say that that's not the case or not necessarily the case, except that I don't know that it was Mister -- hey, you know, book him, would you, Bernie?
MCGUIRK: Right away --
IMUS: Because I tell you why? He doesn't need the help to sell this book, his book is going to be number one instantly. But he is an interesting guy but I'm interested in knowing how this started.
I mean, did this guy -- what's his name? From -- the Canadian, what was his name?
MCSHANE: That's the guy --
MCDOWELL: I'll look it up --
MCGUIRK: Yes --
MCSHANE: One look more --
MCDOWELL: It's a Japanese --
MCGUIRK: Right --
MCDOWELL: Name, he works for the Royal Bank of Canada --
MCSHANE: Right --
IMUS: OK --
(CROSSTALK)
MCDOWELL: If about --
IMUS: So a very bright guy, whether -- because he was the guy who sort of discovered this and they got another Mathematician type involved in this, to try to figure out the technical part of it. Brilliant stuff, I mean but you know -- but may -- but I don't know. So --
MCSHANE: Yes, it's basically an allegation that there's legalized front- running going on that you --
MCDOWELL: Brad Katsuyama --
IMUS: OK, but --
MCDOWELL: Business trader --
IMUS: OK --
MCSHANE: Right --
IMUS: He is the guy -- he was the guy on "60 Minutes", so he has the same very little -- very legit -- just, I mean he is -- just some consumer watching this stuff.
But I'm wondering how they came -- why he -- how he discovered this. He tried to explain it but it's -- because they --
MCDOWELL: A trade --
IMUS: It's his -- it's his large trading firms gaining millisecond advantages over and perhaps only amounting to a penny or two.
MCDOWELL: Which adds up --
IMUS: Which adds up to hundreds of millions of dollars.
MCDOWELL: The trader at RBC first started investigating it because his orders were not getting filled at prices that made sense to him. And he is like why did that order get filled at that price?
And so he started investigating it, he was getting a bad deal -- a raw deal, essentially.
MCSHANE: It's like you want to buy a stock for 25 bucks and they've seen those $25.20, you know, hey, what happened?
MCDOWELL: Hey, where did that come from, right? --
MCSHANE: Right, because they get there before you do, they being these high frequency traders.
IMUS: And so they tell you that's what the price is or --
MCSHANE: Well, they drive it up, right? Because if you buy a stock, the demand -- and so you're driving up the price by --
MCGUIRK: Right --
MCSHANE: Buying it. So they buy it first, so then it goes up a few cents, next thing you try to buy it -- as you said, a millisecond later and it's a little bit higher than you thought it would be.
MCDOWELL: And by the way, the FBI is investigating this high speed trading that's been for a year --
IMUS: And probably most people acquiesce and say, well, OK --
MCSHANE: Absolutely --
IMUS: Because what's a few pennies except it can be a lot --
MCSHANE: True, well, he was even -- he wasn't even talking, I know a lot of attention is on like small investors, they were really talking about this big institutions really getting hurt by this.
And for them it's hundreds of millions of dollars a year or whatever that - -
MCDOWELL: It was --
MCSHANE: Did add up to --
MCDOWELL: He -- the people who weren't aware of it were some of the biggest investors in the country, if not the world. Major hedge funds, pension funds, mutual fund companies, they were getting screwed too.
Now they invest money for the little guy, but the little guy and the big guy who were getting the shaft.
MCSHANE: And now not to defend -- the thing about all this is and now all the Wall Street people are coming out, saying this is nonsense, it's an oversimplification.
And I feel like we can't really speak informed about it until we read the book and see what he said. But it does remind me a little bit of when "Moneyball" came out, and all the old baseball guys said, oh, yes.
So what he's talking about on base -- I mean and that is the way the baseball -- "Moneyball" drastically changed the way sports is run and the way baseball is run and basically everybody runs their team that way now.
And they will never admit it had anything to do with the book, they'll say, all right, we were to do it anyway or that's --
IMUS: And it had everything to do with the book.
MCSHANE: It had a lot of -- yes, I think it did, a lot of it did, a lot of it did --
IMUS: Well, Lewis, I don't know him, I mean we talked to him a couple of times but he doesn't seem to me to be some bomb-throwing nitwit --
MCSHANE: He's a great --
IMUS: At all --
MCSHANE: Great story-teller, terrific writer --
IMUS: Wonderful story, a wonderful writer --
MCSHANE: Right --
MCGUIRK: No agenda --
IMUS: He doesn't appear to have any agenda, does he?
MCSHANE: No --
MCGUIRK: He is independently wealthy, doesn't need anything --
IMUS: This is really cool. So, the other book, Wyatt ordered this book, it's this novel that Seth MacFarlane has written, the guy -- "Family Guy" guy based on a screen play of a movie that they've already done, right, Dagen?
MCDOWELL: Yes --
IMUS: The movie is called "A Million Ways to Die in the West". So the book is not doing anything for whatever reason. But I started to read it - - so Wyatt ordered that and the biography of Axl Rose for some reason.
He just finished Kurt Vonnegut's "Hocus Pocus", but big Vonnegut's fan. Anyway, so I started to read it, it's screamingly funny. I mean it's -- this may not be the right word, it's stupid funny -- it's just a scream.
MCSHANE: Right and youth --
IMUS: I mean if you think "Family Guy" is funny, which it is, and you just like this kind of stuff, it's written pretty well, but it is really funny.
MCSHANE: It's like made for you too, the whole thing. I mean you love Seth MacFarlane, the western stuff, I mean, come on --
IMUS: Oh, God, man, it's just -- but it's kind of a send-up of "Blazing Saddles", you know, the old Mel Brooks thing that they did a hundred years ago --
MCDOWELL: Farting(ph) is always funny --
IMUS: Which is funny then and it's funny now.
MCSHANE: Right --
IMUS: But do you like Seth MacFarlane, Lou?
LOU RUFINO, PROGRAM ENGINEER, IMUS IN THE MORNING: Yes, very much --
IMUS: Do you, Bernie?
RUFINO: "Family Guy" --
MCGUIRK: Oh, yes --
IMUS: Funny guy, isn't he?
MCGUIRK: He's more, yes, no doubt, absolutely.
IMUS: So I would recommend that you buy that book and you don't need me to recommend "Flash Boys" because it's already going to be --
MCSHANE: Yes --
IMUS: It will debut at number one, period. I mean, you can't be on "60 Minutes" and have a magazine piece in the "New York Times" this morning as well as a glowing review in this morning's "New York Times" and not being number one.
I mean, nothing else has to happen, so I'm very pleased with "HOLLYWOOD & VINE", it was very good.
MCSHANE: All right --
IMUS: Happy about that --
MCSHANE: Well done.
IMUS: And I went home yesterday and I turned on the IMUS IN THE MORNING program and watched it and I have re-evaluated my assessment yesterday, "IT MIGHT BE ELVIS" which I think is really funny, it was good.
And what was interesting about it, how good Trevor was.
MCSHANE: Trevor?
IMUS: Trevor is the musician and audio guy here at Fox and somebody asked my wife, well, how do these people who work on your husband's program get on the show, do they ask? No, they don't, no.
Well, how did Nat get on? I asked Nat to be on, and I asked Trevor and here's -- and like Gunz, Gunz was a behind the scenes guy. And here's -- you know how I discovered these people? By talking to them.
Because this sounds like a patronizing phrase and it's not. But it's stunning how many talented people there are on the other side from where I'm sitting.
MCSHANE: Right.
IMUS: And many -- and you know that happen -- it happens all the time.
MCSHANE: The other side of the glass.
IMUS: And somebody has to give -- somebody has to -- now I'm not riding around in a limo looking for people to help either by the way.
MCSHANE: Or the Escalade these days.
IMUS: Or the Escalade, yes, thank you --
MCSHANE: Yes, welcome.
IMUS: But I'm just looking for -- I'm just looking to do a great program. And then I see these people -- it's like -- as I was talking earlier this morning about Bernard and Lou, I mean it was my brother who discovered them.
You know, he was over back in the years ago at Fox or at "Fan", and Fred was sitting in the control room with Lou and Bernard and they were -- Bernard was funny anyway from the day at "Nbc" as an intern.
But -- they were saying funny, outrageous crazy things and Fred said, man, you ought to turn their mics on, these guys are hilarious and here you are.
MCSHANE: Yes, here you are --
IMUS: So you got to talk to people, I mean you can't --
MCSHANE: It's kind of funny right, certain irony in that you don't necessarily enjoy talking to people on the daily basis and then --
IMUS: Well, I'll give you another example, look at old Hannity. Now, Hannity, I accused him of some inappropriate conduct with old Ainsley, what's her name? Which was ridiculous, of course.
MCSHANE: Of course --
IMUS: Hannity is a happily married man and a good father and all that, but that poor little Ainsley.
She was just -- poor old thing was probably an intern or something and he gave her a chance on his show and used to take her on the road with him, and you do want to give her -- getting all this experience and all that --
MCSHANE: Yes, just --
IMUS: What's the matter?
MCSHANE: Nothing.
MCGUIRK: What happened?
MCSHANE: Nothing is the matter --
IMUS: And now she is an anchor on Fox News --
MCSHANE: Yes, she is --
IMUS: Well, there's another behind the scenes person --
MCSHANE: Yes, another wonderful story --
IMUS: In my case I reached out to help Gunz and --
MCSHANE: Yes --
IMUS: Trevor and Nat --
MCSHANE: Yes, right --
IMUS: All really unattractive men.
MCSHANE: Yes, especially Gunz.
IMUS: And Hannity of course had better sense --
(LAUGHTER)
If you see what I'm saying here.
MCSHANE: Yes, I'm sure, check your e-mail --
IMUS: It's 18 after the hour here on the IMUS IN THE MORNING program. By the way, what are we supposed to do? Did we do any news yet?
MCSHANE: No, I don't think we've done --
IMUS: Have we done any sports? Any business news, anything?
WARNER WOLF, SPORTS PRESENTER, IMUS IN THE MORNING: No --
MCDOWELL: No --
MCSHANE: We had that --
IMUS: No, I just have been talking for 18 minutes --
WOLF: Yes --
MCSHANE: Well, we had the Russell Crowe interview --
IMUS: Oh, yes, that, well, that's two minutes. So that's what -- I mean that's what all that's happened --
MCSHANE: That's all --
IMUS: Oh, man --
MCSHANE: All right, we can remember --
IMUS: Well --
MCSHANE: What do you want to do?
IMUS: No, I don't know. Yes, you got any --
MCSHANE: Yes --
IMUS: Quick news stuff?
MCSHANE: Everybody have any ideas? So the -- well, let's see here, there's a few headlines, this story in this "Washington Post" we haven't talked about this morning about the CIA that seems to be getting a lot of attention.
And this is from the "Post", report by the Senate Intelligence Committee concludes the CIA misled the government and the public about aspects of its interrogation program.
IMUS: Oh, this is -- this is not good.
MCSHANE: And according -- this story or something on your e-mail --
IMUS: Oh, something on my e-mail?
MCSHANE: Oh, OK --
MCDOWELL: Oh --
MCSHANE: Would you like to share it with us now? I mean we have --
IMUS: I will, yes --
MCSHANE: Plenty of time, so --
IMUS: This is from Michael Lynne, who is the guy -- movie guy.
MCSHANE: Sure --
IMUS: Who produced among many other films "Lord of the Rings" and all of those new line cinema movies going back to the "Ninja Turtles" --
MCSHANE: Right --
IMUS: That he and old Bob Shaye did, so he knows something about what's happening in --
MCSHANE: Sure --
IMUS: And he says Rob killed with the Russell Crowe bit.
MCSHANE: All right --
IMUS: Now that's --
MCGUIRK: Yes --
IMUS: High praise indeed from somebody who really didn't like Rob all that much.
(LAUGHTER)
MCSHANE: No, Jesus, it's got to be that --
IMUS: This is pretty good, I mean, isn't it?
MCSHANE: And it was really funny.
IMUS: It's funnier than I thought it was, you know --
MCSHANE: See --
IMUS: Let me see what Deirdre has to say --
MCSHANE: Oh, yes, sure, we have plenty -- oh, like I said, plenty of time, so --
IMUS: Yes, well, we'll get to this later.
MCSHANE: Don't push yourself here --
IMUS: You didn't have to introduce what Rob was doing, it was quite a -- well, just let me handle this, OK, Deirdre?
MCSHANE: Right --
IMUS: Hand me a little tasty snack fix when I get home.
(LAUGHTER)
What else?
MCSHANE: So the -- well, here is the quick thing, the Obamacare 7 million figure, the government -- the White House saying that's what the -- looks like they got to that by the deadline last night, unclear though how many have actually paid their first month's premium, so there'll be more on that.
United States said to be talking to Israel about releasing the convicted spy Jonathan Pollard, give the Israelis incentive on the peace talk.
Although there was word from an Israeli cabinet minister this morning, Pollard himself as opposed to being released if it's in exchange for the release of Palestinian prisoners.
And the death toll from the Washington State mudslide now up to 24 officially. So there's still some bodies not identified and 22 people listed as missing.
And the search continues for the Malaysian plane, visibility as well and the weather is rough out --
IMUS: All right, time for a little business news and here with that is Dagen McDowell, what's going on, Dagen?
MCDOWELL: Right, good morning, sir. The Futures are up 41 points on the Dow Futures to start a new quarter.
Two pieces of news. Chrysler sales were up 13 percent, we're getting auto sales today for last month that was better-than-expected --
IMUS: Even though there -- it was GM, now GM cars are killing people, right?
MCDOWELL: Well, there were 13 deaths related to this ignition switch default.
IMUS: Well, that's what -- that's people, 13 --
MCDOWELL: Yes, and --
IMUS: Dead people as a result of the cars --
MCDOWELL: There's a hearing -- there's a hearing today on Capitol Hill, 2:00 p.m. Eastern Time on that note --
IMUS: How many people were injured in it?
MCDOWELL: I don't know how many people were injured. There were 31 --
IMUS: Can we find that out? --
MCDOWELL: Thirty one crashes --
IMUS: That's right --
MCDOWELL: And 13 deaths I believe --
IMUS: And they already -- they knew something wrong, they didn't do anything about it, did they?
MCDOWELL: They knew there was a defect for more than a decade.
IMUS: Why are you trying to cover up for them?
MCDOWELL: No, I'm just stating the facts.
MCSHANE: Yes --
IMUS: Well, we didn't -- we're not interested in that here --
MCSHANE: Facts --
IMUS: The facts, no --
MCSHANE: No --
IMUS: Twenty one after the hour, time for sports sponsored by Peerless Boilers and here with that is Warner Wolf, good morning, Warner.
WOLF: Good morning, i-man. Full house, 42,000, Citi Field, the Mets Bullpen blew ninth-inning lead then lost in the tenth to the Nats 9 to 7, Mets batter struck out 18 times. The Mets by the way have picked up 40- year-old Bobby Abreu --
MCSHANE: All right --
RUFINO: Yes --
WOLF: Who hasn't played in two years?
RUFINO: Oh --
MCSHANE: Yes, give him a chance.
WOLF: The Yankees --
IMUS: How that -- how that new acquisition Curtis Granderson do?
WOLF: Zero for five, struck out three times, grounded out and lined out.
MCGUIRK: The Grande man here --
MCSHANE: Grande man attached --
IMUS: Well, didn't -- Nat was in here wearing his jersey --
WOLF: Yes --
IMUS: The last "VINNY from QUEENS" --
WOLF: Yes, he just --
MCSHANE: Of course --
WOLF: Sold it --
MCSHANE: Oh --
IMUS: That aint right, is it?
WOLF: No --
MCGUIRK: It's me --
IMUS: All right, what else?
WOLF: And the Yankees play in Houston tonight --
IMUS: Yes --
WOLF: Astros manager Bo Porter after having the worst record in baseball last year has put a mirror in each player's locker room, cubicle, so they'll have to look at themselves in the face before every game.
MCSHANE: Yes --
IMUS: Look themselves in the face, so --
WOLF: Yes --
IMUS: That's where they would look, yes --
WOLF: That's right, i-man --
MCSHANE: Let's hope --
MCGUIRK: See who is sneaking --
IMUS: Because I admit, I initially thought it was to cut their cocaine on but apparently not --
WOLF: Oh, no --
IMUS: Twenty two after the hour, Bernie, what's coming up in the briefing?
MCGUIRK: Ugliness on the "Good Morning America" set.
IMUS: Oh, that sounds great. I love this girl, Brandy Clark, great song writer, pretty good singer herself, come on, girl.
(MUSIC)
IMUS: Oh, that's good. That is not good. What'll keep me out of heaven going to take me there tonight. We've been down that road, that's your baby.
Well, take one look at those bags under your eyes because today is the last day you need to stare back at that. Speaking of putting a mirror in your cubicle.
MCSHANE: OK --
IMUS: Thanks to Genucel, those bags are going to disappear on you naturally and without surgery.
The new Genucel stem cell therapy for bags and puffiness under the eyes for my friends at Chamonix is doing just that for the men and the women all across this great country of ours.
Jersey girl, overall, so she wrote him a letter, she said I felt the bags under my eyes firm up and my skin is glowing, your product helped me reduce the puffiness immediately and in a few weeks.
I stopped using concealer because of the improvement, actually I'm going a week without applying heavy make-up. I would recommend it to anyone I've noticed a great difference.
Genucel guarantees that you'll see a difference within 12 hours or they will give you your money back, that's Chamonix, that's what they are, there're some good people there.
So call them at 800-754-6980, 800-754-6980, have you called them this morning, these fools will throw in a jug of Esotique which is not cheap stuff, the skin cream deal.
So call them, 800-754-6980.
ROTHMAN: And good morning. Chrysler is out with its latest sales numbers for the month of March. Chrysler saying sales rose 13 percent last month compared with this month a year ago.
Now the estimate was for a gain of 11.1 percent according to Edmunds. Chrysler saw an 11 percent rise in February. Sales of Ram Pickups jumped 26 percent for their best March sales in 10 years.
The Jeep brand had its best sales month ever up 47 percent. Checking Futures after yesterday's rally, we're looking at a higher open, but Dow Futures up 40 points at the moment.
IMUS IN THE MORNING continues right now on Fox Business, giving you the power to prosper.
IMUS: You know, I didn't realize that, man, I can't -- but I can't -- I don't think I broke anything.
MCGUIRK: When did this happen, boss?
IMUS: Saturday night.
MCSHANE: Oh, man --
MCGUIRK: Oh --
TOM BOWMAN, PRODUCER, IMUS IN THE MORNING: What did you trip over?
IMUS: My oxygen hose.
MCSHANE: Oh, Jesus --
MCGUIRK: Yes --
(LAUGHTER)
MCSHANE: It's not --
IMUS: Oh, I --
MCSHANE: Son of a --
MCGUIRK: Hey --
IMUS: I don't know --
WOLF: Not good --
IMUS: I tripped on something, I tripped on a rug or whatever.
MCSHANE: Is that funny to you guys?
IMUS: It doesn't -- I mean what I tripped on?
MCSHANE: What are you guys laughing at?
RUFINO: It's not -- it's not time at all --
IMUS: How is this amusing?
MCGUIRK: Yes --
MCSHANE: Yes --
MCGUIRK: Twenty years ago you were tripping on like acid. Now.
(CROSSTALK)
(LAUGHTER)
IMUS: Thirty minutes past the hour here on IMUS IN THE MORNING program. Juan Williams (Inaudible) is coming up. We will talk to that dude about what is happening. So, I wonder who he is Mount Rushmore? However, we will find out (ph). Well, Bernie doing a Bernie Briefing sponsored by My Pillow. And here he is now. Bernard McGuirk. Good morning, Mr. McGuirk.
MCGUIRK: Good morning, Mr. Imus. Stephen Colbert (ph) last week undercover of attacking the Washington Redskins, and their team name. He created this Ching Chong Ding Dong Foundation for Sensitivity to Orientals or Whatever, and aired this last week. Take a listen.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
STEPHEN COLBERT: My beloved character Ching Chong Ding Dong. Whoohoo, I rove tea. It's so good for you. You pretty American girl. You come here and kiss my tea and make all sweet.
(LAUGHTER)
COLBERT: I need no sugar (ph) when you're around. Come on. I give you a ride to Bangkok.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
MCGUIRK: He took a lot of heat for that, and last night he sort of capitulated and spent about 20 minutes on the topic, but here is less than a minute of a -- towards the end of the upshot of what he said. Take a listen.
(BEGIN VIDEO CLIP)
COLBERT: But, the people have called for cancelling Colbert (ph), and I'm willing to meet them halfway. Effective immediately, and I cannot believe I am saying this, I am shutting down the worldwide operations of the Ching Chong Ding Dong Foundation for Sensitivity to Orientals or Whatever. I have to. I can tell how sad you are about it. You are a little late with that.
(LAUGHTER)
COLBERT: Now, the saddest part is because of all the attention we raised a lot of money over the weekend. Money that will now, be donated to Dan Snyder's Washington Redskins Original American Foundation, which twitter seems to be fine with because I haven't seen (BLEEP) about that. That ends that controversy. I just pray that no one ever tweets about the time I said Rosa Parks was overrated, Hitler has some good ideas, or ran a cartoon during black history month showing President Obama teaming up with the Ku Klux Klan, because, man, that sounds pretty bad out of context.
(END VIDEO CLIP)
MCGUIRK: And that ends that controversy. Now, listen, there is some ugliness on the set of Good Morning America even though, you know, Josh Elliott, who is by all accounts just a fat D-bag, according to page6 and other reports.
IMUS: That's pretty harsh, isn't it?
MCGUIRK: That's essentially what they said.
IMUS: On what basis?
MCGUIRK: They say the people behind the scenes say he smiles on air and he's nice, but off air, he's a real blank (ph) whole. That's according to page 6 yesterday, on the New York Post.
IMUS: You mean to the peeps on the show?
MCGUIRK: That's right. And now, that he's -- he and Sam Champion are on NBC, the hated Matt Lauer and the almost as much hated Al Roker, they're looking over their shoulders. Any way, there is ugliness there, and that's all good. We like that, but the New York Daily News reports this morning that Elliott's replacement, Amy Robach, is very, very disliked by Laura Spencer, who she has work with. They are all angry that Rob and Robert make 40 million a year, and they are making about $2 million a year, so there's ugliness on that set.
IMUS: Well, Rob and Roberts is worth that.
MCGUIRK: Yeah. And they are all angry about it. That they're making.
(CROSSTALK)
IMUS: Why? Because she's worth that?
MCGUIRK: Well, I think, apparently, Josh Elliott as well, they think that they contribute as much as she did, but clearly that's not case.
IMUS: It's not the case.
MCGUIRK: Without a doubt.
IMUS: Yeah.
MCGUIRK: So, they're off -- he's off the show because of that. And these girls are all angry. They all hate each other.
IMUS: Laura Spencer, who is that?
MCGUIRK: She is one of the co-hosts on Good Morning America.
IMUS: She doesn't like Amy?
MCGUIRK: She does not like Amy, not according to the New York Daily News this morning. In fact.
IMUS: Who's better looking, Amy or her?
MCGUIRK: It's a toss up.
IMUS: Oh, yeah.
MCGUIRK: Here's a quote from the Daily News quote, Robach and Spencer don't get along, and now, they must share desk space. Laura was furious when she heard the news, unquote, about Robach, taking over for Josh Elliott.
IMUS: A shot of Amy on the Fox Business network.
MCGUIRK: Yes. She's beautiful.
IMUS: Nice girl, too. She moved over (ph) to MSNBC.
MCGUIRK: She first works in Morning News on the IMUS IN THE MORNING program. That's a fact.
IMUS: She is good, too.
MCGUIRK: Speaking of good-looking people, Juan Williams is coming up. I won't take up any more of his time.
IMUS: We will talk to him. All right.
Don: This is the IMUS IN THE MORNING program, on the Fox Business network. Now, here's Lori Rothman.
LORI ROTHMAN: Good morning. Our top story, the CEO of General Motors is apologizing for the ignition switch defect that has been linked to at least a dozen deaths, leading to that massive recall. Mary Bar is due to testify today, before a house subcommittee about the problem. She's expected to face tough questions from lawmakers on why GM waited more than a decade to recall vehicles due to faulty switches and problems with airbags and break parts. Federal regulators will also be on the hot seat according to preliminary findings. Congressional investigation found the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, twice failed to investigate complaints and crash reports about GM cars. Bars, also due to testify before the senate tomorrow, which is holding its own hearing, late yesterday GM announced, it is recalling another 1.3 million vehicles to fix a problem with the power steering. The automakers recalling now a total of more than 6.3 million vehicles.
Well, speaking of cars, Chrysler's out with its sales numbers for March. The company says sales rose 13 percent last month compared to a year ago. The estimate was for a gain of 11.1 percent according to admin (ph), so the improvement for (Inaudible) month over month. The company saw an 11 percent rise in February.
Now, sales of Ram pickups jumped 26 percent for their best March sales in ten years and the Jeep brand had its best sales month ever up 47 percent. So, we're gonna get car sale figures through out the day. Here sales at Ford cars is expected to rise 1.6 percent. The estimate for GM sales is for only an increase of half of 1 percent.
Checking futures, after yesterday's U.S. stock market rally they are adjusting a higher open, again with the Dow Futures up 30 points. IMUS IN THE MORNING continues after this now on Fox Business, giving you the power to prosper.
IMUS: Twenty minutes till the hour here in the IMUS IN THE MORNING program. Fox news contributor Juan Williams is on the phone. Good morning, Mr. Williams.
JUAN WILLIAMS, FOX NEWS CONTRIBUTOR: Good morning, Mr. Imus.
IMUS: Hey, Big foot, who was alerted you to this anniversary?
TOM BOWMAN: Our technical director here is Stew.
IMUS: So, Juan, did you know that according to do Stew -- because on your Musical Mt. Rushmore which we already discussed, you have Marvin Gaye and today is the 30th anniversary of his death.
WILLIAMS: It was a pretty awful death, too, his father shine.
IMUS: Yeah. Do you know why he shot him?
WILLIAMS: You know I think it had been a long argument over money and over management issues, but, I mean, I think it -- I you know, I'm not an expert on Marvin Gaye, but I live here in DC, so I hear a lot of, if -- you know you can walk by murals and tributes to him. And the father was a minister so many of this things comes out of the church, but apparently, he always felt that his son didn't have enough respect. He wasn't giving him enough money.
IMUS: His father shooting him was hardly a solution.
WILLIAMS: I'm telling you, you know it was pretty awful.
IMUS: I don't get that. I don't know why people do that.
WILLIAMS: No, you know, now that you said it, also on my Mt Rushmore was Sam Cooke. He got shot, too.
IMUS: In a motel.
WILLIAMS: Yes. He was with a hooker I guess and he asked something of the motel clerk and the motel clerk didn't like it or something, and he shot him at once.
IMUS: How do we know it was a hooker?
WILLIAMS: Again, I'm not an expert. I don't pretend, but that's the story.
IMUS: I bet he could sing, could be? The both could.
(LAUGHTER)
IMUS: And if you run a football team would you drop Johnny Mandel?
WILLIAMS: Not number one or not the first round, no.
IMUS: Really?
WILLIAMS: No.
IMUS: Why?
WILLIAMS: You know, he's magical. I'll say that for him, but it sure reminds me of that player the New York Jets that didn't work out.
IMUS: Who is that?
WILLIAMS: What his name? I can't remember.
IMUS: Tebow.
MCSHANE: Tebow.
IMUS: Tebow.
WILLIAMS: Tebow, yeah. It looks like a little too much you know and also I think there would be so much pressure on the Texans for the number one pick. And here - they're being pushed to draft, but then -- so, they got to put the kid in and he has to start right away he's on the sideline the guy starting is under pressure to get out a way. I think it's an invitation to a lot of headaches that you don't need if you trying to run a football team.
IMUS: He's a lot different college football player than Tim Tebow.
WILLIAMS: Oh. I think Tim Tebow was pretty successful.
IMUS: Yeah, I know. He was but not successful throwing the ball like (Inaudible).
WILLIAM: No, I think Johnny Mandel is more -- more of a natural to me, but Tim Tebow is kind of tremendous body, very strong and very, very much a guy who -- you know, if you're putting a team together you say I want that guy I think that guy is a winner. It didn't turn out that way and in the NFL you really do have to have a throwing skills that you're talking about, I- man. But you know, now, everybody gonna to put down Tim Tebow, but he was a terminus athlete.
IMUS: I always wonder, these people who -- and I think its fine, obviously. But, these people who thank Jesus every time something happens right for them. I don't think they blame Jesus when it doesn't go well.
(LAUGHTER)
WILLIAMS: God is on our side.
(LAUGHTER)
WILLIAMS: I'm glad he is not on the other guy.
IMUS: Yeah.
WILLIAMS: Well, you know, I find that juvenile and I think it's a perversion of Christianity, but you know let it be. But anyway, that's not why you would it draft Tim Tebow, is it?
IMUS: No.
WILLIAMS: OK. So, what do think? I'm so curious about what you think about letting this guy, Pollard, out of jail so we can get a deal with the Israelis.
IMUS: Well, how else will we get the deal?
WILLIAMS: We can get the deal. I mean, come on now, if the deal is fragile, but I don't know. I just think there are a lot of people in the intelligence community who will be very upset. I think gonna bite their tongues because of these -- as I understand he is scheduled to get out of jail in the next year or 2015. And they say he's sick, who knows if he's sick, whatever, but I don't know. I just think that it's a bad sign when you start you know letting spies out. But if it makes for a deal, that's a greater good. I can understand that. I just wondered how you felt about it.
IMUS: A lot of people are dead as a result to him, are they?
WILLIAMS: That's the argument. I don't remember all the details. But certainly, people were damaged. Intelligence operations -- can speak were revealed as a result of his action.
IMUS: I don't know. Bernie, what you think?
MCGUIRK: Well, I don't like it. But, we have to look into it.
IMUS: Bernie is about half-paying attention, Juan.
(LAUGHTER)
MCGUIRK: I'm all over this Jonathan Pollard thing. They haven't trying to get him out for years and years, but they say because he was fined for the Israelis it's not really -- it wasn't a big threat and we should let him out, but still, he was working for our spy agency and he spied on us, and gave away our secrets and you can't be having that.
WILLIAMS: No, and I think in the age of Snowden -- you know, people are supposed be on your side and then they you know turn your back on you and I don't like it. You can't play ball like that. You -- you got to have some loyalty on your team.
IMUS: You would think. Yeah. Well, now that I have consulted you and Bernard, I'm against it.
MCSHANE: There you go.
IMUS: I am not paying much attention to it to be honest.
WILLIAMS: It's a real intelligence being around DC today because -- you know, the fight between the Senate Intelligence Committee and the CIA. So, in the newspaper in the Washington Post this morning, anyway, there is a story that says that the CIA was spying on that Intel committee. Senator Feinstein is complaining and all that because the Intel committee now has concluded that the CIA was misleading everyone about the effectiveness of their interrogations/torture program. They actually -- the program wasn't getting anything out of anybody. And the CIA didn't want people to know this.
So, now, this thing is gonna get ramped up and now you gonna have more of an argument between the politicians and the intelligence agency and to get back to the Pollard thing, I-man, it's the intelligence agency who would have to complain to the congress and President Obama about releasing Pollard.
So, all of a sudden, intelligences right in the middle, right in the bull's eye of our politics.
IMUS: Who's in charge?
Williams: Well, you know, things have changed. It used to be the CIA director was in charge and now, the director of national intelligence is in charge and ultimately, the president in charge.
IMUS: It doesn't seem like anybody is in charge.
WILLIAMS: And it is so out of control. Especially after 9/11, we -- you know, they tried to reform the intelligence agency they tried to consolidate then they created Homeland Security, you know the relationship between FBI and CIA is still tenuous, but who's in charge? I hadn't thought of it. That's really an intelligent question. Because you have to have somebody that you go to who tries to direct and coordinate how we do intelligence and don't forget the military is part of this. They had their own intelligence operation.
IMUS: Exactly. And who is saying stop doing this or start doing it? Nobody. And here's something even more outrageous, Bo Dietl is in here yesterday screaming about -- and he was absolutely right, it's more I was gonna say symbolic, but they may be not the case. But down here at the New World Trade Center that these guys sneak in there and climb up there and jump off the top it, while the guards were asleep.
(LAUGHTER)
IMUS: I'm not blaming it on the president, but maybe I am. I mean, it starts their. It starts with the example and not just the president, but I mean, the people on the other side of the aisle are equally complicit in all of this, but it trickles down from the top and it trickles down to having some dork -- (inaudible) when I do.
MCSHANE: Yeah.
IMUS: Asleep at the World Trade Center. I mean, that's insane, isn't it?
WILLIAMS: It sounds so ridiculous. It sound like you would have to make it up.
IMUS: Yeah.
WILLIAMS: And people would say it's not believable and then throw it in, you can't go anywhere without a camera tracing you these days or you go through security. I mean, anywhere even to get into a school. And I think - - you know, the whole -- the whole intelligence security apparatus in our country is out of control and then you have this guy sleeping at the wheel.
IMUS: Oh, man.
WILLIAMS: At the World Trade Center. Is that crazy?
IMUS: Sleeping at the switch at the Oval Office is where it starts.
WILLIAMS: Oh, man.
IMUS: Oh, baby. Thank you. Juan Williams here on the IMUS IN MORNING program. Coming up on 10 till the hour.
ROTHMAN: Good morning. Listen to this, Facebook CEO Mark Zuckerberg, reap $3.3 billion gain last year by exercising stock options in the social networking company. Meanwhile, Facebook paid him about 650,000 in 2013. And that includes a base salary of $1 which is down 67 percent from 2012. Because Zuckerberg declined to participate in the bonus plan for the year. Now, in 2012, Zuckerberg received a total comp of about $2 million from Facebook.
Minutes away from Opening Bell with Maria Bartiromo. Here she is with the preview. Good morning, Maria.
BARTIROMO: Hi, Lori. Thanks. At the top of the hour on Opening Bell, GM's new CEO in Washington today, answering questions about the recall crisis. The FBI now looking into high frequency trading and Apple has a new ideas for a new iPhone. Plus, Priceline's founder Jay Walker talks technology innovation with me. Plus, April is traditionally a good month for investors. But will that hold true in this market environment? Join me at the top of the hour for Opening Bell. I'll see you then. Back to you, Lori.
ROTHMAN: Thank you, Maria. Ahead of that, futures are pointing to a higher open for the U.S. stock market today. Oil and gold prices are steady. IMUS IN THE MORNING continues right now on Fox Business, giving you the power to prosper.
IMUS: I was telling Bernie and Lou and Connell, I walked out of the studio yesterday. So, I have security, of course, and Brandt gets out of the car and he opens the door. So, but meanwhile, a guy starts talking to me. So, I don't know. I mean, he seemed okay, but you'll never know.
MCSHANE: Yeah. Just some guy on the street.
IMUS: Yeah.
MCSHANE: Right.
IMUS: So, he follows me to the car.
MCSHANE: OK.
IMUS: So, I get in the car thinking that Brandt is gonna close the door.
MCSHANE: Right.
IMUS: But, no, like the moron that he is, he stands there with the door open.
MCSHANE: So, the guy can continue.
IMUS: So, the guy can continue to.
(LAUGHTER)
RUFINO: Great.
MCGUIRK: Because he didn't know. He thought maybe the guy was legit. Maybe somebody you knew, or somebody from Fox, could be.
RUFINO: Nice coat.
RUFINO: Need a ride? We're going uptown.
MCSHANE: One thing's for sure, I'm sure you took it in stride?
IMUS: No, I mean I'd fire him, but what's the point? I've fired him a hundred times. The last thing on his mind is.
(LAUGHTER)
MCSHANE: He's outside right now.
IMUS: He's parked out there now.
RUFINO: Only got two people sitting there getting warm.
(LAUGHTER)
MCGUIRK: Hey, Brandt.
RUFINO: I'm not leaving for an hour, you can sit in the back.
IMUS: If I say to him we're gonna go someplace and he doesn't know where it is. He doesn't have the initiative to find out where it is.
MCSHANE: The initiative.
IMUS: I can't tell you how many times that happen.
MCSHANE: The Initiative. Wouldn't be that GPS these days?
IMUS: You would think. Yeah, he doesn't even do that.
MCSHANE: OK.
IMUS: One time he, and then one time. He decides, now, I used to live in -- used to have a house in Connecticut in West Port -- South Port. So, and we'd go there every weekend for, I don't know, 20 years.
MCSHANE: Right.
IMUS: Twenty years, at least. So, he gets a new -- we had a sponsor called TomTom or something, the GPS deal.
MCSHANE: Yeah, yeah.
IMUS: So, he gets it. And you can program it a number of different ways.
MCSHANE: Right.
IMUS: So, here comes Friday, we're going to west port, wherever we're going and I think we went to Bruckner for some reason, and he got off and got on some local road.
RUFINO: That's a good area.
MCSHANE: Maybe a shortcut.
(LAUGHTER)
IMUS: So, he gets on a Bonfire Vanities deal.
RUFINO: It's exactly where it was.
MCSHANE: He just randomly gets off in the Bronx somewhere or something right.
IMUS: He has programmed it to take local roads.
(LAUGHTER)
IMUS: So, you either go I-95 or the Merit Parkway, there's no other way to go.
MCSHANE: Maybe he doesn't like driving on the highway.
MCGUIRK: He gets off the Bruckner.
IMUS: Really unbelievable.
MCGUIRK: The guy yesterday. The beer in the paper bag. That should have been a tip-off.
RUFINO: Want to stop off at White Castles sir.
IMUS: Has the statue of Dan Marino diminished in your eyes Warner because of this?
WOLF: No, look, he's not a deadbeat dad. I think that's a plus for him. It's not right, of course, what he did because he was married.
IMUS: Why don't you go home and see if how Mrs. Wolf feels about that?
WOLF: That's good.
IMUS: Why don't you go home and tell her you have a love child and see what she thinks.
WOLF: Look, the flesh is weak. I mean, like the Bible says, who are we to throw stones are.
IMUS: OK.
WOLF: Right?
IMUS: Something you want to tell us?
WOLF: No.
IMUS: Well, it sounds to me like you're inching up on something.
WOLF: I have no love child that I know about.
IMUS: And Bernie is out there.
MCGUIRK: Gunz doesn't look like Warner.
IMUS: Hey, Gunz.
GUNZELMAN: What's up, baby?
IMUS: Is Warner your dad?
GUNZELMAN: Ah, possibly. You never know.
(LAUGHTER)
RUFINO: Definitely, not.
(LAUGHTER)
GUNZELMAN: Where am I?
MCSHANE: Look at the two of them over there.
]]></text></news-item>