<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-0CH1-F06S-P4D5"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Research and Markets Adds Report: Analyzing the Global Tobacco Industry</title><source>Professional Services Close-Up</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Research and Markets has announced the addition of the "Analyzing the Global Tobacco Industry" report to its offerings.
In a release, Research and Markets noted that report highlights include:
There is no denying the fact that in spite of a global economic downturn, lawsuits, health problems, and rising prices of cigarettes, the global tobacco industry has continued to generate strong growth as well as profits. Many legal problems continue to plague the global tobacco industry as governments around the world continue to put in place strict regulations to curb the use of tobacco. The health impact of tobacco are many and many smokers are suffering from cancer or other side effects of tobacco consumption.
For the global tobacco industry we analyze the industry through an industry definition, industry overview wherein we look at the market statistics, an industry value analysis, industry segmentation, regional share of the industry, industry distribution, along with an analysis of the competition in the industry and company market share. Future of the global tobacco industry is also analyzed.
For each of the country profiles, we analyze the tobacco market through an industry overview, industry value analysis, industry segmentation, regional share analysis, industry distribution, market competition, major players in the market and their market share, as well as an analysis of the future of the tobacco market in the country.
Major players in the industry are analyzed through a company overview, business segment analysis, financial analysis, and a SWOT analysis.
With tobacco being one of the most commonly used addictive substances in the world, the industry will continue to grow in the coming years, though the growth is going to be faced with many challenges as countries put in place stringent laws to combat the health effects of consuming tobacco. Aruvians Rsearch's analysis of the global tobacco industry is a comprehensive analysis of the industry.
Companies Mentioned
-Altria Group, Inc
-Amergon Corp.
-British American Tobacco Plc
-China National Tobacco Corp.
-Cojimar Cigar Co.
-Godfrey Phillips India
-Golden Tobacco Limited
-Imperial Tobacco Group PLC
-ITC Limited
-Japan Tobacco Inc.
-Korea Tobacco & Ginseng Corp.
-Langaard
-Lorillard
-Philip Morris International Inc.
-Reynolds American, Inc.
-Scandinavian Tobacco Group
-Souza Cruz SA
-Swedish Match AB
-Taiwan Tobacco and Liquor
Research and Markets is a source for international market research reports.
((Comments on this story may be sent to newsdesk@closeupmedia.com))
]]></text></news-item>