<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-90B1-JCB3-40TC"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Officials: Pan Am to be fined for Westford derailment</title><source>Lowell Sun (Massachusetts)</source><author>By Samantha Allen , sallen@lowellsun.com</author><text><![CDATA[WESTFORD -- Federal Railroad Administration officials have determined the train derailment in February was caused by a track issue and Pan Am Railways will be fined.
According to Rep. Niki Tsongas' office, FRA inspectors went to the site of the train derailment on Bridge Street in the Graniteville neighborhood following an incident Feb. 19, where five cars slipped off the track. After walking the site, the administration determined there was a "wide gage" track condition. Pan Am, based in Billerica, will be charged with a violation for that issue which generally carries a $5,000 fine, according to Tsongas' Regional Director Jane Adams. Town Manager Jodi Ross said she was made aware of the development last Wednesday.
Around 11 p.m. Feb. 19, cars slipped off their track right over the town's Stony Brook aquifer, two of which were carrying liquid-petroleum gas, a chemical with a risk for explosion. A Pan Am representative said town officials were not notified of the event then because it was not an "urgent matter" but when town officials learned of the incident the next morning, they readied the neighborhood for evacuation and set up shelters.
Ross has been openly critical of the corporation since the incident for not notifying the town of the event. She said on the day of the derailment, she only learned of the situation when Westford Fire Chief Joe Targ happened to drive by the scene. The cars appeared to be leaning over a bridge above the town brook in Graniteville.
Once on scene, Ross said she and Targ were ordered by Rail General Manager Luke McCaul to get off the tracks. Ross said they were told they were trespassing even after the two identified themselves as Westford officials; she added Police Chief Tom McEnaney then called to inform her he was contacted by Boston and Maine Railroad Police for reports of trespassers near the cars.
"I was not happy about that," Ross said in an interview in February.
Pan Am officials told The Sun they would conclude their investigation on what caused the accident some time in late February. The corporation has yet to comment on the situation and has not returned multiple calls to The Sun on the matter in the last several weeks.
Pan Am Vice President Cynthia Scarano spoke at a selectmen's meeting this week in Greenland, N.H., according toSeacoastonline.com , in which she stated "every regulation was followed" in the Westford derailment case. The news organization reports on Monday, New Hampshire residents voiced their concerns at a meeting related to Pan Am's proposal to increase a number of their cars carrying propane through the area there. Greenland officials said at that time they worried about the company's communication and "trust" issues, citing the Westford incident as an example.
Since the Westford incident, the state Department of Environmental Protection has voiced their concerns for the threat of contamination at the Bridge Street site. Pan Am must now perform "immediate-response actions" to evaluate the situation. Local politicians from the state and congressional delegation, including U.S. Sens. Ed Markey and Elizabeth Warren, have also insisted Pan Am President David Fink meet with Westford officials; they sent out a letter making the request last week.
Sen. Eileen Donoghue, D-Lowell, said Tuesday she hopes a meeting will be held soon so officials can talk openly on issues of transparency and Pan Am's operations. Donoghue said when she was mayor of Lowell and on the City Council, there were issues with Pan Am running cars through the southern part of the Mill City as well.
"It's a very serious and frustrating issue for the residents and (Westford) and also for the public-safety folks," she said. "It's not just about getting to the bottom of what happened and what's being done about it, but what we are going to do in the future."
Rep. James Arciero, D-Westford, said in a statement to The Sun Tuesday he has "serious concerns" regarding the conduct of Pan Am officials since the derailment. He questioned the company's "professional competence" as well as their "moral integrity."
"It is unacceptable, given the long history of the citizens of Westford in bearing the burden of idling, noisy trains in their neighborhoods, to be treated in this manner," Arciero said. "Protection of our public safety and water supply are not to be taken lightly."
Charlie Banks, a rail expert and president of R.L. Banks and Associates in Virginia, explained the widened gage issue reported by the FRA is related to space forming between train wheels and tracks, which can lead to equipment going off-kilter and trains slipping off tracks. Banks said this can be caused by many things, including weather or poor track maintenance. He added since a company like Pan Am owns their own tracks, it's the company's responsibility to maintain it.
"Was this something that happened as a result of weather, or was it a failure on the part of one or more employees of Pan Am to follow their own rules?" Banks posed.
According to the Journal of Wheel/Rail Interaction from 2004, the wide-gage code is cited nearly 30 percent of the time in all track-related derailments.
Follow Samantha Allen on Twitter and Tout @SAllen_89.
]]></text></news-item>