<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-KC51-DYTJ-40MM"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>PROSECUTORS FOUND UNREGISTERED DIAMONDS AT ZVEZDOCHKA</title><source>DEFENSE and SECURITY (Russia)</source><author>Pavel Kochegarov</author><text><![CDATA[Prosecutor's office of Archangelsk Region presumed that a workshop for processing of diamonds that worked at the plant illegally produced and sold precious stones because it did not submit reports about the deals struck to Rosfinmonitoring contrary to the law on counteraction to money laundering.
Prosecutors found breaches at the diamond plant at Zvezdochka that produced and sold precious stones during a preplanned inspection. According to prosecutors, employees of the plant made numerous breaches that were subject to administrative article "Non-observance of requirements of the law about counteraction to legalization (laundering) of the incomes received in a criminal way" (article 15.27 of the Code of Administrative Breaches). According to this article, a legal entity may get a penalty from 500,000 rubles to 1 million rubles or administrative suspension of operations for up to 90Ê days.
The press service of the prosecutor's office of Archangelsk Region, reported:
- A plant for rectal sale of jewelry was opened at the plant. According to the law, they had to send financial reports to Rosfinmonitoring in three days after striking of the deal but these deadlines were not followed.
Prosecutors found out that information about deals with precious stones came to Rosfinmonitoring with delay or was not sent there at all.
Representatives of the prosecutor's office added:
- Thus, it turned out that jewelry pieces were made actually illegally. The general director of the plant was ordered to eliminate all breaches of the administrative law.
All documents of the case were sent to the northern inspectorate of the assay supervision of the state assay chamber of the Finance Ministry for hearing in essence. It is impossible to rule out that the administrative case may end with criminal persecution for executives of the plant.
Representatives of the shipyard say that they do not recognize the claims of the prosecutor's office and promise to eliminate the breaches in the shortest possible time.
The press service of Zvezdochka reported:
- Critique from the prosecutor's office has been received, we will eliminate the breaches. This was a single case in preparation of documentation and there would be no such breaches anymore.
Zvezdochka is one of the biggest Russian ship repair enterprises. Along with the Northern machine-building enterprise it is one of the two main employers of Severodvinsk being parts of United Shipbuilding Corporation. The company specializes in shipbuilding and ship repair, construction of ship platforms, production of rowing propellers for various purposes. Zvezdochka also specializes in repair and liquidation of nuclear submarines. Vladimir Nikitin has headed the plant for six years.
A jewelry workshop was opened at Zvezdochka in 2000 when a big diamond deposit was found not far from Archangelsk and faculties were required to start cutting the diamonds. In 2004, the plant put into operation a full production cycle of its own line of jewelry.
Source: Izvestia (Moscow issue), March 31, 2014, p. 7
]]></text></news-item>