<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-16P1-F0K1-N20S"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>US Department of Labor's OSHA cites Garfield, NJ, masonry contractor for repeat fall and scaffolding hazards</title><source>M2 PressWIRE</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[March 31, 2014GARFIELD, N.J. -- The U.S. Department of Labor's Occupational Safety and Health Administration has cited Garfield-based East Coast Stucco & Construction Inc. for fall and scaffolding hazards found at a work site in North Brunswick, where a two-story restaurant was under construction. OSHA's November 2013 inspection was prompted by safety and health complaints regarding lack of fall protection at the site. Proposed penalties total $ 58,520 and include four violations for repeatedly putting workers at risk.
"This employer is well aware that the chief scaffolding hazard involves falls, yet it continues to jeopardize worker safety by failing to provide proper fall protection and ensuring scaffolding safeguards are in place," said Patricia Jones, director of OSHA's Avenel Area Office. "Changes must be made immediately to prevent serious injury or death."Four repeat violations, with a $ 52,360 penalty, were cited for not bracing scaffolds properly, lack of fall protection, incomplete work platforms and unsafe access to scaffolds. Similar violations were cited in 2010 . A repeat violation is issued when an employer previously has been cited for the same or a similar violation of a standard, regulation, rule or order at any other facility in federal enforcement states within the last five years.Carrying a $ 6,160 penalty, two serious violations were cited, including failure to erect scaffolds on a firm foundation and provide a competent, trained person for scaffolding work. A serious violation occurs when there is substantial probability that death or serious physical harm could result from a hazard about which the employer knew or should have known.For more information on scaffolding safeguards, visit http://go.usa.gov/KMH3 .OSHA's fall prevention campaign provides employers and workers with lifesaving information and educational materials about working safely from ladders, scaffolds and roofs. Information on fall protection standards is available in English and Spanish.The company has 15 business days from receipt of the citations to comply, request an informal conference with the OSHA area director in Avenel, or contest the citations and proposed penalties before the independent Occupational Safety and Health Review Commission.To ask questions, obtain compliance assistance, file a complaint, or report workplace hospitalizations, fatalities or situations posing imminent danger to workers, the public should call OSHA's toll-free hotline at 800-321-OSHA800-321-OSHA (6742) or the agency's Avenel Area Office at 732-750-3270732-750-3270.Under the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970, employers are responsible for providing safe and healthful workplaces for their employees. OSHA's role is to ensure these conditions for America's working men and women by setting and enforcing standards, and providing training, education and assistance. For more information, visit http://www.osha.gov .Contact: Joanna Hawkins Leni FortsonPhone: 215-861-5101 215-861-5102Email: : hawkins.joanna@dol.gov uddyback-fortson.lenore@dol.govU.S. Department of Labor news materials are accessible at http://www.dol.gov . The information above is available in large print, Braille or CD from the COAST office upon request by calling 202-693-7828202-693-7828 or TTY 202-693-7755.CallSend SMSAdd to SkypeYou'll need Skype CreditFree via Skype
]]></text></news-item>