<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-N701-JD3N-52GK"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Banks push to widen money laundering net</title><source>The Australian</source><author>EXCLUSIVE: ANNABEL HEPWORTH, National business correspondent</author><text><![CDATA[THE major banks are demanding the government extend tough laws to counter money laundering and terrorism financing to new businesses and professions, warning there is a "gap" in Australia's regime.
In a submission to the Attorney-General's Department, obtained by The Australian, the banks also insist more funding is needed for the anti-money-laundering regulator and that more emphasis should be put on making lax controls by financial institutions public instead of just increasing fines.
The Australian Bankers' Association submission comes ahead of a visit later this year by the -Financial Action Task Force - the Paris-based global body that sets standards for combating -financial crime - to Australia to review the effectiveness of Australia's regime.
FATF's findings will be considered in a statutory review of the 2006 laws being done by the government. The Attorney-General's Department and regulator Australian Transaction Reports and Analysis Centre (AUSTRAC) will consider submissions to the review and deliver a report to Justice Minister Michael Keenan.
The existing laws require the financial sector and gambling industry to implement rigorous -client identity checks. A second stage of reforms was expected to cover lawyers, accountants and real estate agents, but this stalled during the global financial crisis.
But the ABA has told the review it is "vital" that the second tranche of reform should be done as instances of money laundering and terrorist financing often -involve a "gatekeeper" such as solicitors and accountants, a high Continued on Page 25 Continued from Page 19 value goods dealer, or the real -estate industry. They have been brought under the regime in Britain and the US, but not in Australia. As well as introducing a "jurisdictional risk" to Australia, the situation "places an increasing compliance challenge and burden on existing reporting entities", the submission says.
It also says that AUSTRAC is "poorly resourced" and would need a "significant" increase in resources to do the extra work.
On enforcement, the submission says that instead of increasing penalties, there should be public disclosure of poor compliance capability.
Globally regulators have been cracking down on money laundering controls, leading to industy expectations that AUSTRAC could come under pressure to be more punitive.
In late 2012, HSBC agreed to pay $US1.9 billion in fines to US authorities for failing to have effective controls on money laundering.
Deloitte's anti-money laundering senior adviser and partner Chris Cass said that dealing with the second tranche of the reforms was "well overdue" as it had "been socialised as a requirement of AML regimes since 2005".
"With tranche 1 already well in place, the focus will turn to when tranche 2 will be included," he said. Extending the rules to lawyers, accountants, real estate, jewellers would mean they would have to develop anti-money-laundering programs risk assess the customer base and provide regulatory reportingamong other obligations, Mr Cass said.
]]></text></news-item>