<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-KDV1-JBM5-F0MP"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>CLEANUP SEEMS DONE AT INDIANA REFINERY</title><source>Wisconsin State Journal (Madison, Wisconsin)</source><author> State Journal staff, wire services </author><text><![CDATA[Crews didn't find any more oil during the latest search of the Lake Michigan shore following last week's spill at BP's northwestern Indiana refinery, the Coast Guard said.
A Coast Guard, BP and U.S. Environmental Protection Agency assessment team checking the area near the Whiting refinery on Sunday spotted no visible oil on the shore or in the water. Cleanup workers spent last week removing oil from about a half-mile section of shoreline.
The company estimates between 15 and 39 barrels of oil were discharged into the lake southeast of downtown Chicago where a refinery malfunction discharged oil on March 24. That's between 630 and 1,638 gallons.
Farmers shifting from corn to soybeans
The amount of American cropland devoted to corn is expected to shrink about 4 percent this year as farmers devote more acres to soybeans, the U.S. Department of Agriculture said Monday.
The USDA said it expects 91.7 million acres of corn to be planted this year, down from 95.4 million acres last year. The acreage devoted to soybeans is expected to grow about 6 percent to 81.5 million acres from last year's 76.5 million acres.
Over the last several years, farmers planted more corn in response to strong prices for that crop, thanks to growing international demand and increasing ethanol production.
Now farmers are shifting land back to a more normal split between corn and soybeans because corn prices have cooled after the government proposed reducing the amount of ethanol that must be blended with gasoline this year.
Supreme Court to hear pharmaceutical case
The Supreme Court is wading into a patent dispute between rival pharmaceutical companies over a multiple sclerosis treatment.
The justices agreed Monday to hear an appeal from Teva Pharmaceutical Industries Ltd., which claims the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit wrongly overturned five of its patents for the drug Copaxone.
The appeals court ruling would allow rivals Mylan Inc., Momenta Pharmaceuticals Inc. and Sandoz, Inc., to start selling generic versions of the drug later this year, after the remaining patents on the drug expire.
European group joins action against Google
Europe's leading consumer rights advocacy group has joined an antitrust complaint against Google because it considers the display of some search results biased.
The European Consumer Organisation, known by its French acronym BEUC, will join an existing group of companies in trying to get Google to change the way it displays its search results.
The EU Commission has been assessing the case for three years and declined to say whether the new complaint might delay a settlement. In February, it accepted Google Inc.'s concessions to settle allegations, suggesting the case might close within months.
BEUC says the changes Google proposes would harm consumers as they would allow it to "stack its search results as suits itself."
In its complaint Monday, BEUC says users are given a false impression that search results are impartial, especially for price comparisons.
BRIEFLY
COMMODITIES: The price of a bushel of corn increased 10 cents to $5.02. Soybeans rose 28 cents to $14.64 a bushel, while wheat inched up 2 cents to $6.97. Gold for June delivery fell $10.50 to settle at $1,283.80. Silver for May lost 4 cents to $19.75. May copper slipped 2 cents to settle at $3.03 a pound.
]]></text></news-item>