<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-B2K1-DXCW-D1VM"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>California: - FleetPride Inc. to pay $418,500 penalty for violating California air pollution laws</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[California Air Resources Board, The state of California has issued the following news release:
A Texas-based automotive products distributor hasentered into a settlement agreement with the California AirResources Board, agreeing to pay $418,500 in penalties forsupplying illegal windshield washer fluid to retailers throughoutthe state.
The de-icing windshield washer fluid products distributed byFleetPride Inc. contained smog-causing chemicals at levelsconsidered illegal in all areas of California. In most cases, theproducts contained concentrations of volatile organic compoundsexceeding 25 percent, an upper limit for this type of productunder a state consumer products regulation. Windshield washerfluid with a VOC content of 25 percent is allowed for sale onlyin the more mountainous areas of California that routinelyexperience freezing temperatures in winter.
The penalty in such cases, in which products exceed state limitsfor smog-forming VOCs, is based on the amount of excess VOCsemitted from the products. In this case, it is estimated thatmore than 31 tons of VOCs were emitted as a result of directsales to consumers.
These compounds are regulated by the ARB because they react withother pollutants under sunlight to form ground-level ozone, amain ingredient in smog. VOCs are used in windshield washer fluidas an anti-freeze.
“It is important that the composition of windshield washer fluidmeets ARB’s VOC limits established for the region where it issold,” said Jim Ryden, ARB’s enforcement chief. “Our goal is toprotect public health.”
During the course of an ARB investigation, it was discovered thatFleetPride was distributing several windshield washer fluidproducts that do not comply with a state consumer productsregulation ranging in size from 1-gallon containers found insmall service stations, repair shops and other commercial outletsto 55-gallon drums supplied to truck stops. Krystal KleerWindshield Washer Fluid 0 Degrees Fahrenheit was among theproducts supplied to truck stops.
FleetPride signed the settlement agreement Feb. 7. The illegalproducts were in circulation approximately three years beforethey were discovered by an ARB staff member. The company laterself-disclosed additional noncompliant products.
FleetPride has agreed to pay $418,500 in penalties under thesettlement. The penalty goes to the California Air PollutionControl Fund to support projects and research to improve thestate's air quality.
For more information please visit: http://www.arb.ca.gov
]]></text></news-item>