<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-5261-DY9P-N4G2"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>'Concerned' Osborne ups pressure on FCA over insurance fiasco</title><source>The Evening Standard (London)</source><author>Russell Lynch</author><text><![CDATA[CHANCELLOR George Osborne piled the pressure on the UK's financial watchdog today as he expressed "profound concern" over the damaging press briefing that wiped billions off the value of insurance firms.
A pre-briefing to a newspaper by the Financial Conduct Authority's director of supervision Clive Adamson threatening a review of 30 million pensions and policies sold since the 1970s hammered the sector last Friday, causing shares to plummet for several hours before the regulator intervened again to clarify its intentions.
The FCA has launched an independent inquiry but Osborne turned up the temperature on the regulator today, writing to FCA chairman John Griffith-Jones that he was "profoundly concerned".
Chief executive Martin Wheatley has so far refused to resign over the fiasco, which was labelled an "extraordinary blunder" by Treasury Select Committee chairman Andrew Tyrie. Asked if he had considered his position, he replied: "No, I haven't. I think I have got a big job to do."
But the Chancellor wrote: "These events go to the heart of the FCA's responsibility for the good order and integrity of UK financial markets, and have been damaging both to the FCA as an institution and to the UK's reputation for regulatory stability and confidence. I expect you and the FCA board to do everything possible to make good that damage." Osborne said the starting point of the FCA's review should be that the regulator "holds itself to at least as high standards as it would expect of a listed company handling highly market-sensitive information, and should hold its own staff to the same standards it would expect of any approved person" - dropping a heavy hint over disciplinary action for Adamson and Wheatley.
He wants to know who authorised the briefing to a single journalist, whether it was an "isolated exception" and why the FCA took so long to react when shares plunged. He also wants the inquiry to focus on broader lessons for the FCA's PR strategy and "where senior accountability should lie".
The Association of British Insurers has also written to the Chancellor to express its concern. A spokesman said: "The events of last week were very serious and we believe the investigation into the regulator needs to be completely independent, the regulator cannot investigate itself. Our letter is not calling for heads to roll, but for lessons to be learned."
Comment Page 42 WATCHDOG IN PAYDAY LENDERS PLEDGE ABOUT a quarter of payday lenders could be forced out of business as the industry faces up to stricter regulation, the head of the Financial Conduct Authority said today.
Martin Wheatley, pictured, is taking on responsibility for more than 500 payday loan firms as the financial regulator's regime extends to the UK's £200 billion consumer credit market following the abolition of the Office of Fair Trading.
"Our processes will probably force about a quarter of the firms out of the industry - and that's a good thing, as those are the ones that have poor practices," he told the BBC. His comments come as the founder of the UK's most high-profile payday lender, Errol Damelin, is poised to step down as chairman of Wonga.
Research by the Government's Money Advice Service revealed that nine million Britons are considered in serious debt and facing problems with debt - but just 1.5 million have sought debt advice.
Wheatley said: "Last Christmas over a million people planned to use a payday loan to help with their bills, so the need for transparent and effective regulation of the sector is clear."
Russell Lynch
]]></text></news-item>