<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-VC11-JC6P-C3YC"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Former employee files suit against Midwest Sanitary Service</title><source>The Telegraph (Alton, Illinios)</source><author>Sanford Schmidt, The Telegraph, Alton, Ill.</author><text><![CDATA[April 02--EDWARDSVILLE -- A rural Alton man is suing Midwest Sanitary Service, claiming the firm fired him for blowing the whistle on allegedly illegal dumping of toxic waste.
Paul Crane Jr. claims he was working for the company when he took pictures of the alleged illegal violations of Environmental Protection Agency regulations.
He alleges he reported the violations to state regulators prior to his being fired on Nov. 18, 2013.
"On Nov. 18, 2013 at approximately 11:24 a.m., Midwest signed for a certified letter from the EPA; the certified letter from the EPA enumerated numerous environmental violations engaged in by the defendant.
"On Nov. 18, 2013, at approximately 3:15 p.m. defendant terminated plaintiff's employment with Midwest," the suit claims.
The complaint alleges that there was a note included in Crane's final paycheck. It allegedly read: "Think before you speak. Words can get you into trouble much easier than they can get you out of it."
A Telegraph Freedom of Information Act request to the Illinois Environmental Protection Agency was not immediately addressed. A company official did not return a phone call seeking comment.
The plaintiff is asking for damages for loss of income, loss of benefits, emotional distress, embarrassment and humiliation.
The suit claims the alleged retaliatory firing is against Illinois public police and contrary to the Illinois Whistleblower Act.
Also named in the suit are Midwest employees Bob Evans Sr., Bob Evans Jr. and Nancy Donovan, who allegedly had to authority to act on behalf of the company. The three-count suit is asking for at least $50,000 in each count. Crane is represented by Lee W. Barron of Alton.
___ (c)2014 The Telegraph (Alton, Ill.) Visit The Telegraph (Alton, Ill.) at www.thetelegraph.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>