<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-53W1-JB4F-Y1XW"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>ChoiceQuote Insurance Services Limited: Mechanic fined for swapping car parts</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
A mechanic from Widnes has been prosecuted for swapping parts from a new hire car with those in his own older vehicle.
Alexander Keating, 23, of Upton Lane, Widnes, stole a gear shift knob, steering wheel, brake callipers and other parts from a brand-new Audi A3 that he had hired and swapped them with the same component parts from his ageing S3. He has been fined Pound2,000 and sentenced to complete 200 hours of community service for the crime.
While this mechanic might have been trying to cut corners in a bid to save money, his peers are advised to find legal means of boosting the bank balance. One such way is to find cheap motor trade insurance - shopping around for the best quote on the right policy is a great way for any car dealership, mechanic or garage to keep their outgoings down.
Mr Keating's theft was spotted by a garage worker who noticed the parts from the new car had been replaced by older ones. The garage then reported the theft to local Police and Accident Exchange's bespoke anti-fraud team, the Asset Protection Unit (APU).
An investigation found that he used the workshop of his former employer - a garage in Wilmslow - to remove and replace the parts between the two vehicles. He has since been fired after his crime was exposed.
He pleaded guilty at Chester Crown Court last month and has subsequently been sentenced to 200 hours unpaid community service, fined Pound2,004, and ordered him to pay Pound535 costs and Pound60 victim surcharge.
click http://www.choicequote.co.uk/news/motortrade/motortrade-mechanic-fined-for-swapping-car-parts-195650.asp
COMPANY BACKGROUND
ACTIVITIES
ChoiceQuote Insurance Services Limited operates as an insurance intermediary. It offers personal insurance products, such as motorbike, travel, car, life, scooter, moped, haulage, minibus, motorcycle, home, commercial property, public and employers' liability, pickup truck, and let property insurance products; and commercial insurance products, such as taxi, motor trade, van, liability, courier, goods in transit, and fleet insurance products. The company was founded in 1995 and is based in Liverpool, the United Kingdom with additional offices in Manchester, Leeds, Birmingham, and Glasgow, the United Kingdom. As of April 2, 2008, ChoiceQuote Insurance Services Limited operates as a subsidiary of Gan UK.
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
01 April 2014: ChoiceQuote Insurance Services Limited: Man fined for using pavement as dealership forecourt
A used car salesman has become the first person in the UK to be prosecuted for using the pavement as a motor showroom. Azeem Afsar, 22, used the public pavement on a street in the north-east to sell used cars. Under the law you must not advertise cars for sale if they are within 500 metres of each other; Mr Afsar was fined after he admitted to breaching the legislation but said that the council was "punishing small businesses", according to The Chronicle. Trying to run a makeshift car dealership from your residential premises might sound like a simple enough business plan, but there are many other factors you must consider besides adhering with commercial laws.
click http://www.choicequote.co.uk/news/motortrade/motortrade-man-fined-for-using-pavement-as-dealership-forecourt-195685.asp
31 March 2014: ChoiceQuote Insurance Services Limited: Lucky mechanic scoops Pound108 million lottery jackpot
Neil Trotter, a mechanic from Surrey, was the lucky winner of the Pound107.9 million EuroMillions jackpot, it was revealed last week. The 41-year-old, who runs a car repair garage in Mitcham, south London, is the National Lottery's fourth biggest winner of all time.
click http://www.choicequote.co.uk/news/motortrade/motortrade-lucky-mechanic-scoops-108-million-lottery-jackpot-195529.asp
14 March 2014: ChoiceQuote Insurance Services Limited: UK could see electric car invasion
There could be a huge rise in the number of electric cars on the UK's roads over the coming years, following two major announcements this week. Firstly, the Tesla electric car company in California revealed that it was going to invest around $5 billion in a new "gigafactory" that would double the world's production of lithium-ion batteries, which power electric cars.
click http://www.choicequote.co.uk/news/motortrade/motortrade-uk-could-see-electric-car-invasion-195391.asp
13 March 2014: ChoiceQuote Insurance Services Limited: Man suffers third-degree burns at St Albans car garage
An incident at a motor trader in St Albans has left a worker with third-degree burns. Paramedics were called to Bridge Motors at Frogmore Business Park in St Albans, at 10:25 on Tuesday 11 March after a fire had left a man severely injured. Having receiving treatment at the scene he was airlifted to Broomfield Hospital in Essex.
click http://www.choicequote.co.uk/news/motortrade/motortrade-man-suffers-thirddegree-burns-at-st-albans-car-garage-195377.asp
12 March 2014: ChoiceQuote Insurance Services Limited: UK car parc reaches record high
A decade of record growth for the automotive industry has resulted in there being almost 32 million cars on British roads - an all-time high - according to new figures. The results of a study by the Society of Motor Manufacturers and Traders (SMMT) found that an additional 436,000 new cars were on the roads in the UK last year, bringing the total to 31,917,885.
click http://www.choicequote.co.uk/news/motortrade/motortrade-uk-car-parc-reaches-record-high-195359.asp
]]></text></news-item>