<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-VC11-JC6P-C535"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Guilford commission expected to rule on controversial proposed propane tanks</title><source>New Haven Register (Connecticut)</source><author>Ebony Walmsley, New Haven Register, Conn.</author><text><![CDATA[April 02--GUILFORD -- Public hearings and presentations are over. Now residents and the owners of J.J. Sullivan Inc. will wait for the Inland and Wetlands Commission to hand down its decision on the proposed propane tanks that has rattled some residents and sparked controversy in the town.
The final meeting is scheduled for April 9.
If approved, two 30,000-gallon tanks at 11-feet wide, 41-feet long will sit above ground on the corner of Route 1 and Moose Hill Road.
The proposed tanks have been a hot-button issue with residents raising concerns about safety hazards and environmental issues. There are currently four storage tanks on Soundview Road owned by Hocon Propane Gas.
Elssa Green, a resident, said she's grateful the issue came to the forefront before it received approval from the commission.
"At this point, we are feeling very fortunate to have been made aware of this propane terminal proposal before it was constructed. We have presented and organized well-researched argument to the Inlands and Wetlands Commission that we feel represents the community not just at this end of Guilford, but in the town, as a whole," Green said.
Last month, the commission heard plans for the Route 1 property that could consist of demolishing an abandoned house, installing propane tanks along with an office building, driveway and parking lot. If approved, a storm water infiltration and an upgraded septic system could be added to the property.
Robert E. Sonnichsen of Waldo and Associates, LLC, and Robert C. Russo, soil scientist of CLA Engineers, presented the plans.
A retail store could replace the abandoned house, according to town documents.
Sonnichsen said wildlife on the property won't be disturbed as the highland is not a habitat for wetland species, according to town documents.
Town documents show commission members questioned the effects a storm water system could have on wetlands, the distances of propane tanks to the street and protecting the Moose Hill Road property.
Sonnichsen said approximately 75-feet stands between the proposed tanks and the edge of Moose Hill Road. He noted trees will outline the Moose Hill Road property along with a chain link fence.
But, residents are still skeptical of the suggested changes.
Tony Cafiero said nobody spoke in favor of the plan at the last public hearing.
"In our minds, yea or nay on the (April) ninth, we'll still have two problems. One, the town of Guilford has no propane cap and we need to address that. Two, the planning and zoning amendment needs to be amended back to where it originated, as not allowing bulk propane on the West end," Cafiero said.
Last year, the Planning and Zoning Commission changed the zoning code as requested by the oil company.
It states, "in addition, the bulk storage and retail sale of propane on parcels of land containing less than four acres in area and located west of West Lake Avenue and south of U.S. Route 1 in C-D zone is permitted, by special permit."
Brian McGlone, town economic development coordinator, said he views the proposal as a "long-term viability of a business in town."
"It will impact their ability to supply materials that people need to heat their homes. There's certainly a movement for propane," McGlone said.
J.P. Sullivan said his family is committed to working with the town and its residents.
"We feel as if we have made compelling arguments for the Inlands and Wetlands Commission to approve our application. We are hopeful for an approval and look forward to submitting an application for a special permit. Our family is very proud of our long record of service to the citizens of Guilford by looking to continue to provide essential services in the form of delivery of environmentally friendly, domestically produced green-fuel-like propane. We have looked to the letter and spirit of town's regulations through this entire process," Sullivan said.
Call Ebony Walmsley at 203-789-5734. Have questions, feedback or ideas about our news coverage? Connect directly with the editors of the New Haven Register at AskTheRegister.com.
___ (c)2014 the New Haven Register (New Haven, Conn.) Visit the New Haven Register (New Haven, Conn.) at www.nhregister.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>