<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-9VP1-JCF0-K17S"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>GM Faces the Music on Capitol Hill</title><source>CTV Television, Inc.</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[LISA LAFLAMME: A failure to recall its cars when they became dangers on the road had the CEO of General Motors pinned down in the public eye today. Mary Barra was summoned to Washington over a deadly ignition problem, one the company knew about for ten years. Victims' families were also on Capitol Hill to hear the testimony. Thirteen deaths and 32 crashes linked to that particular ignition issue and a series of other malfunctions that caused GM to recall a staggering six million vehicles over the past two months alone. CTV's Washington bureau chief Paul Workman has more on the demand for an explanation.
SEN. ED MARKEY (Democrat - Massachusetts): This is a 2007 Chevy Cobalt ignition switch.
PAUL WORKMAN (Reporter): And the woman wiping away the tears is Daryl Kennedy Chansuthus from Nashville, Tennessee. She shudders at the memory of police coming to her door five years ago. Her daughter Seyde was dead, killed behind the wheel of a Chevy Cobalt that shut down going 95 kilometres an hour.
DARYL KENNEDY CHANSUTHUS (Victim's Mother): He said ma'am, her airbags didn't deploy. Something's wrong. She had gone full force into the steering column. And he told me that she had died on impact.
WORKMAN: Other families with similar tragic stories came to Washington today demanding answers. Stories of Cobalts and Saturn Ions shutting down after hitting a pothole or when the ignition switch got bumped, even slightly. And worst of all, GM knew about the problem for a decade and did nothing.
MARKEY: Two dollars. That's how little this ignition switch could have cost to repair.
WORKMAN: GM's new boss testified on Capitol Hill, began by saying sorry, but offered few answers to many questions.
MARY BARRA (General Motors CEO): Sitting here today, I cannot tell you why it took so long for a safety defect to be announced for this program. But I can tell you we will find out.
WORKMAN: Who knew what and when, she was asked, and was GM simply being sloppy or covering up.
UNIDENTIFIED WOMAN: Is the company responsible?
BARRA: We are committed to our customers and we are going to work very hard to do the right thing for our customers.
WORKMAN: GM no longer makes either the Cobalt or the Ion, cars that were cheaper, made during the recession, and aimed at young people. What makes you the angriest?
CHANSUTHUS: Her loss was inexcusable and completely unnecessary.
WORKMAN: What hurts even more, she and her daughter specifically picked out an American car to help the bankrupt auto industry.
CHANSUTHUS: The first American car, the Chevy Cobalt I bought for my daughter became her coffin.
WORKMAN: GM's stock is already down sixteen percent this year and the company could face hefty fines. So for one of America's leading automakers, this is nothing short of a corporate disaster, Lisa.
LAFLAMME: Mm-hmm. Paul, the question was asked of Mary Barra today, is the company going to be accountable? Has GM committed to any kind of financial settlement yet?
WORKMAN: Not yet, at least not formally, but it has hired Kenneth Feinberg. And that's significant because he's the man who handed out millions of dollars, hundreds of millions of dollars in compensation after 9/11 and after that terrible oil spill in the Gulf of Mexico a few years ago.
LAFLAMME: Alright, Paul. Obviously, again, enormous legal and moral obligations.
]]></text></news-item>