<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-8711-JBM5-S0NN"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>OIL TERMINAL FIRM FACING OREGON FINES</title><source>The Times-Union (Albany, NY)</source><author>BRIAN NEARING</author><text><![CDATA[Albany
An oil terminal operator at the Port of Albany under increasing state scrutiny over expansion plans has run afoul of state regulators at its West Coast terminal in Oregon, where the company allegedly ran through six times more crude oil than its permit allowed.
Massachusetts-based Global Companies faces a $117,000 fine from the Oregon Department of Environmental Quality for crude shipments through its terminal, called the Columbia Pacific Bio-Refinery and located in Clatskanie on the Columbia River, about an hour's drive from Portland.
In late 2012, Global purchased the dormant refinery, which had been processing ethanol, and began using it to handle surging crude oil shipments arriving in massive trains from the Bakken oil fields of North Dakota.
Global, a Fortune 500 company, also ships Bakken crude in such trains eastward to Albany, and is facing increased state review over plans to heat crude oil -- which some opponents believe will be Canadian tar sands crude, something Global has neither confirmed nor denied -- to make the heavy crude easier to pump and ship down the Hudson River.
In Albany, Global has a state permit to handle up to 1.8 billion gallons a year of crude oil. Global reports its shipments to the state Department of Environmental Conservation, which verifies figures "through site inspections and cross checks of on-site permit paperwork and logs," said spokeswoman Emily DeSantis.
In Oregon, the state air pollution permit for Global's new refinery allowed 50 million gallons of ethanol to be handled, and the company got state permission to apply that limit to crude oil shipments beginning in November 2012. By March 2013, Global was ramping up crude shipments, and by May it had already reached the 50 million-gallon annual limit, prompting a warning from Oregon officials that a new air pollution permit would be needed for any increase over the limit.
Global applied for a revised permit in August, but continued increasing shipments; by November, Global had pushed nearly 295 million gallons through the terminal in the previous 12 months, according to a Thursday order from state Department of Environmental Quality that called it a "serious violation."
In a statement, Global Executive Vice President Edward Faneuil said Oregon state findings were "not accurate" and would be challenged by the company in an administrative hearing.
"Operations at Columbia Pacific Bio-Refinery are in full compliance with state environmental regulations," he added.
The state order also required Global to limit future shipments to 50 million gallons a year until it got its new air pollution permit, which is currently under review and public comment, or face "additional civil penalties." A spokesman for the Oregon Department of Environmental Quality said the state learned that Global was shipping more oil than its permit allowed when it asked the company to provide shipping records.
The problems in Oregon come as Global faces increased scrutiny over terminal projects in Albany and New Windsor, Orange County, from the state Department of Environmental Conservation. Last week, the state demanded answers to questions about fire risk, evacuation plans, spill response and insurance coverage for accidents before it would consider action on a required air pollution permit.
DEC also extended public comment on the project another two months, through June, and warned it could rescind a November ruling that the crude heating proposal would have no negative impact on the environment -- which could result in a detailed, time-consuming review.
DEC also raised questions over the company's planned expansion of its terminal on the Hudson in New Windsor, Orange County, to accept oil from rail cars for transfer onto river transport vessels.
On Monday, Global Chief Executive Officer Eric Slifka told industry analysts that DEC's actions could hamper "the carrying of different products," including Canadian heavy crude oil, according to a report by Reuters.
Albany's port has become a major shipping route for crude oil moving eastward in mile-long trains from the Bakken fields of North Dakota. Two companies, Global and Houston-based Buckeye Partners, operate oil terminals at the port and have state permission to handle 2.8 billion gallons of crude a year.
bnearing@timesunion.com - 518-454-5094 - @Bnearing10
BOX:
In a statement, Global Executive Vice President Edward Faneuil said Oregon state findings were "not accurate."

]]></text></news-item>