<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-STV1-JDKC-R161"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Let New Government Take a Call on Coal Reforms</title><source>New Indian Express</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Chennai, April 1 -- The UPA government has set up the office of coal regulator through an executive order. This follows its failure to enact the Coal Regulatory Authority Bill which was introduced in Parliament in December last. Alas, the new office is not a substitute for a proper law. The coal regulator is expected to advice the government on coal prices but it will be more in theory than in practice. This is because the Coal India Limited, which enjoys monopoly, will fix the prices, subject to the government's approval. In other words, the advice of the new regulator will not be binding on coal companies. Also, it is a reform, too late and too little to make an impact.
Over a quarter century after the economic reforms were launched, the coal sector remains one of the least reformed. The villain of the piece is the Coal Mines (Nationalisation) Act, 1973, which needs urgent repeal. It is this law that empowers the CIL and its subsidiaries with monopoly rights. Coal users have been complaining about the CIL's monopoly practices under which they have no right but to accept whatever coal is supplied at whatever price is demanded. Since the major purchasers of coal were also public sector companies like the National Thermal Power Corporation, the CIL could get away.
Things have changed with the advent of private power companies and other large users of coal. They are the ones who have been importing coal. Not only is coal imported of better quality but they are also able to get it in time. The imports cause enormous drain on India's foreign exchange reserves. It is unacceptable as India is known to have one of the world's largest coal reserves. The wasteful expenditure can be curtailed if private companies are given a level playing field and allowed to compete with the CIL. Instead of tinkering with half-baked ideas, the UPA government should wait for the next government to take a call on the much-required coal sector reforms.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from New Indian Express. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>