<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-VC11-JC6P-C3R0"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>COGA, TOP ask judge to kill Longmont fracking ban</title><source>Daily Times-Call (Longmont Colorado)</source><author>Daily Times-Call, Longmont, Colo.</author><text><![CDATA[April 01--A Longmont fracking ban violates state law and should be struck down without trial, attorneys for the oil and gas industry argued in motions filed Friday with the Boulder County District Court.
The ban, passed by Longmont voters in 2012, forbids drilling companies from using hydraulic fracturing, or "fracking," in city limits. The method uses high-pressure water, sand and chemicals to crack open hard-to-reach oil and gas deposits. Opponents of fracking call it dangerous to the environment while supporters say the practice is so common that a ban on fracking is practically a ban on drilling.
Karen Spaulding, an attorney for the Colorado Oil and Gas Association argued that upholding the ban would essentially negate state law, which permits and regulates fracking under the Colorado Oil and Gas Conservation Commission.
Oone drilling company, Synergy, has already backed away from drilling some of its Firestone wells because it would have passed beneath Longmont city limits, Spaulding wrote.
"The city's hydraulic fracturing bans ... intrude into these areas of oil and gas operations in which the state has a sufficiently dominant interest," she wrote in her request for summary judgment. "Moreover, the city's bans affect the ability of those with mineral interests both within and outside the city boundary to obtain an equitable share of the production profits."
TOP Operating, the principal oil and gas company operating in Longmont, filed a separate motion that also asked the judge to kill the ban.
"This determination can and should be made without the need to take any evidence, such as to the safety or environmental effects of fracking," TOP attorney Thomas Kimmell wrote, arguing the ban was pre-empted by state law.
No trial date has been set for the COGA lawsuit.
The case was originally second in line behind a COGCC lawsuit over Longmont's new drilling regulations, also adopted in 2012. Both the city and the state agreed to a "stay" in that case, postponing it until after Judge D.D. Mallard rules on the fracking ban.
Contact Times-Call staff writer Scott Rochat at 303-684-5220 or srochat@times-call.com
___ (c)2014 the Daily Times-Call (Longmont, Colo.) Visit the Daily Times-Call (Longmont, Colo.) at www.timescall.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>