<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWF-RY81-JBKR-R2H6"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>HSBC faces 'much work' in money-laundering accord; Deadline Nears</title><source>National Post's Financial Post &amp; FP Investing (Canada)</source><author>Erik Larson, Bloomberg News</author><text><![CDATA[HSBC Holdings PLC has "much work" to do as part of a $1.9-billion agreement with the Justice Department to avoid prosecution for money laundering, the U.S. said in a status report Tuesday on the U.K.-based bank's performance.
HSBC must reach an accord this month on a monitor's recommendations for improving its anti-money laundering and sanctions compliance programs, the government said in a filing in federal court in Brooklyn, New York. The bank is handling the matter in "good faith," the U.S. said.
"The monitor believes that the leadership of HSBC Group is appropriately committed to addressing the bank's long-standing compliance deficiencies," prosecutors said in the filing. "HSBC Group has made significant progress under the current management team."
The accord, approved by a judge in July, resolved claims that London-based HSBC failed to monitor more than $670-billion in wire transfers and more than $9.4-billion in purchases of U.S. currency from HSBC Mexico, allowing for money laundering. The bank also violated U.S. economic sanctions against Iran, Libya, Sudan, Burma and Cuba, according to a criminal complaint.
An HSBC spokesman, Rob Sherman, declined to comment on the report when reached by phone Tuesday.
The report describes initial findings by the monitor, Michael Cherkasky, which were filed Jan. 20 with U.S. District Judge John Gleeson in the Brooklyn court. Mr. Cherkasky based his findings on information provided by the bank and didn't independently verify it because that will happen later, the U.S. said.
The monitor found that HSBC needs to improve the reliability of the data it gathers on its customers and improve methods of sharing the data with affiliates, the U.S. said.
Mr. Cherkasky, a former chief executive officer of the security and investigative company Altegrity Inc., also found that HSBC's information technology and transaction monitoring systems "lack integration, coordination and standardization," the U.S. said.
The bank, Europe's largest, agreed to pay a $1.25-billion forfeiture and $665-million in civil penalties under the settlement, prosecutors announced in December 2012. At a hearing the same month, Judge Gleeson told prosecutors there had been "publicized criticism" of the agreement, which lets the bank and management avoid further criminal proceedings over the charges.
]]></text></news-item>