<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-DNY1-JC17-F18S"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>LANDOWNERS TO PAY FOR 2009 CLEANUP</title><source>The Record (Bergen County, NJ)</source><author>James M. O'neill, Staff Writer; Email: oneillj@northjersey.com</author><text><![CDATA[Three real estate companies have agreed to pay the federal government a combined $2.1 million to cover the costs of a 2009 cleanup involving more than 1,600 drums of hazardous material at a Clifton chemical facility.
The three companies had leased a nearly 4-acre site to Abrachem Group, which operated the facility starting in 2003. Five years later the federal Environmental Protection Agency found that caustic chemicals and solvents on the site were leaking from rusted and mislabeled drums. Samples contained corrosive and flammable chemicals as well as PCBs, volatile organic chemicals and cancer-causing benzene.
The EPA, which had been alerted by the state Department of Environmental Protection, determined that Abrachem Group was storing the drums and bulk containers of chemicals improperly in 17 shipping containers and an adjacent warehouse.
One of the property owners, Clifton 2003, refused to grant access to the site, delaying cleanup efforts, the EPA said. The agency obtained a warrant for access from a federal judge in January 2009.
The cleanup came with some tense moments. Bomb squad robots were used to take samples from drums that the agency thought could ignite. Periodically, when potential explosive chemicals were discovered, areas of the nearby community were evacuated.
The $2.1 million settlement was signed by Clifton 2003 LLC, Hampshire Generational Fund and WEA Enterprises Co. Clifton 2003 is owned by Hampshire Generational Fund.
The settlement "means that the responsible parties will bear the financial burden for cleaning up the site, not taxpayers," said Judith Enck, the EPA administrator for the region that includes New Jersey. "The Abrachem Chemical site was found in a horrible state of disrepair and posed serious risks to the health of people in the surrounding community."
Abrachem Group vacated the site in 2009, following eviction proceedings by Clifton and WEA Enterprises. Abrachem and its owner, Tilghman Frey, filed for bankruptcy.
James. A. Kosch, the lawyer for WEA Enterprises, said: "We settled because we didn't want to go through a lengthy suit. In the settlement we do not admit any liability."
He said WEA owns a vacant property that provided access to the property, owned by the other two companies, where the Abrachem facility was located.
"Our lease agreement with them specifically prohibited the storage of hazardous materials on the site," Kosch said. "But obviously, Abrachem did what Abrachem did."
Clifton 2003 and Hampshire Generational Fund are part of the Morristown-based Hampshire Cos., which owns and operates 259 properties in 28 states. The company did not respond to requests for comment.
In August of 2010, Frey was charged by the state Attorney General's Office with unlawful storage of hazardous waste. He agreed in a consent order to pay a $54,000 fine to the Northeast Environmental Enforcement Project, which provides professional training to environmental regulators.
Abrachem Group pleaded guilty to third-degree unlawful storage of hazardous waste and creating the risk of widespread injury or damage. It did not pay any fines.
The Clifton site has since been redeveloped. New York-based data center services provider Telx Group opened a 215,000-square-foot flagship data center there last year.
The Mountain Development Corp. of Woodland Park sold the facility for $54 million last fall to the California Public Employees' Retirement System and the private equity firm GI Partners. Telx continues to occupy and operate the facility.
Email: oneillj@northjersey.com
]]></text></news-item>