<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-G001-F08V-6001"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Trial in alleged $46M Ponzi scheme to feature broke investors, elderly </title><source>Grand Rapid Press (Michigan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[URL: http://www.mlive.com/news/grand-rapids/index.ssf/2014/03/david_mcqueens_trial_in_allege.html
By John Agar
jagar@mlive.com
David McQueen, of Byron Township, made a decent living as an insurance salesman but saw big potential in a company, Multiple Return Transactions, which promised monthly 10 percent returns.
After months of apparent success, McQueen started his own investment company, Accelerated Income Group. His company, investing in MRT, promised investors a 5 percent return on their money. Investors were happy, and he kept the5 percent difference.
Then, MRT stopped making payments.
"Unfortunately for McQueen and AIG's investors, MRT was merely a Ponzi scheme, and they had been defrauded," Assistant U.S. Attorney Matthew Borgula wrote in court documents.
"Their money was gone and would never be recovered. Instead of notifying AIG investors that MRT had failed, McQueen continued to tell investors their money was safe and growing. Without MRT making its monthly payments, McQueen and AIG could not meet their 5 percent monthly obligations based on investment earnings. Instead, McQueen used the only funds he had available to make promised interest payments -- money from new investors."
McQueen allegedly stood at the top of a $46 million Ponzi scheme, one of the largest financial frauds in West Michigan history.
The government made these allegations in a brief filed ahead of today's jury trial before U.S. District Judge Gordon Quist.
McQueen's attorney said his client, in good faith, relied on a lawyer's advice in meeting company obligations.
"Defendant contends that the evidence at trial will show that the conduct that the government complains of in the mail fraud and money laundering counts was the result of defendant's reliance on the advice of the law firm of Rhoades McKee and a sole practitioner, Thayer Lindauer," attorney Scott Graham wrote.
"He was aware of all of the facts relating to the operation of the businesses and he advised defendant to use existing money to pay old debts," Graham wrote.
The judge will decide after hearing testimony whether to instruct jurors about good-faith reliance on the advice of an attorney.
The defense also said it would ask the court to grant immunity to certain witnesses who invoke their Fifth Amendment rights against self-incrimination. McQueen "believes that a number of witnesses may refuse to testify ..." Graham wrote.
Typically, the government decides whether to seek immunity.
Borgula said that "McQueen likely did not set to create a criminal enterprise that would result in a financial tragedy for his investors" but his "arrogance and hubris prevented him from admitting that his investment scheme had failed."
Instead of shutting down AIG, he created other "sham organizations," and "falsely touted his investment success," Borgula wrote.
"Despite knowing he had absolutely no revenue coming in, McQueen took $100,000 of investor money per month tax free for his own personal use and enjoyment," Borgula wrote.
McQueen sent out statements showing that "investors had tens of millions safe and growing in their 'separate accounts.' Those statements concealed the truth -- that McQueen had nearly run out of money."
The government plans to call 75 witnesses at trial. About 40 are investors, including retirees who have lost everything.
Others, including co-defendants, had a business relationship, or sold his investments. Still others investigated the case, or are considered expert witnesses.
There were about 800 investors, the government said.
McQueen also hired several law firms but ignored their advice, the government said.
John Agar covers crime for MLive/Grand Rapids Press E-mail John Agar: jagar@mlive.com and follow him on Twitter at twitter.com/ReporterJAgar
David McQueen
]]></text></news-item>