<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-9XX1-JC3H-02T3"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Roxbury sues to test Fenimore soil</title><source>Asbury Park Press (New Jersey)</source><author>By, William Westhoven</author><text><![CDATA[| @wwesthoven
The mayor and council turned up the heat on the state Department of Environmental Protection Monday, filing a legal action to compel the agency to allow them to test soil samples from more than 20 new wells being dug at Fenimore Landfill.
The order to show cause, filed in state Superior Court in Morristown, follows a March 14 statement from Mayor Jim Rilee and the council expressing disappointment with the DEP's March 11 public presentation of its chosen plan to remediate Fenimore - by capping it instead of excavating the materials producing toxic emissions - and demand more evidence be produced to support its conclusions.
In a statement, Rilee said DEP last Wednesday denied the township's request to collect and test soil samples from the well digs.
"We are very disappointed that we must take this extraordinary action because DEP denied our request to test the soil," said Rilee, who also is the chairman of the New Jersey Highlands Council. "We cannot determine the best way to remediate the serious problems caused by this landfill until we know exactly what was buried there. Collecting the soil from the new wells presents a unique opportunity to conduct those tests."
DEP spokesman Larry Ragonese said the department is ready to move forward with its capping plan and referred to the lawsuit as "a delay tactic."
"We are very disappointed by this lawsuit," he said. "Our plan is to cap the landfill as a permanent solution to this hydrogen sulfide problem so it is done by the end of the year. ... I can't fathom why anyone would want to delay this. That should be the last thing they want to do."
The mayor and council also had demanded DEP not take any action at Fenimore that would rule out other permanent remediation solutions. DEP officials at the contentious March 11 public meeting at Roxbury High School surprised both township officials and the public by announcing it would be implementing its capping plan within a matter of weeks. But DEP later said that the more than 20 wells it was digging at Fenimore would enhance the hydrogen sulfide gas collection system already operating at Fenimore.
The actual capping project, DEP said, was separate from the well project, and has not yet gone to bid.
"The Township Council and the residents of Roxbury are not convinced that we have all the information necessary to determine what the correct mediation plan should be," Rilee said. "Testing the material in the landfill will provide essential information necessary for us to complete our own independent study and determine the best course for a permanent solution that protects both the health and safety of our residents."
DEP already has conducted soil tests, Ragonese replied, and township officials are welcome to join them when the well drilling and boring begins, saying they are ready to begin the work now.
"We want to have this done by the end of the year, and with as little disruption to the residents as possible," Ragonese said, adding that other remediation solutions, such as excavation, would result in a "horrifying" amount of hydrogen sulfide being released.
All parties agree that the smelly hydrogen sulfide gas - which can be toxic at levels frequently recorded by air monitors around the landfill - is largely the byproduct of gypsum-based drywall that was part of the construction debris dumped at the landfill since it was reopened in 2010. New owners SEP Properties announced a plan in 2010 to cap Fenimore and establish a solar farm there, using tipping fees to fund the project.
But in late 2012, nearby residents began detecting the rotten-egg odor of hydrogen sulfide, igniting a controversy that led to DEP seizing control of the site in June. The state has since filed lawsuits against DEP, but many residents, especially those from the Roxbury Environmental Action Coalition, still blame DEP for approving the SEP plan in the first place.
REACT has been vocal in calling for DEP to truck out the offending materials, a solution DEP and Gov. Chris Christie have repeatedly said is too expensive and impractical.
REACT President Bob Schultz, though, said the township's legal action is a good sign.
"It's about time, a great first step," Schultz said. "We hope (the mayor and council) will join us in blocking the (Fenimore) gate if the lawsuit doesn't work to stop the DEP closure plan until testing is complete, and public comments and desires are taken into consideration. Because nobody here wants this landfill sitting there for the next 20 years. We want this trucked out."
Jeff Tittel, executive director of New Jersey Sierra Club and a vocal supporter of REACT, said the township's action is a positive step.
"It is late but finally Roxbury Township is doing something," he said. "For too long DEP has mishandled the oversight, then the cleanup, of Fenimore Landfill and the town has let them. And now finally the town wants to do their own test on the soil. It is a start. The town needs to do more, they must hold DEP accountable and take action to get the toxic mess removed."
Tittel also criticized the DEP for poor communication with the public and what he feels is the wrong solution to the problem.
"The DEP plan was so bad and the (March 11) meeting even worse that the town is now taking action," Tittel said. "Hopefully this is just the first step, but don't hold your breath."
The Roxbury lawsuit was filed by the New Brunswick-based environmental law firm Hoagland, Longo, Moran, Dunst and Doukas.
Staff Writer William Westhoven: 973-428-6627; westhoven@dailyrecord.com
]]></text></news-item>