<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-9XW1-JC3H-04YK"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Wren resigns</title><source>The Montgomery Advertiser (Alabama)</source><author>By, Kala Kachmar and Brian Lyman</author><text><![CDATA["Former Representative Wren's guilty plea, negotiated in light of his acceptance of responsibility and cooperation with the state, marks a significant point in the ongoing investigation."
W. Van Davis,
Acting attorney general appointed by Attorney General Luther Strange
"Greg, from day one, has talked. He had a right not to say anything. He's talked and cooperated fully."
James Anderson,
Wren's attorney
Rep. Greg Wren, R-Montgomery, abruptly resigned Tuesday from the House of Representatives, and pleaded guilty to a charge of using his office for personal gain.
Wren's guilty plea and the acting attorney general's statement that it marked "a significant point in the ongoing investigation" of "alleged corruption at high levels of state government" has only fueled already rampant rumors concerning an investigation involving House Speaker Mike Hubbard.
Rumors have swirled for several months concerning a grand jury convened in Lee County, part of which is represented by Hubbard, R-Auburn, and the speaker is referred to in Wren's plea agreement.
Wren, 59, received two years probation, a 12-month suspended sentence and agreed to pay $24,000 in restitution to the General Fund within 90 days. Documents filed in the case said that Wren, an insurance agent by trade who served as chairman of the Joint Legislative Medicaid Committee, inserted language that would have given Bessemer-based American Pharmacy Cooperative Inc. (APCI) an edge in certain Medicaid contracts.
The cooperative helped Wren secure an $8,000-a-month consulting contract with RxAlly, a national association of pharmacies, and Wren later passed confidential documents related to the Alabama Medicaid Agency to a senior manager there, according to the plea agreement
The former representative could have faced up to a year in jail if convicted in court on the charge. Wren, appearing calm, quiet and remorseful after entering the agreement Tuesday morning, said he was ready to move on.
"I'm kind of glad to have this behind me," he said. "It's been a difficult process."
An attempt to reach APCI for comment Tuesday was not successful.
Acting Attorney General W. Van Davis, a supernumerary district attorney appointed by Attorney General Luther Strange, said in a statement announcing the plea that he was looking into "a matter involving alleged corruption at high levels of state government.
"Former Representative Wren's guilty plea, negotiated in light of his acceptance of responsibility and cooperation with the state, marks a significant point in the ongoing investigation," the statement said. "We will continue to enforce the laws of the state of Alabama vigorously and professionally without regard to political affiliation or position."
The Alabama Medicaid Agency has been exploring the possibility of a pharmacy benefit manager (PBM) in order to bring down the costs of prescription drugs in the program. The plea agreement says the APCI provided language to Wren early in the 2013 legislative session to put in the General Fund budget. The language would effectively mean the co-op would be the only company that could meet the requirements of any contract authorized by the Alabama Medicaid Agency.
As Wren was shopping the language around to legislative leadership, the agreement says, senior management with the cooperative helped Wren secure a contract with RxAlly, partly owned by the APCI, for consulting, worth a total of $24,000.
According to the plea agreement, Hubbard endorsed the "exclusive language and directed staff to add it to Medicaid's section of the General Fund budget," after meetings with Wren on the subject. The language was ultimately struck from the General Fund budget that year.
The Auburn Network, a company owned by Hubbard, has done consulting work for APCI; Hubbard told AL.com last year that the work was exclusively on out-of-state issues.
J. Mark White, an attorney representing Hubbard, said Tuesday that the speaker's work for APCI "has been public knowledge for some time and vetted with ethics staff."
In an earlier statement, White said Wren's actions "do not involve or affect Speaker Hubbard.
"Speaker Hubbard has never failed to cooperate with any law enforcement authority," the statement said. "Unlike his political opponents, the speaker respects the need for the legal process to operate free of political influences."
The plea agreement says that "subsequent" to Hubbard endorsing the language, Wren was told about Hubbard's "ongoing financial relationship" with APCI. "The Speaker of the House had not informed Wren, or others Wren interacted with, in those meetings, of that ongoing relationship," the agreement says.
James Anderson, an attorney representing Wren, said the representative "has been to the grand jury in Lee County" and has a "relationship" worked out with investigators and prosecutors.
The attorney also said Wren's actions were not "an intentional violation."
"He did not know who had a financial interest," Anderson said. "The $24,000 in restitution was not anything that came from the state of Alabama. Greg has agreed to pay back all the money he was paid by a company with which he had a consulting agreement."
Wren directed the Legislative Fiscal Office to provide him confidential documents involving oral and written testimony from PBM companies, as well as a Medicaid analysis of the proposals, at the end of April 2013, according to the affidavit by Robert Stuart, a special agent with the Alabama Attorney General's Special Prosecutions Division.
In May, Wren provided the documents to a senior manager at RxAlly, according to the affidavit. The plea agreement says that in testimony before the grand jury on Feb. 13, 2014, Wren "made a materially false statement," and said the documents were "publicly available and that he had obtained them from the Internet."
Anderson said Wren didn't know the company had any involvement with the state of Alabama at the time.
"Greg, from day one, has talked," Anderson said. "He had a right not to say anything. He's talked and cooperated fully."
RxAlly went out of business last August. According to a report in Chain Drug Review, the firm, which claimed to represent 22,000 independent pharmacies and Walgreen's, did not give a reason for its closure.
Wren, who represented eastern Montgomery for 16 of the last 20 years, announced in January that he would not seek re-election to his House seat. Republican County Commissioner Reed Ingram and Democrat Therese Ford will run for the seat.
State house corruption investigation
"Former Representative Wren's guilty plea, negotiated in light of his acceptance of responsibility and cooperation with the state, marks a significant point in the ongoing investigation."
W. Van Davis,
Acting attorney general appointed by Attorney General Luther Strange
who's next?
Columnist Josh Moon believes Greg Wren's plea spells trouble for Speaker of the House Mike Hubbard » 9A
View more photos, affidavit and the plea agreement as well as watch a video of the news conference at montgomery advertiser.com
"Greg, from day one, has talked. He had a right not to say anything. He's talked and cooperated fully."
James Anderson,
Wren's attorney
]]></text></news-item>