<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-3MX1-DYG2-R4BF"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Federal Agency Grants Delaware Riverkeeper Network Petition to Address Contaminated Drinking Water in Delaware River Region</title><source>Targeted News Service</source><author>Targeted News Service</author><text><![CDATA[The Delaware Riverkeeper Network issued the following news release:
The U.S. Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry (ATSDR) notified Delaware Riverkeeper Network (DRN) that it has agreed to investigate the exposure of residents in Paulsboro and the region to Perfluorononanoate acid (PFNA) and other perfluorinated chemicals through drinking water. DRN filed a Petition with the ATSDR on August 2, 2013 asking the agency to conduct a public health assessment of the communities located near the Solvay Solexis Inc. facility in Thorofare/West Deptford and near Paulsboro, NJ, on the Delaware River, Gloucester County. The ATSDR is a federal public health agency, part of the Public Health Service in the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services that works to prevent exposure and adverse human health effects from pollution releases in the environment. http://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/com/pha.html
DRN focused the Petition on Paulsboro because of the extremely high levels of PFNA, a compound with toxic human health effects and that is bioaccumulative, in the raw groundwater and, it was later discovered, in tap water in Paulsboro. 150 parts per trillion (ppt) of PFNA was discovered in Paulsboro's water supply in September 2013 by the Borough, after the Petition was filed with ATSDR and the public began to learn of the water contamination. Over the past months, the Borough of Paulsboro filed a Notice of Intent to Sue with Solvay, the company that used PFNA in its patented manufacturing process of durable plastics since 1985 and released huge amounts of PFNA and other PFCs into the air, water and soil, over the decades since. Private lawsuits have been filed by residents against the company as well. Other municipalities in the region have tested their water or had their water tested by Solvay and more contamination has been found. Most recently, West Deptford, East Greenwich, and Woodbury have all shut down wells that were found to contain PFNA as a precaution until further analysis is completed.
As pressure built, NJ Department of Environmental Protection (NJDEP) finally required Solvay to prepare a work plan to assess the pollution; Solvay issued a proposed work plan last December. DRN and others submitted comments regarding the proposed work plan, which DRN's expert concluded is not acceptable due to its limited extent and faulty sampling program. DRN's expert report warns that the Solvay work plan, which is supposed to provide a guide that can be used by NJDEP for clean-up, may yield little to no useful information. To see the comment and expert report: http://bit.ly/DRN_Comment_Solvay_Sampling
DRN held two community meetings in the Solvay area (West Deptford and Paulsboro) to gather information that was submitted to ATSDR to help them in their decision making process regarding the Petition. Residents of the municipalities attended the meetings where DRN also shared its findings from files obtained from NJDEP, EPA, and scientific and health journals regarding PFCs and PFNA. DRN also submitted Solvay's work plan, DRN's expert report, and other supplemental information to ATSDR since the original Petition was filed.
PFNA is in the family of perfluorinated chemicals (PFCs) that is being investigated by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) and is recognized as a contaminant of concern that is so dangerous it is subject to programs to phase out, control, and monitor its use.
EPA set a Provisional Health Advisory for short-term drinking water exposure to perfluorooctanoic acid (PFOA) and perfluorooctane sulfonate (PFOS), two of the most widely distributed PFCs and New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection (NJDEP) issued an Occurrence Study for PFOA in New Jersey public drinking water in 2007 and established a PFOA drinking water guidance level of 0.04 ppb (40 ppt) based on lifetime health effects. In 2009 NJDEP conducted a second occurrence study on PFCs, including PFNA, but the report has never been released, despite requests filed by DRN under the Open Public Records Act. On March 14, 2014 NJDEP proposed a draft interim specific groundwater criterion for PFNA. DRN has engaged a toxicology expert to evaluate the proposal and will be submitting comment to the agency.
The NJ Department of Health has issued fact sheets on PFCs and PFNA to help inform the public: http://www.state.nj.us/health/eohs/pfc_in_drinkingwater.shtml NJDEP has announced that the NJ Drinking Water Quality Institute (DWQI), charged with recommending to NJDEP safe drinking water standards under the state's Safe Drinking Water Act and which was shut down by the Christie Administration in September 2010, will reconvene on April 29. The furor over PFNA in the communities surrounding Solvay is seen as the impetus that pushed the state administration to bring the DWQI back into operation, at long last.
"It is very important that the ATSDR has accepted our Petition and will investigate PFCs, particularly PFNA, in the Paulsboro region. Delaware Riverkeeper Network believes it is essential that an independent outside agency step in to investigate this rampant contamination problem. Their acceptance of our Petition for a public health assessment shows how serious this pollution problem is and the need for the expertise and experience this federal agency will bring. Working together with New Jersey's Department of Health, who is the state lead for the investigation, these experts will apply an all-important public health perspective. We hope this will lead to providing safe drinking water and to the cleanup of PFCs that pollute this region, including the Delaware River - a cleanup done at the expense of the responsible party or parties", said Tracy Carluccio, Deputy Director, Delaware Riverkeeper Network. "We gratefully thank the residents of this area who provided information we shared with ATSDR and who have bravely demanded at public meetings and in their communities that Solvay and NJDEP take action after doing nothing for so long," added Carluccio.
The acceptance letter from ATSDR, received March 31, is available at: http://bit.ly/1fLHxMR
To view the ATSDR Petition go to: http://bit.ly/DRN_ATSDR_Petition
A copy of DRN's investigative Memo regarding PFNA and other PFCs is at: http://bit.ly/pfnamemo
A copy of DRN's letter to NJDEP is at: http://www.delawareriverkeeper.org/resources/Letters/ltr%20to%20DEP%20re%20sampling%20and%20action%207%2013%20final.pdf
To view the full file of documents DRN received under New Jersey's Open Public Records Act: http://www.delawareriverkeeper.org/resources/Reports/Perfluoronated_Chemicals_in_NJ_Drinking_Water.pdf
In addition to NJDEP's sampling that revealed PFCs in raw water supplies, data collected by the Delaware River Basin Commission (DRBC) and published in a report in July 2012 revealed very high levels of PFNA in surface water in samples between 2007-2009 in the Delaware River http://www.state.nj.us/drbc/library/documents/contaminants-of-emerging-concernJuly2012.pdf.
Contact: Tracy Carluccio, Deputy Director, 215-369-1188, ext.104
Copyright Targeted News Services
CC AutoTriage6yd-140402-4687731
]]></text></news-item>