<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-37W1-F0NV-F01C"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Manchin demands Blankenship filmmakers pull movie</title><source>The Register-Herald (Beckley, West Virginia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Sen. Joe Manchin, D-W.Va., demanded Tuesday that the company that filmed and produced the Don Blankenship-funded documentary for which the senator was interviewed remove "this propaganda from all websites, discontinue the distribution of the film and delete all references of Manchin's name, image and representation," the senator said in a press release.
Manchin's office has repeatedly attempted to contact Adroit Films via phone and e-mail, according to the release.
Manchin wrote, in part, "Your fraudulent behavior in securing the interview and your misrepresentation of my interview are actionable offenses. I expect you to cease distribution of this film and remove any references to my name, image, and likeness. Please respond to this letter in writing immediately to confirm what actions you are taking in response to my request."
Blankenship is the former Massey Energy CEO who funded the documentary about the Upper Big Branch mine disaster that killed 29 miners in 2010.
Manchin said he was unaware of the Blankenship connection when he was interviewed by the filmmakers. He said they told him the interview would be about mine safety.
The film is titled "Upper Big Branch: Never Again."
The release of the film on Monday was timed to coincide with the fourth anniversary of the explosion at the Upper Big Branch Mine in Raleigh County that killed the 29 miners on April 5, 2010.
* * *
Full text of the Manchin letter:
Gailon Totheroh
Producer
Adroit Films, LLC
805 Live Oak Dr #102
Chesapeake, VA 23320
Dear Mr. Totheroh:
I write to demand you cease and desist the distribution of your documentary "Upper Big Branch - Never Again," posted yesterday, March 31, 2014, remove the documentary from any websites where you posted it, and remove any and all references to my name, image, and likeness from the film.
On March 24, 2014, your firm interviewed me for a documentary, which you claimed was related to "mine safety" and would be "dedicated to the victims' families from [the Upper Big Branch mine disaster.]" In fact, this is a film by Don Blankenship, an individual under investigation for his role in the deaths of 29 brave miners. Your omission of this material fact was a gross misrepresentation of the true purpose of your film. Further, I would never have consented to the interview if I had known of your association with Mr. Blankenship.
Your deliberate acts of omission and misrepresentation are compounded by the final product. Despite my thirty-minute interview, you only dedicated one minute and thirty-two seconds to mine safety - one of the most important issues in West Virginia - in an attempt to vindicate Mr. Blankenship.
Your fraudulent behavior in securing the interview and your misrepresentation of my interview are actionable offenses. I expect you to cease distribution of this film and remove any references to my name, image, and likeness. Please respond to this letter in writing immediately to confirm what actions you are taking in response to my request.
Sincerely,
Joe Manchin III
United States Senator
]]></text></news-item>