<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-T7B1-JBHM-S1WT"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>House GOP Budget Seeks To Cut Climate Funds</title><source>InsideEPA.com's Daily Briefing</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Posted: April 1, 2014 House Republicans have unveiled a fiscal year 2015 budget resolution that would significantly scale back spending on climate change programs, including cutting the amount of money that EPA and other agencies can spend on domestic programs while also eliminating overseas payments designed to spur energy efficiency and mitigate climate change.
The resolution, released April 1 by House Budget Committee Chairman Paul Ryan (R-WI), would also likely mean funding cuts for EPA's other pollution control programs in FY15 and beyond because it would cut overall federal spending by $5.1 trillion over the next ten years -- largely by repealing President Obama's health care law.
The measure's provisions are unlikely to be implemented soon as Congress last year enacted a bipartisan budget agreement -- which Ryan negotiated with his Senate counterpart, Sen. Patty Murray (D-WA) -- governing spending in FY14 and FY15.
Ryan's plan for FY15 follows spending levels agreed to in the budget deal, but Ryan's 10-year plan seeks to impose discretionary spending cuts in future years. "This is a plan to balance the budget and create jobs, and it builds off a simple fact: We can't keep spending money we don't have," he said.
While Ryan's plan may not be implemented this year, its provisions could garner greater consideration in 2015 as Republicans compete to gain control of the Senate in upcoming elections.
On climate change, the resolution suggests "illustrative policy options" for the congressional budget committees to consider, including eliminating contributions to the Clean Technology Fund and Strategic Climate Fund -- accounts created by the Obama administration in 2010 giving foreign assistance to support energy efficiency technologies that aim to reduce energy use and mitigate climate change. "[T]he government should not attempt to pick winners and losers in terms of which technologies and companies to favor and advance abroad," the plan says.
The resolution also "reduces spending for government-wide climate change-related activities, primarily by reducing the funding federal agencies spend on overseas climate change activities. It also recommends better coordination of programs and funds to eliminate duplicative and unnecessary spending."
Ryan's targeting of these funds is likely to be heavily contested as pressure grows to increase the United States' and other countries' contributions to global climate programs. Representatives of some developing countries are indicating they plan to step up their calls for increased contributions especially in the wake of the just-issued report by the United Nations' Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, which provided its hardest warnings yet that human-induced climate change will produce extreme weather, reduce crop yields, and raise sea levels.
For example, Ronald Jean Jumeau, the Seychelles' ambassador to the United Nations and a spokesman for the Alliance of Small Island States, told the New York Times that the $100 billion fund proposed by the United States and other countries to address rising sea levels is not adequate, especially given that Congress appropriated $60 billion for states affected by Hurricane Sandy.
"We know that $100 billion is not going to be enough," he said. "After Sandy, Congress voted for $60 billion in recovery for New York, New Jersey and Connecticut -- for one storm. It shows you how much $100 billion is going to cover."
The legislative text of Ryan's plan also criticizes EPA regulations as part of a policy statement on federal regulations, which accuses the administration of excessive issuance of new rules. The highest regulatory costs come from EPA's coal sector rules, the bill claims, including the agency's proposed climate new source performance standard for future power plants that would mandate carbon capture and sequestration (CCS) at newly constructed coal utilities. The text says that because CCS is not commercially available, the proposed standards would be unachievable and therefore a "de-facto ban on new coal-fired power plants."
To address concerns about the rules' costs, the bill calls on Congress, in consultation with "the public burdened by excessive regulation," to enact legislation that would pursue a "cost-effective" approach to regulation that relies on "sound and publicly available scientific data," streamlines the approval process for energy and water projects, and aims to promote a limited government, while ensuring that regulations do not disproportionately disadvantage low-income Americans by using a "more rigorous" cost-benefit analysis for new rules.
House Natural Resources Committee Chairman Doc Hastings (R-WA) said the plan "prioritizes expanded American energy production and recognizes that new energy development is one of the best ways to raise new revenue, put Americans back to work, bolster the economy, lower gasoline prices, and create good-paying jobs."
But House and Senate Democratic lawmakers signaled strong opposition to the Republicans' plan, with House Budget Committee ranking member Chris Van Hollen (D-MD) calling it "reckless," and House Appropriations Committee ranking member Nita Lowey (D-NY) labeling it "extreme and draconian."
The Senate Democratic majority is also fighting the proposal, with Sen. Charles Schumer (D-NY) faulting the call to repeal Obama's health care law and saying, "The problem is the Ryan budget wouldn't do a thing to help the middle class, and simply attacking Obamacare won't get them the political victory they seek."
The White House also expressed its opposition to the House GOP budget plan, with Press Secretary Jay Carney in a statement saying, "Because of a stubborn unwillingness to cut the deficit in a balanced way by closing tax loopholes for the wealthy and well connected, the House Republican Budget would slow the economy, stack the deck against the middle class, and threaten the guaranteed benefits seniors have paid for and earned."
]]></text></news-item>