<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-F8Y1-F12F-F2H2"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>TREASURER MCCORD JOINS INSTITUTIONAL INVESTORS CALLING FOR INDEPENDENT INVESTIGATION AT DUKE ENERGY</title><source>US State News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[HARRISBURG, Pa., April 1 -- The Pennsylvania State Treasurer issued the following news release:
State Treasurer Rob McCord expressed profound concern that recent findings about Duke Energy Corporation's conduct related to a major environmental accident could wind up diminishing the long-term value of Pennsylvania's nearly $44 million in securities issued by the company.
McCord joined a group of institutional investors from around the country last week in calling for an independent investigation at Duke Energy into events surrounding the February 2 spill of more than 30,000 tons of coal ash and 27 million gallons of contaminated water into the Dan River in North Carolina. The North Carolina Department of Environment and Natural Resources found that Duke Energy failed to take all reasonable measures to prevent the spill.
"While a lax approach to managing environmental risks may appear to benefit shareholders in the short-term by reducing expenditures, recent events show this approach dramatically increases risk for investors - including Pennsylvania's 529 College Savings Program and our pension funds - in addition to jeopardizing the health of the environment and those living nearby," said McCord.
He and other co-signers wrote to Philip R. Sharp, Chair of the Regulatory Policy and Operations Committee of Duke Energy Corporation. They asked the committee to conduct an investigation as allowed by its charter - separate from the company's investigation - and to report to shareholders. They said they were troubled by various matters related to the Dan River spill, including its severity, Duke's purported violations of numerous regulations, the lack of clarity on clean up and costs, the disposition of Duke's other coal ash ponds, and federal criminal subpoenas issued to Duke and several North Carolina government agencies. These events - and Duke's response - they wrote, have shaken investors' confidence in Duke and its board.
The letter was coordinated by the Nathan Cummings Foundation and included signatures from several institutional investors in addition to McCord. Among the signatories were the state treasurers from Oregon and Connecticut, the Illinois State Board of Investment, the California State Teachers' Retirement System, the Service Employees International Union (SEIU), private investment managers, and several social welfare organizations.
They stated their fears in the letter about the future of their investments in the company: "The spill, subsequent revelations regarding regulatory violations and the ensuing criminal investigation have created serious reputational risks. These developments also raise broader questions about Duke's approach to the management of long-term environmental risks like climate change and water pollution and underscore the need for greater transparency of political and lobbying activity . . . If they remain unaddressed, these matters may have material consequences for Duke Energy and its long-term shareholders."
McCord, as Pennsylvania's state treasurer, is the sole fiduciary of $2.2 million of Duke securities held by several commonwealth funds, including Treasury's 529 College Savings Program. Additionally, McCord is the custodian and an ex officio board member for the commonwealth's two largest pension funds, which also have Duke holdings.
"These events are a reminder that we need to properly manage environmental risks not only for the health and well-being of our citizens, but also for taxpayers and investors who foot the bill when incidents occur," McCord noted.
Coal ash is residue left after treated coal is burned to produce electricity. On February 2, a 48-inch storm water pipe situated beneath an unlined ash pond used by Duke Energy's retired coal-fired electric plant collapsed. The collapse resulted in the spill of 30-39,000 tons of coal ash and 27 million gallons of contaminated water. Regulators reported that the river bottom was coated with coal ash for 70 miles. Then on March 11, regulators caught Duke allegedly dumping 61 million gallons of coal ash illegally into a tributary of the Cape Fear River.
Visit http://www.patreasury.gov/assets/pdf/rls-040114-LETTERDukeEnergy.pdf to read the text of the letter.
For more information, visit www.patreasury.gov. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>