<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-3671-JCDT-K1FD"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Mill safety scrutinized for sawdust; WorkSafeBC inspects local facilities this spring to ensure dust accumulation standards are met</title><source>Alberni Valley Times (British Columbia)</source><author>Eric Plummer, Alberni Valley Times</author><text><![CDATA[Provincial workplace safety authorities are cracking down on sawmills this spring with another round of inspections to operations across the province, including visits to two Alberni Valley facilities.
WorkSafeBC has doubled its team of safety specialists to 20, who will be looking into the accumulation of combustible sawdust in B.C. mills over April, May and June to determine the risk of fire in the facilities.
WorkSafeBC concluded a round of inspections over the winter on Jan. 31 to find that 42 per cent of the province's sawmills failed to comply with safety standards. The workplace safety authority was unable to provide the Times with inspection information specific to Port Alberni's sawmills without the submission of a Freedom of Information request.
This spring the 61 sawmills that did not meet regulations will be scrutinized with closer safety inspections, while some of the other operations that passed will see random visits from Work-SafeBC representatives.
"We want to ensure, in visiting the sawmills and other wood processors around the province, that they are managing combustible dust to keep workers safe," said Scott McCloy, WorkSafeBC's director of media relations. "We will be looking, this time around, for better results than we found in the last phase of inspections."
Western Forest Products, which locally runs the Somass and Alberni Pacific Division sawmills, is expecting WorkSafeBC to conduct inspections this spring.
"We just see this as a continual process. Our mills are continually inspected by WorkSafe," said Tony Sudar, vice-president of manufacturing with Western Forest Products.
"We're working hard and diligently to continue to improve the safety in all our operations, dust and otherwise."
Sawmills have been identified by the province as particularly vulnerable to fire since two fatal explosions two years ago. These took the lives of two people and injured 20 others during the Babine Forest Products disaster in Burns Lake in January 2012.
In April of that year, another worker died, while 24 were sent to the hospital from the Lakeland Mills blast in Prince George. Representatives from the provincial government, WorkSafeBC and trade unions met in Victoria Friday to discuss the next round of safety enforcement measures to B.C.'s sawmill operations, and another meeting occurred Tuesday. WorkSafeBC stated that contravention of industry standards this spring will bring penalties or orders to halt operations until conditions are met.
Stop work orders were already imposed on 11 employers last winter following inspections.
"A stop work order means that you have to stop work immediately because there is imminent risk to workers for either serious injury or death," McCloy said.
Mill inspectors will be looking for accumulations of sawdust, which must be limited to one eighth of an inch on level surfaces in no more than five per cent of an operation's workspace.
Dust control systems must also be installed, bringing adequate collection and ventilation of combustible materials, and WorkSafeBC also assesses equipment to determine the risk of igniting airborne dust.
"A robust dust extraction system is critical to the management of dust ," McCloy said. "Someone gets sick, someone gets moved off manual cleanup to do something else and all of a sudden dust starts to build up."
Sudar said the local Western Forest Products' sawmills have a low incidence of employee injury, thanks to regular safety inspections by the company and dust-control systems.
"We have systems on all our main machine centres that suck dust up," he said. "We do extensive auditing of our mills and our processes in regards to safety."
EPlummer@avtimes.net 250-723-8171, ext. 226
]]></text></news-item>