<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-3FY1-DXX7-H1FP"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Community rallies outside Wallarah public hearing</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author>Mary-Louise Vince</author><text><![CDATA[A public hearing has been told the risk to the central coast water catchment far outweighs the benefit of an underground coal mine proposed for the area.
More than 100 people turned out to a hearing by the Planning and Assessment Commission on the Wallarah Two mine.
It was the final chance for the community to put its case on the development before a final decision is made.
The Mayor of Wyong, Doug Eaton told the Commission the risk to the region's water catchment far outweighs any employment benefits from the mine.
The potential impact on the region's water supplies remains the key concern about the project, which is backed largely by the Korean Government.
President of the Liberal Party's Gosford branch and former Gosford Mayor Malcolm Brooks said he was against the mine.
Mr Brooks said little had changed since the mine's original development application, which was rejected by the Labor Government in 2011.
"Nothing has changed except a new application, a new government and an ICAC inquiry," he said.
Outside the meeting Labor's Environment spokesman, Luke Foley says the Premier has betrayed central coast residents by failing to stop the mine project.
Mr Foley told the crowd legislation is needed to stop the mine going ahead.
The Wallarah Two mine has become a political headache for the O'Farrell Government.
In Opposition, Barry O'Farrell agreed the mine's environmental risks were too great and made a 'no ifs, no buts guarantee' that it would never even be considered on his watch.
However the Planning Department backed the project in March subject to strict conditions.
ICAC inquiry still to be held
Meanwhile, an Independent Commission Against Corruption inquiry is yet to to be held into Wallarah's major players, including Liberal party fundraiser and lobbyist Nick di Girolamo, and the former Resources Minister and Central Coast MP, Chris Hartcher.
Labor and the Greens want the the project halted until that investigation is complete.
More than 30 people addressed the hearing, including local and state politicians, environmental groups, the local Aboriginal Land Council, an economist as well as mining industry representatives.
An economist from the Australia Institute, Rod Campbell said the mine's economic value had been overstated and its economic benefits were based on discredited modelling.
The Darkinjung Aboriginal Land Council declared the the entire mining proposal invalid.
Darkinjung's CEO, Sean Gordon said he would never approve access to build a rail spur across Land Council land and legal action is underway on the issue.
Industry groups voice support for mine
But industry groups including the Mining and Energy Services Council of Australia voiced their support for the project, saying it will provide a much needed boost to the Central Coast economy.
The Central Coast Poultry Club told the Commission many of its members live in the vicinity of the proposal but believe it will help create local jobs.
A final determination on the Wallarah proposal is expected in May.
]]></text></news-item>