<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-8SW1-JC86-C1VC"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Nigeria; Eni CEO Sentenced to Three Years in Prison</title><source>Africa News</source><author>This Day (Lagos)</author><text><![CDATA[An Italian court has sentenced the chief executive officer of an oil major, Eni, Paolo Scaroni, to three years in prison.
The ruling, which came amidst a separate judicial inquiry into corruption allegations in Algeria concerning Eni and service unit Saipem, also bars Scaroni from holding public office for five years.
Eni, Italy's largest industrial company with market cap of $90 billion is a major player in Africa's oil and gas industry, holding key assets in Nigeria, Egypt, Tunisia, Libya and Algeria.
Recently, Saipem, which is 43 per cent owned by Eni was alleged to have been involved in a $268 million bribery scandal with a government official in a bid to secure contracts in Algeria worth an estimated $11 billion.
Investigations were subsequently opened by Algerian and Italian authorities, leading to the dismissal of several top level employees while Scaroni continued to face interrogations from prosecutors.
Also, in 2013, Siapem was fined 600,000 Euros for bribing Nigerian officials to secure a juicy contract. Other companies linked to bribery in Nigeria are Shell, Pride International, Inc., Tidewater Inc., Transocean, Inc., GlobalSantaFe Corp. and Noble Corporation, and Willbros.
Specifically, Panalpina, a US subsidiary of the Swiss freight forwarding giant Panalpina World Transport (Holding) Ltd. (PWT), was in 2010, charged with paying bribes to customs officials in Nigeria, Angola, Brazil, Russia and Kazakhstan to enable importation of goods into those countries and the provision of logistics services.
Willbros, an oil and gas industry services firm in 2008, agreed to make corrupt payments of over $6.3 million to Nigerian government officials to get a $387 million contract in a major natural gas pipeline project. The company later agreed to pay over $32 million in fines and forfeitures to settle the allegations of bribery. However, a court ruling in the north-eastern town of Rovigo reported by Reuters said Scaroni had been sentenced, though no other details were provided.
Sources cited by the news wire said the ruling was a result of violations of "environmental norms" at the Porto Tolle power plant in northern Italy during a period in which Scaroni was chief executive at Italy's top utility, Enel.
Scaroni said he was shocked by the decision in a statement seen by Reuters. "I am in no way involved in this matter and will appeal immediately," he was quoted by Reuters as saying. "As shown by the defence, Enel's Porto Tolle station has always met the existing standards including at the time of the facts contested," he said.
The Italian court said the current chief of utility Enel, Fulvio Conti, had been acquitted in the same case. Scaroni has already served three terms as chief at state-controlled Eni and his current mandate expires in May.
The Italian government, according to the newswire wants state-controlled companies to eject from their boards any director charged of financial crimes, in a drive to fight corruption and improve corporate accountability.
]]></text></news-item>