<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-FTT1-JC8H-K161"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Briefing.com: Hourly In Play (R) - 07:01 ET</title><source>Briefing.com</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Hourly In Play (R)
Updated: 02-Apr-14 07:01 ET
06:59
LQDT Liquidity Services is Apparent High Bidder for Non-Rolling Stock Surplus Contract with the U.S. Department of Defense (22.35 )
....
06:54
CEL Cellcom Israel announces dismissal of purported class action filed against the co (13.53 )
Co announced that further to the co's report dated Nov 2011 regarding a purported class action filed against the co alleging that the co raised tariffs for business customers unlawfully and in violation of its agreements with them, the purported class action was dismissed with prejudice. The total amount claimed from the co, had the lawsuit been certified as a class action, was estimated by the plaintiffs to be at least hundreds of millions of NIS.
06:48
WIRES On The Wires
Provectus Biopharma (PVCT) announced that data on its investigational drug PV-10 will be featured in a presentation by investigators from Moffitt Cancer Center in a Poster Highlights Session of the American Society of Clinical Oncology Annual Meeting in Chicago, IL, May 30-June 3, 2014.Foundation Medicine (FMI) announced that new clinical data including additional validation for FoundationOne and FoundationOne Heme will be presented at the American Association of Cancer Research Annual Meeting 2014 taking place April 5-9, 2014 at San Diego Convention Center.Illumina (ILMN) announced new products that can be applied directly to the discovery and translation of genomic variation in blood and tissue associated with cancer. The expanded portfolio leverages the co's next-generation sequencing and microarray scanning systems to deliver sample-to-data solutions for basic and clinical cancer research.Integrated Device Technology (IDTI) announced mass production of its DDR4 chipset that is compliant to the JEDEC 1.0 specifications for use in DDR4 registered dual in-line memory modules and load-reduced dual in-line memory modules.
06:45
CP Canadian Pacific's President and COO addressed Agriculture Standing Committee hearing in Ottawa on Bill C-30; highlighted that interswitching would worsen the situation for the movement of Canadian grain to markets (150.72 )
Co's President and COO Keith Creel provided his comments on Bill C-30 to the Standing Committee on Agriculture. Mr. Creel encouraged the Committee to consider the serious capacity constraints within the current grain supply chain and highlighted that interswitching would worsen the situation for the movement of Canadian grain to markets."The reality is the current grain supply chain, of which rail is only one component, cannot move these extraordinary volumes over this short period of time. We need solutions that will increase throughput of grain from farm to ship." With respect to the proposed extended interswitching, Mr. Creel expressed concerns with its potentially damaging unintended consequences and how it would slow down the grain supply chain due to increased handlings, further constraining capacity. He noted that allowing grain to be interswitched to U.S railroads could also potentially lead to a negative impact on the Canadian economy.
06:40
BBRY BlackBerry ends T-Mobile (TMUS) licensing agreement (8.10 )
Co announced that it will not renew the T-Mobile U.S. (TMUS) license to sell BlackBerry products when it expires on April 25, 2014. BlackBerry customers on the T-Mobile network should not see any difference in their service or support. BlackBerry will work closely with T-Mobile to provide the best possible customer service to any customer remaining on the T-Mobile U.S. network or to any customer purchasing devices from T-Mobile's existing inventory.
06:38
BP BP announced it intends to halt refining operations at its Bulwer Island refinery in Brisbane, Queensland by mid-2015 (48.44 )
Co announced that it intends to halt refining operations at its 102,000 barrels per day Bulwer Island refinery in Brisbane, Queensland by mid-2015.Andy Holmes, President of BP Australasia, said that the growth of very large refineries in the Asia-Pacific region was driving structural change within the fuels supply chain in Australia and putting huge commercial pressure on smaller scale plants.It is expected that it will take some twelve months to implement the changes required to maintain supply and safely shutdown the process units. Once processing has been halted, the import jetty, aviation fuel tanks and associated pipelines will remain operational while other storage tanks and pipelines will be placed on a care and maintenance basis pending a decision to convert the site to a multi-product import terminal.
06:34
SDRL Seadrill Ltd secures contracts for multiple jack-up units (34.92 )
Co has secured new contracts for the jack-up units West Tucana, West Telesto, West Ariel, and West Prospero. Additionally, the contract for the West Mischief has been extended by four months. The total rev potential for the four new contracts and one extension is ~ $319 million.
06:34
AXX Alderon Iron Ore commences work at its proposed terminal site near the Port of Sept-Iles (1.46 )
Co announced that it has commenced preliminary work for the Pointe-Noire Terminal facility at the Port of Sept-Iles, Quebec. This is the product handling facility for the Kami Iron Ore Project with mining and processing facilities located in western Labrador. The Kami Project is held by the co's affiliate The Kami Mine Limited Partnership.Site preparations have commenced at the terminal facility, which will be built for receiving, unloading, stockpiling and reclaiming concentrate for ship loading. The terminal facility will consist of a railcar unloading stub track, a single rotary car dumper, a concentrate storage yard with stacker-reclaimer and interconnecting conveyor systems. Two of the most critical pieces of the material handling system for the Kami Project, the car dumper and the stacker-reclaimer, have already been ordered.
06:32
WILN Wi-LAN announces its subsidiary has entered into a license agreement with a wireless carrier in the U.S. for certain patents related to wireless network management; terms are confidential (2.99 )
06:27
S&P futures vs fair value: +2.00. Nasdaq futures vs fair value: +6.00.
06:27
European Markets
FTSE...21819.24...+17.40...+0.30%. DAX...9632.67...+29.00...+0.30%.
06:27
Asian Markets
Nikkei...14946.32...+154.30...+1.00%. Hang Seng...22523.94...+75.40...+0.30%.
06:18
WIRES On The Wires
Mediaset, Italy's largest commercial broadcaster, has turned to Accenture (ACN) to create and manage its Mediaset Infinity service, which delivers film and television shows on-demand to a wide array of IP-enabled devices such as set-top boxes, PCs, tablets, connected TVs and gaming consoles. Infinera (INFN), provider of Intelligent Transport Networks, and Internet Solutions, a leading pan-African telecommunications provider, announced today the deployment of the Infinera DTN-X platform across the company's South African long distance network. Radware (RDWR), a leading provider of application delivery and application security solutions for virtual and cloud data centers, today announced JD Williams, a leading internet and catalogue home shopping company has recently deployed Radware's FastView, cutting page load times for its website by over 25%.
06:15
ACTG Acacia Research announces settlements and patent license agreements (15.94 )
Co announced that its Brandywine Communications Technologies subsidiary has entered into a settlement and patent license agreement with CenturyTel Broadband Services and Qwest (CTQ). The agreement resolves all disputes between Brandywine and certain Century Link affiliates pending in the United States District Court for the Middle District of Florida, Civil Action No. 6:12-cv-286-CEH-DAB.Also, co GT Gaming subsidiary has entered into a settlement and patent license agreement with Digital Chocolate. The agreement resolves litigation that was pending in the United States District Court for the Southern District of California.Finally, co's Brilliant Optical Solutions subsidiary has entered into a settlement and patent license agreement with Fairpoint Communications (FRP). The agreement resolves litigation that was pending in the United States District Court for the Western District of Missouri.
06:03
LLEX Lilis Energy provides update on the status of its Wattenberg horizontal drilling; 3 horizontal wells to drill in April: Lang Prospect - 2 Niobrara, 1 Codell (3.23 )
Co provided an update of its horizontal drilling program in the Greater Wattenberg Field. In October 2013, Lilis Energy announced its participation in one non-operated horizontal well in its Lang (North Wattenberg) Prospect. This well, which is operated by PDC Energy (PDCE), has been recently completed and Lilis Energy expects initial production results later this month. Three additional non-operated horizontal wells are scheduled to commence drilling in the Lang Prospect within the next few days. Co owns a 50% working interest in two of the three wells that will be drilled and owns a 25% working interest in the third well, in addition to a 25% working interest in the PDC well. Co anticipates that an additional three to four wells will be drilled in the Lang Prospect later this year. Both the Niobrara and Codell formations are being targeted in this prospect. The co has also permitted, and is in the final stages of preparations to commence drilling two horizontal wells in its Sawyer (South Wattenberg) Prospect, and expects to spud these wells in early June. Co will operate this project and plans to test both the Niobrara and Codell formations. Seven additional wells are expected to be drilled in this prospect later in 2014. Co will maintain an average working interest in all wells drilled in the Sawyer Prospect of ~ 49%.
06:00
CUI CUI Global announces distribution agreement between its subsidiary, Orbital Gas Systems and Benchmark Instrumentation & Analytical Services, for Canadian sales of its GasPTand VE Technology Systems (9.34 )
Co announced that its wholly owned subsidiary, Orbital Gas Systems, through its Products Division, Orbital Global Solutions (OGS), has signed a Distribution Agreement with Benchmark Instrumentation & Analytical Services, a natural gas equipment distribution company based in Edmonton, Alberta, Canada. The Agreement calls for distribution of CUI Global's patented natural gas technology, including the GasPT, the GasPTi and its VE Technology. Specifically, the agreement gives Benchmark exclusive distribution rights for sale of the devices in the country of Canada.The agreement calls for Benchmark to initially purchase thirty GasPTi-P devices - two GasPTi-P devices for customer demonstration to be delivered immediately and another twenty eight units as inventory to be sold by Benchmark during the term of the agreement.
05:48
PCG PG&E and its subsidiary, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, expects legal process to demonstrate that federal criminal charges filed today have no merit (42.37 )
The charges were filed by the U.S. Attorney's Office in San Francisco in connection with the 2010 San Bruno natural gas transmission pipeline accident. The charges allege that PG&E's past operating practices violated the federal Pipeline Safety Act in areas such as record keeping, pipeline integrity management and identification of pipeline threats.
05:28
SSYS Stratasys to acquire Solid Concepts and Harvest Technologies (110.97 )
Co announces that it has entered into definitive agreements to acquire two privately-held companies, Solid Concepts and Harvest Technologies.
Solid Concepts is the largest independent additive manufacturing service bureau in North America and a fast-growing partner to RedEye, Stratasys' existing digital manufacturing service business. The transactions are expected to be accretive to Stratasys' Non-GAAP earnings per share within the first 12 months after closing. Upon completion of the transactions, Stratasys will combine Solid Concepts and Harvest Technologies with RedEye to establish one additive manufacturing services business unit. Transaction details:
Under the terms of the definitive agreement with Solid Concepts, Stratasys will acquire Solid Concepts for total consideration of up to $295 million, including a payment on closing of $172 million (or, if settled in cash, part on closing and part six months after closing), deferred payments of $60 million and up to $63 million in retention-related payments. Subject to certain requirements for cash payments, Stratasys retains discretion to settle any of the amounts payable under both the definitive agreement and the retention plan in either Stratasys shares, cash or any combination of the two. The value of a portion of the purchase price as well as the deferred and retention-related payments may increase or decrease in line with the market price of Stratasys shares. Under the terms of the definitive agreement with Harvest Technologies, Stratasys will acquire Harvest Technologies for an undisclosed amount, including retention-related payments, payable in cash, shares or a combination thereof.
03:33
WIRES On The Wires
CareerBuilder, owned by Gannett Co (GCI), Tribune Company and The McClatchy Company (MNI), announced that it is acquiring Broadbean, a leader in job distribution, candidate sourcing and big data analytics software. The latest step in CareerBuilder's evolution as the premiere HR Software as a Service provider, the acquisition will bring recruiters and HR managers a faster, more convenient and more cost-effective way to acquire talentBlackBerry (BBRY) announced that it will not renew the T-Mobile U.S. (TMUS) license to sell BlackBerry products when it expires on April 25, 2014.Taylor Morrison Home Corp (TMHC) announced that it has formed a joint venture with its two largest shareholders, funds managed by Oaktree Capital Management and TPG to acquire and develop Marblehead, a prestigious coastal residential development in San Clemente, California. Marblehead consists of 195.5 coastal acres and can accommodate over 300 luxury home sites.Montage Technology Group (MONT) announced the production release of its DDR4 RDIMM and LRDIMM chipsets, which include the DDR4 Registering Clock Driver and the DDR4 Data Buffers. The chipset fully supports Intel's next-generation Xeon Processor ES-2600 V3 product family.Micron Technology (MU) announced it is ramping production of DDR4 memory to support upcoming Intel CPU launches.Prudential (PRU) Real Estate Investors and Algemene Pensioen Groep have launched Pramerica Real Estate Capital V. PREI raised $366.7 million of discretionary capital of which the majority is provided by APG, the leading pension fund manager in the Netherlands, which has more than $477.3 billion of assets under management.Cliffs Natural Resources (CLF) announced that, following a comprehensive review of the trading volume, costs and administrative requirements related to its listing on Euronext Paris, the Company voluntarily requested the delisting of its shares from Euronext Paris.TriNet Co, a subsidiary of Thailand's second-largest mobile operator dtac, has assigned long-time partner Ericsson (ERIC) to deploy a 4G/LTE network.
03:23
AGEN Agenus provides update on GSK'S (GSK) MAGE-A3 Cancer Immunotherapeutic Phase 3 study in non-small cell lung cancer (3.31 )
Agenus (AGEN) announces that GlaxoSmithKline's (GSK) MAGRITi study, a Phase 3 randomized, blinded, placebo-controlled MAGE-A3ii cancer immunotherapeutic trial in non-small cell lung cancer patients, which contains Agenus'QS-21 Stimulon adjuvant, will be stopped. GSK announced that it will not be possible to identify a sub-population of gene-signature positive NSCLC patients that may benefit from the treatment.
The Independent Data Monitoring Committee indicated that its review of the current safety information revealed no specific safety concern and the data is in line with the known safety information for the MAGE-A3 cancer immunotherapeutic.
Update on GSK's Phase 3 DERMA Program in Melanoma
GSK is continuing another Phase 3 clinical trial to evaluate whether a gene signature can identify a sub-population of melanoma patients that would benefit from the same investigational MAGE-A3 cancer immunotherapeutic. This follows the read-out of the first co-primary endpoint in September 2013 of disease free survival in the overall MAGE-A3 positive population, which was not met. Work is progressing on the mathematical model (the gene signature classifier) to allow assessment of DFSiii in the gene signature population, the second co-primary endpoint in the DERMA trial. The outcome is expected in 2015.
03:03
TU Telus announces offering of $1 bln in new debt notes (35.85 )
Co announces that it is offering $1 bln of senior unsecured notes in two series, the first with a 7-year maturity, the second with a 30-year maturity.
7-year $500 mln of notes with 3.20% interest rate
30-year $500 mln of notes with 4.85% interest rate
02:58
CRNT Ceragon lowers Q1 revenue guidance; expects $17 mln settlement with Eltek (2.91 )
Co issues downside guidance for Q1 (Mar), sees Q1 (Mar) revs of $70-73 mln vs. $88.11 mln Capital IQ Consensus Estimate. This was below the company's earlier guidance of $83 million to $93 million, primarily due to the company's decision not to ship and install equipment for a certain customer until completing the renegotiation of payment terms. A secondary factor affecting Q1 revenue was a higher than expected proportion of IP-20 products in Q1 bookings. Some of the orders were received too late in the quarter to ship within the quarter because manufacturing for the new products was ramping and had not reached full productivity. Final results for the first quarter will be released on May 8, 2014. The company also announced a settlement agreement pursuant to which it expects to receive $17 million in cash during the second quarter of 2014.
Settlement Agreement Signed
On April 1, 2014, Ceragon signed an agreement with Eltek ASA, to settle all claims, counter claims, legal proceedings, and any other contingent or potential claims regarding alleged breaches of representations and warranties contained in the purchase agreement governing Ceragon's acquisition of Nera Networks from Eltek in January 2011. Pursuant to the settlement agreement, Ceragon expects to receive $17 million in cash during the second quarter of 2014.
02:40
IPOXX Rubicon Project (RUBI) prices 6,770,995 share IPO (1,354,199 shares by selling stockholders) at $15 per share, at the low end of the $15-17 expected range
The shares will be traded on the NYSE.
02:19
BSX Boston Scientific reports key data for cardiac resynchronization therapy technology, platinum chromium stents and Lotus Valve System (13.62 )
Co reports favorable results in studies related to cardiac resynchronization therapy, platinum chromium stent platforms and transcatheter aortic valve replacement.
Patients with mild heart failure have lower mortality rates with CRT defibrillators
In the longest follow-up of CRT for patients with mild heart failure to date, Boston Scientific announced significant findings from the continued analysis of the landmark MADIT-CRT study, demonstrating a significant and sustained survival benefit in the indicated population. The long-term results demonstrated a 41% relative reduction in the risk of death in patients who received a Boston Scientific defibrillator with CRT compared to patients who received a defibrillator alone. In addition to the mortality benefit, the results demonstrate that these patients experienced a 62% relative reduction in the risk of experiencing a first heart failure event when compared to patients who didn't receive CRT therapy.
02:05
MDR McDermott prices 10 mln of 6.25% tangible equity units with stated value of $25.00 (7.03 )
02:04
QPAC Quinpario Acquisition Corp agrees to purchase $45 mln in shares of a newly authorized 8.0% Series A Convertible Perpetual Preferred Stock (10.23 )
In addition to the preferred commitment agreements, Quinpario also entered into common equity support agreements pursuant to which a group of investors have agreed to purchase $17.5 million of Quinpario common stock in open market purchases and/or through the issuance of shares of common stock through a private placement, each at a purchase price of $10.255 per share.
02:04
AVH Avianca Holdings prices $250 mln 8.375% International Bond due 2020 (16.90 )
02:03
AHC A.H. Belo receives proceeds from sale of Apartments.com by Classified Ventures (11.65 )
Co announces it received a gross cash distribution of ~ $18.9 million following the close of the sale of Apartments.com by Classified Ventures. A. H. Belo owns a 3.3%t interest in Classified Ventures.
02:02
ELLI Elli Mae reports on system outages (28.39 )
Co reports on recent outages that have made Ellie Mae's Encompass services unavailable to users.
Ellie Mae has detected unusually high demand for services consistent with an external malicious attack characteristic of a distributed denial of services. The Company has taken actions to isolate the suspicious activity and prevent future unwarranted access. Ellie Mae's technical operations teams are continuing their work to restore full functionality for Encompass users.
There is no evidence of any data breach and the Company confirmed that client data and personal borrower data remain secure.
18:20
AEE Ameren announces pricing of $350 mln of 3.50% senior secured notes due 2024 (40.76 -0.44)
Co announced the pricing of a public offering of $350 million aggregate principal amount of 3.50% senior secured notes due 2024 at 99.982% of their principal amount. The transaction is expected to close on April 4, 2014. Ameren Missouri intends to use the net proceeds of the offering to repay at maturity $104 million aggregate principal amount of its 5.50% senior secured notes due May 15, 2014 and to repay outstanding short-term debt. Merrill Lynch, Pierce, Fenner & Smith Incorporated, Mitsubishi UFJ Securities (USA), Inc., Morgan Stanley & Co., LLC and SunTrust Robinson Humphrey, Inc. are acting as joint book-running managers for the offering.
18:01
STLY Stanley Furniture announces it will cease domestic production in Robbinsville, NC; Q1 results delayed to April 30, 2014 (stock halted) (2.73 -0.01)
Co reported it will cease domestic furniture production in the factory that supports its Young America brand. "We have decided to cease manufacturing operations in Robbinsville," said Glenn Prillaman, President and Chief Executive Officer. "After a thorough review of both our own operations and the current marketplace for nursery and youth furniture, management and the Board concluded that the Young America business could not achieve an acceptable level of revenue within an adequate time frame to assure sustainable profitability and has decided that it is time for our company to focus its efforts on our profitable and growing Stanley brand," continued Prillaman.
Orders for the company's Stanley brand were up double digits in the first quarter, even with the weather-related challenges that plagued retailers across the country. "We have a healthy Stanley business that is making money. It is supported by a wonderful heritage, strong product in the field and future pipeline, and we are looking forward to the prospects of focusing our team solely on the growth and profitability of this brand in the short-term," concluded Prillaman.
The company ended its first quarter with approximately $16.7 million in cash and remains debt free. The results of the first quarter and impact of the restructuring will be discussed in detail on the upcoming conference call.
To allow for sufficient evaluation of restructuring charges, the company will delay its release of first quarter results until after market closes on April 30, 2014 and will hold its conference call on the following morning at 9:00 a.m. Eastern Time. The Annual Shareholder's Meeting remains scheduled for April 17, 2014.
17:54
TPZ Tortoise Power and Energy provides balance sheet information and asset coverage ratio update as of March 31, 2014 (25.29 -0.11)
Co announced that as of March 31, 2014, the company's unaudited total assets were approximately $238.4 million and its unaudited net asset value was $200.1 million, or $28.79 per share.
17:51
MNKD Mannkind confirms FDA Advisory Committee recommends approval of AFREZZA (4.20 0.00)
Co confirmed that the Endocrinologic and Metabolic Drugs Advisory Committee of the FDA voted 13 to 1 to recommend that AFREZZA (insulin human [rDNA origin]) Inhalation Powder be granted marketing approval by the FDA to improve glycemic control in adults with type 1 diabetes and voted 14 to 0 to recommend that AFREZZA be granted marketing approval by the FDA to improve glycemic control in adults with type 2 diabetes. If approved, AFREZZA would be the first ultra rapid-acting mealtime insulin therapy available in the United States.
17:41
MNI McClatchy receives $147 mln cash distribution from Classified Ventures as a result of sale of Apartments.com (6.54 +0.12)
McClatchy expects that proceeds on an after-tax basis will be approximately $90 million. McClatchy owns a 25.6% interest in CV and its portion of the gain from the sale of Apartments.com will be recorded in its equity income in unconsolidated companies in the second quarter of 2014. Taxes on its portion of the gain will also be included in McClatchy's tax provision in the same quarter of 2014. Management reiterated that the funds from the distribution will be used for general corporate purposes, including debt reduction.
17:39
TYG Tortoise Energy Infrastructure, Tortoise Energy Capital (TYY), and Tortoise North American Energy (TYN) provide balance sheeet information and asset coverage ratio update as of March 31, 2014 (46.19 +0.39)
Tortoise Energy Infrastructure (TYG) announced that as of March 31, 2014, the company's unaudited total assets were approximately $2.4 billion and its unaudited net asset value was $1.3 billion, or $45.87 per share.
Tortoise Energy Capital (TYY) announced that as of March 31, 2014, the company's unaudited total assets were approximately $1.2 billion and its unaudited net asset value was $692.1 million, or $34.48 per share.
Tortoise North American Energy (TYN) announced that as of March 31, 2014, the company's unaudited total assets were approximately $295.7 million and its unaudited net asset value was $191.1 million or $30.26 per share.
17:38
ICPT Intercept Pharma announces proposed public offering of 1 mln shares of common stock: 600k sold by Intercept, 400k being sold by institutional selling stockholders (334.19 +4.40)
Co announced that it has commenced an underwritten public offering of 1,000,000 shares of its common stock. 600,000 of the shares in the offering are to be sold by Intercept and 400,000 are to be sold by certain institutional selling stockholders. BofA Merrill Lynch, Citigroup, Goldman, Sachs & Co. and Deutsche Bank Securities are acting as joint book-running managers for the proposed offering.
Intercept intends to use the net proceeds of this offering to fund: work to support the company's anticipated filings for marketing approval of obeticholic acid (OCA) in primary biliary cirrhosis (PBC) at the end of 2014; the long-term safety extension portion of the company's POISE trial and its planned clinical outcomes trial in PBC patients; preparation for the potential commercial launch of OCA in PBC; continued development of OCA in NASH and conduct market research and pre-commercial activities in NASH; and expansion of the company's infrastructure, including development and corporate personnel, to support the planned increased scale of its operations. The balance, if any, will be used for general corporate purposes. Intercept will not receive any proceeds from the sale of shares of common stock by the selling stockholders, including any sale of shares of common stock if the underwriters exercise their option to purchase additional shares of common stock from the selling stockholders.
17:18
AUQ AuRico Gold announces preliminary Q1 production results: Gold ounces produced rose 17.4% year/year to 54,205 ounces (4.26 -0.09)
Co is reporting its seventh consecutive quarter of record production, representing a 10% increase over the prior quarter and a 17% increase over the first quarter of 2013. The solid quarter-over-quarter production growth was driven by increased production from both our cornerstone Young-Davidson mine and the El Chanate mine. Period-over-period production growth is expected to continue going forward, underpinned by the ongoing ramp-up in production at the Young-Davidson mine located in northern Ontario. Total gold ounces produced in Q1 2014 was 54,205 vs 48,526 in prior quarter and 46,170 in prior year.
"We are pleased with the progression of the ramp-up at the Young-Davidson mine, which has underpinned a seventh consecutive quarter of record, company-wide production," stated Scott Perry, President and CEO of AuRico. He continued, "The increase in underground mining rates to 4,000 tonnes per day by the end of 2014 and to an ultimate target of 8,000 tonnes per day in 2016 will continue to drive higher production at lower unit costs."
17:16
PACW PacWest Bancorp and CapitalSource (CSE) announce receipt of final regulatory approval (44.71 +1.70)
Co and CapitalSource (CSE) announced they have received regulatory approval from the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System and that the merger will close on Monday, April 7, 2014 at the close of business. As previously announced, the integration of CapitalSource Bank systems and the conversion of CapitalSource Bank's branches to Pacific Western Bank's operating platform are scheduled to be completed over the weekend of April 11, 2014. CapitalSource has 21 branches, twelve of which are being closed in the consolidation with Pacific Western Bank at the close of business on April 11. One overlapping Pacific Western branch is also being closed in the consolidation at the close of business on April 11. All remaining branches will re-open on Monday, April 14, 2014 as Pacific Western Bank branches.
17:16
HBHC Hancock Holding announces the divestiture of selected insurance lines of business (37.42 +0.77)
Co announced today that it has agreed to sell its property and casualty (P&C) and group benefits lines of business within its subsidiary insurance agencies to AssuredPartners Inc. in Lake Mary, Florida. Hancock will retain its life and title insurance lines of business within Hancock and Whitney Insurance Agencies. In addition, a referral program has been established with AssuredPartners so that Hancock and Whitney can continue providing clients P&C insurance and employee group benefits services. The transaction is expected to close April 4, 2014, with an effective date of April 1, 2014. Although ownership of the business will be transferred on the closing date, certain transitional services will be provided by Hancock to AssuredPartners for a 120 day period. The transaction will be reflected in the Company's second quarter 2014 financial results. The lines of business being divested represent approximately half of the Company's 2013 insurance revenue, and the sale is not expected to have a material impact on future net operating results.
17:08
CCI Crown Castle announces pricing of $850 mln offering of 4.875% senior notes due 2022 (74.76 +0.98)
Co announced that it has priced its previously announced public offering of senior notes due 2022. Due to investor demand, the offering was increased to $850 million. The notes will have an interest rate of 4.875% per annum and will be issued at a price equal to 99.5% of their face value to yield 4.951%. The net proceeds from the offering will be approximately $837 million, after deducting underwriting discounts and commissions and other offering expenses payable by Crown Castle. Crown Castle expects to use a portion of the net proceeds from the offering to purchase or redeem all of its outstanding 7.125% Senior Notes due 2019 and pay fees and expenses related to the foregoing. Crown Castle intends to use the remaining net proceeds for general corporate purposes, which may include the repayment or repurchase of certain other outstanding indebtedness. Barclays, Credit Agricole CIB, BofA Merrill Lynch, TD Securities, RBC Capital Markets, RBS, SunTrust Robinson Humphrey, Morgan Stanley, J.P. Morgan, Mitsubishi UFJ Securities and Citigroup are the joint book-running managers of the offering.
17:06
PKY Parkway Prop amends unsecured credit facilities (18.39 +0.14)
Co announced it has entered into an Amended, Restated and Consolidated Credit Agreement for its senior unsecured credit facilities, which increased the size of the Company's revolving credit facility to $250.0 million and consolidated its two existing unsecured term loans into a five-year term loan tranche totaling $250.0 million and a seven-year term loan tranche totaling $100.0 million. Additionally, the Company has amended its $10.0 million working capital revolving credit facility under substantially the same terms and conditions.
17:01
TA TravelCenters of America announces delayed annual report filing (8.58 +0.43)
Co announced that it has not timely filed its 2013 annual report on Form 10-K ("10-K") in accordance with the requirements of the Securities Exchange Commission ("SEC") and the New York Stock Exchange ("NYSE"). The reasons for the current delay are the same as those described in TravelCenters' Form 12b-25 filing with the SEC made on March 17, 2014, except that more time is required to complete the 10-K. TravelCenters expects that it will regain compliance with the NYSE listing standards upon filing the 10-K, and it is working towards filing the 10-K as soon as possible.
16:52
ROYT Pacific Coast Oil Trust provides 2014 operations and permitting update and capital program summary (13.13 -0.14)
Randall Breitenbach, CEO of PCEC, said, "As the sponsor of Pacific Coast Oil Trust, a perpetual royalty trust, 2014 will be another active year for PCEC. Our 2014 capital program balances the goals of maximizing current year distributions with enhancing the long term value and development potential of PCEC's assets. We will continue ongoing development of the conventional resources in the Orcutt Field and the Los Angeles Basin as planned. In addition, development of the Orcutt diatomite formation remains on track. During the remainder of 2014 we will continue to pursue Santa Barbara County Planning Commission approval for the Orcutt Hill Resource Enhancement Plan, which calls for the addition of 96 diatomite wells to our current inventory of 78 active diatomite wells. We currently expect a final hearing on approval of this phase of the plan in late 2014 or early 2015."
Operations and Permitting Update:
Orcutt Field - Non-Diatomite and Diatomite Development: The producing diatomite formation in the Orcutt Field lies approximately 500 to 1,100 feet below the surface. PCEC began cyclic steam development in 2005 and was producing from about 78 active diatomite wells as of December 31, 2013. Current production is about 1,500 Boe per day. During 2014 while the OHREP permitting process is moving through the approval process, PCEC plans to undertake the following diatomite projects: recomplete four wells, upgrade various instruments and controls, and improve efficiencies of existing equipment.
East Beverly Hills Field - West Pico Drillsite: There are currently 37 producing wells and six waterflood injection wells in the West Pico Unit. Twelve new wells have been drilled from this location since 2003. During 2014, PCEC plans to convert two wells to improve water injection performance, recomplete one existing well to improve production and to upgrade and optimize equipment at the drillsite.
Sawtelle and East Coyote Fields: There are currently 11 producing wells and three waterflood injection wells in PCEC's Sawtelle property. BreitBurn Operating L.P. ("BOLP") operates the Sawtelle Field. BOLP has indicated that capital spending during 2014 will be minimal. There are currently 51 producing wells, and 20 waterflood injection wells in PCEC's East Coyote property. BOLP also operates the East Coyote field. During 2014, BOLP plans to recomplete three wells, return three currently non-producing wells to production, optimize the downhole performance of four other existing wells and undertake minor mandatory facility upgrades.
2014 Capital Program Summary:
PCEC has informed the Trustee that its calendar year 2014 capital program will total approximately $21.7 million. This total includes investments of approximately $8.8 million ($7.1 million net to the Trust's interest) in the Developed Properties and approximately $12.8 milliona in the Remaining Properties.
16:48
CSGP CoStar Group files multi state lawsuits with multiple defendants alleging thousands of instances of copyright infringement (188.95 +2.21)
Co is filing a series of lawsuits against 8 real estate firms and individuals as part of a coordinated anti-piracy campaign aimed at ending theft of CoStar services. The suits allege systematic theft of CoStar's services though acts of online piracy and computer hacking via illegal password sharing. The defendants in these cases could be ordered to pay millions of dollars in damages. CoStar is also filing a "John Doe" lawsuit in New York federal court based on allegations of improper use of CoStar data and photos to populate a competing service called CompStak. To move the case forward against named defendants rather than John Does, CoStar seeks to compel CompStak's disclosure of the identities of its users that have allegedly violated CoStar's copyrights.
16:46
ONNN ON Semiconductor and Studio One Media to jointly develop audio solutions (9.45 +0.05)
Studio One Media has entered into an agreement with ON Semiconductor (ONNN) to develop integrated circuits (ICs) utilizing Studio One's award-winning AfterMaster audio technology and ON Semiconductor's DSP product development expertise. The devices are expected to offer an unprecedented level of audio clarity, depth and loudness for consumer electronic devices such as headphones, televisions, sound bars, computers, home and car stereos, tablets and mobile phones. It is expected that the audio ICs will also be used in a broad number of industrial applications, including business phone systems, police and military radios, intercom systems and many other product categories.
16:45
SENEA Seneca Foods acquires 50% of Truitt Bros (31.86 +0.38)
Co and Peter W. Truitt have entered into a Share Purchase Agreement whereas the Company has acquired Peter's 50% ownership interest in Truitt Bros., Inc., and directly related holdings. The effective date of the transaction is April, 1, 2014. The management of Truitt Bros., Inc. will remain unchanged. The remaining terms of the Share Purchase Agreement are currently not being disclosed. In addition to the aforementioned Share Purchase Agreement, the Company also entered into an Agreement with David Truitt and other shareholders. This Agreement grants the Company the right to acquire the remaining 50% ownership of Truitt Bros., Inc. at a future point in time.
16:41
AET Aetna and Medical Professional Services announce a value-based collaborative care agreement (75.05 +0.08)
Co announced enhancements to their longstanding Independent Practice Association agreement in Connecticut. A new contract addendum will facilitate improved care coordination and clinical quality of care for Aetna members while lowering their overall health care costs. Nearly 15,000 Aetna members covered under fully insured and self-funded plans in Connecticut who have sought care from MPS providers in the past 24 months are included in this new program with MPS. Under the new collaboration agreement, Aetna will reward MPS and MPS physicians for quality, efficiency and patient satisfaction via specified measures.
16:40
CENT Central Garden acquires Envincio assets (8.30 +0.17)
Co announced that it has purchased certain assets of Envincio LLC, a wholly-owned subsidiary of SantoLubes LLC. The assets acquired include established brands, EPA registration assets, inventory, and trade receivables.
"This acquisition will enable Central to be a key supplier and product innovator in the growing natural insecticides product market, often characterized as EPA-exempt products, as well as expanding offerings in traditional pesticides," said Frank Jusich, SVP Professional Brands. "The exclusive rights that Central acquired through this transaction will allow us to leverage these patented essential oil blends, along with building our existing business, to best serve the professional pest control markets."
16:30
VVC Vectren: Energy Systems Group acquires Chevron Energy Solutions' Federal Operations, awarded $45 million Waste-to-Energy contract (39.32 -0.07)
Co announced two major business developments. ESG has acquired the federal sector energy services unit of Chevron Energy Solutions (CES), which is owned by Chevron U.S.A., Inc.; the business unit employs 48 experienced professionals, performs under several long-term operations and maintenance contracts, and has a robust construction project sales funnel. Separately, ESG was awarded a $45 million contract with the Frederick-Winchester Service Authority (FWSA) for the design and construction of energy efficiency and infrastructure improvements at the Opequon Water Reclamation Facility in Winchester, Virginia.
16:29
MEMP Memorial Production Partners announces closing of acquisition of Oil and Gas Properties; expected to be immediately accretive to distributable cash flow (22.80 +0.27)
Co announced that it has closed its previously announced acquisition of certain oil and natural gas producing properties in East Texas from its sponsor, Memorial Resource Development LLC, for approximately $34 million, subject to customary post-closing adjustments. The acquisition was funded with borrowings under MEMP's revolving credit facility. The effective date of this transaction is February 1, 2014. Transaction Highlights:
Expected to be immediately accretive to distributable cash flow Estimated net proved reserves of 15.4 Bcfe (100% proved developed producing and 54% gas / 46% liquids) November net production of approximately 4.3 MMcfe/d (54% natural gas and 46% liquids) Proved reserve to production ratio of 9.8 years Properties consist of 80 gross (26.0 net) wells; Pro forma 39.5 net wells
16:16
TEP Tallgrass Energy Partners announces completion of the Trailblazer acquisition and an increased distribution for the first quarter of 2014 (36.90 +0.49)
Co announced that it has closed on the acquisition of Trailblazer Pipeline Company LLC from a wholly owned subsidiary of Tallgrass Development, LP for total consideration valued at approximately $164 million. In addition, the Partnership declared a quarterly cash distribution to unitholders of $0.3250 per common unit for the first quarter of 2014, or $1.30 on an annualized basis. This represents an amount that is 13% over the minimum quarterly distribution of $0.2875 and a 3.2% sequential increase from the fourth quarter 2013 distribution of $0.3150. "We are pleased to announce the completion of our first dropdown transaction at TEP and the third consecutive increase in our quarterly distribution. We expect the acquisition of Trailblazer to be immediately accretive to our unitholders, and as a result of this acquisition, we plan to recommend to our Board of Directors an increase in our annualized distribution of at least $0.20 beginning with the second quarter of 2014," said Tallgrass' President and CEO, David G. Dehaemers Jr.
16:15
WFC Wells Fargo names CFO Sloan to Head Wholesale Banking Group; Dave Hoyt to retire at the end of June (49.77 +0.03)
Co announced today that Timothy J. Sloan, the company's current chief financial officer and a senior executive vice president, will become head of the Wholesale Banking group, effective May 15, 2014. He will succeed David A. Hoyt who has decided to retire. Mr. Hoyt will continue in his role until May 15, 2014, and will remain with the company until June 30, 2014, to help with the transition of responsibilities.
John R. Shrewsberry, current head of Wells Fargo Securities and an executive vice president, will succeed Sloan as chief financial officer and become a senior executive vice president, also effective May 15, 2014. As CFO, he will report directly to John Stumpf, Wells Fargo's chairman and chief executive officer, and will serve on the company's Operating Committee.
16:15
AMD AMD Amends Wafer Supply Agreement With GLOBALFOUNDRIES (4.07 +0.06)
Co announced that it amended its Wafer Supply Agreement (WSA) with GLOBALFOUNDRIES Inc. for 2014. Under the terms of the amendment, AMD and GLOBALFOUNDRIES agreed on purchase commitments for 2014 and established fixed pricing and other terms of the WSA which apply to products AMD will purchase from GLOBALFOUNDRIES. Under this amendment AMD expects to pay GLOBALFOUNDRIES approximately $1.2 billion in 2014. These purchases contemplate AMD's current PC market expectations and the manufacturing of certain Graphics Processor Units (GPUs) and semi-custom game console products at GLOBALFOUNDRIES in 2014. The 2014 amendment does not impact AMD's 2014 financial goals including gross margin.
16:13
MORN Morningstar acquires ByAllAccounts, a provider of data aggregation technology for financial applications, for $28 mln (79.85 +0.83)
Co acquired ByAllAccounts, Inc., a provider of innovative data aggregation technology for financial applications. ByAllAccounts uses a knowledge-based process, including patented artificial intelligence technology, to collect, consolidate, and enrich financial account data and deliver it to virtually any platform. The company has built a network of more than 2,100 clients, 4,300 custodians, and 40 platform and service providers. Clients include independent financial advisors, asset managers, wealth managers/family offices, trust companies, and broker-dealers. Currently, more than $730 billion in assets move daily through the ByAllAccounts aggregation engine. Morningstar acquired ByAllAccounts for $28 million, subject to working capital adjustments.
16:13
WRAPX Closing Market Summary: S&P 500 Sets Fresh Record High
The stock market kicked off April on an upbeat note with the Nasdaq Composite (+1.6%) leading the charge. The S&P 500 (+0.7%) settled at a fresh record high of 1885.52 with eight sectors registering gains while the Dow Jones Industrial Average (+0.5%) lagged.
In the absence of notable pre-market data or earnings, the major averages began the day with a steady climb that was assisted by upbeat action in Europe, where markets in France, Germany, and Great Britain posted solid gains between 0.5% and 0.8%.
For the second day in a row, the Nasdaq began the day in the lead, maintaining its outperformance throughout the session. The early strength of biotechnology (IBB +2.2%) propelled the initial advance while the index was kept near its session high into the afternoon by the daylong outperformance of the technology sector (+1.3%).
The tech sector received considerable support from several of its top components. The largest sector member, Apple (AAPL 541.65, +4.91), rose 0.9% while other large names like Cisco Systems (CSCO 23.10, +0.88), Google (GOOG 1134.89, +20.38), Oracle (ORCL 41.49, +0.58), and Qualcomm (QCOM 80.10, +1.24) gained between 1.4% and 3.9%.
Although the largest sector finished ahead of the broader market, that was not the case with all top-weighed groups. Financials (+0.4%) and energy (+0.5%) lagged while the discretionary space (+1.4%) finished in the lead.
The growth-sensitive discretionary sector was underpinned by momentum names like Amazon.com (AMZN 342.99, +6.62), Netflix (NFLX 364.69, +12.66), and Priceline.com (PCLN 1251.37, +59.48), all of which struggled in March, but started April on an upbeat note. Shares of Ford (F 16.32, +0.72) also contributed, gaining 4.6% after the company reported a 3.0% year-over-year increase in monthly sales.
On the countercyclical side, consumer staples (-0.1%), telecom services (+0.3%), and utilities (-0.7%) ended behind the broader market while health care settled in-line with the S&P 500.
With stocks holding gains throughout the session, participants did not show strong interest in volatility protection, sending the CBOE Volatility Index (VIX 13.10, -0.78) lower by 5.6%.
Treasuries registered modest losses with the benchmark 10-yr yield climbing four basis points to 2.76%.
Participation was on the light side as less than 700 million shares changed hands on the NYSE floor.
Today's economic data was limited to February Construction Spending and the March ISM Index:
Construction spending increased 0.1% in February after falling a downwardly revised 0.2% (from +0.1%) in January while the Briefing.com consensus expected an increase of 0.1%. Extreme winter weather conditions in January and February were blamed for a general downturn in economic data; however, construction, which should feel the brunt of the negative winter effects, was largely in-line with recent trends. Thus, there is no reason to expect construction spending to surge due to pent up demand in the near future.The ISM Manufacturing Index increased to 53.7 in March from 53.2 in February. The Briefing.com consensus expected the index to increase to 54.0. Extreme winter weather conditions were blamed for a deterioration in the ISM Manufacturing Index in January. Yet, as temperatures returned to normal, the ISM Manufacturing Index remained well below its Q4 2013 averages. This tells us that weakness in manufacturing activities was likely not tied to the adverse weather, but rather caused by cyclical trends. Tomorrow, the weekly MBA Mortgage Index will be released at 7:00 ET while the March ADP Employment Change will be announced at 8:15 ET (Briefing.com consensus 215K). The day's data will be topped off with the February Factory Orders report (Briefing.com consensus 1.1%), which is set for a 10:00 ET release.
Nasdaq Composite +2.2% YTD Russell 2000 +2.2% YTD S&P 500 +2.0% YTD Dow Jones Industrial Average -0.3% YTD
16:08
ENVI Envivio announces that it is powering premium live HD sports channels on Apple TV (AAPL) for a European Tier 1 service provider (3.30 +0.22)
ENVI announced that it is powering premium live HD sports channels on Apple TV for a European Tier 1 service provider.
The premium channels are compressed using Envivio Muse Live encoders, protected using a new encryption mode by Envivio Halo network media processors (NMP) and delivered to Apple TV. Envivio showcased the live service at the recent TV Connect exhibition in London. Halo is designed to support live or on-demand adaptive bitrate TV for the full range of Apple devices, using the latest content protection technologies. This capability is critical for video operators desiring to securely deliver high quality premium content to Internet-connected devices.
16:06
OME Omega Protein announces termination of shareholder rights plan (12.63 +0.56)
Co announced that its Board of Directors has approved an amendment to its Shareholder Rights Plan to accelerate the final expiration date to April 1, 2014, more than six years earlier than initially specified in the Plan. The Plan was originally adopted in June 2010 in view of various factors that were then impacting the price of the Company's common stock, including the 2010 BP oil spill in the U.S. Gulf of Mexico.
16:06
VPRT Vistaprint Agrees to acquire Italian company Pixartprinting Srl for a base purchase price of ~ EUR127 mln; co expects transaction to be accretive to its fiscal 2014 rev and operating cash flow, but dilutive to GAAP EPS due to transaction costs and expected amortization expense for acquisition-related intangible assets (50.30 +1.08)
VPRT announced it has entered into a definitive agreement to acquire Pixartprinting Srl for a base purchase price of approximately 127 million, resulting in Vistaprint ownership of 97 percent of Pixartprinting, and 3 percent retained ownership by Pixartprinting's founder.
As part of the transaction, Vistaprint will assume 100 percent of the majority stake in Pixartprinting that is currently held by private equity firm Alcedo SGR. The agreement also includes a sliding-scale earn-out of up to 10 million for Pixartprinting, subject to the achievement of revenue and EBITDA performance targets for calendar year 2014. Vistaprint expects Pixartprinting will have a net debt position of 18 million at the close of the transaction. Based in Quarto D'Altino, Veneto, Italy with approximately 330 employees, Pixartprinting is a web-to-print business serving over 100,000 customers. The company's revenue primarily comes from graphic design agencies, print resellers and local printers that in turn serve small and medium businesses for flyers, brochures, decorated apparel, business cards, signs, banners, labels, textiles and other printed products.Consideration for the transaction will be in cash, using Vistaprint's existing debt facility. Vistaprint expects this transaction to be accretive to our fiscal 2014 revenue and operating cash flow, but dilutive to GAAP EPS due to transaction costs and expected amortization expense for acquisition-related intangible assets. On a non-GAAP EPS basis, which excludes amortization expense for acquisition-related intangible assets, the transaction is expected to have a neutral impact in fiscal 2014. In fiscal 2015, we expect the transaction to be dilutive to GAAP EPS, but accretive on a non-GAAP basis. Vistaprint will provide updated detailed guidance in the next quarterly earnings announcement following the close of the transaction.
16:04
NYMT New York Mortgage Trust announces public offering of 13 mln shares of its common stock (7.82 +0.04)
NYMT announced today that it plans to make a public offering of 13,000,000 shares of its common stock.
NYMT intends to use a majority of the net proceeds of this offering to acquire distressed residential loans and the remainder of the net proceeds to invest in mezzanine loans to and preferred equity investments in owners of multi-family properties and certain of its other targeted assets. The Company may also use a portion of the net proceeds for general working capital purposes, including the repayment of indebtedness.
UBS, Credit Suisse, Barclays, and RBC Capital Markets will serve as joint bookrunning managers for the offering.
16:04
APOL Apollo Group beats by $0.09, misses on revs; reaffirms FY14 guidance (35.16 +0.92)
Reports Q2 (Feb) earnings of $0.28 per share, excluding non-recurring items, $0.09 better than the Capital IQ Consensus Estimate of $0.19; revenues fell 18.6% year/year to $679.1 mln vs the $689.02 mln consensus.
University of Phoenix Degreed Enrollment was 250,300, a 16.8% decrease YoY.New Degreed Enrollment was 32,500, a 16.5% decrease YoY.Co reaffirms guidance for FY14, sees FY14 revs of $3.0-3.1 bln vs. $3.06 bln Capital IQ Consensus; adj. operating income $400-450 mln.
Under its share repurchase program, the Company repurchased ~1.7 million shares of its common stock at a weighted average purchase price of $31.93 per share for a total cost of $54.7 million during the three months ended February 28, 2014.
16:03
MN Manning & Napier Advisors announces exchange of units of Manning & Napier Group (16.82 +0.05)
Co provided an update regarding its legacy ownership exchange. Pursuant to the existing exchange agreement established during the co's initial public offering, the legacy shareholders, consisting of its founder, management team and certain other employees, have the opportunity to exchange on an annual basis a portion of their interests in Manning & Napier Group, LLC for either cash or shares of the co's Class A common stock. This annual process was recently completed, and as a result, legacy shareholders exchanged an aggregate of 2,098,837 Class A units of Manning & Napier Group, LLC for ~ $30.3 million. Subsequent to the exchange, the Class A units were retired. As a result of the exchange, the co's ownership interest in Manning & Napier Group, LLC has correspondingly increased.
The price of each Class A unit was $14.45, or the average closing-price of the Class A common stock, for the 15 trading days prior to March 27, 2014, less a 5% discount.
16:03
PSIX Power Solutions International announces the acquisition of Professional Power Products for $46 mln; the transaction is expected to be accretive to the co's results in 2014 (76.93 +1.76)
The co acquired all of the outstanding capital stock of PPPI for an initial cash purchase price of $46 mln. In addition, the co will issue to the sellers between $5 mln and $15 mln in the co's common stock, valued at $76.02 per share, based upon PPPI's 2014 operating results. The cash portion of the transaction is being financed initially with the co's bank credit facility. To facilitate the transaction, the co entered into an amended and restated agreement with Wells Fargo Bank, N.A. increasing its revolving line of credit from $75 mln to $90 mln, among other things.
Excluding one-time transaction, integration and purchase accounting related costs, the transaction is expected to be accretive to the Company's results in 2014. The earnings per share impact also will be subject to the accounting allocation of the purchase price and contingent consideration.
16:02
BXMT Blackstone Mortgage Trust announces public offering of 8 mln shares of Class A common stock (28.68 -0.07)
BXMT announced it has commenced an underwritten public offering of 8,000,000 shares of its class A common stock.
Co intends to use the net proceeds from the offering to originate and purchase additional commercial mortgage loans and other target assets and investments consistent with its investment strategies and investment guidelines, and for working capital and other general corporate purposes. Citigroup, BofA/Merrill, J.P. Morgan, Wells Fargo, and Morgan Stanley are acting as joint book-running managers for the offering.
16:02
AVHI AV Homes announces results of repurchase right for $5.402 mln aggregate principal amount of its 4.50% convertible senior notes (18.26 +0.17)
Co announced the results of the previously announced option of holders of $5,402,000 aggregate principal amount of its outstanding 4.50% Convertible Senior Notes due 2024 to require the Company to repurchase all or a portion of their Notes pursuant to the terms of the Notes and the indenture governing the Notes. Under the terms of the Repurchase Right, holders of the Notes had the opportunity to surrender the Notes for repurchase prior to 5:00 p.m., New York City time, on March 27, 2014 and had the opportunity to withdraw any Notes previously surrendered for repurchase at any time prior to 5:00 p.m., New York City time, on March 31, 2014. $5,402,000 aggregate principal amount of the Notes was validly surrendered as of the Repurchase Deadline and not validly withdrawn as of the Withdrawal Deadline, and therefore $5,402,000 aggregate principal amount of the Notes were repurchased by the Company as of April 1, 2014 pursuant to the Repurchase Right. The repurchase of the Notes will be funded by the Company's available cash. The full aggregate principal amount of the Notes was surrendered for repurchase, and therefore none of the Notes remain outstanding.
16:00
HRS Harris Corporation receives $49 mln in orders from nation in Asia for Falcon III Wideband tactical radios (73.79 +0.66)
]]></text></news-item>