<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-9781-F0NV-F379"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>UPDATE: More than 50 employees of Hillsville business hospitalized</title><source>CBS - 7 WDBJ (Roanoke-Lynchburg, Virginia)</source><author>Orlando Salinas</author><text><![CDATA[HILLSVILLE, Va.
Investigators with Virginia Department of Labor and Industry are still trying to determine what sent more than 50 employees of Virginia Produce to the hospital Tuesday.
They were on the scene at Virginia Produce for most of the afternoon.
Tests on the air quality in the plant came back clean.
Mechanical systems at the plant are back up as of 8 p.m.
Air quality will be monitored through the night, according to a press release.
=======================
More than 50 employees of a large produce company in Hillsville are in the hospital after getting sick on the job in Carroll County.
We are waiting to find out if they were poisoned from carbon monoxide or some other gas.
Twin County 911 received a call Tuesday afternoon around 1 p.m. When rescuers and law enforcement arrived many employees were outside the building complaining of headaches, nausea, dizziness and trouble breathing.
Victims were taken to Twin County Regional Hospital, Northern Hospital of Surry County, and Wythe County Community Hospital. At least three people were flown to Duke Hospital for treatment. A law enforcement source tells WDBJ7 that some were taken by ambulance, some by police car, and some by bus.
Fire, rescue, and police units are still working to determine what type of gas may be responsible.
Several law enforcement sources tell WDBJ7 it looks like a new A/C system was being installed or a new piece was being added on, and there may have been a leak.
We 're also told it's possible the new unit may have been filled with the wrong refrigerant. That may have made everyone sick.
Federal investigators are now involved.
The owner of Virginia Produce Company, Moir Beamer, spoke with WDBJ7 reporter Orlando Salinas on Tuesday afternoon. Beamer said he believes the problem started somewhere in the packing area of the building.
Virginia Produce is one of the largest produce companies in the commonwealth. It's located at 227 Industrial Park Drive in Hillsville.
We'll update the story with more information as it becomes available.
]]></text></news-item>