<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-9XX1-JC3H-0303"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>When the big bad is worse</title><source>Battle Creek Enquirer (Michigan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Let's put it this way: If the Koch Brothers were Russians, we'd call them oligarchs: grasping barbarians exercising crude political power.
Hence "Americans for Prosperity," the group funded by billionaire brothers David H. and Charles G. Koch that's spending untold millions in 2014 on TV commercials attacking the Affordable Care Act as a government boondoggle that "just doesn't work."
The deeper strategy, AFP president Tim Phillips told the New York Times, is to present the law as "a broader cautionary tale" crafted "to change the way voters think about the role of government for years to come."
Or as the sloganeering sheep in Orwell's "Animal Farm" might have put it, "Big government bad, big business good!"
As so often happens with corporate malfeasance, the details can be hard to believe. Documents turned over to the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration by General Motors show that company engineers knew about problems with an ignition switch in Chevy Cobalts as long ago as 2001.
That it could be a fatal flaw wasn't immediately recognized.
By 2009, however, engineers concluded that the faulty switch played a causal role in several fatal accidents and that while Cobalts were going out of production, hundreds of thousands were still rolling.
Nevertheless, GM did nothing, while company lawyers fought off or stonewalled lawsuits alleging product liability.
Twenty-three fatal accidents and 26 deaths later, GM finally issued a recall notice for 1.6 million vehicles last month.
Which brings us to the Tea Party paradise of North Carolina and Duke Energy's massive coal ash spill into the Dan River - spreading as many as 82,000 tons of toxic sludge along 70 miles of scenic river bottom. According to the Associated Press, "coal ash contains arsenic, lead, mercury and other heavy metals highly toxic to humans and wildlife."
In addition to the "accidental" spill, caused by a collapsed corrugated pipe seemingly uninspected since 1986, environmental activists photographed Duke employees pumping an estimated 61 million gallons of coal ash-contaminated water into the Cape Fear River further east.
The resulting uproar has persuaded GOP Gov. Pat McCrory, a 29-year Duke Energy employee (and recipient of some $1.1 million in Duke-sponsored campaign donations), to change his mind about burdensome federal regulation. His state's toothless regulators will now "partner" with the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency to pursue joint enforcement against the utility.
Meanwhile, arguing strenuously against stricter regulation of coal ash has been an industry front group called ALEC (the American Legislative Exchange Council) financed by - you guessed it - those well-known philanthropists David and Charles Koch.
Gene Lyons' email is a eugenelyons2@yahoo.com
Gene Lyons
]]></text></news-item>