<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-9801-JD6S-R3YF"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>Iler touts Brunswick company for coal ash cleanup</title><source>The Brunswick Beacon (Shallotte, North Carolina)</source><author>Brian Slattery</author><text><![CDATA[OCEAN ISLE BEACH - State Rep. Frank Iler has pitched a Brunswick County business as a possible solution to Duke Energy's environmental pollution problem.
On Friday, March 21, state regulators asked a judge to withdraw a proposed settlement that would have allowed Duke Energy to resolve environmental violations by paying a $99,000 fine with no requirement that the $50 billion company clean up pollution caused by its coal ash spill onto the banks of the Dan River near Eden in early February.
In a March 26 statement, Iler addressed news reports about the coal ash spill into the Dan River, as well as the apparent pumping of coal ash-contaminated water into the Cape Fear River in Chatham County.
"These incidents have suddenly brought a sense of urgency to clean-up plans that have been discussed for years. I, for one, am concerned about the Dan River spill, as a former resident of that beautiful area. However, I am equally concerned about the Cape Fear River, as it is the source for drinking water in Brunswick County, the area I represent and in which I live," Iler said.
Iler said Ocean Isle Beach-based EnviRemed is in touch with Duke Energy about one of EnviRemed processes to reduce heavy metals from contaminated water sources.
"This company produces a geochemical compound that removes the toxins and the heavy metals in coal ash - with no negative residual effect to the environment," Iler said. "Their compound has been proven in a previous situation, with EPA sanctioning, to neutralize arsenic, lead, mercury and other toxic wastes in coal ash. They have been in touch with (Department of Environment and Natural Resources) DENR and Duke, and we hope their solution is being considered."
Colby Price, project manager for EnviRemed's soil stabilization department, said he could not comment on whether the company is in contact with Duke Energy.
"(Rep. Iler) was speaking in terms of, I know of this company. They might possibly be of help," Price said.
But Price explained the six-year-old company's flagship product is an enzyme-based soil stabilization process that can increase the load bearing properties of soil, providing an alternative aggregate fill under asphalt roads.
The company also provides three other services: a gasification process to turn garbage into clean energy; a product able to reliquefy oil sludge to reuse the oil; and treatments for contaminated water and soil to remove organic materials or heavy metals.
According to the EnviRemed website, the company's coal treatment method involves applying a specially formulated slurry to bind metals that are found in water and soil. The metals are permanently bound in a crystalline structure in the solids that is not leachable according to Toxicity Characteristic Leaching Procedure (TCLP) standards. The bond created only strengthens with time.
"You do not have to excavate and haul (the solids) to a hazard landfill. You can leave it in place and it will not harm the environment," Price said.
Price said the company's processes are 100 percent organic and environmentally friendly.
EnviRemed reports it can treat contamination of phosphorus, mercury, arsenic, aluminum, lead, copper, silver, zinc, nickel, cobalt, iron, manganese, chromium, cadmium, vanadium, beryllium, selenium, strontium, cesium, barium, radium and uranium.
Coal ash, the waste material produced during the burning of coal, is a toxic substance containing arsenic, lead, mercury and other contaminants.
The Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) says people who live near coal ash disposal sites face higher risks for cancer and nervous system damage, cognitive defects, developmental delays and behavioral problems in children, reproductive problems, birth defects, lung disease and asthma.
A baseball field at South Brunswick Middle School has not been used for school activities of any kind since last spring after South Brunswick administrators were made aware of the presence of coal ash by the school district.
Workers noticed the coal ash as they excavated and regraded the field last year.
Coal ash is the nation's second-largest waste stream, but has never been regulated by the federal government, according to a recent report in The Washington Post. This means some states may have stricter standards for municipal trash than for toxic coal ash. The EPA proposed the first rules to regulate coal ash as hazardous waste in 2010, but a decision on them by President Obama's administration is not expected until the end of this year.
Brian Slattery is a staff writer for the Beacon. Reach him at 754-6890 or bslattery@brunswickbeacon.com
]]></text></news-item>