<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-9811-JD6S-R0N6"><date>2014-04-01</date><title>FERC hears both sides of pipeline dispute</title><source>The Daily Star (Oneonta, New York)</source><author>Joe Mahoney Staff Writer, THE DAILY STAR</author><text><![CDATA[RICHMONDVILLE - The superintendent of the Schoharie Central School District urged federal regulators Monday night to reject the proposed route of the Constitution Pipeline, saying the natural gas transmission system would endanger students at the Schoharie Career and Tech campus operated by Capital Region BOCES.
"It would be an accident waiting to happen," said Brian D. Sherman, the first person called on to comment in the first of a series of public meetings this week on a draft environmental impact statement prepared by Federal Energy Regulatory Commission staffers on the controversial $700 million project.
About 350 people packed the Cobleskill-Richmondville High School auditorium for the emotionally charged forum, including some 80 trade union workers, many of them clad in bright orange shirts, showing their support of the pipeline and the jobs they said it will bring to the region.
Some of those opposed to what the pipeline company calls its preferred route stopped short of asking FERC to reject the project, but simply urged that its path be altered to avoid their property. Others suggested FERC to refuse to issue a certificate of public convenience, which, if granted, would allow the project to be constructed and confer eminent domain authority to the company.
The draft environmental impact statement (EIS) issued by FERC in February found that while the project would have adverse impacts, they could be mitigated through a variety of measures. Representative of the BOCES campus, including several students, said they disagreed.
One student, Angelina Martinez, unfurled a list of 294 commercial pipeline ruptures since the year 2000, pleading with the FERC officials to not allow her school to be the site of the 295th mishap.
Late Monday night, a source close to the pipeline company said the company has advised BOCES officials that it is prepared to eliminate the plan to have an access road through the BOCES property and would relocate the route to an area of school property that is unused by BOCES.
According to BOCES officials, Constitution initially offered the the school system $25,475.02 for a right of way for the pipeline to run through the campus where students are trained in the use of heavy machinery and construction equipment. After school officials rejected that offer, the company followed up with an offer of $172,830 for the right of way, they said.
"No amount of money" would be worth agreeing to having the campus dissected by the pipeline, Sherman said.
Dave Parker, a Worcester town councilman and supporter of allowing shale gas drilling in New York, said he read the hundreds of pages of the environmental impact statement and called the document impressive.
He said he had accompanied a team of pipeline representatives conducting soil and wetland assessment last fall.
"The four young professionals who conducted the study were courteous, competent and extremely thorough, " he said, "and I'm sure the quality of their work is representative of the entire EIS."
Pete Stearns of Gloversville, representing Laborers International Union Local 157, said the families of many workers were counting on the project to keep them gainfully employed. He urged FERC to approve the EIS.
Jeff Stark of the Capital Region Construction and Building Trades Council agreed, saying: "This project is for the public good."
Noting the pipeline would cut through his property, Kenneth Stanton, who owns a 1,200-acre dairy farm in Middleburgh, the largest in the county, said the pipeline would jeopardize the business he has spent decades building up.
"That farm is going to die a slow death" if the project is approved, Stanton said. "It just seems like we're not in America anymore."
Others questioned the integrity of the FERC staff's findings, contending the agency appeared to accept the company's plans too readily.
"The bias in favor of approving the project is blatant and obvious," said Andy Mason of the Delaware Otsego Audubon Society. He said the pipeline pathway poses "a clear and present threat" to bird populations because it would leave the forest habitat fragmented.
Speaking in favor of the project, Leo McAllister, the Cobleskill town supervisor, said the pipeline would bring $4 million in new property tax revenue to the county and more than $1 million in new revenue to the local school district.
It would take the construction of more than 300 new homes to generate that much money in new revenue for the local taxing jurisdictions, McAllister said.
The federal agency has been assessing the controversial proposal using the standards spelled out in the National Environmental Policy Act. FERC is expected to decide whether to license the project being touted by a consortium of energy companies led by Williams Partners of Houston, which holds a 41-percent stake in the Constitution Pipeline.
The public will get to comment on the draft EIS at 7 p.m. tonight at Oneonta High School. On Wednesday night, FERC will hear comments at Afton High School.
The project sponsors say the pipeline will become a key piece of natural gas infrastructure in the U.S. Northeast.
]]></text></news-item>