<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-F151-DY0P-G0M8"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Appeals Court Rejects Cost Recovery By Subcontractor Against Landowner</title><source>Environmental Policy Alert</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[An appellate court in a first impression ruling is pulling back a lower court's broad reading of the Superfund law's cost recovery reach, saying that the right of cost recovery does not extend to unpaid subcontractors who conducted cleanup work and are seeking payment from a landowner whose general contractor failed to pass on the owner's payments to the subcontractor.
"There is no need -- and CERCLA is not designed -- to hold the responsible party perpetually liable as a surety in any dispute relating to the cleanup between or among contractors, subcontractors, employees, or suppliers," the U.S. Court of Appeals for the 2nd Circuit says in a March 18 ruling that is significant for subcontractors conducting cleanup at Superfund sites.
The ruling in Price Trucking Corp. v. Norampac Industries, Inc. reverses a lower court decision but stops far short of entirely barring cost recovery actions under the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation & Liability Act (CERCLA) by private contractors or subcontractors. The decision also avoids any interference with common law principles and state law remedies, such as state lien laws. The decision is available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID: 2465818)
Norampac, a potentially responsible party (PRP) that owns a brownfield property in Erie County, NY, hired general contractor AAA Environmental, Inc. to conduct soil excavation and removal at the property, which was contaminated with lead and other pollutants exceeding state standards. AAA Environmental, in turn, subcontracted the hauling aspect of the work to Price Trucking.
While Norampac paid AAA Environmental for the work, and the general contractor initially passed on payments to Price, AAA Environmental then stopped paying Price, despite the full payments from the landowner. While Norampac went on to directly pay Price for the final stages of the work, Price never received earlier payments AAA Environmental should have passed on to the hauler, after AAA Environmental had been paid by Norampac, according to the decision.
In 2009, Price sued Norampac, originally seeking more than $780,000 in unpaid bills, premising its claim on CERCLA's section 107 cost recovery provision, according to the court. Price has also sought payments separately from AAA Environmental through state court, but the general contractor appears to be out of business. Other claims Price has made have been partly successful.
"The sole question presented on appeal is whether CERCLA grants the subcontractor a right of recovery against the landowner in these circumstances, effectively requiring the landowner to pay twice for the same work performed -- once to the contractor and once to the subcontractor," the appeals court says. "We concluded that it does not," reversing a district court ruling.
Norampac had urged the court to go even further, and "find that CERCLA does not permit cost-recovery actions by private contractors and subcontractors," the court says. "Although this Circuit has not addressed the issue, other courts have determined that response contractors may indeed bring cost-recovery actions under certain circumstances."
In a footnote, the court explains that the landowner argued that Price's actions were a "response" only to its subcontract with AAA Environmental, and not directly a response to the discovery of contaminated soil. But the court says, "This argument would have the practical effect of foreclosing contractors' recourse to CERCLA's cost-recovery provisions, insofar as a contractor's only involvement with the site is as a participant in the response effort."
It concludes that "Because we agree with Norampac's position on a narrower ground, we need not decide and do not imply a view as to whether there may be cases in which a cleanup contractor or subcontractor could successfully bring a cost-recovery action."
The court found that Norampac paid for Price's work either through direct payments or payments to the general contractor, satisfying its responsibility to bear cleanup response costs. "In seeking to treat Norampac as though it were a surety to its subcontract with AAA Environmental, Price Trucking pushes the terms of CERCLA beyond their intended assignment of responsibilities," it says.
Later in the ruling, it concludes, "CERCLA does not create an additional system of insurance for the benefit of all contractors, subcontractors, employees, or suppliers who work on a cleanup operation."
]]></text></news-item>