<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWG-3F81-DYN6-W532"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>Chinese group sues Mitsubishi Materials over wartime forced labor</title><source>Japan Economic Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[SHIJIAZHUANG, China, April 2 - A group of Chinese people filed a lawsuit Wednesday against Mitsubishi Materials Corp., seeking compensation of 227 million yuan (about $37 million) from the company for wartime forced labor in Japan.
The lawsuit, the latest in a series of similar legal moves amid frayed Sino-Japanese ties over divergent views of history, was filed at the High People's Court of Hebei Province in Shijiazhuang.
The lower court in the provincial capital is likely to first examine claims of 149 plaintiffs, including survivors and bereaved families, to decide whether to begin a trial.
Last month, Beijing No. 1 Intermediate People's Court decided to take up a similar lawsuit for the first time. Since then, a string of compensation lawsuits related to wartime forced labor in Japan have been filed in China.
Until recently, Chinese authorities virtually did not allow individuals to file compensation lawsuits against Japanese firms, apparently out of concern for bilateral relations and to not discourage Japanese investment.
In 2007, Japan's top court ruled Chinese individuals' wartime compensation claims had already been renounced when Sino-Japanese diplomatic ties were normalized in 1972.
The plaintiffs in the lawsuit in Shijiazhuang are seeking compensation of 2 million yuan for seven who died after forcefully being taken to Japan by the company's laborer recruiters during World War II and 1.5 million yuan for other victims.
In addition, they want Mitsubishi Materials to print apologies in major newspapers in the two countries and build a monument to the forced laborers in Japan.
Chinese individuals started taking legal steps after South Korean courts ordered several Japanese firms in 2013 to pay damages for wartime forced labor even though Tokyo and Seoul agreed in 1965 when normalizing bilateral ties that compensation issues had been settled.
Chinese and South Korean victims of wartime forced labor and their lawyers have been strengthening cooperation in recent months.
A day before filing the lawsuit with the high court, the plaintiffs also held a meeting in the Chinese city with South Korean citizens who had taken similar legal action in their country.
]]></text></news-item>