<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5BWH-0NW1-JCXB-2241"><date>2014-04-02</date><title>London Stock Exchange Group PLC Statement re Board Member</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[RNS Number : 9087D London Stock Exchange Group PLC 02 April 2014 2 April 2014 LONDON STOCK EXCHANGE GROUP PLC statement re. board member London Stock Exchange Group plc (the "Company" or "LSEG") is providing an update in relation to prior disclosures made in respect of a Board member. Paolo Scaroni, a non-executive director and Deputy Chairman of the Company, has received a first instance conviction from a regional Italian Court relating to inadequate environmental standards at Enel, a company of which he was chief executive between 2002 and 2005. Mr Scaroni is appealing such decision as unfounded and under Italian law the decision is suspended and conditional pending appeal. LSEG's relevant regulators have been notified of this development. Paolo Scaroni continues as a non-executive director of the Company. LSEG will provide further updates if appropriate. - ends - For further information, please contact:
About London Stock Exchange Group: London Stock Exchange Group (LSE.L) is a diversified international exchange Group that sits at the heart of the world's financial community. The Group can trace its history back to 1801. The Group operates a broad range of international equity, bond and derivatives markets, including London Stock Exchange; Borsa Italiana; MTS, Europe's leading fixed income market; and the pan-European equities platform, Turquoise. Through its markets, the Group offers international business, and investors, unrivalled access to Europe's capital markets. Post trade and risk management services are a significant and growing part of the Group's business operations. LSEG operates CC&G, the Rome headquartered CCP and Monte Titoli, the significant European settlement business, selected as a first wave T2S participant. The Group is also a majority owner of leading multi-asset global CCP, LCH.Clearnet. The Group offers its customers an extensive range of real-time and reference data products, including Sedol, UnaVista, Proquote and RNS. FTSE calculates thousands of unique indices that measure and benchmark markets and asset classes in more than 80 countries around the world. London Stock Exchange Group is also a leading developer of high performance trading platforms and capital markets software. In addition to the Group's own markets, over 30 other organisations and exchanges around the world use the Group's MillenniumIT trading, surveillance and post trade technology. Headquartered in London, United Kingdom with significant operations in Italy, France, North America and Sri Lanka, the Group employs approximately 2,800 people. Further information on London Stock Exchange Group can be found at: www.lseg.com
]]></text></news-item>