<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5C79-51E6-1E71-A81A"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>LETTER TO THE EDITOR</title><source>The Newburyport Current (Massachusetts)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[On March 11, 2014, on the third anniversary of the Fukushima Daiichi nuclear power plant disaster, No More Fukushimas presented Sen. Kathleen O'Connor Ives and Rep. Michael Costello our 2014 annual Award for Seabrook Safety. We recognized them for their courage and leadership on behalf of public safety at the Seabrook plant and to thank them for their bold stand against the continued operation of the degradation-plagued Seabrook facility.
On Dec. 18, 2013 at a Nuclear Regulatory Commission (NRC) public meeting, Sen. O'Connor Ives and Rep. Costello did what no other elected officials have done, they called for an immediate shutdown of the Seabrook plant to protect their constituents from the risk of a nuclear disaster. (See https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YAJPe-HMlow.)
We thank them and every elected official who has stood up for public safety in regard to Seabrook. By doing so, we are saying that we remember the 150,000 Japanese people whose lives will never be the same because of the Fukushima disaster.
Sen. O'Connor Ives and Rep. Costello thought long and hard before calling for Seabrook's shutdown. Rep. Costello and former Sen. Steve Baddour were the first state officials to write a letter to the NRC expressing concern about the alkali-silica reaction (ASR) problem at the Seabrook plant and the prospect of premature plant relicensing.
Later, during her election campaign, Sen. O'Connor Ives stressed her concerns about safe evacuation. Realizing that ASR has increased the potential risk of a nuclear disaster at Seabrook, Sen. O'Connor Ives and Rep. Costello made the decision to stand up for their constituents' safety.
It is particularly fitting that Sen. O'Connor Ives and Rep. Costello should make this call. They represent the 60,000 Massachusetts citizens who live within the 10-mile Seabrook evacuation zone. They are closest to those most affected by a potential radiological release. They know that within the 10-mile radius few residents believe that a safe evacuation is possible. Safe evacuation is especially unfathomable during summer beach congestion, storm surges, and winter weather conditions.
Sen. O'Connor Ives' district includes Amesbury, Newburyport, and Salisbury - which have evacuation plans - and Haverhill, Merrimac, Methuen, and North Andover - which don't. Is there anyone who seriously believes that, in the event of an accident, radiation will stop at the edge of the 10-mile zone? When the Fukushima disaster occurred in Japan, the NRC recommended that all U.S. citizens immediately move 50 miles from Fukushima.
Both Sen. O'Connor Ives and Rep. Costello called for an immediate shutdown after carefully reviewing scientific and technical information. They attended NRC public meetings in New Hampshire and a C-10 Research and Education Foundation forum. They reviewed NRC documents and scientific analyses prepared by the Union of Concerned Scientists.
As the Union of Concerned Scientists and the C-10 Foundation have eloquently said, there are too many unknowns about ASR and there is no known technology that can remedy or arrest the progression of ASR.
Thank you, Sen. O'Connor Ives and Rep. Costello, for having the courage to not wait to see which way the political winds are blowing. Thank you for caring so deeply about your constituents' lives, property, and businesses, and for making your constituents' public safety your top priority. - Bruce Skud (Newburyport) and Joanna Hammond (Amesbury); co-founders, No More Fukushimas
]]></text></news-item>