<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5C8F-7A60-85AC-5AF0"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>CBI to probe former Sebi chief over MCX-SX nod; Initiates Preliminary Enquiry against him and former member K M Abraham for alleged irregularities in approval to the bourse</title><source>DNA</source><author>dna correspondent</author><text><![CDATA[New Delhi/Mumbai: Former Securities and Exchange Board of India (Sebi) chairman C B Bhave and former member K M Abraham would be probed by the Central Bureau of Investigation for alleged irregularities in granting sanction to MCX's equity bourse.
Abraham, in 2011, had levelled charges against the then finance minister Pranab Mukherjee of being asked to go easy on some corporates. He had also investigated the Sahara case.
The CBI has registered a Preliminary Enquiry on Thursday against Bhave, Abraham and Jignesh Shah, the founder of Financial Technologies India Ltd, and MCX, among others.
The PE was registered on issues of alleged irregularities in granting sanction to the MCX Stock Exchange (MCX-SX) by the Sebi in 2008 and renewing the recognition in 2009 and 2010. According to CBI, the probe is to ascertain how MCX-SX was granted permission despite opposition by Sebi when Bhave was head of the regulatory authority.
Bhave became Sebi chairman in February 2008 and his three-year term ended in February 2011. Abraham's term as a whole-time member of Sebi also ended in 2011. Bhave was appointed a trustee of the IFRS Foundation, responsible for the governance and oversight of the International Accounting Standards Board (IASB), in 2012.
Abraham, in 2011, had written to Prime Minister's Office that Sebi was being pressurised by the finance ministry to go easy on some corporates, including MCX and Sahara, against whom he had passed orders.
However, these charges were rejected by the finance ministry and Sebi as well.
MCX-SX was set up by Shah-led FTIL and its commodity exchange arm is MCX. It started functioning as a full-fledged stock exchange in 2013.
An FTIL spokesperson told reporters that they would provide "full cooperation to the investigating agencies".
MCX-SX was initially granted permission for a limited segment of currency derivatives in 2008, on the condition its licence would require approval every year.
In 2013, Sebi asked MCX-SX to restructure its board and governance structure after a payment crisis at the National Spot Exchange Ltd (NSEL), also promoted by FTIL.
The CBI on Thursday also carried out searches at 15 locations across the country, including offices of NSEL in Mumbai, in a case of alleged irregularities in investments by state-owned trading company Project and Equipment Corporation (PEC) causing a loss of Rs 120 crore to exchequer. The agency sources claimed that the total worth of the fraud is being estimated to be around Rs 5,500 crore.
As per sources, the FIR, registered on late Wednesday night, names NSEL senior executives including promoter Jignesh Shah, CEO Anjani Sinha and others.
NSEL was hit by crisis after it suspended trade on July 31 last year following a government directive, raising concerns about possible default of Rs 5,600 crore due to about 13,000 investors, including 7,000 small ones.
CBI sources said searches were conducted at 15 places including Shah's Juhu residence after his name emerged as one of the accused in the FIR. Other locations that saw searches were residential premises of five PEC officials, two of NSEL officials and one of private persons.
"Seven offices of NSEL and six offices of counterpart in PEC transactions are being searched as part of the operation" said a senior CBI officer.
As for the locations of the searches sources said four were in Mumbai, two in Karnal and nine in Delhi.
The searches were carried out after the agency registered a case of alleged criminal conspiracy to cheat a public sector unit (PEC) in the matter of floating fraudulent paired contracts for trading of agro commodity on the platform of NSEL, without actually undertaking any genuine trade. The accused persons have also been booked under sections of prevention of corruption Act, cheating and forgery.
CBI alleged that the scam has caused a loss to the government to the tune of Rs 120 cr (approx). About Rs 343 crore of state-owned trading firms MMTC and 'PEC' is stuck with the crisis-ridden National Spot Exchange which has to settle nearly Rs 5,400 crore with 148 entities including many brokerage firms.
Sources say more FIRs are likely to follow as investigations have begun in other companies promoted by Jignesh Shah.
]]></text></news-item>