<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5CAA-3B33-786E-C1A9"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Power tariff raise by Rs 2.24 per unit</title><source>Business Recorder</source><author> MUSHTAQ GHUMMAN</author><text><![CDATA[National Electric Power Regulatory Authority (Nepra) on Thursday allowed power distribution companies (DISCOs) to raise electricity tariff by Rs 2.24 per unit on account of fuel adjustment for January 2014. The regulator allowed the increase after a public hearing on a tariff petition filed by Central Power Purchasing Agency (CPPA). Vice Chairman Nepra Khawja Muhammad Naeem presided over the hearing.
Central Power Purchasing Agency (CPPA), in its tariff petition, had sought increase in power tariff by Rs 2.19 per unit but the regulator raised tariff by Rs 2.24 per unit leaving the participants of the hearing in a state of shock. Lifeline and KESC consumers have been exempted from the hike. The raise will reflect power bills of March 2014.
CPPA revealed during the hearing that the actual fuel cost of power had jumped to Rs 11.77 per unit against the reference price of Rs 9.58 per unit. Therefore, the CPPA pleaded, power firms should be allowed to raise their power tariff by 2.19 per unit to recover the additional cost incurred. Thereafter, Nepra allowed the price hike by Rs 2.24 per unit. During the hearing, serious concerns were expressed by Nepra Members over power generation through furnace oil instead of cheaper source like gas. They noted that government produced power from expensive fuel to minimise load shedding which led to a hike in power tariff putting an additional burden on consumers.
They observed that government could produce cheap electricity by providing gas to the power plants. "Due to producing power from expensive fuel, the consumers would be paying Rs 6 billion additional money," they noted. Nepra members also expressed serious concerns over transmission losses which stood at 35 paisa per unit.
It was observed that power production was low but generation cost was high due to generation through furnace oil. It was noted that 6.19 billion units were produced at a cost of Rs 72.97 billion. The average generation cost was Rs 11.77 per unit in month of January 2014. It was noted that power producers had been producing average 8 billion units per month at a cost of Rs 54 billion but during month of January generation was less whereas cost was high putting an additional burden on the consumers.
CPPA representatives revealed during the hearing that hydel generation was low in January and therefore, electricity was produced through furnace oil and other sources. They said that total share of hydel generation was 13 per cent, coal based generation 0.11 per cent, High Speed Diesel (HSD) 3.07 per cent, furnace oil 54.51 per cent, gas 19.19 per cent, nuclear 7.07 per cent and import from Iran 0.48 per cent. The cost of generation by coal was Rs 3.61 per unit, HSD Rs 23.07. RFO Rs 17.08, gas Rs 4.37, nuclear Rs 1.32 and imported electricity from Iran Rs 10.55 per unit.
]]></text></news-item>