<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5CCC-8EED-A209-B26D"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>ProSight Specialty Insurance Holdings, Inc. : Company Profile and SWOT Analysis</title><source>SBWire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 14, 2014 (SBWire:http://www.sbwire.com Delivered by Newstex) Naperville, IL -- (SBWIRE[1]) -- 03/14/2014 -- Reportstack, provider of premium market research reports announces the addition of ProSight Specialty Insurance Holdings, Inc. : Company Profile and SWOT Analysis[2] market report to its offering This report is a crucial resource for industry executives and anyone looking to access key information about "ProSight Specialty Insurance Holdings, Inc."
The report utilizes a wide range of primary and secondary sources, which are analyzed and presented in a consistent and easily accessible format. World Market Intelligence strictly follows a standardized research methodology to ensure high levels of data quality and these characteristics guarantee a unique report.Scope Examines and identifies key information and issues about "ProSight Specialty Insurance Holdings, Inc." for business intelligence requirements. Studies and presents the companyaposs strengths, weaknesses, opportunities (growth potential) and threats (competition). Strategic and operational business information is objectively reported. The profile also contains information on business operations, company history, major products and services, key employees, and locations and subsidiaries.Reasons to Buy Quickly enhance your understanding of "ProSight Specialty Insurance Holdings, Inc." Gain insight into the marketplace and a better understanding of internal and external factors which could impact the industry. Increase business/sales activities by understanding your competitors businesses better. Recognize potential partnerships and suppliers.Key HighlightsProSight Specialty Insurance Holdings, Inc. (ProSight) is a privately held insurance company based in the US. The company offers a wide range of property and casualty insurance products for individuals and businesses. It offers comprehensive insurance coverage across various sectors including entertainment, construction, professional services, transportation, real estate, and marine. Under professional services, ProSight offers errors and omission coverage for insurance agents, lawyersapos professional liability insurance, and accountantsapos professional liability insurance. Additionally, the company offers excess workersapos compensation insurance, lenders misrepresentation insurance, contractorsapos liability insurance, towing company operator insurance, surety bonding insurance and truck fleet insurance. Moreover, the company provides risk management and claim services to its customers. It principally operates in the US and UK through its offices in New Jersey, New York, California and London. ProSight is headquartered in Morristown, New Jersey, US.Companies MentionedProSight Specialty Insurance Holdings, Inc. To view the table of contents for this market research report please visit http://www.reportstack.com/product/150996/phoenix-group-holdings-phnx-company-profile-and-swot-analysis.html[3] Contact: Roger Campbell contactus@reportstack.com Naperville Illinois United States Ph: 888-789-6604###For more information on this press release visit: http://www.sbwire.com/press-releases/prosight-specialty-insurance-holdings-inc-company-profile-and-swot-analysis-475769.htm[4] Media Relations Contact Roger Campbell Director of Marketing Email: Click to Email Roger Campbell[5] Web: http://www.reportstack.com[6] [1]: http://www.sbwire.com/?utm_source=ntutm_medium=feedutm_campaign=distribution [2]: http://www.reportstack.com/product/150996/phoenix-group-holdings-phnx-company-profile-and-swot-analysis.html [3]: http://www.reportstack.com/product/150996/phoenix-group-holdings-phnx-company-profile-and-swot-analysis.html [4]: http://www.sbwire.com/press-releases/prosight-specialty-insurance-holdings-inc-company-profile-and-swot-analysis-475769.htm?utm_source=ntutm_medium=feedutm_campaign=distribution [5]: http://www.sbwire.com/press-releases/contact/475769?utm_source=ntutm_medium=feedutm_campaign=distribution [6]: http://www.reportstack.com

]]></text></news-item>