<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5D3E-9A35-9F99-8671"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Top News Advisory for Friday, March 14, 2014; Top News Advisory</title><source>Canadian Press</source><author>The Canadian Press</author><text><![CDATA[Friday, March 14, 2014
3:00 p.m.
TOP NEWS ADVISORY
Here are the latest Top News stories from The Canadian Press. All times are Eastern unless otherwise stated. Coverage plans are included when available. Entries are subject to change. Contact the National Desk at 416-507-2150.
___
TOP NEWS AT THIS HOUR
Investigator: Missing plane flew over Malaysia
AS-Malaysia-Plane
KUALA LUMPUR - Investigators are increasingly certain the missing Malaysian Airlines jet turned back across the country after its last radio contact with air traffic controllers, and that someone with aviation skills was responsible for the change in course, a Malaysian government official said Friday.A U.S. official said in Washington that investigators are examining the possibility of "human intervention" in the plane's disappearance, adding it may have been "an act of piracy." The official, who wasn't authorized to talk to the media and spoke on condition of anonymity, said it also was possible the plane may have landed somewhere. PHOTO. AUDIO.
See also: MALAYSIA-PLANE-PILOTS
___
Kerry: US won't recognize Crimea vote
EU-United-States-Ukraine
LONDON - Washington and the international community won't recognize the outcome of Sunday's referendum in Crimea on seceding from Ukraine, U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry said Friday after six hours of talks with Russia's foreign minister.His comments came after Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov acknowledged there was no "common vision" between the two nations over the crisis in Ukraine. PHOTO. AUDIO.
See also: UKRAINE'S NEIGHBORS
___
Russia in Ukraine not yet spilling to Arctic Council
Cda-Russia-Arctic
OTTAWA - Like a smooth and pristine, white winter landscape, all looks surprisingly serene between Russia, Canada and their fellow Arctic Council members. But not far beneath the unblemished surface, political fault lines are forming, a ripple effect of the crisis between Russia and Ukraine. Prime Minister Stephen Harper and Canada's allies in the G7 and NATO may have ostracized Russia over its occupation of the Crimean Peninsula. But at the Arctic Council, it appears to be business as usual between Canada, Russia and most other members - at least for now. VIDEO.
___
No fast recognition of Que in 1995: documents
Que-Referendum-US
WASHINGTON - Newly released documents say the United States would not have immediately recognized an independent Quebec after a Yes vote in the 1995 referendum.The material released today includes a response the U.S. government prepared for Oct. 30, 1995, in the event the province had voted to separate. Will be Writethru
___
Elxn-Que
MONTREAL - Canadians shouldn't be afraid of the outcome of next month's election, Parti Quebecois Leader Pauline Marois said Friday. Marois said relations between Quebec and the rest of Canada have been good for the past 40 years, regardless of whether her pro-independence party or the federalist Liberals have been in power. AUDIO. PHOTOS.
See Also Elxn-Que-PQ-Kosher-Tax
___
Conservative TV ads again target Trudeau
Conservative-Trudeau-Ads
OTTAWA - The Conservative party is blanketing the country with a fresh round of television ads attacking Liberal Leader Justin Trudeau - but unlike past campaigns, it hasn't posted the spots online nor informed its supporters about the big ad buy. Vigilant politics watchers began posting ad sightings on Twitter on Monday, and by week's end it was evident that three different Trudeau ads are being aired on everything from morning news shows to prime time network TV and sports specialty channels.
___
Canada looks to promote mining in Afghanistan
Afghan-Cda-Business
KABUL - Canadians could go from digging trenches to helping dig gold and copper mines in Afghanistan if the Harper government has its way. The country's ambassador to Kabul signalled this week that the moribund Afghan economy will be a principal focus for Canada, which has formally ended its military mission. PHOTO. Moves Business and National
___
Taliban issues congratulations to its forces on 'defeat' of Canadians
Afghan-Cda-Taliban
KABUL, Afghanistan _ A round of goodbye messages are following the last Canadian troops out the door in Afghanistan and some of them are rather nasty. The Taliban's information arm issued a statement Thursday to followers in Kandahar congratulating its fighters and Canada has been defeated. AUDIO
___
Suit seeks $500 million over missing bitcoins
Bitcoin-Bankruptcy-Lawsuit
TORONTO - A proposed class action announced Friday will seek $500 million in compensation for Canadians with deposits in what was once the largest bitcoin digital-currency exchange in the world.The lawsuit targets Mt. Gox and its two owners, Mark Karpeles and Jed McCaleb, as well as a one of the largest banks in Japan, according to a notice of action to Ontario Superior Court. Will be writethru
___
Household finances show improvement: StatsCan
StatsCan-Credit-Debt
OTTAWA - The financial health of Canadian households improved ever so slightly in the final three months of 2013, a development that will give some comfort to the Bank of Canada in maintaining its low-interest-rate policy.Statistics Canada said Friday that household worth in the country rose by three per cent to $217,700 on a per capita basis in the fourth quarter, largely as a result of a sharp 5.9 per cent gain in the value of shares and other equities held by Canadians. PHOTO. Moves Business and National
___
Information watchdog loses case over delays
Court-Info-Delays
OTTAWA - Canada's information commissioner has lost a landmark case over delays in the release of government documents, a ruling one critic says will make an ailing freedom-of-information system even worse. A Federal Court judge said she was unable to censure National Defence for taking a three-year extension on delivering records requested under the Access to Information Act, an extension the commissioner had argued was unreasonable.
___
Documents reveal more about warehouse rampage
Warehouse-Stabbing
EDMONTON - Police believe a man accused of a stabbing spree at a grocery warehouse first stopped at West Edmonton Mall and bought two large knives before heading to work.Two men were killed and four others wounded during the bloody attack at the Loblaws building last month. Will be writethru
___
Pistorius was photographed in bloody prosthetics
AF-Pistorius-Trial
PRETORIA - Police photographs of a bare-chested Oscar Pistorius standing in his garage on blood-stained prosthetic legs and wearing shorts covered in blood, taken shortly after the athlete fatally shot his girlfriend, were shown to the court at his murder trial Friday.Prosecutors displayed two photos on TV monitors in the courtroom, with the first of the muscled double-amputee Olympic athlete standing facing a camera. There are blood stains up to the knees of his limbs and his shorts are also bloodied, but his naked chest appears to be clean of blood. PHOTO. AUDIO.
___
Port waiting for union in truckers strike
Truckers-Dispute
VANCOUVER - Vancouver's container terminals continue to operate at reduced capacity due to a strike by port truckers, despite a proposal aimed at ending the dispute.The federal and B.C. governments and Port Metro Vancouver have announced a 14-point proposal designed to bring the strike to an end by making changes in a number of areas, including how truckers are paid. Will be writethru. Moves National and Business. Guard against duplication
___
Radiation scare slows port's operations
Halifax-Port-Leak
HALIFAX - Fire officials say an evacuation zone remained in place Friday at a port in Halifax after four steel cylinders carrying radioactive material fell about six metres the night before as they were being unloaded from a container ship, prompting a short-lived radiation scare.Phil McNulty, the city's executive fire officer, said the area is being monitored by emergency crews after the cylinders carrying granular uranium hexafluoride fell. PHOTO. Moves Atlantic and National, please guard against duplication.
___
Russian diplomat injured in stabbing; reports
Diplomat-Stabbing
OTTAWA - A Russian diplomat is recovering after being stabbed at an apartment building near his embassy.The 44-year-old man suffered non life-threatening injuries, Ottawa city police say.
___
Arrest made in shooting at Toronto's YorkU
York-University-Shooting
TORONTO - A 22-year-old Toronto man is facing multiple charges in a shooting at a York University food court that injured two women and triggered a campus lockdown. The incident took place at a student centre late on March 6.
___
Malnutrition grows among Syrian refugee children
ML-Syria-Malnourished-Children
KAB ELIAS - Trapped in her northern Syrian village by fighting, Mervat watched her newborn baby progressively shrink. Her daughter's dark eyes seemed to grow bigger as her face grew more skeletal. Finally, Mervat escaped to neighbouring Lebanon, and a nurse told her the girl was starving.The news devastated her. "They had to hold me when they told me. I wept," the 31-year-old mother said, speaking in the rickety, informal tent camp where she now lives with her husband in the eastern Lebanese town of Kab Elias. PHOTO.
___
BUZZ
Rob Ford's brother slams Kevin Spacey
Ford-Nation-Spacey
TORONTO - The infamous mayor of Toronto might have been given the cold shoulder by popular actor Kevin Spacey while on a recent trip to L.A.That's what Rob Ford's brother, and fellow city councillor Doug Ford is telling the viewers of "Ford Nation," the YouTube produced by the brothers. PHOTO. AUDIO.
___
Turkey video shows 'culture of cruelty'
Turkey-Abuse
TORONTO - Disturbing video showing employees of one of the world's leading turkey producers clubbing, kicking and otherwise abusing the hapless birds is evidence of a culture of cruelty and neglect at the factory farm, an animal-rights group said Friday.The company in question, Hybrid Turkeys, said it had suspended four employees and called the abuse depicted in the video an isolated incident. PHOTO.
___
Hughes sets out on 12,000 kilometre ride
CYC-Claras-Big-Ride
TORONTO - Clara Hughes is off on her 12,000-kilometre bike ride around Canada.The six-time Olympic medallist left Toronto's Maple Leaf Square at lunch time for Clara's Big Ride for Bell Let's Talk, a 110-day journey to promote conversation about mental health. Moves Sport and National; Will be updated
___
UK holds cyberwar game in Churchill's WW2 bunker
EU-Britain-Cyber-Challenge
LONDON - Bent over their computers in a World War II-era bunker beneath London's streets, dozens of young techies have spent Friday racing to understand why Britain's banking network suddenly seems to have gone offline.The exercise - it is just an exercise - comes complete with sirens and mock newscasts. It's meant to recruit the next generation of tech talent, and is also meant to help highlight the threat many here see as inevitable: A major cyberattack on the nation's critical infrastructure. PHOTO.
___
Dog walk doggone hazardous for woman
Alta-Coyote-Attack
EDMONTON - Emergency crews had to rappel down a steep riverbank in Edmonton to help a woman who had gone to rescue her dog from a pack of coyotes. The woman was walking three dogs in the city's river valley Thursday night when as many as nine coyotes attacked one of her pooches and dragged it onto the North Saskatchewan River. PHOTO.
___
]]></text></news-item>