<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5D56-824E-3853-551E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Drug and alcohol experts concerned with N.H. House efforts to legalize pot: Say letting residents have an ounce of marijuana is too much</title><source>Foster's Daily Democrat, Dover, N.H</source><author>Kimberley Haas, Foster's Daily Democrat, Dover, N.H.</author><text><![CDATA[March 14--DOVER -- Experts on substance-use disorders are voicing their concern about two House bills relative to the legalization and decriminalization of up to one ounce of marijuana.
"We need to look at the marijuana policies in New Hampshire, but an ounce is a pretty significant amount, something like 40 to 60 joints," Linda Paquette, the executive director of New Futures in Concord said during an editorial board meeting at Foster's Daily Democrat Thursday.
New Futures is a nonpartisan, nonprofit organization with the mission of preventing and reducing alcohol and drug problems in the state.
Paquette was joined by Tym Rourke via telephone. Rourke is the director of programs and substance use disorders grantmaking at New Hampshire Charitable Foundation in Concord.
The bills Paquette and Rourke were referring to are HB 492 and HB 1625.
On Wednesday, the House of Representatives passed HB 1625, which would decriminalize the possession of up to one ounce of marijuana, making it a violation punishable by a fine of up to $100. The bill was passed on a bipartisan vote of 215-92.
HB 1625 would also decriminalize the possession of hash, Paquette said.
In January, the House passed HB 492, which is still being evaluated by a subcommittee of the Ways and Means Committee. That bill would allow adults over the age of 21 to possess up to one ounce of marijuana. Residents would be able to grow up to six plants legally.
Proponents of HB 492 say the state could earn between $20 and $30 million by selling and taxing the drug. State licensed stores would be authorized to sell marijuana under the bill. The operation would mirror hard liquor sales by the state and is modeled after the marijuana laws in Colorado and Washington.
Rourke said in Colorado, where recreational marijuana is legal and has become a tourist attraction, residents are already seeing the effects of big marijuana. Edible marijuana products such as cookies, soda, even candies, are being sold at specialty shops in addition to smokable marijuana. These products, Rourke said, are aimed on getting the younger generation hooked, just as tobacco companies used to market cigarettes to youth.
"You can't build a business on substances like these unless you get people to use them heavily. To do that, you have to start them young," Rourke said.
Rourke said Philip Morris, the nation's leading cigarette manufacturer, bought the domain for a marijuana website years ago. There are reports that tobacco companies have bought large tracts of land in California anticipating the legalization of marijuana in that state.
For Rourke, the statistics about youth marijuana consumption are particularly troubling. One in 10 New Hampshire adolescents already report they are using marijuana regularly. One in six adolescents who try marijuana will become dependent on the drug.
With daily use, marijuana can lower a teenager's IQ by eight points, Rourke said.
Adults, too, can become dependent on marijuana. One in 11 adults who try marijuana become dependent on the drug, according to literature provided by New Futures.
Rourke said our society has learned its lessons with tobacco and alcohol, two substances that have caused a number of problems in the state due to the people who abuse them. To generate revenue on the backs of the addicted is a breach of ethics in his opinion.
"There is no cost benefit to this state by legalizing the drug," Rourke said. "And the public health threat is too big."
For more information, visit new-futures.org.
___ (c)2014 the Foster's Daily Democrat (Dover, N.H.) Visit the Foster's Daily Democrat (Dover, N.H.) at www.fosters.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>