<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5D78-67A8-770C-C2D9"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Panel debates if pipeline is in national interest</title><source>Great Falls Tribune (Montana)</source><author>By, Malia Rulon Herman</author><text><![CDATA[WASHINGTON ¿ A key Senate committee posed a controversial question Thursday: Is the 1,700-mile long Keystone XL pipeline in the nation's national interest?
The answer wasn't clear.
A retired military official and representative of the U.S. Chamber of Commerce said the pipeline is in the national interest.
They told members of the Senate Foreign Affairs Committee the $5.3 billion project would create thousands of jobs and promote energy independence at a critical time for the U.S. to be a strong international leader and reliable energy partner.
"The decision on the pipeline is a litmus test of whether America is serious about national, regional and global energy security ¿ and the world is watching," said retired Gen. James Jones, who heads Jones Group International, a national security firm.
The head of a leading environmental group and a climate science professor offered an opposing view.
"Our country has a clear science-based goal to limit carbon pollution, and we must keep in mind and realize that keeping that goal is incompatible with approving this permit," said Michael Brune, executive director of the Sierra Club.
Brune said the pipeline, still awaiting approval or rejection by President Barack Obama, would carry toxic oil through farmland to Gulf Coast refineries, creating major health implications for communities near those refineries.
"If the president approves the pipeline, he will be effectively approving the further development of the tar sands," Brune said.
Democratic Sen. Robert Menendez of New Jersey, chairman of the committee, pressed Brune for details.
"It seems strange to limit carbon by means of transportation," said Menendez, who opposes the pipeline.
"Why should we regulate carbon through this pipeline?"
But Menendez also repeatedly questioned Karen Harbert, president and CEO of the Institute for 21st Century Energy, an affiliate of the Chamber of Commerce, whether humans are the cause of climate change.
Harbert ultimately said climate change is "caused by lots of different things."
"We believe we should be doing everything in our power to address the environment," she said.
Democratic Sen. Tim Kaine of Virginia said climate change is real, and the U.S. has an obligation to do something about it.
"The disapproval of this project might have an incremental effect on this, but it also might have an incremental effect (improving) the nation's energy security," he said. "The U.S. sends a powerful message about whether we want to lead on (climate change) or not based on whether or not we embrace tar sands oil."
Meanwhile, Democratic Sen. Barbara Boxer of California, chairwoman of the Senate Environment and Public Works Committee, called on the Obama administration to conduct a thorough study of the pipeline's potential health effects before making a decision on whether to approve it.
"This is an issue that has been swept under the rug," she said, referring to families living near the Gulf Coast refineries.
"I want energy security desperately, but we can't do something in the name of national interest where it winds up costing us the health of our families."
Menendez pressed witnesses, especially Jones, about whether the oil would stay in the U.S. "and contribute to our energy security" or be shipped overseas.
"We should be honest with the American people," he said. "There is no guarantee that even if we put up the pipeline and have the tar oil shipped through our country that it will even stay in our country."
Jones said the pipeline would be "transformational on the global playing field and could have huge ramifications" for how the U.S. projects itself in the global energy arena.
"For that reason, I think we should move forward with it," he said.
The Keystone XL pipeline, which has been in the works for more than five years, would transport thousands of barrels of crude each day from Canada and the Bakken region of Montana and North Dakota to the Gulf Coast for refining.
Obama could make a decision on the project as early as late May.
The State Department released its final environmental impact statement on Keystone in January.
Thursday's hearing included no administration witnesses.
Menendez said they were invited but declined to appear because they felt it was inappropriate to comment on a matter currently under review.
Secretary of State John Kerry did appear at a budget hearing Thursday before a Senate Appropriations subcommittee, where he declined to say what he would do on Keystone if the decision were his to make.
"I am not at liberty to go into my thinking at this point. It is just not appropriate, except to say that I am approaching this tabula rasa," Kerry said.
]]></text></news-item>