<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5DDD-243D-4C79-81DE"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Jordan Islamic Bank decreases 0.5% on low volume</title><source>News Bites - Middle East &amp; North Africa: Jordan</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Jordan Islamic Bank (ASE:JOIB), Jordan's 2nd largest bank by market capitalisation, decreased 2.0 piastre (or 0.5%) to close at JOD3.90. Compared with the ASE Index which fell 5.9 points (or 0.3%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -0.2%. Trading volume was 65% lighter than average. The stock fell for a second day on Sunday bringing its two-day fall to 3.0 piastre or 0.8%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Jordan Islamic Bank, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/00105172174031427
Bearish Signals
Bullish Signals- The 2.7% discount to 12-month high of JOD4.01 against the 41.3% premium to 12-month low of JOD2.76 suggests the stock continues to push for new highs. - In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week high seven times, pointing to a significant uptrend. - The present value of JOD1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Jordan Islamic Bank is JOD1,270, for a capital gain of JOD270.

NoteVolume: there were 15,832 shares worth JOD61,692 (US$87,307) traded.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 3 company announcements are:February 09: JIB inaugurates a cash office in AlShajara/ Ramtha[Company Release] Jordan Islamic Bank (JIB) announced inaugurating a new cash office in AlShajara area /Ramtha - Irbid governorate / king Hussein street on Sunday 9th February, 2014. Residents and dignitaries of AlShajara welcomed and congratulated the inauguration of the office of Jordan Islamic Bank in there are to be the first Jordanian bank in AlShajara.Mr. Musa Abdelaziz Shihadeh, Vice Chairman, General Manager of JIB said inaugurating the sixteenth cash office of the bank in AlShajara / Ramtha which is distinguished by high population density and relies in its production on agricultural and commercial projects, aims to meet citizens 'needs in AlShajara and nearby villages and decrease the pressure on AlRamtha branch which was inaugurated in 1995.
January 26: JIB inaugurates a cash office in Subaihi[Company Release] Jordan Islamic Bank (JIB) celebrated a new cash office in Subaihi - Arda Area beside civil consumer institution by the presence of Balqa governor Mr. Hasan Assaf and his deputy, Head of Subaihi municipality, Mr. Hisham alManaseer and by a participation of residents and dignitaries of Balqa governorate and Arda area who expressed their thanks and appreciation of the bank welcoming its existence in Subaihi area during a celebration held on Sunday, 26th January, 2014.On this occasion, Mr. Musa Shihadeh, Vice Chairman, General Manager of JIB said the inauguration of the fifty fifth cash office of the bank within Subaihi area which is considered the primary centre of Arda subsidiary of Balqa'a governorate aims to meet the needs and demands of residents and businessmen in the area who are eager for the existence of Jordan islamic bank in different places within the governorate borders in order for the bank to be the first Jordanian bank in the area in addition to three main branches within the governorate which are Salt branch, Bawabat Salt branch and Deir Allah branch and to ensure the latest banking technologies which are compliant with provisions and principles of islamic sharia and lessen the pressure on other bank's branches, accordingly, the bank has currently 82 branches and cash offices.
May 09: JIB and Customs Dept sign an electro for bank guaranteesnic link agreementJordan Islamic Bank (JIB) and Customs Department have signed an electronic connection agreement to facilitate the procedures of bank guarantees for customers of Jordan Islamic Bank and Customs Department in order to provide the best facilities in the processes and procedures of banking guarantees electronically.The agreement has been signed at the head office of Customs Department on Thursday, 9th May, 2013.
ISIN: JO1100111011
AJ:JOIB; JR:JOIB
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>