<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5DEA-D4FB-C5C0-7AE5"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Full text: Report on China's economic, social development plan</title><source>Xinhua General News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[1) Granting urban residency to rural people who have moved to cities in an orderly manner. We will holistically develop support policies concerning household registration, land, capital, housing and basic public services and grant urban residency in an orderly way to permanent urban residents who are able to have stable jobs and live in urban areas. We will work out measures to narrow disparity within cities. We will promote the equalization of basic public services in urban and rural areas.
2) Improving the structure and form of urbanization. The state will formulate and implement a plan for developing major city clusters, while localities will work out and implement plans for a new type of urbanization in light of the conditions of their respective regions, in order to develop cities of all sizes and small towns in a coordinated manner. We will develop new cities and districts in accordance with rules and procedures.
3) Making the development of cities more sustainable. We will get industries and employment to better sustain the development of cities, and provide better urban utilities and public service facilities to sustain greater population concentrations and provide better services.
4) Improving the institutions and mechanisms of urbanization. To foster an institutional environment conducive to the sound development of urbanization more quickly, we will carry out trial programs of different types in different regions and at different levels to establish a number of systems and mechanisms. These include a mechanism for sharing the costs of granting urban residency to rural people who have moved to cities and a diversified investment and financing mechanism for urban development.
5. Strengthen price regulation and controls
1) Guaranteeing supplies. We will properly manage the scale, timing and pace of purchasing, stockpiling and selling grains, edible oils, cotton, sugar, pork and chemical fertilizers. We will implement well the reserve system for winter and spring vegetables in major northern cities. We will speed up the building of storage and logistic infrastructure for grains, cotton and other staple agricultural products, vigorously develop cold chain logistics for agricultural products, and promote the renovation and upgrading of wholesale agricultural product markets. We will fully implement the system of provincial governors assuming responsibility for the "rice bag" (grain supply) and city mayors for the "vegetable basket" (non-staple food supply).
2) Improving the price control mechanism. We will earnestly implement the contingency plan for controlling the prices of hogs and continue with trial programs of policy-based insurance for these prices. We will scale up the trial program of policy-based insurance for the prices of basic vegetables, and establish a long-term mechanism to keep vegetable prices stable. We will consolidate and improve the system of price adjustment funds. We will build a price index system for main commodities and services.
3) Strengthening price regulation. We will inspect prices and charges in education, medical care, banking and other sectors. We will clear up and abolish charges that violate regulations. We will work harder to rid monopoly pricing.
4) Improving the mechanism coupling subsidies with prices. We will improve and activate in a timely manner the mechanism to increase social assistance and social security benefits when prices rise to alleviate the impact higher prices have on those in need.
6. Improve and upgrade the industrial structure
1) Adjusting and improving the distribution of key industries. We will issue guidelines on adjusting the distribution of and relocating key industries, improve the industrial distribution in coastal, border and inland areas, and relocate high-polluting enterprises in cities to minimize their environmental impact. We will promote clustering and intensive development of industries and advance the transformation and upgrading of industrial parks and clusters.
2) Working hard to address the serious problem of overcapacity. We will firmly prohibit the addition of production capacity that breaches regulations, and make optimal use of existing production capacity by various means. We will step up the establishment and improvement of a permanent, market-based mechanism to address the serious problem of overcapacity. We will raise and strictly implement industry entry standards concerning energy consumption, environmental protection and workplace safety and abolish preferential policies to phase out outdated production capacity more quickly. We will implement a tiered electricity pricing policy for industries, such as those that produce electrolytic aluminum and cement. (more)
]]></text></news-item>