<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5E1F-4171-E425-1029"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Plumber's Fibro Case Set for Trial</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Heather Isringhausen Gvillo, writing for Legal Newsline, reportedthat a Florida plumber's asbestos personal injury lawsuit may soongo to trial in the nation's epicenter for asbestos litigation. Plaintiffs John and Grace Reidy filed their lawsuit in the MadisonCounty Circuit Court, claiming the venue is proper because one ofthe original defendants, John Crane Inc., does business in MadisonCounty. Asbestos Judge Steve Kings continued the trial preparations duringjury selection. If the case does not settle, jury selection willcontinue. The Reidys filed their lawsuit on June 4, against 40 defendantsalleging negligence, willful and wanton conduct, failure to warn,negligent spoliation of evidence, among others. The defendant list has been dwindled down to just a handful ofnames. Crane Co., Bryant Heating & Cooling, Carrier Corporation,Burnham LLC and Nibco, Inc. were still involved in the action onFeb. 3. According to the complaint, John Reidy began his career as aplumber and boiler tender while serving in the U.S. Navy in 1951.His work in the plumbing industry continued after his militarycareer, divided between various employments until 1996. His duties throughout the years included plumbing, as well asinstalling and maintaining boilers, furnaces and cement pipe. The Reidys allege that he was exposed to and inhaled asbestosfibers contained in certain products he worked with. He was laterdiagnosed with mesothelioma on Feb. 27. The plaintiffs claim the defendants should have known of thepresence of asbestos and dangers involved in working with theasbestos-containing products. The Reidys claim John Reidy developed mesothelioma as a directcause of working with those toxic asbestos-containing products,"which has disabled and disfigured him." The plaintiffs also allege that the defendants at one point helddocuments and information relating to identification of asbestos-containing products, locations where those products were sold,identity of manufacturers and knowledge regarding the hazards ofasbestos. However, the whereabouts of those documents are nowunknown. "It was foreseeable to a reasonable person/entity in therespective positions of defendants that said documents andinformation constituted evidence, which was material to potentialcivil litigation, namely asbestos litigation," the suit states. Nate Mudd of Maune Raichle Hartley French & Mudd LLC in St. Louisrepresents plaintiffs.
]]></text></news-item>