<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5EB5-062C-FEA7-9AC8"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Ecotricity extends energy price freeze till October</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Ecotricity, Britain's leading green energy company today extended its energy price freeze for all customers until October 1st - meaning the company will have frozen its prices for a total of 21 months, giving it the longest period of price stability in the energy industry.
Ecotricity, who have not increased prices since January 2013, had previously announced a price freeze from the end of last summer until the end of the winter.
The company cites two principal causes for the freeze: greater energy independence after a good year for wind in 2013, and improved economies of scale after passing 100,000 customers.
Ecotricity generates around 40% of the green electricity it supplies from its own wind and solar parks, and after a record year for wind power in 2013 the company is keen to share the benefits of that record generation with its customers.
The company has grown customer numbers by 50% in just 6 months and only this week passed the 100,000 mark, the first green energy company to reach that milestone -- the significant increase has given the company greater ability to absorb cost increases and maintain stable prices.
Dale Vince, Ecotricity founder, said: "This price freeze is about sharing our success with our customers. We had a great year for wind energy in 2013, and a big increase in people switching to us from the Big Six - and because of our unique not-for-dividend model, we can ensure it's our customers who benefit, not shareholders.
"Generating about 40% of our energy through our own wind and solar parks gives us a greater degree of price stability and protection from a fluctuating energy market - it's a model that works for us, it works for our customers, and it's a model that would work for the country too. Recent events in Ukraine show the importance of energy independence in Britain - the price of wind does not go up and it's not affected by external events."
Ecotricity, who were the first green energy company in the world, has just one simple tariff for green electricity and green gas, and all customers are on the latest best price, regardless of how they pay, whether it's direct debit, cash or prepayment meter- this latest price freeze applies to all new and existing customers.
Dale Vince continued: "People are bored with the tactics of the Big Six, and the independent suppliers who mimic them too. At Ecotricity we offer green energy, unrivalled customer service, and price stability that's comparable to a fixed tariff, but without any strings - no exit fees, no penalties, and the best price for everyone, regardless of when they joined or how they choose to pay.
"The more people that join us the more we'll be able to invest in new sources of green energy - which in itself further protects our customers from price rises. It's a virtuous circle, and it's people power in action."
The Gloucestershire based firm has also created 65 new jobs since December - mainly in customer services- as record numbers of households switch their electricity and gas supply away from the Big Six energy companies. Ecotricity was also awarded 1st place in the recent Which? Consumer Satisfaction Survey.
Ecotricity's average dual fuel bill is Pound1,232 (for 3,200 kWh of electricity and 13,500 kWh of gas) - but again, unlike other energy suppliers this is available to all customers, regardless of how they pay, whether it's direct debit, cash or prepayment meter, with no exit fees or penalties.
click http://www.ecotricity.co.uk/news/news-archive/2014/ecotricity-extends-energy-price-freeze-till-october
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
26 February 2014: Ecotricity turns up heat on frackers with campaign film launch
Britain's leading green energy company Ecotricity are set to launch a new online film next week as part of a new anti-fracking campaign - the film will premier at a launch event with Green Party MP Caroline Lucas on Thursday 6th March. The short animated film, created with London based advertising agency Man+ Hatchet, follows Ecotricity's previous Dump the Big Six films, the first of which has so far been viewed nearly 3 million times on YouTube. Ecotricity has become the first energy company in Britain to reject shale gas, vowing never to invest in or supply customers with shale gas from fracking; and the film will urge consumers to vote with their energy bills and not support energy companies that finance the fracking industry. The new film, to be buttressed by social media, PR and community engagement, features a series of fracking chimneys flatulently expelling gas, and carries the tag line 'Don't squeeze the last gas out of Britain'. David Oliver, Head of Marketing at Ecotricity, said: "Like many people in Britain, we believe that fracking is wrong and we want households to be aware of which energy companies are investing in shale gas. "This film takes an irreverent view of the fracking industry by following a long tradition of British fart gags.
click http://www.ecotricity.co.uk/news/news-archive/2014/ecotricity-turns-up-heat-on-frackers-with-campaign-film-launch
17 February 2014: Ecotricity Group Ltd.: Wind turbines at Michelin, Dundee pass milestone
Britain's leading green energy company Ecotricity say their wind turbines at Michelin's Dundee factory had a bumper 2013, producing enough green electricity to power over 1,500 homes or brew over 350 million cups of tea. The turbines have now passed a significant energy milestone, having generated over 50 million units (kWh) of electricity since being installed in 2006. The two turbines generated over 7 million units (kWh) of electricity last year, up 13% on 2012's total - the second best year the turbines have had since being installed nearly eight years ago. UK wind energy generation as a whole broke several generation records in 2013: wind power produced over 6.1 GW of energy at peak in one day in December (the highest wind has produced in one day in the UK) and contributed 22.4% of total UK electricity generation in November of last year. John Reid, Factory Manager at Michelin Dundee, said: "The wind turbines have been a great asset to our Dundee site, where they have helped to alleviate the challenge of increased energy costs and allowed us to reduce our dependence on the energy grid by producing our own sustainable power. "The environment is an important priority for Michelin and we are always looking at ways we can improve our energy performance.
click http://www.ecotricity.co.uk/news/news-archive/2014/wind-turbines-at-michelin-dundee-pass-milestone
08 February 2014: Ecotricity Group Ltd.: New electricity tariff offers 1,000 free car miles
Drivers of electric cars will receive 1,000 free miles every year with a new electricity tariff being launched by green energy company Ecotricity. Green Electricity + Car - will not only power customers homes with green energy but also their cars (either 100% electric or plug-in hybrids), plus they'll get free access to Ecotricity's national network of fast chargers[1] - the Electric Highway. This latest move comes after Ecotricity announced a price freeze for all gas and electricity customers until the end of winter (April 1st), making them cheaper[2] than the standard tariff of the Big Six energy companies. Dale Vince, founder of Britain's leading green energy company, Ecotricity, said: "To get the greatest environmental benefit from an electric car, it needs to be charged using 100% green electricity from the wind and the sun - otherwise you're still powering it from dirty fossil fuels. "Ecotricity's new tariff ensures customers with electric cars are recharging at home with green energy and as a bonus they'll get at least 1,000 free miles worth of electricity[3]. "And when away from home - drivers of electric cars will also have access to the Electric Highway which will allow fast-charging at 90%[4] of motorway service stations around Britain.
click http://www.ecotricity.co.uk/news/news-archive/2014/new-electricity-tariff-offers-1-000-free-car-miles
28 January 2014: Ecotricity wins approval for their first wind turbine of 2014
Britain's leading green energy company Ecotricity today won their first planning approval of 2014, after their single 500kW windmill at Orton near Kettering was consented on appeal. Known as the Aspenfield windmill, the turbine is a medium sized model at just 50 metres to the hub, but it will generate almost 2 million units (kWh) of electricity every year, powering the equivalent of around 500 average UK homes annually. Dale Vince, Ecotricity founder, said: "We've had a great start to 2014 - more and more people are joining Ecotricity, particularly after we froze energy bills until April, and we've now reached 100,000 customers on contract.
click http://www.ecotricity.co.uk/news/news-archive/2014/ecotricity-wins-approval-for-their-first-wind-turbine-of-2014
10 December 2013: Ecotricity's rapid growth creates 50 new jobs
Green energy company Ecotricity is creating 50 new jobs as record numbers of households switch their electricity and gas supply away from the Big Six energy companies. After announcing a price freeze on October 1st - while the Big Six energy companies rushed to increase prices by up to 10% - Ecotricity have now gone one step further and extend that price freeze until the end of winter. As they approach 100,000 customers, the Gloucestershire-based firm is now attracting new households at up to five times their previous rate. Twenty-two new roles will be filled before Christmas to reinforce all areas of Ecotricity's customer services department in Stroud, which is already the best performing in the industry - with just 0.55 complaints per 1,000 customers - almost 20 times better than any of the Big Six. While 50 vacancies in total will need to be filled before the end of the financial year, It comes just two weeks after as energy giant nPower revealed that they were cutting more than 1,400 UK jobs, with many customer service roles transferring to India. Ecotricity founder Dale Vince said: "Since we froze energy bills, we've become more price competitive and are attracting people who are deserting the Big Six energy companies. "It's great to be able to create another 50 jobs in Stroud and it's not going to stop there.
click http://www.ecotricity.co.uk/news/news-archive/2013/ecotricity-s-rapid-growth-creates-50-new-jobs
]]></text></news-item>