<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5FBA-0949-90DD-024D"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Workers comb rubble for victims</title><source>The Virginian-Pilot(Norfolk, VA.)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[By Marc Santora and William K. Rashbaum
The New York Times
NEW YORK
Firefighters and emergency personnel on Thursday dug deeply into the wreckage of two buildings in East Harlem that were leveled in a powerful explosion, looking for survivors and possible evidence of what caused the blast.
But as they cut into a mountain of twisted metal, brick and wood, they found only more victims.
The death toll rose to eight, as four more bodies were found overnight and one later Thursday.
One of the victims was so badly burned that the person could not be identified.
The search for the cause of the gas leak, which a preliminary investigation indicates touched off the collapse of the buildings on Park Avenue, was equally elusive, even as new details emerged about the explosion.
Two FBI agents saw the blast blow out the front of the piano store at 1646 Park Ave., according to two city officials briefed on their statements.
The agents said the building at 1644 had then collapsed pancake-style, with each successive floor quickly giving way and crumbling into the floor beneath it.
The agents were hospitalized with non-life-threatening injuries, according to an FBI spokesman.
Among the dozens injured, two people, including a 15-year-old boy, remained in critical condition.
Some residents said they had smelled gas the night before the explosion, or even earlier.
City officials insisted that the one and only warning had come too late - less than 20 minutes before the blast.
City officials said they had reviewed calls to 311 in the preceding 30 days and found no reports of suspected gas leaks from anywhere on the block.
Even as officials searched for answers as to what caused the blast, hundreds of firefighters, construction workers and emergency personnel continued to sift through the jumbled wreckage.
Edward S. Kilduff, the chief of department for the Fire Department, said firefighters were still working as if on a "potential rescue operation."
]]></text></news-item>