<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="5FDB-D853-3AFD-16AB"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Health Insurers Sue to Pry Open Bankruptcy Trusts</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Daniel Fisher, writing for Forbes.com, reported that insurancecompanies have joined the list of parties that want to pry openthe records of secretive bankruptcy trusts that plaintiff lawyersset up to pay asbestos-related claims. Humana, Aetna, Blue Cross and Blue Shield, and hospital networksoperated by Johns Hopkins and Tufts have filed a complaint instate court in Philadelphia demanding claims records from the H.K.Porter Asbestos Trust. The insurers say they need the names ofplaintiffs who have recovered money from the trust so they can bereimbursed for medical expenses they paid to cover the sameasbestos-related illnesses. In a similar so-called subrogation action, insurers are preparingto sue Pfizer PFE +0.31% in federal court in New York to recoversome of the $1.2 billion the pharmaceutical maker agreed to pay tosettle lawsuits linked to its Quigley unit, which filed forbankruptcy in 2004. In that case, United, Humana and otherinsurers say the secrecy of the Pfizer settlement with some230,000 plaintiffs prevents them from demanding reimbursement formedical costs already incurred. Once Pfizer pays the asbestos plaintiffs, the insurers say, their"rights to those funds will be substantially impaired." Courtdockets "contain only partial identifying information for eachclaimant," making it impossible to "match these lists againsttheir enrollment records." There is a bit of irony in this latest wave of demands. Defendantmanufacturers have been trying for years to lift the veil coveringbankruptcy trust records in order to show that people suing themfor asbestos exposure have made conflicting claims against othercompanies, or are trying to collect money for smoking-relateddiseases like lung cancer. The health insurers, on the other hand,are taking the plaintiffs and their lawyers at their word anddemanding trust records so they can recover the money they spenttreating what the plaintiffs have said, frequently on penalty ofperjury, are injuries stemming from their exposure to asbestos. A Humana spokesperson said the firm doesn't comment on litigation.United Health didn't respond to my request for comment, andlawyers at Lowey Dannenberg, the lead firm in both cases, declinedcomment. This isn't the first time health insurers have tried to asserttheir right to collect money paid to people covered by theirpolicies. The U.S. Supreme Court upheld the principal with its2006 decision Sereboff v. Mid-Atlantic, in which a self-insuredcompany sued to recover some $75,000 in medical expenses it paidfor the care of an employee injured in a car accident. Under theEmployment Retirement Security Act, the court ruled, the companycould sue for a piece of the employee's $750,000 legal settlement. In their lawsuits over asbestos claims, the insurers cite ERISAand other federal laws that allow them to collect as much asdouble damages from "primary payers" that disregard theirsubrogation rights. The right stems from the insurance contractembedded in most plans, in which employees agree to reimbursetheir healthcare costs if they are also compensated throughlitigation. "Given that plaintiffs represent a substantial proportion of theU.S. population, and that over 230,000 individuals have alreadyreceived at least a partial payment from Pfizer since 2004,plaintiffs should have received tens of thousands of suchnotices," the insurers say in the expected Pfizer suit, which wassubmitted as an exhibit in the Quigley bankruptcy. "In fact, theyhave received only a handful." Asbestos companies tried a similar tack in the 1990s, suingtobacco companies to recover the billions of dollars they paid outfor lung conditions likely caused by smoking. Judges inMississippi and elsewhere dismissed those claims, however. Critics have long complained that plaintiff lawyers who drivecompanies into bankruptcy with asbestos claims also control thetrusts that courts set up to pay their clients' claims. Mosttrusts keep claims secret, supposedly to protect the healthrecords of claimants, and resist requests for information on whatplaintiffs said caused their illness. Some trusts will pay claimsbased on the barest evidence of exposure to a company's products,such as work records showing a person once was employed at afacility identified in other records as having received asbestos-containing materials. "There's at least one trust that where all you have to say is youworked at Penn State's main campus," said S. Todd Brown, anassociate professor at State University of New York Buffalo LawSchool and expert on asbestos bankruptcy trusts. "It can be thatloose for claims at some trusts." Normally plaintiffs surrender their anonymity and privacy whenthey file a lawsuit, but secrecy crept into the asbestos-litigation business in the early 2000s when a single judge washandling almost 20 bankruptcies simultaneously, Brown said.Insurance companies that were footing most of the bills demandedproof that plaintiff lawyers had legal representation agreementswith their plaintiffs. But as they started turning over thoserecords, high-volume asbestos firms realized that could unveilproblematic details such as the fee-splitting arrangements thatare common in this business. Many asbestos claimants enter the system through a nationwidenetwork of lawyers who advertise for plaintiffs and then hand themoff to specialist firms in exchange for a piece of the ultimatefees. Ethical rules prevent fee-splitting, however, unless thereferring firm performs meaningful legal work on the case. "The larger firms said `Wait a sec, if we produce this it is goingto be horrible for us,'" Brown told me. "This is going to be badfor our business model." Plaintiff lawyers took a hit recently when a bankruptcy judgeslashed the amount of money they were seeking in the Garlockbankruptcy, citing the "impropriety of some law firms" insubmitting claims to bankruptcy trusts that conflicted with theirclaims in the gasket maker's bankruptcy. The judge allowed Garlockto conduct discovery on 15 settled cases, and discovered plaintifflawyers had failed to disclose evidence in all 15. Last year the House of Representatives passed the FACT Act, whichwould require asbestos bankruptcy trusts to disclose the names ofclaimants. It cannot get past the Democratic Senate or thepresident, however. The Pfizer settlement included a deal with high-volume plaintifffirms Weitz & Luxenberg and Peter Angelos to pay $800 million, orsome $20,000 per claimant before fees, to settle 40,000 claims. In a surprising twist, one of the firms representing healthinsurers is Hagens Berman, best known for its class-actionlitigation and the epic 1997 tobacco settlement that continues toyield hundreds of millions of dollars a year in fees to thelawyers who negotiated it.
]]></text></news-item>