<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6169-BDFC-A8D7-AB3D"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Bribery label doesn't fit in Legislature</title><source>The Montgomery Advertiser (Alabama)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[As another session of the Alabama Legislature conducts its business and moves into its final stages and toward adjournment, critics decry its inability to address important problems and issues that confront the state of Alabama. Much of the criticism related to this legislative body, as well as Congress and other state legislatures, is the influence that big money interests have on legislative decision making.
The legislative arena is especially frustrating to those individuals and groups who are advocating what they consider to be "good causes" that seldom receive the attention their proponents believe is justified. The process is viewed, especially by those who are unsuccessful in it, as one that is unfairly distorted by better financed interests.
Making the process even more frustrating is that the well-financed interests hire well-connected lobbyists and these lobbyists who, with their principals, contribute large sums to candidates for these offices.
This view manifested itself, I believe, in a recent column by the Advertiser's Josh Moon. In the column, he was highly critical of the Alabama legislative process that has been unable to curtail the Alabama payday loan/car title industry from charging outrageous interest rates. He indicated that the large majority of committee members who considered this issue received campaign contributions from this industry.
Moon asked the question: "Can someone tell me where the line is when it comes to determining the difference between a legal campaign contribution and a illegal bribe?" He answered his question with these words: "Seriously, I can't tell anymore." He goes on to make two comparisons of the similarity of the process to how the "Gambino Family" may pursue its public policy goals.
Notwithstanding Mr. Moon's excellent sense of wit and sarcasm, the clear message of the column is that, for at least this issue, the Alabama legislative process is one that is brought and sold with the exchange of dollars as well might be the case where a Mafia transaction takes place. This portrayal of the legislative process in Alabama does a profound disservice to the very large majority of the legislators and lobbyists who are the key players in this environment.
While I am as bothered as Mr. Moon that hard-working, low-income persons have been ensnared by an industry that charges interest rates that keep people beholden to it for years, I am not willing to accept the implication that this system is in place and continues to be in place because of "bribes." There is a large difference between campaign contributions and bribes and the players in this process know it. More importantly, those responsible for educating the citizenry should be informing rather than confusing them regarding this reality.
The Alabama legislative process, as is the case with other American legislative bodies, is one where is are a well-defined set of formal and informal rules. The advantage in this process goes to the players who know these rules and have the best access to legislative decision makers. There is no denying, of course, that financial resources give groups an edge in securing the talent needed to succeed in the legislative arena.
Thus, I am unwilling to concede that "bribery" is a way of life for the Alabama legislative process. At the same time, I am keenly aware that campaign contributions are made with an eye toward helping elect candidates who are sympathetic to a group's cause or who can be cultivated as a friend of their cause. A half century or more ago, a state-level office holder characterized money as the "mother's milk of politics." In the second decade of the 21st century, this characterization is truer than ever.
Financial resources will allow those with a legislative agenda to hire lobbyists who know the system and how to get things done in the system. Investments in the form of campaign contributions and the hiring of talent that knows the legislative system facilitates communication between interested groups and legislators which is the leverage money brings to the table. Such relationships are what gives those with a public policy agenda a greater ability to make their case.
The ability to build relationships which could be characterized as "access" is the goal of groups involved in the public policy process. It, rather than "bribes," makes the difference in achieving public policy objectives.
Thomas Vocino is executive director of Alabama State University's Center for Leadership and Public Policy.
Alabama Voices
Thomas Vocino
]]></text></news-item>