<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="61CC-A259-F3A9-4413"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Dundon relative had links to well-known gangland figures</title><source>Irish Independent</source><author>BARRY DUGGAN</author><text><![CDATA[STEPHEN 'Dougie' Moran was not a household name but he had links stretching all the way to the top of gangland crime in Ireland.
From a young age he was involved with criminal elements in his native city of Limerick, and as he got older his contacts got more dangerous.
His murder on Saturday night is the first time the extended McCarthy-Dundon gang have lost a blood relation to the gun.
As a young boy, 'Dougie' Moran left Limerick in the 1970s with his family after their home was shot up.
However, rather than keep 'Dougie' away from a life of crime, the incident appears to have encouraged him to get more involved.
He became well-known to gardai for everything from intimidating jurors to forcing 'safety' money out of contractors working on the state road network.
He was a cousin of Larry McCarthy senior, whose son Larry junior (35) became the head of the McCarthy clan in Limerick at the turn of the millennium. The Dundon criminal brothers - Wayne, John, Dessie and Ger - were distant cousins and 'Dougie' was often seen in their company.
A key figure in organised crime, Moran collected hitman James Martin Cahill from a train in Limerick in 2002.
Cahill shot dead nightclub security man Brian Fitzgerald (32) - who refused to allow drug dealers to operate in Doc's nightclub - hours later and subsequently identified Moran as being complicit in the murder but gardai did not have enough evidence to charge him.
In 2003, he attempted to intimidate a jury member who had been sworn on to a jury panel at the Central Criminal Court for the trial relating to the murder of Limerick crime boss, Kieran Keane. 'Dougie' and an accomplice followed the jury member on to a Dublin Bus.
However, the juror soon realised he was being followed and got off the bus. Gardai were alerted and the intimidation plot failed.
Five men - including Moran's cousins Dessie Dundon and Anthony 'Noddy' McCarthy - were all on trial for the Keane murder and ultimately found guilty.
'Dougie' supplied the McCarthy-Dundons with two Germanmanufactured, armour-plated, bullet-proof vehicles in 2008. The cars were ultimately seized by the Criminal Assets Bureau following a lengthy investigation.
When the M50 route around Dublin was being built, 'Dougie' Moran extorted cash from some contractors who were advised their machinery would be safe as long as they used his security business.
Moran also had links to the CIRA.
In recent years, he made several prison visits to the Dundon brothers and brought Ciara Killeen - girlfriend of John Dundon - to see her jailed partner.
When Ger Dundon was released from Wheatfield Prison on January 18, Moran was waiting for him outside the jail.
BARRY DUGGAN
]]></text></news-item>