<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6272-9A6F-93F1-C3F5"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>National Gas in its biggest trailing week loss for 3 weeks</title><source>News Bites - Middle East and North Africa: Oman</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[National Gas (MSM:NGCI), Oman's 2nd largest oil & gas company by market capitalisation, decreased 0.80 Baisa (or 0.8%) from its last traded date of March 12, 2014 to close at 99.20 Baisa. In the past week the shares have plummeted 12.6%, the biggest trailing week fall since February 20. Compared with the Muscat Securities Market Index which rose 8.5 points (or 0.1%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -0.9%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on National Gas, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/00105144174031483
Bearish SignalsSignificant Downtrend- The stock continues its significant downtrend.- The stock dropped on high volatility today.- Falls to Rises: in the past month the number of falls outnumbered rises 13:6 or 2.2:1.- The price plummeted 17.7% in the last month.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price/Earnings of 60 [29.1]. - Price/Sales of 0.8 [0.6]. We estimate National Gas stock is trading at a current year Price/Sales of 0.5 and a forward year Price/Sales of 0.3. - Return on Equity 5.7% [8.9%].- Return on Assets 0.7% [2.6%].- Return on Capital Employed 2.9% [10.7%].Other Bearish Signals:- Total Liabilities/ EBITDA of 29.7 is more than or equal to 5, this compares unfavourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity is less than stellar at 5.7%. This is computed as net profit margin of 1.4% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 0.53 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 7.6. Also, this has deteriorated from 14.8% last year.

Bullish Signals- The present value of OMR1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in National Gas is OMR1,837, for a capital gain of OMR837.
Oversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The stock is oversold according to the Williams % R indicator of -84.8, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day low of 96.0 Baisa.- Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.4. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- Net profit margin has averaged 5.2% in the last 3 years. This is better than the sector average of 3.3% and suggests a high margin of safety.- Net Profit margin has shown signs of recovery in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]
- Revenue growth rate is positive and has seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]
NoteVolume: there were 28,540 shares worth OMR28,312 (US$73,546) traded. The volume was 0.5 times the average trading of 59,752 shares. - National Gas is at a discount of 39.9% to its 12-month high of OMR1.65 on 30 Jan, 2014. It is also at a premium of 143.7% to the 12-month low of 40.70 Baisa on 19 Sep, 2013.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 27: National Gas: Agenda for Annual General Meeting to be held on 20.03.2014[News Story]The Board of Directors of National Gas Co. SAOG. are pleased to invite the shareholders to attend the Annual General Meeting proposed to be held at 5.00 p.m. on Thursday, 20.03.2014 at the Business Hall of Capital Market Authority Building to discuss the following agenda :Study the report of the Board of Directors for the financial year ended 31/12/2013 and sanctioning the same.Study the company's management report for the financial year ended 31/12/2013 and approve the same.3.
February 20: National Gas announces AGMNational Gas has announced its Annual General Meeting will take place on March 20, 2014.
February 12: National Gas: Disclosure regarding CEO[News Story]We would like to notify our valued shareholders that we have received a letter from Muscat Securities market dated 11 February 2014 which requires the Company to clarify on the disclosure regarding the detention of the CEO of the Company. Our clarification is as follows:Our earlier disclosure was based on the only official information available from the public prosecutor at that point of time when we checked on the reason for detention of the CEO.
February 04: National Gas: Disclosure regarding CEO[News Story]The Board of Directors wish to inform that the Company has received a reply from the public prosecution regarding the detention of the Company's CEO. The reply received states that the CEO has been accused of bribing a government official.The Board also wishes to reassure the shareholders that the business would run as usual and they do not expect any financial implications on the Company due to this development.In the meantime, the Finance Controller of the Company would be acting on behalf of the CEO so that routine operations of the Company do not get affected.
Source: Muscat Securities Market
February 03: National Gas: Disclosure regarding CEO[News Story] The Board of Directors has come to know that the Company's CEO has been held by the public prosecution. The Board of Directors met on 2 February 2014 to discuss this matter. The Company has written to the public prosecution asking for the details on the case. The Company will provide more details on this matter as and when further information is received.
January 30: National Gas : Unaudited Consolidated Results for the year ended 31 December 2013[News Story] http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Oman/Stock/News/4854.html.
Source: Muscat Securities Market
January 22: National Gas: Announces Qaryan steel project win in KSA[News Story] National Gas Company SAOG is pleased to inform that it has bagged a prestigious LPG project in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia valuing US$ 968,000 from Qaryan Steel Company. They are a reputed business group in KSA and are making their first foray into the steel business.
ISIN: OM0000001160
OM:NGCI
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>