<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="62B1-4F39-BD02-A8AC"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Hampshire Victims Face Losing Part of Payout</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Rob Merrick, writing for Southern Daily Echo, reported thatministers have been accused of deceiving asbestos victims inHampshire, England, with fatal lung cancer, after dealing them asecond heavy blow. Mesothelioma sufferers face losing up to 25 per cent of theirdamages payments to their lawyers under changes brought throughParliament. Alan Whitehead, pictured, the Southampton Test MP, condemned theprospect of sufferers having compensation "snatched away" in legalcosts. The Labour MP also protested that the Government had, lastApril, pledged to carry out a proper review before allowingcompensation to be stripped out for court bills. The so-called "review" was simply a single, complicated questionwrapped up in a separate consultation -- with no proper study ofthe impact of the change, he said. Mr Whitehead said: "The Government indicated that people withmesothelioma -- including many in my constituency -- would nothave a substantial part of their award snatched away "Now this isexactly what will happen. It was clearly not a proper consultationand, not surprisingly, it has come to its pre-determinedconclusion. "People in this terrible situation deserve the peace of mind andthe certainty that was promised when the legislation was firstsuggested." Nearly 2,400 people, mostly men, die from mesothelioma every year,usually within 18 months of diagnosis. A 'standardised mortality ratio' (SMR) is used to identifyblackspots, where a figure of 100 would be the expected number ofdeaths, given the age of the population. The figures are far higher in Southampton (282), Eastleigh (253),Gosport (240) and Fareham (208) -- and even in Winchester (139),New Forest (133) and Test Valley (130). Asbestos was used as insulation in ships, exposing workers duringfitting out and ship breaking. Carpenters, joiners, plumbers andheating engineers are also at particular risk. The latest row comes just weeks after the Government was accusedof caving in to the insurance industry, to limit payouts to othervictims of the deadly disease. Around 3,000 people unable to trace the employer who exposed themto asbestos dust will, finally, receive compensation from a  350mpackage. But Labour MPs condemned the decision to limit thosepayouts to 75 per cent of average compensation levels, under adeal struck with insurance companies. Furthermore, only sufferersaffected after July 2012 will be helped and there is no agreementto fund a research centre into the causes of mesothelioma.
]]></text></news-item>