<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="62E8-CDE2-DD1E-F31F"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Rock-breaking oil technology splits an Illinois town on Election Day</title><source>St. Louis Post-Dispatch (Missouri)</source><author> By Kevin McDermott kmcdermott@post-dispatch.com 314-340-8268   </author><text><![CDATA[VIENNA, Ill. • This little farming town at the edge of Shawnee National Forest has become an unlikely axis in the fight between U.S. environmental and oil interests over hydraulic fracturing - better known as "fracking."
The issue hits Johnson County polling places Tuesday, with a referendum question that's seldom been asked of American voters regarding the controversial oil-extraction process: Do you want to keep it out?
The question has fractured this quiet community like a piece of oil-soaked shale.
"In the last 20 years I've been here this is the first issue that I've actually seen people get upset at each other," says Robin Harper-Whitehead, clerk and recorder for Johnson County, a picturesque but economically struggling collection of scattered farms and tiny towns near the bottom of Illinois.
The battle lines here mirror those across the country.
On one side are environmental activists who say Illinois' leaders were too quick last year to throw open the state to fracking. They claim their local politicians and a local media blackout are conspiring to let it get a foothold here before residents can grasp the environmental implications.
"A few people will make a lot of money in the short term," predicts Tony Gerard, Shawnee College biology instructor and one of the local activists pushing the anti-fracking referendum in Tuesday's Illinois elections. "We'll be left with this environmental mess for our children to deal with."
On the other side are local political and business leaders who say the struggling deep-south region of the state needs the economic boost they claim fracking will bring. They suspect there is a wider environmentalist agenda to impede landowners' control over their own property.
"At best, such an effort will only waste money and time. At worst, it will obstruct economic development and increase unemployment in our county," area resident Zachary Garrett claims in a recent quarter-page ad in the local newspaper, The Vienna Times - which has refused in recent weeks to accept ads from the anti-fracking side of the debate.
The question on the ballot Tuesday reads: "Shall the people's right to local self government be asserted by Johnson County to ban corporate fracking as a violation of their rights to health, safety and a clean environment?"
It's an advisory referendum with no legal weight. But it asks a question that voters haven't had a chance to answer anywhere else in Illinois, nor in most of the country. As a result, it has drawn state and national players on both sides to the Johnson County seat of Vienna (pronounced Vy-anna).
Each side is accusing the other of bringing outsiders into the fight, and both are right.
One recent mailer criticizing the anti-fracking side highlights the fact that a Pennsylvania-based environmental organization is coordinating the referendum drive. "Dear out-of-state radicals: Thanks but no thanks," reads the copy. "We don't want out-of-state special interests in our community telling us what to do."
The mailer has a Des Moines, Iowa, postmark.
Both sides say principles are at stake that go beyond the particulars of fracking.
"Who should decide if it happens? Shouldn't it be the people who have to live with that outcome?" asks Ben Price, national director of community organizing for the Pennsylvania-based Community Environmental Legal Defense Fund. The group has an attorney on the ground in southern Illinois organizing support for the referendum.
The opposition believes the referendum threatens the region's economic future.
"I think the whole thing is about trying to prevent any kind of oil and gas exploration in Southern Illinois. It's just a way to keep waving the flag," said Doug Whitley, executive director of the Illinois Chamber of Commerce. The Chamber recently dumped more than $23,000 into a local campaign opposing the anti-fracking referendum.
Whitley and others claim it's a matter of economic survival in the most unemployed region of Illinois. The referendum "sends a signal ... that Illinois is going to be a hard place to do business in. We'd like to nip it in the bud so it won't keep coming back."
NEW TECHNOLOGY, NEW QUESTIONS
"Fracking" generally means "horizontal hydraulic fracturing." It's a relatively new technique of pumping water, sand and chemicals under high pressure along horizontal shale veins as far as 10,000 feet down, creating fractures in the rock to allow the oil and natural gas to seep to the well. It gets at hidden reserves that conventional drilling can't touch.
It has revolutionized the oil industry, allowing companies to revisit long-abandoned oil fields such as the ones that dot Southern Illinois, looking for trapped shale gas and oil that couldn't be economically gathered before.
The environmental concerns center on the high-pressure, chemical-laden water it uses. Critics say the industry has yet to find a reliably safe way to collect and dispose of it. Other concerns include the sheer amount of water used by the process.
Industry proponents say those concerns are overblown. They say the jobs created by a renewed Southern Illinois oil industry could mean economic salvation for the region.
In June, Illinois Gov. Pat Quinn signed into law the Illinois Hydraulic Fracturing Regulatory Act, which establishes a regulatory framework for fracking in hopes of drawing in the industry. "This new law will unlock the potential for thousands of jobs in Southern Illinois and ensure that our environment is protected," Quinn said at the time.
Some Johnson County residents who oppose fracking weren't convinced and asked the three-member county council to ban it locally.
"We feel the state just completely betrayed our interests and sold us out," said attorney Natalie Long, a southern Illinois native who has returned to the area representing CELDF, the Pennsylvania-based environmental group.
Long and the local group she's working with, Southern Illinoisans Against Fracturing Our Environment, say it was the three county commissioners themselves who suggested a referendum on the question, to determine citizens' views. They say the clear implication was that the commissioners would take no position on the issue.
That changed after the group gathered more than three times the required 374 signatures to get the referendum on the ballot. In February, one of the commissioners, Ernie Henshaw, announced formation of a group to oppose the referendum, called Citizens Opposed to Johnson County Fracking Proposition.
Henshaw argues that the goal isn't to defend fracking but to defend landowners' rights to use their land as they see fit - as well as the validity of state law.
"As of June of last year, the state of Illinois has passed a law that regulates fracking in Illinois," Henshaw said last week. "We have no legal authority over that."
Henshaw alleges, as do others, that the environmentalists' ultimate goal is to create a "community bill of rights," which CELDF has promoted in other places. They claim it would impose a range of environmental restrictions on landowners, including potential ban on agricultural chemicals.
The fracking referendum is just "the point of the arrow," alleged Henshaw.
Long flatly denied that. "The referendum question only asks about fracking. It doesn't ask about anything else."
With the passage of the new state law, oil companies from around the country have been buying up Johnson County lease rights for oil exploration - almost 200 leases as of last week, according the county recorder.
Most of those leases are to Woolsey Energy Corp. of Wichita, Kan. Company President Wayne Woolsey disputed the anti-fracking movement's claims as unproven and misleading.
"I've fracked over 300 wells on the last eight or nine years, and we've never done any damage to any fresh water," Woolsey said Friday, adding: "From what I can see, the state of Illinois can use a little boost in its economy, to build schools and maybe take care of some of their debt."
Local landowners signing the leases have included another of the county's three commissioners, Phil Stewart. He couldn't reached for comment last week.
A MEDIA BLACKOUT
The debate has been sharply personal here in Vienna - and online, where referendum supporters can buy T-shirts announcing, "No Fracking Way." Both sides' busy Facebook pages allege bad faith and hidden agendas.
Fracking defenders have placed nature-green signs all over town that say only: "Protect Johnson County; Vote NO." Some anti-fracking activists say it's a deliberate attempt to confuse people about the referendum's counter-intuitive wording, which requires people who oppose fracking to vote "yes." Others allege the anti-frackers are driven by radicalism and quasi-science.
"People are upset," says Harper-Whitehead, the county clerk and recorder. "I think it's because it's about their land."
Joe Rehana, until last week an editor with the Vienna Times/Goreville Gazette newspaper company, said he resigned after receiving a memo from Publisher Lonnie Hinton "flat-out stating we will not be accepting any more materials" from the anti-fracking groups.
"I thought the things that were happening in Johnson County were too important to have this as our message," Rehana said. Hinton, the publisher, didn't respond to requests for comment.
Illinois Primary Election Day
Tuesday, March 18
Polls are open statewide from 6 a.m. to 7 p.m. Voters may choose only one party's ballot.
Nominations to be decided include governor, one U.S. Senate seat and all Illinois seats in the U.S. House.
Coming Monday: A look at contested primary races
]]></text></news-item>