<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="640C-BE34-633F-64DE"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>ACC Probes Airport Tenders</title><source>The Namibian (Windhoek)</source><author>Ndanki Kahiurika</author><text><![CDATA[THE Namibia Airports Company (NAC) has given a N$15.2 million contract for the installation of security cameras to a company that charged two times more than other companies and came second in the technical evaluations for the job.
This contract and another amounting to about N$50 million for airport scanners have attracted the attention of the Anti- Corruption Commission (ACC) whose director, Paulus Noa, confirmed yesterday.
Meanwhile, the two tenders have allegedly also led to an internal revolt with senior staff in the department that is supposed to work with the equipment allegedly refusing to implement the systems because they questioned the awarding of the contract.
The Namibian is in possession of emails stating that the recommendation made by a staff member tasked with evaluating the bids was "modified to favour Syntex", the company that was awarded the contract.
The NAC first advertised the tender in 2012 for security cameras to be installed at Eros and Hosea Kutako airports. Sources close to the process told The Namibian that the tender was cancelled early last year, because Syntex had not applied.
Sources close to NAC said the board removed management members and some employees from working on the tender process and re-established the internal tender committee with directors as members.
When the tender was re-advertised last year, about nine companies submitted bids. Three were selected for final evaluations. Schoemans Technologies scored the highest with 65 points, followed by Syntex Technologies at 63 points and Business Connexion on 60 points.
The NAC's tender committee said in the evaluation document: "Although Schoemans Technologies scored the highest points, the indigo Vision solution offered by Syntex Technologies is the preferred solution."
Schoemans Technologies quoted NAC N$7.7 million for both airports, Syntex Technologies asked for N$15.2 million and Business Connexion was charging N$7.7 million for the security cameras system.
The acting chief executive officer, Tamar El Kallawi said he would issue a statement today because he was held up in meetings yesterday.
Syntex's managing director Linus Amulungu, who is believed to be a close friend of Ndeuhala Katonyala, the board chairperson and a member of the tender committee, confirmed that Syntex did not bid the first time the tender was advertised in 2012 because their application was late.
Katonyala laughed off the allegations that she is friends with Amulungu, saying that she also has nothing to do with the tender committee.
A prominent source within the NAC alleged that the engineering department manager, Courage Silombela, tampered with the evaluation in order to favour Syntex.
Silombela declined to comment saying he was not authorised to speak. However, in an email, Silombela, allegedly wrote to company secretary Gerson Katjangua, who is also a member of the tender committee, that: "I have modified Paulus' (Iilonga) comments to favour Syntex as per the tender committee resolution."
Iilonga is a technician tasked to see whether bidders comply with the NAC's technical requirements.
Engineering staff members, however, began raising questions in February and allegedly refused to implement the Syntex system, saying the tender had been awarded unprocedurally. They also asked to meet the human resources department and the legal adviser, but this has not been done yet.
Katjangua declined to comment, referring questions to the company's legal adviser and acting chief executive officer, El Kallawi.
Speaking to The Namibian yesterday, Amulungu confirmed that he was aware the tender was awarded to his company but no contract has been signed.
Asked about his friendship with the directors, Amulungu said: "It's a good thing to know people in the right places, people of influence. There is nothing wrong with that. It's a business world and if one wants to go far, one must win the trust of prominent people."
He added: "We are waiting for them so that we can start to work on the project."
Amulungu added that Syntex would wait until the NAC decides to give them a project manager to implement the tender.
Theo Schoeman, the chief executive officer of Schoemans Technology, said he could not comment, and was still waiting for the NAC to formally inform them about the developments.
Noa said the complaint was filed against the NAC by a Schoemans worker who claimed that the tender was supposed to be awarded to them.
"We are investigating but we request that the people involved should volunteer more information for the investigation to be successful," said Noa.
]]></text></news-item>