<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6458-4760-F740-5B40"><date>2014-03-14</date><title></title><source>Mobile Register (Alabama)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[PANAMA CITY BEACH
SPRING BREAK UPDATE
Panama City Beach police and the Bay County Sheriff’s Office continue to search for missing Rice University student Reny Jose.
Jose disappeared last week from a beach house on the west end of Panama City Beach. Police believe Jose went swimming after taking LSD and may have drowned.
Police are also investigating a non-fatal stabbing that occurred Monday night and a fatal traffic accident in which alcohol was likely a factor. The traffic accident has been reported as a two-vehicle crash.
The driver of the scooter was ejected in the crash and was pronounced dead at a local hospital. The driver of the car, 18-year-old Bruce George, has been charged with DUI manslaughter. His blood alcohol level was reportedly 0.159, well over the legal benchmark of 0.08 at which a driver is considered impaired.
Dennis Pillion
BALDWIN COUNTY
SUNKEN TREASURE?
The two automated teller machines found in a south Baldwin County creek Wednesday disappeared nearly a year ago when they were stolen from a golf club and a restaurant in Foley.
The machines were stolen May 13 during break-ins at Glenlakes Golf Club, 9530 Clubhouse Dr., and Gelato Joe’s, 202 East Michigan Ave., police Lt. David White said. The ATMs were found in a creek in the unincorporated Miflin community. No arrests have made in connection with the thefts of the machines.
Thyrie Bland
MAGNOLIA SPRINGS
BREAK-INS
The Baldwin County Sheriff’s Office is looking into whether a burglar used a three-wheel trike to get to two Magnolia Springs stores that were broken into this week.
The Sheriff’s Office said it needs the public’s help in trying to identify the man believed to be involved in the break-ins.
The break-ins happened at the Magnolia Springs Pharmacy on U.S. 98 and across the street at a BP gas station, Sheriff’s Office Maj. Anthony Lowery said.
Thyrie Bland
MOBILE COUNTY
RECYCLing
Mobile County Commission will sponsor a Household Hazardous Waste Collection Day.
The event will be Saturday, March 22, from 9 a.m. to 2 p.m. at the Grounds, formerly known as the Greater Gulf State Fairgrounds, and gives Mobile County residents an opportunity to properly dispose of household hazardous waste.
Recycling is limited to household hazardous waste only and will include:
Paints (oil-based and latex)
Household cleaners
Automotive fluids
Pesticides
Herbicides
Fungicides
Pool chemicals
Aerosols
Cassie Fambro
]]></text></news-item>