<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="64D6-44B6-B07E-0394"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>In defence of Ezemvelo security firms</title><source>Sunday Tribune (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Jeff Wicks's article (Sunday Tribune, February 23: "Parks security firms make killing") warrants correction.
The story is premised on incorrect information that nullifies its overall leaning towards suggestions of corruption and tender fraud in the appointment of these security companies.
It saddens me that the Sunday Tribune has already aired smoke. As far as public perception is concerned, there must be fire. Well, please allow me to douse it.
Ezemvelo KZN Wildlife employed these two security firms following a transparent and legal process.
Seven security companies were initially identified to fulfil the contract of guarding five critical "corridor" areas in our parks (Ozabeni, Weenen, Ndumo Game Reserve's Mbangweni area, Ndumo's Usuthu and Hluhluwe iMfolozi Park).
Of these, only two were approved. The other five were disqualified on grounds of non-compliance - not having tax clearance certificates and neither the company nor the directors being registered with the Private Security Industry Regulatory Authority.
Yes, the bid was a closed one, but I am sure readers will appreciate the need for the secrecy that underscores rhino security. We cannot afford to have information leaking into the wrong hands.
These companies' credentials were recommended by the evaluation and adjudication committees and passed on to our board for ratification.
Both were subsequently approved by an extraordinary meeting of the board.
The emphasis given in your story to the R3.5 million we paid for their combined services bears scrutiny.
The allegation that each company supplied only two guards each for this contract is misleading. For the record, each employs 20 full-time and 10 part-time security guards.
But the real point is that Ezemvelo employed two companies. What each one's total overheads are, quite frankly, is not our business.
Their fees had to be market-related or our board would never have sanctioned these contractors.
Finally, it is simply not true that these guards arrived at their specific stations without the firearms and equipment that formed part of their overall tender.
This comment so alarmed me that I personally commanded the investigation into its veracity.
Ezemvelo never bought any equipment for either of these companies to fulfil their duties. If this had been the case, not only would they have been in breach of their contract, but I would have terminated these contracts.
BANDILE MKHIZE
Chief executive officer, Ezemvelo KZN Wildlife
]]></text></news-item>