<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6551-DEC1-7AD1-52E0"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>EQUITY ALERT: The Rosen Law Firm Files Securities Fraud Class Action Against Hyperdynamics Corporation -- HDY</title><source>GlobeNewswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NEW YORK, March 15, 2014 (GLOBE NEWSWIRE) -- The Rosen Law Firm announced today that it has filed a class action lawsuit on behalf of all purchasers of the securities of Hyperdynamics Corporation (NYSE:HDY) between November 8, 2012 and March 11, 2014, inclusive, seeking remedies under the federal securities laws.
To join the Hyperdynamics class action, go to the website at http://rosenlegal.com or call Phillip Kim, Esq. or Kevin Chan, Esq. toll-free at 866-767-3653 or email pkim@rosenlegal.com or kchan@rosenlegal.com for information on the class action.
NO CLASS HAS YET BEEN CERTIFIED IN THE ABOVE ACTION. UNTIL A CLASS IS CERTIFIED, YOU ARE NOT REPRESENTED BY COUNSEL UNLESS YOU RETAIN ONE. YOU MAY ALSO REMAIN AN ABSENT CLASS MEMBER AND DO NOTHING AT THIS POINT. YOU MAY RETAIN COUNSEL OF YOUR CHOICE.
According to the lawsuit, defendants made materially misleading statements and failed to disclose that Hyperdynamics obtained and retained oil and gas concession rights in violation of the U.S. Foreign Corrupt Practices Act and U.S. anti-money laundering statutes. When this adverse information entered the market, the price of the Company's stock dropped more than 58%-- damaging investors.
A class action lawsuit has already been filed. If you wish to serve as lead plaintiff, you must move the Court no later than May 12, 2014. If you wish to join the litigation or to discuss your rights or interests regarding this class action, please contact, Phillip Kim, Esq. or Kevin Chan, Esq. of The Rosen Law Firm toll free at 866-767-3653 or via e-mail at pkim@rosenlegal.com or kchan@rosenlegal.com
The Rosen Law Firm focuses on prosecuting securities class action litigation and actions involving financial fraud. The Rosen Law Firm represents investors throughout the globe.
]]></text></news-item>