<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="655F-AA38-1437-CE72"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>New maps put Layton homes in floodplain</title><source>Standard-Examiner (Ogden, Utah)</source><author>Bryon Saxton, Standard-Examiner, Ogden, Utah</author><text><![CDATA[March 16--LAYTON -- Updated flood insurance rate maps concern Layton City engineers because the maps project a significant amount of increased flow from Kays Creek, resulting in 119 homes being added to the floodplain.
"If homes are placed in the floodplain, homeowners are required to purchase flood insurance. This insurance is expensive and will increase over the next few years without government subsidizing it," City Engineer Woody Woodruff said.
Layton intends on appealing the 2014 changes the Federal Emergency Management Agency has made to the Davis County floodplain based on flood insurance studies.
"For example, the 2007 flood insurance study for Kay's Creek at Union Pacific Railroad estimated flow of 680 cubic feet per second. The proposed preliminary 2014 study introduces a flow of 1,189 cubic feet per second, an increase of 509 cubic feet per second," Woodruff said.
"Because the channels and bridge structures cannot handle the estimated flows, the study proposes to add 119 homes in Layton city to the 100-year floodplain and impact many acres of additional undeveloped land," Woodruff said.
FEMA is in the process of updating the flood insurance rate maps for the county. A public open house on the revised mapping will be held from 5 to 7 p.m., March 26, in the Layton City Council Chambers, 437 N. Wasatch Drive.
Attendees will have an opportunity to ask questions about the impacts the new maps will have on their property.
A web viewer has been created to show the preliminary data and changes since the last flood insurance rate maps data. The public can access the web viewer at http://bit.ly/1dUT37Z. The public can use the "Basemap" button to view aerial photography.
For more information visit www.floodsmart.gov or www.laytoncity.org/public/Depts/PubWorks/StormWater/default.aspx.
The new floodplain maps prepared by URS Corp. for this project will have a substantial impact on residences in Layton, Woodruff said.
Studies by URS were completed for Kayscreek, Holmes Creek and Snow Creek in Layton, and for several channels in Davis County. Of all the communities studied, Layton is impacted the most with a large number of additional homes being added to the floodplain along Kayscreek, Woodruff said.
The city will be filing an appeal to FEMA during the 90-day "appeal and comment period" from May to July.
"We have already retained a consultant to help review, evaluate and prepare more practical and realistic hydrology and hydraulic studies for the new flood insurance maps," Woodruff said.
Layton officials have also met with other community officials in sharing their concerns of these impacts to county residents, he said.
"We have been waiting for the public meeting so Layton city can file their formal appeal to FEMA," Woodruff said.
The city will schedule an additional public meeting after the March 26 open house to discuss the details of their appeal to local residents, he said.
Contact reporter Bryon Saxton at 801-625-4244 or bsaxton@standard.net, or follow him on Twitter at @BryonSaxton.
___ (c)2014 the Standard-Examiner (Ogden, Utah) Visit the Standard-Examiner (Ogden, Utah) at www.standard.net Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>