<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="65B4-2B41-CB55-839D"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>CHRISTIE'S  IN-YOUR-FACE TOWN HALL  6 protesters challenging governor on GWB, Sandy aid scandals tossed out </title><source>The Star-Ledger (Newark, New Jersey)</source><author>Salvador Rizzo, STAR-LEDGER STAFF</author><text><![CDATA[With more than 100 town halls behind him, Gov. Chris Christie has plenty of experience bantering with youngsters and charming his fans, sparring with teachers and dishing out his trademark Jersey attitude to the naysayers.
But he never had to deal with a stream of angry protesters getting in his face for half an hour, which is what he got yesterday at his 113th town hall meeting in Mount Laurel.
One after another, six college students from Rowan University stood up to demand answers about the George Washington Bridge scandal and Christie's handling of federal relief aid for victims of Hurricane Sandy. All six were escorted from the YMCA by local and State Police.
"I really love youthful enthusiasm," Christie said sarcastically amid the interruptions. "I really do. And these folks who come in here today, ginned up for their own partisan purposes, see, they're getting exactly what they want. "¦ What they want is attention."
Having just unveiled a $34.4 billion budget last month, the governor began with a brief discussion about property taxes and pension costs.
It was during the question-and-answer session that one of the Rowan students, Michael Brein, teed off on Christie about Sandy funds. "Either sit down and keep quiet, or get out," Christie told him. "We're done with you."
But Brein, 19, continued until police officers led him away.
"He spent two-and-a-half times as much money on advertisements with himself in them "¦ than on small businesses affected by Hurricane Sandy," Brein said afterward, referring to the $2.5 million "Stronger Than The Storm" ad campaign that featured the Christie family and was paid for with federal Sandy relief funds. "I just wanted to ask how he can justify that."
The Republican governor had many supporters in the crowd of more than 400 -- but protesters kept piping up, police kept removing them, and Christie scolded them for interrupting other people.
"Don't take away from them for your own partisan, personal purposes," he said.
The politically charged closing of access lanes at the George Washington Bridge last September and the pace of rebuilding from the storm have become sore topics for Christie this year.
Documents subpoenaed by a legislative committee investigating the traffic-clogging incident have shown that a cluster of his top aides and associates organized the closings for reasons that remain unexplained.
The governor has also faced heightened scrutiny over how he distributed hundreds of millions of dollars in Sandy aid. Mayor Dawn Zimmer of Hoboken, a Democrat, has alleged that top administration officials held out on her city because she refused to approve a development project Christie wanted.
In the three town halls held earlier this year, Christie did not get one question about the lane closings, which he told one reporter was because "people care about real problems."
"I'm here to say people still care about the Bridgegate scandal," Brein said. "They still care about the misappropriation of Sandy money."
Kailee Whiting, 20, another Rowan student who was ejected from the event, said she believed Christie when he said he had nothing to do with the lane closings. Still, Whiting said, even if it was a group of rogue aides, "what does it show his leadership skills were by hiring all these crooks?"
Brein said he was representing the New Jersey Working Families Alliance, a coalition of union and environmental groups.
While environmentalists and housing advocates for the poor who are opposed to Christie's policies were also on hand, they said they weren't going to shout to get his attention.
Mike McNeil, state chairman of the housing section of the NAACP, said afterward that he disagreed with Christie over the way he has neglected affordable housing issues in New Jersey.
Mount Laurel is considered to be the birthplace of affordable housing laws nationwide, since the state Supreme Court ruled in 1975 that the Burlington County town could not use its zoning powers to price out its poorest residents, nearly all of them African American.
Salvador Rizzo: (609) 989-0341 or srizzo@starledger.com
]]></text></news-item>