<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="65EB-E815-556F-50CF"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Facing Increased FDA Presence, India Defends Drug Oversight As High Quality</title><source>FDA Week</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[India's Ministry of Health and Family Welfare pushed back against recent criticism of its pharmaceutical regulatory oversight as baseless and intended "to malign the well-earned reputation of the Indian national regulatory authority," coming as FDA steps up its regulatory presence in that country and some U.S. cardiologists and pharmaceutical experts question the safety of India's drug supply. The regulator stressed March 6 that it passed a stringent World Health Organization review of its vaccine oversight program last year and said drugs exported to the United States meet FDA standards.
India's regulators and drug industry have come under scrutiny in recent years, and FDA last month signed an agreement with that country's drug regulators to collaborate on inspections and information sharing. Lawmakers on Capitol Hill also have expressed concerns after being presented data from cardiologists questioning the safety and efficacy of certain drugs produced in India. Plus, India-based Ranbaxy Laboratories recently agreed to pay $500 million for allegedly making false statements to FDA and other alleged violations that FDA said led to adulterated products.
In its March 6 statement, the Indian ministry says the Drug Controller General, the top official at India's Central Drug Standard Control Organization, was inspected in 2013 by an international team from the World Health Organization. The regulatory authority was deemed functional for vaccines against stringent international parameters, the statement says. The release also points out that there are 360 FDA-approved drug manufacturers in India and 150 manufacturers approved by the European Directorate for the Quality of Medicines. The ministry maintains that drugs exported to the United States meet FDA standards.
"There are adequate provisions under the Drugs and Cosmetics Act 1940 and Rules made there under for ensuring the quality, safety and efficacy of drugs manufactured in India for marketing," the statement says. "In fact Indian drug products are accepted in more than 2015 countries which include both developed and developing countries."
The statement also points out that there isn't harmonization between the different regulatory agencies. "A product from India complying with the US standards would still have to comply with the regulatory requirements of Japan if it has to be exported to Japan," it says.
A panel of researchers and doctors recently alleged that India's Central Drug Standard Control Organization is limited in power and ineffective. The panel -- at a Feb. 26 meeting -- told congressional staff, State Department and FDA representatives, and reporters that India's drug safety laws are outdated. Cardiologists also presented research and testimony alleging widespread contamination of India's generic drugs are affecting patient health.
The Indian press release targeted one panelist, Roger Bate of the American Enterprise Institute, who urged U.S. regulators to consider limiting imports of Indian drugs, and several media outlets, including the Business Standard, The Times of India and The Economic Times, for reporting the criticisms about the country's regulatory authority, saying that these items were factually incorrect and largely unsubstantiated.
"Indian laws and India's robust regulatory framework ensures the high standards of quality, safety and efficacy of drugs manufactured in the country," the regulator says. "The allegations made in these news items appear to be baseless and solely printed with the intention of harming the reputation of the Indian national regulatory authority as well as Indian drug industry." -- Erin Durkin
]]></text></news-item>