<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6614-3549-DF19-D156"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>MPs slam 'too big to fail' firms over huge public contracts; Scandals 'undermined trust'</title><source>Daily Post (North Wales)</source><author>DAVID WILLIAMSON</author><text><![CDATA[A WARNING will be made today that companies with giant UK Government contracts are "too big too fail" and need greater scrutiny of how taxpayers' cash is spent.
The public accounts committee - whose members include Welsh MPs Guto Bebb and Nick Smith - has grilled Atos, Capita, G4S and Serco, which between them had contracts worth around £4bn in 2012-13 - and will publish a hard-hitting report on how Government contracts must change to ensure whistle-blowers enjoy new protection and account books are opened.
Management of contracts is damned as "very weak" and the commissioning process is attacked for excluding small and medium-sized businesses and allowing taxpayer-funded "monopolies" to form. Highlighting recent scandals, the report states: "Government is clearly failing to manage performance across the Guto Bebb MP, left, Committee chair achieve the best for citizens out of the contracts into which they have entered. Government needs a far more professional and skilled approach to managing contracts and contractors, and contractors need to demonstrate the high standards of ethics expected in the conduct of public business, and be more transparent about performance and costs. "The public's trust in outsourcing has been undermined recently by the poor performance of G4S in supplying security guards for the Olympics, Capita's failure to deliver court translation services, issues with Atos's work capability assessments, mis-reporting of out of hours GP services by Serco, and most recently, the astonishing news that G4S and Serco had overcharged for years on electronic tagging contracts: these high profile failures illustrate contractors' failure to live up to standards expected and have exposed and Public Accounts Margaret Hodge serious weaknesses in Government's capability in negotiating and managing private contracts on behalf of the taxpayer."
Aberconwy Conservative MP Guto Bebb said: "I think the report highlights the difficulties faced by small businesses who want to tender for work. To be perfectly frank, it has concerned me for a while, even before I was elected... The complexity and the daunting nature of the documentation will often persuade small businesses not even to apply."
Margaret Hodge, the Labour committee chair, said: "An absence of real competition has led to the evolution of privately-owned public monopolies which have become too big to fail. Some public service markets such as for private prisons, asylum accommodation or disability benefit assessments, are now controlled by just one or two major contractors. Small and medium enterprises have been crowded out by the complexity of the contracting process, excessive bureaucracy and high bidding costs."
The MPs demand a "standard term in contracts requiring suppliers to have whistleblowing policies in place".
]]></text></news-item>