<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6617-7C1D-EF1D-7529"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Sen. Baucus Took "Vow" to Help Libby Residents</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Mike Dennison, writing for The Missoulian, reported that forresidents of Libby ravaged by asbestos-related diseases, U.S. Sen.Max Baucus has delivered on health care -- including specialgovernment coverage like nowhere else in America. "Just about every step of the way, Max has been there," says GaylaBenefield, a Libby resident and activist who helped expose theasbestos pollution in Libby. "All we've had to do is ask, and he'sbeen right on it." Libby's infamous asbestos problem stems from a now-defunctvermiculite mine last operated by W.R. Grace and Co. on the edgeof town. Generations of workers at the mine breathed asbestosfibers from the vermiculite and brought the deadly fibers home ontheir clothes, infecting their families with lung disease as well. Grace also left piles of low-grade vermiculite near the mine, foranyone to take. It was used in gardens, baseball fields, trackfields and for home insulation throughout Libby, exposing hundredsmore to its asbestos fibers. More than 3,000 people from Libby have been diagnosed withasbestos-related lung disease, some 400 have died and the numberscontinue to grow. Libby residents diagnosed with the disease, however, have a uniquebenefit, thanks to Baucus: They are covered by Medicare,regardless of their age. Medicare, usually reserved for Americans 65 or older, providesfree hospital care, insurance for non-hospital care for about $105a month and prescription drug coverage. Tanis Hernandez, administrative director of the Center forAsbestos Related Disease in Libby, says ever-younger residents arecoming to the clinic to get screened for asbestos lung diseases.If they screen positive, they get Medicare coverage. Baucus, D-Mont., chief architect of the 2010 Affordable Care Act-- "Obamacare" -- wrote the Medicare provision into the bill, forcitizens affected by contamination at Superfund sites declared a"public health emergency." Libby is the only such site in thecountry. Baucus also has announced expansion to several counties near Libbyof a pilot program covering some additional services not usuallycovered by Medicare, like home health assistance. This specialMedicare coverage isn't the only help Baucus has helped arrangefor Libby's asbestos victims. He helped get seed money and grantsfor the clinic, which provides free screening for Libby residents,secured funding to help pay for its expansion, pushed for the 2009public health emergency declaration, and supported a $10 milliongrant in 2011 to cover future screening costs. "We wouldn't be where we are today without his support," Hernandezsays. "He's always been there to hear the latest concerns andstruggles, and to try to find a solution." Baucus visited Libby last summer, and brought along the head ofthe U.S. Centers for Medicaid and Medicare Services with him. Hesaid Libby had been a top priority for him, since meeting victimsand activists 14 years earlier. "I made a vow to myself," he said, "(that) I would do whatever ittook to help the people of Libby."
]]></text></news-item>