<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="664D-1117-7A64-031B"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Michael Murray: The latest Brussels proposals on bankers' pay are daft, and likely to have the opposite effect to what is intended</title><source>Sunday Business Post</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Seeking to tame the global financial sector is akin to trying to put tidiness and order into a large urn of spaghetti.
The sheer scale, complexity and obtuseness of the interlinkages within global financial markets, the proliferation of financial innovation and the exotic and often toxic financial instruments that underpin it, makes the consequences of much regulatory intervention impossible to predict and even more difficult to undo.
When it comes to banking, sometimes a little forethought and focus on what drives human endeavour would help avoid at least some of the mistakes of the past.
The most controversial aspect of corporate governance over the past decade has related to the topic of directors' and chief executives' pay. The extent of coverage on the topic has actually made it boring.
That said, the outrage in respect of how, throughout the English speaking world, those most responsible for the financial crisis have walked away with the biggest rewards for the worst results has been fully justified. The fact that the taxpayer has had to pick up the bill makes the task of defending some aspects of the current capitalist system impossible.
Since the financial crisis, much has been done to clamp down on excessive risk taking in banks. Most of the new rules, designed in Brussels, Washington and Basel, have been of a technical nature and well beyond the day to day interest of the ordinary taxpayer or shareholder. Some will be effective and should serve to make our financial sector and the global financial system a little safer.
But in recent weeks draft -- and daft -- proposals on bankers' pay were published in Brussels. Supposedly these have been designed to prevent excessive risk taking by bankers being encouraged by short-term incentives that are not aligned with long-term performance and shareholder value. Sadly, if implemented as currently envisaged, the proposals look certain to have the opposite effect to that intended, and risk forcing further taxpayer-funded bank rescues in the future.
The focus of the proposals on remuneration has been on identifying those charged with the taking and managing of risks in financial institutions and then seeking to cap at a multiple of one the level of bonus paid to those risk takers relative to their base salaries.
The immediate and most obvious consequence of this proposal, if implemented, will be to push base salaries up so that -- combined with the new, controlled, single' multiple of bonus on top, the total remuneration package will be back to exactly where it was when the bonus was up to a multiple of four times base salary.
But the important point from a taxpayer and systemic point of view is whether this new proposed regulated pay structure would be consistent with encouraging responsible risk taking. If it isn't, taxpayers will almost certainly find themselves called to the rescue again in the future. We were told in the past that bankers' rewards were aligned to ''risk adjusted'' returns, ie to profits from the amount of capital designated to the risk inherent in the asset they underwrote as risk weighted and measured by the banks' own in-house risk models.
If you look at the outcomes from many of these risk models over the past seven years you will see that they made a mockery of risk management and risk measurement but were verified by passive external risk management consultants who got paid their consulting fees for giving the ''right'' answer that turned out, when push came to shove, to be wrong by a factor of up to about 30 times, resulting in the wipeout many times over of bank capital across nearly every indigenous financial institution in this country! And we all saw where that landed the taxpayer.
The truth is that back in the 1970s and 1980s financial institutions didn't use ''sophisticated'' risk adjusted models designed by either nerds or opportunists. Most, in those days, operated either no bonus-based incentive system at all (a bad idea) or, if they did, they took one of two approaches. First, by giving everyone the same percentage bonus every year -- wholly unrelated to personal performance -- a seriously bad idea that made a mockery of the incentivisation aspect.
Others -- the more advanced banks at that time -- awarded the bonus on a three to four-year deferment basis so that the award could be clawed back if risk crystallised in the form of bad debts in the meantime.
That was, and remains, the most appropriately structured methodology in a banking context. But the power and success of the investment banking lobby in the US and Europe has been such that a return to a structure of this kind has been very damagingly squashed.
Regulators often put their proposals out to consultation among ''stakeholders''. But unfortunately the lion's share of the responses to the consultations come from those with embedded corporate interests that are neither aligned with the public interest nor the interest of buy-side investors who rarely get represented in lobbying quarters but who, along with taxpayers are the real stakeholders.
It is very obviously the variable element of pay -- the bonus -- that drives human behaviour. And in a financial service business it is human behaviour including risk taking that drives or wrecks corporate performance.
If the bonus has been paid on the back of short-term results then short-term human behaviour will be geared towards those results. This applies in pretty well every business. But it is usually only in systemically important businesses -- as banking and insurance are -- that the taxpayer is left to pick up the bill to avoid the dreadful alternative of systemic financial and economic collapse.
Unintended consequences have invariably been the outcome of regulation on directors' remuneration to date. It is about two decades ago since disclosure first became mandatory. This was in the belief that such disclosure would curb excessive remuneration. It did precisely the opposite. Never has the explosion in directors' remuneration been as great as it has been since the introduction of the disclosure requirements, whether you calculate it relative to the rest of the workforce or relative to inflation.
Instead of a board of directors becoming embarrassed by the level of their chief executive's remuneration they became embarrassed if it was below the level of the chief executive of its nearest competitor. It might be seen to be communicating to the market that the chairman and board considered their chief executive less worthy than that of his closest peer in an organisation of similar size and sector.
The earnings dynamics of every business model are different. And the timing and cycle that determines true profits and losses also differ. From the fish and chip shop where true profit can probably be accurately counted at the end of every week to the biotech company where it might be prudent to count it only at the end of every decade.
The problem with the most recent proposals from Europe in relation to bankers' pay is that the timing of payment of incentive-based pay in the form of bonuses doesn't seem to come into consideration at all.
Get the earnings and high yields from the high risk assets this year, collect the bonus at the end of the year, and so what if the assets turn rotten the following year? Pay me now and let the shareholder (first) and taxpayer (second) yet again pick up the bill.
Have regulators learned nothing and forgotten everything?
It is time that fund managers and financial intermediaries -- whose clients are on the ''buy side'' of the market -- started to involve themselves more in lobbying to represent the interests of the people whose money they are paid to manage and whose savings are at stake. These are their clients -- the buy side investors -- who get no voice in respect of regulatory proposals in which they have a stake via their pension fund investments or other savings - not to mention via their taxes.
]]></text></news-item>