<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="666E-1AEB-AF8A-B748"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Lennar seeks foreclosure on 76 acres in Miami-Dade County</title><source>South Florida Business Journal</source><author>Brian Bandell</author><text><![CDATA[An affiliate of home building giant Lennar Corp. wants to seize 76.2 acres of farmland in Homestead through foreclosure. Coco Palm 82 LLC, an affiliate of the home builder (NYSE: LEN) filed a foreclosure lawsuit on March 12 against MD Holdings II LLC. It concerns a $25.6 million mortgage that the plaintiff previously acquired from Doral-based U.S. Century Bank.
RELATED CONTENT: U.S. Century Bank sells $30M in loans, Lennar buys biggest
MD Holdings II owns the farmland at 11760 S.W. 248th Street. It previously secured approval for 581 market-rate hosuing units and 83 workforce housing units there but construction didn't get started. Michael Latterner, the managing member of MD Holdings II, wasn't named in the lawsuit. Miami attorney Jessica C. Silver, who represents Coco Palm 82 in the lawsuit, declined comment. Palm Beach County office building hit with foreclosure Northpointe Professional Center in North Palm Beach has been targeted for foreclosure by a commercial mortgage-backed securities (CMBS) trust. U.S. Bank, representing the CMBS trust, filed a foreclosure lawsuit on March 10 against Northpointe Realty Partners. It concerns the 27,888-square-foot building on 1.4 acres at 824 U.S. Highway One. The building was constructed in 1982 and last purchased for $2.15 million in 2004. The following year, Northpointe Realty Partners got a $2.72 million mortgage that helped fund renovations to the building. The borrower is managed by Jonathan R. Satter, although he wasn't named in the complaint. According to CMBS analysis firm Trepp LLC, the mortgage has $2.45 million outstanding and has been delinquent for nearly a year. Its interest rate is 5.37 percent. The building was recently 66 percent occupied after two tenants left due to their deteriorating financial positions, according to Trepp. Its largest tenants are Meridian Commodity Corp. with 3,540 square feet, Laszlo J. Mate MD with 2,979 square feet and Caretenders Visiting Service with 2,864 square feet. In the first half of 2013, the building generated net operating income of $86,047 on revenue of $158,988, which wasn't enough to make mortgage payments without outside assistance, according to Trepp. The property was recently appraised at $1.53 million, down from $3.4 million when the loan was made in 2005 Trepp found. Tampa attorney Jason Sampson, who represents U.S. Bank in the lawsuit, couldn't be reached for comment. C-III Asset Management is the special servicer of the CMBS trust loan. The special servicer's notes to Trepp stated that the borrower is expected to cooperate with the foreclosure process and turn over the property. Developer's beachfront mansion in $4.6M foreclosure auction A beachfront mansion developed as a spec home is headed to auction over a $4.6 million foreclosure judgment. RADC/CADC Venture 2010-2 LLC won the judgment against Ark Development/Oceanview and guarantors Isaac Kodsi, Joseph Kodsi and Peter Tocci over a $3.1 million mortgage. The loan was originated by Rockbridge Commercial Bank, which later failed. The 4,877-square-foot home at 1423 N. Fort Lauderdale Beach Blvd. is set for online auction June 10. It was built in 2011 and has five bedrooms and five bathrooms. Miami attorney Robert F. Cooke represented the plaintiff in the lawsuit. In 2011, Ark Development/Oceanview lost a neighboring mansion to foreclosure over a $3.4 million judgment. Mobile home park avoids foreclosure with sale The Ocean Tide mobile home park in Riviera Beach resolved its foreclosure lawsuit by getting sold. Back in 2012, Petra CRE CDO 2007-1 Ltd. filed a foreclosure lawsuit against and Ocean Tide of Riviera Beach and Suni Sands Mobile Home Park over a $29.5 million mortgage. The latter defendant owned a Jupiter mobile home park that was sold in 2013 for $17.5 million. On March 10, the 236-unit Ocean Tide on 12.1 acres at 3051 Broadway was sold for $3.1 million to Fort Lauderdale-based Ocean Tide MHP LLC. The buyer, which is managed by Christopher Dunn, got a $2.25 million mortgage from Fort Lauderdale-based Landmark Bank. The mortgage was released and the foreclosure lawsuit was withdrawn. Given that the mobile home parks sold for a combined $20.6 million and the mortgage was $29.5 million, it appears the Petra fund lost some of the loan principal in allowing the short sales. Flamingo Market Place resolves foreclosure Flamingo Market Place in Pembroke Pines resolved its foreclosure problems and appears in good standing with its lender. Back in 2011, GSMS 2005-GG4 Pembroke Retail LLC, representing a CMBS fund with Miami Beach-based LNR Properties as special servicer, filed a foreclosure lawsuit against Flamingo Market Place, along with Gary Hahn and Rubin Pikus, the CEO of New York-based Milbrook Properties. It targeted the 145,946-square-foot shopping center at 12105 Pembroke Road. According to data from CMBS analysis firm Trepp LLC, the mortgage had $14.4 million and had gone delinquent on payments. Trepp's latest notes on the property from February state that the loan was brought current by the borrower and is in the "rehab" period. On Feb. 7, the lender withdrew the foreclosure lawsuit. The largest tenants in the shopping center are Bravo Supermarket with 44,000 square feet and 21st Century Oncology with 10,100 square feet. Warehouse escapes foreclosure The North Miami warehouse that is home to Atlantic Shutters is no longer in foreclosure. John Kurzman and Rhoda Kurzman filed a foreclosure lawsuit in 2011 against Arch Creek Warehouse Complex, along with managing member Kevin P. Kennedy and his Atlantic Shutters. The lawsuit concerned a $2.8 million mortgage on the 24,571-square-foot warehouse at 1970 N.E. 153rd Street. The plaintiffs voluntarily dismissed the lawsuit on March 7. "The defendant made payments at the 11th hour to bring it mostly current so we were able to dismiss the foreclosure," said Plantation attorney Michael Kurzman, who represents the plaintiff. "The lender is working with them so these folks don't lose their building because they are working hard to keep it."
To search for other large commercial foreclosures in South Florida, including by location or property type, check out our Foreclosure Roundup Database.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to South Florida Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>