<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="668E-B3A4-0CD8-F0FB"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>San Marino: a republic under seige</title><source>The Toronto Star</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[San Marino, the world's oldest republic, celebrates its independence with a holiday called the Feast of Saint Agatha.
On this day, Feb. 5, even the occupants of the country's six prison cells are allowed to enjoy an expensive meal. This year, it consisted of risotto with parmesan, followed by roasted turkey with seasonal vegetables and fruit for dessert. It was accompanied by wine.
At least one inmate, Piero Berti - a former San Marino head of state - is accustomed to fine foods. He's enjoyed many meals with other dignitaries at Ritrovo dei Lavoratori (the name means "Workers' Meeting Place"), the upscale restaurant that supplied the prisoner's holiday meal.
Berti, 46, and a doctor by profession, was arrested on Jan. 21 under suspicion of having sexually harassed female patients. It's likely that he'll contest the charges. Regardless of how the case is resolved, however, it's already landed the Republic of San Marino - a microstate tucked into the countryside along Italy's Adriatic coast - in the international spotlight against its will.
Italy's national television station broadcast live interviews from San Marino using the prison as a backdrop. Newspapers, including the Jornal do Brasil, followed. As a result, approximately 32,500 Sammarinese - proud inhabitants of the world's fifth-smallest country - are once again seeing themselves labelled as exotic oddballs with strange customs.
People were already sensing that all was not well in San Marino. For years, the republic's banks were obscenely successful - rich Italians squirrelled away unreported earnings here to hide them from tax authorities. But with the start of the financial crisis, many of those rich Italians withdrew their illegal wealth.
That was the first blow. Then the Italian government enticed tax evaders back home with an amnesty offer. As a result, several banks in San Marino folded, and the once flourishing banking centre is experiencing record levels of unemployment. Italy refuses to remove the country from its black list, which means anyone doing business with San Marino is closely monitored.
According to the republic's finance minister, the Italian media picks up every piece of bad news out of spite; the Berti case, he says, is more of the same.
That, he continues, is despite the fact that Berti has been an "ordinary citizen" since 1999. The man's "private concerns," adds the country's foreign minister, are being used by the resentful to spread "a negative image of the republic" and its institutions.
And there's something else making San Marino's reputation more difficult to maintain. Here, more than anywhere else in the world, it's more likely that someone who has broken a law was also once a head of state - the republic inaugurates two new heads of state every six months. Since this rotation began in 1243, the small nation has seen more than 3,000 Captains Regent come and go.
San Marino currently finds itself, according to its own calculations, in the 1713th year since its founding. In the year 301, Saint Marinus, a pious stonemason and hermit, supposedly declared that his fellow residents were henceforth free of servitude to popes or emperors. The balcony of the country's parliamentary and government building bears the historical inscription "Libertas" as a testament to that event.
On the Feast of Saint Agatha, the Captain Regent - dressed in a frock coat and top hat - strides through the medieval alleyways of the old town on his way to church. He's escorted by a Carabinieri general carrying a cavalry sabre and a republican guard of honour, and accompanied by the sound of cannon blasts.
During the service in the church crypt, Berti's wife, herself a member of parliament, sits next to a cousin who is a former president. The justice and health ministers, both officially connected to the Berti case simply by dint of their posts, have taken up position in the pew across the way.
Some say the country's powerful are a clique, that the members of the ruling class know one another all too well and that things get hushed up.
Antonella Mularoni, the country's foreign minister of many years, says it is high time San Marino opened up and did something to combat its reputation as a cabinet of curiosities.
"Why is it," she asks, "that everyone knows Monaco, but hardly anyone knows San Marino? Is it because we don't have princesses? San Marino is, after all, the oldest republic in the world."
Translated from German by Ella Ornstein
]]></text></news-item>