<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="66B0-8E2B-6ACA-BC44"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>US Contract Notice: Department of the Air Force Issues Solicitation for "Columbus Aircraft MX Bridge Contract"</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Department of the Air Force, Air Education and Training Command Officer has issued requirement for "Columbus Aircraft MX Bridge Contract."
Solicitation no. FA3002-13-R-0006 Posted on: March 14, 2014
Notice Type: Special Notice / Cancelled
The NAICS code number for this requirement: 488
Description: The Headquarters (HQ) Air Education and Training Command (AETC), HQ AETC/A4PM, Randolph Air Force Base (AFB), Texas 78150-4302, announces the intent to award a firm-fixed price bridge contract on a sole source basis to DynCorp International, LLC (DI). This has become necessary as a result of delays beginning performance under FA3002-13-C-0006, which was awarded to L-3 Communications Vertex Aerospace, LLC (L-3) on 26 Oct 12 as a single Firm-Fixed-Price contract follow-on contract for Columbus AFB Aircraft Maintenance. The current award is presently suspended pending GAO's ruling on a post-award protest. The incumbent contractor, DI, would continue to furnish adequate supervision, labor, materials, supplies, and equipment necessary to perform aircraft maintenance and support functions at Columbus AFB, MS. Services include, but are not limited to: aircraft maintenance operations support (Organizational Level) for T-1A, T-6A, T-38C Specialized Undergraduate Pilot Training (SUPT) and T-38C Introduction to Fighter Fundamentals (IFF) aircraft; On-and off-equipment maintenance (repairs, scheduled and unscheduled maintenance, inspections, Time Compliance Technical Orders (TCTOs), Time Change Items (TCIs) and One-Time Inspections (OTIs) on aircraft and support equipment; Manage the Periodic (PE) inspection sections and Jet Engine Intermediate Maintenance (JEIM) support for the T-38 flying mission at Naval Air Station (NAS) Patuxent River, including calibration and certification of Test, Measurement and Diagnostic Equipment (TMDE) by the Precision Measurement Equipment Laboratory (PMEL) for organizations in Mississippi, Tennessee, Kentucky, and Alabama; Provide for Crashed, Damaged or Disabled Aircraft Recovery (CDDAR) and off-station aircraft recovery within the region specified by HQ AETC for T-1, T-6 and T-38 aircraft; Manage maintenance operations and other services: Maintenance Operations Center (MOC), Plans, Scheduling and Documentation (PS&D), maintenance data system analysis, engine management and Quality Assurance.
Set Aside: N/A
Deadline for All responses: Mar 28, 2013 4:00 pm Central
Contact Details: 2021 First Street WestJBSA Randolph, Texas 78150-4302United States
Point of Contact(s): Todd S. Joyner,Procurement Analyst/Contracting Officertodd.joyner.1@us.af.milPhone: 2106522444
For more information visit: https://www.fbo.gov/index?s=opportunity&mode=d32715960861682a71fffa77464c4c51&tab=core&_cview=1. In case of any query regarding this article or other content needs please contact: editorial@plusmediasolutions.com
]]></text></news-item>