<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="66FA-464E-D413-9278"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>The Plains SouthCap Pipeline Ongoing Environmental Racism In Historic Plateau/Africatown ,AL.</title><source>Left in Alabama</source><author>Michele Harmon</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 12, 2014 (Left in Alabama:http://www.leftinalabama.com Delivered by Newstex) First, let me start by defining "environmental racism." It occurs when one community generally a minority or impoverished community is disproportionately affected by industrial development and the pollution created by those developments. The community bears most of the risk, but receives little or no financial reward. Now allow me to give you a little background on the community known as Plateau/ Africatown. Plateau / Africatown community was settled by Africans who had been kidnapped from their homeleand and brought over to be sold as slaves on one of the last US Slave ships the "Coltilde" which arrived in Mobile Bay in the Autumn of 1859.
This ship was owned and operated by the Meaher brothers who were arrested and the people were abandoned on the banks of the Mobile River. The abandoned people decided to settle the area which we now know as Plateau/Africatown. Many of the decendants of those original African settlers still live in the community today and are quite proud of their community and it's historical designation. Throughout recent history this community has been plagued by industries like International Paper and others that have polluted their land and used it as an industrial dumping ground. One of the most well known places in Plateau/Africatown is the Mobile County Training School which is to my knowledge the oldest County Training School the entire state. The original school was built in 1880 and has served the educational needs of the community since it's founding. The MCTS Baseball field has now become ground zero for the latest case of environmental racism and this time, the company involved is Plains Southcap Pipeline company. Yes that is the same company that recently settled with Mobile Area Water Sewer System to place the toxic crude oil pipeline through the only approved source of clean drinking water of 250,000 people[1]. In1951 the MCTS leased a portion of their land to then Hess Oil company for a pipeline for a little more than $300 a year. Since then that lease and pipeline ownership was transferred to Plains SouthCap. In 2013 Plains announced that they would be replacing a portion of that pipeline which was outside the school yard and baseball field. The people of Africatown gathered several times to protest this new section of pipeline which is believed to be capable of carrying Tar sands crude to Ten Mile Terminal. Earlier this week, MEJAC held a meeting about the current pipeline issue and how to move forward. I will update as the story unfolds, but for now this is what I know and what is currently happening in the community. In a recent meeting at the school with Mobile County Superintendent Martha Peek it was revealed that the pipeline lease was renewed for the same amount as the original lease in 1951.When asked by a concerned citizen if the pipeline company had presented the school board with an emergency response plan Superintendent Peek replied NO. She stated that the school had it's own, but there was not one given to them by the Pipeline company and seemed as if it was no big deal. As a parent of children in public schools, if this were my children's school, I'd have been furious. First because the pipeline is so close to my child's school. Second because of the tiny amount of money the lease was renewed for. The third and probably the most important reason of all: they were not required to give the school and board an Emergency response plan for how they would proceed if there was a pipeline rupture. Here is where I feel the environmental racism and injustice comes into play even more. Remember the Meaher brothers I mentioned earlier in this piece ? The Meaher family still owns property in Plateau/ Africatown today. In fact, it is adjacent to the school property. The pipeline also crosses through their property and for their lease they were paid aproximately $100,000.00 ... The questions I pose and want to leave you with to ponder are as follows ...Why did a prominant white family recieve more money for their property than a Minority school where children's health is placed at risk daily by the chance of a crude oil pipeline rupturing outside their school?Why did the school board renew a lease for so little money allowing this pipeline company to basically place these children at risk for a little more than $300 a year? If this were happening in any community other than a minority or impoverished community would the school board have allowed this pipeline to proceed?I sincerly hope after you read this you take a minute and think about that as you pack your kids off to school in the morning . Could your child's school be the next one being placed in the path of a toxic crude oil pipeline? On a side note Plains did give one community memeber $25,000 in an what we all believe is an attempt to divide and conquer the community this move is straight out of the Big Oil playbook! [1]: http://www.leftinalabama.com/diary/10810/we-were-sold-out-plains-southcaps-pipeline-through-250000-citizens-drinking-water-supply

]]></text></news-item>