<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6776-BA33-A520-C116"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Polluters put up smog screen</title><source>Daily Dispatch (South Africa)</source><author>Sue Blaine</author><text><![CDATA[Air of unpreparedness follows power plants By THE Department of Environmental Affairs is considering Eskom's application to postpone air quality standards regulation for five years to which it is subject under environmental legislation it says.
While South Africa has not suffered the hazardous smog blankets that have affected China's tourism industry and fomented public discontent in the world's most populous nation the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research has shown that air quality across South Africa often exceeded the country's and the World Health Organisation's limits for aerosols. But state utility Eskom which is battling to keep the lights on across South Africa due to inadequate generating capacity and problems with coal supplies is not the only air polluter to have asked the department for a postponement. Others include the Natref refinery in Sasolburg owned by Sasol and Total ArcelorMittal SA Northam Platinum and Engen. Applications for the postponement of compliance with the standards which will commence next year have to be submitted to the department's national air quality officer by the end of this month. The department said it was legally required to consider all applications but could not guarantee "positive responses". The Centre for Environmental Rights in its submissions in opposition to Eskom's application argued that air pollution emissions from Eskom's coal-fired power plants were causing an estimated 2200 premature deaths per year due to exposure to fine particulate matter. The organisation which used research by Greenpeace International estimated the economic cost to South Africa at R30-billion a year including the premature deaths. Eskom had applied for postponements for 16 of its power stations 14 of which were coal-fired. They include the 4800MW Medupi station the first unit of which is expected to be commissioned at the end of the year. It has been fined more than R3-million for illegal activities since 2009 and has applied for the postponement of compliance to meet existing plant standards by April 1 next year and stricter new plant standards by April 1 2020. The other entities had made submissions that had the same theme. But Eskom had indicated its intention to apply for "rolling" postponements thereby in effect asking for complete exemption from certain standards. The postponement applications were coupled with applications for variations of the conditions of its licences to allow certain stations to emit more than the licences allow. It argued that the potential gains from compliance did not justify the costs. It calculated about R200-billion in capital costs before financing charges and about R6-billion a year in operational expenditure. - BDLive MURKY ACTIONS: The Department of Environmental Affairs is weighing an application by Eskom to postpone air quality standards regulation
]]></text></news-item>