<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="67AB-1D76-E6F0-28BD"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>F1 stepping into the great unknown; AUSTRALIAN GRAND PRIX Rule changes set to herald changing of guard on track Ecclestone's fate in court could shape sport's future</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Daniel Johnson</author><text><![CDATA[This could be a momentous year for Formula One but, for now, it is simply an unpredictable one. Even before a point has been scored, the first of which are up for grabs in Melbourne tomorrow, 2014 marks a new chapter in the sport's history. There is revolution on the track and the potential for seismic change off it.
The move from comparatively straightforward V8 engines to V6 hybrid power units (the change in terminology says it all), which harness energy both from braking and from the turbocharger, has already had a big impact. Not only are the new units vastly more complicated to operate - teams say the number of potential problems, as well as the time it takes to remedy them, has increased dramatically - they have already ushered in a changing of the guard.
The indications from pre-season are that Mercedes have stolen a march on the rest of the field, while Renault are some way behind, leaving Red Bull's position at the summit in doubt. After an awful 12 days of winter testing, the team appear to have recovered quickly, based on yesterday's evidence, although they admit they still have plenty to do to catch the Mercedes.
With drivers managing fuel much more closely, the early races may be difficult to follow, but the added uncertainty is a welcome relief from last season. As Jenson Button said last night: "There's so much interest in the sport right now, which is good. We've got to try to keep it that way. There are negatives, but the racing, especially on TV, should be great."
If fans understand and engage with the new formula, then the new direction will be hailed a success. If they do not, and are turned off by one engine supplier's dominance, Formula One may have to think again.
The elephant in the room away from the track, which is possibly of even greater significance than the rule changes this year, is the fate of Bernie Ecclestone. He has ruled F1 for four decades with his unique brand of deal making, and many are fearful of what a future without him would look like.
Aside from his 83 years, there is the small matter of a bribery trial in Munich. Although found not guilty by a High Court judge last month, he was branded an untruthful and unreliable witness. If he is found to have bribed a German banker when his trial concludes in September, it is dif-ficult to imagine Ecclestone carrying on, not only because of public pressure, but because Donald Mackenzie, chairman of CVC Capital Partners, Formula One's largest shareholder, said last November that Ecclestone would be fired if found guilty.
Even though the trial has been organised to suit Ecclestone's schedule - proceedings will take place on Tuesdays and Wednesdays, to allow him to be at races - many in F1 will have one eye on the German courtroom throughout the season.
And if he does leave the stage, possible successors range from the Red Bull team principal, Christian Horner, to former Sainsbury's chief executive Justin King, to a more committee-led structure. Whatever that future is, it could have enormous ramifications for how the sport is run, and where it travels to for races, largely because Ecclestone handles deals so personally.
It is also a year which could impact on the fortunes of some of the biggest names. Some drivers could claw themselves into the elite group - which, on form, includes Sebastian Vettel, Lewis Hamilton, Fernando Alonso and, possibly, Kimi Raikkonen - while some could slip out.
The battle between Hamilton and Nico Rosberg for supremacy at Mercedes will be fascinating. If paddock wisdom holds any truth, then it might be the German who adapts best to a formula which has shifted the balance in the direction of intelligence rather than raw speed; an idea which Hamilton firmly rebuffed this week.
Will Hamilton be remembered as a driver of immense natural talent and aggression, simply born in the wrong era? Or will he claim his second world title, six years on from his first, and finally take his place among the sport's greats?
For the teams, 2014 has already provoked the jumbling of the pecking order. Red Bull could be left with their hands tied by an uncompetitive engine. Meanwhile, after an apparently inspired switch from Renault to Mercedes power, Williams could make a long overdue return to the front, at least in the early part of the season before the inevitable development race gathers pace.
On the financial side, too, Jean Todt, the FIA president, is adamant a cost cap of some description will be agreed this year.
The scale of the change this season may be overplayed. But more than anything else, Formula One is unpredictable again.
What's new in Fl How the cars have changed
By Daniel Johnson
1 WEIGHT
The new engines, extra electrical power and larger batteries mean cars are significantly heavier - a minimum of 691kg, rather than 642kg.
Former F1 car designer Gary Anderson's analysis It is never a good thing to add weight to an F1 car: it takes more energy to stop on the brakes. I think the compromise is a little bit wrong. It is too near the mark. A heavier driver should never have to suffer and should be able to do the job. It seems that is the reason why Nico Hülkenberg has struggled to get a top, top drive, because he is one of the heavier drivers, and that is wrong.
2 FRONT WING AND NOSE
The front wing is 150mm narrower and the tip of the nose is lowered to 185mm, to try to improve safety in collisions.
Anderson's analysis A designer's job is look at the rules and say: 'How can I comply with them and come up with the best solution to get airflow under the car?' The majority have come up with an anteater-type style. The front wing and nose is the most critical area for directing the airflow through the rest of the car. Expect it to be the prime area for developments as the season progresses.
3 EXHAUST
In the past, teams directed exhaust gases onto the rear diffuser to improve downforce. Now a single exhaust pipe has fixed dimensions, as well as the angle at which it must exit the car.
Anderson's analysis The exhaust-blown diffusers were very good for traction. The traction, particularly for medium and slow-speed corners, will definitely not be as good this year. Once you take away downforce, you will always end up with drivers complaining.
4 ENGINE
Gone are the 2.4-litre V8 engines, replaced by 1.6-litre V6 turbos. The internal combustion engine itself produces around 600bhp, and has an rpm limit of 15,000 compared to 18,000 before. The turbocharger also returns.
Anderson's analysis The basic engine from Mercedes, to Renault, to Ferrari, should be very similar. But it is what you do with that electrical power which makes one engine company stand out from another. Without doubt, in the early races the engine or power unit is probably going to be the most important determining factor in performance, and reliability will be hugely significant.
5 ENERGY RECOVERY SYSTEMS
What makes the power units radically different from previous years is how they harvest wasted energy and use it to give an additional 160bhp for approximately 33 seconds per lap. There are two systems, the MGU-K, which harvests kinetic energy from braking in a similar way to KERS, and the MGU-H, which harvests heat from the turbocharger.
Anderson's analysis: How you use the energy harvested from the turbo will be massive, because it is effectively free power. You can use it at any point in time that you want, on top of what you have got from the engine. In my book, the drivers will not really know too much about it, and it is going to be down to how the teams map the engine.
6 FUEL
The teams are allowed only100kg of fuel, as opposed to around 160kg in 2013. The rate at which they can use the fuel is also limited: the rate has gone down to 100kg/hour from around 170kg/hour.
Anderson's analysis Fuel economy is now the name of the game. You could drive flat out at the beginning, and save more at the end, or vice versa, or you could drive consistently throughout. The teams will be analysing it lap by lap, but it will be an unknown for everybody.
7 TYRES
Pirelli had a torrid year in 2013, with constant complaints from drivers and teams, which reached their peak at Silverstone when there were several high-speed blowouts. This year, Pirelli say the tyres are more durable, particularly the rears, and will create fewer 'marbles'; debris which gathers off the racing line.
Anderson's analysis Pirelli have made the tyres a step harder, so it is a slightly more durable tyre. But having a stiffer compound is not always slower, and they seem to have achieved that. If there are fewer marbles it should make for more overtaking at the end of the race, because the racing line will be wider.
]]></text></news-item>