<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="67C8-0024-D896-D370"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Protesters to hold anti-fracking demo in Doncaster</title><source>Thorne and District Gazette</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Around thirty Green Party activists from around the Yorkshire and Humber region will take to the streets of Doncaster today to mark their opposition to drilling and fracking plans in the area.
Among the activists will be Green Party candidates for the upcoming European elections.
Andrew Cooper, the lead Green Party candidate for the region, will be leading the demonstration from Clock Corner at 11.30am.
Andrew said "We are in Doncaster to reinforce the strong opposition to fracking and other unconventional gas extraction planned in the area.
"There is already a great campaign being fought by local people, but we need elected politicians to stand up for local people against this dash for dirty gas."
Last month, protesters opposed to fracking staged a demonstration at a site earmaked for drilling.
Demonstrators gathered at Daneshill Energy Forest at Sutton-cum-Lound to protest at proposals put forward by Dart Energy - even though the firm is not considering fracking, which involves fracturing rock to release energy resources.
Pete Kennedy, spokesman for Frack Free South Yorkshire said: "We attended the demonstration against Dart Energy to send a strong message that risky unconventional techniques of gas extraction are not welcome.
Dart have been granted a Petroleum Exploration and Development Licence (PEDL) to extract coal-based methane from the ground.
According to campaigners, Dart are proposing to drain water from the coal seam at Daneshill by removing fluid and releasing trapped methane to be captured and used to generate energy.
Earlier this year a Dart spokeman said: "A vertical coal bed methane well may be drilled with the objective of extracting a core from the coals to enable lab testing of methane content."
"There are no current plans to drill a shale exploration well on the licence."
Fracking, short for hydraulic fracturing, was first used in the USA in 1947 and has since spread across the globe but has met with fierce crictism.
Opponents point to environmental risks, including contamination of ground water, depletion of fresh water, air and noise pollution, the migration of gases and hydraulic fracturing chemicals to the surface and even earthquakes.
]]></text></news-item>