<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="684D-A7ED-0157-FF7E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Fitch Publishes Sector Credit Factors for U.S. Utilities, Power and Gas Companies</title><source>Manufacturing Close-Up</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Fitch Ratings has published a sector-specific special report describing the credit factors the agency uses to analyze U.S. utilities, power and gas (UPG) companies.
Fitch's rating coverage of investor-owned UPG companies in the U.S. includes those with a wide range of risk profiles and business interests. These include both utilities with monopoly or market-dominant positions that are typically subject to tariff regulation and regulatory oversight of their service levels and terms of service, and companies that do not have a monopoly market position and are exposed to market competition. Finally, there are utility parent companies with varied holdings of companies engaged in regulated and competitive businesses.
UPG companies are evaluated considering various qualitative and quantitative credit factors, including but not limited to: regulatory environment, market and service territory, asset base and operations, commodity exposure, capitalization and leverage, financial flexibility, and liquidity.
In its new special report, Fitch has placed the various building blocks used to formulate its ratings within typical ranges in order to increase the transparency of its analysis. The report includes various median financial ratios by rating category, as well as a chart that demonstrates how key qualitative factors can impact a typical rating range.
Fitch's existing public ratings of approximately 180 UPG companies in the U.S. span the 'A' to 'C' rating categories. Regulated utilities regularly access the capital markets to fund their investment programs, and it is therefore important for them to maintain an efficient capital structure and minimize the cost of debt, which is normally commensurate with an investment-grade credit profile. The non-investment-grade entities are typically competitive generators that operate in deregulated markets or highly leveraged parent holding companies, or, in a limited number of cases, regulated utilities that are either constrained by parent ratings or highly leveraged themselves.
Additional information is available at 'fitchratings.com'.
Applicable Criteria and Related Research:
--Fitch Fundamentals Index - U.S. Index Trend Analysis - 4Q13 (January 2014)
--Recovery Ratings and Notching Criteria for Utilities (November 2013)
--Corporate Rating Methodology: Including Short-Term Ratings and Parent and Subsidiary Linkage (August 2013)
Applicable Criteria and Related Research: Rating U.S. Utilities, Power and Gas Companies (Sector Credit Factors)
Additional information is available at 'fitchratings.com'.
((Comments on this story may be sent to newsdesk@closeupmedia.com))
]]></text></news-item>