<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6877-51E8-54C5-FC5B"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Duke had direct line to regulators</title><source>The Virginian-Pilot(Norfolk, VA.)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[By Michael Biesecker and Mitch Weiss
The Associated Press
RALEIGH, N.C.
Internal emails at North Carolina's environmental agency suggest state regulators were coordinating with Duke Energy before intervening in efforts by groups trying to sue the company over groundwater pollution leeching from its coal ash dumps.
The emails were provided Thursday to The Associated Press by the Southern Environmental Law Center, which had filed notice in January 2013 of its intent to sue the nation's largest electricity company under the Clean Water Act.
Within days, the emails show, a Duke lobbyist contacted the Department of Environment and Natural Resources to set up a meeting. The emails suggest the company and regulators were in frequent contact, with a lawyer for Duke even advising the state on legal strategy on April 30.
At the time, lawyers for the Environmental Law Center were worried that Duke and state regulators would work out a deal without input from citizens groups. They told the state that the groups couldn't legally be blocked from participating.
But the emails show that Duke lawyer Charles Case tried to find a case that could be used to convince a judge otherwise.
An email with an attachment was forwarded by Special Deputy Attorney General Kathy Cooper to Lacy Presnell, the top lawyer at the environmental agency, on May 15. Cooper had been assigned to represent the state in the lawsuit.
"Mr. Presnell asked during our meeting for an example of participation by a intervenor on a non-party basis," Case wrote, adding that he looked forward to speaking with them.
On July 3, a transcript shows, Cooper went before Wake County Judge Paul Ridgeway and argued that the citizens groups should be excluded from the legal proceedings.
"They tried to keep us from being full parties in the case," said Frank Holleman, a senior attorney for the Law Center. "Duke is the lawbreaker. DENR is the law enforcement agency. They are supposed to be protecting the people. Instead, they are working with the lawbreaker to find a way to limit the participation of the citizens groups in the law enforcement proceedings in the way that will benefit the lawbreaker. It's astonishing."
The agency ultimately used its authority to intervene in the lawsuit, quickly negotiating a proposal in which the $50 billion company would pay a $99,100 fine to settle environmental violations but be under no requirement to clean up its pollution.
Environmentalists have derided the proposal as a "sweetheart deal" by compliant state regulators to shield Duke from far harsher and more expensive penalties the company would have likely faced had the citizens groups been allowed to move forward in federal court.
That proposed settlement was tabled last month after a massive spill from a Feb. 2 Duke dump in Eden that coated 70 miles of the Dan River in toxic gray sludge. Coal ash contains dangerous chemicals, including arsenic, lead and selenium.
Duke spokeswoman Paige Sheehan said Thursday the company wouldn't comment on the "content of any specific emails."
Federal prosecutors have launched a criminal investigation in the wake of the spill, issuing at least 23 grand jury subpoenas to Duke executives and state officials.
Democrats at the North Carolina legislature rolled out a nine-point proposal Thursday to dispose of and monitor coal ash now sitting in pits throughout the state, saying Duke and state officials have waited too long to address their environmental risk.
]]></text></news-item>