<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="688D-D94D-BC60-568F"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>A self-made man whose legacy will never be forgotten</title><source>Belfast Telegraph</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ith his eyewatering Wfortune estimated at more than £600m, Eddie Haughey was worth more than many a small nation, but Northern Ireland''s wealthiest individual still got the self-made man''s pleasure of sealing a deal which could save what were, to him, almost inconsequential sums of as little as £50.
"Yes, he loved a bargain" said one man who knew him. "Even in the smallest of transactions, he always enjoyed it if he could talk you down from the price you were asking."
That''s not, of course, to say that Eddie Haughey (or Lord Ballyedmond, as he became) was a skinflint. Indeed, he spared little on largesse, helping out charities and universities as well as funding the refurbishment of his old parish church just south of the border.
His lavish dinner parties at his fabulously appointed stately homes in England and Rostrevor became the stuff of legend, with the great and the good, the politicians and the prelates and the showbiz stars and society''s shapers on his guestlists.
The A-listers would regularly be flown in and out on Dr Haughey''s helicopter, or private jet, for weekends of what was regularly overthe-top over-indulgence in his estates, where horse-drawn carriages would ferry his dinner parties to game shoots, or even outdoor operatic performances of Carmen beside a waterfall.
One man who broke bread with him more than once said the opulence was staggering. "In Ballyedmond Castle''s grand ballroom there were even plates embossed with King Edward the Sixth or Seventh''s name. One fellow guest said she was almost afraid to eat off them.
"Everything was done immaculately and the guest list included politicians like Albert Reynolds and lords and ladies, who discovered extraordinary details which Eddie Haughey knew about his castles and their interiors. He even had books in the bedrooms to inform his guests about their surroundings."
The same man also flew in the Norbrook helicopter to England for soirees there. "The pilot was like something out of James Bond and we landed on the lawn at the start of what would be fabulous evenings with fabulous food and conviviality. Eddie could talk about anything to anyone.
He was always in his element as the host of his social gatherings."
" And as he mingled among his guests - sometimes up to 30 at a time - on such grand occasions, Eddie Haughey's mind must have wandered back to his humbler beginnings in Kilcurry, north of Dundalk in Co Louth in January 1944.
He started with nothing and worked for a time in a shop in Newry, but after leaving school, he followed the traditional emigrant route in the Sixties to America.
But he only stayed long enough to garner an insight into the veterinary pharmaceutical business, before he came home to set up his own firm in Newry.
He often told of how he began with a briefcase and a price list of pharmaceutical products, which he imported and sold on with his own labels on them, competing against the likes of Glaxo and ICI.
The upshot was the hugely successful Norbrook Laboratories, which Haughey said at the last count employed nearly 2,000 people, making it one of the biggest pharmaceutical companies in the world and bringing countless millions to help revive the economy of south Down and south Armagh in the process.
But, as he helped others prosper, he fully enjoyed the fruits of his - and their - labour.
His pride and joy was his palatial home in the old Ballyedmond Castle on the outskirts of Rostrevor, which had been designed by the architect Sir Charles Lanyon and which had been operating as a luxury hotel before it became a victim of the Troubles, destroyed by firebombs in 1979.
Dr Haughey set about rebuilding the 19th century mansion, which enjoys magnificent views over Carlingford Lough with a relish and an attention to detail which stunned the architects and interior designers.
He famously bought the iconic Sicilian marble staircase from the old Robinson and Cleaver''s department store in the centre of Belfast and made it the centrepiece of his new home.
The extensive Ballyedmond grounds were another passion for the businessman, who recently developed an orangery in the estate.
In 1994, Dr Haughey also bought and restored Corby Castle - a sister castle to Castle Howard, which was used for the filming of Brideshead Revisited - and Gillingham Hall in Norfolk, as well as a six-storey £12m townhouse in Belgrave Square in London.
He also set up an air transport company and once owned Carlisle airport. But his business and property interests were worldwide. He owned land in Uganda and several islands on Lake Victoria. He also served as an honorary counsel to Chile in South America. But DrHaughey wasn''t all smiles and saccharin. He was known as someone who could be stubborn and ruthless, a man who could be quick to the boil and slow to simmer down.
Disputes about the grounds and even the very wall around Ballyedmond brought out the litigious side of Eddie Haughey as he went to the High Court to protect rights of way on his land and to seek redress for perceived injustices against him - including allegations of libel.
Friends said he wouldn''t shy away from a courtroom battle, even if his lawyers cautioned him against it. Indeed, he was taking legal action about possible safety defects against the manufacturers of the helicopter which crashed, killing him.
"Once he got his teeth into something, he never gave up," said one legal source. But the industrialist was also on the receiving end of writs.
A former housekeeper, Linda Heaton, was awarded £7,000 compensation against him in 2003 after she won her claim for unfair dismissal from her job at Corby Castle in the heart of Cumbria.
She said her once-cordial relationship with Eddie Haughey disintegrated after he complained that the bedrooms for guests at a shooting party hadn''t been cleaned properly and even questioned how often his underpants were washed.
Mrs Heaton said her choice of cutlery was also questioned and she claimed her employer - who was represented by his solicitor wife, Mary - reduced her to tears over a missing gold menu holder, which later turned up at Ballyedmond.
The tribunal rejected claims that Dr Haughey had bullied and intimidated staff, however, saying he liked to have things done to a high standard.
Former Belfast Telegraph Editor Ed Curran knew the sharp end of Dr Haughey''s tongue after he took umbrage at an article in the newspaper.
But they agreed to disagree and they got to know each other quite well.
Mr Curran said: "He was a man who was incredibly driven - not only by his business, but also in his personal life. He had a capacity to grasp a whole range of matters and keep many, many balls in the air at the same time."
Dr Haughey rarely gave interviews to the media. But he would sometimes send a helicopter to collect the journalists who were to question him. Some said it was a move to impress; others said he was trying to intimidate his interrogators.
A former member of the Irish Senate, he took the title of Baron Ballyedmond when he was ennobled by the former Unionist leader David Trimble, but he later switched to sit in the House of Lords with the Conservatives, to whom he donated large sums of money.
Former Stormont Minister John Taylor - now Lord Kilclooney - was a close friend, who was an occasional, but always uncomfortable, fellow-flier with him on his helicopter and saw him in the House of Lords only last week.
He said he didn''t just bring jobs to Newry, but also promoted the area and pushed its bid to become a city.
Lord Ballyedmond didn''t exactly overtax the Upper House Hansard writers. His maiden speech, in March 2005, was on plans to introduce identity cards in the UK and, a year later, he opposed a Bill about helping terminally ill people to die.
He said: "My view is that to legalise assisted suicide is an attempt to regulate death and to remove the very aspects that in life we fight to protect."
But quietly, behind the scenes, he worked hard as an ambassador for Northern Ireland, recently hosting a reception in the House of Lords in a bid to attract new companies to the province.
That Dr Haughey should die near one of his stately homes, Gillingham Hall, while flying onboard on one of the outwardly displays of his immense wealth was, in its own way, a tragic irony - the £10m two-engined Agusta Westland AW139 helicopter had been adapted by Lord Ballyedmond to transport him and his associates in luxury.
Residents in Rostrevor barely gave a second look to the distinctive helicopter coming and going from Ballyedmond, as Haughey used it to travel across the Irish Sea with the same regularity that they hopped on a bus. Tragically, another Norbrook helicopter crashed in 1996, killing three pilots.
But, in Newry, there''s hardly anyone who hasn''t a Haughey story to tell.
The begrudgers said he was a hard man to work for. His admirers countered that he was a fair boss, whose contribution to Newry simply couldn''t be underestimated.
"If you got your head down and did your work there were no problems.
You knew your future was assured," said one businessman.
The story is told of one girl who got her head down - to sleep at her workpost - and got a rude awakening from DrHaughey as he happened to walk through the Norbrook plant.
She expected the sack, but escaped with a telling off. She didn''t doze off again.
The hope now in Newry, which has been left stunned by news of the Norf olk tragedy, is that Norbrook willgo on in spite of its pioneer''s passing with his son, James Haughey, fully taking up the reins of the family business.
The Baron will be a hard act to follow. Business associates said Lord Ballyedmond''s enthusiasm and energy were indefatigable. One said: "He was a great networker, who used his contacts with a fervour. He was an astonishing worker, who took great pride in how he''d built up his business.
"Certainly he could be incredibly difficult, but he could also be unbelievably charming and he never lost that broad border accent of his, no matter whose company he found himself in."
Eddie Haughey married his wife Mary in 1973 and they had two sons and a daughter, Caroline.
Downpatrick photographer Bobbie Hanvey took Caroline''s wedding pictures.
He said: "I first got to know Eddie Haughey after I approached him to do his portrait. He was a wonderful man. I went to Ballyedmond, where I had shot wedding pictures in the days when it was a hotel and the place looked beautiful.
"He was a very confident and astute man all round. He even knew what sort of photograph he wanted. But he seemed to like what I did and he asked me to take his daughter''s wedding pictures in England."
In Newry, yesterday they lowered the company flags fluttering above the Norbrook plants as the workers and city remembered the businessman whose legacy will, quite simply, never be forgotten.
A-listers were flown in on his private jet for weekends
]]></text></news-item>