<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6897-BD49-E879-6D37"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Editorial: In the Senate vs. CIA, the president can't wait</title><source>St. Louis Post-Dispatch (Missouri)</source><author> By the Editorial Board </author><text><![CDATA[With his usual eerie outward detachment, President Barack Obama has stepped back from the furor surrounding U.S. intelligence agencies. On this, as on other issues, the president ignores the sound-bite wars on cable news. He plays the long game, preferring to patiently let matters sort themselves out before moving in with a scalpel rather than a cleaver.
There is much to be said for approaching public policy like a Jedi knight; knowing when not to employ the Force is as important as knowing when to use it. But it's now become apparent that the National Security Agency and the Central Intelligence Agency have assumed vast powers for themselves never contemplated by Congress and almost certainly not countenanced in the law. Mr. Obama must get them under control.
The United States has been here before. In 1975, in the wake of the Watergate affair, the Senate formed the Select Committee to Study Governmental Operations with Respect to Intelligence Activities. Clearly this awkward name would not do; it quickly became known as the Church Committee, after its chairman, Sen. Frank Church, D-Idaho.
The committee was determined to rein in abuses by the intelligence agencies during the administrations of Presidents Lyndon B. Johnson and Richard M. Nixon. These included spying on Americans, including the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.; attempts to involve the FBI and CIA in the Watergate coverup; and covert attempts by the CIA to topple foreign governments.
The committee's reports were damning. Congress put in place several measures to prevent abuses from recurring. Select Committees on Intelligence were made permanent. And a new institution called the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court was created to provide proper judicial oversight over intelligence gathering.
But politicians, however long-lived, are temporary. Bureaucracies are permanent. As years and decades passed, the espiocrats arrogated ever more power. The FISA court became a rubber stamp. The congressional oversight committees became victims of bureaucratic capture. Its members tended to adopt the values of the agencies they were overseeing.
All of this makes what happened last week remarkable and suggests why Mr. Obama should act quickly. Sen. Dianne Feinstein, D-Calif., who as chairman of the Senate Intelligence Committee since 2009 has been a devout believer in whatever the agencies have told her, turned on the CIA like the watchdog she should have been all along.
After defending the NSA's vast monitoring program that sweeps up information on American citizens and foreign allies in an unrestrained search for anything resembling a terrorist, Ms. Feinstein decided the CIA had gone too far by spying on staff members of her committee.
In a cold, stark speech on the Senate floor Tuesday, Ms. Feinstein said, "I have grave concerns that the CIA's search may well have violated the separation of powers principle embodied in the United States Constitution, including the speech and debate clause. It may have undermined the constitutional framework essential to effective congressional oversight of intelligence activities or any other government function."
Since 2009, the committee staff, having been given access to CIA-linked computers at a facility in northern Virginia, had been culling more than 6 million pages of documents related to the Bush administration's "enhanced interrogation" program of suspected terrorists captured in the early days of the wars in Afghanistan and Iraq. Eventually the staff produced a 6,300-page report that apparently details significant torture and abuse of prisoners.
Among the documents the staffers found in 2010 was something called the "Internal Panetta Review," a summary done by the agency for then-director Leon Panetta. The review "documented at least some of the very same troubling matters already uncovered by the committee staff, which is not surprising in that they were looking at the same information," Ms. Feinstein said.
At some point, she said, the Panetta review - along with other documents the staff had found - disappeared from the computers the Senate staff was using. "These were documents provided by the executive branch pursuant to an authorized congressional oversight investigation," Ms. Feinstein said.
CIA Director John Brennan, who worked for the agency when the torture program was underway, and Robert Eatinger, the agency's acting general counsel, whose name appears in the Senate staff report 1,600 times, are claiming, in effect, that the Senate spied on the spies. The CIA's inspector general has asked the Justice Department to open an investigation into how the staff got secret documents.
For sheer effrontery, this would be hard to top. Having dumped 6.2 million pages of documents onto computers they gave to the Senate, the CIA is now complaining that somehow it's a crime that the Senate found that some of the documents were incriminating, including one (the Panetta review) in which the CIA apparently reached the same conclusion as the Senate.
It's bizarre: One unit of the executive branch is asking a second executive branch unit to investigate the legislative branch for finding evidence, with which it agrees, that it did things it shouldn't have done.
None of this is being done in furtherance of the CIA's intelligence-gathering mission. Mr. Obama reined in the CIA's detainee interrogation program in 2009 and gave the people who were involved a pass from prosecution. He was taking, as always, the long view.
But the CIA doesn't want to be accountable to anyone, not even the United States Senate. It's hiding secrets to cover its own grievous mistakes. It should change its name to the CYA.
Mr. Obama waited to take action on the NSA's abuses until a presidential advisory board gave him cover. He says he's waiting on the CIA abuses now because the matter is under investigation - as it has been for five years. Rep. James Sensenbrenner, R-Wis., of all people, the man who wrote the Patriot Act that the Bush administration used for cover in its war on terror abuses, is accusing the Obama administration of being "almost Nixonian."
If he waits much longer, the president will have Congress in revolt and a full-blown constitutional crisis on his hands. That's a lot to handle, even for a Jedi knight.
]]></text></news-item>