<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="68B9-8356-F913-3EB5"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Lawsuit Filed Against Lockout Function in Keurig 2.0 Brewers</title><source>Single Serve Coffee</source><author>Jay Brewer</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 14, 2014 (Single Serve Coffee:http://www.singleservecoffee.com Delivered by Newstex) After successfully winning an appeal to be able to use it's own brand of single cups for Keurig brewers, Rogers Family Company has filed a lawsuit hoping to ensure Keurig 2.0 brewers will be able to use non-licensed K-Cups and not only those with the Keurig brewed license.
In the suit which will seek damages as determined by the trial, The Rogers family alleges that Keurig has used its monopoly power in the single-serve coffee brewer and coffee pod markets to require its distribution partners to enter into exclusive anticompetitive agreements designed to maintain Keurig's monopoly power by excluding competition. In addition, Keurig has announced plans to launch a new line in 2014 of Single-Serve Brewers - Keurig 2.0 - that Keurig has stated will contain lockout technology to prevent Keurig 2.0 brewers from functioning with competitors' coffee pod products. According to Keurig, the Keurig 2.0 brewers would replace its existing lines of Keurig brewers that function with competing coffee pod products. It seems another lawsuit is in order if Rogers and other companies are to be able to use the Keurig brewers to brew their K-Cups. We would imagine some non-Keurig K-Cup brewers are also on the horizon. Given the expiration of the patents for Keurig K-Cups, it's interesting to see how Keurig Green Mountain will fair this year as they try and launch Keurig 2.0. At Rogers Family Co. Files Lawsuit Against Keurig Green Mountain, Inc.[1]. [1]: http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/rogers-family-co-files-lawsuit-against-keurig-green-mountain-inc-for-alleged-anti-competitive-single-serve-coffee-market-conduct-that-rogers-believes-has-harmed-consumers-250209461.html

]]></text></news-item>