<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="68CF-80E0-DC83-D2F7"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Telco industry will never make broadband widely available</title><source>New Europe</source><author>suman</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 16, 2014 (New Europe:http://neurope.eu Delivered by Newstex) by Christian Engstrom[1] The Telco industry has worked diligently to make itself synonymous with the internet service provider industry, in a strategic effort dating back over a decade.
From the deceptive renaming of 'IT' to 'ICT' in order to include the Telco industry, via the buyout of all small ISPs to consolidate power with the old national Telco monopolies, all is part of a regulatory capture to prevent the Internet. The telephony industry is obsolete. It has no further value proposition to the market. It tries to charge me ten cents per minute for a 9,600 bits-per-second connection when I have an always-on 100,000,000 bits-per-second connection at a flat rate. In addition, the telephony connection can only be used for a low-grade voice application, whereas my hundred megabits are general-purpose. In short, the Telco industry has no value proposition whatsoever. The problem is that the Telco industry understands this, that their industry is dead in the water in the face of the internet, and has therefore worked diligently to prevent the Internet from reaching critical household mass. They have done this both in terms of preventing bandwidths where its cash cow - voice calls - are threatened as a concept, and by outright sabotaging voice applications such as Skype in their networks. The old national Telco monopolies see it as their duty to protect their old voice call cash cow, and force people to use it if they are also using the underlying data services. This is the kind of behaviour we normally drag into court for illegal anticompetitive behaviour. This tragedy started in the late 1990s as the old national Telco monopolies, usually privatized to some degree, bought all the small mom-and-pop ISPs before they had grown to a major threat. The old national monopolies understood perfectly what was about to happen. On one of the few markets where this didn't fully succeed, in Sweden, apartments were fibered with 100 megabits per second full-duplex as early as 1999 - fifteen years ago. That's what could have been in all of Europe, fifteen years ago. Instead, in most other markets and member states, the Telco industry managed a regulatory capture to prevent the future's most critical infrastructure from taking hold and threatening their previous, now obsolete, business. The Telco industry has pulled a number of stunts toward legislators in trying to convince legislators they will provide bandwidth for households, when in reality, there are not and were never any such plans. They are, and have been, stalling for time. There is no intention whatsoever to eliminate their obsolete industry by providing modern communications lines to everybody. This is obvious to anybody who sees the Telco industry's long-term strategic incentive, and how it goes completely counter to the public interest. In the United States, studies have arrived at the breath-taking observation that Telco's who were given billions of US dollars to roll out household broadband basically took the money and did nothing. This comes as a surprise to absolutely nobody who understands either the Internet or strategic corporate management. The Cable TV industry is in a similar position - the concept of high-bandwidth household connectivity will obliterate their entire business model, which is essentially the ability to send video streams into homes using highly specialized equipment. If you have generalized equipment and connections that can do this much better and cheaper, the whole industry becomes obsolete overnight. Therefore, 'high-speed DSL' is a contradiction in terms used only by the same Cable TV industry. To sum up, if we want high-speed competitive broadband in Europe, it needs to come from small independent providers that don't have the luggage of the old Telco monopolies or cable TV companies. Those old monopolies will try every trick in the book attempting to avoid the already-evident obsoleting. What we need is municipal household fibre for Europe, as important as water and electricity. We need municipal Wi-Fi wherever there is street lighting. And we specifically need that to be provided by an actor who doesn't have old luggage to protect on their balance sheet. The Telco industry's continued entrusting with internet infrastructure goes completely counter to the public interest. [1]: http://www.neurope.eu/author/christian-engstrom

]]></text></news-item>