<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6916-A905-44E7-1BA2"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>2 years on, no takers for victim compensation fund scheme</title><source>Hindustan Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Jalandhar, March 16 -- Even two years after its notification, the victim compensation fund scheme has failed to find takers in the city.
Officials blame the lack of publicity and awareness among people about the benefits of the scheme which the government notified in December 2011.
With no response from people, the District Legal Services Authority (DLSA) has decided to install hoardings and banners at public places to sensitise people to the scheme.
The Authority also held a meeting with members and lawyers a few days ago to make people aware of this so that they could make maximum use of the scheme.
The state government last year had even increased the compensation for many crime victims like that of rape, road accident, murder and others, but the DLSA is yet to get any application.
The scheme offers ex gratia from Rs. 40,000 to Rs. 4 lakh to crime victims under Section 357-A of the CrPC in which anyone who has become a victim of a violent crime can approach the DLSA for compensation.
Under Section 357-A, the victims or their dependents will be awarded compensation either on the recommendation of the court or on the application given by such victims or their dependents to the DLSA formed in each district of the state.
In Jalandhar, a committee comprising district and sessions judge Raj Shekhar Attari, chief judicial magistrate Tejinderbir Singh and a social worker has been formed to decide the compensation amount.
Under this scheme, Rs. 4 lakh in compensation will be awarded for a case of rape with murder, Rs. 3 lakh for rape, acid attack (disfigurement of face), Rs. 1 lakh for loss of life and Rs. 50,000 will be given to those who have suffered agony in case of human trafficking.
Speaking to HT, chief judicial magistrate, DLSA secretary, Tejinderbir Singh said that due to lack of awareness among victims or their dependents about the scheme, the DLSA had not received any application.
He said Section 357-A of the CrPC Act enabled legal services authorities to recommend payment of compensation to victims or their dependents.
Tejinderbir said only those who had not received any compensation from the government or an insurance company for the loss or injury, and those whose loss or injury had substantially affected their family income, where the accused had not been traced or identified, would be compensated.
"We intend to place information boards at various sites such as bus stand, civil hospital and other places to create awareness," Tejinderbir said.
The DLSA contact number is 0181-2235 775 and the toll-free number is 1968.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Hindustan Times. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>