<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="69BB-E987-2F33-6CC2"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>BRIEFS</title><source>Sydney Morning Herald (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Sydney locked in for Lego sequel
The sequel to The Lego Movie, the animated film that has become a smash hit around the world in recent weeks, is to be shot in Sydney. Newly announced director Chris McKay said that he will return to Animal Logic, the Fox Studios animation studio where the first movie was made for Warner Bros. "I'm super-psyched to come back," McKay said from LA. "It's such a neat place and Grant Freckelton, the production designer, I'd follow that guy to the end of the earth." It is scheduled for release in 2017.
Rudd tipped to chase UN top role
Kevin Rudd has his eye on the top job at the United Nations, according to a rumour heard both in diplomatic circles in Washington and by staff of Australia's UN mission in New York. The former prime minister has accepted a research role at Harvard University in Boston, leaving him with ample time to travel to New York to lobby for the secretary-general's post, currently held by Ban Ki-moon of South Korea, who began his second five-year term in mid-2011. The secretary-general is appointed by a vote of the UN's General Assembly upon the recommendation of the Security Council, of which Australia is a currently a member.
Satos rejects coal seam gas ban push
Satos has dismissed shareholder demands for an immediate end to its coal seam gas project in the Pilliga, saying they are being led by "extremist activist groups". Shareholders on Friday presented Satos with a resolution to be voted on at the company's annual general meeting in May, warning of "ongoing reputational, regulatory and investment risks" associated with its Narrabri Gas Project. Fairfax Media revealed last week leaking waste water from a Satos site had raised uranium levels in groundwater to 20 times higher than safe drinking standards. Satos said its testing showed the contamination would not affect aquifers.
News Review - Page 36
]]></text></news-item>