<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="69E3-3203-DC52-2CE2"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>EPA starts designing East Fishkill water fix</title><source>Poughkeepsie Journal (New York)</source><author>By, John Ferro</author><text><![CDATA[Darryl Bautista/Poughkeepsie Journal file
The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency is proceeding with the design of a system that would bring clean drinking water to the only federal Superfund site in Dutchess County still lacking a permanent fix.
The EPA held a kickoff meeting Wednesday with local, state and federal officials to advance the design of a municipal water system for the Hopewell Precision Superfund site in the Town of East Fishkill. The design work marks the first steps in years toward a specific remedy for groundwater contamination discovered more than a decade ago.
"Things have gelled," said Doug Garbarini, chief of the EPA's remediation branch for New York. "We have a source, and we have a team working on it."
The goal, the agency said, is to present the project to a review board late this year or early next year. That panel would decide whether to fund - or put off - the system's construction.
"These are concrete steps that point in the direction of a permanent solution supported by federal funds that will make the residents happy," said U.S. Rep. Sean Patrick Maloney, D-Cold Spring, who added that he has been in contact with Judith Enck, the EPA's local administrator. "The people of Hopewell have waited far too long for this to get fixed, and I will not rest until we have a solution that works."
At the earliest, construction would begin in late 2015, the EPA said.
Some 250 properties have wells contaminated with unsafe levels of trichloroethene, or TCE, and trichloroethane, or TCA. The contamination occurred when chemical waste products were dumped onto the ground at Hopewell Precision Inc. on Ryan Drive.
The decision to proceed with a municipal system was prompted by feedback the EPA received from residents at a public meeting in January, the first such meeting in four years.
At the suggestion of some residents, the EPA last year investigated drilling deeper wells at the affected properties, a cheaper and potentially quicker option. But at the January meeting, EPA officials expressed concerns - and residents agreed - that the deeper wells might not provide the same long-term assurances that piping in clean water from another source would.
Identifying that source, long a stumbling block at the Hopewell Precision site, was accomplished when East Fishkill in 2012 purchased property with a plentiful groundwater supply. The property is across the street from town hall.
Some residents have expressed concern that as the process dragged on, other parts of town would tap into - and perhaps deplete - the new supply. But East Fishkill Supervisor John Hickman said the town continues to factor Hopewell Precision's needs into its plans.
"In all of our models, it has always been included," Hickman said.
Hickman said he was encouraged by Wednesday's meeting.
"There was a much more positive tone with the EPA," he said.
The process of finding and then connecting a source has gone through fits and starts since the problem became widely apparent in 2003.
And concerns remain about funding. Federal funding for Superfund cleanups has dwindled consistently for more than 20 years.
Whether Hopewell Precision will get a piece of the Superfund pie likely will depend on a review by the EPA's National Risk-Based Priority Panel. The panel determines which Superfund sites get available funding each year.
The panel weighs the population size of the site, the mobility of the contaminant, the toxicity and any threats to other environmental concerns such as endangered species.
It also considers what it calls "high profile" projects that could be highlighted by top officials from the agency's 10 regions.
John Ferro: 845-437-4816; jferro@poughkeepsiejournal.com
jferro@poughkeepsiejournal.com; Twitter: @PoJoEnviro
]]></text></news-item>