<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6A5D-A555-F879-CE2A"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Riverbend coal-ash removal plan to go before Charlotte City Council on March 24</title><source>Charlotte Business Journal</source><author>Susan Stabley</author><text><![CDATA[A proposal to move 4 million tons of coal ash from the shuttered Riverbend Steam Station to property at Charlotte Douglas International Airport will go before Charlotte City Council members at a dinner workshop March 24.
Duke Energy (NYSE:DUK) is in talks with the city to remove the ash waste from a pair of unlined basins at the retired power plant. Coal ash ponds are waste lagoons that hold the powdery residue of coal-fired electrical generation in a liquid slurry.
The&nbsp; proposal would move the ash from Riverbend to be used as fill material at the airport, where expansion construction is under way.The Charlotte energy giant is working with Louisville, Ky.-based Charah Inc. on reuse options for the coal ash, and on permanent storage of the ash.&nbsp;
The ash would be "encapsulated" in engineered areas that are "fully-lined," according to a letter Duke sent to city officials. The fill areas would be multi-layered and include a high-density polyethylene flexible membrane liner that's 10 times thicker than a typical plastic tarp. The areas would then be capped with six feet of soil to allow for future development.
The exact location of where the ash would be stored and reused on the airport's 6,000 acres hasn't been determined, says Jack Christine, deputy aviation director. The airport is starting the process of looking at what kinds of permitting and environmental studies may be needed if the City Council signs off on the plan. That also includes updating the Federal Aviation Administration on the proposal.
City Council members&nbsp; have raised concerns about the waste lagoons in the wake of the Feb. 2 coal ash spill in the Dan River as well as back-to-back chemical spills that disrupted local wastewater treatment plants. Riverbend's 71 acres of coal ash ponds are a few miles upstream from Mountain Island Lake, the source of about 80 percent of the area's drinking water.
It appears Duke's proposal would clear out the coal ash now stored at Riverbend. Catawba Riverkeeper Sam Perkins says his organization has estimated the ponds contain about 3.2 million tons of material from the closed plant in Gaston County, plus a mound identified as an ash pile.
City officials say they have invited the Catawba riverkeeper to speak at the March 24 meeting, along with officials from Duke Energy and Charrah, which provides ash-management services to the coal-fired electric utility industry. The company is contracting for a similar project for coal ash reuse at the Asheville Regional Airport.
The idea of moving coal ash to an airport site from Riverbend was first proposed in a pitch to airport officials last summer, says Christine, the deputy aviation director. But he says there had been no follow-up to the suggestion until last week, when Duke and Charah officials approached the city.
Using the ash as fill at the airport could save the city the expense of paying for dirt for that use. Coal ash, because it is not regulated as a hazardous material, has been used in roadbeds and in cement and concrete products. Moving and using the ash to the airport also could create 100 jobs during the project, based on Charah's work in Asheville.
But city officials stress this is still just a proposal and that many questions remain.
Assistant City Manager Hyong Yi says Charlotte officials will begin conversations with a swath of stakeholders, including residents, regulators and&nbsp;Mecklenburg County.
Charlotte's energy and sustainability manager, Rob Phocas, says the city will need to determine the potential impact of the ash removal, studying details such as how the material will be transported from Rivebend in trucks covered with tarp. Phocas plans to visit Charah's project at the Asheville airport and see how that work may be applied to the proposal in Charlotte.
Charlotte-Mecklenburg Utilities Director Barry Gullet says his department will seek to ensure the Catawba River remains protected during any digging of coal ash at Riverbend.
"My concern is that the water supply is protected," Gullet says, adding that CMUD hasn't had any issues with ash ponds in the past as it affects the quality of the area's drinking water.
Gullet, Phocas and council members John Autry and Ed Driggs toured Riverbend earlier this month, before Duke proposed the new plan for moving the ash to the airport.
The Riverbend proposal is one of several initiatives outlined by Duke CEO Lynn Good in a letter to N.C. regulators in response to questions on how the&nbsp;company will manage its coal ash ponds.
"Work will begin immediately upon securing the appropriate fill solution or landfill location and any necessary permits, with an expected completion thereafter within 48-54 months," Good's letter states in regard to Riverbend.
However, officials with N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources say they&nbsp;are dissatisfied with Duke's response and will push the company for more details on its cleanup plans.
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Charlotte Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>