<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6AD5-C92C-0B72-5B65"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>SO WHO IS RUNNING OUR STATE?</title><source>Sunday Times (Perth, Australia)</source><author>KATIE ROBERTSON</author><text><![CDATA[Future planning compromised as bureaucrats left leaderless THE vacuum at the top of WA's public service is now crippling almost every arm of the State Government.
More than a dozen vital departments and commissions are without a permanent boss - affecting areas ranging from the state's finances to health, planning and the arts.
Unions and the Opposition are warning that the "extraordinary" number of senior vacancies is compromising future planning and has left many of the state's 150,000 public servants without direction.
The Barnett Government is searching for six directors-general, three commissioners, a chief scientist and an under-treasurer.
Two other senior jobs - heads of the Department of Child Protection and Family Support and the Corruption and Crime Commission - will also be vacant soon.
There could hardly be a worse time for all this, with the Barnett Government still reeling from the resignation of Troy Buswell as treasurer.
The role of Health Department boss, which comes with a $600,000 a year salary, has been vacant since Kim Snowball stepped down a year ago.
Premier Colin Barnett put the search for his replacement on hold last year, after a $122,000 recruitment drive proved fruitless.
Australian Medical Association WA president Richard Choong said that while acting director-general Bryant Stokes was doing a great job, the Government needed to find a full-time replacement urgently.
"The position is one of the most important in our state public service," Dr Choong said.
"It is vital that the very best person be found for this key role and that they be ready to seamlessly take over the reins from Professor Stokes." Opposition Leader Mark McGowan said the lack of permanent senior bureaucrats proved there was dysfunction "at the heart of Government".
"It shows a lackadaisical attitude towards these important positions, because I think they need to be filled with urgency," he said.
This week, Mr Barnett was pressed in Parliament about the vacant position of chief scientist. He said he purposely left a "period of time" between appoint-ments.
But Mr McGowan said many of the vacant positions have been empty for months and in some cases years.
"To have firmness of direction and authority in decision- making you need to have a permanent appointee," he said. "Acting appointees don't have that authority." Mr McGowan said he would expect the recruitment process for the senior bureaucrats would take about three months.
Community and Public Sector Union/Civil Services Association WA secretary Toni Walkington said the public deserved to know why there were delays in filling jobs.
"They are all critical positions that must be filled to ensure the government agencies run properly and have direction," she said.
Ms Walkington said the Children's, Equal Opportunity and Corruption and Crime commissions needed permanent people in place to maintain their independence.
A spokeswoman for Mr Barnett said there was "nothing exceptional" about the number of chief executive vacancies and app-ointments in several positions would be announced soon. "The Government is satisfied the vacancies aren't having an impact on public sector operations," she said.Editorial Page 64
]]></text></news-item>