<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6B4C-2BE0-D38A-FD1C"><date>2014-03-09</date><title>Make cheaper HIV/AIDS drugs available to all</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Millions of people die in developing countries every year because they cannot get the medicines they need to treat illnesses like HIV/AIDS. In sub-Saharan Africa alone, where grandmothers are raising millions of vulnerable children who have been orphaned by AIDS, there are about 240,000 new HIV infections among children every year, but only about one-third of them will receive the treatment they need. Medicines are a luxury beyond their reach.
Provisions in a proposed trade agreement, the Trans Pacific Partnership (TPP), being negotiated now by 12 countries around the Pacific Rim, will see these numbers climb even higher, as a result of more stringent patent protection for big pharmaceutical companies.
How do we know this? It is not because our government, which seems eager to bring the deal to a conclusion, is consulting Canadians about what is at stake in a trade agreement that will affect three-quarters of a billion people around the world. We know this because leaked documents have allowed us to peek behind the curtain into the secret trade talks.
The intellectual property chapter is most worrying for Canadian grandmothers who are members of the Grandmothers Advocacy Network. (We work here in Canada to advocate for changes in programs and policies that will improve the conditions of life for African grandmothers and their communities.)
Our peek behind the curtain has revealed the U.S. is pushing to extend intellectual property protection that would give pharmaceutical companies even longer monopolies on brand-name drugs. Current proposals would extend patent terms beyond 20 years, impose stricter rules on data exclusivity and impede legitimate trade in generic medicines. Longer monopolies by drug companies will stop or delay generic manufacturers from making cheaper drugs available to the developing world.
Médicins sans Frontières (MSF) has said that the TPP could become "the most harmful trade pact ever for access to medicines in developing countries." This will have a catastrophic effect on countries where the need for affordable medicines is acute.
And prices for prescription drugs in Canada could also be affected if patent protections are lengthened and our ability to access generic drugs is delayed.
Negotiations are being led and dominated by the U.S. in what Lawrence Herman in the Financial Post called the "biggest floating trade game on the planet."
While negotiators would probably prefer that Canadians "pay no attention to the man behind the curtain," a trade deal of this proportion, which will have implications not only for public health, but also for the environment and other regulatory protections we enjoy, ought to be subject to debate and scrutiny by our elected representatives and by civil society before it is signed.
Canada has been a contributor to the Global Fund to Fight AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria and recently increased its contribution to this important mechanism for tackling these preventable diseases.
Those dollars will go much further if affordable, generic drugs are available.
We have recently written to Prime Minister Stephen Harper, imploring him to make sure we are not complicit in preventing those most in need from receiving life-saving medicines. Let's hope he instructs negotiators not to give in to pressure from the U.S. and big pharma.
Marilyn Coolen and Pat Evans are co-chairs of the Grandmothers Advocacy Network. www.grandmothersadvocacy.org( http://www.grandmothersadvocacy.org )
© Copyright (c) The Ottawa Citizen
]]></text></news-item>