<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6C11-3590-2802-6DFB"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Child sex sting extends north; U.S. man's online investigation leads Quebec police to arrest Maniwaki resident</title><source>Ottawa Citizen</source><author>Meghan Hurley, Ottawa Citizen</author><text><![CDATA[When police announced a child-luring arrest in Maniwaki, north of Gatineau, this week, they didn't initially make any mention of Jason Weis.
But the chain of events that led to the arrest began last year with Weis and the work he does with his Oklahoma organization The Demand Project.
Since January 2013, Weis and his wife, Kristin, have run the project to combat child sexual exploitation.
Weis said he was on his computer on Yahoo chat last year, posing as a 14-year-old girl, when a random man began to message him. The man engaged in a few sexually explicit conversations before he disappeared from Yahoo chat.
This January he reappeared. "He was online and said: 'Hey, I haven't talked to you in a while. What's going on?'" Weis recalled. "It was more testing the waters to see how receptive I would be."
The small talk soon turned sexual when the man asked the "girl" - in this case Weis - if he could turn on his web camera.
Weis knew the man's intentions as soon as he appeared on the camera naked from the waist down.
"As long as you're continuing to talk to them, they're going to escalate the dialogue," Weis said. Weis said one of three things had to happen before he went to the police: masturbation on a web camera, an attempt to set up a meeting to have sex or sharing child pornography.
When the man performed a sexual act on the web camera, which was recorded along with the chat logs, Weis called Quebec's provincial police.
Weis also had personal information about the man that he turned over to authorities.
Weis says it's amazing how much information men tell him when they think they're talking to a 14-year-old girl.
"They will tell me where they live, where they work. They turn on their webcam so I can see them," Weis said. "They will tell me about their kids, their wife situation. They will show me their tattoos."
Obviously, this isn't Weis's first time doing this kind of work.
By his count, he's spent 1,000 hours talking to more than 550 alleged online predators. The Demand Project has partnered with several law enforcement agencies, including the Oklahoma Bureau of Narcotics and Dangerous Drugs, Tulsa police and the U.S. Department of Justice.
Weis and his wife were living in Colorado with their two children in 2004 when they saw a disturbing story on the evening news that would change their lives.
The story was of a father who raped his three-year-old daughter and posted a video of the attack online.
"It was one of those fistclenching moments where we felt that this is something we need to get involved with and do something about," Weis said. "We can't just be these people that hear about these horror stories and go back to normal life."
Weis was driven to track down those consuming the child pornography.
After volunteering with another cyber-watch group for years, the Weis family uprooted their life in Colorado and moved to Oklahoma to launch their organization. They have two children, but Weis said he wants to protect their identities because of the work he does.
When Weis moved to Oklahoma, he received training from a Homeland Security agent, a retired navy SEAL and a group of computersavvy people to learn how to interact with online predators.
"There are predators that are actively seeking to exploit you," Weis said.
Weis said he has been invited by police on several undercover operations to help rescue human trafficking victims.
The Demand Project volunteers transport the women and girls to a shelter and help them access the care they need.
"These girls have been beaten, they have been tortured, they have been abused. Some of them are drug addicted, and some of them are so psychologically damaged that they don't trust anyone," Weis said.
After doing their own undercover online investigation, police executed a search warrant at a home in Maniwaki on Tuesday.
Bruno Gorman, 58, has been charged with two counts of child luring, possession of child pornography and indecent exposure. He will next appear in court on March 20.
Police said they believe there could be more victims.
mhurley@ottawacitizen.com twitter.com/meghan_hurley
]]></text></news-item>