<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6D2F-E5E6-FD48-667A"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Quigley Urges Secretary Kerry to Oppose Harmful Keystone XL Pipeline</title><source>Targeted News Service</source><author>Targeted News Service</author><text><![CDATA[Rep. Mike Quigley, D-Ill. (5th CD), issued the following news release:
Today, U.S. Representatives Mike Quigley (IL-05) led a letter with 26 of his colleagues urging Secretary of State John Kerry to oppose the harmful Keystone XL pipeline, arguing that approval of the pipeline would be extremely detrimental to the environment. He further argues it does little to lower Midwest gas prices or create jobs.
"Keystone XL sets false expectations for lower gas prices and long-term job growth, when in fact it will likely raise Midwest gas prices, further pollute our environment and jeopardize the health and well-being of our communities," said Rep. Quigley. "Instead of pursuing projects that undermine our environmental and economic progress, we should focus on a long-term national clean energy plan that puts America on a path to sustainability."
The pipeline would transport tar sand oil to refineries in the United States, crossing America's agricultural heartland and key sources of drinking and agricultural water. Expanding tar sands oil production would make it virtually impossible to avoid a two degree Celsius global temperature increase - the maximum temperature increase experts agree the planet can realistically absorb before climate change becomes irreversible. The 830,000 barrels of tar sands oil the pipeline would carry into the U.S. daily is equal to adding more than 5.6 million new cars to U.S. roads.
Accidents with pipelines like Keystone XL are very common. In fact, the first phase of the Keystone pipeline spilled a dozen times in its first year of operation, including a spill in North Dakota that released 21,000 gallons of oil. Tar sands oil spills are also more threatening than conventional oil spills because tar sands oil sinks rather than floats, making clean-ups more difficult and costly.
The affect on Midwest gas prices of Keystone XL has been drastically misunderstood. Noted oil economist Philip Verleger has argued the pipeline would increase gasoline prices in the upper Midwest between 5-10 cents per gallon. A Consumer Watchdog report found that gas prices will increase by 25-40 cents in the Midwest and have no long-term economic benefit to the U.S. economy. Even President Obama acknowledged in a New York Times interview (http://www.nytimes.com/2013/07/28/us/politics/interview-with-president-obama.html?pagewanted=all&_r=2&) last year that the oil will be sold on the world markets, "so it does not bring down gas prices here in the United States."
Job creation benefits of Keystone XL have also been overestimated. The State Department has acknowledged that pipeline development would create 6,500 temporary, short-term construction jobs at best.
The full letter and a list of signatories can be found here (http://quigley.house.gov/uploads/2014.03.14_Schakowsky-Quigley-Holt_KeystoneXLCarbonBudget.pdf).
The letter has received vocal support from environmental groups including the National Wildlife Federation, the Natural Resources Defense Council, 350.org, Sierra Club, and Friends of the Earth.
Rep. Quigleyis a stalwart supporter of the environment and a member of the House Sustainable Energy and Environment Coalition. He has previously spoken out against the Keystone XL Pipeline and recently received one of the highest scoresfrom the League of Conservation Voters for his record on environmental issues. He has urged his colleagues in the House to put partisanship aside and craft America's first national energy plan (http://quigley.house.gov/speeches/the-house-must-tackle-climate-change-with-a-national-energy-plan/).
Copyright Targeted News Services
TNS 30VitinMar-140315-4669618 30VitinMar
]]></text></news-item>