<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6DA8-6BFA-5EEE-9D53"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Chatters express their disgust at report on abuse of chickens</title><source>Daily News (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Nulaid
l It's simple: our family and friends will never purchase any Nulaid products again.
l I'm so sick and tired of hearing about animal abuse. Now it's Nulaid chickens. I cannot believe the cruelty. We should ban the brand until the company can prove otherwise. Nicole.
l Let us know under what labels Pioneer Foods sell its products. It's disgusting to read about gangrene-infested, sick and injured chickens being distributed by Quantum and Nulaid. We have reached the bottom when people pass off rotten food as good. Sam.
l I've just eaten my very last Nulaid egg. Never again will my family support them. What a disgrace. Hennie Lourens, karma will get you. DH
l Please boycott all Nulaid eggs because of abuse of chickens at the distribution outlet, as per page 3 of the Daily News on Wednesday. Concerned animal lover.
l It's spine-chilling to realise we enjoy eating eggs "Nulaid" by birds that are forced to live only to lay eggs and then summarily killed at their end-of-lay period. Amazing how we humans bury our heads in the sand like ostriches and selectively turn a blind eye to all the cruelty around us. Halima-massi.
l A picture tells a thousand words, especially about the starved, gangrene-infested, maimed, battery-caged, helpless, diseased hens sold |by Nulaid employees. |Stocked at the most reputable stores trusted for quality |and grading, Nulaid eggs |turn out to be another |greedy and crude |chicken enterprise. Shameema Omar
l I've bought my last eggs from Nulaid. How can |people be so cruel ?
Politics
l Gwede Mantashe and President Jacob Zuma, please give us back our old ANC and form your own corrupt party. Joe Soap.
l Any government minister who wishes to be remembered on retiring as "dignified" needs to do just one thing during his term of office: nothing. e.s.e.
l We are losing two of the best people in government. Maybe they've realised they can no longer swim against the tide of corrupt, lazy and clueless peers. Heaven help us if this tide continues.
l What has the ANC integrity committee recommended about Dina Pule and Travelgate MPs who put the ANC into disrepute? As an ANC voter, I am disappointed with the inclusion on the parliamentary candidate list of Pule, Humphrey Mmemezi and other looters. This party is openly out of order but for Zuma this is a good story. Muzi Skhakhane.
l ANC all the way to nowhere.
l The secret of success for the DA is to make 100 percent sure that the masses of ANC supporters are kept informed of all the fraud, theft and |corruption perpetrated by the ruling party in the past 20 years. Remind them via the black-language media of the billions that cannot be accounted for. This should help many people realise how they are being duped. VT.
l What are the similarities between the ANC and the recent storms? Both cause havoc. Thula
l I just heard the ANC radio advert. Don't the people involved in this advert feel ashamed? Haven't they got a conscience when they refuse our children the right to study further? Raj Govender.
l The leopard never changes its spots, and so it is that the ANC keeps insisting on having shady characters in Parliament so corruption can continue unabated. The writing is |on the wall: crooked politicians are going to run this country for the next five years.
l "Of course they were expensive. Do you think they were bought from a bargain basement? You are just a useful idiot for those who were unsuccessful." This was |Trevor Manuel shouting |down Patricia de Lille in Parliament when she queried the inordinate cost of the merchandise in the arms deal. He shouted this while the backbenchers of his party were laughing like hyenas. I am recalling this and the fact that Manuel was at the epicentre of the arms deal before he is given a gilded halo for posterity. Remember that he was as duplicitous as the best of serpents. Kim
Sport
l I am an admirer of Hashim Amla but he was not the right choice to open the batting in Wednesday's |rain-shortened game. |David Miller should have opened the innings with Quintin de Kock. The decision to send in Amla robbed the Proteas of additional runs which could have affected the outcome of the game.
l Bad captaincy by Faf du Plessis in the T20. It was the wrong decision to start with Lonwabo Tsotsobe because he is very average, and he does not deserve to be in the squad. And to give debutant Beuran Hendriks the second last over? Better choices next time, Faf.|L Moodley
l Well done, Faf, bowl Wayne Parnell again in a tight situation after he's proven before that he |can't bowl at the death. Now use him in the World Cup so he can bowl us to defeat and we can proudly hold on to our chokers' |tag.
l Please send Makhaya Ntini to a commentators' academy. He is not ready for the job. MDS
Oscar Pistorius
l A recent letter asked "if Oscar had not been white would this trial have been so publicised?" Remember OJ Simpson? It's nothing to do with colour and everything to do with being famous. G2.
l Bolo-bolo-42, quick question, How do you know that shot to the head happened first? Were you there?
l OK guys, I don't remember whether I had my prosthesis on or not. Can you please get on |with the case?
Gatvol 99, you are 100 percent correct with regards to Oscar trial. As for Shameema Omar, please remove your blinkers. Dayanand, Phoenix.
l I am following Oscar's trial closely. I am waiting for the day he gives evidence. Gerrie Nel will not only ask him to demonstrate his skill at screaming like a woman, but also to sing like a canary. Alan.
l Is Oscar pretending to be sorrowful? If you're following this trial carefully, you'll notice how he cynically laughs when the witnesses are cross-examined by his lawyer. Please prove me wrong about what I'm noticing. |He is not looking remorseful at all. Why should we sympathise with anyone who shows no remorse? Gatvol 99.
l Advocate Barry Roux's cross-examinations of the various witnesses prove one fact only: Reeva Steenkamp's cold-blooded murder means |another money-making case for the defence lawyers. The Pistorious family and mine tycoons will pay any price for Oscar's life and freedom. The shots have been fired and humble Barry and June Steenkamp bear a burden of grief that no one in court can take away. Shameema Omar.
l Every day we read about crime - robberies, |hijackings, people being killed like there is no tomorrow. Nothing really gets done about it and yet here we getting flooded with Oscar's story. I guess famous people's lives are worth more than those of common folk.
Crime
l Pluto, what's so special about farm murders? More people get murdered in the cities and townships. Anyone who lives in remote areas will be a target for criminals. Realist.
l Zuma states that crime has diminished since the advent of democracy. I wonders which country he lives in.
Metro police
l I always felt safe going to the coffee shop inside Avondale Spar. At any time of the day the metro police vehicles occupied most of the parking and 50 percent of the coffee shop was occupied by hungry officers in uniform. Since the revamp of the store I haven't seen a single metro police official at the coffee shop - apparently because it's now too "open". I wonder what that means. GTiGUY
l The metro police are a total mess, and what are Willies Mnchunu and S'bu Sithole doing about it? Bring back Bheki Cele to cleanse the police and save us from paying wasted taxes on hooligans who themselves have no respect for the law.
City
l Have you ever wondered how the municipality allows illegal structures on slopes of hills then provides electricity to them? However, dare to put up something illegal in a middle-class suburb and the custodians of law and order prosecute you. What bull.
l Senzo, my dear |brother, first clean up |the city centre, get rid |of all criminals and |taxi washers, introduce visible, competent police as done during the World Cup in 2010, then share your bizarre dream of canal walks and night shopping in Durban. Clean out the bums and filthy vendors then use high-pressure water trucks to scrub out the filth at night, as done in Rome, then ask me for my vote.
l The plan to "upgrade" Durban central with canals and a pedestrian walk is ridiculous. The area has been allowed to deteriorate for 20 years and everyone has moved out of the CBD. The proposed upgraded area will be a new home for vagrants. Call it Whoonga Canal.
l Please can we have a second waterfront near Albert Park and Maydon Wharf so that I can |ake a bath. Homeless squatter.
Eskom
l I have stockpiled candles, purchased paraffin and filled gas bottles in readiness for rolling blackouts. Now Eskom keeps the lights on.
l I'm disappointed and surprised Eskom unions don't demand free food as well. Ban all unions and watch our land progress. We must be the laughing stock of the world. Pops.
l Every top executive should be given a free copy of Arthur Hailey's novel Overload. Then they can read how a power utility is run at 200 percent efficiency.
l If the government can spend millions giving solar geysers to low-cost home occupiers, why can't it clear up kilometres of barren land and install solar panels for power to |be supplied to neighbourhoods? Surely this will alleviate the demand for electricity. It's been done in Italy and other parts of the world.
]]></text></news-item>