<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6E4C-FB63-C3D9-AA0E"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Blacktower Financial Management Limited: Asset declaration - 31st March deadline</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
The modelo 720 otherwise known as the Asset declaration needs completing and filing by 31st March 2014. This is the form that all people who live in Spain for more than 183 days per calendar year (irrespective as to whether they consider themselves tax resident in Spain or not) need to complete in order to declare their overseas assets to the Spanish tax authorities if they are collectively valued over EUR50,000 per person, per asset class.
If you filed a form last year and your assets have not increased by more than EUR20,000 and/or you haven't disposed of assets already declared last year then you do not need to file a new one.
If you do need to file a new one and do not do so, the minimum fine for late filing will be EUR1,500. Minimum fine for a non declaration where there is a need is EUR10,000 and for every item omitted EUR5,000 (such as a particular bank account). The form has to be submitted electronically by an authorised agent i.e an accountant.
As a Spanish neighbour once said to me, "in Spain the hammer falls slowly but when it does, it falls hard."
Unfortunately he was, and continues to be, right.
The fact is that you need to make sure you are paying tax where it needs to be paid. The EU saving directive has ensured that most jurisdictions within Europe will now disclose tax information to any tax authority in Europe if this information is requested. If they don't disclose they will charge you a withholding tax of circa 35%, which can be considerably higher than the tax liability in your country of residence if you declared your income.
This is where Blacktower and I can help you, by using our skills, experience and knowledge we can create packages with all the elements combined to help lessen your tax burden.
If you have a frozen pension fund in the UK, have cash sitting around in a bank, or an underperforming investment then we can help make YOUR money work for YOU.
Don't believe me? If you have a minimum of EUR25,000 / Pound20,000 that is sitting in a bank earning little or no interest, call me and I'll show you a tax efficient way to get it to grow without excessive risk. Your initial cost with no future obligation is the price of your telephone call to arrange a free, impartial financial review and a cup of tea for yours truly.
For further information or to arrange a free impartial consultation call David Diggle on + 34 615 607 278 or email dave.diggle@blacktowerfm.com
click http://www.blacktowerfm.co.uk/latest-news/asset-declaration-31st-march-deadline
COMPANY BACKGROUND
ACTIVITIES
Blacktower Financial Management Limited offers financial planning and wealth management advisory services. The company provides personal, inheritance, and corporate tax planning; private banking and insurance; asset allocation; foreign exchange; residential and commercial property mortgage; pension and retirement planning; pension advisory services. Additionally, it offers conveyancing, will writing, custodian, and money broker services. The company caters to individuals, companies, charities, pension funds, and trustees. It has strategic partnerships with PenTech Ltd, World First, Lloyd-Roberts Investments LLP, and Capital Growth Limited. Blacktower Financial Management Limited was founded in 1986 and is based in Oxshott, United Kingdom with additional offices in Almancil, Portugal; Marbella, Spain; Saint Herblain, France; and Gibraltar.
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
12 March 2014: Blacktower Financial Management Limited: Retirement Options Unveiled!
I have had a lot of enquiries lately from clients wanting to know what to with regards what to do with their Pension Funds at retirement. The answer is that there is no one size fits all - there are a multitude of things to consider some of which being: Where resident, nationality, age, sex, lump sum, tax status, existing savings, risk profile, annuity rate, company invested with, type of scheme, marital status, death benefit, the list is endless so please do not be surprised if the stock answer is 'it depends' What is essential is that if you have a company or private pension scheme from the UK is -DO NOT just accept the first offer that comes along.
click http://www.blacktowerfm.co.uk/latest-news/retirement-options-unveiled
]]></text></news-item>