<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="6FE9-D043-B0EA-BB8D"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Beware of extortion scams</title><source>The Jackson Sun (Jackson, Tennessee)</source><author>By, South, Kelly</author><text><![CDATA[I wrote a column last year about the "FBI Ransomware Scam" in which a person's computer suddenly locks up and he gets a screen message purportedly from the FBI saying he's suspected of downloading unauthorized material, including pornography. He's told he can avoid arrest and prosecution by paying a fine and given instructions on how and where to send the money.
This is just one example of what the BBB calls "extortion scams". The crooks hope to scare victims into sending money before they come to their senses.
The most recent extortion scam we've heard about involves crooks impersonating Drug Enforcement Agency (DEA) agents. The DEA has a warning about the scam on its website.
The crooks call people, most of whom have bought drugs over the Internet or by phone, and claim that the purchases were illegal. The victims are told they must pay a fine to avoid arrest. It's not clear how the crooks are able to identify people who have bought drugs online or by phone.
The phone number on one consumer's caller ID had a District of Columbia area code and was answered with a recording saying you've reached the DEA and need to leave a message. Technology called "spoofing" allows crooks to fake the number that shows up on caller ID.
The IRS issued an alert last week about people, including recent immigrants, being called and told they owe back taxes that must be paid immediately through a pre-loaded debit card or wire transfer. If the victims refuse to cooperate, they're threatened with arrest, deportation or suspension of a business or driver's license.
We've heard about these extortion scams closer to home:
"Lt. Jeff Johnson" of the Murfreesboro police department calls and says a loved one failed to show up for jury duty and will need to appear in front of a judge to contest an arrest warrant.
Restaurant and other small business owners receive calls from someone claiming they owe money to the local utility company and threatening to turn off the power.
Victims are told they must send money immediately.
For many years, the crooks' preferred method of payment was a wire transfer. Once they picked up the money at a Western Union or MoneyGram office, it was gone.
The BBB, Western Union, and law enforcement agencies have educated many people that wiring money to someone you don't know is foolish. Although wire transfers are still a popular tool for the crooks, they've adopted a new method of payment to consummate many of their scams.
Green Dot MoneyPak cards can be bought at well-known retailers and are a legitimate payment device when used for the right purposes. You can download money on the card and use it to reload prepaid cards, add money to a PayPal account, and make payments to companies that accept it.
The crooks like it because it can also work like a wire transfer service. You simply provide them with the number on the card and they can access the funds.
You can avoid becoming a victim of an extortion scam by remembering that government agencies won't contact you in this manner and won't demand payment by wire transfer or Green Dot MoneyPak card.
Randy Hutchinson is president and chief executive officer of the Better Business Bureau of the Mid-South.
Randy Hutchinson
]]></text></news-item>