<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7033-6DEB-C959-A21A"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Insolvency specialists to fight policy</title><source>Business Day (South Africa)</source><author>AMANDA VISSER</author><text><![CDATA[Insolvency specialists to fight policy
Pretoria Correspondent
THE South African Restructuring and Insolvency Practitioners Association (Saripa) has taken up the baton on behalf of its members against the new policy on the appointment of provisional insolvency practitioners, which restricts white males to 10% of the cases.
The multimillion-rand insolvency industry in SA has been shrouded in controversy for many years, and several changes made to the appointment of liquidators have led to fronting and even corruption.
Saripa, which represents 445 members, warned that the new policy might have similar unintended consequences.
The association argued in papers before the Western Cape High Court filed on Tuesday that the policy was unlawful and unconstitutional.
Saripa said the policy would cause undue harm to a particular class of people and was not & reasonably capable& of achieving its objectives.
The application comes shortly after the Concerned Insolvency Practitioners Association filed papers in the North Gauteng High Court earlier this month against the same policy.
The policy was published on February 7 by the Department of Justice, and will become effective at the end of this month. The objective is to promote consistency, fairness, transparency and equality for persons previously disadvantaged by unfair discrimination.
According to the policy, 40% of the appointments of provisional liquidators by the master's office would go to African, coloured, Indian and Chinese women, 30% to men of the same groups, 20% to white women and 10% to white males.
They would also be appointed in alphabetical order from the lists at the master's office.
Jurgens Steenkamp, a member of Saripa's national board, stated in his affidavit that there were not enough previously disadvantaged male or female practitioners to perform the amount of work that they would receive under the new policy.
He said those appointed would & undoubtedly& have to outsource the work to other practitioners. & This is likely to result in fronting, which the policy is allegedly designed to eradicate.& A letter from the Association for Black Business Rescue and Insolvency Practitioners to its members, forwarded to Business Day, informs them that 70% of all future appointments would be allocated to them.
The black practitioners' association offered a crash course of training workshops to members who felt they were not equipped to take up the appointments before the end of this month.
Mr Steenkamp argued in the court papers that the policy would lead to the appointment of practitioners who were not qualified for the assignment.
The master is obliged to mechanically apply the policy on a rotational basis.
The task of matching the estate to a trustee with experience in a particular industry would no longer be a key consideration, which might seriously prejudice the estate and its creditors.
Saripa said the policy unlawfully fettered the discretion of the master, infringed on the right to equality set out in the constitution, and was irrational and ultra vires (beyond the powers of) the Insolvency Act.
It said the policy would create an absolute barrier to African, Indian, Chinese and coloured people who became South African citizens after April 27 1994, while white males and females who became citizens after that date might be placed on the list for appointments by the master's office.
According to the policy, insolvency practitioners on every master's list would need to be an African, coloured, Indian, or Chinese person who became a South African citizen before April 27 1994, or a descendant of such a citizen.
Saripa said the definition of African, coloured, Indian and Chinese practitioners excluded them from the category and no provision had been made in any of the other categories.
& There is no possible justification for that differentiation. It is irrational, and is presumptively unfair in terms of section 9(5) of the constitution,& it said.
]]></text></news-item>