<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7063-1DC5-1B10-809D"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Stupid Media Bias Tricks, The Grade-Fixing Lying Obamacare Edition</title><source>The Lid</source><author>Jeff Dunetz</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 16, 2014 (The Lid:http://www.jeffdunetz.com Delivered by Newstex) To paraphrase the Grateful Dead, what a long strange trip the past two weeks have been. Since Last week at this time I was driving home from CPAC this edition covers two weeks.Since last time, we saw Obama admit another Obamacare lie and once again Sheila Jackson Lee proved Ron White was right when he said, you can't fix stupid as the Representative from Texas failed American History. We saw Mark Zuckerberg whine to President Obama and Rep.
Loretta Sanchez encourage truthers. Speaking about not fixing stupid, Code Pink's Medea Benjamin was arrested in Egypt on her way to Gaza and a UN and EU Funded Palestinian News Agency announced the 'Jews Plan to Subjugate the World'. Senator Boxer used a long discredited claim as global warming scare tactic and Chelsea Handler told Piers Morgan that he is a Terrible Interviewer. MSNBC's Mika Brzezinski called Sarah Palin a 'Multimillion-Dollar Moron' and the Columbia Journalism Review declared Fox Is More Balanced than MSNBC Below are the stupid media bias tricks from the last 14 days. Headlines are linked to the full article (and will open a new window). When it is a broadcast story the video/audio will also be found at the end of the link. So click on the links below and read about the stupid bias tricks of the last two weeks: Obama: You 'Might Have to Switch Doctors'[1] Interviewed by WebMD President Obama admitted his "you can keep your doctor" promise wasn't true, saying, "They're going to have to make some choices, and they might have to switch doctors in part because they are saving money." ... Grade-Fixing Scandal at Winston-Salem State University[2] Winston-Salem State University (WSSU) was one of only two schools out of the 17 in the UNC system to receive the $200,000 grant for meeting graduation and retention rate goals. But according to an investigation by Campus Reform, those graduation goals ... HHS Official Resigns, Writes Scathing Rebuke Of Federal Bureaucracy[3] David Wright, director of the Office of Research Integrity (ORI) in the Department Of Health And Human Services, quit his job, writing a scathing resignation letter which claimed most of his time was spent negotiating his way through the dysfunctional f ... Facebook's Zuckerberg Calls Obama To Complain About Latest NSA Spying Revelations[4] On Thursday, company founder Mark Zuckerberg posted on Facebook that he called President Obama to vent his frustrations and concerns regarding a report that the NSA has been aping his Facebook's servers to install malware on other computers. ... Democratic Spin Of Loss In Florida Given Three Pinocchios[5] Democrats have been claiming that Alex's Sink's loss in Florida demonstrated an underperforming GOP and put the Democrats in a strong position for the midterm's in November. WAPO fact checker Glenn Kessler says the claim is untrue. ... Arafat Recognized Israel As the Jewish State, But Abbas Wont[6] In recent days Palestinian President Abbas and the Arab League have each rejected calls to recognize Israel as the Jewish state, but a video has surfaced which shows his predecessor, Yasser Arafat, did. ... US State Dept Denying Israelis Entry Visas at Record Level[7] Nearly one out of every ten Israelis who apply for tourist visas to the United States are denied entry by the U.S. State Department. According to figures posted in Israeli newspaper Yediot Aharonot, in 2013 year of the 125,000 Israelis requested tourist ... Palin Brings Down CPAC House With New 'Green Eggs and Ham'[8] For the second time in the past three years, Sarah Palin gave the Keynote address to CPAC, her speech elicited a few standing ovations, but perhaps the loudest was a parody of the Dr. Seuss book, "Green Eggs and Ham." ... Rep. Loretta Sanchez (D-CA) Encourages Truthers To Send Evidence To Their Reps[9] Rep. Loretta Sanchez (D-CA), appearing on C-SPAN's Washington Journal, championed the cause of 9/11 Truthers, encouraging them to "push" for more answers as to why Building Seven collapsed on 9/11. ... Rep. Sheila Jackson Lee: The Constitution is 400-Years-Old[10] Rep. Sheila Jackson Lee (D-TX) lectured her colleagues in the House of Representatives Wednesday on the history of the Constitution, claiming the 226-year-old document is 400 years old. ... Dr. Ben Carson: U.S. is Like Nazi Germany[11] During the annual New York Meeting on Monday, Carson reportedly mentioned that we 'live in a Gestapo age.' Interviewed after the event, Carson doubled down, saying, "I mean, [we are] very much like Nazi Germ ... Joe Scarborough: GOP Win in FL Sign of Doom for Dems in 2014[12] Wednesday's Morning Joe featured a postmortem of the previous day's special election in Florida, won by Republican David Jolly in an upset. According to the host, the win by a " lousy, lousy candidate" is a signal that the 2014 midterm ... Sen. Portman (R-OH) Won't Rule Out Running For POTUS in 2016[13] Senator Rob Portman was a guest on Tuesday evening's Hugh Hewitt program and refused to rule out a presidential run in 2016. ... UN and EU Funded Palestinian News Agency: 'Jews Plan to Subjugate the World'[14] According to an article published by independent Palestinian News Agency Ma'an, based on the plan outlined in the Protocols of the Elders of Zion, Jews "are planning means to take over the reins of world politics, by spreading organized destr ... Liam Neeson Tells NYC To 'Man Up' About Proposed Horse Carriage Ban[15] Actor Liam Neeson is fighting NY Mayor DeBlasio's plan to shut down the popular Midtown horse carriage business ​. While some in the City Council joined him for a tour, the mayor stayed home, prompting Neeson to tell the press, 'He should hav ... Chelsea Handler to Piers Morgan 'You're a Terrible Interviewer'[16] Author, Comedian and talk show host Chelsea Handler was a guest on the Piers Morgan program Monday night, and she didn't seem to enjoy the experience. After making a comment about having to " tolerate this nonsense," Handler told Morgan he ... Senator Boxer Uses Long Discredited Claim As Global Warming Scare Tactic[17] Senator Barbara Boxer (D-CA) blamed hurricane Sandy and the California drought on global warming during a Tuesday appearance on Jansing Co. Even though those claims have been long discredited, the host did not challenge the Senator. ... Netanyahu Blasts World-Wide Hypocrisy[18] Standing at Israel's naval base in Eiat, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu blasted the world's hypocrisy on Monday, saying there is a wave of condemnation of Israel when it "builds a balcony in Jerusalem," but only a drizzle of censure ... Former Owner/Editor Of New Republic Blasts the Magazine's Anti-Israel Editorial[19] Martin Peretz, a liberal pundit and former owner and editor of the New Republic, wrote a letter to the NY Times asking, " Why is a liberal magazine like The New Republic not to be permitted to consistently make the case that the notion of Israeli sta ... MSNBC's Brzezinski: Sarah Palin 'Multimillion-Dollar Moron'[20] Monday's discussion about the just-completed CPAC convention brought out the usual venom from Morning Joe's liberal panel. ... Max Blumenthal Goes All 'Tin Foil Hat'[21] During a Monday appearance at Brandies, Max Blumenthal author of the anti-Semitic book "Goliath" started talking conspiracy theories about the pro-Israel organizations on the Brandeis campus. ... NY Times WH Correspondent: Putin Doesn't Have A Lot of Respect For Obama[22] On his Tuesday night program, Hugh Hewitt hosted Peter Baker, the White House correspondent for the NY Times. According to Baker, Russian President Putin does not have much respect for President Obama. ... F***ing Zionist, F***ing Pricks, Get The F*** Off Our Campus'[23] Nowhere in Europe is the anti-Israel hatred movement stronger than in Ireland. This video in this post displaying the vile hatred of the pro-BDS crowd was taken during an anti-Boycott meeting on the campus of National University of Ireland Galway. ... CPAC 2014: Dr Ben Carson Warns About PC Police[24] Dr. Ben Carson fought back against the progressives and the liberal media who have been twisting his words. Speaking to a full crowd at CPAC 2014 Saturday afternoon Dr. Carson said bluntly anybody who believes some of the statements that he has been acc ... Chris Matthews' Presents Pure CPAC Demagoguery[25] Chris Matthews led off his Thursday Hardball with a monolog trashing the CPAC convention happening this week. Matthews must have gotten his information from the short clips presented by the mainstream media, because very little of the information he pres ... Sen. Harkin: DOJ Civil Rights Nominee Would Have Been Confirmed If He Was White[26] Sen. Tom Harkin (D-IA) took to the Senate floor Wednesday to call the senators who voted to block the nomination of Debo Adegbil to a top Justice Department post racists. ... J Street Activist Upset 'Liberal' Organizations Not Invited To Donors Conference[27] A student at University of Maryland, Benjy Cannon, is upset. In January 2014 there was a conference were 17 pro-Israel groups got to pitch over 100 Jewish-American philanthropists for money, and groups he described as "liberal" were not invited ... Bloomberg's Jonathan Alter Says Hillary Clinton is Old News[28] Long-time political reporter Jonathan Alter, now at Bloomberg, is not convinced Hillary Clinton is a slam-dunk. Today he cautioned that " a lot can happen, and it may be that she is old news." ... Russia Today Anchor Resigns On Air, Says Network 'Whitewashes Actions of Putin'[29] An American news anchor working in the Washington DC bureau of the Russian Government owned Russia Today network stunned viewers on Wednesday with an on-air resignation after blasting the network's coverage of Vladimir Putin and the Ukraine invasion. ... Obama Advisor Attacks AGW Believing Scientist For Telling Congress Extreme Weather Not Caused By Warming[30] Professor Rogert Pielke, Jr. is a man-made global warming believer, however he sees no evidence that increased temperatures have led to an increase in extreme weather. As a result, he drew a 6-page long rebuke by the President's science advisor, John Hold ... Reuters Falsely Claims Netanyahu's 'Jewish State' Demand is Brand New[31] Though "Jewish State" recognition has been part of Netanyahu's platform since he took office in 2009, Reuters writer Crispian Balmer claimed Wednesday that Netanyahu's demand that Palestinians recognize Israel as the "Jewish s ... Joy Reid Refuses To Call Tyrants 'Evil'[32] In the world of progressives no one is evil. MSNBC host Joy Reid was a guest on the Hugh Hewitt program Monday evening. Hewitt asked Reid if Putin was evil, she refused to answer the question. ... Russia Today Anchor Abby Martin Speaks Out Against Russian Invasion Of Crimea[33] An anchor for the Kremlin-controlled English language news outlet Russia Today (RT) went off-script Tuesday morning and condemned Russia's incursion into the Crimean peninsula. ... CODEPINK Founder Medea Benjamin Arrested in Egypt, Deported To Turkey[34] CODEPINK Founder Medea Benjamin reported on Monday evening that Egyptian police held her at an airport jail without explanation and that they had broken her arm. Later in the day, CODEPINK reported she had been deported to Turkey. ... CNN's Kohn Calls Republicans 'Hypocrites' for Criticizing Obama, Gets Schooled[35] CNN's Sally Kohn called the GOP hypocrites for beating up Obama about Ukraine but not doing the same with Bush when Putin invaded Georgia, but guest Pletka corrected Kohn, reminding her that Senators McCain and Graham both did in fact criticize Bus ... MSNBC 's Joy Reid Ignores Her Own Definition of Climate To Hype Global Warming[36] On her Monday program, Joy Reid gave a perfect definition of climate and how it is different than weather-- and then ignored her own definition of climate so she could push the global warming theory. ... Anti-Israel Apartheid Week Forced to Edit Pro-Israel Student Out of Video[37] After facing strong pressure, organizers of the Israel Apartheid Week edited out the picture of a pro-Israel student whose image was used part of their promotional video for their anti-Israel event. ... Columbia Journalism Review: Fox Is More Balanced than MSNBC[38] In a Monday column on Columbia Journalism Review, Alexis Sobel Fitts compares the way MSNBC and Fox News present opposing points of view and suggests that Fox News is fairer in the way it presents the progressive point of view than MSNBC is at presenting ... Please email me at yidwithlid@aol.com to be put onto my mailing list. Feel free to reproduce any article but please link back to http://www.jeffdunetz.com [1]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/obama-you-might-have-switch-doctors [2]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/grade-fixing-scandal-winston-salem-state-university [3]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/hhs-official-resigns-writes-scathing-rebuke-federal-bureaucracy [4]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/facebooks-zuckerberg-calls-obama-complain-about-latest-nsa-spying-revelations [5]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/democratic-spin-loss-florida-given-three-pinocchios [6]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/arafat-recognized-israel-jewish-state-abbas-wont [7]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/us-state-dept-denying-israelis-entry-visas-record-level [8]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/palin-brings-down-cpac-house-new-green-eggs-and-ham [9]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/rep-loretta-sanchez-d-ca-encourages-truthers-send-evidence-their-reps [10]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/rep-sheila-jackson-lee-constitution-400-years-old [11]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/dr-ben-carson-us-nazi-germany [12]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/joe-scarborough-gop-win-fl-sign-doom-dems-2014 [13]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/sen-portman-r-oh-wont-rule-out-running-potus-2016 [14]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/un-and-eu-funded-palestinian-news-agency-jews-plan-subjugate-world [15]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/liam-neeson-tells-nyc-man-about-proposed-horse-carriage-ban [16]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/chelsea-handler-piers-morgan-youre-terrible-interviewer [17]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/senator-boxer-uses-long-discredited-claim-global-warming-scare-tactic [18]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/netanyahu-blasts-world-wide-hypocrisy [19]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/former-ownereditor-new-republic-blasts-magazines-anti-israel-editorial [20]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/msnbcs-brzezinski-sarah-palin-multimillion-dollar-moron [21]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/max-blumenthal-goes-all-tin-foil-hat [22]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/ny-times-wh-correspondent-putin-doesnt-have-lot-respect-obama [23]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/fing-zionist-fing-pricks-get-f-our-campus [24]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/cpac-2014-dr-ben-carson-warns-about-pc-police [25]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/chris-matthews-presents-pure-cpac-demagoguery [26]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/sen-harkin-doj-civil-rights-nominee-would-have-been-confirmed-if-he-was-white [27]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/j-street-activist-upset-liberal-organizations-not-invited-donors-conference [28]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/bloombergs-jonathan-alter-says-hillary-clinton-old-news [29]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/russia-today-anchor-resigns-air-says-network-whitewashes-actions-putin [30]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/obama-advisor-attacks-agw-believing-scientist-telling-congress-extreme-weather-not-caused [31]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/reuters-falsely-claims-netanyahus-jewish-state-demand-brand-new [32]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/joy-reid-refuses-call-tyrants-evil [33]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/russia-today-anchor-abby-martin-speaks-out-against-russian-invasion-crimea [34]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/codepink-founder-medea-benjamin-arrested-egypt-deported-turkey [35]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/cnns-kohn-calls-republicans-hypocrites-criticizing-obama-gets-schooled [36]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/msnbc-s-joy-reid-ignores-her-own-definition-climate-hype-global-warming [37]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/anti-israel-apartheid-week-forced-edit-pro-israel-student-out-video [38]: http://www.truthrevolt.org/news/columbia-journalism-review-fox-more-balanced-msnbc

]]></text></news-item>