<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7112-4909-0336-2A37"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Sealed Air Finalizes $930MM Payment to Trusts</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Heather Isringhausen Gvillo, writing for Legal Newsline, reportedthat a New Jersey bubble wrap manufacturer paid $930 million incash into two asbestos trusts as part of W.R. Grace & Co'sbankruptcy settlement agreement. In addition to the $930 million settlement, Sealed Air Corporationagreed to pay 18 million shares of Sealed Air common stock. Thecompany stated in a press release from Feb. 4 that it intended tofund most of the asbestos trust payments using available cash"with the remainder from our committed credit facilities." "This is very positive news for Sealed Air, as the completion ofthe settlement has been anticipated for some time and now bringsfinality to a matter after more than a decade of preparation,"said Jerome Peribere, CEO of Sealed Air. "We will no longer incurinterest on the settlement, which amounted to $48 million in 2013.Additionally, we anticipate meaningful cash tax benefits over thenext several years." Sealed Air's payments settle a claim resorting from its $4.3billion purchase of Cryovac from Grace & Co. in 1998. Grace & Co.filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy in April 2001. Sealed Air'ssettlement agreement was held up by Grace & Co.'s bankruptcylitigation, which ended earlier this month. Grace & Co. emerged from its bankruptcy on Feb. 3, one of thelongest in U.S. history, when its Joint Plan of Reorganizationbecame effective, establishing two independent trusts tocompensate asbestos personal injury claimants and asbestos cleanupefforts. Together, the two trusts are funded by more than $4 billion from avariety of sources including cash, warrants to purchase Grace &Co. common stock, deferred payment obligations, insurance proceedsand payments from former affiliates, the company explained in astatement. Sealed Air originally agreed to pay $512 million to settle itscurrent and future asbestos-related, fraudulent transfer andsuccessor claims against the company in its bankruptcy settlementagreement in 2001, which took place in the United StatesBankruptcy Court for the District of Delaware. Sealed Air's payment grew to $930 million due to interest, whichwas set at 5.5 percent per annum and was compounded annually. According to the settlement agreement, Sealed Air and Cryovac,Inc. received the full benefit of an injunction of the bankruptcycode, forbidding future debtors from filing asbestos-relatedclaims in the future. The injunction "shall be in form andsubstance reasonably acceptable to Sealed Air Corporation andCryovac, Inc. and which injunction shall include, withoutlimitation, provisions enjoining any and all persons from takingany and all legal or other actions . . . or making any demand. . . for the purpose of, directly or indirectly, claiming,collecting, recovering, or receiving any payment, recovery or anyother relief whatsoever from any of the Released Parties withrespect to any and all Asbestos-Related Claims," the settlementagreement states. The settlement also makes it clear that the agreement does notconstitute guilt or wrongdoing on Sealed Air's behalf. Rather, thecompany simply sealed its "peace." "Neither this agreement nor any of the transactions contemplatedhereby is, or shall be construed as, an admission of liability,fault or wrongdoing by the released parties, who have denied andcontinue to deny any liability, fault, or wrongdoing, but,instead, is a compromise settlement of disputed claims, made inorder to avoid the further substantial expense, burden, andinconvenience of protracted litigation and appeal that may occurin further proceedings relating to these actions or any futureactions, but which the released parties have forever bought theirpeace," the agreement states.
]]></text></news-item>