<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7198-585C-846A-61FA"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Nigeria; Govt Urged to Fortify Security At Cargo Terminals</title><source>Africa News</source><author>This Day (Lagos)</author><text><![CDATA[Some of the challenges in freighting cargo to Nigeria is the exposure of the imported goods to vandalisation and the predilection of government inspection officials to tamper with the content of the goods.
A freight forwarding operator, Mr Humphrey Okonkwo, who made this known said freighting has become a huge business in Nigeria and urged the federal government to install close circuit television cameras at the export and import terminals at major seaports and international airports in the country.
Okonkwo, who is managing director of Hont Global Services Nigeria Limited, also complained about bottlenecks in the clearing of goods at the airports and seaports and the tendency of Customs and other government officials concerned with clearing to institute arbitrary and illicit laws to defraud and exploit importers.
He said many importers and exporters are getting worried over the tampering of their cargo at seaports and major international airports, which are being pilfered under the guise of inspection by relevant agencies.
Okonkwo remarked that the old practice of ripping the cargo open could be eliminated if government acquires state of the art scanners at the air and seaports, which would check the cargo without giving room to physical examination and the attendant rough handling of such goods.
He observed that in other parts of the world cargoes are screened and scanned electronically without ripping them open, thereby preventing pilferage.
"So the government should put in place better technology, security system in place at the airports and seaports so that pilfering can be eliminated. The Installation of CCTVs is part of it and putting a standard security system in place then tracking. These can be done but who is going to implement it? We advise government should install sophisticated scanning machines at the airports and seaports as one of the ways of checking piferage of cargo," Okonkwo said.
He explained that the firm, Hont Global Services Limited, has opened an office in Nigeria to offer world class services in sea and air freight for clients who want to import or export goods to and from Nigeria, adding that since the company started its successful freight services it has attended to the needs of individual and corporate organisations.
He however flayed the double charge regime policy at the ports urging government to standardise tariff on import and export to make operations seamless.
"Our operations in Nigeria, particularly clearing our goods from the seaport, are where we have great challenges. The charges especially the terminal charges and handling charges are too expensive."
Okonkwo said there are a lot of hidden charges, most of which are illegal.
"After we have given your client quotation you still incur a lot of hidden charges that are not receipted and which you cannot claim from your clients. If the government can help us in standardising this process so that all those things can be eliminated, I think we should be fine."
]]></text></news-item>