<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="71B5-4207-43B2-FF39"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: WR Grace Reports $29.7MM Fourth Quarter Profit</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Baltimore Sun reported that W. R. Grace & Co. announced thatit earned $29.7 million in the fourth quarter, a swing from a$184.3 million loss in the same period a year earlier. Both quarters included charges related to the Columbia-basedchemical maker's asbestos-related liability and bankruptcyreorganiztion, which it emerged from on Feb. 3. On a per share basis, Grace earned 38 cents in the October-to-December period, compared to a loss of $2.44 a year earlier. For the full year, Grace made $256.1 million, or $3.30 per share,up from $40 million, or 52 cents a share for 2012. Sales slipped 3percent to $3.06 billion in 2013, partly as a result of a declinein surcharges for rare earth materials used in catalysts andslightly lower sales volume. Grace recorded about $155 million in asbestos and bankruptcy-related expenses, driven largely by a $129 million interest ratesettlement, in 2013's fourth quarter, down from about $369 milliona year earlier. Grace shares rose 85 cents on Feb. 5 trading to close at $96.87each. Grace employs about 1,100 people in Maryland between itsheadquarters and a research facility in Columbia and a large plantin Curtis Bay. Headquartered in Columbia, Maryland, W.R. Grace & Co. (NYSE:GRA)-- http://www.grace.com/ -- supplies catalysts and silicaproducts, especially construction chemicals and buildingmaterials, and container products globally. Grace employsapproximately 6,500 people in over 40 countries and had 2012 netsales of $3.2 billion. The company and its debtor-affiliates filed for chapter 11protection on April 2, 2001 (Bankr. D. Del. Case No. 01-01139). The Debtors are represented by Adam Paul, Esq., and John Donley,P.C., Esq., at Kirkland & Ellis LLP, in Chicago, Illinois; RogerHiggins, Esq., at The Law Offices of Roger Higgins, in Chicago,Illinois; and Laura Davis Jones, Esq., James E. O'Neill, Esq.,and Timothy P. Cairns, Esq., at Pachulski Stang Ziehl & Jones,LLP, in Wilmington, Delaware. The Debtors hired Blackstone Group, L.P., for financial advice.PricewaterhouseCoopers LLP is the Debtors' accountant. Stroock & Stroock & Lavan, LLP, and Duane Morris, LLP, representthe Official Committee of Unsecured Creditors. The CreditorsCommittee tapped Capstone Corporate Recovery LLC for financialadvice. Roger Frankel serves as legal representative for victims ofasbestos exposure who may file claims against W.R. Grace. Mr.Frankel, a partner at Orrick Herrington & Sutcliffe LLP, replacesDavid Austern, who was appointed to that role in 2004. Mr.Frankel has served as legal counsel for Mr. Austern who passedaway in May 2013. The FCR is represented by Orrick Herrington &Sutcliffe LLP as counsel; Phillips Goldman & Spence, P.A., asDelaware co-counsel; and Lincoln Partners Advisors LLC asfinancial adviser. Herrington & Sutcliffe LLP and Phillips Goldman & Spence, PA.Elihu Inselbuch, Esq., at Caplin & Drysdale, Chartered, and MarlaR. Eskin, Esq., at Campbell & Levine, LLC, represent the OfficialCommittee of Asbestos Personal Injury Claimants. The AsbestosCommittee of Property Damage Claimants tapped Scott Baena, Esq.,and Jay M. Sakalo, Esq., at Bilzin Sumberg Baena Price & Axelrod,LLP, to represent it. Thomas Moers Mayer, Esq., at Kramer LevinNaftalis & Frankel, LLP, represents the Official Committee ofEquity Security Holders. W.R. Grace obtained confirmation of a plan co-proposed with theOfficial Committee of Asbestos Personal Injury Claimants, theOfficial Committee of Equity Security Holders, and the AsbestosFuture Claimants Representative. The Chapter 11 plan is builtaround an April 2008 settlement for all present and futureasbestos personal injury claims, and a subsequent settlement forasbestos property damage claims. District Judge Ronald Buckwalter on Jan. 31, 2012, entered anorder affirming the bankruptcy court's confirmation of the Plan.Bankruptcy Judge Judith Fitzgerald had approved the Plan onJan. 31, 2011. W.R. Grace defeated four appeals from approval of the Plan. Afifth appeal was by secured bank lenders claiming the right to$185 million of interest at the contractual default rate.Pursuant to a settlement announced in December 2013, lenders areto receive $129 million in settlement of the claim for additionalinterest. The Plan became effective on Feb. 3, 2014, following the approvalof the settlement of the last appeal from the order confirmingW.R. Grace's Plan.
]]></text></news-item>