<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="727A-4C09-6880-ED91"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>No excuse for slow delivery of mail</title><source>The Nelson Mail (New Zealand)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[New Zealand Post is under fire again. This time it's over the length of time it takes for a letter to go between two addresses in Stoke.
In the case of John Martin, a letter from Stoke Motors took a week to arrive. That's bad enough until you find out that it went from Stoke to Christchurch, then to Wellington, before arriving at Mr Martin's home just a stone's throw away.
His case is not an isolated one. In another local example, resident Carolyn Burman received a letter on Thursday which had been posted in Upper Moutere the previous Friday.
Not surprisingly, the problem is due to NZ Post axing the processing of standard letters in Nelson last December, with the loss of 30 jobs. Despite this, the company has a delivery target of three working days.
These are not isolated cases around the country. What's worrying is that the medical profession still relies on postal deliveries to contact patients.
Just last week the Canterbury District Health Board criticised NZ Post because the delays were causing some patients to miss hospital appointments. Frustrated patients began contacting the DHB last September because of the delays.
The Postal Workers Union of Aotearoa last month exposed NZ Post for deliberately "holding back" standard mail, as an incentive for people to pay more for FastPost. That in itself is reason enough for the management at the national postal service to act. What's worrying is that from July next year, NZ Post plans to cut urban deliveries to three days a week.
Everyone understands that times have changed with the internet. Demand for postal services has plummeted, and NZ Post has had to react to the changing nature of the business.
Apart from the number of NZ Post employees losing their jobs, which is traumatic enough, the impact of the changes is felt most keenly by the elderly and people on low incomes. They are two significant groups who don't have ready access to technology and rely on postal deliveries. The rise of email and the decline of physical mail mean that these two groups are becoming increasingly disadvantaged.
The risk of a poor service increases the number of people turning away from using it. For disadvantaged groups, it's essential that the postal service is maintained to a high standard.
Inspirational Marty
What an inspiration Marty Clark is. The one- legged "wonder" we featured in Saturday's edition has not let his disability get in the way of what he wants to achieve.
Marty could have been forgiven for just wanting to survive after losing a leg in a horrific motorcycle accident 30 years ago, but he didn't. He has skied and sailed for New Zealand at the Paralympics, and has even won a national surfing title.
It's his sheer determination that shines through, and is something we can all learn from. As he says, "find something you can be passionate about and pursue it, and always be open to new directions . . . jump in boots and all and be part of the community".
]]></text></news-item>