<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="72F1-61A4-259E-76DD"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>FINTRAC disputes watchdog's objections; Agency argues it can collect private data</title><source>Ottawa Citizen</source><author>Jordan Press, Postmedia News</author><text><![CDATA[Canada's anti-money-laundering agency believes it can legally collect and keep personal information such as social insurance numbers, despite the objections of the federal privacy commissioner. Records released to Postmedia News under the access to information act show the agency, known as FINTRAC, disputing key points in a 2013 report by the privacy watchdog that was critical of its data-gathering reach.
The privacy commissioner's report argued FINTRAC collected and retained too much personal information on Canadians. It also found that the agency had made only limited progress on addressing similar criticisms it had made in a 2009 report.
FINTRAC's job is to track the flow of money to terrorists and organized crime, mapping who is involved in financing and where the money goes, but also flagging cases of financial fraud to police.
To do that job, federal legislation requires FINTRAC to receive transaction reports from banks, casinos and other financial institutions about transactions over $10,000, such as down-payments for a house or car, or those deemed suspicious. Each report must have the details of the government-issued identification used in the transaction, which sometimes means a health card or social insurance number is given to FINTRAC. When the privacy commissioner first looked at FINTRAC in March 2009, the database had about 101 million transaction reports. In March 2012, FINTRAC's database had about 165 million transaction reports, the privacy commissioner found.
Some of those files, the privacy commissioner argued, included sensitive personal information on Canadians who weren't involved in anything approaching terrorism or organized crime.
Draft documents for a March 2013 letter to the privacy commissioner from FINTRAC director Gerald Cossette say the audit report "reads as if FINTRAC has no authority to collect and retain SINs and health card numbers."
"FINTRAC has the authority to do so ... for evidentiary purposes related to ensuring compliance," the note reads.
In another letter, from May 2013, Cossette raised concerns that the privacy commissioner's report was factually flawed, even though the audit report had been amended to "bring clarity" on "key aspects of FINTRAC's role and responsibilities."
FINTRAC spokesman Peter Lamey said Thursday that in some cases, a health card or a social insurance number may be the only government-issued identification given for a transaction. FINTRAC can't legally share social insurance numbers and health cards with police or national security agencies, Lamey said, thus the agency takes steps to ensure it doesn't violate anyone's privacy.
"The system that FINTRAC has in place is sound," Lamey said. "From the time FINTRAC receives a report, to the time of its destruction, FINTRAC safeguards all information by controlling access and limiting the use of this information to the purpose for which it was received or collected."
The privacy commissioner's office said Thursday that some organizations have to collect client information and give it to FINTRAC, but "these reporting requirements must always be balanced with customers' privacy rights."
Anne-Marie Hayden, a spokeswoman for the office, said the privacy commissioner had heard the agency's concerns about the report containing factual errors. She said if the office sees "evidence of an error" from any organization being reviewed, "the report is updated." Neither the privacy commissioner nor FINTRAC said if there were factual errors in the 2013 report.
]]></text></news-item>