<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7305-2087-8ECD-A77B"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Sulu sultanate condemns kidnappings</title><source>BusinessWorld</source><author>Albert F. Arcilla</author><text><![CDATA[ZAMBOANGA CITY - The Sulu sultanate has condemned the spate of kidnapping that continues in the island-province of Sulu and urged the public to stay vigilant. It also warned against the spread of false and unfounded accusations against local authorities and provincial leaders.
"As the reigning Sultan of Sulu and North Borneo, I am condemning this act of crime to the highest degree and I am calling my constituents to be vigilant for only these kidnappers will benefit from false and unfounded accusations," said Sultan Muedzul-Lail T. Kiram.
He said some sectors in the province are pointing to the local government, the military and the police as being behind the kidnappings.
"This is a baseless accusation for I am in constant touch with these authorities concerning the peace and order of the province. I would like to appeal to the people to refrain from issuing such baseless statements," Mr. Kiram said.
"They are doing their best to solve this problem or perhaps eradicate it. One thing we know for sure, the kidnappers are the ones feeding you these false information and to capitalize on the situation," he added.
Mr. Kiram also branded the spate of kidnappings in the Muslim province as "un-Islamic in any perspective."
He noted that even ordinary citizens have been kidnapped for a small amount of cash. He said that because of the kidnappings, some people have been arming and organizing themselves into a vigilante group, but pointed out that this move could further complicate matters in Sulu.
Capt. Ryan Lacuesta, civil military operation officer of the 2nd Marine Brigade based in Jolo, said that they are in full support of civil society's initiatives for peace in the island.
"Bringing peace and order to this province is not only (the responsibility) of the government, the military and the police," he said. "It also needs the participation of all the stakeholders of Jolo including its local residents."
]]></text></news-item>