<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7326-9CD3-21B7-7AA9"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Policeman's spying a 'gross breach of trust'</title><source>The Western Mail</source><author>Sion Morgan</author><text><![CDATA[ASOUTH Wales Police officer abused his position within the force to access confidential information about former partners and their associates, a court heard yesterday.
Nathan Cantelo, 47, of Cwmbran, pleaded guilty to 11 counts of breaking the data protection act during a 13-month period from 2010.
The defendant, who was dismissed by South Wales Police following a conviction for common assault last April, was fined £1,565 and ordered to pay costs of £1,400 at Cardiff Crown Court.
The breaches were only discovered during an internal audit by South Wales Police's anti-corruption unit, carried out following his arrest for assault. They found that Cantelo had, on numerous occasions from December 3, 2010, accessed the Police NICHE computer records system for personal use.
Simon Goodman, for the prosecution, said an initial police investigation found the defendant had accessed intelligence logs regarding his then partner, a former partner of hers and other individuals connected to the pair.
A second police investigation found the defendant had also been accessing information about individuals including his estranged wife. The court heard that under interview in October 2012, Cantelo told South Wales Police that his actions had only been motivated by "concern for the safety and welfare" of those concerned.
Mr Goodman added that at no point did the defendant "alter or add to the intelligence logs".
"His actions were out of curiosity," Mr Goodman added.
Speaking in mitigation, defence barrister David Leathley said his client had been a police officer for 23-years with an "unblemished record" until 2012.
"He was previously a man of good character," Mr Leathley said.
The court heard how Cantelo had been struggling with alcohol-related issues.
He had also been treated for stress and depression at the time the data breaches occurred.
Mr Leathley stressed his client's actions were "born from morbid curiosity and not to be destructive".
The defence barrister said Mr Cantelo's finances were in an "appalling" state and that he was near-bankruptcy following his trial for assault, during which the defendant hired an expert witness at a cost of £10,000.
Mr Leathley added: "The irony of this case is that years ago it would have been considered 'good-coppering' if a police officer on the street handed over sensitive information about someone he had suspicions about.
"Such actions could have led to the arrest of individuals like Peter Sutcliffe."
Delivering his verdict, Judge Neil Bidder QC said the defendant's actions represented a "gross breach of trust" and a "complete lack of integrity."
He said that despite Castelo's financial prospects the law did not allow him powers of imprisonment for such indictments, meaning he was bound by the court to serve a financial penalty, which would have to be paid back over three years.
Judge Bidder added: "It is very much in the public interest that you should no longer be a serving officer."
]]></text></news-item>