<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7403-6970-5BDF-2824"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Retired executive is animals' best friend</title><source>Palm Beach Post (Florida)</source><author> By Bill DiPaolo   Palm Beach Post Staff Writer </author><text><![CDATA[Herbert Baum, a retired Campbell's Soup executive who lives in Jupiter, is the president of the board of directors of Furry Friends, a no-kill center at 401 Maplewood Drive. He has donated about $2 million to the project since 2009.
Hours for the hospital/clinic are Monday-Saturday, 8 a.m.-6 p.m., closed Sunday. The adoption center is open Monday-Saturday from 11 a.m.-6 p.m.; Sundays noon-5 p.m. The thrift store is open Tuesday-Saturday 10 a.m.-5 p.m. and is Sunday and Monday.
Question: Why was Furry Friends established?
Answer: Furry Friends was established at a time when its predecessor (Safe Harbor) was in disarray. Furry Friends is the operating name for The Humane Society of Greater Jupiter/Tequesta. The new team made changes in organization structure, brought in a new chief veterinarian and vetted its new board of directors.
Q: What services does Furry Friends provide?
A: We are a full-service veterinary clinic and hospital, with three top-rated doctors on staff. We are open to the public and our shelter animals get to benefit from our first-rate medical care as well. We have an adoption facility adjacent to the clinic with a variety of dogs and cats of different breeds, sizes and ages to pick from. Our playroom is available to perspective adopters to bring in their furry family member, so they too can be a part of the adoption process. We have a sizable thrift store located on Indiantown Road, with all types of merchandise including clothes, furniture, collectibles, pet supplies and more, with the proceeds benefiting Furry Friends.
Q: Why should Palm Beach County residents support Furry Friends?
A: Palm Beach County is where the majority of our rescued animals come from as well as the families that adopt them. We rely on donations from the community in order to keep our doors open. We have 37 full- and part-time employees that care for the 250 animals in our care, most of which reside in Palm Beach County. We take in cats and dogs that are sick, injured, abused and abandoned orphans of the streets. We do our best to heal and reintroduce our animals to forever homes.
Q: Does Furry Friends need volunteers?
A: We always need volunteers. When we get them, we cherish them. I am so proud of our group of dog-walker volunteers who each week give our dogs joy by taking them to the beach and for runs in the park. Volunteers are a heart that beats deep with love for our animals. Volunteers reduce our need for a huge staff. Volunteers do everything from helping with care and feeding of our animals to working in the thrift store. Prospective volunteers must complete a personal application. If accepted, each goes through a comprehensive orientation .
Q: Does Furry Friends receive government money?
A: We received $10,000 from the town of Jupiter in February.
Q: What goes on at the Furry Friends property in Palm City?
A: The ranch is now used for socializing big dogs, housing our overflow of cats that someday may all be housed in Palm City and serving as a sanctuary for older horses, pygmy goats, a ram, several pigs chickens, etc. ... that need home and food. It's costly to keep all those animals, but we do it for the love of animals.
For information or to make a contribution, go to furryfriendsadoption.com or call 561-747-5311. bdipaolo@pbpost.com Twitter: @Billdipaolo
]]></text></news-item>