<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7421-FEDF-B264-3CAD"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Team 26 Rides Again For An End To Gun Violence</title><source>The Newtown Bee (Connecticut)</source><author>ELIZA HALLABECK &amp; JOHN VOKET</author><text><![CDATA[Team 26 members and supporters gathered on the steps of Edmond Town Hall on Saturday, March 8, before embarking on a 400-mile journey - the 2nd Annual Sandy Hook Ride on Washington (SHROW) - to show how diverse communities across the nation have one common goal: make streets safer and put an end to the gun-violence epidemic.
The riders arrived in Washington, DC, on Tuesday.
The four-day "rolling rally" included events in Ridgefield, Greenwich, Harlem, N. Y., Morristown, N. J., Doylestown, Penn., Baltimore and College Park, Md., and the Washington National Cathedral before ending at the steps of the US Capitol Building.
Four Newtown residents - Monte Frank, Bill Muzzio, Chris Peck, and Armand Daccache - are members of the team that includes a former Junior World Championships National Team member, US National Team member, Canadian National Team member, Maccabiah World Games Silver Medalist, State and Regional Champions, and Omar Samaha, whose sister Reema was killed in the Virginia Tech shootings.
"We will land at on the west lawn of the National Cathedral at 1 pm on Tuesday," Mr Frank said during Saturday's event.
Specifically, the riders support common sense measures to help curb gun violence
* Requiring all gun buyers pass criminal background checks.
* Instituting a ban of military-style assault weapons and high-capacity magazines.
* Making gun trafficking a federal crime, including real penalties for "straw buyers."
* Strengthening gun ownership restrictions for people with severe mental illness.
Along the ride, Mr Frank said Team 26 looked forward to seeing mothers, fathers, hunters, veter- ans, farmers, bankers, "Americans in pickup trucks and tractor trailers honking at us, encouraging us as we peddle along."
In all the communities Team 26 would ride through, Mr Frank said the message was "that the status quo is not acceptable, that the constant parade of pain must end."
Prior to Saturday's event, Mr Frank told The Bee that the tragedy at Sandy Hook on 12/14 spurred the team into action, "but we ride for all victims of gun violence. We ride to remember them, and to push for stronger gun violence prevention laws to reduce the epidemic of gun violence that plagues our nation, whether it is in a one-stoplight town or our nation's most populous city."
The Edmond Town Hall kickoff Saturday morning featured US Senator Richard Blumenthal (DCT), US Representative Elizabeth Esty (CT-5), Reverend Matthew S. Crebbin, pastor of Newtown Congregational Church; Pastor Sam Saylor, a Hartford clergy member who lost his son to gun violence; Team 26 Founder Monte Frank; Sarah Clements, representing the Junior Newtown Action Alliance; and Mark Barden, father of 12/14 victim Daniel Barden and a representative of Sandy Hook Promise.
Representatives of Ben's Bells Newtown also presented the riders with bells for the ride.
US Representative Jim Himes (CT-4) rode with the team from Newtown to Greenwich. From Newtown, the group headed to Ridgefield for a 10:30 am stop at Ridgefield Community Center, 316 Main Street. That event featured Ridgefield First Selectman Rudy Marconi, Mr Himes, Mr Blumenthal, and Mr Frank.
A 12:30 pm stop at Greenwich Town Hall, 101 Field Point Road, featured Jonathan Perloe, Greenwich Council Against Gun Violence; Mr Himes; Connecticut Attorney General George Jepsen; Greenwich First Selectman Peter Tesei; Greenwich Selectmen Drew Marzullo and David Theis; Mr Frank; Dawn Spearman, founder, You are Not Alone of Bridgeport; Reverend Maxwell Grant, senior minister, Second Congregational Church of Greenwich; Ron Pinciaro, executive director, Connecticut Against Gun Violence; and Rabbi Andrew R. Sklarz, MSW, of Greenwich Reform Synagogue.
When Team 26 arrived in Morristown on Sunday, March 9, the riders were greeted by Maura Sherlach Schwartz, the daughter Mary Sherlach, the Sandy Hook School psychologist killed on 12/14. Moms Demand Action-New Jersey played a role in organizing the Morristown rally, according to MorristownGreen.com.
"Team 26's ride is America's ride," Mr Frank said Saturday. "It's not about Newtown, but about how America is getting together and demanding that our children be allowed to grow up in pursuit of their dreams. We ride as patriots fighting for a safer America for our children. We ride as Americans who respect the Second Amendment and how it is interpreted by the Supreme Court. We ride as mothers and fathers who have watched their children lose their innocence, way too early."
Mr Frank shared why different members of Team 26 are making the journey before saying, "We are bike messengers. Our message to congress is simple: put the politics aside and get it done."
When Mr Blumenthal spoke before the crowd gathered at Edmond Town Hall, he began by pointing out people are serving in the military to preserve democracy and to make America more peaceful.
"What kind of nation fails to preserve peace in our streets and in our neighborhoods and allows the carnage of gun violence to continue?" Mr Blumenthal said. "What kind of nation seeking to preserve democracy abroad allows the will of 90 percent of its people - 90 percent of the American people favor gun violence prevention and background checks and ban on illegal trafficking - to be thwarted by a small minority. Congress is thwarting and stopping the will of the American people by failing to approve common sense measures like background checks, a ban on illegal trafficking, a mental health initiative, and other measures that will help stop the carnage."
According to Mr Blumenthal, since the tragedy at Sandy Hook School, 30,000 people have died as a result of gun violence, and there have been 44 school shootings.
"This failure to act is intolerable and unacceptable," said Mr Blumenthal.
Before Ms Esty spoke, Mr Frank said, "She hasn't let this issue go. She continues to fight on, right from her heart and we thank her so much."
Ms Esty called up all of the children present at the event to stand with Team 26, "because this is what we are fighting for. We are fighting for our children," she said.
Children, she said, are the future of the country.
"We talk about 30,000 people having been killed by gun violence in the last year. Guess what folks? Newtown is about 30,000 people. Imagine if this entire community had guns to their heads and were shot today," said Ms Esty. "That is what the cost is of the political inaction in Washington. It is shameful and it must change."
Ms Esty said "Peace, Hope, and Love," the words written on the back of the Team 26 jackets, is what will prevail over injustice and inaction.
"We will not give up. We will not surrender," said Ms Esty. "However long it takes, this rolling rally is going to keep on rolling however many years it takes to shame our colleagues to have them do the right thing, to have them stand up for the American people, to have them stand up for our children."
When Mr Barden, the advocacy director for Sandy Hook Promise, spoke, he thanked Newtown Action Alliance for organizing the kick-off event for Team 26's journey.
Prior to the events of 12/14, Mr Barden said he was peripherally aware of "the gun violence that plagues our nation on a daily basis."
"But on December 14, 2012, the scourge of gun violence reached right into my world and took the life of our little boy," Mr Barden said.
Since then, Mr Barden said he has devoted his life to learning about the depth and magnitude of gun violence.
"I know there is no quick and simple fix. Gun violence knows no boundaries," Mr Barden said, "from inner cities to suburbs, cross economic, social, racial, geographic spectrum, the chances are that either you or somebody you know has been effected by gun violence directly."
Mr Barden received applause and one, "We love you Mark," from the crowd when he said there is a growing number of people who no longer accept "this as a way of life. There's a growing number of people who know that to be a true patriot means that you embrace the moral obligation to protect our communities, our neighborhoods, and our children from gun violence."
Representing the Junior Newtown Action Alliance (Jr NAA), Newtown High School senior Sarah Clements said she was speaking as a student, a close friend of Mr Frank, a daughter of a 12/14 survivor, a supporter of Team 26, and as the founder of the Jr NAA.
"America has been at war for most of the 18 years I have been alive," Sarah said. "I'm a child of the Iraq and Afghanistan conflicts, and yet I am also a child of the domestic war we continue to wage today. A war that has no name, a war that can most definitely be labeled as a public health crisis, a war that we have yet to fully acknowledge as a collective nation, and a war that I personally shamefully failed to see until it arrived at our doorstep here in Newtown on that dark day in December 2012."
Sarah said she suspects she knew hours after the events of 12/14, the only way she would be able to move forward is if she helped bring about change, "so that no one else had to go through what we did."
"Yet they have," said Sarah. "As you heard today, more than 40 school shootings have occurred, and hundreds of young people have died from gun shot wounds in the city of Chicago alone since 12/14. Children and teens in the US are 65 times more likely to be killed with a gun than our peers in the [United Kingdom]."
She later said, "We see profit made from weapons proliferation and fear mongering from the gun lobby, deemed more important and useful than the lives of our peers. We see a nation where so many of my friends' fates have teetered on the barrel of a gun, and we turn our backs each time. We see a nation where our young people are tired of folks looking at their block and being surprised they have made it so far. We see a nation where 20 students and six teachers can be gunned down in their classrooms with no real action on the federal level in response, and we see a nation where we too often wait for the voice of a loved one to be muted before we exercise our own."
Before thanking Team 26 for what it is doing, Sarah said if she and her friends have learned anything it is that their rights are worthless unless they fight for others to have them too.
"We can be and are one voice when it comes to the change we must make," said Sarah.
Four hundred miles later, when Team 26 arrived at the US Capitol on Tuesday, March 12, a press conference organized by Ms Esty convened.
Mr Frank said, at the conference, that he was heartened by the support Team 26 received in its long ride to Washington, D. C., including from the police in Morristown, N. J., who got out of their cruisers to salute the riders and the man in Pennsylvania who shouted, "Don't give up y'all. Don't give up."
(Reports by The Connecticut Mirror were used in this story.)
]]></text></news-item>