<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="747D-F053-0419-59E9"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>SA-RWANDA RELATIONS. Darling dictator checked</title><source>Financial Mail (South Africa)</source><author>Troye Lund</author><text><![CDATA[SA-RWANDA RELATIONS
Darling dictator checked
In a dramatic move SA draws the line against Kagame for breaking the law
WHAT IT MEANS
EXPULSION OF RWANDAN ENVOYS NOT A DIPLOMACY ISSUE
KIGALI'S ECONOMIC MIRACLE NOW UNDER SCRUTINY
As SA looked set to cut diplomatic ties with Rwanda this week, the stand-off was being described as the country's worst diplomatic crisis since 1995, when Nelson Mandela persuaded Commonwealth leaders to suspend Nigeria after it executed nine dissidents led by the Ogoniland environmentalist, Ken Saro-Wiwa.
But this isn't a foreign diplomacy issue. It's about a violation of SA law. While this could have some implications for SA relations with other countries on the continent, the incident has also unnerved Rwanda's friends. They are now subjecting the Rwandan economic miracle under President Paul Kagame to a lot more scrutiny.
SA expelled three Rwandan diplomats and one Burundian diplomatic after the State Security Agency (SSA) linked them to last week's assassination attempt on former Rwandan army chief Gen Faustin Kayumba Nyamwasa. This was the fourth attempt on Nyamwasa's life since 2010, when he came to SA to seek political asylum.
Nyamwasa has been in the SA witness protection programme and the latest attack on his life was at the safe house where he has been living under the close guard of the SA government.
The SSA now believes it has proof that Rwanda's government was behind the assassination attempt.
he expelled diplomats had been providing money, logistical support and key information in diplomatic bags, which would not be searched, to the assassins sent by Rwanda to eliminate opposition politicians.
The Rwandan courts have declared Nyamwasa and his colleague, Patrick Karegeya, guilty of being terrorists. On New Year's Day this year, Karegeya was found murdered in a Sandton hotel. Kagame denied any involvement. But he warned that "no-one will betray Rwanda and get away with it".
Kagame reacted to his diplomats being expelled by doing the same to six SA diplomats in Kigali, Rwanda's capital. Rwandan foreign minister Louise Mushikiwabo warned: "We have expelled six SA diplomats in reciprocity and concern at SA's harbouring of dissidents responsible for terrorist attacks in Rwanda."
SA Institute of International Affairs research associate Tom Wheeler, a former SA ambassador, argues that SA's decision to expel the diplomats doesn't indicate any shift in SA foreign policy.
"Africa remains at the top of SA's foreign diplomacy agenda. This hasn't changed. SA has acted in a correct way. It had no option. You can't have people coming into the country to assassinate others," says Wheeler.
Stephanie Wolters, of the Institute for Security Studies, agrees. Though SA's failure to issue a statement explaining its position was a public relations blunder, she says, Pretoria has the moral high ground in this case.
"This isn't about foreign diplomacy. SA law is being violated as part of Rwanda's state-sponsored assassination of opposition politicians," says Wolters, who adds that SA is also obliged to show that asylum seekers are protected and taken seriously.
The US government, which Kagame considers among his closest allies, appears to be in no doubt about who is behind the attempts on Nyamwasa's life. The US embassy in Pretoria issued a terse statement that warned: "Efforts to silence dissidents run counter to Rwanda's democratic development.
"We urge the government of Rwanda to respect the rights of members of all political parties and political leaders."
Kagame is the darling of Western governments. While at pains to make amends for its failure to stop the 1994 genocide in Rwanda, the West has credited Kagame for rebuilding his country after the genocide. They have awarded him honorary degrees for making Rwanda the eighth easiest place to start a new business and for reducing corruption. In the process, they have turned a blind eye to the police state that Kagame has created.
They have ignored the way opposition parties have been banned from participating in elections, and how government critics are murdered or, if they are newspapers, shut down. Kagame has also escaped censure over what the UN is convinced is Rwandan-sponsored support for rebels in the eastern Democratic Republic of Congo. The New York Times has now dubbed Kagame as the "darling dictator".
On the African continent, the jury is out about how other East African countries like Kenya will react and whether they will take sides on this issue.
The potential for any country to take Kagame's side would have been limited if the SA government had not kept silent for so long about why it acted as it did. This unexplained silence could play into the hands of Kagame, who is known to be a master at public relations.
But it's also clear that the Rwandan leader won't be able to rely on as much blanket support from his friends as he has in the past.
lundt@fm.co.za
Paul Kagame
Credited with rebuilding Rwanda
but now attracting the disapproval
of the US and SA governments
]]></text></news-item>