<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7558-20AD-C5C0-C058"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>For the kids</title><source>Springfield News-Leader (Missouri)</source><author>By, Christine Temple</author><text><![CDATA[After Hailey Owens was abducted and killed last month, Cherise Carter started navigating through the many Facebook pages created in the 10-year-old's honor.
She found a lot of concerned citizens who were passionate about keeping kids safe.
But she wanted more than discussion, she wanted action. So one week after Hailey was killed, Carter founded the Springfield Guardians Association. It's a grassroots effort that encourages businesses to become safe havens for kids as they walk home from school. It also wants people across the city to get to know their neighbors and take ownership of their streets.
The heart of Springfield Guardians is rallying the community to work together to keep kids safe.
There are about 900 'likes' on the Guardians' Facebook page and Carter said well over 200 people have RSVP'd for the first meeting on Saturday. Carter said the wide-spread support tells her she has a good idea.
"Since I have started, I have literally made this my passion," she said. "If I could ever keep one kid from going through what Hailey went through ... it would be so worth it."
Carter said the group would take a multifaceted approach to try to protect kids.
There are 22 Neighborhood Watch groups registered with the Springfield Police Department. Carter said she wants Springfield Guardians to be the hub that connects those groups to create a kind of city-wide watch. She said she's open to more ideas about how to connect these groups.
Carter said people should introduce their kids to trusted adults in their community that could help them if they are in trouble.
"The more you take pride in your community, the more proactive you are in your community, the less crime you have," Carter said.
Idania Duncan, Springfield Guardians director of operations, said people need to think differently when it comes to protecting their kids.
"How do we keep kids safe? We need to go about it completely differently because the monster is Joe from next door," she said referencing Hailey's abduction and slaying.
Her alleged killer, charged with first-degree murder, armed criminal action and child kidnapping, Craig Michael Wood, was a Springfield schools employee with no criminal past, except for a guilty plea in his early 20s to marijuana possession and a misdemeanor charge for illegally killing a wild turkey, according to court documents.
Duncan said getting to know your neighbors and being aware of their activity is key to curbing violence.
Springfield Officer Benjamin Lord said Carter and Duncan are absolutely right. He called Neighborhood Watch groups "vital" to safety in the community.
He also said when a child is missing, the information those groups provide to law enforcement is critical.
"If you're really familiar with your neighbors, then you're going to be able to identify something odd going on at your neighbor's house," he said.
Lord said the Springfield Police Department offers a program four times a year that citizens can attend to start a neighborhood watch. They learn observation skills, how to spot suspicious behavior and how to effectively report issues to the police.
Since the group was recently formed, Lord said he was not familiar with Springfield Guardians, but he can see a lot of benefits from a group whose goal is to get the community involved in keeping kids safe. He said he looks forward to working with the organization.
Carter said communication across neighborhoods could help police find missing kids faster.
"Get those lines of communication open because somewhere in the details, someone is going to know something," she said.
"We want to teach people, if you see something, that is what you need to get to the police right away."
Duncan and Carter said they want people to move away from the idea that they need to be polite in possibly dangerous situations.
Carter said, "We've all been so conditioned to not make waves, to mind your own business."
Duncan said people should trust their gut instinct and not be afraid to call the police if they see something suspicious.
"If the person's innocent, he'll say, 'I'm so sorry,' but if he's not, he's going to run with his tail between his legs."
Carter added that Springfield Guardians advocates "do not approach" in suspicious situations. People should always contact the police and not take matters into their own hands.
Carter said it took Hailey's abduction and slaying to wake the community up to realize that everyone can play a part in keeping Springfield safe and that it's not solely a job for law enforcement.
"We want to build safeguards between police," she said. "This way, we'll have a net of safety."
Businesses along the routes where kids walk to school, parks or other facilities would be asked to display a sign in their window that indicates to kids that they are a safe place for kids to go if they are in trouble. This is similar to the national Safe Place campaign, but Guardian Businesses will primarily focus on helping kids in immediate danger.
"If a child runs in here because they feel threatened, they're being bullied, someone is chasing them, this is what you do," Carter said.
"Call the police, call their parents and keep them calm."
McAlister's Deli general manager Tiffany Howard said she loved the idea. The restaurant is located one-fifth of a mile from Sunshine Elementary School.
"I would be more than happy to be a part of something like that," she said. "We probably should have done this a long time ago."
Duncan said, "At the end of the day, it does come back to personal responsibility. There are thousands of people in Springfield, (police) can't protect everyone. I really want to sit down with some police officers and say, 'What can we do to help you be more effective?'"
Carter said everyone becomes safer when people take responsibility for their community.
"It takes somebody saying, 'We can do something about this, let's get together,'" she said.
"I just happened to be the person that started the page, but immediately there were so many good, hardworking people that wanted to do something. There's power in numbers."
Want to go?
What: Springfield Guardians Association public meeting
Where: Library Center's auditorium, 4653 S. Campbell Ave.
When: 5:30 p.m. Saturday
Information: springfieldguardians.wordpress.com; springfieldguardians@gmail.com
Starting a neighborhood watch
Neighborhood Watch is a program organized by citizens to reduce crime in their communities, according to the Springfield Police Department's website. Groups work with law enforcement to report suspicious activities and implement home security measures and precautions.
"One of the most important steps you can take to prevent or lessen crime in your neighborhood is to start a Neighborhood Watch program," according to the police department.
Those interested in starting a Neighborhood Watch, can contact the Springfield Police Department Crime Prevention at 874-2113 or email CrimePreventionUnit@springfieldmo.gov
]]></text></news-item>