<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="755F-4FEF-F53A-F4DC"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Euphemisms to the corporate rescue</title><source>The Gazette (Montreal)</source><author>MARK ABLEY, The Gazette</author><text><![CDATA[Until recently, "fracking" was a very rare word. Yet, over the last few years, in Quebec and elsewhere, it has become a well-known term and a political issue. Will Anticosti Island effectively cease to be a wildlife reserve and become a centre for large-scale energy production instead? If so, credit or blame advances in the technology of fracking - a term that is short for "hydraulic fracturing," and that refers to the process of breaking up underground rock by injecting large volumes of water, sand and chemicals at high pressure, thereby releasing oil or gas. The word is short, ugly and memorable.
Rock formations aren't simple to shatter. The renowned American physicist Edward Teller wanted to do so by means of nuclear explosives. He laid out his vision, using the term "hydraulic fracturing," in 1968. Fifteen years earlier, Oil and Gas Journal had printed an article under the headline 'Fracking' - A New Exploratory Tool. It was a new
word as well. Yet for decades, "hydraulic fracturing" remained the expression of choice. "Fracking" first appeared in The Gazette in October 2009; last year, it was mentioned in no fewer than 50 stories. The main drawback of fracking is the environmental damage it causes, notably to the water table. And, as so often happens with controversial devices or techniques, there have been efforts to find milder-sounding euphemisms. In a bucolic corner of southern England, for instance, a landowner asked for permission to engage in "exploratory oil drilling." The company that was hoping to conduct the drilling explained to local villagers that the work would involve "prospecting with possible stimulation." "Stimulation" is a gentler term than "fracking with hydrochloric acid, ethylene glycol and other toxic chemicals." Even so, the villagers managed to discover what was being proposed.
Another word that attracts euphemisms is "drone," which the Oxford English Dictionary defines as "a pilotless aircraft or missile directed by remote control." The original sense of drone belongs to a male honeybee, whose sole mission in life is to impregnate the queen; this is such an arduous job that drones are exempted from collecting honey as worker bees do. The low sound of bees buzzing also came to be called a drone. From those ancient beginnings, "drone" turned into a noun for anyone who avoids work and a verb for talking endlessly (it's often applied to politicians). In his poem Against the Scots, the medieval English writer John Skelton complained about "The rude rank Scots, like drunken drones."
I imagine the Scots complained about Skelton, too.
The meaning of drone as an unpiloted aircraft goes back to the 1940s. It's an excellent metaphor, I think, as it combines a suggestion of engine noise with the absence of a working human inside the machine. Yet because of the word's negative associations, General Atomics, a California firm that is the world's leading manufacturer of drones, recently told a British government committee that "drone" should be abandoned in favour of some other term. All its suggestions were initialisms: UAV (unmanned aerial vehicle), UAS (unmanned aircraft system) and the latest favourite, RPA (remotely piloted aircraft). When you string a few initials together, you create a term devoid of emotions, of connotations. To say that, "At least 2,700 people have been killed by drone strikes" creates a different impression than "At least 2,700 people have been killed by RPAs." President Obama has so far resisted the temptation. In his 2014 State of the Union address, he declared: "America must move off a permanent war footing. That's why I've imposed prudent limits on the use of drones."
"With St. Patrick's approaching," writes Allan Swift of St. Lambert, "maybe you could explain to us the origin and meaning of O, as in O'Toole, etc."
I'm glad to oblige. Various Internet sites say that "O" means "son of " in Irish Gaelic. But that isn't quite right. The Gaelic way of saying "son of" is "Mac" - very familiar in Scottish names, but common in Irish ones, too.
"MacDermott," for example, is the son of Diarmuid. In fact "O" means "grandson of" or "from the clan of," and therefore the great actor Peter O'Toole came from the clan of Tuathail.
Gaelic spelling is so extraordinary, I'd need a few pints of Guinness to explain it.
markabley@sympatico.ca
]]></text></news-item>