<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="75FC-5E16-F9B0-9C90"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>was pilot angry at election?; Mystery of missing flight MH370: New clues emerge as authorities raid apartment</title><source>Daily Mirror</source><author>BEN GLAZE ; JOSH LAYTON</author><text><![CDATA[THE pilot of the missing Malaysia Airlines jet is pictured in a T-shirt with a Democracy Is Dead slogan as fears emerge he could have hijacked the plane as an anti-government protest.
We can reveal Captain Zaharie Ahmad Shah was a fervent supporter of his country's opposition leader who was jailed for homosexuality - illegal in Malaysia - only hours before flight MH370 vanished with 239 passengers and crew on board.
Colleagues have told investigators he had planned to attend the trial, but police have yet to establish if he was at the court.
And in a new twist, it emerged that the pilot's wife - from whom he is separated -and three children moved out of the family's home the day before the plane's disappearance.
It has also emerged investigators are examining two laptops taken from Capt Shah's home in a secret raid.
One is thought to contain data from a homemade flight simulator and could show routes he had been training on. His personal laptop was not found during the low-key visits - which had been denied by officials - and is understood to have been with him in the cockpit of the plane. FBI agents from the US are helping Malaysian police investigate the political and religious backgrounds of both Capt Shah and his co-pilot. The revelations came after Malaysian Prime Minister Najib Razak confirmed the Boeing 777 was deliberately diverted from its route between his country's capital Kuala Lumpur and Beijing.
Investigators said trackers aboard the plane, which transmit its location to airtraffic controllers, were disabled moments after take-off last Friday.
The airliner could have flown on for seven hours after vanishing from radar over the South China Sea. Police yesterday again raided Capt Shah's home in a Kuala Lumpur suburb. They spent two hours at the gated property and left carrying small bags. Inside, the experienced pilot, who has worked for Malaysia Airlines since 1981, had a Boeing 777 flight simulator. But his friend Peter Chong insisted Capt Shah, 53, would be "the last person" to hijack the aircraft.
He told the Sunday Mirror: "I would trust that man with my life. He loves people and being involved in something like that would hurt people. I would not believe he was involved in any way at all.
"If I went on a plane and was allowed the choice of a pilot, I would choose Captain Zaharie." Mr Chong last saw his friend two weeks ago. They had agreed to meet this week and the pilot had been "his normal, cheerful self ", he said.
But Capt Shah's political background is now a focus of the investigation. On Twitter and YouTube he has backed human rights groups and campaigners for internet freedom in Malaysia, which has strict Government controls.
The slogan on his T-shirt, as he poses with his pal Peter, is dated May 5, 2013 - the day of elections which led to violent protests against alleged poll fraud. Opposition leader Anwar Ibrahim called activists on to the streets and Capt Shah has "liked" videos by Ibrahim posted on YouTube. Ibrahim was sentenced to five years' jail on gay sex charges on March 7, provoking condemnation across the country. The jet vanished early on the 8th.
Experts say it could have crossed 14 countries and landed in Kazakhstan or crashed into the Indian Ocean.
Mr Chong, a political secretary to a Malaysian MP, described his friend as "a very caring person who puts people ahead of himself ". He said the pilot installed the mock-up of a 777 cockpit at his home only "to share his joy of flying with friends".
Capt Shah posted snaps of himself with the simulator on his Facebook page, along with another showing him brandishing a meat cleaver and holding a bowl of mince. Mr Chong said Capt Shah would have done everything to ensure his 227 passengers were safe in the event of a hijack. He was angry at suggestions the pilot could have "gone rogue" and hijacked his own plane.
Mr Chong said: "I just do not believe it until there is concrete evidence. What I hope has happened is that it has been hijacked (by a passenger), landed somewhere and negotiations are going on." Investigators believe someone with flying experience steered Flight MH370 off its planned route. A Malaysian official said the hijacking theory was now "conclusive". Radar tracks show the plane climbing and descending in unusual patterns, which should have alerted air traffic controllers that something was wrong. MH370 flew to 45,000ft - almost 2,000ft above its maximum recommended height - then descended to 23,000ft.
It changed course at least twice from its scheduled route - first to fly west back towards Malaysia then north-west into an air lane for commercial planes.
A total of 57 ships, 48 aircraft and 13 nations are taking part in the search. Loaded with maximum fuel, a Boeing 777 can fly 7,725 miles. But aviation experts said it was unlikely it would have that much in the tanks for its scheduled flight. If MH370 flew through other countries' airspaces it should have triggered national air defences.
Flight Global's operations and safety editor David Learmount said: "If it has flown north, why have none of the countries it has flown over said anything? " They would have sent up aircraft to investigate. If it's gone south there's nothing there until you hit Antarctica."
Boeing 777s need a runway up to a mile long to land, making it unlikely it touched down safely on a remote Asian strip. "I can't think which airfield it would be - and what would they do with the passengers?" said Mr Learmount.
Malaysian authorities have been criticised for keeping the possibility of a hijack secret for eight days. Mr Learmount said their "total incompetence is unforgivable", and created more agony for families desperate for news.
Malaysian PM Razak said: "We can say with a high degree of certainty that the aircraft communications addressing and reporting system was disabled just before it reached the east coast of peninsular Malaysia. Shortly afterwards the transponder was switched off.
Satellite: Signals from jet "From this point onwards, the Royal Malaysian Air Force primary radar showed an aircraft believed to be MH370 did indeed turn back. It then flew in a westerly direction back over peninsular Malaysia before turning north west.
"These movements are consistent with deliberate action by someone on the plane." ben.glaze@sundaymirror.co.uk
]]></text></news-item>