<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="75FE-874F-9B63-F1C2"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Aamir Khan: I take money for Satyamev Jayate, I think I should take money for the work I do!</title><source>Bollywood Life</source><author>Letty Mariam Abraham | PTI</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 17, 2014 (Bollywood Life:http://www.bollywoodlife.com/ Delivered by Newstex) The superstar, who is currently busy with his TV show Satyamev Jayate says that his monetary earnings from the programme are less but he is enriched by the experience of meeting different peopleThere were reports that Aamir Khan[1] was not charging anything for the show but the actor said, 'I do take money for the show… I think I should take money for the work I do. I used to earn more money through ads but I don't do much ads now. If I look at it financially, commercially… then I am earning less. (But) My earning is more in another way… like meeting people from various walks of life, touching their lives. I feel enriched,' said Aamir[2].
Satyamev Jayate[3] has been one of the most influential television shows in the recent times. The first season saw Aamir raising some sensitive topics like female infanticide, child sexual abuse, medical malpractice, dowry system, love marriages and honour killings among others. In the second season, which kicked off on March 2, issues like rape and police reforms were raised. The actor, however, did not elaborate on the subjects, which would be highlighted in the upcoming episodes. On ensuing polls, he said, 'I will come forward for an issue… but I will not campaign… support any party or person. I know people in politics. I don't want to influence anyone. I think youngsters should vote… think and vote.'Aamir Khan cheats his fans: Watch video![4]In the past, Aamir did support social activist Anna Hazare when he was fighting for corruption. On Aam Aadmi Party [5]leader Arvind Kejriwal, Aamir said, 'It is a new party let's see what kind of work they do. I don't want to comment on them right now.' His good friend Salman Khan too would be seen in a social show Mission Sapne, where the celebrity would be leading the life of a common man for a day and give the earnings to them (common man). 'I am very happy Salman is doing this kind of a show. I wish more people from industry come and support it (social issues[6]),' added Aamir. [1]: http://www.bollywoodlife.com/news-gossip/will-aamir-khans-loss-be-hrithik-roshans-gain/ [2]: http://www.bollywoodlife.com/news-gossip/why-has-aamir-khan-bought-rs-10-crore-bomb-proof-car/ [3]: http://www.bollywoodlife.com/news-gossip/satyamev-jayate-2-review-aamir-khan-needs-to-up-his-game/ [4]: http://www.bollywoodlife.com/news-gossip/aamir-khan-cheats-his-fans-watch-video/ [5]: http://www.bollywoodlife.com/news-gossip/why-is-aamir-khan-not-a-supporter-of-arvind-kejriwals-aap/ [6]: http://www.bollywoodlife.com/news-gossip/aamir-khans-satyamev-jayate-generates-rs-22-crore-for-social-initiatives/

]]></text></news-item>