<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7627-4DCB-9B14-075F"><date>2014-03-15</date><title></title><source>The Star (South Africa)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[RABBIE SERUMULA
rabbie.serumula@inl.co.za
Area focus - Houghton
History
The quiet suburb of Houghton is located north-east of the city centre. It developed as a residential hub during the turn of the 20th century, mostly due to the Johannesburg Consolidated Investment Company (JCI) which was founded in 1889 by Barney Barnato, a British entrepreneur. JCI was a major force in South African mining for over 100 years. It owned large industrial and property holdings, including the Houghton Estate in northern Johannesburg.
Houghton has traditionally been informally divided into two areas, Upper Houghton and Lower Houghton. Upper Houghton is the hilly southern portion located on a ridge, while the northern Lower Houghton is flatter, and has a grid street pattern, with portions lying on both sides of the M1 freeway. Upper and Lower Houghton are separated by the East-West section of Houghton Drive. Upper Houghton has been declared a National Heritage Area. As a historically wealthy area, the suburb consists of numerous lavish upper-class homes, along with a few blocks of flats and office parks. The suburb is architecturally varied with good examples of art deco building, particularly evident in some of the blocks of flats.
The most famous resident of Houghton was Nelson Mandela, who died at his Lower Houghton home on December 5 last year , surrounded by his wife, Graça Machel and members of his family.
What two Estate agents say
RE/MAX
Adrian Goslett, CEO of RE/MAX of Southern Africa, says that property in Houghton is mostly freestanding homes, sectional title units and estates to a lesser extent. Goslett notes that from 2004 to 2006 property prices in the area saw a steady but marginal increase, however, from 2007 until 2009 prices rose by much greater increments.
"Prices dipped slightly in 2010, but recovered in 2011 with the price of a freestanding home hitting a record high of R4.6 million. The average price of a sectional title unit was around R900 000 at the time," he said. In 2012 prices saw another dip, with the average price of a freestanding home dropping to around R4.1 million and a sectional title unit costing approximately R894 000. "Although freestanding home prices have remained stable so far, the average price of a sectional title unit has seen an increase and is currently around R1.1 million," he explained.
Goslett said the demographics of recent buyers in Houghton is fairly evenly distributed between the various age groups. The majority of buyers are aged between 50 and 64 years old, then 36 and 49 years old and a smaller percentage is under the age of 35 years old. "Currently the highest number of homeowners in the suburb is those between the ages of 36 and 49 years old," he said.Goslett said while the majority of the sales in the area from 2004 to 2007 were freestanding properties, sectional title units became more popular during 2008, outselling freestanding homes ever since.
Contact RE/MAX at 011 274 '8
SOTHEBY'S INTERNATIONAL
Lew Geffen, chairman of Sotheby's International Realty in the country said his advice to property investors right now is to buy as much land as they can in the best areas they can afford - almost irrespective of the condition of any buildings on the property - because substantial land parcels in sought after areas are set to become an increasingly rare commodity.
There are at least two factors currently working in concert that will significantly boost the value of properties and the potential returns from them over the next few years in Houghton, said Geffen.
"In the first place, the new spatial plans for our large cities lean heavily towards densification and better use of their land and resources to accommodate the rapid urbanization of our population. And this predisposes city councils to the subdivision - albeit within limits - of the very large stands that are still fairly common in such affluent suburbs as Houghton.
"Secondly, steep increases in property rates and maintenance costs over the past few years, as well as security concerns, are prompting many wealthy homeowners to consider modern clusters or high-end sectional title homes as alternatives to the large houses they have traditionally favoured.
"Meanwhile those fortunate enough to already own large stands in the heritage suburbs should seriously investigate the possibility of subdividing them and developing them to accommodate three or four homes - one for their own use, perhaps, and the others for sale or to let."
Contact Sotheby's at 011 438 7300
Showcase properties 1
RE/MAX
Regal mansion is located in a the heart of Houghton estate. It has a 24hour guarded gate and spans 700ms on 1700ms land. A landscaped garden with a heated pool leads to a covered patio with roof awnings. This wooden floor house has an open plan kitchen with granite stone tops, a formal lounge, dining room and study. Four bedrooms, three bathrooms, a Jacuzzi, three gas places and staff accommodations with bathrooms. The selling price is R9.5 million
Showcase properties 2
SOTHEBY'S INTERNATIONAL
This large house on a huge stand is located in a quiet and affluent part of Houghton. It boasts lovely reception room leading on to a covered patio overlooking a pool. four large bedrooms, three bathrooms and a study. Approval to subdivide the stand into three portions is also already in place. The asking price for this home is R8 million
WHAT THE COUNCILLOR SAYS
Q and A with Houghton (Ward 73) Councillor, Marcelle Ravid
Q - Are there any pressing service and infrastructure problems in the area?
A - Ageing infrastructure such as water pipes, electricity cables and roads. Joburg Water fixes them in one spot and then they burst a few meters down the road. Excavations can remain open for months until done. There is a considerable upgrade taking place at the local substation on Athol-Oaklands Road. Hopefully this will alleviate some of the problems in the area.
Q - Are the roads in a good state, is the water and electricity supply reliable and does the area have what is needed to attract investment in property, both commercial and residential property?
A - Some roads are in a very bad state. There will be resurfacing of a few streets in Houghton (8th and 9th Avenues) in this financial year. Pavements are in an appalling state of disrepair. Reinstatements are not properly monitored by the Johannesburg Road Agency, and many companies do not return to complete a job. I have to keep eagle eyes out for contractors and make sure I have their contact details for follow ups. I sometimes wonder if people will ever walk on the pavements again, missing covers can be a serious hazard to pedestrians and runners.
I have noticed on two occasions recently that City Power has objected to applications for rezoning in Houghton. Obviously they are worried about capacity. Interesting to note that five years ago, City Power objected to the Houghton Golf Course development for that reason, but miraculously withdrew the objection just before the hearing.
Q- Does the area have problems with, for example, illegal buildings?
A- Yes, there is many illegal buildings. The council's planning department have a backlog of plans to pass as it is under-resourced by about 50% of its full manpower compliment. And apparently the problem of obtaining clearance certificates for properties sold is still an enormous obstacle to the completion of property transfers which is hindering the whole real estate industry. People can't complete the sales and purchase agreements.
Q - Are you happy with the mayor's pledge to fix northern suburbs roads which were neglected. What about other infrastructure?
A - The Mayor's pledge is welcome but a it's a drop in the ocean. And where will the budget come from? Only from cutting down on other necessities.
Q - What do you think would attract residents and businesses to the area, and what about the area is unattractive?
A- Houghton is still an extremely desirable residential address. The introduction of the Gautrain had influenced the planning and Oxford Road is now allowed high, mixed use densities. The heritage area of Upper Houghton will safeguard the important heritage houses there. This needs to be done in Lower Houghton as well.
If general maintenance was done systematically and the basics were looked after, the area would be far more attractive. The Upper Houghton Association and the Lower Houghton Residents Association do an enormous amount of work behind the scenes to try fill in the gaps where the council fails.
Q - What issues/complaints have you as a councillor had to deal with?
A- Incorrect billing and incorrect valuations. Lately the sudden billing of second stands or double billing for rates. I managed, after many months to get a ruling from Valuation Services, that if one has proof in one's Title Deeds that two or more stands are notarially tied, the second stand must be zero-rated by the department. Many people have been double billed since July last year when the new rates took effect. If there is no proof of notarially tied stands, the council has recently decided to charge rates on the other stands as "vacant land" which is charged at a higher rate.
Other issues include very sloppy by-law enforcement; illegal businesses, illegal signage, illegal noise pollution, illegal dumping, illegal drinking in public, illegal shebeens, over crowding of properties, deterioration of unoccupied properties, illegal hawking and illegal parking.
Taxis and buses not using their dedicated routes along main arteries and using side, residential streets instead is also an issue.
People also report potholes, broken street lights, road markings, broken robots, flooding due to storm water inlets and outlets not being cleaned and maintained.
Q- Is crime in the area an issue? As a councillor are you involved in dealing with security issues in the area?
A- Crime in Houghton could have been a bigger issue but for the private security companies that patrol the streets 24 hours a day. Crime in the Orange Grove section of the ward however, is very high.
Crime stats
The number of reported burglaries at non-residential premises remained the same at 76. Burglaries at residential premises showed a slight decrease from 320 to 308. Theft of motor vehicles and motorcycles increased slight from 201 to 206. Theft out or from motor vehicles however, increased from 306 to 356
The total number of property-related crimes reported at Honeydew police station in the 2012 and 2013 calendar years showed an increase from 906 to 949
Sources:
http://www.joburghappenings.co.za/houghton_homepage.htm
http:// www.sa-venues.com /searchga/houghton.php
http:// www.crimestatssa.com
http:// www.safarinow.com /destinations/houghton/hub.aspx
]]></text></news-item>