<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="76A3-8ED0-4029-A93D"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Arvind Kejriwal set to contest against Narendra Modi in Varanasi</title><source>The Economic Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NEW DELHI | BANGALORE: Deep in the heartland, David is set to take on Goliath. Arvind Kejriwal has been asked by his Aam Aadmi Party to contest against the man who would be prime minister, Narendra Modi of Bharatiya Janata Party, in Varanasi. And he’s almost accepted.
While he did build up to what seemed like an announcement of his intent to do so, Kejriwal didn’t quite say that he would be pitting himself against Modi. Instead, he told AAP supporters in Bangalore on Sunday to wait till March 23, when he plans to hold a rally in Varanasi. But he also revealed a key element of AAP’s strategy against Modi — derisive comments about the Gujarat chief minister seeking a second “safe” seat from his home state.
“That will mean he’s the leader of Gujarat, not someone who can be the prime minister of the country... We want a brave prime minister, not someone looking for a ‘safe’ seat,” Kejriwal said.
The AAP convenor declared that he was “ready” to take on Modi if the people of Varanasi supported him. But that he will take on Modi is a virtual certainty, senior AAP leaders told ET. “The party had made it clear right from the beginning that it would like Arvind to fight Modi. Now it’s just a matter of official endorsement by AAP’s political advisory committee. Arvind is a democratic man and will acquiesce to the majority decision,” said AAP spokesperson Ashutosh.
AAP had deliberately kept up the willhe-won’t-he suspense regarding Kejriwal’s candidature as it was waiting for BJP to first announce Modi’s seat. “We wanted it to be a battle of equals and therefore we were keen to pit Arvind provided Modi contested outside Gujarat,” said a senior AAP leader, who did not want to be identified.
While BJP announced Modi’s Varanasi candidature late Saturday night, the AAP leader played his cards close to his chest. “Many people asking me – ‘Will I contest against Modi ji?’ I will talk on this issue in today’s rally at Bangalore,” Kejriwal tweeted.
At the Bangalore rally, he said, “The party wants me to contest against Modi. It’s a big challenge. I am not here for power and money, I want to serve my country. I am ready for this challenge.” He then added the rider: “I am going to Varanasi on the 23rd (of March) and I urge everyone to join me there.
The party ticket does not matter to me. I’ll contest from this seat only if the people there want me to.” Kejriwal, according to party ideologue Yogendra Yadav, will only contest from one seat.
“The AAP strategy would be to attack Modi for his (likely) decision to contest from two seats,” said another leader on condition of anonymity. Yadav added: “The debate over whether Modi will contest from one or two seats shows the seriousness of his candidature.
Arvind will not do that because he doesn’t believe in playing safe.” Kejriwal's likely decision exemplifies the party’s determination to take on the strongest contenders. “It's an example of the newer kind of politics that AAP wants to bring in,” said political analyst Achin Vanaik.
“You don't have to agree or disagree with Kejriwal to recognise that what he's doing is something courageous and he is open to a direct fight with the Opposition's strongest leader regardless of the outcome. This is in contrast to, say, a Modi who seems to be looking to fight from two seats.”
Although Varanasi is a BJP stronghold, AAP is confident that Kejriwal’s fight will be more than symbolic. The party’s confidence stems from the fact that the Lok Sabha constituency is made up of five assembly constituencies, of which three are largely urban, and essentially media-dense areas.
“Moreover, our organisational strength in UP is far ahead than in other states,” said AAP member Adarsh Shastri, who is in charge of drafting AAP’s Uttar Pradesh vision document.
On the stage in Bangalore, the former Delhi chief minister was accompanied by AAP candidates in Karnataka, including former Infosys director V Balakrishnan. Kejriwal devoted the larger part of his Hindi speech to attacking Modi and BJP, and wondered if former Karnataka chief minister BS Yeddyurappa had been readmitted into BJP so he could be made the next petroleum minister and B Sriramulu the next minister for mining.
This is a reference to both men facing corruption allegations, besides the campaigns that AAP has been running against Reliance Industries and coal block allocations, among others.
Kejriwal ridiculed Modi’s claims on Gujarat being corruption-free and well-developed. He joked that Modi’s Gujarat was very transparent even in corruption. Kejriwal urged the people to defeat Modi and accused the Gujarat CM of snatching farmers’ land and giving it to big industrialists.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>