<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="76B4-3235-2DE3-6EDF"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Programme summary of Russian NTV "Segodnya" news 1500 gmt 14 Mar 14</title><source>BBC Monitoring Former Soviet Union - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Segodnya presented by Igor Poletayev, times are gmt.
1. 1500 Headlines: Crimea referendum, Donetsk situation, Kiev gun market, business news.
2. 1501 Not long to go to the referendum in Crimea. The head of the government there has outlined his plans at a news conference.
Linkup to correspondent. Serhiy Aksyonov said, inter alia, that Crimea will wake up a different place on Monday. He predicted a high turnout and a solid vote for joining Russia, and set out the timetable post-referendum. He also thinks that most Tatars will vote and questioned the credentials of the Majlis to represent them.
3. 1504 Preparations for the referendum are in full swing, so are preparations for the transitional period after it.
Correspondent's report. A high turnout is predicted and polling stations are ready, electoral lists are being updated, facilities are ready for observers, Aksyonov promises there will be no food shortages or welfare and pension cuts after the vote.
4. 1508 Russia reserves the right to protect Russians in Ukraine, the foreign ministry says after one dies in violence in Donetsk.
5. 1509 Arrests in Donetsk after yesterday's violence.
Correspondent's report. A rally of opponents of the Kiev government was attacked by supporters of it, who were well armed so the violence was pre-planned. Video shows fighting. The city is now in mourning but more rallies are planned.
6. 1511 Two Ukrainian politicians charged by Russian prosecutors with extremism and put on the wanted list. They are implicated in the killings by snipers at Maydan.
7. 1512 Kiev authorities not in control of the situation in the city.
Correspondent's report. Maydan self-defence organizations, manned by nationalist radicals and criminals, are undergoing paramilitary training. Weapons stolen from the police and armed forces are still in circulation and the price on the black market is dropping because of the glut in supply. Stolen weapons were used in a bank robbery, and the robbers let go because they were Maydan defenders. The correspondent cites other cases of lawlessness.
8. 1516 UN Security Council discusses situation in Ukraine, with Ukrainian premier attending. Video shows not him but Russian envoy Churkin responding, that nobody wants a war.
9. 1517 Sergey Lavrov and John Kerry hold talks in London.
10. 1517 Patriarch Kirill holds service for peace in Ukraine.
11. 1518 Rally for Ukraine to be held in Moscow tomorrow. Other rallies held across Russia, humanitarian aid being donated.
12. 1519 Putin judged a stronger leader than Obama in a western press poll.
13. 1520 Putin meets Russian trade union leader, transport minister. Video shows photocalls.
14. 1521 Duma passes law on golden goodbyes to departing managers, and other business news including a warning that Ukraine's economy will collapse if it joins the EU.
15. 1524 Poletayev signs off, bulletin ends.
Source: NTV, Moscow, in Russian 1500 gmt 14 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>