<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7780-C332-39DC-FDD3"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>All shall have rights; Changing constitutions</title><source>The Economist</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Latin America's politicians fiddle far too much with their constitutions
"DON'T interfere with anything in the constitution. That must be maintained, for it is the only safeguard of our liberties." The United States has taken Abraham Lincoln's admonition to heart: its constitution has been amended several times since coming into effect in 1789, but never replaced. South of the border, however, constitutions are perishable items.
By one calculation, Latin America boasts the four countries that have gone through the most constitutions. The Dominican Republic heads the list, with 32, from its first in 1844 to its latest version in 1994. (Scholars differ over whether the 2010 document counts as a rewrite or a thorough edit.) Other serial revisers include Ecuador—20 versions, the latest in 2008—and Venezuela, whose 26th constitution was drawn up in 1999. The average lifespan of a Latin American constitution is 16.5 years; in western Europe, it is 77.
The chopping and changing has slowed in recent decades; Latin America's propensity to fiddle is now not so different from that of other developing countries. Even so, since 1978 the region has enacted an average of almost one new constitution per country. In that time, not a single country has left its constitution unamended. Michelle Bachelet, inaugurated as Chile's president for a second time this week, has pledged a new constitution to replace the Pinochet-era one. In response to last year's wave of protests, Dilma Rousseff, Brazil's president, reached for the idea of a constituent assembly.
Pace Lincoln, it is too simple to damn all change. Political upheavals, from independence struggles to democratic transitions, sometimes warrant new texts—enshrining, for example, human rights that military juntas have scorned. Constitutions are not meant to be immutable; America's is constantly reinterpreted by the Supreme Court. Some need to be updated: until 1994 Argentina's constitution mandated that the president had to be a Catholic. Some need to have bad ideas excised: Mexico was right to change its constitution last year, to end a ban on foreign investment in its oil-and-gas industry. Small amendments can obviate the need for wholesale changes.
But habitual fiddling is still corrosive. Constitutions represent the institutional continuity of the state. The players may change and regulations may get tweaked, but the promise of a constitution is that the rules of the game are predictable. The more contingent those rules appear, the less confidence citizens have in their ability to plan and invest for the long term. And change begets change. Once altering the constitution becomes just another policy option, politicians are much more likely to do so to help themselves. In January the Nicaraguan constitution was changed to scrap term limits, enabling President Daniel Ortega to run for a third term. Venezuela's Hugo Chávez did the same in 2009. In Ecuador President Rafael Correa, who is due to leave office in 2017, is having second thoughts about the two-term limit his own 2008 constitution placed on elected officials. The best test of respect for the constitution is the willingness of politicians to leave such clauses alone.
One way for Latin Americans to discourage fiddling is to write simpler documents in the first place. Constitutions need not be as minimalist as that of the United States, but Latin America's framers tend to prescribe the nature of their states in detail, sometimes to a point of absurdity. Venezuela's constitution mandates a national industry to produce health-care supplies; Bolivia's pledges to protect coca; Brazil's requires a higher wage for night-shift work than for daytime labour. The bossier the document, the greater the chance of having to make constitution-sapping amendments in future.
Politicians tempted to fiddle with their founding documents should exercise more self-restraint, and generally leave them alone. Mr Correa would do his country a great service by respecting its institutions, even if that means depriving it of his own talents. Chile's constitution needs changing, but not binning. Brazil does not need a constituent assembly.
Voters asked to approve constitutional change should regard the prospect with deep scepticism. The more often rules are altered, the less seriously people take them; and without proper rules, democracy becomes a dangerous game.
]]></text></news-item>