<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="779F-EBCB-A863-2274"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>10 MIN WRAP</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[More aviation jobs set to be lost MORE jobs are set to be lost at the aviation arm of construction giant John Holland. John Holland Aviation Services (JHAS) said yesterday it had started to reduce maintenance operations at its Melbourne base at Tullamarine, blaming current market conditions.
The company did not say how many jobs were at risk, but the Australian Manufacturing Workers' Union said 230 airline maintenance positions were set to go, including 150 jobs at Tullamarine and the rest at JHAS's operations in Sydney, Perth, Adelaide and Brisbane. Forty engineers and technical staff were laid off at JHAS's Tullamarine base in July 2013.
BP to return to gulf after deal THE US has announced an end to its ban on BP obtaining government contracts following the 2010 Deepwater Horizon oil spill disaster in the Gulf of Mexico.
The Environmental Protection Agency said on Thursday that BP had "agreed to safety and ethics improvements" in exchange for removing the ban, which had hurt the British company's ability to do business in the US. The five-year deal with the EPA will allow BP to pursue new oil exploration leases in deepwater tracts in the Gulf of Mexico, which still bears many traces of the massive 2010 spill, the worst in US history.
"After a lengthy negotiation, BP is pleased to have reached this resolution, which we believe to be fair and reasonable," BP America chairman and president John Minge said.
Umemployment remains steady THE unemployment rate in advanced countries was steady at 7.6 per cent in January, with 46.2 million people looking for work nearly six years after the financial crisis began, OECD data show.
The unemployment rate in the 18-member eurozone was also steady, but at a far higher level of 12 per cent, the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) said.
The OECD said that the number of people looking for work among its 34 member countries was now 11.5 million higher than in July 2008.
The rate in the US in January fell by 0.1 per cent to 6.6 per cent, while in Japan it was steady at 3.7 per cent.Youth unemployment remains a chronic problem in several eurozone countries. In Greece, the last figures available were for November showing the rate among young people to be 59 per cent, in Spain in January it was 54.6 per cent, in Italy 42.4 per cent, Portugal 34.7 per cent and in the Slovak Republic 31.3 per cent.
]]></text></news-item>