<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="77F9-8A99-430D-2FA7"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Fouled pond gets clean bill of health</title><source>Kent Messenger</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[by James Walker
jameswalker@thekmgroup.co.uk
@JWalkerKM
Raw sewage which flooded a Scout pond and gardens across Loose has now cleared, inspectors have declared.
The contaminated water at Salts Pond, in Salts Lane, was discovered following flooding at the end of February.
Pollution was still detected five days later, but inspections conducted by the Environment Agency have found that the water is now clean.
Bob Jesshope, land warden for the Scouts, said: "It's all been dealt with now, thanks to a small group of volunteers who helped clear the mess.
"John MacDonald, who lives nearby and volunteers for the Loose Valley Conservation Society, did most of it and there's none around now.
"I wanted to see where it came from and saw contract workers pumping water down a drain in Hubbards Lane, Boughton Monchelsea. It smelt foul but whether they knew they were dumping sewage or not I have no idea."
Salts Lane resident Diane Fair said the sewage could be smelt in Loose village, about half a mile away. She said: "It was horrible but I was told by the Environment Agency that it's just 'organic matter.'
"Well, the Victorians were upset by open sewers and they did a great deal to get rid of them. Have we gone back in time?"
It is believed that the huge increase in the volume of Salts Stream was caused by floodwaters in the nearby Boughton Monchelsea Quarry being moved into the stream bed.
Lindsay Faulkner, an officer for the Environment Agency, said it was still investigating the source of the pollution.
She said: "Our officers attended the site and undertook tests which revealed that there was no remaining impact on the water quality.
"We are keen to hear from members of the public if they witness an environmental incident and ask that they contact our 24-hour incident hotline on 0800 80 70 60."
]]></text></news-item>