<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7893-8EA6-56A8-9498"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Law professor to speak at UCSC about justice for Holocaust victims</title><source>Santa Cruz Sentinel (California)</source><author>Kara Guzman, Santa Cruz Sentinel, Calif.</author><text><![CDATA[March 15--SANTA CRUZ -- More than $8 billion has been awarded to victims of Nazi atrocities, thanks to Morris Ratner and a team of a dozen lawyers.
In the late 1990s, Ratner's team prosecuted claims against European businesses that profited from the Holocaust, such as banks with dormant accounts, life insurance companies that didn't make payments and weapons manufacturers that used slave labor.
Some consider awarding money to Holocaust victims as disrespectful, given the gravity of the moral crimes, said Ratner, now a law professor at UC Hastings College of Law.
"What we did was pretty controversial," said Ratner. "There was criticism even within the Jewish community."
Hosted by UC Santa Cruz, Ratner will speak April 7 about what justice means for Holocaust victims and the role of private litigation.
The talk kicks off a UC Hastings social justice speaker series at UCSC -- upcoming talks include Provost and Academic Dean Elizabeth Hillman on sexual assault in the military and Professor Hadar Aviram on the financial crisis's impact on the prison system.
The series signals the start of a partnership between UCSC and the San Francisco-based law school, which will offer a new joint program called 3+3 BA/JD, in 2015. The program will allow UCSC students to obtain a bachelor's degree and law degree in six years instead of seven.
The series highlights common values between the campuses, said UC Hastings Professor Kelly Weisberg, organizer for both the series and the program. UC Hastings students can choose to concentrate in social justice, learning how to work for underrepresented clients, she said.
"Social justice is a cornerstone of the Hastings experience for many students, and it's been important to students at UC Santa Cruz since the days of the founders," said Weisberg, who is married to UCSC's Chancellor George Blumenthal.
For Ratner, justice for Holocaust victims needs to be considered on individual terms. People, especially Americans, tend to think of the Holocaust from a safe distance, he said.
"It's that sort of aggregate vision of the Holocaust, as an unimaginably large catastrophe that was experienced by European Jews, that's the common vision today," Ratner said.
After talking with hundreds of Holocaust survivors about the cold, hunger and losses they experienced, Ratner said he gained a more intimate understanding.
"Once the Holocaust becomes personal, personal remedies make sense," Ratner said.
Follow Sentinel reporter Kara Guzman at Twitter.com/Karambutan
___ (c)2014 the Santa Cruz Sentinel (Scotts Valley, Calif.) Visit the Santa Cruz Sentinel (Scotts Valley, Calif.) at www.santacruzsentinel.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>