<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="790C-A016-1341-D969"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Sex trade ad bill facing uphill battle; First Amendment and federal law may hurt effort targeting Backpage</title><source>Chicago Tribune</source><author>By Annie Sweeney and Stacy St. Clair, Tribune reporters</author><text><![CDATA[Kubiiki Pride's daughter had been missing for nine months when she found the ad on Backpage.com.
It was 4:30 a.m. and she was in bed on her computer, scrolling Backpage in a desperate search to find her 14-year-old runaway. She clicked on the "escorts" section and moved down two or three entries to one with childlike hearts. There was her daughter.
"My first emotion was complete happiness. Just seeing my child alive made me so happy," said Pride, who lived in St. Louis at the time. "When I took the whole picture in, that's when I noticed the nakedness, the tattoos and the other woman in the pictures."
Pride would learn soon enough about the horrifying ordeal her daughter had endured after being prostituted by a trafficker on the website. With an estimated 70 percent of prostitution ads nationally credited to Backpage.com, it has drawn the ire of mothers like Pride -- who brought a civil suit against the company -- and law enforcement, which has tried to change state laws and hold the website accountable for paid ads posted by pimps and traffickers.
The site also was linked locally this year to a high-profile slaying involving a longtime Brother Rice Catholic High School business teacher. In that case, prosecutors say Alan Filan was fatally stabbed by a prostitute he met through Backpage.
So far, all efforts have failed on account of strong existing federal law that says Web operators can't be held liable for what people post on their sites because doing so would be a threat to free speech and to a healthy exchange of ideas.
Now, Cook County prosecutors are working with Sen. Mark Kirk on a different approach -- a new federal law that focuses on the Internet sex trade, making it possible to criminally charge site operators who sell or promote ads that facilitate sex crimes, including prostitution and trafficking.
Jack Blakey, head of special prosecutions for the Cook County state's attorney's office, said the law aims to strike at the "centralized and nationalized" aspect of a website such as Backpage, which provides traffickers a way to ply their illicit trade by moving people around quickly and anonymously.
"People don't have a right to recklessly facilitate crime," Blakey said. "It is not an attack on the First Amendment; it is a very targeted and narrowly focused attempt to prevent unlawful conduct."
In announcing the legislation last week, Kirk singled out Jim Larkin and Michael Lacey, the unapologetic owners of Backpage.com, even though any Web operator in violation of the act could face charges under his proposal. The Arizona-based pair -- award-winning journalists who have exposed corruption and raised awareness about social issues such as immigration and civil rights abuses -- sold their interest in Village Voice Media, which publishes alternative newspapers across the country, two years ago to focus on the more lucrative website.
The site, which promotes classified ads in a format similar to Craigslist, charges $5 to $10 per post. On the Chicago page alone during one recent 24-hour period, there were about 400 advertisements for female escorts. Pages promoting male escorts, body rubs and fetish services also had dozens of advertisements.
And its market share has grown since 2009, when Craigslist bowed to pressure and stopped accepting ads for erotic services.
An ongoing civil suit brought in Washington state on behalf of three minors alleged that the company earned $20 million annually from the ads sold under the escort category alone. Other court records also outline a brisk business for Backpage.com with 3.3 million user ads posted in one month of 2012 alone. The pair has become so powerful that Kirk had poster-sized pictures of the longtime colleagues at his news conference last week. Though the sexagenarians appear more avuncular than evil, the senator portrayed them as among the great public menaces.
"We're naming names, and we're being very specific," Kirk said. "If Lacey and Larkin got out of this business, we would really help lower human trafficking rates in the United States."
Lacey and Larkin declined comment for this story, displaying unusual reticence for businessmen who previously had taken great glee at thumbing their noses at critics. In an email to the Tribune, their attorney said they made a decision not to publicly discuss Kirk's proposal.
"The aim of stopping the sex trafficking of minors, indeed the trafficking of any human being, is laudable," Backpage.com attorney Liz McDougall wrote. "However, identifying and vilifying a single U.S. website (previously craigslist, now Backpage.com) as the cause of the problem and the key to the solution are ill-founded and unproductive."
The website has beat similar state laws in Washington, New Jersey and Tennessee, where legislators enthusiastically passed the measures and the courts later struck them down for violating the First Amendment and the Federal Communications Decency Act. There were also concerns the measures could overreach, leaving any site operator liable for comments posted on its pages or ads provided by third-party content providers.
Kirk's proposal is expected to face similar challenges while enjoying broad public support because of the vulnerable populations he's trying to help.
"There's no doubt that it's a very well-intentioned bill," said Matthew Zimmerman, a senior staff attorney with the San Francisco-based Electronic Frontier Foundation. "But if there was an easy, narrow fix, it would have already been done. There have been a lot of people who have raised this concern, but they haven't found a way to fix it without collateral impact."
Robert Pedroli Jr., who represented Kubiiki Pride in her unsuccessful civil suit, said the law faces a powerful challenge in the Internet lobby. Meanwhile, victims who suffer physical and emotional damage are left only with the recourse to sue the low-level pimps and traffickers.
"What are you going to do with that?" Pedroli said. "Nothing. The bottom line is what is right and fair and just. It's an issue that Democrats, conservatives, (the) tea party, everyone can get behind: ending child trafficking."
Larkin and Lacey have portrayed themselves as partners in the fight against sex trafficking, pointing to 80 Backpage.com workers who police the site.
Law enforcement uses the site as a tool for finding pimps and traffickers too. Cook County prosecutors subpoena records from the company, and annual FBI stings aimed at rescuing child trafficking victims rely on Backpage.com.
The Cook County Sheriff's Department made some 565 arrests of prostitutes using Backpage.com since 2009.
But for a mother like Kubiiki Pride, she can't imagine a legitimate reason for allowing Backpage.com to continue offering an adult services section. With the trafficker convicted and her daughter rebuilding her life with the help of family, counseling and GED classes, Pride intends to continue speaking out against the site and the damage she says it has done to her family.
"It's a site no parent should ever see. You should never see your child being compromised and sold for sex," she said. "There should be no place (for that) in America."
asweeney@tribune.com
sstclair@tribune.com
Twitter @annie1221
Twitter @stacystclair
ct14 0018 140316 N S 0000000000 00002573
]]></text></news-item>