<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="793F-CA81-89AE-83C9"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Comfort Intech drops 3.2% on low volume</title><source>Indian Company News Bites - Stock Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[STOCK REPORT
Comfort Intech Ltd. (BSE:531216), India's 60th largest finance/non-bank financial company (nbfc) by market capitalisation, dropped Rs0.05 (or 3.2%) to close at Rs1.50, ending a two-day streak of rises. Compared with the BSE Sensex Index which rose 35.2 points (or 0.2%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -3.4%. The volume was 0.3 times the average trading of 154,261 shares.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Comfort Intech, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051141940314531216
Bearish SignalsSignificant Downtrend- Falls to Rises: in the past month the number of falls outnumbered rises 13:7 or 1.9:1.- The price plummeted 21.1% in the last month.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price/Earnings of 18.1 [8.9]. - Price/Sales of 3.1 [1.8]. - Year-on-Year Earnings Growth of 14.3% [34.7%].- Price/Earnings/Growth of 1.3 [0.3].- Dividend yield of 1.3% [2.4%].- Price to EBITDA of 7.5 [3.1].Other Bearish Signals:- Net profit margin has averaged 10.5% in the last 3 years. This is lower than the sector average of 19.8% and suggests a low margin of safety.
Bullish Signals- In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week high six times, pointing to an uptrend. - The present value of Rs1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Comfort Intech is Rs1,457, including a capital gain of Rs429 and dividend reinvested of Rs29.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Return on Equity 2.9% [0.4%].- Return on Capital Employed 6.8% [0.9%].Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 3.3 is comfortably below 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The P/E of 18.1 multiplied by the P/NTA of 0.5 is 9.4. Being less than the Benjamin Graham benchmark of 22.5 the stock appears undervalued. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 25.3%. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.4. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity is less than stellar at 2.9%. This is computed as net profit margin of 17.2% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 0.14 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 1.2.- Net Profit margin, EBIT margin and EBITDA margin are positive and have seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 43,429 shares worth Rs64,405 (US$1,050) traded. - Comfort Intech is at a discount of 30.2% to its 12-month high of Rs2.15 on 12 Feb, 2014. It is also at a premium of 97.4% to the 12-month low of Rs0.76 on 03 Sep, 2013.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 5 company announcements are:February 10: Comfort Intech appoints Additional DirectorComfort Intech has appointed Anil Nevatia as Additional Director. The effective date is February 08, 2014.
August 23: Comfort Intech announces dividendComfort Intech today announced a final dividend of Rs0.02 per share. The ex dividend date is August 23, 2013.
August 16: Comfort Intech: Limited Review for June 30, 2013[News Story] Comfort Intech Ltd has submitted to BSE a Copy of the Limited Review Report for the period ended June 30, 2013.http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/India/Stock/News/3706870.pdfSource: Bombay Stock Exchange of India
July 18: Comfort Intech: Outcome of Board Meeting[News Story] Comfort Intech Ltd has informed BSE that the Board of Directors of the Company at its meeting held on July 18, 2013, inter alia, has transacted the following:- The Board of Directors has wish to increase the Remuneration of the Managing Director and Executive Director of the Company.Source: Bombay Stock Exchange of India
July 18: Comfort Intech announces AGMComfort Intech has announced its Annual General Meeting will take place on August 31, 2013.
ISIN: INE819A01023
BSE:531216; NSE:531216; BO:531216; IN:531216
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>