<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="795C-8D8C-E14A-3D84"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>New Haven 'cop's cop' walks beat, aims to make difference</title><source>New Haven Register (Connecticut)</source><author>Rich Scinto, New Haven Register, Conn.</author><text><![CDATA[March 16--NEW HAVEN -- Officer Robert Hayden rolled to the corner of Read Street and Shelton Avenue in one of the department's new Dodge Charger cruisers on the afternoon of March 12.
The Charger is a smoother and arguably better-looking ride than the department's aging Crown Victoria cruisers, but that doesn't mean Hayden is apt to cruise around all day.
"A lot of times, you can actually hide in this car and that's not good for the community," he said as he got out of the cruiser and surveyed the surrounding streets.
Instead, Hayden opts to stretch his legs around the Newhallville neighborhood.
"I think one of the best things done was bringing the walking beat back," Hayden said, noting that he started on a walking beat, and that the department got away from the practice for a bit.
Hayden, a 12-year veteran, is officially assigned to the Dixwell police district, but he's often afforded the opportunity to travel into Newhallville and recently, Beaver Hills.
He started his career as a walking-beat cop in the Wayfarer Street area. Before that, he was a corrections officer who applied to become a city cop only after a coworker got him an application and paid the filing fee.
Hayden is known by different names on the street. Some residents just call him Hayden, others call him "Uncle," or joke that he is the mayor of Newhallville because he knows so many of the residents.
Quick Check Stop store clerk Khal Jassar calls him the "black Columbo" in reference to the police detective TV show that aired in the 1970s.
Hayden's iPhone is filled with 672 different numbers, many of them for city residents that he has helped out at some point; whether it's an elderly woman on Lilac Street or a mother whose son got arrested.
Hayden purposely parked his car at an angle where it's visible from both sides of Read Street and Shelton Avenue. The corner is mostly quiet during this gloomy afternoon.
The area of Shelton and Read was R-2 gang territory years ago; things have quieted down significantly since then.
"The days of shooting at will at any time are gone, but we still have a long way to go," Hayden said.
The R-2 gang was notorious for its brazen penchant for violence including attempted assaults on police officers. Local and federal law enforcement authorities conducted a round-up of alleged members in 2010.
Lilac Street has also improved significantly through the years.
"If you look at it now, it's not perfect, but I could move here and feel comfortable," Hayden said about Lilac Street.
Housecleaning
Hayden's work week started on Wednesday after his two days off.
"Today is my Monday, and that means housecleaning," said Hayden, adding he likes to take care of tasks like follow-ups for crime victims and get proactive projects started on the first work day of his week.
Summer, which typically brings an uptick in violence, is only a few months away. For now, the entire city has gone more than a month without a single reported shooting victim. Part of Hayden's day involved consulting a local property owner about better lighting that will make it safer for cops and residents in the area.
The owner wished to remain anonymous for this article, but told Hayden he would put a plan in place for better lighting before summertime. Hayden thanked the owner and said that improved lighting would help keep both residents and cops safe at night.
Before that, Hayden ran into Jerome T. Moore in front of the Quick Check Stop store. Moore grew up in New Haven and still has family in the Newhallville area. His son had been getting into some trouble in the neighborhood.
He said he tried persuading his son to go down a different path, but to no avail.
Hayden arrested his son, but also talked him out of the street life.
"(Hayden) spoke to him and it got through," Moore said.
That conversation happened about a year ago. Now Moore's son has a stable job and a child of his own.
It takes a village to raise a child, Moore said. In this case, a cop was part of that village.
"You don't know if you are making a difference or not until years later," Hayden said.
Hayden had a similar conversation with resident Trina Shealy, whose son Brandon had a similar interaction with Hayden. An arrest and some advice helped turn her son's life around, Shealy said. Now, he's a straight-A student at a school in Middletown.
"He's a good cop, he talks to the kids a lot," she said. "He knows everybody in this neighborhood."
Walking the beat for Hayden is far from only checking-in on residents he has helped in the past. Resident Blossetta Chambers was outside her house when Hayden walked up to say hello.
She said she has had a recurring problem where kids break into her backyard and take her possessions.
"Anything that looks good, they take it," she said.
She said she doesn't call police because she doesn't think they will get to her house on time.
Hayden again gave her his number and said that just because he or other officers don't show up immediately on the scene doesn't mean the situation can't be solved.
"Try me next time; these kids talk a lot," he said. "You'd be surprised what I can do."
A cop's cop and a community cop
Hayden's supervisor, district manager Sgt. Sam Brown, said Hayden is an extremely valuable asset to the district, the department and the city as a whole. He described him as a proactive worker who is not only a "cop's cop," but also a community and youth-oriented officer.
"He's a great community guy. He gets down to earth with them," Brown said about Hayden's interaction with youth.
Hayden's work ethic and skills make him a role model and an effective field training officer, Brown said. New officers are put on a three-month probationary period where they pair with a field training officer to learn the ropes of the streets.
"His perseverance and diligence have not faded one bit over the years, which is very admirable," Brown said.
Hayden often relays information, even after he has clocked-out for the day. Information he received while on vacation led to the arrest of two teenagers who allegedly attacked and beat 83-year-old Yale University architecture professor Paul Brouard in Newhallville last May.
The gloom of Wednesday afternoon turned into a rainy evening.
Hayden set off for another neighborhood to try to turn yet another person's life around. He called for Officers Lesley Billingslea and Cherelle Carr on the radio as he went to the residence of a man he arrested three days prior after an alleged drug transaction.
The man had taken off running from Hayden after Hayden came up from behind. The man attempted to vault a porch rail and fell.
Unfortunately, the man's face broke the fall, Hayden said.
The three officers went to the man's residence. A neighbor let the officers inside and to the second-floor where the man lived.
The man opened the door and let the officers inside.
One side of his face was almost completely covered by scabs, his lips were swollen and some of his teeth had been knocked out of place. His right arm was in a cast.
Brown is working with several community leaders, including street outreach worker Doug Bethea, to establish a new program to help young males who are at risk of perpetrating or falling victim to violence. The program is in its infancy, Brown said, but will include mentoring, job training and other aspects to set people on a safer path through life.
Hayden informed the man that he and Brown thought he would be a good candidate for the program.
"It's Wednesday, and I said I'd have an answer for you Wednesday," Hayden told the man.
The man seemed happy and said he just wanted to pay child support for his kids as he pulled out stubs for payment.
"This (expletive) ain't worth it," the man mumbled through his swollen face as he pointed to his injuries.
The whole interaction was representative of Hayden's relationships in the area. Things start off with love, then go to hate and then back to love. The man's mother and other relatives weren't happy when she saw her son's injuries and assumed Hayden beat him down.
"I told them 'ask your son if I put my hands on him,'" Hayden said.
One of the biggest routes to building trust is keeping a promise, Hayden said. He previously told the man he couldn't guarantee he would be in the program or that he could get him a job, but that he would have an answer.
"Out here, all you have is your word," he said.
Call Rich Scinto at 203-789-5748. Have questions, feedback or ideas about our news coverage? Connect directly with the editors of the New Haven Register at AskTheRegister.com.
___ (c)2014 the New Haven Register (New Haven, Conn.) Visit the New Haven Register (New Haven, Conn.) at www.nhregister.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>