<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7A1D-E54A-3353-DB45"><date>2014-03-09</date><title>Letters: GOP leaders in Austin should leave Tiguas alone</title><source>El Paso Times (Texas)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[GOP leaders in Austin should leave Tiguas alone
You know in a way its our own fault. El Paso historically has always been Democratic.
This means anybody that is in Austin can pick on El Paso and the Tiguas as long as a Republican is in office.
My grandfather (God rest his soul) always told me, "I better never hear you didn't vote for something you believe in."
I will make sure I vote and make sure that Greg Abbott and anyone else pays the price for opposing anything that someone in El Paso is doing to help the community.
The Tiguas, just like some of the philanthropists we keep reading about in the paper are who help El Paso.
I run a family supply business here in El Paso and I thank God for my customers everyday, and thank God we have the Tiguas, who support the El Paso contractors and sub-contractors who buy from me every day.
If you don't want to support El Paso and the Tiguas, don't bother coming to El Paso.
Mike Sanchez East SideGeorge Will goes astray on climate change
George Will's column on March 1 shows that even a (relatively speaking) moderate conservative can descend to the dark side.
He states, in regard to climate change, that when a politician (Obama in his example) "says, concerning an issue involving science that the debate is over, you may be sure the debate is rolling on and not going swimmingly for his side."
This dishonestly implies a scientific controversy over whether climatic change is real, despite a strong scientific consensus that it is real and is serious. (It is a favorite trick among the far right to claim scientific controversy that exists only in their imagination.)
By generally accepted criteria, Obama's statement that "Climate change is a fact" is indeed true.
Mr. Will then goes on to imply that gathering large sums to combat the right wing preference to do nothing to alleviate the coming changes is equivalent to the Koch brothers' campaign of propaganda against taking common sense steps to lessen the impact of the coming climatic chaos.
Arthur H. Harris West SideGrandfather gave bad advice on health insurance
The gentleman who wrote the Feb. 23 letter to the editor saying he talked his grandson out of buying the $69 dollar health insurance because he would never reach the $5,000 deductible is making himself responsible for a serious illness the young man might get.
I have met my $5,000 dollar deductible two years in a row and my insurance company has paid $180,000.
Would you help pay for his expenses?
Good health to both of you.
Jose Flores East SideLara is wrong choice for New Mexico race
New Mexico congressional candidate Roxanne "Rocky" Lara has a long history of supporting highly controversial industries.
Lara has evaded questions about her activities promoting extraction industries and her involvement in the private nuclear waste industry now riddled with safety issues.
Lara promotes fracking, extracting fossil fuel by injecting huge quantities of water during extreme drought.
She supports energy being obtained through all available means despite known environmental costs.
Worse, she promotes New Mexico as the nation's nuclear waste depository.
She's a member of the Eddy County Energy Alliance, Energy Communities Alliance and Nuclear Task Force.
The Nuclear Task Force is vested in stockpiling wastes near Carlsbad for fewer than 1,000 jobs and "national defense".
Apparently the consequences of fracking, drilling, and storing nuclear wastes are New Mexico's patriotic duty.
Amazingly, the Energy Communities Alliance thinks nuclear wastes should be stored above ground in tanks spread over nearly 1,000 square miles of New Mexico.
When she dodges direct questions about these issues she shortchanges the people of District 2.
The difference in the candidates opposing Steve Pearce is clear: "Pearce Lite" or Leslie Endean Singh.
Connie J. Potter Las CrucesYISD needs better explanation for bond issue
I get it.
The Ysleta school district population isn't reproducing as fast as they used to. Welcome to the club.
The education infrastructure is most efficient with a higher population using all their facilities near or at maximum capacity, but it ain't gonna happen any time soon.
Anna L. Perez's pitch for more money is justifiable, but what's with "we do have the the opportunity for a $155 million bond with no tax increase?"
Like it's going to pay for itself.
Something more like, "If you want your kids to have the best chance to get a quality education (without leaving the district) you YISD people are going to have to suck it up and dish out the dough."
Eduardo Calderon East Side
]]></text></news-item>