<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7A37-8901-1E6A-2787"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Maryland: Consumer Safety Inspector 8/9 Vacancy No. FSIS-MMP-2014-0399</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The State of Maryland has issued the following job vacancy:
Department Food Safety and Inspection ServiceSalary $47,212.00 to $67,787.00 Grade 08 to 09Perm/Temp Permanent FT/PT Full-timeOpen Date 3/13/2014 Close Date 3/27/2014Job Link Apply Online Who may apply Status CandidatesLocations:WILLIAMSPORT, MDJob Description (Please follow all instructions carefully)
Job Title:Consumer Safety Inspector 8/9
Department:Department Of Agriculture
Agency:Food Safety and Inspection Service
Job Announcement Number:FSIS-MMP-2014-0399SALARY RANGE: $47,212.00 to $67,787.00 / Per YearOPEN PERIOD: Thursday, March 13, 2014 to Thursday, March 27, 2014SERIES & GRADE: GS-1862-08/09POSITION INFORMATION: Full-time - PermanentPROMOTION POTENTIAL:09DUTY LOCATIONS: 1 vacancy - Williamsport, MDWHO MAY APPLY: CURRENT Food Safety and Inspection Service (FSIS) Employees Nationwide with Status or USDA Career Transition (CTAP) Employees with Priority Placement.SECURITY CLEARANCE: Q - NonsensitiveSUPERVISORY STATUS: NoJOB SUMMARY:
About the Agency
SPECIFIC VACANCY INFORMATION:
Consumer Safety Inspector, GS-1862-08/09, SJ-518Establishment: 10805 M, Hamzah Slaughter House located in WASHINGTON County.Work Schedule: 1st Shift, Monday-Friday, 6:00 a.m. - 2:30 p.m.
For more information about the agency, please visit FSIS Salary Range: GS-08 $47,212.00 - 61,377.00; GS-09 $52,146.00 - 67,787.00. This is a Bargaining Unit position covered by the National Joint Council (NJC) of Food Inspection Locals.
TRAVEL REQUIRED
Occasional Travel Travel required may vary, depending on geographical assignment.
RELOCATION AUTHORIZED
Yes Entitlement to the payment of relocation expenses will be determined in accordance with the provisions outlined in FSIS DIRECTIVE 3820.2.
KEY REQUIREMENTS
MUST BE A CURRENT FSIS EMPLOYEE OR USDA CAREER TRANSITION ELIGIBLE (CTAP) MEET TIME-IN GRADE (TIG) BY COMPLETING 52 WEEKS AT NEXT LOWER GRADE RESUME DOCUMENTING 52 WEEKS OF SPECIALIZED EXPERIENCE TRAINING AS A CONDITION OF EMPLOYMENT IS REQUIRED (TCOE)
DUTIES:
As a CSI you will ensure that regulated establishments produce a safe product by executing appropriate inspection methods,determining noncompliance with regulatory requirements, documenting noncompliance and initiating enforcement action, where warranted. Here's what you will be assigned to do:
Verify that meat and poultry slaughter and/or processing establishments’ Sanitation Standard Operating Procedures (SSOP) and Hazard Analysis and Critical Control Point (HACCP) Plans meet regulatory requirements and are being executed effectively to prevent unsanitary conditions and adulteration of product. GS-8 (SJ-518a) May be required to perform Hazard Analysis Verification (HAV) under the oversight of the supervisor. HAV is an analytical review of establishments' production process in order to insure regulatory obligations to conduct a food safety hazard analysis. GS-9 (SJ-518): Independently performs Hazard Analysis Verification (HAV). HAV is an analytical review of establishments' production process in order to insure regulatory obligations to conduct a food safety hazard analysis. Review records, observe plant operations and conduct hands-on verification to ensure compliance with regulatory requirements. You will prepare detailed documentation (Non-Compliance Records) of noncompliance with regulatory requirements. You will determine when regulatory control action is necessary. You will assess whether the plant's corrective or preventative actions are acceptable and effective, if there are trends in noncompliance, or if enforcement action is warranted. Conduct regulatory oversight activities inside plants in matters relating to other consumer protections (e.g., economic adulteration and misbranding). Have contact with plant managers, owners and others to explain legal and regulatory requirements, discuss operation of the plants' SSOP, HACCP plan and other food safety programs. You will communicate on and defend determinations on noncompliance issues and discuss plans for addressing non-compliance. You will also work with a variety of individuals to resolve problems, clarify differences of interpretation concerning HACCP and other food safety or consumer protection requirements and you will advise other Agency inspectors, supervisors and officers on inspection and enforcement matters for which you are involved. You may conduct various samplings, surveys and tests to obtain pertinent data on potential problem areas, industry trends, or other issues of current interest to the Agency. You may be involved in performing health and safety verification sampling and tests for detection of specific microbes (e.g., salmonella, listeria, etc.), residues or contaminants. You may also perform direct, structured sampling involving Protein Fat Free (PFF), undeclared species, undeclared ingredients or suspected economic violations involving net weight or labeling.
QUALIFICATIONS REQUIRED:
For this position, there are two (2) basic components that together define the qualifications.
Time-In-Grade/Time-In-Band: Applicants for this position must have 52 weeks of time-in-grade/time-in-band at the next lower level in the Federal Service. For more information on TIG: 5 CFR 300.604 Specialized experience: (CSI GS-8) In order to meet the specialized experience requirement, you will need to have completed 52 weeks of progressively responsible specialized experience at the GS-7 grade level within 30 days after the closing date of this announcement. (CSI GS-9) In order to meet the specialized experience requirement, you will need to have completed 52 weeks of progressively responsible specialized experience at the GS-8 grade level within 30 days after the closing date of this announcement.
Specialized experience includes; working with the Federal Meat, Poultry, and Egg Products Inspection Acts in order to inspect meat, poultry and egg products; working with basic SSOP and HACCP principles and practices in order to verify plant HACCP and SSOP responsibilities; performing basic mathematics and elementary statistical concepts and methods to perform testing and sampling procedures and experience in reaching and interpreting conclusion.
All qualification requirements must be met within 30 days after the closing of this announcement. Please view OPM's Qualifications Standards. Consumer Safety Inspector Series, GS-1862If you are a current FSIS employee and a non-competitive applicant (reassignment, change to lower grade, or noncompetitive re-promotion) wanting consideration for this position, you must complete the on-line application process and/or apply to the Voluntary Reassignment System. In order to apply to the Voluntary Reassignment System, you must submit a hard copy of "Form 4335-3, Employee Request for Reassignment within Field Operations". The required form(s) must be filled out and mailed to: USDA, FSIS, HRO Systems Section, Butler Square West, Suite 420C, 100 N Sixth Street, Minneapolis, MN 55403.HOW YOU WILL BE EVALUATED:
Applicants are evaluated in accordance with Merit Staffing procedures which govern Status candidates.
All are rated on the extent and quality of experience, education, and training relevant to the duties of the position. An automated ranking system based on the on-line application process is used. We will carefully review your resume and your answers to the questions, to ensure you meet the minimum qualifications. Your resume will be reviewed to verify that it supports the answers provided to the job-specific questions; that your resume addresses experience and education relevant to this position. Copies of any required documents will also be reviewed to verify they support your application and meet the vacancy requirements. The occupational questions will evaluate you on the following competencies: Communication - Oral and Written; Mathematics, Attention to Detail; Problem Solving; Dependability. High self-assessment in the applicant questions that is not supported by information in your resume may eliminate you from best-qualified status and subsequent referral to the selecting official.
**REMINDER** Applicants - Be sure that experience/education as described on your resume contains accurate and sufficiently detailed information to clearly support the competencies. All information used to evaluate your application must be received by the closing date of the announcement. Once the position is closed, no additional information will be accepted.To preview questions please click here.
BENEFITS:
You can review our benefits at: https://jobs.mgsapps.monster.com/usda/vacancy/preview!benefits.hms?orgId=27&jnum=130941
OTHER INFORMATION:
This position has a training program requirement as a condition of employment (TCOE). If selected, you must successfully complete a 4-week training program, the Inspection Methods course, at a designated location which may require travel outside the duty location for an extended period. This training is necessary to perform the duties and responsibilities of a CSI to further the mission of the Office of Field Operations and FSIS. You must begin the training within 90 days of the effective date of your selection, and you must successfully complete it within 12 months of the effective date of your selection. Failure to successfully complete the training may result in returning you to your former position (depending on availability and the needs of the Agency); or if qualified, be offered another position at the same or lower grade than the position held immediately before accepting the covered position; or removal from Federal Service. THIS POSITION REQUIRES A PRE-EMPLOYMENT PHYSICAL. (Applicants hired under CTAP) Functional requirements and environmental factors If selection is made below GS-9, promotion to that level may be made without further competition, upon completion of 12 months of satisfactory performance. This announcement may be used to fill additional like vacancies should any occur in the announced duty location. U.S. Department of Agriculture NON-Discrimination Statement Reasonable Accommodation Statement
HOW TO APPLY:Applying to this announcement requires the online submission of basic applicant information, responses to the vacancy specific questions and submission of supporting documentation. You will be found ineligible if you fail to submit the required documents. All application materials/documentation will be accepted until 11:59 P.M. Eastern Time on the closing date of the announcement. To submit a complete application:
Answer all core questions (completed when registering on-line in USAJOBS and as part of the initial application process) Answer all vacancy-specific questions (completed for each job) Submit your on-line resume. Resumes are entered into USAJOBS. Resumes can be copied and pasted into the personal information area of your application from other word processing documents at any time prior to the closing date. Applicants who do not respond to the on-line vacancy questions and who do not submit a supporting resume or required supporting documents will be rated ineligible.
If you are unable to apply Online, contact the number listed in the Agency Contact Information section prior to the closing date. An application package will be mailed out. Prior to the closing of the announcement your completed package along with any required supporting documents must be received in the HR Office. Information received after the closing date will not be accepted. NOTE: 18 U.S.C. 1719 prohibits the use of Government franked envelopes for application packages.
REQUIRED DOCUMENTS:Current FSIS employees need to submit their current resume and answer the vacancy specific questions. FOR INFORMATION ON UPLOADING DOCUMENTS: Uploading Information.To exercise selection priority for this vacancy, non-FSIS federal employees with USDA CTAP eligibility may apply and must provide the following:
A copy of their most recent SF-50 and performance appraisal Proof of USDA CTAP eligibility. Meet all qualification, eligibility requirements and be able to perform the duties of the position upon entry
Click Here: Employee's Guide to Career TransitionAGENCY CONTACT INFO:Merri StellburgPhone: 612-659-8541Fax: 612-370-2007TDD: 800-877-8339Email: merri.stellburg@fsis.usda.govAgency Information:USDA, FOOD SAFETY AND INSPECTION SERVICEHuman Resources Operations DivisionButler Square West, Suite 420C100 North 6th StreetMinneapolis, MN55403USFax: 612-370-2007WHAT TO EXPECT NEXT:Applicant qualifications are evaluated after the position closes. Top ten (10) best qualified and non-competitive eligible candidates will be referred to the selecting official, in alphabetical order. When filling more than one (1) position, up to three (3) additional eligible candidates are sent for each vacancy. You may check your status on USAJOBS. Individual notifications will not be sent. Applications are reviewed after the announcement closing date.
For further information please visit: http://federalgovernmentjobs.us
]]></text></news-item>