<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7A41-AF6A-40A3-422A"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>60% Amdavadis not aware of rights; Majority of Amdavadi consumers are unaware of their consumer protection laws, says Assocham survey</title><source>DNA</source><author>dna correspondent</author><text><![CDATA[Ahmedabad: Day after day, consumers are being fooled by companies through illusions or marketing gimmicks. And, of the number of consumers cheated in Amdavad, 60% are just not aware of their rights and consumer laws.
Even in Ahmedabad, fake products, misleading ads and lack of transparency are major concerns. A majority of the Amdavadis are ignorant and ill-informed about their rights, revealed a survey conducted by apex industry body, Assocham.
Only 30% urban Indians are aware of their consumer rights. But a majority of them are still ignorant and ill-informed about their rights, said the survey conducted in the wake of World Consumer Rights Day celebrated globally on March 15.
A majority of Amdavadis said they were not familiar with consumer protection-related laws. Around 40% of the over 250 consumers interviewed, about 40% said they were aware of their rights. Most of them said though they had faced problems on several occasions, they did not move consumer courts considering it a hassle.
Assocham Social Development Foundation (ASDF) interacted with about 4,000 people at 15 centres - Ahmedabad, Bangalore, Bhubaneswar, Chandigarh, Chennai, Delhi, Hyderabad, Kanpur, Kolkata, Kochi, Lucknow, Mumbai, Nagpur, Pune and Thiruvanathapuram in January-February 2014.
"Growing market for counterfeit products and imported goods from China, largely driven by web-shopping portals, is promoting trust deficit among consumers, besides promoting products and services through misleading advertisements together with lack of transparency, complex terms and conditions, non-disclosure of hidden charges/fees, penalties and others are certain key concerns of modern Indian consumers," stated the survey.
Nationally, about 30% of all respondents admitted that they were aware of consumer rights and a majority of them said they pursued their rights after they were mistreated, duped or cheated.
"India Inc. is taking significant steps in this direction as companies today are serious about informing, educating and communicating with their target consumers in a bid to enhance their knowledge and awareness about products, services offered by the company and also seeking consumers' feedback, complaints and suggestions thereby nurturing a positive culture of consumer consciousness and behaviour," said Assocham secretary-general DS Rawat.
A majority of the respondents said they were unfamiliar with any rights and laws relating to consumer protection. Some of them said that though they have heard about certain rights, they did not find the need to learn about it as they had not faced problems so far.
Companies are using Twitter, Facebook and blogs to connect with consumers of all age groups, said Rawat. "However, a simple, speedy and an inexpensive consumer grievance redressal mechanism is imperative to boost awareness levels and the authorities must perk up the system to file complaints in consumer courts that would strengthen the reach of government campaigns," he pointed out.
]]></text></news-item>