<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7A7A-A2D3-F22F-5557"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>It's our city - keep it clean, green, caring</title><source>Sunday Tribune (South Africa)</source><author> James Nxumalo</author><text><![CDATA['It's your city - it starts with you. Let's pick it up." This is the core message in eThekwini Municipality's Clean My City programme aimed at a clean, green and caring city.
Our initiative sets the course towards realising a healthy, prosperous and resilient future for our city. It calls on us all to rise to the challenge of transforming our community to create a better life for future generations and achieve the vision of becoming the most caring and liveable city by 2030.
We have looked at the successes of other cities, particularly Singapore and in Canada, and would like to emulate the good work done, where total co-operation has been achieved from every citizen.
To do this, it is crucial that we change our mindsets. I have no doubt that we will realise the objectives successfully and witness ordinary people do extraordinary things.
The campaign, officially launched on March 7 at Durban's Inkosi Albert Luthuli International Convention Centre, is the municipality's response to service delivery and social challenges identified in parts of the city. A clean-up operation followed at Umlazi C-Section.
The campaign is about all of us taking pride in the place where we live, play, shop and work. It's about reclaiming our city.
Key issues being tackled with this multidisciplinary campaign include by-law infringements, derelict buildings, litter, pollution and social ills. These social challenges are tarnishing the image of our city. We are taking a zero-tolerance approach to challenges like crime, drugs and illegal activities.
A task team, comprising different municipal departments and other stakeholders, has been set up and is focusing on general maintenance of the city, including dealing with potholes, faulty street lights and infrastructure.
Through this city-wide clean-up, we are reclaiming our public spaces while creating a safe environment.
The campaign is a clarion call to all citizens to support the programme by partnering with the city, taking part in education campaigns and doing clean-ups.
As the city leadership, we have elected to own the problems our communities face and lead the way in our operations by demonstrating what a clean city looks like in terms of municipal-owned buildings, facilities and operations.
But the municipality alone cannot achieve the goal of maintaining a cleaner, greener city.
Leadership from other spheres of government and public agencies will be crucial to our success.
By working with citizens, schools, street traders, businesses and non-governmental organisations to address the issues we face, the vision of a safer, sustainable and socially cohesive city will soon become a reality.
To ensure inclusive participation, the campaign will focus on educating the public that it is not only the responsibility of the people hired by the municipality to clean up. Everyone has an obligation to maintain their environment.
The programme will be rolled out across the city. Apart from the central business district, areas that will receive special attention include Umlazi, Isipingo, Pinetown, Clermont, Phoenix, Inanda, Ntuzuma and KwaMashu.
Durban is competing with other cities for tourists, investors and talent, so it is crucial for us to maintain global competitiveness.
The campaign was first launched internally so that the 23 000 municipal employees could own the campaign and be ambassadors in their communities.
The stakeholder launch at the ICC informed citizens about their roles and responsibilities, what they could do to ensure their city was sustainable and successful, and to familiarise themselves with the branding of the campaign.
Don't be surprised if you are driving on one of the city freeways and spot a bright-yellow billboard that has pictures of your family or friends on it. We have used ordinary citizens from Durban to portray the message that we must all come together to clean up the city.
Municipal officials have begun implementing action plans that will address vagrancy, particularly in Albert Park, after a profiling exercise of the homeless in the area.
Multidisciplinary interventions involve the municipality's safer-cities unit and metro police, as well as the home affairs and social development departments, to help young people living in the park become rehabilitated and to take them off the streets.
Officials have identified 87 derelict buildings in the inner city and 45 outside, most of which have become a breeding ground for criminals.
One of the successes from this profiling exercise is court action taken against owners of the buildings that pose health, safety and security risks.
Over the years, the municipality has embarked on a full-scale programme to rid the city of illegal dumping and encourage people to use the correct and proper methods to safely dispose of waste.
But some citizens and businesses are violating their right to enjoy an environment that is not harmful to their health by constantly dumping illegally. Illegal dumping poses a serious threat to public health - when the waste decomposes, it releases toxic chemicals that contaminate the environment.
Rapid growth in eThekwini's urban population has put enormous pressure on service infrastructure and led to a significant increase in all types of environmental pollution.
Urban areas drive economic development and deliver many public services, such as education, health care and transport, but they are also associated with environmental degradation, congestion and economic and social exclusion.
Climate uncertainty, rising fuel prices and shifting economic opportunities also compel us to work hard to remain one of the best places in the world in which to live.
eThekwini should offer the kind of quality of life and opportunities that make people want to live in Durban and which attract investment.
The problems call for decisive action and innovation. Every resident and the business community can play a crucial role in helping us to reach our goals.
The municipality is committed to ensuring the programme is sustainable. The campaign should be at the top of every citizen's agenda. Whether you are involved in the local business community, active in your neighbourhood or interested in cleaning up and greening your environment, your efforts are essential to our shared success.
l Nxumalo is eThekwini mayor.
]]></text></news-item>