<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7ACB-07F4-3675-6691"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>All Nippon Airways keeps sliding: down 3.0% in 2 days</title><source>News Bites Asian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[All Nippon Airways Co., Ltd. (TO:9202), the largest air transport company by market capitalisation in the Tokyo Stock Exchange, extended its slide Monday, shedding an additional JPY4.0 (or 1.8%) to close at JPY223.0. The shares have dropped JPY7.0 (or 3.0%) over the past two trading days. Compared with the Nikkei 225 Index which fell 538.3 points (or 3.63%) in the two days, this represented a relative price increase of 0.6%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on All Nippon Airways, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051711770314235
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- The stock dropped 1.8% on high volatility today.- The price dropped 3.0% in the last week.
- Net profit margin has averaged 2.2% in the last 3 years. This suggests the company is less profitable with a low margin of safety.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity is less than stellar at 5.6%. This is computed as net profit margin of 2.9% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 0.69 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 2.8.
Bullish SignalsOversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The stock is oversold according to the Williams % R indicator of -90.0, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day low of JPY222.0.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Earnings/Growth of 0.3 [0.5].Other Bullish Signals:- The P/E of 17.8 multiplied by the P/NTA of 1.1 is 19.6. Being less than the Benjamin Graham benchmark of 22.5 the stock appears undervalued. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.4. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- Net Profit margin is negative but improving in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]
- Net Profit margin has shown signs of recovery in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 16,757,000 shares worth JPY3.7 billion (US$37 million) traded. The volume was 0.7 times the average trading of 22.7 million shares. Beta: the Beta of All Nippon Airways stock is 0.4. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market. - All Nippon Airways is at a discount of 9.7% to its 12-month high of JPY247.0 on 23 May, 2013. It is also at a premium of 23.9% to the 12-month low of JPY180.0 on 02 Apr, 2013. - The present value of JPY1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in All Nippon Airways is JPY1,093, for a capital gain of JPY93.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Parity:- Price/Earnings of 17.8 [16.6]. We estimate All Nippon Airways stock is trading at a current year P/E of 13 and a forward year P/E of 9.5. - Price to Book of 1.1 [1.1]. - Return on Equity 5.6% [5.9%].- Return on Assets 2% [2.2%].
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:December 19: ANA and Garuda Indonesia Agree Comprehensive Partnership[Company Release] JAKARTA, INDONESIA, December 19, 2013 - ANA, Japan's leading airline group, and Garuda, the flag-carrier airline of Indonesia, today announced a comprehensive partnership under which the two airlines will codeshare on flights between the two countries and will allow passengers to be able to collect and redeem miles on Frequent Flyer Program of both airlines.The partnership, which will enhance passenger choice and frequency of services, was announced at a ceremony in Jakarta, Indonesia attended by Osamu Shinobe, President and CEO of ANA, and Emirsyab Satar, President and CEO of Garuda Indonesia.From March 30, 2014, ANA will operate new route between Tokyo's Haneda Airport and Jakarta Airport, followed by Garuda opening the same route from first semester 2014.
December 10: ANA's Japanese Facebook Page Attracts 1 Million Fans![Company Release] TOKYO December 10th, 2013- ANA has become the first organization within the Japanese travel industry to attract 1 million fans to its Facebook page. Since setting up the page in January 2011, ANA has posted content on a variety of themes to entertain fans such as "ANA Smiles", "Aircraft and Airport Photographs" and "Have a nice weekend" to introduce staff, new aircraft and services and to promote tourist destinations.ANA's Facebook page is also used to elicit customer feedback on its products and services through projects such as the "Vote for your favorite Economy in-flight menu" which gave passengers the chance to vote for their favorite dishes on international economy class routes.In addition to the Japanese page, ANA also runs the ANA Global Facebook page, written in English, which has around 450,000 fans, followed by the ANA Hong Kong page and the ANA Taiwan page both written in traditional Chinese.
December 10: ANA to introduce MPL Training for Pilots[Company Release] TOKYO, December 10th, 2013- ANA isto introduce a new type of basic training into its pilot education program. Multi-crew Pilot License (MPL) training is specifically designed for aircraft cockpits crewed by two pilots and was introduced in 2006 by the International Civil Aviation Organization.ANA will begin MPL training from summer 2014 and will outsource the training to Lufthansa Flight Training GmbH (LFT)1, the flight training subsidiary of Lufthansa, one of ANA's Star Alliance partners as well as Joint Venture partner.The MPL trainingis expected to result in a significant reduction in training time compared to previous training methods, but it will effectively and efficiently allow trainees not only to acquire piloting skills, but also essential skills required for airline operations including supporting flight operations.ANA decided to introduce the training after determining it met the group's requirements as a mean of providing effective, consistent training from basic stages to training on actual aircraft.LFT has a proven track record, and more than 400 copilots have already completed the course.
November 29: ANA Group Traffic Results - October 2013[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Japan/Stock/News/18102.pdfSource: Company Website
November 15: ANA to promote Hokkaido through 'Tastes of JAPAN' project[Company Release] TOKYO November 15th, 2013 -ANA Group promotes lesser-known aspects of Japan through its 'Tastes of Japan' project. The campaign particularly aimed at overseas customers, is designed to raise the profile of Japan's prefectures an, in turn increase tourism to Japan and stimulate local economies.
November 15: ANA to Support Typhoon-Damaged Philippines and Izu-Oshima in Japan[Company Release] Tokyo November 15th, 2013 -The ANA Group offers its deepest condolences to all those affected by and Typhoon Haiyan which directly struck the central Philippines on November 8, and Typhoon Wipha which directly struck Izu-Oshima on October 16, 2013, We would like to express our deepest sympathy to those who have lost loved ones and suffered loss of property and livelihoods.As an airline which provides regular flights to disaster areas, The ANA Group, offers humanitarian cooperation and support as follows:http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Japan/Stock/News/18015.htmlSource: Company Website
August 21: ANA to expand flight schedule for second half of FY2013[Company Release] Tokyo August 21, 2013 -ANA Group is set to expand capacity on routes between Japan, Asia and North America in a modification to its international and domestic air transportation plan for second half of FY2013. This expansion will allow the airline to capitalize on the strong demand for travel to Japan and for flights between Asia and North America.On international routes, ANA Group is preparing for the second round of additional takeoff and landing slots for international routes at Haneda Airport.
ISIN: JP3429800000
TO:9202; TYO:9202; T:9202; JP:9202
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>