<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7AD0-8028-C025-C39E"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Marois denies PQ anti-jewish; Candidate a believer in 'kosher tax'</title><source>National Post (f/k/a The Financial Post) (Canada)</source><author>Tristin Hopper, National Post</author><text><![CDATA[After a PQ candidate was discovered to have supported a fringe conspiracy theory holding that Jews use kosher food to fund clandestine political causes, Quebec Premier Pauline Marois publicly declared Friday that her party is not anti-Semitic.
At Friday campaign stop, Ms. Marois stood by Louise Mailloux, and told reporters "the Parti Québécois is not an anti-Semitic party."
"We have very good relations with the leaders of this community and all the different communities in Quebec," she said.
Ms. Mailloux has made repeated public statements backing the idea of the "kosher tax," a widely debunked canard claiming that kosher certification drives up the cost of food and imposes a de facto tax on secular consumers.
"This is a religious tax, and it's a tax we pay directly to mosques, to synagogues and to religious groups. It's a theft," Ms. Mailloux said on a March 2012 edition of Bazzo. tv, a panel show on Télé-Québec.
Ms. Mailloux, a philosophy professor at the Cégep du Vieux Montréal, had been invited to speak on the issue of halal and kosher certifications, and quickly dominated the discussion with accusations that Quebecers were unwittingly funnelling tens of thousands of dollars to potentially shady religious causes.
"What you have to see is that, when we have established a link between halal certification, an imam and a mosque, we have to go see what they are saying in these mosques and the ideology that lives there," she said.
In a Thursday statement, the Quebec branch of the Centre for Israel and Jewish Affairs accused Ms. Mailloux of echoing "a conspiracy created and spread by the Ku Klux Klan, and championed by many other racist and neo-Nazi groups."
Although theories vary, the premise of the so-called kosher tax is that Jews extort food companies for the cost of certification, and then pass on the funding to Zionist causes.
As a KKK pamphlet cited by the Anti -Defamation League writes: "Jews have discovered a way to coerce business to pay taxes directly to Jewish organizations and pass the cost on to the consumer."
In reality, while kosher and halal certification is not free; food companies do it for the same reason they would claim a product is low fat or free of genetically modified organism: to open up a new market segment and boost sales.
In a 2010 interview posted to the website of the Quebec Humanist Association, Ms. Mailloux said halal and kosher certifications were a "challenge to modernity and an attempt to inject religion into secular society."
"But companies are not wise to these political considerations, and unfortunately see these demands as nothing more than a fertile market in which to reap profits," she said.
Later, in an April 2012 editorial for L'aut'journal, she mocked the lack of culinary prohibitions in Christianity, claiming that the church missed "a great opportunity to make money."
"Just as the prayers of a priest turns bread and wine into the body and blood of Christ, those of the rabbi turns slaughtered chickens, Nestlé Quik and ketchup into thousands of dollars," she wrote.
On Thursday, Ms. Mailloux refused to renounce the existence of a kosher tax, telling a reporter from La Presse, "At this time, what interests me is defending the charter [of values]."
She is running in the Montreal riding of Gouin, very close to some of the city's Hasidic Jewish communities. A prominent secularist, she has been a persistent champion of the charter.
In a Januar y inter view with the Radio-Canada program Second Regard, Ms. Mailloux said that Quebec is under siege by a "religious offensive" and accused the Catholic Church of quietly hoping for Muslims to destroy Quebec secularism.
thopper@nationalpost.com Twitter.com/TristinHopper National Post
]]></text></news-item>