<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7B33-375B-4078-D3E2"><date>2014-03-10</date><title>Coal seam gas opponents 'scaremongering' over groundwater contamination at Pilliga gas project in NSW</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author>By state political reporters Liz Foschia, Sarah Gerathy and staff</author><text><![CDATA[Santos has accused opponents of coal seam gas of scaremongering over uranium contaminated groundwater near its Pilliga Forest gas project near Narrabri.
Farmers and environmentalists want the CSG project in the north-west of New South Wales to be suspended after Santos was fined $1,500 over a leaking wastewater pond at Bibblewindi Water Treatment Plant.
The Opposition's Environment spokesman Luke Foley says the incident undermines the assurances the community has been given about the safety of CSG.
"The industry's been saying for years, they have no impact on aquifers. Well here's some evidence, some concrete evidence," he said.
But the Vice President of Santos James Baulderstone has described it as a very minor incident and says the Environment Protection Authority (EPA) found it posed no danger to humans or animals.
He says anti-CSG activists are exaggerating.
"People are hell bent on stopping what is a very important industry for this country," he said.
He says the Pillaga project has the potential to provide 10 years worth of gas supply.
The EPA says it is confident the polluted water is not leaking any further into the underground water table.
Chief Environmental Regulator Mark Gifford says the polluted water does not seem to be spreading.
Santos will be required to implement a Groundwater Remediation and Monitoring Plan.
Mr Gifford says the site is still being monitored.
"The data that we received from the monitoring bores showed us that it was not moving from that aquifer, and the ongoing monitoring that is required around there continues to confirm that is the case," he said.
"We'll be requiring Santos to develop a thorough groundwater remediation and monitoring plan, which will be a legally enforceable condition of their license."
Coonamble grain grower Mark Robinson has been fighting Santos' Narrabri CSG project.
He says his worst nightmares were realised when he learned that Santos' waste water pond has been leaking.
"Our groundwater is so so precious to us. And to find that's it been contaminated with uranium and arsenic and all sorts of things it really is just devastating," he said.
But the Environment Minister Robyn Parker says the damage is minimal.
"This fine is because this wasn't deemed to be a serious environmental issue," she said.
The Greens will introduce a parliamentary call for papers next week, to seek information about the EPA's handling of the groundwater contamination.
Upper House Greens MP Jeremy Buckingham says he wants to know why it took a year for information about the contamination to become public.
He also wants to know whether anyone in the Government was aware of the leak when it was negotiating a memorandum of understanding with Santos to fast-track the project.
]]></text></news-item>