<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7C35-CF6D-BDA6-C420"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Washington: Intelligence Specialist Operations Support Job in SAN ANTONIO, TX</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[US Army has issued the following job vacancies:
Intelligence Specialist Operations Support Job in SAN ANTONIO, TXVacancy No. WTST148533931071839 Department U.S. Army SouthSalary $69,497.00 to $90,344.00 Grade 12 to 12Perm/Temp Permanent FT/PT Full-timeOpen Date 3/14/2014 Close Date 3/27/2014Job Link Apply Online Who may apply PublicLocations:SAN ANTONIO, TX
Job Description (Please follow all instructions carefully)
Job Title:Intelligence Specialist (Operations Support)
Department:Department of the Army
Agency:U.S. Army South
Job Announcement Number:WTST148533931071839SALARY RANGE: $69,497.00 to $90,344.00 / Per YearOPEN PERIOD: Friday, March 14, 2014 to Thursday, March 27, 2014SERIES & GRADE: GG-0132-12POSITION INFORMATION: Full Time - Excepted Service PermanentDUTY LOCATIONS: 1 vacancy in the following location:Fort Sam Houston, TXWHO MAY APPLY: US Citizens and Status CandidatesSECURITY CLEARANCE: Top Secret/SCISUPERVISORY STATUS: NoJOB SUMMARY:
Civilian employees serve a vital role in supporting the Army mission. They provide the skills that are not readily available in the military, but crucial to support military operations. The Army integrates the talents and skills of its military and civilian members to form a Total Army.
About the Position:
This position is in the Defense Civilian Intelligence Personnel System (DCIPS). Employees occupying DCIPS positions are in the Excepted Service and must adhere to U.S. Code, Title 10, as well as Department of Defense Instruction 1400.25. This position is located with the US Army South, 6th Army, Counterintelligence (CI) and Human Intelligence (HUMINT) Division, Fort Sam Houston, TX.
Who May Apply:
Only applicants who meet one of the employment authority categories below are eligible to apply for this job. You will be asked to identify which category or categories you meet, and to provide documents which prove you meet the category or categories you selected. See Proof of Eligibility for an extensive list of document requirements for all employment authorities.
Current Army Defense Civilian Intelligence Personnel System (DCIPS) Employee Current Defense Civilian Intelligence Personnel System (DCIPS) Employee (excluding Army) Current Civilian Employee with the Department of the Army Current Permanent Department of Defense (DOD) - Civilian Employee (non-Army) Current Permanent Federal Civilian Employee (non-DOD) Former Permanent Federal Employee eligible to be reappointed Veteran with a service-connected disability of 30% or more Disabled Veteran with a service-connected disability of more than 10%/less than 30% Applicant eligible for 10-Point Other veteran's rating or Derived Veterans' Preference Veteran eligible for 5-Point Preference U.S. Citizen
Army DCIPS positions apply Veteran's Preference to preference eligible candidates as defined by Section 2108 of Title 5 U.S.C., in accordance with the procedures provided in DoD Instruction 1400.25, Volume 2005, DCIPS Employment and Placement.
This is a Career Program Position (CP) 35.
TRAVEL REQUIRED
25% or Greater Temporary Duty (TDY) may be performed 30% of the time.
RELOCATION AUTHORIZED
Yes Relocation costs may be paid if the selecting official determines the relocation is in the best interest of the government.
DUTIES:
The purpose of this position is to serve as an Operations Support Branch Chief within the Counterintelligence (CI) and Human Intelligence (HUMINT) Division (G2X), G2 Directorate, USARSOUTH/Sixth Army DCS-G2, G2X, Fort Sam Houston, TX. Incumbent is responsible for providing a variety of operations support services essential to the daily operation of the organization. Duties may include, but are not limited to, Counterintelligence (CI), and Human Intelligence (HUMINT), systems management and administrative functions.
QUALIFICATIONS REQUIRED:
In order to qualify, you must meet the education and/or experience requirements described below. Your resume must clearly describe your relevant experience; if qualifying based on education, your transcripts will be required as part of your application. Additional information about transcripts is in this document.
Experience required: To qualify based on your work experience, your resume must describe at least one year of experience which prepared you to do the work in this job. Specialized experience is defined as: progressively responsible experience which has included experience in / with DoD and non-DoD Counterintelligence (CI) and Human Intelligence (HUMINT) agencies and investigative agencies in areas such as, programs, policy, operations, methodology and governing laws, Executive Orders and regulations to independently review, coordinate and make recommendations on CI and HUMINT administration and operations. This definition of specialized experience is typical of work performed at the next lower grade/level position in the federal service GG/GS-11.
0132: Progressively responsible experience is that which has included intelligence-related research, analysis, collections and /or operations. This experience should have included intelligence analysis and/or production, intelligence collection and/or operations, counterintelligence, or threat support directly related to the position to be filled. Creditable specialized experience may include previous military intelligence experience, experience gained in the private sector or in another government agency as long as it was at a level at least equivalent to the next lower grade in the series. This experience should demonstrate: Knowledge of intelligence processes, cycle and organizations; Knowledge of and/or ability to use research tools such as library holdings, photographs, statistics, graphics and maps; Knowledge of the systems, procedures and methods of analyzing, compiling, reporting and disseminating intelligence data; and/or Knowledge of organization(s) for and methods of collecting and analyzing intelligence data.
You will be evaluated on the basis of your level of competency (knowledge, skills, abilities) in the following areas:
Counterintelligence / Human Intelligence Operational Support Systems Management Verbal and Written Communication
NOTE: Creditable experience may include previous military experience, experience gained in the private sector, or experience gained in another government agency so long as it was at a level at least equivalent to the next lower grade in the series.
Some federal jobs allow you to substitute your education for the required experience in order to qualify. For this job, you must meet the qualification requirement using experience alone--no substitution of education for experience is permitted.
Other Requirements: Click here for expanded definitions.
Male applicants born after December 31, 1959 must complete a Pre-Employment Certification Statement for Selective Service Registration. You will be required to provide proof of U.S. Citizenship. Two year trial period may be required. Direct Deposit of Pay is Required. Must obtain and maintain Top Secret security clearance with access to Sensitive Compartmented Information (SCI) and selected Special Access Programs. Subject to undergo psychological screening and polygraph testing. Must obtain and maintain a valid vehicle operator's licenses. In accordance with Change 3 to AR 600-85, Alcohol and Drug Abuse Prevention and Control Program, employee must successfully pass a urinalysis screening for illegal drug use prior to appointment and periodically thereafter. Temporary duty (TDY) travel may be required 30% or less of the time. A pre-appointment and annual physical are required.
HOW YOU WILL BE EVALUATED:
Your application package (resume, supporting documents, and responses to the questionnaire) will be used to determine your eligibility, qualifications, and quality ranking for this position. Please follow all instructions carefully. Errors or omissions may affect your rating or consideration for employment.
BENEFITS:
The Department of Defense offers an excellent benefits program. In addition to your take-home pay, your comprehensive compensation/benefits package will include most of the benefits described in the USAJOBS Resource Center.
OTHER INFORMATION:
Selection is subject to restrictions resulting from Department of Defense referral system for displaced employees. Salary indicated includes applicable locality pay. Multiple positions may be filled from this announcement. Recruitment Bonus/Incentive is Not authorized. Relocation (Government Home Sale) Expenses are NOT authorized.
HOW TO APPLY:
To apply for this position, you must complete the online questionnaire and submit the documentation specified in the Required Documents section below.The complete application package must be submitted by 11:59 PM (EST) on Thursday, March 27, 2014 to receive consideration.
To begin, click Apply Online to create a USAJOBS account or log in to your existing account. Follow the prompts to select your USAJOBS resume and/or other supporting documents and complete the occupational questionnaire. Click the Submit My Answers button to submit your application package. It is your responsibility to ensure your responses and appropriate documentation is submitted prior to the closing date. To verify your application is complete, log into your USAJOBS account, select the Application Status link and then select the more information link for this position. The Details page will display the status of your application, the documentation received and processed, and any correspondence the agency has sent related to this application. Your uploaded documents may take several hours to clear the virus scan process. To return to an incomplete application, log into your USAJOBS account and click Update Application in the vacancy announcement. You must re-select your resume and/or other documents from your USAJOBS account or your application will be incomplete. It is your responsibility to verify that information entered, uploaded, or faxed (i.e., resume) is complete, accurate, and submitted by the closing date. Uploaded documents may take up to one hour to clear the virus scan. Faxed documents must be completely transmitted by 11:59p.m. Eastern Standard Time on the closing date of the announcement.
The Department of the Army provides reasonable accommodations to applicants with disabilities. If you need a reasonable accommodation for any part of the application and hiring process, please notify the servicing civilian personnel unit. Your requests for reasonable accommodation will be addressed on a case-by-case basis.
REQUIRED DOCUMENTS:
The documents you are required to submit vary based on the authority you are using to apply (i.e., applying as a veteran, applying as a current permanent Federal employee, applying as a reinstatement, etc). Please review the following links to see which documents you need to provide to prove your eligibility to apply: Applicant Merit Checklist and Proof of Eligibility.
As described above, your complete application includes your resume, your responses to the online questionnaire, and documents which prove your eligibility to apply. If you fail to provide these documents, you will be marked as having an incomplete application package and you will not be considered any further.
Your resume:
Your resume may be submitted in any format. If you submit more than one copy of your resume, only the most recent version will be reviewed. The latest timestamp will be used to determine which version of your resume is "most recent." It is your responsibility to check the status and timestamp of all documents you submit as part of your application. If your resume includes a photograph or other inappropriate material or content, it will not be used to make eligibility and qualification determinations and you may not be considered for this vacancy. For qualifications determinations your resume must contain hours worked per week and the dates of employment (i.e., HRS per week and month/year to month/year or month/year to present). If your resume does not contain this information, your application will be marked as incomplete and you will not receive consideration for this position.
If you are relying on your education to meet qualification requirements: You MUST submit a copy of your transcript if you want to substitute your education for experience. If you claim qualifications based on education, and do not submit a transcript, your education will not be used in making a qualification determination and you may be found "not qualified." See: Transcripts and Licenses
Proof of Eligibility to Apply: Your application must include the documents which prove you are eligible to apply for the vacancy. The “Proof of Eligibility” document describes authorities commonly used in merit promotion recruitment and what document(s) are required to prove you meet the requirements of the authority. You must meet the requirements of at least of the authorities listed in the Who May Apply section above to receive further consideration.
If you are unable to apply online or unable to upload your supporting documents follow the directions located at: Faxing Applications and Documents The Vacancy ID is 1071839. You will need the questionnaire, View Occupational Questionnaire, to complete your faxed application.
NOTE: Documents submitted as part of the application package, to include supplemental documents, may be shared beyond the Human Resources Office. Some supplemental documents such as military orders and marriage certificates may contain personal information for someone other than you. You may sanitize these documents to remove another person's personal information before you submit your application. You may be asked to provide an un-sanitized version of the documents if you are selected to confirm your eligibility.AGENCY CONTACT INFO:Central Resume Processing CenterPhone: (000)000-0000Email: USARMY.APG.CHRA-NE.MBX.APPLICANTHELP@MAIL.MILAgency Information:WJMW99 HQ 6A US Army SouthHQ US Army SouthFort Sam Houston, TX78234WHAT TO EXPECT NEXT:
If you provided an email address, you will receive an email message acknowledging receipt of your application. Your application package will be used to determine your eligibility, qualifications, and quality ranking for this position. If you are determined to be ineligible or not qualified, your application will receive no further consideration.
The documents you submit must support your responses to the online questionnaire. If your application contradicts or does not support your questionnaire responses, you will receive a rating of "not qualified" or "incomplete application" and you will not receive further consideration for this job.
For more information please visit:http://federalgovernmentjobs.us
]]></text></news-item>