<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7CBF-FE88-EBBE-B5DD"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Not Everyone in Russia Supports Intervention in Ukraine</title><source>Russia!</source><author>asluhn</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 15, 2014 (Russia!:http://readrussia.com Delivered by Newstex) As Crimea gets ready to for a referendum on joining Russia tomorrow—with two choices on the ballot, 'yes' and 'yes but later'—all of Russia seems to be hurrahing Vladimir Putin's decisive move to intervene in Ukraine. Television airs almost nothing but reports of fascist violence in Ukraine and ecstatic Crimean pensioners dreaming of Soviet Union redux. A poll by the independent Levada Center this week found that 58 percent of Russians support the deployment of troops to Crimea and other regions of Russia.
But not everyone is ready to bang the war drums. A peace march in Moscow on Sunday drew at least 10,000 people, the strongest turnout for an opposition march since last fall, showing that there is a vocal minority opposed to intervention in Ukraine. Despite the fact that Russia's most popular street opposition leader, Alexei Navalny—during the speeches at the end of the march, a 'Navalny' chant broke out—the march's organizers managed to gather an impressive number of people, especially considering the information war all around. (A rival protest at the Kremlin also drew large numbers in favor of intervention.) The seizure of Crimea by Russian troops has given the opposition movement a new reason to rally, and a new wind. Besides Navalny and Sergei Udaltsov, both of whom are under house arrest, all the usual faces were there, including Boris Nemtsov, Ilya Yashin and Gennady and Dmitry Gudkov. The major opposition parties were also there, from Solidarnost to the December 5 party to Parnas to Navalny's Progress Party. There were also at least two anarchist blocks chanting 'No to fascism, no to capitalism!' Marching in the first row, Nemtsov, now a regional parliamentarian in Yaroslavl, told reporters that Russia should respect the Budapest Memorandum, in which the United States, United Kingdom and Russia pledged to uphold Ukraine's territorial integrity if it gave up its nuclear weapons. Nemtsov was also the first speaker at the rally at the end of the march, which started with the strains of the Ukrainian band Okean Elzi. (An upcoming concert by the band in St. Petersburg was cancelled amid politicians' calls to ban the group from Russia over its support of the Euromaidan protests.) 'Ukraine will leave the nuclear non-proliferation agreement, and nukes will pop up in Ukraine pointed at Moscow. Do we need that?' he cried, to cries of 'no' from the crowd. 'Costs will rise, wages and pensions will contract due to sanctions. Do we need that?' Putin has 'decided to move to open dictatorship,' he added. 'Do we need that?' 'No!' As a last order of business, protestors shouted their approval of a resolution that called for the immediate withdrawal of Russian troops from Crimea. Although peace signs could be found sprinkled throughout the crowd, this march was very much a continuation of Moscow's recent tradition of opposition rallies i.e. focused intently on anti-Putin rhetoric. It would have been good to see more peace signs, more anti-war slogans, more of an understanding that the Crimean intervention represents not just Putin's megalomania but a systematic problem of today's geopolitics, where it's acceptable for the United States and anyone else to wage war without actually declaring it. That said, today Putinism and military intervention are more intertwined than ever. Unfortunately, the anti-war crowd is definitely in the minority, and probably confined mostly to St. Petersburg and Moscow. The Levada Center poll this week not only found that 58 percent support Russian intervention, but also that 63 percent think that nationwide media outlets—i.e. state-controlled television—are covering the events in Crimea and Ukraine 'objectively.' And indeed, this is the root of the problem. Russians are not bloodthirsty: 83 percent are worried by the prospect of armed conflict between Ukraine and Russia. But the nationwide media have constantly repeated the official mantra that fascists have taken power in Ukraine, the country is in a state of violent chaos and Russian-speakers there are in grave danger. When a majority still rely on television for their information, of course most will look favorably at intervention. (The information war extends to pressure on independent news media like TV Dozhd and Lenta.ru[1].) [1]: http://readrussia.com/2014/03/13/rip-lenta-ru-why-we-shall-not-look-upon-its-like-again/

]]></text></news-item>