<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7D00-EDF4-FAE1-FF1F"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Confusion as tanker flees port in Libya</title><source>Canberra Times (Australia)</source><author>Pyongyang</author><text><![CDATA[Confusion as tanker flees port in Libya Pyongyang North Korea has denied any responsibility for an oil tanker that loaded crude from a Libyan rebel-held port and fled the country's attempt to seize it, saying the vessel that carried the North Korean flag was linked to an Egyptian company.
The incident marked the first sale of Libyan crude bypassing the government and was a huge humiliation for Tripoli as it struggled to rein in armed militias who helped oust dictator Muammar Gaddafi in 2011 but want to grab power and oil revenues.
Libya's parliament ousted prime minister Ali Zeidan on Tuesday after rebels loaded crude at Es Sider terminal onto the North Korean- flagged tanker.
The ship later fled naval forces amid reports of a gunfight as it sailed off along Libya's eastern Mediterranean coast.
It was unclear where the tanker had planned to sail. The North Korean flag is considered a flag of convenience, which is used to keep the ownership secret.
North Korea said that the tanker violated its laws and a contract with the Alexandria-based company by carrying contraband cargo.
It said it had notified Libya and the International Maritime Organisation that it had severed all association with the ship.
"Therefore, the ship has nothing to do with the DPRK at present and it has no responsibility whatsoever as regards the ship," the North's Maritime Administration said in a statement carried by the official KCNA news agency. DPRK is short for the North's official name, the Democratic People's Republic of Korea.
North Korea said it had temporarily allowed Egypt's Golden East Logistics to use its flag under a six- month contract signed in late February.
It said the company ignored its demand to leave the rebel-held Libyan port without loading oil.
Golden East Logistics said it had been responsible for the vessel's certification until its North Korean flag was cancelled earlier this week but was not the operator and had no knowledge of its cargo, whereabouts or ultimate destination.
"Our company only represents the certification management and nothing else and we have no relation, from near or far, to the operation of the said vessel nor its commercial management nor the undertaking of any agreements regarding its cargoes," Golden East Logistics said. It was unusual for an oil tanker flagged in secretive North Korea to operate in the Mediterranean, shipping sources said. It had changed ownership in the past few weeks, a source said. Reuters
]]></text></news-item>