<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7D8D-3656-1E13-3560"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Coal intimi</title><source>Weekly Cutting Edge</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Pakistani planners are facing stiff resistance from the West, particularly the United States, on installing coal run power plants to overcome its power shortages. The US Ambassador to Pakistan Richard Olson has, in fact, publically cautioned Pakistan against using this option, as coal pollutes the environment.
The United States and its Western allies conveniently ignore the fact that they produce the bulk of their electricity from the same pollutant fuel. The United States, for instance, produces 43 percent of electricity from coal.According to the Global Coal Council, coal accounts for 41 percent of the total electricity produced in the world. Pakistan hardly produces 1 percent of power from coal, while all major industrial countries generate most of their power from coal. They are high electricity consumers as well. The statistics released by the Council reveal that South Africa produces 94 percent of electricity from coal, while power production from coal is 79 percent in China, 78 percent in Australia, 68 percent in India, 59 percent in Israel, 51 percent in the Czech Republic, 54 percent in Greece, 43 percent in United States, 41 percent in Germany, 40 percent in England and 27 percent in Japan. All these countries consume many times more power than Pakistan. In fact, if Pakistan fulfills all its power needs from coal, it would pollute the environment at least 50 times less than the pollution that the US causes by producing power from coal.World powers should stop using double standards to endorse every environment polluting step of their own, while harassing others on the slightest fear of environmental pollution. Coal is the cheapest fuel for power production after hydro-electricity and gas-run generators. Moreover, coal fired power plants can be established in the shortest possible time. In countries like Pakistan, where the power shortage is very acute, coal-based power plants are the only short term remedy. If the global community has concern about the pollution caused by coal, they should start eliminating their coal-fired power plants before discouraging poorer countries from adopting a cheaper power generation option. Until they do, they have no right to object to other countries striving to reduce their power deficit through coal based power generation.According to creditable statistics, total coal consumption in Pakistan is only 4.6 metric tons of oil equivalent (MTOE) whereas it is 277.7 MTOE in India and a whopping 17,135 MTOE in China. In the United States, it is almost twice that of China as its electricity consumption is four times higher than China's. Even if Pakistan installs 12,000 MW coal-based plants the use of coal would not exceed 100 MTOE. Interestingly, the US objection on coal came when the Prime Minister of Pakistan Nawaz Sharif and former President Asif Ali Zardari buried their differences to support the Thar Coal project. This was a welcome show of unity on national interests as Pakistan is sitting on one of the largest coal reserves in the world and it has every right to use that natural resource.The objection of the US to projects that could alleviate miseries in Pakistan is not new. In fact, it has always faced discrimination from the developed world. When sanctions were imposed on Iran, the United States granted a waiver to India, permitting it to continue importing oil from that country. Japan was similary allowed to continue importing oil from Iran. But when Pakistan desired to buy gas from Iran, it was warned in clear terms about the consequences of the violation of sanctions. Experts say that had the Pak-Iran gas pipeline been allowed at the right time, there would have been no need to produce power from coal. Now growth in Pakistan is hostage to acute power shortages. Experts warn that Pakistan could see irreversible increase in poverty if it continued to remain an energy-starved country after four years. The United States did facilitate Pakistan in improving the efficiency of our existing power plants, but the incremental power that we may get would not be more than 1,300 MW, while average power shortages in Pakistan, even at suppressed demand, is 5000-6000 MW. The need is for power increases by around 2,000 MW every year as the GDP moves up even at small pace.The United States discriminated against Pakistan on nuclear technology as well. India's stand and needs on the nuclear issue are the same as those of Pakistan. The United States has provided India with nuclear technology for peaceful purposes, but the same has been denied to Pakistan. Not only that, the US government puts pressure on China as well, which continues to supply nuclear power plants to Pakistan. Such discrimination is increasing poverty in Pakistan and providing fodder to the extremists. US opposition to coal-based power plants is the ultimate hypocrisy. How can it oppose a technology when it produces the largest amount of power from that same technology? Even globally, the highest amount of electricity (41 percent) is produced from coal, 5 percent from oil, 21 percent from gas, 13 percent hydro and 3 percent other renewable sources.Pakistan is facing a grave power crisis. The best option is to produce hydro-electricity as its potential in Pakistan is very high. The problem with hydro-electric projects is that they are completed in 7-10 years. Only the initial studies, feasibility and engineering design costs are very high. The cost of these projects is also very high as these are executed in difficult terrain. Pakistan has, in fact, initiated some power projects which would be completed in four to seven years. Neelam-Jhelum hydro-electric project of 969 MW would be operational in the first half of 2016, Tarbela extension worth 1,000 MW is expected to start producing electricity in three years time. Other bigger projects will take more time.The reason to opt for coal was that these projects could be installed in two to three years and at a reasonable cost. Industrial production in Pakistan is suffering badly due to shortage of power. New investments are not coming in due to this very reason. Pakistan first sought the assistance of its Western friends to finance coal-fired power projects, but after their lukewarm attitude, turned to China. The Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif in his address at the Pakistan Auto Show at Lahore revealed that China would be financing coal fired power projects at Gwadar and Gadani. Project loans for coal fired power projects are not being provided by multilateral donor agencies. The Chinese exim bank is providing these loans.
]]></text></news-item>