<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7E30-78A6-4A3D-AF96"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>ELECTRICITY SUPPLY. On the brink - again</title><source>Financial Mail (South Africa)</source><author>Sikonathi Mantshantsha</author><text><![CDATA[ELECTRICITY SUPPLY
On the brink - again
Last week's power outages put the spotlight on SA's vulnerable electricity grid. examines Eskom's woes and argues that systemic problems at the utility could result in more power cuts this winter
THEY ARE TRYING TO PREVENT THE WORST POSSIBLE OUTCOME, AND THAT IS A TOTAL COLLAPSE OF THE GRID
NEREN RAU
WHAT IT MEANS
UNSCHEDULED MAINTENANCE BIGGEST THREAT TO SUPPLY
AT LEAST 121 GENERATING UNITS AT 23 STATIONS OUT OF SERVICE
After three power emergencies since November, Eskom resorted to load shedding last week. To cope with an unprecedented 29% loss of capacity, the utility was forced into rolling blackouts for the first time since 2008.
Though they were shorter and came with more communication, the power interruptions are by no means over. Eskom has blamed wet coal for the outages but a combination of factors caused the blackouts and will persist even after the wet coal dries.
The SA economy, however, is in for more pain as the power supply will continue to be constrained until new generation capacity is added to the system.
The additional capacity of an initial 800MW is expected to be from the Medupi power station which is still under construction. However, Medupi has been racked by delays and will contribute to the grid by the end of the year only in the unlikely event that no further glitches hamper progress.
More rolling blackouts cannot be ruled out even after the rainy season ends as Eskom is struggling to meet even the lowest demand.
SA should prepare for more power cuts as:
Eskom is able to keep the lights on only because large industrial customers have been asked to switch off, which is likely to affect economic growth if this is done repeatedly or for a prolonged period;
For the first time, unplanned outages exceed planned outages. Winter demand is higher so there's little chance that Eskom will have additional capacity any time soon;
The Financial Mail has learnt that maintenance programmes are often delayed as equipment is not ordered on time due to cash flow constraints even though the budget for maintenance has almost doubled since last year; and
Lax quality control increased problems with wet coal.
The lack of electricity has had a negative effect on the economy as large industrial consumers - including mines and smelters - have been asked to cut back usage, and in some instances were asked to shut down. In the past two weeks, immediately before, during and after the load shedding on Thursday, Eskom instructed its largest customers to reduce demand by 20% to help stabilise supply.
As these companies consume about 44% of total capacity and help drive economic activity in SA, they are likely to continue to suffer in the short term as the delicate supply will persist beyond problems with the wet coal caused by high rainfall and scheduled maintenance.
"The [traditional] 10% demand reduction wasn't enough to meet available supply," says Eskom CEO Brian Dames. "We were stuck with a shortfall of 3000MW that we couldn't make up."
The two "emergency situations" in February and the blackout happened even though the largest platinum mining companies, which employ more than 100000 people between them, have been using less electricity due to a nearly two month-long work stoppage by workers demanding higher wages. When the mines restart production Eskom's supply will again be stretched to close to breaking point.
However, the return of the platinum miners to consumption will not necessarily cause a break of the supply system as Eskom has always maintained a tight system with those miners on the grid. In addition, Eskom has learnt lessons from 2008 and now has better working relations with its customers.
A telephone call to the single largest electricity consumer, BHP Billiton's Hillside smelter at Richards Bay, yields the desired result, allowing it to stabilise the supply system before switching the smelter back on in a period of about two hours. Such was the situation last week; Eskom called on its largest customers to reduce demand and then started rationing the power.
As a result, companies were able to limit losses due to load shedding, says the SA Chamber of Commerce & Industry (Sacci).
"This was much better than the blackouts of 2008; companies were forewarned to expect and plan around the load shedding," says Sacci CEO Neren Rau. He says it was a "disciplined process that brought about limited costs". Rau says the best thing about this round of load shedding was the open communication that accompanied it.
Last week's blackouts didn't cause too much damage as regards business confidence, but if there were to be more load shedding, then business confidence would take a hit, says Rau. "Though it is relatively new to SA, load shedding is a fairly common occurrence in other emerging markets, such as India and China."
Rau says Sacci appreciates Eskom's handling of a difficult situation but its members would prefer that other consumers share in reducing demand because when the burden falls on industry only, the economic impact is worse.
"This will have an absolutely bigger negative impact on economic performance, but for consumers it will just be an inconvenience if they go without power for a few hours a day," Rau says.
Eskom had to start load shedding after a week of heavy rains drenched its coal, rendering it unusable and tripping generating units at three power stations in Mpumalanga. The wet coal choked four units of the 4100MW Kendal station outside Emalahleni, which tripped, causing the blackouts.
Rau says Eskom has done its utmost to keep the lights on, and that load shedding wasn't the worst possible outcome of a power shortage. "They are trying to prevent the worst possible outcome, and that is a total collapse of the grid," he says. Undesirable as it is, load shedding is the better of the two.
Last week, in addition to the four units down at Kendal, the rain caused outages at a unit each at Majuba and Grootvlei power stations. Unplanned shutdowns at other power stations took down a total 7800MW of capacity, which was almost 19% of the total. Scheduled maintenance meant that a further 4500MW was not available to the grid. By last Thursday, an unprecedented 29,3% of generating capacity was unavailable to produce power.
The units out of commission are: 87 at 14 coal-fired power stations; 20 units at four open-cycle gas turbine power stations, two units at the Koeberg nuclear power station, six units at two pumped storage schemes and six units at two hydro power stations, totalling 121 units, says spokesman Tony Stott. "The maintenance outages of three units have been delayed over the past six months. All of these were delayed due to capacity constraints."
Delays in maintenance could worsen the problems: when a fault occurs, there is no leeway - the unit will have to be taken off line immediately to be repaired.
Eskom has stuck to its official line that the wet weather of early March was the main contributor to the blackouts, but senior employees say internal inefficiencies together with cash-flow problems should be blamed. Employees who spoke to the Financial Mail on condition of anonymity say poor logistical planning, a shortage of skills and inadequate cash flow are the real reasons behind the blackouts.
In an interview with Talk Radio 702, Dames appeared to give this contention some credibility. He said the wet coal that tripped Kendal came from an open pit mine at the rain-soaked Khutala mine. The mine failed to mix the open pit coal with drier coal from underground, as is the requirement in such a situation. Eskom has its own quality controllers at the mine, which means they allowed unsuitable coal to be sent to clog the station's conveyor belts.
Also, costly overruns to its build programme have put pressure on Eskom's balance sheet. The most notorious example of delay is at Medupi where Hitachi - which until recently had the ANC's investment firm Chancellor House as a local partner - did substandard work on boilers. Eskom has laid criminal charges against a Hitachi subcontractor.
Last year the National Electricity Regulator of SA granted Eskom half the 16% tariff increase it had requested. As a result, it collects less revenue, reducing cash flow and stretching its maintenance budget.
Another source within Eskom says a major problem is a lack of logistical planning and unnecessarily long approval processes as a result of the cash-flow problems. He works in the maintenance unit for a cluster of stations, including Duvha and Tutuka at Standerton in Mpumalanga. He says: "It is still raining heavily. The rain hasn't stopped since the beginning of March, but there is no load shedding now. How do you explain that?"
His argument is that it is not only the rain and wet coal that caused most stations to trip up, but rather poor quality controls and lack of spares to fix power stations, which are on average 31 years old.
In the normal operation of a fleet of power stations, parts have to be ordered at least six months in advance as they are mostly big-ticket items that can cost millions of rand each. But Eskom takes at least three months to approve a purchase order for the major components of a boiler. "Orders that could have been done at least six months ago are being approved only a month before the generating unit must be shut down for maintenance," says the source.
The result is that the downtime for power stations has doubled. An overhaul of a boiler unit takes approximately 60 days when all the parts are in place. "But it now takes us 120 days a year on average to do maintenance on a unit," says the source. That's because by the time the unit must be shut down, not all the replacement parts are on site.
"It takes at least six months for some of the parts to be dispatched by our suppliers as there are really high-cost items that can be made only upon receipt of a valid order," says the mechanical engineer, who has about 10 years' experience at the parastatal.
The tight supply capacity also means Eskom has to skip other essential parts of the maintenance process, such as the shutting down of a generating unit for a two-week inspection ahead of the planned two-month overhaul.
The inspection helps to gauge the level of work that must be done at each boiler and what parts need replacing. Once the boiler is opened up and parts checked, a document with required items is drawn up for the procurement division, says the engineer.
That document provides the basis for procurement orders, and must be done at least nine months before the annual shutdown so that parts can be ordered to arrive on time. "But what has happened in the past three years is that most of the stations don't do the inspection, they just shut down," he says.
That's because by the time a generating unit must be shut down, there is already tight supply that threatens load shedding. So the engineers just order the parts that must be changed at regular service intervals. Surprise faults they may find inside the boiler can add a further 60 days to the shutdown as new parts have to be ordered again, which means the unit misses its deadline to be back in full production.
Also, ordering spares for the additional work gets snarled up in red tape, which has become stricter due to the cash-flow problems. "The process to get approval has become arduous. But you will eventually get the money to buy the parts," says the engineer.
An employee of one of Eskom boiler maintenance contractors confirms that the logistical and cash-flow problems negatively affect the downtime of power stations. "The key delay seems to be centralised procurement, which means foreign skilled workers [hired for the maintenance work] are paid but are not working as they sit idly waiting for parts that were ordered late," she says.
Her employer does maintenance work for several stations, including Kriel, Matla and Majuba in Mpumalanga which, she says, are all facing shortages of equipment. The contractor provides only the skilled personnel on maintenance contracts - Eskom must procure the equipment and parts itself.
The foreign workers she's referring to are artisans who have to be hired from abroad to do specialised maintenance if Eskom does not have the capacity locally.
Eskom's failure to procure the equipment on time means that the entire schedule gets pushed out with hardly any units going back to generating energy when they are expected to. "None of my stations has come back on time from scheduled maintenance this financial year," says the Eskom employee. He helps co-ordinate the maintenance of a cluster of four power stations.
During the heavy rains last week two generating units at Tutuka in Standerton tripped while two had already been brought down for scheduled maintenance, leaving only two working. "But none of that had anything to do with wet coal. We have three down now on unplanned maintenance, and only one is shut for scheduled maintenance," says the source. "So I don't buy the wet coal story. It is a cash flow and logistics issue."
Eskom's chief of the generation unit, Thava Govender, admits that sourcing parts is an issue, but not the major issue that contributed to the load shedding. However, Dames admits that the cash flow situation has become "severe".
Dames says that none of the essential maintenance has had to be shelved because of a lack of funding. "We have increased the budget every year for the past three years because our stations are old and require more maintenance," he says. In fact, the company has almost doubled its maintenance budget for the financial year ending March, he says. Last year it spent R12,2bn on maintenance.
The aggressive prewinter maintenance schedule is taking out 6500MW until the end of April. By itself, this has not affected generation - it was the combination of this with the 7800MW of unplanned shutdowns that caused last week's outage.
SA, therefore, has to brace itself for a tough winter as that's when demand peaks (see graphic) as consumers need more power to heat their homes.
Another factor compounding the supply problem is that three years after the initial deadline, the Medupi station under construction in Limpopo will still not be able to generate any electricity this winter. That deprives Eskom of a desperately needed additional 800MW. "The system remains tight and is vulnerable to any changes going into winter, and will remain so for the next few years until the build programme is completed," says Dames.
Eskom and SA's key challenge will be to limp through winter without major power interruptions, and to hope that Eskom will be able to start generating electricity from the Medupi plant by the end of the year. Additional base load capacity - even if it's just the initial 800MW of unit six at Medupi - will go a long way to alleviating the supply pressure that Eskom faces. That, together with the renewable energy projects that have started coming on line, will give confidence to industry and restore certainty of supply.
Sacci decided to be proactive, says Rau. Immediately after the load shedding it asked for a meeting of its member organisations with Eskom and public enterprises minister Malusi Gigaba, which was due to take place this week.
The meeting would be Dames's last as Eskom CEO as he is leaving at the end of March (see story on page 26). If government does not appoint a successor soon, this will add to a lack of confidence in the utility, a situation it can ill afford.
mantshantshas@fm.co.za @sikonathim
Brian Dames
The system remains
tight and is vulnerable
to any changes
]]></text></news-item>