<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7E40-33ED-79A7-F600"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Close encounters of the weird kind</title><source>Arts &amp; Book Review</source><author>REVIEWS BY LAURENCE PHELAN</author><text><![CDATA[UNDER THE SKIN (15) *****
Dir. Jonathan Glazer; Starring Scarlett Johansson, Antonia Campbell-Hughes, 108mins
Notionally, Jonathan Glazer's third film is a sci-fi horror starring Scarlett Johansson as a predatory alien who uses sexual allure to catch her prey. But it definitely isn't Species, the 1995 Natasha Henstridge movie about the same thing. Showing us our own world through alien and existentially lonely eyes, it does share some strands of DNA with Nicolas Roeg's The Man Who Fell to Earth. But stripping back Michel Faber's already spare source novel even further, it is a chilly, bloodless, semi-abstract and singular mood piece. It is completely wordless for long stretches. It has the strangest, most surreal and eerily beautiful death scenes you've ever seen.
Such moments of symbolist cinematic beauty contrast with a documentary rawness elsewhere. Much of the film was shot with hidden cameras, on the streets of Glasgow at night. The effect is disorientating. Commonplace city scenes begin to look unwelcoming and harsh. There are moments of sympathy and tenderness in the third act, in which Johansson's character escapes into the Highlands. But they are short-lived.
Under the Skin warns us that our position at the top of the food chain is provisional. But, as in all of the most chilling horror films, what is most scary is the detached indifference with which our lives are regarded by the rest of the universe.
THE ROCKET (12A) ****
Dir. Kim Mordaunt; Starring Sitthiphon Disamoe, Loungnam Kaosainam, 96mins
This colourful magical- realist underdog fable is about the misadventures of a loveable motherless scamp who was born under a curse in a small village in Laos, whose family is displaced by the building of a new hydro-electric dam, and who is taken under the wing by a former child soldier turned alcoholic James Brown obsessive. Comedy and tragedy are crowded together in every scene, unexploded bombs still litter the majestic landscape, but hardships and Laos's unhappy history would seem not to diminish its people's spirits.
THE ZERO THEOREM (15) **
Dir. Terry Gilliam; Starring Christoph Waltz, Mélanie Thierry, 106mins
Christoph Waltz plays a lowly, solipsistic, paranoid and possibly schizophrenic data cruncher frantically searching for meaning in a hyperstimulated near-future corporatocracy. Terry Gilliam cannibalises aspects of 1984, Blade Runner and the Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy as well as his own Brazil and Twelve Monkeys in order to sustain his satirical sci-fi vision. But even with all these colourful parts there is a suspicion that, as with the mathematical formula of the title, it doesn't add up to all that much.
NEED FOR SPEED (12A) ***
Dir. Scott Waugh; Starring Aaron Paul, Imogen Poots, 130mins
Like the video games on which it is based, this high-gloss, high-speed driving movie has the thinnest of plots with which to string together its various race and chase scenes. But it also has a cheery, unpretentious attitude, some impressive stunts and a likeable cast. Imogen Poots is even able to do something fresh with her role as the token female.
PLOT FOR PEACE (12A) ***
Dir. Carlos Agulló + Mandy Jacobson, 82mins
A documentary about the role played by one Monsieur Jacques - a French businessman or spy; he isn't saying - in the highly complex and confusing negotiations between various African nations, the US, Cuba and the Soviet Union, that contributed to the ending of Apartheid in South Africa.
SUZANNE (12A) ****
Dir. Katell Quillévéré; Starring Sara Forestier, François Damiens, 92mins
Spanning 25 years in the lives of Suzanne, a wayward young French single mother; her sister; their widowed lorry-driver father; and the man who leads her astray, this watchful, non-judgemental, beautifully controlled and tender slice of poetic realism shows us how easily, and with how little of their own input, a person's life can be derailed. Every performance is very well-judged and completely naturalistic, but you can't take your eyes off Sara Forestier as Suzanne.
VERONICA MARS (12A) **
Dir. Rob Thomas; Starring Kristen Bell, Jason Dohrin, 105mins
From the pre-credits "Previously on Veronica Mars" catch-up onwards, this continuation of the 2004-07 television show about a sassy, then-teenaged private eye is unambitious and resolutely small-screen. It was partly crowd-funded by fans who might still enjoy the nostalgic reunion, but even they will have to admit that its characters should really have graduated from such shallow hijinks and Murder, She Wrote-style plotting by now.
BACK TO THE GARDEN (12A) ***
Dir. Jon Sanders; Starring Emma Garden, Bob Goody, 94mins
This low-budget British film is an unapologetically mellow, minor and minor- key actor's piece, in which a late-middle-aged theatre troupe gathers in a Kentish garden to scatter the ashes of one of their friends, talk about loss, mortality and their marriages, and read the odd poem.
]]></text></news-item>