<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7EB1-0725-9D82-ECAC"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>MORE VIEWS</title><source>Wisconsin State Journal (Madison, Wisconsin)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[State health insurance shouldn't cover abortion
As Catholic physicians from around the state who practice in many medical settings and specialties, members of our organization are concerned that two reasonable bills, Assembly Bill 216 and AB 217, are stalled in the Wisconsin Senate.
The bills would align state law with federal law and affirm established protections in the provision of health care.
AB 216, the Health Care Conscience Act, mirrors federal law by providing an exemption from objectionable contraceptive coverage requirements for religious entities. And like the Federal Employee Health Benefits Program, it prohibits state employee health insurance from covering most abortion services.
AB 217 prohibits medical professionals from knowingly performing sex-selective abortions. This legislation promotes the dignity of human life by ensuring physicians and other health care professionals are not a party to gender discrimination.
These bills affirm protections that have been recognized both federally and internationally. The Wisconsin Senate should take action and pass AB 216 and AB 217.
- Dr. Robin J. Goldsmith, Neenah, president, Wisconsin Catholic Medical Guilds
Advance Fox Valley Regional Transit Authority bill
Gov. Scott Walker declared the week of March 3 Wisconsin Transit Week. A broad coalition of transportation stakeholders gathered in the Capitol for Public Transit Day March 4.
Groups pushed for increased funding to maintain roads and expand transit service. But the elephant in the room was the Fox Valley Regional Transit Authority Bill, SB 259.
This bill already passed the Senate with bipartisan support last month. Unfortunately, it is being held up by Assembly Speaker Robin Vos, R-Rochester, and the legislative session is ending.
The Fox Valley urgently needs this authority to buffer against funding cuts, as population growth makes them ineligible for nearly $2 million in federal transit operating funds.
Time is running out for the Fox Valley RTA. Vos should put biases aside and do what's right for the Fox Valley, for seniors and disabled citizens who can't drive, and for students and workers who choose not to drive for environmental or economic reasons.
The Fox Valley RTA bill deserves another hearing, a Rules Committee vote, and a full Assembly vote before the session ends.
- Ryan Wnuk, Madison, Sierra Club intern
Ukraine needs our help in struggle for freedom
Is it worth it to stand with Ukraine? Having been there, in the south of Ukraine, I say yes.
Ukrainians are basically like us, except they are poorer. We have much more in common with them than with the people of Afghanistan or Iraq.
Their recent freedom fight was not unlike our own struggle for freedom. This was not just the European Union and United States versus Russia in a battle for the Ukrainians. It was also a matter of personal freedom and ridding themselves of corrupt leaders.
Good friends of mine in Ukraine say Russians have infiltrated areas where Russian speakers live to foment fears and create hostility toward the leaders in Kiev. If Ukraine were to fall, who would be next? Poland, Romania, Bulgaria? Or how about Georgia again, or Azerbajian?
It's time for NATO and the United States to show some backbone and willingness to protect Ukraine. Ukraine has much to offer both the EU and Russia, but it remains a buffer to the megalomaniac ideas of Russian leader Vladimir Putin.
Ukraine is worthy of our help. I hope we help Ukraine rather than appeasing or lecturing Putin like the Allies did in World War II with Adolf Hitler. Will history teach us anything?
- Peter Olson, Monona
Corporate farms are buying up and taking over
In 1965 you could buy a 120-acre farm with a house and outbuildings for $50,000 or less.
Fast forward 50 years and you want to retire. Unless you bought more property and expanded, your farm is now worth $600,000. Your children can't afford to take on that much debt, and the farm isn't big enough to generate adequate income for everyone to live on. So you decide to sell.
A corporate farm or big grain farmer will come along and buy your farm and sell your house and outbuildings and a small amount of acreage to a hobby farmer.
They will then parcel out as many single-family plots as the local policy will allow. The town likes it because those plots will generate more tax revenue.
The corporate farm will rent all the crop land for $160 an acre or more. They will even bulldoze the fence lines and get rid of those unsightly trees. "No Trespassing" signs will be posted and hunting areas leased to private parties.
Anyone interested in farming will be welcome to work as farm labor.
Big farms, like big corporations, will keep steamrolling until we are forced to accept their terms.
The future of farming in Wisconsin lies in the ability to have income, health insurance and a market available for your product. Good luck.
- Rex Tilley, Brooklyn
Repeal the state mining law for Gogebic Taconite
Gov. Scott Walker signed Act 1 into law a year ago for Gogebic Taconite. Despite overwhelming opposition from around the state and obvious dangers to the safety of the local economy, environment and democracy, Walker signed it.
Now Gogebic Taconite President Bill Williams is being charged in Spain with mismanaging and polluting groundwater. According to the complaint, while director at Cobre Las Cruces copper mine, Williams failed to meet permit conditions, ignored the spirit and letter of permit, and failed to get authorization for changes to the permitted system. Their hydrogeological model failed to produce the promised results. An investigation claims the company had no plans to meet any of the demands of the permit.
Politicians who have abandoned the people and now appear to work for mining corporations have stolen Wisconsin's rich tradition of environmental stewardship. It is our duty to stand up and demand a repeal of Act 1, as well as Act 118, the wetlands destruction law that goes hand in hand with it.
If Spain is any indication, then a repeal is in order.
- Barbara With, Madeline Island
Give convicts with good records a second chance
In response the State Journal's March 5 editorial, "Public expects caution with killers," about keeping "many of the worst" prisoners in prison:
Your editorial board misses several key points. Most of these individuals committed a violent crime when they were young men, some still teenagers. They have now been in prison for decades. Many of them are much wiser individuals who understand the wrong that they did, and deeply regret it. Do they not deserve a second chance after being incarcerated for decades? Do most of our faith traditions not recognize the possibility of personal transformation and require forgiveness?
Secondly, when these individuals were sentenced, their judges knew exactly how the old parole system worked. If they sentenced someone to 25 years, they knew he would be eligible for parole in half that time or less. The state has no right to now keep individuals sentenced under the old law locked up indefinitely when the sentencing judge determined parole should be considered. If an individual has a good prison record, has taken required courses such as anger management, and has reached his parole eligibility date, he deserves a second chance.
Finally, the risk of recidivism is not high just because someone committed a violent crime. A recent Stanford University study covered in the State Journal reported that out of 860 California murderers sentenced to life in prison who were eventually paroled between 1990 and 2010, none committed another murder and only 5 committed any new crime. Prisoners convicted of rape of an adult woman have a very low likelihood of re-offending. Let's get facts before we talk about keeping violent offenders locked up for as long as we can.
- Carol Rubin, president, Madison Organizing on Strength, Equality and Solidarity (MOSES)
]]></text></news-item>