<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7EF9-764D-3118-A12E"><date>2014-03-16</date><title></title><source>The Japan News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[MORIOKA--To help create jobs for elderly people affected by the 2011 Great East Japan Earthquake, business leaders in Kagawa Prefecture, the home of Sanuki udon noodles, helped open an udon noodle restaurant in Rikuzen-Takata, Iwate Prefecture, last week.
Ten elderly people living in a nearby temporary housing complex for disaster victims are employed at the udon restaurant, named Pippi-ya Sanuki Rikuzen-Takata Sohonten. Pippi is a child's word, used in the Sanuki district of Kagawa Prefecture, meaning udon.
The restaurant's construction was funded by donations. A company running an udon restaurant chain in Kagawa Prefecture is supplying it with udon noodles and broth at cost to help disaster victims who have lost their jobs and tend to be isolated from the rest of their community.
Business leaders have outsourced management of the udon restaurant to Sanriku Porano Hiroba, an incorporated association that runs a restaurant employing female disaster victims near JR Takekoma Station in the city. The new restaurant is located in a prefabricated one-story building next to this restaurant.
The idea of opening an udon restaurant arose when members of Kagawa Prefecture's small and mid-sized business association visited the city in March 2012 to ask what kind of help they could offer.
Association members Tetsuya Matsuda, 51, a tax accountant from Takamatsu, came up with the idea of an udon restaurant after residents of a temporary housing complex told him they had enough food and clothes but nothing to do.
Matsuda also learned that they were isolated from their neighbors and did not have many chances to talk with other people, so he looked for a way to create jobs for them.
"If there is a place to work, they will regain the joy of life and connections with other people," he said.
Matsuda noticed there were not enough restaurants for the many construction workers coming to the area for restoration projects. He therefore planned to open a restaurant serving authentic Sanuki udon at a reasonable price.
About 4 million yen in costs for constructing the restaurant and other expenses were financed by donations from association members. The Takamatsu municipal government donated cooking utensils and other items worth 1 million yen.
Takamatsu-based Tamoya, a company that runs an udon restaurant chain in Shikoku and other regions, willingly consented to provide noodles and broth at cost. Earnings from the restaurant will be used for restoration work in the area.
"I'd like to offer a seminar to teach the workers how to make hand-kneaded noodles," said Tamoya President Tamotsu Kurokawa, 51.
Yoju Moriya, 58, head of Sanriku Porano Hiroba, said, "We'd like to make this a restaurant where disaster survivors gather and spread their cheerfulness in the area."
The association is collecting contributions in increments of 1,000. yen For further information, call its secretariat at (087) 869-3770.
]]></text></news-item>