<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="7FD6-D8A0-A53F-DCA3"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Oregon: Solid Waste Cleanup and Enforcement Program Supervisor</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[City of Metro, The State of Oregon has issued the following news release:
Job Title: Solid Waste Cleanup and Enforcement Program SupervisorClosing Date/Time: Fri. 03/14/14 5:00 PM Pacific TimeSalary: $67,797.00 - $94,262.00 AnnuallyJob Type: Full TimeLocation: 600 NE Grand Ave, Portland, Oregon
Position Summary Benefits Supplemental Questions
The Solid Waste Cleanup and Enforcement Program Supervisor develops strategies and directs programs to investigate illegal dumps and solid waste flow control violations; manages contracting activities; and ensures that the regulated parties maintain compliance with all applicable Metro solid waste laws, rules, policies and procedures. Supervises Metro employees in the outreach and assistance unit and provides oversight for local law enforcement in an investigative and clean-up unit. Enforces solid waste requirements at private facilities.
At Metro, we strive to hire a workforce representative of the communities we serve, understanding that a diverse workforce strengthens our organization. We value diversity and support a positive and welcoming environment where all of our employees can thrive.
As part of your application materials, please include a resume and a cover letter describing your experience as it relates to the duties of this position.
Essential Job Duties:An employee in this position must be able to perform all the essential job duties listed below with or without reasonable accommodation; however, this list is not intended to include all of the specific tasks which an employee in this position may be expected to perform.
Supervises programs to identify, investigate and prosecute suspected flow control violators, illegal disposal, illegal dumpers, theft of service and other illegal solid waste activities. Ensures investigations and enforcement actions are completed in a fair, timely, appropriate and consistent manner. Ensures investigations and enforcement can generally withstand legal challenges. Recommends issuance of and prepares non-compliance advisory letters, notices of violation, citations and penalties. Supervises programs that assure illegal disposal and illegal campsite cleanups are completed in a timely and responsive manner. Ensures Metro Code and internal procedures are consistently followed and accurately reported. Institutes strategies to assure consistency of practices, such as conducting periodic ride-alongs with law enforcement investigators and cleanup crews. Develops and oversees strategies and programs to prevent and reduce dumping, flow control violations and other illegal solid waste activities. Develops techniques to improve efficiency of identify potential flow control violations. Establishes and maintains written policy guidelines that set forth conditions in which Metro will participate in cleanups on behalf of local governments. Assists with illegal dumping and illegal camp cleanups at Metro-owned property. Develops and maintains framework and guidelines for cleanup of illegal dumps. Establishes and maintains written policy guidelines that set forth procedures in which Metro will notify, post, cleanup and maintain personal property at illegal campsites. Develops and oversees strategies and programs to enforce Metro Code, authorizations and policies. Develops and maintains enforcement procedures, classification and penalty calculation system. Develops and maintains penalty calculation policy to assure consistent and defensible monetary penalties for various types of violations, including cost recovery. Coordinates effectively with local governments, law/code enforcement agencies and DEQ. Negotiates and manages Metro agreements under which Metro will conduct illegal camp cleanups. Manages various contracts with local law enforcement agencies. Works with Communications to provide outreach to the construction industry regarding flow control regulations, including ethnically diverse populations. Supervises, trains and mentors program staff, including contracted officers from the Multnomah County Sheriff’s Office and Tigard Police Department. Prepares budget based on resource availability and requirement, and program goals and objectives; ensures spending within available resources. Performs related duties as assigned.
For further information please visit: http://news.oregonmetro.gov
]]></text></news-item>