<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8024-C686-EB66-DDB4"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Jobs spike lifts spirits but labour outlook still bleak'; Gareth Costa ; China industrial production growth off target</title><source>The West Australian (Perth)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
A surge in domestic job creation last month and lack of negative Chinese news drove the Australian sharemarket higher yesterday but optimism waned into the close.
Weakness in bellwether industrial metal copper suggested ongoing margin funding stress in China while statistical and sampling distortions explained a sizeable portion of the 47,300 seasonally adjusted increase in jobs.
The S&P-ASX 200 index rose 0.4 per cent before the jobs data and it surged to a 0.8 per cent gain before sliding to close up 28.4 points, or 0.53 per cent, at 5412.6 as the steady unemployment rate of 6 per cent signalled labour slack.
After the close of the ASX, Chinese stocks dipped following a rare miss of uncannily accurate economic forecasts, stoking slowdown concerns.
Chinese industrial production growth of 8.6 per cent missed the consensus forecast for 9.5 per cent, while retail sales slowed to 11.8 per cent against forecasts for a 13.5 per cent increase.
The Australian Bureau of Statistics warned that sample rotations accounted for about a third of the increase of jobs created in February, while the positive data was also undermined by a 0.9 per cent drop in total hours worked.
There needs to be consecutive months of strong job creation before we change our fairly bleak view of the labour market, Forex.com strategist Chris Tedder said. We see last month's data as an outlier as opposed to the start of a new trend of strong job creation.
The Australian dollar leapt US0.7¢ to US90.60¢ on the news, while government two-year yields rose 7.2 per cent to 2.851 per cent as the data swung the rate yield outlook slightly back towards a tightening bias.
The Bank of New Zealand became the first central bank in the developed world to raise rates yesterday as it lifted overnight rates 25 points to 2.75 per cent.
The Shanghai composite index rose 0.8 per cent, led by banks as officials outlined plans to introduce a deposit insurance scheme.
Premier Li Keqiang also confirmed the 7.5 per cent growth target was flexible and admitted this year would be complicated as the country rebalanced growth and tackled dangers from shadow banking and pollution.
In Tokyo, the Nikkei index slipped 0.1 per cent.
Copper dropped 0.5 per cent to $US6470 a tonne.
Bloomberg reported that Chinese regulators were assessing the risk to banks from the falling price of iron ore and a weaker yuan used as collateral for company financing.
Given the recent spike in Chinese currency exchange rate volatility and the fact that most major port inventories have hit maximum storage capacity, we think it likely that this type of financing activity has started to taper off, UBS China economist Tao Wang said.
]]></text></news-item>