<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="80C1-4C92-9AB6-477D"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>British Columbia: Ministry of Jobs, Tourism and Skills Training Issues Solicitation for "Settlement and Integration Services in Metro Vancouver"</title><source>Canadian Government News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Ministry of Jobs, Tourism and Skills Training has issued requirement for "Settlement and Integration Services in Metro Vancouver"
Reference No.: 14-LMID-03
Solicitation Type: Request for Proposal
Description: Notice is hereby given by the Ministry of Jobs, Tourism and Skills Training (the "Ministry") of its intent to contract with 20 community based agencies (agency list attached) to deliver settlement/integration services in Metro Vancouver (Horseshoe Bay to Langley). The purpose of these contracts is to continue to support clients who will not be eligible for such services due to the transitioning of program administration from British Columbia to Canada on April 1, 2014. Contracted services will target federally ineligible clients, i.e. temporary foreign workers living/working in Metro Vancouver, provincial nominees who are still awaiting a letter of approval for permanent residency from the federal government and immigrants who have become naturalized citizens.
These contracts will allow federally-funded community agencies to enhance their program for the continuation of the following activities/services for the above-mentioned federally ineligible clients: - Information, referral and action planning that meet and support the settlement, employment and integration needs of the target clients; - Supporting clients' access to government, community and employment networks and services/programs; - Educating and supporting clients with respect to their rights and responsibilities as residents, workers and citizens of B.C.; - Providing time-limited group support for clients, if applicable (programming will aim to provide cultural/language support to overcome isolation or enhance community integration); - Training and coordination of volunteers/mentors to provide further support if needed; - Collecting information on the specific needs of the target client groups and best practices to address those needs.
The term of the contracts will be twelve months, from April 1, 2014 to March 31, 2015, with two one-year options to renew subject to Ministry funding availability. The value of the contracts will range from $10,000 to $345,000 depending on the number of federally ineligible clients receiving settlement services administered by the Ministry prior to April 1, 2014.
The agencies on the list are deemed uniquely qualified for the reasons outlined below: - Pending successful negotiation, they are anticipated to deliver federal settlement services in 2014/15 under a Contribution Agreement with Citizenship and Immigration Canada; - Established processes and service delivery models are in place to continue the above noted services to clients; - They have the required background, depth of knowledge, skill and expertise to deliver the services; and, - They have strong connections to and work in partnership with local community partners.
Vendors wishing to object to this decision must contact David Groden at David.Groden@gov.bc.ca on or before 2:00 p.m. (PST) on March 25, 2014 presenting in writing, specific reasons for their objection, including detailed information on how their services, meet or exceed the direct award reasons as stated above. Vendors providing an objection must provide information to support relevant experience and ability to provide the described services for the same or better price. This information will be key in considering the validity of an objection.
Where objections are not received on or before the deadline stated above, or where objections made are not substantiated, the Ministry will continue to undertake direct award as outlined within this NOI.
Agency List:
1. Collingwood Neighborhood House 2. DIVERSEcity 3. Fédération des francophones de la Colombie-Britannique 4. Frog Hollow Neighbourhood House 5. Immigrant Services Society of B.C. 6. Jewish Family Service Agency 7. Langley Community Services Society 8. Little Mountain Neighbourhood House 9. MOSAIC 10. Mount Pleasant Neighborhood House 11. Multicultural Helping House 12. North Shore Multicultural Society 13. Options Community Service Society 14. Progressive Intercultural Community Services 15. REACH Center Association 16. Richmond Multicultural Community Services 17. S.U.C.C.E.S.S. 18. South Vancouver Neighborhood House 19. YMCA of Greater Vancouver 20. Vancouver Public Library
Deadline for All responses: 2014/03/25 14:00
Contact Information:
Groden, David Performance Manager Ministry of Jobs, Tourism and Skills Training Immigrant Integration & Multiculturalism 5th floor, 605 Robson St. Vancouver, British Columbia V6B 5J3 Phone: Fax: Email: David.Groden@gov.bc.ca
For more information visit: http://www.bcbid.gov.bc.ca/. In case of any query regarding this article or other content needs please contact: editorial@plusmediasolutions.com
]]></text></news-item>