<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="811A-72F2-FDB5-1C96"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Letters</title><source>Lewiston Morning Tribune (Idaho)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Cowboy up, Butch
On Feb 28, Gov. C.L. (Butch) Otter signed this bill that would prohibit animal activists from taking pictures of animal abuse on dairy farming.
In the Legislature, Democrats opposed the bill on grounds that it makes Idaho's agriculture industry seem like it's hiding something.
Mercy For Animals immediately decried Otter's signature Friday, saying that it transforms Idaho into "a safe haven for animal abuse."
"Gov. Otter has failed Idaho and the American people," said the group's executive director, Nathan Runkle. "By signing this bill into law, he has sided with those who seek to keep Idaho's corrupt factory farming practices hidden from public view and created a safe haven for animal abuse and other criminal activity in the state."
The measure passed Idaho's Senate earlier in February to the applause of agricultural representatives who said it would help ensure farmers' right to privacy. But animal rights groups say the measure will have a chilling effect on investigations that attempt to expose wrongdoing on Idaho's farms.
This prehistoric thinking on the part of Otter and his cronies reminds me of the time that Otter drunk drove down a one-way street in Boise going the wrong way. He was in a fog then and has remained in that fog to this day. Come on, Butch, cowboy up to 21st-century thinking. Enough of that vigilante justice.
Margot Mackey
Lewiston
Buy the land
I have a few comments to make about the land swap involving the checkerboard-square privately owned land of the upper Lochsa near Powell.
... I don't want you to get me mixed up with that guy in Moscow whose name is ah, gee whiz, I forgot. I think his initials are G.H. or B.G. or B.S. or something like that. But I do know that he must live in a house with absolutely no wood (because he is desperately against cutting down even one tree or twig), and he certainly doesn't have a lawn, because the dirt might contain the infamous giant earthworm of the Palouse (and thousands of other areas).
Finally, he absolutely loves wolves (although I don't think he sleeps with one? But wolves are such gentle and affectionate little doggies).
Now, as to my comments on the land swap. Many, many U.S. Forest Service personnel are working around the clock making hundreds of thousands of dollars every year. Some of these people work exclusively on this problem.
I would think the Forest Service could easily purchase this land with the millions of dollars spent of researching all of the hundreds of options.
Now, back to that guy in Moscow. If he and his many cohorts would buy some of the land mentioned above and live in wood-free houses with no lawns ... and have wolves as their (wonderful frolicking pets), the Forest Service might just act with a little more intelligence and action and just buy it.
Alan M. Syron
Kooskia
]]></text></news-item>