<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8203-64FB-F48C-DD59"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Horns of a Dilemma</title><source>ABC Transcripts (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[PIP COURTNEY, PRESENTER: But first today, a story on something the beef industry can be reluctant to talk about, but knows it must deal with. Dehorning calves is carried out by cattle producers in order to prevent stock harming themselves and their handlers. It's a confronting and bloody procedure and many in the industry believe it's a matter of time before it becomes an animal welfare flashpoint. That's why the industry has been trying to find a painless genetic solution and it now says it's made a breakthrough. And a warning, this report contains scenes of dehorning.
In the wild, horns served a purpose - protecting cattle from prey animals and each other. They served a purpose when cattle were used as beasts of burden too, for they prevented them from slipping out of the yoke. But in modern agriculture, horns are expensive and dangerous.
SCOTT HANSEN, FMR MLA CEO: Bumping into each other not only in transport, but in yards on properties and in yards at processing works was creating a real loss of value because that meat had to be devalued and the hides had to be devalued.
PIP COURTNEY: Horns are a danger in the workplace too.
BURNETT JOYCE, 'GYRANDA' QLD: Cattle with horns are aggressive because they have the artillery to be aggressive, even to one another.
JIM ROTHWELL, MLA: They certainly are more dangerous, they are more difficult to manage, they certainly can hurt farmers and operators and there's an unquestioned occupational health and safety issue around horns, and many of us have seen animals bullying each other, there's no doubt that horny animals are more likely to bully non-horny animals. It's bad for social interaction. The food lots don't want to take animals with horns.
TIM LEE: For decades, industry has dealt with the problem by dehorning. Laws differ state by state, but it's accepted the practice should be done before an animal turns one, preferably under six months of age.
JIM ROTHWELL: The aim is to remove the growth area, the horn bud, if you like, from the skull of the animal, so it's surgically excised.
Look, it is a painful operation, there's no question that if it's done in young animals, particularly as in the dairy industry, for example, or in more intensively managed beef herds when the animal is young and the horn bud is small, it's less painful. The problems, I think, arise as the horn grows into the skull and connects to the skull - then the dehorning operation becomes more painful.
PIP COURTNEY: If, say, for producers, you mentioned more intensively managed they can do them young, but up in the north, with the vast distances and they might only be mustering once or twice a year, is that where you get into trouble with the whole issue of pain and maybe leaving them too late?
JIM ROTHWELL: Yes, that is, in a nutshell, Pip, that is the issue. When they muster them once or twice a year, inevitably some of those animals are going to be more than six to eight months of age, so inevitably some of those calves, the horn bud will have grown into the skull. So inevitably when you dehorn them, you will be cutting a piece of the skull out.
PIP COURTNEY: Jim Rothwell from Meat and Livestock Australia, or MLA, says it's hard to gauge how much pain calves experience. Cattle are a prey animal so they're good at hiding pain and the desire to mother up and to drink is strong.
JIM ROTHWELL: I think that demonstrates that the pain is modest, particularly in those younger animals, that they do go back and join their mother and have a suck, and the mother probably comforts the calf, you know, in that maternal way.
MELINA TENSEN, SCIENTIFIC OFFICER RSPCA: Dehorning is extremely painful and distressing. We're talking about a fairly large wound, particularly the older the animal, the bigger the horn, and the bigger the wound, of course. There's potential for heavy blood loss, for infection and even death. From an RSPCA perspective, we'd certainly like to see that done by trained and competent operators and yes, preferably with the use of pain relief. But the unfortunate thing in this industry is that easily applicable and cost-effective pain relief simply isn't available for farmers at the moment.
PIP COURTNEY: While there's a cost to leaving horns on, there's also a cost to removing them. The side effects include a two per cent mortality rate and a $47 a head drop in value due to weight loss.
Those small numbers, when you add them all up, are they important for producers?
SCOTT HANSEN: They certainly are. They're accumulating costs, so they occur every time, every year.
MELINA TENSEN: There's also a longer chronic pain response which is indicated by reduced weight gain over a period of up to six weeks, so that's indicative of chronic pain. So there's definitely science to support the fact that it is a painful procedure that the animal would definitely feel.
PIP COURTNEY: Trials of the analgesic Trissulfin began several years ago. Well-known cattleman the late Zander McDonald was involved and if approved for use he'd planned to introduce it to the family's 180,000-head beef operation in far North Queensland. With plans to market the beef as ethically raised, he told ABC Radio it was time the northern cattle industry pushed its welfare credentials.
(Zander McDonald on ABC Radio - 2012)
ZANDER MCDONALD, BEEF PRODUCER: We think it probably takes anywhere from 20 to 40 minutes before the anaesthetic starts to work, but we're quite confident that it's then good for about 18 hours afterwards which is the work we did last year. So we're very pleased how it's working. We think it's the only practical way of administering an anaesthetic in a timely and cost-effective manner for the volume of animals that we process in a single day.
PIP COURTNEY: While approved for use in the sheep industry for mulesing, Mr McDonald was frustrated Trisulfin was several years and several million dollars away from being approved for the beef industry.
While supporting industry investment into pain relief options, the RSPCA says the best long-term solution to dehorning is to phase it out.
MELINA TENSEN: I think it's our obligation to make sure that we're taking up that opportunity and relieving the pain and distress on those calves - and we're literally talking hundreds of thousands of calves each year.
PIP COURTNEY: The Joyce family run 4,000 head of Santa Gertrudis at Gyranda in central Queensland. Burnett Joyce and his son-in-law Peter Mahoney are trying to breed horns out. They're making progress. Every year, fewer calves are born with horns, but they're not there yet.
Dehorning is done when calves are tagged, branded and castrated when they're between two and three months old.
PETE MAHONEY, 'GYRANDA' WLD: I've no doubt it hurts, Pip. I guess our job is to try and manage that and we do that in terms of trying to lower the stress of that animal. And surprisingly, when the animal goes out of that crush they're back with their mother, they settle down very quickly and they're back, and as soon as they go into the paddock, they seem to be eating and comfortable. I've no doubt it hurts, but I don't think it hurts for a long period of time.
PIP COURTNEY: While he'd prefer not to do it, Burnett Joyce prides himself on being skilled at the job. He even designed his own knife so he can do it quickly, accurately and humanely.
BURNETT JOYCE, 'GYRANDA' QLD: It's extremely important you get it right because a bad dehorning job is worse than no dehorning job. You've got to know how to restrain the calf and how to apply the pressure because we're working with a razor-sharp implement all the time, so that if you make a mistake, that mistake can be fairly devastating.
PIP COURTNEY: Is it a traumatic process?
BURNETT JOYCE: No, Pip, it's not. It might look bad because there's some cut and blood but it's not traumatic. And if you take note of the calves that we operate on, they'll bellow, they might bellow coming up the crush, they might bellow when we put them in the calf race and drop them on the ground, but they don't react to any of the operations we do on them. It's only a few seconds.
PIP COURTNEY: In recent years, Burnett Joyce has grown troubled by dehorning. First, because staff who can do it right are getting hard to find, and second, because of the potential for animal rights groups to target the industry over it.
BURNETT JOYCE: We've always got to be mindful that there's people out there that don't like what we do and in some case to the extreme.
PIP COURTNEY: It's not just producers who realise dehornings time is up. On its website, the NSW Department of Primary Industries warns that greater awareness of animal welfare in recent years means past methods can no longer be accepted without question.
It says: "With the general community becoming increasingly concerned about animal welfare issues, dehorning is seen by many people as being cruel and offensive."
Still bruised from the live cattle furore two years ago, former MLA boss Scott Hansen acknowledges dehornings potential to throw the industry into another animal welfare controversy.
SCOTT HANSEN: There's a range of animal husbandry practices that, with a growing disconnect between city and rural lifestyles, would be hard to explain and hard to show.
They're always done with animal welfare at their centre cause as to why they're done, but it's certainly the industry's been proactive in investing and trying to find innovative ways, new ways and, in this case, genetic tools, that will allow them to continue to deliver the economic and welfare benefits, but in a way that increases that welfare benefit to the livestock.
PIP COURTNEY: And that's where the scientists come in. MLA believes the solution to the dehorning problem lies with DNA testing allowing producers to breed horns out.
Since 2005, MLA has invested several hundred thousand dollars on research into the DNA of polled cattle, or those born without horns.
EMILY PIPER, CSIRO: In British and European-derived breeds, Angus for example, are all polled, Hereford, there's a pretty even mix of horned and polled in the breed. But in the tropical breeds in northern Australia, such as Brahman, have very few polled animals.
PIP COURTNEY: Emily Piper is an animal geneticist at the University of Queensland. She's part of a team searching for the elusive polled gene.
EMILY PIPER: There's been researchers all over the world hunting for the actual gene that causes horned or polled and we still don't know exactly what that is. There's one major gene that controls horned and polled in cattle. We know approximately where it is and we inherit one form of the gene from our mum and the other from our dad. So we're basically looking for different forms of the gene in different animals and we can identify whether an animal's going to produce mainly polled progeny or a mixture of horned and polled progeny.
[Speaking to another scientist] About 140 - just over a plate's worth, yeah.
PIP COURTNEY: Scientists thought finding the gene would be easy, but they were caught by surprise.
JOHN HENSHELL, CSIRO: 20 years ago when molecular genetics was just starting, people thought we should be able to get this one because people knew all about polled long before that. But it's turned out to be much, much more complicated and it's only now that we're starting to see the results from some of the international research groups that suggests that we are getting very close to the cause.
PIP COURTNEY: Despite these challenges, in 2010 the Australian team released a polled gene DNA marker test - the first test applicable to Brahmans.
Up until then Burnett Joyce was using traditional methods to breed out horns. He selected polled bulls with other desirable traits and hoped they'd pass on the polled gene, but it was an educated guess. The test meant after paying $25 for tail hairs from each polled bull to be analysed, he'd be 99 per cent sure if that bull would throw progeny without horns.
BURNETT JOYCE: We did some cooperative work with the beef CRC to do some validation work on the test and from that we got some more information that gave us a bit more confidence in using it, but we still knew from the calf crop we were getting that it really wasn't the answer.
PIP COURTNEY: When problems emerged with the accuracy of the test with the Brangus and Limousin breeds, Emily Piper and John Henshall went back to the lab. In just two years, they devised a new test with ten gene markers, not one, and it's just been released.
EMILY PIPER: The new test can be used across a much wider range of breeds and with a higher degree of accuracy across those breeds.
PIP COURTNEY: Scott Hansen says the test will put more money in producers' pockets and should take dehorning as a target for animal rights groups off the table.
SCOTT HANSEN: Your investment in polled genes is a one-off investment that then flows through to future generations for your herd. So economically, it makes a lot of viable sense.
PIP COURTNEY: Without this genetic tool, how long could it have taken producers to move to polled herds?
SCOTT HANSEN: Well, one of the other options for a producer other than dehorning was obviously selective genetic tools. So being able to selectively choose the genetics in the herd to try to breed a polled herd. Now typically that will take you about 39 years. This test reduces that down to an 8-year cycle.
PIP COURTNEY: The results of choosing bulls based on DNA testing are already apparent at Gyranda, with more than 70 per cent of calves born last year being polled.
Do you like it now when marking's on and you can look at one and go, 'I don't have to do anything there. I can keep my knife in my pocket'?
BURNETT JOYCE: It's great leaning against the post and watching the people work at the other end and have no dehorning to do.
PIP COURTNEY: With more clients wanting polled Santa bulls, the Joyce family believes it will be well positioned to take advantage of growing demand for polled genetics.
PETE MAHONEY: There's definitely been a trend towards polled cattle. I think part of that is economic and part of it is fear. Agriculture has been knocked from pillar to post over the last decade or so from these extremist groups and farmers are scared, you know. We don't know which end it's coming from and so there's definitely been a driver there towards those polled cattle.
PIP COURTNEY: The RSPCA is pleased to see the industry is changing voluntarily.
MELINA TENSEN: It's absolutely fabulous that farmers now have this option that they can use to basically eliminate the need for dehorning on their properties, even though it will take some years. It's great to see an industry be progressive and look at ways of reducing or indeed eliminating procedures that are painful for animals.
PIP COURTNEY: MLA is excited about the potential impact of the new test, but is worried producers in the Brahman-dominated north will be reluctant to use it because of the widely-held belief polled cattle are inferior to those with horns.
JIM ROTHWELL: To link polled cattle with inferior cattle is simply wrong. However, it's important - and I'm sure the breeders are doing this - they need to provide superior bulls that carry the poll condition. So it's just a question of breeding those superior bulls that carry the poll condition. It's not that they're intrinsically inferior in any way. That would be like saying Angus are inferior because they don't have horns, that's crazy.
PIP COURTNEY: Jim Rothwell says the reason polledness has a bad rep in the north is based on numbers, not genes.
Because there haven't been many top quality polled bulls to choose from, producers who did try to breed horns out used sires with some undesirable characteristics. As a result, polledness became associated with fertility and production problems - something Burnett Joyce saw firsthand when his father first tried polled bulls. The results weren't good.
BURNETT JOYCE: There's always a danger, if you chase a trait and don't monitor where the other ones are going. That's, I guess, the catchphrase is single trait selection - make extreme progress on that one trait, but you forsake a lot of the other things that you spent a lifetime developing and most of those things you spent a lifetime developing are the things that make you money.
PIP COURTNEY: Burnett Joyce says he'll only use polled bulls that tick all the production boxes, like temperament, size, growth rate and fertility, and in time he's confident more top-quality polled bulls will be available. I think some of us need to be out there setting the pace, trying to lead the industry and trying to educate our clients to take up that technology and hopefully produce a better product.
]]></text></news-item>