<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8216-458E-0A24-136C"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Sanctions on horizon as Crimea votes to join Russia; The referendum result / Separation victory hailed by Moscow, swiftly rejected by West The diplomatic reaction / Harper rejects 'illegitimate' vote, EU to meet Monday to discuss next steps</title><source>The Globe and Mail (Canada)</source><author>PAUL WALDIE, MARK MacKINNON and KATHRYN BLAZE CARLSON</author><text><![CDATA[Western nations are condemning the overwhelming vote by Crimeans to leave Ukraine as illegitimate and dangerous, setting the stage Monday for a fresh wave of sanctions against Russia, and deepening the worst crisis in East-West relations since the Cold War's end.
Preliminary results showed 96 per cent of Crimeans voted in favour of annexation, a decision hailed by Crimean leaders as historic but condemned by the United States and its European allies as "dangerous." The stage is now set for the U.S. and the European Union to introduce sanctions that are expected to include travel bans and asset freezes at first but could go further. Canada has said Russia could be kicked out of the G8.
"Russia's actions are dangerous and destabilizing," the White House said in a statement released hours after the polls closed in Crimea. The U.S. called on countries to "condemn such actions, to take concrete steps to impose costs."
In some of his strongest language yet, Prime Minister Stephen Harper said the results of Sunday's vote reflect nothing more than Moscow's military hold in Crimea. "This 'referendum' is illegitimate. It has no legal effect, and we do not recognize its outcome," Mr. Harper, who will travel to Ukraine this week, said in a statement Sunday evening.
"As a result of Russia's refusal to seek a path of de-escalation, we are working with our G7 partners and other allies to co-ordinate additional sanctions against those responsible.
"[Russian President Vladimir Putin's] reckless and unilateral actions will lead only to Russia's further economic and political isolation from the international community," Mr. Harper said.
The EU also called the referendum illegitimate and said foreign ministers will meet Monday in Brussels to consider what sanctions to impose. Earlier this month, the United States and Canada each imposed limited sanctions against individuals deemed to be responsible for the military intervention in Crimea.
Mr. Putin said Russia will recognize the result, arguing it is a valid expression of the will of Crimeans who reject the new government in Kiev for removing the elected president, Viktor Yanukovych, a pro-Russian. In a phone call with U.S. President Barack Obama on Sunday, Mr. Putin said the referendum was "completely in line with the norms of international law."
Just how far the U.S. and Europe will go with sanctions remains to be seen. Russia is expected to retaliate and it supplies roughly one-third of Europe's natural gas. It is also the world's largest exporter of a range of industrial metals such as titanium, which is used to build aircraft.
In Kiev, the mood was sombre Sunday and a handful of people gathered in the city's Independence Square in freezing rain to hear the results of the vote. Many worried about the future of Ukraine and expressed fears Russia would invade.
"I'm very concerned because I would really like to see peace and I don't want to see any more dead bodies," said Anastasia Radchenko, a doctor who is expecting her first child with her husband.
"We would never have even thought that this was possible," said Tamara Olexandriva, a great-grandmother, as she sat with a friend in a local shopping mall. "We're Ukrainians. We live here, I was born here and I'm very concerned."
Earlier on Sunday the Ukrainian government announced plans to dramatically increase military spending in response to the referendum, and it vowed to track down those responsible for leading separatist movements in the country. "We will find all of them - if it takes one year, two years - and bring them to justice and try them in Ukrainian and international courts," Prime Minister Arseniy Yatsenyuk told an emergency meeting of his cabinet. "The ground will burn beneath their feet."
Despite the tough talk there appears to be little the Ukrainian government can do about Crimea, particularly with more than 20,000 Russian troops in the territory. Thousands of Ukrainian soldiers remain trapped on their bases in Crimea, surrounded by troops from Russia and the territory's new self-defence force. For now, the Ukrainian government has said it will not evacuate its soldiers. Other parts of the country are also agitating to join the move to separate. Tensions flared all weekend in several cities in Eastern Ukraine as pro-Russian and pro-Ukrainian demonstrators clashed. There are fears in Ukraine that Russia will seize on the unrest and move into these regions, which, like Crimea, have a sizable population of ethnic Russians. Political analyst Sergei Markov, who is a long-time adviser to Mr. Putin, said that is a likely scenario.
Mr. Markov said the U.S. has a short time to find a suitable "coalition, democratic government" to replace what he called the "junta" government in Kiev. "If this doesn't happen, Russia will probably move to protect the Russian-speaking coalition in Donetsk, Lugansk, Odessa, Dnipropetrovsk, Mykolaev and Kherson," he said referring to several cities in Eastern Ukraine. "There is no sovereign Ukraine. It doesn't exist. We have a junta in Kiev that was appointed by Washington."
Crimea's recently appointed Prime Minister, Sergei Aksyonov, said the government would apply to join Russia on Monday. Plans are also being prepared to replace the Ukrainian currency with the Russian ruble within days. The Russian parliament is expected to consider Crimea's request on March 21.
]]></text></news-item>