<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8239-83BE-2BC4-658A"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Pats ink Edelman, Browner in busy offseason</title><source>The Sun Chronicle (Attleboro, Massachusetts)</source><author>Staff Writer</author><text><![CDATA[Ponderous thoughts I was pondering while making the transition away from basketball, which is harder than you think:
- It certainly has been an interesting period for free agency where the New England Patriots are concerned, as things progressed from being an unmitigated disaster earlier in the week to a far more acceptable performance by the time they reached Saturday's announcement that former Seattle cornerback Brandon Browner had been signed.
Here's how Browner expressed his thoughts, as written on Twitter: "I am honored that the Patriots are making me part of their legendary organization, and am grateful for the opportunity Mr. Kraft, Coach Belichick, Nick Caserio and the entire team have given me. I intend to diligently work with the same passion and dedication that I have displayed since coming into the NFL to uphold the great traditions and qualities that are embodied by the Patriots."
OK, I know that's more than 140 characters. I guess there are ways of getting around that, and I really don't need to know the explanation.
In any event, the Patriots clearly responded in a big way to how badly their pass defense was exposed in last year's AFC Championship Game by signing Browner and Darrelle Revis, who could potentially give the Patriots the best cornerback tandem they've ever had. It also gives Logan Ryan more time to blossom at the nickel corner and it serves notice to Alfonzo Dennard to shape up and fly right.
Those positives may have been offset by a significant negative, however.
The Vince Wilfork situation is regrettable in that it will probably force him to finish his career elsewhere, and his recovery from Achilles' tendon surgery is not going to enhance his marketability.
I can understand Wilfork's pique to some extent, in that he was forced to labor for a long time under market value by the six-year rookie contract he signed - one of the reasons why rookie contracts of that length are no longer permitted - but it's not as if any of this should come as a surprise. He's been a Patriot long enough to know how they do business.
So, the Patriots will likely enter the season without Wilfork and without a suitable replacement. My feeling is that it will probably spur a change in defensive philosophy, putting less emphasis on run-stopping and gearing toward a pass-rushing front with fleeter feet. But that's one area that has not yet been addressed in free agency.
Another area of concern was at least kept at the status quo when Julian Edelman and the Patriots reached agreement on a new contract (terms not yet available) Saturday afternoon. Edelman had visited San Francisco earlier in the week, but I suspect that just as I was skeptical of his ability to reproduce his outstanding numbers of 2013, potential suitors probably were as well. Edelman is a classic case of a player whose value with his present team was not likely to be exceeded elsewhere.
Still, I don't think there's been enough of an effort to give an aging Tom Brady (amazing how frequently you hear that these days, huh?) adequate weapons in his receiving corps. It was sad to see the Jets snap up Denver's Eric Decker - not just because he might have been a good target for Brady, but also because he may never catch another pass with Geno Smith throwing at him. The Patriots supposedly had some interest in the ever-talkative Steve Smith, but he signed with Baltimore, so it's already looking as if Brady will again enter a season with substandard receivers that he's supposed to turn into All-Pros.
Hey, maybe the Patriots will buck the trends and be the only team left in the league that runs the football. Worth a try, given that everyone else has gone hog-wild in shoring up their pass defense
- So President Obama appeared on a faux Internet talk show to promote his health care program. Big deal. Bill Clinton played the saxophone on a late-night TV talk show. Richard Nixon appeared on "Rowan and Martin's Laugh-In." And I'll bet there were critics that thought FDR was breaking down too many barriers when he did his "Fireside Chats" on radio.
The point is, even the Founding Fathers didn't want the presidency to become as aloof and separated from the people as the monarchy that preceded it. We elect men to these posts, not deities
- Seriously, how many more liquor licenses do the Krafts need for Patriot Place? Aren't there enough drunks coming out of those parking lots already? And soon enough, I'm going to have to avoid that whole U.S. 1-Interstate 495-Route 152 area in Plainville because of the slot machine crowd
- The hosts on the Sports Hub's afternoon drive show have certainly taken an anti-media stance lately. When the Red Sox media is discussed, it's always accompanied by a portion of the song "Everything is Awesome" that's on the Lego Movie soundtrack (or so they tell me) - the premise being that everyone covering the Sox is on board with the company line. As for the Patriots' media corps, we're supposedly a "cartel," all in the back pockets of Robert and Jonathan Kraft.
The sad part is that Michael Felger and Tony Massarotti were once beat writers themselves, individuals that did the jobs they now so easily criticize, and may have once rankled over similar accusations sent their way. It's so easy to sit back and criticize when you're no longer doing the job
- I enjoyed watching some of our area's best basketball players in action for the last time this year Thursday night at the all-star games at Mansfield High that were sponsored by the website HockomockSports.com - and from the look of things, plenty of you did as well. The Albertini Gym was filled to see the boys' and girls' teams do battle, as well as a three-point shooting contest between those games.
The Hockomock League sponsored and staged such all-star games many years ago, and while some leagues have continued the practice (the Mayflower League, for one), it fell by the wayside locally. Kudos, therefore, go to the guys at HockomockSports.com for reviving the practice - and doing it for a worthwhile cause, the fight against ALS (Lou Gehrig's disease). The event was well-organized and lots of fun for spectators and participants alike.
Among my favorite memories from the night? The times when North Attleboro teammates Melissa Beaupre and Danielle Perron, opponents in the all-star games, had to play defense against each other. Big smiles and not a lot of defense
- Speaking of all-stars, many thanks go to the 28 athletes and four coaches that arrived with smiles on their faces Tuesday at our Attleboro office for the annual basketball all-star photo sessions. We'll be announcing them soon, so keep your eyes peeled for the two Sunday editions in which those teams will appear.
- Good to see that the Incredible Hulk is making its way back to the wall at the James Albertini Memorial Gymnasium. The mural will be on the wall opposite of where it used to be, so it will be the first thing you'll see when you enter Mansfield High's gym
- Anybody seen any of the area's baseball diamonds yet?
MARK FARINELLA may be reached at 508-236-0315 or via email at mfarinel@thesunchronicle.com Read Farinella 's blog, "Blogging Fearlessly," at thesunchronicle.com/blogs/markfarinella.
]]></text></news-item>