<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8280-B367-A0A3-B3E8"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Truth is hidden</title><source>Herald Sun (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[WHY couldn't the jury hear about Brett Peter Cowan's criminal history in the Daniel Morcombe trial ("Justice for Daniel", HS, Mar 14)?
Juries should know about a defendant's past criminal behaviour if it has relevance to the case and establishes a pattern of behaviour.
Regardless of what jurors know, they still have to establish guilt beyond reasonable doubt.
The jury found him guilty without this information, so suppressing his criminal history didn't help Cowan.
W. De Lacy, Ringwood East
Why protect them?
DANIEL Morcombe's killer is a serial offender, yet we only now find out. We are hamstrung by the insane legal requirement that protects such animals. In court we must never tell the truth about the accused. Their defence can destroy the character of any witness, but "don't reveal bad things about my client, it may prejudice the jury". Well, so it should. It should tell them this person is capable of such a crime.
This must be changed so people like Brett Peter Cowan do not get off because juries don't think them capable of a crime.
Paul Pearce, Croydon
Pursuit of justice BRUCE and Denise Morcombe are amazing, inspirational people. I will forever feel sad for you, but I am so pleased you pursued justice for your beautiful son. I hope this verdict brings you some sense of relief.
Melanie Treherne, Point Cook
Failings mounting VICTORIA'S child protection system is so underfunded that kids as young as eight are being groomed by paedophile groups ("Fiends prey on children in care", HS, Mar 12).
Has anyone kept count of how many government departments are able to meet their commitments? It shouldn't be too difficult because they are so few.
Ron Fischer, Horsham
What are their rights?
IN 2009, the Herald Sun reported that the Department of Human Services placed abused and neglected children in caravan parks and cheap motels for lack of appropriate accommodation. The then Opposition spokeswoman, Mary Wooldridge, slammed Labor for this.
Since the Liberals took office in 2010, at least 4000 destitute children have been evicted from public housing. What of the human rights of these children? Where is the adults' duty of care, and accountability?
Gagging of state employees prevents disclosure of the full picture. An open inquiry and an internationally proven model of state care should be an immediate priority.
Barbara Chapman, Hawthorn
Talent undermined AN old schoolfriend of mine got an impressive graduate engineering job with a big mining company recently.
On Thursday she "liked" Adam Bandt's article ("Liberals are lacking a long-term view", heraldsun.com.au) on Facebook. When I asked her if there was any contradiction between her new job and the views Bandt expresses, she pointed out that she's a chemical engineer with a Melbourne University education, and if there were jobs in renewable energy she'd be at the forefront.
This woman is brilliant and her work could make a difference. Instead, she feels if she doesn't take a job in mining, she'll be on the dole.
We are not making the most of this country's resources.
Jessica O'Riley, Fitzroy North
Speedy resolution DR Bruce Corben (YS, Mar 11) explains the science of low-level speeding, yet does not acknowledge legal or design issues in the debate.
The push to penalise drivers who are 2-3km over fails to recognise the Australian Design Rules for vehicles, which allow a 10 per cent deviation on speedometers. A long list of variables also affect speed.Ray Hutchinson, Doreen
]]></text></news-item>