<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8286-A0B3-4496-3FE6"><date>2014-03-10</date><title>Call for inquiry on remote housing</title><source>The Australian</source><author>PATRICIA KARVELAS</author><text><![CDATA[Indigenous bodies are pressing the government to consult traditional owners
TWO of the most powerful indigenous bodies in the country have urged the Abbott government to consult traditional owners before embarking on moves to radically transform Aboriginal housing, with one calling for an inquiry before far-reaching changes are implemented.
The nationally elected indigenous representative body the National Congress of Australia's First Peoples has criticised moves revealed by The Weekend Australian that would transform Aboriginal land rights.
Congress co-chairs Les Malezer and Kirstie Parker told The Australian that congress would not support government policies developed in ``isolation from our peoples and communities''.
The chief executive of the powerful Northern Land Council, Joe Morrison, said while all options must be on the table, communities should not be disadvantaged where traditional owners did not want to sign on to 99-year leases.
The Abbott government is proposing the most radical and far-reaching changes to Aboriginal housing.
They include a plan to move indigenous people who send their children to school forward in waiting lists.
The changes would also enable Aboriginal people who get jobs away from remote communities to transfer their social housing and home ownership entitlements.
Indigenous Affairs Minister Nigel Scullion signalled that preference for new public housing would be given to areas where land tenure provided for home ownership, such as 99-year leases or freehold title.
Congress yesterday called on the federal government to establish a meaningful process, such as an inquiry or commission, ``that will allow our organisations and communities to publicly comment on any proposal to link land leasing in exchange for access to critical housing needs''.
``In the meantime, congress will engage with our members to seek advice on how to best work on this issue in partnership with the government,'' it said.
``Our peoples have a right to exercise free, prior and informed consent to any measures impacting on their daily lives.
``In fact, the success of any program or policy depends upon it,'' congress said.
``Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander peoples are entitled to both safe and affordable housing as well as education, employment, and support to maintain their connection to traditional lands.
``Closing the Gap requires a sustained and systemic approach.
``We cannot be trading one right off against others,'' congress said.
Mr Morrison said he looked forward to discussing home ownership options in Aboriginal communities with Senator Scullion and Indigenous Advisory Council chairman Warren Mundine.
``My view is everything must be on the table for consideration to improve housing and employment, as well as a suite of other connected social issues in Aboriginal communities,'' he said.
``There are a range of models to ensure home ownership but there is no silver bullet and no one answer, and it would be wrong to preference new public housing only for communities with a Section 19A township lease, as seems to have been indicated in recent media reports.''
]]></text></news-item>