<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="82F8-624E-9EED-B9C0"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Court threat hangs over firm after leak</title><source>Aberdeen Press and Journal</source><author>Morag Lindsay</author><text><![CDATA[Oil giant Total could face criminal charges over its Elgin Platform gas leak.
All 238 workers were evacuated from the platform, about 150 miles off Aberdeen, during a 51-day emergency in March 2012.
The French firm lost tens of millions of pounds as a result - and last night it emerged the incident could now land it in court.
The leak has been under investigation by the Health and Safety Executive and the UK Government's Department of Energy and Climate Change (DECC).
Last night, the HSE confirmed it had submitted its investigation to the Crown Office, which will decide whether the firm should face criminal proceedings.
"We can confirm the HSE-DECC investigation reports into aspects of the well operations leading up to the blowout have been presented to the Crown Office and Procurator Fiscal Service," an HSE spokesman said.
"They will now consider our recommendations and decide what action is to be taken."
The leak was stopped in May 2012 in an operation which pumped heavy mud and cement into the underwater well. At the height of the incident, about 200,000 cubic metres of gas was escaping every day, but the level reduced when workers drilled a relief well.
The leak caused Total to miss out on about £83million of potential income, according to its financial results for the second quarter of 2012.
It took a year for production to resume, and the shutdown was partly blamed for the UK's double-dip recession that year.
It has since been reported that the company could face a £1.4billion bill to repair wells in the Elgin-Franklin field.
Total did not respond to the Press and Journal's request for a comment yesterday.
The Crown is also currently considering whether Shell should face criminal charges over its Gannet Alpha oil spill.
More than 200 tonnes of light crude spewed into the North Sea in August 2011 from a leak in a pipeline serving the Gannet Alpha, 112 miles east of Aberdeen.
Shell was accused of playing-down the incident after it estimated 120 barrels had been spilled. The company later revised the figure to 1,300 barrels, making it the worst North Sea spill in more than a decade.
]]></text></news-item>