<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8373-7B87-C99B-DA23"><date>2014-03-14</date><title></title><source>The Tampa Tribune (Florida)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Dow Jones industrial average fell more than 200 points Thursday, its biggest decline in six weeks.
The pullback came as investors reacted to discouraging economic reports from China and intensifying tensions in Ukraine. The Dow slid 231.19 points, or 1.4 percent, to 16,108.89. The S&P 500 index fell 21.86 points, or 1.2 percent, to close at 1,846.34. The Nasdaq composite dropped 62.91 points, or 1.5 percent, to 4,260.42. It was the worst day for the market in six weeks and the fourth loss in a row for the Dow. The plunge was a sharp contrast to the relatively quiet trading earlier in the week following a record-setting run last week. Thursday's slide erased the S&P 500 index's gains for the year and extended the Dow's year-to-date loss to 2.8 percent. The Nasdaq is still up 2 percent so far this year.
째The International Monetary Fund warned Thursday that wide income inequality can slow economic growth and is proposing ways to reduce it. Its recommendations include raising property taxes, taxing the rich more than others and raising the eligibility age for government retirement programs. The proposals are the latest sign of the IMF's growing concern about income inequality and are an unusual focus for a global lending organization best-known for providing loans paired with strict budget cuts. IMF officials say it is up to individual countries to decide whether and how to try to reduce income disparities.
째U.S. retail sales bounced back in February after suffering a steep decline during a bitterly cold January.
The Commerce Department said Thursday that seasonally adjusted retail sales rose 0.3 percent in February. Spending had fallen 0.6 percent in January, revised down from the 0.4 percent decline initially reported.
째The oil company behind the largest offshore oil spill in U.S. history can once again perform work for the federal government. Under an agreement announced Thursday, more than two dozen BP entities and its Houston-based oil production and exploration arm can secure new government contracts. The company had been suspended from performing any new government work since November 2012. That's when BP agreed to plead guilty to criminal charges involving the deaths of 11 workers and lying to Congress about how much oil was spilling into the Gulf of Mexico.
째The number of people seeking U.S. unemployment benefits dropped 9,000 last week to a seasonally adjusted 315,000, its lowest level in three months. It was the second straight decline, and it added to evidence that the job market is picking up after a winter slump. The Labor Department said Thursday that the four-week average of applications, a less volatile figure, fell 6,250 to 330,500, the lowest point since early December.
From wire reports
]]></text></news-item>