<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="83BF-0277-E7AF-7D09"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Lawyer files legal claim to be hired</title><source>The Daily Journal (Vineland, New Jersey)</source><author>By, Joseph P. Smith</author><text><![CDATA[VINELAND - An attorney the City Council wants to use to investigate allegations of misconduct by Business Administrator William E. Lutz is asking a state court to support the council's right to hire him.
The council on Feb. 4 voted to hire Hammonton attorney Robert J. Pinizzotto for $10,000 and a 90-day completion timetable, only to have Mayor Ruben Bermudez block it a few days later.
Pinizzotto said on Thursday his legal complaint, which was filed on Tuesday, is based on the provisions of the state's Faulkner Act. The city's form of government, including divisions of authority, is laid out in that law.
"The first thing is that council under the law does not need mayoral approval to hire their own employees and, in the event that they do need it, require the mayor to approve it," Pinizzotto said.
The court is being asked to recognize that claim and then to order the municipal government, specifically Chief Financial Officer Roxanne Tosto, to clear the funds for release.
Bermudez has ordered Tosto not to certify the availability of funds to pay Pinizzotto. The certification is a technical but required action.
Tosto is part of the municipal administration, which makes her answerable first to the mayor.
Pinizzotto's firm filed multiple documents on Tuesday with Cumberland County Superior Court's Chancery Division, including what is known as an "order to show cause" and a "complaint in lieu of prerogative writ."
On the same day, the firm served the mayor and the chief financial officer papers notifying them of the legal action. The mayor did not have a comment on Thursday.
The order to show cause asks the court to issue two primary findings: That the council is authorized to execute a contract with Pinizzotto; and that Bermudez will "direct any and all employees" to do what is needed to execute the contract.
"As a result of Mayor Bermudez's actions irreparable harm will occur to the City of Vineland and its citizens and taxpayers," Pinizzotto's complaint states. "If Council is not able to continue its investigation within its legal authority, the city may be harmed if the Business Administrator continues to conduct business on behalf of the City, even though he may not be qualified."
The complaint will be heard in Gloucester County Superior Court due to a conflict of interest that prevents it from being heard in Cumberland. A date for a hearing remains to be scheduled.
Council intends to examine whether Lutz, who retains the mayor's support, told City Councilwoman Angela Calakos of an attempt to bribe him last fall. The point of the alleged bribe would have been to help stop a proposed city takeover of the Landis Sewerage Authority.
At the same meeting on Feb. 4, the council rejected a request by Bermudez for money to hire a different attorney to investigate Lutz but under the control of the mayor's office.
On Feb. 6, Bermudez sent a letter to Pinizzotto advising him that his hiring was illegal. Council and Pinizzotto rejected that claim but did not have an immediate answer on how to respond.
According to the new filing, the council on Feb. 19 asked Pinizzotto to proceed with an investigation of Lutz.
INSIDE
Court date not set yet in mayor's lawsuit. Page A2
]]></text></news-item>