<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8401-600D-DF86-5AC5"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Emails Link Duke Energy and State</title><source>The New York Times</source><author>By MICHAEL WINES</author><text><![CDATA[Environmental regulators in North Carolina consulted Duke Energy last year before seeking to exclude citizen activists from talks to settle charges that the utility's coal ash ponds had polluted the state's groundwater, newly released email exchanges among the regulators indicated on Thursday.
Duke officials and the state later settled the charges by proposing a fine and a requirement that Duke study the potential for further pollution before offering solutions. That agreement collapsed in February after one of the utility's coal ash ponds spilled tens of thousands of tons of toxic slurry into the Dan River.
Federal prosecutors have since opened a criminal investigation into the spill and the relationship between Duke and the state's environmental bureaucracy. Critics charge that environmental regulation has been hobbled by political interference since Gov. Pat McCrory, a Republican, a former mayor of Charlotte and a Duke Energy employee for 29 years, took office last year.
The emails were obtained in legal proceedings by the Southern Environmental Law Center, which had announced in January 2013 that it planned to sue Duke over charges that its coal ash pollution violated the federal Clean Water Act. The act allows citizens to sue over pollution violations unless governments move to correct them -- and to go to court if a settlement is too weak.
Shortly after the announcement, the emails show, Duke officials contacted the State Department of Environment and Natural Resources, apparently seeking an agreement addressing the center's complaints. Lawyers for the Southern Environmental Law Center argued that they should be allowed to join those talks.
An April 30 email from a Duke Energy lawyer suggests, however, that state regulators were looking to block that. In that email, the Duke lawyer said the environment department's senior lawyer, Lacy Presnell, had ''asked during our meeting for an example of participation by a intervenor on a nonparty basis.'' The email offered an example -- an effort by utility interests to join a federal lawsuit against the state -- and in July, state lawyers asked the court, unsuccessfully, to exclude citizens groups.
Environmental groups contested the settlement, which fined Duke about $99,000, arguing that it saved the company from harsher fines that could have stemmed from a private lawsuit.
http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/14/us/emails-link-duke-energy-and-state.html
]]></text></news-item>