<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="840D-3396-75B3-7706"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>South Fly landowners support Morauta</title><source>PNG Post-Courier (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[LANDOWNER factions of the South Fly electorates have come out in support of Sir Mekere Morauta and his fight for the Western Province people's long term funds.
Pastor Steven Bagari, speaking on behalf of the non-CMCA landowners, said yesterday that as a church leader and strong community leader for more than 30 years in the Fly River affected area he totally supported Sir Mekere.
"I totally support the stand taken by Sir Mekere Morauta in protecting the Western Province people's long term funds in Singapore," he said.
"I know I am speaking for the majority of people in the South Fly and my conversations with other leaders of the North and Middle Fly suggest we all express the same sentiment.
Those funds do not belong to the State or the Fly River Provincial Government.
So the Government must be kept away from getting their hands on the money.
"There are already serious allegations of misappropriation and fraud against both men that the police are investigating.
What we in the Western Province fear is that if they get a hold of these funds, they will not reach the poor suffering people.
I am calling on all the people in the Western Province to stand and support Sir Mekere Morauta who has done an excellent job of protecting our funds.
"Prime Minister: Why are you continuing to operate the Ok Tedi mine as the owner and regulator without a proper mining lease, and dumping toxic waste into the river system when you have not paid us our compensation monies as promised by the State and OTML from 2001 to 2013?
"You have complete control of these funds and now you really want to kill us all in the Western Province by taking our long term fund?
"I am humbly praying to Governor Wobiro and Prime Minister O'Neill please stop your greed now and give us what belongs to us and concentrate on running the country and the Western Province transparently," Pastor Bagari said.
]]></text></news-item>