<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8455-8D8F-EEFD-8081"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>BANKING ON DIVERSITY</title><source>Herald Sun (Australia)</source><author>Debra Bela</author><text><![CDATA[careerone Multicultural workplaces are good for staff and good for business, writes Debra Bela
CULTURALLY diverse jobseekers must overcome an unconscious bias and celebrate their differences if they are to gain traction in a competitive jobs market.
There are billions of dollars to be made in making the workforce more culturally diverse. Reconciliation Australia and Deloitte Access Economics estimate $24 billion could be added to the economy if 80,000 indigenous jobs were created by 2031.
Increased retention rates, sales revenue, innovation and lower labour management costs are also cited by a Diversity Council of Australia report as benefits of cultural diversity at work.
Multinational companies are leading diversity engagement by appointing diversity managers and creating targets such as PricewaterhouseCooper's pledge to ensure 5 per cent of partners have an Asian cultural background by 2016. The Federal Government has commissioned an Indigenous Jobs and Training Review to better understand the cultural and practical steps needed to encourage business to support more marginalised workers.
But Diversity Council of Australia program and development director Lisa Annese says workplaces must have their own inclusive practices.
"Most of the work has to be done with the employer," Annese says. "Individuals can only do so much - they are up against a system and if it is not encouraging diversity there is a problem.
Australian Bureau of Statistics figures show 46 per cent of Australians are born overseas or have at least one overseas-born parent. Almost 10 per cent of Australians have Asian cultural origins.
However, the 2013 Capitalising on Culture report reveals only 1.9 per cent of executive managers and 4.15 per cent of directors have Asian cultural origins.
Reconciliation Australia co-chair Tom Calma urges workplaces to engage in cross-cultural awareness or competency programs to educate staff and remove undesirable behaviour around racism and discrimination but feels it is already changing.
Many firms already have diverse workforces. At Westpac Group, 44 per cent of employees come from cultural backgrounds other than Australia. Jane Counsel, Westpac's head of diversity and flexibility says diversity helps the bank better relate to its customers and improves leadership qualities.
1.9% OF EXECUTIVE MANAGERS AND 4% OF DIRECTORS HAVE ASIAN ORIGINS 1 IN 5 LEADERS HAVE CULTURALLY DIVERSE ORIGINS $24bn ADDED TO THE ECONOMY IF 80,000 INDIGENOUS JOBS WERE CREATEDBY 2031
JOB OF THE WEEK BANK TELLER Pay Summary $k 30 LOW 44 MEDIUM 51 HIGHSOURCE: PayScale
]]></text></news-item>