<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8560-57DC-B71A-1F44"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Andhra minorities finance body official in the dock for hiding files</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[HYDERABAD: In what could prove to be another scam at the AP State Minorites Finance Corporation (APSMFC), an executive director (ED) has been suspended after hundreds of clearance files pertaining to loan sanctions were seized from him on Thursday.
Upon receiving numerous complaints from loan applicants alleging that Hameed had sought bribes for clearing files, officials of the corporation, including managing director Syed Vilayat Hussain and regional managers Amjad Pasha and Shaik Abid Ali, raided Hameed's office in Ranga Reddy district collectorate in Khairatabad and his residence in Shaikpet.
Sources said that officials found 934 files, out of which 64 were recovered from his house, all carrying approvals of loans running into Rs.4.7 crore. Officials are not allowed to carry files out of the office without obtaining prior consent from seniors such as the general manager or vice chairman and managing director, in this case, Prof Syed Abdul Shukoor, said an APSMFC official.
In what is seen as flagrant violation of rules, Hameed had failed to inform loan beneficiaries that their applications had been approved. Instead, he instructed "brokers" to contact them and sought money for clearing their files. "The files were cleared by the RR district collector on February 18. While some applicants told us that the brokers were asking for money, others said they were not informed that their applications were approved. This in itself is prima facie evidence against the erring officer," said Syed Vilayat Hussain.
Explaining the procedure of funds transfer, Hussain said that beneficiaries are informed once the loan is approved, after which a proceeding is sent to the bank concerned. An 'inoperative bank account' is opened in the beneficiary's name within a couple of days, after which the beneficiary is instructed to inform the APSMFC of the account number. The funds are then transferred to this account by the corporation.
Sources said that Hameed was suspended on three other occasions - once when he was serving as ED Anantapur around seven years ago and again two years later when he was posted in Medak.
A third suspension order was served last December by former managing director Hashim Shareef after he reportedly received complaints of corruption against Hameed. But, despite his suspension, he was reinstated due to political pressure, sources added.
When contacted, APSMFC vice chairman and managing director Prof Syed Abdul Shukoor said: "The official has been suspended. We are in the process of framing charges, after which we will carry out a definite inquiry. I have informed all EDs to inform beneficiaries of approvals."
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>