<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="85D2-96B6-BF9B-97D8"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Questions arising over oil, gas royalty payments to Ohioans from Chesapeake Energy</title><source>Columbus Business First (Ohio)</source><author>Tom Knox</author><text><![CDATA[Ohio soon may join Pennsylvania and other oil and gas field states where lawsuits are mounting as the most-active driller in the state faces questions about its royalty payments.
"Production is just starting. People are in early stages of even understanding royalty statements and getting an idea of what they might deserve," said Mark Okey, a Carroll County attorney who represents landowners in the Utica shale region. "Litigation and arbitration (are) just now beginning."
Chesapeake Energy Corp. (NYSE:CHK) dominates Carroll County land leasing and counts the most well permits in the state. Okey told me he already has clients fighting the Oklahoma City-based energy company over what they claim are under- or unpaid leasing royalties.
The ProPublica news organization&nbsp; published an investigative report this week alleging Chesapeake maneuvered around paying landowners the correct royalties for gas and oil found on their land, especially in Pennsylvania,&nbsp; whose governor last month called for a probe.&nbsp;
The dispute is garnering attention from those with stakes in Ohio's oil and gas industry.
Okey, whose father, Mark, tried to usher in protections for landowners during his recent stint as an Ohio legislator, told me he has reviewed dozens of royalty statements from Chesapeake to Ohioans and said they don't show details about deductions by the company for operating costs.
"In fact, they show the number zero in the deduction column," he said. "We have good information that it is false and deductions are being taken. At least in Pennsylvania they can see what is being taken. In Ohio they're being led to believe that zero dollars are taken. That's a giant difference."
Messages were left with Chesapeake for comment on the accusations.
For more background on the story and how it has affected Pennsylvania landowners,&nbsp; click here.
Ohio, unlike Pennsylvania and other states, doesn't require oil and gas companies to provide standardized royalty statements to landowners. That has prompted confusion among landowners, state Rep. John Carney, D-Columbus,&nbsp; told me in January.&nbsp;
That's also why he and Rep. Jack Cera, D-Bellaire, introduced a proposal that Ohio land and mineral rights owners no longer would be forced to request well owners to provide them with comprehensive royalty statements.
House Bill 400 suffered a quick death, but Cera and Carney are trying to get most of the bill tacked on as an&nbsp; amendment to House Bill 375, the energy severance tax proposal being debated at the Statehouse.
It's unlikely elements of H.B. 400 will stick to the severance tax bill - Carney gives it a less than 50 percent chance - but Cera told me he hopes to pass some type of protection legislation for landowners.
"Reporting of production is not only a problem for landowners, it's a problem for the state," he said. "Because we're taxing them, so we need to make sure we're getting accurate numbers. It's going to be a difficult way to go, let's just put it that way."
Carney and Cera intend to teach Ohio Farm bureaus in the Utica region on what landowners should look for in royalty statements.
"This sort of huckster attitude that 'We've got these people who aren't as sophisticated as us, we can pull one over on them' - every politician regardless of political stripes should be saying, 'No, you can't,' " Carney said. " 'You're not going to waltz in my state and steal from these citizens.' "&nbsp;
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Columbus Business First for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>