<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8799-090E-1EC2-3AA7"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>African Press Review 14 March 2014</title><source>Radio France Internationale</source><author>William Niba</author><text><![CDATA[A massacre in Nigeria comes ahead of a visit by Goodluck Jonathan. A man is questioned over how he came to be in possession of 18 human skulls and what he meant to do with them. Nigerian ministers dig in their heels over anti-gay laws. Uganda has its eyes on the oil prize. SA women are alleged to be used as sex slaves in Mozambique's jails. Sierra Leone bids goodbye to Ahmad Tejan Kabbah.
In Nigeria the papers are reacting to the massacre of at least 69 people in simultaneous attacks carried out on four villages across the northern Katsina State.
Punch quotes the local police commissioner saying that the attackers were not Boko Haram but Fulani herdsmen, blamed in the past for a deadly dispute with Christian farmers over land.
The Sun puts the death toll at 100, pointing out that the killing spree in Faskari local government area occurred less than 24 hours before President Goodluck Jonathan's visit to Katsina State this Friday.
ThisDay claims that the attack has drawn the ire of the main opposition All Progressives Congress which criticised the president for continuing with his state visit.
The Guardian says the massacre was perpetrated as the Speaker of the House of Representatives, Aminu Tambuwal, warned against playing politics with the welfare of soldiers and other security personnel deployed to tackle the Boko Haram insurgency in the North-East states.
In its own reaction to the massacre, the Nigerian Tribune says Fulani herdsmen have for years complained about the loss of grazing land, which is crucial to their livelihood, with resentment between the herdsmen and their agrarian neighbours rising over the past decade.
Vanguard takes up the arrest of an Ogun State man transporting a bag containing 18 human skulls. The paper says he's currently being interrogated at the State Department of Investigations in Abeokuta to find out where he got the human heads and what he intended to do with them.
Nigeria's refusal to repeal the law banning same-sex relationships and marriage is also on the front pages of several Nigerian papers this Friday. Punch underlines that the firm message was delivered to the visiting UN High Commissioner for Human Rights, Navi Pillay, in Abuja on Thursday by Nigeria's Foreign Minister Aminu Wali.
Vanguard says the federal government made it clear to the UN that no amount of pressure will force it to reverse the law.
Uganda is facing a freeze of vital Western aid due to its own anti-gay laws but may not feel the pinch for long, thanks to its new oil producing status.
The Kampala-based New Vision newspaper reports the government on Thursday announced it will pick the lead investor and operator for its planned oil refinery in July, its eyes set for the launching of commercial oil production in 2016 from the Albertine rift basin along its border with Democratic Republic of Congo.
Uganda's oil reserves are estimated by the government at 3.5 billion barrels. France's Total is one of three major firms bidding to build a thermal-power generation plant, a planned refinery and an export pipeline alongside Britain's Tullow Oil and China's state-owned petroleum giant the CNOOC. In December the energy ministry announced five consortia and one individual firm had been shortlisted to bid for the 1.8 billion euros refinery, according to New Vision.
In South Africa The Star investigates shocking allegations that South African women prisoners, jailed in Mozambique for drug trafficking, have been used by prison officials as "sex slaves". The report that guards often demanded sex in exchange for food and toiletries, carried by Sunday Times, has been denied by the Mozambican prison services. Sunday Times claimed that one of the women died in 2012 after being denied adequate medical treatment.
Kenya's Standard newspaper marks the passing of Sierra Leone's former president Ahmad Tejan Kabbah on Thursday at his Freetown home at the age of 82.
According to the paper, Kabbah is widely credited with returning peace to the shattered west African nation after years of brutal civil war. It underlines that he is the one who led the country during an 11-year conflict in which thousands had their limbs hacked off and 120,000 people were killed.
]]></text></news-item>