<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="88F0-9ED8-96D9-78CF"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>White House Tightens Health Plan's Standards After Consumers Complain</title><source>The New York Times</source><author>By ROBERT PEAR</author><text><![CDATA[WASHINGTON -- The Obama administration issued stringent new standards on Friday for health insurance to address a flood of complaints from consumers who said that costs were too high and that the choice of doctors, hospitals and prescription drugs was too limited in many health plans offered this year under the Affordable Care Act.
In deciding which products can be sold in the federal marketplace next year, officials said, they will scrutinize health plans more closely and rely less on evaluations by state insurance regulators and private groups that accredit health plans.
Consumer advocates welcomed the standards and said they should have gone further. But insurers and employer groups complained of burdensome overregulation and said the White House should focus first on getting the online exchanges to work properly.
The federal government sets standards for insurers in the federal exchange, which serves three dozen states with about two-thirds of the nation's population. States running their own exchanges generally build on the federal standards.
Claire McAndrew, the director of the private insurance program at Families USA, a consumer group, said the administration was taking ''a more active approach, with more intensive review'' of insurers seeking permission to do business in the federal exchange next year.
Officials issued the new standards, buried in a stack of documents, at 7:15 p.m. on Friday even as President Obama was stepping up efforts to increase enrollment in health plans this year.
The administration proposed new insurance regulations to go along with the new standards. In so doing, officials acknowledged problems that have bothered many consumers for months.
''We are concerned that some enrollees, particularly those with certain complex medical conditions, are having trouble accessing in a timely fashion clinically appropriate prescription drugs,'' said a preamble to the proposed rules. They were issued by Kathleen Sebelius, the secretary of Health and Human Services, and Marilyn B. Tavenner, the administrator of the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services.
Many health plans held down premiums this year by limiting the choices of doctors and hospitals available in the exchanges, and consumers expressed concern about such narrow networks. The administration said it would examine health plans to make sure consumers have ''reasonable access'' to care in 2015.
Federal officials will look, in particular, at whether health plans have enough hospitals, primary care doctors, cancer specialists and mental health experts in their networks.
Consumers Union, the American Cancer Society and other groups representing patients had urged the administration to conduct a more rigorous review of provider networks.
Under the new standards, insurers will generally be required to have contracts with at least 30 percent of ''essential community providers'' in their service area. They include community health centers, clinics for people with H.I.V./AIDS, family planning clinics, children's hospitals and hemophilia treatment centers.
People shopping for insurance often want to know if they can keep their doctors and if their prescription drugs will be covered. But consumers say it is often hard to find an up-to-date list of providers or a list of covered drugs that shows exactly how much patients must pay for each medicine.
The administration will require insurers to provide direct links to this information from HealthCare.gov and similar websites. It will require insurers to say whether doctors are accepting new patients. And it encourages insurers to pay for a 30-day supply of any drug that a new customer had been taking, even if it would not ordinarily be covered.
''This would prevent disruptions in treatment for new enrollees,'' the administration said.
Daniel T. Durham, an executive vice president of America's Health Insurance Plans, a trade group, said insurers were concerned that the administration was contemplating so many new requirements just months before the deadline for insurers to file applications for 2015. Many consumers, he said, prefer less expensive health plans with a limited network of providers.
Katie W. Mahoney, the executive director of health policy at the U.S. Chamber of Commerce, accused the administration of a ''regulatory power grab'' and said some of the requirements could increase health costs for employers and employees.
Federal officials said insurance plans must not discriminate against people with ''significant health needs.'' To enforce that standard, the government will analyze co-payments charged for prescription drugs, hospital stays and visits to specialists, and it may challenge any health plan that requires ''prior authorization'' for an unusually large number of drugs used to treat a particular condition.
http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/15/us/white-house-tightens-health-insurance-standards-in-response-to-complaints.html
]]></text></news-item>