<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="88FE-60E2-74CA-2204"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>'Sabarmati swimming in pollutants'</title><source>DNA</source><author>dna correspondent</author><text><![CDATA[While the civic body is going all out to ensure that Sabarmati remains clean and pure, the quality of water flowing in it has a different story to tell altogether. For, a recent survey by environment activist Mahesh Pandya and his team revealed that the river contains a huge amount of pollutants, which should not be released into the water body at all.
Blame the industrial areas for disposing of effluents or inefficient sewage treatment plants and common effluent treatment plants (CETP), the river is highly polluted and the level of pollutants is much higher than the prescribed standard.
"According to the survey, the river water contains pH 6.75, while the chemical oxygen demand (COD) was 720 mg per litre, against the prescribed standard of 250 mg per litre," said Pandya.
Moreover, the suspended solids found measured 530, whereas the prescribed standard is 100 for the controlled waste disposal by the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB).
Pandya also said that against the prescribed standard for biochemical oxygen demand (BOD) is 30 mg per litre, the river water had BOD of 288 mg per litre, which is shocking. "Also, total dissolved solids (TDS) should be just 200. But, the survey showed TDS being as high as 3,670. Fortunately, the oil and grease was under the limit with 8 mg/litre whereas the prescribed limit is 10 mg/litre," indicated Pandya.
The survey was conducted a month back when Pandya's team took water samples from three different locations. While one sample was collected before the industrial water gets released into the river, the second and third were collected from the point of waste water release through sewage treatment plant (STP) as well as after the release.
"All the samples were collected from Gyaspur at three different points, out of which the water after mixing with 'treated' water was found to be highly polluted. This indicates that the CETP as well as STP does not function according to standard, allowing effluent water into the river," pointed out Pandya.
According to a study by the Gujarat Pollution Control Board (GPCB), 340 MLD of waste water is directly released into the Sabarmati without any treatment. However, the figures of pollutants like pH, TDS, BOD found in both the surveys differed.
When asked whether the change in figures was due to an increase of pollutants, a GPCB official said: "It entirely depends on where the sampling was done. If GPCB had collected samples from Vasna and Narol bridge and some other agency collected the same from other point, then the result is likely to differ."
"We are aware of the BOD and COD levels in the river water being too high. For this, we will identify the illegal connections which link to the sewage trunk main line used by industries for releasing effluent water. These connections will be disconnected to avoid pollution in the river. Also, we have decided to charge a heavy penalty on the industries for such activity. We have already identified six such illegal lines and will disconnect them soon," said an official of the Ahmedabad Municipal Corporation.
]]></text></news-item>