<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="89A1-C3A6-E00D-5231"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>PM already looking for scapegoats in case of tanker disaster - Busuttil</title><source>The Malta Independent</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Opposition leader Simon Busuttil today said that Prime Minister Joseph Muscat is already looking for people to blame in case of a disaster at the gas-fired plant in Delimara.
On Friday, Dr Muscat told the Opposition leader that if something goes wrong at the plant, it will probably be down to sabotage by the PN.
Speaking at a political activity in Mellieha, Dr Busuttil said that the country will grind to a standstill for months if something goes wrong with the tanker anchored in Marsaxlokk bay, as it will inevitably knock out the power station.
"Anchor it outside of the port. Do not anchor a problem and a risk like that in the port, when all the experts are saying that it's dangerous." "Residents of the South placed their faith in Labour. This government used them for their votes and is now betraying them," Dr Busuttil said.
He implored the Prime Minister and MEPA to act in the best interests of the Maltese population, repeating warnings by chemical engineer Hans Pasman,  who said that in the case of a leak from the tanker the resultant gas cloud would envelop all of Marsaxlokk, leading to many fatalities.
One year in to the Labour government, Dr Busuttil attacked Dr Muscat for abandoning his meritocracy pledge, and failing to deliver on his promise for more transparency.
"We file PQ after PQ and asking for information and details, yet they give us nothing. Even if we ask for the remuneration of government appointees they say no, we do not give that sort of information." "It had to be us who found out that Konrad Mizzi's wife earns EUR13,000 a month, more than some people earn in a year.  He appointed her simply because she is the minister's wife, this is the only reason why she was chosen," Dr Busuttil said.
He accused the Prime Minister of "accepting and living with corruption" which has now become "institutionalised," as evidenced by his failure to take action against the 1,000 Enemalta employees who bribed public officials.
Dr Busuttil said that he will leave it up to people to judge whether Malta's reputation has been enhanced or tarnished internationally.
He said that the government's citizenship scheme has given the impression that Malta is a cash-strapped country, as not even the likes of Greece with its multiple bailouts resorted to selling passports.
It was only the Opposition's strength and persistence that led to multiple changes to the scheme, but it is still not happy with the scheme, he said.
He said that the Prime Minister is clearly isolated in Europe, and seems to be more comfortable when mingling with dictators.
On unemployment, Dr Busuttil said that if the number of unemployed increases much further, the Opposition will come out in force and give a voice to those unable to find a job.
"There is no point ignoring the unemployment problem. It is turning into a serious problem, almost 8,000 are unemployed." "We recognise that it is a problem. We in Opposition are ready to cooperate with you [the government]. We will help you create a programme for creating employment," Dr Busuttil said, pointing out that the government has thus far ignored the Opposition's offer to assist it.
]]></text></news-item>