<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8A2F-B5D9-EB44-97D9"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>DPP Wants the Media Out of Masjid Hearing</title><source>The Star</source><author>Martin Mwaura</author><text><![CDATA[THE Director of Public Prosecutions Keriako Tobiko has applied to have the media and members of the public barred from attending court proceedings of the missing Masjid Musa (now Masjid Shuhadaa) man.
The DPP and AG's offices want the case to proceed in camera. A state counsel for both the DPP and the AG on Wednesday said the lives of witnesses summoned to explain the mysterious disappearance of Hemed Salim after his arrest are at risk.
Photographs and videos of acting Urban police station CID boss inspector Evans Wesonga and constable Owino Okuta captured giving evidence in court have been circulating online. The two police officers are the main witnesses called upon to explain Hemed's disappearance moments after he was captured by the press handcuffed at the back of a police land rover.
A video of his arrest was played in court following an application by lawyer Abubakar Yusuf and human rights activist Okiya Omtatah to prove he was in police custody. Alex Muteti also protested enquiries by lawyers into the sensitive anti terror police operation that was conducted at the Masjid Musa to disrupt an alleged jihadist convention by militant youths.
"All we are asking from the court is to put protective measures in place to ensure the public right to information is limited to ensure witnesses are protected," said Muteti. "We have seen lawyers questioning on how the police conducted the exercise and what apparatuses were involved. If disclosed these can compromise security," said Muteti.
In his application Muteti said the Witness Protection Act could be invoked to gag the media and the public from broadcasting the proceedings. The application was however opposed by Hemed's family, who questioned the intention by the state to apply for the proceedings to be held in camera.
Lawyer Abubakar accused the DPP of attempting to prevent accountability and transparency by the police over the disappearance. "If it were not for the media, the family would not have a guarantee that he was arrested. This is a strategy to shut out Kenyans wanting to know where Hemedi is," said Abubakar.
]]></text></news-item>