<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8A3E-BC14-C2F6-C979"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>EPA IG Touts Independence But Warns Tight Budget May Limit Investigations</title><source>InsideEPA.com's Daily Briefing</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EPA Inspector General (IG) Arthur Elkins Jr. is rejecting Republican senators' concerns that recent IG program evaluations have shown deference to EPA, saying that the IG's work has uncovered major fraud, waste and abuse -- but that tight budgets and staffing reductions may limit future work.
"We have shown significant progress not only on some of the metrics that are important to us, such as return on investment and uncovering significant areas of fraud, waste and abuse, but we've also had some significant program evaluations for the agency that have increased its efficiency in certain areas," Elkins said in an exclusive March 10 interview with Inside EPA. "We've done all this under a very challenging budget environment."
Elkins and several of his top deputies who attended the interview highlighted as successful work an investigation of misuse of an EPA storage warehouse; an evaluation of the agency's comments on National Environmental Policy Act reviews; and work uncovering elements of former EPA air office staffer John Beale's pay fraud.
President Obama's fiscal year 2015 budget proposal would fund the IG's office at $56.2 million, an increase over its current $51.8 million funding, according to an IG spokeswoman.
Elkins said he welcomes the proposed funding boost as the IG could start to consider hiring investigators to fill staff shortfalls, but added that the office will still struggle with its workload. A tighter budget "creates an environment where more things can fall through the cracks and obviously we don't want that to happen," he said.
Prior year EPA budget cuts and a recent round of agency-wide staff buyouts have had a negative impact on the IG's office and created some notable limitations in its investigative division, Elkins said. A total of 24 employees took advantage of the staff buyouts, and the IG's staffing level currently stands at 304, according to an IG spokeswoman. There is no statutory or other requirement for the IG to maintain a particular number of employees.
"We have some areas on the investigative side where we definitely need more staff," Elkins added, saying there are some regional agency offices that have no IG investigators. "If you have folks co-located in a regional office, they can do more proactive things, and that's being ahead of the curve, and that's part of our mission: to prevent and detect fraud, waste and abuse. You can't do that when you don't have somebody in an office."
Fewer staff means that investigations, audits and evaluations are likely to take more time or potentially not occur at all. "And it also creates a burden on the investigators because they're human beings and if anyone is overworked it can lead to turnover, morale issues, unintended consequences," Elkins cautioned.
Tight Funding
Having a limited staff due to tight funding could mean that some cases of fraud might go undetected, he said. Asked whether this means potential future cases similar to those of former EPA Office of Air & Radiation staffer Beale -- who defrauded the agency out of hundreds of thousands of dollars by taking time off under the false pretense he was on Central Intelligence Agency detail -- might go undetected, Elkins said, "Sure, that's a possibility."
The IG in a report released in December said EPA Administrator McCarthy had become aware of bonus pay issues with Beale and requested to pursue the topic with human resources officials, but the report said no actions were taken on the advice of the assistant administrator for the Office of Administration and Resources Management.
The Beale incident also highlighted an ongoing disagreement between the IG and the EPA Office of Homeland Security (OHS) over whether the IG has oversight of that office. The dispute was recently highlighted in a letter exchange between Elkins and EPA Deputy Administrator Bob Perciasepe, in which both sides largely reiterate their positions.
Elkins during the interview noted EPA management's position that believes that OHS staff are exempt from oversight and review by the IG due to the sensitive nature of their work -- but the IG disagrees.
"I think it's clear that we have the oversight responsibility . . . some on the agency side might have a different point of view," he said. But the IG authorizing legislation does not include any specific exemptions for any agency divisions, and Elkins said that exempting OHS staff from purview could hinder the IG's ability to do its work.
"In order to do that we have to have unfettered access to records, people and documents. If you don't have that then you don't have oversight," Elkins said. "If you have a unit within an agency that is not subject to oversight, who's doing the oversight? You could have fraud, waste and abuse. In an area like homeland security, you can see it's a critical need for the IG to have the ability to do that oversight. If not, you have staff who are not subject to any oversight."
Elkins stressed that the IG believes that OHS has the jurisdiction and authority over homeland security policies and issues, but said that does not exempt the office's staff from having to cooperate with IG investigations.
IG's Independence
Sen. David Vitter (R-LA), ranking member of the Senate Environment & Public Works Committee, and other GOP panel members have claimed that several IG investigations suggest a lack of independence between the IG and the Obama administration on controversial policy issues including air data and hydraulic fracturing.
For example, six Republican senators -- including several EPW members -- signed a Feb. 26 letter criticizing an IG investigation of an emergency order issued and later withdrawn over reported contamination at a hydraluic fracturing site in Texas, saying the IG "disregarded an abundance of evidence showing that facts were manipulated, conclusions were unjustified, science was ignored, and EPA colluded with radical environmental groups." The letter was signed by Vitter and GOP Sens. James Inhofe (OK), John Cornyn (TX), John Boozman (AR), Tom Coburn (OK) and Ted Cruz (TX).
But Elkins in the interview defended his office's independence and said that the scope of the IG's reviews is determined through several legislative and regulatory parameters. The Inspector General Act of 1978 as amended, created the EPA IG and said it is considered independent from the agency in order to give it an unbiased approach to the audits, evaluations and investigations that form the bulk of its work. The IG also follows peer-reviewed standards established by the Council of the Inspectors General on Integrity and Efficiency on how to pursue its work, Elkins said.
Other guidelines for how the IG is meant to conduct its audits, evaluations and investigations include Government Accountability Office auditing standards and U.S. attorney general investigative guidelines.
Adhering to these mandatory guidelines means "there's going to be tension" with groups that request or respond to IG reports, Elkins said, depending on the reports' conclusions. "We follow facts. The facts that we report on have to be corroborated with citation, authority. There has to be a record in place that anybody can come in to take a look at. Even after all that, if the report doesn't come out the way a particular reader would like to see it come out, they are prone to say, 'Well you're biased because it didn't come out the way I thought.' One could say that's biased in the other way, because if it happened to come out the other way then the other side would say you're biased," he said.
"So you're always in the middle with this, but we fall back on the fact that we follow standards. We're not making this up. The facts are what they are, and based on the facts we have to draw conclusions. And that's what we do. To the extent there are folks who are unhappy with our interpretation of our facts, that goes with the territory," Elkins added. "Sometimes you're going to land at a place where folks over here don't like what you said, or folks there don't like what you said. But we're independent and we're going to tell the story" based on facts, he said.
He compared the IG's work to the work done by objective journalists researching and writing an impartial story. "If you think a story, based on the facts, should end here, you're not going to bend to any kind of manipulation or pressure to turn the story differently," he said. "And we're in the same situation. We have to call it the way we see it."
Elkins added that former New York Democratic Senator Daniel Moynihan "was fond of saying, 'You're entitled to your opinion but not your facts -- I think that's probably an appropriate comment."
Pending Reviews
Despite the budget limits and other hurdles facing the IG's office, Elkins touted a successful prior year of IG reviews and said his team is planning an ambitious year ahead for audits, evaluations and investigations.
The IG recently released its plan for FY14 -- which began Oct. 1 and ends Sept. 30 -- detailing significant reviews of key agency programs, including whether companies comply with Clean Air Act consent decrees; spending of Hurricane Sandy relief money; and the risks of siting renewable energy on contaminated land.
The IG's program evaluation offices does work that has the most potential direct impact on the agency's regulations, as they can lead to reports that fault EPA programs or suggest gaps in regulatory areas. The auditing office detects problems such as misuse of agency funds, while the investigation office reviews potential criminal matters.
Several top IG officials also attended the interview with Elkins, and highlighted recent IG reports as well as touting recently launched and ongoing work. For example, Assistant IG for Program Evaluation Carolyn Copper noted the IG is pursuing a request from EPA Region II Administrator Judith Enck to assess the Virgin Island's execution of authorized federal environmental programs, as well as concerns about compliance and financial management.
Patricia Hill, assistant IG for mission systems, stressed the extensive work that the office is doing on cybersecurity and protecting the agency's networks from hackers who might be seeking sensitive EPA data -- potentially such as pre-decisional information on rulemakings -- or looking to shut down the agency's computer network.
Meanwhile, Acting IG for Audit Richard Eyermann said the audit of the Landover, MD, warehouse as an example of "proactive" work, with IG staff inspecting the facility and finding significant problems, such as discarded office equipment that could be used to avoid new furniture purchase costs in agency offices with furniture needs.
The investigation into the Beale fraud case separately highlights the "cross-pollination" that sometimes occurs between the IG's auditing and investigative divisions, said Deputy IG Charles Sheehan.
As a result of that case, the IG's hotline has received numerous tips that the investigative division is currently pursuing, noted Craig Ulmer, one of two deputy IGs for investigations. -- Anthony Lacey (alacey@iwpnews.com)
]]></text></news-item>