<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8A47-EE09-EEBF-7F8E"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>AFPTV Advisory 2000 GMT</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[We will file the following videos:
-- TOP WORLD NEWS --
+ UKRAINE
Coming up:
SIMFEROPOL, UKRAINE: Not so much Six Nations as One Nation, Russia played Crimea Saturday in a rugby union match which ended in a draw, the day before a referendum on breaking from Ukraine expected to go in Moscow's favour. PKG. 2300 GMT
Filed over past 12 hours:
SIMFEROPOL, UKRAINE: Polling stations set up ahead of referendum. RAW. VID607077_EN
SEVASTOPOL, UKRAINE: Pro-Russian activists campaign for a vote to join Russia. RAW. VID607116_EN
DONETSK, UKRAINE: Pro-Kremlin protesters attacked a security service building in the eastern city of Donetsk, demanding the release of their "governor" and their own right to vote on joining Russia. RAW. VID607184_EN
KHARIV, UKRAINE: Two people are killed in clashes between pro-Moscow and pro-Kiev supporters in Ukraine's Russian-speaking city of Kharkiv. RAW. VID607172_EN
KIEV: US Senator John McCain calls for massive military assistance to Ukraine, warns that Russia's actions could lead to unprecedented measures by the United States and it allies. RAW. VID607202_EN
PYROHOVKA, UKRAINE: Serb militiamen join pro-Russian activists in Crimea, taking up positions at road checkpoints. RAW. VID606584_EN
MOSCOW: 50,000 people rally in protest at Russia's intervention in Ukraine. RAW. VID607096_EN
UNITED NATIONS: Russia vetoes a Western-backed resolution condemning the Crimea referendum at a UN Security Council emergency vote. RAW. VID607170_EN (vote) RAW. VID607157_EN (US envoy)
PARIS: French President Francois Hollande says France will not recognise the result of a Crimean referendum on switching to Kremlin rule. RAW. VID607150_EN
Ahead of the referendum, we have refiled the following videos:
Stockshots and file images of various locations in Crimea. STOCKSHOTS/FILE.
- Simferopol: VID606034_EN
- Yalta / Alushta (economy): VID606258_EN
- Simferopol populations and protests: VID606075_EN
- Simferopol politics: VID606077_EN
- Sevastopol military: VID606073_EN
SIMFEROPOL, UKRAINE: Crimea votes in a referendum on Sunday on whether to join Russia or increase autonomy from Ukraine, a ballot that could reshape Russia's diplomatic relations with the rest of the world. PKG. NSV - VID606738_EN / VOICED - VID606739_EN
DZHANKOY, UKRAINE: Visits home for 17-year-old university student Dima have become increasingly tense, with the family split down the middle on whether Crimea should become part of Russia or stay with Ukraine, reflecting deep divisions between even blood relatives ahead of Sunday's referendum. PKG. NSV - VID606476_EN / VOICED - VID606477_EN
LONDON: Political expert comments on Crimea referendum and what Russia stands to gain or lose in the vote's outcome. RAW. VID606620_EN / VID606832_EN
+ MALAYSIA AIRLINES SEARCH
Filed over past 12 hours:
KUALA LUMPUR: Press conference by Prime Minister Najib Razak who says the missing Malaysia Airlines jet was deliberately diverted and flown for hours after vanishing from radar. RAW. VID607093_EN
BEIJING: Families of the passengers aboard the missing Malaysia Airlines flight 370 react angrily to the latest developments. RAW. VID607063_EN
JAKARTA: Interview with an aviation expert on the latest information about the missing Malaysia Airlines flight. RAW. VID607067_EN
-- OTHER WORLD NEWS --
+ EUROPE
Attention clients: due to technical issue, coverage of Syrian opposition leader Ahmed Jarba's speech has been delayed. We apologise for the inconvenience.
Filed over past 12 hours:
PARIS: French President Francois Hollande holds talks with new Italian Prime Minister Matteo Renzi. RAW. VID607136_EN (arrival) VID607150_EN (presser)
BRATISLAVA: Slovakia votes in first round of presidential election. RAW. VID607100_EN
BUDAPEST: On Hungary's national day, Prime Minister Viktor Orban rallies supporters ahead of the general election on April 6. RAW. VID607145_EN
ROME: Theatre group stages historical reconstruction of the assassination of Julius Caesar by a group of conspirators led by Brutus to mark the Ides of March. RAW. VID607138_EN
BORDEAUX, FRANCE: Sneak peak at American choreographer Carolyn Carlson's new ballet "Pneuma" ahead of its world premiere on Monday. RAW. VID607075_EN
+ MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
YABRUD, SYRIA: Syrian troops advance on the key rebel bastion of Yabrud. RAW. VID607079_EN
BEIRUT: On third anniversary of Syrian conflict, aid organisations warn the situation is getting worse, not better. RAW. VID607214_EN
CAIRO: Gunmen kill six soldiers at a Cairo checkpoint in a brazen morning attack. RAW. VID607069_EN
BAALBECK, LEBANON: One person is killed and three wounded in eastern Lebanon by rockets fired from neighbouring Syria, a security sources say. RAW. VID607213_EN
ALGIERS: Protest in central Algiers against ailing President Abdelaziz Bouteflika's decision to seek a fourth term in next month's presidential election. RAW. VID607072_EN
FARAYA, LEBANON: Ski season is finally in swing here as the winter's first snowfall finally arrives. RAW. VID607091_EN
+ AFRICA
Filed over past 12 hours:
ABUJA: At least seven people are killed and dozens injured after during a stampede at a government recruitment drive at the national stadium. RAW. VID607166_EN
CAPE TOWN/LONDON: Global march for lions calls for an end to 'canned' hunting whereby lions are bred in captivity with the sole purpose of being hunted by wealthy thrill-seekers. RAW. VID607173_EN (Cape Town) VID607175_EN (London)
We have refiled the following angled report:
MOKOPANE, SOUTH AFRICA: Canned hunting for rich thrill-seekers and Lion bones have become a hot commodity for their use in Asian traditional medicine, driving up exports from South Africa to the East and creating new fears of the survival of the species. PKG. NSV - VID443706_EN / VOICED - VID443707_EN
BUULA BURDE, SOMALIA: African peacekeepers operating with government forces have recaptured several strategic towns in southwest Somalia from the Al-Qaeda-linked Shebab militia. RAW. VID607113_EN
+ ASIA-PACIFIC
Filed over past 12 hours:
TOKYO: Anti-nuclear protesters rally in Tokyo to demand the abolition of atomic energy three years after the Fukushima accident. RAW. VID607051_EN
MITHI, PAKISTAN: As the death toll from the latest outbreak of poverty-driven diseases in Pakistan's Thar desert nears 100 children, experts are warning that corruption and a dysfunctional political system make a repeat of the disaster almost inevitable. RAW. VID606688_EN
JAKARTA: Indonesia's main opposition party nominates the hugely popular governor of Jakarta, Joko Widodo, as its presidential candidate, setting him up as the leading contender for July elections. FILE. VID607040_EN
-- SPORT -
Coming up:
SAINT-DENIS, FRANCE: Post-match reax after Ireland beats France 22-20 to clinch the rugby Six Nations title. RAW. 2300 GMT
RIO DE JANEIRO: Former French international footballer Lilian Thuram visits the Complexo do Alemao favela. RAW. TBA
AFPTV is launching a new service on Europe's main football leagues covering key games of the week in England, Germany, Spain, France and Italy. This service will be available upon request as a special subscription.
LONDON: Post-match reax after Chelsea lose 0-1 to Aston Villa in the Premier League. RAW. Overnight Saturday to Sunday
Filed over past 12 hours:
ROME: Post-match reax after England routs Italy 52-11 for their final match of the rugby Six Nations tournament. RAW. VID607197_EN
As part of our new Eurofootball offer available as a special subscription, we have filed the following videos:
BARCELONA, SPAIN: Pre-match presser ahead of Sunday's La Ligua match between Barcelona and Osasuana. RAW. EFT57_EN
LONDON: Pre-match training and pressers ahead of Saturday's Premier League match between Aston Villa and Chelsea. RAW. EFT73
-- FEATURES --
Filed:
AUSTIN, TEXAS: Their first album was almost scuppered by US sanctions and they do not have enough money for instruments, but Myanmar indie rockers Side Effect have played the gig of their dreams in America, becoming the first band from their isolated nation to play South by South West music festival. PKG. NSV - VID607147_EN / VOICED - VID607148_EN
ANSHUN, CHINA: Chinese workers in coal-mining villages who bear the brunt of toxic air and tragic accidents may have to find new jobs as the government plans to shut down half the province's mines in its fight the country's broader problem - pollution. PKG. NSV - VID604427_EN / VOICED - VID604426_EN
QUITO: CCTV camera surveillance is gaining ground in Ecuador. Introduced to fight crime, the cameras are now omnipresent. While some welcome the initiative, others fear that they intrude on private lives and could even be used by the authorities to monitor political opponents. PKG. NSV - VID606844_EN / VOICED VID606843_EN
Contact:
London desk: +44 207 776 2768
Hong Kong desk: +852 2829 6216
Nicosia desk: +357 22 391 453
Washington desk: +1 202 414 0550
Montevideo desk: +598 2 900 5095 ext 257
For contact via email: afptv-en@afp.com
]]></text></news-item>