<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8A76-374A-BED7-37F5"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Animal Drug Companies Formally Agree To Phase Out Certain Antibiotics</title><source>FDA Week</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Animal drug companies, keeping with an FDA 90-day deadline, notified the agency Monday (March 10) that they will cooperate with the agency's plans to phase out growth promotion indications on antibiotics. Industry awaits a finalized Veterinary Feed Directive from FDA, but companies are otherwise on schedule to stay within FDA's plans for a three-year phase in of new animal antibiotic policies, an industry source said.
Advocates of restricting animal antibiotics had questioned whether industry would fully cooperate with FDA's approach and how the agency will measure progress under the new policies. "Those questions should be put to bed," said Ron Phillips, vice president of legislative and public affairs at Animal Health Institute, responding to concerns about industry participation.
AHI and Generic Animal Drug Alliance members told FDA in writing that they will comply with the agency's new policy on the judicious use of antibiotics, the groups said Monday. When FDA finalized guidance on the transition in December, the agency asked companies to communicate their intent to comply within 90 days.
"We understand that consumers have concerns about medically important antibiotics being used to promote growth," AHI President and CEO Alexander Mathews said in a statement. "We hope this change in regulation and control will increase consumer confidence and lead to a more productive discussion about animal welfare, sustainability and public health."
In December, FDA finalized guidance 213, which lays out the process for companies to remove production uses, such as growth promotion, from the antibiotic label. The agency also issued a proposed rule updating requirements for Veterinary Feed Directive drugs used with the oversight of the veterinarian. Under FDA's approach, which has been widely criticized for being voluntary, companies would change product labels to remove production uses for medically important antibiotics and put antibiotics under the supervision of a veterinarian.
FDA gave companies three months to notify the agency whether they intend to make the labeling changes. Companies have three years to make the transition before FDA will seek other regulatory action. If FDA finalizes the VFD rule in a timely manner, companies are on track to stay within this three year time frame, said Phillips.
Further, as part of a bigger food safety funding increase proposed in the administration's fiscal 2015 budget, the agency plans to support these antibiotic activities.
"To support this initiative, FDA will collect use data and conduct other research to better understand antimicrobial drug use practices in animals and the public health impacts on antimicrobial resistance," according to FDA's budget justification document. "FDA will use this funding to enhance methods for characterizing bacteria, conduct studies to better understand drug effects on bacteria, and develop approaches to monitor and assess drug use and antimicrobial resistance trends."
The antibiotics initiative would be among the activities funded by a $263 million proposed increase for several food safety, including Food Safety Modernization Act implementation. However, FDA's $1.48 billion proposed budget for food safety is heavily dependent on unauthorized user fees. -- Alaina Busch
]]></text></news-item>