<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8B3F-F91C-A470-2763"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Hoeness stands down as Bayern president after accepting three-and-a-half year jail term for tax evasion</title><source>MailOnline</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Uli Hoeness has accepted a three-and-a-half year prison term for evading 27million euros (£22.5) in taxes and will step down as president and business chairman of Bayern Munich.
The 62-year-old was sentenced on Thursday after a high-profile court case which had captivated Germany.
'After discussions with my family I have decided to accept the ruling of the Munich court on my tax affairs,' he said in a statement. 'This befits my understanding of decency, dignity and personal responsibility.
'Tax evasion was the biggest mistake of my life.'
Judge Rupert Heindl ruled on Thursday that Hoeness's voluntary disclosure of tax evasion was incomplete and therefore did not meet a vital requirement for amnesty laws designed to encourage tax dodgers to come clean.
Hoeness had admitted evading taxes on income earned in secret Swiss bank accounts, but had hoped for leniency in one of the most closely watched tax evasion cases in German history.
The case hinged on the question of whether Hoeness, who as a player helped West Germany win the 1974 World Cup, cooperated fully with his voluntary disclosure. His case shocked the nation and prompted thousands of tax dodgers to turn themselves in.
Hoeness was first charged with evading 3.5m euros in taxes. But when the trial began on Monday he stunned the court by admitting he had actually evaded five times that amount - or 18.5m euros.
That figure was raised further to 27.2m euros on the second day of the trial based on testimony by a tax inspector. Hoeness's defence team acknowledged the higher figure.
Hoeness said he would step down from his positions with the club in order to spare Bayern Munich - last season's Champions League winners - any damage.
The club's earnings have soared under his stewardship, which has lasted 35 years in various posts. With more than 220,000 members, it is one of the world's biggest clubs.
'Bayern Munich is my life's work and will also remain so,' said Hoeness, who had been a friend of Chancellor Angela Merkel and a popular TV talk show guest. Ironically, he had spoken out for higher taxes and railed against tax evasion.
SO, WHAT'S GOING ON? YOUR FULL GUIDE TO THE TRIAL...
Uli Hoeness has just been found guilty of tax evasion by a German court and sentenced to three and a half years in jail. But, unless you've been following the trial closely, you may have a few questions. Like who is he, what has he done, and why does it matter? 
Who is Uli Hoeness?
Winner of the World Cup, European Championship and three European cups as a player with Germany and Bayern Munich, Hoeness is now the President of the most successful club in the world, having led Bayern to an unprecedented treble last season. He also part owns a sausage factory and has outspoken views about European football.
Outspoken views? Like what?
Hoeness has been highly critical of the super-rich clubs, in particular Manchester City and Paris Saint Germain. In fact, he was instrumental in the creation of the new financial fair play rules.
But now he's going to prison for tax evasion? 
That's right. Despite the prosecution calling for a five and a half year sentence the ex-footballer has only been given three and a half years. But that's still a long time, considering Hoeness himself turned himself in.
Why did he do that?
The German authorities have been getting tough on tax evasion. Whether Hoeness knew they were investigating him or not, he seems to have come to the decision that any sentence would be less harsh if he cooperated. Although he said he was "aware that reporting myself doesn't change this fact," it seems clear that he hoped he would earn some sympathy from coming forward. So he didn't try to defend himself, and actually seemed to help the prosecution.
He helped the prosecution in his own case. How does that work?
There isn't a plea system in this type of case, but when the prosecution came forward with the suggestion that he had failed to pay (EURO)3.5m in taxes, he said the actual figure was more like (EURO)18m. He had hoped that he would be able to gain some form of amnesty by cooperating
But that didn't work, did it?
No. The prosecution successfully argued that he hadn't made a full enough disclosure early enough. The court then saw documents that suggested he should have paid (EURO)27.2m, and Hoeness admitted that he hadn't come forward earlier because he hoped there would be a deal between Germany and Switzerland, where he held an account, for tax evaders. 
Where does this leave Bayern?
Hoeness has been a hugely successful President since taking over from Franz Beckenbauer in 2009. The club have never been in better shape, currently 49 games unbeaten in the Bundesliga and into the quarter-finals of the Champions League. Their President's trial doesn't seem to have damaged performances so far, but it seems certain that Hoeness, permitted to remain in charge throughout the investigation, will be removed now. Whether that will lead to instability or not remains to be seen, but it can't be good news.
And what about Germany as a whole?
Hoeness isn't just a footballing figure, he's a national icon, and a regular to TV chat shows. This case, and those like it, has already caused thousands more Germans to turn themselves in, while Angela Merkel, the German Chancellor and a political ally of the Bayern President, has spoken of her 'disappointment' in Hoeness' actions.
By Jonny Singer
]]></text></news-item>