<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8B51-D311-CA15-3377"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>STATE PUTS BRAKES ON ROUTE 460 PROJECT {SUMMHD} Transportation secretary cites environmental concerns, says alternate routes possible</title><source>Daily Press (Newport News, Virginia)</source><author> By Cathy Grimes  cgrimes@dailypress.com</author><text><![CDATA[Virginia Secretary of Transportation Aubrey L. Layne on Friday said the state has suspended all contract and permit work on the Route 460 construction project.
Layne said the decision was made to issue a stop work order to US 460 Mobility Partners so the state can continue environmental reviews for the $1.4 billion public-private partnership project. US 460 Mobility Partners is the private entity working in partnership with Virginia Department of Transportation to build the road.
Layne, speaking at the VDOT operations center in Virginia Beach, said the order was temporary, "until, quite frankly, we know where we are going to end up going."
Layne said the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers had expressed concerns about the proposed corridor for the 55-mile road between Prince George County and Suffolk. He said significant mitigation would be needed for almost 500 acres of wetlands.
The project, approved by former Gov. Bob McDonnell's administration in 2012, has had permitting issues since the Army Corps of Engineers and the Federal Highway Administration ordered additional assessment of the wetlands in the area in October 2013. Initial estimates of how much wetland would be affected by the road were lower than both federal agencies saw on the proposed construction route.
In January, Layne told the Commonwealth Transportation Board that VDOT had suspended rights-of-way acquisitions and other work while conducting an environmental study of the area.
Layne said on Friday, "the Corps has been consistent for many years letting us know this particular corridor was going to be problematic."
He said the state and the Army Corps of Engineers "did reach agreement on the objectives" related to wetlands-mitigation needs for the project, and the state now is reviewing alternative proposals with an eye toward environmental impact. Those alternatives include improving the existing road.
The process will take about a year, Layne said, and will include public hearings. At its conclusion, the Corps will consider whether to issue a permit for the project.
"This corridor still could be the one selected, but it would have to show it has a lesser impact on the environment," Layne said.
So far, the state has spent $300 million on the Route 460 project, which began in December 2012 after the contract was awarded. Of that total, $225 million was paid to US 460. The rest covered VDOT work on the project.
Layne said he could not estimate how much an alternative route would cost, including using the current road. He said not much of the $300 million spent thus far would be applicable, if the state chooses to improve the existing roadway.
"The contractor has been paid for things we have not utilized," he said. "By contract, they have no legal obligation to repay (the state)."
Layne said no actual construction has started on the project, but the order to halt work will save the state the $35 million monthly payments to the US 460 Mobility Partners.
VDOT officials said the state was responsible for $900 million of the $1.4 billion cost of the project. Virginia Port Authority contributed $250 million in public funds, and the rest of the cost is covered by $244 million in tax-exempt toll revenue bonds issued for the project. Layne was chairman of the 460 Funding Corporation, which issued the bonds.
Part of the contract for the public-private partnership called for using tolls to help pay for the road, but Layne said the existing road, if that route is chosen, may not lend itself to tolling.
"I cannot tell you today if it's a toll facility," he said.
The Southern Environmental Law Center issued a statement in response to Layne's action, calling it a step in the right direction.
"The proposed new Route 460 is a wasteful and destructive project heading nowhere fast," wrote Trip Pollard, senior attorney for the center.
Shannon Moody, public relations manager for US 460 Mobility Partners, said in a prepared statement, "We are hopeful that the project will advance following this unexpected pause. We ... look forward to continuing our partnership with VDOT and the Route 460 Funding Corporation."
Sen. John Miller, D-Newport News, responded to the news on Friday. In an email, Miller, a member of the Senate Transportation Committee, said, "Secretary Layne has made a wise decision. A year-long review will help to ensure the state chooses the proper option and hopefully prevents spending billions of dollars on a road that will not relieve congestion or solve our traffic issues."
Layne said he and Gov. Terry McAuliffe remain committed to the Route 460 project.
"We are stopping work. Neither the contract nor the project are terminated. ... We are not backing off the project," he said. "We believe it is very important that we get enhanced mobility in that corridor, and we get an evacuation route ... and also for the economic development of the port."
Reporter Travis Fain contributed to this story.
Grimes can be reached by phone at 757-247-4758.
MORE INSIDE
Isle of Wight officials react. Page 4 of News
]]></text></news-item>