<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8BE9-4328-08DF-2109"><date>2014-03-14</date><title></title><source>Washingtonpost.com</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Unemployment benefitsA Senate bipartisan deal would allow retroactive payments to go to more than 2 million Americans. A2
Climbing cost of convenienceAmazon said it will raise the price of its Prime membership service by $20, to $99 a year. A12
the economy
A review of federal crash data found that 303 drivers and front-seat passengers died in accidents in which air bags failed to inflate in two models that General Motors recalled. A12
A plan to unwind Fannie Maeand Freddie Mac pits taxpayers against the companies' shareholders. A14
Mobile apps are unlikely to help babies learn their ABCs and1-2-3s, despite the apps' marketing claims, experts said in a filing with the Federal Trade Commission. A14
BP can once again bid on oil and gas leases on U.S. lands and waters, four years after its disastrous oil spill in the Gulf of Mexico. A13
the nation
A Mali national accused in the 2000 slaying of an American diplomat in Niger was arraigned in federal court in Brooklyn. A3
Hill leaders invited Pope Francis to address a joint session of Congress next year. A3
An Algerian man who spent 12 years at the U.S. military prison at Guantanamo Bay, Cuba, without being charged was returned home. A2
the world
The dismissal of charges against an Indian diplomat in a domestic worker case was greeted with skepticism and relief in India. A8
Israel's killing of a Jordanian judge of Palestinian origin has triggered an outpouring of anger in Jordan. A9
the region
A Temple Hills husband and wife, both 72, were found dead in an apparent murder-suicide, Prince George's County police said. B1
An employee at a child-care centeron Joint Base Myer-Henderson Hall was charged with assaultafter investigators said they uncovered incidents in which she hit or pushed children. B3
A D.C. man was charged with defacing a tree, among more than 100 found with deep carvings. B3
A federal lawyer warned Maryland lawmakers that Purple Line funding could be jeopardized if a bidder is required to compensate Holocaust victims. B1
A Montgomery County woman accusedof stabbing her childrenin an exorcism was indicted on first-degreemurder charges. B3
]]></text></news-item>