<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8C56-AD49-2820-A864"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>W.VA. briefs</title><source>Mineral Daily News-Tribune (Keyser, West Virginia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Mediation Round 2 set in Mountain State claims
CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) - A second round of mediation is scheduled stemming from the loss of accreditation of the nursing program at Mountain State University.
The Charleston Daily Mail (http://bit.ly/1ez8YJl) reports that the mediation is scheduled for March 26-28.
The mediation stems from lawsuits filed by former Mountain State students following the nursing program's loss of accreditation. The university later lost school-wide accreditation and closed. The University of Charleston took over the school.
Hundreds of cases were transferred to West Virginia's mass litigation panel. The first round of mediation was last August.
Lawsuits still are joining the mass litigation panel. Among the claims are fraud and breach of contract.
25 puppies seized from W.Va. business
MARTINSBURG, W.Va. (AP) - Twenty-five puppies have been seized from a business in Martinsburg amid complaints of cruel conditions.
The Berkeley County Sheriff's Department and animal control agents seized the puppies this week at a business called WV Puppies. Officials said they served a search warrant on the business after receiving complaints the puppies were being held under inhumane conditions. There were also allegations the animals were improperly transported across state lines.
The Journal reports the owners of the business have refused to identify themselves.
Officials acted after they saw a van with out-of-state tags delivering crates of puppies to the business.
A court hearing on the seizure has been scheduled for March 20.
Farmer seeks to delay prison report date
FRANKFORT, Ky. (AP) - Former University of Kentucky basketball star Richie Farmer wants to delay his report date to federal prison by a week.
Farmer's attorney asked a federal judge to bump the reporting date until March 25. He's currently due to report March 18 to the federal prison in Hazelton, W.Va. to serve his 27-month prison term.
The former Kentucky Agriculture Commissioner says he wants to see his son play in the Kentucky State High School Basketball Tournament. The earlier report date would make that impossible.
Farmer pleaded guilty in September to using state resources for his personal benefit.
Farmer gained basketball fame as part of "The Unforgettables" - a group of Wildcats who stayed with the program through NCAA sanctions and led Kentucky back to the NCAA tournament in 1992.
W.Va. man's oxygen machine stolen by 3
SOUTH CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) - South Charleston police say a man just released from the hospital was robbed of his oxygen machine by three men.
WCHS-TV says the theft occurred shortly after 1 a.m. Friday as the man walked home from the hospital. Police say they believe the men didn't realize they were stealing the man's oxygen machine, which was in a bag.
One of the men had a knife.
The victim is in his 50s. He wasn't hurt.
W.Va. art contest winners named
CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) - State officials have announced the West Virginia winners of the 2014 Congressional Youth Art Competition.
The nationwide high school competition recognizes and encourages artistic talent in each congressional district.
The West Virginia winners are: Allison McIntyre of Lincoln High School in Harrison County, Kaylee Icenhower of Ravenswood High School in Jackson County, and McKayla Meade of Mingo Central High School.
Each winner's art will be on display at the U.S. Capitol for a year. An exhibition at the Culture Center in Charleston will feature the work of West Virginia's winners through April 10.
Since the competition began in 1982, more than 650,000 high school students have participated.
W.Va. groups getting humanities grants
CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) - Several West Virginia organizations are receiving grants to support humanities programs.
The West Virginia Humanities Council says it recently awarded seven grants. The council is the state affiliate of the National Endowment for the Humanities and offers a variety of grants to nonprofit organizations in West Virginia to support educational programming.
Officials say the council budgets more than $530,000 for grants and programs in the humanities each year. The recently awarded grants were for projects requesting $1,500 or less.
The recent grant recipients are: Glenville State College, the town of Athens, the Larry Joe Harless Community Center, the WVU Research Corporation, the Monroe County Historical Society, High Rocks Educational Corporation and the Northern Webster County Improvement Council.
W.Va. AARP names new president
CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) - The West Virginia chapter of AARP has a new president.
Officials say the organization has selected Rich Stonestreet of Charleston to serve as the state chapter's volunteer leader. He'll represent nearly 300,000 members in West Virginia.
Stonestreet has served as a member of the all-volunteer panel that advises and helps set strategic direction for the West Virginia AARP chapter.
In 2013, he was the state recipient of the organization's highest volunteer recognition: the Andrus Award for Community Service. The award honors individuals who are sharing their experience, talent, and skills to enrich the lives of their community members.
The retired educator and labor relations professional is a graduate of West Liberty University and the University of Tennessee, and completed doctoral coursework at Ohio State University.
W.Va. students recognized by federal prosecutors
CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) - Federal prosecutors are recognizing 88 high school juniors from throughout West Virginia as Ambassadors for Justice.
U.S. Attorneys Booth Goodwin and Bill Ihlenfeld honored the students this week at a ceremony in Charleston.
The U.S. Attorney's Ambassador for Justice program honors high school juniors who have shown outstanding leadership skills and a commitment to social justice.
Goodwin created the program two years ago in response to rising school bullying and social media threats involving young people.
Nominations are made by school principals and administrative leaders. This year, 87 high schools in 46 counties nominated the students that were honored this week.
W.Va. police participate in 6-state patrol
CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) - The West Virginia State Police is touting a recent multi-state criminal patrol that led to more than 500 arrests.
The 6-State Trooper Project consisted of the Michigan State Police, Kentucky State Police, Ohio Highway Patrol, West Virginia State Police, Pennsylvania State Police, and Indiana State Police.
Officials say the participating agencies recorded a total of 542 drug arrests and 47 illegal weapon violations during the patrol last week.
The totals reported by the West Virginia State Police were 86 drug arrests and 4 illegal weapon violations.
Pa. woman charged in W.Va. crash that killed 2
ELKINS, W.Va. (AP) - West Virginia State Police say a Pennsylvania woman has been charged in an accident that killed two people, including a 7-week-old girl.
State Police in Elkins arrested 28-year-old Janel Sturm of Baden, Pa., on two counts of driving under the influence causing death and one count of child neglect resulting in death.
State Police tell WBOY-TV (http://bit.ly/1fWk0Ob) that Sturm is accused of having methamphetamine and other controlled substances in her system at the time of the Oct. 28 accident. The accident on U.S. Route 250 in Barbour County killed 29-year-old Travis Felton of Belington and his daughter, Raele Felton.
Sturm was arraigned in Randolph County Magistrate Court and was being held Thursday in the Tygart Valley Regional Jail on $150,000 bond. Jail records didn't indicate whether Sturm has an attorney.
]]></text></news-item>