<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8CB1-9E67-B845-B81C"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Pakistan: Children in KP, FATA inoculated against Polio: FO</title><source>Right Vision News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ISLAMABAD, March 15 -- Pakistan has said unlike the perception, most of children in Khyber Pakhtunkhwa and FATA areas have been inoculated against Polio.
Speaking at weekly Foreign Office press briefing in Islamabad Thursday, Spokesperson Tasnim Aslam said federal and provincial governments are determined to eradicate polio from the country. She said immunization of children against polio relates Pakistan's future.
She said Pakistan is well-aware of World Health Organization's concerns and recently in her visit to Pakistan, the head of WHO held very constructive meetings regarding the issue. She said despite the security concerns, WHO is keen to help Pakistan in overcoming the problem.
FO spokesman said a decree issued at a conference in Jeddah attended by Ulemas from across the world declared Polio vaccine as Halal and legitimate. She said polio vaccine being used in Pakistan is procured from Indonesia, a Muslim country, Indonesia.
Replying to a question, she said after GSP Plus status, there have been positive trends about our trade relations with European Union.
Regarding EU Ambassador's comments, Tasnim Aslam said Pakistan expects from diplomatic community including him to abide by the norms of internationally recognized diplomatic behavior, and not to comment on our internal matters.
She said Pakistan is implementing twenty-seven international conventions to inculcate a culture of respect for human rights. Regarding Iran-Pakistan gas pipeline, Tasnim Aslam refuted the impression Pakistan is not serious in the project. She said Iran is well-aware of Pakistan's stance.
On the question of mass deportation of Pakistanis from UK, she said Pakistan and European Union signed the Readmission Agreement, under which Pakistan is ready to accept illegal Pakistanis residing in EU and UK.
She, however, rejected the notion if there are mass deportations of Pakistanis.
Regarding the expected meeting of Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif and President Barack Obama on the sidelines of International Security Summit in The Hague this month, the spokesperson said no formal meetings have been scheduled bilaterally.
On Afghan presidential elections, Tasnim Aslam said it is Afghan government's decision not to allow their refugees residing in Pakistan to participate in the elections.
She said had Afghan government requested Pakistan would have extended all possible cooperation for polling in Pakistan.
She said certain timelines were agreed between Pakistan and India on the sidelines of SAARC Business Conclave about granting NDMA status and the two sides will exchange status when the commitments are honored.
To question about Director General IAEA visit, the spokesperson said Yukiya Amano has expressed complete confidence in the safety and security of our nuclear installations.
She told DG IAEA visited Chashma nuclear power plant on Wednesday and was impressed with in place security measures. She said Pakistan has long-standing cooperation with IAEA in the field of safety and all our nuclear facilities are under IAEA safeguard.
The spokesperson said Pakistan will endeavor to strengthen its ties with all GCC countries in all the fields particularly in trade and energy. She said an issue emerged between two countries of GCC is their internal matter.
Earlier, Tasnim Aslam informed that PM's Advisor Foreign Affairs Sartaj Aziz met UK's International Development Secretary Justine Greening, Home Secretary Theresa May and Defence Secretary Philip Hammond during his visit to London to review Enhanced Strategic Dialogue.
She said Secretary Greening appreciated the concrete steps taken by the present Pakistan government in the areas of tax collection and economic reforms.
Tasnim Aslam said UK Secretary Theresa May lauded Pakistan's new internal security policy and offered her country's support for its timely and effective implementation.
She said Sartaj Aziz and Defence Secretary Hammond discussed post-NATO withdrawal scenario in Afghanistan and its implications for the region besides Pakistan-UK defense cooperation.
She said the two sides expressed satisfaction over cooperation under the framework of Enhanced Strategic Dialogue and hoped that the targets set under the framework would be achieved within the given time frame
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Right Vision News. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>