<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8D22-00AE-8BAF-B565"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Not your typical tip Not your typical tip</title><source>The Press (Christchurch, New Zealand)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Kate Valley landfill has made the headlines recently as the home of Christchurch's asbestos. Reporter RACHEL YOUNG discovers there is a lot more to this dump.
--------------------
BY THE NUMBERS Since it opened in 2005, 2.32 million tonnes of waste has been disposed of.
In excess of 290,000 tonnes will be processed at the end of this financial year.
Total site is about 1000ha, of which 37ha is the landfill.
On a busy day up to 1200 tonnes can be processed.
Total refuse capacity about 10.5 million tonnes.
About 2500 cubic metres per hour of methane gas is produced.
--------------------
To the naked eye, the landfill looks like part of the valley.
The first sign something is different is a faint anti- odour spray dispersing across the site.
"Most people that come out here they can't see it [the landfill]. It's not like a traditional tip," Canterbury Waste Service regional manager Rangi Lord says.
"Nothing gets out of here without us knowing about it."
Welcome to Kate Valley, the North Canterbury landfill, home to 2.32 million tonnes of waste.
Lord is correct. This certainly is not a typical tip.
Modern methods of disposal (more about that later) mean it's hard to detect any waste, let alone smell it.
Lord's sense of smell, however, is highly tuned. With one quick sniff he can tell what's being dumped.
Transpacific Industries NZ and five local councils - Christchurch City, Hurunui, Waimakariri, Selwyn and Ashburton - formed a public-private partnership, Transwaste Canterbury, to develop and run the Kate Valley landfill with the rest owned by Canterbury Waste Services.
Chinese state-owned Beijing Capital Group bought Transpacific Industries NZ recently.
However, Transwaste Canterbury chairman Gill Cox says it will be business as usual for the landfill.
Waste from all five councils is dumped there, including asbestos and to guarantee no harmful fibres of the deadly substance blow away its handling is meticulously managed.
A worker in full protective gear, including a respirator, removes the hatch on the truck's trailer.
A large grey blob - bagged asbestos - slithers its way into a hole after its release and another operator quickly covers it with dirt and waste. The whole operation takes barely two minutes.
Nearby an operator notes down its location and its logged into a global positioning system.
It's all designed to ensure the asbestos stays there in perpetuity.
Canterbury District Health Board medical officer of health Alistair Humphrey says asbestos is not harmful once buried, and WorkSafe New Zealand say this method of disposal is best practice.
Lord says most people think waste is dumped and left exposed.
This is not the case.
If something is even slightly off, such as an increase in temperatures or water levels, Lord is automatically sent a text message prompting him to check the systems.
A stone's throw away, a piece of North Canterbury land known as Tiromoana Bush covers Kate Valley from the landfill to the coast.
It's 410 hectares of "scenic New Zealand" that Transwaste plans to protect forever. The bush has been secured by a QEII National Trust open space covenant.
A publicly accessible loop track from the carpark takes walkers to a clifftop lookout overlooking the Pacific Ocean.
"I'd live out here, even though it's right beside a landfill," Lord says while surveying the vista.
However, it will never be developed into housing as the company has a long-term plan to ensure native forest and wetland species are introduced to support the land's natural regeneration.
The walkway, which takes about four hours to complete, snakes down to a developed wetland.
Lord proudly points out native species and where more planting is being done as he refills the free pamphlet display.
He says protecting the environment and being sustainable is vital.
The business has plans to become more sustainable by producing its own energy.
Lord explains as the waste decomposes, it produces leachate and methane gas.
Currently, the gas is collected and burnt, but later this year some will start being used to power a gas energy system for the site.
Eventually it will generate enough power for itself, and a few thousand homes.
One day he hopes to sell the energy into the local grid, as it will produce gas for several decades from now.
Kate Valley has a 35-year consent with about 27 years to go. But filling the site could take less time.
"Our tonnes are certainly on the rise because of the increased activity in Canterbury," Lord says.
Eventually, the whole landfill will be full. Then, it will be covered with grass and return to looking like North Canterbury country.
Lord muses it could be used by future generations for conservation and recreation with families one day having picnics on top of what is currently the landfill before taking a walk to the edge of the country.
--------------------
CAPTION:
Scenic salvation: The lookout point of the Tiromoana Bush Walkway, where walkers can look out over the Pacific Ocean.
Picture: JOHN KIRK-ANDERSON/FAIRFAX NZ
Nose for waste: Rangi Lord on the Tiromoana Bush Walkway at the Kate Valley landfill site.
Gone for good: A load of asbestos is unloaded at the Kate Valley landfill site in North Canterbury.
Toned down: Anti-odour spray stops any smell from the landfill drifting to the public roads
]]></text></news-item>