<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8E91-2E66-8C1B-E129"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Danone rises on high volatility</title><source>News Bites - Western Europe: France</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Danone (FR:BN), France's largest food producer company by market capitalisation, traded between an intraday low of EUR49.06 and a high of EUR49.92. The price range has expanded in the last two days (from 72.0c two days ago to 85.50c today) which, accompanied by a price rise, is a bullish signal. The average daily volatility of 1.6% places the stock in the 3rd quartile in the market meaning it is mildly volatile. Today its volatility (highest price minus lowest price/lowest price) of 1.7% was 1.7 times the average daily volatility of 1.6%, up from 1.3% on Thursday and 1.5% on Wednesday. A price rise on high volatility is a bullish signal. The stock price increased 38.50c (or 0.8%) to close at EUR49.87, ending a five-day streak of losses. Compared with the CAC 40 Index which fell 27.0 points (or 0.6%) in the day, this represented a relative price increase of 1.4%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Danone, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051811940314211
Bullish SignalsOversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The Stochastic indicator of 14.6 has pierced the oversold line of 20.
Bearish Signals- The price decreased 1.3% in the last week and 0.9% in the last month. - In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week low four times, pointing to a downtrend. - The 2.8% premium to 12-month low of EUR48.50 against the 17.5% discount to high of EUR60.45 suggests the stock continues to push for new lows. - The present value of EUR1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Danone is EUR898, for a capital loss of EUR102.

NoteBeta: the Beta of Danone stock is 0.3. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market.
AGGREGATE VOLUMES, PRICES AND TURNOVER PERIOD [Volume Index or VI in brackets; 1 is average] Paris: BN.FR 288,979 [VI of 0.2] volume 96.481% of aggregate. Price: EUR49.87. Hamburg: BSN.HAM 10,171 [VI of 8.1] volume 3.396% of aggregate. Price: EUR49.93. SIX Swiss: DAN.SIX 330 [VI of 0.9] volume 0.11% of aggregate. Price: CHF59.75. Using the current exchange rate of CHF1 equals 0.824EUR, The shares are at a 1.3% discount to the close price in Paris. Aggregate volume: there were 299,480 shares of Danone worth EUR14.9 million traded. The aggregate volume was 0.2 times average trading of 1.5 million shares.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 12: Danone Announces Global Partnership Between Activia And Shakira For Its New 'Dare To Feel Good' Campaign[Company Release]Today sees the launch of Activia's exciting partnership with global icon, Shakira, as the Colombian-born superstar supports the yogurt brand's new 'Dare to Feel Good' campaign. The international collaboration will bring to life Activia's 'Feeling Good Starts from Within' initiative with a new dance-themed creative that celebrates making inner health and well-being.Filmed in Barcelona, the new TV advertisement features Shakira in a fantasy forest where she is showered with swirls of gold stardust and is seen dancing to express how good she feels inside.
March 06: Danone: Information on the total number of voting rights and shares[News Story]
http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/France/Stock/News/17290.pdfSource: NYSE Euronext
February 20: Danone: 2013 Full-Year Results[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/France/Stock/News/17046.htmlSource: NYSE Euronext
February 11: DANONE : Danone raises its stake in China's leading dairy company Mengniu[News Story]Danone raises its stake in China's leading dairy company MengniuDanone today announced an agreement, together with COFCO Dairy Investments, to subscribe a reserved rights issue by China's leading dairy company Mengniu, raising its interest in this company from 4.0% to 9.9% for an investment of EUR486 million[1].The transaction makes Danone the second largest shareholder in Mengniu, and follows on from agreements signed on May 20, 2013 with Mengniu and with COFCO, China's largest state-owned food company.In parallel, COFCO, Danone and Arla - Mengniu's three core shareholders - will combine their stakes (16.3%, 9.9% and 5.3%, respectively) within COFCO Dairy Investments, a jointly-owned company pooling all three shareholders' interests in the governance of Mengniu.The transaction is subject to the approval of Mengniu's shareholders, and is expected to be finalized within the next few months.[1] At an exchange rate of EUR0.0942/HK$ 1.00Source: NYSE Euronext
January 16: Danone : Implementation of a liquidity contract[News Story]As of January 17th, 2014 and for a period of one year automatically renewable, DANONE requested ROTHSCHILD & CIE BANQUE to implement a liquidity contract in accordance with the Charter of ethics established by the AMAFI and approved by the decision of the AMF March 21st, 2011.
January 09: Danone : Information on the total number of voting rights and shares[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/France/Stock/News/16150.pdfSource: NYSE Euronext
January 08: Danone sets terms for continued partnership with Fonterra and initiates legal proceedings[News Story]
Paris, January 8, 2014 -- On August 2, 2013, Fonterra issued an alert concerning a possible contamination of certain ingredients supplied to Danone. Additional tests revealed later on that it was in fact a false alert.This affair illustrates serious failings on Fonterra's part in applying the quality standards required in the food industry.Danone is terminating its existing supply contract with Fonterra and making any further collaboration contingent on a commitment by its supplier to full transparency and compliance with the cutting-edge food safety procedures applied to all products supplied to Danone.Danone is also initiating proceedings in the New Zealand High Court, as well as arbitration proceedings in Singapore to bring all facts to light and to obtain compensation for the harm it has suffered.As a leading food company, Danone makes food safety an absolute priority and is committed to working only with suppliers that share and respect the same demanding professional standards.Source: NYSE Euronext
ISIN: FR0000120644
FR:BN; EPA:BN; PA:BN; FP:BN
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>