<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8EAA-C96A-0736-2532"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Haze worsens in 14 areas</title><source>New Straits Times (Malaysia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[THE haze enveloping the country has worsened in several areas With the Air Pollutant Index (API) in Port Klang breaching the "very unhealthy" level at 233, as of 5pm yesterday.
The API also reached "unhealthy" levels in 13 other areas, namely Banting (189), Kuala Selangor (179), Nilai (172), Putrajaya (168), Batu Muda (163), Petaling Jaya (159), Shah Alam (150), Seremban (141), Port Dickson (137), Cheras (137), Bukit Rambai (128), Tanjung Malim (120) and Malacca town (109).
Nineteen other areas recorded moderate readings.
This has prompted the natural resources and environment ministry to impose a ban on open burning in Negri Sembilan, Malacca, Kuala Lumpur and Putrajaya With immediate effect. The ban had earlier been imposed in Selangor.
Its minister, Datuk Seri G. Palaniel, said the ban Would not involve cremation, burning related to religion, grills or barbecues and gas flaring.
"Following this, all parties are advised not to engage in open burning or allow their land or premises to be trespassed by any irresponsible parties leading to open burning either intentionally or unintentionally," he said in a statement here.
An API reading of 0 to 50 is categorised as good, 51 200 is unhealthy, 201 to 2 300 is very unhealthy and to 100 is moderate, 101 to 300 and above is hazardous.
Palanivel said anyone found guilty of open burning could be jailed up to five years, or fined up to RM500,000, or both, while the maximum compound for each offence is RM2,000.
The Fire and Rescue Department had recorded 6,377 cases of open burning, bush and peat fires in Selangor, Johor, Kelantan and Perak since March 1.
However, the total number of fires dropped to 478 cases yesterday from 643 cases on Wednesday.
Malaysian Meteorological Department (MMD) director-general Datuk Che Gayah Ismail assured that seeding operations which had been put on hold, would he conducted by this Week.
She said the operation that was initially planned to be conducted on Monday was suspended as the military aircraft for the exercise were being utilised for the search-and-rescue operation to locate the missing Malaysia Airlines aircraft.
She added that the increasing API readings in several parts of the country yesterday were caused by local sources.
MMD said heavy rain was expected during the inter-monsoon season from mid-March to early May, that would put an end to the hot and dry spell.
( END )
]]></text></news-item>