<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8EEF-6E5D-F65A-B344"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Search for parole violator leads police to drug stash; East Williamson residence was raided during search for felony parole violator</title><source>Williamson Daily News (West Virginia)</source><author>Rachel Dove rbaldwin@civitasmedia.com</author><text><![CDATA[By Rachel Dove
rbaldwin@civitasmedia.com
EAST WILLIAMSON - What began as a search to apprehend a West Virginia State Prison parole violator resulted not only in his capture, but also the discovery of a large amount of street drugs that had been packaged and was ready for sale.
State probation officers Rebecca Harrison, Jonathan Tackett and Josh Croft, who work out of the Logan office, came to Mingo County on Thursday with a warrant for the arrest of Eugene Carl Likens, 29, who was wanted for failure to report. The probation officers were accompanied by Williamson Police Chief Barry Blair, Sgt. John Hall, Patrolmen Jerrod Marcum and Josh Tincher, State Police Trooper D.M. Williamson and Mingo County Sheriff 's Deputy Cpl. Norman Mines, to an East Williamson residence where they had been told the wanted man was staying.
The officers were granted entry by Tasha Renee Mitchem, 25, of Williamson, whose relative had leased the property. Mitchem at that time chose not to disclose the location where Likens was hiding. After a short search, the defendant was discovered cowering inside a crawl space in the utility room of the rented apartment. During the search for the fugitive, the large stash of illegal drugs was uncovered.
According to the counts released by the arresting officers, they confiscated 36 bags of crack cocaine and 63 bags of cocaine that was believed to have been laced with heroin. The drugs will be sent to the West Virginia Crime Lab for a complete analysis. An assortment of prescription pills also was discovered during the search, hidden inside a diaper bag.
Mitchem, who was also on probation for a previous crime, was taken into custody for violating her parole by being in contact with convicted felons and associating with drug trafficking.
"I am glad to see these defendants taken into custody and off the streets," Blair said. "We're putting a dent in the drug trade, one arrest at a time. The drugs we confiscated today show we're definitely on the right path."
"We have a long battle ahead of us but we're up to the fight," Mines said.
Blair expressed his appreciation for the support the Williamson Police Department had received from the state police and the sheriff's department.
The investigation into these arrests continues, and may produce additional arrests. Drug charges are expected to be filed against Likens and Mitchem.
]]></text></news-item>