<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8FBE-085A-A154-F717"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>The poor man's Las Vegas</title><source>The Toronto Star</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The sign on the window promises "fun and games." But inside the slot-machine arcade, it looks more like compulsion and mundane clerical work.
Behind the colourfully painted plate-glass window, it's impossible to tell if it's three in the morning or the afternoon. Apart from the faint strains of light rock music and an overriding mechanical hum, it's silent.
Presiding over the fun is 28-year-old Ayesha, a bleached-blond German of Turkish origin who declined to give her last name to avoid trouble with her boss. It's like this day in and day out, she says.
"A lot of people in this neighbourhood are unemployed. After the first of the month, when the unemployment cheques come out, that's when we get a crowd."
Described as "poor but sexy" by Mayor Klaus Wowerheit, the German capital is home to some 600 gambling arcades, 300 sports betting houses and around 2,500 café-casinos, according to police.
Nearly 20,000 of Germany's more than 100,000 gambling addicts are in Berlin, according to Caritas International.
Tough regulations designed to protect gambling addicts from themselves - including a rule against opening a new gambling outlet within 500 metres of an existing one - have failed to make a dent.
Across the southern district of Neukoelln, home to many immigrants, betting shops, gambling arcades and café-casinos line blocks of major thoroughfares.
"I never saw this many gambling shops until I moved to Berlin," says Ayesha, whose arcade is across the street from three sports betting shops and two more arcades.
During a recent crackdown, Berlin police found that a whopping 90 per cent of the city's gambling shops violated tough regulations adopted in May 2011, says Wolfgang Petersen, head of the department's gambling wing.
"Berlin is Las Vegas for poor people," Petersen said.
The authorities continually monitor Berlin's few full-service casinos. But there are too many slot-machine arcades and sports betting shops for regulators to visit frequently, according to Germany's federal association of private casinos.
"Operators of arcades feel they are unobserved, so many of them violate the regulations," Miriam Benert, a spokeswoman for the association, said in an email. "This only comes to light once the police conduct a surprise raid."
Police say the arcades are guilty of more than just minor infractions.
In addition to around 2,000 violations of the new gambling rules - which prohibit smoking and the consumption of alcohol in gambling outlets, for example - the police have filed another 1,500 cases of robbery, assault, money laundering and drug-dealing connected with gambling outlets.
Gambling hall workers such as Mustapha, a 50-year-old employee at another Neukoelln arcade who also declined to give his full name, say the stricter regulations have had little impact.
"Sometimes they lose and sometimes they win," he says. "But almost no one takes his winnings and goes home. It's a sickness, like drugs."
Jason Overdorf is a reporter for GlobalPost.
]]></text></news-item>