<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="8FEF-84C8-63CC-F8AC"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>WORD FROM THE WEB</title><source>The Sentinel (Stoke)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[RAPIST Solomon Smith claimed his human rights had been violated after he was forced to share a cell with a smoker for a week. He argued it breached his privacy and damaged his health and took his case to court (Sentinel, March 12).
The Human Rights Laws are for the benefit of the legal professionals. Any citizen with a modicum of common sense would not give this 'victim' the time of day, and yet our powdered wig-wearing snout in trough elite see fit to take up the fight of this lowlife, for a publicly funded fee of course.
hardship I would have thought that the smoker would have more of an objection to having to share a cell with a sick, twisted pervert.
stanley10 Strange how he didn't consider his victims' human rights.
caz112 ALMOST £31 million of Government cash has been secured to help create 20,000 thousand jobs and cut energy bills for residents and businesses. But the City Deal cash falls well short of the £1 billion requested last year to create 31,000 jobs (Sentinel, March 12).
'... Reduce bills for people in up to 1,000 homes in the Hanley area'. What a surprise.
Six_Towns Wishful thinking and spin from a few people with tarnished reputations in the area. With 20,000 jobs being created and an official unemployment rate for North Staffordshire at 10,439 and falling (source: ONS/Sentinel) are we lead to believe that SOT is to exceed 100% employment rates in the near future. Maybe some of the allocated re-training money could be used to teach people maths and statistics so that we can get accurate numbers.
Frameworks Media COUNCIL leaders are set to ignore a 15,500-name petition against cuts to youth services. Staffordshire County Council is planning to press ahead with its shake-up of youth provision (Sentinel, March 12).
The Conservatives are the ruling party at the county council. At this moment in time they are making the decisions. Think on in the election to come.
bond1 The Staffordshire county councillors seem unable to learn from previous mistakes, but I'm thinking they will be made to pay for this massive mistake.
The youth of today is the future of tomorrow. It is a proven fact that youth services are invaluable to each community.
Booboobunny NOW JOIN THE DEBATE ONLINE www.thesentinel.co.uk
]]></text></news-item>