<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9041-075B-6D87-4684"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Davis LLP Reinforces Market-Leading Expertise With the Addition of Prominent Litigator</title><source>Marketwired</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[VANCOUVER, BRITISH COLUMBIA--(Marketwired - March 14, 2014) - One of Canada's leading class action litigators, David Neave, joins Davis LLP's Vancouver office as a partner in the Litigation & Dispute Resolution and International Risk Management Practice Groups. David's significant experience in competition-restraint of trade, products liability, securities and consumer class actions as well as in other complicated cases will reinforce Davis' reputation as the firm of choice for significant and complex cases.
"David is a great addition to the Davis team," said Rob Seidel, Q.C., Firm Managing Partner of Davis LLP. "His extensive experience and deep legal knowledge give him a unique perspective, which is invaluable to our clients' needs when faced with complex and high risk litigation."
David has acted on some of the most notable cases in the country. His recent work includes representing an international manufacturer of computer memory chips on conspiracy price fixing allegations, two international airlines in consumer class actions, international pharmaceutical and medical products companies in products liability actions, the leading conducted energy weapons manufacturer in a variety of inquiries and civil actions as well as a credit card company with respect to credit card fees.
Prior to practising law, David enjoyed a 20-year career with the Royal Canadian Mounted Police. As part of its commercial crime section for 11 years, he conducted stock market manipulation investigations and a variety of complex fraud and theft investigations. Just before leaving the RCMP, he acted as in-house counsel to the senior management of the RCMP in British Columbia.
David is recognized as a leading litigator in Chambers Global, (Dispute Resolution: Class Action (Defence)), The Canadian Legal Lexpert Directory (Class Actions), The Best Lawyers in Canada (Class Action Litigation & Corporate and Commercial Litigation), Benchmark Litigation (Class Actions, Securities, Competition, Product Liability, White Collar Crime and nominated for Litigator of the Year in BC in 2014), and Who's Who Legal (Life Sciences -Products Liability).
Davis continues to make strategic investments that enhance the firm's provision of legal services. David's addition reinforces this commitment of excellence to clients and boosts the firm's reputation as a sophisticated litigation firm.
About Davis LLP
Davis LLP is a full-service national law firm with over 250 lawyers across Canada and in Tokyo, Japan(1). The firm has well-known and respected capabilities in core legal services, and is a leader in a number of niche markets. Davis LLP is described by Chambers Global as "a lean outfit that punches above its weight." The firm acts for Canadian and international clients, and is often involved in complex matters with an international dimension. For more information about Davis LLP, visit www.davis.ca.
/T/
---------- (1) Through its associate office, Davis & Takahashi.
/T/
]]></text></news-item>