<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="90BB-BE17-23C4-E981"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Today in History</title><source>The Westerly Sun (Rhode Island)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Today is Sunday, March 16, the 75th day of 2014. There are 290 days left in the year.
Today's Highlight in History: On March 16, 1964, President Lyndon B. Johnson sent Congress the Economic Opportunity Act of 1964 as part of his War on Poverty. (The measure was passed by Congress, and was signed by Johnson in August 1964.) On this date:
In A.D. 37, Roman emperor Tiberius died; he was succeeded by Caligula.
In 1521, Portuguese navigator Ferdinand Magellan reached the Philippines, where he was killed by natives the following month.
In 1751, James Madison, fourth president of the United States, was born in Port Conway, Va.
In 1802, President Thomas Jefferson signed a measure authorizing the establishment of the U.S. Military Academy at West Point, N.Y.
In 1894, the opera "Thais," composed by Jules Massenet, premiered in Paris.
In 1926, rocket science pioneer Robert H. Goddard successfully tested the first liquid-fueled rocket in Auburn, Mass.
In 1935, Adolf Hitler decided to break the military terms set by the Treaty of Versailles by ordering the rearming of Germany.
In 1945, during World War II, American forces declared they had secured Iwo Jima, although pockets of Japanese resistance remained.
In 1968, during the Vietnam War, the My Lai Massacre of Vietnamese civilians was carried out by U.S. Army troops; estimates of the death toll vary between 347 and 504.
In 1994, figure skater Tonya Harding pleaded guilty in Portland, Ore., to conspiracy to hinder prosecution for covering up an attack on rival Nancy Kerrigan, avoiding jail but drawing a $100,000 fine.
Ten years ago: China declared victory in its fight against bird flu, saying it had "stamped out" all its known cases.
Five years ago: Joining a wave of public anger, President Barack Obama blistered insurance giant AIG for "recklessness and greed" for handing its executives $165 million in bonuses after taking billions in federal bailout money.
One year ago: Police said a Swiss woman who was on a cycling trip in central India with her husband was gangraped by eight men; the reported attack came three months after the fatal gangrape of a woman aboard a New Delhi bus outraged Indians.
]]></text></news-item>