<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="91C7-3FF3-FC01-4937"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>OUR TOWNS: LI NOW</title><source>Newsday (New York)</source><author>PATRICK WHITTLE; MITCHELL FREEDMAN; AISHA AL-MUSLIM; SID CASSESE</author><text><![CDATA[FREEPORT
Information seminar
today on storm water
Operation SPLASH plans to host a seminar about Long Island storm water today.
The program, "Storm Water Solutions for Long Island," will focus on the quality of water that regional tributaries contribute to Long Island bays and wetlands, organizers said.
Operation SPLASH is a volunteer group that advocates for coastal environmental preservation on Long Island.
Greg Kent, president of California-based Modular Wetland Systems and Bio-Clean Environmental Services, is the event's scheduled main speaker.
"This is a unique opportunity to obtain valuable insight on applications available for stormwater pollution," organizers said in a statement.
The event will take place at Operation SPLASH offices, 202 Woodcleft Ave. in Freeport from 12:30 to 3 p.m.
It is free and open to the public, and lunch will be served, organizers said.
- PATRICK WHITTLE
RIVERHEAD
Alternate power OK'd on town-owned acres
Riverhead officials have given seven companies permission to use town land to operate alternate power-generating facilities, although the actual decision on whether any of those projects will be built will be up to the Long Island Power Authority.
The town board, at a special meeting yesterday, voted to accept requests for proposals to build solar or other sustainable energy projects on a portion of a 95-acre site at the town-owned Enterprise Park at Calverton planned for energy development, or on a now-capped town landfill. "It gives them the ability to file proposals with the Long Island Power Authority," Supervisor Sean Walter said.
Several other Long Island towns are also offering property that could be developed, and any decision on which of those plans is accepted will depend, in part, on the price of producing electricity.
Riverhead officials are interested in the project because renting out the town-owned land is a potential source of revenue for the town.
- MITCHELL FREEDMAN
LONG BEACH
Financial seminar
focuses on youth
STW Advocacy for at Risk Youth Inc., in partnership with three local churches, plans to host a financial empowerment seminar in Long Beach to raise economic consciousness among parents and youth tomorrow.
The free event is scheduled from 10 a.m. to 1 p.m. at the Christian Light Missionary Baptist Church's Margaret Evans Community Center, at 620 Rev. JJ Evans Blvd. in Long Beach.
Donations will be accepted for the event, which is open to Long Beach and surrounding communities, including Freeport, Roosevelt and Uniondale.
"We believe that 'financial education' is a major key to the educational process to achieving a breakthrough with our youth," group founder Sueveria J. Vann said in a statement.
New York Life Insurance Co. is the sponsor, along with Christian Light Missionary Baptist Church, Evangel Revival Community Church and New Life Church of Christ.
The nonprofit group's mission is to empower youth by providing scholarships to college and trade school students, holding youth dialogue sessions on topics concerning youth, and introducing youth and adults to career opportunities.
For more information, call Vann at 516-564-0455 or marketing chairman Nicole Burke at 516-564-3272.
- AISHA AL-MUSLIM
ROCKVILLE CENTRE
St. Pat's parade
set for March 22
The 18th Annual Rockville Centre St. Patrick's Parade, one of Long Island's largest, starts at noon March 22 and travels from municipal parking field 12 at Sunrise Highway and North Forest Avenue to parking field 2, at North Centre Avenue and Washington Street.
"It's a wonderful feeling to see all of our residents and businesses out in full force celebrating while giving back to three worthy causes," said village Mayor Francis X. Murray.
The parade, based in the Long Island headquarters for the Roman Catholic Church, shares its success with three charities with national, Irish and village focuses.
Last year it raised $70,000 through its pre-parade dinner, where advertisements, merchandise and sponsorships are sold. The parade holds other fundraising events throughout the year.
Rockville Centre's parade has become one of the most successful and well-attended in the state, Murray said, adding that the event is not only a source of cultural pride, but also civic pride.
This year's grand marshal is longtime Rockville Centre resident Sean O'Rourke, who emigrated from Ireland's County Galway in 1971 at age 19. He is president of Coastline International Distributors Ltd., which serves the airline and aerospace industries and had sales of about $4.4 million last year.
For more information about the parade, visit its website at rvcstpatrick.com.
- SID CASSESE
]]></text></news-item>