<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="91CA-952A-36E7-64CF"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>NH attorney's harassment claims likely not crimes</title><source>Associated Press State &amp; Local</source><author>LYNNE TUOHY, Associated Press</author><text><![CDATA[CONCORD, N.H. (AP) - Accusations of a longstanding culture of sexual harassment prosecutors say permeated the Rockingham County attorney's office are outrageous but probably not criminal, according to the director of the New Hampshire Coalition Against Domestic and Sexual Violence.
Attorney General Joseph Foster is seeking to remove Jim Reams from his elected post - four months after stripping him of his duties amid a joint state and federal investigation into sexual harassment and financial mismanagement.
In a lengthy complaint filed in Merrimack County Superior Court last week, Foster said Reams has sexually harassed female employees since taking office in 1999. Reams has denied the allegations.
Coalition director Lyn Schollett said sexual harassment is not a crime but is handled through civil rights actions and administrative sanction. Schollett - a lawyer - said the exception is when the harassment includes unwanted touching, which rises to the level of criminal assault. But if the inappropriate touching - and Foster details two such incidents - occurred more than five years ago, it falls beyond the deadline for bringing criminal charges.
Schollett is not surprised Reams' alleged harassment went on so long, saying women were put in the untenable position of safeguarding their jobs.
"Because of the potential for retaliation - which was blatant - women may have chosen to keep their jobs rather than raise these issues," Schollett said. "Women shouldn't be forced to choose between a safe workplace and a paycheck, and Reams made them do that."
There were exceptions, Foster's complaint makes clear. Within three months of taking office, a female employee complained of sexual harassment to then-Attorney General Phil McLaughlin. Reams adamantly denied the allegations and acknowledged no wrongdoing.
Based on his investigation, Foster wrote, the "inappropriate behavior never abated."
The current investigation was triggered by a sexual harassment complaint filed in October and has turned up evidence Reams mishandled state and federal funds, including federal forfeiture money. The allegations of financial improprieties could trigger criminal charges.
"If you're managing funds given to you in trust for a specific program and you recklessly spend the money on other things, that's a violation of the theft statute," said Attorney David Ruoff, a former prosecutor. He said the crime is called "theft by misapplication of property" and whether it rises to the level of a felony depends on the amount of money involved. It's typically applied to public employees and investment counselors.
Reams' lawyer, Michael Ramsdell, stressed that despite a lengthy probe, no criminal charges have been brought.
"I certainly would like to think that, when they looked at all the evidence in their investigation, they determined that criminal charges were not warranted," Ramsdell said.
Foster's complaint paints a picture of an office where Reams made vulgar comments to staffers, demonstrated inappropriate behavior including touching a woman's blouse where a button was undone and rubbing the thigh of a female employee at a domestic violence conference. Foster said he also discriminated and retaliated against staffers who became pregnant. His repeated actions earned him the nickname "creepy Uncle Jim" among women in the office, the complaint states.
U.S. Attorney John Kacavas declined to comment on whether the conduct described in the complaint is sufficient to justify a federal civil rights case.
Foster stressed at the outset of his 25-page complaint that more evidence against Reams will come out at trial.
Both sides are scheduled to return to court April 7.
]]></text></news-item>