<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="922F-F22D-FA29-34CF"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Tit-for-tat expulsions</title><source>Sunday Tribune (South Africa)</source><author> Peter Fabricius</author><text><![CDATA[Rwandan and Burundian diplomats co-ordinated "organised criminal networks" in an assassination campaign against Rwandan dissidents in South Africa, said the Department of International Relations and Co-operation.
In its first official comment on the row over the expulsions of Rwandan, Burundian and South African diplomats, the department raised the number of Rwandan diplomats South Africa had expelled from three to four, plus a Burundian.
The expulsions last week were precipitated by yet another attempt to kill former Rwandan army chief of staff General Faustin Kayumba Nyamwasa on March 4, at a safe house in Joburg where he and his family were under South African government protection.
The statement by department spokesman Clayson Monyela also mentioned the murder of former Rwanda intelligence chief, Colonel Patrick Karegyeya, in a Joburg hotel on December 31 last year and previous attempts against Nyamwasa's life in 2010.
Rwanda retaliated by expelling six South African diplomats. The country's foreign minister, Louise Mushikiwabo, said on Twitter this was in response to the expulsion of Rwanda's diplomats but also for South Africa harbouring Rwandans responsible for terrorist attacks.
Mushikiwabo accused the Rwandan dissidents in South Africa of working in "close collaboration" with the FDLR - founded by Hutus who participated in the genocide against the Tutsis in 1994 - to carry out a spate of grenade attacks in Rwanda in recent years.
These "terrorists" were being protected by the South African government and "despite repeated promises from Pretoria, the problem was not resolved", the foreign minister said.
Justice Minister Jeff Radebe confirmed this week that the Rwandan and Burundian diplomats had been expelled for breaching diplomatic conventions by engaging in illegal acts related to murder and attempted murder of Rwandans in South Africa.
Detailing the attacks on Nyamwasa and Karegyeya, Monyela said: "There have been sustained and organised efforts to kill some of the refugees living in the republic."
These attacks "undermined our national security, territorial integrity and put South Africans in harm's way. For these reasons, South Africa expelled four Rwandan diplomats and one from Burundi".
"The action we took targeted only those who violated Vienna Convention Article 41 and our own Diplomatic Immunities and Privileges Act."
Though officials had indicated Pretoria was considering further action such as recalling its high commissioner to Rwanda, George Twala, Monyela's statement gave no indication of this.
"The South African government regrets that the Rwandan government reciprocated disproportionately by expelling all our diplomats except the ambassador, making the work of our mission in Rwanda difficult as it cannot discharge its services that our people and Rwandans normally receive.
"The South African government sends a stern warning that action will be taken against any individual or group that abuses the human rights dispensation of the republic.
"We remain steadfast in ensuring our territory is not used as a launch pad for any form of attack, including terrorist activities against any member of the international community. In the same vein, we will continue to act against those who abuse relations, diplomatic immunities and privileges.
"We appreciate the understanding and co-operation received from the government of Burundi and commit to sustaining this collaboration with a view to getting to the bottom of this matter," Monyela said.
That appeared to provide confirmation of reports that the Burundi government had arrested its expelled first secretary Jean-Claude Sindayigaya on his return to Bujumbura and that President Jean-Pierre Nkurunziza had called President Jacob Zuma to apologise for Sindayigaya's behaviour. "
]]></text></news-item>