<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9244-E3B1-DE0C-82D3"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>'Take children skiing in term time and we'll pay the fine'; Holiday firm offers parents 'bribe' to go on a family holiday in the off-peak season</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Daily Telegraph Reporter</author><text><![CDATA[A SKI holiday company is offering to pay fines for parents who take their children away during term time.
MountainBase has advertised its offer on Facebook - and admits its deal would encourage parents to break the law.
In its advertisement, the firm says: "Are Schools in the UK taking the piste? We think so! So we have a special offer... Book a week with children at Mountain-Base [and] if you receive a fine from your school/local authority we will pay it on copy of a receipt from yourselves."
The Bedford-based operator selling skiing holidays in the French Alps offers all-inclusive holidays starting at £199 per person in the off-peak season. But it said it is forced to put its prices up by almost 50 per cent during the peak season.
The firm's owner, Lee Quince, thinks Britain is falling behind in winter sports events because so few children have a chance to try skiing and other snow activities. Mr Quince, who said that "ultimately the decision was down to parents", added: "It is a bribe. We could offer to pay [parents'] fines, or ski passes - it is a financial incentive and the lowest risk to us as a business. It is not guaranteed parents will be fined but there is a comfort factor if we are offering to pay for it."
This week a report revealed that the number of parents fined for taking their children out of school for a holiday rose by more than 70 per cent last year, after the Government hardened its stance on the issue.
Nearly 5,300 fines were imposed during last year's autumn term, across 34 councils, according to research conducted by the BBC. Mr Quince said: "The Government was targeting compulsive truants but has hit innocent families who just want to teach their kids how to ski."
He added: "People accuse us of ripping families off by charging higher prices in school holidays but we are actually just balancing our books.
"From the perspective of a ski company in the Alps, this year there are three weeks of holidays across the whole of the season out of 21 weeks. If we get the majority of our bookings in those three weeks we have to balance our costs for the weeks we don't get any bookings."
A Department for Education spokesman said: "Parents should never simply discount a possible penalty notice from the cost of a cheaper holiday.
"Taking children out of school without permission for a holiday is a criminal offence. Children who attend school regularly are nearly four times more likely to get five or more good GCSEs than those who are regularly absent."
Christine Blower, the general secretary of the National Union of Teachers, said: "Rather than encouraging parents to take their children out of school it would be more helpful for companies not to increase their costs during the school holiday period."
]]></text></news-item>