<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9296-B9D6-33BE-2B46"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Regulating wage gap risks promoting mediocrity</title><source>Business Day (South Africa)</source><author>Mark Barnes</author><text><![CDATA[Regulating wage gap risks promoting mediocrity
NEW legislation is being considered in Brussels which, if enacted, would allow shareholders to vote on the ratio of executive to worker pay. That's the wrong focal point. It is not about different rates of creating wealth. The real debate should be about the retention of wealth among the so very few versus its deployment for the benefit of the many. And, of course, education, education, education.
There can be no doubt that the disparity between the rich and poor is growing ever wider. This is not sustainable beyond a point, and it is certainly not self-correcting. Just as the vicious circle of poverty caves in on itself, so the circle of wealth may spin out of control. Something has to be done, but it's complicated.
Soon after the global financial crisis which they nearly caused in 2008, all bonus-greedy bankers were put on notice. Governments and central banks warned that their extravagances were no longer palatable and that they should somehow limit their intergalactic bonuses or at least let them bear some relation to their planetary salaries. Much fuss was made over this rap over the knuckles and some executives even gave a few million dollars back, probably just to lower their tax brackets.
It didn't take long for those Wall Street bankers to bounce back. Of course, the central banks made it up to them with buckets of cheap money to play with. In fact, the more money you'd blown leading up to 2008 the more you were given to have another go. The best part was that you didn't have to lend the money out into the real economy - god forbid.
In the lead-up to 2008, bankers have proven conclusively they are incapable of assessing and pricing differential credit risk. Instead, they were allowed to secure it with some or other toxic credit paper, even if it was sovereign backed, and then simply hand it back, at a margin. Don't blame the banks, don't curse the bonuses - it was you, the European Central Bank and the US Federal Reserve and the Bank of Japan - who made it so, in search of your own popularity, making the bankers rich, and the people poor.
You'd have to be ignorant on purpose not to work out nothing has really changed for those top bankers - the same take-home pay, same tailor, none of that cut-your-cloth stuff. It was back into the trading rooms, back to whispering corridors to fix prices and make money.
These no-risk, get-rich executives gave the wage gap the worst name. Not because it shouldn't be there - it always will be- but because of how irreconcilable the differences became on Wall Street, given the different risk, effort and reward equations that applied at the top and bottom of the corporate ladder.
The accusation has spread. It is now fair game to compare the pay packages of all executives to the lowest-paid workers in their firms.
No surprises here - in some of the world's most successful companies, the ratio is the highest. At Walt Disney, the highest-paid executive earns 653 times the wage of the lowest-paid worker; at Coca-Cola the ratio is 427.
But this is a blunt measure, a blunt debate. The determinants of pay at the top and bottom of the scale are quite different and to ram them into some relationship that is artificial, just for the sake of finding middle ground, is misguided.
Labour, like capital and any other unit of production, will find its way to where it is required, at the right price. Overriding these & natural forces& with regulatory force cannot be sustained.
In the global marketplace, relative geographical or sovereign advantage is primarily a function of natural resources, financial policy and currency exchange rates which together determine the competitive or otherwise price of delivered goods and services. Some of these are more manageable than others and the playing field between countries is not equal. The lowest wages in Norway are probably fifty times higher than those in China or India.
The hundreds of millions of people around the world who do not have jobs are not evenly distributed across jurisdictions or relative advantages. To construct a global minimum wage regime would be as ill-advised as it would be impossible. A complex set of choices has to be made to find the right balance between minimum wage and unemployment so as to remain competitive and yet eliminate exploitation. This is not much different than the constant choice that has to be made between employment and inflation.
Top pay scales are determined by quite different influences.
The human individual is the rarest of all resources. There can be no doubt that an individual can make a difference, the difference. Organisations take on the character of their leaders. Would we have Liberty without Gordon, Rembrandt without Rupert, Shoprite without Basson, Investec without Koseff, Naspers without Bekker, Pick n Pay without Ackerman, DeBeers without Oppenheimer, Discovery without Gore, Bidvest without Joffe, Pepkor without Wiese?... the list goes on, as it should. These South Africans have, between them, defined the corporate landscape in SA, and others, in a more appropriate demographic mix, will follow. These may be highly paid individuals but they have created multiples of value way beyond the multiple that their pay bears to the lowest-paid workers in their companies - and that, surely, is the test of whether they deserve it? These leaders maintain competitive advantage and build groups that play on the world stage - who would want to penalise them for that?
When the regulators intervene we take a step closer to the middle - outliers are eliminated, the lowest and the highest legislated out of the game ... let's eliminate the rich and the poor. That is so wrong.
Eliminating the upside doesn't take care of the downside - it just caps aspirations - those who can will find it elsewhere; many have.
Of course, the government is a vital player, but it should focus on level playing fields and equal opportunity, not equal outcomes. Who would watch the Olympics if the objective was to cross the finish line all tied? The competition is outside the room and forcing everyone into the mediocre middle will chase away the superstars and actually increase the number of unemployed. Or we'll end up being like Australians. I can think of nothing worse.
The disparity between the rich and poor is growing ever wider. This is not sustainable, and not self-correcting
They maintain competitive advantage and build groups on world stage - who would want to penalise them for that?
]]></text></news-item>