<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9335-23B9-BF95-1D23"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Readers' forum</title><source>Charleston Gazette (West Virginia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Water solutions must be done effectively
Editor:
It would appear more cost-effective to modify the water plant to cope with a spill than to deal with 1,600 tanks plus pipelines, tankers, etc., that could be a potential source of contamination.
Improvements to the water plant defenses are obviously needed. If not a new inlet, then provisions to put the plant on recycle and run on stored water for a while might work. Detection improvement is also an obvious need.
One way or another. we are all going to pay for correcting the problem. Let's study it carefully and do it in the most effective manner.
Vann Carroll
Charleston
Mining deregulation unrelated to water
Editor:
I write in response to the March 3 editorial, "Tomblin's water pollution rhetoric embarrassing. With this piece I think the Gazette has reached new heights even for it in vacuity and disingenuousness. To suggest that it is "embarrassing for our governor to extend a gracious appreciation to the EPA for assistance in addressing our recent contaminated water crisis, while continuing to note his disagreement with EPA's approach to global warming-motivated emissions controls is nonsense. Based on EPA's recently published regulations proposing to impose unprecedented emission limits on greenhouse gases from new coal-fired electric generating plants, it is clear that no such plants will be constructed. Coupled with that agency's unrelenting efforts to severely curtail the surface mining of coal in West Virginia, it is fair to say that EPA has been responsible for the dismantling of a substantial portion of our coal industry. As we have already started to see, there will be long-term social and economic effects from this massive loss of employment, and despite what one might read in the pages of the Gazette, the environmental need for (not to mention the legality of) such excessively stringent restrictions on mining is far from demonstrated.
Moreover, as utility executives have repeatedly warned, the emissions rules are likely to have substantial regional (if not national) effects on the reliability of our power system - all without any significant reduction in the worldwide emissions of pollutants that are modeled as contributing to global warming.
The glib grouping of tragedies that have befallen our miners as being somehow connected to Gov. Tomblin's proper effort to protect our state from these unjustified regulatory assaults is the icing on the cake. Obviously, there is no line that our "State's Newspaper will not cross in the service of political correctness. Embarrassing? Indeed.
Christopher "Kip Power
Charleston
Thanks for a job well done
Editor:
Recently I had my second knee replacement surgery at St. Francis Hospital performed by Dr. Paul Legg.
I would like to thank Dr. Paul Legg and the nursing staff on 4 West, they were so kind and caring throughout my week long stay after the operation and during my recuperation.
I would also like to thank the staff of Thomas Memorial Hospital Physical Therapy Department. They have been a great asset to my recovery. I am now able to walk pain free!
Bob Anderson
South Charleston
Public servants need to serve
Editor:
A politician is a public servant. They are elected to serve and protect the public, but as soon as they are elected they get amnesia. Their only concerns are getting re-elected with money from big corporations. That is why we do not need Shelley Moore Capito in the Senate. All she has done as a representative is genuflect to big coal companies.
My father was a coal miner before there was a union. He worked in harsh conditions and was forced to retire because of high blood pressure.
So without a union he had no pension after working in the mines over 30 years. He was left with nothing. So I know about coal miners. I also had brothers who were coal miners, unlike Capito and others who give lip service.
We also need term limits so these politicians cannot continue to buy their way in.
Margaret Plumley
Charleston
]]></text></news-item>