<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9354-77A1-F402-4953"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>THE WORLD IS NOT ENOUGH; Advance Global Australian Awards</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>Patrick Durkin</author><text><![CDATA[An Australian at the frontier of space technology, leads the pack of Advance Global Award winners 2014, who have been recognised as global achievers from the more than one million Australians living overseas.
Overall winner: Christopher Boshuizen, founder Planet Labs, advanced manufacturing
WE ARE both watching a live NASA feed of the International Space Station circling 420 kilometres above the earth while Christopher Boshuizen is interviewed by Boss.
It is not surprising the laid-back 35-year-old is slightly on edge as we talk: he is watching to see if two satellites made by his company are launched without mishap.
"It is something that I have built in the lab and touched with my own hands," he says, "so to see it up in space just blows my mind."
Without warning, a robotic arm reaches inside the module to open the air lock and rapidly spits out two satellites.
"There they go, they just went, did you see that? That was it, the door opened, the spring released and out they shot," he says.
The process will be repeated in 12 hours when another two of Boshuizen's satellites are deployed. The mini-spacecraft are the first of the 28-satellite Flock 1: Earth-watching cameras which Planet Labs launched in February to create a photographic map of the earth that will update every 90 days.
The multi-million dollar operation Boshuizen has set in train comes just two years after the young Aussie and two co-founders started the company from a garage in Silicon Valley.
"A couple of us got jobs with NASA in Mountain View right next to Google, I ended up there for about five years. Because you are in Silicon Valley you are surrounded by all these start-up companies.
"It just seemed natural to us at some point that we should take what we had learned and actually start a company ourselves."Space enthusiasts
The band of space enthusiasts ran their first test for the start-up by sticking an iPhone in a cube. They took it out to the Black Rock Desert in Nevada and strapped it to a rocket. It was meant to fly to 36,500 metres and parachute back to earth. Halfway up, the parachute deployed and tore the rocket to shreds. It came crashing back to earth at terminal velocity and they had to dig it out of the ground. Instead of admitting defeat, Boshuizen put the wreckage ito a perspex case and showed it to investors.
"They loved it. I nearly bankrolled the whole project carrying around this broken, crushed wreckage in a perspex box. It symbolised something to people and it was a really interesting lesson in just going out there and doing it," he says.
The team then built their first satellite, which was about the size of a toaster, and bought a rocket ride ito space with $275,000 of their own money. The success of the mission meant private investors quickly began to come on board.
Boshuizen says the project is not just about spying on your neighbour's house.
"There are a lot of things happening out there that no one sees. When we launch 28 satellites we will be able to cover the whole Earth on a really frequent basis and not miss anything.
"What is really happening with the climate? What is really happening with our ecosystems? Are forests growing or shrinking? Is anyone actually taking enough photos of the Amazon to know for sure? What I want to do is to create the biggest data set of changing information on the planet so that we can learn about what is really happening on the ground and make much better decisions about managing the planet, our environment and our urban areas."
Karyl Nairn QC, Skadden Arps, legal services
KARYL NAIRN is as much a diplomat, confidante and negotiator as a lawyer.
"You are a crisis manager. I only get called in when things have gone terribly wrong," Nairn says. "People are very stressed when they call you."
Only the third female solicitor advocate to become a Queen's Counsel in Britain (the appointments are usually reserved for barristers), Nairn specialises in complex disputes and negotiations between countries.
"You don't sleep much. At the moment I have a case in Asia which means I am up early, then I have my day job in London and I am also up late for a case in the States. You often have to give up really good theatre tickets at the last minute."
It is after 10pm when she speaks to Boss. She is working late after court hearings to write an advice for the Venezuelan government, which is among a number of countries being sued by the World Bank.
Perth-born Nairn has been involved in many high-profile cases such as acting for the owner of Chelsea Football Club, Russian Roman Abramovich, who was being sued by Russian oligarch Boris Berezovsky.
"Every dispute is on some level about ego and pride and power," she says.
Another case, which left a lasting mark on Nairn, was when she won $100 million for Israeli investor Ronnie Fuchs, who had his rights to oil transportation in the former Soviet state of Georgia expropriated. "The government said they were only prepared to pay a portion of the money. Fuchs was invited to a major lunch in Georgia to receive the money. Instead he was arrested and thrown in jail.
"We sent human rights barrister Geoffrey Robertson, Q.C. His public profile offered some protection against him also being arrested. He had to pass notes under an umbrella so that they couldn't be seen by security cameras.
"We also used the former White House Counsel to President Barack Obama Gregory Craig and formed a case for entrapment, threatened to undermine their case for entry to the EU and lobby for the withdrawal of aid.
"It was a case of who blinked first. We got right to the 'court door' and managed to negotiate a deal which satisfied both sides."
Milton Catelin, CEO World Coal Association, mining and resources
IN MILTON CATELIN'S interview to head up the World Coal Association, he was asked about his biggest weakness.
"I told them that the only problem was that I didn't know sh-- about coal.
"They laughed and said, 'That's OK, we know everything about coal, but they wanted someone who understood government processes, the climate change debate and the UN.'"
Catelin had handled climate negotiations for Australia and had also worked for the UN environment program in Geneva before taking up the role of defending coal.
The job means Catelin has had to get used to being painted as the bad guy.
"My biggest advice is just to persevere. The coal sector is a difficult sector. It is undeniable that burning coal does release CO2 and therefore exacerbates global warning. But you have to persevere and explain the complexity of the case and that coal does not just bring costs but brings benefits to people," Catelin says.
Catelin says that there are different ways to burn coal and there is merit in carbon capture and storage [CCS], although it is regularly criticised by green groups as a temporary solution.
"If you want to achieve [a reduction in global temperature] of 2 degrees lower this century it is critical to look at the efficiency of coal plants which currently sit at around 33 per cent.
"If you were to increase that to 40 per cent, you would reduce CO2 emissions by the equivalent of India's annual emissions."
Catelin says because coal makes up 30 per cent of global energy needs it cannot be ignored: "A quarter of a century ago it made up 25 per cent. Predictions suggest that in 25 years' time, it will still contribute around 25 per cent."
That is why you need clean coal technology and CCS, he says.
"It is not a means to smuggle coal ito the future. The reality is that coal will remain a major long-term contributor of energy. Therefore you need to make sure it is used in the most environmentally friendly way."
Catelin says that if you care about the environment and want to make a difference you have no choice but to work on the global stage.
"I have really had 17 years of jobs of travelling extensively overseas. I used to come home with a present but after a while one of my two daughters said, 'I don't want a present, I don't want you to go.'
"It takes a toll on your family when you take on an international job and that has been a challenge for us all."
Prue Clarke, president New Narratives, social innovation
FOREIGN CORRESPONDENT Prue Clarke was interviewing women who had been raped in the Congo when she realised they didn't know why it was happening to them. "They were telling me it was witchcraft. Unless you know about the government backing various militias to access the minerals under their feet, there is nothing you can do to stop it. I was reporting to people in international audiences who couldn't do anything about the situation while the local community didn't know the truth."
Clarke was able to convince a partner at Goldman Sachs in 2010 to give her a quarter of a million dollars over two years to set up New Narratives to empower women journalists in Liberia to tell women's stories.
"In these countries women are considered second-class citizens and the journalists are constantly asked for sex in return for interviews and dismissed as not serious.
"But once they started producing stories for the front pages of their papers and everyone was talking about the stories they were breaking, momentum continued to build."
Her most shocking and inspiring moment was when a female journalist broke a story on female genital cutting in Liberia. Her life was threatened and she and her daughter were forced to go ito hiding. A follow-up story was done by a colleague for radio.
"I had lost my nerve and I told her to drop the story. She and her radio station said that they knew we couldn't protect them but they wanted to do it anyway because they thought it was that important," Clarke says.
Her advice to others is to never think you can't do it.
"Australians are very practical and real. You just have to put one foot in front of the other and you will find that you have suddenly taken things to a whole other level," she says.
"We are not missing any of the ingredients that we need to make an impact on the global stage. I grew up in rural NSW on a farm and have now lived on four continents and run projects in Africa.
"I would never have expected to be here but I have realised there truly are no barriers to what we can achieve," says Clarke.
Vikram Mehta, Pacific Venture Advisors, information and communications technology
VIKRAM MEHTA feels the need for speed. His life mission is to secure real-time connectivity for the internet. His team has already created technology that has sped up the transfer of information.
In some cases that can mean the difference between life and death, he says.
"If this was a healthcare program and someone you knew was about to have a heart attack, that may make a difference between life and death," he says.
"Imagine if an oil company knew eight seconds earlier than otherwise that a rig was about to blow up, you would be able to take action sooner."
Indian-born Vikram founded BLADE, which sped up connectivity between computers. The technology was sold to retailers, financial institutions, telecommunications companies, airlines and governments. The company grew its sales from its modest operations in Silicon Valley to win 100 companies as clients. It had a capital raising in 2009 before being acquired by IBM in 2010.
Vikram doesn't ascribe his success to his own intelligence.
"I don't consider myself the sharpest knife in the draw," he tells Boss. "Often I joke that I have the lowest IQ in the room. But I do have a special ability to inspire a team. A lot of opportunities are lost because people look at things too individually. When you are trying to solve the hardest problems, it is about pulling together the best in the business and making it work."
His latest venture is as head of Kaazing, technology he says will change the world.
"The internet needs to work as if people are next to each other, we are the invetors of technology that makes that possible."
Amusingly, his advice is drawn from the 1990s advertising campaign for the Northern Territory: "You never, never know if you never, never [have a] go. You just have to earn your keep every single day."
THE OTHER WINNERS ARE:
Creative industries: Sir Jonathan Mills, director Edinburgh International Festival
Clean technology: Andrew Tanner, chief engineer, THiNKnrg,
Biotechnology: Richard Pestell, founder Prostagene; director Kimmel Cancer Centre
Alumni: Sekai Holland, Zimbabwean co-Minister of State for National Healing, Reconcilitation and Integration
]]></text></news-item>