<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9479-9E8B-ED3B-7467"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Mega-rich society hostess - now facing a massive fraud probe - paid for his £500,000 birthday party... Is Charles' love of billionaires about to taint him with scandal - again?</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>RICHARD KAY and GEOFFREY LEVY</author><text><![CDATA[This week, royal courtiers were evaluating the implications of a £500,000 black-tie gala evening which Charles allowed a rich Indian couple to pay forThe event was to celebrate his 65th birthday in November last yearIt has now emerged Priya Hiranandani-Vandrevala is facing claims involving £350 million which allegedly went 'missing' in an investment schemeShe and her father deny any wrongdoing and are defending the claimsHer legal problems would probably have passed unnoticed in the capital's social jostle but for one thing: the couple's friendship with Charles
So much has changed for the Prince of Wales since his father Prince Philip gave him a dressing down in front of other family members for taking millions of pounds worth of largesse from rich acquaintances, some of whom had decidedly shady backgrounds.
Philip, now 92, no longer bawls out his son, who has, after all, shared much of the 87-year-old Queen's work and been elevated almost to a position of 'co-monarch'.
One thing, however, doesn't seem to have changed very much since that reprimand more than a dozen years ago at Sandringham - Charles's appetite for the company and favours of rich friends.
This week, royal courtiers were evaluating the implications of a £500,000 black-tie gala evening at Buckingham Palace celebrating the prince's 65th birthday last November, which Charles allowed a rich Indian couple to pay for.
For it has emerged that glossy Indian socialite Priya Hiranandani-Vandrevala is facing embarrassing claims involving £350 million which allegedly went 'missing' in an investment scheme, set up with her father, for a luxury development near Mumbai. She and her father deny any wrongdoing and are defending the claims. Even though the Valentino-wearing Priya and her private equity billionaire husband Cyrus live in London's fashionable Holland Park - in a £20million house with a two-storey basement with pool - her legal problems would probably have passed unnoticed in the capital's social jostle but for one thing: the couple's friendship with Charles.
The relationship with the 'Bollygarch' philanthropist couple obviously means a lot to the Prince of Wales. They have been to tea at Highgrove, and Charles and the Duchess of Cornwall have come to know them well.
Prince Andrew is also close to them, and they have even become patrons of the Elephant Family, the conservation charity run by the Duchess of Cornwall's brother Mark Shand.
It was certainly a lavish party that this charming couple laid on for the heir to the throne, with endless champagne and the Philharmonia Orchestra playing an evening of Wagner - at Charles's special request he wanted to recognise the bi-centenary of his favourite composer's birth. And how well orchestrated the evening was, by who else but Michael Fawcett, Charles's former assistant, who continues to organise the Prince's entertaining.
As 400 guests gathered before dinner, they were directed into three separate rooms, in one of which Charles greeted guests. When they sat down to dinner, Priya was next to Charles, and Cyrus next to Camilla.
Back in Mumbai, the Vandrevalas' pinnacle of social success has caused a great deal of comment and excitement. But one question still hangs over the event some four months later: why did they pay for Charles's extravagant birthday party?
The answer is they were 'approached' by a supporter of the Philharmonia who was also a friend of Prince Charles. And the couple say they 'could not have been more honoured' to finance it.
For his part, the prince saw it as a brilliant opportunity to bring together under the Queen's roof (she was away, of course) some of the richest and, significantly, most generous people in the world, such as the Labour-party donors the Hinduja brothers, steel tycoon Lakshmi Mittal and Mercedes-Benz heir Muck Flick.
But once again, it has made palace courtiers concerned by the ease with which the Prince of Wales continues to allow the rich to do favours for him.
For he does so despite the fact that his private income from the Duchy of Cornwall last year was more than £19 million, some £10 million of which he was able to offset against tax as 'business expenses'.
So even though his own fortune can be counted in millions, he continues to be drawn with giddying speed to the super-wealthy. And they, of course, to him.
One place where names of his very rich acquaintances are beginning to appear (in spots where they can be easily seen by visitors) is Dumfries House, the Palladian mansion in Ayrshire which Charles has refurbished at enormous expense.
He put his Prince's Foundation under significant strain with a £20 million debt to finance the restoration - a huge gamble. Predictably, rich people of his acquaintance are coming forward to help him out with his most cherished heritage project.
To pay for its upkeep, the house can be hired for weddings, banquets and conferences.
But in addition, the grounds are now showing tell-tale signs that Charles's monied friends are riding to the rescue.
There is, for example, a banner proclaiming the Tamar Manoukian Outdoor Centre, a youth centre named after the wife of Armenian-born property developer Bob Manoukian, who lives in London.
There is also the Kuanyshev Sawmill and Workshops, including a restored derelict waterwheel, that is named after oil tycoon Timur Kuanyshev, who made his fortune in the Klondike melee of Kazakhstan.
He and his wife Alfiya were once stopped at Moscow airport and found to be carrying $1 million in cash stuffed in their underwear. They were not prosecuted.
In May, another new facility opens in the grounds of Dumfries House: an adventure playground for disabled children. It is costing £200,000 to build, and the birthday party-giving Vandravelas have paid for it.
Prince Charles himself is due to declare the playground open, and the Vandrevalas are to be very much a part of the proceedings.
In a special gesture of princely gratitude, the couple have been invited to spend the night in the house, as guests of Charles. They are expected to dine with him.
But now there may be a hitch. We understand that this week, following the disclosures that Priya Vandrevala was facing legal claims involving the alleged 'missing' £350 million, a subtle change of plan to the opening ceremony has been under consideration.
The original idea was for invited media to record the occasion - the playground is seen as a key attraction for visitors.
Now royal sources suggest that the Prince of Wales could open the playground in a private ceremony away from the cameras.
The Vandrevalas are baffled. Understandably, they were keen for the world to see them with the prince, and feel rather let down. But there could yet be another development. Privately, advisers to the prince have discussed the possibility of offering to refund the philanthropic couple the money.
For their part, we understand the Vandrevalas might pre-empt any such decision and consider asking for their donation back.
All of which is highly embarrassing for Prince Charles's best friend, Tory MP Nicholas Soames, grandson of Sir Winston Churchill. 
For he is a £100,000 a year part-time 'senior adviser on strategic issues' to Intrepid Capital Partners, Cyrus Vandravala's Knightsbridge-based investment vehicle (which is not involved in the legal dispute). All in all, however, this is a minor issue compared with some of the complications that have dogged the Prince of Wales concerning previous links with generous billionaires.
Over the years, from borrowed private jets and helicopters to floating gin palaces and Riviera retreats, the prince has displayed an extraordinary ability to suspend judgment in the pursuit of a good time in glamorous surroundings.
Some of his benefactors have been decidedly - and recognisably - shady. The late shipping tycoon John Latsis, a man described in his native Greece as a 'gangster', often lent Charles his fabulous 400ft yacht the Alexander for holidays, after being introduced by Charles's cousin, ex-King Constantine.
During one holiday around the Mediterranean, the prince took a party of 22 people with him, including his then mistress, Camilla Parker Bowles, and her children Tom and Laura. Had Charles opened his chequebook to pay for it, the cost would have been in the region of £500,000.
Over many years the Prince of Wales also couldn't resist regularly borrowing the tycoon's private Boeing 767 as well.
And he borrowed the Alexander's helicopter to ease his regular pilgrim's journey to Mount Athos, the monks' sanctuary in Greece where he went on retreat.
Latsis got out of the relationship what all sycophantic billionaires get out of sucking up to royalty. He was puffed up with glee and pride that other rich Greeks envied his closeness to British royalty.
He adored the fact that Charles and Diana's 1992 cruise on the Alexander was described as a 'second honeymoon', little knowing that months later they would have parted.
Thanks to his yacht, Latsis, born in poverty, believed he was being written into the history of the royal saga. But personal pride was only half the story.
He also believed that apparent 'approval' from the heir to the British throne bought him business and political leverage which allowed him to make even more money.
Then there was Armand Hammer, often described as the most odious and corrupt tycoon of modern times. The disgraced U.S. oil billionaire, exposed after his death in 1990 aged 92 as having spied for Russia, bankrolled Charles's favourite causes with upwards of £40million.
He also loaned him the use of his luxuriously appointed Boeing 727, which led to hand-written letters of unctuous gratitude from the prince.
'My Dear Mr Hammer,' he wrote to the billionaire after he and Princess Diana were flown home from America at the end of a royal tour.
'I have so many things to thank you for that I hardly know where to begin. Your kindness in letting us fly back in your 727 was enormously appreciated and I am now thoroughly spoiled for any other form of flying.'
Some unsettled courtiers cringed at what they saw as a coded request to keep the free flights coming. 'The prince appears to be entirely devoid of embarrassment,' one said.
Another rich benefactor, Turkish telecoms entrepreneur Cem Uzan lavished more than £400,000 on Charles's pet projects after dining with the prince at Highgrove and at Buckingham Palace, his wife sitting next to the prince.
Soon afterwards he declined to set foot in Britain because of a 15-month prison sentence imposed on him by a High Court judge over his non-appearance at a court-ordered examination by lawyers looking into $2 billion fraud allegations.
Manuel Colonques, wealthy boss of Spanish tiling company Porcelanosa, has also enjoyed Charles's patronage after picking up the £100,000 bill for the prince's 'Islamic Garden', which won a silver at the Chelsea Flower Show, as well as financing several events in royal palaces.
As a mark of his gratitude, Senor Colonques was on the guest list for Prince William's wedding to Kate Middleton in 2011.
As was Joe Allbritton, former owner of Washington-based Riggs Bank, which was fined $25 million as a result of a U.S. congress investigation into a money-laundering plot involving Chilean dictator General Pinochet. Mr Allbritton, who died in 2012, always denied any wrongdoing. He and his wife Barbie were regular guests at Highgrove, lent the prince a Gulfstream private jet and gave £190,000 a year to the U.S. Prince of Wales Foundation.
Surely there is a simple solution to these embarrassing episodes.
All Prince Charles has to do is bring out his own cheque book and pay for his own luxury lifestyle.
]]></text></news-item>