<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="94ED-C8E6-DE82-CF2A"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>E-Street: Do you support the increasing density in Vancouver and other parts of the Lower Mainland?</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[NOT AT ALL. Because of this density, housing is unavailable AND unaffordable. My soon-to-be husband and I can't afford in the Lower Mainland and are considering moving to Chilliwack, as have a few of our friends and family. It's appalling that in the 30 years since my parents bought their first home the Lower Mainland has become so disgustingly full that I cannot come close to the same quality of life in the neighbourhood I grew up in. Frankly, something has to change...but that's a topic for a different discussion.
--Sarah Tymoschuk, Surrey
As a human being on this planet at this time, where there are more than 7 billion living people, it is without a doubt that I fully support increasing density in Vancouver and beyond. I just moved to the Vancouver area. Our city is destined to become a mega city but right now, we are very small compared to places that already have more than ten million people. Vancouver is nothing compared to that but we have an opportunity to plan and prepare infrastructure to support this expected growth.
-Troy Hunter, Burnaby
No I do not. I live in Chillwack and increasing population figures are reeking havoc on the infrastructure, destroying farmlands and creating more and more pollution and garbage. I'm not against progress but it needs to happen in a controlled manner, not by throwing the floodgates open to unrestricted development.
-Jim Haslett, Chilliwack
No I don't. I do not see the advantage of increasing density (population) when our services like education, medical care, police services and just getting around because of traffic density are already over-burdened. We seem to have the mindset that growth itself is good; even somehow mandated by an invisible force of virtue. Bigger isn't necessarily better.
-Charlie Criticist, Burnaby
Do I support it ? What hell choice do we have but no, I would prefer them to not let anymore people in to or little piece of paradise.
-David Bain, Maple Ridge
I absolutely support the boneheads who are turning the areas mentioned into a blackboard jungle where standing room only is knocking at the door. I have written about the over crowding of city's many times but who listens to a nobody. Where I reside in Olalla there is still the true meaning of peace in the valley. We don't even have a corner store or coffee shop here in the lost but beautiful untouched frontier called Olalla /. Keep your blackboard Jungle's that I spent many years listening to the clock ticking till the day finally arrived.to depart. I moved to an untouched valley of serene beauty and stress free living where the birds -sing joined in chorus by all kinds of wildlife living in peace and tranquility. No you city dweller's can have your congestion as you may never know anything about living the good part of life that unfortunately has pretty much disappeared in the wayward winds and bad planning of yester-year?
-Tom Isherwood, Olalla
I do not support the increasing density in Vancouver. The politicians are in bed with the developers and all common sense has flown the coop over their mutual love of money. On the North Shore, we do not have the amenities to support all these people in their new condos. The bridges are already crowded, there are long waits at our one hospital emergency, parking is challenging, its difficult to get a doctor already and so on. Our fair city is symptomatically being destroyed and sadly what is being done here cannot be undone.
-Brenda E Hamilton, North Vancouver
Yes, the denser the better. I am hoping that my commercial property will be rezoned soon for high rise. That would triple my property value, making me a multi millionaire. Then I can sell out and move out of this ridiculous city and escape this Mayor Moonbeam inspired insanity. Thanks for paycheck, Mayor Moonbeam!
-Charles Waggett, Vancouver (for now)
I support density if its done respectfully in consultation with the residents of the individual neighborhoods. In Marpole, for instance, they want to build high rise structures and destroy a single family home neighborhood and sometimes I think its driven by greedy developers and tax hungry city planners. Those are not good enough reasons for me. We do need to preserve our neighborhoods. I was in Vancouver when the developers and planners got into the Kits area and began tearing down entire blocks of really nice old but well built craftsman houses to build ugly apartment blocks and I feel Vancouver lost some of its heritage by allowing that. We need to always look at the bigger picture. Modernization and the greed for profit are not good reasons to pursue densification. Densification can happen without compromise only if the city planners respect existing residents and don't just plough ahead with THEIR good ideas regardless. When developers secretly work with planners this is not acceptable and I would oppose any plans coming out of those meetings. Open and transparent planning that is inclusive of all affected parties is what a democracy is all about. This isn't China or Russia where might makes right.
-Les Braden, Vancouver
Density is great if it comes with community facilities, local workplaces, schools, transit levies and developer guarantees that these will have lifelong support. Otherwise it's simply unrealistic and creates congestion and severe environmental impact.
-Farrell Segall
Yes, they are where the transit is so they won't need cars so it is a win, win situation for everyone.
-Bud March, 100 Mile
Increasing density is the only sane way to accommodate housing needs - we cant keep clear cutting into wilderness &; its inhabitants &; continue to spread like we did last century. HOWEVER density needs to be planned with long term needs in site - i.e. leisure areas, day care, &; other needs of a denser population. Europe - especially the Netherlands &; the Baltic states have been doing it for centuries....we could learn from them.
-Rachel Cormier, Mission
Density of Vancouver or any city for that matter, should adhere to guidelines set out relative to green space, infrastructure, safety and medical services. On the green space topic, there must be compliance to numbers of population ratios verses acres of green space, ie. trees, grass areas and water. Uses of these are must haves. A number like 500 people per 500 acres comes to mind but that can always be researched.
-Rudy Hiebert, Abbotsford
It's better to go up and out. In advanced countries a single high rise building is an entire ecoystem and city in itself, with all the amenities we currently have to drive all over hell to get too. Canada just has to become advanced. Hopefully soon.
-Duane Burnett, Sechelt
Unfortunately, it's the obvious next step when there is too much local government with unfunded liabilities to pay for, where no-one will politically risk doing the right thing (i.e. get voted out and/or lose the nice job!) It seems to have become the fashion to simply increase density to and the tax base to expand public revenue rather than addressing and reducing the empires/ongoing liabilities, which were built up during the good times and are neither appropriate nor sustainable.
-Mike Aston, Pender Island
(I am assuming by "density" you mean human population) I do not support allowing extra people in unless we can take care of the people who were here first. It's similar to working in pubs with limited seating capacities. If we let in extra people there would be nowhere for these people to sit and their services would be very poor or non existent. The staff struggles greatly and it's a bad experience for everyone with potential for danger. It's a similar situation, just a different scenario.
-Kim Patterson, Surrey
My question is do we have a choice? The vast majoity of immigrants to our country don't move out to rural parts, they move into our largest cities. Until our laws change to encourage immigrants to move out and into the rural areas, our cities are just going to get denser and larger.
-R.Morben, Victoria
"Population density is inevitable. The issue remains planning for it. Governments at every level will inevitably be involved in planning and it would be foolish to exclude any shareholder."
-W. Perry, Victoria
Increasing density should have started decades ago so we wouldn`t have to be fighting for the scraps that are left. For too long developers have had too close a relationship with Councils to open up easy to build on land - agricultural or otherwise - to increase their own profit margins at the expense of the environment. Just looking at what has happened to Richmond should be a warning sign to all of us that aren`t guided by unthinking greed and always taking the easy way out. So, yes, increase density so that open spaces are protected either for agriculture or for the sake of the natural environment. Contrary to the opinions of the Fraser Institute who have said that they want the farmland totally eaten up by development, we have to realize before its too late that open spaces have value, too. As long as people move here then we will need housing for them. Higher density is the only answer that is sustainable. Besides, with the cost of single family homes going beyond the ability of most people to afford them, there is no alternative that I can see because doing business as usual just isn`t working anymore. Stop the sprawl and build upwards not outwards.
-Robert T. Rock, Mission City
One of the reasons I moved out of Vancouver to the Shuswap! Nice quiet living up here!
-Madelaine Lawson, Canoe
High density and low density people will stop meeting. High density people will have no cars to visit their low density friends and will forever complain about to cost of the roads and carbon from the cars. Low density people and delivery people will not come to high density areas because they cannot park.
-Wayne Wagstaff, Surrey
I think we are at the point where we don't have a choice. People are entitled to choose the area in which they live, and since not everyone enjoys the suburbs, what are they left with? I actually think lane houses can and do work and should be considered as an option for those who would prefer an urban lifestyle. Whatever, increasing density will continue.
-Maureen Parks
If the increase in density decreases taxes on the tired &; heavy laden present tax payers, I am all for it! We need a break.
-Ruth Enns, Vancouver
Yes: It will be booming economy and jobs. No: It will worsen traffic and pollution headaches.
-Husen Huang, Vancouver
Like over 65 per cent of the population I am horrified at the feeding frenzy on the part developers and the local politicians all throughout the Lower Mainland in terms of every square inch of land must be turned into a tower of cement. What is more disgusting is that local politician's are NOT listening to the present citizens in the municipalities and cities that they represent because time after time people are showing up at public hearings and expressing displeasure at increased density plans but the people are being continually ignored in favour of developers. The big question that NO ONE is answering is who is all this building for? The Canadian birth rate is very small compared for the millions of people they are apparently excepting. Obviously the Lower Mainland is expecting one million immigrants. Where will the come from? How wealthy will they be? Will English be their first language, or will there be ethnic enclaves throughout the Lower Mainland. The worst thing is that we cannot even discuss immigration without being labelled a "racist" which says that our immigration is not multi-cultural but only accepting people from 3 or 4 countries in the world. Why?
-Sue Lakes Cook
Since $100,000 won't even buy a hole in the wall what other choice to renters and people in need of subsidized non-market housing have than to live in a home that is slightly larger than a prison cell?
-Leslie Benisz, Vancouver
Respectfully, but where else are people supposed to live?
Donna Vandekerkhove, Port Moody
How do you stop it? Every medium and large city in the world is growing, and it is hard to put your head in the sand and ignore it. The main problem is a vastly overpopulated planet. If India and China could half their populations, the whole planet would be much better off. We are chocking the planet with people, and it must stop.
-Derek Coughtrey, Surrey
There is of course a reciprocity between density and quality of life. The more population density increases, the more attention has to be paid to maintaining a balance between people living close enough together so that they can enjoy the most positive rewards inherent to safe and stable communities and neighbourhoods, but distanced enough that each individual and/or family can maintain the degree of privacy that is necessary for living dignified lives. Increasing density without paying attention to this equation is simply writing a recipe for disaster.
-Ray Arnold, Richmond
More housing this time courtesy the Musqueam probably just as ugly, leaky and overpriced as the rest is slated for development on the University Endowment Lands (UEL) at the golf course near UBC. Will land parcels be devised in fee simple? If not, would anyone be stupid enough to buy? An interesting social experiment in the midst of a wealthy community that until very recently never paid its fair share of taxes. One way or another, they will pay now.
-Leo Biblitz, Vanc-Hooverville-Under-Tarps
Any individual in his right mind does not want increased density because it detracts from his or her enjoyment of life. Unfortunately individually we can not fight this no matter how much we try, we need to get together to elect the city officials that have similar ideas as we do, and let them do the job. They will not altogether be successful, as developers and owners of land have rights too, but they can minimize growth and direct it.
-Eberhard Bergler
NO ! Absolutely not . But , what can we do about it . The city keeps building accommodations for people ; so that more people can come and live here . Then , City bosses raise property taxes to try to get rid of people who were here originally , but who now can't afford to live here anymore because of the density problem . Not all of us a rich and can afford the taxes. yes , I know , too long . but it has to be said .
-Dave Gibney
All this density will just make earthquake disasters that much more interesting for emergency vehicles to try and navigate over fallen buildings. Not to mention spreading fires so much more easier from building to building.
-Barry O'Regan, Burnaby
Not when it changes the city and parts of the Lower Mainland into a dense forest of ugly mega storey towers. Downtown Vancouver is only interesting when seen from a distance. Walk around and you never see sunlight, even when it's shining! Heritage designation is a joke as old buildings are stripped to bare boards and rebuilt to attempt duplication of the original. As the saying goes: build it and they will come. Perhaps it is time to stop building at such a frantic pace and step back to consider aesthetics before our city becomes any uglier than it is now becoming.
-Natalie Speckmaier, Vancouver
No, it's creating major construction, problematic congestion, angry drivers and ugly neighbourhoods. And Yes, the population is never ending and the bears deserve to live in a forest, not a backyard.
-Tara Torrell, Port Moody
"What's in it for us". More congestion. more taxes and less money for individuals to spend to enjoy their lives. In addition, less feeling of 'belonging" to the Community which is running afoul. We have been asking these questions for some time and get no satisfactory answer. Our Municipality is bent on proceeding down this dark path of Community destruction by "densification". Just look at all of the high rises. Not friendly areas and lack of greenery and parks in the immediate areas. Very damp and cold. No sunshine! What benefits for existing taxpayers? None.
-Elwin Mowry, Coquitlam
Too fast increase in density without the increase of info structure is bad as it produces human problems. We can already see the decrease of the units floor area , meaning that it is not only increasing number of units being built but people are jammed into them and in time they loose their value. Slaw down or it will turn into a chaos eventually.
-Laszlo Novotny, Vancouver
Yes. The continuous growth in population has put a lot of pressure on the land. The. Land stays the same. As such, it is not only desirable to have increased density but also needed. This will take pressure off the much needed farmland.
-Balwant Sanghera, Richmond
No. More density equals more congestion and more strain on the overburdened infrastructure and more noise pollution than ever. Quality of life is constantly being eroded for the almighty dollar.
-Donna Rae, Native Vancouverite living in Surrey due to being forced out from extreme cost of living in Vancouver.
Increasing density in Vancouver and other parts of the lower mainland is not a good idea. Density means congestion and congestion is getting into each other space. Getting into others space means friction and friction leads to other undesirable consequences. What is the point of herding people in a designated area when we have lots of living space in the province? What do we do with the then abandoned living space? Return it to nature? I originally came from a place a tad smaller than BC and it is home to 100 million people so I know what density is. There you're practically living on top of one another every second of your life and it is not a good feeling. I suspect those who proposes higher density have been impressed by European cities but those places do not have choices. They do not have a place to expand. That is why the New World is populated by Europeans. There are admittedly advantages to high density urban areas such as easier social and transportation infrastructure planning and so forth and on. Still it does not appeal to me. No I'm against it.
-Norman M Ostonal, New Westminster
As time goes by in any given city in Canada, density is inevitable. People has to live somewhere. It's natural for people to move around into different city or areas in a city as time goes by. Personallly I was born in Manitoba and arrived here in B.C. in 1947 with my parents. We all come from somewhere however it's natural for people to move around to different areas of the world for whatever reasons they have. Therefore density in any given area is a natural phenomenon. As time goes by, Density is enevitable. Therefore, we must accommodate families as needed. If bigger buildings are needed municipal laws must accommodate living standard as needed. There was a time in ancient history that people lived in tents,however, things have changed with time. So we must go with the flo.
-Aime J. Therrien
No.
-Michael O'Keeffe., Richmond
Great idea! fill the whole place with concrete buildings - the days of a proper development plan have long passed and cannot be fixed now.
-J R Turpin, Victoria
NO I do not support increased density anywhere unless nature can sustain it. I believe that population density MUST be determined by SUSTAINABILITY!!!! Ask a farmer what happens when you do not respect the limits of land, water and clean air. There has to be a limit on density based on a healthy balance, which Vancouver (proper) crossed long ago. Therefore, only areas that could benefit are the suburbs that have not already exceeded healthy limits. Health being based in physical, mental, social and emotional states.
-Zanie Mollica, West Kelowna
This densification is not being done properly. It is developer-driven planning, not community-driven. This has resulted in many problems, including traffic congestion, pollution, more crime, and the loss of the family and all that encompasses. Where are the traffic plans? It is backward to build and expect "TransLink" to follow through. I believe the only people who are in favour of these massive development projects are people who have solid financial and/or political involvement.
-Wendy Qureshi, North Vancouver
Yes we need to increase density in Vancouver as people need decent places to live. But we also need to make sure there is green space available as well as investment in good public services like schools, child care and community centres. Newcomers to BC and Canada could also be encouraged to move to locations outside of Metro Vancouver to ensure the entire province remains vibrant with thriving local economies.
-Sharon Gregson, East Vancouver
The editorial pages editor is Gordon Clark, who can be reached at ( mailto:provletters@theprovince.com ). Letters to the editor can be sent to provletters@theprovince.com( mailto:provletters@theprovince.com ).
]]></text></news-item>