<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="95CF-5761-50D0-708C"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>HEALTH INSPECTIONS: 3 York County businesses out of compliance</title><source>The York Dispatch (Pennsylvania)</source><author>By CANDY WOODALL 505-5437/@ydbiz</author><text><![CDATA[The state Department of Agriculture conducts annual inspections of food-serving businesses to ensure public safety and safe food-handling practices. Schools are inspected twice per year, according to the Bureau of Food Safety and Laboratories.
Whether an establishment is considered compliant or non-compliant is the discretion of the inspector. There are, however, several violations for which inspectors should automatically consider establishments non-compliant. Called "critical violations," they include food temperature issues, issues with chemicals and how they're handled, and employee hygiene.
Depending on the severity of the situation, inspectors and their supervisors could file citations or close an establishment.
Below is a list of establishments listed as out-of-compliance for inspections conducted March 7 - March 11.
OUT OF COMPLIANCE
Heaven's Rain Cafe, 3501 Concord Road, York.
Action: Violations included the owner wearing single-use gloves without a prior hand wash; an employee's open beverage container in the food-preparation area; the owner touching ready-to-eat foods with his bare hands; several raw animal foods (pork, chicken and eggs) stored above ready-to-eat foods (lettuce and tomatoes) in the refrigerator; in-use knives stored between tables or table edges areas that are not easily cleaned and sanitized; pizza was not held at proper temperature; time in lieu of temperature was being used to control ready-to-eat, potentially hazardous foods without written procedures or documentation to verify disposition of food; no consumer advisory posted on the breakfast menu; no hood system with fire suppression for frying foods which produce a grease-laden vapor; wiping cloth sanitizer below proper levels; plumbing system not maintained in good repair; invalid food employee certification.
Comment: Owner Anthony Mentzel said violations have been corrected and the restaurant is waiting on a follow-up inspection.
Aunt Bee's Candies, 208 E. Chestnut St., Hanover.
Action: Violations included plastic food containers with sticker/label residue; no handwash sink in the immediate area of the food stand; lights not shielded or shatterproof above the service counter/candy area.
Comment: A manager could not be reached.
Kennie's Market, 440 N. Main St., Spring Grove.
Action: Violations included toxic levels of ammonia sanitizer; inadequate packaging records and procedures; plastic bowls used as scoops inside food-storage containers; possible cross contamination (raw chicken displayed above raw beef in the fresh meat case); possible cross contamination during packaging; time in lieu of temperature being used to control ready-to-eat, potentially hazardous foods; improper labeling; reuse of single-use items; no sign or poster at the handwash sink in the bakery area reminding food employees to wash their hands.
Comment: A manager did not return calls seeking comment.
IN COMPLIANCE
Central York High School, 601 Mundis Mill Road, York.
Candadochly Evangelical, 4845 E. Prospect Road, York.
]]></text></news-item>