<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="960D-6B3B-1D07-1E69"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Acknowledge what works already with voluntary sector groups; First Person Geoff Ogden, director (Hon), The High Sheriffs' and Humberside Police Tribune Trust</title><source>Hull Daily Mail</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[THIRTEEN voluntary sector youth organisations in Hull all supported by the High Sheriffs' and Humberside Police Tribune Trust met recently to outline their work, share experiences and improve joint working for the benefit of disadvantaged young people in the city.
They included Maximum Life Youth, Hessle Road Network, Child Dynamix, Pet Respect, Longhill Link Up Trust, Bridge Project, North Bransholme, Quality Personal Development, Rainbow Gardens, North Hull, No Way Trust, Kingston Boxing Club, NSPCC Face To Face Project, Humbercare and Corner House Children At Risk Of Exploitation Project. Between them, they work with more than 2,000 young people a week but many more thousands have been supported over the years in well-structured programmes.
The overall theme of all the projects is a very strong emphasis on helping those young people most at risk and never giving up on them.
Several of the projects are quite new but via the networks available will enhance services significantly.
The range of intensive support provided includes leaving care, employability, education, social responsibility, sexual exploitation, drugs crime, safe internet use, families and respecting animals - acknowledging that there are strong links with animal cruelty and other forms of abuse.
All the projects understand value for money and have limited resources.
They achieve impressive results for the young people and families they support and, by doing so, the wider community in Hull.
In the short and succinct presentations made, while acknowledging that we are in a period of austerity, there was no complaining about funding, only the sharing of ideas, staff, volunteers, premises and outreach work to enhance voluntary sector services.
At a time when there is a chance once again of initiative overload with new larger projects nationally and locally being introduced, there needs to be a greater acknowledgment about what works already with small voluntary sector groups and social enterprises. They already deliver positive lifestyles, restorative justice and citizenship.
There is as ever a danger of the "old wine, new bottle syndrome" as people in senior positions think up ideas without realising the work is being done already but quietly and without fuss through so many amazing voluntary sector projects. These have the ability to respond quickly and together to new threats that young people face because they are closer to them than many statutory sector organisations.
Not to harness this network in the current difficult economic climate would be a shame. If these projects and others like them did not exist the social infrastructure of the region would collapse.
Do you have an opinion to share in our First Person feature? If so, email a 400 to 500-word article, with a paragraph explaining your connection to the subject matter, to firstperson@mailnewsmedia.co.uk We also need a head and shoulders picture and a daytime contact number.
]]></text></news-item>