<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9628-CF5F-8F1E-3683"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Moffit vs. Turner, coal ash, fest folds</title><source>The Asheville Citizen-Times (North Carolina)</source><author>By, Casey Blake</author><text><![CDATA[Have a favorite feed on social media? Want a closer look at who's behind a Twitter curtain? Find me at @CaseyBlakeACT on Twitter or email your ideas to cblake@citizen-times.com
Moffitt vs. Turner
Constituents are about as divergent in their takes on a disagreement between Rep. Tim Moffitt and challenger Brian Turner as the men claim to be, and the debate played out endlessly on social media late last week.
The candidates met privately at Travinia Italian Kitchen in Biltmore Park on Feb. 24, with Buncombe commissioner David King present. The two disagree over what transpired during the hourlong conversation, but Turner alleges Moffitt essentially asked him to drop out of the race, threatening him with the promise of a nasty negative campaign and offering him an alternative job with UNC-TV.
Turner has filed formal complaints with the state. Mofitt and King say he misunderstood, that no threats or offers were made.
The range of responses on social media - and presumably the voter pool as a whole - has been wide. Some are outraged by Moffitt's gall, calling him a "bully" and a "narcissist." Some say Turner comes off looking weak and naïve for calling him out. Neither candidate is coming out a clear winner or a victim in this one.
"It's unbelievable that 2 adult men could have a conversation and come away from it with such a polar opposite report of what transpired during the conversation," one Facebook commenter added.
Coal ash backlash
The Duke coal ash debate has found a fervent home on Twitter, and hundreds have taken to piling on the power company over a proposed rate hike to cover the costs of an environmental cleanup.
Toxic waste from the burning of coal has piled up in two unlined lagoons at Duke Energy's Lake Julian power plant for decades with little government oversight or public attention.
A break in an underground wastewater pipe that caused the spill of tons of coal ash slurry into the Dan River north of Greensboro a month ago moved the coal ash issue to the front burner.
Duke Energy CEO Lynn Good said last week Duke Energy will pay for the spill cleanup but suggested customers shoulder the cost of disposing what's in other ponds.
An online petition making the rounds on Twitter has garnered close to 400 signatures, demanding that "Governor McCrory hold Duke Energy responsible for 100 percent of the cost to clean up the disaster they created and to prevent coal ash from ever again polluting our water supply."
Mourning Mountain Oasis
The electronic music festival organizers dropped the bomb last week that the festival would be canceled this year while the Oasis team "presses pause" on the event.
Festival followers immediately took to Twitter and Facebook asking about refunds, alternative events, and, of course, asking why.
Event founder Ashley Capps made the announcement Monday, tweeting, "It can be difficult but letting go of things that aren't working is liberating, inspiring, and energizing. Next! @Mtn_Oasis #Asheville."
Full refunds will be issued and no "replacement" concerts have been set. Check out www.mountainoasisfestival.com for more on the fallen festival.
]]></text></news-item>