<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9718-6278-F98F-A476"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>A hazier, drier future?</title><source>TODAY (Singapore)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[HAZE
Chua Chin Wei: There were many episodes of fire last year. With drier weather, we can expect more accidental fires and if wind direction goes in a bad way, there could be a huge fire.
Jose Raymond: In terms of health and what could happen if there is a fatality, we have not really considered that lives are probably at stake. When the Transboundary Haze Pollution Bill is enacted, it will have some teeth because of the hefty fines and would probably drive some behaviour in the region. Companies would be fearful of getting fined and especially of the negative public relations. They would probably make efforts to ensure that their supply chain is not involved in burning.
Tejas Ewing: In the short term, there must be laws. In the long run, it is about consumer behaviour. In Europe, consumers try to follow the work being done on sustainable palm oil to be aware of their sources of palm oil, that it is not from illegal deforestation or burning. For that to happen, legislation must come first, usually starting at levels that are not quite what we want; we would prefer the fines to be higher. Organisations like the Singapore Environment Council must then increase awareness about what the public can do and how they can learn about the source of products and its relation to the haze and burning.
Chin Wei: Regional challenges remain the same: Ground capabilities in enforcement, putting out fires, addressing the culprits. These are the most difficult to address, especially if one looks at the land-based industries, say, the palm oil industry, which would comprise two million farmers and their practices such as slash-and-burn, whether intentionally or not.
DROUGHT
Chew Men Leong: U-Save plays an important role, allowing us to price water correctly, rather than subsidise it across the board; when households cannot pay their bills, we can intervene in a more targeted fashion. In any case, if one continually uses water below the national average, one would save on one's utility bills on a long-term basis and play a part in saving water.
Tejas: The hardest thing to do is to penalise heavy users of water. Very few countries have sorted this out. If Singapore could find an equitable way to penalise, more from an educational viewpoint, say, people who use over 200 per cent of the national average, it could be exported across the world.
Men Leong: We have a two-tier pricing. If you use over 40 cubic metres a month, we charge another price, which is a disincentive. There is always scope for review, but this has worked well.
路 Chua Chin Wei is Deputy Director and Fellow for Environment and Resources at the Singapore Institute of International Affairs
路 Jose Raymond is Executive Director of the Singapore Environment Council
路 Tejas Ewing is a sustainable development consultant
路 Chew Men Leong is Chief Executive Officer of the PUB
]]></text></news-item>