<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9766-2CDB-E207-83A1"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>The Cutting Edge - 17 March 2014</title><source>Sunday Nation (Kenya)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The hope residents of the Karen and Runda suburbs of Nairobi had in the youthful Jubilee leadership is fast waning.
INSECURITY RIFE
The hope residents of the Karen and Runda suburbs of Nairobi had in the youthful Jubilee leadership is fast waning, warns Sue McPhee, adding that the main reason is the rising incidence of carjackings and general insecurity.
"The people now sleep only after 5am because of the fear of break-ins.
We hear of whole blocks of flats raided from top to bottom, which was never the case before.
The President should show leadership on this the way he has done with the salary cut."
**********************************************************************
PROBE THIS GK LORRY
Joining the campaign to curb the wanton wastage of public resources, John Chege is inviting officials to establish whether a GK lorry (number withheld) that delivered building materials to a private construction site about 500 metres from the main gate of the Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology on March 13 had been cleared.
"Can the accounting officer confirm that this had been officially sanctioned," pleads John, whose contact is githakwa1952@yahoo.com
**********************************************************************
THERE'S NO REFUND
While the Higher Education Loans Board appreciates George Morara Abuga's appreciation of the funding that enabled him to pay for his university education, his claim about a pending refund is not true, says corporate communications officer Olive Metet.
"His refund was paid on June 24, 2013. However, we wish to congratulate him for repaying his loan. We call upon other loanees to take advantage of a penalty amnesty waiver that ends on May 30."
For more information, her contact is OMetet@helb.co.ke
**********************************************************************
WELL DONE KQ
A frequent flier and elite member of the Sky Team, Juliana Melanie is proud that Kenya Airways, has been strongly distinguishing itself for punctuality on both its domestic and overseas routes.
This, she adds, is crucial for passengers both on business and holiday travel.
"Delayed take-off and late arrivals are most frustrating as they disrupt scheduled arrangements.
Punctuality is the essence of client satisfaction. Keep it up, KQ; you do us proud."
Her contact is melsouz@yahoo.com
**********************************************************************
SHAPE UP CDSC
The Central Depository & Settlement Corporation (CDSC) is not in the good books of stocks investor Harrison Kabue, who wants the people advised on how to deal with such "monopolistic and monolithic institutions".
He has been unable to trade because his CDS account, No. 2526512, has been held up by the regulator.
"I have incurred losses from unexecuted orders, but they are not bothered about it. Competition promotes competency."
His contact is kabue2000@yahoo.com
**********************************************************************
JUBILEE SHIP LOSING DIRECTION
As the Jubilee ship appears to be running into strong headwinds over questionable decisions and projects, diehard supporter Dominic Cheres says it urgently needs redirection.
He adds: "We cannot just sit back and watch our vessel get lost on the high seas."
To salvage the situation, Dominic is calling for the restoration of the old Constitution, the suspension of the laptop and standard gauge railway projects, an audit of the civil servants' payroll, and the shelving of a plan to retrench government workers.
Have a steadfast day, won't you!
E-mail: watchman@ke.nationmedia.comor write to Watchman,POB 49010, Nairobi 00100.Fax 2213946.
]]></text></news-item>