<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9771-9183-6EAE-D70D"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Employee Care Consultant</title><source>Canadian Government News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Public Service Commission has issued the following Job Opportunity:
Employee Care ConsultantNova Scotia Liquor Corporation
Job Location: Halifax City
For over 80 years, the NSLC has been managing the safe and responsible sale of beverage alcohol in Nova Scotia, returning 100% of its profits to government to help fund key public services. As a true partner in our communities, the NSLC conducts its business with integrity and respect for the environment while supporting the sale of over $30 million in local products every year.
Employee Care Consultant
Reporting to the Manager, HR Services, the Employee Care Consultant is responsible for the development, implementation and administration of attendance support and accommodation programs, as well as managing the return to work process for all employees; supporting them in understanding the requirements for substantiating sick leave or WCB claims; and supporting managers in assisting employees to address return to work issues. The Employee Care Consultant uses and/or performs functional abilities assessments/demands analysis; assessments of cognitive demands/abilities; and applies ergonomic principles in workplace modification.
As the ideal candidate, you will have:
An undergraduate degree in a health related field (Nursing, Physiotherapy, Kinesiology or Occupational Therapy) 3 years’ experience performing complex disability case management in a unionized environment 3 years’ experience working with attendance support and accommodation programs Experience interpreting functional abilities assessments/demands analysis and assessments of cognitive demands/abilities, as a tool to return to work Experience in an Occupational Health/Human Resources capacity related to return to work, with direct involvement in data retrieval and analysis
We are looking for an Employee Care Consultant with high ethical standards, who demonstrates strong initiative and leadership and the ability to handle complex projects. The successful candidate will be innovative, resourceful and creative, and superior at critical thinking and problem solving. They will also have excellent interpersonal, facilitation and communication skills. If you possess the above attributes, we’d like to hear from you!
If you are interested in exploring this opportunity, please merge your resume and cover letter in one document and submit it by email to: recruiting@myNSLC.com no later than 4:00 pm on March 28, 2014 (MS Word or PDF attachments only please).
Please quote: #14007-CB Employee Care Consultant in your email.
To view a detailed job description of this position, please visit our Careers page at www.myNSLC.com/careers.
Thank you for your interest in the NSLC.
For further information please visit: http://www.careerbeacon.com
]]></text></news-item>