<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9793-7C44-D00F-EDB2"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Attorneys threaten to sue state over lagoon</title><source>The Stuart News/Port St. Lucie News (Stuart, Florida)</source><author>Scott Wylandscott.wyland@scripps.com</author><text><![CDATA[Septic tanks leaking sewage into the Indian River Lagoon could contribute to manatees dying and should be cleaned up immediately, even if that means compelling homeowners to scrap ailing systems, say two attorneys who threatened Thursday to sue the state Department of Health under federal law.
The attorneys are giving the Health Department 60 days to halt permitting on new septic systems and issue orders to fix or remove all septic tanks polluting the lagoon. After that, they’ll sue the agency under the Endangered Species Act.
They say they represent a Cocoa Beach eco-tour kayaking business called Fin Expeditions, as well as manatees, green turtles and marsh snakes, three species listed as endangered.
“It’s a clear violation of federal law,” said Christopher T. Byrd, an Orlando attorney who specializes in environmental law. “The condition of the lagoon is a dire situation.”
Byrd and attorney Lesley Blackner, of Palm Beach, sent the notice Thursday to state health officials, along with the U.S. Interior and Commerce departments.
When asked about the potential lawsuit, state health officials issued a
brief, prepared statement saying they referred the matter to the agency’s legal office to analyze.
“The Department has been an active partner in discussions regarding the Indian River Lagoon and has taken all necessary steps to protect the public health,” the statement said.
The Treasure Coast has 120,000 septic systems and the state has 2.7 million septic tanks.
Roughly half of these systems were installed before 1983, when stricter state rules went into effect. The older systems are considered by researchers to be the worst culprits, especially when they are buried on shoreline properties.
Some septic tanks as far away as Orlando could affect the lagoon, because the sewage can travel a long distance through canals, Byrd argued.
Sewage contains nitrogen and phosphorus, which spur algae blooms that overtake sea grass, a prime part of the lagoon’s food web and a staple in manatees’ diet.
Researchers debate about whether septic tanks or fertilizers contribute more nutrients to regional waterways.
Since 2011, about 47,000 acres of sea grass has vanished. More than 110 manatees have died in the past year, mostly in the northern lagoon.
Sewage taints the entire 156-mile lagoon, with areas in the central portion — namely Indian River County — showing amounts as high as Boston Harbor when raw sewage was dumped there, according to a 2011 analysis by Harbor Branch Oceanographic Institute.
Past efforts to increase regulation of septic tanks have met widespread resistance from conservative lawmakers and some property owners. A law that required statewide septic-tank inspections stirred a political backlash and was repealed soon after it went into effect in 2012.
And new systems are going into the ground. In late 2012, St. Lucie County commissioners unanimously approved 47 septic tanks for Riverbend, a waterfront subdivision near the troubled St. Lucie River. Critics worry the septic systems could further pollute a river still recovering from last year’s massive Lake Okeechobee discharges.
Byrd contends the state’s unwillingness to stop septic-tank pollution could make it necessary to kick it to federal court.
“That’s the beauty of a federal case — it goes above all the local jurisdictions and the state,” Byrd said.
A conservationist commended the attorneys’ effort but said septic pollution is only one of many things plaguing the lagoon.
“This problem is much bigger than that,” said Patrick Rose, executive director of Save the Manatee Club, based in Maitland. “It’s a lot of things that have come together to cause this calamity.”
The attorneys should prepare for a long battle, Rose said, adding “special interests and those that are polluting will line up” to fight any policy changes.
In 2000, his group sued the Army Corps of Engineers and the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service under the Endangered Species Act, arguing the agencies were lax in enforcing manatee protections.
They settled several years later, with the two agencies agreeing to enforce stricter rules on projects that could affect manatees and their habitat, Rose said.
Those cases need good science behind them, Rose said. “Rhetoric will never win a lawsuit.”
In the intent to sue, the attorneys point to 30 years of studies on how sewage can leach into groundwater, canals and nearby waterways. Some of the research they cite is from state regulatory agencies’ own studies, Byrd noted.
“We are ready for the long haul,” Byrd said. “It has to be a serious action because it’s a serious issue.”
Erik Martin, an environmental consultant, said he didn’t know enough about the prospective lawsuit to comment on it. However, he agreed more should be done to protect the green turtles from harmful contaminants.
“The lagoon is a very developmental habitat to green turtles,” said Martin, scientific director for Ecological Associates in Jensen Beach. “If there are pollutants going into the lagoon, they would be affected by that.”
The Endangered Species Act, Clean Water Act and other similar laws need to be enforced, said Richard Baker, president of the Pelican Island Audubon Society.
Septic tanks are designed to filter out solids but not nutrients that can seep into the lagoon, Baker said. For that reason, they’re OK on a 5-acre parcel, but not jammed together in a small area near a waterway, he said.
“People are getting concerned,” Baker said. “You have to come to a point where you’re saying, ‘No more.’ ”
See lagoon, 11A
Septic tanks leaking sewage into the Indian River Lagoon could contribute to manatees dying and should be cleaned up immediately, even if that means compelling homeowners to scrap ailing systems, say two attorneys who threatened Thursday to sue the state Department of Health under federal law.
The attorneys are giving the Health Department 60 days to halt permitting on new septic systems and issue orders to fix or remove all septic tanks polluting the lagoon. After that, they’ll sue the agency under the Endangered Species Act.
They say they represent a Cocoa Beach eco-tour kayaking business called Fin Expeditions, as well as manatees, green turtles and marsh snakes, three species listed as endangered.
“It’s a clear violation of federal law,” said Christopher T. Byrd, an Orlando attorney who specializes in environmental law. “The condition of the lagoon is a dire situation.”
Byrd and attorney Lesley Blackner, of Palm Beach, sent the notice Thursday to state health officials, along with the U.S. Interior and Commerce departments.
When asked about the potential lawsuit, state health officials issued a
brief, prepared statement saying they referred the matter to the agency’s legal office to analyze.
“The Department has been an active partner in discussions regarding the Indian River Lagoon and has taken all necessary steps to protect the public health,” the statement said.
The Treasure Coast has 120,000 septic systems and the state has 2.7 million septic tanks.
Roughly half of these systems were installed before 1983, when stricter state rules went into effect. The older systems are considered by researchers to be the worst culprits, especially when they are buried on shoreline properties.
Some septic tanks as far away as Orlando could affect the lagoon, because the sewage can travel a long distance through canals, Byrd argued.
Sewage contains nitrogen and phosphorus, which spur algae blooms that overtake sea grass, a prime part of the lagoon’s food web and a staple in manatees’ diet.
Researchers debate about whether septic tanks or fertilizers contribute more nutrients to regional waterways.
Since 2011, about 47,000 acres of sea grass has vanished. More than 110 manatees have died in the past year, mostly in the northern lagoon.
Sewage taints the entire 156-mile lagoon, with areas in the central portion — namely Indian River County — showing amounts as high as Boston Harbor when raw sewage was dumped there, according to a 2011 analysis by Harbor Branch Oceanographic Institute.
Past efforts to increase regulation of septic tanks have met widespread resistance from conservative lawmakers and some property owners. A law that required statewide septic-tank inspections stirred a political backlash and was repealed soon after it went into effect in 2012.
And new systems are going into the ground. In late 2012, St. Lucie County commissioners unanimously approved 47 septic tanks for Riverbend, a waterfront subdivision near the troubled St. Lucie River. Critics worry the septic systems could further pollute a river still recovering from last year’s massive Lake Okeechobee discharges.
Byrd contends the state’s unwillingness to stop septic-tank pollution could make it necessary to kick it to federal court.
“That’s the beauty of a federal case — it goes above all the local jurisdictions and the state,” Byrd said.
A conservationist commended the attorneys’ effort but said septic pollution is only one of many things plaguing the lagoon.
“This problem is much bigger than that,” said Patrick Rose, executive director of Save the Manatee Club, based in Maitland. “It’s a lot of things that have come together to cause this calamity.”
The attorneys should prepare for a long battle, Rose said, adding “special interests and those that are polluting will line up” to fight any policy changes.
In 2000, his group sued the Army Corps of Engineers and the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service under the Endangered Species Act, arguing the agencies were lax in enforcing manatee protections.
They settled several years later, with the two agencies agreeing to enforce stricter rules on projects that could affect manatees and their habitat, Rose said.
Those cases need good science behind them, Rose said. “Rhetoric will never win a lawsuit.”
In the intent to sue, the attorneys point to 30 years of studies on how sewage can leach into groundwater, canals and nearby waterways. Some of the research they cite is from state regulatory agencies’ own studies, Byrd noted.
“We are ready for the long haul,” Byrd said. “It has to be a serious action because it’s a serious issue.”
Erik Martin, an environmental consultant, said he didn’t know enough about the prospective lawsuit to comment on it. However, he agreed more should be done to protect the green turtles from harmful contaminants.
“The lagoon is a very developmental habitat to green turtles,” said Martin, scientific director for Ecological Associates in Jensen Beach. “If there are pollutants going into the lagoon, they would be affected by that.”
The Endangered Species Act, Clean Water Act and other similar laws need to be enforced, said Richard Baker, president of the Pelican Island Audubon Society.
Septic tanks are designed to filter out solids but not nutrients that can seep into the lagoon, Baker said. For that reason, they’re OK on a 5-acre parcel, but not jammed together in a small area near a waterway, he said.
“People are getting concerned,” Baker said. “You have to come to a point where you’re saying, ‘No more.’ ”
lagoon from 1A
]]></text></news-item>