<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="97B3-64DF-44A8-8798"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Alaska: Eligibility Technician IV (PCN 06-8431M)</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The State of Alaska has issued the following Job Vacancy:
Job #: 03323Job Title: Eligibility Technician IV (PCN 06-8431M)Opening Date/Time: Mon. 01/27/14 12:00 AM Alaska TimeClosing Date/Time: Thu. 02/06/14 5:00 PM Alaska TimePosition Open To: Alaska Residents OnlyJob Type: Full TimeRange: 17Salary: $4,480.00/MonthDepartment: Health & Social ServicesDivision: Public AssistanceLocation: Anchorage, AlaskaBargaining Unit: Supervisory
Job Description Benefits Supplemental Questions
Do you enjoy working with dedicated professionals?Do you enjoy helping others that are experiencing challenges?
Do you excel in a team-oriented work environment?Are you a leader who enjoys developing others skills?
Are you known as a leader who listens, works hard, and makes fair decisions?If so, this may be the position for you!
The Division of Public Assistance (DPA) is recruiting a full-time, Eligibility Technician IV, for the Gambell Office in Anchorage.
The Supervisor will lead a team of 10-12 Eligibility Technician II's and one (1) Eligibility Technician III with the scope of work focusing on customers that are newly applying or have on-going cases for Public Assistance programs.
The division is looking for a dedicated professional who has consistently demonstrated these strengths:
A strong work ethic Positive contributions to teams Excellent organizational skills Effective and respectful communication In-depth knowledge of the division's policies and procedures The ability to remain flexible and embrace new initiatives
The team is staffed with dedicated professionals who take pride in providing timely and accurate benefits, excel in customer service, and are committed to continuous improvement and teamwork. This position is responsible for planning, organizing, and managing the operations of a team who administer Public Assistance programs, as well as, monitoring workloads and team performance, which includes sampling cases to ensure quality. Training, coaching and mentoring staff are also primary responsibilities of the ET IV position. The selected applicant will also participate as an active member of the local and regional leadership teams and with other leaders in the division to ensure a smooth delivery of services.
We are seeking applicants demonstrating the following Knowledge, Skills, and Abilities (KSA's):
Demonstrated work experience supervising, monitoring, evaluating, coaching, mentoring, and training staff effectively in a team environment. Demonstrated work experience effectively directing the work of others, setting priorities, and coordinating assignments and activities. Demonstrated work experience demonstrating ability to interpret, apply, and convey complex program rules, regulations, and procedures governing public assistance to staff and customers. Knowledge of State personnel policies and procedures. Demonstrated work experience assisting upset individuals, resolving issues, and customer complaints in a satisfactory manner. Demonstrated work experience working independently in a deadline-oriented environment and establishing priorities with minimal supervision. Demonstrated work experience accurately and efficiently determining eligibility for Federal and State Public Assistance Programs. Demonstrated work experience providing guidance and training to staff in a lead or advanced worker role.
In your cover letter, please provide examples on your Knowledge, Skills, and Abilities as they pertain to the KEY RESPONSIBILITIES & DEMONSTRATED STRENGTHS listed above.
The Division of Public Assistance offers a dynamic team environment valuing staff with a strong commitment to ensuring a professional work environment and excellence in customer service while achieving performance outcomes.
For Further information please visit: http://agency.governmentjobs.com/alaska/
]]></text></news-item>