<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="97C5-F479-B191-EA3E"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Calendar - Monday, March 16, 2014</title><source>The Register-Herald (Beckley, West Virginia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Raleigh County Emergency Services Authority regular monthly meeting, 5 p.m., their office, 162 Industrial Park Road, Beaver. Public is welcome to attend.
MCNB Bank and Trust along with Raleigh County Humane Society will accept deposits for "Pet Bank," 85 Jerome Van Meter Drive, Beckley, through March 31. Bring pet food, animal treats, cat littler, shampoo, brushes or monetary donations. Today, stop for refreshments and "goodies" to celebrate. Donations can be dropped off 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Monday through Thursday and 9 a.m. to 6 p.m. Friday.
Free sign language class, 5 p.m., Mabscott Holiness Church, call 304-252-9684.
Coal City Chapter No. 136 Order of the Eastern Star meeting, 7:30 p.m., 204 Tingler St., Coal City.
Raleigh County Cycle Club Mountain and Road meeting, 7:30 p.m., Y Soccer Complex (for summer). Ride at 6 p.m. Call Craig Spurlock for more information at 304-731-0262.
Benefits counseling for coal miner and widow applicants for Federal Black Lung, 10 a.m. to noon, UMWA District 17, New Raleigh Road, Beckley. Sponsored by New River Health Association Inc., Scarbro. To register call Cathy Stover at the Breathing Center, 304-469-3261, or call the District 17 office, 304-252-0611.
SHAPED Coalition monthly meeting, noon to 1 p.m., Raleigh County Board of Education, basement conference room, Safe, Healthy, Active, Positive, Empowered and Drug-free, for those concerned about substance abuse in your community. Sponsored by the Raleigh County Family Resource Network. Call 304-255-3764.
Raleigh County Memorial Airport Authority meeting, 4:30 p.m., Airport Terminal Building.
Board of Commissioners of the Mount Hope Housing Authority, 5:30 p.m., community room, Midtown Terrace, Mount Hope. Agenda, approval of minutes, approval of disbursements, business that comes before the board.
Pyramid Counseling LLC Family Support Group meeting, 130 George St., Suite E-F, Beckley, for family members affected by addiction within their family, 6 to 7 p.m. Call 304-256-0200.
Celebrate Recovery meeting, First United Methodist Church, 217 S. Heber St., Beckley, program, 7 p.m., open share, 8 p.m. and refreshments, 9 p.m. A Christian recovery program to help overcome habits, hurts and hang-ups, based on eight principles from the Beatitudes and 12 Christ-centered steps to recovery. Call 304-252-3435.
Carolina Shag lessons, McBee's, Neville Street, Beckley. Basic at 6 p.m. and Basic Plus at 7 p.m. Call 304-228-9938.
Basic computer classes, 6 to 8 p.m., Mabscott Fire Department.
Beckley Duplicate Bridge Club, noon, Beckley Woman's Club, 202 Park Ave., Beckley. Call Fred Mason at 304-253-3464 or 304-255-4557.
Freedom Area Narcotics Anonymous meeting, The Learn Center, FMRS, South Eisenhower Drive, Beckley, 9 a.m.; First Presbyterian Church, 1809 W. Main St., Princeton, 7:30 p.m.; Summerlee Road School House, Oak Hill, 2:30 p.m.; Drop Inn Center, 325 Prince St., Beckley, 7 p.m.
Narcotics Anonymous meeting, 601 Nicholas St., Rupert (next to City Hall), 7 p.m. Call 304-667-3446.
Gamblers Anonymous meeting, FMRS Health Systems Inc., L.E.A.R.N. Center, 8 p.m. Call Brad Ball, 304-256-7144 or 304-256-7100.
AA meetings, Beckley Noon Group, Presbyterian Church, 203 S. Kanawha St., noon (OD; Beckley, Came to Believe Group, St. Stephen's Episcopal Church, 200 Virginia St., 8 p.m. (OD/); Oak Hill, St. Andrews Episcopal Church, 8 p.m., Kelly Avenue (OD**), Al-Anon; Webster Springs, St. Anne's Catholic Church, 160 McGraw Ave., 8 p.m. (OBB/); for information on any meetings, call 304-252-9444 or 1-800-333-5051.
SDT Girls Discussion Group, 5:30 to 7:30 p.m., CAC, REACHH, Family Resource Center. Call 304-466-2226.
TOPS WV No. 237 Mullens meeting, 5 to 6 p.m., Wesleyan Church, Rt. 54, call 304-294-6224.
West Virginia Specialized Family Care Program, for more information call Debbie Wiley at Raleigh County DHHR, 304-256-6930, ext. 78902.
WV Birth to Three, for more information or to make a referral, call 1-866-321-4728. Is your child moving, hearing, seeing, learning and talking like others his or her age?
Food distribution program, Lochgelly Baptist Church, for all seniors and veterans age 55 and older, sponsored by Women United for Christ. Must meet guidelines, provide proof of income and medical expenses, first-come, first-served. Call Margaret or Jo at 304-469-8709, leave name and number.
Problem Gamblers Help Network of W.Va., call 1-800-GAMBLER help-line or (304) 1-800-522-4700.
Birthright of Beckley, 10 a.m. to 1 p.m., free pregnancy test, confidential. Call 304-253-7656 or 1-800-550-4900.
MSCIL needs wheelchairs and/or other adaptive equipment for its Loan Closet. Donations accepted. Also referral service for sign language interpreting. Call 304-255-0122.
Teen-age pregnancy programs, Beckley-Raleigh County Health Department, 1602 Harper Road, Beckley. Programs are Family Planning Clinics, Immunizations, Prenatal Clinics, Preventive Services and General Medical Services.
Free hearing screening for senior citizens, Rainelle Medical Center. Call 304-438-6188 for appointment.
Free tutoring by the Fayette County Literacy Council, learn to read or improve reading skills, by appointment.
NARCONON, a nonprofit organization, helping people with drug addictions. Call 1-800-556-8885.
]]></text></news-item>