<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="97E3-8FBB-1F54-BC0F"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Iran: Roundup of Kerman Province Friday prayer sermons 14 Mar 14</title><source>BBC Monitoring Trans Caucasus UnitSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[In the Friday prayer sermons in Kerman Province, Friday imams focused on "resistant economy", the Iran-P5+1 nuclear talks, the recent statement by US President Barack Obama about the extension of sanctions, the meeting of the EU foreign policy chief with human rights activists in Tehran, and the approach of the death anniversary of the daughter of Prophet Muhammad, Fatimah, provincial TV reported on 14 March.
The Supreme Leader's representative in the province and Friday imam of Kerman, Ayatollah Ja'fari, said that "resistant economy requires double efforts and activities". He said that "the resistant economy doctrine which was stressed by the Supreme Leader several times is one of the ways of resisting enemies and the entire nation and authorities should keep this issue in mind". He said that this doctrine was aimed at the accurate and right use of the potential and resources.
The cleric also spoke about the nuclear talks between Iran and P5+1, and cited the Supreme Leader as saying that he was not optimistic about the talks but supported the authorities so that they proved to the world that the Islamic Republic was not seeking nuclear weapons. He added that "fortunately, the Iranian nation revealed the dirty essence of the global arrogance which is devoid of logic and violates human rights".
Regarding the recent statement by US President Barack Obama about the extension of sanctions, the cleric said that "despite the sabotage activities of the arrogance we will defeat enemies by following the guidelines of the foresighted leader".
He also condoled on the approach of the death anniversary of the daughter of Prophet Muhammad, Fatimah, and urged people to attend the Fatemiyeh mourning ceremonies.
The Friday imam of Narmashir, Hojjat ol-Eslam (Irannezhad?), spoke about the approach of the anniversary of the nationalization of the oil industry in Iran and stressed the importance of "resistant economy". He said that "by wide-scale production of crude oil we can build a progressing and global economy easily." He then referred to the approach of the anniversary of the chemical attack on Halabjah and condemned "the brutal action of the Baath regime in killing over 5,000 innocent people".
The Friday imam of Ravar, Hojjat ol-Eslam (Pirserfani?), touched on the address of Supreme Leader Ayatollah Ali Khamene'i to the members of the Assembly of Experts, and said that "enemies will never stop to be hostile and will always intend to hit Iran". Regarding the recent visits of the European delegations to Tehran and the "undiplomatic meetings" of the members of these delegations, he said relevant departments should be held responsible in this regard.
Source: Vision of the Islamic Republic of Iran Kerman Provincial TV, Kerman, in Persian 1630gmt 14 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>