<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="97FE-4B44-7CE6-A7D6"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>VERDICT STILL OUT ON VALUE OF TRAFFIC-LIGHT CAMERAS</title><source>Herald News (Passaic County, NJ)</source><author>John Cichowski; Email: cichowski@northjersey.com</author><text><![CDATA[Now might not be an ideal time for Governor Christie to jump headlong into another heated debate over traffic issues, but thousands of motorists caught on cameras while appearing to run red lights would probably like to know where he stands on New Jersey's nearly four-year effort to curb this dangerous practice.
So far, they've had a long wait.
The state Department of Transportation's third annual interim report on this controversial, five-year pilot plan to install cameras at more than 70 intersections was due in November. But Christie has been uncharacteristically taciturn when discussing the cameras. For the record, the U.S. attorney-turned-governor has said only that he believes people should obey the law by stopping on a red light.
Few issues are that black and white, especially the one involving red, green and amber. Except perhaps for rising taxes, no issue produces more public distress than those associated with cars -- as in big toll hikes, miles of unattended potholes, decals that identify teen drivers, long waiting lines that circle motor vehicle offices and, of course, traffic jams that last longer than a Russian movie.
Many critics believe traffic-light cameras rank highest on any list of hated traffic policies. According to them, the supposed public-safety benefits -- reducing crashes by freeing police for more complex duties -- are far outweighed by: 1, invasion of privacy; 2, greed exhibited by municipalities anticipating huge revenues; and 3, amber lights with timing so short that cameras all but guarantee catching unsuspecting innocents.
Chronic traffic problems can take a political toll. If he didn't know it already, Christie must have learned that lesson in January when emails surfaced tying some of his top aides to lane closures that caused hours of daily traffic jams in Fort Lee for five mornings last September. These disclosures suggested that his staff conspired with one of the governor's men at the Port Authority to close two of three lanes leading to the George Washington Bridge to punish the Fort Lee mayor for not supporting his reelection. Heads rolled soon thereafter.
"The red-light-camera program has always been such a hot-button issue," said Assemblyman John Wisniewski, chief sponsor of the camera law and the Democratic co-chairman of a legislative committee investigating the lane closures. "So maybe the governor doesn't want to deal with that at this time, particularly with the fallout from what happened at the ... bridge. And now he no longer seems to have a universally loyal following at his town meetings."
Spokesmen for the DOT and the governor, who was booed mercilessly by a handful of students at one of these meetings last week, did not respond to requests for comment.
But Assemblyman Declan O'Scanlon, a Christie loyalist and a chief traffic-light-camera opponent, insisted that the governor's office was simply being thorough in its review of the 2013 interim report.
"They just want to get it right," said the Monmouth County Republican. "I'm very skeptical of the people at DOT running the camera program, but I have every confidence in the people in Governor Christie's office."
At issue is the DOT's evaluation process.
The law, adopted under former Gov. Jon Corzine, calls for the DOT to assess the progress of the camera experiment in the prior year by submitting interim reports to the governor's office in the spring. The governor reviews it and usually makes it public by November. Despite political pushback, lawsuits and angry complaints about Big Brother and big revenue, the 2011 and 2012 reports attracted little attention because short-term data can be unreliable and the number of towns enrolled in the program, including Wayne, Palisades Park and Englewood Cliffs, was relatively small.
Officials in Newark, which has installed the most cameras, praised the program, but not every experience has been positive. One group of some 500,000 drivers won a class-action suit after arguing many municipalities weren't properly maintaining the timing mechanisms on many of their traffic lights, though each defendant gained only $6. In time, some of the 25 towns in the program -- most recently Brick Township -- withdrew from it, contending that the cameras did not lower the number of crashes.
But Douglas Bartlett, a retired DOT safety manager, made no apologies for a program he helped organize.
"We purposely made it a pilot program so we could work out some of the kinks in the first five years," Bartlett said. "We never said cameras would be perfect for every location in every town."
O'Scanlon, however, said his review showed camera companies and the DOT manipulated figures at some locations, partly by comparing two years of data against one year of statistics.
"It was bad science," he said.
In its executive summary, the 2012 report recommended "continued data collection and monitoring" after noting that "the data are still too limited to draw any definitive conclusions."
Charles Territo, a spokesman for Arizona-based Automatic Traffic Solutions, claimed a 60 percent statewide reduction in crashes as of last October in locations where his company's cameras operated.
"The number of drivers who get subsequent tickets is only 10 percent," Territo said, "so it's obvious that we're changing behavior."
With more recordings and many more tickets evaluated, the third-year report was expected to be more definitive. And once free of reelection distractions, the governor appeared ready to take a stand by either blessing the program, or if he couldn't find a way to kill it, some critics thought he might recommend changes that, in his view, might make it more effective.
"Good or bad, the report should be released," said Pam Fischer, former director of the state Division of Highway Traffic Safety. "The public should know."
Ridgewood lawyer Joseph Santoli, who represents clients who have fought camera tickets, agreed.
"They've had enough time," he said.
Email: cichowski@northjersey.com
]]></text></news-item>