<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9847-CBB6-60C8-D2C0"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Depleting resources</title><source>Daily The Pak Banker</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[There is little doubt that the rise of consumerism and the consequent increase in demand and production has led to large-scale environmental degradation over the past century. In response to this, the scientific community and various environmental organisations have worked tirelessly over the last few decades to educate consumers and regulators about the market’s effect on the environment. This development has led to a more environmentally conscious consumer that demands “greener” products. Unsurprisingly, there has been an increased effort from corporations and producers - especially in the private sector - to portray their products and their organisations as environmentally sustainable or “green”.
Despite these developments, the bigger picture tells us that environmental degradation still persists and much is still desired from the private sector in improving sustainability. Glaring examples of this include the Exxon Valdez incident and the recent oil spill in the Gulf of Mexico.
Average everyday consumers, sitting in front their TV screens, watching these events unfold thousands of miles away from the comfort of their living rooms may understandably feel that these events have no relation to them. However, nearly everything we own, from the furniture we sit on to the electronics we carry and the clothing we wear, are produced by corporations that are rapidly depleting the earth of its resources and leaving an irreversible footprint on the environment.
With measures such as recycling, eco-labeling and bio-trade, steps have been taken to educate the consumer and mitigate the damage. This has seen a surge in environmentally conscious consumers who buy electronics that consume relatively less energy and purchase foods with eco labels which certify that foods are grown free of chemicals such as insecticides and pesticides. While it is true that these products consume relatively less energy when used, consumers know very little about the resources that are used in production and the impact it has on the environment.
Environmental degradation and resource depletion are not the same thing as commonly perceived. Environmental degradation is the deterioration of the environment through depletion of resources such as air, water and soil, the destruction of ecosystems and the extinction of wildlife. Resource depletion is an economic term that refers to to the exhaustion of raw materials within a region.
An example of this is the latest trend of buying hybrid vehicles, which are advertised as more environmentally friendly because they consume less fuel when compared to a vehicle with a petrol or diesel engine. No car epitomizes this trend like the Toyota Prius. The Prius is sold in almost 80 countries and has sold more than 3 million units to consumers looking for better mileage while leaving a smaller carbon footprint. In addition, the US Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) rates it as the cleanest car in terms of smog-forming emissions.
However, upon examination of the resources used to produce a Prius and other hybrid vehicles, a radically different picture emerges. The nickel contained in many hybrid vehicle batteries is mined and smelted at a plant in Ontario, Canada that has caused so much damage to the surrounding environment that NASA has used the ‘dead zone’ around the plant to test moon rovers. The factory that produces the batteries is infamously known as the “Superstack” for the sulfur dioxide it has spread across Northern Ontario. According to the Canadian Greenpeace energy-coordinator David Martin, acid rain resulting from the emissions has resulted in destruction of all the plants in the area. After leaving the plant, the nickel travels to Europe, China, Japan and the United States – hardly an environmentally sound round-the-world trip for a single battery.
Surely, if a hybrid is so resource inefficient and environmentally irresponsible, other cars must be costing the environment drastically more? Surprisingly, no. The Hummer (every environmentalists nightmare) will last three times longer than a Prius and uses almost 50 percent less combined energy according to CNW Marketing. The Prius costs an average of $3.25 per mile driven over a lifetime of 100,000 miles - the expected lifespan of a hybrid. The Hummer, on the other hand, costs a mere $1.95 per mile to put on the road over an expected lifetime of 300,000 miles.
This trend is not limited to the motor vehicle industry. Electronics firms are increasingly starting to use various environmental statistics to persuade consumers to buy their products. On their website, Apple uses buzz-phrases such as “environmentally responsible” and “environmentally conscious” to describe its products. However, in the not-so-distant past, Greenpeace accused Apple of using environmentally hazardous materials such as PCB, lead, mercury, nickel, cadmium, phthalates, and chlorine in manufacturing their iPhones.
However, Apple is just a single drop in a sea of environmentally irresponsible producers. Extracting and processing materials for cell phones creates environmental and health problems all over the world. Transforming resources we extract from the earth (e.g., crude oil, copper, gold, palladium, silicon, etc.) into a product like a cell phone requires considerable amounts of energy and water, and generates large amounts of pollution and waste. An assessment by Mireille Faist Emmenegger of Switzerland has found that 40-50% of the environmental impacts over the life of a cell phone – including its production, use and disposal –occur during the single process of manufacturing printed wiring boards and integrated circuits.
This article does not aim to discourage consumers from buying products that have environmental claims, as many products do in fact mitigate environment damage. However, instead of buying these products, consumers can be more environmentally responsible by extending the life of the products that they currently own.
According to Mireille Faist Emmenegger, instead of buying a cell phone every year, extending the service life of our current phones from one to four years decreases the environmental impacts by about 40%. In the same vein, by continuing to drive the cars that we currently own, we can save several tons of natural resources that will go into manufacturing new hybrids. It may be true that a new product on the market is less harmful to the environment than the previous one, it is still being produced and every unit produced depletes the environment of vital resources.
]]></text></news-item>