<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9863-D5E1-4990-6493"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Roxbury mayor to DEP: Halt dump plan</title><source>Daily Record (Morristown, New Jersey)</source><author>By, William Westhoven</author><text><![CDATA[ROXBURY - Three days after a state Department of Environmental Protection presentation further angered residents already upset about Fenimore Landfill, Mayor Jim Rilee labeled the DEP remediation plan "wholly inadequate" and demanded that the state provide more data to support its conclusions.
"We were extremely disappointed with the presentation made by DEP officials at our council meeting on Tuesday," Rilee wrote in a news release. "The health and safety of Roxbury residents must be the most important consideration in determining how to repair the significant damage done to our community because of the reopening of the landfill. Clearly, the DEP was not adequately prepared to respond to questions from residents," said Rilee, who also serves as the chairman of the New Jersey Highlands Council.
Rilee wrote that he contacted DEP Commissioner Bob Martin's office on Friday and said the DEP should stop any action it plans to take if it would rule out implementing other remediation options in the future, including trucking out the material that was dumped in the landfill. He also said DEP officials failed to adequately address residents' concerns about air and water quality.
State Sen. Anthony R. Bucco, R-Morris, who co-sponsored a bill passed in Trenton allowing the DEP to seize the site, also criticized the DEP in a news release on Friday.
"I am disappointed that DEP representatives only came to tell hundreds of resident victims how they would cap the landfill, rather than conduct a true hearing to fully listen and take into consideration information from those suffering in the community that have performed extensive research on this issue," Bucco wrote. "When government forgets even for a moment that it is beholden to the people, everyone loses."
"The DEP brought in an engineering firm that analyzed options for the best way to protect the health of the community - and that best option is to cap the landfill and seal in the material producing the hydrogen sulfide so that it can no longer produce the gas," a DEP spokesperson wrote in an email reply to the Bucco and Rilee comments. "The consultant's report showed that excavating would expose the entire community to uncontrolled release of hydrogen sulfide gas. In addition to Tuesday's presentation and Q&A session, we have posted all supporting data online, including the landfill closure plans and gas-abatement options."
The DEP PowerPoint presentations and related reports are available for view at http://nj.gov/ dep/fenimore/.
Bucco's and Rilee's comments echo concerns expressed by residents, who also were outraged to learn at the meeting that DEP planned to initiate its capping plan at the landfill within two weeks. Members of the Roxbury Environmental Action Coalition said they expected the meeting to be a two-way discussion with DEP about the options to eliminate hydrogen sulfide emissions from the landfill, which was reopened in 2010, more than two decades after it had been closed, but never capped.
But they quickly learned that DEP was going ahead with the capping plan and had rejected other options, including REACT's preference - excavating the offending materials brought in by new owners SEP Properties.
"We are outraged that the DEP failed to provide adequate supporting data showing their remediation plan is the most effective way to protect the health and safety of Roxbury residents," Rilee wrote. "The council demands that the state provide factual evidence that they are working on a solution that will ensure clean air and clean water for Roxbury's residents. Anything less is completely unacceptable."
Roxbury and the surrounding area have suffered the foul smell of the toxic gas since late 2012, and many residents have reported health problems, including migraine headaches and increased asthma attacks. When the gas was traced back to Fenimore, with the likely cause being wet gypsum drywall coming from debris of homes wrecked by superstorm Sandy, REACT lobbied to have the DEP take over the site. That seizure took place in June but the DEP's initial remediation efforts proved unsuccessful.
The situation improved over the winter as new remediation methods, along with cold temperatures and an ice cap, combined to contain emissions. But residents fear what will occur as spring warms the ground. Additional concerns have been raised about how the capping plan will affect the water supply in the area.
"This is too important a decision for the DEP to act without demonstrating to our satisfaction that they have thoroughly and completely considered all of the options," Rilee added. "The Council and I will continue to demand that the DEP show us compelling data that supports its conclusions and that its plan is based only on what is best for township residents."
Staff Writer William Westhoven: 973-428-6627; wwesthoven@
dailyrecord.com.
]]></text></news-item>