<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9865-0A82-1665-DB64"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Wide range of liquor brands ordered, will Tasmac deliver?</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Arun Janardhanan</author><text><![CDATA[CHENNAI: Like in many other states, tipplers in Tamil Nadu contribute considerably to the exchequer. However, the Tasmac-monopolised sale of liquor has been carried out according to the whims and fancies of the high and mighty who favour some brands and block some others, leaving customers high and dry.
Thursday’s Madras high court order criticising the state of Tasmac affairs may come as a relief for buyers, but the result of previous instructions on billing and maximum retail price are not very encouraging, feel many. On a petition filed by Golden Vats that the company received orders for only 28,300 cases while other companies received orders for 10 lakh cases for five months from July 2013, the court asked the government-owned liquor retailer to make all brands of liquor available in its outlets. “There should be a la carte system, and the consumer should be allowed to purchase according to his wishes,” the court held.
The problem is steeped in history. After former chief minister M G Ramachandran established Tasmac in 1983 as a wholesale vendor of alcohol in Tamil Nadu, it took two long decades for the government to open government-run retail outlets in the state, in 2003. The change in the status from the wholesale vendor to the retail vendor has not only established a state monopoly, but also led to the emergence of distilleries owned by politicians or those close to politicians.
In November last year, the country’s largest liquor company United Spirits, after it was acquired by British drinks giant Diageo, embarrassed the state by declaring their exit from TN. It said the new owner wouldn’t manage markets which could potentially violate international anti-graft laws.
A former secretary with the state prohibition and excise department said political parties have benefited from the situation. “Decisions on procurement and price are made at closed-door meetings attended by the excise minister and a couple of bureaucrats in consultation with a few company owners. Irrespective of which party is in power, all to parties get benefits from the preferred companies,” he said.
Justice K Chandru, retired judge of Madras high court, said the state liquor policies don’t protect customers’ rights and the right to commercially trade liquor. “The existing norms are in favour of a monopolised market, and the government has the right to maintain the monopoly. Drinking and selling liquor is not a constitutional right, unless there are valid reasons including medical.”
Admitting that favouritism and arbitrariness are common, a Tasmac official said the corporation believes that a majority of its customers are not brand-specific, but are price conscious. “When there are more than 20 distilleries in Kerala, we have 12. Our customers want cheap products,” he said.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>