<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9873-0C9C-2CBB-2560"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Robert Fulford: Pauline Marois is playing a dangerous game of make-believe</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Premier Pauline Marois has staged the April 7 provincial election as a dazzling revival of Quebec nationalism, a hugely depressing event. Through most of history, the spirit of nationalism has proven the best friend of hungry politicians and eager bureaucrats but no friend at all to most of humanity.
Nationalism glorifies the state while limiting the freedom of individuals. It encourages bigotry against outsiders and gives grievance-collectors a voice. It narrows the possibilities of creative community life. It celebrates uniformity and denies pluralism. It makes ugly demands on loyalty.
In pandering to voters who fear change, the Quebec government wants to make it illegal for a doctor or a teacher to wear a turban or hijab on the job. That bizarre twist on identity politics is a small taste of where nationalism can lead if, as Marois urges, Quebec becomes a separate country.
Politicians adore wielding power. Those who want it most are potential heads of government, such as would-be future Quebec President Pierre Karl Péladeau, who may be planning right now his first address to the UN General Assembly. Nationalism, as George Orwell said, is power-hunger tempered by self-deception.
Related
Weissenberger &; Koch: The power of nationalism in Quebec( http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2014/03/11/weissenberger-koch-the-power-of-nationalism-in-quebec/ )
Tasha Kheirridin: Marois' separatism talk isn't as crazy as it seems( http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2014/03/14/tasha-kheirridin-marois-separatism-talk-isnt-as-crazy-as-it-seems/ )
The self-deception that nationalism encourages takes the form of a giddy, mindless optimism. Nationalist thought nourishes itself on a dreamy vision of how great everything will be "after the revolution." Marois believes that her newborn nation will have open borders with Canada, which bearers of Quebec passports will cross freely, just as they do now. She believes the Canadian dollar will be Quebec's currency ("For sure," she says) and Quebec will get a seat on the board of the Bank of Canada.
Of course it will. Residents of the other nine provinces, after watching Canada dismantled, after a nightmare of costly inconvenience, after the great city of Montreal is turned against itself, after they have watched their currency depreciate and their economy tumble into recession - after all this pain, they'll be delighted to make any accommodation Quebec suggests.
This is pure fantasy, but it seems that a good many Quebeckers join Marois in her dangerous game of make-believe. It's more satisfying than reality.
History suggests that nationalism appears attractive but usually turns out to be a colossal disappointment
If the Bank of Canada, why not some seats in the federal cabinet? Or the senate? In return, perhaps members of the Order of Canada will be allowed to continue displaying their lapel buttons in Quebec, though not in government jobs.
As for the colleagues of Marois in the Parti Québécois, they are so addled by the prospect of victory that they changed their politics literally overnight. A week ago, the PQ was a democratic socialist party. But on Sunday, they were joined by a union-busting billionaire media baron who inherited much of his power from his dad. That transformed the PQ into a home for admirers of Thatcher and Reagan. Two former PQ premiers, Jacques Parizeau and Bernard Landry, have generously explained that it would be unfair to ask Péladeau to sell his shares in the family firm just because he's now in politics.
History suggests that nationalism appears attractive but usually turns out to be a colossal disappointment. A century and a half of passionate nationalism has made the Balkans what they are today. Generations of politically inspired nationalism have left the Arab states so fractious that they can't even come together in a common market. The Russians were so intoxicated by historic nationalism that they placed themselves in the hands of a braggart KGB agent who may well be leading them back to disaster. Iranian nationalists broke free of a monarch and his foreign supporters in 1979; today their children live under theocratic tyrants. In the 1950s, Algerians found themselves part of a highly imperfect French democracy. After a long, deadly battle with France they ended up as subjects of a long-term Algerian dictatorship.
Separatism would close off the great and beneficial project of Canadian unity, to which many lives have been devoted
In Turkey, the metastasizing of nationalism has been derailing a once promising democracy. A few years ago, a law went on the books providing a jail term for any Turk who "insults the Republic or Turkish Grand National Assembly." Prosecutors then retroactively charged the greatest Turkish writer, Orhan Pamuk, winner of the Nobel Prize, for stating (accurately) that a million Armenians were killed in Turkey. A technicality freed him, but nationalism-crazed Turks burned his books at public rallies.
With separatism once more a possibility and Péladeau threatening "to make Quebec a country," the nine English-language provinces should be worried. Separatism would close off the great and beneficial project of Canadian unity, to which many lives have been devoted. But those who have the most to fear in this election are the people of Quebec, no matter how intoxicating some of them may find the rhetoric of nationalism.
National Post
robert.fulford@utoronto.ca
]]></text></news-item>