<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="997B-4628-12F4-240A"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Oklahoma: AG Pruitt Files Lawsuit against Chinese Company for Violating Antitrust Laws</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Department of Health, The State of Oklahoma has issued the following news release:
Oklahoma Attorney General Scott Pruitt on Thursday filed a lawsuit against a Chinese oil equipment supplier for selling equipment in Oklahoma at artificially low prices, gaining an unfair competitive advantage over lawfully licensed Oklahoma companies in violation of the state’s antitrust laws.
The lawsuit is the first of its kind filed in Oklahoma and one of the first lawsuits in the nation filed by an attorney general to stop business-related piracy.
The complaint, filed in Oklahoma County District Court, claims Chinese manufacturer Neway Valve Company stole manufacturing process related software that is used by several Oklahoma companies, including longtime oil equipment company, Kimray, then used the pirated technology to sell its competing equipment in Oklahoma at a lower price. Oklahoma’s lawsuit seeks penalties and an injunction against Neway for creating an unfair market and violating Oklahoma’s Antitrust Reform Act and Oklahoma common law.
“Law-abiding companies invest significant capital to license software to operate their businesses and serve their customers. The use of stolen software and other intellectual property by unscrupulous companies is unfair, unlawful and gives them an advantage over those companies who follow the law. Piracy is costing Oklahoma companies billions of dollars in lost revenue, impacting their ability to invest in their companies to create new jobs and bolster the Oklahoma economy. Any company that seeks a market advantage through piracy, should be held accountable,” Attorney General Pruitt said. “This lawsuit sends a message that Oklahoma will not tolerate those companies, both foreign and domestic, that seek to gain an unfair advantage by engaging in software piracy.”
Oklahoma manufacturing companies affected by software theft include Cameron, Balon Corporation, CIRCOR, and Kimray Inc., which collectively employ several thousand employees.
“At Kimray, we are proud of our heritage as a lawful company focused on quality products and good character. Piracy provides an unfair advantage and creates unlawful gain. In the long-term, it damages all parties involved. We appreciate the effort by Attorney General Pruitt and his office to address this issue,” said Tom Hill, CEO and Chairman of the Board at Kimray.
Oklahoma companies lost an estimated $3 billion in revenue between 2002 and 2012 due to global companies using pirated American software, according to a report by the Harvard Business School and National Association of Manufacturers. The study concluded American manufacturers lost $239.9 billion in revenue during the same time period and that the competitive advantage gained by violators decreased U.S. GDP by nearly $70 billion and led to the loss of 42,000 jobs nationally.
For further information please visit: hhttp://www.oag.ok.gov/
]]></text></news-item>