<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9988-B2D8-5172-BB25"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Washington: EXECUTIVE COMMUNICATIONS, ETC. -- (House of Representatives - March 14, 2014)</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Library of Congress, The Government of USA has issued the following news release:
Under clause 2 of rule XIV, executive communications were taken from the Speaker's table and referred as follows:
4995. A letter from the Chief Counsel, FEMA, Department of Homeland Security, transmitting the Department's final rule -- Suspension of Community Eligibility [Docket ID: FEMA-2013-0002] [Internal Agency Docket No.: FEMA-8323] received March 5, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Financial Services.
4996. A letter from the Director, Regulations Policy and Management Staff, Department of Health and Human Services, transmitting the Department's final rule -- Irradiation in the Production, Processing, and Handling of Food [Docket No.: FDA-1999-F-2405 (formerly 1999F-5522)] received March 5, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Energy and Commerce.
4997. A letter from the Director, Regulatory Management Division, Environmental Protection Agency, transmitting the Agency's final rule -- Approval and Promulgation of Implementation Plans; State of Missouri [EPA-R07-OAR-2013-0698; FRL-9907-32-Region 7] received March 4, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Energy and Commerce.
4998. A letter from the Director, Regulatory Management Division, Environmental Protection Agency, transmitting the Agency's final rule -- Approval and Promulgation of Implementation Plans; Washington: State Implementation Plan Miscellaneous Revisions [EPA-R10-OAR-2013-0628; FRL-9907-38-Region 10] received March 4, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Energy and Commerce.
4999. A letter from the Director, Regulatory Management Division, Environmental Protection Agency, transmitting the Agency's final rule -- Fluopicolide; Pesticide Tolerances [EPA-HQ-OPP-2012-0941; FRL-9906-19] received March 4, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Energy and Commerce.
5000. A letter from the Director, Regulatory Management Division, Environmental Protection Agency, transmitting the Agency's final rule -- Metconazole; Pesticide Tolerances [EPA-HQ-OPP-2013-0656; FRL-9906-13] received March 4, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Energy and Commerce.
5001. A letter from the Director, Regulatory Management Division, Environmental Protection Agency, transmitting the Agency's final rule -- Triflumizole; Pesticide Tolerances [EPA-HQ-OPP-2012-0949; FRL-9906-47] received March 4, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Energy and Commerce.
5002. A letter from the Deputy Assistant Administrator for Regulatory Programs, NMFS, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, transmitting the Administration's final rule -- Fisheries of the Caribbean, Gulf of Mexico, and South Atlantic; Revisions to Headboat Reporting Requirements for Species Managed by the Gulf of Mexico Fishery Management Council [Docket No.: 000002673-4053-02] (RIN: 0648-BD49) received March 5, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Natural Resources.
5003. A letter from the Acting Deputy Director, Office of Sustainable Fisheries, NMFS, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, transmitting the Administration's final rule -- Fisheries of the Exclusive Economic Zone Off Alaska; Reallocation of Pacific Cod in the Bering Sea and Aleutian Islands Management Area [Docket No.: 000008563-3148-02] (RIN: 0648-XD111) received March 5, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Natural Resources.
5004. A letter from the Acting Deputy Director, Office of Sustainable Fisheries, NMFS, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, transmitting the Administration's final -- rule Fisheries of the Caribbean, Gulf of Mexico, and South Atlantic; Coastal Migratory Pelagic Resources of the Gulf of Mexico and South Atlantic [Docket No.: 000006604-1758-02] (RIN: 0648-XC464) received February 26, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Natural Resources.
5005. A letter from the Deputy Director, Office of Sustainable Fisheries, NMFS, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, transmitting the Administration's final rule -- Fisheries of the Exclusive Economic Zone Off Alaska; Pacific Cod by Catcher Vessels Greater Than or Equal to 60 feet Length Overall Using Pot Gear in the Bering Sea and Aleutian Islands Management Area [Docket No.: 000008563-3148-02] (RIN: 0648-XD101) received February 26, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Natural Resources.
5006. A letter from the Deputy Assistant Administrator for Regulatory Programs, NMFS, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, transmitting the Administration's final rule -- National Appeals Office Rules of Procedure [Docket No.: 000009524-3999-02] (RIN: 0648-BA36) received February 26, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Natural Resources.
5007. A letter from the Attorney-Advisor, Department of Homeland Security, transmitting the Department's final rule -- Safety Zone for Ice Conditions; Baltimore Captain of the Port Zone [Docket Number: USCG-2013-0509] (RIN: 1625-AA00) received February 25, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure.
5008. A letter from the Attorney-Advisor, Department of Homeland Security, transmitting the Department's final rule -- Safety; Alaska Marine Highway System Port Valdez Ferry Terminal, Port Valdez; Valdez, AK [Docket No.: USCG-2012-0365] (RIN: 1625-AA00) received February 26, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure.
5009. A letter from the Attorney-Advisor, Department of Homeland Security, transmitting the Department's final rule -- Security Zone; Mississippi River, New Orleans, LA [Docket No.: USCG-2013-0994] (RIN: 1625-AA87) received February 26, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure.
5010. A letter from the Attorney-Advisor, Department of Homeland Security, transmitting the Department's final rule -- Security Zone, Potomac and Anacostia Rivers; Washington, DC [Docket No.: USCG-2013-1050] (RIN: 1625-AA87) received February 26, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure.
5011. A letter from the Attorney-Advisor, Department of Homeland Security, transmitting the Department's final rule -- Security Zone; North American International Auto Show; Detroit River, Detroit, MI [Docket No.: USCG-2013-0034] (RIN: 1625-AA87) received February 26, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure.
5012. A letter from the Attorney Advisor, Department of Homeland Security, transmitting the Department's final rule -- Security Zone; On the Waters in Kailua Bay, Oahu, HI [Docket No.: USCG-2013-0934] (RIN: 1625-AA87) received February 26, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure.
5013. A letter from the Director, Regulatory Management Division, Environmental Protection Agency, transmitting the Agency's final rule -- Effluent Limitations Guidelines and Standards for the Construction and Development Point Source Category [EPA-HQ-OW-2010-0884; FRL-9906-51-OW] (RIN: 2040-AF44) received March 4, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure.
5014. A letter from the Chief, Publications and Regulations, Internal Revenue Service, transmitting the Service's final rule -- Method Changes for Tangible Property Dispositions (Rev. Proc. 2014-17) received March 6, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Ways and Means.
5015. A letter from the Chief, Publications and Regulations Branch, Internal Revenue Service, transmitting the Service's final rule -- Annual price inflation adjustments for passenger automobiles first placed in service or leased in 2014 (Rev. Proc. 2014-21) received February 27, 2014, pursuant to 5 U.S.C. 801(a)(1)(A); to the Committee on Ways and Means.
For more information please visit: http://thomas.loc.gov
]]></text></news-item>