<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="99F6-CFC8-9AB9-5EB5"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Lifescript: Italy prosecutors open probe against Roche, Novartis executives</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
ROME (Reuters) - Prosecutors in Rome have opened an investigation into four executives at Swiss drugmakers Roche and Novartis on suspicion of fraud and manipulation of the pharmaceutical market, judicial sources said on Friday.
Earlier this month, Italy's antitrust authorities said Roche and Novartis colluded to try to stop cancer drug Avastin from being used to treat a serious eye disease and fined the companies 182.5 million euros ($251 million).
A Novartis spokesman had no immediate comment, while a Roche spokesman referred to the company statement issued after the antitrust ruling that called the charges "unfounded" and said it would appeal.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/14/italy_prosecutors_open_probe_against_roche_novartis_executives.aspx
COMPANY BACKGROUND
ACTIVITIES
LifeScript is a online publishing company based in Mission Viejo, CA.
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
14 March 2014: Lifescript: Breastfeeding past two years linked to infant tooth decay
NEW YORK (Reuters Health) - Breastfeeding is credited with a long list of benefits, but one downside of extended and intensive breastfeeding may be a higher risk of cavities in baby's first teeth, according to a new study. The more frequently a mother breastfed her child beyond the age of 24 months during the day, the greater the child's risk of severe early tooth decay, researchers found. "The No.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/14/breastfeeding_past_two_years_linked_to_infant_tooth_decay.aspx
14 March 2014: Lifescript: Gates Foundation awards Notre Dame $23 million for malaria, dengue studies
(Reuters) - The Bill & Melinda Gates Foundation has awarded $23 million for research being led by University of Notre Dame biologists to prevent malaria and dengue fever, the school said. The five-year project by biologists Neil Lobo and Nicole Achee aims to show the effectiveness of a new method of mosquito control, called spatial repellency, in quelling the illnesses, the university said in a statement this week. According to the World Health Organization, 207 million cases of malaria were reported in 2012, and 50 million to 100 million dengue infections occur yearly. Both the malaria parasite and dengue virus are transmitted through the bites of infected mosquitoes.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/14/gates_foundation_awards_notre_dame_23_million_for_malaria_dengue_studies.aspx
14 March 2014: Lifescript: 'Dead' Mississippi man who kicked out of body bag has died
JACKSON, Mississippi (Reuters) - A Mississippi man pronounced dead last month and put in a body bag only to come alive just before embalming, has now died, a coroner said on Thursday. Walter Williams, 78, died at about 1 a.m. local time in Lexington, two weeks after shocking people when he started breathing and kicking at a funeral home where he was taken after being declared dead, said Holmes County Coroner Dexter Howard. "I think he's gone this time," Williams' nephew, Eddie Hester, told a local television station. Williams had been receiving hospice care at home for end-stage cardiovascular disease and other ailments before his near-death experience on February 27.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/14/dead_mississippi_man_who_kicked_out_of_body_bag_has_died.aspx
13 March 2014: Lifescript: U.S. FDA chief defends approval of Zogenix's 'unique' pain drug Zohydro
WASHINGTON (Reuters) - U.S. Food and Drug Administration Commissioner Margaret Hamburg on Thursday defended the agency's approval of Zogenix Inc's Zohydro, saying the powerful prescription opioid offered a unique option to help treat pain. Law enforcement officials, doctors and addiction treatment specialists are concerned that Zohydro would set off a wave of addiction similar to problems with the original form of OxyContin. Hamburg, responding to a query from a U.S.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/13/us_fda_chief_defends_approval_of_zogenixs_unique_pain_drug_zohydro.aspx
13 March 2014: Lifescript: Mindfulness meditation can cut chocolate cravings
NEW YORK (Reuters Health) - Looking to cut cravings? A recent study suggests the key may be attaining a sense of detachment from them through a form of meditation with roots in Buddhism. Practicing mindfulness meditation, which emphasizes identifying and distancing oneself from certain thoughts - without judging them - weakened chocolate cravings among people with a self-declared sweet tooth, Canadian researchers say. "There is now good evidence that mindfulness strategies generally work at managing food cravings, but we don't yet know what aspect of mindfulness and what mechanisms are responsible for these effects.
click http://www.lifescript.com/health/news/reuters/2014/03/13/mindfulness_meditation_can_cut_chocolate_cravings.aspx
]]></text></news-item>