<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9A06-B8F3-6788-80A9"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Politicians frustrating medical-pot growers in Okanagan: lawyer</title><source>Prince George Citizen (British Columbia)</source><author>Don Plant, The Canadian Press</author><text><![CDATA[Medical-marijuana growers in British Columbia's Okanagan Valley are growing frustrated with local politicians who are banning their operations from farmland, says a lawyer.
More than 1,000 adults in Kelowna have federal approval to grow pot at home for medical reasons, but Health Canada is switching to large-scale producers so people who are allowed to use cannabis can continue to get a supply.
However, West Kelowna's council voted this week to restrict commercial pot producers to industrial land, and the City of Kelowna could do the same after a public hearing on Tuesday.
Two weeks ago, city councillors in Kelowna practically rejected any notion that operators could set up on farmland within city limits.
The City of Vernon is also considering a proposal to zone the large grow operations.
Jennifer Thorne, a Kelowna lawyer representing more than 10 clients who have applied to Health Canada for growing permits, said she is infuriated by the misinformation area politicians have been working with.
"Nobody's doing their homework," she said, noting there's a misconception out there that the grow operations are a mask for the criminal element.
"These new facilities will be more akin to running a liquor store or a pharmacy. We're talking about professional business people with training and experience."
She said the new legislation makes the larger-scale operations so secure and accountable, they're almost impregnable.
In fact, Health Canada's marijuana for medical purposes regulations demand strict standards for on-site security and criminal background checks.
To prevent money laundering or other crimes, applicants undergo rigid screening and must reveal in detail where they earned their income over the last decade.
Kelowna Coun. Colin Basran said he is now reconsidering his vote of two weeks ago and plans to keep an open mind at the public hearing.
Basran said he is happy that largescale facilities are unwelcome in residential neighbourhoods. But he said he is now concerned about fairness. Basran said medicalmarijuana growers can operate on agricultural land just outside the city limits and in the regional district thanks to the Municipal Act.
"How can we say to our Kelowna growers 'you can't do it, but your neighbour in the regional district can?' "That's part of my frustration ... How does that make sense?" Thorne said a new industry is emerging in the province, and the Okanagan has the farmland and expertise to cash in.
"We have so much knowledge and experience here that I think we should be capitalizing on," she said. "This could be a great industry for B.C. "It could be world-renowned because not only does this legislation allow you to grow, but you can export and import. I see a real opportunity."
]]></text></news-item>