<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9A09-57F2-00C5-1D27"><date>2014-03-14</date><title></title><source>South China Morning Post</source><author>Name Name name.name@scmp.com</author><text><![CDATA[Chongqing Balcony victim recovering
A two-year-old boy thrown from a 25th-floor balcony by a girl aged 10 has recovered from brain surgery and is able to once again walk independently, the Nanfang Daily reports. The tragedy happened on November 25 when the girl beat up the boy, in the lift of an apartment block, kicked him in the head, and then took him to her 25th-floor flat where she continued to assault him. The girl said she then "played with the boy" on the balcony and he fell off. The report said the girl was too young to be detained or charged and her family has paid 78,000 yuan (HK$98,600) for the boy's medical treatment.
An elderly couple called the police and asked for help to evict their unemployed son and daughter-in-law from their apartment, Xinhuanet.com reports. The couple said the young couple had not worked, studied or trained for several years and were living off their pensions. They said they were forced to demand the pair leave because they had no money left to pay their doctor's bills.
Fujian
Man 'kept sex slaves'
A man in his 30s has been arrested in Fuzhou on charges of raping two woman and trying to keep them in a rented dog kennel as sex slaves, Fjsen.com reports. On July 29 last year, the man lured the two victims - a sex worker and a jobseeker - to the remote kennel and locked them in. One of the women escaped later that night and called the police.
Four men were detained on Tuesday for hunting hundreds of stray and pet cats since last month in Putian , the Putian Evening News reports. The paper said the men caught and killed dozens of cats each night. They froze the carcasses and sold them to local restaurants for between 10 yuan and 25 yuan each.
Guangdong
A job fair in Shenzhen had to close because of a shortage of jobseekers, the Shenzhen Daily reports. The annual one-day event opened on Wednesday morning at the Shenzhen Convention and Exhibition Centre, but closed around 2pm as most booths had been left without visitors since before noon. The fair, which opened in 1999, has seen as many as 32,000 visitors in previous years. This year, more than 300 companies were offering about 12,000 positions.
A senior Shenzhen housing official has been removed from his post for using an official car to drive to dinner with friends, the Southern Metropolis Daily reports. The city housing and construction bureau said the employee, who worked for the policy and regulation department, used the vehicle after work. Last month, a city department head received an internal Communist Party disciplinary warning for using official vehicles while travelling to play golf.
Henan
A man bought a car with 119,300 yuan in one-yuan notes and coins, China News Services reports. The buyer, a snack vendor in Handan , said purchasing a car was a good way to spend his pile of small-denomination cash. He paid for the vehicle using 103,000 one-yuan-notes and 16,300 one-yuan-coins.
More than 80 new cars worth over 10 million yuan burned in two separate fires on Wednesday in Zhengzhou , Dahe.cn reports. The fires broke out at different car dealers. Police are still investigating the cause of the fires but there are believed to be no witnesses.
Two men have been detained by police for a credit card scam which involved them pretending to be bank managers and tricking eight people into increasing their credit limits, Eastday.com reports. One of the victims said he handed over his credit cards and paid 6,000 yuan to a man who said he could increase his credit limits to up to 200,000 yuan. Thirty minutes later the victim received a message from his bank saying 49,000 yuan had been withdrawn from his accounts.
An owner of a food-processing company has been sentenced to five years in jail for using out-of-date mooncakes left unsold in 2011 as raw materials to make more mooncakes the following year, the Oriental Morning Post reports. The paper said that the food-processing company owner was also fined 1 million yuan by the No1 Intermediate People's Court.
Shaanxi
A patient's relative who slapped a nurse in a traditional Chinese medicine hospital in Ankang was given a suspended five-day detention by Hanbin district police on Wednesday, the Sanqin Daily reports. The Monday outburst was triggered by a dispute over medical fees. The hospital charged the patient an extra 5 yuan for moving a electrocardiogram machine to her ward. Surveillance video showed the relative quarrelling with a male nurse over the charge when she suddenly slapped a woman nurse seated beside him. The hospital then reported the case to the district police bureau.
A 29-year-old man is being hunted by police in Weinan on suspicion of killing a family of four on Wednesday, including a four-year-old boy, Cnwest.com reports. A woman, two of her adult daughters and her grandson were all found dead at home when a school bus driver came to pick up the boy. Police believe the suspect is the boyfriend of one of the woman's daughters.
About 2,200 people backed up by a helicopter have been battling a forest fire which started on Wednesday morning in Lufeng county, Xinhuanet.com reports. The fire broke out at about 1.30am on Mount Wangjiajian near Maguanying village. The authorities are investigating the cause of the fire and the area of forest it has scorched. It was the second fire in the county within a week. An earlier blaze, which started on Saturday afternoon, was tackled by 250 forest rangers and 2,300 volunteers.
An official from the Dali tobacco bureau had been sentenced to six years for embezzling 130,000 yuan in public money, the Kunming Daily reports. The man was charged with stealing wages of temporary workers and money from research projects over a decade.
Zhejiang
Ningbo has approved a plan to build a second bridge across Hangzhou Bay between Shanghai and the city, Xinmin.cn reports. The 66 kilometre road-and-rail bridge, will reduce the distance between the cities to 160 kilometres from 200 kilometres.
More than 12,500 couples, of whom one partner must be an only child, applied to have a second child between January 17 and February 28, Zjol.com reports. Zhejiang became the first province to relax the birth control policy in January. The authorities estimate that about 100,000 couples each year will have a second child by 2018.
]]></text></news-item>