<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9A91-C9FA-880E-A6DD"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>FCI employee arrested on bribery charges</title><source>The News-Times (Danbury, Connecticut)</source><author>Dirk Perrefort, The News-Times, Danbury, Conn.</author><text><![CDATA[March 15--DANBURY -- A case manager at the Federal Correctional Institution in the city was arrested by authorities Friday and charged with participating in a scheme that collected cash from inmates in exchange for a recommendation for early release.
According to a statement released Friday by the U.S. Attorney's Office, Kisha Perkins, 42, of Waterbury, was charged with aiding and abetting a bribery scheme of a public official, which carries a sentence of up to 15 years in prison.
Authorities said Perkins, who was described as the prison's "unit counselor," approached another employee at the prison in June about an opportunity to participate in a bribery scheme.
Perkins allegedly told the other employee that an inmate's husband was willing to pay $20,000 in exchange for a recommendation that the prisoner be released early into a halfway house, authorities said.
Perkins was not authorized to give such recommendations at the time, but her co-worker was.
The employee, whose name was not released, contacted law enforcement officials about the conversation and agreed to cooperate in an investigation that included a number of recorded conversations.
While the co-worker told Perkins in July that she wanted to take part in the scheme, Perkins told the employee that the previous deal was no longer available.
Perkins, however, approached her co-worker in February with a similar scheme involving another inmate, authorities said.
On March 8, Perkins and the co-worker traveled to a commuter parking lot off Interstate 84 to pick up a partial bribe payment of $5,000 from someone Perkins believed was an acquaintance of the inmate, according to the statement released Friday.
Perkins was arrested in her home Friday by agents with the FBI and was held on a $100,000 bond after her appearance before U.S. Magistrate Judge Joan G. Margolis in New Haven.
"Plainly and simply, the FBI has zero tolerance for corruption of any kind, at any level of government," said FBI Special Agent in Charge Ferrick.
"The allegations in the complaint are clearly very serious crimes. And the resulting law enforcement response to committing those crimes should be equally clear," he added.
"If you put your position of trust with the government up for sale, you will be investigated and prosecuted to the fullest extent of the law."
dperrefort@newstimes.com; 203-731-3358; www.twitter.com/DirkPerrefort
___ (c)2014 The News-Times (Danbury, Conn.) Visit The News-Times (Danbury, Conn.) at www.newstimes.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>