<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9AE9-F670-1CD1-2253"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Warrants for SSGC officials' arrest suspended</title><source>Dawn (Pakistan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Sindh High Court on Thursday suspended the operation of bailable warrants issued for the arrest of the managing director and other senior officials of the Sui Southern Gas Company Limited by a district court in Sanghar.
The district and sessions judge, Sanghar, on March 3 issued the bailable warrants for the arrest of the SSGC MD and other officials as they had failed to appear in court despite notices.
A two-judge bench headed by Chief Justice Maqbool Baqar ordered the suspension of operation of warrants while hearing the constitutional petition of the SSGC officials against the order of the district and sessions court.
The petitioners, represented by Advocate Asim Iqbal, submitted in the petition that the district judge, also director of the Human Rights Board, told the SSGC chief and other officials to appear before it on March 3 to submit their replies on a human rights petition filed by the Sanghar District Bar Association seeking sufficient gas supply to the district.
It was submitted that the SSGC officers could not appear as legal proceedings at the Sanghar district court were suspended in protest against the attack on the district courts in Islamabad on March 3.
The SSGC officials stated that the district judge issued bailable warrants for arrest of senior officials without conducting proceedings on that date and adjourned the hearing to March 18.
They stated that the district court did not have the jurisdiction to issue such orders against SSGC officials under the Companies Ordinance, 1984 in public interest litigations.
The petitioner requested the court to declare the issuance of the warrants for their arrest as illegal and restrain the district judge from issuing such orders.
The bench issued notices to the district judge and the Sanghar District Bar Association and put off the hearing to March 27.
Notices repeated
The same bench once again issued notices to the interior secretary, the director general of Rangers and others to submit their comments in a petition of the Muttahida Qaumi Movement against alleged extra-judicial killing of its activist Muhammad Adil. The bench directed the government law officer to file comments on the matter within three weeks and put off the hearing to April 8.
]]></text></news-item>