<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9B3A-38D9-3FA2-E677"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Washington: Human Resources Specialist Owcp Awards T9 Job in PITTSBURGH, PA</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[US Department of Veteran Affairs has issued the following job vacancies:
Human Resources Specialist Owcp Awards T9 Job in PITTSBURGH, PAVacancy No. HP-646-14-AS1071339 Department Veterans Affairs, Veterans Health AdministrationSalary $39,937.00 to $63,503.00 Grade 07 to 07Perm/Temp Permanent FT/PT Full-timeOpen Date 3/14/2014 Close Date 3/24/2014Job Link Apply Online Who may apply Status CandidatesLocations:PITTSBURGH, PA
Job Description (Please follow all instructions carefully)
Job Title:Human Resources Specialist (OWCP/Awards) GS-201-7, T9
Department:Department Of Veterans Affairs
Agency:Veterans Affairs, Veterans Health Administration
Job Announcement Number:HP-646-14-AS1071339SALARY RANGE: $39,937.00 to $63,503.00 / Per YearOPEN PERIOD: Friday, March 14, 2014 to Monday, March 24, 2014SERIES & GRADE: GS-0201-07POSITION INFORMATION: Full Time - Agency Employees OnlyPROMOTION POTENTIAL:9DUTY LOCATIONS: 1 vacancy in the following location:Pittsburgh, PAWHO MAY APPLY: Current Permanent VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System EmployeesSECURITY CLEARANCE: Public Trust - Background InvestigationSUPERVISORY STATUS: NoJOB SUMMARY:
Vacancy Identification Number (VIN) 1071339
Our Mission: To fulfill President Lincoln’s promise – “To care for him who shall have borne the battle, and for his widow, and his orphan” – by serving and honoring the men and women who are America’s Veterans. How would you like to become a part of a team providing compassionate care to Veterans?
WHO MAY APPLY: Current Permanent VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System Employees
Note: The incumbent, although assigned to the HJ Heinz facility, may be required to perform duty assignments at either of the two facilities (University Drive, and HJ Heinz) of VA Pittsburgh Healthcare System.
TRAVEL REQUIRED
Not Required
RELOCATION AUTHORIZED
No
KEY REQUIREMENTS
You must be a U.S. citizen to apply for this job. Subject to a background/suitability investigation. Registered with Selective Service
DUTIES:
OWCP Program Responsibilities
· Serves as the specialist on injury compensation claims and benefits issues.
· Resolves problems in the administration of this program.
· Responsibilities include the development and maintenance of local policies and regulations to implement this program; briefing management and serviced organizations on the status of this program; training employees and supervisors regarding the latest information; preparing communications to inform as large an audience as possible of current and future requirements and information; and serving as the policy and regulatory specialist for this program.
· Plans, organizes and conducts injury compensation seminars, to include the development of a training schedule based on accident rates, organization strengths, and similar issues.
· Coordinates with the Department of Labor, its subdivision (Office of Worker's Compensation), and other agencies and organizations in order to monitor the injury compensation program.
· Prepares feedback reports to management regarding injury compensation issues.
· Ensures that communication efforts with management and employees meet local needs.
· Coordinates with the HR recruitment staff and rehabilitation counselors in order to place employees who can perform limited-duty work.
· Coordinates with Occupational Health staff to ensure that medical determinations are reviewed; advises management of alternatives when medical documentation is not forthcoming from an employee.
· Coordinates with Resource Management staff to evaluate costs and reduce the number of compensation costs paid by the organization, Coordinates with the Safety Office to ensure that management is enforcing safety rules; reports violations to the servicing HR (Employee Relations) specialist or recommends appropriate disciplinary action to higher-level management.
· Works with the retirement specialist when an on-the-job injury results in death; advises and assists survivors in obtaining benefits.
· The emphasis of the work is on controlling costs associated with the program through intensive management of outstanding cases.
· The incumbent gives equal attention to identifying and pursuing the resolution of fraudulent claims, returning employees to productive work as quickly as possible, and removing employees from WC roles as appropriate.
· Counsels and trains employees, supervisors, and managers regarding their rights and obligations under the Federal Employees Compensation Act.
· Analyzes information related to on-the-job injuries or illnesses provided by supervisors and employees in support of on-the-job worker's compensation claims and provides timely advice and recommendations to management and supervisors on these claims.
· Remains cognizant of the latest changes as issued by Department of Labor or other committees.
Awards Program Responsibilities
· Reviews and evaluates all agency award recommendations to determine if technical requirement are met and appropriate justification is submitted.
· Provides technical advice to supervisors concerning necessary criteria.
· Determines bargaining or non-bargaining unit status of nominated employees and coordinates awards panel for review of all bargaining employee awards.
· Processes each award according to policy procedures.
· Composes announcements for external awards and special programs.
· Monitors special awards programs and advises supervisors and management of criteria for submitting nominees.
· Serves as the Local VAPHS coordinator of the Federal Executive Board Excellence in Government Award (FEB EIG) program and sits on the central FEB EIG committee.
· Maintains electronic database of all award data and provides various reports on this data as necessary.
· Codes all awards in accordance with PAID coding regulations.
· Provides station-wide training to supervisors on the Incentive Awards Program, identifies needs and takes initiative to implement any necessary further training as the program dictates.
This is a non-bargaining unit position.
Work Schedule: 8:00 am to 4:30 pm, Monday through FridayPosition Description Title/PD#: HR Specialist (OWCP/Awards) / PD#33240 Relocation Expenses: Relocation expenses are not authorized for this position.
QUALIFICATIONS REQUIRED:
To qualify for this position, applicants must meet all requirements by the closing date of this announcement.
Time-in-grade: Applicants who are current Federal employees and have held a GS grade any time in the past 52 weeks must also meet time-in-grade requirements. For the GS-7, 52 weeks at the GS-5 grade level.
QUALIFICATION REQUIREMENTS: GS-7: One (1) year of Specialized experience equivalent to the next lower grade level (GS-5) in the normal line of progression for the occupation in the organization; or One (1) full year of graduate level education or successful completion of a Bachelor Degree with Superior Academic Achievement; or equivalent combinations of successfully completed graduate education and specialized experience. Specialized experience is experience that has equipped the applicant with the particular knowledge, skills and abilities to perform successfully the duties of the position to be filled. Examples of specialized experience would typically include, but are not limited to experience administering an organization's injury compensation and awards programs or similar program/project management; acting as a liaison between supervisors and employees to facilitate claims; evaluating suspected fraud cases or performing investigative services; and experience providing training or guidance to supervisors and employees on practices and regulations of the injury compensation or similar program and/or experience reducing case workloads. Experience in reviewing/evaluating agency award recommendations for technical requirements or processing award recommendations.
A transcript must be submitted with your application if you are basing all or part of your qualifications on education.
Additional information on the qualification requirements is outlined in the OPM Qualifications Standards Handbook of General Schedule Positions. It is available for your review on OPM's web site at http://www.opm.gov/qualifications/standards/indexes/alpha-ndx.asp
Your application and/or resume must support the following Knowledge, Skills, and Abilities and responses to occupational questionnaire for this position. IN DESCRIBING YOUR EXPERIENCE, BE CLEAR AND SPECIFIC. WE WILL NOT MAKE ASSUMPTIONS REGARDING YOUR EXPERIENCE. Evidence of experience, must be supported by detailed documentation of duties performed in positions held on your resume/application. Also, provide work experience information such as hours per week and starting/ending dates of employment (month and year) to establish one (1) full year of experience.To qualify for this position.
1. Knowledge and application of Human Resource concepts, practices, laws, regulations, policies and precedents sufficient to provide advisory services and technical guidance on OWCP and Awards programs.
2. Ability to identify and resolve issues and problems.
3. Ability to effectively communicate to employees, management, and other federal agencies.
4. Skill in the use of analytical methods and techniques sufficient to identify, evaluate and recommend appropriate course of action.
If you are referred for consideration, you may be asked to submit additional job related information, which may include, but not limited to; responses to the knowledge, skills and abilities; completion of a work sample, and/or contact for an interview.
PLEASE NOTE: Education must be accredited by an accrediting institution recognized by the U.S. Department of Education in order for it to be credited towards qualifications (particularly positions with a positive education requirement.) Therefore, applicants must report only attendance and/or degrees from schools accredited by accrediting institutions recognized by the U.S. Department of Education. Applicants can verify accreditation at the following website: http://www.ed.gov/admins/finaid/accred/index.html All education claimed by applicants will be verified by the appointing agency accordingly. If you are using foreign education to meet qualification requirements, you must send a Certificate of Foreign Equivalency with your transcript in order to receive credit for that education.
Physical Requirements: The work is primarily sedentary. Some walking, standing, bending, carrying of small office items is required.
Veterans' Preference: When applying for Federal Jobs, eligible Veterans should claim preference on the Occupational Questionnaire in the section provided and provide a legible copy of your DD214(s) and/or documentation related to your active duty service which shows dates of service, character of service (honorable, general, etc.), or dates of impending separation.
Additionally, disabled veterans and others eligible for 10-point preference (such as widows or mothers of eligible Veterans) must also submit an SF-15 "Application for 10 Point Veterans Preference" with required proof as stated on the form. For more information, please review the information for disabled Veterans in the application checklist or visit http://www.fedshirevets.gov/job/vetpref/index.aspx.
HOW YOU WILL BE EVALUATED:
Your résumé and/or supporting documentation will be verified. Please follow all instructions carefully. Errors or omissions may affect your rating or consideration for employment.
BENEFITS:
VA offers a comprehensive benefits package. This link provides is an overview of the benefits currently offered:
http://www.va.gov/JOBS/Job_Benefits/benefits.asp.
VA supports the use of telework as a way to help attract and retain talented individuals in public service, increase worker productivity, and better prepare the agency to operate during emergencies. This position may be authorized for telework. Telework eligibility will be discussed during the interview process.
OTHER INFORMATION:The Interagency Career Transition Assistance Plan (ICTAP) and Career Transition Assistance Plan CTAP) provide eligible displaced Federal competitive service employees with selection priority over other candidates for competitive service vacancies. To be qualified you must submit appropriate documentation and be found well-qualified (have a final rating of 90 or more before any Veterans preference points) for this vacancy. Information about ICTAP and CTAP eligibility is on OPM's Career Transition Resources website.
Receiving Service Credit for Earning Annual (Vacation) Leave : Federal Employees earn annual leave at a rate (4, 6 or 8 hours per pay period) which is based on the number of years they have served as a Federal employee. VA may offer newly-appointed Federal employee's credit for their job-related non-federal experience or active duty uniformed military service. This credited service can be used in determining the rate at which they earn annual leave. Such credit must be requested and approved prior to the appointment date and is not guaranteed.
Placement Policy: The posting of this announcement does not obligate management to fill a vacancy or vacancies by promotion. The position may be filled by reassignment, change to lower grade, transfer, appointment, or reinstatement. Management may use any one or any combination of these methods to fill the position.
This job opportunity announcement may be used to fill additional vacancies.
HOW TO APPLY:
HOW TO APPLY: All applicants are encouraged to apply online.
To apply for this position, you must complete the occupational questionnaire and submit the documentation specified in the Required Documents section below.
The complete application package must be submitted by 11:59 PM (EST) on Monday, March 24, 2014 to receive consideration.
1. To begin, click Apply Online to create a USAJOBS account or log in to your existing account. Follow the prompts to select your USAJOBS resume and/or other supporting documents and complete the occupational questionnaire.
2. Click the Submit My Answers button to submit your application package.
It is your responsibility to ensure your responses and appropriate documentation is submitted prior to the closing date.
To verify your application is complete, log into your USAJOBS account, https://my.usajobs.gov/Account/Login, select the Application Status link and then select the more information link for this position. The Details page will display the status of your application, the documentation received and processed, and any correspondence the agency has sent related to this application. Your uploaded documents may take several hours to clear the virus scan process.
To return to an incomplete application, log into your USAJOBS account and click Update Application in the vacancy announcement. You must re-select your resume and/or other documents from your USAJOBS account or your application will be incomplete.
REQUIRED DOCUMENTS:
Resume/Application Responses to Occupational Questionnaire SF-50 (see checklist)
Please use this checklist to make sure you have included other documents required for your application, such as a copy of your transcript (if using education to qualify), documentation to support Veterans Preference claims, or ICTAP/CTAP documentation (for displaced Federal employees). You will not be contacted for additional information.
INCOMPLETE APPLICATION PACKAGES will receive a rating of IDMA (Failed to submit required documents). Requests for reconsideration of ratings will not be considered for applicants who fail to submit a complete application package. We cannot be held responsible for incompatible software, fax transmissions, etc.
Faxing Applications or Supporting Documents:
You are encouraged to apply online. Applying online will allow you to review and track the status of your application.
NOTE: If you applied online and your application is complete, do not fax the paper application (1203FX) as this will overwrite your prior online responses and may result in you being found ineligible.
If you completed the occupational questionnaire online and are unable to upload supporting document(s):
1. To fax your documents, you must use the following cover page http://staffing.opm.gov/pdf/usascover.pdf and provide the required information. The Vacancy ID is 1071339.
2. Fax your documents to 1-478-757-3144. If you cannot complete the Application Package online, you may fax all of your materials.
If you cannot complete the Application Package online, you may fax all of your materials. The complete application package must be submitted by 11:59 PM (EST) on Monday, March 24, 2014 to receive consideration. Keep a copy of your fax confirmation in the event verification is needed.
To complete the occupational questionnaire and submit via fax:
1. Click the following link to view and print the occupational questionnaire. View Occupational Questionnaire 2. Print the 1203FX form (http://www.opm.gov/forms/pdfimage/opm1203fx.pdf), follow the instructions and provide your responses to the occupational questionnaire items 3. Fax the completed 1203FX form along with any supporting documents to 1-478-757-3144. Your 1203FX will serve as a cover page for your fax transmission.
AGENCY CONTACT INFO:Arlene SchwemmerPhone: (412)822-3502Email: ARLENE.SCHWEMMER@VA.GOVAgency Information:VHA Pittsburgh VAMCPLEASE DO NOT MAIL APPLICATIONSAPPLY ONLINE OR FAXPittsburgh, PA00000WHAT TO EXPECT NEXT:
After the vacancy announcement closes and a referral certificate is issued, an electronic notification letter - or e-mail - will be sent to applicants who provide an e-mail address. Otherwise, you will receive a notification letter via the U.S. Postal Service within 2 to 4 weeks.
For more information please visit:http://federalgovernmentjobs.us
]]></text></news-item>