<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9B51-5143-8BA5-5FC7"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>community news briefs</title><source>Home News Tribune (East Brunswick, New Jersey)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[CRANFORD
Association hosting College Fair Monday
The Union County School Counselors Association will be hosting a College Fair on Monday (March 17) at Union County College's Cranford campus.
More than 80 colleges and universities from throughout the tri-state area will be in attendance. All members of the community, particularly high school students and their parents, are encouraged to attend.
The College Fair will be held from 6:30 to 8:30 p.m. in the gymnasium, cafeteria, and the Richel Student Commons. This is an opportunity to speak with representatives from the varied colleges and universities and to learn about the differences and similarities amongst the many institutions of higher education. Representatives from the Armed Services, State Police, and Vocational-Technical Schools will also be in attendance. A financial aid information session will also be held.
There is no cost for the College Fair or for parking for the event. Union County College's Cranford campus is located at 1033 Springfield Ave. For directions or more information about Union County College, visit www.ucc.edu.
Staff Report
EAST BRUNSWICK
Memory loss discussion planned
A discussion on dealing with memory loss, dementia, and Alzheimer's disease will be held at the East Brunswick Public Library on Tuesday (March 18).
The program begins at 1 p.m. Dr. Jeffrey Apter, will be on hand to discuss diagnosis, treatment and prevention. He'll also cover mild cognitive impairments and medications that can slow the process of memory loss. This free program is sponsored by the Middlesex Chapter of the Brandeis National Committee and The Library's Just for the Health of It initiative.
For more information, call 732-390-6767 or go www.ebpl.org and click on "News & Events." Follow them on Twitter at https://twitter.com/EBLibrary1, and Facebook at www.facebook.com/eastbrunswicklibrary.
Staff Report
EDISON
Rabbi appointed
to Holocaust panel
Rabbi Bernhard Rosenberg, spiritual leader of Congregation Beth-El, has been appointed by state Senate President Stephen M. Sweeney to the New Jersey Commission on Holocaust Education.
Rosenberg thanked state Sen. Peter Barnes III (D-Middlesex) for his tireless efforts in helping him get this appointment. The rabbi previously served six years on the commission under then-Gov. Christine Todd Whitman.
Born in a displaced persons' camp in Regensburg, Germany, Rosenberg is the only child of Holocaust survivors Jacob and Rachel Rosenberg of Poland. Their entire families, except for one cousin, were murdered by the Nazis.
Rosenberg is the township chaplain for Edison. The author of numerous books, he recently received the Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. Humanitarian Award.
He also received the Chaplain of the Year Award from the New York Board of Rabbis for his efforts during and following the terrorist attacks of Sept. 11, 2001. In 2002, he was presented with the annual Rabbi Israel Mowshowitz Award by the New York Board of Rabbis.
Staff Report
EDISON
Society will sponsor Beatles tribute
The Edison Arts Society will sponsor a tribute to the 50th Anniversary of the Beatles arrival in the US with a concert on March 29, at Middlesex County College.
The performance takes place at 7 p.m. in the Student Center. The British Invasion Tribute is a group who salutes the Beatles by performing many of their songs such as "Yellow Submarine," "Hey Jude," "Love Ya," and more.
Tickets can be purchased at Eventbrite.com or locally at Devine's Pharmacy on Oak Tree Road and PM Studio on Amboy Avenue both in Edison; Brass Lantern on Main Street and Marifika Fair Trade on New Street, both in Metuchen.
The tickets are $35 per person.
Middlesex County College is at 2600 Woodbridge Ave.
For further details, contact EAS at 732-548-9134.
Staff Report
ELIZABETH
Learn about female healers in Civil War
The Union County Civil War Sesquicentennial Committee invites the public to hear a special lecture by Dr. Sandra W. Moss, program chair and past president of the Medical History Society of New Jersey, on Wednesday (March 19).
The lecture, entitled "Women Healers in the Civil War," will be presented at 2 p.m. at the First Presbyterian Church.
The program is free. First Presbyterian Church ("Old First") is located at 42 Broad St. After the lecture, visit the special exhibit on Civil War nursing and medicine at the Union County Courthouse, 2 Broad St., next door to the church.
To reserve a seat for the lecture, call 908-527-4999. Parking is available nearby in the J. Christian Bollwage municipal garage on Caldwell Place at Elizabethtown Plaza.
The Civil War Exhibit is on display until 2015 in the rotunda of the Union County Courthouse. The exhibit may be viewed from 8:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. weekdays.
The displays will change from time to time. Anyone wishing to loan historical artifacts from the Civil War era for the exhibit can contact committee member Katherine Craig at 908-282-7617.
All objects will be secured, locked and acknowledged.
Staff Report
KENILWORTH
Procedures are set for filling vacancy
The Kenilworth Board of Education has established the following procedures for filling the vacancy left on the Board as a result of the resignation of Board of Education member Steven Benko.
Benko, who has served on the Kenilworth Board of Education since 2006, resigned from the Board of Education on Feb. 17, citing personal circumstances.
The following are the procedures established to fill the vacancy:
Applicants must be 18 years of age or older, be able to read, write and be a resident of Kenilworth, for one year, and a registered voter.
Interested individuals are to send a letter of intent to the Kenilworth Board of Education c/o Vincent A. Gonnella, Business Administrator/Board Secretary, 426 Boulevard, Kenilworth, NJ 07033.
Letters must be received in the Board of Education Office by 3 p.m. on March 31.
Candidates must be prepared to attend a Special Board of Education Meeting at 7 p.m. on April 1,in the Board of Education Conference Room, Brearley School, Kenilworth. at which time an interview will be conducted.
The term of office, once filled, will last until Dec. 31.
Staff Report
MIDDLESEX COUNTY
Drop off household hazardous waste
The Middlesex County Division of Solid Waste Management will hold its Household Hazardous Waste Drop-Off Day today at Middlesex County College.
Household hazardous wastes that are improperly disposed of are potentially dangerous to children and animals, a potential cause of ground water and other environmental pollution and a potential threat to garbage collection crews.
The hours of the drop-off are 8 a.m. to 2 p.m.
Acceptable materials include but are not limited to: pesticides/herbicides, flammable liquids, solvents, pool chemicals, used motor oil, oil filters, paints, rechargeable and button cell batteries, anti-freeze, propane tanks, fluorescent light bulbs including compact fluorescent bulbs (no broken bulbs) and asbestos.
Residents wishing to bring asbestos must pre-register by calling the Division, and can only bring up to a maximum of 500 pounds.
Materials not accepted at the drop-off day include: tires, electronics, explosives and munitions, infectious and medical waste, household medications, appliances, furniture, unknown materials and empty containers.
Residents with tires and electronics can contact the division for information regarding separate tire and electronics recycling programs.
Alkaline batteries (AAA, AA, C, D and 9-volt that have the word ALKALINE imprinted on them) can be thrown out in the normal trash.
The drop-off day is sponsored by the Middlesex County Board of Chosen Freeholders and is conducted in cooperation with Middlesex County College.
The event is open to residents of Middlesex County and is free of charge. Items should be brought in clearly marked containers.
Middlesex County College is at 2600 Woodbridge Ave. in Edison. Enter the college through the Mill Road entrance.
For further information, contact the Division of Solid Waste Management by calling 732-745-4170, by emailing solidwaste@co.middlesex.nj.us or by visiting www.co.middlesex.nj.us/planningboard/solidwaste.asp.
Staff Report
]]></text></news-item>