<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9BA2-1970-56FC-E9E8"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>A gem in Sterling Heights</title><source>Windsor Star (Ontario)</source><author>Chris Vander Doelen, The Windsor Star</author><text><![CDATA[The Chrysler assembly plant here has come back from the dead, twice. Ordered closed for a second time in 2009 after the company's bankruptcy, its employees rallied and protested and begged the company not to give up on it.
So Chrysler didn't. And what SHAP, as it calls itself, became Friday after a $1.6-billion investment is what Windsor Assembly hopes it can be one day, if the company ever ends its bitter feud with Canada: home to a new global platform.
Global platforms usually become a whole family of new vehicles.
Sterling Heights will start its own family Monday by launching assembly of the 2015 Chrysler 200. The company calls it the most advanced and competitive car it's ever launched in the crowded midsized market.
That's an oft-made boast in the automotive world. But an up-close look at the new 200 reveals more welds, more sealer, better paint, beefier components, better interior design and a host of other major improvements to the critically unpopular Sebring and the refreshed 200 it became.
Fiat Chrysler Automobiles invited the media on an exhaustive five-hour, miles-long tour of the three-building site Friday to show off what it calls the best, most technologically advanced manufacturing plant in its system worldwide.
Company CEO and president Sergio Marchionne says Chrysler spent "$1 billion in architecture" on the site for two new stand-alone separate plants that expand the plant by nearly two million square feet. The whole place now totals five million, a million square feet larger than Windsor Assembly.
Half of the money was invested in a gleaming new stand-alone, super-clean paint shop, the rest on a state-of-theart body shop also built from scratch on the 286-acre site eight miles north of Detroit on Van Dyke Road. The original paint shop sits empty.
So what did SHAP staff get for the money? Quite a lot that would be foreign to the employees of Windsor Assembly which, although retooled for Pacifica in 2003, hasn't received a large injection of capital since.
In Windsor, the company is still outsourcing work to cut costs.
In Sterling Heights they're in-sourcing, bringing back rear suspension sub-assemblies and a host of smaller sub-assemblies.
A 450,000-square-foot sequencing shop has been set up in the main assembly area, where 54 transport trucks will disgorge one million parts per day to 206 employees staffing 26 sequencing cells and 27 delivery routes within the assembly plant.
In Windsor, most of that work is done off site by Tier One suppliers.
In all, 800 jobs have been in-sourced back to the mother plant due to a two-tier wage structure and other costcutting deals struck with the UAW, company officials said. Chrysler believes bringing the work back in-house raises quality, too.
But this plant also has more robots, by far, than any other Chrysler plant.
SHAP's new body shop boasts 1,056 robots and 554 UAW staff, plus 35 salaried supervisors. Incoming body stampings are robotically measured by 3-D imaging systems to ensure consistent quality. Completed bodies are driven by robot carriers into a laser measuring facility that checks every gap for tightness. Robots do that work too, of course.
Welding is completely roboticized, and includes a 15-station framing line with "monster" open gate framing station whose 18 roof-hung robots do 40 welds in 45 seconds. The framing line can do 69 jobs an hour on four different vehicle models.
Roofs are now brazed to the side body panels, instead of welded - which is the standard in luxury cars because it eliminates two plastic filler trim pieces in the roof gutters, creating a classier look.
Chrysler first started using the system in 2011 on the 300 model in Brampton Assembly.
Windsor doesn't have it yet. And whether it will ever get it now appears in doubt.
The innovations in the new paint shop would make Windsor's crew envious: all-glass booths for total visibility; 14 colours plus tri-coats; robots hung from the ceiling that spray down, eliminating spray loss and drips; extra robots on the line that allow the broken ones to be taken offline for repair without the loss of a single production unit; spray tips and purge buckets that are accessible through hatches while the paint shop is running at full tilt. All the massive air-handling machinery is on the roof.
"It's really quiet for a paint shop," says Chris Kulka, paint project manager and a veteran of Chrysler's demolished St. Louis minivan plant.
Gone is the traditional, deafening chain-driven line carrying bodies on carriers throughout the paint shop. It's been replaced by the same kind of smooth, silent friction drive conveyor system used on the rides at Disneyland. Two rubber wheels squeeze and turn, and the carriers roll silently down the line.
"You don't hear the carriers banging; you don't hear the chains clanging and the dogs banging as they disengage," Kulka says. "It's scary quiet - you don't even hear the bodies moving. You have to keep an eye out when you're walking through."
Another innovation in body: fewer people have to work overhead: the cars rotate upside down in their carriers for sealing and underbody coating.
Total staff: 357 people, 327 UAW staff plus 30 supervisors.
"We're making a big bet with this plant," Marchionne told SHAP's 2,800 hourly employees from two shifts as they gathered for an opening ceremony. They'd just spent the week all working the same training shift together to load the line for a Monday morning production start.
One thousand completed production 200s have already come off the line during startup, and if the car is a sales hit up to a million more could theoretically follow in the coming years.
Its future appears assured for a long, long time, Marchionne said.
But when the media's questions turned to Windsor's future, Marchionne's answers turned terse, his answers abrupt. The upshot of his political message: he'll do what he has to to continue building vehicles in Canada in the short term.
But he has no intention now of making either of his Canadian plants the equal of the gem he feels he just built in Sterling Heights.
cvanderdoelen@windsorstar.com
]]></text></news-item>