<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9C0B-2FD3-9751-EB40"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Public Record for March 16, 2014</title><source>The Advocate-Messenger (Danville, Kentucky)</source><author>Staff Writer</author><text><![CDATA[BOYLE
DISTRICT COURT
Cases handled recently in Boyle District Court, listed by name, charge, fine and jail sentence, where applicable, include the following. Court costs also were assessed in most cases. Ages and addresses are listed if available.
Judge Jeff Dotson presiding
Dennis H. Back, 50, driving under the influence of intoxicants, $250, license suspended 120 days; no insurance, $1,000, $900 probated one year; license to be in possession, disregarding stop sign, failure to use signal, and no insurance card, all dismissed.
Chyvonna D. Gordon, 34, Stanford, reckless driving, dismissed; DUI, $250, license suspended 120 days.
Jimmy Charles Richardson, theft by unlawful taking less than $500, $200, 60 days, consecutively with any other sentence, probated one year, $10.90 restitution, banned from Kroger.
Rodger L. Ross, 53, 169 Majestic Prince, DUI, $250, 30 days, to serve four days, credit for one day served, remaining time probated one year, license suspended 120 days.
Stacie Coffman, 24, Liberty, theft by unlawful taking less than $500, $200, 90 days, probated one year, banned from Burke's Outlet.
Brian Zachery Brombach, 22, 316 High St., driving under the influence of intoxicants, $250, license suspended 120 days; possession of marijuana, $200; vehicle a noise nuisance, dismissed.
Krystal Michelle Ford, Nicholasville, theft by unlawful taking less than $500, $200, 45 days, probated one year, banned from Burke's Outlet.
Andresa Davonne Lofton, 24, 46 E. Madison Ave., theft by unlawful taking less than $500, $200, 45 days, probated one year, banned from Burke's Outlet.
Charles H. Rodes, 54, 5851 Perryville Road, DUI, second offense, $400, seven days, credit for one day served, license suspended 18 months; no seat belt, $25; no or expired registration, no or expired Kentucky registration and no insurance, all continued.
Kendall N. Rumford, 29, 4925 Hustonville Road, DUI, $325, license suspended 120 days; careless driving, disregarding stop sign and possession of open alcohol container in vehicle, all dismissed.
Dillon Jay Treadway, 21, Hustonville, violation of emergency protective order, 52 days, credit for 52 days served.
Freddie W. West, 42, 4096 Webster Road, third-degree terroristic threatening, 60 days, credit for 30 days served; contempt of court, dismissed.
Zachary Dawson, 23, 611 McMillan Court, trafficking in marijuana less than eight ounces, 120 days; two counts of possession of drug paraphernalia, 30 days on each count; two counts of possession of marijuana, 30 days on each count, all time consecutively, credit for nine days served, remaining time probated two years.
Isaiah T. Henry, 18, 813 E. Main St., public intoxication with a controlled substance, 30 days; second-degree unlawful transaction with a minor, amended to third-degree, 120 days, consecutively, credit for six days served, remaining time probated one year.
Michael Lee Stephens, 35, Perryville, fourth-degree domestic assault, $100, 30 days, credit for three days served, remaining time probated one year.
Dusten C. Thomas, 27, 126 Lausman Ave., fourth-degree assault, amended to harassment, one day, credit for one day served.
Meagan Whitley, 21, 408 N. Sixth St., three counts of endangering the welfare of a minor, 210 days on each count, concurrently with each other; second-degree disorderly conduct, dismissed; second-degree fleeing or evading police, 30 days, consecutively, probated two years.
Ryan M. Coffey, 23, 1358 Taylor Road, DUI, second offense, $350, 14 days, credit for 14 days served, license suspended 18 months; no insurance, continued; possession of open alcohol container in vehicle and one headlight, dismissed.
Jeffery C. Hackle, 22, 217 E. Mason Ave., second-degree criminal mischief, 60 days; first-degree wanton endangerment, amended to menacing, 60 days, consecutively, credit for four days served, remaining time probated one year.
Donald W. Jones, 41, Perryville, first-degree conspiracy to trafficking in a controlled substance, meth, amended to facilitation, 180 days; two counts of first-degree possession of a controlled substance, both amended to third-degree, first count 180 days consecutively, second count 180 days concurrently, credit for 13 days served, remaining time probated two years; resisting arrest, dismissed.
Ruby Ann Lofton, 46, 240 Randolph Hill, possession of drug paraphernalia, $150.
GRAND JURY
Cases referred to the Boyle County grand jury recently include:
Harlan D. Baker, 27, Junction City, possession of marijuana; possession of drug paraphernalia; second-degree possession of a controlled substance; controlled substance prescription not in original container; first-degree possession of a controlled substance, meth; first-degree possession of a controlled substance, cocaine.
Patrick M. Sisco, 28, 113 Baughman Ave., third-degree unlawful transaction with a minor; first-degree burglary; fourth-degree assault; second-degree unlawful transaction with a minor, all sent to the grand jury; and possession of marijuana and possession of drug paraphernalia, continued in district court.
Cassandra R. Stevens, 29, 1136 Claunch Road, conspiracy to traffic in a controlled substance, amended to attempt, 365 days; two counts of second-degree possession of a controlled substance, first count, 90 days, concurrently, second count dismissed, credit for 13 days, remaining time probated two years.
Chad A. Adams, 42, Junction City, no or expired license plate; first-degree possession of a controlled substance, opiate; conspiracy to traffic in a controlled substance; controlled substance prescription not in original container.
Michelle C. Adams, 43, Junction City, first-degree trafficking in a controlled substance, opiates; first-degree wanton endangerment; possession of drug paraphernalia.
Kenneth L. Richards, 54, 575 Winterhawk Road, first-degree conspiracy to traffic in a controlled substance, second or more offense; trafficking in marijuana less than five pounds.
Charles E. Scott, 51, 416 Boone Trail, public intoxication, first and second offense; fourth-degree domestic assault; violation of emergency protective order.
Michael Thomas Yates, 32, 130 Michelle Court, first-degree conspiracy to traffic in a controlled substance, second or more offense; trafficking in marijuana less than five pounds.
CIVIL JUDGMENTS
Civil judgments handed down in Boyle Circuit Court include:
C&F Finance Co. vs. Jeffery C. Jones, default judgment for plaintiff, $9,495 plus interest and fees.
PNC Bank vs. Susan M. Prueitt and Michael W. Prueitt, judgment for plaintiff and order of sale, $62,215 plus interest and fees.
Jennifer Gale Dotson vs. Bobby Carl Dotson, divorce granted.
NEW DRIVERS
New driver's licenses issued recently in Boyle County include:
Hannah Bolling
Cailee Young
Ashley Taylor
Tanner Brown
CASEY
DISTRICT COURT
Cases handled recently in Casey District Court, listed by name, charge, fine and jail sentence, where applicable, include the following. Court costs also were assessed in most cases. Ages and addresses are listed if available.
Judge Michael Loy presiding
Cornelio Utreral, Lexington, DUI, $755.50, license suspended 90 days; no driver's license, $25.
GRAND JURY
Cases referred to the Casey County grand jury recently include:
Guy W. Butler III, 51, Delp Road, second-degree assault, domestic violence; third-degree terroristic threatening.
CIVIL JUDGMENTS
Civil judgments handed down in Casey Circuit Court include:
Dun & Bradstreet vs. Davis Distributing Inc. of Liberty, foreign judgment for plaintiff, $8,912 plus interest and fees.
CRIMINAL JUDGMENTS
Criminal judgments handed down in Casey Circuit Court include:
Kody Chadwell, 22, Tennessee and Casey County jail, second-degree burglary, amended to third-degree, five years; three counts of second-degree persistent felony offender, possession of marijuana and resisting arrest, all dismissed; first-degree criminal mischief, five years; theft by unlawful taking, 12 months; first-degree possession of a controlled substance, one year, all time to run consecutively, suspended five years, probation five years; possession of drug paraphernalia, 12 months, concurrently.
MARRIAGE LICENSES
Marriage licenses issued recently in the office of Casey County Clerk Casey Davis include:
Michelle Lynn Johnson, 34, homemaker, and Donnie Brock Jr., 29, disabled veteran, both of Dunnville.
Vanessa Ann Roy, 39, registered nurse, and Kevin Allen Clements, 36, conductor, both of Windsor.
Maria Roberta Tellez Ortiz, 39, housekeeping, and Jose Antonia Varilla Martinez, 32, landscaping, both of Liberty.
GARRARD
DISTRICT COURT
Cases handled recently in Garrard District Court, listed by name, charge, fine and jail sentence, where applicable, include the following. Court costs also were assessed in most cases. Ages and addresses are listed if available.
Judge Bill Oliver presiding
John Paul Baker Jr., 20, 107 Ridgefield Drive, second-degree wanton endangerment, $200, 120 days, probated two years; reckless driving, merged; improper passing, traffic school; possession of marijuana, $100, 30 days, consecutively, probated two years.
CIVIL JUDGMENTS
Civil judgments handed down in Garrard Circuit Court include:
Tidewater Motor Credit vs. Kristen Heyne, default judgment for plaintiff, $6,729 plus interest and fees.
CitiMortgage Inc. vs. Darryl Carpenter and Karla Carpenter, judgment for plaintiff and order of sale, $150,106 plus interest and fees.
NationStar Mortgage LLC vs. Mary Graham, also known as Mary Massey, judgment for plaintiff and order of sale, $22,029 plus interest and fees.
Kentucky Housing Corp. vs. Shawn B. Powell and Tonya Powell, judgment for plaintiff and order of sale, $95,660 plus interest and fees.
Capital One Bank vs. Ronald D. Scott, default judgment for plaintiff, $5,653 plus interest and fees.
CRIMINAL JUDGMENTS
Criminal judgments handed down in Garrard Circuit Court include:
Anthony D. Frederick, two counts of first-degree trafficking in a controlled substance, amended to first-degree possession of a controlled substance, three years, suspended three years, five years probation, on each count, concurrently.
MARRIAGE LICENSES
Marriage licenses issued recently in the office of Garrard County Clerk Kevin Montgomery include:
Cassaundra Marie Cheek, 22, unemployed, Lancaster, and Christopher Reuben Hubbard, 20, military, Virginia.
LINCOLN
DISTRICT COURT
Cases handled recently in Lincoln District Court, listed by name, charge, fine and jail sentence, where applicable, include the following. Court costs also were assessed in most cases. Ages and addresses are listed if available.
Judge Bill Oliver presiding
Jeffrey S. Adams II, 28, Junction City, theft by failure to make required disposition of property, 90 days, probated one year, $665 restitution.
Angela D. Cross Daugherty, 27, Lancaster, theft by unlawful taking, $200, 40 days, to serve 10 days, remaining time probated two years.
Zachary Dawson, 23, Danville, second-degree criminal mischief, 90 days, probated two years, $500 restitution.
Lindsey May York, 28, Crab Orchard, public intoxication, $25; theft by unlawful taking, $100, 40 days, to serve 10 days, remaining time probated two years, $20.61 restitution.
CIVIL JUDGMENTS
Civil judgments handed down in Lincoln Circuit Court include:
Jeanette Micheale Wilson vs. Johnny O'Dell Wilson, divorce granted.
Tax Ease Lien Investments 1 LLC vs. Lisa Stringer and Victor Keith Middleton, default judgment for plaintiff, $4,387 plus interest and fees.
Marilyn S. Morris vs. John L. Morris, divorce granted.
Nationwide Advantage Mortgage Co. vs. Carol Jean Pittman, order to reschedule master commissioner sale.
Kentucky Housing Corp. vs. Bart B. Smith and Jennifer Smith, judgment for plaintiff and order of sale, $82,297 plus interest and fees.
Tracie King vs. Robert King, divorce granted.
Robert Dewayne Whitaker vs. Mary Jo Whitaker, divorce granted.
MARRIAGE LICENSES
Marriage licenses issued recently in the office of Lincoln County Clerk George O. Spoonamore IV include:
Anna Louise Johnson, 33, home health, and Christopher Allen Bidwell, 33, sawmill, both of Waynesburg.
Kayla Jane Taylor, 24, homemaker, and Charlie Andrew Snyder, 23, Dana, both of Stanford.
Cassandra Danielle Harker, 31, homemaker, and David Lee McKitric, 51, retired, both of Stanford.
Alexandria Elaine Walker, 18, student, and Mason Slade Payton, 18, student, both of Hustonville.
MERCER
DISTRICT COURT
Cases handled recently in Mercer District Court, listed by name, charge, fine and jail sentence, where applicable, include the following. Court costs also were assessed in most cases. Ages and addresses are listed if available.
Judge Jeff Dotson presiding
Jeffery D. Cutter, 27, 125 Poplar St., possession of marijuana, $250.
Michael J. Harris, 36, 445 E. Factory St., possession of marijuana, $250.
Sierra Morgan Mills, 18, 1758 Central Pike, theft by unlawful taking, $100, 30 days, probated one year, banned from Walmart.
Markus D. Moore, 22, 700 W. Office St., theft by unlawful taking less than $500, $100, 30 days, probated one year, $10.94 restitution, banned from Walmart.
Terrence L. Walker, 24, 262 W. Office St., theft by unlawful taking less than $500, $100, 30 days, probated one year, $15.22 restitution, banned from Walmart.
Brittey L. White, 28, 161 Franks Court, theft by unlawful taking less than $500, $100, 30 days, probated one year, $15.13 restitution, banned from Walmart.
Jessica Leann Young, 35, Salvisa, theft by unlawful taking, $100, 30 days; possession of marijuana, $100, 30 days, concurrently, credit for two days served, remaining time probated one year, banned from Dollar General; two counts of failure to appear for citation, first count dismissed, second count, 20 days, consecutively, probated the same.
GRAND JURY
Cases referred to the Mercer County grand jury recently include:
Ashley R. Semones, 25, 648 Countryside Drive, first-degree possession of a controlled substance; possession of marijuana; possession of drug paraphernalia.
CIVIL JUDGMENTS
Civil judgments handed down in Mercer Circuit Court include:
Thomas L. Cummins vs. Erica N. Cummins, divorce granted.
Farmers National Bank of Danville vs. Tamsen Metcalf, judgment for plaintiff and order of sale, $109,931 plus interest and fees.
William Harry Wheeler III vs. Kathy Jo Wheeler, divorce granted.
Ronnie Dillard Moore vs. Martha Karen Moore, divorce granted.
MARRIAGE LICENSES
Marriage licenses issued recently in the office of Mercer County Clerk Chris Horn include:
Kamillia Marie Wallingford, 28, factory, and Wesley Ryan Morris, 27, self-employed, both of Harrodsburg.
Janice Ann Dunn, 54, homemaker, and Sidney Glen Hunt, 66, retired, both of Harrodsburg.
Kayla Marchelle Dunn, 20, unemployed, and Thomas Lee Cummins, 31, custodian, both of Harrodsburg.
INCORPORATIONS
Buckin' B's LLC, P.O. Box 602 Harrodsburg, Ky.
Southside Hardware & Supply LLC, Steven B. McMullin, 1000 Danville Road, Harrodsburg.
BANKRUPTCIES
Cases filed recently in U.S. Bankruptcy Court include the following:
LEXINGTON
Chapter 7
Nikki Jo Rothwell, 111 S. Harris Creek Spur, Stanford, 14-50499.
Saundra Jo Curry, 250 Rolling Meadows Drive, Lancaster, 14-50543.
William Wilburn and Dianna Wilburn, 11783 Forkland Road, Parksville, 14-50550.
Denise L. Elliott, 208 Country Drive, Hustonville, 14-50553.
Jackie D. Devine, 416 Talmage Mayo Road, Harrodsburg, 14-50561.
Chapter 13
Brian Caudill, 125 Lester Road, Harrodsburg, 14-50494.
Robert Lee Coulter Jr. and Cammie P. Coulter, 2525 Boneyville Road, Stanford, 14-50516.
BOWLING GREEN
Chapter 7
James Davenport and Jennifer Hope Davenport, 1369 Contown Road, Liberty, 14-10239.
Chapter 7: Court-appointed trustee sells assets, and debtor is discharged of debt.
Chapter 13: Debtor arranges to repay debt.
]]></text></news-item>