<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9C68-BA9C-6CDE-92CB"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>program; Horseman's Day bigger than ever</title><source>Ag Journal (La Junta, Colorado)</source><author>Candace Krebs Contributing Writer</author><text><![CDATA[With at least three horse rescue operations located in the Colorado Springs area, Sara Gibson knew the topic of how to dispose of unwanted horses was a touchy subject.
Even so, offering a broad and diverse program with something for everyone - even where there are differences of opinion - has helped the Colorado Springs Horseman's Day continue to grow in size and importance, said Gibson, a horse owner from Ellicott and the event's organizer.
"Denver has the National Western, and Pueblo has the state fair, but I really think there is a need here in Colorado Springs for something like this, with the large horse population we have in the area," she said.
Five years ago, Gibson was working for Colorado Equine Veterinary Services, a private veterinary clinic in Peyton with about 10,000 customers, when she suggested to co-founder Clinton Unruh they host an educational seminar.
Unruh, a vet originally from the Texas Panhandle who established the clinic in 2003 with fellow practitioner Greg Brown, not only endorsed the idea, he encouraged her to think big.
"Our goal was to keep it free to the public and make it an educational day for the whole family with a variety of topics, not limited just to horse care," she said.
The first three years the event was held at Falcon High School before moving to its current location at the Norris-Penrose Event Center two years ago.
Foot traffic increased by nearly a thousand people this year to around 2,500.
Practical aspects of horse ownership - including nutrition, pasture management and general horsemanship - are always mainstays, but Gibson also looks for inspirational "feel good" speakers like last year's Kate Chenery-Tweedy, who shared her family's experiences raising Triple Crown racehorse Secretariat on their farm.
With nearly 70 vendors, a kid's corral and a diverse list of workshops and presentations, horseman's day has become an opportunity for local horse people of all kinds to meet up, network and share their enthusiasm for the industry, Gibson said.
For the first time this year the program touched on animal welfare issues, with presentations by equine veterinarian Tom Lenz and Colorado State University's world-renowned animal expert and author Temple Grandin. Gibson said she knew the topic of humane horse disposal - slaughter in particular - is always controversial but wanted to provide timely information that was fair, even-handed and broad-based.
One visitor who enjoyed the presentations was Michelle Wolf, who was looking for advice about how to engage friends and acquaintances on food production issues. She recently moved to Monument after being a horse trainer and ag educator on the East Coast. She said she found it difficult to navigate sensitive issues with people who often had no background in production agriculture, but wanted to take a positive role sharing her support for the industry.
"There are lots of ways to contribute," Lenz told her, following his wide-ranging talk. He recommended she start by reaching out to the American Horse Council as well as leading equine experts at Colorado State University.
]]></text></news-item>