<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9C8A-B5B1-A965-5BB5"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Sorted Weekly Tweets</title><source>The Aleph Blog</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 15, 2014 (The Aleph Blog:http://alephblog.com Delivered by Newstex) Rest of the World China premier warns on economic slowdown as data fans stimulus talk http://t.co/B4uN1uP6OU[1] Stimulus just leads 2more overcapacity debt $$ Mar 14, 2014Teslas in California Help Bring Dirty Rain to China http://t.co/YTBdiM77Pi[2] Mining graphite adds 2 Chinese air pollution $$ Ironic, huh? Mar 14, 2014Deeper Ukraine Invasion Lurks in Putin's Warnings, 'Provocations,' Clashes in East http://t.co/L5GbJqx8j6[3] 1 mistake away from major war $$ Mar 14, 2014Finland Trapped in Recession as Investment Fades http://t.co/DL9m3nGy13[4] Punk global economy exhausted from 2 much stimulus debt $$ $SPY Mar 14, 2014Norway's Oil Stimulus Nears Tipping Point as Growth Fades http://t.co/ct5Mt8RY5i[5] Government economics stimulus fails; ppl have 2much debt $$ Mar 14, 2014Warnings From the Ukraine Crisis http://t.co/lcC1RDpjRv[6] Not being George W. Bush is not a foreign policy. Let Nobel winner get a strategy $$ Mar 14, 2014US Investigators Suspect Missing Malaysia Airlines Plane Flew On http://t.co/dhM6rlQlf1[7] Engine Data Suggest Flight Airborne for 5 hrs $$ Mar 13, 2014Treasury's Lew Uses Mideast Toolkit to Back Ukrainian Bonds http://t.co/QeyvWdDKZ1[8] Another example of ways to buy US credit with spread $$ Mar 13, 2014Qatar World Cup: 400 Nepalese die on nation's building sites since bid won http://t.co/uUY4neKHbF[9] Slavery is alive sick in Qatar $$ Mar 13, 2014The Malaysia Airlines Disappearance Shows Technology's Limits 
http://t.co/dWgmOKk42v[10] Interesting read: rare cases of disappearing planes $$ Mar 13, 2014Ukraine Starts Military Exercises as Russia Warns on East http://t.co/8ZeISGvEcA[11] All u need is 1 significant mistake u could have war $$ Mar 10, 2014Israelis in Berlin Signal Middle Class Struggles at Home http://t.co/mydWWz9j7M[12] It's cheaper living in Berlin, forget the past, live well $$ Mar 10, 2014China Strike Illustrates Shift in Labor Landscape http://t.co/DDWIN8KLhM[13] Would rather work 4 a foreign firrm than Chinese firm $$ $FXI Mar 10, 2014 Companies Industries $GLCH Gleacher Co is liquidating. Looking at the price chart, it has seen better days http://t.co/aIYv7zxrfd[14] $$ $SPY $TLT Mar 14, 2014IBM's double dilemma http://t.co/HJfljGY7Wq[15] If you buy back stock at levels over the company's intrinsic value, you destroy value. $IBM $$ Mar 14, 2014Even in its final days, Windows XP still looms large http://t.co/m2VUtiTJIp[16] Last night friend told her hospital just upgraded to XP $$ $MSFT Mar 14, 2014BNSF pledges 2get caught up on ND ag shipments http://t.co/XGah5Xmop6[17] $CNI made a similar promise in Canada recently. Coincidence? $BRK.B $$ Mar 13, 2014Target Missed Alarms in Epic Hack of Credit Card Data http://t.co/lYLAWDI04m[18] $TGT got ample warning from $FEYE $SYMC but ignored it $$ Mar 13, 2014Candy Crush Maker's Realm Spans Across Continents http://t.co/9dZyVNhqWp[19] A global firm that uses tax regulatory haven 2 their advantage $$ Mar 13, 2014'Candy Crush' Maker Seeks Valuation Up to $7.6B http://t.co/L1Kaf4WLjK[20] I would b wary here, not just the IPO, but a faddish company $$ $SPY Mar 12, 2014US Wind-Down Bill Clips $FNMA $ FMCC Shares http://t.co/rZxsLenQk4[21] Would require most borrowers 2make down payments of gt;5%, lenders hit 2 $$ Mar 12, 2014Fannie, Freddie Shares Plunge http://t.co/XfNZ1Jv5Rv[22] Taxpayers should reap the reward for bailing out $FNMA $FMCC as mtge gtees change $$ Mar 12, 2014Buffett's Berkshire Reaches $300B Market Cap http://t.co/lqnyQ0F4sN[23] As he buys profiable businesses, growing retained earnings builds MC $$ Mar 10, 2014Chiquita to Acquire Irish Fruit Distributor Fyffes in Stock Deal http://t.co/MJBhJuuxM3[24] $CQB is no 'top banana' in the fruit biz $$ $SPY Mar 10, 2014 Market Impact Corporate Cash Pushes Further Into Corporate Bonds http://t.co/Vk9PGzrItp[25] Corporate finance gets urge 2b a profit center @ wrong moment $$ Mar 14, 2014Bio-finance? Why high-frequency trading makes stocks flock like birds http://t.co/UB6jzwgjla[26] Reasonable defense of HFT H/T: @matt_levine $$ Mar 14, 2014ETFs Get $41B Erasing Stock Withdrawals on Economy http://t.co/l1hrnCWuel[27] This is y I advocate low turnover strategies $$ sell low, buy high Mar 13, 2014BlackRock Junk ETFs Push Buyers to Dark Corners http://t.co/vjydZFBFwG[28] Same problem exists w/index bonds not in ETFs; high short interest $$ Mar 13, 2014A man and his signals @reformedbroker http://t.co/12SiH3ZkCp[29] No 1 has a set of signals that can be relied upon in all market environments $$ Mar 13, 2014Wall Street and Casinos…Are They Similar? http://t.co/MYNALbXAJm[30] @howardlindzon tells us 2b prepared, understand mkts not blame ump $$ Mar 13, 2014Activist Investors Put Bondholders in Crossfire http://t.co/k1BdJx1gR6[31] Investment grade corps offer little2no protection frm negative MA $$ Mar 13, 2014How Market Tops Get Made http://t.co/Saa7j6zkCQ[32] Good piece by @Ritholtz on technicals of market tops. For dessert: http://t.co/VIGN6jhACy[33] $$ Mar 12, 2014Stock Market Surge Bypasses Most Americans, Poll Shows http://t.co/IJ0S2rRx8x[34] People don't get stocks; worse, they think they get housing $$ Mar 12, 2014Chart of the Day: No Profits, No Problem? http://t.co/HpYPLqoOKP[35] IPO quality is down, many private companies want to IPO. IP-uh-oh $$ $SPY Mar 12, 2014Bull Market Rivals '90s at Half Valuation as Demand Broadens http://t.co/YzXZDj9HlK[36] Profit margins were a lot lower corp yields higher $$ Mar 10, 2014Still Corporate Cash Everywhere http://t.co/gseGZd38Th[37] How much $$ is encumbered? More derivatives today, which induces some calc bias $SPY Mar 10, 2014 US Politics Policy Regulators Size Up Wall Street, With Worry http://t.co/aQolfRq0Y4[38] Allowing big banks to fail, while protecting depositors is a solution $$ Mar 14, 2014Senate Investigation of Bush-Era Torture Erupts Into Constitutional Crisis http://t.co/qkqkAGiP9Y[39] Obama-era also; what he tell CIA 2 do? $$ Mar 13, 2014CFPB targets 'zombie' foreclosures after Reuters report http://t.co/RohgKncAnm[40] What happens when an owner walks away bank doesn't f/c $$ Mar 13, 2014How the NSA Plans to Infect 'Millions' of Computers with Malware http://t.co/N72lYfxhr9[41] Another reason to end the existence of NSA $$ #nonsa Mar 13, 2014Raskin Confirmed by Senate as US Treasury's No. 2 Official http://t.co/TvwMcqj6eI[42] Maybe she'll do as much at Tsy as she did at the Fed $$ Mar 12, 2014ObamaCare's Secret Mandate Exemption http://t.co/s6OCOdwU83[43] HHS quietly repeals the individual purchase rule for two more years $$ $SPY $TLT Mar 12, 2014 Central Banking Fed Sends $79.6B in Profit to Treasury http://t.co/W313rKFj2k[44] That profit is taken from the pockets of savers, it is not like manna $$ $TLT Mar 14, 2014Fed Nominees Vow To Fight for Recovery http://t.co/KjdmHILaCV[45] Stanley Fischer 2 blanks in the gun; really unimpressed w/shuffle Tsy/Fed $$ Mar 13, 2014Yellen Job One Is Redoing Guidance Without Roiling Markets http://t.co/2Hu8ALqIwW[46] Unlikely, her own work established current verbiage $$ Mar 12, 2014 Economics Your Job Taught to Machines Puts Half US Work at Risk http://t.co/a0WSKAEIom[47] W/o labor-saving innovation we wouldn't b so well off $$ $SPY Mar 12, 2014Global Debt Exceeds $100T as Governments Binge, BIS Says http://t.co/cDgYwRUI7A[48] When large amts of securities get issued -gt; underperform $$ Mar 10, 2014Where's Economics When We Need It? http://t.co/3SMaboCeG6[49] Games played by obscure mathematicians explaining a world that does not exist $$ Mar 10, 2014Will Housing Bloom Again This Spring?http://t.co/KEHLTIKesD[50] There r2 many investors looking to make $$ in housing; makes further gains hard Mar 10, 2014 Other Want a Lasting Relationship? Give Up Sex [before marriage] http://t.co/nxSBVl2QB2[51] Interesting piece that supports traditional morality $$ Mar 13, 2014Vanishing Planes Since 1948 http://t.co/2mSC2NGByA[52] Interesting lost planes graphic @BloombergNews | Rare, but more common than expected $$ Mar 13, 2014The Risk Behind Buffett's Advice http://t.co/LE6EGqinq2[53] Asset allocation driven by valuation time horizon. Don't BH if you need the $$ Mar 10, 2014Morgan Stanley, Goldman Said to Swap Fees for Deal Credit http://t.co/dH1FwKNEsr[54] $$ less valuable 2 investment banks than pride $GS $MS $SPY Mar 10, 2014 Wrong Wrong: US to Be Energy Self-Sufficient by 2035: $BP http://t.co/hr8TTFBpge[55] Many don't notice how quickly production tails off w/new wells $$ Mar 13, 2014Wrong: Repo Fire-Sale Plan Said Within Reach After Fed Sounds Alarm http://t.co/Kzbgp20yRG[56] These r just band-aid solutions $$ $NLY $TLT $SPY Mar 12, 2014 Retweets, Replies Comments Here's to Martin Rimes @hitmarktrading, my 9,000th Twitter follower; thanks to all who follow me. $$ Mar 13, 2014@Money_in_Stereo I'm writing an article about it tonight at Aleph Blog. This was last night's article: http://t.co/bjvqvgXRc5[57] $$ $BRK.B Mar 13, 2014@Money_in_Stereo Did anyone respond to you when you asked about the Harney Investment Trust $BRK.B ? Mar 13, 2014 [1]: http://t.co/B4uN1uP6OU [2]: http://t.co/YTBdiM77Pi [3]: http://t.co/L5GbJqx8j6 [4]: http://t.co/DL9m3nGy13 [5]: http://t.co/ct5Mt8RY5i [6]: http://t.co/lcC1RDpjRv [7]: http://t.co/dhM6rlQlf1 [8]: http://t.co/QeyvWdDKZ1 [9]: http://t.co/uUY4neKHbF [10]: http://t.co/dWgmOKk42v [11]: http://t.co/8ZeISGvEcA [12]: http://t.co/mydWWz9j7M [13]: http://t.co/DDWIN8KLhM [14]: http://t.co/aIYv7zxrfd [15]: http://t.co/HJfljGY7Wq [16]: http://t.co/m2VUtiTJIp [17]: http://t.co/XGah5Xmop6 [18]: http://t.co/lYLAWDI04m [19]: http://t.co/9dZyVNhqWp [20]: http://t.co/L1Kaf4WLjK [21]: http://t.co/rZxsLenQk4 [22]: http://t.co/XfNZ1Jv5Rv [23]: http://t.co/lqnyQ0F4sN [24]: http://t.co/MJBhJuuxM3 [25]: http://t.co/Vk9PGzrItp [26]: http://t.co/UB6jzwgjla [27]: http://t.co/l1hrnCWuel [28]: http://t.co/vjydZFBFwG [29]: http://t.co/12SiH3ZkCp [30]: http://t.co/MYNALbXAJm [31]: http://t.co/k1BdJx1gR6 [32]: http://t.co/Saa7j6zkCQ [33]: http://t.co/VIGN6jhACy [34]: http://t.co/IJ0S2rRx8x [35]: http://t.co/HpYPLqoOKP [36]: http://t.co/YzXZDj9HlK [37]: http://t.co/gseGZd38Th [38]: http://t.co/aQolfRq0Y4 [39]: http://t.co/qkqkAGiP9Y [40]: http://t.co/RohgKncAnm [41]: http://t.co/N72lYfxhr9 [42]: http://t.co/TvwMcqj6eI [43]: http://t.co/s6OCOdwU83 [44]: http://t.co/W313rKFj2k [45]: http://t.co/KjdmHILaCV [46]: http://t.co/2Hu8ALqIwW [47]: http://t.co/a0WSKAEIom [48]: http://t.co/cDgYwRUI7A [49]: http://t.co/3SMaboCeG6 [50]: http://t.co/KEHLTIKesD [51]: http://t.co/nxSBVl2QB2 [52]: http://t.co/2mSC2NGByA [53]: http://t.co/LE6EGqinq2 [54]: http://t.co/dH1FwKNEsr [55]: http://t.co/hr8TTFBpge [56]: http://t.co/Kzbgp20yRG [57]: http://t.co/bjvqvgXRc5

]]></text></news-item>