<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9CBE-9B63-36E6-6B07"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Grabbing river lands key target</title><source>The New Nation (Bangladesh)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Dhaka, March 15 -- The encroachment into rivers by land grabbers in liaison with some influential vested quarters continues unabated across the country allegedly taking the relax mood of the concerned authorities.
Sand traders along with dozens of powerful housing companies and big industrial groups are also grabbing rivers and wetlands in and around the capital Dhaka. The scenario is almost reportedly the same in other parts of the country.
In this backdrop, country's eminent environmentalists on Friday urged the government to form a River Authority and an impartial River Commission to save the rivers from illegal encroachment by the vested quarters. Besides, they also laid emphasis on immediate formulation of a River Policy.
They revealed the observation report of the rivers of Bangladesh- 2013 on the eve of International Rivers Saving Day at the Dhaka Reporters Unity. The environmental organizations include Bangladesh Paribesh Andolon [BAPA] and National Rivers Save Movement [NRSM].
In Dhaka, the land grabbers have already eaten vast areas of the five rivers - Buriganga, Shitalakhya, Dhaleshwari, Turag and Balu by dumping barbage. Not only that about forty canals and couples of floodwater flow zones in the capital are also under the grip of illegal encroachers.
There is widespread allegation that the joint committee, comprising the officials of the deputy commissioner offices in Dhaka, Gazipur, Narayanganj along with the BIWTA, has demarcated the river area apparently leaving a large portion on both sides of the rivers in favour of the grabbers.
Coordinator of National Rivers Save Movement Dr Abdul Matin, in his report, gave reference of 143 reports on country's 57 rivers and said the rivers are going under the grip of illegal grabbers due to 'ill motive of a powerful quarters'.Apart from sand extraction, Dr Matin said, the unplanned dams and sluice gates made by WDB and low-height bridges and culverts are contributing to the river disaster.
"Besides, local influential vested quarters, political leaders and activists, industrialists, government and private organizations are grabbing the rivers in various ways. Piling of wastages of industries, hospitals, residences and others beside the riverbanks are not only polluting the water, but also narrowing the waterways," he noted.
Dr MdSamsuddoha Khandaker, Chairman of BIWTA, however, refuting the allegation said, "In a meeting in February at the Ministry of Shipping, we took some decisions to save the rivers from land grabbers. We will take stern action against those who are grabbing the rivers and polluting the water body by dumping waste.
"Experts have alleged that the Detailed Area Plan [DAP] for Dhaka city and other relevant laws to protect country's mainstream water flows are simply remaining on paper only. And so, taking the advantage, the encroachers are grabbing the rivers and wetlands without fear.
"Real Estate developers have filled up most of the wetlands and flood flow zones in and around Dhaka using the loopholes of laws. Obviously, the grabbing of flood-prone zones and water bodies will destruct the ecological balance," Dr Sarwar Jahan, Prof of Department of Urban and Regional Planning, BUET, said.Prof Jamilur Reza Choudhury said, "Several land developers have grabbed embankment of rivers around Dhaka.
They are filling up flood flow zones also. But it was not possible for them, if the DAP was implemented properly. In fact, the DAP was not implemented due to negligence of the authorities concerned." "There are many reasons for non-effectiveness of DAP. However, we are now working to make the DAP effective.
To apply acts and laws properly, the DAP to be divided into eight areas. We are also conducting drives against illegal land grabbing by developers," said Engineer Nurul Huda, Chairman of Rajdhani Unnyan Katripakha [RAJUK].
Published by HT Syndication with permission from The New Nation. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>