<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9CD5-83E7-1D19-757D"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Pak Sar Zameen</title><source>Weekly Cutting Edge</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Gul Saba picks on the food in her plate, takes two bites of it and stops. I look at her, "Have some more, Gul. You have a long way to go before you reach Islamabad."Her eyes, misty and moist, stare straight ahead at nothing in particular. She drops her gaze. "I don't know if Bhai has had even a sip of water, how can I eat? My mother faints each time she hears his name. She doesn't eat, no one does, no one can."
Mohammad Ramzan has been missing for 4 years now. On 14 July, 2010, he left home with his brother and son, Ali Haider, then 6 years old, for Gawadar, never to come back. Ali Haider witnessed the abduction of his father from Zero Point ,Uthal, with his own eyes. He brought back his father's traditional Balochi cap on his return home. Mohammad Ramzan ironed people's clothes for a living. How his mother, wife and children are coping and surviving is another story, a lesson in fortitude.Gul Saba, Ali Haider and Samina (Ali Haider's sister) have walked with Mama Qadeer Baloch and other marchers from Quetta to Islamabad, in a determined, profound and dignified attempt, to raise awareness of the nation about the 18,000 missing, abducted or killed Baloch. They were not, as many believe, chanting anti-state slogans, they weren't out to get anyone, and they weren't asking for a separate homeland for the Baloch; these people are mostly women and children. They were, and still are, asking the state to follow its own rules; to account for their missing family members: a father, a brother, a son; bring them to a court of law and provide them with fair trials. And they are hoping for international organizations to take notice. It's a call for justice from the families of the victims of extrajudicial disappearance. Their destination was the UN Office in Islamabad, where they reached, after their long hard trek through Balochistan, Sind and most of the Punjab, to present their memorandum on March 3, 2014.Each member of the march puts the blame for the disappearances and murders squarely on the establishment, saying that it has either witnessed, or has eyewitnesses to, the abductions and killings by the agencies. One feels skeptical of the claims, until, first a truck tries to make mince meat of the marchers near Sakrand, injuring 3. The truck driver conveniently flees police custody after arrest. Then, on arriving at Wazirabad, the marchers and their supporters are harassed, even threatened by "authorities". They are told to stop the march and disperse. The sympathizers, supporters, activists and the common curious citizens are questioned and intimidated. Even their hosts at 7 Chak Raowan Wala and one of the drivers are contacted and questioned. Their CNIC numbers and telephone numbers are collected and they are asked how they knew these Baloch and why they are supporting them.The drama is repeated at Gujrat by different faces in uniform and plain clothes.Why? Why is this peaceful group of women who are hardly more than girls, and children, the youngest being 8, accompanied by a 72-year-old man, such a threat? What brand of freedom punishes you for walking a few yards with the bereaved and aggrieved for purely humanitarian reasons? What kind of people are we? Are we so dead within that the solemn group of photograph-carrying marchers, with feet cracked and bleeding after walking over 2,800 km on foot, doesn't move us? Or is it fear? Fear of offending the powers in some obscure way and have their wrath befall us?Also, one wonders about the media presence or, rather, the lack of it, in Lahore and other areas of the Punjab. Most Lahorites remained unaware of the arrival and presence of the historical march in their city. They missed the opportunity to meet the Baloch and hear their story. The Baloch, for their part, did not seem surprised. "This is what we expect of the Punjab" said Mama Qadeer, while the few in attendance squirmed. It seems that the people of the Punjab were intentionally kept uninformed by keeping the story untold in the electronic media.The VBMP March did not stop and has safely concluded in Islamabad, the mission to petition the UN accomplished. What it has accomplished in over a 100 days of the history-making walk to justice, is a slightly raised awareness of the nation. No one will have the excuse of not knowing about the plight of Balochistan and its people anymore. It has also exposed the ethnic biases and the totalitarianism in a country that calls itself free.Farzana Majeed, the sister of the missing political activist Zakir Majeed, and one of the leaders of VBMP asked the media to give her answers instead of asking inane questions about Baloch politics. She said that she has gone on hunger strikes, has demanded justice in the High Court and the Supreme Court to no avail. "Bring my brother to the court, try him for the allegations the State has put against him, and then you will see if Farzana Majeed will still protest."In the aftermath of the discovery of mass graves in Khuzdar region of the insurgence-struck Balochistan, where 169 bodies were found in advanced stages of decomposition, the VBMP march raises tough questions about the state's governance, intelligence agencies' involvement and military operation in the area. Amnesty International, in its recent report regarding the finding, has expressed grave concern: The Pakistan government must immediately provide accountability for the alarming number of killings and abductions in Balochistan attributed to government forces in recent months. The military and government agencies categorically deny their involvement and say that the casualties are a result of rival groups fighting each other.In the last few months, about 90 Baloch have disappeared or been murdered. The top targets being political activists, journalists, lawyers and teachers. Most operations were "kill and dump" according to the report. The bodies, when recovered bore torture marks in addition to the "usual bullet holes." Sam Zarifi, Director Asia-Pacific for Amnesty International said, "These atrocities are carried out with flagrant impunity. Credible investigations into these incidents - resulting in prosecutions - are absolutely necessary to establish some trust between the Baloch people and the Pakistan government."
]]></text></news-item>