<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9D7A-6D64-45BB-F2D0"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Ethical standards in finance still fall short</title><source>The Business Times Singapore</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[THE 2008 financial crisis so epitomised greed and misselling of investment products that one thought one had seen the worst of the finance industry. But then came the scandal over the manipulation of the benchmark Libor interest rate, over which a number of banks have been fined. Then there are rumblings over the possible manipulation of exchange rates. And as if all that was not enough, there is now the allegation of price fixing in the gold market.
While the principle of "buyer beware" generally applies to most things that are bought and sold, that does not and should not apply to aspects of the financial market which depend on confidence in market benchmarks, and where the setting of benchmarks such as Libor and forex indices is rife with information asymmetry.
The forex market in particular is touted as the most efficient financial market with US$4.7 trillion traded daily. Yet it is also the least regulated. As it takes place outside exchanges, the potential for manipulation, as alleged in a Bloomberg report last June, is huge. The largest banks are market makers themselves, who buy and sell on clients' behalf and also on their own accounts. The conflicts of interest are obvious, and the so-called code of ethics or best practices may not be worth the paper they are printed on. Absent regulation, the alleged practice of front-running, where a dealer favours trades for selected clients or for himself at the expense of others, should perhaps not be surprising. But what was also egregious was that trade information was apparently shared among dealers and counterparties through chatrooms and instant messaging.
Regulators in the UK and the US are scrutinising not just forex but other indices including commodities and gold. The investigations have come none too soon; such practices have reportedly been going on since the 1990s. Concern over possible manipulation were apparently raised with the Bank of England in 1996.
The prospect of regulation in forex trading, however, is unclear as currencies are not considered financial products and hence, sit in a regulatory gray area. The currency market, for example, is not included in the US' Dodd-Frank Act which seeks to establish a regulatory framework for derivatives. In any case, market participants in forex would be reluctant to have strictures that could add friction to trades.
The investigations are a good wake-up call. Banks and market makers should exercise stricter oversight of their dealers; internal systems should monitor any unusual bunching up of trades around the time that benchmark rates are set. The best practice guideline where dealers are told to avoid conflicts of interest should be internally enforceable, and errant traders should be censured. What is at stake is confidence in the financial industry. Many institutions rely on benchmarks to price their products and there are repercussions even for retail investors. A 2013 Edelman Investor Trust Survey found that the financial services industry was the least trusted by the general public to do the right thing.
Ultimately financial institutions have a fiduciary role even if this is not spelt out in service contracts. Banks would do well to pay more than lip service to their ethical standards.
]]></text></news-item>