<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9DAB-CC17-B610-5792"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Levin opening statement, Senate Armed Services Committee hearing on U.S. Northern Command, U.S. Southern Command</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Office of the Senator Carl Levin, U.S Government has issued the following news release:
The committee meets this morning to consider the posture of our two combatant commands in the Western Hemisphere. We are pleased to welcome General Chuck Jacoby, the Commander of U.S. Northern Command, and General John Kelly, the Commander of U.S. Southern Command. Thank you both for your service and leadership, and we ask that you pass along our gratitude to the many men and women, military and civilian, who serve with you, as well as their families, who help to make your missions successful.
One of the three strategic pillars of the national defense strategy highlighted in the recent Quadrennial Defense Review is to “protect the homeland, to deter and defeat attacks on the United States and to support civil authorities in mitigating the effects of potential attacks and natural disasters.” That sums up the mission of NORTHCOM. We look forward to hearing how General Jacoby is implementing this strategic priority and what impact the budget caps imposed by the Budget Control Act are having on this mission.
General Jacoby is responsible for the operation of our homeland ballistic missile defense system, the Ground-based Midcourse Defense system, which has had several flight test failures caused by problems that need to be corrected and demonstrated before we deploy more interceptors. We will be interested in his views on the need for testing and improving our GMD system, particularly its sensor and discrimination capabilities, and on improving its future kill vehicles with a new design.
In its mission to provide defense support to civil authorities, NORTHCOM works closely with other federal agencies and with the Governors and the National Guard. We hope to hear how the budget request will affect the command’s ability to respond to natural and man-made disasters and to promote regional security through our security partnerships with Canada and Mexico, including efforts with Mexico to reduce the twin scourges of violence and illicit trafficking of drugs, money, weapons, and people.
Both of our witnesses face the threat of Transnational Criminal Organizations, or so-called TCOs – organizations that breed instability, corruption, and violence throughout the region, undermining democratic institutions and civil society with their illicit trafficking operations. General Kelly, your prepared opening statement goes so far as to call these TCOs “corporations.” I look forward to your views on the effectiveness of our law enforcement, military, and intelligence efforts to take on these entities.
General Kelly, as a result of funding restrictions required by the budget caps, the military services have reduced their support of your requirements substantially. I hope you will provide the committee with an understanding of the choices you have had to make in mitigating the impact of funding cuts. As an example, last year, you reported the success of “Operation Martillo,” which fused intelligence and operations efforts to take on illicit drug trafficking. The results of this operation were impressive. However, under current and proposed funding levels, I understand the Navy will have little choice but to reduce the deployments that would support the continuation of this operation.
SOUTHCOM faces a multitude of other security challenges, including training and equipping militaries of friendly nations; training and equipping peacekeepers for deployment to multilateral peacekeeping operations across the globe; enabling, advising, and supporting Colombian military and law enforcement operations; monitoring the activities of Russia, China, Iran, and non-state actors in the hemisphere; growing political instability in Venezuela; and responding to requests from the State Department for additional security forces and evacuation support. We would be interested in any targeted funding or authorities that may be needed to carry out these missions.
For further information please visit:http://www.levin.senate.gov
]]></text></news-item>