<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9DEE-5031-1911-5633"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>The 24-hour political party people! Bez wants to be MP; Happy Mondays star to stand in Salford and pledges support to anti-fracking protesters</title><source>Manchester Evening News</source><author>Emily Heward</author><text><![CDATA[HAPPY Mondays star Bez has revealed he plans to run for MP in Salford at next year's general election.
The freaky dancer, 49, said he wanted to 'stir things up' as he described his vision for a new world order, the redistribution of wealth and an end to war.
He revealed his plans as he spoke out in support of anti-fracking protesters at Barton Moss.
He will visit the camp tomorrow before joining environmental campaigners as they walk in front of energy firm IGas's lorries to slow their entry into the site on Monday.
He said: "I've been saying we need a revolution and there's no good shouting about it when you're not actually doing anything.
If you want to do something about things you've got to get into the corridors of power and take them on."
The 2005 Celebrity Big Brother winner added: "If you're voting for me, you're voting as a protest about what's happening in the world at the moment."
He said his policies would end the present banking system before confiscating their wealth and redistributing it.
Bez added: "I'm going to create a new world order and get rid of them and start again with a new, fairer system without evil being the main policy."
Ending 'all war' and putting a stop to 'divide and rule' strategies he accused current world leaders of would also be top of his agenda, he added.
And promoting sustainable living would also be a priority for the keen beekeeper.
He said: "One of my policies would be a permacultural society where we'll end illness and get everybody back to an alkaline state."
Bez claimed doing so could tackle diseases such as cancer and dementia.
His policies for Salford, however, are less clear.
"I don't know yet, I'm in the midst of writing it up.
"I've got lots of meetings with different people next week."
Bez, who was born and raised in Salford, said he had only made the decision to stand in the last few days but said he was 'pretty serious' about it.
It is likely he will stand as an independent candidate in his bid to replace Labour MP, Hazel Blears, who is stepping down next year.
The star also pledged his support to anti-fracking groups, saying: "I've always supported it quietly but I'm going along because people have put a lot of time and effort into protesting against an unsafe technology.
"I believe in free energy and there's alternative energy sources out there but the bankers and the people in charge don't want to use them."
Martin Porter, of Frack Free Greater Manchester, said the maraca-shaker's visit would 'pep up the camp a bit' after a tough week of battling eviction.
He said: "Camp life can be a bit chaotic, but after being in the Happy Mondays I'm sure he'll be used to that."
Comment: Page 8 »
'I'm going to create a new world order'
]]></text></news-item>