<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9DEF-15B5-25EC-631E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Car plows into SXSW crowds; 2 killed, 23 injured when driver flees after DUI stop</title><source>Chicago Tribune</source><author>By August Brown and Matt Pearce, Tribune Newspapers</author><text><![CDATA[Rashad Charjuan Owens was a music producer with hopes of stardom. He lived in Killeen, Texas, about 70 miles from this city's famed South by Southwest conference, the annual festival where the world of music, film and technology blur.
An officer on drunken-driving patrol tried to get Owens to stop at about 12:30 a.m. Thursday, police said. But the car took off, weaving, then accelerating the wrong way on a one-way street. The driver went through police barricades set up on Red River Street to make the area safe for SXSW pedestrians and then dashed through the entertainment district where the bands X and TEEN had just wrapped up their sets.
During the chase, the vehicle -- which may have been stolen -- hit a moped, a taxi and a bicyclist, then went up on a sidewalk and hit a van, police said. The suspect police have identified as Owens took off on foot, they said, and two officers gave chase, eventually using a Taser to subdue him.
Two people -- the bicyclist, who was an employee of a music company in the Netherlands, and an Austin woman, who worked as a sales clerk at a local boutique -- were dead. In all, 23 others, including the suspect, were injured; five are listed in critical condition, police said.
"I saw bodies fly into the air, and there was blood and it was unbelievable," said Jayda Luna, 21, a junior at Texas State University who was waiting in line to buy tickets when the person standing next to him was hit. "It was the most horrific thing I've ever seen in my entire life."
Formal charges are pending and will include two counts of capital murder and multiple counts of aggravated assault with a motor vehicle, police said.
Owens described himself on his Facebook page as a father and an employee of fast-food stores. He said he recently earned his GED in Alaska and attended a Florida university, studying toward a degree in music production.
A search of public records shows Owens had several misdemeanor arrests out of the Fairbanks Fourth District in Alaska, including being charged as a minor under the influence of alcohol and criminal trespass. In October 2011, he was charged with driving under the influence and leaving the scene of an accident, the Fairbanks records show.
He pleaded guilty only to the DUI misdemeanor charge, and prosecutors dismissed the misdemeanor offense for fleeing, according to the filings.
Owens was twice convicted of criminal trespass in Killeen, which seems to have been his most recent home. In August 2010, he was arrested for criminal trespass at Killeen High School, and in the second case, in January 2011, he entered a convenience store from which he had previously been banned. The clerk recognized him and contacted police.
He served 60 days in jail on each conviction and was ordered to pay $324 in court costs and fines for each.
The bicyclist who died at the scene was identified as Steven Craenmehr, 35, of the Amsterdam-based music booking and promotion agency MassiveMusic.
The second fatality was identified as Jamie Ranae West, 27, of Austin. She was married and worked as a sales clerk at a boutique.
xcxabrown@tribune.com
ct14 0037 140314 R S 0000000000 00003479
]]></text></news-item>