<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9E6F-F38A-D879-B27C"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Health advocates ask gov't to ban tobacco industry's CSR works</title><source>Philippines News Agency</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ANILA, March 16 -- The New Vois Association of the Philippines (NVAP), a group of cancer survivors and former smokers, is urging the government to ban tobacco companies from engaging in corporate social responsibility activities which health advocates suspect are being used as fronts to promote smoking.
While CSR may be viewed as a noble way to give back to the people, NVAP believes that tobacco firms are using these activities to promote their products which violates the ban on advertising.
'Philip Morris Fortune Tobacco Corporation Incorporated, the country's largest tobacco maker, for instance, has been spending millions of pesos in CSR activities that they course through some government departments and a couple of non-government organizations.
These happen despite the ad ban and Memorandum Circular (MC2010-01) of the Civil Service Commission prohibiting public servants from interacting with the tobacco industry," said Emer Rojas, NVAP's president.
In 2012 alone, PMFTC spent more than P90 million in funding projects for some NGOs and a couple of local government units in Ilocos where most tobacco products come from.
'The cash and goods donated by the tobacco companies are paid by the blood money of tobacco victims. Sure there are people made happy by these donations but let's not forget that these are paid by the lives of 10 people who die every hour because of smoking-related diseases. Money received from tobacco firms will never outweigh the cost of losing a loved one and the burden that smoking creates on our health care system,' said Rojas whose group is also pushing for the passage of the graphic health warnings law in Congress.
Last month, the Southeast Asia Tobacco Control Alliance ranked the Philippines as the worst in terms of having 'unnecessary interactions' between government and the industry in a study that indexed tobacco industry interference among seven countries in Southeast Asia.
'It is unfortunate when you read the newspapers and see industry bosses shaking hands with government officials for photo ops of certain CSR activities. Because of tobacco industry's close interaction with government they tend to influence policy development. How can government be so oblivious to these dirty tactics?' lamented Rojas.
Aside from the CSC circular, Rojas said allowing industry CSR also violates provisions of Republic Act 9211 or the tobacco ad ban because the law explicitly prohibits all forms of sponsorship from cigarette makers.
'As cunning as it is, the industry uses CSR activities as a front to advertize their products. When you read about a local government official or a bishop of a northern Luzon province openly praising a tobacco company for infusing money to certain projects you know that the problem of industry interference in this country is really serious. Unless we put a stop into these activities all our efforts for stronger tobacco control would surely be compromised,' ends Rojas.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Philippines News Agency. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>