<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9EDD-6473-77F5-0496"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Ukraine sanctions move upsets oligarchs</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Roland Gribben</author><text><![CDATA[RUSSIAN oligarchs with extensive interests in Britain have been attempting to lower the risk to their assets from sanctions, which the EU is expected to impose over the Ukraine crisis.
Some are understood to have switched funds out of London but others are said to be prepared to "sweat it out" in anticipation that the crisis will ease.
The potential impact of sanctions has been reflected in estimates showing that Russia's 10 top billionaires have seen the value of their assets slump by $6.6bn (£3.9bn) in just the past week.
Russian companies have already switched vast sums out of western banks in anticipation of sanctions.
The Federal Reserve Bank of New York has reported a drop of $104bn in treasury securities held by foreign institutions in recent days and pointed the finger at the Russian central bank.
EU ministers are due to meet in London today to try to agree on sanctions. Britain will press for an extensive freeze on Russian assets and a widespread travel ban.
David Cameron is said to be anxious to throw Britain's full weight behind a tough list of sanctions after being embarrassed by photographs of a government document expressing concern about the effect on London markets and the global economy of anti-Russian sanctions.
EU ministers have already agreed to introduce targeted sanctions freezing the assets of key figures in the dispute but officials have gone further and drawn up lists of individuals they feel are guilty of money-laundering.
The growing London population of Russian businessmen is attempting to come to terms with action that could halt their operations and damage a London luxury housing market highly dependent on their purchases.
Sanctions would halt the flow of Russian companies seeking London listings. Analysts feel the overall effect on Britain would be limited but, with exports to Russia showing rapid growth, the impact on exporters could be damaging in the event of retaliatory measures.
Already-nervous markets will also provide an early pointer today about the impact of the Crimea election.
]]></text></news-item>