<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="9F71-7AB9-6895-7939"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Volusia mortgage fraud trial rescheduled, new judge assigned</title><source>News-Journal (Daytona Beach, Florida)</source><author>Lyda Longa, Lyda Longa lyda.longa@news-jrnl.com</author><text><![CDATA[The Volusia mortgage fraud trial set for federal court next week has been rescheduled to theof the month and a new judge has been assigned, court records show.
Enlarge
James Sotolongo is a convicted cocaine smuggler who is charged in a large-scale mortgage fraud case in Volusia County. He is affiliated with Waverly Media and Waverly Properties.
The case, investigated by the FBI for three years before several suspect were indicted, will now be heard by U.S. District Judge Anne C. Conway, the chief judge of the Middle District of Florida. The trial will begin on March 31.
U.S. District Judge Roy B. Dalton Jr. recused himself from the case because he is a stockholder in a bank linked to one of the co- conspirators who was never charged in the case, but who pleaded guilty for his part in the mortgage fraud operation.
The main suspects in FBI-dubbed Sotolongo Mortgage Fraud Ring include Jim Sotolongo; his live-in girlfriend Ramara Garrett, a former real estate broker; title agent Stephanie Musselwhite and mortgage broker Christopher Mencis.
According to Dalton's order, issued Thursday, Musselwhite's attorney Richard Klugh asserted that Dalton had a conflict because he once sat on the board of Seaside National Bank, an institution that Sidney Coton of Deltona -- named as a co-conspirator in the operation by the FBI but who was never charged -- was linked to.
Klugh did not return a message left Friday.
In his four-page order, Dalton said information in the media didn't lead to the decision.
"As to the claim regarding recently published news articles, the media's assessment of the Court's disposition toward these defendants is not grounds for disqualification," Dalton wrote.
Dalton quoted from the case United States v. Greenough: "A charge of partiality must be supported by facts, and although public confidence may be as much shaken by publicized inferences of bias that are false as by those that are true, a judge considering whether to disqualify himself must ignore rumors, innuendos, and erroneous information published as fact in the newspapers."
Dalton then mentioned Klugh, saying: "Tellingly, Musselwhite's counsel has previously characterized the exact same media coverage to which he cites in support of recusal, as 'prejudicial' and 'inflammatory' when the coverage was directed at his own client."
The jurist also said that his knowledge of the Coton issue with Seaside is not a basis for his disqualification.
Dalton said the reason he is recusing himself from the case is because he is a current stockholder of Seaside and if Musselwhite and any other member of the ring are found guilty and ordered to pay restitution, then Seaside could possibly benefit from that restitution.
"Inasmuch as the undersigned remains a stockholder in the bank, this factor, and only this factor properly raises an issue warranting recusal," Dalton stated.
Klugh tried to have Dalton removed from the case once before.
In a hearing on the case in mid-February, Klugh said that federal prosecutor Tanya Wilson and the attorney representing Coton had arranged for the case to be transferred to Dalton without the knowledge of defense attorneys. The practice is referred to as "forum shopping." Klugh argued that the judge who had the case before Dalton -- U.S. District Judge Charlene Honeywell -- was more flexible. Klugh also complained that a newspaper editorial implied Dalton was tougher and would "hammer" the individuals accused by the FBI of committing mortgage fraud. Klugh wanted the case transferred back to Honeywell, but his motion was denied by Dalton.
Klugh's motions were filed soon after Dalton rejected the guilty plea filed by Sotolongo and his attorney John Bergendahl in early February. The judge nixed the agreement after learning that Sotolongo would be convicted of one count of defrauding the United States, an offense that carries a maximum of five years in prison. The judge said the plea agreement offered to the suspect was "too lenient."
The four main conspirators in the operation were arrested last spring and charged with various counts of bank fraud and conspiracy to defraud the United States. FBI agents have said the mortgage fraud transactions carried out by Sotolongo, Garrett, Musselwhite and Mencis and their three co-conspirators -- which includes Coton - - involved 70 properties in Central Florida and the theft of $50 million.
]]></text></news-item>