<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A06D-EA61-E31C-2689"><date>2014-03-17</date><title></title><source>South China Morning Post</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Tycoon meets journalists after conviction
Businessman Steven Lo Kit-sing (pictured) meets the media today following his conviction by a Macau court on corruption charges. He and property tycoon Joseph Lau Luen-hung were sentenced to five years and three months in jail for their part in a bribes-for-land racket involving jailed former Macau official Ao Man-long. They were accused of giving Ao a HK$20 million bribe in return for land for a luxury housing project. Neither is likely to serve time unless they visit Macau.
Barrister speaks about information access
Barrister Russell Coleman addresses the Foreign Correspondents' Club on whether Hong Kong needs freedom of information legislation. Coleman heads a Law Reform Commission sub-committee which is studying the issue. Hong Kong has had an administrative code on access to information since 1995. Critics say the current system is not good enough and formal legislation is required.
Chief Justice Geoffrey Ma Tao-li (pictured) addresses the question of rights and respect for the rights of others at the Lingnan University assembly. He will focus on the Basic Law and its provisions on fundamental rights of Hong Kong residents. He is also likely to be questioned about his predecessor, Andrew Li Kwok-nang's comments on the need to protect press freedom, following the stabbing of former Ming Pao chief editor Kevin Lau Chun-to.
A commission of inquiry on the human rights situation in North Korea presents its hard-hitting report to the UN Human Rights Council. The report shows evidence for a wide array of crimes, including deliberate starving of people and abductions. The commission, which conducted public hearings with more than 80 victims and other witnesses, calls on the UN Security Council to refer its findings to the International Criminal Court.
Palestinian president Mahmoud Abbas (pictured) meets US President Barack Obama at the White House for talks on the peace process. The two leaders are expected to discuss Israeli-Palestinian negotiations and further bilateral co-operation. The talks come two weeks after Obama met Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu for discussions on the peace talks and relations with Iran.
Irish people throughout the world - including Hong Kong - celebrate St Patrick's Day. There will be traditional parades in Dublin and New York. The event is particularly poignant this year after Ireland won the Six Nations rugby tournament after a close victory over France.
]]></text></news-item>