<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A0BE-DD92-7A0E-14B3"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Opp outcry govt's failure over Amina Bibi suicide</title><source>The Frontier Post</source><author> Naeemullah</author><text><![CDATA[The opposition in Punjab Assembly outcry over the hear-trembling incidence of Amina Bibi suicide after allegedly being deprived of justice subsequent to her rape triggered the government to take serious notice of the issue- thereafter the Provincial Law Minister Rana Sanaullah ensured the house to present police inquiry report next Monday.
The house of legislators which witnessed tremendous unanimity of opposition and treasury members came apart here on Friday on the issue of Amina Bibi, who committed suicide in Muzaffargarh by setting herself on fire in front of local police station after being deprived of justice.
The opposition made consistent outcry and boycotted the house proceedings over the issue. Members lamented government and police performance which released the alleged rapist Nadar Khan owing to which Amina Bibi committed suicide.
Upon opposition protest and boycott, the law Minister pledged to present the report in the house and stated that Punjab Chief Minister has appointed Additional Inspector General to probe the sad incident.
The Law Minister told the House that according to the FIR, Amina was not raped but some accused made attempt to rape her when she was going with brother.
He further said that she had identified one of the accused named Nadar Khan who is younger brother-in-law of her sister and the victim and accused families have some mutual business disputes too and on the same grounds he was bailed from the jail and declared innocent in the police report.
Law minister said that police department could not be blamed after misconduct of some police officials. He also showed concerns over NGOs on-going allegation over government and said that Farzana Bari, an human rights activist, was showing poor face of the government and the society before the world to build only her own image.
The law minister maintained support of culprits and police officials' negligence as he did not described them as innocent.
On this, the opposition members stood on their benches and alleged the law minister for giving cover to the killer-police and twisting the investigation from rapists to toward the general public who were standing near the girl when she set her on a fire.
Meanwhile, provincial minister Malik Tanveer Aslam answered queries about his department, the Communication and Works. Replying to a query, he informed the House that his department had no concern with the construction and completion of the new building of Punjab Assembly or its residential facilities for legislators.
The opposition leader Mehmood ur Rasheed also raised the issue of disappearance of the machinery used in construction of new assembly building. The session started one hour and 20 minutes late to its schedule time at 9am under the Chair of Deputy Speaker Sher Ali Gorchani. Assembly session would resume again on Monday at3pm.
]]></text></news-item>