<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A0DC-2929-AD39-DDEE"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Asbestos scare brings Origin drills to a halt</title><source>The Australian</source><author>SARAH-JANE TASKER</author><text><![CDATA[GAS: Origin Energy, operator of the Australia Pacific LNG project, has suspended drilling at coal-seam gas sites in Queensland after asbestos was found in drilling fluids.
The company announced to the market yesterday that it had taken the precautionary measure to suspend its drilling operations across 12 rig sites in southwest central Queensland to allow for an investigation into a supply incident.
``This measure follows notification from one of our drilling fluid suppliers, Australian Mud Company, that an imported product (NUTPLUG) sometimes used in drilling fluids has been found to contain asbestos,'' Origin said.
Origin Energy, which has the nation's biggest CSG reserves, said that when it was notified by AMC of the potential of affected material it took immediate action to safeguard its employees, contractors and landholders.
``All stocks of affected material have been quarantined and accounted for throughout the supply chain from storage warehouse to site, and specialist waste removal experts are in the process of removing that material from each location for safe disposal,'' the company said. ``In the interim, an alternative product has been sourced.''
Green groups have voiced strong opposition to CSG projects amid concerns of water contamination. It was revealed this week that Santos was fined $1500 for a minor leak from a holding pond at its project in the Pilliga forest in northwestern NSW.
The project was previously owned by Eastern Star Gas before Santos took it over and Santos was fined $52,000 last year for a spill at the site that occurred under the watch of Eastern Star Gas.
The NSW government has signed a memorandum of understanding to fast-track the Pilliga project to address a looming shortage in gas supplies in NSW but opposition groups are concerned by the move.
Protests were held yesterday outside the offices of Nationals MPs for Tamworth, Dubbo, Grafton and Lismore as locals from across northern NSW call for action to protect water supplies and farmland from CSG mining following the groundwater contamination in the Pilliga.
]]></text></news-item>