<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A10F-B681-698F-5E29"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Minister Demanded $70k Bribe - Mugabe</title><source>New Zimbabwe</source><author>Staff Reporter</author><text><![CDATA[If there was corruption, people will answer for it ... President Robert Mugabe on Friday
Mugabe birthday party in pictures
PRESIDENT Robert Mugabe claimed Friday that an unnamed cabinet minister and a lawmaker demanded a bribe from a potential investor as he vowed a crackdown against corruption and warned that those implicated would be sent to prison.
Speaking at a birthday luncheon hosted by security services chiefs and the Public Service Commission, Mugabe said the minister demanded a bribe of $70,000 while the lady legislator demanded a $50,000 facilitation fee.
"Corruption, corruption, corruption! It is hurting us, it is hurting Africa," the Zanu PF leader declared.
"I was being told that there is this man who wants to invest, and was led to a lady in Parliament and this lady says yes, yes I can take you to more important people but give me $50,000, alright and I will open the door for you.
"He went to another high placed minister and said I want to establish some company, take me to the President, yes but give me $70,000."
Mugabe's latest claim will likely be taken with a pinch of salt after he, last year, ordered the arrest of Godwills Masimirembwa, the former head of the government's mining development firm (ZMDC) over alleged corruption.
Officially opening the current Parliament last September, Mugabe claimed Masimirembwa had taken a $6 million bribe from a Ghanaian investor who wanted to venture into diamond mining in the country.
The Zanu PF leader however backtracked this year, saying he had been misled by his informers.
However media reports have alleged rampant corruption involving senior officials across a number of state-run bodies including the government pensions authority, power utilities and the national airline, Air Zimbabwe.
Bosses at the ZBC grossly inflated their salaries while failing to pay ordinary workers for more than six months. Elsewhere, the CEO of a public service health insurance fund, which has been in arrears in its remittances to hospitals and practitioners, was said to be earning a monthly salary of $230,000.
Ministers have also been implicated in the rot, with several accused of demanding bribes from prospective investors and companies bidding for government contracts.
On Friday Mugabe vowed insisted warned that, "If there was any corruption, people will answer for it, I tell you."
"We will send them to prisons netai dzenyu idzodzo, munonodzibisirwa ikoko, momboenda kujeri, takamboendeswawo kumajere but takanga tisina corruption tairwira nyika, mombonobvumbiswa ikoko, majeri gadhi, zvese izvi vanozviita.
"But we do not want people to undergo such unnecessary suffering, but it is what is happening, what is happening everywhere, vanoda chemuhomwe ichochi," said Mugabe.
He said corruption as a "growing disease" which had "ruined the country. Anyway, we are still better but the disease definitely is growing amongst us and it needs us all us to prevent it from going further.
"Be clean. The cleanliness that I am talking about is not that of suit and tie, that is important yes, it is that of your conduct and character," he said.
]]></text></news-item>