<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A170-4DCA-2019-F418"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Money laundering Dr Mosharraf on 3-day remand</title><source>The New Nation (Bangladesh)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Dhaka, March 14 -- A Dhaka court on Thursday placed BNP Standing Committee member Dr Khandaker Mosharraf Hossain on a three-day remand in a money laundering case.The BNP leader was arrested from his Gulshan residence on Wednesday night.Magistrate Shamsul Arefin of the Chief Metropolitan Magistrate (CMM) Court of Dhaka passed the order hearing on the remand plea for a three-day remand.Khandaker Mosharraf was produced to the court at about 2.30 pm amidst tight security. The Anti-Corruption Commission (ACC) Deputy Director Md Ahsan Ali sought the remand to quiz the accused in connection with the money laundering. The prosecution says that he laundered Tk 9,53,95,381 in his joint account with his wife Bilquis Akhter maintained with a private bank in London from 2001 to 2006, when he was a minister.
He was shown arrested in the case, the ACC filed on Wednesday.In the beginning of the hearing, ACC Special Public Prosecutor Md Kabir Hossain placed his arguments in favour of the three-day remand. Later, public prosecutors Meer Ahmed Ali Samad, Md Ruhul Amin Khan and Mahmud Hossain Zahangir supported move.On the other hand, defence lawyers Masud Ahmed Talukder, Abul Kalam Azad, Zainul Abedin Meah, Roknuzzaman and others filed bail petition for the BNP leader rejecting, the remand pleas. On February 6, the ACC filed the money laundering case against Khandaker Mosharraf Hossain, who was health minister in the BNP-led 2001-2006 coalition government.Mosharraf was granted anticipatory bail by a High Court Division but the Appellate Division scrapped that on February 24.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from The New Nation. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>