<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A202-4F6F-6DA1-C0B1"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>US and Russia talks fail to evolve consensus on Ukraine</title><source>Big News Network.com</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[LONDON - Talks between US Secretary of State John Kerry and Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov on the ongoing crisis in Ukraine ended Friday without any consensus as Moscow claimed it has the right to intervene to protect its people there as the West prepared to impose sanctions in the wake of a referendum in Crimea.
Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov said that Russia had no plans to invade eastern Ukraine but would respect Sunday's referendum in Crimea on whether to join Russia.
Speaking at the residency of the Russian Ambassador to London after talks with Kerry, Lavrov said that "differences remained" between the West and Russia over the future of the country, but stressed that the ongoing crisis was not the result of Russia's actions.
"We will respect the expression of the will of the Crimean people in in the upcoming referendum," Lavrov told reporters.
"The Russian Federation does not and cannot have any plans to invade the southeastern regions of Ukraine" he added, following recent clashes in the Ukrainian city of Donetsk.
Kerry, who described the talks with Lavrov as "constructive", said he would like to see "actions and not words" that Russia was diminishing its presence in Ukraine.
"Our position on the referendum is clear," said Kerry during a press conference. "We believe the referendum is contrary to the constitution of Ukraine."
Kerry also said the US was "deeply concerned" about Russia sending troops to the Ukraine border and in Crimea.
Kerry warned: "There will be consequences if Russia does not find a way to change course."
The Russian Foreign Ministry in a statement issued Friday however reiterated that the nation reserved the right to intervene to defend ethnic Russians being threatened in eastern Ukraine.
At least one person was killed and 29 injured in violence when a hostile pro-Russian crowd confronted pro-Ukrainian activists in the city of Donetsk.
"Russia is aware of its responsibility for the lives of compatriots and fellow citizens in Ukraine and reserves the right to take people under its protection," the statement said.
Ukraine termed the Russian statement "impressive in its cynicism."
"(The Donetsk clashes had) a direct connection to deliberate, destructive actions of certain citizens of Russia and some Russian social organizations, representatives of which are present in our country to destabilize the situation and escalate tensions," Ukrainian Foreign Ministry spokesman Evgeny Perebiynis said, according to the Interfax news agency.
If Crimea secedes, the U.S. and European Union plan to slap sanctions as early as Monday on Russian officials and businesses accused of escalating the crisis and undermining Ukraine's new government, said Fox News.
It quoted German newspaper Bild as saying that visa bans - threatened by the U.S. and the European Union if Crimea votes to join Russia - would target 13 Russian politicians and industry leaders, including Russian President Vladimir Putin's close aides.
Bild said the visa ban list includes Russian Defense Minister Sergei Shoigu, Deputy Prime Minister Dmitry Rogozin, and several other prominent figures, Reuters reported.
The Bild story is an advance copy of a report to be published Saturday, citing diplomatic sources in Brussels and Washington.
Visa bans could also be slapped on the chief executive of Russian energy firm Gazprom Alexei Miller, and Igor Sechin, head of Russia's top crude oil producer Rosneft.
A spokesman for Rosneft lashed out about the report Friday, saying any move by the EU to impose a visa ban on Sechin would be "stupid" and hurt the Russian state oil company's Western partners more that Rosneft itself.
Russia has refused to recognise the interim government that took over in Kiev following Viktor Yanukovych's departure as president.
Thursday night saw clashes in Ukraine's eastern city of Donetsk between a pro-Russian crowd and supporters of the new Kiev government, which left at least one person dead..
]]></text></news-item>