<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A20E-CF67-DD19-5696"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Briefly</title><source>Sun Journal (Lewiston, Maine)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Church plans free, public dinner
AUBURN -- The Auburn Church of the Nazarene will hold a free, public spaghetti dinner at 5:30 p.m. Saturday, March 15, at the the church on Summer Street.
YPLAA trip is tomorrow
LEWISTON - The Young Professionals of the Lewiston Auburn Area invites the public to join in their second YPLAA Adventure Series trip from 11:30 a.m. to 7 p.m. Sunday, March 16.
Enjoy a Maine Red Claws basketball game followed by an evening in Portland. Perhaps grab dinner at a restaurant in the Old Port, visit a museum or browse the shops. The bus will be making different stops in downtown Portland for both drop off and pick up.
The cost to attend is a low $20 per ticket, which includes transportation and admission to the Red Claws Game. The bus will depart from Lewiston Park and Ride. All are welcome; YPLAA membership not required.
For more information and to purchase tickets visit yplaa.com/ calendar-of-events or call 207-783-2249.
National Service Animal Eye Exams
PORTLAND -- American College of Veterinary Ophthalmologists is gearing up for the seventh annual National Service Animal Eye Exam Event this May, and the success of this event hinges on the number of service animal owners that sign up for the free exams. Registration for the free exams opens April 1.
More than 250 veterinary ophthalmologists from the U.S., Canada and Puerto Rico will be participating, including the Portland area.
Registration for service animals and handlers runs from April 1- 30 at www.ACVOeyeexam.org.
Sparks' Ark aids Brain Injury Voices
PORTLAND -- A live animal presentation by Sparks' Ark, as well as photos with Squeezer the snake, animal crafts, door prizes, raffle table and bake sale will be held from 1:30 to 3 p.m. Saturday, March 22, at Stevens Avenue Armory, 772 Stevens Ave. Doors open at 1.
Donation is $5 per person. Photos with your camera are $2 extra. Tickets at the door. Space is limited.
Brain Injury Voices is a local volunteer group of brain injury survivors who educate, advocate and support those living and working with brain injury.
Brain Injury Voices was recently selected for the national Hospital Award for Volunteer Excellence, and members are trying to raise money to travel to Washington, D.C. to accept the award.
Role of archives socially, culturally
AUGUSTA -- The Holocaust and Human Rights Center and the Maine Jewish Film Festival will present a free conference titled "The Role of Archive in Restoring and Conserving Identity" from noon to 9 p.m. Tuesday, March 25, at the Michael Klahr Center, on the University of Maine at Augusta campus.
This dynamic conference -- open to students, professionals and the general public -- will encourage discussion on the critical role archive plays in both social and cultural contexts.
The day will conclude with a screening of the new documentary "Harbour of Hope," which features archival footage filmed on April 28, 1945 -- the day several hundreds of concentration camp survivors came to Malmo, Sweden on ships from Copenhagen.
The conference is free, but advance registration is strongly recommended. To register, call 207-621-3530 or email betsy.spekke@maine.edu For more information, visit the calendar page at hhrc.uma.edu.
SOUTH PORTLAND -- Tommy Pelletier, a long-term camper at Camp Susan Curtis in the 90s, will share his story of transformation from a Maine child-in-need to a senior currency trader at a private trading firm in New York when he speaks at the Camp Susan Curtis Leadership Celebration on Friday, March 28.
The Leadership Celebration marks the culmination of the Susan L. Curtis Charitable Foundation's annual campaign in support of camp programs and will be held at the Portland Marriott at Sable Oaks. The theme for this year's event echoes the motto for the programs of Camp Susan Curtis: "Every Child Matters."
More information and tickets for the semi-formal event are available by visiting www.susancurtisfoundation.org or by calling 207-774-1552.
UMA Youth Leadership Conference
AUGUSTA -- The UMA Student Government Association will host its annual leadership conference, Exemplary Leadership Through Community Service, in the Randall Student Center's Fireside Lounge from 9:30 a.m. to 2:30 p.m. Saturday, March 29.
Geared towards people of all ages, this year's conference features representatives from Pay It Forward x 1,000,000, The Red Barn Cares Foundation, Time Initiative of Maine and UMA's Office of Civic Engagement.
The cost of attending is $15 per person which includes lunch and a conference t-shirt. UMA students can attend free of charge. RSVP by contacting UMA Coordinator of Student Life, Rose Pelletier, at 207-621-3374 or rosep@maine.edu
]]></text></news-item>