<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A28A-A795-58A7-419B"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Families want tasty, safe pork, exec says</title><source>Des Moines Register</source><author>By, Christopher Doering</author><text><![CDATA[WASHINGTON - Consumers are more interested in how the pork they buy at the grocery store is raised, but most aren't demanding products that address those concerns, the head of the organization responsible for promoting the industry said in an interview.
Chris Novak, chief executive of the National Pork Board headquartered in Des Moines, said that while "a relatively small percentage of consumers" are looking to purchase pork from animals raised without antibiotics or under conditions they consider more humane, most families are more interested in buying meat that tastes good, is safe to eat and is fairly priced.
"When you get down to consumers making choices at the grocery store, we're not seeing any major shifts" toward these products, Novak said.
"We're doing a lot to make certain that we're attempting to speak to those consumers (focused on issues of food and food production), that we're attempting to address those needs and the concerns that they have brought forward. But at the end of the day we can't lose sight of the family that may be on a limited budget. They want a quality product; they want an affordable product."
A challenge for the pork industry is taking into account the varying and sometimes conflicting interests of the animal, farmer and consumer. For example, pork producers must not only consider the demands of the consumer, but also their need to produce a competitive, affordable item in a sustainable way. "There are tradeoffs and balances that have to be made, and that's part of our struggle right now," he said.
Increasingly, the pork industry has been under fire from critics who contend it has been reluctant to embrace more humane treatment for animals despite growing interest in such practices from consumers, producers and the food industry.
Despite these concerns, pork consumption rose 1.8 percent to 48.3pounds person in 2013, according to industry figures. An estimated 30 million pigs are raised in Iowa each year, making it the No. 1 pork-producing state in the United States and the leading state in pork exports.
Pork producers acknowledge they have struggled to effectively communicate to the public that they are using the best measures available while also looking for better ways to raise their animals. American pig farmers have given millions of dollars to the country's checkoff program to study animal welfare research and the best practices to use on the farm, Novak said.
"In my own background growing up on the farm, there wasn't necessarily a whole lot of people that looked or cared about what we did on our farm," Novak said. That has changed, he said, as consumers want to know more about where their food comes from and how it is raised - a shift evident by the rapid growth of farmers markets across the country.
The debate has centered predominantly on the use of gestation crates, narrow stalls used to house breeding sows. The pork industry contends they are the best for the overall care and health of the animal. Critics, led by the Humane Society of the United States, have called the practice inhumane and said there are many other options that would still ensure a safe, cost effective and abundant food supply.
Matthew Prescott, food policy director with the HSUS, said the pork industry has spent money to defend its housing practices and the use of blunt force trauma to kill animals, among other issues, rather than "investing to find alternatives to these practices that people just don't accept."
He cited animal welfare announcements from major meat companies including Smithfield Foods, which asked its contract sow growers in January to phase out the use of gestation crates at their operations. Target, McDonald's and Campbell Soup are among the major companies that have announced during the last five years that they will eliminate gestation crates from their pork supply chains. "To refuse to embrace that is to have your head in the sand," Prescott said.
Scott VanderWal, South Dakota Farm Bureau president, said meat producers, including pork, are using production practices that have been found to be both economical and humane for the animals for decades. "When someone like the HSUS comes in and tries to change those practices, basically based on emotions, it causes an upset in the industry," he said. Whenever we compromise with them, "whatever they get is never quite good enough. They just keep coming back."
Coming Sunday
A highly infectious disease is spreading through U.S. pork herds, and the impact is affecting producers, processors and consumers.
]]></text></news-item>