<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A3A9-36EC-3953-83C8"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Clean water is good for business and the environment</title><source>The News Journal (Wilmington, Delaware)</source><author>By, Brian Winslow and Paul H. Morrill</author><text><![CDATA[The environmental community and the business/development community do not always see eye to eye. But it happens more often than one might think and the Delaware Nature Society and The Committee of 100 are joining now in support of Gov. Markell's Clean Water for Delaware's Future initiative.
Crafted by Collin O'Mara, secretary of the Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Control, the initiative is an ambitious proposal to accelerate the clean up of the state's water resources, while creating jobs and strengthening the economy. As proposed, the governor's plan will generate $800 million in projects over the next five years, financed by leveraging $30 million in annual revenues from a fee levied on real estate parcels. The average homeowner will pay about $45 a year. It has been estimated that the program will create 5,000 jobs over five years.
Delaware has some outstanding examples of programs in which government and the private sector, working together, have made progress in cleaning up and preventing water pollution. The Brownfields program assists property owners in remediating contaminated sites - legacies of Delaware's industrial past. At the same time, every $1 spent by the program produces more than $17 in economic benefits, creating jobs and returning lands to productive use.
Many farmers have long contributed to soil and water conservation and pollution prevention by participating in voluntary state and federal cost share programs. They understand that nutrient management plans can minimize inputs, while reducing water pollution from the application of too much costly fertilizer. This is good business for farmers as well as good stewardship of the land and we should encourage more of it.
In both these examples, it is important to realize that the programs succeed because they are supported by dedicated, or reasonably consistent, revenue streams, because they share costs between the public and private sectors, and because they do not regulate or assess blame - they focus on cleaning up the environment. This is the same approach proposed for the Clean Water for Delaware's Future initiative: create a dedicated source of revenue, borrow against it to increase and accelerate the clean-up projects, cost share with local governments and private industry, and focus on measurable environmental results.
There are many details yet to be worked out before the concept becomes a plan. Assurance is needed that the fees will be assessed equitably and that the project selection process will be transparent and science-based, just to name a couple. But this can be a creative, no nonsense, fiscally responsible way to fast-track the restoration of our water resources for the benefit of our state's economic and ecological health, without relying on regulations alone. Like no-fault insurance, the program does not waste time pointing fingers. Instead, we all chip in, roll up our sleeves and get to work.
Delaware's environment, economy and quality of life are inextricably intertwined. Tourism is a major contributor; imagine what would happen if we allowed our beaches to become as polluted as our ponds, lakes and waterways. Our beaches are a major attraction but imagine how tourism will grow when visitors can swim and fish throughout the state. Imagine how executives and entrepreneurs will consider those same resources when deciding where to grow their businesses.
Imagine the economic and social benefits when we make waterfront towns more resilient to rising sea levels. Imagine neighborhoods and commercial centers freed from the threat of flooding. Imagine reduced inland flooding and pollution as a result of mapping and planning for development on a watershed basis rather than relying on the ad hoc parcel-by-parcel decisions as we do now.
Imagine Delaware's unique freshwater wetlands permanently protected by conservation easements.
Reaching these goals and restoring our water resources to health is no longer a distant dream. We can start now and achieve measurable and meaningful progress before the end of this decade. We support Gov. Markell's Clean Water for Delaware Future's initiative which outlines a bold strategy and challenges us to act. We understand the issues and the science behind them. Cleaning our waters is the right thing to do and it will pay us back many times over, if we have the wisdom to follow through.
Brian Winslow is executive director of the Delaware Nature Society. Paul H. Morrill Jr. is executive director of The Committee of 100.
]]></text></news-item>