<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A42B-8A6A-7ED8-8172"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Comment: No 'hug a banker'. Labour has to take on the boardroom: The Co-op chief has gone, and polls show a great majority disgusted by the greedy and overpaid. This can be Miliband's moment</title><source>The Guardian (London) - Final Edition</source><author>Polly Toynbee</author><text><![CDATA[Long-suffering Co-op members were sent reeling again this week by revelations of their new chief executive's astronomic pay. Who let the corrupt kleptocracy of the plc sector infect a movement founded on quite different principles? No one doubted that the Co-op's labyrinthine structures needed reform, but what kind of organisation did Euan Sutherland think he'd joined? Many like me moved bank to join the ethical Co-op (although most people really do change spouse more often than bank) only to witness mismanagement under Paul Flowers, the "crystal methodist".
To pay their chief executive £3.5m including a "retention bonus" just for being there left members appalled, as they hastened to tell the Co-op party's group of 33 Labour MPs. Watching Sutherland stomp off in a huff because someone leaked his pay to the Observer's Will Hutton would be comic, if it wasn't so gobsmackingly disgraceful. After all, any plc has to publish its executives' pay. Now the Co-op's new structure looks even less accountable than an ordinary plc's, with its executive team only loosely overseen by members. Was he ashamed of the size of his bung? Shame is unknown in the CEO plutocracy, but perhaps his angry embarrassment suggests cracks in that self-certainty.
Barclays, HSBC, RBS and Lloyds are paying themselves £5.5bn in bonuses this year. How much is that? About a penny and a half off the income tax, or the cost of the BBC plus the Department of Culture, Media and Sport, and museums. Look how strenuously the bankers are avoiding the EU's new rules limiting bonuses to a stingy 100% of salary, or 200% with shareholder approval. Astonishingly, George Osborne is taking legal action against the EU to try to get this lifted. The Bank of England's plan announced yesterday - a six-year period in which bonuses can be clawed back in the case of serious wrongdoing - would be hard to effect, says the High Pay Centre. Instead, slithering round the law, the banks re-badge bonuses as "monthly allowances", while the regulator turns a blind eye: ignoring the spirit of the law is regulatory capture - and we know where that led last time.
All this comes with the usual empty threats: Antony Jenkins of Barclays warns that if these bonuses aren't paid, there'll be a "death spiral" dearth of bankers to take the top jobs. The High Pay Centre has collated the international and UK research showing no flight, no shortage of top talent, and no relation between pay and performance.
The EU will soon demand that companies reveal the pay ratio between top and bottom staff, following the US Dodd-Frank Act. Will the UK stand alone, to protect the blushes of those like Sutherland who would defy scrutiny? In 2012 FTSE 100 chief executive pay rose to £4.8m on average: the High Pay Centre expects this summer's figures to reveal a much higher increase for 2013. Why? David Sainsbury, a former Labour business minister and author of Progressive Capitalism, says bonuses based on performance and crudely related to share price often act as perverse incentives for CEOs not to invest in productive growth but to buy back shares, so inflating share price and their bonuses.
What a week for contemplating the monstrous dysfunctions of Britain's fractured system of rewards, as public sector pay is knocked back yet again. With inequality rising over 30 years, the top is pulling away even faster. Quantitative easing has washed great sums into top wallets by pumping up share and property values. The IMF reports that inequality leads to lower growth.
Sir George Bain, founder of the minimum wage, published his review for the Resolution Foundation this week: the minimum wage has lost £1,000 in real value, with 5 million people on low pay. Bain says many sectors could well afford to pay more, and he was forthright in his comments on high pay: "Quite obscene." And, the TUC asks, how do people claim their working rights, when high fees have caused a 79% fall in people turning to employment tribunals?
Bob Crow's death this week brought a curious array of homilies from enemies. Crow was 70s union man personified: with his "no one like us and we don't care" stance, he showed how union muscle keeps up the wages of workers when all around see their pay fall. Back when the unions were strong, pay was fairer, equality reached its peak, and boardrooms dared not pay themselves 185 times more than their workers. Battles were fierce when unions strove to keep pay up with soaring inflation, but look what boardrooms do to their workers' pay and their own "remuneration" when they hold all the power.
Poll after poll finds a great majority disgusted by the greedy and overpaid, so why doesn't that translate into political action by every party? The power of money outweighs democracy as the voice of "business" convinces voters that no one questioning the accretions of top wealth is safe to run the economy. If ever there were a vested interest, it's the 24 captains of industry who recently protested at Labour's top tax rise for "discouraging business investment" and "putting the recovery at risk."
The Financial Times this week ran a series of reports warning Labour: "Political risk rises up the agenda in boardrooms"; "Labour warned of appearing averse to business"; and "City alert for Labour's political reckoning". Pans for a bank bonus tax, a rise in the bank levy, the 50p tax rate, a cut in top pension relief, and a mansion tax on homes over £2m would be "siphoning off money from Britain's wealthy", possibly to the tune of £6bn. After Ed Miliband's attacks on energy firms, land-hoarding builders, insurers, payday lenders and cream-skimming pension funds, the FT's informants worry who's next in his crosshairs.
Plainly, they think Labour will be the next government. After these opening cannonades, as the election approaches expect much more shameless self-interest from high earners pretending concern for "business". Miliband will have to tough it out, hoping people will see through them. Too late now to "hug a banker", as one candidate suggests. Better by far to answer the hand-wringing, hair-tearing, teeth-gnashing public fury with out-of-control boardrooms.
A Conservative win now threatens mortal danger to British business by risking exit from the EU, so a genuinely concerned business lobby should rally behind Labour to make sure that never happens. But, weighed down by the gold in their trousers, don't expect those pigs to fly.
polly.toynbee@theguardian.com
]]></text></news-item>