<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A493-A3AA-9141-28FA"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Pakistan: Operation to continue till crime ends in Karachi: Nawaz</title><source>Right Vision News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[KARACHI, March 16 -- Prime Minister Muhammad Nawaz Sharif on Friday said the ongoing targeted operation in the port city against terrorists, extortionists and criminals would continue till their complete elimination.
Chairing a meeting here at the Governor's House to review the Karachi law and order situation, the prime minister directed the provincial authorities to transfer the location of the Anti-Terrorism Courts (ATCs) functioning in Karachi to Malir Cantonment in order to give due protection to judges, prosecutors, investigators, witnesses involved in the process of speedy disposal of court cases against notorious criminals and terrorists being caught during the ongoing targeted operation.
Sindh Governor Dr Ishratul Ebad Khan, Chief Minister Syed Qaim Ali Shah, Interior Minister Chaudhry Nisar Ali Khan, Federal Finance Minister Ishaq Dar and other officials attended the meeting.
The prime minister's fresh orders are reminiscent of his second tenure when in the late 1990s, military courts were established and started functioning in Malir Cantonment in view of the adverse law and order situation in Karachi, but later on the superior judiciary outlawed the setting up of military courts for the accused terrorists having civilian background.
Nawaz also directed the authorities concerned to lift the ban on recruitments for civil armed forces and security institutions in the country, including those responsible for maintenance of law and order in Karachi. He also directed that the services of recruitment centres of the Pakistan Army should be availed of for making recruitments for the police department.
He also directed the creation of a Quick Response Force for the Sindh Police to fight urban terrorism. He also gave directives for establishing more police stations in Lyari. The premier said the proposed Quick Response Force should be raised on the pattern of the Special Services Group (commandoes) of armed forces while the personnel of the proposed forces should be given the required modern weapons and equipment.
He also directed that an operation be launched against unscrupulous elements involved in instances of land grabbing in Karachi and the politically influential persons patronising criminals.
Nawaz said he was personally supervising the progress of the ongoing targeted operation against the criminals and terrorists in Karachi and in this regard the federal government would continue to support the Sindh government.
The meeting resolved that cases against the target killers, extortionists and criminals involved in land grabbing instances in Karachi, being caught by the LEAs, would be instituted in accordance with the anti-terrorism laws.
The meeting further resolved that the authorities concerned of the Sindh government would approach the superior judiciary for setting up new ATCs in the city while a request would also be made to speed up the proceedings of trial court cases against the accused terrorists while remaining within the ambit of relevant criminal laws.
The PM directed the authorities concerned to conduct investigations against the apprehended accused terrorists and criminals under a composite system and for the purpose a joint committee should be established for maintaining the required coordination among the institutions involved in conducting investigations against the accused criminals and terrorists.
The prime minister expressed serious concerns over the outbreak of violence and armed hostilities in the troubled area of Lyari in recent days and directed the home department to spare no effort to restore law and order in the southern locality of the city, which hitherto had been known in the country for promotion of sports.
The premier directed the officials concerned to take steps for speeding up development projects in Lyari and also for launching projects for encouraging healthy, peaceful, and recreational activities among the residents of Lyari.
The meeting resolved that the provincial government would decide and then publicise head money for catching and bringing to justice criminals and terrorists, presently at large, affiliated with the criminal gangs of Lyari. While for those patrons and notorious criminals related to criminal gangs of Lyari who had fled and got refuge in foreign countries, the Interior Ministry would do the required consultation with the Sindh government authorities concerned for approaching the Interpol for issuance of red warrants against them.
Director-General Sindh Rangers Maj. Gen. Rizwan Akhtar, reportedly, while giving his input on Lyari emphasized that political backing of criminal gangs should be stopped at once as the compulsory pre-condition for complete restoration of peace in Karachi.
He was of the view that the paramilitary force was just doing the fire-fighting job in Lyari while complete peace in the southern locality of the city could not be restored until political backing of criminal gangs operating there was ended.
Nawaz Sharif was also briefed about the state of security at the Sindh jails. The premier directed the authorities concerned to work in collaboration with the Interior Ministry for adopting a policy on composite basis for transferring notorious criminals and terrorists at present languishing in jails of Karachi to jails of other provinces.
On the issue of unregistered and illegally issued SIMs, the premier said these should be banned on an immediate basis in order to curb the resurgence of crime in the city. He also directed the provincial authorities to evolve an updated system using bio-metric technology for issuance of new SIM cards.
He directed the interior minister and secretary interior to maintain a close liaison with the Government of Sindh for the required intelligence sharing, support and sharing of resources needed for speeding up the ongoing targeted operation in Karachi
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Right Vision News. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>