<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A4DA-10CA-6413-860E"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Graham Corp. Continues to Defend PI Lawsuits</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Graham Corporation continues to defend itself against lawsuitsalleging personal injury from exposure to asbestos, according tothe Company's Form 10-Q filing with the U.S. Securities andExchange Commission for the quarterly period ended December 31,2013. The Company has been named as a defendant in certain lawsuitsalleging personal injury from exposure to asbestos allegedlycontained in products made by the Company. The Company is a co-defendant with numerous other defendants in these lawsuits andintends to vigorously defend itself against these claims. Theclaims are similar to previous asbestos suits that named theCompany as defendant, which either were dismissed when it wasshown that the Company had not supplied products to theplaintiffs' places of work or were settled for immaterial amounts. As of December 31, 2013, the Company was subject to the claims, aswell as other legal proceedings and potential claims that havearisen in the ordinary course of business. Although the outcome of the lawsuits to which the Company is aparty cannot be determined and an estimate of the reasonablypossible loss or range of loss cannot be made, management does notbelieve that the outcomes, either individually or in theaggregate, will have a material effect on the Company's results ofoperations, financial position or cash flows. Graham Corporation (Graham) designs, manufactures and sellscritical equipment for the energy industry which includes the oilrefining, petrochemical, as well as cogeneration, nuclear andalternative power markets. It design and manufacture custom-engineered ejectors, pumps, surface condensers and vacuum systemsas well as supplies and components for inside the reactor vesseland outside the containment vessel of nuclear power facilities.The Company's equipment is also used in nuclear propulsion powersystems for the defense industry and can be found in other diverseapplications such as metal refining, pulp and paper processing,water heating, refrigeration, desalination, food processing,pharmaceutical, heating, ventilating and air conditioning. TheCompany's two wholly owned subsidiaries include Graham Vacuum andHeat transfers Technology (Suzhou) Co., Ltd.
]]></text></news-item>