<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A4E9-38F6-BC5D-7042"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Stewart speaks on crime</title><source>Washingtonpost.com</source><author>Julie Zauzmer</author><text><![CDATA[Corey A. Stewart, chairman of the Prince William Board of County Supervisors, said at a news conference Tuesday that he thinks the county needs 260 more police officers to combat a spike in crime, a move that would increase the size of the force by more than 40 percent. Although there is little statistical evidence of such a spike, several high-visibility incidents have spooked county residents in recent weeks.
The county has had one homicide this year, a shooting at a Woodbridge grocery store in February. Three men entered the store, opened fire and left without taking anything, all in fewer than nine seconds. A 21-year-old mother, Glenda Coca-Romero, was killed, and her co-worker at the store was injured.
Police have asked for information on the homicide and have offered an $11,000 reward in conjunction with the FBI. According to court records, police have identified a suspect using tips from community members.
Stewart also cited a fight in February between about 20 members of rival gangs at Potomac Mills mall, which led to the arrests of three teenage boys.
The weekend before Stewart's news conference, county police responded to three sexual assaults in the Manassas area. In two of the cases, the suspects, who were known to the victims, were arrested quickly. No suspect has been identified in the third case, in which a 40-year-old woman awoke to find a stranger assaulting her in her bed.
Early this month, Stewart (R-At Large) sent an e-mail to county residents with the subject line "Spike in Crime." But Jonathan Perok, a police spokesman, said Tuesday that he was unaware of "any particular spike in crime" in recent weeks.
From 2011 to 2012, the county's violent crime rate increased by 9 percent, driven mostly by a large increase in rapes, which included many committed in previous years but reported in 2012. The rates of murder, aggravated assault and property crimes all decreased in 2012. The police department has not yet made statistics available for last year.
At Tuesday's Board of County Supervisors meeting, Stewart directed the county executive and police department to study the recent crimes to see whether they revealed any trends. He also asked that the findings be made available in time for supervisors to consider them in their budgeting process, which will end next month.
Stewart said his top priority for the fiscal 2015 budget is increasing the size of the county's public safety staff. To fund the new hires, he has supported a tax rate that would raise the average residential tax bill by about 5 percent.
"We have not hired the number of officers required to keep up with the population over the past seven years," Stewart said at Tuesday's conference. Residents in the fast-growing county, he said, "are very concerned about this perceived or real spike in crime."
He said that he would like to see the department of 610 officers grow to 870. In each of the past three years, the department has hired 10, 12 and 14 new officers, respectively, according to Stewart's staff.
"If we only hire five new police officers this year, we will be shirking our responsibility for the most important responsibility we have as a board, public safety," Stewart said.
He drew a connection to several other issues that have come up frequently as the county formulates its budget: class sizes and sports fields. "It's all interrelated. If the schools are overcrowded, if the kids can't get onto the fields, it goes without saying that they're going to find something else to do. And it might not be a very good thing."
Supervisor Peter K. Candland (R-Gainesville), who has been the board's most vocal proponent of a smaller budget, said he supported a study of crime in the county but was not convinced that there was any unusual problem.
"The experts are saying it's not a trend. We need to listen to them very carefully before we make a budget decision based on a knee-jerk reaction," he said. "We don't want to worry anyone if there's not a problem."
julie.zauzmer@washpost.com
]]></text></news-item>