<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A570-FFFA-A686-1489"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Economic Viewpoint. The alternative is gas</title><source>Financial Mail (South Africa)</source><author>Nazmeera Moola</author><text><![CDATA[Economic Viewpoint
The alternative is gas
Gas would be a real alternative to dirty coal or expensive nuclear power in providing base-load power in SA in the near future
After I complained about the banking system two weeks ago and warned last week about the dire threats the SA consumer is facing, a colleague of mine asked me to come up with something a bit more cheery this week. Unfortunately, I read a rather long-winded whinge on fracking just before I switched on my
computer to write. So this column may be a little less upbeat than I had planned.
Fracking is an emotive subject. Another colleague has said that my support for it amounted to destroying my daughter's environmental heritage for short-term gains. Opponents of fracking include John Lennon's son, his widow and the well-funded producers of the "Shell, frack off" stickers in SA.
In 2005, shale gas provided less than 2% of US energy requirements. Today that has risen to close to 30%. As a result, imported gas is falling from 15% to close to zero. In fact the US may soon become a net exporter of energy products.
Yes, there have been a number of small areas in the US that have curtailed fracking in their jurisdictions but the country as a whole is an enthusiastic supporter of fracking and has benefited from it.
The US was the root cause of the global financial crisis. However, five years later it has recovered far better than Europe. That is at least partially because it has become energy independent in the intervening years. In the US, much of the gas is used for heating. In SA it could be converted into petrol or used to build a power station.
Perhaps more importantly, SA desperately needs more base-load electricity capacity. Currently this is met by coal-fired power stations, which supply 93% of all SA's electricity. It is being supplemented by very expensive turbines that run on diesel. This is why energy imports surged in the January trade data. (20%-25% of SA's imports currently comprise oil.)
Solar and wind are quickly becoming part of SA's electricity generation landscape. As technology improves, their cost effectiveness will continue to improve and they could well capture a larger share of the generation pie. Unfortunately, I've seen no evidence that they are capable of providing base-load power in the near future.
One of the biggest proponents of green energy is Germany. However, it has simply outsourced its environmental problems by buying "dirty" power from various Eastern European countries.
SA is left choosing between dirty coal, expensive nuclear power or potentially cheap gas.
Recent estimates of the gas available in the Karoo Basin have brought down the historical mega number of 485trillion cubic feet (Tcf) of gas to something that may be as low as 10%-15% of this. This is still material. The Mossel Bay gas to liquid project was based on only 1Tcf of gas. The rough rule is 25Tcf of gas could produce 25GW of electricity (around 60% of SA's current electricity demand) for 25 years.
At the recent Discovery Leadership Summit, former World Bank chief economist Joseph Stiglitz discussed how ramping up investment in education and infrastructure were the key to promoting long-term growth and increasing the equality of opportunity. However, with limited funds the biggest bang for buck needs to be obtained. This means not squandering money on higher teacher pay without improved student outcomes and looking for the most reliable infrastructure projects - like gas-fired electricity.
Last week we saw how too much rain could hinder coal-fired power stations and damage their ability to supply power. The subsequent aggressive load shedding was a wake-up call. I'd guess that too much rain would have the same impact on solar-powered cells.
Fortunately, gas would provide a real alternative. Can we please move beyond the emotions and make a decision based on the facts?
Moola is an economist & strategist at Investec Asset Management
]]></text></news-item>