<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A5E2-F250-5D07-7E2F"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>EAB Backs EPA Right To Review Waste Permits But Grapples With Limits</title><source>Inside EPA Weekly Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EPA's Environmental Appeals Board (EAB) is backing the agency's power to require site-specific risk assessments (SSRAs) that can be used to strengthen emissions limits for hazardous waste combustion units, but during March 11 oral arguments in a precedent-setting case the board grappled with how officials crafted permit limits for the facility at issue.
Judge Leslye Fraser asked during arguments, should EPA be "forever forbidden" from strengthening standards simply because a prior risk assessment has been conducted? Fraser and the other judges suggested federal regulators should respond to new science or emerging pollutants that indicates new or more severe risks to human health or the environment.
But the judges also appeared to back industry arguments that simply because the agency followed default values in recent EPA guidance does not necessarily mean the permit limits for an Indiana facility are not overly restrictive.
The EAB is considering the case, In re: ESSROC Cement Corporation, where industry has sought EAB review of Region V's renewal of the Resource Conservation & Recovery Act (RCRA) permit for the company's hazardous waste combustor facility in Logansport, IN. ESSROC is asking the EAB to either vacate a 2012 SSRA and the strict annual mercury feed rate limit that resulted, or to remand the SSRA back to regional officials for further consideration.
The case renews industry's long-standing effort to overturn or narrow EPA's policy that allows the agency to require facilities to conduct SSRAs for determining whether current permit limits are adequate for upwards of 100 waste combustion units that burn waste to produce energy, about 14 of which burn hazardous waste.
The suit marks a new test for the risk assessment requirements EPA attached to its 2005 regulations governing hazardous waste combustion facilities. Those regulations set strict new maximum achievable control technology standards under the Clean Air Act for combustion facilities that burn waste to produce energy.
As part of the regulations, EPA authorized regulators to conduct site-specific risk assessments to determine if additional permit conditions are needed, but declined industry lobbying requests to promulgate regulations defining how the risk assessments must be conducted.
While the Cement Kiln Recycling Coalition (CKRC) and other industry groups challenged the risk assessment protocol after it was issued, a federal appellate court rejected the suit, finding the protocol was not a final agency action subject to judicial review.
In the pending EAB suit, the ESSROC Cement Company in July petitioned EAB to review Region V's renewal of its RCRA permit for its Logansport, IN, facility, arguing that EPA's requirement of a new SSRA was unlawful because the agency did not meet the criteria officials established in a 2005 rule for when additional SSRAs must be conducted for determining whether strict permit conditions are needed.
The agency first required an SSRA of the facility in 2003, but then conducted a second SSRA in 2012 while renewing the facility's RCRA permit. The Logansport facility is the first hazardous waste combustor that has completed a second SSRA, industry officials have said. An EPA Region V official has said second SSRAs are underway at two other facilities in Region V, but the official did not know whether other facilities outside the region are currently undergoing assessments.
EPA says the criteria in its 2005 rule are not exclusive and that regulators can require additional assessments if they are needed, such as the need to consider mercury depositions from the facility into a nearby lake that were not considered in the earlier assessment.
During the March 11 EAB hearing, ESSROC attorney Philip Schworer argued that Region V lacked authority to require the SSRA, and that the region imposed the strict annual mercury feed limit without completing the SSRA. While the agency ran a computer model that showed unreasonable risk from mercury deposition in nearby lakes, they should have sought additional information and more fully evaluated uncertainties surrounding the risk.
ESSROC has said that limit "goes far beyond what is necessary to protect human health and the environment, and narrows the allowable mercury feed rate to less than a tenth of what ESSROC's previous permit required."
CKRC attorney Richard Stoll said the annual mercury feed rate limit Region V imposed is a mere 5 percent of what MACT standards would normally allow. Stoll said agency risk assessors crafted the limit using an unrealistic default value in agency guidance, and that the limit "was not based on reality."
Should the case reach the U.S. Court of Appeals for the 7th Circuit, that court would likely find the limit a failure of reasoned decision making, Stoll said.
Robert Stachowiak, of EPA's Office of General Counsel, told the panel that EPA should not be bound by outdated and inadequate assessments and that the agency's decision to conduct an SSRA was reasonable and consistent with regulation. In addition, Stachowiak said changes in science are among the factors that might trigger a new SSRA. He also said a company could challenge specific factors underlying an EPA decision to conduct an SSRA at a particular facility, but not the agency's authority to conduct SSRA's. -- Dave Reynolds
]]></text></news-item>