<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A5FB-A225-EFE2-35CD"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Headline</title><source>The Daily Gleaner (New Brunswick)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[CBC ombudsman questions speaking fees
TORONTO - The CBC's ombudsman says anchor Peter Mansbridge did nothing wrong by accepting fees for speaking engagements but questions whether the public broadcaster's staff should accept such fees in future.
Esther Enkin posted a response this week to a complaint from a member of the public against CBC commentator Rex Murphy for accepting fees for speaking to an oil industry gathering.
Mansbridge wasn't part of the complaint, but Enkin noted her office has received concerns from viewers about a paid speech he gave to Canadian petroleum producers.
She writes viewers expressed concerns about possible bias and questioned if CBC employees should get extra income through speaking engagements.
Enkin writes Mansbridge's speech focused on what it means to be a Canadian and noted most of the money he gets from speaking goes to charity and scholarships.
However, Enkin says accepting fees for speaking leads to a perception of a conflict of interest, and CBC management should consider whether its appropriate for its employees to accept such payments.
In Murphy's case, Enkin noted he is a commentator and works for the CBC on a freelance basis and is not a spokesman for anyone.
"Throughout his career, he has been outspoken and frequently iconoclastic in his views on a range of issues, the fact that he is a supporter of resource development is not the issue here," she writes.
Traces of plant radiation on West Coast soon
Scientists have crowdsourced a network of volunteers taking water samples at beaches along the U.S. West Coast in hopes of capturing a detailed look at low levels of radiation drifting across the ocean since the 2011 tsunami that devastated a nuclear power plant in Japan.
With the risk to public health extremely low, the effort is more about perfecting computer models that will better predict chemical and radiation spills in the future than bracing for a threat, researchers say.
Federal agencies are not sampling at the beach. The state of Oregon is sampling, but looking for higher radiation levels closer to federal health standards, said state health physicist Daryl Leon. Washington stopped looking after early testing turned up nothing, said Washington Department of Health spokesman Donn Moyer.
The March 2011 tsunami off Japan flooded the Fukushima Dai-Ichi nuclear plant, causing radiation-contaminated water to spill into the Pacific. Airborne radiation was detected in milk and rainwater in the U.S. soon afterward. But things move much more slowly in the ocean.
"We know there's contaminated water coming out of there, even today," said Ken Buesseler, a senior scientist at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution in Massachusetts.
Alberta Premier Redford facing more criticism
EDMONTON - Alberta Premier Alison Redford is facing more criticism from within her party ahead of a weekend meeting of Tory executives.
The president of a Progressive Conservative riding in northeast Edmonton says Redford has to resign or the party will lose the next election.
Steve Robson says Redford is an arrogant leader who doesn't listen to her caucus and has no regard for the Tory establishment.
Redford has been under fire for taking a $45,000 trip to attend Nelson Mandela's memorial in South Africa.
She resisted calls to pay the money back for weeks, then cut a cheque Wednesday for the expenses.
Robson says the payback was too little too late and she's already done too much damage to the party.
Sources: The Canadian Press, The Associated Press
]]></text></news-item>