<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A77E-648B-0D23-378B"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Claims processing to start from Mar 24</title><source>The Financial Express (Bangladesh)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Bangladesh, March 15 -- Processing of compensation claims for the Rana Plaza victims will officially start from March 24 from an office in Savar, according to a statement issued by Clean Clothes Campaign (CCC).
Welcoming the launch of the Rana Plaza Arrangement claims processing Friday, IndustriAll, UNI Global Union and CCC said they are now calling on brands to contribute to the Rana Plaza Donors Trust Fund and ensure that families of those killed and injured in the tragedy finally get the compensation.
Potential beneficiaries will be contacted directly, and invited to come to the office to file their claims. A pre-claim legal team will work with each claimant to ensure that they fully understand what claims can be made for and how they will be decided, the statement added.
"A hotline in Savar will be launched at the same time to respond to any question or enquiry about the claims processing. It is expected that first payments will be provided by the first anniversary of the disaster." Payments made under the arrangement will be funded through the Rana Plaza Donors Trust Fund, which is collecting contribution from the brands, sourcing from Bangladesh in general and Rana Plaza in particular.
The fund was launched at the beginning of February, with an initial target of $10 million, believed to be the amount needed to pay first installments to all the potential claimants. A total of $40 million is needed to cover full payments to over 3,000 workers and families of those killed.
Since then the fund has garnered widespread support. The Ethical Trading Initiative, the Bangladesh Accord Foundation and the Business Social Compliance Initiative have all issued appeals to their members to contribute to the fund.
Seven brands - Bon Marche, El Corte Ingles, Inditex, Mango, Mascot, Loblaw and Premier Clothing - have all publicly pledged initial donation.
However, there is a long way to go before the $40 million needed to make payments to all workers is collected, the statement further said.
"Primark remains notably absent from the list of donors, despite their involvement in the development of the Arrangement and their previous commitment to provide full and fair compensation to the Rana Plaza workers through a single, unified scheme. They are the only signatory company of the Arrangement yet to make a contribution."
IndustriALL, UNI Global Union and the CCC are urging Primark and other brands to fulfil their commitments and immediately pledge funds to the Rana Plaza Donors Trust Fund, so that the disaster victims and families receive compensation by April 24.
IndustriALL Global Union general secretary Jyrki Raina said: "As we are happy to see the Arrangement roll out on March 24, it is now time for Primark to make its response to the industrial homicide at Rana Plaza."
UNI Global Union general secretary Philip Jennings said: "Execution of this Arrangement is good news for the families of Rana Plaza victims, who have waited too long for compensation. A transparent and coordinated approach is far stronger than a handful of separate voluntary corporate schemes. Companies need to commit and pay up."
CCC's Ineke Zeldenrust added: "With the launch of the claims processing we hope that the families, suffering as a result of the disaster, will finally get what they deserve before the first anniversary."
Roy Ramesh Chandra, general secretary of IndustriAll Bangladesh Council said, "Many meetings, seminars and workshops have been done. We can't delay any more, as the victims' sufferings knew no bound. We want the Rana Plaza victims are compensated before April 24."
Published by HT Syndication with permission from The Financial Express. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>