<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A7B2-DB51-2C5A-74F4"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Other voices, other views</title><source>The Eagle-Tribune (Massachusetts)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Excerpts from the editorials of other New England newspaper.
In his recent book "Duty: Memoirs of a Secretary at War," Robert Gates, former secretary of defense under both Presidents George W. Bush and Barack Obama, makes pertinent observations on our defense policy.
Oddly enough, Gates' primary problem is not with our allies or the defense bureaucracy but with our legislators, both House and Senate members.
Gates was constantly belabored with requests on the part of their constituents - not lowly individuals who have one vote, but business owners represented by lobbyists whose primary interest is not American defense but how they can profit from doing business with the Department of Defense.
Gates' efforts to enhance efficiency and lower costs were hampered by the demands of these legislators, whose power was exercised in committee meetings and budget decisions.
The defense secretary's problem with political opportunism in Washington was constant.
Given that background, Gates makes a number of interesting observations about the political climate in Washington.
In one instance Gates refers to a conversation between Obama and Hillary Clinton. Gates recalls that "in strongly supporting a surge in Afghanistan, Hillary told the president that her opposition to the surge in Iraq had been political because she was facing him in the Iowa primary. She went on the say, 'The Iraq surge worked.' The president conceded vaguely that opposition to the Iraq surge had been political. To hear the two of them making these admissions, and in front of me, was as surprising as it way dismaying."
Gates’ observations on Russia and Vladimir Putin also are intriguing. He felt that Putin's predecessor as president, Dmitry Medvedev, was realistic about Russia's internal problems and its relationship with the West, and was more willing to closely align with the West.
Gates' feelings toward Putin are worth quoting, especially given the recent happenings in Ukraine: "Putin's lust for power led him to shoulder Medvedev aside and reclaim the presidency. I believe Putin is a man of Russia's past, haunted by lost Empire, lost glory, and lost power. ...As long as he remains in office, I believe Russia's internal problems will not be addressed. Russia's neighbors will continue to be subject to bullying from Moscow, and while attentions of threats of the Cold War period will not return, opportunities for Russian cooperation with the United States and Europe will be limited."
Our country needs more people like Robert Gates serving in government
- The Journal Inquirer of Manchester, Conn.
In "The Meat Racket," Christopher Leonard writes about the state of America's meat industry, most notably, poultry production. The book isn't necessarily about animal welfare or the health consequences of eating animal products from factory farms. It's more about how big business has come to monopolize the production of the meat we find in our supermarkets.
"Leonard is a harsh critic of the system as it now operates, not so much because of what it might do to our health but because of what he believes it does to farmers," wrote Bethany McLean, in a review of Leonard's book for the Washington Post.
Leonard focuses on the Tyson family, which turned Tyson Foods into a megalith of modern farming by buying up competitors and expanding vertically in an effort to control every step of production, noted McLean.
Leonard claims Tyson's tactics have wreaked havoc on middle America, transforming it from "an archipelago of clean, prosperous towns ... with busy town squares, bustling department stores and a thriving middle class" into a meth-ridden wasteland where "drugs and crime seep in ... where improvisational chemists left behind toxic waste."
While Tyson owns virtually all aspects of its food production operation, the one aspect it does not is the actual chicken raising, Leonard told Kerry Trueman for civileats.com.
- The Brattleboro, Vt., Reformer
"Once Tyson realized that the actual raising of the chickens was the one area of production that wasn't profitable, they offloaded the risks onto the farmers."
While Tyson pioneered the system, said Leonard, Cargill, JBS, Conagra, and Smithfield are using Tyson's playbook.
"It's at the expense of the American consumer, the environment, the livestock. (Tyson) pioneered the treatment of animals as widgets, like, how can we squeeze these animals into ever tighter quarters, how can we breed bigger chickens faster, even though their health suffers as a consequence."
A failed attempt by the Obama administration to rein in the abuses of the system "also illustrates the remarkable level of influence that giant meat companies have in Washington, where they quietly shape public policy to their advantage through groups like the American Meat Institute and the National Chicken Council," wrote Leonard in his book. "Their well-orchestrated effort to beat back Obama's reform efforts has arguably left them more powerful than they were when Obama entered office. And like many of the changes in America's meat industry, it all played out under the public's radar."
Prior to the deregulation craze that swept across America during the Reagan administration, the four biggest beef companies controlled only 44 percent of the market and the four chicken producers controlled only 32 percent of the market.
While we can rail all we want at the industry, the root of all of this is the American consumers' willful blindness to the abuses of the industry, just as long as meat is plentiful and cheap.
"They're not paying attention," said Leonard. "There's too much of a mentality that if I walk into a store and the meat is there at an acceptable price, I don't really care how it's produced."
The result is not only the increase in the chances of a widespread outbreak of food poisoning, but also the "mediocritization" of meat.
- The Brattleboro, Vt., Reformer
There's a fascinating - and historic - dynamic playing out right now in Washington, where U.S. Sen. Dianne Feinstein, D-Calif., has accused the CIA of snooping on Senate staffers who were investigating the spy agency's interrogation techniques during the Bush era.
What's stunning is not just that Feinstein, who chairs the Senate Intelligence Committee, made the allegations public during a remarkable speech on the floor of the Senate. What's even more alarming is that Feinstein has long been an ardent supporter of the nation's intelligence community.
At root, Feinstein alleges that the CIA provided documents about interrogation techniques to Senate investigators on a secure computer, and then secretly removed some of the documents it had turned over from the computers being used by Senate staffers.
According to an Associated Press timeline of the matter, "the committee complains to the CIA, which first denies that anything was taken from the system and later contends that removal of the documents was ordered by the White House. Officials at the White House deny in such order. Feinstein complains to the White House and gets an apology from the CIA and assurances that it won't happen again."
But, according to Feinstein, it did happen again, though it was fascinating to hear CIA Director John Brennan deny Feinstein's allegations.
"We wouldn't do that," Brennan told NBC News.
For those who think phraseology has meaning, that's a telling choice of words; not "we didn't," but "we wouldn't."
In fact, our first thought - even before we heard from Brennan - was that it sounds exactly like the kind of thing the CIA would do.
We think Sen. Lindsey Graham, R-S.C., is right. "Heads should roll, people should go to jail, if it's true," said Graham, who called it "Nixon stuff."
And scary stuff, at least for anyone who cares about principles like democracy and privacy and separation of powers.
- The Nashua, N.H., Telegraph
]]></text></news-item>