<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A807-7563-5901-DFDD"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>AFPTV Agenda</title><source>Agence France Presse -- English</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[We plan to file the following videos on Monday. Please check the daily advisories for any additions and amendments:
-- TOP WORLD NEWS --
+ UKRAINE
SIMFEROPOL, UKRAINE: Crimea's regional government is expected to make a formal application to join the Russian Federation after an overwhelming number of voters chose to join Russia in a referendum. TBC
SIMFEROPOL/SEVASTOPOL/DONETSK, UKRAINE: Rolling news coverage of the follow-up of a referendum in which voters in the southern region of Crimea voted overwhelmingly to join Russia. RAW. TBA
BRUSSELS: EU foreign ministers meet to discuss possible sanctions response to the Crimean referendum. RAW. 1300 GMT (arrivals) TBA (presser)
MOSCOW: Russia reacts to Crimea referendum. RAW. TBA
BRUSSELS: NATO Secretary-General Anders Fogh-Rasmussen meets Ukrainian interim Foreign Minister Andriy Deshchytsya. RAW. TBC
UNITED NATIONS: Monitoring reax to Crimea referendum. TBC
WASHINGTON: Monitoring reax to Crimea referendum. TBC
WASHINGTON: US Vice President Joe Biden travels to Lithuania and Poland to discuss the Ukraine crisis. TBC
CHICAGO: Following calls from Chicago's large Ukrainian community for further US support against Russian activity in Crimea, city councillors are proposing several measures such as a ban on flights en route to Russia stopping in Chicago. PKG. 2200 GMT
+ MALAYSIA AIRLINES SEARCH
KUALA LUMPUR: Monitoring the search for a Malaysia Airlines jet that vanished with 239 people on board. RAW. TBC
BEIJING: The families of the Chinese passengers wait for news in a Beijing hotel. RAW. TBA
MANILA: A security analyst comments on the MH370 mystery. RAW 0600 GMT
+ PARIS CAR BAN
PARIS: The French capital launches alternate driving days for the first time since 1997 to tackle dangerous air pollution levels. RAW. 1130 GMT
-- OTHER WORLD NEWS --
+ EUROPE
BERLIN: Germany and Italy hold talks, with new Prime Minister Matteo Renzi bringing six members of his cabinet to Berlin. RAW. TBC
BELGRADE: News coverage of results of Serbia's snap election, political parties are expected to start talks on forming the government. RAW. TBC
GENEVA: A landmark commission of inquiry on North Korea presents its hard-hitting report to the UN Human Rights Council. RAW. 1600 GMT
PARIS: Altice, Vivendi's preferred buyer for its ailing SFR mobile phone unit, gives a press conference. RAW. 1600 GMT
STOCKHOLM: The Stockholm International Peace Research Institute publishes report on international arms transfers in 2013. On merit. TBC
PARIS: Appeal in "Hamidovic gang", France's biggest ever child pickpocketing ring. RAW. 1800 GMT
+ MIDDLE EAST & NORTH AFRICA
YABRUD, SYRIA: Monitoring after Syrian troops capture the town of Yabrud, a key opposition stronghold near the border with Lebanon. RAW. TBC
+ AFRICA
PRETORIA: News coverage of day 11 of the murder trial of Paralympian star Oscar Pistorius, who is accused of killing his girlfriend Reeva Steenkamp. RAW. 1100 GMT / 1600 GMT
+ ASIA-PACIFIC
JAPAN: Vietnamese President Truong Tan Sang visits Japan. RAW. TBC
+ NORTH AMERICA
NEW YORK: New York turns green for the St. Patrick's Day Parade. RAW. TBA
WASHINGTON: Palestinian leader Mahmoud Abbas is received at the White House. RAW. TBA
-- SPORT --
MADRID: Pre-match training and pressers ahead of second leg last 16 Champions League match between Real Madrid and Schalke. RAW. 2100 GMT
AFPTV is launching a new service on Europe's main football leagues covering key games of the week in England, Germany, Spain, France and Italy. This service will be available upon request as a special subscription.
MUNICH, GERMANY: Post-match reax after Bayern Munich take on Leverkusen in the Bundesliga. RAW. TBA
-- FEATURES --
PARIS: Dozens of pre-historic stone chimes will be dusted off to star in a unique concert. PKG. 0500 GMT
Contact:
London desk: +44 207 776 2768
Hong Kong desk: +852 2829 6216
Nicosia desk: +357 22 391 453
Washington desk: +1 202 414 0550
Montevideo desk: +598 2 900 5095 ext 257
For contact via email: afptv-en@afp.com
aftpv
]]></text></news-item>