<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A85B-4FA3-95AC-7A11"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Eye on Clallam: Commissioners, Olympic National Park eye cross-deputizing officers at Tuesday meeting</title><source>Peninsula Daily News (Port Angeles, Washington)</source><author>Peninsula Daily News</author><text><![CDATA[The three Clallam County commissioners will consider a memorandum of understanding with the National Park Service to cross-deputize officers Tuesday.
The meeting will begin at 10 a.m. in the commissioners' boardroom (160) at the Clallam County Courthouse, 223 E. Fourth St., Port Angeles.
If the agreement is approved, certain sheriff's deputies would be deputized to work within Olympic National Park, and certain park rangers would be deputized to work within the Clallam County jurisdiction.
Other agenda items for the commissioners' meeting include:
"   A notice of an April 1 hearing on a proposed addition to the Clallam County code for solid waste flow control.
"   An agreement with K&H Printers for the April election.
"   An agreement with First Step Family Support Center to provide the Parents as Teachers program.
"   An agreement with the Port Angeles School District to provide Positive Behavioral Intervention Supports training for staff.
"   An agreement with the city of Port Angeles to sublet a portion of a storage facility.
"   A bid opening for the public printing of Clallam County legal publications
"   A bid opening 2014 hot-mix-asphalt requirements.
"   Resolutions appointing members to the Sheriff's Citizens Advisory Committee, Developmental Disabilities Advisory Committee and Peninsula Regional Support Network.
Commissioners will meet in the same boardroom at 9 a.m. Monday for their weekly work session to discuss several action items.
Port Angeles City Council
Port Angeles City Council members will consider an amendment adding up to $75,000 to a $463,522 construction management contract with Lacy-based Exeltech Consulting for the Lauridsen Boulevard bridge replacement project when they meet Tuesday.
The meeting will begin at 6 p.m. in council chambers at City Hall, 321 E. Fifth St.
An executive session is set for 4:45 p.m. in the Jack Pittis Conference Room to discuss potential litigation.
The $4.5 million Lauridsen bridge replacement work by Kent-based Scarsella Bros. Inc. has taken longer to complete than expected. It is expected to be completed in mid-April, according to the city, pushed backed from an original predicted finish date of February.
Other agenda items for the 6 p.m. meeting include:
" An ordinance making a collection of 2014 city budget changes.
" An ordinance codifying the city's electrical plan review process.
" An amendment to the city's sales agreement with the Bonneville Power Administration.
" Approving 2014 city health and human services allocations in the amount of $46,350 and signing an agreement with the United Way of Clallam County to administer the funds.
Clallam Transit
The Clallam Transit board will consider an interlocal agreement for the summer youth pass program when it meets in Sequim on Monday.
The meeting will begin at 1 p.m. at the Sequim Transit Center, 190 W. Cedar St.
Agenda items include a resolution revising an equal employment opportunity/affirmative action program, staff reports and customary business.
Clallam PUD
Clallam County Public Utility District commissioners will consider awarding a bid for a 40-foot serviceman truck Monday.
The meeting will begin at 1:30 p.m. in the boardroom of the Port Angeles main office, 2431 E. U.S. Highway 101.
Other agenda items include staff reports, customary business and an executive session for a performance evaluation of a public employee.
Board of Health
The Clallam County Board of Health will conduct a public hearing on 2014 public health fee revisions Tuesday.
The meeting will begin at 1:30 p.m. in Room 160 of the Clallam County Courthouse, 223 E. Fourth St., Port Angeles.
Other agenda items include an update on the Clallam County syringe services program, a report on a community health improvement plan for substance abuse prevention, a legislative report and a wrapup of the influenza season.
Olympic Medical Center
Olympic Medical Center commissioners will hear a presentation on digital 3-D mammography Wednesday.
The meeting will begin at 6 p.m. in Linkletter Hall in the lower conference area of the hospital at 939 E. Caroline St., Port Angeles.
The board also will take public comment on the proposed Sequim School District facility bond, consider a real estate purchase and hear an administrator's report on operations and advocacy.
Planning Commission
The Clallam County Planning Commission will hold a work session on the implementation of the state recreational marijuana law Wednesday.
The meeting will begin at 6:30 p.m. in the commissioners' meeting room (160) of the Clallam County Courthouse.
]]></text></news-item>