<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A872-9776-3C9A-8EFE"><date>2014-03-15</date><title></title><source>Norwich Bulletin (Connecticut)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[SALEM
Salem man killed in one-car crash
A 21-year-old Salem man was killed early Friday morning when the car he was driving veered off Route 354 and struck a large tree, police said.
Police said Phillip Gaudette III, 21, of 300 Buckley Road was traveling east on Route 354 just east of Brainard Road at 7:14 a.m. when the 2008 Toyota Tacoma he was driving went off the left side of the road.
He was alone in the car and was pronounced dead at the scene, police said.
The case remains under investigation.
- Elizabeth Regan
LEBANON
Police: CO poisoning was cause of deaths
State police said Friday the deaths of a man and woman earlier this week in Lebanon were the result of carbon monoxide poisoning from mechanical problems with the vehicle.
State Police spokeswoman Master Sgt. Donna Tadiello said there is no criminal aspect to the investigation. The case remains open as police await conclusive testing results from the office of the Chief Medical Examiner, though the office has already ruled the deaths accidental.
Casey Senechal, 26, of Lebanon , and Brittany Holland, 25, of Hebron, suffered acute carbon monoxide intoxication, the medical examiner's office said.
The bodies were found in a car with its engine running Monday morning on Smith Road in Lebanon.
- Elizabeth Regan
HEBRON
Teacher critical after hit by car
RHAM Middle School math teacher Dawn Mallory-Bushor, 65, fractured her skull when she was struck by a vehicle Friday morning outside the school, police said.
Mallory-Bushor also suffered a brain bleed when she was hit by a vehicle driven by Elizabeth Everett, 50, of Hebron, who was backing up, police said.
Mallory-Bushor was flown by Life Star helicopter to Hartford Hospital.
No one else was injured and no charges have been filed.
- Elizabeth Regan
KILLINGLY
School board OKs $40.6M budget
The Killingly Board of Education on Wednesday approved a $40.6 million budget for 2014-15.
The spending plan represents a 5.77 percent, or $2.2 million, increase from this year. The budget includes funding for full-day kindergarten and includes money for a new elementary school assistant principal. Special education funding also gets a $1.1 million boost in the budget, which will be scrutinized by the Town Council on April 5.
- John Penney
PLAINFIELD
Dodgeball fundraiser today
The Plainfield Rotary Interact Club will host its 3rd Annual Dodgeball Tournament today, featuring teams from local and state police, Day Kimball Hospital and others.
The double-elimination event, which begins at 6 p.m. at Plainfield High School, serves as a fundraiser for scholarships and community needs.
- John Penney
Teams this year will include members of the Plainfield Police Department, state police troopers from Troop D, Plainfield Congregational Church and Atwood Hose fire department, as well as employees from local businesses.
DANIELSON
Groton man charged in fatal accident
A 37-year-old Groton man was arrested Wednesday and charged with negligent homicide with a motor vehicle in connection with an accident that killed a Thompson man last year.
Michael Gagne, 97 Butternut Road, also was charged by state police with unsafe movement. On March 26, 2013, police said Gagne, who was driving a Dunbar Armored vehicle, struck 88-year-old Ellsworth Sheldon in the parking lot of the Putnam Stop & Shop supermarket.
Sheldon died of his injuries on March 30.
Gagne was arrested at 9 p.m. on Wednesday and released on a promise to appear. He is due in Danielson Superior Court on March 26.
- John Penney
]]></text></news-item>