<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A897-149B-28A7-BF9D"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>CBSI: Campaign to boycott supporters of Israel</title><source>Al-Akhbar English</source><author>Paul Gadalla</author><text><![CDATA[Excerpts from a talk at the Israel Apartheid Week, Toronto.
The Campaign to Boycott Supporters of Israel (CBSI) is "the first and most important popular campaign organized outside occupied Palestine...even prior to the call of Palestinian civil society in 2005." These are the words of Omar Barghouti, the co-founder of the global Boycott Divest and Sanctions.
Much less known globally than BDS, CBSI is an earlier sister campaign that a group of Lebanese launched in the spring of 2002 in the wake of the Israeli massacres in Jenin. One of the first of its kind in the Arab world, CBSI is a popular-based campaign relying on a rigorous process of research and documentation to make the case, in Lebanon and beyond, for boycott.
Our boycott is not aimed at certain nationalities, countries, or religions; for that would reproduce the racist and discriminatory ideology of the Zionist project. We had chosen to boycott "supporters" of Israel, not Israel per se because initially we had thought that, given that Israeli companies are barred in Lebanon, there would not be any company to boycott. But in the course of our activism, we found to our dismay, that Israeli companies have actually penetrated Lebanese and Arab markets in roundabout ways.
From the outset, we were clear about our goals and principles: That our boycott is not aimed at certain nationalities, countries, or religions; for that would reproduce the racist and discriminatory ideology of the Zionist project. Nor did we conceive of boycott as an end in itself, but rather as a means of pressuring these companies to end their complicity in Zionist violations of human rights.
With the launch of BDS in 2005, we witnessed the birth of a new and much-welcome ally. We endorse the vision of BDS in its fight against an apartheid system in Historic Palestine including its three pillars: Ending the occupation of Arab lands, eliminating Apartheid in 1948 Palestine, and upholding the Right of Return for any Palestinian to his or her homeland. Nevertheless, our movement is partly informed by the long history of crimes committed by Israel within Lebanon and the Arab world and by the counter-history of resistance.
At the level of the Arab world, it is important to point out the long history of boycott that stretches all the way back to the early part of the 20th century. Egyptian leader Saad Zaghlul invoked boycott to build an independent national economy in the face of British domination, and the call for boycott was popularized through the writings of poet Bayram al-Tunisi. In Palestine, commercial boycotts were endorsed on a massive scale as far back as the 1930s against Zionist expansion and complicit British policy. The Arab League imposed a boycott of Israel and the companies supporting it in the late 1940s, but the official path of "settling" the conflict that culminated in the Oslo process undermined official boycott efforts; companies that were initially banned regained a foothold in the Lebanese and Arab markets.
Another important dimension of boycott efforts in the Arab world and other parts of the world is the long history of armed resistance. Very few people may highlight the role played by armed struggle in the defeat of Apartheid, a role that Nelson Mandela rightly refused to denounce till the very end of his life. In Lebanon, had it not been for the resistance, which started back in the 1960s as secular and leftist in nature, there is little doubt that the Israeli Apartheid regime would have extended all the way into Lebanon's southern river, the Litani. A people's journey to triumph over its oppressor has more than one path. While armed struggle is often the fruit of a dedicated, courageous and young few, civil resistance, including boycott, has a wider audience and allows all segments of society to participate.
Another important dimension of boycott efforts in the Arab world and other parts of the world is the long history of armed resistance.Our criteria for enlisting a company on our boycott list were also shaped by the political context of our country and the lived reality of our people. Our boycott campaign is without doubt a form of solidarity with the Palestinian people, but it is equally a form of resistance of the Lebanese people themselves for all the suffering that continues to be inflicted on them by the Zionist state. Israel has killed, maimed, and dispossessed tens of thousands of Lebanese people in the course of over 60 years of repeated invasions, full scale bombing campaigns of residential areas, medical facilities, power stations, and basic infrastructure.
***
So what are the criteria for boycotting pro-Israeli companies?
- Building factories, as well as research and development centers, in ethnically cleansed Palestinian areas. In 2002, Coca Cola opened a new factory in the settlement of Kiryat Ghatt that was founded on the ruins of two ethnically cleansed villages, Falluja and Iraq al-Manshiyyah. The factory provided a material base for the sustenance of the settlement and thus consolidated the colonial presence of the Zionist state.
- Buying stocks in Israeli companies. This enhances the standing of these companies in the international capital market. Examples include General Electric that has invested hundreds of millions of dollars in Israeli companies, and Coca Cola that bought in 2005 the majority of shares in Tifour, an Israeli brewery.
- Funding Zionist "charity" organizations that ultimately help "resettle" Jews only, while depriving Palestinians of their inalienable right of return.
- Contributing to the Israeli war effort. General Electric manufactures plane engines and body parts of the phantom and F16 fighter jets. As for Caterpillar, its D-9 model has broken the bones of Palestinians under the ruins of their own homes while demolishing the latter, and led to the murder of activist Rachel Corrie in 2002 while she was trying to prevent a home demolition.
- Sponsoring cultural, artistic, sports, and educational events.
- Publicly supporting the Israeli army or government. Microsoft put up a huge banner in Tel Aviv in the wake of the Jenin massacre in 2002 expressing "from the bottom of its heart" its gratitude for the Israeli army.
- Extolling Zionism. Hasbro issued a rubber doll of an Israeli soldier brandishing grenades and an M-16 rifle, providing children with a supposed role model in the face of Arab "terrorism."
***
In light of these principles, what are some of the challenges we continue to face in Lebanon?
- The persistence of a culture of antipathy to boycott as a powerful weapon against Israel.
- Political parties and organizations that are explicitly opposed to the Zionist project have unfortunately failed to endorse the cause of boycott.
- The collapse of a near-consensus among the Lebanese people over the priority of the struggle against Israel, especially after the assassination of Rafik al-Hariri and the Syrian uprising.
- The campaign's difficulty in expanding its membership base, improving its research skills, and reaching out to other campaigns abroad.
- The negative role played by some intellectuals that are "specialized" in chronic self-criticism and spread an atmosphere of defeatism, thus systematically doubting the ability to achieve any meaningful victory against Israel through boycott.
***
The road to boycott is a long and winding path, as is the case with every road to freedom.Despite these challenges, we have scored several victories in the past. These include:
- Barring two Israeli companies, Syneron and Lumenis, from doing any further business in the country.
- Barring a movie, The Shock, in Lebanon and other Arab countries. Its Lebanese director had shot much of it in Tel Aviv in collaboration with an Israeli technical team and actors - in direct violation of Lebanese law. We also dissuaded an Israeli apologist French singer, Lara Fabian, from performing in Lebanon after we sent her letters urging her to rescind her public support of Israel. We were accused of cultural terrorism, even though we simply exercised our right to call on people to freely boycott her; our critics seemed to care much less for the cultural terrorism exercised by the Israeli government against Palestinian artists, scholars, and intellectuals.
- The successful cancellation of a normalizing festival sponsored by the Israeli embassy in Austria after we alerted all the Arab participants to the sponsor's identity.
- The near-setting up of the Arab world's major online research and documentation website to serve as an information portal for boycotting Israel and its supporters.
The backlash we have faced has not been solely motivated by political interests. Following our campaign's calling on the Lebanese to boycott a concert by music band Placebo, the event organizer had the audacity to sue the campaign (and me personally as well as the BDS movement itself and Aidoun Center for Palestinian Refugees) for compensation because we allegedly caused a drop in sales. The case led to an unprecedented support for our group and hundreds of prominent activists and politicians signed a petition declaring the lawsuit one against all of them.
***
The road to boycott is a long and winding path, as is the case with every road to freedom. For decades, Lebanon has emerged as a vanguard for armed struggle against Zionist oppression. Through our persistence and resilience, and in partnership with other boycott campaigns around the world, we hope that Lebanon will also provide a model of civil resistance in Lebanon and the Arab world - so that the inevitable end of apartheid takes place sooner rather than later.
Samah Idriss is Al-Adab Magazine's editor, and co-founder of the Campaign to Boycott Supporters of Israel (CBSI). He has published two books on literary criticism, and fourteen books for children and young adults.
Samah Idriss
]]></text></news-item>