<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A8E9-E69A-3536-BADB"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>5 anti-union VW workers in Tenn. file 'collusion' suit</title><source>The Detroit News (Michigan)</source><author>By, Bryce G. Hoffman</author><text><![CDATA[The Detroit News
Five workers at Volkswagen AG's plant in Chattanooga have filed a federal lawsuit in an attempt to block "further collusion" between the United Auto Workers and the German automaker.
The workers, who are represented by the National Right to Work Foundation, called it a pre-emptive move aimed at preventing cooperation between the company and the union in the event that the National Labor Relations Board sets aside last month's poll at the plant and allows another vote.
Hourly employees at the VW factory in Tennessee rejected the UAW, despite tacit support for union representation by their employer.
"UAW union officials and Volkswagen management have colluded to deprive these workers of a fair vote from the start," said Mark Mix, president of the National Right to Work Foundation in a statement after the suit was filed Thursday morning. "Enough is enough, which is why these workers are seeking to prevent further VW assistance to the UAW's organizing efforts."
UAW President Bob King said the lawsuit was another example of what he has characterized as "outside interference" in the union's effort to organize the plant.
"The lawsuit filed by the National Right to Work Legal Foundation is baseless. At the time it negotiated its election agreement with Volkswagen Group of America, the UAW had already established for the company that it was the majority representative of hourly Volkswagen employees, on the lawful basis of authorization cards signed by a majority of such employees," King said in a statement Thursday.
"Moreover, even if the UAW had not demonstrated this status, the UAW's Election Agreement with Volkswagen Group of America would still be lawful, just like many other neutrality agreements the UAW and other unions have negotiated with employers throughout the United States."
The lawsuit is based on a case the foundation successfully brought against a Florida casino company that it also accused of working with union officials during a card-check campaign.
In that case, the court ruled that such cooperation could constitute a violation of Labor Management Relations Act, which prohibits employers from giving "any money or other thing of value" to union officials.
The union appealed that ruling, but that appeal was thrown out last year by the U.S. Supreme Court.
Bryce.Hoffman@detroitnews.com
(313) 222-2443
Twitter.com/brycehoffman
Five workers at Volkswagen AG's plant in Chattanooga have filed a federal lawsuit in an attempt to block "further collusion" between the United Auto Workers and the German automaker.
]]></text></news-item>