<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A962-0A98-FCE5-FB11"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>General Environmental Conservation decreases 1.2% on low volume</title><source>News Bites Asian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[General Environmental Conservation Public Co., Ltd. (SET:GENCO), Thailand's 2nd largest professional services company by market capitalisation, decreased 1.0 satang (or 1.2%) to close at 84.0 satang. Compared with the SET100 Index which fell 3.1 points (or 0.2%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -1.0%. The volume was 0.03 times the average trading of 7.3 million shares.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on General Environmental Conservation, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051781940314408
Bearish Signals- The present value of THB1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in General Environmental Conservation is THB712, for a capital loss of THB288.
Overbought/Bearish/Resistance Signals- The Money Flow Index [MFI] is 98.6 suggesting an overbought 14-day trend, being above 80. The Money Ratio of 72.8 suggests positive money flow was 72.8 times negative money flow.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price/Earnings of 27.6 [14.8]. - Price/Sales of 2.5 [1.7]. - Return on Equity 2.6% [5.7%].- Return on Assets 2.4% [3.6%].- Return on Capital Employed 3.3% [9.1%].Other Bearish Signals:- Net profit margin has averaged 6.1% in the last 3 years. This is lower than the sector average of 9% and suggests a low margin of safety.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity is less than stellar at 2.6%. This is computed as net profit margin of 8.9% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 0.27 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 1.1.
Bullish SignalsFundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price to Book of 0.7 [1.1]. We estimate General Environmental Conservation stock is trading at a current year Price to Book of 0.7 and a forward year Price to Book of 0.7.Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 1.2 is comfortably below 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The P/E of 27.6 multiplied by the P/NTA of 0.7 is 19.9. Being less than the Benjamin Graham benchmark of 22.5 the stock appears undervalued. - Interest cover defined by EBIT/I is 22.4 times. This indicates it is less leveraged. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.7. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- EBITDA margin is positive and has seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 200,900 shares worth THB168,756 (US$5,215) traded. Beta: the Beta of General Environmental Conservation stock is 1.6. A Beta greater than 1 suggests this is a high risk, high return stock with volatility greater than that of the market. - General Environmental Conservation is at a discount of 37.3% to its 12-month high of THB1.34 on 14 Mar, 2013. It is also at a premium of 23.5% to the 12-month low of 68.0 satang on 28 Aug, 2013.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:December 25: The General Environmental Conservation: Opportunity for Shareholders to Propose AGM Agenda and Director Nomination[News Story]The General Environmental Conservation Public Company Limited (GENCO) would like to inform that, according to the good corporate governance regarding the equitable treatment of shareholders, the Company would like to invite the shareholders to propose agenda of the Annual General Shareholders Meeting 2014 and name of qualified candidates to be nominated for selection as the Company's Board of Directors in compliance with the criteria and procedure as announced on the Company's website at www.genco.co.th from now until February 15, 2014.
September 20: General Environmental Conservation appoints Independent DirectorGeneral Environmental Conservation has appointed Trairat Rungaratna as Independent Director. The effective date is September 20, 2013.
September 20: General Environmental Conservation appoints DirectorGeneral Environmental Conservation has appointed Itthirit Wipoosiri as a Director. The effective date is September 20, 2013.
September 02: Resignation of the Director of GENCOWe would like to inform you that Dr.Somyot Sangsuwan, has submitted his resignation from position of the Board of Directors, the member of the Executive Committee and the authorized signatory director of the General Environmental Conservation Public Company Limited. The effective date is August 30, 2013.
August 09: General Environmental Conservation: Resignation of Independent Director and Member of Audit CommitteeAccordingly to the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) filed a criminal complaint with the Department of Special Investigation (DSI) against the former directors and executives of Agro Industrial Machinery Public Company Limited ("AMAC"), which changed name to Max Metal Corporation Public Company Limited ("MAX"), and team included 8 persons for falsifying the company's documents, accounts and financial statements and/or misappropriation.One of the person accused namely Mr. Suthisak Lohsawat, the former director and Chief Executive Officer of AMAC is relevant as an Independent Director, Audit Committee and Nomination/Remuneration Committee of the General Environmental Conservation Public Company Limited ("GENCO") has resigned from all posted of GENCO effective August 8, 2013.
May 09: General Environmental Conservation: Decreasing of the Subsidiary Company's Registered and Paid-up Capital[News Story]The General Environmental Conservation Public Company Limited would like to inform that Asia Patana Land Company Limited, a subsidiary company, has registered the capital decrease from the registered and paid-up capital of Baht 200 million to 170 million by decreasing the ordinary share of 3 million shares with par value of Baht 10 at the Department of Business Development, Ministry of Commerce on March 29, 2013.
May 08: General Environmental Conservation: Disclosure of Minute of the AGM 2013 on Company's Website[News Story]With reference to the Annual General Shareholders Meeting 2013 of the General Environmental Conservation Public Company Limited held on April 26, 2013 at 15.00 hours at the Magic 2 room, 2nd Floor, Miracle Grand Convention Hotel, located at 99 Vibhavadi Rangsit Road, Laksi, Don Muang, Bangkok 10210, in previous notification.For additional channel regarding information disclosure to the shareholders, Company has disclosed the Minute of the Annual General Shareholders Meeting 2013 on Company's website at http//:www.genco.co.th since May 8, 2013.
ISIN: TH0636010Z01
TH:GENCO; TB:GENCO
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>