<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A999-C77E-9ED3-10CF"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Were wars in Afghanistan and Iraq worth it?</title><source>Deseret Morning News (Salt Lake City)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[By James Jay Carafano
McClatchy-Tribune News Service
WASHINGTON - Former secretary of state, national security adviser and Nobel Peace Prize winner Henry Kissinger is, by all measures, a foreign policy heavyweight. At a recent black-tie dinner, he stood - stoop-shouldered and peering imperiously over his signature thick, black-frame glasses - and remarked: "Unilateral withdrawal is not victory."
Whom could he have been talking about?
Kissinger knows a thing or two about the pain of walking away. After negotiating the Paris Peace Treaty to end the Vietnam War, he saw President Nixon resign in disgrace over Watergate, then watched Congress pull the plug on all support for South Vietnam.
America's 25-year effort was squandered. With Soviet-backing, the North Vietnamese rolled over the South. Vietnam, Laos and Cambodia were washed in a bloodbath of oppression and genocide. Emboldened, the Soviet Union bankrolled new revolutions in South America and Africa and fostered a wave of transnational Islamist terrorism in the Middle East.
Though many Vietnam War protesters, including now Secretary of State John Kerry, trumpet America's withdrawal as a triumph, there is no reason to be proud of how we left. While we can still debate the wisdom of going to war there, there is no doubt that our total abandonment of our allies left a bloody and shameful legacy.
Dr. Kissinger's comments weren't meant to recall ancient history. He was lamenting history repeating itself. The prospects are now high that Afghanistan will fail, needlessly.
The Obama administration's Afghan strategy is a virtual carbon copy of its withdrawal from Iraq. It assumes that once the imminent threat of the collapse of the regime has passed, it's OK to head for the exit. But absence of imminent failure is a poor criterion for declaring victory - no better than George W. Bush's unfortunate high-five under the "Mission Accomplished" banner after the initial invasion of Iraq.
That's not to say that the United States should plan major, unending commitments to a country after a fight. But once the levels of violence have come down, some further commitment is usually necessary to help peace and stability become "the new normal" and let good governance takes root.
Iraq is a case study in how to get it wrong. It is fatuous to argue that the White House could not have gotten permission to retain a residual force there. It simply didn't want to. It is also clear that the U.S. pull-out left a vacuum that was eagerly filled by a resurgent al-Qaida. Today, Iraq suffers much higher levels of violence than when Obama took office.
The prospects for Afghanistan are even grimmer. Obama's Afghan "surge" was not nearly as massive and effective as the Bush surge in Iraq. The Taliban still have sanctuaries in Pakistan; the Haqqani Network is as robust as ever and al-Qaida is waiting in the wings. The narco-trade that fuels the insurgency remains robust as well. These are daunting challenges for the Afghan people.
While Obama talks of finishing the job in Afghanistan, many in the administration would be delighted to go with the "zero" option - no U.S. troops, period. But it's not clear that a small multinational presence will be enough to hold the hard won gains there.
The U.S. went to war in Iraq and Afghanistan to eradicate the terrorist forces that had killed thousands of Americans and threatened to kill many, many more. Job 1 was not to bring freedom and justice to those lands, but America always prefers to leave a path to liberty and prosperity in the wake of its war.
Sadly in the case of Afghanistan, Obama seems once again poised to pluck defeat from the jaws of victory, as he did in Iraq. Future administrations will reap the blowback and have to deal with it - probably at greater cost. "Unilateral withdrawal is not victory."
James Jay Carafano is vice president for foreign and defense policy studies at The Heritage Foundation. Readers may write to the author in care of The Heritage Foundation, 214 Massachusetts Avenue NE, Washington, D.C. 20002
By John B. Quigley
McClatchy-Tribune News Service
COLUMBUS, Ohio - Our withdrawals from Iraq, and now imminently from Afghanistan, are not the reason that we find ourselves dealing with governments in both these countries that are not doing as we think they should.
We are learning the hard lesson that while our military can remove an existing government, we cannot dictate what will replace it. It is a lesson with huge immediate implications, because in recent days we are hearing new rumblings about a possible military intervention in Syria.
In Iraq, President George W. Bush apparently gave little thought to what might replace the government of then leader Saddam Hussein.
In 1991, when his father, President George H.W. Bush attacked Iraq over its occupation of Kuwait, he was urged by some in Congress to expand the operation to attack the capital city, Baghdad, and remove Saddam Hussein from power.
Wisely, he knew that such action would open a can of worms. Under Saddam Hussein, power rested in the hands of the Sunni community, a minority within Iraq. The majority Sh'ia community was resentful over its treatment at the hands of Saddam Hussein. Removal of Saddam Hussein would upset the existing order.
What was not difficult to see in Iraq was the likelihood that any new government in Iraq would be dominated by the majority Sh'ia community, and that it might redress its grievances in a way that would leave the country in turmoil.
So when we see current Prime Minister Nouri al-Maliki tilting toward the Sh'ia, that is the result of the dynamic we set up with our invasion of Iraq in 2003.
The Sunni in Iraq are reacting now with violence. Whether we are there with troops or not, that dynamic is playing itself out. Iraq experiences inter-communal violence on a daily basis.
Nor was it difficult to guess that a Sh'ia-led government in Iraq would be on good terms with the government of Iran, with which we are perennially at odds. So by invading Iraq, we were bolstering support in the region for the government of Iran.
In Afghanistan, we removed a government headed by the Taliban. Afghanistan, as was known at the time, houses a variety of ethnic constituencies. It has no history of a country-wide political order.
Now the warlords who ruled small fiefdoms in Afghanistan are making a comeback. One of them may wind up as the next president in elections to be held soon. We are having trouble convincing Hamid Karzai, the current president, to let our troops remain in some numbers past the end of 2014. We want to keep Afghan courts from having jurisdiction over any offenses that may be committed in the future by U.S. personnel there. Karzai rejects this demand.
In both instances, our initiation of military operations - Afghanistan in 2001, Iraq in 2003 - could have been avoided. In Afghanistan, our demand on the Taliban - that it turn over Osama bin Laden and his associates - was not pursued. The Taliban was beginning to respond to our demand, but instead we invaded.
In Iraq, there was even less reason to send our troops. We invaded because, we said, Iraq was preparing mass-destruction weapons to use to attack us. That reason was quickly shown to be implausible.
So in both Afghanistan and Iraq, we took military action that could have been avoided but which had predictable consequences that were negative both for the target country and for ourselves.
And this does not include the thousands killed, maimed, or otherwise wounded among our own forces and among the populations of those countries.
Now we have to live with the political reality in both Iraq and in Afghanistan. We are leaving both countries in shambles. If we don't like the governments we see, we have no one to blame but ourselves.
John B. Quigley is a professor of law at Ohio State University. Readers may write him at Moritz College Law, 55 West 12th Street, Columbus, Ohio 43210.
]]></text></news-item>