<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="A9FA-3E22-9627-00C8"><date>2014-03-14</date><title></title><source>Muskegon Chronicle (Michigan)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[By Dave Alexander
dalexan1@mlive.com
Citizens and members of the Muskegon Lake Watershed Partnership wanted specific declarations on the conditions being found on the former Sappi paper mill site on Muskegon Lake.
Officials from the Michigan Department of Environmental Quality gave a lengthy presentation Thursday on the former Sappi site, but it is "too early in the process" for state environmental regulators to make definitive statements, they said.
"We have not seen any red flags as of yet, and we've worked on many sites with many contaminates," Bob Wagner said, concerning the 120-acre former paper mill property now under the final stages of demolition. Wagner is the DEQ chief of the remediation and redevelopment division, who spoke at a public meeting of the watershed partnership at the Grand Valley State University energy center in Muskegon.
"The worst conditions were years ago when the plant was operating," Wagner said of the 109 years of paper-making operations on the waterfront site. "Mother Nature has a way of taking care of those issues over time. The longer it has been an issue, the lesser the problem."
Wagner said his agency has years of experience with paper-making companies and hundreds of other polluted "brownfield" sites, many of them successfully cleaned and redeveloped throughout Michigan. The most problematic time was when the Sappi plant was operating -- discharging pollutants into the air or, prior to the county wastewater system, directly into Muskegon Lake, he said.
"I don't expect any surprises out there," he said of the former Sappi site with nearly a mile of Muskegon Lake shoreline. He said the site eventually will be available for all kinds of redevelopment options, including residential. "And I don't expect to find anything that we haven't already dealt with."
DEQ officials said they just recently have been provided a batch of environmental data from owner Melching Inc.'s environmental consultant, and state regulators are just beginning to evaluate it. In the future, DEQ officials will return to Muskegon and report in more specifics, Wagner said.
Wagner and DEQ Senior Policy Adviser Anne Couture recounted the deed restrictions placed on the property when, in 2011, Melching purchased it from Sappi -- the South African global paper company that closed the plant in 2009. The deed restrictions limited environmental investigation and redevelopment to industrial uses without Sappi approval.
Couture described the intensive behind-the-scenes discussions and negotiations underway to remove the deed restrictions as an unidentified investment group attempts to purchase the property from Melching for mixed-use waterfront redevelopment. Sappi, Melching, the potential new owners, the DEQ, the Michigan Attorney General's Office and the city of Muskegon all are working on an agreement that would allow a sale to be completed, cleanup to proceed and safe redevelopment to take place, Couture said.
In the meantime, demolition nears its end stages and environmental investigation and work continues on the project, despite the deed restrictions, Couture told the watershed partnership group.
"The attorney for property owner Doug Melching has done some creative work with Sappi," Couture said. "They have done a lot of work out there by getting Sappi's permission. They have chipped away at those deed restrictions."
Couture concluded: "I feel very confident that we are going to move the ball forward on this work. Every single day, we are working on getting this property transacted, sold and moving on with redevelopment."
The 200-foot-tall section of the former Sappi Fine Paper, in Muskegon, still stands on the morning of Oct. 27, 2013, just prior to being brought down by explosives. (MLive.com files)
]]></text></news-item>