<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AA0A-F123-8250-FFB0"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>LETTERS</title><source>Newsday (New York)</source><author>John D. Cameron Jr.; Ilene Corina; Suzanne Mattei; Roy Willis; Ed Konecnik; Peter Schmidt</author><text><![CDATA[Debate on new water law appropriate
It is unfortunate that columnist Michael Dobie elected to disparage critics of the proposed Long Island Water Pollution Control Act legislation ("Critics make waves over water bill," March 9, 2014).
At a recent Long Island Regional Planning Council meeting, speakers expressed opposition to the proposed bill. Neither the environmental advocates, who drafted the bill, nor the sponsors - State Assemb. Robert Sweeney (D-Lindenhurst) and State Sen. Kenneth LaValle (R-Port Jefferson) - availed themselves of the technical expertise of the scientists and engineers in the professional environmental community. That could explain why the bill is not grounded in sound scientific principles.
One example of myriad deficiencies in the bill is projecting nitrogen standards for drinking water into a marine environment.
Other vocal opponents of the bill included town and village elected officials who are concerned that the legislation would permit an unelected panel to trump local zoning.
Dobie argued that the bill was being revised, and therefore it was counterproductive to hold a public forum. Before our meeting, I was told by Senate majority co-leader Dean Skelos' office that because the bill had been introduced into committee, it was appropriate to receive comments.
With 70 percent of Suffolk County unsewered, and pollution abounding in our ground and surface waters, what Long Island should be focused on instead of more regulation is developing strategies to fund sewers, upgrade treatment plants, clean up brownfields and restrict chemical use.
John D. Cameron Jr.
Editor's note: The writer is the chairman of the Long Island Regional Planning Council.
Rockville Centre
Protocol breach is unacceptable
Your story about South Nassau Communities Hospital raises important questions ["Hospital is flooded with calls," News, March 13]. The hospital urged roughly 4,200 patients to be tested for hepatitis B and C and HIV, because some might have received insulin injections from pens possibly used on more than one patient.
How could such a thing have happened? This is such a basic safety imperative, there should be no room for error.
Ilene Corina
Suzanne Mattei
Editor's note: The writers are, respectively, president of Pulse of New York and executive director of New Yorkers for Patient & Family Empowerment, two advocacy groups.
Levittown
MTA is responsible for its own math errors
When the Metropolitan Transportation Authority contracts to build a tunnel for $4.3 billion and miscalculates by more than $4 billion, no one even blinks an eye ["East Side access," News, March 7]!
However, when the MTA makes a mistake in someone's retirement of about $27,000, it's major news .
Considering that the MTA can afford a $4-billion goof, I really do not understand why the agency can't absorb a meager $27,000 mistake. The MTA should own up to its fallibility and keep quiet about how incompetent it really is.
If you can't correctly calculate retirement costs, how can you build a multibillion-dollar tunnel?
Roy Willis
Massapequa
School reform troubling
I worked for 38 years as an educator in the New York City school system. I support charter schools and oppose Mayor Bill de Blasio's decision to reject some Success Academy co-locations ["Schools chief flips in charter school flap," News, March 8].
Say you're passionate about pizza and you live in a neighborhood where only one establishment is permitted to produce and sell pizza. Imagine those pizzas are unappetizing, but you are compelled to purchase them by law and forbidden to make your own.
Substitute education for pizzas in this scenario, and this is the true nature of compulsory public education. In a free market, anyone who produces an unsavory pizza would soon be out of business. However, in education, competition and freedom of choice, which nurture creativity and excellence, are conspicuously missing.
Many who rail against the power, control and influence of Wall Street, corporations, banks, and the "1 percenters" readily accept government's absolute control of education. The education bureaucracy's monopoly mandates a one-size-fits-all curriculum, awards accreditation to approved colleges and professors to teach that curriculum, requires everyone to read approved text books, administers approved tests, certifies and awards tenure to approved teachers and supervisors, and provides pay raises based on date of hire rather than merit.
After reviewing results of recent achievement tests, some have suggested the education monopoly should not only be charged with violating our liberties but with intellectual genocide.
What we desperately need is separation of schools and state.
Ed Konecnik
Flushing
As someone who works with teachers in the metropolitan area, and as a parent of two boys in the fifth grade, I take exception to your strong support of New York State's rush to impose teacher evaluations linked to student performance on the new Common Core standards tests ["Sensible tweaks to Common Core," Editorial, March 12].
Before implementing the standards, the state Education Department was slow to offer guidelines to school districts, forcing an impossibly short timeline for developing materials and training teachers. With little or no input from teachers, many districts opted to solve the problem by purchasing packaged curricula with scripted lesson plans.
These slick corporate products include some poorly written test questions and shoddily constructed work sheets. Many of the teachers saddled with these scripts are capable of crafting much more effective lessons on their own.
If students do poorly on the statewide tests, should negative evaluations fall on the teachers, the New York State Education Department or the script? It seems that the rollout of the Common Core is more about imposing central oversight, privatizing curriculum development and testing, and preparing to attach blame for failure, than about improving the quality of our children's education.
Peter Schmidt
Editor's note: The writer is the associate director of Globe NY Metro, a science education program at Queens College.
Queens
]]></text></news-item>