<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AA36-978E-EC00-F365"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Siamgas And Petrochemicals keeps rising: up 10.0% in 3 days</title><source>News Bites Asian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Siamgas And Petrochemicals Public Company Limited (SET:SGP), Thailand's 12th largest energy & utilities company by market capitalisation, extended its gains Monday, rising an additional THB1.20 (or 6.1%) to close at THB20.90. The shares have soared THB1.90 (or 10.0%) over the past three trading days. Compared with the SET100 Index which rose 24.3 points (or 1.2%) in the three days, this represented a relative price increase of 8.8%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Siamgas And Petrochemicals, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051781770314345
Bullish SignalsUptrend- The stock rose 6.1%, for a 3-day rise of 10.0%, on high volatility today and expanding price range.- The stock hit a year-high 13th time in one month and 21st time in three months.- The stock continues its significant uptrend.- Rises to Falls: in the past month the number of rises outnumbered falls 12:6 or 2:1.- The Moving Average Convergence Divergence (MACD) indicator of 12-day Exponential Moving Average (EMA) of 18.93 minus the 26-day EMA of 17.94 is positive 1.0 suggesting a bullish signal. Both EMA prices are rising, another bullish signal.- The present value of THB1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Siamgas And Petrochemicals is THB1,585, including a capital gain of THB537 and dividend reinvested of THB48.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Sales of 0.3 [0.4]. We estimate Siamgas And Petrochemicals stock is trading at a current year Price/Sales of 0.2 and a forward year Price/Sales of 0.2. - Return on Equity 17.9% [12.5%].Other Bullish Signals:- Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.6. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity of 17.9% is better than sector average of 12.5%. This is computed as net profit margin of 2.4% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 2.2 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 3.3.- Earnings per share growth rate is negative but improving in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

Bearish SignalsOverbought/Bearish/Resistance Signals- At THB20.90 the price has risen above the upper Bollinger band resistance of THB20.40, indicating a downside risk for it to fall back within the band. - The Relative Strength Index (RSI) of 91.8 has penetrated the overbought line of 70, suggesting the price gain of 20.8% in the last 14 days is unusually high. - The Money Flow Index [MFI] is 92.2 suggesting an overbought 14-day trend, being above 80. The Money Ratio of 11.9 suggests positive money flow was 11.9 times negative money flow.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price to Book of 2.7 [1.7]. - Dividend yield of 1.7% [5.9%].- Price to EBITDA of 5.7 [3.9].Other Bearish Signals:- Total Liabilities/ EBITDA of 6.1 is more than or equal to 5, this compares unfavourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - Net profit margin has averaged 2.2% in the last 3 years. This suggests the company is less profitable with a low margin of safety.
NoteVolume: there were 8,667,603 shares worth THB181.2 million (US$5.6 million) traded. This has been propped up by high volume of 4.3 times average.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Parity:- Price/Earnings of 12 [11.0]. We estimate Siamgas And Petrochemicals stock is trading at a current year P/E of 8.6 and a forward year P/E of 6.2. - Return on Assets 5.4% [5.3%].- Return on Capital Employed 13.8% [12.8%].
FINANCIALSAnnual Report for the year ended December 31, 2013 (year-on-year comparisons with previous corresponding period)-Favourable Changes: total revenue up 38.8% to THB66.3b ($US2.0b); net profit up 94.6% to THB1.6b ($US48.8m); EPS up 95.5% to THB1.74 (US5.3c); interest cover up 32.2% to 4.8; EBIT Margin up 9.1% to 3.6%; a 5-year track record of positive earnings; 5-years average annualized earnings growth rate of 6.0%; total liabilities to EBITDA down 29.9% to 6.1. While this compares unfavourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of less than 5, the trend is favourable; total liabilities to total assets down 6.8% to 0.7; Net tangible assets per share up 25.0% to THB7.8 (US23.8c); EBIT to total assets up 43.1% to 8.0%; total revenue to total assets up 31.7% to 2.2.Unfavourable Changes: current ratio down 6.8% to 1.0; Retained earnings to total assets down 5.2% to 0.6%.Major Common Size Ratios: total non-current assets to total assets up from 55.1% to 59.3%; fixed assets to total assets up from 45.8% to 48.8%; total current assets to total assets down from 44.9% to 40.7%; current inventory to total assets down from 29.0% to 17.7%; current debtors to total assets up from 10.2% to 15.9%; cost of goods sold to sales down from 94.8% to 94.6%; EBITDA to Sales up from 5.0% to 5.1%; EBIT to Sales up from 3.3% to 3.6%; profit before tax to sales up from 2.4% to 2.8%; profit after tax to sales up from 1.7% to 2.4%.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 21: Siamgas And Petrochemicals announces dividendSiamgas And Petrochemicals today announced a cash dividend of 50.0 satang per share. The ex dividend date is March 06, 2014 and the record date is March 10, 2014 and it is payable on May 15, 2014.
February 21: Siamgas And Petrochemicals announces AGMSiamgas And Petrochemicals has announced its Annual General Meeting will take place on February 25, 2014.
February 03: Siamgas And Petrochemicals: Change in the Shareholding Structure[News Story]www.set.or.th/dat/mds_news/news/0979NWS030220141248230967E.pdfSource: Thailand Stock Exchange
November 08: Siamgas And Petrochemicals: Explanation of the change in operating result for Q3/2013 over 20%[News Story]www.set.or.th/dat/news/201311/13061089.pdfSource: Thailand Stock Exchange
August 12: Siamgas And Petrochemicals announces dividendSiamgas And Petrochemicals today announced a cash dividend of 10.0 satang per share. The ex dividend date is August 27, 2013 and the record date is August 29, 2013 and it is payable on September 05, 2013.
August 09: Siamgas And Petrochemicals: Explanation of the change in operating result for q2/2013 over 20%[News Story]www.set.or.th/dat/mds_news/news/0979NWS090820131958040121E.pdfSource: Thailand Stock Exchange
August 09: Siamgas And Petrochemicals: Increase of capital in subsidiary[News Story]Reference : Letter No. SGP/SET-056 dated on 12 May 2011 entitled "Setup new subsidiary" Reference is made to the above notification, Siamgas and Petrochemicals Public Company Limited. ("the Company") would like to inform that the Board of Director Meeting No.3/2013 held on 9 August 2013 approved increase the capital in SG GAS SDN.
ISIN: TH0979010004
TH:SGP; TB:SGP
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>