<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AA39-02E8-BE1F-4A7C"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>LAN Associates hired to address fuel leak issues</title><source>Suburban Trends (Morris, North Jersey)</source><author>David M. Zimmer</author><text><![CDATA[The school board has agreed to spend a significant sum in an effort to get a handle on a substantial concern.
Last month, West Milford's Board of Education authorized a $230,480 contract for contamination investigation services at its fuel-product polluted transportation depot. The agreement with its go-to engineering firm LAN Associates will continue the examination into the site's environmental issues and use that data to develop a remediation plan to submit to the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection (NJDEP), according to district Business Administrator Barbara Francisco.
"This is only an investigation," she said. "A plan would have to be developed, approved by the NJDEP to proceed with any cleanup."
According to NJDEP records, the site requires remediation for the contamination of groundwater and soil to protect the area's water and wetlands. Skyline Environmental Group excavated estimated roughly 2,000 tons of contaminated soil remained in need of disposal after hauling off 334 tons from 51 Highlander Drive under a partial cleanup in 2007.
Once this investigative phase has determined the current extent of the fuel contamination, Francisco said the district will have a better idea of both what and how long it will take to clean up the site to strict state standards.
First discovered following the 1998 removal of two massive underground storage tanks, the contamination includes naphthalene, known to destroy red blood cells, and perchloroethene, an established carcinogen. It also includes a variety of volatile organic compounds that degrade the central nervous system. All are found in petroleum derivatives like the gasoline and diesel fuels that were stored at the depot in 6,000- and 10,000-gallon underground drums, respectively. They also destroy the quality of groundwater, according to the NJDEP, which is requiring an isolation and removal program to nullify the threat to nearby wells.
The $230,000 contract approved last month included labor, subcontractor allowance, reimbursable expenses, and contingency fees. The board also authorized LAN to submit a timeframe extension form for the remedial investigation. Regulations signed by Governor Christie in January permit an extension until May 7, 2016 for the completion of qualifying investigations as long as certain conditions are met. That form is due by March 21, according to the NJDEP website.
Without an extension, the Site Remediation Reform Act requires the NJDEP to assume direct oversight over remediation of certain contaminated sites if the investigation is not complete by May 7. LAN's director of environmental services, Gerrit Visscher, has been serving as the district's state-mandated licensed site remediation professional for the bus depot cleanup.
]]></text></news-item>