<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AA3C-AEB1-BA57-02F4"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Russian banker once again contests Estonian minister's extradition order</title><source>Baltic News Service / - BNS</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Russian banker once again contests Estonian minister's extradition order
TALLINN, Mar 15, BNS - Alexander Dmitriyev, former head of the Omsk branch of the Russian AK BARS Bank wanted by the Russian authorities for large-scale embezzlement, has once again contested the decision of Estonia's justice minister to extradite him.
It is already the third extradition order issued by the minister that Dmitriyev has contested, and the previous two were quashed by the circuit court and the administrative court, respectively. The administrative court found last November that the minister's second extradition order did not treat claims of political persecution of the complainant with sufficient thoroughness due to which it had to be revoked. The justice minister decided not to contest the ruling of the administrative court but to draft an entirely new order instead. Dmitriyev's new contestation will be discussed at the Tallinn administrative court next week.
The minister first made the decision to surrender Dmitriyev to the Russian authorities at the end of last summer but the ex-banker contested it in the administrative court. The lower-level court found the extradition order to be competent, but the second-tier circuit court judged that the minister had not paid enough attention to the question whether the accusations could be politically motivated. The circuit court also pointed out that according to the Russian authorities the statute of limitations concerning one episode incriminated to Dmitriyev had lapsed in the meanwhile and the minister would have to refer to it in his order.
The minister issued a new extradition order in October but Dmitriyev contested this as well in the administrative court and achieved its revocation.
Estonia's central criminal police apprehended Dmitriyev, whom the Russian authorities have declared internationally wanted and charged with defrauding the Omsk bank of more than 10 million euros, in January 2013.
The ex-banker and former member of the council of the Siberian city of Omsk is alleged to have persuaded more than 100 people between 2007 and 2009 to sign mortgage contracts with the bank worth around 8.6 million euros then pocketing the money. He allegedly paid the phony borrowers 25-250 euros for it.
Dmitriyev also allegedly contracted around two million euros' worth of loans with the help of his associates in the Omsk council who nominally ran the businesses controlled by him. The borrowed funds were transferred to the businesses and used for personal purposes "including the acquisition of valuable property -- cars, speedboats and aircraft," prosecutors in Russia have said.
According to information published earlier, Dmitriyev gave statements as witness in the case beginning from mid-2010. He stopped seeing investigators in December 2010, then went into hiding and was declared a fugitive.
Tallinn newsroom, +372 610 8832, sise@bns.ee
Baltic News Service
]]></text></news-item>