<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AAF2-6DD4-B22F-385C"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>The undercover sting that brought a monster to justice</title><source>Canberra Times (Australia)</source><author>The Canberra Times</author><text><![CDATA[The undercover sting that brought a monster to justice STEPHANIE WOOD looks inside the police operation that led to the conviction of Daniel Morcombe's killer.
JUSTICE: Daniel's parents, Bruce and Denise Morcombe, and brother Bradley, far left, leave the court after Brett Peter Cowan, left, was found guilty.
B rett Peter Cowan told one of his new friends he thought Daniel Morcombe was "a f---in' cute little [thing]" when he spotted the 13-year-old waiting for a bus. He told the friend he'd had his "man fun" four other times in the abandoned demountable building where he took Daniel.
He told him he knew if Daniel got away he "was f---ed". He told him he used a shovel to crush up a fragment of Daniel's skull.
Cowan's new friend, a man called "Paul Fitzsimmons", told Cowan he was his mate. He told Cowan, a serial paedophile, his new gang would look after him, that honesty was what bonded the gang together. "That's what it is, mate, it's about brotherhood."
Paul told him they'd all done "s--- we shouldn't of" and the gang could make his s--- go away.
But Paul wasn't his friend. He was a police officer, covert operative 452 in a complex and protracted undercover sting that united Queensland and West Australian police forces in one of the most remarkable investigations in Australian policing history, one that led ultimately to Cowan confessing to the murder of Daniel on December 7, 2003.
In the absence of forensic evidence, the confession was the foundation of the prosecution case which on Thursday resulted in the jury returning a guilty verdict against Cowan.
But it was not just the policing that was remarkable. The fact so much information has been laid out on the public record about the controversial method of operation, known as the "Mr Big" technique or the "Canadian" technique, is unprecedented.
"It is a very expensive exercise and quite intense, requiring an enormous amount of resources and controls," said a former Australian police undercover operative. "This technique has been used in Australia, especially in regards to the infiltration of organised crime syndicates and [outlaw motorcycle gangs]."
It's the stuff of lurid crime novels: undercover police groom a suspect to convince them they have what it takes to be part of a successful crime gang with rich rewards. But, the suspect is told, the gang is only as strong as its weakest link and honesty is all. Tell us your dirt and we'll make it go away.
Cowan had inconceivable dirt to divulge, but he didn't do it in a hurry.
In March 2011, he appeared at an inquest into Daniel's disappearance.
"He gives everyone in the courtroom the shivers," Bruce Morcombe said outside the court, where details of Cowan's history of vile sex offences against small boys was revealed.
On April 1, 2011, when Cowan was excused and caught a flight back to Perth where he was living, police hit the go button.
Initially, Cowan was suspicious. "It was just like it was a bit sus, I'd just walked out of, um, the Coroner's Court and s--- ... this bloke sits beside me on the plane and starts talkin' and that," Cowan later told one of his new gangster friends.
But by flight's end he had offered to help his companion - an undercover officer going by the name "Joseph (Joe) Emery" who said he was moving to Perth - to buy a car and had given him his phone number.
Police script writers were ready to roll out gripping follow-up episodes.
The next day, Cowan helped his new friend buy a Ford Fairmont at Mr McGoo Motors. They caught up for some sightseeing around the Fremantle foreshore. "At this stage I was still just building rapport and trying to build a relationship with Mr Cowan," Joe told the court.
His efforts were helped along by Cowan's own down-and-out situation.
He'd lost his job, was skint. In early May, when Joe introduced Cowan to another mate, Paul, and they suggested they could help him get some "easy work, easy money", Cowan was putty in their hands.
Cowan's "gang" friends and an extensive and sleazy cast of undercover operatives initiated him through more than 20 escalating criminal scenarios. He helped to get boxes of illegal crayfish to Eddie the Chinese restaurateur, picking up about $200 for the job. He picked up some more cash by helping to collect an outstanding $2000 from a brothel madam called Cassie. On June 13, he flew to Melbourne with Paul to pick up $40,000 worth of "blood diamonds". They met "Arnold", the gang's "Mr Big".
Paul had become his primary point of contact and hammered how vital "loyalty, honesty and respect" were to the gang. Paul told him the gang had the connections to whitewash his past. "There's s--- that's been fixed, there's nothin' they can't fix."
He also told Cowan there was a "big job" coming up and he stood to earn $100,000 from it.
In early August, police stepped up the operation. Cowan was told a corrupt copper who was part of the gang had learnt there was a subpoena for him to give more evidence about Daniel's disappearance. He told Paul he had nothing to do with the case. Paul kept on-message.
"We're the best blokes in the world at cleanin' up s--- you know."
On August 9 it was time for another meeting with Arnold who told him he was doing some "good stuff" for the gang. But, he said, the information about Cowan's past needed to be sorted out. "I don't care what you've done," Arnold said. "You know, I've dealt with a lot, lot of real bad c----."
A grainy video recorded the moment. "No, yeah, I did it," he told Arnold. "It is my deepest, darkest secret ... I'm not proud of it."
That Cowan felt comfortable enough to reveal his crime is a testimony to the officers' skills - and to his own twisted standards of normalcy.
]]></text></news-item>