<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AB11-5C8F-BEED-C350"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>'Illegal' quarries irk Sanvordem locals</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[QUEPEM: Residents of Ambeaudok, Sanvordem, have complained to the mines department that 'illegal' extraction of laterite stones in quarries has been carried out by unknown persons near their residential houses due to which they are the victims of dust and noise pollution as the activity commences early morning and ends late at night.
Ashirwad Dessai and 17 other residents complained to the mines department, deputy collector, Quepem, mamlatdar of Sanguem and village panchayat Sanvordem about the 'illegal' operations. The complainants alleged that around 15 machines are engaged in the operation due to which there is noise pollution affecting their normal lives and disturbing their childrens studies.
Speaking to TOI, Dessai said that not a single department carried out any site inspection even after several complaints made by the locals. He wonders how the department of mines or the local panchayat allowed this extraction for years, neglecting the problem faced by the residents since around eight ancestral houses are near the quarry.
Priti Dessai, who's house is less than 50 meters from the stone quarry, said that all the dust from the quarry enters their house and it is very difficult to maintain cleanliness. "Our children are falling sick because of dust pollution. As the operations start around 5am and stop late at night, their sleep gets disturbed they cannot concentrate on their studies," she said.
When contacted, Sanvordem sarpanch Shashikant Bhandhari said that after conducting the site inspection, he will take appropriate action as per panchayat rules and will not allow any illegality in his panchayat area. " I will check whether the earlier panchayat had given any permission to the quarry operator. Taking into consideration the problem faced by the residents, the panchayat will issue a notice," the sarpanch stated.
Assistant director of mines Parag Nagarsekar informed that he will soon carry out a inspection and will take appropriate action against the mine operator.
Deputy collector of Quepem Ajit Panchwadkar was quick when this was brought to his notice and conducted a site inspection to verify the facts as alleged by the residents. He informed TOI that he will study the case and take appropriate action into the matter.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>