<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="ABFA-BE00-21C1-3F93"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Former DHS-OIG supervisor found guilty on some falsification counts</title><source>The Brownsville Herald (Texas)</source><author>Mark Reagan, The Brownsville Herald, Texas</author><text><![CDATA[March 15--BROWNSVILLE -- After five days of testimony from special agents and employees of the U.S. Department of Homeland Security Office of Inspector General McAllen field office, its former top lawman stoically listened as he was found guilty of conspiracy and falsifying government documents.
A federal jury deliberated for 2 1/2 hours Friday afternoon and found former DHS-OIG supervisor Eugenio Pedraza, 49, guilty of conspiracy and five counts of falsifying government documents to impede and obstruct an internal review of the office's practices in late 2011.
Pedraza was found not guilty of obstruction of justice and destroying falsified supervisory case reviews in early 2012.
Prosecutor with the Department of Justice declined to comment, citing government policy.
Pedraza's attorney, Larry Eastepp, said neither he nor his client had any comment.
Eastepp did, however, clarify that U.S. District Judge Andrew S. Hanen dropped five charges of obstructing an agency proceedings a few months ago.
Pedraza was found guilty of conspiring with DHS-OIG special agent Robert Vargas and former special agent Wayne Ball, who was convicted of falsifying documents in January 2013, of falsifying documents to impede an internal inspection of his office in September 2011.
According to Vargas' testimony, Pedraza ordered the special agent, who is on paid administrative leave and has a non-prosecutorial agreement with the government, to draft false memorandums of activity to reflect investigative work in a criminal case containing allegations that a U.S. Customs and Border Protection officer was working with a Mexican cartel to move drugs and immigrants into the country via a Brownsville port of entry.
Although Vargas had conducted said investigative work, Pedraza ordered him to "stretch it out" and "fill the gaps" in investigative activity prior to when he was with the agency and assigned to the case.
Ball was convicted of signing those documents.
Pedraza was also found guilty of ordering special agent Rolando Gomez to forge a memorandum of activity regarding the "deactivation" and deportation of a confidential source. Gomez is on paid administrative leave and reached a non-prosecutorial agreement with the government as well.
In addition, Pedraza was found guilty of directing special agent Marco Rodriguez, who was initially charged in the indictment, to forge memorandums of activity on two cases, one alleging a prisoner was working with a Border Patrol agent to move drugs and immigrants into the United States and another about an unknown CBP officer accused of helping pregnant Mexican women get into the country to give birth.
It is not clear whether Rodriguez reached a non-prosecutorial agreement with the government, but the charges were dropped with prejudice, which means they can't be brought against him ever again, according to his lawyer, Michael Rodriguez.
Also, Pedraza was found guilty of ordering special agent Edwin Castillo to forge a memorandum of activity concerning an investigation into an unknown CBP officer who was allegedly selling entry documents in Matamoros for $600 apiece.
Castillo is on paid administrative leave and reached a non-prosecutorial agreement with the government.
All of the agents on paid administrative leave will face administrative hearings where DHS-OIG supervisory agents determine whether to let them keep their jobs or to fire them.
During closing arguments, Eastepp alleged the special agents conspired to get Pedraza fired during the DHS-OIG internal review because they were unhappy with his leadership.
"It's about continuing this story, this setup -- and no doubt it shifted from getting him fired to getting him in prison," Eastepp said during closing.
Government lawyer Brian K. Kidd said that was illogical, arguing that the special agents were doing the right thing by telling the truth.
Eastepp "wants you to believe an entire office of agents conspired and perjured to remove Pedraza as boss," Kidd told the jury.
As for Pedraza, he is free on bond until sentencing, which is scheduled for June 16.
mreagan@brownsvilleherald.com
___ (c)2014 The Brownsville Herald (Brownsville, Texas) Visit The Brownsville Herald (Brownsville, Texas) at www.brownsvilleherald.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>