<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AC85-F487-E84D-2101"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Nation Briefs</title><source>Tulsa World (Oklahoma)</source><author>Wire Reports</author><text><![CDATA[Obama says health care program now stable
WASHINGTON - Despite a disastrous start and relentless Republican opposition, President Barack Obama said Friday that enrollment in his signature health care program is high enough to make it stable for the millions who have signed up.
"We look forward to seeing more and more people take advantage as some of the politics of the thing get drained away, as people start feeling more confident about the website," the president told WebMD in his latest, less-than-conventional attempt to spread the gospel about the law known by his name.
The president's remarks were made public as House Republicans held the 51st vote in 38 months to repeal or undermine the law, and the first since they won a fiercely contested election for a House seat in Florida this week in a race that featured health care as an issue. The measure calls for a delay in imposing penalties on individuals who fail to purchase health care under the law.
Tenn. told to recognize marriages during appeal
NASHVILLE, Tenn. - A federal judge ordered the state of Tennessee on Friday to recognize the marriages of three same-sex couples while their lawsuit against the state works its way through the court system.
U.S. District Judge Aleta Trauger issued the preliminary injunction barring the state from enforcing laws prohibiting recognition of their marriages.
In her written memorandum, Trauger makes clear that her order is only temporary and only applies to the three same-sex couples. A preliminary injunction can only be granted in cases the judge believes the plaintiff will likely win.
U.S. judge strikes down 12-week abortion ban
LITTLE ROCK - A federal judge Friday struck down Arkansas' attempt to ban most abortions beginning 12 weeks into a woman's pregnancy, saying viability, not a heartbeat, remains the key factor in determining whether abortions should be allowed.
U.S. District Judge Susan Webber Wright last year had stopped enforcement of the law while she reviewed it, and on Friday she declared that it was unconstitutional. She cited previous court decisions that said abortions shouldn't be restricted until after a fetus reaches viability, which is typically at 22 to 24 weeks.
"The state presents no evidence that a fetus can live outside the mother's womb at twelve weeks," the judge wrote.
In her decision Friday, Wright said only a doctor could determine viability.
Wright left in place a portion of the law that requires doctors to check for a fetal heartbeat and to notify the pregnant woman if one is present.
Indian diplomat faces new charge in fraud case
NEW YORK - An Indian diplomat was re-indicted Friday on U.S. visa fraud charges that touched off an international stir after she was arrested and strip-searched last year.
The new indictment, filed Friday, essentially just reinstates the charges against the diplomat, Devyani Khobragade — charges that now arrive with her out of the country. A judge had dismissed last year's virtually identical indictment Wednesday on diplomatic immunity grounds, but the ruling left a door open to federal prosecutors to revive the case and they suggested they would.
Khobragade is back in India, and it's unclear when, if ever, she might appear in court in New York again.
Research into medical marijuana approved
WASHINGTON - The Obama administration handed backers of medical marijuana a significant victory Friday, opening the way for a University of Arizona researcher to examine whether pot can help veterans cope with post-traumatic stress, a move that could lead to broader studies into potential benefits of the drug.
For years, scientists who have wanted to study how marijuana might be used to treat illness say they have been stymied by resistance from federal drug officials.
The Arizona study had long ago been sanctioned by the Food and Drug Administration, but under federal rules, such experiments can use marijuana only from a single, government-run farm in Mississippi. Researchers say that the agency which oversees the farm, the National Institute on Drug Abuse, has long been hostile to proposals aimed at examining possible benefits of the drug.
Rescue operation continuing in N.Y. blast
NEW YORK - The bodies of all eight people reported missing after a deadly gas explosion destroyed two buildings have been recovered, the fire commissioner said Friday, but workers are treating the scene as a rescue operation in case there are unknown survivors in the rubble.
Salvatore Cassano said no one else is known to be unaccounted for but workers will continue to scour the debris from the flattened buildings.
Cassano said about 70 percent of the debris had been cleared at the upper Manhattan blast site. But he said the pace was expected to quicken after firefighters removed a hazardous rear wall.
He predicted detectives and fire marshals would gain access to the East Harlem buildings' basements by midday Saturday to begin the investigation into what caused the explosion.
The rescue effort continued as federal investigators announced that gas was detected in underground tests of the site in the hours after the explosion, lending support to the hypothesis a gas leak may have been the cause.
]]></text></news-item>