<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="ACF2-433F-E08D-43F6"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Police Beat; 863-676-3467</title><source>Polk County Sun (Florida)</source><author>Compiled by Kathy Leigh Berkowitz; klberkowitz@heartlandnewspapers.com</author><text><![CDATA[Polk County Sheriff 's Office
PCSO, DBPR crack down on unlicensed contractors
PCSO, DBPR crack down on unlicensed contractors
From Monday, March 3 through Thursday, March 6, the Polk County Sheriff's undercover deputies, working in conjunction with investigators from the Florida Department of Business and Professional Regulation did an investigation into unlicensed contractual work performed in Polk County. At the end of "Operation Tool Time," detectives arrested 20 people for advertising and proposing contracting work in Polk County without a professional business license.
"When you don't take the time to research the people you hire to do repairs in your home, you open yourselves up to being victimized. Don't trust your home repairs to people who aren't licensed and insured-spend the extra time and money verifying licenses and insurance credentials before letting someone into your home," said Polk County Sheriff Grady Judd. "Unlicensed contractors can perform shoddy work, resulting in damage, fires, or even injury."
During the operation, detectives answered ads placed online or in periodicals advertising home repairs, and scheduled appointments with those who placed the ads. The types of home repairs the suspects claimed they did ranged from plumbing to electrical. Those who provided written or verbal proposals to perform the work showed up at the location where the "work" was to be done, and were arrested for engaging in contracting business without a license
"Unlicensed activity not only threatens the livelihood of Florida's consumers, but it also takes away jobs from those who are licensed as required by law," said DBPR Secretary Ken Lawson. "Floridians should always verify an individual's professional license with my department prior to having any work performed on their home."
Those arrested were:
· Ernie Garcia, 33, of 512 Petteway Drive, Lakeland
Reports say Garcia was working under the business name E&J Mobile Home A/C Service and arrived at the location to install an air handler and condenser. He allegedly told detectives he has never held a license to work in the state of Florida. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license; one count attaching unassigned tag. The PCSO says his criminal history includes theft and possession of prohibited weapons (Texas).
· Reynaldo Morales, 32, of 513 W. Crescent Drive, Lakeland
PCSO says Morales arrived at the location with Garcia, also working under the business name E&J Mobile Home A/C Service and told detectives he works for Garcia and is paid in cash. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license. He has no criminal history, according to the PCSO.
· John Ziegler, 29, of 449 Park Drive, Babson Park
Reports say he maintains a website using company name JZ Maintenance (www.jzmaintenanceservices.com) and advertises A/C service and installation. Detectives say he arrived at the location with his half-brother, Allen O'Rilley, and both were wearing T-shirts advertising their company. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license. PCSO notes his criminal history includes grand theft, possession of marijuana, and criminal mischief.
· Allen O'Rilley, 23, of 408 St. N., Dundee
PCSO says he arrived at the location with his half-brother, John Zeigler, and was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license and one count of violation of probation.
Reports say he is currently on probation for possession of controlled substance, criminal mischief, and grand theft; his criminal history includes burglary, possession of marijuana, controlled substance, paraphernalia, hydrocodone, drugs within 1,000 feet of a school, larceny, DWLSR, resisting arrest, and aggravated assault.
· Jason Stern, 30, of 3210 Bloomingdale Village Court, Brandon
Reports say he told detectives he has been working for D&M Ultimate Drain Team for the past 1.5 months. PCSO says the company advertises on the Internet and is unlicensed, noting that Stern does not have a license either. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license; one count VOP. PCSO says he is also currently on probation for burglary, grand theft, dealing in stolen property, giving false information to a secondhand metal dealer. His criminal history includes possession of a controlled substance, burglary, larceny, criminal mischief, grand theft, according to reports.
· Jorge Davila, 41, of 227 Satinwood Circle, Kissimmee
PCSO says he advertises on Craigslist for A/C repair and electrical work under the business name BYL Refrigeration and arrived at the location with credentials identifying him as a retired Puerto Rican law enforcement officer, and was wearing a T-shirt with his company logo on it. Reports say he was accompanied by Blanca Rodriguez-Baez. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license and one count unregistered electrical contractor. Reports say his criminal history includes DUI.
· Blanca Rodriguez-Baez, 40, of 277 Satinwood Circle, Kissimmee
PCSO says she arrived at the location with Davila, also working under the business name BYL Refrigeration, also wearing a Tshirt with the company logo, and that like Davila, she also had retired Puerto Rican law enforcement credentials. She was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license; one count unregistered electrical contractor. Reports say she has no criminal history.
· Anthony Higgins, 51, of 1310 McClellan Road, Frostproof
Reports say he advertises on Craigslist under the business name Customer First Appliance and arrived at the location to repair an A/C unit and do plumbing and electrical work. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license, one count unregistered electrical contractor. PCSO says his criminal history includes assault and harassing phone calls.
· Manuel Cordero-Acevedo, 46, of 1917 4th Street NE, Winter Haven
According to reports, he advertises on Craigslist under the business name M&G Handyman and arrived at the location to do plumbing work. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license. His criminal history includes assault, disorderly conduct and public intoxication, reports say.
· David Canfield, 39, of 200 Dennis Ave., Winter Haven
PCSO says he advertises on Craigslist and has used the business name Dave's Painting to Painting and arrived at the location to do plumbing work. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license. Reports note his criminal history includes battery, marijuana possession, and DWLSR.
· Nephtali Otero, 31, of 929 Kenbar Ave., Haines City
According to reports, he advertises on Craigslist. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license, one count electrical contracting business without a license, and has no criminal history.
· Deborah Ferra, 31, of 929 Kenbar Ave., Haines City
Reports say she arrived at the location with Nephtali Otero. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license; one count electrical contracting business without a license. She has no criminal history.
· Terry Hines, 35, of 167 Lake Thomas Drive, Winter Haven
PCSO says he advertises on Craigslist and was arrested and charged with one count electrical contracting business without a license. Reports note that his criminal history includes resisting arrest, larceny, fraud.
· Randy Monk, 32, of 4631 Carl Boozer Road, Haines City
Reports say he arrived at the location with Terry Hines. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license. His criminal history includes school trespassing, resisting arrest, escape, aggravated battery, possession of marijuana, contempt of court, DWLSR, petit theft, burglary, reckless driving, hit and run, aggravated fleeing to elude, possession of ammo by convicted felon, giving false information to a law enforcement office and violation of parole
· Basilio Rios, 33, of 658 Caribou Court, Kissimmee
Reports say he advertises on Craigslist and was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license. PCSO says his criminal history includes disorderly conduct, harassment, unlawful restraint, VOP, no valid driver's license.
· Daniel Martinez-Matassini, 44, of 539 Hummingbird Court, Kissimmee
PCSO says he advertises on Craigslist. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license; one count driving with suspended driver's licesence; and he has no criminal history.
· Michael Spring, 29, of 315 Coronado Court, Lakeland
Reports say he advertises on Craigslist under a former business name. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license; one count unregistered electrical contractor; one count possession of marijuana and paraphernalia. PCSO says his criminal history includes possession of marijuana.
· Terry Wellington, 28, of 3018 Helms Drive, Auburndale
Reports say he arrived at the location with Michael Spring. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license; one count electrical contracting without a license; one count possession of marijuana & paraphernalia. He has no criminal history.
· Jonathon Wellington, 26, of 116 Temple St., Winter Haven
Reports say he arrived at the location with Michael Spring. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license, one count electrical contracting without a license. He has no criminal history.
· Dean Menendez, 48, of 334 Appaloosa Hill Road, Polk City
PCSO says he advertises on Craigslist and Angie's List under the company name Dean's Handyman. He was arrested and charged with one count engaging in contracting business without a license; one count unregistered electrical contractor; one count possession of marijuana and paraphernalia. Reports note that his criminal history includes marijuana possession.
]]></text></news-item>