<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AD5E-78E0-D3B0-6BFD"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Ombudsman dismisses case vs. ex-Batangas City mayor for 'lack of merit' By Jaimee Maurico</title><source>Philippines News Agency</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[BATANGAS CITY, March 14 -- The Deputy Ombudsman for Luzon has dismissed for 'lack of merit' the criminal, administrative and grave misconduct complaints filed against former Batangas City mayor Vilma Dimacuha after she granted a protest filed by a power-generation firm over a penalty imposed on late tax payment.
Former Mayor Dimacuha remarked on Friday 'I am relieved that the truth has come out, that I did make the right decision in granting KEILCO that tax refund.'
Dimacuha added 'during my term as mayor of Batangas City I had always tried to be fair with my constituents as well as the companies helping in the development of our city.'
The decision noted that the respondent had the authority to grant tax protests, in accordance with Section 22 of the Batangas City Revenue Code and to indict Dimacuha for violation of Section 3(a) of Republic Act 3019, or the Anti-Graft and Corrupt Practices Act, it must first be shown that she had committed a crime or offense.
In a statement quoted from the dismissal order on Feb. 12, the Deputy Ombudsman's office disclosed 'Wherefore, premises considered, it is respectfully recommended that the criminal and administrative complaints against respondent Vilma A. Dimacuha be DISMISSED for lack of merit' based on a July 23, 2013 decision approved by Ombudsman Conchita Carpio-Morales.'
The 14-page document said that on Feb. 27, 2013, a certain Rodan H. Espiritu filed a complaint before the Office of the Deputy Ombudsman for Luzon asking for Dimacuha's 'preventive suspension' while the administrative case involving the KepcoIlijan Power Corp. (KEILCO) against then Mayor Dimacuha was being resolved.
Spiritu alleged that Dimacuha had violated the rules and regulations of Batangas City on the imposition of business taxes when she directed the City Treasurer's Office (CTO) on June 9, 2011 to credit the P1.69 million which KEILCO paid the city as penalty for its late payment of tax to the company's future tax liabilities.
But the respondent said her granting of the refund of the penalty paid by KEILCO, which delivered on May 3, 2011, or a day after the May 2 deadline, to the CTO a check worth P6.13 million for its business tax for the second quarter of that year, was justifiable since the power-generation firm had been a good taxpayer.
'In the criminal case under consideration, complainant did not even specify what rules and regulations concerning the imposition of business taxes were allegedly violated by respondent,' the decision said.
The Deputy Ombudsman's decision further stated 'By necessary implication, this authority includes allowing the crediting of penalty already paid to future tax liabilities. As it stands, respondent's actions enjoy the presumption of regularity and there is no evidence on record which effectively overturns the same.'
On May 16 last year, then Mayor Dimacuha submitted her counter-affidavit citing the complaint filed against her by Spiritu was a form of political harassment, since the latter was a fictitious person and a mere tool by her opponents and those who were interested in her position.
She had based her decision to grant KEILCO's prayer for a tax refund on the opinion of Teodulfo Deguito, Batangas City legal officer who noted that besides the company's good track record in tax payments for seven years, it had no intention to delay the payment of its taxes as the check was prepared earlier.
On June 23, 2011, city lawyer Dequito drew his opinion upon the CTO's request, which explained that KEILCO prepared its Citibank manager's check for P6,134,728.61 as early as April 28, 2011.
Dequito's opinion expressed it was unfortunate that the employee who delivered it arrived at the CTO after 5 p.m. on May 2, 2011 when the office was already closed.
The CTO imposed a penalty of P1,687,050 which KEILCO paid but with a protest, asking for a refund.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Philippines News Agency. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>