<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="ADB8-CF78-E698-BC67"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>FACES OF FRAUD</title><source>Richmond Times-Dispatch (Virginia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Donald C. Lacey and David A. Silver
Real estate investment scam: Lacey, a former Henrico County police officer, ran Capital Funding & Consulting in Henrico. Silver was president of the defunct Old Dominion Financial Services, also in Henrico. Lacey and Silver, through their companies, solicited money from people to invest in real estate. Silver funneled money from his investors to Lacey. The money was supposed to be used to buy and renovate fixer-uppers in Richmond and rent or flip the properties at a profit. In most cases, the work was never done. In all, 136 people, mostly from the Richmond area, lost a total of $15.2 million.
Sentence: Lacey, 46, was sentenced in August 2010 and is serving 10 years in prison. Silver, 61, was sentenced in June 2012 and is serving a five-year sentence.
Brenda Grubbs
Embezzlement, Internet scam: As Goochland County's treasurer, Grubbs held broad powers over the control of money and county accounts. But she was as much victim as perpetrator when she siphoned off some $180,000 in county money and sent it to a Nigerian-based swindler she'd become enamored of. By the time Grubbs was arrested in February 2011, she'd sent her online boyfriend $100,000 of her own money on top of what she took from the county.
Sentence: Grubbs, whose husband raised livestock on a family farm, was 54 when she was sentenced in December 2011 to 40 years in prison with all but four years suspended.
Edward Hugh Okun
Financial fraud: Okun, a Miami businessman, used his Richmond-based business to conduct a $126 million fraud that victimized hundreds of people across the country. Investment Properties of America and other Okun companies looted funds from customers legally deferring capitalgains taxes, in some cases wiping out life savings. The money was spent on an $8 million divorce, a 131-foot yacht, aircraft, jewelry and other luxuries.
Sentence: A federal judge sentenced Okun in 2009 to 100 years in prison.
John Ross Greer
Mail and wire fraud: Greer was convicted in federal court in 1982 for victimizing clients of his Richmond-based Virginia Gold and Silver Trading Co. He then victimized clients of his Unusual Villas and Island Rentals business, a brokerage between villa owners and vacationers wishing to rent them. In 2008 he started keeping the vacationers' funds intended for owners and used new funds to pay old claims.
Sentence: He served four years of a 10-year sentence for the $1 million fraud related to his gold and silver company and was released in 1986. In 2012, Greer was sentenced to five years and ordered to pay $627,000 in restitution to clients of his vacation business.
Iris Allen
Embezzlement: The South Richmond resident, a 45-year-old single mother of two, was in charge of benefit programs for children entered into the Virginia Birth-related Neurological Injury Compensation Program and was given broad authority to disperse benefits to families and the children. She drained as much as $1.3 million from the multimillion-dollar fund reserved to pay for the care of children whose injuries at birth are so severe that they will never lead independent lives. The money ended up going largely for clothing and jewelry for herself, including $20,000 for shoes and handbags.
Sentence: In May 2010, Allen was sentenced to 10 years in federal prison.
Kyle Leftwich
Embezzlement: Lawyer and Fan resident Kyle Leftwich, a 14-year veteran with the Marks & Harrison law firm, deposited Social Security claimant checks made out to her for legal services into her own account rather than the account of the firm. The firm estimated she made off with about $430,000 over several years.
Sentence: She was sentenced in November 2011 in Henrico County to serve more than three years in prison, a term she began serving after her appeals failed last year.
Tonya Farnsworth
Extortion: Tonya Michelle Farnsworth, 34, advertised her outcall services online and lured customers to a western Henrico County home. The victim, a church youth minister, sent nearly $180,000 of his own funds and those of the Mechanicsville Advent Christian Church to Farnsworth after she threatened to make public a $200 sexual encounter she had with the minister, who has pleaded guilty to embezzlement.
Sentence: Farnsworth pleaded guilty in Hanover County Circuit Court in October last year to extortion but is still awaiting sentencing in a case where she, as well as her victim, face up to 10 years in prison.
Martha Ann Nicholas
Cancer donation/Medicaid scam: Martha Ann Nicholas, who believed she had cancer and became a very public voice of a victim asking that donations be made to research programs, pocketed some $20,000 in Medicaid funds in the process. The Hanover County resident, now 44, suffered more, though, from a mental disorder that saw her craving for attention, forging medical histories, and firmly believing that she had terminal cancer and had survived an earlier terminal episode.
Sentence: With a presentence report calling for no prison time despite guilty pleas to charges that carried up to 40 years in prison, Hanover Circuit Court Judge J. Overton Harris issued a 10-year suspended prison sentence in April last year.
Darrell and Cynthia Underwood
Real estate investment scam: The Underwoods, a Chesterfield couple and the owners of Walkwood Properties, conducted a real estate Ponzi scheme. They pleaded guilty to charges in federal court in 2009. Many victims attended Mount Gilead Full Gospel International Ministries with the couple and some borrowed money on their credit cards to invest with the Underwoods.
Sentence: In October 2009, Darrell Underwood was sentenced to 10 years in prison and Cynthia to three years for defrauding fellow church members and others out of $9.7 million.
Clyde B. Pitchford Jr.
Embezzlement and bank fraud: Pitchford was a Richmond socialite who frequented the Commonwealth Club, rode in fox hunts and owned a $134,000 Rolls-Royce. He was convicted in 1986 of stealing $1.1 million from clients and banks. Before his arrest, Pitchford, who died in 2011, was a broker-investor with Dean Witter Reynolds Inc. and E.F. Hutton & Co. Inc. In 1986, he was deep in debt and disappeared on a trip to New York. Radio stations aired "The Ballad of Clyde Pitchford" and bumper stickers asked "Have You Spied Clyde?" After a three-month manhunt, he surrendered.
Sentence: Pitchford received a 25-year state sentence in 1986 and was released in 1990 when he began a federal bank fraud sentence. He was released from federal custody in 1992.
Eric M. Freedlander
Investor fraud: Freedlander, president of the former Freedlander Inc., the Mortgage People, was convicted in 1991 in what was then the largest fraud ever prosecuted in state history. The family business, started as a small real estate company by his parents, turned into one of the largest second-mortgage companies in the country operating in 33 states in 1986. From 1982 to 1988, the company operated a pyramid scheme in which investors were solicited under false pretenses and paid a return with money from subsequent investors.
Sentence: Freedlander was sentenced to nine years in prison in a $500 million fraud that caused more than $70 million in losses.
Kenneth and Bernice Morris
Identity theft: Kenneth Morris stole wallets and bank and credit cards from office buildings. Bernice Morris called the theft victims claiming to represent their bank and checking on questionable transactions on their account. She tricked them into revealing personal identification numbers that she gave to her husband, who used the stolen cards and PINs to make cash withdrawals and purchases.
Sentence: The Morrises, of Richmond, were sentenced in federal court in 2010 to four and three years, respectively, in an identity-theft scheme that netted more than $30,000.
Nicole Hathaway
Mortgage fraud: Hathaway, a New Kent County resident who was president of Mortgage Solutions II, admitted she attempted to obtain nine fraudulent mortgage loans totaling more than $1 million causing $568,000 in losses. The mortgage fraud conspiracy included recruiting straw borrowers, making false statements on loan documents and settlement statements, inflating purchase prices and forging documents.
Sentence: Hathway was sentenced in federal court in 2012 to two years and nine months in prison.
Justin G. French and Billy G. Jefferson Jr.
Historic tax credit scam: French and Jefferson grossly inflated the cost of historic renovations and submitted false applications for historic tax credits to the Virginia Department of Historic Resources, which administers the program. Historic tax credits are used to offset the cost of renovations. French and Jefferson worked mostly separately but together on at least one building in Richmond. French submitted false applications on about 36 Richmond properties in Richmond and cheated taxpayers and more than 110 investors out of at least $11.2 million. Jefferson pleaded guilty in December in federal court to fraudulently obtaining more than $12 million in historic tax credits.
Sentence: French, 43, imprisoned since May 2011, is serving a 16-year sentence. He forfeited assets in stocks, bonds, real estate, furniture and art and was ordered to pay $7.8 million in restitution. Jefferson, 52, incarcerated since Feb. 14, is scheduled to be sentenced May 9. He faces restitution of $12.9 million, forfeiture of $750,000 and as much as 20 years in prison.
James Frederick Price
Mail fraud: Price, of Midlothian, the owner of Madison Precious Metals, operated a website where people could invest in precious metals such as gold, silver and platinum. People invested millions of dollars through Price and most did not get any of their investment back. Instead Price purchased a lavish house and vehicles with the money.
Sentence: In 2012, Price was convicted and sentenced to more than four years in federal prison for mail fraud and ordered to pay more than $4 million in restitution to victims.
Robert B. Wilton III
Embezzlement: Wilton, a Christian man and part of Henrico County's most prominent development family, pocketed more than $1.4 million from a deceased client's estate when some of his development projects ran into trouble. A relative of the victim in the embezzlements said Wilton gained the trust of his elderly female target by quoting Bible verses and with frequent visits. Wilton, now 65, was so remorseful he surrendered at the county jail before he'd even been charged.
Sentence: In March 2007, Wilton was ordered to serve 29 years in prison with all but 23 months of that suspended.
Lynn Newell
Embezzlement: Newell acknowledged stealing as much as $30,000 from the Ashland Little League, whose books she kept, and from a badly injured county child whose recovery fund she oversaw.
Sentence: Guidelines called for a suspended sentence, but Newell dashed any hope that she'd escape prison time when she argued that her kindnesses to an injured child and dedication to the Ashland Little League had gone unappreciated. "This is what I get?" Newell, 40, complained as she stood before Hanover Circuit Judge J. Overton Harris in September last year. Harris delivered a 10-year sentence with all but six months suspended.
Mary Beth Redford
Embezzlement: A Henrico County medical office apparently was not aware that a woman named Mary Beth Redford it had hired as its accountant had a history. But when it came to light that New Kent County resident Redford had made off with more than $200,000 in company funds from Advanced Orthopaedics, so did her three previous embezzlement convictions dating back to 1988.
Sentence: In November 2010, Redford, then 44, was sentenced to six years in prison.
]]></text></news-item>