<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="ADE7-5C24-01C2-A2C8"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Letters to the Editor; Ending fossil fuel dependency a recurring theme</title><source>The Westerly Sun (Rhode Island)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[You can call it the "web of life," but to my eyes, it's the web of interconnected articles driven by our fossil fuel dependency/ excessive carbon dioxide emissions that seems to thread through tying everything together. Westerly Sun on March 4, Page 4, for example: "Promoting Clean Energy" guest editorial alongside "Power of Projection can be Disastrous" on top of "Coal Industry Unable to Keep Toxins out of Water Supply."
Let's focus on the power of projection, since it's the least obvious but perhaps most educational. "You project on others the traits that come naturally to you ..." Yeah, in elementary school. Surely by the end of high school after disappointing wake-up calls that are hopefully limited to losing your milk money, you realize everyone is different, possessing different skills as well as different agendas. And the best way to protect yourself against life's impossible-to-avoid disappointments is to limit your expectations in inverse proportion to the extent things are out of your control.
Power of projection's attributing lack of food stamp support to politicians unable to see beyond their projection of success is generous at best but delusional in the real world. It's dubiously misleading to think of politicians' highest priority serving the common good. Re-election is the highest calling, with advancing the interests of the highest campaign contributors ipso facto commanding resolute attention.
"The political leader states that we need to spend more on the military so we should spend less on food stamps. This is a false choice." In a zero-sum world, this isn't a false choice since one does exclude the other, but it is a bogus choice to give more money to a military that already "currently spends as much as China and Russia - as well as the next 10 countries combined," which has gotten us where exactly? Only the naïve or those stuck in elementary school take words at face value without considering the motivations, goals and objectives of the source of those words. Factor in the devastating political impact of the Citizens United outcome on politics, then you tell me it's Iraq Architect Oil War poster boy Dick Cheney who can't support food stamps all because of the power of projection? Hello? Anybody home?
The web of the power of fossil fuels is now playing itself out on the Crimean Peninsula, as Russian strongboy Vladimir Putin exercises his delusions of the Russian messiah empowered by Russia's cornucopia of energy (oil and gas revenues account for more than 50 percent of Russia's federal budget revenues), which Russia uses as a geostrategic lever in its Rodney Dangerfield world relationship. Syrian civil war humanitarian crisis? Iran nuclear nightmare? Closer to home, climate change drought in California has you hungry? Coal ash spills in West Virginia leaving you thirsty? Ultimately, fossil fuel usage has just too many similarities to tobacco usage - we pay good money to poison ourselves with second-hand smoke's counterpart in second-hand fossil fuel impact driving many of our non-human animal friends to extinction, which is happening right now as we breathe.
Ultimately, knowledge is power, and here's hoping you use this knowledge to power our community out of these problems of our own making. Surf the web and it's time to lose winter fat. Continue surfing and it's time to lose our fossil fuel dependency. Today is the first day of the rest of your life that just might be prolonged by limiting your carbon footprint and embracing renewable energy any way you can.
Jay Lustgarten Westerly
]]></text></news-item>