<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="ADEE-430C-C490-5E80"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>OneSavings Bank Plc Financial Results Year End 31 -28-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The table below indicates the source of inputs used to derive the carrying value of the Group's assets and liabilities that are held at fair value:
Fair values are determined using the following fair value hierarchy that reflects the significance of the inputs used in making the measurements: Level 1 These are valuation techniques that are based entirely on quoted market prices in an actively traded market and are the most reliable. Level 2 These are valuation techniques for which all significant inputs are taken from observable market data. These include valuation models used to calculate the present value of expected future cash flows and may be employed either when no active market exists or when there are quoted prices available for similar instruments in active markets. Where discounting techniques are used in respect of derivatives, management have chosen to use LIBOR rather than the Overnight Index Swap ('OIS') rate. This will be reviewed when derivative clearing is introduced. The fair value of the Group's derivative financial instruments includes a Debt Valuation Adjustment (DVA) as disclosed in note 4. In considering which similar instruments to use, management take into account the sensitivity of the instrument to changes in market rates and the credit quality of the instrument. Basis risk derivatives are valued using discounted cash flow models and observable market data and will be sensitive to benchmark interest rate curves. Level 3 These are valuation techniques for which any one or more significant input is not based on observable market data. None of the Group's financial assets or liabilities are valued using this technique. Valuation techniques include net present value and discounted cashflow models, comparison to similar instruments for which market observable prices exist, Black-Scholes and other valuation models. Assumptions and market observable inputs used in valuation techniques include risk-free and benchmark interest rates, foreign currency exchange rates, equity index prices and expected price volatilities. The objective of valuation techniques is to arrive at a fair value determination that reflects the price of the financial instrument at the reporting date that would have been determined by market participants acting at arm's length. Observable prices are those that have been seen either from counterparties or from market pricing sources including Bloomberg. The use of these depends upon the liquidity of the relevant market. 30. Pension scheme Defined contribution scheme: The amount charged to profit or loss in respect of contributions to the Group's defined contribution and stakeholder pension arrangements is the contribution payable in the period. The total pension cost in the year amounted to GBP645k (2012: GBP499k). Defined benefit scheme: KRBS operated a defined benefit pension scheme (the Scheme) funded by the payment of contributions to a separately administered fund for nine retired members. The Society's Board decided to close the Scheme with effect from 31 December 2001 and introduced a new defined contribution scheme to cover service of Scheme members from 1 January 2002. The Scheme Trustees, having taken actuarial advice, decided to wind up the Scheme rather than continue to operate it on a "paid up" basis. The winding up is largely complete. As at 31 December 2013 the liability to remaining members is GBP1.6k (31 December 2012: GBP1.6k) matched by Scheme assets. 31. Capital Management The Group is governed by its Capital Management Policy. The objectives of the Bank's Capital Management Policy are to efficiently manage the capital base to optimise shareholder returns whilst maintaining capital adequacy and satisfying key stakeholders such as customers and regulators. The Bank's prime objectives in relation to the management of capital are to comply with the requirements set out by the Prudential Regulation Authority (PRA), the Bank's primary prudential supervisor, to provide a sufficient capital base to cover business risks and support future business development. The Bank has implemented Basel II requirements in measuring credit risks under the standardised approach and operational risk under the basic indicator approach. Under Pillar I of Basel II, the Bank calculates its minimum capital requirements based on 8% of risk weighted assets. The Prudential Regulation Authority then applies a multiplier to this amount to cover risks under Pillar II of Basel II and generate an Individual Capital Guidance (ICG). As instructed by the PRA, the Bank manages and reports its capital on a solo consolidated basis and hence the Bank's capital position is not disclosed separately. The ultimate responsibility for capital adequacy rests with the Board of Directors. The Bank's ALCO, which consists of the Chief Executive Officer, Finance Director and other senior executives, is responsible for the management of the capital process including approving policy, overseeing internal controls and setting internal limits over capital ratios. The Bank actively manages its capital position and reports this on a regular basis to senior management via the ALCO and other governance committees. Capital requirements are included within budgets, reforecast and strategic plans with initiatives being executed against this plan.
]]></text></news-item>