<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AEED-43AD-121C-2E71"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Pearl Oriental Oil decreases 1.2% on low volume</title><source>News Bites Asian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Pearl Oriental Oil Limited (HK:00632), Hong Kong's 25th largest retail/wholesale company by market capitalisation, decreased 0.30c (or 1.2%) to close at 24.60c. Compared with the Hang Seng Index which fell 70.8 points (or 0.3%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -0.9%. The volume was 0.3 times the average trading of 3.6 million shares. The stock fell for a second day on Monday bringing its two-day fall to 0.90c or 3.5%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Pearl Oriental Oil, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051871770314912
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- Falls to Rises: in the past month the number of falls outnumbered rises 10:6 or 1.7:1.- In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week low once.- Net Profit margin has shown signs of deterioration in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

Bullish Signals- The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 24.8%. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.3. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued and ranks in the top quartile of stock by value of Q Ratio.
NoteVolume: there were 956,000 shares worth HKD235,176 (US$30,267) traded. - Pearl Oriental Oil is at a discount of 57.6% to its 12-month high of 58.0c on 02 Jul, 2013. It is also at a premium of 26.2% to the 12-month low of 19.50c on 20 Dec, 2013.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 05: Pearl Oriental Oil: Monthly Return of Equity Issuer on Movements in Securities for the month ended 28 February 2014[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Hongkong/Stock/News/313546.pdfSource: HongKong Stock Exchange
February 05: Pearl Oriental Oil: Monthly Return of Equity Issuer on Movements in Securities for the month ended 31 January 2014[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Hongkong/Stock/News/309223.pdfSource: HongKong Stock Exchange
January 02: Pearl Oriental Oil: Monthly Return of Equity Issuer on Movements in Securities for the month ended 31 December 2013[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Hongkong/Stock/News/304574.pdfSource: HongKong Stock Exchange
December 23: Pearl Oriental Oil: Update on S&P AgreementReference is made to the announcements of Pearl Oriental Oil Limited (the "Company") dated 28 June 2013 and 15 October 2013 ("Previous Announcements") in relation to a very substantial acquisition by the Company of part of an oil and gas exploration and production company with oil reserves mainly located in Russia.
December 23: Pearl Oriental Oil: Further Update on Announcement dated 28 October 2013[News Story] Reference is made to the announcements dated 28 October 2013 and 19 November 2013 of the Company (together with its subsidiaries, the "Group") (the "Announcement"). Capitalised terms used in this announcement shall have the same meanings as those defined in the Announcements.On 20 December 2013, the Company was informed by Mr. Wong Kwan, the Chairman and executive director of the Company ("Mr. Wong"), that he faced seven additional charges of dealing with property during 2010 to 2011, comprising a total of HK$200 million in cash and a total of 678,250,000 shares of the Company, known or believed to represent proceeds of an indictable offence (the "New Charges").
November 27: Pearl Oriental Oil: Framework Agreement for Possible Acquisition[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Hongkong/Stock/News/300991.pdfSource: HongKong Stock Exchange
November 19: Pearl Oriental Oil: Update on Announcement dated 28 October 2013[News Story] Reference is made to the announcement dated 28 October 2013 of the Company (together with its subsidiaries, the "Group") (the "Announcement"). Capitalised terms used in this announcement shall have the same meanings as those defined in the Announcement.On 19 November 2013, the Company was informed by Mr. Wong Kwan, the Chairman and executive director of the Company ("Mr. Wong"), that he was additionally charged with an offence, namely, "employing a device, scheme or artifice in a transaction in securities with intent to defraud or deceive, contrary to section 300(1)(a) of the Securities and Futures Ordinance", concerning a transaction involving Mr. Wong's disposal of certain shares in the Company (the "Additional Charge").Mr. Wong has informed the Board that he denies and will strongly contest the Additional Charge.The Board believes that the Additional Charge has nothing to do with ordinary businesses of the Company, therefore the Board believes that there is no material impact on the existing financial positions and operations of the Group.
ISIN: BMG6962P1187
HK:00632
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>