<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AEF5-8494-4023-2B3D"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Independence 'could hit UK-wide terrorism fight'</title><source>Aberdeen Press and Journal</source><author>Tim Pauling</author><text><![CDATA[The home secretary has claimed that the fight against crime and terrorism would be undermined by Scottish independence.
Theresa May said a border between England and Scotland would create "bureaucracy, delays and legal impediments".
Not only would cross-border crime-fighting be weakened, Scotland would lose access to the UK's vast intelligence-gathering mechanism. The current co-operation which exists at a national level "would have to change", Tory delegates heard.
Ms May said the manpower assistance given by police forces to each other would be threatened and officers from the UK and Scotland would lose their powers of arrest in each other's jurisdictions.
Police Scotland would lose access to the National Crime Agency's intelligence centre, its network of overseas liaison officers and specialist capabilities used to tackle crimes such as child abuse, slavery and human trafficking, and the smuggling of drugs and weapons. If Scotland votes to "go it alone", Police Scotland, while still being an important law partner, would lose its automatic access to MI5, MI6, GCHQ and the National Cyber Security Programme.
"The people who wish us harm can strike on any side of the border - or target Britain and her allies overseas," the home secretary said. "We must all remain vigilant in the face of such evil - and that crucial task will be made easier if we stick together."
Ms May said the British Government would expect passport checks between Scotland and England if a looser immigration policy was adopted north of the border after independence.
Her view is at odds with the Scottish Government's aim of keeping passport-free travel across the UK and Ireland.
She warned that the SNP administration's pledge to pursue "healthy population growth", outlined in the white paper on independence, would "undermine" Tory policies south of the border.
"If the people of Scotland vote to leave the UK there would be profound changes for migration policy," she said.
"An international border would be created where one does not currently exist. This would have implications for people travelling to visit family, go on holiday or do business, and for our economies more generally. Buried deep in Alex Salmond's white paper is the admission that, just like the last Labour Government, a separate Scotland would pursue a looser immigration policy."
]]></text></news-item>