<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AF1F-F08C-D08F-B377"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Power distribution companies saved Rs800m in 2013</title><source>Daily The Pak Banker</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Power distribution companies saved Rs800 million in 2013 on the purchase of transformers as a result of open competition among bidding companies, according to documents available with media on Saturday.
The savings could be possible only after all manufacturers were given equal opportunities in the bidding for the procurement of transformers. Lahore Electric Supply Company (Lesco) management also welcomed the move of open competition and recommended that any new condition that could hamper open competition should not be imposed.
The Lesco opinion has been concluded following unilateral decision taken by the former chief engineers (Design and Standards) of the National Transmission and Dispatch Company (NTDC) about attaching certain conditions with transformer manufacturing process.
The ex-official of NTDC altered such parameters in total disregard to the already verified requirements for the pre-qualification and registration of manufacturers, which have been finalised by the competent authority after due deliberation in meetings with the stakeholders.
Official sources said these parameters were subsequently communicated to DISCOs for compliance. However, Zubair Malik, former chief engineer (Design & Standards), NTDC, ignored this exercise and altered the parameters in order to oust small manufacturers from this industry and pave the way for an alleged cartel of big manufacturers.
The confusion and subsequent wrangling over suppliers’ pre-qualification has also hindered supply of power transformers, adversely affecting the electricity supply in various parts of the country, the officials said.
The consumers have to suffer a lot due to the unavailability of transformers, they said.
In order to check quality of transformers, Lahore Electric Supply Company (Lesco) has recommended holding an inquiry for ascertaining the use of substandard or scrap metal by all the manufacturers of power transformers.
A director of Lesco confirmed that his company had already given opinion in favour of free competition in the procurement of distribution transformers. He expressed the hope that after resolving this issue, supply of transformers will be restored, helping the power utility to make supply smooth.
An inquiry report prepared by the National Accountability Bureau (NAB) also identified cartelisation in the procurement of distribution transformers and resultant elimination of small companies from this procurement process.
The NAB report revealed that it is prima facie established that the allegation of use of scrap material is just to kick-out new / small firms from competition process, resulting in cartelization / pooling.
Moreover, it is the responsibility of the material inspection department to ensure procurement as per the specification after conducting many tests. In this regard, it is added in the report that the record of inspection pertaining to three years has been sought from NTDC, whereby no instance of scrap material has been proved.
Small manufacturers have claimed that new requirements are only aimed at putting extra financial burden on them. In fact, they said, the modus operandi has been adopted to oust the small manufacturers from this industry by creating financial hardships and to pave the way for big manufacturers.
When contacted, NTDC spokesman said Zubair Malik, the then chief engineer (D&S), has issued instructions regarding the quality control of distribution transformer manufacturing vide an office letter dated August 17, 2012.
The transformer manufacturers were asked to develop / update their infrastructure by installing CNC machines in order to improve the quality of the product.
It was suggested to Lesco and Hesco to incorporate these instructions in their prequalification criteria, the spokesman said.
He said that most of the transformer manufacturers (seven of 13) have made compliance to the instructions regarding quality control by installing CNC machines, while six remaining manufacturers, including Hammad Engg, AB Ampere and Pan Power, approached this office and requested for an extension in the timeframe to comply with the instructions, as they were facing shipping, financial and time constraints.
The timeframe was relaxed up to June 30, 2014, keeping in view their problems.
Moreover, the spokesman said, Hammad Engg, AB Ampere and Pan Power, have filed writ petitions in the Lahore High Court, challenging the instructions regarding quality control issued by the office, the spokesman said.
PEL has also filed a writ petition in the Lahore High Court to implement the instructions regarding quality control issued.
Meanwhile, NTDC on February 27 again asked small manufacturers to submit the invoices for the procurement of CNC machines, installation of which is a prerequisite for all manufacturers under the altered set of conditions.
]]></text></news-item>