<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AF49-DA1C-AC5A-2EC8"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Spanish armada seizes Leighton NEW CEO TAKES THE HELM AS EXECUTIVE RANKS, BOARDROOM PURGED</title><source>The Australian</source><author>BRIDGET CARTER, RESTRUCTURES</author><text><![CDATA[THE Spanish-backed construction giant Hochtief has cleared the decks at Leighton Holdings, cleaning out the executive ranks, and sweetened its $1.2 billion bid for the business.
In a dramatic day of long knives at the iconic engineering company that brought its chairman Bob Humphris to tears, Hochtief's own chief executive Marcelino Fernandez Verdes has replaced boss Hamish Tyrwhitt, who will leave with an $11 million-plus payout.
Leighton's chief financial officer Peter Gregg has also left, and three board members will depart the business, as the company rocked the market with news of dramatic changes.
``The focus is whether Leighton can be more efficiently structured,'' Mr Fernandez Verdes said.
Hochtief, controlled by Spanish parent ACS, said it would lift its proportional bid, which was launched on Monday, from $22.15 a share to $22.50.
Should Leighton shareholders accept the revised offer, it will increase Hochtief's stake in Leighton to a maximum of 73.82 per cent, from its current holding of 58.77 per cent.
Hochtief will also appoint ACS directors Pedro Lopez Jimenez and Jose Luis del Valle Perez to Leighton's board.
Paula Dwyer, Russell Higgins and Vickki McFadden will retire as directors before or at the May annual meeting, leaving chairman Mr Humphris and director Mike Hutchinson as the only existing board members remaining.
Mr Humphris described letting Mr Tyrwhitt and Mr Gregg go as personally distressing. He and Mr Fernandez Verdes did not attribute their departures to any failings in their roles, but rather part of the move by Hochtief to assume control.
``I find it gut-wrenching. I have been in tears,'' Mr Humphris said. ``I have grown fairly close to them.''
Mr Humphris said the board backed the higher offer from Hochtief after it earlier pressed the German firm to launch a full takeover for Leighton.
``We thought (it) would solve all of the issues and problems, but they declined to do that,'' he said.
It became evident Hochtief was planning to make yesterday's changes at the annual meeting in May regardless, Mr Humphris said.
A deal was struck whereby Hochtief was able to accelerate its intentions in exchange for a higher takeover bid. ``There's been some very tough negotiations, but let me stress they have been in goodwill,'' Mr Humphris said.
The changes mark the final chapter for Leighton as an iconic Australian construction company and have been welcomed by some shareholders, who believe they will stabilise the business and resolve any questions surrounding Hochtief's future intentions.
Madrid-based ACS is one of the world's largest companies dedicated to civil engineering and construction, operating in Germany, India, Brazil, Chile and Morocco. However, its debt levels of 47 per cent have sparked fears of asset sales through Leighton's subsidiaries, Thiess and John Holland, with the proceeds funnelled back to its parent company via a share buyback program or special dividend.
Mr Fernandez Verdes declined to comment on speculation surrounding any asset sales.
ACS holds at least 50 per cent of Hochtief, and Mr Fernandez Verdes said he wanted Leighton's strategy with Hochtief's, with a focus on risk and profitability.
``Leighton is a big part of Hochtief, and if you focus on Leighton, you are improving the balance sheet of Hochtief,'' he said.
Leighton's $22bn of annual turnover accounts for at least 57 per cent of Hochtief's overall revenue and at least 100 per cent of its net profit, following cost blowouts by Hochtief on some projects.
Mr Fernandez Verdes will relocate to Australia to become Leighton's fourth chief executive in four years. He will initially focus on analysing the business.
His appointment left questions looming surrounding his long-term commitment to the business, following news earlier this week that he had been named as the successor to Florentino Perez as chairman and CEO of ACS.
``I don't know what is going on in the future, but today my commitment is to stay here and to do my best in the best interests of shareholders, and also for myself, because I love this business,'' Mr Fernandez Verdes said.
He dismissed suggestions the departures of the management team were linked to any of the controversies Leighton had faced in the past year, including media allegations suggesting rampant corruption through the firm's international operations, which have been strenuously denied by the builder.
Mr Humphris described the resignations of the pair as ``a resignation they had to make''.
Mr Tyrwhitt's $11m-plus payout includes his bonus, salary and shares.
Mr Gregg's payment amounts to at least $8m.
Hochtief's increased offer now values the company at $7.59bn,
Continued on Page 18
Continued from Page 17
compared to $7.5bn previously, and is a 20.6 per cent premium over the dividend-adjusted five-day volume-weighted average price of $18.65 per Leighton share.
Previously, Hochtief said it would buy a maximum of 74.23 per cent.
Hochtief securing more than 75 per cent of the company would trigger requirements for it to repay a number of its debts.
As part of the offer by Hochtief, Leighton said its shareholders on the register as at March 21 would be entitled to a 50 per cent franked dividend of 60c per share, declared on February 20 and to be paid on April 4.
The bidder's statement would be dispatched by the end of the month.
Shares in Leighton closed down 34c yesterday at $21.90.
]]></text></news-item>