<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AF66-281E-FCE2-A0EE"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Haze 'hazardous' in Klang, schools shut</title><source>The Straits Times (Singapore)</source><author>Yong Yen Nie Malaysia Correspondent In Port Klang</author><text><![CDATA[MALAYSIA'S haze worsened, with air pollution in two Selangor towns reaching hazardous and very unhealthy levels due to a combination of industrial pollution and hot and dry weather, shutting schools and prompting the authorities to restart cloud seeding today.
Yesterday, the air quality in Port Klang was "hazardous" with the Air Pollution Index (API) as high as 358 at 8am, before falling to 314 at 6pm, the Department of Environment said.
Meanwhile, the air quality in Banting was "very unhealthy", at 311 in the morning, and falling to 221 at 6pm.
A reading of between 0 and 50 is considered "good", 51 and 100 is "moderate", 101 and 200 is "unhealthy" and 201 and 300 is "very unhealthy". Anything above 300 is "hazardous".
Petaling Jaya and Shah Alam had "unhealthy" air, with API of up to 185 in the morning before improving later in the day. Towns along the west coast of Peninsular Malaysia including Seremban, Port Dickson and Malacca also had "unhealthy" air yesterday.
The Meteorological Department said it will resume cloud seeding today.
"We just got the green light from Tentera Udara Diraja Malaysia (the Royal Malaysian Air Force) to use their airplane for cloud-seeding operations," Mr Mohd Hisham Anip, the department's spokesman, told The Straits Times yesterday.
Daily cloud seeding was halted last week as military planes were used to search for the missing Malaysia Airlines plane.
In Port Klang town some 50km from Kuala Lumpur, the haze reduced visibility to about 1km and the air smelled of smoke, keeping most people indoors.
Nasi lemak seller Hussin Tambi, 56, did not open his stall yesterday as he expected business to be bad. "I would probably lose RM500 (S$190) in income these two days," he told The Straits Times.
Selangor's education department has ordered all 131 schools in the Klang district, including in Port Klang town, closed yesterday. Another 71 schools in the Kuala Langat district, also on the coast of Selangor, were closed.
Port Klang town is often the worst hit by haze whenever smoke from forest fires in Sumatra island, Indonesia, blows over.
In 2005, the government declared a state of emergency in Port Klang when the API rose above 500.
But this time, the Department of Environment said the haze is mainly due to forest fires in Peninsular Malaysia as well as industrial pollution from factories and vehicles.
On Thursday, the government reminded offenders that open burning is illegal. Offenders face a RM500,000 fine or a jail term of not more than five years.
Mr Mohd Hisham said stronger winds in the next few days are expected to thin the haze. But with only stray showers expected until early next week, he said it could worsen again.
Mr Tan Eng Giam, 64, who lives in Port Klang, said he still cycles outdoors daily for exercise. "What else can we do about it, except to drink more water and herbal tea, and wait for rain'"
yyennie@sph.com.sg
SEE WORLD
]]></text></news-item>