<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AF75-7886-AADB-ED94"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Europe's tax fraud drive nets German soccer hero; Bayern Munich president gets jail term for evading millions in payments</title><source>International New York Times</source><author>ALISON SMALE</author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
The drive in Europe to expose and prosecute tax dodgers claimed its most prominent target so far on Thursday, when Uli Hoeness, long one of Germany's most beloved soccer stars and more recently president of the country's most storied team, Bayern Munich, was convicted of evading taxes estimated at more than 28 million euros and sentenced to three and a half years in prison.
Even amid growing German anxiety over the conflict between Russia and Ukraine, the trial riveted the nation, pitting the appeal of an athletic hero against growing populist anger at the use by the wealthy and powerful of secret Swiss bank accounts and other means of tax avoidance.
Even the normally staid Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung noted on its website that this was Germany's ''most sensational trial in decades.''
The verdict and sentencing, which lawyers for Hoeness said they would appeal, were the latest in a series of tax evasion prosecutions against prominent people in Germany and are part of a broader trend in which governments across Europe, strapped for tax revenues, are cracking down on avoidance schemes, especially among the wealthy.
Some 55,000 tax evaders have turned themselves in to German authorities over the past four years and paid a total of about (EURO)3.5 billion, or $4.8 billion, in back taxes, according to the country's taxpayers' association, quoted by Reuters.
The number of voluntary disclosures reportedly rose fourfold in 2013 from 2012 - which some observers have suggested was in part prompted by the case against Hoeness.
Hoeness, 62, who grew up as a butcher's son, was always a hard driver and joined Bayern, long one of Germany's best soccer clubs, when he was 18 years old.
In eight and a half years as a player, he helped the team win three league titles and three European Cups.
In 1974, he was part of the winning World Cup squad but was essentially knocked out of top competitive soccer when he sustained a grave knee injury in 1975.
That propelled him into the ranks of managers, where his successful record only helped his reputation. In recent years, he was a TV personality, known for his folksy style.
Answering a general appeal made to Germans holding secret Swiss bank accounts, Hoeness had admitted to authorities in January 2013 to holding an account with the Swiss bank Vontobel and said it was used for private speculation in financial markets.
The four-day trial opened on Monday with Hoeness expressing remorse. He apologized for what he termed his ''wrongdoing.''
But Hoeness's original confession to evading (EURO)3.5 million in taxes was swiftly exposed as a mere fraction of his dodges.
By late Monday, the total had climbed to (EURO)18.5 million, and after the second day to (EURO)27.2 million. When sentence was passed on Thursday, the amount in question was said by the Munich court to be some (EURO)28.5 million.
The defendant bowed his head and stared at the floor when the verdict was delivered, his face turning red, according to reporters in what was described as a tense courtroom. He left without commenting to reporters or fans waiting outside.
His lawyer, Hanns Feigen, said he would appeal. State prosecutors, who had asked for a five-year sentence, also said they might take Hoeness to court again if fresh financial information came to light.
Hoeness is likely to remain free until any appeal proceeding is complete, which could take several months.
His future as president and general manager of Germany's biggest and best soccer club was unclear. Some of Germany's most prominent businessmen are on the board of directors of the soccer club, which in 2013 won the coveted Champions' League title, the Bundesliga championship and the national soccer federation cup. They represent top German companies - Volkswagen, Allianz, Audi or Deutsche Telekom - which have ethics policies that would exclude someone like Hoeness, who has now been convicted of substantial tax fraud.
The Sueddeutsche Zeitung, which is based in Munich, said that board members were huddling Thursday night to consider Hoeness's fate, with no announcement expected until Friday.
''To depose Uli Hoeness, that is not so simple,'' the newspaper commented on Wednesday, as Germany absorbed the news that one of its most beloved figures was likely a substantial tax cheat. ''That would give the impression that big companies now fix the policies at Germany's biggest sports club, with roughly half a million people in its club and fan organizations.''
Past tax scandals enveloped the tennis champion Boris Becker, who was fined (EURO)500,000 and sentenced to two years' probation in 2002, and Peter Graf, the late father of the tennis star Steffi Graf. He was sentenced in 1997 to three years and nine months for evading the equivalent of (EURO)6.3 million. He was released on good behavior after serving half his term.
More recently, in 2009, the former head of Deutsche Post, Klaus Zumwinkel, was sentenced to two years' probation and paid (EURO)1 million in fines.
This year, the drive to expose tax dodgers has caught some more surprising figures, including Alice Schwarzer, Germany's leading feminist, who like Hoeness confessed to holding a Swiss bank account - back to the 1980s, it emerged - and paid about (EURO)200,000 in back taxes.
The former publisher and senior editor of the weekly Die Zeit, Theo Sommer, was sentenced to one year and seven months in jail - commuted to a probation of three years - and fined (EURO)20,000 for dodging (EURO)649,000 in taxes.
The source of the millions of euros with which Hoeness apparently engaged in massive bets on financial markets has remained unclear.
Back in April last year, as reports implicated the soccer star in multimillion-euro trades, even Chancellor Angela Merkel - an avowed soccer fan - expressed her shock. ''Many people in Germany are now disappointed in Uli Hoeness,'' her spokesman, Steffen Seibert, said then. ''The chancellor is one of those people.''
British police arrested Eric Cantona, who starred for Manchester United, and warned him for assaulting a man in London, The Associated Press reported Friday from London.
Cantona was briefly taken into custody after the altercation in the Primrose Hill area of north London on Wednesday.
When asked about Cantona's arrest, the police confirmed that ''a man in his mid-40s was arrested on suspicion of common assault. He was taken into custody and subsequently cautioned for common assault.''
]]></text></news-item>