<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AF8E-FFE1-835E-5E07"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>SWEETWATER UNION CLEARED TO CALL STRIKE; Health plan contributions key issue in talks with district</title><source>The San Diego Union-Tribune</source><author>ALLISON SAMPITE-MONTECALVO, U-T</author><text><![CDATA[CHULA VISTA
The Sweetwater teachers union has overwhelmingly voted to authorize its board to call a strike if an agreement is not reached with the district, primarily over the level of health plan contributions.
The voting by the Sweetwater Education Association took place over two days, with results announced Friday night. Officials said 90 percent or more of those voting authorized the board to call a strike in two questions on the same ballot.
They said 1,443 of the 1,800 union members voted.
Union president Roberto Rodriguez said the union took a vote at this time because it believes the district is engaging in unfair labor practices.
“The overwhelming mandate shows the level of frustration teachers are feeling,” he said.
Superintendent Ed Brand on Wednesday sent a letter to staff and community members stating that because the union and district are currently engaged in impasse mediation, it’s illegal for teachers to “threaten, prepare for, and/or engage in a strike.”
The union rejects that.
The teachers union and district for months have been negotiating terms to update a contract that expired in July 2013.
The parties reached an impasse in December and have since had three negotiation sessions with a state-appointed mediator.
The union contends the district has reneged on previously agreed terms. Earlier this year, the union filed an unfair labor practice charge against the district, which is being reviewed by the Public Employment Relations Board.
Rodriguez said the district could avoid a strike by contributing to health benefits according to what was negotiated last year.
In November, the district offered the union an increase in health and welfare benefits in its annual contribution from $9,000 per employee to more than $12,000, in addition to incremental wage increases.
“The part that’s misleading is that if (the wage increase was) effective in January, it’s actually half of that because it wouldn’t be for the whole year,” Rodriguez said.
Rodriguez said that while the offer from the district is still on the table, teachers should already have the $12,000 contribution.
Rodriguez said the district agreed to contribute 68 percent of the cost for employee health care based on the lowest-priced family rate plan.
Teachers say the district changed the agreement three weeks before open enrollment, making it more expensive.
Superintendent Brand decried the union’s tactics in his letter.
“PERB (Public Employment Relations Board) has made clear that such conduct by the union before the completion of statutory impasse resolution procedures constitutes an illegal pressure tactic…,” Brand said.
Rodriguez disagreed.
“There are absolutely no rules against us taking a strike authorization vote at any time,” Rodriguez said.
District spokesman Manny Rubio said the district is legally prepared to ensure compliance and prevent disruption to education.
“We’re preparing in case there is any action taken (for a strike) for the sake of maintaining some sense of normalcy in our schools,” he said.
Both sides have accused the other of bad faith bargaining.
allison.sampite-montecalvo@utsandiego.com • (619) 293-1394 Twitter: @allisonUTSD
]]></text></news-item>