<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="AFB0-F4DB-E812-F1A3"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>PARC, PSB kick start plantation drive</title><source>South Asian Media Network</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ISLAMABAD, March 16 -- The Pakistan Agricultural Research Council (PARC) and Pakistan sports Board (PSB) started spring Tree Plantation drive at Pakistan Sports Complex with an aim to provide clean, greener and healthier environment to players and people at the complex. The joint venture for tree plantation is also aimed at promoting horticulture activities at the complex. ' The plantation drive was formally inaugurated by the Federal Minister for Inter-Provincial Coordination (IPC) Mian Riaz Hussain Pirzada who planted Avocado Plant at the complex.
On the occasion, olive and orange plants were also planted by Federal Secretary, Ministry of IPC, Muhammad Ejaz Chaudhary and Chairman PARC, Dr. Iftikhar Ahmad at the site. ''''''''''' Speaking on the occasion, Mian Riaz Hussain Pirzada said PARC was playing a pivotal role for self-sufficiency in agriculture sector and was a role model for public sector, so government departments must follow PARC in ensuring clean environmental through various technologies, including bioremediation. ''''''''''' He however, criticized the Capital Development Authority for damaging the environment of Islamabad Capital Territory which was considered one of the naturally beautiful cities in the world. The Minister appreciated the PARC work, new interventions and support in this tree plantation campaign. He also appreciated the PSB management and staff efforts for working on his vision of clean, green and healthy environment at PSC premises. He requested PARC to assist Pakistan Tourism Development Corporation (PTDC) for fruits tree plantation on their land near National Library and Zero Point and other areas. Dr. Iftikhar Ahmad, Chairman Pakistan Agricultural Research Council (PARC) said that there was dire need to plant fruit plants and other precious trees in our houses and encourage the people for urban horticulture to obtain fresh fruits and vegetables to meet their nutritional food requirements. He shared the idea of kitchen gardening and rooftop horticulture. He said roof top horticulture also helps to minimize the sun heat during summer season besides other benefits. Dr. Muhammad Akhtar Nawaz Ganjera, Director General, Pakistan Sports Board (PSB) said that joint venture of PSB and PARC for tree plantation was aimed at promoting horticulture activities at the complex. He said under this campaign 2000 fruit plants have been planted and appreciated Dr. Iftikhar Ahmad, and his team for their contribution and support. A large number of people from all walk of life including high govt officials, agri. experts, women from Institute of Science and Humanities and media participated in the event
Published by HT Syndication with permission from South Asian Media Network. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>