<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B0C6-A5B6-EAD6-BA8A"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: W.R. Grace Pays $63MM to Clean Up Contamination</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Annie Youderian, writing for Courthouse News Service, reportedthat W.R. Grace & Co. paid the government more than $63 millionfor the costs of cleaning up 39 sites in 21 states, the JusticeDepartment said, two days after the company emerged from Chapter11 bankruptcy. The specialty chemical company agreed to the payment as part ofits bankruptcy reorganization plan, put into place after the firmand 61 affiliates filed for bankruptcy in April 2001. Two yearslater, the Environmental Protection Agency sued W.R. Grace,seeking reimbursement for the costs of cleaning up asbestos andother pollution caused by the company. About $54 million of the $63 million went to the EPA and $9million to other federal agencies, according to a press releaseissued by the Justice Department. "Cleaning up toxic pollution in communities is the responsibilityof the company that created it, not the American taxpayer," saidCynthia Giles, assistant administrator for EPA's Office ofEnforcement and Compliance Assurance. In 2008, W.R. Grace paid the EPA $250 million to settle claimsthat it contaminated the small town of Libby, Mont., withasbestos. The Justice Department said W.R. Grace's $54 million payment tothe EPA will reimburse the agency for cleanup costs associatedwith these Superfund sites: Acton Plant in Acton, Mass.; Amber Oilin Milwaukee; Aqua Tech in Greer, S.C.; Big Tex Site in SanAntonio, Texas; Blackburn and Union Privileges in Walpole, Mass.;Cambridge Plant in Cambridge, Mass.; Casmalia Resources in SantaBarbara, Calif.; Central Chemical in Hagerstown, Md.;Galaxy/Spectron in Elkton, Md.; Green River in Maceo, Ky.;Harrington Tools in Glendale, Calif.; Intermountain Insulation inSalt Lake City; IWI Site in Summit, Ill.; Li Tungsten in GlenCove, N.Y.; Malone Services Co. in Texas County, Texas;Massachusetts Military Reservation in Barnstable County, Mass.; N-Forcer Site in Dearborn, Mich.; Operating Industries Inc. inMonterey Park, Calif.; R & H Oil/Tropicana in San Antonio; RAMPIndustries in Denver; Reclamation Oil in Detroit; RobinsonInsulation in Minot, N.D.; Solvents Recovery Service of NE inSouthington, Conn.; Vermiculite Exfoliation Site in Nashville;Vermiculite Expansion Site in High Point, N.C.; VermiculiteIntermountain in Salt Lake City; Vermiculite Northwest in Spokane,Wash.; Watson Johnson LF in Richland Township, Pa.; Wells G & H(Source & Central Areas) in Woburn, Mass.; Western MineralsProcessing in Denver; Western Minerals Products in Minneapolis;W.R. Grace in Weedsport, N.Y.; Zonolite in Wilder, Ky.; PrinceGeorge's Co., Md.; Hamilton Township, N.J.; Ellwood City, Pa.; andNew Castle, Pa.; Zonolite/W.R. Grace in Easthampton, Mass.; andZonolite Road in Atlanta.  About W.R. Grace Headquartered in Columbia, Maryland, W.R. Grace & Co. (NYSE:GRA)-- http://www.grace.com/ -- supplies catalysts and silicaproducts, especially construction chemicals and buildingmaterials, and container products globally. Grace employsapproximately 6,500 people in over 40 countries and had 2012 netsales of $3.2 billion. The company and its debtor-affiliates filed for chapter 11protection on April 2, 2001 (Bankr. D. Del. Case No. 01-01139). The Debtors are represented by Adam Paul, Esq., and John Donley,P.C., Esq., at Kirkland & Ellis LLP, in Chicago, Illinois; RogerHiggins, Esq., at The Law Offices of Roger Higgins, in Chicago,Illinois; and Laura Davis Jones, Esq., James E. O'Neill, Esq.,and Timothy P. Cairns, Esq., at Pachulski Stang Ziehl & Jones,LLP, in Wilmington, Delaware. The Debtors hired Blackstone Group, L.P., for financial advice.PricewaterhouseCoopers LLP is the Debtors' accountant. Stroock & Stroock & Lavan, LLP, and Duane Morris, LLP, representthe Official Committee of Unsecured Creditors. The CreditorsCommittee tapped Capstone Corporate Recovery LLC for financialadvice. Roger Frankel serves as legal representative for victims ofasbestos exposure who may file claims against W.R. Grace. Mr.Frankel replaces David Austern, who was appointed to that role in2004. Mr. Frankel has served as legal counsel for Mr. Austern whopassed away in May 2013. The FCR is represented by OrrickHerrington & Sutcliffe LLP as counsel; Phillips Goldman & Spence,P.A., as Delaware co-counsel; and Lincoln Partners Advisors LLC asfinancial adviser. Mr. Frankel was a partner at Orrick Herrington& Sutcliffe LLP, until January 2014, when he resigned from Orrickto became a new partner in his new law firm, Frankel Wyron LLP. Elihu Inselbuch, Esq., at Caplin & Drysdale, Chartered, and MarlaR. Eskin, Esq., at Campbell & Levine, LLC, represent the OfficialCommittee of Asbestos Personal Injury Claimants. The AsbestosCommittee of Property Damage Claimants tapped Scott Baena, Esq.,and Jay M. Sakalo, Esq., at Bilzin Sumberg Baena Price & Axelrod,LLP, to represent it. Thomas Moers Mayer, Esq., at Kramer LevinNaftalis & Frankel, LLP, represents the Official Committee ofEquity Security Holders. W.R. Grace obtained confirmation of a plan co-proposed with theOfficial Committee of Asbestos Personal Injury Claimants, theOfficial Committee of Equity Security Holders, and the AsbestosFuture Claimants Representative. The Chapter 11 plan is builtaround an April 2008 settlement for all present and futureasbestos personal injury claims, and a subsequent settlement forasbestos property damage claims. District Judge Ronald Buckwalter on Jan. 31, 2012, entered anorder affirming the bankruptcy court's confirmation of the Plan.Bankruptcy Judge Judith Fitzgerald had approved the Plan onJan. 31, 2011. W.R. Grace defeated four appeals from approval of the Plan. Afifth appeal was by secured bank lenders claiming the right to$185 million of interest at the contractual default rate.Pursuant to a settlement announced in December 2013, lenders areto receive $129 million in settlement of the claim for additionalinterest. The Plan became effective on Feb. 3, 2014, following the approvalof the settlement of the last appeal from the order confirmingW.R. Grace's Plan.
]]></text></news-item>