<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B0F8-BE7D-10DA-3053"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>ABC, SBS STIFLE MEDIA INNOVATION</title><source>The Australian</source><author>ADAM CREIGHTON</author><text><![CDATA[Private companies are crowded out of the landscape
THE ABC's reputation has been the subject of relentless scrutiny in recent months following reporting about the Australian military and a gratuitous vulgarity broadcast to humiliate journalist Chris Kenny. This is not the first time the organisation's political agenda has come into question, nor will it be the last.
Renowned writer David Marr famously said journalists were naturally of a ``soft Left'' persuasion. Regardless of whether that is true or desirable, it must be the case for the bulk of journalists employed by the ABC.
This is not, though, anyone's conscious design, nor the fault of the ABC, which has periodically featured many people who would not be described as ``soft Left''. It is rather for the same reason Canberra is a Labor stronghold: people who seek to work for public broadcasters are in the main predisposed to government and ``soft Left'' issues -- what economists call ``self-selection''.
Quite naturally and rationally, those whose pay depends on government are less inclined to attack it. Charges of bias levelled at the ABC are routinely made about its behemoth cousin in Britain, the BBC, along with public broadcasters elsewhere.
For the same reason one finds very few ``Austrian school'' economists in the federal Department of Innovation, ``soft Left'' bias is inherent in public broadcasting.
The debate about bias obfuscates the more important question of whether the ABC should exist at all, bias or no bias. The idea of government-owned carmakers, supermarkets or newspapers meets with derision but government-owned broadcasters are popular.
Our refreshingly frank Communications Minister Malcolm Turnbull hit on the reason only last week, telling Sky News' Australian Agenda: ``The best case for public broadcasting is that it is there, it is part of the landscape.'' Humour aside, inertia and conservation for its own sake is powerful and explains much of what passes for sensible public policy.
In a liberal society, the government should provide only ``public goods'' that the market cannot or will not provide if left to its own devices. To do otherwise means higher taxes that favour some groups of workers and consumers over others, and slower overall growth in living standards.
Public goods should share two characteristics: it is impractical to make individuals pay for them, and one person's consumption does not prevent someone else's.
National defence is still the classic example, as was public broadcasting.
But the advent of pay-TV in the 1980s undermined that rationale by creating a mechanism to charge individual households. The proliferation of news and entertainment available cheaply and widely on the internet has since demolished it. Indeed, given the havoc online piracy has created for the music industry, the case for government-owned pop bands is probably stronger.
The idea SBS is necessary to give Australians of foreign language background ``culturally sensitive'' programming is farcical in the age of the internet. Reading Greek or Vietnamese newspapers online is more authentic than the contrived material produced here.
Arguments for public broadcasting now rest on emotion or self-interest -- users of the ABC and SBS determined to keep their subsidy, for instance, and their employees wanting to be shielded from what can be uncomfortable free market forces.
The Gillard government's media convergence review facilely asserted the ABC and SBS made ``vital contributions'' and offered a ``range of valuable programming that would not otherwise be delivered by the market''.
Far from acknowledging the crumbling case for a taxpayer-funded ABC and SBS, the review proposed their charters be updated to reflect their ``free'' online activities, which logically sap revenues from private media.
Arguments that existing private radio and TV are not of sufficient range or quality forget that those organisations are being starved of resources by public broadcasting's very existence.
Closure of ABC's 24-hour news channel, for instance, would lead to a dramatic increase in subscriptions to Sky News, or whatever other private-sector news channel emerged.
The best check on government is a competitive, well-resourced free press, whose journalists have an incentive to break stories critical of those in power. Cases of corruption in government and business are typically, if not exclusively, broken by privately owned newspapers and commercial television.
A rational approach to expenditure of public funds would call for ending any ABC and SBS programming that overlaps with programs provided by private media, whether it be television, radio, or newspapers. That would include the ABC's online presence and 24-hour news channel.
Some public support for broadcasting might still be warranted. Whatever technology does, a nation-state has a right to subsidise its own culture. But it could do so transparently by commissioning documentaries and other ``Australian'' content from private media firms at far less cost to taxpayers.
That would mean it could remove the obligation for struggling free-to-air TV networks to produce their own ``Australian content'', which in practice has met a deluge of the same rubbish that is shown in every other country: programs devoted to watching fat people lose weight, cooking and renovation competitions.
]]></text></news-item>