<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B139-E3C4-41B8-53DB"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Russia: Experts praise Karachay-Cherkessia leader's stabilization efforts</title><source>BBC Monitoring Trans Caucasus UnitSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Experts in the southern Russian republic of Karachay-Cherkessia have noted the improved socio-economic and crime situation in the region since Rashid Temrezov became local leader in 2011. Among the improvements they named more investment, a crackdown on corruption and the investigation of various high-profile crimes committed in the past years, Kavkazskiy Uzel reported on 12 March.
Summing up his three-year tenure as regional head at a news conference in the capital Cherkessk on 3 March, Temrezov vowed to continue work to expose corruption and attract investment to the region. Temrezov was appointed acting head of Karachay-Cherkessia on 26 February 2011 and was approved as regional leader by parliament on 1 March 2011.
At the news conference, Temrezov spoke about a number of investment projects, continuation of the construction of the all season mountain resort Arkhyz and the construction of a shoe factory in Cherkessk. He also said that he does not intend to resign any time soon.
"It is the president of the Russian Federation who takes decisions regarding my resignation. After two and a half years I think it will be possible to return to this topic. I continue to work in the usual manner. I have a rather busy schedule," the report quoted Temrezov as saying.
October 2013 saw the resumption of the investigation into the murder of Karachay-Cherkessia MP from the LDPR party, Rasul Bogatyrev, and his six friends in Cherkessk in 2004. In 2014, an investigation was re-launched into the murder of republican deputy prime minister, Ansar Tebuyev, in 2004, the report said.
In an interview with Kavkazskiy Uzel, Ruslan Khabov, the head of "Karachay Alan Khalk" public organization, said that Temrezov's coming to power has brought about many positive changes for Karachay-Cherkessia.
"Over the three years more has been done than what had been done for the previous 30 years. Sporting facilities, dozens of kindergartens and schools have been built; road infrastructure has been improved and the new resort, Arkhyz, has been built. Serious steps have been undertaken in agriculture as well," Khabov said.
Nikolay Khokhlachev, head of the public organization Rus, said that Temrezov's coming to power helped stabilize the situation in the region.
"There is no interethnic tension and social building is actively ongoing; towns and settlements are being developed. On the whole, issues in various spheres of the republic's life are being settled," he said.
Nikolay Silayev, head of the Caucasus Cooperation organization, also said that the situation under Temrezov's rule is much calmer than under the previous leaders.
"The government has become more bureaucratic, more formal and to a greater extent, it has become immersed in socio-economic problems, rather than in political or property division issues. As a general impression it seems to me that everything has become calmer and more stable. There are no major statements, news or large-scale conflicts," Silayev said.
However, he added that a number of problems remain.
"Everything should be improved to ensure that the legacy of the 1990s and 2000s is removed completely. It is also true that this applies to the entire country," he said. He added that apart from the Arkhyz resort, the government has not achieved any breakthroughs in the economy either.
Member of the Russian Public Chamber, Azamat Tlisov, did not agree that there have been no economic breakthroughs in the republic recently.
"Even if we do not talk about the success of Arkhyz construction resort, we should say that business is developing stably. Producers of mineral water continue their activities. Car manufacturing is actively developing - the Derveis car factory, Kavkaztsement, a cement factory in Khabezskiy [District], are also expanding their activities. In addition, small construction businesses have emerged here that are oriented on the local, as well as the Russian market," Tlisov said.
Source: Kavkaz-uzel.ru website, Moscow, in Russian 12 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>