<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B18B-D04B-9F2B-3CE0"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Washington: Airline Pilot Indicted for Traveling to Have Sex with Minor</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[US Federal Bureau of Investigation, The Government of USA has issued the following news release:
A commercial airline pilot has been indicted on charges of traveling across state lines in order to have sex with a minor female.
U.S. Attorney William J. Ihlenfeld, II, announced that MUSTAFA M. BAZBAZ, age 28, of Oakdale, Pennsylvania was named in a two-count indictment charging him with travel with intent to engage in illicit sexual conduct and transportation of a minor with intent to engage in criminal sexual activity. BAZBAZ allegedly began communicating with a 15-year old female from Jefferson County, Ohio in December of 2013 via the website known as MeetMe.com. BAZBAZ is alleged to have misrepresented his age and name to the victim, claiming to be 17 years old and to be named “Mike B.” It also alleged that BAZBAZ sent sexually explicit images of himself to the victim before arranging to pick up the victim near her home in Jefferson County in December of 2013. The criminal complaint asserts that BAZBAZ then took the victim to a hotel room in Hancock County, where he engaged in sexual intercourse with her.
If convicted, BAZBAZ faces up to 40 years in prison. This case will be prosecuted by Assistant U.S. Attorney Robert H. McWilliams, Jr. and is being investigated by the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the Hancock County (WV) Sheriff’s Department.
In other matters considered by the Clarksburg grand jury, Ihlenfeld announced that CLAUDE JONES a/k/a “MIKE JONES,” age 29 and DESEAN LAMARR AARON, age 24, of Fairmont, West Virginia, were named in an eight-count indictment charging them with conspiracy to possess with intent to distribute and to distribute crack cocaine, cocaine HCL and heroin. JONES faces an additional six counts and AARON faces an additional two counts for the distribution of the controlled substances. The defendants each face up to 20 years in prison on each count. The case will be prosecuted by Assistant U.S. Attorney Zelda E. Wesley and was investigated by the Three Rivers Drug Task Force.
ROBERT DALE TASKER, age 43, an inmate at the Tygart Valley Regional Jail in Belington, West Virginia, was named in a four-count indictment charging him with three counts of threats against the president and one count of threats against family members of the president. TASKER faces up to five years in prison on each count. This case will be prosecuted by Assistant U.S. Attorney Randolph J. Bernard and was investigated by the United States Secret Service.
GARY ALLEN STEWART, age 31, of Sutton, West Virginia, was named in a four-count indictment charging him with obstruction of correspondence. STEWART faces up to five years in prison on each count. This case was investigated by the United States Postal Inspection Service-Office of Inspector General, and will be prosecuted by Assistant U.S. Attorney Michael Stein.
ANTHONY SCOTT MOATS, age 39, of Lost Creek, West Virginia, was charged with being a felon in possession of a firearm. MOATS, who has prior felony convictions for burglary, drug distribution, and bank theft, is alleged to have possessed a firearm in September of 2013 in Monongalia County. MOATS faces up to 15 years in prison if convicted. This case will be prosecuted by Zelda E. Wesley and was investigated by the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives and the U.S. Marshals Service.
An indictment is merely an accusation and a defendant is presumed innocent unless and until proven guilty.
For more information please visit: http://www.fbi.gov
]]></text></news-item>