<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B238-0FFE-B2C6-A76D"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>CELTICTIGRESS; When the going gets tough, the tough get going. And the fighter that is coming out of the corner of Bill Cullen's ruined empire, says Will Hanafin, is his longtime partner, Jackie Lavin. . Styling by Liadan Hynes</title><source>Sunday Independent</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Their Renault car empire is gone. The five-star Muckross Park Hotel in Killarney is in the hands of a receiver, and Bill Cullen is being pursued personally for (EURO)10m by the banks. While Bill sometimes looks punch-drunk from the whole horrific experience, it''s Jackie Lavin who is stepping up to the plate.
"I am! Maybe I''m more aggressive. That''s my character," Jackie says. "Bill just wants to work and get on with his business. You have to get up and fight. My hair will probably fall out some time soon. But, seriously, I feel as strong as a horse and empowered by the people supporting us."
"I get empowered by the fight. I am angry that something like that can be done to honest people. It''s not that we were squirrelling away money. We didn''t have Cayman Island accounts. Maybe we shouldn''t have been as straight as we were.
"I''m not Mother Teresa," Jackie adds, "but we played it straight. We did everything by the book and are left with nothing. I''m sure that story can be echoed in thousands of homes around Ireland."
Recently, Jackie is emerging as an unlikely advocate for business people who lost everything in the crash, when the banks called in their loans. "I don''t know what else they can take! They can''t take my voice and my spirit," she says.
They labelled Rupert Murdoch''s ex-wife, Wendi Deng, the Tiger Wife for her spirited defence of her then husband in happier times. Now Jackie has transformed into our very own Celtic Tigress to fight Bill''s corner. "My focus, in particular, is to get back into business, primarily for Bill, because he''s the car man. I want him to focus on what he does best, which is to sell cars."
It looks like the business collapse hit Bill very hard, I suggest. "I think it did," Jackie says. "It was Bill''s whole life and the rug was pulled from under him. But what really hit him badly was the death of his brother seven days after the business was pulled.
"The motor business was pulled in October 2012 and, seven days later, his brother, Aidan, dropped dead of a heart attack in his home, sitting on his couch on a Saturday evening. Aidan worked in the business and was Bill''s younger brother, and all the pressure and stress didn''t do any favours to his health."
Jackie feels that stories like Aidan Cullen''s are common. "That''s the story resonating around the country.
"People that are dead, people that are saying nothing, people who are terrified of speaking out in case the banks come after them in a more vicious fashion. The country is in a grip of fear," she says.
But that wasn''t the end of Bill''s woes. "Then his sister died in America," Jackie explains. "Bill was punched from all sides. Family is very important to him and he''d be the godfather."
Is Bill Cullen a different man after these two years of hell? "I don''t think he changed and he's still very positive," she says. "But when you go from running a very busy and successful business one week, to having nowhere to go a week later, that''s a huge blow. And then your brother dies!" Old habits die hard, though. "Bill still gets up at 4.30am and still has unbelievable energy. We exercise at home - free weights and Pilates," says Jackie.
Even though they were mega-rich, Jackie argues that it was never about the money.
"Bill never worked for money, which was a strange thing," she says, "because he made a lot of money during his business career. Most entrepreneurs don''t do it for money.
"If Bill was doing it for the money he wouldn''t have put (EURO)19m of his own cash into the car business and (EURO)9m into the hotel. He never separated the two. The last thing they''re ever going to do is pull their own business." Jackie''s main focus now is to help him to set up their new SsangYong car franchise on the Naas Road, and Bill is doing little things to lift his spirits, including a recent cameo in the Happy Days musical when it came to Dublin last month.
"Hitchcock always had one line in his movies. It was like that," Jackie says, explaining the cameo. "One of the producers rang and asked me would Bill have any retro clothes? I said everything he has is retro! It was great fun!" The thing that hits Jackie hardest is the loss of her beloved Muckross House Hotel in Killarney. The couple bought it back in 1991, when it was just a roadside inn, and brought it up to five-star standard.
"It was that lovely notion that everyone in Ireland wants to own their own pub," she says. "The first weekend was Easter weekend and I did all the catering myself. There were so many people! I had a chef, and the chef didn''t come and we were inundated!" Jackie is from Ballyduff, County Kerry, went to school in Cahirsiveen, and has always loved south Kerry - although Ballyduff was never her long-term plan.
"Salmon fishing and greyhounds in Ballyduff, and that''s it! My parents had a smallholding and we grew everything ourselves. Killed the pig every so often, and you had the turkey and pigs, and all of that.
"I always wanted to get the hell out of there and get to Dublin," she says. "The civil service got me there. It was the Department of Defence, right beside Government Buildings. The Bureau of Military History. I would be fascinated now, but, at the time, I had zero interest, even though I was handling original documents from the Civil War and the War of Independence. I lasted six months.
"As a country child, you were expected to better yourself in Dublin," Jackie explains. "I joined a choir and a French class, and then I saw an ad in the paper looking for models. I did that. Never really took it seriously.
"I was things like Miss Harp, going all over the country promoting drink. At that time, you weren''t that socially aware. I had a great time, it was easy. It was good money compared to a nine-to-five job. I was on every car ad and Bord Failte photograph, and I did ramp as well."
She then set up a boutique in the Stillorgan Plaza, before moving to the Blackrock Shopping Centre.
"In 1981, when I opened in Stillorgan, people told me I was crazy and that I wasn''t going to make it. I am always battling and nothing fazes me. I traded for 18 years in Blackrock, until I saw all the chain stores coming into Ireland.
"There was no M50 then and I used to spend three hours a day in the car. Our home is between Naas and Sallins. I always claim that Eamon Dunphy kept me alive and entertained on the Last Word in those days."
Jackie then switched her energies to the Muckross Park Hotel. The biggest expansion phase was in 2006, when they went five-star and ACCBank came on board - the latter of which, ultimately, was an ill-fated move.
"We borrowed (EURO)9m to completely redo the hotel, adding 43 bedrooms and a spa. The Italians, French and Americans loved it. I did it in the cosy-cottage look as I''m a bit of a builder in my head - it''s all stone, wood and glass.
"I love the g Hotel in Galway, but that won''t work in Kerry. You have to have a different experience when you go to Kerry.
"The loan wasn''t risky at the time, and they would have given us more! The problem is we didn''t owe them enough. We weren''t Nama-ed because we were too small. Our hotel was loss-making back then because of the recession. After the development, we got up and running in 2007. Bill propped it up to the tune of (EURO)9m, but this money is now an unsecured asset."
The couple got a moratorium on interest for six months between October 2012 and March 2013. "We had forecasts for the next three years and we were gearing up for Paddy's weekend," Jackie says.
"We had tripled our bookings, had a new management team and were really focused on bringing all the costs down. The whole thing was coming together beautifully."
But then disaster struck last March. "Then, on a Monday morning in March last year, we got the demand letters from ACC - demanding full payment of (EURO)9m in 48 hours. We weren''t in default.
"Our interest payment for the first quarter wasn''t due until 25th March. They just said, 'Thank you very much,' and pulled the plug because everything is on demand. I had big problems with that!
"We had given them (EURO)3m cash from the house in Florida, which went off the principal [of the loan]. We could have left the (EURO)3m over there [in the US]. We thought we were doing the right thing," Jackie says.
"We got the demand letter on the Monday.
We were shocked, to be perfectly honest. We tried to contact ACC and they wouldn''t answer the phone. At 5.30pm Tuesday evening, we arranged to meet ACC in Dublin at 9.30am the following morning. We went in at 9.30am and, at 9.35am, we were told the receiver had been appointed to our hotel and was already in Killarney. We were drawn to Dublin and they were in Killarney."
It took Bill and Jackie three days to get rid of the receiver, and they got interim examinership with the intention of getting full examinership.
Then their problems got even worse when they read the small print of the ACC loan.
"It sounds completely crazy now, but we totally forgot that part of the loan was in Bill Cullen''s personal name," Jackie says, "so we lost the examinership.
"When they loaned the money to the company, they decided they were going to put half of it in Bill Cullen''s personal name," she says. "I actually didn''t know it. It didn''t dawn on us. For the bank, Bill was the better bet at the time. They knew what they were doing. They put the personal loan into the new wing and the spa," she adds.
Did Bill and Jackie ever consider the bankruptcy option? "To be honest, bankruptcy was never an option for us. We''re not the type to do that. We felt Muckross Park was going in the right direction - which it was."
The Muckross Park Hotel was put back into receivership last April after Bill and Jackie failed in their bid for full examinership - effectively losing the hotel.
It''s something that has hit Jackie hard.
An attempt to revisit the Muckross Park Hotel since the receiver was appointed ended particularly badly.
"They''re my management team!" she exclaims. "With my bookings! And they''re not allowed to speak to me. I went in and photographed, because all my furniture and effects are still there, and I wanted to see if they were being properly upkept and not being destroyed. And I got a solicitor's letter telling me not to enter the premises again.
"They said that I entered parts of the premises where the public weren''t allowed. I went into the kitchen to see if my kitchen equipment was being used correctly!" Jackie believes the stress that she and Bill are under is mirrored by thousands of others in this country. "People are under such stress. I don''t blame anyone for doing whatever they feel they need to do - like going to the UK for bankruptcy.
"You know there is a huge amount of mental anguish and mental trauma, and breakdowns, and heart attacks and suicides in this country."
Jackie is now taking up the mantle for more protection for business people. "There is a huge human rights issue here that no one is talking about. The legal profession aren''t talking about it, and the Government aren''t talking about it.
"It would level the playing pitch if there was some form of legal aid for business people to argue your case. At the moment, there is a whole raft of Irish people who have been literally thrown to the wolves," Jackie continues, "in all classes. Whether you''ve got a mortgage, you''re an electrician, taxi driver or whatever. They''re all thrown to the wolves and it's sink or swim."
"There''s a disconnect between the Government and Revenue and business people. Most business people, small or big, all they want to do is to run their business. They''re not a burden on the state. "I have to laugh at the 40-hour week - Bill Cullen would have that done in two days! Most business people would have it done in three."
She illustrates this point by an encounter she had with Taoiseach, Enda Kenny. "You''d meet him out at a do and he''d slap you on the back and say, 'Oh, sure, you''ll be alright.' That''s it! You''re all right, Enda, but we''re not!
"When the whole shutters came down on the car business, we met him at the Mayomen's dinner in the Burlington," she recalls. "He just came up and slapped Bill on the back and said, 'Sure, you''ll be alright, won''t you?' He''s on another planet."
If she''s so fired up, what is Jackie''s plan to make life better for Irish businesses? "What I''m going to do is ask everyone to write to all their local reps, MEPs, to lobby for legal aid for businesses to have some sort of pull-back on the banks. These banks, who are exiting the country, are just grabbing and going. We are entitled, as a nation, to have institutions that will support business.
"It''s all fine to have international people coming in, and they''re very welcome, but not at the expense of Irish people. They are selling all the Irish assets to vulture funds that are coming in to pick the bones of Irish businesses. Give the Irish an opportunity to buy back their businesses," Jackie adds.
Jackie reserves particular ire for Ulster Bank, who called in the loans on Bill Cullen's car business in October 2012.
"Ulster Bank pulled the rug and then it was a domino effect. Ulster Bank had the main business. They squeezed the overdraft and took us down to where we couldn''t write cheques.
"They took 13 or 14 properties. Of the (EURO)10.5-11m we owed them, they have got (EURO)8.1 million back out of five properties. We could have sold those properties ourselves."
After all the receiverships, what have they left? "Not a lot. Ulster Bank took Bill''s pension into the business. We are just surviving. Friends and family helped us. We didn''t have it in the back pocket. Things that were dear to me I had to sell in order to get stuff to get a fund together. I sold furniture, and bits and pieces that I needed to get a fund together."
And what do they both owe? "Personally? Nothing," she answers. "Bill? (EURO)10m personally. Muckross is gone. The main business, Glencullen, is gone. They have all the properties and will get 120 per cent of their money back. They are all for sale.
"We looked to lease one back and they don''t want to know. They don''t want to speak to the person who had the business originally."
Are they hopeful that their new car franchise will work out? "If you look at the other two Korean brands on the market, Hyundai and Kia, no one heard of them six or seven years ago," she says. "It''s mainly SUVs and crossover cars. I''m driving a white Korando, and Bill''s driving a black one. It''s the new Challenger!
"We''re going to challenge the Government, challenge the legal system, going to try and get some sort of legal level playing pitch between business people and the banks."
Like their mode of transport, Jackie''s ditched the rose-tinted glasses and is determined to look at life in black and white from now on. Watch out world!
LCover Dress, Key Collection by Ashley Roberts, Diamonds and Pearls.
Jewellery throughout, Jackie's own Contents and page 11 Dress, Eva Kayan, Diamonds and Pearls. Shoes, Fitzpatricks Shoes, Fitzpatricks.
Page 12 Dress, Pinko; shoes, The Amy Huberman Collection, both Arnotts Page 13 Dress Pinko, Harvey Nichols. Shoes, Fitzpatricks shoes, Fitzpatricks This page Dress, Marc by Marc Jacobs, Brown Thomas. Shoes, Fitzpatricks Shoes, Fitzpatricks Opposite page Dress, The Red Admiral by Tanyia Deane. Shoes, Fitzpatricks Shoes, Fitzpatricks Diamonds and Pearls, 1st Floor, Block A, Granary Court, Edenderry, Co. Offaly, tel: (046) 977 3332, or see www.diamondsandpearls.ie. See www.theredadmiralbytanyiadeane.com.
Shot at Carton House, Maynooth, Co Kildare As one of Ireland's most luxurious resorts, Carton House is ideally located to celebrate Irish Grand National weekend at Fairyhouse Racecourse. For only (EURO)99pps, enjoy one night's accommodation, with breakfast and dinner in the award-winning Linden Tree restaurant, and entry ticket to Fairyhouse Racecourse for Carton House Most Stylish Lady and the Irish Grand National on Easter Monday. For more information, tel: (01) 505-2000, or see www.cartonhouse.com Photography by Kip Carroll Assisted by Michael McDonald Styling by Liadan Hynes Assisted by Jessica Gaffney Hair by Jennifer Lil Buckley Make-up by Cara Macken, both for Brown Sugar, 50 Sth William St, D2, tel: (01) 616-9967
'It sounds completely crazy now, but we totally forgot that part of the loan was in Bill Cullen's name'
]]></text></news-item>