<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B284-3586-851A-E769"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Russia: Dagestan press selection list 3-9 Mar 14</title><source>BBC Monitoring Trans Caucasus UnitSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Nastoyashcheye Vremya
From the outset of the year, the financial sector of the republic has been under systematic and focused purge, author Gadzhi Magomedov reports. Last week, the licence of the Esid bank was revoked and it filled a short list of the local credit institutions which turned out to be deep in black books of the Central Bank of Russia. On 5 March, the bank kept its promise and revoked the banking licence from the Dagestan commercial bank for social development. The bank is blamed for the frequent violation of requirements of the law on combating money laundering. Obviously, the closure of the bank Dagestan - one of the oldest banks in the republic - indicates the tightening of the regulatory requirements of the Central Bank. The purge of the Dagestani banking sector will expand the capacities of the federal financial institutions - primarily, Sberbank, the , VTB and the Rosselkhozbank (the Russian Agricultural Bank); p 3 .
Chernovik
Author Mairbek Agayev reports that Aleksandr Mironov is the new chief of the Dagestani Department of the Federal Security Service (FSB). He flew into the republic accompanied by Deputy Director of the Russian FSB Aleksandr Sedykh. On Tuesday, they were received by the head of Dagestan, Ramazan Abdulatipov. The outgoing head of the department Lt-Gen Andrey Konin was awarded a medal For Services to the Republic of Dagestan. Speaking about the key merits of the former head of the special services, Abdulatipov stressed the maintenance of security during the Olympic Games in Sochi, in particular, minimizing the terrorist threats. With the appointment of Andrey Konin in March 2011, the internal discipline of the security officers has significantly improved. Another aspect is the activities of the seconded security agents, their relations and contacts (friendly) with all sorts of groups of political influence. Unlike some of his predecessors, such as the FSB general Nikolay Gryaznov, Konin distanced himself from them, and in our view, as much as possible and better. Nevertheless, Chernovik believes the main task of the new chief in the republic will be fighting extremism and terrorism. We do not rule out that Andrey Konin will keep in touch with the republic and in the foreseeable future he will return to the region...; p 3.
Author Abdulnasyr Magomedov views the endorsement of the statute of the Kizlyarskiy District special frontier Cossack community and a meeting with the new head of the Dagestani department of the FSB, Aleksandr Mironov on 4 March as symbolic. For example, the signing of the Cossack statute is viewed as an attempt to the reconciliation with the local Cossacks who throw their weight behind the protection of the Kizlyarskiy cognac plant; p 5.
Novoye Delo
Paper's correspondent Idris Yusupov reports on a theological conference "Russian Muslims: rights and responsibilities" held in the Dagestani capital and attended by members of the International Union of Muslim Scholars (IUMS) headed by Secretary-General of the IUMS Yusuf al-Qaradawi. The conference was also attended by Mufti Akhmad-khadzhi Abdullayev of the Spiritual Board of the Muslims of Dagestan, muftis of the spiritual boards of Muslims of the North Caucasus and other Russian regions, representatives of the Russian fund for support of the Islamic culture, science and education, Dagestani theologians and imams; pp 1, 2.
Ragimat Adamova writes that villagers of Irganay in Untsukulskiy District, left without compensation for flooded lands, are demanding that they are paid the required money and the completion of all work in the flood zone. Originally, planned was a rally of residents of Irganay, Untsukul, Maydanskiy and Arakani villages of Untsukulskiy District and the village of Kudutl of Gergebilskiy District, affected by the flooding of the reservoir of the Irganayskiy power station. The rally was to be held on 5 March. However, plans changed subsequently, and under pressure from the local law-enforcers, it was decided to hold a meeting in the village to be attended only by residents of the village of Irganay. To avoid the participation of other persons, police posts were set up at the entrances to the village. The presidential envoy to the mountain territorial district, Ibragim Ibragimov, arrived in the venue on behalf of the government of the republic. Speakers at the meeting think the Dagestani head "does not possess accurate information" and the terms of compensation are delayed through the fault of the government of the republic; p 5.
Makhachkalinskiye Izvestiya
Author Patimat Pakhrudinova reports on the departure of Dagestani vehicles carrying 80 t of humanitarian aid to the Autonomous Republic of Crimea. The humanitarian aid included computer equipment for educational and social institutions in Crimea. Dagestani cities and districts were involved in the collection of the humanitarian aid. The chairman of the Dagestani government, Abdusamad Gamidov, described Crimeans as our brothers and relatives. Therefore, Dagestan cannot stay away from developments in the peninsula. Everything what depends on us will be done to support the people of Crimea until the end - financially, morally and, if need be, physically, the prime minister concluded; p 3.
Source: Dagestani press selection list, in Russian 09 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>