<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B28F-453D-91CC-8798"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Could working into old age help keep you healthier?; As we get older, many of us are working longer or face the prospect of having to do so. But are there any health benefits to working later? Alison Sanders looks at whether the rising retirement age is actually good for you</title><source>The Western Mail</source><author>Alison Sanders</author><text><![CDATA[It was seen as a victory against ageism in the workplace and the removal of a barrier for those who wanted to continue doing the jobs they loved when the official retirement age of 65 was abolished in 2011.
This allowed workers in Britain to officially work beyond the age of 65 for the first time.
It was welcomed by older people's organisations but is it actually healthy for people to work beyond 65 or should people start to be winding down when they hit their 60s? According to the Office for National Statistics, the average current life expectancy in Wales for women is now 82.2 years and 78.2 years for men.
Compare this with 20 years ago when life expectancy was 78.85 for women and 73.25 for men and it's clear that things are changing.
We have an ageing population. By 2037 the number of people aged 65 or over in Wales is projected to rise by 292,000 and the increase in life expectancy is partly responsible for this rise.
So society is clearly changing, and as society changes, we're presented with new opportunities and challenges.
One of the changes we will be facing in future is that we will be working for longer.
In 2011, the UK Government scrapped the law that allowed employers to effectively sack workers as soon they turned 65.
Charities such as Age Cymru, which had campaigned for the abolition of this law, celebrated this landmark in the battle to win equality for older workers.
This heralded a new dawn which saw workers up to the age of 65 receiving the same employment rights as their younger counterparts.
However, let's not forget that over-65s still don't have the same rights at work as younger workers and that age discrimination still exists in employment.
Another change we've seen in UK Government policy that reflects the fact we are all living longer and healthier is the rise in State Pension Age.
At the moment, men can claim State Pension when they reach 65 years of age.
For women, the State Pension age is gradually increasing from 60 and will reach 65 by November 2018.
But by October 2020, State Pension Age for men and women will increase to 66, and after that, to at least 68.
So those are the demographic changes we're facing and part of the UK Government's response to it, but what else is happening? Campaigners say we already know that older workers are disadvantaged.
The Office for National Statistics said long-term unemployment remains a particular problem for the 50 to 64 age group.
Around 45% of those who are unemployed have been so for more than a year - higher than any other age group.
People aged over 50 also typically experience longer unemployment than other age groups. Labour market statistics from February 2012 show that 25.4% of people aged over 50 in Wales claiming Jobseeker's Allowance had been doing so for more than 12 months - a higher proportion than in any other age group. Experts have said "semi-sedentary" work could benefit older people working beyond the existing default retirement age and that physical and mental health generally are both maintained, and possibly improved, by activity.
But it could depend on what this work actually involves. Older people who have had particularly physical or even dangerous jobs, for example working in mines or on building sites, could find this too much once they are over the 65 mark.
The decision on whether to carry on would be up to the individual and dependent on their own circumstances.
A study by the Institute of Economic Affairs and the Age Endeavour Fellowship last year found that although there is a small boost in health immediately after retirement, over the long term there is a signifi-cant deterioration.
The research suggested that retirement increases the likelihood of suffering from clinical depression by 40% and the chance of having at least one diagnosed physical condition by about 60%. The probability of taking medication for such a condition rises by about 60% as well, according to the findings. It also found that people who are retired are 40% less likely than others to describe themselves as being in "very good" or "excellent" health.
It concluded that, for men and women alike, longer-term health benefits of employment among older people seem to exist.
Its authors said: "The policy implication is that impediments to continuing paid word in old age should be decreased. This does not necessarily mean that people should be expected to work full-time until they die, but rather that public policy should remove the strong financial incentives to retire at earlier ages."
Edward Datnow, chairman of the Age Endeavour Fellowship, had said: "In highlighting the positive link between work and health in old age, this research is a wake-up call for the UK's extensive and well-funded retirement lobbies.
"More emphasis needs to be given to ways of enabling a work-life balance beyond today's normal retirement age with legislative discouragements to extending working life being replaced with incentives. There should be no 'normal' retirement age in future.
"More employers need to consider how they will capitalise on Britain's untapped grey potential and those seeking to retire should think very hard about whether it is their best option."
Jeff Hawkins, chief executive for Age Connects Cardiff and the Vale, said: "The fact that people are now living longer and on the whole receiving a better standard of health care can be viewed as positive reasons for the rise in retirement age. However, the opinion on whether this rise is a good or bad thing will no doubt differ by who you ask and whether they work through choice or necessity. As an organisation, which exists to support older people, we advocate how keeping active physi-cally can also greatly benefit your mental health and well-being.
Therefore, working for longer does keep many of us young but the effects of what the rise the age of retirement will mean to each individual will depend entirely on personal circumstance."
Iwan Rhys Roberts, from Age Cymru, said that part of the debate about working longer has to be making sure that we are tackling the barriers which he said are currently facing older workers.
He said: "After all, if we can't give them a level playing field now, how can we expect to effectively support and encourage older people in the workplace in future? The benefits of encouraging and making it easier for older people to work are many.
When we consign older workers to the scrapheap, we're throwing away years of valuable experience and knowledge.
By stopping older workers from earning a wage, we also prevent many from being able to lift themselves out of financial hardship.
And let's not forget as well that by making it easier for older people to work, we're letting them contribute economically and giving them some self-respect."
Problems remain for older people despite the landmark 2011 decision. Age Cymru believes age discrimination is still rife in Welsh workplaces. A survey carried out by Age Cymru found 20% of people aged between 50 and 64 have experienced some form of age discrimination at work.
Questions also arise as to whether many are in a position to keep working, with growing numbers helping to look after grandchildren.
Mr Roberts said many grandparents feel their role has evolved and now involves more practical support than previously. They now contribute an estimated £259m to the Welsh economy.
For peace of mind, security and excellent value for money, why not take advantage of Golden Charter's funeral plans? A GROWING number of people nowadays are paying for their funeral in advance. This is due to factors including rising funeral costs and people's sense of duty towards their families to ensure it's all taken care of.
An advant~age funeral plan from Golden Charter is simple and affordable.
They are designed specifically for those who want peace of mind and a sense of security. It's a thoughtful yet practical decision that makes good financial sense.
What's more, an advant~age funeral plan offers excellent value for money. This year sees a price freeze on all advant~age plans, plus £40 of M&S vouchers when you take out a plan before March 31.
Why not make life easier by taking out an advant~age plan today? You will enjoy the following benefits: You can choose exactly the funeral you ¦want, deciding everything in advance if you wish, even down to the kind of music you'd like; You will benefit from excellent value for ¦money; By taking out a plan now, the funeral ¦ director's services are frozen at today's prices, saving money; We guarantee that your family won't be ¦asked to pay any more for these services; When the time comes, one simple phone ¦call is all it takes to activate the plan; You will receive £40 M&S vouchers if you ¦take out a plan before March 31.
¦ Find out more today. If you live in ¦Cardiff or the Vale of Glamorgan, call 029 2068 3604. For Rhondda Cynon Taff, Bridgend or Merthyr Tydfil, call 01443 490650.
We have an ageing population. By 2037 the number of people aged 65 or over in Wales is projected to rise by 292,000 and the increase in life expectancy is partly responsible for this rise
]]></text></news-item>