<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B307-C065-3B36-7E7E"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>British Columbia: Ministry of Jobs, Tourism and Skills Training Issues Solicitation for "Settlement and Integration Services Outside of Metro Vancouver"</title><source>Canadian Government News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Ministry of Jobs, Tourism and Skills Training has issued requirement for "Settlement and Integration Services Outside of Metro Vancouver"
Reference No.: 14-LMID-02
Solicitation Type: Request for Proposal
Description: Notice is hereby given by the Ministry of Jobs, Tourism and Skills Training (the "Ministry") of its intent to contract with 38 community based agencies (agency list attached) to deliver settlement/integration and English language training services in areas outside of Metro Vancouver. The purpose of these contracts is to continue to support clients who will not be eligible for such services due to the transitioning of program administration from British Columbia to Canada on April 1, 2014.
BC settlement services will target the following federally ineligible clients: a) temporary foreign workers, b) provincial nominees who are still awaiting a letter of approval for permanent residency from the federal government, and c) immigrants who have become naturalized citizens; and BC language services in non-Metro areas will target the following federally ineligible clients: a) provincial nominees who are still awaiting a letter of approval for permanent residency from the federal government, b) immigrants who have become naturalized citizens and c) individuals who are working in BC under the Live-In Caregivers Program.
These contracts will allow federally-funded community agencies to enhance their program for the continuation of the following activities/services for the above-mentioned federally ineligible clients: - English language instruction in classes that are primarily funded by Citizenship and Immigration Canada (CIC) and implement Canadian Language Benchmark aligned assessment tools to facilitate student intake/placement and demonstrate client progress in language acquisition; - Childminding for English learners while they are in class. (The above English language instruction in CIC classes and associated childminding services are only for provincial nominees who are awaiting approval for PR, naturalized citizens, and live-in caregivers); - Other forms of English language training/practice where CIC funded classes are full or unavailable, for example, conversation classes for adults or family literacy programs for adult learners and their children; - Information, referral and action planning that meet and support the settlement, employment and integration needs of the target clients; - Supporting clients' access to government, community and employment networks and services/programs; - Educating and supporting clients with respect to their rights and responsibilities as residents, workers and citizens of B.C.; - Providing time-limited group support for clients, if applicable (programming will aim to provide cultural/language support to overcome isolation or enhance community integration); - Training and coordination of volunteers/mentors to provide further support if needed; - Collecting information on the specific needs of the target client groups and best practices to address those needs.
The term of the contracts will be twelve months, from April 1, 2014 to March 31, 2015, with two one-year options to renew subject to Ministry funding availability. The value of the contracts will range from $10,000 to $365,000 depending on the number of federally ineligible clients receiving settlement and language services administered by the Ministry prior to April 1, 2014.
The agencies on the list are deemed uniquely qualified for the reasons outlined below: - Pending successful negotiation, they are anticipated to deliver federal settlement services in 2014/15 under a Contribution Agreement with Citizenship and Immigration Canada; - Established processes and service delivery models are in place to continue the above noted services to clients; - They have the required background, depth of knowledge, skill and expertise to deliver the services; and, - They have strong connections to and working in partnership with local community partners.
Vendors wishing to object to this decision must contact David.Groden@gov.bc.ca on or before 2:00 p.m. (PST) on March 25, 2014 presenting in writing, specific reasons for their objection, including detailed information on how their services, meet or exceed the direct award reasons as stated above. Vendors providing an objection must provide information to support relevant experience and ability to provide the described services for the same or better price. This information will be key in considering the validity of an objection.
Where objections are not received on or before the deadline stated above, or where objections made are not substantiated, the Ministry will continue to undertake direct award as outlined within this NOI.
Agency List:
1. Abbotsford Community Services 2. Capilano University 3. Cariboo Chilcotin Partners for Literacy 4. Central Vancouver Island Multicultural Society 5. Chetwynd Public Library 6. Chilliwack Community Services 7. College of New Caledonia 8. Columbia Basin Alliance for Literacy 9. Cowichan Valley IIAS 10. Dawson Creek Literacy Society 11. Fort Nelson Community Literacy Society 12. Ft St John Literacy Society 13. Hecate Strait Employment Development Society 14. Inter-Cultural Association of Greater Victoria 15. Immigrant and Multicultural Services Society of Prince George 16. Kamloops-Cariboo Regional Immigrant Society 17. Kelowna Community Resources Society 18. Ki-Low-Na Friendship Society 19. Kitimat Child Development Centre Association 20. Kitimat Community Services Society 21. Literacy Alberni Society 22. Lower Similkameen Community Services Society 23. Multicultural and Immigrant Services Association of North Vancouver Island 24. Mission Community Services 25. New Focus Society 26. New Page Human Services Society 27. North Island College 28. Northwest Community College 29. Okanagan College 30. Powell River Employment Program Society 31. Shuswap Settlement Services Society 32. Smithers Community Services Association 33. South Okanagan Immigrant and Community Services (also know Penticton & District Multicultural Society) 34. Skeena Diversity Society 35. S.U.C.C.E.S.S 36. Valemont Learning Society 37. Vernon ISS 38. Volunteer Terrace
Deadline for All responses: 2014/03/13
Contact Information:
Groden, David Performance Manager Ministry of Jobs, Tourism and Skills Training Immigrant Integration & Multiculturalism 5th floor, 605 Robson St. Vancouver, British Columbia V6B 5J3 Phone: Fax: Email: David.Groden@gov.bc.ca
For more information visit: http://www.bcbid.gov.bc.ca/. In case of any query regarding this article or other content needs please contact: editorial@plusmediasolutions.com
]]></text></news-item>