<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B30D-7F9F-5896-FAB4"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Surge in drug smuggling boats on Central Coast</title><source>Santa Cruz Sentinel (California)</source><author>Stephen Baxter, Santa Cruz Sentinel, Calif.</author><text><![CDATA[March 15--SANTA CRUZ -- Slicing through the ocean with more than 2,000 pounds or more of marijuana, drug smugglers on Mexican fishing boats known as pangas have skipped Southern California landing zones in recent months and headed to Santa Cruz and Monterey County.
Pushed north by heavier law enforcement and border security in Southern California, about 70 open-hulled pangas have been seized since October in the state and three pangas from Big Sur to Davenport.
But many more of the motor boats have zipped up the coast undeterred and unloaded drugs to crews waiting on shore with RVs and other vehicles, according to the Department of Homeland Security.
Recent court documents and interviews with federal and Santa Cruz County law enforcement dig into the mechanics of the maritime drug trade and explain why boaters should be aware of the boats and report them.
"This is a new trend that we're seeing," said Don Kinnamon, senior deputy harbormaster at the Santa Cruz Small Craft Harbor. "We know what these vessels look like and we know where they're coming from. The more awareness local law enforcement officials have, the better off we are to deal with this problem and put a stop to it."
It might seem odd to ship marijuana to Santa Cruz County where it is sold legally in dispensaries, but authorities said the pot trafficked on pangas is typically lower grade and headed for the Midwest. Smuggling is not a victimless crime, federal authorities said.
Mexican drug cartels that send pangas filled with pot are responsible for shootings, human trafficking, coercion and the killing of a Coast Guard officer during a boat ramming off the Channel Islands in December 2012, according to federal officials.
Authorities on the Central Coast want boaters to report suspicious pangas by calling 911 or VHF channel 16 if they're on the water.
Some of the publicity already has helped law enforcement. Since fall 2013, 753 suspected smugglers have been arrested and dozens of boats have washed ashore and been cataloged by Immigration and Customs Enforcement or ICE.
Some of the boats crashed in waves on the shore. Others have been scuttled by drug runners as a "cost of doing business," said Virginia Kice, an ICE spokeswoman.
RECENT CASES
On Sept. 30, a white panga with about 80 pounds of packaged marijuana crashed at Four Mile Beach north of Santa Cruz. No one was arrested, and authorities estimated that several hundred pounds of pot already had been unloaded before it likely flipped in heavy surf.
On Feb. 16, another panga was found scuttled at Garrapata Beach in Big Sur not far from a large bag of pot hidden under a tree on the beach. Authorities found no one with the boat.
In July, four men were apprehended at Shark Tooth Beach near Davenport after a State Parks lifeguard supervisor spotted a panga on the beach and saw men using hand signals to communicate as they unloaded drugs.
Federal authorities said smugglers often launch from Tijuana or Ensenada, Mexico, with fuel tanks of 250 gallons or larger to make it up the coast.
Another factor in the increased use of pangas has been heightened security on the U.S.-Mexico land border, according to Immigration and Customs Enforcement.
More smugglers also have been unloading on the Central Coast because many of its beaches can't be seen from the road.
"Nooks and crannies in the coastline" make it easier to hide, said Tony Cipolla, a San Luis Obispo County Sheriff's Office spokesman.
The boats are used in part because they are relatively small and cheap -- but they can stick out to Central Coast boaters because they're uncommon. They also lack California hull identification or "CF" numbers, similar to a license plate number on the boat's hull -- which also can raise suspicion, according to the Santa Cruz Harbor Patrol.
HOW IT WORKS
At night and sometimes under a full moon, boats headed for the Central Coast have been stopped near the Channel Islands to get fuel from another waiting boat. Once they reach the Central Coast beaches, they rendezvous with a separate crew on shore with an RV or other large vehicle to transfer hundreds of pounds of marijuana to it, according to Homeland Security.
"If you're trying to deliver a 2 1/2-ton load of dope, you need a conveyance to get it across the water. Then you've got to off load the cargo and get it on the road," said Kice.
The pot is often driven to a safe house and packaged for sale elsewhere in the country, authorities said.
Kice said that pangas loaded with drugs starting coming to Southern California in significant numbers around 2008. One reason was that smugglers faced more security on the land border, authorities said.
As authorities there became more aware of boats and patrolled with boats, helicopters, planes and other means, drug runners started to outfit pangas with faster, more powerful engines.
With more fuel, pangas could go farther north to areas where county law enforcement hadn't seen such boats -- landing in recent years in Ventura, Santa Barbara, San Luis Obispo, Monterey and Santa Cruz counties.
The bust near Davenport in March 2013 was the farthest north they have been spotted, said U.S. Coast Guard Lt. Anna Dixon.
"They're not common, but they have been more common in the past year" on the Central Coast, Dixon said Friday. "We've had a lot of success (intercepting pangas) in our southern areas. It sort of like a balloon, where you squeeze one end and it comes out the other end."
Some brighter news is that nearly all the smugglers who have been caught have not carried guns, According to federal indictments and agents investigating the cases. The men on the boats often are hired -- in essence outsourced -- by drug cartel members in Mexico, authorities said.
RECRUITMENT
The smugglers who have been caught sometimes have been picked up off the street in Ensenada or Tijuana. They are offered a few thousand dollars to drive boats to California, according to federal documents.
In the Davenport panga case, for instance, a man who was arrested with three others said he was promised $1,000 from a drug cartel member to help a shore crew unload a panga's marijuana.
Alex Cerna was picked up at a CVS drug store in Lynwood, in Southern California, and driven with seven other men to a Comfort Inn in Salinas, according to court documents. They showered, ate and were driven to Shark Tooth Beach near Davenport for the job, according to federal court documents.
Cerna and the others were charged with conspiring to possess marijuana with intent to distribute, and their case remains in federal court.
Other drug runners on pangas are coerced into smuggling.
In another case, an Ensenada, fisherman had been renting pangas to drug lords for smuggling operations in California, and he decided he didn't want to rent the boats any more.
"In retaliation, the drug trade ambushed (him) on a lonely part of the highway and shot him three times in the face and neck," according to federal court documents filed in 2013.
The man survived, and drug leaders later coerced his nephew to help with organized drug smuggling and provide GPS coordinates of drug routes.
In yet another case in 2012, a panga boat chase turned deadly off the Channel Islands.
Manuel Beltran-Higuera, a 44-year-old Mexican national, was approached in Ensenada and offered $3,000 to transport a load of gasoline to an awaiting panga north of Los Angeles, according to a 2013 federal complaint.
DEADLY CRASH
On Dec. 1, 2012, Beltran-Higuera and another man drove a 30-foot panga to a small bay off Santa Cruz Island in the Channel Islands called Smuggler's Cove. Approaching midnight, they waited there for about 20 minutes.
The other panga never arrived.
Coast Guard officers in a C-130 plane spotted the panga on a routine patrol and relayed its location to other officers on a Coast Guard cutter.
The cutter crew launched an inflatable vessel and shouted at the men on the panga in English and Spanish "Stop, police, put your hands up," according to court documents.
"In response, the crew members of the panga boat throttled the engines and steered the panga boat toward the small boat," prosecutors wrote.
The officers tried to steer out of its way, and one officer fired shots at it to try to avoid being rammed. But they kept going, ramming the small Coast Guard boat and sending two officers into the water.
One of them, Chief Petty Officer Terrell Horne, struck his head on a propeller and later died.
In February 2014, Beltran-Higuera was found guilty of assault and the 42-year-old panga driver, Jose Meija-Leyva, was found guilty of murder, assaulting federal officers with a deadly and dangerous weapon and other charges.
While none of the panga problems have turned fatal on the Central Coast, authorities cautioned boaters and beach-goers not to approach them.
Federal and Santa Cruz County officials want boaters to call 911 if they spot a suspicious looking panga.
"They know what's suspicious and what's not," said an undercover ICE agent who asked not to be identified. "We're asking people, if they see something suspicious to report it."
The vessels also are becoming more sophisticated, with expensive, powerful engines and better navigation tools.
"We are seeing more and more incidents with 'super pangas' -- large boats designed to carry more cargo," said ICE's Kice. "It's troubling."
Immigration and Customs Enforcement asks that anyone with information call 911 or 415-426-8815. The Coast Guard also can be reached at 415-399-3300.
Sentinel reporter Jason Hoppin contributed to this story. Follow Sentinel reporter Stephen Baxter at Twitter.com/sbaxter_sc
___ (c)2014 the Santa Cruz Sentinel (Scotts Valley, Calif.) Visit the Santa Cruz Sentinel (Scotts Valley, Calif.) at www.santacruzsentinel.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>