<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B47C-703B-0E5A-06A4"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Deutsche Post increases 1.8% after finding support</title><source>News Bites - Western Europe: Germany</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Deutsche Post AG (ETR:DPW) increased 1.8% after hitting the lower Bollinger Band twice in the last ten days. This is a bullish signal. The lower Bollinger Band marks the trajectory of support on a stock price. Compared with the DAX Index which rose 60.1 points (or 0.7%) in the day, this represented a relative price increase of 1.1%.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Deutsche Post, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051111940314267
Bullish Signals- In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week high eight times, pointing to a significant uptrend. - The present value of EUR1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Deutsche Post is EUR1,380, for a capital gain of EUR380.
Oversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The Stochastic indicator of 15.8 has pierced the oversold line of 20.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Return on Equity 13.9% [12.2%].- Price/Earnings/Growth of 0.5 [0.6].- Return on Assets 4.9% [4.2%].Other Bullish Signals:- Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.9. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- Brandirectory have estimated Deutsche Post brand value at EUR2 billion (US$2.8 billion). The Brand Value represents 5.8% of the estimated Enterprise Value of EUR34.6 billion (US$48.1 billion).- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity of 13.9% is better than sector average of 12.2%. This is computed as net profit margin of 2.9% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 1.7 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 2.9.- EBIT margin and EBITDA margin are positive and have seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteBeta: the Beta of Deutsche Post stock is 0.9. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market. - Deutsche Post is at a discount of 7.4% to its 12-month high of EUR27.24 on 26 Feb, 2014. It is also at a premium of 47.4% to the 12-month low of EUR17.10 on 22 Apr, 2013.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Parity:- Price/Earnings of 18.4 [20.0]. We estimate Deutsche Post stock is trading at a current year P/E of 18.9 and a forward year P/E of 19.5. - Price/Sales of 0.5 [0.5]. - Year-on-Year Earnings Growth of 37.5% [35.6%].- Price to EBITDA of 7.6 [7.7].Bearish Signals:- Total Liabilities/ EBITDA of 5.5 is more than or equal to 5, this compares unfavourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - Net profit margin has averaged 3.2% in the last 3 years. This suggests the company is less profitable with a low margin of safety.- The Enterprise Value/EBITDA multiple of 8.6 compares unfavourably with sector average of 8.8. Enterprise Value is estimated at MCap EUR30.5 billion plus net debt of EUR3.9 billion plus minority interest of EUR213 million and EBITDA is estimated at EUR4 billion.- Revenue growth has shown signs of deterioration in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]

AGGREGATE VOLUMES, PRICES AND TURNOVER PERIOD [Volume Index or VI in brackets; 1 is average] Xetra : DPW.ETR 10,650,000 [VI of 0.4] volume 97.914% of aggregate. Price: EUR25.22. Stuttgart: DPW.STU 115,881 [VI of 1.9] volume 1.065% of aggregate. Price: EUR25.24. Frankfurt: DPW.FRA 84,398 [VI of 1.9] volume 0.776% of aggregate. Price: EUR25.25. Hamburg: DPW.HAM 12,176 [VI of 1.8] volume 0.112% of aggregate. Price: EUR25.12. Munich: DPW.MUN 9,600 [VI of 2.6] volume 0.088% of aggregate. Price: EUR25.18. Aggregate volume: there were 10.9 million shares of Deutsche Post worth EUR274.3 million traded. The aggregate volume was 0.4 times average trading of 26.4 million shares.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:October 08: Deutsche Post: DHL introduces unique carbon reporting feature[Company Release]DHL Global Forwarding, Freight expands its green service portfolio with a new, automatic tracing application on CO2-emissionsNew feature available for customers worldwideDHL Global Forwarding, Freight is the industry's first company to include an automatic carbon footprint reporting feature as part of its track and trace system.
October 07: Deutsche Post: DHL prepares an airport in Armenia for emergencies[Company Release]"Get Airports Ready for Disaster" training program in Yerevan20 airports worldwide have already received trainingDeutsche Post DHL is taking its GARD program ("Get Airports Ready for Disaster") to the Zvartnots international airport in the Armenian capital of Yerevan and the Gyumri regional airport in the northwestern part of the country.
September 10: Deutsche Post director sellsDeutsche Post (ETR:DPW) director Ken Allen sold 3,000 shares worth EUR69,000 on September 05, 2013. The selling price was EUR23.0.
September 05: Deutsche Post DHL again serves as main sponsor of the Beethovenfest in 2013[Company Release] Free events in the Post Tower Lounge starting on September 8Financial support provided to the festival for the 10th yearDeutsche Post DHL concentrates in particular on education and culture at its home base in Germany. In 2013, one of the focal points of these activities will once again be the Beethovenfest Bonn.
September 03: Deutsche Post: DHL crowd sources deliveries in Stockholm with MyWays[Company Release] DHL launched the unique MyWays platform to facilitate last-mile deliveries throughout Stockholm by involving the city's residents. With the pilot, individuals now have the opportunity to deliver packages with products ordered online directly to other end consumers.
September 02: Deutsche Post: DHL launches day definite groupage service across Europe to speed up business expansion[Company Release]DHL Freight's Eurapid ensures fast and reliable deliveries to Europe's major markets on a daily basisCustomers benefit from prioritized handling and scheduled door-to-door deliveryBonn, 09/02/2013, 11:00 AM CESTDHL Freight has introduced its new high-quality Eurapid service offering day-definite lead times and priority treatment for less-than-truckload shipments (LTL).The service also entails full end-to-end visibility and simple rate cards.
August 06: Deutsche Post DHL remains on successful path[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Germany/Stock/News/45329.pdfSource: Company Website
ISIN: DE0005552004
DE:DPW; ETR:DPW; GR:DPW
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>