<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B4A8-5C42-83F4-10DF"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Fracking rush fuels a property boom; Could the oil revolution transforming North Dakota show the shape of things to come for Britain? By Ed Cumming</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Ed Cumming</author><text><![CDATA[On the open plains of North Dakota, where buffalo roamed and winters drop to 40F below, the once-sleepy town of Williston is an unlikely candidate for the most expensive city in the United States.
Yet Williston - or "Boomtown USA" as a sign at the entrance to the town announces - is at the centre of the oil fracking boom. This economic near-miracle is revitalising the area and dragging the rest of the country along with it.
So many workers have arrived in such a short space of time that there is nowhere for them to stay. Properties are occupied as fast as they are built. It is supply and demand red in tooth and claw, and rents per square foot are higher than in Manhattan, Silicon Valley or London.
There had been spurts of interest in oil here before, in the Fifties and the Eighties, but they ended in busts. Many large firms lost hope in the area, but smaller companies kept looking, key among them Harold Hamm, an oil billionaire and friend of Mitt Romney. They were interested in the Bakken, an oil-rich layer of rock 10,000ft below the Earth's surface but only around 60ft thick.
Conventional drilling, always hit and miss, had all-but dried up. By turning the drill sideways along this layer, and splitting the rock open with high-pressure water and sand, they were able to extract vast, reliable amounts of oil.
Other companies followed suit, with the same results - 99.9 per cent of these new wells are productive. Production is now up to around a million barrels a day, with 8,000 wells. It is thought that eventually there will be between 100,000 and 150,000, over an area the size of the UK. Refineries and rail terminals are popping up. Roads strain with the volume of trucks.
"It is not just a boom," says Robert Gavin, CEO of North Dakota Developments, who invited me to see for myself. "That label is old. People now talk about an oil plain. It is here to stay, it is an industry, and is lasting."
Robert, who was born in South Yorkshire and went to the same grammar school as William Hague, is one of the developers taking advantage of the new wealth. He spotted an opportunity to provide accommodation for oil workers.
This serviced accommodation, or "man camps" as they are known, provides each worker with a bed, desk, wardrobe and not much else. These rooms go for around $80 (£48) a night, including meals. It sounds like a lot for 60 sq foot, but it is a small price to pay for a piece of the oil boom. The workers have a warm shelter from the hostile winters. Robert's investors get a healthy return. The company has around 559 beds, but hopes to expand to around 6,000.
The boom has not been without problems. This prefabricated accommodation is hardly beautiful, but is necessary where the ground is too hard to build on during winter. There are those who disapprove of the environmental disruption, and there are stories of old people forced from their homes because of the surge in prices. Farmland used to be sold for $5,000 (£3,000) an acre. Now a decent plot near a road can go for up to $50,000 (£30,035) per acre. A three-bedroom family home that would have sold for $60,000 five years ago can now fetch $275,000 (£164,000). These numbers will only rise in the years to come. But on the flip side there are more positive statistics: unemployment in Williams County is just 0.3 per cent.
Fracking - for gas, rather than oil - controversially has been mooted in the UK, in Yorkshire and East Sussex, but has met fierce opposition. Partly this has been on environmental grounds, and partly because of the different way our property law works. In the US, mineral rights to land can be sold separately. One farmer is reputed to be bringing in more than $200,000 (£119,000) a month, simply from owning the land. In the UK, all minerals are owned by the Government. Locals here can rightly ask what's in it for them.
In Williston, the benefits are clear. There is a new multi-million-pound recreation centre. The high street is about to be refurbished. There are new roads and restaurants. McDonald's workers can earn $20 (£12) per hour. A 22-year-old petrol station owner is said to be making half a million dollars a week in profit. Young people have flocked from all over the US, drawn by the prospect of high salaries in their early twenties. They are overwhelmingly male - at least 10:1, possibly as high as 40:1.
Fracking has spread to Texas and Virginia. At a time when Europe is alarmingly aware of its dependence on Russian oil and gas, the US is poised to become a net exporter of oil - unthinkable even 10 years ago.
At his new $5million (£3.01m) restaurant in the centre of town, where the walls are decorated with heads of moose he's shot, Marcus Jundt, a restaurateur hoping to become Mayor of Williston in June, says: "It is shameful that old people who have lived their whole lives here are kicked out because of rent.
"The town needs a clearer plan for dealing with what's happening: better infrastructure, better zoning and a better way of making developers pay for their impact. We need to build as many houses as we can, as fast as we can, to bring the prices down.
"But the truth is that people are coming to take risks, experience the unknown and make money. Make a new life. This is what made America."
]]></text></news-item>