<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B4A9-3CC6-7D2E-0C0D"><date>2014-03-10</date><title>South Dakota Purchasers Of Computers, Video Game Systems And Other Digital Devices To Share In $310 Million Settlement</title><source>PR Newswire</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The following is being released by the Claims Administrator for the DRAM Settlement Fund by order of the United States District Court for the Northern District of California.
Settlements totaling $310 million have been reached with 12 manufacturers of Dynamic Random Access Memory (DRAM) over accusations of price fixing. Class counsel and state Attorneys General alleged that the price fixing caused millions of consumers and businesses in South Dakota and around the country to pay too much for DRAM and products containing DRAM, such as computers, printers, and game systems.
Class Counsel Tracy Kirkham says, "Products containing DRAM can be found in homes and businesses throughout South Dakota. If you purchased a DRAM product you may be eligible to receive money as a result of these settlements. We encourage you to go online and file a claim to get your money back."
Eligible purchasers that submit claims will receive a minimum $10 payment, and perhaps $1,000s depending on the amount of their DRAM purchases and the number of claims received. The quick and easy online claims process takes only five minutes to complete.
DRAM is a high density, low cost per bit, memory component that stores digital information and provides high-speed retrieval of data. DRAM is sold separately or pre-installed in electronic devices such as computers (laptops, desktops, and servers), graphics cards, video game consoles, MP3 players, printers, PDAs, DVD players, Digital Video Recorders, and others.
DRAM purchasers could get money from the Settlements if:
They purchased DRAM or a device containing DRAM; The purchase was made anytime from January 1, 1998 to December 31, 2002; The purchase was made in the United States or from a seller located in the United States; and, The purchase was not made directly from a DRAM manufacturer, but from a reseller such as a computer maker (Apple, HP or Dell), a retailer (Best Buy, Staples or Costco) or any other reseller (CDW, Ingram Micro or Amazon.com).
Purchasers must submit a claim by August 1, 2014 to receive money from the Settlements. Purchasers can submit claims directly online athttp://www.DRAMclaims.com. Purchasers that prefer to submit their claim by mail can download claim forms fromhttp://www.DRAMclaims.comor receive claim forms in the mail by calling 1-800-589-1425.
Purchasers who do not want to be included in the Settlements must exclude themselves by May 5, 2014.  Purchasers who do not exclude themselves may object to the Settlement or counsels' fee request by May 5, 2014. Purchasers who do nothing will not receive money from the Settlements and are bound by the Court's decisions.
More detailed information about the litigation and Settlements is available by:
Visiting:http://www.DRAMclaims.comCalling: 1-800-589-1425 (toll-free) Emailing:Info@DRAMclaims.comWriting to: DRAM Indirect Purchaser Antitrust Litigation, P.O. Box 8097, Faribault, MN 55021-9497.
SOURCE DRAM Settlement Fund
]]></text></news-item>