<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B569-4603-AC14-D9C1"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Murder bid case hold up</title><source>The Monday Messenger</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A 22-year-old man accused of attempted murder after an alleged stabbing made a brief appearance at Maidstone Crown Court on Thursday.
Glebs Konovalos, of Prospect Row, Chatham, was due to enter a plea to the charge, but could not do so because his lawyer was unable to attend.
Konovalos is alleged to have attacked Lauris Apsits in Bryant Street, Chatham, and to have assaulted Jelena Tahomirova, causing her actual bodily harm, on December 1 last year.
A provisional trial date has been set for May 27.
n From front page
woman of the All Party Parliamentary Group on Alcohol Misuse, said: "I'm very disappointed because this isn't what their core selling is about. They're about health and beauty products.
"They are clearly marketing at young, female consumers and I don't think it's a responsible thing to do.
Concerns
"I share the concerns about cheap booze in supermarkets and Superdrug is contributing to the issue of people pre-loading before they go out in an evening.
"They should remove alcohol from their stores. Other shops might follow Superdrug's lead, which will be damaging for our High Street and won't help us, as a nation, deal with young people binge drinking on cheap booze."
Prime Minister David Cameron has also previously pledged to crack down on promotional deals.
But Superdrug managing director Joey Wat defended the alcohol sales in a letter to the MP, saying it was the only way to stop some branches closing down.
About the Chatham branch, he wrote: "We sell alcoholic drinks in a very small number of our stores - only six out of 870.
"There is one reason for the sale of alcohol in these stores - to drive footfall and sales as the six are significant loss-making stores and at serious risk of closure. It is the last resort to save the jobs of our people."
None of the stores selling alcohol has a pharmacy.
]]></text></news-item>