<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B583-D947-F48C-F04A"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>NH can offer women more help in workplace</title><source>The Telegraph (Nashua, New Hampshire)</source><author>TAMARA FUCILE</author><text><![CDATA[Women in New Hampshire have a lot to be proud of these days. Much attention has been paid to the fact that our state was the first in the nation to send an all-female delegation to Washington at the same time we elected a woman governor. Both the speaker of the House and our chief justice of the Supreme Court are women, and we have the third highest percentage of women serving in state legislature in the country. And while 2016 is still a long way off, New Hampshire's political operatives are busy making preparations for another primary season that could very well set the stage for the election of the first female president.
There certainly is no shortage of strong women leaders for our daughters to emulate. And now, we have a policy victory to cheer for as well: thanks to Gov. Maggie Hassan's leadership, the New Hampshire Senate passed legislation that addresses inequalities in pay between men and women. With the unanimous 24-0, vote New Hampshire's lawmakers proved that when an issue matters to women and families in the state, they can overcome partisan bickering and ideology to get things done.
The pay equity bill is particularly significant because while New Hampshire has come so far in providing our daughters with strong women role models, substantial inequalities still exist for women across the Granite State. A report by the Center for American Progress, which examined the state of American women with a specific focus on three categories critical to women's overall well-being - economics, health and leadership, concluded that New Hampshire ranked only 18th overall. When compared to our New England counterparts, the overall state of women in New Hampshire placed a paltry fifth place - only Maine fared worse.
Why is that?
The primary reason for New Hampshire's poor overall ranking is that women in the state are less economically secure than women across New England and around the country. While women make up almost half of the New Hampshire workforce, their wages continue to lag behind that of their male counterparts. Our sisters in Vermont and Rhode Island have made strides in closing the wage gap - making, on average, 85 cents and 81 cents, respectively, for every dollar a man makes. Yet, Granite State women face greater inequality, earning only 77 percent of men's wages. These unfair pay practices have considerable consequences for New Hampshire women and their families that are exacerbated as the percentage of women who are the sole breadwinner for their family continues to rise.
In addition to facing pay discrimination, women in the New Hampshire workforce do not enjoy many of the employment protections offered to women in other states. While several states have enacted legislation to guarantee workers sick days or give employees paid time off so that they can respond to health and family needs without putting their economic stability at risk, New Hampshire has enacted no such protections. These types of family-friendly policies are crucial to eliminating the tough choices women have to make, including sacrificing higher paying jobs to meet family obligations.
Fortunately, because of the work of New Hampshire's legislators, the Granite State is taking steps in the right direction. This week, New Hampshire's House and Senate showed strong support for women and working families when they voted to pass the Paycheck Fairness bill, which strengthens protections of equal pay, makes it legal for employees to voluntarily share earning information, and prohibiting retaliation against workers who do share information about their earnings.
There are some in New Hampshire who argue that they are for pay equity, but question whether pay inequality is a real issue in New Hampshire. The data leaves us with no doubts about the reality: where the average man in our state earns $977 a week, his female peers earn just $748 a week - $129, or 23 percent less. With the Paycheck Fairness Bill, New Hampshire's lawmakers proved that they have awakened to this reality.
Tamara Fucile, who grew up in Nashua and once had a paper route delivering The Telegraph, is vice president for government affairs at the Center for American Progress.
]]></text></news-item>