<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B598-7C9C-BF65-3A31"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Flag fall; New Zealand's politics</title><source>The Economist</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A date for the general election is set
WHEN he announced September 20th as the date for the next election, New Zealand's prime minister, John Key, highlighted the difficulties of forming the next government. The country has a voting system of proportional representation much like Germany's, and a party leader who may hold the balance of power has a record of prevarication. It could, said Mr Key, be a "very complex environment. And if New Zealand First holds the balance of power, goodness knows how long it will take him to decide what he's going to do."
The "him" in question is Winston Peters of New Zealand First, who after an election in 1996 took eight weeks to decide between throwing in his lot with the centre-right National Party, Mr Key's bunch, or with the Labour Party. In the end he chose National, but he has since served as a minister in both National-led and Labour-led governments. Mr Key has been pushing Mr Peters to declare beforehand which side he will back. A government supported by a minor party or parties looks likely this time, too.
Eight parties sit in New Zealand's unicameral Parliament, three of them in league with the National Party, which in 2011 won 59 seats, two shy of a majority. Since 1996, when the country adopted mixed-member proportional representation, no party has governed alone.
Although voters appear to be tilting towards a third term for the National Party, its options for political partners are more limited than those of Labour Party, which could work with the Green Party, now hungry for power. By contrast, National's current partners may fare badly in September. Party tacticians are therefore entertaining some strange permutations.
One is to try to ensure that Colin Craig, leader of another party, the Conservatives, gets elected. Mr Craig is a man of striking views. He wants to revoke a law against parents smacking their children and another one legalising same-sex marriage. Not only is he a climate-change sceptic, but, impressively, also a man-on-moon sceptic. Mr Craig's party has little hope of getting the 5% of the vote needed to bring him into Parliament. But National could toss him a voting district. If it did that, however, it would then have to persuade loyal voters to cast their ballot for the Armstrong-denying Mr Craig in the broader interests of the party—no small task.
The political scene is further complicated by Kim Dotcom, an internet entrepreneur convicted in Germany for hacking and in Hong Kong for fraud. He has announced plans to set up a new entity, the Internet Party. Mr Dotcom, once Kim Schmidt, is fighting extradition to the United States, where he is wanted for online piracy. His file-sharing company, Megaupload, was forced to shut down when New Zealand police, acting on an American request, conducted an armed raid on his property. It also turned out that the government's spy agency had been snooping on him. Because Mr Dotcom is a New Zealand resident, the spying was illegal. A physically huge man, he has acquired the stature of an anti-establishment hero. Both the Greens and Labour fear that the Internet Party will take votes from them.
As a prime minister, Mr Key is popular enough, with an easy-going, one-of-us manner. By contrast, David Cunliffe has led Labour for only five months, and voters do not feel they know him yet. Still, Mr Key may be a little vulnerable to the suggestion that he lacks vision. That may explain his promise on March 10th to hold a referendum, if re-elected, on whether to redesign the national flag, including by removing the Union Jack from it. (Labour dismisses the proposal as a diversion.)
National will make its election pitch on its past record—particularly its management of the economy—and on keeping the Greens out of power. Labour will highlight growing inequality, the high price of housing, shortcomings in education and environmental issues. Its chief policies are to introduce a tax on capital gains and raise the pensionable age—sensible policies, perhaps, but hardly likely to be popular with everyone.
]]></text></news-item>