<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B5E0-927B-6162-05C5"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Programme summary of Russian Ch 1 "Vremya" news 1700 gmt 14 Mar 14</title><source>BBC Monitoring Former Soviet Union - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Vremya presented by Yekaterina Andreyeva, times are gmt.
1. 1700 Headlines: violence in Donetsk, Crimea referendum, Crimea passengers abused at airport, neo-Nazis in Ukraine, Kerry and Lavrov talks, golden goodbye law, Paralympics, frigate launched, weather.
2. 1703 Mourning in Donetsk Region after one man dies in fighting between two rallies yesterday.
Correspondent's report with footage of violence. The pro-Russian rally was unarmed, the pro-Kiev crowd turned up with flares and other weaponry, showing they were prepared for trouble. Why did the police allow two opposing rallies at the same time in the same place? The situation is getting worse in other eastern regions.
3. 1706 Russian Foreign Ministry says Moscow reserves the right to protect its own people.
4. 1707 Crimean head of government holds press conference about the referendum and afterwards.
Correspondent's report. Serhiy Aksyonov promises law and order but is ready for trouble should it happen; promises continuity of utility services and welfare payments; denies the vote is at gunpoint; predicts a solid vote to join Russia and promises social guarantees in the post-vote transition period.
5. 1711 UN envoy in Kiev calls for investigations of human rights breaches.
Correspondent's report on examples of human rights being breached. Crimean passengers in Ukraine have their passports confiscated at immigration. Crimea, by contrast, is calm and festive apart from some minor provocations by west Ukrainians. Observers and pundits reiterate why the referendum is legitimate, and a minister predicts that nearly all Crimeans will soon swap their passports for Russian ones.
6. 1716 Putin tells Ban Ki-moon that the referendum is legal.
7. 1717 Rabbi attacked in Kiev. The new National Guard is being set up from the Right Sector, and it could have been they who carried out the assault.
Correspondent's report in which the rabbi describes what happened to him. They were fascists, he says, but he does not know who. But the report continues that the Right Sector is setting up paramilitary units across the country. Lawlessness is rife, banks are being robbed and weapons are being stolen from military sites. A pundit fears the proliferation into Europe of these weapons. The purpose of these Right Sector units is to oppress the south and east, which they will do with US funding according to a pundit.
8. 1723 Moscow condemns treatment of Russian pilots in Ukraine, who are forced to sleep overnight in their aircraft.
9. 1723 Sergey Lavrov and John Kerry meet in London.
Correspondent's report with excerpts from Lavrov's news conference after the talks. He defends the referendum and equates Crimea to Kosovo. Kerry at his conference warns of consequences if the referendum goes ahead. But in the West they understand that sanctions will backfire. Meanwhile Ukrainian Premier Yatsenyuk is in Washington but has received little; the USA in offering aid is breaking its own law which bans funding for authorities that come to power by force of arms. The correspondent tackles the American arguments against the referendum with contributions from pundits and quotes from a US journalist interviewed by Iran's Press TV.
10. 1731 UN Security Council debates Ukraine, is addressed by Yatsenyuk who is rebuffed by Russian envoy Churkin.
11. 1733 Patriarch Kirill holds service for Ukraine.
12. 1734 Rallies across Russia in support of Russians in Crimea and Ukraine.
Correspondent's report features aid convoy from Moscow and vox pops from elsewhere about halting fascism.
13. 1738 Rally tomorrow in Moscow for Ukraine.
14. 1738 Commentary by journalist Mikhail Leontyev in the "However" slot. He attacks the fifth column of Russian politicians, especially Khodorkovskiy, who hate their country so much that they debased themselves by addressing Maydan.
15. 1740 State Duma debates a bill on rehabilitation of Crimean Tatars and halting golden goodbyes for managers.
Correspondent's report highlighting the draft law on the Tatars and discussions at a Duma working group on the situation in Ukraine, where politicians again equate Crimea to Kosovo and defend the legality of the vote.
16. 1745 Russia tops the medal table at the Sochi Paralympic Games. Linkup to Sochi for roundup.
17. 1756 Prime Minister Medvedev chairs government session about housing, with promises to resettle more families currently in slums.
18. 1757 Money laundering gang busted in Moscow.
19. 1758 Russian airborne troops parachute onto airfield in Arctic. Video.
20. 1758 Frigate Admiral Grigorovich launched in Kaliningrad.
Correspondent's report with video footage of the ship under construction and complete and contributions from the deputy CO of the Navy among others.
21. 1800 Search continues for vanished Malaysian airliner.
22. 1801 Warm weather in Moscow. Forecast.
23. 1804 Andreyeva signs off, programme ends.
Source: Channel One TV, Moscow, in Russian 1700 gmt 14 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>