<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B5EE-D62F-9C6C-3E23"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Is day of reckoning approaching for payday lenders?</title><source>The Independent on Sunday</source><author>Sarah Pennells</author><text><![CDATA[It's just over two weeks until the financial regulator, the Financial Conduct Authority (FCA), takes over the regulation of payday lenders and the rest of the consumer credit sector, from the Office of Fair Trading. Payday lenders make up a fraction of the sector, but they've attracted the most headlines and condemnation of consumer groups, so it's what the FCA will do about curbing the industry's excesses that's attracting interest now.
FCA's plans
The FCA will start regulating payday lenders from April Fools Day and says ominously that companies should "feel the difference" from day one. This week it announced an in-depth review into how payday lenders deal with arrears and defaults. A third of payday loans aren't paid back on time - if at all - so it's an important issue.
Let's hope the FCA is starting as it means to go on. So far, despite what the industry trade bodies say about their codes of practice, voluntary attempts to clean up their act have been woefully inadequate.
If standards have risen, it's probably as much down to the fact that around 20 payday lenders have left the industry as a result of the OFT crackdown.
Sharp rise in debt problems
The debt charity Stepchange saw an 80 per cent rise in the number of people asking for help with payday loan problems in 2013 compared to a year earlier, with an average payday loan debt of around £300 a month more than their take home pay. Only two weeks ago the OFT suspended the credit licence of a payday lender.
Better practices?
The industry introduced a code of conduct over a year ago, which was supposed to improve practices. It hasn't. Well, not by enough. Last month Citizens Advice said it found that lenders only carried out affordability checks on payday loan rollovers in six per cent of cases (and 39 per cent of "first" loans).
Rollover limits
The new FCA rules will limit the number of rollovers someone can have to two, which could make a dent in some of the payday lenders' profits. Last year, the Office of Fair Trading's report found that 28 per cent of loans were rolled over at least once, providing 50 per cent of lenders' revenues.
Multiple loans
Some debt advice charities, including Stepchange, wanted the number of rollovers to be limited to one, while a number of payday lenders preferred a maximum of three. Peter Tutton, Head of Policy at Stepchange, says limiting rollovers is only part of the answer. "Multiple loans can make a mockery of limiting rollovers. One in five of the people with payday loans who contact us has five or more payday loans while the average client has three."
Adverts
Only last month the Advertising Standards Authority banned an advert by one payday lender, which extolled the virtues of a payday loan to "treat yourself and a loved one to a weekend away and a slap-up meal". I'm assuming someone from the payday loan firm must have approved that advert, but I have no idea what they were thinking when they did.
Risk warnings
From April, payday lenders will also have to carry risk warnings on their adverts, including the words "late repayment can cause you serious money problems". Will this make someone who's desperate for cash think twice? On its own, probably not, but it might make payday loans seem like a bit less of a quick fix.
Arrears
The FCA's investigation into how payday lenders deal with arrears will involve visits from the regulator and analysis of lenders' business models. And an industry that targets the financially vulnerable must expect more scrutiny than most (especially when a payday loan can, in some circumstances, spiral from £200 into £1,851 in three months).
VERDICT
The signs are that the FCA is going to do more than just talk tough. The Consumer Finance Association, which represents some of the payday industry, says it's already been "raising standards to pave the way for the FCA's regulation". Well, I guess it would say that. But there's still plenty of room for standards to be raised. Whether a new regulator and new rules will do the job or whether (as the rich crop of banking scandals have shown us), rules alone won't be enough???we'll have to wait and see.
savvymoney.co.uk
]]></text></news-item>