<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B70D-A96D-1D94-8B55"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Biennale boycott is no more than commercial bullying in the name of the arts</title><source>Weekend Australian</source><author>CHRIS KENNY, ASSOCIATE EDITOR</author><text><![CDATA[This ugly episode sounds an ominous warning to other companies considering arts sponsorships
The romantic notion of the starving artist may be losing some of its appeal, replaced by the state-funded activist grandstander. Instead of bohemians burning Rodolfo's manuscript to keep warm, today's artists can burn the dollars of private sponsors to make party political points. Artists happy to take government grants or exhibit at events funded by government then can use them as platforms to target a private sponsor.
Any artist involved in the Biennale of Sydney would know it is funded by government; the government branding is more prominent than Transfield's.
And any artist who objected to offshore processing of asylum-seekers has had plenty of time to decide they cannot accept Canberra's largesse.
The Nauru and Manus Island detention centres were reopened from August 2012 (during the previous Biennale) by the Gillard Labor government and the tough and controversial Papua New Guinea Solution was announced by the Rudd Labor government in July last year.
In the intervening years hundreds of asylum-seekers died at sea. Yet it is only in the past few weeks (as the perilous trade nears an end with no boats in 85 days) after one tragic death during a riot on Manus Island that the artists have decided to make a stand.
At least nine threatened to boycott the Biennale because its founding partner is Transfield Holdings, which, indirectly through Transfield Services, holds contracts to manage detention centres. The Biennale capitulated to the pressure, dumped Transfield and kept the protesting artists happy.
The artists are free to parade their works and their political sensibilities at some expense to taxpayers but without the apparently tainted Transfield dollars.
To comprehend the hypocrisy and intolerance, try to imagine it the other way round: that Transfield had tried to ban artists opposed to offshore processing.
It is clearly silly that complex policy challenges of border protection are somehow distilled into simple, morally black-and-white choices devoid of any necessity to find a resolution.
Yet the real point here is not the issue itself. It is about the idea of tolerating one another's views, political positions, commercial freedom and obligations. The stunt would be opportunistic and pointless if taken against any company or event but the Transfield-Biennale example is extraordinary.
Founded by the Belgiorno-Nettis family, the construction and business services giant has a long history of supporting the arts and was instrumental in establishing the Sydney Biennale 40 years ago.
The Biennale chairman - until this ugly episode - was Transfield executive director Luca Belgiorno-Nettis.
Hounding Transfield from the Biennale was like cleaving the Nine Network from cricket.
It is a nasty insult to the Belgiorno-Nettis family, a misdirected swipe at a government policy through a company going about legitimate business and an ominous warning to other companies considering arts sponsorships.
Federal Arts Minister George Brandis is right to take this up with the Australia Council to try to enforce a simple principle: organisations with a handout for taxpayer funding ought not unreasonably to turn their back on private funding.
It is a matter of freedom of expression, the sort of freedom artists would normally demand for themselves.
The artists have ample opportunity to express their views through the ballot box, social media or elsewhere just like the rest of us, along with the added avenue of sharing their perspectives through their art.
They could reject government grants or patronage, or turn their backs on an event because it is supported by government.
They might even have done this under Labor when the detention practices they apparently abhor were put in place. Instead they adopt the faux morality of attacking the soft underbelly of a generous private patron. These actions will hurt the arts but not the artists.
None of this will assist a solitary asylum-seeker. Whether it is Japanese whaling, coal-fired electricity generation, live sheep exports or coal-seam gas exploration, we can expect to see more of this commercial bullying in the name of the arts, which is another reason Brandis is wise to act.
It is one of the more insidious aspects of social media that a radical minority can make disproportionate noise and intimidate public and commercial enterprises.
The Arts Minister will meet resistance and he is bound to find a paucity of courage in many organisations. But he must persist.
Crucially, the arts organisations themselves must develop the fortitude to withstand the posturing - the events need to be bigger than the hijackers. In the social media age the sensible majority is often denied a voice while real-time protests and frenetic media drive organisations to make reflexive decisions before common sense has had a chance to have its say.
This is a tricky area because in a robust democracy the freedom to protest is also precious.
But acceptability must be drawn somewhere south of having overseas artists and artists in receipt of federal government grants blackballing private companies conducting legal business for that government.
The compassionistas should be imaginative enough to make their point through a sacrifice of their own rather than impose sacrifices on the broader arts community.
The damage done to our arts industry and the standard of our public debate far outweighs the reputational benefits for artists seeking to add another cause to their CVs of moral superiority.
]]></text></news-item>