<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B748-2A0E-AEB4-974E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Astorino doesn't have to live with fracking waste</title><source>Press &amp; Sun-Bulletin (Binghamton, New York)</source><author>By, Pat Roberts</author><text><![CDATA[When Westchester County Executive Rob Astorino came to Binghamton last month to promote fracking in the Southern Tier, I couldn't help but remember he was coming from one of nine counties in New York that have passed bans on fracking waste.
In the case of Westchester, this means no fracking wastewater can be spread on any of their roads and lands, and no fracking wastes will be accepted in their wastewater treatment facilities. So what Asrtorino is saying is that while fracking wastes are not safe for Westchester County, fracking itself is just fine for the rest of us.
According to Astorino, hydrofracking will create "tens of thousands of new jobs" in New York. Unfortunately, this was merely an assertion. I keep waiting for real studies based on real evidence to back this up, not just the marketing claims of the energy companies. We do know, however, that the amount of radioactivity and toxic chemicals in fracking waste is great enough that its disposal remains a big problem for the industry. Inject it in the ground and you run the risk of earthquakes. Try to process it in regular treatment plants and the result is still toxic.
But this will not be Astorino's problem. Whatever waste there is isn't going to be spread, treated or stored in Westchester County. And if he gets elected, Astorino is safe in the Capitol too. Albany County doesn't want it either. In other words, Astorino's Westchester County will get the gas and Broome County will get to keep the problems.
Some have been callous enough to suggest Astorino's promotion of hydrofracking in New York is just a way to attack Gov. Andrew Cuomo ("All the Democratic leaders in other states had the guts to do it") while he receives donations from the gas and oil industry. It takes guts, or something, to promote an industry whose waste (and noise and traffic and pollution) you don't want to see anywhere near your own backyard.
To give him his due, Astorino is in good company. Rex Tillerson, the president and CEO of ExxonMobil, the largest energy company in the world, has just joined a class action lawsuit to keep a fracking water tower out of his upscale hometown in Texas.
It also takes a very narrow view of what a governor's job is. Our own county executive was quoted as saying, "Soon, hopefully, he will be working for all the people in New York."
Right now, Astorino is working for the people of Westchester, and that means they won't have to deal with radioactive fracking waste. If he wants to work for all of us, he can make sure that the rest of us don't have to accept fracking waste either. And the best way to make this happen is to make sure fracking does not take place in Broome County or anywhere else in New York.
Roberts is a member of Vestal Residents for Safe Energy.
]]></text></news-item>