<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B78D-0C8F-4552-A0AE"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Province missing out on highway tolls</title><source>The Telegraph-Journal (New Brunswick)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[I just returned home after driving from Florida through 12 states along the Eastern Seaboard. Without question, the best highway conditions we encountered were when we returned to New Brunswick.
The four-day trip involved paying more than $50 in tolls along the way. Did this deter us from making the trip? No. Does this mean we will not head south again? Absolutely not.
Based on the amount of traffic from the USA that enters New Brunswick and to get to either Nova Scotia, Prince Edward Island, Newfoundland or into Quebec and beyond, it seems quite ludicrous that toll gates are not placed on strategic sections of our first-class highways. Government officials tell us that the expense would not be covered by the possible revenue. I disagree.
I must believe that the trucking lobby has convinced government it would not be in its best interest to implement highway tolls. When will a province, such as ours, in the dire financial straits we are in, consider collection of tolls as an additional revenue stream? It doesn't make sense not to do so!
Ross Mavis
Saint John
RCMP shouldn't enforce own rules
It was part of my upbringing that I have always (and still do) maintain support for the law enforcement agencies of Canada. I was therefore upset when a news item has informed us that the standard "Serve and Protect" motto of police may become "Serve, Protect, and Legislate," at least for the Mounties. I see no reason why they should not advise the lawmakers when they want to change firearms laws, but it seems to me that they go too far when they try to change the regulations themselves and enforce their own rules.
I have maintained that no civilian should have in his keeping a fully automatic weapon. If your first aimed shot at, say, a deer cannot hit, you have no business spraying the whole forest and endangering the rest of the countryside. But I have been told of a one-armed man of Grand Manan who went deer hunting with a semi-automatic rifle that did not need bolt- or lever-action to fire a followup of his first shot, and I thought that was very sensible.
Obviously, if all firearms are illegal, only criminals will carry guns, which would simplify when a lawman should shoot (whenever he sees a weapon), but then we would not need specialists, would we?
So please, members of the RCMP, remember your motto, "Maintain the Right," and don't let it slide down to be advice to a boxer about to meet an opponent with a mean left hook: "Keep your right up."
Stuart Mills
Fredericton
Council made right fluoride decision
We attended the Saint John city council meeting on March 10, listened to the presentation made by the medical and dental societies and were disappointed that our elected officials were then to debate the subject and vote on the continued use of fluoridation of our water without hearing the other side.
This point was made quite clear by Coun. Ray Stowbridge. It was mentioned by Susan Fullerton and Shirley McAlary, but very little else was said that night about the fact that there are many citizens of this city who do not want to ingest these toxins.
There is well-known scientific research that has been peer reviewed proving this is a poisonous substance that even in small amounts, over time, can cause disorders such as bone disease to dementia.
I want to thank the councillors on the "Nay" side and also Mayor Mel Norton who made the deciding vote to end the use of fluoridation in our city's supply. Thank you, council, for making the right decision.
Georgette &; Paul Thom
Saint John
Trade expo looking for area companies
The Construction Association of New Brunswick has partnered with the Department of Post Secondary Education Training and Labour in an initiative aimed at providing youth with the opportunity to "try a trade."
On April 10 and 11 at the Saint John Trade and Convention Center, we will host the "Building for the Future Trades Career Expo," where 1,600 Grade 9 students in our region will attend the event. The objective is to give as many students as possible the opportunity to try their hand at a variety of apprenticeable trades in New Brunswick.
By swinging a hammer, striking an arc, or installing a switch students will be exposed to various trades, and a possible career path. We are looking for companies in our area to come forward to set up live displays and interact with the students. There is no registration fee, and all companies are welcome. If you are interested in participating in this event, please call 633-1101 or email sjcic@nb.aibn.com for more information.
Krista Collins
Construction Association of New Brunswick - Saint John Region
Health group short of funds
One of Canada's finest foreign assistance achievements is TB Reach, a grassroots health organization dedicated to help those tuberculosis sufferers that other programs miss: those who are physically isolated and difficult to treat. There are an estimated three million of these, with each untreated sufferer eventually infecting about 10 other people.
Canada is the only major funder of TB Reach. Our federal government already does great work fighting this ancient scourge through the Global Fund to Fight AIDS, TB and Malaria, but TB Reach is Canada's own gift to the world. Currently, TB reach is short about $200 million, spread over 5 years.
I sincerely hope that on March 24, World TB Day, Canada pledges to complete funding of TB Reach and saves the lives of those last 3 million.
Nathaniel Poole
Victoria, B.C.
New forestry plan lacks protesters
On the new forestry plan, where are the protesters, road blocks and burning vehicles? Where are the protesters to worry about actual drinking water that will be affected, animals that will no longer have a wintering home?
To me, the new plan will cause more environmental issues than fracking, and yet where are the protesters?
The reason this province is so poor is because people will block any industry that they truly will not learn about. Forestry has been done for generations and that is all they know. Protesters are one-sided due to the lack of learning. It is the reason that no matter how many trucks they burn or roads they block, no one will ever truly listen to them.
All we see are people draining taxpayer money and taking away jobs from a jobless province due to their stubbornness to have an open mind. The protesters have hurt themselves by not protesting this new forestry plan. They have lost all credibility and right to ever protest against the oil industry again. Why can't people can live off fresh lake fish in New Brunswick? Fracking did not poison our fish with high levels of mercury.
This province needs industry. It also needs protesters to protect us and the environment. But, there needs to be a balance and this truly shows there is none. If you protest for one, you must protest for all, and if don't protest for all, then you should protest for none.
Travis Costello
Fredericton
Animals deserve our protection
I wish some of those responsible would open their eyes and apprehend those who are doing cruel things to our wildlife. Our raccoons, skunks, foxes, etc., should have protection. It's a shame our animals are being killed.
The government will tell people there are too many deer so they allow these animals to be shot. The deer have no where to go and all they hear is the sound of guns. The government tells people don't feed the deer, but when hunting starts, hunters bait the deer by feeding them so they come to that space to be shot.
Is there anyone out there that realizes what our bears are going through? Some have arrows shot in them and must be suffering. If a mother bear dies, she leaves her babies to starve as well.
Visitors come and guides bait the poor bears so the visitor can return with a wall mount.
The government has to do something to help out animals.
Joan MacNeill
Saint John
]]></text></news-item>