<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B7D9-6795-CD9B-8854"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Pakistan: Imported urea price fixed at Rs1,786</title><source>Right Vision News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[LAHORE, March 16 -- The federal government has fixed the price of imported urea at Rs1,786 per 50kg bag to uniform the market prices after considering all the incidentals and financial cost of the imported urea, official documents revealed on Friday.
Following the fixation of the price of the imported urea, the Ministry of Industries and Production has also issued letters to all the chief secretaries to instruct the agriculture departments and district coordination officers to carry out regular price checking in the market and take serious actions against the violators in the public interest, it showed. Of the total requirement of urea fertiliser in Pakistan, 16 percent is being imported by the Trading Corporation of Pakistan (TCP) and distributed through the National Fertilizer Marketing Company (NFML).
The imported urea is then distributed to all the provinces through authorised dealers. Punjab has 70 percent share in the imported urea fertilizer followed by Sindh 20 percent, Khyber-Pakhtunkhwa seven percent and Balochistan three percent, it revealed.
Official sources said that due to gas curtailment to the fertiliser sector, plants are operating at sub-optimal level. Therefore, to bridge the demand and supply gap, urea is being imported from international market by the TCP after the approval of the ECC. The government cannot influence the fertiliser sector after its privatisation; however, to ensure affordable price to farmers, the only mechanism is the ample supply of urea in the market through imports, the officials said.
The import of deficient quantity of urea and its distribution in the market to end-users enables the government to ensure its supply at an affordable price.
The government expects that through open market intervention it will be succeeded in maintaining the price of urea at affordable level during the kharif season. The government intervention is likely to benefit the end users by at least Rs200 to Rs300 per bag in urea fertiliser price, an official of the Ministry of Industries and Production said
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Right Vision News. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>