<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B824-FB33-8DE0-9423"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Company challenges OSHA blast findings</title><source>Sun-Sentinel (Fort Lauderdale, Florida)</source><author>Stephen Hudak, Staff writer</author><text><![CDATA[Blue Rhino is challenging the findings of federal workplace investigators who accused the company of 26 safety violations after an explosion and fire at the Tavares propane depot severely burned five employees last summer.
The infractions, 20 of which were deemed "serious" by investigators with the Occupational Safety and Health Administration, included the company's failure to train workers and exposing them to fire and explosion hazards during the process of refurbishing and filling propane cylinders, commonly used by consumers to fuel backyard barbecue grills.
State fire investigators think a sparking forklift ignited a cloud of propane in a storage yard about 10 p.m. July 29, touching off a blast felt a mile away. Leaping flames could be seen as far away as Mount Dora as the gas-fed blaze cast an orange glow across the night sky.
Five employees were hospitalized for months with severe burns. One of the workers awoke from a coma a month after the accident.
An injured employee told investigators that workers manually drained propane from customer-returned cylinders, allowing the gas to seep into the air, because a machine used to suck out and capture the gas had not worked properly for a year. The company denied the worker's claim.
The depot, on County Road 448 in Tavares, resumed operations in December before the OSHA findings were released and before the State Fire Marshal's Office completed its investigation. The state Bureau of Liquefied Petroleum (LP) Gas Inspection also investigated the accident but has not released its report.
OSHA spokesman Dustin A. Cavanaugh on Thursday said a hearing date has not been set for appeals by Blue Rhino or by Custom Driven Staffing, the temporary-employment agency that provided the Tavares depot with many workers. OSHA cited the staffing company for failing to review Blue Rhino's emergency-action plan with employees assigned to the job and failing to train them to handle hazardous chemicals.
"Currently, the status of these proceedings is very preliminary," Cavanaugh said in an email.
Scott Brockelmeyer, a spokesman for Ferrellgas, Blue Rhino's parent company, confirmed the company was appealing the OSHA citations and fines, but he would not discuss the findings.
"We believe any further public comments regarding this ongoing matter would be disrespectful to OSHA and we prefer to let the appeals process run its course before commenting further," he said in an email.
A call seeking comment from Custom Driven Staffing was not returned.
The explosion and fire caused $3.5 million in damage at the plant and unnerved its neighbors as hundreds of 20-pound propane cylinders rocketed from the storage yard.
]]></text></news-item>