<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B828-14B2-97D4-871E"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Two people dead and two injured in Ukraine's Kharkov clashes</title><source>Yerepouni Daily News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Two people died and two were injured in a conflict between the residents of Kharkov and militants from the Right Sector (radical Ukrainian group), Mayor of Kharkov Gennady Kernes reported today.
An Itar-Tass correspondent reports that 40-50 militants are in the building hosting the Right Sector headquarters. The police cordoned off the building, and a special operation is underway. The mayor is holding talks with radicals.
A representative of the local movement against Maidan protests told an Itar-Tass correspondent earlier today that clashes were underway between Kharkov residents and militants reportedly from western Ukraine on Rymarskaya Street (in downtown Kharkov).
The activist said Kharkov defenders were standing against militants, presumably from the Right Sector, who were shooting from assault rifles. Reports also said fire was delivered and stun grenades and Molotov cocktails thrown from the windows of the building hosting the Right Sector headquarters.
Maidan is the name for downtown Kiev's Independence Square, which is the symbol of Ukrainian protests. The word "Maidan" is also used as a collective name for anti-government protests in Ukraine.
Right Sector activists were reportedly involved in clashes with police in Ukraine's anti-government protests that started in November 2013 when the country's authorities refused to sign an association agreement with the European Union in favor of closer ties with Russia.
The Ukrainian protests led to a coup in the country in February. President Viktor Yanukovich had to leave Ukraine citing security concerns. Yanukovich told reporters in south Russia on Tuesday that he remained the legitimate Ukrainian president despite "an anti-constitutional seizure of power by armed radicals.
Clashes erupt in Ukraine's Kharkov, 3 anti-Maidan activists injured
Clashes have occurred in the eastern Ukrainian city of Kharkov between city residents and militants reportedly from western Ukraine, a representative of the local movement against Maidan protests said.
"Clashes are underway on Rymarskaya Street [in downtown Kharkov]. Kharkov defenders are standing against militants, presumably from the Right Sector. The visitors are shooting from assault rifles," the activist told an Itar-Tass correspondent.
Fire is delivered from the windows of a building hosting the headquarters of the Right Sector radical organization. Stun grenades and Molotov cocktails are being thrown from the second floor of the building. Three people from among anti-Maidan activists are reported to have been injured.
Donetsk clashes: 22-year-old victim identified, 28 injured
One person was killed and 28 injured in a clash between participants of a pro-Russia rally and the For United Ukraine protesters on Lenin Square in Donetsk on Thursday night, the health department of the Donetsk Regional State Administration reports. The victim was identified by local media as Dmytro Chernyavskiy, an activist with the local branch of the Svoboda nationalist party.
Two victims were provided with medical assistance on the scene, they later chose to go home. Two others were transported to a regional accident hospital, one was brought to municipal hospital No.17, 11 people now remain in the neurosurgery department of the Kalinin hospital. One person was killed, a male resident of Donetsk who died in an ambulance from knife wounds. 22-year-old Dmitry Cherniavsky was an activist and former spokesman for the Donetsk regional organization Svoboda.
The acting President of Ukraine, Chairman of the Verkhovna Rada Aleksandr Turchynov gave the Interior Ministry an urgent order to immediately arrest and punish those responsible for the murder and inflicting bodily injuries in Donetsk on March 13.
Crisis in Ukraine: one killed in Donetsk in clashes between rival rallies
A 22-year old citizen of the Ukrainian city of Donetsk was killed in clashes that erupted between Maidan protesters armed with batons and peaceful demonstrators chanting pro-Russian slogans. More than a dozen were injured as violence ensued after participants broke through a police barrier in the centre of the city. Tensions swelled in the Ukrainian industrial center of Donetsk on Thursday, where the Russian-speaking population has been rallying in support of creating an eastern Ukrainian autonomy and against the decisions of the controversialy appointed caretaker government in Kiev.
According to hospital sources the 22-year-old man was stabbed. News media reports, the man was just a passerby who didn't participate in demonstrations. This is the first death reported outside the capital during the recent violence triggered by the political crisis in Ukraine.
It was unclear who started the clashes, as protesters broke through a police cordon keeping the two sides apart.
According to local media reports pro-Maidan activists started provoking the pro-Russian crowd, by shouting far-right slogans "Glory to Ukraine" and "Glory to heroes", loudly demanding respect for Ukrainian territorial sovereignty.
"According to preliminary conclusions by doctors, a man has been stabbed," the local branch of Ukraine's health ministry said, as regional authorities spoke of 17 wounded in the clashes.
Donetsk is the Ukrainian industrial center. A rally of Ukraine's integrity supporters was taking place in the city at the same time and place as the anti-government protest.
According to the newspaper Novosti Donbassa ("The News of Donbass City"), three people were taken to a hospital neurosurgery department after the clashes. The 22-year-old male died in the ambulance. Seventeen people were administered first aid on the scene, and 11 were taken to intensive care at a local hospital, according to the newspaper.
Authorities in Donetsk are requesting a referendum to widen the eastern industrial region's autonomy. Donetsk has a large Russian-speaking population.
Euromaidan protestors start fight with pro-Russia activists in Donetsk
Euromaidan protestors started a fight with pro-Russia activists during their mass-meeting in Donetsk. A peaceful mass-meeting turned into a clash, that was hardly controlled by Ukrainian law enforcers.
Euromaidan protestors suddenly appeared, witnesses say. In the very beginning they behaved calmly, but then began to throw petards.
Police tried to arrest several pro-Russian activists, but had to set them free due to the crowd's pressure.
The police is trying to establish order, but pressure from the part of provokers is growing. The latter throw stones and steel bars. Someone urges to turn over the busses, where the police keep arrested people. The activists reached the buss with arrested people and called upon the police to set these people free. The police reinforced a defensive formation around the buss, but they can hardly contain the activists.
There is no medical staff on the square, LifeNews journalists says. Wounded people can't get any medical aid. People use gas sprays. The number of wounded people is unknown.
Ambulances have just arrived at the square. Activists begin to leave the place. There is no threat of serious disorders.
Members of two mass-meetings - the Euromaidan supporters and pro-Russian activists gathered on the Lenin Square in Donetsk. Pro-Russian activists claim
]]></text></news-item>