<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B85B-2903-7F12-9426"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Consumer rights need further work</title><source>China Daily</source><author>Li Yang</author><text><![CDATA[What companies will be featured on China's national television network on Saturday when it airs 3.15 Evening, an annual muckraking program for World Consumer Rights Day?
After targeting Volkswagen, Apple Inc, Carrefour SA, Toyota Motor Corp and The McDonald's Corp in the past three years for allegedly treating Chinese customers differently from those in other countries, State-owned broadcaster China Central Television came in for some criticism itself for double standards toward Chinese and foreign companies.
"You can surely criticize Apple. But you shouldn't be blind to the markedly more defective products made by Chinese companies, which are much easier to find", wrote Li Chengpeng, a famous Chinese blogger.
CCTV ran its first 3.15 Evening in 1991. The program, featuring a range of government officials, was an immediate success, because it exposed actual cases of shoddy products and told people how to defend their rights.
That was before China had its first law on consumer rights.
Businesses exposed on the program were invariably investigated and penalized.
Yet, after CCTV began to focus heavily on popular foreign brands starting in 2010, with strong support from quality and market regulators, some Chinese consumers became skeptical of CCTV itself, as well as other media outlets.
CCTV pocketed at least 16 billion yuan ($2.67 billion) in ad revenue last year, the largest figure among all media in China.
Other media outlets have reported that many companies increase their ad spending on CCTV ahead of the annual program "to avoid trouble," as some put it.
That allegation has been supported by some production staff involved in 3.15 Evening. Moreover, as the Internet expanded in China, a host of websites emerged offering to help companies delete negative posts about their operations or products.
Some of those posts are actual consumer complaints. Others are fabricated criticisms planted by competitors. The media actually can play a positive role in addressing consumer issues in some new areas, such as e-commerce and online finance services, which aren't fully covered by current laws.
Consumer culture
China's former planned economy, based on a strict rationing system, meant that Chinese people had no idea of consumerism, much less consumer rights.
There was nothing much to buy-indeed, buying and selling were mostly illegal. It was only when reform and opening-up began in the late 1970s that the concept of consumption emerged.
Material shortages in the 1980s exacerbated Chinese citizens' longing for "stuff", under any conditions.
Many people now in their 60s and 70s recall the 1980s as an era where "no rights existed in our awareness, except that of possessing," as one retiree put it.
A Chinese consumers' association was established in 1983, and the global consumer rights day began to be observed in 1985.
Yet, Chinese didn't form a deep sense of consumer rights until the early 1990s, when there was a wave of faulty and defective products, some of which caused injuries and deaths, and deceptive and misleading ads.
That was the era in which CCTV's annual muckraking program was born.
The first consumer rights law only came into being in 1994, and even then, it still wasn't easy for citizens to seek redress against companies providing shoddy or dangerous goods.
The plight of consumers provided great fodder for the media to frame itself as a defender of the public interest.
China revised the law in late 2013, making it easier for consumers to defend their rights and more expensive for businesses to break the law.
But even now, Chinese consumers don't see the law as their first choice in disputes with companies.
According to a survey by Beijing Youth Daily, only 5.2 percent of respondents said they would sue companies directly. The rest said they'd negotiate with dealers and producers, because the legal process is too lengthy and expensive.
Longstanding scandal
Although Chinese people became increasingly aware of their rights as consumers in the 1990s, the government seemed unenlightened until a scandal emerged in 2008 involving infant formula powder.
After thousands of infants across the nation were diagnosed with kidney problems, which killed some of them, a Shanghai-based financial journalist uncovered an industrial secret: many domestic dairy producers were putting melamine, an inedible industrial chemical, into milk to raise the apparent protein content.
An investigation found that many major domestic dairy companies had been doing this for a long time. The domestic dairy sector has yet to recover fully from that scandal.
The incident also led many Chinese consumers to become better informed about food product standards, quality inspections and the nature of trade associations.
China's standards for many products were outdated or markedly lower than those of developed countries.
Consumers also discovered that quality inspectors and supervisory agencies were keener to make money from issuing quality exemption certificates to "famous brands" and conducting symbolic examinations of samples, than in doing spot checks in the market.
And that doesn't even take into account the vast number of informal markets in the hinterlands, which are filled with defective and shoddy products rejected by urban retailers and consumers.
There are no strict accountability systems for government regulators. When individual consumers post concerns online about the safety of specific food items, their comments are likely to be classified as rumors. And when inspectors are found to have failed in their duties, few face any serious penalties.
Even in the melamine scandal, only some local government officials and inspection departments' heads in Shijiazhuang, capital of Hebei province, were sacked. Many of the officials involved turned up in other government posts.
Meanwhile, Sanlu Group Co Ltd, which became a scapegoat for the dairy industry, faced tougher penalties. Managers, factory directors and even some workers went to jail. The 50-year-old local brand was merged into a Beijing dairy company soon.
The message was clear: regulators won't be punished, and if there are many violators, only one will be punished as a symbolic gesture.
Meanwhile, dairy industry associations, sponsored by the big brands, have never even tried to hide their loyalty and support for the offending dairy companies.
One sign of progress since 2008 is that Chinese governments at various levels attach more importance to updating domestic standards for products in many fields and urging manufacturers to improve their product quality and provide better services for consumers.
Passive supervision
Although the government abolished the quality inspection exemption certificate, which was used as a shield by many holders, the system of passive supervision has been largely unchanged since 2008.
And the scandals continue to surface. From drug capsules made from chemicals intended to treat leather to "lamb" that's actually rat meat, frequent appalling food safety scandals continue to undermine public trust in the domestic food industry and weaken government credibility.
There's still another facet to the consumer rights story involving State-owned enterprises, especially in the fields of telecommunications, railway and banking.
Some "hegemony clauses" imposed by the SOEs with monopoly positions or dominant power in their industries put consumers at a disadvantage to begin with. And it's tough for consumers to win suits against these government-backed giants.
Chinese lawmakers are revising the Food Safety Law to increase the penalties for violators. These penalties could involve the death sentence for those who cause "grave" injuries with unsafe food or drugs.
On Saturday, officials will show up and deal with consumer complaints efficiently on CCTV's 3.15 Evening.
But there are 364 other days in the year, when consumer rights won't have such a high profile. Only when there's a strict system of accountability for supervisory departments will consumers begin to gain their proper rights.
Timeline
Significant people and dates
1995
Wang Hai, the first professional businessman involved in cracking down on counterfeit products.
The 22-year-old from Shandong bought shoddy products in Beijing on purpose and then reported them to business administrations, claiming compensation of twice the price he paid from the dealers, in accordance with the law. This has been a source of income for him.
1995
Jia Guoyu, the first person to receive damages for mental anguish in a case involving consumers' rights. The girl in her 20s was disfigured in a fire caused by a badly made gas stove in a restaurant where she was dining in Beijing in 1995. In 1997 the court ordered the stove producer to compensate her to the tune of 170,000 yuan ($27,720) for medical treatment and 100,000 yuan for mental distress.
1997
Wang Ying, the first person to formally request that makers of liquor should indicate that excessive drinking is harmful to health. The middle school teacher grieved deeply over her husband's death, which was caused by drinking too much. Although the court dismissed her appeal, she has not stopped trying to persuade the administration to make it a mandatory practice for liquor-makers that warnings should be put on bottles of liquor.
2000
Huang Guoqing, whose appeal started a system to recall faulty automobiles in the country
The driver from Ningxia Hui autonomous region found a leak in the brake-oil pipe caused by poor design of the Mitsubishi off-road vehicle caused fatal brake failures in 2000. In 2004, China launched its automobile recall system.
2005
Pang Biao, the first person to demand the highway administration return his toll.
The lawyer from Beijing paid a 25 yuan toll to drive 70 kilometers along the highway from Beijing to Tianjin in 2005. However, traffic congestion caused by an accident delayed his trip by two hours. He demanded the toll office should return 12.5 yuan of the toll fee. Although the court rejected his appeal, Pang said his complaint was worthwhile because it raised the public's awareness.
2006
Huang Jing, the first person to request punitive fines to be imposed on enterprises. The 20-year-old junior student at a college in Beijing found her laptop froze twice on the day she bought it. The company repaired her laptop several times. Huang found the original central processing unit of the computer was replaced by a sample CPU used to test computers. She demanded $5 million in punitive fines from the company. The court rejected her appeal.
Fake and substandard food and medicine being destroyed in Beijing on Friday on the eve of World Consumer Rights Day. In 2013,the China Consumers' Association handled 550,000 complaints from consumers and resolved 93 percent of them. Cao Boyuan / China Daily
(China Daily 03/15/2014 page10)
]]></text></news-item>