<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B883-D202-3A73-0607"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>u.s. to give up role in overseeing domain names</title><source>The Virginian-Pilot(Norfolk, VA.)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[By Edward Wyatt
The New York Times
WASHINGTON
The United States will give up its role overseeing the system of Web addresses and domain names that form the basic plumbing of the Internet, turning it over in 2015 to an international group whose structure and administration will be determined during the next year, government officials said Friday.
Since the dawn of the Internet, the United States has been responsible for assigning the numbers that form Internet addresses, the .com, .gov and .org labels that correspond to those numbers, and for the vast database that links the two and makes sure Internet traffic goes to the right place.
The function has been subcontracted since 1998 to the Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers, an international nonprofit organization, with the expectation that the United States would eventually step back from its role.
But that transition has taken on a new urgency in the past year because of revelations that the U.S. intelligence community has been intercepting Internet traffic as part of its global spying efforts.
While other countries have called for the United States to turn over the keys to the system, many businesses, dependent on the smooth functioning of the Internet for their livelihoods, have expressed concern about what form the new organization will take.
"We don't want to break the Internet," said Laura DeNardis, a professor at American University and author of "The Global War for Internet Governance."
For consumers who use the Internet to stream movies or send email, nothing will change, if everything goes according to plan.
"We want to carefully transition to something that doesn't just give the power to one stakeholder, but that takes into account the interests of private industry, of large users of the Internet, of the purchasers of domain names, of governments and of civil society," DeNardis said.
Lawrence E. Strickling, the assistant secretary of commerce for communications and information, said Friday the U.S. will not accept a proposal that replaces it with a government-led or intergovernmental organization.
]]></text></news-item>