<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B885-D67A-41E3-DB0C"><date>2014-03-14</date><title></title><source>South Jersey Times (New Jersey)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[To the Editor:
At one time, the United States was the most admired and most respected country in the world. Those days are long gone.
We are so divided as a country that a large segment of our citizens have been led to believe we would be better served with former KGB operative and Russian President Vladimir Putin running our country.
It's as if the right wing has a severe man-crush on our geo-political foe. With former U.S. Sen. Joe Lieberman gone, they've still got two of the three foreign policy Senate stooges, John McCain, R-Ariz., and Lindsey Graham, R-S.C., leading the yahoo chorus.
Yet, we are at a point in time where we can make some inroads into the mistrust and downward spiral of our national reputation. The new dust-up involving claims that the CIA spied domestically on the Senate Intelligence Committee has reopened the door for the country and President Barack Obama to confront a large part of why our nation is so disrespected.
An investigation into the destroyed tapes of interrogations of terrorist suspects done by the CIA under the George W. Bush administration was started in 2009 by the intelligence committee. The investigation was stonewalled by the CIA. The Obama administration then exonerated the officials who destroyed the tapes, effectively sweeping the whole record into the annals of history until the other day.
Obama must declassify the Senate investigation into these torture interrogations and bring about some accountability for those responsible. That would be some atonement for those transgressions and would restore some respect for our country.
The president just telling us in 2009 that he had ended the intelligence program established under Bush is not sufficient, and never has been. We are not a banana republic.
If the president fails to take action on this, he will be remembered as the constitutional law professor who refused to bring war criminals and banker criminals to justice.
Roy Lehman
Woolwich Township
Water quality concerns put South Jersey at risk
To the Editor:
"Location! Location! Location!" is a real estate axiom that describes the most important three factors when purchasing a home. In South Jersey, that saying may be replaced by "Water! Water! Water!"
Would you buy a house and raise your family in a town that has a contaminated water supply? There are class-action lawsuits in Paulsboro centering on that issue, because of alleged contamination by Solvay Specialty Polymers in neighboring West Deptford.
Is Logan Township the next Paulsboro?
The Delaware Riverkeeper Network is suing Soil Safe Inc., which has a soil recycling and dredged material site in Logan, for contributing to "imminent and substantial endangerment" to the environment for its storage, handling, treatment and disposal of contaminated soil.
According to the federal lawsuit, Gloucester County's DREAM equestrian park, also in Logan, has received the Soil Safe material almost daily as dirt for riding trails for up to five years. It is alleged to contain petroleum, arsenic, lead and other heavy metals, and PCBs. This is a long time to allow these chemicals to seep into our groundwater.
Gloucester County officials who agreed to this arrangement should provide free water well tests to all property owners in the vicinity of the DREAM Park.
The public deserves to know exactly which sites received this material, and if Gloucester County employees who handled it on a daily basis were provided with proper safety training and gear.
It didn't take long for the lawyers to file class-action suits in Paulsboro. Will Logan be their next destination?
Carol Rhodes
Barnsboro
]]></text></news-item>