<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B961-0550-A967-83A1"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Must unit owner put up with patter of little feet?</title><source>Chicago Tribune</source><author>Howard Dakoff</author><text><![CDATA[Q: We live in a small condominium association, and the unit above us has three children under 6 years old living with their parents.
In the early morning and throughout the afternoon and evening, the children are running and stomping, causing unreasonable noise and vibrations in our unit. Sometimes it feels like the ceiling will come down.
When we approached the unit owner, he told us to use earplugs, and the management company refuses to take any action. What can we do?
A: When living in a community association, homeowners will be subjected to noises and sounds they would not otherwise be subjected to if they lived in a single-family home. However, all declarations and bylaws contain provisions prohibiting noxious or offensive activities from occurring in a unit. The board of directors may levy fines for violations of this prohibition, and the board may even file a lawsuit seeking an injunction to prohibit such conduct if it does not stop upon demand.
The issue is how to apply such a provision to the facts. The board should use a subjective, and objective, standard. This means that not only must the complaining unit owner subjectively feel there is a nuisance, but the nuisance should be verified as being objectively unreasonable.
Small children will create noise when living and playing in a condominium unit. However, just as a stereo being played too loud in a unit may rise to the level of a noxious activity, excessive running and jumping in a unit may give rise to a noxious activity. It is fact-specific.
In such cases, the complaining unit owner should submit written complaints to the managing agent and board, requesting action to abate violations of the noxious-activities prohibition. The board may first discuss possible solutions with the parties for the noise issues, but ultimately, the board may levy fines or file a lawsuit if the unit owner refuses to take reasonable measures to mitigate unreasonable noise.
Q: I live in a small self-managed condominium association. The unit owners have recently learned that the board of directors has elected to give themselves a 60 perce nt discount off their monthly assessments as compensation for their time spent serving as board members. Is this allowed? Will the board members have to pay the association back?
A: Condominium directors serve on the board without compensation unless the declaration and bylaws allow for compensation to be paid to board members. Section 18(o) of the Condominium Act prevents a condominium board from forbearing assessments.
This means no unit owner or board member may be given a discount off their monthly assessments for any reason. Those board members who self-servingly gave themselves a 60 percent discount off their monthly assessments are liable to pay back all unpaid condominium assessments, and future boards should visit that issue.
Q: Two board members in our condominium association have recently married. The wife has moved into her husband's unit, and her unit is for sale. Is it legal for both of them to continue serving on the board?
A: Any unit owner may serve on a condominium board, but only one individual per unit is entitled to serve on the board representing a particular unit.
If a husband and wife owns only one unit, only one of them may serve on the board. On the other hand, as long as a husband and wife own two or more units, each may serve on the board because each will represent different units.
ctc-realestate@tribune.com ct14 0254 140316 N S 0000000000 00002868
]]></text></news-item>