<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="B969-A05D-355B-3B50"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Parisians told to leave the car as pollution hits deadly levels; Public transport is made free in bid to reduce traffic after dangerous cloud settles over city</title><source>The Independent (London)</source><author>JOHN LICHFIELD IN PARIS</author><text><![CDATA[Half the diesel and petrol cars in greater Paris will be banned from the roads of the French capital today in an attempt to reduce the health-threatening cloud of polluted air which has settled on northern France.
From 5am, only odd-numbered cars will be allowed to drive in the ??le-de-France region, in which Paris sits, unless they have electric or hybrid motors. Taxis, buses, emergency vehicles and cars carrying three people or more are exempted. All trucks are banned.
The restrictions will apply to even-numbered cars on Tuesday, unless the weather changes. Foreign vehicles must also obey the rules.
Since last Wednesday, a run of warm, windless days and cold clear nights has kept a lid of warm air over northern France. Minuscule particles of pollution from car exhausts, industry and agriculture have accumulated under that lid to dangerous levels.
The pollution is largely invisible and certainly not the "smogs" or pea-souper fogs of the kind which existed up to the 1970s. Paris enjoyed bright sunshine throughout the weekend.
There was, in fact, almost a carnival atmosphere. All underground and suburban trains and buses were free to try to keep cars off the road. A slight breeze reduced pollution on Saturday and Sunday.
Nonetheless, the level of official "pollution alert" - 80 microgrammes of tiny particles for every cubic metre of air - is likely to be exceeded again tomorrow as the wind drops. The government decided on Saturday night to impose regulations, which have not been triggered since 1997, on "alternate" use of cars.
Motorists' organisations complained that this was an overreaction and would cause enormous hardship to commuters. The government said that it had no choice.
Marisol Touraine, the French Health Minister, said: "Pollution is a public health issue. We were obliged to take tough action."
France is especially vulnerable to this kind of pollution because it is 60 per cent dependent on diesel cars. In the 1960s, France made a strategic decision that diesel engines were less polluting and would gradually supercede petrol.
The French car giants Renault and Peugeot Citroën invested heavily in diesel engines and diesel fuel was taxed less heavily than petrol. It still is.
For nearly two decades, France has been aware that this was a mistake. Diesel engines are, in fact, more polluting, not less. Fumes from diesel cars, as well as industrial emissions and agricultural fertilisers, are blamed for increasing the micro-particles in the French atmosphere to dangerous levels.
Successive governments have shied away from increasing taxes on the diesel fuel which is used by two out of three motorists, and therefore voters.
According to one study, there are 40,000 premature or unnecessary deaths in France each year because of the high level of atmospheric pollution. Other experts insist the scare has been exaggerated.
A French lung specialist, Professor Jean-Philippe Derenne, said: "In 50 years, I have never come across anyone who died from air pollution. Between those people who smoke two packets of cigarettes a day and those people who walk in the streets of Paris, there is not the beginnings of a comparison."
]]></text></news-item>