<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BA68-67D1-3099-585B"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Crosswalk signs proposed on West Street in Keene</title><source>The Keene Sentinel, N.H.</source><author>Ella Nilsen, The Keene Sentinel, N.H.</author><text><![CDATA[March 15--Signs and warnings could be going up near West Street crosswalks in Keene in an attempt to slow drivers.
The signs are planned in front of four crosswalks on West Street: one just west of Federal Street, two on either side of St. James Street and one angular crosswalk from a parking area next to NGM Insurance Co. at 55 West St. to the St. George Greek Orthodox Church lot at 70 West St.
The unanimous recommendation came at this week's City Council Municipal Services, Facilities and Infrastructure Committee and next heads to the City Council.
NGM's parent company, the Main Street America Group, submitted a letter to the city complaining of unsafe pedestrian crossing on West Street.
"There's a number of people saying they've had near-misses or been brushed by cars," said committee Chairman James P. Duffy. "We're trying to figure out how often that's happening, because there's no data there."
In a letter, Kendera O'Neill, facilities supervisor for the company's Keene office, said, "We have a public safety concern for not only our almost 400 employees, but also for any pedestrians that attempt to cross the street between our National Grange Mutual Building and the Greek Orthodox Church.
"We have not only received many complaints from our employees in regards to them almost being hit by a fast moving vehicle or distracted driver, but I have also heard that some employees have in fact been hit by vehicles," O'Neill's letter continued. "We even had one fatality in the past."
Duffy said he believes the fatality occurred in the 1980s, and in response, the city installed a crosswalk.
He also said drivers failing to slow for pedestrians or not seeing them is something he's noticed.
"It's a problem," he said. "I live downtown and I use those crosswalks sometimes going back and forth to work. We're hoping this will alert pedestrians and drivers alike to slow down."
In her letter, O'Neill also said NGM has been putting its own caution signs in the crosswalks, but she said the signs don't seem to help the problem.
"Furthermore, we take these signs in at the end of the business day, which does not help ensure the safety (of) our many employees that stay late, come in early or work on weekends," she said.
Keene Public Works Director Kurt D. Blomquist said his department would install "stop" bars painted across the road and signs telling cars to stop for pedestrians in front of the four West Street crosswalks. The signs would encourage vehicles to slow down and stop 6 to 8 feet away from the crosswalks.
"These signs are going to be 3-feet-by-3-feet, so they're in no way small," Duffy said.
If there is room on the sidewalks, Blomquist said he hopes the department will also be able to install "look left" signs similar to the ones on Main Street to remind pedestrians to check for cars before they cross a street.
Duffy said he hoped to see the signs up by next month, and said that in one year, the committee would reassess the situation to see if the measures have worked.
But he said other changes could be coming to West Street in the next few years that could alter the flow of pedestrians, including library renovations or potentially a parking garage.
"We want to look at all of that," Duffy said. "Hopefully this will make a difference."
___ (c)2014 The Keene Sentinel (Keene, N.H.) Visit The Keene Sentinel (Keene, N.H.) at www.sentinelsource.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>