<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BB08-0806-9417-72B5"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>ZERO HOURS CONTRACTS CONSULTATION CLOSES WITH OVER 30,000 RESPONSES</title><source>UK Government News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[LONDON, March 15 -- The Department for Business, Innovation and Skills issued the following press release:
The government's consultation on zero hours contracts has now closed, having received more than 30,000 responses.
The 12 week consultation was launched in late December 2013 (visit: https://www.gov.uk/government/news/ministers-to-consider-outlawing-exclusivity-on-zero-hours-contracts) by Business Secretary Vince Cable, following a review of evidence on the extent of the use of zero hours contracts conducted last summer (2013).
The consultation focused on 2 key issues that were raised in the summer review: exclusivity in employment contracts and lack of transparency for employees.
We recognise that a growing number of employers and individuals are using zero hours contracts. The latest ONS at http://www.ons.gov.uk/ons/about-ons/index.html estimates put these at 580,000, but we expect further detailed estimates soon. These contracts are 1 of the flexible arrangements that give individuals more choice to combine their work with other commitments. But it was also clear from the review BIS conducted over the summer that there was some abuse. The government has always been clear that we will crack down on any exploitation of individuals in the workplace and this consultation is the first step in that process.
Commenting on the consultation, Business Secretary Vince Cable said:
It is clear that a growing number of people are using zero hours contracts. While for some they offer welcome flexibility to accommodate childcare or top up monthly earnings, for others it is clear that there has also been abuse around this type of employment, which can offer more limited employment rights and job security.
We believe they can have a place in today's labour market and are not proposing to ban them outright, but we also want to make sure that people are getting a fair deal.
This is why we conducted research last summer (2013) and launched a consultation looking at the key concerns, such as exclusivity clauses and the availability of clear information. We don't think that people should be tied exclusively to 1 employer if it unfairly stops them from boosting their income when they are not getting enough work to earn a living. We also want to give employees and employers more guidance and advice on their rights and responsibilities around these types of employment contracts.
The consultation received a high level of interest, with over 30,000 responses. We will publish our response to the consultation in due course. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>