<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BBC3-2A92-370E-36D1"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Civic body to conduct 2-day drive to clean Rankala lake</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Kolhapur: The Kolhapur Municipal Corporation (KMC) will conduct a two-day drive to clean up the Rankala Lake and surrounding areas from Tuesday.
Around 2,000 KMC workers have been employed for the clean-up.
The lake was surrounded by filth and garbage and sewage had also clogged the river at several places. The blue-green algae floating over the lake water will be removed with the help of suction pumps.
Mayor Sunita Raut said, "The historical lake is one of the most important natural heritage sites of the city. It has been polluted for the last few years and needs a special drive to clean the lake and adjoining areas. Around 2,000 employees with the necessary instruments and vehicles will be deployed for the work. We will appeal to citizens and social organizations through awareness programmes to participate in the drive."
The civic administration is making efforts to stop the sewage from entering the lake water from areas such as Sarnaik Vasahat, Shyam Society and Partala. The continuous sewage discharge has led to growth of toxic bacteria and death of the flora and fauna in the lake.
"The work of the laying the underground drainage pipeline is in its last stages. Civic officials have pledged to complete the work in 15 days. If the work is completed, then it will solve the issue of lake pollution forever," Raut added.
The civic administration has started removing of the sediments from the Irani Quarry accumulated due to the Ganesh idols' immersion during last year's festivities and cleaning of the nearby areas on Saturday. Around 200 odd idols, more than 15-feet high, were immersed in the quarry on immersion day.
Sanjay Herwade, the KMC deputy commissioner said, "The immersed material was found floating on the quarry a few days ago. Also, residents near the quarry complained about the filthy atmosphere. We deployed 40 workers, 2 earth movers and 2 dumpers to remove the sediment. The work will be completed in two to three days. The remover sediment will be disposed in a dumping site at Kasaba Bawda."
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>