<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BC08-2B3B-A409-0321"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>In the church, rows of skulls are set out on wooden shelves… a grisly memorial to the 5,000 who were slaughtered in this village.; But now the killers and the survivors of the country's bloody ethnic massacres are living side by side again… and learning to forgive 20 YEARS AFTER GENOCIDE, ITN'S MARK AUSTIN GOES BACK TO RWANDA EXCLUSIVE</title><source>Daily Mirror</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[I REMEMBER it as if it were yesterday. That day 20 years ago when I came across the most appalling scene I have ever witnessed.
The village church in Ntarama stands in a pretty glade on a gentle hillside about 40 minutes drive from the Rwandan capital, Kigali.
On the day in question, from a distance, it was a picture of sunlit serenity.
But then we got close. My cameraman and I had been warned by the few villagers left in Ntarama that there had been a massacre there. But nothing could adequately prepare us.
It was the stench that hit us first. It was overwhelming. Then we saw the brightly coloured clothing scattered outside.
And then the bodies.
The hacked bodies of mainly women and children, cut down and killed as they tried to flee. This was the Rwandan genocide, in all its hideous horror.
We moved towards the doorway, tentatively, fearing the scene that would confront us.
It was dreadful. You couldn't even see the floor of the church, or the wooden pews, for the bloodsoaked clothing and the dead.
So many bodies sprawled grotesquely throughout the church. We filmed for a few minutes and then we left, scarcely believing what we had seen.
It's believed 300 people died in the church. In all, 5,000 were killed in the village - 60 per cent of the population.
The church was supposed to be a place of sanctuary for Tutsi families sheltering in fear of the Hutu militias roaming the countryside with machetes, knives, clubs and spears. In the event it offered no protection at all.
Now, 20 years on from the genocide, I have come back to Rwanda, back to the church in Ntarama.
And returning with me is 55-year-olImmaculate Mukanyaraya, who was caught up in the killing that day but who somehow managed to survive.
SHOCKING
Walking through the door, we are greeted with a sight almost as shocking now as it was then.
Inside, set out neatly on wooden shelves, are the skulls and other bones of those who died. Tiny skulls, cracked skulls, skulls with rusty nails and spear tips in them.
And the clothes are still there, and the discarded shoes and the unrepaired damage to bloodied walls and windows. And coffins are laid out across the pews.
It is now a memorial to the dead, a macabre but effective reminder of what happened here. And it is only one of many similar shrines across Rwanda.
The killing was on such a scale that few villages, few families, were unaffected.
Inside Ntarama church, Immaculate wipes tears from her eyes and tells me her memories of the day.
She tells me how the Hutu attackers, many of whom she recognised as her neighbours, first threw crude grenades and then came in slashing everyone with machetes and scythes.
They were like animals, she says, and they showed no mercy to anyone. Not to women, not to children, not even to babies.
She was eight months pregnant, but she managed to squeeze through a window and flee.
Three of her children managed to escape too but her husband, three brothers, four sisters and nine cousins were all slaughtered.
Immaculate and her children hid in a nearby swamp for more than three weeks. She gave birth to a baby daughter here, using a reed to cut the umbilical cord.
"They killed so many of us Tutsis in churches that we thought maybe God does not think of us as wandans, does not think of us as people," she said.
But I have returned to Rwanda less to hear the story of then, than the story of now.
And what has happened in the last few years is in many ways remarkable, because under way here is an unprecedented experiment in reconciliation involving the entire country.
During those three awful months 20 years ago, 800,000 people were killed in 100 days - nearly 15 per cent of the population. More than six men, women and children were murdered every minute of every hour of every day. How can a small country even begin to recover from that?
The process of recovery began with a controversial system of justice. Six months after the genocide, in late 1994, we filmed in Kigali's central prison, packed with thousands of suspected killers or genocidaire.
A few years later 150,000 accused were still crammed in jails across the country.
They didn't have enough judges, lawyers or courts to put the killers on trial so they faced the prospect of keeping them locked up without hearings or freeing them without them accounting for their crimes. President Paul Kagame decided the answer lay in special village courts or 'gacacas' where sentences depended on confessions and atonement.
Millions of pages of evidence from the courts now sit in a Kigali warehouse, representing the most complete history of the genocide. Only the ringleaders or most prolific killers were dealt with by the normal criminal justice system. But the most extraordinary stage of Rwanda's reconciliation process was to follow.
EVIDENCE
It involved thousands of survivors accepting that those who murdered their families would leave prison to live again in their midst - sometimes in the same village as neighbours.
All over the country killer and survivor are once again living side by side, with the Government's encouragement or even, in some cases, at its insistence.
The man leading the drive towards national reconciliation is Bishop John Rucyahana, whose own niece was gang raped and killed during the genocide.
"I have forgiven those who killed her," he told me. "Now we need others to forgive. Where there is repentance there should be forgiveness. It is very hard to do but our future depends on it. It is not enough just to manage the hatred and the desire for revenge, we have to deal with it."
He walks me around one of several "reconciliation villages" dotted around the country. I meet Abdul Jajyambere and Chantal Mutuyimana. He was part of the Hutu militia who murdered scores of Tutsis. Her cousins and in-laws were among the victims. Yet now they are living virtually side by side.
"I have repented and was given a Presidential pardon," he told me. "And now I help Chantal and there is no problem."
Chantal says: "I have forgiven him. He helps water my cows and our children play together."
It is too early to say if it will work, but it is not an exaggeration to say that President Kagame is staking his country's future on the project.
Among those I spoke to there is a will to see it succeed, but you only have to scratch beneath the surface to realise Rwanda remains a country of suspicion and fear.
How could it be otherwise?
President Kagame remains popular within Rwanda but faces criticism from outside that he's using the legacy of the genocide to impose a Tutsi-dominated authoritarian regime on the country.
His retort is to say he will take no lessons on human rights from western countries who failed to intervene to stop the killing in 1994.
Immaculate agrees with him. "When the killing began there was no one to rescue us," she says. "Even the foreigners, the white people, didn't think about coming to the rescue of Rwanda. They just forgot about us."
RECONCILIATION
Immaculate is part of the reconciliation process. Working in a soap-making co-operative with the wives of convicted killers, she says she can forgive, but will never forget.
And remembering may be the best way to ensure it doesn't happen again.
It seems to me the best hope for Rwanda lies with the two-thirds of the population who are under 25.
In schools they are now encouraged to reject all notion of Hutu and Tutsi and instead find common cause in building a new Rwanda.
Economic empowerment will help and over the last few years the economy has grown by an average of around eight per cent. A million Rwandans have been lifted out of poverty.
Twenty years after its darkest days, Rwanda is embracing hope. It is a beautiful country, scarred by atrocity and, at its moment of greatest need, abandoned by the world.
As it reflects on its past, it's clear that the very least it deserves is a future.
features@sundaymirror.co.uk
Mark Austin is RTS Presenter of the Year. Watch On Assignment, Wednesday, 10.35pm, ITV.
]]></text></news-item>