<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BC14-584B-98DB-D619"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>The Sunday Interview: Declan O'Rourke</title><source>Sunday Business Post</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[CV: Declan O'Rourke
**Role:**General manager, AIG Ireland
**Age:**43
**Lives:**Kilteel, Co Kildare
**Family:**wife Liza, and five children, Tiarnan, Almha, Senan, Finnian and Lochlann
**Favourite book:**The Rascal King: The Life and Times of James Michael Curley, by Jack Beatty
.....
Insurance is not an exact science. Pricing for risk may involve the trappings of financial precision -- actuarial tables, accounting projections and premiums calculated to the penny -- but there has always been an element of guesswork in the practice. Careful estimates work well enough, though. That is, until they don't. The unforeseen outlier, the marginal risk, can sometimes blow apart even the most tightly-constructed model.
Global insurer AIG learned this the hard way in 2008, when the tiny part of its business that wrote credit default swaps (CDS) threatened to wipe out the whole company. A $187 billion bail-out from Washington averted catastrophe, but not embarrassment. The CDS operation had nothing to do with Ireland, yet AIG Ireland general manager Declan O'Rourke looks faintly ill when discussing the subject.
''September 2008 was a big shock to our system, he says. ''A small part of AIG with less than 1 per cent of revenue had nearly cost us the company. There was a lot of disquiet at the time, but our business [in Ireland] retained virtually all of our clients.
AIG Ireland actually added new business during the worst phase of that time. Two factors helped: the company's strong relationship with brokers, and a strong credit rating. AIG kept its A-rating on the strength of its property and casualty financial products, as the assets were ring-fenced from the CDS horror show. Brokers understood this and kept writing the business, helping the company trade through a difficult period. Which is not to say it was all smooth sailing, however.
''We're the market-leading writer of directors' and professional liability insurance, so the crisis hurt a lot, O'Rourke said. ''The reality is the financial crisis in Ireland hurt us [in Ireland] more than the CDS crisis did. Because we were exposed to a huge amount of solicitor negligence and fraud, issues with institutions, estate agents -- there were a lot of significant claims. You occasionally get the sting of a dying wasp now, but it's tailing off.
The idea of eliminating the unexpected is behind AIG's new push into car insurance and the broader consumer market. The company has always been a leader in insuring businesses and corporates, but the broader retail market has never been its forte in Ireland. O'Rourke admitted part of that was down to pricing - ''we've never been the cheapest - and lack of profile. AIG's new ''telematic car insurance product is supposed to help change that, though.
Under the Boxymo brand, AIG is rolling out a type of car insurance that is based not on a judgment about age, occupation and type of car, but on actual driver behaviour. The current version of the product involves fitting a black box -- similar to those used on jetliners -- to the customer's car to collect and report all the data relevant to pricing for real, rather than estimated, risk.
''You get a rating on a person's driving that's updated constantly, says O'Rourke. ''You can see how they turn corners, how they accelerate and decelerate. It all gets fed into an algorithm which gives you a driver's score.
The Big Brother aspects of the technology are obvious, but O'Rourke is quick to point out the benefits for customer as well as the insurer. The incentive structure, he says, should cut costs and prices for all concerned.
''What it will do in the long term is punish bad drivers, reward good drivers and make the roads safer, which brings costs down generally. If you're not rating people according to telematics, you're going to be selected against.
So that's the pitch: come and have a go if you think you're hard enough. It's the black box challenge. Either you're a good driver who will pay less, or a bad driver who will be quickly found out. Either way, AIG improves its customer segmentation and can offer tighter pricing with better profitability.
The technology available now is aimed mainly at high-premium young drivers, because the upfront costs are high. But AIG is piloting GPS-based plug-ins and smart phone apps for different types of drivers, too.
Women drivers are expected to be the next target market. Gender equalisation for insurance quotes has penalised women -- historically a less risky demographic -- and telematics will give them an opportunity to have their actual driving evaluated, which could restore favourable pricing on a legal and measurable basis.
Having the product is only one part of the equation. Being known in the market is the other. When your highest profile brand association is the crash of 2008, there is more than a little work to do in terms of customer perception. In the case of AIG Ireland, retail awareness of the brand has been low, mainly due to the product profile, which has traditionally been aimed at businesses, not households.
''Business people know who AIG is, says O'Rourke. ''AIG insures 98 per cent of the Fortune 500 and virtually all of the companies on the Irish Stock Exchange, but when you step down to people who are buying car insurance, they are not as aware of us.
AIG has had a lot of success with sports branding elsewhere, so a decision was made to try the same thing here. The result was a deal to sponsor Dublin GAA for the next five years -- football and hurling, men and women. Depending on how you look at it, the timing was either perfect or just wide of the goal. Dublin men's football won the all-Ireland with Vodafone on their jerseys. AIG missed that opportunity, but could yet ride the wave if it hasn't crested already. The company does have a history of picking long-term winners.
''We did market research and a lot of people knew AIG was on the Manchester United jersey and the All Blacks jersey, but when it came to actually what we did in Ireland they didn't know much about it, says O'Rourke. ''The feedback we get is that they think the brand is part of a big multinational rather than something local. Our job is to make people realise that there is more to it than that. We're hoping people can support us the way we do local sport.
This is all part of a coordinated effort by AIG to use it's global balance sheet strength to pick off profitable areas of local markets to maximise return on capital. It's less about market share in any one market than the quality of the share the company takes.
''With AIG's footprint, we'd be the first choice for major companies and that has helped our business a lot, says O'Rourke. ''If there's an earthquake in Chile or a flood in Thailand or a tornado in the US, you've got all of the business globally to balance that out. You're diversified by geography and line of business.
The plan in Ireland is to build out the consumer business, despite the lower margins available on motor cover and home lines of protection. Selectivity and segmentation are the bywords here, not saturation. AIG is advertising and cutting big sponsorship deals to achieve recognition in the market, but the company doesn't want the whole market -- just the choice bits. That comes with some hard choices in the short term, but O'Rourke is happy to avoid some of the common pitfalls of insurance, like mispricing risk and losing money in the pursuit of new business.
''We're trying to pick profitable segments, but it means we haven't grown quickly, he says. ''We've stagnated a little bit. A lot of that has been down to pricing because we haven't always been able to get down to the cheapest price. But it's better than losing money.
The insurance industry is indeed struggling in Ireland. Private motor insurance lost EUR 63 million in 2012, the last year for which statistics are available. There was a profit of EUR 46 million in 2011, but a loss of EUR 96 million in 2010. None of those numbers include the inevitable adjustments arising from last year's discovery that RSA Insurance Ireland had misstated its accounts by £200 million, giving a completely false impression of profit and loss in its rapidly growing business.
What O'Rourke calls ''recession behaviours are becoming a factor again in relations between insurers and their customers. A feature of RSA's troubles was a steep rise in bodily injury claims that led to under-reserving (along with the shenanigans relating to premium and claims timing). The phenomenon is not limited to RSA, though.
''It improved a lot over the last 10 years, but recently we're starting to see suspicious activity we haven't seen in a while, says O'Rourke. ''We're seeing more opportunistic claims in the last 18 months. You can challenge the claims, but they go through the courts or the injuries board. There's a reality that it's just going to cost you more.
It's a worrying development for AIG, which prides itself on its customer service. O'Rourke says 95 per cent of customer complaints are resolved by the company. Of those that go to the Financial Services Ombudsman, few are upheld. It's a tricky balance all the same to protect the balance sheet while also building a retail brand. The market can be unforgiving.
''You still have to make sure you're at the right price and still have to make sure you're reserved properly, O'Rourke insists, with reference to RSA's consumer-friendly 123.ie brand. ''I can only speak for ourselves. We have actuaries, accountants, portfolio analyses and they're reviewed locally and on a corporate basis.
''Hopefully in a few years we'll be as well known among consumers as among the business people of Ireland. You want to associate yourself with a really strong brand.
]]></text></news-item>