<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BC68-7E49-0660-4EF4"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Crane Co. Records $699-Mil Liability at Dec. 31</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Crane Co. recorded a $699 million liability to cover the estimatedcost of pending asbestos claims, according to the Company's Form8-K dated January 27, 2014, filed with the U.S. Securities andExchange Commission on January 28, 2014. The Company has retained the firm of Hamilton, Rabinovitz &Associates, Inc. ("HR&A"), a nationally recognized expert in thefield, to assist management in estimating the Company's asbestosliability in the tort system. HR&A reviews information provided bythe Company concerning claims filed, settled and dismissed,amounts paid in settlements and relevant claim information such asthe nature of the asbestos-related disease asserted by theclaimant, the jurisdiction where filed and the time lag fromfiling to disposition of the claim. The methodology used by HR&Ato project future asbestos costs is based largely on the Company'sexperience during a base reference period of eleven quarterlyperiods (consisting of the two full preceding calendar years andthree additional quarterly periods to the estimate date) forclaims filed, settled and dismissed. The Company's experience isthen compared to the results of widely used previously conductedepidemiological studies estimating the number of individualslikely to develop asbestos-related diseases. Those studies wereundertaken in connection with national analyses of the populationof workers believed to have been exposed to asbestos. Using thatinformation, HR&A estimates the number of future claims that wouldbe filed against the Company and estimates the aggregatesettlement or indemnity costs that would be incurred to resolveboth pending and future claims based upon the average settlementcosts by disease during the reference period. This methodology hasbeen accepted by numerous courts. After discussions with theCompany, HR&A augments its liability estimate for the costs ofdefending asbestos claims in the tort system using a forecast fromthe Company which is based upon discussions with its defensecounsel. Based on this information, HR&A compiles an estimate ofthe Company's asbestos liability for pending and future claims,based on claim experience during the reference period and coveringclaims expected to be filed through the indicated forecast period.The most significant factors affecting the liability estimate are(1) the number of new mesothelioma claims filed against theCompany, (2) the average settlement costs for mesothelioma claims,(3) the percentage of mesothelioma claims dismissed against theCompany and (4) the aggregate defense costs incurred by theCompany. These factors are interdependent, and no one factorpredominates in determining the liability estimate. Although themethodology used by HR&A can be applied to show claims and costsfor periods subsequent to the indicated period (up to andincluding the endpoint of the asbestos studies referred to),management believes that the level of uncertainty regarding thevarious factors used in estimating future asbestos costs is toogreat to provide for reasonable estimation of the number of futureclaims, the nature of such claims or the cost to resolve them foryears beyond the indicated estimate. In the Company's view, the forecast period used to provide thebest estimate for asbestos claims and related liabilities andcosts is a judgment based upon a number of trend factors,including the number and type of claims being filed each year; thejurisdictions where such claims are filed, and the effect of anylegislation or judicial orders in such jurisdictions restrictingthe types of claims that can proceed to trial on the merits; andthe likelihood of any comprehensive asbestos legislation at thefederal level. In addition, the dynamics of asbestos litigation inthe tort system have been significantly affected over the pastfive to ten years by the substantial number of companies that havefiled for bankruptcy protection, thereby staying any asbestosclaims against them until the conclusion of such proceedings, andthe establishment of a number of post-bankruptcy trusts forasbestos claimants, which are estimated to provide $36 billion forpayments to current and future claimants. These trend factors haveboth positive and negative effects on the dynamics of asbestoslitigation in the tort system and the related best estimate of theCompany's asbestos liability, and these effects do not move in alinear fashion but rather change over multi-year periods.Accordingly, the Company's management continues to monitor thesetrend factors over time and periodically assesses whether analternative forecast period is appropriate. Each quarter, HR&A compiles an update based upon the Company'sexperience in claims filed, settled and dismissed during theupdated reference period (consisting of the preceding elevenquarterly periods) as well as average settlement costs by diseasecategory (mesothelioma, lung cancer, other cancer, and non-malignant conditions including asbestosis) during that period. Inaddition to this claims experience, the Company also considersadditional quantitative and qualitative factors such as the natureof the aging of pending claims, significant appellate rulings andlegislative developments, and their respective effects on expectedfuture settlement values. As part of this process, the Companyalso takes into account trends in the tort system. Managementconsiders all these factors in conjunction with the liabilityestimate of HR&A and determines whether a change in the estimateis warranted. Liability Estimate. With the assistance of HR&A, effective as ofDecember 31, 2011, the Company updated and extended its estimateof the asbestos liability, including the costs of settlement orindemnity payments and defense costs relating to currently pendingclaims and future claims projected to be filed against the Companythrough 2021. The Company's previous estimate was for asbestosclaims filed or projected to be filed through 2017. As a result ofthis updated estimate, the Company recorded an additionalliability of $285 million as of December 31, 2011. The Company'sdecision to take this action at such date was based on severalfactors which contribute to the Company's ability to reasonablyestimate this liability for the additional period noted. First,the number of mesothelioma claims (which although constitutingapproximately 8% of the Company's total pending asbestos claims,have accounted for approximately 90% of the Company's aggregatesettlement and defense costs) being filed against the Company andassociated settlement costs have recently stabilized. In theCompany's opinion, the outlook for mesothelioma claims expected tobe filed and resolved in the forecast period is reasonably stable.Second, there have been favorable developments in the trend ofcase law which has been a contributing factor in stabilizing theasbestos claims activity and related settlement costs. Third,there have been significant actions taken by certain statelegislatures and courts over the past several years that havereduced the number and types of claims that can proceed to trial,which has been a significant factor in stabilizing the asbestosclaims activity. Fourth, the Company has now entered intocoverage-in-place agreements with almost all of its excessinsurers, which enables the Company to project a more stablerelationship between settlement and defense costs paid by theCompany and reimbursements from its insurers. Taking all of thesefactors into account, the Company believes that it can reasonablyestimate the asbestos liability for pending claims and futureclaims to be filed through 2021. While it is probable that theCompany will incur additional charges for asbestos liabilities anddefense costs in excess of the amounts currently provided, theCompany does not believe that any such amount can be reasonablyestimated beyond 2021. Accordingly, no accrual has been recordedfor any costs which may be incurred for claims which may be madesubsequent to 2021. Management has made its best estimate of the costs through 2021based on the analysis by HR&A completed in January 2012. ThroughDecember 31, 2013, the Company's actual experience during theupdated reference period for mesothelioma claims filed anddismissed generally approximated the assumptions in the Company'sliability estimate. In addition to this claims experience, theCompany considered additional quantitative and qualitative factorssuch as the nature of the aging of pending claims, significantappellate rulings and legislative developments, and theirrespective effects on expected future settlement values. Based onthis evaluation, the Company determined that no change in theestimate was warranted for the period ended December 31, 2013.Nevertheless, if certain factors show a pattern of sustainedincrease or decrease, the liability could change materially;however, all the assumptions used in estimating the asbestosliability are interdependent and no single factor predominates indetermining the liability estimate. Because of the uncertaintywith regard to and the interdependency of such factors used in thecalculation of its asbestos liability, and since no one factorpredominates, the Company believes that a range of potentialliability estimates beyond the indicated forecast period cannot bereasonably estimated. A liability of $894 million was recorded as of December 31, 2011to cover the estimated cost of asbestos claims now pending orsubsequently asserted through 2021, of which approximately 80% isattributable to settlement and defense costs for future claimsprojected to be filed through 2021. The liability is reduced whencash payments are made in respect of settled claims and defensecosts. The liability was $699 million as of December 31, 2013. Itis not possible to forecast when cash payments related to theasbestos liability will be fully expended; however, it is expectedsuch cash payments will continue for a number of years past 2021,due to the significant proportion of future claims included in theestimated asbestos liability and the lag time between the date aclaim is filed and when it is resolved. None of these estimatedcosts have been discounted to present value due to the inabilityto reliably forecast the timing of payments. The current portionof the total estimated liability at December 31, 2013 was $88million and represents the Company's best estimate of totalasbestos costs expected to be paid during the twelve-month period.Such amount is based upon the HR&A model together with theCompany's prior year payment experience for both settlement anddefense costs. Prior to 2005, a significant portion of the Company's settlementand defense costs were paid by its primary insurers. With theexhaustion of that primary coverage, the Company begannegotiations with its excess insurers to reimburse the Company fora portion of its settlement and/or defense costs as incurred. Todate, the Company has entered into agreements providing for suchreimbursements, known as "coverage-in-place", with eleven of itsexcess insurer groups. Under such coverage-in-place agreements, aninsurer's policies remain in force and the insurer undertakes toprovide coverage for the Company's present and future asbestosclaims on specified terms and conditions that address, among otherthings, the share of asbestos claims costs to be paid by theinsurer, payment terms, claims handling procedures and theexpiration of the insurer's obligations. Similarly, under avariant of coverage-in-place, the Company has entered into anagreement with a group of insurers confirming the aggregate amountof available coverage under the subject policies and setting fortha schedule for future reimbursement payments to the Company basedon aggregate indemnity and defense payments made. In addition,with ten of its excess insurer groups, the Company entered intopolicy buyout agreements, settling all asbestos and other coverageobligations for an agreed sum, totaling $82.5 million inaggregate. Reimbursements from insurers for past and ongoingsettlement and defense costs allocable to their policies have beenmade in accordance with these coverage-in-place and otheragreements. All of these agreements include provisions for mutualreleases, indemnification of the insurer and, for coverage-in-place, claims handling procedures. With the agreements, theCompany has concluded settlements with all but one of its solventexcess insurers whose policies are expected to respond to theaggregate costs included in the updated liability estimate. Thatinsurer, which issued a single applicable policy, has been payingthe shares of defense and indemnity costs the Company hasallocated to it, subject to a reservation of rights. There are nopending legal proceedings between the Company and any insurercontesting the Company's asbestos claims under its insurancepolicies. In conjunction with developing the aggregate liability estimate,the Company also developed an estimate of probable insurancerecoveries for its asbestos liabilities. In developing thisestimate, the Company considered its coverage-in-place and othersettlement agreements, as well as a number of additional factors.These additional factors include the financial viability of theinsurance companies, the method by which losses will be allocatedto the various insurance policies and the years covered by thosepolicies, how settlement and defense costs will be covered by theinsurance policies and interpretation of the effect on coverage ofvarious policy terms and limits and their interrelationships. Inaddition, the timing and amount of reimbursements will varybecause the Company's insurance coverage for asbestos claimsinvolves multiple insurers, with different policy terms andcertain gaps in coverage. In addition to consulting with legalcounsel on these insurance matters, the Company retained insuranceconsultants to assist management in the estimation of probableinsurance recoveries based upon the aggregate liability estimateand assuming the continued viability of all solvent insurancecarriers. Based upon the analysis of policy terms and otherfactors noted by the Company's legal counsel, and incorporatingrisk mitigation judgments by the Company where policy terms orother factors were not certain, the Company's insuranceconsultants compiled a model indicating how the Company'shistorical insurance policies would respond to varying levels ofasbestos settlement and defense costs and the allocation of suchcosts between such insurers and the Company. Using the estimatedliability as of December 31, 2011 (for claims filed or expected tobe filed through 2021), the insurance consultant's modelforecasted that approximately 25% of the liability would bereimbursed by the Company's insurers. While there are overalllimits on the aggregate amount of insurance available to theCompany with respect to asbestos claims, those overall limits werenot reached by the total estimated liability currently recorded bythe Company, and such overall limits did not influence the Companyin its determination of the asset amount to record. The proportionof the asbestos liability that is allocated to certain insurancecoverage years, however, exceeds the limits of available insurancein those years. The Company allocates to itself the amount of theasbestos liability (for claims filed or expected to be filedthrough 2021) that is in excess of available insurance coverageallocated to such years. An asset of $225 million was recorded asof December 31, 2011 representing the probable insurancereimbursement for such claims expected through 2021. The asset isreduced as reimbursements and other payments from insurers arereceived. The asset was $171 million as of December 31, 2013. The Company reviews the aforementioned estimated reimbursementrate with its insurance consultants on a periodic basis in orderto confirm its overall consistency with the Company's establishedreserves. The reviews encompass consideration of the performanceof the insurers under coverage-in-place agreements and the effectof any additional lump-sum payments under policy buyoutagreements. Since December 2011, there have been no developmentsthat have caused the Company to change the estimated 25% rate,although actual insurance reimbursements vary from period toperiod, and will decline over time, for the reasons cited. Estimation of the Company's ultimate exposure for asbestos-relatedclaims is subject to significant uncertainties, as there aremultiple variables that can affect the timing, severity andquantity of claims and the manner of their resolution. The Companycautions that its estimated liability is based on assumptions withrespect to future claims, settlement and defense costs based onpast experience that may not prove reliable as predictors. Asignificant upward or downward trend in the number of claimsfiled, depending on the nature of the alleged injury, thejurisdiction where filed and the quality of the productidentification, or a significant upward or downward trend in thecosts of defending claims, could change the estimated liability,as would substantial adverse verdicts at trial that withstandappeal. A legislative solution, structured settlement transaction,or significant change in relevant case law could also change theestimated liability. The same factors that affect developing estimates of probablesettlement and defense costs for asbestos-related liabilities alsoaffect estimates of the probable insurance reimbursements, as do anumber of additional factors. These additional factors include thefinancial viability of the insurance companies, the method bywhich losses will be allocated to the various insurance policiesand the years covered by those policies, how settlement anddefense costs will be covered by the insurance policies andinterpretation of the effect on coverage of various policy termsand limits and their interrelationships. In addition, due to theuncertainties inherent in litigation matters, no assurances can begiven regarding the outcome of any litigation, if necessary, toenforce the Company's rights under its insurance policies orsettlement agreements. Many uncertainties exist surrounding asbestos litigation, and theCompany will continue to evaluate its estimated asbestos-relatedliability and corresponding estimated insurance reimbursement aswell as the underlying assumptions and process used to derivethese amounts. These uncertainties may result in the Companyincurring future charges or increases to income to adjust thecarrying value of recorded liabilities and assets, particularly ifthe number of claims and settlement and defense costs changesignificantly, or if there are significant developments in thetrend of case law or court procedures, or if legislation oranother alternative solution is implemented; however, the Companyis currently unable to estimate such future changes and,accordingly, while it is probable that the Company will incuradditional charges for asbestos liabilities and defense costs inexcess of the amounts currently provided, the Company does notbelieve that any such amount can be reasonably determined beyond2021. Although the resolution of these claims may take many years,the effect on the results of operations, financial position andcash flow in any given period from a revision to these estimatescould be material. Crane Co. (Crane) is a diversified manufacturer of engineeredindustrial products. It operates in five segments: Aerospace &Electronics, Engineered Materials, Merchandising Systems, FluidHandling and Controls. The Aerospace & Electronics segment has twogroups, the Aerospace Group and the Electronics Group. TheEngineered Materials segment manufactures fiberglass-reinforcedplastic panels. The Merchandising Systems segment is comprised oftwo businesses, Vending Solutions and Payment Solutions. The FluidHandling segment is a provider of engineered fluid handlingequipment. The Controls segment provides customer solutions forsensing and control applications. In December 2013, the Companyannounced that it has completed the acquisition of MEI ConluxHoldings.
]]></text></news-item>