<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BCE5-558F-801B-9303"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>'Democracy is dead': Pilot of missing Malaysian airliner was 'fanatical' supporter of Muslim Brotherhood-linked politician</title><source>Jihad Watch</source><author>Robert Spencer</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 16, 2014 (Jihad Watch:http://www.jihadwatch.org Delivered by Newstex) http://redirect.viglink.com?key=11fe087258b6fc0532a5ccfc924805c0u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.jihadwatch.org%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2014%2F03%2FMalayPilotDemocracyDead.jpgZaharie Ahmad Shah was a 'fanatical' supporter of Anwar Ibrahim. ' That is telling[1]: 'Anwar Ibrahim's ties to the Muslim Brotherhood run deep[2]. Ibrahim helped establish the International Institute for Islamic Thought, or IIIT, a Muslim Brotherhood front group in the United States. IIIT has come under fire for their connections with terrorist organizations. In 2002, Anwar Ibrahim's IIIT was included in a lawsuit by victims of 9/11 seeking damages from organizations linked to 'rendering material support to radical Islamism.' In 2003, US government prosecutors 'submitted court documents detailing financial support (PDF) from the IIIT for convicted Palestinian Islamic Jihad fundraiser Sami al-Arian.' They also found that Taha Jaber al-Alwani, the president of IIIT had once stated via a fatwa that 'jihad is the only way to liberate Palestine.' A US Customs official said that the government is also looking into the possibility that IIIT was involved in 'terrorism-related money laundering activities.''''Democracy is dead': 'Fanatical' missing airliner pilot pictured wearing political slogan T-shirt,' by Simon Parry, Amanda Williams and Wills Robinson for the Daily Mail[3], March 15:
An image has emerged of the pilot of the missing Malaysia Airlines jet wearing a T-shirt with a 'Democracy is Dead' slogan as it has been revealed he could have hijacked the plane in an anti-government protest. Captain Zaharie Ahmad Shah, a father-of-three, was said to be a 'fanatical' supporter of the country's opposition leader Anwar Ibrahim - jailed for homosexuality just hours before the jet disappeared. It has also been revealed that the pilot's wife and three children moved out of the family home the day before the plane went missing. It comes as FBI investigators say the disappearance of MH370 may have been 'an act of piracy' and the possibility that hundreds of passengers are being held at an unknown location has not been ruled out. Officials also revealed that it is possible the aircraft could have landed and transmitted a satellite signal from the ground. If the plane was intact and had enough electrical power in reserve, it would be able to send out a radar 'ping'. Captian Shah was an 'obsessive' supporter of Ibrahim. And hours before the doomed flight left Kuala Lumpur it is understood 53-year-old Shah attended a controversial trial in which Ibrahim was jailed for five years. Campaigners say the politician, the key challenger to Malaysia's ruling party, was the victim of a long-running smear campaign and had faced trumped-up charges. Police sources have confirmed that Shah was a vocal political activist - and fear that the court decision left him profoundly upset. It was against this background that, seven hours later, he took control of a Boeing 777-200 bound for Beijing and carrying 238 passengers and crew. Yesterday, Malaysian police searched his house in the upmarket Kuala Lumpur suburb of Shah Alam, where he had installed a home-made flight simulator. But this newspaper can reveal that investigators had already spent much of last week examining two laptops removed from Shah's home. One is believed to contain data from the simulator Confirming rising fears, Malaysia's prime minister Najib Razak announced yesterday that MH370 was deliberately steered off course after its communication system was switched off. He said it headed west over the Malaysian seaboard and could have flown for another seven hours on its fuel reserves. It is not yet clear where the plane was taken, however Mr Razak said the most recent satellite data suggests the plane could have been making for one of two possible flight corridors. The search, involving 43 ships and 58 aircraft from 15 countries, switched from the South China Sea to the Bay of Bengal in the Indian Ocean. In another dramatic twist early Sunday Indian officials however, said the search was on hold until 'fresh search areas' were defined by Malaysia. It is unclear what the reason was for the delay. Data showing the number of plausible runways where the plane could have touched down - which need to be at least 5,000ft - offer a baffling number of potential locations. According to a map drawn up by U.S. radio station WNYC, there are 634 locations which could fit, from Australia to the Maldives to Pakistan. However, the true number is likely to be even higher, as estimates of how far the plane could have travelled have been increased since the calculations were carried out. US investigators say faint 'pings' were being transmitted for several hours after the flight lost contact with the ground. Meanwhile, military radar showed the jet climbed to 45,000ft - above its service limit - which could have been a deliberate attempt to knock out the passengers and crew. Anwar Ibrahim is a broadly popular democracy icon and former deputy prime minister whose prosecution on a charge of sodomy is seen by many Malaysians as political persecution. The raids on Captain Shah's home appeared stage-managed as a display of intent after the Prime Minister said the focus of the investigation was now on 'crew and passengers' as a result of the latest leads. But investigators have told the Mail on Sunday inquiries into the background of the pilot actually began days earlier. Malaysian police, helped by FBI agents from the US, are looking into the political and religious backgrounds of both Zaharie and his co-pilot. Zaharie's home was sealed off yesterday as police spent an hour inside. However, a senior investigation source said two laptops were taken from the property in low-key visits by police early last week despite a series of denials by officials that his home had been searched or raided. One laptop taken away is thought to contain data from the flight simulator while a second contained little information. Zaharie's personal laptop was not found, and is thought to have been with him in the cockpit of the plane, the source said. Zaharie's co-workers have told investigators the veteran pilot was a social activist who was vocal and fervent in his support of Ibrahim. 'Colleagues made it clear to us that he was someone who held strong political beliefs and was strident in his support for Anwar Ibrahim,' another investigation source said. 'We were told by one colleague he was obsessed with politics.' In their interviews, colleagues said Zaharie told them he planned to attend the court case involving Anwar on March 7, just hours before the Beijing flight, but investigators had not yet been able to confirm if he was among the crowd of Anwar supporters at court. Zaharie is believed to be separated or divorced from his wife although they share the same house, close to Kuala Lumpur's international airport. They have three children, but no family members were at home yesterday: only the maid has remained there. Anwar Ibrahim is a broadly popular democracy icon and former deputy prime minister whose prosecution on a charge of sodomy is seen by many Malaysians as political persecution. Campaigners say the politician, the key challenger to Malaysia's ruling party, was the victim of a long-running smear campaign and had faced trumped-up charges. Captain Shah, who is thought to have attended the trial in Putrajaya hours before flying, is thought to be incensed by the verdict. Co-workers have told investigators the veteran pilot was a social activist who was vocal and fervent in his support of Ibrahim. Investigators said: 'We are looking into the theory that Zaharie's political beliefs may be a factor. There are huge sensitivities surrounding this but we cannot afford not to pursue any angle brought to our attention.' In the days after Flight MH370 disappeared, Zaharie was affectionately described as a good neighbour and an eccentric 'geek' who had a flight simulator at home simply because he loved his work so much. Malaysian officials initially appeared keen not to direct any suspicion towards Zaharie or his co-pilot, 27-year-old Fariq Abdul Hamid, who was last week revealed to have invited two women passengers into the cockpit and smoked on an earlier flight to Phuket. But evidence of the way the plane's transponder and communication systems were disabled and the way the plane was expertly flown over the Indian Ocean apparently using navigational waypoints meant only a skilled aviator could have been at the controls. Investigators were also baffled by why, if hijackers took over the plane, there was no Mayday call or signal from the two pilots to say the cockpit had been breached. At yesterday's press conference, the suspicion over the pilot's involvement mounted as prime minister Najib Razak said that investigators had found 'deliberate action' on board the plane resulted in it changing course and losing contact with ground crews. As a result of the new information, Malaysian authorities had 'refocused their investigation on crew and passengers aboard', he said. Police sealed off the area surrounding Zaharie's home and searched the house shortly after the press conference. Mr Razak said the new satellite evidence shows 'with a high degree of certainty' that the one of the jet's communications devices - the Aircraft and Communications Addressing and Reporting System was disabled just before it had reached the east coast of Malaysia. ACARS is a service that allows computers aboard the plane to relay in-flight information about the health of its systems back to the ground. Shortly afterwards, near the cross-over point between Malaysian and Vietnamese air traffic controllers, the plane's transponder, which emits an identifying signal, was switched off or, less likely, failed. According to a military radar, the aircraft then turned and flew back over Malaysia before heading in a north-west direction. Here is Anwar Ibrahim with Sheikh Yusuf al-Qaradawi, the international Muslim Brotherhood spiritual leader who has praised Hitler and endorsed jihad/martyrdom suicide bombing: http://redirect.viglink.com?key=11fe087258b6fc0532a5ccfc924805c0u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.jihadwatch.org%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2014%2F03%2Fanwaribrahimqaradawi.jpg [1]: http://redirect.viglink.com?key=11fe087258b6fc0532a5ccfc924805c0u=http%3A%2F%2Fsarawakreport.org%2Farch%2Fnewledger%2F2011%2F01%2Fmuslim-brotherhoods-terrorist-money-flowing-to-anwar-ibrahim%2Findex.html [2]: http://redirect.viglink.com?key=11fe087258b6fc0532a5ccfc924805c0u=http%3A%2F%2Fmalaysiawatcher.com%2F2011%2F01%2F10%2Fanwar-ibrahim-and-the-muslim-brotherhood-a-picture-is-worth-a-thousand-words%2F [3]: http://redirect.viglink.com?key=11fe087258b6fc0532a5ccfc924805c0u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.dailymail.co.uk%2Fnews%2Farticle-2581817%2FDoomed-airliner-pilot-political-fanatic-Hours-taking-control-flight-MH370-attended-trial-jailed-opposition-leader-sodomite.html%3FITO%3D1490%26amp%3Bns_mchannel%3Drss%26amp%3Bns_campaign%3D1490

]]></text></news-item>