<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BD00-75DA-DE86-7BAC"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Programme summary of Yekaterinburg's Channel Four TV news 1430 gmt 13 Mar 14</title><source>BBC Monitoring Former Soviet Union - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Presenter of "Novosti. Itogi Dnya" news: Margarita Balakirskaya.
1. 0055 Headlines over video: baby hatch installed in Yekaterinburg; Ukrainian journalist detained at Koltsovo airport; Emir Kusturica plays concert in Yekaterinburg; and travel report from Sri Lanka.
2. 0155 A baby hatch has been installed at an Orthodox church in Yekaterinburg. Video report shows the facility; metropolitan of Yekaterinburg and Verkhoturye Kirill blessing it.
3. 0515 A Yekaterinburg NGO helping mothers in distress has received R4m from the regional association of industrialists and entrepreneurs. The money is to be spent on building a shelter for women.
4. 0630 Billionaire Andrey Komarov, the main stakeholder in the Chelyabinsk Pipe Rolling Plant (GhTPZ Group), has been arrested in Samara Region on suspicion of an attempt to bribe a government official. The Pervouralsk New Pipe Plant in Sverdlovsk Region is part of ChTPZ Group.
5. 0725 Chair of the board of ChTPZ Aleksandr Fedorov said in a message on the company's website that all enterprises of the group continue operating as usual.
6. 0815 A Ukrainian journalist has been detained at Yekaterinburg's Koltsovo airport for abusive behaviour while under the influence of alcohol.
7. 0930 Serbian actor and musician Emir Kusturica and his band have played a concert in Yekaterinburg. One of their songs was dedicated to Russian people in Ukraine.
8. 1055 The Uralmash stadium is being renovated in Yekaterinburg ahead of the 2018 FIFA World Cup. Video report.
9. 1305 Players of FC Ural have taken part in a photoshoot.
10. 1335 Midway headlines; adverts.
11. 1755 An oil spill has occurred at the Kosulino train station in Sverdlovsk Region.
12. 1835 Ice hockey enthusiasts and students from Africa have played a game of hockey wearing felt boots instead of ice skates.
13. 1935 Travel report from Sri Lanka shows Hindu and Buddhist shrines.
14. 2335 A local rap singer presented his new video.
15. 2430 Adverts; weather.
16. 3040 End of news bulletin.
Source: Channel Four TV, Yekaterinburg, in Russian 1430 gmt 13 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>