<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BD19-F1D1-F85B-AA31"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Danone rises 0.7% from 14-day low</title><source>Global Round Up - ADRs and Depository Receipts</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ADRS AND DEPOSITORY RECEIPTS
Sponsored Danone (OT:DANOY) was up 0.7% from its 14-day low of US$13.66 on 14 March, 2014. Its Williams % R is -81.8. A reading of between -80 and -100 suggests it is near its 14-day low. This is defined as oversold, a bullish signal. The ADR price increased 3.0c (or 0.2%) to close at US$13.76, ending a three-day streak of losses. Compared with the Bank of New York Mellon Composite ADR Index which fell 0.3 points (or 0.2%) in the day, this represented a relative price increase of 0.4%.
Bullish SignalsOversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The ADR is oversold according to the Williams % R indicator of -81.8, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day low of US$13.66.
NoteBeta: the Beta of Danone ADR is 0.4. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return ADR with volatility less than that of the market. - Danone is at a discount of 14.6% to its 12-month high of US$16.12 on 02 Aug, 2013. It is also at a premium of 5.0% to the 12-month low of US$13.11 on 31 Jan, 2014. - The present value of US$1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in Danone is US$945, for a capital loss of US$55.
Bearish Signals:- The price decreased 0.6% in the last month. The ADR has been exacerbated by firm volume of 1.6 times average for the month. - In the last three months the ADR has hit a new 52-week low once.
AGGREGATE VOLUMES, PRICES AND TURNOVER PERIOD [Volume Index or VI in brackets; 1 is average]US Market: DANOY.OT 297,162 [VI of 0.37]; volume 15.5% of aggregate. Price: US$13.76. Paris: BN.FR 1,620,306 [VI of 0.96]; volume 84.5% of aggregate. Price: EUR49.48. Using the current exchange rate of EUR1 equals 1.39 USD, the shares are at a 0.2% premium to the close price in the US Market. Aggregate volume: there were 1,917,468 shares worth USD115,772,844 traded. The aggregate volume was 0.77 times average trading of 2,488,488 shares.
SHAREHOLDER PATTERN- Top 15 Institutional Shareholders of Danone(DANOY.OT) hold 51,614,609 shares (or 1.62%).- Fiduciary Management, Inc. was the largest institutional holder with reported holdings of 36,537,929 shares as at September 30, 2013.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 12: Danone Announces Global Partnership Between Activia And Shakira For Its New 'Dare To Feel Good' Campaign[Company Release]Today sees the launch of Activia's exciting partnership with global icon, Shakira, as the Colombian-born superstar supports the yogurt brand's new 'Dare to Feel Good' campaign. The international collaboration will bring to life Activia's 'Feeling Good Starts from Within' initiative with a new dance-themed creative that celebrates making inner health and well-being.Filmed in Barcelona, the new TV advertisement features Shakira in a fantasy forest where she is showered with swirls of gold stardust and is seen dancing to express how good she feels inside.
March 06: Danone: Information on the total number of voting rights and shares[News Story]
http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/France/Stock/News/17290.pdfSource: NYSE Euronext
February 20: Danone: 2013 Full-Year Results[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/France/Stock/News/17046.htmlSource: NYSE Euronext
February 11: DANONE : Danone raises its stake in China's leading dairy company Mengniu[News Story]Danone raises its stake in China's leading dairy company MengniuDanone today announced an agreement, together with COFCO Dairy Investments, to subscribe a reserved rights issue by China's leading dairy company Mengniu, raising its interest in this company from 4.0% to 9.9% for an investment of EUR486 million[1].The transaction makes Danone the second largest shareholder in Mengniu, and follows on from agreements signed on May 20, 2013 with Mengniu and with COFCO, China's largest state-owned food company.In parallel, COFCO, Danone and Arla - Mengniu's three core shareholders - will combine their stakes (16.3%, 9.9% and 5.3%, respectively) within COFCO Dairy Investments, a jointly-owned company pooling all three shareholders' interests in the governance of Mengniu.The transaction is subject to the approval of Mengniu's shareholders, and is expected to be finalized within the next few months.[1] At an exchange rate of EUR0.0942/HK$ 1.00Source: NYSE Euronext
January 16: Danone : Implementation of a liquidity contract[News Story]As of January 17th, 2014 and for a period of one year automatically renewable, DANONE requested ROTHSCHILD & CIE BANQUE to implement a liquidity contract in accordance with the Charter of ethics established by the AMAFI and approved by the decision of the AMF March 21st, 2011.
January 09: Danone : Information on the total number of voting rights and shares[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/France/Stock/News/16150.pdfSource: NYSE Euronext
January 08: Danone sets terms for continued partnership with Fonterra and initiates legal proceedings[News Story]
Paris, January 8, 2014 -- On August 2, 2013, Fonterra issued an alert concerning a possible contamination of certain ingredients supplied to Danone. Additional tests revealed later on that it was in fact a false alert.This affair illustrates serious failings on Fonterra's part in applying the quality standards required in the food industry.Danone is terminating its existing supply contract with Fonterra and making any further collaboration contingent on a commitment by its supplier to full transparency and compliance with the cutting-edge food safety procedures applied to all products supplied to Danone.Danone is also initiating proceedings in the New Zealand High Court, as well as arbitration proceedings in Singapore to bring all facts to light and to obtain compensation for the harm it has suffered.As a leading food company, Danone makes food safety an absolute priority and is committed to working only with suppliers that share and respect the same demanding professional standards.Source: NYSE Euronext
ISIN: US23636T1007
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>