<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BD71-8A1F-B869-D994"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Contractor Fined for Violations at Project</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Aaron Nicodemus, writing for Telegram & Gazette, reported that ademolition company has been fined up to $125,000 for mishandlingasbestos during a renovation of the Crompton and Knowles buildingat 95 Grand St., Worcester, Massachusetts. According to Attorney General Martha Coakley's office, thecontractor, McConnell Enterprises Inc., of Essex and Braintree,"uncovered piping wrapped with asbestos insulation duringdemolition in 2011 and allegedly left it hanging three storiesabove the ground, putting workers and others in the area at riskof contact with harmful fibers for an extended period of time." McConnell -- a state-licensed asbestos removal contractor --"finally removed the asbestos-covered pipes and other asbestos-containing materials from the building on Grand Street, thecompany failed to properly handle and store it, leaving it inunmarked black plastic bags in a nearby building where peopleregularly come and go and other businesses operate." The complaint, filed in Suffolk Superior Court, McConnell "alsofailed to follow proper notification procedures, preventing theMassachusetts Department of Environmental Protection (MassDEP)from conducting appropriate oversight of the company's asbestosremoval activities." In order to secure payment under its demolition contract with thecity of Worcester, the complaint alleged that McConnell "falselycertified that it had complied with the applicable laws andregulations, violating the Massachusetts False Claims Act. Thecomplaint also alleges various violations of the commonwealth'sair pollution prevention statute, its asbestos regulations, andits solid waste management statute and regulations." Under the settlement, McConnell must pay $82,500 in civilpenalties to the state, and another $42,500 in civil penalties ifit fails to conform to waste regulations over the next 18 months. When reached at its Braintree headquarters, a McConnell employeesaid the company would have no comment. "Licensed asbestos contractors are fully aware of the removal,handling, packaging and storage requirements that must be followedwhen dealing with asbestos-containing materials and of therequirement to provide notification to MassDEP in advance of thiswork," said DEP Commissioner Kenneth Kimmell in a press release."Asbestos is a known carcinogen, and following the rules isimperative to protect workers as well as the general public andenvironment. Failure to do so will result in significant penaltyexposure, as well as escalated cleanup, decontamination andmonitoring costs."
]]></text></news-item>