<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BDA7-7114-5501-9273"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>N.J. gasoline tax to rise under senator's plan  4-cent-a-gallon hike to pay to fix decaying roads, bridges, he says </title><source>The Star-Ledger (Newark, New Jersey)</source><author>David Giambusso, Star-Ledger staff</author><text><![CDATA[State Sen. Raymond Lesniak, one of the most powerful lawmakers in Trenton, will propose a 4-cent-per-gallon increase in the state's gasoline tax to address mounting infrastructure problems he says have left New Jersey's roads and bridges in "terrible condition."
Lesniak said the increase, which he expects to formally propose tomorrow, would generate $240 million a year in additional revenue.
A increase in the gas tax has long been considered the "third rail" of New Jersey politics, but Lesniak (D-Union) said yesterday a drive around the state provides powerful evidence to support a hike.
"The deterioration in our quality of life and long-term detrimental effect on our economy of a collapsing transportation infrastructure need to be fixed," he said. "There are no other options.
"It's not going to solve all our transportation problems but it'll have a major impact," he said.
Lesniak has considerable clout in Trenton, but his proposal is likely to face an uphill climb.
A recent Rutgers-Eagleton poll found that 65 percent of New Jersey voters oppose it. And Gov. Chris Christie has mocked Democratic efforts to raise the tax in past years.
The state's 14.5-cent-per-gallon gas tax is second lowest in the country (behind Alaska) and has not been raised since 1992.
Under Lesniak's plan, the tax would increase by 4 cents a gallon each year for the next six. So each year that would translate into an additional 60 cents per fill-up for a vehicle with a 15-gallon tank.
Lesniak said that's a small price to pay to fix New Jersey's ravaged roads and bridges.
He is not alone in that thinking.
"There is an investment you have to make in your infrastructure that is critically important," said Michael Egenton, senior vice president for government relations at the New Jersey Chamber of Commerce. "For the business community, that means moving people to work and moving goods and services."
The chamber, a powerful pro-business lobby, typically frowns on tax increases, but Egenton commended Lesniak for starting the debate. He stopped short, however, of a full-throated endorsement before reading the legislation.
This is not the first time Lesniak has sought an increase in the gas tax. In 2010, he floated a 2-cent-per-gallon increase, but even his fellow Democrats declared the idea dead on arrival.
There may be a bit more support this year.
Assembly Speaker Vincent Prieto (D-Hudson) told The Star-Ledger last month he, too, supports a gas tax hike.
"If you do not figure out any recurring revenues you can put in as a new revenue stream, we're going to have problems," Prieto said.
But Assemblyman Declan O'Scanlon (R-Monmouth) criticized the proposal.
"It seems like our friends on the other side of the aisle like to take taxes separately as if they don't exist together as a whole," O'Scanlon said. "Yes, our gas tax is less than surrounding states but our overall taxes are higher."
O'Scanlon said that until property taxes are addressed, there will be little appetite for a higher gas tax.
"I'm willing to have a discussion, but property taxes should be the first priority," he said.
One factor Lesniak may have working in his favor is potholes.
The state Department of Transportation typically fills about 160,000 potholes a year.
This year's brutal winter has made the situation even worse.
By the end of last month, the DOT had already filled 100,000, and New Jersey drivers will attest there are a lot more to go.
Extreme shifts in temperature, tons of salt and the constant parade of plows over the state's highways this winter have created some of the worst road conditions in recent memory.
"I've never seen them this bad, ever," state Transportation Commissioner Jim Simpson said last month.
That may be good news for mechanics, but for nearly everyone else, it means spending more money on repairs.
According to the American Society of Civil Engineers, New Jersey motorists last year spent nearly $3.5 million in extra vehicle repairs and operating costs -- or $601 per motorist -- as a result of driving on damaged roads. And that was after a relatively mild winter.
The state Transportation Trust Fund, established in 1984 to maintain roads and bridges, has been routinely plundered by state lawmakers and is running on fumes.
Moreover, the American Society of Civil Engineers said that last year, 66 percent of New Jersey's roads were in poor or mediocre condition, 10 percent of bridges were structurally deficient and 26 percent of bridges were considered functionally obsolete.
Christie has refused to consider an increase in the gas tax, preferring instead to cobble infrastructure money from a series of other pools.
In 2011, he introduced a five-year, $8 billion plan to pay for infrastructure repairs. That figure included $1.8 billion the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey pledged after Christie canceled the ARC Hudson River rail tunnel project. State leaders said then that they would be able to "pay-as-you-go" for road repairs but have ended up borrowing year after year to fund the transportation trust.
Christie's office did not respond to requests for comment on Lesniak's proposal.
Even if the political winds are shifting in favor of a increase in the gas tax, Egenton said it will be a hard sell.
"If we make it to the finish line, the real big mountain to climb will be how to convince the public that this is a good thing," he said.
Part of that will be stipulating the revenue be used only for infrastructure repairs, he said.
"What the (public is) cynical about is we raise money and shift the funds," Egenton said. "It has to be in a lockbox."
Staff writer Eunice Lee contributed to this report. David Giambusso: (973) 392-4178 or dgiambusso@starledger.com Sen. Raymond Lesniak wants to raise the tax each year for six years.
]]></text></news-item>