<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BECE-90D0-B286-FA2F"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>@HD New Head 36 light;Buffett overtakes Slim to reclaim</title><source>The Nation (Thailand)</source><author>The Nation</author><text><![CDATA[@HD New Head S/C;the world's second-richest title
Bloomberg News
New York
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;
Warren Buffett has passed Carlos Slim to become the world's second-richest person.
The 83-year-old Berkshire Hathaway chairman has a net worth of US$63.4 billion (Bt2 trillion), according to the Bloomberg Billionaires Index, up 4.3 per cent year-to-date.
Berkshire said on March 1 that its annual profit climbed to a record $19.5 billion on gains at its operating businesses, including railroad Burlington Northern Santa Fe, which Buffett bought in 2010. The Nebraska-based company posted its biggest weekly advance in 14 months last week after Buffett told investors that the true value of his company has been rising faster than accounting metrics suggest.
"The value of his underlying holdings continue to grow," said Patrick Brennan, co-chief investment officer at Hutchinson Capital Management, which oversees about $550 million including Berkshire shares. "The Burlington acquisition continues to look cheaper and cheaper by the day."
Slim's fortune has fallen $10.9 billion since the start of 2014 – the most of any billionaire on the Bloomberg ranking – as Mexico City-based America Movil, the largest mobile-phone operator in the Americas, has plummeted 14 per cent. He has a $62.9-billion net worth.
Regulators in Mexico are cracking down on America Movil's dominance of the phone industry with new rules to fix its prices and force it to share its infrastructure with competitors. As a consequence, the operator's profits in its home market will decline by about $1 billion in the next three years, according to Sanford C Bernstein and Co and Banco Itau BBA. America Movil has about seven out of ten of Mexico's mobile-phone subscribers and 80 per cent of landlines.
"The new regulations may intensify the current contraction of margins in Mexico," said Lucio Aldworth, an analyst at Citigroup, in a research note. "With this, we expect the consolidated margins of the biggest Latin American telecommunications operator to keep declining."
America Movil trades at a lower valuation than its peers because of impending regulation in Mexico, uncertainty over mergers and acquisitions and expectations for slower growth, Aldworth said. "We don't think any of those factors will improve enough in the short term to justify higher multiples," he said.
Slim, 74, was unseated as the world's richest man by Bill Gates in May 2013 as Mexican lawmakers started to tackle the lack of competition in the telecommunications market. Gates, 58, has a net worth of $77.7 billion, according to the ranking.
Amancio Ortega, the 77-year-old founder of Inditex, is the world's fourth-richest person with a $60.3 billion fortune. Inditex is the world's largest clothing retailer and owner of the Zara chain.
The 300 billionaires on the Bloomberg ranking have a collective net worth of $3.6 trillion.
Buffett announced in 2006 that he would donate the majority of his fortune to charity.
]]></text></news-item>