<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BF0B-55B8-E493-9E40"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>LETTERS: Contributing to climate change; free-range call centers</title><source>The Gazette (Colorado Springs, Colorado)</source><author>Letters</author><text><![CDATA[Contributing to climate change
While Sen. Mark Udall joined other nervous Democrats up for election this year in grandstanding on the Senate floor about climate change, freshly loaded petroleum product railroad tank cars from North Dakota and Canada moved along the spine of the Front Range by rail instead of via the most efficient and effective method, the XL pipeline. The tracks (and loaded tank cars) go through countless Front Range Colorado neighborhoods, now, day after day.
My personal climate changed when those rail cars started to ship through my neighborhood. And yet Sen. Udall waits for the final State Department report, as does Sen. Michael Bennet, and just as his party leader, President Barack Obama, does. What is it now, a five-year delay on 20,000 jobs, a reduction in energy dependency on nonfriendly nations? Oh, and now because of the delays we are not using the most efficient and safest way to move these new energy sources safely. Please .
Start representing your constituents for a change, instead of some overarching themed "maybe" man-made problem. Stop contributing to climate change (hot air) and get to work.
Lee Williams, Monument
-
Students are not like Coke bottles
The more I read about Common Core, the more I see it is not good for our children, our schools nor our country.
- The math standards are lower than what most local school districts have now. It de-emphasizes correct answers by awarding points for reasoning, even when the students don't get the correct answer.
- The nationalizing of school standards takes autonomy away from the local school boards. Students are not like Coke bottles that can be filled and all come out the same. Children learn in different venues, at different rates and in different styles.
- Testing is computer based, meaning about one-fourth of the school year will be spent on testing instead of learning; besides adding facilitating costs to the schools.
- The teaching of true American history is being cut back to bring in an ideology that is not part of the founding of this country and the values that made this country great. It is supporting a system that mirrors socialism, social justice and wealth redistribution, instead of the tenets of a democratic Republic.
Even now, cameras are in an elementary classroom in Fort Collins, facing the children. I wonder, "WHY"? Colorado has traded control of its children's education for federal dollars and what is taught in the schools. Let the parents have control, not the government.
Erna A. Haring. Colorado Springs
-
Five years isn't enough
Monument Academy had to be put on lockdown due to a threat of a shooting. A man had called a teacher and threatened to put a bullet in her brain. I see people worrying about how we need to take guns away because guns are killing people, but in reality people kill people.
The problem is criminals are not getting big enough sentences. Criminals need to be put in prison and stay in there for a long time because a lot of criminals are compulsive burglars or murderers, for example, so when they get let out of prison, they go right back to what got them in prison.
The man who threatened this school is going to face a maximum of five years, which isn't enough. So when this man gets out, he will be mad that she told on him and he already threatened her. To keep everyone at the school safe and to keep the teacher safe, he needs to be locked up for a lot longer than five years.
Collin Ryba, Colorado Springs
-
Extortion prices for traffic offenses
Anyone else think that the Colorado Springs police charge extortion prices for traffic offenses? A $145 fine for going 13 mph over the speed limit and four points on the license? Are we funding the city law enforcement officer retirement fund? How much annual revenue does the Colorado Springs Police Department rake in for traffic violations?
With all the tax revenue coming into the state now with pot sales, I think the costs for traffic violations could be reduced. I for one don't want exorbitant amounts of money going into law enforcement coffers; that's how corruption gets out of hand. And the city should get rid of the traffic violation/fine quotas for the police.
Scott Martin, Colorado Springs
-
Free range call centers
The controversy recently over backyard chicken farming makes me want to compare call centers today to industrial chicken farming. You have plenty of hens (and a few roosters) cackling all day laying the golden eggs for the company.
On a good day, you may receive some extra feed in the form of doughnuts and pizza, heavy laden with GMOs, which are Genetically Modifying your Obesity.
If it is a seasonal job, it is a contest to see how many chickens can withstand the pressure without getting cooked or fried.
Chickens, if cooped up for too long, start to go crazy and peck at each other, which can be true of humans, too. I guess that is when it becomes a slaughterhouse instead of a call center.
I wonder if we need a Front Range town for backyard call centers where people, like chickens, can freely roam outside instead of being stuck in cubicles.
Jody Davis, Colorado Springs
]]></text></news-item>