<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BF0E-94E1-A1F6-77E2"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Constable shoots sister dead, wife seriously injured</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Soumittra S Bose</author><text><![CDATA[NAGPUR: A naik police constable shot his elder sister and wife, killing the former and leaving the wife seriously injured, in front of his children and father at their Sumedh Nagar, Jaripatka, house on Friday. The cop is currently posted at the Gangajhari police station of Gondia district, and was here on leave.
Jaripatka police recovered three empty cases and 67 live cartridges of the carbine machine gun used by constable Rajesh Brahmankar. A simmering property dispute most probably led Brahmankar to shoot his wife Rita and elder sister Prema alias Premlata.
Rajesh intended to rejoin duty as body guard to the tehsilder at Tiroda in Gondia on Friday morning. Leaving to catch a bus, he had taken the children to drop them at school, but returned with them in some time. He then got into an argument with his wife Rita and slapped her.
Rita rushed to her sister-in-law Prema for support, which enraged Rajesh further, since he had a tense relationship with the elder sister, who had embraced Christianity against his wishes. Rajesh had already been angry since the family members were opposing his decision to bring home another elder sister, Nandabai, a widow who lost her son recently.
A furious Rajesh pushed aside his father Nathulal, who tried to intervene, before firing at his wife and sister.
Rajesh shot wife Rita twice before firing one bullet into Prema’s chest from his service carbine machine gun, which is generally used by cops in Naxal-affected regions. The constable, who was probably inebriated. shot the women from close range.
Rita is in Mayo Hospital’s intensive care unit, being treated for serious injuries to her chest and liver. She was able to alert relatives on a mobile phone despite suffering two bullet injuries. Prema too was alive while being rushed to Mayo Hospital in a police van with Rita. The doctors declared her dead at the hospital even as Rita was rushed into an emergency operation.
Rajesh was taken to Jaripatka police station along with his carbine machine gun. He claimed the firearm went off accidentally while he was intimidating family members.
Rita had earlier complained about harassment by Rajesh. He had even forced Rita to discontinue her office. Jaripatka cops had twice intervened and settled fights between them.
Family sources claimed that Rajesh, a habitual drinker, harassed his wife regularly and was also suffering from psychological problems. He once was rescued by Wardha GRP police, while on his way to Mumbai on duty, after he was robbed in an inebriated condition.
It’s learnt that Rajesh’s father Nathulal, a former railway employee, had built the house on the plot in Prema’s name. Rajesh, whose elder brother had been run over by a train some years ago, had built the floor he occupied with his wife and children.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>