<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="BFAB-F5CE-1DA5-BD4F"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>News briefing</title><source>Sun-Sentinel (Fort Lauderdale, Florida)</source><author>Tribune Newspapers and news services</author><text><![CDATA[Signs point to an Assad re-election bid in Syria
BEIRUT -- As indications mount that Syrian President Bashar Assad will seek re-election, the government lashed out Friday at the United Nations mediator who said elections could doom U.N.-sponsored peace talks meant to end the 3-year-old civil war.
Syria's top official spokesman charged that Lakhdar Brahimi, the U.N. and Arab League peace envoy, had "overstepped" his duties by saying that Syria's apparent plans to forge ahead with elections despite the ongoing conflict could effectively end the so-called Geneva peace process.
"Brahimi, by his talk, has overstepped his missions and powers," Omran Zoubi, the Syrian information minister, said in comments carried in state media.
A day earlier, Brahimi declared that elections would likely prompt opposition delegates to walk away from the high-profile diplomatic peace initiative. Backing the Geneva talks are the United States, which has supported the opposition, and Russia, an Assad ally.
Representatives of the opposition fighting to oust Assad have said repeatedly that any election held while the nation's civil war was still raging would be a sham -- especially if Assad was on the ballot.
Assad, whose current term ends in July, has not definitively declared his candidacy, though he has frequently hinted that he would seek a third seven-year term. Any decision to run rests with the "Syrian people," Assad has told interviewers.
No specific date has been set for a presidential election.
Dozens killed in insurgent attack on Nigerian military
Dozens of insurgents attacked a military barracks in the troubled Nigerian city of Maiduguri in an apparent attempt to free detained rebels, government officials said.
It was unclear how many prisoners were freed in the attack on the Giwa Barracks, which left dozens dead, authorities said.
No group claimed responsibility for the assault in Borno state, which bore hallmarks of raids on jails and military barracks by the al-Qaida-linked Boko Haram terrorist group, which has used the tactic previously.
Judge: Out-of-state gay marriages count in Tenn.
Tennessee must recognize the legal same-sex marriages of three couples who wed in other states, federal Judge Aleta Trauger ruled Friday in Nashville, Tenn., in a limited decision that echoed a similar case in Kentucky.
Meanwhile, 13 people filed a lawsuit urging a federal judge to overturn an Indiana law that bans gay marriage or recognition of same-sex marriages performed elsewhere.
<hl2 style="briefs_subhead">Son of ex-N.J. governor killed self, family says
Jeffrey Corzine, 31, the youngest son of former New Jersey Gov. Jon Corzine, committed suicide at a Mexico City hotel this week, a family spokesman said.
Jeffrey Corzine, who died Tuesday after a struggle with depression, had been living in Malibu, Calif., and was an aspiring photographer.
Jon Corzine, who also served in the U.S. Senate, is the former co-chairman of Goldman Sachs.
6 slain in 2nd knifing in China in last two weeks
BEIJING -- Six people were reported dead after a knife-wielding man slashed passers-by Friday morning following a fight in a market in Changsha, in China's central Hunan province.
Authorities said the incident was the result of a dispute between vendors.
The attack initially raised fears of a premeditated attack because militants from far western China were implicated in a knifing rampage March 1 that left 33 dead at a train station in Kunming.
The Newsmaker
Ex-Sen. Brown eyes run
Former Sen. Scott Brown, R-Mass., who moved to New Hampshire last year, said Friday he is considering a run for the Senate in his new home state and had formed an exploratory committee. He would seek the seat held by Democrat Jeanne Shaheen. Maduro regime blames U.S. for Venezuela unrest
CARACAS, Venezuela -- Foreign Minister Elias Jaua lambasted Secretary of State John Kerry on Friday as a "murderer" fomenting unrest that has killed 28 people as turmoil roils Venezuela.
Since street demonstrations began against President Nicolas Maduro's socialist government in early February, Venezuelan officials have been accusing Washington of stirring up trouble.
U.S. officials say Venezuela is using them as a scapegoat.
<hl2 style="briefs_subhead">Jury re-indicts Indian official in visa fraud case
NEW YORK -- A grand jury in New York has returned a new indictment against Indian diplomat Devyani Khobragade for visa fraud, two days after a judge dismissed a similar indictment because she had diplomatic immunity.
Khobragade's arrest in December and subsequent strip-search drew outrage in India, causing a major diplomatic rift between the United States and India.
The new indictment effectively returns the case to where it was before Wednesday's dismissal.
Pinkberry founder gets 7 years for 2011 beating
LOS ANGELES -- Judge Henry Hall was blunt when he addressed Pinkberry co-founder Young Lee in court Friday, calling his 2011 attack on a homeless man both "horrendous" and "fairly merciless."
Lee, 49, was convicted last year of beating Ronald Bolding with a tire iron while Bolding was panhandling in Los Angeles. The frozen yogurt chain's co-founder got the maximum sentence of seven years in prison Friday, despite his attorney's bid for possible probation.
]]></text></news-item>