<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C029-C93B-07AF-6860"><date>2014-03-09</date><title>Rabies fear as puppies are smuggled into the UK</title><source>Express Online</source><author>Stuart Winter</author><text><![CDATA[ROGUE foreign puppy farmers are putting Britain at risk of a deadly rabies plague by exploiting Britain's weak ­border controls.
Huge numbers of young dogs from Eastern Europe are being smuggled into the country with false paperwork and without being vaccinated against one of the most virulent diseases known to mankind.
Since animal import laws were relaxed in 2012, there has been a huge spike in the number of dogs coming into the country, with a 1,150 per cent increase from Romania and 507 per cent rise from Lithuania.
Britain has been rabies free since 1902 but relaxed quarantine rules and greater demand for cheap puppies is threatening to see the disease slipping into the country under the cover of bogus paperwork.
Last night the RSPCA called on the Government to tighten up dock-side controls, warning that the only barrier from stopping an infected animal entering the country and causing a disaster are inexperienced port workers.
The animal welfare organisation has published a detailed report called "Pushing at an open door - how the present UK controls on rabies are failing" and calls for spot checks at Dover and Holyhead to target dogs coming in from Ireland and other European countries.
It also wants more proactive work in Lithuania, Hungary, Poland and Romania to cut down on the fraudulent use of pet passport certificates that are used to ship commercially bred puppies illegally into the UK and which are then sold for hundreds of pounds online.
RSPCA investigations into the puppy trade show that since rules were relaxed, the number of dogs coming into the UK have doubled. In 2011, around 27,000 dogs came in from the EU but last year it rose to 53,911. The Society has also seen a 21 per cent increase in the number of calls it is receiving about puppy farms and trafficking.
RSPCA Chief Veterinary Officer James Yeates warns: "If we want to protect the rabies free status of our country, the Government needs to take very seriously the number of dogs being fraudulently smuggled in as pets from the continent and then sold commercially on the internet.
"At present, controls are in the hands of the Tunnel and ferry companies. The decreased controls place an unfair burden on the ports.
"Our rabies free status should not be left to a person working at a ferry company who is not experienced in what to look for as the Government's own figures clearly show this is not working. "The huge rise in dogs being imported as pets since controls were relaxed shows how puppy dealers are evading controls and selling on dogs which can often be sick to unsuspecting buyers."
Shadow Environment Minister Huw Irranca-Davies MP also called for the Government to close loopholes putting the country at threat from rabies.
He said: "It is deeply concerning to see under this Government such a rapid increase in the number of dogs being imported to UK as pets from countries where rabies has been reported, where the health and condition of the dogs is unknown, often having not been properly micro-chipped or vaccinated.
"The Government must do more to clampdown on the illegal trade of dogs purchased abroad without the appropriate documentation and to ensure that ferry operators do not inadvertently become tools of an illegal and dangerous trade."
As an island, Britain has had a natural marine barrier against rabies, a disease that has slowly been edging westwards across Europe over the past few decades and is regarded as  "high risk" in many of the former Iron Curtain states.
Over the past century there have been 26 deaths in the UK from the disease, the vast majority coming from infections caught overseas.  There were two deaths in 2001 from infections contracted in Nigeria and Philippines and another victim died four years later after being bitten by a dog in Goa. In 2009, a woman died in Belfast after being infected by a dog scratch in South Africa.
Britain's membership of the EU has seen a relaxing of the one-time strict dog movement rules with quarantine being phased out completely for pets coming into the country for non-commercial reasons in 2012.
The Pet Travel Travel Scheme was introduced to make it easier for owners to travel with their animals overseas but the regulations were not meant for the mass movement of commercial animals.
Yet in its report, the RSPCA warns: "Many more dogs are being imported than envisaged from central and eastern Europe, suggesting that PETS is being used as a cover to import dogs and puppies for commercial sale; veterinary controls to ensure dogs comply with the age and vaccination controls are being flouted; instances of dogs and puppies being imported illegally are increasing."
The RSPCA has collated numerous cases to highlight the level of regulations being exploited and, this year alone, discovered:
In January, Hampshire Trading Standards seized and quarantined nine German Shepherd puppies from one puppy dealer who had imported them from Bulgaria.The same month, two Pug puppies were seized and quarantined by Hampshire Trading Standards after being illegally imported from Lithuania.In February, Swindon Borough Council successfully prosecuted a dealer who imported up to 30 puppies, mostly Dachshunds from Czech Republic.  Although some of these dogs had pet passports and were micro-chipped, they had not been vaccinated against rabies and were being sold as British puppies.  The dealer was fined and sentenced to 200 hours community work. The dogs were put into quarantine.Again last month, a Shih Tzu illegally imported had to be destroyed in Keighley after it had been sold over the internet and was only found to be illegally imported when it was taken to the vets.In another case last month, six Pug puppies were seized by East Riding animal welfare officers that had been illegally imported under the rules for pets.
By rights, any animal entering the UK should be micro-chipped, vaccinated against rabies and be clearly identified on a pet passport, to comply with PETS.
The RSPCA's head of public affairs, David Bowles, warned: "Puppy traders are evading controls by not doing this and the huge numbers of dogs being imported show the system is being abused. These dogs cannot all be personal pets as most human migration from countries in the east of Europe happened in 2004 and 2005.
"Although PETS exists to make it easier for people to travel abroad with their dogs, puppy dealers have taken advantage of these loopholes by bringing in many popular breeds including French Bulldogs and Pugs from puppy farms in central Europe, saying they are personal pets and selling them online to unsuspecting buyers who are often left with large veterinary bills when the puppies become ill."
A spokeswoman for the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, which has responsibility for animal welfare issues, said: "The risk of a dog with rabies coming into the UK remains very low and we carry out the same stringent checks on dogs coming in to the country as ever.
"The increase in attempts to bring dogs into the country illegally is being driven by the high demand for cheap puppies.
"We would urge anyone looking to buy a puppy to ensure it comes from a reputable supplier and ask to see the puppy interact with its mother."
]]></text></news-item>