<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C05C-59EB-C50E-4B75"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Council's leadership questioned</title><source>Clifton Journal (Passaic, North Jersey)</source><author>Tony Gicas</author><text><![CDATA[CLIFTON - After several months away from the dais due to health issues, a member of the City Council returned with a fury when he passionately voiced displeasure regarding what he believed to be a lack of follow-through from members of the municipality's leadership.
Citing multiple issues which he said have gone unresolved in his absence, Councilman Matt Grabowski, stormed out of the governing body's last meeting following critical comments pointed at many of his colleagues.
"Does the Council ever enforce its own policies?" Grabowski asked. "We have no leadership who stands up for what's right."
He added that a motion he made months ago regarding residency, the policy which would require City first responders to live in Clifton, has still not been implemented.
"Months ago, I made a motion that was approved by the entire Mayor and Council to bring back residency, which would make it good for our police and fire [departments] to live in the City and know better what's going on," Grabowski said at the meeting. "The entire council said 'yes' and nothing has been done. Now, I don't care if we take it to court and lose, but it's just baffling that we made a motion, it passed, and nothing's happened."
City Manager Matthew Watkins said the City planned to schedule meetings with a neighboring municipality which reinstated a residency policy, but the holidays and snowstorms have left both sides without the necessary time to meet.
"It is something that we're trying to move along," Watkins added. "But, it's been a tough couple of months here."
The Council member said his anger first sparked at the meeting after noticing a Clifton resident who was seated adjacent to the governmental dais in an area of the chamber which, long ago, was reserved for representatives of the press and now is reserved for public defender applications during court proceedings.
"We also made a motion that there was no one to be sitting in the press area, and there's someone sitting there again," added Grabowski, pointing to Clifton resident Alex Bidnik.
"Why are we making motions that we aren't even implementing ourselves?" Grabowski asked.
Last year, residents complained to the Council that Bidnik, 78, who distributes a weekly newsletter, was a distraction during the public speaking portion of meetings because of where he was sitting.
"Speakers were complaining about Mr. Bidnik sitting on the dais too close to the podium because, when they were addressing the City Council, Mr. Bidnik would look at their documents, pick them up and read them," Councilman Joseph Kolodziej said on Monday. "He would interrupt them while they were speaking or mutter comments to them while they were trying to speak."
Kolodziej said complaints from public speakers began mounting following spirited Council meetings in May that were dominated by discussions on whether or not to move the municipal elections to November.
He said the issue "came to a head" at the Aug. 20 meeting and, as a result, Kolodziej made a motion, seconded by Councilman Grabowski, and passed by the Mayor and Council, that no one be seated to the left of the podium during meetings.
"My rationale was any member of the press acting in an official press capacity should have their credentials with them just like you need to have your driver's license on you when operating a motor vehicle," Kolodziej said. "So, until he produced these documents, he shouldn't sit there representing himself as a member of the press."
Kolodziej said Bidnik has not produced press credentials since that meeting and, up until last week's meeting, had not attempted to sit there again.
When asked by Grabowski why he continues to sit in the area, Watkins said last week that he has asked Bidnik not to sit in the area specified in the motion.
One City official said no one else "pushed the issue" regarding Bidnik vacating the press area because members of the dais preferred to take a preventative approach such as removing chairs. Multiple sources said the area will be roped off during the Council's next meeting, slated for March 18.
According to Robert's Rules of Order, all conversations and actions go through the chairman which, in Clifton's case, is Mayor James Anzaldi because he sets the agenda and chairs the Council's meetings. As a result, it is Anzaldi's responsibility to enforce all aspects of the meeting, officials said.
The Mayor is tasked with enforcing such measures but would have someone other than himself actually carry the work out, a City Hall source explained.
After the motion was carried at the Aug. 20 meeting, the mayor directed the city manager to address Bidnik sitting on the dais and a two-minute recess was enacted for Watkins to carry our Anzaldi's order.
"I don't get it. We're saying don't do something and people do it. Why should anyone listen to us when no one listens to us even in our own court room?" Grabowski asked. "It's a shame and a disgrace."
Anzaldi said he spoke to Watkins about the issue in an attempt to be "proactive" and intends to place a restrictive chain to prevent others from sitting in the area in the future.
"I tried my best to keep it as calm as possible," said Anzaldi. "And I told Mr. Bidnik after the meeting that he's not supposed to sit there anymore. I think everybody on the Council felt we should wait until the meeting's over and come up with a solution."
At Clifton school board meetings, Bidnik has also made a habit of sitting at a table directly next to Assistant Superintendent Mark Tietjen.
In addition to the seating issue, multiple City officials said soon after receiving election or appointment to municipal bodies Bidnik approached them and requested donations to go toward his weekly newsletter. Two of the newly-elected individuals who wished not to be named, said when they declined to donate money to the publication, Bidnik printed false and negative information about them in the following newsletter.
"As soon as you say 'no' he hammers you," one City board member said on Tuesday.
Additionally, a member of a prior Clifton administration said Bidnik was told he would be charged with trespassing if he stepped foot on the Department of Public Works property stemming from incidents that took place about a decade ago.
The source added that Bidnik often distributed his newsletter inside City Hall, an action which broke Clifton's policy that any newsletter distributed on municipal grounds had to first be authorized by the City Manager.
"He was never approved and was advised to stay out of certain areas of City Hall where the public was not invited," the source said.
Despite rumors to the contrary, Watkins said he'd never heard that Bidnik was placing his newsletter into City employees' mail boxes, an action which he would strictly prohibit because the boxes may contain personal information or paychecks. Officials said it is under the City Manager's purview to oversee the daily operations at City Hall but, Watkins stated that he was not aware of Bidnik's newsletters being distributed on City Hall property.
In 1981, Bidnik was found guilty on five counts of extortion for threatening to write damaging articles in his weekly newspaper if victims did not provide him with advertising and/or information. At the time, news reports contended he was the first newspaper publisher in the country to be charged with extortion.
In 2004, police charged Bidnik with impersonating a police officer at a School 15 graduation ceremony. In 2005, Bidnik was charged with creating false public alarm after he allegedly told an AT&T customer service operator that he would send a bomb to blow up the company's South Brunswick service center. Also, according to reports, Bidnik has also lost more than a dozen libel lawsuits.
Bidnik did not return numerous calls seeking comments.
]]></text></news-item>