<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C0BD-EEF4-F4A1-C25E"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Politicians backing Lyari gangsters: DG Rangers No stopping Karachi operation: Nawaz</title><source>The Frontier Post</source><author> Naimat Khan</author><text><![CDATA[Prime Minister Mian Nawaz Sharif, who chaired a high level meeting to review law and order situation in Karachi, was informed of the astonishing fact that gangsters in troubled Lyari enjoy direct support of the ruling party of Sindh.
DG Rangers, who is the operational head of Karachi Operation, was of the view that no peace could be restored until all political parties disassociate their militant groups.
Sources privy to the meeting said though the revelations were secret as it was being reported several times, the statement from the head of paramilitary force stunned Qaim Ali Shah, Chief Minister Sindh who was also part of the meeting. The Prime Minister also did not issue any directives to this regards but the official statement in front of the Prime Minister was highly disturbing for Qaim Ali Shah, sources said.
The meeting, here at Sindh Governor House on Friday, was attended by Governor Sindh Dr. Ishratul Ebad Khan, Chief Minister Sindh, Syed Qaim Ali Shah, Federal Interior Minister Chaudhry Nisar Ali Khan, Federal Finance Minister Ishaq Dar, Federal Commerce Minister Engineer Khurram Distagir Khan, Chief Secretary Sindh, Inspector General of Police Sindh and Director General of Intelligence Bureau.
Keeping in view the protection of witnesses, investigators, prosecutors and Judges, the Prime Minister directed to shift Anti Terrorism Courts to Malir Cantonment. Prime Minister also directed to lift ban on recruitment in all civil armed forces of Pakistan. It was also agreed in-principle that additional police stations to be established in Lyari, Karachi.
On the recommendation of D.G. Rangers, the Prime Minister directed that Army Recruitment Centres should be utilized for recruitment. He further directed that recruitment should be purely on merit and without any favouritism, observing strict transparency in the process.
The Prime Minister also directed that Sindh Government should expedite establishment of isolated high security Prisons in Sindh for imprisoning terrorists. Prime Minister directed Ministry of Interior to expedite the blocking of illegal mobile phone SIMs and further directed to ensure use of biometric system for issuance of SIMs in the future. Prime Minister directed Sindh Provincial Government and Rangers to take action against land-mafia that is illegally grabbing state lands.
Prime Minister said that "Karachi operation will continue. The sacrifices rendered by our security agencies are invaluable.
Karachi operation is not a routine issue for the government and I will regularly monitor and supervise operation and will help the provincial Government in resolving the issues". PM further said that a high level meeting in the next week is being called wherein all Chief Ministers, Chief Secretaries and IGs will participate to review the overall security situation of the country. Prime Minister said that "We will also discuss coordination mechanism regarding border control, intelligence sharing and combating terrorism". Police and Rangers should use new Anti- Terrorism Laws to combat terrorism, extortion and land- grabbing, said the PM.
Earlier, Chief Secretary Sindh briefed the Prime Minister on law and order situation. He apprised the Prime Minister that 393 cases of heinous crimes have been registered. Prime Minister was apprised that illegal migration of foreign nationals is also causing law and order problems. Fresh inductions in the Police force are needed in order to strengthen the force. Prime Minister appreciated the fast-track procurement of high-tech equipment for security purposes.
Earlier, the Prime Minister, while addressing to Award ceremony of KCCI, said that operation will not be halted until last criminal is eliminated of the city. He said Government intended to do much for the city which was a revenue engine of the country. He said that MQM was an important part of the city. He said the operation was not against any specific party but criminal elements.
PPP rejects allegations: Although Chief Minister Sindh Qaim Ali Shah was reportedly with sealed lips when DG Rangers told about the patronage of Lyari Gangsters by the ruling Party, PPP Sindh information secretary and spokesperson for the CM Sindh, Waqar Mehdi Friday termed the allegation completely baseless. "
The PPP supports no criminals at all" he said. In statement issued here on Friday as rejoinder to the allegation Mehdi said Chief Minister Sindh had given freehand to the law enforcement agencies to carry out operation against criminals with any background. Earlier, DG Rangers had informed a meeting presided over by Prime Minister Mian Nawaz Sharif that the Lyari gangsters were enjoying the support of Sindh's ruling party.
]]></text></news-item>