<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C106-D6FB-C41F-3D1C"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>MPs campaigning full-time for Afghan presidential candidates - paper</title><source>BBC Monitoring South Asia - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Text of editorial in Dari entitled "The parliament will be paralysed during this legislative period" published by Afghan independent secular daily newspaper Hasht-e Sobh on 15 March
The new legislative period begins today, but all MPs are busy campaigning. From MPs to parliament Speaker, everyone is busy working with different election campaign teams. Some MPs simultaneously appear in several campaign teams.
It appears that some MPs are seeking concessions in this fashion also. Every citizen has a right to vote, study candidate manifestos and brief the public about it, but an MP must not spend all of his or her time supporting a candidate. MPs are unfortunately so lost in election campaigns that they have no time for their main responsibilities. This is a betrayal of other MPs.
MPs may remain busy in campaigns until elections are held and power is transferred. They might then return to the parliament to bargain on the approval of nominees for ministerial positions.
The current parliament has not achieved much during previous legislative periods. The number of bills passed during the current period is also limited.
MPs have also failed to provide oversight because major acts of corruption were not stopped. Ministers who failed to spend their development budgets remained in their positions as ministers. The parliament failed to stop administrative and financial corruption. In fact, the parliament became a source of corruption. The former interior minister has revealed how some MPs are busy cutting deals. Speaking at a general session of the parliament during summer this year, the finance minister openly accused several MPs of involvement in illegal businesses. The Kabul police also accused some MPs and senators of supporting suspects and actual hardened criminals. The current parliament had no answer for any of these [accusations]. It lost its credibility in the society. Its image was also tarnished within the government.
Parliament plays no role in major acts of government decision-making. A number of MPs revealed themselves during interviews that some of their colleagues seek concessions from some ministers, an act which totally eroded parliament's credibility. The simultaneous appearance of a considerable number of MPs on the same election campaign teams made it absolutely clear that minor deals are more important to some MPs than anything else.
The parliament will most likely remain paralysed during this legislative period until elections are held and power is transferred to an elected president. The parliament will go into summer recess as of 1 Saratan [22 June]. Haggling, however, will continue until the parliament completes its mandate.
The worst step the parliament took was rejecting the role of political parties. The future parliament would not have had many shortcomings of the current parliament had it been composed of political party members. It is sad that this parliament snatched this opportunity too.
Source: Hasht-e Sobh, Kabul, in Dari 15 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>