<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C146-FB03-BB81-D61E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Royal commission gets under way next month</title><source>The Australian</source><author>DAVID CROWE</author><text><![CDATA[THE royal commission into union corruption will hold its first public hearing next month after being formally established, amid a dispute over gains to the economy from workplace change.
Clearing the way for months of investigation, Governor-General Quentin Bryce signed the papers yesterday to set up the inquiry, with orders that it report by December 31.
The final letters patent, seen by The Australian, confirm the focus on five key unions in an effort to uncover any bribes, secret commissions or unlawful payments and benefits. The document also asks the commission to investigate ``any person or organisation'' involved in the unlawful conduct, a key provision that captures employers or business groups.
Employment Minister Eric Abetz and Attorney-General George Brandis are expected to issue the letters patent today, saying the commission will ``get to the bottom'' of systemic problems.
The five unions targeted are the Australian Workers Union, Health Services Union, Transport Workers Union, Electrical Trades Union and Construction Forestry Mining and Energy Union, which is at the heart of recent claims about gangsters in the building industry.
The commission, led by former High Court judge Dyson Heydon, proposes to hold its first public hearing on April 9. The inquiry comes as political debate intensifies over union tactics on building sites, with the CFMEU ordered by the Federal Court this week to pay $500,000 to Brookfield Multiplex over disrupted construction in West Australia.
Senator Abetz is citing the court decision as proof of the need for a more powerful regulator to investigate the industry, as the parliament considers legislation to revive the Howard government's building watchdog.
Labor scrapped the Australian Building and Construction Commission to rely on the general workplace regulator. The Abbott government is seeking Senate approval to reinstate the commission with strong powers to police the industry.
Labor and the Greens oppose the measure and gained an edge in one aspect of the debate this week when the Productivity Commission dismissed building industry claims that the ABCC had added billions of dollars to the economy.
]]></text></news-item>