<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C149-66CF-CA03-1F43"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Oklahoma: COMMUNITY CENTER SUPERVISOR</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Department of Employment, The State of Oklahoma has issued the following job announcement:
COMMUNITY CENTER SUPERVISOR Opening Date/Time: Mon. 03/10/14 12:00 AM Central Time Closing Date/Time: Fri. 03/14/14 11:59 PM Central Time Salary: $42,114.96 - $64,352.16 Annually Job Type: Full Time Location: TBD: Various Locations, Oklahoma Department: Parks and Recreation This job is located in the Parks and Recreation Department at various Community Centers located throughout The City of Oklahoma City. Essential job functions include: administering the center's programs or activities to ensure compliance with departmental policy and supervising the center staff. The worker has frequent contact with civic groups, school leaders and social organizations to develop and organize community participation in the center. The individual in this position may have daily contact with all age groups, from pre-school to senior citizens, and is responsible for the implementation of Community Center programs which ranges from arts and crafts to various recreational activities. A close working relationship is established between the employee, the center's staff and participants, to develop and carry out programs specifically oriented to community needs and desires. Employees in this classification will receive occasional supervision from a field supervisor.
VETERANS PREFERENCE
A five-point preference will be awarded on the initial scored selection process for honorably discharged veterans of the United States Armed Forces not currently employed full time by the City of Oklahoma City. Qualified applicants must upload or submit a copy of their DD Form 214 indicating discharge type/character of service at the time of application.
Job Requirements:
Skill in soliciting parental assistance in disciplinary matters. Skill in instructing in proper use of facilities and equipment. Skill in supervising. Skill in determining solutions to problems in community center. Skill in identifying safety hazards. Skill in identifying abusive and/or improper use of equipment/facilities. Skill in instructing in special activities, i.e., arts/crafts, and recreation center activities. Skill in communicating verbally and in writing using tact and diplomacy. Skill in planning schedules and work activities. Possession of a valid Oklahoma State Driver License.
DEPARTMENTAL PREFERENCES
Bachelor’s degree in Recreation or related field. Experience developing and implementing after school programs. Previous experience supervising staff. Prior work experience in a community center environment. Proficient in Microsoft Office Suite. Previous experience working with the public or providing customer service.
Working Conditions and Physical Requirements:
WORKING CONDITIONS
Primarily inside in a climate controlled environment; occasionally outside exposed to heat, cold, humidity, rain, etc. (Outside work is curtailed during inclement weather.) May be exposed to slippery or wet conditions when working in community centers with pools. Possibility of physical contact from monitoring, officiating or instructing such field activities as football, soccer, baseball, tennis, etc. Exposed to steady and fairly loud noises from people participating in recreational activities. Exposed to allergy causing agents such as bee and wasp stings, poison oak and ivy, fiddle-back spiders, etc. Occasional exposure to chemical irritants such as acrylic and oil paints, glazes and paint thinners, cleansers, etc. Frequently required to work irregular hours such as shifts, weekends, and overtime. Local travel on a daily basis. Subject to periodic stress from working with difficult or irate individuals and disadvantaged persons from various socio-economic backgrounds, i.e., gangs, etc.
PHYSICAL REQUIREMENTS
Near vision enough to perform duties such as reading and reviewing written correspondence. Far vision enough to perform duties such as observing employees and participants involved in recreational activities. Speech and hearing enough to communicate clearly and distinctly in person or by telephone.
Other Notes:
The City of Oklahoma City may use the services of HireRight, Inc., a consumer reporting agency, for lawful employment purposes, to collect background information about you in connection with your employment or application for employment.
For further information please visit: http://agency.governmentjobs.com/
]]></text></news-item>