<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C393-5184-3988-3CFB"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Washington: HON. ADAM B. SCHIFF OF CALIFORNIA IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES Friday, March 14, 2014</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Library of Congress, The Government of USA has issued the following Speech:
Mr. SCHIFF. Mr. Speaker, I rise today in honor of Women's History Month. Each year, we pay special tribute to the contributions and sacrifices made by our nation's women. It is an honor to pay homage to outstanding women who are making a difference in my Congressional District. I would like to recognize a remarkable woman, Ruth Williams of West Hollywood.
Ms. Williams is one of the original founders of the City of West Hollywood. Incorporated in 1984, West Hollywood has been her home for over sixty years. Her history of activism and volunteerism in West Hollywood is astonishing. She has served as a member of the Eastside Redevelopment Project Area Committee since its inception, is a former board member of Good Neighbors, and has organized the annual Fourth of July Picnic and Holiday Food Drive for many years. With a strong commitment to public safety issues, Ms. Williams helped create the original Disaster Volunteer Core Committee, worked tirelessly with the Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department to create neighborhood watch groups, and served on West Hollywood's Public Safety Commission. Ms. Williams also founded Citizens for Seniors and helped draft West Hollywood's first rent control ordinance while serving on the City's Rent Stabilization Commission.
As Director of Advocacy at the National Council of Jewish Women/Los Angeles (NCJW/LA), Ms. Williams has firsthand knowledge of the need for providing social services in the community. She strives to educate the community about current issues such as child abuse, human trafficking, domestic violence, teen bullying, and human rights, as well as advocate for domestic violence shelter funding. Many of the NCJW/LA programs under Ms. Williams' leadership have received statewide and federal recognition.
In addition to Ms. Williams' work in the community and with NCJW/LA, she is also active in the Hollywood National Organization for Women, is a former Chair and life member of the Fairfax High School Alumni Association, current Vice Chair of the Fairfax Business Association, and is involved in various political organizations. Ms. Williams has received numerous awards, including the 2010 Los Angeles County Older American Recognition Day Award, a City of West Hollywood Senior Advisory Board Award, and a city proclamation to recognize March 15, 2013 as ``Ruth Williams Day'' in honor of her 75th birthday.
I ask all Members to join me in honoring an exceptional woman of California's 28th Congressional District, Ruth Williams.
For more information please visit: http://thomas.loc.gov/
]]></text></news-item>