<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C449-3313-DF41-7641"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Looking ahead to this week</title><source>Sun-Sentinel (Fort Lauderdale, Florida)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Maria Sachs, member, Florida Senate
Revenues from dog racing have been steadily declining for years and its cruelty to animals has become indisputable. So why do we allow this "sport" to persist? It's simple: Florida law requires tracks to conduct races in order to offer other forms of gaming, such as card rooms. Now is the time to change the law. "Decoupling" will allow dog tracks to cease mandatory racing but still be allowed to conduct other gaming. The Legislature might not be able to teach an old dog new tricks, but it can certainly change an old law that's doing more harm than good.
Tom Shea, CEO, Right Management
Keep eyes open for a bipartisan bill coming out of the Senate Banking Committee to eliminate Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, the U.S.-owned mortgage financing companies. Will Congress take real action on housing finance reform despite election year politics? Aiming to protect taxpayers against future bailouts, while keeping access to mortgages open, the bill is likely to draw heated debate. Ironically, the two companies, which taxpayers bailed out with $187.5 billion in 2008, have repaid that debt and are producing high returns to the U.S. Treasury.
Rabbi Sheldon Harr, Temple Kol Ami Emanu-El
Apparently someone with inside information was able to steal $600,000 to $700,000 from Pastor Joel Osteen's Sunday morning collection plate. I presume many of us religious leaders are amazed -- perhaps even envious? -- at the amount of support he elicits. I only hope that all free-will charitable donations, for the whatever the cause, are always spent well, going to the right places and persons.
Archbishop Thomas Wenski, Archdiocese of Miami
Later this month, President Obama will meet Pope Francis at the Vatican. Expect the Pope to support U.S. bishops in their concerns about the erosion of religious freedom represented by the ill-considered HHS "contraceptive" mandate. But at same time, Pope will remind the president of the need for America to resist a "globalization of indifference" -- seeking solutions that address on the world level, policies that result in the exclusion of the poor and marginalization of whole populations. I would also expect the Pope to urge Obama to do more to open relations with Cuba.
Eleanor Sobel, member, Florida Senate
Would you like French fries or anabolic steroids with your hamburger? Do you think it's right to make it this easy to obtain steroids, HGH and other anti-aging drugs? Right now, cash-only clinics across the state are acting without any form of supervision, many times to the detriment of the consumer. My health care act bill, SB746, will bring these clinics under the auspices of the Agency for Health Care Administration. These clinics need to be regulated like every other health care clinic in the state. Floridians should know that we will not tolerate under-the-table health care dealings.
Barbara Sharief, mayor, Broward County
Citizens with insurance tend to care for themselves before problems become worse, which costs less. Citizens without insurance, usually working people with low incomes, wait until they face emergencies. That costs more and they can't pay. In the end, businesses and individuals who pay for insurance pick up the tab. We need to fix this. It is unfortunate that the Florida Legislature refuses to accept more than $50 billion in federal money to insure the poor between now and 2020 through Medicaid expansion. If Florida does not take the money, it will be costly for every citizen in the state.
Mike Ryan, mayor, Sunrise
In 2002, voters overwhelmingly demanded the county and municipalities build a system to dispatch the closest medical rescue unit to serious medical emergencies, no matter where the rescue unit calls "home." A decade of work by many has improved interoperability. Over the past year, Sunrise, Lauderhill, Tamarac and North Lauderdale (and separately Sunrise and Davie) have demonstrated "closest unit automatic aid" improved response times. When a closer medical rescue unit from a neighboring municipality is dispatched, patients can receive help quicker. Let's work together to improve public safety by expanding closest-unit automatic aid response. Sometimes, minutes matter.
Ina Lee, president, Travelhost Elite of Greater Fort Lauderdale
Fort Lauderdale Beach is getting ready to Rock the Ocean in the 2nd annual Tortuga Music Festival April 12-13. Headliners Luke Bryan, Eric Church, Sheryl Crow, Ziggy Marley and Train are just a few from the star-studded lineup. Besides great music, this is a festival with a purpose, raising awareness and money to protect the world's oceans and marine research and conservation.
Jack Seiler, mayor, Fort Lauderdale
On March 17, Fort Lauderdale will launch a new free midday bus service for the Uptown Business District. The Uptown Link will service the Tri-Rail station and Cypress Creek corridor Monday through Friday from 10 a.m. to 3 p.m. This new transportation initiative is designed to create connectivity, enhance mobility and improve traffic flow by promoting the use of public transit.
Burnadette Norris-Weeks, attorney,
Burnadette Norris-Weeks PA
There is a new law involving the collection of absentee ballots that may affect how campaigns are run in the future. In the past, well-known campaign strategists and savvy politicians figured out ways to pay campaign workers for the pick-up and delivery of absentee ballots. Now, a crime will be committed by anyone who physically possesses more than two absentee ballots per election, not including their own or that of an immediate family member. Beware of anyone who wants to touch your absentee ballot. It is far better to return it yourself than be a potential witness to a crime.
]]></text></news-item>