<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C451-9A3B-80C0-7184"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Vocal critic of chili smells takes tour of Sriracha plant</title><source>San Bernardino Sun (California)</source><author>Sarah Favot</author><text><![CDATA[IRWINDALE >> One of the most vocal critics of the smells coming from a factory that makes the popular Sriracha hot chili sauce toured the facility Friday.
Dena Zepeda, an Irwindale resident who circulated a petition last fall asking air quality inspectors to investigate the Sriracha odors, was part of a small tour group that was led around the facility to see how Sriracha is made.
But Zepeda declined to comment on her tour.
Zepeda has said the Sriracha fumes have aggravated her throat and have forced her and her family to stay inside her home when the odor is at its strongest.
Last month Huy Fong Foods CEO David Tran opened the doors to his 650,000 square-foot facility on Azusa Canyon Road so the community and Sriracha lovers could see his state of the art equipment that produces the bright red rooster sauce in action.
After a public hearing last month at Irwindale City Hall where the City Council was considering sanctioning the factory, Tran urged residents who complained about the smell to tour the factory.
My plant has an open door, he said. Anyone who has questions is welcome to first-hand see how we do it. Anytime we will let you come in. Anytime. You just make a call and first-hand you see what we are doing.
Huy Fong has operated four tours a day for the past month. Hundreds of people have flocked to the facility, according to Tran.
After signing a non-disclosure agreement and donning a hair net, visitors are whisked around the factory in a golf cart.
The tour starts with a look at the hoppers where the chilies are dumped right from the trucks that deliver the chilies from Kern County farms.
The chilies are ground as soon as they arrive at the factory, which lasts for about four months. That process ended in mid-November.
Right now at the factory, garlic and sugar is being added to the chilies that have been ground, then mixed with salt and vinegar.
The sauce is then bottled, boxed, stacked on pallets and packaged for distributors.
At the end of the tour visitors are asked to fill out an Odor Survey, which asks the guest if they experienced odors or fumes, to describe the smells and to rate the smell as either: slight, mild or strong. The survey also asks if the odors were experienced inside or outside the factory.
The city has given Huy Fong until April to work with the South Coast Air Quality Management District to address the odors. A lawsuit filed by the city of Irwindale against Huy Fong in Los Angeles County Superior Court is also pending.
Donna Lam, Huy Fong s executive operations manager, declined to comment on Zepeda s visit.
]]></text></news-item>