<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C472-BAD8-489B-412E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Turkish column views Alevi attitudes, need to foster inclusion</title><source>BBC Monitoring Europe - PoliticalSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Text of report by Turkish privately-owned, mass-circulation daily Hurriyet website on 13 March
[Column by Taha Akyol: "The Alevi Factor"]
Incidents like the funeral of Berkin Elvan [a teenaged boy who was struck by a police-fired teargas canister during the Gezi Park protests of June 2013 and died in March 2014 after spending the interval in a coma] and the Gezi protests are not, with regard to their general character, sectarian or identitarian movements, but rather widespread societal protest movements.
Yesterday, a vast crowd saw Berkin off to eternity...
But it is true that the tendency to protest against the established order is stronger among the Alevis.
The tendency for protest, and the longing for equality, is strong among all of those groups who feel they have been excluded by the majority and in the implementations of the state. Throughout history, this has been what it means to be a Catholic in Great Britain, a Protestant in France, or a Catholic or a "Negro" even in liberal America. They have experienced very bloody repression as well.
Sociologist Hilmi Ziya Ulken explains that the Jewish communities that in Europe had been socialist, internationalist, and ultra-secular became religious and nationalist when they migrated to Palestine.
Do you see just how much more determinant the nature of the political order is than one's "essential" identity?
From Diffidence to the Public Squares
That the Alevis have felt themselves to have been victimized is not without reason, unfortunately...
Even the most conservative Sunni needs to open his heart and see and feel this reality.
When I was writing my book Mezhep ve Devlet [Sect and State], I was very touched by [an excerpt from] a poem I found. A poem by Ismail Noksani Baba, from Erzurum, who lived in the 18th century:
Yezidler elinde muskil halimiz
Munkir munafik fers etti yolumuz
[Our difficult situation among the Yezids [Sunnis]
And the deniers and the hypocrites [both referring to Sunnis] made our path]
Thus the Alevis, because of this "difficult situation," lived in a diffident manner, turned inward, and to some extent for this reason, myths were made up about them. But urbanization and education have put an end to their timidity, and they now have educated spokesmen, associations, and foundations. They want equal treatment from the state. They are bringing cases in the ECHR [European Court for Human Rights] and conducting demonstrations in the public squares.
According to KONDA
The findings of KONDA [public opinion research firm] show the anti-authority protest tendency of the Alevis:
-The proportion of Sunnis who consider the use of teargas by police in incidents of social unrest to be a violation of human rights is 59 per cent; among Alevis, it is 90 per cent...
-Among Sunnis, those who consider police intervention in public demonstrations to be wrong amount to 50 per cent, and among Alevis, 80 per cent...
-31 per cent of Sunnis, while 93 per cent of Alevis, consider the Gezi Park incidents to have been an effort to attain rights...
-Among Sunnis, those who see criticism of the government as a requirement of democracy are 87 per cent, while among Alevis, 93 per cent...
-53 per cent of Sunnis consider marriage with someone from a different sect to be normal, and 85 per cent of Alevis...
-Those who say that newspapers and television should be controlled as needed are 60 per cent among Sunnis and 39 per cent among Alevis.
Both the public squares and the statistics show that the Alevis are more critical towards the established order, and have a higher tendency to protest.
Equal Citizenship
If KONDA's questions were to be asked today of the constituency of the [Islamic sect leader Fethullah] Gulen community, or had been asked during the 28 February [1997] period of the rank-and-file of today's AKP [Justice and Development Party], you should have no doubts that the "protest" tendency would have manifested in the same way. Indeed, the AKP was established and developed with a longing for liberal democracy, and has only turned authoritarian in its third term.
This means that as long as feelings of having been victimized and repressed are not eliminated in society, protest movements will not end, and will even gradually increase! For that reason, principles like "the political neutrality of the state" and "the state's remaining equidistant to different faiths," which is the most important element in the definition of secularity, are not things dreamed up by philosophers but rather principles of universal law taught by the history of democracy, which has been full of great suffering.
In the hands of those who govern, the state has enormous powers. On the basis of a fixed majority, to increase the feelings of being repressed among a numerical minority or among sectors that are in political opposition produces no other results than increasing social tension. The only way to become a society that is harmonious and at peace is laws, implementations, and just as importantly, a style, that will strengthen the feelings of "equal citizenship" and "an impartial state."
Source: Hurriyet website, Istanbul, in Turkish 13 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>