<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C489-260F-ED2F-F958"><date>2014-03-15</date><title></title><source>Coffs Coast Advocate (New South Wales)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TO THE brainless cretin in Bultitude St, Woolgoolga, on Friday night letting off illegal fireworks. My poor dogs were frightened out of their wits and spent the night hiding, shaking under the bed. You may be a hero to your drunken mates, but to us you are a sad old man.
TO THE guys in a red car who were doing burnouts through Bruxner Park. In the meantime they came around a corner on the wrong side of the road, nearly taking out two pushbike riders and myself coming the other way in a car.
TO THE man that got out and abused an L-plate driver at the Englands Rd roundabout. Not cool.
TO A local petrol station. We put $50 worth of your e85 petrol in our brand-new car and got water in our fuel tank. The bill to fix it was $1400 so we put our insurance claim through but yous denied our claim due to no other fuel contamination complaints in Coffs Harbour. I've heard other people have had the same problem with your petrol. If you have, please send your claim through.
TO HOSPITAL parking. Thumbs up to those with four-wheel drives who park on the grass so cars can use paved spaces. Thumbs down to the funding of upkeep at the hospital that doesn't fill in the potholes that appear at those access points after rain so it is dangerous for those four-wheel drivers to try to park on the grass.
TO THE people who have nothing better to do than complain about hardworking garbos.
TO THE owner of the black and white cat in Toormina that goes around yowling every night, waking me up. Please keep it inside at night.
TO THE female mannequins/dolls placed on the 10th fairway at the golf course to be aimed at by (golfers). This is disgracefully sexist, offensive and completely out of order.
TO THE two boys riding their skateboards down Toormina Rd this week.
TO THE bully of a man at Sapphire Beach who is renowned for his complaints against his neighbours. It's about time you got a life and stopped making false accusations. Pity your grandiose thoughts of believing your rights are more important than others' are spoiling the area. Thought this quote was applicable to you: "Minding your business eliminates half the problems in your life."
TO THE residents of (a Coffs Harbour street) for abusing and threatening children with disabilities on a daily basis.
TO A P-plater speeding through a school zone.
TO THE trucks using compression braking in town. I followed one on Wednesday and not once did his brake lights come on, just engine breaking. No need.
TO THE drivers of the dump trucks with trailers on Waterfall Way who don't give a rats about the speed limit. Last Thursday I followed one (trailer number and rego noted) and when we got to Boggy Creek and the speed limit dropped to 60kmh for trucks, I slowed to 80kmh and the driver still pulled away from me.
TO THE driver of a four-wheel drive who parked his car (Victorian number plates) across the last two car spaces available at a High St medical centre on Tuesday about 2.45pm. He locked the car then proceeded to walk not in the direction of the medical centre but towards town. It's amazing how the older generation flap their gums about the disrespect of the younger generation.
TO THE maroon Ford Falcon that drove out of a southside fast food drive-through and proceeded to throw the rubbish out the window onto the road.
TO THE two idiots who pulled out on me from the single entry point on the Englands Rd roundabout. I was already well and truly on the roundabout and had to brake hard to avoid hitting you both. Don't know what happened on the other side when you both tried to exit onto Stadium Dr side by side in a single-lane exit point.
TO THE pushbike riders who ride five-wide in groups on busy roads. Fair enough, use the road, but do it properly and people might not complain so much.
TO THOSE on bicycles riding on the main roads (eg. 15 minutes to 6am, on Hogbin Dr) when bike roads were provided to ride on safely, all the way to Coffs Harbour.
IF YOU have bothered to get on a bike you'll know the Hogbin Dr cycleway is not made for "road" bikes hence the name.
WHAT is it with people complaining about bicycle riders riding on roads? Seriously. Get over it. They might hold you up for, what, two seconds as you pass safely. Wow, that's a massive inconvenience. They have just as much right to be on the road as cars whether there is a bike path or not.
TO THE pedestrian crossing on Gordon St. The crossing is too close to the roundabout as motorists on the outside lane are coming around too fast. Pedestrians are at risk of being hit. I have witnessed several close calls.
To contribute to Thumbs Up Thumbs Down: Email your Bouquet or Brickbat to editorial@coffscoastadvocate.com.au, or post on The Coffs Coast Advocate Facebook page when the call for Thumbs goes out on a Wednesday afternoon.
]]></text></news-item>