<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C587-5956-2B5A-7CD9"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Arm-twisters anonymous; From oil companies to think tanks, many groups wield secret power over our politicians, argues Mary Riddell</title><source>The Daily Telegraph (London)</source><author>Mary Riddell</author><text><![CDATA[A Quiet Word: Lobbying, Crony Capitalism and Broken Politics in Britain
by Tamasin Cave and Andy Rowell
400PP, BODLEY HEAD, T £18 (PLUS £1.35 P&P) 0844 871 1515 (RRP £20, EBOOK £8.03) ***
Lobbyists are the zombies of the political world.
Despite endless, if half-hearted, efforts by politicians to rid themselves of this tribe, they refuse to die. The first problem in any attempt to root out rogue influencers is that we are all lobbyists now.
From bishops castigating the Government for neglecting the poor to patients demonstrating against the closure of their local hospital, vested interests try - often quite properly - to make their voices heard above those of their opponents.
But, as the authors of an ordinary person's guide to lobbying correctly point out, there is an imbalance. The parent who wants a lollipop lady at the school gates is not to be compared to the chieftains of the £2 billion "influence industry" who use their contacts to advance the interests of profit-hungry corporations.
Our choice of food and drink, our wars, our energy security and the future of a warming planet are all being manipulated to a greater or lesser extent by influencers operating far below the radar. Tamasin Cave and Andy Rowell, both influential campaigners for greater transparency among lobbyists, aim to spell out the risk they pose and dispel the mystique that surrounds their methods.
Take the danger first. The arm-twisters on Cave and Rowell's hit list - people working for the food industry, big pharma and cigarette and alcohol manufacturers - may be very undesirable.
But as any casual reader might infer, they aren't all that good at what they do. Smoking is on the wane, as is alcohol consumption in at least some parts of the population.
As for unhealthy food, a cursory glance at any newspaper will reveal copious claims about the curse of sugar, often accompanied by a detailed checklist of rogue foods. Equally, papers are hardly short of articles rehearsing the risks of excessive drinking, passive smoking and other modern curses that some lobbyists are trying (and increasingly failing) to inflict upon the masses.
Still, politicians, as Cave and Rowell suggest, are hopeless at stamping out improper lobbying - not least because lobbying is what politicians do after (or even during) their parliamentary careers.
Both the Tories and Labour have a substantial roll call of those who regard themselves (explicitly, in the case of one former minister) as "cabs for hire", ready to pull strings for those who pay for leverage.
This spider's web of collusion is impossible for the general public to unravel. As the authors point out, the Lobbying Bill currently before Parliament falls woefully short of transparency. Who, then, is to shine a light on the murky ways of lobbyists?
Cave and Rowell provide some useful examples, but their account is short on depth and detail. Partly, the problem is the ambitious task they have set themselves. The pharmaceutical industry alone would merit a book of exploration, as would the petroleum multinationals, the nuclear lobby and the other giants this text seeks to slay.
There are some good hits, as well as familiar stories, such as Shell's record in the Niger Delta, which certainly bear repeating. If the book posits a Manichean world in which the struggle of good versus bad sometimes leaves little room for nuance, that is the fault and virtue of all polemics.
The portrayal of the media, however, will strike many journalists as superficial. When some, even those in the profession, portray newspaper writers as gullible saps at the mercy of influencers, it is not surprising if others follow suit. Yet the facts simply do not bear this out.
From the "cash for questions" investigation and this newspaper's forensic inquiry into MPs' expenses to the current furore over sugar, the media has been diligent in excavating shady secrets. For sure, some journalists are climate change deniers or supporters of other dubious causes, but they are perfectly capable of forming their opinions without some lobbyist telling them what to write. (In the same way, the repeated assertion that some think tanks are dubiously financed "wonk whores" offers a partial picture of a world in which more scrupulous research organisations seek to influence public policy in a wholly ethical manner.)
If lobbying is to become more transparent, the awkward, contrarian British media is far more likely to be a solution than a problem. The fourth estate, for all its faults, is also the much-needed watchdog of democratic values.
]]></text></news-item>