<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C714-38E0-63A9-74AB"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Pooches are pretty in pink, blue, purple ...</title><source>The Lawton Constitution (Oklahoma)</source><author>TIFFANY MARTINEZ ; &lt;PrimitiveTag T_TYPE="LOC"&gt;STAFF WRITER TMARTINEZ@LAWTONCONSTITUTION.COM</author><text><![CDATA[The latest trend in the dog grooming world - creative pet styling - has made its way to Southwest Oklahoma. While the poodle-painting fashion fad grows in popularity, it also continues to spark controversy among animal lovers across the country. Seasoned pet groomers within the community, however, say the designing, dye and decorations are nothing more than a safe, pleasant
- sometimes overly complicated
- pampering for furry friends.
"I get people that say it's mean, cruel or abusive to the animal, but it truly isn't - it's all in the way you do it," said Leslie Uhlenhake, owner of Bella Luna Pet Resort in Elgin. "We do it in a way that the pet enjoys it, and we are always gentle."
In addition to hair coloring services, Uhlenhake's spa offers massaging baths, blueberry facials and temporary pet tattoos. She began her business three years ago.
"We practice aroma therapy; we keep it relaxing for the dog," Uhlenhake said. "It's always done in a warm and safe environment. If the dog is stressed out we will either find another way to do it, or we won't do it at all."
Uhlenhake, like many other pet groomers, uses the same coloring technique that is used when humans receive color treatments at a salon: foiling. It is used to separate and target certain strands of hair on animals when dyeing different parts of their bodies. Lawton groomer Carmen Murriel, owner and operator of Fresh Pet Grooming, says that while she enjoys the end result, the foiling process is a tricky procedure. Management and upkeep of a pet's new 'do can also be tiresome.
"Coloring - it's a long task, and it's semi-permanent, which means every time it gets wet, it fades a little more," Murriel said. "That means it may get on your carpet or furniture. You also have make sure while the dog's hair is being colored that it doesn't get in their eyes or nose or ears. We have to take care of the dogs just as we take care of ourselves. ... They have the tendency to want to move around, of course, because they're dogs so you just have to be really careful. If they start shaking, the foil comes off and that color will get everywhere."
Nontoxic products are used for dyeing, but Murriel says this can make little difference in the hands of an inexperienced groomer.
"These are chemicals, even though they are nontoxic," she said. "They can be dangerous. Even if we do put the mineral oils in the eye to protect the eye, if it isn't a goggle or something like that, it could still burn if it gets in an eye. Then you have retina damage or whatever the case may be
- baby oil is nontoxic but if you get some in your eye, you're blinking and irritated for quite some time. Here with me, it's safety, safety, safety first. You can never be too careful."
Her "safety first" rule may require setting aside an extra couple of hours, even in the midst of treating 40 dogs a day, to transform the tone of a dog's coat. Prices depend on the size of the dog, and how much of the dog the
owner wants colored, she said. Coloring of a tail or an ear may run for $20, while an entire dog could cost $100 or more.
Blow pins and stencils are another popular coloring technique, especially since foiling can only be done on a certain type of hair. These tools are most commonly used with the temporary tattooing of pets, intricate or small design-making.
P r e v i o u s winners of the Groom Expo, the w o r l d 's l a r g e s t g r o o m i n g competition held annually in Pennsylvania, include poodles designed after Disney movie themes and complex garden landscapes.
"I've seen dogs that look like lions and buffalo," Murriel said. "I've seen people even sign their name to a design. It's pretty amazing. That's a lot of work, and that's being done by someone who is very artistic."
In recent years, creative grooming has grown into an artistic family affair. In cities such as New York or Dallas, dog owners will grace the runway with pets during fashion shows, complete with matching makeup or outfits. The majority of groomers in the Lawton area stick to basic and solid coloring because requests for such services are few and far between.
Lizzy Druvenga, owner of Zoom Groom Mobile Groomer in Lawton, travels Southwest Oklahoma bathing, trimming and pet styling puppies each day. She has practiced different coloring techniques on the pets of her clients, as well as her own animals, and agrees that the task should be left to professionals.
The process is lengthy indeed, she said, but that isn't always a bad thing - especially for the dog.
"Dogs love attention more than anything else, and being dyed gets them a lot of attention," Druvenga said. "I would say every dog I have dyed has enjoyed the extra attention. Whether or not they know it's because of the dye, they like being treated extra special."
Feather extensions, nail painting and bow arrangements are additional forms of creative grooming, which are also offered by most area groomers.
"I would recommend (creative grooming) to other pet owners," Druvenga said. "It's just fun and adds another way to express your pet's personality. I think this trend is becoming more popular. It's not for everyone, but most people really love it."
]]></text></news-item>