<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C721-D95F-CA70-BE09"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Tap water - Mpumalanga's ticking time bomb; Parents are keeping their children away from schools, the local pharmacy has run out of anti-diarrhoea medication and a councillor says the water smells like sh*t</title><source>The Star (South Africa)</source><author> Sydney Masinga</author><text><![CDATA[Nearly half the four million people who live in Mpumalanga have been warned not to use their tap water - yes, tap water - without sterilising it first.
Mpumalanga is, officially, the worst in the country when it comes to its water management, scoring just 60.9 percent in the most recent Blue Drop Report, which relates to 2012. And the situation could be worse when last year's report is released in May after at least a dozen raw sewage spills were reported across the region between October 2012 and this January.
This week, the South African Human Rights Commission released a report titled "Water and Sanitation, Life and Dignity: Accountability to the People who are Poor", which confirms the dire situation in the province.
In his State of the Province Address, Premier David Mabuza also admitted that the service delivery protests that have plagued Mpumalanga over the past five years have been fuelled mainly by concerns over water.
"Of the many service delivery challenges experienced by our municipalities, access to water tops the list," he said.
But providing people with access to piped water does not guarantee them safe drinking water because, despite the fact that 85 percent of Mpumalanga's population already has access to piped water, diarrhoea remains the second leading cause of death among children under 5, after acute respiratory infections. That's according to the Mpumalanga Department of Health and Social Development's Annual Performance Plan for 2013/2014.
Those most at risk of falling ill or even dying as a result of unsafe drinking water are children, the HIV positive, and the elderly.
Attempts to get exact official figures from the provincial and national health departments about outbreaks of waterborne disease in Mpumalanga were unsuccessful. But by scouring news archives, African Eye News Service is starting to map the extent of outbreaks as well as other water-related information in the province.
National health spokesman Joe Maila said that while hospitals keep their own records of outbreaks, the department "lacks the technology" to consolidate the information.
The most dramatic outbreak on record was between December 2008 and March 2009 when more than half the cholera cases in South Africa were reported in Mpumalanga. Of the 12 787 cases reported nationally, 6 855 were reported in the province. Nationally, 64 people died, nearly half of whom, or 30, were in Mpumalanga.
Residents of Standerton in the Lekwa local municipality are afraid that they are facing a looming cholera outbreak because raw sewage has flowed unchecked into their only water source - the Vaal River - for the past two-and-a-half years.
Widespread cases of diarrhoea were reported in January and independent tests by civil rights organisation AfriForum found high levels of E coli in the tap water.
"National standards require that there be no more than 1 000 units of E coli per 100ml of water, but in Standerton we found one million units per 100ml. This is way above the national standards and presents the potential for a cholera outbreak. We presented our findings to the municipality and we will monitor the situation going forward," said Julius Kleynhans, AfriForum's head of environmental affairs.
AfriForum is liaising with relevant departments and organisations to restore a clean water supply and plans to press criminal charges against officials accused of misspending funds earmarked for the crisis.
The diarrhoea outbreak was so severe that the town's biggest pharmacy ran out of diarrhoea and rehydration medicines in January.
"In January, our clinic treated over 500 children for diarrhoea, which was caused by the tap water. At least 74 of these cases were severe. It was the first time in years that our pharmacy ran out of Gastropect Suspension and Scripto-Lyte in a single month," said Phillip Scheepers, owner of Link Pharmacy.
He said some children developed ringworm from the water.
"We've advised parents to find alternatives to tap water. It's very unfortunate that residents have to spend money they don't have on bottled water and medication for diseases caused by municipal tap water."
Johannes van der Wath, chairman of the main opposition party in the municipality, the DA, blames the town and province's water problems on cronyism.
"How can you give a schoolteacher the responsibility of cleaning municipal water? Cadre deployment needs to stop," said Van der Wath, adding that he hasn't had a decent shower in six months because the water smells "like sh*t or raw fish sometimes".
The DA has been lobbying municipalities across the province to address collapsing water services. The party has identified 12 disease outbreaks between 2012 and this year. The party has laid criminal charges in terms of the National Water Act against the Thaba Chweu, Govan Mbeki and Victor Khanye local municipalities.
The South African Human Rights Commission is also expected to release a report this month regarding water quality issues in Thaba Chweu, Govan Mbeki, and Emalahleni local municipalities.
Spokesman for the Department of Water and Environmental Affairs, Mava Scott, said water samples were collected on February 13 in Standerton for both chemical and bacteriological testing.
The results were presented to the municipality on February 21 and, according to Scott, could not confirm that tap water was to blame for the diarrhoea outbreak.
"Although the results did not confirm the outbreak of diarrhoea, there were some chemical concerns like high content of aluminium in the water," said Scott.
According to the World Health Organisation high aluminium levels in water may be linked to diarrhoea.
Other symptoms are nausea, vomiting, mouth ulcers, skin ulcers, skin rashes and arthritic pain. The effects are short-lived.
Scott said the department's engineers are on site helping the municipality to clean up its water sources.
"Almost 95 percent of the valves required for the project are on-site," he said.
In the meantime residents are continuing to buy in or filter and sterilise their tap water.
Some are cashing in on the crisis, like Hendrik Dippenaar, owner of the Total garage in Standerton. He sells filtered water for R1 a litre - although it cost him R40 000 to replace the |filter when the turbid tap water clogged it up.
Government Investment
In his State of the Province Address, Premier David Mabuza said that over the past five years, the Mpumalanga government has invested in the following water projects:
1) Victor Khanye local municipality (Delmas):
The Delmas Bulk Water Treatment Works (R96 million)
The Bloemendal to Delmas Bulk water pipeline (R171m)
2) Bushbuckridge local municipality:
The Bushbuckridge-Acornhoek Bulk Pipeline and Inyaka Water Treatment Works of 100 megalitres (R1 075 billion)
The Hoxane water treatment plant (R78m), which will be officially opened in a few weeks. More than R221m is also being invested in a reticulation programme.
3) Msukaligwa local municipality (Ermelo):
Temporary Bulk Pipeline (R52m) to restore water supply in surrounding communities
4) Albert Luthuli local municipality (Carolina):
Installation of water treatment system to resolve the mine water pollution at |Carolina.
Water infrastructure is also being upgraded and maintained in Emalahleni, Nkomazi, Mbombela, Dr JS Moroka, Thembisile Hani, Bushbuckridge and Mkhondo at a cost of R171m.
Check Your Water
The Blue Drop Certification system is a campaign that encourages local municipalities to improve their water quality management while empowering consumers with the right information about what is coming out of their taps.
Residents with access to the internet can check the status of the water by visiting this link http:// www.dwaf.gov. za/dir_ws/DWQR/ and typing the name of their town or even suburb.
The most recent data relates to 2012.
Results for last year will be released this May.
Towns with
toxic water
The most recent Blue Drop Report has warned roughly 1.7 million residents living in the following five local municipalities to sterilise their tap water before using it. Any improvements will only be known when last year's results are released in May:
Bushbuckridge local municipality in Bushbuckridge (782 716 people).
Mkhondo local municipality in Piet Retief (96 495 people).
Msukaligwa local municipality in Ermelo (113 000 people).
Nkomazi local municipality in Malalane (523 500 people).
Chief Albert Luthuli local municipality in Carolina (173 168 people).
MEGA steps in
The Mpumalanga Economic Growth Agency (MEGA) has been tasked with addressing the problem of bulk water and sanitation infrastructure in eight selected municipalities.
"While this process has taken longer than anticipated due to the lack of co-operation by some municipalities, we have started to record progress and contractors have been appointed. During this period we undertook a number of initiatives working with the Minister of Water Affairs (Edna Molewa) to deal with the acute bulk water infrastructure challenges in selected areas," said Premier David Mabuza in his State of the Province Address.
The eight municipalities are: Bushbuckridge, Nkomazi, Chief Albert Luthuli, Dr Pixley ka Isaka Seme, Mkhondo, Dipaleseng, Thembisile Hani and Dr JS Moroka.
Nompilo Hadebe has been running Mpilos Pre-School in the township of Sakhile near Standerton for five years. She says she has never experienced cases of severe diarrhoea with any of her children, until recently.
"I have 66 small children in the school, and for the first time in our history, six of them experienced severe diarrhoea in January. We had two water taps in the schoolyard, but we had to remove them after realising that the water was smelly and dirty."
The future of Nompilo's school is uncertain as some of the parents have decided to keep their children at home.
"We use Jik or boil the water for those children whose parents can't afford to give them bottled water. But some of the parents have decided to keep their children at home. I don't know if they will ever come back."
In January, the town's biggest pharmacy, Link Pharmacy, treated at least 500 cases of children with diarrhoea and eventually ran out of anti-diarrhoea and rehydration medicines.
]]></text></news-item>