<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C7A0-6FCE-1C0B-671E"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Phiyega wades into computer tender storm</title><source>The Sunday Independent (South Africa)</source><author> JEFF WICKS </author><text><![CDATA[Police Commissioner Riah Phiyega brought the police's forensic investigation and IT support capability to its knees with the controversial cancellation of three tenders worth billions just hours before they were set to be awarded.
Phiyega's 2am e-mail, which The Sunday Independent has seen, listed three tenders that were to be "withdrawn" because "they did not follow the internal processes of the South African Police Services".
The procurement committee was set to finalise the projects at 9am.
The brief instruction to Freeman Nomvalo, the head of the State Information Technology Agency (Sita), three weeks ago has far-reaching financial implications and could delay the rollout of key justice projects, like the e-Docket system, by up to two years.
Not only does Phiyega's decision scupper development directed by parliament, but also leaves the police without a vital maintenance and support contract for over 100 000 computers across the country.
But documents obtained by the Sunday Independent show that Phiyega signed off on two of the projects personally, and that all three had followed procurement processes required by law.
The first of the cancelled tenders is for the refurbishment of the police's wide area network infrastructure, worth R125 million, which was to upgrade the organisation's bandwidth, as well as cabling and equipping hundreds of police stations. The cancellation effectively stops in its tracks a national network upgrade project started in 2007, on which nearly R3 billion has been spent to date. Phiyega personally signed off on the tender in July 2012.
The second cancelled tender relates to the purchase of an Automated Ballistics Identification System, as well as a maintenance and support contract for three years worth nearly R150m. Used to identify and link firearms and cartridges from crime scenes, this is a critical system in forensic labs. Since 2012 there has been no maintenance contract in place for the system, which places the entire operation at risk. A month before Phiyega took office, the tender was signed by acting head Nhlanhla Mkhwanazi.
The third withdrawal by Phiyega was a service level agreement with Sita, for the maintenance of over 100 000 computers across the country, worth R1.4bn. With the police logging over 15 000 requests for maintenance each month, their IT capabilities are all but destroyed with the cancellation of the agreement. Phiyega signed the deal in October last year.
The failure of the police to upgrade their wide area network, and thereby equip stations, will further prevent vital justice initiatives like the e-Docket system, which is part of the broader Detention Management System.
The system is collaboration between the SAPS, National Prosecuting Authority, Department of Justice and Constitutional Development and the Department of Corrections.
It aims to have a streamlined system from when an emergency call is logged, across the evidence chain from investigation to the time a person is arrested and sentenced.
The tender for the system has been published and cancelled four times since 2008.
It is understood that last year, when the tender was on the verge of award, Phiyega intervened once again and cancelled the tender because it was not a priority.
Phiyega's sweeping decision was highlighted with parliamentary questions last week, in an inquiry as to how many bids had been cancelled by the police.
If bids for the contracts expire, the procurement process will start afresh, meaning further delays of up to two years.
Police spokesman Lieutenant General Solomon Makgale said only Phiyega wanted to be sure that there was adequate "governance".
Makgale said the national commissioner has indicated that one of the things that requires strengthening at the SAPS is governance.
"Procurement of technology products and services is done through Sita. Last year she instructed that going forward, all the services and products procured by Sita on behalf of the police must first be approved by the supply chain management department," he said.
"In February Sita indicated that certain procurement processes had not been followed and the tenders were withdrawn for investigation. The investigation has been concluded and it was found that internal process was followed. Sita has been informed and there is no risk to the SAPS," he added.
In a letter from Nomvalo to Phiyega, which The Sunday Independent has seen, he highlights major delays that would be incurred should the contracts be cancelled and calls for an urgent resolution.
It makes no mention of process not being followed. In fact, there is an emphasis on the involvement of police supply chain management commanders.
Phiyega's reign as commissioner has been mired by controversy, most notably her handling of the Marikana Massacre. It is also not the first time the top cop has run into trouble over tenders.
In the weeks after her appointment, it emerged that she quit her post as director of a company, then - a few days later - headed a probe of the same company for fraud and corruption. In the profile she provided as chairwoman of the investigative task team in 2010, she did not reveal that she ever had links with the company, Lefatshe Technologies.
The Star reported that a few days before investigations began, Phiyega was still listed on the Companies Intellectual Property Commission as a director of Lefatshe.
]]></text></news-item>