<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C7B0-7056-CB9B-FCA1"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>'SHOT AT DAWN FOR SHOWING COMMON SENSE'; Hundreds of men were shot for desertion during World War One. The family of a 22-year-old soldier from the Worcestershire Regiment who was killed by firing squad kept it secret for many years but always believed he was wrongly executed - and nearly 90 years later he was pardoned. JUSTINE HALIFAX reports.</title><source>Birmingham Mail</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ACK Wall served on the Western Front from the beginning of the First World War.
JUntil being shot for desertion, he had an impeccable military career which had seen him involved in extensive battlefield fighting and receiving promotions.
After joining the Worcestershire Regiment at the age of 16 in 1912 as a Drummer Boy, he rose to the rank of Lance Corporal by the start of the Great War in August 1914.
He was later promoted to Sergeant after fighting with his Battalion in every engagement.
An ideal soldier, experienced, battle-hardened and brave.
Yet in 1917 he was shot at dawn for desertion after taking refuge from heavy enemy fire in a bunker and refusing to lead his men into nearcertain death.
With hindsight, it is believed that his execution was most likely a "disgraceful" opportunity to make an example of him by a new senior officer looking to assert his position as someone who meant business.
Adding weight to this theory is that, in a bizarre, twist Jack Wall's execution papers were unusually sent directly to Douglas Haig, who was commander on the Western Front for most of World War One.
They therefore bypassed all other senior personnel who, given Jack's record, may have called for his execution to be halted.
Piet Chielens, who directs In Flanders Fields, the war museum in the Belgian city of Ieper (better known to the soldiers of 1914-18 by its French name, Ypres), said: "It is clear he was an excellent soldier. Then one day he decides to stay in a bunker with eight men because the stretch he has to cover is open to German fire. He is charged with desertion and executed for that one crime."
Lynne Baird, of Yardley, Birmingham, who got in touch to share her great uncle Jack's story, said what Jack did may have been an error in judgment but was probably good soldiering common sense.
During his court-martial on August 20, 1917, in the Belgian town of Poperinge, Jack said he'd remained hunkered down to avoid German gun-fire but did not claim shellshock or battle fatigue.
Instead records suggest that he used tactical arguments in his defence.
But Sergeant (13216) John Thomas Wall, of Bockleton, near Tenbury, Worcestershire, of the 3rd Battalion Worcestershire Regiment, was shot at dawn on September 6, 1917.
It's something that the family had kept a closely guarded secret until recent years.
Grandmother-of-ten Lynne, a carer for her disabled son, who is one of five children - including one who is said to look like Jack - said: "I had never heard anything about my great uncle Jack Wall until a couple of years ago.
"My great grandmother, Fanny Evans was Jack's www.sister.No one ever spoke of it at all. I am very shocked at what happened.
"My aunt, Jill Turner, told me of it and I began to research the story and I have since discovered a wealth of detailed information about him and the events leading up to his execution.
"I believe that he was wrongfully, in my mind, and disgracefully, executed.
"The picture of the execution post at Poperinghe, where Jack was killed is horrible.
"No wonder the family never talked about it. My aunt Jill attends the Cenotaph ceremony with other families every year.
"My dad has never spoken of this to me.
"This is all pretty new to me and I find it hard to believe how the family hid it all for so long.
"Countryside communities remember everything, so that is probably why any mention of Tenbury or Bockleton was never allowed when I was little."
Jack's family strongly believes that he should never have been executed.
And in 2006 - just shy of 90 years after his tragic death - Sgt Wall and 305 other British soldiers were pardoned under a law approved by the British Parliament with the Queen's assent.
the condemned men had been soldiers of exemplary behaviour, courage and leadership but had cracked under the dreadful strain of trench warfare."
Jack was one of those exemplary soldiers and his story also features on the website www.ww1ieper1917.wordpress.com which is dedicated to Ieper 1917.
John Wall's "crime" happened during his company's attack on heavily defended German positions on a ridge.
Mr Putkowksi said: "Weighed down with rifles, buckets of grenades, digging implements and wirecutters, the platoons, at 200-yard intervals, made their way towards the assembly positions.
that these finally stigma their have lived years.' "Plodding through gas-polluted mud, Wall's company was inching over Bellewarde Ridge when the leading platoon lost its way in the darkness. "The British bombardment erupted.
"Two minutes later German heavy guns retaliated, targeting the reinforcements assembled behind the advancing troops.
"Caught on the exposed crest of the Ridge, Wall's platoon column was raked by a storm of enemy shellfire.
"Lt Thomas Randle ordered the platoon to take cover and nine men, including Wall, huddled into a nearby concrete dugout.
"Others cowered outside, partially protected by the emplacement's bulky exterior.
"After a while small parties of the more exposed group made their way forward. Amongst those who squeezed into the dugout was Private W.H. White, who later testified for the prosecution at Wall's trial.
"White recalled that after hearing a summons from outside, six of the men in the dugout departed, leaving himself, Wall and Pte. Rowlands.
"After the shelling had abated Wall and White emerged from the dugout, searched vainly for the rest of the Company and concluded that they had gone back towards dugouts in a wood.
"White added: 'Just then the enemy got up their barrage and so we remained in the dugout.
"'We stayed there all that day and through the next day, the 11th August, up till about 6pm when the shelling had ceased.' "Wall, White and Rowlands then returned to the dugouts and remained there until the Company returned on the morning of 12 August, when the sergeant reported himself present to the duty sergeant.
"On being asked where he had been, Wall explained that he had reported what had happened to an officer from another regiment.
"Wall was subsequently charged with desertion and tried by Field General Court Martial on 20 August.
"He was undefended but gave sworn testimony about his conduct.
"He said: 'As far as I knew the Company was going up in the supports for an attack.
"'On the way we lost direction and halted. The enemy opened fire and our officer ordered us, 'to take cover.' .
"'I looked round for cover from my platoon.
"'I did not find any place except a concrete dugout in which I found nine or 10 men and I joined them there, the rest of the company was sheltering around the dugout and in an old piece of trench.
"'I stopped in the dugout. "'Whilst there Sergeant Barlow of my company came in and said he wanted 'four to six men to go an a patrol.' .
"'He got his men from the dugout, leaving only Rowlands, White and I there.
"'About five minutes later I went outside to see what the company was doing, or to get some men into the dugout, but I found that the company had gone.'" Mr Putkowski added: "Wall had an impeccable military career.
"He had probably been faced by enemy fire more frequently than any of those who passed judgement on his behaviour.
"But his behaviour and battle experience was of little consequence to the court. Had it been otherwise then the Court Martial Officer attending Wall's trial, Captain Griffith-Jones, an experienced barrister, would have been certain counsel caution.
"The comments of officers confirming the sentences passed on soldiers convicted by courts sometimes make observations to justify their view asoldiers' character, fighting ability and the combat performance of his unit.
"In Wall's case there was only one entry: 'Confirmed: D. Haig 2/9/17.' .
"Since it was Wall's first offence, Haig's isolated confirmation departed from the usual confirmatory procedure."
The officer who authorised Wall's court-martial was celebrated Hampshire cricketer, Lt Col Alexander Johnston, who had taken over from Brigadier General Cranley Onslow barely 24 hours before Wall's platoon set out.
The advance was the first operation Lt Col Johnston approved - and it botched with heavy casualties.
Wall was executed at 5.25 am on September 6 at Poperinghe.
Commenting in his diary, an officer referred to his execution as a "miscarriage of justice".
It seems, therefore, quite possible that Lt Col Johnston deliberately sent the court martial papers straight on Haig, bypassing all other levels of confirmation.
"Given this man's record some senior officer might have objected Wall being executed, and had the sentence commuted, which would have harmed Johnston's position," said Mr Putkowski.
A TRAGIC LETTER TO HIS SISTER SADLY, it seems clear that Jack did not expect to be executed in any event.
Just a day before his trial Jack, pictured below, wrote a loving letter to his sister in which he refers to a photo and tobacco she sent and refers to life after the war.
It reads as follows: "19 August 1917: Sergt J.Wall, 13216 B.Coy, 3rd Battalion Worcs. Regt. B.E.F.Franc.
Dear sister, I now take the pleasure of writing these few lines in answer to your most kind and ever welcome letter which I received quite safe. Pleased to hear that you are in the best of health as it leaves me quite well at the present time of writing.
Well dear Emily, I received the photo alright and I think he looks very nice it is as you say he does look wicked. It's a nice little boy all the same. Dear Emily, I received the tobacco alright. I wrote back and answered your parcel. They must have crossed on the way. Well dear Emily, I had a letter from home the other day they are all getting on alright there at present. We are having some lovely weather over here, very hot, the people are all busy harvesting now. You asked me if I have heard about the draft, well yes. I have heard about them. Well dear Emily, I haven't married that Belgian girl, not yet. I don't think I shall not till after the war, nor where we are because we are not allowed to. Well dear sister, I think I have said all for this time and I will close my short letter in sending my best hope and kisses from your loving brother Jack XXXXXX P.S. Remember me to all. Thanks very much for the tobacco and photo."
]]></text></news-item>