<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C887-8B97-E781-F87F"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Generous response to Woodbridge Have-A-Heart</title><source>Home News Tribune (East Brunswick, New Jersey)</source><author>By, Staff Report</author><text><![CDATA[WOODBRIDGE - The 2014 Woodbridge Township Have-A-Heart food drive collected more than 20,000 pounds of nonperishable food and netted more than $33,200 in cash donations to support the efforts of local food pantries in their work to aid needy families throughout the township, Mayor John E. McCormac announced.
More than 100 township corporations, businesses, retail outlets, school students, charitable organizations and residents contributed to the food drive.
"The Have-A-Heart food drive is one of the most important programs that we as a community participate in each January and February," McCormac said. "I am proud to be part of the effort to extend the generosity of the holiday season and to replenish and restock township food banks. Hunger knows no season and no boundary. It's crucial that we work every day - not just during the holiday season - to collect food as we work to help provide the necessities of life to our neighbors and families who might otherwise go hungry."
This year, the food drive issued a "2/14" challenge to township corporate offices, businesses, retail outlets, restaurants, the hospitality industry, charitable organizations and residents to donate 214 pounds of food or contribute $214 to assist food pantries in providing food and meals to the needy and homeless.
Peter Barcellona, chairman of We Feed Woodbridge, reported that more than 200 pounds of nonperishable food, including canned goods, pre-packaged and boxed foods, baby food and paper products, was collected and sorted for donation by third-grade students from Robert Mascenik School No. 26 in Iselin.
Significant contributors to the 2014 Have-A-Heart food drive include:
Colonia Business Community and Colonia Corner newspaper: $7,300
Structure Tone Inc.: $4,000 and 300 pounds
Wegmans of Woodbridge: 1,000 pounds
Woodbridge ShopRite: 2,500 pounds
Northfield Bank: $2,140
Colonia Country Club: $500
BCB Community Bank: $2,000
Woodbridge YMCA: 2,100 pounds
Goya Food Service: 1,410 pounds
Bessemer Trust Co.: $1,200 and 1,000 pounds
Sansone Auto Group: $500
The food items will be distributed to needy Woodbridge families and individuals through the following food pantries:
Heavens Helper's Pantry, 343 Pearl St., Woodbridge
First Presbyterian Church, 20 Middlesex Ave., Iselin
Trinity Episcopal Church, Trinity Lane, Woodbridge
Metro Park Assembly of God, 48 Berkeley Blvd., Iselin
First Presbyterian Church, 600 Rahway Ave., Woodbridge
St. James Roman Catholic Church, 174 Grove St., Woodbridge
First Presbyterian Church of Avenel, 621 E. Woodbridge Ave.
First Congregational Church-Women of Faith, Barron Avenue, Woodbridge
St. Cecelia Roman Catholic Church, 45 Wilus Way, Iselin
Elijah's Bread Food Pantry, Ridgedale and E. Prospect avenues, Woodbridge
Nonperishable foods can be dropped off any weekday between 8:30 a.m. and 4:30 p.m. at the Woodbridge Township Public Health Center, 2 George Frederick Plaza. Additional food drop-off locations are at Woodbridge Town Hall, 1 Main St.; the Woodbridge Library, 1 George Frederick Plaza; or at the Woodbridge Community Center, 600 Main St.
]]></text></news-item>