<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C8A5-6647-70D2-D0E3"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>United Nations rep cautions on death penalty</title><source>PNG Post-Courier (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[THE UN special rapporteur on extrajudicial and summary executions, Christof Heyns has cautioned PNG saying the death penalty is not the answer to the current level of violence in the country.
"I am concerned about the possible resumption of executions in PNG which may result in violations of international law," Mr Heyns said.
"I understand that the society is looking for ways to curb the violence it is experiencing, but the death penalty in my view provides a false sense of security. More effective policing of violent crime and education are but two of the areas where the focus should lie."
After a 12-day tour of selected PNG centres, he presented his findings in a Port Moresby last Friday.
He said PNG is likely to grow and play an increased role at least at the regional level in the near future, and has an opportunity to ensure that this future society is based on a solid human rights and rule of law foundation. He examined the level of unlawful killings in as well as efforts to prevent them and ensure justice and redress in such cases.
"There are high levels of violence in PNG. During my visit, I was informed about various types of killings perpetrated in PNG, such as killings related to accusations of sorcery or witchcraft, domestic violence, and killings during tribal fighting. But also the lethal consequences of the excessive use of force by the police and sometimes private security forces," he said.
Mr Heyns also made a series of recommendations to strengthen human rights including the right to life.
Among them is the creation of an efficient national human rights institution, reform of the police investigative unit and creating an enabling environment for the establishment of human rights NGOs.
Another is the involvement of the country's organised legal profession in impact litigation, education on the right to life in primary schools and the establishment of a country office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights.
On the Australian-funded Manus Island regional processing centre, he said: "This is a highly problematic situation. The situation should be resolved as soon as possible, and there must be transparency."
]]></text></news-item>