<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C8DE-1510-551B-39CD"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Miscellaneous repair and maintenance services</title><source>TendersInfo - Contract Awards</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Contract award: Miscellaneous repair and maintenance services The contract is for the completion of maintenance services as part of a multi-technique a fixed term 48 month contract. The contractor must make every working day, corrective and preventive multi-technical maintenance up to level 4 (electrical, mechanical, pneumatic ..) of all site tools Printing Chamalières and sites associated and the conduct of Boiler for two industrial sites (Printing and Stationery) and maintenance of compressors Stationery. Outside the periods of operation of the service receiving and processing requests from the client, the service provides 24/24 and 7/7 days a penalty charge of taking measures in case of an incident on facilities service.
The market is divided into 1 slice firm composed of 3 parts and 7 slices conditional. A firm order, namely: Component I) Chamalières multi-technical package These benefits include: - Corrective and preventive as well as minor improvements in the field of Maintenance: Heating, ventilation, air conditioning, smoke, fluid networks including AC compressors, plumbing, treatment of prevention against legionella. This item represents approximately 7,500 hours of actual work per year excluding management structure - Corrective and preventive as well as minor improvements in the field of Maintenance: Strong currents and low currents. This item represents approximately 3,000 hours of actual work per year excluding management structure. - Corrective and preventive as well as minor improvements in the field of Support: metalworking, woodworking. This item represents approximately 4,500 hours of actual work per year excluding management structure. - The supply of spare parts and consumables for a unit price of 150EUR maximum is included in the package. Component II) package boilers (2 sites) and maintaining compressors (Stationery). These benefits include: - The conduct of the boiler for two industrial sites (Printing and Stationery Chamalières Vic le Comte) that is to say, energy production and maintenance associated with the dual-energy boilers of two industrial sites in the Making tickets (located in Auvergne Printing and Stationery based in Vic le Comte) - Maintenance of compressors installed on the site of Stationery. - This provision excludes the supply of gas or fuel is the responsibility of the BDF. - The supply of spare parts and consumables for a unit price of 150EUR maximum is included in the package.
Component III) component purchase order called "non-package" consisting of: a) the supply of spare parts above the threshold 150EUR/pièce b) benefits of modification and / or major repairs performed on equipment covered by this contract. September conditional slices, namely: Conditional tranches # 1: A passage in the boiler 72h00 take a loss on the delivery pipe boiler for printin Contractor name : COFELY SERVICES (GROUPEMENT GDF SUEZ : COFELY INEO/COFELY AXIMA/ COFELY SERVICES) Contractor address : Agence Auvergne - ZI le Brézet 16 Rue Pierre Boulanger 63017 Clermont-ferrand Implementing agency : Banque de France 57210489100013 39 rue Croix des Petits Champs For the attention of: Marie Pascale-Aboulfaraj 75049 Paris Cedex 01 FRANCE Telephone: +33 473174009 Fax: +33 473174132 E-mail: cham.marches-europeens@banque-france.fr Internet address(es): General address of the contracting authority: www.banque-france.frAddressofthebuyerprofile:https://banque-france.achatpublic.com Electronic access to information: https://banque-france.achatpublic.com Electro Country :France Email : jacques.levan@cofely-gdfsuez.com Ltd.
]]></text></news-item>