<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C954-36C9-3941-4642"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Chinese Estates CEO And Billionaire Joseph Lau Resigns After Court Verdict</title><source>RTT News (United States)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[(RTTNews) - Chinese investment holding company Chinese Estates Holdings Limited (0127.HK) that Executive Director, Chairman and Chief Executive Officer Joseph Lau has resigned from the positions, effective Friday, after being convicted of bribery and money laundering charges. The company appointed his 33-year old son Ming-wai Lau as executive director chairman and acting CEO, effective Friday, to replace him.
Joseph Lau,a billionaire Hong Kong real estate investor, was prosecuted in Macau for committing offenses of bribery and money laundering in relation to the acquisition of the Macau Land. He was sentenced to imprisonment for five years and three months. However, he will not be put into jail as long as he does not set foot in Macau.
He was found guilty of the charges for paying a HK$20 million bribe to disgraced ex-public works chief Ao Man-long, in return for five plots of prime land in Macau. The company said he has filed an application to appeal against the verdict.
Joseph Lau confirmed that the resignation is not due to disagreement with the board. The company said its board does not expect the conviction and resignation to have any material adverse impact its operations and financial conditions.
Joseph Lau has over 39 years of experience in corporate finance, manufacturing and property investment and development. He founded and joined the company in 1989 and has been at the helm since then.
Meanwhile, the younger Lau joined his father's company in 2006 and has been serving as the vice chairman of Chinese Estates. He worked at Goldman Sachs Group, Inc. (GS) and hedge fund Longview Partners LP, both in London, prior to joining the company. He is also the nephew of Amy Lau, Yuk-wai, a non-executive director of the company.
Chinese Estates Holdings closed trading in Friday's regular trading session on the HKEx at HK$19.80, up HK$0.10 or 0.51% on a volume of 38,500 shares.
For comments and feedback: contact editorial@rttnews.com
Copyright(c) 2014 RTTNews.com. All Rights Reserved
]]></text></news-item>