<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C9FB-B825-F63B-A85D"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Protesters block logging equipment from Rocky Branch; Pre-strip mine logging temporarily halted Thursday morning</title><source>Harrisburg Daily Register (Illinois)</source><author>Tom Kane, TKANE@DAILYREGISTER.COM</author><text><![CDATA[COTTAGE TOWNSHIP Protesters claiming Thursday that logging trucks contracted to Peabody Energy were exceeding the legal weight limits on Rocky Branch Road, attempted to block the progress of those vehicles by stretching a yellow tape across the road.
The protesters - who numbered fewer than 25 - were led by environmentalist Georgia Mason De La Garza and ranged in age from college students to older local environmentalists.
The group was observed blocking the road with a yellow caution tape when the reporter arrived on the scene at 11:15 a.m., but the tape was lowered and the protesters then began allowing private vehicles to pass on the roadway moments later.
Rocky Branch citizen Allan Porter was present when the protesters were blocking the road. He witnessed the event and had sharp words with a woman and some of the men of the logging company contracted by Peabody Energy.
Porter said, "I just told them they was breaking the law and that one girl, she got hostile. She was with that contractor working for Peabody. She said, 'Who are you?' and I said 'I just live right up there and you guys are breaking the law."
The truck had driven right by a sign that stated the road had a ten ton weight limit, Porter said.
"She said, 'We don't care what the sign says.'
"'You will when the law gets here,' I said.
"She was still mouthing off when two of their guys dragged her away," said Porter.
"Then I asked them where they found a little smart aleck like that and they got in my face. One guy was belly to belly with me. I wouldn't let him stir me up and he backed off. A couple of guys calmed them down."
Ken Clore, chief deputy for the Saline County Sheriff 's Department arrived later.
"We had a call from the coal mine and then a call from the loggers that people were blocking the road out there on Rocky Branch Road. The first call came in at 10:55 a.m. and the second one at 11 a.m. We arrived and shortly after us the state police arrived," Clore said.
The deputies found a group of individuals who were trying to block the loggers. Clore said he believes the loggers were from John Hunter's Company out of Goreville.
"The owner of Hunter's company was there and he was asking about weight limits on the road. He talked with the protesters and no one wanted to file anything," Clore said.
Neither did the loggers want to press charges, according to Clore.
"I talked with the loggers and they just wanted to get back to work," he said.
"We (Sheriff's deputies) stayed around to make sure no one got hurt. When there didn't seem to be any threat of violence we left."
Clore said, "The DNR officer on the scene said they had a permit to log that property. We had traffic accidents here in the county to take care of and we had four deputies counting myself at the scene, two state troopers and one DNR officer."
The loggers resumed work clearing the trees on Peabody land and the road was clear and unobstructed at 2 p.m.
One of many points of contention with the mine permitting for the protestors was Illinois Department of Natural Resources granting the mine a permit Wednesday while the Illinois Environmental Protection Agency has yet to grant a permit regarding the water outflow from the future mine and its affect on area waterways. The comment period for the National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System ends March 19. The IEPA says logging is permissible during the comment period, though mining itself is not.
Chris Young, public information officer for Illinois Department of Natural Resources said in a prepared statement, "The decision to grant a permit to Peabody Energy for a surface coal mine in Saline County was made in accordance with state law. All permit applications are reviewed according to statute and the Illinois Department of Natural Resources must approve or deny permits based on what the law requires. The permit issued to Peabody Energy was issued and became effective Wednesday, March 12."
Kim Biggs, public information officer for IEPA said in a prepared statement, "Peabody is allowed to commence timber harvesting activities at the Rocky Branch mine property pursuant to 40 CFR 122.27. Timber harvesting is a non-point source activity and therefore exempt from NPDES permitting. Mining activities are not permitted to commence at Rocky Branch prior to an NPDES permit being issued."
The protesters, including local citizen Allan Porter are questioning whether Peabody is violating local laws pertaining to weight limits on local roadways.
De Le Garza said she used Google to obtain the weights of one piece of equipment and its transport vehicle and that total was 118,000 pounds. She said she contacted a dealer for the weight of the piece of equipment and another dealer for the weight of the transport vehicle. She used her cell phone to access the Internet.
The posted weight limit for the road is ten tons or 20,000 pounds.
Saline County Highway Engineer Jeff Jones said Clore contacted him to determine if the logging company had applied for a special permit to haul over Rocky Branch Road, which is a part of the county's highway system.
"The logger has not inquired about a special permit to haul over Rocky Branch Road," Jones said.
]]></text></news-item>