<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="C9FD-5834-DDCB-D8E0"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Campaign Finance Scandal: Donor launders $2 million - must be the Koch Brothers!</title><source>The Minority Report</source><author>Michael Becker</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 15, 2014 (The Minority Report:http://www.theminorityreportblog.com/ Delivered by Newstex) Breitbart is reporting that there's dirty money in politics. No, the story isn't about the Koch Brothers, it's about Hillary Clinton and her campaign donors.
Jeffrey Thompson, a major Democratic donor who became wealthy by providing corporate services to the government of the District of Columbia, pled guilty on Monday in federal court to two felony charges of making illegal campaign contributions to local and federal elections.U.S. Attorney for the District of Columbia Ron Machen, who prosecuted the case, said in a press conference[1] after Thompson entered his guilty plea that Thompson's illegal donations to two Washington, D.C. mayoral elections and six city council elections were nearly $2 million. Thompson's illegal donations to one 2008 Democratic presidential campaign exceeded $800,000.It looks like there's more to come too. Thompson is getting a sweetheart deal so he can spruce up his tennis game, and it sounds like he's singing a tune for the Feds.Machen claimed that Thompson implicated two high profile District of Columbia politicians and one 'senior advisor' to a 2008 presidential campaign in his illegal scheme. Though Machen did not name either the presidential campaign or the 'senior advisor,' the Washington Post has reported[2] the campaign was Hillary Clinton's and the 'senior advisor' is long time Clinton confidante Minyon Moore. Under the plea deal[3], Thompson could serve as little as six months in jail if he fully and truthfully cooperates with federal prosecutors who are currently building cases against Thompsons' unindicted co-conspirators. Machen said that list included political candidates, public officials, and political operatives. Machen said that Thompson 'admitted to bankrolling efforts to secretly inject millions of dollars into local and federal elections.' He added that 'DC campaigns have been compromised by covert corporate money for years….Jeffrey Thompson's guilty plea pulls back the curtain to expose widespread corruption.'Guess what? All the people Thompson funneled money to were Democrats.Thompson also admitted to spending more than $600,000 on illegal federal campaign donations used to promote the campaign of a Democratic candidate for president in 2008 (identified in the press as the Hillary Clinton campaign) in the states of Texas, Indiana, Pennyslvania, North Carolina, and in the territory of Puerto Rico.Color us shocked!Image source: WJLA TVSource: Dem Donor Connected To Hillary Aide Pleads Guilty $2 Million in Illegal Campaign Donations[4] http://www.zemanta.com/?px http://www.therightcurmudgeon.com/subscribe/http://www.zemanta.com/?px [1]: http://www.wusa9.com/story/news/local/2014/03/10/jeff-thompson-vincent-gray-dc-mayor-shadow-campaign-press-conference/6269845/ [2]: http://www.nationaljournal.com/politics/clintonworld-goes-after-the-washington-post-20140311 [3]: http://archive.wusa9.com/assetpool/documents/140310073854_Thompson,%20Jeffrey%20-%20Signed%20Plea%20Agreement%20-%20March%202014.pdf [4]: http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/BreitbartFeed/~3/mubXYWB1l8o/story01.htm

]]></text></news-item>