<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CA21-B2E3-8883-F003"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Is there something in the water? Pollution study release on hold</title><source>The Daily News (New Plymouth, New Zealand)</source><author>Sue O'Dowd</author><text><![CDATA[Veteran journalist Jim Tucker is still waiting for online publication of his research into the state of Taranaki's waterways.
Mr Tucker had an informal arrangement with New Plymouth's Puke Ariki Research Centre to publish Clearing the water online to coincide with yesterday's Taranaki Daily News preview.
But Puke Ariki has delayed publication to ensure consistency with its brand and to undertake checks. Mr Tucker, who understands Puke Ariki wants to launch the online and book version of Clearing the water together, is concerned his research will be out of date before that happens.
He said timing was critical because TRC would release new data on the state of rivers next week and the oil and industry chapter would need revising after the Commissioner for the Environment's imminent release of her definitive report on fracking.
He had offered Puke Ariki a fully designed version of his research, so its desire to produce its own seemed a waste of ratepayers' resources.
Clearing the water is an illustrated 140,000-word document tracing the recovery of Taranaki's waterways since he exposed their pollution in an award-winning series in the Taranaki Herald in 1972.
Puke Ariki Research Centre commissioned him more in 2012 to undertake the project under a sponsorship relationship with TRC. Both Puke Ariki and TRC say they are committed to publishing what they describe as brilliant research as soon as possible.
Corporate services director Mike Nield said TRC was not delaying publication, the research was not being edited, and he understood Mr Tucker's concerns about timeliness. "We're not talking months, we're talking weeks."
Puke Ariki tumuaki (director) Kelvin Day said a meeting with TRC today would set a publication timeline to present to Mr Tucker on Monday.
"We're 100 per cent committed to (his research) and want to get it out and about as soon as we can."
But Mr Tucker wonders whether the delay is a backhanded way of censoring his research. TRC had tried to persuade him to remove from the oil and industry chapter a 4000-word section on deep well injection of oil drilling waste because it said groundwater and aquifers were outside his brief.
Their opposition was perhaps based on moves to divert hydrocarbon wastes from landfarms to deep well injection. "If that is the case, all the more reason for us to be analysing the implications of that method of disposal and its potential to affect freshwater, both surface and in aquifers."
No issues were raised about his investigation of fracking, deep well injection, land-farming and offshore oil exploration when he consulted TRC ahead of the research.
TRC scientists felt he focused excessively on non-compliance in some chapters, but he wanted to establish a context for judging the modern performance of organisations with potential to wreck the environment, he said.
--------------------
CAPTION:
Jim Tucker
Kelvin Day
Mike Nield
]]></text></news-item>