<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CA42-960B-D0AB-8953"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Czech Republic - Q2 2014</title><source>Czech Republic Power Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Since January 1 2006, when the Czech electricity market was fully liberalised in line with EU directives, three major distributors have been operating in the country:
The market remains characterised by limited competition. Although the anti-monopoly authorities required CEZ to dispose of some of its distribution company interests and its 34% minority stake in CEPS, the country's transmission-grid operator CEZ currently supplies more than 70% of the country's power.
The company operates the country's two nuclear power plants (Dukovany and Temelín), along with 13 coal-fired plants, 37 hydropower plants, three wind plants and 14 solar plants. However, while the electricity distribution sector sees some, albeit limited, competition, the electricity transmission segment remains in the sole hands of CEPS which is responsible for 400 kilovolts (kV), 220kV and selected 110kV lines, for the development of the transmission system, and for providing the system services that help to ensure safe and reliable operation. At lower-voltage levels (110kV and lower), electricity distribution is now provided by only three distribution-system operators (DSOs) with more than 90,000 customers, whose facilities are connected directly to the transmission system. Besides these regional distributors, there are also 312 operators of other distribution systems, connected only to DSOs with more than 90,000 customers, which distribute electricity within areas specified in their electricity distribution licences.
CEZ
CEZ Group was created in 2003, when CEZ merged with several regional distribution companies. Today, it is one of Europe's 10 biggest power companies, both in terms of installed capacity and number of customers. Following the acquisition of three distribution companies in Bulgaria, one in Romania, two Polish power plants and one Bulgarian power plant, CEZ Group has become a multinational enterprise comprising more than 90 Czech and foreign companies. CEZ is almost 70%-owned by the Czech government and delivers electricity to nearly 3.5mn customer supply points in the Czech Republic.
CEPS
Former state transmission operator CEPS is 66%-owned by steel-based conglomerate Osinek, which acquired its stake from CEZ via the national property fund. CEPS is responsible for electricity transfer, transmission-system operation, maintenance and development, and real-time dispatch in the Czech power-supply system.
The CEPS transmission system is part of the Czech power supply system, which links major entities operating within the power supply system and across which the majority of cross-border exchanges are carried out. The CEPS transmission system consists of 39 sub-stations, made up of 68 transformers, and operates 2,979 kilometres (km) of 400kV lines and 1,371km of 220kV lines.
PRE
Having 690,000 customers, Prazska Energetika Group (PRE) is the third biggest electricity supplier in the Czech Republic. The company has approximately 1,400 employees and supplies circa 6.3 terawatt hours (TWh) of electricity to its customers per year. PRE's close connection with Prague dates back to 1897, when the company was founded as the Electrical Works of the Royal City of Prague. At that time the company's task was the supply of electricity, as well as providing for street lighting and the operation of tramways.
E.ON
E.ON owns and operates two regional distributors - JME and JCE. It has restructured its Czech power interests into three 100%-owned units, namely E.ON Distribuce, E.ON Energie and E.ON Ceska Republika. E.ON serves 1.3mn customers in the Czech Republic and is the largest foreign investor in the Czech electricity market. Its subsidiaries in the Czech Republic hold shares in energy industry-associated companies. These are mainly partners providing services and technologies associated with the production and distribution of electrical energy or companies ensuring additional services for its clients.
]]></text></news-item>