<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CA92-6C64-AB32-9CD4"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>I have been falsely implicated in cases: Singh</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[What prompted you to contest general elections?
I have been in electoral politics for a long time. At present, I am the chairman of Balia (UP) Zila Parishad. I know my candidature has upset the political calculations of many. But I am here on the directives of my party (BSF) chief Mayawati.
But don't you think that this would upset the political alliance of your family. Your sister in-law Kunti Singh is a BJP MLA from Jharia?
No, nothing of that sort is going to happen. I have been with the BSP for the past five years now and no one has ever objected to it. I will get the support of everyone, which includes my family.
What are the issues you will be raising?
I am the president of trade union Janta Mazdoor Sangh, which has the highest membership in BCCL and is considered to be the most worker-friendly union. I have been fighting relentlessly for the restoration of services of nearly 1000 workers dismissed from BCCL and payment of wages as per the recommendation of the high-powered committee to nearly 40,000 unorganized sector workers of "outsourcing" companies. This will be my main poll plank besides other issues affecting common people.
But what about corruption and criminalization of politics, which are the burning issues of the day?
Yes, I am dead against corruption and criminalization of politics.
But how can you say that? There are several criminal cases against you.
I have been falsely implicated in all cases. Irrespective of whether I am present in Dhanbad or not, my name is dragged to cases filed by my opponents. The Pramod Singh murder case is a glaring example of this.
Your wife is mayor of Dhanbad and Dhanbad Municipal Corporation, which has utterly failed in implementing projects. Why should people vote for you.
The state government is not cooperating with the municipal corporation and the mayor is not allowed to work freely. If I go there, people will start blaming me for interference with the intent of looting the coffers. I assure you to complete the work that my wife as mayor and others have not been able to do. I am always available for people without any appointment and have solved more number of problems of the common people than any other candidate. I have my sympathizers in all parties whom I have helped in times of crisis and I am quite sure of getting their support.
What are your views on the domicile issue?
All people living in Jharkhand are inhabitants and domicile of this state and the dispute is created for political mileage. My family is the saviour of the people of Jharkhand and has always stood for them during disputes over CNT Act and domicile.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>