<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CB1B-FFF6-3DFE-90B4"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Other voices</title><source>New Town News (North Dakota)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Radioactive filters, untested slop pits..all part of the game.
North Dakotas oil industry, operated out of Houston, had better step up to address the environmental catastrophe they are inflicting and soon. Our group, through FOIA and Open Record Requests, has repeatedly called for both enforcement of (woefully inadequate) current regulations and adoption of newer standards. The recent filter sock issues (think of them as the used condoms of the oil industry) is simply a reflection of a 20th century Dept. of Health bureaucracy in the 21st. The Division of Mineral Resources, a proxy and mouthpiece for the petroleum council (s), cannot in any way justify their subservience to the oil industry waste stream generators.
The 5mb of info we received from the DoH points to a gross dereliction, to the level jeopardizing their primacy function (EPA), and is still under review by our team of scientists and legal counsel. The DMR on the other hand believes they answer to no one except the oil companies. Our group, as stated in our Mission Statement, has targeted the biggest threat to the States citizens: the millions of tons of untested, undocumented oil well waste being dumped in slop pits--thousands of them--every year. Virtually no other state allows the "dump and run" rule embedded at the DMR. You'd actually find most of those radioactive filters at the bottoms of the reserve/slop pits, historically. No content testing rules, ripped open pit liners from suction hose holes, back hoes, dropping ice chunks.leaking who knows what---and no one does know because the DMR doesn't want to know.
We are preparing a downloadable PDF. file with the rule changes we seek, in the near future. We are not going to wait for the DMR and DoH to stumble along, as they have for decades, to address the waste management issue. We do not trust them. We do not believe them.
Please refer to our website: www.bakkenwastewatchcoalition.org, for further, daily, updates.
]]></text></news-item>