<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CB9D-13A3-08F4-C3D9"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Egyptian Iron &amp; Steel decreases 1.5% on firm volume</title><source>News Bites - Middle East &amp; North Africa: Egypt</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Egyptian Iron & Steel (CA:IRON), Egypt's 2nd largest basic resources company by market capitalisation, decreased 17.0 qirsh (or 1.5%) to close at LE11.05. Compared with the EGX 30 Index which fell 13.7 points (or 0.2%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -1.3%. This has been exacerbated by firm volume of 1.5 times average.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Egyptian Iron & Steel, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051101740314183
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- The stock dropped 1.5% on high volatility today.- The Moving Average Convergence Divergence (MACD) indicator of 12-day Exponential Moving Average (EMA) of 11.13 minus the 26-day EMA of 11.21 is negative 0.08 suggesting a bearish signal. Both EMA prices are falling, another bearish signal.- The price dropped 3.7% in the last month. The stock has been exacerbated by robust volume of 2.5 times average for the month.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price/Sales of 3.6 [0.9].Other Bearish Signals:- Net Profit margin has seen consecutive falls and seems to be on a slippery slope in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 412,814 shares worth LE4.6 million (US$655,045) traded. Beta: the Beta of Egyptian Iron & Steel stock is 1.7. A Beta greater than 1 suggests this is a high risk, high return stock with volatility greater than that of the market. - Egyptian Iron & Steel is at a discount of 12.8% to its 12-month high of LE12.67 on 16 Jan, 2014. It is also at a premium of 100.9% to the 12-month low of LE5.50 on 17 Jun, 2013. - The present value of LE1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Egyptian Iron & Steel is LE1,005, for a capital gain of LE5.
Bullish Signals:
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 05: Egyptian Iron & Steel targeting LE 120 m investments[News Story]Arab Finance: Egyptian Iron & Steel (IRON) is targeting LE 119.8 m investments in the next fiscal year for the replacements and renewal of the company's factory according to ALMal newspaper.A source in the company revealed that this is the initial value and might be increased through the fiscal year according to the country's circumstances and in accordance with governmental plants to develop the company and increasing its production capacity.The source added that the company targeting the reduction of its losses to LE 315.3 m in the next fiscal year.
January 15: Egyptian Iron & Steel insider sellsEgyptian Iron & Steel (CA:IRON) insider Egypt Aluminum sold 360,000 shares on January 15, 2014. The selling price was LE12.16.
December 18: Egyptian Iron & Steel syndicate in talks to raise loan by LE 100 m[News Story]Arab Finance: Gamal Adel Mawla, Head of workers' syndicate committee Egyptian Iron & Steel (IRON), stated that the committee is conducting talks with The Holding Company for Metallurgical Industries to increase the loan granted to the company by LE 100 million, Alborsa newspaper reported.He added that, the Holding company agreed to offer LE 70 million, while Ministry of Finance will provide the remaining LE 30 million.It is worth noting that, Investment Ministry is conducting talks with company's management to discuss workers' complaints.
Source: arabfinance.com
December 16: Workers at Egyptian Iron and Steel Company end sit-in[News Story]Workers at the Egyptian Iron and Steel Company (HADISOLB) - (IRON) reached an agreement on Sunday with the ministries of industry and of social solidarity to receive their required profit shares in two installments.Thousands of workers at the state-owned company who have demanded that they be paid profits they are owed have been staging a sit-in since 26 November turning it into a partial strike 10 days ago.The labour action was triggered by a delay in paying the annual profits owed to the company's 12,000 workers by the general assembly, which normally allocates 16 months-worth of profit shares to workers each November.The agreement between the ministries of commerce and industry and social solidarity entails dismissing the CEO, the return of the workers who were redeployed to other factories as punishment for encouraging the strike, increasing production to reach the factory's full potential production levels, as well as paying the workers their full shares of profits in two installments.The agreement did not include improvements in work conditions, an issue the workers plan to discuss with the new board of directors, Mohamed Omar, a worker at the company told Ahram Online.A minority of the workers opposed the agreement and intend to protest outside the cabinet headquarters in central Cairo, to demand their full shares in profits in a single installment."We fear that a new government would not abide by the agreement and we are not sure we will be paid the second installment," Omar told Ahram Online.At the beginning of the strike, workers' representatives explained to Ahram Online that the payment is not a true profit share, but rather part of their monthly pay.
December 15: Egyptian Iron & Steel denies workers' sit-in disperse, CEO dismissal[News Story]Arab Finance: Egyptian Iron & Steel (IRON) denied media reports about workers' sit-in disperse, dismissing CEO and Managing Director and BOD reshuffle.The company added, in a release sent to EGX that, what were mention totally untrue.
Source: arabfinance.com
December 05: Egyptian Iron and Steel Company problems to be solved soon: chairman[News Story] In reaction to accusations of corruption and negligence within the Egyptian Iron and Steel Company (HADISOLB) (IRON), Mohamed Saad Negeada, chairman and managing director, has defended his record in interview with Ahram Online."Any corruption allegation within the company is investigated.
December 03: Workers at Egyptian Iron & Steel company go on strike[News Story]Cairo - Thousands of workers at the Egyptian Iron & Steel (IRON) factory in Helwan, south of Cairo, declared a partial strike on Monday.The workers, who have been holding a sit-in since 26 November, decided to escalate after Metallurgical Industries Co, the holding company, did not respond to their demands to implement their delayed profit shares.Workers did not opt for a full strike because if the factory's blast furnace were to be shut down, it would take three months to make it functional again.The blast furnace will remain open during the strike, as will some steel production lines.
ISIN: EGS3D061C015
CA:IRON; CAI:IRON; EY:IRON
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>