<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CC17-329D-A8C9-DB59"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>LIC asks Maruti to explain Gujarat plant transfer to Suzuki</title><source>The Economic Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[MUMBAI: Life Insurance Corporation of India, Maruti Suzuki’s largest institutional investor, has written to the board of India’s largest carmaker asking it to explain the proposed handover of the Gujarat plant to a 100% subsidiary of its Japanese parent Suzuki.
A senior LIC official told ET on conditions of anonymity that the life insurer in the letter asked Maruti Suzuki to detail the arrangement and how such a move would help minority investors like them. He did not elaborate but added that it would hear from Maruti before taking a decision.
LIC’s move is significant and could serve as a much-needed shot in the arm for minority investors if the insurance giant follows up the letter by signaling its opposition to the transfer.
Institutional investors, largely mutual funds, fear that Maruti could become a shell company in a few years if the Gujarat plant is transferred to a wholly-owned subsidiary of Suzuki. They have twice written to the Maruti board asking them to reconsider their stance and have followed it up with a letter to the Securities and Exchange Board of India. The mutual funds, 16 of them, have asked Sebi to take action against Maruti for lack of transparency.
The funds had approached LIC last week as the insurance giant’s muscle could help them approach the Company Law Board against the Maruti decision. The 16 mutual funds and private insurers are keen on getting LIC, which holds 6.93% in Maruti, on its side as foreign institutional investors have been coy about revealing their stance. The funds own 4% and a stake of over 10% is crucial to make the CLB listen to their grievance, as per the provisions of the new Companies Act.
While it chose to tread alone without joining hands with the mutual funds that include SBI Mutual Fund, ICICI Prudential and HDFC Mutual Fund, LIC’s move would clearly encourage the group of 16 to demand that independent directors on the Maruti board discharge their fiduciary responsibilities in a forthright manner.
Maruti Suzuki’s board is meeting on Saturday to discuss the business plan for 2014-15. So far, the contentious plan to transfer the proposed plant in Gujarat does not feature in the agenda.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>