<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CC4D-3688-DD4C-F1C7"><date>2014-03-15</date><title></title><source>Star-News (Wilmington, NC)</source><author>Wayne.Faulkner@StarNewsOnline.com</author><text><![CDATA[By Wayne Faulkner
Wilmington-based PPD is among five companies awarded contracts by the federal government to design and conduct clinical studies to develop drug and diagnostic tests to protect public health in the event of emergencies such as <0x000A>bioterrorism or pandemic flu.
The services include clinical studies required by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration for approval for human use, comparing the properties of multiple products, or evaluating the potency of products stored in U.S. government stockpiles, the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services announced.
The five-company network will also be able to conduct clinical studies during public health emergencies such as a pandemic, the department said in a news release.
Each contract could be worth up to $100 million.
"Recent disasters, such as Hurricane Sandy, the Deepwater Horizon oil spill, the 2009-H1N1 pandemic, underscored the importance of developing a capability to perform rigorous scientific studies in real time, potentially to shape the response to an unfolding crisis and to support recovery," stated Robin Robinson, director of the Biomedical Advanced Research and Development Authority.
"The scope of our work with (the authority) will be supported from our global headquarters in Wilmington, and the Wilmington community can be proud to play a role in helping protect the country against the threat <0x000A>of public health emergencies," Paul Colvin, PPD's executive vice president of clinical development, said Friday.
"PPD has provided a full range of study services on more than 1,300 government and public health projects in multiple indications, including infectious diseases, vaccines, bio-defense, and autoimmune and asthma/allergic diseases," Colvin said.
The four other companies awarded contracts are Rho Federal Systems Division Inc., of Chapel Hill; EMMES Corp., of Rockville, Md.; Technical Resources International Inc., of Bethesda, Md.; and Clinical Research Management Inc., of Hinckley, Ohio.
Wayne Faulkner: 343-2329
On Twitter: @bizniznews
]]></text></news-item>