<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CC8A-6F93-3DFF-526E"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Group exposes horrific turkey abuse at Hybrid Farms Canada</title><source>Digital Journal</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 15, 2014 (Digital Journal:http://www.digitaljournal.com Delivered by Newstex) Mercy for Animals (MFA) has once again uncovered horrific animal abuse that seems to happen all too often on factory farms. In their undercover video, Hybrid Turkey workers in Canada throw, stomp and crush spines of turkeys.
The video highlights factory farming practices that some agricultural experts believe contribute to pollution, disrespect animal rights, spread disease and bring unhealthy food to the table. The turkeys can be seen being struck with metal tools, kicked and left to suffer from injuries. The aim of factory farming is mass production and profitability. The birds are genetically manipulated to grow fast and grow large. Turkeys and chickens are typically raised to produce large breasts that make it impossible for them to stand or walk, as highlighted in the Mercy for Animals video. David Libertini is Hybrid Turkey's managing director of the operation that is owned by Hendrix Genetics[1]. In a press release[2] Libertini said: 'Based on multiple levels of audits and third party inspections, we believe this to be an isolated incident.' The animal activist group says otherwise, stating the lives of turkeys on farms such as Hybrid are 'short,' 'filled with fear,' suffering and 'brutal.' In response to the turkey abuse captured by Mercy for Animals, the farm will now have video cameras for monitoring. Libertini also says the Hybrid Farm will become the first in North America to employ veterinary review of euthanasia. 'Euthanasia is not easy to do or watch at the best of times. Hybrid has just recently launched a new, easier-to-use tool plus training for this euthanasia method. ' says Dr. Helen Wojcinski, Manager Science and Sustainability for Hybrid Turkeys[3]. Mercy for Animals feels a better option would be to adopt a vegetarian lifestyle for the sake of all animals. Indeed, this isn't the first exposure of factory farm animal abuse[4]. MFA also contends the practice is standard, calling what is seen on the video 'gratuitous cruelty.' The group exposed Butterball turkey in 2011. Digital Journalist Justin King interviewed Matt Rice[5], Former U.S. Marine and current Director of Investigations for Mercy for Animals last month. Rice stated the goal of MFA is to keep consumers informed about the suffering endured by the animals we eat so we can make better choices that are also healthier. Of note, turkeys are gentle. Males are subjected to pain to obtain semen. Females are pushed and held down and forced to breed. Warning: The video below is graphic and was difficult to watch. You can also sign a petition [6]to stop turkey torture or donate to MFA[7]. Play Video[8] [1]: http://www.hendrix-genetics.com/ [2]: http://www.hybridturkeys.com/hybrid-news-centre/animal-welfare-press-release-march-2014/ [3]: http://www.hybridturkeys.com/about-us/animal-welfare-policy/ [4]: http://www.butterballabuse.com/butterball-2011.php [5]: http://www.digitaljournal.com/news/world/laws-attempt-to-make-documenting-animal-cruelty-illegal-at-farms/article/368435 [6]: http://www.turkeytorture.ca/ [7]: https://interland3.donorperfect.net/weblink/weblink.aspx?name=E162888id=5 [8]: http://www.youtube.com/embed/zw_i1Yxc4Oo?wmode=transparent

]]></text></news-item>