<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CCEC-8864-BEE2-1A36"><date>2014-03-14</date><title></title><source>Pittsburgh Post-Gazette</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[INBOUND FORT PITT TUNNEL CLOSED TONIGHT
The inbound side of the Fort Pitt Tunnel will close tonight at 9 for emergency repairs, PennDOT announced today.
Crews will make emergency repairs to the suspended tunnel ceiling after it was determined support brackets had deteriorated.
Traffic inbound was reduced to a single lane today and will continue that way until the full closure begins at 9. Outbound lanes will remain open. Repairs are expected to be completed by 6 a.m. Saturday, but the lanes will open earlier if crews finish earlier.
Motorists should expect significant delays and PennDOT urges drivers to find alternate routes. For updates, visit www.511pa.com or call 5-1-1.
Here is the posted detour from PennDOT:
From eastbound (or inbound) Interstate 376 Parkway West, take Exit 69-C (West End) to northbound Route 51.
Follow northbound Route 51 to Route 837 (Carson Street).
Bear right onto Route 837.
Follow Route 837 to the ramp for eastbound I-376. MAN KILLED IN SCHOOL BUS CRASH
A Gibsonia man was killed this morning in a crash involving a school bus and multiple vehicles in Hampton.
The Allegheny County medical examiner's office identified him as John Krauland Jr., 28. He was pronounced dead at at Allegheny General Hospital at 8:47 a.m., about an hour after the crash at Route 8 and East Hardies Road.
Allegheny County police Sgt. Scott Scherer said Mr. Krauland was waiting at a stoplight at the intersection around 7:40 a.m., and the bus was southbound on Route 8, intending to turn left onto East Hardies. The bus collided with a pickup truck, then careened over a Nissan sedan driven by Mr. Krauland.
Paramedics took the driver of the pickup truck, who was wearing a neck brace, to the hospital. His condition wasn't immediately available. The bus driver was not hurt.
The pickup truck driver and bus driver will be tested for drugs and alcohol. The sergeant said the Allegheny County district attorney will determine if charges are warranted.
No students were on the bus, operated by Monark Student Transportation Corp. and serving the Pine-Richland School District. District spokeswoman Rachel Hathhorn said the bus was preparing to pick up students and take them to Eden Hall Upper Elementary School.
Mr. Krauland worked as a loss control coordinator in the Catholic Diocese of Pittsburgh office of property and planning.
Police did not release the names of the others involved in the crash. PEDUTO CUTS TAKE-HOME CARS
Mayor Bill Peduto today issued an executive order slashing the number of city-owned vehicles permanently assigned to employees from 56 to 38.
In a news release, Mr. Peduto said the only city employees who will keep their take-home vehicles are public works and public safety supervisors who need to be on call for emergencies 24 hours a day and Operations Director Guy Costa. The order also directs Mr. Costa to write a new policy governing when take-home vehicles should be assigned and who should get them.
"City government's oversight of take-home cars has become much too loose over the years, and my administration is committed to tightening up all such standards," Mr. Peduto said in a news release. "I don't have a take-home car myself, and neither should any city worker who is not a first-line responder 24 hours a day to emergencies."
The 18 vehicles being cut from the fleet are coming from the mayor's office, the bureau of building inspection, the fire bureau, parks and recreation, the police bureau, the public safety department and the public works department. Those vehicles will be returned to the city fleet, where they will be available for city employees to check out for city business.
The city's system for monitoring take-home cars was in the news earlier this week in an incident involving a recently terminated spokeswoman for the Pittsburgh police bureau.
City officials said Diane Richard's last day working for the bureau was March 3. The take-home SUV assigned to her was spotted parked outside her Crafton Heights home twice in the following days. She returned the unmarked car Monday, one week after her last day with the bureau.
Officials could not explain why Ms. Richard kept the car past her last day or who was responsible for ensuring that she returned it.
Mr. Costa aid Monday that the lack of oversight was among the issues that the Peduto administration hoped to address when it revamped policies involving take-home cars. NUKE WASTE AMOUNT MORE THAN THOUGHT
A federal report released today by U.S. Sen. Bob Casey, D-Pa., confirmed a significant underestimation of the amount of nuclear waste buried at a former Babcock and Wilcox plant site in Armstrong County.
The report shows a lack of records at the Shallow Land Disposal Area, a 44-acre site in Parks Township near Apollo. Mr. Casey commissioned the report by Nuclear Regulatory Commission's Inspector General.
The study found that a remediation plan begun by the Army Corps of Engineers "significantly underestimated" the amount of the "complex materials" at the site.
"This report confirms an abysmal lack of records and raises serious concerns about the NRC's oversight of the SLDA," Mr. Casey said in a news release.
The Shallow Land Disposal Area houses nuclear waste materials from operations conducted by the Nuclear Materials and Equipment Corp. and Atlantic Richfield Co. The Babcock and Wilcox Co. most recently owned the land before closing the plant in 1983.
The Army Corps has been in charge of the site since 2002. Cleanup stopped in May 2012 after crews detected elevated levels of these "complex materials," such as uranium and plutonium. JOB FAIRS OPEN TO PUBLIC
Community College of Allegheny County today announced four job fairs open not only to its students and alumni but also to the general public.
The events will take place on the following CCAC campuses:
* Allegheny, 9:30 a.m. to 1:30 p.m. Wednesday, Foerster Student Service Center.
* South, 9:30 a.m. to 1:30 p.m. March 26, B Building, Fourth Floor Commons.
* North, 9 a.m. to 1 p.m. April 2, Atrium.
* Boyce, 9 a.m. to 1 p.m. April 9, Student Union.
More information and a list of participating companies and organizations are available from the Job Placement and Career Services offices of each campus. DUCKS KILLED WITH BLOW-GUN DARTS
ROARING SPRING, Pa. - Someone is killing ducks with blow-gun darts and target arrows at a popular southwestern Pennsylvania pond, the state Game Commission said.
The mysterious killings have been going on for about two weeks at Spring Dam Park in Roaring Spring, according to WJAC-TV. The spring-fed pond is in southern Blair County, about 80 miles east of Pittsburgh.
The darts being used to shoot the ducks are made of wood or steel, some of which are 4 inches long.
Officials haven't said how many ducks have been killed, but some carcasses and darts could be seen sticking up out of the still-thawing mud on Thursday.
Wildlife officer Albert Zellner said children come to the pond and "want to feed the ducks and look at the fish and that's a 4-inch piece of sharpened steel. You don't need that here."
Mr. Zellner explained that the birds are not just being killed illegally, but also cruelly.
"It's not a killing shot initially, it just wounds it," he said. "The duck jumps in the water, he can't fly, he can't get away and he just ends up dying in the water. It's a slow and painful death."
Local ordinances ban the use of weapons in the park. Whoever has killed the birds also could face state wildlife charges.
]]></text></news-item>