<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CDDD-C0EE-B380-CFA1"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Deal of the Week: Men's Wearhouse emerges as victorious suitor after months of drama</title><source>Houston Business Journal</source><author>Emily Wilkinson</author><text><![CDATA[After six months of soap opera-level drama over who would acquire whom, Houston-based Men's Wearhouse Inc. (NYSE: MW) and Maryland-based Jos. A. Bank Clothiers Inc. (Nasdaq: JOSB) are seeing eye to eye. Men's Wearhouse will buy its smaller rival in a deal that represents a 56 percent premium to where Jos. A. Bank's stock price was before it made the first move in October.
The combined company will be the fourth-largest U.S. men's apparel retailer, and due to improved purchasing power, lower overhead and more efficient marketing and customer service, savings of at least $100 million a year are expected.
However, the deal was a long time in the making and started when Men's Wearhouse fired its co-founder and executive chairman last summer, which put the firm in the spotlight and piqued the interest of investors.
Long journey and lots of drama led to clothier union
1973
George Zimmer founds Men's Wearhouse in Houston with his college roommates. The store sells $10 slacks and $25 polyester sports coats.
1980s
1990s
2005
Men's Wearhouse acquires two dry cleaning chains in Houston and rebrands them as MW Cleaners, which now has 35 locations in Houston.
June 2011
June 19, 2013
Men's Wearhouse's board of directors fires Zimmer as executive chairman because he was pushing various corporate changes, including taking the company private. The board issues a statement that says Zimmer was meddling and simply couldn't let go of the company he'd started. The investment world pays attention to the juicy drama, and the scrutiny on the company has investors and rivals all atwitter.
July 18, 2013
Men's Wearhouse buys Florida-based JA Holding Inc., the parent company of clothing brand Joseph Abboud, for $97.5 million in cash.
Oct. 9, 2013
The first move: Jos. A. Bank makes a surprise, unsolicited offer of $48 a share, or $2.3 billion, for Men's Wearhouse, setting off one of the most convoluted ongoing deals in recent years. Men's Wearhouse rejects the bid, saying it undervalues the company.
Oct. 10, 2013
Men's Wearhouse issues a shareholder right's plan, or what is known as a "poison pill." It allows shareholders to buy company stock at a discounted price should a person or group acquire 10 percent or more of Men's Wearhouse stock or if a "passive institutional investor" buys 15 percent in a deal not approved by the board.
Oct. 28, 2013
Men's Wearhouse releases a 46-page investors presentation on why it would be better off growing on its own rather than accepting a buyout from Jos. A. Bank.
Nov. 5, 2013
Despite being courted by Men's Wearhouse, high-end shoemaker Allen Edmonds, based in Wisconsin, is bought by Los Angeles-based private equity firm Brentwood Associates for an undisclosed price, removing a hurdle for Jos. A Bank buying Men's Wearhouse.
Nov. 7, 2013
New York-based Eminence Capital LLC, Men's Wearhouse's largest shareholder, issues a letter to the board that it wants to talk with Jos. A Bank about merging. The letter was included in a Securities and Exchange Commission filing showing that Eminence Capital owns 4.7 million shares of Men's Wearhouse, or 9.8 percent of the company. It also is the fourth largest shareholder of Jos. A. Bank, with a 4.9 percent stake.
Nov. 26, 2013
Counter attack: Men's Wearhouse turns the tables on Jos. A. Bank and offers $1.5 billion, or $55 a share, in cash for its smaller rival.
Dec. 23, 2013
Jos. A. Bank rejects Men's Wearhouse's offer, saying it undervalues the company. Men's Wearhouse is "surprised" by the rejection.
Jan. 3
Jos. A. Bank's board lowers its standing poison pill to 10 percent from 20 percent, which would go into effect if Men's Wearhouse - or any other unsolicited buyer - acquires 10 percent of Jos. A. Bank's outstanding common stock.
Jan. 6
Sweetening the deal: Men's Wearhouse raises its offer to buy Jos. A. Bank to $57.50 per share, or $1.6 billion.
Jan. 13
Courtroom drama: Eminence Capital sues Jos. A. Bank for rejecting Men's Wearhouse's bid and for toughening the retailer's anti-takeover defenses.
Jan. 17
Jos. A. Bank rejects the higher bid, saying it is too low.
Feb. 2
Jos. A. Bank issues a letter that refuses to negotiate over Men's Wearhouse's tender offer, saying it raises "serious antitrust concerns."
Feb. 14
The other woman: Jos. A. Bank says it will acquire rival chain Eddie Bauer, based in Bellevue, Wash., for $825 million in cash and stock.
Feb. 23
Men's Wearhouse files suit in Chancery Court in Delaware to block the Eddie
Bauer deal, saying it would make the company too large for Men's Wearhouse to acquire.
Feb. 24
Raising the stakes: Men's Wearhouse increases its offer for Jos. A. Bank by about 10 percent to $63.50 per share. If Jos. A. Bank agrees to terminate the Eddie Bauer deal, Men's Wearhouse will increase that offer to $65 per share.
Feb. 27
Jos. A. Bank rejects Men's Wearhouse's $63.50-a-share offer, but says it will give Men's Wearhouse limited access to its financials so it can decide whether to up its ante.
March 3
Men's Wearhouse receives a draft merger agreement from Jos. A. Bank, and the two retailers reach a nondisclosure agreement.&nbsp;
March 11
Happily Ever After: The boards of directors of both companies unanimously approve Men's Wearhouse to pay $65 per share, or $1.8 billion total, to buy Jos. A. Bank in cash. Jos. A. Bank terminates its deal to buy Eddie Bauer and will pay a $48 million breakup fee to San Francisco-based private equity firm Golden Gate Capital, which originally agreed to help finance its initial bid for Men's Wearhouse. The deal is expected to close in the third quarter.
The Players
New York-based BofA Merrill Lynch and JPMorgan Securities LLC are the financial advisers for Men's Wearhouse, and New York-based Willkie Farr & Gallagher LLP is its legal adviser. Houston-based Dennard Lascar Associates LLC is Men's Wearhouse's investor relations firm, and Deloitte LLP's Houston office is its auditor.
Goldman, Sachs & Co. and Financo LLC are financial advisers for Jos. A. Bank, and New York-based Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher & Flom LLP and St. Louis-based Guilfoil Petzall & Shoemake LLC are its legal advisers.
By the numbers
$4.5 billion: Market capitalization of the combined company due to large rallies in both companies' share prices since Oct. 8, when the saga started
SOURCE: Bloomberg
1,700: Stores operated by the combined company. Jos. A. Bank will not rebrand its stores.
SOURCE: Men's Wearhouse
222: Men's Wearhouse employees at its corporate headquarters in the Westchase area in Houston. The company's executive offices are in Freemont, Calif.
SOURCE: The Westchase District
85: How many of Men's Wearhouse's 1,124 stores sell women's apparel
SOURCE: Men's Wearhouse
Did you find this article useful? Why not subscribe to Houston Business Journal for more articles and leads? Visit bizjournals.com/subscribe or call 1-866-853-3661.
]]></text></news-item>