<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CDFF-C6CA-DDA3-519C"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Shop Smartly To Get The Best Legal Team</title><source>Investor's Business Daily</source><author>MOREY STETTNER</author><text><![CDATA[The best entrepreneurs are proactive: They initiate problem-solving strategies rather than wait and react to crises.
Thinking proactively is especially important when hiring an attorney. Establishing a relationship with a trusted lawyer -- even when there's no pressing need for one -- can help you when you need it most.
When you retain a top attorney, the ongoing advice you receive can ultimately save money and prevent costly mistakes. And you're more likely to get better service if you get embroiled in a legal mess.
"As a business owner, my goal is to have as little stress as possible," said Sean Castrina, a serial entrepreneur and founder of NewBizCoach.org in Charlottesville, Va. "A quality law firm that's part of my team can help take that worry away from me."
Nearly 10 years ago, Castrina faced the possibility of a wrongful termination lawsuit from a disgruntled former employee. He recalls that the individual "threatened to sue me for an obscene dollar figure."
Castrina intended to let his existing lawyer handle the matter. But an experienced businessman advised Castrina to rethink his strategy. "Your attorney is too nice," the businessman warned Castrina. "Compare him to a primary care doctor. If you had cancer, you'd take it to the next level."
Bulldog In His Corner
Castrina, author of "8 Unbreakable Rules for Business Start-Up Success," hired a bulldog who sent a strongly worded letter to the former employee. That extinguished the threat immediately.
"The attorney I had before was very passive," Castrina said. "Had I stayed with him, I would've paid more because he was tinkering around. The big gun I hired didn't strike a defensive posture."
To find a hotshot lawyer, Castrina suggests asking other entrepreneurs, "Is there an attorney you'd hate to go up against?" Then build a relationship with that law firm.
To save money, ask the firm to assign a junior attorney to address your overall legal needs. Castrina has found that "younger, aggressive attorneys can work twice as hard at half the price." He adds that "you still get the firm's letterhead" if you need the firm to write a strong letter on your behalf.
By enlisting a top law firm, you also learn how to lower your legal liability. For example, Castrina's lawyer suggested that he add a mediation clause to his service contracts to resolve certain disputes.
His attorney also advised him to obtain employment practices liability insurance, which covers claims employees make alleging discrimination, harassment, wrongful termination and other issues.
"We did a "legal physical' like a doctor would do," Castrina recalled. "It was an hour of advice on smart steps I should take that has saved me countless dollars and hassles."
]]></text></news-item>