<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CE68-2A6F-948B-A6D1"><date>2014-03-15</date><title></title><source>South China Morning Post</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Groups invited to debate broadcasting licences
The Legislative Council's panel on broadcasting will be listening today to the views of concerned groups on the renewal of licences next year. Both TVB and ATV have attracted controversy. TVB has been accused of taking advantage of its dominant position in the market, while cash-strapped ATV has frequently fallen foul of watchdog the Communications Authority - often due to allegations of interference by its mainland investor, Wong Ching. Both - but especially ATV - have faced complaints of pro-Beijing bias.
In or out vote for Crimeans
Voters in the Crimea will take part in a referendum tomorrow to choose between remaining in Ukraine or joining neighbouring Russia. The vote, organised by the region's government, follows the uprising in Kiev and the incursion of Russian troops into the peninsula. The autonomous region has a 60 per cent ethnic Russian population.
Vietnamese President Truong Tan Sang arrives in Japan tomorrow for a state visit. During his trip, which ends on Wednesday, Sang will meet Japanese Prime Minister Shinzo Abe. They are expected to agree on bilateral co-operation in areas such as agriculture, education and health.
A verdict is expected today in Peshawar, Pakistan, in the case of doctor Shakil Afridi, who was previously convicted of helping the CIA track al-Qaeda chief Osama bin Laden in May 2011. He was sentenced to 33 years in jail but that was overturned in August last year, and a retrial was ordered. He allegedly helped the CIA by running a fake vaccination campaign a month before a US forces raid on a compound that killed bin Laden.
Protesters will be marching in Hong Kong today to raise awareness about "canned" hunting of lions. The event is organised by the Hong Kong Humane Education Coalition, which will be delivering a letter to the South African consulate. The Global March for Lions is taking place in more than 20 cities around the world. Canned hunting involves animals being enclosed, and they may even have been reared for the hunt.
It's a big weekend for sports fans. Hong Kong will play their group opener tomorrow in the International Cricket Council's World Twenty20 competition in Bangladesh against Nepal. In Melbourne, the Formula 1 season starts with the Australian Grand Prix. Meanwhile, Ireland have a crunch match against France in rugby's Six Nations contest. A win of any kind should see them take the title.
]]></text></news-item>