<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CF3A-3AB2-9C16-265F"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Blowing in the wind - watch where you aim your action</title><source>Waikato Times (Hamilton, New Zealand)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Digging into an unheralded $100m lawsuit, Chalkie is intrigued by its links to Hanover Finance.
--------------------
As sailors all know, it's important at sea to avoid urinating to windward. The blow-back can be unpleasant.
This helpful tip has general applications too. Anyone considering legal action to recover debts, such as, say, a receiver, should be aware that what goes around comes around. In a small country like New Zealand a professional firm could find itself plaintiff one day, defendant the next.
Big accountancy firm PwC, for example, is busy suing auditor BDO Spicers over its work on Strategic Finance and has accepted a $10 million settlement in its lawsuit against directors of Lombard Finance and an unnamed third party. According to a press report, Lombard's auditor KPMG has declined to comment on whether it could be the said third party. Meanwhile, PwC is itself being sued for its audit of bankrupt Christchurch developer Dave Henderson's failed business Property Ventures, which collapsed in 2010, causing estimated losses of $150m.
Chalkie wonders how easy it is to negotiate a settlement with an auditor knowing your own firm is in the gun facing a claim on similar grounds.
That aside, the Property Ventures battle could turn into a major eye-opener for finance company investors, particularly those with the disastrous Hanover Finance.
At the centre of the storm is liquidator Robert Walker, a tenaciously independent character who has forced the disclosure of key documents shedding light on Henderson's complex affairs.
Walker was appointed in July 2010 and in November 2012 filed suit against Henderson and four other directors of Property Ventures, along with PwC and property valuation firm Fright Aubrey and its former director Richard Gibbons.
Alleging breaches of the Companies Act relating to reckless trading and failing to act in good faith, Walker wants the directors to pay compensation of $100m, drawing on the resources of their liability insurer Vero.
The suit is being contested by the defendants and its result should be of high interest to investors in Hanover Finance and South Canterbury Finance. When receivers were appointed in March 2010, Property Ventures owed $68.3m to those firms, or at least, to the remains of those firms - Hanover's loans of $40.9m had been transferred to Allied Farmers by then and South Canterbury had just six months left to live.
The money was never recovered.
In these situations the liquidator can struggle to mount a claim because so little money is available to pay for lawyers, but this one is different.
Chalkie understands from sources close to the matter that Allied's claim has been acquired by litigation funding company LPF Group for about $100,000, having topped a bid by Henderson to buy his own debt for about $60,000. This gives Walker, as liquidator, the wherewithal to pursue the claim and presumably gives LPF huge upside if it succeeds.
As it happens, one of LPF's directors is accountant Bruce Sheppard, a fierce critic of Hanover Finance who is fighting a defamation claim brought by Hanover's owners Mark Hotchin and Eric Watson.
Anyway, Chalkie has been intrigued to learn more about Property Ventures and its part in the finance company debacle.
For example, it appears property values could experience significant acceleration during some transactions involving Henderson company Gardez Investments.
Gardez was a property investment company controlled and part-owned by Henderson through his company Montpellier Group. More than 200 outside investors also owned part of Gardez after buying about $18.2m of its securities in 2003.
The money helped Gardez buy two properties: offices at 280 Queen St in Auckland and a 7.8 hectare block of land at Frankton near Queenstown Airport, next to the block later known as "Hendo's Hole".
The Queen St property was bought from a subsidiary of Hotchin and Watson's Hanover Group for $27m in June 2003 with finance from Hanover. This was less than nine months after Hanover had bought it from the National Bank for $21m, providing Hotchin and Watson with a quick gain of about 28 per cent.
The Frankton property was bought from Henderson's company Ladies Mile Holdings on July 31, 2003, for $14m. Property records show Ladies Mile owned it for less than a minute. Unfortunately the records do not show how much Ladies Mile paid for it.
Gardez was at this point financed entirely by debt, with $18.5m from ANZ Bank, $18.2m from investors and $9.2m from Hanover.
In June 2007, Gardez was taken over by another Henderson company, Five Mile Holdings, and the investors got 50c in the dollar back, with the remainder paid in convertible notes issued by Five Mile.
Chalkie reckons this was not a good deal for them, particularly since 280 Queen St was sold after refurbishment for $51.5m to German investors on April 3, 2007. The sale price does not appear in financial statements for Gardez or Property Ventures because the transaction occurred after their March 31 balance date and no further accounts were published. The only reference to the money says "proceeds were used to repay loans from ANZ and Hanover Finance".
Gardez appeared to owe ANZ and Hanover about $30.1m before its takeover, so Chalkie wonders what happened to the balance.
According to the Financial Markets Authority, the then Securities Commission began investigating Property Ventures some time in 2007 in relation to concerns that its 2005 prospectus breached the Financial Reporting Act and the Securities Act. Nothing appears to have happened as a result, although by May 2008, Companies Office investigator John McPherson was involved and reported on Property Ventures to the commission a month later. The commission won't reveal what it found, but an email from McPherson appears in a court-filed affidavit from Walker relating to his litigation.
It says McPherson had spoken with PwC auditor Maurice Noone about Property Ventures' cash flow issues "and he has confirmed that John Waller is providing advice/assistance. On that basis will not pursue the matter further".
Waller was then a senior partner at PwC, Property Ventures' auditor.
The email trail continued to include a comment from Property Ventures director Austin Forbes, who explained that "John Waller has spoken to Maurice Noone, both of PwC, as to possible investors they may have, in particular for Five Mile. Maurice Noone says that Dave is aware of this".
Five Mile, as Hanover investors may recall, was a major contributor to the finance company's failure and collapsed in September 2008 owing at least $77m.
Two months later, Waller signed an independent report from PwC assessing Hanover's moratorium proposal allowing it to stop paying back debenture holders.
The report, which did not mention Waller and PwC's detailed knowledge of Hanover's big debtor Five Mile, compared the moratorium to receivership and said there was a real prospect investors wouldn't get all their money back. However, "virtually the same analysis and conclusions apply in the event of receivership".
On balance, it recommended the moratorium. This was a controversial view.
At Hanover's creditor's meeting to vote on the moratorium, Sheppard stood up and asked Waller why he had not assessed the potential to recover money from claims against directors and others.
Chalkie was there and remembers the reaction well. Waller replied with scorn, saying Sheppard's question was "stupid".
"There are a number of actions a receiver could look at, but to bring a claim would be difficult. It would take considerable time and cost and would be vigorously defended."
This was a crucial point in the decision and investors voted for the moratorium.
Waller was technically correct to point out the cost and difficulty of litigation, but Chalkie reckons he was conflicted and (unless there were other disclosures) should never have advised Hanover investors on the moratorium. Had receivers been appointed, it is not hard to see how litigation could have developed against Hanover's debtors, such as Five Mile, and ultimately against their directors and advisers, such as PwC.
As Walker's litigation shows, this is indeed what happened. Granted, the action may be unsuccessful and Walker may be tilting at windmills, but maybe the wind is changing.
Chalkie is written by Fairfax business bureau deputy editor Tim Hunter.
--------------------
CAPTION:
Busted: Dave Henderson - the battle over his Property Ventures firm could be a big eye- opener.
Picture: FAIRFAX NZ
]]></text></news-item>