<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CF43-5ABA-052D-7584"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Denso drops 4.0% on firm volume</title><source>News Bites Asian Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Denso Corporation (TO:6902), the 3rd largest transportation equipment company by market capitalisation in the Tokyo Stock Exchange, dropped JPY207.0 (or 4.0%) to close at JPY5,029.0. Compared with the Nikkei 225 Index which fell 488.3 points (or 3.3%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -0.7%. This has been exacerbated by firm volume of 1.7 times average.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Denso, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/00105171194031494
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- The stock dropped 4.0% on high volatility today.- The stock dropped to a three-month low.- The stock's relative price strength percentile is slipping at 66 for 6 months, 62 for 3 months and 19 for 1 month.- The Moving Average Convergence Divergence (MACD) indicator of 12-day Exponential Moving Average (EMA) of 5,278.38 minus the 26-day EMA of 5,316.43 is negative 38.05 suggesting a bearish signal. Both EMA prices are falling, another bearish signal.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price/Earnings of 24.5 [18.3]. We estimate Denso stock is trading at a current year P/E of 14 and a forward year P/E of 8. - Price/Sales of 1.2 [0.7]. - Price to Book of 1.9 [1.5].Other Bearish Signals:- Net profit margin has averaged 4.2% in the last 3 years. This suggests the company is less profitable with a low margin of safety.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity is less than stellar at 7.9%. This is computed as net profit margin of 5.1% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 0.9 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 1.7.- Revenue growth has seen consecutive falls and seems to be on a slippery slope in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]

Bullish Signals- The present value of JPY1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Denso is JPY1,248, for a capital gain of JPY248.
Oversold/Bullish/Support Signals- At JPY5,029.0 the price is below the lower Bollinger band support of JPY5,142.72, indicating an upside for it to return to the band. - The stock is oversold according to the Williams % R indicator of -96.7, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day low of JPY5,013.0.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Year-on-Year Earnings Growth of 104.5% [82.7%].- Return on Assets 4.6% [2.9%].Other Bullish Signals:- Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 1.1. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- Net Profit margin is positive and has seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 4,050,000 shares worth JPY20.4 billion (US$199.6 million) traded. Beta: the Beta of Denso stock is 0.9. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return stock with volatility less than that of the market. - Denso is at a discount of 13.3% to its 12-month high of JPY5,799.0 on 20 Jan, 2014. It is also at a premium of 36.3% to the 12-month low of JPY3,690.0 on 02 Apr, 2013.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Parity:- Return on Equity 7.9% [8.1%].- Price/Earnings/Growth of 0.2 [0.2].
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 18: DENSO Develops EGR Valve Unit[Company Release] KARIYA (Japan) - Global automotive supplier DENSO has developed an exhaust gas recirculation (EGR) valve unit, a major component of EGR systems that helps make diesel engine emissions cleaner. The new unit, the first in the world to integrate an air intake throttle valve and an EGR valve, is half the size of conventional models and requires fewer components, thus reducing costs.
February 03: Denso Announces Third-quarter Financial Results[Company Release] Kariya (Japan) - DENSO Corporation today announced its third quarter global financial results for the nine months ending Dec. 31, 2013:Consolidated net sales totaled 3,016.6 billion yen (US$28.8 billion), a 17.4 percent increase from the previous year.Consolidated operating income totaled 289.9 billion yen (US$2.8 billion), a 54.2 percent increase from the previous year.Consolidated net income totaled 225.6 billion yen (US$2.2 billion), a 72.5 percent increase from the previous year.http://www.globaldenso.com/en/newsreleases/140203-01.htmlSource: Company Website
January 16: Toyota Industries and DENSO Establish Automotive Air-Conditioning Compressor Manufacturing Company in China[Company Release]KARIYA (Japan) - Toyota Industries Corporation (TICO) and DENSO Corporation (DENSO) have established a new company, Yantai Shougang TD Automotive Compressor Co., Ltd. (YST), in Yantai City, Shandong Province, People's Republic of China, for the manufacture of automotive air-conditioning compressors in response to the growing Chinese automobile market.
December 23: Denso: The Korea Fair Trade Commission's Announcement Concerning the Monopoly Regulation and Fair Trade Act related to Certain Automotive Components[Company Release] KARIYA (Japan) - The Korea Fair Trade Commission (the "KFTC") announced today that it decided to order to rectify illegal conduct, impose a surcharge and bring an accusation to certain automotive suppliers pursuant to Articles 19, 21 and 22 of the Monopoly Regulation and Fair Trade Act, in connection with sales of automotive windshield wiper systems and instrumental panel clusters.The KFTC has investigated this matter at certain automotive suppliers, including DENSO Corporation and its subsidiaries in Republic of Korea, and the DENSO companies have fully cooperated with the KFTC.As per the KFTC's announcement, DENSO Corporation and its subsidiaries, DENSO Korea Automotive Corporation and DENSO Korea Electronics Corporation, were named as the suppliers involved in violation of the Monopoly Regulation and Fair Trade Act (No.
October 08: DENSO to exhibit at the 20th ITS World Congress Tokyo 2013[Company Release] KARIYA (Japan) - Global automotive supplier DENSO will exhibit at the 20th World Congress on Intelligent Transport Systems, at the Tokyo International Exhibition Center, Tuesday, Oct. 15, - Friday, Oct. 18. DENSO will present its intelligent transport system (ITS)-related products and technologies mainly in the area of safety, under the theme "Technology to keep people safe wherever they drive-Everyday Confidence, Extraordinary Safety."http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Japan/Stock/News/17603.htmlSource: Company Website
September 27: DENSO and Nagoya University Jointly Develop In-vehicle Battery-based Energy Management System[Company Release]KARIYA (Japan) - Global automotive supplier DENSO and Nagoya University have developed an in-vehicle battery-based energy management system (EMS), which uses forecasting models of household electricity demand and vehicle use to reduce electricity costs. The two organizations will start to evaluate the performance of the system in October this year under the Toyota City Low-carbon Society Verification Project, one of the Next-Generation Energy and Social System Demonstration Projects in Japan led by Japan's Ministry of Economy, Trade and Industry (METI).The EMS coordinates with batteries used in electric and plug-in hybrid vehicles to use their stored electricity to help keep down electricity bills.
September 18: DENSO to Form Strategic Alliance with Sharp Corp[Company Release] KARIYA (Japan) - DENSO Corporation has signed a stock subscription agreement with Sharp Corporation to purchase 2.5 billion yen (approximately US$25.4 million) shares of stock issued by Sharp. DENSO and Sharp will collaborate to create new technologies that improve the comfort, safety and convenience of vehicles by integrating vehicle technologies with home electronic technologies.The collaboration between the two companies will mainly involve the development of comfort technologies for vehicle passengers and connecting vehicle technologies with home and home electronics.DENSO Corporation, headquartered in Kariya, Aichi prefecture, Japan, is a leading global automotive supplier of advanced technology, systems and components in the areas of thermal, powertrain control, electronics and information and safety.
ISIN: JP3551500006
TO:6902; TYO:6902; T:6902; JP:6902
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>