<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CF5D-05CB-2AFB-7AC4"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>/ CORRECTION - Faruqi &amp; Faruqi, LLP Encourages Investors Who Suffered Losses In Excess Of $100,000 Investing In The Medicines Company To Contact The Firm</title><source>Marketwired</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[In the news release, "Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP Encourages Investors Who Suffered Losses In Excess Of $100,000 Investing In The Medicines Company To Contact The Firm," issued earlier today, please be advised that the source company should be Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP instead of The Medicines Company as originally issued incorrectly by Marketwired. Complete corrected text follows.
Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP Encourages Investors Who Suffered Losses In Excess Of $100,000 Investing In The Medicines Company To Contact The Firm
NEW YORK, NY -- March 15, 2014 -- Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP, a leading national securities law firm, reminds investors in The Medicines Company ("Medicines" or the "Company") (NASDAQ: MDCO) of the April 22, 2014 deadline to seek the role of lead plaintiff in a federal securities class action lawsuit filed against Medicines and certain executives.
A complaint has been filed on behalf of all persons who purchased or otherwise acquired Medicines securities between February 20, 2013 and February 12, 2014, inclusive (the "Class Period") in the District of New Jersey.
The complaint alleges that the Company and its executives violated federal securities laws with respect to its disclosures concerning its business, operations, and prospects.
Specifically, the action alleges that throughout the Class Period defendants made false and/or misleading statements and/or failed to disclose that: (i) the Company's drug candidate, Cangrelor, did not show superiority when compared to clopidogrel, a competing drug previously approved by the FDA; and (ii) the Company's CHAMPION clinical trials comparing Cangrelor's efficacy with that of clopidorel were unethical and improperly administered.
On February 12, 2014, the Company announced that the NASDAQ had halted the trading of its stock in connection with an FDA advisory panel. Later that same day, the FDA advisory panel voted against approval of Cangrelor.
Following this news, the Company's stock declined $3.82 per share, or over 11%, to close at $29.28 per share on February 13, 2014.
Request more information now by clicking here: www.faruqilaw.com/MDCO. There is no cost or obligation to you.
Take Action
If you invested in Medicines stock, bonds or options between February 20, 2013 and February 12, 2014 and would like to discuss your legal rights, visit www.faruqilaw.com/MDCO. You can also contact us by calling Richard Gonnello or Francis McConville toll free at 877-247-4292 or at 212-983-9330 or by sending an e-mail to rgonnello@faruqilaw.com or fmcconville@faruqilaw.com Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP also encourages anyone with information regarding Medicines' conduct to contact the firm, including whistleblowers, former employees, shareholders and others.
Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP is a national law firm which represents investors and individuals in class action litigation. The firm is focused on providing exemplary legal services in complex litigation in the areas of securities, shareholder, antitrust and consumer litigation, throughout all phases of litigation. The firm has an experienced trial team which has achieved significant victories on behalf of the firm's clients. To keep track of the latest securities litigation news, follow us on Twitter at www.twitter.com/MergerActivity or on Facebook at www.facebook.com/FaruqiLaw.
Attorney Advertising. The law firm responsible for this advertisement is Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP (www.faruqilaw.com). Prior results do not guarantee or predict a similar outcome with respect to any future matter. We welcome the opportunity to discuss your particular case. All communications will be treated in a confidential manner.
SOURCE: Faruqi & Faruqi, LLP
]]></text></news-item>