<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="CFB6-A5E7-6469-5B3D"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Rate shock </title><source>Patriot News (Harrisburg, Pennsylvania)</source><author>For PennLive  ALLISON DOUGHERTY</author><text><![CDATA[Lemoyne raised sewer rates in July, and they went into effect with the January meter reading. The bills are coming due, and some customers' bills have skyrocketed.
"We have a leak somewhere," said Shayne Edmunds, co-owner and founder of Neato Burrito, referring to his thoughts after seeing the first bill with the new rates for his restaurant.
It wasn't a leak. The sewer bill for one month at the Lemoyne restaurant was $655. That's up from roughly $120 to $250 a month before the new rates. The monthly sewer rates at Edmunds' Neato Burrito restaurants in other municipalities are around $100 or less, he said. Edmunds said there's not much the company can do to reduce the size of the Lemoyne bill.
"Our water demand is our water demand," he said.
Edmunds isn't the only one in Lemoyne with sewer-rate sticker shock. Residential and commercial customers saw their rates increase with January's usage, but the increases on the commercial side can be staggering.
The sewer bill for Quality Cleaners went up from about $600 a month to around $1,800. The increase will be felt by the family-run dry cleaner, which has been in business more than 50 years, co-owner Ed Sternberg said.
Lemoyne's rate increase will fund sewer plant operating costs and the loan costs associated with sewer system upgrades at the Lemoyne Sewer Authority that are required by the Chesapeake Bay Initiative. The borough needs about $3 million a year to cover the debt service and the day-to-day operation of the plant, which will be funded by sewer customers.
Lemoyne's new sewer-rate structure includes a monthly minimum plus a possible consumption charge, depending upon water usage. The monthly minimum covers fixed costs at the plant, such as salaries, most utilities and loan costs. The variable usage rate funds changing costs such as chemicals, some electricity and sludge removal, borough manager Robert Ihlein said.
It's a rate structure with which some business owners take issue. Bob Kessler Jr., president of Kessler's Foods, is one of them.
The company uses water in manufacturing its products. Water that goes into the building does not necessarily go out in sewer flow, but Lemoyne sewer customers pay a variable rate based on water consumption, not on sewer use.
"Why should I pay for something I'm not using?" Kessler asked.
Sternberg, who sees some of the water coming into his shop go up in steam from his equipment, has the same question. Sternberg and Kessler suggested metering sewer usage instead of basing rates on water consumption.
Kessler didn't want to share his sewer costs, but he said the rate increase is being passed on to customers in the form of higher prices for products.
Not all Lemoyne business owners were affected by January's rate increase. Some have utility costs included in their lease rates, said Rebecca Yearick, who is with the Cumberland County Housing and Redevelopment authorities and is Lemoyne's downtown services coordinator.
But for tenants of the West Shore Farmers Market, an inclusive lease might only delay possible increases in operating costs that result from Lemoyne's rate increase.
Greg Katshir, owner of the market, said for the time being the market will have to cover the higher sewer costs, which caused the market's sewer bill to go up "double and a half."
As leases of the market's tenants expire, the sewer increase will be passed on to them in higher leasing costs, Katshir said.
Rick Jordan, CEO of Smith Land & Improvement Corp., the parent company of L.B. Smith Ford Lincoln and the West Shore Plaza in Lemoyne, said his firm anticipated rising sewer costs and plans to do a "better job on our utilization of water."
None of the business owners interviewed said their companies were in danger of closing as a result of higher sewer bills. Even with the increased costs of doing business in the borough, Jordan and Edmunds said they are happy with their Lemoyne locations.
But Katshir said, "It hurts our bottom line."
Quality Cleaners
Co-owner Ed Sternberg says the family-run dry cleaner's monthly bill jumped from $600 a month to around $1, 800.
Neato Burrito
Co-owner and founder Shayne Edmunds says its sewer bill rose from between $120 and $250 a month to $655.
INSIDE
Sewer and water bills are piling up across the midstate, leaving municipalities struggling with residents who are months behind in paying. PAGE A10
Debating the Chesapeake Bay pollution limits. PAGE C1
]]></text></news-item>