<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D0B8-30C2-172B-5898"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>38th Conejo Valley Home Remodeling Show: April 26 &amp; 27</title><source>PR.com</source><author>Conejo Valley Home Remodeling Show</author><text><![CDATA[Westalke Village, CA, March 14, 2014 --(PR.com)-- Dates for the 38th Conejo Valley Home Remodeling Show will be Saturday and Sunday, April 26 and 27, at the Westlake Hyatt (880 S. Westlake Blvd., Westlake Village). The spring show will feature local contractors, landscapers, roofers, interior designers, solar installers and other home improvement professionals.
"Spring is the time when people start thinking about upgrading their homes," says Rick Goodman, the show's organizer. "The home show is the biggest in the area with more than 150 home improvement specialists taking part. Every type of home improvement option is on display."
One of the show's vendors is Comfort Zone Sleep Gallery (www.comfortzonesleepgallery.com) with its showroom in Oxnard. Featured at the show will be dual-purpose furniture for small spaces. "This type of furniture maximizes a home's living space," says Joe Lujan, director of sales and marketing. "Say you have an extra bedroom where you only occasionally use the bed. Take out the bed and add a free-standing Murphy chest, which is the size of credenza but opens up to a queen size bed. With dual- purpose furniture, you now have the whole room free but can still accommodate guests who stay overnight. For those who live in small apartments or condos, our traditional Murphy beds make the best use of the home's square footage."
A new vendor this year is Life Systems Group (www.lifetanks.com). It recently introduced its LifeTank clean water system designed to provide households with fresh water in case the public water supply is interrupted. LifeTank provides continuous replenishment of fresh water without maintenance and, when necessary, has the ability to isolate its water supply from outside contamination. Standard models are 80-gallon and120-gallon. Larger capacities tanks are available by custom order. "An earthquake or severe storm can leave residents without clean water for days or even weeks," says Dave Foucar, president of the Camarillo-based company. "LifeTank allows families to easily safeguard against disaster. Simply install it and not think about it until needed."
As an added feature to the home show, on Saturday, April 26, gourmet food trucks will be on hand from 11:00 a.m. to 4:00 p.m.
Home show hours are Saturday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. and Sunday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.
The Conejo Valley Home Remodeling Show, a bi-annual event since 1995, takes place in spring and fall. The entry fee at the door is $4 per person. For free tickets and a list of participating vendors visit www.westlakehomeshow.com. For more information, call 805-529-0760, go to www.facebook.com/ConejoValleyHomeShow or e-mail showkase9@gmail.com
]]></text></news-item>