<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D0F1-56D3-E0A0-3FA8"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>VIDEO - "Turkey torture" hidden-camera video highlights need for transparency</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[A hidden-camera video taken on an Ontario turkey farm is raising questions about Canadian animal welfare standards and a lack of transparency on some farms.
The graphic video, which was secretly taken by a member of Mercy for Animals Canada( https://www.mercyforanimals.org/ ) who got a job at Hybrid Turkeys breeding farm in Ontario, shows several birds with open wounds, as well as a failed euthanization where an employee beats a bird several times with a shovel.
Watch the "turkey torture" video here( http://www.turkeytorture.ca/ ). (Warning: The video contains graphic content.)
"This investigation graphically illustrates that the hidden price of Canadian turkey meat is horrific animal abuse," Mercy for Animals spokeswoman Twyla Francois told The Canadian Press( http://o.canada.com/news/video-shows-blatant-animal-cruelty-at-ontario-turkey-farm/ ).
"This is blatant animal cruelty that shouldn't be supported in a civilized society."
In a statement, Hybrid called the alleged cruelty an isolated incident.
"Hybrid has zero tolerance for animal abuse," said managing director David Libertini.
The company also said it would co-operate with any investigations into the abuse and pledged to become the first turkey producer in North America to employ mandatory video monitoring and veterinary review of all turkey euthanasia.
But Mercy for Animals wants more, calling for all facilities that handle farmed animals to install video monitoring and livestream the footage on the Internet.
According to the pro-vegan group, more than 21 million turkeys are raised and killed for food every year in Canada - of which about 60 per cent come from Hybrid parent stock. Hendrix Genetics, the parent company of Hybrid Turkeys, is the second largest producer in the world.
What for more on this story on Farmgate in coming days.
*
Do you have a story idea for the Farmgate?
Glenda Luymes is an award-winning Province journalist and farmer's daughter who loves local food.
Get in touch at gluymes@theprovince.com( mailto:gluymes@theprovince.com ), twitter.com/glendaluymes( https://postmediaprovince.wordpress.com/wp-admin/twitter.com/glendaluymes ) or on Facebook.
]]></text></news-item>