<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D0F8-0E7E-E527-39F9"><date>2014-03-10</date><title>Chiquita, Fyffes Announce $1.1B Merger</title><source>TheStreet.com</source><author>Renee Cordes</author><text><![CDATA[NEW YORK (The Deal) -- Produce company Chiquita Brands International said Monday it would offer stock worth $526 million for Irish peer Fyffes to create a new global top banana with close to $4.6 billion in 2013 sales.
The stock-for-stock transaction will leave Chiquita shareholders with about 50.7% and Fyffes shareholders owning about 49.3% of a new company to be called ChiquitaFyffes. Fyffes shareholders will receive 0.1567 of a ChiquitaFyffes share for each Fyffes share, while the ratio for Chiquita shareholders will be one for one. That puts the companies' combined equity value at about $1.07 billion.
The transaction values each Fyffes share at 1.22 euros ($1.69), or 38% above Friday's close. Fyffes shares soared more than 47% in Dublin on Monday to 1.31 euros. In New York on Friday, Chiquita shares finished the week at $10.84, little changed from Thursday's close.
The combined company will surpass Westlake Village, Calif.-based Dole Food Co. as the world's top banana company but will hold the No. 2 slot behind Dole in the U.S. ChiquitaFyffes will be the U.S. market leader in packaged salads, its top melon importer, and the third-largest pineapple distributor in the U.S. and Europe. The companies are targeting $40 million in annualized cost synergies by the end of 2016.
During an analyst call, executives said they didn't expect any antitrust issues in any jurisdiction and noted the companies had only a limited customer overlap in Europe, where the new entity will be the market leader. Janney Montgomery Scott LLC analyst Jonathan Feeney said their confidence was surprising, and noted that European regulators have previously been "quite strict" about consolidation in the banana industry.
The deal "is a positive step for the industry, but not one that necessarily portends further consolidation," added the Philadelphia-based analyst.
Charlotte, N.C.-based Chiquita, which markets and distributes bananas, salads and healthy snacks under the Chiquita and Fresh Express brands, has annual revenue of more than $3 billion.
Last month, the company said it had narrowed its full-year loss to $16 million, down from $405 million in 2012, as it restructures to hit operating margins for its core business of bananas and salads that it has set itself for the end of 2015. Chiquita operates in more than 70 countries but gets 61% of revenue from the U.S.
Dublin-based Fyffes has annual sales of more than $1.5 billion, including $342 million from joint ventures. It markets its produce under several trademarks including the Fyffes and Sol brand names. It operates in Europe, which accounts for 81% of revenue, the United States, Central and South America, and recently launched operations in Asia.
Chiquita CEO Ed Lonergan will serve as chairman and Fyffes chairman David McCann as CEO of ChiquitaFyffes, which will be listed on the New York Stock Exchange.
Senior executives will work out of corporate offices in Charlotte and Dublin, and the combined company's board will be split between the companies and include a mutually agreed-upon director.
Goldman, Sachs & Co. is Chiquita's lead adviser. Wells Fargo Securities LLC is advising Chiquita's board.
Lazard's Tim George, Alexander Hecker and Nicholas Shott are advising Fyffes.
A Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher & Flom LLP team including David Friedman, Peter Krupp, Nathaniel Carden, David Rievman, Timothy F. Nelson, Michael Zeidel and Lynn McGovern; McCann FitzGerald; and Taft Stettinius & Hollister LLP are Chiquita's law firms.
A Simpson Thacher & Bartlett LLP team led by Mario Ponce and Elizabeth Cooper and Arthur Cox are advising Fyffes.
]]></text></news-item>