<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D2C5-E5A0-1A7F-D04A"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Zimbabwean leader threatens to close some diamond firms</title><source>Bangladesh Government News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The official news Agency of Bangladesh (BSS) has issued following news release:
Zimbabwean President RobertMugabe reiterated yesterday that his government will restructurethe diamond sector to leave only one state- controlled company inoperation in the country's diamond-rich area.
Speaking at a ceremony to celebrate his 90th birthdayorganized by civil servants, Mugabe said the restructuring willensure government plays a greater role in mining of the diamonds.
"We are reorganizing our diamond sector in a way toconsolidate the systems there. We are going to say good-bye tosome of the mines there so that we consolidate and just have onemining group in which the state will be the main company," Mugabesaid.
Zimbabwe's diamond mining concentrates in the eastern regionof Marange, near the border with Mozambique. There are sevencompanies licensed to mine diamond in Marange fields, accountingfor more than 80 percent of the country's diamond output, whichis estimated to have reached 11 million carats in 2013.
While income from diamond export has been instrumental to thecountry's economic boom since 2010, there have been allegationsof lack of transparency in the diamond mining industry with theTreasury saying that it had received little diamond revenue.
Mugabe, who turned 90 last month, has hinted on government'splans to streamline operations in Marange. He said Zimbabwe wouldneed to mould its diamond sector along the same lines as that ofBotswana and South Africa which have very few diamond companies.
The veteran president also condemned growing corruption inthe public sector and warned that his government would soonlaunch investigations to flush out corruption in the diamondsector.
"We will be investigating operations in Marange to find outhow things have been going on there and if any corrupt activitiesare detected, people will answer for it. I can tell you," thepresident vowed.
Mines Minister Walter Chidhakwa has warned tough measuresagainst mining firms in Marange who he accuses of prejudicinggovernment of a lot of revenue through cartels which under-valueddiamonds. Operations will be halted until it was certain that thegovernment would get fair returns, Chidhakwa said.
Some of the diamond firms have said they are facing seriousfinancial problems due to declining diamond deposits, and havesince asked government for more mining concessions.
]]></text></news-item>