<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D3FA-04B1-BCEC-D0B7"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>The Shuman Law Firm Investigates Hyperdynamics Corp.</title><source>News Bites US Markets</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[[News Story] BOULDER, Colo.-- The Shuman Law Firm announces that it is investigating potential claims against certain officers and directors of Hyperdynamics Corp. ("Hyperdynamics" or the "Company") (NYSE: HDY). Hyperdynamics is a Houston, TX-based independent oil and gas exploration company, primarily working in Guinea and North Africa.
The Firm's investigation relates to the Company's February 7, 2014 disclosure in a 10-Q Quarterly Report filed with the Securities Exchange Commission ("SEC") that [d]uring September 2013, we received a subpoena from the United States Department of Justice. Subsequently, in January 2014 we received a subpoena from the United States Securities and Exchange Commission. Both subpoenas request that the Company produce documents relating to its business in Guinea. We understand that the DOJ and SEC are investigating whether our activities in obtaining and retaining the Concession rights and our relationships with charitable organizations potentially violate the U.S. Foreign Corrupt Practices Act or U.S. anti-money laundering statutes. We have retained legal counsel to represent us in these matters, initiated an internal investigation, and we are cooperating fully with the government."
On February 12, 2014, Bloomberg reported that Tullow Oil Plc had suspended work at a Guinea project it was partnering with Hyperdynamics on as a result of the DOJ and SEC investigations. Following this news, Hyperdynamics stock fell approximately 58% to close at $2.19 per share.
If you currently own Hyperdynamics common stock and are interested in discussing your rights, or have information relating to this investigation, please contact Kip B. Shuman or Rusty E. Glenn toll free at (866) 974-8626 or email Mr. Shuman at kip@shumanlawfirm.com or email Mr. Glenn at rusty@shumanlawfirm.com
Source: NASDAQ Stock Exchange
ISIN: US4489541072
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>