<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D42F-2711-3F41-EBB5"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Farmers: Time to collect your cow pats</title><source>The Sunday Star-Times (Auckland, New Zealand)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Why aren't our milk exporters pressured to be certifiably sustainable?
--------------------
LISTEN UP dairy farmers, the people have spoken and you have to collect your cow pats.
An independent survey released last week of 3134 people aged 18 and over concluded 89 per cent of New Zealanders think fresh water streams and rivers should be cleaned by you polluters, not ratepayers and taxpayers. Interestingly, just over 76 per cent of farm owners and managers agreed with polluter-pays, and 89 per cent of those who voted for National in the 2011 election.
And why shouldn't farmers fork out? Farms are businesses, just like department stores, shopping malls or supermarkets. Taxpayers don't pay to take away the rubbish polluting these places when we schlepp through with our families. Farmers would argue public money cleans the streets outside shops but we all walk the footpaths; the public can't troop across private paddocks but we pay to clean up the shit (literally, 'scuse the language) downstream that's been discharged from their stock.
The cleaning of dairying's pollution is subsidised because it's "the backbone of the economy". But hang on, only increased revenue is counted, just one side of the balance sheet. The impacts, such as the cost of returning Canterbury's groundwater to drinking standard or to remove a tonne of nitrate from Lake Rotorua, are ignored. Expose the truths and dairying's probably the patella of the economy.
It's somewhat unfair to heap all the blame on dairying though - intensive and bad management of hill country, with gullies stripped of bush cover, doesn't help. Nor does urban discharge such as wastewater plants like the one owned by Palmerston North City Council which repeatedly discharged dreadful unmentionables into the Manawatu River, already one of the most polluted rivers in the Western world. But was the council prosecuted? No, while the Kapiti Coast District Council will prosecute pensioners, the Manawatu-Whanganui Regional Council didn't have the guts to penalise the council.
When our waterways are in such dreadful condition, we can't keep converting land to intensive dairy (more cows per hectare), particularly in drought-prone regions, and expecting, as of right, to dam rivers to irrigate, as with Hawke's Bay and the Ruataniwha project. Whoever said this will mitigate climate change is bonkers - just more cows weeing nitrogen into the soil and into the waterways - and another nettlesome nutrient, phosphate, flowing into water with sediment. Farmers have to bite the bullet and fence streams to prevent these problems.
And political parties can stop blaming each other - 21 years ago we signed up to polluter-pays in the Rio Declaration - so it's about time MPs listened to the electorate instead of trading shrill rhetoric. We have an issue with youth unemployment and a need for fencing: let's put the two together for a solution. In the wine industry it's difficult to export without being certifiably sustainable, and illegal to dump acidic waste in waterways. But have you ever seen "sustainable milk" out there?
When eight out of 10 New Zealanders want water that's safe for swimming, fishing and food gathering, it's time for more farmers to take note and stop expecting the public to kiss goodbye to freshwater activities simply because they claim mega wealth. That's a quasi-economic blackmail attitude which allowed Kim Dotcom into the country, and look at the carnage he's created.
It's obvious we have problems when you can't take your dog to the river in case it eats toxic algae because the water's so polluted.
It's time to call taihoa on dairy conversions. Enough already.
]]></text></news-item>