<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D53C-E5DE-35AF-8027"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>'Street kids abuse correction fluid to fight hunger pangs'</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Bindiya Chari</author><text><![CDATA[PANAJI: It is not surprising that substance abuse is common among the street children in the state, however, what's rather shocking is the substance they use to get a "high."
The easily-accessible correction fluid (diluter) is the commonest form of substance abused by street children in the state. Non-government organizations (NGOs) working with street children in Goa, claim they invariably find children, beggars, ragpickers and children at railway stations abusing correction fluid to get intoxicated.
The fluid can be easily bought by paying 30 to 35 from any stationary shop.
Emidio Pinho, director at the NGO, SCAN, says substance abuse is most common amongst children at railway stations. "We have come across children sniffing correction fluid when they were rescued. Children mostly sniff whitening liquid to get rid of their hunger pangs."
The NGOs, however, are not able to trace from which stores children procure the stuff. "These children are always on the move and travel between states and hence it is difficult to zero in on the place of supply. Though it is a known fact that all stationary shops sell it with no questions asked," says Pinho.
In Vasco too, there are many street children addicted to sniffing diluting substance, particularly those residing in the slums. Some are also found to be addicted to tobacco products.
Aftab Shah, Jamiat Ismail group, that works on issues that affect society, says street children are initiated into abusing diluter or any other substance thanks to peer pressure.
Arun Pandey of Arz, a Vasco-based NGO, working with children and women, says they have observed 30-40 street children doing ragpicking in the port town and many of them are used to sniffing.
He says while boys mostly use diluters, girls chew tobacco, mostly gutkha.
"With long hours of work and no parental care, these children are easily drawn to such addictions. At times, they are also involved in petty crimes," says Pandey.
They have come across several cases of children committing crime after getting a high, he adds.
Pinho says children into substance abuse, when referred to a child welfare committee, are sent for medical treatment to help them get rid of the addiction.
"Such children are sent to the Institute of Psychiatry and Human Behavior (IPHB), Bambolim, where they are kept under observation and discharged only after they are cured," he said.
While medical treatment of addicts is not the problem, it's not possible to keep a tab on them once they are discharged and left in the company of their guardian or parents. "Often, they are on the move and it's not easy to keep a check on them. Chances of them reverting back to their old habits are high," he pointed out.
The NGOs claim that diluter is widely abused by street children, and there are no statistics available to pinpoint the exact number of children addicted to sniffing ink diluter. There is nothing under the law that prohibits sale of diluter to children.
Salim Veljee, director, food and drugs administration (FDA) said he is aware that diluter is misused for other uses, however, he said he can't do anything about it for it is not listed as a food or drug item.
He said sometime back, the government of India had issued guidelines for packaging such items so that their abuse can be controlled. "I'm not sure whether its implementation has started or not," he said.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>