<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D55B-50BD-F38A-EB55"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Power suit</title><source>Green Bay Press-Gazette (Wisconsin)</source><author>By, Scott Cooper Williams</author><text><![CDATA[A former business partner is seeking nearly $400 million in damages in a breach-of-contract lawsuit that stems from a failed waste-to-energy venture by the Oneida Tribe of Indians.
The suit filed in Chicago accuses the Oneida tribe and its affiliate, Oneida Seven Generations Corp., of violating agreements to lease equipment and share profits with Generation Clean Fuels LLC, a firm based in suburban Chicago.
The dispute arises from an Oneida effort to build a plant in the Green Bay area that would convert common household trash into a new source of energy using a heating process known as pyrolysis or gasification.
Because of concerns about environmental hazards, the proposed plant has been rejected in Green Bay and elsewhere, including by the tribe's members, who also acted last year to dissolve Oneida Seven Generations.
The suit, filed March 6, states that the tribal-owned company reneged on deals that would have brought Generation Clean Fuels and its affiliates $397 million in lease payments, revenues and other benefits from the failed development.
The Oneida tribe is named as a co-defendant, along with Green Bay Renewable Energy LLC, another firm associated with Oneida Seven Generations.
Gerald Dombrowski, attorney for Generation Clean Fuels, said in a written statement that his clients have "an iron-clad cause of action" against the tribe and its affiliated businesses in relation to the failed waste-to-energy venture.
"We will not rest until we receive fair and just compensation for all of the damages caused by the tribal entities," Dombrowski said, adding that he expects the final judgment to amount to "hundreds of millions of dollars."
The suit is pending in Cook County Circuit Court in Chicago.
Oneida tribal spokesman Phil Wisneski said officials were aware of the suit, but they declined to comment on it.
At Oneida Seven Generations offices in Hobart, a spokeswoman said the company had no comment.
Created by the tribe in 1995 to identify new business ventures, Oneida Seven Generations has spent several years pursuing its proposed gasification plant. The facility would process tons of municipal waste at high temperatures, creating a source of energy while reducing the need for landfill dumping.
Proponents call it a green-friendly energy concept, but critics liken it to a trash incinerator that would pollute the environment.
Opposition in Ashwaubenon, Green Bay and finally the Oneida Indian Reservation have prevented the company from building the plant. The company sued the city of Green Bay for revoking a permit, in a separate court fight that remains under appeal after a judge ruled in the city's favor.
Dissatisfied with Oneida Seven Generations, members of the tribe voted in December to dissolve the company.
According to the new lawsuit, then-company President Kevin Cornelius signed agreements with Generation Clean Fuels and its affiliates in May and June 2013. In the agreements, Cornelius agreed to lease "liquefaction machines" for the gasification plant and to give 49 percent of the operation's proceeds to General Clean Fuels, along with subsidiaries identified as ACF Leasing LLC and ACF Services LLC.
Cornelius subsequently left Oneida Seven Generations without explanation.
Alleging that the gasification venture was "inadequately capitalized," the suit states that Oneida entities breached the deal and committed "a violation of the covenants of good faith and fair dealings."
Damages sought include $22 million in lost lease payments, $3 million in costs and fees, $122 million in lost profits and another $250 million in value that the plaintiffs feel they would have gained from the venture.
No schedule has been announced for a hearing in the case.
John Filcher, a leader of Incinerator Free Brown County, a group opposed to the waste-to-energy development, said he was surprised by some revelations in the suit. He noted that the disputed contracts allegedly were signed long after Oneida officials had encountered widespread opposition to the project.
"You have to wonder what in the world were they thinking," he said.
Noting the large amount of damages sought, Filcher also said naming the tribe as a co-defendant was significant.
"The deep pocket here would be the tribe itself," he said. "This is going to be a bruising spectacle."
- swilliams@pressgazettemedia.com and follow him on Twitter @pgscottwilliams
On the Net
Read the lawsuit online at greenbaypressgazette.com.
]]></text></news-item>