<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D574-1CC9-E7A9-5A09"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Royal Commission into the Home Insulation Program: The four tradesmen who died</title><source>ABC Premium News (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The royal commission into the Rudd government's troubled home insulation program that resulted in the deaths of four young men will begin hearing evidence in Brisbane today.
Former Labor prime ministers Kevin Rudd and Julia Gillard have been asked to provide documents to the Royal Commission into the Home Insulation Program and face the prospect of being called to appear in person before Commissioner Ian Hangar QC.
It is believed other senior Labor figures including current Opposition frontbencher Penny Wong have been contacted by the commission.
Read more about the men whose deaths are linked to the scheme, which was set up in 2009 as an economic stimulus measure to help ward off the effects of the global financial crisis.
Matthew Fuller
Matthew Fuller was the first of the four young people who died working under the home insulation program.
He was 25 when he was electrocuted in a roof cavity in outer Brisbane in October 2009. His girlfriend, who was working alongside him, was badly burnt.
The young couple had been saving to move in together.
Matthew's father Kevin Fuller said his son had been laying ceiling insulation for less than a fortnight when he accidentally put a metal staple through aluminium foil and into a live electrical cable lying underneath.
"Matthew was a worker and knew that he could go and earn enough money to set up his future life," he said."
"On the day Matthew got killed, in the car was the application for Monique and Matt to move into a new rental place.
Matthew had been working for installation company QHI when he died.
The company was directed by 19-year-old electrician Ben McKay, who was in charge of on-the-job safety for unqualified insulation installers like Matthew.
During the inquest into Matthew's death, Mr McKay told the Brisbane coroner's court that the installation could have been made 100 per cent safe by disconnecting power from the mains source.
But he said this was not routinely done because the work involved would have made it impossible for his company to make a profit.
At the inquest in May 2013, Mr McKay acknowledged he had been aware of up to four instances where staples had been put through cables before Matthew's death.
He said those incidents had not resulted in deaths.
The Queensland Government's regional manager of electrical safety compliance, Michael Gibson, told that inquest he had held concerns about the safety of the installation scheme three months before Matthew's death and had voiced these concerns to his manager.
Rueben Barnes
The youngest victim of the installation scheme was Rueben Barnes, who was 16 when he was electrocuted at a home near Rockhampton in 2009.
The first-year carpentry apprentice had been working for installation company Arrow Maintenance for less than a month and had received no insulation training and no induction.
His co-workers at the site had not been trained in first aid treatment for electric shock.
Lawyer Bill Potts, who is representing Rueben's family, says his client hopes the royal commission will provide answers to some lingering questions.
"Murray Barnes, who was Rueben's father, knows what killed his son," he said.
"What he wants to know is the whys. Why were decisions made? Why were warnings not heeded?"
Marcus Wilson
Marcus Wilson, 19, died of heat exhaustion after spending his first day in a new job working in a roof cavity installing insulation.
He was the third person to die in connection to the scheme and his death prompted calls from the Australian Council of Trade Unions to halt the scheme until safety standards were improved.
At the time, the Labor government said that although the deaths were regrettable, the insulation program had the highest safety requirements ever imposed.
Marcus's sister, Jessica Wilson, said the $2.5 billion program prompted employers to cut corners.
"I think it's just a make money scheme, basically. Get any workers you can in there, experienced or not, just get them in there, get your money's worth out of them, who cares about the workers," she said.
"Unfortunately it did take the death of my brother but I want someone responsible for this. I think the Government needs to wake up and just start taking action."
The Labor government shut down the insulation scheme on February 19, 2010.
Mitchell Sweeney
Mitchell Sweeney was the last person to die as a result of the scheme. He was killed in north Queensland in February 2010, months after the safety hazards of the insulation installation had become apparent.
The 22-year-old died after being electrocuted while using metal staples to lay conductive insulation in a roof in Cairns.
The practice had known safety hazards and had already been banned in New Zealand.
Lawyer Peter Koutsoukis from Maurice Blackburn is suing Mitchell's employer, Titan Insulations, on behalf of the young man's mother and two older brothers.
Mr Koutsoukis says Titan is in liquidation but has insurance and $330,000 in compensation for nervous shock is being sought.
He says his firm has considered seeking compensation from the Queensland and Commonwealth governments as well.
"We've looked at that and we don't think it's necessary because we're focusing on what happened on the day," he said.
"And on the day that this event occurred Titan Insulation was responsible for his supervision, for his training, for instructions and all of those things, and so it's a strong action against them and so we're just focused on them."
]]></text></news-item>