<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D585-11EC-6CE1-C0DE"><date>2014-03-15</date><title></title><source>South China Morning Post</source><author>Name Name name.name@scmp.com</author><text><![CDATA[Anhui Gas racket busted
Six people have been detained in Chuzhou for allegedly producing and selling illegal liquified fuel to homes in nearby Nanjing , capital of neighbouring Jiangsu province, the Nanjing Daily reports. The gang mixed liquified gas with dimethyl ether, a combustible compound, at two illegal plants in Chuzhou. The producers made 1,000 yuan (HK$1,260) on each tonne of illegal fuel sold, earning 17 million yuan on more than 3,000 tonnes sold since late 2012.
Three miners were killed and another was injured in an underground blast at Huaibei on Wednesday, China News Service reports. Leaking seam gas was blamed for the blast. Eighteen other miners working underground escaped injury. China's mines are among the world's most dangerous. While safety has improved in recent years, in 2007, the mainland produced a third of the world's coal but had 80 per cent of the industry's deaths, according to the UN.
Gansu
A total of 242 rooms were destroyed in a fire in a Tibetan village in Zhouqu county on Thursday, Xinhua reports. The fire was caused by an electrical short circuit and took nearly seven hours to extinguish. There were no reports of injuries, but 133 villagers lost their homes in the blaze.
Two men who injured two doctors in a quarrel at a hospital in Lanzhou were jailed for 22 months on Thursday, the Lanzhou Morning Post reports. The two were hailing a taxi, which hit one of them when it stopped. They called an ambulance, but later refused to pay for the service or the hospital medical fees, claiming they were victims of a traffic accident. The two then quarrelled with the doctors, and injured them slightly.
Guangdong
A 16-year-old high school pupil jumped to his death in Shenzhen on Thursday, the Southern Metropolis Daily reports. Classmates said the 11th grader jumped from the fifth floor after a teacher blamed him for cheating or helping others to cheat during an exam on Thursday morning.
A woman in Dongguan has complained to the city government after her unemployment insurance claim was rejected, even though the municipal unemployment fund had a surplus of more than 1.3 billion yuan at the end of last year, the Yangcheng Evening News reports. The woman was told she was not entitled to the insurance as she quit her previous job. But the woman argued that many employers forced workers to leave instead of firing them, to avoid severance payments.
Hebei
A 20-year-old man who sold fake branded electronics online was jailed for 15 months and fined 70,000 yuan in Shijiazhuang on Wednesday, the Yanzhao Evening News reports. The man bought the knock-offs cheaply before trying to pass them off as the real thing online. He was arrested after buyers reported his online shop on Taobao to police.
A village committee comprised of five officials near Xingtai has spent more than 20,000 yuan on restaurants in the past three months, China News Service reports. Villagers questioned whether the village cadres were still squandering public funds despite the latest crackdown on extravagance. The village chief said the committee had already cut spending by 80 per cent compared to previous years.
Hubei
Police arrested 27 suspected drug traffickers recently in Gongan county, Jingzhou , People.com.cn reports. Drugs, a makeshift gun and two bullets were also confiscated during the raid. The gang had allegedly transported narcotics from Laos and Myanmar to Yunnan and Guangdong since 2011. The arrests follow an 18-month operation by Jingzhou police to bust the trafficking network.
Wuhan is setting up a food-tracking system for dairy products to improve food safety, China News Service reports. All products made by the city's seven dairy processors will be monitored along the supply chain when it comes into use at the end of the year. Wuhan is one of the first mainland cities to establish such a monitoring system.
Jiangsu
A former vice-mayor of Xinghua city who took 300,000 yuan in bribes over five years has been sentenced to 10 years in prison, the Modern Express reports. The court also ordered him to pay 150,000 yuan. Mei Jiancheng, 50, had held the position since 2001, but started cashing in on his power to approve development plans in 2008. His wife admitted that Mei had given her money, but said he told her it came from bonuses at work.
A passenger in Xuzhou mistakenly paid a taxi driver 6,969 yuan for a 10-yuan fare when he used a smartphone app for payment, Jiangsu TV reports. The mistake was noticed immediately, but as it takes 15 days for such payment to be transferred to the driver's bank account, he had to refund the passenger in advance.
Sichuan
A 25-year-old Chengdu man is seeking 40,000 yuan in compensation from a hair salon after the hairdresser cut his ear, the Chengdu Business Daily reports. The customer received eight stitches to his right ear, in a medical treatment which cost him about 1,000 yuan. The hair salon manager agreed to cover the medical expenses but refused to pay the compensation. The man argued the scar may be permanent and could be a disadvantage when looking for a wife.
A salvage company in Chengdu tied the body of a man who drowned to a bridge on Monday to demand payment from his family, the West China Metropolis Daily reports. The victim was a 22-year-old man who fell from the bridge. The family paid only 4,000 yuan while the company demanded 15,000 yuan after they found the body. The company then asked for more cash in red envelopes to bring the body ashore, saying it was a traditional request to avoid bad luck.
Zhejiang
Two people were killed and three others were injured when a tanker truck exploded in Taizhou on Thursday night, Xinhua reported. The driver was killed instantly while a passenger died in hospital. The explosion shattered windows at nearby homes, which caused the injuries. Local authorities were still investigating the cause of the explosion and what the truck was delivering. Lax road safety rules for hazardous cargo have been blamed for scores of deadly truck blasts on the mainland.
Ningbo city government is offering one-time subsidies to graduates who have worked for more than a year at small-scale enterprises, the Modern Gold Express reports. The 6,000-yuan subsidy for each graduate will be effective from 2013 to 2015. The city said the scheme was meant to be an incentive for graduates to take jobs at smaller firms.
]]></text></news-item>