<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D5D8-8347-DCFA-84E9"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Plans for quarry rattle neighbors</title><source>The Tennessean (Nashville, Tennessee)</source><author>By, Getahn Ward</author><text><![CDATA[Bobby Stockard points to cracks in the bricks of his home off Whites Creek Pike in North Nashville as one example of effects over the years from blasting at the Rogers Group quarry a mile away.
"It's just a rumble, and you can feel the vibration from the blasts," said the longtime Trinity Hills resident, who routinely calls the company to complain.
In response to such concerns and to extend the working life of the quarry, Nashville-based Rogers is pitching neighbors a plan to relocate the mining operation underground to property across Knight Road. By May, the company plans to seek a zoning change that would allow it to mine limestone 100 feet below the surface and create 300 acres of green space above - including on 183 acres it wants to buy from Habitat for Humanity.
"It's a rare opportunity when we get to do something that improves our operation, and improves the conditions for the neighbors at the same time," said Dan Rose, vice president and general counsel for Rogers. He said plans also include a new asphalt plant across Knight that would use newer technology, and be hidden from street view.
Rogers expects the changes to significantly reduce noise, dust and odor and help Metro achieve its goal of more green space, especially in a neighborhood identified among areas of the city with the most need.
Some residents, however, are skeptical the plan will produce the results the company touts. They fear it would extend the quarry's life beyond the 25 years the company claims is left and also hurt property values.
Metro Councilman Frank Harrison is against Rogers' plans, which include building a tunnel below Knight Road to access the limestone on the other side. "Blasting will continue for another 100 years, and they would much rather have houses than have blasting on a rock quarry," he said.
However, Rogers executives cite results of its survey of residents showing more than 250 households in favor of the company's plans to buy the acreage from Habitat for Humanity.
"It would look a whole lot better," said Sarah Majors, a supporter who lives in the Haynes Manor area across from the quarry and asphalt plant. "I can hear when they're blasting. They would make it a better site to look at; it would be less noisy and under the ground. It would be more natural, have trees, and the landscape would be better."
Relocating the asphalt plant would take about two years. Moving mining from the open-pit quarry to the new operation would take five to 10 years.
'Out of the ordinary'
A rock quarry has operated from the site off Whites Creek Pike for 60 years, with Rogers operating it for the past nine. The site, one of Rogers' six Nashville-area quarries, supplies the stones used for construction projects and produces asphalt for road projects, such as the widening of Interstate 65. Last year, 500,000 tons of stone was extracted from the quarry.
The zoning change Rogers is seeking would require approval from Metro Planning Commission and Metro Council, while the council also would have to approve an amendment to the area's community plan to make the policy fit with the zoning. Later, Metro Parks' board would have to approve any acquisition or acceptance of property for a park or green space.
"This is something totally out of the ordinary that's come our way," said Tommy Lynch, director of the city's parks department. "We would have an environmental assessment to see what's involved, or what type of risks are involved in occupied space above a mine."
Rogers said its own assessment showed no risks. Rose cites examples in other cities such as Louisville, Ky., where a zoo sits atop an old Rogers underground mine, and the company's active underground mine under the Gene Snyder Freeway in the Louisville area.
"The only structure that will reside on top of the underground mining operation will be Rogers' own multimillion-dollar asphalt plant," he said, referring to the planned roughly $5 million plant. "We'll not be mining under anybody's home or under any other structure."
The underground mining would occur 100 feet below ground the length of a football field from the closest home, Rose said. But David Padgett, an associate professor of geography at Tennessee State University, doesn't consider that distance to be far enough. "Anytime you start to tinker around underground, it opens up potential void spaces which can increase underground erosion, and this is erosion that can potentially result in sinkhole collapses," Padgett said.
Long-term impact
The last major fight over land use in the area pitted Habitat against neighbors, especially in Haynes Manor, who were against plans for a residential community on up to 225 acres. About 70 homes have been built out of the 450 for which the nonprofit group was approved. The goal has been cut to 185 homes, pending completion of the transaction with Rogers and approval of the rezoning that company is seeking away from residential use, said Danny Herron, CEO of Habitat for Humanity of Greater Nashville.
"This gives us an opportunity to do what we think the community wanted," Herron said, adding that the nonprofit group still plans 15 to 20 homes each year over the next decade at the Park Preserve subdivision near Whites Creek, which remains its largest in Middle Tennessee.
Joyce George, secretary and acting president of Haynes Manor Neighborhood Association, said that, despite Rogers' assurances, she's concerned about potential long-term environmental impact of extending the life of the quarry.
Sarah Bellos, a small-business owner whose home is a mile down Knight Road, said that street has more pressing needs, such as new sidewalks. "The big question for whether they should be allowed to expand the quarry or not is do we really need to mine resources that are underground in our city when we should be respecting resources that we have above ground, like neighboring communities?" she said. "Rather than perpetuating a very extreme industrial use for this urban area, we would rather see Nashville come together to make ... a public park and work with a developer that wants to bring something positive into the community."
Rose said Rogers is playing a critical role in Nashville's growth by providing a key raw material for roads, schools, hospitals and other buildings. "Transportation is the biggest piece, and the objective is for the raw material to be close to the final project," he said.
Stockard, the Trinity Hills resident whose parents built the house where he lives 51 years ago, estimates spending $5,000 to replace the living room ceiling that collapsed from effects of blasting and install a fireplace to replace the radiant heating system 15 years ago.
As a teenager, Stockard recalls his now-deceased father complaining that the quarry, then owned by another company, was a nuisance. Over the years, the semi-retiree said, he also has dealt with drywall coming apart and now at age 66 is still experiencing little tremors.
One of Stockard's concerns is an overlapping of blasting as Rogers develops the new underground site while continuing to extract from the current quarry. "I know how corporate America promises you things and no sooner than you come out of the meeting that you had, they go right back to operating in the same manner," he said.
Reach Getahn Ward at 615-726-5968 and on Twitter @Getahn.
If you go
Meeting of Concerned Citizens of District 2 neighborhoods
6:30 p.m., March 27
Mt. Hopewell Baptist Church
2911 Stokers Lane, Nashville 37218
Go to Tennessean.com for video of the quarry and one of its neighbors.
]]></text></news-item>