<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D671-B98D-21D4-3758"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Cebu, Leyte among top 10 landslide-prone provinces in Phl By Leonardo V. Micua</title><source>Philippines News Agency</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[SAN FERNANDO CITY, March 15 -- The provinces of Cebu and Leyte, two of the Philippine provinces worst hit by typhoon Yolanda last year, were tagged as among the top ten landslide-prone provinces in the country.
Alan Taulle of the Science and Technology Information Institute of the Department of Science and Technology identified the other top eight provinces as La Union, Rizal, Benguet, Nueva Viscaya, Mt. Province, Romblon, Marinduque, and Batangas.
'These provinces probably have problems on illegal logging or degrading forest protection,' Taulle said.
Taulle spoke during a two-day Disaster Risk Reduction Management seminar for mediamen sponsored by the Office of Civil Defense Region 1 held at the Sea and Sky Hotel here.
He said the landslide-prone provinces were identified through the geographical hazard mapping conducted by the Mines and Geo-sciences Bureau (MGB) of the Department of Environment and Natural Resources (DENR).
Aside from naming the top 10 landslide-prone provinces, Taulle also identified the top 10 provinces that are most susceptible to flooding.
They are: Pampanga, Nueva Ecija, Pangasinan, Tarlac, Maguindanao, Bulacan, Metro Manila, North Cotabato, Oriental Mindoro and Ilocos Norte.
It was learned that rainwater in some of these provinces are being impounded due to lack of large waterways while others are on the same level with the sea.
Meanwhile, Charmaine Villamil, a geologist of the Philippine Institute of Volcanology and Seismology (Philvolcs), said the country is prone to earthquakes and tsunamis because the Philippines is located in the Pacific 'ring of fire.'
Villamil revealed all Philippine coastlines are prone to tsunami.
She said the country is experiencing an average of 20 earthquakes daily because of the fault lines, the Manila trench and the Philippine fault which stretches from northern Luzon to Mindanao.
To address and mitigate disaster risk such as landslide, earthquake and flood, President Aquino has instructed concerned agencies to conduct the Nationwide Operational Assessment of Hazards or project NOAH.
The government also implemented the Philippine Disaster Risk Reduction Management Act of 2010 or Republic Act No. 10121 to strengthen disaster risk reduction and management.
Melchito Castro, OCD regional director, said disaster imagination is important to visualize what would happen in the future and to think of mitigating measures.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Philippines News Agency. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>