<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D703-E76D-F9F6-5397"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>No progress in ACC graft probe against Biman CBA leaders</title><source>The Financial Express (Bangladesh)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Bangladesh, March 15 -- The Anti-Corruption Commission's (ACC's) initiative to probe into the alleged irregularities by a section of the CBA (Collective Bargaining Agent) leaders of Biman Bangladesh Airlines remains virtually halted.
Terming the ACC's latest move 'illegal', the CBA leaders now intend to go to court to prove themselves innocent.
The anti-graft body launched the investigation against the accused CBA leaders after Biman Managing Director Kevin Steele wrote a letter to ACC Chairman M Badiuzzaman in early January this year in this connection.
The ACC also formed a committee to expedite the inquiry.
As part of investigation, the ACC summoned the CBA leaders to face interrogation from January 23 to 26 last, but they did not appear before the Commission.
The CBA leaders now say that they will not help the anti-graft body's investigation; rather will go to court if needed. President of Biman CBA Masiqur Rahman told the FE that the allegations against them were ridiculous as they had no big role in the affairs of the national flag carrier.
"We also want a fair investigation into any possible corruption in Biman. But, we will not accept any biased move," he said.
Mr Rahman said they did not appear before the ACC for two reasons. Firstly, they think the investigation against them is unfair, and secondly, they got the notice just one day before the interrogation deadline.
"Biman has about 5,000 officials. Why would only 17 of them face corruption allegation? Is it because they are new leaders of the CBA?" he said adding that former leaders should also be brought under the ACC investigation.
Moreover, he said the ACC did not ask them directly to face interrogation; instead it wrote to the Biman MD telling him to send them to the Commission.
An ACC official, preferring not to be named, told the FE that they were now trying to take another move to complete the investigation since the CBA leaders did not appear before the ACC according to Commission's summons.
"We will discuss further proceedings of the case with the top officials," he said.
The ACC chairman told the FE that he would try to know the latest situation with the investigation.
"I did not follow the issue, but will try to know its latest situation," he said.
In the letter which was written to the ACC chairman, Mr Kevin had expressed his concern over unabated corruption by a section of officials of the airlines.
"I am, therefore, very concerned at the level of corruption within the Biman. I have tried to reduce corruption by taking some measures like changing procedures, increasing audits and other checks, and introducing computer systems at different levels," he said.
The Biman MD said these initiatives have had a positive effect in some areas, but some inherent graft cases still remain.
Published by HT Syndication with permission from The Financial Express. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>