<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D74F-3BBF-D950-78D5"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Airline sues Siptu for  multiple millions ; Trade union says it will  vigorously resist  proceedings issued by Aer Lingus</title><source>The Irish Times</source><author>Martin Wall</author><text><![CDATA[
Aer Lingus has served legal proceedings on the trade union Siptu seeking damages of "multiple millions" arising from the planned strike action which was scheduled to take place yesterday.
Last night, Minister for Transport Leo Varadkar described the action by Aer Lingus as unhelpful.
"All parties should be focusing on the core problems so that the public won't be inconvenienced by future strikes, and so that members of the pension scheme can get clarity regarding their future entitlements," he said in a statement.
Earlier this week the High Court granted injunctions to the Dublin Airport Authority which prevented the planned four-hour strike taking place.
However Aer Lingus claimed it had already incurred significant losses to revenue as well as additional costs as a result of the planned dispute.
The airline had hired additional aircraft to deal with a projected backlog of passengers if the dispute had gone ahead.
It said its advance booking had been affected by the threat while it also had to alter schedules, rebook passengers and cancel flights.
Aer Lingus has confirmed that it has served proceedings on Siptu seeking compensation for damage to its business and for forcing it to break contracts with customers as a result of the planned dispute.
'Multiple millions'Highly placed sources in the airline say the amounts involved would be "multiple millions".
A Ryanair spokesman says it is considering its options in relation to any similar action.
Siptu says it will fully oppose the Aer Lingus action. "We will be consulting with our legal advisers over the next number of days and we will be vigorously resisting this action in the courts." The planned strike was over the pension scheme which covers staff both in Aer Lingus and the DAA.
In its claim, Aer Lingus is seeking a declaration that the secret ballot held by Siptu was unlawful and not in compliance with industrial relations legislation. It is also seeking a declaration that the notification of the planned industrial action was "wrongful and unlawful".
The airline is seeking damages for breach of contract, unlawful interference with its business and for inducing a breach of contract with its customers.
Aer Lingus also wrote to Siptu pension policy adviser Dermot O'Loughlin and said it was holding him and the union responsible and liable for the losses and damages sustained.
In the letter, Aer Lingus director of change and engagement Seán Murphy said the airline reserved its right to take any additional necessary action, including court action, to prevent any further loss and damage to the company.
"The changes made to our flight schedule, to circumvent the planned strike, could not be undone at such short notice . . ."
It added: "This is yet another occasion where the trade union has cynically caused damage, threatening a strike, only to withdraw their strike notice at the last minute.
]]></text></news-item>