<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D83F-3EC4-169F-AB52"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Zimbabwean leader threatens to close some diamond firms</title><source>Xinhua General News Service</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Zimbabwean President Robert Mugabe reiterated Friday that his government will restructure the diamond sector to leave only one state-controlled company in operation in the country's diamond-rich area.
Speaking at a ceremony to celebrate his 90th birthday organized by civil servants, Mugabe said the restructuring will ensure government plays a greater role in mining of the diamonds.
"We are reorganizing our diamond sector in a way to consolidate the systems there. We are going to say good-bye to some of the mines there so that we consolidate and just have one mining group in which the state will be the main company," Mugabe said.
Zimbabwe's diamond mining concentrates in the eastern region of Marange, near the border with Mozambique. There are seven companies licensed to mine diamond in Marange fields, accounting for more than 80 percent of the country's diamond output, which is estimated to have reached 11 million carats in 2013.
While income from diamond export has been instrumental to the country's economic boom since 2010, there have been allegations of lack of transparency in the diamond mining industry with the Treasury saying that it had received little diamond revenue.
Mugabe, who turned 90 last month, has hinted on government's plans to streamline operations in Marange. He said Zimbabwe would need to mould its diamond sector along the same lines as that of Botswana and South Africa which have very few diamond companies.
The veteran president also condemned growing corruption in the public sector and warned that his government would soon launch investigations to flush out corruption in the diamond sector.
"We will be investigating operations in Marange to find out how things have been going on there and if any corrupt activities are detected, people will answer for it. I can tell you," the president vowed.
Mines Minister Walter Chidhakwa has warned tough measures against mining firms in Marange who he accuses of prejudicing government of a lot of revenue through cartels which under-valued diamonds. Operations will be halted until it was certain that the government would get fair returns, Chidhakwa said.
Some of the diamond firms have said they are facing serious financial problems due to declining diamond deposits, and have since asked government for more mining concessions.
]]></text></news-item>