<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D84B-B2CF-E72E-8AC3"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>RICHARD LITTLEJOHN: A dangerous job - but someone's got to do it...</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>RICHARD LITTLEJOHN</author><text><![CDATA[Five years ago, I had the honour of being invited to deliver an after-dinner speech at the annual jolly-up of the Metropolitan Police's Retired CID Officers' Association.
My late father served in the Met and I've always enjoyed the company of proper coppers, so it was a pleasure to accept. In the bar afterwards, I got talking to one ex-detective who had infiltrated the notorious Richardson gang, the South London version of the Kray Twins.
He'd been sent to flight training school in Florida, with the intention of becoming the pilot of Charlie Richardson's private plane.
After qualifying, he got the job and was the source of vital intelligence about the gang's activities.
Coincidentally, in the mid-Eighties, I was approached out of the blue to write Charlie Richardson's autobiography. I decided against it. But the brief time I spent with him gave me some insight into his character.
Like so many criminal masterminds, he was personally charming, highly intelligent and suspicious of everyone. So my admiration for the skill with which this policeman managed not only to conceal his identity but to gain Charlie's confidence was immense.
Especially as the Richardsons had a reputation for extreme violence towards anyone who crossed them. Charlie was said to be the brains of the outfit, his younger brother Eddie the enforcer. Mad Frankie Fraser helped them out when they were busy.
Their speciality was alleged to be nailing people to the floor and fastening electrodes to their genitals.
Imagine the bravery of a police officer who is prepared to put himself in that position, knowing that at any moment his cover might be blown and he could end up wearing a coffee table on his head, with his unmentionables plugged directly into the mains. He's a better man than I am, Gunga Din.
This story came back to me when I read that the Home Secretary Theresa May is setting up a 'judge-led' inquiry into claims that Scotland Yard had an undercover officer spying on the family of Stephen Lawrence.
While no one can ever defend covert surveillance directed against the bereaved, innocent relatives of a murdered teenager, some context is essential. My information is that the Yard was merely keeping an eye on some of the more dubious elements who always latch on to such campaigns for their own political ends.
That's absolutely no excuse whatsoever for intruding on the private grief of Neville and Doreen Lawrence. As former Commander Roy Ramm, who founded the Yard's undercover surveillance units, said this week: if the Lawrence allegation is true it is reprehensible.
But it isn't representative of the fine work of some of the Met's bravest and boldest. Theresa May's opportunist intervention is grandstanding, pure and simple.
If you want to know where 'judge-led' inquiries have got us in the past, laydees and gentlemen of the jury, let me direct you to the Leveson fiasco, the Bloody Sunday lawyers' bonanza and the Iraq War tribunal set up to find Tony Blair not guilty.
All such an inquiry will do is top up Michael Mansfield QC's pension fund and further undermine legitimate policing.
It is the job of the Old Bill to Hoover up intelligence from all manner of sources. At the time they are said to have been 'spying' on the Lawrence family, they also bought a house next door to one of the murderers to compile evidence against him.
As the old cliche goes: it's dirty and dangerous work, but someone's got to do it.
This column is no fan of Met Commissioner Bernard Hyphen-Howe, but he has my full support in attempting to block the publication of the identities of undercover officers.
If their names and faces are made public, it will compromise dozens - maybe hundreds - of operations. Right now, courageous men and women are burrowed away inside criminal gangs and terrorist cells.
They do it not for the excitement, and certainly not for the money, but to keep the rest of us safe.
You have to be a special kind of individual to work undercover, cut off from family and friends with only a 'handler' as your contact to the real world. It's hardly surprising so many of these officers go native in the process.
They become embroiled in a sort of reverse Stockholm Syndrome - that's the process by which hostages identify with their captors.
No wonder. They are living on the edge, a whisker from exposure which could cause them, in the most extreme circumstances, to be killed.
There are currently a number of cases in which an assortment of unwashed dopey birds who slept with undercover officers are seeking compensation, even though no force or coercion was involved.
Oh, do grow up. Women often fall for dubious men who pretend to be millionaires, or airline pilots or friends of the Royal Family.
That doesn't mean they were assaulted, just duped.
What are these officers supposed to do when an obliging madwoman in an anarchist group takes a fancy to them - make the old News of the World excuse and leave?
In the paranoid world of criminality, political subversion and terrorism, every action is scrutinised microscopically. One false move and the consequences can be fatal.
Yes, of course, we should be vigilant and ensure police officers operate within the bounds of what is lawful and decent.
But we should never forget the risks and sacrifices young men and women - and they are generally young and relatively poorly paid - are making on our behalf.
They shouldn't be sacrificed on the altar of political ambition - whether that ambition belongs to a bunch of posturing Trots who hate the police or a third-rate Tory chancer like Theresa May.
Somehow, I can't see any of the undercover officers' most  vociferous critics being prepared to retrain as a pilot to infiltrate one of London's most vicious  torture gangs, in the certain knowledge that one slip could cost them their lives.
And my best guess is that every single member of the Retired CID Officers' Association agrees with me.
Super-hot curries have always been an excuse for macho madness. Young men compete to prove who can eat the most toxic tandoori.
I can remember sitting  in an Indian restaurant in West London with a crazy Geordie friend of mine, who asked the waiter: 'Haven't you got anything hotter than a Chicken Cyclone?'
The chef duly obliged. When the meal was served, my mate took one bite and immediately reached for his pint of lager, which he downed in one - followed by my pint of lager, the finger bowl and the water out of the vase of flowers on the table.
By the end of the meal he was doing a passable impersonation of Chernobyl.
I thought that this extreme food craze had disappeared until I read about the five people taken to hospital after eating what is billed as 'Britain's spiciest burger'.
Apparently, diners at the restaurant in Hove, Sussex, have to sign a waiver to prevent them suing for compensation.
One man suffered an anaphylactic shock and another ended up with a perforated bowel.
Call me old-fashioned, but why would anyone want to eat a meal which gives you a perforated bowel?Would you like fries with that, sir?
Today's edition of You Couldn't Make It Up comes from Norfolk, where a fire station has burned down.
[IMG 8846875 noborder /]
Crews from across the county were called to Downham Market, when flames were reported coming from the garage where the fire engine is housed.
But they were too late and the station was destroyed. Investigators discovered that the building, which was opened in 2006, did not have either sprinklers or a fire alarm.
Deputy chief fire officer Roy Harold, aka Captain Flack, said: 'I think there is a safety message here for us. This building is fairly new, but it wasn't sprinklered.'
Don't you just love that word - 'sprinklered'?
Rebuilding the station and buying a new fire engine will cost taxpayers around £1.75 million. Captain Flack immediately held a roll-call to establish that no one was hurt.
Pugh.
Here!
Pugh.
Here!
Barney McGrew.
Here!
Cuthbert? Cuthbert?
Anyone seen Cuthbert...?
We'll fight them on the beeches
The British Army used wooden soldiers during World War I to fool the Germans.
Maybe that's where the police got the idea for those cardboard coppers they stick up in shopping centres to deter muggers.
Mind you, given the size of Britain's dwindling defence budget, it's probably only a matter of time before the MoD deploys paper aeroplanes on our new fleet of Mary Celeste Class aircraft carriers.
A burglar died while fleeing an attempted break-in at an 89-year-old widow's home in Essex. He broke his neck and suffered a heart attack after getting trapped under a fence. Good.
]]></text></news-item>