<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="D871-BE5F-5875-B2C6"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>WorkSafeBC required to have investigative expertise</title><source>Prince George Citizen (British Columbia)</source><author>Gordon Hoekstra, Vancouver Sun</author><text><![CDATA[A 2007 agreement with B.C.'s solicitor general to give Work-SafeBC investigators special powers requires them to know how to conduct interviews and seize evidence so it can stand up in court.
Those requirements are among key issues cited by the Criminal Justice branch in rejecting charges in January in the deadly Babine Forest Products sawmill explosion two years ago.
The special constable agreement - obtained by The Vancouver Sun through a freedom of information request - raises more questions about why WorkSafeBC investigators did not use search warrants during its investigation and warn interviewees of their Charter rights to remain silent.
That issue has already been raised in an internal B.C. Liberal government review, after which B.C. Premier Christy Clark said she was "deeply disappointed" with how WorkSafeBC conducted the Babine investigation.
The Burns Lake families of the killed workers Robert Luggi Jr., 45, and Carl Charlie, 42, have also raised questions about the investigation and rejection of charges. The special constable powers apply only to fraud investigations under the Criminal Code, not fatality investigations, WorkSafeBC said.
But the agreement signed by WorkSafeBC on Aug. 22, 2007 appears to say otherwise, referring to fraud investigations but also to compliance and fatality investigations.
WorkSafeBC did not make an official available for an interview, saying it was not appropriate to give an interview while it was responding to the recommendations in the internal review led by Clark's deputy minister John Dyble.
Without the agreement with the solicitor general, WorkSafeBC fraud investigators could only investigate under the Workers' Compensation Act and not Criminal Code issues, WorkSafeBC spokeswoman Trish Knight-Chernecki said in an email.
"Board officers who investigate fatalities and serious injuries do not have special constable status," she said.
WorkSafeBC did not respond to a question on why special constable status wasn't conferred on Work-SafeBC officers conducting fatality investigations, given the significance of those investigations. The MOU allows the appointment of special constables to conduct formal investigations on fraud, but also misrepresentation, compliance and fatal and serious workplace incidents under both the Criminal Code of Canada and the Workers' Compensation Act.
It covers elements such as search and seizure, but does not allow WorkSafeBC investigators to arrest or detain people.
The agreement outlines that WorkSafeBC investigators who have special constable status must have knowledge of the procedures for obtaining and issuing subpoenas, of search provisions under the Criminal Code, court processes including rules of evidence, the procedures and authorities needed to seize evidence for administrative and/or criminal processes and the Charter of Rights and Freedoms.
The investigators must have interview skills and knowledge of appropriate warnings and when to give them.
More details are provided in a 59-page field investigation and procedure manual that is part of the memorandum.
In rejecting charges on Jan. 10 in the Babine case, the Crown said some evidence would likely not be admissible in court because Work-SafeBC investigators had not used search warrants or warned those they interviewed of their Charter rights to remain silent. The Crown also noted the mill owners would likely have had a good argument of due diligence.
WorkSafeBC responded that it had conducted its investigation in a similar fashion for two decades, a system that had netted both charges and convictions in court.
But the Dyble review concluded WorkSafeBC paid "insufficient attention" to important legal precedents regarding the legitimate gathering of evidence for prosecutions, even though the Criminal Justice Branch had previously shared its concerns on the issue. A
key ruling on regulatory investigations was handed down by the Supreme Court of Canada in 2002.
United Steelworkers (USW) union western director Steve Hunt said Wednesday it's clear Work-SafeBC is not properly considering the possibility of court charges when it investigates fatalities.
The USW has already called for better training of WorkSafeBC officers, police and the Crown in handling workplace fatality investigations.
Hunt, who just returned from a memorial for the 22nd anniversary of the Westray mine disaster in Nova Scotia, said it's also clear that if investigations aren't done right, there won't be court charges. And if regulators don't do their jobs, workers die, he added.
"The regulators, government and Crown seem to be oblivious to that fact," said Hunt.
Instead, he said, mistakes from the past are being repeated, and frustrated workers and families are left to form support groups, as is happening in the aftermath of the Babine explosion, and a similar deadly explosion three months later at Lakeland Mills in Prince George.
Further evidence that there was awareness of the need to ensure evidence would stand up in court is provided in another agreement between WorkSafeBC and municipal police forces signed in 2006, also obtained through a freedom of information request by The Sun.
It notes that if a police department does not consider there to be sufficient evidence to initiate a criminal investigation, Work-SafeBC will continue its investigation and may gather further evidence, keeping in mind Criminal Code and Charter issues to ensure evidence is admissible.
Bond defends WorkSafeBC
Jobs Minister Shirley Bond defended Work-SafeBC's record in question period Thursday as the opposition NDP accused the agency of dysfunction after a bungled investigation into a fatal mill explosion in Burns Lake. In Janurary 2012, an explosion at Babine Forest Products killed two workers and injured 20 others.
Two years later, provincial Crown determined that it could not proceed with criminal charges in the case because some evidence collected by WorkSafe may not hold up in court.
Premier Christy Clark then asked her top civil servant John Dyble to investigate and he released a report in February that was critical of WorkSafe's handling of the file.
"WorkSafeBC is failing its mandate under the watch of [the current] government," NDP MLA Harry Bains said during question period
Thursday. "It means in this particular case, no one will be held criminally accountable. WorkSafeBC is obviously failing, and the people of British Columbia deserve to know why."
Bond replied that the government intends to fix any problems at the agency, but said the NDP are failing to recognize the good work done at WorkSafe.
"What is really additionally unfortunate in this chamber is that the member opposite writes offall of the good work that hundreds of people who work for WorkSafe, hardworking individuals who do their best every single day," Bond said. "He writes them off." The NDP also continued their call for a public inquest into what happened at the mill that led to the explosion. MLA Norm Macdonald said the upcoming cororner's inquest won't go far enough because it won't be able to assign blame for what happened. "When are those families going to get the justice they deserve? When are workers going to be protected in the way that they deserve?" he asked. "When is there going to be a full public inquest into what took place at Babine?" Bond said that the province has received legal advice that a public inquiry would do nothing to change the Crown's decision about the admissibility of evidence and that a coroner's inquest is the best venue to address any unanswered questions about the blast. "I have been the first to say that words are not enough for families - action is required," Bond said. "That's why we expect WorkSafe to make changes and for them to co-operate with Crown to ensure that this does not happen again."
- JAMES, Citizen staff
]]></text></news-item>