<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DA34-11ED-26E9-0A5F"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>I remember the day my dad died in the Great War</title><source>Daily Post (North Wales)</source><author>DAVID POWELL</author><text><![CDATA[THE son of a soldier who died in World War I says the centenary of the outbreak of the conflict has rekindled memories of his late father.
David Hughes, of Llanrwst, who is now 100 years old, was speaking about his parent - also called David Hughes - who was a sniper but was killed in Flanders in 1917, aged 36.
As 100th anniversary of the start Great War approaches, the Daily Post a range of stories columns from August, when produce Private David Hughes had served in the Territorials then joined the 9th Welsh Regiment before being posted to northern France. He and late wife Elizabeth had six children but David is their only surviving son.
David said: "My father's family was from Dolgellau.
"He lived in South Wales for a time and then moved to Llanberis."
His life was touched by tragedy even before the start of hostilities on the Western front.
In the Senghenydd mining disaster in Caerphilly, 439 people died in a gas explosion at the Universal Colliery, Glamorganshire on October 14, 1913.
the of the Mr Hughes was in a rescue party after what was Britain's worst mining accident which left 205 widows, 542 children and 62 dependent parents.
will publish and now until we'll His son Mr Hughes "junior" grew up to become an inspector at Dolgarrog Aluminium Ltd in the Conwy Valley.
He became a school caretaker at Llanrwst Secondary School then rejoined the metalworks.
He had two sons of his own Gwyn and John. John, who lives in Cambridgeshire, said: "My grandfather is buried in Tyne Cot Commonwealth War Graves Cemetery near Ypres. I was there with my family last year."
." ? ORGANISERS of the Welsh Memorial in Flanders Appeal are appealing for donations.
Send a cheque made out to "The Welsh Memorial in Flanders Campaign" to Phil Edwards, 6 Whitehall Road, Rhos on Sea, LL28 4HW. Or donate at a Lloyds TSB Bank (sort code 30-93-53, account no 37974560).
who was Flanders explosion 1913. As the 100th anniversary of the start of the Great War approaches, the Daily Post will publish a range of stories and columns from now until August, when we'll produce a special commemorative supplement
]]></text></news-item>