<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DB36-D9B1-3785-752D"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>WHAT THE PAPERS SAY</title><source>Press Association Mediapoint</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[EXPRESS:
PIRATES STOLE MISSING PLANE
Fears were growing last night that the Malaysian jet which vanished from the skies has been hijacked by pirates.
LABOUR ICON BENN DIES AT 88
Tributes poured in from across the political spectrum yesterday for veteran leftwinger Tony Benn, who has died aged 88.
SPRING WILL BE A SUNNY DELIGHT
Britain will enjoy an amazing three months of warm weather with balmy conditions set to last until June, according to forecasters.
Sport:
WE'LL KILL OFF UNITED
Brendan Rodgers will look to extinguish Manchester United's lingering top-four hopes tomorrow - and cast them into the European wilderness.
HURT LOCKERS COSTS STOKES T20 SPOT
Ben Stokes has been ruled out of the World T20 after breaking his hand punching a locker.
INDEPENDENT:
DEATH OF A MAVERICK
Tony Benn, the veteran Labour politician and campaigner for socialism, died yesterday at the age of 88.
A NEW CHAPTER IN CHAGOS ISLANDS SAGA: ILLEGAL SEWAGE DUMPING
The American military has poured hundreds of tonnes of human sewage and waste water into a protected coral lagoon on the British-owned base of Diego Garcia over three decades in breach of environmental rules, The Independent can reveal.
QUEEN OF THE TEA PARTY - ON HER BEST BEHAVIOUR
Margaret Thatcher may have ascended to that great free-market enterprise in the sky. But Michele Bachmann, the former US presidential candidate and ``queen of the Tea Party'', laid claim to be her political heir when she addressed students at the Oxford Union.
City:
BARCLAYS CUTS CONTRACT STAFF'S PAY BY 10% - AS BONUSES RISE BY 10%
Barclays has told thousands of contract staff that they must accept a 10 per cent cut in pay or have their roles terminated, The Independent can reveal.
BOOHOO CHEERS ON ITS DEBUT
Boohoo.com yesterday became the latest company to soar on its stock market debut.
TELEGRAPH:
GOVE ATTACKS OLD ETONIAN BIAS IN PM'S INNER CIRCLE
Michael Gove the Education Secretary, has criticised the ``ridiculous'' number of Old Etonians in David Cameron's inner circle.
FOR SALE: EU CITIZENSHIP
Non-Europeans can buy European Union citizenship entitling them to live and work in Britain for as little as £150,000 under a scheme operating in Bulgaria, an investigation by the Daily Telegraph discloses today.
OSBORNE WILL UNVEIL A NEW GARDEN CITY IN HIS BUDGET
George Osborne will announce plans to build the first garden city in Britain for 40 years in his Budget, the Daily Telegraph has learnt.
City:
FTSE 100 SUFFERS WORST WEEK FOR NINE MONTHS AS CRIMEA FEARS GROW
The FTSE 100 has suffered its worst week since last June, with £46.4bn wiped off the value of Britain's biggest companies, amid growing fears about the crisis in Ukraine and slowing growth in China.
CO-OP 'WILL GO BUST' IF IT FAILS TO BACK TOTAL REFORM
The Co-operative Group will run out of money unless it urgently reforms its board and voting structure, its senior independent director has said.
MIRROR:
'HIJACKERS FLEW JET TOWARDS REMOTE ISLAND'
Missing flight MH370 may have been hijacked and flown west towards islands in the Indian Ocean.
CHAMPION OF THE POWERLESS
Friends and political foes united yesterday to pay tribute to Tony Benn, hailing the Labour stalwart as a ``champion of the powerless'' after his death at the age of 88.
DATA DISASTER FOR MORRISONS
Struggling Morrisons has suffered another blow after the bank account details of nearly 100,000 staff were plundered.
Sport:
WE CAN SEND YOU INTO EURO EXILE
Brendan Rodgers has warned Manchester United they face a long exile from Europe if they lose tomorrow to his Liverpool side.
IT ONLY TOOK ME A MINUTE TO SAY YES TO CHELSEA AGAIN
Nemanja Matic was out in London when his little son, Filip, thought he'd spotted Benfica's ``big red bus'', which used to take his dad to work in Portugal.
STAR:
MISSING JET WAS HIJACKED
Hijackers have flown a missing Malaysian airliner to a remote island, it was feared last night.
LEE RIGBY VID COUPLE CAGED
Two British Muslims were jailed yesterday for glorifying the murder of Fusilier Lee Rigby in sick YouTube videos.
CBB JAS DITCHES '2% MAN' RYAN
Celebrity Big Brother babe Jasmine Waltz has dumped Lee Ryan, branding him ``2% man, 98% bullsh*t''.
Sport:
WE'LL KEEP YOU OUT OF EUROPE
Brendan Rodgers has warned Manchester United they could face years out of the Champions League if they miss out this season.
BENDTNER'S GUN FOR
Bad boy Nicklas Bendtner has played his last game for Arsenal.
TIMES:
TORIES OFFER SQUEEZED MIDDLE A TAX REPRIEVE
George Osborne is preparing to head off a growing rebellion over the tax burden on middle-earners with a promise to stop more professionals from being dragged into the 40p bracket under a future Conservative government.
GOVE TAKES AIM AT 'RIDICULOUS' OLD ETONIAN CIRCLE AT NO 10
Michael Gove last night took aim at David Cameron for surrounding himself with Old Etonians, describing it as ridiculous and preposterous.
GREEDY COUNCILS' PARKING SPY CAMERAS TO BE BANNED
Councils will be banned from using spy cameras to issue parking tickets as the ballooning sums that they rake in from fines is revealed.
City:
CO-OP WILL GO BROKE WITHOUT RADICAL REFORM, MYNERS SAYS
The Co-operative Group will run out of money unless it radically reforms its leadership, according to a damning report that accuses elected directors of ``breathtaking'' mismanagement.
ONS'S HEAD FOR FIGURES IS THROWN INTO DOUBT AGAIN
The national statistics agency faced further embarrassment yesterday after announcing the second delay to the release of market-sensitive data this week.
GUARDIAN:
CO-OP SHAMBLES EXPOSED
The shambolic state of the Co-operative Group was laid bare yesterday in a scathing verdict warning that the survival of Britain's biggest mutual organisation was at stake.
MOD'S POSTER BOY: OUR AWFUL MISTAKES IN AFGHANISTAN
A former army commander has given a devastating insider's account of some of the mistakes that beset the military campaign in Afghanistan, saying the training and equipment provided to troops ``wasn't good enough'' for the mission they faced.
LATEST THEORY: JET FLEW ON FOR FIVE HOURS WITH COMMUNICATIONS SWITCHED OFF
Almost a week after Malaysia Airlines flight MH370 vanished, there was another extraordinary development in the story yesterday after it emerged the aircraft could have flown on for a further five hours with its communications systems deliberately switched off.
City:
CITY OPERATED LIKE GIANT HEDGE FUND BEFORE CRASH, SAYS BANK OFFICIAL
The City operated like a giant hedge fund in the run-up to the financial crisis, and the resulting crash could leave the British economy with permanent low productivity and stagnant earnings, according to a senior Bank of England official.
UKRAINE AND CHINA WORRIES HELP TO DRIVE FTSE 100 DOWN
The FTSE 100 suffered its largest weekly fall since June last year, as investors reacted to a cocktail of concerns, from tensions in Ukraine to worries about a Chinese slowdown and the prospect of the US Federal Reserve cutting its economic stimulus again next week.
i:
OSBORNE'S BUDGET SNUB TO MIDDLE CLASSES
George Osborne will reject growing demands by Conservative MPs for significant tax cuts for the middle classes in his Budget this Wednesday.
ENGINE SIGNALS REVEAL MISSING AIRLINER MAY HAVE FLOWN ON FOR HOURS
Investigators were last night pursuing the theory that the missing Malaysia Airlines Flight MH370 may have been deliberately diverted off course towards a remote chain of islands in the Indian Ocean.
'IN THOSE DAYS, FOR POLITICIANS, POLITICS WAS ALL THAT MATTERED'
On a day of tributes to one of the most admired - and divisive - politicians of the post-war era, one in particular stood out.
City:
BARCLAYS TELLS THOUSANDS OF STAFF TO ACCEPT 10% PAY CUT
Barclays has told thousands of contract staff that they must accept a 10% cut in pay or have their roles terminated, 'i' can reveal.
MYNERS HITS OUT AT CO-OP BOARD'S 'LACK OF RESPECT'
Lord Myners yesterday attacked the way the Co-operative Group's board works and in particular its non-executive directors, ``few of whom have any serious business experience''.
MAIL:
SCIENTISTS' HIDDEN LINKS TO THE GM FOOD GIANTS
The authors of a study calling for GM crops to be fast-tracked into Britain's farms and kitchens all have links to the industry, it can be revealed.
40P TAX RATE 'ROBS PETER TO PAY PAUL'
A former Tory cabinet minister who advised George Osborne to introduce a dramatic increase in the basic rate of tax has condemned him for ``robbing Peter to pay Paul'' by dragging hundreds of thousands more families into the 40p rate.
WILLS AND KATE'S £6,500-A-NIGHT HIDEAWAY WHERE THEY'LL STAY MINUS GEORGE... AT CUT-PRICE, OF COURSE
With breathtaking views across crystal clear waters, this is the £6,500-a-night bolthole laid on for the Duke and Duchess of Cambridge on their forthcoming New Zealand tour.
Sport:
FRANCE CAN WIN US TITLE
England go into their RBS 6 Nations finale against Italy in Rome today believing there is ``a good chance'' old enemy France can hand them the title.
THE LORD OF CHELTENHAM
Outsider Lord Windermere won the Cheltenham Gold Cup on one of the most dramatic days in Festival history.
FINANCIAL TIMES:
GOVE SCORNS PMS' OLD ETONIAN ELITE
Michael Gove, education secretary, has described as ``ridiculous'' and ``preposterous'' the concentration of Old Etonians in David Cameron's inner circle, saying such a bastion of privilege did not exist in any other rich country.
RUSSIAN COMPANIES PULL BILLIONS FROM WEST OVER THREAT OF UKRAINE SANCTIONS
Russian companies are pulling billions of dollars out of western banks, fearful that any US sanctions over the Crimean crisis could lead to a painful asset freeze, according to bankers in Moscow.
FRIENDS AND FOES OFFER TRIBUTES
Tributes have poured in from friends and former political enemies following the death at the age of 88 of Tony Benn, simultaneously one of the most revered and divisive figures in the history of the Labour party.
Companies and Markets:
US AND EUROPE STOCKS RIDE SURGE IN LISTINGS
A surge of flotations in London and New York has helped to give European and US equity markets their strongest start to any year since 2007, before the financial crisis set in.
MYNERS REVIEW OF CO-OP GROUP CALLS FOR 'FAILED' BOARD REFORMS
The Co-operative Group, which was dubbed ``ungovernable'' by its departing chief executive, has been run by a ``failed'' and underqualified board that took ``breathtakingly value-destructive'' decisions, according to independent director Lord Myners.
SUN:
LOUIS IN BGT 'FIX'
Louis Walsh was in a Britain's Got Talent ``fix'' row last night after his new boyband Hometown sailed through auditions.
ANELKA WALKOUT AT WBA
Footie's Nicolas Anelka stuck two fingers up to West Brom last night - by quitting via Twitter.
FEARLESS, NO DULL MOMENTS
Labour was yesterday plunged into mourning for one of its titans - after Tony Benn died aged 88.
Sport:
TOP FOUR OR YOU'RE DOOMED
Brendan Rodgers has warned Manchester United: Miss out on the top four and you're doomed.
GONER
Nicolas Anelka quit West Brom last night - on Twitter.
]]></text></news-item>