<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DBEB-5EDB-6126-FD49"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Opening Bell 14 March | Crompton Greaves, Financial Technologies group in focus</title><source>MINT</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Mumbai, March 14 -- Asian markets are trading lower. Shares fell as tensions in Ukraine ahead of a weekend referendum prompted investors to decrease their exposure to riskier assets. Read the Reuters report. The tensions in Ukraine overshadowed US data indicating an improving American economy.
Retail sales rose in February while jobless claims unexpectedly fell last week. The data, however, reinforced the perception that the US central bank will stick to its stimulus withdrawal. This led to a 1.17% fall in S&P 500 index to 1,846. The Securities and Exchange Board of India (Sebi) is likely to send another letter to Maruti Suzuki India Ltd, seeking further clarification of its contentious contract manufacturing deal with its Japanese parent, reports Mint. The capital market regulator is likely to raise fresh concerns expressed by institutional investors. Maruti Suzuki is planning to launch a mini truck next year, reports Business Standard. According to the report, the vehicle will be priced close to the Tata Ace. Tata Sons Ltd is underwriting nearly half of Tata Power Co. Ltd's Rs.2,000 crore rights issue starting, reports Mint. The other half of the issue is being underwritten by a clutch of merchant bankers like JM Financial Ltd, HSBC Securities and Capital Markets India Pvt. Ltd, BNP Paribas SA and Kotak Mahindra Capital Co. Ltd. Larsen and Toubro Ltd will sell 83 million shares in its non-banking finance company L&T Finance Holdings Ltd through a qualified institutional placement. The share sale will happen at Rs.70 per share, an 11.6% discount to Thursday closing price. Indian Oil Corp. Ltd is mulling setting up a Rs.30,000 crore refinery at Mundra in Gujarat as part of a plan to increase its processing capacity, reports PTI. The company has seven refineries with a total capacity of 54.2 million tonnes. DLF Ltd has come under Competition Commission of India's scanner again. The regulator has ordered a probe against the company for abusing its dominant position and imposing unfair conditions on buyers. Read more. Keep an eye on Crompton Greaves Ltd. The promoters are planning to sell their stake in the company, reports The Economic Times. According to the report, the promoters expect the company to be valued at $3 billion (Rs.18,000 crore) against the current market valuation of about Rs.9,500 crore. The troubles of Jignesh Shah and his Financial Technologies (India) Ltd (FTIL) intensified with the Central Board of Investigation registering preliminary enquiries against several of its entities, reports Mint. The enquiry has been registered in connection with the grant of a licence to MCX Stock Exchange (MCX-SX). Dr Reddy's Laboratories Ltd has voluntarily recalled 58,656 bottles of its Lansoprazole formulation from the American market due to microbial contamination, reports Business Standard. The drug, used for treatment of heartburn, is reportedly recalled in January. Textile company Raymond Ltd has initiated measures to grow faster and reduce its borrowings, reports Mint. The company plans to launch ready-to-wear line and sell stake in two group companies. Mphasis Ltd posted a fourth successive decline in quarterly net profit on lower orders from Hewlett Packard Co., its biggest customer. For the three months ended 31 January the company posted a net profit of Rs.180 crore, down from Rs.184 crore a year earlier. Read more. Lastly, AstraZeneca Pharma India Ltd's board will meet later this week to consider delisting the company, reports PTI. The promoter of AstraZeneca Pharma is proposing to make a voluntary delisting offer to the public shareholders. Published by HT Syndication with permission from MINT. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>