<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DC0C-5956-A2B1-7C78"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Duke may close Asheville plant</title><source>The Asheville Citizen-Times (North Carolina)</source><author>By, Clarke Morrison</author><text><![CDATA[Duke Energy says in a letter to state officials that it would consider shutting down its Asheville power plant as part of a plan for dealing with coal ash contamination.
The utility also said it might convert to producing dry ash at the Lake Julian plant rather than the wet material that has leached toxic chemicals from storage ponds into the groundwater.
But the letter Duke CEO Lynn Good sent Gov. Pat McCrory on Wednesday leaves in doubt what might eventually be done with coal ash already in two Asheville lagoons, which cover 91 acres at the plant near the French Broad River.
Good's letter doesn't say whether the company is considering removing all the old ash. State officials said Friday they might force Duke to remove all of it, regardless of what the utility wants.
The N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources said in the Friday announcement that it planned to modify permits to potentially require Duke eliminate move coal ash from basins at the utility's Riverbend and Asheville power plants.
North Carolina can make additional demands of Duke because a wastewater discharge permit for the Lake Julian plant is still under review, the agency said.
Environmental groups opposed to storing coal ash in unlined ponds applauded Good's commitment in the letter to move ash at a plant near Eden to a lined landfill away from the Dan River, where a Feb. 2 spill coated the river's banks and bottom with toxic sludge for 70 miles downstream.
But D.J. Gerken, an attorney with the Southern Environmental Law Center, said the letter doesn't go far enough.
"As far as I can read in this letter, the intent for the Asheville plant may be pretty positive," he said. "But there is so much ambiguity that we can't really tell.
"Most significantly, the letter commits to either using a dry storage method for ash at the Asheville plant, or better yet, retiring the coal-fired units at Asheville. But they don't commit to moving ash off the Asheville site."
After the Dan River spill, McCrory and the N.C. Department of Environment and Natural Resources gave Duke a March 15 deadline to provide detailed plans for how handle coal ash at its 32 ponds across the state.
But environment Secretary John Skvarla said the four-page letter Good sent in response to the deadline was inadequate.
"There are too many questions left unanswered, and Duke should provide the information we originally requested, including the estimated costs of cleanup, plans for the future and a detailed timeline," Skvarla said in a statement.
There are two options for the Asheville plant that Duke officials are proposing, said Jason Walls, district manager for the utility.
The first is to convert to producing dry ash, which would be completed 30-36 months after receiving permits to do the work, he said.
"Alternatively, we could retire the plant," Walls said.
Walls declined to say how likely that options is, but said Duke has spent more than $300 million in environmental upgrades at the plant over the last decade.
"We can't retire the plant without a practical and proven way to replace the electricity that residents and businesses depend on," he said. "Today, that doesn't exist. But (shuttering the plant) is an option that is being considered."
Walls said the Asheville plant employs about 100 people. At 324 megawatts, it's the primary supplier of electricity in Western North Carolina, he said.
Good's letter also proposes continuing to remove ash from the lagoons and using it as fill in a project to create flat, useable land at nearby Asheville Regional Airport, while also working to "look for ash reuse opportunities where such uses remain permissible" under future regulations.
"That would include exploring the possibility of extending the current project at the airport to other areas of the airport," Walls said. "Our commitment is to explore the possibility of moving the ash to beneficial fill projects."
Gerken said that doesn't go far enough. Duke should commit to removing all the ash from the Asheville lagoons, he said.
"I'm heartened they are not ruling that out, but we are too far down the road for vague promises at this point," he said. "All (the letter) tells us about the old ash at the Asheville plant is that they will continue to move it to the airport and consider expanding the scope of that project.
"We've been demanding that Duke comply with the law and remove the ash from all the ponds that are contaminating groundwater."
Kelly Martin, of the Sierra Club, said Duke should be commended for taking responsibility for the Dan River spill and considering a plan to close the Asheville plant.
She said the company's proposal for dealing with coal ash is a "good first step," but is "incomplete and does not fully rise to the challenge presented."
"Without more information, North Carolinians cannot be sure that their right to clean, safe drinking water will be protected," Martin said.
Good said in her letter that Duke's long term plans for handling coal ash won't be ready until the end of the year when the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency issues rules for federal regulation of coal ash.
"This strategy will include a review of active ponds, inactive ponds and closure strategies for the remaining retired plants, will be informed by outside experts, and will include a risk-informed, tiered approach," Good said.
She said the company wants a meeting with state environmental officials to discuss the matter.
]]></text></news-item>