<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DC37-3188-E276-6B4A"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Links 3/14/14</title><source>Naked Capitalism</source><author>Yves Smith</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 14, 2014 (Naked Capitalism:http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/ Delivered by Newstex) Tony Benn dies, aged 88[1] Telegraph. The Telegraph has made the death of this great Socialist its lead story, while it is below the fold at the Guardian. Success mainly down to having a loud voice[2] Daily Mash Beautiful Games: a complete illustrated history of football[3] Guardian. Lambert: 'That is, soccer.'
Dozens of Planes Have Vanished in Post-WWII Era[4] Bloomberg I am Tim Berners-Lee. I invented the WWW 25 years ago and I am concerned and excited about its future.[5] Reddit (Richard Smith) Silicon Valley is turning our lives into an asset class[6] Financial Times (David L) Bitcoin's Evolution toward Self-Destruction[7] Dan Kervick, New Economic Perspectives Troubled waters: Nuclear radiation found in B.C. may pose health concerns[8] Vancouver Sun (David L) Desperately seeking (Chinese) stimulus[9] MacroBusiness Fresh corporate default tests China's resolve[10] Financial Times Markets fall on weak Chinese data, Fed worries and Ukraine fears - as it happened [11]Guardian. Notice Chinese data was so bad that the Guardian went into live blog mode. When Should Government Officials Be Criminally Liable for Failure to Prevent Corruption? [12]Reflections on Thailand, and Beyond Global Atlantic Corruption Blog Prince Charles letters: attorney general acted unlawfully, say senior judges[13] Guardian (Richard Smith) Washington's Back-to-the-Future Military Policies in Africa, America's New Model for Expeditionary Warfare[14] Nick Turse, Tom Engelhardt Former Egyptian General Calls Promise of Free Elections a 'Farce'[15] New York Times Ukraine Russian Troops Mass at Border With Ukraine[16] New York Times Russia holds the cards in Crimea[17] DW Ukraine crisis: John Kerry and Sergey Lavrov to meet in London for talks[18] Guardian. This is a climbdown by the US. Kerry had attached conditions to a meeting and has been forced to drop them. US Using Oil to Fight Russian Gas Politics in Ukraine?[19] OilPrice Kiev's protesters: Ukraine uprising was no neo-Nazi power-grab[20] Guardian. Lambert: ' Fascist iconography is never accidental. While the headline is IMNSHO technically correct, it's what comes next that is the issue, right?' Ukraine: EU Parliament Warns Of Association With Svoboda Party[21] Moon of Alabama Big Brother is Watching You Watch In 1975, the CIA Director Told Congress That Enemies of America Could Destroy the CIA with Freedom of Information Act Requests[22] Matt Stoller Facebook CEO Calls Obama Regarding Out of Control NSA; Change You Can't Believe In [23]Michael Shedlock. Godzilla v. Mothra. Late Night: Ass Forward[24] cocktailhag, Firedoglake (Carol B) SASC Hearing: Dunford Advocates for Forever War in Afghanistan[25] Marcy Wheeler Sen. Elizabeth Warren Takes FDA Chief To Task On Weak Antibiotics Guidance[26] Consumerist Study Proves Campaign Donations Buy Access[27] DSWright, Firedoglake (Carol B) Watchdog group says review identified 303 deaths in GM cars with undeployed air-bags[28] Washington Post Telecoms take HUNDREDS OF BILLIONS for national broadband, but don't want to deliver[29] Daily Kos (Carol B) HORROR: Five Cops Beat Innocent, Unarmed Father to Death Outside Cinemas[30] Alternet U.S. Criticized for Lack of Action on Mortgage Fraud[31] New York Times. I wish I felt more excited about this. But all this means is the critics of the DoJ have been vindicated. It does nothing for borrowers, particularly since the statute of limitations for the best legal theories for going after the perps have expired. And so what if Holder et al get hauled up before the Senate and roughed up? The fact that they'd do so little to address a problem of this magnitude means they are beyond shame. Lawsky Prepared to Name Individuals at BNP in Crackdown[32] Bloomberg (Richard D) RELEASE OF OFFSHORE RECORDS DRAWS WORLDWIDE RESPONSE[33] ICIJ (Richard Smith) Countdown to taper mark III[34] MacroBusiness Why all the pessimism in the NFIB Small Business Optimism Index?[35] Walter Kurtz all Street Bonuses Are Bouncing Back, While Everyone Else's Wages Are… Meh[36] Business Insider Far from the Wolf of Wall Street: how did young people become so risk averse?[37] New Statesman (Chuck L) The Surprisingly Large Cost of Telling Small Lies[38] New York Times (Lambert) Antidote du jour (furzy mouse): http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/image010.jpg [1]: http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/politics/labour/10697094/Tony-Benn-dies-aged-88.html [2]: http://www.thedailymash.co.uk/news/society/success-mainly-down-to-having-a-loud-voice-2014031484595 [3]: http://www.theguardian.com/football/gallery/2014/mar/12/beautiful-games-a-complete-illustrated-history-of-football [4]: http://www.bloomberg.com/infographics/2014-03-13/vanishing-planes-mapped-since-1948.html [5]: http://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/2091d4/i_am_tim_bernerslee_i_invented_the_www_25_years/ [6]: http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/0/9d2a73fe-a54a-11e3-8070-00144feab7de.html [7]: http://neweconomicperspectives.org/2014/03/bitcoins-evolution-toward-self-destruction.html [8]: http://www.vancouversun.com/news/Toxic+waters+Nuclear+radiation+found+pose+health+concerns/9606269/story.html [9]: http://www.macrobusiness.com.au/2014/03/desperately-seeking-chinese-stimulus/ [10]: http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/0/27f9f4aa-aa82-11e3-9fd6-00144feab7de.html?siteedition=intl#axzz2vYB9Nv7q [11]: http://www.theguardian.com/business/blog/2014/mar/13/chinas-economy-slows-markedly-start-year [12]: http://globalanticorruptionblog.com/2014/03/11/when-should-government-officials-be-criminally-liable-for-failure-to-prevent-corruption-reflections-on-thailand-and-beyond/ [13]: http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2014/mar/12/attorney-general-unlawful-prince-charles-letters?CMP=twt_gu [14]: http://www.tomdispatch.com/blog/175818/ [15]: http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/14/world/middleeast/former-egyptian-general-calls-promise-of-free-elections-a-farce.html [16]: http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/14/world/europe/ukraine.html [17]: http://www.dw.de/russia-holds-the-cards-in-crimea/a-17495721 [18]: http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/mar/14/ukraine-crisis-john-kerry-sergey-lavrov-meet-london-talks [19]: https://oilprice.com/Energy/Energy-General/US-Using-Oil-to-Fight-Russian-Gas-Politics-in-Ukraine.html [20]: http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/mar/13/ukraine-uprising-fascist-coup-grassroots-movement [21]: http://www.moonofalabama.org/2014/03/ukraine-eu-parliament-warns-of-association-with-svoboda.html [22]: http://mattstoller.tumblr.com/post/79503748901/in-1975-the-cia-director-told-congress-that-enemies-of [23]: http://globaleconomicanalysis.blogspot.com/2014/03/facebook-ceo-calls-obama-regarding-out.html [24]: http://firedoglake.com/2014/03/13/late-night-ass-forward/ [25]: http://www.emptywheel.net/2014/03/13/sasc-hearing-dunford-advocates-for-forever-war-in-afghanistan/? [26]: http://consumerist.com/2014/03/13/sen-elizabeth-warren-takes-fda-chief-to-task-on-weak-antibiotics-guidance/ [27]: http://news.firedoglake.com/2014/03/13/study-proves-campaign-donations-buy-access/ [28]: http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/watchdog-group-says-review-identified-303-deaths-in-gm-cars-with-undeployed-air-bags/2014/03/13/458de81c-ab1f-11e3-98f6-8e3c562f9996_story.html?hpid=z1 [29]: http://www.dailykos.com/story/2014/03/13/1284324/-Telecoms-take-HUNDREDS-OF-BILLIONS-for-national-broadband-but-don-t-want-to-deliver# [30]: http://www.alternet.org/news-amp-politics/horror-five-cops-beat-innocent-unarmed-father-death-outside-cinemas [31]: http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2014/03/13/u-s-overstates-efforts-to-prosecute-mortgage-fraud-watchdog-says/ [32]: http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2014-03-13/lawsky-prepared-to-name-individuals-at-bnp-in-crackdown.html [33]: http://www.icij.org/blog/2013/04/release-offshore-records-draws-worldwide-response [34]: http://www.macrobusiness.com.au/2014/03/countdown-to-taper-mark-iii/ [35]: http://soberlook.com/2014/03/why-all-pessimism-in-nfib-small.html [36]: http://www.businessinsider.com/wall-street-bonuses-vs-income-2014-3 [37]: http://www.newstatesman.com/politics/2014/03/far-wolf-wall-street-how-did-young-people-become-so-risk-averse%20 [38]: http://boss.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/03/11/the-surprisingly-large-cost-of-telling-small-lies/

]]></text></news-item>