<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DC50-189A-105F-DA8F"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Drug Pricing And Patents Come Under Scrutiny Of FAS</title><source>Business Monitor Online</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[BMI View : Multinational pharmaceutical companies in Russia have not faced the same regulatory issues that the Indian market has presented on pricing and intellectual property, but statements from the head of the Federal Antimonopoly Service (FAS) signify a shift in sentiment from the state regulatory body. With drug pricing also the focus of the FAS and given the macroeconomic outlook for Russia, we now see further downside risk to our forecasts for Russian pharmaceutical sales.
The Federal Antimonopoly Service (FAS) of Russia has published a report that potentially indicates further readiness by the regulatory body to intervene in pharmaceutical pricing. The report compared pharmaceutical prices in Russia relative to European and emerging markets, and concluded that foreign pharmaceutical companies had introduced price inflation or purposefully charged Russian consumers a premium relative to other markets. According to the head of the FAS, Igor Artemyev, in a statement to the Duma, "[Russia] has the most expensive drugs in the world due to regulatory errors." He attributed this to drug companies abusing patents to undermine competition, creating a monopoly and contravening the notion of 'interchangeability' as written in the Russian law "On Circulation of Medicines".
Artemyev was referring to what some market observers cynically label as "evergreening", but which the industry describes as necessary, iterative innovations to existing pharmaceutical compounds. The debate over whether modifying existing compounds to derive better efficacy has been a flashpoint of contention globally; the Indian Patent Office has explicitly denied or overridden intellectual property protection to multinational companies for modified versions of already available drugs such as Glivec (imatinib mesylate) and Nexavar (sorafenib) on the grounds of price and more importantly, on the basis that the drugs were not 'inventive'.
Artemyev also commented on how drugs were cheaper in some CIS countries relative to Russia and we believe this is an erroneous comparison to make, considering the relative incomes of Russians versus their CIS counterparts. This argument also ignores how business environments impact pricing; in Russia, all drugs must go through costly, local clinical trials, in order to gain approval, whereas regulatory authorities in Europe and emerging markets mutually recognise approvals from European or US agencies. Drug manufacturers simply factored these additional costs into their pricing in Russia. Other costs factored into the price are foreign exchange movements, start-up overheads, marketing, local wages, reliability of importer payments and the sales volumes expected.
Earlier, in January, the Ministry of Health proposed to revise the reference pricing mechanism used to calculate prices of foreign drugs on the Vital and Essential Drugs (VED) list, a list of drugs that all pharmacies and hospitals must stock. The Ministry proposed removing some countries from the reference mechanism, but according to industry officials, the countries to be removed were those with the highest reference prices, essentially forcing foreign drugmakers to concede a discount. The only way to circumvent this limit would be to licence the full production cycle to a Russian company, as the drug price would then be up to the discretion of the licensee. In essence, this move was designed to catalyse the move towards joint ventures and in-licensing, as part of Russia's Pharma2020 strategy on reducing import reliance.
While Russia has been less imposing than India in granting patents to MNCs, the comments from the head of FAS in front of the Russian parliament is potentially a worrying development for the industry, especially considering the proportion and value of patented drug sales relative to the total market. The vast majority of patented medicines are sold to hospitals and federally-reimbursed drug programmes (DLO) and while the Russian government historically increased funding towards healthcare, it has recently reversed course, instead pushing more of the cost of healthcare onto citizens. On balance, the head of the FAS suggested long-term contracts with drugmakers in return for pricing negotiations, but given that the Russian government procures through tenders, the state holds a large amount of leverage over pricing.
Bearish Macroeconomic Outlook
Russia relies overwhelmingly on oil and gas exports to drive state revenues and consumption growth. We have previously noted that healthcare spending would unlikely be able to maintain the growth trajectory of the past five years, as peak oil prices subsided and supply rose globally. Our Country Risk analysts have grown progressively bearish towards the Russian economy over the course of 2013 and now into 2014, as pressure has mounted on the Russian economic growth model and geopolitical tensions have dampened the growth outlook for 2014. Indeed, the Russian government has reversed course on healthcare spending, budgeting a net reduction in spending by 22% to RUB383bn (US$11.86bn) by 2015. In light of the macroeconomic outlook and the realities of financing healthcare, we see this focus on pricing now as delivering long-term downside risk on top of the elevated risk levels in the Russian pharmaceutical market currently and thus, we will be updating our Russian forecasts over the coming weeks.
2014 will be an important year for the industry in Russia, as the rollout of a regional drug reimbursement programme will begin and legislation that will undoubtedly impact the competitive landscape will be tabled in the Duma. This year, the Russian pharmaceutical market will post double-digit growth in local currency terms and high single digit growth in US dollar terms. We forecast pharmaceutical spending to reach RUB859.37bn (US$25.43bn) in 2014, growing 12.2% year-over-year in rouble terms and 4.6% in US dollar terms.
]]></text></news-item>