<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DC5A-1AAD-E987-B6FB"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Last Tuesday I watched Al Gore's An Inconvenient Truth</title><source>The Warrnambool Standard</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Last Tuesday I watched Al Gore's An Inconvenient Truth documentary. That was copyright 2006 and some of the predictions have come to pass.
I used to think that some politicians were asleep at the wheel but now I think they have taken their hands off the wheel completely and withdrawn their feet from the pedals. And with the abandonment of advisory committees have also placed their hands over their collective eyes.
Yes, and we're just sitting here watching the unfolding car crash. Less than $2 a day would have been cheap insurance. The Prime Minister and his ministers say repeatedly that by 2030 we will be paying $300 per tonne of carbon dioxide emitted. This price is to drive us away from digging up and burning carbon.
OK, that gives us 15 years to build at least one, preferably a string of, large-scale solar-thermal power plants with storage north-west of the Sunraysia district.
If we had started when the White Paper was delivered several years ago we might have made some progress by now.
Spain had theirs running within a few years. Solar attracts very little carbon tax, even at $300/tonne.
Anyone deriving power from these plants alone won't pay a carbon tax for this power. Now that the auto workers have been liberated we have all the personnel we need. This'll be a new industry with new opportunities unless we ship the project offshore as we did with the desal plant in some deluded sense that it would be cheaper.
No point saving billions and giving it away, we need to own this.
We might be able to export said power to Indonesia or Malaysia. The export technology is being developed now.
Climate change is now referred to as climate variability! Just who are these government officials protecting? It is certainly not us and why do/how can those being protected think they are immune?
Once the global leaders in this regard we are now to be dragged inevitably screaming like a petulant child ito an emissions trading scheme? For who are our governments working?
Rod Muir, Port Fairy
Fracking: it's all bad
The report in the Sydney Morning Herald of pollution of an aquifer in New South Wales by Satos' gas fracking operations is very worrying. There are now very high levels of radionucleides in the aquifer, as well as toxic chemicals and dangerous heavy metals.
The pollution from gas fracking will be permanent.
The methods and money are not available to remove the radioactive elements, chemicals and heavy metals from the vast amounts of water in underground aquifers. No weasel words of industry and government can magically perform such a gargantuan task.
In a few short years, the gas fracking in NSW and Queensland has had terrible consequences for farming, water supplies and people's health.
Apart from the pollution, each well can use from two million to eight million litres of water, and the amount of water wasted by pollution is a disposal problem, as the water cannot be reused on land.
If the polluted water is reinjected ito the aquifer, then these aquifers will not be usable now or in the future. And we will need the water in this dry land with its fast-growing population and the agriculture that government is fond of saying will feed the world.
If the gas industry is not stopped from fracking right now, the results will not be in the dim distant future. The present pollution of the NSW aquifer will be the first of many such incidents. It is known by the gasfield industry that a large proportion of the gas wells fail immediately, and many fail after a few short years as concrete seals decay.
This industry must be shut down before it destroys any more water resources, and damages any more people's health. The question is: do the Labor, Liberal and National parties have the wisdom to ban the industry and look at the clean renewable alternatives?
The Australian people elected these parties, but if they cannot put our health first then other parties and independent candidates, not just the Greens, will rise up and act ethically on our behalf. Our governments need to remember that decisions made on fracking will affect whether or not they get voted in at the next state and federal elections.
Gillian Blair, secretary,
Sustainable Agriculture & Communities Alliance
TV reception woes
Am I alone? Or are there others out there who are totally frustrated with the quality of TV reception in Warrnambool? I have tried everything, cut down trees in the line of sight of Albert Park, installed a new antenna and previously sought the services of an expert, who confirmed that everything is OK!
Why then do I still have to endure the continual break down of signal quality, particularly when watching the ABC? I have all the up-to-date technology and during the day have signal strength at the top end of the scale. Night time is different.
At one stage I lost quality around 6.30 every evening. I have reported this to the powers that be but have never received any reply or follow-up despite what their website says. I've had enough and need to see if others have been sitting quietly by hoping that one day this may not be the case. It is amazing what many voices can achieve!
Alan Richardson, Warrnambool
Post-disaster care
Floods, fires, cyclones and heatwaves have made this summer a difficult one for many Australians.
Yet again we've been reminded, just how disruptive and devastating emergencies can be. Disasters can happen in a moment, but their effects can be felt for a lifetime.
As time passes and media attention shifts, those not directly affected tend to forget, but for people impacted by the disaster the process of recovery has just begun.
People who have experienced a disaster this summer may be contemplating significant changes to their lives. Whether this includes rebuilding, missing friends and loved ones who have relocated or dealing with the trauma of the experience, it can be a daunting time. It's so important that people look after themselves emotionally and not be afraid to reach out for help. If you are recovering, seeking support from family, government agencies or organisations like Red Cross is a critical part of taking care of yourself.
For people concerned about loved ones, checking in to make sure they're OK is a simple step to show support. Red Cross has developed recovery resources to help with the psychological and practical stages of recovery, which are available on our website.
Unfortunately, the threat of disaster isn't over yet.
The Hazelwood mine fire is still burning, threatening the wellbeing of Morwell residents. As we continue to respond to the immediate threat, I encourage people to take care in recovery and to take action to prepare for the future disasters.
Andrew Coghlan,
national manager of emergency services, Australian Red Cross
A job well done
Last weekend, by being a member of the Warrnambool Surf Life Saving Club, I had the pleasure of being involved in Victorian Junior lifesaving championships otherwise known as the Nipper Vics. And what a pleasure it was! To see Lady Bay chock-a-block with over 5000 nippers and spectators was a great sight.
To see such wonderful volunteering, including people driving IRB's, providing water safety for the kids, marshalling events, judging events, providing first aid, erecting competition fencing, beach cleaning, making lunches etc etc is truly heartening, remembering that many of these volunteers don't have kids competing at this event.
I witnessed 25 or so Lions club members work their arses off for 12 hours each day preparing cooking and selling all manner of food so they can fund-raise for other charitable of community causes. I saw the mayor, Michael Neoh, Cr Rob Askew and WCC director city infrastructure, Peter Robertson come and personally inspect the beach to ensure its suitability for the carnival. We saw WCC staff led by 'Rock' Wilkinson organise, at incredibly short notice, heavy machinery to clean the beach of seaweed. I don't know if this sort of council involvement occurs at other cities/shires but it's great that it happens in Warrnambool.
I saw 1400 young kids run, swim, wade and paddle for two days and have an absolute ball. And at the end of it all I saw over 1000 families leave the beach truly knackered from a great event.
This event is a credit to the Warrnambool Surf Life Saving Club and all involved and is indicative of what communities are doing over Australia. I was privileged to have been involved in this event. Well done Warrnambool.
Alan Aulsebrook,
Hervey Bay, Queensland
]]></text></news-item>