<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DC78-A2BF-8279-0627"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: WorkSafe Probing Over Fibro in Dickson Building</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Emma MacDonald, writing for The Canberra Times, reported thatWorkSafe ACT has ordered the owners of a building in WoolleyStreet Dickson, in Canberra, Australia, to either remove or seal alarge commercial roof space after finding loose asbestos fibreswere falling from asbestos sheeting lining the roof. The building owners, registered as Choi and Lau Enterprises and Jand S Chan, face repair bills in the hundreds of thousands withWorkSafe also investigating whether they breached ACT legislation.If that were the case, they could also face potential prosecutionand sizeable fines. The formal orders, which were handed to all parties, also placethe future of two automotive businesses working from the buildingunder a cloud as they will remain sealed until the roof issue isresolved. The contents of both workshops, including tools, equipment andcars, will also be off limits until they are forensically cleanedof asbestos particles by a licensed asbestos cleaner -- adding tothe hefty repair bill. Meanwhile, Lucky's Barber, one of three businesses within thebuilding allowed to continue operating because it is protectedfrom immediate risk by a false ceiling, reported that people wereso fearful of entering the building over the past fortnight thatbusiness had fallen off dramatically. Hairdresser Thanittha Prommahom said she was considering whetherthe business would need to move. "People see the [WorkSafe prohibition notice] signs and turnaround and walk back out," Ms Prommahom said. Work Safety inspectors closed two workshops, CNS Transmission andMorris Bros Automotive and Marine, on January 24 after they actedon a report that asbestos was falling from the roof. This waslater confirmed in testing. CNS could not be contacted and Morris Bros did not wish tocomment. The building's co-owners are the Chan family behind the well-knownand popular Ruby Restaurant. The family said they were cooperatingfully with WorkSafe ACT and were in the process of organisingdecontamination for the affected businesses, as well as their ownstoreroom, which has also been sealed off. The family said they planned to have the roof replaced. The other co-owner, Henry Lau, could not be contacted. Ruby Restaurant is in a separate and adjacent building frontingonto Woolley Street and it has not been affected by looseasbestos. ACT Work Safety Commissioner Mark McCabe said a formalinvestigation into the building owners still continued todetermine whether they had the proper Asbestos Management Plan inplace and whether they had followed it. "Business and owners of buildings being used for commercialpurposes must have an Asbestos Management Plan, prepared by aqualified professional, which identifies if asbestos is present intheir workplace, where it is present, and what must be done toeliminate or manage any risks arising from that material," MrMcCabe said. "Asbestos is a fairly ubiquitous material in our builtenvironment, not only here but across Australia. When it isproperly managed it should not present a health and safety risk toeither workers or the general public. When it is not properlymanaged, however, it has the potential to present an unacceptablelevel of risk to health and safety. "It is incumbent on businesses and property owners to meet theirobligations in respect of managing the risks associated withasbestos. Failure to do so can not only put workers and the publicat risk, but could lead to severe business consequences, includingprosecution for failure to comply with their legislativeobligations." Canberra Asbestos Removal manager Wade Rogers said the costs ofremoving the roof of the building could rise above $250,000 andthat loose asbestos falling from sheeting, known as Super 6, was aticking time bomb across many commercial and industrial businessesin Canberra. "People should be thinking about managing and removing it soonerrather than later," he said. The costs of sealing the space was a short-term solution and couldalso cost in excess of $100,000, he said. It would mean the building could no longer be used or tenanted.Mr McCabe also warned there were likely to be a number of otherlocal businesses in the ACT with similar roof sheeting, which weredeteriorating over time. "The owners of those businesses should check that they have anAsbestos Management Plan for their premises and that they areresponding to any action identified as necessary in that plan." Mr Wade said there was a lot of fear surrounding the issue ofasbestos. "It is a difficult situation, and I feel for everyone, it's notnice for the tenant, who's business gets shut down, but someonehas got to take responsibility and that's the owner."
]]></text></news-item>