<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DC98-9DF8-153A-8B5F"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Study: Metro-North ignored safety</title><source>The Chronicle (Willimantic, Connecticut)</source><author>MARTIN CASSIDY</author><text><![CDATA[Stamford Advocate
A new investigative report on Metro- North Railroad's safety culture found that the railroad's management endangered the public with an emphasis on on-time performance and failed to give proper attention to needed repairs, training, and safety protocols.
The results of the Federal Railroad Administration's 60-day intensive review of Metro-North's safety culture released Friday morning faulted railroad leaders for de- emphasizing necessary safety precautions, poor training for workers and a pervasive lack of diligence in defining the railroad's safety goals and rules on everything from required rest periods, to cellular phone usage.
" The findings of Operation Deep Dive demonstrate that Metro-North emphasized on-time performance to the detriment of safe operations and adequate maintenance of its infrastructure," the report said. "This led to a deficient safety culture that has manifested itself in increased risk and reduced safety on Metro-North."
The review begun in December and completed last month found a wide array of lax practices and an inability to safety from poor training of workers, a lack of supervision of track inspections and pressure to rush repairs to keep service running normally, according to the report.
The railroad's operations were guided by a premium on on-time performance over other priorities, according to the report.
"The report is a searing indictment of Metro-North's sustained severe safety failings," U.S. Sen. Richard Blumenthal, D- Conn., said. " It notes the absence of key technology or safety improvements like confidential close call reporting."
The probe began in December after a seven-car train careened off the tracks in Spuyten Duyvil on the Hudson line traveling 82 miles per hour where the top speed was 30. The crash killed four and injured 70, and sparked the regulatory agency to mandate changes including speed restrictions and upgrades to signal systems to enforce automatic brak- (Study:, Page 4)
(Continued from Page 1)
ing.
The railroad's track inspection process was found to be subpar due to under-trained track inspectors, inadequate supervision and an overall backlog of necessary repairs exacerbated by a lack of allotted time to fix problems, according to the report.
The report also highlighted concerns about track worker fatigue from working overly long hours to make overtime, increasing the risk of accidents due to overwork.
The railroad is being asked to create a plan with unionized workers to moderate their work hours and overtime to limit poor performance.
In the report, federal regulators cite track workers being expected to complete repairs within a narrow time frame dictated by the need to maintain service, and operations control center employees including rail traffic controllers were pushed to fix signal problems quickly.
The report also criticizes Metro- North's failure to institute a so-called C3Rs system to allow workers to confidentially report potential safety problems, an FRA recommendation made repeatedly since the derailment of a commuter train in Bridgeport 10 months ago, Blumenthal said.
In a statement, the railroad's new president, Joseph J. Giulietti, said that the railroad administration "has performed an important review of Metro-North operations and recommended significant improvements." While he said the railroad would discuss the recommendations in more detail once the report was released formally, he said Metro-North was taking "aggressive actions to affirm that safety is the most important factor in railroad operations."
The 60 day investigation represented an unusually aggressive use of the FRA's authority to intervene, and the report is the culmination of the FRA rapidly stepping up focus on Metro North's safety culture.
After the Bridgeport derailment the agency increased its inspections of Metro-North tracks and spot audits of compliance with federal regulations.
Then on Dec. 1 after a second derailment in Spuyten Duyvil that killed four people, the Federal Railroad Administration issued an emergency order to implement signal system changes that would automatically slow trains down when engineers fail to brake when approaching speed restricted areas, and other mandatory interim safeguards until the signal systems enforced speed control.
The increased scrutiny and publicity surrounding the lack of automated safeguards to protect against an engineer's failure to act drew harsh criticism from lawmakers like Blumenthal, who has pressed for accelerated probes of the two derailments and a string of other accidents in 2013 to kick start reform of the railroad's safety culture.
After the derailment in Spuyten Duyvil on Dec. 1 killed four people, the Federal Railroad Administration asked Metro-North to hold a safety stand down with all employees and to implement a confidential close call reporting system allowing whistleblowers to report potential safety problems anonymously.
Distributed by MCT Information Services.
]]></text></news-item>