<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DD2B-D3F6-8663-E8CB"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Animal Welfare Board of India bats against battery cages</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>Ch Sushil Rao</author><text><![CDATA[HYDERABAD: Animal Welfare Board of India (AWBI) chairman Maj Gen Dr. R.M Kharb (rtd) said while there has been a dramatic improvement in the field of animal welfare in the country, much is needed to be done to reduce animal cruelty issues related to farm animals and street dogs.
Humane Society International/India in collaboration with Blue Cross of Hyderabad hosted an interactive session headed by prominent veterinarian and AWBI Chairman, Maj Gen Kharb who delivered a talk on the functions of AWBI and India's progress in varied verticals of animal welfare on Thursday.
Officials from the various departments including animal husbandry, Greater Hyderabad Municipal Corporation, forest department, veterinary doctors participated in the programme noted animal welfare activist and Blue Cross of Hyderabad co-founder Amala Akkineni said the meeting had garnered a positive focus on welfare of animals.
AWBI Chairman, Gen Kharb expressing his concern over the treatment of animals in slaughter houses and growing population of street dogs, said several cruelty issues were reported in animal transportation, poor hygiene in and out of slaughter houses and dog abuse in localities. He urged government officials, medical officers and NGOs to work in tandem to ensure that animals were treated compassionately.
Calling a stray dog as the smartest of all other breeds, he said: "It is our moral obligation to save these intelligent animals from brutality. Uncontrolled dog population is seen as a menace in both urban and rural areas which can only be curbed in a scientific manner through mass sterilization and vaccination programs."
Talking about the growing consumption of meat and dairy products, he said "the barbaric treatment of animals in battery cages is appalling'. He said intensive confinement of egg laying hens in barbed battery cages denied them all their natural freedom.
He appreciated Humane Society International/India and its managing director, N G Jayasimha's efforts in leading the battery cage campaign in India. He spoke about AWBI's advisory to all Indian states to phase out battery cages. Dr. Venkateswarlu, director, animal husbandry assured that intensive confinement of egg laying hens was an alarming issue and that the department was committed to the cause of elimination of battery cages from India.
Dr. Manmohan Singh, IAS and principal secretary, animal husbandry said schools and educational institutions equally share the onus of promoting the concept of compassionate living in pupils who will make better citizens in the future.
Animal husbandry and GHMC officials requested AWBI to support them in animal birth Control program, capacity building, management of goshalas and slaughter houses and waste management.
Battery cages in Andhra Pradesh is an important issue as the state is the biggest producer of eggs in India. Indian factory farms confine more than 200 million hens in barren battery cages. Each bird lives within a space smaller than a single sheet of paper for more than a year before she's slaughtered. Factory farms that confine more than 50,000 birds within a single shed are increasingly common in India. Cage-free hens have more space and are able to walk, spread their wings and lay their eggs in nests - all behaviors denied to hens confined in barren battery cages, it was informed.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>