<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DD68-C0AC-D620-22D7"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Who the Uighurs are</title><source>Ottawa Citizen</source><author>Shannon Gormley, Ottawa Citizen</author><text><![CDATA['China's Uighurs: Who are they?" asks one Christian Science Monitor headline.
"Islamic militants in China," answers a headline from the Daily Mirror.
The question has been asked following the disappearance of Malaysian Airlines flight MH370 and a mass stabbing in Kunming, China. But the question reveals a global ignorance of the very existence of Uighurs, and the answer reveals a global ignorance of the identity of most Uighurs. Since so many people have to ask who Uighurs are, the Chinese government gets to define for the world much of what Uighurs represent.
Most recently, the Chinese government's pejorative definition of Uighur people has made it easy to unfairly accuse them of hijacking planes. More generally, it's led to absurd justifications for economic conditions and cultural crackdowns so grim that it's likely the government has dramatically exacerbated the same extremism it chronically exaggerates.
The Chinese government largely defines Uighurs - roughly 10 million mostly Muslim people living in Xinjiang, a northwestern province of China - as a group that harbours relatively high levels of religiousbased antipathy toward the Chinese Communist Party and its values.
The problem is that the government has a nasty habit of conflating Uighurs' antipathy with separatist intentions, and separatist intentions with acts of criminal extremism, and acts of criminal extremism with violent terrorism.
Other governments, particularly America's - who can sometimes appear more afraid to be soft on terrorism than afraid to appear soft on truth - have perpetuated the CCP's dangerously inaccurate characterization of Uighurs by, for example, listing some Uighur groups as terrorist organizations with only the Chinese government's word as evidence.
As Human Rights Watch has pointed out, by winning even tepid international support for its propaganda war against Uighurs, the Chinese government wins a massive conceptual coup.
Thus, with nearly each public utterance of the word "Uighur," Uighurs are increasingly defined as Islamic militants in China - as, in a word, terrorists.
The international community may make many mistakes, but it rarely makes the mistake of taking China's claims about human rights or security issues at face value.
If ever there's a time to treat the party's claims with skepticism rather than naiveté, it's when those claims are made about a group that it systematically represses.
So, if a Uighur shouldn't be defined as an Islamic militant in China, who are Uighurs? Uighurs are Turkic-speaking people who have lived, died and suffered under Chinese rule since China took over the territory of Xinjiang in 1949. Most Uighur Muslims practise a moderate form of Islam and, by even the wildest stretch of an imagination petrified by visions of religious-based terrorism, Uighur Muslims in Xinjiang don't have a long and strong history of advocating Islamic extremism. So as the last few years have seen rising violence from some Uighurs, it's worth asking why.
And rather than only ask who Uighurs are, we should ask what kind of conditions Uighurs live under.
In a word: repressive. In four words: culturally and economically repressive.
When the Chinese government took over Xinjiang, the population of ethnic Chinese people was about six per cent. The Chinese government orchestrated a mass migration into the province, and Han Chinese people now represent over 40 per cent of the province's population. The cultural and economic status of those Han Chinese and Uighurs are oppositional to one another.
Culturally, over the past couple of decades, the CCP has outlawed minors from participating in any religious activities. It has destroyed mosques and censored religious publications and purged schools. Imams have been required to attend regular confessionals, in which they must prove loyalty to the party by confessing "errors." After inspections, mosque are presented with certificates declaring them either "conforming" or "non-conforming."
According to one government manual obtained by Human Rights Watch, Uighurs are forbidden from "propagating separatist thought" From "presenting the subject in satires or allegories that give free rein to and disseminate dissatisfaction." From "spreading rumours to confuse the people." From "making use of broadcasts, the Internet and other means to intensify campaigns of reactionary propaganda and infiltration of ideas into public opinion." From "using popular cultural activities to make the masses receptive to reactionary propaganda encouraging opposition."
Little wonder Uighurs live in fear of expressing critical opinions, religious-based or otherwise. Earlier this year, authorities snatched a prominent (and critical) Uighur scholar. Human rights groups have warned that there's a very real risk that he'll be tortured.
Economically, Xinjiang is rich in oil, but you'd never know it by the fact that Uighurs work menial jobs, especially compared to Han Chinese. As Reuters recently reported, job advertisements can be found specifying "no Uighurs accepted."
Of course, the fact that most Uighurs face daunting cultural and economic obstacles doesn't justify a small number of Uighurs committing violent crimes.
That's why the exiled leader of the World Uighur Congress has called for dissent to remain peaceful. The conditions that may inflame violence don't excuse it, but by addressing the former we may reduce the latter.
That's why it's so disturbing that, according to the South China Morning Post, since the knife attacks reportedly carried out by Xinjiang separatists, even Uighurs in faraway Beijing are facing much stricter identity checks. While the Chinese government asks who Uighurs are, we should be skeptical of how it answers its own question.
Shannon Gormley is a Canadian journalist based in Beirut. She writes for the Citizen every Saturday about global affairs and the state of democracy and liberalism around the world.
]]></text></news-item>