<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DDEF-F9CC-4460-CC60"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>New business owners suffer from firm's history</title><source>Times Colonist (Victoria, British Columbia)</source><author>Sian Thomson, The Courier-Islander</author><text><![CDATA[Jos and Rentia Krynen were hoping for a fresh start, but they didn't realize the past would come back to haunt them. Even though it wasn't their past.
The couple bought Eagle Eye Adventures, whalewatching and wildlife tours, in July 2011, after selling their dental practices in the Netherlands and immigrating to Campbell River. Voted as one of the top five Canadian outdoor adventures by TripAdvisor, the world's largest travel website, the company was thriving and business was up by 57 per cent in 2013.
Jos, who is also a marine biologist, and his wife Rentia, were not expecting their business venture to encounter choppy waters.
"There was an incident with Jason Smith, a former employee of Eagle Eye Adventures before we bought the company," Krynen said. "In 2010 he was charged with disturbing killer whales, keeping the boat too close for an extended period of time. We were not aware of this, and have never met Mr. Smith. He has never worked for us."
On Jan.30, Smith was found guilty of violating the Fisheries Act, from an incident in 2010, fined $6,000 and prohibited from working in the whale-watching industry for 10 years. It was also disclosed that Smith was found guilty in 2011 for a similar incident in 2008.
"This got into all the newspapers and media," Krynen said. "Now the words 'harassing whales,' 'Jason Smith' and 'Eagle Eye Adventures' are all used in the same sentences and we are not that old Eagle Eye Adventures." Since the conviction became public, Krynen said he has been "losing business like crazy."
"Somebody else did this. I don't know the guy. I have never met him. I don't know what he looks like and nobody is asking us about it," he said. "If I had known this was going to happen, I still would have bought the business but I would have definitely changed the name of it. We have been screwed. Everyone is using our name negatively. It just isn't fun any more."
Krynen said he has worked with the Department of Fisheries and Oceans from the beginning and does everything in his power to make sure his boats stay outside the buffer zone of 100 metres from the whales.
"We use range finders to make sure we are at the right distance from them," he said.
"Our rules are there to protect the whales, obey the law and make sure we preserve our nature.
"We do provide our people with the material and electronics so they do not have to go too close to the whales. We even provide them with camera equipment so that they can take pictures that we share for free with our guests. As a marine biologist, I sure do know how we love the wildlife and how we need to protect it. We do not cut corners; we obey the law."
Krynen is not happy with the media.
"If only reporters would do their jobs properly and don't drag out innocent business names," he said. "It just isn't fair to us, using footage without us knowing, not even consulting me.
"We are busting our you know what off every day to build a business and then without any background information, they use the name that I try to build and bring tourists into our community."
]]></text></news-item>