<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DE1C-0754-0651-28FA"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Grupo Clarin S.A. Annual Financial Report -35-</title><source>London Stock Exchange Aggregated Regulatory News Service (ARNS)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Where there is objective evidence of an impairment loss in the value of loans granted, receivables or held-to-maturity investments recorded at amortized cost, the loss amount is measured as the difference between the book value and the present value of estimated future cash flows (without including future non-incurred losses), discounted at the original effective interest rate of the financial asset. The asset's book value is written down under a contra asset account. The loss amount is recognized in net income for the year.
If, in subsequent periods, the impairment loss amount decreases and such decrease can be objectively related to an event occurring after the impairment has been recognized (such as an improvement in the debtor's credit rating), the previously recognized impairment loss is reversed. A loss reversal can only be recorded to the extent the financial asset's book value does not exceed the amortized cost that would have been determined if the impairment loss had not been recorded at the reversal date. The reversal amount is recognized in net income for the year. 2.21.1.4 Derecognition of Financial Assets The Company derecognizes a financial asset when the contractual rights to the cash flows of such assets expire or when it transfers the financial asset and, therefore, all the risks and benefits inherent to the ownership of the financial asset are transferred to another entity. If the Company retains substantially all the risks and benefits inherent to the ownership of the transferred asset, it will continue to recognize it and will recognize a liability for the amounts received. 2.21.2 Financial Liabilities Financial liabilities, except for derivatives, are valued at amortized cost using the effective interest rate method. 2.21.2.1 Debt Debt is initially valued at fair value net of the transaction costs incurred, and subsequently valued at amortized cost using the effective interest rate method. Any difference between the initial value net of the transaction costs and the settlement value is recognized in the income statement over the term of the loan using the effective interest rate method. Interest expense has been allocated to "Financial Costs" in the consolidated statement of comprehensive income, except for the portion allocated to the cost of works under construction recorded under "Property, Plant and Equipment". Debt maturing within the 12 months preceding the closing date is classified as current and those maturing within the 12 months following the closing date are classified as non-current. Loans in foreign currency have been valued as mentioned above, at the exchange rates prevailing as of each year-end. Foreign exchange differences were charged to net income for each year. 2.21.2.2 Trade Payables and Other Trade payables with fixed or determinable payments not traded in an active market are classified as "Trade Payables and Other". Trade Payables and Other are initially measured at fair value, and subsequently measured at amortized cost using the effective interest rate method. Interest expense is recognized using the effective interest rate method, except for short-term balances for which the recognition of interest is not significant. Trade Payables and Other are classified as current, except for the maturities exceeding 12 months from the closing date. Trade payables in foreign currency have been valued as mentioned above, at the exchange rates prevailing as of each year end. Foreign exchange differences were charged to net income for each year. 2.21.2.3 Derecognition of Financial Liabilities An entity shall derecognize a financial liability (or part of it) when it has been extinguished, i.e., when the obligation specified in the corresponding agreement is discharged, cancelled or expires. 2.21.3 Derivatives and Hedge Accounting The Company executes certain financial instruments to manage its exposure to interest rate and exchange risks, including foreign currency hedges, interest rate swaps and currency swaps. Derivatives are initially recognized at fair value at the date of execution of the related contract and subsequently measured at fair value at the end of the reporting year. The resulting gain or loss is immediately recognized in net income unless the derivate is designated as a hedging instrument, in which case the timing for its recognition will depend on the nature of the hedging relationship. The Company uses certain derivatives to hedge the fair value of its recognized liabilities (fair value hedge). The Company documents at the beginning of the transaction the existing relationship between the hedging instruments and the hedged items, as well as its objectives to manage risk and the strategy to carry out hedge transactions. The Company also documents its assessment, both at the beginning and on an ongoing basis, of the high effectiveness of its hedging transactions to offset the changes in the fair value of the hedged items. The fair value of hedging derivatives is fully classified as a non-current asset or liability if the hedged item matures in more than 12 months, and as a current asset or liability if the hedged item matures within 12 months. Fair Value Hedge Changes in the fair value of derivatives designated and classified as fair value hedges are charged to net income, together with any change in the fair value of a hedged liability attributable to the hedged risk. The Company only applies fair value hedge accounting to cover the exchange rate fluctuations of the liabilities it holds in foreign currency. The gain or loss relating to the effective portion of foreign currency forward contracts is charged to net income under Financial Costs. The loss or gain related to the ineffective portion, if any, is charged to net income under Other Income and Expense, net. Changes in the fair value of the Company's hedged liabilities denominated in foreign currency, attributable to the risk detailed above, are charged to net income under Financial Costs. 2.21.4 Refinancing of Indebtedness Liabilities arising from the restructuring of financial debts have been initially valued at fair value and will be subsequently measured at amortized cost using the effective interest rate method. 2.22 Other Liabilities Advances from customers involving obligations to deliver assets that have not yet been produced have been valued at the higher of the amounts received or the share in the estimated value of the related assets. The other liabilities have been valued at nominal value. 2.23 Assets and liabilities held for sale Non-current assets and liabilities (or disposal groups) are classified as assets and liabilities held for sale where their value will be mostly recovered through the sale thereof, to the extent such sale is highly likely to occur. These assets and liabilities are valued at the lower of book value and fair value less cost of sales. 2.24 Consolidated Statement of Cash Flows For the purposes of preparing the consolidated statement of cash flows, the item "Cash and Cash Equivalents" includes cash and bank balances, certain high liquidity short-term investments (with original maturities shorter than 90 days). Bank overdrafts payable on demand, if any, are deducted to the extent they are part of the Company's cash management. Bank overdrafts are classified as "Debt" in the consolidated balance sheet. Cash and cash equivalents at each year-end, as disclosed in the consolidated statement of cash flows, may be reconciled against the items related to the balance sheet as follows:
In the years ended December 31, 2013 and 2012, the following significant transactions were carried out, which did not have an impact on cash and cash equivalents:
2.25 Distribution of Dividends The distribution of dividends to the Company's shareholders is recognized as a liability in the financial statements for the year in which the distribution of dividends is approved by the Shareholders' Meeting. NOTE 3 - ACCOUNTING ESTIMATES AND JUDGMENTS In applying the accounting policies described in Note 2, the Company has to make judgments and prepare accounting estimates of the value of the assets and liabilities which may not be otherwise obtained. The estimates and related assumptions are based on historical experience and other pertinent factors. Actual results may differ from these estimates. The underlying estimates and assumptions are continually reviewed. The effects of the reviews of accounting estimates are recognized for the year in which estimates are reviewed. These estimates basically refer to: Allowance for Bad Debts The Company calculates the allowance for bad debts for debt instruments that are not valued at fair value, taking into account the uncollectibility history, the opinion of its legal advisors, if any, and other circumstances known at the time of calculation. Impairment of Goodwill
]]></text></news-item>