<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DE5D-EE83-2BF4-ABED"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>JBS plant fined $98,750</title><source>The Courier-Journal (Louisville, Kentucky)</source><author>By, James Bruggers</author><text><![CDATA[Louisville officials have slapped the JBS pork-processing plant on Story Avenue with its biggest air pollution fine since at least 2003, a $98,750 penalty based on odor, record-keeping and permit violations.
The Louisville Metro Air Pollution Control District has offered to settle for $74,050 and possible "remedial measures or corrective action," district Executive Director Keith Talley wrote in a March 7 letter made public Thursday.
District records show the plant, known locally as Swift, has previously paid $89,900 in air-district fines since 2003, including $32,000 in 2011 and $35,500 in 2009.
In addition to odor violations, the company in the past has been cited for dozens of deficiencies in its risk-management planning involving the use of anhydrous ammonia, as The Courier-Journal reported Sunday in its Chemical Danger Zones special report.
MORE | Chemical danger zones blanket Louisville area.
The plant has also been involved in a long-running dispute with its neighbors over truck traffic, zoning issues, odors and chemical safety.
The latest fine was issued as JBS prepares to go back before the Metro Board of Zoning Adjustment on Monday for a continuing review of its request to modify its conditional-use permit, which allows it to operate a meatpacking plant, and the proposed penalty prompted new outrage.
"The alleged violations should come as no surprise to anyone who lives or works in any neighborhoods surrounding the JBS Swift slaughterhouse," said Butchertown Neighborhood Association President Andy Cornelius. "JBS Swift should be held accountable for refusing to follow the law and required to take all steps necessary to keep its animal slaughtering odors out of our homes, businesses and schools."
JBS spokesman Cameron Bruett said the company was reviewing the notice-of-violation letter and supporting documents.
"We will get a team together and review each of the complaints. We will look at our data and work with APCD to address any issues. We will use it as a means to hopefully improve performance."
Air district spokesman Tom Nord declined to answer questions about the enforcement action. But he provided 29 pages of incident-violation reports that cite permit record-keeping and reporting problems from 2009 through 2013 - and numerous odor violations in 2012 and 2013 related to its stock pen, trucks and other operations.
Among the alleged violations, the company failed to monitor and keep records of the operation of its odor-control equipment in each year from 2009 through 2013.
The records also show that inspectors found that the company was allowing too many pig trucks, as many as seven on at least one day last year, to crowd around the plant simultaneously. The odors in the neighborhood were sometimes described as "intense" by district inspectors.
Some of the violation reports say the company must submit a plan to control its livestock odors by March 28.
The main request Monday before the Metro Board of Zoning Adjustment is to add 162 square feet to its bleeding and stunning building for slaughtering hogs - after previous reviews dating back to August. JBS' request also includes adding a covered break area for employees, a fence along Story Avenue and an animal-unloading chute enclosure to help control odors.
Bruett said the company needs approval from the zoning board before it can enclose the unloading chute.
"We would really like to partner with the neighborhood and community," he said, adding that "unfortunately ... we have been blocked."
The Butchertown association has objected to any modifications to the permit, and the case has not yet been resolved.
Attorney Jon Salomon, who represents the association, said the Board of Zoning Adjustment can't approve modifications to the conditional use permit because JBS has failed to resolve other issues related to its nuisance uses, and hasn't obtained other permits required for its operations.
Moreover, the association contends the company's conditional use permit expired on Aug. 31, 2010, Salomon said.
Attorney Glenn Price, who represents JBS, has disagreed. With regard to the main request for the 162-square-foot addition, he has said it's needed to comply with government safety regulations for workers and to ensure humane treatment of hogs when they are rendered unconscious.
Reach reporter James Bruggers at (502) 582-4645 and on Twitter @jbruggers. Reporter Martha Elson contributed to this report. She can be reached at (502) 582-7061.
Zoning board meeting
8:30 a.m. Monday
Mayor's Gallery, fourth floor, Jefferson County Courthouse, 527 W. Jefferson St.
]]></text></news-item>