<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DEF1-AC8C-DA1E-E1C3"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Lessons from court veto #124of mega-project loan</title><source>The Nation (Thailand)</source><author>The Nation</author><text><![CDATA[Like Premier Yingluck and Federation of Thai Industries vice-chairman Kriengkrai Thiennukul, I rue the many months lost in getting started on infrastructure mega-projects. However, I applaud the court's verdict, because the veto was in accordance with the law and made sense. Rather, it was Yingluck's own lack of good governance that cost us this opportunity.
We haven't had a large infrastructure project for 15 years, and this despite Thai logistics costs running as high as 15.2 per cent of GDP, placing us at a major disadvantage vis-a-vis our competitors, where logistics are only 8-9 per cent of GDP. So an overhaul is badly needed. What should we learn from Yingluck's fiasco?
First, be transparent. Many projects were proposed without in-depth feasibility studies, even though they cost billions. Do we really need a state-of-the-art high-speed rail system when we cannot safely manage a creaky single-rail system? We should demand that Yingluck put all the studies on the Internet, where we taxpayers can see what we're getting.
Second, decentralise, and promote civil society and freedom of expression. Get the regions and professional associations involved and have them debate the pros and cons of mega-projects that would affect them.
Third, practise good governance (the Pheu Thai MP who used his colleagues' ID cards to cast votes for them should have been drummed out of the party – but has he?) We should ensure that the government doesn't seek to bypass checks and balances, such as parliamentary scrutiny, especially when polls show that Thailand has become more corrupt under Pheu Thai.
Fourth, we should practise political toleration and listen to the opposition both inside and outside Parliament. Rather than using its majority to railroad a bill through, Pheu Thai must show that what it proposes is better for the public than what the Democrats want. Make the politicians of all parties earn your vote every day.
Do the above and we'll have put former Prime Minister Anand Panyarachun's "7 Pillars of Sustainable Democracy" into action – and benefited the nation as a whole, rather than just vested interests.
Burin Kantabutra
Bangkok
A guide to #124Thai news speak
The caretaker Sor Por Sor has initiated a Por Por Chor into alleged evasion of Por Ngor Dor payable by Gor Por Por Sor members in outlying Tor Jor Wor. In another story, directors of the Tor Por Tor say they welcome a Por Por Chor into alleged rigging of the recent Gor Kor Tor.
The cast is as follows: Gor Kor Tor (election) Gor Por Por Sor (anti-government protesters) Sor Por Sor (deputy PM) Por Ngor Dor (tax) Por Por Chor (investigation) Tor Jor Wor (provincial area) Tor Por Tor (central bank).
The trial continues.
Guilt Gland
Bangkok
Tuk-tuk cartels#124 preying on tourists
Though many tuk-tuk drivers rely on tourists to make a living, most seem to have poor knowledge and communication skills, with no regulations requiring them to improve. A simple request to visit the local orphanage at a neighbouring village near our hotel in Khao Lak, Phang Nga, was met with "I don't know where" and "Must be far away". We showed the driver a simple map in Thai showing the orphanage was no more than 10 kilometre away. He said he didn't understand but offered to take us for Bt1,000. Of course we rejected that and opted to rent a car and drive ourselves.
If authorities cracked down on the cartels that control the tuk-tuks, perhaps drivers would not be able to wait around idly, seeking the one or two suckers they need to overcharge per day to make a living. Tuk-tuks should be about turnover and service. I wonder if the cartels give anything to locals in need and orphanages, which visitors like us have supported since the tsunami.
This happens to tourists every day in the region and yet the tuk-tuk cartels continue not to give a damn about their customers.
Stuart Davie
Australian tourist in Thailand
]]></text></news-item>