<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="DFE1-0AB3-2367-4753"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>The man who tried to prevent World War I; Edward House embarked on a quixotic mission in spring 2014 as Europe was gripped by 'militarism run stark mad'</title><source>The Toronto Star</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[On May 16, 1914, "Colonel" Edward House boarded the ocean liner Imperator in New York City. Thousands gathered at the docks to watch their loved ones set sail for Europe, but few of the passengers would have been on a mission as exciting as House's.
In his private journal, the Texan privately described the trip as the "great adventure." It was more like a quixotic mission. A keen student of international affairs, House was worried by what he had been reading in the newspapers and hearing in Washington, D.C. He believed turbulence in the Balkans was a threat to world peace, and so he took it upon himself to convince the Europeans to pull back from the "track of war," as he put it in his published journal, The Intimate Papers of Colonel House.
But House, 55, was no professional diplomat travelling with an entourage of clever State Department advisers and a stack of briefings. He wasn't even in the army: House had been made an honorary lieutenant colonel in 1892 after helping a Texas governor get re-elected.
He was simply a private American citizen, albeit a rich one, and his chief calling card was that President Thomas Woodrow Wilson was a close friend. House had supported Wilson during the 1913 election, which earned him a place in his inner circle as a trusted adviser.
"House was very close to Wilson, and Wilson, I think, was a liberal and a progressive and wanted to see alternative ways of settling disputes and wars," says Canadian historian Margaret MacMillan, author of The War That Ended Peace: The Road to 1914. "And he and his secretary of state at that time were keen on arbitration."
Although the American president had little interest in international politics, he was persuaded by House's idea that Germany and Britain should join the United States in a grand alliance, perhaps a council that would establish permanent peace among the Great Powers.
"Unless someone acting for you can bring about a different understanding, there is some day to be an awful cataclysm," House wrote in a letter to Wilson. "No one in Europe can do it. There is too much hatred, too many jealousies."
House believed he was the man for the job. The Houston-born millionaire was the son of a cotton plantation owner who had left him a huge fortune. His wealth hadn't shielded him from the horrors of the American Civil War, and the young House saw the murder of his neighbours and the pillaging of Texas.
Slim and well-dressed, the Cornell University-educated House was mild-mannered and listened carefully, giving the impression that he was sympathetic - qualities that would serve him well as he navigated the treacherous politics of the Great Powers.
This was an elite club to which America did not yet belong. Yet the U.S. was a rising power, accounting for 11 per cent of world trade and producing more iron and steel than Germany and Britain together. Its inventions and innovations - the Wright brothers built the first successful airplane in 1903 - were marvels for the entire world.
Young and optimistic, America may have been a colonial upstart as far as the Old World was concerned, but it was a superpower in the making and the Europeans knew it. Europe was divided into two camps, so the support of the United States in the event of war was important.
"The expansion of U.S. trade impressed everyone," says Jennifer Jenkins, a professor of history at the University of Toronto. "This is the coming world empire and it is how the Germans were looking at them."
House's first stop was Berlin. The embassy arranged a meeting with Kaiser Wilhelm II, the bellicose German emperor. The first practical step in House's ambitious plan for world peace was a U.S.-brokered agreement between Britain and Germany to limit the size of their navies. The two nations had been engaged in an expensive naval arms race for many years.
The Germans gave House a tour of a military airfield and introduced him to a fearless young aviator named Anthony Fokker, who demonstrated his skills in one of the newfangled airborne machines. A guide explained that 36 pilots had been killed on the airfield. "I was relieved when he landed unharmed," House wrote. Fokker was Dutch but had come to Germany at the request of its government to build his airplanes there.
House met the powerful Prussian officers the Kaiser had surrounded himself with. There was Alfred von Tirpitz, the frightening naval minister with a long, forked beard who ranted about the British in a way that "almost amounted to hatred," House noted. And there was Gen. Helmuth von Moltke, the war-mongering, Faust-quoting chief of general staff.
House wrote his impressions in a letter to Wilson: "The situation is extraordinary," he said. "It is militarism run stark mad."
The friendship between Russia, Britain and France would mean a war against Germany by 1916 or 1917. On the other hand, Russia, Britain and France joined forces partly because they believed Germany had nefarious designs.
The idea of war was gaining momentum. Russia had increased the speed of its mobilization and had the largest army at 1.4 million soldiers, compared with Germany's 890,000. In Britain, 40 per cent of government spending went to defence. The biggest company in Europe was Krupp, the German arms manufacturer. Rivals such as Skoda and Vickers-Maxim followed close on Krupp's heels.
"In the new industrial age Europe's business had been the business of preparing for war," writes historian David Fromkin in Europe's Last Summer.
There were other new technologies: poison gas, tanks, airships called Zeppelins invented by a German and, most terrifying of all, howitzers and whistling mortar shells, which pierced the air and obliterated whatever they struck.
The buildup of Europe's armed forces was intended to bring security but undermined the chance for peace, observes Fromkin. "The unrelenting competitiveness achieved the opposite of what was intended," he writes.
What the well-intentioned House did not know was just how dangerous Moltke was. He had modified the notorious German war strategy, known as the Schlieffen Plan, to lay out a blueprint for invading France through neutral Belgian territory. Once the French were dealt with, Germany would turn its attention to the more difficult and larger Russia on its eastern flank. Trampling through Belgium to get to Paris would be a violation of an international treaty guaranteeing Belgium's neutrality, and Moltke would have been aware that such a violation could provoke Britain to get involved in a war.
At last, the big day of House's meeting with Kaiser Wilhelm came. The American was invited to lunch at Potsdam on June 1 to watch the annual "White Roll Feast." The Kaiser, so-called supreme warlord, sat at a table with ordinary soldiers eating white bread, a luxury to fighting men used to brown rolls.
House and his companion, American ambassador to Germany James Gerard, arrived in formal black tuxedos, looking incongruous among the soldiers. "Like two black crows," the Kaiser guffawed with his typical lack of tact.
After the ceremony, lunch was announced and House was ushered into the Shell Hall, the walls of which were plastered with seashells. "Probably the ugliest room in the world," Gerard muttered.
There was some confusion about House's title, and he spent most of the meal explaining to the bemused imperial family and military top brass that he was not actually in the U.S. army.
But the muddle may have been to the U.S. president's advantage since Wilson had other motives besides world peace, says Jenkins. The Germans were doing a lot of business in America's backyard, Latin America, and Wilson was worried about German intentions.
The Germans had developed a martial theme for House's visit, believing he was a military representative of the American leader. "The Germans place House at the dinners with all the military brass, but maybe this is appropriate because Wilson gets a full view of the German military," says the U of T's Jenkins.
After lunch, House was informed that the Kaiser was ready to see him on the terrace. "He has what is to me a disagreeable habit of bringing his face very close when he talks most earnestly," House wrote.
Wilhelm told him that the "Latin" and "Slav" races were "barbaric" and that Germany wanted peace but was menaced on every side. "The bayonets of Europe were directed at her," he claimed.
House suggested that if England, Germany and the U.S. "stood together, world peace could be maintained." Perhaps the great powers could give credit to poorer countries to help them develop, House went on to say. The Kaiser made positive noises, House wrote in his journal.
On the issue of the Anglo-German naval race, Wilhelm told him he needed a large navy, and that when the current program ended he would stop. By 1914, Britain had 20 super battleships, the dreadnoughts, compared with Germany's 13. The race had proven ruinously expensive, and the two nations were bitterly hostile toward each other.
House left Berlin feeling upbeat. "I am glad to tell you that I have been as successful as anticipated," he wrote to Wilson.
Next stop: Paris. But the French were interested only in the Caillaux affair, a sex-and-politics scandal involving a senior cabinet minister. Although the French were worried about the Germans, there was little talk of a war with the neighbouring country, House observed. "France I am sure will welcome our offers of peace," he wrote to Wilson.
He arrived in London on June 9 and found Edwardian England to be in the full blossom of the summer social season. Everyone wanted to talk about the races at Ascot or garden parties. On June 17, House met foreign secretary Sir Edward Grey for lunch. Grey, who was going blind, hated politics and preferred quiet weekends watching birds on his country estate up north. This was no warrior.
House reasoned that international affairs could be worked out the same way as private disputes, and that if "the principals knew of the facts, what appeared to be a difficult situation could be easy of solution."
He told Grey about his meeting with the Kaiser. "I thought the Kaiser himself and most of his immediate advisors did not want war because they wished Germany to expand commercially and grow in wealth, but the army was militaristic and aggressive and ready for war at any time," he told the British leader. France was in no mood to fight, he added.
Grey, who had just returned from accompanying King George V on his state visit to Paris, listened carefully to his American guest.
In the last week of June, House met Grey's private secretary, Sir William Tyrell, at his country estate. In front of a crackling log fire, he set out his idea for an Anglo-German-American peace alliance. House was now waiting for Grey to send a message or some kind of signal to Wilhelm.
Little did House realize, an event was about to take place that would not only derail his diplomatic efforts, it would change the course of Western history irrevocably.
Read the full story in Spring 1914. The ebook is available through the Star's weekly electronic book program,
Star Dispatches. Go to stardispatches.com and subscribe for $1/week. Single copies are available for $2.99 at stardispatches.com/starstore and stardispatches.com/itunes. Also available at Star Dispatches, The Winter Before the War. The cafés were busy, the intermarried aristocracies' social season was in full if apprehensive swing. An archduke preened, his wife fretted, and Gavrilo Princip sat freezing.
]]></text></news-item>