<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E01B-0CC6-A33B-BE10"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>PUBLIC NOTICES </title><source>Patriot News (Harrisburg, Pennsylvania)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Patriot-News: All notices must be received 2 business days prior to publication. Community weeklies: Monday at 5 p.m. for following issue. Lengthier notices may require additional notification. For additional information regarding placement for Public Notice Ad Contact: 717-255-8119 Fax 717-257-4726 email legals@pennlive.com
YOUR RIGHT TO KNOW and be informed of the functions of your government are embodied in legal notices. In that self-government charges all citizens to be informed, this newspaper urges every citizen to read and study these notices. We strongly advise those citizens seeking further information, to exercise their right of access to public records and public meetings. The Patriot-News Public Notices can also be read on PennLive.com and publicnoticepa.com
Meeting Notices
LEGAL NOTICE NOTICE OF MEETING NOTICE IS HEREBY GIVEN that on Thursday, March 13, 2014, the Borough Council of the Borough of Hummelstown, Dauphin County, Pennsylvania (the "Borough") enacted an Ordinance, which, among other things, authorized the incurring of non electoral debt in the aggregate principal amount of $6, 335,000 through the issuance of its General Obligation Bonds, Series of 2014 (the "Bonds") and awarded the Bonds to RBC Capital Markets, LLC. A summary of the Ordinance was advertised on March 4, 2014, and the proposed text has been available for examination at the office of the undersigned.
The Bonds were purchased at a bid price of $6, 335,000, less net original issue discount of $73, 935.10, for a total purchase price of $6, 261,064.90, and bear interest ranging from 0.230% to 4.250%. Original issue discount on Bonds maturing on November 15 of the years 2021 through 2029 and 2034 through 2043 increases the effective yield ranging from 2.100% to 4.430%. Original issue premium on Bonds maturing on November 15 of the years 2016 through 2020 and 2031 decreases the effective yield ranging from 0.500% to 3.700%.
Insertions and amendments were made throughout the Ordinance, as follows: The aggregate principal amount of the Bonds, as reflected throughout the Ordinance, was inserted to reflect $6, 335,000. Section 11 of the Ordinance was completed to reflect the winning bidder, the calculation of the total purchase price, original issue premium and range of interest rates for the Bonds. The maturity schedule as reflected on Exhibit B was completed. Exhibit C was completed to reflect the annual amounts appropriated to the sinking fund as to the Bonds.
No other amendments or insertions were made to the Ordinance on final enactment.
Copies of the full text of the proposed Ordinance may be examined by any citizen of the Borough at Borough Office, 136 South Hanover Street, Hummelstown, Pennsylvania, on regular business days from 8:00 a.m. to 4:30 p.m., prevailing time.
The proceedings for the incurring of the debt referred to above will be filed with the Pennsylvania Department of Community and Economic Development, Harrisburg, Pennsylvania (the "Department"), on or after March 17, 2014. Under the terms of the Pennsylvania Local Government Unit Debt Act, 53 Pa. Cons. Stat. 8001 et seq, as amended, the time for filing any complaint with the Department asserting the invalidity of the proceedings or any part thereof, is limited and attention is direct to the specific requirements of the Act.
BOROUGH OF HUMMELSTOWN BY ORDER OF: MICHAEL J. O'KEEFE, SECRETARY McNees Wallace & Nurick LLC, Bond Counsel Public Hearing Notice Cumberland-Dauphin-Harrisburg Transit Authority -Capital Area Transit Public Notice Fixed Route Service Change Capital Area Transit is planning a service change in relation to the closure of the Mulberry Street Bridge in the Harrisburg area. The specific change to be discussed will include service elimination as well as new service implementation and is as follows: -Elimination of route 15 -New service implementation (Route 17) A full copy of the proposed route and schedule for the Route 17 can be reviewed on CAT's web page located at www.cattransit.com. In addition, CAT's Title VI Equity Analysis will be available for review prior to the public hearing as advertised below.
Written comments on the addition of the Carlisle Circulator should be addressed to Capital Area Transit, Attention Robert Philbin, Marketing/Service Planning and Public Information Officer, 901 N. Cameron Street, Harrisburg, PA, 17101, or by email at rphilbin@cattransit.com and must be received by 4:00 pm March 26, 2014.
Capital Area Transit will hold a public Hearing on the addition of the new service on March 27, 2014, at 12:00 noon in the CAT Board Room located on the 2nd floor at 901 N. Cameron Street, Harrisburg, PA, 17101.
Public Hearing Notice Cumberland-Dauphin-Harrisburg Transit Authority -Capital Area Transit Public Notice Fixed Route Service Expansion -Carlisle Circulator Capital Area Transit is in the process of implementing new service in the Carlisle area called the Carlisle Circulator and is seeking public comments and suggestions on the proposed service. A full copy of the Carlisle Circulator study and implementation plan and the proposed routes and schedules can be reviewed on CAT's web page located at www.cattransit.com. In addition, CAT's Title VI Equity Analysis will be available for review prior to the public hearing as advertised below.
Written comments on the addition of the Carlisle Circulator should be addressed to Capital Area Transit, Attention Robert Philbin, Marketing/Service Planning and Public Information Officer, 901 N. Cameron Street, Harrisburg, PA, 17101, or by email at rphilbin@cattransit.com and must be received by 4:00 pm March 26, 2014.
Capital Area Transit will hold a public Hearing on the addition of the new service on March 27, 2014, at 12:00 noon in the CAT Board Room located on the 2nd floor at 901 N. Cameron Street, Harrisburg, PA, 17101. SECOND NOTICE Notice is hereby given that, at a regularly scheduled and duly advertised meeting held on February 27, 2014, the Hampden Township Board of Commissioners approved the Preliminary/Final Land Development Plan for Shepherd's Crossing, PC File #13-09-02, contingent upon a number of conditions. The Board also approved a waiver from the Hampden Township Land Development Ordinance with respect to submission of a Preliminary Plan. The Township issued a written decision in the form of an approval letter dated March 6, 2014 related to both approvals.
The Applicant of the Plan is Monarch Development Group, LLC, the equitable owner of property located at 201 Lambs Gap Road, Mechanicsburg, PA, which is further identified as Cumberland County Tax Parcel 10-19-1606-217.
Members of the general public may review and obtain a copy of the approval letter at the Hampden Township building, located at 230 South Sporting Hill Road, Mechanicsburg, PA 17050.
This publication is intended to provide notification of the decision. Any person claiming a right to challenge the validity of the decision must bring legal action within 30 days of the publication of the second notice.
THE SOUTH MIDDLETON SCHOOL DISTRICT 4 Forge Road Boiling Springs, PA 17007 The Policy Committee meeting of the South Middleton School District Board of School Directors scheduled for Monday, March 17, 2014 at 6:00 p.m. has been canceled.
Richard R. Vensel Business Manager/Board Secretary Miscellaneous Notices CAPITAL SELF STORAGE, in order to satisfy its statutory lien pursuant to 73 P.S. et seq., will sell at PUBLIC SALE all the personal property stored in its facilities, placed by: 2200 Vine Street, Middletown A003 Jeffrey Nester B023 Richard A Pierce D019 Betsy A Wirfel E062 David M Bixler F040 Luke Lawson F309 Harry Mohnshine 3861 Derry Street, Harrisburg B013 Scott E Carroll C043 James Chambers C038 Jeanne Pettis D017 Joshua P Forney D083 Mary A Nye F020 Leon Evans Lewis 1851 Arsenal Blvd, Harrisburg A149 Pride of the Neighborhood A196 Keisha Evans A239 Sheree L Stump A251 Shaneka Wright A272 Alesia R Hartford A275 Stacey L Wallace A276 Sheila Wright B107 Evelyn M DeArmond B155 Takia Easter B202 Jacqueline M Brown B218 Karen Miller B308 Russell Ryan D003 Nakia L Young D013 Noeli Y Minter D028 Khalif Duncan D038 Michael Graham D050 Carlos Velazquez 10 Prospect Dr, Enola C015 Britany Ziegenhagen B051 Denise George D042 Tracee Carter F121 Emma Abate G026 Timothy A Clark 5160 E Trindle Rd, Mechanicsburg A017 Natalie Sciotti F039 Brian Gemberling F024 David J Fisher G004 Jonathan L Mansch G011 Jonathan L Mansch Public Sale is scheduled for Wednesday, March 26, 2014 at 9:00A.M. at 2200 Vine Street, Middletown, PA; Continuous Caravan to 3861 Derry St, Harrisburg, Pa; continuous caravan to 1851 Arsenal Blvd, Harrisburg, PA; continuous caravan to 10 Prospect Dr, Enola, PA; continuous caravan to 5160 E Trindle Rd, Mechanicsburg, PA. Since this is a continuous caravan sale, the sale begins at 9 am and will continue at said properties upon arrival of agent.
Rich Coccodrilli PA Licensed Auctioneer AU005571 as agent for Capital Self Storage. Owner reserves the right to bid at Public Sale, reject any or all bids, and cancel or adjourn the sale. A Bidder's cash security deposit may be required. To resolve this claim, call Christi Collins@Capital Self Storage 717-932-1333.
NOTICE OF PUBLIC SALE OF PERSONAL PROPERTY Notice is hereby given that the undersigned will sell, to satisfy lien of the owner, at public sale by competitive bidding on 19 March 2014 at 4:30 pm at the Extra Space Storage facility located at:5630 Linglestown Rd. Harrisburg, PA 17112 717-657-2124 The personal goods stored therein by the following may include, but are not limited to general household, furniture, boxes, clothes, and appliances.
3412-Edward Chambers 3307-Amy Harbold Purchases must be made with cash only and paid at the time of sale. All goods are sold as is and must be removed at the time of purchase. Extra Space Storage reserves the right to refuse any bid. Sale is subject to adjournment. STORAGE WORLD, LLC, in order to satisfy its statutory lien pursuant to 73 P.S. ss1901 et seq., will sell at PUBLIC SALE all the personal property stored in its facility, placed by: #154 Theodore Wells #353 Nichol M. Stout #507 Bobby V. Randolph, Jr. #531 Korin Dietz #541 Ambreen A. Esmail At 12:00 PM, Thursday March 20, 2014, by competitive bidding, at Storage World of Valley Green, 925 Old Trail Road, Etters, PA. Potential bidders must arrive and register by 11:45 am. They must provide a valid driver's license, and also a $100.00 cash deposit. Bidding is for the entire unit contents. The auction is absolute. Questions, call 717-938-9000. Owner reserves the right to bid at Public Sale, reject any or all bids, and cancel or adjourn the sale. Proposals & Bids INVITATION TO BID Sealed bids will be received online by The Harrisburg Authority via the PennBid Program (www.PennBid.net), until 2pm., Friday, March 28 at which time they will be publicly opened and read immediately thereafter, for: PROJECT NUMBER 2014-002 -6V LITHIUM NON RECHARGEABLE BATTERY Bid security is being waived. Copies of the Project Documents are available at no cost at www.PennBid.net. All questions and/or inquiries about the meaning or intent of the Bidding Documents are to be submitted via the Questions Tab in PennBid. Telephone and email inquiries will not be accepted.
The Harrisburg Authority reserves the right to reject any or all bids and also reserves the right to waive irregularities in any bids or proposals.
The Harrisburg Authority is committed to providing employment opportunity in all aspects of employment without regard to race, color, religion, gender, sexual preference/orientation, national origin, citizenship, age or physical/mental disability.
THE HARRISBURG AUTHORITY 212 Locust Street, Suite 302 Harrisburg, PA 17101-7107 http://www.hbgauthority.com
STATE-OWNED REAL ESTATE FOR SALE in the Borough of Carlisle, PA. The PA Department of General Services will accept bids for the purchase of 2.38-acres + of land and building formerly known as the Cumberland County PennDOT Maintenance Facility located at 540 W. North Street, Borough of Carlisle, Cumberland County. Bids are due Thursday, June 5, 2014. Interested parties wishing to receive a copy of Solicitation #94568 should view the Department of General Services' website at www.dgs.state.pa.us or call Lisa Kettering at (717) 787-1321. INVITATION TO BID Sealed bids will be received by Camp Hill School District until 12:00pm March 25, 2014, for a roofing project at the Hoover Elementary School. All bids to be signed, sealed, and properly identified by envelope marked "Sealed Bid/Hoover Elementary School Roofing Project," and delivered to: Camp Hill School District, Attn: Kerry Chippo (Sealed Bid), 2627 Chestnut Street, Camp Hill, PA 17011.
A mandatory pre-bid meeting will be held at 3:30 pm on Monday, March 17, 2014 at the Hoover Elementary School, 420 S 24th Street, Camp Hill, PA 17011.
When available, a complete set of bidding documents may be obtained electronically from Camp Hill School District, 2627 Chestnut Street, Camp Hill, PA 17011. 717-901-2400 x2407.
Camp Hill School District reserves the right to reject any or all bids and waive, at its discretion, any or all irregularities, mistakes, omissions or informalities of a bid which the District deems in its best interest.
]]></text></news-item>