<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E19E-AC10-127B-A35F"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Bearded man, 53, who may be 'SERIAL KILLER' responsible for three deaths in Alexandra, Virginia is being questioned by police after being arrested on a gun charge</title><source>MailOnline</source><author>ASHLEY COLLMAN and ALEXANDRA KLAUSNER</author><text><![CDATA[Police are questioning Charles S. Severance, 53, about his possible relationship to the Alexandria murdersSeverence was arrested on a gun charge on ThursdaySeverance has run for mayor twice and for congress oncePolice believe the February murder of Ruthanne Lodato, 59, is connected to two other unsolved slayings in Alexandria, VirginaThe prominent community member is the third person to die in eerily similar circumstances within two miles of each other's homesRonald Kirby, 69, was gunned down in November and in December 2003, sheriff's wife Nancy Dunning was also killed inside her homePolice said that they had discovered similar bullet fragments in all three murdersThe three victims were killed at the same time of day after presenting themselves at the front door of their homes
A man was arrested on Thursday who may be the dangerous 'serial killer' on the loose in Alexandra, Virginia.
Police are questioning Charles S. Severance, 53, about his possible relationship to the murders Ruthanne Lodato who died last month, Ron Kirby who died in November, and, Nancy Dunning who was murdered in 2003.
Severance was arrested as a fugitive on  a weapons charge at 2 p.m on Thursday at the Ohio County Library in Wheeling, Virginia.
Severance was wanted for possession of a firearm by a felon in Loudon County, Virginia on March 6.
A scraggly and bearded severance ran away from the authorities and fled to West Virgina, said the Ohio County police department.
NBC Justice Correspondent Pete Williams reported that Severance's convictions in the past were related to a weapons charge.
He spent 10 days in jail in 1997 on a gun charge and in 2005 he had admitted to carrying a concealed weapon which is illegal in Virginia.
In Virginia, those who've been convicted of a felony may not possess a gun.
Severance is being questioned about his ties to the deaths of three Virginia community members over a span of 10 years, not just his weapons possessions. His bearded appearance matches a police sketch of the man police think may be responsible for the killings.
Two of these deaths occurred within a span of four months.
NBC reports that oddly enough, Severance ran for mayor in Virginia twice in 1996 and 2000 and he once ran for congress against Jim Moran in 1996. He got a few hundred votes back then.
Northern Virginia Bureau Chief Julie Carey had a few curious encounters with Severance when he was running for office.
'What made him so identifiable in Old Town and at debates is that he would often wear, like, a blanket over his shoulders. He did not look like the typical candidate,' she said.
She also said that Severance would often rant during speeches.
Residents in the wealthy Washington D.C. suburb of Alexandria warned a week ago that a serial killer may be on the loose.
The February shooting death of Ruthanne Lodato is being investigating in connection with two other unsolved murders that took place in similar circumstances just blocks from each other, police announced about a week ago.
Alexandria Police Chief Earl Cook said at a press conference that they believe Lodato's killer may be the same man suspected of killing Nancy Dunning in December 2003 and Ronald Kirby last November.
Upon studying ballistics in the three murders, police identified similarities in bullet fragments, but Cook wouldn't say for certain whether the same weapon was used in all three shootings.
'The cases appear to be linked, but until we have evidence to point to only one suspect, we investigate all possibilities,' Cook said.
Lodato, a married mother-of-three, was killed February 6 after a man knocked on her door at 11:30am and opened fire on her and a nurse caring for her mother.
Lodato was rushed to the ER in a critical condition but was later pronounced dead and the caregiver who gave police a description of the man who shot her in the arm survived.
All three murders took place at the same time of day after the victims presented themselves at the front door.
The victims were also well-respected in their DC community. Lodato was a well-known music teacher, Kirby was a respected transportation planner and Dunning was a real estate agent who was married to then-Sheriff James Dunning.
Sheriff Dunning was never ruled out as a suspect in his wife's murder, but died in 2012.
Lodato was answering the door when she was shot, but Cook wouldn't say whether that was the same case in the other two shootings.
Police are currently looking for an older, while man with gray hair and a full beard in connection to the homicides. Severance, who fits the description, is curretly being probed by police.
No motive has been established for any of the killings, which police fear may spark 'hysteria' in the community.
Cook said that residents should be vigilant and not answer their door for strangers, but not to overreact.
'I'm hoping it doesn't create any type of hysteria,' he said.
So far, residents have taken the warning relatively well.
Pam Beard, who lived across the street from Nancy Dunning when she was shot in 2003, says she's been locking her door in the ten years since.
'I just couldn't believe it,' Ms Beard told WJLA. 'You hear the cliche "it doesn't happen in this neighborhood." Well, it does.'
Fellow neighbor Judy Miller she says she's not going to let the latest warning impact her life too much.
'I wouldn't let anything change the way I live. I am not going to live in fear and I think anyone who does shouldn't,' Ms Miller said.
Police find Lodato's death strikingly similar to two other unsolved murders in the neighborhood.
In November last year, 69-year-old Ronald Kirby was shot inside his home, less than one mile from Lodato's house and to date police have not arrested anyone in connection with that murder.
And in 2003, real estate agent Nancy Dunning and the wife of now deceased Sheriff Jim Dunning was killed inside her Del Ray home - less than two miles from where Lodato lived.
Family members of Kirby and Dunning told the Washington Post that they were stunned by the killings and were struck by the fact that all three seemed to be 'random'.
Liz Dunning, whose mother Nancy was shot inside her home, said that so far she had not been informed by police of any possible link between her death and Lodato's or Kirby's.
'It's heartbreaking there is another family that is experiencing this type of loss without answers,' said Dunning, 36.
Joan Gartlan, who was a friend of Lodato said that she had on idea who would hurt Lodato, who had three daughters with her husband Norman, Lucia Lodato, 32; Gina Lodato Pelusi, 29; and Carmen Lodato, 20.
'We're all devastated,' Gartlan said. 'She was really kind of the glue that held everything together.'
In December, Ronald Kirby's wife Anne Haynes, 67, said that she was still devastated by the loss of her husband - and that they were planning on taking a tour to the Antarctic before he was shot dead inside their home.
'I've lost the love of my life. I've lost my life's companion,' said Haynes, 67 at the time to the Washington Post.
'I have my memories, but that's all I have. I loved Ron, right down to his little feet.'
Father-of-two Kirby, was shot between between 11am and 12:30pm on November 11 and was found by his son on the floor of his home, holding his glasses, having been shot multiple times with an automatic weapon.
Nothing was stolen and Haynes said her husband had no enemies.
And more than a decade on from the death of Nancy Dunning, law enforcement are seeing scary similarities between her death, Lodato's and Kirby's.
The real estate agent who was married to then Sheriff James Dunning, was known as the 'Queen of Del Ray' for her efforts in organizing arts festivals and other events within the community.
On December 5, 2003, she failed to meet her husband and son for a lunch date and when they returned home, they discovered her on the floor, shot dead.
After her death, Sheriff Dunning moved to Souh Carolina and died in 2012 - but at the time of her death, police investigators said that she was targeted by someone she knew.
So far, Severance is one of the main suspects in the case.
]]></text></news-item>