<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E1A6-11F0-A2A6-85FB"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>The burden of toxic cleanup</title><source>Chapel Hill Herald (Durham, N.C.)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[This editorial appeared in The Virginian-Pilot in Norfolk, Va.
Duke Energy CEO Lynn Good received a Businesswoman of the Year award from a North Carolina college last weekend. It may be the last honor the company sees for a while.
After the awards ceremony, Good told a Charlotte Observer reporter that her company expects customers to pay the costs of closing down ponds like the one that dumped 87,000 tons of coal ash and spilled 27 million gallons of contaminated water into the Dan River last month.
The sludge, which includes arsenic, lead and other toxins, coated 70 miles of the river. The spill occurred just south of the Virginia line at Danville ? and within 10 miles of the Kerr Reservoir, which feeds into Lake Gaston, a drinking-water supply for more than a million people in South Hampton Roads.
The Dan River fiasco has been a public relations ? and public accountability ? nightmare for Duke. The company waited a day to tell people about the spill, downplayed the damage and took six days to seal off the pipe causing the problem.
And all of this was after the Environmental Protection Agency had been pushing Duke to clean up leaky coal ash dumps. The utility had balked.
Federal prosecutors are now investigating whether state officials improperly meddled in the push for a cleanup effort.
After briefing Gov. Pat McCrory ? who worked for Duke Energy for nearly 30 years and owns stock in the company ? about the environmental threat last year, state officials negotiated a paltry $99,111 settlement with the company over leaks at two power plants.
Now Duke Energy faces the prospect of closing up to 32 ash ponds at 14 power plants in North Carolina.
Duke's CEO said the company and its shareholders will pay for cleaning up last month's spill.
But the cost of closing the other ash ponds, Good told the Observer, is expected to be passed along to customers. N.C. Attorney General Roy Cooper said he'll fight that plan before the state's utilities commission.
Virginia officials, meanwhile, said they're monitoring the damage from the spill. David Paylor, director of Virginia's Department of Environmental Quality, said the company would be held "fully accountable."
Duke Energy's customers have benefited from the electricity generated by those coal-fired plants. But they weren't the ones who balked at dealing with the disasters-in-waiting at the coal ponds ? or who were enriched by taking cheap but environmentally risky shortcuts.
Dumping the costs on customers now ? rather than have shareholders like McCrory pay for it ? is hardly an honorable choice.
]]></text></news-item>