<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E1FC-ACC5-A47D-021E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Bradley Arant Boult Cummings Attorneys Summer Austin Davis and J. Thomas Richie Named B-Metro Magazine 2014 Rising Stars</title><source>News Bites - Private Companies</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[
Bradley Arant Boult Cummings LLP is pleased to announce that attorneys Summer Austin Davis and J. Thomas Richie have been named by B-Metro Magazine as 2014 "Rising Stars/Attorneys of Note," a distinction that recognizes the region's next generation of legal leaders.
Each year B-Metro names a new class of Rising Stars, who are elected by members of the legal community. This year's class is featured in the March 2014 issue of the Birmingham monthly lifestyle publication. B-Metro's 2014 Rising Stars were honored at the magazine's March 13 reception at the Premier Group Hangar in Birmingham.
"We congratulate Summer and Thomas for this well-deserved recognition of their achievements so early in their careers," said Firm Chairman Beau Grenier.
Ms. Davis is a member of the firm's Litigation Practice Group and focuses her practice on products liability and other complex litigation. Her practice involves developing and implementing litigation strategy in a variety of labor and employment matters, including claims of discrimination and retaliation under Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964, Section 1981, the Americans with Disabilities Act, and the Age Discrimination in Employment Act. Ms. Davis earned her J.D., cum laude, from Cumberland School of Law at Samford University. She also has a B.S. from the University of Alabama at Birmingham and attended the Jefferson County International Baccalaureate School.
Also a member of the firm's Litigation Practice Group, Mr. Richie represents clients in procedurally complex civil litigation, both in trial and appellate courts throughout Alabama and across the country. He has litigated a broad range of cases, from class actions to municipal tax disputes, to the Chapter 9 bankruptcy case of Jefferson County, Alabama. He earned his J.D., summa cum laude, from Cumberland School of Law at Samford University. He also holds a B.S.B.A., summa cum laude, and a B.A., summa cum laude, both from Samford University.
click http://www.babc.com/bradley-arant-boult-cummings-attorneys-summer-austin-davis-and-j-thomas-richie-named-ib-metro-magazinei-2014-rising-stars-03-13-2014/#.UyMel86YIwo
BUSINESS NEWS ROUND UP
24 February 2014: Bradley Arant Boult Cummings Partner J. David Stewart Named Among Birmingham Business Journal's 2014 Top 40 Under 40
Bradley Arant Boult Cummings LLP is pleased to announce that partner J. David Stewart, chair of the firm's Governmental Affairs Practice Group, has been named by Birmingham Business Journal as one of its 2014 Top 40 Under 40, which recognizes talented up-and-comers in the Birmingham business community. "We are proud of David's professional achievements and successes and we congratulate him on this well-deserved recognition," said Firm Chairman Beau Grenier.
click http://www.babc.com/bradley-arant-boult-cummings-partner-j-david-stewart-named-among-ibirmingham-business-journalsi-2014-top-40-under-40-02-24-2014/#.Uw1sJdJDvp8
21 February 2014: Bradley Arant Boult Cummings Partner David G. Hymer Elected to American Board of Trial Advocates
Bradley Arant Boult Cummings LLP is pleased to announce that partner David G. Hymer has been elected to the American Board of Trial Advocates (ABOTA), a national association of trial lawyers and judges dedicated to the preservation and promotion of the constitutional right to a civil jury trial. "We congratulate David on his election to the American Board of Trial Advocates," said Firm Chairman Beau Grenier.
click http://www.babc.com/bradley-arant-boult-cummings-partner-david-g-hymer-elected-to-american-board-of-trial-advocates-02-21-2014/#.Uwfl39JDvp8
18 February 2014: Bradley Arant Boult Cummings Secures Appellate Victory for Metcalf Construction Company
Bradley Arant Boult Cummings LLP has secured a key reversal from the United States Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit on behalf of government contractor Metcalf Construction Company, Inc. The decision in Metcalf Construction Company, Inc. v. United States, which involves failures by the federal government to properly administer a contract, has broad implications for the rest of the government contracting community. "We are pleased for our client that the court ruled in their favor," said Bradley Arant Boult Cummings partner Robert J.
click http://www.babc.com/bradley-arant-boult-cummings-secures-appellate-victory-for-metcalf-construction-company-02-18-2014/#.UwRD3GKSxb0
14 February 2014: Bradley Arant Boult Cummings Partner Dana C. Lumsden Named to List of Nation's Most Influential Minority Attorneys
Bradley Arant Boult Cummings LLP is pleased to announce that partner Dana C. Lumsden has been named to On Being a Lawyer of Color Magazine's "Power List" for 2014. The annual list identifies the nation's most influential minority attorneys. Included this year are Attorney General Eric Holder, National Urban League President Marc Morial, and Juan Cartagena, who heads LatinoJustice PRLDEF.
click http://www.babc.com/bradley-arant-boult-cummings-partner-dana-c-lumsden-named-to-list-of-nations-most-influential-minority-attorneys-02-14-2014/#.Uv7WV9JDvp8
10 February 2014: Bradley Arant Boult Cummings Partners E. Mabry Rogers and John E. Goodman Named 2014 BTI Client Service All-Star Attorneys
Bradley Arant Boult Cummings LLP is pleased to announce that partners E. Mabry Rogers and John E. Goodman have been recognized as 2014 BTI Client Service All-Star Attorneys for delivering the highest levels of service to clients. Mr. Rogers also received the same honor in 2011. "We congratulate Mabry and John on this recognition for their outstanding service to our clients," said Firm Chairman Beau Grenier.
click http://www.babc.com/bradley-arant-boult-cummings-partners-e-mabry-rogers-and-john-e-goodman-named-2014-bti-client-service-all-star-attorneys-02-10-2014/#.UvngjNJDvp8
]]></text></news-item>