<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E1FC-3D42-0150-743C"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>People power could beat the Big Six energy suppliers</title><source>Express Online</source><author>Hilary Douglas</author><text><![CDATA[SOARING energy prices could be forced down by people power, claims a new campaign which aims to bring together hundreds of ­thousands of households to put pressure on energy companies.
The Big Deal is modelled on an Australian scheme launched in 2012 to which 250,000 people signed up and saved 16.5 per cent on their energy bills. A similar deal in Britain would mean savings of around £200 a year per bill.
Henry de Zoete, co-founder of The Big Deal and former special adviser to Education Secretary Michael Gove, said: "People think the energy market is stacked against them. Energy bills keep going up and people are having to make sacrifices.
"They don't trust the Big Six to give them a good deal, nor do they have faith in politicians to help them. It's time to take action ourselves. By joining together we can all get a better deal. More people means lower bills."
The campaign launched as it was revealed one in 10 consumers rarely or never opens an energy bill. In the 18 to 34 age bracket, just one in five bothers to check.
Mr de Zoete said of bills: "People find them confusing and complicated. They go up year on year and it feels like you can't do anything about them. However, there is an answer: it's people power.
"By bringing ­everyone together in huge numbers we can demand cheaper bills. The Big Deal will make life simple for people with clear, simple and cheaper bills."
A new poll by Populus has found four out of five consumers think the energy market is "broken" while three-quarters think energy companies act like a "cartel".
It also revealed half of people have had to make sacrifices because of energy bills.
The campaign could help to break the stranglehold of the 'Big Six' [PA]
The majority think politicians are "incapable" of helping them get a better deal. Just 17 per cent say they get a fair deal from their providers and 83 cent say the energy market is "broken".
Populus planning director Chris Wilkins said: "Even the banks at the height of the financial crisis are unlikely to have experienced ­figures this bad."
Sarah Willingham, consumer champion and TV money expert, said: "I'm joining The Big Deal because if we all come together, companies will listen."
Tory MP and energy campaigner Rob Halfon added: "Millions across the country feel powerless against poor customer service, great energy rip-offs like premium charges on non-direct debit payments and increasing bills.
"That is why I am backing the Big Deal."
Independent figures show that since 2005 the average household's annual dual fuel bill from the Big Six has risen from under £600 to more than £1,200, with profits for energy providers quadrupling and rising by £1billion.
Consumers are being asked to register with The Big Deal online or by using a local rate phone number.
Sign up at thisisthebigdeal.com or call 0333 222 5871.
]]></text></news-item>