<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E21C-80BA-2AF3-9942"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Sky's the limit for airborne snoopers; SUNDAY EXPLAINER</title><source>Sunday Age (Melbourne, Australia)</source><author>Ben Grubb</author><text><![CDATA[It's a bird, it's a plane, it's ... a drug mule? Last week, police intercepted a drone allegedly trying to deliver drugs over the wall of a Victorian remand centre. What do these robots mean for our safety, security, privacy - and the remote delivery of pizza? Ben Grubb takes a bird's-eye view.
"HOW WIDESPREAD HAVE DRONES BECOME IN CIVILIAN INDUSTRIES AND AMONG CONSUMERS?
In Australia, drones increasingly are being used by emergency services, photography, surveying and agricultural industries, with more than 81 operators licensed to fly them, according to aviation regulator CASA. Drones have also become popular among hobbyists, thanks to companies such as Parrot, which sells a Wi-Fi controlled quad-copter for about $350 online and in retail stores. Retailers speculated last year that about 100 new multi-rotor drones and fixed-wing drones take to Australian skies each week.
"WHAT KINDS OF THINGS ARE THEY BEING USED FOR?
Commercially, drones are often used instead of helicopters to shoot TV ads, inspect infrastructure, such as power lines, monitor livestock, and assess emergency situations such as bushfires. Animal welfare groups are also using them to conduct covert operations above free-range egg, sheep and cattle farms to gather evidence of alleged abuse, causing some controversy. Melbourne's Metropolitan Fire Brigade and the Queensland Police also use drones. The MFB used one last year to assess a truck dangling off the Bolte Bridge.
"WHAT KINDS OF LOADS CAN THEY CARRY?
It depends on the type but some quad-copters, such as the Australian-built Coptercam, which costs $13,000, can carry loads up to two kilos. Other fixed-wing drones, such as ScanEagle, which costs about $100,000, can carry up to six kilos. Cheaper drones on sale in retail stores generally have cameras attached to them that can be viewed remotely and are not designed to carry additional payload.
"IF DRONES COULD CARRY DRUGS INTO A PRISON, COULD THEY ALSO CARRY A GUN OR A BOMB?
It's entirely possible but there are no known cases of this occurring; drone drug delivery to jails, however, have also reportedly been achieved, attempted or foiled in Brazil (250 grams of cocaine), Georgia (500-900 grams of tobacco) and Russia (700 grams of heroin).
"WHAT DO THEY COST AND DO YOU NEED A LICENCE TO BUY OR FLY THEM?
Australia was the first country in the world to introduce legislation covering civilian use of drones in 2002. It requires operators to be licensed to use a drone commercially; to qualify, operators need to undertake training and register their drones with CASA. Recreational operators, however, don't need to be licensed or register their drones. Regardless of whether a drone is used for commercial or recreational purposes, the law stipulates a pilot must be in command at all times via remote control and keep the drone within his or her line of sight. The rules also require the drone be kept below 122 metres, operated only in daylight, and kept away from populous areas, airports and people unless a special licence has been issued. Infringement notices of up to $8000 can be issued if the rules are broken.
"ARE THEY HARD TO FLY?
Consumer drones on sale at retail stores are relatively easy to fly but commercial ones require operators to sit a private pilot theory exam and conduct a number of hours of experience with an instructor before being allowed to fly alone.
"HOW HIGH AND FAR CAN THEY FLY?
There's virtually no altitude limit. The law, however, prevents most drones going above 122 metres without a special licence. Some fixed-wing drones used by the military fly at 16,800 metres to avoid planes flying at 9100 metres. Civilians' quad-copters need to be visible to the pilot and while their remotes can work over two to three kilometres, operators generally use them within a range of 500 metres so they can see and operate them safely.
"WHAT ARE THE REGULATORY LIMITS ON THEIR USE FOR FILMING AND SURVEILLANCE?
There are no specific rules around filming and using drones for surveillance. Despite this, operators of drones are still subject to privacy laws and council bylaws. If a council didn't want a drone to fly at a local park or beach, for example, it could draft a law preventing their use and erect a "Drones prohibited" sign. CASA's director of aviation safety, John McCormick, this month told a parliamentary inquiry looking ito drones' privacy implications that the regulator had no interest in being responsible for policing any new privacy laws because it did not have the resources or budget.
"WHAT ARE THE REGULATORY LIMITS ON THEIR USE FOR OTHER ACTIVITIES?
Some companies, such as Sydney-based Flirtey and US-based Amazon, want to use drones to deliver goods. Flirtey wants to start off by delivering textbooks to university students while Amazon wants to deliver goods that are bought online from its website. Companies have also teased customers with the idea of being able to deliver pizza by drone. Many commercial operators are sceptical the current technology makes such pilotless delivery feasible.
"SHOULD I BE WORRIED?
The federal Privacy Commissioner raised concerns about drones last year, sparking the parliamentary inquiry that is due to report to government later this month. It was largely focused on the privacy aspects of drones. Concerns about air safety and terrestrial crashes are still unresolved.
]]></text></news-item>