<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E269-5297-74D1-6616"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Weekly Summary: Startup Mistakes; Dhingana Buyout; Quikr's $90 Mn &amp; More</title><source>Nextbigwhat.com</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[India, March 15 -- Not a dull moment in the world of startup and technology. This week, we covered how classifieds site Quikr raised $90 mn and what it plans to do with that money, how Skype founders are buying music streaming site Dhingana, the entry of State Bank of India into the online payments space, Amazon's new store pick up launch and other such stories. We also profiled a lot of interesting startups. If you missed some of our posts, here's a quick recap.
Editorially Recommended
When to Pivot? "P" For Pivot OR "P" For Persistence?
India Election 2014: THE Online Guide to Track it
Early Stage Investment Terms in India : What You Should Know
Quikr To Double Headcount; Focus on Mobile & Marketing [Interview]
4 Lessons from Buffer on Customer Happiness
Entrepreneurship
How MindTickle Built Their Startup Story from Scratch, Evangelising and Not Giving Up
What You Really Must Know As You Pivot
5 + 1 Mistakes Early Stage Startups Commit : Enter a Lion's Den Hunting For Breakfast
Funding
Skype Founders' Music Service Rdio Acquires Dhingana
The Opportunity Koovs Sold for $37 Mn & How it Got Around India's Ban on FDI in Ecommerce
Indian Language Speech Recognition Startup Uniphore Secures Angel Funding
Bangalore & US HQ'd Data Analytics Firm DataRPM Raises $5.1 Mn Funding
Online Book Retailer BookAdda Announces KoolSkool Acquisition
Sachin Tendulkar's Smaaash & Sports Management Firm Techfront Raise Funding
Affordable Health Care Services iKure Raises Seed Funding
Siliguri Based TeaBox Secures $1 mn Funding from Accel Partners
KarmYog Media Secures Funding for Pan India Roll Out of Indian Idol Academy
India Online
Target Knows You Are Pregnant, Flipkart Wants to Know if You are a Doting Father!
Indian Online Retail Spending to hit $16 Billion by 2018
Amazon Partners With Oil Company BPCL to Launch Store Pickup
With 10 Mn Visits a Month, Comparison Site Junglee Will Continue to Get Amazon's Attention [Interview]
Delhi's Select Citywalk Mall to Soon Go Hybrid; Are Malls Losing their Mojo?
State Bank of India Launches Payment Aggregator; More trouble for Incumbents!
Worldfloat is Back With $500 Mn Valuation & 50 Mn Users; One Word: LOL!
Facebook Drives Majority of Social Traffic & Sales for E-commerce Companies: Shopify
Microsoft Transparency Report Says Information Requests from Indian Government Up by 50%
Google Could End up with a $5 Bn Antitrust Penalty in Report
getitBazaar Launch DealGuru for Product Deals; Partners with 99labels
Startups
Pune Based Startup CarIQ Launches Connected Car Platform for Vehicle Health Monitoring
Exam Prep Marketplace BOOKstreet Selected for BSE-Ryerson Incubation Program Along With Blynk
Lukup Media's All in One Middleware Wants to Take Over the Living Room
Preparing for GRE, GMAT? Learningpod Makes Practice Easy
Talent58: A Job Portal Only for Retirees and Those Looking to Retire
Socioboard Wants to be The Magento & WordPress of Social Media Management
Stuff/ Apps
Vodafone India Testing Mobile Data Offloading Technology to Keep Up With Demand
Apple Launching Neighborhood Stores in India to Tackle Samsung's Growing Market Share
Now Build Your Resume Via Mobile Using Super Resume Builder
TastyKhana App Makes Ordering Food Through the Phone Simpler
Bored? Find a Friend Near You With LocoMapia App
Marketwatch App Brings Up to Date Wholesale Market Prices To You
Indian Medical Electronics Market Set to Grow to $11.7 Bn by 2017
Published by HT Syndication with permission from NextBigWhat.com. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>