<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E2DE-9CCD-CBC6-5470"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Arrest of businessman Firtash sends a message to Russia; UKRAINE</title><source>i-Independent Print Ltd</source><author>Jim Armitage and Ian Burrell</author><text><![CDATA[He is one of Ukraine's richest men, with an energy empire worth billions of dollars, links to senior Conservative parliamentarians and a luxurious home near Harrods. But that all counted for little when Austrian police arrested Dmitry Firtash on Wednesday, on a warrant from the FBI.
The 48-year-old, who has given millions of pounds to Cambridge University and last month visited the Foreign Office in London to discuss the crisis in his home country, was held on suspicion of involvement in the creation of an organised criminal group and paying bribes.
i last week revealed connections between the tycoon and Conservatives John Whittingdale, chairman of the powerful Commons media select committee, and Lord Risby, a former Tory Party vice-chairman and shadow minister for Financial Services.
Both men serve on the board of the British Ukrainian Society (BUS), which has strong ties to the magnayr, one of Ukraine's most powerful figures under the deposed President Victor Yanukovych. The billionaire was arrested in Vienna's Margareten district in front of his bodyguards on the orders of a US court. The move was described as "an absolutely seismic development" by one analyst, who pointed to Mr Firtash's strong ties to Russia and suggested it was a show of intent from the US against pro-Russian oligarchs and the Kremlin as the West struggles to contain Russian President Vladimir Putin's ambition in Ukraine. Mr Putin declared Russia's right to invade its neighbour on 1 March, even as Russian troops were already seizing control of Crimea.
Since then, the US and the EU have threatened to punish Russia economically, including by freezing the assets of Russians and those linked to Mr Yanukovych.
A US Senate panel passed a bill last week that allows the Obama administration to impose economic penalties on Russian officials responsible for the military intervention or culpable of corruption. The EU also agreed this week on a framework to impose travel bans and asset freezes on Russian individuals and firms.
Mr Firtash, whose wealth has been estimated at between $673m and $5bn, has been under investigation by the FBI since 2006. Standard Bank economist Timothy Ash said: "Firtash is probably in the top two of Ukrainian oligarchs in terms of wealth/influence across borders. Historically he had close ties to Russia via the energy sector and perhaps even to Putin. It sends a strong message to Russia that the West is willing to go down the financial sanctions route, unless it backtracks over Crimea."
Neither the two senior Conservatives on the BUS, nor Cambridge University, which accepted millions of pounds from Mr Firtash, returned calls and emails yesterday. The former head of his company, DF Group, the Conservative party donor and BUS member Robert Shetler-Jones, issued a statement saying the arrest related to an investment project in 2006. It was not associated with either the situation in Ukraine or with the activities of the Group in Europe and America, the statement said. Sources close to Mr Firtash deny wrongdoing on his part
The arrest tells Moscow that the West is willing to pursue financial sanctions
]]></text></news-item>