<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E3EB-D08D-4562-F649"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>For marijuana, legal against not</title><source>The Wenatchee World (Washington)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The Port of Douglas County turned down the opportunity to lease land for a legal and licensed agricultural/industrial business that would employ 26 people and produce $1 million in tax revenue for Douglas County. On its face this seems out of character. What are port districts for, if not to encourage job-creating industry and incubate fledgling enterprise?
But, like it or not this was not an ordinary offer. The business in question would be a cooperative facility to manufacture marijuana, and so our culture, lifelong obedience to law and preference for general sobriety surely play on the decision. As we should expect, the port's neighbors were adamantly opposed, citing all the fears we associate with intoxicating drugs - crime, corruption, temptation and disorder. The port commissioners voted 2-1 to turn down the offer, and you cannot blame them. Elected officials rarely are comfortable voting counter to public opinion, especially when the public so opposed live next door.
The decision is understandable, and perhaps the proposal from East Wenatchee entrepreneur Grant Guelich was not the best deal possible for the port. The legal marijuana business is still filled with unknowns, unresolved conflicts and risk. The commissioners were asked to approve a business that just a few months ago would have landed them in jail.
Understandable, yes, but sometime soon we will have to get a grip on our squeamishness and learn to live with more public evidence of marijuana use. We shouldn't forget that because we can't see the pot greenhouse on the corner of the port property doesn't mean that people aren't growing and using marijuana all over the county. The evidence is clear that they are, and in the process contribute to a vast criminal enterprise. Our efforts to keep marijuana use out of sight are our own contribution to the success of the thriving black market in intoxicants. That is the way prohibition works. The crime, corruption, temptation and disorder we fear are with us already, and we can make it worse.
Facing reality was the point of Initiative 502, and was probably the motivation for its passage and support even in conservative enclaves, support even from large numbers of people with absolutely no personal interest in marijuana use. You cannot stop others from using marijuana. Perhaps, however, we can defeat the black market and undermine its corrupting effects. To do that requires that legal marijuana be available, even if we find it unsettling.
That's hard. There are many local governments facing the same pressures as the Douglas County port commissioners and reacting in an understandable fashion. Efforts in the Legislature to provide cities with additional motivation to end moratoria and bans on retail operations, an enticement in the form of excise tax revenue from marijuana shops, died Thursday despite an 11th-hour push led by Rep. Cary Condotta, R-East Wenatchee. The revenue issue was key in the death of a measure to reform the state's medical marijuana market, to bring it into a more regulated format the federal government could overlook. Condotta continually made the point that the state has an interest in the geographic diffusion of marijuana shops. Where they are not, he said, the users will simply continue to buy from their accustomed sources. Democratic leaders in the House said they had not yet heard and argument strong enough to let them voluntarily share marijuana revenue.
How much is that? The state Economic and Revenue Forecast Council estimates $190 million over four years. That may be an overestimate if the law-abiding sources don't show up and take a sizable market share. We shall see.
Tracy Warner's column appears Wednesday through Friday. He can be reached at warner@wenatcheeworld.com or 665-1163.
]]></text></news-item>