<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E448-C9C0-91B7-11AD"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>FROM THE FIRST EDITIONS</title><source>Press Association Mediapoint</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[DAILY EXPRESS
PIRATES STOLE MISSING PLANE
Fears were growing last night that the Malaysian jet which vanished from the skies has been hijacked by pirates.
LABOUR ICON BENN DIES AT 88
Tributes poured in from across the political spectrum yesterday for veteran Leftwinger Tony Benn, who has died aged 88.
SPRING WILL BE A SUNNY DELIGHT
Britain will enjoy an amazing three months of warm weather with balmy conditions set to last until June, according to forecasters.
SPORT
WE'LL KILL OFF UNITED
Brendan Rodgers will look to extinguish Manchester United's lingering top-four hopes tomorrow - and cast them into the European wilderness.
HURT LOCKERS COSTS STOKES T20 SPOT
Ben Stokes has been ruled out of the World T20 after breaking his hand punching a locker.
INDEPENDENT:
DEATH OF A MAVERICK
Tony Benn, the veteran Labour politician and campaigner for socialism, died yesterday at the age of 88.
A NEW CHAPTER IN CHAGOS ISLANDS SAGA: ILLEGAL SEWAGE DUMPING
The American military has poured hundreds of tonnes of human sewage and waste water into a protected coral lagoon on the British-owned base of Diego Garcia over three decades in breach of environmental rules, The Independent can reveal.
QUEEN OF THE TEA PARTY - ON HER BEST BEHAVIOUR
Margaret Thatcher may have ascended to that great free-market enterprise in the sky. But Michele Bachmann, the former US presidential candidate and ``queen of the Tea Party'', laid claim to be her political heir when she addressed students at the Oxford Union.
City:
BARCLAYS CUTS CONTRACT STAFF'S PAY BY 10% - AS BONUSES RISE BY 10%
Barclays has told thousands of contract staff that they must accept a 10 per cent cut in pay or have their roles terminated, The Independent can reveal.
BOOHOO CHEERS ON ITS DEBUT
Boohoo.com yesterday became the latest company to soar on its stock market debut.
TELEGRAPH:
GOVE ATTACKS OLD ETONIAN BIAS IN PM'S INNER CIRCLE
Michael Gove the Education Secretary, has criticised the ``ridiculous'' number of Old Etonians in David Cameron's inner circle.
FOR SALE: EU CITIZENSHIP
Non-Europeans can buy European Union citizenship entitling them to live and work in Britain for as little as £150,000 under a scheme operating in Bulgaria, an investigation by the Daily Telegraph discloses today.
OSBORNE WILL UNVEIL A NEW GARDEN CITY IN HIS BUDGET
George Osborne will announce plans to build the first garden city in Britain for 40 years in his Budget, the Daily Telegraph has learnt.
City:
FTSE 100 SUFFERS WORST WEEK FOR NINE MONTHS AS CRIMEA FEARS GROW
The FTSE 100 has suffered its worst week since last June, with £46.4bn wiped off the value of Britain's biggest companies, amid growing fears about the crisis in Ukraine and slowing growth in China.
CO-OP 'WILL GO BUST' IF IT FAILS TO BACK TOTAL REFORM
The Co-operative Group will run out of money unless it urgently reforms its board and voting structure, its senior independent director has said.
MIRROR:
'HIJACKERS FLEW JET TOWARDS REMOTE ISLAND'
Missing flight MH370 may have been hijacked and flown west towards islands in the Indian Ocean.
CHAMPION OF THE POWERLESS
Friends and political foes united yesterday to pay tribute to Tony Benn, hailing the Labour stalwart as a ``champion of the powerless'' after his death at the age of 88.
DATA DISASTER FOR MORRISONS
Struggling Morrisons has suffered another blow after the bank account details of nearly 100,000 staff were plundered.
Sport:
WE CAN SEND YOU INTO EURO EXILE
Brendan Rodgers has warned Manchester United they face a long exile from Europe if they lose tomorrow to his Liverpool side.
IT ONLY TOOK ME A MINUTE TO SAY YES TO CHELSEA AGAIN
Nemanja Matic was out in London when his little son, Filip, thought he'd spotted Benfica's ``big red bus'', which used to take his dad to work in Portugal.
STAR:
MISSING JET WAS HIJACKED
Hijackers have flown a missing Malaysian airliner to a remote island, it was feared last night.
LEE RIGBY VID COUPLE CAGED
Two British Muslims were jailed yesterday for glorifying the murder of Fusilier Lee Rigby in sick YouTube videos.
CBB JAS DITCHES '2% MAN' RYAN
Celebrity Big Brother babe Jasmine Waltz has dumped Lee Ryan, branding him ``2% man, 98% bullsh*t''.
Sport:
WE'LL KEEP YOU OUT OF EUROPE
Brendan Rodgers has warned Manchester United they could face years out of the Champions League if they miss out this season.
BENDTNER'S GUN FOR
Bad boy Nicklas Bendtner has played his last game for Arsenal.
MIRROR:
BETRAYAL OF THE NHS NURSES
Millionaire Tory Jeremy Hunt yesterday refused to give thousands of NHS staff a measly 1% pay rise.
BENEFIT CHEATS' TVS AND IPADS WILL BE SEIZED
Benefit fraudsters living in luxury on the taxpayer face having valuables such as TVs, cars and iPads seized in a new crackdown.
MASTERCHEF TATTIE SPAT
The BBC's commercial rules looked half-baked last night after it emerged host Gregg Wallace was allowed to advertise potatoes.
Sport:
RVP: GIVE ME A NEW DEAL
Robin van Persie is ready to sign a new contract with Manchester United.
CHELSEA NOW THE FAVOURITES CLAIMS TOURE
Yaya Toure claims Chelsea are now favourites to win the Premier League.
DAILY MAIL:
PRICE WAR AT THE CHECKOUTS
A supermarket price war on an unprecedented scale was under way last night with the prospect of permanent cuts in the cost of many basic foods.
WHY WOMEN IN THEIR 50S ARE THE HAPPIEST
In an age when youthful celebrities dominate our screens and magazines, you might think the older generations would be the least confident about their bodies.
TORY FURY AT 40P TAX
Downing Street was under mounting pressure last night to ease the 40p tax burden on the middle classes.
Sport:
I WANT TO STAY, RVP: UNITED EXIT TALK IS NONSENSE
Robin van Persie has dismissed speculation he could leave Manchester United this summer and says he could spend the rest of his top-flight career at Old Trafford.
EURO HOPES IN TATTERS FOR SPURS
Tottenham crashed to defeat in the Europa League against Benfica last night as Tim Sherwood's brutal criticism of his players backfired.
GUARDIAN:
OSBORNE'S £1BN SWEETENER
George Osborne has pocketed a spare £1bn before the budget next week to help fund a series of road and other infrastructure projects as the chancellor moves to reassure Tory heartlands that the government has ideas well beyond its divisive high-speed rail project.
NEW DRUGS FAST-TRACKED FOR SEVERELY ILL PATIENTS
A scheme to fast-track innovative new medicines to patients without waiting years to get a licence will be announced today by the government, which says it will give hope to patients and boost the pharmaceutical industry in the UK.
USE GM CROPS - OR BRITONS MAY GO UNFED, SAYS REPORT
David Cameron's science advisers have called for GM crops to be rolled out across the UK by scrapping ``dysfunctional'' EU regulations that risk curtailing future food supplies.
City:
MORRISONS TRIGGERS SUPERMARKET PANIC
More than £2bn was wiped off the value of the UK's listed supermarkets yesterday as Morrisons said taking on discounters such as Aldi and Lidl with aggressive price cuts would see its profits slashed by more than 50%.
RBS EDGES CLOSER TO JUNK BOND STATUS
Royal Bank of Scotland has edged closer to junk bond status after a leading credit ratings agency downgraded the state-controlled bank's debt following record losses and fears of regulatory punishment.
i:
PAY NURSES BY PERFORMANCE - HUNT'S PLAN FOR THE NHS
NHS workers' pay should be linked to performance rather than how long they have held their jobs, Jeremy Hunt has said - while announcing that more than half the health service workforce will be denied a widely expected 1% pay rise.
SEARCH FOR MISSING PLANE WIDENS AFTER ENGINE CLAIMS
The British company Rolls-Royce was last night at the centre of growing confusion about the plight of missing Flight MH370 after it was claimed that data sent from the plane's engines suggested it had flown for a further four hours from its last-known location.
GM CROPS ARE NOT DANGEROUS AND SHOULD BE GROWN IN UK, SAY SCIENTISTS
There is no compelling evidence that genetically modified crops are any more dangerous to humans or the environment than conventionally farmed food, and it is time for Europe to be stripped of its obstructive control of the technology, scientists have advised the Prime Minister
City:
MORRISONS' PRICE-CUT PLEDGE EXPOSES PLIGHT OF BIG FOUR
The tanks of the discount chains have been firmly parked on the lawns of the Big Four supermarkets.
BARCLAYS 'SET TO AXE THOUSANDS OF BANKERS'
Barclays is planning to axe thousands of investment bankers' jobs in a radical overhaul of the controversial division.
FINANCIAL TIMES:
CHINA WARNING ON DEFAULTS SPARKS FEARS OVER GROWTH
China's premier has warned that future defaults on bonds and other financial products are ``unavoidable'', underlining wider concerns that a wave of bad debts threatens to derail growth in the world's second-largest economy.
BARCLAYS INVESTMENT BANK SET FOR NEW JOB CULL
Barclays is preparing a radical overhaul of its troubled investment bank in a move expected to result in thousands of job cuts, adding to pressure on the division's two heads.
MALEMA TARGETS BIG GAME IN ANC'S HEARTLAND
Julius Malema speaks softly but carries a big political stick.
Companies and Markets:
MORRISON SPARKS FEARS OF STORES PRICE WAR
Wm Morrison sparked alarm over a price war in the supermarket sector with plans to spend £1bn cutting prices over the next three years to take on German discounters Aldi and Lidl.
LIONS GATE ADMITS IT MISLED INVESTORS TO REPEL ICAHN BID
Lions Gate Entertainment agreed to pay 7.5m dollars and admit wrongdoing to resolve civil charges that the movie studio misled its investors in an attempt to thwart a 2010 takeover bid by activist investor Carl Icahn.
SUN:
I DOUGH
Love-split Lotto winner Adrian Bayford is getting married again - to a stable girl he began romancing six weeks ago.
DI 'SENT EDITOR' PALACE SECRETS
Princess Diana sent a restricted Palace phone book to News of the World royal editor Clive Goodman, a jury heard.
CARRY ON NURSE? NOT A CHANCE
Nurses and paramedics are gearing up for a wave of strikes after ministers blocked a blanket pay rise for NHS workers.
Sport:
RVP: I'LL SIGN FOR LIFE
Robin van Persie insists he is happy with David Moyes and wants to spend the rest of his career at Manchester United.
TIM'S TOUCHLINE BUST-UP
Tim Sherwood was involved in a furious bust-up with rival boss Jorge Jesus as Spurs suffered a disastrous Europa League defeat.
]]></text></news-item>