<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E463-38C1-E33F-7E04"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>When public interest is compromised</title><source>The Age (Melbourne, Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Although the definition of the term "conflict of interest" is so self-contained as to require little further explanation, it is, in practice, an elusive concept. In fact, conflict of interest in Victoria's public sector continues to be so prevalent, the subject has again attracted the attention of state Ombudsman George Brouwer, who this week tabled a report on the subject in Parliament. Its wry subtitle? "Ongoing concerns".
Mr Brouwer's findings are disturbing and damning. Various alarming case studies leave little doubt of the extent of such conflicts, particularly in incidents of alleged nepotism and favouritism in procurement and recruitment practices. For example, an employee of a statutory body was found to have engaged his own company for a six-year period. As the Ombudsman says: "Conflict of interest, badly managed, undermines the integrity of public administration and government."
This has a familiar ring. In recent weeks, an investigation by this newspaper has identified numerous potential conflicts of interest at the state government's new water agency, the Office of Living Victoria (OLV). On Tuesday, The Age revealed that Water Minister Peter Walsh has been drawn ito the affair after his office made a mysterious payment to a consultant - former Howard government adviser Simon Want - a year before Mr Want was chosen to head the OLV without the job being advertised. Our investigation has also found the OLV awarded split contracts to more than 10 consultants (many with strong ties to federal or state National Party ministers) in a bid to keep their identities secret and to avoid public tenders. The OLV has yet to answer a series of questions put by our reporters.
The OLV's climate of secrecy is also a climate of fear. Many of its employees agreed to be interviewed by The Age on condition of anonymity; they feared retribution if they were identified as whistleblowers. This is a government agency, not the KGB. This is also an organisation that has a $50 million fund to provide councils, water authorities and developers with project grants. That money is public money, and the public has every right to know what sort of body is responsible for allocating it; and that body should be beyond reproach and open to scrutiny.
That the OLV appears to be bypassing proper procedures, showing favouritism and remaining publicly unaccountable for its actions makes it the exemplar of the Ombudsman's continuing conflict-of-interest concerns.
More broadly, the Ombudsman's report outlines succinctly not just the extent and nature of conflict-of-interest problems, but how they could best be dealt with. This, the report says, involves a more preventive approach, whereby "disclosure and discussion ensures accountability and transparency", allied with proper policies and procedures, including a central register of all conflict-of-interest regulations - "poor record-keeping" is another issue of public sector concern to Mr Brouwer. Is this concept too difficult to grasp?
The Ombudsman's two recommendations to the State Services Authority - review its own guidance materials, and consider further ways to support greater awareness and action on the part of public sector agencies - have been accepted, but they place responsibility firmly on the SSA, and by extension the Napthine government, to implement them. It is troubling that too little has been done to tackle the severity and frequency of conflicts of interest in the public sector. The fault, as Mr Brouwer pertinently says, lies as much with agencies as their employees. Clearly, a whole culture that has been allowed to spread must now change.
]]></text></news-item>