<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E47B-9E83-79C1-681C"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>DUBIOUS DEEDS </title><source>Patriot News (Harrisburg, Pennsylvania)</source><author>MATT ZENCEY</author><text><![CDATA[Each week, Pennsylvania offers up a rich harvest of weird doings by oddballs, misbehaving pols and other intemperate agitators who deserve special attention for their efforts. Well, Deed readers, the candidate-filing deadline came and went and so did some of the candidates. Though that nasty polar wind nearly blew this week's compendium halfway to Three Mile Island, here we go:
ANOTHER TREE FALLS IN THE FOREST, MAKING NO SOUND. Democrat Jo Ellen Litz of Lebanon dropped out of the race for governor.
AND ANOTHER The Rev. Micah Sims alerted the media that he'd be running for Congress, but one week later, he failed to file enough petitions to get on the ballot.
NOW, THAT TREE WAS BIG ENOUGH TO MAKE A SOUND. Democrat John Hanger, a former state Department of Environmental Protection secretary who had raised more than $1 million for his campaign, also dropped out of the race for governor.
NO MERIT SYSTEM HERE! Explaining why Dauphin County Dems did not endorse Rep. Patty Kim for renomination without an open primary, party chairwoman Marilyn Levin said, "I think [not supporting Thompson for mayor] hurt her in the African-American community today. They were out in full force. If you're an incumbent, you support incumbents, and I don't think she quite understood it would come back to bite her one day."
AW, SHUCKS, WE WERE JUST DOING OUR JOB. "[Thompson] is coming into the [4th Congressional District] race with $200,000 worth of name recognition. Thank you, Patriot-News," Levin said.
PEOPLE DO LIKE A CIRCUS, BUT THAT DOESN'T MEAN THEY'LL VOTE FOR THE CLOWN. Levin said this about that "$200,000 worth of name recognition" that Linda Thompson got: "Now, maybe it wasn't all good, but everyone in Adams County and everyone in York County wants to meet this woman, and that's a big advantage for her."
YAWN. But be sure to wake us up if the Koch brothers deliver a check for $10 million.
MONTGOMERY COUNTY REPUBLICAN BOB GUZZARDI FILED PETITIONS to qualify for the Republican primary for governor, saying Gov. Tom Corbett broke his promise not to raise taxes.
NO. REALLY? GEE, HAZLETON WOULD BE THE LAST PLACE YOU'D EXPECT SOMETHING LIKE THAT. Democratic congressional candidate Andrew Ostrowski filed suit alleging that a Hazleton police officer illegally harassed a Hispanic campaign volunteer and confiscated the nominating petitions she had collected on his behalf. Ostrowski is running against incumbent Republican Lou Barletta, the former Hazleton mayor who led a controversial crackdown on illegal immigrants.
DEFROCKED BIRDS OF A FEATHER, FLOCKING TOGETHER. Ostrowski is a former lawyer who has lost his authorization to practice law in state and federal courts. His lawsuit was filed by former state Auditor General Don Bailey, an attorney whose law license has been suspended by the state Supreme Court for five years.
"THIS LAND IS OUR LAND. YOU STAY OUT!" A judge has barred anti-fracking activist Vera Scroggins, a 63-year old grandmother, from setting foot on 300 square miles of Susquehanna County - 40 percent of the county - because the land is owned or leased by Cabot Oil and Gas. Under the exclusion order that Cabot obtained, Scroggins is barred from many businesses that are open to the public, including restaurants, grocery stores and a new health care complex.
WE COULD TELL YOU, BUT THEN WE'D HAVE TO KILL YOU. Scroggins says Cabot has so far refused to give her a map or a list of places it owns or has leased, so she knows where she can and cannot legally go.
OUR BAD! According to State Impact Pennsylvania, a Cabot spokesman said the company sought the restraining order against Scroggins but didn't mean for it to be so broad.
BUT SOMEHOW WE DON'T THINK JAY IS CONTRIBUTING TO HIS LEGAL DEFENSE FUND. Among the signatures on lieutenant governor candidate Jay Paterno's nominating petitions was that of ex-Penn State President Graham Spanier.
SOMEWHERE, THE GHOST OF AVA BERG IS SMILING Colorado reported that the state collected $2 million in just one month from taxes on the newly legalized sale of recreational marijuana.
Matt Zencey is deputy opinion editor of PennLive/The Patriot-News. Email him at mzencey@pennlive.com, and follow him on Twitter: @MattZencey.
'The Meter' will return Wiley McKellar III is off this week.
]]></text></news-item>