<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E48E-EA06-91E1-685E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>SHAREHOLDER ALERT: Pomerantz Law Firm Announces the Filing of a Class Action Against Aegerion Pharmaceuticals, Inc. and Certain Officers - AEGR</title><source>Marketwired</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Pomerantz LLP has filed a class action lawsuit against Aegerion Pharmaceuticals, Inc. ("Aegerion" or the "Company") (NASDAQ: AEGR) and certain of its officers. The class action, filed in United States District Court, District of Massachusetts, and docketed under 14-cv-10105, is on behalf of a class consisting of all persons or entities who purchased or otherwise acquired Aegerion securities between March 15, 2012 and January 9, 2014, both dates inclusive (the "Class Period"). This class action seeks to recover damages against Defendants for alleged violations of the federal securities laws pursuant to Sections 10(b) and 20(a) of the Securities Exchange Act of 1934 and Rule 10b-5 promulgated thereunder.
If you are a shareholder who purchased Aegerion securities during the Class Period, you have until March 17, 2014 to ask the Court to appoint you as Lead Plaintiff for the class. A copy of the Complaint can be obtained at www.pomerantzlaw.com. To discuss this action, contact Robert S. Willoughby at rswilloughby@pomlaw.com or 888.476.6529 (or 888.4-POMLAW), toll free, x237. Those who inquire by e-mail are encouraged to include their mailing address, telephone number, and number of shares purchased.
Aegerion Pharmaceuticals, Inc., is a biopharmaceutical company, engaged in the development and commercialization of novel therapeutics to treat debilitating and fatal rare diseases in the United States. The Company's products include JUXTAPID (lomitapide) capsules, an adjunct to a low-fat diet and other lipid-lowering treatments in patients with homozygous familial hypercholesterolemia. Aegerion Pharmaceuticals, Inc. was founded in 2005, and is headquartered in Cambridge, Massachusetts.
The Complaint alleges that throughout the Class Period, Defendants made false and/or misleading statements, as well as failed to disclose material adverse facts about the Company's business, operations, and prospects. Specifically, Defendants made false and/or misleading statements and/or failed to disclose to Aegerion investors that: (1) the Company marketed its drugs in violation of the FDCA; (2) as a result, the Company faced heightened regulatory scrutiny by the FDA and other governmental bodies; and (3) as a result of the foregoing, Aegerion's statements were materially false and misleading at all relevant times.
On November 8, 2013, news reports revealed that the Company received an FDA Warning Letter, addressed to Defendant Beer, (the, "Warning Letter") in connection with statements the Company's CEO made regarding JUXTAPID capsules, during broadcast interviews on CNBC's television show, "Fast Money," that aired on June 5, 2013, and October 31, 2013. The Warning Letter stated that Defendant Beer made public statements which "provide evidence that Juxtapid is intended for new uses, for which it lacks approval and for which its labeling does not provide adequate directions for use, which renders Juxtapid misbranded within the meaning of the Federal Food Drug and Cosmetic Act ("FDCA") and makes its distribution violative of the FDCA."
On January 10, 2014, the Company received a subpoena from the U.S. Department of Justice requesting documents regarding its marketing and sale of JUXTAPID. On this news, Aegerion shares declined $ 7.98 per share, or nearly 11%, to close at $65.77 per share on January 10, 2013.
The Pomerantz Firm, with offices in New York, Chicago, Florida, and San Diego, is acknowledged as one of the premier firms in the areas of corporate, securities, and antitrust class litigation. Founded by the late Abraham L. Pomerantz, known as the dean of the class action bar, the Pomerantz Firm pioneered the field of securities class actions. Today, more than 70 years later, the Pomerantz Firm continues in the tradition he established, fighting for the rights of the victims of securities fraud, breaches of fiduciary duty, and corporate misconduct. The Firm has recovered numerous multimillion-dollar damages awards on behalf of class members. See www.pomerantzlaw.com.
SOURCE: Pomerantz LLP
]]></text></news-item>