<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E4AF-5DF2-CF2D-8D12"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Anti-union group files lawsuit against VW and UAW</title><source>Autoblog</source><author>Chris Bruce</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 14, 2014 (Autoblog:http://www.autoblog.com/ Delivered by Newstex) Filed under: Government/Legal[1], Plants/Manufacturing[2], Volkswagen[3], UAW/Unions[4] http://www.freep.com/article/20140313/BUSINESS0104/303130144/UAW-Volkswagen-right-to-work-election-union-lawsuitThe fight for unionization at Volkswagen's Chattanooga, TN, factory isn't letting up. Yesterday, the National Labor Relations Board decided to allow anti-United Auto Workers employees at the plant the right to defend voting down[5] the measure. Now, a group called the National Right to Work Foundation has filed a federal lawsuit on behalf of five workers against VW[6] and the UAW[7] for allegedly working together to organize.
The group says in a release[8] that it wants "to block further collusion between the company and the United Auto Workers." It alleges that VW forced workers to attend "mandatory pro-union meetings" and prevented managers from opposing. In a rebuttal on its website[9], the UAW called the claims "baseless" and said its actions were entirely legal.One possible problem faces the carmaker in regards to the lawsuit. According to the Detroit Free Press[10], a recent US Court of Appeals ruling found that neutrality agreements like the one the business had with the UAW could be illegal if the company provided "things of value" to the union. The newspaper also claims that VW held a mandatory employee meeting concerning the election, but workers were free to leave during the UAW's presentation.The union vote was held from February 12-14 and was defeated 712-626[11]. The UAW has filed an appeal with the NLRB citing interference in the vote[12], and it's hoping for a second ballot. Other workers are hoping to save the works council at the factory[13]."We have no comment at this time," said Scott Wilson, head of PR at the Volkswagen Chattanooga factory, to Autoblog. Read more[14] [1]: http://www.autoblog.com/category/government-legal/ [2]: http://www.autoblog.com/category/plants-manufacturing/ [3]: http://www.autoblog.com/category/volkswagen/ [4]: http://www.autoblog.com/category/uaw-unions/ [5]: http://www.autoblog.com/2014/03/13/uaw-angry-over-vw-workers-right-appeal-chattanooga-vote/ [6]: http://www.autoblog.com/volkswagen/ [7]: http://www.autoblog.com/tag/united+auto+workers/ [8]: http://www.nrtw.org/en/press/2014/03/chattanooga-volkswagen-workers-file-federal-suit-03132014 [9]: http://www.uaw.org/articles/uaw-statement-regarding-nrtw-lawsuit [10]: http://www.freep.com/article/20140313/BUSINESS0104/303130144/UAW-Volkswagen-right-to-work-election-union-lawsuit [11]: http://www.autoblog.com/2014/02/15/vw-chattanooga-workers-reject-uaw-union/ [12]: http://www.autoblog.com/2014/02/22/uaw-appealing-vw-tennessee-loss/ [13]: http://www.autoblog.com/2014/02/25/vw-chattanooga-works-council-union/ [14]: http://www.autoblog.com/2014/03/14/anti-union-group-files-lawsuit-against-vw-uaw/

]]></text></news-item>