<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E4CC-91E0-C973-0D67"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Programme summary of Armenian Public TV "Haylur" news 1700 gmt 14 Mar 14</title><source>BBC Monitoring Trans Caucasus UnitSupplied by BBC Worldwide Monitoring</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Presenter: Kristine Melkonyan
Headlines
1. 0135 Report on the participation of Armenian chess grandmaster Levon Aronyan in World Chess Tournament in Russia.
2. 0217 President Serzh Sargsyan visited the construction site of a new compound of government buildings in Yerevan today. The construction is planned to be over in two and a half years. Video shows Sargsyan visiting the construction site.
3. 0555 President Serzh Sargsyan has welcomed the appeal of the Swiss authorities against a verdict of the European Court of Human Rights (ECHR) on Turkish politician Dogu Perincek. (See separate News.am report)
4. 0956 French MP Valerie Boyer has welcomed the decision of the Swiss authorities to appeal against ECHR verdict on Dogu Perincek.
5. 1034 The Dutch branch of the Hay Dat (Armenian Cause) organization is optimistic, believing that the ECHR will overturn its verdict on Perincek and will restore justice, presenter quotes the head of the branch, Masis Abrahamyan, as telling the Armenpress news agency.
6. 1116 A group of Hay Dat organization (which, in particular, seeks recognition of Armenian "genocide") has been established in Warsaw, Poland. The branch will be tasked with raising awareness on Armenian issues in Poland and reinforcing cooperation within the Armenian community in Poland.
7. 1146 Foreign Minister Edvard Nalbandyan, who arrived on a working visit to Paris on 13 March , and his French counterpart, Laurent Fabius, have discussed preparatory work ahead of the coming May visit of the French president to Armenia. The sides discussed the development of economic ties; Armenia-EU ties; and Karabakh settlement. Video shows the meeting.
8. 1244 The deputy chief of the Azerbaijani presidential staff, Novruz Mammadov, has accused US co-chair of the OSCE Minsk Group, James Warlick, of having the same position as the Armenian side on Karabakh settlement, on his Twitter page.
9. 1406 US House of Representatives Member Brad Sherman has called on US Secretary of State John Kerry to stop US aid provided to Azerbaijan at a session of foreign relations committee of the US Senate in Washington.
10. 1447 Representatives of opposition parliamentary factions have discussed the unification of four opposition factions at parliamentary briefings in Yerevan today. Video shows the briefings.
11. 1612 The State Commission for the Protection of Economic Competition has presented a number of violations in the sphere of business competition at a meeting in Yerevan today. The Commission has fined a number of companies who have violated the rights of consumers and rules of advertisement in the republic.
12. 2006 Report on the situation in Ukraine.
13. 2239 Video report on President Serzh Sargsyan's visit to the Ministry of Health. Sargsyan and the senior staff of the ministry discussed the performance of the ministry in 2013 and the 2014 action plan.
14. 3158 Video report on preparatory work ahead of Armenia's participation in the coming Eurovision 2014 song contest.
15. 3546 Presenter signs off.
Source: Public Television of Armenia, Yerevan, in Armenian 1700gmt 14 Mar 14
]]></text></news-item>