<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E6A8-9583-B528-FE28"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Voucher bill may benefit nonprofit; Insider; nonprofit; could get; a payoff; Bill gives; boost to; insider; nonprofit; Politically connected group could triple what it currently collects. Critics say voucher bill triples profit for agency with political ties.</title><source>Palm Beach Post (Florida)</source><author> By John Kennedy   Palm Beach Post Capital Bureau </author><text><![CDATA[A proposal expanding private school vouchers in Florida could pour millions of dollars into a politically connected nonprofit, creating what a rising chorus of Democrats, public school officials and business rivals are condemning as a taxpayer-financed monopoly.
Step Up for Students, which administers the Florida Tax Credit Scholarship Program created under former Gov. Jeb Bush, could more than triple the amount of money it collects under voucher legislation that Republican leaders are terming a priority this session.
The bill makes the scholarship program eligible for sales tax money for the first time in its 12-year history. With the new cash, the 60,000 students now getting private-school scholarships could double in four years, rivaling the size of larger public school districts in Florida.
While Republicans are rallying around the expansion, the proposal also is drawing fierce critics.
"The issue is not simply an argument between public schools and private schools and vouchers," said Rep. David Richardson, D-Miami Beach. "It's an outrageous amount of taxpayer money that is involved here."
The Florida Tax Credit Scholarship Program can spend as much as $286 million this year to send 59,674 mostly black and Hispanic low-income students to more than 1,400 private schools across the state, three-fourths of them faith-based.
Tax credits given
The program gives corporations dollar-for-dollar tax credits for donations they make to finance the private school scholarships.
The program's funding has steadily climbed, with $357.8 million already the cap for scholarships next year.
But under legislation that recently cleared the House Finance and Tax Committee, lawmakers are looking to bump that up to $390 million, on course for the program to spend $873.6 million by 2018.
This year's legislation also continues an allowance of 3 percent of the annual cap for administrative costs, a fee that allows Step Up for Students, a Tampa-based nonprofit, to collect $8.6 million this year.
When the program reaches its full capacity, Step Up could be collecting $26.2 million for expenses.
Supporters point out Florida's 3 percent is the lowest level among the 14 states with tax credit scholarship programs.
Still, another scholarship funding organization (SFO) is among those accusing lawmakers of tilting the program in Step Up's favor.
"It has every semblance of a monopoly," said Kim Dyson, chief executive officer of AAA Scholarship Foundation, which is also looking to direct scholarships to low-income students.
"I know the way the regulations were originally set up, that it wasn't designed to create a monopoly for one SFO," she added. "But that's what has happened and the legislation would create new barriers to keep anyone else from coming into Florida."
Official, speaker close
Step Up's chairman, John Kirtley, is an equity-fund manager close to Republican House Speaker Will Weatherford, who is promising a "massive expansion" of school choice this year.
Kirtley, who runs a political committee that has spent almost $2.4 million in Florida elections since 2010, once dubbed Weatherford the "poster child" for school choice. The speaker was home-schooled until his first year of high school.
Under current law, the 3 percent for administrative costs can't be collected until an SFO has been in the state for three years. Step Up is the only one currently qualifying and has been for several years.
Still, AAA Scholarship and two others this year have successfully applied to work in Florida.
But being barred from recovering any costs for three years is difficult, said Dyson, who worked in the Florida program from 2002-10 and now runs tax-credit scholarship programs in Georgia, Alabama, Arizona and Pennsylvania.
"I was shocked when I found out that such a longstanding program as this has only one scholarship funding organization," said Ty Mullis, whose Rotary Club of Spring Hill also is looking to participate in the program.
"I think Step Up is doing a fine job. But I think we could supplement what they're doing for children in our area," he added.
But additional regulations proposed in the legislation (HB 7099, SB 1620) require those looking to run a voucher program to submit a financial bond, win approval from the state's Board of Education and compile costly survey data showing there are students needing scholarships in a region.
Step Up for Students Vice President Jon East acknowledged that the rules are rigorous. But he said they are designed to keep out "bad actors."
"The law is much stricter here," East said. "But in recent years we have not had the problems that some other states have had. It's more an accident in history that we have become the only scholarship funding organization."
The Palm Beach Post reported extensively a decade ago on the Tax Credit Scholarship Program's early-stage problems, involving misuse of dollars by schools and funding organizations that led to a critical state audit.
Since then, advocates say oversight has been strengthened, even as the program expanded and Step Up's control tightened.
The organization's leadership also has flourished since fee collection was authorized in 2008.
According to its most recent IRS filings, Step Up has six administrators earning more than $100,000 annually, topped by President Doug Tuthill's $214,102.
"We've been able to grow," Tuthill said. "But our position is that we have to be perfect with everything we do."
This year's legislation, though, could dramatically change the program.
While families of four getting scholarships can earn no more than $44,000 annually, that would grow to $62,000 under this year's proposal.
The program could not only accept more children, it could begin to market to not just the poorest households.
The size of the scholarships also would go up, making the program more attractive. Students this year can receive $4,335 scholarships to private schools, representing 80 percent of the cost of sending the child to public schools.
Lawmakers would increase that level to 84 percent of public school spending.
Palm Beach County Schools officials are among those opposing the expansion.
They warn that the proposal diverts available sales tax dollars -- the state's chief source of general revenue -- while also steering public school students into private academies, reducing district enrollment, which determines state funding.
"At a time where funding for public schools is below where it was when Gov. Rick Scott took office, and more than $200-per-student below where it was in the 2007-08 school year, do we really need to be expanding the money provided to unregulated voucher schools?" said the Florida Education Association, the state's largest teachers' union.
Weatherford, though, said he isn't worried about the expansion -- or adding muscle to Step Up.
"It's been shown over the years, the program is extremely successful," Weatherford said, adding, "I think the administrative fee is there to make sure they can oversee the program; it's a large program. They also market the program to parents and students.
"I don't have any reservations about it," he added.
Rep. Manny Diaz, R-Miami, the sponsor of the legislation agreed.
"These are not barriers. We want to make sure whoever comes in is not fly-by-night, that they're a legitimate organization," Diaz said. "Whoever does a good job is going to be the organization that winds up with the most money. That's the way it is in any market."
jkennedy@pbpost.com Twitter: @jkennedyreport
private school tax dollars
Florida's Tax Credit Scholarship Program would grow under proposed legislation. A look at maximum levels of tax dollars that could flow to private schools:
-14 (current level) $286 million
-15 $390 million
2015-16 $475 million
2016-17 $590 million
-18 $730 million
-19 $873.6 million
Source: Florida Legislature, HB 7099, SB 1620
]]></text></news-item>