<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E6BE-943D-CA23-6E3E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>The Landrieu Era Begins</title><source>The National Journal</source><author>Ben Geman and Clare Foran</author><text><![CDATA[The Landrieu Era Begins
The crisis in Ukraine is giving advocates of U.S. natural-gas exports new political ammunition as they argue that exports can eventually weaken the hand of Russia, a major supplier of gas to Europe.
Eventually, who knows when, Ukraine will cease to be Washington's biggest story. But don't expect the gas-export battle, and the related tussle over whether to lift restrictions on crude-oil exports, to fade along with it.
At least if new Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee Chairwoman Mary Landrieu has anything to do with it.
Landrieu today announced her first hearing as leader of the committee, and it's likely to include a heavy dose of pro-export testimony and questions.
The title of the March 25 hearing is "Importing Energy, Exporting Jobs: Can it be Reversed?"
The hearing arrives as the oil-and-gas industry and its allies are pressing the Energy Department to speed up its approval of natural-gas export proposals. The department has authorized a handful already, but critics complain that DOE is dragging its feet.
Landrieu's decision to spotlight natural-gas exports out of the gate is a sign that advocates won't lack platforms on Capitol Hill to make their case this year.
Ben Geman @ben_geman bgeman@nationaljournal.com
By Clare Foran ( @ckmarie )
HOUSE DEMS PUSH BACK ON KEYSTONE XL. Twenty-seven House Democrats, including Jan Schakowsky of Illinois, Rush Holt of New Jersey, and Raul Grijalva of Arizona , sent a letter to Secretary of State John Kerry asking him to nix the proposed pipeline.
Our take: It would take a bigger Democratic revolt to influence the administration's upcoming decision on Keystone.
CRUDE-BY-RAIL SHIPMENTS SOAR. According to the Association of American Railroads, transport of crude by railroad was up by 83 percent last year. Meanwhile, crude shipments are creating railway bottlenecks in some areas of the country. (Paywall)
BILL GATES TALKS CLIMATE WITH CONSERVATIVE FINANCIER. Gates recently discussed the issue of climate change with conservative mega donor Charles Koch.
EUROPE CAN'T CONVINCE THE U.S. TO EXPORT LNG. The European Union wants the U.S. to open up natural-gas exports in a new trade deal, but the U.S. is hesitant to sign on.
HERE IS EXACTLY WHAT THE CHAMBER OF COMMERCE THINKS ABOUT CLIMATE CHANGE. A Senate hearing Thursday on the proposed Keystone XL pipeline produced a clear piece of news: The U.S. Chamber of Commerce isn't especially fond of talking about humans' contribution to global warming.
COULD YOUR PRIUS CAUSE AIR POLLUTION IN CHINA? Graphite used in Tesla and Prius car batteries and other electronic devices is mined in China, where it's leading to air and water pollution .
REFINERS DIVIDED OVER CRUDE EXPORTS. A handful of domestic refiners recently formed a coalition to battle attempts to ease export restrictions, but other refiners say they see no threat to expanded exports. (Paywall)
HAGAN TALKS CLIMATE. Moderate Democrat Sen. Kay Hagan of North Carolina took to the Senate floor to urge action on climate change , despite the fact that she sat out the Senate climate talkathon that took place earlier in the week.
OIL PRODUCTION ON PUBLIC LANDS IS UP. According to an analysis of Interior Department stats, oil production on public lands increased last year while production of natural gas continued to decline. (Paywall)
GREENS SAY COST OF CARBON IS TOO LOW. According to a report released with environmental backing the administration's metric for the social cost of carbon fails to account for the full extent of damage caused by climate change .
DEMS FACE KEYSTONE DILEMMA. As midterm elections approach, Senate Democrats are divided over the proposed oil pipeline.
GREEN GROUPS NEED MARY LANDRIEU. Environmental groups would further their policy aims by backing Louisiana Democrat Mary Landrieu in her hotly contested Senate midterm election, according to the results of the latest National Journal energy poll. Seventy percent of respondents said that greens should jump into the race to help Landrieu keep her seat and maintain the Democratic majority in the Senate while only 30 percent of those surveyed said that if green groups support Landrieu it could actually hurt them by sending a message to other Democrats that they can take the movement's backing for granted.
Next week's National Journal Energy & Environment Insiders discussion will ask: Should consumers bear the cost to upgrade the grid? Given that it will cost upwards of $4 trillion over the next 20 years to modernize electricity, gas, and water lines, is it OK to allow utilities to tack on extra charges to customers' bills to pay for those upgrades? How can consumers voice their opinions as part of the process?
WILDFIRE EVENT. Oregon and Idaho congressional members will hold a briefing, beginning at 1:15 p.m., on the 2014 wildfire season and media availability on federal wildfire funding.
INFRASTRUCTURE EVENT. The Interstate Natural Gas Association of America will hold a briefing on a new report on midstream energy infrastructure investments needed by 2035.
]]></text></news-item>