<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E6F2-69B8-169E-F9E6"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Telstra Corporation weakens below EMAP</title><source>Global Round Up - ADRs and Depository Receipts</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ADRS AND DEPOSITORY RECEIPTS
Sponsored Telstra Corporation Limited (OT:TLSYY), the ADR market's 9th largest telecommunication company by market capitalisation, has dropped below its trend. The MACD indicator (12 day EMA less 26 day EMA) is negative -0.1, a bearish signal. The ADR fell for a second day on Friday bringing its two-day fall to 22.0c or 1.0%. The ADR price decreased 16.0c (or 0.7%) to close at US$22.67. Compared with the Bank of New York Mellon Composite ADR Index which fell 0.3 points (or 0.2%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -0.5%.
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- The Moving Average Convergence Divergence (MACD) indicator of 12-day Exponential Moving Average (EMA) of 22.89 minus the 26-day EMA of 22.94 is negative 0.06 suggesting a bearish signal. Both EMA prices are falling, another bearish signal.
Bullish SignalsOversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The Relative Strength Index (RSI) of 23.9 has breached the oversold line of 30, suggesting the price decrease of 1.9% in the last 14 days is unusually high. - The ADR is oversold according to the Williams % R indicator of -89.1, suggesting the price is close to its 14-day low of US$22.60.
NoteBeta: the Beta of Telstra Corporation ADR is 0.9. A Beta lower than 1 suggests this is a low risk, low return ADR with volatility less than that of the market. - Telstra Corporation is at a discount of 14.4% to its 12-month high of US$26.50 on 03 May, 2013. It is also at a premium of 10.6% to the 12-month low of US$20.50 on 24 Jun, 2013. - The present value of US$1,000 (PV$1000) invested one year ago in Telstra Corporation is US$1,041, including a capital loss of US$16 and dividend reinvested of US$57.

AGGREGATE VOLUMES, PRICES AND TURNOVER PERIOD [Volume Index or VI in brackets; 1 is average]US Market: TLSYY.OT 42,519 [VI of 0.4]; volume 0.2% of aggregate. Price: US$22.67. ASX: TLS.AU 23,117,605 [VI of 0.84]; volume 99.8% of aggregate. Price: $5.02. Aggregate volume: there were 23,160,124 shares worth USD105,803,689 traded. The aggregate volume was 0.84 times average trading of 27,670,815 shares.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 13: Telstra Executive Changes13 March 2014 - Telstra today expanded its executive committee appointing Mark Buckman as Group Managing Director, Media and Marketing, and Mike Wright as Group Managing Director, Networks.CEO David Thodey said Buckman and Wright would immediately join the senior executive group, which supports the CEO leadership team setting and achieving Telstra's strategic goals.Mr.Thodey said Media Group Executive Rick Ellis would leave Telstra following the completed majority sale of Sensis to Platinum Equity Group significantly reducing his portfolio.Buckman's role will be expanded to encompass all of Telstra's brand and digital media growth activities.
October 03: Telstra Corporation announces dividendTelstra Corporation today announced a cash dividend of 63.61c per share. The ex dividend date is August 23, 2013 and it is payable on September 30, 2013.
August 09: Telstra: Initial Director's Interest Notice[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Australia/Stock/News/233393.pdf
August 09: Telstra: Transcript from Full Year Fin Results - analyst briefing[News Story]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Australia/Stock/News/233268.pdfSource: Australian Securities Exchange
August 08: Telstra: Letter to Shareholders[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Australia/Stock/News/233087.pdf
August 08: Telstra: Preliminary Final Report[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Australia/Stock/News/233058.pdf
June 03: Telstra responds to media speculation[Company Release]Telstra notes speculation in the Australian Financial Review today regarding potential liability faced by Telstra in relation to the asbestos lining in its pits and pipes.In response to the speculation, Chief Executive Officer David Thodey said "We have been managing the risk of the asbestos within our network for many years.
ISIN: US87969N2045
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>