<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E810-EF23-D427-A8AA"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Letters to the editor</title><source>Hobart Mercury (Australia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Raise white flag on drug war IMAGINE this headline - "War on drugs won!" Imagining is one thing. Believing is quite another. And after nearly half a century, can anyone in their right mind seriously believe victory is any closer now than when the war was declared? Surely, the opposite is the case.
Yet we go on fighting the same unwinnable war in the same unwinnable way, as if hitting ourselves on the head with a hammer for another 50 years is going to be worth it because it will feel so much better when we stop.
There is only one thing drug criminals fear more than getting caught, and it is the idea society will find a way to make their products unsaleable, and the best way to do that is to decriminalise drug use. That is the first step, but the second and most controversial step is for society to start making drugs available to users at no cost in exchange for their participation in education and other programs aimed at helping them to break their addictions. This would render the sale of illegal drugs by criminals to addicted users virtually unprofitable, but it would involve the state becoming a de facto drug provider.
Some people will find this idea abhorrent, but if it helps drug users to overcome their addictions without the stigma of criminality hanging over their heads, and at the same time help to put drug dealers out of business, then surely the idea is worth considering.
There will be those who will want to go on trying drugs, just like they do now - illegally and without support. New users intent on becoming addicted should be the only market left for criminals to exploit, but when such users become addicted they should then be able to seek state-sanctioned support to help them break their habits. Over time, drug crime would be diminished to the point where victory in the war on drugs wouldn't just be a meaningless phrase or an unimaginable headline, but a real possibility.
Michael McCall Primrose Sands
Gateway to peninsula IN 2007, after widespread community consultation, Parks and Wildlife released the "Tasman National Park Plan" which identified the Eaglehawk Neck precinct as the preferred site for an interpretation, information and service centre for the Tasman Peninsula. The 2007 plan further recommended the Parks authority "carefully assess and provide input" concerning development on land adjoining the heritage site.
Shortly after the release of the Parks and Wildlife Tasman National Park Plan, The Resource Management and Planning Appeal Tribunal (without reference to objectors) approved a four-lot housing subdivision on the land adjoining the heritage site, which up until then had been identified as "public amenity". Seven years have passed since this planning disaster occurred and Eaglehawk Neck remains without any service facility and the residential subdivision remains unsold.
Currently about $50 million of taxpayers' money is being expended on tourism in the Tasman Peninsula (walking tracks and maintenance at the Port Arthur site). Without an "Information Service Centre" at the Eaglehawk Neck gateway to the Tasman Peninsula, the true potential of this huge investment will not be realised.
Graeme Foster Koonya
Waterfront carousel I WRITE in support of Peter and Netty Hazel (Mercury, March 14). Geelong is only one of many cities that have a carousel as a feature and Hobart could have been one of them. I have continually supported this, but sadly a decision was made not to proceed with such a proposal. I understand the comments made by the Hazels, but it will not only be our children who are saddened. Many adults would also be disappointed. People power is the only way to put the smiles on those faces. If Tasmanians want it, they will need to stand up and be counted or it will be lost.
Marti Zucco Hobart alderman
Modest increase CLAIMS by the Tasmanian Constitutional Society's Peter Chapman to restore 35 MHAs in line with population growth (Letters, March 14) lacks logic.
Firstly, the many Government Business Enterprises nowadays reduce politician job loads and, secondly, modern communication and transport mean their executive assistants can follow instructions better than in earlier decades.
However, Mr Chapman's plea to "bring parliament to the people" is worthy of action, and what more likely way to achieve balanced majority government than with two-member electorates? His wish to boost the committee system and succession planning is met by modestly enlarging the House to a 30-seat assembly.
Martin Kjar Somerset
Tearful children HERE we go again, world charities trotting out pictures of tearful children in war zones and waving the begging bowl to play on our finer sensibilities. The people of these unfortunate countries have been tribally dominated for 1000 years and have done nothing about it. They have never helped anyone in their entire history, any spare cash has gone into attacking neighbour countries and religions.
Rick Cordell Devonport
Disability shame PERHAPS we should ask why so many people on Disability Support Pension can't find help? ("Editorial", Mercury, March 11). As you report, many would be able to work with the right support. That's the crucial part of the equation that will be ignored. Cruel hearts and minds will lower the tone of the argument and those in need will be blamed. Benefits will be cut, services and help will remain elusive, and, again, our most vulnerable will suffer.
Sativa LuckusRisdon Vale
]]></text></news-item>