<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E903-CE48-B5E8-15C4"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Weekly: Catlin Group decreases 1.8% on average volume</title><source>News Bites - Western Europe: United Kingdom</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Catlin Group Ltd (L:CGL), United Kingdom's 6th largest non life insurance company by market capitalisation, decreased GBX9.50 (or 1.8%) in the trailing week to close at GBX523.50, ending a two-week streak of rises. Compared with the FTSE 100 Index which fell 184.8 points (or 2.8%) in the week, this represented a relative price increase of 1.0%. The volume was 0.9 times average trading per week of 4,095,210 shares. In the past week the market capitalisation has declined GBX3.4 billion.
Bearish SignalsOvervaluation:- The stock has a score of merely 4 out of 9 set by Joseph Piotroski [pass mark greater than or equal to 5 ]:Positive net income; positive operating cashflow; Return of Assets improvement [from 0.3% to 2.2%]; good quality of earnings [operating cashflow exceeds net income].- Return on Equity of 10.4% versus sector average of 14.1% and market average of 7.1%. - Total Liabilities/ EBITDA of 24.5 is more than or equal to 5, this compares unfavourably with Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - Return on Assets of 2.2% versus sector average of 3.0% and market average of 0.9%. Technicals:- The price tumbled 6.6% in the last month. This was on volume of 1.1 times average for the month. - Compared with the FTSE 100 Index which fell 2.0% for the month, this represented a relative price decrease of 4.6% for the month. - The price to 50-day EMAP ratio is 0.98. In the past 50 days this ratio has been under 0.98 just six times suggesting a support level. The 50-day EMAP has decreased to GBX535.47. A decrease is another bearish indicator.
The past weekBearish Signals outnumbered Bullish Signals 3:2 or 1.5 times.[All figures in GBX]
Bullish SignalsUndervaluation:- Price/Earnings of 10.3 versus sector average of 11.0 and market average of 22.5. - Price/Sales of 0.61 versus sector average of 0.8 and market average of 0.9. We estimate the shares are trading at a current year Price/Sales of 0.6 and a forward year Price/Sales of 0.5. - The Price to Book of 1.4 lower than average of 1.9 for the Total United Kingdom Market. - Dividend Yield of 5.7% (based on trailing 12 months dividends of GBX30.0) versus sector average of 4.8% and market average of 3.0%. The company paid out a dividend of GBX30.0 in the past 12 months. The 10-year bond yield is currently 3.5%. Also, the following criteria set by Benjamin Graham:--"An earnings-to-price yield of at least twice the triple-A bond"; the stock's earning yield of 9.7% is 2.8 times the triple-A bond yield of 3.5%.-"A dividend yield of at least two-thirds the triple-A bond yield"; the stock's dividend yield is 1.6 times the tripe-A bond yield of 3.5%.- Net Profit margin, EBIT margin and EBITDA margin are positive and have seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]
Technicals:- In the United Kingdom market of 1,384 stocks & 128 units traded today, the stock has a 6-month relative strength of 56 which means it has outperformed 56% of the market. - The value of GBX1,000 invested two years ago is GBX1,412, including a capital gain of GBX249 and dividend reinvested of GBX163.
Note- The stock traded between an intraweek low of GBX521.0 and a high of GBX546.50. - There were 3,644,487 shares worth GBX1.9 billion (US$32.2 million) traded. The turnover rate in the 12 months to date was 56.7%. - It is at a discount of 12.3% to the 12-month high of GBX597.0 on 22 May, 2013. It is also at a premium of 16.5% to the 12-month low of GBX449.30 on 13 Jun, 2013.
VOLUME WEIGHTED PRICE (VWP) AND TRENDThe price is at a discount of 3.8% to the 3-month volume weighted average price of GBX544.13, which may appeal as a value proposition. The Volume Weighted Price is the summation of turnover [or price at which shares were sold times the volume of shares] divided by the total volume and represents an average based on turnover of all transactions over the period. In the past week the Volume Weighted Price was GBX531.76, up from GBX529.81 in the previous week. Average daily volume of some 4,095,210 shares rose 0.03% from 4,094,110 shares. The 5-week VWP is GBX539.70. [All figures except Volume in GBX]:
ACTIVITIESCatlin Group Limited, through its subsidiaries, provides property and casualty insurance and reinsurance services worldwide. It offers insurance products and services in the areas of accident and health, aerospace, airlines, aquaculture, bloodstock and equestrian, cargo, construction and engineering, contingency, downstream and upstream energy, energy and marine liability, facultative property, general aviation, general liability, kidnap and ransom, life, livestock, marine and aviation reinsurance, marine hull, and medical malpractice and healthcare professional liability. The companys products and services also include non-marine binding, pharmaceutical product liability, political risk, political violence, product contamination, space, specie, trade credit, structured risk, motor fleet, directors' and officers' liability, and professional indemnity insurance products. Catlin Group Limited was founded in 1984 and is headquartered in Hamilton, Bermuda.
TOP MANAGEMENTThe chairman is Graham Hearne, the chief financial officer is Benjamin Meuli and the chief executive officer is Stephen Catlin.
Currency Conversion: Pence Sterling GBX1= US$0.0166 [or US$1= GBX60.24]; Against the US$ the GBX was unchanged for the day; declined 0.6% for the week; rose 1.2% for the month; advanced 8.5% in the past year. Great Britain Pound [GBP] 1 = GBX100.
ISIN: BMG196F11004
L:CGL; LON:CGL; LN:CGL;
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>