<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E926-9748-20C4-95E3"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Worker tried to warn boss of danger; Burnaby: Pipe-layer angry after no charges laid in co-worker's death after retaining wall collapse</title><source>The Vancouver Province (British Columbia)</source><author>Ian Austin, The Province</author><text><![CDATA[Twice pipe-layer Thomas Richer tried to warn his bosses that the pit he and a co-worker were in was dangerous. Twice he was told to keep working.
And minutes after the second warning he watched in horror as 27-year-old Jeff Caron was crushed to death.
Now, a WorkSafe B.C. report has pinned blame - but no criminal charges are being laid.
"That's the part I don't understand," Richer told The Province on his first visit back to the fatal work site in Burnaby. "If I steal a candy bar from a store, I'm going to get charged - but Jeff is dead and there are no charges. I want justice for Jeff."
The report cites the City of Burnaby and three other firms for a "lack of hazard recognition," and goes on to cite a lack of training, lack of communication, failing to act after Richer pointed out the danger and inadequate meetings with the workers to explain potential dangers.
On Oct. 11, 2012, Caron and Richer, 47, were laying storm and sewer lines in a trench cut in the laneway behind 4009 Edinburgh St., on the north side of Capitol Hill, where the land slopes steeply down toward Burrard Inlet.
Richer had 12 years' experience and was concerned that the line was being installed directly beside a number of pre-existing retaining walls used to shore up the Edinburgh Street properties.
It was nearly 10:45 a.m. when the pipe-laying crew returned from their coffee break and Richer spoke to the foreman about a retaining wall behind 4009 Edinburgh.
"The wall looks like it has shifted," Richer said, according to the report. According to the report, the foreman's response was, "Don't worry about it, we're going to get past this."
But they didn't get past it - the wall collapsed on the two workers, killing Caron and injuring Richer, who remains seriously traumatized.
The report says, "when (Richer) brought up this concern, work should have stopped immediately and the stability of the concrete wall should have been investigated."
Richer has a tattoo on his wrist dedicated to Caron.
"I think of Jeff every day," said Richer, who was diagnosed with post-traumatic stress disorder after watching his co-worker die.
"I shared my lunch with Jeff right over there," said Richer, pointing to a table just metres from a memorial plaque that marks the spot where Caron perished. "No one goes to jail when someone dies on the job - I just don't understand that."
The report documents how the foreman shouted to his two workers as the wall tumbled onto them.
Richer heard the shout and clambered for his life. Caron was wearing ear protection and didn't hear the shout to "get out!" The report states that twice Richer tried to draw attention to the danger - if a trench is unstable, a protective cage is introduced to prevent workers from being buried. According to the report, his initial warning eight days earlier was dismissed with the comment, "Oh, we've just got to keep going."
Caron's injuries have kept him off work ever since.
Subsequent inspection reports provided by WorkSafe B.C. show that fines are being considered for three of the four defendants - the City of Burnaby, J. Cote and Son, and Earthbitat Engineering.
In addition, compliance orders still outstanding require six actions by J. Cote, three by Burnaby and two actions by Earthbitat.
The Province tried to contact all four of the named parties.
"We have no comments at this time," said an employee of J. Cote and Son.
An employee at Vector Engineering Services said the individual involved with the project was on vacation and not available for comment.
The office of the mayor of Burnaby asked to be sent a copy of the original WorkSafe B.C. report, but at press time no one had phoned back.
A message left at Earthbitat wasn't returned by press time.
iaustin@theprovince.com twitter.com/ianaustin007
]]></text></news-item>