<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E935-7291-8C1A-7B3D"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Valley Girl - Open the barn doors</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The release of a hidden-camera video showing an Ontario turkey farmer striking a bird with a shovel several times is renewing calls( http://www.cbc.ca/news/turkey-farm-video-shows-gaping-hole-in-government-animal-welfare-oversight-1.2571451 ) for better oversight on Canadian farms.
Find the VIDEO and the reaction to its release here( http://blogs.theprovince.com/2014/03/14/video-turkey-torture-hidden-camera-video-highlights-need-for-transparency/ ).
The animal rights group( https://www.mercyforanimals.org/ ) that secretly filmed it wants "video monitoring systems installed in all facilities that handle farmed animals and footage streamed live onto the Internet" to help prevent abuse.
That's a pretty tall order - but maybe it's not as crazy as it sounds.
The video is appalling. I think anyone - turkey farmers included - will agree. The Turkey Farmers of Canada( http://www.turkeyfarmersofcanada.ca/news/article/20122-Video-Footage-%E2%80%93-Turkey-Farm-in-Ontario-/ ) called it "concerning," while the farm, Hybrid Turkeys, pledged to install video monitoring for all euthanasias in future (here's their press release( http://www.hybridturkeys.com/en/hybrid-news-centre/animal-welfare-press-release-march-2014/ ), posted a week in advance of the video's release to the public.)
Both groups are calling the alleged abuse an isolated incident. And from what I've seen on local farms, I believe it.
It's now up to farmers to prove it.
Maybe that's not fair. Maybe your grandpa didn't have to justify the way he farmed to the world.
But the way to put a stop to these hidden-camera videos by animal welfare groups is to give them nothing to film (as opposed to the approach( http://abcnews.go.com/Blotter/idaho-bill-jail-animal-activists-caught-hidden-cameras/story?id=22599192 ) being considered in some U.S. states looking at "ag gag" laws to jail activists caught wearing hidden cameras).
Traditional agriculture or commercial agriculture or whatever you want to call it is sometimes vilified. I can't count the number of times I've heard large family-run farms called "factory farms" or corporate farms. I don't really know what that term means, but it doesn't sound good.
The way to fight back is to open the barn doors.
Live-streaming to the Internet seems costly and ridiculous. Farm tours aren't always possible for bio-security reasons. Sometimes, farming is messy. Animals get sick and die.
But being transparent is easy: Run a good farm. Keep happy, healthy animals and minimize their suffering when they die. Be proud to be a farmer, and make Canada proud of the way you farm.
I've decided to collect my personal musings under the title Valley Girl. If you're more of a news hound, you may want to steer clear! The title before a post's headline (ie. News, Farm photo of the week, Review, What's in season now?) should help you find what you're looking for on the Farmgate site.
*
Do you have a story idea for the Farmgate?
Get in touch at gluymes@theprovince.com( mailto:gluymes@theprovince.com ), twitter.com/glendaluymes( https://postmediaprovince.wordpress.com/wp-admin/twitter.com/glendaluymes ) or on Facebook.
]]></text></news-item>