<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="E9CA-6256-4987-518E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Nuclear Plants Cite Climate Role In Late Push To Soften Cooling Water Rule</title><source>Inside EPA Weekly Report</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The nuclear power industry is stressing its role in providing extensive carbon-free electricity in a last-minute lobbying push to soften monitoring and technology control provisions in EPA's pending rule governing cooling water intake structures, though the industry's late push to block protections for endangered species appears to be failing.
As EPA has moved closer to issuing the rule, now due for release April 17, top industry officials, grid operators and supportive lawmakers have warned agency officials that requiring strict closed-loop cooling systems would impose costly mandates on a sector that provides a reliable power supply but is struggling to compete with cheap natural gas.
"The retirement of even a small number of nuclear units would have significant reliability and climate change implications," says a Jan. 24 letter to EPA signed by the top executives of five companies with large nuclear portfolios, Exelon Corp., PG&E Corp., Dominion, Public Service Enterprise Group and NextEra Energy. Relevant documents are available on InsideEPA.com. (Doc. ID: 2463382)
The letter adds that since October 2012, companies have announced the retirement of five reactors representing nearly 4,200 megawatts of power. If that pace continues, a quarter of the nation's nuclear fleet could shutter by 2020, causing the country to "lose over half of the progress we have made to date toward meeting President Obama's 2020 emissions reduction goal of 17 percent of 2005 emissions."
In addition to potential regulatory costs from the cooling water rule, the letter highlights continued economic viability threats the sector faces from low natural gas prices.
One of the executives, Exelon CEO Chris Crane, who is also the vice chairman of the Nuclear Energy Institute, met Feb. 20 with EPA Administrator Gina McCarthy. A company spokesman says the discussion "focused primarily on nuclear power" but declined to provide further details.
The grid operator for the mid-Atlantic region, PJM Interconnection, also wrote a Jan. 30 letter to EPA urging "that the present economic challenges facing the existing [nuclear] fleet be considered as you develop [Clean Water Act (CWA)] Section 316(b) regulations" because of the sector's role in maintaining a mix of generation sources in the region.
And a group of GOP senators echoed the industry's arguments when they called on federal wildlife regulators last month to "vacate" the ongoing consultation with EPA to ensure the final rule does not adversely affect threatened or endangered species (Inside EPA, Feb. 21).
The lawmakers argued that the Endangered Species Act (ESA) can only be addressed on a site-specific basis, and not in a national rule, adding that strict requirements could jeopardize facilities "that provide clean and low-cost power to many of our constituents," though Fish & Wildlife Service (FWS) Director Dan Ashe appeared to reject the request during recent Senate testimony.
While Ashe rejected the request to abandon the consultation, EPA Administrator Gina McCarthy is suggesting the agency will address the industry's concern. "I think they will find that when this final rule is released that we have listened very closely to their comments," she told POWERNews.
EPA in the coming weeks is set to finalize the section 316(b) regulation, which generally sets a flexible, site-specific standard for reducing the entrainment of fish eggs and larvae into cooling systems but sets a strict nationwide standard for reducing the impingement of live adult fish on the structures.
The rule is a top priority for environmentalists, who are seeking to limit mortality of aquatic species that are sucked up into cooling systems for power plants. To do this, they are pressing the agency to require closed-cycle cooling systems that limit water intake, as well as discharges of heated water.
But the energy and industrial sectors are seeking to limit any mandate for closed-cycle cooling systems that they say are costly and provide few environmental benefits. Instead, they are pushing for EPA to allow alternative technologies and continued use of once-through cooling.
The issue is particularly acute for the nuclear and coal sectors, both of which are facing major economic challenges from cheap natural gas.
Though the nuclear sector is highlighting its climate role to convince the administration that changes to the rule are needed to continue progress on its broader climate efforts, such changes would also benefit a host of other plants with a more intense greenhouse gas profile, most notably nearly 400 coal-fired plants with once-through cooling systems.
Adding to the industry's cost concerns, some plants are facing safety issues that may require costly upgrades. The St. Lucie nuclear plant in Florida is under fire over reports showing wear on more than 3,700 cooling tubes at the plant, according to the Tampa Bay Times.
The concern is that if one of the tubes bursts, it could release radioactive fluid, though plant owner Florida Power & Light (FPL), a subsidiary of NextEra, said that the plant is safe and that the wear spots are relatively shallow.
Similar cooling tube wear issues sparked the San Onofre nuclear plant in California to permanently close, though FPL argued those issues were far more extensive than the Florida plant. The majority owner of the San Onofre plant in June cited high costs to replace or fix damaged equipment and uncertainty about when federal regulators would allow the plant to operate again as reasons to close the plant.
The decision leaves one nuclear facility in California, the Diablo Canyon nuclear plant, which is located on the coast in San Luis Obispo County and must comply with the state Water Resources Control Board's once-through cooling policy by 2024 or close.
The nuclear executives' letter cites the Diablo Canyon plant, noting it "serves about 10 percent of the state's electricity needs with no greenhouse gas emissions." It argues closed-cycle cooling would cost between $9 billion and $12 billion, "providing negligible environmental benefit."
To limit potential costs, the industry and its supporters are seeking to soften a series of provisions in EPA's rule,including monitoring requirements to assess potential impacts to endangered species, requirements for repowered, replaced or rebuilt units -- which if deemed "new" units could have to install closed-loop cooling systems -- and provisions that could be interpreted to require controversial willingness to pay surveys that monetize non-use benefits when making site-specific best technology available determinations.
Those issues were among a series of requests identified in a December letter to EPA signed by the nuclear executives and others in an effort led by the Edison Electric Institute. -- Lee Logan
]]></text></news-item>