<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="EAB8-9605-E2BA-B158"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Missing plane: Piracy theory gains credence</title><source>Chicago Sun-Times</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[KUALA LUMPUR, Malaysia - Piracy and pilot suicide are among the scenarios under study as investigators grow increasingly certain the missing Malaysian Airlines jet changed course and headed west after its last radio contact with air traffic controllers.
The latest evidence suggests the plane didn't experience a catastrophic incident over the South China Sea as was initially suspected. Some experts theorize that one of the pilots, or someone else with flying experience, hijacked the plane or committed suicide by plunging the jet into the sea.
A U.S. official said Friday in Washington that investigators are examining the possibility of "human intervention" in the plane's disappearance, adding it may have been "an act of piracy." The official said it also was possible the plane may have landed somewhere. While other theories are still being examined, the official said key evidence suggesting human intervention is that contact with the Boeing 777's transponder stopped about a dozen minutes before a messaging system on the jet quit. Such a gap would be unlikely in the case of an in-flight catastrophe. London 'No common vision' on Crimea crisis Despite six hours of talks, the U.S. and Russia found "no common vision" Friday over the crisis in Ukraine, where residents in the country's strategic Crimean region are holding a secession vote this weekend. Russian Foreign Minister Sergey Lavrov made the comment after meeting with U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry in London. Lavrov made it clear that Russian President Vladimir Putin would not make any decision about what to do with Crimea - which is now under the control of Russian-backed forces - until after Sunday's vote. Kerry, however, said Washington and the international community won't recognize the outcome of the referendum. paris Terrible pollution in France Air pollution that has turned the skies over Paris a murky yellow and shrouded much of Belgium for days forced drivers to slow down Friday. The belt of smog stretched for hundreds of miles, from France's Atlantic coast to Belgium and well into Germany. It was the worst air pollution France has seen since 2007, the European Environment Agency said. The smog is particularly severe because France has an unusually high number of diesel vehicles, whose nitrogen oxide fumes mix with ammonia from springtime fertilizers and form particulate ammonium nitrate. Pollutants from the burning of dead leaves and wood contribute as well. new haven, Conn. Dad won't be charged for shooting masked son A popular fifth-grade teacher will not face prosecution for fatally shooting a knife-wielding prowler in a ski mask who turned out to be his 15-year-old son, a prosecutor announced Friday. Investigators were unable to determine why the boy was outside after midnight wearing a ski mask and carrying a flip-style knife with the blade open and a roll of duct tape under his arm. seattle FBI balks at pot background checks The FBI is refusing to run nationwide background checks on people applying to run legal marijuana businesses in Washington state, even though it has conducted similar checks in Colorado - a discrepancy that illustrates the quandary the Justice Department faces as it allows the states to experiment with regulating a drug that's long been illegal under federal law. The Justice Department declined to explain why it isn't conducting the checks in Washington when it has in Colorado. New york Federal review blasts N.Y. commuter railroad Metro-North, the nation's second-largest commuter railroad, allowed safety to erode while pushing to keep its trains on time, resulting in a lax culture of inadequate inspections, poor training and inappropriate cellphone use, according to a stinging federal report prompted by the Dec. 1 derailment in the Bronx that killed four passengers and injured about 70 others. deerfield beach, Fla. Leavenworth escapee caught 37 years later In the nearly 40 years after he escaped from the maximum-security military prison at Fort Leavenworth, convicted killer James Robert Jones carved out a new life for himself in Florida, living under an assumed name, getting married and working for an air conditioning company.It all came to an end this week when Jones - or Bruce Walter Keith, as the former Army private was known in Florida - was recaptured.
]]></text></news-item>