<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="EAB9-9F4B-BAA9-4748"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>As Crews Search for Survivors, They Discover Only More Victims</title><source>The New York Times</source><author>By MARC SANTORA and WILLIAM K. RASHBAUM; Reporting was contributed by Patrick McGeehan, Kate Pastor, Eli M. Rosenberg, Michael Schwirtz, Nate Schweber, Kate Taylor and Julie Turkewitz.</author><text><![CDATA[Firefighters and emergency personnel on Thursday dug deeply into the wreckage of two buildings in East Harlem that were leveled in a powerful explosion, looking for survivors and possible evidence of what caused the blast.
But as they cut into a mountain of twisted metal, brick and wood, they found only more victims.
The death toll rose to eight, as four more bodies were found overnight and one later on Thursday. One of the victims was so badly burned that the person could not be identified.
The search for the cause of the gas leak -- which a preliminary investigation indicates touched off the collapse of the buildings on Park Avenue near 116th Street on Wednesday morning -- was equally elusive, even as new details emerged about the explosion.
Two agents for the Federal Bureau of Investigation saw the blast blow out the front of the piano store located at 1646 Park Avenue, according to two city officials briefed on their statements.
The agents, whose vehicle happened to be at a red light almost directly in front of the buildings, said the building at 1644, which housed the Spanish Christian Church, then collapsed pancake-style, with each successive floor quickly giving way and crumbling into the floor beneath it, the officials said.
The adjacent building, 1646, was next, the walls of each floor falling like dominoes, each floor then giving way to the next.
''It certainly looked like 1644 went first, and the theory is that it must've emanated from the basement of 1644, based on the nontechnical investigation, based on structural damage and witness accounts,'' one of the two city officials said.
One former church member said the basement had a full kitchen, where potluck lunches were served after service each Sunday.
The agents were hospitalized with non-life-threatening injuries, according to an F.B.I. spokesman. Among the dozens injured, two people, including a 15-year-old boy, remained in critical condition.
About 70 people who live in seven neighboring buildings were not allowed to go home on Thursday because their power had been cut off; the authorities could not say when they would be able to return.
Many families, including 51 children, gathered at a Red Cross shelter set up in a Salvation Army building at 125th Street and Third Avenue. Military-style cots were unfolded and clustered into family groups. The stress and tension were obvious, with word filtering in that loved ones had died.
Some families made a painful trip to the medical examiner's office to provide information that might help with identification; others held out hope for a miraculous rescue.
One woman, who declined to be identified, arrived at the office saying she was looking for her cousin, who lived in one of the two buildings. Officials told her they would not stop looking.
Some residents said they had smelled gas the night before the explosion, or even earlier.
With those assertions continuing on Thursday and residents claiming that firefighters, the police and Consolidated Edison workers had come to the area last week to investigate possible gas leaks, city officials insisted that the one and only warning came too late -- less than 20 minutes before the blast.
City officials said they had reviewed calls to 311 in the preceding 30 days and found no reports of suspected gas leaks from anywhere on the block.
Additionally, Con Edison officials said they had reviewed 10 years of records on the history of the gas main beneath that street.
There were only two reported cases of work being done -- in 2011, when 70 feet of pipe was replaced, and in 2004, when coupling on the pipe was replaced. They also investigated reports of leaks going back three years and found only two incidents, the last on May 17. Both involved leaks in residential apartments and were fixed, the utility said.
The harsh winter weather might have played a role in rupturing the gas line, officials said.
The majority of the pipe that runs beneath the street in that area is cast iron and was laid more than a century ago. The utility says it surveys all gas mains in the city every year and, with the older cast-iron pipes, is attentive to the effects of cold weather, which can cause the ground to heave and damage the them.
When the city was plunged into a deep freeze in February, two inspections were conducted on the street where the blast took place. No problems were found.
Mark McDonald, who investigates gas explosions, said the accumulation of frost beneath streets and subsequent thawing could cause cast-iron gas mains to move and break suddenly. After a hard freeze, the gas that leaks out from a broken main could become trapped under a cap of frost a few inches thick, he said.
Prevented from rising up through the street and dissipating, the escaping gas could migrate into the basement of an adjacent building. Often, Mr. McDonald said, large furnaces suck air into basements. If gas has collected nearby, it, too, could be drawn into a basement, where any flame or spark could cause it to explode, he said.
''Gas wants to rise; it's lighter than air,'' said Mr. McDonald, the president of NatGas Consulting in Boston. ''If there's a layer of frost, it acts as an actual cap and blocks the gas from being able to leak into the atmosphere. Instead, it goes sideways.''
Investigators were also looking into the possibility that a water main break, which caused a large sinkhole to form in front of the buildings, might have played a role in rupturing a gas line, officials said.
Mayor Bill de Blasio said it was too early to say whether the water main broke before or after the explosion.
The Department of Environmental Protection, which maintains water pipes, said it had no reports of a leak before the explosion. It was first notified of a problem when firefighters saw water bubbling up beneath the wreckage.
Whatever the cause, the explosion renewed focus on the safety of some of the city's aging infrastructure. ''Areas with old and vulnerable infrastructure describes a lot of New York City,'' Mr. de Blasio said.
Robert L. Sumwalt III, the member of the National Transportation Safety Board at the scene, said that unlike other natural gas explosions he has investigated, the main pipe, running under Park Avenue, remained intact.
''There is no apparent leak location,'' he said.
Once the site is secured, officials would run a pressure test to find the source of the leak.
It could be some time before that test because firefighters were still working to clear the debris, often a very delicate operation.
''What we need to do is get to the basement,'' Fire Commissioner Salvatore J. Cassano said. There, he said, investigators would look at ''places that could possibly be a source of ignition or a source of the leak and then work our way back towards the street.''
Even as officials searched for answers as to what caused the blast, hundreds of firefighters, construction workers and emergency personnel continued to sift through the wreckage.
Edward S. Kilduff, the chief of department for the Fire Department, said firefighters were still working as if on a ''potential rescue operation.''
''There's always a possibility of someone being alive -- if someone is in a somewhat protected area and wasn't exposed to smoke, perhaps on lower floor,'' he said.
The dead were identified by relatives and Mexican officials as Griselde Camacho, 44; Andreas Panagopoulos, 43; Carmen Tanco, 67; and a mother and daughter, Rosaura Barrios Vazquez, 43, and Rosaura Hernandez Barrios, 22.
Firefighters have used video and audio probes to reach into gaps in the rubble in search of victims, Mr. Kilduff said. Because most of the floors fell on top of each other, there were few gaps to search, he said.
Progress had been slowed because between the collapsed floors, he said, the fires were still burning.
http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/14/nyregion/east-harlem-building-collapse.html
]]></text></news-item>