<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="EADC-AD5D-87D3-7C4D"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Court News</title><source>Rushville Republican (Indiana)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[CIRCUIT COURT
Marriage Applications
David Lee Burns, 30, of Carthage, and Elizabeth Lou Irene Swincher, 26, of Carthage.
Richard Michael Lemen, 44, of Rushville, and Sherri Lynn Messer, 41, of Rushville.
Judgments
GE Capital Retail Bank vs. Emily Adams, $3,068.99 judgment plus court cost and interest.
Portfolio Recovery Associates LLC vs. Sunshine M. Noe, $5,058.43 judgment plus court cost and interest.
Marriage Decrees
In re the marriage of Phyllis and Norman Mahan, dissolution of marriage decree.
Criminal Action
State of Indiana vs. Craig C. Thomas on a class "A" misdemeanor charge of operating a motor vehicle after driving privileges were suspended (with a prior conviction within 10 years). Guilty by admission of guilt or plea agreement to unspecified charge(s).
SUPERIOR COURT
Judgments
Collection Associates LLC vs. Ashlee Cress, $2,690.74 judgment plus court cost, interest, $107.74 prejudgment interest and $580 attorney fees.
- vs. Joshua D. Snyder, $1,853.65 judgment plus court cost, interest $75.97 prejudgment interest and $270 attorney fees.
Asset Acceptance LLC vs. Monica D> Fussner, $5,835.63 judgment plus court cost and interest.
Credigy Receivable Inc. assignee of First Select Inc., vs. Michelle Houston, $2,807.60 judgment plus court cost and interest.
State of Indiana vs. Donald J. McCullough, $1,368 judgment plus interest.
Discover Bank vs. Angela Weatherspoon, $13,221.83 judgment plus court cost and interest.
Criminal Action
State of Indiana vs. Rebecca L. Pollitt on class "A" misdemeanor charges of possession of marijuana and possession of drug paraphernalia. Guilty by admission of guilt or plea agreement to unspecified charge(s).
- vs. Clint M. Edwards on charges of unlawful possession of a syringe (class "D" felony), and class "C" misdemeanor charges of operating a motor vehicle while intoxicated and OWI with a schedule l or ll controlled substance or its metabolite in the body. Guilty by admission of guilt or plea agreement to unspecified charge(s).
- vs. Stephanie L. Counceller on class "D" felony charges of possession of a schedule l, ll, lll or lV controlled substance ad unlawful possession of a syringe and possession of drug paraphernalia (class "A" misdemeanor. Guilty by admission of guilt or plea agreement to unspecified charge(s).
- vs. John M. Wilson on class "C" misdemeanor charges of operating a motor vehicle while intoxicated and OWI with a schedule l or ll controlled substance or its metabolite in the body and possession of marijuana (class "A" misdemeanor). Guilty by admission of guilt or plea agreement to unspecified charge(s).
- vs. Chad J. Dishman on charges of dealing methamphetamine (class "B" felony), possession of methamphetamine (class "D" felony), possession of two or more precursors with the intent to manufacture a controlled substance, resisting law enforcement (class "A" misdemeanor) and maintaining a common nuisance (class "D" felony). Guilty by admission of guilt or plea agreement to unspecified charge(s).
- vs. Suzette E. Williams on charges of possession of methamphetamine (class "D" felony) and dealing methamphetamine (class "B" felony). Guilty by admission of guilt or plea agreement to unspecified charge(s).
- vs. Donald J. McCullough on class "B" felony charges of dealing methamphetamine, possession of methamphetamine, possession of two or more precursors with the intent of manufacturing a controlled substance (class "C" felony), passion of marijuana (class "D" felony) and unlawful possession of a syringe (class "D" felony). Guilty by admission of guilt or plea agreement to unspecified charge(s).
- vs. Dalton K. Mull on class "D" felony charges of possession of methamphetamine and unlawful possession of a syringe. Guilty by admission of guilt or plea agreement to unspecified charge(s).
- vs. Diane E. Giden on charge of operating a motor vehicle while intoxicated with a blood alcohol content of .08 percent or greater. Guilty by admission of guilt or plea agreement to unspecified charge(s).
- vs. James F. Davis on charges of operating a motor vehicle while intoxicated (class "D" felony) and OWI with a schedule l or ll controlled substance or its metabolite in the body (class "C" misdemeanor). Guilty by admission of guilt or plea agreement to unspecified charge(s).
- vs. Derrek P. Cleveland on charges of disorderly conduct (class "B" misdemeanor), resisting law enforcement (class "A" misdemeanor) and public intoxication endangering a person (class "B" misdemeanor). Guilty by admission of guilt or plea agreement to unspecified charge(s).
Marriage Decrees
In re the marriage of Ronnie and Julie Gardner, dissolution of marriage decree.
In re the marriage of Julie and Todd Lawhome, dissolution of marriage decree.
]]></text></news-item>