<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="EB1A-D4AB-A91A-5A98"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Legal Notices</title><source>The Oak Ridger (Tennessee)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[PUBLIC NOTICE INVITATION TO BID Oak Ridge Schools is seeking qualified bids for the District's Annual Paper Order.
Bids will be accepted until 2:00 p.m. on 3/28/14. Bid information can be obtained from the Oak Ridge Schools website www.ortn.edu.If you have any questions contact Amy Moore at 865-425-9005 or by e-mail at admoore@ortn.edu NOTICE OF PUBLIC HEARING 2014 ANNUAL AGENCY PLAN CLINTON HOUSING AUTHORITY
Notice is hereby given to the residents of the Clinton Housing Authority, the citizens of Clinton, and all persons interested, that the housing authority is required by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD), and Section 511 of the Quality Housing and Work Responsibility Act of 1998 Interim Rule to submit a Public Housing Agency Plan.
Further, the Agency Plan shall consist of an Annual Plan for the upcoming fiscal year 2014. The Annual Plan provides details about the housing authority 's immediate operations, program participants, programs and services, and the housing authority's strategy for handling operational concerns, residents' concerns and needs, programs and services for the upcoming fiscal year.
Prior to submission of the Agency Plan to HUD, we are soliciting comments and suggestions.
We will be conducting a Public Hearing on Tuesday, April 1, 2014 at 6:30 p.m., at Clinton Housing Authority, 825 McAdoo Street, Clinton, Tennessee, to discuss the proposed plans. All residents are encouraged to attend.
If you are unable to attend the meeting, you may submit written comments regarding the Annual Agency Plan to Josh Hinman, Executive Director, Clinton Housing Authority, 825 McAdoo Street, Clinton, TN 37716.
Written comments will be received through Tuesday, April 1, 2014 at 4:30 p.m. Estate of Joseph Thomas Thomas, Late of Anderson County, Tennessee.
Notice is hereby given that on February 26, 2014 Letters in respect to the Estate of Joseph Thomas Thomas deceased, who died January 22, 2014 were issued to the undersigned by the Clerk and Master of the Chancery-Probate Court of Anderson County, Tennessee.
All persons, resident and non-resident, having claims, mature or unmatured against the Estate are required to file the same in triplicate with the Clerk and Master of the above named Court on or before the earlier of the dates prescribed in (1) or (2) otherwise their claims will be forever barred.
(1) (A) Four (4) months from the date of the first publication (or posting as the case may be) of this notice if the creditor received an actual copy of this notice to creditors at least sixty (60) days before the date that is four (4) months from the date of the first publication (or posting); or (B) Sixty (60) days from the date the creditor received an actual copy of the notice to creditors if the creditor received the copy of the notice less than sixty (60) days prior to the date that is four (4) months from the date of first publication (or posting) as described in (1) (A); or (2) Twelve (12) months from the decedent's date of death.
All persons indebted to the above Estate must come forward and make proper settlement with the undersigned at once.
This February 26, 2014 Joseph Daniel Thomas Personal Representative STEVE R. QUEENER CLERK AND MASTER BY: Angela Buck, Deputy Clerk Estate of Joseph Thomas Thomas 16 Laurel Place Norris, Tn 37828 Robert W. Wilkinson Attorney NOTICE TO CREDITORS (As required by TCA 30-2-306 as amended by Chapter 886, Public Acts of Tennessee) Docket No. 14PB0050 Estate of Charles F. Baes, Jr., Late of Anderson County, Tennessee.
Notice is hereby given that on February 26, 2014 Letters in respect to the Estate of Charles F. Baes, Jr. deceased, who died January 26, 2014 were issued to the undersigned by the Clerk and Master of the Chancery-Probate Court of Anderson County, Tennessee.
All persons, resident and non-resident, having claims, mature or unmetered against the Estate are required to file the same in triplicate with the Clerk and Master of the above named Court on or before the earlier of the dates prescribed in (1) or (2) otherwise their claims will be forever barred.
(1) (A) Four (4) months from the date of the first publication (or posting as the case may be) of this notice if the creditor received an actual copy of this notice to creditors at least sixty (60) days before the date that is four (4) months from the date of the first publication (or posting); or (B) Sixty (60) days from the date the creditor received an actual copy of the notice to creditors if the creditor received the copy of the notice less than sixty (60) days prior to the date that is four (4) months from the date of first publication (or posting) as described in (1) (A); or (2) Twelve (12) months from the decedent's date of death.
All persons indebted to the above Estate must come forward and make proper settlement with the undersigned at once.
This February 26, 2014 Charles F. Baes, III Personal Representative STEVE R. QUEENER CLERK AND MASTER BY: Angela Buck, Deputy Clerk Estate of Charles F. Baes, Jr. 102 Berwick Dr Oak Ridge, Tn 37830 Robert W. Wilkinson Attorney
]]></text></news-item>