<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="EC0E-C901-2448-AC59"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Secret to ending pilferage lies in strengthening procurement law</title><source>Daily Nation (Kenya)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Institutions award tenders to incompetent and unreliable companies at very high costs.
The public procurement system in Kenya lacks effectiveness in ensuring the public sector gets maximum value for money.
The government risks making greater loses through procurements that are neither fair nor transparent unless more reforms are implemented.
Despite the reforms through the creation of the PPOA, provisions of law are ignored. Regulations in the supplier manual are regularly breached, the tenders awarded are weak and unreliable, and the tender documents are sub standard.
Institutions award tenders to incompetent and unreliable companies at very high costs. Corruption through bribery, blackmail and contact with influential people takes precedence. No wonder most construction projects on roads and in public institutions such as schools normally stall.
The suppliers down their tools and no legal action can be taken against them since the procurement transaction did not observe the law.
Recently, the Sh24.6 billion laptop tender for Standard One pupils was cancelled after an appeal board found the award to an Indian firm questionable.
The tender documents never meet the quality threshold after being done in an unskilled manner deficient of important details. Consequently, the services accorded are poor, and the result is not equivalent to the cost.
Proper procurement will assist the government save millions.
Harsh penalties to those who breach the guidelines in the public procurement act should put in place. It will discourage those involved in corruption.
Tender documents should be cross-checked thoroughly by relevant bodies before issuance.
The documents should specify the conditions for participation, specify the technical specification, the nature and scope of the service, and detail the information and documents to submit. These assist a potential supplier to evaluate its abilities.
Most importantly, procurement entities should evaluate the legal, commercial, technical and financial abilities of a supplier.
GRACE MUMBI GITAU, Maseno
]]></text></news-item>