<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="EC85-B136-F4E8-F87B"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Board member offers to resign; She says she meant no offense, wants focus to stay on village's issues.</title><source>Palm Beach Post (Florida)</source><author> By Kristen M. Daum   Palm Beach Post Staff Writer </author><text><![CDATA[The embattled planning board member who gave the Hitler salute during a public meeting last week has offered her resignation.
Wellington village leaders, employees and residents have expressed outrage since Marcia Radosevich referenced the Nazi dictator during a Planning, Zoning & Adjustment Board meeting March 5, when she directed the gesture at the village's planning director.
In a letter late Thursday to the Wellington Village Council, Radosevich apologized for her actions and said, "Although I have been asked to remain on the PZAB, I am offering my resignation ... so that the public and the village council can focus on important issues regarding the government's responsibilities to us."
It's unclear whether the village council must vote to accept her resignation. Village hall is closed on Fridays.
Councilman Matt Willhite, who appointed Radosevich to the planning board in 2012, said Friday her resignation is "probably for the best."
"We've gotten emails on it," he said. "This should put the matter to rest."
Prior to receiving her resignation, village council members were already taking steps to discuss the controversy at their next meeting March 25 and possibly vote on whether Radosevich should stay on the planning board. Members of the village's citizen advisory boards are volunteers who serve at the pleasure of council. They can be removed by a majority vote of the board.
In her letter, Radosevich said she will make a donation to the Anti-Defamation League "as a gesture of where my heart and mind reside." Radosevich, 61, is a wealthy entrepreneur, originally from Boston.
She said she recognizes "the horror of Nazi Germany" and has "been the subject of anti-Semitism and would never intentionally subject another person to that experience." She added that her grandfather was interned in a concentration camp and her father, a World War II veteran, suffered post traumatic stress syndrome from fighting the Nazis.
"There is no excuse for using such an offensive symbol any more than using offensive language," she wrote.
Councilwoman Anne Gerwig said Radosevich's donation is "a very noble gesture."
"I appreciate her not wanting this controversy to continue," Gerwig said.
Radosevich attempted to explain herself in her letter, writing that "my reaction was prompted by the complete and utter frustration of trying to work with the staff."
"After spending countless hours analyzing the proposed code amendments drafted by staff, after listening for over four hours to staff continuing to evade, misconstrue and misrepresent what they were trying to do, the truth finally came out: The proposal would concentrate power for many land-use and zoning decisions in one person," Radosevich wrote.
"That shook me to my very core. I grew up with a healthy respect for the democratic process and a healthy fear of threats against it."
Radosevich gave the Hitler salute about three hours into a nearly four-hour discussion about village staff members' authority to approve applications for development projects.
Tim Stillings, the village's planning and development services director, was proposing to allow planning and engineering staff to make decisions more openly outside the confines of the village's Development Review Committee.
He stated repeatedly throughout the meeting that the policy change would not change how decisions are made, because project applications are either approved or denied based on existing standards. Neither the Development Review Committee nor staff votes to approve project applications, he said.
kdaum@pbpost.com Twitter: @kristendaum
The Salute
The Palm Beach Post' first reported that Marcia Radosevich, a member of Wellington's Planning, Zoning & Adjustment Board, was facing criticism after she likened the village's planning director to Adolf Hitler during a public meeting March 5. She gave the Nazi dictator's salute and said "Heil Hitler" while the board was discussing the powers of village staff members.
]]></text></news-item>