<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="EC9D-D028-6096-718E"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Oman Cables Industry increases on thin volume</title><source>News Bites - Middle East and North Africa: Oman</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Oman Cables Industry (MSM:OCAI), Oman's largest industrial company by market capitalisation, increased 0.50 Baisa (or 0.2%) to close at OMR2.44, ending a two-day streak of losses. Compared with the Muscat Securities Market Index which rose 8.5 points (or 0.1%) in the day, this represented a relative price increase of 0.1%. The volume was 0.7 times the average trading of 79,135 shares.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Oman Cables Industry, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/00105144174031494
Bullish SignalsUptrend- Rises to Falls: in the past month the number of rises outnumbered falls 10:4 or 2.5:1.- The 3.0% discount to 12-month high of OMR2.52 against the 73.4% premium to 12-month low of OMR1.41 suggests the stock continues to push for new highs. - In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week high fifteen times, pointing to a significant uptrend. - The present value of OMR1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Oman Cables Industry is OMR1,686, for a capital gain of OMR686.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Return on Equity 22.0% [16.5%].- Return on Assets 8.8% [4.3%].- Return on Capital Employed 22.4% [14.2%].Other Bullish Signals:- Interest cover defined by EBIT/I is 13.9 times. This indicates it is less leveraged. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 1.5. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued.- As per the Du Pont analysis, Return on Equity is high at 22.0%. This is computed as net profit margin of 5.0% times asset turnover [sales/assets] of 1.8 times leverage factor [total assets/shareholders' equity] of 2.5. Also, this has improved from 14.6% last year.
- Net Profit margin, EBIT margin and EBITDA margin are positive and have seen consecutive rises in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 58,200 shares worth OMR142,299 (US$369,650) traded. Beta: the Beta of Oman Cables Industry stock is 1.6. A Beta greater than 1 suggests this is a high risk, high return stock with volatility greater than that of the market.Bearish Signals:Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Overvaluation:- Price/Earnings of 13 [11.3]. - Price/Sales of 0.7 [0.5]. - Price to Book of 3.8 [1.9].Other Bearish Signals:- Total Liabilities/ EBITDA of 5.3 is more than or equal to 5, this compares unfavourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - Net profit margin has averaged 3.9% in the last 3 years. This suggests the company is less profitable with a low margin of safety.- Net Profit margin is positive but falling in recent quarters.[Quarter ended, all figures in %]

COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:March 14: Oman Cables Industry appoints AuditorOman Cables Industry has appointed Deloitte & Touche (M.E) & Co. as Auditor. The effective date is March 12, 2014.
February 27: Oman Cables Industry announces AGMOman Cables Industry has announced its Annual General Meeting will take place on March 12, 2014.
February 27: Oman Cables Industry announces EGMOman Cables Industry has announced its Extra Ordinary General Meeting will take place on March 12, 2014.
January 23: OCI Board approves Audited Financial Results for 2013[News Story] The Board of Directors of Oman Cables Industry (SAOG), in the meeting held on 22 January 2014, approved the audited Financial Statements for the year 2013 of the Parent Company and the Group and recommended the same for approval to the Shareholders at the Annual General Meeting.Highlights of Financial Statements for the group are as follows:- Sales of 2013 were RO 306.1 million compared to RO 257.2 million in 2012, a increase of 19%- Net Profit after tax was RO 16.9 million in 2013 compared to RO 11.9 in 2012, a increase of 41.8%- Earning per share (Face Value RO 0.100) was RO 0.188 in 2013 compared to RO 0.133 in 2012- Net asset per share (Face Value RO 0.100) increased to RO 0.760 on 31 December 2013 compared to RO 0.653 on 31 December 2012The Board recommended cash dividend of RO 0.088 per share of the face value of RO 0.100, to be approved by the Shareholders at the Annual General Meeting
Source: Muscat Securities Market
January 08: Oman Cables Industry: Update on the Individual Labor Complaint[News Story]Following the disclosure made on 12 September 2013 on an individual labor complaint filed against the company before the Department of labor disputes in the Ministry of Manpower which included a claim for unfair dismissal and various compensation elements totaling more than ten million Omani riyals.The company is updating the shareholders that no settlement was reached before the Department of labor disputes in the Ministry of Manpower and that the case is referred to the labor department in the Primary Court in Seeb.The company will update the shareholders on this topic.
Source: Muscat Securities Market
October 24: Oman Cables Industry: Update on OAPIL expansion project[News Story]"Further to the Company's [public disclosure dated 24 July 2012] regarding OAPIL's Expansion Project (Oman Aluminium Processing Industries Limited LLC) (subsidiary company), the Company hereby reports on the status of the Project as follows:The Company has reaffirmed its in-principle approval for the Project subject to receiving the necessary pre-approvals".
Source: Muscat Securities Market
October 23: Oman Cables Industry: Unaudited Financial Statements for nine month period ended 30 September 2013[News Story] The meeting of Board of Directors of Oman Cables Industry (SAOG) was held on 22 October 2013 at the office in Rusayl. The unaudited Financial Statements of the parent and the group of Oman Cables Industry (SAOG) for nine month period ended 30 September 2013 were approved in the meeting.Oman Cables (Parent) Performance:The Net Profit after tax for the nine month period ended 30 September 2013 was Rial Omani 11.8 million compared to Rial Omani 6.9 million during the same period in 2012, an increase of 71.1%.
ISIN: OM0000001707
OM:OCAI
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>