<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="ECBD-193F-660C-8E5E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Second trial date rescheduled for convicted El Paso lawyer</title><source>El Paso Times (Texas)</source><author>By Adriana M. Chávez achavez@elpasotimes.com @AChavezEPTimes on Twitter</author><text><![CDATA[Lawyers for an El Paso attorney convicted of participating in a money laundering scheme for a Mexican drug cartel have withdrawn from the case two weeks before his second trial.
However, documents tied to the request are sealed.
Attorneys Ray Velarde and Richard Esper who represented Marco Antonio Delgado, 47, have been allowed to withdraw. Their reasons were sealed by Senior U.S. District Judge David Briones.
The matter was scheduled for a hearing Thursday. According to federal court documents, the case has been referred to a federal magistrate judge to appoint new attorneys for Delgado.
In January, Briones sentenced Delgado to 20 years in prison after a jury convicted him to conspiring to launder up to $600 million for the Mileno drug cartel in 2007 and 2008. The cartel has since been dismantled.
A second jury trial for Delgado had been scheduled to begin March 31 in an unrelated case. Delgado is also charged with three counts of wire fraud and 16 money-laundering charges stemming from a case linked to Mexico's state-owned electricity utility the Comision Federal de Electricidad.
An indictment alleged that Delgado was representing FGG Enterprises in a deal with Mexico's federal electricity commission for the acquisition and maintenance of equipment for a power plant in Agua Prieta, Sonora.
Delgado is accused of submitting fraudulent wire transfer requests to the electricity commission that resulted in $32 million being deposited in a bank account that Delgado had in the Turks and Caicos islands. Authorities alleged that $1.9 million was then transferred from the island bank account to banks in El Paso, Pittsburg and Taos, N.M.
If convicted, Delgado faces 10 to 20 years in prison on each of the pending counts. Court records show Briones has postponed Delgado's upcoming trial date but has not yet rescheduled it.
Delgado, a lawyer with expertise in energy and international law, was a former Carnegie Mellon University trustee who once donated a $250,000 endowment for a scholarship for Hispanic students.
Adriana M. Chcvez may be reached at 546-6117.
]]></text></news-item>