<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="ECC2-9FCE-C7FF-E975"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>'Anarchist' ODs on comic barrage; Theater review</title><source>The San Francisco Chronicle (California)</source><author>Robert Hurwitt</author><text><![CDATA[RATING: POLITE APPLAUSEAccidental Death of an Anarchist: Farce. By Dario Fo. Directed by Christopher Bayes. Through April 20. Berkeley Rep's Roda Theatre, 2015 Addison St., Berkeley. Two hours, 15 minutes. $29-$99, subject to change. 510 647-2949. www.berkeleyrep.org.
Steven Epp doesn't tell jokes. He embodies one comic morsel after another or several on top of each other so thickly that your brain can't possibly keep up because you're laughing too hard. And he's far from alone in the hilarious ensemble of the "Accidental Death of an Anarchist" that opened Wednesday at Berkeley Repertory Theatre.
It's a feast of foolishness, a fairly rare look at one of Nobel Prize winner Dario Fo's most notable plays, and a welcome return by the inspired comic actor of "The Miser" and "Figaro." But it's also a conundrum. As packed with inventive comedy as director Christopher Bayes' Berkeley-Yale Repertory Theatre co-production is, it's more exhausting than energizing.
It may be too anarchic or too topically Italian, problems that have plagued most American productions of "Anarchist" - with the bright exception of the 1984 Eureka Theatre version directed by Tony Taccone now the Rep's artistic director, adapted by Joan Holden and starring Geoff Hoyle. But even that one couldn't replicate the particularity that made the farce more than a theatrical sensation in Italy.
First staged in 1970, "Anarchist" was Fo's remarkably immediate response to the 1969 death of an anarchist who "fell" from a police station window while being interrogated as a suspect in the bombing of a bank in Milan that killed 16 people. In what Fo called a "tragic farce," a Maniac Epp in the role Fo wrote for himself, arrested for fraud, becomes an avenging investigator in the same station, exposing police brutality, corruption and widespread collusion with the neo-fascist gangs responsible for a plague of such bombings in Italy at the time.
This is farce as a potent political act - in conditions impossible to replicate here. Bayes and his terrific actors have adapted, updated and Americanized Gavin Richards' 1979 British adaptation from Gillian Hanna's translation, filling it with current pop culture lampoons and gibes at everything from "Bush-Cheney" waterboarding to Berkeley self-righteousness.
It's an almost nonstop laugh riot of brilliant solo turns and musical comedy or operatic quartets under Aaron Halva's infectious music direction. It's a wildly meta-theatrical romp - "Up against the audience," one gun-wielding cop commands - presented on an artfully run-down police station set.
Stage stereotypes abound, from Jesse J. Perez's song-and-dance mafioso Inspector Bertozzo to Allen Gilmore's black-sidekick-like Inspector Pissani and Liam Craig's homicidal Superintendent. Renata Friedman is brilliant as a sexy-tough, remarkably fast-tongued feminist journalist, as is Eugene Ma as two identically childlike Constables with angelic falsettos.
Bayes and Epp build on Fo's conceit that Maniac suffers from "histrionic mania" - an uncontrollable urge to act many parts - to create an extended tour de farce of instant thumbnail characterizations. He packs almost infinite personalities -sometimes three at once - into astonishing streams of free-association riffs, at one point delivering a retrospective of Marlon Brando's career in a split-second aside.
It's breathtakingly funny, but it isn't anchored to a serious purpose that invests us in the story's outcome. In place of Fo's political analysis, we get a laundry list of issues on which most of us already agree, making us feel not so much engaged in the comedy as relentlessly tickled by it.
]]></text></news-item>