<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="ED59-33F3-2F45-E8BD"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Gun discovered at thrift store leads to tragic, deadly accident</title><source>Chicago Tribune</source><author>Barbara Brotman</author><text><![CDATA[There she is, in photographs, leaning against a lamp, lovely in a strapless black top in one shot, grinning in a black leather jacket in the other.
But sitting down to dinner with her husband, giving their daughter a ride home from school, getting ready for her weekly stint at her church caring for kids she called "my children" -- there she will never be again.
Carmen Dominguez, 55, was buried Friday, a week after she was killed in a freak occurrence at the thrift store where she worked.
She and a colleague at the Unique Thrift Store at 9341 S. Ashland Ave. were sorting donated clothes when the other worker came upon a sock with something inside it.
He emptied the sock into his hand, according to police, and a .22-caliber handgun tumbled out. The gun discharged, striking Dominguez in the chest.
She was pronounced dead at Advocate Christ Medical Center in Oak Lawn.
Police ruled the shooting an accident.
Inside a small house on a Bridgeview cul-de-sac, the accident led to grief.
One day in the week that followed the shooting, Victor Campos, Dominguez's husband of 12 years, sat at the dining room table and took out two small black velvet boxes. They held pins she had been given for years of service to Unique Thrift Stores.
She had worked at the for-profit thrift store chain for 25 years.
She had spent decades sorting and pricing items at its thrift stores. Her specialty was pricing. Her expertise was so highly regarded that at one point Unique promoted her to become a traveling pricer, charged with training new hires and less-skilled employees at various stores.
"She knew what the customers were looking for and how to price the items accordingly so they can sell," said Martine Lewis, district manager of Unique's North Side locations, who knew and worked with Dominguez for 20 years.
"She had a lot of thrift store knowledge," said Gisela Martinez, a former Unique employee who worked with her there. "She liked to go around to check on the competition. ... She was always looking out for the company."
Her husband doesn't think the company was looking out for her. He says Unique pushed its workers to sort clothes too quickly and did not do enough to ensure their safety.
"You go to a school, they have metal detectors," he said. "This was a tragic accident, but it could have been avoided."
Sara Gaugl, spokeswoman for Savers Inc., the for-profit thrift store chain that acquired Unique Thrift Stores in 2011, said "the safety of our team members is our top priority, and never before has such a tragic accident occurred in any of our stores.
"We do not knowingly accept as donations weapons of any kind. We are cooperating with the Chicago police in their investigation of this incident, which they have also identified as an accident."
The Bellevue, Wash.-based company is setting up a memorial fund to benefit Dominguez's family and has offered them counseling and financial assistance. It is also offering counseling to her co-workers, several of whom witnessed the accidental shooting.
The Occupational Safety and Health Administration is investigating the incident, which spokesman Scott Allen called "unusual and tragic."
"We have confirmed that the employer did have a policy in place if a weapon was found, which we feel the workers were well aware of," he said. "But unfortunately, the gun went off shortly after being removed from the sock."
Victor Campos does not know who was holding the gun when it fired, and does not want to know.
"The police told me he was broken down, really sorry about it," he said. "I told the cops, 'You tell the guy my family and I don't blame him for anything.' We feel sorry for him. It wasn't his fault."
Dominguez's work at the thrift store was a big part of her life. She and her husband were introduced more than 20 years ago by a co-worker, who was Campos' sister. But there was far more to her life.
She was a spiritual searcher, her husband said, who spent decades looking for the right church. Her search ended when she and Campos saw two young women knocking on doors on their street in the middle of a snowstorm.
"Those poor girls," his wife had said. "If they knock at our door, I'm going to let them in."
They turned out to be Mormon missionaries, and Dominguez had found her church. For the last seven years she attended services, cared for children, taught Sunday school at the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints in Westchester.
She didn't miss a Sunday, "even if she was sick; even if the weather was bad," said Campos, an unemployed construction worker. "I would say, 'You don't have to go.' But she would say, 'No, I have my kids -- I can't leave them.' "
She loved dogs, especially their wet noses, which she couldn't resist touching. She was quick to help a neighbor and eager to guide her children.
"She said, 'Just do whatever you can to study.' She really wanted me to go to college," said her 17-year-old daughter, who asked not to be named. The high school junior plans to take the ACT in April and apply to colleges in fall.
"She kind of steered me out of that street stuff," said her son from her first marriage, who also asked not to be named but was home from the traveling he does for his job installing industrial machinery.
"If she didn't, I'd probably be somewhere," he said, his voice trailing.
"She was the pillar of the family," Campos said. "She kept us together."
Her thrift store colleagues remembered her with affection.
"She was so kind and she was always willing to help," Martinez said. "And she was always so happy."
"She was just a dear," Lewis said.
You never know what you'll find at a thrift store; that's what keeps devotees like me coming back. But employees never know what they'll find, either, when they open a bag of donations.
It was a deadly discovery that morning in the back room of a thrift store. And with it, a tragic fate found Carmen Dominguez.
blbrotman@tribune.com ct14 0010 140317 R S 0000000000 00006263
]]></text></news-item>