<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="ED6F-A289-E098-CC68"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>New Mexico: Nurse Practitioner -PRN #14-0275 Psych NP - PRN #14-0276</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[New Mexico Workforce Connection has issued the following news release:

Job Order Number: 285011 * Job Title: Nurse Practitioner -PRN #14-0275 Psych NP - PRN #14-0276 * Projected Occupation: Nurse Practitioners * Job Duration: Over 150 Days * Type of Job: Regular * Full or Part Time:
PRN (As Needed) * Job Position(s): 2 * Date Job Order Created/Updated: 3/14/2014 9:37:00 AM * Last Day Job Order Available Online: 03/22/2014 * Source: Preferred Employer * Site: New Mexico Workforce Connection * Other Related Jobs: View other jobs available for Nurse Practitioners * Supply and Demand: View competition for Nurse Practitioners Employer Information Help for Employer Information. This link opens a new window. * Employer Name: CHC Companies, Inc. * Company Website: View company website * Company Size: 1,000-4,999 * Type of Employer: Private Sector * Company Profile: View company profile * Other Employers: View largest employers of Nurse Practitioners Job Requirements Help for Job Requirements. This link opens a new window. * Test Requirement: No test required * Hiring Requirements: Drug Testing/Screening,Background Checks * Minimum Education Level: Master's Degree View typical education requirements for Nurse Practitioners * Minimum Experience: 36 months View typical work experience requirements for Nurse Practitioners * Driver's License Certification Requirement: No * Job Skills: View Employer Skill Requirements Compensation and Hours Help for Compensation and Hours. This link opens a new window. * Salary Range: $75.00 - $115.00 Hour * Labor Market Wage Rates: View typical labor market wage rates for Nurse Practitioners * Pay Comments: DOE (Depends on Experience) * Hours per Week: Hours Vary * Shift: Not Applicable * Benefits: 401K Work Site Information Help for Work Site Information. This link opens a new window. * Location Name: Valencia County Detention Center * Address: 436 Courthouse Road * City, State, Zip, and Country: Los Lunas, NM 87031 US Map Address
* Public Transportation Accessible: Yes * Worksite Industry (NAICS): Correctional Institutions (922140) Job Description Help for Job Description. This link opens a new window. 2 POSITIONS AVAILABLE: Nurse Practitioner and Psychiatric Nurse Practitioner: Pay range includes the 2 different positions, and will be based on experience. Both PRN as needed positions, hous shifts and days may vary and is based on needs of the facility.
Working Conditions: Work is performed inside a correctional facility. CHC expects employees to work in accordance with all security rules and regulations to minimize the risk of danger and/or harm to themselves or other employees. Due to the nature of our business, we cannot clear individuals with H1B or J1 status for employment and some facilities will not to clear individuals with bad debt or recent bankruptcies on their credit report. CHC provides excellent compensation and benefits packages (medical, dental, tuition reimbursement, 401K, etc.) to eligible employees.
Basic Duties: Registered Nurses Practitioners (RNP) provided general medical care to inmate patients within a correctional facility. Must be able to work within a correctional facility environment and treat inmate patients with respect.
Minimum Educational/Experience Requirements: - Must have and maintain a current and unrestricted license as a Registered Nurse Practitioner in the state of practice. - Current DEA controlled substances license/registration - Must be a graduate from an accredited nurse practitioner program approved by the legally-designated state accrediting agency at the time the program was completed by the applicant. - Must have two (2) years experience within a private practice, hospital, or correctional facility as an RNP. - Applicant required to be currently CPR certified.
Employment Requirements: - Must be able to pass a criminal background investigation by the company - Must successfully complete a pre-employment drug test. - Must comply with all requirements of the company substance abuse policy. - May be required to pass a consumer credit check - Must obtain and maintain security clearance with the client as a requisite for initial and/or continued employment
Physical/Mental Requirements: Must be able to perform all of the essential elements of the position with or without an accommodation. This position routinely requires (but is not limited to) the following: - Frequent walking throughout site; to include walking up and down flights of stairs - Ability to lift up to 20 lbs
We are an Equal Opportunity Employer. We do not discriminate on the basis of race, color, religion, sex, age, disability, sexual orientation, citizenship status or national origin or any other status protected by law or regulations. It is our intent that all qualified applicants are given equal opportunity and that selection decisions be based on job-related factors.
For further information please visit: https://www.jobs.state.nm.us/
]]></text></news-item>