<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="EDBF-5BE8-44E4-EDF0"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Wipro Cited a Leader in IDC MarketScape on Worldwide Life Science Research &amp;Development &amp;#8211; R&amp;D ITO as well as BPO Space</title><source>Market News Publishing</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[WIPRO LTD ("WIT-N") - Wipro Cited a Leader in IDC MarketScape on Worldwide Life - Science Research &Development &#8211; R&D ITO as well as BPO - Space
Wipro Ltd., a leading global information technology, consulting and outsourcing company, has been named a 'Leader' in both R&D ITO &BPO by advisory and research firm International Data Corporation (IDC) in its report IDC MarketScape: Worldwide Life Science Research &Development - BPO 2013 Vendor Assessment, Doc #244934, December 2013 and IDC MarketScape: Worldwide Life Science Research &Development - ITO 2013 Vendor Assessment, Doc #HI245309, December 2013.
After a close evaluation of Wipro's offerings and capabilities, IDC MarketScape has positioned Wipro in the 'Leaders' category within R&D ITO and R&D BPO. Relative to other vendors discussed in these reports, and based on feedback from multiple customer references, Wipro received high marks for its strong technical team, solid account relationships, and ability to deliver high value for the money.
Manoj Punja, Senior Vice President and Global Head, Wipro BPO, said, "The Life sciences industry is a huge focus area for Wipro BPO and we are investing significantly in this space. To be named as a Leader by IDC is indeed a validation of our investments and strategy in building differentiated industry capabilities, regulatory knowledge, analytics and best of class operations for this market."
Sangita Singh, Senior Vice President and Global Head - Healthcare and Life sciences, Wipro, said, "Wipro has reinforced its position in the R&D space. Wipro Healthcare and life sciences has been pursuing differentiated domain offerings to drive sustainable and predictable growth. We have gained traction, by following Wipro's three-pronged strategy of programmatic mining of existing accounts, new logo pursuits and creating differentiated domain offerings to solve real problems faced by clients."
Within the Life Science R&D BPO space, Wipro has been quoted as a strong player particularly in the area of delivering enterprise content document management, drug safety services, post market surveillance, and training services. In the Life Science R&D ITO space, Wipro is particularly strong in delivering both industry-specific and industry-agnostic engineering and software ITO services, supplemented by a broad portfolio of traditional life science ITO offerings.
Elaborating on Wipro's experience with Life Sciences clients, the IDC MarketScape reports state that the company's strong global presence, focused portfolio of services, aggressive growth strategy, competitive pricing, and strong customer focus have made Wipro a top contender for ITO &BPO services in areas where the company competes and a vendor that should be regularly on the short list in RFPs. As an experienced global service provider to the life science industry, Wipro is well positioned for continued growth.
About Wipro Ltd.
Wipro Ltd. (NYSE:WIT) is a leading Information Technology, Consulting and Outsourcing company that delivers solutions to enable its clients to do business better. Wipro delivers winning business outcomes through its deep industry experience and a 360 degree view of "Business through Technology" - helping clients create successful and adaptive businesses. A company recognized globally for its comprehensive portfolio of services, a practitioner's approach to delivering innovation, and an organization wide commitment to sustainability, Wipro has a workforce of 140,000 serving clients across 61 countries. For more information, please visit www.wipro.com.
About IDC MarketScape
IDC MarketScape vendor analysis model is designed to provide an overview of the competitive fitness of ICT (information and communications technology) suppliers in a given market. The research methodology utilizes a rigorous scoring methodology based on both qualitative and quantitative criteria that results in a single graphical illustration of each vendor's position within a given market. IDC MarketScape provides a clear framework in which the product and service offerings, capabilities and strategies, and current and future market success factors of IT and telecommunications vendors can be meaningfully compared. The framework also provides technology buyers with a 360-degree assessment of the strengths and weaknesses of current and prospective vendors.
Forward-looking and Cautionary Statements Certain statements in this release concerning our future growth prospects are forward-looking statements, which involve a number of risks, and uncertainties that could cause actual results to differ materially from those in such forward-looking statements. The risks and uncertainties relating to these statements include, but are not limited to, risks and uncertainties regarding fluctuations in our earnings, revenue and profits, our ability to generate and manage growth, intense competition in IT services, our ability to maintain our cost advantage, wage increases in India, our ability to attract and retain highly skilled professionals, time and cost overruns on fixed-price, fixed-time frame contracts, client concentration, restrictions on immigration, our ability to manage our international operations, reduced demand for technology in our key focus areas, disruptions in telecommunication networks, our ability to successfully complete and integrate potential acquisitions, liability for damages on our service contracts, the success of the companies in which we make strategic investments, withdrawal of fiscal governmental incentives, political instability, war, legal restrictions on raising capital or acquiring companies outside India, unauthorized use of our intellectual property, and general economic conditions affecting our business and industry. Additional risks that could affect our future operating results are more fully described in our filings with the United States Securities and Exchange Commission. These filings are available at www.sec.gov. We may, from time to time, make additional written and oral forward-looking statements, including statements contained in the company's filings with the Securities and Exchange Commission and our reports to shareholders. We do not undertake to update any forward-looking statement that may be made from time to time by us or on our behalf. NYSE closing price for WIT-N Date: 2014/03/13 Closing Price: 13.03
____________________________________________________________
(c)2014 Market News Publishing Inc. All rights reserved. Toronto:(416)366-8881 Vancouver:(604)689-1101 Fax:(604)689-1106
]]></text></news-item>