<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="EDD6-F957-60F8-91DD"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Washington: ENVIRONMENTAL FACILITATOR Job # 57271</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[American Herbal Products Association has issued the following job vacancy:

Job Category: 710 Title: ENVIRONMENTAL FACILITATOR Job Location: Harrisonville Percent Travel: --- Hiring Co.: CHURCH & DWIGHT CO., INC. Specialty Area: CPG Size of Company: - Sales Volume of Position:
Base Salary: $ - Bonus Potential: - Bonus Percent: Bonus Dollars: $ - Total Compensation: Based on Experience Stock Options: - How Many Options: Car: - Allowance: - Sign-On Bonus: - Other Benefits: Position Level in Co.: Position Reports to Whom: Company Description: Church & Dwight Co., Inc., founded in 1846, is the leading U.S. producer of sodium bicarbonate, popularly known as baking soda, a natural product that cleans, deodorizes, leavens and buffers. The Company’s ARM & HAMMER brand is one of the nation’s most trusted trademarks for a broad range of consumer and specialty products developed from the base of bicarbonate and related technologies. Church & Dwight’s consumer products business is organized into two segments: Consumer Domestic, which encompasses both household and personal care products, and Consumer International, which primarily consists of personal care products. About 40% of the Company’s U.S. consumer products are sold under the ARM & HAMMER brand name and derivative trademarks, such as ARM & HAMMER DENTAL CARE Toothpaste and ARM & HAMMER SUPER SCOOP Clumping Cat Litter. Church & Dwight’s consumer products business is organized into two segments: Consumer Domestic, which encompasses both household and personal care products, and Consumer International, which primarily consists of personal care products. About 40% of the Company’s U.S. consumer products are sold under the ARM & HAMMER brand name and derivative trademarks, such as ARM & HAMMER DENTAL CARE Toothpaste and ARM & HAMMER SUPER SCOOP Clumping Cat Litter. Position Responsibilities: This position is responsible for planning, establishing, implementing and maintaining environmental and DOT programs to ensure the safety for all employees and environmental compliance in a lean manufacturing and distribution environment. Responsibility to ensure compliance with Federal, State, and local regulations related to all hazardous materials. Responsibilities: Essential Functions: 1.Developing and maintaining management information systems which identify the location of hazardous materials in all facilities 2.Updating and delivering employee training programs related to hazardous materials and waste 3.Supervising work of outside contractors involved in removing or testing hazardous materials 4.Investigating employee complaints concerning exposure to hazardous materials or air pollutants 5.Maintaining accurate records related to chemical inventories, complaint investigations, and shipments of hazardous wastes 6.Keeping informed of current and proposed regulations related to program areas assigned 7.Performing related field work as required 8.Sampling hazardous and/or industrial waste and bulk sampling of material suspected of containing asbestos 9.Maintaining operation and inspection logs 10.Submitting clear and concise written reports based on field inspections 11.Recommending and coordinating the development of programs needed by the district to comply with hazardous materials regulations 12.Providing coordination with regulatory agencies in regard to hazardous materials 13.Disseminating Right-to-Know information 14.Performing other duties as assigned Qualifications: Knowledge, Skills, and Abilities: 1.Excellent interpersonal and skills – ability to build positive relationships at all levels of the organization 2.Excellent communications skills – ability to communicate clearly and concisely – verbal, written, etc. 3.Must have knowledge and training in environmental, occupational health and safety and compliance with applicable federal and state regulations and standards. 4.Highly skilled in the standards, concepts, practices, and procedures within the environmental, health and safety fields. 5.Demonstrated knowledge of delivering hands-on environmental, Hazardous Materials, and DOT 6.Ability to develop, implements, and coordinate comprehensive environmental, Hazardous Materials, and DOT accident-prevention programs. 7.Excellent organizational and time management skills, strong attention to detail. 8.Ability to facilitate, lead and direct teams and/or committees. 9.Ability to prioritize work assignments in a fast-paced work environment 10.Strong computer skills (MS Office Suite, Windows-based applications). 11.Ability to maintain absolute confidentiality at all times and in all situations. 12.Knowledge of PLC programming a plus. 13.Knowledge of CAD software a plus. Education: 1. Bachelor’s Degree in Environmental Engineering, Industrial Hygiene, Hazardous Material or related field. Biology or Chemical knowledge a plus. 2. 1-3 years experience in a fast-paced manufacturing and distribution environment. CPG industry experience a plus. Church & Dwight Co., Inc. is proud to be an equal opportunity employer M/F/D/V Number Direct Reports: - Position Experience Required: Class of Trade Experience Required: Education Required: BS/BA Paid Relocation: No Other Remarks: Clicking on “Apply Now” will send you to the company`s website to complete your submission. The online application MUST be completed. Remember, you have a greater chance of being reviewed if you indicate that you found this job on CPGjobs. If the URL link for this job does work OR the job is no longer active on the company`s career site, please let us know by sending an email to loraine@cpgjobs.com We will remove it right away. Thank you for helping us keep our job board up-to-date!
For further information please visit: http://jobboard.cpgjoblist.com
]]></text></news-item>