<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="EF7B-4019-0490-C174"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>French press review 15 March 2014</title><source>RFI (English)</source><author>William Niba</author><text><![CDATA[Pollution in France and all over Europe dominates today's front pages.
France is losing patience with Europe as Paris continues await EU support for its Sangaris operation in the Central African Republic.
Libération reports that French Foreign Minister Laurent Fabius and his Defence counterpart Jean -Yves Le Drian issued a harsh press release on Friday stating that all they'd received from non-EU nations like Georgia, Lettonia and Estonia was lip-service. It’s a damning report by French authorities says Libération.
The daily states that whilst some EU nations are ready to send troops for a month-long mission, others are only offering a limited military force, without any commanders or weapons. It’s a barely veiled message to Paris that the Central African Republic is not Europe's priority, according to the left-leaning newspaper.
Le Figaro reacts to the failure of diplomatic efforts to halt a Crimea referendum to boost ties with Russia. According to the paper, last-ditch talks between US Secretary of State John Kerry and Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov in London ended with no clear commitment from Moscow to back down over the Ukraine crisis.
Lavrov reiterated Moscow’s resolve to respect the Crimean people’s will to hold the referendum, while Kerry restated Washington’s stance that there will be consequences.
Le Figaro reports that the UN Security Council is scheduled to hold an emergency session Saturday morning to vote on a Western resolution denouncing Sunday’s Crimean referendum. EU leaders are due to meet on Monday, and then on Thursday, according to Le Figaro, to consider sanctions on Russia, if the referendum is passed.
Libération marks three years of the Syrian war with a series of special reports from two opposition strongholds in the north which have expelled foreign Jihadists from their territory. The coverage is illustrated by graphic pictures of the horrifying experience endured by residents of Al Dana and Harem in Idlib region after the enclaves were overran by pro-Assad forces and then by Hezbollah-backed Islamists...The pictures including bodies of people who were starved to death are selected from 54,000 photos smuggled out of the country by a deserter of Syria’s Intelligence Services, according to Libération.
Air navigation experts searching for the Malaysian Airliner which has been missing for over a week have renewed theories of hijacking. This is according to Le Figaro. It points to allegations that military radars traced the plane in the Golf of Bengal where search teams are now concentrating their efforts. The vast area includes the Andarman archipelago made up of more than 200 islands with only 18 of them inhabited, according to Le Figaro.
Le Monde issues a red alert against pollution in France accusing politicians of negligence after it failed to heed warnings of high volume traffic and carbon dioxide emissions from diesel powered cars. Experts had warned of carcinogenic particles filling the air.
Le Figaro is also preoccupied by the clouds of pollution particles hanging over France. It warns that normal levels of pollution were exceeded throughout the week, not just in the Parisian region of Ile de France but also in two-thirds of France’s regions. It’s the first time since 2007 that such atmospheric conditions are being experienced in France, according to Le Figaro.
The right-wing newspaper however underlines that Paris is not the only European town suffocating at this moment. Brussels it claims has opted to bring the speed limit for road traffic from 70 km per hour to 50. London is reinforcing congestion charges set at the major arteries of the city while Berlin is applying the Low Emission Zones legislation which bans heavy duty vehicles from ecologically sensitive areas covering 88 square kilometers of the city’s motorways. Only 300 European cities which have applied the Low Emission Zone’s mechanism have reaped any concrete results by reducing emissions of NO2 between 6 and 10 percent, according to Le Figaro.
Anti-pollution efforts in the Greek capital Athens are also highlighted by Le Figaro. It claims that the city’s authorities set up an alternating traffic system for cars matriculated with even and non even number plates since 1982, 23 square kilometers within the city’s periphery. But according to Le Figaro, the law flopped due to circumvention by cab drivers and car owners who simply bought themselves an extra vehicle.
More videos available on http://www.english.rfi.fr/
Radio France Internationale - All rights of reproduction and distribution reserved.
]]></text></news-item>