<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="EFAB-8670-4EBE-430A"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Malta Fibro Removers Not Insured for Accidents</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Mark Micallef, writing for Times of Malta, reported that companiesoffering asbestos-clearing services in Malta do not need to havepublic health risk insurance and though government tenders for itsdisposal normally demand this sort of cover, the requirement wasrecently dropped. An exercise carried out by The Sunday Times of Malta shows that amajority of Malta's asbestos-handling companies are not insuredfor the accidental exposure of third parties to asbestos fibres,which, when airborne, can be inhaled and potentially cause cancer.The companies were asked for a quotation from a journalist posingas a prospective client, who also inquired whether they hadinsurance cover. Only two companies out of the five that advertise such servicesclaim to have cover and the owner of one said his company does notactually do the cleaning itself but leaves it to an unnamed"foreign company". It is this company that has the insurancecover, not his. Moreover, industry sources said there are many more small outfitswhich do not advertise the service but take clearing jobs withouthaving any particular expertise, let alone cover. One contractor even claimed such insurance "probably does notexist", as he argued it was not necessary. The "miracle mineral", as it was sometimes called in the industry,was used widely for insulation and fireproofing until the late1970s, before the full extent of the health hazards it poses wasaccepted. The toxic substance is hazardous when airborne since it is made oftiny fibres that are easily inhaled. It is particularly dangerouswhen being transported, unless covered in plastic and disposed ofcarefully. As a result, the material became heavily regulated butwhile Malta too follows EU prescribed directives on the subject,there is no licensing regime, which means that in theory anycompany could start doing this work. Moreover, there is no requirement for insurance covering forpublic exposure in spite of the inherent risk in the business,which has been plagued by lawsuits from individuals who would havecontracted lung cancer from asbestos exposure. A spokesman for Mepa said the authority is responsible foroverseeing the transportation, storage and export of the materialbut the actual regulation of asbestos cleaning companies fallsunder the Occupational Health and Safety Authority (OHSA). However, the OHSA pointed out it is mostly responsible for the"health and safety of workers engaged in the handling of asbestos-containing material". The authority's environmental health CEO Mark Gauci said there areother regulations that safeguard public health and theenvironment. However, there was no response when the healthauthorities were asked to point out which body is responsible forpublic and environmental health risks. The authority does overseethe industry in the sense that it requires that asbestoscontractors submit a method statement every time they plan tocarry out a job involving the material. However, the regime is far more stringent in places like the UK,for instance, where companies in this business require a licencethat is only granted after they meet certain industry standardsimposed by the British Health and Safety Commission. Moreover, a precondition of the licence is the requirement of apublic health and environmental insurance cover. The situation is aggravated by the fact that the government issuesseveral large-scale contracts for asbestos removals in oldfactories, mostly belonging to the Malta Industrial Parks (MIP). Over the past years, many factories have been cleared out of tonsof asbestos, and there are many more on stream, some of themsitting right next to residential areas. Public tenders normally require third party exposure insurance.However, the requirement has not been consistent. In a recent tender, the clause requiring insurance cover wasmysteriously dropped. Questions sent to the authorities asking forexplanations remained unanswered at the time of writing. A spokesman for the Economy Ministry said MIP was currentlyinvestigating a tender issued for the removal of asbestos at afactory in Marsa last year on suspicion that the winning bidderdid not actually have insurance cover, despite it having been aspecific requirement of the tender. Diseases caused by asbestos usually take between 10 to 40 years todevelop. Malta had its fair share of asbestos victims. In 2012, the heirsof several former dockyard workers filed individual and classaction lawsuits in the US, seeking their right to compensation indamages for occupational exposures to asbestos products whileworking -- among other places -- on US warships. Some of them also took their battle for compensation to theEuropean Court of Human rights in the same year, over thegovernment's refusal to payout on behalf of the now defunct MaltaShipyards.
]]></text></news-item>