<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="EFB4-6655-CA9B-1E2D"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>City Invited to Review Proposal for Repurpose of Coal Ash</title><source>Targeted News Service</source><author>Targeted News Service</author><text><![CDATA[The city of Charlotte issued the following news release:
On Thursday, March 13, Duke Energy and Charah, a company known for its work in innovative environmental solutions, invited the City of Charlotte to participate in a due diligence review of a proposal to repurpose coal ash from the retired Riverbend Steam Station.
The project proposes to transfer coal ash from unlined impoundments at Riverbend to a fully encapsulated engineered structural fill development at Charlotte Douglas International Airport, which would be used for future projects.
"We see this as a potential opportunity to protect the City's water supply and environment by repurposing the coal ash at Riverbend," said Rob Phocas, Environment and Sustainability Manager for the City of Charlotte. "However, we plan to thoroughly and carefully vet this proposal to ensure it is the right type of project for our community."
The management of coal ash at the Riverbend Steam Station has already been referred to the City Council's Environment Committee for further study and discussion. Engagement of key stakeholders including residents, environmental groups, regulators and business organizations has also begun.
The effort would be similar to an engineered structural fill project at the Asheville Regional Airport. In that project, the coal ash is fully encapsulated with a synthetic liner, in accordance with EPA requirements, and then covered by multiple feet of dirt.
On Monday, March 24, Mayor Patrick Cannon and City Council will hear a presentation on the proposal, as well as additional background on the beneficial use of coal ash.
Contact: Keith Richardson, 704/336-5865, kmrichardson@charlottenc.gov
Copyright Targeted News Services
CC AutoTriage6yd-140315-30VitinMar-4669676
]]></text></news-item>