<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="EFF7-4324-17C8-A0BE"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>New York Healthy Workplace Advocates Press Conference</title><source>The WORD: Hunter College</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[March 18, 2014, LCA Room, Legislative Office Building - Albany, NY
::
Assemblyman Steve Englebright, Senator Diane Savino and Advocates speak out about the need to address the problem of repeated workplace mistreatment.
WHO:
- Assemblyman Steve Englebright, Chair of Committee on Governmental Operations and Prime Sponsor of the Healthy Workplace Bill A4965
- Senator Diane Savino, Chair of Senate Labor Committee and Prime Sponsor ofthe Healthy Workplace Bill S3863
- Randy Goldberg, President of CSEA Local 658
- John Richter, Director of Public Policy, Mental Health Association in NYS (mhanys.org)
- Professor Doe (alias to protect identity), Target of Workplace Bullying
- Catherine Redmond (on behalf of her husband Graham)
- Mike Schlicht, New York Healthy Workplace Advocates - Upstate Coordinator (nyhwa.org)
- Tom Witt, New York Healthy Workplace Advocates - Downstate Coordinator (nyhwa.org)
And others
WHAT:
Workplace bullying is defined as repeated verbal abuse, psychological abuse, work interference and work sabotage. At the present time, unless abusive treatment experienced at work can be attributed to membership in a "protected class" (i.e. civil right violation, age discrimination, genderbased mistreatment), prolonged abusive behavior at work is perfectly legal. "Status-blind" harassment is four times more prevalent than protected class harassment, and there is no protection for mistreated workers who fall into this much larger category.
Bullying at work is health harming, drives up the costs of healthcare and insurance, causes dysfunction in the workplace that drives up the cost of doing business, and unjustifiably destroys careers along with the well-being of individuals and their families.
WHEN:
Tuesday, March 18, 2014 at 1:00 PMLCA Room, Legislative Office Building, Albany, New York
WHY:
The Healthy Workplace Bill addresses repeated abusive mistreatment at work and offers recourse to the targets of workplace bullying.
The bill currently has 19 Senate sponsors and 86 Assembly sponsors, and over twenty unions and professional organizations have issued a Memorandum of Support for the bill including: 1199SEIU - United Healthcare Workers East, DC37, Mental Health Association of New York, NYCOSH, New York State AFL-CIO, NYSUT, PSC-CUNY and PEF.
The latest just announced endorsement of the Healthy Workplace Bill comes from the Newspaper Guild of Albany.
We are at the same point now that we were at just over two decades ago, right before Sexual Harassment Law was passed. Only this time we are discussing another equally wrongful abusive behavior called workplace bullying. It is the elephant is in the room and it needs to be addressed. Workplace bullying mimics the behaviors associated with domestic violence and this form of violence can no longer be passively tolerated by society.
With over 93% of Americans supporting enactment of a law that would protect all workers from repeated abusive mistreatment at work, the time to pass this legislation is now!
Gregg Morris can be reached at gmorris@hunter.cuny.edu
]]></text></news-item>