<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F0C0-9B78-E2B6-80D9"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>NGOs to play more important role</title><source>Shenzhen Daily</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Wu Guangqiang jw368@163.com SHENZHEN, a reform pioneer in China, has never ceased experimenting in economic and social fields. A recent development, despite its limited media attention, may signify major progress in the city’s endeavor to create a civil society.
On Feb. 22, a Shenzhen-based nongovernmental organization released a review report that rated local public services, the first of its kind in China. The report, compiled by Shenzhen Ma Hong Foundation, a nongovernmental research organization under the China Development Institute, rated the work performance of 43 government agencies across the city. Criteria for the ratings included the execution of work targets set for 2013, public recognition, evaluations by netizens, and assessments by experts. The city’s education bureau, Futian District Government and the municipal meteorological observatory topped the ranking list, while Dapeng New Area Government, the city’s financial authorities and its emergency office came right at the bottom of the list. The aim of Shenzhen Ma Hong Foundation is to promote public assessment and supervision of governmental work. The foundation is one of hundreds of thousands of nongovernmental organizations (NGOs) in China (sometimes known as civil society organizations or CSOs). While still in their infancy, NGOs will undoubtedly become an important element in China’s social advancement. By definition, NGOs are organizations that are neither a part of the government nor a conventional for-profit business. Usually set up by ordinary citizens, NGOs may be funded by governments, foundations or businesses, and they are primarily run by volunteers. Taking various forms in different parts of the world, NGOs engage in a wide range of activities, including charity and environmental protection. Chinese NGOs are chiefly involved in such tasks as poverty alleviation, environmental protection, disaster response and adolescent education. The emergence and expansion of NGOs is an indication of a nation’s economic prosperity and social advancement. The number of NGOs operating in the U.S. is estimated at 1.5 million and Russia has about 280,000. According to the data released by the Minister of Civil Affairs in March 2012, China had 460,000 legally registered NGOs. More recent data is unavailable. China’s fast economic growth in the past three decades has given birth to a huge middle class, along with a new wealthy class. Having found satisfaction in their economic status, the better-off citizens have developed a new aspiration — to do their part for the country’s management and improvement. Creating NGOs and participating in pro-social activities is the best way for them to fulfill their desire to be the master of their country. The Chinese Government has been supportive of more public participation in social affairs and volunteer activities. Chapter 20 of The 21st Century Agenda of China issued by the State Council in 1994 outlined related policies and goals. New NGOs have been mushrooming since China lowered barriers to NGO registration in 2013, including removing approval procedure for the registration of four specific types of NGOs, including charities and urban and rural community services. One of the impressive contributions that Chinese NGOs have made to society is their active participation in rescue operations and disaster relief in natural calamities. Just hours after the 8.0-magnitude earthquake hit Wenchuan area in Sichuan Province on May 12, 2008, thousands of volunteers, along with professional teams, reached the quake zone, started digging survivors from the rubble and distributed relief supplies. That was the first time ordinary Chinese citizens showed their strong capability to make the nation better. It is no overstatement that NGOs can play a role greater than anyone’s imagination. They can do what the government can’t do or can’t do well enough. A niece of mine, working together with some of her friends, donated a primary school to a poverty-stricken village in Jiangxi Province. They don’t even have an organization; they did it out of sheer sympathy for the poor kids. They pooled money, devoted their spare time and had the school built. If total freedom is given to mass enthusiasts to care for the needy, the trickle will became a stream and the stream, a torrent. Working with the government, NGOs can do more to benefit the interests of the country. For example, in Western countries, NGOs have great influence in foreign affairs. Yet in China, only official voices can be heard, which is often misinterpreted by Western media as a lack of popular support in the Chinese foreign policies. More hands make light work! (The author is an English tutor and a freelance writer.)
]]></text></news-item>