<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F0E4-073A-60CB-4E19"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Parking ordinance now better for businesses</title><source>The Westerly Sun (Rhode Island)</source><author>CYNTHIA DRUMMOND</author><text><![CDATA[Council deletes section following residents' protests.
Sun Staff Writer
CHARLESTOWN - After hearing objections from business owners, the town has removed a section from its parking ordinance that would have prohibited the parking of commercial trailers in residential areas unless they are hidden from view by natural landscape features such as trees.
Builder Bruce Loeckler of Partridge Run told the Town Council at a March 10 public hearing that Chapter 218-59 of zoning ordinance No. 363 is unfair to residents who are self-employed.
"I have a pickup truck and I tow a 10-foot work trailer almost every day for my remodeling business," he said. "Planting trees is expensive. If nothing else, at least allow us to put a fence up and not have to plant the trees. That would be a little bit cheaper. My question is, is the town of Charlestown so wealthy that it can afford to close down the self-employed, thus getting no more tax money from small businesses that now exist? It's been a very long winter for a lot of us that are self-employed. This ordinance is like another nail in the coffin for self-employed small businessmen."
Charlestown Economic Improvement Commission Chairman Frank Glista asked why the ordinance did not apply to boats and campers.
"Why doesn't this ordinance include boats, boats on trailers, campers and other recreational vehicles, such as snowmobiles and jet skis?" he asked. "The EIC feels that our town should make it easier for businesses to survive without them having to worry about the next restrictive ordinance that appears."
Carolina resident Beth Richardson took offense to the requirement that trailers be hidden from public view, and asked the council to remove that section from the ordinance.
"The trucks parked in people's yards and the trailers are a sign of prosperity and entrepreneurship," she said. "This is what we want in Charlestown. We're not some sort of [community] like in Florida where they have these planned developments where you can't have a clothesline. We're not like that in Charlestown."
After hearing residents' complaints, council members said they were willing to remove the section governing commercial trailers.
Council member George Tremblay, who wrote the offending chapter, said he was willing to delete it entirely.
"I have no objection to striking the whole section," he said.
Councilor Patricia Andersen agreed.
"I'd like to see it taken out," she said. "I think there are a lot of people who have pickup trucks and they tow trailers, whether they're closed trailers or open trailers, or toolbox trailers. Where do people hide them? If you don't have a lot big enough and this is your livelihood, where do you put it? Do you have to go rent a piece of property or a garage?"
Andersen made a motion to amend the ordinance by deleting the section on towed equipment, and the council unanimously approved it.
Just before members voted, Loeckler returned to the podium to make one final comment.
"I've got two words: Thank you," he said.
]]></text></news-item>