<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F137-DAED-248A-C65F"><date>2014-03-10</date><title>The open line: Webb Hubbell writes a legal thriller, 'When Men Betray'</title><source>Arkansas Times</source><author>Max Brantley</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 09, 2014 (Arkansas Times:http://www.arktimes.com Delivered by Newstex) The Sunday line is open. One item to pass along: * WEBB HUBBELL SOON TO RELEASE THRILLER NOVEL: A friend passes along a press release on a book coming from Webb Hubbell, the former Little Rock lawyer and Clinton administration official who went to federal prison for stealing from clients of the Rose Law Firm. (He also made Special Prosecutor Kenneth Starr very unhappy for being one in a series of people who gave him no goods on the Clintons, perhaps because they had none.)
Hubbell's novel, "When Men Betray" is set in Little Rock and delves into politics, law and Southern society, thus drawn from his own experience. Since completion of his prison sentence he's worked in insurance and lists his home as Charlotte on LinkedIn. The books is pitched as the first as a series based on the fictional exploits of antitrust lawyer Jack Patterson who returns to Little Rock — "a town he swore he'd never set foot in again" — to figure out why political wingman Woody Cole shot a U.S. senator in cold blood on live television.The books is set for May release by Beaufort Publishing, but it's on Amazon and his website for pre-ordering. $24.95. with autograph from Hubbell's website. Also an e-book.NEWS RELEASE 'John Grisham, move over—the legal thriller has a new master! When Men Betray is the real thing, a gripping, literate thriller from an author who knows the courthouse …. Breath-stopping action, romance, and suspense rush forward to a climactic ending that will keep the sharpest readers guessing.' ~ Steven Spruill, author of Ice Men When Men Betray (Beaufort Books, May 2014) is the first novel by Webb Hubbell. Set in his home town of Little Rock, Arkansas, this page-turner tests friendship, family, and race relations, and delves deeply—indeed cynically—into the behavior of politicians, lawyers, judges, and the accused. Readers will be immersed into a steamy world behind southern garden parties and polite facades—a seedy underbelly of secrets and betrayals, and the possibility of redemption. As former Mayor of Little Rock, Chief Justice of the Arkansas Supreme Court, and Associate Attorney General of the United States appointed by former President Bill Clinton, Webb Hubbell is well- versed in the intricacies of the US government and our criminal justice system. He has first-hand experience on both sides of the bench and brings his unique knowledge and experience to every page. When Men Betray is the first novel in a series Hubbell is creating centered on his main character, antitrust lawyer Jack Patterson. 'When Men Betray is a delightful page-turner, crime/mystery that captivates the reader from the first page, with wonderfully detailed descriptions that made me feel I was in Little Rock. It is clear he drew liberally from his own fascinating life.' ~R. Keith Stroup, Esq., founder of the National Organization for the Reform of Marijuana Laws (NORML) 'A brilliant read.' ~Anne Harding Woodworth, author of The Artemis Sonnets, Etc. "In When Men Betray, Webb Hubbell's insider knowledge of politics and natural storytelling ability combine for a shrewd mystery exposing the wooly underside of southern culture and government. May this be the first of many Hubbell novels." ~B. Brandon Barker, author of Operation EMU ### ABOUT THE AUTHOR Webb Hubbell is a nationally recognized author, and speaker on government, business, and law. He has held executive level positions in government and industry including: U.S. Associate Attorney General, Chief Justice of the Arkansas Supreme Court, Mayor of Little Rock Arkansas, Managing Partner of the second largest law firm in Arkansas, and Executive and Chief Counsel for a large Washington based Commercial Insurance Company. [ Subscribe to the comments on this story[1] ] [1]: http://www.arktimes.com/arkansas/Rss.xml?oid=3238219id=comments

]]></text></news-item>