<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F18E-3276-8DD7-7892"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>NEW FEARS ON PAYDAY LOAN FIRMS; Call for action as high number of stores revealed</title><source>Liverpool Echo</source><author>OLIVER DUGGAN</author><text><![CDATA[HALTON has among the highest concentration of payday loan companies in the UK, according to an investigation into the industry.
The Merseyside borough ranks third in the study with nearly ten stores for just over 100,000 people - just behind south east London and Harlow, Essex.
Among the payday lenders with outlets in the area are The Money Shop and Cash Generator, two firms that have come under fire for high interest on short-term loans.
The research, which focused on the seven largest payday loan companies in the UK, found nine outlets split between Halton, Widnes and Runcor n.
A further 26 stores have opened in Liverpool and nine in the Wirral, contributing to a national total of 1,437 shops - one for every seven banks on the British high street.
Derek Twigg, Labour MP for Halton, said the area faces significant economic challenges that force vulnerable people to rely on risky loans to pay for essential services.
He said: "We have a problem with payday lenders, and indeed illegal money lending. There is a cost of living crisis and we have to do more to support people.
"I would welcome, for instance, a cap and levy on the highest interest rates. Some find these loans useful, but many people get into trouble due to the extortionate costs attached. We have got to do more for people who often face a choice between being able to eat and heating their homes.
"The people who use these loans are often the most vulnerable.
The findings by the Bureau of Investigative Journalism suggest a direct relationship between a community's affluence and the prevalence of payday lenders.
Halton is the 32nd most deprived local authority in the England while Liverpool, which comes 12th in the study's rankings of 326 local authorities, is the 5th most deprived. The news comes ahead of an indepth review by the Financial Conduct Authority (FCA) into the way lenders deal with customers who are unable to make their repayments.
Beginning next month, the study into companies like those operating across Merseyside is expected to be followed by tough new industry-wide regulations. Join the conversation
]]></text></news-item>