<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F1A0-B98E-C91C-D001"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>How to create system change that solves sustainability challenges</title><source>guardian.co.uk</source><author>Bruce Watson (Contributor)theguardian.com</author><text><![CDATA[FULL TEXT
For those involved in sustainability, one of the biggest challenges is perspective; how can you tackle the big, systemic problems such as poverty, water scarcity and climate change? At a recent event, hosted by Guardian Sustainable Business and Forum for the Future, sustainability actors from businesses, NGOs, academia and the media discussed how to create the system change needed to address sustainability challenges.
Rather than focusing on an individual problem or issue, system innovation looks at the larger context of a problem, defining the roles, needs, and potential actions of all stakeholders. Here are some of the ways that it works:
Identify the process of change
Forum for the Future, a non-profit that works in sustainability, has outlined six steps to significant change, a general road map for system innovation.
Stakeholders begin by identifying the need for a change. They then diagnose the problem, develop "pioneering" solutions for solving it, and implement those solutions until they reach a tipping point. Afterward, they effectively create a new status quo, by sustaining the transition, and, finally, establishing the rules of the new mainstream.
Get a full understanding of the problem
The six steps, which seem to draw heavily from the dialectic, outline the generally theoretical process of a systemic transition. Joe Hsueh, partner in Second Muse and founding partner of the Academy for Systemic Change, offers a more tangible process for system change.
He begins by gathering all stakeholders, then asking them, together, to bring all problems to the table. In this way, Hsueh notes, stakeholders are able to create a "Participatory Causal Systems Map." Or to put it simply, they're able to diagram every aspect of a problem, so that each actor is aware of the challenges facing every other actor.
Find the core issue
To some extent, Hsueh suggested, sustainability problems are a matter of perspective. Using the example of the fishing industry, he noted that, while fishermen, fish buyers and seafood companies might regard themselves as opponents, they share a common interest: maintaining the health and integrity of the fish population. Having identified and agreed upon that core issue, the stakeholders can begin to approach a systemic problem from a common ground.
Let all stakeholders find their place in the problem
Having established a common problem, all stakeholders then need to determine how they contribute to it. And having done so, Hsueh notes, they will then find the way that they can contribute to the solution. Using the fishing example, fish buyers might realize that, by lowering prices, they are encouraging fishermen to overfish. Fishermen, on the other hand, could realize that, by overfishing, they are driving down prices and depleting fishing stocks.
Find leverage points in the problem
Having identified their place in the core problem, stakeholders can begin to find places where they can compromise to reach a mutual benefit. In the fisheries example, Hsueh notes, fish buyers agreed to offer a consistent, relatively high price for fish and fishermen agreed to limit their catch. By guaranteeing a consistent income, the buyers were able to give the fishermen security. And by guaranteeing a consistent supply, fishermen were able to promise a relatively stable market.
Push for corporate consistency
Companies will often work toward sustainability in one area but then undermine efforts by pushing unsustainability in another area. Alnoor Ladha, executive director of The Rules, suggests that companies need to be held to a consistent standard. To illustrate, he uses the example of an acquaintance who had a top job at MTV.
However, the employee discovered that the company, which was working for sustainability in one area, was also employing 12 lawyers to lobby for Sopa and PIPA, legislation that, opponents argue, would lead to online censorship. On an ad hoc sustainability level, this disconnect would be unnoticeable, but on a systemic level, the inconsistency is glaring.
Sometimes it comes down to values
Systemic thinking tends to seek out solutions that benefit all stakeholders. But what about situations in which there is no room for compromise? Sometimes zero-sum solutions seem to be the only options available.
One example is pollution. As one participant noted, a fundamental aspect of the current capitalist system is that "the impact of a transaction" is often fundamentally separated from its "economic aspect". In other words, companies that derive profits from polluting the environment often do not have to deal with the long-term effects of their actions. Potential solutions for this disconnect, including carbon offsets or Superfund liabilities, are losing propositions for many corporations.
Another issue is corporate involvement in government. Ladha cited a Harvard study showing that "Every dollar that is spent on lobbying Congress has a $770 return." For companies that are able to take advantage of the US lobbying system, campaign finance reform is bound to be a net negative.
Ultimately, while compromise and mutual benefit is ideal, there are times when a systemic solution will require fundamental, difficult change from a single actor. In these cases, it seems, the key may lie in recognizing that, while compromise is ideal, moral values are - and must be - a fundamental compass.
]]></text></news-item>