<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F23B-466F-AC19-EF00"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Human trafficking expert to speak at Misericordia</title><source>The Citizens' Voice (Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania)</source><author>Matt Bufano, The Citizens' Voice, Wilkes-Barre, Pa.</author><text><![CDATA[March 16--Colleen E. Owens has dedicated her career to human rights issues.
In one of her more recent studies, the Wilkes-Barre native served as a lead researcher in identifying challenges to improve the investigation and prosecution of human trafficking cases. The study was a collaborative effort between Owens and other researchers at the Urban Institute, along with researchers at Northeastern University.
After her career has now led her to Washington, D.C., Owens, 32, returns Wednesday to Misericordia University to discuss her findings.
When asked what she hopes attendees of her speech take away from the event, she said, "First and foremost, an awareness of what human trafficking is -- and an awareness that it occurs in the United States."
To the first point, human trafficking revolves around three elements -- force, fraud and coercion -- that compel a person into commercial sex or other forms of labor or services, Owens said.
Owens, a Meyers High School graduate, went on to explain that human trafficking happens throughout the U.S. and locally.
"It does exist in Wilkes-Barre and in the surrounding areas," Owens said. "The cases haven't been called human trafficking, but they do have the elements."
According to Owens, the fact that some local cases haven't been identified as human trafficking is part of a larger problem, in which prosecutors and investigating officers do not necessarily have the resources or knowledge to fully uncover the incidents.
Owens said she hopes her aforementioned report, along with future studies, bring awareness to the problem.
"I think first of all, a lot more resources are needed for law enforcement ... they can only do so much based on the resources available," Owens said.
Another problem in the world of finding and prosecuting those involved with human trafficking is often times vice units are in charge of looking for human trafficking. Owens said this presents a challenge to officers who might see victims as criminals.
Among the findings outlined in the executive summary of the aforementioned report is: About 35 percent of sex trafficking victims were arrested.
While different parts of her co-led report on human trafficking were picked up by mainstream media, she said the study received "a lot of attention behind closed doors" within the prosecution community.
However, one of the next reports Owens worked on, which will be released in the summer, aims to make a larger splash. The study revolves around labor trafficking in the U.S.
Owens explained workers are brought to the U.S. in a completely legal fashion, but sometimes the job they sign up for is not the job they get.
"(Workers) get paid severely under wage --sometimes they're kept in isolated locations --they're threatened to be deported or arrested if they complain," Owens said about the preliminary findings in the human trafficking report.
Owens plans to speak on both studies Wednesday at Misericordia, hoping the crowd is filled with students, along with members of the community and law enforcement.
She said she hopes attendees will take the knowledge and do something with it to create a public interest.
Owens added: "We have political leaders. People can make these changes."
mbufano@citizensvoice.com
570-821-2117, @CVBufano
IF YOU GO
Who: Colleen E. Owens, a research associate with the Justice Policy Center at the Urban Institute in Washington, D.C.
What: Owens will discuss findings from reports she did on human and labor trafficking
When: 12 to 1:15 p.m. Wednesday
Where: Misericordia University, Insalaco Hall, Rooms 218-219, Dallas
___ (c)2014 The Citizens' Voice (Wilkes-Barre, Pa.) Visit The Citizens' Voice (Wilkes-Barre, Pa.) at citizensvoice.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>