<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F2FD-1B1B-7E4D-7DB2"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Ill-Suited for Suits </title><source>Patriot News (Harrisburg, Pennsylvania)</source><author>AL LEWIS</author><text><![CDATA[Mark 2014 as the year that sales of the business suit peaked.
The defining moment: Men's Wear house's $1.8 billion deal to buy Jos. A. Bank Clothiers, purveyor of the "Buy One, Get Seven Free" sale.
Thousands of baby-boomer men turn 65 years of age every day. They don't need suits. They need "active wear."
Millennials who are replacing boomers don't need suits, either. They communicate by text. The most successful among them-Facebook founder Mark Zuckerberg- goes to business meetings in a hoodie.
Unemployment has hit millennials hard. They may need a suit for their brutally long quests to land their first real jobs. Once employed, many of them will work via the Internet, with their web cameras off, and focus on paying off their unfathomable student debt loads instead of fashion.
Business suits won't go entirely the way of the top hat. It's just that the market is mature. Growth will be slow. Suit sellers will succeed by taking business away from competitors, and through consolidations and cost cutting. In this environment, Men's Wear house ousted its own founder, George Zimmer-the guy who says "You're going to like the way you look. I guarantee it."
Mr. Zimmer has shunned interviews, but he reportedly wanted to take Men's Wear house private, borrowing money at low interest rates to buy out public stockholders and get away from Wall Street's insanity.
With Mr. Zimmer out the door, Jos. A. Bank made a bid for Men's Wear house in October. Men's Wear house then rejected that offer and made a bid for Jos. A. Bank. Then Jos. A Bank struck a deal to merge with Eddie Bauer. Then, in a deal announced last week, Jos. A. Bank is suddenly prepared to pay a $48 million breakup fee to get out of its Eddie Bauer deal and be bought by Men's Wear house.
Once combined, Men's Wear house and Jos. A. Bank will have more than 1, 700 U.S. stores and $3.5 billion in annual sales. It will be one of the biggest suits in the sagging suit business.
At this point, nobody is saying anything about store closings and layoffs. A news release simply mentions $100 million to $150 million of "annual synergies" achieved in part through "streamlining duplicative corporate functions." How's that for dressing it up?
Like most mergers, this deal inevitably will mean less for customers, employees and, in the long term, even shareholders. But in the short term it will mean more for managers, investment bankers, accountants, lawyers and consultants.
"Together, Men's Wear house and Jos. A. Bank will have increased scale and breadth," Men's Wearhouse chief Doug Ewert said in a news release.
In another news release, issued in October, Men's Wear house said something different. "The proposed transaction would be subject to regulatory review and could raise significant antitrust concerns."
That was when Jos. A. Bank was trying to buy Men's Wear house. See, that would have been a very ugly monopoly. Now that Men's Wear house is buying Jos. A. Bank, well, it's a plan to "broaden our customer reach."
It's doubtful any regulator will care about a suit monopoly in an economy so ill-suited for suits.
If anything, Men's Wear house should be getting J.C. Penney and several other struggling apparel retailers as part of the deal. You know, buy one, get seven free.
Al Lewis is a columnist based in Denver. He blogs at tellittoal.com; his email address is al.lewis@tellittoal.com
]]></text></news-item>