<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F348-6A5D-BB34-0079"><date>2014-03-09</date><title>Pakistan: Opp stops govt from tabling women representation bill</title><source>Right Vision News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[LAHORE, March 9 -- The PML-N government was embarrassed by the opposition in the Punjab Assembly on Friday when they prevented the government from tabling a bill aimed at enhancing women representation in all government departments and allied bodies, by pointing out quorum.
Deputy speaker Sher Ali Gorchani prevented the government from further embarrassment by adjourning the session for Saturday afternoon (today), after the provincial ministers failed to bring back the treasury members despite trying their best for more than 15 minutes.
The government wanted to table the Punjab Fair Representation of Women Bill 2014 on Friday since it was already schedule to be passed in the special session of the House on Saturday, to mark the International Women's Day but the opposition members, infuriated by the deputy speaker's refusal to allow PTI member to discuss the alleged corruption in the Metro Bus Project Rawalpindi, indicated that the House lacked quorum.
The speaker rang the bells for about 20 minutes while several ministers ran into the lobbies to haul back the treasury members but remained unsuccessful. The helpless deputy speaker adjourned the proceedings for the special session on Saturday.
The trouble began when the House took up the brief official business comprising the laying of two bills at the close of the day's proceedings. Arif Abbasi rose on a point of order and drew the attention of the House to some alleged corruption and overspendings for removing the power pylons from Murree Road to allow the construction of Metro Bus project.
Law minister Rana Sanaullah interrupted him and replied that Abbasi was levelling only verbal accusations. He said if Abbasi had proofs he should come out with details as to how many pylons were to be removed and documentary evidence of the alleged huge sum of money being paid to the contractors. The deputy speaker asked Arif Abbasi to sit down but he continued to speak loudly which forced the speaker to order switching off his microphone.
Meanwhile, Rana Sanaullah began laying down the two bills amidst loud shouting by Arif Abbasi and other opposition members. He had barely laid down the first bill titled Punjab Public Private Partnership Ordinance 2014 when Arif Abbasi walked out of the House during the commotion.
The deputy speaker asked him to stay in the House and assured him that he would be given time afterwards. Amidst the commotion, Ahsan Riaz Fatiana and Mian Aslam Iqbal pointed out the lack of quorum. Though deputy speaker did not initially responded to the opposition's quorum shortage call and Rana Sanaullah continued to read out the laying of the first Bill but Aslam Iqbal drew chair's attention that the quorum had already been pointed out and proceedings could not continue.
Earlier, the deputy speaker ordered the government to resolve the issue of making proper arrangements in the House for allowing the private TV channels live coverage of the Punjab Assembly proceedings.
Speaking on his adjournment motion on the issue, PML-N member Sheikh Allauddin said it was a matter of sorrow that Sindh Assembly proceedings were aired by private TV channels for about 20 minutes but the Punjab Assembly which represented about 100 million people was deprived of this right. He said only PTV briefly aired the Punjab Assembly proceedings at such late hours in the night when no gentlemen could remain awake. He said it was the right of the voters and general public to see what their representatives were doing inside the House.
He also expressed the existing temporary facilities for the electronic media outside the assembly premises.
To this, Rana Sanaullah said the government had always supported private channels to cover the House proceedings in principle but the House building lacked the required space to allow about three to four dozen channels to bring in cameras and staff. He said that, during his negotiations with the representatives of media, it was decided to install modern devices which would allow live coverage for channels without bringing in their cameras. He said the government had already ordered preparing feasibility on the issue and if budget exceeded the limit of Assembly's allocation, the government was prepared to provide the remaining funds. He asked the mover to provide his suggestions and consult the media representatives to install better equipment in the House. He said the coverage was already being given to House proceedings but its quality was poor because of outdated equipment of the official channel. He also indicated that media only gave coverage to such issues and events in the House which should not have been covered at all.
He cited the incidents of hot exchanges of words among members and their commotion, and said it was the media discretion to cover such things and suppress the public service which was being done inside the House.
The deputy speaker directed the minister to resolve the issue during the current session
Published by HT Syndication with permission from Right Vision News. For any query with respect to this article or any other content requirement, please contact Editor at htsyndication@hindustantimes.com
]]></text></news-item>