<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F3AE-0EFF-29D3-9760"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Judge: State Farm owes more than $3 million attorney fees, damages in whistle-blower case</title><source>The Biloxi Sun Herald (Mississippi)</source><author> ANITA LEE; calee@sunherald.com</author><text><![CDATA[A federal judge has ordered State Farm Fire and Casualty Co. to pay $750,000 in damages, plus $2.9 million in attorney's fees and expenses, for defrauding the U.S. government on a Hurricane Katrina homeowner's insurance claim.
However, U.S. District Court Judge Sul Ozerden also dismissed the broader case former insurance adjusters and whistle-blowers Kerri and Cori Rigsby had hoped to pursue if they prevailed on the single homeowner claim. The Ocean Springs sisters allege State Farm's fraud against the National Flood Insurance Program was widespread along the Coast after Katrina.
Ozerden ruled whistle-blower law limits the lawsuit to the one claim for which the Rigsbys were able to offer independent, personal knowledge about what happened. The Rigsbys, who filed their lawsuit in April 2006, allege the insurance company minimized its losses for wind damage by blaming Katrina's storm surge, covered under the federal government's National Flood Insurance Program. Insurance companies adjust their own wind claims, and NFIP pays them to adjust flood claims.
The Rigsbys proved their case to a jury's satisfaction regarding the claim filed on the North Biloxi home of Thomas and Pamela McIntosh. An engineer initially concluded wind caused the loss but, under pressure
from State Farm, the engineering firm re-examined the claim and blamed Katrina's surge, testimony showed. Kerri Rigsby subsequently discovered an altered engineering report in the McIntosh file.
At State Farm's direction, NFIP paid the McIntoshes policy limits of $250,000. State Farm initially paid the couple $36,000 for wind damage on a policy that provided more than $500,000 in coverage.
Ozerden tripled the amount of the false NFIP payment to award damages.
State Farm has denied any wrongdoing. The company has not decided whether to appeal the verdict to the 5th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals.
The Rigsbys have filed a 5th Circuit appeal of Ozerden's decision to dismiss the broader case.
The Rigsbys will each receive 15 percent of the damages, and the remainder is supposed be paid to the federal government. The Rigsbys, whose attorneys recovered the legal fees and expenses, pursued the case after the federal government declined to intervene and prosecute.
A counterclaim State Farm filed against the Rigsbys is pending. State Farm alleges they violated federal fraud laws by taking company computer and paper files while employed as independent adjusters. Magistrate Judge Robert H. Walker Jr. recently cancelled a settlement conference in the case.
"Based on a review of confidential settlement documents submitted by counsel for the parties," the file noted, "the Court has determined that conducting a settlement conference at this time would not be productive."
]]></text></news-item>