<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F3C1-FDF9-9858-4D35"><date>2014-03-16</date><title></title><source>The State Journal- Register (Springfield, IL)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Here's something cheery to contemplate. Suppose tomorrow you're hit by a bus and die.
Are your affairs in order?
You need to prepare for your death.
You need a will (probably), you need advanced health care directives if you end up in the hospital, you need to leave your loved ones a list of instructions.
Where there's a will
You can probably come up with many reasons not to write your will. It sounds intimidating. It sounds expensive. You actually have to think about dying.
Then again, don't you want to be the one who decides who'll raise your (minor) children in your absence? Or who'll get your possessions?
"It irks me when people take the attitude of 'I'll be dead, so why should I care?'" says Dan Mathews, a certified financial planner with Stepp & Rothwell Inc. in Overland Park, Kan.
But it's irresponsible, he says, not to have a plan in place for your estate.
"You want people to remember you for the good things you did, not the mess you left," Mathews says.
You're not too young to worry about this. About 1 in 8 of today's 20-year-olds will die before reaching age 67, according to the Social Security Administration.
There are plenty of books and online resources on estate planning, but if you go the do-it-yourself route you should still consult a lawyer before executing a will. "There are too many pitfalls," Mathews says. Laws vary from state to state.
A will substitute
It might take a chunk of time to list your assets, decide who gets them and then put it all down in a will. But there's one thing you can do right now: Make sure you have beneficiaries on file for your life insurance policy, retirement accounts and the like.
If you have registered those beneficiaries already, make sure the names (and percentages each gets) are up-to-date after major life events.
Designating beneficiaries - with an insurance company or mutual funds company or whatever - is known as a will substitute, says financial adviser Barbara McMahon, president of Innovest Financial Partners in Kansas City.
"Registration rules," she says. "It doesn't matter what the will says."
So, if a guy remarried but never changed the beneficiary of his 401(k) account from first wife to second wife, the first wife gets the dough if he dies - even if his will states otherwise.
Another will substitute: the old T.O.D., "transfer on death."
That "classic" car of your dad's? He might have listed you as the T.O.D. beneficiary on the clunker's title. Again, McMahon says, T.O.D. trumps the will.
There's also P.O.D., "payable on death," for such assets as checking and savings accounts.
Low-income property owners without the means to execute a will should consider a beneficiary deed, aka a transfer-on-death deed. It's like the T.O.D. notation on a car title, but it gets filed with the recorder of deeds, says Gregg Lombardi, executive director of Legal Aid of Western Missouri.
He gives this example. If an older woman owns a home and dies without a will, her adult daughter who moves in and goes to the bank for a loan discovers her dead mom still owns the house.
"By that time it costs $10,000 or more to bring action to clear the title," Lombardi says. If the daughter can't afford that, she finds herself stuck in a house she doesn't own and can't afford to maintain.
If the mother had filed a beneficiary deed, a simple two-page document, ownership would have transferred immediately to the daughter.
Health care directives
You never know when you'll wind up in the hospital. To put it bluntly, decide when you want the plug pulled. Also, designate someone who can make health care decisions for you when you can't speak for yourself.
The forms to fill out are a health care treatment directive (sometimes called a living will) and a durable power of attorney for health care decisions.
These forms are available online for free from various sources. Go to practicalbioethics.org and click Resources, then Caring Conversations. You must provide your name and email address to download information and forms.
"Caring Conversations for Young Adults" includes guidance on how to talk about organ donation, do-not-resuscitate orders and serious illness.
Time to write a letter
By putting pen to paper, you can tell your nearest and dearest just how much you love them. But you should also tell them things like where you have bank accounts, where the keys to the safe deposit box are and your email and Facebook passwords ... just for starters.
And after you've written that letter, make sure your family and friends know about it.
McMahon says that her mother, when she was dying of cancer, told her adult children she'd left them an envelope on the coffee table in the living room. "And it had everything in it," McMahon says.
Jeanne Fleming, co-author with Leonard Schwarz of the Money Manners column, notes that in many households one person handles the investments. If that's you, write a memo explaining where they are, how they work and how they should be handled. Also include the name of someone who can help the executor and beneficiaries make sense of it all.
List your "digital assets" - all your online user names, passwords and security-question answers, he says. (You could also put this information on a USB drive.)
Especially if you live alone and have pets, you should also give some thought to who will care for them after you're gone and maybe provide some money for that. Put pet-care instructions in your letter.
Distributed by McClatchy-Tribune News Service
]]></text></news-item>