<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F43C-432A-0385-2CCF"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>JOY IS TAINTED</title><source>DAILY MAIL (London)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[TANGLE OF HORSE AND HUMAN FLESH
BY ALAN FRASER
The final day of a Cheltenham Festival full of brilliant racing and exciting finishes was marred by a series of injuries to both horses and humans yesterday.
A bizarre accident prior to the third race resulted in Daryl Jacob needing an operation today on a broken elbow, knee and leg. Earlier, Ruby Walsh suffered a compound fracture of the upper right arm.
And, in the last of the 27 races, the Alan King-trained Raya Star had to be put down, the fourth horse killed in action this week.
It was surely with a kind of macabre prescience that Walsh had quite deliberately provoked a debate at the start of the Cheltenham Festival on the way racing and the wider public view horses compared to humans.
Given that the injury to Walsh was not life-threatening, it is surely not poor taste to suggest the animal rights activists, so incensed by his insistence that horses were replaceable', humans not, somehow conjured the retribution.
Jacob's injuries appear more serious. His accident was bizarre, not just in the manner in which he was thrown from the Paul Nicholls-trained Port Melon. Something spooked the horse as it made its way on to the course and, as the animal tried to duck under a barrier, it careered into a TV camera, dumping the jockey on to a very unforgiving surface, if not concrete itself.
A riding boot was ripped as Jacob complained about no feeling down the side of his left arm and left leg. That reportedly passed as he was assessed and subsequently taken to hospital for further examination.
Unbelievable, this game,' Nicholls remarked, in the way Sir Alex Ferguson spoke of football.
Unbelievable because Jacob had just ridden a much-needed, overdue first winner for his boss at the Festival when taking the Vincent O'Brien County Handicap Hurdle on Lac Fontana.
Unbelievable because, in the previous race, Jacob looked a likely winner when one of his stirrup leathers broke, forcing him to finish with his feet out of the irons. That after two days of defeats and dreadful luck. At times he had looked on the point of tears.
The incident looked horrific,' Nicholls said. Thank goodness he rode that winner, otherwise he would have been suicidal. He's ridden a winner and is generally in good spirits despite having a terrible injury like that.'
The sequence of despair, short-lived joy and despair again is the kind of combination that makes all sport so fascinating. Not all sports, however, have changing rooms which can look like field hospitals. Among the great climaxes and photo-finishes this week has been a catalogue of falling horses which cost equine life and caused human pain.
Bryan Cooper's badly broken leg needs specialist repair; Jason McGuire did not even reach Cheltenham because of an eve-of-Festival fall which precipitated life-saving surgery.
The jockeys were falling like flies yesterday. Replacements were being replaced and one trainer joked about calling on Rishi Persad. The television presenter had distinguished himself in a charity race the previous day.
When the fastest jumpers in the world come together on ground quickening in dry weather, the risks increase. It makes for great sport set against the background of danger.
The racing has been brilliant and breathtaking this week. But there are times when breath has been held in the tangle of horse and human flesh.
The last race had run as Tony McCoy, a last-fence faller and again kicked by hooves, limped to the weighing room. Screens surrounded the stricken Raya Star. An ambulance drove round the track. Happily, it was empty.
Regardless of ethical questions, this is one tough sport involving many tough customers.
© Daily Mail
]]></text></news-item>