<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F54B-04D5-2830-8B24"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Richland Resources sinks 4.5% on weak volume</title><source>News Bites - Western Europe: United Kingdom</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Richland Resources Ltd (L:RLD), the 98th largest mining company by market capitalisation in the United Kingdom, sank 0.13 GBX (or 4.5%) to close at GBX2.75. Compared with the FTSE 100 Index which fell 25.9 points (or 0.4%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -4.1%. Trading volume was 38% lighter than average.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Richland Resources, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/00105183194031482
Bearish SignalsDowntrend- The stock dropped 4.5% on high volatility today.- The price sank 4.5% in the last week and plummeted 18.6% in the last month. - Compared with the FTSE 100 Index which fell 2.8% for the week and 2.0% for the month, this represented a relative price decrease for Richland Resources stock of 1.8% for the week and 16.6% for the month. - The present value of GBP1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Richland Resources is GBP478, for a capital loss of GBP522.
- Revenue growth rate has shown signs of deterioration in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 80,000 shares worth GBX220,000 (US$3,652) traded. - Richland Resources is at a discount of 56.9% to its 12-month high of GBX6.38 on 02 Apr, 2013. It is also at a premium of 57.1% to the 12-month low of GBX1.75 on 30 Jul, 2013.Bullish Signals:Oversold/Bullish/Support Signals- The Stochastic indicator of 19.8 has pierced the oversold line of 20.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Price/Sales of 0.6 [0.7]. We estimate Richland Resources stock is trading at a current year Price/Sales of 0.6 and a forward year Price/Sales of 0.5. - Price to Book of 0.5 [1.7].Other Bullish Signals:- The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 16.4%. - Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 0.2. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is undervalued and ranks in the top 9% of stock by value of Q Ratio.
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:February 05: Richland Resources: Memorandum of Understanding Signed for Graphite[News Story] Richland Resources Ltd, the gemstone producer, cutter and polisher, today announces the signing of a Non Binding Memorandum of Understanding ("MoU") with ASX quoted Kibaran Resources Limited (ASX: KNL, "Kibaran") over consolidation and development, through a Joint Venture ("JV") of both companies respective graphite assets located in Northern Tanzania.Highlights' Non Binding MOU to potentially consolidate Richland's Arusha Graphite Project with Kibaran's Merelani-Arusha Graphite Projectin Tanzania.' Objective to realise Medium-term graphite production from both assets upon conclusion of JV agreement.' Richland's current tanzanite mining operations previously hosted a graphite mine' Richland's subsidiary, TanzaniteOne Mining Limited, have a 15,000tpa graphite processing plant and associated infrastructure.' Kibaran has rights to the Merelani-Arusha Graphite Project, located in the north-east of Tanzania, and neighboring Richland's tenements.' Kibaran undertaking due diligence over 90 days exclusivity period.Richland's Chief Executive Officer Bernard Olivier said "Our team in Tanzania led by Ami Mpungwe, the Chairman of TanzaniteOne Mining Limited, are looking forward to working with Kibaran with a view to commercialising the graphite potential of the Merelani mine for the benefit of TanzaniteOne Mining and STAMICO."Kibaran's Executive Director Andrew Spinks said, "Following the recent milestone achievement of a signed binding off-take agreement for Epanko graphite, we are pleased to be in negotiations to progress the [our] Merelani-Arusha Graphite Project with the Richland group - the owners of the historical Merelani Graphite Mine.
December 19: Richland Resources: Proposed Placing and Open Offer (replacement)[News Story]Richland Resources Ltd is pleased to announce that it is proposing to raise up to Pound4.0 million (Pound3.9 million net of expenses) through the issue of up to 118,148,951 New Common Shares by way of a Placing and Open Offer at an issue price of 3.4p per New Common Share.Highlights:* Minimum proceeds of Pound2.0 million (before expenses) pursuant to the Placing and the shares committed by Directors and existing shareholders under the Open Offer* Minimum proceeds, together with cash and facilities and cash generated from operations will fund capital expenditure at TanzaniteOne Mining Limited ("TanzaniteOne") mine site to allow the restart of activities at two recently recovered mine shafts, fund expansion of operations and settle royalty claims and provide additional working capital* Seeking up to Pound4.0 million under the Open Offer* Additional proceeds, in excess of the minimum, would be applied towards an accelerated capital expenditure programme at the mine site and its diversification programme, including the development of the Tsavorite project and the potential option exercise over the sapphire project* Recently signed agreement with the State Mining Corporation ("STAMICO") will aid endeavours to curb illegal mining operationsBernard Olivier, Chief Executive Officer commented: "The recently signed agreement with STAMICO, the Tanzania Government's securing of shaft systems on the northern part of the licence area from illegal intrusion and the commitment of STAMICO to assist the Group's subsidiary, TanzaniteOne, in obtaining government assistance with mine site security now enables TanzaniteOne to further re-commence its mining activities in the recovered areas.
December 12: Richland Resources: Joint Venture Agreement With STAMICO, Tanzania[News Story] Richland Resources Ltd today announces that the Company's subsidiary, Tanzanite One Mining Limited ("TML") has signed a full and formal legally binding Agreement with the State Mining Corporation ("STAMICO") over the operation and licence ownership relating to tanzanite mining.Highlights:Joint Venture Agreement and appointment contracts executed between TML and STAMICO covering:· 50:50 Joint Venture partnership over new licence: ML 490/2013· 10 year agreement securing all licence areas relating to existing TML tanzanite production· Net profit share arrangement on 50:50 basis between TML and STAMICO· US$ 4 million payable by STAMICO in recognition of the previous expenditure incurred by TML, to be paid by STAMICO utilising 40% of its future share of the net residual profit· All existing assets, including all buildings, plant, equipment etc., remain in the sole ownership of TML· STAMICO will facilitate and liaise with the Tanzanian Government authorities to ensure that necessary regulatory and law enforcement actions are taken to curb tanzanite smuggling and illegal mining operations· TML to run operations as Operator.
November 21: Richland Resources: Sale of Dubai Office Secures US$640,000[News Story]Richland Resources Ltd, the gemstones producer and developer, today announces the completion of the sale of its Dubai marketing and rough gemstone sales office (the "Dubai Office") for a gross value of approximately US$650,000 on 20 November. The net sale proceeds from the sale of the Dubai Office were approximately US$640,000 after deduction of all costs and taxes.
September 09: Richland Resources: Interim Results for 30 June 2013[Company Release]http://www.buysellsignals.net/BuySellSignals/report/Unitedkingdom/Stock/News/140119.pdfSource: Company Website
July 29: Richland Resources: Result of AGM[News Story]We advise that proxies representing 43,676,385 shares were received in relation to the Annual General Meeting of Richland Resources Limited on 26th July 2013 and that all proxies were voted in favour of all resolutions with no votes against and no abstentions and that therefore all the following resolutions and items of business were unanimously passed:
1.
July 22: Richland Resources: Shooting of an Employee by Illegal Miners[News Story] Richland Resources Ltd, the gemstones producer and developer, regrets to announce that an employee at its wholly owned subsidiary, TanzaniteOne Mining Limited, Mr.Willy Onesmo Mushi, was killed by illegal miners within its Block C licence area. Mr. Mushi's family has been informed.As previously reported over 12 months of uncontrolled illegal mining and violence directed against Company employees, especially within high grade and quality areas, has severely affected the Company's operations, which have been curtailed due to our concerns about the safety of the working environment in certain parts of the Company's mining licence area.On 18 July 2013 a Government led and supported operation to expel the illegal miners, which included the Field Force, a division of the Tanzanian Police Force as well as officials from the Ministry of Minerals and Energy worked in conjunction with the Company to re-enter areas of the Block C Merelani mine that were previously taken over by hostile illegal miners from neighbouring blocks.
ISIN: BMG7567C1064
L:RLD; LON:RLD; LN:RLD
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>