<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F5CD-6A9E-E9BC-07E9"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Legals</title><source>Waycross Journal-Herald (Georgia)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[gpn7 STATE OF GEORGIA COUNTY OFWARE IN RE: ESTATE OF LULA ANN GROVER, DECEASED All creditors of the Estate of Lula Ann Grover, late of Ware County, Georgia, are hereby notified to render their demands to the undersigned according to law, and all persons indebted to said Estate are required to make immediate payment to me.
This 17th day of February, 2014.
/s/BOBBY J. GROVER AND LACY WENDELL GROVER, Executors of the Estate of Lula Ann Grover Mary Jane Cardwell Attorney for Executors P. O. Box 756 Waycross, GA 31502-0756 (912) 285-0393 2-22-4Sats.-7-8485
gpn7 In The Probate Court Ware County, Georgia All creditors of the Estate of Josie Irene Smith Henderson, deceased, late of Ware County, Georgia are hereby notified to render their demands to the undersigned according to law, and all persons indebted to said estate are required to make immediate payment to the undersigned.
This 22nd day of February, 2014.
James C. Henderson Jr., Executor 176W. Graham Street McRae, Georgia 31055 2-22-4Sats.-7-8486
gpn12 IN THE SUPERIOR COURT OF WARE COUNTY STATE OF GEORGIA Forfeiture: OCGA. §16-13-49 THE STATE OF GEORGIA ex rel. Bradley L. Collins District Attorney, Waycross Judicial Circuit, Plaintiff, v. FOUR THOUSAND, THREE HUNDRED, NINE DOLLARS ($4, 309.00) IN U.S. CURRENCY; Defendant in rem. OTTIS TYRONE GAINER, Potential Claimant.
NOTICE OF SEIZURE AND FORFEITURE OF PERSONAL PROPERTY VALUED AT LESS THAN $25, 000 Pursuant to O.C.G.A. §16-13-49, you are hereby notified that on the 5th day of February, 2014, the following property was seized from Ottis Tyrone Gainer, by the undersigned agency and there is a forfeiture pending against said property in Ware County, Georgia: Four thousand, three hundred, nine dollars ($4, 309.00) in U.S. currency.
The conduct giving rise to said seizure was as follows: On February 5th, 2014, Officer John Lee, Officer Tyler Wescott, and Officer Martin Davis of the Waycross Police Department arrived at 1139 Folks Place, Waycross, Georgia, to serve a pending felony arrest warrant on Ottis Gainer. Officers knocked on the door and informed Ashanti Smith that they needed to talk to Gainer. Officer Davis could smell a strong odor of marijuana coming from inside the residence. Gainer came to the door and officers advised him to step outside. Gainer closed the door and fled out the back door of the residence. Officer Wescott observed Gainer carrying a plastic grocery bag containing items. The Officer observed clear plastic bags containing a white substance being dropped or thrown down as Gainer ran. Officers chased Gainer on foot and he was apprehended and arrested behind a residence on Martin Luther King Drive. While searching Gainer, the Officer located a bag of marijuana in his front pocket and a large amount of folded money in his left front pocket. Underneath Gainer was another large quantity of money rubber banded together. The total amount of money seized from Gainer was $4, 309.00. Officers backtracked the area Gainer had run and located 3 sandwich bags of crack cocaine and a sandwich bag of powder cocaine. Det. Weiss secured a search warrant for the residence. Marijuana and large amounts of crack cocaine and cocaine were seized. There was also evidence that crack cocaine was being manufactured in the residence. Digital scales and drug related items were also seized. The seized property is now in the custody of theWaycross Police Department, 512 Oak Street, Waycross, Georgia. Ottis Tyrone Gainer was charged with Obstruction of Officer, Possession of Cocaine and Crack Cocaine With Intent to Distribute, Possession of Controlled Substance Within 1000 Feet of Housing Authority, Trafficking/Manufacturing Cocaine/Crack Cocaine, Possession of Marijuana with Intent to Distribute and other related charges. Said property was used or intended for use, to facilitate a violation of O.C.G.A. 16-13-30, or proceeds derived or realized therefrom, and said property was found in close proximity of said unlawful drugs.
You may file a claim by sending the claim by certified mail, return receipt requested, to the District Attorney and to the seizing agency at the addresses shown below. Your claim must comply with the requirements set forth in O.C.G.A. §16-13-49 (n) (4) and must be filed within thirty (30) days of the second publication of this notice in the official organ of Ware County, Georgia.
This 20th day of February, 2014. BRADLEY L. COLLINS DISTRICTATTORNEY State Bar Number 940389 306 Albany Avenue Waycross, GA 31501 Waycross Police Department P.O. Box 176 Waycross, Georgia 31502 Det. R.G.Weiss, Jr.
3-1-3Sats.-12-8488
gpn6 IN THE PROBATE COURT WARE COUNTY, GEORGIA All creditors of the Estate of James W. Cox, Sr., deceased, late of Ware County, Georgia, are hereby notified to render their demands to the undersigned according to law, and all persons indebted to said estate are required to make immediate payment to the undersigned.
This 26th day of February 2014.
Winston M. Corbitt, Executor 6128 Swamp Road Waycross, Georgia 31503 James F. Thomas, Jr.
Attorney at Law Post Office Box 98 Waycross, Georgia 31502-0098 3-1-4Sats.-6-8489
gpn18 In The Probate Court County ofWare State of Georgia In Re: Estate of Ruby L.Williams, Deceased Estate No.
Notice of Petition To File For Year's Support The petition of Cleveland Ellis Williams, Sr., for a year's support from the estate of Ruby L. Williams, deceased, for decedent's surviving spouse, having been duly filed, all interested persons are hereby notified to show cause, if any they have, on or before March 24, 2014, why said petition should not be granted.
All objections to the petition must be in writing, setting forth the grounds of any such objections, and must be filed on or before the time stated in the preceding sentence. All pleadings/objections must be signed before a notary public or before a probate court clerk, and filing fees must be tendered with your pleadings/objections, unless you qualify to file as an indigent party. Contact probate court personnel at the following address/telephone number for the required amount of filing fees. If any objections are filed, a hearing will be held in the PRobate Court of the above named County, courtroom 123, (address) 800 Church Street, Waycross, Georgia scheduled at a later date. If no objections are filed the Petition may be granted without a hearing.
Calvin Bennett Judge of the Probate Court 800 Church Street, Room 123 Waycross, Georgia 31501 Tel. 912-287-4315 3-1-4Sats.-18-8490
gpn13 PUBLIC NOTICE The Commission of the City of Waycross has scheduled a public hearing to be held on March 18, 2014 at 6:30 p.m., at the City Hall, 417 Pendleton Street, Waycross, Georgia, for the purpose of considering an amendment to the zoning ordinance of the City of Waycross so as to rezone the areas described below: M Street -ParcelWA0704 004 Tract 4 M Street -ParcelWA0703 207 Tract 3 L Street -911 Rear Portion Present Zoning Classification: G-I -General Industrial Proposed Zoning Classification: R-50MH Residential Mobile Home District Description of Property: TRACT 3: All of that tract or parcel of land situate, lying and being in the City of Waycross, County of Ware and State of Georgia known and described as follows: Beginning at the southeast corner of 'M' and Wilson Streets one hundred and seventy-five (175) feet to lands of Pompie and Rosie McRae; thence southward and parallel with 'M' street one hundred (100) feet; thence westward and parallel with Wilson Street one hundred and seventy-five (175) feet to 'M' Street; thence northward along the eastern margin of 'M' Street one hundred (100) feet to the beginning corner, and being a part of City Block 536.
TRACT 4: All of that tract or parcel of land situate, lying and being in the City of Waycross, County of Ware and State of Georgia known and described as follows: Beginning at a point on the eastern margin of "M" Street one hundred (100) feet south of the southeast corner of "M" and Wilson Street and extending southward along the eastern margin of "M" Street fifty (50) feet and thence eastward parallel to Wilson Street one hundred (100) feet, thence northward parallel to "M" Street fifty (50) feet, thence westward parallel to Wilson Street one hundred (100) feet to "M" Street at point or place of beginning, this is in City Block 536.
L Street 911 rear portion. This 27th day of February, 2014.
JULIE DINKINS CITY CLERK 3-1-3Sats.-13-8391
gpn11 NOTICE OF SALE UNDER POWER, WARE COUNTY Pursuant to the Power of Sale contained in a Security Deed given by Mary Colleen Clark to Centex Home Equity Company, LLC dated 8/2/2002 and recorded in Deed Book 40-T Page 163, WARE County, Georgia records; as last transferred to or acquired by Nationstar Mortgage LLC fka Centex Home Equity Company, LLC, conveying the after-described property to secure a Note in the original principal amount of $17, 000.00, with interest at the rate specified therein, there will be sold by the undersigned at public outcry to the highest bidder for cash before the Courthouse door of WARE County, Georgia, within the legal hours of sale on April 01, 2014 (being the first Tuesday of said month unless said date falls on a Federal Holiday), the following described property: ALL THAT TRACT OR PARCEL OF LAND BEING 0.5255 ACRE IN LAND LOT 212 OF THE 8TH LAND DISTRICT OF WARE COUNTY, GEORGIA, AND MORE PARTICULARLY DESCRIBED AS FOLLOWS: TO ARRIVE AT THE BEGINNING POINT, BEGIN AT A POINT WHERE THE SOUTHWESTERLY RIGHT-OF-WAY OF WASHINGTON STREET INTERSECTS THE EASTERLY LAND LOT LINE OF SAID LAND LOT 212, THENCE NORTH 49°04'36" WEST A DISTANCE 1, 370.71 FEET TO THE BEGINNING POINT OF THE HEREIN DESCRIBED TRACT; THENCE SOUTH 75°10'02' WEST A DISTANCE OF 192.46 FEET TO AN IRON PIN; THENCE NORTH 26°17'17" WEST A DISTANCE OF 222.44 FEET TO AN IRON PIN ON THE SOUTHWESTERLY RIGHT-OFWAY OF WASHINGTON STREET; THENCE SOUTH 65°05'33" EAST ALONG THE SOUTHWESTERLY RIGHT-OF-WAY OF WASHINGTON STREET A DISTANCE OF 189.09 TO A POINT; THENCE IN A SOUTHEASTERLY DIRECTION ALONG AN ARC THE CHORD OF WHICH ARC RUNS SOUTH 58°02'38" EAST 133.25 FEET TO THE BEGINNING POINT. ALL ACCORDING TO THE PLAT OF A SURVEY BY FRANKLIN MILES, REGISTERED LAND SURVEYOR, WHICH PLAT IS INCORPORATED HEREIN BY REFERENCE AND WHICH PLAT IS RECORDED IN PLAT BOOK A, PAGE 1994 OF THE PUBLIC LAND RECORDS OFWARE COUNTY, GEORGIA.
Being that parcel of land conveyed to MARY COLLEEN CLARK from LUCILLE CORBITT NASWORTHY by that deed dated 12/12/1991 and recorded 12/13/1991 in deed book 24J, at page 268 of theWARE County, GA Public Registry.
The debt secured by said Security Deed has been and is hereby declared due because of, among other possible events of default, failure to pay the indebtedness as and when due and in the manner provided in the Note and Security Deed. The debt remaining in default, this sale will be made for the purpose of paying the same and all expenses of this sale, as provided in the Security Deed and by law, including attorney's fees (notice of intent to collect attorney's fees having been given).
Said property is commonly known as 1958 East Washington Avenue, Waycross, GA 31503 together with all fixtures and personal property attached to and constituting a part of said property, if any. To the best knowledge and belief of the undersigned, the party (or parties) in possession of the subject property is (are): Mary Colleen Clark or tenant or tenants.
Nationstar Mortgage LLC is the entity or individual designated who shall have full authority to negotiate, amend and modify all terms of the mortgage.
Nationstar Mortgage LLC 350 Highland Dr.
Lewisville, TX 75067 1-888-480-2432 Note, however, that such entity or individual is not required by law to negotiate, amend or modify the terms of the loan.
Said property will be sold subject to: (a) any outstanding ad valorem taxes (including taxes which are a lien, but not yet due and payable), (b) unpaid water or sewage bills that constitute a lien against the property whether due and payable or not yet due and payable and which may not be of record, (c) the right of redemption of any taxing authority, (d) any matters which might be disclosed by an accurate survey and inspection of the property, and (e) any assessments, liens, encumbrances, zoning ordinances, restrictions, covenants, and matters of record superior to the Security Deed first set out above.
The sale will be conducted subject to (1) confirmation that the sale is not prohibited under the U.S. Bankruptcy Code; and (2) final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan with the holder of the Security Deed. Pursuant to O.C.G.A. Section 9-13-172.1, which allows for certain procedures regarding the rescission of judicial and nonjudicial sales in the State of Georgia, the Deed Under Power and other foreclosure documents may not be provided until final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan as provided immediately above. Nationstar Mortgage LLC fka Centex Home Equity Company, LLC as agent and Attorney in Fact for Mary Colleen Clark Aldridge Connors, LLP, 15 Piedmont Center, 3575 Piedmont Road, N.E., Suite 500, Atlanta, Georgia 30305, (404) 994-7400.
1006-667500151A THIS LAW FIRM MAY BE ACTING AS A DEBT COLLECTOR ATTEMPTING TO COLLECT A DEBT. ANY INFORMATION OBTAINED WILL BE USED FOR THAT PURPOSE. 1006-667500151A 3-8-4Sats.-11-8492
gpn11 NOTICE OF SALE UNDER POWER, WARE COUNTY Pursuant to the Power of Sale contained in a Security Deed given by Charles Henry Crews to Mortgage Electronic Registration Systems Inc., as nominee for Suntrust Mortgage Inc. dated 4/3/2007 and recorded in Deed Book 53N Page 340, Ware County, Georgia records; as last transferred to or acquired by Suntrust Mortgage, Inc., conveying the after-described property to secure a Note in the original principal amount of $71, 000.00, with interest at the rate specified therein, there will be sold by the undersigned at public outcry to the highest bidder for cash before the Courthouse door of Ware County, Georgia, within the legal hours of sale on April 01, 2014 (being the first Tuesday of said month unless said date falls on a Federal Holiday), the following described property: All that tract or parcel of land lying and being in original Land Lot No. 119 in the Eighth Land District of Ware County, Georgia, and more particularly described as follows:
Beginning at a point, which point is on land lot line between land lots 158 and 119, said point being 20 feet east of the northwest corner of land lot 158; thence north along the east side of Sunnyside Drive a distance of 47 feet to an iron pin, which is the Beginning Point of the land herein described; thence running in an easterly direction and at right angles to Sunnyside Drive a distance of 200 feet; thence running north and parallel with Sunnyside Drive a distance of 100 feet; thence running west a distance of 200 feet to the east side of Sunnyside Drive; thence south along said Sunnyside Drive a distance 100 feet to the point or place of beginning, according to plat and of said land made November 6, 1956, revised April 27, 1957, by T. L. Watts, Registered Engineer, together with all improvements located thereon, including a house known as 1908 Sunnyside Drive, Waycross, Georgia.
Subject to such utility easements and ways as may be shown of record or evidence by use.
The debt secured by said Security Deed has been and is hereby declared due because of, among other possible events of default, failure to pay the indebtedness as and when due and in the manner provided in the Note and Security Deed. The debt remaining in default, this sale will be made for the purpose of paying the same and all expenses of this sale, as provided in the Security Deed and by law, including attorney's fees (notice of intent to collect attorney's fees having been given).
Said property is commonly known as 1908 Sunnyside Drive, Waycross, GA 31501 together with all fixtures and personal property attached to and constituting a part of said property, if any. To the best knowledge and belief of the undersigned, the party (or parties) in possession of the subject property is (are): Charles Henry Crews or tenant or tenants.
SunTrust Mortgage, Inc. is the entity or individual designated who shall have full authority to negotiate, amend and modify all terms of the mortgage.
SunTrust Mortgage, Inc. Loss Mitigation 1001 Seemes Avenue Richmond, VA 23224 1-800-443-1032 Note, however, that such entity or individual is not required by law to negotiate, amend or modify the terms of the loan.
Said property will be sold subject to: (a) any outstanding ad valorem taxes (including taxes which are a lien, but not yet due and payable), (b) unpaid water or sewage bills that constitute a lien against the property whether due and payable or not yet due and payable and which may not be of record, (c) the right of redemption of any taxing authority, (d) any matters which might be disclosed by an accurate survey and inspection of the property, and (e) any assessments, liens, encumbrances, zoning ordinances, restrictions, covenants, and matters of record superior to the Security Deed first set out above.
The sale will be conducted subject to (1) confirmation that the sale is not prohibited under the U.S. Bankruptcy Code; and (2) final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan with the holder of the Security Deed. Pursuant to O.C.G.A. Section 9-13-172.1, which allows for certain procedures regarding the rescission of judicial and nonjudicial sales in the State of Georgia, the Deed Under Power and other foreclosure documents may not be provided until final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan as provided immediately above. Suntrust Mortgage, Inc. as agent and Attorney in Fact for Charles Henry Crews Aldridge Connors, LLP, 15 Piedmont Center, 3575 Piedmont Road, N.E., Suite 500, Atlanta, Georgia 30305, (404) 994-7400.
1034-287A THIS LAW FIRM MAY BE ACTING AS A DEBT COLLECTOR ATTEMPTING TO COLLECT A DEBT. ANY INFORMATION OBTAINED WILL BE USED FOR THAT PURPOSE. 1034-287A 3-8-4Sats.-11-8493
gpn11 NOTICE OF SALE UNDER POWER, WARE COUNTY Pursuant to the Power of Sale contained in a Security Deed given by Austin Eugene Nipper and Paula M. Nipper to Mortgage Electronic Registration Systems, Inc. as nominee for New Century Mortgage Corporation dated 2/28/2007 and recorded in Deed Book 53-I Page 109, Ware County, Georgia records; as last transferred to or acquired by Deutsche Bank National Trust Company, as Trustee for the registered holders of Morgan Stanley ABS Capital I Inc. Trust 2007-NC4 Mortgage Pass Through Certificates, Series 2007-NC4, conveying the after-described property to secure a Note in the original principal amount of $72, 225.00, with interest at the rate specified therein, there will be sold by the undersigned at public outcry to the highest bidder for cash before the Courthouse door of Ware County, Georgia, within the legal hours of sale on April 01, 2014 (being the first Tuesday of said month unless said date falls on a Federal Holiday), the following described property: All of Lots No. six (6) and seven (7) of Block "A" of the L. W. Odum and S. G. Coleman subdivision of the east half of Block No. 14 of "North Deenwood" as shown by plat of record on Page No. 48 of the plat records of the Clerk of the Superior Court ofWare County, Georgia, All of said land being in land lot No. 154 of the 8th district ofWare Country, Georgia.
The debt secured by said Security Deed has been and is hereby declared due because of, among other possible events of default, failure to pay the indebtedness as and when due and in the manner provided in the Note and Security Deed. The debt remaining in default, this sale will be made for the purpose of paying the same and all expenses of this sale, as provided in the Security Deed and by law, including attorney's fees (notice of intent to collect attorney's fees having been given).
Said property is commonly known as 2008 Albany Avenue, Waycross, GA 31503 together with all fixtures and personal property attached to and constituting a part of said property, if any. To the best knowledge and belief of the undersigned, the party (or parties) in possession of the subject property is (are): Austin Eugene Nipper and Paula M. Nipper or tenant or tenants.
Ocwen Loan Servicing, LLC is the entity or individual designated who shall have full authority to negotiate, amend and modify all terms of the mortgage.
Ocwen Loan Servicing, LLC Foreclosure Loss Mitigation 1661Worthington Road Suite 100 West Palm Beach, FL 33409 1-877-596-8580 Note, however, that such entity or individual is not required by law to negotiate, amend or modify the terms of the loan.
Said property will be sold subject to: (a) any outstanding ad valorem taxes (including taxes which are a lien, but not yet due and payable), (b) unpaid water or sewage bills that constitute a lien against the property whether due and payable or not yet due and payable and which may not be of record, (c) the right of redemption of any taxing authority, (d) any matters which might be disclosed by an accurate survey and inspection of the property, and (e) any assessments, liens, encumbrances, zoning ordinances, restrictions, covenants, and matters of record superior to the Security Deed first set out above.
The sale will be conducted subject to (1) confirmation that the sale is not prohibited under the U.S. Bankruptcy Code; and (2) final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan with the holder of the Security Deed. Pursuant to O.C.G.A. Section 9-13-172.1, which allows for certain procedures regarding the rescission of judicial and nonjudicial sales in the State of Georgia, the Deed Under Power and other foreclosure documents may not be provided until final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan as provided immediately above. Deutsche Bank National Trust Company, as Trustee for the registered holders of Morgan Stanley ABS Capital I Inc. Trust 2007-NC4 Mortgage Pass Through Certificates, Series 2007-NC4 as agent and Attorney in Fact for Austin Eugene Nipper and Paula M. Nipper Aldridge Connors, LLP, 15 Piedmont Center, 3575 Piedmont Road, N.E., Suite 500, Atlanta, Georgia 30305, (404) 994-7400.
1017-655789A THIS LAW FIRM MAY BE ACTING AS A DEBT COLLECTOR ATTEMPTING TO COLLECT A DEBT. ANY INFORMATION OBTAINED WILL BE USED FOR THAT PURPOSE. 1017-655789A 3-8-4Sats.-11-8494
gpn11 NOTICE OF SALE UNDER POWER GEORGIA, WARE COUNTY THIS IS AN ATTEMPT TO COLLECT A DEBT. ANY INFORMATION OBTAINED WILL BE USED FOR THAT PURPOSE.
Under and by virtue of the Power of Sale contained in a Security Deed given by Thomas A. Vance and Elissa Vance to SAXON MORTGAGE, INC., dated December 06, 2000, recorded in Deed Book 37-H, Page 130, Ware County, Georgia records, as last transferred to DEUTSCHE BANK TRUST COMPANY AMERICAS F/K/A BANKERS TRUST COMPANY, AS TRUSTEE FOR SAXON ASSET SECURITIES TRUST 2000-4, MORTGAGE LOAN ASSET BACKED CERTIFICATES, SERIES 2000-4 by assignment recorded or to be recorded, Ware County, Georgia records conveying the after-described property to secure a Note in the original principal amount of ONE HUNDRED THIRTY-SIX THOUSAND AND 00/100THS DOLLARS ($136, 000.00); with interest thereon as set forth therein, there will be sold at public outcry to the highest bidder for cash before the courthouse door of Ware County, Georgia, within the legal hours of sale on the first Tuesday in April, 2014 the following described property: ALL THAT TRACT OR PARCEL OF LAND SITUATED, LYING AND BEING IN THE CITY OF WAYCROSS, WARE COUNTY, GEORGIA, AND BEING PART OF LOT 14 OF BLOCK 718 OF CHEROKEE HILLS, A SUBDIVISION AS PER PLAT OF RECORD IN THE OFFICE OF THE CLERK OF WARE COUNTY SUPERIOR COURT, PLAT BOOK A, PAGE 280 AND ALSO BEING THE LAND NORTH OF SAID BLOCK 718, NOT PLATTED BUT LYING EAST OF A CONTINUATION OF DANORA DRIVE, SAID PROPERTY BEING MORE PARTICULARLY DESCRIBED AS FOLLOWS: BEGIN ON THE EASTERN MARGIN OF DANORA DRIVE A DISTANCE OF 1337 FEET NORTH OF THE NORTHEAST CORNER OF THE INTERSECTION OF DANORA DRIVE AND SEMINOLE TRAIL AND RUN THENCE NORTH ALONG THE EAST MARGIN OF DANORA DRIVE A DISTANCE OF 763 FEET TO A CANAL; RUN THENCE IN AN EASTERLY DIRECTION ALONG SAID CANAL A DISTANCE OF 200 FEET TO A POINT WHICH WOULD BE A CONTINUATION OF THE EAST BORDER OF SAID BLOCK 718; RUN THENCE SOUTH ALONG SAID CONTINUATION OF THE EAST BOUNDARY OF SAID BLOCK 718 AND ALONG THE EAST BOUNDARY OF PART OF LOT 14 IN BLOCK 718 A DISTANCE OF 776.5 FEET TO PROPERTY NOW OR FORMERLY OWNED BY H. M. WARREN; RUN THENCE WEST ALONG SAID WARREN PROPERTY A DISTANCE OF 200 FEET TO THE EAST MARGIN OF DANORA DRIVE AND THE PLACE OR POINT OF BEGINNING.
The debt secured by said Security Deed has been and is hereby declared due because of, among other possible events of default, failure to pay the indebtedness as and when due and in the manner provided in the Note and Security Deed. The debt remaining in default, this sale will be made for the purpose of paying the same and all expenses of this sale, as provided in Security Deed and by law, including attorney's fees (notice of intent to collect attorney's fees having been given).
Said property will be sold subject to any outstanding ad valorem taxes (including taxes which are a lien, but not yet due and payable), any matters which might be disclosed by an accurate survey and inspection of the property, any assessments, liens, encumbrances, zoning ordinances, restrictions, covenants, and matters of record superior to the Security Deed first set out above.
The entity that has full authority to negotiate, amend, and modify all terms of the mortgage with the debtor is: Ocwen Loan Servicing LLC, Attention: Home Retention Department, 1661 Worthington Road, Suite 100, West Palm Beach, FL 33409, Fax 407-737-5693. Please understand that the secured creditor is not required by law to negotiate, amend, or modify the terms of the mortgage instrument.
To the best knowledge and belief of the undersigned, the parties in possession of the property are Thomas A. Vance and Elissa Vance or a tenant or tenants and said property is more commonly known as 1900 Danora Drive, Waycross, GA 31501.
The sale will be conducted subject (1) to confirmation that the sale is not prohibited under the U.S. Bankruptcy Code and (2) to final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan with the holder of the security deed.
DEUTSCHE BANK TRUST COMPANY AMERICAS F/K/A BANKERS TRUST COMPANY, AS TRUSTEE FOR SAXON ASSET SECURITIES TRUST 2000-4, MORTGAGE LOAN ASSET BACKED CERTIFICATES, SERIES 2000-4 As Attorney in Fact for Thomas A. Vance and Elissa Vance Weissman, Nowack, Curry & Wilco, PC Attn: Ocwen Team One Alliance Center 3500 Lenox Road Atlanta, GA 30326 Our File# 019740 3-8-4Sats.-11-8495
gpn11 NOTICE OF SALE UNDER POWER GEORGIA, WARE COUNTY THIS LAW FIRM IS ACTING AS A DEBT COLLECTOR ATTEMPTING TO COLLECT A DEBT. ANY INFORMATION OBTAINED WILL BE USED FOR THAT PURPOSE.
Under and by virtue of the Power of Sale contained in a Security Deed given by James H. Morgan to Mortgage Electronic Registration Systems, Inc. as nominee for Irwin Mortgage Corporation, it's successor and assigns, dated June 30, 2004, recorded in Deed Book 45 W, Page 235, Ware County, Georgia Records, as last transferred to MidFirst Bank by assignment to be recorded in the Office of the Clerk of Superior Court of Ware County, Georgia Records, conveying the after-described property to secure a Note in the original principal amount of SEVENTY-THREE THOUSAND SEVEN HUNDRED EIGHTY-SIX AND 0/100 DOLLARS ($73, 786.00), with interest thereon as set forth therein, there will be sold at public outcry to the highest bidder for cash before the courthouse door ofWare County, Georgia, or at such place as may be lawfully designated as an alternative, within the legal hours of sale on the first Tuesday in April, 2014, the following described property: SEE EXHIBIT "A" ATTACHED HERETO AND MADE A PART HEREOF The debt secured by said Security Deed has been and is hereby declared due because of, among other possible events of default, failure to pay the indebtedness as and when due and in the manner provided in the Note and Security Deed. The debt remaining in default, this sale will be made for the purpose of paying the same and all expenses of this sale, as provided in Security Deed and by law, including attorney's fees (notice of intent to collect attorney's fees having been given). Said property will be sold subject to any outstanding ad valorem taxes (including taxes which are a lien, but not yet due and payable), any matters which might be disclosed by an accurate survey and inspection of the property, any assessments, liens, encumbrances, zoning ordinances, restrictions, covenants, and matters of record superior to the Security Deed first set out above. MidFirst Bank is the holder of the Security Deed to the property in accordance with OCGA § 44-14-162.2. The entity that has full authority to negotiate, amend, and modify all terms of the mortgage with the debtor is: Midland Mortgage, a division of MidFirst Bank, 999 N.W. Grand Boulevard Suite 100, Oklahoma City, OK 73118-6116, 800-654-4566. To the best knowledge and belief of the undersigned, the party in possession of the property is James H. Morgan or a tenant or tenants and said property is more commonly known as 2645 Connecticut Ave, Waycross, Georgia 31503. The sale will be conducted subject (1) to confirmation that the sale is not prohibited under the U.S (Continued on next page).Bankruptcy Code and (2) to final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan with the holder of the security deed.
MidFirst Bank as Attorney in Fact for James H. Morgan McCalla Raymer, LLC 1544 Old Alabama Road Roswell, Georgia 30076 www.foreclosurehotline.net MR/rkd 4/1/14 Our file no. 544114-FT17 EXHIBIT "A" All that tract or parcel of land situate, lying and being in Land Lot 216 of the 8th Land District of Ware County, Georgia, and being 8.862 acres, more or less, and being more particularly described in that plat of survey prepared by Merlin J. Tomberlin, Georgia Registered Surveyor No. 2477, dated September 24, 2002, and being recorded in the Office of the Clerk of the Ware Superior Court in Plat Book "A", page 3074, reference being made to said plat for all purposes. This real estate being the same real estate convey from Otis Spivey and Berta Mae Spivey to Eureta C. Holloway and William Ray Holloway, as joint tenants with right of survivorship, dated January 5, 1979, and recorded in the Office of the Clerk of the Ware Superior Court in Deed Book 15Y, page 267.
MR/rkd 4/1/14 Our file no. 544114 -FT17 3-8-4Sats.-11-8496
gpn11 Notice of Sale Under Power.
State of Georgia, County of WARE. Under and by virtue of the Power of Sale contained in a Deed to Secure Debt given by WALTER R HIERS AND MARIE ANN HIERS to JPMORGAN CHASE BANK, N.A., dated 11/29/2007, and Recorded on 02/04/2008 as Book No. 55-P and Page No. 249, WARE County, Georgia records, as last assigned to JPMORGAN CHASE BANK, N.A. (the Secured Creditor), by assignment, conveying the after-described property to secure a Note of even date in the original principal amount of $48, 000.00, with interest at the rate specified therein, there will be sold by the undersigned at public outcry to the highest bidder for cash at the WARE County Courthouse within the legal hours of sale on the first Tuesday in April, 2014, the following described property:
ALL THAT PARCEL OF LAND IN WARE COUNTY, GEORGIA DESCRIBED AS FOLLOWS: BEGINNING AT THE NORTHEAST CORNER OF THE INTERSECTION OF WARING STREET AND DOROTHY STREET AND RUNNING THENCE NORTH ALONG THE EAST MARGIN OF DOROTHY STREET A DISTANCE OF 133.5 FEET TO AN IRON PIN AND OTHER LANDS OF GRANTOR HEREIN; THENCE RUN EAST ALONG OTHER LANDS OF GRANTOR HEREIN A DISTANCE OF 133.4 FEET TO AN IRON PIN; THENCE RUN SOUTH AT AN INSIDE ANGLE OF 90 DEGREES A DISTANCE OF 133.5 FEET TO AN IRON PIN ON THE NORTHERLY MARGIN OF WARING STREET; THENCE RUN WEST ALONG THE NORTHERLY MARGIN OF WARING STREET A DISTANCE OF 133.4 FEET TO DOROTHY STREET AND THE PLACE OR POINT OF BEGINNING. THIS COMPRISES ALL OF LOTS 1 AND 2 AND THE SOUTH 33.5 FEET OF LOT 10 OF BLOCK 1 OF GOLF HEIGHTS SUBDIVISION. ACCORDING TO A PLAT THEREOF RECORDED IN THE OFFICE OF THE CLERK OFWARE SUPERIOR COURT IN PLAT BOOK A, PAGE 46. TOGETHER WITH ALL IMPROVEMENTS LOCATED THEREON. 052B 10 005 The debt secured by said Deed to Secure Debt has been and is hereby declared due because of, among other possible events of default, failure to pay the indebtedness as and when due and in the manner provided in the Note and Deed to Secure Debt. Because the debt remains in default, this sale will be made for the purpose of paying the same and all expenses of this sale, as provided in the Deed to Secure Debt and by law, including attorney's fees (notice of intent to collect attorney's fees having been given). JPMORGAN CHASE BANK, N.A. holds the duly endorsed Note and is the current assignee of the Security Deed to the property. JPMORGAN CHASE BANK, N.A., acting on behalf of and, as necessary, in consultation with JPMORGAN CHASE BANK, N.A. (the current investor on the loan), is the entity with the full authority to negotiate, amend, and modify all terms of the loan. Pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 44-14-162.2, JPMORGAN CHASE BANK, N.A. may be contacted at: JPMORGAN CHASE BANK, N.A., 8333 RIDGEPOINT DRIVE, IRVING, TX 75063, 866-550-5705. Please note that, pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 44-14-162.2, the secured creditor is not required to amend or modify the terms of the loan. To the best knowledge and belief of the undersigned, the party/parties in possession of the subject property known as 801 E WARING ST, WAYCROSS, GEORGIA 31501 is/are: WALTER R HIERSAND MARIEANN HIERS or tenant/tenants. Said property will be sold subject to (a) any outstanding ad valorem taxes (including taxes which are a lien, but not yet due and payable), (b) any matters which might be disclosed by an accurate survey and inspection of the property, and (c) all matters of record superior to the Deed to Secure Debt first set out above, including, but not limited to, assessments, liens, encumbrances, zoning ordinances, easements, restrictions, covenants, etc. The sale will be conducted subject to (1) confirmation that the sale is not prohibited under the U.S. Bankruptcy Code; and (2) final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan with the holder of the security deed. Pursuant to O.C.G.A. Section 9-13-172.1, which allows for certain procedures regarding the rescission of judicial and nonjudicial sales in the State of Georgia, the Deed Under Power and other foreclosure documents may not be provided until final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan as provided in the preceding paragraph.
JPMORGAN CHASE BANK, N.A. as Attorney in Fact for WALTER R HIERS AND MARIE ANN HIERS.
THIS LAW FIRM IS ACTING AS A DEBT COLLECTOR ATTEMPTING TO COLLECT A DEBT. ANY INFORMATION OBTAINED WILL BE USED FOR THAT PURPOSE.
00000004155453 BARRETT DAFFIN FRAPPIER LEVINE & BLOCK, LLP 15000 Surveyor Boulevard Addison, Texas 75001 Telephone: (972) 341-5398.
3-8-4Sats.-11-8497
gpn11 Notice of Sale Under Power.
State of Georgia, County of WARE. Under and by virtue of the Power of Sale contained in a Deed to Secure Debt given by LINDA M MILES to MORTGAGE ELECTRONIC REGISTRATION SYSTEMS, INC. ("MERS"), AS NOMINEE FOR ACCESS NATIONAL MORTGAGE, dated 06/25/2008, and Recorded on 07/22/2008 as Book No. 56-S and Page No. 019-031, WARE County, Georgia records, as last assigned to WELLS FARGO BANK, N.A. (the Secured Creditor), by assignment, conveying the after-described property to secure a Note of even date in the original principal amount of $122, 307.00, with interest at the rate specified therein, there will be sold by the undersigned at public outcry to the highest bidder for cash at the WARE County Courthouse within the legal hours of sale on the first Tuesday in April, 2014, the following described property:
ALL THAT TRACT OR PARCEL OF LAND SITUATE, LYING AND BEING IN WAYCROSS, WARE COUNTY, GEORGIA, BEING KNOWN AS LOTS 15 AND 16 OF BLOCK 11 OF BONITA SUBDIVISION AND BEING MORE PARTICULARLY DESCRIBED AS FOLLOWS: COMMENCE AT THE NORTHEAST INTERSECTION OF THE RIGHT OF WAY OF CONGRESS STREET AND LORD STREET; THENCE RUN NORTH ALONG THE EASTERN MARGIN OF THE RIGHT OF WAY OF LORD STREET A DISTANCE OF 140 FEET; THENCE FORMAN INTERIOR ANGLE OF 88 DEGREES 38 MINUTES 18 SECONDS RUN EASTA DISTANCE OF 100 FEET; THENCE FORM AN INTERIOR ANGLE OF 91 DEGREES 21 MINUTES 42 SECONDS RUN SOUTH A DISTANCE OF 140 FEET TO THE NORTHERN MARGIN OF THE RIGHT OF WAY OF CONGRESS STREET; THENCE FORM AN INTERIOR ANGLE OF 86 DEGREES 38 MINUTES 18 SECONDS RUN WEST ALONG THE NORTHERN MARGIN OF THE RIGHT OF WAY OF CONGRESS STREET A DISTANCE OF 100 FEET TO THE POINT OF PLACE OF BEGINNING OF THE LANDS HEREIN CONVEYED.
SUBJECT TO RESTRICTIONS, RESERVATIONS, EASEMENTS, CONVENANTS, OIL, GAS OR MINERAL RIGHTS OF RECORD, IF ANY.
PARCEL NO. WA1906 037 The debt secured by said Deed to Secure Debt has been and is hereby declared due because of, among other possible events of default, failure to pay the indebtedness as and when due and in the manner provided in the Note and Deed to Secure Debt. Because the debt remains in default, this sale will be made for the purpose of paying the same and all expenses of this sale, as provided in the Deed to Secure Debt and by law, including attorney's fees (notice of intent to collect attorney's fees having been given). WELLS FARGO BANK, N.A. holds the duly endorsed Note and is the current assignee of the Security Deed to the property. WELLS FARGO BANK, N.A., acting on behalf of and, as necessary, in consultation with WELLS FARGO BANK, N.A. (the current investor on the loan), is the entity with the full authority to negotiate, amend, and modify all terms of the loan. Pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 44-14-162.2, WELLS FARGO BANK, N.A. may be contacted at: WELLS FARGO BANK, N.A., 3476 STATEVIEW BLVD, FORT MILL, SC 29715, 803-396-6000. Please note that, pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 44-14-162.2, the secured creditor is not required to amend or modify the terms of the loan. To the best knowledge and belief of the undersigned, the party/parties in possession of the subject property known as 1401 CONGRESS STREET, WAYCROSS, GEORGIA 31501 is/are: LINDA M MILES or tenant/tenants. Said property will be sold subject to (a) any outstanding ad valorem taxes (including taxes which are a lien, but not yet due and payable), (b) any matters which might be disclosed by an accurate survey and inspection of the property, and (c) all matters of record superior to the Deed to Secure Debt first set out above, including, but not limited to, assessments, liens, encumbrances, zoning ordinances, easements, restrictions, covenants, etc.
The sale will be conducted subject to (1) confirmation that the sale is not prohibited under the U.S. Bankruptcy Code; and (2) final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan with the holder of the security deed. Pursuant to O.C.G.A. Section 9-13-172.1, which allows for certain procedures regarding the rescission of judicial and nonjudicial sales in the State of Georgia, the Deed Under Power and other foreclosure documents may not be provided until final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan as provided in the preceding paragraph.
WELLS FARGO BANK, N.A. as Attorney in Fact for LINDAM MILES.
THIS LAW FIRM IS ACTING AS A DEBT COLLECTOR ATTEMPTING TO COLLECT A DEBT. ANY INFORMATION OBTAINED WILL BE USED FOR THAT PURPOSE.
20120169802879 BARRETT DAFFIN FRAPPIER LEVINE & BLOCK, LLP 15000 Surveyor Boulevard Addison, Texas 75001 Telephone: (972) 341-5398.
3-8-4Sats.-11-8498
gpn11 Notice of Sale Under Power.
State of Georgia, County of WARE. Under and by virtue of the Power of Sale contained in a Deed to Secure Debt given by JAMES T CROSBY AND A/K/A JAMES TIMOTHY CROSBY to PRIME SOUTH MORTGAGE, dated 05/14/2004, and Recorded on 05/25/2004 as Book No. 45 and Page No. 254, WARE County, Georgia records, as last assigned to THE BANK OF NEW YORK MELLON FKA THE BANK OF NEW YORK AS TRUSTEE FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE CERTIFICATE HOLDERS OF THE CWALT, INC., ALTERNATIVE LOAN TRUST 2004-16CB, MORTGAGE PASS THROUGH CERTIFICATES, SERIES 2004-16CB (the Secured Creditor), by assignment, conveying the after-described property to secure a Note of even date in the original principal amount of $105, 500.00, with interest at the rate specified therein, there will be sold by the undersigned at public outcry to the highest bidder for cash at the WARE County Courthouse within the legal hours of sale on the first Tuesday in April, 2014, the following described property: ALL THAT TRACT OR PARCEL OF LAND, SITUATE, LYING AND BEING IN LAND LOT NO. 122 OF THE 8TH LAND DISTRICT OF WARE COUNTY, GEORGIA, DESCRIBED AS BEING ALL OF LOT 2 OF PARK PLACE SUBDIVISION. SAID PROPERTY BEING FULLY SHOWN BY THAT CERTAIN PLAT OF SURVEY MADE BY HARRY W. PREVATT, AND RECORDED IN THE OFFICE OF THE CLERK OF WARE COUNTY SUPERIOR COURT, IN PLAT BOOK A, PAGE 2611, WHICH PLAT IS INCORPORATED HEREIN BY REFERENCE FOR A MORE COMPLETE AND PARTICULAR DESCRIPTION AS TO METES, BOUNDS, COURSES AND DISTANCES AND FOR ALL OTHER LEGAL PURPOSES.
The debt secured by said Deed to Secure Debt has been and is hereby declared due because of, among other possible events of default, failure to pay the indebtedness as and when due and in the manner provided in the Note and Deed to Secure Debt. Because the debt remains in default, this sale will be made for the purpose of paying the same and all expenses of this sale, as provided in the Deed to Secure Debt and by law, including attorney's fees (notice of intent to collect attorney's fees having been given). THE BANK OF NEW YORK MELLON FKA THE BANK OF NEW YORK AS TRUSTEE FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE CERTIFICATE HOLDERS OF THE CWALT, INC., ALTERNATIVE LOAN TRUST 2004-16CB, MORTGAGE PASS THROUGH CERTIFICATES, SERIES 2004-16CB holds the duly endorsed Note and is the current assignee of the Security Deed to the property. RESURGENT CAPITAL SERVICES, LP, acting on behalf of and, as necessary, in consultation with THE BANK OF NEW YORK MELLON FKA THE BANK OF NEW YORK AS TRUSTEE FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE CERTIFICATE HOLDERS OF THE CWALT, INC., ALTERNATIVE LOAN TRUST 2004-16CB, MORTGAGE PASS THROUGH CERTIFICATES, SERIES 2004-16CB (the current investor on the loan), is the entity with the full authority to negotiate, amend, and modify all terms of the loan. Pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 44-14-162.2, RESURGENT CAPITAL SERVICES, LP may be contacted at: RESURGENT CAPITAL SERVICES, LP, 15 SOUTH MAIN ST., SUITE 600, GREENVILLE, SC 29603, 864-678-8300. Please note that, pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 44-14-162.2, the secured creditor is not required to amend or modify the terms of the loan. To the best knowledge and belief of the undersigned, the party/parties in possession of the subject property known as 406 LAMPLIGHTER LANE, WAYCROSS, GEORGIA 31503 is/are: JAMES T CROSBY AND A/K/A JAMES TIMOTHY CROSBY or tenant/tenants. Said property will be sold subject to (a) any outstanding ad valorem taxes (including taxes which are a lien, but not yet due and payable), (b) any matters which might be disclosed by an accurate survey and inspection of the property, and (c) all matters of record superior to the Deed to Secure Debt first set out above, including, but not limited to, assessments, liens, encumbrances, zoning ordinances, easements, restrictions, covenants, etc. The sale will be conducted subject to (1) confirmation that the sale is not prohibited under the U.S. Bankruptcy Code; and (2) final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan with the holder of the security deed. Pursuant to O.C.G.A. Section 9-13-172.1, which allows for certain procedures regarding the rescission of judicial and nonjudicial sales in the State of Georgia, the Deed Under Power and other foreclosure documents may not be provided until final confirmation and audit of the status of the loan as provided in the preceding paragraph.
THE BANK OF NEW YORK MELLON FKA THE BANK OF NEW YORK AS TRUSTEE FOR THE BENEFIT OF THE CERTIFICATE HOLDERS OF THE CWALT, INC., ALTERNATIVE LOAN TRUST 2004-16CB, MORTGAGE PASS THROUGH CERTIFICATES, SERIES 2004-16CB as Attorney in Fact for JAMES T CROSBYAND A/K/A JAMES TIMOTHY CROSBY.
THIS LAW FIRM IS ACTING AS A DEBT COLLECTOR ATTEMPTING TO COLLECT A DEBT. ANY INFORMATION OBTAINED WILL BE USED FOR THAT PURPOSE.
20110031410539 BARRETT DAFFIN FRAPPIER LEVINE & BLOCK, LLP 15000 Surveyor Boulevard Addison, Texas 75001 Telephone: (972) 341-5398.
3-8-4Sats.-11-8499
gpn12 IN THE SUPERIOR COURT OF WARE COUNTY STATE OF GEORGIA Forfeiture: OCGA §16-13-49 THE STATE OF GEORGIA ex rel. Bradley L. Collins District Attorney, Waycross Judicial Circuit, Plaintiff, v. FIVE HUNDRED, NINETY SIX DOLLARS ($596.00) IN U.S. CURRENCY; AND ONE (1) 1998 FORD CROWN VICTORIA, VIN-2FAFP71W5WX186930; Defendant in rem.
ANDRE DEANGELO ADDISON, Potential Claimant.
NOTICE OF SEIZURE AND FORFEITURE OF PERSONAL PROPERTY VALUED AT LESS THAN $25, 000 Pursuant to O.C.G.A. §16-13-49, you are hereby notified that on the 10th day of February, 2014, the following property was seized from Andre Deangelo Addison by the undersigned agency and there is a forfeiture pending against said property in Ware County, Georgia: Five hundred, ninety-six dollars ($596.00) in U.S. currency; and One (1) 1998 Ford Crown Victoria, black in color, VIN-2FAFP71W5WX186930, GA tag WX9G02.
The conduct giving rise to said seizure was as follows: On February 10th, 2014, Det. J.J. Nolan of the Ware County Sheriff's Office was stopped at a red light on the Brunswick Hwy at City Boulevard, in Ware County, Georgia, when he heard loud music from over 100 feet away and observed a black Crown Victoria vehicle coming up from behind his patrol car. Det. Nolan conducted a traffic stop and advised the driver, Andre D. Addison, that he pulled him over for loud music (in violation of 40-6-14 (a). While talking to Addison, Det. Nolan noticed a strong smell of marijuana coming from inside the vehicle, and called for the Ware County S.O. K-9 Unit. When Deputy Drury arrived, Addison took off at a high rate of speed eastbound on the Brunswick Hwy, driving in excess of 110 mph. While driving from Hatcher Point Road to Miles Still Road, Addison was throwing ounce sized bags of marijuana out of the driver's window. Georgia State Patrol Tpr. G. Stone joined in the pursuit and as Addison tried to turn onto Whitehall Church Road the vehicle skidded on the shoulder of the roadway and came to a stop. Addison exited the vehicle and Deputies were able to take him into custody before he tried to escape on foot. While searching Addison, Det. Nolan located $596.00 in his front right pocket. Addison was taken to the Ware County Jail. Deputies seized the marijuana that was thrown out during the high speed chase, along with a bag of marijuana lodged in the grill of Dep. Drury's patrol vehicle and marijuana found in Addison's vehicle. The approximate weight of recovered marijuana seized was 89 grams. The seized property is now in the custody of the Ware County Sheriff's Office, 3487 Harris Road, Waycross, Georgia. Andre D. Addison was charged with Possession of Marijuana with Intent to Distribute, Felony Fleeing and Attempting to Elude a Police Officer, Reckless Driving, and Loud Music violation. Said currency and property were used or intended for use, to facilitate a violation of O.C.G.A. 16-13-30, or proceeds derived or realized therefrom, and said property was found in close proximity of said unlawful drugs.
You may file a claim by sending the claim by certified mail, return receipt requested, to the District Attorney and to the seizing agency at the addresses shown below. Your claim must comply with the requirements set forth in O.C.G.A. §16-13-49 (n) (4) and must be filed within thirty (30) days of the second publication of this notice in the official organ of Ware County, Georgia.
This 27th day of February, 2014. BRADLEY L. COLLINS DISTRICTATTORNEY State Bar No.940389 Waycross Judicial Circuit 306 Albany Avenue Waycross, Georgia 31501 (912) 287-4395 Ware County Sheriff's Office 3487 Harris Rd.
Waycross, GA 31503 Attn: Det. J.J. Nolan 3-8-3Sats.-12-8500
gpn6 NOTICE OF INTENT TO INCORPORATE Notice is given that Articles of Incorporation which will incorporateWAYCROSS PHYSICAL THERAPY, LLC will be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing in accordance with the Georgia Business Corporation Code. The initial registered office of the Corporation will be located at 1063 Woods Road, Waycross, Ware County, Georgia, and its initial Registered Agent at such address is Philip M. Suess, IV.
MARY JANE CARDWELL P. O. BOX 756 WAYCROSS, GA 31502 912-285-0393 3-8-2Sats.-6-8501
gpn6 Notice of Intent to Incorporate "Notice is given that Articles of Incorporation which will incorporate Taylor Pools, Inc., will be delivered to the Secretary of State for filing in accordance with the Georgia Business Corporation Code. The initial registered office of the corporation is located at 408 Harrison St., Waycross, Ware County, Georgia 31501, and its initial registered agent is Christopher R. Taylor."
3-8-2Sats.-6-8502
gpn6 Notice is given that articles of incorporation that will incorporate Mae's Grocery and HObby Store, Inc. have been delivered to the Secretary of State for filing in accordance with the Georgia Business Corporation Code. The initial registered office of the corporation is located at 1910 Woodrow Avenue Waycross, Ga. 31501 and its initial registered agent at such address is Earl A. Lawson, Jr.,
3-8-2Sats.-6-8503
gpn11 Georgia, Ware County Under and by virtue of power of sale contained in certain unrecorded contract between Robert N. Howard of Pierce County, Georgia, and Freddy Davis of Ware County Georgia in the original sum of $16, 227.48. With interest as specified the undersigned of the contract will sell at public outcry to the highest bidder for cash before the court house door in Ware County, Georgia, during the legal hours of sale on the first Tuesday in April 2014. The following property. All that improved parcel of land being in Ware County Georgia. Described being all of lot 216 of the 8th land distract Ware County Georgia and in land lot 10 block B of record in the office of Ware County Clerk of Superior Court. In plat book A page 2264 which said plat is incorporated here in.
And together with all improvements located there on including a 1988 Peach State Mobilehome. The debt secured by said contract has been here by declared due because among other events of default failure to pay the indebtedness when due in purpose of paying the same and all expenses of the sale. In said contract including attorney fees. To the best of belief the party in possession is Freddy Davis. Robert Howard Attorney in fact for Freddy Davis.
Robert Howard 6502 Hacklebarney Dr. Blackshear, Ga 31516 Bankrupts cancels sale.
3-8-4Sats.-11-8504
gpn4 IN THE SUPERIOR COURT OF WARE COUNTY STATE OF GEORGIA DEPARTMENT OF TRANSPORTATION vCAF# 13V-0897 0.789 ACRES OF LAND; and DAN JUNIORWASHINGTON; HEIRS OF DAN JUNIORWASHINGTON; ELLAWASHINGTON, SPOUSE OF DAN JUNIORWASHINGTON; DARRELL E.WASHINGTON, BELIEVED TO BE AND HEIR OF DAN WASHINGTON; KEESHA WASHINGTON, BELIEVED TO BE AN HEIR OF DAN WASHINGTON; TERRENCE WASHINGTON, BELIEVED TO BE AN HEIR OF DANWASHINGTON; DERRICK WASHINGTON, BELIEVED TO BE AN HEIR OF DANWASHINGTON; ANGELA DANETTEWASHINGTON, BELIEVED TO BE AN HEIR OF DAN WASHINGTON; ALBERT JONES, BELIEVED TO BE AN HEIR OF DAN WASHINGTON; AND DAN WASHINGTON, JR., BELIEVED TO BE AN HEIR OF DANWASHINGTON; AND WARE COUNTY TAX COMMISSIONER, INDIVIDUALLY.
NOTICE OF SUMMONS TO: ALBERT JONES, a Condemnee Named Above: You are hereby notified that the abovestyled condemnation proceeding was filed against you in said Court on December 3, 2013 and that by reason of an Order for Service of Summons By Publication entered by the Court on January 17, 2014 and filed with the Clerk of Ware Superior Court on January 17, 2014, you are hereby commanded and required to file with the Clerk of Said Court and serve upon Neal L. Conner, Jr., Condemnorís Attorney, whose address is Post Office Box 1278, Waycross, GA 31502, an appeal to the Petition within sixty (60) days of the date of the Order for Service by Publication.
Witness the Honorable Michael Devane, Judge ofWare County Superior Court.
This the 25th day of February, 2014.
/s/Melba H. Fiveash Clerk ofWare Superior Court CONNER AND JACKSON, P.C. P O. BOX 1278 WAYCROSS, GA 31502 1-912-283-4394 3-8-2Sats.-4-8505
gpn18 IN THE PROBATE COURT COUNTY OFWARE STATE OF GEORGIA IN RE: ESTATE OF KENNETH LARRY BECHIOM, DECEASED ESTATE NO. NOTICE OF PETITION TO FILE FOR YEAR'S SUPPORT The petition of Sandra Rouse Bechiom, for a year's support from the estate of Kenneth Larry Bechiom, deceased, for decedent's surviving spouse, having been duly filed, all interested persons are hereby notified to show cause, if any they have, on or before March 31, 2014, why said petition should not be granted.
All objections to the petition must be in writing, setting forth the grounds of any such objections, and must be filed on or before the time stated in the preceding sentence. All pleadings/objections must be signed before a notary public or before a probate court clerk, and filing fees must be tendered with your pleadings/objections, unless you qualify to file as an indigent party. Contact probate court personnel at the following address/telephone number for the required amount of filing fees. If any objections are filed, a hearing will be scheduled at a later date. If no objections are filed the Petition may be granted without a hearing.
/s/Calvin A. Bennett Judge of the Probate Court By: Melissa Paul Clerk/Deputy Clerk of the Probate Court Conner and Jackson P O Box 1278 Waycross, GA 31501 912-283-4394 3-8-4Sats.-18-8506
gpn20 IN THE MUNICIPAL COURT OF THE CITY OFWAYCROSS STATE OF GEORGIA CITY OFWAYCROSS, GEORGIA, COMPLAINT IN REM Plaintiff, vs.
CASE NO. 14-0008 JAMES KEVIN SMITH, CLAIMANTS KNOWN OR UNKNOWN, and that property at 1202 Byrd Street, Waycross, Ware County, Georgia, according to the current numbering system in said City, Defendants. SUMMONS TO THE DEFENDANTS: JAMES KEVIN SMITH, CLAIMANTS KNOWN OR UNKNOWN, and that property at 1202 Byrd Street, Waycross, Georgia.
You are hereby summoned and notified that a hearing will be held at 1:30 p.m. on March 20, 2014, at the Municipal Court of the City of Waycross, located at the Waycross Police Station, 512 Oak Street, Waycross, Georgia, being within the County where the property described in the Complaint is located. If you fail to appear, judgment by default will be taken against you for the relief demanded in the Complaint.
This 4th day of March, 2014.
CLERK OF MUNICIPAL COURT, CITY OFWAYCROSS BY: CARLA NIPPER Clerk 3-8-2Sats.-20-8508
gpn20 IN THE MUNICIPAL COURT OF THE CITY OFWAYCROSS STATE OF GEORGIA CITY OFWAYCROSS, GEORGIA, COMPLAINT IN REM Plaintiff, vs.
KEVIN ALTMAN, CASE NO. 14-0007 CLAIMANTS KNOWN OR UNKNOWN, and that property at 315 Butler Street, Waycross, Ware County, Georgia, according to the current numbering system in said City, Defendants. SUMMONS TO THE DEFENDANTS: KEVIN ALTMAN, CLAIMANTS KNOWN OR UNKNOWN, and that property at 315 BUTLER STREET, Waycross, Georgia.
You are hereby summoned and notified that a hearing will be held at 1:30 p.m. on March 20, 2014, at the Municipal Court of the City of Waycross, located at the Waycross Police Station, 512 Oak Street, Waycross, Georgia, being within the County where the property described in the Complaint is located. If you fail to appear, judgment by default will be taken against you for the relief demanded in the Complaint.
This 4th day of March, 2014.
CLERK OF MUNICIPAL COURT, CITY OFWAYCROSS BY: CARLA NIPPER Clerk 3-8-2Sats.-20-8509
gpn20 IN THE MUNICIPAL COURT OF THE CITY OFWAYCROSS STATE OF GEORGIA CITY OFWAYCROSS, GEORGIA, COMPLAINT IN REM Plaintiff, vs.
ODELL BARNES, LLC, CASE NO. 14-0006 CLAIMANTS KNOWN OR UNKNOWN, and that property at 1203 Margaret Street, Waycross, Ware County, Georgia, according to the current numbering system in said City, Defendants. SUMMONS TO THE DEFENDANTS: ODELL BARNES, LLC, CLAIMANTS KNOWN OR UNKNOWN, and that property at 1203 Margaret Street, Waycross, Georgia. You are hereby summoned and notified that a hearing will be held at 1:30 p.m. on March 20, 2014, at the Municipal Court of the City of Waycross, located at the Waycross Police Station, 512 Oak Street, Waycross, Georgia, being within the County where the property described in the Complaint is located. If you fail to appear, judgment by default will be taken against you for the relief demanded in the Complaint. This 4th day of March, 2014.
CLERK OF MUNICIPAL COURT, CITY OFWAYCROSS BY: CARLA NIPPER Clerk 3-8-2Sats.-20-8510
gpn20 IN THE MUNICIPAL COURT OF THE CITY OFWAYCROSS STATE OF GEORGIA CITY OFWAYCROSS, GEORGIA, COMPLAINT IN REM Plaintiff, vs.
JOSEPH JORDAN, CASE NO. 14-0005 CLAIMANTS KNOWN OR UNKNOWN, and that property at 1701 Overton Avenue, Waycross, Ware County, Georgia, according to the current numbering system in said City, Defendants. SUMMONS TO THE DEFENDANTS: JOSEPH JORDAN, CLAIMANTS KNOWN OR UNKNOWN, and that property at 1701 Overton Avenue, Waycross, Georgia.
You are hereby summoned and notified that a hearing will be held at 1:30 p.m. on March 20, 2014, at the Municipal Court of the City of Waycross, located at the Waycross Police Station, 512 Oak Street, Waycross, Georgia, being within the County where the property described in the Complaint is located. If you fail to appear, judgment by default will be taken against you for the relief demanded in the Complaint.
This 4th day of March, 2014.
CLERK OF MUNICIPAL COURT, CITY OFWAYCROSS BY: CARLA NIPPER Clerk 3-8-2Sats.-20-8511
gpn20 IN THE MUNICIPAL COURT OF THE CITY OFWAYCROSS STATE OF GEORGIA CITY OFWAYCROSS, GEORGIA, COMPLAINT IN REM Plaintiff, vs.
DOROTHY DILLINGHAM, CASE NO. 14-0004 CLAIMANTS KNOWN OR UNKNOWN, and that property at 705 Miller Street,
]]></text></news-item>