<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F671-1D16-F7E4-BB15"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Anti-union group files suit against UAW, VW</title><source>Detroit Free Press (Michigan)</source><author>By, Brent Snavely</author><text><![CDATA[An anti-union organization and three Volkswagen workers in Chattanooga, Tenn., have sued the automaker and the UAW to prevent them from colluding to overturn the results of a vote last month in which more than half the workers rejected UAW representation.
The National Right to Work Foundation filed the lawsuit in federal court in Chattanooga.
Volkswagen was officially neutral in an election held at the plant Feb. 12-14. Workers rejected UAW representation 712-626.
The UAW has filed an appeal with the National Labor Relations Board to challenge those results, charging interference from U.S. Sen. Bob Corker, R-Tenn., Tennessee Gov. Bill Haslam and other politicians.
The union wants the NLRB to order a new election. Some elected officials threatened to withhold tax incentives for an expansion of the assembly plant if workers joined the UAW.
The National Right to Work Foundation alleges "the neutrality arrangement between VW and UAW union organizers contain numerous prohibited provisions, including mandatory pro-union meetings, use of company property by outside UAW organizers, and clauses preventing VW and its managers from opposing unionization."
UAW President Bob King called the suit baseless.
"The National Right to Work Legal Foundation has a history of frivolous lawsuits trying to stop workers from joining the UAW, including failed lawsuits at Dana and Freightliner," King said.
The anti-union group is attacking a pillar of union organizing that could have widespread ramifications for all of organized labor, said Charlotte Garden, assistant professor law at Seattle University School of Law.
"Its been an accepted for a long time that unions and corporations can enter into neutrality agreements," Garden said.
A recent U.S. Court of Appeals ruling found that some neutrality agreements could violate federal law if the company is providing "things of value" to the union during the organizing campaign or election.
In February, Volkswagen said it held mandatory employee meetings about the election, but then told employees they could leave during UAW presentations. Volkswagen said it allowed anti-union groups to distribute material both inside and outside the plant.
In its lawsuit, the National Right to Work Foundation said such meetings are "organizing assistance" to the UAW. It asks the court to prohibit such assistance if the NLRB orders a new election.
Volkswagen declined to comment.
Contact Brent Snavely: 313-222-6512 or bsnavely@freepress.com Follow him on Twitter @BrentSnavely.
]]></text></news-item>