<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F6A7-777B-5D4E-E757"><date>2014-03-10</date><title>Google Gets Clean Chit From US Antitrust, Only To Be Pulled-Up By India's CCI</title><source>WATBlog.com</source><author>Alap Naik Desai</author><text><![CDATA[Google Inc (http://www.google.com/). appears to have become involved in an Antitrust Investigation being conducted by Competition Commission of India (CCI (http://www.cci.gov.in/%E2%80%8E)).
The provider of Search Engine, Mobile Operating System, E-mail and many other internet based products seems to have gotten itself involved (http://www.watblog.com/2012/08/14/indian-antitrust-body-has-google-under-its-radar/) in an Antitrust allegation levied upon by India's CCI. The company has been accused of violating 'Competition Norms'.
Facing an Antitrust probe (http://www.watblog.com/2012/10/17/eu-gives-google-months-to-rectify-privacy-policy/) is nothing new for Google. Big nations like the USA and the European Union (http://www.watblog.com/2010/12/02/european-union-opens-antitrust-investigation-against-google/) have always felt Google skillfully monopolized the Search Segment and in many cases even violated Personal Privacy. This time though, the Privacy violation allegations have not been levied.
This time the complaint has been formally filed by advocacy group CUTS (http://www.cuts-international.org/)International in 2011 as well as an official complaint from matrimonial company Matrimony.Com Private Ltd about Google's unfair promotion of its own products in search results and the company resorting to discrimination by favoring paid searches. Other allegations include 'Denial of Access' to content and "imposing of unfair and discriminatory conditions on 'AdWords' customers".
Is Google guilty? A similar antitrust allegation, which was followed by a lengthy two-year review by USA's antitrust watchdog (http://www.consumerwatchdog.org/) incidentally stood aside Google and confirmed that the company's services were in fact good for the competition!
However, the EU adopted a less-than-favorable stand and Google settled. Unfortunately the Indian Judiciary doesn't have provisions for a settlement & if found guilty Indian laws mandate handing over 10% of the company's three-year annual average turnover. Knowing that Google earns around US$ 49.3 Billion, the company is looking at a potential fine of US$ 5 Billion!
Unfair trade practices certainly have a detrimental effect on the businesses in India. Moreover, search products like Google and Bing have grown to be more than companies (http://www.watblog.com/2011/03/18/microsoft-is-ethical-google-apple-facebook-are-not/) that operate purely for profit. But, will they sacrifice revenues to ensure completely fair search results?
]]></text></news-item>