<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F720-3A02-B8AA-BCF0"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Nigeria; Campaign Against Poor Telco Services Now a Global Issue</title><source>Africa News</source><author>This Day (Lagos)</author><text><![CDATA[As the world sets to mark the World Consumer Right Day tomorrow, themed 'Consimer Rights in the Digital Age', Raheem Akingbolu takes a look at the global campaign on the day, 'Fix Our Phone Rights' with particular reference to Nigeria.
At both local and international markets, stakeholders have continued to mount pressure on telecommunications operators to improve on their quality of services. In Nigeria, the campaign has been thorough in the last six months, following complaints of reap-offs by service providers from consumers.
At the forefront of the struggle are the ministry of Communication Technology, the Consumer Protection Council (CPC) and the National Communication Commission (NCC). It got to the climax towards the end o last year when government gave a matching order to the operators on the urgent need to improve on service or ready to face sanction.
The Consumer International (CI), the global voice for consumer right will be launching a new Consumer Agenda for Fair Mobile Services to mark WCRD tomorrow. The agenda sets out the issues that most effect consumers including the need for access to a reliable service, the security of their data and fair contracts and billing.
CI is expected to submit the agenda to the World Telecommunications Development Conference, held by the International Telecommunications Union, which will later call phone regulators and companies to take action to stop the issues undermining the success of the new technology.
The international body though admitted that the world without mobile phones can be frustrating but opined that it is necessary for stakeholders to worry about the sort of service consumers are receiving, especially when the number of consumers using mobile services now nears seven billion. CI wondered why in just a few years, the operators have become an indispensable part of consumer lives and can be found in almost every country around the world.
"Are consumers being treated fairly? Our 2014 World Consumer Rights Day (WCRD) campaign Fix Our Phone Rights! Is devoted to tackling the issues that most affect consumers of mobile services," a statement issued by the international body stated.
The day is organised by Consumers International, a federation which acts as an independent voice for all of us consumers, wherever we are in the world. The organisation was founded in 1960.
The day was first observed in 1983, demanding that consumer rights were respected and protected. The aim of the day is to celebrate solidarity within the international consumer rights movement.
According to the organisers, WCRD 2014 will be an important opportunity for consumer organisations to draw the world's attention to the crucial role that consumer protection plays in making societies safer and fairer, and how important it is that 21st Century consumers receive 21st Century protection.
Why Phone Rights are important
In 2013, it was estimated that 6.8 billion people owned a mobile phone. In 2011 that figure was 6 billion and in 2010 it was 5.4 billion. At the same time, mobile services have transformed from just being telephones that enable people to talk and text, to mini computers giving users access to information and services that are crucial to livelihoods and health.
Considering this achievement, mobile phones are not just convenient, but increasingly important tools that help to empower citizens and consumers. Based on this, it is generally believed that having access to mobile connectivity is a necessity.
Among other highlights, the 2014 agenda requests that operators should provide consumers with access to an affordable, reliable service provide consumers with fair contracts explained in clear, complete and accessible language and provide consumers with fair and transparent billing. Others include the need to provide consumers with security and power over their own information and listen and respond to consumer complaints.
Consumers want to be able to have access to affordable mobile services in order to communicate and to access information. It is only reasonable that they then expect those services to be consistent and of a high quality without drop outs in service.
Consumers often feel cheated by their mobile provider, either because of unfair contract terms and conditions or because they didn't understand what they had signed. Telecom providers are expected to always provide consumers with fair contracts with all relevant information explained clearly so that consumers can exercise their right to make informed choices.
It is also expected that consumers shouldn't be billed for services they didn't request. The international body is therefore demanding fairness and transparency in consumers' bills, and protection from billing fraud. On data, CI wants the providers and regulators alike to protect the personal data that consumers give up in order to use mobile services.
Whilst giving consent to use personal data can enhance the experience of using a mobile phone, it is believed that it can also compromise the consumer's right to safety. In other words, it expects consumers to be able to set the terms of how this data is used.
In the area of customer relation, it is stated that telecom providers should have effective complaints systems and if consumers are not satisfied there should be redress mechanisms to ensure a fair outcome. In the view of the body, operators must be able to penalise providers for abusive and unjust business practices.
Nigeria experience
For years, Nigerian consumers bear the brunt of poor services and adulterated goods, with little or no effort made by individual or government agency to bring the perpetrators to book. Every day, cases of abuse of consumer rights are brought to public glare but they naturally fizzled out as a result of weak system.
Like other sectors of the economy, the telecommunication industry has over the years received serious bash from Nigerians for poor services and insensitivity of operators to consumers' feelings. However, towards the end of last year, the federal government through the Minister of Communication Technology, Mrs. Omobola Johnson, the Consumer Protection Council (CPC) and the Nigeria Communications Commission (NCC), set 1st of January, 2014 as deadline for operators to meet previously agreed targets on Quality of Services QoS indicators.
At a press briefing jointly addressed by the ministry and the agencies, it was stated that operators that fail to abide by the rule would be prevented from further expansion of their subscribers' base.
Following the pronouncement, many analysts concluded that succor might have come in the way of helpless subscribers, who have for over a decade remained at the mercies of telecommunication operators, whose priority in the market was to make profit, far above service delivery.
Since then, the Director General of the CPC, Mrs. Dupe Atoki, a former commissioner of National Human Rights Commission and her team have not looked back on the resolve to sanitise the industry. Before her appointment, Atoki was the chairperson of the African Union Commission on Human and People's Rights.
In what looked like a build up to the 2014 global campaign of the WCRD, the council met with the chief executive officers of telecommunications companies operating in the country last week over complaints of poor services by consumers. Those summoned to the meeting by the council included the CEOs of Visafone, Airtel and MTN.
Speaking with journalists after the meeting, the Director-General, CPC, Mrs. Dupe Atoki, said ways of addressing various consumer complaints arising from poor network and unsolicited services were discussed.
Others issues discussed according to her are; unlawful deductions, wrong billings, exploitative automated services; unauthorised SIM swaps/line disconnection, as well as poor Internet and customer service.
She said, "I called the meeting of all the CEOs of the telecommunications operators in Nigeria to discuss issues that all Nigerian subscribers are aware of. The main issues that are of concern to Nigerian consumers are drop calls, truncated services, poor network services, unsolicited services, unlawful deductions/wrong billings, exploitative automated services and poor customer services. I commend the operators that attended. Some of them did not attend,"
With the issue now being look into at the international level, it is believed that federal government will support the council and other relevant agencies to call the operators to other.
Infrastructural challenge
While the regulators can be blame for not taking the issue of quality services serious, not a few commentators have condemned government for its failure to provide conducive environment for the operators. It has been argued by many stakeholders that government inability to fix the power sector has become a serious challenge to the operators, who spend billions on diesel to power their base stations.
A reference material on the contribution of the telco sector to Nigeria economy is the recent report of a Pyramid Research study commissioned by the Association of Licensed Telecoms Operators of Nigeria (ALTON) on the socio-economic impact of the telecommunications industry on Nigeria and Nigerians.
According to the report, there are now over 120 million active telephone lines, compared to 400,000 in 2001 before the revolution started. By this statistic, it is obvious that millions of Nigerians now earn their living either directly or indirectly from the sector.
While this is cheering news, the discovery that the service providers must have spent over N50billion to power their business in 2014 is devastating. On this note, it is believed in many quarters that the operators will be able to invest more in their technical operations if government prioritises the fixing power sector.
]]></text></news-item>