<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F7BF-9CE1-108E-F850"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Companies built up by taxation 'too big to fail'</title><source>The Western Mail</source><author>David Williamson</author><text><![CDATA[AWARNING will be given today that companies with giant UK Government contracts are "too big too fail" and greater scrutiny of how taxpayers' cash is spent is needed.
The public accounts committee - whose members include Welsh MPs Guto Bebb and Nick Smith - has grilled Atos, Capita, G4S and Serco, which between them had contracts worth around £4bn in 2012-13. It will today publish a hard-hitting report on how Government contracts must change to ensure whistle-blowers enjoy new protection and account books are opened.
The report will make tough reading for Government ministers. Management of contracts is damned as "very weak" and the commissioning process is attacked for excluding small and mediumsized businesses and allowing taxpayer-funded "monopolies" to form.
Highlighting recent scandals, the report states: "Government is clearly failing to manage performance across the board, and to achieve the best for citizens out of the contracts into which they have entered. Government needs a far more professional and skilled approach to managing contracts and contractors, and contractors need to demonstrate the high standards of ethics expected in the conduct of public business, and be more transparent about their performance and costs.
"The public's trust in outsourcing has been undermined recently by the poor performance of G4S in supplying security guards for the Olympics, Capita's failure to deliver court translation services, issues with Atos' work capability assessments, mis-reporting of out of hours GP services by Serco, and most recently, the astonishing news that G4S and Serco had overcharged for years on electronic tagging contracts: these high pro-file failures illustrate contractors' failure to live up to standards expected and have exposed serious weaknesses in Government's capability in negotiating and managing private contracts on behalf of the taxpayer."
Margaret Hodge, the Labour committee chair, said: "An absence of real competition has led to the evolution of privately-owned public monopolies which have become too big to fail. Some public service markets such as for private prisons, asylum accommodation or disability benefit assessments, are now controlled by just one or two major contractors.
Small and medium enterprises (SMEs) have been crowded out by the complexity of the contracting process, excessive bureaucracy and high bidding costs."
Ms Hodge said G4S, Atos, Serco and Capita had all told the committee they were prepared to accept measures to improve transparency.
The committee wants the extension of Freedom of Information rules to cover public contracts with private providers and access rights for the National Audit Office.
The MPs demand a "standard term in contracts requiring suppliers to have whistleblowing policies in place" that would "require contractors to nominate designated officials within departments to receive disclosures from whistleblowers".
Blaenau Gwent Labour MP Nick Smith said: "This sort of corporate chicanery is a disgrace. What I find the most galling in all this is the overcharging by these companies was not as a result of an oversight, but a conscious decision that clearly skirted the boundaries of right and wrong.
"When I pressed these companies on this very issue in PAC meetings, they apologised and admitted it was 'ethically wrong' but that is all well and good after the fact. Still billing for equipment despite it having already been removed or not even fitted is an absurd situation any public service would be slaughtered for, so private services should not escape that scrutiny. We need to know if we are tendering public services to private companies that they are using their expertise to deliver value for money. We certainly shouldn't expect those companies to be using that expertise to find ways of taking advantage of technical loopholes for financial gain." Aberconwy Conservative Guto Bebb said: "I think the report highlights the difficulties faced by small businesses who want to tender for work. To be perfectly frank, it's something that has concerned me for a while, even before I was elected... The complexity and the daunting nature of the documentation will often persuade small businesses not even to apply."
]]></text></news-item>