<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F7F1-0395-35A5-1727"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Justice must precede peace if a resolution is to be found; This week pro-Palestinian organisations held Israel Apartheid Week. We asked two Wits students whether the apartheid analogy is fair ...</title><source>The Star (South Africa)</source><author> Shaeera Kalla Wits Palestine Solidarity Committee</author><text><![CDATA[Apartheid is not a word people throw around lightly. In fact, as South Africans, we understand the abhorrent nature of the word and its implications better than most people.
Israeli Apartheid Week is a very fitting way for people around the world to identify with the plight of the Palestinians living particularly in the Occupied Palestinian Territories.
In light of the 20 years of peace talks which have done nothing for Palestinians, for any successful dialogue between Palestinians and Israelis, critical awareness and a fundamental commitment to the values of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and the application of the standards of international law without fear or favour must be adhered to.
There is a dual legal system that governs the existence of Palestinians: the indigenous population (the Palestinians) are governed by military rule and the settler population (Jewish Israeli settlers) are governed by civilian law.
Forty-one years ago apartheid was defined in international law. The UN General Assembly adopted the International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid.
According to the convention, apartheid involves "inhuman acts" committed for the purpose of "establishing and maintaining domination by one group over another, and systematically oppressing them".
A 2009 Human Sciences Research Council (HSRC) report found that Israel's policies in the West Bank are no different from the draconian colonialist ways of past colonisers. Israel's continuous expansion of illegal settlements further entrenches its colonialist nature.
In no way do Palestinians in the Occupied Palestinian Territories have any agency; their existence is contingent on Israel, from the land they are allowed to or not allowed to live on, to their water supply, to their economy.
Palestinians, as a result of Israeli occupation, have been forced to become reliant on foreign aid since they are humiliated and denied their right to self-determination.
Israel's 800km "security fence", or more appropriately its "Apartheid Wall", is not even built on the 360km-long Green Line (the internationally recognised border that existed between Israel and the West Bank until the 1967 war); it is more than double that distance because it snakes through the West Bank in order to capture more of what is left of Palestinian land.
This fragmentation of the West Bank makes travelling difficult; in addition to the wall, Israeli checkpoints tightly control Palestinian movement. Permits are required for Palestinians to travel from one district to another. Freedom of movement is hence denied to Palestinians.
The wall divides the West Bank into six separate areas, eerily reminiscent of the apartheid Bantustan ethno-territorial system of separate development. Israel's only excuse for its constant military presence is state security.
The Palestinian Authority is in effect a surrogate of the occupiers of historic Palestine. It is a complete and utter farce to say that the Occupied Palestinian Territories are sovereign.
B'Tselem, the Israeli Information Centre for Human Rights, reports that at the end of 2012 there were more than 4 100 Palestinian "security prisoners" (Israel's term for political prisoners). Palestinians who engage in rightful protest are treated as terrorists.
We must not forget that Nelson Mandela was also labelled a terrorist during South Africa's struggle for self-determination. In the 2007 UN Special Rapporteur for Palestine Richard Falk found Israel guilty of apartheid.
The people's court known as the Russell Tribunal on Palestine also came to the same conclusion in 2011.
Let it be known that calling Israel an apartheid state is not some kind of witch hunt. It is an academic and rational observation by the international community, in alignment with international law
This is why Israeli Apartheid Week is being observed by 250 countries worldwide.
In 1979, Nelson Mandela, in jail for 16 years, wrote this from his Robben Island cell: "The purpose of freedom is to create it for others."
This is exactly what Israeli Apartheid Week, together with the boycott, divestment and sanctions movement is all about.
Israel must be accountable for its crimes against humanity in order for a peaceful resolution to materialise, for in any situation, justice must precede peace.
]]></text></news-item>