<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F8A6-CFCF-C58E-D650"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Dr Reddys Lab trades higher on the bourses; The company has recalled 58,656 bottles of heartburn drug in US</title><source>Accord Fintech</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Dr Reddys Lab is currently trading at Rs. 2777.00, up by 42.85 points or 1.57% from its previous closing of Rs. 2734.15 on the BSE.
The scrip opened at Rs. 2724.00 and has touched a high and low of Rs. 2784.35 and Rs. 2713.00 respectively. So far 11991 shares were traded on the counter.
The BSE group 'A' stock of face value Rs. 5 has touched a 52 week high of Rs. 2939.80 on 28-Feb-2014 and a 52 week low of Rs. 1732.75 on 28-Mar-2013.
Last one week high and low of the scrip stood at Rs. 2840.00 and Rs. 2659.00 respectively. The current market cap of the company is Rs. 47251.14 crore.
The promoters holding in the company stood at 25.52% while Institutions and Non-Institutions held 40.90% and 16.48% respectively.
Dr Reddy's Laboratories has recalled 58,656 bottles of the heartburn drug lansoprazole in the United States due to a microbial contamination. It was classified as a 'Class II' recall which indicates a remote chance of severe adverse consequences or death due to the product flaw.
Dr. Reddy's is an integrated global pharmaceutical company, committed to providing affordable and innovative medicines for healthier lives. Through its three businesses - Pharmaceutical Services and Active Ingredients, Global Generics and Proprietary Products - the company offers a portfolio of products and services including APIs, custom pharmaceutical services, generics, bio-similars, differentiated formulations and NCEs.
DISCLAIMER: Accord Fintech provides the Content on "AS IS" basis without any express or implied warranties. Accord Fintech does not warrant the accuracy, timeliness, completeness, adequacy, merchantability, or fitness for a particular purpose of the Content, and Accord Fintech shall not be liable to Licensee or to any third party with respect to any actual or alleged inaccuracy, untimeliness, incompleteness, inadequacy, unmerchantbailty or unfitness.
]]></text></news-item>