<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F903-396F-F73E-11A4"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Port endangers Eco-Sensitive Zone (ESZ)</title><source>The Times of India (TOI)</source><author>M N Samdani</author><text><![CDATA[NELLORE: Human Rights Forum (HRF) has demanded that the Centre should immediately drop the proposal to construct a major port near Dugarajapatnam in Vakadu mandal of Nellore district as it seriously endanger the country’s second largest brackish lagoon, the Pulicat Lake. A 10-member HRF team visited several villages in and around the Pulicat Lake on Wednesday.
After interacting with local people and officials, HRF team concluded that port has been planned by violating all rules, regulations and restrictions.
Speaking to reporters after making an in-depth assessment on the impact of the proposed port, HRF general secretary V S Krishna said that it was clear that a large portion of the land from 5300 acrres proposed for acquisition was actually located within the northern boundary of the Pulicat Bird Sanctuary and its Eco-Sensitive Zone (ESZ).
Apart from being an ecological treasure trove, the Pulicat Lake also sustains the livelihood of thousands of fisherfolk, dalits and Yanadis (STs) who depend on the bio-resources in the area.
The proposed port would seriously undermine their livelihood, feared Krishna. He explained that Pulicat, a valuable wetland, with its rich biodiversity should have already been declared a Ramsar wetland and further steps taken to conserve and nurture it. Instead, the government was rushing to set up a major port in a fragile eco-system, he wondered.
"This is nothing but environmental vandalism," he remarked. He took strong objection at the Ministry of Environment and Forests (MOEF) for issuing a draft notification on to reduce the eco-sensitive zone (ESZ) from 10 km to 2 km radius around the Pulicat Sanctuary. He alleged that attempts to reduce the ESZ were being made only with a sole intention of facilitating statutory clearances for the proposed major port at Dugarajapatnam. He said that MoEF’s decision was a brazen attempt to bypass environmental law.
He said that union rural development minister Jairam Ramesh, who had handled environment portfolio in the past, should be ashamed for making statements such as there were no abiding environmental issues with regard to setting up the port in Nellore. He said that Centre should immediately drop plans to reduce the ESZ as it was an invitation to an impending ecological disaster.
No permission must be accorded or relaxation given to establish any ecologically damaging activity like hazardous industries, thermal power plants, seaports or airports in the 10 km width ESZ, he said. He suggested the Centre to examine alternative sites for setting up the port in an area that is not ecologically sensitive.
HRF Nellore convenor B Narayana said that their team visited Anjalapuram, Kondurupalem, Pulinjirivaripalem, Sreenivasapuram and Tupilipalem villages in Vakadu mandal.
For Reprint Rights: timescontent.com
]]></text></news-item>