<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F950-7726-3D28-8E5E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>More Benghazi Dredging Unearths Questions, No Answers - And From The CIA</title><source>Rat's Right!</source><author>Cultural Limits</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 13, 2014 (Rat's Right!:http://mikesright.wordpress.com/ Delivered by Newstex) http://mikesright.files.wordpress.com/2014/03/ap_benghazi_us_consulate_attack_jt_121020_wmain.jpg Any decent prosecutor worth his or her salt would be blushing with shameif their offices took so long to uncover key facts In the year and a half since the name Benghazi came to Americans' vocabularies, precious few details about what exactly happened that night and fewer regarding who gave the stand down order have surfaced.
With today's 'Very Upset: CIA Sat On Benghazi Investigation, US Personnel Fuming[1]' Adam Housley of FoxNews provides more details, but they are the sort that spawn more questions than provide answers:American personnel on the ground in Benghazi the night of the 2012 terror attack are outraged after learning that the CIA's inspector general never conducted an investigation into what happened — despite two CIA workers being killed in the attack and despite at least two complaints being filed by CIA employees. …Many in the agency were told, or were under the impression, that an investigation was in the works, but that is not the case. One person close to the issue told Fox News: 'They should be doing an investigation to see what the chief of base in Benghazi and station chief in Tripoli did that night. If they did, they'd find out there were some major mistakes.' This source claimed an investigation would likely uncover a lot of details the public does not know. Asked why such a probe has not been launched, a CIA spokesman said: 'CIA's Office of the Inspector General (OIG) always reviews carefully every matter that is brought to its attention, and takes appropriate action based on a variety of factors.'…. 'That decision was based on a determination that the concerns raised fell under the purview of the State Department's Accountability Review Board, and that a separate OIG action could unnecessarily disrupt the FBI's criminal investigation into the Benghazi attacks,' the spokesman said. The Accountability Review Board probe was ordered by the State Department, and the board reported its findings in December 2012. But separate investigations haven't stopped the OIG from investigating issues before. Why they held back in this instance is a question starting to filter through the agents at the CIA. Fox News has been told some of the investigators initially assigned to review the Benghazi complaints are 'very upset and very frustrated' that they were told to stop the process. Some members of the Senate Intelligence Committee expressed some of these same concerns in their review of the Benghazi attacks. On page 15 of the Republican response on Jan. 15, it states: '… the committee has learned that the CIA Inspector General did not investigate complaints relating to the Benghazi attacks from CIA whistle blowers. Whether these complaints are ultimately substantiated or dismissed is irrelevant. On a matter of this magnitude involving the deaths of four Americans, the Inspector General has a singular obligation to take seriously and fully investigate any allegation of wrongdoing. His failure to do so raises significant questions that we believe the Committee must explore more fully.' Fox News has also learned that the Senate Committee was told by the CIA that the investigation did not take place because it would interfere with the State Department Accountability Review Board, which was conducted to 'examine the facts and circumstances of the attacks.' While that review contained major criticism aimed at State Department officials in Washington, it didn't directly mention the CIA. 'Since when does the CIA defer to State? The ARB is in a total different agency anyway,' one special operator said. Former U.S. United Nations spokesman Richard Grenell also is critical of the CIA actions. 'It's puzzling that the Obama administration is so reluctant to do a real investigation of the facts surrounding the Benghazi attack,' he said. 'The ARB conveniently never interviewed Hillary Clinton or her political team about what they knew in the lead up or how they reacted during the crisis. And now we learn that the CIA wasn't interested in conducting a real investigation either.'Not that this is any great shock, but not one of the executive branch entities - CIA, State, FBI (WTF?) or the Accountability Review Board - conducted a real investigation after the incident? What kind of incompetent nincompoops were in charge? Don't answer that. Not that we did not know this before, but this smells massively of coverup. The CIA's investigation was stopped. State never really conducted one so as to not disrupt the FBI's criminal investigation? This was an attack on foreign soil. Why would the FBI take precidence. None of this works unless there is a massive 'MAKE THIS THING GO AWAY' campaign in progress. Not that there are going to be any quick or easy answers until all the tell all books come out or after a few people have expired, but at least there are some reporters and patriots still digging. Because, after all this time, it makes a big difference to know how corrupt a government can be. http://feeds.wordpress.com/1.0/gocomments/mikesright.wordpress.com/60273/ [1]: http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2014/03/13/very-upset-cia-sat-on-benghazi-investigation-us-personnel-fuming/

]]></text></news-item>