<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F976-8959-CF6F-0642"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Malaysia Flight MH370: ACARS Disabled Early - Captain Shah Supporter of Anwar Ibrahim Convicted of Sodomy by Religion of Peace</title><source>Maggie's Notebook</source><author>Maggie</author><text><![CDATA[
Mar 16, 2014 (Maggie's Notebook:http://maggiesnotebook.com Delivered by Newstex) Three pieces of news today about missing Malaysia Flight MH370: The first is that the flight did not (as in 'never') enter Vietnam airspace. The second is that the ACARS (Aircraft Communications Addressing and Reporting System) was disabled before the hand-over to Vietnamese controllers when we are told the last words heard from Flight MH370 was one of the MH370 pilots responding 'All right. Goodnight.' The ACARS system is said to be located underneath the cockpit. It is not a button to push or a switch to flip.
http://www.maggiesnotebook.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/Malaysia_MH370_Captain_Zaharie__Ahmad_Shah_Democracy_is_Dead_1.jpg A friend (L) with Malaysia Flight MH370 Captain Zaharie Ahmad Shah The third is that Captain Shah, shown wearing a t-shirt declaring 'Democracy is Dead,' is reportedly an ardent supporter of Malaysian opposition leader Anwar Ibrahim, a married man who has been accused and convicted of sodomy in Malaysia more than once. The day before Captain Shah's fated flight departed, he allegedly attended the court proceeding that once again overturned the acquittal. Some believe Shah may have been so upset that he 'disappeared' MH370 in protest — or something. Ibrahim's story is a sordid tale of political power gone 'horribly wrong' in a Muslim country that, as with all Muslim countries, is accustomed to treating their own 'horribly wrong,' and doing so often. Ibrahim is free on bail pending yet another appeal, but is facing five years in prison. In 1998 he was convicted on sodomy charges, sentenced to nine years, and released after six years. He was charged on new accusations of sodomy in 2008[1], tried in 2010-2011 and acquitted in January 2012. The acquittal was overturned on March 7, 2014. The Religion of Peace, in Ibrahim's case, has raised it's ugly head once again in complete disregard for human rights. I may be wrong in my guess that Captain Shah is not the perpetrator here. I'm willing to give a man credit who lives a good life in Kuala Lumpur, loves the craft of flying and supports democracy with great passion. It is co-pilot Fariq Abu Hamid who is said to be the 'devout Muslim.'Phil Robertson, Deputy Director, Asia Division, Human Rights Watch said 'this was a politically-motivated trial that was all about knocking Anwar Ibrahim out of politics and the government was prepared to do whatever it took to make that happen.' 'Anwar and his family appear caught in a never-ending nightmare of his political adversaries' making, with the courts as the instrument of his political execution,' Mr Robertson said. 'It's truly a dark day for the Malaysia judiciary which has shown itself incapable of standing up straight when national political issues are in play in cases before them,' he said. Mr Robertson said the crime that Anwar is accused of should never have been considered a crime in the first place. Source: SMH[2]About the ACARS, which is much more difficult to shutdown than the transponders. Turning off the radios and ACARS would be more difficult. NPR's Geoff Brumfiel spoke with commercial pilots, including two who have flown Boeing 777s similar to the jet that vanished with 239 people aboard. He says the pilots tell him that those systems are 'pretty hard-wired into a modern aircraft. 'They said you'd have to go through big checklists, you'd have to possibly pull circuit breakers if you wanted to deactivate [all the communications equipment]…' 'So, to do this, you'd have to have some degree of premeditation and a lot of knowledge of the aircraft,' he says. Even without those systems, the plane's satellite antenna appears to have kept communicating for at least 5 1/2 hours after Malaysia Air MH370 disappeared from air-traffic controllers' radar. Read more at NPR[3] The Washington Post:[4] Najib said the plane's Aircraft Communications Addressing and Reporting System, or ACARS, was disabled just as MH370 reached the eastern coast of Malaysia. The transponder was then switched off, Najib said, as the aircraft neared the border between Malaysian and Vietnamese airspace. A reminder: the words we are told were the last words heard from the flight and the pilots are not actually the last. A pilot flying to Narita, Japan was asked by Vietnamese airspace controllers to try to contact MH370 through his emergency communications to help them establish the MH370′s location. The pilot made contact, said there was a lot of interference on the frequency, but he heard someone 'mumbling' before losing contact.[5] He said while he couldn't be certain, he thought the voice he heard was the co-pilot (Hamid). Background and Related: Malaysia Flight MH370: ACARS Disabled Early - Captain Shah Supporter of Anwar Ibrahim Convicted of Sodomy by Religion of Peace [6] China's New Radar and Malaysia MH370: 370 Did Not Follow The Rules[7] Malaysia Flt 370: Two Transponders Shut Down manually 14 minutes apart[8] Malaysia Flt MH370: Mike McKay May Have Seen It Go Down: CONFUSION! Flew for 4-5 Hours More, Pakistan Potential?[9] Malaysia Flt MH370: Communications 'Black Spot' - Pieces of 777 Seen on Satellite Day After Disappearance? [10] Malaysia MH370: Tracked 200-350 Miles Off Course, Lower Altitude, Transponder Off: Two Iranians Identified[11] Malaysia Flt. MH370: Iranian Source Booked Stolen Passport Tickets[12] Malaysian Flt. MH370: Pilot Headed to Japan Made Contact[13] Malaysian Pilots Zaharie Ahmad Shah and Fariq Ab Hamid in Charge of Missing Flt. MH370: 2 Stolen Passports[14] H/T Hot Air[15] If you would like to receive Maggie's Notebook daily posts direct to your inbox, no ads, no spam, EVER, enter your email address in the box below. [1]: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anwar_Ibrahim_sodomy_trials [2]: http://www.smh.com.au/world/anwar-ibrahim-sodomy-acquittal-overturned-20140307-34cxi.html [3]: http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2014/03/14/290255899/boeing-777-pilots-its-not-easy-to-disable-onboard-communications [4]: http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/jet-was-hijacked-malaysian-official-tells-ap/2014/03/15/ec7397d6-abff-11e3-af5f-4c56b834c4bf_story.html [5]: http://www.maggiesnotebook.com/2014/03/malaysian-flt-mh370-pilot-headed-to-japan-made-contact-4-suspicious-passengers-2-uighurs-on-flight-flt-370-down-in-andaman-sea/ [6]: http://wp.me/p1cuXL-emw [7]: http://www.maggiesnotebook.com/2014/03/chinas-new-radar-and-malaysia-mh370-370-did-not-follow-the-rules/ [8]: http://www.maggiesnotebook.com/2014/03/malaysia-flt-mh370-two-transponders-shut-down-manually-14-mins-apart-can-a-bomb-disable-transponders/ [9]: http://www.maggiesnotebook.com/2014/03/malaysia-flt-mh370-mike-mckay-may-have-seen-it-go-down-confusion-flew-for-4-5-hours-more-pakistan-potential/ [10]: http://wp.me/p1cuXL-ekY [11]: http://wp.me/p1cuXL-ek4 [12]: http://www.maggiesnotebook.com/2014/03/malaysia-flt-mh370-iranian-source-booked-stolen-passport-tickets-not-asian-men-oil-slick-door-false-leads/ [13]: http://www.maggiesnotebook.com/2014/03/malaysian-flt-mh370-pilot-headed-to-japan-made-contact-4-suspicious-passengers-2-uighurs-on-flight-flt-370-down-in-andaman-sea/ [14]: http://www.maggiesnotebook.com/2014/03/malaysian-pilots-zaharie-ahmad-shah-and-fariq-ab-hamid-in-charge-of-missing-flt-mh370-2-stolen-passports/ [15]: http://hotair.com/archives/2014/03/15/malaysia-flight-370-signals-continued-for-more-than-seven-hours/

]]></text></news-item>