<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F9AC-058A-15B6-61B2"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Letters To The Editor - 3/15/2014</title><source>The Times-Tribune (Scranton, Pennsylvania)</source><author>Staff Report</author><text><![CDATA[Merger won't benefit Scranton
Editor: In my limited experience with company and department mergers, I find former Scranton Mayor James Barrett McNulty's comments in his Feb. 25 guest column much wishful thinking.
Perhaps Mr. McNulty never heard of the expression, "A new broom sweeps clean." In time programing will change regardless of what is now said about the merger, including the layoff of many if not most of Time Warner Cable personnel.
Mr. McNulty states Comcast is building a technology center just a two-hour drive down the turnpike. The 4,000 permanent jobs he indicates to be created, in addition to 20,000 temporary positions, will in no way reduce Scranton's unemployment. The jobs are in Philadelphia, not Scranton. Even with car pooling of qualified workers to fill positions there, it would be a four-hour-plus daily commute.
Mr. McNulty states that the location of Comcast's new technology center will "help us retain our talented young people and give some of our brightest and best reason to relocate back home." But not in the Scranton area.
If Comcast's plan to acquire Time Warner Cable comes to fruition I'm sure many, if not all qualified local college graduates offered a position, will elect to move closer to their employment rather than commute from the Scranton area.
While it remains to be seen if the $2.75 billion economic activity will translate into the 4,000 jobs Mr. McNulty suggests, this merger is still just a proposal.
I agree with The Times-Tribune editorial of Feb 16, "Pull plug now on cable deal." The "big merger" will eventually lead to no choice of quality programming or reduced customer monthly billing.
Mr. McNulty's column, in my opinion, sounds like "political speak" or a press release put out by Comcast's public relations department.
FRANK S. NICODEM
TITUSVILLE, CRAWFORD COUNTY
Welcome addition
Editor: When I went out recently with my home-care aide I noticed a new market had opened where Farley's had been located. We stopped to check out the City Market & Café.
While wandering around I had the chance to meet the owner and the workers. They all took the time to introduce themselves. This in itself attracted me.
This is a well thought-out business that I believe will be great for downtown Scranton. I use a wheelchair and live in a downtown highrise. This business gives me the opportunity to shop alone or with my aide. This is going to help so many others living downtown where there are many seniors and handicapped individuals living.
With each of their sandwiches having names related to our city, friendly owners and employees, and its location, I hope other family-owned businesses will follow and come to our area.
Scranton can be a nice place to live, but it takes local people supporting local businesses to survive.
The more each of us supports our local communities, the more each community grows. So, as a city resident, I say thank you to the City Market & Café for starting this unique business in our city.
LISA BOND
SCRANTON
Failed deterrent
Editor: If the allegations against Philadelphia state Sen. LeAnna Washington are true, she is yet another poster child for state government corruption, one who learned nothing from the indictment, conviction, and imprisonment of many of her colleagues who believed that they could do whatever they wished after becoming firmly ensconced in office.
The extraordinary public outcry and revolt over the smarmy middle-of-the-night pay grab of 2005 caused our "leaders" to reverse themselves, but the cycle of dishonesty and a lack of ethics by those who serve in the General Assembly did not end.
It would appear that the prison sentences dispensed to those who violated the public trust were not sufficiently long.
OREN M. SPIEGLER
UPPER SAINT CLAIR,
ALLEGHENY COUNTY
Beyond 'smidgen'
Editor: President Obama made a statement on Super Bowl Sunday regarding the IRS scandal. He stated "there wasn't a smidgen of corruption."
The House Ways and Means Committee issued a press release March 7, "IRS agrees to turn over Lerner documents." What is most interesting in this report is that before February 2010, the IRS was processing and approving tea party cases within three months without Washington, D.C., intervention. Afterward, 100 percent of the groups selected for audit were right leaning.
A Wall Street Journal opinion piece by Bradley A. Smith includes a timeline in this scandal. It mentions the State of the Union in 2010 when the president voiced his displeasure with the Citizens United v. FEC ruling. This ruling established the right of corporations and unions to make independent expenditures in political races. It is seen as giving the GOP a powerful new advantage.
According to opensecrets.org, ACTBlue and the NEA are the largest contributing political groups. They happened to be Democrat donors. The Koch brothers were 59th on the donor list.
I am convinced that this scandal is an attempt to shut down political opposition speech. Why is Lois Lerner pleading the 5th Amendment? Obviously she is hiding something.
WILLIAM TORBECK
DUNMORE
Veers off road
Editor: I read your auto review ("VW Passat 'a best buy,'" March 8) by Greg Zyla, a so-called "auto expert."
Not only does he rarely test American-built cars, when he does it's normally a list of long complaints, but he sure drools over the imports.
Now he injects his anti-union sentiments.
Perhaps all states should be right-to-work so no one will have pensions, vacations, job protection, working conditions and most importantly, no union representation.
I'm a proud Teamster retiree.
FRED VRABEL
CLARKS SUMMIT
]]></text></news-item>