<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F9B0-EF84-3C5F-F82A"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Spanish move to impose culture on Leighton</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>Jenny Wiggins and Anne Hyland</author><text><![CDATA[Marcelino Fernandez Verdes is a man to be feared. The new Leighton chief executive has brutally wrested control of one of Australia's oldest construction companies, knifing the company's two top executives and almost half its board, with all the calm and precision of a Spanish matador.
It took just one week.
After blindsiding Leighton chairman Bob Humphris with a $1.15 billion takeover bid on March 9, the 57-year old Spaniard - who runs Hochtief, Leighton's majority shareholder - dumped Leighton chief executive Hamish Tyrwhitt and chief financial officer Peter Gregg.
Both men are understood to have been shell-shocked. The 49-year old Tyrwhitt, who has spent nearly his whole career at Leighton, lost his coveted CEO's office - where photos of his sons skiing were pinned to the walls - on Thursday after his fate was sealed at a board meeting Wednesday night.
While Fernandez Verdes was explaining to stunned employees why he was the right man for the job, Tyrwhitt donned a black Nike t-shirt and headed for Balmoral Beach.
"I want to take this great company forward," Fernandez Verdes proclaimed, before jumping on a plane back to Germany. "My aim is to give Leighton all my knowledge and experience and to convey principles on how to be sustainable on profitability."
How Fernandez Verdes, whom one critic has described as "vain", will manage running both Hochtief and Leighton simultaneously - he says he will split his time between Germany and Australia - remains to be seen.
But the speed with which Leighton's new Spanish CEO knifed the company's two top men and sealed a takeover deal reflects Fernandez Verdes's modus operandi as the Australian construction group prepares for yet more turmoil after some of the most troubled years in its 64-year history.
"When he makes a decision, he goes for it, there's not a lot of ambiguity," says one Leighton employee.
Insiders described the past week at Leighton's headquarters in north Sydney as chaotic - "there was lots of running between rooms" - as Fernandez Verdes held one-on-one talks with Tyrwhitt and Gregg.
Tyrwhitt believed he had a close relationship with Fernandez Verdes, whom he first met in 2005, well before the Spaniard was sent by employers ACS to Germany to run Hochtief in late 2012. (ACS bought a controlling stake in Hochtief in a hostile takeover in late 2011.) Tyrwhitt has previously described his chemistry with Fernandez Verdes as "incredibly comfortable", arguing the relationship would outlast "whatever happens in the future".
But it is doubtful whether Tyrwhitt, who has a reputation for ditching people who cross him, will remain close to Fernandez Verdes after being shafted so viciously.
"Hamish made the fatal error of thinking the Spanish were his mates," says one person familiar with Leighton. "The whole play for him was gaining a senior management position in ACS's empire." People close to Fernandez Verdes say he was conscious of his longstanding relationship with Tyrwhitt, and tried to ease the blow by holding extensive discussions with the former CEO before he was ditched, and approving a $13.7 million exit package that sparked cries of outrage from investors.
Still, the ruthlessness with which the Spanish have dealt with Tyrwhitt and Gregg underscores their determination to impose their culture on Leighton.
Leighton's competitors have been equally surprised by the week's turn of events. "It was generally considered that Hamish and Peter were performing pretty well and Hamish was definitely seen to have the support of ACS," says the CEO of a mid-tier construction group.
And doubts are already being raised about how ACS's aggressive operational style will be received in the Australian market. "Fernandez Verdes has zero regard for cultural considerations in Australia, but the pipeline of work is largely Australian," claims one Leighton employee. "The way they treat people matters."
Others concur that ACS has little time for cultural niceties or building knowledge of local markets. "They don't understand but they don't care either," one former Leighton executive says. "The difference between [operating in] Australia and Europe will become very obvious very quickly."
Some of Leighton's rivals say that while ACS, which is one of the world's largest construction groups, is highly-regarded as an operator, the way it handled the takeover and management changes may hurt Leighton's ability to win construction contracts.
"Whether or not the fairly undignified spat that has been unfolding publicly is going to do any damage to the brand I'm not sure," one person says. Many companies learn the hard way that having a foreigner run an Australian business creates unexpected challenges. Financial services group AMP and telecommunications group Telstra have both had bad experiences with American executives such as George Trumbull and Sol Trujillo, who both departed in controversial circumstances.
Foreign CEOs often lack the relationships and networks in government and corporate Australia that are important to winning business, as well as an understanding of Australia's layers of law and regulation - although good advisers and staff can provide valuable assistance. Still, the Productivity Commission's review of the infrastructure market, which has questioned whether Leighton and rival Lend Lease wield too much market power, as well as increasing competition from foreign construction groups like the United Kingdom's Balfour Beatty, Spain's Acciona and France's Bouygues is expected to help break open a parochial market.
Meanwhile Fernandez Verdes, who has yet to reveal his specific plans for Leighton, has no qualms about ruffling feathers. The Spaniard is expected to accelerate the restructuring of Leighton's operating companies like Thiess, John Holland and Leighton Contractors, and has not ruled out selling or merging some of them.
Simon Fitzgerald, analyst at Moelis & Co, says he expects Fernandez Verdes to be "heavy handed", aggressively pursuing the return of more than $5 billion of bills owed to Leighton as well as potentially merging subsidiaries and selling underperforming assets.
The first asset sale under the new CEO's watch is John Holland's aircraft maintenance business, which is based at Melbourne's Tullamarine airport.
Some 230 jobs have already been cut ahead of the sale.
Further job cuts are expected at Leighton, which employs some 56,000 people globally. Some analysts estimate Hochtief could slash as much as 10 percent of the workforce by removing duplication between Leighton's existing businesses, as well as between Leighton and Hochtief.
Citigroup analyst Guy Robinson has suggested that Leighton may move to a centralised divisional model, similar to ACS, moving away from Leighton's operating company model.
Early this year Fernandez Verdes, who has described Leighton as "complex," restructured Hochtief from six divisions ito four: Building, Infrastructure, Engineering and PPP Solutions (which will arrange financing for public private partnerships). Investors, many of whom have steered clear of Leighton shares in recent years following a series of profit writedowns, ongoing management turnover - Fernandez Verdes is the company's fourth CEO since Wal King's departure in late 2010 - and allegations of corruption overseas, are in no hurry to buy back in.
"You can only wait and see at this stage, we don't know these guys," says Richard Colquhoun, investment manager at Antares Equities, which does not currently own Leighton stock.
Investors have been promised changes by Leighton's management in the past, only to have been disappointed, and remain uncertain whether Fernandez Verdes will be any better. "If it was a normal company and it had gone through the sort of experiences this company had had, you would have expected a clean-out at board level and management to show there was genuine change," one institutional fund manager says, pointing out Leighton is one of the most shorted stocks in the S&P/ASX 200 Index.
"Normally you would have a clear out at board level, recognising all the problems, fixing up the balance sheet and getting everything at least recognised in the accounts and then moving on; you never got that."
The Australian Shareholders' Association has already criticised ACS for keeping Bob Humphris on as chairman because he was on the board of subsidiary Leighton International during a period of alleged corruption by former executives, as well as approving Tyrwhitt's and Gregg's exit packages, which total more than $24 million.
The 70-year old Humphris is however only expected to remain at the company for a short time to steer Leighton through the completion of Hochtief's takeover offer and its annual general meeting in May. Once the deal is done, Humphris's days are expected to be numbered.
Shareholders 'shafted'
Mum and dad investors have copped the brunt of a bad deal in Hochtief's proportional $1.2 billion takeover of Leighton Holdings, Australian Shareholders' Association policy coordinator Stephen Mayne says.
"Everyone's been equally shafted by the offer not being a full takeover. But retail are a disproportionately large percentage of the residual register because most large institutions are fully out of the stock."
Roughly 57,000 retail shareholders own shares in the construction giant, which will be 74 per cent owned by Germany's Hochteif - a subsidiary of Spain's ACS - if all shareholders accept.
The Spanish construction giant wasted no time this week, dumping Leighton boss Hamish Tyrwhitt and chief financial officer Peter Gregg.
Former ACS executive Marcelino Fernández Verdes was then installed as chief executive.
The two ousted executives took home a combined $24 million in severance payments, a move Mr Mayne described as "a dreadful start by Madrid" that showed a "complete lack of respect for shareholders".
Leighton is one of the most heavily shorted stocks on the Australia market. Because short sellers profit when a share price falls, rumours of impending disaster at Leighton should be taken with a grain of salt.
"Retail investors need to be wary of false rumours and speculation to drive the stock price down like [the] rumour that there are $2 billion worth of write-downs coming," Mr Mayne said.
"We are advising shareholders to wait and see".
Analysts are divided in their advice to clients. CIMB analysts Andrew Hodge said he thinks Leighton faces negative earnings news over the next 12 months and investors should accept the offer and sell while they can.
Commonwealth Bank analyst Ben Brownette said the stock will trade down after the offer and investors should sell ito the market as short sellers cover their positions rather than accept the offer from Hochtief.
Spanish conquest
Key players in Hochtief's takeover of Leighton Holdings
Marcelino Fernandez Verdes
Chief executive of Hochtief, key executive at ACS Lobbed a $1.25bn takeover bid at Leighton Holdings, dumped its CEO and COO, riled the group's independent directors - all in one week.
Hamish Tyrwhitt
Former Leighton chief executive Unexpectedly knifed by Hochtief's bosses, but walks away with a $13.7m exit package
Bob Humphris
Chairman of Leighton Under fire for negotiating massive payouts to departing CEO and COO. Facing calls to step down
Adolfo Valderas Martínez
Chief operating officer of Leighton The Spaniard joined the company in December after previously heading Iridium, a subsidiary of ACS
Paula Dwyer
Deputy chair One of three independent directors who will depart the board by Leighton's annual general meeting on May 19
Peter Gregg
Former Leighton chief financial officer Walks away with almost $10m in severance pay after his surprise dumping
]]></text></news-item>