<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F9B4-D23F-D1D0-B242"><date>2014-03-17</date><title></title><source>NewsMail and Rural Weekly (Wide Bay, Bundaberg, Queensland)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Unions have place
IN REPLY to my letter re unions Bill Loudon said I must be stuck in a time zone of yesteryear, he did admit there was a time when unions were necessary but workers don't need them now.
The ignorant, gullible, less intelligent will be looked after by the Ruling Class (LNP). We all know Howard lost his election because of his plans to strip workers of their leave loading, overtime and penalty rates, and with all the union bashing that's going on now it won't be long before we see Abbott have another go although he has just had a setback with his own back benchers.
Dr Stone accused him of lying about workers' perks at the Ardmona SPC (a food processing plant); she even mentioned Hockey and Abetz telling lies.
Bill Loudon says these gentlemen are going to stamp out corruption in the union movement. Does he know any highly paid politicians with their noses in the trough?
I do. I would rather live in a country with a strong union movement than the alternative.
There are plenty of corrupt union officials but I believe they are outnumbered by decent dedicated men who I trust more than I do the Ruling Class.
T LEWIS
Burnett Heads
IT WAS with some interest that I read Dieter Moeckel's letter (NM 27th February) with his apparent concerns over the huge profits and subsequent high dividends of three mining companies and the four major banks.
I'm afraid I don't share his concern however if ever the big four banks start operating at a loss then I'll be greatly concerned.
Expansions of mining company operations are funded out of profits, not losses.
A return of 20% on investment would bring a smile to any self-funded retiree relying on the share market to provide him with an income. Mum and dad investors with shares in the four major banks would be happy with the return on their investment.
All Australians with money in a super fund should also be happy as super fund operators will no doubt have extensive investments in banking and mining companies.
Rather than being concerned with companies making "huge profits" I'm more concerned with the companies making "huge losses" such as Ford, Toyota, Holden that are shutting down and moving their operations overseas and other struggling companies such as Qantas and Virgin.
If labour market deregulation is an euphemism for gutting wages and conditions them maybe some need to be gutted.
How a restaurant owner can be expected to open on a public holiday and pay an employee $44 per hour (double time and a half) and make a return on his investment is hard to comprehend.
BARRY CEDERGREEN
North Bundaberg
DOES Ergon really want you to have solar power?
The answer is unknown.
I had a solar power system installed to my home just on a month ago. The company I used was very efficient and lodged the necessary forms with Ergon the next day.
I am still waiting for Ergon to arrive and carry out whatever is required so the system can be turned on and used.
Consequently I will have lost over a month of power generation which is of course one third of my quarterly bill.
Cost to me $200; profit to them $200.
Makes you wonder if they really want you to have solar.
Contrary to this my son in Brisbane had his system installed a day after mine and Energex was on his doorstep within a week.
The difference - he has an old analog meter and with his system turned on his meter runs in reverse when the system is working, resulting in a one of one ratio sell and buy, not the lopsided buy from you for 8 cents you buy from them 28 cents after they convert the meter.
In my case I have a digital meter that can't run backwards. Enough said?
SHARON BOB
Sharon
I AM writing in reply to G Rushton's letter to the editor on February 26 regarding the state of the botanic gardens. First of all, the photo is pretty ancient and was obviously taken shortly after the floods and a lot of work has been carried out around the Chinese Tea House since then. Unfortunately the gardens crew can't complete this until the erosion damage in the adjacent lake is fixed and is estimated to cost $500,000 plus - a grant for this has been obtained from the State Government but the extent of the damage is incredible and not an easy fix. I wonder if the writer of the article actually checked this area out before putting pen to paper.
I walk through the gardens every day after work and I consider the gardens crew do a great job and really take a pride in their work and I can imagine their disappointment to see all their good work float away during the floods and leave nothing but tons of sand and wreckage. Then the flying foxes decided to make a home in the rainforest area and destroy all the canopy in that area.
Each morning their first job of the day is to collect and bury all the baby egrets found dead that have fallen out of their nests.
The dry weather of late has not helped but the guys do try to keep the lawns watered and gardens mulched etc.
I always believe in credit where credit is due and the letter in the NewsMail was very disheartening for them.
Don't forget the department can't be seen to be spending too much money on improvements but need to work within budget otherwise another spate of letters to the editor.
MONICA ELSEY
Millbank
]]></text></news-item>