<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="F9C9-D88E-3933-124C"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Hellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry drops 3.5% on thin volume</title><source>News Bites - Western Europe: Greece</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Hellenic Exchanges S.A. Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry (AT:EXAE), Greece's largest financial services company by market capitalisation, dropped 33.0c (or 3.5%) to close at EUR8.97. Compared with the FTSE/Athex Market Index which fell 24.2 points (or 2.3%) in the day, this represented a relative price change of -1.2%. The volume was 0.7 times the average trading of 323,309 shares.
To download our Detailed Research Report (PDF), giving comprehensive trading and background information on Hellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry, please click http://www.buysellsignals.com/001051011940314120
Bearish SignalsOverbought/Bearish/Resistance Signals- The Relative Strength Index (RSI) of 74.3 has penetrated the overbought line of 70, suggesting the price gain of 16.8% in the last 14 days is unusually high. - The Stochastic indicator of 93.7 has broken through the overbought line of 80.- Tobin's Q Ratio, defined as MCap divided by Total Assets, is 3.6. Compared with the rest of the market the stock is overvalued and ranks in the bottom 1% of stocks by value of Q Ratio.
Bullish Signals- The 4.8% discount to 12-month high of EUR9.42 against the 139.2% premium to 12-month low of EUR3.75 suggests the stock continues to push for new highs. - In the last three months the stock has hit a new 52-week high four times, pointing to an uptrend. - The present value of EUR1,000 (PV1000) invested one year ago in Hellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry is EUR1,957, including a capital gain of EUR929 and dividend reinvested of EUR28.
Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Undervaluation:- Dividend yield of 1% [0.6%].Other Bullish Signals:- Total Liabilities/EBITDA of 1 is comfortably below 5, this compares favourably with the Joseph Piotroski benchmark of 5. - The company is cash rich with Cash to Market Capitalisation at 19.5%. - Net profit margin has averaged 40.2% in the last 3 years. This is considered superior and suggests a high margin of safety.- Revenue growth rate is negative but improving in recent years.[Year ended, all figures in %]

NoteVolume: there were 230,963 shares worth EUR2.1 million (US$2.9 million) traded. Beta: the Beta of Hellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry stock is 1.1. A Beta greater than 1 suggests this is a high risk, high return stock with volatility greater than that of the market.Fundamental measures by comparison with the sector average [in brackets] indicate Parity:- Price to Book of 3.9 [4.0].
COMPANY ANNOUNCEMENTSThe last 7 company announcements are:January 24: Hellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry substantial shareholder sells; shares at a one-month lowHellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry (AT:EXAE) substantial shareholder Eurobank Equities sold 566 shares worth EUR4,458 on January 21, 2014. The selling price was EUR7.90. The shares hit a one-month low on the day.
January 24: Hellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry substantial shareholder sells; shares at a one-month lowHellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry (AT:EXAE) substantial shareholder Eurobank Equities sold 4,331 shares worth EUR35,376 on January 21, 2014. The selling price was EUR8.20. The shares hit a one-month low on the day.
January 24: Hellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry substantial shareholder buysHellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry (AT:EXAE) substantial shareholder Eurobank Equities bought 16,699 shares worth EUR126,208 on January 22, 2014. The purchase price was EUR7.60.
December 17: Hellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry: Information Document availability[News Story] HELLENIC EXCHANGES S.A. (the Company) announces that an Information Document has been prepared, in accordance with paragraph 4.1.3.12 of the Athens Exchange Rulebook and decision 25/17.7.2008 of the ATHEX Board of Directors. This Information Document contains all information concerning the changes in the activity of the Company, due to the merger by absorption of its 100% non-listed subsidiary "ATHENS EXCHANGE S.A." and the spin-off of the Central Securities Depository business, the Registry and Settlement services that are being provided, as well as the management of the Dematerialized Securities System, which were performed by the Company, acting as Central Depository in accordance with the provisions of articles 39 et seq.
November 25: Hellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry: 1st Repetitive General Meeting of HELEX[News Story] HELLENIC EXCHANGES S.A. HOLDING, CLEARING, SETTLEMENT AND REGISTRY announces that on Friday November 22nd 2013, the 1st Repetitive General Meeting of shareholders of the Company was held in the "HERMES" hall at the offices of the Company. Shareholders representing 36,372,209 common registered shares and voting rights, i.e.
November 25: Hellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry: HELEX 9M 2013 financial results[News Story] The consolidated net after tax profits of HELEX amounted to EUR40.5m vs. EUR8.8m in 9M 2012 and are significantly increased mainly due to the recapitalization of the systemic banks. The net after tax profits per share in 9M 2013 including bond valuation differences amounted to EUR0.63 vs.
October 02: Hellenic Exchanges SA Holding Clearing Settlement and Registry: Tax certificate for fiscal year 2012[News Story] HELLENIC EXCHANGES informs investors that, following the completion of the tax audit for fiscal year 2012 by its certified auditors, it has received a clean tax certificate without qualifications.The subsidiaries of the Group ATHENS EXCHANGE (ATHEX), ATHENS EXCHANGE CLEARING HOUSE (ATHEXClear) and THESSALONIKI STOCK EXCHANGE CENTRE (TSEC) also received clean tax certificates without qualifications for fiscal year 2012.Source: Athens Stock Exchange
ISIN: GRS395363005
AT:EXAE; ATH:EXAE; GA:EXAE
Source: www.BuySellSignals.com
]]></text></news-item>