<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FA2B-8023-5853-A396"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Path-breaking</title><source>Daily Tribune</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[<h2>Company invents way to turning waste gas into LPG</h2>
A revolutionary way to turn waste gas from daily flaring operations in the oil and gas industry into highly valuable LPG, Butane and Naphta was revealed recently at the World Annual Water and Food Sustainability Summit. Gas Recapture Systems is a company founded by President and CEO Albert Cerenzie, the inventor of the process that promises to turn waste gas released into the atmosphere from oil and gas processing operations into products that can be profitable for companies.
"After developing the technology in Alberta, Canada and working with the leading oil companies there, we have decided to expand our operation to the Middle East and promote this new technology in the region. After coming to the Bahrain in March last year, we have opened an office in Muharraq with engineers in the ground," said Mr. Cerenzie.
He explained that the process benefits in two ways. One is that it eliminates releasing of pollutants in the atmosphere. "The process allows the recapture of propane pumped into fracks instead of flaring off the waste gas, which creates pollution and environmental concerns. By converting the waste gas stream to a liquid, instead of flaring off the gas, emissions are eliminated," he said. In addition to the environmental benefits, there is profit to be made.
"Tremendous savings can be made by reusing the recaptured propane in another well, and not having to buy new propane. Alternatively, the propane can be sold. It is estimated that a cube of propane used for fracturing costs around $350. Naptha can cost up to $750," Mr. Cerenzie added. He said that since his arrival in Bahrain, so far, companies have been very interested in his technology.
"Oil companies are primarily focused on returns on investments and now there has been an increased interest in environmentally-friendly operations. So I can see how this technology will be very interesting to them," Mr. Cerenzie said.
By Roberto Carrilloroberto@dt.bh
]]></text></news-item>