<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FA80-FBC0-0E3C-17FB"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>END OF AISLE BOOZE DISPLAYS FACE BAN TO BEAT OBESITY</title><source>DAILY MAIL (London)</source><author>BY SEAN POULTER CONSUMER AFFAIRS EDITOR</author><text><![CDATA[SUPERMARKETS could be blocked from putting sugary drinks and alcohol in eye-catching positions in a bid to curb consumption.
Researchers found that sales of fizzy drinks soared by 52 per cent when displayed at the end of aisles. Similarly, sales of drink rose by up to 46 per cent when placed at the end rather than in the middle of the aisle.
The study, which was funded by the Department of Health, will inform decisions by ministers who are under fierce pressure to tackle obesity and the health problems associated with sugar and alcohol.
Dame Sally Davies, the chief medical officer, recently suggested it may be necessary to impose a sugar tax on fizzy drinks and other foods to curb consumption. Separately, David Cameron is under pressure from the medical profession to impose a minimum price on alcohol amid concerns over binge drinking.
However, the new research suggests that a meaningful reduction in consumption could be delivered by simply putting controls on where products are placed. At the same time, a decision by stores to put healthy foods, such as fruit, in premium positions could boost sales and improve the nation's diet.
The researchers from the Behaviour and Health Research Unit (BHRU) based at Cambridge University used sales data for beer, wine and spirits as well as three non-alcoholic options - fizzy drinks, coffee and tea - from a branch of a major supermarket.
After taking into account prices, promotions and a number of display locations, they found that sales of fizzy drinks soared by 51.7 per cent when placed at the end of an aisle. The rise for coffee was even higher at 73.5 per cent, while tea sales rose 113.8 per cent.
For alcohol, sales of beer went up by 23.2 per cent, wine by 33.6 per cent and spirits by 46.1 per cent.
Supermarkets have long been aware that certain positions generate stronger sales. However, this is the first time that independent scientific research has quantified the remarkable impact on products linked to diet and health. Dr Ryota Nakamura, from the BHRU, whose research was published in the journal Social Sciences and Medicine, said controls on where products are placed in stores may be necessary.
Our study shows, for the first time, that these types of displays dramatically influence people's decisions to purchase alcohol and carbonated drinks,' he said. Prohibiting or limiting this marketing tactic for less healthy options, or utilising this for healthier ones, holds the promising possibility of encouraging healthier lifestyle choices.'
A spokesman for the British Retail Consortium said retailers lead the way in clear labelling and advice to customers to help them eat and drink responsibly'.
© Daily Mail
]]></text></news-item>