<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FAB9-223E-4722-9B71"><date>2014-03-16</date><title></title><source>Birmingham News (Alabama)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[BESSEMER
DRUG RAID
A two-week drug probe led to a raid that yielded drugs, guns and cash from a home in the Broadmoor Community.
Two people were arrested on drug trafficking charges. Seven pounds of marijuana and 41 grams of cocaine were among the drugs found on the scene, said Bessemer police Deputy Chief Mike Roper.
Police launched an investigation into drug activity in Broadmoor two weeks ago, Roper said. Just after 5:30 p.m. Thursday, the department’s Special Operations Unit carried out a search warrant at 551 Selma Road. Officers encountered the man they described as the target of the investigation — Kimothy Ronely Hale, 39. Rickea Dwan Jordan, 33, was also there.
A search turned up cocaine and marijuana, as well as oxycodone, alprazolam, $6,304 in cash and three guns. Police also seized scales and packaging material commonly used in drug distribution operations. Hale and Jordan were charged with trafficking marijuana and cocaine and unlawful possession of drug paraphernalia.
Carol Robinson
FAIRFIELD
SLEEPy SUSPECT
Note to perp: If you’re allegedly hauling $26,000 worth of heroin, don’t fall asleep in a running car at an intersection.
That, according to Fairfield police, is exactly what 27-year-old Christopher Taylor did early Thursday. Police officers found him at the intersection of E.J. Oliver Boulevard and Valley Road at 6:10 a.m., passed out at the wheel of a Cadillac. The motor was running, the car was in the drive position, and there was an empty whiskey bottle nearby, police said.
Officers put the car in park and turned it off, Fairfield Police Chief Leon Davis said. Davis said officers woke up Taylor, and got him out of the car, although not without a fight. A search turned up 4.5 ounces of heroin, an ounce of cocaine worth $1,500 and assorted pills. Taylor is charged with trafficking heroin, unlawful possession of a controlled substance and resisting arrest.
He was held in the Jefferson County Jail with bond set at $516,000. If convicted, Davis said, Taylor could face life in prison.
Taylor was arrested last year after Jefferson County sheriff’s deputies found a music video on YouTube showed Taylor selling and using drugs. Court records show he pleaded guilty last year to drug possession and was given 10 years probation. He also has drug convictions in 2012, 2011 and 2008.
Carol Robinson
HOOVER
ALDRIDGE GARDENS
The City Council is being asked to chip in an extra $150,000 to help Aldridge Gardens pay its bills.
Hoover Mayor Gary Ivey told the council last week that the public gardens needs more assistance to continue operating.
In fiscal 2011 through 2013, the city budgeted $75,000 each year for Aldridge. This year, that amount was increased to $86,576, and if the council approves the mayor’s proposed budget amendment on Monday, the city’s total contribution would rise to $236,576.
Ivey said Aldridge had a fairly significant reserve fund that allowed it to get by, but the city is going to have to examine its contribution to the gardens.
The $150,000 should help it get at least through the end of the fiscal year, which is Oct. 31, Ivey said. The city’s contribution is only a part of the overall budget for Aldridge, which is operated by a nonprofit with a board of directors. Just a couple of years ago, its annual budget was about $600,000.
Jon Anderson
JEFFCO
PROPOSED DEVELOPMENT
The County Commission rejected last week a rezoning request for an 80-unit apartment building near McCalla.
Nearly three dozen residents Thursday filled the commission chamber in opposition of the project at 4900 Eastern Valley Road. Some said the proposed complex would bring a number of families with school-aged children to already overcrowded schools in the area.
Applicant Mitchell Davenport told the commission the complex would be the “new urbanism everybody wants to accomplish.” Restaurants, shopping and schools were all in walking distance, he said.
Barnett Wright
]]></text></news-item>