<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FB15-21F4-47C3-6A60"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Udall, Bennet, Hickenlooper Announce $199 Million in HUD Funds to Help Colorado Recover from 2013 Flood</title><source>US Official News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Office of the Senator Mark Udall, U.S Government has issued the following news release:
U.S. Senators Mark Udall and Michael Bennet joined U.S. Housing and Urban Development Secretary Shaun Donovan and Gov. John Hickenlooper today to announce Colorado will receive an additional $199.3 million to help communities recover from the September 2013 flood. The recovery funds, provided through HUD's Community Development Block Grant- Disaster Recovery (CDBG-DR) Program, will support long-term disaster recovery efforts in areas with the greatest extent of unmet need, primarily in Boulder, Weld and Larimer counties.
These new funds build on the $62.8 million Udall and his colleagues secured for Colorado in December 2013 to assist recovery efforts in Colorado. Today's award brings HUD's combined CDBG-DR investment to $262.1 million.
"Since the catastrophic flood half a year ago, I have been proud to lead efforts in Washington to help Colorado rebuild its devastated communities, protect our homes and businesses from future floods and mudslides, and secure federal aid for flood victims," Udall said. "This second wave of recovery funds will supplement the emergency funds I have already helped secure for Colorado. But while these funds are an important milestone in our recovery efforts, I will keep fighting to ensure Coloradans have every resource we need to rebuild smarter and stronger."
"These resources will help flood-ravaged communities in our state rebuild their homes and businesses, repair their roads and bridges, and invest in infrastructure to make Colorado more resilient the next time disaster strikes," Bennet said. "We will continue to work together throughout the recovery process to build a stronger Colorado, and we are thankful for Secretary Donovan's support."
"After visiting Lyons and Evans in December I promised HUD would do more to help the state recover," Donovan said. “This additional money will fund a local vision to rebuild homes and businesses, repair badly damaged roads and bridges, and spur economic development. While we can never truly replace all that was lost, I remain committed to helping Colorodo rebuild more resilient and better prepared for future storms."
"This week marks six months since the flooding began," Hickenlooper said. "From the beginning, HUD and our federal partners have been instrumental in investing in Colorado's recovery. This second round of CDBG-DR funds is critical for families, businesses and economic development in the flood-impacted communities. We know we will never make whole those impacted by the floods, but these funds can help us build back sustainable, resilient communities for Colorado’s future."
A minimum of 80 percent of the funds awarded today will be targeted in Boulder, Weld, and Larimer Counties where approximately 2,800 homes incurred major or severe damage. Although the majority of this funding is intended to address the remaining disaster recovery and resiliency needs from the September flooding, the state may target remaining funds to other especially hard-hit areas from other major disasters in 2011, 2012, and 2013. Those disasters include the 2012 High Park and Waldo Canyon wildfires, and the 2013 Royal Gorge and Black Forest wildfires.
HUD's CDBG-Disaster Recovery grants are intended to confront housing, business and infrastructure needs beyond those addressed by other forms of public and private assistance. Using a combination of data from the Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA) and the Small Business Administration (SBA), HUD identified particular counties in Colorado with the greatest extent of damage to housing, businesses and infrastructure.
For further information please visit: http://www.markudall.senate.gov
]]></text></news-item>