<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FB66-9441-8B49-EB29"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Employees catch xylene in system</title><source>Odessa American (Texas)</source><author>Nathaniel Miller, Odessa American, Texas</author><text><![CDATA[March 16--Located in the southwest corner of Midland County sits the City of Odessa's Bob Derrington Water Reclamation Plant; almost invisible to anyone driving south on East Loop 338.
It's easy to reach the plant, that is, after taking a few side roads and following the few signs in the area. First built in 1982, the plant recycles most of Odessa's waste water, using a process that is different from the water treatment plant located near West 42nd Street and Golder Avenue.
And it was here that alert employees discovered the presence of a chemical waste that was dumped into the city's sewers from a manhole cover, according to a City of Odessa lawsuit.
Ben Jordan, assistant director of utilities for Odessa, said the discovery occurred Jan. 8 and almost by accident.
With employees doing maintenance at the "top of the plant," or the area where raw sewage initially comes in, Jordan said the employees noticed a difference in the way the air smelled.
Explaining that after working near sewage for many years, Jordan said the employees can usually detect something different in the water by the way it smells.
"It was sweet, almost like Pine-Sol," Jordan said. "We just knew it was a different smell."
Taking a sample, they sent a sample off to be tested and did a second sample on Jan. 30. However, because the sample was not the same quality as the Jan. 8 samples, Jordan said they did not send it in for testing.
"I make sure to do it the same way; that way our tests have integrity," he said, adding a third sample was sent on Feb. 10.
When the results came back, it showed that there were high levels of xylene in the water.
Xylene, a liquid hydrocarbon obtained by distilling wood, coal tar, or petroleum, and used in fuels and solvents, and in chemical synthesis, is also highly flammable and causes irritation of the skin and birth defects if ingested.
Lab reports done by Ana-Lab Corporation indicate the test in January reported that the water had 17.04 micrograms per liter of xylene in the water.
In a separate test conducted in February, water from the plant again showed elevated levels of xylene, this time at 14.14 micrograms per liter.
The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency's website states that federal law allows no more than 10 microgram per liter of xylene in the city's sewer system.
But the xylene also did more than that. Jordan said it killed all the microorganisms that are used to treat the sewer water.
As the raw sewage comes in, various types of microorganisms start eating at the sewage, and each other, eventually dropping all the fecal matter out of the water as it goes through the process, Jordan said.
Next, chlorine is poured into the water and then taken out with sulfur dioxide because any runoff from the plant goes into the Monahans Draw, which is about a mile south of the plant, Jordan said.
"The state says you can't have water with chlorine go back out," Jordan said.
But once the xylene hit the plant, Jordan said it started to kill off the microorganisms, which started to slow down how fast the plant could process water.
Sitting in the tanks halfway through the process is a large amount of dried sludge, which sits on top of the pools, and forces the running water to go under it. But at the end of the process, Jordan pours out some water which is clear.
Because of state standards, Jordan said the water is tested every day, with the employees walking around the plant during shifts to make sure everything is flowing smoothly.
"I tell people that if I had the choice between swimming in there and swimming in a lake, I'll take that every time," he said while pointing to the finished product. "It's because I know that we treat it so well."
The xylene that came into the plant was the result of 90 barrels of the waste poured into the sewer system by employees with Roywell Services Inc., a lawsuit filed by Ector County alleges.
When Odessa and Ector County law enforcement officials did their investigation, an unnamed employee with the company said he saw two employees use a pump to drain the contents of a lined pit --identified as a mixture of acid, chemicals and water -- from the property and into a manhole, the lawsuit stated.
The mixture that was reportedly dumped into a manhole cover at the property located at 2425 West Interstate 20 was "hot," and was dissolving caliche rock and dirt.
Additional interviews with employees stated that they dumped about 90 barrels of the waste into the sewer system and lifted the manhole cover with company-owned equipment at the direction of one of their managers, the lawsuit stated.
An interview with the unnamed manager stated he instructed the employees to dump the xylene in the manhole cover, the lawsuit stated. A second manager told investigators that the first manager told him that it was only "fresh water," the lawsuit stated.
Calls made to Roywell Services Vice President John McLain Jr. went unanswered throughout the week.
There are also concerns that the waste could have bypassed the plant, with the lawsuit stating that there was traces found in the unincorporated areas of Ector County and could potentially end up in the Monahans Draw. The draw eventually leads into the upper Colorado River.
But John Grant, general manager for the Colorado River Municipal Water District, said the recent drought will probably help keep the chemicals out of the 60-mile stretch between the draw the Colorado River.
Without any rain to push the water, Grant said he was not immediately concerned about finding the chemicals in the river. He added that tests are done regularly to make sure the water quality is good.
"We work real close with TCEQ (Texas Commission on Environmental Quality) and the Texas Railroad Commission," Grant said. "If there was a problem, we can clean it up like we would ... like if it was an oil spill."
Michael Marrero, assistant city manager for the City of Odessa, gave praise to the employees at the plant for being able to keep the plant running while they cleaned out the chemicals.
"They've had years of experience and time at the plant to keep it running," Marrero said.
Jordan said he did not have a comment on the investigation, instead saying that the thing that matters to him is making sure that the plant runs efficiently to serve the residents of Odessa.
"I take care of the City of Odessa,' he said. "I have no control of what happens out there."
--Contact Nathaniel Miller on twitter at @OAgovernment, on Facebook at OA Nathaniel Miller or call 432-333-7769
___ (c)2014 the Odessa American (Odessa, Texas) Visit the Odessa American (Odessa, Texas) at www.oaoa.com Distributed by MCT Information Services
]]></text></news-item>