<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FC0F-F271-7589-B4F2"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Sealed Air Subsidiary Paid WRG Trusts $929.7-Mil</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Sealed Air Corporation's wholly-owned subsidiary Cryovac, Inc.,paid an aggregate amount of $929.7 million to the WRG Asbestos PITrust and the WRG Asbestos PD Trust and transferred the SettlementShares to the WRG Asbestos PI Trust, according to Sealed AirCorp's Form 8-K filed with with the U.S. Securities and ExchangeCommission on February 4, 2014. On November 10, 2003, Sealed Air and its wholly-owned subsidiaryCryovac, entered into a definitive settlement agreement with thecommittees appointed to represent asbestos claimants in thebankruptcy case of W. R. Grace & Co., and the settlement agreementwas approved by order of the United States Bankruptcy Court forthe District of Delaware dated June 27, 2005. The Settlementagreement contemplates, in connection with the consummation of anappropriate plan of reorganization for Grace (including provisionsfor asbestos trusts, releases, and injunctions barring theprosecution of asbestos-related claims against the Company and itsaffiliates): (i) the payment by Cryovac, in cash, in the aggregateamount of $512.5 million with interest thereon from December 21,2002 until paid at a rate of 5.5% per annum (the "CashConsideration") and (ii) the transfer by Cryovac of 18,000,000shares (after giving effect to certain anti-dilution adjustments)of the Company's common stock (the "Settlement Shares"), in eachcase, to certain trusts to be established for the benefit ofasbestos claimants. On September 19, 2008, Grace and certain other co-proponents fileda plan of reorganization that incorporated the Settlementagreement. The PI Settlement Plan was confirmed by orders of theBankruptcy Court dated January 31, 2011 and February 15, 2011 andby orders of the United States District Court for the District ofDelaware dated January 30, 2012 and June 27, 2012, and fiveappeals of the Confirmation Orders were filed with the UnitedStates Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit. The Third Circuitentered opinions and orders denying four of these Appeals and theappealing parties did not pursue further appeals of theConfirmation Orders. On February 3, 2014, the Third Circuitdismissed the remaining Appeal filed by certain of Grace's banklenders, by agreement of Grace with the appealing bank lenders,resulting in the Confirmation Orders becoming final and notsubject to appeal. On February 3, 2014, the remaining conditions to the effectivenessof the Pl Settlement Plan and the Settlement agreement weresatisfied or waived by the relevant parties and the PI SettlementPlan became effective with Grace emerging from bankruptcy.Pursuant to the Settlement agreement and the PI Settlement Plan,on the Effective Date, Cryovac paid the Cash Consideration,consisting of cash payments in the aggregate amount of $929.7million, to the WRG Asbestos PI Trust and the WRG Asbestos PDTrust and transferred the Settlement Shares to the WRG Asbestos PITrust, in each case reflecting adjustments made in accordance withthe Settlement agreement. In connection with the issuance of the Settlement Shares and theirtransfer to the WRG Asbestos PI Trust by Cryovac, the Companyentered into a Registration Rights Agreement, dated as of February3, 2014 (the "Registration Rights Agreement"), with the WRGAsbestos PI Trust as initial holder of the Settlement Shares.Under the Registration Rights Agreement, the Company will berequired to use reasonable best efforts to prepare and file withthe Securities and Exchange Commission (the "SEC") a shelfregistration statement covering resales of the Settlement Shareson or prior to 60 days after February 3, 2014, and to usereasonable best efforts to cause such shelf registration statementto be declared effective by the SEC as soon as reasonablypracticable.  About Sealed Air Sealed Air Corporation is engaged in food safety and security,facility hygiene and product protection business. The Companyserves a range of end markets, including food and beverageprocessing, food service, retail, health care and industrial,commercial and consumer applications. The Company's brands includebubbles Wrap brand cushioning, Cryovac brand food packagingsolutions and Diversey brand cleaning and hygiene solutions. TheCompany operates in four segments: food and beverage,institutional and laundry and protective packaging, and othercategory, which includes its medical applications and new venturebusinesses. On November 14, 2012, the Company completed the saleDiversey G.K. (Diversey Japan).  About W.R. Grace Headquartered in Columbia, Maryland, W.R. Grace & Co. (NYSE:GRA)-- http://www.grace.com/ -- supplies catalysts and silicaproducts, especially construction chemicals and buildingmaterials, and container products globally. Grace employsapproximately 6,500 people in over 40 countries and had 2012 netsales of $3.2 billion. The company and its debtor-affiliates filed for chapter 11protection on April 2, 2001 (Bankr. D. Del. Case No. 01-01139). The Debtors are represented by Adam Paul, Esq., and John Donley,P.C., Esq., at Kirkland & Ellis LLP, in Chicago, Illinois; RogerHiggins, Esq., at The Law Offices of Roger Higgins, in Chicago,Illinois; and Laura Davis Jones, Esq., James E. O'Neill, Esq.,and Timothy P. Cairns, Esq., at Pachulski Stang Ziehl & Jones,LLP, in Wilmington, Delaware. The Debtors hired Blackstone Group, L.P., for financial advice.PricewaterhouseCoopers LLP is the Debtors' accountant. Stroock & Stroock & Lavan, LLP, and Duane Morris, LLP, representthe Official Committee of Unsecured Creditors. The CreditorsCommittee tapped Capstone Corporate Recovery LLC for financialadvice. Roger Frankel serves as legal representative for victims ofasbestos exposure who may file claims against W.R. Grace. Mr.Frankel replaces David Austern, who was appointed to that role in2004. Mr. Frankel has served as legal counsel for Mr. Austern whopassed away in May 2013. The FCR is represented by OrrickHerrington & Sutcliffe LLP as counsel; Phillips Goldman & Spence,P.A., as Delaware co-counsel; and Lincoln Partners Advisors LLC asfinancial adviser. Mr. Frankel was a partner at Orrick Herrington& Sutcliffe LLP, until January 2014, when he resigned from Orrickto became a new partner in his new law firm, Frankel Wyron LLP. Elihu Inselbuch, Esq., at Caplin & Drysdale, Chartered, and MarlaR. Eskin, Esq., at Campbell & Levine, LLC, represent the OfficialCommittee of Asbestos Personal Injury Claimants. The AsbestosCommittee of Property Damage Claimants tapped Scott Baena, Esq.,and Jay M. Sakalo, Esq., at Bilzin Sumberg Baena Price & Axelrod,LLP, to represent it. Thomas Moers Mayer, Esq., at Kramer LevinNaftalis & Frankel, LLP, represents the Official Committee ofEquity Security Holders. W.R. Grace obtained confirmation of a plan co-proposed with theOfficial Committee of Asbestos Personal Injury Claimants, theOfficial Committee of Equity Security Holders, and the AsbestosFuture Claimants Representative. The Chapter 11 plan is builtaround an April 2008 settlement for all present and futureasbestos personal injury claims, and a subsequent settlement forasbestos property damage claims. District Judge Ronald Buckwalter on Jan. 31, 2012, entered anorder affirming the bankruptcy court's confirmation of the Plan.Bankruptcy Judge Judith Fitzgerald had approved the Plan onJan. 31, 2011. W.R. Grace defeated four appeals from approval of the Plan. Afifth appeal was by secured bank lenders claiming the right to$185 million of interest at the contractual default rate.Pursuant to a settlement announced in December 2013, lenders areto receive $129 million in settlement of the claim for additionalinterest. The Plan became effective on Feb. 3, 2014, following the approvalof the settlement of the last appeal from the order confirmingW.R. Grace's Plan.
]]></text></news-item>