<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FC2E-7F80-04E3-59E9"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>ABC should retain Australia Network</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>Dominic White</author><text><![CDATA[Three of Australia's highest-profile businessmen - Hugh Morgan, Maurice Newman and Harold Mitchell - and senior former diplomat John McCarthy, have all cautioned the Abbott government against scrapping the ABC's Asian broadcasting unit, the Australia Network.
The ABC has also made a last-ditch bid to save the soft-diplomacy service by releasing figures showing its reach has expanded 40 per cent to 167 million households in the seven months since the ABC re-won the contract to run it.
The news comes after Foreign Minister Julie Bishop last week questioned the future of the broadcaster, saying the money it costs to run - $223 million over 10 years - could be better directed elsewhere. The ABC is fighting to defend the programming content and expense of the service amid growing expectations it will be canned by the Abbott government in the May budget as part of its cost-saving push.
Hugh Morgan, former CEO of Western Mining and founding chairman of the Asia Society (AustralAsia Centre), told The Australian Financial Review it would be "really bad news" if the service was canned and it looks like an attack by the government for any perceived left-leaning bias by the ABC.
"To pack up and go would send an immediate message, particularly if it is seen as retribution against the ABC in a political context," he said. "The signals [back] would be 'why the hell have you gone, we've spent all this time setting up, we thought you were coming to Asia'."
Maurice Newman, former ABC chairman and the chairman of the Prime Minister's Business Advisory Council, took a nuanced view, criticising the previous government for awarding the contract to the ABC against recommendations that Sky News should win it.
He called for "editorial separation", saying that the ABC's controversial coverage of revelations about Australian spying by former National Security Agency contractor Edward Snowden was evidence that "what the ABC might deem is appropriate for domestic consumption, might not be for international consumption".
But he added: "Certainly there is a case to be made for having Australia Network in a soft-power advocacy role, particularly to the region. A BBC survey found that wherever the BBC was, the view of the UK was better than where the BBC was not. By extension if Australia Network portrays Australia in a positive light one might expect it to rub off favourably on people."A presence in the region helps our nation
Harold Mitchell, chairman of Free TV Australia, which represents the ABC's free-to-air commercial rivals, said: "The new geographic landscape for a developing Asia has many interests and countries which strongly present their point of view. We should do the same."
John McCarthy, former senior diplomat, warned that China could launch its own rival service if the network is scrapped. "I think television is crucial in strategic terms in the South Pacific," he said. "We are really the only serious international broadcaster there. A lot of people could seek to fill the vacuum and I don't think that's in our interests . . . Clearly the Chinese could, and it's an area that's in our backyard. It's also highly desirable to keep Australian TV going ito south-east Asia."
In a statement, Ms Bishop told the Financial Review: "The former Labor government committed to the $223 million 10-year Australia Network contract with the ABC after a botched tender process that was the subject of a scathing ANAO report.
"The Australian government is assessing if the $223 million Australia Network contract is achieving its objective to promote Australia's interests in the Asia-Pacific region and is considering options for effective and cost-efficient public diplomacy initiatives."
The CEO of ABC International Lynley Marshall said Ms Bishop made "very fair points" in asking whether the service was value for money and could deliver on its soft-diplomacy remit with DFAT. "Our growth in reach shows we are delivering far more value through this new service than we think has ever been delivered for DFAT before," she said. She added: "We are not slaves to the ABC's agenda."
Separately, the SBS will announce that its chair Joseph Skrzynski will step down when his five-year term ends on March 26.
]]></text></news-item>