<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FC4B-AD33-BFBB-6A3A"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Understanding the intent of TED; The goal is to get people out of their silos and 'to engage, think outside the box, dream a little'</title><source>The Vancouver Sun (British Columbia)</source><author>Jeff Lee, Vancouver Sun</author><text><![CDATA[A highly subjective, eclectic and non-exhaustive look at TED, the technology, entertainment and design conference starting Monday in Vancouver
Every few years, anthropologist and explorer Wade Davis has pencilled out a week in March, hopped a plane to California, and spent time in the company of a group of wildly disparate people needing to rejuvenate and open their minds.
As a longtime attendee at TED, the technology, entertainment and design conference, Davis has long understood why people will travel from all over the world to the event. It is at its basic level, he said, a place that breaks with orthodoxy and strives to reinforce "that despair is an insult to the imagination."
On Tuesday, Davis will introduce the 1,200 attendees to TED's new home in Vancouver with what he calls a whimsical and amusing welcome.
"It is a sweet little talk on how landscape affects the Canadian spirit," said Davis, a B.C. resident and National Geographic Society "explorer in residence."
Davis is keeping the details of his four-minute talk under wraps, but he says it may help the attendees, mostly Americans, understand that Vancouver is more culturally complex than they may think.
"I will probably point out that they will hear for the first time at the beginning of the conference this tradition we now have of acknowledging the Coast Salish and the fact TED is being held on unceded territory ," he said.
After three decades as a largely U.S.-based phenomenon, TED is entering middle age. It hasn't entirely lost its geeky element, and likely always will be a place where you can find speakers who, even in this age of instant digital infamy, would otherwise remain obscure or generally unexposed.
That is largely TED's bread-and-butter attraction as something of a crossroads for academia, technologists and scientists, and the just plain quirky.
In moving to Vancouver, it is transitioning through another of what its curator, Chris Anderson, says is a natural, if necessarily uncomfortable, process. The weeklong event opens Monday, and already he is hinting that TED's initial two-year commitment to Vancouver may be extended.
"I think it needs to grow and to reinvent itself and to never get comfortable. That doesn't mean it needs to change location," Anderson said in an interview Thursday. "I would love to be in Vancouver for a very long time. It has so much going for it."
As Anderson offered a brief tour of the David Rockwell-designed theatre under construction at the Vancouver Convention Centre, he paused in front of the floor-to-ceiling glass windows to watch a float plane take off. The facility is just what TED needs to reinvent itself, he said.
"This is a combination of both scale and intimacy that we think is really special, both in the way that the theatre is designed and the specialness of Vancouver itself," he said. "If you want people to come and engage and think outside the box, dream a little, imagine a little, having this setting is crucial. It just takes your breath away." If the loyal TED community is anything to go by, that may not be a hard sell. The move has been greeted favourably by most, and all of the tickets, starting at $7,500, were quickly snapped up last year.
TED has its detractors - from Canadian media who sniff at what they say is the event's elitist structure (you have to "apply" for entry and even media access is tightly controlled) to those who say the almost speed-dating style of its talks trivialize the gravitas of the speakers' subjects.
In a somewhat ironic reinforcement of TED's own willingness to expose people to different ideas, Benjamin Bratton, an associate professor of visual arts at the University of California, used a TEDx franchise event in San Diego last year to slag TED, suggesting it "stands for middlebrow, megachurch infotainment."
"If we really want transformation, we have to slog through the hard stuff (history, economics, philosophy, art, ambiguities, contradictions)," he said. "Bracketing it off to the side to focus just on technology, or just on innovation, actually prevents transformation. Instead of dumbing-down the future, we need to raise the level of general understanding to the level of complexity of the systems in which we are embedded and which are embedded in us."
Ron Burnett, president of Vancouver's Emily Carr University of Art and Design, couldn't disagree more. Burnett has attended every TED event in California since 2009, and is going to the inaugural Vancouver event, as well.
"I am a strong supporter of bringing education and knowledge out from all the very cloistered places in which it is exchanged," he said. "I see it as a way of investing in the opening of ideas to the world. I think the criticism of TED - and I saw the TEDx presentation that has this negative view of it - has its place and that is what discussion is about. But I would describe my own experience as one of tremendous learning and exposure to really interesting people."
Anderson laughs off the criticism. "I had some great advice from (Amazon's) Jeff Bezos last year. He said there is an easy way to stop being criticized. Stop being relevant. So we actually take it as a compliment," Anderson said.
"You get it from people who think we are too far left or that we are in the service of corporations. They kind of balance themselves out."
Michael Green, the Vancouver architect who gave a TED Talk last year on tall environmentally sustainable wooden skyscrapers, thinks critics fundamentally misunderstand TED's aim.
"To me the power of TED is not to answer all questions ," he said. "It is a way to bring to a much broader audience really provocative ideas and hopefully help people twist and shake up their own way of thinking of the problem they are trying to solve."
He also wonders why people criticize TED as elitist when it offers its videos to the public for free.
"I struggle with the fact that there is criticism over something that really fundamentally is a charity, that involves charitable giving to fund a lot of ideas that are really positive and that are designed to be helpful to society," Green said.
"I think the piece that people sometimes misunderstand is (that it is supposed) to address what to me feels like a real tragedy. You've got all these amazing ideas out there in the world somewhere, and they are siloed. "How bad is it that you have a person who honestly knows how to solve one of the world's problems but no one is listening to them?" jefflee@vancouversun.com Twitter.com/sunciviclee Blog: vancouversun.com/jefflee
A is for TEDActive, the satellite simulcast of Vancouver's TED program, this year held in Whistler. It's a cheaper version of the main event - tickets cost half the main price of $7,500 - and has events and tours built around its mountain location.
B is for Stewart Brand, the environmentalist, futurist and a 1984 inaugural TED speaker, whose "de-extinction" talk last year showed it may be possible using old DNA to bring back species long thought gone.
C is for Chris Anderson, whose Sapling Foundation bought TED from its founders in 2001 and turned it into the global phenomenon it now is. Oh, and also for "curator," Anderson's oddly appropriate title.
D is for David Rockwell, the New York architect TED commissioned to design its new laser-cut signature amphitheatre for the Vancouver Convention Centre. The thousands of pieces will take four days to erect.
E is for expensive. Tickets for the sold-out TED started at $7,500 this year with proceeds to Sapling Foundation's works. It's all about networking and access. After all, the talks are published online for free.
F is for TED Fellows, a mentorship program that since 2009 has sought out 328 of the world's brightest young innovators, scientists, artists and social entrepreneurs, helping to amplify and publicize their work.
G is for Charmian Gooch, the co-founder of Global Witness, who is this year's $1-million TED Prize winner. Her society investigates and exposes corruption in developing countries, particularly around natural resources.
H is for health breakthroughs, one of TED'S frequent themes. The new Peek Vision app of this year's TED Fellow, Andrew Bastawrous, aims to cheaply eradicate avoidable blindness in developing countries.
I is for ideas. That's the entire basis of TED'S concept, rendered into its motto "Ideas worth spreading," which it cheekily modifies online daily, such as "well, the spreading is up to you."
J is for artist Janet Echelman, who with Aaron Koblin designed TED's 227-metre aerial art display hanging outside the Vancouver Convention Centre. It will employ some interactive digital lights, we're told.
K is for Sir Ken Robinson, whose 2006 TED talk "How schools kill creativity" has been viewed a combined 31 million times on TED and YouTube. He's now a perennial speaker at TED.
L is for Sara Lewis, the Tufts University evolutionary ecologist whose unusual research into the sexual habits of fireflies promises to be one of the more striking talks at this year's TED.
M is for Monterey, Calif ., the original home of TED from its birth in 1989 until 2009, when the event was moved to Long Beach. In 2013, TED announced it was moving to Vancouver for at least two years.
N is for net worth. As in the collective net worth of many of the speakers and attendees - such as Bill and Melinda Gates and Google co-founders Sergey Brin and Larry Page - which could float a mid-sized country.
O is for original. If imitation is the sincerest form of flattery, TED has lots of competition, including BIL, which bills itself as a "quirky, populist, unconference", and former Vancouver mayor Sam Sullivan's public salons.
P is for TED Prize, an annual award to an innovator to help enable their "wish to change the world." Started in 2005 as multiple winning $100,000 prizes, it was changed in 2013 to a single $1 million prize.
Q is for questions that many unnoticed scientists, authors, entrepreneurs, designers and artists have asked - and the answers that have led them to be highlighted by TED, which helps spread the answers widely.
R is for Richard Saul Wurman, architect and designer, who founded TED in 1984 with Harry Marks as a one-offconference around the convergence of technology, entertainment and design. (Hence, TED.)
S is for six, the number of years it took for another TED to be organized after the unprofitable 1984 inaugural event, which also featured one of the first demonstrations of the Apple Macintosh computer and Sony compact disc player.
T is for time, as in the 18 minutes each main stage speaker has to deliver their talk. There is a countdown clock on the stage. The 50 "All-Stars" are given only four minutes, leading one person to quip that it's akin to a bunch of "jazz riffs."
U is for unusual. As in some of the jobs this year's TED speakers have. Such as David Kwong, "cruciverbalist"; Bjorn Lomborg, "global prioritizer"; and Jill Bolte Taylor, "neuroanatomist."
V is for visual. TedTalks, the collective reference to more than 1,600 influential speeches TED has put online for free viewing since 2006, and which as of late 2013 had been viewed more than 1.9 billion times.
W is for Taylor Wilson, who at 14 built a working nuclear fusion reactor in his garage, earning him a speech at TED in 2012. Now the young nuclear scientist is back, talking about "saving seaports from nuclear terror."
X is for TEDx, the free licence franchise TED created, allowing anyone to put on non-profit mini-versions of the bigger show. It is now so popular an average of eight TEDx events are organized around the world daily.
Y is for You. You generally won't know who's coming to TED. The organization guards its attendees' privacy jealously, and accredited media can't name them or use cameras without an attendee's permission.
Z is for Zak Ebrahim, a peace activist and TED speaker this year whose radicalized father assassinated Rabbi Meir Kahane and participated in the 1993 World Trade Center bombing.
Ted Talks will be livestreamed free of charge at six Vancouver locations Monday through Friday: at BC Place Society Library, downtown branch School of Business at Robson Square library Community Centre
The Vancouver Sun's JeffLee will be at next week's TED conference. Follow him in the paper and at vancouversun.com Monday through Friday.
]]></text></news-item>