<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FCE4-DA84-609E-E920"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Alejo maxes out on bills authored</title><source>The Californian (Salinas, California)</source><author>By, Jeff Mitchell</author><text><![CDATA[State Assemblyman Luis Alejo (D-Watsonville) said Thursday he has maxed out the number of bills that a lawmaker can author for a single session.
Alejo, considered by many observers to be one of the more productive state lawmakers, said his 2014 legislative package focuses on many things, including safe drinking water, the dissolution of redevelopment agencies and flood control along the Salinas River.
"I think that it is important for state lawmakers like myself to make good use of our limited time in the legislature," Alejo said in a prepared statement. "In the short time that I have spent in the Assembly, I have always made sure that I am doing all that I can to influence policy for the benefit of my constituents and the rest of California."
Last year, Alejo sent 11 bills to the desk of Gov. Jerry Brown, who signed all of them.
One of those bills, AB 10, raises California's minimum wage while another, AB 60, grants undocumented immigrants the opportunity to apply for a driver's license.
This year, Alejo hopes to send the governor another set of bills to address issues important to both the entire state of California and the Salinas Valley. Key pieces of legislation Alejo will pursue in 2014:
AB 155: Salinas River Flood Control
Grants the Monterey County Water Resource Agency authority to create a comprehensive long-term plan for the management of flooding along the Salinas River to preserve surrounding farmland and protect public health.
AB 1585: Protecting Victims of Human Trafficking
Helps victims of human trafficking recover by providing them an opportunity to start with a clean conviction record.
AB 1609: Enforcement of Interstate Gun Trafficking Laws
Addresses illegal interstate gun trafficking by authorizing the Attorney General to prosecute individuals who illegally purchase firearms out-of-state and transport them into California.
AB 1630: Salinas Valley Clean Water
Authorizes the Legislature to appropriate $2 million to the State Water Resources Control Board in order to develop an integrated water quality and wastewater treatment program plan for disadvantaged communities in the Salinas Valley.
AB 1645: Tax Reduction for Small Business
Exempts businesses from paying the state's Minimum Franchise Tax for the first two taxable years of net income in order to help encourage job creation and entrepreneurship.
AB 1660: AB 60 Technical Clean-up
Makes technical changes and clarifies that the anti-discrimination provisions of the Safe and Responsible Drivers Act (AB 60) apply to individuals in both the public and private sectors.
AB 1708: Jury Duty Exemption
Exempts probation, parole and correctional officers from jury duty in civil and criminal matters in order to maximize realignment resources and improve critical public safety services.
AB 1746: Ensuring Access to Workers' Compensation
Directs the Administrative Director of the Division of Workers' Compensation to place cases in which there is a worker with an illegally uninsured employer on the priority conference calendar in order to provide greater access to workers' compensation benefits. This bill is a reintroduction of the winning submission from the "Ought to be a Law" contest.
AB 1750: K-12 Ethnic Studies
Requires the Department of Education to commission a report that identifies model programs, standards and curricula pertaining to ethnic studies at the high school level.
AB 1795: Filling Council Vacancies
Ensures a community's proper representation during an appointment process on a city council by clarifying when a vacancy occurs and specifying that a resigning city councilmember may vote in the appointment of his or her replacement. The provisions of this bill will not apply to cities whose charter addresses this issue.
AB 1870: Apprenticeship Programs
Addresses the unequal distribution of grant funds by mandating that funding be divided equitably between all approved multiemployer apprenticeship programs serving the same craft or trade.
AB 1905: Agricultural Permit Streamlining
Streamlines the water rights permitting process for small agricultural water ponds with multiple uses in order to develop economically viable and ecologically sustainable water supplies for farmers.
AB 2280: Community Revitalization Investment Authority
Allows the creation of new entities called Community Revitalization Investment Authorities, which would be allowed to invest property tax increments of consenting local agencies (excluding schools) and other available funding in order to improve conditions of blighted areas and encourage economic development.
AB 2737: Community-Based Safe Drinking Water Projects
Addresses the immediate needs of small, disadvantaged communities with drinking water contamination by enabling community-based non-profit organizations to assist in providing immediate access to clean drinking water.
Got a tip or story idea for Under the Dome? Email Jeff Mitchell at jemitchell@thecalifornian.com Thanks!
]]></text></news-item>