<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FD34-250F-2930-F53D"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>First indictment in corruption probe at court as graft summaries leaked</title><source>Cihan News Agency (CNA)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[ANKARA (CIHAN)- A public prosecutor on Friday completed an indictment regarding corruption and bribery claims which became public after a major police operation on Dec. 17, 2013 and sent the document to a deputy chief prosecutor in Istanbul, who, after approving the document, forwarded the indictment to a high criminal court.
On Thursday night a Twitter account behind a string of leaks in the corruption scandal posted what it presented as police files detailing graft allegations against four former ministers. The documents revealed bribes received from businessmen by the ex-ministers. Prosecutor Ekrem Aydiner, who is at the helm of the corruption and bribery investigation, presented the indictment to Istanbul Deputy Chief Prosecutor Orhan Kapici. The indictment concerns suspects detained in the investigation into Istanbul's Fatih Municipality, news sources said. Kapici approved the indictment shortly after receiving it and sent the document to the Istanbul 20th High Criminal Court for examination. The court has 15 days to either accept the indictment or send it back to the prosecutors for revision. Reports said the indictment includes 21 suspects who are accused of "giving and accepting bribes," "destroying or obscuring official documents" and "violating Law No. 2863 on the Protection of Cultural and Natural Assets," among other things. No details from the indictment were immediately available. News sources said the primary suspect in the indictment is Fatih Mayor Mustafa Demir. The mayor was detained on Dec. 17 as part of the major corruption operation along with the sons of three former ministers, businessmen and bureaucrats. The mayor was later released pending trial after being questioned by a court. Today's Zaman learned that an investigation into the sons of three former ministers -- Interior Minister Muammer Güler, Economy Minister Zafer Çaglayan and Environment and Urban Planning Minister Erdogan Bayraktar -- is still ongoing. A separate indictment will be prepared against them by prosecutor Aydiner. On Dec. 17, Istanbul police raided, along with several addresses, the Fatih Municipality building and detained 37 people, including Mayor Demir and his brother Sebahattin Demir. Ten of the suspects were arrested following their questioning by a court in Istanbul. However, the suspects were recently released pending trial. Graft summaries reveal bribes received by ex-ministers On Thursday night a Twitter account using the pseudonym Haramzadeler (sons of thieves) posted online links to a 299-page document and a 32-page document of what it presented as summaries of proceedings on four former Cabinet ministers facing corruption allegations.
The authenticity of the documents was not immediately verified. The four former ministers -- Interior Minister Güler, Economy Minister Çaglayan, Environment and Urban Planning Minister Bayraktar and EU Affairs Minister Egemen Bagis -- resigned from their posts roughly one week after the major graft operation. They have denied any wrongdoing. The graft summaries on the four ex-ministers were sent to Parliament in late February, where a summary would usually be read aloud to deputies. However, Parliament went into recess for the election campaign period shortly after and the files have been kept under lock and key ever since. On Thursday, main opposition Republican People's Party (CHP) submitted a petition to Parliament signed by 132 of its deputies for an extraordinary session to be held on March 18 to address the summaries of proceedings on the former ministers. According to the leaked documents, the accusations leveled against Güler, Çaglayan and Bagis are compiled in a 299-page summary of proceedings. The summary against Bayraktar consists of 32 pages. In the documents, Çaglayan is accused of accepting bribes 28 times amounting to $52 million. He stands accused of "establishing a criminal group for the purpose of committing crimes," "conducting imports with fake documents" and "violating the Anti-Smuggling Law." In one of his phone conversations with Iranian businessman Reza Zarrab, which were legally wiretapped by the police and prosecutors involved in the corruption investigation, said the documents, the ex-minister was heard telling Zarrab to increase gold exports to Iran from Turkey. Suspects in the corruption investigation have been criticized for engaging in oil-for-gold exchanges with Iran. It is suspected that some several tons of gold may have been traded with Iran for oil. According to Turkish media reports last year, Turkey traded nearly 60 tons of gold for several million tons of Iranian crude oil, despite its promises to observe Western sanctions on Iran's energy sector. By using gold instead of money, Turkey was able to skirt Western sanctions on Iran's oil trade, particularly those pertaining to SWIFT, the global money transfer service that until recently assisted the Central Bank of Iran and other Iranian financial institutions. The summary of proceedings also suggested that Zarrab, who was arrested but later released pending trial as part of the corruption investigation, had financed AK Party surveys. According to the documents, Zarrab transferred TL 352,000 to Çaglayan's advisor, Mehmet Sari, on June 28, 2013, to be used to cover the costs of conducting surveys by the AK Party
According to the summary of proceedings, Güler stands accused of accepting bribes 10 times amounting to $10 million. He is also accused of "establishing a criminal group with the purpose of committing crimes," "abusing his authority" and "protecting the guilty." In addition, Bagis is accused of accepting three bribes amounting to $1.5 million. According to the summary of proceedings, an investigation into Bayraktar began following a separate investigation into construction mogul Ali Agaoglu. In 2012, the Ministry of Forestry and Water Affairs launched an investigation into a project known as "Maslak 1453," which would be built by Agaoglu, after claims that the ministry had allocated part of Fatih Forest for the project. After realizing that its project would encounter problems, Agaoglu contacted then-Minister Bayraktar through his son, Abdullah Oguz Bayraktar, to resolve the issue. The document said Bayraktar helped Agaoglu undergo ministry inspections free of any problems. The ex-minister did the same favor for other construction moguls as well, the document added. According to the document, the former minister illegally changed the zoning plans of some first-degree environmentally protected zones in Istanbul's Ataköy, Kadiköy and Tuzla districts and opened them up to construction. Parliament's emergency session scheduled for March 19 Parliament Speaker Cemil Çiçek announced on Friday that an extraordinary parliamentary session will be held on March 19 at 3 p.m. During the session, Çiçek will present a verbal summary of the contents of the summary of proceedings against the four former Cabinet ministers and deputies will not be allowed to examine the documents. Deputies will be able to examine the documents only if a parliamentary commission is established to discuss the summary of proceedings. In what is being seen as an attempt to water down the damaging information in the case file, the ruling Justice and Development Party (AK Party) has asked the Parliament speaker to send the part that details all the incriminating evidence against the former ministers back to the prosecutor's office. AK Party Parliamentary group deputy chairman Mustafa Elitas called on the speaker to return the detailed summary of proceedings to the relevant prosecutor's office and submit only a condensed version to Parliament. He also confirmed that AK Party deputies will attend Parliament on March 19 as the three opposition parties have announced that all of their deputies will attend the extraordinary session in Parliament.
In the meantime, main opposition CHP Deputy Chairman Umut Oran submitted a motion in Parliament on Friday asking whether the leaked summaries of proceedings on the four former Cabinet ministers which were posted on the Internet on Thursday night matched the ones submitted to Parliament by the prosecutor's office. The CHP also issued a notice to all its deputies asking them to cancel their travel plans and be present for Parliament's extraordinary session on March 19. (Cihan/Today's Zamam) CIHANCopyright © 2014 Cihan News Agency.
]]></text></news-item>