<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FD43-2993-FA26-96DA"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>This is peace in Obama's time</title><source>Lewiston Morning Tribune (Idaho)</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[To be honest, I expected Barack Obama to lose the Iraq and Afghan wars. Mission accomplished!
But I never imagined that he could lose the Cold War too.
Neville Chamberlain may have just surrendered his status as history's Great Appeaser. He sold out an ally to Adolf Hitler in exchange for "peace in our time," but at least he never called Nazi Germany's subsequent invasion of Czechoslovakia an "uncontested arrival."
The historical similarities between 1939 and 2014 are remarkable. The Nazis first occupied Czechoslovakia's German-speaking Sudetenland in 1938, much as Russia just seized the Crimean peninsula. Russia gives every sign that it covets all of eastern Ukraine, where the majority speaks Russian. In 1939, Nazi Germany seized the Czechoslovakian rump. What stands between Russia and what's left of Ukraine?
The first response from western democracies was to threaten Russia's membership in the G-8. That's akin to the popular kids in high school telling one of the nerds that he can't sit at their lunch table. Vladimir Putin shows no evidence that he craves western approval.
The German Wehrmacht was so weak in 1936 that Hitler's generals considered overthrowing the fuehrer when he ordered them to march into the Rhineland. Documents recovered after World War II revealed that the Nazi army made plans to flee eastward at the first sight of a French bayonet. The French never lifted a finger. The Treaty of Versailles was dead and Nazism was ascendant.
We have no means of driving the Russians out of Ukraine, but we can make Russian imperialism prohibitively expensive. And it would only require that the western democracies act in their own best interests. We even have a name for this policy: "Drill, baby, drill!"
Sarah Palin was right again.
Russia has a hybrid government composed of neo-fascists and organized crime. Putin serves at the pleasure of the Russian oligarchs who are little different from Mexican drug cartel bosses. Nearly all of Russia's hard currency is gained through oil and natural gas exports. Without that revenue, the Russian economy would collapse, as would its thuggish foreign policy.
Russia bullies its neighbors by threatening to turn off the gas pipelines that Europe depends upon. Meanwhile, current law forbids the U.S. from exporting natural gas. Environmentalist wackos have been obstructing hydraulic fracturing in Europe. If we could export liquefied natural gas to Europe until it developed its own resources, Russia would be brought to its economic knees.
Putin's neo-fascist imperialist fantasies are just as fragile as Hitler's militarization of the Rhineland was. Only a little spine is required to crush it.
The problem with this plan is that Obama has opposed oil and gas exploration to the greatest extent possible. Since Obama was elected, federal oil leases are down 42 percent and drilling permits are down by 37 percent. The Keystone XL pipeline would reduce the civilized world's dependence upon corrupt, hostile oil-exporting nations and would create tens of thousands of jobs. Only the most dogmatic left-wing fundamentalists could oppose it. Obama has dithered for five years, seeking an excuse to deny its construction.
GazProm, the Russian natural gas monopoly, has underwritten European environmentalists who oppose fracking. It's not inconceivable that Russia rewards opponents of energy development in this country. After all, didn't the Chinese Red Army contribute to Bill Clinton's 1996 presidential campaign?
Europe has plenty of natural gas potential. It only lacks the political will and the technology to develop it. Even here in the United States, the richest natural gas reserves are locked away in California's Monterey Shale, where that state's environmental regulations keep it off limits.
We have met the enemy, and he is us.
But in spite of Obama's obstruction, the fact remains that what little growth the U.S. economy has experienced during his reign is entirely attributable to fossil fuel development. Without growth in the oil and gas industry, the U.S. economy would still be in recession.
If the United States and the western democracies simply got out of their own way and permitted the fossil fuel industries to do what that they do best, we could reduce fuel prices in the short term, which would hurt Russia. And in the long run, European dependence upon Russian natural gas would cease.
Game over.
But instead we throw billions at "green energy" initiatives.
Is it any wonder that Putin laughs at us?
---
Costello is a research technician at Washington State University. His email address is kozmocostello@hotmail.com
]]></text></news-item>