<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FD4A-1693-6A88-F356"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>UWSA defers Israel boycott; Critics say Wildeman overstepped</title><source>Postmedia Breaking News</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[The University of Windsor Students' Alliance( http://www.uwsa.ca/ ) has deferred its controversial endorsement of the Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions( http://www.bdsmovement.net/ ) movement - essentially foll0wing the wishes of university president Alan Wildeman( http://blogs.windsorstar.com/2014/03/04/wildeman-to-uwsa-hold-back-on-israel-boycott/ ).
At a meeting on Thursday night, student council voted 18 to 14 not to receive the chief returning officer's report on last month's student referendum( http://blogs.windsorstar.com/2014/03/02/u-of-w-students-pass-controversial-referendum-to-boycott-israel/ ) - which would have ratified UWSA's official support of the BDS movement against Israel.
Now the matter will be delayed at least until the UWSA's annual general meeting on March 26.
"It's been requested that we should wait," UWSA president Rob Crawford said at Thursday's meeting.
Jake DeJong, UWSA's vice-president of university affairs, agreed. "We've had some issues with elections in the past, and the validity of them ... Before we even consider accepting results, we should get all information possible from all sources."
Mohammed Almoayad, president of the U of W Palestinian Solidarity Group.
But Mohammed Almoayad - president of the university's Palestinian Solidarity Group( https://www.facebook.com/windsorpsg ) - was disappointed with the deferral.
"They basically caved in to the administration," Almoayad said outside of the meeting room.
Earlier this month, Wildeman publicly sent a letter to the UWSA( http://blogs.windsorstar.com/2014/03/04/wildeman-to-uwsa-hold-back-on-israel-boycott/ ) asking for the BDS referendum to be deferred until university administration completes its own investigation into complaints that the student vote wasn't conducted properly.
Almoayad called the letter "unprecedented," and pointed out that Wildeman has no jurisdiction over the UWSA.
"Administration is under a lot of pressure from people who are against BDS and Palestinian activism. We feel their ultimate goal is to try to find a way to stop this (referendum) from going through," Almoayad said.
The referendum took place from Feb. 27 to March 1. A total of 798 undergraduate students voted in favour of supporting the BDS movement, while 585 voted against it.
"This was a democratic process," Almoayad argued. "Students need to be totally autonomous in the way they make decisions."
U of W President Alan Wildeman.
Almoayad said he knows there are faculty members who disagree with Wildeman's intervention, and the organization Independent Jewish Voices Canada( http://ijvcanada.org/ ) has also come forward in support of the student vote.
Almoayad said the Palestinian Solidarity Group was aware of the controversial nature of the referendum question, but took pains to consult with others and ensure fairness. There were discussions with legal counsel and the human rights office.
Almoayad said he even met with Wildeman prior to the vote taking place.
"We never expected (administration) to interfere like this ... (to have) the audacity to try to stop the UWSA's democratic processes."
As for accusations that the BDS movement is anti-Israeli or even anti-Semitic - charges that have come from such figures asEssex MP Jeff Watson( http://blogs.windsorstar.com/2014/03/04/mp-jeff-watson-denounces-u-of-w-boycott-controversy-as-misguided-and-hateful/ ) and federal minister Jason Kenney( https://twitter.com/kenneyjason/status/439180019202400256 ) - Almoayad said that is far from the case.
"Whenever criticism of Israel happens on almost any level ... people will call it anti-Semitic," Almoayad said. "They'll find ways to twist it.
"To us, this is a desperate, weak tactic. There are real human rights violations. There are cases where Palestinians have been killed. We have family members living under this military occupation (in the West Bank)."
Almoayad stressed that the BDS movement targets specific companies that support Israeli settlement of the occupied territories. He pointed out the BDS movement has been endorsed by such organizations as CUPE, CUPW, and the United Church of Canada.
But political science student Jordan Renaud said he's glad UWSA council is delaying endorsement.
"I trust the judgment of Dr. Wildeman and the administration," Renaud said. "By deferring this, we're not ceding to anyone's authority. This went to a democratic vote within council.
"This is not cancelling (the referendum). This is not saying 'Don't ratify it.' This is a deferral."
dchen@windsorstar.com( mailto:dchen@windsorstar.com )
]]></text></news-item>