<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FD8D-9F44-367C-38BA"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Preliminary report on HB energy project released</title><source>Orange County Register (California)</source><author>Jaimee Lynn Fletcher STAFF writer, The Orange County Register</author><text><![CDATA[A preliminary analysis of the proposed redesign for a power plant at Pacific Coast Highway and Newland Street finds the project overall meets state and federal laws, but it could have a temporary impact on the environment.
California Energy Commission staff last week released the second part of its preliminary analysis of AES' Huntington Beach Energy Project, which is expected to be a cleaner and more efficient power plant that will replace the Huntington Beach Generating Station.
The commission is the agency responsible for regulating and permitting the state's power plants, and the commission will be responsible for licensing AES' project.
The project is expected to cost about $500 million to $550 million and could be completed by 2020, according to AES.
The company in October released the first part of its initial review, which looked at biological resources, facility design and traffic, among other impacts.
Part two of its preliminary review covered air quality, public health and potential alternatives to the project.
Although most of the project meets criteria for environmental impacts, the commission staff wrote in its report that air quality during the 90-month construction period would not meet appropriate standards. This is partly because the AES Generating Station would still be running its power operations, which produce emissions, the report said.
Commission staff has asked AES to keep looking for ways to improve air quality during that time.
"Overall, we're pretty happy with our application. It's consistent with helping California meet its environmental goals," said AES spokeswoman Clarissa Cordova. "We did anticipate some minor impacts with a project this size."
Cordova added AES will pay up to $72 million in South Coast Air Quality Management District projects, which is part of a new fee the agency can collect from power plants going through a rebuild.
The funding does not have to be slated for Huntington Beach projects, but city leaders are pushing for the money to stay local.
"These funds that AES will be providing ... will help to improve the overall air quality in the district for years to come," Cordova said. "I think that's the most important thing to do and the right thing to do on our end."
A major overhaul of AES' power plant operations is an effort to find a greener way to produce energy, according to the company.
The project would use less natural gas, pump out more megawatts of power and emit fewer greenhouse gas emissions.
It would also be an air-cooled system, which strays from current operations that use ocean water to cool the equipment.
Using ocean water, called once-through cooling, has drawn a critical eye from environmentalists and some state officials who say it harms marine life and affects the ecosystem near these oceanfront facilities.
The state is handing down several energy requirements in the next decade in an effort to change the way California produces and consumes energy, which includes requiring coastal power plants to greatly reduce the amount of ocean water they use for cooling by 2020.
The plant is also expected to use new technology that will enable it to power up and shut off quickly.
Plans for the nearly 29-acre site include lower-profile buildings and a less-industrial look. The 214-foot tall stacks the facility has had for decades will also come down.
AES officials in October unveiled proposed design concepts that included installing massive classic-style surfboards in front of the buildings and adding an architectural mesh structure shaped like a wave.
Gathering public input on the study is the next step before drafting a final review that will go before the Energy Commission for consideration.
The commission plans to hold a meeting to collect public comments on April 3 at the Huntington Beach Central Library.
]]></text></news-item>