<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FDA7-7F1C-AA90-813E"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Christie slams door on change</title><source>Courier News (Bridgewater, New Jersey)</source><author>By, Riley, Michael</author><text><![CDATA[The rule change is wrong-headed and serves as another example of Gov. Christie as the same old type of politician, willing to cave to special interests
Gov. Chris Christie has touted himself as a business-friendly, innovation-loving chief executive, who thinks government should get out of the way in order to unleash the entrepreneurial spirit.
Try telling that to Tesla Motors, the California electric automaker. Tesla, which sells all-electric cars that start at about $60,000, has made a mark selling autos without dealers. The governor is running the company into a ditch and kowtowing to powerful lobbyists.
This week, the N.J. Motor Vehicle Commission adopted a rule change that essentially prohibits the company from continuing to sell its cars here. Two other states - Arizona and Texas - ban the selling of cars directly to consumers. Colorado and Virginia have placed limits on Tesla's ability to sell directly to consumers, and several other states are considering following suit.
The rule change had been sought by the New Jersey Coalition of Automotive Retailers, which apparently fears the spread of Tesla's strategy of selling autos without dealers. In New Jersey, it sells directly to consumers at its stores at the Short Hills Mall and Paramus Mall. The car dealers are apparently fearful that if Tesla's business model is successful, it eventually will render them obsolete.
The rule change is wrong-headed and serves as another example of Gov. Christie as the same old type of politician, willing to cave to special interests - in this case car dealers - at the expense of the consumer. And this sudden change represents an abrupt about-face on the part of the state.
In fact, the MVC licensed Tesla in October 2012 under a state law the automaker said only restricts automakers from competing with their own dealers. Things changed when Tesla applied last year for a third license in New Jersey and also had plans for two service centers.
On Tuesday, the MVC adopted a rule that requires automakers to sell their vehicles solely through franchise dealers and not directly to the public. The rule change specifically requires dealer license applicants to submit a franchise agreement with their license application.
It also seeks to "clarify" an existing rule requiring "sellers of new motor vehicle dealers to sell new motor vehicles through franchisees only."
According to the car dealers, Tesla has been violating state regulations from the beginning, begging the question of why the state issued the first two licenses.
Now, the company is being shown the door by departmental regulation, rather than legislative amendment, which would have required public hearings
One would assume, given Christie's small government, pro-business rhetoric, that his administration would be doing all it can to promote Tesla's presence in the state.
Instead, he has sided with the status quo, denying New Jerseyans an opportunity to kick the tires and slam the doors of Tesla products right in their back yards.
The rule change is wrong-headed and serves as another example of Gov. Christie as the same old type of politician, willing to cave to special interests
]]></text></news-item>