<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FDD4-084A-3B3C-660B"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>Formula femme; Grand Prix</title><source>Australian Financial Review</source><author>John Stensholt</author><text><![CDATA[Hosting the race puts Melbourne in the spotlight but the cost might be too high, write John Stensholt and Lucille Keen.
Driving at speeds of 280 kilometres an hour doesn't faze Susie Wolff. "After you do a few laps you get ito it and focus mentally; you don't feel like you're going that fast," she tells AFR Weekend.
The 31-year-old Scot has been elevated to the role of test driver for the famous Williams team, breaking through speed and gender barriers in the famously male-dominated sport of formula one.
With a good showing she has hopes of one day earning a full-time drive on the toughest and most popular racing circuit in the world, a circuit, she says, that has given Melbourne a place on the world map.
"Melbourne is a really important event," Wolff tells AFR Weekend after fulfilling one of her many sponsor obligations, competing in a cycling challenge around the Melbourne circuit at Albert Park for investment bank UBS early on Friday morning. "The Grand Prix puts Melbourne in the spotlight."
Whether that is enough to justify the sheer expense to Victorian taxpayers of putting on the event is another matter, with the contract to hold the race expiring after the 2015 event.
The Melbourne race late on Sunday afternoon this weekend is the first of the 2014 season, with motor racing enthusiasts around the world tuning in to watch new drivers in new teams with new engines and body shapes.
Not all Victorian taxpayers are so excited. Debate has raged for all of the 19 years Melbourne has now hosted the event, with the state government chipping in hundreds of millions of dollars for the privilege of the formula one circus coming to town for almost a week every year. The 2013 race alone needed a $50 million subsidy.
Australian Grand Prix Corporation [AGPC] chairman Ron Walker, not surprisingly, insists it is still good value for money in terms of acting as a global promotion for Melbourne and Victoria.
"The event gets beamed all around the world and to our major trading partners like India, China, Russia and Japan at lunchtime on Sunday," says Walker. "How else could we get that much exposure? It showcases Melbourne and shows it is the world's most liveable city and safe for tourism."
Debate always rages about how big a TV audience the race attracts. The AGPC and state government have claimed 450 million to 500 million viewers. But one analysis by London research firm Initiative, based on official television ratings across dozens of countries, found it to be as little as 30 million. Even then, it attracts more TV viewers than the Wimbledon tennis final every year.
Walker, 74 years old and recovering from cancer, has an offer on the table with the state government to extend the contract, and while he refuses to say when a deal will be done, he does admit: "I would expect that there would not still be an unsigned contract in November" when the Victorian state election takes place. In other words, it seems Victorian taxpayers are going to cough up again.
AGPC chief executive Andrew Westacott says he has spent about nine months negotiating terms with formula one supremo Bernie Ecclestone, a colossus of the motor racing business who has ruled formula one with an iron fist for four decades even though private equity company CVC owns the major share of the sport.
Westacott says Ecclestone tried to impose a standardised contract on the AGPC that would have added considerable expenses and stripped out agreements with local suppliers and support races such as the V8 Supercars, in favour of global supplier contracts. He says the AGPC has retained its rights in the pending agreement, but will not say if the new contract would be more expensive for taxpayers. Walker says: "I'm confident that we have done the best we can in the negotiations and that is good value. It is now up to the government if they want to retain it or not."
Walker and Ecclestone have known each other for 40 years and their close relationship has been called ito question by the Australian Grand Prix's many critics. Some wonder whether the Victorian government should be dealing with someone like Ecclestone, who faces a criminal trial in Germany related to him allegedly paying a bribe in 2005 to facilitate the sale of a stake in formula one.
Unsurprisingly, his friend Ron Walker says Ecclestone's travails are not an issue. "No one [in the Victorian government] has said one word to me about it. Not one. The business of formula one goes on."
At 83, Ecclestone won't run the sport forever, but losing the criminal trial in Germany would hasten his departure and set in chain a sequence of events that would cast uncertainty over an entire sport.
Any new contract extension for Melbourne, or letting the rights to hold the race go, would come at a time when the entire formula one circuit is on the cusp of change. As well as dealing with the Ecclestone issue, formula one majority owner private equity company CVC has at least twice delayed plans to float the business on the Singapore Stock Exchange, while the administrators of the collapsed Lehmann Brothers wants to sell its holding this year. The uncertainty extends to the frantic work being done in the garages in pit lane, and the offices behind them.
McLaren, a famous name in the sport, has begun the season without a major sponsor and has employed Morgan Stanley to find a backer.
Teams are also coping with new fuel-friendly rules including the introduction of more efficient V6 engines.
50 $ million subsidy provided by the Victorian state government for the Melbourne Grand Prix
]]></text></news-item>