<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FDFA-73DB-C0DB-F36B"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>Family support key to starting a Midstate business</title><source>The Sentinel (Carlisle, Pennsylvania)</source><author>Debbie Chestnut</author><text><![CDATA[Many people dream of starting their own business, but they aren't always prepared for the amount of time, money and commitment it takes to be successful.
Robin Burtner and Cheryl Young, business consultants at the Shippensburg University Small Business Development Center, say a slow economy often sparks interest in entrepreneurship because people who have lost their jobs may have trouble finding other employment. While their biggest challenge is usually having enough money to cover start-up costs, many aspiring entrepreneurs don't realize how much time it takes to get a new business off the ground.
Linda Hartman, owner of East meets West Emporium, 29 E. King St., Shippensburg, said it's not easy to run a business without family support.
"If you have children and a family and other obligations, it becomes extremely difficult," she said. "You really have to be good at multi-tasking. People don't understand the time commitment ... You have to have a commitment from your family that they understand the hours and can help you out when you need it."
Terry Bigler, owner of B & H Bikes and Antiques, 44 E. King St., Shippensburg, said his family schedules special events, like birthday parties, around his store hours.
"They know I won't be there until I'm done working," he said.
Although being the boss has many perks - like setting your own hours - it isn't a 9-to-5 job with holidays and weekends off.
"If you want a small business, you've got to be in business seven days a week," Bigler said. "It's not much different than someone who works five days a week (and does errands on the weekends)."
According to Burtner, a 60- to 70-hour work week is typical for someone who is self-employed.
"In addition to working full-time, you're responsible for record keeping, sales, marketing, overseeing employees," she said. "You're wearing all the hats in the business and are responsible for everything."
That, Hartman said, is why a supportive family is so important.
"You may put in a 10-hour work day, but you may also take home a lot of paperwork to do," she said. "These are the things that eat into the home time."
Hartman, who has been in business nearly 17 years, said she also spends a lot of time "researching the market for new products."
"You really have to have your finger on the pulse of your business," she said. "Retail has totally changed with the internet and competition with people buying online."
The cost of starting a new business can also be intimidating.
"The potential owner must be financially secure in their personal life and have reserve cash," Burtner said. "It is possible you might not be paid for a few months."
As a first step, Young recommends having a business plan with financial projections.
Burtner said that in addition to needing money to invest in the business, it is also important to have an emergency fund to cover living expenses, like mortgage and utility payments. She said people may not realize that they will lose unemployment benefits if they start a business.
"If you estimate that you need $100,000 for rent, equipment (and other startup costs), you need at least $20,000 in cash and collateral," Burtner said.
Don't overlook health insurance, liability insurance and taxes, said Bigler, who has been in business since 1987.
"I'm paying more today in payments for health care and taxes than what I paid for three mortgages 20 years ago," he said.
For more information on the Small Business Development Center, call 477-1935 or visit www.ship.edu/edu
]]></text></news-item>