<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FE09-4364-C134-19BC"><date>2014-03-14</date><title>@HD2 New Briefs head;Thousands sue nuclear giants over Japan Fukushima disaster</title><source>The Nation (Thailand)</source><author>The Nation</author><text><![CDATA[@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;A class action lawsuit against nuclear suppliers General Electric, Toshiba and Hitachi has ballooned to more than 4,000 claimants who are seeking damages over the Fukushima atomic disaster, the lead lawyer said yesterday.
The claimants, hailing from Japan and 32 other countries including the United States, Germany and South Korea, want the US and Japanese nuclear power plant suppliers to pay compensation, lawyer Akihiro Shima told media in Tokyo.
The filing was described by Shima as the first lawsuit to be brought against nuclear power suppliers over the 2011 accident.
It alleges that the firms did not make necessary safety updates to the stricken site, which was swamped by an earthquake-sparked tsunami.
Under Japanese law, nuclear plant suppliers are usually exempt from damage claims in the event of an accident. #124– AFP
@HD2 New Briefs head;Obama takes satirical hit to #124his chin to sell healthcare
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;US President Barack Obama is trying a new strategy in his struggle to sell his stumbling healthcare law … self #124parody.
Obama ventured onto the spoof online comedy show "Between Two Ferns" in which host and "Hangover" star Zach Galifianakis grills showbiz luminaries with embarrassing questions.
"What's it like to be the last black president," Galifianakis asked Obama in the show, which debuted on the "Funny or Die" website on Tuesday.
"What's it like for this to be the last time you ever talk to a president," Obama hit back.
Galifianakis, spoofing low budget television interview shows, also jabbed Obama over "ambassador" Dennis Rodman's trips to North Korea and ribbed him over his "home country" of Kenya. For the president, the point of the exercise was to reach a youthful audience since the healthcare law depends on healthy, young Americans to sign up to subsidise care for the sick and elderly. – AFP
@HD2 New Briefs head;Pakistan clerics declare ban #124on child marriage un-Islamic
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;Pakistan's top religious body has declared the prohibition of child marriage incompatible with Islam and demanded that the government amend its laws, prompting outrage from human rights activists.
The Council of Islamic Ideology, which was formed in 1962 to advise parliament on the compatibility of laws with Sharia, also ruled that a man does not need permission from his wife if he wants to marry another woman.
Tahir Ashrafi, a member of the body said that Pakistan's Prohibition of Child Marriages Act, which stipulates the age of marriage at 16 for women and 18 for men, was not in accordance with Islamic teachings. – AFP
@HD2 New Briefs head;US pimps can pull in $33,000 #124a week, study finds
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;From streetwalkers who charge as little as $5 (Bt161) per sex act to pimps who bring in tens of thousands a week, prostitution is big business in the United States a study released on Wednesday found.
The Urban Institute is the first research group to come up with a solid estimate on how much money changes hands and how the market for sex works in eight US cities.
In the tourism and convention hub of Atlanta, Georgia, the underground sex economy was pegged at $290 million a year, more than the illicit sale of drugs and guns combined.
Police described their struggles infiltrating brothels, massage parlours and topless bars that cater to specific ethnicities, Latino, Asian or Russian and Eastern European men, and are often run by organised crime rings. – AFP
@HD2 New Briefs head;Next up from Keith Richards; #124a book for kids
@BT New Screen/briefs Text - no indent;Not content with writing a best-selling autobiography, Rolling Stone guitarist Keith Richards now is coming out with his first children's book in September, publishing house Little, Brown said yesterday.
"Gus and Me; The Story of My Granddad and My First Guitar" harks back to the rocker's childhood when his grandfather, Theodore Augustus "Gus" Dupree, a big-band musician, introduced him to the instrument that would define his life. "I have just become a grandfather for the fifth time, so I know what I'm talking about," Richards said. – AFP
]]></text></news-item>