<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FEEE-06BE-0A5D-06F7"><date>2014-03-15</date><title>ASBESTOS UPDATE: Gov't. Report Shines Light on Fibro Litigation</title><source>Lloyd's Asbestos Litigation Reporter</source><author></author><text><![CDATA[Amanda Ciccatelli, writing for Inside Counsel, reported thatmesothelioma, a serious form of cancer mainly caused by inhalingasbestos, has caught the attention of lawmakers lately. According to a U.S. government report, companies have set asidemore than $30 billion for victims of mesothelioma since the 1980s.In fact, asbestos lawsuits have played a role in approximately 100companies going bankrupt. One such company is a gasketmanufacturer called Garlock. As part of its $1 billion bankruptcycase, a judge has slashed what the manufacturer owes asbestosvictims after learning that the victim's lawyers abused thesystem. "It's laid bare the massive fraud that is routinely practiced inmesothelioma litigation," Lester Brickman, told NPR. Brickman is aCardozo law school professor who has researched asbestoslitigation for over 20 years and who testified for Garlock. In Texas, one plaintiff said his exposure to asbestos was fromGarlock after his lawyers filed a claim with another company.Meanwhile, in California, another plaintiff's lawyers misled ajury to make Garlock look worse. In Philadelphia, lawyers madeevidence of their client's exposure to 20 different asbestosproducts disappear. "As Hodges says in his order, we were able to demonstrate in all-- each and every one of those 15 cases -- that there wasextensive suppression of exposure evidence," said Rick Magee, oneof Garlock's attorneys. Garlock convinced Judge Hodges to reduce the estimate for how muchthe company owes victims. The victims' lawyers argued that thecompany still owes $1 billion. However, in his January decision,Hodges wrote that that estimate is "infected with the improprietyof some law firms and inflated by the cost of defense." Peter Kraus, managing partner of Waters & Kraus in Dallas, said,"There are some of those cases that involve my firm. So I know fora fact from those cases that the judge's description of whathappened is simply not correct." According to Kraus, Hodges took a radical approach with hisdecision. "It's very, very different from the rulings and findingsby judges with more experience in this area." But that argument doesn't work for the Institute for Legal Reformat the U.S. Chamber of Commerce. "When you start building thecase, when you start seeing more and more of these instances, yougot to really question whether this is an outlier or not," saidHarold Kim, the organization's executive vice president. Kim said the case will be a wake-up call for other judges, whichwill lead to more accurate estimates of what companies really owe.The judge currently estimates that Garlock owes $125 million.
]]></text></news-item>