<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FF4A-E88F-8A54-5FEF"><date>2014-03-17</date><title>Views diverge on the 'good story' Zuma tells</title><source>Business Day (South Africa)</source><author>Natasha Marrian</author><text><![CDATA[Views diverge on the 'good story' Zuma tells
SA has makings of failure but opinion differs over its makings of success, writes
THE central debate in the run-up to the May 7 elections, as Nelson Mandela's rainbow nation celebrates the 20th anniversary of democracy, is whether SA has a & good story& to tell.
A near-unanimous view is that the country has made immense progress in its transformation from a pariah state to a functioning constitutional democracy. It is also widely agreed that the lives of the majority of South Africans have been transformed for the better in the two decades of African National Congress (ANC) rule. The questions, & Could we have done better?& and & Where to from here?& remain the point where the confluence ends, and political parties and commentators veer off along different trajectories.
The ANC has moulded its election campaign around the & good story& President Jacob Zuma says ours is a story to & write home about& when viewed through the lens of our segregated past. Naturally, opposition parties disagree. As the debate rages, communities across the country are making clear their views on their lived realities in the often violent protests against poor service delivery and corruption.
Releasing the government's 20-year review last week, Mr Zuma noted that while progress had been made, apartheid's legacy persisted.
On local government, the site of protests estimated at one every second day, the review says remaining backlogs and unevenness contribute to deep-seated dissatisfaction in some communities. The pre-democratic period was & fragmented, undemocratic, unaccountable and racially divided& Over the past two decades municipalities have delivered basic services to millions of households that did not receive them before.
In line with increasing service delivery protests recorded since 2009 by Municipal IQ, the review shows a decline in public opinion of delivering basic services.
A shortage of & technical skills& capacity constraints, poor recruitment practices and political interference were blamed for some of the problems at local government level.
Political analyst Alex Boraine, in discussion with Constitutional Court Justice Edwin Cameron on Thursday evening at the Gordon Institute of Business Science, said that when the ANC took over, its first priority was towards the homeless, the hungry and the poor.
& Mandela recognised that and followed that, and I am sad to say that neither Thabo Mbeki nor Jacob Zuma has.& He said this was evidenced in the dissatisfaction in communities.
Under Mr Mandela, homes were electrified, millions were provided with clean water, houses and schools were built, but his departure marked the beginning of a & different kind of story& Mr Boraine said.
But Justice Cameron doubted SA's material gains were registered only in its first five years of democracy. He argued SA had gained a good structural base over the past two decades - for constructive economic growth and for a decent national life.
The country has also gained a & sceptical citizenry& its largest guarantee against autocracy, authoritarianism and dictatorship.
& I would make the argument that although it hasn't all been bad, it's no reason for complacency ... for self-congratulation, but my goodness, after 20 years we have a functioning state, we have a functioning separation of powers, we have a functioning judicial system, we have a government that has made, I think, quite considerable progress in changing material conditions,& he said.
Mr Boraine felt this was too rosy a picture, citing the hopelessness, degradation, hunger and unemployment among communities in Khayelitsha, for instance.
& They are not cheering and saying, we have had 20 years and they have served me well. They are saying they are not getting what they hoped to get and they are protesting and they are protesting violently.... I think there's a lot wrong ... I think we should hear them and I think we should warn ourselves and our government in particular that you can't forever go on depending on the capital of liberation politics,& he says.
Justice Cameron dispelled likening service delivery protests in SA to the protests experienced in the Arab Spring, saying South African communities were not out to & replace the government& Rather, the protests amounted to a & candid demand& for the government to meet its obligations. & They know there is a different form of material provision which is within reach, and they are right.& The warning signs Mr Boraine saw were Parliament's failure to function the way it ought to due to the ANC's & majoritarian& approach and, more recently, the revelation that those accused of fraud or corruption appeared on its election lists.
These include former ANC Youth League treasurer Pule Mabe, facing charges of fraud, theft and money laundering; and former communications minister Dina Pule, who was sanctioned by Parliament's ethics committee after damning findings by the public protector on her handling of a communications indaba.
The 20-year review identifies corruption as an impediment to service delivery which also undermines public confidence. Citing Transparency International, it shows perceptions of corruption increased between 1998 and 2013 but says this does not necessarily mean rising levels of actual corruption: & It could mean that more incidents ... are being exposed.& It acknowledges that weak management and operating systems create the space for corruption to thrive and says improving the National Anti-Corruption Hotline, set up in 2004, must remain a goal.
A nongovernmental organisation, Corruption Watch, was established in 2012 to tackle corruption. It runs campaigns to encourage people to report corruption, offers a platform for them to do so, and investigates and researches corruption in SA.
Suspended Congress of South African Trade Unions boss Zwelinzima Vavi was on the verge of facing an ANC disciplinary committee in 2010 due to his outspoken criticism of the velvet gloves approach to dealing with corruption.
Legislation is pending to prevent public servants from conducting business with the state. But Mr Boraine said an independent body was needed to probe corruption, which was & out of control& and took the highest toll on the poorest of the poor.
Justice Cameron said protests were also & obliquely and at times not so obliquely& against corruption, and this anger should be harnessed.
The two men agreed SA had the & makings of failure& but while Justice Cameron said it also had the makings of success, Mr Boraine felt the country was on a downward slope and, unless this decline were arrested, it would fail.
Concluding his presentation of the review, Mr Zuma said the & biggest barrier& to deepening social cohesion in SA was inequality, which needed to be & attended to further& marriann@bdfm.co.za
Mandela's departure marked the beginning of a different kind of story
The protests are a 'candid demand' for the government to meet its obligations
LOOKING BACK: President Jacob Zuma addresses the launch of the 20-year review at Sefako Makgatho Presidential Guest House in Pretoria last week. Picture: GCIS
]]></text></news-item>