<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FF9D-E741-AD46-14E4"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>Moving up</title><source>Arizona Daily Star (Tucson)</source><author>Arizona Daily Star</author><text><![CDATA[United Way welcomes development director
Gloria White has been named business development director for the United Way of Tucson & Southern Arizona.
White moved to Tucson from San Diego in 2001 to join the Omni Tucson National Resort sales team. While in San Diego, she was executive director of the Del Mar Chamber of Commerce and a national sales manager with the San Diego Convention & Visitors' Bureau.
Most recently, she was business development director for the Northern Pima County Chamber of Commerce and president of the Oro Valley Business Club.
She is also on the Foundation Boards of the Humane Society of Southern Arizona, the Pima Council on Aging and the Oro Valley Optimist Club.
White attended Indiana University and has worked in the hospitality and public-relations industries with major corporate accounts, including Microsoft, Mitsubishi Motors and Nike, the United Way said in a news release.
Sanchez takes manager job at Universal Avionics
Bob Sanchez has been named to the newly created position of program development manager, military and government, for Universal Avionics.
He will be responsible for maintaining Universal Avionics' existing programs and relationships within those market segments, as well as seeking out and developing new programs both domestically and internationally.
Sanchez comes to Universal Avionics with more than eight years of experience at BAE Systems, where he was responsible for business development for a wide range of military programs. Before joining BAE, he served 15 years in the U.S. Air Force as an avionics flight test specialist, then worked as a consultant to the military and to NASA, Universal Avionics said in a news release.
Laure Mendenhall to lead Hundred Palms Tucson
Laure Mendenhall is the new executive director of Hundred Palms Tucson, after managing retirement and assisted living communities for the past 20 years.
She started her senior housing career in Mesa as general manager of two retirement communities, Whispering Pines and Hohokam Village. She then worked as general manager for Leisure Care, and she spent 10 years as general manager for Broadway Proper Retirement Community in Tucson.
Mendenhall is active in charities, including the Pima County Council on Aging, Support the Troops, Toys for Tots and the Community Food Bank of Southern Arizona.
Lammers named partner at Rusing Lopez & Lizardi
Mark D. Lammers has joined the Tucson law firm of Rusing Lopez & Lizardi PLLC as a partner.
Lammers, who has practiced law in Tucson since 1985, is experienced in civil litigation, including complex personal injury and commercial litigation.
Lammers has litigated in state and federal courts, including Arizona appellate courts and the 9th Circuit Court of Appeals. He has litigated cases before various state agencies and arbitration panels, including the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority.
His areas of expertise include stockbroker negligence/unsuitable investments, securities fraud, personal injury/wrongful death, medical and professional malpractice, dangerous products, breach of contract, insurance bad faith/wrongful denial of disability benefits and employment law.
Lammers is experienced in class-action litigation.
He previously served as a prosecutor for the Pima County Attorney's Office, prosecuting white-collar crimes, violent crimes, sex crimes and child-abuse cases.
Since 1999, he has maintained an AV rating by the Martindale- Hubbell peer review system.
Lammers received bachelor's and master's degrees from Adams State University in Alamosa, Colo. He was awarded a juris doctor with high distinction from the University of Arizona James E. Rogers College of Law in 1985.
He serves on the Federal Bar Rules Committee and is an adjunct assistant professor at the UA College of Law, where he teaches pretrial litigation.
Kappler is marketing director
for Hundred Palms Tucson
Tom Kappler has been named the sales and marketing director of Hundred Palms Tucson.
Kappler began his career in senior housing in 1989 at Broadway Proper as an assistant activity director, and was promoted to activity director and then to general manager.
He has previously served as executive director at retirement communities in Arizona, California and New Mexico.
He helped create a 149-unit community in Oro Valley and opened Heritage Estates, a 250-unit retirement community in Livermore, Calif., which he managed for two years, Hundred Palms said in a news release. He served as executive director of Hundred Palms Tucson from 2008 to 2013. He then retired but is returning to the property.
Volk adds third-generation commercial real estate agent
Volk Co. has announced that Kevin Volk has joined the firm as a commercial real estate agent.
He is the third-generation Volk in commercial real estate. His grandfather, George Volk, started in commercial real estate in Tucson in the 1960s, and Volk Co. was founded in 1987 by Rick Volk, Kevin's father.
Kevin Volk will assist clients in all phases and types of transactions, including site analysis, development, project and individual space leasing, investment sales, land acquisitions and strategic expansion.
From Salpointe Catholic High School, Kevin Volk went to Brown University, where he graduated magna cum laude in economics. His path back to Tucson included stops in California, where he taught elementary school as a Teach for America corps member; Mexico, as a Fulbright scholar; and Virginia, where he worked in politics, Volk Co. said in a news release.
Herrick is project estimator for Bates Paving & Sealing
Joseph Herrick has accepted the position of project estimator with Bates Paving & Sealing Inc. of Tucson.
He will be responsible for business development, sales of paving, reconstruction and maintenance of parking lots and roads, and asphalt maintenance serving commercial, residential and property managers in Arizona.
Most recently, Herrick was the business development manager for Barker Morrissey Contracting Inc., securing approximately $11 million in commercial solar, industrial, retail, health-care and historic preservation projects, Bates Paving said in a news release.
His awards include Tucson Utility Contractors Association Man of Year Award, ABA/Associated General Contractors' Cornerstone Award and the Metropolitan Pima Alliance Common Ground Award.
Sampsel joins V.I.P. Morgage
Hunter H. Sampsel has joined V.I.P. Mortgage as vice president, overseeing the Scottsdale-based mortgage brokerage's expanded Southern Arizona operations.
Sampsel, who has more than 20 years of experience in the mortgage industry, opened American Home Mortgage in 1997 and then worked under Fairway Independent Mortgage Co. starting in 2009.
He holds a degree in finance and real estate from the University of Arizona.
Scharr rejoins intelliTECH
Nathan Scharr has rejoined intelliTECH as a dedicated server administrator.
Scharr has worked at IT companies including Silverado Technologies. He holds various certifications from Microsoft, including Exchange 2010.
]]></text></news-item>