<?xml version="1.0" ?><news-item id="FFB9-02CB-B774-C652"><date>2014-03-16</date><title>County police accidents, payouts on the decline; 'Our car is our office'</title><source>The Capital (Annapolis, MD)</source><author>BEN WEATHERS bweathers@capgaznews.com</author><text><![CDATA[From 2011 to 2013:
There were 541 police-involved traffic accidents.41 percent of those accidents were ultimately deemed to be preventable by the police department's accident review board.19.4 percent of police-involved accidents resulted in injuries.85.5 percent of accidents which were deemed to be preventable occurred while on duty.$562,295 was paid out of the county's self-insurance fund for claims from police-involved auto accidents.
Sources: Anne Arundel County Police Department, Risk Management office.
Neil Kenworthy was waiting to turn left into his Arnold neighborhood when he saw the headlights in his rear-view mirror.
It was shortly before 7:40 p.m. on Jan. 19 at the intersection of College Parkway and Raintree Road. Kenworthy, 18, and a friend, both busboys at nearby Deep Creek Restaurant, had just finished their shifts and were headed home.
"I just saw a set of headlights really close to my car and he hit us," Kenworthy said.
The rear of Kenworthy's 1994 Mercury Topaz was smashed. The car was totaled.
"If there was anybody sitting in the back seat of my car, they probably would have died," he said.
Following the initial shock from the crash, Kenworthy called 911. To his surprise, the dispatcher on the other end of the line already knew about the collision.
Kenworthy then noticed the Anne Arundel County police cruiser behind him with a damaged front end.
"I was in shock," Kenworthy said. "At first I thought that the police car was there to help - then I realized that he actually hit me."
In the past three years, county police vehicles have been involved in more than 530 traffic accidents, resulting in some $560,000 paid out in claims by the county's self-insurance fund, according to information provided to The Capital through requests made under the Maryland Public Information Act.
More than 40 percent of those accidents were ultimately deemed to be preventable on the part of the officer or county driver, according to the data.
The county police department's Accident Review Board examines wrecks involving all police vehicles, including those used by civilians such as Animal Control officers and evidence collection units, said Cpl. Mark Gass, who sits on the board.
The department constantly provides its officers with in-service driver education and safety tips to try and prevent accidents, police spokesman Lt. T.J. Smith said.
The agency also has tried to cut down on distractions that officers have in their cars, Smith said.
When legislation last year prohibited the use of handheld cellphones by drivers, Police Chief Kevin Davis banned officers from using the devices while behind the wheel - even though the new law exempts law enforcement officers.
Before being named police chief in July, Davis was the assistant chief at the Prince George's County Police Department. In that post, he created the "Arrive Alive" police driver safety program after three officers were killed in crashes within three years.
But with officers in their vehicles at least eight hours a day throughout a six-day workweek, the probability of accidents remains high, Smith said.
"Obviously, we're human beings like everybody else," he said.
Decrease in claims
While the percentage of accidents ultimately deemed preventable has remained relatively steady, the auto damage claims paid out by the county for police have decreased more than 30 percent over the last three years - from $200,500 in 2011 to $138,500 last year, according to data provided by the county's Office of Risk Management.
The car Kenworthy was driving was owned by his mother. The family has settled, he said.
The percentage of accidents ultimately deemed preventable is lower than in surrounding jurisdictions.
In 2013, 46.3 percent of the 423 police-involved accidents in Prince George's County were preventable, according to an agency spokeswoman.
In 2012, 48.3 percent of police-involved accidents in Baltimore County and 42.9 percent of those in Montgomery County were found to be preventable, spokesmen for those agencies said. Both departments were unable to provide complete numbers for 2013.
Of the 222 preventable police-involved accidents over the past three years in Anne Arundel, 85.5 percent occurred while the driver was on duty.
Slightly fewer than 20 percent of the county's police-involved accidents during that period resulted in injuries, police data show.
Of the accidents that resulted in injuries, county employees were more likely than civilians to be hurt. Employees were injured 65.7 percent of the time, compared to 34.2 percent for civilians.
In Kenworthy's case, both he and his passenger were taken to the hospital with minor injuries, police spokesman Justin Mulcahy said.
The officer behind the wheel, Cpl. Keith Doyle, was uninjured. Doyle did not return a call for comment for this article.
None of the police-involved accidents in the past three years resulted in fatalities.
The vast majority of auto claims against the county are settled, County Attorney David Plymyer said.
Plymyer estimated that the county defends about six to eight lawsuits resulting from auto accidents each year. Only two or three cases ultimately go to court, he said.
'Not your average guys'
Gass, one of five members of Anne Arundel's accident review board, said the majority of collisions are relatively minor.
While many motorists who, for instance, back into a sign may decide not to call the police or their insurance provider, Gass said, police officers are held to a higher standard.
When an accident occurs, officers are prohibited from even pulling over to the side of the road. They must stop the vehicle where the accident occurred.
A supervisor will then go to the scene to take photos and interview drivers and witnesses, Gass said.
Internal Affairs then presents its findings to the review board, but, to prevent favoritism, it doesn't disclose the names of the employees involved.
The majority of accidents can be traced to inattention, improper backing and following too closely, Gass said.
"We're not your average guy who drives to work for 40 or 30 minutes, then goes inside," Gass said. "Our car is our office."
In addition to spending a lot of time behind the wheel, officers also have more distractions than the average driver, Gass said.
Officers are expected to use their in-car computer and monitor their radios while responding to calls. They may also be fielding calls from supervisors or monitoring their GPS systems, Gass said.
Many recruits who go through the police academy find that they can't pass the driving component, said O'Brien Atkninson, president of the county's Fraternal Order of Police Lodge.
"They usually weed out the bad drivers in the academy," Atkinson said.
Sanctions imposed
Once an accident is determined to be preventable, Atkinson said, "sometimes they suspend the car privilege. Sometimes they fine the officer, depending on the amount of damage to the vehicle. It could result in as serious of a penalty as suspension or termination."
Smith said that "if a person appears to have some need for driver retraining, that's going to happen and has happened."
Additional penalties may be taken against personnel who continue to have accidents, Smith said.
A preliminary investigation following the January accident in Arnold indicated that Doyle was at fault, Mulcahy said.
The accident was the fourth in Doyle's 14 years with the department. Citing personnel issues, the department declined to disclose whether the three previous accidents Doyle was involved in were preventable.
In March 2008, Doyle was driving on Broadwater Road in Arnold when he crossed over the center line and struck a Buick. According to the accident report, he told police that he was looking down at the time and didn't realize he had drifted into oncoming traffic.
The following year, Doyle was in stop-and-go traffic on Benfield Boulevard near Tewkesbury Lane in Severna Park when he struck another vehicle from the rear while swerving to avoid it, the accident report states.
"Just because we have the right to speed to a call doesn't neglect the duty to drive safely," Smith said. "We don't want to want to bury somebody over an accident that could have been preventable."
]]></text></news-item>